<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="397025" ns="0" title="Ace of Base"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
| name                = Ace of Base
| image                 = Ace_Of_Base_Toronto_2010.JPG
| caption            = Ace of Base, 2010. L-R: Ulf Ekberg, Jonas Berggren, Julia Williamson, Clara Hagman
| image_size            = 250
| landscape           = yes
| background          = group_or_band
| origin              = [[Gothenburg]], [[Sweden]]
| genre               = [[Pop Music|Pop]], [[Dance music|Dance]], [[Eurodance]], [[Europop]]
| years_active        = 1987–present
| label               = [[Universal Music Group|Universal Music]]/[[Playground Music Scandinavia|Playground Music]] &lt;small&gt;(2008 – present)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Arista Records]]/[[BMG]] &lt;small&gt;(Americas/Japan, 1993-2000)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Barclay Records]] &lt;small&gt;(France 1993-95)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Metronome Records &lt;small&gt;(Europe, 1993-98)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Polydor Records]] &lt;small&gt;(Europe, 1998-2002)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Edel-Mega Records|Mega Records]] &lt;small&gt;(Scandinavia, 1992-2002)&lt;/small&gt;
| website                 = [http://www.aceofbase.com/ www.aceofbase.com]
| current_members    = | current_members = [[Jonas Berggren]]&lt;br&gt; [[Ulf Ekberg]] &lt;br&gt; [[Clara Hagman]] &lt;br&gt; Julia Williamson
| past_members = [[Malin Berggren]]&lt;br&gt; [[Jenny Berggren]] &lt;br&gt; 
}}

'''Ace of Base''' is a pop band based in [[Gothenburg]], [[Sweden]]. Its original lineup consisted of [[Ulf Ekberg|Ulf &quot;Buddha&quot; Ekberg]], and three siblings, [[Jonas Berggren|Jonas &quot;Joker&quot; Berggren]], [[Linn Berggren|Malin &quot;Linn&quot; Berggren]] and [[Jenny Berggren]]. They released four studio albums between 1993 and 2002, which sold in excess of 30 million copies worldwide.

''[[Happy Nation|Happy Nation / The Sign]]'' is one of the best-selling debut albums of all time, and was certified nine times platinum in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?resultpage=2&amp;table=tblTop100&amp;action|title=Top 100 Albums|publisher=''[[Recording Industry Association of America|RIAA]]''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was the first debut album to produce three number 1 singles on the ''[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]'' [[Mainstream Top 40]] chart: &quot;[[All That She Wants]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Sign (song)|The Sign]]&quot; and &quot;[[Don't Turn Around]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.com/news/lady-gaga-makes-mainstream-top-40-history-1003992987.story#/news/lady-gaga-makes-mainstream-top-40-history-1003992987.story|title=Lady GaGa Makes Mainstream Top 40 History|last=Trust|first=Gary|date=2009-07-13|publisher=''Billboard.com''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the formal departure of singer Linn in 2007, the band performed a series of concerts as a trio in Europe and Asia from 2007 through 2009, before Jenny revealed in November 2009 that she would be taking indefinite leave from the band to focus on her own solo career.&lt;ref name=&quot;twitter.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://twitter.com/jennyberggren/status/6206340746|title=@Jenny Berggren|last=Berggren|first=Jenny|date=11-30|publisher=Twitter|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Jonas and Ulf have since recruited two new female vocalists, [[Clara Hagman]] and [[Julia Williamson]].  The new line-up released their first album together ''[[The Golden Ratio (album)|The Golden Ratio]]'' in September 2010.

==Career==
===Formation===
In 1987, following a number of years as part of a [[new romantic]] and [[punk music|punk]] covers band called G Konrad, Jonas Berggren formed a band with two friends, Johnny Lindén and Niklas Tränk for a school project; his sisters Linn and Jenny joined as singers. The new band went through several names: [[New Arbat Avenue|Kalinin Prospect]] (after an avenue in Moscow); CAD (Computer-Aided Disco); and Tech-Noir (French for ''black technology'', after a [[nightclub]] in the film ''[[The Terminator]]'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aceofbase.co.uk/biography.html|title=Totally Addicted to Base!|publisher=''AceofBase.co.uk''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}{{Dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They toured the clubs of Sweden with their new self-written material, [[techno music|techno]] inspired by the likes of [[The KLF]] and [[Snap!]].

Johnny left the group in 1989. Niklas made his departure known by failing to appear at a gig at Bältesspännarparken on 6 August 1990; he preferred to attend a [[Rolling Stones]] concert on the other side of town.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.happynation.net/aobgbg.htm|title=Ace of Base GBG|publisher=''HappyNation.net''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}{{Dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Jonas asked his friend Ulf Ekberg to stand in for Niklas. The new quartet sought a new name to make a fresh start; Linn was reported saying: &quot;No one could pronounce the name of the group and nobody could remember it&quot;. They settled on Ace of Base, because they were the &quot;masters of their studio&quot;, the basement of a car-repair shop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heathenworld.com/bandname/nav1.aspx|title=Origins of Band Names[A-E&amp;#93;|year=1996|publisher=''HeaThen WoRLD.com''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However the band continued to struggle to gain any recognition, partly due to the preference of [[Heavy metal music|heavy metal]] over [[techno]] in their home town, according to singer Jenny.&lt;ref&gt;Happy Nation Home Video, VHS, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991 they responded to a newspaper ad by producer John Ballard who was looking for new talent. He was somewhat unsure about their potential, but did pass them on to Klas Lunding at Telegram Records who helped them record an early demo for the song &quot;[[Wheel of Fortune (Ace of Base song)|Wheel of Fortune]]&quot; in their newly renovated studio. But it did not convince Telegram to sign the band, and other labels in Sweden still showed no sign of interest. In the end, the unfinished demo was sold for a small price to the independent [[Denmark|Danish]] label Mega Records in March 1992.&lt;ref&gt;Our Story, SVT documentary, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Wheel of Fortune&quot; was re-recorded and released as a single in Denmark in May but failed to hit the charts. A small-budget music video was shot and directed in a small studio by Viking Nielsson&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mvdbase.com/artist.php?last=Ace%20of%20Base|title=Ace of Base|publisher=''MvdBase.com''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in September, after two failures, the single finally reached the charts.

===International success and ''Happy Nation'' (1993–1994)===

It was another song that was to help Ace of Base's career take off internationally. After hearing Swedish top 20 hit &quot;Another Mother&quot; by [[Kayo Shekoni|Kayo]], the band decided that was exactly the sound they wanted to create.&lt;ref&gt;Beatlab, SVT documentary, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; They contacted the song's producer [[Denniz PoP]] and sent him a demo of a song called &quot;Mr Ace&quot;. Coincidentally, the tape got stuck in the cassette tape player in his car, so he was forced to listen to it over and over again, which helped him decide to produce the track. The song became &quot;All That She Wants&quot;, a dark fusion of [[dub music|dub-reggae]] with pop which became the band's trademark sound. On release in October 1992, it quickly climbed to #1 on the Danish chart while the previous single was still sitting at #2. Keen to rush out an [[LP album|LP]] for the Christmas market, [[Mega Records]] pressed the band for an album and it was hastily recorded, mixed, and released within a few weeks.

Preceded by a single of the same name, the album, titled ''Happy Nation'' was an instant hit in Denmark, and its success prompted interest elsewhere in Europe. A Pan-European license was signed with [[PolyGram|Metronome/PolyGram]] (now [[Universal Music]]) but they were turned down by the American division. Within a few months, &quot;All That She Wants&quot; had reached number 3 in [[Sweden]] and had spent eight weeks at number 1 in Germany.

In April 1993 the band performed alongside [[Inner Circle (reggae band)|Inner Circle]] and [[Dr. Alban]] in [[Tel Aviv, Israel]] at what would be their biggest audience ever, 55,000 people.

In May, &quot;All That She Wants&quot; continued to be a hit all around the world and topped the chart for three weeks in the United Kingdom.  However, despite [[Mega Records]]' hard efforts to secure a distribution deal in the United States the response was always the same: &quot;this band will never work in the States&quot;. Eventually, however, [[Clive Davis]], founder of [[Arista Records]], thought otherwise, and by the end of 1993 &quot;All That She Wants&quot; had made its way to #2 on the [[Billboard Hot 100]].

In order to freshen up the album for US release, Davis insisted that some new tracks were recorded, including &quot;[[The Sign (Ace of Base song)|The Sign]]&quot; which became the new title for the album and the second American single. It was even more successful than the first, spending six weeks at #1 and becoming the best-selling single of 1994. It was also a major hit in Europe, peaking at #2 in the UK and Sweden and doing one better in Germany.  PolyGram re-released the album under the name ''[[Happy Nation (US Version)]]''.

Two more singles were released: &quot;[[Don't Turn Around]]&quot; and &quot;[[Living in Danger]]&quot;, by [[Diane Warren]]. The former was originally recorded by [[Tina Turner]] on the [[b-side]] of a single she released which went on to become a UK #1 hit for the reggae band [[Aswad (band)|Aswad]]. Davis suggested that the band record the song and it was yet another worldwide hit. By the end of 1994, they were an  international commercial success.  The Ace of Base version of &quot;Don't Turn Around&quot; is distinguished from other versions by its use of a [[minor key]]

===Ace of Base on 1994 European Music Awards===
In 1994 Ace of Base performed on the first ever MTV Europe Music Awards held in Germany. Ace of Base performed &quot;[[Living in Danger]]&quot; in the  front of [[Berlin]]'s [[Brandenburg Gate]]. They were also nominated for Best Cover with &quot;[[Don't Turn Around]]&quot; this year.

===''The Bridge'' (1995–1996)===
Even though the band was exhausted from two long years of international promotion, they could hardly believe how successful they had become.  In April 1994, a crazed German fan broke into the Berggren family's home brandishing a knife.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} After managing to restrain her, the band decided that from then on they needed [[bodyguard]]s.  However, they were not allowed to take time to reflect before starting work on a second album because their record companies all over the world were demanding a swift follow-up.  To speed up the process, instead of Jonas and Ulf writing the bulk of the album, each member was encouraged to submit his or her own tracks for consideration. {{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

In the end, 17 tracks made the cut of the second album titled ''[[The Bridge (Ace of Base album)|The Bridge]]''. It marked a considerable change of direction in sound; out were the reggae and club sounds that made the group so popular in favour of a more experimental sound and several ballads.  The lead single &quot;[[Lucky Love]]&quot; however was a mainstream pop record and on release in October 1995 became the band's first number 1 single in Sweden, which came as a pleasant surprise as they had found that their fellow Swedes had been their harshest critics.  It charted at a more modest number 13 in Germany and number 20 in the United Kingdom, but Arista Records decided that it wasn't appropriate for US release so they opted for the pulsating dance beat of &quot;[[Beautiful Life (Ace of Base song)|Beautiful Life]]&quot; which peaked at number 15 both in the US and UK.  The album was still certified platinum but the phenomenal success of the band's first album proved difficult to follow.  In February 1996, the band performed at the [[Viña del Mar, Chile|Viña del Mar]] Festival de la Cancion in [[Chile]], topping the bill alongside [[2 Unlimited]].

===''Flowers'' (1997–1999)===
After this, Ace of Base disappeared from the limelight for a while, only emerging in July 1997 to perform at a concert to celebrate the 20th birthday of [[Victoria, Crown Princess of Sweden|Princess Victoria]] of Sweden.  They were given as much time as they wanted to produce their third album, much of it being recorded in Jonas' own studio &quot;The Barn&quot;.  When it was finally released in June 1998, the band declared it their best album yet. It was titled ''[[Flowers (Ace of Base album)|Flowers]]'' because they believed that the songs, wildly different in style including [[Motown]] and [[Gospel music|gospel]] influences, resembled a varied bouquet of flowers.  Fans were surprised to see that blonde singer Linn had relinquished lead vocal duties to sister Jenny, and on many promotional photos Linn's face was blurred.  They were reassured that Linn was happy with her new backing role in the group, and many reasons were given for her decision including her having damaged her voice, fear of flying putting her off from travelling round the world, and her dislike of fame.

The radio-friendly single &quot;[[Life Is a Flower]]&quot; was certified the most-played track on European radio for 1998 and sold more than 250,000 copies in the UK, peaking at number 5; the colorful video of the same name was produced and directed by [[Andreas Neumann]].  British label [[London Records]] had requested the band record the 1983 hit &quot;[[Cruel Summer]]&quot; by [[Bananarama]] and it was selected as the second European single.  Deciding that &quot;Life Is a Flower&quot; was &quot;too European in nature&quot;, Clive Davis pushed &quot;Cruel Summer&quot; as the lead-off single for the United States and it took Ace of Base back into the US Top 10 for the first time in four years, being certified gold.  The album was also re-named ''[[Cruel Summer (Ace of Base album)|Cruel Summer]]'' and featured a different tracklist to the European release.  Davis persuaded a reluctant Linn to record a Billy Steinberg ballad &quot;[[Everytime It Rains]]&quot; and &quot;Life Is a Flower&quot; was re-recorded as &quot;[[Whenever You're Near Me]]&quot; and was the second single, but it could only peak at number 76.  &quot;[[Travel to Romantis]]&quot; and &quot;[[Always Have Always Will|Always Have, Always Will]]&quot; were further hits in Europe while &quot;Everytime It Rains&quot; was issued as a single in the UK along with a re-packaged edition of ''Flowers'' released only in the UK.

===''Singles of the 90s'' and ''Greatest Hits'' (1999–2000)===
''[[Singles of the 90s]]'', a compilation of sixteen hit singles was released in November 1999.  Its first single, &quot;[[C'est La Vie (Always 21)]],&quot; went on to become a surprise number 1 hit in Spain.  Attempting to capitalize on the success of the previous single, &quot;[[Hallo Hallo (Ace of Base song)|Hallo Hallo]]&quot; was released with special remixes just for the Spanish market.  The album's marketing push closed with the limited radio-only single release of &quot;[[Love in December]]&quot;.  &quot;[[Everytime It Rains]]&quot;, previously included on the ''[[Cruel Summer]]'' album was released as a radio single in the US the following year in remixed-form (pushed by Clive Davis) in order to promote a new ''[[Greatest Hits (Ace of Base album)|Greatest Hits]]'' album for the American market, which failed to chart, selling fewer than 5,000 copies in its first week. It completed the band's four-album contract with Arista Records and was not renewed. &quot;Hallo Hallo&quot; was planned initially to be the first single from this American compilation, but in the end it was not included on the album at all. &quot;C'est La Vie (Always 21)&quot; was the only new recording included on the U.S. release.  Two old remixes of both &quot;[[Lucky Love]]&quot; and &quot;[[Beautiful Life (Ace of Base song)|Beautiful Life]]&quot; were also included.

===''Da Capo'' (2002–2003)===
Ace of Base released their fourth studio album ''[[Da Capo (Ace of Base album)|Da Capo]]'' in September 2002 in Europe, and in Japan through [[Toshiba EMI]] with a different cover and three bonus tracks. The album contained twelve original tracks and had originally been planned for release in mid-2000, but was repeatedly postponed due to record company complications.  The album is named after the musical term ''da capo'', meaning &quot;back to the beginning&quot;. It was intended to be a return to the band's earliest sound.

Although the album entered the album charts in many European countries, it was not as successful as previous releases. Only Jenny and Ulf went on a promotional tour of Sweden, Denmark, Norway, Finland, Germany, Poland and Austria; Jonas wanted to stay at home with his two children and Linn attended only one performance in Germany. The album was not released in America or Australia, and received only a 'soft release' in the United Kingdom, as their new British label [[Polydor]] thought that their sound was no longer relevant to the UK music scene.

The first single release from the ''Da Capo'' album was &quot;[[Beautiful Morning]]&quot;, which peaked at number 14 in Sweden and number 38 in Germany, where it was followed by &quot;[[The Juvenile]]&quot;, which was used for a Christmas campaign by German TV channel [[RTL Television|RTL]]. &quot;[[The Juvenile]]&quot; was a &quot;lost track&quot;; Ace of Base had previously written it for the ''[[Goldeneye]]'' James Bond movie in 1995. However, Arista, the band's American record label at the time, shelved the idea. The band was no longer involved in the soundtrack for the movie, and [[Bono]]'s composition of the same name was substituted, sung instead by [[Tina Turner]].

In Scandinavia, [[Edel-Mega]] released the album's opening track, &quot;[[Unspeakable (song)|Unspeakable]]&quot;, as the second single. But its poor chart performance ended the promotion of the album prematurely.

===Hiatus (2003–2006)===
The band remained out of the spotlight throughout 2003 and 2004, although Jenny kept busy by performing solo live performances in several Christian shows with her husband Jakob Pétren, and joined the Swedish group Arose.

The band returned at the end of 2005 (without Malin) for several live performances at the [[Night of the Proms]] in Belgium alongside other artists such as [[Donna Summer]], performing some of their hits such as &quot;All That She Wants&quot; and &quot;[[The Sign (song)|The Sign]]&quot;.

===Reunion and breakup (2007–2009)===
[[Image:Ace OF Base Vantaa Finlandia 2-10-2008.JPG|thumb|left|alt=Ulf, Jenny and Jonas after a concert in [[Finland]], 2008.|Ulf, Jenny and Jonas after a concert in [[Finland]], 2008.]]
Ace of Base reunited to perform their first full-length concert since 1996 in [[Yekaterinburg]], [[Russia]] on November 15, 2007. Several other concerts followed mainly in eastern Europe and [[Denmark]].  The set list included various songs from their past albums and notably, a brand new remix of their very first single &quot;Wheel of Fortune&quot;.

Jenny confirmed Linn's departure in Danish press: &quot;She hasn't been part of Ace of Base for several years,&quot; she stated in ''[[Se og Hør (Denmark)|Se &amp; Hør]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;SeHor&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| last =Olausen| first =Tonny| author-link =| title =Vi Elsker Danmark [We Love Denmark]| journal =Se &amp; Hør| volume =| issue =| pages =20–21| date =November 2007| year =| url =| doi =| id =| postscript =&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The band was on world tour and performed at several summer music festivals in 2008 and 2009. The tour reached [[Scandinavia]], some eastern European Countries as well as [[Singapore]] and the [[Dominican Republic]]. At their show at Rock Under Broen (Middelfart, [[Denmark]]) on June 14, 2008, the group performed a new song called &quot;Sparks from a Fire&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aceboards.com/index.php?showtopic=6706|title=New song performed at Rock Under Broen|first=AcerStan|date=2008-06-15|publisher=''The Ace Boards''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QCOyvBHCXZU|title=Ace of Base - Sparks From A Fire (Live in Vantaa)|date=2008-10-06|publisher=''YouTube|accessdate=2010-10=18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ace of Base released a new Greatest Hits CD/DVD, ''[[Greatest Hits, Classic Remixes and Music Videos]]'' on November 12, 2008. The 3-disc set includes one CD with the hits, a second CD containing remixes, and a DVD containing all the music videos.  Five re-recorded songs were released: &quot;Lucky Love 2009&quot;, &quot;Don't Turn Around 2009&quot;, &quot;Happy Nation 2009&quot;, &quot;The Sign - Freedom Bunch Mix&quot;, and &quot;Wheel of Fortune 2009&quot;, which was released worldwide on October 24, 2008 as a digital single.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playgroundmusic.com/Global/Articles.aspx?ProductId=PGMCDX%2055|title=Wheel of Fortune 2009|publisher=Playground Music Scandinavia|accessdate=2010-10-18}}{{Dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Breakup and Name Dispute'''

During the touring from 2007-2009, the band recorded new songs designated for a fifth studio album.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GndnwUOJUVE&lt;/ref&gt; The trio didn't get a record contract with the songs that were produced and Jenny announced she was working on her own solo material.&lt;ref name=&quot;marko-saavala.blogspot&quot;&gt;http://marko-saavala.blogspot.com/2010/05/jenny-berggren-slingrar-sig.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zxckegcJz8A&lt;/ref&gt;

During this time, Ulf and Jonas secretly recruited two other female vocalists, [[Clara Hagman]] and Julia Williamson.&lt;ref&gt;http://arbetarbladet.se/noje/spellistan/1.2200616-clara-hagmans-spellista&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aceboards&quot;&gt;http://www.aceboards.com/index.php?showtopic=8385&amp;st=0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aceboards.com/index.php?showtopic=8401&amp;st=0&lt;/ref&gt; When this came to the fans' attention, Jonas and Jenny independently stated that the new band would not be called Ace of Base, but have another name.&lt;ref name=&quot;aceboards&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tv4play&quot;&gt;http://www.tv4play.se/noje_och_humor/forkvall?videoId=1.1643333&lt;/ref&gt;

This alternative line-up later presented a slightly changed name: &quot;Ace.of.Base&quot;, but this was mainly a graphical adjustment used on the cover of their releases only. In an interview for Swedish TV Ulf stated: ''&quot;We're still called Ace of Base. The dots are more for styling and the logo&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tv4play.se/noje/forkvall?title=hur_ar_det_att_jobba_med_farbroder%3F&amp;videoid=1137145&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/aceofbase/posts/117459284973810&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aceofbase-music.de/biography&lt;/ref&gt; 

Jenny has stated several times that she has never left the band and on the contrary declared that all four original members are still band members and own the brand Ace of Base, by agreement with her brother Jonas and by legal documents.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/permalink.php?story_fbid=110543982317036&amp;id=349147288370&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/permalink.php?story_fbid=116101985084450&amp;id=349147288370&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;marko-saavala.blogspot&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tv4play&quot; /&gt;

This was later confirmed by Jonas in an interview stating: &quot;''She (Jenny) never officially said ‘’I quit’’. But to the record company, she was a leaving member. And they cancelled her contract. But she never said ‘’Oh, I don’t want to be in the band’’''.&quot; Additionally Jonas said in this interview, asked about why Jenny refused to accept a new 4th member beside her: &quot;'' At first Jenny said ‘’yes, I can do that’’. But then it was always no. And what she wanted to do was impossible, for all kinds of reasons. You say yes, but then you have so many terms, and it has to be this and this and this and this, that you actually really mean no. You can act like you’re very very positive about it all, but you really mean no. And then we found out from the record label that she had gone and recorded her solo album, and that caught us by surprise. She had told us that she was just going to record some church songs, but this was a proper album, so we were really caught by surprise. ''&quot;. When asked about the record company demanding a new additional singer: &quot;''It wasn’t so much that it had to be younger girl, but yes, they wanted a new girl, a new lead vocalist.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scandipop.co.uk/?p=3615|title=The Ace of Base Interview|publisher=''www.scandipop.co.uk''|accessdate=2010-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding the name dispute, Ulf stated that he had &quot;No problems using the name even though all the original members are not included&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.aftonbladet.se/nojesbladet/musik/rockbjornen2010/article7429969.ab&lt;/ref&gt; Jenny commented further on this topic in a 2010 newspaper interview. She said she wasn't allowed by Jonas and Ulf to participate in the songwriting for the band's album. ''&quot;From now on, I want things in writing. I agreed to work under certain conditions, and they just vanished.&quot; &quot;They didn't want me in&quot;.'' When asked, &quot;Do you want to go back to Ace of Base again?&quot; she responded &quot;''Not right now. It would take some apologies''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aftonbladet.se/nojesbladet/musik/article7971852.ab&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jenny Berggren]] released her first autobiography &quot;Vinna hela världen&quot; (&quot;To Win The World&quot;) in late September 2009.  It is currently only available in Swedish, but will be translated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://twitter.com/#!/jennyberggren/status/11138713993|title=@Jenny Berggren|last=Berggren|first=Jenny|date=2010-03-27|publisher=''Twitter''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported in December 2009 that she was being considered as the final wildcard &quot;joker&quot; in [[Melodifestivalen 2010]], Sweden's national selection show for the [[Eurovision Song Contest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.expressen.se/noje/1.1805611/de-tavlar-om-sista-platsen|title=De tävlar om sista platsen|last=Johansson|first=Lars|date=2009-12-07|publisher=''Expressen.se''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ultimately, she was not selected.

On November 13, 2009, Ulf, acting as head judge on [[Idol 2009]], announced, &quot;We're in the studio right now, planning to release a new album in the beginning of next year. It's practically finished and we're negotiating with different labels.  That's all I can say.&quot;

===New members and relaunch (2010 – present)===

In late June, 2010, Facebook and Twitter accounts for an Ulf and Jonas project without Jenny were launched under the name Ace of Base. Pictures have been released via these accounts featuring two new vocalists, whose names have been given as Clara and Julia. One of them is [[Clara Hagman]], who made it to the semi-finals round of [[Idol 2009]], on which Ulf appeared as a judge. The first single from ''[[The Golden Ratio (album)|The Golden Ratio]]'', &quot;[[All for You (Ace of Base song)|All For You]]&quot;, was serviced to European radio stations in mid-July 2010 and was released as a single on September 10, 2010. ''The Golden Ratio'' was released on September 24, 2010. The album entered the German album charts at #20. &quot;[[All for You (Ace of Base song)|All For You]]&quot; reached #38 in the official German singles chart.

==Singers and musicians influenced by Ace of Base==

Many musicians and singers have cited Ace of Base as a musical influence: [[Lady Gaga]] has claimed that her album ''[[The Fame Monster]]'', with songs such as &quot;[[Alejandro (song)|Alejandro]]&quot;, was influenced by &quot;super pop melodies of the 90s&quot; by acts such as Ace of Base.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.com/?bcpid=40911305001&amp;bctid=52584416001#/news/lady-gaga-talks-fame-monster-freakishness-1004048479.story|title=Lady Gaga Talks &quot;Fame Monster,&quot; Freakishness|date=2009-11-25|publisher=''Billboard.com''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The song &quot;[[Eh, Eh (Nothing Else I Can Say)]]&quot; from ''[[The Fame]]'' has also been likened to the band.

[[Katy Perry]] has claimed that she would like her follow-up album to ''[[One of the Boys (Katy Perry album)|One of the Boys]]'' to sound like &quot;The Sign&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1622080/20090922/katy_perry.jhtml|title=Katy Perry Wants To Make New Music Her Fans Can 'Roller-Skate To'|last=Elias|first=Matt|date=2009-09-23|publisher=''[[MTV]]''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;It's what I said I wanted earlier,&quot; she told MTV. &quot;We nailed it: It's roller-skating! It's '90s! It's Ace Of Base! It's Cyndi Lauper! It's like all these colors and more&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fmqb.com/article.asp?id=1750575|title=Katy Perry Excited For Her New Summer Record|date=2010-03-29|publisher=''FMQB''|accessdate=2010-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The British pop group [[Steps (group)|Steps]]' third album ''[[Buzz (Steps album)|Buzz]]'' was also reportedly influenced by their early material.

==Awards==
* 1993 Swedish [[Grammis|Grammi]] &amp;ndash; Best Pop Group &lt;ref name=&quot;Grammy Sweden 1990&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ifpi.se/wp/wp-content/uploads/100428-lc-vinnare-genom-%C3%A5ren.pdf|title=Grammy Sweden 1990|publisher=''ifpi''|accessdate=2010-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1993 Swedish [[Grammis|Grammi]] &amp;ndash; TV audience price &lt;ref name=&quot;Grammy Sweden 1990&quot;/&gt;
* 1993 Bronze [[Bravo (magazine)|BRAVO]] Otto (Germany) &amp;ndash; Best rock/pop Group&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bravo-archiv.de/auswahl.php?link=ottosieger1993.php|title=Bravo magazine archive&amp;ndash;Otto awards 1993|publisher=''[[Bravo (magazine)|BRAVO]]''|accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1994 American Music Award &amp;ndash; Favorite Band, Duo or Group - Pop / Rock
* 1994 American Music Award &amp;ndash; Favorite New Artist - Pop / Rock
* 1994 Billboard Music Award &amp;ndash; No.1 Single
* 1994 Billboard Music Award &amp;ndash; Top New Artist
* 1994 Billboard Music Award &amp;ndash; Artist of The Year
* 1994 World Music Award &amp;ndash; World's Best-Selling Scandinavian Recording Artists of the Year
* 1994 Echo (Germany) &amp;ndash; Group of the Year &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.echopop.de/der_echo/die_preistraeger?eid=12|title=Echo Preisträger|publisher=''Echo''|accessdate=2010-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1995 Grammy Awards &amp;ndash; Pop Vocal Group(Nominee)
* 1995 Grammy Awards &amp;ndash; New Artist(Nominee)
* 1995 World Music Award &amp;ndash; World's Best-Selling Scandinavian Recording Artists of the Year
* 1996 World Music Award &amp;ndash; World's Best-Selling Scandinavian Recording Artists of the Year
* 1997 World Music Award &amp;ndash; World's Best-Selling Scandinavian Recording Artists of the Year
* 2007 BMI Award for over 3 million performances of 'The Sign' on US TV and radio &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bmi.com/news/entry/535579|title=BMI Awards|publisher=''BMI''|accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2011 The scandipop award &amp;ndash; Best Group Album &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scandipop.co.uk/?p=4386 List of Scandy Pop awards 2011 winners]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
''For more on all single and album releases including extended chart information, see [[Ace of Base discography]]''.

''For a complete list of all the songs, see [[List of Ace of Base songs]]''

===Studio albums===
* ''[[Happy Nation]]'' / ''The Sign'' (1993)
* ''[[The Bridge (Ace of Base album)|The Bridge]]'' (1995)
* ''[[Flowers (Ace of Base album)|Flowers]]'' / ''[[Cruel Summer (Ace of Base album)|Cruel Summer]]'' (1998)
* ''[[Da Capo (Ace of Base album)|Da Capo]]'' (2002)
* ''[[The Golden Ratio (album)|The Golden Ratio]]'' (2010)

=== Number one singles ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot;
!align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Year
!align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Single
!align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;8&quot; | Chart position
|- bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFFF&quot;
! width=&quot;60&quot;|U.S.&lt;br&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Hot 100&lt;/sup&gt;
! width=&quot;60&quot;|U.S.&lt;br&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Mainstream&lt;/sup&gt;
! width=&quot;60&quot;|U.S.&lt;br&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Dance&lt;/sup&gt;
! width=&quot;60&quot;|UK
! width=&quot;60&quot;|CAN
! width=&quot;60&quot;|GER
! width=&quot;60&quot;|SWE
! width=&quot;60&quot;|ESP
! width=&quot;60&quot;|RUS
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;1&quot;|1993
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[All That She Wants]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|3
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|1994
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[The Sign (song)|The Sign]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|13
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|align=&quot;center&quot;|
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[Don't Turn Around]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|4
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|36
|align=&quot;center&quot;|5
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|6
|align=&quot;center&quot;|11
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[Living in Danger]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|20
|align=&quot;center&quot;|7
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|18
|align=&quot;center&quot;|4
|align=&quot;center&quot;|23
|align=&quot;center&quot;|15
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|11
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|1995
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[Lucky Love]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|30
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|20
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|align=&quot;center&quot;|13
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|8
|align=&quot;center&quot;|14
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[Beautiful Life (Ace of Base song)|Beautiful Life]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|15
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|15
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|20
|align=&quot;center&quot;|22
|align=&quot;center&quot;|10
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;1&quot;|1999
|align=&quot;left&quot;|&quot;[[C'est la Vie (Always 21)]]&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot;|64
|align=&quot;center&quot;|38
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|-
|-
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|'''Total number one hits
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|3
|align=&quot;center&quot;|3
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|4
|align=&quot;center&quot;|2
|align=&quot;center&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot;|3
|align=&quot;center&quot;|4
|}

==See also==
*[[Swedish pop music]]
*[[List of best-selling music artists]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.aceofbase.com Ace of Base official web site]
*[http://www.facebook.com/aceofbase Ace of Base Official Facebook Page]
*[http://www.myspace.com/aceofbase Ace of Base Official MySpace Page]
*[http://www.twitter.com/aceofbase Ace of Base Official Twitter Page]

{{Ace of Base}}
{{Billboard Year-End number one singles 1980–1999}}
{{Billboard Year-End number one albums 1990–2009}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ace Of Base}}
[[Category:Ace of Base| ]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1990]]
[[Category:Musical groups from Gothenburg]]
[[Category:Reggae fusion artists]]
[[Category:Swedish electronic music groups]]
[[Category:Swedish pop music groups]]
[[Category:Swedish house music groups]]
[[Category:Techno music groups]]
[[Category:Synthpop groups]]
[[Category:Eurodance groups]]
[[Category:Arista Records artists]]

[[ar:أيس أوف بيس]]
[[bg:Ace Of Base]]
[[ca:Ace of Base]]
[[cs:Ace of Base]]
[[da:Ace of Base]]
[[de:Ace of Base]]
[[el:Ace of Base]]
[[es:Ace of Base]]
[[fa:ایس آو بیس]]
[[fr:Ace of Base]]
[[ko:에이스 오브 베이스]]
[[it:Ace of Base]]
[[he:אייס אוף בייס]]
[[ka:Ace of Base]]
[[lt:Ace of Base]]
[[hu:Ace of Base]]
[[nl:Ace of Base]]
[[ja:エイス・オブ・ベイス]]
[[no:Ace of Base]]
[[nn:Ace of Base]]
[[pl:Ace of Base]]
[[pt:Ace of Base]]
[[ro:Ace of Base]]
[[ru:Ace of Base]]
[[simple:Ace of Base]]
[[fi:Ace of Base]]
[[sv:Ace of Base]]
[[th:เอซออฟเบส]]
[[tr:Ace of Base]]
[[uk:Ace of Base]]
[[vi:Ace of Base]]
[[zh:爱司基地]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
