<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4020635" ns="0" title="Barbaro"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Thoroughbred racehorse infobox
|horsename= Barbaro

'''
|image= [[Image:Barbaro-005.jpg|250px]]
|caption= Barbaro (middle) walking to the track at the [[Fair Hill Training Center]] a week after winning the [[Kentucky Derby]]
|sire= [[Dynaformer]]
|grandsire = [[Roberto (horse)|Roberto]]
|dam= La Ville Rouge
|damsire= Carson City
|sex= [[Colt (horse)|Colt]]
|foaled= April 29, 2003
|death= January 29, 2007
|country= [[United States]]
|colour= [[Bay (horse)|Bay]]
|breeder= Lael Stables
|owner= Roy and Gretchen Jackson
|trainer= [[Michael R. Matz]]
|record= 7:6-0-0 (1 DNF)
|earnings= $2,302,200
|race= [[Laurel Futurity]] (2005)&lt;br&gt;[[Tropical Park Derby]] (2006)&lt;br&gt;[[Holy Bull Stakes]] (2006)&lt;br&gt;[[Florida Derby]] (2006)
&lt;br&gt;
'''[[American Classic Races|American Classic Race]] wins:'''&lt;br&gt;[[Kentucky Derby]] (2006)
|awards= [[National Thoroughbred Racing Association Moment of the Year|NTRA &quot;Moment of the Year&quot;]] (2006)
|honours= [[Barbaro Stakes at Pimlico Race Course]]&lt;br&gt;[[Barbaro Stakes at Delaware Park]]

}}
'''Barbaro''' (April 29, 2003 – January 29, 2007) was an American [[thoroughbred]] who decisively won the 2006 [[Kentucky Derby]], but shattered his leg two weeks later in the 2006 [[Preakness Stakes]], ending his racing career and eventually leading to his death.

On May 20, 2006, Barbaro ran in the Preakness Stakes as a heavy favorite, but, after he false-started, he fractured three bones in and around the fetlock of his right hind leg. The injury ruined any chance of a [[Triple Crown of Thoroughbred Racing|Triple Crown]] in 2006 and ended his racing career. The next day, he underwent surgery at the [[New Bolton Center]] at the [[University of Pennsylvania]] for his injuries. In July he developed [[laminitis]] in his left rear leg. He underwent five further operations, and his prognosis varied during an exceptionally long stay in the Equine Intensive Care Unit at the New Bolton Center. While his right hind leg eventually healed, a final risky procedure on it proved futile because the colt soon developed further laminitis in both [[equine forelimb anatomy|front legs]]. His [[veterinarian]]s and owners concluded that he could not be saved, and Barbaro was [[Animal euthanasia|euthanized]] on January 29, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;Smiley, Jane (2007), [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/29/AR2007012901004.html &quot;Barbaro, The Heart in the Winner's Circle: Time Line&quot;], The Washington Post, 30 Jan, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was a third-generation descendant of [[Mr. Prospector]], and as such Barbaro was related to many Triple Crown hopefuls of his time including [[Big Brown]], [[Afleet Alex]], [[Smarty Jones]], [[Funny Cide]] and [[Fusaichi Pegasus]].

==2006 Kentucky Derby==
[[Image:Barbaro2006.jpg|thumb|left|2006 Kentucky Derby Winner's Sign at Churchill Downs]]
Going into the [[2006 Kentucky Derby|Kentucky Derby]], Barbaro was undefeated. He was sent off as the second choice of the betting public, at odds of 6:1, in a full field of twenty horses. Barbaro charged ahead during the last turn and straightaway of the race to win by six and a half lengths. Barbaro's lead in the final furlong expanded, although jockey [[Edgar Prado]] did not use the whip and ask for his top speed. This margin of victory at the Kentucky Derby was the largest since 1946, when Triple Crown winner [[Assault (horse)|Assault]] took the &quot;Run for the Roses&quot; by eight lengths. Barbaro's win made him only the sixth undefeated horse to win the Kentucky Derby.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/sports/horse/triplecrown06/news/story?id=2435981 &quot;Barbaro makes Derby his sixth victory in six starts&quot;]. [[ESPN]], May 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  Barbaro had not competed for five weeks prior to the race, which was the longest layoff in 50 years for a Derby winner.

==2006 Preakness Stakes and injury==
Barbaro's [[Preakness Stakes]] began with a false start when he broke from the starting gate prematurely. Barbaro was deemed fit upon being reloaded into the gate.&lt;ref&gt;Maryland's Chief Veterinarian, David G. Zipf, personally attested to Barbaro's fitness&lt;/ref&gt; As the restarted race began, Barbaro broke cleanly, but suffered a catastrophic injury as the horses passed the grandstand shortly after the start.

Many theories as to the cause of the accident have been offered, though none have been confirmed. Barbaro broke his right hind [[Skeletal system of the horse|leg]] in more than 20 places:&lt;ref&gt;[[Bob Costas]] on the television special ''Barbaro: A Nation's Horse'' states that there were more than 20 breaks&lt;/ref&gt; a broken cannon bone above the pastern, a broken [[sesamoid bone]] behind the fetlock and a broken long [[pastern]] bone below the fetlock. The [[fetlock]] joint was dislocated, and his foot was left dangling loosely. Veteran jockey Edgar Prado immediately pulled Barbaro up, and brought him to a gentle stop. He dismounted and leaned his shoulder into the horse's shoulder to support Barbaro until track attendants could arrive. [[Bernardini]] went on to win the race.

==Injury aftermath==
Barbaro's injuries were life-threatening, partially because a thoroughbred's breeding optimizes its anatomy for speed rather than durability. Unlike other mammals, such as dogs, a horse cannot survive in humane circumstances on three legs. A broken leg in a horse can lead to complications as the other legs attempt to bear the weight of the horse's body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slate.com/id/2142159 &quot;Explainer: Why a Broken Leg Is Bad News for a Horse&quot;] ''Slate'', May 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Initial surgery===
In 1971 [[Hoist The Flag]] underwent successful pioneering surgery for a similar injury as that suffered by Barbaro.[http://www.ntra.com/video.aspx?id=18273] Having been taken to the [[University of Pennsylvania]]'s [[New Bolton Center]] in [[Kennett Square, Pennsylvania]] for treatment, Barbaro was assigned to the care of equine surgeon Dr. Dean Richardson. The New Bolton Center is renowned for its specialized care, especially for animals needing complicated bone surgery. The day after the race, Richardson performed a fusion of the fetlock and pastern joints to stabilize the leg and make it strong enough for Barbaro to walk on. It was a five hour procedure and was one of the most difficult surgeries Richardson had performed. The surgical team successfully implanted a [[Synthes]] [[stainless steel]] Locking Compression Plate (LCP) and 27 screws into the colt's injured leg to span the comminuted fracture and joints. They used the LCP because its screws thread into the plate to provide maximum strength. Richardson was one of the first equine surgeons to implement this new technology, originally designed for humans. A fiberglass cast was placed over the LCP to further protect the construct. Barbaro was put into the recovery pool at 7:40 pm.&lt;ref name=&quot;surgery&quot;&gt;[http://msn.foxsports.com/horseracing/story/5626796 &quot;Derby winner Barbaro undergoes surgery&quot;]. [[Associated Press|AP]], May 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timwoolleyracing.com/news/|title=Tim Woolley Horseracing News|accessdate=May 22, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After about an hour in the pool, at around 9:00 p.m. EDT, Barbaro began to calmly awaken from the anesthesia. He stood and then practically jogged to his stall. He ate and was able to comfortably put weight on the injured leg. The blood supply to the injury site was very good, but Richardson still gave Barbaro a 50-50 chance of survival.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tcm.bloodhorse.com/viewstory.asp?id=33671 &quot;After Successful Surgery, Barbaro's Chances Remain 'Coin Toss'&quot;]. [[The Blood-Horse magazine|The Blood-Horse]], May 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firstcoastnews.com/sports/news-article.aspx?storyid=58016 &quot;Barbaro surgery successful, Derby winner begins road to recovery&quot;]. AP, May 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; By the following morning Barbaro was already showing interest in some of the mares at the facility. He was walking well on his limb around the stall and was quite active for his condition; in short, his first week of recovery went well. The cast was replaced on June 13, and again on July 3.

===Complications===
In the first week of July, complications arose, and Barbaro had problems with both hind legs. He developed an [[abscess]] on his uninjured left foot, which was treated topically, but he carried a fever through the weekend and failed to put weight on his injured right foot for any significant time.

By July 13, Barbaro had developed a severe case of [[laminitis]] in the left hind hoof—a potentially life-threatening affliction that is common in horses who shift weight to one foot for extended periods to keep pressure off an injured foot (in Barbaro's case, the right ankle he broke in the Preakness). A procedure called a hoof wall [[Segmental resection|resection]] removed 80% of Barbaro's left rear hoof. The remaining 20% of his hoof wall was still attached to the coffin bone and was still living tissue, but it was unclear how much of it would grow back. Both rear legs were in casts. Richardson stated that his plans were to restrict himself to aggressive but standard treatments; he would use no experimental procedures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.breitbart.com/news/2006/07/13/D8IR84907.html|title=Barbaro May Die Due to Foot Inflamation (sic)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.horsetalk.co.nz/news/0607/063.shtml Vets lose confidence in Barbaro's recovery; laminitis hits] July 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/R/RAC_BARBARO?SITE=TXMID&amp;SECTION=HOME&amp;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT &quot;Doctors Say Barbaro's Life Is at Risk Due to an Inflammation in His Left Hind Foot&quot;] [[Associated Press]], July 14, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2006/more/07/14/barbaro.better.ap/index.html Barbaro doing 'much better'] July 14, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Barbaro was given a special support boot for his laminitic hoof and placed on painkillers; a support sling was brought into his stall to allow him to take the weight off his hooves for hours at a time.

===Slow recovery===
On August 8 Barbaro's broken right leg had fused to the point where the veterinarians would have replaced the cast with a brace if his left leg had been sound. The coronary band (the area from which the hoof grows) on his left leg appeared healthy and all signs were encouraging.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/sports/horse/news/story?id=2536511 Veterinarian: Barbaro's right hind leg healing well] August 1, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; On August 15 it was reported that Barbaro had been allowed to graze outside for the first time since his accident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://horseracing.sportsline.com/cbs/headlines/showarticle.aspx?articleId=12153 Barbaro goes out to graze] August 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Two days later, Barbaro was no longer using the sling to support his weight, and its use was discontinued.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/sports/horse/news/story?id=2552969 Barbaro no longer needs support sling] August 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, August 18, radiographs showed that his fractured right leg was almost completely fused.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vet.upenn.edu/newsandevents/news/Barbaro_Update8-28.htm|title=Barbaro has cast change|accessdate=2007-02-11|date=2006-08-28|author=Penn Veterinary Medicine |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070204095623/http://www.vet.upenn.edu/newsandevents/news/Barbaro_Update8-28.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By September 26, it was decided that Barbaro's cast would not be replaced as long as he was comfortable in it. His left hind hoof had regrown about 18 millimeters and the support shoe had been replaced with a bandage. The hoof would have to grow to at least three times that length, a process that could take more than six months.

On October 10, Barbaro's cast and protective shoe were changed. His left rear hoof was gradually improving from laminitis. There was good growth along the quarters (closer to the heel) but there were still months of healing required for the front of the hoof.&lt;ref&gt;[http://msn.foxsports.com/horseracing/story/6047292?FSO1&amp;ATT=HCP&amp;GT1=8705 Barbaro's condition gradually improving] Associated Press, October 10, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Barbaro reached another milestone on November 6, 2006 when his cast was removed permanently and replaced with a splinted bandage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baltimoresun.com/sports/horseracing/bal-sp.digesttop07nov07,0,7371513.story?coll=bal-sports-horse After cast removed, Barbaro uses 'all of his legs quite well'] &quot;The Baltimore Sun&quot;, November 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Barbaro's laminitic hoof showed no new problems, but several months of growth would have been necessary before it could be further diagnosed. Around December 12, Barbaro's bandage on his right hind leg was removed completely. This was announced during a press conference on Wednesday, December 13.

===Further complications and death===
Early in January 2007, the laminitic left hoof became the source of further complications. On January 10, another section of the hoof was surgically removed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vet.upenn.edu/newsandevents/news/Barbaro_Update1-10.htm Barbaro suffers setback] January 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Updates over the next few days revealed that the cast had been reapplied to Barbaro's right hind leg for support, and that aggressive pain management and the use of the support sling had been resumed. Nevertheless, Barbaro's condition was better than it had been the previous July.

In another setback, Barbaro developed a deep [[abscess]] in his right hind foot, a problem generally caused by lack of grip exercise. Additional surgery was performed on January 27 to insert two steel pins into the healed bones of Barbaro's right foot as part of an external skeletal fixation device. This would allow the right foot to bear more weight, but the procedure was risky, with the major danger being that the bones might break again.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070128/ap_on_sp_ot/rac_barbaro Barbaro has another significant setback] January 28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2007/more/01/28/bc.rac.barbaro.ap/index.html Latest surgery on right hind leg marks new setback] SI.com, January 29, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Later that same weekend, Barbaro's front legs, which had remained healthy throughout the ordeal, displayed clear signs of laminitis due to him not being able to bear weight on his hind legs.  Thus, Barbaro could not then comfortably put his weight on any of his legs.  


Barbaro was [[animal euthanasia|euthanized]] on January 29, 2007 at around 10:30 A.M. EST by decision of his owners Roy and Gretchen Jackson, who indicated that they felt that his pain was no longer manageable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/sports/horse/news/story?id=2747087 Barbaro euthanized Monday morning] January 29, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

For his efforts to save Barbaro, the Turf Publicists of America voted to award Richardson their 2006 [[Big Sport of Turfdom Award]].

==Memorial==
[[File:Barbaro's Monument.jpg|thumb|right|200px| Monument and statue honoring Barbaro at entrance to Churchill Downs.]]
Barbaro was cremated shortly after he was euthanized. On January 29, 2008 it was announced that his remains would be interred in front of an entrance to Churchill Downs, and that a bronze statue of Barbaro would be placed atop his remains. The Jacksons chose to place his remains outside of both Churchill Downs and the adjacent [[Kentucky Derby Museum]] to allow his many admirers to pay their respects without having to pay an admission fee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.yahoo.com/rah/news?slug=ap-barbaro-churchilldowns&amp;prov=ap&amp;type=lgns |author=Graves, Will, [[Associated Press]]|title=Barbaro’s ashes and bronze statue to be placed at Churchill Downs|publisher=[[Yahoo!|Yahoo! Sports]] |date=2008-01-29 |accessdate=2008-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Barbaro Sculpture, created by Alexa King, was unveiled April 26, 2009 at Churchill Downs, the week preceding the Kentucky Derby.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bloodhorse.com/article/43312.htm?id=43312 |author=Ron Mitchell |title=Barbaro Statue to be Unveiled |publisher=The Blood-Horse magazine|date=2009-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gulfstream Park]] established scholarships to the [[University of Florida]] with an initial total funding of $30,000 for two fourth-year students in Veterinary Medicine and one graduate student in equine veterinary research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ntra.com/content.aspx?type=news&amp;id=23973|author=Welsch, Mike|title=Barbaro inspires scholarship fund|publisher=[[Daily Racing Form]]|date=2007-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Barbaro also inspired a large anonymous donation to the New Bolton Center, allowing the establishment of the Barbaro Fund to aid the treatment and care of large animals.

In 2006, a Limited Edition Ty [[Beanie Babies]] Barbaro Beanie plushie was released. The plushie is 7&amp;nbsp;inches tall, 8&amp;nbsp;inches long and wears Barbaro's No. 8 on a pink saddle cloth.

In 2007, Breyer Animal Creations released a Barbaro model that includes a Certificate of Authenticity from his owners, jockey, and main doctor at the New Bolton Center.

The Jacksons have endowed a chair for equine disease research at the University of Pennsylvania's veterinary school.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ntra.com/content.aspx?type=news&amp;id=23392 Jacksons give $3M for research] February 13, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In honor of Barbaro's valiant fight against his injuries in the 2006 Preakness Stakes, NTRA has established the NTRA Charities, Barbaro Memorial Fund. This fund will focus on Equine Health and Safety, which will include research to find a cure for laminitis, the disease that ultimately led to Barbaro's death.

==Public reaction==
After his breakdown in the Preakness, Barbaro became the object of public affection. His stall at the New Bolton Center was decorated with many thousands of [[greeting card|Get Well cards]] (including a 7&amp;nbsp;ft by 72&amp;nbsp;ft card from fans at the [[Belmont Stakes]]), and flowers and presents sent in by fans. Others sent in items meant to help his recovery, such as saint medallions and holy water. His condition was reported by news organizations on a daily basis.

Over the course of Barbaro's treatment and after his death, there were sections of the media that felt that Barbaro did not merit the amount of attention that he was receiving from either his supporters or the media.
Others suggested that Barbaro had demonstrated a disposition that might enable him to survive and in time become a stud.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.courant.com/sports/bal-te.medical21may21,0,6592683.story &quot;Poise on the track may save horse's life&quot;] ''The Baltimore Sun'', May 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine commented that despite the difficulties, Barbaro's fight was inspiring and that the hope for a near-miracle was not pointless.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1583250,00.html|title=Barbaro: Was It All Worth It?|author=Time Magazine|authorlink=Time Magazine|date=2007-01-29|accessdate=2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Barbaro's accident and difficulties have led some to call for a review of the practices of tradition-bound thoroughbred horse racing and breeding. Many acknowledge that modern thoroughbreds are more delicate than their forebears. Barbaro's injury intensified the debate over the use of artificial track surfaces at racecourses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/sports/horse/columns/story?columnist=forde_pat&amp;id=2747259 Barbaro's death: Equine beauty meets harsh reality] Jan. 30, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Connections==
Barbaro was bred and owned by Gretchen and Roy Jackson's Lael Stables of [[West Grove, Pennsylvania]].

Barbaro was trained by [[Michael R. Matz]] at [[Fair Hill Training Center]]. During his racing career he was ridden by [[Edgar Prado]] and Jose Caraballo. Neither jockey rode him at any time other than in his races: Peter Brette was his regular exercise rider.

==Pedigree==
{{Pedigree
|name = Barbaro
|f = [[Dynaformer]]&lt;br /&gt;dk. b/br. 1985
|m = La Ville Rouge&lt;br /&gt; b. 1996 &lt;!-- article deleted 10-Jun-2006 and 2-Feb-2007; see [[Wikipedia:Articles for deletion/La Ville Rouge]] --&gt;
|ff = [[Roberto (horse)|Roberto]]&lt;br /&gt;b. 1969
|fm = Andover Way&lt;br /&gt;dk. b/br. 1978
|mf = Carson City&lt;br /&gt;ch. 1987
|mm = La Reine Rouge&lt;br /&gt;b. 1978
|fff = [[Hail To Reason]]&lt;br /&gt;br. 1958
|ffm = Bramalea&lt;br /&gt;dk. b/br. 1959
|fmf = His Majesty&lt;br /&gt;b. 1968
|fmm = On The Trail&lt;br /&gt;b. 1964
|mff = [[Mr. Prospector]]&lt;br /&gt;b. 1970
|mfm = Blushing Promise&lt;br /&gt;b. 1982
|mmf = [[King's Bishop]]&lt;br /&gt;b. 1969
|mmm = Silver Betsy&lt;br /&gt;b. 1971
|ffff = [[Turn-To]]
|fffm = Nothirdchance
|ffmf = [[Nashua (horse)|Nashua]]
|ffmm = Rarelea
|fmff = [[Ribot (horse)|Ribot]]
|fmfm = Flower Bowl
|fmmf = Olympia
|fmmm = Golden Trail
|mfff = [[Raise a Native]]
|mffm = Gold Digger
|mfmf = [[Blushing Groom]]
|mfmm = Summertime Promise
|mmff = [[Round Table (horse)|Round Table]]
|mmfm = Spearfish
|mmmf = [[Nearctic (horse)|Nearctic]]
|mmmm = Silver Abbey
|}}

==Racing career==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|'''Dat'''e
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Race
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Track
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Location
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Distance
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Surface
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Condition
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Finish
|-
|October 4, 2005
|[[Maiden]]
|[[Delaware Park (race track)|Delaware Park]]
|[[Wilmington, Delaware]]
|1&amp;nbsp;mi.
|Turf
|Firm
|1st
|-
|nowrap|November 19, 2005
|[[Laurel Futurity]]
|[[Laurel Park Racecourse]]
|[[Laurel, Maryland]]
|1{{Fraction|1|16}} mi.
|Turf
|Firm
|1st
|-
|January 1, 2006
|[[Tropical Park Derby]]
|[[Calder Race Course]]
|[[Miami Gardens, Florida]]
|1{{Fraction|1|8}} mi.
|Turf
|Firm
|1st
|-
|February 4, 2006
|[[Holy Bull Stakes]]
|[[Gulfstream Park]]
|[[Hallandale Beach, Florida]]
|1{{Fraction|1|8}} mi.
|Dirt
|Sloppy
|1st
|-
|April 1, 2006
|[[Florida Derby]]
|Gulfstream Park
|Hallandale Beach, Florida
|1{{Fraction|1|8}} mi.
|Dirt
|Fast
|1st
|-
|May 6, 2006
|[[Kentucky Derby]]
|[[Churchill Downs]]
|[[Louisville, Kentucky]]
|1{{Fraction|1|4}} mi.
|Dirt
|Fast
|1st
|-
|May 20, 2006
|[[Preakness Stakes]]
|[[Pimlico Race Course]]
|[[Baltimore, Maryland]]
|1{{Fraction|3|16}} mi.
|Dirt
|Fast
|DNF, injury
|}

==Honors==
*[[Pimlico Race Course|Pimlico Racecourse]] has renamed the [[Sir Barton]] Stakes the [[Barbaro Stakes at Pimlico Race Course|Barbaro Stakes]]. The race is a part of the [[Preakness Stakes]] Day undercard. The winner of the first Barbaro Stakes on May 19, 2007 was Chelokee, a three year old colt trained by Michael Matz.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pimlico.com/NewsEvents/FeatureStories/Details/Baltimore122006B.htm Barbaro Stakes to Debut at Pimlico in May 2007 After Maryland Jockey Club Renames Sir Barton Stakes] December 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Delaware Park Racetrack]] also renamed the Leonard Richards Stakes, a Grade III race for three year olds, the [[Barbaro Stakes at Delaware Park|Barbaro Stakes]].  Its inaugural running took place on Sunday, July 15, 2007 and was won by Xchanger.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ntra.com/content.aspx?type=news&amp;id=26592 Xchanger finds winning formula in Barbaro S. - NTRA&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
Several books have been written about Barbaro. In 2007, [[HarperCollins]] published ''[[Barbaro: A Nation's Love Story]]'' written by Pamela K.Brodowsky and Tom Philbin. ''[[Barbaro, Smarty Jones &amp; Ruffian: The People's Horses]]'', written by Linda Hanna was published in 2008 by Middle Atlantic Press as was ''[[My Guy Barbaro: A Jockey's Journey Through Love, Triumph, and Heartbreak with America's Favorite Horse]]'' written by Edgar Prado, Barbaro's Derby-winning jockey, co-written by John Eisenberg and published by HarperCollins.

==Feature Film==
In 2007 [[Universal Pictures]] announced director [[Peter Berg]] would be producing and directing a feature film entitled &quot;Gone Like The Wind&quot; based on an article published in [[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]] by [[Buzz Bissinger]]. Berg and Bissinger previously worked together on [[Friday Night Lights (film)|Friday Night Lights]]. Berg will be producing the film along with [[Sarah Aubrey]]. The film has currently been shelved in favor of the Peter Berg directed ''[[Battleship (film)|Battleship]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://movies.about.com/od/moviesinproduction/a/barbaro071207.htm Movies.about.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Curse of Billy Penn]] - curse believed to affect the four Philadelphia-area sports teams ([[Philadelphia Phillies]], [[Philadelphia Eagles]], [[Philadelphia 76ers]], and [[Philadelphia Flyers]])
*[[Kentucky Derby winners]]
*[[List of leading Thoroughbred racehorses]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ntra.com/stats_bios.aspx?id=17274 Barbaro Statistics and Media], NTRA
*[http://www.ntra.com/ridingwithbarbaro/ Barbaro Memorial Fund - NTRA Charities] Finding a cure for Laminitis

{{Kentucky Derby Winners}}

[[Category:2003 racehorse births]]
[[Category:2007 racehorse deaths]]
[[Category:Horses who died from racing injuries]]
[[Category:American racehorses]]
[[Category:Kentucky Derby winners]]
[[Category:Northern Dancer bloodline]]
[[Category:Racehorses bred in Kentucky]]&lt;!-- His owners are from Pennsylvania, but he was bred in Kentucky.--&gt;
[[Category:Racehorses trained in the United States]]
[[Category:Thoroughbred racehorses]]

[[nl:Barbaro]]
[[ja:バーバロ]]
[[pl:Barbaro]]
[[sv:Barbaro]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
