<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4059023" ns="0" title="Web search engine"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Search engine}}

A '''web search engine''' is designed to search for information on the [[World Wide Web]] and FTP servers. The search results are generally presented in a list of results often referred to as SERPS, or &quot;search engine results pages&quot;. The information may consist of [[web page]]s, images, information and other types of files. Some search engines also [[data mining|mine data]] available in [[database]]s or [[web directory|open directories]].  Unlike [[web directories]], which are maintained only by human editors, search engines also maintain [[real-time computing|real-time]] information by running an [[algorithm]] on a [[web crawler]].

== History ==
{|class=&quot;bordered infobox&quot;
|-
! colspan = &quot;3&quot; | Timeline ([[List of search engines|full list]]) &lt;!--Note:  &quot;Launch&quot; refers only to web availability of original crawl-based web search engine results.--&gt;
|-
!|Year
!|Engine
!|Current status
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |1993
||[[W3Catalog]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Aliweb]]
||Closed
|-
||[[JumpStation]]
||Closed
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |1994
||[[WebCrawler]]
||Active, Aggregator
|-
||[[Go.com]]
||Active, Yahoo Search
|-
||[[Lycos]]
||Active
|-
| rowspan=&quot;6&quot; |1995
||[[AltaVista]]
||Bought and operated by Yahoo!
|-
|[[Daum Communications|Daum]]
||Active
|-
||[[Magellan]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Excite]]
||Active
|-
||[[SAPO (company)|SAPO]]
||Active
|-
||[[Yahoo!]]
||Active, Launched as a directory
|-
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; |1996
||[[Dogpile]]
||Active, Aggregator
|-
||[[Inktomi]]
||Acquired by Yahoo!
|-
||[[HotBot]]
||Active (lycos.com)
|-
||[[Ask.com|Ask Jeeves]]
||Active (ask.com, Jeeves went away)
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |1997
||[[Northern Light Group|Northern Light]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Yandex]]
||Active
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |1998
||[[Google Search|Google]]
||Active
|-
||[[MSN Search]]
||Active as Bing
|-
|rowspan=&quot;5&quot;|1999
||[[AlltheWeb]]
||Closed (URL redirected to Yahoo!)
|-
||[[GenieKnows]]
||Active, rebranded Yellowee.com
|-
||[[Naver]]
||Active
|-
||[[Teoma]]
||Active
|-
||[[Vivisimo]]
||Closed
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|2000
||[[Baidu]]
||Active
|-
||[[Exalead]]
||Acquired by [[Dassault Systèmes]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;1&quot;|2002
||[[Inktomi]]
||Acquired by Yahoo!
|-
||2003
||[[Info.com]]
||Active
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |2004
||[[Yahoo! Search]]
||Active, Launched own web search&lt;BR/&gt;(see Yahoo! Directory, 1995)
|-
||[[A9.com]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Sogou.com|Sogou]]
||Active
|-
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; |2005
||[[AOL Search]]
||Active
|-
||[[Ask.com]]
|| Active
|-
||[[GoodSearch]]
|| Active
|-
||[[SearchMe]]
|| Closed
|-
| rowspan= &quot;6&quot; |2006
||[[wikiseek]]
||Active
|-
||[[Quaero]]
||Active
|-
||[[Ask.com]]
|| Active
|-
||[[Live Search]]
|| Active as Bing, Launched as&lt;BR/&gt;rebranded MSN Search
|-
||[[ChaCha (search engine)|ChaCha]]
||Active
|-
||[[Guruji.com]]
||Active
|-
| rowspan= &quot;4&quot; |2007
||[[wikiseek]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Sproose]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Wikia Search]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Blackle.com]]
||Active
|-
| rowspan= &quot;8&quot; |2008
||[[Powerset (company)|Powerset]]
||Acquired by Microsoft
|-
||[[Picollator]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Viewzi]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Boogami]]
||Active
|-
||[[LeapFish]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Forestle]]
||Active
|-
||[[VADLO]]
||Active
|-
||[[Duck Duck Go]]
||Active, Aggregator
|-
| rowspan= &quot;4&quot; |2009
||[[Bing]]
||Active, Launched as&lt;BR/&gt;rebranded Live Search
|-
||[[Yebol]]
||Active
|-
||[[Search2.net]]
||Active
|-
||[[Mugurdy]]
||Closed due to a lack of funding 
|-
||[[Goby Inc.|Goby]]
||Active
|-
|rowspan= &quot;5&quot; |2010 
||[[Yandex]]
||Active, Launched global&lt;BR/&gt;(English) search
|-
||[[Cuil]]
||Closed
|-
||[[Blekko]]
||Active
|-
||[[Yummly]] 
||Active
|-
||[[Solusee]] 
||Active
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |2011
|-
||[[Interred educational search engine|Interred]]
||Active
|}

During the early development of the web, there was a list of [[webserver]]s edited by [[Tim Berners-Lee]] and hosted on the [[CERN]] webserver. One historical snapshot from 1992 remains.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.w3.org/History/19921103-hypertext/hypertext/DataSources/WWW/Servers.html World-Wide Web Servers&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; As more webservers went online the central list could not keep up. On the [[NCSA]]  site new servers were announced under the title &quot;What's New!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.mcom.com/home/whatsnew/whats_new_0294.html What's New! February 1994&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The very first tool used for searching on the Internet was [[Archie search engine|Archie]].&lt;ref name=LeidenUnivSE&gt;
     &quot;Internet History - Search Engines&quot; (from [[Search Engine Watch]]),
     Universiteit Leiden, Netherlands, September 2001, web:
     [http://www.internethistory.leidenuniv.nl/index.php3?c=7 LeidenU-Archie].
&lt;/ref&gt;
The name stands for &quot;archive&quot; without the &quot;v&quot;.  It was created in 1990 by [[Alan Emtage]], Bill Heelan and J. Peter Deutsch, computer science students at [[McGill University]]  in [[Montreal]]. The program downloaded the directory listings of all the files located on public anonymous FTP ([[File Transfer Protocol]]) sites, creating a searchable database of file names; however, Archie did not index the contents of these sites since the amount of data was so limited it could be readily searched manually.

The rise of [[Gopher (protocol)|Gopher]] (created in 1991 by [[Mark McCahill]]  at the [[University of Minnesota]]) led to two new search programs, [[Veronica (computer)|Veronica]]  and [[Jughead (computer)|Jughead]]. Like Archie, they searched the file names and titles stored in Gopher index systems. Veronica (''V''ery ''E''asy ''R''odent-''O''riented ''N''et-wide ''I''ndex to ''C''omputerized ''A''rchives) provided a keyword search of most Gopher menu titles in the entire Gopher listings. Jughead (''J''onzy's ''U''niversal ''G''opher ''H''ierarchy ''E''xcavation ''A''nd ''D''isplay) was a tool for obtaining menu information from specific Gopher servers.  While the name of the search engine &quot;Archie&quot; was not a reference to the [[Archie Comics|Archie comic book]] series, &quot;[[Veronica Lodge|Veronica]]&quot; and &quot;[[Jughead Jones|Jughead]]&quot; are characters in the series, thus referencing their predecessor.

In the summer of 1993, no search engine existed yet for the web, though numerous specialized catalogues were maintained by hand. [[Oscar Nierstrasz]] at the [[University of Geneva]] wrote a series of [[Perl]] scripts that would periodically mirror these pages and rewrite them into a standard format which formed the basis for [[W3Catalog]], the web's first primitive search engine, released on September 2, 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;Announcement html&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://groups.google.com/group/comp.infosystems.www/browse_thread/thread/2176526a36dc8bd3/2718fd17812937ac?hl=en&amp;lnk=gst&amp;q=Oscar+Nierstrasz#2718fd17812937ac|title=Searchable Catalog of WWW Resources (experimental)|author=[[Oscar Nierstrasz]]|date=2 September 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1993, Matthew Gray, then at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]], produced what was probably the first [[web robot]], the [[Perl]]-based [[World Wide Web Wanderer]], and used it to generate an index called 'Wandex'.  The purpose of the Wanderer was to measure the size of the World Wide Web, which it did until late 1995.  The web's second search engine [[Aliweb]] appeared in November 1993.  Aliweb did not use a [[web robot]], but instead depended on being notified by website administrators of the existence at each site of an index file in a particular format.

[[JumpStation]] (released in December 1993&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20010620073530/http://archive.ncsa.uiuc.edu/SDG/Software/Mosaic/Docs/old-whats-new/whats-new-1293.html Archive of NCSA what's new in December 1993 page]&lt;/ref&gt;) used a [[web crawler|web robot]] to find web pages and to build its index, and used a [[web form]] as the interface to its query program.  It was thus the first WWW resource-discovery tool to combine the three essential features of a web search engine (crawling, indexing, and searching) as described below.  Because of the limited resources available on the platform on which it ran, its indexing and hence searching were limited to the titles and headings found in the web pages the crawler encountered.

One of the first &quot;full text&quot; crawler-based search engines was [[WebCrawler]], which came out in 1994.  Unlike its predecessors, it let users search for any word in any webpage, which has become the standard for all major search engines since.  It was also the first one to be widely known by the public.  Also in 1994, [[Lycos]] (which started at [[Carnegie Mellon University]]) was launched and became a major commercial endeavor.

Soon after, many search engines appeared and vied for popularity. These included [[Magellan (search engine)]], [[Excite]], [[Infoseek]], [[Inktomi]], [[Northern Light Group|Northern Light]], and [[AltaVista]]. [[Yahoo!]] was among the most popular ways for people to find web pages of interest, but its search function operated on its [[web directory]], rather than full-text copies of web pages.  Information seekers could also browse the directory instead of doing a keyword-based search.

In 1996, [[Netscape]] was looking to give a single search engine an exclusive deal to be the featured search engine on Netscape's web browser. There was so much interest that instead a deal was struck with Netscape by five of the major search engines, where for $5 million per year each search engine would be in rotation on the Netscape search engine page.  The five engines were Yahoo!, Magellan, Lycos, Infoseek, and Excite.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Yahoo! And Netscape Ink International Distribution Deal|url=http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/YHOO/701084386x0x27155/9a3b5ed8-9e84-4cba-a1e5-77a3dc606566/YHOO_News_1997_7_8_General.pdf|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document |date=1 April 1996|title=Browser Deals Push Netscape Stock Up 7.8% |publisher=Los Angeles Times |url=http://articles.latimes.com/1996-04-01/business/fi-53780_1_netscape-home |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Search engines were also known as some of the brightest stars in the Internet investing frenzy that occurred in the late 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Gandal |first=Neil |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2001 |title=The dynamics of competition in the internet search engine market |journal=International Journal of Industrial Organization |volume=19 |issue=7 |pages=1103–1117 |doi=10.1016/S0167-7187(01)00065-0  |url= |accessdate=|quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several companies entered the market spectacularly, receiving record gains during their [[initial public offering]]s. Some have taken down their public search engine, and are marketing enterprise-only editions, such as Northern Light.  Many search engine companies were caught up in the [[dot-com bubble]], a speculation-driven market boom that peaked in 1999 and ended in 2001.

Around 2000, [[Google Search|Google's search engine]] rose to prominence.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}  The company achieved better results for many searches with an innovation called [[PageRank]].  This [[iterative algorithm]] ranks web pages based on the number and PageRank of other web sites and pages that link there, on the premise that good or desirable pages are linked to more than others.  Google also maintained a minimalist interface to its search engine. In contrast, many of its competitors embedded a search engine in a [[web portal]].

By 2000, Yahoo! was providing search services based on Inktomi's search engine. Yahoo! acquired Inktomi in 2002, and [[Overture]] (which owned [[AlltheWeb]] and AltaVista) in 2003.  Yahoo! switched to Google's search engine until 2004, when it launched its own search engine based on the combined technologies of its acquisitions.

Microsoft first launched MSN Search in the fall of 1998 using search results from Inktomi.  In early 1999 the site began to display listings from [[Looksmart]] blended with results from Inktomi except for a short time in 1999 when results from AltaVista were used instead.  In 2004, [[Microsoft]] began a transition to its own search technology, powered by its own [[web crawler]] (called [[msnbot]]).

Microsoft's rebranded search engine, [[Bing]], was launched on June 1, 2009.  On July 29, 2009, Yahoo! and Microsoft finalized a deal in which [[Yahoo! Search]] would be powered by Microsoft Bing technology.

== How web search engines work ==
[[File:WebCrawlerArchitecture.svg|thumb|280px|High-level architecture of a standard Web crawler]]
A search engine operates in the following order:
# [[Web crawling]]
# [[Index (search engine)|Indexing]]
# [[Web search query|Searching]]

Web search engines work by storing information about many web pages, which they retrieve from the html itself. These pages are retrieved by a [[Web crawler]] (sometimes also known as a spider) &amp;mdash; an automated Web browser which follows every link on the site. Exclusions can be made by the use of [[robots.txt]]. The contents of each page are then analyzed to determine how it should be [[Search engine indexing|indexed]] (for example, words are extracted from the titles, headings, or special fields called [[meta tags]]). Data about web pages are stored in an index database for use in later queries. A query can be a single word.  The purpose of an index is to allow information to be found as quickly as possible.  Some search engines, such as [[Google]], store all or part of the source page (referred to as a [[web cache|cache]]) as well as information about the web pages, whereas others, such as [[AltaVista]], store every word of every page they find.  This cached page always holds the actual search text since it is the one that was actually indexed, so it can be very useful when the content of the current page has been updated and the search terms are no longer in it.  This problem might be considered to be a mild form of [[linkrot]], and Google's handling of it increases [[usability]] by satisfying [[user expectations]] that the search terms will be on the returned webpage.  This satisfies the [[principle of least astonishment]] since the user normally expects the search terms to be on the returned pages.  Increased search relevance makes these cached pages very useful, even beyond the fact that they may contain data that may no longer be available elsewhere.

When a user enters a [[web search query|query]] into a search engine (typically by using [[Keyword (Internet search)|key words]]), the engine examines its [[inverted index|index]] and provides a listing of best-matching web pages according to its criteria, usually with a short summary containing the document's title and sometimes parts of the text.  The index is built from the information stored with the data and the method by which the information is indexed. Unfortunately, there are currently no known public search engines that allow documents to be searched by date. Most search engines support the use of the [[boolean operators]] AND, OR and NOT to further specify the [[web search query|search query]]. Boolean operators are for literal searches that allow the user to refine and extend the terms of the search.  The engine looks for the words or phrases exactly as entered.  Some search engines provide an advanced feature called [[Proximity search (text)|proximity search]] which allows users to define the distance between keywords.  There is also concept-based searching where the research involves using statistical analysis on pages containing the words or phrases you search for.  As well, natural language queries allow the user to type a question in the same form one would ask it to a human.  A site like this would be ask.com.

The usefulness of a search engine depends on the [[relevance (information retrieval)|relevance]] of the '''result set''' it gives back. While there may be millions of web pages that include a particular word or phrase, some pages may be more relevant, popular, or authoritative than others. Most search engines employ methods to [[rank order|rank]] the results to provide the &quot;best&quot; results first. How a search engine decides which pages are the best matches, and what order the results should be shown in, varies widely from one engine to another. The methods also change over time as Internet usage changes and new techniques evolve.  There are two main types of search engine that have evolved: one is a system of predefined and hierarchically ordered keywords that humans have programmed extensively.  The other is a system that generates an &quot;[[inverted index]]&quot; by analyzing texts it locates.  This second form relies much more heavily on the computer itself to do the bulk of the work.

Most Web search engines are commercial ventures supported by [[advertising]] revenue and, as a result, some employ the practice of allowing advertisers to [[paid inclusion|pay money to have their listings ranked]] higher in search results.  Those search engines which do not accept money for their search engine results make money by [[contextual advertising|running search related ads]] alongside the regular search engine results.  The search engines make money every time someone clicks on one of these ads.

==Market share==
{{expand section|Information abouth national search engines like [[StatCounter]], [[Yandex]], [[Naver]] and their market share in respective countries.|date=October 2011}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! Search engine !! colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Market share in May 2011 !! colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Market share in December 2010&lt;ref&gt;[http://marketshare.hitslink.com/search-engine-market-share.aspx?qprid=4 Net Marketshare - World]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Google]] || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable|82.80|%|2}} || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable|84.65|%|2}} 
|-
| [[Yahoo!]]  || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 6.42|%|2}} || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 6.69|%|2}}
|-
| [[Baidu]]  || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 4.89|%|2}} || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 3.39|%|2}}
|-
| [[Bing]]   || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 3.91|%|2}} || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 3.29|%|2}}
|-
| [[Ask.com|Ask]]    || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 0.52|%|2}} || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 0.56|%|2}}
|-
| [[AOL]]    || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 0.36|%|2}} || align=&quot;right&quot;|{{bartable| 0.42|%|2}}
|}

Google's worldwide market share peaked at 86.3% in April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://marketshare.hitslink.com/report.aspx?qprid=5&amp;qpcustom=Google%20-%20Global&amp;qptimeframe=M&amp;qpsp=120&amp;qpnp=25 Net Marketshare - Google]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yahoo!]], [[Bing]] and other search engines are more popular in the US than in [[Europe]]. 

According to [[Hitwise]], market share in the U.S. for October 2011 was Google 65.38%, Bing-powered (Bing and Yahoo!) 28.62%, and the remaining 66 search engines 6%. However, the &quot;success rate&quot; of searches sampled in July. Over 80 percent of Yahoo! and Bing searches resulted in the users visiting a web site, while Google's rate was just under 68 percent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hitwise.com/us/about-us/press-center/press-releases/bing-powered-share-of-searches-at-29-percent Experian Hitwise reports Bing-powered share of searches at 29 percent in October 2011], [[Experian Hitwise]], November 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

An Experian Hitwise report released in August 2011 gave the &quot;success rate&quot; of searches sampled in July. Over 80 percent of Yahoo! and Bing searches resulted in the users visiting a web site, while Google's rate was just under 68 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.yahoo.com/google-remains-ahead-bing-relevance-drops-210457139.html |title=Google Remains Ahead of Bing, But Relevance Drops |date=August 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[People's Republic of China]], Baidu held a 61.6% market share for web search in July 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://risetothetop.techwyse.com/internet-marketing/search-engine-market-share-july-2009/ Search Engine Market Share July 2009 | Rise to the Top Blog&lt;!--Bot generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Search engine bias==
Although search engines are programmed to rank websites based on their popularity and relevancy, empirical studies indicate various political, economic, and social biases in the information they provide.&lt;ref&gt;Segev, Elad (2010). Google and the Digital Divide: The Biases of Online Knowledge, Oxford: Chandos Publishing.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vaughan, L. &amp; Thelwall, M. (2004). Search engine coverage bias: evidence and possible causes, Information Processing &amp; Management, 40(4), 693-707.&lt;/ref&gt; These biases could be a direct result of economic and commercial processes (e.g., companies that advertise with a search engine can become also more popular in its [[organic search]] results), and political processes (e.g., the removal of search results in order to comply with local laws).&lt;ref&gt;Berkman Center for Internet &amp; Society (2002), [http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/filtering/china/google-replacements/ “Replacement of Google with Alternative Search Systems in China: Documentation and Screen Shots”], Harvard Law School.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Google Bombing]] is one example of an attempt to manipulate search results for political, social or commercial reasons.

== See also ==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
* [[List of search engines]]
* [[Question answering|Answer engine]] (question answering) &lt;!-- examples necessary here until article comprehensible to normal reader--&gt;
** [[Quora]]
** [[True Knowledge]]
** [[Wolfram Alpha]]
* [[Collaborative search engine]]
* [[Enterprise search]]
* [[Google effect]]
* [[Internet Search Engines and Libraries]]
* [[Metasearch engine]]
* [[Natural language search engine]]
* [[OpenSearch]]
* [[Search directory]]
* [[Search engine marketing]]
* [[Search engine optimization]]
* [[Search oriented architecture]]
* [[Selection-based search]]
* [[Semantic Web]]
* [[Social engine]]
* [[Social search]]
* [[Spell checker]]
* [[Web indexing]]
* [[Web search query]]
* [[Website Parse Template]]
&lt;/div&gt;

== References ==
{{Citation style|date=September 2009}}
{{Reflist}}
* GBMW: Reports of 30-day punishment, re: Car maker BMW had its German website bmw.de delisted from Google, such as: [http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=06/02/05/235218 Slashdot-BMW] (05-Feb-2006).
* INSIZ: Maximum size of webpages indexed by MSN/Google/Yahoo! (&quot;100-kb limit&quot;): [http://www.sitepoint.com/article/indexing-limits-where-bots-stop Max Page-size] (28-Apr-2006).

== Further reading ==

* For a more detailed history of early search engines, see [http://searchenginewatch.com/showPage.html?page=3071951 Search Engine Birthdays] (from [[Search Engine Watch]]), Chris Sherman, September 2003.
* {{cite journal | quotes = | author = Steve Lawrence; C. Lee Giles | date = | year = 1999| title = Accessibility of information on the web | journal = [[Nature (journal)|Nature]] | volume = 400 | issue =  6740| page = 107 | doi = 10.1038/21987 | pmid = 10428673 | pages = 107–9 }}
* Bing Liu (2007), ''[http://www.cs.uic.edu/~liub/WebMiningBook.html Web Data Mining: Exploring Hyperlinks, Contents and Usage Data].'' Springer, ISBN 3540378812
* Bar-Ilan, J. (2004). The use of Web search engines in information science research. ARIST, 38, 231-288.
* {{cite book | first = Mark | last = Levene | year = 2005 | title = An Introduction to Search Engines and Web Navigation | publisher = Pearson | location = | isbn = }}
* {{cite book | first = Randolph | last = Hock | year = 2007 | title = The Extreme Searcher's Handbook}} ISBN 978-0-910965-76-7
* {{cite journal | quotes = | author = Javed Mostafa | date = | year = 2005 | month = February | title = Seeking Better Web Searches | journal = [[Scientific American Magazine]] | volume = | issue = | pages = | publisher = | pmid = | doi = | bibcode = | url = http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?articleID=0006304A-37F4-11E8-B7F483414B7F0000 | language = }}{{dead link|date=September 2010}}
* {{cite journal |last=Ross |first=Nancy |authorlink= |coauthors=Wolfram, Dietmar |year=2000 |title=End user searching on the Internet: An analysis of term pair topics submitted to the Excite search engine |journal=Journal of the American Society for Information Science |volume=51 |issue=10 |pages=949–958 |doi= 10.1002/1097-4571(2000)51:10&lt;949::AID-ASI70&gt;3.0.CO;2-5|url= |accessdate=|quote= }}
* {{cite journal |last=Xie |first=M. |authorlink=  |year=1998 |title=Quality dimensions of Internet search engines |journal=Journal of Information Science |volume=24 |issue=5 |pages=365–372 |doi=10.1177/016555159802400509 |url= |accessdate=|quote= |display-authors=1 |last2=Wang |first2=H. |last3=Goh |first3=T. N. }}
* {{cite book | title=Information Retrieval: Implementing and Evaluating Search Engines  | url=http://www.ir.uwaterloo.ca/book/ | year=2010 | publisher=MIT Press | author8=Stefan B&amp;uuml;ttcher, Charles L. A. Clarke, and Gordon V. Cormack}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Internet search engines}}
* {{Dmoz|Computers/Internet/Searching/Search_Engines/|Search Engines}}

{{Internet search}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Web Search Engine}}
[[Category:Information retrieval]]
[[Category:Internet search engines| ]]
[[Category:Internet terminology]]
[[Category:History of the Internet]]

[[af:Soekenjin]]
[[ar:محرك بحث]]
[[ast:Motor de gueta]]
[[be-x-old:Сеціўная пошукавая сыстэма]]
[[bar:Suachmaschin]]
[[bs:Internet pretraživač]]
[[bg:Търсачка]]
[[ca:Motor de cerca]]
[[cs:Internetový vyhledávač]]
[[cy:Peiriant chwilio rhyngrwyd]]
[[da:Søgemaskine]]
[[de:Suchmaschine]]
[[el:Μηχανή αναζήτησης]]
[[es:Motor de búsqueda]]
[[eo:Serĉilo]]
[[ext:Landeru]]
[[eu:Bilaketa motor]]
[[fa:جویشگر]]
[[fr:Moteur de recherche]]
[[gl:Motor de busca]]
[[gu:વેબ શોધ એન્જીન]]
[[ko:웹 검색 엔진]]
[[hy:Որոնողական համակարգ]]
[[hi:खोज संयन्त्र]]
[[hr:Tražilica]]
[[id:Mesin pencari]]
[[ia:Mechanismo de recerca]]
[[os:Агуырды системæ]]
[[it:Motore di ricerca]]
[[he:מנוע חיפוש]]
[[kn:ಅಂತರ್ಜಾಲ ಹುಡುಕಾಟ ಯಂತ್ರ]]
[[ka:საძიებო სისტემა]]
[[kk:Іздеу жүйесі]]
[[lv:Meklētājprogramma]]
[[ln:Motɛ́lɛ mwa boluki]]
[[hu:Keresőmotor]]
[[mk:Веб пребарувач]]
[[ml:വെബ് സെർച്ച് എഞ്ചിൻ]]
[[ms:Enjin gelintar]]
[[nl:Zoekmachine]]
[[ja:検索エンジン]]
[[no:Søkemotor]]
[[nn:Søkjemotor]]
[[mhr:Кычалше системе]]
[[uz:Veb qidiruv tizimi]]
[[pl:Wyszukiwarka internetowa]]
[[pt:Motor de busca]]
[[ro:Motor de căutare]]
[[ru:Поисковая система]]
[[stq:Säikmaskiene]]
[[scn:Muturi di circata]]
[[simple:Search engine]]
[[sl:Spletni iskalnik]]
[[sr:Интернет претраживач]]
[[fi:Hakukone]]
[[sv:Söktjänst]]
[[ta:தேடுபொறி]]
[[te:వెబ్ శోధనా యంత్రం]]
[[th:เสิร์ชเอนจิน]]
[[tr:Arama motoru]]
[[uk:Пошукова система]]
[[vi:Máy truy tìm dữ liệu]]
[[fiu-vro:Võrgostotsja]]
[[yi:זוכמאשין]]
[[zh:搜索引擎]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
