<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4061679" ns="0" title="Pieter Van den Abeele"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=May 2008}}
{{distinguish|Pieter van Abeele}}
'''Pieter Van den Abeele''' is a computer programmer,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9593-5546033-3.html
|title=Sun poised to take open-source Solaris step | Tech News on ZDNet
|publisher=news.zdnet.com
|accessdate=2008-05-28
|last=
|first=
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and the founder of the [[PowerPC]]-version of [[Gentoo Linux]], a foundation connected with a distribution of the [[Linux]] computer operating system.{{Clarify me|date=February 2009}} He joined Gentoo shortly after its conception, merging Gentoo's first port into the mainline Gentoo repository, paving the way for other [[Gentoo Linux]] ports by implementing amongst many other things the Gentoo architecture keywords and portage profiles. Working together with [[Daniel Robbins]], Pieter spearheaded the Gentoo architectures and platforms effort. He founded Gentoo for [[Mac OS X]], for which he received a scholarship by [[Apple Computer]]. In 2004 Pieter was invited to the [[OpenSolaris]] pilot program and assisted [[Sun Microsystems]] with building a development eco-system around the [[Solaris operating system]]. Pieter was nominated for the OpenSolaris Community Advisory Board and managed a team of developers to make Gentoo available on the Solaris operating system as well. Pieter is a co-author of the Gentoo [[Social Contract]] and a co-author of the [http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/ Gentoo handbook].

The teams managed by Pieter Van den Abeele have shaped the [[PowerPC]] landscape with several &quot;firsts&quot;. Gentoo/PowerPC was the first distribution to introduce PowerPC Live CDs. Gentoo also beat Apple to releasing a full [[64-bit]] PowerPC userland environment for the IBM [[PowerPC 970]] (G5) processor.

Pieter Van den Abeele's academic work at the [[Vrije Universiteit Brussel]], [[Belgium]], involves the redesign of the technology at the heart of [[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]]; [[Portage (software)|Portage]].  His Gentoo-based Home Media and Communication System, based on a [[Freescale Semiconductor]] [[PowerPC_G4#PowerPC_7447.2F7457_.22Apollo_7.22|PowerPC 7447]] processor won the Best of Show award at the inaugural 2005 Freescale Technology Forum in Orlando, Florida. Pieter is also a member of the [[Power.org]] consortium and participates in committees and workgroups focusing on disruptive business plays around the [[Power Architecture]]. Pieter Van den Abeele is also a founding member of the [http://www.metapkg.com MetaPkg alliance] between Gentoo, Apple's [[OpenDarwin]] and [[Fink]], to coordinate porting efforts.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*http://www.metadistribution.org/blog/

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Abeele, Pieter Van den
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Abeele, Pieter Van den}}
[[Category:People in information technology]]
[[Category:Power Architecture]]
[[Category:Gentoo Linux people]]
[[Category:Living people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
