<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4085872" ns="0" title="WAAY-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the [[radio station]] in Huntsville, [[Alabama]] formerly known as WAAY|WLOR}}

{{Infobox broadcast 
| call_letters             = WAAY-TV
| city                     = Huntsville
| station_logo             = [[Image:31firstnews.jpg|150px]]
| station_slogan           = ''Your FirstNews&lt;br&gt; Station''
| station_branding         = WAAY 31 &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;WAAY 31 FirstNews
| analog                   = 
| digital                  = 32 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 31 ([[PSIP]])|
| other_chs                = 
| affiliations             = 
| subchannels              = 31.1 [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]
| network                  = 
| founded                  = 
| airdate                  = August 1, 1959
| location                 = [[Huntsville, Alabama|Huntsville]]/[[Decatur, Alabama|Decatur]]/[[Florence – Muscle Shoals metropolitan area|Shoals]]/&lt;br&gt;[[Sand Mountain (Alabama)|Sand Mountain, Alabama]]
| callsign_meaning         = the word '''WAY'''&lt;br&gt;with an extra '''A'''
| former_callsigns         = WAFG-TV (1959-1963)
| former_channel_numbers   = 31 (UHF analog, 1959-2009)
| owner                    = [[Calkins Media]]
| licensee                 = Huntsville Broadcast Corporation 
| sister_stations          = 
| former_affiliations      = ABC (1959-1968)&lt;br&gt;[[NBC]] (1968-1977)&lt;br&gt;[[CBS]] (secondary, 1959-1963)
| effective_radiated_power = 468 [[kilowatt|kW]]
| HAAT                     = 537.8 m
| class                    = 
| facility_id              = 57292
| coordinates              = {{coord|34|44|12.7|N|86|31|58.9|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}
| homepage                 = [http://www.waaytv.com/ waaytv.com]
|}}

'''WAAY-TV''' is the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]-affiliated [[television station]] for the [[Tennessee Valley]] area of [[North Alabama]] that is licensed to [[Huntsville, Alabama|Huntsville]]. It broadcasts a [[high-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 32 from a transmitter at its Monte Sano Boulevard studios on top of [[Monte Sano Mountain]].  [[Calkins Media]] owns the station.  It airs its daily 4 p.m. newscast from local [[Lifestyle center (retail)|lifestyle center]] [[Bridge Street Town Centre]]. [[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on WAAY includes: ''[[Entertainment Tonight]]'', ''[[The Doctors (2008 TV series)|The Doctors]]'', ''[[Jeopardy!]]'' and ''[[Live with Regis and Kelly]]''.

==History==
The station's first broadcast was on August 1, 1959 as '''WAFG-TV'''. It was [[Alabama]]'s first primary ABC affiliate. There was only one other station in the area at the time, [[Decatur, Alabama|Decatur]]'s WMSL-TV (now Huntsville's [[WAFF (TV)|WAFF]]). This was an unusual arrangement for a two-station [[media market|market]] especially one as small as Huntsville was at the time. When the station was sold to Smith Broadcasting (owners of WAAY now [[WLOR]] radio) in 1963, the call sign was changed to '''WAAY-TV'''. It switched network affiliation to [[NBC]] in January 1968 but returned to ABC nearly ten years later in December 1977 citing higher network ratings and the lack of a duplicate ABC affiliate in [[Florence, Alabama|Florence]] (where WOWL, now [[WHDF]], was then an NBC affiliate) as reasons. 

Smith Broadcasting sold WAAY-TV to GOCOM Broadcasting (later renamed [[Piedmont Television|Piedmont Communications]]) in 1999. The Smith family, who previously owned broadcasting properties in [[Birmingham, Alabama|Birmingham]] before coming to Huntsville, was the last local owner of a Huntsville television station as rivals [[WHNT-TV]] and WAFF had been sold to larger corporations years before. [[WZDX]], which was the first station in Northern Alabama not affiliated with the traditional networks or the educational television system, has always belonged to outside interests. The Smith family also owned radio stations in [[Fort Walton Beach, Florida]] and [[South Pittsburg, Tennessee]]. At one time, all three of Huntsville's major-network affiliates (WAAY included) had studios located beside its transmitters and towers on Monte Sano. 

After a 1982 fire gutted the building of WAFF, that station and later WHNT moved offices and production facilities into the city itself employing microwave relays to send signals to the transmitters. Only WAAY continues to maintain its full operations on Monte Sano Boulevard. WHIQ-TV which is a [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] affiliate serves as a translator relay of [[Alabama Public Television]] with programming originating from Birmingham, not Huntsville. On September 4, 2003, the 1,000 foot broadcasting tower leased by WAAY collapsed killing three people. 

In 2006, Piedmont Broadcasting agreed to sell WAAY to Calkins Media which is a [[Pennsylvania]]-based [[mass media]] company that owns several small [[newspapers]] in Pennsylvania and two other television stations ([[WWSB]] in [[Sarasota, Florida]] and [[WTXL]] in [[Tallahassee, Florida]]). The sale to Calkins became official on February 1, 2007. WAAY is Calkins' first broadcasting property outside of [[Florida]]. On February 17, 2009, WAAY-TV ended its analog service on UHF channel 31 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.al.com/news/huntsvilletimes/local.ssf?/base/news/1233829009315960.xml&amp;coll=1&lt;/ref&gt;, the station remains to provide digital service on its current pre-transition channel 32. &lt;ref name=&quot;FCCForm387&quot;&gt;[http://fjallfoss.fcc.gov/cgi-bin/ws.exe/prod/cdbs/forms/prod/cdbsmenu.hts?context=25&amp;appn=101234148&amp;formid=387&amp;fac_num=57292 CDBS Print&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==News operation==
In the Spring 2007 ratings period, all of the station's newscasts ranked in third place. This is in contrast from the 1970s through the early-1990s, when WAAY was still family-owned. At one point, the station aired weekend morning newscasts but currently does not. On July 16, 2007 at 5, WAAY unveiled a new set and graphics package similar to that of sister stations WWSB and WTXL. Beginning September 13, 2010, its news title became ''WAAY 31 FirstNews''. The station is now using the FirstNews brand and logo in all branding, including commercials for syndicated programming. The station was the first to air a 4:30 a.m. newscast in the market and is the only station in the area airing local news weekday at 11 a.m. and 4 p.m. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.waaytv.com/Global/story.asp?S=12972053&lt;/ref&gt; The channel produced a prime time newscast at 9 for [[UPN]] affiliate WHDF during the early-2000s. On September 20, 2010 through a new news share agreement, a second WAAY-produced broadcast at 9 began airing every night on [[Fox Network|Fox]] affiliate [[WZDX]]. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.waaytv.com/Global/story.asp?S=13097072&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to its main studios, WAAY maintains news bureaus in [[Decatur, Alabama|Decatur]] (on Lee Street Northeast) and [[Florence, Alabama|Florence]] (on North Pine Street within the [[University of North Alabama]] campus), and broadcasts each weekday from Bridge Street Town Centre at 4 p.m. The station operates its own [[weather radar]] at the main studios called &quot;Live Storm Force 31 Doppler Max&quot;.

==News team==
'''Anchors'''
*Erin Dacy - weekday mornings
*T.W. Starr - weekday mornings and &quot;Did You Know&quot; segment producer
*Meredith Wood - weekdays at 11 a.m. and 4 p.m.
*Guy Hornbuckle - Monday through Thursday at 4 p.m., 5 p.m., and 10 p.m., and Sunday nights
*Melissa Riopka - Monday through Thursday at 5 p.m., and 10 p.m., and Sunday nights
**&quot;Focus on Faith&quot; segment producer
*Greg Privett - Friday and Saturday
*Ellis Eskew - Sunday through Thursday at 9 (on WZDX) and reporter
*Chase Gallimore - Sunday through Thursday at 9 (on WZDX) and reporter
*Sharon Doviet - ''31 Law Line'' host

'''''Storm Force 31 Meteorologists'''''
*Spencer Denton - chief meteorologist; Monday through Thursday at 4 p.m., 5 p.m., and 10 p.m., and Sunday nights
*Gary Dobbs - weekday mornings and 11 a.m. 
*Ben Luna  - weekends

'''Sports'''
*Ronnie Duncan - Sunday through Thursday 
*Kyle Burger - Friday and Saturday 
**news and sports reporter
**&quot;Burger Bytes&quot; segment producer

'''Reporters'''
*Shea Allen
*Lillian Askins
*Erika Odell - Shoals bureau reporter
*Rachel Keith
*Rebecca Shlien
*Tim Reid

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.waaytv.com/ WAAY-TV website]
*[http://www.fox54.com/ WZDX website]
*{{TVQ|WAAY}}

{{Huntsville TV}}
{{ABC Alabama}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Waay-Tv}}
[[Category:ABC network affiliates]]
[[Category:Channel 32 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 31 virtual TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1959]]
[[Category:Television stations in Huntsville, Alabama]]
[[Category:Television stations in Alabama]]
[[pt:WAAY-TV]]
[[simple:WAAY-TV]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
