<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4090888" ns="0" title="Musix GNU/Linux"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS
| name                   = Musix GNU/Linux
| screenshot             = [[File:Musix1R4.png|250px|Musix 1.0 R4 DVD]]|
| caption                = Musix 1.0 R4 DVD.
| developers             = Marcos Guglielmetti, Gilberto Borges and collaborators
| family                 = [[Unix-like]]
| source_model           = [[Open source]]
| latest_release_version = 2.0 &lt;ref&gt;http://distrowatch.com/?newsid=05794&lt;/ref&gt;
| latest_release_date    = {{release date and age|2009|11|28}}
| working_state          = Current
| kernel_type            = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]] ([[Linux kernel|Linux]])
| ui                     = [[IceWM]] (previously [[KDE]])
| supported_platforms    = [[IA-32]]
| license                = Mainly the [[GNU GPL]] / Various others
| website                = [http://www.musix.org.ar/ www.musix.org.ar]
}}

'''Musix GNU/Linux''' is a [[Live CD|live CD and DVD]] [[Linux distribution]] for the [[IA-32]] processor family based on [[Debian]]. It contains a collection of software for [[Sound recording and reproduction|audio production]], [[graphic design]], [[video editing]] and general purpose applications. The initiator and co-director of the project is Marcos Germán Guglielmetti.

Musix GNU/Linux is one of the few GNU/Linux distributions recognized by the [[Free Software Foundation]] as being primarily available on sites distributing free software and excluding any non-free information for practical use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnu.org/links/links.html#FreeGNULinuxDistributions Links to Other Free Software Sites - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Musix is developed by a team from [[Argentina]], [[Spain]], [[Mexico]] and [[Brazil]]. The main language used in development discussion and documentation is [[Spanish language|Spanish]]; however, Musix has a community of users who speak Spanish, Portuguese, and English.

== Software ==
=== Musix 1.0 ===
The Musix 0.x and 1.0 Rx versions were released from 2005 to 2008, with Musix 1.0 R6 being the last stable Release on DVD and Musix 1.0 R2R5 the last stable release on CD.

The Live-CD system has more than 1350 software packages and runs directly from the CD/DVD without the need to install anything on the PC. It can be installed on the PC relatively easily if desired in a few minutes, just like Knoppix or Kanotix. The Live-DVD 1.0 R3 test5 has 2279 software packages.

Some of the programs include: [[Rosegarden]] and [[Ardour (audio processor)|Ardour]], both for musicians; [[Inkscape]] for vectorial design; [[GIMP]] for manipulation of images; [[Cinelerra]] for video editing and [[Blender (software)|Blender]] for 3D animation.

Its desktop is very light (only 18 MB of RAM with X.org), based on [[IceWM]]/[[ROX-Filer]] and it has a unique feature: multiple &quot;pinboards&quot; ordered by General Purpose apps, Help, Office, Root/Admin, MIDI, Internet, Graphics, and Audio. The pinboards are arrays of desktop backgrounds and icons.

A small version of the [[KDE]] desktop is installed by default too on the Live-CD version. The Live-DVD has a full KDE version, supporting several languages.

=== Musix 2.0 ===
Musix 2.0 is being developed using the live-helper scripts from the Debian-Live project. The first Alpha version of Musix 2.0  &lt;ref&gt;''[http://distrowatch.com/5394 first Alpha version of Musix 2.0]''&lt;/ref&gt; was released on 2009-03-25 including two [[Real-time operating system|realtime]] patched [[Linux-Libre]] kernels.

On 2009-05-17 the first Beta version of Musix 2.0 was released.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://distrowatch.com/5483 first Beta version of Musix 2.0]''&lt;/ref&gt;

The final Musix GNU/Linux 2.0 version on CD, DVD and USB will be launched before November 20, 2009 by Daniel Vidal, Suso Comesaña, Carlos Sanchiavedraz, Joseangon and other Musix developers. This version will be presented at the &quot;[[Palau Firal de Congressos de Tarragona, España]]&quot; by [[Suso Comesaña]].

One other version is knoppix-based. It is developed by a Brazilian music teacher Gilberto Borges and is named &quot;Adriane&quot; or &quot;Musix Brazil&quot;. This version is not a fork and is derived from Knoppix 6.1 Adriane. This version is in RC1 stage.

== See also ==
{{portal|Free software}} 
* [[List of GNU/Linux distributions endorsed by the Free Software Foundation]]
* [[AGNULA]]
* [[dyne:bolic]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.musix.org.ar Official Musix website]

{{linux-distro}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Musix Gnu/Linux}}
[[Category:Debian-based distributions]]
[[Category:Free audio software]]
[[Category:Operating system distributions bootable from read-only media]]
[[Category:Knoppix]]
[[Category:Linux media creation distributions]]

[[ar:ميوسكس]]
[[ca:Musix]]
[[es:Musix]]
[[fa:موسیکس]]
[[fr:Musix]]
[[nl:Musix]]
[[pl:Musix]]
[[pt:Musix]]
[[sk:Musix GNU+Linux]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
