<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="411203" ns="0" title="Union Station (Washington, D.C.)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the subway station|Union Station (WMATA station)}}
{{refimprove|date=March 2010}}
{{Infobox station
 | name=Washington Union Station
 | style=Amtrak
 | image=Union Station from Columbus Circle, Washington, D.C. 2011.jpg
 | image_size=
 | image_caption=
 | address=50 [[Massachusetts Avenue (Washington, D.C.)|Massachusetts Avenue]] [[Northeast, Washington, D.C.|NE]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Washington, DC]]
 | coordinates={{coord|38.89731|-77.00626|type:railwaystation_region:US-DC|display=inline,title}}
 | line = Amtrak:{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Acela Express}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Capitol Limited}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Cardinal}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Carolinian}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Crescent}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Northeast Regional}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Palmetto}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Silver Meteor}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Silver Star}}{{rail color box|system=Amtrak|line=Vermonter}}[[MARC Train|MARC]]:{{rail color box|system=MARC|line=Brunswick}}{{rail color box|system=MARC|line=Camden}}{{rail color box|system=MARC|line=Penn}}[[Virginia Railway Express|VRE]]:{{rail color box|system=VREX|line=Fredericksburg}}{{rail color box|system=VREX|line=Manassas}}
 | other={{rail color box|system=WMATA|line=Red|note=at [[Union Station (Washington Metro)|Union Station Metro]]}}[[Metrobus (Washington, D.C.)|WMATA Metrobus]]&lt;br&gt;[[DC Circulator]]&lt;br&gt;[[List of MTA Maryland bus routes|Maryland MTA Buses]]&lt;br&gt;[[Loudoun County Commuter Bus]]&lt;br&gt;[[Potomac and Rappahannock Transportation Commission|PRTC Buses]]
 | platform= 18
 | tracks= 20
 | parking= 2,448
 | bicycle= 180
 | passengers=
 | pass_year=
 | pass_percent=
 | opened= 1908
 | rebuilt= 1981–1989
 | ADA=yes
 || baggage_check=Available for [[Capitol Limited (Amtrak train)|Capitol Limited]], [[Cardinal (train)|Cardinal]], [[Carolinian (train)|Carolinian]], [[Crescent (Amtrak)|Crescent]], [[Northeast Regional (Amtrak)|Northeast Regionals]] 66 and 67, [[Palmetto (Amtrak)|Palmetto]], [[Silver Meteor]] and [[Silver Star (Amtrak train)|Silver Star]] services
 |code=[[List of Amtrak station codes|Amtrak code]]: [http://www.amtrak.com/servlet/ContentServer?pagename=am/am2Station/Station_Page&amp;code=WAS WAS] | owned=[[Amtrak]]
 | zone=1(VREX)
 | services=
{{s-rail|title=Amtrak}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Acela Express|previous=|next=BWI Airport}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Capitol Limited|previous=Rockville|next=}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Cardinal|previous=Alexandria|next=Baltimore|rows2=6}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Carolinian|previous=Alexandria|next=Baltimore|hide2=yes}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Crescent|previous=Alexandria|next=Baltimore|hide2=yes}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Palmetto|previous=Alexandria|next=Baltimore|hide2=yes}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Silver Meteor|previous=Alexandria|next=Baltimore|rows1=2|hide2=yes}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Silver Star|previous=Alexandria|next=Baltimore|hide1=yes|hide2=yes}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Regional|previous=Alexandria|next=New Carrollton|type2=Both}}
{{s-line|system=Amtrak|line=Vermonter|previous=|next=New Carrollton}}
{{s-rail-next|title=MARC}}
{{s-line|system=MARC|line=Brunswick|previous=Silver Spring}}
{{s-line|system=MARC|line=Camden|next=Riverdale|rows1=2}}
{{s-line|system=MARC|line=Penn|next=New Carrollton|hide1=yes}}
{{s-rail-next|title=VREX}}
{{s-line|system=VREX|line=Manassas|previous=L'Enfant|next=|rows2=2}}
{{s-line|system=VREX|line=Fredericksburg|previous=L'Enfant|next=|hide2=yes}}
{{s-note|text=Former&amp;nbsp;services}}
{{s-rail-next|title=B&amp;O}}
{{s-line|system=B&amp;O|line=main|previous=Silver Spring|next=Hyattsville|note=([[Metropolitan Subdivision|Metropolitan Branch]])|note2=([[Capital Subdivision|Washington Branch]])}}
 | mpassengers=
{{rail pass box|system=Amtrak|passengers=4,572,878&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Amtrak Fact Sheet, FY2010, District of Columbia|publisher= [http://www.amtrak.com Amtrak] |date= November 2010 |url= http://www.amtrak.com/pdf/factsheets/DC10.pdf |format= PDF |accessdate= 2011-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;|pass_year=2010|pass_percent=6.9}}
{{rail pass box|system=VRE|passengers=201,561|pass_year=2004|pass_percent=10}}
 | nrhp={{Infobox NRHP
 | name           = Washington D.C. Union Station
 | nrhp_type      = 
| locmapin       = District of Columbia
| area           =
| built          = 1908
| architect      = Daniel Burnham
| architecture   = [[Classical architecture|Classical]], [[Beaux-Arts architecture|Beaux-Arts]], among others
| designated_nrhp_type = March 24, 1969
 | governing_body = Private
 | refnum         = 69000302
}}
}}
'''Washington Union Station''' is a [[train station]] and leisure destination{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} visited by 32 million people each year in the center of [[Washington, D.C.]] The train station is served by [[Amtrak]], [[MARC Train|MARC]] and [[Virginia Railway Express]] [[commuter rail]] services as well as by [[Washington Metro]] [[rapid transit|subway trains]] and local buses. It opened in 1907 and at its height during [[World War II]] some 200,000 people passed through it every day. It is also the headquarters for Amtrak.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.amtrak.com/pdf/factsheets/DC08.pdf Amtrak Fact Sheet, Fiscal Year 2008 District of Columbia].&quot; [[Amtrak]]. Retrieved  2009-09-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
[[Image:Union station dc food court.jpg|thumb|left|Food court in Union Station]]
Today Union Station is again one of Washington's busiest and best-known places, visited by 32 million people each year and has many shops, cafes and restaurants.

Passenger services include [[Amtrak]]’s high-speed ''[[Acela Express]]'', ''[[Northeast Regional (Amtrak)|Northeast Regional]]'', and several of Amtrak's long-distance sleeper trains (including, among others, the ''Capitol Limited'', ''Crescent'', ''Palmetto'', and ''Silver Service'' trains); the [[MARC Train|MARC]] and [[Virginia Railway Express|VRE]] [[commuter train|commuter railways]], linking Washington to [[Maryland]] and [[Virginia]], respectively; and the [[Washington Metro]] [[Red Line (Washington Metro)|Red Line]].  From Union Station Amtrak also operates long-distance service to the southeast and midwest, including many intermediate stops to destinations like [[Chicago (Amtrak station)|Chicago]], [[Atlanta (Amtrak station)|Atlanta]], [[New Orleans (Amtrak station)|New Orleans]], and [[Miami (Amtrak station)|Miami]].  Approximately 12,500 passengers boarded or detrained Amtrak services daily in FY2010.

The station is at the southern end of the [[Northeast Corridor]], an [[railway electrification system|electrified rail line]] extending north through major cities including [[Baltimore, Maryland|Baltimore]], [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Philadelphia]], [[New York, New York|New York City]], and [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]].

The track area of the station is divided into upper and lower levels. On the Upper Level are tracks 7–20 which are used by MARC (weekdays) and Amtrak Acela Express, as well as a few Amtrak Regional trains. The Lower Level consists of tracks 22–29 and is used by all southbound service, including all VRE trains, via the [[First Street Tunnel]], as well as some northbound Amtrak services during the week. The D.C. Metrorail Red Line station is located underground at the western side of the building, and is the busiest station in the entire Metro system.

Union Station has a mix of terminal and through tracks.  Most of the upper level platforms, used mainly by MARC, Amtrak's Northeast Regional trains, and Acela, are terminal, with trains only arriving from and departing to the north.  Several of the lower level tracks are through platforms, and are mainly used by VRE, as well as most of Amtrak's long-distance trains and Northeast Regional trains operating to/from [[Newport News, Virginia|Newport News]], and [[Lynchburg, Virginia|Lynchburg]].

==Architecture ==
[[Image:Union-Sta-interior.jpg|thumb|left|The grand, central interior of Union Station]]
Architect [[Daniel Burnham]], assisted by Pierce Anderson, was inspired by a number of different [[architectural style]]s. [[Classical architecture|Classical]] elements included the [[Arch of Constantine]] (exterior, main facade) and the great vaulted spaces of the [[Baths of Diocletian]] (interior); prominent siting at the intersection of two of [[Pierre L'Enfant|Pierre L'Enfant's]] avenues, with an orientation that faced the [[United States Capitol]] just five blocks away; a massive scale, including a facade stretching more than 600 feet and a waiting room ceiling 96 feet above the floor; stone inscriptions and [[allegorical sculpture]] in the [[Beaux-Arts architecture|Beaux-Arts style]]; expensive materials such as marble, [[gold leaf]], and white granite from a previously unused quarry.

In the [[Attic style|Attic]] block, above the main cornice of the central block, stand six colossal statues (modeled on the [[Dacia]]n prisoners of the Arch of Constantine) designed by [[Louis St. Gaudens]]. These are entitled &quot;[[The Progress of Railroading]]&quot; and their iconography expresses the confident enthusiasm of the [[American Renaissance]] movement: [[Prometheus]] (for Fire), [[Thales]] (for Electricity), [[Themis]] (for Freedom and Justice), [[Apollo]] (for Imagination and Inspiration), [[Ceres (Roman mythology)|Ceres]] (for Agriculture) and [[Archimedes]] (for Mechanics). The substitution of Agriculture for Commerce in a railroad station iconography vividly conveys the power of a specifically American [[lobbying]] bloc.  St. Gaudens also created the 26 [[centurion]]s for the station's main hall.

Burnham drew upon a tradition, launched with the 1837 [[Euston railway station]] in [[London]], of treating the entrance to a major terminal as a [[triumphal arch]]. He linked the monumental end pavilions with long arcades enclosing [[loggia]]s in a long series of bays that were vaulted with the lightweight fireproof [[Guastavino tile]]s favored by American Beaux-Arts architects. The final aspect owed much to the Court of Heroes at the [[World's Columbian Exposition|World’s Columbian Exposition]] of 1893 in [[Chicago]], where Burnham had been coordinating architect.  The setting of Union Station’s facade at the focus of converging avenues in a park-like green setting is one of the few executed achievements of the [[City Beautiful]] movement: elite city planning that was based on the &quot;goosefoot&quot; (''patte d'oie'') of formal garden plans made by [[Baroque]] designers such as [[André Le Nôtre]]. The radiating avenues can be seen in the satellite view (''illustration, left'').

The station held a full range of dining rooms and other services, including [[barber]] shops and a mortuary.  Union Station was equipped with a presidential suite which is now occupied by a restaurant.

==History==
===Planning===
When the [[Pennsylvania Railroad]] and the [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]] announced in 1901 that they planned to build a new terminal, people in the city celebrated for two reasons:
*The decision meant that both the Pennsylvania and the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad would soon remove their trackwork and terminals from the [[National Mall]]. Though changes there appeared only gradually, the consolidation of the depots allowed the creation of the Mall as it appears today.
*The plans to bring all the city's railroads under one roof promised that Washington would finally have a station both large enough to handle large crowds and impressive enough to befit the city's role as the federal capital.

===Operation===
Union Station opened on October 27, 1907, with the arrival of a Baltimore and Ohio Railroad passenger train from [[Pittsburgh]]. The terminal quickly became the portal to the Capitol. At no time was it busier than during [[World War II]], when as many as 200,000 people passed through in a single day.

For most of its existence, Union Station served as a hub, with service of the [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]], [[Pennsylvania Railroad]], and [[Southern Railway (US)|Southern Railway]]. The [[Richmond, Fredericksburg &amp; Potomac|Richmond, Fredericksburg &amp; Potomac Railroad]] provided a link to [[Richmond, Virginia]], about 100 miles to the south, where major north-south lines of the [[Atlantic Coast Line Railroad]] and [[Seaboard Air Line Railroad]] provided service to the Carolinas, [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], and [[Florida]].

===Decline===
[[File:WashingtonUnionStation1974.jpg|thumb|left|South entrance, 1974]]
In 1967, the chairman of the [[United States Civil Service Commission|Civil Service Commission]] expressed interest in using Union Station as a visitor center during the upcoming [[United States Bicentennial|Bicentennial]] celebrations. Funding for this was collected over the next six years, and the reconstruction of the station included outfitting the Main Hall with a recessed pit to display a slide show presentation. This was officially the PAVE (Primary Audio-Visual Experience), but was sarcastically referred to as &quot;the Pit.&quot; The entire project was completed, save for the parking garage, and opening ceremonies were held on [[Independence Day (United States)|Independence Day]] 1976.  Due to a lack of publicity and convenient parking, the [[National Visitor Center]] was never popular. Following a 1977 [[Government Accountability Office|General Accounting Office]] report indicating Union Station was in danger of imminent structural collapse, the [[National Park Service]] closed the presentation in &quot;the Pit&quot; on October 28, 1978.

===Restoration===
{{further|[[National Visitor Center]]}}
As a result of the [[Redevelopment Act of 1981]], Union Station was closed for restoration and refurbishing. [[Mold]] was growing in the leaking ceiling of the Main Hall, and the carpet laid out for an [[United States presidential inauguration|Inauguration Day]] celebration was full of cigarette-burned holes. In 1988, [[United States Secretary of Transportation|Secretary of Transportation]] [[Elizabeth Dole]], awarded $70 million to the restoration effort. &quot;The Pit&quot; was transformed into a new basement level, and the Main Hall floor was refitted with marble.  While installing new [[HVAC]] systems, crews discovered antique items in shafts that had not been opened since the building's creation. The decorative elements of the station were also restored.

The station reopened in its present form in 1988.  The former “Pit” area was replaced with an [[AMC Theatres|AMC]] movie theater (later Phoenix Theatres, closed October 12, 2009, to be replaced with additional restaurants) and a large [[food court]] in the former baggage-mail level. The food court still retains the original arches under which the trains were parked as well as the track numbers on those arches. A variety of shops opened along the Concourse and Main Hall, and a new [[Amtrak]] terminal at the back behind the original Concourse. In 1994, the passenger concourse was renamed to honor [[W. Graham Claytor Jr.|W. Graham Claytor, Jr.]], who served as Amtrak's president from 1982 to 1993.

On August 1, 2011, [[John Porcari]], the [[United States Deputy Secretary of Transportation]], announced that Union Station would begin serving intercity busses operated by [[Greyhound Lines]], [[BoltBus]], [[Megabus (North America)|Megabus]] and [[Washington Deluxe]] later that year from a new bus facility in the station's parking garage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Thomson|first=Robert|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/union-station-to-become-intercity-bus-center/2011/07/29/gIQAFcPwjI_story.html|title=Union Station to become intercity bus center|work=PostLocal|publisher=[[The Washington Post]]|date=2011-07-30|accessdate=2011-08-02|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60cvLQo4P | archivedate=2011-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By November 15, 2011,  BoltBus, Megabus and Washington Deluxe were operating from the new facility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Associated Press|authorlink=Associated Press|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/officials-to-inaugurate-revamped-bus-departure-zone-at-washingtons-union-station/2011/11/15/gIQAZJwiNN_story.html|title=Officials to inaugurate revamped bus departure zone at Washington’s Union Station|work=PostLocal|publisher=[[The Washington Post]]|date=2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ivy City Yard, just north of Union Station, houses a large Amtrak maintenance facility. This includes the new maintenance facility for the Acela high speed train sets. Amtrak also does contract work for [[MARC Train|MARC]]'s electric locomotives. Metro's Brentwood maintenance facility is also located in the southwest corner of the [[Ivy City, Washington, D.C.|Ivy City]] Yard. Riding the Metro Red Line between Union Station and Rhode Island Avenue Station gives you a great aerial view of the south end of the Ivy City yard.

Union Station is owned by the non-profit Union Station Redevelopment Corporation, but an 84-year lease of the property is held by New York-based [http://www.aacrealty.com/pressfiles/pdfs/washingtonpost.pdf Ashkenazy Acquisition Corporation] and managed by Chicago-based [[Jones Lang LaSalle]].  It houses the headquarters of [[Amtrak]] and carries the [[IATA airport code]] of ZWU.&lt;ref name=&quot;airport&quot;&gt;[http://www.lastupdate.com/usairports/airportcodes_us_w.html LastUpDate.com – Help – Three Letter Airport Codes&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Incidents==
===1953 overrun===
On the morning of January 15, 1953, the Pennsylvania Railroad's ''[[Federal Express (passenger train)|Federal]]'', the overnight train from [[Boston South Station|Boston]], crashed into the station.  When the engineer tried to apply the [[Train brakes|trainline brakes]] two miles out of the platforms, he discovered that he only had engine brakes. He radioed a warning ahead, and the concourse was cleared as the train coasted downhill into track 16. The [[GG1]] locomotive, No. 4876, hit the bumper post at about 25 miles per hour, jumped onto the platform, destroyed the stationmaster’s office at the end of the track, took out a newsstand, and was on its way to crashing through the wall into the Great Hall. Just then, the floor of the terminal, having never been designed to carry the weight of a locomotive, gave way, dropping the engine into the basement. The 447,000-pound electric locomotive fell into about the center of what is now the [[food court]]. Remarkably, no one was killed, and passengers in the rear cars thought that they had only had a rough stop. An investigation revealed that an anglecock on the brakeline had been closed, probably by an [[icicle]] knocked from an overhead bridge. The accident inspired the finale of the [[1976 in film|1976 film]] ''[[Silver Streak (film)|Silver Streak]]''.{{fact|date=October 2011}} The durable design of the GG1 made its damage repairable, and it was soon back in service after being hauled away in pieces to the PRR's main shops in [[Altoona, Pennsylvania]]. Before the latter action was undertaken, however, the GG1 and the hole it made were temporarily planked over and hidden from view due to the imminent inauguration of [[General of the Army (United States)|General]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] as the thirty-fourth [[President of the United States]].

==Union Station in the media==
Washington’s Union Station has featured as a location in numerous movies, not all as memorable as ''[[Mr. Smith Goes to Washington]]''. Others include ''[[Strangers on a Train (film)]]'', ''[[Hannibal (film)|Hannibal]]'', ''[[The Recruit]]'', ''[[Along Came a Spider]]'', ''[[Collateral Damage (film)|Collateral Damage]]'', ''[[The Sentinel (2006 film)|The Sentinel]]'', ''[[My Fellow Americans]]'', and ''[[Wedding Crashers]]''.

Several episodes of the television series ''[[The West Wing (TV series)|The West Wing]]'' used Union Station as a setting. Union Station was used as a setting for one episode of the [[CBS]] military courtroom drama ''[[JAG (TV series)|JAG]]'', and was frequently mentioned in that series as being a landmark located to the south of the main character [[Harmon Rabb]]'s apartment building.

The station has also been the subject of multiple books.  The 128-page ''Union Station: A Decorative History of Washington’s Grand Terminal'' by [[Carol Highsmith]] and [[Ted Landphair]] tells the complete history of the station through text and photographs.  Presidential daughter [[Margaret Truman]]’s Capital Crimes mystery series includes a ''[[Murder at Union Station]]'' novel.

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; perrow=4&gt;
Image:Union station washington.jpg|Entrance area
Image:Union StationDC.jpg|Wide-angle view of the main hall
Image:Louisstgaudens1.jpg|[[Thales]] (Electricity) statue by [[Louis St. Gaudens]] over entrance
Image:Union Station - Washington, D.C..jpg|Union Station, 1925
Image:Washington-union-nec.jpg|Northeast Corridor platforms and tracks at Union Station (Lower Level)
Image:Union Station at Dusk.jpg|The front of Union Station at dusk
Image:AcelaWashington.JPG|Amtrak Acela Express at Union Station (Upper Level)
File:MARC and Amtrak at Union Station.JPG|Amtrak and MARC at Union Station (Upper Level)
File:Loggia - Union Station, DC.jpg|Union Station's [[loggia]]
Image:Washington DC Union Station (USGS).png|[[United States Geological Survey]] [[satellite image]] of Union Station
File:Liberty Bell Replica.jpg|[[Liberty Bell]] replica outside station
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Union stations]]
*[[Union Station (Washington Metro)]]
*[[Columbus Fountain]] located in front of Union Station.
*[[Washington Terminal Company]]
*[[American Legion Freedom Bell]] located in front of Union Station.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Union Station (Washington, D.C.)}}
*[http://www.unionstationdc.com/ Official Site]
*[http://www.washingtonunionstation.com/ History of Union Station]
*[http://www.bluffton.edu/~sullivanm/washdc/unionsta/unionstation.html Union Station]
*[http://www.cr.nps.gov/nr/travel/wash/dc80.htm Renovation of Union Station]
*[http://www.dcnrhs.org/union_station/ National Railway Historical Society:] brief history
*[http://www.dcnrhs.org/learn/washington-d-c-railroad-history/wreck-of-the-federal-express NIHS Wreck of the ''Federal Express'']
{{Amtrak web|WAS|Washington Union Station|DC}}
*[http://www.vre.org/service/stations/WAS.htm Virginia Railway Express]
*[http://www.wmata.com/metrorail/Stations/station.cfm?station=25 WMATA Metro Bus Connections] and [http://www.wmata.com/metrorail/Stations/evacuation/06.025.pdf Evacuations]
* [http://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=38.896836,-77.007669&amp;spn=0.003975,0.013443&amp;z=17&amp;layer=c&amp;cbll=38.896602,-77.007509&amp;panoid=P7-ees8HR9GVOBMY1o4H6g&amp;cbp=12,46.9,,0,-1.03 Station Building from Google Maps Street View]

{{MTA Maryland}}
{{Registered Historic Places}}
{{DC Malls}}

[[Category:Railway stations on the National Register of Historic Places in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Amtrak stations in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Beaux-Arts architecture in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Stations along Baltimore and Ohio Railroad lines|Washington]]
[[Category:Stations along Philadelphia, Baltimore and Washington Railroad lines|Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad]]
[[Category:Union stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1907]]
[[Category:Shopping malls in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Railway stations opened in 1907]]
[[Category:Transit centers]]
[[Category:Transit centers in the United States]]
[[Category:Virginia Railway Express stations]]
[[Category:Maryland Area Regional Commuter stations]]
[[Category:Jones Lang LaSalle]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Arcades (architecture)]]

[[da:Union Station (Washington D.C.)]]
[[fa:یونیون استیشن]]
[[it:Union Station (Washington)]]
[[ka:იუნიონ სტეიშენი (ვაშინგტონი)]]
[[nl:Union Station (Washington D.C.)]]
[[ja:ユニオン駅 (ワシントンD.C.)]]
[[sv:Union Station, Washington D.C.]]
[[zh:聯合車站 (華盛頓特區)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
