<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4120656" ns="0" title="Windows Mobility Center"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Windows component
| name               = Windows Mobility Center
| logo               = Windows Mobility Center icon.png
| screenshot         = Windows Mobility Center screenshot.png
| caption            = 
| included_with      = [[Windows Vista]], [[Windows 7]] 
| replaces           = 
| replaced_by        = 
| related_components = 
}}
'''Windows Mobility Center''' is a component of [[Microsoft Windows]], introduced in [[Windows Vista]], that centralizes the most relevant information to mobile computing.

==Overview==
The Windows Mobility Center [[user interface]] presents a series of square tiles that each contain one piece of information about a component of the system, as well as action items related to that component.  The tiles that appear depend on the system.  Windows Vista includes the following tiles:

* Brightness adjustment
* Sound adjustment / mute
* Battery level / power scheme selection
* Wireless network status
* Screen orientation (portrait or landscape)
* External displays
* Synchronization to other machines
* Presentation settings

Additional panes can be added by individual mobile computer manufacturers wanting to reveal functionality unique to their products.

Windows Mobility Center is located in the [[Control Panel (Windows)|Control Panel]], and can also be launched by pressing the [[Windows key]] + X.  It is inaccessible on non-mobile computers, however it is possible to enable Mobility Center on desktop systems using a registry hack.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dubuque.k12.ia.us/it/mobilitycenter/&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows Mobility Center is included with the Home Basic (although a Windows Vista help topic misinformed that Mobility Center is not available there), Home Premium, Business, Enterprise, and Ultimate editions of Windows Vista.

== Customization ==

Windows Mobility Center can be customized by adding extensions, called &quot;tile&quot;s. This customization is [[OEM]]-specific, according to [[Microsoft]] whitepaper; but there are several extensions available on the net from non-OEM origin.

== See also ==
* [[Windows Vista]]
* [[Features new to Windows Vista]]

== External links ==
* [http://windowshelp.microsoft.com/Windows/en-US/help/b09c69fb-c6c8-44cf-9e8d-c990fd1a13141033.mspx Using Windows Mobility Center] from Windows Help and Support

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Windows Components}}

[[Category:Mobile computers]]
[[Category:Windows components|Mobility Center]]

[[bg:Windows Mobility Center]]
[[et:Windows Mobility Center]]
[[ko:윈도 모바일 센터]]
[[ru:Центр мобильности Windows]]
[[tl:Windows Mobility Center]]
[[vi:Windows Mobility Center]]
[[zh:Windows行動中心]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
