<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4128916" ns="0" title="Sawsan Al Sha&#039;er"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Sawsan Al Sha’er''' ({{lang-ar|سوسن الشاعر}}) is widely regarded as [[Bahrain]]’s most influential liberal intellectual. A journalist and author, she is a columnist with Al Watan newspaper, having joined the staff there from the pro-government Al Ayam. 

Ms Al Sha’er is well known for her liberal opinions and has been an outspoken critic of religious extremism. Unlike many Arab liberals, Ms Al Sha’er has not been afraid to debate with religious clerics and criticize their opinions. This has brought her into confrontation with many of Bahrain’s [[Islamist]] politicians, such as [[Ali Salman]] and [[Adel Mouwda]]. She has accused extremists backing suicide bombers in Iraq of trying to ‘lead Bahrain to hell’.

While a leading supporter of King Hamad’s [[Politics of Bahrain|political liberalization]], Ms Al Sha’er has criticised the government whenever it has failed to meet its reform commitments and over the performance of individual ministers. On 26 February 2006, in Al Watan she was scathing about the Minister of Housing, Fahmi Al Jowder, over his &quot;ludicrous praise reminiscent of the Saddam Hussain coterie&quot; [http://archive.gulfnews.com/articles/06/03/01/10022312.html].

==External links==
* [http://memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=archives&amp;Area=sd&amp;ID=SP93105 MEMRI] translates into English a debate in the Bahraini press on suicide bombers between Sawsan Al Sha’er and Akhbar Al Khaleej columnist Hafez Al-Sheikh Saleh (8 July 2005).
* [http://www.freemuslims.org/news/article.php?article=648 The Proponents of the Suicide Ideology Have Taken Advantage of Global Communications] (Eng trans by MEMRI), Free Muslims, (15 May 2005)

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Al Sha'er
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Al Sha'er}}
[[Category:Bahraini journalists]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Arab journalists]]
[[Category:Year of birth missing (living people)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
