<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4131220" ns="0" title="List of Grand Theft Auto Advance characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--Note also that facts covered in this article is as of the release of ''Advance'' in 2004, and as such, primarily discusses the characters based on information in ''Advance'' and earlier ''Grand Theft Auto'' games. While ''San Andreas'' was released at the same time as ''Advance'', ''Advance'' was developed by a different development house, the consistency of canons from ''Advance'' and ''San Andreas'' is unconfirmed. Thus ''San Andreas'' is not currently considered when discussing characters in ''Advance''. For information on listed characters in later ''GTA'' games, see their respectable &quot;see also&quot; link(s) at the end of each section (when available).--&gt;
A number of recurring '''characters''' appear during the various missions or [[cut scene]]s in the [[video game]] '''''[[Grand Theft Auto Advance]]''''', set roughly one year before events in ''[[Grand Theft Auto III]]'' (which takes place in late-2001). Prominent characters are listed here in rough order of appearance.

==Major characters==
===Mike===
''Introduced in: &quot;Jump Start&quot;''

'''Mike''' is '''Grand Theft Auto Advance'''s [[protagonist]] and [[player character]]. He and partner [[#Vinnie|Vinnie]] had earned enough money to leave [[Liberty City (Grand Theft Auto)|Liberty City]] for good, but Mike was coaxed by Vinnie to take a few more jobs from the Mafia before leaving. After Vinnie was thought to be killed by a car bomb, Mike attempted to trace the killer, while attracting negative attention from all gangs in the city. Learning that Vinnie was still alive, was responsible for killing several of his bosses, and was intending to leave with Mike's share of the earned money, he killed Vinnie. Mike eventually escapes the city with a private aircraft owned by [[#Cisco|Cisco]], Mike's deceased ally and leader of the [[List of gangs in Grand Theft Auto series#Colombian Cartel|Colombian Cartel]]. In the final cutscene in Cisco's plane, Mike says he may travel to Colombia.

===Vinnie===
''Introduced in: &quot;Jump Start&quot;''

''Killed in: &quot;Truth Revealed&quot;''

'''Vinnie''' is the partner and boss of Mike, who insisted Mike in doing a few more jobs before leaving the city. He was allegedly killed by a car bomb, with &quot;his&quot; remains found in the car. He would be killed by Mike, as he reveals his true nature and motive. He is the main [[antagonist]] of the game.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===8-Ball===
''Introduced in: &quot;Fake ID's&quot;''

'''8-Ball''' is Mike's second boss after Vinnie was thought to be killed. Initially supplying Mike with several missions while aiding him in tracking Vinnie's murderer, 8-Ball would be on the run as he was chased by Vinnie's assassins.

A mission near the end of the game features Mike ambushed by the Colombian Cartel while meeting 8-Ball at a diner. During this attack, the Cartel members use [[flamethrower]]s as their primary weapons; 8-Ball was caught in the crossfire. Upon completion of the mission, 8-Ball reveals that he has been severely burned, and tells Mike to escape as police arrive on the scene. He is eventually arrested by the police, connecting to the start of ''[[Grand Theft Auto III]]''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s storyline (in which he would later escape, with his &quot;messed up&quot; hands wrapped in bandages, from police custody along with [[Claude (Grand Theft Auto)|Claude]] in ''GTA III''). This is disputed, however, as an article from the ''[[The New York Times|Liberty Tree]]'''s website, created as a teaser for ''GTA III'', states that 8-Ball's hands were scalded by a pot of burning fat while involved in a scuffle with police.

:''See also: [[List of characters in Grand Theft Auto III#8-Ball|GTA III rendition]] &amp; [[List of characters in Grand Theft Auto: Liberty City Stories#8-Ball|GTA: Liberty City Stories rendition]]

===Jonnie===
''Introduced in: &quot;Love Boat&quot;''

''Killed in: &quot;Show the Money&quot;''

'''Jonnie''' is a bartender in the Red Light District, Portland Island. He served as Mike's third boss, before he was assassinated. Mike's discovery of Jonnie's death was followed by a pursuit of Yardie members that led to [[#King Courtney|King Courtney]], the head of the [[List of gangs in Grand Theft Auto series#Uptown Yardies|Yardies]].
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===King Courtney===
''Introduced in: &quot;Race to Run&quot;''

'''King Courtney''' is the leader of the [[List of gangs in Grand Theft Auto series#Uptown Yardies|Uptown Yardies]] and Mike's fourth boss. Involved in a turf war with the Colombian Cartel, Courtney is also involved in illegal racing around Staunton Island. He and his gang would serve as another primary antagonist alongside Vinnie near the end of the storyline.

:''See also: [[List of characters in Grand Theft Auto III#King Courtney|GTA III rendition]]

===Cisco===
''Introduced in: &quot;Fine Dining&quot;''

''Killed in: &quot;Decoy Disaster&quot;''

'''Cisco'''  is the leader of the [[List of gangs in Grand Theft Auto series#Colombian Cartel|Colombian Cartel]] and Mike's fifth boss. He was killed by Vinnie.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

===Asuka Kasen===
''Introduced in: &quot;Kid's a Hero&quot;''

'''Asuka Kasen''' ([[Japanese language|Japanese]]: 飛鳥加瀬) is the leader of the Yakuza and is Mike's sixth boss. Asuka is revealed to have bizarre fetishes and sexual preferences ([[BDSM]]).

:''See also: [[List of characters in Grand Theft Auto III#Asuka Kasen|GTA III rendition]]

===Yuka===
''Introduced in: &quot;School's Out&quot;''

'''Yuka''' ([[Japanese language|Japanese]]: 優香) is Asuka Kasen's young niece. Yuka served in only two major plotlines, in which Mike was ordered by Cisco to kidnap Yuka as Cartel blackmail to the Yakuza, before she would eventually be rescued by Mike and returned to Asuka.

===Misty===
''Introduced in: &quot;Ill Repute&quot;''

'''Misty''' is working as a prostitute and was an associate of 8-Ball. She agrees to help 8-Ball and Mike find out more information about Vinnie's death by sleeping with some high-rolling clients who may have information. She later works for Yakuza co-leader Asuka Kasen on Staunton Island and meets Mike again, when Asuka sends him to deal with a pimp who had been stalking some of her girls.

:''See also: [[List of characters in Grand Theft Auto III#Misty|GTA III rendition]]

{{Grand Theft Auto}}

==External links==
*[http://www.grandtheftwiki.com/Characters_in_GTA_Advance Characters in GTA Advance article on Grand Theft Wiki]

[[Category:Grand Theft Auto Advance|Characters]]
[[Category:Lists of Grand Theft Auto characters| 3.4]]

[[pt:Anexo:Lista de personagens de Grand Theft Auto Advance]]
[[ru:Список персонажей Grand Theft Auto Advance]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
