<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="413436" ns="0" title="Puebla"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the state|the city|Puebla, Puebla}}
{{Other uses}}

{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Puebla
| native_name             = &lt;small&gt;Estado Libre y Soberano de Puebla&lt;/small&gt;
| native_name_lang        = 
| settlement_type         = [[States of Mexico|State]]
| image_flag              = Flag of Puebla.svg
| flag_size               = 160px
| flag_alt                = 
| image_seal              = Coat of arms of Puebla.svg
| seal_size               = 65px
| nickname                = &lt;!--NO--&gt;
| motto                   ={{-}}&lt;small&gt;''Unidos En El Tiempo, En El Esfuerzo, En La Justicia y En La Esperanza''&lt;/small&gt;{{-}}&lt;small&gt;''(United in time, effort, justice and hope)''&lt;/small&gt;
| anthem                  = Himno al Estado de Puebla
| image_map               = Puebla en Mexico.PNG
| map_caption             = State of Puebla within Mexico
| latd  =19  |latm  =00  |lats  =13 |latNS  =N
| longd = 97 |longm =53  |longs =18 |longEW =W
| coor_pinpoint           = 
| coordinates_type        = region:MX-PUE_type:adm1st
| coordinates_display     = inline,title
| coordinates_footnotes   = 
| subdivision_type        = [[Country]]
| subdivision_name        = [[Mexico]]
| subdivision_type1       = [[Capital City|Capital]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Puebla de Zaragoza]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of cities in Mexico|Largest&amp;nbsp;City]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Puebla de Zaragoza]]
| subdivision_type3       = [[Municipalities of Mexico|Municipalities]]
| subdivision_name3       = [[Municipalities of Puebla|217]]
| established_title       = [[Sovereign state|Admission]]
| established_date        = December 21, 1823&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Las Diputaciones Provinciales| url =http://biblio.juridicas.unam.mx/libros/6/2920/11.pdf|page=15 |language =Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| established_title2     = [[Territorial evolution of Mexico|Order]]
| established_date2      = [[Territorial evolution of Mexico|4th]]
| founder                 = 
| seat_type               = 
| seat                    = 
| government_footnotes    = 
| leader_party            = 
| leader_title            = [[List of Mexican state governors|Governor]]
| leader_name             = [[Rafael Moreno Valle Rosas|Rafael Moreno Valle]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|[[National Action Party (Mexico)|PAN]]|23px]]
| leader_title1           = [[Senate of Mexico|Senators]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Senadores por Puebla LXI Legislatura |url=http://www.senado.gob.mx/index.php?ver=int&amp;mn=4&amp;sm=4&amp;id=22 |publisher=Senado de la Republica |accessdate=April 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| leader_name1            = [[María del Rosario Leticia Jasso Valencia|Leticia Jasso Valencia]] '''([[Independent (politician)|I]])'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Marco Humberto Aguilar Coronado|Humberto Aguilar]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Melquiades Morales Flores|Melquiades Morales]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
|leader_title2           = [[Chamber of Deputies of Mexico|Deputies]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Listado de Diputados por Grupo Parlamentario del Estado de Puebla |url=http://sitl.diputados.gob.mx/LXI_leg/listado_diputados_gpnp.php?tipot=Edo&amp;edot=21|publisher=Camara de Diputados |accessdate=April 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_name2            = {{Collapsible list
 |title       = [[Chamber of Deputies of Mexico|Federal Deputies]]
 |frame_style = border:none; padding: 0;
 |title_style = &lt;!-- (optional) --&gt;
 |list_style  = text-align:left;display:none;
 |1           = • [[José Óscar Aguilar González|Óscar Aguilar]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |2           = • [[José Alberto González Morales|Alberto González]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |3           = • [[Janet Graciela González Tostado|Janet González Tostado]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |4           = • [[María del Carmen Izaguirre Francos|María Izaguirre]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |5           = • [[Juan Pablo Jiménez Concha|Juan Pablo Jiménez]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |6           = • [[Blanca Estela Jiménez Hernández|Estela Jiménez]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |7           = • [[Francisco Alberto Jiménez Merino|Alberto Jiménez]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |8           = • [[Jorge Alberto Juraidini Rumilla|Alberto Juraidini]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |9           = • [[Juan Carlos Lastiri Quirós|Juan Carlos Lastiri]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |10          = • [[Julieta Octavia Marín Torres|Julieta Marín]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |11          = • [[María Isabel Merlo Talavera|María Isabel Merlo]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |12          = • [[Fernando Morales Martínez|Fernando Morales]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |13          = • [[Francisco Ramos Montaño|Francisco Ramos]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |14          = • [[Leobardo Soto Martínez|Leobardo Soto]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |15          = • [[Ricardo Urzúa Rivera|Ricardo Urzúa]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |16          = • [[Augusta Valentina Díaz de Rivera Hernández|Valentina Díaz de Rivera]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]
 |17          = • [[María del Carmen Guzmán Lozano|Carmen Guzmán]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]
 |18          = • [[Juan Carlos Natale López|Juan Carlos Natale]]  
 }}
| unit_pref               = Metric&lt;!-- or US or UK --&gt;
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Resumen |url=http://cuentame.inegi.gob.mx/monografias/informacion/pue/default.aspx?tema=me&amp;e=21|publisher=Cuentame INEGI |accessdate=April 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_km2          = 34290 
| area_land_km2           = 
| area_water_km2          = 
| area_water_percent      =
| area_note               = [[List of Mexican states by area|Ranked 21st]]
| elevation_m             =
| elevation_max_footnotes =&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Relieve |url=http://cuentame.inegi.gob.mx/monografias/informacion/pue/territorio/relieve.aspx?tema=me&amp;e=21|publisher=Cuentame INEGI |accessdate=April 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| elevation_max_m         = 5610
| elevation_max_ft        =
| elevation_min_m         = 
| elevation_min_ft        =
| population_footnotes    = &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Mexico en Cifras |url=http://www.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/mexicocifras/default.aspx?ent=21|publisher=INEGI |accessdate=April 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_total        = 5779829
| population_as_of        = 2010
| population_rank         = [[List of Mexican states by population|5th]]
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_density_rank = [[List of Mexican states by population density|6th]]
| population_demonym      = Poblano (a)
| population_note         = 
| timezone1               = [[Central Time Zone|CST]]
| utc_offset1             = −6
| timezone1_DST           = [[Central Daylight Time|CDT]]
| utc_offset1_DST         = −5
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal codes in Mexico|Postal code]]
| postal_code             = 72-75
| area_code_type          = [[Area code]]
| area_code               = {{Collapsible list
|title       = [[Area codes in Mexico by code (900-999)|Area codes]]
|frame_style = border:none; padding: 0;
|title_style = &lt;!-- (optional) --&gt;
|list_style  = text-align:left;display:none;
 |1           = • [[Area codes in Mexico by code (200-299)|1]]
 |2           = • [[Area codes in Mexico by code (700-799)|2]]
 |3           = • [[Area codes in Mexico by code (900-999)|3]]
}}
| iso_code                = MX-PUE
| blank_name_sec1         = [[Human Development Index|HDI]]
| blank_info_sec1         = {{increase}} 0.791 &lt;span style=&quot;color:#fc0&quot;&gt;medium&lt;/span&gt; &lt;small&gt;[[List of Mexican states by HDI|Ranked 28th]]&lt;/small&gt;
| blank_name_sec2         = [[GDP]]
| blank_info_sec2         = US$ 23,525,310.625 [[Million|mil]]{{Ref label|engfactobox|a|}}
| website                 = {{URL|http://www.puebla.gob.mx/|Official Web Site}}
| footnotes               = 
{{note|engoffbox}}a. The state's GDP was 301,123,976 million of [[Mexican peso|pesos]] in 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Jalisco. |url=http://www.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/mexicocifras/default.aspx?ent=21|year=2010 |accessdate=April 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; amount corresponding to 23,525,310.625 millon of [[Dollar coin (United States)|dollars]], being a dollar worth 12.80 pesos (value of June 3, 2010).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Reporte: Jueves 3 de Junio del 2010. Cierre del peso mexicano. |url=http://www.pesomexicano.com.mx/archivo/2010/junio/03/reporte-jueves-3-de-junio-del-2010--cierre-del-peso-mexicano.htm#leermas |publisher=www.pesomexicano.com.mx |accessdate=August 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
}}

'''Puebla''' ({{IPA-es|ˈpweβla}}) officially ''Estado Libre y Soberano de Puebla'' ({{lang-en|Free and Sovereign State of Puebla}}) is one of the 31 states which, with the [[Mexico City|Federal District]], comprise the [[Political divisions of Mexico|32 Federal Entities]] of [[Mexico]]. It is divided in [[Municipalities of Puebla|217 municipalities]] and its capital city is [[Puebla, Puebla|Puebla]].

It is located in [[Eastern Mexico|East-Central Mexico]]. It is bordered by the states of [[Veracruz]] to the north and east, [[Hidalgo (state)|Hidalgo]], [[State of Mexico|México]], [[Tlaxcala]] and [[Morelos (state)|Morelos]] to the west, [[Guerrero (state)|Guerrero]] and [[Oaxaca]] to the south.

The origins of the state lie in the city of Puebla, which was founded by the Spanish in this valley in 1531 to secure the trade route between [[Mexico City]] and the [[Veracruz, Veracruz|port of Veracruz]]. 

By the end of the 18th century, the area had become a colonial province with its own governor, which would become the State of Puebla, after the [[Mexican War of Independence]] in the early 19th century. Since that time, the area, especially around the capital city, has continued to grow economically, mostly through industry, despite being the scene of a number of battles, the most notable of which being the [[Battle of Puebla]]. Today, the state is one of the most industrialized in the country, but since most of its development is concentrated in Puebla and other cities, many of its rural areas are very poor, forcing many to migrate away to places such as Mexico City and the United States.

Culturally, the state is home to the [[China Poblana]], [[mole poblano]], active literary and arts scenes and festivals such as [[Cinco de Mayo]], Ritual of Quetzalcoatl, [[Day of the Dead]] celebrations (especially in [[Huaquechula]]) and [[Carnival]] (especially in [[Huejotzingo (municipality)|Huejotzingo]]). It is home to five major indigenous groups: [[Nahuas]], the [[Totonac]]as, the [[Mixtec]]as, the [[Popoloca]]s and the [[Otomi people|Otomi]], which can mostly be found in the far north and the far south of the state.

==Geography and ecology==
[[File:NECAXA.JPG|thumb|left|Lake and mountains in Necaxa]]
The state is located on the central highlands of Mexico between the [[Trans-Mexican Volcanic Belt|Sierra Nevada]] and the [[Sierra Madre Oriental]]. It has a roughly triangular shape with its narrow part to the north. It borders the states of Veracruz, Oaxaca, Guerrero, Morelos, State of Mexico, Tlaxcala and Hidalgo. The state has a territory of 33,919km2 and ranks 20th out of 31 states in size, and 4,930 named communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.e-local.gob.mx/work/templates/enciclo/puebla/regi.htm |title= Medio Fisico |year=2009 |work= Enciclopedia de los Municipios de México Estado de Puebla |publisher= Instituto Nacional para el Federalismo y el Desarrollo Municipal |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=Fisical Medium |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mountains===
Most of its mountains belong to the Sierra Madre Oriental and the Trans-Mexican Volcanic Belt. The first is locally called the Sierra Norte del Puebla, entering the state from the northwest and then breaks up into the smaller chains of Sierra de Zacapoaxtla, Sierra de Huauchinango, Sierra de Teziutlán, Sierra de Tetela de Ocampo, Sierra de Chignahuapan and Sierra de Zacatlán, although these names may vary among localities. Some of the highest elevations include Apulco, Chichat, Chignahuapan, Soltepec and Tlatlaquitepec. The highest elevations are the volcanoes [[Pico de Orizaba]] or Citlaltepetl (5,747masl), [[Popocatépetl]] (5,452masl), [[Iztaccíhuatl]] (5,286masl) and [[Matlalcueitl (volcano)|Malinche]] (4,461masl) which are found on the state’s borders with Veracruz, Mexico State and Tlaxcala respectively.   In the south of the state, the major elevations are the Sierra de Atenahuacán, Zapotitlán, Lomerio al Suroeste and the Sierra de Tehuacán. Dividing much of the state from Veracruz is a small chain of mountains called the Sierra Madre del Golfo.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

The natural geography of the state subdivides into the Huasteco Plateau, Llanuras y Lomeríos zone, Lagos y Volcanes del Anáhuac, Chiconquiaco, Llanuras y Sierras de Querétaro e Hidalgo, Cordillera Costera del Sur, Mixteca Alta, Sierras y Valles Guerrenses, Sierras Centrales de Oaxaca, Sierras Orientales and Sur de Puebla. The Huasteco Plateau and the Llanuras y Lomeríos zone are located in the north and northeast, with the Lagos y Volcanes del Anáhuc in the center and north. Together, they account for over 50% of the state.  The east and northeast are occupies by the Chiconquiaco and Llanudras y Sierras de Querétaro e Hidalgo areas and account for about three percent of the state.  The Cordillera del Sur and Mixteca Alta are located in the west and southwest covering less than 2.5% of the state. The Sur de Puebla is in the southwest and accounts for 26% of the state. Other southern subregions include the Sierras y Valles Guerrerenses, the Sierras Centrales de Oaxaca and the Sierras Orientales. Together, they account for about 15% of the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

===Hydrology===
[[File:Río Petlapa.jpg|thumb|Petlapa River]]
The hydrology of Puebla is formed by three major river systems. This first is based on the [[Atoyac River]], which  originates with the melting runoff of the Halos, Telapón and Papagayo mountains along with those from the Iztaccihuatl volcano and waters from the Zahuapan River, which enters from Tlaxcala. This river receives further water from tributaries such as the Acateno, Atila, Amacuzac, Molinos and Cohetzala. The river has one major dam called Valsequllo or Manuel Avila Camacho. This river eventually flows west to the [[Pacific Ocean]]. The next system empties into the Gulf of Mexico and consists of the [[Pantepec River|Pantepec]], [[Cazones River|Cazones]], [[Necaxa River|Necaxa]], Laxaxalpan, San Pedro/Zun, Zempoala, Apulco, Cedro Viejo, Salteros, Martínez de la Torre and other rivers on the east side of the state. This system has two major dams called the Necaxa and Mazatepec. The third is based on the large number of small lakes fresh water springs as well as some volcanically heated springs. The best known of these include Chignahuapan, Agua Azúl, Amalucan, Cisnaqullas, Garcicrespo, Almoloya  and Rancho Colorado. Lakes include Chapulco, San Bernadino, Lagunas Epatlán, Ayutla, Almoloyan, Alchichica, Pahuatlán, Las Minas, Aljojuca and Tecuitlapa.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

===Climate===
The state has a widely varied climate due to the range of altitudes. It has an average temperature of 16C but this varies greatly locally. There is a rainy season from May until October with an overall precipitation of 801&amp;nbsp;mm.  The state subdivides into eleven different climate zones, but five predominate. The central and south of the state has a temperate and semi moist climate, with an average temperature of 15C and {{convert|858|mm|2|abbr=on}} of rainfall. The southwest has a warm to hot climate and semi moist with {{convert|830|mm|2|abbr=on}} of precipitation and 22C average temperature. The north is also dominated by warm and hot climates 22C average temperature but with an average rainfall of {{convert|2250|mm|2|abbr=on}}. The southeast is semi dry with warm and temperate temperatures with average temperature of 22C and precipitation of {{convert|550|mm|2|abbr=on}}. The last is the cold climates around the high volcano peaks.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

===Ecosystems===
[[File:Barranca Zacatlán CRC.jpg|thumb|Ravines at Zacatlán]]
The state has three main ecosystems, forests in temperate and cold areas, tropical rainforest and arid and semi-arid zones.  Colder forests can be found in the Huasteca Plateau, Chiconguiaco, Lagos de Volcanos de Anáhuac, Sierras Orientales and Sierras Centrales de Oaxaca.  These forests mostly consist of pines, [[holm oak]], [[oyamel]] fir and other conifers ([[Abies religiosa]],  [[Pinus pseudostrobus]], [[Pinus attenuata]], [[Pinus ayacahuite]], [[Pinus leiophylla]], [[Pinus patula]], [[Pinus teocote]], [[Quercus|Quercus spp]], [[Quercus rugosa]], [[Alder|Alnus spp]], [[Arbutus|Arbutus spp]], [[Cupressus|Cupressus spp]] and [[Juniperus|Juniperus spp.]]). Much of these areas have been extensively logged and some areas are used to farm trees. These trees are used for wood, paper and other wood-derived products. Due to human activity over 107,000 hectares are considered to be severely damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

Tropical forests are divided into moist, semi-moist and dry forests. These can be found in the Huasteca Plateau, Chiconguiaco, Lagos y Volcánes de Anahuac, Sur de Puebla, Cordillera Costera del Sur, Sierras y Valles Guerrerenses, Sierras Orientales, Sierras Centrales de Oaxaca and Mixteca Alta. The most common species include [[Ceiba parviflora]], [[Bursera simaruba]], [[Cedrela odorata]], [[Swietenia macrophylla]], [[Spondias mombin]], [[Brosimum alicastrum]], [[Coccoloba barbadens]], [[Pithecellobium arboreum]], [[Lysiloma divaricate]], [[Phoeba tampicensis]], [[Bursera simaruba]], [[Acacia coulteri]] and [[Ficus|Ficus spp.]] These forests are also exploited for wood and other products, including traditional handcrafts. Low growing plants are used to feed livestock. Little is known about the ecosystems of these forests, but it is known that these areas are important to the regulation of water in area rivers. Human activity has severely damaged over 32,000 hectares.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

The arid and semi arid area can be found in the Lagos y Volcanes de Anáhuac, Sur de Puebla, Cordillera Costera del Sur, Sierras y Valles Guerrerenses, Sierras Orientales and Sierras Centrales de Oaxaca. Types of vegetation often found includes mesquite, huizachal and agave, with species such as Agave spp, Yuca spp, Opuntia spp, Aristida spp and Stipa spp. There is no forestry here but a number of plants are used for fibers, waxes, resins, handcrafts, medicine and a number are edible to both humans and livestock. Many of these arid areas subdivide into microclimates depending on minor variations in temperature and precipitation. Some areas, especially dry grasslands, have suffered overgrazing and soil erosion.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

Temperate and cold area forests cover just under 22% of the surface of the state with various species of pine accounting for more than 80% of the trees.  These are mostly found in the higher elevations of the mountains where the average temperature is around 15C and at heights of between 2,500 and 2,750masl. Above 3,000masl [[Pinus hartwegil]] is dominant. Pine species which are the most economically valuable and include [[Pinus montezumae]],  [[pinus psedudostrobus]], [[pinus ayacahuite]], [[pinus geggil]], [[pinus hartwegil]], [[pinus lawsoni]], [[pinus leiophylla]], [[pinus michoacana]], [[pinus ocarpa]], [[pinus patul]] and, [[pinus teocote]]. The second most common kind of forest is dominated by oyamel fir, often intermingling with pines and oaks. These forests are found at altitudes of between 2,500 and 3,600masl and with an average temperature of between 7 and 15C and annual precipitation of {{convert|1000|mm|2|abbr=on}}. Forests with trees such as Juniperus spp., [[Pseudotsuga|Pseudotsuga spp.]], [[Pseudotsuga menziesii]], and [[Cupressus lindleyii]] can also be found.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

Tropical forests are divided by altitude. Upper forests are characterized by dense vegetation in fairly humid climates. The tree canopy reaches an average height of 15 meters. Not all species are evergreen, with a number losing leaves during the dry season. During the same season, a number of species also flower. For this reason, these forests never completely lose their color. Common species include [[Cedrela|Cedrela sp.]], [[Brosimun alicastrum]], [[Heliocarpus|Heliocarpus spp.]], [[Calophyllum brasiliense]], [[Zuelania Guidonia]] and [[Ficus|Ficus spp.]] Most forests of this type are located near the borders with Veracruz and Hidalgo. Tropical forests at lower altitudes are found in areas with median temperatures of over 20C, and annual rainfall of between 800 and {{convert|1200|mm|2|abbr=on}}. These areas often have a dry season of seven or eight months, and many of these forests will lose most or all of their leaves during this time. Common species include [[Bursera simaruba]], [[Lysiloma divaricata]], [[Phoebe tampicensis]], [[Acacia coulteri]], [[Beaucamea inemis]], [[Lysiloma acapulcensis]] and [[Zuelania guidonia]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;

In the south, near Puebla’s borders with Oaxaca and Guerrero are dry mountainous areas, some of which are completely devoid of vegetation, similar to African deserts. Other are populated only the by occasional cactus, with those belonging to the [[Fouquieria columnaris]] family standing out on the landscape. Where there are arroyos, the vegetation changes drastically to include a wide variety of plants packed along a narrow strip. Other areas in this part of the state are semi-arid, home to a variety of plant and bird species.&lt;ref name=&quot;mexdesdesierto&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.mexicodesconocido.com.mx/desierto-bosque-y-selva-puebla.html |title= Desierto, bosque y selva (Puebla)  |publisher=Mexico Desconocido magazine |location=Mexico City |language=Spanish |trans_title=Desert, forest and rainforest (Puebla) |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Natural attractions===
[[File:Orizaba&amp;SierraNegra.jpg|thumb|Pico de Orizaba and the Sierra Negra]]
Natural attractions in the state include the Bosque Mesófilos de la Sierra Madre Oriental in the north of the state, [[Valle de las Piedras Encimadas]], [[Izta-Popo Zoquiapan National Park]], [[La Malinche National Park]],  and the [[Pico de Orizaba National Park]].&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones5253&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, pp. 52–53&lt;/ref&gt; The best known wilderness area is the Izta-Popo National park, which the state shares with neighboring [[State of Mexico]]. It is located only 55&amp;nbsp;km west of the state capital and the two often snow covered volcanoes are easily visible from this area, and important to the state culturally. The park is an area protected by the federal government because of its biological diversity and considered to be the “lungs” of the area due to its forests. Access to the park, especially to the volcanoes themselves is more restricted than in the past due to past ecological damage.  Even further restrictions are put into place when the Popocatepetl volcano is active. However, the park has numerous hiking and horse paths in the forests that cover the lower elevations. On the slopes, there are many small caves, which in pre-Hispanic times were often used for ceremonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones56&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;

The Sierra Madre Oriental, locally called the Sierra Norte, is a series of rugged mountains covered in abundant vegetation, which has had an isolating effect on the people here over the centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones59&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;  The Valle de Piedras Encimadas (Valley of the Stacked Stones) is located near the town of [[Zacatlán (municipality)|Zacatlán]]. It is really a series of small valleys covering 400 hectares filled with conifer forest. The attraction here are the stone formations which resemble stones stacked one over the other which take on numerous forms. Some have been said to resemble objects such as dogs, elephants, human heads and monsters. Most of the area is only accessible by foot or horseback.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones66&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;

In the center of the state, just before the land rises to the north to form the Sierra Norte, there is an area filled with lakes, both with water and dry. The dry lakebeds contain water only during the rainy season, which runs from summer through fall. The two largest are Salado and Totocingo Lakes. The first is seven km long and two km wide and the second is larger.  The largest “wet” lakes are Laguna Preciosa, Laguna Quechulac, Laguna de Atexcac and Laguna de Aijojuca.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones8182&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, pp. 81–82&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Cantona10.jpg|thumb|Cantona archeological site]]
The territory of the state was one of the first in modern Mexico to be inhabited by humans.  Most of the earliest settlements have been found in the valley of Tehuacán, with the oldest near the Agujereado Mountain, which dates back to 10,000 BCE. At this site the oldest sample of corn ever found in the world has been found, which dates back to 1500 BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones32&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; Along with Agujereado Mountain, there are more than 450 prehistoric sites in the Tehuacan Valley alone. Stone tools date to between 6500 and 4900 BCE, and evidence of agriculture to 3500 and 2000 BCE in areas such as [[Aljojuca (municipality)|Aljojuca]], [[Totimiuacan]], [[Cholula, Puebla|Cholula]] and [[Izúcar de Matamoros|Izucar]]. By 900 BCE, there is ample evidence of the cultivation of corn, beans, squash, [[chili pepper]]s and cotton. The rise of city states was established by 700 BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.e-local.gob.mx/work/templates/enciclo/puebla/regi.htm |title= Historia |year=2009 |work= Enciclopedia de los Municipios de México Estado de Puebla |publisher= Instituto Nacional para el Federalismo y el Desarrollo Municipal |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=History |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Pipe with Bluebird.jpg|thumb|left|Mixtec-Puebla Style Pipe with Bluebird, A.D. 1100-1400]]
By the [[Mesoamerica]]n period, the area was inhabited by a number of ethnicities. The regions of [[Acatlán de Osorio, Puebla|Acatlán]] and part of [[Chiautla (municipality)|Chiautla]] were dominated by the [[Mixtec]]s. [[Tepexi de Rodríguez (municipality)|Tepexi]] was dominated by the Popolocas. The central part of the state was dominated by the [[Olmec-Xicalancas]] and [[Nahuas]], with strong cultural links to the [[Toltec]]-based culture at Cholula. The north was populated by the [[Totonac]]as, the [[Mazateco]]s and the [[Otomi peoples|Otomi]], whose cultural center was in [[El Tajín]]. In the 14th century, [[Nonoalca]] ruler Xelhua, came to dominate almost all of the territory of Puebla. In the 15th century, [[Aztec Empire|Aztec domination]] took over the same area and more. Initially, the center and south areas were under the control of [[Tenochtitlan]] with [[Texcoco (altepetl)|Texcoco]] dominant in the north. Aztec domination continued until the Spanish Conquest.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

[[Hernán Cortés]] entered the area which is now Puebla state in 1519, along with his indigenous allies from Veracruz, on his way to [[Tlaxcala (Nahua state)|Tlaxcala]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=154:sucesos-historicos-de-puebla&amp;catid=32:sucesos-historicos&amp;Itemid=56   |title= Sucesos históricos  de Puebla |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Historic events of Puebla |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Spanish takeover of the Puebla area was relatively easy. Many of the peoples here were under Aztec domination and saw the foreigners as a way to escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones32&quot;/&gt; One notable exception was the city of Cholula. While negotiating with the city’s leaders, Cortés was told of a plot to attack him and his men. Cortés ordered his army to commit the [[Spanish_conquest_of_the_Aztec_Empire#Massacre_of_Cholula|Massacre of Cholula]] on 12 October 1519. This act terrified those who opposed the Spanish and they submitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;/&gt; In 1520, after his initial defeat in Tenochtitlan ([[La Noche Triste]]) Hernán Cortés founded a Spanish settlement at [[Tepeaca (municipality)|Tepeaca]], and took areas such as [[Huaquechula]] and [[Itzocan]]. Many natives leaders then provided men and supplies for the conquest of Tenochtitlan in 1521, and later to go with [[Pedro de Alvarado]] to [[Guatemala]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones32&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt; Local indigenous governments survived in the very early colonial period, subject to the Spanish. These included Tuchpa, Tzicoac, Metztitlán, Tlapacoyan, Atotonilco, Tlatlaquitepec, Huaxtepec, Tepeaca, Tlacozautitlán, Quiauhteopan, Yoaltepec, Teotitlán del Camino, Cuautochco and Coixtlahuacan.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Cholula Massacre (1519).jpg|thumb|right|Cholula Massacre]]
The origins of the modern state lie in the founding of the city of Puebla in the Cuetlaxcoapan Valley in 1531 by [[Toribio de Benaventa]] and [[Juan de Salmerón]].&lt;ref name=&quot;angelopolis&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=4&amp;Itemid=7 |title= Angelópolis  |author= Luz Cortés Padilla  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 21, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Angelopolis |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city was laid out by Hernando de Elgueta, marking out residential areas, commercial areas etc. The city received its royal seal in 1532 but flooding forced the settlement to move across the San Francisco River and start over that same year. The city’s (and now state’s) seal was granted in 1538.&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;/&gt; The city of Puebla was created to secure the route between Mexico City and the port of Veracruz, and was initially populated by soldiers and those who made a living by providing shelter and supplies to travelers between the two cities. However, it soon became the economic and cultural center of the valley areas between the [[Valley of Mexico]] and the [[Gulf of Mexico|Gulf Coast]], as it provided a starting point for Spanish settlement. The area’s economy expanded rapidly as many Europeans and indigenous decided to settle permanently, with the settlement of Puebla reaching city status in 1532 with the name of Ciudad de los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones33&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Exconvento franciscano (siglo XVI).jpg|150px|thumb|left|Former Franciscan monastery at Tecali de Herrera]]
The [[Franciscans]] were in charge of the evangelization process in the state, starting from 1524, when they founded the monastery of [[Huejotzingo (municipality)|Huejotzingo]]. Between 1540 and 1560, they founded others such as those in [[Tecamachalco (municipality)|Tecamachalco]], [[Quecholac (municipality)|Quecholac]], [[Tecali de Herrera (municipality)|Tecali]], [[Calpan (municipality)|Calpan]], [[Cuautinchán]], [[Zacatlán (municipality)|Zacatlán]], [[Cholula, Puebla|Cholula]], Huaquechula, Tepeaca, [[Tehuacán]], [[Xalpa]] and [[Coatepec (municipality)|Coatepec]]. The [[Augustinians]] arrived next, constructing monasteries in [[Chiautla (municipality)|Chiautla]], [[Chietla (municipality)|Chietla]], [[Huatlatlauca (municipality)|Huatlatlauca]], [[Tlapa]], [[Xicotepec (municipality)|Xicotepec]] and [[Papaloticpac]]. The last of the evangelists were the Dominicans, who built monasteries at [[Izúcar de Matamoros]], [[Tepapayeca]], [[Huehuatlán]] and [[Tepexi de Rodríguez (municipality)|Tepexi]]. The bishopric was established in 1526. Initially, the seat was in the [[Yucatán]], but it was eventually moved to [[Tlaxcala]], then to Pueba by 1550. Eventually, its extension included the current states of Tlaxcala and Puebla during much of the colonial period.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

In 1783, the royal government in Spain divided New Spain into “intendencias” or provinces, one of which was centered on the city of Puebla.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt; The first governor of Puebla was Manuel de Flon, Count of La Cadena.&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;/&gt;  Initially, this intendencia included Tlaxcala, but it was separated out in 1793. Other parts were eventually separated out into other provinces/states such as Mexico, Guerrero and Veracruz.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt; 

During the [[Mexican War of Independence]], the city of Puebla remained loyal to the [[viceroy]] in Mexico City, sending troops to defend it at the [[Battle of Monte de las Cruces]] against [[Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla]]. Ecclesiatical authorities in the Cathedral excommunicated insurgent priests and battles took place in Izúcar and Chiautla.  Most of the south of the state, especially Izucar and the Sierra Mixteca were firmly in insurgent hands. Control then bypassed the capital and reached the more northern settlements of Tehuacan and [[Atlixco (municipality)|Atlixco]].&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones34&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; After Independence, the first governor of the state was Carlos García Arriaga in 1821. The first state congress was seated in 1824, with the first state constitution adopted the same year. The new state was divided initially into 21 parts. The Spanish were expelled from the state in 1827. In 1849, the state was reorganized into eight departments and 162 municipalities and again in 1895 with 21 districts and 180 municipalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

During the rest of the 19th century, the state developed economically through industry. The first mechanized textile mill was established in 1831, soon followed by 17 others in the city of Puebla. Progress was interrupted by [[Antonio López de Santa Anna|Santa Anna’s]] siege of the city in 1845 and two years later when the Americans under [[Winfield Scott|General Winfield Scott]] took the city on their way to Mexico City. The Americans left three years later at the end of the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;
[[File:BattleofPuebla2.jpg|thumb|150px|Mexican cavalry charge at the Battle of Puebla]]
Much of the rest of the century was occupied with civil strife such as the insurrection of Francisco Ortega against the federal government, the [[Reform War]] and the [[French Intervention in Mexico|French Intervention]]. The last provoked the [[Battle of Puebla]] on 5 May 1862, when 6,000 French troops attacked the forts named Loreto and Guadalupe outside of the city of Puebla, but they were repelled by forces under [[Ignacio Zaragoza]]. Zaragoza died some months after this battle, and he would be later honored by having his name added to that of the city. However, less than a year later, the city would be taken and shortly after, [[Emperor Maximilian I of Mexico]] would be installed. However, his rule would be brief and the French, along with their conservative Mexican allies, expelled from the state in 1867.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;/&gt;

From this time to the Mexican Revolution, a number of important infrastructure projects were undertaken. One was the Puebla-Veracruz rail line in 1873 and the Escuela Normal para Profesores (Teachers’ College) in 1879. In 1907, a hydroelectric plant was built in Necaxa. However, the economic policies of this area caused widespread unrest, beginning with workers’ strikes. Directly against the regime of [[Porfirio Díaz]] was the Club Antireeleccionista (Anti-reelection Club) headed by [[Aquiles Serdán]] in 1909. In November 1910, after long government surveillance, troops attacked the Serdán house in Puebla killing Aquiles and his brother Máximo. For this reason, the state claims one of the first battles of the [[Mexican Revolution]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

In 1912, the [[Liberation Army of the South]] or Zapatistas took over a number of communities in the state. In 1914, they were challenged by forces loyal to [[Venustiano Carranza]], which occupied the capital briefly. However, the Zapatistas would hold power for the rest of the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt; Under the [[1917 Constitution of Mexico|1917 Constitution]], the state was reestablished with 222 municipalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;/&gt; One of the last skirmishes of the war occurred in [[Aljibes, Puebla]] in May 1920 when forces of [[Álvaro Obregón]] attacked those of Carranza as he was headed to Veracruz. Carranza was assassinated in [[Tlaxcalantongo]] in the Sierra Norte de Puebla  soon thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

The 1920s immediately after the war is marked by instability. The governorship changed hands frequently with resistance to whoever was in power from other parts of the state. Despite this, the [[Universidad Autónoma de Puebla|Universidad de Puebla]] was established by [[Maximino Ávila Camacho]] during this decade. True political stability would not come until the governorship of [[Gustavo Díaz Ordaz]] in 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

Since the Mexican Revolution, the city of Puebla and its suburbs are one of the most industrialized areas in Mexico, with the metropolitan area ranked fourth in size. Its position near both Mexico City and the Gulf coast continues to be an advantage. However, modern development of the city area has been restricted to outside the city center, in order to preserve its traditional look. This historic center was named a World Heritage Site in 1987, with the [[Biblioteca Palafoxiana]] named as part of the [[Memory of the World Programme]] in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones3536&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, pp. 35–36&lt;/ref&gt; Today, Puebla’s economic development is centered on its capital. This capital is part of the [[megalopolis]] centered on Mexico City.&lt;ref name=&quot;enchistoria&quot;/&gt;

In 1977, the center of the city of Puebla was named a “Zone of Historic Monuments.” The same area was later named a [[World Heritage Site]] in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;sucesos&quot;/&gt;

In 1998, the state was declared in a state of emergency due to 122 forest fires with affected 2,998 hectares of land over two weeks. Many of the fires were started by fires on agricultural lands and the extremely dry conditions made the fires out of control.&lt;ref name=&quot;emergencia&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Declaran en Puebla estado de emergencia  |author= Clara Ramirez  |newspaper=Reforma |location=Mexico City |date=March 3, 1998 |page=13 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Puebla declared a state of emergency}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1999 Tehuacán earthquake did major damage to much of state, especially many of its colonial era churches,&lt;ref name=&quot;prayer&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Mexicans See a Call to Prayer In Quake Damage to Churches |author=Julia Preston |newspaper=New York Times |location=New York |date=June 17, 1999 |page=A14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the colonial buildings of the historic center of the city of Puebla.  The state of Puebla was declared a disaster area.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= 6.7 Temblor in Mexico Kills 12  |author= Mary Beth Sheridan |url= http://articles.latimes.com/1999/jun/16/news/mn-46948  |newspaper=Reforma |location=Mexico City |date=June 16, 1999 |page=13 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Puebla declared a state of emergency}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the 2000s, Organizations such as Reporters Sans Frontieres (RSF) have accused state governmental officials of restricting and suppressing the press. Some of the threats against reporters have included false arrests and death threats.&lt;ref name=&quot;monitoring&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Mexican government urged to stop press freedom violations by local politicians |newspaper=BBC Monitoring Americas |location=London |date=July 15, 2007 |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
[[File:Nahuas en Zacatlán.jpg|thumb|Nahuas in Zacatlán]]
In 2005, the state had a population of 5,383,133 according to the [[INEGI]] census, ranking fifth in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;habitantes&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://cuentame.inegi.org.mx/monografias/informacion/pue/poblacion/default.aspx?tema=me&amp;e=21 |title= Numero de Habitantes |publisher= INEGI |language=Spanish |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;perfilsoc&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.e-local.gob.mx/work/templates/enciclo/puebla/regi.htm |title= Perfil Sociodemografico |year=2009 |work= Enciclopedia de los Municipios de México Estado de Puebla |publisher= Instituto Nacional para el Federalismo y el Desarrollo Municipal |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=Socio demographic profile |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 93% of the state’s population identifies as Roman Catholic with 4.4% identifying as Protestant or Evangelical.&lt;ref name=&quot;perfilsoc&quot;/&gt;

In 1921, Puebla had the second largest population, after [[Oaxaca]], of purely indigenous people according to the national census. Since then, the official census has eliminated categories for race, counting only those who speak an indigenous language. In 2000, an attempt was made to count indigenous ethnicities, regardless of language spoken. This count ranked Puebla as fifth with a total population of 957,650.&lt;ref name=&quot;indcensus&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.houstonculture.org/hispanic/census.html |title=Indigenous Identity in the Mexican Census |author= John P. Schmal  |publisher= The Hispanic Experience Houston Institute for Culture |location=Houston |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to the 2005 census, there were  548,723 people who spoke an indigenous language.&lt;ref name=&quot;perfilsoc&quot;/&gt; 

The state has five major indigenous ethnic groups: the [[Nahuas]], the [[Totonac]]s, the [[Mixtec]]s, the [[Popoloca]]s and the [[Otomi people|Otomi]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;perfilsoc&quot;/&gt; The state has two well-defined areas in which indigenous peoples still main many ancient traditions, rites and customs. These two regions are called the Sierra Norte in the north and the Sierra Negra in the south. In these areas, these traditions, and the agriculture they are dependent on, have survived because industrialization has not penetrated the rugged landscape.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones23&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

The Sierra Norte, especially the municipalities of [[Cuetzalan]], [[Pahuatlán (municipality)|Pahuatlán]], [[Huehuetlán el Grande (municipality)|Huehuetla el Grande]] and [[Teziutlán (municipality)|Teziutlán]], are dominated by the Nahuas, Totonacas and Otomi. There is also a small region locally called the Sierra Negra in which there are communities of Popolocas, Nahuas and [[Mazateco]]s, especially in the municipality of [[Eloxochitlán, Puebla|Eloxochitlán]], [[Tlacotepec de Benito Juárez (municipality)|Tlacotepec]] and part of the city of [[Tehuacán]].&lt;ref name=&quot;perfilsoc&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones23&quot;/&gt;

The Mixtec people who live in the south of Puebla are part of an ethnic group which are still the dominant indigenous group in an area that stretches over Puebla, Oaxaca and the mountains of [[Guerrero]]. They are the fourth largest indigenous group in Mexico. The Sierra Mixteca region in Puebla is part of the [[Mixteca Baja]] region, which crosses into parts of Oaxaca as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;uvmixteco&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.uv.mx/popularte/esp/scriptphp.php?sid=44 |title=Mixtecos |publisher=Universidad Veracruzana |location=Veracruz, |language=Spanish |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Mesoamerica]]n period, the Mixtecs of Puebla dominated further north than they do now and archeologists classify “Mixteca-Puebla” art as distinct from other Mixtec arts and crafts.&lt;ref name=&quot;mixtecaarte&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.historiadelarte.us/mexico/arte-de-la-mixteca-puebla.html |title= Arte de la Mixteca-Puebla |year= 2007–2010 |work= Historia del Arte |location=Veracruz |language=Spanish |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are an estimated 6,700 Mixtecs living in Puebla, however, many have emigrated out of traditional Mixtec areas into other parts of the state, Mexico City and even the United States to work.&lt;ref name=&quot;arqueomex&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.arqueomex.com/S2N3nDOSIER90.html |title= La cultura mixteca |year= 1993 |publisher= Arqueología Mexicana magazine/ Editorial Raíces S.A. de C.V.  |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gruposetnicos&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Aumenta migracion de grupos etnicos |author= Cecilia Gonzalez |newspaper=Reforma |location=Mexico City |date=February 7, 2001  |language=Spanish |trans_title=Migration of ethnic groups increases}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
===General economy===
[[File:Pueblaskyline.jpg|thumb|Puebla city and San Andres cholula skyline]]
The state is divided into seven socioeconomic regions for planning purposes: Region I-[[Huauchinango (municipality)|Huauchinango]], Region II – [[Teziutlán (municipality)|Teziutlán]], Region III [[Chalchicomula de Sesma (municipality)|Ciudad Serdán]], Region IV [[San Pedro Cholula (municipality)|San Pedro Cholula]], Region V – Puebla, Region VI [[Izúcar de Matamoros]] and Region VII [[Tehuacán]].(regionalacion) Region I is located in the north of the state and consists of 32 municipalities. Its climate is mostly warm and moist with significant rainfall in the summer. It also has a large number of small rivers. Region II is located in the north and northeast of the state with 31 municipalities. It transitions from the temperate climates of the Sierra Norte to the warmer zones that descend towards the Gulf of Mexico. This area also has a large number of rivers, fresh water springs, waterfalls and dams. Region III is located in the northeast of the state and consists of 24 municipalities. It has a variety of climates from cold to temperate depending on the altitude. Region IV is located in the center-west of the state and has 27 municipalities. Much of this area has a cold climate due to altitude. It contains the highest areas of the Atoyac River basin, which is important to both Puebla and the State of Mexico. Region V is located in the center of the state and consists of eight municipalities. This climate here is mostly temperate, semi-moist to semi-dry. Most of the rivers here empty into the Atoyac and contains the Manuel Avila Camacho Dam with {{convert|405000000|m3|2|abbr=on}} of capacity. This water is mostly used for irrigation. Region VI is in the southwest with 45 municipalities. Temperature varies with attitude and rainfall varies as well. Much of the water here is provided by the Atoyac. Region VII is located in the southeast with 50 municipalities. Climates range from the cold in the Sierra de Zongolica to the hot in the Valley of Tehuacan. The area is formed by the convergence of the Sierra del Tentzo, Sierra Mixteca and Sierra Negra.&lt;ref name=&quot;regionalizacion&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.e-local.gob.mx/work/templates/enciclo/puebla/regi.htm |title= Regionalización |year=2009 |work= Enciclopedia de los Municipios de México Estado de Puebla |publisher= Instituto Nacional para el Federalismo y el Desarrollo Municipal |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=Regions |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The state was a diverse economic base supporting industries such as textiles, tourism, agribusiness, storage, medical services, furniture making and logistics services in clusters.(promotedor) In 2010, [[Standard &amp; Poor's]] reconfirmed the state’s ‘mxA+’ rating with a stable outlook due to the state’s finances.  The state’s economy grew at a rate of 4.5% from 2003 to 2007, above the national average of 3.9%. Since then, economic growth has slowed but less than in other parts of Mexico. Its [[gross domestic product]] accounts for 3.4% of the country’s total. It is one of Mexico’s most industrialized states.&lt;ref name=&quot;standardpoors&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www2.standardandpoors.com/portal/site/sp/es/la/page.article/2,1,7,0,1204856865349.html |title= Standard &amp; Poor's revisa perspectiva del estado de Puebla a positiva de estable y confirma calificación de 'mxA+' |publisher= Standard and Poors |language=Spanish |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

However, almost all of the state’s development has been centered on the capital city and the surrounding areas. This has caused a wide economic gap between rich and poor and between the city areas and the rural areas, with much of the state lacking investment by the government (infrastructure) or by private interests.&lt;ref name=&quot;polarizacion&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Teme IP de Puebla crisis y polarizacion |author= Francisco Rivas|newspaper=El Norte |location=Monterrey, Mexico |date=March 1, 2006  |language=Spanish |trans_title=IP fears crisis and polarization in Puebla}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Puebla, un estado prometedor |author= Daniela Clavijo López |newspaper=El Economista |location=Mexico City |date=November 3, 2005  |language=Spanish |trans_title=Puebla, a promising state}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This has led the [[United Nations]] to rank the state as the seventh most underdeveloped in the country, despite the industry in the Puebla city area in 2006–2007, with areas lacking basic services such as health, water and education along with high unemployment.&lt;ref name=&quot;standardpoors&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;septimo&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Puebla, séptimo estado subdesarrollado: ONU |author= Jorge Machuca |url= http://impreso.milenio.com/node/7087503 |newspaper=Milenio |location=Mexico |date=November 16, 2008 |accessdate=October 10, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Puebla, seventh most underdeveloped state according to the UN}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The state is even ranked lower for these than [[Lebanon]], [[Cuba]] and [[Bosnia]]. The UN blames poor government policies and corruption for much of the state’s poverty.&lt;ref name=&quot;septimo&quot;/&gt;

According to several [[NGO]]’s, such as the Consejo Nacional de Evaluación de la Política de Desarrollo Social (Coneval), and Marcos Gutiérrez Barrón, professor of economics at the  [[Universidad Popular Autónoma del Estado de Puebla]],&lt;ref name=&quot;UPAEP&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.upaep.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=18&amp;Itemid=130|title= Historia de la UPAEP  |publisher= Universidad Popular Autónoma del Estado de Puebla |language=Spanish |location=Puebla |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Puebla has the third highest level of poverty in the country. This ranking takes into account factors such as income per capita, housing, educational opportunities, food supply and family cohesion. As much as two-thirds of the state’s population or about 3.5 million live under the poverty line. The state’s Secretaria de Desarrollo Social (Secretariat of Social Development) increased its budget in 2008 to 757 million pesos. Ten of the state’s municipalities are ranked among the poorest in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;tercer&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Puebla se ubica en el tercer lugar de pobreza del país |url= http://www.elfinanciero.com.mx/ElFinanciero/Portal/cfpages/contentmgr.cfm?docId=255618&amp;docTipo=1&amp;orderby=docid&amp;sortby=ASC |newspaper=El Financiero |location=Mexico |date=April 10, 2010 |accessdate=October 10, 2010 |language=Spanish}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Puebla is a state where migrant workers both head to and leave from.&lt;ref name=&quot;gruposetnicos&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;septimo&quot;/&gt; Most incoming workers are indigenous from the states of Oaxaca and Guerrero, according to a study done by the [[National Indigenous Institute]] and the United Nations.  Most of these emigrants are Mixtecs from the south of the state, which head to areas such as Mexico City and the north of the country either seasonally or permanently.&lt;ref name=&quot;gruposetnicos&quot;/&gt;  Many also head to the United States to work illegally. The migration situation has caused the population to drop in a number of areas in the state. The UN states that the main reason for emigration is the lack of local economic development especially in rural and indigenous areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;septimo&quot;/&gt;

===Agriculture and forestry===
[[File:Puebla farmers.jpg|thumb|Farmers in a field in Puebla]]
Thirty seven percent of the population is employed in agriculture, livestock and fishing. Agricultural units cover 2,233,897 hectares in rural areas of the state. Just over fifty percent is dedicated to the growing of crops, 46.5% to pasture, 2.6% is forest and .8% is wild vegetation.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.e-local.gob.mx/work/templates/enciclo/puebla/regi.htm |title= Actividad Economica |year=2009 |work= Enciclopedia de los Municipios de México Estado de Puebla |publisher= Instituto Nacional para el Federalismo y el Desarrollo Municipal |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=Economic activity profile |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Agriculture is the most important economic activity of the rural areas, but it is mostly limited to the rainy season from June to October, as there are few facilities for irrigation. This limits the sector’s growth potential significantly.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;agronegocios&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Opinion – Agronegocios. Limitada, la inversion en Puebla; [Source: El Economista]|author= Eligio Esquivez Gonzalez |newspaper=Noticias Financieras |location=Miami |date=May 12, 2006 |page=1 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Opinion- Agribusiness. Investment in Puebla limited}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to lack of investment only 11% of the state’s arable land is irrigated. Seventy two percent of farmland is privately own with the rest belonging to [[ejido]]s or other types of communal ownership. The municipalities with the most cultivated land are [[Chignahuapan (municipality)|Chignahuapan]], [[Chalchicomula de Sesma (municipality)|Chalchicomula de Sesma]], [[Tlachichuca (municipality)|Tlachichuca]] and [[Zacapoaxtla (municipality)|Zacapoaxtla]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt;

The most important activities include production of domestic fowl (eggs and meat), which accounts for 37%, cattle (dairy and meat) at 12%, grains (90% corn) and pork at 10% each, vegetables ([[tomatillo]]s, onions, carrots, tomatoes, and squash) at 8% and fruit (oranges, limes, [[cactus pear]], apples, [[avocado]]s and peaches at 4%.&lt;ref name=&quot;agronegocios&quot;/&gt; Other important crops include beans, animal feed, [[alfalfa]] and [[sugar cane]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt;  Most crops are grown in the municipalities of [[Hueytamalco (municipality)|Hueytamalco]], [[Francisco Z. Mena (municipality)|Francisco Z. Mena]], [[Venustiano Carranza (municipality)|Venustiano Carranza]], [[Xicotepec (municipality)|Xicotepec]] and [[Jalpan (municipality)|Jalpan]]. Most crops, especially corn, are grown on relatively small farms, communal fields and family plots, but perennial crops such as rubber trees, coffee and citrus from are mostly grown on large plantations.&lt;ref name=&quot;mediofisico&quot;/&gt; The most important livestock in the state are cattle, pigs and domestic fowl. Cattle are prevalent in the municipalities of Francisco Z. Mena, Venustiano Carranza, Jalpan, Hueytamalco and [[Chiautla (municipality)|Chiautla de Tapia]]. Pigs are mostly found in Tehuacán, [[Ajalpan (municipality)|Ajalpan]], [[Tepanco de López (municipality)|Tepanco de López]], [[Tecamachalco (municipality)|Tecamachalco]] and [[Yehualtepec (municipality)|Yehualtepec]].   The entire state ranks first in the production of domestic fowl with most being produced in the municipalities of Ajalpan, Tehuacán, Tecamachalco, Tepanco de López and [[Tochtepec (municipality)|Tochtepec]]. Other livestock raised include goats, sheep and horses.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt;

Other production of primary materials includes forest products and fish. Over 93% of the tree species exploited in the state are conifers mostly cut for wood production. In 2007, the annual production of wood products had risen to 244,803 cubic meters. Most forestry occurs in the municipalities of Chignahuapan, [[Tetela de Ocampo]], [[Vicente Guerrero Municipality|Vicente Guerrero]], Zacatlán and Huauchinango. Fish are both caught wild and farmed and mostly concentrate on species such as [[carp]], [[trout]] and [[mojarra]]. Most are harvested in the state’s dams and lakes, which cover a surface area of 6,500 hectares.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt;

===Industry and mining===
The state has been an important industrial center since colonial times, mostly known for the production of textiles and pottery, both of which continue to be made.&lt;ref name=&quot;angelopolis&quot;/&gt; Today, industries of various types, along with mining and construction employ about twenty five percent of the state’s population.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt; More than 150,000 small and medium sized factories operate in the state, providing 60% of the state’s GDP.&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;/&gt; Most industry in the state in concentrated in and around the capital. The most important industries are in metals, chemicals, electronic items and textiles.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt; Textiles produced in the state mostly involve thread, machinery, knitted items and woven fabrics.&lt;ref name=&quot;textilesgob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=144&amp;Itemid=191  |author= Eduardo Carrera |title= Sector Textil |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=May 25, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Textile Sector |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the first and one of the biggest textile factory in Mexico and in [[Latinamerica]], The &quot;[[La Constancia Mexicana]] Factory&quot;, was build in capital of Puebla. Two important employers are Hylsa and the Volkswagen plant, both in the Puebla area.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt;

Two important industries are automotive and agribusiness. The automotive sector is important for the state as a leading manufacturer of both automobiles and automobile parts. Some of the businesses located in the state include Denso México, Arvin Meritor de México, Mabe, Leoni, Hyundai-Kia Motors, Coramex Company and Forteq.&lt;ref name=&quot;automotriz&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=143&amp;Itemid=190  |author= Eduardo Carrera |title= Sector Automotriz |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=May 25, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Automobile Sector |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Industry related to agriculture consists of  both producing products needed by farmers and processing agricultural produce. Some of these companies include Nestle de México, Pasan, [[Chocolatera Moctezuma]], [[Sabormex]], [[Big Cola]], [[Bomba Energy]], [[Ochoa Comercial]], [[Grupo Pepsico]], [[Compañía Topo Chico]], [[Red Bull]], [[Grupo Bimbo]], [[Unifoods]], [[Novamex]], [[Coca Cola|The Coca Cola Company]], [[Supermercados Gigante]], [[Soriana]], [[La Costeña (food company)|La Costeña]] and [[Jugos del Valle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;agroindustrial&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=145&amp;Itemid=192|author= Eduardo Carrera |title= Sector Agroindustrial |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=May 25, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Agro-industrial  Sector |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are nine state and four federal programs targeting small and medium-sized producers, which provide training, consulting, trademarks and other services. Some programs target specific industries such as software. One focus of the state is to promote technology based industries which produced high-value products. There are eleven industrial parks and other special industry zones for this purpose. Another area identified for improvement is higher education, to produce graduates to work in these kinds of industries.&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;/&gt; Commercial events include the Exintex International Exhibition, which is held in the state each year and attracts textile manufacturers from states such as [[Morelos]], [[Tlaxcala]], [[Tamaulipas]], [[Guanajuato]], [[Querétaro]] and [[Aguascalientes]] as well as the cities of [[Guadalajara, Mexico|Guadalajara]] and Mexico City.&lt;ref name=&quot;textilesgob&quot;/&gt; 

Mining produces [[calcite]], [[marble]], [[calcium oxide]], [[onyx]], and [[lime (material)|lime]]. The most important mining processing concerns are [[Calera Santa Ma. S.A]], [[Marmiparquet S.A]], [[Química Sumex S.A de C.V]] and [[Yacimientos de Travertino S.A.]], and the sector employs about 270,000 workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt;

===Handcrafts===
[[File:FacadeUriartePuebla.JPG|thumb|Uriarte Talavery pottery workshop in Puebla, Mexico]]
[[Talavera (pottery)|Talavera pottery]] is the state’s best known craft. This pottery is a type of [[maiolica]], which was introduced into Spain by the [[Arab]]s, and into Mexico by the Spanish. Talavera is considered to be the finest of Mexico’s pottery traditions, which is still made with the same techniques as in the colonial period.&lt;ref name=&quot;artesaniasgob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=35&amp;Itemid=59  |title= Artesanias  |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Handcrafts |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Talavera pottery began in the city of Puebla when the Spaniards brought over from Europe the techniques of making maiolica pottery, itself brought from China via the Arabs. The techniques and designs were based on the pottery made in [[Talavera la Real|Talavera, Spain]]. The high-quality clay and the formation of [[guild]]s to ensure quality soon made pottery made in Puebla a near-luxury item. The craft waned after [[Mexican War of Independence|Independence]], but made a comeback in the latter 20th. Today certified Talavera pottery in only made in a handful of workshops in the capital and other nearby communities. To be certified as genuine the same methods and used in the 16th century must be applied. True Talavera pottery is expensive and considered to be collectors’ items.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones44&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; 

Other types of pottery in the state exist. One is the black clay figures made in [[Acatlán de Osorio, Puebla|Acatlán de Osorio]]. Most of these figures are animals and are almost always painted with white designs. Black clay is also used to make cups, plates and other utilitarian items in other communities. Another important clay craft are the [[Tree of Life (craft)|Trees of Life]], mostly made in the community of [[Izúcar de Matamoros]] and Acatlán de Osorio. Traditionally, these are sculptures depicting [[Adam]] and [[Eve]] in the [[Garden of Eden]], but the craft has evolved to include other themes as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones45&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt;

The making of textiles and embroidery dates back to pre-Hispanic times. Traditional clothing such as [[rebozo]]s, [[sarape]]s, shirts and pants are still made in various parts of the state and reflect the different indigenous communities which are found here. [[Hueyapan (municipality)|Hueyapan]] is one of the better known artisanal textile producers, with clothing items and others richly and colorfully embroidered. Both the thread used to weave the cloth and embroider it are [[dyeing|dyed]] with [[natural dye]]s such as those obtained from the [[cochineal]] insect. Another area known for its textiles is [[Zacapoaxtla (municipality)|Zacapoaxtla]] in the north of the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones46&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;

The town of [[Amozoc (municipality)|Amozoc]] is known for its silverwork. This tradition began when a number of metalworkers of various types settled here after the [[Spanish conquest of the Aztec Empire|Conquest]] in the 16th century. These smiths made a variety of objects from the everyday such as knives, swords, stirrups and more, eventually branching into finer metals such as silver and gold, mother-of-pearl, ivory and more. However, it is silver smithing which has best survived to the present day.&lt;ref name=&quot;artesaniasgob&quot;/&gt;

There are two widely practice paper crafts in Puebla. The making of bark paper or [[amatl|amate]] was known in pre-Hispanic times when such was reserved for special ceremonies and the recording of important information. It had an almost magical quality to it and was used for spells, clothing of idols and other ceremonial purposes. Today, the paper is still made as an art form and often painted with elaborate designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones48&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; In Puebla, the paper is still made by hand and often it is hand-painted with pre-Hispanic designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;artesaniasgob&quot;/&gt; One area noted for this craft is  [[San Salvador Huixcolotla (municipality)|San Salvador Huixcolotla]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones48&quot;/&gt; Another is [[Pahuatlán (municipality)|San Pablito Pahuatlán]] in the Sierra Norte.&lt;ref name=&quot;artesaniasgob&quot;/&gt; One notable amate paper artist is [[curandero]] Alfonso García Téllez, who narrates stories and ceremonies in his works.&lt;ref name=&quot;artesaniasgob&quot;/&gt; Another paper craft is [[papel picado]], or “chopped paper.” This craft began with the introduction of [[crepe paper]] from Asia. This paper is elaborately cut to form figures and scenes which are then hung for decorative purposes for holidays such as [[Day of the Dead]]. This most traditional of these are laborious cut by hand, but most are done today by machine. Those native to Puebla feature a large figure with a detailed background and are considered to be part of the state’s cultural heritage (Patrimonio Cultural del Estado de Puebla) .&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones48&quot;/&gt; 

A relatively recent craft is the making of blown glass Christmas ornaments in [[Chignahuapan (municipality)|Chignahuapan]]. This municipality has about 200 workshops which employ about 1,500 workers, which makes the spherical ornaments individually and many are shipped internationally to the United States and Latin America. This craft is still growing and represents one of the more stable small scale manufacturing endeavors in Puebla.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones47&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

For many rural communities, the making of handcrafted furniture, both fine and rustic, is an important economic activity. One such community is [[Chalchicomula de Sesma (municipality)|Ciudad Serdán]], which makes wooden utensils, decorative figures  and banister work in addition to furniture. It has a strong reputation along with Chignahuapan. Areas outside of Ciudad Serdán are known for specializing in reproductions of [[Louis XV style|Louis XV]] and [[Louis XVI style|Louis XVI]] furniture. The community of [[Trinidad Alonso Báez]] is known as the only place in Latin American where pianos are made purely by hand. They are also known for the repairing of musical instrument with many of the state’s antique church organs fixed by craftsmen from here.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones47&quot;/&gt; 

Onyx is a plentiful stone in the state and it is worked into figures and other items in various parts of the state. The most important deposit of the stone is in [[Tecali de Herrera (municipality)|Tecali]] and many workshops fill the streets of this town. Most of the pieces made are decorative in nature but small utilitarian items such as plates and ashtrays are also made.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones48&quot;/&gt; 

Amozoc has been known for silver smithing since colonial times, when European techniques were brought over by the Spanish. As back then, they still make items such as jewelry, silverware, and items for church rituals. These smiths’ work is considered to be quality, with the finest pieces encrusted with precious and semi-precious gems, gold, and ivory.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones4849&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, pp. 48–49&lt;/ref&gt;

The first glass workshop in [[New Spain]] was established in Puebla by Spaniard Rodrigo Espinoza in 1542. It remained the only one in Spain’s colonies for decades, exporting glass items to places such as [[Peru]] and [[Guatemala]]. In the 18th century, Pedro Antonio revitalized the craft with a new factory. This factory was the main producer until the establishment of the Compañia Empresarial para la Fabricacion del Vidrio Plano y Cristal in 1838. This company introduced French designs and techniques to Mexico. The next major glassmaker was Victor Martinez Filoteo, who established the Fabrica La Luz in 1935. This company is still the major producer of glass items in the state. Small workshops are prevalent in [[Huaquechula (municipality)|Huaquechula]], where they specialize items made with black and smoke-colored glass.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones49&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;

===Commerce and transportation===
Thirty five percent are employed in commerce, tourism and transportation.&lt;ref name=&quot;actecon&quot;/&gt; The state has 8,995&amp;nbsp;km of highways and 1,024&amp;nbsp;km of rail line, as well as twenty three major malls.&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;/&gt; Outlet Puebla was opened in 2001 on the highway between Mexico City and the city /of Puebla where it intersects with the Periferico Ecologico. It contains more than 80 outlet stores with major national and international brands such as [[Reebok]], [[Guess (clothing)|Guess]] and [[Pepe Jeans]], located on a site of over 30,000m2. The enterprise is run by Asesores en Exposiciones y Calpro, S. A. de C. V. The mall target traveling customers from the states of Puebla, Veracruz, Oaxaca and Tlaxcala as well as Mexico City.&lt;ref name=&quot;apertura&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Anuncian apertura de Outlet Puebla |newspaper=Reforma |location=Mexico City |date=April 1, 2001  |language=Spanish |trans_title=Announce opening of Outlet Puebla}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The international airport in [[Huejotzingo (municipality)|Huejotzingo]] is linked to the Mexico City airport by land transport.&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;/&gt; Efforts have been made to expand the airport in Huejotzingo to be an auxiliary to the overcrowded [[Mexico City International Airport|Mexico City airport]]. The airport has been chosen due to its relatively quiet airspace and proximity to the nation’s capital. As of 2010, the airport handles sixty operations per day, 40 of which are commercial flights serving 2.5 million passengers per year.&lt;ref name=&quot;pidemano&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Pide &quot;mano&quot; Puebla como aeropuerto alterno al DF  |author= Ignacio Álvarez Hernández  |url= http://www.unomasuno.com.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=5650:pide-mano-puebla-como-aeropuerto-alterno-al-df-&amp;catid=116:republica&amp;Itemid=515 |newspaper=Uno mas Uno |location=Mexico |date=September 8, 2010 |accessdate=October 10, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Pueblas asks for &quot;hand&quot; to become the alternative airport to Mexico City}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tourism===
[[File:Iglesia de Tonantzintla.jpg|left|thumb|200px|Church of San Francisco Acatepec]]
The state has 2,600 historic buildings, antiques, bars and pottery workshops.&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;paravisitar&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=3&amp;Itemid=6 |title= Rutas Turísticas |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=Tourist Routes |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The downtown of the capital is filled with churches, government buildings and large homes, built by indigenous hands for their Spanish overlords. This downtown was declared a [[World Heritage Site]] in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;angelopolis&quot;/&gt; 

The state promotes twelve tourist routes, seven in the city of Puebla and five in the rest of the state. The cover the most representative buildings of the history of the state up to modern attractions such as the [[Africam Safari]] zoo.&lt;ref name=&quot;paravisitar&quot;/&gt; The first tourist route in the city of Puebla passes by the Cathedral, the Palafoxiana Library, the Capilla del Rosario, Calle de Santa Clara, Palacio Municipal, Casa de los Muñecos and the Museo Amparo. The second route passes by the Casa del Alfeñique, the Mercado de Artesanias, the Barrio del Artista, the Teatro Principal and the San Francisco Church. The third route contains the Railroad Museum, the Museo y Pinacoteca Ex-Convento de Santa Monica, the Ex-Convento de Santa Rosa, the Museo de la No-Intervencion Fuerte de Guadalupe and the Mercado de Antiguedades. The forth route contains the San Francisco Acatepec Church, the Santa Maria Tonatzintla Church, the Capilla Real, the Cholula archeological site, the Los Remedios Church and Huejotzingo. The fifth route includes [[Cuauhtinchan]], [[Tecali de Herrera (municipality)|Tecali]] and the [[Africam Safari]] Zoo.&lt;ref name=&quot;angelopolis&quot;/&gt;

Outside of the Puebla metropolitan area, the state promotes natural attractions such as the cacti of [[Zapotitlán (municipality)|Zapotitlán]], the 100 million year old fossils of Cantera Tlayùa in [[Tepexi de Rodríguez (municipality)|Tepexi de Rodríguez]] and smaller ones such as waterfalls, churches, caverns, archeological zones, former monasteries, [[Traditional fixed markets in Mexico|traditional markets]], fresh  water springs, lakes and more.&lt;ref name=&quot;smixteca&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=53  |title= Ruta Turística – Sierra Mixteca  |author= Luz Cortés Padilla  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= April 27, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Tourist Route – Sierra Mixteca |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tourist routes outside of the Puebla metro area are divided into the Sierra Mixteca area in the south and the Sierra Norte in the north. The Sierra Mixteca area includes the Ruta de Aguacate (Avocado Route), the Ruta del Ónix (Onyx Route), the Ruta del Maiz (Corn Route) and the Ruta Paleontológica (Palentology Route). The Avocado Route includes the municipalities of [[Atlixco (municipality)|Atlixco]], [[Tianguismanalco (municipality)|Tianguismanalco]], [[Tochimilco (municipality)|Tochimilco]], [[Huaquechula (municipality)|Huaquechula]], [[Tlapanalá (municipality)|Tlapanalá]], [[Izúcar de Matamoros]], [[Epatlán (municipality)|San Juan Epatlán]], [[Chietla (municipality)|Chietla]], [[Chiautla (municipality)|Chiautla de Tapia]] and [[Acatlán de Osorio, Puebla|Acatlán de Osorio]].  The Onyx Route includes the Africam Safari Zoo, [[Cuauhtinchan]], [[San Salvador Huixcolotla (municipality)|San Salvador Huixcolotla]], [[Tecali de Herrera (municipality)|Tecali de Herrera]], [[Tecamachalco (municipality)|Tecamachalco]] and [[Tepeaca]].  The Corn Route includes [[Tehuacán]], [[Santa María del Monte]] and [[Zapotitlán Salinas]]. The Paleontology Route includes [[Atoyatempan (municipality)|Atoyatempan]], [[Huitziltepec (municipality)|Santa Clara Huitziltepec]], [[Molcaxac (municipality)|Molcaxac]], [[Huatlatlauca (municipality)|Huatlatlauca]], [[Chigmecatitlan (municipality)|Chigmecatitlán]], [[Tepexi de Rodríguez (municipality)|Tepexi de Rodríguez]] and [[Ixcaquixtla (municipality)|San Juan Ixcaquixtla]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;smixteca&quot;/&gt;

The Sierra Norte contains a number of pre-Hispanic archeological sites and colonial architecture. Crafts to be found here include wool clothing, [[amatl|amate paper]], clay figures, wood carvings, and embroidered blouses. This area of the state contains the Ruta de la Flor (Flower Route), Ruta Interserrana (Inter-Mountain Route), Ruta del Huipil y Café (Huipil and Coffee Route) and the Ruta Perla Norte (North Pearl Route). The Flower Route includes the municipalities of [[Chignahuapan (municipality)|Chignahuapan]], [[Zacatlán (municipality)|Zacatlán]], [[Huauchinango (municipality)|Huauchinango]], [[Juan Galindo (municipality)|Juan Galindo]], [[Pahuatlán (municipality)|Pahuatlán]], [[Tenango, Puebla|Tenango]], [[Tetela de Ocampo]] and [[Xicotepec (municipality)|Xicotepec]]. The Inter-Mountain Route includes [[Ahuacatlán, Puebla|Ahuacatlán]], [[Zapotitlán (municipality)|Zapotitlán]], [[Xochitlán de Vicente Suárez (municipality)|Xochitlán]], [[Tepango de Rodríguez (municipality)|Tepango]] and [[Nauzontla (municipality)|Nauzontla]]. The Huipil and Coffee Route include [[Tenextatiloyan]], [[Acajete, Puebla|Acajete]], [[Cuetzalan]], [[Jonotla (municipality)|Jonotla]], [[Libres (municipality)|Libres]], [[Nopalucan (municipality)|Nopalucan]], [[Oriental (municipality)|Oriental]], [[Oriental (municipality) (municipality)|San José Chiapa]], [[Tepeyahualco (municipality)|Tepeyahualco]] and [[Zacapoaxtla (municipality)|Zacapoaxtla]].  The North Pearl Route includes [[Atempan (municipality)|Atempa]], [[Chignautla (municipality)|Chignautla]], [[Hueyapan (municipality)|Hueyapan]], [[Xiutetelco (municipality)|San Juan Xiultetelco]], [[Teziutlán (municipality)|Teziutlán]], [[Tlatlauquitepec (municipality)|Tlatlauquitepec]] and [[Yaonáhuac (municipality)|Yaonahuac]].&lt;ref name=&quot;smagica&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=30&amp;Itemid=54  |title= Ruta Turística – Sierra Mágica  |author= Luz Cortés Padilla  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= April 27, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Tourist Route – Sierra Magica |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a number of former haciendas in the state, many of which have been converted into hotels, spas and other kinds of attractions. Some have also been used as movie and television sets for projects such as [[Alondra (telenovela)|Alondra]], [[Amor es Querer]], [[Man on Fire (2004 film)|Man on Fire]], [[Vantage Point (film)|Vantage Point]] and [[Frida]]. These include the [[Chautla Hacienda]] in San Salvador el Verde, Las Calandrias in Atlixco, Micuautla in Puebla, Netxalpa in Atlixco, San Pedro de Ovando in Acatzingo, Ozumba in San José Chiapa, Rancho Jesús in Cuautinchan, San Agustín in Atlixco, San Mateo in Amalucan, San Roque in Atlixco, Santiago Texmelucan in Tepeyahualco de Hidalgo and Oriental Tenextepec in Atlixco.&lt;ref name=&quot;filmhaciendas&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=68&amp;Itemid=92 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Filmaciones Haciendas |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=August 25, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Hacienda filmings |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;filmproyectos&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=66&amp;Itemid=90 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Proyectos Filmados en Puebla  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=September 15, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Films shot in Puebla |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Natural attractions in the state include Amacas in Cuetzalan, Bosque Chignahuapan Forest, the Quetzalapa Chignahuapan Waterfall, Zacatlán Waterfall, La Gloria Cuetzalán Waterfall, Las Brisas Cuetzalan Waterfall, Las Golondrinas Cuetzalan Waterfall, Nexcapa Hauachinango, Ocpaco Zacatlán Waterfall, the arid landscapes of Zapotitlan de Salinas, the Iztalcihual and Popocatepetl volcanos, the basalt columns of Huauchinango, the Valle de Piedras Encimadas in Zacatlán and the Nexcaxa Dam in Huauchinango.(scenarios)

Puebla is working with neighboring Veracruz to promote the area’s tourist attractions and develop them in an ecologically sustainable way. Both state governments are working with organizations of tour operators, hotels and restaurants to pool a fund for activities such as advertising campaigns, especially to Mexico City and the [[State of Mexico]], which account for 80% of all the state’s visitors. Another is the reimbursement of tolls for those who travel to certain attractions such as the Africam Safari park and two-for-one specials. Efforts have succeeded in raising hotel occupancy rates from 40% to 56% in a number of areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;reactivar&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Estados de Puebla y Veracruz inician campanas para reactivar turismo |author= Humberto Nino de Haro|newspaper=Noticias Financieras |location=Miami |date=June 8, 2009  |language=Spanish |trans_title=States of Puebla and Veracruz begin campaigns to reactivate tourism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archeological sites==
[[File:Cantona12.jpg|thumb|Cantona]]
[[Cantona (Mesoamerican site)|Cantona]] is a 12km2 archeological site, located in the north of the state between the municipalities of [[Tepehualco]] and [[Coyoaco]]. It is divided into three units, with work only done on the south unit, which is the best preserved. Here is found the “Acropolis,” an area with temples, palaces and other seats of authority. The site was occupied between the 7th and 11th centuries CE and reached its height at the time many other Classic era urban centers were falling. It is thought that this city interrupted the flow of goods from the coast of Veracruz to [[Teotihuacan]], one of the many causes of that city’s downfall. The site is filled with a large number of patios which measure 50 x 40 meters or larger. Total number of patios found is 620, and 997 mounds have been found as well. In some areas, remains of obsidian and sandstone workshops have been found.&lt;ref name=&quot;cantonagob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=152:zonas-arqueologicas-cantona&amp;catid=31:arqueologia&amp;Itemid=55 |title=Cantona  |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= January 8, 2007 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Cantona |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cholula was one a major Mesoamerican city with a multicultural population that was bound by a common religion based on the worship of [[Quetzalcoatl]]. The city was a pilgrimage site for the worship of this deity. Its architecture was complex and shows various foreign influences. Its height was reached during the Classic period between 100 to 900 CE along with [[Tula, Hidalgo|Tollan]] and Teotihuacan. It was regionally influential for much of the Mesoamerican period, and its polychromic pottery has been found in a large number of sites, indicating trade. By the time the Spanish arrived, it was still a very large city, second only to Tenochtitlan, to which it was subject. Today, the site is known for its Great Pyramid.&lt;ref name=&quot;cholulagob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=151:zona-arquelogica-cholula&amp;catid=31:arqueologia&amp;Itemid=55 |title=Cholula  |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Cholula |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:TepejiViejo.jpg|thumb|Tepexi el Viejo]]
[[Tepexi el Viejo]] is located southeast of the city of Puebla. It was founded as the seat of one of the most important [[Popoloca]] dominions and control much of what is now the south of the state from 1200 to 1500 CE. This area’s light orange colored pottery has been found as far away as Teotihuacan. The site is naturally protected by mountains and canyons and is divided into five areas. Each has platforms, pyramidal mounds, residential areas and tombs. The most important pyramidal mound is located in the center of the site and other, smaller one is located to the extreme west. Residences are located in the northwest, many of which are L-shaped. There is only one natural opening to the area, which is in the south about 6&amp;nbsp;km outside the city’s walls.&lt;ref name=&quot;tepexigob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=149:tepexi&amp;catid=31:arqueologia&amp;Itemid=55|title= Tepexi el Viejo |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Tepexi el Viejo |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike other sites in the state, [[Yohualichan]] was dominated by coastal groups, which eventually abandoned it in the face of incursions from peoples from the central highlands. The site was a ceremonial center which was probably dominant over other similar sites. Containing niched pyramids as well, it is related to the [[El Tajín]] site in Veracruz. There is also a residential area, but it has not been studied.&lt;ref name=&quot;yohualichangob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=150:yohualichan&amp;catid=31:arqueologia&amp;Itemid=55 |title= Yohualichan |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Yohualichan |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Tepatlaxco (Mesoamerican site)|Tepatlaxco]] is located on the south side of the Totlqueme mountain. It is centered on a ceremonial center which has more than eight structures, surrounded by numerous smaller mounds. Much of the site was constructed into the mountain itself, causing it to blend in. In addition to the mountain, there are two large ravines to give the site added protection. The most important structure is named Mound A, which also shows the longest occupation. It measures nine meters high and 36 meters at its base.&lt;ref name=&quot;tepatlaxcogob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=148:tepatlaxco&amp;catid=31:arqueologia&amp;Itemid=55 |title= Tepatlaxco |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Tepatlaxco |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gastronomy==
[[File:CemitaSandwich2.JPG|thumb|Cemita sandwich]]
Other foods common to the state include [[atole]] with [[chili pepper]] (chileatole), spicy [[mole (sauce)|mole verde]], [[barbacoa]], chilate with chopped onion, camitas, [[cecina]], guaxmole with lime, and mole de caderas or mole espinazo. Many of these are found in the Sierra Mixteca region.&lt;ref name=&quot;smixteca&quot;/&gt; However, the state is best known for [[cemita]]s, [[mole poblano]], [[chiles en nogada]] and [[chalupa]]s.

The cemita is a kind of sandwich on a roll, related to the [[torta]], particularly popular in Mexico City and the [[pambazo]], which is of French origin and popular in several areas in central Mexico. The sandwich has its origin with two kinds of bread which were brought over from Spain during the colonial period: one called “bizcocho de sal,” which was long and hard and a kind of hollow cracker. Both breads were developed for long storage and eventually were made in Puebla with grain from the Atlixco area. These two breads eventually fused into a unique type that became softer by the mid 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;cemitasgob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=173:cemitas-poblanas&amp;catid=38:Gastronom%C3%ADa&amp;Itemid=62 |title= Cemitas Poblanas  |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Cemitas of Puebla |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name is derived from a Jewish unleavened bread called “semita,” which was brought over by [[Sephardi Jews]] to [[New Spain]]. These were also produced in Puebla state. The cemitas were prepared at home and filled with potatoes, beans and nopal cactus and eaten by the lower classes. Later, an establishment in the Mercado Victoria market began to sell them to the public filled with meat from bull’s feet with a [[vinaigrette]], herbs, onions and chili peppers. This new filling was a hit and eventually this and other variations became a staple in many markets and popular eateries. Today, a large number varieties exist but all are prepared using the same type of bread.&lt;ref name=&quot;cemitasgob&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Mole Poblano.jpg|thumb|left|mole poblano]]
The best-known mole is named after the city of Puebla, [[mole poblano]]. The origin of this sauce is disputed and there are two versions of the legend that are most often cited. The first states that 16th century nuns from the Convent of Santa Rosa were worried because they had just found out that the archbishop was going to visit them and they had nothing to prepare for him except for an old turkey in the yard. Supposedly due to divine inspiration, they began to mix together many of the spices and flavorings they had on hand in the kitchen, including different types of chili peppers, other spices, day-old bread, chocolate and approximately twenty other ingredients. They let the sauce simmer for hours and poured it over the turkey meat. Fortunately, the archbishop was very pleased with the meal and the nuns were able to save face.&lt;ref name=&quot;national&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.mexonline.com/molepoblano.htm |title= Mole Poblano: Mexico’s National Food Dish  |publisher=Mexonline |accessdate=2009-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The other story states that the sauce is of pre-Hispanic times and this was served to [[Hernán Cortés]] and the other conquistadors by [[Moctezuma II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;national&quot;/&gt; The Aztecs did have a preparation called “chilmulli,” which in [[Nahuatl]] means “chili pepper sauce.” &lt;ref name=&quot;92percent&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Josefina |last=Quintero M. |title=92% de la población se dedica a la preparación y venta del mole |url=http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2007/09/23/index.php?section=capital&amp;article=035n1cap |publisher=La Jornada |location=Mexico City |date=2007-09-23 |accessdate=May 30, 2009 |language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is no evidence that chocolate  was ever used to flavor prepared foods or used in chilmulli.&lt;ref name=&quot;national&quot;/&gt; What has happened is that the sauce gained ingredients as it was reinterpreted over the colonial period.&lt;ref name=&quot;92percent&quot;/&gt;

Many food writers and gourmets nowadays consider one particular dish, the famous turkey in mole poblano, which contains chocolate, to represent the pinnacle of the Mexican cooking tradition.&lt;ref name=&quot;national&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Chile en nogada.jpg|thumb|Chile en nogada]]
According to the legend of chiles en nogada, there were three sisters from the city of Puebla who were in Mexico City. When the [[Army of the Three Guarantees]] entered the capital at the end of the [[Mexican War of Independence]], they were feted by many. At one of these parties, the three sisters fell in love with three of the army’s officers. Soon after, [[Agustín de Iturbide]] himself was set to visit the city of Puebla. Remembering the sisters, the soon-to-be emperor wanted to visit them. Wanting to impress Iturbide but not knowing how to cook, the sisters turned to the nuns of the Santa Monica convent who were famous for their food. The nuns decided to invent a dish for the sisters, which would represent the three colors of the [[Flag of Mexico|new Mexican flag]]. On the appointed day, the banquet was prepared with the dish now called chiles en nogada, which pleased Iturbide.&lt;ref name=&quot;chilesnogada&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=171:chiles-en-nogada&amp;catid=37:Leyendas&amp;Itemid=61  |title= Chiles en Nogada |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Chiles en Nogada |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chalupas are thick corn tortillas fried in lard then covered in red or green chili pepper sauce and topped with shredded meat and other things. According to legend, they were named after the barges that the [[Aztec]]s used to travel in areas such as [[Tenochtitlan]] (today Mexico City). Chalupas are popular in other areas of central Mexico but are considered a specialty of Puebla, where they are served from humble street carts to upscale restaurants.&lt;ref name=&quot;chalupasgob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=174:chalupas&amp;catid=38:Gastronom%C3%ADa&amp;Itemid=62  |title= Chalupas  |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Chalupas |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Myths and legends==
[[File:Fundacion Puebla.jpg|thumb|Mural of the founding of Puebla by Roberto Cueva Del Río]]
The legend of the founding of the city of Puebla attributes the act to a vision had by friar [[Julián Garcés]], who became the first bishop of Puebla. The legend states that while praying, the friar fell asleep, when he dreamed of a festival in honor the [[Archangel Michael]] happening in a place with leafy trees and a crystal clear river, flowing from springs. As the contemplated the scenery, angels descended from heaven and traced the outlines of the city to be built. When he awake he drew what he had seen, deciding he had had a divine vision. He communicated the dream to other [[Franciscans]] and found the place he saw five days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;fundacion&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=37&amp;Itemid=61   |title= Leyendas |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Legends |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The story of the [[China Poblana]] is one of the most popular in the state. The girl was taken on the [[Manila Galleon]], but she was sold to Puebla resident Miguel de Sosa for a price ten times what the [[viceroy]] offered.  She was taken to the city and baptized with the name of Catarina de San Juan in 1620. She maintained her oriental dress which made her conspicuous and it became a fad to imitate some aspects of this dress.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones37&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;

When de Sosa and his wife died, Catherine entered a convent and began to see visions of the Virgin Mary and the [[Child Jesus]]. Some say that a number of miracles occurred while Catherine lived at the convent and this provoked a kind of veneration of her.  When the China Poblana died in 1882, veneration of her as a saint began in earnest, but the practice was put to an end by the [[Mexican Inquisition]]. Today her remains are in a crypt in the Temple de La Compañia in the city of Puebla.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones38&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

The Aztec myth of [[Popocatépetl]] and [[Iztaccíhuatl]], a [[Romeo and Juliet]] type story, has equal significance in this state as it does in the [[Valley of Mexico]] as the two are equally visible from the city of Puebla, but only in reverse (with Popocatépetl on the left).&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones39&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a popular saying “todo terminó como el Rosario de Amozoc, a golpes y farolazos” (it all ended like the Amozoc Rosary, with blows and drinks.  The saying is derived from a legend from the community of [[Amozoc (municipality)|Amozoc de Mota]] in the state. A silversmith apprentice by the name of Alberto was in love with a beautiful girl named Catalina, nicknamed La Culata. However, another apprentice from another shop named Enrique, was also in love with her. Alberto was accepted by la Culata and this made Enrique jealous. Festivities for the beginning of the year were supposed to be organized by the different silver workshops together but the rivalry caused a split in which ecclesiastical authorities needed to intervene. On the first day of the event, at Mass, Enrique saw Alberto and Catherine kiss briefly, which enraged him. During the rosary, while the choir sang “Mater Inmaculata,” Enrique heard “mata a la Culata” (kill La Culata), took a knife from his clothing and attacked the couple, killing Catarina. Alberto took a machete from his belt and killed Enrique. A fight ensued which left many dead and wounded. It is said that one can still hear the cries of Catalina as she died.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones3940&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, pp. 39–40&lt;/ref&gt;

The house at Avenida 3 Ote 201 in the city of Puebla belonged to Pedro de Carvajal, who was a wealthy and respected man. However, he lost his young wife as she gave birth to their second child, a boy. When his daughter turned 15, there were many interested suitors but she was not interested in them. One day a monster appeared at a party in the city provoking terror. The monster went to the Carvajal house and ate the younger son, who was playing out front of the house. Pedro offered a large reward for the capture of the beast. One young man, who wanted the hand of Pedro’s daughter, appeared at another festival, bearing the head of the beast. It is said that this young man gained noble title and the hand of the daughter as a reward.&lt;ref name=&quot;matoanimal&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=170:casa-del-que-mato-al-animal&amp;catid=37:Leyendas&amp;Itemid=61 |title= Casa del que mato al Animal |author= Luis Alberto Martínez Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date= May 28, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title= House of He who killed the animal |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culture==
===The two volcanoes===
The state of Puebla is located on the east side of the volcanoes of Popocatepetl and Iztaccihuatl, opposite of the Valley of Mexico and Mexico City. The two volcanoes have as much significance here as they do on the west side, with many communities nearby maintaining ritual specific to honoring the two. These arose as fertility rituals but today are called “birthdays” with 12 March reserved for Popocatepetl and 30 August for Iztaccíhuatl.  On these events, special foods and gifts are prepared as offerings and left in certain places. These traditions have survived despite the evangelization efforts of the colonial period.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones24&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;

===Festivals and holidays===

The state is home to a number of festivals and traditions, from those with a purely pre-Hispanic background, to the far more numerous saints’ days to modern fairs located to regional economies.&lt;ref name=&quot;fiestastrad&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=13&amp;Itemid=20 |title= Fiestas y tradiciones  Álvarez  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title= Festivals and traditions |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, pp. 25–29&lt;/ref&gt; The largest important events include the [[Day of the Dead]] in Huaquechula, the Carnival of Huijotzingo, [[spring equinox|Spring Equinox]] in Cantona, Fiesta de Santo Entierro y Feria de las Flores, the Fería del Café y el Huipil, the Huey Atlixcáyotl Festival, the Quetzalcoatl Ritual and [[Cinco de Mayo]], celebrated in the entire state.&lt;ref name=&quot;fiestastrad&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cincoschmal&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.houstonculture.org/mexico/cincodemayoesp.html |title= El cinco de mayo: una lucha por la libertad. |author= John P. Schmal  |publisher= The Hispanic Experience Houston Institute for Culture |language=Spanish |location=Houston |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cinco de Mayo is an important celebration in a number of places the United States, but it is a minor holiday or even unknown in much of Mexico proper. The only place where the holiday, which commemorates the [[Battle of Puebla]] during the [[French Intervention in Mexico]], is important is in the state of Puebla. The French army invaded the country in 1862 and marched from Veracruz towards the city of Puebla. Just outside the city, inexperienced Mexican troops attacked the French who were camped. This resulted victory, but the French were ultimately able to move on and take Mexico City, dominating the country until 1867. The annual celebration of the battle began in the state in areas of the country not occupied by the French as a symbol of Mexican pride.&lt;ref name=&quot;cincoschmal&quot;/&gt;  Today it is the most important state political commemoration. The most important observances take place at the Loreto and Guadalupe forts in the city of Puebla, where the battle occurred in 1862. The highlight is a reenactment of the event at the site.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt; 

[[File:Ofrenda mixteca poblana.jpg|thumb|Day of the Dead altar in the Sierra Mixteca]]
Like the rest of Mexico, Day of the Dead is celebrated in the state. Two aspects which feature prominently on altars in this state are [[mole (sauce)|mole]] with turkey and large wax candles. Other items can include black [[candelabra]]s, incense burners, candy skulls, decorative paper cutouts, oranges and other fruits in season. Leading to these altars often are a line of small candles to guide the returning spirits. One municipality which is particularly known for its events is [[Huaquechula (municipality)|Huaquechula]]. Here, altars constructed in homes can be of multiple levels and are usually covered in white paper. On the first level, food and drink are usually placed, with religious objects and objects related to the deceased on the second level.&lt;ref name=&quot;huaquechula&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=227:dia-de-muertos-y-altares-de-huaquechula&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Día de muertos y altares de Huaquechula |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=July 27, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Day of the Dead and altars of Huaquechula |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a number of communities in the state, Carnival is celebrated. The best known of these carnivals takes place in [[Huejotzingo (municipality)|Huejotzingo]], as it began as a synthesis of a celebration honoring [[Tlaloc]] and the Catholic tradition related to the days before [[Ash Wednesday]]. Today, this carnival includes many traditional activities such as music, masks and parades, but this one also includes a reenactment of the Battle of Puebla and local legends such as the kidnapping of a governor’s daughter and&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt; the legend of Agustìn Lorenzo (called the Robin Hood of the 18th century) .&lt;ref name=&quot;huejotzingocarn&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=228:carnaval-de-huejotzingo&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Carnaval de Huejotzingo  |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=May 22, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Carnival of Huejotzingo |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Locals attend in colorful costumes and masks representing the [[Conquistador]]s, demons or animals, adorned with palm fronds or feathers.&lt;ref name=&quot;huejotzingocarn&quot;/&gt;  The capital of Puebla also celebrates Carnival with its signature tradition of the Las Marias, where men disguise themselves as women and mischievous devils.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt; 

Another major time for religious observance is [[Holy Week]] or Semana Santa. In Puebla, there is the Procession del Silencio or Procession of Silence which occurs on [[Maundy Thursday]], when the city observes a period of silence to mark the death of Jesus.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt; 

The spring equinox is the setting for rituals at some of Puebla’s archeological sites such as Cantona and Cholula. Cantona is an archeological site located near the city of Puebla and was one of the largest cities in early Mesoamerica. Today, the site is popular gathering place on the spring equinox ([[Spring equinox in Teotihuacán|much like Teotihuacan]]), where people sing, dance and greet the sunrise on this date.&lt;ref name=&quot;equinoxcan&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=230:equinoccio-en-cantona&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67  |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Equinoccio en Cantona |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=July 22, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Equinox in Cantona |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another site where similar observances are held is the Great Pyramid of Cholula. Here indigenous dances and rituals are performed. The event culminates with the Ritual of Quetzalcoatl, which was an important part of the ancient Cholula culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt;  This event draws attendees from various parts of Mexico.&lt;ref name=&quot;ritquet&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=235:ritual-quetzalcoatl&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Ritual Quetzalcóatl |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=July 22, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Quetzalcoatl Ritual |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Huey Atlixcáyotl Festival is celebrated in the town of Atlixco to celebrate the area’s local culture and identity. The name means “Atlixco tradtion” in [[Nahuatl]] and is centered on the San Miguel Hill (called Popocatica in ancient times) located in the center of the town. It was locally sacred in the pre-Hispanic era, and in colonial times, a hermitage was built there. The event was named a Cultural Heritage of the State of Puebla in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;festhuey&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=234:huey-atlixcayotl&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Festival Huey Atlixcáyotl |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=July 27, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Huey Atlixcáyotl Festival|accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The purpose of the event is to celebrate the survival of indigenous culture after the [[Spanish conquest of the Aztec Empire|Conquest]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt; 

In July, the [[Pueblo Mágico]] of [[Cuetzalan]] has the cultural festival of Festival Tradicional, which features traditional dancers who come from various parts of the state. [[Tetela de Ocampo]] celebrates its Peach Festival in August. On the last day of August, the Procession de los Faroles (Procession of the Lanterns) takes place in [[Cholula, Puebla|Cholula]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt; 

Puebla has a number of annual fairs meant to highlights the various regions’ products. In [[Huauchinango (municipality)|Huauchinango]], an economic fair and a religious observance are conducted at the same time. The Feria de las Flores (Flower Festival) and the Santo Entierro (Holy Burial) occur in the second half of March. It consists of religious events such as processions and masses. Many cut flower and ornamental plant growers come to display their products and there is the coronation of the Queen of Flowers. Other events include includes other agricultural displays, parades with floats, dances, crafts, [[cockfight]]s, sporting events and more.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;huachinango&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=232:fiesta-del-santo-entierro-y-feria-de-las-flores-huauchinango&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Fiesta del Santo Entierro y Feria de las Flores Huauchinango |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=July 22, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= Feast of the Holy Burial and Flower Fair of Huauchinango |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Feria del Café y el Huipil (Coffee and [[Huipil]] Festival) takes place in Cuetzalan. The event promotes the area’s locally grown coffee as well as traditionally made huipil dresses. There are also displays of pre-Hispanic dance, popular music, fireworks and more. The event began in 1949 as the National Festival of Coffee, which is economically important here. The event centered on the choosing of a Coffee Queen, much like other similar kinds of festivals. In 1962, the National Festival of the Huipil was established. Eventually, the two merged to the current event.&lt;ref name=&quot;cafehuipil&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.puebla.gob.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=233:feria-nacional-del-cafe-y-el-huipil-en-cuetzalan&amp;catid=43:principales-ferias-y-tradiciones&amp;Itemid=67 |author= Luz Cortés Padilla |title= Feria Nacional del Café y el Huipil en Cuetzalan |publisher=Government of Puebla |location=Puebla, Mexico |date=July 27, 2009 |language=Spanish |trans_title= National Coffee and Huipil Far in Cuetzlan |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other events to promote Puebla’s products include the Feria de Café in Xicotpec in March and the Feria Nacional de Puebla. The latter is held in the state capital and brings together many of the state’s agricultural, livestock, craft and industrial producers in an event very analogous to a state fair. The regional fair called the Piloto de Cholula occurs in September.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones2529&quot;/&gt;

===China Poblana===
[[File:China poblana.jpg|thumb|Woman in &quot;china poblana&quot; dress]]
The China Poblana was a real person who lived during the colonial period. Her real name was Mirra. She was an [[Indians in the Philippines|Indian]] who was brought over from [[Manila]] in the 1620s on the [[Manila Galleon]] as a child to work as a slave for the [[viceroy]] Marques de Gélves. She was soon sold to ship captain Miguel de Sosa who lived in Puebla. According to legend, Mirra was originally a princess in her home country but her family was displaced by the [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] and she was kidnapped by pirates who sold her. Mirra was considered to be beautiful and exotic. She had been converted to the Catholic faith. Later in her life, she began to have visions of the child Jesus and angels. Her fame grew and she was eventually considered to be something of a prophet. When she died in 1688, people began to venerate her as a saint and many women copied her Asian/Mexican inspired dress.&lt;ref name=&quot;chinpob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://redescolar.ilce.edu.mx/redescolar/act_permanentes/historia/histdeltiempo/mexicana/colonia/c_chinap.htm |title= Historia y leyenda de la china poblana De la Colonia |work=Red Escolar |publisher=Instituto Latinoamericano de la Comunicacion Educativa |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=History and legend of the &quot;China Poblana&quot; of the colonial period |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This fashion led to the now-traditional “china poblana” dress. It consists of a red skirt heavily decorated with colored sequins that in one part form the image of the eagle found on the Mexican flag and a blouse embroidered with colored thread and beads around the bust area. It is often worn with a [[charro]] type hat. The outfit is the amalgam of several cultures such as Spanish, especially in the skirt, Chinese, with its use of sequins and beads, and indigenous with colorful embroidery.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones23&quot;/&gt;

===Dance===
Folk dance of both indigenous and mixed European and indigenous origin are most often seen at religious and cultural events in many parts of the state. Some of the most popular dances include “Moors and Christians,” Dance of the Santiagos” and “Danza de los Arcos.” The last is usually performed only by men who dress in white and with a scarf-like garment across the chest, dance in pairs which carry large arch portals covered in flowers and paper decorations. The dance has a number of variations which can include leaps into the air and complicated twirls.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones23&quot;/&gt; 

The Dances of the Quetzales is most popular in the Sierra Norte, especially in Cuetzalan. It is a highly symbolic dance and usually performed in conjunction with rituals that relate to good harvests. The dancers form crosses, which signify the four cardinal directions and move in circles, which symbolize the rotation of time. The dancers wear large circular headdresses of quetzal feathers, which give the dance its name, and red suits. The [[Danza de los Voladores de Papantla|Dance of the Voladores]], which more common in [[Papantla, Veracruz]], is also performed in a number of communities in the north of Puebla. This consists of five men who climb a tall pole and then four fall and spin from the pole while attached by ropes. The fifth dancer stays on top and plays music and dances as the other men fall. Another important dance in Puebla is the Doce pares de Francia, which recalls the events of the Battle of Puebla.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones24&quot;/&gt;

===Architecture===
[[File:TiledBldgs5OrientePuebla.JPG|thumb|Buildings decorated with tile in the historic center of Puebla]]
The colonial architecture of the state is defined by is heavy use of ornamental tiles called [[Talavera (pottery)|Talavera]]. This is particularly true in the capital. This makes these buildings more colorful than most of their contemporaries in other parts of Mexico and were one of the reasons that the historic center of the capital was selected as a [[World Heritage Site]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones13&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of churches and other buildings in rural parts of the state are noted for their “folk baroque” architecture and decoration, especially in Atlixco and the southwest. Folk baroque consists of the use of tile and painted raised stucco based on more traditional [[Baroque architecture|Baroque designs]], which was most popular in the 18th century. One well known church of this type is the church of [[Jolapan]], which is modeled after the [[Tepalcingo]] Sanctuary in neighboring [[Morelos]]. The church of Jolalpan contains richly decorated [[pilaster]]s, [[Solomonic column]]s and other elements in a design very similar to that of Tepalcingo. Between these there are a number of small churches which also show folk baroque influence such as those in [[Tlancualpican]] and [[Tzicatlán]]. The church in Tlancualpican is painted in bright blues, greens and red, with an ornate [[façade]] with sculpted leaves, tendrils and niches divided by spiral half-columns all done in stucco. Even more ornate is the church in Tzicatlán, which is a small rural farming village, with every bit of the surface of the main facade decorated with brightly colored images and sculptures.&lt;ref name=&quot;folkbaroque&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.colonial-mexico.com/Central%20Mexico/tepalcingo.html |title= The Folk Baroque churches of southern Morelos and Puebla |work=Exploring Colonial Mexico |publisher=Espadaña Press |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the modern era, architectural styles have evolved into new and sometimes eclectic forms. Skyscrapers, almost all of which are in the city of Puebla, include Edificio Vacas at 42 meters high, Torre Géminis at 50 meters high, Torre Nora at 69 meters high to the tallest, Torre Ejecutiva JVI and Torre Ejecutiva JVI at 100 meters high each. These last two have a triangular shape and are covered in blue tinged glass.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones13&quot;/&gt;

===Literature===
Literature is one of the better-developed arts in the state and includes works such as novels, essays, poetry and theatrical plays. One prominent name from the colonial period is that of José Mariano Beristáin de Souza who was a priest and writers in the 18th century. He is also known for amassing a large library of writings in Spanish over twenty years of his life, which resulted in the Biblioteca Hispanoamericana Septentrional.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones13&quot;/&gt; However, literature would not be a major cultural force in the state until the 20th century. One early prominent writer was poet [[Gregorio de Gante]]. In his early career, he was a professor but after the [[Mexican Revolution]] broke out the joined revolutionary forces under Antonio Medina.  After the war, he began his career as a poet, eventually writing regularly for a newspaper called “El Nacional” and become one of Mexico’s most popular writers by the 1930s.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones14&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

Many modern works with themes of social injustice and sometimes about the culture and scenery of the state itself. Modern Puebla literature can be traced back to the work of poet [[Arturo Trejo]], one of the “Generacion de los 50” or Generation of the 1950s.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones13&quot;/&gt; 

[[Elena Garro]] was active during the mid and latter 20th century, whose writings were said to “grab” the reader. Most of her work was autobiographical in one sense or another. She was married to another Mexican writer [[Octavio Paz]], from whom she divorced in 1959.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones14&quot;/&gt; 

Born in Atlixco in 1930, [[Hector Azar]] is one of Mexico’s most noted playwrights in the 20th century. Some of his works include Revista de Revistas, Revista de la Universidad and Jueves de Excelsior. He has also directed and produced plays in Mexico and Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones16&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sergio Pitol Demeneghi]] is a writer, translator and diplomat who was born in the city of Puebla in 1933. Most of his works relate to the theme of human rights. Much of his writing and translating work relates to his diplomatic functions. His best kown works include No hay tal lugar, Infierno de todos and Los climas.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones16&quot;/&gt; 
Born in Puebla in 1949, [[Ángeles Mastretta]]’s writings are known for their female characters which are prominent. She has found most of her popularity in Spain and Mexico publishing stories in magazines such as Ovaciones and La Jornada. Her books include El Mundo Ilumninado, Arrancame la vida and Mujeres de ojos grandes.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones17&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;
[[José Francisco Conde Ortega]], also known simply as Paco Conde, was born in Atlixco in 1951. His writings include chronicles, essays and poetry. His works mostly reflect on everyday urban life with book titles such as Estudios para un cuerpo, Los lobos viven del viento and Práctica de lobo.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones18&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;

[[José Luis Zárate]] was born in Puebla in 1966. He is best known for novels such as Xanto, novelucha libre, La ruta del hielo y la sal and Del cielo oscuro y del abismo, but he has published numerous short stories, essays and poems. He is known in the fantasy genre and has established organizations dedicated to this such as the Asociacion Mexicana de Cienca Ficcion y Fantasia and Circulo Puebla de Ciencia Ficcion y Divulgacion.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones18&quot;/&gt; 

Other notable writers from the state include, Fritz Glockner, Pedro Ángel Palou Garcia, Miguel Maldonado, Eduardo Montagner Anguiano, Gabriel Wolfson Reyes, Jaime Mesa and Gabriela Puente.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones19&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt;

===Painting===
Much of the historical painting in the state is found in its colonial churches and reflect the artistic styles of the 16 to 19th centuries. These consist of murals, portraits and biblical scenes done on canvas, wood and other mediums. José Joaquín Magón was born in Puebla in the 18th century is known for his portrait paintings but his other works have mostly religious and mythological themes. He also did a number of works related to [[New Spain]]’s [[casta|caste system]]. [[Luis Berrueco]] is one of the major Pueblan painters from the 18th century. He was also prolific, painting images of religious martyrs and saints which can still be found today in many churches in the state. His style is considered to be unique, marked by delicate faces and profuse ornamentation. Some of his best work can be found at the Santa Clara Church in Atlixco.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones19&quot;/&gt;  Gonzalo Carrasco was born in Otumba, Puebla in 1859. He was both and artist and a Jesuit monk who produced over 500 religious paintings that can be found all over Mexico and some murals including those in the Basilica de Guadalupe in Puebla and Fordham University in the U.S.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones20&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;

Much of Puebla’s art scene had disappeared before the 20th century but in the 1920s, a group of young artists from the Escuela de Bellas Artes de Puebla (School of Fine Arts of Puebla) began to band together for mutual support. These artists eventually caught the attention and patronage of artists such as [[Diego Rivera]] and [[Dr. Atl]] and received visitors such as [[David Alfaro Siquieros]], [[Frida Kahlo]], [[Francisco Cornejo]] and [[Alfredo Guati Rojo]]. This effort would become the Barrio del Artista.&lt;ref name=&quot;artefluye&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Encuentros con Mexico / El arte fluye en las calles; [1] |author= Ricardo Diazmunoz |author2=Maryell Ortiz de Zarate |newspaper=Reforma |location=Mexico City |date=April 24, 2005  |language=Spanish |trans_title=Encounters with Mexico/Art flows in the streets}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Barrio del Artista is a neighborhood in the city of Puebla which is home to artists from a number of disciplines. It contains 46 small workshops which permit visitors to observe the work and even chat with the artists. These workshops mostly surround a large plaza with a fountain near a building known as the Café del Artista, managed the Union de Artes Plasticas, A.C. “Barrio del Artista,” which was founded in 194|.&lt;ref name=&quot;artefluye&quot;/&gt;

[[Ignacio Dávila Tagle]] was born in the city of Puebla in 1898 into an artistic family, learning to paint from his father, Daniel Dávila Domínguez. One of his best-known works is his dreamlike mural called “El sueno de fray Julián Garcés” which depicts the legendary founding of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones20&quot;/&gt; 

[[Faustino Salazar Garcia]] was born in Puebla in 1912. He turned to painting as a child after he lost his mother. His works are known for their emotional qualityAs an established painter, he was one of the founding members of the Unión de Artes Plásticas.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones20&quot;/&gt;

[[Alejandro Honda]] was born in San Martin Texmelucan in 1952. This painter’s works show his fascination for Mesoamerica, which began when he was young. They can also have a sensual edge to them, even his religious paintings such as the María de Magdalena.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones21&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gustavo Cadena]] was born in Puebla in 1974 has been a noticed painter since he was a young child. Many of his works reflect daily life, customs and traditions of the state. Some of his better known works include Niño indígena mexicano, Catedral de Puebla, and Pensando en Puebla.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones21&quot;/&gt;

===Music===
Traditional music in Puebla has been influenced by the waltz, zarzuela and the Mexican version of trova. Although it waned in the 20th century, it has since experienced a revival.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones21&quot;/&gt; 

[[Pelagio C. Manjarrez]] (1886–1952) was from Tochimilco. He is not only known for his musical ability but also as a fighter in the Mexican Revolution, professor, journalist and poet. Most of his musical composition relate to dance such as waltzes, marches, foxtrots and tangos. Best known titles include “Porque me has besado tu,” “La mañana está de fiesta” and “Alma herida.”&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones21&quot;/&gt; 

[[Vicente T. Mendoza]] (1894–1964) was from Cholula who dedicated himself to researching the folk music of the area, especially those traditions that told the history of many of the state’s communities. He founded the Folclorología Musical Mexicana. He also composed a number of pieces including the polka “La hora del crepúsculo,” the waltz “La molinera,” and religious pieces such as “Villancicos alegres para la Navidad” and “Cánticos para Navidad.”.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones22&quot;&gt;Gonzalez, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gerardo Pablo]] is one of the main Pueblan composers of modern trova Mexicana who was born in Puebla in 1977. Many of his lyrics deal with social problems in Mexico and his work has been compared to that of Guty Càrdenas. Some of his best known works include “Tres noches por semana,” “Càntaro”, “Reflejos acústicos”, &quot;Trago de Ron&quot;, &quot;Delirio&quot;, &quot;Los Numerosos Nadies&quot; which is based on the work of Uruguayan writer Eduardo Galeano,&quot;Escucha a Gerardo Pablo&quot; and &quot;Quesoy&quot; his most recent work with a Jazz Trio. Other notable musicians include Carlos Espinosa de los Monteros (waltz composer), pianist Celia Valderrábano Andrew who has also composed waltzes. Zarzuela composers include Félix Maria Alcerreca who is a lawyer by profession and Ignacio León who is a priest.&lt;ref name=&quot;rincones22&quot;/&gt;

==Education==
[[File:BibliotecaUDLAP.JPG|thumb|UDLAP library]]
On average, the population of the state over the age of 15 has finished the first year of middle school with an average number of years in school at 7.4. This is under the national average of 8.1.  At of every 100 over age 15, 12 have not gone to school at all, 17 have left school before the end of primary, 21 finish primary, 3 start, but do not finish middle school, 19 finish middle school, 5 begin but do not finish high school, 8 obtain a bachelor’s degree and 1 has an advanced degree. There are 441, 699 illiterate people, or 13%, according to INEGI, above the national average of eight percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;eduinegi&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://cuentame.inegi.org.mx/monografias/informacion/pue/poblacion/educacion.aspx?tema=me&amp;e=21 |title= Educacion |publisher= INEGI |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One problem that the educational system has is an ongoing power struggle in the teachers’ union of the state. On 8 October 2010, a group of teachers attacked a union office in the state capital with stones, poles and even Molotov cocktails in an attempt to get the union to oust the secretary general of the union, José Uber Romero Ronquillo. Earlier that day, a group of 800 teachers, peacefully marched for the same purpose.&lt;ref name=&quot;retoman&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Profesores retoman oficinas en Puebla; 10 lesionados |author= Arturo Alfaro Galán |url= http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2010/10/09/index.php?section=estados&amp;article=027n2est |newspaper= La Jornada de Oriente |location=Puebla |date=October 9, 2010 |page=27 |accessdate=October 10, 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Teachers retake offices in Puebla;10 hurt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Puebla is ranked second in higher education in Mexico with 57 technological colleges (Institutos Tecnologicos) and 110 research centers. It ranks fourth in the number of universities and colleges in the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;prometedor&quot;/&gt; It is home to very prestigious institutions such as the [[Universidad de las Americas-Puebla]], which has substantial ties to the United States, such as being accredited by the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] and numerous student exchange programs. It has also received substantial economic assistance from the [[U.S. Agency for International Development]]. Much of the school’s setup mimics that of U.S. universities, including student dormitories.&lt;ref name=&quot;chronicle&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Campbell |first=Monica |date=December 14, 2007 |title= Dissension Racks Elite Mexican University |journal=The Chronicle of Higher Education |volume=54 |issue=16 |page=A1 |location=Washington }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Universidad Popular Autónoma del Estado de Puebla]] (UPAEP) was founded in 1973 at a former ranch called La Noria in response to social and political unrest that was prevalent in the state in the 1960s and early 1970s. It was also created to fill a need for higher education in a number of fields formerly underrepresented.&lt;ref name=&quot;UPAEP&quot;/&gt;

Instituto Tecnologico de Puebla (Puebla Institute of Technology), which was founded in 1972.

==Government==
[[File:Government Building In Puebla.jpg|thumb|200px|Hall of protocols of the State Government of Puebla, Puebla city.]]
The current division of the territory was created in 1895, which is a system of 21 districts and 217 municipalities. This is down from a high of 222, but the municipalities of San Jerónimo Caleras, San Felipe Hueyotlipan, San Miguel Canoa, La Resurrección and Totimehuacan were incorporated into the city of Puebla in 1962.&lt;ref name=&quot;gobierno&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.e-local.gob.mx/work/templates/enciclo/puebla/regi.htm |title= Gobierno |year=2009 |work= Enciclopedia de los Municipios de México Estado de Puebla |publisher= Instituto Nacional para el Federalismo y el Desarrollo Municipal |location=Mexico |language=Spanish |trans_title=Government |accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The state is headed by a governor who is directly elected. The executive branch of the government is contains the following departments: Governing (Gobernación), Finance, Development, Evaluation and Control of the Public Administration, Economic Development, Tourism, Rural Development, Urban and Ecological Development, Communications and Transportation, Health, Public Education, Culture and Public Defender (Procuraduia General de Justicia). The legislative branch is unicameral with deputies or representatives elected from the various districts of the state. It also consists of a number of commissions dedicated to issues such as state heritage sites, education, agriculture and more.The judicial branch is headed by the Tribunal Superior de Justicia.&lt;ref name=&quot;gobierno&quot;/&gt;

==Major communities==
*[[Acatlán de Osorio]]
*[[Amozoc de Mota]]
*[[Atlixco]]
*[[Cholula, Puebla|Cholula]] (Cholula de Rivadabia)
*[[Cuetzalán]]
*[[Huauchinango]]
*[[Izúcar de Matamoros]]
*[[Puebla, Puebla]]
*[[San Martín Texmelucan de Labastida]]
*[[Tehuacán]]
*[[Teziutlán]]
*[[Zacatlan, Puebla]]

==Notable natives and residents==
*[[Ignacio Comonfort]] – [[President of Mexico]] 1855–1858
*[[Juan N. Méndez]] – [[President of Mexico]] 1876–1877
*[[Manuel Ávila Camacho]] – [[President of Mexico]] 1940–1946
*[[Gustavo Díaz Ordaz]] – [[President of Mexico]] 1964–1970
*Vicente Suárez – one of the Niños Héroes of the [[Battle of Chapultepec]]

==See also==
{{Portal|Mexico}}
{{satop|Geography|North America|Northern America|Latin America|Mexico|Puebla}}
{{clear}}

==Notes and references==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |title=Puebla:Guía para descubrir los encantos del estado |trans_title=Puebla: Guide to discover the charms of the state |editor1-first=Victor Manuel |editor1-last=Jimenez Gonzalez |year=2010 |publisher=Editorial Oceano, S. L.|location=Barcelona |language=Spanish |isbn=9786074002348}}

==External links==
* {{es icon}} [http://www.puebla.gob.mx Government of the state of Puebla]
* {{en icon}} [http://www.maps-of-mexico.com/puebla-state-mexico/puebla-state-mexico-map-main.shtml Detailed Puebla State Map @ Maps-of-Mexico.com]
* {{es icon}} [http://www.htsjpuebla.gob.mx/division.html?n=3 Puebla Judicial Districts]

{{Puebla}}
{{States of Mexico}}

[[Category:States of Mexico]]
[[Category:Puebla| ]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1824]]

[[ar:ولاية بويبلا]]
[[an:Puebla]]
[[be:Штат Пуэбла]]
[[be-x-old:Пуэбля (штат)]]
[[br:Puebla]]
[[bg:Пуебла (щат)]]
[[ca:Estat de Puebla]]
[[cs:Puebla (stát)]]
[[cy:Puebla]]
[[da:Puebla (stat)]]
[[de:Puebla (Bundesstaat)]]
[[et:Puebla osariik]]
[[es:Puebla]]
[[eo:Puebla]]
[[eu:Puebla]]
[[fa:پوئبلا]]
[[fr:État de Puebla]]
[[gl:Estado de Puebla]]
[[ko:푸에블라 주]]
[[hr:Puebla]]
[[id:Puebla]]
[[ia:Puebla]]
[[it:Puebla (stato)]]
[[ka:პუებლა (შტატი)]]
[[kw:Puebla]]
[[sw:Puebla (jimbo)]]
[[la:Puebla]]
[[lv:Puebla]]
[[lt:Puebla (valstija)]]
[[hu:Puebla (állam)]]
[[mr:पेब्ला]]
[[ms:Puebla (wilayah)]]
[[nah:Puebla]]
[[nl:Puebla (staat)]]
[[ja:プエブラ州]]
[[no:Puebla]]
[[nn:Delstaten Puebla]]
[[pnb:پیبلا]]
[[pms:Puebla (stat federal)]]
[[pl:Puebla (stan)]]
[[pt:Puebla (estado)]]
[[ro:Puebla (stat Mexic)]]
[[rm:Puebla]]
[[ru:Пуэбла]]
[[simple:Puebla (state)]]
[[sr:Држава Пуебла]]
[[sh:Puebla]]
[[fi:Puebla]]
[[sv:Puebla (delstat)]]
[[tl:Estado ng Puebla]]
[[th:รัฐปวยบลา]]
[[tg:Иёлати Пуэбла]]
[[chy:Puebla]]
[[tr:Puebla]]
[[uk:Пуебла (штат)]]
[[vec:Puebla (stato)]]
[[vi:Puebla]]
[[war:Puebla]]
[[zh:普埃布拉州]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
