<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4139033" ns="0" title="United States Ski Team"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Us skiteam shield.jpg|right|150px]]

The '''United States Ski Team''', operated under the auspices of the [[United States Ski and Snowboard Association]] (USSA), develops and supports men's and women's athletes in the sports of [[alpine skiing]], adaptive alpine, [[freestyle skiing]], cross country, adaptive cross country, ski jumping, and nordic combined. The team and association has been headquartered in [[Park City, Utah]] since 1974. &lt;ref&gt; http://www.ussa.org/magnoliaPublic/ussa/en/about/history.html USSA history information &lt;/ref&gt;

These athletes represent the best athletes in the country for their respective sports and compete as a team at the national, world and Olympic level. 

== History ==
''*The first US Ski Team was officially named in 1965 for the 1966 season, however the United States participated in skiing at all Olympic Winter Games and sent various athletes to World Championships prior to the '66 season.''

'''1882 - First US Ski Club Founded'''

The first ski club in the United States was founded in 1882. The [[Nansen Ski Club]] of [[Berlin, New Hampshire]], was founded by [[Norway|Norwegian]] immigrants and named in honor of Norway's legendary Arctic explorer [[Fridtjof Nansen]]. It continues to operate. 

'''1905 - National Ski Association Founded'''

The National Ski Association, the forerunner of the present-day [[United States Ski and Snowboard Association]], was founded on Feb. 21, 1905 in [[Ishpeming, Michigan]]. A meeting was held by the Ishpeming Ski Club in conjunction with a 1904 ski jumping meet in Ishpeming - but the association was not formed at that gathering. Club President [[Carl Tellefsen]] proposed holding a meeting after the 1905 jumping meet – a national meet - to found a ski association which, among other duties, would oversee jumping tournaments. In 1905, the association was formally organized during a meeting attended by officers from the Ishpeming, Minneapolis, Red Wing, Stillwater and Eau Claire ski clubs. On Feb. 21, 1905, Carl Tellefsen announced the National Ski Association - and said he was its first president. 

'''1910 - International Ski Commission Formed'''

Skiing grew throughout the last two decades of the 19th Century in Europe, including [[Russia]]; the first ski club in [[Switzerland]] was formed in 1863 and national associations were created in Russia (1896), [[Czechoslovakia]] (1903), the [[United States]], [[Austria]] and [[Germany]] (all in 1905) and Norway, [[Sweden]] and [[Finland]] (1908). 

In 1910, the International Ski Commission was formed to monitor development of skiing globally. On Feb. 2, 1924 in Chamonix, [[France]], while what would come to be recognized as the first [[Winter Olympic Games]] were being held, the commission gave way to the International Ski Federation; 14 member nations were present at the founding; 108 are FIS members today. 

'''1924 - Jan. 25-Feb. 4 - Inaugural Olympic Winter Games - Chamonix, France''' 

The first Winter Olympic Games actually were under the banner of International Sports Week, but were renamed the Winter Olympic Games in 1925 after organizers saw how successful they were (and after Norway, which had opposed &quot;Winter Olympic&quot; events because of concern Norwegians wouldn't dominate, saw it would be a winter power) supported the concept. Ski events were only Nordic, including cross country, ski jumping (then the premier ski event everywhere) and Nordic combined. Sixteen nations competed.

Anders Haugen, a Norwegian [[immigrant]] to the United States, was listed as fourth in ski jumping because of a calculation error. In 1974, as Norwegians prepared to celebrate the 50th anniversary of those first Winter Games, a recalculation in [[Oslo]] found Haugen was the real bronze medalist and not Thorleif Haug (1894-1934). A medal presentation was arranged in Oslo, where a frail Haugen received the bronze medal from the daughter of Thorleif Haug, who had been dead since the Thirties. Haugen's medal remains the only jumping medal won by an American in the Olympics or World Championships. Originally, the IOC did not recognize the medal exchange and kept Haug listed as its 1924 bronze medalist for years before recognizing Haugen as the legitimate medal-winner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.snl.no/.nbl_biografi/Thorleif_Haug/utdypning ''Thorleif Haug'' (Store norske leksikon)]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''1925 - First World Nordic Championships held in Johannisbad, Czechoslovakia'''

'''1931 - First World Alpine Championships held in Murren, Switzerland'''

Skiing was still primarily a European sport in the Twenties. Although the United States participated in the Winter Olympics of 1924, '28 and '32 - where there were only Nordic events, there was no US Ski Team. Athletes were selected for the various championships. 

'''1932 - Feb. 4-15 - Olympic Winter Games - Lake Placid, New York'''

The 1932 Summer Games were headed to [[Los Angeles]], but Godfrey Dewey – whose father had founded the [[Lake Placid Club]] – out-foxed a half-dozen other candidates (including [[Denver]]; [[Minneapolis]] and [[Duluth, Minnesota]]; [[Yosemite]] and [[Lake Tahoe]], California; and [[Bear Mountain (Hudson Highlands)|Bear Mountain]], New York). Then-Gov. [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] pledged to build a [[bobsled]] run and Dewey, who had finagled a posting as manager of the 1928 Olympic Ski Team, parlayed those contacts to land the ’32 Winter Olympics for the small [[Adirondacks]] village. Some 300 athletes from 17 nations competed. Skiing was still a Nordic show; top US skier was another jumper, [[Casper Oimoen]], who finished fifth. 

''*** This was the first major international ski event in the United States'' 

'''1935 - US sends first alpine team to FIS World Championships'''

The championships returned to Murren, Switzerland, site of the first official alpine championships in 1931. Six men, seven women were on that first official US squad at Worlds. 

'''1936 - Feb. 6-16 - Alpine added to Olympic Winter Games - Garmisch-Partenkirchen, [[Germany]]''' 

Alpine skiing was introduced with to the Olympics with a single event, the combined (one downhill run and two slalom runs). While Nordic remained an all-male province, alpine was opened to men and women. Germans took gold and silver in both the men’s and women’s alpine combined events; Franz Pfnuer and Christl Cranz were the new champions; Dick Durrance, who grew up in [[Florida]] but spent several years in Germany learning to ski before [[Hitler]] took power, was the runaway best US skier, finishing 10th. 

For the only time, the FIS authorized a World Championships in addition to the Olympics with alpine championship races held in [[Innsbruck]], Austria.

'''1948 - Jan. 30-Feb. 8 - Olympics return with first US alpine medals - St. Moritz, Switzerland'''

The Olympics (with Germany and [[Japan]] barred from competing) returned after a 12-year hiatus, with American Gretchen Fraser (then of Vancouver, WA, later of Sun Valley, ID) winning the first two US Olympic ski medals – and they came on the same day, Feb. 5; the combined downhill had been run the previous day and when she won the slalom, it gave her second place in the combined calculation. In addition to the combined, which debuted in 1936, alpine added both elements of combined as individual events, meaning alpine was now equal with Nordic, having three events (slalom, downhill and the combined; however, there were no women's Nordic events until 1952).
 
Fraser led US skiers, collecting the first medals by a US skier - gold in slalom and silver in combined. The US women included a talented young teen – Andrea Mead, 15, whose parents owned Pico Peak, near Rutland, VT.

Also of note, Gordy Wren (Steamboat Springs, CO) qualified for all four individual ski teams. He eventually competed only in jumping. “I was going ragged, bumping into myself, trying to train, ski alpine, cross country and the rest, so I decided to focus on jumping,” he explained. He finished fifth. 

'''1950 - World Championships in USA, Lake Placid, NY (Nordic) and Aspen, CO (alpine)'''

Poor snow in the Adirondacks almost forced cancellation of the Nordic events, but, alerted by 1948 Olympic cross country racer &quot;Chummy&quot; Broomhall that there was more than a foot of snow in his hometown of Rumford, Maine, officials agreed to stage opening ceremonies and the jumping events in Lake Placid, then everyone drove to Rumford for the cross country competitions. At one point, Broomhall helped set the race tracks – no machine-setting equipment in those days, so skiers would ski-in the tracks – and then went home to change into his racing outfit; traffic at the site meant Broomhall missed his scheduled start time, but officials let him run at the end of the pack. 

The alpine Worlds, organized by racing great Dick Durrance, then general manager at the fledgling Aspen Ski Area, included slalom, downhill and GS for men, and only downhill for women. American Katy Rodolph ([[Salt Lake City]]) led the USA, finishing fifth. [[Aspen]] was established as an alpine destination as a result of the successful World Championships. 

'''1960 - Feb. 18-28 - Olympics return to USA - Squaw Valley, CA''' 

The young [[Squaw Valley Ski Resort|Squaw Valley]] resort near [[Lake Tahoe]] in California ushered in a new Olympic era under the direction of Alex Cushing. No bobsled run was built but the skiing was memorable. In cross country, Squaw Valley introduced the initial machine-set tracks; everything had been walked or skied in before Squaw Valley but – with Al Merrill and Chummy Broomhall setting the tone as chief of competition and chief of course, respectively – snow machines were used to help groom Nordic courses for the first time. 

'''1962 - NSA renamed US Ski Association'''

The 57-year-old National Ski Association got a new name as the US Ski Association. The renamed organization moved from Denver to [[Colorado Springs]], CO. 

Also, the US Ski Education Foundation, designed to &quot;Establish, administer and promote educational programs devoted to the development and training of skiers&quot; and promote ski museums, was founded Oct. 8, 1862 (and chartered June 13, 1964). By enabling donors to receive tax deductions for contributions, it would become the fundraising arm of the US Ski Team, the forerunner of the US Ski and Snowboard Team Foundation.

'''1964 - Jan. 29-Feb. 9 - US alpine men earn first Olympic medals - Innsbruck, Austria'''

The Olympics came to Austria for the first time in 1964. US men earned their first medals Feb. 8 as Billy Kidd (Stowe, VT) won silver in slalom and Jimmie Heuga (Tahoe City, CA) took slalom bronze. Jean Saubert (Hillsborough, OR) was a double medalist, tying for silver in giant slalom and collecting bronze in slalom.

'''1965 - Bob Beattie named US Ski Team alpine head coach'''

On June 21, 1965, the USSA took the first steps in the formation of a formal US Ski Team by naming its first head alpine coach. At the annual USSA convention on June 21 in Spokane, WA, Bob Beattie was named the first full-time US alpine skiing head coach. &quot;When you think you're going too fast--accelerate!&quot; he would goad team members. Chuck Ferries, a 1964 Olympian, was named assistant coach, with primary responsibilities as head coach of the women's alpine team. Ferries took leave from his job with Head Ski Co. to coach, and was named full-time women's coach in 1966. No full-time Nordic jumping or skiing coaches were yet designated.

'''1973 - National Training Centers created'''

National Training Centers were created for both national alpine and Nordic teams. It was opened Oct. 28 in three old, mid-mountain, mining buildings at Park City Ski Area (now Park City Mountain Resort). Former Alpine Director [[Willy Schaeffler]] was the center's director.

'''1974 - US Ski Team moves to Park City, UT'''

In the summer of 1974 the alpine portion of the US Ski Team relocated from USSA's Denver office to [[Park City, Utah]]. The athletes and coaches began utilizing the Alpine Training Center, a building designed by Willy Schaeffler, that opened in old mining buildings at Park City Ski Area. Administrative offices were set up in the old Mountain Air Grocery on lower Main Street. Eventually, the Ski Team move up the hill to the old Treasure Mountain Inn.

'''1976 - USSA and US Ski Team split'''

In 1976 the USSA and the US Ski Team agreed to part ways. The USSA continued to control the rules and governance of the sport, as well as organizing travel programs for recreational skiers, while the US Ski Team focused solely on the elite national team. 

'''1988 - USSA and US Ski Team rejoin'''

Years of operating separately came to an end in the Summer of 1988 when USSA President and CEO Howard Peterson directed the consolidation of USSA and moved its national offices from Colorado Springs to join the ski team in Park City, UT, establishing headquarters at its present location on 1500 Kearns Blvd.

'''2007 - Center of Excellence Groundbreaking'''

The USSA broke ground on July 18, 2007 for a $22.5 million [http://www.usskiteam.com/public/news.php?&amp;dId=6&amp;aId=3014 Center of Excellence], which when complete in the fall of 2009 will house world-class high-performance athletic facilities including strength-training areas, a gymnasium, a climbing wall, ski and snowboard ramps, trampolines, a nutrition center and rehabilitation facilities. Plus, it will feature educational areas for athletes, coaches and clubs such as a computer lab, multimedia rooms for performance analysis and equipment workshops. And all of the educational resources will be shared with USSA's 400 clubs around the country.

== Making the US Ski Team ==
Interested young athletes generally begin competing through one of 425 local U.S. Ski and Snowboard Association clubs located in communities around the country, generally at ski and snowboard resorts. Clubs provide introductory education and training, as well as competition programs. 

Each U.S. Ski Team sport is also organized at a regional and divisional level, with slight variances by sport. Alpine skiing, for example, is organized in three regions: Eastern, Rocky/Central and Western. Within those regions are divisions including Northern, Eastern, Southern, Central, Rocky Mountain, Intermountain, Far West and Alaska. In some areas, such as New England, there are also state-based organizations.

Competition programs are held within each region or division leading up to national and international events. From these competitions, athletes earn points and are ranked nationally with the highest ranking athletes earning nominations to join the US national teams, which compete at the [http://www.fis-ski.com/ World Cup] level.

The USSA is one of the only Olympic sports in America to support a full-time standing national team in every sport. Teams are nominated each spring or summer based on results. Teams for FIS World Championships (held every odd year) and Olympic Winter Games (held every four years) are selected by specific criteria and named for those individual events.

== US Alpine Highlights ==
===Olympic Winter Games===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Location
! Athletes
! Medals
|-
| [[1948 Winter Olympics|1948]]
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} [[St. Moritz, Switzerland]] 
| [[Gretchen Fraser]]
| Gold, [[slalom skiing|slalom]]; silver, [[alpine combined|combined]]
|-
| [[1952 Winter Olympics|1952]]
| {{flagicon|Norway}} [[Oslo, Norway]]
| [[Andrea Mead-Lawrence]]
| Gold, slalom; gold, [[giant slalom]]
|-
| [[1960 Winter Olympics|1960]]
| {{flagicon|United States}} [[Squaw Valley, Placer County, California|Squaw Valley, California, USA]]
| [[Penny Pitou]]&lt;br&gt;[[Betsy Snite]]
| Silver, [[downhill]]; silver, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, slalom
|-
| [[1964 Winter Olympics|1964]]
| {{flagicon|Austria}} [[Innsbruck, Austria]]
| [[Jimmy Heuga]]&lt;br&gt;[[Billy Kidd]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jean Saubert]]
| Bronze, slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, slalom; bronze, combined&lt;br&gt;Silver, giant slalom (tie); bronze, slalom
|-
| [[1972 Winter Olympics|1972]]
| {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Sapporo, Japan]]
| [[Barbara Cochran]]&lt;br&gt;[[Susie Corrock]]
| Gold, slalom&lt;br&gt;Bronze, downhill
|-
| [[1976 Winter Olympics|1976]]
| {{flagicon|Austria}} Innsbruck, Austria
| [[Greg Jones (skier)|Greg Jones]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cindy Nelson]]
| Bronze, combined&lt;br&gt;Bronze, downhill
|-
| [[1980 Winter Olympics|1980]]
| {{flagicon|United States}} [[Lake Placid, New York|Lake Placid, New York, USA]]
| [[Phil Mahre]]&lt;br&gt;Cindy Nelson
| Gold, combined (unofficial Olympic event); silver, slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, combined
|-
| [[1984 Winter Olympics|1984]]
| {{flagicon|Yugoslavia}} [[Sarajevo|Sarajevo, Yugoslavia]]
| [[Debbie Armstrong]]&lt;br&gt;[[Christin Cooper]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bill Johnson (skier)|Bill Johnson]]&lt;br&gt;Phil Mahre&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Mahre]]
| Gold, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Gold, downhill&lt;br&gt;Gold, slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, slalom
|-
| [[1992 Winter Olympics|1992]]
| {{flagicon|France}} [[Albertville, France]]
| [[Hilary Lindh]]&lt;br&gt;[[Diann Roffe]]
| Silver, downhill&lt;br&gt;Silver, giant slalom
|-
| [[1994 Winter Olympics|1994]]
| {{flagicon|Norway}} [[Lillehammer, Norway]]
| [[Tommy Moe]]&lt;br&gt;Diann Roffe-Steinrotter&lt;br&gt;[[Picabo Street]]
| Gold, downhill; silver, [[super G]]&lt;br&gt;Gold, super G&lt;br&gt;Silver, downhill
|-
| [[1998 Winter Olympics|1998]]
| {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Nagano, Japan]]
| Picabo Street
| Gold, super G
|-
| [[2002 Winter Olympics|2002]]
| {{flagicon|United States}} [[Salt Lake City|Salt Lake City, Utah, USA]]
| [[Bode Miller]]
| Silver, combined; silver, giant slalom
|- 
| [[2006 Winter Olympics|2006]]
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Torino, Italy]]
| [[Julia Mancuso]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ted Ligety]]
| Gold, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Gold, combined
|- 
| [[2010 Winter Olympics|2010]]
| {{flagicon|Canada}} [[Vancouver, Canada]]
| [[Lindsey Vonn]]&lt;br&gt;Julia Mancuso&lt;br&gt;Bode Miller&lt;br&gt;[[Andrew Weibrecht]]
| Gold, downhill; bronze, super-G&lt;br&gt;Silver, downhill; silver, super combined&lt;br&gt;Gold, super combined; Silver, super G; bronze, downhill&lt;br&gt;Bronze, super-G
|}

===FIS World Alpine Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Location
! Athletes
! Medals
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1954|1954]]
| {{flagicon|Sweden}} [[Are, Sweden]] 
| [[Jannette Burr]]
| Bronze, giant slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1958|1958]]
| {{flagicon|Austria}} [[Bad Gastein|Bad Gastein, Austria]]
| [[Sally Deaver]]
| Silver, giant slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1962|1962]]
| {{flagicon|France}} [[Chamonix, France]]
| [[Barbara Ferries]]&lt;br&gt;[[Joan Hannah]]
| Bronze, downhill&lt;br&gt;Bronze, giant slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1966|1966]]
| {{flagicon|Chile}} [[Portillo, Chile]]
| [[Penny McCoy]]
| Bronze, slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1970|1970]]
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Val Gardena|Val Gardena, Italy]]
| Billy Kidd&lt;br&gt;Barbara Cochran&lt;br&gt;[[Marilyn Cochran]]
| Gold, combined; bronze, slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, slalom&lt;br&gt;Bronze, combined
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1978|1978]]
| {{flagicon|West Germany}} [[Garmisch-Partenkirchen|Garmisch-Partenkirchen, West Germany]]
| [[Pete Patterson]]
| Bronze, combined
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1982|1982]]
| {{flagicon|Austria}} [[Schladming|Schladming, Austria]]
| Christin Cooper&lt;br&gt;Steve Mahre&lt;br&gt;Cindy Nelson
| Silver, slalom; silver, giant slalom; bronze, combined&lt;br&gt;Gold, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, downhill
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1985|1985]]
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Bormio|Bormio, Italy]]
| [[Doug Lewis (skier)|Doug Lewis]]&lt;br&gt;Diann Roffe&lt;br&gt;[[Tamara McKinney]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eva Twardokens]]
| Bronze, downhill&lt;br&gt;Gold, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Bronze, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Bronze, combined
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1987|1987]]
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Crans-Montana|Crans-Montana, Switzerland]]
| [[Tamara McKinney]]
| Bronze, combined
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1989|1989]]
| {{flagicon|United States}} [[Vail, Colorado|Vail, Colorado, USA]]
| Tamara McKinney
| Gold, combined; bronze, slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1993|1993]]
| {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Morioka, Japan]]
| [[AJ Kitt]]&lt;br&gt;[[Julie Parisien]]&lt;br&gt;Picabo Street
| Bronze, downhill&lt;br&gt;Silver, slalom&lt;br&gt;Silver, combined
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1996|1996]]
| {{flagicon|Spain}} [[Sierra Nevada, Spain]]
| Hilary Lindh&lt;br&gt;Picabo Street
| Bronze, downhill&lt;br&gt;Gold, downhill; bronze, super G
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 1997|1997]]
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Sestriere|Sestriere, Italy]]
| Hilary Lindh
| Gold, downhill
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 2001|2001]] 
| {{flagicon|Austria}} [[St. Anton|St. Anton, Austria]]
| [[Daron Rahlves]]
| Gold, super G
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 2003|2003]] 
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} St. Moritz, Switzerland
| [[Kirsten Clark]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jonna Mendes]]&lt;br&gt;Bode Miller&lt;br&gt;[[Erik Schlopy]]
| Silver, super G&lt;br&gt;Bronze, super G&lt;br&gt;Gold, giant slalom; combined; silver, super G&lt;br&gt;Bronze, giant slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 2005|2005]]
| {{flagicon|Italy}} Bormio/[[Santa Caterina di Valfurva|Santa Caterina]], Italy
| Julia Mancuso&lt;br&gt;Bode Miller&lt;br&gt;Daron Rahlves
| Bronze, super G; bronze, giant slalom&lt;br&gt;Gold, downhill; gold, super G&lt;br&gt;Silver, downhill; Bronze, giant slalom
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 2007|2007]]
| {{flagicon|Sweden}} Are, Sweden
| [[Lindsey Kildow]]&lt;br&gt;Julia Mancuso
| Silver, downhill; silver, super G&lt;br&gt;Silver, [[super combined]]
|-
| [[FIS Alpine World Ski Championships 2009|2009]]
| {{flagicon|France}} [[Val d'Isère|Val d'Isère, France]]
| [[Lindsey Vonn]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ted Ligety]]
| Gold, downhill; Gold, super G&lt;br&gt;Bronze, giant slalom
|}

===FIS Alpine World Cup===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Athletes
! Titles
|-
| [[1969 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1969]]
| Marilyn Cochran
| Giant slalom champion
|-
| [[1978 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1978]]
| Phil Mahre 
| 2nd in overall
|-
| [[1979 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1979]]
| Phil Mahre
| 3rd in overall
|-
| [[1980 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1980]]
| Phil Mahre
| 3rd in overall
|-
| [[1981 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1981]]
| Phil Mahre&lt;br&gt;Tamara McKinney
| Overall champion&lt;br&gt;Giant slalom champion
|-
| [[1982 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1982]]
| Christin Cooper&lt;br&gt;Phil Mahre&lt;br&gt;Steve Mahre
| 3rd in overall&lt;br&gt;Overall, slalom &amp; giant slalom champion&lt;br&gt;3rd in overall
|-
| [[1983 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1983]]
| Tamara McKinney&lt;br&gt;Phil Mahre
| Overall &amp; giant slalom champion&lt;br&gt;Overall &amp; giant slalom champion
|-
| [[1984 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1984]]
| Tamara McKinney
| 3rd in overall, slalom champion
|-
| [[1995 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1995]]
| Picabo Street
| Downhill champion
|-
| [[1996 Alpine Skiing World Cup|1996]]
| Picabo Street
| Downhill champion
|-
| [[2003 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2003]]
| Bode Miller
| Combined champion
|-
| [[2004 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2004]]
| Bode Miller
| Giant slalom &amp; combined champion
|-
| [[2005 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2005]]
| Bode Miller
| Overall &amp; super G champion
|-
| [[2006 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2006]]
| Bode Miller
| 3rd in overall
|-
| [[2007 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2007]]
| Julia Mancuso&lt;br&gt;Bode Miller
| 3rd in overall&lt;br&gt;Super G champion
|-
| [[2008 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2008]]
| Lindsey Vonn&lt;br&gt;Ted Ligety&lt;br&gt;Bode Miller
| Overall &amp; Downhill champion, 2nd in combined&lt;br&gt;Giant slalom champion&lt;br&gt;Overall &amp; Super Combined champion
|-
| [[2009 Alpine Skiing World Cup|2009]]
| Lindsey Vonn&lt;br&gt;Ted Ligety
| Overall, Downhill, &amp; Super G champion, 2nd in Combined, 3rd in Slalom&lt;br&gt;3rd in Giant Slalom

|}

== US Freestyle Highlights ==
===Olympic Winter Games===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1988 Olympic Games (non-medal exhibition event)
| {{flagicon|Canada}} Calgary, Canada
| [[Melanie Palenik]]
| 1st Aerials
|-
| 1988 Olympic Games (non-medal exhibition event)
| {{flagicon|Canada}} Calgary, Canada
| [[Jan Bucher]]
| 2nd Ballet
|-
| 1988 Olympic Games (non-medal exhibition event)
| {{flagicon|Canada}} Calgary, Canada
| [[Lane Spina]]
| Silver - Acrobatic Skiing
|-
| 1992 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|France}} Albertville, France
| [[Donna Weinbrecht]]
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 1992 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|France}} Albertville, France
| [[Nelson Carmichael]]
| Bronze Moguls
|-
| 1992 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|France}} Albertville, France
| Lane Spina
| Bronze - Acrobatic Skiing
|-
| 1992 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|France}} Albertville, France
| [[Sharon Petzold]]
| 3rd Ballet (non-medal exhibition event)
|-
| 1994 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Norway}} Lillehammer, Norway
| [[Liz McIntyre (skier)|Liz McIntyre]]
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 1998 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Nagano, Japan
| [[Eric Bergoust]]
| Gold Aerials
|-
| 1998 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Nagano, Japan
| [[Jonny Moseley]]
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 1998 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Nagano, Japan
| [[Nikki Stone]]
| Gold Aerials
|-
| 2002 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|United States}} Salt Lake City, Utah
| [[Joe Pack]]
| Silver Aerials
|-
| 2002 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|United States}} Salt Lake City, Utah
| [[Travis Mayer]]
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 2002 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|United States}} Salt Lake City, Utah
| [[Shannon Bahrke]]
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 2006 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Italy}} Torino, Italy
| [[Toby Dawson]]
| Bronze Moguls
|-
|2010 Olympic Games
|{{flagicon|CAN}} Vancouver, Canada
|[[Hannah Kearney]]
| Gold Moguls
|-
|2010 Olympic Games
|{{flagicon|CAN}} Vancouver, Canada
|[[Shannon Bahrke]]
| Bronze Moguls
|-
|2010 Olympic Games
|{{flagicon|CAN}} Vancouver, Canada
|[[Bryon Wilson]]
| Bronze Moguls
|}

===World Freestyle Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1986 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} Tignes, France
| Mary Jo Tiampo
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 1986 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} Tignes, France
| Maria Quintana
| Gold Aerials
|-
| 1986 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} Tignes, France
| Jan Bucher
| Gold Ballet
|-
| 1986 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} Tignes, France
| Lane Spina
| Silver - Acrobatic Skiing
|-
| 1986 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} Tignes, France
| John Witt
| Silver Combined
|-
| 1986 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} Tignes, France
| Hayley Wolff
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 1989 World Championships
| {{flagicon|West Germany}} Oberjoch, West Germany
| Jan Bucher
| Gold Ballet
|-
| 1989 World Championships
| {{flagicon|West Germany}} Oberjoch, West Germany
| Melanie Palenik
| Gold Combined, Bronze Aerials
|-
| 1989 World Championships
| {{flagicon|West Germany}} Oberjoch, West Germany
| Scott Ogren
| Silver Combined
|-
| 1989 World Championships
| {{flagicon|West Germany}} Oberjoch, West Germany
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Lane Spina
| Gold - Acrobatic Skiing
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Ellen Breen
| Gold Ballet
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Jan Bucher
| Silver Ballet
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Chuck Martin
| Bronze Moguls
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Dave Valenti
| Bronze Aerials
|-
| 1991 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Lake Placid, New York
| Kriste Porter
| Bronze Combined
|-
| 1993 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Austria}} Altenmarkt, Austria
| Ellen Breen
| Gold Ballet
|-
| 1993 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Austria}} Altenmarkt, Austria
| Trace Worthington
| Silver Aerials
|-
| 1993 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Austria}} Altenmarkt, Austria
| Lane Spina
| Bronze - Acrobatic Skiing
|-
| 1993 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Austria}} Altenmarkt, Austria
| Kriste Porter
| Bronze Aerials, Bronze Combined
|-
| 1995 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} LaClusaz, France
| Trace Worthington
| Gold Aerials, Gold Combined
|-
| 1995 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} LaClusaz, France
| Nikki Stone
| Gold Aerials
|-
| 1995 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} LaClusaz, France
| Kriste Porter
| Gold Combined
|-
| 1995 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} LaClusaz, France
| Ellen Breen
| Silver Ballet
|-
| 1995 World Championships
| {{flagicon|France}} LaClusaz, France
| Jonny Moseley
| Bronze Combined
|-
| 1997 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Nagano, Japan
| Eric Bergoust
| Silver Aerials
|-
| 1997 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Nagano, Japan
| Ian Edmondson
| Silver Acro
|-
| 1997 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Nagano, Japan
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 1999 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} Meiringen, Switzerland
| Ann Battelle
| Gold Moguls, Bronze Dual Moguls
|-
| 1999 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} Meiringen, Switzerland
| Ian Edmondson
| Gold Acro
|-
| 1999 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} Meiringen, Switzerland
| Eric Bergoust
| Gold Aerials
|-
| 1999 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} Meiringen, Switzerland
| Nikki Stone
| Bronze Aerials
|-
| 1999 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} Meiringen, Switzerland
| Joe Pack
| Bronze Aerials
|-
| 2001 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Canada}} Whistler, Canada
| Joe Pack
| Bronze Aerials
|-
| 2003 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Deer Valley, Utah
| Jeremy Bloom
| Gold Dual Moguls, Silver Moguls
|-
| 2003 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Deer Valley, Utah
| Michelle Roark
| Silver Moguls
|-
| 2003 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Deer Valley, Utah
| Toby Dawson
| Bronze Moguls, Bronze Dual Moguls
|-
| 2003 World Championships
| {{flagicon|United States}} Deer Valley, Utah
| Shannon Bahrke
| Bronze Dual Moguls
|-
| 2005 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Finland}} Ruka, Finland
| Nate Roberts
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 2005 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Finland}} Ruka, Finland
| Hannah Kearney
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 2005 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Finland}} Ruka, Finland
| Toby Dawson
| Gold Dual Moguls
|-
| 2005 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Finland}} Ruka, Finland
| Kristi Leskinen
| Silver Halfpipe
|-
| 2005 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Finland}} Ruka, Finland
| Jeremy Bloom
| Bronze Dual Moguls
|-
| 2007 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Italy}} Madonna di Campiglio, Italy
| Shannon Bahrke
| Silver Dual Moguls
|-
| 2007 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Italy}} Madonna di Campiglio, Italy
| Nate Roberts
| Bronze Moguls
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Inawashiro, Japan
| Patrick Deneen
| Gold Moguls
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Inawashiro, Japan
| Ryan St Onge
| Gold Aerials
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Inawashiro, Japan
| Jennifer Hudak
| Bronze Halfpipe
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Inawashiro, Japan
| Hannah Kearney
| Bronze Dual Moguls
|}

===Freestyle World Cup===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1978
| Marion Post
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1978
| Kerri Ballard
| Aerials Champion
|-
| 1978
| Genia Fuller
| Grand Prix Champion
|-
| 1979
| Bob Howard
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1979
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1979
| Lea Hillgren
| Aerials Champion
|-
| 1980
| Bob Howard
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1980
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1980
| Hayley Wolff
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1981
| Bob Howard
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1981
| Frank Beddor
| Grand Prix Champion
|-
| 1981
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1981
| Hayley Wolff
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1982
| Ian Edmondson
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1982
| Frank Beddor
| Grand Prix Champion
|-
| 1982
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1982
| Hayley Wolff
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1983
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1983
| Hayley Wolff
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1984
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1984
| Hilary Engisch
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1985
| Mary Jo Tiampo
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1986
| Steve Desovich
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1986
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1986
| Mary Jo Tiampo
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1988
| Nelson Carmichael
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1989
| Nelson Carmichael
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1989
| Jan Bucher
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1990
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1991
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1992
| Trace Worthington
| Combined Champion
|-
| 1992
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1993
| Trace Worthington
| Combined Champion
|-
| 1993
| Ellen Breen
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1994
| Ellen Breen
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1994
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1995
| Trace Worthington
| Aerials Champion, Combined Champion
|-
| 1995
| Ellen Breen
| Ballet Champion
|-
| 1995
| Nikki Stone
| Aerials Champion
|-
| 1996
| Jonny Moseley
| Combined Champion
|-
| 1996
| Donna Weinbrecht
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1998
| Jonny Moseley
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1998
| Nikki Stone
| Aerials Champion
|-
| 1999
| Anne Battelle
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 1999
| Michelle Roark
| Dual Moguls Champion
|-
| 2000
| Anne Battelle
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 2001
| Eric Bergoust
| Aerials Champion, 2nd overall standings
|-
| 2001
| Joe Pack
| 3rd overall standings
|-
| 2002
| Jeremy Bloom
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 2002
| Eric Bergoust
| Aerials Champion
|-
| 2003
| Travis Cabral
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 2003
| Shannon Bahrke
| Moguls Champion
|-
| 2005
| Jeremy Bloom
| Overall Champion, Moguls Champion
|-
| 2005
| Jeret Peterson
| Aerials Champion
|-
| 2007
| Jeret Peterson
| 3rd overall standings
|-
| 2007
| Jessica Cumming
| Halfpipe Champion
|}

== US Cross Country Highlights ==
===Olympic Winter Games===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1976 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Austria}} [[Innsbruck, Austria]]
| [[Bill Koch (skier)|Bill Koch]]
| Silver 30&amp;nbsp;km
|-
| 2002 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|United States}} Salt Lake City, Utah
| [[John Bauer (skier)|John Bauer]], [[Kris Freeman]], [[Justin Wadsworth]], [[Carl Swenson]]
| 5th 4x10km Relay - Historic best US Olympic relay finish
|-
| 2006 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Turin, Italy]]
| [[Kikkan Randall]]
| 9th 1.1&amp;nbsp;km Classic Sprint - Historic Best US Women's Olympic or World Championships Sprint Result
|}

===World Cross Country Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1982 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Norway}} [[Oslo]], Norway
| Bill Koch
| Bronze 30&amp;nbsp;km
|-
| 2003 Under-23 Championships
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Valdidentro, Italy]]
| Kris Freeman
| Gold 30&amp;nbsp;km Classic
|-
| 2003 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Switzerland}} [[Lausanne, Switzerland]]
| Kris Freeman
| 4th 15K Classic
|-
| 2007 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Sapporo, Japan]]
| Andy Newell
| 5th in Classic Sprint - Historic Best US Worlds Sprint Result
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Czech Republic}} [[Liberec]], Czech Republic
| Kikkan Randall
| Silver in Individual Sprint Freestyle - First ever medal for an American Woman
|}

===Cross Country World Cup===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1976
| Bill Koch
| Tied for 3rd in World Cup Overall
|-
| 1982
| Bill Koch
| World Cup Champion
|-
| 1983
| Bill Koch
| 3rd in World Cup Overall
|-
| 2006
| Andy Newell
| 3rd in 1&amp;nbsp;km Freestyle Sprint in Changchun, China - First US Man on a World Cup Podium Since 1983
|-
| 2007
| Kikkan Randall
| 3rd in 1.2&amp;nbsp;km Sprint at Rybinsk, Russia (January 21, 2007)- First US Woman on a World Cup Podium 
|}

== US Nordic Combined Highlights ==
===Olympic Winter Games===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1932 Olympic Games
| {{flagicon|United States}} [[Lake Placid, New York]]
| Rolf Monsen
| 9th in K100/10&amp;nbsp;km Individual - Historic Best US Olympic Nordic Combined Individual Finish
|-
| 2002 Olympic Games 
| {{flagicon|United States}} Salt Lake City, Utah
| Bill Demong, Matt Dayton, Johnny Spillane, Todd Lodwick
| 4th in K90/4x5 Team Relay - Historic Best US Olympic Nordic Combined Result
|-
| 2010 Olympic Games
| {{flagicon|CAN}} Vancouver, British Columbia
| Bill Demong
| Gold in Individual Large Hill/10km
|-
| 2010 Olympic Games
| {{flagicon|CAN}} Vancouver, British Columbia
| Johnny Spillane
| Silver in Individual Large Hill/10km, Silver in Individual Normal Hill/10km
|-
| 2010 Olympic Games
| {{flagicon|CAN}} Vancouver, British Columbia
| Brett Camerota, Todd Lodwick, Bill Demong, Johnny Spillane
| Silver in Team Large Hill/4 x 5km
|}

===World Nordic Combined Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 2003 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Italy}} [[Val di Fiemme]], [[Italy]]
| Johnny Spillane
| Gold K120/7.5&amp;nbsp;km Sprint - Historic First US Nordic Combined Medal Olympics or Worlds
|-
| 2007 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Japan}} Sapporo, Japan
| Bill Demong
| Silver HS100/15&amp;nbsp;km Individual
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Czech Republic}} Liberec, Czech Republic
| Todd Lodwick
| Gold HS100/10&amp;nbsp;km Mass Start
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Czech Republic}} Liberec, Czech Republic
| Todd Lodwick
| Gold HS100/10&amp;nbsp;km Normal Hill
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Czech Republic}} Liberec, Czech Republic
| Bill Demong
| Bronze HS100/10&amp;nbsp;km Normal Hill
|-
| 2009 World Championships
| {{flagicon|Czech Republic}} Liberec, Czech Republic
| Bill Demong
| Gold HS134/10&amp;nbsp;km Large Hill
|}

===Nordic Combined World Cup===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 2008 
| Bill Demong
| 3rd in World Cup Overall - Historic Best US Result (Demong also was 3rd in 2009)
|}

== US Jumping Highlights ==
===Olympic Winter Games===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! Place
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1924 Olympic Games (doubled as World Championships)
| {{flagicon|France}} Chamonix, France
| Anders Haugen
| Bronze Large Hill (medal not awarded until 1974 due to scoring error)
|}

===Ski Jumping World Cup===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Athlete
! Highlights
|-
| 1981
| John Broman
| First US World Cup victory - February 22, 1981, [[Thunder Bay, Ontario]]
|}
==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.usskiteam.com/ U.S. Ski Team] official site
*[http://www.ussa.org/ U.S. Ski &amp; Snowboard Association] official site
*[http://www.fis-ski.com/ International Ski Federation]
*[http://www.facebook.com/usskiteam U.S. Ski Team] Facebook page

{{USNationalTeams}}

[[Category:Skiing in the United States]]
[[Category:Sports governing bodies of the United States|Skiing]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
