<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="414897" ns="0" title="America&#039;s Funniest Home Videos"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television
 | show_name             = America's Funniest Home Videos
 | image                 = [[File:AFHV logo.png|200px]]
 | genre                 = [[Reality television]]
 | format                = Funny videos
 | camera                = [[Videotape]]; [[Multi-camera setup|Multi-camera]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(studio segments)&lt;/small&gt;
 | creator               = [[Vin Di Bona]]
 | executive_producer    = Vin Di Bona
 | writer                = [[Todd Thicke]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(supervising writer)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Erik Lohla&lt;br&gt;Mike Palleschi&lt;br&gt;Jordan Schatz
 | director              = Vin Di Bona
 | presenter                = [[Bob Saget]] (1989–1997; guest, 2009)&lt;br&gt;[[John Fugelsang]] &amp; [[Daisy Fuentes]] (1998–1999)&lt;br&gt;[[Tom Bergeron]] (2001–present)
 | narrated              = [[Ernie Anderson]] (1989–1995)&lt;br&gt;[[Gary Owens]] (1995–1997)&lt;br&gt;[[Jess Harnell]] (1998–present)
 | theme_music_composer  = Dan Slider
 | opentheme             = &quot;The Funny Things You Do&quot;, performed by Jill Colucci (1989–1996),&lt;br&gt;performed by Peter Hix &amp; Terry Wood (1996–1997),&lt;br&gt;Rearranged ska/reggae instrumental (1998–present)
 | company               = [[Vin Di Bona Productions]]&lt;br&gt;[[ABC Entertainment]]
 | distributor           = [[MTM Enterprises]] (1995–1997)&lt;br&gt;[[20th Television]] (1998–2001)&lt;br&gt;[[Disney-ABC Domestic Television|Buena Vista Television]] (2001–2007)&lt;br&gt;[[Disney-ABC Domestic Television]] (2007-present)
 | picture_format        = [[480i]] ([[SDTV]]) &lt;br&gt; [[720p]] ([[HDTV]])&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(home videos [[Video scaler|upscaled]] to [[widescreen]])&lt;/small&gt;
 | audio_format          = [[Stereo]]
 | runtime               = 60 minutes (1989 and 1999–2000 specials; 2001–present, series)&lt;br&gt;30 minutes (1990–1999, series)
 | country               = [[United States]]
 | language              = [[English language|English]]
 | network               = [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]
 | first_aired           = {{start date|1989|11|26}} &lt;small&gt;(as a special)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{start date|1990|1|14}} &lt;small&gt;(as a series)&lt;/small&gt;
 | last_aired            = present
 | num_seasons           = 21
 | num_episodes          = 450+
 | related               = ''[[America's Funniest People]]'' (1990–1994)&lt;br&gt;''World's Funniest Videos'' (1996)
 | website               = http://abc.go.com/primetime/afv/index?pn=index
}}

'''''America's Funniest Home Videos''''' (often simply abbreviated to '''''AFHV''''', or its on-air abbreviation '''''AFV''''') is an American [[Reality show|reality]] television program on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] in which viewers are able to send in humorous homemade videotapes. The most common videos usually feature [[slapstick]] physical comedy arising from incidents, accidents and mishaps. Other popular videos include humorous situations involving [[pet]]s or children, while some are staged practical jokes and various forms of act. The show is based on the Japanese series ''[[Fun TV with Kato-chan and Ken-chan]]'', which aired on the [[Tokyo Broadcasting System]].&lt;ref&gt;&lt;refname=AFV closing credits&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally airing as a special on November 26, 1989, it debuted a regular weekly series on January 14, 1990. First hosted by [[Bob Saget]] for the initial 1989 special and the show's first eight seasons, then by [[John Fugelsang]] and [[Daisy Fuentes]] for its ninth and tenth seasons; the series has been hosted by [[Tom Bergeron]], currently the show's longest-serving host, since 2001. ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' is currently in its 22nd season, which began on October 2, 2011.

==Synopsis==
Executive produced by [[Vin Di Bona]], with co-executive producers [[Todd Thicke]] and Michele Nasraway,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://abc.go.com/primetime/afv/index?pn=about
|title = America's Funniest Home Videos – About the Show..
|accessdate = 2007-08-27
|archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5RPKaTE3S
|archivedate = 2007-08-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is currently the longest-running prime time entertainment program on ABC. It is based on the [[Tokyo Broadcasting System]] show ''[[Fun TV with Kato-chan and Ken-chan]]'', which featured a segment in which viewers were invited to send in [[video clip]]s from their [[home movies]]; Vin Di Bona Productions pays a royalty fee to the Tokyo Broadcasting System for the use of the format.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-18306720.html Littleton, Cynthia. &quot;Putting the fun in 'Home Videos'; Vincent John Di Bona, executive producer of television program ''America's Funniest Home Videos''], ''[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]]'', May 20, 1996. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; Contestants can either send their videos in via mail on [[DVD]] or [[VHS]], or, since 2008, upload them onto ABC's official website.

Due to its very low cost, the format has since been reproduced around the world, and AFV-inspired TV specials and series continue to emerge periodically in the United States. American television series inspired by ''AFV'''s format that are not related to the series itself include ''[[The Planet's Funniest Animals]]'', ''[[The World's Funniest!]]'', ''[[The World's Funniest Moments]]'', ''[[Funniest Pets and People]]'' and ''[[It Only Hurts When I Laugh (TV Series)|It Only Hurts When I Laugh]]''; however, most of the series inspired by ''AFV'' (with the minor exception of ''The Planet's Funniest Animals'') have not matched the success of ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' and have not lasted as long. Several local television stations, even those not affiliated with ABC, also developed special funny home video segments in their newscasts during the early 1990s, inspired by the series.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-3995573.html Scott Williams. &quot;Local TV getting into 'Funniest Videos' act&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', April 26, 1990. Retrieved March 8, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many videos are range from a few to a couple of seconds and are mostly related to the host's monologues. Videos usually feature people and animals getting into humorous to dangerous accidents caught on camera. A group of screeners view the submitted tapes, giving them a grade (on a scale of 1-10) based on that particular tape's humor; the videos deemed funniest by the screeners then go on to the show's producers, then is turned over to Di Bona and another producer for final approval.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-8162596.html Susan Bickelhaupt, Globe Staff. &quot;'Funniest Home Videos' Outstrips '60 Minutes'.&quot;], ''[[The Boston Globe]]'', February 28, 1990. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; Home video material that involves staged accidents, or/and adults, children or babies getting seriously injured or the abuse of animals are generally not accepted, and will not appear on the show.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-3995728.html Ernest Tucker. &quot;Saget aims to clip hurtful video bits&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', April 27, 1990. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;

Every week, three videos are chosen by the producers and voted on by the studio audience. The winner wins [[US$]]10,000, and is in the running for the $100,000 prize at the end of the season, while the runner-up receives $3,000, and third place banks $2,000. Very early in the show's run, the second and third prizes were a new TV and VCR and a new camcorder, respectively. On the initial hour-long special, the grand prize was $5,000 with second and third places winning a new camcorder; the producer picked the winner, with no audience voting. Periodically beginning with the Tom Bergeron run of the series, the $100,000 winner at each season's final $100,000 contest will also win a free vacation package, supplied by either [[Adventures by Disney]] or [[Disney Vacation Club]], in addition to the monetary prize.

The show produced a [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] titled ''[[America's Funniest People]]'', which began in 1990 and lasted until 1994. Another short-lived spinoff was created in 1996 with ''World’s Funniest Videos'', which was cancelled after its first season. Show creator Vin Di Bona also created two series featuring home videos that are largely culled from those seen on ''AFHV'' and ''America's Funniest People'': the first-run syndication series ''[[That's Funny]]'', which ran from 2004 to 2006&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-113230359.html Dempsey, John. &quot;Di Bona's 'Funny' will get gags gig&quot;], ''[[Variety (magazine)|Daily Variety]]'', January 23, 2004. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;, and the [[ABC Family|Fox Family Channel]] series ''[[Show Me The Funny]]'', which ran from 1998 to 2000. Many of the clips have been used internationally in various comedy compilation programs, with changes such as dubbing and subtitling. The title of the show is usually changed and the studio segments are omitted.

According to the closing credits of each episode, most of the videos have been edited for length due to time constraints. In addition according to the contest plugs, family members (both immediate or relatives) of employees of [[Vin Di Bona Productions]], [[ABC, Inc.]], its corporate parent [[The Walt Disney Company]] and their related subsidiaries are ineligible for the show's contests and prizes.

On October 3, 2010, beginning with the 21st season premiere,&lt;ref name=&quot;thefutoncritic1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefutoncritic.com/showatch/americas-funniest-home-videos/ |title=Shows A-Z - america's funniest home videos on abc |publisher=TheFutonCritic.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' began broadcasting in high definition. Many of the videos, which are largely shot using standard definition camcorders, are now [[Stretch-o-Vision|stretched horizontally]] to fit 16:9 screens, instead of using [[pillarboxing]]. 

== Ratings ==
=== Season averages ===
''America's Funniest Home Videos'' became an instant hit with audiences, with the original special in November 1989 averaged a 17.7 rating and 25 share, finishing at ninth place in the Nielsen ratings that week. When it debuted as a weekly Sunday night series in January 1990, the show averaged a 18.0 rating/27 share, finishing at 16th place.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-13665606.html Coe, Steve. &quot;Home is where the video is; 'America's Funniest Home Videos' is one of TV's most successful reality shows&quot;], ''[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]]'', April 12, 1993. Retrieved March 8, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; It placed within Nielsen's Top 5 highest-rated weekly series within weeks of its debut&lt;ref name=&quot;Big&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D8113AF93AA25751C0A966958260 ABC's 'Home Videos' Pays Off Big], ''[[The New York Times]]'', February 19, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;; by March 1990, ''AFHV'' became the #1 primetime series for a short time, causing CBS' ''[[60 Minutes]]'' to be unseated for the top spot in the Nielsen ratings for the first time in 12 years. ''AFHV'' finished the 1989-1990 season in the Top 10 watched shows, with an approximate average of 38 million viewers &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.audiencesusa.com/article-35909003.html |title=RETRO 89-90 : le classement intégral de la saison 89-90 - AudiencesUSA.com : Audiences, actu et programmation de la télé US |language={{fr icon}} |publisher=AudiencesUSA.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; for each episode.

''AFHV'' finished the 2009-2010 season at the 55th rank, with an approximate average of 7.52 million viewers, and finished in 69th in viewers 18-49, with 2.0/6.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Andreeva |first=Nellie |url=http://www.deadline.com/2010/05/full-series-rankings-for-the-2009-10-broadcast-season/ |title=Full Series Rankings For The 2009-10 Broadcast Season – |publisher=Deadline.com |date=2010-05-27 |accessdate=2010-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Bob Saget (1989–1997)===
The show debuted on November 26, 1989 as an hour-long special,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Moran
  | first = James
  | title = There's No Place Like Home Video
  | publisher = University of Minnesota Press
  | year = 2002
  | isbn = 0-8166-3800-4
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; produced by Vin Di Bona and Steve Paskay, with actor/comedian [[Bob Saget]] (then starring in the ABC sitcom ''[[Full House]]'') as host. Saget was assisted in hosting the special by actress [[Kellie Martin]], then the star of fellow ABC series ''[[Life Goes On (TV series)|Life Goes On]]'', which would be the [[lead-in]] show to ''AFHV'' in its early seasons. Prior to the airing of the initial special, in the fall of 1989, Vin Di Bona Productions took out ads in national magazines such as ''[[TV Guide]]'', asking people to send in their home videos featuring funny or amazing moments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-3988564.html [[Richard Roeper]]. &quot;The camcorder never blinks&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', March 11, 1990. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally intended as a one-off special, it had became an unexpected hit, causing ABC to place an episode order for the show turning it into a regular weekly half-hour primetime series&lt;ref name=&quot;Big&quot;/&gt;, it made its debut as a series on January 14, 1990.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1105148.html Patricia Brennan. &quot;NBC's 'Grand'; 'Eyes on Prize II'.&quot;], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', January 14, 1990. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ernie Anderson]] served as announcer; once Anderson became too ill to continue, [[Gary Owens]] took over as announcer in 1995 (though Anderson briefly returned until his death in 1997). Besides hosting the series, Saget also served as a writer for the series, alongside Todd Thicke and Bob Arnott. The success of ''AFHV'' led to a spinoff called ''[[America's Funniest People]]'', hosted by Saget's ''[[Full House]]'' co-star [[Dave Coulier]] (and co-hosted by actress/producer [[Arleen Sorkin]] for the first two seasons, then model [[Tawny Kitaen]] for the final two), focusing on videos featuring people doing celebrity impressions, committing pranks and doing short amateur comedy routines, among other things.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4001399.html Ernest Tucker. &quot;'Video' host rewinds pal's format&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', June 3, 1990. Retrieved March 8, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;

From the premiere of the ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' until the start of the fifth season, it aired Sunday nights at 8 p.m. [[Eastern Time Zone|ET]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1226954.html John Carmody. &quot;The TV Column&quot;], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', December 6, 1989. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;; beginning with the fifth season, the show started the Sunday [[primetime]] lineup on ABC, airing at 7 p.m. ET, followed by ''America's Funniest People'' at 7:30 p.m. ET as part of an hour of funny home videos.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC153DF932A25756C0A965958260 Bill Carter. Coming Next: New ABC Prime Time], ''[[The New York Times]]'', May 11, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; Saget always ended each episode with the phrase &quot;Keep those cameras safely rolling&quot;, and saying something to his wife who was (implied to be) watching the show.

[[Image:AFHV logo (1989-1997).jpg|175px|thumb|left|The original logo, used from 1989-1997.]]
Beginning about the middle of the first season, the show began featuring the &quot;Assignment America&quot; segment; which called for a series of videos to be sent in (collected or made) pertaining to a specific theme. Another segment introduced in the Saget era called &quot;Backwards Classics&quot; shows videos being played in reverse. Since the show's debut as a regular series, the show routinely includes two to three times per episode, a montage of themed videos set to a particular song, better known as the &quot;Music Montage&quot;. In the fifth season, an animated sidekick was introduced named &quot;Stretchy McGillicuddy&quot;, who was known for trying to tease Bob and other crazy things, one episode in the fifth season had him on the two large TV monitors on both sides of the set, and Bob had to turn him off with a remote. His catchphrase was: &quot;Don't get a little touchy Bob, I'm just a little stretchy!&quot; He was dropped at the end of the seventh season. His voice was supplied by [[Danny Mann]]. [[Johnny Carson]] made both the show and Saget regular targets of his monologues on ''[[The Tonight Show]]''.

In 1994, ABC canceled ''America's Funniest People'' after four seasons due to declining ratings, and had to decide what to do with the Sunday night 7:30 p.m. ET slot now vacant. After trying out the short-lived sitcom ''[[On Our Own (1994 TV series)|On Our Own]]'' in the 7:30 p.m. slot after ''AFHV'' during the 1994-95 season&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4228101.html Lon Grahnke. &quot;ABC Saves 'Superman,' Gives 'Coach' New Night This Fall.&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', May 10, 1994. Retrieved March 07, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;, ABC then later chose to expand the show to one hour with back-to-back airings, first showing that week's new episode for the first half-hour and then showing a repeat from a previous season to fill the remaining time. On February 1, 1996, another spinoff of ''AFHV'' debuted called ''[[World's Funniest Videos]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4314288.html Darel Jevens; Kevin M. Williams. &quot;Funny Video Search Goes Global&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', December 19, 1995. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;; taped at [[Walt Disney World]], this series was also hosted by Coulier, along with actress [[Eva LaRue]]. Paired with a weekly version of the popular ''[[Before They Were Stars]]'' specials on Thursday nights, ''World's Funniest Videos'' focused on funny or amazing home videos from around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-22773591.html Alan Pergament. &quot;ABC Oprts for the Cheap Route and NBC Takes Low Road on Cox Chants&quot;], ''[[Buffalo News]]'', December 21, 1995. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; However due to low ratings, it lasted after only one season&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-18194879.html Coe, Steve. &quot;Fall is in the air; fall 1996 programming for television networks&quot;], ''[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]]'', April 15, 1996. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;; with ABC putting the show on hiatus a few weeks after its debut, and the remaining episodes were burned off that summer. For Saget's final season on ''AFHV'', two new episodes would be shown.

Numerous comedy skits were performed on the set during Saget's tenure as host. The set basically consisted of a living room design, similar to that of a sitcom. The beginning of each episode was tied in with a skit just before the transition was made from the introduction to Saget. This usually consisted of several actors in a fake room (usually in the upper part of the audience section or in another soundstage) pretending to get excited watching ''America's Funniest Home Videos''. This technique was scrapped at the end of the fifth season.

Saget soon grew tired of the repetitive format and was eager to pursue other projects as an actor and director. Producer Di Bona held him to his contract, resulting in a frustrated Saget listlessly going through the motions, constantly getting out of character, and making pointed remarks on the air during his last two seasons. Saget's contract expired in May 1997, and he decided to leave the show afterward.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-83875289.html &quot;News Lite: Names in the News; ABC 'Videos' Gets New Host&quot;], ''[[Los Angeles Daily News]]'', August 2, 1997. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4384250.html &quot;Entertainment Briefs&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', June 12, 1997. Retrieved March 07, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; His former ''Full House'' cast (except for [[Mary-Kate and Ashley Olsen]]) were present in the episode prior to the $100,000 season finale, which was his final episode.

He returned to ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' for a 20th anniversary special edition of the series, which aired on November 29, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Seidman |first=Robert |url=http://tvbythenumbers.com/2009/10/30/abcs-november-sweeps-programming-to-include-hank-the-forgotten-and-eastwick/32124 |title=ABC's November Sweeps programming to include Hank, The Forgotten and Eastwick |publisher=Tvbythenumbers.com |date=2009-10-30 |accessdate=2010-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Saget co-hosted the episode with current host Tom Bergeron.

===Daisy Fuentes and John Fugelsang (1998–1999)===
After Saget's departure from the series, ABC sidelined ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' from the 1997-98 fall network schedule, choosing to bring it back as a mid-season replacement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4399176.html Darel Jevens. &quot;Daisy Fuentes signs to host 'Home Videos'.&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', August 1, 1997. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; The series returned for its ninth season on January 5, 1998, with new hosts and an overhauled look; comedian [[John Fugelsang]] and model-turned-television personality [[Daisy Fuentes]] took over as co-hosts of the show.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4417136.html Lon Grahnke. &quot;News &amp; Reviews&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', November 25, 1997. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jess Harnell]] also succeeded Owens as the show's announcer. The set was also revamped and show began to be alternately called ''AFV'' at this point (though the show officially continued to be titled ''America's Funniest Home Videos'').
 
During this period, the show introduced a segment called &quot;Bad News, Good News,&quot; which shows a video of an accident; then one of the hosts makes a humorous statement about the upside of what happened. This segment continued to appear occasionally until the fourth year of Tom Bergeron's current stint as host. Another notable segment was the &quot;AFV Hall of Fame&quot;, in which a clip is shown, and co-host John Fugelsang reveals the moment of impact (a screen that shows a still picture of that clip) that occurred in it; this segment was scrapped at the end of the tenth season. Also featured was a segment called &quot;Who Would You Like to See...&quot;, in which a random person is asked which celebrity they would like to see involved in a random humorous mishap, with a photo of a celebrity's face posterized over the face of the actual person in the video.

With the Sunday night 7 p.m. ET slot now occupied by Disney films aired as part of ''[[The Wonderful World of Disney]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-72821518.html &quot;Disney May Return to Sundays&quot;], ''[[The Cincinnati Post]]'', November 23, 1996. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;, the show occupied constantly changing slots, from Monday nights&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-156920243.html &quot;Networks Tune in to Midseason with Some New Lineups&quot;], ''[[Albany Times Union]]'', December 2, 1997. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; to Thursday nights&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-577721.html Lisa de Moraes. &quot;For ABC and CBS, a Rewarding Tale of Two Monicas&quot;], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', March 10, 1999. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; to Saturday nights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-19723535.html The Associated Press. &quot;ABC's fall television schedule&quot;], [[Associated Press|AP Online]], May 19, 1998. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; The ratings for the show suffered during this period, and both hosts left the show after two seasons in 1999. Their last episode was taped at the [[House of Blues]] in West Hollywood, California.

===Brief end as regular series and reduction to specials (1999-2000)===
In May 1999, ABC announced that it would discontinue ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' as a regular weekly series&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-64099423.html &quot;Last Call: Here's What Won't Be Back on ABC, The WB&quot;], ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'', May 19, 1999. Retrieved March 6, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;, but the show returned occasionally as a series of specials hosted by various ABC sitcom stars including ''[[The Hughleys]]'' star [[D.L. Hughley]] and ''[[Spin City]]'' star [[Richard Kind]]. The show moved to a much smaller [[soundstage]] and the set featured various video screens and monitors placed on shelves. A special sports version of the show that continues to be re-shown every New Year's Day, and until 2008 aired occasionally before [[NBA playoff]] games with a post 8:30 p.m. ET tip-off, was hosted by [[ESPN]] anchor [[Stuart Scott]]. A special entitled ''America's Funniest Home Videos: Deluxe Uncensored'' was hosted by [[Steve Carell]] and taped on the set from the Fuentes/Fugelsang era. These specials (with the exception of the special sports edition) were not taped in front of a live studio audience, so applause and laugh tracks were used during commercial bumpers and just before, during, and after video packages.

===Tom Bergeron (2001–present)===
In October 2000, ABC announced its decision to return ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' as a regular weekly series, ordering an eleventh season consisting of thirteen episodes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4571525.html &quot;America's Funniest' to return&quot;], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', October 27, 2000. Retrieved March 6, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; On July 20, 2001, the show returned again in its third format, this time with host [[Tom Bergeron]]. By this point, the show was expanded to a full hour-long episode, instead of being aired as two half-hour episodes. The show was now being seen on Friday nights at 8:00 p.m. ET; however, it went off the air for several months due in part to the [[September 11 attacks]] and in part to ABC airing specials and trying a new Friday night line-up. The new Friday night line-up was short-lived, and the show returned in December 2001. In his earlier episodes, Bergeron used the set from the AFV specials that aired in 2000, until the latter part of his first season, when a new set (with a studio audience) was introduced featuring a round video screen with several monitors.

In September 2003, the show returned to the timeslot of Sunday nights at 7:00 p.m. ET, still an hour long (though special episodes occasionally aired on Friday nights until 2007). Unlike Saget, who provided voiceovers to the clips, Bergeron humorously narrates them.

The Bergeron version added new segments, such as &quot;Tom's Home Movies,&quot; where his face is digitally superimposed over the faces on the videos with varying expressions shown to match the person's reaction to their mishaps in the videos (a recurring gag referenced by Bergeron in this segment is on his superimposed head being larger than a person's head would normally be), various audience participation games using funny home videos including &quot;Head, Gut or Groin,&quot; where Tom picks two members of the studio audience to guess whether the person in the video will be hit in the aforementioned three areas of the body (though occasionally, a video in this segment may feature a person getting hit in two of the three areas) in order to win an ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' compilation [[DVD]], and the &quot;slo-mo gizmo&quot;, where a video is played first at normal speed and then again at a slower speed and [[telestrator|telestrated]]. Except in a few episodes, Bergeron always ends each episode with the phrase &quot;If you get it on tape, you could get it in cash&quot;, which was later changed to &quot;Upload to us. Get rich, get famous&quot; by the 2008-09 season.

Other segments introduced in the Tom Bergeron era included &quot;Vs.&quot;, &quot;The Dog/Cat Park&quot;, &quot;AFV Family of the Week&quot;, &quot;Nincompoop Corner&quot;,  &quot;What's Up with the French?&quot; &quot;AFV Dictionary&quot;, &quot;Pick the Real Video&quot;, &quot;A Moment of... Ewww&quot;, &quot;Kid, Cat, or Canine&quot;, What's Behind the Blue Blob&quot;, and  &quot;The Naughty File&quot;. Starting with the 2007–08 season, the series began allowing viewers to upload their funny home videos online at ABC.com, in addition to sending their videos via standard mail.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-174845414.html &quot;America's Funniest Videos Takes Submission Via Internet&quot;], [[PR Newswire]], February 15, 2008. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;

==$100,000 contest==
Near the end of each season, the $10,000 winners from selected episodes are brought back to participate in a contest called to win an additional $100,000. Three $100,000 contests air each season, though only one aired in the first season. During the Saget era, the set would be decorated with balloons, and a revolving gag involved the &quot;money&quot; being guarded in some bizarre way from Saget on-stage, including a security guard or a force field. Once the winner is announced, a marching band would often appear on stage playing the theme song (other times the regular theme would be heard), and balloons are dropped from the ceiling. All of this was scrapped after Saget left the show. 

For the Fuentes/Fugelsang and Bergeron eras, only confetti would be dropped and the regular theme would be heard.

===Voting===
* Saget version: ABC stations (five in the first season, three from 1990 to 1993, and two from 1993 onward) around the country were joined via satellite to cast their votes along with the Los Angeles audience. (The final $100,000 show of Season 2 was decided by a telephone vote)
* Fuentes version (1998–1999): Only the Los Angeles audience voted (although Minneapolis, Minnesota joined via satellite in one episode).
* Bergeron version (2001–present): Viewers log onto [http://www.abc.com abc.com] to cast their votes with the LA audience.

===Other contests===
* 2002 &quot;Battle of the Best&quot;: The Quad Squad ($25,000 and trip to Maui)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Levin |first=Josh |url=http://www.slate.com/id/2148214/ |title=The agonizing journey from America's Funniest Home Videos to YouTube. – By Josh Levin – Slate Magazine |publisher=Slate.com |date=2006-08-24 |accessdate=2009-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2004: Disney Dream Vacation ($100,000 and free vacations to all 11 [[Walt Disney Parks and Resorts|Disney theme parks]] around the world)
* 2006: Dancing Machine ($100,000 and free vacations to 500+ places for 48 years)
* &quot;Funniest Video of All-Time&quot;: The Quad Squad ($250,000)
* 2009: Birthday Blowout ($100,000 and free vacations to 500+ places for 50 years)

==Theme songs==
The first theme was &quot;The Funny Things You Do&quot;, composed by Dan Slider and performed by [[Jill Colucci]], who also wrote the lyrics with Stewart Harris. This version of &quot;The Funny Things You Do&quot; accompanied the opening and closing credits for the first seven seasons. This theme was reused once again for when Tom Bergeron introduced Saget as well as a montage of classic videos from the pilot episode and a segment showcasing Bob Saget's run on the show (the latter segment used the theme's original lyrics) in the ''AFV'' 20th anniversary special, which aired on November 29, 2009. During the final part of the $100,000 shows, bands as well as other artists would play the theme.

During the 1996–97 season (the final season with Saget as host), the theme was revamped (as well as the graphics and animation of the show's intro) featuring a duet of new vocals, Peter Hix (who had previously performed the theme song for ''[[America's Funniest People]]'') and Terry Wood. The new version was also in a different key than the original.

When ''AFHV'' returned for its ninth season with new hosts Daisy Fuentes and John Fugelsang and a completely new look, the current arrangement of &quot;The Funny Things You Do&quot; made its debut. Since that time, the theme has been an instrumental (also composed by Dan Slider) with a faster, ska/reggae beat, with the original key (of the 1989-96 version) restored, making it sound similar to &quot;[[The Impression That I Get]]&quot; by [[The Mighty Mighty Bosstones]]. An alternate version of this theme exists that is stripped of the trumpets (this version is only heard as the closing theme during the 2002-03 season in ABC and broadcast syndication runs, as well as in re-edited bumpers with added video clips from that particular episode in some 2002-03 season episodes in broadcast syndication). In reruns of the Fugelsang-Fuentes episodes on [[WGN America]] and the Tom Bergeron episodes on WGN America and [[ABC Family]], the theme is noticeably slowed down (albeit slightly) during the show's opening titles and commercial bumpers.

The current theme can be heard in its entirety at the [http://www.tvmusicmuseum.com/documents/230.html Television Production Music Museum]. The two themes used in the Saget era have not been released to this day, as they are reportedly being held by [[Vin Di Bona]] for unknown reasons.

&quot;The Funny Things You Do&quot; was the theme song to the [[Australia's Funniest Home Videos|Australian version]] between 1991 and 2004. &quot;The Funny Things You Do&quot; was replaced by an instrumental version as part of the 2005 major revamp.

==Reruns/syndication==
All episodes of ''AFHV'' are currently in [[television syndication|syndication]] though for unknown reasons, the 1989–1994 Saget episodes, the 1994–97 Saget episodes, the 1998–99 Fugelsang/Fuentes episodes and the current Tom Bergeron episodes of ''AFV'' have virtually never been aired together in off-network broadcast or cable syndication; instead each era of the series has aired separately, with a minor exception for the 1994–97 Saget episodes and the Fugelsang-Fuentes episodes, which have never been aired in broadcast syndication. Until 2001, the Saget version was syndicated by [[20th Television]], who assumed syndication rights from their purchase of [[MTM Enterprises]], which had syndicated the show from 1995–1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-15768681.html McClellan, Steve. &quot;MTM launches 'Videos'; MTM Television Distribution offers syndication of America's Funniest Home Videos&quot;], ''[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]]'', October 3, 1994. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, [[Disney-ABC Domestic Television]] (formerly Buena Vista Television), the corporate cousin of one of the show's production companies [[ABC Productions]], distributes all versions of the series. 

The 1989–1994 Bob Saget episodes have aired in off-network syndication starting in September 1995, and also on [[TBS (TV network)|TBS]] from October 2, 1995–September 1998, [[USA Network]] from 1998–2001, and the [[Hallmark Channel]] from August 5, 2001–2003 and January 4-February 25, 2010 (during the latter Hallmark run, [[DirecTV]] on-screen program guides misstated the host as being &quot;Tom Bergeron&quot; rather than &quot;Bob Saget&quot;, despite Hallmark only having rights to the Saget episodes; this error was later removed when the Hallmark Channel moved ''AFHV'' to the late night and afternoon [[graveyard slot]]s), [[PAX TV]] (now [[Ion Television]]) on Monday-Thursday nights (Fridays were later added) from 2003–2005, and [[Nick at Nite]] from April-October 2007. When Nick at Nite began airing the early Saget episodes (including the 1989 special) the first week the show aired, every $100,000 Grand Prize show (excluding those from 1994–1997) was aired to commemorate the show joining Nick at Nite's schedule.

The 1998–99 Fugelsang-Fuentes episodes aired on [[ABC Family]] from the fall of 1999 (known as [[Television networks preceding ABC Family#Fox Family|Fox Family]] and owned by [[News Corporation]] at the time), until the fall of 2003; the 1994–97 Saget episodes also aired on the network from the fall of 2003 to September 2007, usually on Monday-Saturday nights, and occasionally Sundays if a movie ended before 11 p.m. ET. The Tom Bergeron episodes began airing on ABC Family on October 1, 2007, and usually airs 3–6 nights a week with episodes regularly airing at 6 p.m. ET (depending upon the night's schedule), and a four-hour block on Fridays from 6-11 p.m. ET (as of September 2010, these episodes are misidentified by DirecTV as episodes from the Saget era). The Tom Bergeron and Daisy Fuentes/John Fugelsang episodes have aired on [[WGN America]] since 2004, although the channel mostly shows the Tom Bergeron run, which airs weeknights at 7 p.m. ET, along with Saturday primetime and Sunday afternoon blocks; the Fugelsang-Fuentes episodes air on occasions (more frequently from 2004 to 2010, due to primetime movie overruns) when a sporting event airing on [[WGN-TV]] Chicago not cleared to air on WGN America forces the preemption of its simulcast of WGN-TV's 9 p.m. newscast outside of Chicago. [[Atlanta]] independent station [[WPCH-TV]] (channel 17, known as &quot;PeachtreeTV&quot;; formerly the local Atlanta feed of [[TBS (TV channel)|TBS]]) aired the entire Saget run, the first (and so far, the only) channel ever to do so since the original ABC run, from 2007 to 2009. The Tom Bergeron episodes of ''AFV'', with some minor editing for suggestive content (generally blurring backside nudity of babies and toddlers, which is usually permissible on television), began airing in off-network syndication on September 14, 2009; WGN America also aired the off-network syndicated episodes in late night until September 2011, while alternate versions of the Bergeron (and sometimes the Fugelsang-Fuentes) episodes with the Buena Vista Television tag before the end credits aired in the evening.

Outside the United States, family-oriented Canadian cable channel [[YTV (Canada)|YTV]] has aired ''AFV'' on Saturday nights since September 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=All: Fall TV Preview [www.falltvpreview.com]; e-mail: info@falltvpreview.com |url=http://www.falltvpreview.com/channel.php?id=131 |title=YTV |publisher=Falltvpreview.com |date=2010-09-06 |accessdate=2010-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian broadcaster [[Citytv]] also began airing a simulcast of ''AFV'' episodes from the current or previous season on Sundays at 7 p.m. ET, as it airs on ABC in the United States (but factoring [[simultaneous substitution]]), starting in the Spring of 2010.

The Saget and Bergeron episodes on ABC Family and the Saget episodes on Pax, after Bob or Tom close the show, showed the credits in a network generic format (or in a squeeze-down format in Hallmark Channel airings) to allow promotion for network programs. In Pax airings of the Saget run, when back-to-back episodes aired, the opening titles of the second episode was cut and replaced with an announcer saying &quot;Now don't go away, here's more of ''America's Funniest Home Videos''&quot; before cutting to Ernie Anderson introducing Bob Saget (this was done possibly due to time constraints). Nick at Nite and WPCH airings replaced the Saget era contest plugs with the more recent plugs, though the old plugs were kept in airings of the Saget run elsewhere (although, some episodes aired on Hallmark Channel removed the plugs). Some airings of the Saget run on Pax TV, Hallmark and Nick at Nite cut the interviews with the winners in some episodes, likely due to time constraints because of the longer ad breaks that were not seen on U.S. broadcast television at the period the episodes originally aired on ABC. Also because of time constraints, some of the Hallmark episodes have the opening titles (as well as various portions of the show) sped up, which many viewers have found it to be inconvinient and unnecessary as the speeding messes up the rhythm and melody of the theme song and video clips in the show's opening and commercial bumpers.

==Seasons==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||'''Season'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|'''First airdate'''|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|'''Last airdate'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;  
||Season 1 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|January 14, 1990 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 20, 1990 
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 2 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 16, 1990 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 12, 1991  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 3 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 22, 1991 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 17, 1992  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 4 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 20, 1992 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 16, 1993  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 5 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 19, 1993 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 22, 1994  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 6 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 18, 1994 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 21, 1995  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 7 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 17, 1995 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 19, 1996  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 8 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 22, 1996 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 18, 1997  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 9 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|January 9, 1998 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 1998   
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 10 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|1998 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|1999   
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;  
||Season 11 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|July 20, 2001 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|December 2001  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 12 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|January 4, 2002 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 2002  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 13 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 27, 2002 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 9, 2003 
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 14 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 28, 2003 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 23, 2004  
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 15 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 26, 2004 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 13, 2005 
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;  
||Season 16 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 2, 2005 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 19, 2006 
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 17 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 1, 2006 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 18, 2007
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;   
||Season 18 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 7, 2007 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 16, 2008 
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 19 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 5, 2008 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 15, 2009
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;   
||Season 20 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 4, 2009 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 16, 2010    
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 21 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 3, 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;thefutoncritic1&quot;/&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|May 15, 2011
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
||Season 22 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 2, 2011&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aoltv.com/2011/06/27/abc-fall-premiere-dates/&lt;/ref&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|2012
|} 


==Lawsuit==
In 2002, David Sawicki filed a $1 million lawsuit against ABC, its corporate parent [[The Walt Disney Company]], [[Shout! Factory]] (the distributor of ''AFV''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s compilation DVDs) and Vin Di Bona Productions over a tape filmed in 1992, which originally aired on the July 5, 2002 episode, in which a couple of friends of the then-[[Boston University]] student shaved a smiley face on his chest while a shirtless Sawicki was passed out drunk following a New Year's Eve party. Sawicki charged in the suit filed in Suffolk County Superior Court that he never gave approval for the video to be broadcast, alleging the show was negligent when it disregarded a policy of requiring releases &quot;from all identifiable persons depicted in the video&quot;. Sawicki said he did not know who had sent in the video to the show, and alleged emotional distress from the exhibition of the video.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-93016821.html Fee, Gayle; Laura Raposa. &quot;'Funniest Videos' star sues for $1M&quot;], ''[[The Boston Herald]]'', October 18, 2002. Retrieved March 7, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Merchandise==
===VHS/DVD===
[[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]], [[Shout! Factory]], and Slingshot Entertainment has released numerous compilation releases of ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' on VHS and DVD in Region 1. 

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!VHS/DVD Name!!Release Date !!Studio
|-
|The Best of America's Funniest Home Videos&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-1071544.html Martie Zad. &quot;'Funniest Home Videos' Now A Home Video&quot;], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', June 23, 1991. Retrieved March 8, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|June 27, 1991 || ABC Home Video&lt;br /&gt;CBS-Fox Video
|-
|America's Funniest Pets&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0312350/&lt;/ref&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|1992 || ABC Home Video&lt;br /&gt;CBS-Fox Video
|-
|America's Funniest Families&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amazon.com/dp/6302554756&lt;/ref&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|1992 || ABC Home Video&lt;br /&gt;CBS-Fox Video
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Animal Antics || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 12, 1999 || Slingshot Entertainment
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Deluxe Uncensored || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|June 6, 2000 || Slingshot Entertainment
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Family Follies || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|June 6, 2000 || Slingshot Entertainment
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Volume 1 with Tom Begeron|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|July 26, 2005 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Home for the Holidays || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|October 4, 2005 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: The Best of Kids and Animals || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|December 27, 2005 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Nincompoops &amp; Boneheads || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|June 13, 2006 || Shout! Factory
|- 
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Athletic Supporters || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|August 1, 2006 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Battle of the Best || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 12, 2006 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Sports Spectacular || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 12, 2006 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Love and Marriage || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|September 12, 2006 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Salute to Romance || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|January 9, 2007 || Shout! Factory
|- 
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Motherhood Madness || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|April 17, 2007 || Shout! Factory
|-
|America's Funniest Home Videos: Guide to Parenting || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|July 17, 2007 || Shout! Factory
|}

===Games===
[[Parker Brothers]] released a board game in 1990. [[Graphix Zone]] released a hybrid CD-ROM titled ''America's Funniest Home Videos: Lights! Camera! InterAction!'' in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-17588534.html &quot;Graphix Zone ships America's Funniest Home Videos Lights! Camera! InterAction! CD-ROM&quot;], [[Business Wire]], November 9, 1995. Retrieved March 8, 2011 from HighBeam Research.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Imagination Games]] released a DVD game in 2007.

===Toys===
An ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' micro movie viewer was released in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.licollectiblesstore.com/product/americas-funniest-home-videos-mirco-movie-viewer&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[America's Funniest People]]'', a spinoff of ''America's Funniest Home Videos''
* ''[[Australia's Funniest Home Video Show]]'', a 1990–2004 show also created by [[Vin Di Bona]]
* ''[[Australia's Funniest Home Videos]]'', a post-2005 show also created by [[Vin Di Bona]]
* ''[[Australia's Naughtiest Home Videos]]'', a half-off similar show also created by [[Vin Di Bona]]
* ''[[You've Been Framed]]'', the UK version of this show.
* ''[[Video Gag]]'', the French equivalent.
* ''[[It Only Hurts When I Laugh (TV Series)|It Only Hurts When I Laugh]]'', a TV show on [[truTV]] similar to ''AFV'' but mainly involving painful injuries (hence the title).
* ''[[The Planet's Funniest Animals]]'', a [[Animal Planet]] series similar to ''AFV'' but mainly involving animals doing crazy things.
* ''[[Sprockets (Saturday Night Live)|Sprockets]]'', which featured an ''AFV'' spoof, &quot;[[Germany]]'s Most Disturbing Home Videos&quot;, narrated by guest Karlheinz Schoeltker ([[Kyle MacLachlan]]).
* ''[[The World's Funniest Moments]]'', a series similar in format to both ''AFV'' and ''America's Funniest People''

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://abc.go.com/primetime/afv Official website]
* {{imdb title|id=0098740|title=America's Funniest Home Videos}}
* {{tv.com|3780|America's Funniest Home Videos}}
* [http://www.shoutfactory.com/browse/5/americas_funniest_home_videos.aspx America's Funniest Home Videos] page from [[Shout! Factory]]

{{ABCNetwork Shows (current and upcoming)}}

[[Category:1989 television series debuts]]
[[Category:1980s American television series]]
[[Category:1990s American television series]]
[[Category:2000s American television series]]
[[Category:2010s American television series]]
[[Category:Video clip television series]]
[[Category:American Broadcasting Company network shows]]
[[Category:American reality television series]]
[[Category:English-language television series]]
[[Category:Home video]]
[[Category:Television series by Buena Vista Television]]
[[Category:Television series by Lionsgate Television]]
[[Category:Television series by Fox Television Studios]]

[[da:America's Funniest Home Videos]]
[[de:Heimvideo-Sendung]]
[[fa:خنده‌دارترین ویدئوهای خانگی آمریکا]]
[[fr:America's Funniest Home Videos]]
[[nl:America's Funniest Home Videos]]
[[no:America's Funniest Home Videos]]
[[pt:America's Funniest Home Videos]]
[[th:กระตุกต่อมฮาอเมริกา]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
