<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4149830" ns="0" title="Windisch"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{See also|Windisch (disambiguation)|Windisch (surname)}}
{{Infobox Swiss town
|subject_name		= Windisch
|image_photo            = WindischAG01.JPG
|municipality_name	= Windisch
|municipality_type	= municipality
|imagepath_coa	= Windisch-blason.png|pixel_coa=
|map			=
|languages		= German
|canton		= Aargau
|iso-code-region 	= CH-AG
|district		= [[Brugg (district)|Brugg]]
|lat_d=47|lat_m=29|lat_NS=N|long_d=8|long_m=13|long_EW=E
|postal_code		= 5210
|municipality_code	= 4123
|area			= 4.91
|elevation		= 357|elevation_description=
|population		= {{Swiss populations NC|CH-AG|4123}} |populationof = {{Swiss populations YM|CH-AG}} | popofyear = {{Swiss populations Y|CH-AG}}
|website		= www.windisch.ch
|mayor		=|mayor_asof=|mayor_party=
|mayor_title	=|list_of_mayors	=
|places		=
|demonym		=
|neighboring_municipalities= [[Birmenstorf, Aargau|Birmenstorf]], [[Brugg]], [[Gebenstorf]], [[Hausen, Aargau|Hausen]], [[Mülligen]]
|twintowns		=
|}}
[[File:Karte Gemeinde Windisch 2010.png|thumb|Windisch]]
'''Windisch''' is a [[Municipalities of Switzerland|municipality]] in the district of [[Brugg (district)|Brugg]] in the [[Cantons of Switzerland|canton]] of [[Aargau]] in [[Switzerland]].

==History==
[[File:Vindonissa Suedtor01.jpg|thumb|left|Location of the south gate of the Vindonissa camp]]
[[File:Agnes Regina.JPG|thumb|left|Agnes of Hungary with Königsfelden Abbey]]
Windisch is situated at the site of the Roman legion camp [[Vindonissa]].  In 1064 the current municipality was mentioned as ''Vinse'', and in 1175 as ''Vindisse''.  Until the 19th Century the official name was ''Windisch und Oberburg''.&lt;ref name=HDS/&gt;  The village grew into a regional power following the foundation of [[Königsfelden Abbey]] in 1309 in memory of the [[regicide]] of King [[Albert I of Germany]] in the previous year.  Albert was on the way to suppress a revolt in [[Suebi|Swabia]] when he was murdered on May 1, 1308,  near Windisch on the [[Reuss River]], by his nephew [[John Parricida|John of Swabi]], afterwards called &quot;the Parricide&quot; or &quot;John Parricida&quot;, whom he had deprived of his inheritance.&lt;ref name=HDS&gt;{{HDS|1715|Windisch}}&lt;/ref&gt;  After the foundation of the Abbey, the village was placed under the authority of the Abbey.  Starting in 1348 the rights to [[High, middle and low justice|high and low justice]] were held by [[Agnes of Austria (1281–1364)|Agnes of Hungary]].  In 1411 those rights transferred back to the monastery.   The abbey church, possibly in antiquity under the patronage of St. Martin but in the [[Middle Ages]] under the patronage of [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]], is built on the site of the 6th Century [[Bishop]]'s church.  The present building, with a [[Romanesque architecture|late-Romanesque]] [[nave]] and [[Gothic architecture|Gothic]] [[choir]], was built between 1310-30.  The church's [[charnel house]] was rebuilt in 1793 into a schoolhouse.&lt;ref name=HDS/&gt;

After the conquest of the Aargau by [[Bern]] and the introduction of the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] (1528) the monastery was suppressed.  Until 1798 it served as the residence of the Bernese [[bailiff]]s ({{lang-de|Hofmeister}}).  People from Windisch worked in the bailiff's residence as servants, maids and workmen, while the poor came to the former abbey for alms.

The main sources of income in Windisch included handicrafting, ferries, fisheries, shipping, tavern and iron ore mining in Lindhof, but agriculture was the major contributor.  There was a ferry over the Reuss river on the Bern-Zurich road.  This was replace in 1799 by a bridge.  Plague epidemics (in 1667 60% of the population died of the plague) and the restrictive immigration policies of the municipality prevented growth.  However, during the 18th Century, the emergence of new occupations, led to a significant population increase.  These new industries included cap and stocking weaving, and water powered light industry (including plaster and flour mills).  At the same time improved agriculture techniques allowed more food to be produced from the fields.  The nearest neighbor to Windisch was the town of [[Brugg]].  The close proximity led to centuries of conflicts over grazing rights, city monopolies, taxation and especially the location of the municipal boundary.  In 1863, due to a border adjustment, Windisch lost {{convert|45|ha|acre}} to Brugg.

In the 19th Century the economy of the village changed.  In 1825 Henry Kunz founded the [[cotton mill]] ''Kunz'' which had 567 employees in 1846.  They built factory workers' homes and a village school.  In 1804 part of Königsfelden Abbey converted into a District Hospital.  In 1872 a new building was built and since 1887 it has been a psychiatric clinic.  The construction of the railway network transformed Brugg and Windisch into a railroad hub with a large depot and repair shop (primarily for steam locomotives).  These innovations resulted in the influx of factory workers, nurses and trained staff.  This led to a restructuring of the population: for example, the locally born and working population fell from 88% (1815), 55% (1837) and 21% (1900) to 4% (1970), while the proportion of Catholics rose from 9% (1850) to 45 % (1970).  Agriculture employs only 0.6% of the population (1990).  In 1965, a Higher Technical School of Windisch (now a university) opened.  The changing population structure led to political shifts in favor of the [[Social Democratic Party of Switzerland|Social Democratic Party (SP)]] (1921-49 was known as the period of the &quot;red Windisch&quot;). With a pronounced emphasis on political independence, Windisch grew together structurally and economically with Brugg.&lt;ref name=HDS/&gt;

==Geography==
[[File:WindischAG04.jpg|thumb|left|Windisch]]
Windisch has an area, {{as of|2009|lc=on}}, of {{convert|4.91|km2|sqmi|sp=us}}.  Of this area, {{convert|1.16|km2|sqmi|sp=us}} or 23.6% is used for agricultural purposes, while {{convert|1.22|km2|sqmi|sp=us}} or 24.8% is forested.   Of the rest of the land, {{convert|2.23|km2|sqmi|sp=us}} or 45.4% is settled (buildings or roads), {{convert|0.31|km2|sqmi|sp=us}} or 6.3% is either rivers or lakes.&lt;ref name=BFS_land&gt;[http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/de/index/themen/02/03/blank/data/gemeindedaten.html Swiss Federal Statistical Office-Land Use Statistics] 2009 data {{de icon}} accessed 25 March 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the built up area, industrial buildings made up 5.3% of the total area while housing and buildings made up 21.6% and transportation infrastructure made up 9.6%.  Power and water infrastructure as well as other special developed areas made up 1.8% uof the area while parks, green belts and sports fields made up 7.1%.  22.4% of the total land area is heavily forested and 2.4% is covered with orchards or small clusters of trees.  Of the agricultural land, 13.8% is used for growing crops and 6.9% is pastures, while 2.9% is used for orchards or vine crops.  All the water in the municipality is in rivers and streams.&lt;ref name=BFS_land/&gt;

The municipality is located in the Brugg district, between the [[Aare]] and [[Reuss river]]s in the region known as the ''Wasserschloss''.  It consists of the former [[linear village]]s of Windisch  and Oberburg as well as the [[hamlet (place)|hamlets]] of Fahrgut, Schürhof, Lindhof and Bachtalen and the region around the former [[Königsfelden Abbey]].

==Coat of arms==
The [[blazon]] of the municipal [[coat of arms]] is ''Or on a Sevenfold Mount Vert a Castle embattled Sable towered on dexter and to its sinister a Lion rampant Gules.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fotw.us/flags/ch-ag096.html Flags of the World.com] accessed 12-April-2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
Windisch has a population ({{as of|{{Swiss populations YM|CH-AG}}|lc=on}}) of {{Swiss populations|CH-AG|4123}}{{Swiss populations ref|CH-AG}}  {{as of|2009|June}}, 29.1% of the population are foreign nationals.&lt;ref name=AG_pop&gt;[http://www.ag.ch/staag/ Statistical Department of Canton Aargau -Bereich 01  -Bevölkerung] {{de icon}} accessed 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  Over the last 10 years (1997–2007) the population has changed at a rate of 4.5%.  Most of the population ({{as of|2000|lc=on}}) speaks German (80.6%), with Italian being second most common ( 4.9%) and Serbo-Croatian being third ( 3.2%).&lt;ref name=SFSO&gt;[http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/en/index/regionen/02/gemeindesuche.html Swiss Federal Statistical Office] accessed 12-April-2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The age distribution, {{as of|2008|lc=on}}, in Windisch is; 732 children or 11.0% of the population are between 0 and 9 years old and 783 teenagers or 11.8% are between 10 and 19.  Of the adult population, 837 people or 12.6% of the population are between 20 and 29 years old.  888 people or 13.3% are between 30 and 39, 1,017 people or 15.3% are between 40 and 49, and 826 people or 12.4% are between 50 and 59.  The senior population distribution is 693 people or 10.4% of the population are between 60 and 69 years old, 525 people or 7.9% are between 70 and 79, there are 302 people or 4.5% who are between 80 and 89,and there are 55 people or 0.8% who are 90 and older.&lt;ref name=structure&gt;[http://www.ag.ch/staag/ Statistical Department of Canton Aargau -Bevölkerungsdaten für den Kanton Aargau und die Gemeinden (Archiv)] {{de icon}} accessed 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

{{as of|2000}} the average number of residents per living room was 0.57 which is about equal to the cantonal average of 0.57 per room.  In this case, a room is defined as space of a housing unit of at least {{convert|4|m2|sqft|abbr=on}} as normal bedrooms, dining rooms, living rooms, kitchens and habitable cellars and attics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite manual |  author = Eurostat| title = Urban Audit Glossary| section = Housing (SA1)| version = 2007| url = http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/en/index/international/22/lexi.Document.116365.pdf |format = pdf | page= 18| accessdate = 12 February 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  About 32.9% of the total households were owner occupied, or in other words did not pay rent (though they may have a [[mortgage loan|mortgage]] or a [[rent-to-own]] agreement).&lt;ref&gt;Urban Audit Glossary pg 17&lt;/ref&gt;

{{as of|2000}}, there were 316 homes with 1 or 2 persons in the household, 1,576 homes with 3 or 4 persons in the household, and 774 homes with 5 or more persons in the household.  The average number of people per household was 2.29 individuals.&lt;ref name=zahlen/&gt;  {{as of|2000}}, there were 2,726 private households (homes and apartments) in the municipality, and an average of 2.3 persons per household.&lt;ref name=SFSO/&gt;  {{as of|2008|alt=In 2008}} there were 763 single family homes (or 24.9% of the total) out of a total of 3,066 homes and apartments.&lt;ref name=AG_data&gt;[http://www.ag.ch/staag/ Statistical Department of Canton Aargau] {{de icon}} accessed 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  There were a total of 16 empty apartments for a 0.5% vacancy rate.&lt;ref name=&quot;AG_data&quot;/&gt;  {{as of|2007}}, the construction rate of new housing units was 0.6 new units per 1000 residents.&lt;ref name=SFSO/&gt;

In the 2007 [[Swiss federal election, 2007|federal election]] the most popular party was the [[Swiss People's Party|SVP]] which received 32.7% of the vote.  The next three most popular parties were the SP (23%), the [[Christian Democratic People's Party of Switzerland|CVP]] (12.6%) and the [[Free Democratic Party of Switzerland|FDP]] (10.7%).&lt;ref name=SFSO/&gt;

In Windisch about 61.8% of the population (between age 25-64) have completed either non-mandatory [[Education in Switzerland#Secondary|upper secondary education]] or additional higher education (either university or a ''[[Fachhochschule]]'').&lt;ref name=SFSO/&gt;  Of the school age population ({{as of|2009|alt=in the 2008/2009 school year}}), there are 579 students attending [[Education in Switzerland#Primary|primary school]], there are 316 students attending secondary school, there are 302 students attending [[Education in Switzerland#Tertiary|tertiary or university level schooling]] in the municipality.&lt;ref name=zahlen/&gt;

The historical population is given in the following table:&lt;ref name=HDS&gt;{{HDS|1715|Windisch}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! year
! population
|-
| 1529
| 33 households
|-
| 1578
|  61
|-
| 1736
|  77
|-
| 1736
|  402
|-
| 1815
|  661
|-
| 1850
|  1,287
|-
| 1880
| 2,052
|-
| 1900
|  2,389
|-
| 1910
|  3,231
|-
| 1950
|  4,363
|-
| 1980
|  7,598
|-
| 1990
|  6,915
|-
|}

==Heritage sites of national significance==
There are five sites in Windisch that are listed as Swiss [[Swiss inventory of cultural property of national and regional significance|heritage site of national significance]].  The oldest is the [[Celts|celtic]]/[[Switzerland in the Roman era|roman]] military fort and settlement of Vindonissa.  The other large site is the church of the former Königsfelden Abbey with its glass paintings of 1325, [[Agnes of Rome|Agnes]] chapel, comptrollery and convent building.  The other three are the former Upper Technical School at Klosterzelgstrasse, the former cotton mill ''Kunz'' at Alte Spinnerei 4,5 and the psychiatric clinic of Königsfelden.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bevoelkerungsschutz.admin.ch/internet/bs/de/home/themen/kgs/kgs_inventar.html Swiss inventory of cultural property of national and regional significance] 21.11.2008 version, {{de icon}} accessed 12-Apr-2010&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Amphitheater of Vindonissa.jpg|Amphitheater of Vindonissa
File:Königsfelden05.jpg|Church of Königsfelden Abbey
File:Koenigsfelden 04.jpg|Interior of Königsfelden Abbey Church
File:Windisch Villa.jpg|Villa near the ''Kunz'' cotton mill
File:Vindonissa 01.jpg|Psychiatric clinic of Königsfelden
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Economy==
{{as of|2007|In 2007}}, Windisch had an unemployment rate of 2.52%.  {{as of|2005}}, there were 20 people employed in the [[Primary sector of the economy|primary economic sector]] and about 9 businesses involved in this sector.  353 people are employed in the [[Secondary sector of the economy|secondary sector]] and there are 46 businesses in this sector.  2,308 people are employed in the [[Tertiary sector of the economy|tertiary sector]], with 195 businesses in this sector.&lt;ref name=SFSO/&gt;

{{as of|2000}} there was a total of 3,181 workers who lived in the municipality.  Of these, 2,446 or about 76.9% of the residents worked outside Windisch while 1,765 people commuted into the municipality for work.  There were a total of 2,500 jobs (of at least 6 hours per week) in the municipality.&lt;ref name=&quot;ag.ch&quot;&gt;[http://www.ag.ch/staag/ Statistical Department of Canton Aargau-Bereich 11  Verkehr und Nachrichtenwesen] {{de icon}} accessed 21 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  Of the working population, 20.6% used public transportation to get to work, and 39% used a private car.&lt;ref name=SFSO/&gt;

==Religion==
[[File:Windisch Kirche.jpg|thumb|Reformed Church of Windisch]]
From the {{as of|2000|alt=2000 census}}, 2,288 or 34.4% were [[Roman Catholic]], while 2,252 or 33.9% belonged to the [[Swiss Reformed Church]].  Of the rest of the population, there were 5 individuals (or about 0.08% of the population) who belonged to the [[Christian Catholic Church of Switzerland|Christian Catholic]] faith.&lt;ref name=zahlen&gt;[http://www.ag.ch/staag/ Statistical Department of Canton Aargau - Aargauer Zahlen 2009] {{de icon}} accessed 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{HDS|1715|Windisch}}
{{commons category|Windisch}}

{{Municipalities of the district of Brugg}}

[[Category:Municipalities of Aargau]]
[[Category:Cultural property of national significance in the canton of Aargau]]

[[als:Windisch]]
[[ca:Windisch]]
[[de:Windisch AG]]
[[es:Windisch]]
[[eo:Windisch]]
[[fr:Windisch]]
[[it:Windisch (Svizzera)]]
[[lmo:Windisch]]
[[nl:Windisch]]
[[pms:Windisch]]
[[pt:Windisch]]
[[ru:Виндиш]]
[[simple:Windisch]]
[[sv:Windisch]]
[[uk:Віндіш]]
[[vo:Windisch]]
[[war:Windisch]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
