<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4153862" ns="0" title="History of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Chef einer Luftflotte Version 1.svg|thumb|right|Luftwaffe eagle. The image is attached to a ''[[Luftflotte]]''.]]
The [[Nazi Germany|German]] '''''Luftwaffe''''' was one of the strongest, most doctrinally advanced, and most battle-experienced air forces in the world when [[World War II]] started in [[Europe]] in September 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Killen 2003, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; Officially unveiled in 1935, in violation of the [[Treaty of Versailles]], its purpose was to support Adolf Hitler's &quot;''[[Blitzkrieg]]''&quot; across Europe. The aircraft that were to serve in the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' were of a new age and technically superior to that of most other nations in the 1930s. Types like the [[Junkers Ju 87]] ''Stuka'' and [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] came to symbolise German air power.

The ''Luftwaffe'' became an essential component in the German military campaigns. Operating in support of ground forces, it helped the German armies to conquer the bulk of the European continent in a series of short and decisive campaigns in the first nine months of the war. It experienced its first defeat by the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) during the [[Battle of Britain]] in 1940.

Despite this setback the ''Luftwaffe'' remained formidable and in June 1941 embarked on Hitler's quest for [[Lebensraum|an empire in eastern Europe]] by invading the [[Soviet Union]], with much initial success. However, the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s striking victories in the Soviet Union were brought to a halt in the [[Russian winter]] of 1941–42.

Having failed to achieve victory in the [[Soviet Union]] in 1941 or 1942, the ''Luftwaffe'' was drawn into a war of attrition which extended to [[North Africa]] and the Channel Front. The entry of the [[United States]] into the war and the resurgence of the RAF's offensive power created the Home Front, known as ''[[Defence of the Reich]]'' operations. The ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s strength was slowly eroded, and by mid 1944 it had virtually disappeared from the skies of Western Europe leaving the German Army to fight without air support. It continued to fight into the last days of the war with a new generation of turbojet-powered, and even rocket-engined aircraft, such as the [[Messerschmitt Me 262]], [[Messerschmitt Me 163]] and the [[Heinkel He 162]].
[[File:Balkenkreuz.svg|right|thumb|150px|The ''Luftwaffe'' ''[[Balkenkreuz]]'' (beam cross) was carried on the upper and lower wings and the fuselages.]]

==Origin of Luftwaffe==
{{Main|Luftwaffe}}
{{stack|
[[File:NSFK Wimpel Fördernde Mitglieder.svg|thumb|right|200px|The NSFK pennant. Members helped form the nucleus of the ''Luftwaffe'' in 1933]]
[[File:Wimpel DLV.svg|thumb|right|200px|Flag of the ''Deutscher Luftsportverband'' (DLV), German Airsports Association.]]}}
The origins of the ''Luftwaffe'' were born just months after Adolf Hitler came to power. [[Hermann Göring]], a [[World War I]] ace with 22 victories and the holder of the ''[[Pour le Merite|Orden Pour le Merite]]'', became National Kommissar for aviation with former [[Deutsche Luft Hansa]] director [[Erhard Milch]] as his deputy. In April 1933 the ''[[Reichsluftfahrtministerium]]'' (RLM - Reich Air Ministry) was established. The RLM was in charge of development and production of aircraft, and soon afterwards the test site at [[Rechlin]] became its testing ground. Göring's control over all aspects of aviation became absolute. On 25 March 1933 the [[German Air Sports Association|''Deutschen Luftsportverband'']] (DVLA) (German Air Sport Association) absorbed all private and national organizations, whilst retaining its 'sports' title. The merging of all [[military aviation]] organizations in the RLM took place on 15 May 1933, which became the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s official 'birthday'.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 30. (''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt; Many members of the ''[[National Socialist Flyers Corps|Nationalsozialistisches Fliegerkorps]]'' (National Socialist Flyers Corps - NSFK) transferred to the ''Luftwaffe''. As all such prior NSFK members were also Nazi Party members; this gave the new ''Luftwaffe'' a strong Nazi ideological base in contrast to the other branches of the German military. Göring had played a leading role in the build up of the ''Luftwaffe'' in 1933-1936, but played little further part in the development of the ''Luftwaffe'' until 1936, and Milch became the ''de facto'' minister until 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 31.(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt;

The absence of Göring in planning and production matters was fortunate. Göring had little knowledge of current aviation, had last flown in 1922, and had not kept himself informed of latest events. Göring also displayed a lack of understanding of doctrine and technical issues in aerial warfare which he left to the more competent. The [[Commander-in-Chief]] left the organisation and building of the ''Luftwaffe'', after 1936, to Erhard Milch. However Göring, as a part of Hitler's inner circle, was to provide enormous financial materials for rearming and equipping the ''Luftwaffe''.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 124-125.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another prominent figure in German air power construction this time was Helmuth Wilberg. Wilberg was to play a large role in the development of German air doctrine. Having headed the ''[[Reichswehr]]'' air staff for eight years in the 1920s, Wilberg had considerable experience and was ideal for a senior staff position.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; Göring considered making Wilberg [[Chief of Staff]] (CS). However, it was revealed Wilberg had a [[Jewish]] mother. For that reason Göring could not have him as CS. Not wishing his talent to go to waste, Göring ensured the racial laws of the ''Third Reich'' did not apply to him. Wilberg remained in the air staff and helped draw up the principle doctrine ''The Conduct of the Aerial War'' and its ''Regulation 16'' under [[Walther Wever (general)|Walther Wever]].&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2010, pp. 20–21.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Preparing for war: 1933–1939==
===The Wever years, 1933 - 1936===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 141-1941, Walther Wever.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Walther Wever, Chief of the Luftwaffe General Staff, 1933-1936.]]
Contrary to popular belief in American and British circles, the ''Luftwaffe'' was not &quot;the hand maiden of the German Army&quot;. The German officer Corps was keen to develop [[strategic bombing]] capabilities against its enemies. However, economic and [[Geopolitics|geopolitical]] considerations had to take priority. The German air power theorists continued to develop strategic theories, but emphasis was given to Army support, as Germany was a continental power and would likely face ground operations immediately following any declaration of hostilities.&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1983, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

For these reasons, between 1933 and 1934, the ''Luftwaffe'' leadership was primarily concerned with tactical and operational methods. In aerial terms, the Army concept of ''Truppenführung'' was an operational concept, as well as a tactical doctrine. In the [[First World War]] air units had been attached to specific Army formations and acted as support. [[Dive bomber]] units were considered essential to ''Truppenführung''; destroying [[Headquarters]] and [[Line of communication|lines of communications]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Corum 1997, p. 129&quot;&gt;Corum 1997, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Luftwaffe'' ''Regulation 10'', ''The Bomber'' (''Dienstvorschrift 10'': ''Das Kampfflugzeug''), published in 1934, advocated air superiority and approaches to ground attack tactics without dealing with operational matters. Until 1935, the 1926 manual ''Directives for the Conduct of the Operational Air War'' continued to act as the main guide for German air operations. The manual directed the ''OKL'' to focus on limited operations (not strategic-operations); the protection of specific areas and support of the Army in combat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corum 1997, p. 129&quot;/&gt;

With an effective tactical-operational concept,&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; the German air power theorists needed a strategic doctrine and organisation. Robert Knauss, a serviceman (not pilot) in the ''[[Luftstreitkräfte]]'' during the First World War, and later an experienced pilot with Luft Hansa,&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt; was prominent theorist of air power. Knauss promoted the [[Giulio Douhet]] theory that air power could win wars alone by destroying enemy industry and morale by &quot;terrorizing the population&quot; of major cities. This advocated attacks on civilians.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; The General Staff blocked the entry of Douhet's theory into doctrine fearing revenge strikes against German civilians and cities.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 133-134.&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1934, Chief of the ''Luftwaffe'' [[General Staff]] [[Walther Wever (general)|Walther Wever]] sought to mould the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s battle doctrine into a strategic plan. At this time, Wever conducted war games (simulated against the French) in a bid to establish his theory of a strategic bombing force that would, he thought, prove decisive by winning the war through the destruction of enemy industry, even though these exercises also included tactical strikes against enemy ground forces and communications. In [[1935]], &quot;Luftwaffe Regulation 16: The Conduct of the Air War&quot; was drawn up. In the proposal, it concluded &quot;The mission of the Luftwaffe is to serve these goals&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooton 2007, p. 34(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&quot;&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 34(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2010, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;

Within this doctrine, the ''Luftwaffe'' leadership rejected the practice of &quot;[[terror bombing]]&quot; (see [[Blitzkrieg#Luftwaffe doctrine|Luftwaffe strategic bombing doctrine]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Corum 1997, p. 7&quot;&gt;Corum 1997, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Terror bombing was deemed to be &quot;counter-productive&quot;, increasing rather than destroying the enemies will to resist.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 143–144.&lt;/ref&gt; Such bombing campaigns were regarded as diversion from the ''Luftwaffe's'' main operations; destruction of the enemy armed forces.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; The bombings of [[Guernica]], [[Rotterdam]] and [[Warsaw]] were considered tactical missions in support of military operations and were not intended as strategic terror attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 6-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, Wever recognised the importance of [[strategic bombing]]. In newly introduced doctrine, ''The Conduct of the Aerial Air War'' in 1935, Wever rejected the theory of Douhet&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; and outlined five key points to air strategy:
&lt;blockquote&gt;1. To destroy the enemy air force by bombing its bases and aircraft factories, and defeating enemy air forces attacking German targets.&lt;br /&gt;2. To prevent the movement of large enemy ground forces to the decisive areas by destroying railways and roads, particularly bridges and tunnels, which are indispensable for the movement and supply of forces&lt;br /&gt;3. To support the operations of the army formations, independent of railways, i.e, armoured forces and motorised forces, by impeding the enemy advance and participating directly in ground operations.&lt;br /&gt;4. To support naval operations by attacking naval bases, protecting Germany's naval bases and participating directly in naval battles&lt;br /&gt;5. To paralyse the enemy armed forces by stopping production in the armaments factories.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Wever began planning for a [[strategic bomber]] force and sought to incorporate strategic bombing into a war strategy. He believed that tactical aircraft should only be used as a step to developing a strategic air force. In May 1934, Wever initiated a seven year project for the [[Ural bomber|''Ural Bomber'']], the bomber that would take the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s bombing campaign into the heart of the Soviet Union. In 1935, this led to the [[Dornier Do 19]] and [[Junkers Ju 89]] prototypes, although both were underpowered. In April 1936, Wever ordered a requirement for 'Bomber A' which would have a range of 6,700&amp;nbsp;km (4,163&amp;nbsp;mi) with a 900&amp;nbsp;[[kilogram|kg]] (1,984&amp;nbsp;lb) bomb load. However Wever's vision of a &quot;Ural&quot; bomber was never realised,&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 33.(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt; and his emphasis on strategic aerial operations was lost,&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 224.&lt;/ref&gt; with the only design submittal for Wever's 'Bomber A' that would reach production being [[Heinkel]]'s ''Projekt 1041'', which became officially known on November 5, 1937 as the [[Heinkel He 177]].&lt;ref&gt;Griehl, Manfred and Dressel, Joachim. ''Heinkel He 177 - 277 - 274''. Shrewsbury, UK: Airlife Publishing. ISBN 1-85310-364-0, pg.9.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the late 1930s the ''Luftwaffe'' had no clear purpose. The air force was not subordinated to the army support role, and it was not given any particular strategic mission. German doctrine fell between the two concepts. The ''Luftwaffe'' was to be an organisation capable of carrying out broad and general support tasks rather than any specific mission. Mainly, this path was chosen to encourage a more flexible use of air power and offer the ground forces the right conditions for a decisive victory. In fact, on the outbreak of war, only 15 percent of the ''Luftwaffe's'' aircraft was devoted to ground support operations, exposing a long-held myth that the ''Luftwaffe'' was designed for only tactical and operational missions.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley 1998, pp. 85-86&lt;/ref&gt;

===A change of direction, 1936 - 1937===
Wever's participation in the construction of the ''Luftwaffe'' came to an abrupt end on 3 June 1936 when he was killed along with his engineer in a [[Heinkel He 70]] ''Blitz''. After Wever's death Göring began taking more of an interest in the appointment of ''Luftwaffe'' staff. Göring appointed his successor [[Albert Kesselring]] as CS and [[Ernst Udet]] head the Reich's Air Ministry Technical Office (''Technisches Amt''), although he was not a technical expert. Despite this he was appointed to and helped change the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s tactical direction towards producing fast medium bombers that were to destroy enemy air power in the battle zone rather than through industrial bombing of its aviation production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooton 2007, p. 34(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&quot;/&gt;
Kesselring and Udet did not get on. During Kesselring's time as CS, 1936–1937, a power struggle developed between the two as Udet attempted to extend his own power within the ''Luftwaffe''. Kesselring also had to contend with Göring appointing &quot;yes men&quot; to positions of importance.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt; Udet himself realised his limitations, and his failures in the production and development of German aircraft would have serious long term consequences.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1984-112-13, Ernst Udet.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Ernst Udet. Along with Kesselring, Udet was responsible for establishing the design trend of German aircraft. Udet's focus was on tactical army support air forces]]
The failure of the ''Luftwaffe'' to progress further towards attaining a strategic bombing force was attributable to several reasons. Many in the ''Luftwaffe'' command believed medium bombers to be sufficient power to launch strategic bombing operations against Germany's most likely enemies; [[France]], [[Czechoslovakia]] and [[Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1983, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Kingdom]] presented greater problems. ''[[General der Flieger]]'' [[Hellmuth Felmy]], commander of ''[[Luftflotte 2]]'' in 1939, was charged with devising a plan for an air war over the British Isles. Felmy was convinced that Britain could be defeated through morale bombing. Felmy noted the alleged panic that had broken out in [[London]] during the [[Munich crisis]], evidence he believed of British weakness. A second reason was technical. German designers had never solved the issues of the [[Heinkel He 177]] design difficulties. Moreover, Germany did not possess the economic strength and resources to match the British and American effort of 1943-1944. In addition, the ''OKL'' had not foreseen the industrial and military effort strategic bombing would require. By 1939 the ''Luftwaffe'' was not much better prepared than its enemies to conduct a strategic bombing campaign,&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1938, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; with fatal results during the [[Battle of Britain]].&lt;ref&gt;Overy 1980, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

The German rearmament program faced difficulties acquiring raw materials. Germany imported most of its essential materials for rebuilding the ''Luftwaffe'', in particular [[rubber]] and [[aluminium]]. Petroleum imports were particularly vulnerable to blockade. The Germans pushed for synthetic fuel plants, but still failed to meet demands. In 1937 Germany imported more fuel than at than it had at the start of the decade. By the summer 1938 only 25 percent of requirements could be covered. In [[steel]] materials, industry was operating at barely 83 percent and by November 1938 Göring reported the economic situation was serious.&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1983, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' (''OKW'') ordered reductions in raw and steel materials for armament production. The figures for reduction were substantial: 30 percent steel, 20 percent [[copper]], 47 percent aluminium and 14 percent rubber.&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1983, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Under such circumstances, it was not possible for Milch, Udet or Kesselring to produce a formidable strategic bombing force even had they wanted to.&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1983, p.11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of aircraft was now confined to the production of twin-engined [[medium bomber]]s that required much less material and manpower than Wever's 'Ural Bombers'. German industry could build two medium bombers for one heavy bomber and the ''RLM'' would not gamble on developing a heavy bomber which would also take time. Göring remarked, &quot;the ''Führer'' will not ask how big the bombers there are, but only how many there are&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Homze 1976, p. 125&lt;/ref&gt; The premature death of one of the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s finest officers, one that left the ''Luftwaffe'' without a strategic air force during World War II, eventually proved fatal to the German war effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hooton 2007, p. 34(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dressel &amp; Griehl 1994, p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bergström 2007, pp. 129-130&lt;/ref&gt;

The lack of strategic capability should have been apparent much earlier. The [[German occupation of Czechoslovakia|Sudeten Crisis]] highlighted German unprepardness to conduct a strategic air war (although the British and French were in a much weaker position), and Hitler ordered the ''Luftwaffe'' be expanded by five times.&lt;ref&gt;Ketley,Barry, and Rolfe, Mark. ''Luftwaffe Fledglings 1935-1945: Luftwaffe Training Units and their Aircraft'' (Aldershot, GB: Hikoki Publications, 1996), p.3.&lt;/ref&gt; ''OKL'' badly neglected the need for transport aircraft; even in 1943, transport units were described as ''Kampfgeschwadern zur besonderen Verwendung'' (&quot;Bomber Units on Special Duties&quot;, ''KGzbV'').&lt;ref&gt;Ketley and Rolfe, p.7.&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1938, as the ''[[Anschluss]]'' was taking place, Goring ordered Felmy to investigate the prospect of [[strategic bombing|air raids]] against Britain. Felmy concluded it was not possible until bases in [[Belgium]] and the [[Netherlands]] were obtained and the ''Luftwaffe'' had heavy bombers. Fortunately it mattered little, as the British betrayed the Czechs, war was avoided, and the need for long-range aircraft did not arise.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, ''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering Storm'', p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt;

These failures were not exposed until wartime. In the meantime German designs such as the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]], [[Heinkel He 111]], [[Junkers Ju 87]] ''Stuka'', and [[Dornier Do 17]], performed very well. All first saw active service in the ''[[Condor Legion]]'' against Soviet-supplied aircraft. The ''Luftwaffe'' also quickly realized the days of the biplane fighter were finished, the [[Heinkel He 51]] being switched to service as a trainer. Particularly impressive were the Heinkel and Dornier, which fulfilled the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s requirements for bombers that were faster than fighters.

Despite the participation of these aircraft (mainly from 1938 onward), it was the venerable [[Junkers Ju 52]] (which soon became the backbone of the ''Transportgruppen'') that made the main contribution. During the Spanish Civil War Hitler remarked, &quot;Franco ought to erect a monument to the glory of the Junkers Ju 52. It is the aircraft which the Spanish revolution has to thank for its victory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 51.(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dive-bombing===
Poor accuracy from level bombers in 1937 led the ''Luftwaffe'' to grasp the benefits of dive-bombing. The latter could achieve far better accuracy against small mobile tactical targets than heavier, conventional bombers. Range was not key criteria for these tasks and it was not always viable for the ''Heer'' to move heavy artillery over recently captured territory to bombard fortifications or support ground forces when faster dive-bombers could do the job more quickly. Dive-bombers, often single-engine two-man machines, could achieve better results than larger six or seven-man aircraft, at a tenth of the cost and four times the accuracy. This led to [[Ernst Udet]] championing the dive-bomber, particularly the [[Junkers Ju 87]].&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 38. ''The Gathering Storm''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Udet's &quot;love affair&quot; with dive-bombing seriously affected the long-term development of the ''Luftwaffe''. The tactical [[strike aircraft]] programs were meant to serve as interim solutions until the next generation of aircraft arrived. In 1936 the [[Junkers Ju 52]] was the backbone of the German bomber fleet. This led to a rush on the part of the ''RLM'' to produce the [[Junkers Ju 86]], [[Heinkel He 111]] and [[Dornier Do 17]] before a proper evalutation was made. The Ju 86 was poor while the He 111 showed most promise. The [[Spanish Civil War]] convinced Udet (along with limited output from the German munitions industry) that wastage was not acceptable in munition terms. Udet sought to build dive-bombing into the [[Junkers Ju 88]] and conveyed the same idea, initiated specifically by the [[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe|OKL]], for the [[Heinkel He 177]]. In the case of the Ju 88, 50,000 modifications had to be made. The weight was increased from seven to twelve tons. This resulted in a speed loss of 200&amp;nbsp;km/h. Udet merely conveyed the OKL's own dive-bombing capability request to [[Ernst Heinkel]] concerning the He 177, who vehemently opposed such an idea, which ruined its development as a heavy bomber.&lt;ref&gt;Murray 1983, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mobilisation, 1938 - 1939===
By the summer of 1939, the Luftwaffe had nine ''Jagdgeschwader'' (fighter wings) mostly equipped with Messerschmitt Bf 109, four '[[Organization of the Luftwaffe during World War II#Types of Geschwader|''Zerstörergeschwader'']] (destroyer wings) equipped with the Messerschmitt Bf 110 heavy fighter, 11 ''[[Kampfgeschwader]]'' (bomber wings) equipped with mainly the Heinkel He 111 and the Dornier Do 17Z, and four ''Sturzkampfgeschwader'' (dive bomber wings).&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 79 (''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt; The Junkers Ju 88 had encountered design difficulties, as a result only 12 were available when hostilities commenced. The ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s strength at this time stood at 373,000 personnel (208,000 parachute troops, 107,000 in the Flak Corps and 58,000 in the Signals Corps). Aircraft strength was 4,201 operational aircraft; 1,191 bombers, 361 dive bombers, 788 fighters, 431 heavy fighters, and 488 transports. Despite deficiencies it was an impressive force.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, even by the spring of 1940, the ''Luftwaffe'' still had not mobilized fully. Despite the shortage of raw-materials ''Generalluftzeugmesiter'' Ernst Udet, had increased production through introducing a 10 hour working day for aviation industries and rationalizing of production. During this period 30 ''Kampfstaffeln'' and 16 ''Jagdstaffeln'' were produced. A further five ''Zerstorergruppen'' were created (JGr 101, 102,126,152 and 176), all equipped with the Bf 110.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 23. (''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Luftwaffe'' also greatly expanded its aircrew training programs by 42%, to 63 flying schools. These facilities were moved to eastern Germany, away from possible Allied threats. The number of aircrew reached 4,727, an increase of 31%. However, the rush to complete this rapid expansion scheme resulted in the deaths of 997 personnel and another 700 wounded. 946 aircraft were also destroyed in these accidents. The number of aircrew completing their training was up to 3,941, The ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s entire strength was now 2.2 million personnel.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 24.(''Luftwaffe at War: Gathering storm'')&lt;/ref&gt;

==Luftwaffe organization==
{{Main|Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933-1945)}}

===Luftwaffe commanders===
[[File:Goering1932.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Hermann Göring. Göring was commander-in-chief of the ''Luftwaffe'' until April 1945.]]
[[File:Nuremberg Trials retouched.jpg|thumb|right|Nuremberg Trials. Defendants in the dock. The main target of the prosecution was [[Hermann Göring]] (at the left edge on the first row of benches), considered to be the most important surviving official in the [[Third Reich|Third ''Reich'']] after [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]]'s death.]]
Throughout the history of the ''[[Third Reich]]'', the ''Luftwaffe'' had only two commanders-in-chief. The first was [[Hermann Göring]], the second was ''[[Generaloberst]]'' [[Robert Ritter von Greim]] as the second (and last) commander-in-chief of the ''Luftwaffe'', concomitant with his promotion to ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'', the last German officer in World War II to be promoted to the highest rank. Other officers promoted to the second highest military rank in Germany were [[Albert Kesselring]], [[Hugo Sperrle]], [[Erhard Milch]], and [[Wolfram von Richthofen]].

At the end of the war, with [[Battle of Berlin|Berlin surrounded]] by the [[Red Army]], [[Göring Telegram|Göring sent a telegram]] to Hitler suggesting he take over leadership of the ''Reich''.&lt;ref&gt;Killen 2003, p. 291.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler interpreted this as an ultimatum and coup. Hitler ordered his arrest and execution. Göring's SS guards did not carry out the order and he was arrested by the United States Army in Bavaria on 9 May 1945. Göring was prosecuted at the [[Nuremberg Trials]] after the war. The indictments were for:
# Participation in a [[Conspiracy (crime)|common plan or conspiracy]] for the accomplishment of a [[crime against peace]]
# Planning, initiating and waging [[war of aggression|wars of aggression]] and other crimes against peace
# [[War crime]]s
# [[Crime against humanity|Crimes against humanity]]
He was found guilty on all four counts and sentenced to death by [[hanging]]. He appealed to the court requesting to be shot as a soldier. The court refused. However, Göring defied the sentence and committed [[suicide]] by taking [[potassium cyanide]].&lt;ref&gt;Killen 2003, p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sperrle was prosecuted at the [[High Command Trial|OKW Trial]], one of the last twelve of the [[Nuremberg Trials]] after the war. He was acquitted on all four counts of all charges. He died in [[Munich]] in 1953.

===Organization and chain of command===
At the start of the war the ''Luftwaffe'' had four ''Luftflotten'' (&quot;air fleets&quot;), each responsible for roughly a quarter of Germany. As the war progressed more air fleets were created as the areas under German rule expanded. As one example,  [[Luftflotte 5|''Luftflotte'' 5]] was created in 1940 to direct operations in Norway and Denmark, and other ''Luftflotten'' were created as necessary. Each ''Luftflotte'' would contain several ''Fliegerkorps'' (Air Corps), ''Fliegerdivision'' (Air Division), ''Jagdkorps'' (Fighter Corps), ''Jagddivision'' (Air Division) or ''Jagdfliegerführer'' (Fighter Air Command). Each formations would have attached to it a number of units, usually several ''Geschwader'', but also independent ''Staffeln'' and ''[[Kampfgruppen]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feldgrau.com/luftorg.html Luftwaffe Operational Organisation]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Luftflotten'' were also responsible for the training aircraft and schools in their operational areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ketley and Rolfe, p.4&quot;&gt;Ketley and Rolfe, p.4.&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''Geschwader'' was commanded by a ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'', with the [[Military rank|rank]] of either ''[[Major]]'', ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' ([[Lieutenant Colonel]]) or ''[[Oberst]]'' ([[Colonel]]). Other &quot;staff&quot; officers within the unit with administrative duties included the [[adjutant]], technical officer, and operations officer, who were usually (though not always) experienced [[Aircrew member|aircrew]] or pilots still flying on operations. Other specialist staff were [[navigation]], [[Military communications|signals]] and [[Military intelligence|intelligence]] personnel. A ''Stabschwarm'' ([[headquarters]] [[Flight (military unit)|flight]]) was attached to each ''Geschwader''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luftwaffe Tactical Organisation&quot;&gt;[http://www.feldgrau.com/luftorg.html Luftwaffe Tactical Organisation]&lt;/ref&gt;

''Jagdgeschwader'' (Fighter wings) (JG) was a fighter Geschwader (literally &quot;hunting wing&quot;), typically equipped with Bf 109 or Fw 190 aircraft flying in the fighter or fighter-bomber roles. It consisted of groups (''Gruppen''), which in turn consisted of ''Jagdstaffel'' (fighter squadrons). Hence, Fighter Wing 1 was JG 1, its first ''Gruppe'' (group) was I./JG 1, using a [[Roman numeral]] for the ''Gruppe'' number only, and its first ''Staffel'' (squadron) was 1./JG 1. ''Geschwader'' strength was usually 120 - 125 aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luftwaffe Tactical Organisation&quot;/&gt;

Each ''Gruppe'' was commanded by a ''Kommandeur'', and a ''Staffel'' by a ''Staffelkapitãn''. However, these were ''appointments'', not ranks, within the ''Luftwaffe''. Usually, the ''Kommodore'' would hold the rank of ''Oberstleutnant'' (lieutenant colonel) or, exceptionally, an ''Oberst'' (colonel). Even a ''Leutnant'' (second lieutenant) could find himself commanding a ''Staffel''.

Similarly, a bomber wing was a ''Kampfgeschwader'' (KG), a night fighter wing was a ''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' (NJG), a dive-bomber wing was a ''Stukageschwader'' (StG), and units equivalent to those in RAF Coastal Command, with specific responsibilities for coastal patrols and search and rescue duties, were ''Küstenfliegergruppen'' (Kü.Fl. Gr.). Specialist bomber groups were known as ''Kampfgruppen'' (KGr). The strength of ''Geschwader'' was about 80 - 90 aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luftwaffe Tactical Organisation&quot;/&gt;

==Spanish Civil War==
{{Main|Operational history of the Luftwaffe (1939–1945)}}
[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H25224, Guernica, Ruinen.jpg|thumb|300px|Ruins of Guernica (1937)]]
The ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s [[Condor Legion]] experimented with new doctrine and aircraft during the [[Spanish Civil War]]. It helped the ''[[Falange]]'' under [[Francisco Franco]] to defeat the Republican forces. Over 20,000 German airman gained combat experience that would give the ''Luftwaffe'' an important advantage going into the Second World War. One infamous operation was the bombing of [[Guernica]] in the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque country]]. It is commonly assumed this attack was the result of a &quot;terror doctrine&quot; in ''Luftwaffe'' doctrine. The ''Luftwaffe'' did not apparently have an official policy of terror bombing in which civilians were deliberately targeted, but the effects of the raids on Guernica and [[Madrid]] caused many civilian casualties and a wave of protests in the democracies. It has been suggested that the bombing of Guernica was carried out for military tactical reasons, in support of ground operations, but the town was not directly involved in any fighting at that point in time. It was not until 1942 that the Germans started to develop bombing policy in which civilians were the primary target, although the [[The Blitz]] on [[London]] and many other British cities involved indiscriminate bombing of civilian areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corum 1997, p. 7&quot;/&gt;

==Second World War==
When the Second World War began, the ''Luftwaffe'' was one of most technologically advanced Air Forces in the world. During the [[Polish Campaign]] that triggered the war, it established [[air superiority]], and then [[air supremacy]], quickly. It supported German Army (''[[Heer]]'') operations which ended the campaign in five weeks. The ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s performance was as the ''[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]'' had hoped. The ''Luftwaffe'' had rendered invaluable support to the Army,&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; mopping up pockets of resistance. Goring was delighted with the performance.&lt;ref&gt;Hooton 2007, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; Command and control problems were experienced, but owing to the flexibility and improvisation of both the Army and ''Luftwaffe'', these problems were solved. The ''Luftwaffe'' was to have in place a ground-to-air communication system, which played a vital role in the success of ''[[Fall Gelb]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley 1998, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the spring of 1940, the ''Luftwaffe'' assisted the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' and ''Heer'' in the daring [[Battle of Denmark|invasion of Denmark]] and [[Norway]], ''[[Operation Weserübung]]''. Flying in reinforcements and winning air superiority, the ''Luftwaffe'' contributed decisively to the German conquest and expulsion of the [[Western Allies]] from [[Scandinavia]].&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 274-275&lt;/ref&gt;
In the summer of 1940, the ''Luftwaffe'' contributed to the unexpected success in the [[Battle of France]]. It helped destroy three Allied Air Forces and secure the defeat of [[France]] in just over six weeks.&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, pp. 275-277.&lt;/ref&gt; However, during the [[Battle of Dunkirk]] it experienced its first failure. Despite intense bombing, it could not deliver Goring's promise to destroy the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)|British Expeditionary Force]], which escaped to continue the war.&lt;ref&gt;Killen 2003, pp. 114-116.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Spitfires camera gun film shows tracer ammunition.jpg|thumb|left|[[Gun camera]] film shows tracer ammunition from a Supermarine Spitfire Mark I of [[No. 609 Squadron RAF]], flown by [[Flight Lieutenant]] J H G McArthur, hitting a [[Heinkel He 111]] on its starboard quarter.]]
During the [[Battle of Britain]], the ''Luftwaffe'' experienced its first defeat. Despite causing severe damage to the [[Royal Air Force]]'s infrastructure and British cities during the subsequent [[The Blitz|Blitz]], it failed to achieve the [[air superiority]] Hitler demanded for ''[[Operation Sea Lion]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Killen 2003, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; The invasion was cancelled in December 1940, when Hitler ordered preparations to be made for ''[[Operation Barbarossa]]'', the invasion of the [[Soviet Union]].
The following spring, the ''Luftwaffe'' helped its [[Axis powers|Axis]] partner, [[Italy]] secure victory in the [[Balkans Campaign (World War II)|Balkans Campaign]] and continued to support the Italians in the [[Mediterranean, Middle East and African theatres of World War II|Mediterranean, Middle East and African theatres]] until May 1945.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 141-2497, Flugzeug Me 262A auf Flugplatz.jpg|thumb|right|Me 262 A, circa 1944/45. The ''Luftwaffe'' produced advanced fighter aircraft in an effort to turn the tide of the air war in 1944 and 1945]]
In June 1941, Germany invaded the Soviet Union. The ''Luftwaffe'' achieved huge operational successes, destroying thousands of Soviet aircraft. But it failed to destroy the [[Red Air Force]]. Due to a lack of [[Strategic bomber]]s, the ''Luftwaffe'' could not strike at Soviet production centers regularly or with the needed force.&lt;ref&gt;Killen 2003, pp. 171-184.&lt;/ref&gt; As the war dragged on, the ''Luftwaffe'' was eroded in strength. The defeats at the [[Battle of Stalingrad]] and [[Battle of Kursk]] ensured the gradual decline of the ''Wehrmacht'' on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]].

Meanwhile, the ''Luftwaffe'' continued to defend [[German–occupied Europe]] against the growing offensive power of [[RAF Bomber Command]] and the [[United States Army Air Force]]s. The ''[[Defense of the Reich]]'' campaign gradually destroyed the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s fighter arm. Despite using advanced Jet and rocket propelled aircraft, it was overwhelmed by Allied numbers and a lack of trained pilots and fuel. A last ditch attempt, known as &quot;[[Operation Bodenplatte]]&quot;, to win air superiority on 1 January 1945 failed. Afterwards the ''Luftwaffe'' had ceased to be an effective fighting force.

==Omissions and failures==
===Mistakes in Command: The lack of aerial defense===
The failure of the Luftwaffe in the ''[[Defense of the Reich]]'' campaign was a result of a number of factors. The ''Luftwaffe'' lacked an effective air defense system early in the war. [[Adolf Hitler]]'s foreign policy had pushed Germany into war before these defenses could be fully developed. The ''Luftwaffe'' was forced to improvise and construct its defenses during the war itself.
The daylight actions over German controlled territory were sparse in 1939-1940. The responsibility of the defense of German air space fell to the ''Luftgaukommandos'' (air district commands). The defense systems relied mostly on the ''[[Anti-aircraft warfare|Flak]]'' arm. The defenses were not coordinated and communication was poor. This lack of understanding between the Flak and flying branches of the defense would plague the ''Luftwaffe'' throughout the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell &amp; Muller 2007, p. 42&quot;&gt;Caldwell &amp; Muller 2007, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler in particular wanted the defense to rest on anti-aircraft artillery as it gave the civilian population a &quot;psychological crutch&quot; no matter how ineffective the weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, p. 132&quot;&gt;Murray 1938, p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the battles fought by the ''Luftwaffe'' on the Western Front would be against the RAF's ''Circus'' raids and the occasional daylight raid into German air space. This was a fortunate position since the ''Luftwaffe's'' strategy of focusing its striking power on one front started to unravel with the failure of ''[[Operation Barbarossa]]'', the invasion of the [[Soviet Union]]. The &quot;peripheral&quot; strategy of the ''Luftwaffe'' between 1939-1940 had been to deploy its fighter defenses at the edges of Axis occupied territory, with little protecting the inner depths.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell &amp; Muller 2007, p. 46&quot;&gt;Caldwell &amp; Muller 2007, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover the front line units in the West were complaining about the poor numbers and performance of aircraft. Units complained of lack of ''Zerstörer'' aircraft with all-weather capabilities and the &quot;lack of climbing power of the Bf 109&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell &amp; Muller 2007, p. 46&quot; /&gt; The ''Luftwaffe's'' technical edge was slipping as the only formidable new aircraft in the German arsenal was the [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]. ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Erhard Milch]] was to assist [[Ernst Udet]] with aircraft production increases and introduction of more modern types of fighter aircraft. However, they explained at a meeting of the ''Reich Industrial Council'' on the 18 September 1941 that the new next generation aircraft had failed to materialise, and obsolescent types had to be continued to keep up with the growing need for replacements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell &amp; Muller 2007, p. 46&quot; /&gt;

The build up of the ''[[Jagdwaffe]]'' (Fighter Force) was too rapid and its quality suffered. It was not put under a unified command until 1943, which also affected performance. Of the nine ''Jagdgeschwader'' in existence in 1939, no further units were built until 1942, and the years of 1940-1941 were wasted. The ''[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]'' failed to construct a strategy, instead its command style was reactionary, and its measures not as effective without thorough planning. This was particularly apparent with the ''Sturmbock'' units which were armed with heavy 20&amp;nbsp;mm and 30&amp;nbsp;mm cannon to destroy heavy bombers. This increase in weight affected the performance of the Fw 190 and Bf 109 at a time when the two aircraft were meeting large numbers of equal if not superior Allied types.&lt;ref&gt;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mistakes in development and equipment===
[[File:HE 177 ground.JPG|thumb|left|200px|The greatest failure for any German aircraft design in WW II was the always-troubled Heinkel He 177, one shown here captured by the Free French near the war's end.]] 
A significant failure in terms of technological development was not to develop a long-range bomber and capable long-range fighters during this period leaving the ''Luftwaffe'' unable to conduct a meaningful strategic bombing campaign throughout the war.&lt;ref&gt;Bergström 2007, p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this does not take into the account that Germany's economic situation suffered from limited resources - mainly raw materials like oil and [[aluminium]] - which did not provide for much beyond a tactical air force.  Thus the ''Luftwaffe's'' reliance on tactical mid-range, twin engined medium bombers and short range dive-bombers was a rational option under these circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Homze 1976, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bergström 2007, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; It might also be argued that the ''Luftwaffe's'' ''Kampfgeschwader'' were perfectly capable of attacking strategic targets, but the lack of a capable long range escort fighter left the bombers unable to carry out their missions effectively against determined and well organised fighter opposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corum 1997, p. 282&quot;&gt;Corum 1997, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;  The largest failure for the ''Kampfgeschwader'', however, was saddling them with an aircraft meant to be as big and as apparently capable as any [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] four-engined &quot;heavy bomber&quot; - the perpetually-troubled [[Heinkel He 177]] - which had been condemned to being designed to carry out moderate angle [[dive bombing]] missions from the day that the RLM accepted it for production in November 1937, making it overweight from the start, and mandating design features that led its &quot;welded-together engines&quot;, a pair of cumbersome Daimler-Benz DB 606 &quot;power systems&quot;, to perpetually catching fire in flight during operational missons over both the Eastern Front and the United Kingdom.
 [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1978-043-02, Focke-Wulf Fw 200 C Condor.jpg|thumb|150px|Arguably, one of the greatest failures was the neglect of naval aviation in the western theatre, 1939-1941.]]
Another failure of procurement and equipment was a lack of a dedicated [[Naval aviation|naval air arm]]. General Felmy had already expressed a desire to build a naval air arm to support ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' operations in the [[Atlantic]] and British waters. Britain was dependent on food and raw materials from its Empire and [[North America]]. Felmy pressed this case firmly throughout 1938 and 1939, and, on 31 October 1939, ''[[Großadmiral]]'' [[Erich Raeder]] sent a strongly worded letter to Göring  in support of such proposals. The current [[Heinkel He 115]] and [[Dornier Do 18]] [[flying boat]]s were too slow and short ranged. The [[Dornier Do 217]] would have been ideal, but suffered production problems. Raeder also complained about the poor standard of aerial torpedoes, although their design was the ''Kriegsmarine's'' responsibility. (See: [[Heinkel He 111 operational history#Torpedo bomber operations|Heinkel He 111 torpedo bomber operations]])&lt;ref&gt;Corum 1997, p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt; Without specialised naval aircraft, the ''Luftwaffe'' was forced to improvise. The [[Focke-Wulf Fw 200]] ''Condor'' was not suitable as a bomber, lacking speed armour and bomb load capacity. Nevertheless this civilian transport was adapted to the long-range reconnaissance and anti-shipping roles and, between August 1940 and February 1941, Fw 200s sank 85 vessels for a claimed total of 363,000 Grt. Had the ''Luftwaffe'' focused on naval aviation, Germany ''might'' well have been in a position to win the [[Battle of the Atlantic (1939–1945)|Battle of the Atlantic]]. However, Raeder and the Navy failed to press for naval air power until the war began, mitigating the ''Luftwaffe's'' responsibility. In addition, Göring regarded any other branch of the German mlitary developing its own aviation as an encroachment on his authority and continually frustrated the navy's attempts to build its own airpower.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corum 1997, p. 282&quot;/&gt;

The absence of a strategic bomber force for the Luftwaffe, following General Wever's accidental death in 1936 and the end of the [[Ural bomber]] program he fostered before the invasion of Poland, would not be addressed again until the authorization of the ''[[Bomber B]]'' design competition in July 1939, which sought to replace the medium bomber force with which the Luftwaffe was to begin the war, with more advanced, twin-engined high speed bomber aircraft fitted with pairs of relatively &quot;high-power&quot; engines of 1,500&amp;nbsp;kW (2,000&amp;nbsp;hp) output levels and upwards each, that would also be able to function as shorter range heavy bombers.  The spring 1942 ''[[Amerika Bomber]]'' program also sought to produce trans-oceanic range strategic bomber designs for the Luftwaffe, but both the Bomber B and Amerika Bomber programs were victims of the continued emphasis of the Wehrmacht's insistence for the Luftwaffe to support the Army as its primary mission, as well as the increasingly devastating results of the RAF Bomber Command at night, and by 1943 the [[USAAF]]'s Eighth and Fifteenth Air Forces' heavy bomber raids by daylight on the German aviation industry, which catastrophically diminished the Third Reich's overall aviation production capacity later in World War II.  

The RLM lacked a technical-tactical department, that would combine the two elements for better efficiency.{{Clarify|Elucidate - what two elements?|date=March 2010}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;&gt;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt;
As a result all fighter and bomber development was oriented toward short range aircraft, as they could be produced in greater numbers, rather than quality long range aircraft, something that put the ''Luftwaffe'' at a disadvantage as early as the Battle of Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt; Production was also slow, not reaching maximum output until 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt; Production of fighters was not given priority until 1944; [[Adolf Galland]] commented that this should have occurred at least a year earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt; Galland also points to the mistakes made in the development of the Me 262 jet which could have entered service in 1943 when the outcome of the air-war was still in doubt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt; Types that were obsolete were kept in production for far too long, in particular the Ju 87 ''Stuka'', and the Bf 109.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt;

===Production failures===
The failure of German production was evident from the start of the Battle of Britain. By the end of 1940 the ''Luftwaffe'' had suffered heavy losses and needed to regroup. Deliveries of new aircraft were insufficient to meet the drain on resources; the ''Luftwaffe'', unlike the RAF, was failing to expand its pilot and aircraft numbers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy 1980, p. 32&quot;&gt;Overy 1980, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; This was partly owing to production planning failures before the war and the demands of the Army. Nevertheless, the German aircraft industry was being outproduced in 1940. In terms of [[fighter aircraft]] production, the British exceeded their production plans by 43 percent, while the Germans remained 40 percent ''behind'' target by the summer 1940. In fact German production in fighters fell from 227 to 177 per month between July and September 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy 1980, p. 32&quot;/&gt; One of the many reasons for the failure of the ''Luftwaffe'' in 1940 was that it did not have the operational and material means to destroy the British aircraft industry.&lt;ref&gt;Overy 1980, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

No effort was made to address the low production output of the German aviation industry to support the expected increased attrition rates. The so-called &quot;Göring program&quot; envisaged the defeat of the Soviet Union in 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, p. 133&quot;&gt;Murray 1983, p. 133.&lt;/ref&gt; Erhard Milch's reforms expanded production rates. In 1941 an average of 981 aircraft (including 311 fighters) were produced each month.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, p. 133&quot; /&gt; In 1942 this rose to 1,296 aircraft of which 434 were fighters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, p. 133&quot; /&gt;
Milch's planned production increases were initially opposed. But in June, he was granted materials for 900 fighters per month as the average output. By the winter of 1941-1942 just 39 percent of the fighter force was operational and possessed just 60 more combat aircraft than it did in June 1941 despite its increased commitments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, p. 138&quot;&gt;Murray 1983, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout 1942 the ''Luftwaffe'' was out produced in fighter aircraft by 250 percent and in twin-engine aircraft by 196 percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, p. 139&quot;&gt;Murray 1983, p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt;

The appointment of [[Albert Speer]] as ''Minister of Armaments'' increased production. However the intensification of Allied bombing caused the dispersion of production and prevented an efficient acceleration of expansion. The German aviation production reached about 36,000 combat aircraft for 1944. However by the time this was achieved the ''Luftwaffe'' lacked the fuel and trained pilots to make this achievement worth while.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, pp. 253-255&quot;&gt;Murray 1983, pp. 253-255.&lt;/ref&gt;
The failure to maximize production immediately after the failures in the Soviet Union and North Africa ensured the ''Luftwaffe's'' effective defeat in the period of September 1943 - February 1944. Despite the tactical victories won, they failed to achieve a decisive victory. By the time production reached acceptable levels, as so many other factors had for the Luftwaffe late in the war, it was too little too late.&lt;ref name=&quot;Murray 1983, pp. 253-255&quot; /&gt;

===Mistakes in pilot selection and training===
The bomber arm was given preference and received the &quot;better&quot; pilots. Later, fighter pilot leaders were few in numbers as a result of this. As with the late shift to fighter production, the ''Luftwaffe'' pilot schools did not give the fighter pilot schools preference soon enough. The ''Luftwaffe'', the ''OKW'' argued, was still an offensive weapon, and its primary focus was on producing bomber pilots. This attitude prevailed until the second half of 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt; During the ''[[Defence of the Reich]]'' campaign in 1943 and 1944, there were not enough commissioned fighter pilots and leaders to meet attrition rates;&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt; as the need arose to replace aircrew as attrition rates increased the quality of [[Defence of the Reich#Training deterioration|pilot training deteriorated]] rapidly. Later this was made worse by [[Defence of the Reich#German training and tactics response|fuel shortages for pilot training]]. Overall this meant a fall on training on operational types, formation flying, gunnery training, combat training and a total lack of instrument training.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt;

===Mistakes in leadership===
At the beginning of the war commanders were replaced with younger commanders too quickly. These younger commanders had to learn &quot;in the field&quot; rather than entering a post fully qualified. Training of formation leaders was not systematical until 1943, which was far too late, with the ''Luftwaffe'' already stretched. The ''Luftwaffe'' thus lacked a cadre of Staff officers to setup, man and pass on experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;Caldwell and Muller 2007, p. 287&quot;/&gt;

Moreover, ''Luftwaffe'' leadership from the start poached the training command, which undermined its ability to replace losses,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ketley and Rolfe, p.4&quot;/&gt; while also planning for &quot;short sharp campaigns&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ketley and Rolfe, p.8&quot;&gt;Ketley and Rolfe, p.8.&lt;/ref&gt; which did not pertain. Moreover, no plans were laid for [[night fighter]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ketley and Rolfe, p.8&quot;/&gt; In fact, when protests were raised, Jeschonnek himself said, &quot;First we've got to beat Russia, then we can start training!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ketley and Rolfe, quoted p.4.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Luftwaffe ground forces==
One of the unique characteristics of the ''Luftwaffe'' (as opposed to other independent air forces) was the possession of an organic [[paratrooper]] force called ''[[Fallschirmjäger]]''. These were established in 1938. They saw action in their proper role during 1940–1941, most notably in the capture of the Belgian army fortress at the [[Battle of Fort Eben-Emael]] and the [[Battle for The Hague]] in May 1940, and during the [[Battle of Crete]] in May 1941. However, more than 4,000 ''Fallschirmjäger'' were killed during the Crete operation.&lt;ref&gt;Mayer &amp; Taylor, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, although continuing to be trained in parachute delivery, paratroopers were only used in a parachute role for smaller-scale operations, such as the successful rescue of [[Benito Mussolini]], the then-deposed dictator of Italy in 1943. ''Fallschirmjäger'' formations were then used as crack foot infantry in all theatres of the war. 

During 1942 surplus ''Luftwaffe'' personnel was used to form the [[Luftwaffe Field Division]]s, standard infantry divisions that were used chiefly as rear echelon units to free up front line troops.  From 1943, the ''Luftwaffe'' also had an armoured paratroop division called [[Fallschirm-Panzer Division 1 Hermann Göring]], which was expanded to a ''[[Panzerkorps]]'' in 1944.

==War crimes==
{{See also|Nazi human experimentation}}
Throughout the war civilians or prisoners were used as [[Human subject research|human guinea pigs]] in testing ''Luftwaffe'' equipment. It is unclear whether these tests were carried out by ''Luftwaffe'' personnel or on the orders of OKL. These illegal tests are classified as [[war crimes]] and were carried out on the ''Luftwaffe's'' behalf.
 
In 1941, experiments with the intent of discovering means to prevent and treat [[hypothermia]] were carried out. [[Freezing]]/[[hypothermia]] experiments were conducted for the [[Nazi]] high command to simulate the conditions the armies suffered on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], as the German forces were ill-prepared for the cold weather they encountered. The principal locales were [[Dachau concentration camp|Dachau]] and [[Auschwitz]]. Dr [[Sigmund Rascher]], an ''[[Schutzstaffel|SS]]'' doctor based at [[Dachau concentration camp|Dachau]], reported directly to ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] and publicised the results of his freezing experiments at the 1942 medical conference entitled &quot;Medical Problems Arising from Sea and Winter&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NOVA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Tyson, Peter |title=Holocaust on Trial: The Experiments |work=NOVA Online |url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/holocaust/experiside.html |accessdate=2008-03-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately 100 people are reported to have died as a result of these experiments.&lt;ref&gt;Neurnberg Military Tribunal, Volume I · [http://www.mazal.org/archive/nmt/01/NMT01-T200.htm Page 200]&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 1942, prisoners at Dachau concentration camp were used by Rascher in experiments to perfect [[ejection seat]]s at high altitudes. A [[pressure vessel|low-pressure chamber]] containing these prisoners was used to simulate conditions at altitudes of up to 20,000&amp;nbsp;m (66,000&amp;nbsp;ft). It was rumoured that Rascher performed [[vivisection]]s on the brains of victims who survived the initial experiment.&lt;ref name=Cockburn&gt;{{cite book |last=Cockburn |first=Alexander |title=Whiteout:The CIA, Drugs, and the Press |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=s5qIj_h_PtkC&amp;pg=PA149&amp;dq=%22sigmund+rascher%22+brain |accessdate=2008-01-04 |year=1998 |publisher=Verso |isbn=1859841392 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 200 subjects, 80 died outright, and the others were executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;NOVA&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
Note: The name of the book appears next to some author references. The reason for this is that two or more of their sources/works are used for this article, and a distinction is required as readers can then trace the citation to the correct source.
{{Reflist|2}}

==See also==
* [[German Air Fleets in World War II]]
* [[List of World War II military aircraft of Germany]]
* [[Military Ranks of Luftwaffe (1933-45)]]
* [[Ural bomber]]
* [[Schnellbomber]]
* [[Bomber B]]
* [[Amerika Bomber]]
* [[Luftwaffe serviceable aircraft strengths (1940-1945)|''Luftwaffe'' serviceable aircraft strengths (1940-1945)]]
* [[Milch Trial|Trial of Erhardt Milch]]
* [[High Command Trial]]
* [[List of World War II aces from Germany]]
* [[List of German World War II jet aces]]
* [[List of German World War II Ground Attack aces]]
* [[List of German World War II night fighter aces]]
* [[German war crimes]]
* [[Bombing of Guernica]]
* [[Nazi human experimentation]]
* [[Doctors' Trial]]

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{citation|surname1=Bekker|given1=Cajus|title=Angriffshohe 4000|publisher=|place=Germany|year=1964}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Bergström|given1=Christer|title=Barbarossa - The Air Battle: July–December 1941|publisher=Chervron/Ian Allan|place=London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-85780-270-2.
* {{citation|surname1=Bergstrom|given1=Christer|title=Stalingrad - The Air Battle: November 1942 - February 1943 |publisher=Chervron/Ian Allan|place=London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-85780-276-4 .
* {{citation|surname1=Bergström|given1=Christer|title=Kursk - The Air Battle: July 1943|publisher=Chervron/Ian Allan|place=London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-903223-88-8.
* {{citation|surname1=Bergstrom|given1=Christer|surname2=Pegg|given2=Martin|title=Jagdwaffe: The War in Russia: January–October 1942|publisher=Classic Colours|place=London|year=2003}}. ISBN 1-903223-23-7.
* {{citation|surname1=Buckley|given1=John|title=Air Power in the Age of Total War|publisher=UCL Press|place=West Midlands|year=1999}}. ISBN 1-85728-589-1
* {{citation|surname1=Bergstrom|given1=Christer|surname2=Mikhailov|given2=Andrey|title=Black Cross/Red Star-Vol. 1, Operation Barbarossa 1941|publisher=Classic Colours|place=London|year=2003}}. ISBN 978-0-935553-48-2 .
* {{citation|surname1=Bowmen|given1=Martin|surname2=Boiten|given2=Theo|title=Battles with the Luftwaffe: The Air War Over Germany 1942-1945|publisher=Collins|place=London|year=2001}}. ISBN 978-0-007113-63-7
* {{citation|surname1=Bungay|given1=Stephen|title=The Most Dangerous Enemy: A History of the Battle of Britain|publisher=Aurum Press|place=London|year=2000}}. ISBN 1-85410-721-6.
* {{citation|surname1=Caldwell|given1=Donald|surname2=Muller|given2=Richard|title=The Luftwaffe over Germany: Defense of the Reich|publisher=Greenhill Books|place=London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-85367-712-0
* {{citation|surname1=Cooper|given1=Mathew|title=The German Air Force 1933-1945: An Anatomy of Failure|publisher=Jane's Publishing Incorporated|place=New York|year=1981}}. ISBN 0-531-03733 9
* {{citation|surname1=Corum|given1=J.F.|editor=Mueller, R. &amp; Volkmann, H.E.|chapter=Staerken und Schwaechen der Luftwaffe|title=Die Wehrmacht: Mythos und Realitaet|publisher=Oldenbourg Verlag|place=Muenchen|year=1999}}
* [[James Corum|Corum, James]]. 'The Luftwaffe's Army Support Doctrine, 1918-1941' in ''The Journal of Military History'', Vol. 59, No. 1 (Jan., 1995), pp.&amp;nbsp;53–76
* [[James Corum|Corum, James]]. ''The Roots of Blitzkrieg: Hans von Seeckt and German Military Reform''. Modern War Studies. Lawrence: University Press of Kansas. 1992. ISBN 070060541X.
* [[James Corum|Corum, James]]. ''The Luftwaffe: Creating the Operational Air War, 1918-1940''. Kansas University Press. 1997. ISBN 9780700608362
* {{citation|surname1=Crawford|given1=Steve|title=Eastern Front, Day by Day|publisher=Spellmount Publications|place=London|year=2006}}. ISBN 1-86227-359-6.
* {{citation|surname1=Drabkin |given1=Artem|title=The Red Air Force at War :Barbarossa and the Retreat to Moscow: Recollections of Soviet Fighter Pilots on the Eastern Front |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Aviation Publications|place=|year=2007}}.ISBN 978-1-84415-563-7
* {{citation|surname1=Dressel&amp;Griehl|given1=Joachim and Manfred|title=Bombers of the Luftwaffe|publisher=Arms and Armour:DAG Publications|place=London|year=1994}}.ISBN 1-85409-140-9
* {{citation|surname1=Dye|given1=Peter J.|journal=Air Force Journal of Logistics|title=Logistics in the Battle of Britain|year=Winter 2000}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Faber|given1=Harold|title=Luftwaffe: An analysis by former Luftwaffe generals|publisher=Sidgwick &amp; Jackson|place=London|year=1979}}. ISBN 0-283-98516-X
* {{citation|surname1=Goss|given1=Chriss|title=Dornier 17: In Focus|publisher= Red Kite| year=2005}}ISBN 0-9546201-4-3.
* {{citation|surname1=Goss|given1=Chriss|title=The Bombers'Battle: Personal Accounts of the Battle of Britain by Luftwaffe Bomber Crews July–October 1940|publisher= Crecy Publishing| year=2000}}ISBN 978-0-947554-82-8
* {{citation|surname1=Hayward|given1=Joel S.|title=[[Stopped At Stalingrad|Stopped at Stalingrad]]: The Luftwaffe and Hitler's Defeat in the East 1942-1943|publisher=University Press of Kansas|year=2001}}. ISBN 0-7006-1146-0
* {{citation|surname1=Hall|given1=Steve|surname2=Quinlan|given2=Lionel|title=KG55|publisher=red Kite|place=London|year=2000}}. ISBN 0-9538061-0-3.
* {{citation|surname1=Hess|given1=William N.|title=B-17 Flying Fortress: Combat and Development History|publisher=Motorbook International|place=St. Paul, Minnesota|year=1994}}. ISBN 0-87938-881-1
* {{citation|surname1=Holmes|given1=Tony|title= Spitfire vs Bf 109: Battle of Britain|publisher=Osprey Publishing|place=St. Oxford, London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-84603-190-8.
* {{citation|surname1=Homze|given1=Edward|title=Arming the Luftwaffe|publisher=University of Nebraska|place=Lincoln|year=1976}}. ISBN 0-8032-0872-3
* [[E.R. Hooton|Hooton, E.R.]] ''Phoenix Triumphant: The Rise and Rise of the Luftwaffe''. Brockhampton Press, London. 1994. ISBN 1-86019-964-X
* [[E.R. Hooton|Hooton, E.R.]] ''The Luftwaffe: A Study in Air Power, 1933-1945''. Classic Publications, London. 2010. ISBN 978-1-90653-718-0
* {{citation|surname1=Hooton|given1=E.R|title=Luftwaffe at War; Gathering Storm 1933-39: Volume 1|publisher=Chervron/Ian Allan|place=London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-903223-71-7.
* {{citation|surname1=Hooton|given1=E.R|title=Luftwaffe at War; Blitzkrieg in the West: Volume 2|publisher=Chervron/Ian Allan|place=London|year=2007}}. ISBN 978-1-85780-272-6.
* {{citation|surname1=Hooton|given1=E.R|title=Eagle in Flames: The Fall of the Luftwaffe|publisher=Weidenfeld Military |place=|year=1997}}. ISBN 978-1-854093-43-1 .
* {{citation|surname1=Irving|given1=D|title=The rise and fall of the Luftwaffe;: The life of Field Marshal Erhard Milch|publisher=Little, Brown|place=London|year=1974}}. ISBN 978-0-316432-38-2
* {{citation|surname1=Just|given1=Gunther. J|title=Stuka Pilot Hans Ulrich Rudel|publisher=Schiffer Military History|place=Connecticut|year=1986}}. ISBN 0-88740-252-6
* Stalin's Missed Chance (study)- [[Mikhail Meltyukhov]]
* {{citation|surname1=Kaplan|given1=Philip|title=Fighter Aces of the Luftwaffe in World War 2|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Aviation |place=|year=2007}}. ISBN 1-84415-460-2
* Ketley, Barry, and Rolfe, Mark. ''Luftwaffe Fledglings 1935-1945: Luftwaffe Training Units and their Aircraft''. Aldershot, GB: Hikoki Publications, 1996. ISBN 0-951-9899-2-8.
* {{citation|surname1=Manrho|given1=John|surname2=Putz|given2=Ron|title=Bodenplatte: The Luftwaffe's Last Hope–The Attack on Allied Airfields, New year's Day 1945|publisher=Hikoki Publications|place=|year=2004}}. ISBN 1-902109-40-6
* {{citation|surname1=Macksey |given1=K|title=The Memoirs of Field-Marshal Kesselring|publisher=GreenhillBooks|place=London|year=2006}}. ISBN978-1-853672-87-3
* {{citation|surname1=Nowarra|given1=Heinz. J|title=The Flying Pencil|publisher=Schiffer Military History|place=Connecticut|year=1990}}. ISBN 0-88740-236-4
* {{citation|surname1=Neitzel|given1=Söhnke|title=Der Einsatz der Deutschen Luftwaffe über der Nordsee und dem Atlantik: 1939–45|publisher=Bernard &amp; Graefe|place=Bonn|year=1995}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Pegg|given1=M|title= Transporter Vol. 1: Luftwaffe Transport Units 1937-1943 |publisher=Classic Publications|place=London|year=2007}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Price|given1=Alfred|title= The Last Year of the Luftwaffe: May 1944-May 1945|publisher=Greenhill|place=London|year=2001}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Ruffner|given1=Kevin|title=Luftwaffe Field Divisions, 1941-45|publisher=Osprey|place=London|year=1997}}. ISBN 1-85532-100-9
* {{citation|surname1=Scutts|given1=J.|title=Mustang Aces of the Eighth Air Force|publisher=Osprey Publishing|place=Oxford|year=1994}}. ISBN 1-85532-447-4
* {{citation|surname1=Scutts|given1=J.|title=Bf 109 Aces of North Africa and the Mediterranean|publisher=Osprey Publishing|place=Oxford|year=1994}}. ISBN 1-85532-448-2.
* {{citation|surname1=Smith|given1=Peter|title=Luftwaffe at War: Defeat in the West 1943-1945(Luftwaffe at War, Vol. 6)|publisher=Greenhill|place=London|year=1998}} ISBN 978-1-853673-18-4
* {{citation|surname1=Stenman|given1=K.|title=Luftwaffe Over Finland (Luftwaffe at War Series, Vol. 18)|publisher=Greenhill Books|place=London|year=2002}}. ISBN 978-1-853674-69-3
* {{citation|surname1=Smith|given1=Peter|title=Luftwaffe at War - The Sea Eagles: The Luftwaffe's Maritime Operations|publisher=Greenhill|place=London|year=2001}} ISBN 978-1-853674-42-6
* {{citation|surname1=Smith|given1=Peter|title=Luftwaffe at War: Stukas Over Steppe, Blitzkrieg in the East 1941-1944 (Luftwaffe at War Series , Vol. 9)|publisher=Greenhill Books|place=London|year=1999}} ISBN 978-1-853673-55-9
* {{citation|surname1=Smith|given1=R.J|surname2=Creek|given2=E.J|title=Kampfflieger: Bombers of the Luftwaffe: 1942-1943 |year=2004|place=London|publisher=Classic Publications}}. ISBN 978-1-90322-349-9
* {{citation|surname2=Taylor|given2=AJP|surname1=Mayer|given1=SL|title=History of World War II|year=1974|place=London|publisher=Octopus Books}}. ISBN 0706403991 &amp; ISBN 978-0706403992
* [[Adam Tooze|Tooze, Adam]], ''[[The Wages of Destruction|The Wages of Destruction: The Making and Breaking of the Nazi Economy]]'', London: Allen Lane, 2006. ISBN 0-7139-9566-1
* {{citation|surname1=US Air Force|given1=Air University Press|title=US Strategic Bombing Survey|url=http://zfacts.com/metaPage/lib/US-stratigic-bombing-survey-1945-totals.pdf|publisher=Air University Press|place=Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama|year=1987}}. Reprint of the Summary Reports (Europe and the Pacific) of the strategic bombing surveys conducted near the close of World War II.
* {{citation|surname1=Vasco |given1=John|title= Zerstorer: Luftwaffe Fighter Bombers and Destroyers 1939-1945: Volume 1|publisher=Classic Publications|place=|year=2005}}. ISBN 978-1-90322-357-4
* {{citation|surname1=van Creveld|given1=M.|surname2=Cranby|given2=S.|surname3=Brower|given3=K.|title= Airpower and Maneuver Warfare|publisher=Air University Press|place=|year=1994}}.
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|given1=John|year=1997|title=Junkers Ju 87 Stukageschwader 1937-41|publisher=Osprey|place=Oxford}}. ISBN 1-85532-636-1
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|year=1998|given1=John|title=Focke-Wulf Fw 190 Aces of the Russian Front|publisher=Osprey|place=Oxford}}. ISBN 1-85532-518-7.
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|given1=John|year=1999|title=Messerschmitt Bf 110 Zerstörer Aces World War Two|publisher=Osprey|place=Oxford}}. ISBN 1-85532-753-8.
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|given1=John|title=Bf109 Aces of the Russian Front|publisher=Osprey|place=Oxford|year=2003a}}. ISBN 1-84176-084-6
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|given1=John|title=Jagdgeschwader 27 'Afrika'|publisher=Osprey|place=Oxford|year=2003}}. ISBN 1-841765-38-4.
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|given1=John A.|title=Junkers Ju 87 Stukageschwader of North Africa and the Mediterranean|publisher=Osprey Publishing|place=|year=2003b}}. ISBN 1-84176-538-4
* {{citation|surname1=Weal|given1=John|title=Bf109 Defence of the Reich Aces|publisher=Osprey|place=Oxford|year=2006}}. ISBN 1-84176-879-0
* {{citation|surname1=Williamson|given1=Murray|title=Strategy for Defeat: The Luftwaffe 1933–1945|publisher=United States Government Printing|year=1983}}. ISBN 978-9997393487
* {{citation|surname1=de Zeng IV|given1=Henry L.|surname2= Stankey |given2=Douglas G.|title= Bomber Units of the Luftwaffe 1933-1945: A Reference Source: Volume 1|publisher=Midland Publishing|place=|year=2007}}.
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.jg52.de/ Traditionsgemeinschaft JG 52]
* [http://www.graf-grislawski.elknet.pl/index.htm Graf &amp; Grislawski]
* [http://www.bergstrombooks.elknet.pl/bc-rs/ Air War over the Eastern Front]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/apj94/mccrabb2.html The Pre-Normandy Air Battle]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/apj03/win03/muller.html Losing Air Superiority - A Case Study from World War II]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/gnzingr.pdf Lt.Col. Gunzinger Air Power as a Second Front - PDF File]
* [http://forum.axishistory.com/viewtopic.php?t=84436 Forum Discussion on reasons for Luftwaffe Defeat in BoB]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/apj97/win97/davis.html Davis, R. General Spaatz and D-Day]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/andrews.pdf Andrews, W.F. The Luftwaffe and the Battle for Air Superiority PDF-File]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/apj97/spr97/hayward.html Hayward, J.S. Stalingrad An Examination of Hitler's Decision to Airlift]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/apj89/carter.html Carter, W. Air Power in the Battle of the Bulge]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/ETO/Air/index.html iBiblio Hyperwar - The Air War over Europe]
* [http://www.raf.mod.uk/bombercommand/ Bomber Command War Diary Online]
* [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/afhra/ USAF Historical Research Agency at Maxwell AFB]
* [http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/bookrev/samuel.html Book Review of American Raiders] - discusses some of the Luftwaffe secrets captured at the end of the war.
* [http://lexikon.idgr.de/p/p_a/paperclip/paperclip.php German article on Operation Paperclip]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e4kKXi3QncA German wartime newsreel, showing dogfighting Luftwaffe fighters, 1942]
* [http://www.ww2.dk/ The Luftwaffe 1933-1945]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=hMFA8FJ1KXMC&amp;pg=PA174&amp;dq=defense+of+reich&amp;sig=ACfU3U1NMZ-3endfpH3FDBU6mJJMQ7CKHg#PPA177,M1 Book - Strategy for defeat : the Luftwaffe 1933-1945]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=ZDLNaRbHD7gC&amp;pg=PA84&amp;dq=%22JG+11%22+Jagdgeschwader&amp;as_brr=3#PPA81,M1 The Luftwaffe Over Germany By Donald Caldwell, Richard Muller - Details of Goring's rant for heavy bombers.]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=HP3-9NNz71sC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s#v=onepage&amp;q=luftwaffe&amp;f=false The Second World War: Europe and the Mediterranean By Thomas B. Buell, Thomas E. Griess, John H. Bradley, Jack W. Dice]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=_HkHU5RJJekC&amp;pg=PA281&amp;dq=Oberkommando+Der+Luftwaffe&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8RJ3TMrKJ4menQfs8qmXCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CGEQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=OKL&amp;f=false Eagles of the Third Reich: Men of the Luftwaffe in World War II By Samuel W. Mitcham, Jr.]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Luftwaffe}}
[[Category:Luftwaffe]]
[[Category:Air force history]]
[[Category:Aviation history of Germany]]

[[bg:Луфтвафе на Третия райх]]
[[br:Luftwaffe (1933-1945)]]
[[cs:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[da:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[de:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[es:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[it:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[nl:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[ru:Люфтваффе]]
[[sl:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[fi:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[sv:Tysklands flygvapen under andra världskriget]]
[[tr:Luftwaffe (Wehrmacht)]]
[[zh:納粹德國空軍]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
