<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="416988" ns="0" title="The Best of Both Worlds (Star Trek: The Next Generation)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television episode
| Title = The Best of Both Worlds
| Image = [[Image:Cube.jpg|270px]]
| Caption = [[Captain Jean Luc Picard]] ([[Patrick Stewart]]) and the crew of the ''[[Enterprise (Star Trek)|Enterprise]]'' confront the [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]].
| Series = [[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]
| Season = 3 and 4
| Episode = 26 and 1
| Production = 174 &amp; 175
| Airdate = {{Start date|1990|06|18}}&lt;br&gt;{{Start date|1990|09|24}}
| Writer = [[Michael Piller]]
| Director = [[Cliff Bole]]
| Music = [[Ron Jones (composer)|Ron Jones]]
| Guests =
*[[Colm Meaney]] as [[Miles O'Brien (Star Trek)|Miles O'Brien]]
*[[Elizabeth Dennehy]] as Shelby
*[[George Murdock (actor)|George Murdock]] as J.P. Hanson
*[[Whoopi Goldberg]] as [[Guinan (Star Trek character)|Guinan]]
| Prev = [[Transfigurations]]
| Next = [[Family (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Family]]
| Episode list = [[List of Star Trek: The Next Generation episodes|List of ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'' episodes]]
}}
__NOTOC__
&quot;'''The Best of Both Worlds'''&quot; is a two-part storyline (comprising the third season [[season finale|finale]] and the fourth season [[season premiere|premiere]]) from the television series ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/episodes/TNG/detail/68454.html STARTREK.COM : Detail&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/episodes/TNG/detail/68456.html STARTREK.COM : Detail&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Plot==
===Part 1===
The story occurs across [[stardate]]s 43989.1 - 44001.4 (December 2366/January 2367 by the [[Timeline of Star Trek|Okuda timeline]]). The ''Enterprise'' responds to a distress call from a [[Federation (Star Trek)|Federation]] colony, but arrives to discover the colony gone, with only a crater remaining. Based on past knowledge of what happened to colonies along the [[The Neutral Zone (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Romulan Neutral Zone]] and on a deserted planet in [[Q Who?|System J-25]], the Federation suspect [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] activity.

Admiral Hanson arrives with Lt. Commander Shelby, an expert on the Borg, who assists the crew in determining the cause of the colony's disappearance. Hanson advises [[Jean-Luc Picard|Captain Picard]] that [[William Riker|Commander Riker]] has been offered the command of a starship for the third time, and advises that Riker take the position. Although there is tension between Riker and Shelby, who has designs on his position at first officer of the ''Enterprise'', they confirm the colony was assimilated by the Borg. Hanson advises Picard that another Federation vessel encountered a strange &quot;cube-like&quot; vessel before sending a distress call that ended abruptly. The ''Enterprise'' moves to intercept and confronts a [[Borg Cube]].

The Borg demand that Picard surrender himself, although he refuses. Although initially confused by the ''Enterprise''s shield modulation, the Borg lock the vessel in a [[tractor beam]] and begin cutting open the hull.  Shelby suggests randomly changing the frequency of the ship's phasers to prevent the Borg from adapting to the attack, which frees the vessel. The ''Enterprise'' escapes to a nearby [[nebula]], with [[Geordi LaForge]] and [[Wesley Crusher]] adapting a technique suggested by Shelby to modify the deflector dish to fire a massive energy discharge capable of destroying the Borg cube. The Borg flushes the ''Enterprise'' from the nebula with magnetometric-guided charges, and then board the ship and abduct Picard.  The Borg Cube moves off at high [[warp drive (Star Trek)|warp speed]] towards Earth, with the ''Enterprise'' in pursuit.

Riker, now in command of the ship, prepares to join an away team to transport to the Cube to rescue Picard, but [[Counselor Troi]] reminds him his place is now on the bridge. Shelby leads the away team onto the Borg cube, where they discover they are ignored. The team locate Picard's uniform and communicator and then destroy power nodes inside the cube, forcing it out of warp.  As the team prepare to transport to the ''Enterprise'', they see an assimilated Picard. The Borg contact the ''Enterprise'', with Picard stating he is now &quot;Locutus of Borg&quot;, and to prepare for assimilation.  Riker orders the crew to fire the deflector dish.

===Part 2===
The deflector dish has no effect, with Locutus revealing that  as he is in possession of Picard's knowledge the Borg prepared for the attack. The Borg Cube continues at warp speed towards Earth, with the crippled ''Enterprise'' unable to follow.  Upon reporting their failure to Hansom, Riker is promoted to Captain and advised a large fleet of starships is massing at [[Battle of Wolf 359|Wolf 359]] to stop the Borg.  Learning via subspace communications that the battle is going badly, the ''Enterprise'' eventually arrives at Wolf 359 to find the fleet has been destroyed (including the ''Melbourne'', which Riker was offered to command).[[File:Science Fiction Museum and Hall of Fame 3.JPG|thumb|Headgear worn by [[Patrick Stewart]] as Locutus and arm (right) belonging to Capt. Picard's [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] captor. Displayed at [[Science Fiction Museum and Hall of Fame]], [[Seattle]].]]
The ''Enterprise'' follows the cube's warp trail, and offer to enter into negotiations with Locutus. The request is denied, but the communication reveals Locutus' exact location on the Cube.  The ''Enterprise'' locates the Borg cube, and as per a plan suggested by Shelby to Picard, separates into saucer and stardrive section respectively. Although Shelby suggested attacking with the stardrive section, Riker does the reverse and orders the saucer section to fire an [[anti-matter]] spread near the Cube, disrupting its sensors and allowing a shuttlecraft piloted by [[Data (Star Trek)|Data]] and [[Worf]] to pass the Borg shields and beam aboard the Borg cube. They successfully kidnap Locutus, although the Borg ignore this and continue to Earth, destroying all resistance. 

Data and [[Beverly Crusher|Dr. Crusher]] create a [[Brain-computer interface|neural link]] with Locutus to gain access to the Borg's [[Telepathy#Technologically enabled telepathy|collective consciousness]]. Data attempts to use the link to disable the Borg's weapons and defensive systems, but discovers they are protected from external influence.  With the Borg on the verge of invading Earth, Riker orders the ''Enterprise'' to ram the Borg cube, speed but Data asks him to wait. Picard breaks free from the Borg control and tells Data to &quot;sleep.&quot;  Data issues a low-level, unprotected command to the Borg to enter sleep mode, causing their weapons and shields to deactivate. A feedback loop builds in the Borg cube which destroys the vessel. Dr. Crusher and Data are then able to successfully remove all Borg implants from Picard.

The ''Enterprise'' moves to an orbital shipyard for extensive repairs, and Riker, although offered command of his own ship, insists on remaining as the first officer. Shelby is reassigned to a task force dedicated to rebuilding the fleet. Picard recovers slowly but is still disturbed by his ordeal.

==Reception==
The first episode won [[Emmy Award]]s for &quot;Outstanding Art Direction for a Series&quot; and
&quot;Outstanding Sound Editing for a Series&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emmys.com/award_history_search?person=&amp;program=star+trek+the+next+generation&amp;start_year=1990&amp;end_year=1990&amp;network=All&amp;web_category=All&amp;winner=All]&lt;/ref&gt;

The storyline appeared in [[TV Guide]]'s &quot;100 Most Memorable Moments in TV History&quot; (July 1, 1995) and ranked #70 on the 100 Greatest TV Episodes of All Time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071028140448/http://members.aol.com/speaker606/jim/tv.html The 100 Greatest TV episodes of all time&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine rated ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'' 37th on their list of &quot;The 50 Greatest TV Shows of All Time&quot; and cited &quot;The Best of Both Worlds, Part II&quot; as the show's best episode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.empireonline.com/50greatesttv/default.asp?tv=37|title=The 50 Greatest TV Shows of All Time|accessdate=2008-03-29|publisher=[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The episode was ranked #36 on ''[[TV Guide]]'''s list of &quot;TV's Top 100 Episodes of All Time&quot;.&lt;ref name=TVGuide100Episodes&gt;&quot;TV's Top 100 Episodes of All Time&quot; ''[[TV Guide]]''; June 15, 2009; Pages 34-49&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==
The [[Film score|musical score]] was conducted by [[Ron Jones (composer)|Ron Jones]], with a synthetic chorus used as a Borg [[leitmotif]].  The score was eventually was released as an album.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.soundtrack-express.com/osts/bestofbothworlds.htm The Best of Both Worlds - Ron Jones&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moviescore.net/reviews/sttng2.html STTNG Vol. 2: The Best Of Both Worlds by Ron Jones&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Star Trek: The Next Generation#The Best of Both Worlds, Part I .5B3.26.5D|The Best of Both Worlds}}
*{{TV.com episode|19060|The Best of Both Worlds, Part I}}
*{{TV.com episode|19061|The Best of Both Worlds, Part II}}
* {{StarTrek.com link|TNG|68454|The Best of Both Worlds, Part I}}
* {{StarTrek.com link|TNG|68456|The Best of Both Worlds, Part II}}

{{Star Trek Borg Stories}}
{{Star Trek TNG S3}}
{{Star Trek TNG S4}}
{{Star Trek TNG}}
{{Star Trek}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Best of Both Worlds, The}}
[[Category:Star Trek: The Next Generation episodes]]
[[Category:1990 television episodes]]

[[pt:The Best of Both Worlds (Star Trek: The Next Generation)]]
[[sk:Locutus z Borgov]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
