<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4182449" ns="0" title="Tablet computer"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|other forms of tablet and slate computers and devices|Tablet device (disambiguation)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2011}}
[[File:IFA 2010 Internationale Funkausstellung Berlin 03.JPG|215px|thumb|The [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] [[iPad]]]]

A '''tablet computer''', or '''tablet''', is a [[Mobile computing|mobile computer]], larger than a mobile phone or [[personal digital assistant]], integrated into a flat [[touch screen]] and primarily operated by touching the screen. It often uses an onscreen [[virtual keyboard]], a passive [[stylus pen]], or a [[digital pen]]{{Citation needed||date=September 2011}}, rather than a physical [[Keyboard (computing)|keyboard]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Editors PC Magazine&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Definition of: tablet computer|url=http://www.pcmag.com/encyclopedia_term/0,2542,t=tablet+computer&amp;i=52520,00.asp |author=Editors PC Magazine |accessdate=April 17, 2010|work=[[PC Magazine]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Editors Dictionary.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite|title=tablet computer – 1 dictionary result|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/tablet+computer |author=Editors Dictionary.com |accessdate=April 17, 2010|work=[[Dictionary.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term may also apply to a variety of [[form factor]]s that differ in position of the screen with respect to a keyboard. The standard form is called ''slate'', which does not have an integrated keyboard but may be connected to one with a [[wireless]] link or a [[USB port]]. ''Convertible'' [[notebook computer]]s have an integrated keyboard that can be hidden by a [[swivel]] joint or [[Slide (form)#Slider|slide]] joint, exposing only the screen for touch operation. ''Hybrids'' have a detachable keyboard so that the touch screen can be used as a stand-alone tablet. ''Booklets'' include two touch screens, and can be used as a notebook by displaying a virtual keyboard in one of them.

Early examples of the ''information tablet'' concept originated in the 19th and 20th centuries mainly as prototypes and concept ideas, the more prominent the Alan Kay's [[Dynabook]]. First commercial portable electronic devices based on the concept appeared at the end of the 20th century. During the 2000s Microsoft attempted a relatively unsuccessful product line with [[Microsoft Tablet PC]], which carved a niche market at hospitals and outdoor businesses. In 2010 Apple released the [[iPad]] based on the technology developed in parallel with their previous [[iPhone]], and reached worldwide commercial success.

{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

== Background ==
===History===
{{Main|History of tablet computers}}
The [[tablet computer]] and the associated special operating software is an example of [[pen computing]] technology, and thus the development of tablets has deep historical roots. 

Electrical devices with [[input/output|data input and output]] on a flat [[information display]] have existed as early as 1888.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gray&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last =Gray
| first =Elisha
| coauthors =
| title =Telautograph
| work =
| pages =
| language =
| publisher =United States Patent 386,815 (full image)
| date =1888-07-31
| url = http://www.freepatentsonline.com/386815.pdf
| accessdate =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the 20th century many devices with these characteristics have been ideated and created whether as [[blueprint]]s, [[prototype]]s or [[commercial product]]s, with the [[Dynabook]] concept in 1968 being a spiritual precursor of tablets and laptops. In addition to many academic and research systems, there  were several companies with commercial products in the 1980s

During the 2000s [[Microsoft]] attempted to define with the [[Microsoft Tablet PC]] the ''tablet personal computer'' product concept&lt;ref name=&quot;markoff&quot;&gt;John Markoff, ''The [[New York Times]]'', August 30, 1999, &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/30/business/microsoft-brings-in-top-talent-to-pursue-old-goal-the-tablet.html Microsoft brings in top talent to pursue old goal: the tablet]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; as a mobile computer for field work in business,&lt;ref name=&quot;earthweb&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://itmanagement.earthweb.com/netsys/article.php/1495701/Tablet-PC-Coming-to-an-Office-Near-You.htm|title=Tablet PC: Coming to an Office Near You?}}&lt;/ref&gt; though their devices failed to achieve widespread usage mainly due to price and [[usability]] problems that made them unsuitable outside of their limited intended purpose.&lt;ref name='BallStillDoesnt2010'&gt;Bright, Peter [http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2010/07/ballmer-and-microsoft-still-doesnt-get-the-ipad.ars Ballmer (and Microsoft) still doesn't get the iPad], [[Ars Technica]], 2010&lt;/ref&gt; 

In April 2010 [[Apple Inc.]] released the [[iPad]], a tablet computer with an emphasis on [[New media|media consumption]]. The shift in purpose, together with increased usability, battery life, simplicity, lower weight and cost, and overall quality with respect to previous tablets, was perceived as defining a new class of consumer device&lt;ref name=&quot;infoworld&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infoworld.com/d/mobile-technology/the-ipads-victory-in-defining-the-tablet-what-it-means-431|title=The iPad's victory in defining the tablet: What it means|publisher=[[Infoworld]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and shaped the commercial market for tablets in the following year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/08/19/hp-touchpad-ipad-tablet_n_931593.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result, two distinctly different types of tablet computing devices exist as of 2011, the'' Tablet PC'' and the ''Post-PC tablet'', whose [[operating system]]s are of different origin.

=== Traditional tablet PCs ===
{{Main|Early tablet computers}}

A  ''tablet personal computer (tablet PC)'' is a portable personal computer equipped with a [[touchscreen]] as a primary [[input device]], and running a (modified) classic [[operating system#Examples of operating systems|desktop OS]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Beck H 2009, p 402&quot;&gt;Beck H ''et al'', ''Business Communication and Technologies in a Changing World'', Macmillan Education Australia, 2009, p 402&lt;/ref&gt; designed to be operated and owned by an individual.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haven, Kendall F. 2006, p 191&quot;&gt;Haven, Kendall F. ''100 greatest science inventions of all time'', Libraries Unlimited, 2006, p 191&lt;/ref&gt; The term was made popular as a concept presented by Microsoft in 2000&lt;ref name='TabletPC,2000'&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/features/2000/nov00/11-13comdex.mspx Bill Gates introduces Tablet PC, COMDEX Nov 2000]&lt;/ref&gt; and 2001&lt;ref name=&quot;Microsoft Tablet PC Overview&quot;&gt;Page, M [http://www.transmetazone.com/articleview.cfm?articleID=499 Microsoft Tablet PC Overview], TransmetaZone, December 21, 2000 &lt;/ref&gt; but tablet PCs now refer to any tablet-sized personal computer regardless of the (desktop) operating system&lt;ref name=&quot;Free software and cellphones&quot;&gt;Kuhn, Bradley M. [http://www.fsf.org/working-together/next-steps/free-software-phones Free software and cellphones], Free Software Foundation, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Tablet computer|Tablet personal computer]]s are mainly based on the [[x86]] IBM-PC architecture &lt;ref name=&quot;marketwatch.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.marketwatch.com/story/tablet-growth-may-threaten-pc-chip-makers-2010-10-22?pagenumber=2 Are Intel, AMD threatened by tablet growth? Every two to three tablets sold means one lost PC sale, analyst says] accessdate=2010-10-24 &lt;/ref&gt; and are fully functional personal computers employing a slightly modified [[operating system#Examples of operating systems|personal computer OS]] (such as [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] or [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] Linux) supporting their touch-screen, instead of a traditional display, mouse and keyboard. A typical tablet personal computer needs to be [[Stylus (computing)|stylus]] driven, because operating the typical desktop based OS requires a high precision to select [[GUI widget]]s, such as a the [[button (computing)#Buttons in Microsoft Windows|close window button]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

=== Post-PC tablets ===
{{See also|Mobile operating system}}

Since mid-2010, new tablet computers have been introduced with [[mobile operating system]]s that forgo the [[Wintel]] paradigm,&lt;ref&gt;Roger Kay on Intel and Microsoft, as quoted April 29, 2011: &quot;Clearly, each one is looking at a post-PC world...&quot; [http://www.marketwatch.com/story/microsoft-offers-more-muted-view-of-pcs-2011-04-29 MarketWatch]&lt;/ref&gt; have a different interface instead of the traditional [[Desktop environment|desktop]] OS, and represent a new type of computing device.&lt;ref name='iPadTIMEreview'&gt;Lev Grossman (Thursday, Apr. 1, 2010) &quot;[http://www.time.com/time/business/article/0,8599,1976932,00.html Do We Need the iPad? A TIME Review]&quot;, ''TIME''&lt;/ref&gt; These &quot;post-PC&quot; [[mobile operating system|mobile OS]] tablet computer devices are normally finger driven and most frequently use [[capacitive sensing|capacitive]] [[touch screen]]s with [[multi-touch]] capabilities instead of the simple [[resistive touchscreen]]s of typical stylus driven systems.

The most successful of these was the [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] [[iPad]] using the [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]] operating system. &lt;ref&gt; {{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/timworstall/2011/07/02/ipad-one-of-the-most-successful-products-ever/ | work=Forbes | first=Tim | last=Worstall}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Samsung|Samsung's]] [[Samsung Galaxy Tab|Galaxy Tab]] and others followed, continuing the now common trends towards multi-touch and other [[natural user interface]] features, as well as [[flash memory]] solid-state storage drives and &quot;instant on&quot; warm-boot times; in addition, standard external [[USB]] and [[Bluetooth]] [[Computer keyboard|keyboard]]s can often be used. Most frequently the operating system running a tablet computer that's not based on the traditional PC architecture is based on a [[Unix-like]] OS, such as [[Darwin (operating system)|Darwin]], [[Linux]] or [[QNX]]. Some have [[3G]] [[mobile phone|mobile telephony]] capabilities.&lt;ref&gt;i.e. [[ZTE|ZTE V9 Tablet]] and [[Samsung Galaxy Tab]] and some [[iPad]]s&lt;/ref&gt;

In forgoing the [[x86]] precondition (a requisite of Windows compatibility), most tablet computers released since mid-2010 use a version of an [[ARM architecture]] processor for longer battery life versus battery weight, heretofore used in portable equipment such as [[Digital audio player|MP3 players]] and cell phones. Especially with the introduction of the [[ARM Cortex-A9 MPCore|ARM Cortex family]], this architecture is now powerful enough for tasks such as [[Mobile browser|internet browsing]], light production work and gaming.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Coming War: ARM versus x86&quot;&gt;[http://vanshardware.com/2010/08/mirror-the-coming-war-arm-versus-x86/ The Coming War: ARM versus x86] Mirror for: ''The Bright Side of News'' April 8, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

A significant trait of tablet computers not based on the traditional PC architecture is that the main source of 3rd party software for these devices tends to be through [[List of digital distribution platforms for mobile devices|online distribution]], rather than more traditional methods of [[Retail software|boxed software]] or [[Vendor lock-in|direct sales]] from software vendors. These sources, known as &quot;app stores,&quot; provide centralized catalogues of software from both 1st and 3rd parties and allow simple &quot;one click&quot; on-device software purchasing, installation, and updates.

==Touch user interface==
[[File:IFA 2010 Internationale Funkausstellung Berlin 18.JPG|[[Samsung]] [[Galaxy Tab]]|thumb]]
A key and common component among tablet computers is touch input. This allows the user to navigate easily and intuitively and type with a [[virtual keyboard]] on the screen.

The event processing of the operating system must respond to touches rather than clicks of a keyboard or mouse, which allows integrated hand-eye operation, a natural part of the [[somatosensory system]]. Although the device implementation differs from more traditional PCs or laptops, tablets are disrupting the current vendor sales by weakening traditional laptop PC sales in favor of the current tablet computers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13579_3-20016818-37.html Best Buy: iPad cutting into laptop sales]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://tech.fortune.cnn.com/2010/09/17/notebook-sales-growth-goes-negative-can-we-blame-the-ipad-yet/ Notebook sales growth goes negative. Can we blame the iPad yet?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marketwatch.com/story/tablets-hurt-pc-sales-but-not-apples-mac-2010-10-13 Tablets hurt PC sales but not Macs]&lt;/ref&gt;
This is even more true of the &quot;finger driven multi-touch&quot; interface of the more recent tablet computers, which often emulate the way actual objects behave.

===Handwriting recognition===

[[File:人-red.png|thumb|200px|right|Chinese characters like this one meaning &quot;person&quot; can be written by handwriting recognition ([[File:人-order.gif|20px|人 animation]], [[Chinese language|Mandarin]]: ''rén'', [[Korean language|Korean]]: ''in'', Japanese: ''jin'', ''nin''; ''hito'', [[Cantonese]]: jan4). The character has two strokes, the first shown here in dark, and the second in red. The black area represents the starting position of the writing instrument.]]
Because tablet personal computers normally use a stylus, they quite often implement [[handwriting recognition]], while other tablet computers with finger driven screens do not. Finger driven screens however are potentially better suited for inputting &quot;variable width stroke based&quot; characters, like Chinese/Japanese/Korean writing, due to their built in capability of &quot;pressure sensing&quot;. However at the moment not much of this potential is already used, and as a result even on tablet computers Chinese users often use a (virtual) keyboard for input.&lt;ref&gt;[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:rX3A5F0UJKQJ:ca.news.yahoo.com/s/afp/100826/technology/lifestyle_hongkong_china_japan_culture_technology+ca.news.yahoo.com/s/afp/100826/technology/lifestyle_hongkong_china_japan_culture_technology&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=nl&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=nl China using keyboards versus tablet input]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Touchscreen hardware===

Touchscreens are usually one of two forms;
*'''Resistive''': [[Resistive touchscreen]]s are passive and can respond to any kind of pressure on the screen. They allow a high level of [[Accuracy and precision|precision]] (which may be needed, when the touch screen tries to emulate a [[Mouse_pointer#Mouse_cursor|mouse]] for precision pointing, which in Tablet personal computers is common) but may require calibration to be [[accuracy|accurate]]. Because of the high resolution of detection, a stylus or fingernail is often used for resistive screens. Although some possibility exist for implementing [[multi-touch]] on a resistive touch-screen, the possibilities are quite limited. As modern tablet computers tend to heavily lean on the use of multi-touch, this technology has faded out on high-end devices where it has been replaced by capacitive touchscreens.

*'''Capacitive''': [[capacitive sensing|Capacitive touchscreens]] tend to be less accurate, but more responsive than resistive screens. Because they require a conductive material, such as a finger tip, for input, they are not common among (stylus using) Tablet PCs but are more prominent on the smaller scale &quot;tablet computer&quot; devices for ease of use, which generally do not use a stylus, and need multi-touch capabilities.

Other touch technology used in tablets include:
*Palm recognition. It prevents inadvertent palms or other contacts from disrupting the pen's input.

*[[Multi-touch]] capabilities, which can recognize multiple simultaneous finger touches, allowing for enhanced manipulation of on-screen objects.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jkontherun.blogs.com/jkontherun/2007/12/so-what-is-mult.html jkOnTheRun:So what is multi-touch?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some professional-grade Tablet PCs use pressure sensitive films that additionally allows pressure sensitivity such as those on [[graphics tablet]]s.

Concurrently capacitive touch-screens, which use finger tip detection can often detect the size of the touched area, and can make some conclusions to the pressure force used, for a similar result.&lt;ref name =buxtonoverview&gt;Buxton, Bill. [http://www.billbuxton.com/multitouchOverview.html &quot;Multitouch Overview&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other features==
*'''[[Accelerometer]]''': An accelerometer is a unit that detects the physical movements of the tablet. This allows greater flexibility of use since tablets do not necessarily have a fixed direction of use. The accelerometer can also be used to detect the [[Orientation (geometry)|orientation]] of the tablet relative to the center of the earth, but can also detect [[Motion (physics)|movement]] of the tablet, both of which can be used as an alternative control interface for a tablet's software.
*'''Ambient light and proximity sensors''' are additional &quot;[[sense]]s&quot;, that can provide controlling input for the tablet.
*'''Storage drive''': Large tablets use storage drives similar to laptops, while smaller ones tend to use drives similar to MP3 Players or have on-board flash memory. They also often have ports for removable storage such as [[Secure Digital]] cards. Due to the nature of the use of tablets, [[solid-state memory]] is often preferable due to its better resistance to damage during movement.
*'''Wireless''': Because tablets by design are mobile computers, wireless connections are less restrictive to motion than wired connections. [[Wi-Fi]] connectivity has become ubiquitous among tablets. [[Bluetooth]] is commonly used for connecting peripherals and communicating with local devices in place of a wired [[USB]] connection.
*'''3D''': Following mobile phone, there are also 3D slate tablet with dual lens at the back of the tablet and also provided with blue-red glasses.&lt;ref&gt;T-Mobile to sell tablet with 3-D cameras, glasses http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20110202/ap_on_hi_te/us_tec_techbit3_d_tablet&lt;/ref&gt;

==Form factors==
Tablet computers come in a range of sizes, currently ranging from tablet PCs to PDAs. Tablet personal computers tend to be as large as laptops and often are the largest usable size for mobile tablet computing while the new generation of tablet computers can be (much) smaller and use a [[Reduced instruction set computing|RISC]] ([[ARM architecture|ARM]] or [[MIPS architecture|MIPS]]) CPU, and in size can border on [[Personal digital assistant|PDA]]s.

===Slate===
Slate computers, which resemble [[slate (writing)|writing slates]], are tablet computers without a dedicated keyboard. For text input, users rely on handwriting recognition via an active digitizer, touching an on-screen keyboard using fingertips or a [[Stylus (computing)|stylus]], or using an external keyboard that can usually be attached via a [[wireless]] or [[USB]] connection.

Slate computers typically incorporate small ({{convert|8.4|-|14.1|in|cm|disp=s}}) [[LCD]] screens and have been popular in [[vertical market]]s such as health care, education, hospitality, aviation (pilot documentation and maps),&lt;ref&gt;''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' ([http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-isoldiers-20110926,0,2255882,full.story September 26, 2011])&lt;/ref&gt; and field work. Applications for field work often require a tablet computer that has rugged specifications that ensure long life by resisting heat, humidity, and drop/vibration damage. This added focus on mobility and/or ruggedness often leads to elimination of moving parts that could hinder these qualities.

===Booklet===
Booklet computers are [[dual-touchscreen]] tablet computers that fold like a book. Typical booklet computers are equipped with [[multi-touch]] screens and pen writing recognition capabilities. They are designed to be used as digital [[day planner]]s, [[Internet surfing]] devices, project planners, music players, and displays for video, live TV, and e-reading.

===Convertible===
[[File:Lenovo-X61-Tablet-Mode.jpg|thumb|280px|right|A [[Lenovo]] X61 in slate mode]]
Convertible notebooks have a base body with an attached keyboard. They more closely resemble modern laptops, and are usually heavier and larger than slates.

Typically, the base of a convertible attaches to the display at a single joint called a swivel hinge or rotating hinge. The joint allows the screen to rotate through 180° and fold down on top of the keyboard to provide a flat writing surface. This design, although the most common, creates a [[Single point of failure|physical point of weakness]] on the notebook.

Some manufacturers have attempted to overcome these weak points. The [[Panasonic Toughbook]] 19, for example, is advertised as a more durable convertible notebook. One model by [[Acer (company)|Acer]] (the TravelMate C210) has a sliding design in which the screen slides up from the slate-like position and locks into place to provide the laptop mode.

Sliding screens were presented at CES 2011. The first product to use it is the Samsung Sliding PC7 Series,&lt;ref name=&quot;Samsung Sliding PC7 Series&quot;&gt;product presentation and demo [http://www.alltouchtablet.com/touchscreen-tablet-news/samsung-sliding-pc-7-is-the-slider-laptoptablet-you-ever-wanted-6343/ Samsung Sliding PC7 Series], AllTouchTablet, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; a tablet with Intel Atom hardware and a unique sliding screen that allows the product to be used as a laptop or slate tablet when the screen is locked in place covering the whole keyboard. The concept still has to prove its reliability, but is intended to combine the virtues of tablet PCs with those of notebooks. Also presented was the upcoming [[Dell_Inspiron#Inspiron_Duo|Inspiron Duo]] from Dell, which rotates the screen horizontally when opened. Convertibles like that with hardware specs of a netbook are called netvertibles.

=== Hybrid ===
Hybrids, a term coined by users of the [[HP/Compaq TC1000]] and [[TC1100]] series, share the features of the slate and convertible by using a detachable keyboard that operates in a similar fashion to a convertible when attached. Hybrids are not to be confused with slate models with detachable keyboards; detachable keyboards for pure slate models do not rotate to allow the tablet to rest on it like a convertible.

==System architecture==
{{See also|Comparison of tablet computers|Comparison of ARM tablets}}
Two major computer architectures compete in the tablet market,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/Intel-has-ARM-in-its-crosshairs---page-2/2100-1006_3-6210033-2.html?tag=mncol Intel has ARM in its crosshairs]&lt;/ref&gt; [[x86]] and [[ARM architecture]]. x86, including [[x86-64]], is popular on tablet PCs due to its use on laptops which can share common software and hardware and which can run a version of [[Windows]]. There are also non-PC based x86 tablets like the [[JooJoo]]. ARM gained popularity following the success of the iPad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Apple iPad Price, Features Say “ARM” All Over|url=http://www.bnet.com/blog/mobile-internet/apple-ipad-price-features-say-8220arm-8221-all-over/133|publisher=bnet}}&lt;/ref&gt; ARM is more power and cost efficient for mobile computing and is gaining popularity for smaller tablets from other manufacturers such as Samsung with the [[Galaxy Tab]] which runs on Android.

==Operating systems and vendors==
Tablets, like regular computers, can run a number of [[operating system]]s. These come in two classes, namely traditional desktop-based operating systems and post-PC mobile-based (&quot;phone-like&quot;) operating systems.

For the former class popular OS's are [[Microsoft Windows]], and a range of [[Linux]] distributions. [[HP]] is developing enterprise-level tablets under [[Windows]] and consumer-oriented tablets under [[webOS]].
In the latter class the popular variants include [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]], and [[Google]] [[Android (operating system)|Android]]. Manufacturers are also testing the market for products with [[Windows CE]], [[Chrome OS]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eweekeurope.co.uk/news/hp-hints-at-business-focused-windows-7-tablet-8704 HP vice-president Todd Bradley projects HP Slates for enterprise-level tablets, webOS for consumer-level tablets accessdate=2010-10-5]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/Innovation/Horizons/2010/1023/HP-Slate-500-brings-professional-spin-to-the-tablet-wars HP Slate 500 runs Win 7 Pro], an enterprise-level tablet from HP accessdate=2010-10-23 &lt;/ref&gt; and so forth.

[[booting|Boot times]] for iPads are one-half the boot times for current Windows 7 netbooks, which can take over 50 seconds to display the [[login]] prompt.&lt;ref&gt;[http://reviews.cnet.com/8301-31747_7-20001653-243.html?tag=mncol;txt Boot time comparisons for iPad vs netbook]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[BIOS]] initialization for a PC, which has remained unchanged since the invention of the PC, can still take 25 seconds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13924_3-20018475-64.html#ixzz12IPFj4kf Getting a Windows PC to boot in under 10 seconds]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Traditional Tablet PC operating systems ===
====Microsoft====
{{Out of date|lack of Windows 8 information|date=June 2011}}
{{Main|Microsoft Tablet PC}}
Following [[Windows for Pen Computing]], Microsoft has been developing support for tablets runnings Windows under the [[Microsoft Tablet PC]] name.&lt;ref&gt;[http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms840465.aspx Microsoft Tablet PC&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2001 [[Microsoft]] definition&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/features/2000/nov00/11-13tabletpc.mspx Tablet PC Brings the Simplicity of Pen and Paper to Computing: In a conversation with PressPass, Tablet PC general manager Alexandra Loeb discusses how the Tablet PC will brin...&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; of the term, &quot;Microsoft Tablet PCs&quot; are pen-based, fully functional [[x86]] [[Personal computer|PC]]s with handwriting and voice recognition functionality. Tablet PCs use the same hardware as normal laptops but add support for pen input. For specialized support for pen input, Microsoft released [[Windows XP Tablet PC Edition]]. Today there is no tablet specific version of Windows but instead support is built in to both Home and Business versions of [[Windows Vista]] and [[Windows 7]]. Tablets running Windows get the added functionality of using the touchscreen for mouse input, hand writing recognition, and gesture support. Following Tablet PC, Microsoft announced the [[UMPC]] initiative in 2006 which brought Windows tablets to a smaller, touch-centric form factor. This was relaunched in 2010 as ''Slate PC'', to promote tablets running [[Windows 7]], ahead of Apple's iPad launch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=
Live from Steve Ballmer's CES 2010 keynote|url=http://www.engadget.com/2010/01/06/live-from-steve-ballmers-ces-2010-keynote/|publisher=Engadget|accessdate=August 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13860_3-20019267-56.html?tag=mncol;mlt_related Initial Windows 7 tablets are slated to appear during holiday 2010 season.] accessdate=2010-10-19 &lt;/ref&gt; Slate PCs are expected to benefit from mobile hardware advances derived from the success of the [[netbook]]s.

Microsoft has since announced [[Windows 8]] which will have features designed for touch input, while running on both PCs and ARM architecture.&lt;ref&gt;Avi Greengart of Current Analysis states &quot;Windows 8 basically assumes that every PC is a tablet&quot;,  as reported by Gordon Mah Ung et.al. (October 2011) ''Maximum PC'' p.27 ISSN 1522-7249&lt;/ref&gt;. Renee James of Intel states multiple builds are needed, with 1 build for x86 processors and with 4 builds for ARM; ARM targets are defined for AMD, Intel, Qualcomm, and TI processors.&lt;ref&gt; Gordon Mah Ung et.al. (October 2011) ''Maximum PC'' p.24 ISSN 1522-7249&lt;/ref&gt;

While many tablet manufacturers are moving to the [[ARM architecture]] with lighter operating systems, Microsoft has stood firm to Windows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ballmer Admits Apple is Beating Microsoft in the Tablet Sector|url=http://www.dailytech.com/Ballmer+Admits+Apple+is+Beating+Microsoft+in+the+Tablet+Sector/article19215.htm|publisher=DailyTech|accessdate=August 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/news/2010/09/hp-slate-video-shows-all-thats-wrong-with-windows-7-on-tablets.ars Windows 7 is not yet optimized for fingertip events – September 24, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2010/10/05/microsofts-ipad-answer-coming-christmas-holiday/ Windows 7 will not be optimized for slates; that will have to wait for Windows 8]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mashable.com/2010/10/24/microsoft-windows-8-2012/ Windows 8 will not appear until 2012] accessdate=2010-10-24 &lt;/ref&gt; Though Microsoft has [[Windows CE]] for ARM support it has kept its target market for the smartphone industry with [[Windows Mobile]] and the new Windows CE 6 based [[Windows Phone 7]]. Some manufacturers, however, still have shown prototypes of Windows CE-based tablets running a custom shell.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Asus launches Eee Pad tablets and Eee Tablet note-taking thingie|url=http://www.liliputing.com/2010/05/asus-launches-two-tablets-the-eee-pad-and-eee-tablet.html|publisher=liliputing|accessdate=August 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; To date, the full Windows 7 does not yet support ARM architecture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zdnet.com/blog/microsoft/microsoft-no-windows-7-for-arm-based-netbooks-for-now/2953?tag=mantle_skin;content No Windows 7 for ARM] accessdate=2010-10-17
*[http://www.marketwatch.com/story/microsoft-plans-windows-tied-to-arm-chips-reports-2010-12-22?dist=beforebell Microsoft plans Windows tied to ARM chips] Dec. 22, 2010, 4:19&amp;nbsp;am EST&lt;/ref&gt;

====Linux====
One early implementation of a [[Linux]] tablet was the [[ProGear]] by FrontPath. The ProGear used a Transmeta chip and a resistive digitizer.
The ProGear initially came with a version of [[Slackware Linux]], but could later be bought with Windows 98. Because these computers are general purpose [[IBM PC compatible]] machines, they can run many different operating systems. However, the device is no longer for sale and FrontPath has ceased operations. It is important to note that many touch screen sub-notebook computers can run any of several Linux distributions with little customization.

[[X.org]] now supports screen rotation and tablet input through Wacom drivers, and handwriting recognition software from both the [[Qt (framework)|Qt]]-based [[Qtopia]] and [[GTK+]]-based [[Internet Tablet OS]] provide promising free and [[open source]] systems for future development. [[KDE]]'s [[Plasma Active]] is graphical environments for tablet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Plasma Active|url=http://plasma-active.org/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Open source note taking software in Linux includes applications such as [[Xournal]] (which supports PDF file annotation), Gournal (a Gnome based note taking application), and the Java-based [[Jarnal]] (which supports handwriting recognition as a built-in function). Before the advent of the aforementioned software, many users had to rely on on-screen keyboards and alternative text input methods like [[Dasher]]. There is a stand alone handwriting recognition program available, CellWriter, which requires users to write letters separately in a grid.

A number of Linux based OS projects are dedicated to tablet PCs. Since all these are open source, they are freely available and can be run or ported to devices that conform to the tablet PC design. [[Maemo]] (rebranded MeeGo in 2010), a [[Debian]] Linux based graphical user environment, was developed for the [[Nokia Internet Tablet]] devices (770, N800, N810 &amp; N900). It is currently in generation 5, and has a vast array of applications available in both official and user supported repositories. The [[Ubuntu Netbook Edition|Ubuntu Netbook Remix edition]], as well as the Intel sponsored Moblin project, both have touchscreen support integrated into their user interfaces. [[Canonical Ltd|Canonical]] has hinted at better supporting tablets with the [[Unity (desktop environment)|Unity UI]] for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu 10.10]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ubuntu gets multitouch support, Unity netbook UI|url=http://www.linuxfordevices.com/c/a/News/Canonical-uTouch-and-Ubuntu-Maverick-Meerkat/|publisher=eWeek}}&lt;/ref&gt;

TabletKiosk currently offers a hybrid digitizer / touch device running openSUSE Linux. It is the first device with this feature to support Linux.

====Intel and Nokia====
[[File:N800 frontside2.jpg|thumb|The [[Nokia N800]]]]
Nokia entered the tablet space with the [[Nokia 770 Internet Tablet|Nokia 770]] running [[Maemo]], a Debian-based Linux distribution custom-made for their [[Internet tablet]] line. The product line continued with the [[N900]] which is the first to add phone capabilities. The [[user interface]] and [[application framework]] layer, named [[Hildon]], was an early instance of a [[software platform]] for generic computing in a tablet device intended for internet consumption. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/11/21/nokia_hildon_the_great_lost_platform/|title=Nokia's Great Lost Platform
|author=Andrew Orlowski|publisher=[[The Register]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; But Nokia didn't commit to it as their only platform for their future mobile devices and the project competed against other in-house platforms. The strategic advantage of a modern platform was not exploited, being displaced by the [[Series 60]].
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/11/21/nokia_hildon_the_great_lost_platform/page4.html|title=Nokia's Great Lost Platform - Page 4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intel, following the launch of the UMPC, started the [[Mobile Internet Device]] initiative, which took the same hardware and combined it with a Linux operating system custom-built for portable tablets. Intel co-developed the lightweight [[Moblin]] operating system following the successful launch of the Atom CPU series on netbooks. Intel is also setting tablet goals for Atom, going forward from 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/10/17/intel_tablets/ Intel shows pricing pressures for Atom due to competition from ARM] accessdate=2010-10-17 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thinq.co.uk/2010/11/22/intel-launches-fpga-equipped-atom/ Intel launches FPGA-equipped Atom] accessdate=2010-11-23 An FPGA, or [[field programmable gate array]] can then be custom-programmed by tablet computer vendors who have purchased these [[integrated circuit]]s from the semiconductor device manufacturers.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====MeeGo=====
{{Main|Maemo|MeeGo}}
[[MeeGo]] is a Linux-based operating system developed by [[Intel]] and [[Nokia]] that supports Netbooks, Smartphones and Tablet PCs. In 2010, Nokia and Intel combined the Maemo and Moblin projects to form MeeGo. The first tablet using MeeGo is the [[Neofonie]] [[WeTab]] launched September 2010 in Germany. The WeTab uses an extended version of the MeeGo operating system called WeTab OS. WeTab OS adds runtimes for Android and [[Adobe AIR]] and provides a proprietary user interface optimized for the WeTab device. On 27 September 2011 it was announced by the [[Linux Foundation]] that MeeGo will be replaced in 2012 by [[Tizen]], an [[open source]] mobile operating system.&lt;ref name=next&gt;{{cite web|last=Sousou|first=Imad|title=What's Next for MeeGo|url=https://www.meego.com/community/blogs/imad/2011/whats-next-meego|publisher=meego.com|accessdate=28 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-PC operating systems===
{{See also|Mobile operating system}}
Tablets not following the personal computer (PC) tradition use operating systems in the style of those developed for [[PDA]]s and [[smartphone]]s.

====iPad====
{{Main|iOS (Apple)|iPad|ModBook}}
[[File:IPad in Case.jpg|thumb|The iPad in case]]
The iPad runs a version of iOS which was first created for the [[iPhone]] and [[iPod Touch]]. Although built on the same underlying Unix implementation as MacOS, the operating system differs radically at the graphical user interface level. iOS is designed for finger based use and has none of the tiny features which required a stylus on earlier tablets. Apple introduced responsive multi touch gestures, like moving two fingers apart to zoom in. iOS is built for the [[ARM architecture]] which uses less power, and so gives better battery life, than Intel devices required by Windows tablets. Previous to the iPad's launch, there were long standing rumors of an Apple tablet, though they were often about a product running [[Mac OS X]] and being in line with Apple's Macintosh computers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Apple tablet rumors redux: 10.7-inch display, iPhone OS underneath|url=http://www.engadget.com/2009/09/29/apple-tablet-rumors-redux-10-7-inch-display-iphone-os-undernea/|publisher=Engadget|accessdate=August 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This became partially true when a 3rd party offered customized [[Macbook]]s with pen input, known as the [[Modbook]].

Previous to Apple's commercialization of the iPad, Axiotron introduced at Macworld in 2007&lt;ref name='modbookRelease'&gt;[http://www.tabletpcreview.com/default.asp?newsID=695 Tifanny Boggs (2007) &quot;Axiotron and OWC Unveil the ModBook&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; an aftermarket, heavily modified Apple [[MacBook]] called [[Axiotron Modbook|Modbook]], a [[Mac OS X]]-based tablet personal computer. The Modbook uses Apple's [[Inkwell (Macintosh)|Inkwell]] for handwriting and gesture recognition, and use digitization hardware from [[Wacom]]. To get Mac OS X to talk to the digitizer on the integrated tablet, the Modbook is supplied with a third-party driver called [http://www.thinkyhead.com/tabletmagic TabletMagic]; Wacom does not provide driver support for this device.

====Blackberry====
The [[BlackBerry PlayBook]] is a tablet computer announced in September 2010 which runs the [[BlackBerry Tablet OS]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eAaez_4m9mQ BlackBerry PlayBook preview] [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eAaez_4m9mQ BlackBerry PlayBook announcement September 27, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; The OS is based on the [[QNX]] system that [[Research in Motion]] acquired in early 2010. Delivery to developers and enterprise customers is expected in October 2010. The BlackBerry PlayBook was officially released to US and Canadian consumers on April 19, 2011.

====Android====
{{Main|Android (operating system)|Google Chrome OS}}
Google's Linux-based Android operating system has been targeted by tablet manufacturers following its success on [[smartphone]]s due to its open nature{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} and support for low-cost [[ARM]] systems much like Apple's iOS. In 2010, there have been numerous announcements of such tablets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=9 Upcoming Tablet Alternatives to the Apple iPad|url=http://mashable.com/2010/01/27/9-upcoming-tablet-alternatives-to-the-apple-ipad/|publisher=Mashable|accessdate=August 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, much of Android's tablet initiative comes from manufacturers as Google primarily focuses its development on smartphones and restricts the App Market from non-phone devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Don’t bank on KMart’s $150 Augen tablet getting Android Market access|url=http://www.liliputing.com/2010/08/dont-bank-on-kmarts-150-augen-tablet-getting-android-market-access.html|publisher=liliputing|accessdate=August 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Toshiba's AC100 laptop also runs on Android.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13924_3-20008301-64.html Toshiba debuts ultraslim Android laptop], 21 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

There is talk of tablet support from Google coming to its web-centric [[Chrome OS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Forget all these Android tablets, let me at that Chrome OS|url=http://www.crunchgear.com/2010/07/20/forget-all-these-android-tablets-let-me-at-that-chrome-os/|publisher=CrunchGear|accessdate=August 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/services/data/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=226700487 &quot;Google Chrome OS Tablet Brings Ties With Verizon&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some vendors such as Motorola&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marketwatch.com/video/asset/digits-motorola-plans-tablet-device-2010-09-16/7CC13B36-0A8B-42E0-AD1A-72FF9BF04348 Motorola Android tablet in 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; and Lenovo&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slashgear.com/tablets-a-prescription-for-confusion-24109978/ Lenovo is waiting for Honeycomb] accessdate=2010-10-24 &lt;/ref&gt; are delaying deployment of their tablet computers until 2011, after Android is reworked to include more tablet features.&lt;ref&gt;The successor to ''Gingerbread'', Android project ''Honeycomb''  is targeted for tablet computers. – Daniel Lyons ( Oct. 11, 2010), ''Newsweek'' p. 49
*[http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2373943,00.asp Google demonstrated Android Honeycomb Tablet 12/7/2010]
*[http://www.marketwatch.com/video/asset/digits-best-buys-tv-bust-2010-12-14/FD6C213F-D320-4212-BE7C-FECD5B8FEA33?dist=afterbell#!88F98ADB-3F87-49DF-AD08-385D66B0DDE8 Andy Rubin's demo of Motorola Honeycomb tablet]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Update after|2011|04|13}} Android 3.0 (Honeycomb) is optimized specifically for devices with larger screen sizes, mainly tablets, and has access to the Android Market. Android is the software stack for mobile devices that includes operating system, middleware and key applications.

====HP====
'''[[Hewlett-Packard|HP]]'s [[webOS]]''': Hewlett Packard announced the [[HP_TouchPad|TouchPad]] running webOS 3.0 on a 1.2Ghz [[Snapdragon_(System_on_Chip)|Snapdragon]] CPU would be released in June 2011. On Thursday August 18, 2011, HP announced the discontinuation of the Touchpad, due to sluggish sales.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.hp.com/investor/2011q3webcast HP Webcast announcing the end of Touchpad, webOS devices] accessdate=2011-08-18&lt;/ref&gt; The fate of any webOS-based software remains open, as HP casts about for some possible resolution.

====One Laptop per Child organization====
The [[One Laptop per Child]] (OLPC) organization is developing a new version of the OLPC, strongly resembling a tablet computer, called the OLPC XO-3, running its [[Sugar (desktop environment)|&quot;Sugar&quot; operating system]], based on [[Linux]]. The new XO-3 will be based on ARM technology from [[Marvell Technology Group|Marvell]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xconomy.com/boston/2010/10/04/one-laptop-gets-5-6m-grant-from-marvell-to-develop-next-generation-tablet-computer/ One Laptop Gets $5.6M Grant From Marvell to Develop Next Generation Tablet Computer | Xconomy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Developing software for tablet computers ==
{{See also|Mobile development}}

The new class of devices heralded by the [[iPad]] has spurred the tendency of a [[walled garden (technology)|walled garden]] approach where the vendor reserves rights as to what can be installed. The [[software development kit]]s for these platforms are restricted and the vendor must approve the final application for distribution to users. These restrictions allow the hardware vendor to control the kind of software that can be used and the content that can be seen in the devices; this can be used to reduce the impact of [[malware]] on the platform and to provide material of approved [[content rating]], and also to exclude software and content from competing vendors. The walled garden approach to application development has proven to be a competitive advantage for the iPad over HP's Touchpad, triggering HP's withdrawal from the industry, due in large part to sluggish Touchpad sales, after only 49 days on the market.&lt;ref&gt; This &quot;vicious cycle&quot; (slow hardware development masking slow hardware, causing slow response, causing slow software development, causing sluggish performance at an unrealistic price, causing sluggish sales) serves only to impede further software investment. &quot;HP reboots to confront Tablet Effect&quot; ''Barron's'', August 20th, 2011 &lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents of open source software deem that these restrictions on software installation and lack of administrator rights make this category one that, in their view, cannot be properly named ''personal computers''.&lt;ref name=&quot;iPad is iBad for freedom&quot;&gt;Brown, Peter [http://www.fsf.org/news/ibad_launch iPad is iBad for freedom], Free Software Foundation, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The iPad Is Not a Computer&quot;&gt;Cherry, Steven [http://spectrum.ieee.org/consumer-electronics/portable-devices/the-ipad-is-not-a-computer The iPad Is Not a Computer], IEEE Spectrum, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;popsci.com&quot;&gt;Conlon, Tom [http://www.popsci.com/gadgets/article/2010-01/ipad%E2%80%99s-closed-system-sometimes-i-hate-being-right The iPad’s Closed System: Sometimes I Hate Being Right], Popular Science, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; But there are newer [[mobile operating system]] based tablet computers that don't use the [[Walled_garden_(technology)|walled garden]] concept, and are like personal computers in this regard.

== Comparison with laptop computers ==
{{Ref improve section|date=November 2010}}
The advantages and disadvantages of tablet computers are highly subjective measures. What appeals to one user may be exactly what disappoints another. The following are commonly cited opinions of tablet computers versus laptops:

===Advantages===
* Usage in environments not conducive to a keyboard and mouse such as lying in bed, standing, or handling with a single hand.
* Lighter weight, lower power models can function similarly to dedicated reading devices like the [[Amazon Kindle]].
* Touch environment makes navigation easier than conventional use of keyboard and mouse or touch pad in certain contexts such as [[image manipulation]], musical, or mouse oriented games.
* Digital painting and image editing are more precise and intuitive than painting or sketching with a mouse.
* The ability for easier or faster entry of diagrams, mathematical notations, and symbols.
* Allows, with the proper software, universal input, independent from different keyboard localizations.
* Some users find it more direct and pleasant to use a stylus, [[Digital pen|pen]] or finger to point and tap on objects, rather than use a mouse or touchpad, which are not directly connected to the pointer on screen.

===Disadvantages===
* Higher price – convertible tablet computers can cost significantly more than non-tablet portable PCs although this premium has been predicted to fall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.com.com/Convertibles+The+new+laptop+bling/2100-1044_3-5900655.html Convertibles: The new laptop bling? – CNET News.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Input speed – handwriting or typing on a [[virtual keyboard]] can be significantly slower than [[typing speed]] on a conventional keyboard, the latter of which can be as high as 50–150 [[WPM]]; however, [[Slideit]], [[Swype]] and other technologies are offered in an effort to narrow the gap. Some devices also support external keyboards (eg: [[iPad]] can accept [[Bluetooth]] keyboards and [[USB]] keyboards through [[iPad Camera Connection Kit]] [[Dock Connector]]-to-USB adapter. Apple has also released a keyboard dock)
* Ergonomics – a tablet computer, or a folded slate PC, does not provide room for a wrist rest. In addition, the user will need to move his or her arm constantly while writing.
* Weaker video capabilities – Most tablet computers are equipped with embedded graphics processors instead of discrete graphics cards. In July 2010, the only{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} tablet PC with a discrete graphics card was the [[HP TouchSmart]] tm2t, which has the [[ATI]] [[Mobility Radeon]] HD5450 as an optional extra.
* Business-oriented tablet personal computers have been slow sellers from 2001 to date.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/211066/why_tablet_computing_hasnt_been_big_business.html ''PC World'' (Nov 18, 2010 12:25 pm)&quot;Why Tablet Computing Hasn't Been Big Business&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Screen risk – Tablet computers are handled more than conventional laptops, yet many are built on similar frames; in addition, since their screens also serve as input devices, they run a higher risk of screen damage from impacts and misuse.
* Hinge risk – A convertible tablet computer's screen hinge is often required to rotate around two axes, unlike a normal laptop screen, subsequently increasing the number of possible mechanical and electrical (digitizer and video cables, embedded WiFi antennas, etc.) failure points.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}
* Smaller display and lack of keyboard.

==Tablets in developing countries==
[[File:Xo3-fuse-2.jpg|thumb|right|[[One Laptop per Child|OLPC]] XO-3, a tablet computer concept&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.laptop.org/2009/12/24/xo-3-concept/ XO-3 concept design is here! | One Laptop per Child&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The low hardware requirements and easy operation of tablet computers has made it subject to various design studies for use in developing countries, furthermore it will reduce digital gap between the have and the have not. Prototype tablet computers such as the [[Aakash tablet|Aakash]] have been projected to cost $35 with subsidy, according to researchers in India which shall be soon available for the masses as the cheapest tablet working on Android with full functionality;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-10740817 India unveils prototype for $35 touch-screen computer] BBC World news-South Asia Retrieved July 25, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/201769/indias_35_pc_is_the_future_of_computing.html?tk=hp_pop India's ($)35 PC is the future of computing] PCWorld.com&lt;/ref&gt; however the [[bill of materials]] currently comes to $47 and will be avalaible soon at retail shops at $60.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/07/india-35-tablet/ Bill of materials, ''Wired'']&lt;/ref&gt; For the initial government will give for free to students 100,000 unit tablets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://in.reuters.com/article/2011/10/05/idINIndia-59716920111005 |title=India launches &quot;world's cheapest&quot; tablet Aakash |date=October 5, 2011 | work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before it, [[One laptop per child]] (OLPC) plans to introduce a tablet computer for $100.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.csmonitor.com/From-the-news-wires/2010/0723/35-computer-introduced-in-India $100 [[OLPC]] tablet computer&lt;/ref&gt;  Nicholas Negroponte, Chairman of OLPC, has invited the Indian researchers to MIT to begin sharing the OLPC design resources for their tablet computers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goodgearguide.com.au/article/355270/negroponte_offers_olpc_technology_35_tablet/ Adam Shah (July 31, 2010), IDC, &quot;Negroponte offers OLPC technology for $35 tablet&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; OLPC has been awarded a grant for an interim step to their next generation tablet, OLPC XO-3.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xconomy.com/boston/2010/10/04/one-laptop-gets-5-6m-grant-from-marvell-to-develop-next-generation-tablet-computer/ OLPC X03 grant accessdate=2010-10-04]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Comparison of tablet computers]]
* [[Smartbook]]
* [[Ultra-Mobile PC]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Tablet PC}}
*[http://news.cnet.com/8301-31021_3-20006077-260.html?tag=newsLeadStoriesArea.1 What makes a tablet a tablet? (FAQ)] [[CNET.com]] May 28, 2010
{{Computer sizes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tablet Computer}}
[[Category:Tablet computers| ]]
[[Category:Classes of computers]]
[[Category:Personal computing]]

[[ca:Tablet PC]]
[[cs:Tablet (počítač)]]
[[da:Tavlecomputer]]
[[de:Tablet-Computer]]
[[et:Tahvelarvuti]]
[[eml:Tavlátta (zarvlán)]]
[[eo:Tabulkomputilo]]
[[es:Tablet PC]]
[[fr:Tablette tactile]]
[[ga:Ríomhaire táibléid]]
[[ko:태블릿 컴퓨터]]
[[id:Komputer tablet]]
[[it:Tablet computer]]
[[lt:Planšetinis kompiuteris]]
[[ml:ടാബ്‌ലെറ്റ് കമ്പ്യൂട്ടർ]]
[[ja:タブレット (コンピュータ)]]
[[no:Nettbrett]]
[[ro:Calculator tabletă]]
[[ru:Планшетный компьютер]]
[[simple:Tablet computer]]
[[sl:Tablični računalnik]]
[[ta:தத்தல் கணினி]]
[[vi:Máy tính bảng]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
