<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="418434" ns="0" title="Romanian alphabet"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=January 2009}}
{{IPA notice}}

The '''Romanian alphabet''' is a modification of the [[Latin alphabet]] and consists of 31 letters:&lt;ref&gt;{{ro icon}} ''Dicționarul explicativ al limbii române'', 1998, [http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=z Z is the thirty first letter of the Romanian alphabet], dexonline.ro&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Academia Română, Institutul de Lingvistică „Iorgu Iordan – Al. Rosetti”, ''Dicționarul ortografic, ortoepic și morfologic al limbii române'', Editura Univers Enciclopedic, București, 2005, pp. XXVII–XXVIII {{ro icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{|
| style=&quot;vertical-align:top;&quot; |
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Letter !! Name
|-
| [[A|A, a]] || a
|-
| [[Ă|Ă, ă]] || ă
|-
| [[Â|Â, â]] || î / î din a
|-
| [[B|B, b]] || be / bî
|-
| [[C|C, c]] || ce / cî
|-
| [[D|D, d]] || de / dî
|-
| [[E|E, e]] || e
|-
| [[F|F, f]] || ef / fe / fî
|-
| [[G|G, g]] || ge / ghe / gî
|-
| [[H|H, h]] || haș / ha / hî
|-
| [[I|I, i]] || i
|}
| style=&quot;vertical-align:top;&quot; |
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Letter !! Name
|-
| [[Î|Î, î]] || î / î din i
|-
| [[J|J, j]] || je / jî
|-
| [[K|K, k]] || ca / capa
|-
| [[L|L, l]] || el / le / lî
|-
| [[M|M, m]] || em / me / mî
|-
| [[N|N, n]] || en / ne / nî
|-
| [[O|O, o]] || o
|-
| [[P|P, p]] || pe / pî
|-
| [[Q|Q, q]] || kü / chiu
|-
| [[R|R, r]] || er / re / rî
|-
| [[S|S, s]] || es / se / sî
|}
| style=&quot;vertical-align:top;&quot; |
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Letter !! Name
|-
| [[S-comma|Ș, ș / Ş, ş]] || șe / şî
|-
| [[T|T, t]] || te / tî
|-
| [[T-comma|Ț, ț / Ţ, ţ]] || țe / ţî
|-
| [[U|U, u]] || u
|-
| [[V|V, v]] || ve / vî
|-
| [[W|W, w]] || dublu ve / dublu vî
|-
| [[X|X, x]] || ics
|-
| [[Y|Y, y]] || igrec / i grec
|-
| [[Z|Z, z]] || ze / zet / zed / zî
|}
|}

The letters Q (read ''kü'' or ''chiu''), W (''dublu ve''), and Y (''igrec'' or ''i grec'') were officially introduced in the Romanian alphabet in 1982, although they had been used earlier. They occur only in foreign words and their Romanian derivatives, such as ''[[quasar]]'', ''[[watt]]'', and ''[[yacht]]''. The letter ''K'', although relatively older, is also rarely used and appears only in proper names and international neologisms such as ''kilogram'', ''broker'', ''karate''.&lt;ref&gt;{{ro icon}} Academia Română, ''Dicționarul explicativ al limbii române'', [http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=k Entry for ''K''], Editura Univers Enciclopedic, 1998, dexonline.ro&lt;/ref&gt; These four letters are still perceived as foreign, which explains their use for stylistic purposes in words such as ''nomenklatură'' (normally ''nomenclatură'', meaning &quot;nomenclature&quot;, but sometimes spelled with a ''k'' to mean the members of the Communist leadership in the Soviet Union and the Eastern Bloc countries, like ''[[Nomenklatura]]'' is used in English).&lt;ref&gt;Academia Română, Institutul de Lingvistică „Iorgu Iordan – Al. Rosetti”, ''Dicționarul ortografic, ortoepic și morfologic al limbii române'', 2nd Edition, Univers Enciclopedic Publishing House, Bucharest, 2005, ISBN 973-637-087-x, p. XXIX {{ro icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In cases where the word is a direct borrowing having diacritical marks not present in the above alphabet, official spelling tends to favor their use (''[[Munich|München]]'', ''[[Angoulême]]'' etc., as opposed to the use of ''[[Istanbul]]'' over ''İstanbul'').

==Letters and their pronunciation==
{{See also|Romanian phonology}}
Romanian spelling is mostly phonetic. The table below gives the correspondence between letters and sounds. Some of the letters have several possible readings, even if [[allophone]]s are not taken into account. When vowels {{IPA|/i/}}, {{IPA|/u/}}, {{IPA|/e/}}, and {{IPA|/o/}} are changed into their corresponding [[semivowel]]s, this is not marked in writing. Letters K, Q, W, and Y appear only in foreign borrowings; the pronunciation of W and Y depends on the origin of the word they appear in.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Letter
! Phoneme
! Approximate pronunciation
|-
| A a
| {{IPA|/a/}}
| ''a'' in &quot;father&quot;
|-
| [[Ă]] [[ă]] (a with [[breve]])
| {{IPA|/ə/}}
| ''a'' in &quot;above&quot;
|-
| [[Â]] [[â]] (a with [[circumflex]])
| {{IPA|/ɨ/}}
| the [[close central unrounded vowel]] as heard, for example, in the last syllable of the word ''roses'' for some English speakers
|-
| B b
| {{IPA|/b/}}
| ''b'' in &quot;ball&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | C c
| {{IPA|/k/}}
| ''c'' in &quot;scan&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/tʃ/}}
| ''ch'' in &quot;chimpanzee&quot; — if ''c'' appears before letters ''e'' or ''i''
|-
| D d
| {{IPA|/d/}}
| ''d'' in &quot;door&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | E e
| {{IPA|/e/}}
| ''e'' in &quot;merry&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/e̯/}}
| (semivocalic {{IPA|/e/}})
|-
| {{IPA|/je/}}
| ''ye'' in &quot;yes&quot; — in a few old words with initial ''e'': ''este'', ''el'' etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{ro icon}} Several Romanian dictionaries specify the pronunciation [je] for word-initial letter ''e'' in some personal pronouns: [http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=el ''el'', ''ei'', etc.] and in some forms of the verb ''a fi'' (''to be''): [http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=fi ''este'', ''eram'', etc.]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| F f
| {{IPA|/f/}}
| ''f'' in &quot;flag&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | G g
| {{IPA|/ɡ/}}
| ''g'' in &quot;goat&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/dʒ/}}
| ''g'' in &quot;general&quot; or &quot;giraffe&quot; — if ''g'' appears before letters ''e'' or ''i''
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | H h
| {{IPA|/h/}}
| ''h'' in &quot;house&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|(mute)}}
| no pronunciation if ''h'' appears between letters ''c'' or ''g'' and ''e'' or ''i'' (''che, chi, ghe, ghi'')
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | I i
| {{IPA|/i/}}
| ''i'' in &quot;machine&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/j/}}
| ''y'' in &quot;yes&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/ʲ/}}
| (palatalization)
|-
| [[Î]] [[î]] (i with [[circumflex]])
| {{IPA|/ɨ/}}
| Identical to Â, see above
|-
| J j
| {{IPA|/ʒ/}}
| ''s'' in &quot;treasure&quot;
|-
| K k
| {{IPA|/k/}}
| ''c'' in &quot;scan&quot;
|-
| L l
| {{IPA|/l/}}
| ''l'' in &quot;lamp&quot;
|-
| M m
| {{IPA|/m/}}
| ''m'' in &quot;mouth&quot;
|-
| N n
| {{IPA|/n/}}
| ''n'' in &quot;north&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | O o
| {{IPA|/o/}}
| ''o'' in &quot;floor&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/o̯/}}
| (semivocalic {{IPA|/o/}})
|-
| P p
| {{IPA|/p/}}
| ''p'' in &quot;spot&quot;
|-
| Q q
| {{IPA|/k/}}
| ''k'' in &quot;kettle&quot;
|-
| R r
| {{IPA|/r/}}
| [[alveolar trill]] or [[Alveolar tap|tap]]
|-
| S s
| {{IPA|/s/}}
| ''s'' in &quot;song&quot;
|-
| [[S-comma|Ș ș]] (s with [[Comma (punctuation)|comma]]) &lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;
| {{IPA|/ʃ/}}
| ''s'' in &quot;sugar&quot;
|-
| T t
| {{IPA|/t/}}
| ''t'' in &quot;stone&quot;
|-
| [[T-comma|Ț ț]] (t with [[Comma (punctuation)|comma]]) &lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;
| {{IPA|/ts/}}
| ''zz'' in &quot;pizza&quot; but with considerable emphasis on the &quot;ss&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | U u
| {{IPA|/u/}}
| ''u'' in &quot;group&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/w/}}
| ''w'' in &quot;cow&quot;
|-
| V v
| {{IPA|/v/}}
| ''v'' in &quot;vision&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | W w
| {{IPA|/v/}}
| ''v'' in &quot;vision&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/w/}}
| ''w'' in &quot;west&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/u/}}
| ''oo'' in &quot;spoon&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | X x
| {{IPA|/ks/}}
| ''x'' in &quot;six&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/ɡz/}}
| ''x'' in &quot;example&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Y y
| {{IPA|/j/}}
| ''y'' in &quot;yes&quot;
|-
| {{IPA|/i/}}
| ''i'' in &quot;machine&quot;
|-
| Z z
| {{IPA|/z/}}
| ''z'' in &quot;zipper&quot;
|}

&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; See [[Romanian_alphabet#Comma-below (ș and ț) versus cedilla (ş and ţ)|Comma-below (ș and ț) versus cedilla (ş and ţ)]].

==Special letters==
{{Expert-subject-multiple|Linguistics|Typography|date=February 2009}}

[[Image:Two Romanian spellings 1.jpg|thumb|250px|Pre- (''top'') and post-[[1993]] (''bottom'') street signs in [[Bucharest]], showing the two different spellings of the same name]]

Romanian does not use accents. In the sense of [[diacritic]]s as being signs added to letters to alter their pronunciation or to make distinction between words, the Romanian alphabet does not have diacritics. There are, however, five special letters in the Romanian alphabet (associated with four different sounds), formed by modifying other Latin letters; strictly speaking they are not diacritics, but are generally referred to as such.

* [[Ă|Ă ă]] &amp;mdash; ''a'' with [[breve]] – for the sound {{IPA|/ə/}}
* [[Â|Â â]] &amp;mdash; ''a'' with [[circumflex]] – for the sound {{IPA|/ɨ/}}
* [[Î|Î î]] &amp;mdash; ''i'' with [[circumflex]] – for the sound {{IPA|/ɨ/}}
* [[S-comma|Ș ș]] &amp;mdash; ''s'' with [[comma (punctuation)|comma]] – for the sound {{IPA|/ʃ/}}
* [[T-comma|Ț ț]] &amp;mdash; ''t'' with [[comma (punctuation)|comma]] – for the sound {{IPA|/t͡s/}}

The letter ''â'' is used exclusively in the middle of words; its [[majuscule]] version appears only in all-capitals inscriptions.

Writing letters {{Polytonic|ș}} and {{Polytonic|ț}} with a cedilla instead of a comma is considered incorrect by the Romanian Academy. Romanian writings, including books created to teach children to write, treat the comma and cedilla as a variation in font. See [[#Unicode and HTML|Unicode and HTML]] below.

=== Î versus Â ===

The letters ''î'' and ''â'' are phonetically and [[phonology|functionally]] identical. The reason for using both of them is historical, denoting the language's [[Latin language|Latin]] origin.

For a few decades until a [[spelling reform]] in 1904, as many as four or five letters had been used for the same phoneme (''â'', ''ê'', ''î'', ''û'', and occasionally ''ô''), according to an etymological rule.&lt;ref&gt;Alf Lombard, [http://carti.x6.ro/cartea/a/Alf-Lombard-Despre-folosirea-literelor-%E2-si-%EE/lombard.pdf &quot;Despre folosirea literelor â și î&quot;, ''Limba română'', 1992, nr. 10, p. 531]&lt;/ref&gt; The 1904 reform saw only two letters remaining, ''â'' and ''î'', the choice of which followed rules that changed several times during the 20th century.

During the first half of the century the rule was to use ''î'' in word-initial and word-final positions, and ''â'' everywhere else. There were exceptions, imposing the use of ''î'' in internal positions when words were combined or derived with prefixes or suffixes. For example the adjective ''urît'' &quot;ugly&quot; was written with ''î'' because it derives from the verb ''a urî'' &quot;to hate&quot;.

In 1953, during the [[Communist Romania|Communist regime]], the [[Romanian Academy]] eliminated the letter ''â'', replacing it with ''î'' everywhere, including the name of the country, which was to be spelled ''Romînia''. The first stipulation coincided with the official designation of the country as a [[People's Republic]], which meant that its full title was ''Republica Populară Romînă''. A minor spelling reform in 1964 brought back the letter ''â'', but only in the spelling of ''român'' &quot;Romanian&quot; and all its derivatives, including the name of the country. As such, the [[Communist state|Socialist Republic]] proclaimed in 1965 is associated with the spelling ''Republica Socialistă România''.

Soon after the fall of the [[Nicolae Ceaușescu|Ceaușescu]] regime, the [[Romanian Academy]] decided to reintroduce ''â'' from 1993 onward, by canceling the effects of the 1953 spelling reform and essentially reverting to the 1904 rules (with some differences). The move was publicly justified as the rectification of a Soviet influence on the Romanian culture and as a return to a traditional spelling that bears the mark of the language's Latin origin.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} The political context at the time, however, was that the Romanian Academy was largely regarded as a Communist and corrupt institution — Nicolae Ceaușescu and his wife Elena had been its honored members, and membership had generally been granted on political grounds.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} The Academy instituted the 1993 spelling reform as a break with the Academy's Communist past.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} The national community of linguists as well as the foreign linguists specialized in Romanian vehemently opposed the spelling reform; their position was not taken into consideration.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

According to the 1993 reform, the choice between ''î'' and ''â'' is thus again based on a rule that is neither etymological, nor phonological, but positional and morphological. The sound is always spelled as ''â'', except at the beginning and the end of words, where ''î'' is to be used instead. Exceptions include [[proper noun]]s where the usage of the letters is frozen, whichever it may be, and compound words, whose components are each separately subjected to the rule (e.g. ''ne-'' + '''''î'''ndemânatic'' → ''ne'''î'''ndemânatic'' &quot;clumsy&quot;, not *''ne'''â'''ndemânatic''). However, the exception no longer applies to words derived with suffixes, in contrast with the 1904 norm; for instance what was spelled ''urît'' after 1904 became ''urât'' after 1993.

Although the reform was advertised as a means to show the Latin origin of Romanian, statistically only few of the words written with ''â'' according to the 1993 reform actually derive from Latin words having an ''a'' in the corresponding position.&lt;ref&gt;A statistical study cited by George Pruteanu in [http://www.romlit.ro/de_ce_scriu_cu__din_i &quot;De ce scriu cu ''î'' din ''i''&quot; (&quot;Why I spell with ''î''&quot;)] finds that proportion to be only about 15%.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, there are words that used to be closer in spelling to their Latin etymon before the 1993 reform than after; for example ''rîu'' &quot;river&quot;, from the Latin ''rivus'', became ''râu''; the same is true for ''rîde'' &lt; ''ridere'', ''sîn'' &lt; ''sinus'', ''strînge'' &lt; ''stringere'', ''lumînare'' &lt; ''luminaria'', etc.

While the 1993 spelling norm is compulsory in the Romanian [[Romanian educational system|education]] and official publications, and gradually most other publications came to use it, there are still individuals, publications and publishing houses preferring the previous spelling norm or a mixed hybrid system of their own.&lt;ref&gt;''Dicționarul ortografic, ortoepic și morfologic al limbii române'', 2005, p. XLV&lt;/ref&gt; Among them is the weekly cultural magazine ''[[Dilema Veche]]'', whereas some publications, such as ''[[România literară]]'', magazine of the [[Writers' Union of Romania]], and publishing houses such as [[Polirom]] allow authors to choose either spelling norm. Dictionaries, grammars and other linguistic works have also been published using the ''î'' and ''sînt'' long after the 1993 reform.&lt;ref&gt;For instance: Eugenia Dima ''et al.'', ''Dicționar explicativ ilustrat al limbii române'', 2007; Ioan Oprea ''et al.'', ''Noul dicționar universal al limbii române'', third edition, 2008; Dumitru Irimia, ''Gramatica limbii române'', third edition, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many modern English textbooks still insist on the spelling of &quot;I am&quot; as ''eu sînt'', in spite of the modern spelling being ''eu sunt'' – the actual pronunciation of ''sunt'' in rapid speech remains obscure,{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} although most speakers tend to use the sound of ''î''.

=== Comma-below ({{Unicode|ș}} and {{Unicode|ț}}) versus cedilla ({{Unicode|ş}} and {{Unicode|ţ}}) ===

Although the Romanian Academy standard mandates the comma-below variants for the sounds {{IPA|/ʃ/}} and {{IPA|/t͡s/}}, the cedilla variants are still widely used. Many printed and online texts still wrongfully use &quot;s with cedilla&quot; and &quot;t with cedilla&quot;. This state of affairs is due to an initial lack of glyph standardization, compounded by the lack of computer font support for the comma-below variants (see the [[#Unicode_and_HTML|Unicode]] section for details).

The lack of support for the comma diacritics has been corrected in current versions of major operating systems: Windows Vista or newer, Linux distributions after 2005, currently supported MacOS versions. As mandated by the European Union, Microsoft released a [http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/en/details.aspx?FamilyID=0ec6f335-c3de-44c5-a13d-a1e7cea5ddea&amp;displaylang=en&amp;pf=true font update] to correct this deficiency in Windows XP in early 2007, soon after Romania joined the European Union.

=== Obsolete diacritics ===

[[Image:Capac de canal Bucuresci.JPG|thumb|250px|Old Bucharest [[manhole cover]] inscribed according to the etymologically prone spelling at the time, which reads ''BUCURESCI CANALISARE'' (meaning ''Bucharests sewers''). Compare to today's ''BUCUREȘTI CANALIZARE''.]]

Before the spelling reform of 1904, there were several additional letters with diacritical marks.
* Vowels:
** [[ĭ]] &amp;mdash; ''i'' with [[breve]] indicated [[semivowel]] ''i'' as part of Romanian [[diphthong]]s and [[triphthong]]s ''ia'', ''ei'', ''iei'' etc., or a final, &quot;whispered&quot; sound of the preceding [[palatalization|palatalized]] consonant, in words such as ''[[wikt:Bucureşti#Romanian|Bucureşti]]'' ({{IPA|/bu.kuˈreʃtʲ/}}), ''lupi'' ({{IPA|/lupʲ/}} – &quot;wolves&quot;), and ''greci'' ({{IPA|/ɡret͡ʃʲ/}} – &quot;Greeks&quot;) &amp;mdash; ''Bucurescĭ'' (the proper spelling at the time used ''c'' instead of ''t'', ''see [[wikt:-eşti|-eşti]]''), ''lupĭ'', ''grecĭ''. By replacing this letter with a simple ''i'' without making any additional changes, the phonetic value of the letter ''i'' became ambiguous; even native speakers can sometimes mispronounce words such as the toponym ''[[Pecica]]'' (which has two syllables, but is often mistakenly pronounced with three) or the name ''[[Nicholas Mavrogenes|Mavrogheni]]'' (which has four syllables, not three).&lt;ref&gt;{{ro icon}} Mioara Avram, ''Ortografie pentru toţi'', Editura Litera Internaţional, Bucureşti – Chișinău, 2002, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in a number of words such as ''subiect'' &quot;subject&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Most dictionaries give the syllabification ''su-biect'', implying that ''i'' is a semivowel, but ''Dicționar de neologisme'' syllabifies it as ''su-bi-ect'', with vocalic ''i'': [http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=subiect Dexonline.ro]&lt;/ref&gt; and ''ziar'' &quot;newspaper&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Dictionaries generally recommend the pronunciation with vocalic ''i'', ''zi-ar'', but the pronunciation in one syllable is also recorded, among others, by Ioana Chiţoran, in ''The Phonology of Romanian'', 2002, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; the pronunciation of ''i'' as a vowel or as a semivowel is different among speakers.
** [[ŭ]] &amp;mdash; ''u'' with [[breve]] was used only in the ending of a word. Unvoiced in most cases, it served to indicate that the previous consonant was not palatalized, or that the preceding vowel ''i'' was fully voiced. When voiced, it would follow a stressed vowel and stand in for semivowel ''u'', as in words ''eŭ'', ''aŭ'', and ''meŭ'', all spelled today without the breve. Once frequent, it survives today in author [[Mateiu Caragiale]]'s name – originally spelled ''Mateiŭ'' (it is not specified whether the pronunciation should adopt a version that he himself probably never used, while in many editions he is still credited as ''Matei''). In other names, only the breve was dropped, while preserving the pronunciation of a semivowel ''u'', as is the case of [[Bogdan Petriceicu Hasdeu|B.P. Hasdeŭ]].
** [[ĕ]] &amp;mdash; ''e'' with [[breve]]. This letter is now replaced with ''ă''. The existence of two letters for one sound, the schwa, had an etymological purpose, showing from which vowel (&quot;a&quot; or &quot;e&quot;) it originally derived. For example ''împĕrat'' – &quot;emperor&quot; (&lt;[[Imperator]]), ''vĕd'' – &quot;I see&quot; (&lt;vedo), ''umĕr'' – &quot;shoulder&quot; (&lt;[[humerus]]), ''păsĕri'' – &quot;birds&quot; (&lt;cf. [[passer]]).
** [[é|é / É]] &amp;mdash; Latin small/capital letter ''[[e]]'' with [[acute accent]] indicated a sound that corresponds either to today's Romanian [[diphthong]] ''ea'', or in some words, to today's Romanian letter ''e''. It would originally indicate the sound of Romanian letter ''e'' when it were pronounced as diphthong ''ea'' in certain Romanian regions, e.g. ''acéste'' (today spelled ''aceste'') and ''céle'' (today spelled ''cele''). This letter would sometimes indicate a derived word from a Romanian root word containing Latin letter ''e'', as is the case of ''mirésă'' (today spelled ''mireasă'') derived from ''mire''. For other words it would underlie a relationship between a Romanian word and a Latin word containing letter ''e'', where the Romanian word would use ''é'', such as ''gréle'' (today spelled ''grele'') derived from Latin word [[wikt:grevis#Latin|grevis]]. Lastly, this letter was used to accommodate the sound that corresponds to today's Romanian diphthong ''ia'', as in the word ''ér'' (''iar'' today).{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}
** [[ó|ó / Ó]] &amp;mdash; Latin small/capital letter ''[[o]]'' with [[acute accent]] indicated a sound that corresponds to today's Romanian diphthong ''oa''. This letter would sometimes indicate a derived word from a Romanian root word containing Latin letter ''o'', as is the case of ''popóre'' (today spelled ''popoare'') derived from ''popor''. For other words it would underlie a relationship between a Romanian word and a Latin word containing letter ''o'', where the Romanian word would use ''ó'', such as ''fórte'' (today spelled ''foarte'') derived from Latin word [[wikt:forte#Latin|forte]]. Lastly, this letter was used to accommodate the sound that corresponds to today's Romanian diphthong ''oa'', as in the word ''fóme'' (''foame'' today).{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

* Consonants
** [[D-comma|{{unicode|d̦}} / {{unicode|D̦}}]] &amp;mdash; Latin small/capital letter ''d'' with comma below was used to indicate the sound that corresponds today to Romanian letter ''[[z]]''. It would denote that the word it belonged to was assumed to be derived from Latin and that its corresponding Latin letter was ''[[d]]''. Examples of words containing this letter are: ''{{unicode|d̦i}}'' (''[[day]]'' in [[English language|English]]) – assumed&lt;ref&gt;[http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=zi Definition of Romanian word ''zi'' at dexonline.ro]&lt;/ref&gt; to be derived from the Latin word [[wikt:dies#Latin|dies]], ''{{unicode|Dumned̦eu}}'' ([[God]] in [[English language|English]]) – assumed&lt;ref&gt;[http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=dumnezeu Definition of Romanian word ''Dumnezeu'' at dexonline.ro]&lt;/ref&gt; to be derived from Latin phrase [[Dominus|Domine]] [[Deus]]), ''{{unicode|d̦ână}}'' ([[fairy]] in [[English language|English]]) – supposed&lt;ref&gt;[http://dexonline.ro/search.php?cuv=ZÂNĂ Definition of Romanian word ''zână'' at dexonline.ro]&lt;/ref&gt; to be derived from the Latin word [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]]. In today's Romanian language this letter is no longer present and Latin letter ''[[z]]'' is used in its stead.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

Use of these letters was not fully adopted even before 1904, as some publications (e.g. ''[[Timpul]]'' and ''[[Universul]]'') chose to use a simplified approach that resembled today's Romanian language writing.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

=== Other diacritics ===

As with other languages, the [[acute accent]] is sometimes used in Romanian texts to indicate the [[Stress (linguistics)|stressed vowel]] in some words. This use is regular in dictionary headwords, but also occasionally found in carefully edited texts to disambiguate between [[homograph]]s that are not also [[homophone]]s, such as to differentiate between ''cópii'' (&quot;copies&quot;) and ''copíi'' (&quot;children&quot;), ''éra'' (&quot;era&quot;) and ''erá'' (&quot;was&quot;), ''ácele'' (&quot;the needles&quot;) and ''acéle'' (&quot;those&quot;), etc. The accent also distinguishes between homographic verb forms, such as ''încúie'' and ''încuié'' (&quot;he locks&quot; and &quot;he has locked&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;''Dicționarul ortografic, ortoepic și morfologic al limbii române'', 2005, p. LI {{ro icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Diacritics in some borrowings are kept: ''bourrée'', ''pietà''. Foreign names are also usually spelled with their original diacritics: ''Bâle'', ''Molière'', even when an acute accent might be wrongly interpreted as a stress, as in ''István'' or ''Gérard''. However, frequently used foreign names, such as names of cities or countries, are often spelled without diacritics: ''Bogota'', ''Panama'', ''Peru''.&lt;ref&gt;''Dicționarul ortografic, ortoepic și morfologic al limbii române'', 2005, p. LII {{ro icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Digital typography ==
=== ISO 8859 ===
[[Image:WidespreadWrongUsageOfRomanianDiacritics.PNG|thumb|right|600px|Widespread Wrong Usage of Romanian Diacritics]]
The character encoding standard [[ISO 8859]] initially defined a single code page for the entire Central and Eastern Europe — [[ISO 8859-2]]. This code page includes only &quot;s&quot; and &quot;t&quot; with cedillas. The South-Eastern European [[ISO 8859-16]] includes &quot;s&quot; and &quot;t&quot; with comma below on the same places &quot;s&quot; and &quot;t&quot; with cedilla were in ISO 8859-2. The ISO 8859-16 code page became a standard after Unicode became widespread, however, so it was largely ignored by software vendors.

=== Unicode and HTML ===

The circumflex and breve accented Romanian letters were part of the [[Unicode]] standard since its inception, as well as the cedilla variants of s and t. {{Unicode|Ș}} and {{Unicode|ț}} (comma-below variants) were added to Unicode version 3.0.&lt;ref&gt;Unicode 3.0 standard, p.162&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://unicode.org/Public/UNIDATA/DerivedAge.txt Unicode.org]&lt;/ref&gt; From Unicode version 3.0 to version 5.1, the cedilla-using characters were specified by the Unicode Standard to be &quot;used in both Turkish and Romanian data&quot; and that &quot;a glyph variant with comma below is preferred for Romanian&quot;; On the newly encoded comma-using characters, it said that they should be used &quot;when distinct comma below form is required&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://unicode.org/Public/3.0-Update/NamesList-3.0.0.txt Unicode.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://unicode.org/Public/5.1.0/ucd/NamesList.txt Unicode.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Unicode 5.2 explicitly states that &quot;the form with the cedilla is preferred in Turkish, and the form with the comma below is preferred in Romanian&quot;, while mentioning (possibly for historical reasons) that &quot;in Turkish and Romanian, a cedilla and a comma below sometimes replace one another&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode5.2.0/ch07.pdf Unicode 5.2 Chapter 7, European Alphabetic Scripts]&lt;/ref&gt;

Widespread adoption was hampered for some years by the lack of fonts providing the new glyphs. In May 2007, five months after Romania (and Bulgaria) joined the [[EU]], Microsoft released updated fonts that include all official glyphs of the Romanian (and [[Bulgarian language#Alphabet|Bulgarian]]) alphabet.&lt;ref name=&quot;update&quot; &gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/Downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=0ec6f335-c3de-44c5-a13d-a1e7cea5ddea&amp;displaylang=en European Union Expansion Font Update], microsoft.com&lt;/ref&gt; This font update targeted Windows XP SP2, Windows Server 2003, and Windows Vista. The subset of Unicode most widely supported on Microsoft Windows systems, [[Windows Glyph List 4]], still does not include the comma-below variants of S and T.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Phoneme
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | With comma (official)
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | With cedilla
|-
! Character
! Unicode position (hex)
! HTML entity
! Character
! Unicode position (hex)
! HTML entity
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | {{IPA|/ʃ/}}
| {{Unicode|Ș}}
| 0218
| &amp;amp;#x218; or &amp;amp;#536;
| Ş
| 015E
| &amp;amp;#x15E; or &amp;amp;#350;
|-
| {{Unicode|ș}}
| 0219
| &amp;amp;#x219; or &amp;amp;#537;
| ş
| 015F
| &amp;amp;#x15F; or &amp;amp;#351;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | {{IPA|/t͡s/}}
| {{Unicode|Ț}}
| 021A
| &amp;amp;#x21A; or &amp;amp;#538;
| Ţ
| 0162
| &amp;amp;#x162; or &amp;amp;#354;
|-
| {{Unicode|ț}}
| 021B
| &amp;amp;#x21B; or &amp;amp;#539;
| ţ
| 0163
| &amp;amp;#x163; or &amp;amp;#355;
|}
Vowels with diacritics are coded as follows:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! | Phoneme
! Character
! Unicode position (hex)
! HTML entity
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | {{IPA|/ə/}}
| {{unicode|Ă}}
| 0102
| &amp;amp;#x102; or &amp;amp;#258;
|-
| {{unicode|ă}}
| 0103
| &amp;amp;#x103; or &amp;amp;#259;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; | {{IPA|/ɨ/}}
| {{unicode|Â}}
| 00C2
| &amp;amp;Acirc; or &amp;amp;#xC2; or &amp;amp;#194;
|-
| {{unicode|â}}
| 00E2
| &amp;amp;acirc; or &amp;amp;#xE2; or &amp;amp;#226;
|-
| {{unicode|Î}}
| 00CE
| &amp;amp;Icirc; or &amp;amp;#xCE; or &amp;amp;#206;
|-
| {{unicode|î}}
| 00EE
| &amp;amp;icirc; or &amp;amp;#xEE; or &amp;amp;#238;
|}

==== Adobe/Linotype/Vista de-facto standard ====

[[Image:The şuţ șuț font demo in Adobe Caslon Pro Regular via Fontmatrix.png|thumb|200px|Inconsistent cedilla glyphs in Adobe Caslon (left). The correct Romanian rendering (right) can be obtained by activating the [[OpenType]] &lt;code&gt;GSUB/latn/ROM/locl&lt;/code&gt; feature, which remaps the s with cedilla glyph to comma-below. The rendering on the right is visually indistinguishable from the rendering produced by comma-below code points for this font.]]

[[Adobe Systems]] decided&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.typophile.com/node/2764#comment-22015 comments of Canadian type designer John Hudson], typophile.com&lt;/ref&gt; that the Unicode glyphs &quot;t with cedilla&quot; U+0162/3 are not used in any language. Adobe has therefore substituted the glyphs with &quot;t with comma below&quot; (U+021A/B) in all the fonts they ship. The unfortunate consequence of this decision is that Romanian documents using the (unofficial) Unicode points U+015E/F and U+0162/3 (for ș and ț) are rendered in Adobe fonts in a visually inconsistent way using &quot;s with cedilla&quot;, but &quot;t with comma&quot; (see figure). [[Mergenthaler Linotype Company|Linotype]] fonts that support Romanian glyphs mostly follow this convention.&lt;ref&gt;Linotype's font finder allows users to test font rendering with their own sample texts. Tested with the sample text &quot;&amp;#538;â&amp;#537;nit în &amp;#351;an&amp;#355;&quot;.[http://www.linotype.com/featuresearch?cf=adobece&amp;cf=euro&amp;cf=latinext Linotype.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

The fonts introduced by Microsoft in Windows Vista also implement this de-facto Adobe standard. Few Microsoft fonts provide a consistent look when cedilla variants are used; notable ones are [[Tahoma (typeface)|Tahoma]], [[Verdana]], [[Trebuchet MS]], [[Microsoft Sans Serif]] and [[Segoe UI]].

The free [[DejaVu fonts|DejaVu]] and [[Linux Libertine]] fonts provide proper and consistent glyphs in both variants. [[Red Hat]]'s [[Liberation fonts]] only support the comma below variants starting with version 1.04, scheduled for inclusion in [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] 10.

==== OpenType &lt;code&gt;ROM/locl&lt;/code&gt; feature ====

Some [[OpenType]] fonts from Adobe and all C-series [[:Category:Windows Vista typefaces|Vista fonts]] implement the optional OpenType feature &lt;code&gt;GSUB/latn/ROM/locl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/features_ko.htm#locl &lt;code&gt;locl&lt;/code&gt; glyph localization feature tag explained.], microsoft.com&lt;/ref&gt; This feature forces &quot;s with cedilla&quot; to be rendered using the same glyph as &quot;s with comma below&quot;. When this second (but optional) remapping takes place, Romanian Unicode text is rendered with comma-below glyphs regardless of code point variants.

Unfortunately, most Microsoft pre-Vista OpenType fonts ([[Arial]] etc.) do not implement the &lt;code&gt;ROM/locl&lt;/code&gt; feature, even after the European Union Expansion Font Update,&lt;ref name=update/&gt; so old documents will look inconsistent as in the left side of the above figure. Select few fonts, e.g. [[Verdana]] and [[Trebuchet MS]], not only have a consistent look for cedilla variants (after the EU update), but also do a simultaneous remapping of cedilla s and t to comma-below variants when &lt;code&gt;ROM/locl&lt;/code&gt; is activated. The free DejaVu and Linux Libertine fonts do not yet offer this feature in their current releases, but development versions do.

[[Pango]] [[Pango#Support_for_OpenType_features|supports the &lt;code&gt;locl&lt;/code&gt; tag]] since version 1.17. [[XeTeX]] supports &lt;code&gt;locl&lt;/code&gt; since version 0.995. As of July 2008, very few Windows applications support the &lt;code&gt;locl&lt;/code&gt; feature tag. From the Adobe [[CS3]] suite, only [[Adobe InDesign|InDesign]] has support for it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://store.adobe.com/type/browser/pdfs/OTGuide.pdf p. 15], store.adobe.com&lt;/ref&gt;

The status of Romanian support in the free fonts that ship with [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] is maintained at [http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/L10N/Tasks/Ro_fonts#Font_status_matrix Fedoraproject.org].

==== Combining characters ====

Unicode also allows diacritical marks to be represented as standalone [[Unicode#Combining_characters|combining characters]]. For Romanian characters this method is practically unsupported in commercial fonts. A few free fonts like [[Charis SIL]], DejaVu or Linux Libertine support this method, but the typographical quality varies, thus it is preferable to use the single code points instead.

===(La)TeX===

[[LaTeX]] allows typesetting in Romanian using the cedilla Ş and Ţ using the [[Cork encoding]]. The comma-below variants are not completely supported in the standard 8-bit TeX font encodings. The lack of a standard [[LATEX Internal Character Representation|LICR]] (LaTeX Internal Character Representations) for comma-below Ș and Ț is part of the problem. The &lt;code&gt;latin10&lt;/code&gt; input method attempts to remedy the problem by defining the \textcommabelow LICR accent. This is unfortunately not supported by the &lt;code&gt;utf8&lt;/code&gt; input method.
The &lt;code&gt;latin10&lt;/code&gt; package composes the comma-below glyphs by superimposing a comma and the letters S and T. This method is suitable only for printing. In [[PDF]] documents produced this way searching or copying text does not work properly. The Polish QX encoding has some support for comma-below glyphs, which are improperly mapped to cedilla LICRs, but also lacks A breve (Ă), which must always be composite, thus unsearchable.

In the [[Latin Modern]] [[PostScript fonts|Type 1 fonts]] the T with comma below is found under the AGL name /Tcommaaccent. This is in contradiction with Adobe's decision discussed above, which puts a T with comma-below at /Tcedilla. In consequence, no fixed mapping can work across all Type 1 fonts; each font must come with its own mapping. Unfortunately, TeX output drivers, like [[dvips]], [[dvipdfm]] or [[pdfTeX]]'s internal PDF driver, access the glyphs by [[Adobe Glyph List|AGL]] name. Since all of the output drivers mentioned are unaware of this peculiarity, the problem is essentially intractable across all fonts. In consequence, one needs to use fonts that include a mapping which is not bypassed by TeX. This is the case with newer TeX engine [[XeTeX]], which can use Unicode OpenType fonts, and does not bypass the font's Unicode map.

===Keyboard layout===
[[Image:Romanian keyboard letters.jpg|thumb|250px|Romanian letters Â and Ă on the keyboard of an Apple [[MacBook Pro]]]]
[[Image:Romanian-keyboard-layout.png|thumb|400px|Romanian SR 13392:2004 (&quot;primary&quot;) keyboard layout]]

The current '''Romanian National Standard SR 13392:2004''' establishes two layouts for Romanian keyboards: a “primary”&lt;ref&gt;[http://diacritice.sourceforge.net/imagini/ro.png Primary keyboard layout], sourceforge.net&lt;/ref&gt; one and a “secondary”&lt;ref&gt;[http://diacritice.sourceforge.net/imagini/ro_us.png Secondary keyboard layout], diacritice.sourceforge.net&lt;/ref&gt; one.

The “primary” layout is intended for more traditional users that learned long ago how to type with older, Microsoft-style implementations of the Romanian keyboard. The “secondary” layout is mainly used by programmers and it does not contradict the physical arrangement of keys on a US-style keyboard. The “secondary” arrangement is used as the default one by the majority of [[Linux|GNU/Linux]] distributions.

There are four Romanian-specific characters that are incorrectly implemented in all Microsoft Windows versions before Vista:

* “S with comma below” (U+0218) – incorrectly implemented as “S with cedilla below” (U+015E)
* “s with comma below” (U+0219) – incorrectly implemented as “s with cedilla below” (U+015F)
* “T with comma below” (U+021A) – incorrectly implemented as “T with cedilla below” (U+0162)
* “t with comma below” (U+021B) – incorrectly implemented as “t with cedilla below” (U+0163)

Since Romanian hardware keyboards are not widely available, Cristian Secară has created a driver that allows the Romanian characters to be generated with a US-style keyboard, in all Windows versions previous to Vista. It uses the right AltGr key modifier to generate the characters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Cristian Secară|url=http://www.secarica.ro/html/ro_keyboard.html|language=Romanian|title=RO Keyboard|accessdate=6 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An alternative, more ergonomic (though non-standard) keyboard layout, with a user choice between cedillas and commas, is proposed and implemented for the Microsoft Windows operating system by the Ergo Romanian project. They suggest altering keys on the standard QWERTY layout which are less frequent in Romanian, namely q, w, y, k, x, to produce Romanian characters ă, ș, ț, î, â, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Anasoftware|url=http://www.ergoromanian.com/|title=Ergo Romanian|accessdate=6 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Phonetic alphabet==
There is a Romanian equivalent to the English-language [[ICAO spelling alphabet|NATO phonetic alphabet]]. Most code words are people's first names, with the exception of K, J, Q, W, Y, and Z. Letters with diacritics (Ă, Â, Î, {{Unicode|Ș}}, {{Unicode|Ț}}) are generally transmitted without diacritics (A, A, I, S, T).

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;
! style=&quot;width:6em&quot; | Word
! style=&quot;width:9em&quot; | [[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]] (unofficial)
| rowspan=&quot;14&quot; style=&quot;background:white&quot; | &amp;nbsp;
! &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;
! style=&quot;width:6em&quot; | Word
! style=&quot;width:9em&quot; | [[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]] (unofficial)
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | A || Ana || {{IPA|/ˈa.na/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | N || Nicolae || {{IPA|/ni.koˈla.e/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | B || Barbu || {{IPA|/ˈbar.bu/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | O || Olga || {{IPA|/ˈol.ɡa/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | C || Constantin || {{IPA|/kon.stanˈtin/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | P || Petre || {{IPA|/ˈpe.tre/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | D || Dumitru || {{IPA|/duˈmi.tru/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Q || Q || {{IPA|/kju/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | E || Elena || {{IPA|/eˈle.na/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | R || Radu || {{IPA|/ˈra.du/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | F || Florea || {{IPA|/ˈflo.re̯a/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | S || Sandu || {{IPA|/ˈsan.du/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | G || Gheorghe || {{IPA|/ˈɡe̯or.ɡe/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | T || Tudor || {{IPA|/ˈtu.dor/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | H || Haralambie || {{IPA|/ha.raˈlam.bi.e/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | U || Udrea || {{IPA|/ˈu.dre̯a/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | I || Ion || {{IPA|/iˈon/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | V || Vasile || {{IPA|/vaˈsi.le/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | J || Jiu || {{IPA|/ʒiw/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | W || dublu V || {{IPA|/du.bluˈve/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | K || kilogram || {{IPA|/ki.loˈɡram/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | X || Xenia || {{IPA|/ˈkse.ni.a/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | L || Lazăr || {{IPA|/ˈla.zər/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Y || I grec || {{IPA|/ˈi.ɡrek/}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | M || Maria || {{IPA|/maˈri.a/}}
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Z || zahăr || {{IPA|/ˈza.hər/}}
|}

==See also==

* [[Romanian Cyrillic alphabet]]

==References==
===Notes===

{{reflist}}

===Bibliography===

* {{ro icon}} Mioara Avram, ''Ortografie pentru toţi'', Editura Litera Internaţional, 2002
* {{cite book | last = The Unicode Consortium | title = The Unicode Standard, Version 3.0 | publisher = Addison-Wesley | location = Boston | year = 2000 | isbn = 0-201-61633-5 }}

==External links==
&lt;!--* [http://www.omniglot.com/writing/romanian.htm Romanian language, alphabet and pronunciation] Omniglot page on Romanian contains way too many mistakes. Please leave out.--&gt;
* [http://www.unicode.org/charts/PDF/U0180.pdf Unicode Latin Extended-B characters], unicode.org
* [http://www.ergoromanian.com/er1site/short_history.htm Short history on Romanian keyboard layouts], ergoromanian.com
* [http://www.ergoromanian.com/ Ergo Romanian: An ergonomic Romanian keyboard layout for Windows (with comma or cedillas)], ergoromanian.com
* [http://www.etc.tuiasi.ro/sibm/romanian_spoken_language/index.htm Sounds of the Romanian Language], etc.tuiasi.ro

{{Romanian language}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Romanian Alphabet}}
[[Category:Latin alphabets]]
[[Category:Romanian language|Alphabet, Romanian]]
[[Category:Keyboard layouts]]

[[bg:Румънска азбука]]
[[hu:Román ábécé]]
[[mk:Романска азбука]]
[[pl:Alfabet rumuński]]
[[pt:Alfabeto romeno]]
[[ro:Alfabetul limbii române]]
[[rmy:Rumunikano lekhipen]]
[[ru:Румынский алфавит]]
[[sv:Rumänska alfabetet]]
[[tg:Алифбои руминӣ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
