<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4194584" ns="0" title="Purdue University North Central"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University
|name=Purdue University North Central
|image=[[Image:PurdueNorthCentralLogo.jpg]]
|type=[[public university|public]] [[coeducational]]
|endowment=$0.9 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=America's Best Colleges 2006 | publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report | accessdate=2006-02-25 | url=http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_1826_brief.php}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|established=1948 ([[Purdue University North Central#History|details]])
|city=[[Westville, Indiana|Westville]]
|state=[[Indiana|IN]]
|country=[[USA]]
|crazy people=21
|chancellor=James B. Dworkin
|students=4,463 
|undergrad=4,379 
|postgrad=84
|campus=rural: {{convert|305|acre|ha|1}}
|nickname = Panthers
|athletics=[[Chicagoland Collegiate Athletic Conference|CCAC]] ([[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA DII]])
|mascot=Pounce the Panther
|affiliations=[[Purdue University System]]
|website=[http://www.pnc.edu www.pnc.edu]
}}

'''Purdue University North Central''' is a regional campus within the [[Purdue University system]] that is located in rural [[LaPorte County, Indiana|LaPorte County]] near [[Westville, Indiana|Westville]] in northwestern [[Indiana]].
{{TOCleft}}
==Academics==

Purdue North Central offers a number certificate programs, associate degrees, bachelor's degrees, and two master's degrees: in [[Master of Business Administration|Business Administration]] and in Elementary Education. Undergraduate students at Purdue North Central can transfer to any other Purdue campuses and complete their degrees there.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnc.edu/academics/certif.html certificate programs]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnc.edu/academics/associate.html associate degrees]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnc.edu/academics/bachelor.html bachelor's degrees]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnc.edu/academics/master.html master's degrees]&lt;/ref&gt;

For the Fall semester of 2011, Purdue North Central has more than 100 full-time faculty members and over 150 part-time instructors. Over the years, Purdue North Central has graduated more than 8,700 alumni. Most continue to live in Northwest Indiana, but its graduates can be found in 49 states and 7 foreign countries.

===Colleges, departments and programs===
Purdue North Central recently added new degree programs in Electrical Engineering and Early Childhood Education. As the campus continues to grow and offer new degree programs, it is striving to attract students from across the United States and around the world. Purdue North Central has tuition agreements with many midwestern states, which lowers tuition for many out-of-state students.

The smallest campus in the Purdue system, PNC has often been the fastest growing component of the university.  Purdue University North Central is organized into 12 departments, in 4 colleges:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnc.edu/academics PNC Academic web page]&lt;/ref&gt;

*College of Business
**Department of Business 
**Department of Organizational Leadership and Supervision 
**MBA Program 
*College of Engineering &amp; Technology
**Department of Engineering
***Mechanical Engineering Program (ME)
***Electrical Engineering Program (EE)
**Department of Engineering Technology
***Construction Engineering Management Technology (CEMT) Program
***Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering Technology (ECET) Program
***Mechanical Engineering Technology (MET) Program
**Department of Computer &amp; Information Technology 
*College of Liberal Arts
**Department of Communication 
**Department of Education 
**Department of English and Modern Languages 
**Department of Social Sciences 
*College of Science
**Department of Biology and Chemistry 
**Department of Mathematics, Statistics and Physics 
**Department of Nursing

===Accreditation===

Purdue University North Central as a whole has been accredited by the Commission on Institutions of Higher Education of the [[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]] continuously since 1971.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncahlc.org/index.php?option=com_directory&amp;Action=ShowBasic&amp;instid=1207 NCAHLC web site]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[ABET|The Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology]] has continuously accredited Purdue University North Central's bachelor's degree in Mechanical Technology (MT) since 1992, and the following associate degrees since the dates listed: Building Construction Management Technology (BCMT) 2004, Electrical Engineering Technology (EET) 1986, Industrial Engineering Technology (IET) 1986 and Mechanical Engineering Technology (MET) 1992. In August 2010, the baccalaureate programs in Construction Engineering Management Technology (CEMT) and Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering Technology (ECET) received their initial accreditation, retroactive to 2008.  Purdue North Central is the only Purdue campus whose ECET Degree is accredited as both an Electrical ET and a Computer ET program.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abet.org/AccredProgramSearch/AccreditationSearch.aspx ABET Accredited Programs Search] of &quot;Purdue University North Central&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Other individual programs are also accredited by the [[Association of Collegiate Business Schools and Programs]], the [[National League for Nursing Accreditation Commission]], and the [[National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education]].

==Campus and student body==

Purdue University North Central is located on {{convert|268|acre|ha|1}} in rural LaPorte County near [[Westville, Indiana]] along [[U.S. Route 421|U.S. Highway 421]]. Purdue University North Central has three academic buildings and a [[Veterinary medicine|veterinary]] emergency facility. The grounds of Purdue University North Central have Shakespeare's Garden adjacent to a picturesque pond, [[tennis]] courts, a [[baseball]] diamond, and four outdoor [[basketball]] courts.

For the Fall semester of 2009, Purdue North Central has 4,463 students, of which slightly less than half (1,843 students) are from LaPorte County. Female students (2,544; 57%) outnumber male (1,919; 43%) by 32.6%. Almost all are [[undergraduate]] students, except for the 84 graduate students in its two master's program. The majority (2,716; 60.9%) are full-time students taking 12 or more credit hours. 

There are 725 students (16.2%) identified as ethnic minorities, of which there are 297 (6.7%) African-American; 48 (1%) Asian-American; 223 (5%) Hispanic; 32 (0.7%) Native American; and 125 (2.8%) identified as &quot;other&quot; minorities. The average student age is 25.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pnc.edu/about/quickfacts.html PNC Quick Facts]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot; 
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; | '''History at a glance'''
|-
!colspan=4 align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;background:#eFeFeF;&quot;| Purdue University North Central was established via the 1967 merger of:
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; rowspan=2| • 
|width=&quot;100px&quot; rowspan=2| Purdue University Laporte Extension 
| '''Established''' 
| 1948
|-
| '''Location''' 
| [[LaPorte, Indiana|LaPorte]], [[Indiana|IN]] [[USA]]
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; rowspan=2| • 
|width=&quot;100px&quot; rowspan=2| Purdue University Michigan City Extension 
| '''Established''' 
| 1949
|-
| '''Location''' 
| [[Michigan City, Indiana|Michigan City]], [[Indiana|IN]] [[USA]]
|}
Purdue University North Central's first permanent site in which classes were offered was in [[John H. Barker]]'s former mansion in 1948 at [[Michigan City, Indiana]], which was donated by his daughter, Catherine Barker Hickox. Purdue University North Central first opened for classes at its current site in 1967 after having started offering classes in [[LaPorte, Indiana]] during 1948 and in [[Michigan City, Indiana]] during 1949.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Athletics==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:PurdueNorthCentralSpiritMark.jpg|thumb|right|Athletics logo]] --&gt;
Purdue University North Central teams are members of [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]] and compete within the [[Chicagoland Collegiate Athletic Conference]]. Intercollegiately, Purdue University North Central sponsors a men's basketball team, a men's baseball team, a men's golf team, a women's softball team, and a women's volleyball team. The moniker of Purdue University North Central's teams is the Panthers. The official mascot is Pounce the Panther.

Prior to the Panthers moniker, Purdue University North Central's moniker for its intercollegiate athletics teams was the Centaurs from 1967 until 2003.

== See also==
* [[Purdue University System]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://www.pnc.edu Official website]
*[http://www.pnc.edu/athletics Official athletics website]
*[http://www.pnc.edu/cd/campsmap.html Campus map]
{{coord|41.584339|-86.894254|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{Public colleges and universities in Indiana}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Chicago}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indiana]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Purdue University]]
[[Category:Northwest Indiana]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1948]]
[[Category:Education in LaPorte County, Indiana]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in LaPorte County, Indiana]]
[[Category:Education in Porter County, Indiana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
