<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="421579" ns="0" title="Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware
| logo                   = [[Image:Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware Logo.gif|322px]]
| screenshot             =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[Image:Tiki 5 0 default homepage.png|250px]] --&gt;
| collapsible            = yes
| caption                = Tiki 5.0 default homepage screenshot (using Fivealive theme)
| author                 =
| developer              =
| released               = 2002-08-09
| latest release version = 8.1
| latest release date    = {{release date|2011|11|11}}
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| programming language   = [[PHP]]
| platform               =
| language               = [http://tiki.org/i18n Multilingual] (30+)
| status                 = Active
| genre                  = [[Wiki software]] / [[Content Management System]] (CMS) / [[Geospatial Content Management System]] (GeoCMS) / [[Groupware]] [[web application]] / [[Online office suite]]
| license                = [[LGPL]] 2.1
| website                = http://tiki.org
}}
'''Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware''', originally and more commonly known as '''TikiWiki''' or simply '''Tiki''', is a [[free and open source software|free and open source]] [[wiki]]-based, [[content management system]] and [[Online office suite]] written primarily in [[PHP]] and distributed under the [[GNU Lesser General Public License]] (LGPL) license.&lt;ref&gt;[http://info.tiki.org/Fact+Sheet Tiki Fact Sheet]&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition to enabling [[website]]s and [[Web portal|portal]]s on the internet and on [[intranet]]s and [[extranet]]s, Tiki contains a number of collaboration features allowing it to operate as a [[Geospatial Content Management System]] (GeoCMS) or Groupware web application.

Tiki includes all the basic features common to most CMSs such as the ability to register and maintain individual user accounts within a flexible and rich permission / privilege system, create and manage menus, RSS-feeds, customize page layout, perform logging, and administer the system. All administration tasks are accomplished through a browser-based user interface.

Tiki features an all-in-one design, as opposed to a core+extensions model followed by other CMSs. This allows for future-proof upgrades (since all features are released together), but has the drawback of an extremely large (more than 1,000,000 lines) codebase.

Tiki can run on any computing platform that supports both a web server capable of running PHP 5 (including Apache, IIS, Lighttpd, and nginx) and a MySQL database to store content and settings.&lt;ref&gt;http://doc.tiki.org/requirements Tiki Requirements&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major components==
Tiki has four major categories of components: content creation and management tools, content organization tools and navigation aids, communication tools, and configuration and administration tools. These components enable administrators and users to create and manage content, as well as letting them communicate to others and configure sites.

In addition, Tiki allows each user to choose from various visual themes. These themes are implemented using [[Cascading Style Sheets|CSS]] and the open source [[Smarty]] template engine. Additional themes can be created by a Tiki administrator for branding or customization as well.

==Internationalization==
Tiki is an international project, supporting many languages. The default interface language in Tiki is English/en, but any language that can be encoded and displayed using the [[utf-8]] encoding can be supported.&lt;ref&gt;http://tiki.org/i18n Tiki i18n (Internationalization) and languages&lt;/ref&gt; Translated strings can be included via an external language file, or by translating interface strings directly, through the database. As of 29 September 2005, Tiki had been fully translated into eight languages and reportedly 90% or more translated into another five languages, as well as partial translations for nine additional languages.

Tiki also supports interactive translation of actual wiki pages and was the initial wiki engine used in the Cross Lingual Wiki Engine Project.&lt;ref&gt;http://wiki-translation.com/Cross+Lingual+Wiki+Engine+Project Cross Lingual Wiki Engine Project&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Louis-Philippe Huberdeau, Sébastien Paquet, and Alain Désilets, “The Cross-Lingual Wiki Engine: enabling collaboration across language barriers,” in Proceedings of the 4th International Symposium on Wikis (Porto, Portugal: ACM, 2008), 1-14, http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1822258.1822276&amp;coll=ACM&amp;dl=ACM&amp;type=series&amp;idx=SERIES11299&amp;part=series&amp;WantType=Proceedings&amp;title=WikiSym&lt;/ref&gt;

This allows Tiki-based web sites to have translated ''content'' — not just ''interfaces''.

==Implementation==
Tiki is developed primarily in [[PHP]] with some [[JavaScript]] code. It uses [[MySQL]] as a [[database]]. It will run on any server that provides PHP 5, including [[Apache HTTP Server|Apache]] and [[Microsoft]]'s [[Internet Information Services|IIS]].

Tiki components make extensive use of other open source projects, including [[Zend Framework]], [[Smarty]], [[jQuery]], HTML Purifier, [[FCKeditor]], [[Raphaël (JavaScript library)|Raphaël]], phpCAS, and Morcego.&lt;ref&gt;http://tiki.org/partners&lt;/ref&gt; When used with [[Mapserver]] Tiki can become a Geospatial Content Management System.

==Project team==
Tiki is under active development&lt;ref&gt;[http://cia.vc/stats/project/tikiwiki Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware - CIA.vc&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; by a large international community of over 300 developers and translators,&lt;ref&gt;http://sourceforge.net/project/memberlist.php?group_id=64258&lt;/ref&gt; and is one of the largest open-source teams in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohloh.net/projects/tikiwiki/factoids/ This is one of the largest open-source teams in the world, and is in the top 2% of all project teams on Ohloh.]&lt;/ref&gt; Project members have donated the resources and bandwidth required to host the Tiki.org website and various subdomains. The project members refer to this dependence on their own product as &quot;[[Eat one's own dog food|eating their own dogfood]]&quot;, which they have been doing since the early days of the project.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tiki.org/DogFood Tiki DogFood]&lt;/ref&gt; Tiki community members also participate to various related events such as [[WikiSym]] and the [[Libre Software Meeting]].

==History==
Tiki has been hosted on SourceForge.net since its initial release (Release 0.9, named Spica) in October 2002.&lt;ref&gt;http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_name=03d001c27eb8%24e6e4ed00%243800a8c0%40deathstar&amp;forum_name=tikiwiki-devel SourceForge project announcement&lt;/ref&gt; It was primarily the development of Luis Argerich ([[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]]), Eduardo Polidor ([[São Paulo]], [[Brazil]]), and Garland Foster ([[Green Bay, WI]], [[United States]]).

In July 2003, Tiki was named the SourceForge.net July 2003 Project of the Month.&lt;ref&gt;http://sourceforge.net/potm/potm-2003-07.php SourceForge Project of the Month (external link)&lt;/ref&gt; In late 2003, a fork of Tiki was used to create Bitweaver.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bitweaver.org/wiki/bitweaver+and+TikiWiki&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, Tiki was named to CMS Report's Top 30 Web Applications.&lt;ref&gt;http://cmsreport.com/cms-focus-cms-reports-top-30-web-applications CMS Focus&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Tiki was named to EContent magazine's Top 100&lt;ref&gt;http://www.econtentmag.com/Articles/ArticleReader.aspx?ArticleID=40160&amp;IssueId=490&amp;PageNum=4 EcontentMag.com Top 100&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Tiki adopted a six-month release cycle and announced the selection of a Long Term Support (LTS) version and the Tiki Software Community Association was formed as the legal steward for Tiki.&lt;ref&gt;http://tiki.org/Tiki+Software+Community+Association Tiki Software Community Association&lt;/ref&gt; The Tiki Software Association is a not-for-profit entity established in Canada. Previously, the entire project was run entirely by volunteers, loosely organized in a [[do-ocracy]].

In 2010, Tiki received Best of Open Source Software Applications Award (BOSSIE) from InfoWorld, in the Applications category.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.infoworld.com/d/open-source/bossie-awards-2010-the-best-open-source-software-the-year-115 2010 InfoWorld BOSSIE Awards&lt;/ref&gt;

==Derivative software==
*Bitweaver &lt;ref&gt;http://cms.wikia.com/wiki/Impl/Bitweaver&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
The name ''TikiWiki'' is written in [[CamelCase]], a common Wiki syntax indicating a [[hyperlink]] within the Wiki. It is most likely a [[compound word]] combining two [[Polynesia]]n terms, ''[[Tiki culture|Tiki]]'' and ''[[Wiki]]'', to create a self-rhyming name similar to ''wikiwiki'', a common variant of ''wiki''.

Tiki also forms the [[backronym]]: '''T'''ightly '''I'''ntegrated '''K'''nowledge '''I'''nfrastructure.&lt;ref&gt;http://info.tiki.org/Fact+Sheet&lt;/ref&gt;

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Sapir |first=Rick |title=Tiki Essentials |publisher=LuLu.com |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-557-76676-5 }}
* {{cite book |last=Sapir |first=Rick |title=Tiki for Smarties |publisher=LuLu.com |year=2011 |isbn=978-0-557-34575-5 }}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Comparison of wiki software]]
* [[List of content management systems]]
* [[Comparison of office suites]]
* [[List of online spreadsheets]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://tiki.org Tiki.org]
* {{SourceForge|tikiwiki|TikiWiki}}
* [http://www.ohloh.net/p/tikiwiki Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware on Ohloh]
* [http://info.tiki.org/Get+Tiki#Tiki_Demo:_Try_Before_You_Install Tiki] Demo
* [http://twbasics.keycontent.org Tiki for &lt;s&gt;Dummies&lt;/s&gt; Smarties: A beginner's guide to using Tiki Wiki CMS Groupware]
* [http://twessentials.keycontent.org Tiki Essentials]

{{Wiki software}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tikiwiki}}
[[Category:Free wiki software]]
[[Category:Semantic wiki software]]
[[Category:Open source content management systems]]
[[Category:PHP programming language]]
[[Category:Blikis]]
[[Category:Blog software]]
[[Category:2002 software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:Free groupware]]
[[Category:Internet forums]]
[[Category:Free software programmed in PHP]]
[[Category:Website management]]
[[Category:Free project management software]]
[[Category:Bug and issue tracking software]]
[[Category:Groupware]]
[[Category:Content management systems]]
[[Category:Web applications]]

[[ca:TikiWiki]]
[[de:TikiWiki]]
[[es:TikiWiki]]
[[eu:TikiWiki]]
[[fr:TikiWiki]]
[[it:TikiWiki]]
[[pl:TikiWiki]]
[[pt:TikiWiki]]
[[ru:TikiWiki]]
[[uk:TikiWiki]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
