<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="42172" ns="0" title="Walter Mondale"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox officeholder
|birthname         = Walter Frederick Mondale
|image        = U.S Vice-President Walter Mondale.jpg
|imagesize    = 245px
|office       = [[List of Vice Presidents of the United States|42nd]] [[Vice President of the United States]]
|president    = [[Jimmy Carter]]
|term_start   = January 20, 1977
|term_end     = January 20, 1981
|predecessor  = [[Nelson Rockefeller]]
|successor    = [[George H. W. Bush]]
|jr/sr3       = United States Senator
|state3       = [[Minnesota]]
|term_start3  = December 30, 1964
|term_end3    = December 30, 1976
|predecessor3 = [[Hubert Humphrey]]
|successor3   = [[Wendell Anderson]]
|office4      = 24th [[United States Ambassador to Japan]]
|president4   = [[Bill Clinton]]
|term_start4  = September 21, 1993
|term_end4    = December 15, 1996
|predecessor4 = [[Michael Armacost]]
|successor4   = [[Tom Foley]]
|office5      = 23rd [[List of Minnesota Attorneys General|Attorney General of Minnesota]]
|governor5    = [[Orville Freeman]]&lt;br&gt;[[Elmer L. Andersen|Elmer Andersen]]&lt;br&gt;[[Karl Rolvaag]]
|term_start5  = 1960
|term_end5    = 1964
|predecessor5 = [[Miles W. Lord|Miles Lord]]
|successor5   = [[Robert W. Mattson, Sr.|Robert Mattson]]
|birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1928|1|5}}
|birth_place  = [[Ceylon, Minnesota|Ceylon]], [[Minnesota]], [[United States|U.S.]]
|death_date   =
|death_place  =
|spouse       = [[Joan Mondale|Joan Adams]]
|children     = [[Ted Mondale|Theodore A. Mondale]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eleanor Mondale]] (deceased)&lt;br&gt;William Mondale
|party        = [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]]
|alma_mater   = [[Macalester College]]&lt;br&gt;[[University of Minnesota]]&lt;br/&gt;[[University of Minnesota Law School]]
|religion     = [[Presbyterian]]
|signature    = Walter Mondale Signature.svg
|signature_alt = Cursive signature in ink
|branch       = [[United States Army]]
|serviceyears = 1951–1953
|rank         = [[Corporal]]
|unit         = [[Fort Knox]]
}}
'''Walter Frederick''' &quot;'''Fritz'''&quot; '''Mondale''' (born January 5, 1928) is an [[United States|American]] [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] politician, who served as the [[List of Vice Presidents of the United States|42nd]] [[Vice President of the United States]] (1977–1981), under [[President of the United States|President]] [[Jimmy Carter]], and as a [[United States Senator]] for [[Minnesota]] (1964–1976). He was the Democratic Party's presidential candidate in the [[United States presidential election, 1984|United States presidential election of 1984]].

Mondale was born in [[Ceylon, Minnesota]] and graduated from the [[University of Minnesota]] in 1951. He then served in the US Army in the [[Korean War]] before earning a law degree in 1956. He married [[Joan Mondale|Joan Adams]] in 1955. Working as a lawyer in [[Minneapolis]], Mondale was elected to the position of [[attorney general]] in 1960. He was appointed US Senator in late 1964 as a member of the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] upon the resignation of [[Hubert Humphrey]], and held that post until 1976. In the Senate, he supported [[open housing]], [[tax reform]] and the [[desegregation]] of schools. He opposed United States involvement in the [[Vietnam War]].

In 1976, Carter, the Democratic presidential nominee, chose Mondale as his vice presidential running mate in the forthcoming [[1976 United States presidential election|election]]. The Carter/Mondale ticket defeated incumbent president [[Gerald Ford]]. Carter and Mondale's time in office was marred by a worsening economy, and although both were renominated by the Democratic Party, they lost the [[United States presidential election, 1980|1980 election]] to Republican [[Ronald Reagan]].

In 1984, Mondale won the Democratic presidential nomination and campaigned for a [[nuclear freeze]], the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] and a reduction of [[US public debt]]. In the [[1984 United States presidential election|election]], Mondale was defeated in a landslide by President Reagan, gaining electoral votes from only his home state of Minnesota and the [[District of Columbia]].

After the election, Mondale joined the Minnesota-based law firm of [[Dorsey &amp; Whitney]] and the [[National Democratic Institute for International Affairs]] (1986–93), and was credited with successes in [[Poland]] and [[Hungary]]. President [[Bill Clinton]] appointed Mondale [[United States Ambassador to Japan]] in 1993; he retired in 1996. Since then, Mondale has returned to working at Dorsey &amp; Whitney and remains active in the Democratic Party.

==Early life==
Walter Frederick Mondale was born in [[Ceylon, Minnesota|Ceylon]], [[Minnesota]], the son of Claribel Hope (née Cowan), a part-time music teacher, and Theodore Sigvaard Mondale, a [[Methodist]] minister.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://millercenter.org/academic/americanpresident/carter/essays/vicepresident/1829 |title=American President: Walter Mondale |publisher=Millercenter.org |date= |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Encyclop&amp;aelig;dia Britannica |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/389066/Walter-Mondale |title=Walter Mondale|accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/generic/VP_Walter_Mondale.htm |title=Walter F. Mondale, 42nd Vice President (1977–1981) |publisher=U.S. Senate|date= |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father's family was [[Norwegian American]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/carter/peopleevents/p_mondale.html |title=Jimmy Carter|work=American Experience|publisher=PBS |date= |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The family name comes from Mundal by [[Fjærland]] in the [[Sogndal]] Commune of [[Norway]]. He attended public schools. His half-brother [[Lester Mondale]] was a [[American Unitarian Association|Unitarian]] minister.

Mondale was educated at [[Macalester College]] in [[St. Paul, Minnesota|St. Paul]] and the [[University of Minnesota]], where he earned his B.A. in [[Political Science]], graduating in 1951.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mondale, Walter Frederick, (1928 – )|url=http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=m000851|work=[[Biographical Directory of the United States Congress]]|accessdate=August 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He did not have enough money to attend law school. He enlisted in the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] and served for two years at [[Fort Knox]] during the [[Korean War]], reaching the rank of corporal. Through the support of the [[G.I. Bill]], he was able to attend law school, and graduated from the [[University of Minnesota Law School]] in 1956. While at law school he served on the [[Minnesota Law Review]] and as a law clerk in the [[Minnesota Supreme Court]] under Justice [[Thomas F. Gallagher]]. He began practicing law in [[Minneapolis, Minnesota|Minneapolis]], and continued to do so for four years before entering the political arena.&lt;ref&gt;Gillon, ''The Democrats’ Dilemma: Walter F. Mondale and the Liberal Legacy'' (1992)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Entry into politics==
Mondale became involved in national politics in the 1940s. At the age of 20, he was visible in Minnesota politics by helping organize [[Hubert Humphrey]]'s successful [[United States Senate|Senate]] campaign in [[U.S. Senate election, 1948|1948]]. Minnesota Governor [[Orville Freeman]] appointed Mondale in the race for Minnesota Attorney General in 1960, filling the vacancy left by [[Miles Lord]], who was appointed to be [[United States District Court for the District of Minnesota|U.S. Attorney for the District of Minnesota]] by President [[John F. Kennedy]]. Mondale had just managed Freeman's successful gubernatorial campaign. Mondale was 32, and four years out of law school when he became attorney general of Minnesota. During his tenure as Minnesota Attorney General, the case [[Gideon v. Wainwright]] (which ultimately established the right of defendants in state courts to have a lawyer) was being heard by the U.S. Supreme Court. When those saying that a lawyer wasn't required organized a Friend of the Court brief from some state Attorneys General for that position, Mondale organized a countering Friend of the Court brief from many more state Attorneys General, arguing that defendants must be allowed a lawyer. He served for two terms as attorney general.
He also served as a member of the President’s Consumer Advisory Council from 1960 to 1964.  At the 1964 Democratic National Convention, Mondale played a major role in the proposed but ultimately unsuccessful compromise by which the national Democratic Party offered the [[Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party]] two at-large seats.

==U.S. Senator==
{{Missing information non-contentious|Mondale's stance on housing, tax reform, school desegregation and the Viet Nam War|date=March 2011}}
[[File:Mondale as Senator.jpg|thumb|left|Senator Walter F. Mondale]]
On December 30, 1964, Mondale was appointed by [[Governor of Minnesota|Minnesota Governor]] [[Karl Rolvaag]] to the [[United States Senate]] to fill the vacancy caused by [[Hubert Humphrey]]'s resignation after being elected [[Vice President of the United States]]. In [[United States Senate elections, 1966|1966]], Mondale defeated [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] candidate Robert A. Forsythe, 53.9% to 45.2%. In 1972, [[George McGovern]] offered him an opportunity to be his running mate, which Mondale declined.{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}  The voters of Minnesota returned Mondale to the Senate again in [[United States Senate elections, 1972|1972]] with over 57% of the vote. He served in the [[88th United States Congress|88th]], [[89th United States Congress|89th]], [[90th United States Congress|90th]], [[91st United States Congress|91st]], [[92nd United States Congress|92nd]], [[93rd United States Congress|93rd]], and [[94th United States Congress|94th congresses]].

During his years as a senator, Mondale served on the [[United States Senate Committee on Aeronautical and Space Sciences|Aeronautical and Space Sciences Committee]]; the [[United States Senate Committee on Finance|Finance Committee]]; the [[United States Senate Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions|Labor and Public Welfare Committee]]; the [[United States Senate Committee on the Budget|Budget Committee]]; and the [[United States Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs|Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee]]. He also served as chairman of the [[United States Senate Select Committee on Equal Education Opportunity|Select Committee on Equal Education Opportunity]] and as chairman of the [[United States Senate Select Committee on Intelligence|Intelligence Committee]]'s Domestic Task Force. He additionally served as chairman of the Labor and Public Welfare Committee's subcommittee on Children and Youth, as well as chairman of the Senate subcommittee on social security financing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=The Nation: The Straightest Arrow|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,914370,00.html|date=July 26, 1976|work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|format=subscription required|accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}
===Apollo 204 accident===
{{Main|Apollo 1}}
In 1967, Mondale served on the Aeronautical and Space Sciences Committee, then chaired by [[Clinton P. Anderson]], when [[astronauts]] [[Gus Grissom|Virgil &quot;Gus&quot; Grissom]], [[Edward Higgins White|Edward H. White]], and [[Roger Chaffee]] were killed in a fire on January 27 while testing the [[Apollo 1|Apollo 204]] spacecraft. [[NASA]] Administrator [[James E. Webb]] secured the approval of President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] for NASA to internally investigate the cause of the accident according to its established procedures, subject to Congressional oversight. NASA's procedure called for the Deputy Administrator (and de facto general manager), Dr. [[Robert C. Seamans]], to appoint and oversee an investigative panel.

In February, a reporter passed a leak to Mondale, of the existence of an internal NASA report issued in 1965 by Apollo program director [[Samuel C. Phillips]], detailing management, cost, delivery and quality problems of the Apollo prime contractor [[North American Aviation]]. In the February 27 hearing, Mondale asked Webb if he knew of such a report. Webb had not yet seen the December 1965 written report, so he responded in the negative. Seamans had passed along to Webb, neither the written report, nor the briefing presentation made to him in January 1966 by Phillips and Phillips' boss, Manned Space Flight Administrator [[George Mueller]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wamu&quot;&gt;
{{Cite episode
 | title = Washington Goes to the Moon (Part 2)
 | episodelink = 
 | url = http://mail.dve.wamu.org/programs/special/01/washington_goes_to_the_moon.php
 | accessdate = March 15, 2011
 | series = Soundprint
 | serieslink = 
 | credits = 
 | network = NPR
 | station = WAMU 88.5 FM
 | city = Washington D.C.
 | airdate = May 24, 2001
 | began = 
 | ended = 
 | season = 
 | seriesno = 
 | number = 
 | minutes = 
 | time = 
 | transcript = yes
 | transcripturl = http://mail.dve.wamu.org/d/programs/special/moon/fire_show.txt
 | quote = 
 | language = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Both Seamans and Mueller had also been called to testify at this session. Mueller denied the report's existence, even though he must have been well aware of it, as he had appended his own strongly-worded letter to the copy sent to North American president [[Lee Atwood]].&lt;ref name=&quot;phillips_report&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Garber
  | first = Steve
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = NASA Apollo Mission Apollo-1 -- Phillips Report
  | work =
  | publisher = NASA History Office
  | date = February 3, 2003
  | url = http://history.nasa.gov/Apollo204/phillip1.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate = April 14, 2010 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

But Seamans was afraid Mondale might somehow be in possession of a copy (which he was not), so he admitted that NASA often reviewed its contractors' performance, with both positive and negative results, but that this was nothing extraordinary. Under repeated questioning from Mondale, Webb promised that he would investigate whether this &quot;Phillips Report&quot; existed, and if so, to see if a controlled release could be made to the Congress. Immediately after the hearing, Webb saw the Phillips report for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;wamu&quot;/&gt; 

The controversy spread to both houses of Congress, and grew (through the efforts of three of Mondale's fellow committee members, [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]s [[Margaret Chase Smith]], [[Edward Brooke]] and [[Charles H. Percy]]) to include the second-guessing of NASA's original selection in 1961 of North American as the prime Apollo spacecraft contractor, which Webb became forced to defend. The [[U.S. House of Representatives|House]] NASA oversight committee, which was conducting its own hearings and had picked up on the controversy, was ultimately given a copy of the Phillips report.

While the Committee as a whole, believed that NASA should have informed Congress of the Phillips review results in 1966, its final report issued on January 30, 1968, concluded (as had NASA's own accident investigation completed on April 5, 1967), that &quot;the findings of the [Phillips] task force had no effect on the accident, did not lead to the accident, and were not related to the accident.&quot; Yet Mondale wrote a minority opinion accusing NASA of &quot;evasiveness, ... lack of candor, ... patronizing attitude exhibited toward Congress, ... refusal to respond fully and forthrightly to legitimate congressional inquiries, and ... solicitous concern for corporate sensitivities at a time of national tragedy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;as204_senate&quot;&gt;
 {{Cite journal
  | last = Anderson
  | first = Clinton P.
  | authorlink = Clinton P. Anderson
  | coauthors = Edward M. Brooke; Charles H. Percy; Walter F. Mondale
  | title = Apollo 204 Accident
  | journal = Senate Report
  | volume = No. 956
  | issue = 
  | pages = 
  | publisher = U.S. Senate
  | location = Washington, D.C.
  | date = January 30, 1968
  | url = http://klabs.org/richcontent/Reports/Failure_Reports/as-204/senate_956/index.htm
  | issn = 
  | doi = 
  | id = 
  | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mondale explained his actions in a 2001 interview: &quot;... I think that by forcing a public confrontation about these heretofore secret and deep concerns about the safety and the management of the program, it forced NASA to restructure and reorganize the program in a way that was much safer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wamu&quot;/&gt;

===Church intelligence committee===
{{Expand section|date=March 2011}}
In 1975 Mondale served on [[Frank Church|Frank Church's]] [[Church Committee|Committee to Study Governmental Operations with Respect to Intelligence Activities]], which investigated alleged abuses by the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] and the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]].

==Vice Presidency==
{{See|Presidency of Jimmy Carter}}
[[File:Mondale and Carter.JPG|thumb|Walter Mondale and Jimmy Carter, in front of Presidential helicopter [[Marine One]] in January 1979]]
When [[Jimmy Carter]] won the Democratic nomination for [[president of the United States|president]] in [[U.S. presidential election, 1976|1976]], he chose Mondale as his running mate. The ticket was narrowly elected on November 2, 1976, and Mondale was inaugurated as [[Vice President of the United States]] on January 20, 1977. He became the fourth vice president in eight years, the other three being: [[Spiro Agnew]] (1969-73), [[Gerald Ford]] (1973-1974), and [[Nelson Rockefeller]] (1974-77).

Under Carter, Mondale traveled extensively throughout the nation and the world advocating the administration's foreign policy. Mondale was the first vice president to have an office in the White House, and established the concept of &quot;activist Vice President&quot;. Mondale established the tradition of weekly lunches with the president, which continues to this day.  More important, he expanded the vice president's role from that of figurehead to presidential advisor, full-time participant, and troubleshooter for the administration.  Subsequent vice presidents have followed this model in the administrations in which they serve.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Kengor, ''Wreath layer or policy player: the vice president's role in foreign policy'' (2000) p 85&lt;/ref&gt;
===1980 Election===
{{See|U.S. presidential election, 1976 |U.S. presidential election, 1980}}
Carter and Mondale were renominated at the [[1980 Democratic National Convention]], but soundly lost to the Republican ticket of [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[George H. W. Bush]]. That year, Mondale opened the [[XIII Olympic Winter Games]] in [[Lake Placid, New York]].

Carter and Walter Mondale are the longest-living post-presidential team in American history. On December 11, 2007, they had been out of office for 26 years and 325 days, surpassing the former record established by President [[John Adams]] and Vice President [[Thomas Jefferson]], who both died on July 4, 1826.

==Post Vice-Presidency==
===Presidential nominee of 1984===
[[File:WalterFMondaleBust.jpg|thumb|left|Vice President Mondale bust from the Senate collection]]
{{Main|United States presidential election, 1984}}
After losing the 1980 election, Mondale returned briefly to the practice of law at [[Winston and Strawn]], a large Chicago-based law firm, but he had no intention of staying out of politics for long.

Mondale ran for the Democratic presidential nomination in the [[U.S. presidential election, 1984|1984 election]], and from the early going, he was the frontrunner. His opposition included Rev. [[Jesse Jackson]] and Senator [[Gary Hart]] of [[Colorado]]. Hart pulled an upset by winning the New Hampshire primary in March, but Mondale had a large portion of the party leadership behind him. To great effect, Mondale used the [[Wendy's]] slogan &quot;[[Where's the beef?]]&quot; to describe Hart's policies as lacking depth. Jackson, widely regarded as the first serious African-American candidate for President, held on longer, but Mondale clinched the nomination with the majority of delegates on the first ballot.

At the Democratic Convention, Mondale chose [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. Representative]] [[Geraldine Ferraro|Geraldine A. Ferraro]] of [[New York]] as his running mate, making her the first woman nominated for that position by a major party. Aides later said that Mondale was determined to establish a precedent with his vice presidential candidate, considering San Francisco Mayor [[Dianne Feinstein]], also a female, Los Angeles Mayor [[Tom Bradley (politician)|Tom Bradley]], an African American, and [[San Antonio]] Mayor [[Henry Cisneros]], a Mexican American, as other finalists for the nomination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,926644,00.html Trying to Win the Peace], by Even Thomas, [[TIME Magazine]]&lt;/ref&gt; Others preferred Senator [[Lloyd Bentsen]] because he would appeal to the Deep South, or even nomination rival [[Gary Hart]]. Ferraro, as a Catholic, came under fire from some Catholic Church leaders for being [[pro-choice]]. Much more controversy erupted over her changing positions regarding the release of her husband's tax returns, and her own ethics record in the House. Ferraro was on the defensive throughout the campaign, largely negating her breakthrough as the first woman on a major national ticket, and the first [[Italian American]] to reach that level in American politics.

When he made his acceptance speech at the Democratic Convention, Mondale said: &quot;By the end of my first term, I will reduce the Reagan budget deficit by two-thirds. Let's tell the truth. It must be done, it must be done. Mr. Reagan will raise taxes, and so will I. He won't tell you. I just did.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/ALLPOLITICS/1996/conventions/chicago/facts/famous.speeches/mondale.84.shtml Mondale's Acceptance Speech, 1984], AllPolitics&lt;/ref&gt; While this was meant to show that Mondale would be honest with voters, it was largely interpreted as a campaign pledge to raise taxes, which was unappealing to many voters.

Mondale ran a [[modern liberalism in the United States|liberal]] campaign, supporting a [[nuclear freeze]] and the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] (ERA). He spoke against [[Reaganomics|Reagan's economic policies]] and in support of reducing federal [[budget deficit]]s. However, he was going up against a popular incumbent and his campaign was widely considered ineffective. Also, he was perceived as supporting the poor at the expense of the middle class. Southern whites and northern blue collar workers who [[Reagan Democrat|usually voted Democratic]] switched their support to Reagan because they credited him with the economic boom and saw him as strong on [[national security]] issues.

In the first televised debate, Mondale performed unexpectedly well, questioning Reagan's age and capacity to endure the grueling demands of the presidency (Reagan was the oldest person to serve as president—73 at the time—while Mondale was 56). In the next debate on October 21, 1984, Reagan deflected the issue by quipping, &quot;I will not make age an issue of this campaign. I am not going to exploit, for political purposes, my opponent's youth and inexperience.&quot;

In the election, Mondale was defeated in a landslide, winning only [[Washington, D.C.|the District of Columbia]] and his home state of [[Minnesota]] and even there his margin of victory was fewer than 3,800 votes,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20010711205902/http://h0040055bf148.ne.mediaone.net/~dave/POL/PE1984/pedata1984MN.html 1984 Presidential Election Data—Minnesota]&lt;/ref&gt; securing only 13 electoral votes to Reagan's 525. The result was the worst electoral college defeat for any Democratic Party candidate in history, and the worst for any major-party candidate since [[Alf Landon]]'s loss to [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] in [[U.S. presidential election, 1936|1936]].

Mondale received 37,577,352 votes—a total of 40.6% of the popular vote in the election. Mondale received 40-49% in California, Hawaii, Illinois, Iowa, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, Missouri, New York, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, Tennessee, Vermont, Washington, West Virginia, and Wisconsin.

===Private citizen and ambassador===
[[File:Waltermondaleasdiplomat.jpg|thumb|Walter Mondale as U.S. Ambassador to Japan]]
Following the election, Mondale returned to private law practice, with [[Dorsey &amp; Whitney]] in Minnesota in 1987. From 1986 to 1993, Mondale was chairman of the [[National Democratic Institute for International Affairs]]. During the presidency of [[Bill Clinton]], he was [[U.S. Ambassador to Japan]] from 1993 to 1996, chaired a bipartisan group to study [[campaign finance reform]], and was Clinton's special envoy to [[Indonesia]] in 1998.

Until his appointment as U.S. Ambassador to Japan, Mondale was a Distinguished University Fellow in Law and Public Affairs at the [[Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs]], at the [[University of Minnesota]]. In 1990, Mondale established the Mondale Policy Forum at the Humphrey Institute. The forum has brought together leading scholars and policymakers for annual conferences on domestic and international issues. He also served on nonprofit boards of directors for the [[Guthrie Theatre]] Foundation, [[Mayo Clinic|Mayo Foundation]], National Democratic Institute for International Affairs, Diogenes Institute of Higher Learning, Prince Hall Masonic Temple, RAND Corporation and the University of Minnesota Foundation. His corporate board memberships included BlackRock Advantage Term Trust and other BlackRock Mutual Funds, Cargill Incorporated, CNA Financial Corporation, the Encyclopædia Britannica, First Financial Fund and other Prudential Mutual Funds, [[Northwest Airlines]] and United HealthCare Corporation.

Mondale spoke before the Senate on September 4, 2002, when he delivered a lecture on his service, with commentary on the transformation of the office of the Vice President during the Carter administration, the Senate [[cloture]] rule for ending debate, and his view on the future of the Senate in U.S. political history. The lecture was a part of a continuing Senate &quot;Leaders Lecture Series&quot; that ran from 1998 to 2002.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/generic/Leaders_Lecture_Series_Mondale.htm Address by Vice President Walter Mondale, September 4, 2002 in the United States Senate] &lt;br/&gt; [http://www.senate.gov/pagelayout/history/f_two_sections_with_teasers/leader_lecture_series.htm Leader's Lecture Series Speakers]
&lt;/ref&gt;

===2002 Senate election and beyond===
[[File:Mondale speech.jpg|thumb|left|Former Vice President Mondale giving a lecture in the Senate in 2002]]
{{Main|United States Senate elections, 2002|United States Senate election in Minnesota, 2002}}
In 2002, Democratic US Senator [[Paul Wellstone]] of Minnesota, who was running for re-election, died in a [[plane crash]] just 11 days before the November 5 election. At the age of 74, Mondale replaced Wellstone on the ballot, at the urging of Wellstone's relatives. This Senate seat was the one that Mondale himself had held, before resigning to become Vice President in 1977.

During his debate with the Republican nominee, former [[St. Paul, Minnesota|St. Paul]] Mayor [[Norm Coleman]], Mondale emphasized his own experience in foreign affairs while painting Coleman as a finger-in-the-wind opportunist. &quot;We've seen you shift around, Norman,&quot; Mondale said, alluding to Coleman's past as an anti-war college activist and, more recently, as a Democrat who had changed his party allegiance to the GOP while serving as mayor of St. Paul.

In a major upset, Mondale narrowly lost the election, finishing with 1,067,246 votes (47.34%) to Coleman's 1,116,697 (49.53%) out of 2,254,639 votes cast, earning him the unique distinction of having lost a statewide election in all 50 states as the nominee of a major party (he lost the other 49 in the 1984 Presidential Election).

The election was also marked by the controversy surrounding Wellstone's memorial event, which many critics, including then Minnesota Governor [[Jesse Ventura]] ([[Independence Party of Minnesota|IM]]), [[Jesse Ventura#Wellstone memorial|considered]] to have been overly partisan.

Upon conceding defeat, Mondale stated: &quot;At the end of what will be my last campaign, I want to say to Minnesota, you always treated me well, you always listened to me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,69286,00.html ''Mondale Concedes to Coleman''], [[Fox News Channel]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004 Mondale became co-chairman of the [[Constitution Project]]'s bipartisan Right to Counsel Committee.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.constitutionproject.org/righttocounsel/article.cfm?messageID=73&amp;categoryId=6 ]{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He endorsed Senator [[Hillary Clinton]] (D-[[New York|NY]]) for the Presidency of the United States and supported her [[Hillary Rodham Clinton presidential campaign, 2008|campaign for the White House in 2008]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillaryclinton.com/news/release/view/?id=4039 ]{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 3, 2008, following the final primary contests, Mondale switched his endorsement to Senator [[Barack Obama]] (D-[[Illinois|Ill.]]), who had clinched the nomination the previous evening.

Following the U.S. Presidential election of 2004 and the mid-term elections of 2006, Mondale is seen talking with [[Al Franken]] about the possibility of the latter running for [[Norm Coleman]]'s U.S. Senate seat in 2008 in the documentary ''[[Al Franken: God Spoke]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Al Franken: God Spoke at the Internet Movie Database&lt;/ref&gt; In the film, Mondale encourages Franken to run, but cautions him, saying that Coleman's allies and the Republican Party were going to look for anything they could use against him. Franken ultimately ran and won the [[United States Senate election in Minnesota, 2008|2008 Senate election]] by 312 votes after the election results had been contested in court by Coleman until June 30, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.startribune.com/politics/national/senate/42221767.html ''Senate recount trial: Judges' ruling is boon to Franken''], [[Minneapolis Star Tribune]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family==
[[File:WalterMondale.jpg|thumb|Mondale in 2010]]
His wife, [[Joan Mondale]], is a national advocate for the arts and was the Honorary Chairman of the Federal Council on the Arts and Humanities during the Carter Administration.

The Mondales' eldest son, [[Ted Mondale|Theodore A. &quot;Ted&quot; Mondale]], is an entrepreneur and the CEO of Nazca Solutions, a technology fulfillment venture. He is also a former Minnesota state senator. In 1998, Mondale sought the Democratic primary nomination for Minnesota governor. Mondale, a fiscal moderate who had distanced himself from labor, lost in the primary.

The Mondales' daughter, [[Eleanor Mondale|Eleanor]], was a television personality. She also had radio talk shows in [[Chicago]], and a long running program on [[WCCO (AM)]] in [[Minneapolis]]. She died of brain cancer at her home in Minnesota on September 17, 2011, at the age of 51.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/chi-mondale-kennedy-obits-story,0,3709527.story |title=Kara Kennedy, Eleanor Mondale dead at 51 |publisher=chicagotribune.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Walter Mondale continues to maintain a residence near [[Lake of the Isles]] in Minneapolis. Mondale is a [[Presbyterian]]. He enjoys fishing, reading [[Shakespeare]] and historical accounts, barbecuing, skiing, watching [[Monty Python]], and playing tennis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mnc.net/norway/Mondale.htm Biography of Walter F. Mondale]&lt;/ref&gt;

Mondale has maintained strong ties to the [[University of Minnesota Law School]], which named its new residence on the West Bank of the Mississippi &quot;Mondale Hall&quot;.  He contributes cameo appearances to the Law School's annual T.O.R.T. (&quot;Theater of the Relatively Talentless&quot;) presentations, and has allowed his name to be used as the nickname of the school's hockey team: &quot;The Fighting Mondales.&quot;

==In popular culture==
*[[Bill Murray]] and [[Garrett Morris]] played Mondale on ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' in the late 1970s, as did [[Dana Carvey]] in the mid-1980s.
*In ''[[Futurama]]'' Season 1 Episode 11 (&quot;[[Mars University]]&quot;), [[Amy Wong]] mentions him when she says, &quot;Boring! Let's hear about Walter Mondale already.&quot; This remark was made to a professor who was drawn to look like Mondale. In Season 2 Episode 7 (&quot;[[A Head In The Polls]]&quot;), Walter Mondale' Head is in the &quot;Closet Of Presidential Losers&quot; within the Head Museum.
*One of his ads for his presidential campaign was featured on ''[[The Daily Show]]'' on March 3, 2008 as a satirical comparison to one of Hillary Clinton's campaign ads.
*In the ''[[Simpsons]]'' episode &quot;[[Lisa's First Word]]&quot;, [[Homer Simpson]] reads a headline that describes Mondale's &quot;Where's the beef?&quot; comment during the [[United States presidential election, 1984|1984 Presidential Election]].  Homer laughs approvingly and remarks &quot;No wonder he won Minnesota!&quot; In the episode &quot;[[Mr. Spritz Goes to Washington]]&quot;, a janitor who &quot;looks like&quot; Walter Mondale helps newly elected Congressman [[Krusty the Clown]] get a bill to become law using underhanded methods.mIn &quot;[[Bart vs. Australia]]&quot;, the family flees from Australia to a &quot;laundry ship&quot; named ''USS Walter Mondale''.
*In the ''[[American Dad]]'' episode, &quot;[[Stan Knows Best]]&quot;, [[Stan Smith (American Dad!)|Stan Smith]] says &quot;Rubharb&quot; when [[Hayley Smith (American Dad!)|Hayley]] moves in with her boyfriend, Jeff. He claimed the word was a subliminal order he supposedly implanted into her subconscious to kill Walter Mondale. However, it is revealed that the word was implanted into [[Steve Smith (American Dad!)|Steve]]'s mind. In &quot;[[The Best Christmas Story Never]]&quot;, Stan goes back in time and alters the past, where Walter Mondale becomes the President instead of Ronald Reagan, and quickly hands over the US to the [[Soviet Union]].
*In an episode of ''[[The O.C.]]'', &quot;[[The Case of the Franks]]&quot;, [[Sandy Cohen]], in a flashback, is campaigning for the Mondale campaign. He attempts to give future wife [[Kirsten Cohen|Kirsten]] a campaign button and states that he would tell her why Mondale and Ferraro wouldn't win, but campaigning for them felt right.
*In the [[HBO]] Miniseries ''[[From the Earth to the Moon (TV miniseries)|From the Earth to the Moon]]'', Mondale is portrayed by actor [[John Slattery]]

==Published works==
''The Good Fight: A Life in Liberal Politics'', Mondale's memoir, was published in 2010; ''Twelve Years and Thirteen Days: Remembering Paul and Sheila Wellstone'', co-written with Terry Gydesen, was published in 2003; ''Crisis and Opportunity in a Changing Japan'', co-written with William Regis Farrell, was published in 1999; and ''The Accountability of Power: Toward a Responsible Presidency,'' was written in 1976.

==Norwegian ancestry==
Mondale has always maintained strong ties to his ancestral [[Norway]]. His family surname was originally '''Mundal''' and it originated in Mundal, [[Fjærland]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bre.museum.no/Default.aspx?tabid=1503 Information Fjærland] website&lt;/ref&gt; Upon entering the Senate in 1964 he took over the seat of vice president [[Hubert Humphrey]], another [[Norwegian-American]]. In later years Mondale has served on the executive committee of the Peace Prize Forum, an annual conference co-sponsored by the [[Norwegian Nobel Institute]] and five Midwestern colleges of Norwegian heritage. During Norway's Centennial Celebration in 2005, he chaired the committee to promote and develop cultural activities between Norway and Norwegian-American organizations.

While he was in office, [[Twin Cities Public Television]] produced a [[documentary film|documentary]] about him entitled ''Walter Mondale: There's a [[Fjord]] in Your Past,'' a play on the well-known advertising slogan, &quot;There's a [[Ford Motor Company|Ford]] in Your Future.&quot;

On December 5, 2007, Norwegian minister of foreign affairs [[Jonas Gahr Støre]] announced that Walter Mondale would be named Honorary Consul-General of Norway, representing the Norwegian state in Minnesota.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.regjeringen.no/en/dep/ud/Press-Contacts/News/2007/mondale_gc.html?id=493351 Walter Mondale to be new Consul General in Minneapolis], press release from the [[Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Electoral history==
{{Main|Electoral history of Walter Mondale}}

==Records==
In the Walter F. Mondale Papers at the Minnesota Historical Society, digital content is available for researcher use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mnhs.org/library/findaids/00697.xml Finding Aid: Walter F. Mondale Papers]&lt;/ref&gt;  Researchers will find content that includes, but is not limited to: speech files, handwritten notes, memoranda, annotated briefings, schedules, correspondence, and visual materials. 
The entire Walter F. Mondale collection includes senatorial, vice presidential, ambassadorial, political papers and campaign files, and personal papers of the United States Senator from Minnesota (1964–1976), Vice President of the United States (1977–1981), Ambassador to Japan (1993–1996), and Special Envoy to Indonesia (1998), documenting most aspects of Mondale's six-decade career, including all of his public offices, campaigns, and Democratic Party and other non-official activities.
Digital selections from this manuscript collection were made based on user and researcher interest, historic significance, and copyright status.

This project was made possible with the generous help of the National Endowment for the Humanities We the People grant.

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==Further reading==
* Gillon, Steven M. ''The Democrats’ Dilemma: Walter F. Mondale and the Liberal Legacy'' (1992)
* Mondale, Walter. ''The Accountability of Power''  (1975)
* Mondale, Walter. ''The Good Fight: A Life in Liberal Politics'' (2010).

==External links==
*[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=M000851 Congressional biography]
*[http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/common/generic/Leaders_Lecture_Series_Mondale.htm Senate Leaders Lecture Series Address]
*[http://news.minnesota.publicradio.org/features/200211/04_zdechlikm_sendebate/ Minnesota Public Radio: Coleman, Mondale debate on eve of election (November 4, 2002)] – featuring audio of the 2002 debate
*[http://www.hhh.umn.edu/news/mondale/ Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs: The Mondale Lectures on Public Service]
*[http://www.mnc.net/norway/Mondale.htm Great Norwegians]
*[http://www.prospect.org/web/printfriendly-view.ww?id=5159#views Two Views from Pennsylvania Avenue]
*[http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/people/m/walter_f_mondale/index.html?offset=20&amp; List of New York Times articles on Mondale]
*[http://history.nasa.gov/SP-4221/ch4.htm Senator Mondale transfers money from NASA to social programs using political maneuvers]
*[http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/magazine/ah/1992/7/1992_7_60.shtml AmericanHeritage.com / Lost in Space What Went Wrong with NASA?]
*[http://www.mnhs.org/library/findaids/00697.xml Walter F. Mondale: An Inventory of His Papers, including his Vice Presidential Papers, at the Minnesota Historical Society]

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Nelson Rockefeller]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Vice President of the United States]]|years=January 20, 1977 – January 20, 1981}}
{{S-aft|after=[[George H. W. Bush]]}}
{{s-legal}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Miles Lord]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Minnesota Attorney General]]|years=1960–1964}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Robert W. Mattson, Sr.]]}}
{{S-par|us-sen}}
{{U.S. Senator box |state=Minnesota |class=2 |before=[[Hubert Humphrey]] |after=[[Wendell Anderson]] |alongside=[[Eugene McCarthy]], [[Hubert Humphrey]] |years=December 30, 1964 – December 30, 1976 }}
{{S-ppo}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Paul Wellstone]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(deceased)&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Minnesota Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party|Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party]] nominee&lt;br/&gt; for [[List of United States Senators from Minnesota|United States Senator from Minnesota]] (Class 2)|years=[[United States Senate election in Minnesota, 2002|2002]]}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Al Franken]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Jimmy Carter]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[List of United States Democratic Party presidential tickets|Democratic Party presidential candidate]]|years=[[U.S. presidential election, 1984|1984]]}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Michael Dukakis]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Thomas Eagleton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Sargent Shriver]]&lt;sup&gt;(1)&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[List of United States Democratic Party presidential tickets|Democratic Party vice presidential candidate]]|years=[[U.S. presidential election, 1976|1976]], [[U.S. presidential election, 1980|1980]]}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Geraldine Ferraro]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Hubert Humphrey]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Minnesota Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party|Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party]] nominee&lt;br/&gt; for [[List of United States Senators from Minnesota|United States Senator from Minnesota]] (Class 2)|years=[[United States Senate elections, 1966|1966]], [[United States Senate elections, 1972|1972]]}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Wendell Anderson]]}}
{{S-dip}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Michael Armacost]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[List of United States ambassadors to Japan|United States Ambassador to Japan]]|years=1993–1996}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Tom Foley]]}}
{{S-prec|usa}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Neil Abercrombie]]'''&lt;br/&gt;''Governor of Hawaii''}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[United States order of precedence]]'''&lt;br/&gt;''Former Vice President of the United States''|years=}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Dan Quayle]]'''&lt;br/&gt;''Former Vice President of the United States''}}
{{s-ref|Thomas Eagleton was the original Vice Presidential nominee in 1972. He withdrew from the race and was replaced by Sargent Shriver.}}
{{end}}

{{USVicePresidents}}
{{USDemPresNominees}}
{{USSenMN}}
{{MinnesotaAttorneysGeneral}}
{{United States presidential election, 1976}}
{{United States presidential election, 1980}}
{{United States presidential election, 1984}}
{{Carter cabinet}}

{{Persondata
|NAME= Mondale, Walter
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Mondale, Walter Frederick &quot;Fritz&quot;
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= forty-second [[Vice President of the United States]] (1977–1981)
|DATE OF BIRTH=January 5, 1928
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Ceylon, Minnesota]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mondale, Walter}}
[[Category:1928 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American people of Norwegian descent]]
[[Category:American Presbyterians]]
[[Category:Appointed United States Senators]]
[[Category:Carter administration personnel]]
[[Category:Clinton Administration personnel]]
[[Category:Democratic Party United States Senators]]
[[Category:Democratic Party Vice Presidents of the United States]]
[[Category:Democratic Party (United States) presidential nominees]]
[[Category:Macalester College alumni]]
[[Category:Minnesota Attorneys General]]
[[Category:Minnesota Democrats]]
[[Category:People from Martin County, Minnesota]]
[[Category:People from Minneapolis, Minnesota]]
[[Category:United States Senators from Minnesota]]
[[Category:Ambassadors of the United States to Japan]]
[[Category:United States presidential candidates, 1980]]
[[Category:United States presidential candidates, 1984]]
[[Category:United States vice-presidential candidates, 1976]]
[[Category:United States vice-presidential candidates, 1980]]
[[Category:University of Minnesota Law School alumni]]

[[ca:Walter Mondale]]
[[cs:Walter Mondale]]
[[da:Walter Mondale]]
[[de:Walter Mondale]]
[[dv:Walter Mondale]]
[[et:Walter Mondale]]
[[es:Walter Mondale]]
[[fr:Walter Mondale]]
[[ko:월터 먼데일]]
[[id:Walter Mondale]]
[[it:Walter Mondale]]
[[he:וולטר מונדייל]]
[[ka:უოლტერ მონდეილი]]
[[la:Gualterius Mondale]]
[[lt:Walter Mondale]]
[[nl:Walter Mondale]]
[[ja:ウォルター・モンデール]]
[[no:Walter Mondale]]
[[pl:Walter Mondale]]
[[pt:Walter Mondale]]
[[ru:Мондейл, Уолтер]]
[[simple:Walter Mondale]]
[[fi:Walter Mondale]]
[[sv:Walter Mondale]]
[[tr:Walter Mondale]]
[[war:Walter Mondale]]
[[yo:Walter Mondale]]
[[zh:沃尔特·蒙代尔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
