<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="422752" ns="0" title="CA Technologies"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{ad|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox company
| company_name     = CA Technologies
| company_logo     = [[Image:CA Technologies brand.svg‎|200px]]
| company_type     = Public company
| traded_as        = {{nasdaq|CA}}&lt;br&gt;[[NASDAQ-100|NASDAQ-100 Component]]
| foundation       = 1976
| founder          = [[Charles Wang]]&lt;br&gt;[[Russell Artzt|Russ Artzt]]
| location         = [[Islandia, New York|Islandia]], New York, U.S.
| key_people       = Arthur F. Weinbach &lt;small&gt;(Chairman)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;William McCracken &lt;small&gt;(CEO)&lt;/small&gt;
| industry         = [[Enterprise software]]&lt;br&gt;[[IT services]]
| products         = Computer software
| revenue          = {{increase}} US$ 5.082 billion &lt;small&gt;(FY 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/356028/000095012310049691/y83785e10vk.htm|title=2010 Form 10-K, CA Technologies|publisher=United States Securities and Exchange Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operating_income = {{increase}} US$ 1.57 billion &lt;small&gt;(FY 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| net_income       = {{increase}} US$ 870 million &lt;small&gt;(FY 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| assets           = {{nowrap|{{increase}} US$ 12.838 billion &lt;small&gt;(FY 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;}}
| equity           = {{increase}} US$ 5.312 billion &lt;small&gt;(FY 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| num_employees    = 13,800 &lt;small&gt;(March 2011)&lt;/small&gt;
| homepage         = [http://www.ca.com/ CA.com]
}}

'''CA Technologies''' ({{nasdaq|CA}}), formerly '''CA, Inc.''' and  '''Computer Associates, Inc.''', is a [[Fortune 500]] company and one of the largest independent software corporations in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune500/2010/snapshots/2974.html | work= CNN | title=CA – Fortune 500 2010 – CNNMoney}}&lt;/ref&gt; Headquartered in [[Islandia, New York]], the company supports software which runs in mainframe, distributed, virtualized and cloud environments and which a majority of the Forbes Global 2000 has installed.{{Cn|date=October 2011}}
In 2010, CA Technologies announced its cloud computing management strategy at its CA World user conference, and its new CA Cloud-Connected Management Suite of products that address the emerging challenges presented by the cloud. 

Although the company sells [[anti-virus]] and [[internet security]] programs for consumer personal computers, it is primarily known for its [[mainframe computer]] and [[distributed computing]] applications and solutions used by businesses with CA Technologies claiming that its software is used by a majority of the Forbes Global 2000 companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/finance/stocks/companyProfile?rpc=66&amp;symbol=CA.O |title=CA Inc (CA.O)| work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CA Technologies, which posted $4.4 billion US$ in revenue for fiscal year 2010 (ending March 31, 2010),&lt;ref name=&quot;CA Annual Report 2010&quot;/&gt; maintains 150 offices in more than 45 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune500/snapshots/341.html | work=CNN | title=CA – CA, Inc. – Fortune 500 2006 – CNNMoney}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company employs 13,200 people (March 31, 2010),&lt;ref name=&quot;CA Annual Report 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web
    |url       = http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/CA/382014003x0x217348/1A2A1DF5-1DF5-4F98-9BCF-F57E5E5B1C14/200810K.pdf
    |title     = CA Annual Report 2010
    |publisher = CA, Inc.}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; including 5900 engineers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA Annual Report 2010&quot;/&gt; CA holds more than 400 patents worldwide, and more than 700 patent applications are pending.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA Annual Report 2010&quot;/&gt;

In 2010 the company acquired eight companies to support its cloud strategy including: 3Tera,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/news/Press-Releases/na/2010/CA-Technologies-Drives-Revolutionary-Approach-to-Cloud-Computing-with-CA-3Tera-AppLogic.aspx |title=CA.com |publisher=CA.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nimsoft,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://investor.ca.com/releasedetail.cfm?releaseid=451013 |title=Investor.ca.com |publisher=Investor.ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; NetQoS,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://investor.ca.com/releasedetail.cfm?releaseid=425529 |title=Investor.ca.com |publisher=Investor.ca.com |date=November 19, 2009 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oblicore,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arcserve.com/us/sitecore/content/home/news/Press-Releases/na/2010/CA-Acquires-Oblicore-Leader-in-IT-Service-Level-Management.aspx |title=Arcserve.com |publisher=Arcserve.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cassatt,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/news/press-releases/na/2009/ca-acquires-cassatt-data-center-automation-innovation-and-expertise.aspx |title=CA.com |publisher=CA.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 4Base Technology,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/news/press-releases/na/2010/ca-technologies-acquires-virtualization-and-cloud-infrastructure-consulting-firm.aspx |title=CA.com |publisher=CA.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arcot Systems,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/news/Press-Releases/na/2010/CA-Technologies-Completes-Arcot-Systems-Acquisition.aspx |title=CA.com |publisher=CA.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Hyperformix.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/news/Press-Releases/na/2010/CA-Technologies-to-acquire-Hyperformix.aspx |title=CA.com |publisher=CA.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[CA Technologies#cite note-Funding Universe History-6]]&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 22, 2010, the company was ranked among the greenest companies by Newsweek magazine’s Green rankings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gopnik |first=Blake |url=http://www.newsweek.com/feature/2010/green-rankings.html |title=Newsweek.com |work=Newsweek  |date=October 16, 2011 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 28, 2010, CA Technologies announced that William E. McCracken would be its chairman of the board and chief executive officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/press/release.aspx?cid=227312 |title=CA, Inc. Names William E. McCracken Chief Executive Officer |publisher=Ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 6, 2010 Arthur F. Weinbach was appointed as Non-Executive Chairman.

==History==
{{See also|Charles Wang|Russell Artzt}}
Sources:&lt;ref name=&quot;CA_History&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/about/content.aspx?cid=120941 |title=CA History |publisher=Ca.com |date=September 22, 2008 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Funding_Universe_History&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fundinguniverse.com/company-histories/Computer-Associates-International-Inc-Company-History.html |title=Company History |publisher=Fundinguniverse.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Inception and early years===
[[File:Computer-Associates-HQ.jpg|thumb|300px|Headquarters on Long Island]]
In 1969, under regulatory pressure, [[IBM]] announced its decision to unbundle the sale of mainframe computers from computer programs and support services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www-rohan.sdsu.edu/faculty/giftfire/ibm.html |title=IBM: Producer or Predator |publisher=Rohan.sdsu.edu |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (At this time, the computer industry was dominated by mainframes, principally from IBM.) The decision opened new markets to competition and provided an opportunity for entrepreneurs to enter the nascent software industry – an opportunity that [[Charles Wang]] and his friend and business partner [[Russell Artzt|Russ Artzt]] exploited by creating a company to develop and market mainframe software, and they developed several products for the mainframe market, with modest success. In 1976, they obtained the North American distribution rights for CA-Sort, which had previously been distributed by Pansophic Systems under the name PanSort. CA-Sort was originally developed by a Swiss company named Computer Associates, which had been founded by Sam Goodner and Max Sevcik several years earlier. CA-Sort had found success in Europe, but sales in North America hadn't kept pace. Wang and Artzt established a new venture (in partnership with the Swiss company), which they named Trans-American Computer Associates, and went to market with CA-Sort, along with their original products.

The CA-Sort program helped computers to sort data efficiently. Its superior performance (mostly on the DOS/VSE platform), combined with the sales acumen of Charles Wang, led to rapid growth in the large and lucrative North American market. After merging with the original Swiss company in 1980, the new global venture (subsequently known as Computer Associates International, Inc.) was able to expand, hiring more salespeople and programmers and acquiring many smaller software companies in the following years. The acquisition in 1987 of Uccel Corporation (flagship products UCC-1, UCC-7, UCC-11) made CA the largest independent vendor of mainframe infrastructure software and dominant vendor of OS/MVS security software with CA-Top Secret and CA-ACF2.  It also made [[Walter Haefner]], who was half-owner of Uccel at the time, its largest individual shareholder, a distinction he still enjoys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4189/is_20060127/ai_n16038914 |title=Activist investor group becomes No. 1 institutional holder |publisher=Findarticles.com |date=January 27, 2006 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1980s===
Following an [[initial public offering]] in 1981, the company expanded rapidly through a series of acquisitions, including software makers Capex, Information Unlimited Software, Johnson Systems, CGA Computer, and [[Uccel]]. Whereas CA’s focus during this time was on system utilities, the company also sought to compete in the applications market with firms such as [[Microsoft]] and [[Lotus Development Corporation]] through acquisition of companies that provided spreadsheet, word processor, graphics, and other application software. As the decade ended, CA became the first software company after Microsoft to exceed $1 billion USD in sales.

===1990s===
In the early years of the 1990s, CA was forced to address criticism of the company (specifically, a lack of strategic focus, incompatibilities between its disparate product line, a reputation for poor customer service, and failure to win a significant share in application software markets) as well as a sharp decline in its stock price, which fell more than 50% during 1990. The ensuing changes included a push into foreign markets (Japan, Canada, Africa, and Latin America), reform in how the company charged its customers for software maintenance, and improved compatibility with products from other vendors such as [[Hewlett-Packard]], [[Apple Computer]], and [[Digital Equipment Corporation]]. Meanwhile, CA continued to expand through acquisitions, most notably in client-server computing (Legent Corporation for $1.78 billion USD in 1995, at that time the biggest ever acquisition in the software industry) and [[data storage device|data storage]] software (Cheyenne Software for $1.2 billion USD in 1996).

===2000s===
CA faced further challenges in the early 2000s including constraints imposed by the [[United States Department of Justice|U.S. Department of Justice]] on acquisitions, the need to service and refinance large amounts of debt, and a [[proxy fight|proxy battle]] between the board and shareholders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DE1630F932A15755C0A9679C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all |title=Entrepreneur to Begin Proxy Fight for Computer Associates, '&amp;#39;New York Times,'&amp;#39; June 21, 2001 |work=New York Times |date=June 21, 2001 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company also suffered from controversies regarding executive compensation, accounting methods, and insider-trading by its then CEO and chairman, [[Sanjay Kumar]]. Between 2004 and 2006, CA made sweeping changes among its board and executive team, including the appointment of a new CEO, John Swainson, plus new appointments to the positions of Chairman, Executive Vice President of Strategy and Business Development, CFO, COO, CTO, Chief Marketing Officer, Chief Administrative Officer, and co-General Counsel, most of which were outside appointments. On September 1, 2009, CA announced CEO John Swainson's decision to retire by December 31, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/press/release.aspx?cid=215623 |title=CA, Inc. CEO John A. Swainson Announces Plans to Retire by End of 2009 |publisher=Ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During this time, the company presented its [[Enterprise IT Management|Enterprise IT Management (EITM)]] vision to unify and simplify enterprise-wide IT&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internetnews.com/ent-news/article.php/3564046 |title=– ‘Believe Again’ in CA |publisher=Internetnews.com |date=November 14, 2005 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and debuted the largest number of products in its history. Underscoring the message of a changed company, CA also unveiled a new global branding program to inspire the industry to “Believe Again” in the power of technology to support business.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ca.com/us/press/release.aspx?cid=76885 CA Press Release, November 13, 2005: CA Launches New Global Branding Program]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; CA changed its name from Computer Associates Inc. to CA Inc. in 2006 and to CA Technologies in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ca.com/us/press/release.aspx?cid=236083 CA, Inc. Has a New Name: CA Technologies]. May 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Most recently, the company announced its support for [[Lean IT]] through an announcement of 13 new and enhanced EITM products.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ca.com/us/press/release.aspx?cid=203332 CA Enables Lean IT to Help Maximize Value and Minimize Cost]. April 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010s===
CA Technologies embraced the Cloud Strategy by launching the unique{{cn|date=June 2011}} concept of IT Supply Chain, allowing a company to manage and secure dynamically both physical and virtual environments and to deliver more flexible IT services.

In 2011 CA sold its antivirus properties to Updata Partners, which spun the division off as '[[Total Defense]]'.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/05/17/ca_quits_anti_virus_biz/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Software products==
CA offers software products and services for distributed computing, mainframe environments, as well as virtualization and cloud. The portfolio spans the following product categories:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/it-management-products.aspx |title=CA’s Product Categories (CA web site) |publisher=Ca.com |date=September 22, 2008 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Mainframe
* Security/Identity and Access Management
* Cloud
* Virtualization and Automation
* IT Management SaaS
* Service Assurance
* Service and Portfolio Management
* EcoSoftware
* Recovery Management and Data Modeling
* Nimsoft
[[File:CA House in Canberra.jpg|thumb|CA House in [[Canberra]].]]
The company maintains product development staff in locations worldwide including the United States, Australia, China, the Czech Republic, Germany, India, Israel, Japan, and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA Annual Report 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web
    |url       = http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/CA/382014003x0x217348/1A2A1DF5-1DF5-4F98-9BCF-F57E5E5B1C14/200810K.pdf
    |title     = CA Annual Report 2008
    |accessdate= 2008-08-29
    |publisher = CA, Inc.}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of CA’s products target large and medium-size enterprises, but some of its product line – for example, its anti-virus, anti-spyware, and personal firewall solutions – are for home and home-office users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://shop.ca.com/software_products/protect_optimize.aspx |title=CA’s Home and Home-Office Products (CA web site) |publisher=Shop.ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==CA Services==
CA Services is a services organization within CA Technologies employing over 1200 consultants. 

With a presence in over 25 countries, CA Services works with businesses of all sizes to develop implementation, technology roadmap, and education plan. The organization posted US$280M in revenue for fiscal year 2010 (ending March 31, 2010).{{cn|date=June 2011}}

== CA Labs ==
CA Labs was established in 2005 to strengthen relationships between research communities and CA. CA Labs has been working closely with universities, professional associations and government on various projects that relate to CA products, technologies and methodologies. The results of these projects vary from research publications, to best practices, to new directions for products.

Through a variety of University Relations programs, CA is working with many universities to enable and promote innovation—including funding university research projects in specific areas, working with faculty to enhance curriculum, and providing opportunities to interact with CA research and development experts.

== Controversies ==
CA has been party to a number of lawsuits over its thirty-plus year history, and particularly so during the period from the early 1990s to early 2000s. One of the higher-profile disputes was a 1992 suit by [[Electronic Data Systems]] (EDS), which was a CA customer. EDS accused CA of breach of contract, including misuse of copyright, and violations of anti-trust laws. CA filed a counter-claim, also alleging breach of contract, including copyright infringement and misappropriation of trade secrets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sec.edgar-online.com/1994/03/29/00/0000040730-94-000002/Section4.asp |title=Excerpt from General Motors 10-K SEC Filing, March 29, 1994 |publisher=Sec.edgar-online.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The companies reached a settlement in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA_History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Funding_Universe_History&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, a hostile (and unsuccessful) takeover bid by CA in 1998 for computer consulting firm [[Computer Sciences Corporation]] (CSC) prompted a bribery suit by CSC’s (then) chairman Van Honeycutt against CA’s founder and (then) CEO, [[Charles Wang]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forbes.com/forbes/1998/0518/6110098a_print.html |title=A pain in the posterior, '&amp;#39;Forbes,'&amp;#39; May 18, 1998 |work=Forbes |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further controversy followed in 1999 when Wang received the largest bonus in history at that time from a public company. Moreover, this receipt (a $670 million stock grant that dated to the vesting of a 1995 stock option&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.corporatenarc.com/cascandal.php |title=Computer Associates Accounting Scandal |publisher=Corporatenarc.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;) occurred while the company faced a slowdown in European markets and an economic slump in Asia, both of which had affected CA's earnings and stock price. In total, the company took a $675 million after-tax charge for $1.1 billion in payouts to Wang and other top CA executives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Funding_Universe_History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/1999/99_16/b3625017.htm |title=Executive Pay: Up, Up and Away, '&amp;#39;Business Week'&amp;#39; Online, April 19, 1999 |work=Bloomberg BusinessWeek   |date=April 19, 1999 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000 a shareholder-based class-action lawsuit accused CA of misstating more than $500 million in revenue in its 1998 and 1999 fiscal years in order to artificially inflate its stock price. An investigation by the [[Securities and Exchange Commission]] (SEC) also followed, which resulted in charges against the company and some of its former top executives. The SEC alleged that from 1998 to 2000, CA routinely kept its books open to include quarterly revenue from contracts executed after the quarter ended in order to meet Wall Street analysts’ expectations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sec.gov/news/press/2004-134.htm |title=SEC files securities fraud charges against Computer Associates, Inc |publisher=Sec.gov |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company reached a settlement with the SEC and [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] in 2004, agreeing to pay $225 million in restitution to shareholders and to reform its corporate governance and financial accounting controls. Eight CA executives since pleaded guilty to fraud charges – most notably, former CEO and chairman [[Sanjay Kumar]], who received a 12-year prison sentence for orchestrating the scandal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=De |first=Michael J. |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/03/technology/03computer.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=print&amp;oref=slogin |title=Ex-Leader of Computer Associates Gets 12-Year Sentence and Fine, '&amp;#39;New York Times,'&amp;#39; November 3, 2006 |work=The New York Times  |date=November 3, 2006 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company subsequently made sweeping changes through virtually all of its senior leadership positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA_History&quot;/&gt;

==Acquisitions==
{{Main|List of acquisitions by CA Technologies}}
CA has a long history of acquisitions in the software industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Funding_Universe_History&quot;/&gt;
* 2011: [[Itko|ITKO, Inc.]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/BT-CO-20110629-714955.html |title=CA To Acquire Software Maker Interactive TKO For $330M |work=The Wall Street Journal  |date=June 29, 2011 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ($330 million) 
* 2011: [[Torokina Networks]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/news/Press-Releases/na/2011/Torokina.aspx |title=CA Technologies Acquires Torokina Networks, January 25, 2011 (CA web page) |publisher=Ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* 2010: [[Hyperformix]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hyperformix.com/ Home]. Hyperformix. Retrieved on 2010-11-09.&lt;/ref&gt; (undisclosed amount)
* 2010: [[Arcot Systems]] ($200 million)
* 2010: [[4Base Technology]] (undisclosed amount)
* 2010: [[Nimsoft]] ($350 million)
* 2010: [[3tera]]
* 2010: Cassatt
* 2010: [[Oblicore]]
* 2009: [[NetQoS|NetQoS Inc.]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ca.com/us/content/campaign.aspx?cid=215045 NetQoS, a CA Technologies Company – CA Technologies]. Ca.com. Retrieved on 2010-11-09.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2009: Orchestria
* 2008: Eurekify, Inc.
* 2008: IDFocus, LLC.
* 2006: MDY Group (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://searchstorage.techtarget.com/news/article/0,289142,sid5_gci1193633,00.html |title=A buys MDY for records retention management, searchstorage.com, June 14, 2006 |publisher=Searchstorage.techtarget.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006: Cendura (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.networkworld.com/news/2006/092706-ca-cendura.html |title=CA makes buyout to boost application management, NetworkWorld.com, September 27, 2006 |publisher=Networkworld.com |date=September 27, 2006 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006: Control-F1 Corporation (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4189/is_20060111/ai_n16010606 |title='&amp;#39;Long Island Business News,'&amp;#39; January 11, 2006 |publisher=Findarticles.com |date=January 11, 2006 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006: [http://www.cybermation.co.uk/ Cybermation Inc.]&amp;nbsp;— US$75 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.networkworld.com/news/2006/041306-ca-cybermation.html |title=CA ups stake in mainframe management with Cybermation acquisition, NetworkWorld.com, April 13, 2006 |publisher=Networkworld.com |date=April 13, 2006 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006: [http://www.xosoft.com/ XOsoft, Inc.]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://searchstorage.techtarget.com/news/article/0,289142,sid5_gci1198697,00.html# |title=CA acquires XOsoft, adds replication to ARCserve, searchstorage.com |publisher=Searchstorage.techtarget.com |date=November 8, 2011 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2006: [http://www.wilytech.com/ Wily Technology]&amp;nbsp;— US$375 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://investor.ca.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=316670 |title=CA Acquires Privately Held Wily Technology (CA web page) |publisher=Investor.ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2005: [[CA Clarity PPM|Niku]] – US$350 million (renamed CA Clarity)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0ECZ/is_2005_June_10/ai_n13831300 |title=Computer Associates to acquire Niku in USD350m deal |publisher=Findarticles.com |date=June 10, 2005 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2005: Concord Communications/Aprisma Management Technologies&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ca.com/us/content/campaign.aspx?cid=158013 |title=Aprisma is Now CA (CA web page) |publisher=Ca.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2005: iLumin Software Services
* 2005: [[Tiny Software]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://investor.ca.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=316006 |title=CA Acquires Tiny Software, June 27, 2006 (CA web page) |publisher=Investor.ca.com |date=June 27, 2005 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2004: Netegrity
* 2004: PestPatrol (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.byteandswitch.com/document.asp?doc_id=57872 CA Acquires PestPatrol, ByteAndSwitch]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2004: Miramar (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.cnet.com/CA-buys-desktop-management-software-maker/2110-1014_3-5172295.html?tag=nw.6 |title=CA buys desktop management software maker, CNET.com, March 11, 2004 |publisher=News.cnet.com |date=March 11, 2004 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2003: Netreon (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dmreview.com/news/6336-1.html |title=CA Acquires Netreon, '&amp;#39;DM Review Online,'&amp;#39; February 5, 2003 |publisher=Dmreview.com |date=February 5, 2003 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2003: SilentRunner (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cowen.com/InvestmentBanking_635.asp ]{{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2000: [[Sterling Software]]&amp;nbsp;— US$3.91 billion&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.faqs.org/abstracts/Business-general/Computer-Associates-in-$391-billion-deal-in-industrys-biggest-pact-Sterling-Software-to-add-to-mainf.html |title=Computer Associates in $3.91 billion deal; in industry's biggest pact, Sterling Software to add to mainframe business |publisher=Faqs.org |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2000: Applied Management Systems Inc.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
* 1999: [[Platinum Technology|Platinum Technology International]]&amp;nbsp;— US$3.5 billion&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_1999_March_29/ai_54235200 |title=Computer Associates To Acquire PLATINUM Technology in Largest Software Deal in History, BusinessWire, March 29, 1999 |publisher=Findarticles.com |date=March 29, 1999 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1999: CMSI (Computer Management Sciences, Inc.)&amp;nbsp;— US$435 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By Eric&amp;nbsp;Hausman, CRN |url=http://www.crn.com/it-channel/18801409 |title=CA To Acquire CMSI For $435 Million, CRN, February 8, 1999 |publisher=Crn.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1998: QXCOM (undisclosed amount)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Magee |first=Mike |url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/1998/09/02/ca_buys_qxcom/ |title=CA buys QXCOM, '&amp;#39;The Register'&amp;#39;, September 2, 1998 |publisher=Theregister.co.uk |date=September 2, 1998 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1998: Viewpoint DataLabs International, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allbusiness.com/company-activities-management/company-structures-ownership/6909002-1.html |title=Computer Associates Acquires Viewpoint Datalabs, BusinessWire, October 29, 1998 |publisher=Allbusiness.com |date=October 29, 1998 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1998: LDA Systems, Inc.
* 1998: Realogic, Inc.
* 1997: AI Ware, Inc.
* 1997: Avalan Technology, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allbusiness.com/company-activities-management/operations-customer/7020779-1.html |title=Computer Associates Acquires All Assets of AvalanTechnology, Inc., BusinessWire, November 12, 1997 |publisher=Allbusiness.com |date=November 12, 1997 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1996: Cheyenne Software&amp;nbsp;— US$1.2 billion&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_1996_Oct_7/ai_18738324 |title=Computer Associates To Acquire Cheyenne Software, Inc., BusinessWire, October 7, 1996 |publisher=Findarticles.com |date=October 7, 1996 |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1995: Legent Corporation&amp;nbsp;— US$1.78 billion
* 1994: [[ASK Corporation|The ASK Group, Inc.]]&amp;nbsp;— US$311 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3653/is_199405/ai_n8723467?tag=content;col1 |title=Computer Associates springs a bid on ASK Group, '&amp;#39;Corporate Growth Report Weekly,'&amp;#39; May 30, 1994 |publisher=Findarticles.com |accessdate=November 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1992: Glockenspiel Ltd
* 1992: Nantucket Corporation
* 1991: Access Technology
* 1991: Pansophic Systems, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbi.umn.edu/oh/display.phtml?id=330 Oral history interview with Joseph Piscopo], [[Charles Babbage Institute]], University of Minnesota.  Piscopo founded Pansophic Systems in 1969 and led it until his retirement in 1987.  Interview explains the circumstances behind the firm's stumble in the late 1980s and acquisition by Computer Associates.&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;— US$290 million
* 1991: On-Line Software International Inc.&amp;nbsp;— $120 million
* 1989: Cullinet&amp;nbsp;— US$289 million
* 1988: Applied Data Research&amp;nbsp;— US$170 million
* 1987: [[Uccel]]&amp;nbsp;— US$830 million
* 1986: Software International&amp;nbsp;— US$24 million
* 1986: Integrated Software Systems Corporation (ISSCO)&amp;nbsp;— US$67 million
* 1985: Top Secret (from CGA for US$25 million)
* 1985: Sorcim&amp;nbsp;— US$27 million
* 1985: Arkay Computer (undisclosed amount)
* 1984: Johnson Systems, Inc.&amp;nbsp;— US$16 million
* 1983: Information Unlimited Software&amp;nbsp;— US$10 million
* 1983: Stewart P. Orr Associates&amp;nbsp;— US$2 million
* 1982: [[Capex Corporation]] &amp;nbsp;— US$22 million
* 1981: Viking Data Systems, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |year=1987 |title=CBI Begins Study of The History of Software |journal=Charles Babbage Institute Newsletter |publisher=Charles Babbage Institute |volume=9 |issue=2 |page=11|url=http://www.cbi.umn.edu/about/nsl/v9n2.pdf |doi=Winter, 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Companies}}
* [[Endevor]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|CA Technologies}}
*[http://www.cbi.umn.edu/oh/display.phtml?id=352 Oral history interview with Sam Wyly], Charles Babbage Institute, University of Minnesota, by David Allison, December 6, 2002.  [[Sam Wyly|Wyly]] discusses his formation of [[Uccel|University Computer Corporation]] (UCC), a software services business, the eventual sale of this firm to [[Computer Associates]], his formation of [[Sterling Software]], its acquisition of [[Informatics (academic field)|Informatics]], the sale of Sterling, and his ideas on the future of information technology.
* [http://www.ca.com/ CA Technologies]
* [http://shop.ca.com/ CA AntiVirus &amp; Internet Security Software]
* [http://www.ca.com/us/it-services.aspx  CA Services]
* [http://www.linkedin.com/groups?gid=2435288&amp;trk=fulpro_grplogo&amp;goback=%2Econ  CA Services LinkedIn Group]

{{NASDAQ-100}}
{{Major information technology companies}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ca Technologies}}
[[Category:Computer companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Software companies based in New York]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1976]]
[[Category:Computer companies]]
[[Category:Orphan initialisms]]
[[Category:Companies based in Suffolk County, New York]]

[[de:CA Technologies]]
[[fr:CA Technologies]]
[[id:CA Technologies]]
[[it:CA (azienda)]]
[[nl:Computer Associates]]
[[ja:CAテクノロジーズ]]
[[no:Computer Associates]]
[[pl:Computer Associates]]
[[pt:Computer Associates]]
[[ro:CA, Inc.]]
[[ru:CA Technologies]]
[[zh:CA公司]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
