<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="424342" ns="0" title="Pepperdine University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name = Pepperdine University
|image_name = Pepperdine Official Seal.jpg
|image_size = 200px
|motto = ''Freely ye received, freely give''
|established = 1937
|type = [[Private university|Private]]
|affiliation=[[Churches of Christ]]
|president = Andrew K. Benton
|city = [[Malibu, California|Malibu]]
|state = [[California|CA]]
|country = [[United States|USA]]
|undergrad = 3,474 (Seaver College)
|postgrad = 4,294 (Pepperdine University)
|faculty = 636
|endowment = [[United States dollar|USD $]]565 million&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|campus = [[Suburban]], &lt;br/&gt;{{convert|830|acre|ha}}
|mascot = Willy the Wave
|athletics =[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] &lt;br /&gt; [[West Coast Conference]]
|nickname = Waves
|colors = [[Blue]] and [[Orange (color)|Orange]]
{{color box|#0021A5}}{{color box|#E83E00}}
|website = [http://www.pepperdine.edu/ www.pepperdine.edu]
|logo = [[Image:Pepperdine logo stacked.jpg|center]]
}}

'''Pepperdine University''' is an independent, private, medium-sized university affiliated with the [[Churches of Christ]]. The university's {{convert|830|acre|ha|adj=on}} campus overlooking the Pacific Ocean in [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]] [[Los Angeles County, California]], [[United States]], near [[Malibu, California|Malibu]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/MapItDrawServlet?geo_id=16000US0645246&amp;_bucket_id=49&amp;tree_id=339&amp;context=saff&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on Malibu city, California].&quot; [[U.S. Census Bureau]]. Retrieved on October 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://seaver.pepperdine.edu/about/content/seaver-map.pdf Malibu Campus - Seaver College].&quot; Pepperdine University. Retrieved on October 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; is the location for Seaver College, the School of Law, the Graduate School of Education and Psychology, the Graziadio School of Business and Management, and the School of Public Policy.  Courses are taught in Malibu, at six graduate campuses in [[southern California]], and at international campuses in [[Germany]], [[England]], [[Italy]], [[China]], [[Switzerland]], and [[Argentina]].

==History==
===Early years===
In February 1937, against the backdrop of the [[Great Depression]], George Pepperdine founded the university as a Christian liberal arts college in the city of Los Angeles. On September 21, 1937, 167 new students from 22 different states and two other countries entered classes on a newly built campus on {{convert|34|acre|ha}} at West 79th Street and South Vermont Avenue in the Vermont Knolls neighborhood of [[South Central Los Angeles]],&lt;ref name=Ebony&gt;Aldore Collier, [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1077/is_n2_v45/ai_8153049 FaithDome: &quot;A grand-slam homer for Jesus.&quot;], ''Ebony'', December 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; referred to later as the Vermont Avenue campus.&lt;ref&gt;Vanessa Jahn, [http://gsep.pepperdine.edu/alumni/colleaguemagazine/spring2006/35thAnniversary.htm GSEP 35th Anniversary: A Celebratory Evening to Remember], ''Colleague Alumni Magazine'', Spring 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Graphic111402&gt;Tracy Domingo, [http://graphic.pepperdine.edu/news/2002/2002-11-14-miracle.htm Miracle at Malibu Materialized], ''Graphic'', November 14, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;  By April 6, 1938, George Pepperdine College was fully accredited by the Northwest Association.

Pepperdine had built a fortune founding and developing the [[Western Auto|Western Auto Supply Company]], which he started with a $5 investment, but his prosperity led to his greater ambition to discover &quot;how humanity can be helped most with the means entrusted to [his] care. [He] consider it wrong to build up a great fortune and use it selfishly.&quot; Mr. Pepperdine voiced his twofold objective for the college that bore his name, &quot;First, we want to provide first-class, fully accredited academic training in the liberal arts&amp;nbsp;... Secondly, we are especially dedicated to a greater goal—that of building in the student a Christ-like life, a love for the church, and a passion for the souls of mankind.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

===Move to Malibu===
By the 1960s, the young college faced serious problems. The area around the Vermont Avenue campus developed issues with crime and urban decay; tensions also arose due to the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|Civil Rights Movement]] and attempts to circumvent it such as [[California Proposition 14 (1963)|California Proposition 14]], which challenged federal [[fair housing]] laws.&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;  The situation exploded in the 1965 [[Watts Riots]].&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;  In 1969 activists in the Watts area threatened to burn down the campus; however, they were talked out of it after all-night negotiations by then-President M. Norvel Young.&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;  In addition, the Vermont Avenue campus was running out of room to expand.&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;

In 1967, the school put forth a multi-campus idea that would move the undergraduate campus to an alternative location; a committee formed and looked at numerous locations, including sites in [[Valencia, Santa Clarita, California|Valencia]], [[Orange County, California|Orange County]], [[Ventura County, California|Ventura County]] and [[Westlake Village]].&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;  Pepperdine favored the Westlake Village location until the Adamson-Rindge family, who owned hundreds of acres in Malibu, offered {{convert|138|acre|ha}} of Malibu land; despite concerns over building costs on the mountainous site, the school decided to move forward based on its prime location and potential for raising donation.&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;  On April 13, 1971, the university broke ground to commence construction and in September 1972 the Malibu campus opened for student enrollment.&lt;ref name=Graphic111402 /&gt;

(The old Pepperdine University campus was sold to [[Crenshaw Christian Center]], whose pastor, Frederick K.C. Price, then oversaw construction of the &quot;FaithDome,&quot; the largest domed-church in the United States, seating over 10,000).

====School of Law====
{{Main|Pepperdine University School of Law}}
Pepperdine gained university status in 1971 when the [[Pepperdine University School of Law|school of law]] was added and the business and education departments became separate schools. In the 1980s, Pepperdine rose to prominence as one of the United States' leading centers of [[conservatism|conservative]] politics, attracting many conservative-leaning professors from nearby [[University of California, Los Angeles|UCLA]] and [[University of Southern California|USC]]. Prominent conservatives on the Pepperdine faculty have included [[Bruce Herschensohn]], [[Ben Stein]], [[Kenneth Starr]], [[Arthur Laffer]], [[Douglas Kmiec]], and [[Daniel Pipes]].
[[Image:Pepperdinefire.jpg|thumb|right|225px|Smoke billows on a hill near Pepperdine University's Theme Tower.]]

====Brushfires====
In 1993 and 1996, massive brushfires threatened the campus with destruction, but firefighters succeeded in protecting almost all structures. On October 21, 2007, fast-moving wildfires forced campus residents to relocate and shelter in the Firestone Field house and Cafeteria, plus evacuations of local homes and businesses.&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press according to CNN&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, another November 2007 fire in Corral Canyon, accidentally set off by a group of Los Angeles youths, caused an evacuation of the Drescher Campus.  However, most students were off-campus for the Thanksgiving holiday.

==Campus==
The main campus is located among several ridges that overlook the [[Pacific Ocean]] and the [[Pacific Coast Highway (US)|Pacific Coast Highway]] in [[Malibu, California|Malibu]], California. The main campus entrance road ascends a steep, well-groomed grassy slope past a huge stylized cross, known as the Phillips Theme Tower, symbolizing the university's dedication to its original Christian mission. Most buildings were constructed in a typical 1980s-style reinterpretation of classic Californian and [[Mediterranean Revival Style architecture|Mediterranean architecture]] (red tile roofs, white stuccoed walls, large tinted windows). There are views of the Pacific Ocean, [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Catalina Island]], [[Palos Verdes|Palos Verdes Peninsula]], [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]] and the westside of Los Angeles from numerous points. Graduations take place at Alumni Park, a broad expanse of lawn overlooking Pacific Coast Highway and the Pacific Ocean. The main academic plaza for undergraduate programs of Seaver College lies just above Alumni Park and includes Stauffer Chapel, Tyler Campus Center, Payson Library, and the Ahmanson Fine Arts Center. Undergraduate housing and athletic facilities sit to the north/northwest of the academic complex. The Law School exists even higher above these areas. The central campus is surrounded by a loop road consisting of Seaver Drive, Huntsinger Circle, and John Tyler Drive. Banowsky Boulevard separates Alumni Park from the main academic complex and is named in honor of William S. Banowsky, the 4th president of Pepperdine.

Spur roads to the east of the central part of campus lead to faculty housing. To the northwest, Via Pacifica winds uphill to the '''Drescher Graduate Campus''', completed in 2003 and home to the School of Public Policy, the Villa Graziadio conference center, as well as the fulltime programs of the Graziadio School of Business and Management and the Graduate School of Education and Psychology. Housing for graduate students, undergraduate honors students, and faculty are also located here.

=== Frederick R. Weisman Museum of Art ===
[[Image:Gallup_weisman_museum.png|thumb|left|Frederick R. Weisman Museum of Art]]
Recent noteworthy exhibitions in the Frederick R. Weisman Museum of Art include:&lt;br /&gt;

[[Roy Lichtenstein]]:  January - March, 2011&lt;br /&gt;

David Gallup: Channel Islands: May 2011&lt;br /&gt;

===Graduate campuses===
The [[Graziadio School of Business and Management]], [[School of Public Policy]], and the [[Graduate School of Education and Psychology]] are headquartered in [[West Los Angeles (region)|West Los Angeles]] at the [[Howard Hughes Center]] next to [[Interstate 405 (California)|Interstate 405]]. These two schools also offer programs at graduate campuses in [[Encino, Los Angeles, California|Encino]], [[Irvine, California|Irvine]], [[Santa Clara, California|Santa Clara]], and [[Westlake Village, California|Westlake Village]]. International programs of the University's various schools have taken place in [[London]], [[Heidelberg]], [[Florence]], [[Buenos Aires]], [[Paris]], [[Madrid]], [[Lausanne]], [[Johannesburg]], [[Tegucigalpa]], [[Brisbane]], [[Chiang Mai, Thailand|Chiang Mai]], [[Hong Kong]] and [[Tokyo]].

==Academics==
[[Image:Pepperdine University.JPG|thumb|right|250px|Houses adjacent to the Malibu campus.]]
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W = 
| ARWU_N =
| Forbes = 104
| QS_W =
| THES_W =
| USNWR_NU = 53
| USNWR_LA =
| USNWR_WEST =
| Wamo_NU = 137
| Wamo_LA =
| Wamo_MASTERSU = 
}}

===Frank R. Seaver College of Letters, Arts, and Sciences===
Seaver College is named for Mr. and Mrs. Frank R. Seaver, the principal benefactors of Pepperdine's Malibu Campus. The college offers undergraduates a liberal arts education, and each candidate for a Bachelor's Degree must complete a series of general education courses crossing disciplinary lines.  Seaver College students attend classes at the Malibu main campus and study abroad courses are offered at the University's permanent international campuses in Germany, England, China, Italy, Switzerland, and Buenos Aires.  Rick Marrs is the current dean. 

Seaver College comprises 8 divisions and offers 40 majors (listed below), as well as 37 minors:

'''Business Division''':
Accounting
Business Administration
International Business

'''Communication Division''':
Advertising
Integrated Marketing Communication
Journalism
Public Relations
Media Production
Communication

'''Fine Arts Division''':
Art,
Art History,
Music,
Theatre Arts,
Theatre &amp; Music,
Theatre &amp; Media Production

'''Humanities and Teacher Education Division''':
Creative Writing
English
Film Studies
History
Liberal Arts
Philosophy

'''International Studies and Languages Division''':
French
German
Hispanic Studies
International Studies
Italian

'''Natural Science Division''':
Biology
Chemistry
Computer Science/Mathematics
Mathematics
Mathematics Education
Nutritional Science
Physics
Sports Medicine
Natural Science- Engineering 3/2 Program

'''Religion Division''':
Religion 

The Religion Division offers undergraduate and graduate education in ministry, administers a  Center for Faith and Learning and an Office of Church Relations, and publishes ''Leaven: A Journal of Christian Ministry''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://seaver.pepperdine.edu/religion/ Pepperdine's Religion Division web site.]&lt;/ref&gt;	

'''Social Science Division''':
Economics
Political Science
Psychology
Sociology

In addition, the college offers the following graduate degrees: Master of Arts in American studies, Master of Arts in Communication, Master of Science in Communication, Master of Arts in Religion, Master of Divinity, and Master of Fine Arts in Writing for Screen &amp; Television. Seaver students can also earn both single-subject and multiple-subject teaching credentials.

Pepperdine has six international branch campuses located in Heidelberg, Germany; London, England; Florence, Italy; Lausanne, Switzerland; Shanghai, China; and Buenos Aires, Argentina.

===Graziadio School of Business and Management===
Pepperdine University's George L. [[Graziadio School of Business and Management]] enrolls approximately 2,000 students in its full-time and part-time degree programs. The school was founded in 1969, and has since graduated over 30,000 alumni. Dr. Linda Livingstone has served as dean since 2002. In 2011, US News ranked Pepperdine 75th out of  437 business programs in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-business-schools/rankings/page+3  US News Rankings &lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===School of Law===
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Solbuilding.jpg|thumb|right|The Harnish Law Library at Pepperdine's School of Law.]] --&gt;
The [[Pepperdine University School of Law]] is located adjacent to the Seaver College Campus, and enrolls about 670 students who come from all parts of the country. It is fully approved by the [[American Bar Association]] and is a member of the [[Association of American Law Schools]]. The school of law recently has attained membership in the prestigious [[Order of the Coif]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.pepperdine.edu/news/052008_coif.html News | School of Law | Pepperdine University&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orderofthecoif.org/COIF-members.htm member chart&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Pepperdine's [[Pepperdine_University_School_of_Law#Straus_Institute_for_Dispute_Resolution|Straus Institute of Dispute Resolution]] is consistently ranked as the number one dispute resolution program in the country, offering LL.M., master's and certificate programs. Some of its other newer degree offerings include the juris doctor/master of divinity in conjunction with Pepperdine's Seaver College. Other joint degree programs include the JD/MBA, JD/MPP, and JD/MDR. The school offers both a summer session and a fall semester in [[London, England|London]], [[England]]. [[Thomas G. Bost]] is the interim dean.
[[Image:Keck Science Center Pepperdine.jpg|thumb|right|An example of Pepperdine's Mediterranean architecture, The Keck Science Center]]

The school placed 54th among the nation's &quot;Top 100&quot; law schools by the 2011 [[U.S. News and World Report]] rankings&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/law/brief/lawrank_brief.php Best Graduate Schools - Education - USNews&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and is the third highest ranked law school in Southern California. It is known for its [[entertainment law]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.top-law-schools.com/entertainment-law-schools.html Best Entertainment Law Schools and Sports Law Schools&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and also its [[Pepperdine_University_School_of_Law#Straus_Institute_for_Dispute_Resolution|dispute resolution program]], which is currently ranked No. 1 in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/law/brief/lawsp01_brief.php Best Graduate Schools - Education - USNews&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Graduate School of Education and Psychology===
With a focus on collaborative learning, leadership and academic excellence, the Pepperdine University Graduate School of Education and Psychology (GSEP) offers both masters and doctorate programs in education, educational technology, education administration, leadership, organizational change, organizational leadership, school counseling, psychology, and clinical psychology. Margaret Weber is the current dean.

===School of Public Policy===
Approximately 120 graduate students are enrolled in the [[Pepperdine School of Public Policy|Pepperdine University School of Public Policy]], which offers a two-year masters of public policy degree. Not simply the study of government, [[public policy]] is the study of how governments, non-profits, and even individuals and businesses address problems of public concern. Students specialize in economics, international relations, American politics, or local/regional policy in addition to their core studies and are required to complete a policy-related internship.

Joint degree programs include the MPP/Juris Doctor degree in conjunction with the [[Pepperdine University School of Law|School of Law]], the MPP/Masters of Dispute Resolution degree in conjunction with the School of Law's number one ranked [[Pepperdine_University_School_of_Law#Straus_Institute_for_Dispute_Resolution|Straus Institute for Dispute Resolution]] &lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/dispute-resolution&lt;/ref&gt; and the MPP/MBA degree in conjunction with the Graziadio School of Business and Management. 

Notable faculty at the School of Public Policy include: Ted McAllister, [[James Q. Wilson]], James Prieger (Senior Economic Advisor, FCC), Joel Fox, Angela Hawken, Gordon Lloyd and Robert Kaufman.

Notable graduates include at least one former member of the Bush Administration: Eryn Witcher, Director of Television.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepperdine.edu/pr/releases/2006/april/sppgraduation.htm Pepperdine University - School of Public Policy Celebrates 2006 Graduation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The current dean of the Public Policy School is James R. Wilburn.

==Presidents==
*[[Batsell Baxter]] (1937–39)
*[[Hugh M. Tiner]] (1939–57)
*[[M. Norvel Young]] (1957–71)
*[[William S. Banowsky]] (1971–78)
*[[Howard A. White]] (1978–85)
*[[David Davenport]] (1985–2000)
*[[Andrew K. Benton]] (2000–Present)

==Athletics==
{{main|Pepperdine Waves}}
[[Image:Pepperdine logo.png|thumb|130px|right|Pepperdine Waves Logo]]
Pepperdine University participates in the [[West Coast Conference]], a conference made up exclusively of religiously affiliated schools. Appropriate for its location adjacent to the Pacific Ocean, Pepperdine's teams are known as the Waves.

Pepperdine University was recently ranked by the [[NACDA Director's Cup|Sears Cup]] as having the most successful athletic program for non-[[American football|football]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] schools. ([[Stanford]] was ranked the most successful Division I athletic program with football.) Pepperdine University sponsors fourteen [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I intercollegiate athletics teams: baseball, basketball, cross country, golf, tennis, volleyball and water polo teams for men; and basketball, cross country, golf, soccer, swimming, tennis and volleyball for women. There are also a number of intercollegiate sports clubs such as men's soccer, men's and women's lacrosse, surf team, Ultimate Frisbee and men's rugby.

Pepperdine's Men's [[rugby football|Rugby]] Team, despite the small size of the school, has enjoyed great success since it was first initiated in 1955.  The recently storied 2010-2011 season is one their best seasons.  Under the helm of [[Robert Joseph Ahola]], the team went undefeated in the fall pre-season and established itself as a contender for the national tournament.  During the spring cup season, The Waves lost only one controversial match to [[Cal State Fullerton]], whom they had beaten earlier to become the 2011 Southern California Division 2 Champions.  The team qualified for the national championships tournament in San Diego where they beat the top D2 school from [[Texas]] and nationally 9th ranked [[Rice University]] in the sweet 16.  Despite not winning the national championship, The Waves finished among the top 8 at nationals--a first for the historic Rugby club.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Goff|first=Alex|title=Eight Left in DII Men College|url=http://rugbymag.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=532:eight-left-in-dii-men-college&amp;catid=51:mens-dii-college-&amp;Itemid=214}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

NCAA Division I Team Championships:
*Baseball (1992)
*Men's Golf (1997)
*Men's Tennis (2006)
*Men's Volleyball (1978, 1985, 1986, 1992, 2005)
*[[Water Polo]] (1997)

NCAA Division I Individual Titles:
*[[Robbie Weiss]] (1988 Tennis - Singles)
*[[Carlos Di Laura]] &amp; [[Kelly Jones (tennis)|Kelly Jones]] (1985 Tennis - Doubles)
*Jerome Jones &amp; Kelly Jones (1984 Tennis - Doubles)

==Notable alumni==
===Academia===
*[[Michael Shermer]] (B.S., 1976) - Founder of [[The Skeptics Society]]
*[[Christopher Chetsanga]] (1965), Professor at [[University of Zimbabwe]] that discovered two DNA repair enzymes
*[[Victoria Pynchon]] (Master of Law, 2006) - Writer, lecturer, mediator, adjunct law professor at Pepperdine University School of Law
*[[Paul Egertson]] (B.A., 1955) - Senior Lecturer and Adjunct Professor of Religion at [[California Lutheran University]]
*[[Mike Aamodt]] - [[industrial and organizational psychology]] professor at [[Radford University]]
*[[Michael A. O'Donnell (Author)|Michael A. O'Donnell]] (1976-77), Ph.D., author, and former Professor of Family Studies at [[Abilene Christian University]]

===Business===
* [[Neil Clark Warren]] (1956) - Chairman and Co-Founder of [[eHarmony.com]] [http://www.eharmony.com/about/team/board]
* [[Rod Menzies]] (MBA, 1988) - entrepreneur&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Coslovich | first=Gabriella | title=The art of the deal | date=23 January 2010 | publisher=The Age | url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/the-art-of-the-deal-20100122-mqrv.html | location=Melbourne}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Robert Tchenguiz]] (LL.B., 1982) - London-based Property Tycoon&lt;ref&gt;http://www.managementtoday.co.uk/channel/Finance/news/561465/the-imt-i-interview-robert-tchenguiz/ The MT Interview: Robert Tchenguiz&lt;/ref&gt;

===Entertainment===
*Lisa-Marie Kohrs - [[Miss World]] USA 2009 &lt;ref&gt;Wall Street Journal Photo of the Day http://blogs.wsj.com/photojournal/2009/11/09/photos-of-the-day-2/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Los Angeles Times: Sports Section Cover http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jun/21/sports/la-sp-world-cup-usa-fans-20100622/2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press - Sun City, South Africa http://www.daylife.com/photo/0gxq8di1L026D&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nedbank Golf Challenge Pro-AM http://www.golf.com/golf/gallery/article/0,28242,1940098-17,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Elite Model Management http://www.fashionmodeldirectory.com/models/Lisa-Marie_Kohrs/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press: Kohrs meets with South African President Jacob Zuma, Pretoria http://iplextra.indiatimes.com/photo/05Hmbwi1BDeZQ&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Variety's Children's Charity Gala, London - Surfboard Highest Bid http://southern-california-news-media-online-journalism-malibutimes.com/articles/2010/07/22/malibu_life/people/people7.txt&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Todd Matthew Burns]] - American film producer
* [[Marshall Colt]] - Actor, ''[[McClain's Law]]''; later marriage and family therapist in [[San Diego, California|San Diego]]
* [[Chace Crawford]] - Actor, ''[[Gossip Girl]]'' (TV series)
* [[Kim Fields]] (1995) - actress, U.S. TV sitcoms ''[[The Facts of Life (TV series)|The Facts of Life]]'' and ''[[Living Single]]''
* [[Kimberly Forsyth]] - [[Miss Arkansas USA]] 2006
* [[Madison Hildebrand]] - Star of Bravo Channel's &quot;[[Million Dollar Listing]]&quot;
* [[Darby Hinton]] - Actor, ''[[Daniel Boone (TV series)|Daniel Boone]]''
* [[Adam Housley]] - [[Fox News Channel]] Los Angeles correspondent, former [[Milwaukee Brewers]] and [[Detroit Tigers]] baseball player
* [[Ashley Jones]] - American actress
* [[Montell Jordan]] - R&amp;B recording artist famous for his hit 1990s single, &quot;This is How We Do It&quot;
* [[Tahj Mowry]] - Television actor best known for his role on [[the WB Television Network|the WB]]'s ''[[Smart Guy (TV series)|Smart Guy]]''
* [[Tia Mowry]] - Television actress best known for her role on ABC and The WB's ''[[Sister, Sister (TV series)|Sister, Sister]]'' and the BET's ''[[The Game (U.S. TV series)|The Game]]''
* [[Tamera Mowry]] - Television actress best known for her role on ABC's ''[[Sister, Sister (TV series)|Sister, Sister]]'' and Lifetime Television's ''[[Strong Medicine]]''
* [[Porntip Nakhirunkanok]] - Miss Universe 1988
* [[Brandy Norwood]] - R&amp;B artist and actress
* [[Eric Christian Olsen]] - American actor
* [[George Schlatter]] - Emmy-winning American television producer and director, best known for ''[[Rowan &amp; Martin's Laugh-In]]''
* [[Matt &quot;Money&quot; Smith]] - Southern California sports radio personality
* [[Clayton Snyder]] - Actor, on sitcom ''[[Lizzie McGuire]]''
* [[Bill Weir]] - Co-anchor of [[ABC News]] ''[[Nightline]]''
* [[Les Baxter]] - Soundtrack and exotica composer
* [[Kelly Hu]] - Miss Teen USA 1985 and Actress
* [[Cami Edwards]] - Cast member, ''[[Laguna Beach]]'
* [[Brittany Dawn Brannon]] - Miss Teen America 2007
* [[D.J. Caruso]] - Film Director

===Media===
*[[Adam Housley]] (B.A. 1994) -National Correspondent Fox News Channel, Emmy Winner
*[[Anna Song (journalist)|Anna Song]] (B.A., 1999) - [[KATU]] investigative reporter, weekend anchor (1999–present), 2007 Emmy for Human Interest News Series, 2007 Regional Edward R. Murrow award for investigative reporting.

===Politics and Government===
*[[Rod Blagojevich]] (J.D., 1983) - Former Governor of [[Illinois]], 2003–2009
*[[Henry Burns]], (M.A.) - Member of the [[Louisiana State Legislature|Louisiana House of Representatives]] since January 14, 2008
*[[Talis Colberg]] (J.D., 1983) - Attorney General, State of Alaska
*[[James Hahn]] (J.D., 1975) - [[Los Angeles]] Mayor, 2001–2005
*[[Janice Hahn]] - [[U.S.]] [[Congresswoman]] from [[California]], since [[California's 36th congressional district special election, 2011|July 19, 2011]]
*[[Theodore Kanavas]] - Wisconsin State Senator, 33rd District
*[[Joel Kleefisch]], 1993, Wisconsin State Assembly
*[[Jami Miscik]] (1980) - Director of the Office of International Affairs, [[CIA]]{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}
*[[Bernard C. Parks]] - Los Angeles City Councilman, 8th District, former Los Angeles Police Chief
*[[Todd Russell Platts]] (J.D., 1991) - [[U.S.]] [[Congressman]] from [[Pennsylvania]], 2001–Present
*[[Pierre-Richard Prosper|Amb. Pierre-Richard Prosper]] (J.D., 1989) - United States Ambassador-at-Large for War Crimes Issues
*[[Robin Sax]] {J.D., 1997}- Author, legal analyst, victim advocate, former prosecutor for Los Angeles County District Attorney's Office
* [[Arthur K. Snyder]], Los Angeles City Council member, 1967–85
*[[Michelle Park Steel]] - Board Member, California Board of Equalization, 2006–Present

===Sports===
[[File:DiawaraHeat.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Yakhouba Diawara]]]]
[[File:Brad Gilbert.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Brad Gilbert]]]]
[[File:Noah Lowry.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Noah Lowry]]]]
*[[Alex Acker]] (2005) – Professional basketball player (2005–06; 2008–09 [[Detroit Pistons]], [[Los Angeles Clippers]])
*[[Brandon Armstrong]] (2001) – Former professional basketball player (2001–04; [[New Jersey Nets]])
*[[Dain Blanton]] (1994) – 2000 Olympic Gold Medalist in Beach Volleyball
*[[Paul Carroll]] (2009) – Australian Men's National Volleyball Team
*[[Doug Christie (basketball)|Doug Christie]] (1992) – Retired professional basketball player (1992–2007; [[Los Angeles Lakers]], [[New York Knicks]], [[Toronto Raptors]], [[Sacramento Kings]], [[Orlando Magic]], [[Dallas Mavericks]] &amp; [[Los Angeles Clippers]])
*[[Ricardo Brown]](1980) – basketball player drafted in 1979 by Houston Rockets; Southern California Player of the Year in 1979; Played professional basketball in the Philippine Basketball Association (1983–90); member of PBA Hall of Fame (2009) and Pepperdine University Hall of Fame (1995)
*[[Bob Ctvrtlik]] (1985) – 1988 Olympic Gold Medal Volleyball Team Member, Member of International Olympic Committee
*[[Richard Cho]] – Former General Manager of Portland Trail Blazers.
*[[Yakhouba Diawara]] (2005) – Power Forward for the [[Miami Heat]]
*[[Barry Enright]] (2007) – Pitcher for the [[Arizona Diamondbacks]].
*[[Jim Everett]] - Former [[NFL]] QB. Received his [[MBA]] from Pepperdine.
*[[Mike Fetters]] – Former professional baseball player (1989–2004; [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim|California Angels]], [[Milwaukee Brewers]], [[Oakland Athletics]], [[Baltimore Orioles]], [[Los Angeles Dodgers]], [[Pittsburgh Pirates]], [[Arizona Diamondbacks]] &amp; [[Minnesota Twins]])
*[[Greg Genske]] – sports agent
*[[Brad Gilbert]] (1982) – Former professional tour tennis player; prominent coach, of [[Andre Agassi|Andre Agassi's]], [[Andy Murray]]
*[[Jason Gore]] (2000) – Professional golfer
*[[Dan Haren]] – Professional baseball player; 2007 A.L. All Star Starting Pitcher ([[Arizona Diamondbacks]])
*[[Ginger Helgeson-Nielsen]] – Former professional tennis player who holds the all-time match winning percentage at Pepperdine&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pepperdinesports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=18500&amp;ATCLID=204885501|title=Ten of Pepperdine's Female Greats Honored by WCC}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Adam Housley]] (1994) – Former professional minor league baseball player. Drafted by the Montreal Expos
*[[Katherine Hull]] (2003) – Professional golfer
*[[Daniel Johnson (basketball)|Daniel Johnson]] (2008) - Professional basketball player ([[Adelaide 36ers]], [[National Basketball League (Australia)|Australian NBL]])
*[[Dennis Johnson]] (1976) – Former professional basketball player (1977–90; [[Seattle Supersonics]], [[Phoenix Suns]] &amp; [[Boston Celtics]])
*[[Chad Kreuter]] – Former professional baseball player (1988–2003; [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]], [[Detroit Tigers]], [[Seattle Mariners]], [[Chicago White Sox]], [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim|Anaheim Angels]], [[Kansas City Royals]] &amp; [[Los Angeles Dodgers]])
*[[Jennifer Lacy]] – Female Professional Basketball Player [[Phoenix Mercury]] &amp; [[Atlanta Dream]]
*[[Martin Laurendeau]] – Former professional tour tennis player
*[[Mike Leach (coach)|Mike Leach]] – Texas Tech head football coach 2000–2009
*[[Noah Lowry]] – Professional baseball player ([[San Francisco Giants]])
*[[Glenn Michibata]] – Former professional tour tennis player
*[[Merrill Moses]] (2000) – Water polo goalie for USA National Team (2008 Olympic Silver Medalist)
*[[David Newhan]] – Professional baseball player ([[Houston Astros]])
*[[Will Ohman]] – Professional baseball player ([[Los Angeles Dodgers]])
*[[Rob Picciolo]] – Former professional baseball player (1977–85; [[Oakland Athletics]], [[Milwaukee Brewers]] &amp; [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim|California Angels]]) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/p/picciro01.shtml Baseballreference.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Steve Rodriguez (baseball)|Steve Rodriguez]], major league infielder for the [[Boston Red Sox]] and [[Detroit Tigers]], and a player and head coach for the Waves baseball team.
*[[Sean Rooney]] (2004) – USA Men's National Volleyball Team (2008 Gold Medalist)
*[[Dane Sardinha]] – Professional Baseball Player ([[Detroit Tigers]]).
*[[Mike Scott (baseball)|Mike Scott]] – Former professional baseball player (1979–91; [[New York Mets]] &amp; [[Houston Astros]]) &amp; winner of the 1986 NL [[Cy Young Award]]
*[[Jesse A. Smith]] USA Mens Water Polo Olympic Team 2000, 2004, 2008. (2008 Olympic Silver Medalist)
*[[Andy Stankiewicz]] – Former professional baseball player (1992–98; [[New York Yankees]], [[Houston Astros]], [[Montreal Expos]] &amp; [[Arizona Diamondbacks]])
*[[Andrew Sznajder]] – Former professional tour tennis player
*[[Derek Wallace]] – Former professional baseball player (1996–99; [[New York Mets]] &amp; [[Kansas City Royals]]){{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}
*[[Robbie Weiss]] – Former professional tennis player
*[[Randy Wolf]] – Professional baseball player
*[[Danny Worth]] – Professional baseball player ([[Detroit Tigers]])

==Notable faculty==

* [[Allen Fox]] (born 1939), tennis player (ranked as high as # 4) and coach

==Rankings and reputation==
The ''[[Princeton Review]]'' ranked Pepperdine on the list of colleges with &quot;Dorms Like Palaces&quot; in 2004 and 2007 and #1 under &quot;Most Beautiful Campus&quot; in 2006 and 2007. Pepperdine also appeared on other lists including &quot;Students Pray on a Regular Basis,&quot; and &quot;High Quality of Life.&quot; Because of its Christian affiliation, some contend that the student body breeds a religious and politically conservative atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.townhall.com/columnists/MikeSAdams/2006/12/11/colleges_to_attend,_part_i Townhall.com::Colleges to Attend, Part I::By Mike S. Adams&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Princeton Review also ranked Pepperdine University #13 in its list &quot;Alternative Lifestyles not an Alternative&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/rankings/rankingDetails.asp?CategoryID=2&amp;TopicID=25 Register for The Princeton Review&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007 Pepperdine was named as &quot;One of the Top Producing Colleges and Universities&quot; by the [[Peace Corps of America]]. The 2005 edition of the ''[[Fiske Guide to Colleges]]'' has also noted Pepperdine as being one of the nation's largest conservative colleges. ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' (see “Pepperdine at Glance” in the external links section) has ranked Pepperdine as the 53rd best national university for undergraduate education. It is also ranked one of the 10 worst party schools  in the county. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/chi-ap-us-partyschools-list,0,4615411.story?page=2 Top party, sober schools from Princeton Review] Chicago Tribune, August 1, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Pepperdine University School of Law|School of Law]] placed 52nd among the nation's &quot;Top 100&quot; law schools by the 2011 [[U.S. News and World Report]] rankings&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/law/brief/lawrank_brief.php Best Graduate Schools - Education - USNews&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and is the third highest ranked law school in Southern California. It is known for its entertainment law,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.top-law-schools.com/entertainment-law-schools.html Best Entertainment Law Schools and Sports Law Schools&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and also its [[Pepperdine_University_School_of_Law#Straus_Institute_for_Dispute_Resolution|dispute resolution program]], which is currently ranked No. 1 in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/law/brief/lawsp01_brief.php Best Graduate Schools - Education - USNews&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, US News ranked Pepperdine's business school tied with Santa Clara University at 82 in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-business-schools/rankings/page+3  US News Rankings &lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  It ranked its part-time program 9th best in California.&lt;ref&gt;[http://premium.usnews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-business-schools/part-time  Part-time Program Rankings &lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Forbes'' magazine has ranked the Graziadio School's Fully Employed MBA programs in the world's Top 20 based on ROI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/2005/08/16/best-business-schools-list-cz_05mba_land.html | work=Forbes | title=Best Business Schools | date=August 18, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}  In 2008, the magazine ''In Tune'' for music educators named Pepperdine one of the 38 best music schools in the United States.  In 2009, the Sustainable Endowments Institute awarded Pepperdine a &quot;C&quot; for its sustainability efforts in the annual College Sustainability Report Card.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2009/schools/pepperdine-university&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Nickelodeon (network)|Nickelodeon]] series, ''[[Zoey 101]]'' was shot on Pepperdine's Malibu campus. Pepperdine signs were covered with trendy, purple signs reading &quot;Pacific Coast Academy&quot;, the name of the boarding school attended by the students on the show.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Los Angeles|University}}
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.pepperdine.edu/ Official Website]
*[http://www.pepperdinesports.com/ Official Pepperdine Athletics Website]
* [http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_1264_brief.php Pepperdine Review] – ''U.S. News &amp; World Report'', “Pepperdine at Glance”
* [http://www.businessweek.com/bschools/04/full_time_profiles/pepperdine.htm Pepperdine Graziadio School of Business and Management] – ''Business Week'' Review

&lt;!----&gt;

{{West Coast Conference}}
{{Church of Christ Colleges}}
{{Colleges and universities in Los Angeles County}}

{{Coord|34|02|19.26|N|118|42|27.29|W|region:US-CA_type:edu_source:dewiki|display=title}}

[[Category:Malibu, California]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1937]]
[[Category:Pepperdine University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the Churches of Christ]]
[[Category:Independent Colleges of Southern California]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Seminaries and theological colleges in California]]
[[Category:Business schools in California]]
[[Category:Schools accredited by the Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]

[[de:Pepperdine University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه پپرداین]]
[[fr:Université Pepperdine]]
[[ko:페퍼다인 대학교]]
[[nl:Pepperdine-universiteit]]
[[ja:ペパーダイン大学]]
[[no:Pepperdine University]]
[[pt:Universidade Pepperdine]]
[[sv:Pepperdine University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
