<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4247222" ns="0" title="Symbiosis Law School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college 
| name                  = Symbiosis Law School, Pune
| image_name            = Logo of Symbiosis International University.svg
| motto                 = Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam
| mottoeng              = The world is one family
| established           = 1977
| type                  = Private
| academic_affiliation = [[Symbiosis International University]]
| director             = Dr. Shashikala Gurpur&lt;ref name=&quot;principal&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Venkatesan|first=J|title=Centre appoints members to Law Commission |url=http://www.hindu.com/2010/08/04/stories/2010080461160600.htm|accessdate=4 November 2010|newspaper=The Hindu|date=4 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| city                  = Pune
| former_names          = Symbiosis Society's Law College
| website               = {{URL|http://www.symlaw.ac.in}}
}}
'''Symbiosis Law School, Pune''' originally known as Symbiosis Society's Law College, was established in 1977 under the banner of [[Symbiosis Society]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.set-test.org/symbiosis_law_school.html&lt;/ref&gt; under the patronage of Dr. S. B. Mujumdar, President &amp; Founder Director, it is registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 and the Bombay Public Trust, Act,1950.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.symlaw.ac.in/&lt;/ref&gt; Symbiosis Law School, earlier known as Symbiosis Society's Law College, is a constituent college of the [[Symbiosis International University]]. It is situated in Senapati Bapat Road, [[Pune]] in a campus shared with [[Symbiosis School of Economics]], [[Symbiosis Institute of Health Sciences]], [[Symbiosis Arts and Commerce College]] and [[Symbiosis College of Nursing]].

Symbiosis Law School, Pune has been ranked fifth and sixth of India Today and Outlook's ranking respectively.[[Outlook_(magazine)|Outlook]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?265893&lt;/ref&gt; and [[India Today]]&lt;ref&gt;http://indiatoday.intoday.in/site/Photo/3310/3/best-law-colleges-in-india,-2010.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student organizations==
Active clubs and societies of Symbiosis Law School, Pune include the Human Rights Cell (HRC), The Environment Protection and Consumer Rights Organization (Ecocon),  Legal Aid and Literacy Cell, Tech Legal Cell, Alumni Cell, Corporate Cell, Law Hawks Forum, International Cell - ILSA, Sports Committee, Law and Economics cell(LAWECON) and the Moot Court Society (MCS), Student Council.

==Symbhav - Cultural Fest==
The students of Symbiosis Law School, Pune started Symbhav – a Cultural Fest in February 2009 followed by an extremely successful edition in 2010. Since its inception in 2009, it had a wonderful beginning with a participation of 20 teams from all over the country and SAARC Nations including leading National Law Schools and a sponsorship of Rs. 10 Lakhs. In 2010, the fest grew bigger with a sponsorship of Rs. 15 Lakhs and a participation of 15 outstation teams and 200 participants.  This year, Symbhav was a grand success with a sponsorship of Rs. 42 Lakhs in cash and Rs. 9 Lakhs in kind. Symbhav’11 received an overwhelming response all over the country as well as the SAARC Nations with participation in various literary, legal events as well as music, arts and sports. 

==Faculty ==
Dr. Shashikala Gurpur, Director, Symbiosis Law School, Pune and the Dean, Faculty of Law, Symbiosis International University, has a PhD in ‘International Law’ and a rich blend of academics, research and industry brings in a well-rounded insight into the academics &amp; research at the Law Faculty. Dr. Gurpur is a Part-Time Member of the 19th Law Commission of India, Govt. of India, and also Consultant to National Commission for Women. With an illustrious background of teaching at several other universities and a passion for teaching &amp; research, she drives innovative programmes &amp; research projects.

Symbiosis Law School, Pune has 26 full-time faculty members which include 2 Professors, 3 Associate Professors, 20 Assistant Professors, 1 Teaching Associate and 1 Adjunct Faculty. 

All the faculty members are experienced, qualified with Post graduate degrees. 13 faculty members are NET/SET qualified and 5 faculty members are Ph. D. holder. Further, 9 faculty members have registered for Ph.D. 

The faculty members are also involved in various research projects. Some of them have also visited Leibniz University of Hannover, Germany under Erasmus Mundus and DAAD (German Academic Exchange Service) exchange programs. The faculty member has also received the ICCR Rotating Chair Research Fellowship from Government of India in association with Leibniz University of Hannover, Germany.

Faculty members have also attended various national &amp; international seminars, conferences and workshops.

==Internationalization==
SLS is conferred with the honor of being a core partner in the global network of legal institutes, the Erasmus Mundus, DAAD (German Academic Exchange Service) – a grant for bilateral exchange with Leibniz University of Hannover, Germany, membership of International Association of Law Schools (IALS), USA, Asian Law Institute, Singapore and Association of Commonwealth Universities (ACU). 

==Community Services==
Symbiosis Law School, Pune has a Legal Care and Literacy Centre for Providing Legal Aid to the community. The students of SLS, Pune actively participates in such activities. The following are some of the highlights of the Community Services of SLS, Pune:

*Community Lawyering and Legal Aid – in Collaboration with CLRN, CUNY School of Law, USA
*Legal Aid Centre has been set up in Pirangut Village to provide legal aid to the villagers 
*Created Rs. 20 Lacs Corpus Fund with kind assistance from Symbiosis Foundation &amp;  Adv. Ram Jethmalani  for Community Legal Service
*Lecture Series in Pirangut by experts on alternate Saturdays.
*Socio-Legal Survey in progress
*Service Learning as part of curricular activities to groom the students.
*Outreach program: Inter-institute expertise sharing
*Proposal to train Police sent, approval awaited from Government of India
*Legal Aid Camps and Legal literacy activities
*Created Legal Resource Network
*Collaboration with SOFOSH (Society of Friends of the Sassoon Hospitals) to provide legal aid
*Make a Difference’ – Human Rights Cell
*Collaboration with other NGOs like Alert, Saheli, PCGT.

==Centres of Excellence==
Symbiosis Law School has set up six Centres of Excellence in Public Law &amp; Governance, Private Laws, Transnational &amp; Global Legal Studies, Corporate Laws, Justice Education and Technology &amp; Innovation Laws, to promote research activities. Under these Centres of Excellence, many research projects are being carried out, such as Community Legal Care, Legal aid activities, Microsoft IPR Chair, Prisoner’s Rights, Law Reform Projects on Common Property with NLSIU, Bangalore &amp; Compensation for rape victims with National Commission for Women alongside supportive research for Law Commission of India. IPC handbook, book research on Feminist Jurisprudence, Legal Regulation of Biotechnology and Educational Laws are other initiatives.

==In-house Journals ==
;Symbiosis Contemporary Law Journal

It is a revamped journal of Symbiosis Law School, Pune which has replaced the erstwhile journals of the Law School – Symbiosis Law Times and Journal of Symbiosis Law School. It is an attempt to bring the issues which are contemporary to legal education in the country in the fields of Constitutional Law, Corporate Laws and the recent regulations. It is an annual publication and an endeavour to provide momentum to the spread of quality legal education.

;Symbiosis Journal of Comparative and International Legal Studies

This journal is a new addition to the in-house publication of Symbiosis Law School, Pune. This annual publication is an endeavour to act as a medium of exchanging ideas and perceptions for international academicians as well as Indian academicians and to express and share their expertise in the fields of Environmental Law, Comparative Law, European Union Law and various legislations of US, UK, EU, Asia. 

;Symbiosis Journal of Innovation and Law

The erstwhile journal ‘IPR Chronicle’ of Symbiosis Law School, Pune has been renamed as ‘Symbiosis Journal of Innovation and Law’. This journal intends to reflect thought provoking articles in Intellectual Property Rights, Innovations in Technology and Medico-Legal fields. In this era of globalization, IPR, Technology &amp; Medico-Legal fields have come out as an inevitable development. This annual publication thus, aims at being a platform for discussion &amp; expressing views on the innovations in the above mentioned areas of law.

;Symbiosis Student Law Review

It is another new addition to the in-house publication of Symbiosis law School, Pune, which has been fully dedicated to students. Its main purpose is to provide a platform for the students of the Law Schools of the country to express and share their views and expertise in various fields of law. This annual journal aims at encouraging students for research and to publish their research articles, essays and conference papers as a part of this journal.

;Lex-Et Symbiosis - Newsletter

It is a bi-annual newsletter of Symbiosis Law School, Pune which provides updates on various campus activities and encompasses all the events that takes place in the Law School. It also provides legal awareness towards latest happenings in the legal field.

== Admissions ==
Admission for Undergraduate Programmes is through Symbiosis Entrance Test (SET)which is a common written test for the admission processes of Undergraduate Institutes of Symbiosis International University (SIU). The Entrance Test is followed by Group Exercise and Personal Interview which makes Symbiosis Law School, Pune, the first Law School to adopt admission through these steps.

==Programmes==

===Under Graduate===
B.A. L.L.B. and B.B.A. L.L.B., 5 years integrated programme: Both the Undergraduate Programs aim at creating profound legal experts with life skills, employability skills, values, knowledge and research expertise. 

B.B.A. L.L.B. - SLS has been one of the pioneers in India, in introducing B.B.A., LL.B. programme. Since this Programme caters to the growing needs of corporate sector and enhances chances of placement, it has proved its credibility with the students and the industry. It encompasses advanced technical knowledge of law coupled with fundamentals of business management. Apart from the basic and applied law courses, the programme provides in-depth inputs on a range of management courses such as Fundamentals of Business Organization, Managerial Economics, Principles and Practices of Management, Accounting, Human Resource and Total Quality Management, Organizational Behavior and Business and Managerial Communication.

B.A. L.L.B. - The objective of the Programme is to create lawyers with the in-depth knowledge of law with background disciplines such as Economics, Political Science, History, Public Administration, Sanskrit and other foreign languages. The programme aims at producing sentinels of justice with social sensitivity, integrity and ethics.

===Post-Graduate programs===
The L.L.M. programme with an interdisciplinary approach with five specializations in the study of law and research orientation by underlining the relevance of research methodology. The student has the option of a cafeteria approach in terms of specialization, cross specialization courses combining innovation, cutting edge legal acumen and theoretical insights

===Diploma===
There are fifteen Part-time one year Diploma Programs and one Post-Graduate Diploma Programme available as value-addition. Many students pursue these programs alongside their Undergraduate or Masters Program.

===Certificate Programs===
There are nine certificate programs which include the much-acclaimed Certificate in European Legal Studies and Certificate in Securities Laws, among others

===Ph.D.===
Symbiosis Law School, Pune, conducts the Ph.D. programme under the Faculty of Law, Symbiosis International University from the Academic Year 2010-11. A Pre-Ph.D. Coursework is conducted for six-seven months for the registered candidates who are selected on the basis of their performance in the Entrance Test conducted for Ph.D. by the University.

==Achievements==
===By Faculty===
*Dr. Shashikala Gurpur, Director, SLS Pune, received the first ever 'Legal Education Innovation Award' conferred by Society of Indian Law Firms (SILF) and Menon Institute of Legal Advocacy &amp; Training (MILAT).
*Dr. Shashikala Gurpur has been appointed as the Part-Time member of Law Commission of India and as Advisory Board member of School of Law, IGNOU.
*Prof. Asawari Abhyankar and Prof. S. C. Hajare, visited Leibniz, University of Hannover, Germany in April 2010 and in November 2010 respectively, under the DAAD grant.
*Prof. S. C. Hajare has been conferred with Ph. D. Degree.
*Prof. Yuvraj Patil guided two entries in National Level Legal Research Competition on Common Property at NLSIU, Bangalore, which won 2nd Prize.
*Dr. Bindu Ronald is currently in Leibniz University of Hannover Germany under the Erasmus Mundus Research Grant in April 2011 for three months.
*Prof. Rupal Rautdesai visited Leibniz University of Hannover Germany, in May 2011 for one week under the DAAD grant.
*Abhijit Vasmatkar received the prestigious ICCR Rotating Chair Fellowship, from Government of India in association with Leibniz University of Hannover, Germany and visited Germany for six months from November 2010 to May 2011.

===By Students===
*Sweden India Nobel Memorial Quiz winners 2010-11. SLS team composed of Raghav N. C., Sachin Ravi and George Mathew
*Runners up in 5th International Law Competition &amp; 6th International Law Competition, ‘Youth for Peace’ held in Minsk, Belarus in 2010 and 2011 respectively. Team of three students of Symbiosis Law School, Pune participated in the competition for two consecutive years 
*Sports: SPIRITUS 2010 - Overall Champion

==Placements==

With cut throat competition among the law schools rising year after year, placements have occupied a vital position in this race. Campus Recruitments have gone on to become a decisive factor for colleges to be at the apex.

Symbiosis Law School, Pune in this endeavour has left no stone unturned to secure bright future for its spanking legal minds. We at SLS have a full-fledged student cum faculty body working towards placements as well as internship opportunities available in the national as well as the international legal arena.

The Cell working round the year organizes guest lectures, workshops and training sessions for the students enabling them to have an edge in the legal doyen.

Having had a successful academic year 2010-2011, the Cell had managed to secure jobs for a comprehensive portion of the final year Batch. Besides this, the internship cycle is moving on in full swing and numerous students are gaining on field experience during their midterm vacations. 

Industrial experience has gone on to become an indispensable element in a law student’s journey. The Cell, in this endeavour has made all possible efforts in bringing corporate giants to the thresh hold of Symbiosis Law School, Pune.

==See also==
* [[Symbiosis Society]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* http://www.symlaw.ac.in
* http://www.symbhav.org

{{Symbiosis Society}}
{{Autonomous law schools in India}}
{{Pune topics}}

{{coord missing|Maharashtra}}

[[Category:Law schools in Maharashtra]]
[[Category:Education in Pune]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pune]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
