<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4266031" ns="0" title="Marymount College, Tarrytown"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University 
|name           = Marymount College of Fordham University
|image          = [[Image:Marymount-seal.png|Marymount College Seal]] 
|motto          = Tua Luce Dirige: &quot;Guide Us By Your Light&quot; (college); Sapientia et Doctrina &quot;Wisdom and Learning&quot; (university)
|established    = 1907; Fordham University acquisition: 2002
|closure        = June 2007
|type           = [[Private school|Private]], [[Independent school|Independent]] 
|president      = [[Joseph M. McShane, S.J.]] (last)
|city           = [[Tarrytown, New York|Tarrytown]] 
|state          = [[New York]] 
|country        = [[United States|USA]] 
|undergrad      = 798
|postgrad       = 
|staff          = 
|campus         = [[Suburban area|Suburb]], {{convert|25|acre|m2}}
|mascot         = Marymount Saints (college), [[Bighorn sheep|Ram]] (university) 
|colors         = Blue and White; Maroon and White 
|endowment      = $6,126,000 
|website        = [http://www.fordham.edu/ www.fordham.edu]
|closure        = June 2007
}}

'''Marymount College of Fordham University''' was a [[women's college]] in the [[United States]], eventually to become part of [[Fordham University]].  The Marymount campus was located in [[Tarrytown, New York]]. Enrollment peaked at 1,112 in 1978,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lohud.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070831/NEWS02/708310406&lt;/ref&gt; but by 2004 it enrolled 844 students. The last class graduated in 2007, and the campus was sold in 2008.

The college was founded as an independent girls' boarding school in 1907 by the [[Religious of the Sacred Heart of Mary]] (R.S.H.M.). Mother Marie Joseph Butler founded the institution to &quot;create a place of learning where women could grow and where they could receive an education that would prepare them for positions of leadership and influence in the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/Academics/Colleges__Graduate_S/Undergraduate_Colleg/Marymount_College_of/Womens_College/index.html Fordham.Edu&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Early courses at Marymount ranged from courses in [[domestic science]] to classes offered in [[political science]] and [[law]]. In 1924, Marymount became one of the first women's colleges in the United States to offer a study abroad program. Students studied at major universities in London, Madrid, Paris, and Rome, living at Marymount schools ([[Kingston upon Thames|London]], [http://www.ecole-marymount.fr/ Paris], [http://www.marymountrome.com/ Rome]).

Marymount College at Tarrytown was the first of several colleges founded by the RSHM ([[Marymount colleges]]). Several of these still exist, including [[Marymount Manhattan]], [[Marymount University]], and [[Loyola Marymount]]. Marymount College is mentioned in &quot;Valhalla Rising&quot; by Clive Cussler.

'''Original Motto''': Tua Luce Dirige (Direct Us By Thy Light)

'''Original Mascot''': The Saints

'''Original Colors''': Blue and White

==Acquisition and closure by Fordham University==
[[Image:Marymountseal.png|left|350px|thumb|Marymount College of Fordham University seal]]
In July 2002, Marymount officially consolidated with Fordham University, renaming the college as the Marymount College of Fordham University and becoming the institution's fifth undergraduate school. In 2005, Fordham University announced its plans to close the women's college effective June 2007 but to keep the campus, which it renamed the [[Marymount campus#Tarrytown|Marymount campus]], active as a center for graduate studies.  Most of the 798 Marymount students were to finish their education at the {{convert|25|acre|m2|sing=on}} Tarrytown, N.Y., campus, which was permanently to be known as the Marymount Campus of Fordham University - pending the University's decision of its plans to sell, or keep the property. The [[Westchester County, New York|Westchester]] division of the multi-campus Fordham College of Liberal Studies, already housed at the campus, would continue and expand its [[liberal arts]] program. Fordham announced that over time, the professional school programs in [[business administration]], [[social service]] and [[education]] would move their Westchester operations to the Marymount Campus. 

In the press release announcing the phase out, the Board of Trustees of Fordham emphasized that Marymount juniors and seniors who graduated by spring 2007 would complete their degrees at Marymount College (and receive a Fordham degree and diploma), while freshmen and sophomores would complete their degrees in programs offered at one of the other four undergraduate colleges of Fordham University, if they indeed decided to remain at Fordham. The Marymount Sisters, are to remain in the residences they occupied at the closing of the school, although their teaching positions no longer existed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/17/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/17collegewe.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin Marymount Being Sold; Village to Gain Taxes - New York Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
The final class of 203 women graduated in May, 2007, 45 of whom attended the university commencement ceremonies. [http://www.fordham.edu/Campus_Resources/Public_Affairs/topstories_895.asp]

In August, 2007, Fordham announced it would sell the Marymount campus, to the disappointment of many alumnae since the University had purchased the college with the promise that it would try to continue to operate it as a women's institution.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lohud.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070831/NEWS02/708310377&lt;/ref&gt;. The University claimed unjustifiable and disproportionate costs to maintain the large campus as reason for closure. On February 17, 2008, Fordham announced the sale of the campus for $27 million to  [[EF Education]], a chain of private language-instruction schools.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Fordham U. Sells Marymount College Campus for $27-Million&quot; ''Chronicle of Higher Education'' Feb. 17, 2008 [http://chronicle.com/news/article/3982/fordham-u-sells-marymount-college-campus-for-27-million link]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumnae==
*[[Joyce F. Brown]], President, [[Fashion Institute of Technology]]
*[[Patricia Gaffney]], bestselling author
*[[Karen Kopins]], actress
*[[Susan Lucci]], actress
*[[Ann Dore McLaughlin]] (Ann McLaughlin Korologos), businesswoman and politician
*[[Anne M. Mulcahy]], Chairman and CEO, [[Xerox]]
*[[Rosalind Russell]], actress (left sophomore year)

==See also==
*[[Marymount colleges]]

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20011128090531/http://www.marymt.edu/ Marymount College website, 2001], [http://web.archive.org/web/19970515013014/http://www.marymt.edu/index.html 1997], preserved at The Internet Archive
*[http://www.fordham.edu Fordham University]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/21/nyregion/21marymount.html?ex=1337400000&amp;en=c4c5c60513c5dbf4&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss New York Times: At Marymount Graduation, a Centennial, and a Farewell]
*[http://www.nynews.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070608/NEWS01/706080389 Journal News: Marymount timeline: A century of women's education]
*[http://www.nyjournalnews.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070608/NEWS01/706080381 Journal News: Marymount women's college becomes 'victim' of its own success]
*[http://www.nynews.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070611/OPINION/706110313/1151 Journal News: Graduation Gleanings]
*[http://www.lohud.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070831/NEWS02/708310377 Journal News: Fordham to sell Marymount campus]
*[http://www.nynews.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070831/NEWS02/708310406 Journal News: Marymount History: a Timeline]

{{coord missing|New York}}

[[Category:Tarrytown, New York]]
[[Category:Former Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Former women's universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Fordham University]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1907]]
[[Category:Educational institutions disestablished in 2007]]
[[Category:Schools in Westchester County, New York]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
