<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="42730" ns="0" title="Emory University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name=Emory University
|image_name= Emory University Seal.png
|caption= The seal of Emory University
|motto= ''Cor prudentis possidebit scientiam''
|mottoeng= The wise heart seeks knowledge
|established=1836
|type=[[Private university|Private]]
|affiliation = [[United Methodist Church]]&lt;ref name=&quot;William Joseph Whalen - Hospitals &amp; Universities&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=sw9ILcqw2hsC&amp;pg=PA162&amp;lpg=PA162&amp;dq=salvation+of+separated+brethren&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ydrVxGCZ6w&amp;sig=L_-DZRvpoMtZSDkrT6HNQcmd4aU&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xfSvS52yE4faNZX_zJkF&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CA0Q6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=methodist&amp;f=false| title = Separated brethren: a review of Protestant, Anglican, Eastern Orthodox &amp; other religions in the United States|quote=Among Protestant denominations, Methodists take first place in hospitals and colleges. Some of their one hundred colleges and universities have all but severed ties with the denominations, but others remain definitely Methodist: Syracuse, Boston, Emory, Duke, Drew, Denver, and Southern Methodist. The church operates three hundred sixty schools and institutions overseas. Methodists established Goodwill Industries in 1907 to help handicapped persons help themselves by repairing and selling old furniture and clothes. The United Methodist Church runs seventy-two hospitals in the United States.|publisher = [[Our Sunday Visitor]]|accessdate = 2010-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;General Board of Higher Education &amp; Ministry&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.gbhem.org/site/c.lsKSL3POLvF/b.5392245/k.60B4/Schools_by_Jurisdiction.htm#S.Eastern| title =
Schools by Jurisdiction|publisher = [[United Methodist Church]]|accessdate = 2009–11–26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|calendar = Semester
|president=[[James W. Wagner]]
|city=[[Druid Hills, Georgia|Druid Hills]]&lt;!--It is NOT in the Atlanta city limits. Despite the fact that Druid Hills is not a city, it is a census designated place and a substantial populated community. Also, the &quot;city field&quot; does not reflect what the USPS mailing address city name says. Do not change!--&gt; 
|state=[[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]
|country= US|coor={{Coord|33|47|28|N|84|19|24|W|type:edu_region:US-GA|display=inline,title}}
|students=13,893&lt;ref name=&quot;Emory University website&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/factsfigures/index.html#students|accessdate=2011-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad=7,441
|postgrad=6,452
|campus=[[Suburb]]an&lt;br /&gt;631 acres (2.6 km²)
|nickname=Emory Eagles
|colors=Blue and Gold {{color box|#000066}}{{color box|#CC9900}}
|endowment=[[United States dollar|US $]]5.3 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.emory.edu/EMORY_REPORT/stories/2011/09/take_note_update_endowment.html| title=Campus News | publisher=Emory University | accessdate=2011-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|athletics = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]] [[University Athletic Association|UAA]]
|affiliations = [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]], [[Association of American Universities|AAU]]
|website= [http://www.emory.edu/ Emory.edu]
|logo=[[Image:Emory U Logo.svg]]
}}
'''Emory University''' is a [[private university|private]] [[research university]] in [[Greater Atlanta|metropolitan Atlanta]], located in the [[Druid Hills, Georgia|Druid Hills]] section&lt;!--The name of the CDP must be mentioned in the lead--&gt; of [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]]&lt;!--Have to say unincorporated to make clear that it is not in any city--&gt; [[DeKalb County, Georgia|DeKalb County]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[United States]].&lt;!--Cited below--&gt; The university was founded as Emory College in [[1836]] in [[Oxford, Georgia]] by a small group of [[Methodists]] and was named in honor of Methodist bishop [[John Emory]]. A land-grant by [[Asa Griggs Candler|Asa Candler]], the president of [[The Coca-Cola Company]], allowed the small college to move to metropolitan Atlanta in 1915 and become rechartered as Emory University. The university's mission statement is &quot;to create, preserve, teach, and apply knowledge in the service of humanity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emory.edu/president/governance/mission_statement.html |title=University Mission Statement |publisher=Emory University |year=2010 |accessdate=2010-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory is ranked 20th among national universities in the ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: National University Rankings|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/rankings/national-universities|accessdate=10/11/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;   ''[[Newsweek]]'' named it one of its 25 &quot;New Ivies&quot; in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2006/08/20/25-new-ivies.html |title=America's New Elite &quot;Ivies&quot; |publisher=Newsweek |date=2006-08-21 |accessdate=2010-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university has nearly 3,000 faculty members; awards and honors recognizing Emory faculty include the Nobel Prize, the Pulitzer Prize, National Humanities Medal, Guggenheim Fellowship, Fulbright Fellowship, and membership in the American Academy of Arts &amp; Sciences and the National Academy of Sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/rankings-successes/distinguished-professors.html|accessdate=2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The university has nine academic divisions: Emory College of Arts and Sciences, [[Oxford College of Emory University|Oxford College]], [[Goizueta Business School]], Laney Graduate School, [[Emory University School of Law|School of Law]], [[Emory University School of Medicine|School of Medicine]], [[Nell Hodgson Woodruff School of Nursing]], [[Rollins School of Public Health]], and the [[Candler School of Theology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/academics/schools/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The university has more than two million square feet of building space certified by the [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]] program and has a commitment to having three-quarters of the food they serve on campus come from local or sustainable sources by 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;emory1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Sustainability Initiatives at Emory|url=http://sustainability.emory.edu/|accessdate=10/11/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The University holds the distinction of having one of the largest inventories by square footage of LEED-certified building space among campuses in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;emory1&quot;/&gt; 

==History==
'''{{Main|History of Emory University}}'''
[[Image:Emory Glenn Chapel.jpg|200px|left|thumb|Glenn Memorial United Methodist Church near the main entrance of Emory University]]

In 1836, a small group of Methodists from [[Newton County, Georgia|Newton County]] contemplated the establishment of a new town and college. The town was named [[Oxford, Georgia|Oxford]] after the school's prestigious [[University of Oxford|British namesake]],&lt;ref name=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://emoryhistory.emory.edu/history/index.html |title=History &amp; Traditions Overview|publisher=Emory University|accessdate=2009-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; which graduated the two founders of Methodism, [[John Wesley|John]] and [[Charles Wesley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emoryhistory.emory.edu/history/index.html|title=A Brief History|last=Hauk|first=Gary S|publisher=Emory University|accessdate=2009-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college was named after [[John Emory]], an American Methodist bishop who inspired them.&lt;ref name=&quot;overview&quot;/&gt;

Events preceding the chartering of Emory College began in 1783, when the Georgia State legislature provided for the founding of &quot;a college or seminary of learning.&quot; However, general support of education in Georgia was meager until the 1830s, when an educational fad in Germany inspired Georgia Methodists to create a school for manual labor.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; At the Georgia Methodist Conference in 1834, a preacher known as &quot;Uncle Allen&quot; Turner suggested that Georgia Methodists should develop their own school rather than support [[Randolph-Macon College|Randolph-Macon]] in [[Virginia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;english&quot;&gt;English, Thomas H. ''Emory University 1915–1965: A Semicentennial History'' (Atlanta: Emory University, 1966).&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the Manual Labor School was created in Covington, Georgia in 1835.

On December 10, 1836, the [[Georgia General Assembly]] granted the Georgia Methodist Conference a charter to Emory College, named for [[John Emory]], a popular bishop who had presided at the 1834 conference but had died in a carriage accident in 1835.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; Two years after the chartering, the college opened its doors, and on September 17, 1838, the college's first president, [[Ignatius Alphonso Few]], and three faculty members welcomed fifteen freshmen and sophomores.&lt;ref name=&quot;english&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Emory College Oxford.jpg|250px|right|thumb|Emory College quad in Oxford, Georgia]]
[[Image:class of 1845.jpg|250px|right|thumb|Class of 1908]]

Emory College imposed a strict environment during most of the nineteenth century. By signing their names into the ''Matriculation Book'', students were bound to obey the &quot;Laws and Statutes of the College,&quot; which bound students to their rooms during study hours, and forbade them from leaving the town limits without the president's consent and engaging in immoral activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; Until the presidency of [[Warren Candler]] in the 1890s, Emory prohibited intercollegiate sports. He thought the practice &quot;evil, only evil, and that continually,&quot; his principal objection being the cost of intercollegiate athletic programs, the temptation of gambling, and the distraction from academics.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; However, he was not unalterably opposed to athletics, and during his presidency he raised funds for the first gymnasium at Emory and oversaw the creation of the nation's first model [[intramural sports|intramural program]].

Emory College was closed briefly during the [[American Civil War|Civil War]]. In the autumn of 1861, every student left to fight, and the college's trustees closed for the duration. During the war, the college's buildings saw duty both as a [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] hospital and [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; When Emory reopened in January 1866, the school's library was destroyed and its small endowment was depleted.&lt;ref name=&quot;english&quot;/&gt; Only with the aid of a state grant could students afford to resume their education.

In the years following the Civil War, Emory, along with the rest of the South, struggled to overcome financial devastation.&lt;ref name=&quot;overview&quot;/&gt;
The first step toward financial stability came in 1880, when Emory President [[Atticus Haygood|Atticus G. Haygood]] preached a [[Thanksgiving Day]] sermon expressing gratitude for the end of slavery, which captured the attention of George I. Seney, a Brooklyn banker and Methodist. Seney gave Emory College $5,000 to repay its debts, $50,000 for construction, and $75,000 to establish a new endowment.&lt;ref name=&quot;english&quot;/&gt; Over the years, Seney invested more than a quarter-million dollars into Emory College, helping to erect the administration building in Oxford that bears his name.

Under President [[Atticus Haygood|Haygood]]'s direction, Emory College began to offer many technical and professional subjects in addition to courses required for degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emoryhistory.emory.edu/timeline/index.html|title=A Sesquicentennial Timeline: 1833-1987|publisher=Emory University|accessdate=2009-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the turn of the century, Emory had evolved its traditional liberal arts program into a broad curriculum encouraging students to pursue degrees in science, study in theology and law, and even learning and expertise in technology and tool craft. The technology department was launched by President [[Isaac Stiles Hopkins]], a polymath professor at Emory College, who was later convinced by state legislators to become the first president of what is now the [[Georgia Institute of Technology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

The course of Emory's history changed dramatically when, in November 1979, Robert and George Woodruff presented the institution with a gift of $105 million in [[Coca-Cola]] stock. At the time this was the largest single gift to any institution of higher education in American history, and it made a profound impact on Emory's direction in the next two decades, boosting the university to the top ranks of American research universities.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

Emory is celebrating its 175th anniversary in 2011. A university committee identified a list of 175 [http://www.emory.edu/home/about/anniversary/175-of-everything/history-makers.html history makers] for the occasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory History Makers|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/anniversary/175-of-everything/history-makers.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [http://www.emory.edu/home/about/anniversary/almanac/index.html daily almanac] features highlights from Emory's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=175th Anniversary: Daily Almanac|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/anniversary/almanac/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:Emory Quad.jpg|thumb|right|Main Quad on Emory's Druid Hills Campus]]
===Demographics===
Emory is home to 7,441 undergraduates and 6,452 graduate and professional students (fall 2011).&lt;ref name=&quot;Emory University website&quot;/&gt;

===Colleges and schools===
;Emory College of Arts and Sciences (1836)
{{splitsection|Emory College of Arts and Sciences|date=October 2011}}
[[Emory College of Arts and Sciences]], established in 1836, offers some five dozen majors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory College of Arts and Sciences website|url=http://college.emory.edu/home/academic/program/concentrations.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Undergraduates must complete general education requirements that are designed to expose all students to a variety of topics, including physical and social sciences, the humanities, and foreign languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory College of Arts and Sciences website|url=http://college.emory.edu/home/academic/course/requirements/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; About two in five students study abroad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/rankings-successes/community-life.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory students have been recognized with academic honors such as the Fulbright, Marshall, Mellon, National Science Foundation, Rhodes, Rockefeller and Rotary programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/rankings-successes/award-winning-students.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The campus houses a chapter of [[Phi Beta Kappa]], the oldest and most prestigious national academic honor society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory College of Arts and Sciences website|url=http://college.emory.edu/home/life/societies.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The five-year dual-degree program in engineering, offered in collaboration with the [[Georgia Institute of Technology]], allows Emory students to enroll in engineering classes at Georgia Tech. Students typically graduate with a degree from Emory College or the Goizueta Business School and an engineering degree from Georgia Tech.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory College of Arts and Sciences website|url=http://college.emory.edu/home/academic/program/major/engineering.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the undergraduate class of 2015, Emory received 17,027 applications.&lt;ref name=&quot;emory2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Undergraduate Admission: Class Profile|url=http://www.emory.edu/admission/admission/class_profile/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academically, the incoming freshman class earned an average total SAT score of 2020–2220.&lt;ref name=&quot;emory2&quot;/&gt; 

;Oxford College (1836 / 1919)

Prospective undergraduates may apply to the Emory College of Arts and Sciences or to Emory's [[Oxford College of Emory University|Oxford College]], which is located about {{convert|40|mi|km}} from the university's main campus and is the site of Emory’s founding. Oxford, with about 900 students, offers the opportunity to experience a smaller campus community. Typically, students graduate from Oxford after four semesters and continue to the Druid Hills campus, where they may become juniors in Emory College or apply for admission to the Goizueta School of Business or the Nell Hodgson Woodruff School of Nursing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oxford.emory.edu/a_distinctive_place/ |title=Oxford College: A Distinctive Place |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the Oxford class of 2013 (which will go on to receive Emory undergraduate degrees in 2015), 44% of the 4,694 applicants were accepted. The incoming freshman class earned an average GPA of 3.5 in high school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oxford College Entering Class Profile|url=http://oxford.emory.edu/admission/entering-class-profile/|accessdate=11/16/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

;Goizueta Business School (1919)

Emory's [[Goizueta Business School]] offers an undergraduate Bachelor of Business Administration program,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Goizueta Business School website|url=http://www.goizueta.emory.edu/prospectivestudents/undergrad.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; several Master of Business Administration programs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Goizueta Business School website|url=http://www.goizueta.emory.edu/prospectivestudents/mbaprograms.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the option of pursuing a PhD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Goizueta Business School website|url=http://www.goizueta.emory.edu/prospectivestudents/phdprograms.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Rising undergraduate juniors may apply for admission to Goizueta.

Students apply to Goizueta Business school for the junior year of college. There were 317 students admitted to Goizueta Business School’s class of 2011. Its average SAT score was 1371 and its average college GPA is a 3.58.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goizueta.emory.edu/degree/undergra_factsFigures.html |title=Facts &amp; Figures |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The two-year full-time MBA program’s class of 2012 is made up of 134 students with an average GMAT score of 680 and an average undergraduate GPA of 3.3.  The one-year full-time MBA program's class of 2012 has 39 students with an average GMAT score of 642 and an average undergraduate GPA of 3.4.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MBA Class Profiles|url=http://www.goizueta.emory.edu/degree/fulltimemba/class_profiles.html|accessdate=11/16/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Laney Graduate School (1919)

The [[Laney Graduate School]] is home to advanced degree programs in more than four dozen specialties, a number of these offered in partnership with the university's other schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Laney Graduate School website|url=http://www.gs.emory.edu/academics/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of November 2010, 1,917 students were enrolled, 86.7% of which were pursuing a PhD; for the fall 2010 entering class, 14.18% of the 4,796 applicants to a Graduate School PhD program were accepted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Laney Graduate School Facts &amp; Figures|url=http://www.gs.emory.edu/about/facts.php|accessdate=11/16/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

;School of Law (1916)

Students in the [[Emory University School of Law]] may earn a Doctor of Law degree (JD), a Doctor of Juridical Science (SJD) or one of several dual degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's School of Law website|url=http://www.law.emory.edu/academics/academic-catalog/degree-programs.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2011-12 school year, 811 students were enrolled in the School of Law. Of the 3,951 applicants for the Class of 2014, 246 enrolled. The median GPA was 3.7 and the median LSAT score was a 165.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory Law at a Glance|url=http://www.law.emory.edu/about-emory-law/at-a-glance.html|accessdate=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

;School of Medicine (1854)

The [[Emory University School of Medicine]] curriculum was developed for the James B. Williams Medical Education Building that opened in 2007. In addition to the MD degree, the school offers several joint degree and allied health programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/academics/programs/medicine.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The School of Medicine received approximately 6,000 applications each year and accepts an average of 132 students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.med.emory.edu/admissions/generalquestions.cfm |title=Frequently Asked Questions |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For currently enrolled students, the average GPA is 3.7 and the average MCAT score is 34.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.med.emory.edu/admissions/howtoapplyrequirements.cfm |title=How to Apply |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Nell Hodgson Woodruff School of Nursing (1905)

The [[Nell Hodgson Woodruff School of Nursing]] offers the BSN, a range of MSN degrees and a PhD program. One of these is an Accelerated Bachelor of Science in Nursing and Master of Science of Nursing program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Nell Hodgson Woodruff School of Nursing website|url=http://www.nursing.emory.edu/academics/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rising undergraduate juniors may apply for admission to the nursing school.

The School of Nursing currently has 378 students—218 undergraduates, 160 graduate students, and 10 in the doctoral program. For class starting in the fall of 2010, 256 of the 593 applicants were admitted to the undergraduate program and 144 of the 198 applicants were admitted to the masters program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite |title=School of Nursing Year to Date Applicant Summary |publisher=Emory University |date=2010 |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The average GPA for admitted students in the bachelors program is 3.45 and 3.3 for the masters program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nursing.emory.edu/admission/faq.html#Cat2 |title=BSN Questions |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Rollins School of Public Health (1990)

Students in the [[Rollins School of Public Health]] may earn a Master of Public Health, a Master of Science in Public Health or a PhD. The school also offers several dual degree programs as well as distance learning opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Rollins School of Public Health|url=http://www.sph.emory.edu/cms/academic_programs/degree_programs/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The incoming class of the Rollins School of Public Health has 441 students with an average undergraduate GPA of 3.4 and an average graduate GPA of 3.5.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sph.emory.edu/cms/prospective_students/admissions/index.html |title=Admissions |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Candler School of Theology (1914)

The [[Candler School of Theology]], a United Methodist Church seminary, offers four degrees: Master of Divinity, Master of Theological Studies, Master of Theology, and Doctor of Theology in Pastoral Counseling. Students may also pursue one of several joint degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Candler School of Theology website|url=http://www.candler.emory.edu/academics/degree-programs/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The School of Theology class of 2010 was composed of 171 students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.candler.emory.edu/NEWS/051010.cfm |title=Candler School of Theology |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| USNWR_NU             = 20
| USNWR_LA             =
| USNWR_Bus            = 23
| GUR World            = 
| USNWR_Law            = 30
| USNWR_Medr           = 21
| USNWR_Medc           = 
| USNWR_Eng            = 
| USNWR_Ed             =
| USNWR_Ec             =
| USNWR_PolSci         =
| USNWR_PSycc          =
| USNWR_Psycr          =
| USNWR_Soc            =
| QS_W                 = 114
| ARWU_W               = 102-150
| ARWU_N               = 54-68
| ARWU_SCI             =
| ARWU_ENG             =
| ARWU_LIFE            = 
| ARWU_MED             =
| ARWU_SOC             =
| Newsweek             =
| THES_W               = 75
| THES_N               = 
| CMUP                 =
| Wamo_NU = 32
| Forbes               = 45
}}
[[Image:Emory ReadingRoom.jpg|250px|left|thumb|Matheson Reading Room]]

In its 2012 rankings of the best colleges and universities in the United States, ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' placed Emory at #20 in the national university rankings,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-universities-rankings |title=National Universities Rankings |publisher=''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' |accessdate=2011-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has ranked Emory as high as #9 in the past.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emory.edu/EMORY_REPORT/erarchive/1997/August/eraugust.25/8_25_97USNews.html  |title=Emory ranked 9th-best national university by U.S. News &amp; World Report magazine |publisher=''Emory Report'' |date=August 25, 2007 |accessdate=2010-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The school is included on ''[[The Princeton Review]]''’s list of the 371 best colleges in the United States and was named one of the publication’s best schools in the Southeast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/schools/college/CollegeRankings.aspx?iid=1023323 |title=Emory University |publisher=The Princeton Review |accessdate=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2011-12 [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]] place Emory No. 75 in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/ |title=The Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2011-2012 |publisher=Timeshighereducation.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, [[USA Today]] ranked Emory #1 on its list of &quot;The 10 best American colleges for writers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usatodayeducate.com/staging/index.php/the-10-best-american-colleges-for-writers |title=The 10 best American colleges for writers &amp;#124; USA TODAY College |publisher=Usatodayeducate.com |date=2011-04-28 |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Bloomberg Businessweek's 2011 BBA rankings, Emory's Goizueta Business School is ranked at #3, receiving its highest ranking ever on this list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/interactive_reports/bs_ugrank_tab_0303.html?chan=bschools_special+report+--+best+college+business+programs_special+report+--+best+college+business+programs |title=Best Undergrad Business Schools 2011 |publisher=''[[Bloomberg Businessweek]]'' |accessdate=2011-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the graduate schools of Emory University are ranked as some of the best and most competitive in their fields by [[U.S. News and World Report]]. For the 2012 list, Rollins School of Public Health was ranked at #6; the Nell Hodgson Woodruff School of Nursing was ranked at #21; the Goizueta Business School was ranked #23; the School of Law was ranked #30; the School of Medicine was ranked #21 for research and #33 for primary care; the Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering (with Georgia Tech) program was ranked #2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University rankings|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/points-pride/rankings.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Community Education===
[[Emory Continuing Education]] offers certificate programs, computer training, professional development, personal enrichment, and corporate and senior education opportunities for those in the pursuit of lifelong learning, including certification programs, computer training and professional development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Emory Continuing Education website |url=http://www.ece.emory.edu/ |accessdate=2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Emory Pre-College Program]] offers summer programs for rising high school juniors and seniors. College-bound students may take two-week non-credit courses and six-week credit courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory's Pre-College Program|url=http://college.emory.edu/program/precollege/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
===Residential life===
Emory requires its students to live on campus for the first two years of undergraduate life, with defined options for freshmen and sophomores.   Juniors and seniors may elect to live off-campus or continue in campus housing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Residence Life &amp; Housing website|url=http://www.emory.edu/HOUSING/UNDERGRAD/houseopt.html|accessdate=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Fraternities have existed on Emory's campus as early as 1840. One early chronicler makes the case that Emory's &quot;temple&quot; of the Mystic Seven may have been the first chapter of a national fraternity established anywhere in the South. Today, the Greek-letter sororities and fraternities play an important part in leavening Emory's campus life. For undergraduates, Greek life comprises approximately 30% of the Emory student population. The Office of Greek Life recognizes and regulates on-campus chapters of fraternities and sororities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Office of Sorority and Fraternity Life|url=http://www.osfl.campuslifetech.org/|accessdate=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fraternities have on-campus housing located on Eagle Row, and Sorority Village, a series of townhouses, faces the fraternity houses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Residence Life &amp; Housing website|url=http://www.emory.edu/HOUSING/UNDERGRAD/opt_greek.html|accessdate=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Greek Life is an important social engagement for students, but it is not totally exclusive -- students from different sororities and fraternities regularly socialize, and the college's emphasis on on-campus housing helps students make friends inside and outside the Greek system.

===Dooley===
{{Split section|Dooley (mascot)|Talk:Emory University#Dooley|date=July 2011}}
[[Image:Thompson dooley.jpg|120px|right|thumb|Dooley, the unofficial [[mascot]] of Emory University]]
Traditions at Emory include Dooley,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/history/dooley.html|accessdate=2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; the &quot;Spirit of Emory&quot; and the unofficial mascot of the university. Dooley is a [[skeleton]] and is usually dressed in black. The original Dooley was an actual skeleton from a biology/anatomy classroom. The name &quot;Dooley&quot; was given to the unofficial mascot in 1909.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dooleystory&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://emoryhistory.emory.edu/traditions/Dooleystory.html|title=Traditions &amp; Rituals|publisher=Emory University|accessdate=8 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Each year in the spring, during Dooley's Week, Dooley roams Emory's campus, flanked by bodyguards dressed in all black (&quot;Dooley guards&quot;) and lets students out of class with unscheduled appearances in classrooms. A spokesperson amongst the bodyguards walks with him to deliver his messages as he never speaks himself. His identity is unknown and how his guards are involved with the tradition is often fodder for campus gossip. He adopts the first name and middle initial of the University's current president; Dooley's current full name is James W. Dooley, after [[James W. Wagner]]. Dooley's Week culminates with Dooley's Ball, a grand celebration that takes place in the center of campus on McDonough Field. A sporting match called The Dooley Cup is played between the university administration and the [[student government association]] each spring.{{fact|date=October 2011}}

===Community service===
The university received the 2008 Presidential Award for General Community Service, which is the highest federal recognition given to higher education institutions for their commitment to community service, service-learning and civic engagement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=26552 |title=Emory Receives Top Service Recognition |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=September 2, 2009 |accessdate=2010-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

About 25% of Emory students participate in Volunteer Emory, Emory's umbrella community service group. As one of the most popular groups on campus, Volunteer Emory offers dozens of ways to serve the community, working with varied organizations including the Atlanta Community Food Bank, [[Trees Atlanta]], PAWS Atlanta, and Jones Boys and Girls Club.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://volunteer.emory.edu/|title=Volunteer Emory|publisher=Emory University|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory Cares International Service Day brings together students, alumni and other community members to volunteer at a number of projects organized by Emory and its many partners around the city of Atlanta and in cities worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory Alumni Association website|url=http://www.alumni.emory.edu/volunteer-and-give/emory-cares.html|accessdate=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student organizations===
Hundreds of student clubs and organizations operate on Emory's campus. These include numerous [[student government]], [[special interest]], and [[community service|service organizations]].

The Student Government Association (SGA) charters and provides most of the funding for other student groups, and represents students' interests when dealing with the administration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.students.emory.edu/SGA/sga/ |title=Emory University SGA — Student Government Association |publisher=Students.emory.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The SGA oversees divisional councils, each coinciding with the undergraduate, graduate and professional schools of the university. Notable among these are the College Council (CC) which handles students concerns primarily for the undergraduate body of the Emory College of Arts and Sciences and annually sponsors the State of Race event. The Student Programming Council (SPC) is the school's primary programming organization, responsible for planning five events every year: Homecoming Week, Fall Band Party, Spring Band Party, Swoopstock and Dooley's Week.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spc.campuslifetech.org/?page_id=2 |title=Emory SPC - Official Website |publisher=Students.emory.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Emory Wheel]]'', Emory's undergraduate student newspaper, has been continually published since 1919. It is financially independent from the university, covering its costs from self-generated advertising sales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emorywheel.com/about/ |title=About |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freebase.com/view/en/the_emory_wheel/ |title=About |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |accessdate=2010-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[WMRE (Emory)|WMRE]], Emory's student operated radio station, began broadcasting in 1989. Although it was initially only available to on-campus listeners, it now enjoys a worldwide audience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.students.emory.edu/WMRE/About.html |title=About |publisher=Students.emory.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory also has several [[secret societies]]—the [[D.V.S. Senior Honor Society]], the oldest society, founded in 1902; [[Ducemus]]; Speculum; the Order of Ammon; and the Paladin Society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University main website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/history/index.html|accessdate=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arts===
Students may engage in the performing and fine arts as an area of academic study or as extracurricular activities. Undergraduates may pursue a major in the performing arts (dance, theater, or music) or in film studies, art history, visual arts, or creative writing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arts.emory.edu/about/index.html |title=About Arts at Emory |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Graduate programs in art history, film studies, and music are offered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gs.emory.edu/academics/index.php |title=Degree Programs |publisher=Laney Graduate School |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are more than 50 student organizations dedicated to the arts. Students can explore artistic interests as diverse as architecture, breakdancing, poetry, and improvisational comedy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.creativity.emory.edu/student-art-groups.shtml |title=Student Arts Groups |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory routinely hosts arts events in the Schwartz Center for Performing Arts that are open to the Emory and Atlanta communities. Recent performances include Bang on a Can All-Stars (a side project of drummer [[Glenn Kotche]] from the rock band [[Wilco]]), jazz performer [[Esperanza Spalding]], and New York’s Cedar Lake Dance Company. A program called Creativity Conversations brings artistic minds to campus to discuss art and the creative process. Guests have included [[Philip Glass]], [[Jimmy Carter]], [[Salman Rushdie]], and [[Seamus Heaney]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://creativity.emory.edu/creativity-conversations-index.shtml |title=Creativity Conversations |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
[[File:Emory Eagle.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]

Emory ranks among top schools in both the ''U.S. News &amp; World Report’s'' rankings of the best national universities and the Directors Cup of the National Association of Collegiate Directors of Athletics for best all-around athletics program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/life/athletics/scholar-athletes.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory's 18 varsity sports teams, known as the Eagles, are members of the [[Division III (NCAA)|NCAA’s Division III]] [[University Athletic Association| University Athletic Association (UAA)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory Eagles website|url=http://www.emoryathletics.com/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[intramural sports]] program provides an athletic outlet for the entire Emory community. Emory has numerous club sports&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory Club Sports website|url=http://www.rec.emory.edu/clubsports/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and a variety of recreational and competitive intramural teams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory Intramurals website|url=http://www.rec.emory.edu/rec/intramurals/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Outdoor Emory Organization sponsors weekend trips of outdoor activities such as rafting, rock climbing and hiking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Outdoor Emory Organization|url=http://www.students.emory.edu/OEO/|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
===Surrounding area===
Emory's main campus is located in [[Druid Hills, Georgia|Druid Hills]] section&lt;!--The name of the CDP must be mentioned in the lead--&gt; of [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]]&lt;!--Have to say unincorporated to make clear that it is not in any city--&gt; [[DeKalb County, Georgia|DeKalb County]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.emory.edu/home/about/campus/index.html Campus].&quot; Emory University. Retrieved on 2009-05-05.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DHCDPMap&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/MapItDrawServlet?geo_id=16000US1324264&amp;_bucket_id=50&amp;tree_id=420&amp;context=saff&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on Druid Hills CDP, GA].&quot; ''[[United States Census Bureau]]''. Retrieved on 2009-05-05.&lt;/ref&gt; a suburban community near [[Atlanta]]. Emory’s main campus is about a 15-minute drive from downtown and midtown Atlanta as well as the Buckhead area. The Atlanta metropolitan area, with more than 5.5 million people, is the third largest in the Southeastern United States and the ninth largest in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=American FactFinder |publisher=United States Census Bureau |url=http://factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=2011-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Atlanta is home to the world headquarters of corporations such as [[The Coca-Cola Company]], [[The Home Depot]], [[AT&amp;T Mobility]], [[United Parcel Service|UPS]], [[Delta Air Lines]], and [[Turner Broadcasting]]. Atlanta has the country's fourth-largest concentration of Fortune 500 companies, and more than 75 percent of Fortune 1000 companies have business operations in the metropolitan area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Doing Business in Atlanta, Georgia |publisher= Business.gov |url= http://www.business.gov/states/georgia/local/atlanta.html |accessdate=2011-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Popular attractions in the Atlanta area include, the world’s largest indoor aquarium, the [[Georgia Aquarium]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Big window to the sea |publisher= CNN |date=November 23, 2005 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2005/TECH/science/11/21/new.ga.aquarium/index.html |accessdate=2011-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The World of Coca-Cola]], the [[High Museum of Art]] and [[CNN Center]]. Atlanta is also home to The Peachtree Road Race, the world’s largest 10k with approximately  55,000 runners, as well as the [[National Black Arts Festival]], a celebration of African American music, film, visual art, dance and literature, that takes place every summer in [[Atlanta]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Culture and Attractions |publisher= Emory University website |url=http://www.emory.edu/admission/atlanta/culture_attractions/index.html |accessdate= 2011-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sustainability===
The university has one of the largest inventories by square footage of [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]]-certified building space among campuses in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sustainability.emory.edu/page/1007/green-buildings/green-space|title=Green Building/Green Space|publisher=Emory Sustainability Initiative|accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; New buildings on Emory’s campus must comply with the guidelines set by U.S. Green Building Council’s Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design (LEED).

The university also has a policy to preserve more than half the campus as undeveloped green space. For every tree removed for new construction, another must be planted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sustainability.emory.edu/page/1007/green-buildings/green-space |title=Emory Sustainability Initiatives: Green Building/Green Space |publisher=Emory University |year=2010 |accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Emory is committed to having three-quarters of the food served on campus come from local or sustainable sources by 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sustainability.emory.edu/page/1008/Sustainable-Food |title=Sustainability |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Emory’s campus has several small educational gardens, where fresh produce is grown. These gardens are meant to increase awareness about local food and remind members of the community that they can reduce fossil fuel use by eating locally. The upkeep of the gardens is the responsibility of members of the Emory community. During the school year, a seasonal farmers market hosts local farmers and vendors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sustainability.emory.edu/page/1008/Sustainable-Food |title=Emory Sustainability Initiatives: Sustainable Food |publisher=Emory University |year=2010 |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Druid Hills campus has a pedestrian-only center. The Cliff shuttle system provides transportation for students, faculty and staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sustainability.emory.edu/page/1012/Commute-Options |title=Emory Sustainability Initiatives: Commute Options |publisher=Emory University |year=2010 |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alternative transportation is encouraged through initiatives such as Bike Emory and Zipcar, a company that rents cars for short-term use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zipcar.com/universities/how/greenbenefits |title=Green Benefits |publisher=ZipCar |year=2010 |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Students have the option of completing a minor in sustainability. This includes courses on the social, environmental and economic elements of sustainability, as well as a hands-on component, such as research or an internship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=28016 |title=University to Launch Sustainability Minor |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=February 15, 2010 |accessdate=2010-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buildings===
;Michael C. Carlos Museum
The [[Michael C. Carlos Museum|Carlos Museum]] houses one of the most comprehensive art collections in the Southeast, with works from ancient [[Egypt]], Near East, [[Greece]], [[Rome]], ancient Americas, [[Africa]], and [[Asia]]. The museum has been adding to its collection since 1876, when a small museum was opened on the Oxford campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carlos.emory.edu/history-mission |title=History &amp; Mission |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Its permanent collection includes such pieces as an influential statue of [[Aphrodite]] from the first century B.C., which was in two parts until it was fixed by a Carlos employee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=27064 |title=Carlos Fixes Broken Goddess |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=April 27, 2009 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the most notable exhibitions that the Carlos Museum has had was an exhibition about Egyptian pharaoh [[Tutankhamun]] (&quot;King Tut&quot;), which was on display for the first time in 26 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=25439 |title=Museum to Present King Tut Exhibition |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=April 8, 2008 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students may visit the Carlos Museum for free. Many of the curators teach courses at the University and faculty in other departments, including dance and physics, often use the museum as part of their curriculum.

;Manuscripts, Archives, and Rare Books Library (MARBL)
Emory’s Robert W. Woodruff University Library has been ranked #13 in the nation, according to ''[[The Princeton Review]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/college-rankings.aspx |title=College Rankings |publisher=The Princeton Review |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The library’s tenth floor is home to MARBL, which has rare materials relating to literature, African American history and culture, and Southern and Georgia history. Notable pieces of the MARBL collection include a rare first edition of ''[[Robinson Crusoe]]'' by [[Daniel Defoe]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=26298 |title=MARBL Receives 'Crusoe' Editions |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=November 24, 2008 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as works by [[Flannery O’Connor]], [[Alice Walker]], [[Langston Hughes]], [[William Butler Yeats|W.B. Yeats]], and [[Seamus Heaney]]. All students have complete access to MARBL and members of the public may also use the library. Many of these authors become subjects of exhibitions in Schatten Gallery, which is located on the third floor of Woodruff Library and houses various displays throughout the year.

;Lullwater Preserve
Lullwater Preserve features more than {{convert|100|acres|km2}} of green space including woods, walking trails and a lake. The home of the University president and his family, [[Lullwater House]] is located here. The only vehicles allowed are those that have received special permission because they are visiting the president’s house.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/anniversary/essays/lullwater.html/ |title=Lullwater Preserve |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The property was originally the estate of Walter T. Candler, son of Coca-Cola co-founder [[Asa Griggs Candler]].

;Yerkes National Primate Research Center
The [[Yerkes National Primate Research Center]] is one of only eight [[National Institutes of Health]]–funded national primate research centers. Between its two locations—the main center on Emory’s Druid Hills campus and a secondary location in Lawrenceville, Ga.—the Center has nearly 3,400 nonhuman primates and 13,000 rodents. Since 1930, the Center has been conducting research in the fields of microbiology and immunology, neurologic diseases, neuropharmacology, behavioral, cognitive and developmental neuroscience, and psychiatric disorders. Current research includes developing vaccines for infectious and noninfectious diseases, treating drug addiction, and increase understanding of illnesses such as [[Alzheimer’s disease|Alzheimer’s]] and [[Parkinson's disease]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yerkes.emory.edu/history |title=History |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-08-03}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yerkes.emory.edu/about-yerkes |title=About Yerkes |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-08-03}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;The Carter Center
Emory is partnered with the [[Carter Center]], a not-for-profit organization founded by former U.S. President [[Jimmy Carter]] to further human rights. Carter usually visits Emory’s campus several times throughout the year. Most notably, he hosts Carter Town Hall, an open-forum event for all first-year students.

;The Donna and Marvin Schwartz Center for the Performing Arts
The [[Donna and Marvin Schwartz Center for Performing Arts]], which reopened in the fall of 2001, hosts professional and student-run performances throughout the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.schwartzcenter.com/index.shtml |title=Schwartz Center for the Arts |publisher=Emory University |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to various practice facilities and smaller performance spaces, The Schwartz Center now includes Cherry Logan Emerson Concert Hall, which has 825 seats and a large pipe organ.

;Winship Cancer Institute
Winship Cancer Institute of Emory University is Georgia’s first and only cancer center designated by the [[National Cancer Institute]]. The Winship Cancer institute was founded in 1937 with a gift from Robert Woodruff, the former president of Coca-Cola, after he lost his mother to cancer that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;winshipcancer.emory.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Accomplishments and Milestones |publisher=Winship Cancer Institute website |url=http://winshipcancer.emory.edu/about-winship/WinshipContentPage.aspx?nd=543 |accessdate=2011-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For over 65 years, the mission of the Winship Cancer Institute has been  to bring together researchers, physicians, epidemiologists, nurses, engineers, and social workers with the goal of preventing, treating, and curing cancer. Divisions at Winship Cancer Intitute include [[radiation oncology]], [[surgical oncology]], [[hematology]], and [[medical oncology]]. In 2009, Winship Cancer Institute was the first in Georgia to use a new and faster radiation system, called RapidArc, which can reduce treatment times and deliver a complete treatment in a single rotation of the machine around the patient.&lt;ref name=&quot;winshipcancer.emory.edu&quot;/&gt; In 2006, the [[National Cancer Institute]] selected the Emory and Georgia Tech joint research program as one of seven National Centers of Cancer Nanotechnology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Accomplishments and Milestones |publisher=Winship Cancer Institute website |url= http://winshipcancer.emory.edu/about-winship/WinshipContentPage.aspx?nd=543 |accessdate= 2011-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alumni and Faculty==
{{main|List of persons associated with Emory University}}
Emory alumni include: [[Alben Barkley]] (BA 1900), 35th Vice President of the United States, [[Newt Gingrich]] (BA 1965), former Speaker of the House of Representatives, [[Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus Lamar (II)]] (BA 1845) former Associate Justice of the US Supreme Court and [[Bill Haslam]] (BA 1980), current Governor of Tennessee. In academia, [[Isaac Stiles Hopkins]] (BA 1859) and [[Robert Stewart Hyer]] (BA 1881, MA 1882), first presidents of [[Georgia Institute of Technology|Georgia Tech]] and [[Southern Methodist University]], respectively. Business alum include former long time President of the [[Coca Cola Company]], [[Robert Woodruff]], CEO and Chairman of [[Burger King]], [[John Chidsey]] (MBA, JD), CEO and Chairman of [[MetLife]], [[C. Robert Henrikson]] (JD 1972).[[Image:Sir Ahmed Salman Rushdie.jpg|250px|thumb|Author [[Salman Rushdie]] having a discussion with Emory University students]]In arts and entertainment, members of the [[Grammy]] winning folk rock group [[The Indigo Girls]] and [[Adam Richman (actor)|Adam Richman]] (BA), actor and host of the television show [[Man vs. Food]]. [[Pulitzer Prize]] winning writers [[C. Vann Woodward]] (BA 1930), author of ''The Strange Career of Jim Crow'' and [[Dumas Malone]] (BA 1910) are also alumni, the latter also being the recipient of the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]]. Medical and scientific alumni include [[Eugene Stead]] (BS 1928, MD 1932), founder of the [[physician assistant]] profession and [[Arnall Patz]] (BA 1943, MD 1945), ophthalmology researcher and Presidential Medal of Freedom recipient who discovered that oxygen therapy causes blindness in infants. Among notable athletes, [[Bobby Jones]] (Law 1929), the only golfer to win a [[Grand Slam]], founder of the [[Masters Golf Tournament]], and often considered to be one of the greatest golfers of all time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/rankings-successes/famous-alumni.html |title=Points of Pride: Famous Alumni &amp;#124; Emory University &amp;#124; Atlanta, GA |publisher=Emory.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Distinguished faculty members include former U.S. President [[Jimmy Carter]], Booker Prize-winning novelist [[Sir Salman Rushdie]], His Holiness the [[XIV Dalai Lama]], Pulitzer Prize winning poet [[Natasha Trethewey]] and CNN chief medical correspondent [[Dr. Sanjay Gupta]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emory University website|url=http://www.emory.edu/home/about/rankings-successes/distinguished-professors.html|accessdate=7/18/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery caption=&quot;Emory University Alumni&quot; widths=&quot;140px&quot; heights=&quot;140px&quot; perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;

File:35_Alben_Barkley_3x4.jpg|[[Alben Barkley]], 35th [[Vice President of the United States]]

File:NewtGingrich.jpg|[[Newt Gingrich]], Former [[Speaker of the United States House of Representatives|Speaker of the House of Representatives]]

File:BobbyJonesAge14.jpg|[[Bobby Jones (golfer)|Bobby Jones]], Only golfer to win a [[Grand Slam (golf)|Grand Slam]] and founder of the [[Masters Golf Tournament]]

File:Patz_john.jpg|[[Arnall Patz]], Ophthalmology researcher and [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]] recipient

&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Emory in popular culture==
===Film===

* Some scenes of the 2011 film ''Hall Pass'', a comedy that stars [[Owen Wilson]] as a man whose wife allows him to have an affair and was directed by the [[Farrelly brothers]], were shot outside the [[Alpha Tau Omega]] and [[Kappa Alpha Order]] fraternity houses on Emory’s Eagle Row.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=28127 |title=Movie-Making Farrelly's Invade Frat Row |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=March 4, 2010 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=28085 |title=Wilson, Bynes to Film Scene on Emory's Eagle Row |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=February 25, 2010 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 2007 documentary about former president [[Jimmy Carter]], ''Jimmy Carter: Man From Plains,'' features a scene of Carter being interviewed by the editor in chief of Emory’s student newspaper, ''[[The Emory Wheel]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clatl.com/atlanta/jimmy-carter-man-from-plains-missionary-man/Content?oid=1270364 |title=''Jimmy Carter: Man From Plains'': Missionary Man |publisher=Creative Loafing Atlanta |date=2007-10-31 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The novel ''[[Into the Wild (book)|Into the Wild]]'' by [[Jon Krakauer]] and subsequent film by the same title are about 1990 Emory College of Arts and Sciences graduate [[Christopher McCandless]], who gave away his possessions and hitchhiked to Alaska to live in the wilderness after graduation. Production of the 2007 film brought its director and writer, [[Sean Penn]], to Emory’s campus, and some footage for the movie was filmed during the 2006 Commencement ceremonies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=24329 |title=Sean Penn Brings Alum's Journey to the Screen |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=September 28, 2007 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* For the 2005 film version of ''[[The Dukes of Hazzard]]'', the crew visited [[Oxford College of Emory University|Oxford College]] to pay homage to the television series on which it was based. The first episode of the series featured a car jump with Oxford College’s Seney Hall in the background. The jump was also featured in the opening credits of the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oxford.emory.edu/a_distinctive_place/explore_the_region/ |title=Oxford College: Explore the Region |publisher=Oxford College |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 2005 independent film ''Kathy T'' (also known as ''Kathy T Gives Good Hoover''), about a college student whose life becomes more exciting after he reads some graffiti about Kathy T and decides to track her down, was written and directed by Emory University professor of film studies Ken Lieberman. Lieberman shot many scenes in a residence hall and fraternity house on campus and primarily used Emory students for extras.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=20259 |title=Emory Plays Backdrop to Prof's Film |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=December 7, 2004 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* All of the colleges and universities featured in the 2000 comedy ''[[Road Trip]]'', which is about a college student and some of his friends who drive to Texas to prevent his girlfriend from watching an explicit video of him with another girl, are fictional. Many scenes that took place on these campuses, particularly the University of Ithaca, were shot on Emory’s campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0215129/locations |title=Road Trip (2000) Filming Locations |publisher=IMDB.com |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===

* Scenes for [[The CW Television Network|The CW]] television show ''[[The Vampire Diaries]]'' were shot in [[Oxford College of Emory University|Oxford College]]’s Hoke O’Kelley Library.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=27721 |title='Vampires' Descend Upon Oxford Campus |publisher=''[[The Emory Wheel]]'' |date=November 19, 2009 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Scenes from ''[[The Simple Life of Noah Dearborn]]'', a 1999 made-for-TV movie about a 91-year-old carpenter that must protect his land from being turned into a strip mall were shot on Emory University’s Druid Hills campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emory.edu/EMORY_REPORT/erarchive/1999/April/erapril.19/4_19_99terrazas.html |title=First Person: a Day in the Television Background at Emory West |publisher=''Emory Report'' |date=1999-04-19 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Robert W. Woodruff Professor]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* &quot;Emory University&quot;, in [http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/ ''New Georgia Encyclopedia'']. Retrieved July 1, 2006.
* &quot;Emory University&quot;, in ''Encyclopedia of Southern Culture'', ed. C. R. Wilson and William Ferris (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1989).
* English, Thomas H. ''Emory University 1915–1965: A Semicentennial History''. Atlanta: Emory University, 1966.
* Gleason, Jan. &quot;Emory ranked 9th-best national university by U.S. News &amp; World Report magazine&quot; in ''Emory Report'' 50, no. 1 (1997).
* Hauk, Gary S. ''A Legacy of Heart and Mind: Emory since 1836'' (Atlanta: Emory University, developed and produced by Bookhouse Group, Inc., 1999).
* Young, James Harvey. &quot;A Brief History of Emory University&quot;, in ''Emory College Catalog 2003–2005'' (Atlanta: Emory University Office of University Publications, 2003), 9–15.

==External links==
{{Portal box|Atlanta|University}}
* [http://www.emory.edu/ Official website]

{{Emory University}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#FFFFFF;color:#0F4D92;border:1px solid #0F4D92;
|list =
{{University Athletic Association}}
{{Georgia Private Colleges and Universities}}
{{MethodistColleges}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Atlanta}}
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{568 Group}} 
{{Atlanta landmarks}}
{{Druid Hills}}
|state =autocollapse
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Emory University}}
[[Category:Emory University| ]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in DeKalb County, Georgia]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1836]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]

[[da:Emory University]]
[[de:Emory University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه اموری]]
[[fr:Université Emory]]
[[ko:에모리 대학교]]
[[is:Emory-háskóli]]
[[it:Università Emory]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת אמורי]]
[[nl:Emory-universiteit]]
[[ja:エモリー大学]]
[[no:Emory University]]
[[pnb:اموری یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Emory University]]
[[ru:Университет Эмори]]
[[ta:எமரி பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[zh:艾默理大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
