<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="427861" ns="0" title="MEPIS"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS
| name = SimplyMEPIS
| logo = [[Image:MEPIS logo.svg|100px|MEPIS Logo]]
| screenshot = &lt;!-- Do NOT change the screenshot unless there is BIG change in the UI. When taking screenshot, please resize your window (e.g. 640*480), disable your extensions and use the default theme. --&gt;[[Image:Mepis11.png|300px]]
| caption = SimplyMEPIS 11.0 default desktop
| developer = Warren Woodford
| family = [[Unix-like]]
| working_state = Current
| supported_platforms    = [[x86]]
| released = May 2003
| latest_release_version = 11.0
| latest_release_date = {{release date|2011|05|05}}
| package_manager = [[dpkg]]
| updatemodel = [[Advanced Packaging Tool|APT]]
| kernel_type = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]]
| ui = [[KDE Plasma Workspaces|KDE Plasma Desktop]]
| license = Various
| website = [http://www.mepis.org/ www.mepis.org]
}}

'''MEPIS''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|m|ɛ|p|ɨ|s}}) is a set of [[Linux]] distributions, distributed as [[Live CD]]s that can be installed onto a [[hard disk drive]].
MEPIS is developed and maintained by an active community{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} begun by Warren Woodford and the [[eponym]]ous company '''MEPIS LLC'''.

The most popular MEPIS distribution is SimplyMEPIS, which is based primarily on [[Debian]] stable.
It can either be installed onto a hard drive or used as a [[Live CD]], which makes it externally bootable for troubleshooting and repairing many operating systems. It includes the [[KDE]] desktop environment.

MEPIS LLC offers senior consulting services for product strategy, architecture design, business and systems analysis, and cross-platform software development.

== History ==
MEPIS was designed as an alternative to [[SUSE Linux]], [[Red Hat Linux]], and [[Mandriva Linux]] (formerly Mandrake) which, in the creator Warren Woodford's opinion, were too difficult for the average user. MEPIS's first official release was on May 10, 2003.

In 2006, MEPIS made a transition from using Debian [[Software package (installation)|packages]] to using Ubuntu packages.&lt;ref&gt;Rick Lehrbaum, [http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS7900729752.html 'MEPIS founder clarifies MEPIS/Ubuntu relationship'], Feb. 17, 2007, Desktop Linux.com, accessed July 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; SimplyMEPIS 6.0, released in July 2006, was the first version of MEPIS to incorporate the Ubuntu packages and [[Software repository|repositories]].

SimplyMEPIS 7.0 discontinued the use of Ubuntu binary packages in favor of a combination of MEPIS packaged binaries based on Debian and Ubuntu source code, combined with a Debian stable OS core and extra packages from Debian package pools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mepis.org/node/13894|title=MEPIS Begins a Return to Debian With Version 6.9.51prebeta|date=2007-08-02|accessdate=2007-12-23 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071211233101/http://www.mepis.org/node/13894 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Warren Woodford released the source code for the MEPIS Installer and MEPIS System Assistants under the Apache License, in the Fall of 2008.

Major releases occur about six months to one year apart, based mostly on Warren's availability to produce the next version.

MEPIS Community now has a repo team that strives to keep packages up to date between releases, by maintaining a separate 'Community Repository' of various application packages, and has become a major player by producing the artwork and documentation for each release.&lt;ref&gt;http://forum.mepiscommunity.org/viewforum.php?f=78&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://mepis.org/docs/en/index.php?title=MEPIS_Talks_2&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

==Current variants==

*'''SimplyMEPIS''', the most popular MEPIS variant, is designed for everyday desktop and laptop computing. The default desktop environment is KDE-based, although Gnome and/or other GUI-environments can be installed.  SimplyMEPIS 11.0 includes Linux 2.6.36.4, KDE 4.5.1 and LibreOffice 3.3.2, with other applications available from Debian and the MEPIS Community. It was released on May 5, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mepis.org/node/166|title=SimplyMEPIS 11.0 Production Release|date=2011-05-5|accessdate=2011-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is based on Debian 6.
*'''[[antiX]]''', a fast, lightweight and flexible&lt;ref&gt;http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=antix&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|antiX being flexible|date=June 2011}} distribution available in full, base or core editions and based on SimplyMEPIS for x86 systems in an environment suitable for old computers that features the [[Fluxbox]] and [[IceWM]] [[window manager]]s. Version M11 was released on 2 May 2011,&lt;ref&gt;http://antix.mepis.org/index.php?title=Main_Page#News&lt;/ref&gt;  It is now a true [[Rolling release|'rolling-release-cycle']] Linux distribution, and thus continues to remain current. It is based upon the standard Debian repository named 'testing'.

==Name==
According to Warren Woodford, the name MEPIS is pronounced like &quot;Memphis&quot;, with the extra letters removed. Originally, the word &quot;MEPIS&quot; didn't mean anything in particular; it came about by mistake. When Woodford misunderstood a friend over the telephone, he decided to use the name because it was a simple five-letter word and there were no other companies or products with that name.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.mepis.org/}}
* [http://www.mepiscommunity.org/ Community website]
* {{DistroWatch|mepis|NAME=MEPIS Linux}}

===Reviews===
*[http://www.itreviews.co.uk/software/s733.htm April 2009 Review of SimplyMEPIS 8.0]
*[http://www.linux.com/feature/153431 Review of SimplyMEPIS 8.0 Beta 5]
*[http://www.junauza.com/2007/11/antix-fat-free-mepis.html antiX M-7, The Fat-free Mepis]
*[http://kmandla.wordpress.com/2007/09/21/mepis-antix-on-450mhz-k6-2-256mb/ MEPIS AntiX on 450Mhz K6-2, 256Mb]

{{Linux distributions}}

[[Category:Debian-based distributions]]
[[Category:Operating system distributions bootable from read-only media]]
[[Category:KDE]]
[[Category:X86-64 Linux distributions]]

[[ar:ميبيس]]
[[ca:Mepis]]
[[cs:MEPIS]]
[[de:MEPIS]]
[[es:MEPIS]]
[[fa:مپیس]]
[[fr:MEPIS]]
[[ko:메피스]]
[[it:MEPIS]]
[[lt:MEPIS]]
[[nl:MEPIS]]
[[ja:MEPIS]]
[[no:MEPIS]]
[[pl:Mepis]]
[[ro:MEPIS]]
[[ru:MEPIS]]
[[simple:MEPIS]]
[[sk:MEPIS]]
[[fi:Mepis]]
[[sv:MEPIS]]
[[vi:MEPIS]]
[[zh:MEPIS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
