<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4278757" ns="0" title="Javier Mariscal"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Javier mariscal.jpg|thumb|right|Javier Mariscal]]
'''Javier Mariscal''' is a [[Valencian Community|Valencian]] Spanish artist and designer whose work has spanned a wide range of mediums, ranging from painting and sculpture to interior design and landscaping. He was born in February 1950 in the city of [[Valencia, Spain]], into a family of eleven brothers and sisters. Since 1970, he has been living and working in [[Barcelona]].

==Career==
Mariscal's language is synthetic, with few strokes and a great deal of expressiveness. He started studying design at the Elisava School in Barcelona which he soon left so that he could learn directly in his environment and follow his own creative impulses. His first steps were in the world of underground comic, a task that he soon combined with illustration, sculpture, graphic design and interior design.

In 1979, he designed the [[Bar Cel Ona]] logo, a work that would make him popular. The following year, he opened the first bar in Valencia designed by Mariscal, together with [[Fernando Salas]], the Duplex, for which he designed one of his most famous pieces, the Duplex stool, an authentic icon of the 1980s. In 1981, his work as a furniture designer led him to participate in the exhibition Memphis, an International Style, in Milan. In 1987, he gave an exhibition at the [[Centre Georges Pompidou]] in Paris and participated in the [[Documenta de Kassel]].

Throughout the 1980s, he designed several textile collections for Marieta and Tráfico de Modas and exhibited at the [[Vinçon]] salon in Barcelona. In 1989, [[Cobi]] was chosen as the mascot for the [[Barcelona 1992]] [[Olympic Games]]. The mascot was the centre of great controversy because of its vanguard image, although time has shown its creator to have been right and now [[Cobi]] is recognised as the most profitable mascot in the history of the modern games. He later created the cartoon series The Cobi Troupe.

He opened the [[Estudio Mariscal]] in 1989 and has collaborated in several projects with designers and architects such as [[Arata Isozaki]], [[Alfredo Arribas]], Fernando Salas, Fernando Amat and Pepe Cortés. His most notable works include the visual identities for the Swedish socialist party, [[Socialdemokraterna]]; the Spanish radio station [[Onda Cero]]; Barcelona Zoo; the [[University of Valencia]]; the [[Lighthouse]] Centre for Architecture and Design in Glasgow, the [[GranShip]] Cultural Centre in Japan and the London postproduction company, Framestore.

In 1995, [[Twipsy]] was chosen as the mascot for the [[Hannover 2000 Expo]]. The success of this mascot led to the Twipsy series, in which the star is a virtual space messenger and the action is set in Internet.  Twipsy was sold to over one hundred countries. In 1995, he also designed the Amorosos Furniture collection for the Italian manufacturer [[Moroso]], which includes one of his most successful pieces of furniture, the Alexandra armchair, in which the organic shapes and the use he makes of colour communicate the vital, extroverted style that characterises Mariscal's objects.

In 1995, Mariscal, with lots of schoolchildren in the [[Land of Valencia]] created a collective mural sculpture during protest days for the use of the [[Valencian language]] in the education. The mural is now located  in the Teacher's Faculty of the [[University of Valencia]] and open to the public free of charge.

[[image:Mariscalets 1.JPG|200px|thumb|right|Partial view of the mural created by Xavier Mariscal and students of schools in Valencian as part of &quot;Meeting of Schools in Valencian (language)&quot; in 1995.]]

In 2001, he designed the much sought after diary room chair used in [[Channel 4]]'s second instalment of [[Big Brother (UK series 2)|Big Brother]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-75413163.html &quot;Big, posh Brother&quot;,] [[The Daily Mirror]], 9 June 2001 (now archived on Highbeam, accessdate 6 July 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.designweek.co.uk/news/digest/1113541.article &quot;Digest&quot;,] [[Design Week]], 31 May 2001 (accessdate 6 July 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, his multidisciplinary career culminated with the integral design of the Gran Hotel Domine Bilbao, nestling between the [[Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao]] and the ria, the creative concept of which is based on reflecting the history of design of the 20th century. Mariscal designed things from the uniforms to the façade, including the graphic image and its website. He did the interior design of the GHDB with [[Fernando Salas]], who also collaborated in Calle 54 Club, a project in which Fernando Trueba also forms part and which provides Madrid with a live space where the most prestigious Latin jazz musicians perform, such as [[Bebo Valdés]] and [[Paquito D'Rivera]]. Madrid is also the home of Hotel Puerta América, belonging to the Silken Group, a project in which the best architecture and design studios of the moment participated. Estudio Mariscal and Fernando Salas were responsible for the interior design of the eleventh floor.

Another sample of his interdisciplinary vocation is the audiovisual show Colors, which premiered in Barcelona in 1999 and starred the robot Dimitri, another of Mariscal's creatures. The script of Colors has been adapted for the frequent conferences on design he gives all over the world which, rather than conferences are entertaining pocket shows marked with humour and tenderness.

[[Image:Alexandra.png|thumb|100px|right|Sillón Alexandra, para Moroso]]
In 2005, he made several objects for the children's collection, Me Too, by [[Magis]], a fruitful collaboration that is still under way. Some of his most recent works, which he continues to combine with his artistic task, are the image of the Spanish financial institution, Bancaja; that of the [[32nd America's Cup]], of the new brand of bags for [[Camper (company)|Camper]], Camper For Hands, as well as the interior design of the Ikea Restaurant in Vitoria. In 2006, he participated in [[ARCO]] with the sculpture, Crash!, a homage to the optimist design of the 1950s and a way of telling us that that confidence in the future has exploded because now we need to think about how to make a future possible.

In 2009, from 1 July until 1 November,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2009/jun/27/exhibitions-preview-javier-mariscal &quot;Exhibitions preview: Javier Mariscal/Jan Kaplický, London&quot;,] [[The Guardian]], 27 June 2009 (accessdate 6 July 2009).&lt;/ref&gt; a major UK retrospective of Mariscal's work is being shown at the London [[Design Museum]], in which visitors enter through a tunnel showing 640 examples of the designer's style from 1970 to the present day, including his [[typeface]]s. He will also be creating a mural for the outside of the Design Museum itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/3979 &quot;Bright, colourful, refreshing. This exhibition is perfect for a hot summer's day in London&quot;], London SE1, 2 July 2009 (accessdate 6 July 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

Mariscal drew and co-directed, with Oscar-winning director [[Fernando Trueba]], the 2010 British/Spanish animated feature-length film ''[[Chico and Rita]]''. The film celebrates the music and culture of [[Cuba]] and depicts a love story set against backdrops of [[Havana]], [[New York City|New York]], [[Las Vegas metropolitan area|Las Vegas]], [[Hollywood]] and [[Paris]] in the late [[1940s]] and early [[1950s|'50s]].

==Awards==
In 1999, Mariscal received the National Design Prize of the Spanish Department of Industry and the BCD Foundation grants in recognition of achievements throughout a professional career.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mariscal.com Estudio Mariscal]
* [http://www.mariscalsketches.com Mariscal Sketches]
* [http://www.mariscaldrawinglife.com/ Mariscal Drawing Life - UK retrospective]
* [http://www.idfxmagazine.com/story.asp?sectioncode=90&amp;storycode=2673&amp;c=3 Javier Mariscal Profile on IDFX Magazine]
* [http://www.granhoteldominebilbao.com Gran Hotel Domine Bilbao]
* [http://www.hotelpuertamerica.com Hotel Puerta America]
* [http://www.americascup.com America's Cup]
* [http://www.calle54.net Calle 54]
* [http://www.restauranteikea.com Restaurante Ikea]
* [http://www.thelighthouse.co.uk The Light House]
* [http://www.granship.or.jp Granship]
* [http://www.magisdesign.com Magis Design]
* [http://www.moroso.it Moroso]
* [http://www.premiosnacionalesdediseno.com National Prize of Design]
* [http://www.arteseleccion.com/ventanas/autor/autor.php?idioma=en&amp;id=36&amp;autor= Javier Mariscal: the artist]
* [http://bartolomy.com/blog/?p=1322 Javier Mariscal portraits @ Design Museum]

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Mariscal, Javier
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1950
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 2011
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mariscal, Javier}}
[[Category:1950 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Valencia]]
[[Category:Valencian artists]]
[[Category:Spanish artists]]
[[Category:Spanish designers]]
[[Category:RAW (magazine)]]

[[ca:Xavier Mariscal]]
[[de:Javier Mariscal]]
[[es:Javier Mariscal]]
[[eu:Javier Mariscal]]
[[fr:Javier Mariscal]]
[[it:Javier Mariscal]]
[[nl:Javier Mariscal]]
[[pt:Javier Mariscal]]
[[sv:Javier Mariscal]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
