<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4285830" ns="0" title="Internet censorship in Pakistan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Censorship}}
{{Main|Internet in Pakistan}}

'''Internet censorship in Pakistan''' is government control of information sent and received using the [[Internet]].

== Overview ==

The [[OpenNet Initiative]] listed [[Internet filtering]] in [[Pakistan]] as substantial in the social and conflict/security areas, as selective in the Internet tools area, and as suspected in the political area in December 2010.&lt;ref name=ONI-Pakistan/&gt;

In late 2010 Pakistanis enjoyed generally unimpeded access to most sexual, political, social, and religious content on the Internet. Although the Pakistani government does not employ a sophisticated blocking system, a limitation which has led to collateral blocks on entire domains such as Blogspot.com and YouTube.com, it continues to block websites containing content it considers to be blasphemous, anti-Islamic, or threatening to internal security. Pakistan has blocked access to websites critical of the government or the military.&lt;ref name=ONI-Pakistan&gt;[http://opennet.net/research/profiles/pakistan &quot;ONI Country Profile: Pakistan&quot;], OpenNet Initiative, 26 December 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The Pakistan Internet Exchange (PIE), operated by the state-owned [[Pakistan Telecommunication Company Ltd]] (PTCL), was created to facilitate the exchange of Internet traffic between ISPs within and outside of Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nsrc.org/db/lookup/report.php?id=1085847930109:488737327&amp;fromISO=PK &quot;The current state of the Internet in Pakistan&quot;], Tee Emm, e-mail, archived by the Network Startup Resource Center (NSRC), 27 May 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Because the majority of Pakistan's Internet traffic is routed through the PIE (98% of Pakistani ISPs used the PIE in 2004), it provides a means to monitor and possibly block incoming and outgoing Internet traffic as the government deems fit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mailman.apnic.net/mailing-lists/s-asia-it/archive/2000/07/msg00028.html &quot;The National Access Point: The Dilemma of Vision&quot;], by Zubair Fasial Abbasi, e-mail sent to s-asia-it, archived at the Asia Pacific Network Information Center (APNIC), 14 July 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2003 the PTCL announced that it would be stepping up monitoring of [[pornography|pornographic]] [[website]]s. &quot;[[Criticism of Islam|Anti-Islamic]]&quot; and &quot;[[Blasphemy|blasphemous]]&quot; sites were also monitored.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.dawn.com/2003/07/28/local7.htm &quot;KARACHI: PTCL begins blocking proxy servers: Proscribed sites&quot;], Bahzad Alam , ''Dawn'', 28 July 2003Khan&lt;/ref&gt; In early March 2004, the [[Federal Investigation Agency]] (FIA) ordered [[Internet service provider]]s (ISPs) to monitor access to all pornographic content. The ISPs, however, lacked the technical know-ho, and felt that the PTCL was in a better position to carry out FIA's order. A Malaysian firm was then hired to provide a filtering system, but failed to deliver a working system.

== List of current domains/websites banned by Pakistan Telecommunication Authority (PTA) ==
* btjunkie.org
* xvideos.com
* youporn.com

== Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons ==

The [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|''Jyllands-Posten'' Muhammad cartoons controversy]] began after 12 [[editorial cartoon]]s, most of which [[Depictions of Muhammad|depicted]] the [[Islamic]] [[prophet]] [[Muhammad]], were published in the Danish [[List of newspapers in Denmark|newspaper]] ''[[Jyllands-Posten]]'' on 30 September 2005. This led to protests across the Muslim world, some of which escalated into violence with instances of firing on crowds of protestors, resulting in more than 100 reported deaths,&lt;ref name=&quot;web.archive.org&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date=2 March 2006| title=Cartoon Body Count|publisher=Web|url=http://www.cartoonbodycount.com/|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060326071135/http://www.cartoonbodycount.com/|archivedate=26 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; and included the [[2008 Danish embassy bombing in Islamabad|bombing of the Danish embassy in Pakistan]], setting fire to the Danish Embassies in Syria, Lebanon and Iran, storming of European buildings, and the [[Flag desecration|burning]] of the [[flag of Denmark|Danish]], [[flag of the Netherlands|Dutch]], [[flag of Norway|Norwegian]], [[flag of France|French]], and [[flag of Germany|German]] flags in [[Gaza City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,399177,00.html
|title=Arson and Death Threats as Muhammad Caricature Controversy Escalates
|date=4 February 2006
|publisher=Spiegel online
|accessdate=26 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/02/04/syria.cartoon/
|title=Embassies torched in cartoon fury
|date=5 February 2006
|publisher=CNN.com
|accessdate=26 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The posting of the cartoons [[online]] added to the controversy. 

On 1 March 2006 the [[Supreme Court of Pakistan]] directed the [[Government of Pakistan|government]] to keep tabs on Internet sites displaying the cartoons and called for an explanation from authorities as to why these sites had not been blocked earlier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.asiaarts.ucla.edu/071102/article.asp?parentid=40226 | publisher=Dawn | title= Blasphemous websites be blocked, orders SC | date=2 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 March 2006, pursuant to a petition filed under Article 184(3) of the [[Constitution of Pakistan]], the Supreme Court sitting ''en banc'' ordered the Pakistan Telecommunications Authority (PTA) and other government departments to adopt measures for blocking websites showing blasphemous content. The Court also ordered Attorney General [[Makhdoom Ali Khan]] to explore laws which would enable blocking of objectionable websites. In announcing the decision, [[Chief Justice of Pakistan|Chief Justice]] [[Iftikhar Muhammad Chaudhry]], said, &quot;We will not accept any excuse or technical objection on this issue because it relates to the sentiments of the entire [[Islam|Muslim]] world. All authorities concerned will have to appear in the Court on the next hearing with reports of concrete measures taken to implement our order&quot;.

Consequently, the government kept tabs on a number of websites hosting the cartoons deemed to be sacrilegious. This ban included all the [[weblog]]s hosted at the popular [[blog]]ging service [[blogger.com]], as some bloggers had put up copies of the cartoons &amp;ndash; particularly many non-Pakistani blogs.

A three-member bench headed by Chief Justice Chaudhry, summoned the country's Attorney General as well as senior communication ministry officials to give a report of &quot;concrete measures for implementation of the court's order&quot;. At the hearing on 14 March 2006, the PTA informed the Supreme Court that all websites displaying the [[Muhammad]] cartoons had been blocked. The bench issued directions to the Attorney General of Pakistan, [[Makhdoom Ali Khan]], to assist the court on how it could exercise jurisdiction to prevent the availability of blasphemous material on websites the world over.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://archives.dawn.com/2006/03/14/top16.htm | title= Websites blocked, PTA tells SC: Blasphemous material | date=14 March 2006 | publisher= Dawn}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The blanket ban on the blogspot.com blogs was lifted on 2 May 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[[n:Blogspot ban lifted in Pakistan|&quot;Blogspot ban lifted in Pakistan&quot;]], Wikinews, 6 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter the blanket ban was reimposed and extended to [[Typepad]] blogs. The blanket ban on the blogspot.com blogs was later lifted again.

It has been suggested by some Pakistani vigilante web sites and electoral process watchdog groups that the blocks were imposed largely to distract viewers from videos alleging vote-rigging by the ruling [[Muttahida Qaumi Movement|MQM]] party in the recently concluded general elections.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} Allegations of suppressing vote-rigging videos by the [[Musharraf]] administration were also leveled by Pakistani bloggers, newspapers, media, and Pakistani anti-Musharraf opposition parties. The ban was lifted on 26 February 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAK-ban-lifted&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title = Pakistan lifts YouTube ban | url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/02/27/2173501.htm?section=world | publisher = ABC News (Australia) | date = 27 February 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=RSF /&gt;

== Ethno-separatism websites ==

In 2006 the [[Pakistan Telecommunication Authority]] blocked five [[websites]] for &quot;providing misleading informations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pakistan451.wordpress.com/2006/04/27/pta-letter-blocking-websites-april-25-06/ PTA letter blocking websites], Pakistan 451, 25 April 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Some allege that the websites' real crime was reporting on the [[Balochistan conflict|Balochistan separatist conflict]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://politicalpakistan.blogspot.com/2006/04/mush-nervous.html &quot;Mush the Nervous&quot;], The Glasshouse Blog, 28 April 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

== YouTube ==

[[YouTube]] was blocked in [[Pakistan]] following a decision taken by the [[Pakistan Telecommunication Authority]] on 22 February 2007 because of the number of &quot;non-Islamic objectionable videos.&quot;&lt;ref name=RSF&gt;{{cite news| publisher=Reporters Without Borders | url=http://en.rsf.org/pakistan-youtube-access-unblocked-after-27-02-2008,25889.html | title=Access to YouTube blocked until further notice because of &quot;non-Islamic&quot; videos |date=27 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/may/19/facebook-blocked-pakistan-muhammad-drawings &quot;Pakistan blocks Facebook in row over Muhammad drawings&quot;], Declan Walsh, ''The Guardian'', 19 May 2010&lt;/ref&gt; One report specifically named [[Fitna (film)|Fitna]], a controversial Dutch film, as the basis for the block.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7261727.stm &quot;Pakistan blocks YouTube website&quot;], ''BBC News'', 24 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan, an [[Islamic republic]], ordered its ISPs to block access to YouTube &quot;for containing blasphemous web content/movies.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;YahooNews&quot;&gt;[http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5io-SE_bmENEzM46rwdVuDt9iK5zg &quot;Pakistan blocks YouTube for 'blasphemous' content: officials&quot;], ''Agence France-Presse (AFP)'', 24 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The action effectively blocked YouTube access worldwide for several hours on 24 February.&lt;ref name=CNN&gt;[http://bookchin.net/trip-research/youtube/pakistanBlocksYoutube.html &quot;Pakistan move knocked out YouTube&quot;], ''CNN'', 25 February 2008, retrieved 14 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Defaming Muhammad under รยง 295-C of the [[Blasphemy law in Pakistan]] requires a death sentence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thepersecution.org/archive/10_c.html &quot;Section 295-C&quot;], ''Pakistan Criminal Code'', 12 October 1986&lt;/ref&gt;

== Draw Muhammad Day ==

On the 19th and 20th of May 2010, Pakistan's Telecommunication Authority (PTA) imposed a ban on [[Wikipedia]], [[YouTube]], [[Flickr]], and [[Facebook]] in response to a competition entitled &quot;Draw Muhammad Day&quot; on Facebook.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iqKZNUdJFQ6c8ctdkUW0C-vktIEA &quot;Pakistan blocks Facebook over Mohammed cartoon&quot;], Waqar Hussain, ''Agence France-Presse (AFP)'', 19 May 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The competition involved drawing caricatures and cartoons depicting the image of the [[Prophet of Islam]], [[Muhammad]]. The ban imposed on Facebook was the result of a ruling by the Lahore High Court, while the ban on the other websites was imposed arbitrarily by the PTA on the grounds of &quot;objectionable content&quot; on these websites. The Facebook Terms of Service were being violated by the objectionable drawings and Facebook did not remove them of its own accord. This was a different response from earlier requests by the Pakistani government to remove objectionable content, as was the case when pages being created to promote peaceful demonstrations in Pakistani cities were removed because they were &quot;inciting violence&quot;.

== See also ==
* [[Censorship in Pakistan]]
* [[Censorship in South Asia]]
* [[Constitution of Pakistan]]
* [[Censorship]]
* [[Internet censorship]]
* [[Freedom of the press]]
* [[Freedom of speech]]
* [[Internet in Pakistan]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/urdu/pakistan/story/2006/07/060729_ptc_website.shtml &quot;Ban on the web in the national interest&quot;] (Urdu), Reba Shahid, ''BBC Urdu.com'', 29 July 2006, [http://www.google.com/translate_c?langpair=en&amp;u=http://www.bbc.co.uk/urdu/pakistan/story/2006/07/060729_ptc_website.shtml (English translation)]
*[http://kuj.com.pk Karachi Union of Journalists], website

{{Social issues in Pakistan}}
{{internet censorship}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Internet Censorship In Pakistan}}
[[Category:Pakistani media|Internet censorship]]
[[Category:Pakistani law]]
[[Category:Internet censorship by country|Pakistan]]
[[Category:Censorship in Pakistan|Pakistan]]
[[Category:Internet in Pakistan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
