<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="42878" ns="0" title="Nevil Maskelyne"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=October 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Other persons}}

{{Infobox scientist
|name              = Rev. Dr Nevil Maskelyne
|image             = Maskelyne Nevil.jpg
|image_size       = 240px
|birth_date        = {{birth date|1732|10|6|df=y}}
|birth_place       = London, England
|death_date        = {{death date and age|1811|2|9|1732|10|6|df=y}}
|death_place       = [[Greenwich]], England
|nationality       = United Kingdom
|field             = [[Astronomy]]
|work_institutions = Fellow of the [[Royal Society]], 1758&lt;br&gt;Fellow of the [[Royal Society of Edinburgh]], 1784
|alma_mater        = 
|doctoral_advisor  = 
|doctoral_students = 
|known_for         = [[Astronomer Royal]]
|influences        = 
|influenced        = 
|prizes            = [[Copley medal|Royal Society Copley Medal]], 1775
|footnotes         = 
|signature         =
}}

The Reverend Dr '''Nevil Maskelyne''' [[Fellow of the Royal Society|FRS]] (6 October 1732 – 9 February 1811) was the fifth English [[Astronomer Royal]]. He held the office from 1765 to 1811.

==Biography==
Maskelyne was born in London, the third son of Edmund Maskelyne of [[Purton]], Wiltshire. Maskelyne's father died when he was 12, leaving the family in reduced circumstances. Maskelyne attended [[Westminster School]] and was still a pupil there when his mother died in 1748. His interest in astronomy had begun while at Westminster School, shortly after the [[eclipse]] of 25 July 1748.

Maskelyne entered [[St Catharine's College, Cambridge]] in 1749, graduating as seventh [[Wrangler (University of Cambridge)|wrangler]] in 1754.&lt;ref&gt;{{Venn|MSKN749N}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ordained]] as a [[Minister (Christianity)|minister]] in 1755, he became a [[fellow]] of [[Trinity College, Cambridge]] in 1756.

About 1785 Maskelyne married Sophia Rose of [[Cotterstock]], Northamptonshire. Their only child, Margaret (1786–1858), was the mother of [[Nevil Story Maskelyne|Mervyn Herbert Nevil Story-Maskelyne]] (1823–1911) professor of mineralogy at Oxford (1856–95).  Maskelyne's sister, Margaret, married [[Robert Clive, 1st Baron Clive|Robert Clive]].

Nevil Maskelyne is buried in the churchyard of St Mary the Virgin, the parish church of the village of [[Purton]], Wiltshire, England.&lt;ref&gt;Maskelyne's grave can be seen by going through the church gates and veering to the right, against the right outside wall of the church.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
===Measurement of longitude===
In 1758 Maskelyne was admitted to the [[Royal Society]], which in 1761 despatched him to the island of [[St. Helena]] to observe the [[transit of Venus]]. This was an important observation since accurate measurements would allow the accurate calculation of Earth's distance from the Sun, which would in turn allow the scale of the [[solar system]] to be calculated.

Bad weather prevented any useful observations, however Maskelyne used his journey to develop a method of determining [[longitude]] using the position of the moon, which became known as the [[Lunar distance (navigation)|lunar distance method]]. He returned to England, resuming his position as [[curate]] at [[Chipping Barnet]] in 1761, and began work on a book, publishing the lunar distance method of longitude calculation in 1763 in ''The British Mariner's Guide'', which included the suggestion that to facilitate the finding of [[longitude]] at sea, lunar distances should be calculated beforehand for each year and published in a form accessible to navigators. This proposal, the germ of the [[Nautical almanac|Nautical Almanac]], was approved by the government, and under the care of Maskelyne the Nautical Almanac for 1767 was published in 1766. He further induced the government to print his observations annually.

Despite a possible conflict of interests, Maskelyne being an advocate of the lunar distance method of determining longitude, the [[Board of Longitude]] sent him to [[Barbados]] in 1763 to calculate the longitude of the capital, [[Bridgetown]] by observation of [[Jupiter]]'s satellites, and also to test his lunar distance method and compare its accuracy to [[John Harrison]]'s [[chronometer]], the ''No. 4 timekeeper''. Even after a successful trial in Barbados in 1764 observed by Maskelyne, Harrison was required to produce detailed drawings and build two more chronometers, one of which was eventually tested by [[King George III]] himself.

The results of the voyage were made public at a meeting of the Board of Longitude in early 1765, where it was disclosed that Harrison's chronometer had produced Bridgetown's longitude with an error of less than ten miles after a sea voyage of more than 5,000 miles. Maskelyne's method on the other hand showed an error of 30 miles. However, four of the naval officers present stated that their calculations had been performed to Maskelyne's instructions and were therefore subject to their inexperience. Also, since the lunar distance method relied on tables that only Maskelyne was capable of calculating, the method was not yet in a position to take the prize.

However, two Astronomers Royal had recently died in quick succession and Maskelyne was appointed to the position soon after his return to England. The position automatically made him an [[ex-officio]] member of the Board of Longitude and it was not long before a negative report was made on Harrison's chronometer, Maskelyne refusing to allow for the known rate at which Harrison's chronometer gained or lost time and thus dismissing it as inaccurate.&lt;ref name=&quot;sobel&quot;&gt;Sobel, Dava, ''Longitude: The True Story of a Lone Genius Who Solved the Greatest Scientific Problem of His Time'', Walker and Company, New York, 1995  ISBN 0-8027-1312-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Landes&quot;&gt;Landes, David S., ''Revolution in Time'', Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, Cambridge Mass., 1983, ISBN 0-674-76800-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gould&quot;&gt;Gould, Rupert T. ''The Marine Chronometer. Its History and Development'' London: J. D. Potter, 1923, ISBN 0-907462-05-7&lt;/ref&gt;  He was not alone in his position on lunar distances; other members of the Board of Longitude and the Royal Society were also strongly biased toward lunars, as they saw the scientific solution being conceptually and intellectually superior to the mechanic's solution.  When eventually Harrison was paid the money owing to him, it was by a special [[Act of Parliament]] rather than the Board of Longitude.

Nonetheless, while chronometers were indeed more accurate, the lunar distance method was cheaper and was the predominant method used well into the 19th century.  Since Maskelyne's observations and calculations were made at the [[Royal Greenwich Observatory]], the [[Greenwich meridian]] eventually became a common base for longitude worldwide and was adopted internationally as the [[Prime Meridian]] in 1884.&lt;ref&gt;(JR Wills The Royal Society)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Measurement of latitude===
Maskelyne took a great interest in various [[geodetics|geodetical]] operations, notably the measurement of the length of a degree of latitude in [[Maryland]] and [[Pennsylvania]],&lt;ref name=&quot;PTRS323&quot;&gt;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society. lviii. 323&lt;/ref&gt; executed by [[Charles Mason|Mason]] and [[Jeremiah Dixon|Dixon]] in 1766 – 1768, and later the determination of the relative longitude of [[Greenwich]] and Paris.&lt;ref name=&quot;PTRS151&quot;&gt;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society. lxxvii. 151&lt;/ref&gt;  On the French side the work was conducted by [[Dominique, comte de Cassini|Count Cassini]], [[Adrien-Marie Legendre|Legendre]], and [[Pierre Méchain|Méchain]]; on the English side by [[William Roy|General Roy]]. This triangulation was the beginning of the [[Principal Triangulation of Great Britain|great trigonometrical survey]] which was subsequently extended all over Britain. His observations appeared in four large folio volumes from 1776–1811, some of them being reprinted in [[Samuel Vince]]'s ''Elements of Astronomy''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Vince | first = Samuel | authorlink = Samuel Vince | title = The Elements of Astronomy: Designed for the Use of Students in the University | publisher=J. Smith | year = 1811 | url = | id = | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Schiehallion experiment===
In 1772 Maskelyne proposed to the [[Royal Society]] what was to become known as the ''[[Schiehallion experiment]]'' (named after the mountain on which it was performed), for the determination of the [[Earth]]’s density using a [[plumb line]]. He was not the first to suggest this, [[Pierre Bouguer]] and [[Charles-Marie de la Condamine]] having attempted the same experiment in 1738.

Maskelyne performed his experiment in 1774 on Schiehallion in [[Perthshire]], Scotland,&lt;ref name=&quot;PTRS495&quot;&gt;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society. 1. 495&lt;/ref&gt; the mountain being chosen due to its regular conical shape which permitted a reasonably accurate determination of its volume. The apparent difference of [[latitude]] between two stations on opposite sides of the mountain were compared with the real difference of latitude obtained by [[triangulation]].

From Maskelyne’s observations [[Charles Hutton]] deduced a density for the earth 4.5 times that of water (the modern value is 5.515).

==Other work==
Maskelyne’s first contribution to astronomical literature was ''A Proposal for Discovering the Annual [[Parallax]] of [[Sirius]]'', published in 1760.&lt;ref name=&quot;PTRS889&quot;&gt;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society. ii. 889&lt;/ref&gt;  Subsequent contributions to the ''Transactions'' contained his observations of the transits of [[Venus]] (1761 and 1769), on the tides at [[Saint Helena]] (1762), and on various astronomical phenomena at Saint Helena (1764) and at [[Barbados]] (1764).

Maskelyne also introduced several practical improvements, such as the measurement of time to tenths of a second; and prevailed upon the government to replace [[John Bird (astronomer)|Bird]]’s [[Mural instrument|mural quadrant]] by a [[repeating circle]] 6 feet (1.8 m) in diameter. The new instrument was constructed by [[Edward Troughton]] but Maskelyne did not live to see it completed.

==Maskelyne in literature and the arts==

* Maskelyne features prominently in [[Dava Sobel]]'s 1995 book, ''Longitude: The True Story of a Lone Genius Who Solved the Greatest Scientific Problem of His Time'', as well as the [[Longitude (TV serial)|A&amp;E miniseries]] based on the same.

* Maskelyne is a supporting character in ''[[Mason &amp; Dixon]]'' by [[Thomas Pynchon]].

* Maskelyne is portrayed as &quot;Dr. Vickery&quot; in [[Kate Grenville]]'s semi-historical novel ''[[The Lieutenant (novel)|The Lieutenant]]''.

==Honours==

* 1775 – Awarded the Royal Society's [[Copley medal]]

* The lunar crater [[Maskelyne (crater)|Maskelyne]] is named for him.

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
* [[W. W. Rouse Ball]], ''A History of the Study of Mathematics at Cambridge University'', 1889, repr. [[Cambridge University Press]], 2009, ISBN 978-1-108-00207-3, p.&amp;nbsp;108

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | author=Howse, Derek | title = Nevil Maskelyne: The Seaman's Astronomer | year = 1989 | publisher=Cambridge University Press | isbn = }}

==External links==
* [http://janus.lib.cam.ac.uk/db/node.xsp?id=EAD%2FGBR%2F0180%2FRGO%204 Online catalogue of Maskelyne's working papers (part of the Royal Greenwich Observatory Archives held at Cambridge University Library)]

{{1911}}
 
{{Authority control|VIAF=14808697}}

{{Astronomers Royal}}
{{Copley Medallists 1751-1800}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Maskelyne, Nevil
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Fifth [[Astronomer Royal]], 1765 – 1811
|DATE OF BIRTH=6 October 1732
|PLACE OF BIRTH=London, England
|DATE OF DEATH=9 February 1811
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Greenwich]], England
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Maskelyne, Nevil}}
[[Category:1732 births]]
[[Category:1811 deaths]]
[[Category:People from London]]
[[Category:Alumni of St Catharine's College, Cambridge]]
[[Category:Alumni of Trinity College, Cambridge]]
[[Category:Astronomers Royal]]
[[Category:English astronomers]]
[[Category:English clergy]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal Society]]
[[Category:Old Westminsters]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Copley Medal]]
[[Category:18th-century astronomers]]
[[Category:19th-century astronomers]]
[[Category:18th-century English people]]
[[Category:19th-century English people]]

[[ca:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[de:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[es:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[fr:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[it:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[nl:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[ja:ネヴィル・マスケリン]]
[[no:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[pl:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[pt:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[ru:Маскелайн, Невил]]
[[sl:Nevil Maskelyne]]
[[uk:Невіль Маскелін]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
