<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="42978" ns="0" title="Jack London"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{Other people}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name        = Jack London
| image       = Jack London young.jpg
| imagesize   = 250px
| caption     = London in 1903
| birth_name  = John Griffith Chaney
| birth_date  = {{Birth date|mf=yes|1876|1|12}}
| birth_place = [[San Francisco]], [[California]] &lt;br /&gt; [[United States]]
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|mf=yes|1916|11|22|1876|1|12}}
| death_place = [[Glen Ellen, California]] &lt;br /&gt; United States
| occupation  = [[Novelist]], [[journalist]], [[short story]] writer and [[essayist]]
| movement    = [[realism (arts)|Realism]] and [[Naturalism (literature)|Naturalism]]
| influenced  = [[Richard Wright (author)|Richard Wright]], [[Jack Kerouac]], [[Robert E. Howard]], [[George Orwell]], [[Scott Sigler]], [[Anton LaVey]], [[Christopher McCandless]], [[Margaret Atwood]]
| influences  = [[Ouida]], [[Charles Darwin]], [[Herbert Spencer]], [[Friedrich Nietzsche]], [[David Starr Jordan]], [[Thomas Henry Huxley]], [[John Tyndall]], [[Ernest Haeckel]], [[Karl Marx]]
| signature   = Jack London Signature.svg
}}

'''John Griffith &quot;Jack&quot; London''' (born '''John Griffith Chaney''',{{sfn|Reesman|2009|p=[http://books.google.com/books?id=fbrV_fwgcq4C&amp;pg=PA23 23]}} January 12, 1876 – November 22, 1916)&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.library.eb.com/eb/article-9048828 London, Jack]&quot;. Encyclopædia Britannica Online Library Edition. Retrieved 2011-10-05.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/BioRC Dictionary of American Biography Base Set]''. American Council of Learned Societies, 1928–1936. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Thomson Gale. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|London|1939|p=12}}{{sfn|New York Times November 23, 1916}} was an American author, journalist, and social activist. He was a pioneer in the then-burgeoning world of commercial magazine fiction and was one of the first fiction writers to obtain worldwide celebrity and a large fortune from his fiction alone.&lt;ref&gt;(1910) &quot;Specialty of Short-story Writing,&quot; The Writer, XXII, January–December 1910, p. 9: &quot;There are eight American writers who can get $1000 for a short story—[[Robert W. Chambers]], [[Richard Harding Davis]], Jack London, [[O. Henry]], [[Booth Tarkington]], [[John Fox, Jr.]], [[Owen Wister]], and [[Frances Hodgson Burnett|Mrs. Burnett]].&quot; $1,000 in 1910&amp;nbsp;dollars is roughly equivalent to ${{Formatnum:{{Inflation|US|1000|1910|r=-3}}}} today&lt;/ref&gt; He is best remembered as the author of ''[[Call of the Wild]]'' and ''[[White Fang]]'', both set in the [[Klondike Gold Rush]], as well as the short stories &quot;[[To Build a Fire]]&quot;, &quot;An Odyssey of the North&quot;, and &quot;Love of Life&quot;.{{citation needed|date=March 2011}} He also wrote of the South Pacific in such stories as &quot;The Pearls of Parlay&quot; and &quot;The Heathen&quot;, and of the San Francisco Bay area in ''[[The Sea Wolf]]''.

London was a passionate advocate of unionization, socialism, and the rights of workers and wrote several powerful works dealing with these topics such as his dystopian novel, ''[[The Iron Heel]]'' and his non-fiction exposé, ''[[The People of the Abyss]]''.

== Family ==

[[File:Flora Wellman.jpg|thumb|upright|Flora Wellman]]

Jack London's mother, Flora Wellman, was the fifth and youngest child of [[Pennsylvania Canal]] builder Marshall Wellman and his first wife, Eleanor Garrett Jones.  Marshall Wellman was a great-great-great-grandson of Puritan [[Thomas Wellman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wellman1918&quot;&gt;Wellman, Joshua Wyman ''Descendants of Thomas Wellman'' (1918) Arthur Holbrook Wellman, Boston p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;  Flora left Ohio and moved to the Pacific coast when her father remarried after her mother died.  In San Francisco, Flora worked as a music teacher and [[Spiritualist]] claiming to channel the spirit of an [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indian]] chief.&lt;ref name=&quot;london&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.jacklondons.net/writings/BookJackLondon/Volume1/chapter1.html | title = The Book of Jack London | publisher = The World of Jack London | accessdate = 2011-04-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Biographer Clarice Stasz and others believe that London's father was [[astrologer]] William Chaney.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Stasz|2001|p=14}}: &quot;What supports Flora's naming Chaney as the father of her son are, first, the indisputable fact of their cohabiting at the time of his conception;, and second, the absence of any suggestion on the part of her associates that another man could have been responsible... [but] unless [[DNA]] evidence is introduced, whether or not William Chaney was the biological father of Jack London cannot be decided.... Chaney would, however, be considered by her son and his children as their ancestor.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Flora Wellman was living with Chaney in San Francisco when she became pregnant. Whether Wellman and Chaney were legally married is unknown. Most [[San Francisco]] civil records were destroyed by the extensive fires that followed the [[1906 San Francisco earthquake|1906 earthquake]]; it is not known with certainty what name appeared on his birth certificate. Stasz notes that in his memoirs, Chaney refers to London's mother Flora Wellman as having been his &quot;wife&quot; and also cites an advertisement in which Flora called herself &quot;Florence Wellman Chaney&quot;.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}}

According to Flora Wellman's account, as recorded in the ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' of June 4, 1875, Chaney demanded that she have an [[abortion]]. When she refused, he disclaimed responsibility for the child. In desperation, she shot herself. She was not seriously wounded, but she was temporarily deranged. After she gave birth, Flora turned the baby over to ex-[[slave]] Virginia Prentiss, who remained a major maternal figure throughout London's life. Late in 1876, Flora Wellman married John London, a partially disabled [[American Civil War|Civil War]] veteran, and brought her baby John, later known as Jack, to live with the newly married couple. The family moved around the [[San Francisco Bay Area]] before settling in [[Oakland]], where London completed [[grade school]].

In 1897, when he was 21 and a student at the [[University of California, Berkeley]], London searched for and read the newspaper accounts of his mother's suicide attempt and the name of his biological father. He wrote to William Chaney, then living in [[Chicago, Illinois|Chicago]]. Chaney responded that he could not be London's father because he was impotent; he casually asserted that London's mother had relations with other men and averred that she had slandered him when she said he insisted on an abortion. He concluded that he was more to be pitied than London.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=53–54}} London was devastated by his father's letter. In the months following, he quit school at Berkeley and went to the [[Klondike Gold Rush|Klondike]].

== Early life ==

[[File:Jack London age 9 - crop.jpg|thumb|left|upright|London at the age of nine with his dog Rollo, 1885]]

London was born near Third and Brannan Streets in [[San Francisco]]. The house burned down in the fire after the [[1906 San Francisco earthquake]]; the [[California Historical Society]] placed a plaque at the site in 1953. Though the family was working class, it was not as impoverished as London's later accounts claimed. London was essentially self-educated.

In 1885 London found and read [[Ouida]]'s long [[Victorian era|Victorian]] novel ''Signa''. He credited this as the seed of his literary success.&lt;ref&gt;London, Jack (1917) &quot;Eight Factors of Literary Success&quot;, in Labor (1994), p. 512. &quot;In answer to your question as to the greatest factors of my literary success, I will state that I consider them to be: Vast good luck. Good health; good brain; good mental and muscular correlation. Poverty. Reading Ouida's ''Signa'' at eight years of age. The influence of Herbert Spencer's ''Philosophy of Style.'' Because I got started twenty years before the fellows who are trying to start today.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In 1886 he went to the [[Oakland Public Library]] and found a sympathetic librarian, [[Ina Coolbrith]], who encouraged his learning. (She later became California's first ''[[poet laureate]]'' and an important figure in the San Francisco literary community).

In 1889, London began working 12 to 18&amp;nbsp;hours a day at Hickmott's Cannery. Seeking a way out, he borrowed money from his black foster mother Virginia Prentiss, bought the [[sloop]] ''Razzle-Dazzle'' from an [[oyster pirate]] named French Frank, and became an oyster pirate. In his memoir, [[John Barleycorn (novel)|''John Barleycorn'']], he claims to have stolen French Frank's mistress Mamie.&lt;ref&gt;{{Gutenberg|no=318|name=John Barleycorn '', by Jack London''}} Chapters VII, VIII describe his stealing of Mamie, the &quot;Queen of the Oyster Pirates&quot;: &quot;The Queen asked me to row her ashore in my skiff...Nor did I understand Spider's grinning side-remark to me: &quot;Gee! There's nothin' slow about YOU.&quot; How could it possibly enter my boy's head that a grizzled man of fifty should be jealous of me?&quot; &quot;And how was I to guess that the story of how the Queen had thrown him down on his own boat, the moment I hove in sight, was already the gleeful gossip of the water-front?&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|London|1939|p=41}}&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Kingman|1979|p=37}}: &quot;It was said on the waterfront that Jack had taken on a mistress... Evidently Jack believed the myth himself at times... Jack met Mamie aboard the Razzle-Dazzle when he first approached French Frank about its purchase. Mamie was aboard on a visit with her sister Tess and her chaperone, Miss Hadley. It hardly seems likely that someone who required a chaperone on Saturday would move aboard as mistress on Monday.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; After a few months, his sloop became damaged beyond repair. London became hired as a member of the [[California Fish Patrol]].

In 1893, he signed on to the sealing [[schooner]] ''Sophie Sutherland'', bound for the coast of Japan. When he returned, the country was in the grip of the [[panic of 1893|panic of '93]] and [[Oakland, California|Oakland]] was swept by labor unrest. After grueling jobs in a [[jute mill]] and a street-railway power plant, he joined [[Kelly's Army]] and began his career as a tramp. In 1894, he spent 30&amp;nbsp;days for vagrancy in the [[Erie County, New York|Erie County]] Penitentiary at [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]]. In ''The Road'', he wrote:

{{quote |
Man-handling was merely one of the very minor unprintable horrors of the Erie County Pen. I say 'unprintable'; and in justice I must also say undescribable. They were unthinkable to me until I saw them, and I was no spring chicken in the ways of the world and the awful abysses of human degradation. It would take a deep plummet to reach bottom in the Erie County Pen, and I do but skim lightly and facetiously the surface of things as I there saw them.
}}

After many experiences as a hobo and a sailor, he returned to Oakland and attended [[Oakland High School (California)|Oakland High School]]. He contributed a number of articles to the high school's magazine, ''The Aegis''. His first published work was &quot;Typhoon off the Coast of Japan&quot;, an account of his sailing experiences.

[[File:Jack London Studying.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Jack London studying at Heinold's First and Last Chance in 1886]]

As a schoolboy, London often studied at [[Heinold's First and Last Chance Saloon|Heinold's First and Last Chance]], a port side bar in Oakland. At 17, he confessed to the bar's owner, John Heinold, his desire to attend University and pursue a career as a writer. Heinold lent London tuition money to attend college.

London desperately wanted to attend the [[University of California, Berkeley]]. In 1896 after a summer of intense studying to pass certification exams, he was admitted. Financial circumstances forced him to leave in 1897 and he never graduated. No evidence suggests that London wrote for student publications while studying at Berkeley.{{sfn|Kingman|1979|p=67}}

[[File:Heinold’s First and Last Chance 2007.jpg|thumb|Heinold's First and Last Chance, &quot;Jack London's Rendezvous&quot;]]

While at Berkeley, London continued to study and spend time at Heinold's saloon where he was introduced to the sailors and adventurers who would influence his writing. In his autobiographical novel, ''[[John Barleycorn (novel)|John Barleycorn]],'' London mentioned the pub's likeness seventeen times. Heinold's was the place where London met Alexander McLean, a captain known for his cruelty at sea,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = MacGillivray | first = Don | url = http://www.washington.edu/uwpress/search/books/MACCAP.html | title = Captain Alex MacLean | publisher = University of Washington Press | date = April 2009 | accessdate = 2011-10-06 | isbn = 978-0-7748-1471-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; whom the protagonist in London's novel [[The Sea-Wolf]], Wolf Larsen, is based.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = MacGillivray | first = Don | url = http://www.ubcpress.ca/books/pdf/chapters/2008/CaptainAlexMacLean.pdf | title = Captain Alex MacLean | format = PDF | date = 2008-03-19 | accessdate = 2011-10-06 | isbn = 978-0-7748-1471-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Heinold's First and Last Chance Saloon is now unofficially named Jack London's Rendezvous in his honor.

== Gold rush and first success ==

[[File:Jack london nd 2.jpg|thumb|upright|Jack London (date unknown)]]
[[File:Miners climb Chilkoot.jpg|thumb|Miners and prospectors ascend the Chilkoot Trail during the [[Klondike Gold Rush]]]]

On July 12, 1897, London (age 21) and his sister's husband Captain Shepard sailed to join the [[Klondike Gold Rush]]. This was the setting for some of his first successful stories. London's time in the [[Klondike, Yukon|Klondike]], however, was detrimental to his health. Like so many other men who were malnourished in the goldfields, London developed [[scurvy]]. His gums became swollen, leading to the loss of his four front teeth. A constant gnawing pain affected his hip and leg muscles, and his face was stricken with marks that always reminded him of the struggles he faced in the Klondike. [[Father William Judge]], &quot;The Saint of [[Dawson City, Yukon|Dawson]],&quot; had a facility in Dawson that provided shelter, food and any available medicine to London and others. His struggles there inspired London's short story, &quot;[[To Build a Fire]]&quot;, which many critics assess as his best.

His landlords in Dawson were mining engineers [[Marshall Latham Bond]] and [[Louis Whitford Bond]], educated at [[Yale]] and [[Stanford]]. The brothers' father, [[Judge Hiram Bond]], was a wealthy mining investor. The Bonds, especially Hiram, were active Republicans. Marshall Bond's diary mentions friendly sparring with London on political issues as a camp pastime.

London left Oakland with a social conscience and socialist leanings; he returned to become an activist for [[socialism]]. He concluded that his only hope of escaping the work &quot;trap&quot; was to get an education and &quot;sell his brains.&quot; He saw his writing as a business, his ticket out of poverty, and, he hoped, a means of beating the wealthy at their own game. On returning to California in 1898, London began working deliberately to get published, a struggle described in his novel, ''[[Martin Eden]]''. His first published story was &quot;To the Man On Trail&quot;, which has frequently been collected in anthologies. When ''The Overland Monthly'' offered him only five dollars for it—and was slow paying—London came close to abandoning his writing career. In his words, &quot;literally and literarily I was saved&quot; when ''The Black Cat'' accepted his story &quot;A Thousand Deaths,&quot; and paid him $40—the &quot;first money I ever received for a story.&quot;

London was fortunate in the timing of his writing career. He started just as new printing technologies enabled lower-cost production of magazines. This resulted in a boom in popular magazines aimed at a wide public, and a strong market for short fiction. In 1900, he made $2,500 in writing, about ${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|2500|1900|r=-3}}}} in current value. His career was well under way.

Among the works he sold to magazines was a short story known as either &quot;Batard&quot; or &quot;Diable&quot;, in two editions of the same basic story. A cruel French Canadian brutalizes his dog. The dog retaliates and kills the man. London told some of his critics that man's actions are the main cause of the behavior of their animals, and he would show this in another short story.

[[File:Mary Austin, Jack London, George Sterling, Jimmie Hooper, restored.jpg|thumb|left|[[George Sterling]], [[Mary Austin]], Jack London, and [[Jimmie Hooper]] on the beach at [[Carmel, California]]]]

In early 1903, London sold ''[[The Call of the Wild]]'' to ''[[The Saturday Evening Post]]'' for $750, and the book rights to [[Macmillan Publishers (United States)|Macmillan]] for $2,000.  Macmillan's promotional campaign propelled it to swift success.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jacklondons.net/call.html &quot;Best Dog Story Ever Written: Call of the Wild&quot;], excerpted from {{harvnb|Kingman|1979|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While living at his rented villa on [[Lake Merritt]] in Oakland, London met poet [[George Sterling]] and in time they became best friends. In 1902, Sterling helped London find a home closer to his own in nearby [[Piedmont, California|Piedmont]]. In his letters London addressed Sterling as &quot;Greek,&quot; owing to his aquiline nose and classical profile, and signed them as &quot;Wolf.&quot; London was later to depict Sterling as Russ Brissenden in his autobiographical novel ''Martin Eden'' (1910) and as Mark Hall in ''[[The Valley of the Moon (novel)|The Valley of the Moon]]'' (1913).

In later life London indulged his wide-ranging interests by accumulating a personal library of 15,000 volumes. He referred to his books as &quot;the tools of my trade.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton (1986) (as cited by other sources)&lt;/ref&gt;

== First marriage (1900–1904) ==

[[File:Jack London with daughters Bess (left) and Joan (right).jpg|thumb|left|Jack with daughters &quot;Becky&quot; (left) and Joan (right)]]
[[File:Bessie Maddern London and daughters.jpg|thumb|left|Bessie Maddern London and daughters, Joan and &quot;Becky&quot;]]

London married Elizabeth &quot;Bessie&quot; Maddern on April 7, 1900, the same day ''The Son of the Wolf'' was edited. Bess had been part of his circle of friends for a number of years. She was related to stage actresses [[Minnie Maddern Fiske]] and [[Emily Stevens (actress)|Emily Stevens]]. Stasz says, &quot;Both acknowledged publicly that they were not marrying out of love, but from friendship and a belief that they would produce sturdy children.&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Stasz|2001|p=61}}: &quot;Both acknowledged... that they were not marrying out of love&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Kingman says, &quot;they were comfortable together... Jack had made it clear to Bessie that he did not love her, but that he liked her enough to make a successful marriage.&quot;{{sfn|Kingman|1979|p=98}}

During the marriage, London continued his friendship with [[Anna Strunsky]], co-authoring ''The Kempton-Wace Letters,'' an epistolary novel contrasting two philosophies of love. Anna, writing &quot;Dane Kempton's&quot; letters, arguing for a romantic view of marriage, while London, writing &quot;Herbert Wace's&quot; letters, argued for a scientific view, based on Darwinism and eugenics. In the novel, his fictional character contrasted two women he had known.

London's pet name for Bess was &quot;Mother-Girl&quot; and Bess's for London was &quot;Daddy-Boy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Stasz|2001|p=66}}: &quot;Mommy Girl and Daddy Boy&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Their first child, Joan, was born on January 15, 1901, and their second, Bessie (later called Becky), on October 20, 1902. Both children were born in [[Piedmont, California]]. Here London wrote one of his most celebrated works, ''[[The Call of the Wild]].''

While London had pride in his children, the marriage was under strain. Kingman says that by 1903 they were close to separation as they were &quot;extremely incompatible.&quot; Nevertheless, &quot;Jack was still so kind and gentle with Bessie that when Cloudsley Johns was a house guest in February 1903 he didn't suspect a breakup of their marriage.&quot;{{sfn|Kingman|1979|p=121}}

London reportedly complained to friends Joseph Noel and George Sterling that, &quot;[Bessie] is devoted to purity. When I tell her morality is only evidence of low blood pressure, she hates me. She'd sell me and the children out for her damned purity. It's terrible. Every time I come back after being away from home for a night she won't let me be in the same room with her if she can help it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Noel|1940|p=150}}, &quot;She's devoted to purity...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Stasz writes that these were &quot;code words for [Bess's] fear that [Jack] was consorting with prostitutes and might bring home [[venereal disease]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Stasz|2001|p=80}} (&quot;devoted to purity... code words...&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 24, 1903, London told Bessie he was leaving and moved out. During 1904 London and Bess negotiated the terms of a divorce, and the decree was granted on November 11, 1904.{{sfn|Kingman|1979|p=139}}

=== Bohemian Club ===

[[File:Bohemian Grove Camp - Garnett, Sterling, London.jpg|thumb|upright|London ''(right)'' at the [[Bohemian Grove]] with his friends Porter Garnett and [[George Sterling]]; a painting parodies his story ''The White Silence'']]

On August 18, 1904, London went with his close friend, the poet George Sterling, to &quot;Summer High Jinks&quot; at the [[Bohemian Grove]]. London was elected to honorary membership in the [[Bohemian Club]] and took part in many activities. Other noted members of the Bohemian Club during this time included [[Ambrose Bierce]], [[J. Allan Dunn|Allan Dunn]], [[John Muir]], [[Gelett Burgess]], and [[Frank Norris]].

Beginning in December 1914, London worked on ''The Acorn Planter, A California Forest Play'', to be performed as one of the [[List of Grove Plays|annual Grove Plays]], but it was never selected—it was described as too difficult to set to music.{{sfn|London|Taylor|1987|p=[http://books.google.com/books?id=AFfqbTjG7OkC&amp;pg=PA394 394]}} London published ''The Acorn Planter'' in 1916.{{sfn|Wichlan|2007|p=[http://books.google.com/books?id=utnD3Wf2cV0C&amp;pg=PA131 131]}}

== Second marriage ==

[[File:Jack and Charmian London 1911.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Jack and Charmian London (ca. 1911) at the old Winery Cottage, their home at Beauty Ranch]]

After divorcing Maddern, London married [[Charmian London|Charmian Kittredge]] in 1905. London was introduced to Kittredge by his MacMillan publisher, [[George Platt Brett, Sr.]], while Kittredge served as Brett's secretary. Biographer Russ Kingman called Charmian &quot;Jack's soul-mate, always at his side, and a perfect match.&quot;&lt;!--http://www.jacklondons.net/charmianpage.html for now, better reference later--&gt; Their time together included numerous trips, including a 1907 cruise on the yacht [[The Cruise of the Snark|Snark]] to [[Hawaii]] and [[Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Sailing of the Snark,&quot; by [[J. Allan Dunn|Allan Dunn]], ''Sunset'', May 1907.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of London's stories are based on his visits to Hawaii, the last one for 10&amp;nbsp;months beginning in December 1915.{{sfn|Day|1996|pp=113–119}}

The couple also visited [[Goldfield, Nevada]] in 1907, where they were guests of the Bond brothers, London's Dawson City landlords. The Bond brothers were working in Nevada as mining engineers.

London had contrasted the concepts of the &quot;Mother Woman&quot; and the &quot;Mate Woman&quot; in ''The Kempton-Wace Letters.'' His pet name for Bess had been &quot;mother-girl;&quot; his pet name for Charmian was &quot;mate-woman.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|London|2003|p=59}}: copy of &quot;John Barleycorn&quot; inscribed &quot;Dear Mate-Woman: You know. You have helped me bury the Long Sickness and the White Logic.&quot; Numerous other examples in same source.&lt;/ref&gt; Charmian's aunt and foster mother, a disciple of [[Victoria Woodhull]], had raised her without prudishness.{{sfn|Kingman|1979|p=124}} Every biographer alludes to Charmian's uninhibited sexuality.{{sfn|Stasz|1999|p=112}}{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|p=133}}

[[File:StateLibQld 1 165259 Snark (ship).jpg|thumb|The ''Snark'' in Australia, 1921]]

Joseph Noel calls the events from 1903 to 1905 &quot;a domestic drama that would have intrigued the pen of an Ibsen.... London's had comedy relief in it and a sort of easy-going romance.&quot;{{sfn|Noel|1940|p=146}} In broad outline, London was restless in his marriage; sought extramarital sexual affairs; and found, in Charmian Kittredge, not only a sexually active and adventurous partner, but his future life-companion. They attempted to have children. One child died at birth, and another pregnancy ended in a miscarriage.

In 1906, London published in ''[[Collier's Weekly|Collier's]]'' magazine his eye-witness report of the [[1906 San Francisco earthquake|San Francisco earthquake]].

== Beauty Ranch (1905–1916) ==

[[File:LondonCottage.jpg|thumb|The old Winery Cottage, where London died (in the left [[sleeping porch]]) on November 22, 1916]]

In 1905, London purchased a {{convert|1,000|acre|km2}} ranch in [[Glen Ellen, California|Glen Ellen]], [[Sonoma County, California]], on the eastern slope of [[Sonoma Mountain]], for $26,450. He wrote that &quot;Next to my wife, the ranch is the dearest thing in the world to me.&quot; He desperately wanted the ranch to become a successful business enterprise. Writing, always a commercial enterprise with London, now became even more a means to an end: &quot;I write for no other purpose than to add to the beauty that now belongs to me. I write a book for no other reason than to add three or four hundred acres to my magnificent estate.&quot; After 1910, his literary works were mostly [[potboiler]]s, written out of the need to provide operating income for the ranch.

[[File:Jack London 1914 Sunset Magazine.jpg|left|thumb|London in 1914]]

Stasz writes that London &quot;had taken fully to heart the vision, expressed in his agrarian fiction, of the land as the closest earthly version of Eden … he educated himself through the study of agricultural manuals and scientific tomes. He conceived of a system of ranching that today would be praised for its [[ecological wisdom]].&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2011}} He was proud to own the first concrete silo in California, a circular piggery that he designed. He hoped to adapt the wisdom of Asian [[sustainable agriculture]] to the United States. He hired both Italian and Chinese stonemasons, whose distinctly different styles are obvious.

The ranch was an economic failure. Sympathetic observers such as Stasz treat his projects as potentially feasible, and ascribe their failure to bad luck or to being ahead of their time. Unsympathetic historians such as [[Kevin Starr]] suggest that he was a bad manager, distracted by other concerns and impaired by his [[alcoholism]]. Starr notes that London was absent from his ranch about six months a year between 1910 and 1916, and says, &quot;He liked the show of managerial power, but not grinding attention to detail …. London's workers laughed at his efforts to play big-time rancher [and considered] the operation a rich man's hobby.&quot;{{citation needed|date=August 2011}}

London spent $80,000 (${{Formatnum:{{Inflation|US|80000|1905|r=-4}}}} in current value) to build a {{convert|15000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} stone mansion (&quot;Wolf House&quot;) on the property. Just as the mansion was nearing completion, two weeks before the Londons planned to move in, it was destroyed by fire.

London's last visit to Hawaii,&lt;ref name=&quot;TherouxSpiritOfAloha&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.spiritofaloha.com/features/0307/writehawaii.html | title = They Came to Write in Hawai‘i | author = Joseph Theroux |work= Spirit of Aloha ([[Aloha Airlines]]) March/April 2007 |quote= He said, “Life’s not a matter of holding good cards, but sometimes playing a poor hand well.” …His last magazine piece was titled “My Hawaiian Aloha”&lt;big&gt;*&lt;/big&gt; [and] his final, unfinished novel, ''Eyes of Asia,'' was set in Hawai‘i. }} ({{cite web |url= http://www.spiritofaloha.com/features/0307/aloha.html | title = My Hawaiian Aloha | author = Jack London |work= &lt;big&gt;*&lt;/big&gt;From Stories of Hawai‘i, Mutual Publishing, [[Honolulu, Hawaii|Honolulu]], 1916. Reprinted with permission in Spirit of Aloha, November/December 2006 }})&lt;/ref&gt; beginning in December 1915, lasted eight months. He met with [[Duke Kahanamoku]], [[Jonah Kūhiō Kalaniana'ole|Prince Jonah Kūhiō Kalaniana'ole]], [[Liliuokalani|Queen Lili‘uokalani]] and many others, before returning to his ranch in July 1916.{{sfn|Day|1996|pp=113–119}} He was suffering from [[Renal failure|kidney failure]], but he continued to work.

The ranch (abutting stone remnants of Wolf House) is now a [[National Historic Landmark]] and is protected in [[Jack London State Historic Park]].

== Death ==

[[File:Jacklondongrave.jpg|thumb|left|Grave of Jack and Charmian London]]

Many older sources describe London's death as a suicide, and some still do.&lt;ref&gt;''Columbia Encyclopedia'' [http://www.bartleby.com/65/lo/London-J.html &quot;Jack London&quot;], &quot;Beset in his later years by alcoholism and financial difficulties, London committed suicide at the age of 40.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; This conjecture appears to be a rumor, or speculation based on incidents in his fiction writings. His death certificate{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Jack London's death certificate}} gives the cause as [[uremia]], following acute [[renal colic]], a type of pain often described as &quot;the worst pain [...] ever experienced&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;titleUSNews.com: Health: Kidney Stone Disease: Overview&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| author = Mayo Clinic | year = 2008
| url = http://health.psnews.com/usnews/health/pain/kidneystone/kidneystone.about.htm
| title = Kidney Stone Channel | publisher = U.S. News &amp; World Report
| accessdate = 2008-04-23
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; commonly caused by [[kidney stones]]. Uremia is also known as uremic poisoning.

London died November 22, 1916, in a [[sleeping porch]] in a cottage on his ranch. He was in extreme pain and taking [[morphine]], and it is possible that a morphine overdose, accidental or deliberate, may have contributed to his death. The biographer Stasz writes, &quot;Following London's death, for a number of reasons, a biographical myth developed in which he has been portrayed as an alcoholic womanizer who committed suicide. Recent scholarship based upon firsthand documents challenges this caricature.&quot;{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Biography}}

London's fiction featured several suicides.  In his autobiographical memoir ''John Barleycorn'', he claims, as a youth, to have drunkenly stumbled overboard into the San Francisco Bay, &quot;some maundering fancy of going out with the tide suddenly obsessed me&quot;. He said he drifted and nearly succeeded in drowning before sobering up and being rescued by fishermen. In the dénouement of ''[[The Little Lady of the Big House]]'', the heroine, confronted by the pain of a mortal gunshot wound, undergoes a physician-assisted suicide by morphine. Also, in &quot;[[Martin Eden]]&quot;, the principal protagonist, who shares certain characteristics with London himself, drowns himself.

London had been a robust man but had suffered several serious illnesses, including [[scurvy]] in the Klondike. At the time of his death, he suffered from [[dysentery]] and [[uremia]] and late stage alcoholism. During travels on the ''Snark'', he and Charmian may have picked up unspecified tropical infections. Most biographers, including Russ Kingman, now agree he died of uremia aggravated by an accidental morphine overdose.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jacklondons.net/nosuicide.html &quot;Did Jack London Commit Suicide?&quot;&lt;!-- bot-generated title --&gt;], The World of Jack London&lt;/ref&gt;

London's ashes were buried, together with those of his second wife Charmian (who died in 1955), in [[Jack London State Historic Park]], in [[Glen Ellen, California]]. The simple grave is marked only by a mossy boulder.

== Accusations of plagiarism ==

{{Disputed-section|date=August 2011}}
[[File:JackLondon-office-1916.jpg|thumb|upright|Jack London in his office]]

London was vulnerable to accusations of plagiarism not only because he was such a conspicuous, prolific, and successful writer, but also because of his methods of working. He wrote in a letter to Elwyn Hoffman, &quot;expression, you see—with me—is far easier than invention.&quot; He purchased plots and novels from the young [[Sinclair Lewis]] and used incidents from newspaper clippings as writing material.

Egerton R. Young claimed ''[[The Call of the Wild]]'' was taken from his book ''[[My Dogs in the Northland]]''. London acknowledged using it as a source and claimed to have written a letter to Young thanking him.

In July 1901, two pieces of fiction appeared within the same month: London's &quot;[[Moon-Face]]&quot;, in the ''San Francisco Argonaut,'' and [[Frank Norris]]'s &quot;The Passing of Cock-eye Blacklock,&quot; in ''Century.'' Newspapers showed the similarities between the stories, which London said were &quot;quite different in manner of treatment, [but] patently the same in foundation and motive.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} London explained both writers based their stories on the same newspaper account. A year later, it was discovered that Charles Forrest McLean had published a fictional story also based on the same incident.

In 1906, the ''New York World'' published &quot;deadly parallel&quot; columns showing eighteen passages from London's short story &quot;Love of Life&quot; side by side with similar passages from a nonfiction article by [[Augustus Biddle]] and [[J. K Macdonald]], titled &quot;Lost in the Land of the Midnight Sun.&quot; {{sfn|Kingman|1979|p=118}} London noted the ''World'' did not accuse him of &quot;plagiarism,&quot; but only of &quot;identity of time and situation,&quot; to which he defiantly &quot;pled guilty.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Letter to &quot;The Bookman,&quot; April 10, 1906, quoted in full in {{cite book|title=No mentor but myself: Jack London on writing and writers|author=Jack London, Dale L. Walker, Jeanne Campbell Reesman|year=2000|publisher=Stanford University Press|id=978-0804736350}} p. 97: &quot;The ''World'', however, did not charge me with plagiarism. It charged me with identity of time and situation. Certainly I plead guilty, and I am glad that the ''World'' was intelligent enough not to charge me with identity of language.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The most serious charge of plagiarism was based on London's &quot;The Bishop's Vision&quot;, Chapter 7 of his ''[[The Iron Heel]]''. The chapter is nearly identical to an ironic essay that [[Frank Harris]] published in 1901, titled &quot;The Bishop of London and Public Morality.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} Harris was incensed and suggested he should receive 1/60th of the royalties from ''The Iron Heel,'' the disputed material constituting about that fraction of the whole novel. London insisted he had clipped a reprint of the article, which had appeared in an American newspaper, and believed it to be a genuine speech delivered by the Bishop of London.

== Political views ==
=== Socialism ===

London joined the [[Socialist Labor Party]] in April 1896. In the same year, the ''San Francisco Chronicle'' published a story about the twenty-year-old London giving nightly speeches in Oakland's City Hall Park, an activity he was arrested for a year later. In 1901, he left the Socialist Labor Party and joined the new [[Socialist Party of America]]. He ran unsuccessfully as the high-profile Socialist nominee for mayor of Oakland in 1901 (receiving 245 votes) and 1905 (improving to 981 votes), toured the country lecturing on socialism in 1906, and published collections of essays about socialism (''The War of the Classes'', 1905; ''Revolution, and other Essays'', 1906). As London explained in his essay, &quot;How I Became a Socialist&quot;, his views were influenced by his experience with people at the bottom of the social pit. His optimism and individualism faded, and he vowed never to do more hard work than necessary. He wrote that his individualism was hammered out of him, and he was politically reborn. He often closed his letters &quot;Yours for the Revolution.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See Labor (1994) p. 546 for one example, a letter from London to William E. Walling dated November 30, 1909.&lt;/ref&gt;

In his Glen Ellen ranch years, London felt some ambivalence toward socialism and complained about the &quot;inefficient Italian labourers&quot; in his employ.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|p=245}} In 1916, he resigned from the Glen Ellen chapter of the Socialist Party, but stated emphatically he did so &quot;because of its lack of fire and fight, and its loss of emphasis on the class struggle.&quot;

Stasz notes that &quot;London regarded the [[Industrial Workers of the World|Wobblies]] as a welcome addition to the [[Socialist]] cause, although he never joined them in going so far as to recommend sabotage.&quot;{{sfn|Stasz|2001|p=100}} Stasz mentions a personal meeting between London and [[Big Bill Haywood]] in 1912.{{sfn|Stasz|2001|p=156}}

==== Influence on writing ====

London wrote from a socialist viewpoint, which is evident in his novel ''[[The Iron Heel]]''. Neither a theorist nor an intellectual socialist, London's socialism grew out of his life experience.

In his late (1913) book ''The Cruise of the Snark'', London writes, without empathy, about appeals to him for membership of the Snark's crew from office workers and other &quot;toilers&quot; who longed for escape from the cities, and of being cheated by workmen.

In an unflattering portrait of London's ranch days, Kevin Starr (1973) refers to this period as &quot;post-socialist&quot; and says &quot;… by 1911 … London was more bored by the class struggle than he cared to admit.&quot; Starr maintains London's socialism

{{quote |
always had a streak of elitism in it, and a good deal of pose. He liked to play working class intellectual when it suited his purpose. Invited to a prominent Piedmont house, he featured a flannel shirt, but, as someone there remarked, London's badge of solidarity with the working class &quot;looked as if it had been specially laundered for the occasion.&quot; [Mark Twain said] &quot;It would serve this man London right to have the working class get control of things. He would have to call out the militia to collect his royalties.&quot;
}}

=== Racial views ===

London shared common Californian concerns about Asian immigration and &quot;[[yellow peril|the yellow peril]]&quot;, which he used as the title of a 1904 essay.{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: The Yellow Peril}} This theme was also the subject of a story he wrote in 1910 called &quot;[[The Unparalleled Invasion]]&quot;. Presented as a historical essay narrating events between 1976 and 1987, the story describes a [[China]] with an ever-increasing population taking over and colonizing its neighbors, with the intention of taking over the entire Earth. The western nations respond with [[biological warfare]] and bombard China with dozens of the most infectious diseases.{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: The Unparalleled Invasion}}

Many of London's short stories are notable for their empathetic portrayal of Mexican (&quot;The Mexican&quot;), Asian (&quot;The Chinago&quot;), and Hawaiian (&quot;Koolau the Leper&quot;) characters. London's war correspondence from the [[Russo-Japanese War]], as well as his unfinished novel ''Cherry'', show he admired much about Japanese customs and capabilities.{{citation needed|date=August 2010}}

In London's 1902 novel ''Daughter of the Snows'', the character Frona Welse has a speech about Teutonic virtues in contrast to the characteristics of other &quot;races&quot;. The scholar Andrew Furer, in a long essay exploring the complexity of London's views, says there is no doubt that Frona Welse is acting as a mouthpiece for London in this passage.{{citation needed|date=June 2010}}:

London's 1904 essay, &quot;The Yellow Peril&quot;,{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: The Yellow Peril}} criticizes Asians. He admits, &quot;[I]t must be taken into consideration that the above postulate is itself a product of Western race-egotism, urged by our belief in our own righteousness and fostered by a faith in ourselves which may be as erroneous as are most fond race fancies.&quot;

In &quot;Koolau the Leper&quot;, London describes Koolau, who is a Hawaiian leper—and thus a very different sort of &quot;superman&quot; than Martin Eden—and who fights off an entire cavalry troop to elude capture, as &quot;indomitable spiritually—a&amp;nbsp;... magnificent rebel&quot;.

[[File:Johnson jeff.jpg|thumb|upright|Jeffries (left) vs. Johnson, 1910]]

An amateur boxer and avid boxing fan, London reported on the 1910 Johnson-Jeffries fight, in which the black boxer [[Jack Johnson (boxer)|Jack Johnson]] vanquished [[James J. Jeffries|Jim Jeffries]], the &quot;Great White Hope&quot;. In 1908, according to Furer, London praised Johnson highly, contrasting the black boxer's coolness and intellectual style, with the apelike appearance and fighting style of his white opponent, Tommy Burns: &quot;what . . . [won] on Saturday was bigness, coolness, quickness, cleverness, and vast physical superiority... Because a white man wishes a white man to win, this should not prevent him from giving absolute credit to the best man, even when that best man was black. All hail to Johnson.&quot; Johnson was &quot;superb. He was impregnable . . . as inaccessible as Mont Blanc.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2010}}

Those who defend London against charges of racism cite the letter he wrote to the ''Japanese-American Commercial Weekly'' in 1913:

{{quote |
In reply to yours of August 16, 1913. First of all, I should say by stopping the stupid newspaper from always fomenting race prejudice. This of course, being impossible, I would say, next, by educating the people of Japan so that they will be too intelligently tolerant to respond to any call to race prejudice. And, finally, by realizing, in industry and government, of socialism—which last word is merely a word that stands for the actual application of in the affairs of men of the theory of the Brotherhood of Man.

In the meantime the nations and races are only unruly boys who have not yet grown to the stature of men. So we must expect them to do unruly and boisterous things at times. And, just as boys grow up, so the races of mankind will grow up and laugh when they look back upon their childish quarrels.&lt;ref&gt;Labor, Earle, Robert C. Leitz, III, and I. Milo Shepard: ''The Letters of Jack London: Volume Three: 1913–1916'' Stanford University Press 1988. p. 1219, Letter to ''Japanese-American Commercial Weekly'', August 25, 1913: &quot;the races of mankind will grow up and laugh [at] their childish quarrels…&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

In [[Yukon]] in 1996, after the [[Whitehorse, Yukon|City of Whitehorse]] renamed two streets to honor London and [[Robert W. Service]], protests over London's racialist views forced
the city to change the name of &quot;Jack London Boulevard&quot; back to &quot;Two-mile Hill&quot;.{{sfn|Lundberg}}

== Works ==
=== Short stories ===

Western writer and historian Dale L. Walker writes:&lt;ref name=&quot;DaleWalker&quot;&gt;[http://www.jacklondons.net/writings/shortFiction/part1.html Dale L. Walker, &quot;Jack London: The Stories&quot;], The World of Jack London&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote |
London's true métier was the short story … London's true genius lay in the short form, 7,500 words and under, where the flood of images in his teeming brain and the innate power of his narrative gift were at once constrained and freed. His stories that run longer than the magic 7,500 generally—but certainly not always—could have benefited from self-editing.
}}

London's &quot;strength of utterance&quot; is at its height in his stories, and they are painstakingly well-constructed.{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} &quot;[[To Build a Fire]]&quot; is the best known of all his stories. Set in the harsh Klondike, it recounts the haphazard trek of a new arrival who has ignored an old-timer's warning about the risks of traveling alone. Falling through the ice into a creek in seventy-five-below weather, the unnamed man is keenly aware that survival depends on his untested skills at quickly building a fire to dry his clothes and warm his extremities. After publishing a tame version of this story—with a sunny outcome—in ''[[The Youth's Companion]]'' in 1902, London offered a second, more severe take on the man's predicament in ''[[The Century Magazine]]'' in 1908. Reading both provides an illustration of London's growth and maturation as a writer. As Labor (1994) observes: &quot;To compare the two versions is itself an instructive lesson in what distinguished a great work of literary art from a good children's story.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;To Build a Fire&quot; group=&quot;upper-alpha&quot; /&gt;

Other stories from the Klondike period include: &quot;All Gold Canyon&quot;, about a battle between a [[gold]] [[Prospecting|prospector]] and a [[land claim|claim jumper]]; &quot;The Law of Life&quot;, about an aging American Indian man abandoned by his tribe and left to die; &quot;Love of Life&quot;, about a trek by a prospector across the Canadian tundra; &quot;To the Man on Trail,&quot; which tells the story of a prospector fleeing the Mounted Police in a sled race, and raises the question of the contrast between written law and morality; and &quot;An Odyssey of the North,&quot; which raises questions of conditional morality, and paints a sympathetic portrait of a man of mixed White and [[Aleut people|Aleut]] ancestry.

London was a [[boxing]] fan and an avid amateur boxer. &quot;A Piece of Steak&quot; is a tale about a match between older and younger boxers. It contrasts the differing experiences of youth and age but also raises the social question of the treatment of aging workers. &quot;The Mexican&quot; combines boxing with a social theme, as a young Mexican endures an unfair fight and ethnic prejudice in order to earn money with which to aid the revolution.

Numerous stories of London would today be classified as [[science fiction]]. &quot;The Unparalleled Invasion&quot; describes [[germ warfare]] against China; &quot;Goliah&quot; revolves around an irresistible energy weapon; &quot;The Shadow and the Flash&quot; is a tale about two brothers who take different routes to achieving invisibility; &quot;A Relic of the Pliocene&quot; is a tall tale about an encounter of a modern-day man with a [[mammoth]]. &quot;[[The Red One]]&quot; is a late story from a period when London was intrigued by the theories of the [[psychiatrist]] and writer [[Carl Jung|Jung]]. It tells of an island tribe held in thrall by an extraterrestrial object. His [[dystopia]]n novel, ''[[The Iron Heel]]'', meets the contemporary definition of [[soft science fiction]].

Some nineteen original collections of short stories were published during London's brief life or shortly after his death. There have been numerous posthumous anthologies drawn from this pool of nineteen books. Many of these collections have been themed around the locales of the Klondike and the Pacific. A collection of ''[[Jack London's San Francisco Stories]]'' was published in October 2010 by Sydney Samizdat Press.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jacklondon-sanfrancisco.com Jack London: San Francisco Stories] (Edited by Matthew Asprey; Preface by Rodger Jacobs)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Novels ===

[[File:J London writing 1905.jpg|thumb|upright|London writing, 1905]]

London's most famous novels are ''[[The Call of the Wild]]'', ''[[White Fang]]'', ''[[The Sea-Wolf]]'', ''[[The Iron Heel]]'', and ''[[Martin Eden]]''.&lt;ref&gt;These are the five novels selected by editor Donald Pizer for inclusion in the [[Library of America]] series.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a letter dated Dec 27, 1901, London's Macmillan publisher [[George Platt Brett, Sr.]] said &quot;he believed Jack's fiction represented 'the very best kind of work' done in America.&quot;{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|p=109}}

Critic Maxwell Geismar called ''[[The Call of the Wild]]'' &quot;a beautiful prose poem&quot;; editor Franklin Walker said that it &quot;belongs on a shelf with ''[[Walden]]'' and ''[[Adventures of Huckleberry Finn|Huckleberry Finn]]''&quot;; and novelist [[E.L. Doctorow]] called it &quot;a mordant parable … his masterpiece.&quot;{{citation needed|date=June 2010}}

The historian Dale L. Walker&lt;ref name=&quot;DaleWalker&quot; /&gt; commented:

{{quote |
Jack London was an uncomfortable novelist, that form too long for his natural impatience and the quickness of his mind. His novels, even the best of them, are hugely flawed.
}}

Critics have said his novels are episodic and resemble a linked series of short stories. Walker writes:

{{quote |
[[The Star Rover]], that magnificent experiment, is actually a series of short stories connected by a unifying device … [[Smoke Bellew]] is a series of stories bound together in a novel-like form by their reappearing protagonist, Kit Bellew; and [[John Barleycorn (novel)|''John Barleycorn'']] … is a synoptic series of short episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;DaleWalker&quot; /&gt;
}}

[[Ambrose Bierce]] said of ''[[The Sea-Wolf]]'' that &quot;the great thing—and it is among the greatest of things—is that tremendous creation, Wolf Larsen … the hewing out and setting up of such a figure is enough for a man to do in one lifetime.&quot; However, he noted, &quot;The love element, with its absurd suppressions, and impossible proprieties, is awful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Letters of Ambrose Bierce, ed. S. T. Joshi, Tryambak Sunand Joshi, David E. Schultz, Columbus: Ohio State University Press, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Iron Heel]]'' is interesting as an example of a [[dystopian]] novel that anticipates and influenced [[George Orwell]]'s ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]''.{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} London's socialist politics are explicitly on display here.

=== Apocrypha ===
==== Jack London Credo ====

London's [[literary executor]], Irving Shepard, quoted a ''Jack London Credo'' in an introduction to a 1956 collection of London stories:

&lt;poem style=&quot;margin-left: 3em;&quot;&gt;
I would rather be ashes than dust!
I would rather that my spark should burn out in a brilliant blaze than it should be stifled by dry-rot.
I would rather be a superb meteor, every atom of me in magnificent glow, than a sleepy and permanent planet.
The function of man is to live, not to exist.
I shall not waste my days in trying to prolong them.
I shall use my time.
&lt;/poem&gt;

The biographer Stasz notes that the passage &quot;has many marks of London's style&quot; but the only line that could be safely attributed to London was the first.{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Credo}} The words Shepard quoted were from a story in the ''San Francisco Bulletin'', December 2, 1916 by journalist Ernest J. Hopkins, who visited the ranch just weeks before London's death. Stasz notes &quot;Even more so than today journalists' quotes were unreliable or even sheer inventions&quot; and says no direct source in London's writings has been found.

In the short story &quot;By The Turtles of Tasman&quot;, a character, defending her ne'er-do-well grasshopperish father to her antlike uncle, says: &quot;… my father has been a king. He has lived …. Have you lived merely to live? Are you afraid to die? I'd rather sing one wild song and burst my heart with it, than live a thousand years watching my digestion and being afraid of the wet. When you are dust, my father will be ashes.&quot;

==== The Scab ====

{{main|Strikebreaker}}
A short diatribe on &quot;The Scab&quot; is often quoted within the U.S. labor movement and frequently attributed to London. It opens:

{{quote |
After God had finished the rattlesnake, the toad, and the vampire, he had some awful substance left with which he made a scab. A scab is a two-legged animal with a corkscrew soul, a water brain, a combination backbone of jelly and glue. Where others have hearts, he carries a tumor of rotten principles. When a scab comes down the street, men turn their backs and Angels weep in Heaven, and the Devil shuts the gates of hell to keep him out....&quot;&lt;ref name=thescab&gt;{{cite web | url = http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=418&amp;invol=264 | title = Letter Carriers v. Austin, 418 U.S. 264 (1974) | accessdate = 2006-05-23|date=1974-06-25 | author = Thurgood Marshall}} The court decision cites the passage in full. A Google search on [http://www.google.com/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=%22corkscrew+soul%22&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8 &quot;corkscrew soul&quot;] turns up scores of others.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

This passage figured in a 1974 Supreme Court case, in which Justice [[Thurgood Marshall]] quoted the passage in full and referred to it as &quot;a well-known piece of trade union literature, generally attributed to author Jack London.&quot; A union newsletter had published a &quot;list of scabs,&quot; which was granted to be factual and therefore not libelous, but then went on to quote the passage as the &quot;definition of a scab.&quot; The case turned on the question of whether the &quot;definition&quot; was defamatory. The court ruled that &quot;Jack London's... 'definition of a scab' is merely rhetorical hyperbole, a lusty and imaginative expression of the contempt felt by union members towards those who refuse to join,&quot; and as such was not libelous and was protected under the First Amendment.&lt;ref name=&quot;thescab&quot; /&gt;

The passage does not appear in the extensive collection of Jack London's writings at Sonoma State University's website. He once gave a speech entitled &quot;The Scab&quot; which he published in his book ''The War of the Classes,'' which opens{{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}

{{quote |
In a competitive society, where men struggle with one another for food and shelter, what is more natural than that generosity, when it diminishes the food and shelter of men other than he who is generous, should be held an accursed thing? Wise old saws to the contrary, he who takes from a man's purse takes from his existence. To strike at a man's food and shelter is to strike at his life; and in a society organized on a tooth-and-nail basis, such an act, performed though it may be under the guise of generosity, is none the less menacing and terrible.
}}

In 1913 and 1914, a number of newspapers printed a passage virtually identical to the first three sentences of the &quot;scab&quot; diatribe, except that the type of individual being vilified varies: God uses the awful substance to make, not a &quot;scab,&quot; but a &quot;knocker,&quot; or a &quot;stool pigeon,&quot; or a &quot;scandal monger.&quot;

A 1913 Fort Worth newspaper columnist quotes the &quot;Rule Review&quot; as saying &quot;After God had finished making the rattlesnake, the toad and the vampire, He had some awful substance left, with which he made the knocker.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Callan, Claude, 1913, &quot;Cracks at the Crowd&quot;, ''Fort Worth Star-Telegram'', December 30, 1913, p. 6: &quot;Saith the Rule Review: 'After God had finished making the rattlesnake, the toad and the vampire, He had some awful substance left, with which he made the knocker.' Were it not for being irreverent, we would suggest that He was hard up for something to do when He made any of those pests you call his handiwork.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Macon, Georgia]] paper published three full sentences of the definition of a &quot;knocker.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Food for Your Think Tank&quot;, ''The Macon Daily Telegraph,'' August 23, 1914, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

A 1914 Duluth newspaper article, reporting on a trial, has the defense using this passage as a definition of a &quot;stool pigeon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot; Madame Gain is Found Guilty. Jury Decides Woman Conducted House of Ill Fame at the Clifton Hotel,&quot; ''The Duluth News Tribune'', February 5, 1914, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1914 the ''New Age Magazine,'' quoted a paragraph from ''The Eastern Star,'' another Masonic publication. This passage, too, is virtually identical to the first three sentences of the &quot;Scab&quot; diatribe, except that it defines the &quot;scandal monger.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;T. W. H.&quot;, (1914), &quot;Review of the Masonic 'Country' Press: The Eastern Star&quot; ''The New Age Magazine: A Monthly Publication Devoted to Freemasonry and Its Relation to Present Day Problems,'' published by the Scottish Rite of Freemasonry for the Southern Jurisdiction of the United States; June, 1917, [http://books.google.com/books?id=GMVNAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA283&amp;as_brr=1 p. 283]:&quot;SCANDAL MONGER: After God had finished making the rattlesnake, the toad and the vampire, He had some awful substance left, with which He made a scandal monger. A scandal monger is a two-legged animal with a cork-screw soul, a water-sogged brain and a combination backbone made of jelly and glue. Where other men have their hearts he carries a tumor of decayed principles. When the scandal monger comes down the street honest men turn their backs, the angels weep tears in heaven, and the devil shuts the gates of hell to keep him out. —Anon&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Might is Right ====

[[Anton LaVey]]'s [[Church of Satan]] claims that &quot;[[Ragnar Redbeard]]&quot;, pseudonymous author of the 1896 book ''[[Might is Right]]'', was London. No London biographers mention any such possibility. [[Rodger Jacobs]] published an essay ridiculing this theory, arguing that in 1896 London was unfamiliar with philosophers heavily cited by &quot;Redbeard&quot;, such as Nietzsche, and had not even begun to develop his mature literary style.{{sfn|Jacobs|1999}}

== Bibliography ==

Source unless otherwise specified: {{harvnb|Williams}}

{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}

=== Novels ===

* ''[[The Cruise of the Dazzler]]'' (1902)
* ''[[A Daughter of the Snows]]'' (1902)
* ''[[The Call of the Wild]]'' (1903)
* ''[[The Kempton-Wace Letters]]'' (1903) &lt;br /&gt; (published anonymously, co-authored with [[Anna Strunsky]])
* ''[[The Sea-Wolf]]'' (1904)
* ''[[The Game (London novel)|The Game]]'' (1905)
* ''[[White Fang]]'' (1906)
* ''[[Before Adam]]'' (1907)
* ''[[The Iron Heel]]'' (1908)
* ''[[Martin Eden]]'' (1909)
* ''[[Burning Daylight]]'' (1910)
* ''[[Adventure (novel)|Adventure]]'' (1911)
* ''[[The Scarlet Plague]]'' (1912)
* ''[[A Son of the Sun (novel)|A Son of the Sun]]'' (1912)
* ''[[The Abysmal Brute]]'' (1913)
* ''[[The Valley of the Moon (novel)|The Valley of the Moon]]'' (1913)
* ''[[The Mutiny of the Elsinore (novel)|The Mutiny of the Elsinore]]'' (1914)
* ''[[The Star Rover]]'' (1915) &lt;br /&gt; (published in England as ''The Jacket'')
* ''[[The Little Lady of the Big House]]'' (1916)
* ''[[Jerry of the Islands]]'' (1917)
* ''[[Michael, Brother of Jerry]]'' (1917)
* ''[[Hearts of Three]]'' (1920) &lt;br /&gt; (novelization of a script by [[Charles Goddard]])
* ''[[The Assassination Bureau, Ltd]]'' (1963) &lt;br /&gt; (left half-finished, completed by [[Robert L. Fish]])

=== Short story collections ===

* ''[[Son of the Wolf]]'' (1900)
* ''[[Chris Farrington, Able Seaman]] (1901)
* ''[[The God of His Fathers &amp; Other Stories]]'' (1901){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[Children of the Frost]]'' (1902)
* ''[[The Faith of Men and Other Stories]]'' (1904){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[Tales of the Fish Patrol]]'' (1906)
* ''[[Moon-Face and Other Stories]]'' (1906){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[Love of Life and Other Stories]] (1907){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[Lost Face]]'' (1910)
* ''[[South Sea Tales (1911)|South Sea Tales]]'' (1911)
* ''[[When God Laughs and Other Stories]]'' (1911){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[The House of Pride &amp; Other Tales of Hawaii]]'' (1912)
* ''[[Smoke Bellew]]'' (1912)
* ''[[A Son of the Sun (collection)|A Son of the Sun]]'' (1912){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[The Night Born]]'' (1913){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[The Strength of the Strong]]'' (1911){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[The Turtles of Tasman]]'' (1916)
* ''[[The Human Drift (Jack London)|The Human Drift]]'' (1917){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[The Red One (collection)|The Red One]]'' (1918){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[On the Makaloa Mat]]'' (1919)
* ''[[Dutch Courage and Other Stories]]'' (1922){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}

=== Autobiographical memoirs ===

* ''[[The Road (Jack London)|The Road]]'' (1907)
* ''[[John Barleycorn (novel)|John Barleycorn]]'' (1913)

=== Non-fiction and essays ===

* ''[[The People of the Abyss]]'' (1903)
* ''How I Became a Socialist'' (1903)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003UZY72Y | title = How I Became a Socialist. The Comrade: An illustrated socialist monthly. Volume II, No. 6, March, 1903: Jack London: Books | publisher = Amazon.com |date=2009-09-09 | accessdate = 2011-08-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[The War of the Classes]]'' (1905){{sfn|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
* ''[[Revolution, and other Essays]]'' (1910)
* ''[[The Cruise of the Snark]]'' (1911)

=== Plays ===

* ''Theft'' (1910)
* ''Daughters of the Rich: A One Act Play'' (1915)
* ''[[The Acorn Planter: A California Forest Play]]'' (1916)

{{col-break}}

=== Short stories ===

* &quot;Who Believes in Ghosts!&quot; (1895)
* &quot;To the Man on Trail&quot; (1898)
* &quot;In a Far Country&quot; (1899)
* &quot;The King of Mazy May&quot; (1899)
* &quot;The Rejuvenation of Major Rathbone&quot; (1899)
* &quot;The White Silence&quot; (1899)
* &quot;[[A Thousand Deaths]]&quot; (1899)
* &quot;An Odyssey of the North&quot; (1900)
* &quot;Even unto Death&quot; (1900)
* &quot;The Man with the Gash&quot; (1900)
* &quot;A Relic of the Pliocene&quot; (1901)
* &quot;The God of His Fathers&quot; (1901)
* &quot;The Law of Life&quot; (1901)
* &quot;The Minions of Midas&quot; (1901)
* &quot;In the Forests of the North&quot; (1902)
* &quot;The Story of Keesh&quot;
* &quot;Keesh, Son of Keesh&quot; (1902)
* &quot;Nam-Bok, the Unveracious&quot;
* &quot;The Men of Forty Mile&quot;
* &quot;Lost Face&quot;
* &quot;The Death of Ligoun&quot; (1902)
* &quot;[[Moon-Face]]&quot; (1902)
* &quot;[[Bâtard|Diable—A Dog]]&quot; (1902), renamed ''[[Bâtard]]'' in 1904
* &quot;[[To Build a Fire]]&quot; (1902, revised 1908)
* &quot;The League of the Old Men&quot; (1902)
* &quot;The Dominant Primordial Beast&quot; (1903)
* &quot;The One Thousand Dozen&quot; (1903)
* &quot;The Shadow and the Flash&quot; (1903)
* &quot;[[The Leopard Man's Story]]&quot; (1903)
* &quot;Negore the Coward&quot; (1904)
* &quot;All Gold Canyon&quot; (1905)
* &quot;Love of Life&quot; (1905)
* &quot;The Sun-Dog Trail&quot; (1905)
* &quot;The Apostate&quot; (1906)
* &quot;Make Westing&quot; (1907)
* &quot;The Terrible Solomons&quot; (1910)
* &quot;Yah! Yah! Yah!&quot;
* &quot;The House of Mapuhi&quot;
* &quot;The Inevitable White Man&quot;
* &quot;Mauki&quot;
* &quot;The Son of the Wolf&quot;
* &quot;Like Argus of the Ancient Times&quot;
* &quot;A Curious Fragment&quot; (1908)
* &quot;Aloha Oe&quot; (1908)
* &quot;That Spot&quot; (1908)
* &quot;The Enemy of All the World&quot; (1908)
* &quot;The Heathen&quot; (1908)
* &quot;Good-by, Jack&quot; (1909)
* &quot;Samuel&quot; (1909)
* &quot;South of the Slot&quot; (1909)
* &quot;The Chinago&quot; (1909)
* &quot;The Dream of Debs&quot; (1909)
* &quot;The Madness of John Harned&quot; (1909)
* &quot;The Seed of McCoy&quot; (1909)
* &quot;[[A Piece of Steak]]&quot; (1909)
* &quot;Goliath&quot; (1910)
* &quot;The Unparalleled Invasion&quot; (1910)
* &quot;Told in the Drooling Ward&quot; (1910)
* &quot;When the World was Young&quot; (1910)
* &quot;By the Turtles of Tasman&quot; (1911)
* &quot;The Mexican&quot; (1911)
* &quot;The Strength of the Strong&quot; (1911)
* &quot;War&quot; (1911)
* &quot;The Bones of Kahekili&quot;
* &quot;Shin-Bones&quot;
* &quot;The Scarlet Plague&quot; (1912)
* &quot;[[The Red One]]&quot; (1918)
{{col-end}}

== Legacy and honors ==

* [[Mount London]], also known as Boundary Peak 100, on the [[Alaska]]-[[British Columbia]] boundary, in the [[Boundary Ranges]] of the [[Coast Mountains]] of [[British Columbia]], is named for him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite bcgnis | id = 21180 | title = London, Mount }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jack London Square]] on the waterfront of [[Oakland, California]] was named for him.
* He was honored by the [[United States Postal Service]] with a 25¢ [[Great Americans series]] [[postage stamp]].
* [[Jack London Lake]] ({{lang-ru|[[:ru:Озеро Джека Лондона|Озеро Джека Лондона]]}}), a mountain lake located in the upper reaches of the [[Kolyma River]] in Yagodninsky district of [[Magadan Oblast]].

== Footnotes ==

'''Note'''

{{reflist
| group = upper-alpha
| refs =

&lt;ref name=&quot;To Build a Fire&quot;&gt;
Both versions are available on [[Wikisource]]: &quot;[[s:To Build a Fire|To Build a Fire]]&quot; (1902), &quot;[[s:Lost Face/To Build a Fire|To Build a Fire]]&quot; (in ''[[Lost Face]]'', 1908)
&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist|30em}}

== References ==

* {{cite book
  | last = Day
  | first = A. Grove
  | editor-first = Bob
  | editor-last = Dye
  | year = 1996
  | origyear = 1984
  | chapter = Jack London and Hawaii
  | title = Hawai{{okina}}i Chronicles
  | publisher = [[University of Hawaii Press]]
  | location = Honolulu
  | pages = 113–119
  | isbn = 0824818296
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kershaw
  | first = Alex
  | year = 1999
  | title = Jack London
  | publisher = St. Martin's Press
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 0-312-19904-X
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kingman
  | first = Russ
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1979
  | title = A Pictorial Life of Jack London
  | publisher = Crown Publishers, Inc. (original); also &quot;Published for Jack London Research Center by David Rejl, California&quot; (same ISBN)
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 0-517-54093-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = London
  | first = Charmian
  | authorlink = Charmian London
  | year = 2003
  | origyear = 1921
  | title = The Book of Jack London, Volume II
  | publisher = Kessinger
  | isbn = 0-7661-6188-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = London
  | first1 = Jack
  | last2 = Taylor
  | first2 = J. Golden
  | coauthors = Western Literature Association
  | title = A Literary history of the American West
  | publisher = Texas Christian University Press
  | location = Fort Worth
  | year = 1987
  | isbn = 0-87565-021-X
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = London
  | first = Joan
  | authorlink = Joan London, U.S. writer
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1939
  | title = Jack London and His Times
  | publisher = Doubleday, Doran &amp; Company, Inc
  | location = New York
  | id = Library of Congress 39-33408
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite web
  | last = Lundberg
  | first = Murray
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = The Life of Jack London as Reflected in his Works
  | work = Explore North
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080610160906/www.explorenorth.com/library/yafeatures/jack_london.html
  | archivedate = 2008-06-10
  | doi =
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Noel
  | first = Joseph
  | authorlink =
  | year = 1940
  | title = Footloose in Arcadia: A Personal Record of Jack London, George Sterling, Ambrose Bierce
  | publisher = Carrick and Evans
  | location = New York
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Reesman
  | first = Jeanne Campbell
  | year = 2009
  | title = Jack London's Racial Lives: A Critical Biography
  | publisher = [[University of Georgia Press]]
  | location = Athens, GA
  | isbn = 0820327891
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Stasz
  | first = Clarice
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1999
  | origyear = 1988
  | title = American Dreamers: Charmian and Jack London
  | publisher = toExcel (iUniverse, Lincoln, Nebraska)
  | location =
  | isbn = 0-595-00002-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Stasz
  | first = Clarice
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 2001
  | title = Jack London's Women
  | publisher = University of Massachusetts Press
  | location = Amherst, MA
  | isbn = 1-55849-301-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Wichlan
  | first = Daniel J.
  | year = 2007
  | title = The Complete Poetry of Jack London
  | publisher = Little Red Tree Publishing
  | location = Waterford, CT
  | isbn = 0-9789446-2-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Jack London Dies Suddenly On Ranch
  | publisher = nytimes.com
  | date = 1916-11-23
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/bday/0112.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-22
  | quote = Novelist is Found Unconscious from Uremia, and Expires after Eleven Hours. Wrote His Life of Toil—His Experience as Sailor Reflected In His Fiction—'Call of the Wild' Gave Him His Fame.&quot; 'The New York Times,' story datelined Santa Rosa, Cal., Nov. 22; appeared November 24, 1916, p. 13. States he died 'at 7:45 o'clock tonight,' and says he was 'born in San Francisco on January 12, 1876.'
  | ref = {{sfnRef|New York Times November 23, 1916}}
  }}

'''The Jack London Online Collection'''

* {{cite web
  | title = Jack London's death certificate, from County Record's Office, Sonoma Co., Nov. 22, 1916.
  | date = 1916-11-22
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/Documents/I0040981.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: Jack London's death certificate}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | last = Stasz
  | first = Clarice
  | date = 2001
  | title = Jack &lt;nowiki&gt;[John Griffith]&lt;/nowiki&gt; London
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/London/jackbio.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: Biography}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Revolution and Other Essays: The Yellow Peril
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/London/Writings/Revolution/yellow.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: The Yellow Peril}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = The Unparalleled Invasion
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/Writings/StrengthStrong/invasion.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: The Unparalleled Invasion}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Jack London's &quot;Credo&quot;, Commentary by Clarice Stasz
  | date =
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/London/credo.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: Credo}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Jack London's Writings
  | author = Roy Tennant and Clarice Stasz
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/Writings/
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: Writings}}
  }}&lt;!-- 'The Scab' is not referred to at this point...
* {{cite web
  | title = The Scab
  | date = April 5, 1903
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/London/Writings/WarOfTheClasses/scab.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = {{sfnRef|The Jack London Online Collection: &quot;The Scab&quot;}}
  }}--&gt;
* {{cite journal
  | last = Jacobs
  | first = Rodger
  | authorlink = Rodger Jacobs
  | date = July 1999
  | title = Running with the Wolves: Jack London, the Cult of Masculinity, and &quot;Might is Right&quot;
  | journal = Panik
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/Essays/redbeard.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite web
  | last = Williams
  | first = James
  | title = Jack London's Works by Date of Composition
  | date =
  | publisher = The Jack London Online Collection
  | url = http://london.sonoma.edu/Essays/comp_date.html
  | accessdate = 2011-09-30
  | ref = harv
  }}

== Further reading ==

* {{cite book
  | last = Asprey
  | first = Matthew (ed.)
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = Jacobs, Rodger (preface)
  | year = 2010
  | title = Jack London: San Francisco Stories
  | publisher = Sydney Samizdat Press
  | location = Sydney
  | isbn = 1453840508
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hamilton
  | first = David
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1986
  | title = The Tools of My Trade: Annotated Books in Jack London's Library
  | publisher = University of Washington
  | location =
  | isbn = 0-295-96157-0
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Herron
  | first = Don
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 2004
  | title = The Barbaric Triumph: A Critical Anthology on the Writings of Robert E. Howard
  | publisher = Wildside Press
  | location =
  | isbn = 0-8095-1566-0
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Howard
  | first = Robert E.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1989
  | title = Robert E. Howard Selected Letters 1923–1930
  | publisher = Necronomicon Press
  | location = West Warwick, RI
  | isbn = 0-940884-26-7
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Labor
  | first = Earle (ed.)
  | year = 1994
  | title = The Portable Jack London
  | publisher = Viking Penguin
  | location =
  | isbn = 0-14-017969-0
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = London
  | first = Jack
  | coauthors = Anna Strunsky
  | year = 2000
  | origyear = 1903
  | title = The Kempton-Wace Letters
  | publisher = Triality
  | location = Czech Republic
  | isbn = 80-901876-8-4
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=4C00vDmgecMC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;lpg=PA1&amp;dq=%22Jack+London%22
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Lord
  | first = Glenn
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1976
  | title = The Last Celt: A Bio-Bibliography of Robert E. Howard
  | publisher = Donald Grant
  | location = West Kingston, RI
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Pizer
  | first = Donald (ed.)
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1982
  | title = Jack London : Novels and Stories
  | publisher = [[Library of America]]
  | location =
  | isbn = 978-0-94045005-9
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Pizer
  | first = Donald (ed.)
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | year = 1982
  | title = Jack London: Novels and Social Writing
  | publisher = [[Library of America]]
  | location =
  | isbn = 978-0-94045006-6
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Raskin
  | first = Jonah (ed.)
  | authorlink = Jonah Raskin
  | coauthors =
  | year = 2008
  | title = The Radical Jack London: Writings on War and Revolution
  | publisher = University of California Press
  | location =
  | isbn = 0520255461
  }}
* Starr, Kevin (1973) ''Americans and the California Dream 1850–1915.'' Oxford University Press. 1986 reprint: ISBN 0-19-504233-6

== External links ==

{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote|Jack London}}
{{wikisource author|Jack London}}

* {{gutenberg author|id=Jack_London|name=Jack London}}
* {{worldcat id|id=lccn-n78-86415}}
* {{OL author|id=OL44633A}}
* [http://london.sonoma.edu/London/ The Jack London Online Collection] Site featuring information about Jack London's life and work, and a collection of his writings.
* [http://www.jacklondons.net/ The World of Jack London] Biographical information and writings
* [http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=478 Jack London State Historic Park]
* [http://www.huntington.org/LibraryDiv/JackLondon.html The Huntingon Library's Jack London Archive]
* [http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf3t1nb062/ Guide to the Jack London Papers] at [[The Bancroft Library]]
* [http://carl-bell-2.baylor.edu/~bellc/JL/ Jack London Stories], Scanned short stories from original magazines, including the original artwork
* 5 short [http://californialegacy.org/radio_anthology/scripts/london.html radio episodes] from Jack London's writing at [[California Legacy Project]].

{{Jack London novels}}

{{Authority control|PND=118574183|LCCN=n/78/86415|VIAF=46764200}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
| NAME              = London, Jack
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = London, John Griffith (full name); Chaney, John Griffith
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = American writer of fiction and non-fiction; Journalist
| DATE OF BIRTH     = January 12, 1876
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[San Francisco, California]], [[United States]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = November 22, 1916
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Glen Ellen, California]], [[United States]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:London, Jack}}
[[Category:1876 births]]
[[Category:1916 deaths]]
[[Category:1906 San Francisco Earthquake survivors]]
[[Category:American novelists]]
[[Category:Travel writers]]
[[Category:American short story writers]]
[[Category:American socialists]]
[[Category:American travel writers]]
[[Category:War correspondents]]
[[Category:History of Sonoma County, California]]
[[Category:Members of the Socialist Labor Party of America]]
[[Category:Members of the Socialist Party of America]]
[[Category:People from Oakland, California]]
[[Category:People from Piedmont, California]]
[[Category:People of the Klondike Gold Rush]]
[[Category:War correspondents of the Russo-Japanese War]]
[[Category:People self-identifying as alcoholics]]
[[Category:University of California, Berkeley alumni]]
[[Category:Writers from California]]

[[af:Jack London]]
[[ar:جاك لندن]]
[[az:Cek London]]
[[be:Джэк Лондан]]
[[bg:Джек Лондон]]
[[bs:Jack London]]
[[br:Jack London]]
[[ca:Jack London]]
[[cv:Джек Лондон]]
[[cs:Jack London]]
[[da:Jack London]]
[[de:Jack London]]
[[et:Jack London]]
[[el:Τζακ Λόντον]]
[[es:Jack London]]
[[eo:Jack London]]
[[eu:Jack London]]
[[fa:جک لندن]]
[[fr:Jack London]]
[[fy:Jack London]]
[[gl:Jack London]]
[[ko:잭 런던]]
[[hi:जैक लंडन]]
[[hr:Jack London]]
[[id:Jack London]]
[[it:Jack London]]
[[he:ג'ק לונדון]]
[[ka:ჯეკ ლონდონი]]
[[ku:Jack London]]
[[ky:Жек Лондон]]
[[lv:Džeks Londons]]
[[lt:Jack London]]
[[hu:Jack London]]
[[mk:Џек Лондон]]
[[mzn:جک لندن]]
[[my:ဂျက်လန်ဒန်]]
[[nl:Jack London (auteur)]]
[[ja:ジャック・ロンドン]]
[[no:Jack London]]
[[nn:Jack London]]
[[pa:ਜੈਕ ਲੰਡਨ]]
[[pms:Jack London]]
[[pl:Jack London]]
[[pt:Jack London]]
[[ro:Jack London]]
[[ru:Джек Лондон]]
[[sq:Jack London]]
[[simple:Jack London]]
[[sk:Jack London]]
[[sl:Jack London]]
[[sr:Џек Лондон]]
[[sh:Jack London]]
[[fi:Jack London]]
[[sv:Jack London]]
[[tg:Ҷек Лондон]]
[[tr:Jack London]]
[[uk:Джек Лондон]]
[[vi:Jack London]]
[[zh:杰克·伦敦]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
