<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="43051" ns="0" title="Lehigh University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university|
|image_name     = LUwithShield-CMYK.svg
|image_size     = 150px
|name           = Lehigh University
|motto          = ''Homo minister et interpres naturae'' ([[Latin]])
|mottoeng = Man, the servant and interpreter of nature
|established    = 1865
|type           = [[Private school|Private]]
|calendar       = Semester
|endowment      = $1.07&amp;nbsp;billion&lt;ref&gt;As of March 31, 2011.  {{cite web | title = Lehigh University Endowment Fund Report| work = Lehigh Endowment 2010 | publisher = Lehigh University Financial Services | url = http://www.lehigh.edu/~infinsv/endowment.html| format = PPT | accessdate = September 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president      = [[Alice Gast|Alice P. Gast]]
|city           = [[Bethlehem, Pennsylvania|Bethlehem]]
|state          = [[Pennsylvania|PA]]
|zip            = 18015
|country        = USA
|undergrad      = 4,781&lt;ref name=&quot;lufacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www4.lehigh.edu/about/glance |title=Lehigh at a Glance |publisher=.lehigh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad       = 2,270&lt;ref name=&quot;lufacts&quot;/&gt;
|staff          = 1,255
|campus         = [[Suburban]] and [[urban area|Urban]]; {{convert|1600|acre|km2}}
|free_label     = Athletics
|free           = [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]&lt;br&gt;25 varsity teams
|colors         = [[Brown]] and [[white]] {{color box|#4C280F}} {{color box|white}}
|mascot         = [[Lehigh Mountain Hawks|Mountain Hawks]]
|affiliations   = [[Middle Atlantic Intercollegiate Sailing Association|MAISA]]
|website        = [http://www.lehigh.edu/ www.lehigh.edu]
|logo=[[File:Lehigh University text.png|250px]]
}}

'''Lehigh University''' is a [[private university|private]], co-educational university located in [[Bethlehem, Pennsylvania]], in the [[Lehigh Valley]] region of the United States. It was established in 1865 by [[Asa Packer]] as a four-year [[technical school]], but has grown to include studies in a wide variety of disciplines. As of 2010, the university comprises 4,781 undergraduate students, 2,270 [[graduate student]]s, 666 professors, and a staff of 1,255.&lt;ref name=&quot;lufacts&quot;/&gt;

The university has four [[college]]s: the P.C. Rossin College of Engineering and Applied Science, the College of Arts and Sciences, the College of Business and Economics, and the College of Education. While the College of Arts and Sciences is the largest college today, home to roughly 40% percent of the university's students,&lt;ref name=&quot;class_summary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www4.lehigh.edu/Media/Website%20Resources/pdf/admissions/LUadmissions_class_summary.pdf |title=Class Summary |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; the university is historically known for engineering&lt;ref name=&quot;academicinfo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.academicinfo.net/online-schools/lehigh-university#box-1 |title=Introduction to Lehigh University |publisher=Academicinfo.net |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and business. The university offers a variety of degrees, including [[Bachelor of Arts]], [[Bachelor of Science]], [[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|Master of Arts]], [[Master of Science]], [[Master of Business Administration]], [[Master of Engineering]], [[Master of Education]], and [[Doctor of Philosophy]].

==History==
[[Image:Asa Packer.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Asa Packer]]]]
{{Main|Lehigh University History}}
[[Asa Packer]] named his university 'Lehigh' after his other passion, [[Lehigh Valley Railroad|the railroad]], despite suggestions from some to call it 'Packer University'. It was founded to provide a well-rounded education for young men, combining a [[Liberal arts|liberal]] and [[scientific]] education with the technical skills necessary to increase the prosperity of the region. According to [[William Bacon Stevens]], the first president of the board of trustees, Asa Packer's founding gift of $500,000 was the largest single endowment for a literary institution at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;/&gt;

From 1871 to 1891, Packer's endowment allowed the institution to offer its education free of charge by competitive exam.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Yates | first = W. Ross | title = An Institution is Born, A Tradition Begins | publisher = Lehigh University | url = http://www3.lehigh.edu/about/past/luhistory.asp | accessdate = August 14, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This, plus its blend of engineering and liberal arts, attracted some of the nation's brightest students, many of whom went on to distinguished careers in industry and engineering.

Unlike other engineering schools of the day, Lehigh was envisioned as a university instead of an &quot;institute of technology,&quot; offering an education that was rooted in both scientific and classical traditions as espoused by [[Comenius|John Amos Comenius]].&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;/&gt; Initially there were five schools: four scientific (civil engineering, mechanical engineering, mining and metallurgy, and analytical chemistry) and one of general literature. Over time, additional areas of the arts and sciences were added and engineering curricula were both merged and expanded.

The stock market crash accompanying the [[Panic of 1893]] was a major financial blow to the university, since its endowment was largely invested in stocks, particularly shares of [[Lehigh Valley Railroad]] donated by the founder.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;/&gt; As a consequence, Lehigh decided to drop its [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal Church]] affiliation in 1897, allowing it to qualify for state and federal government aid.

Based on the experience of Lehigh engineers who went into industry&lt;ref name=&quot;Scrapbook&quot;&gt;Plotnicki, Rita M., ''Looking Back: A Lehigh Scrapbook,'' Lehigh University, 1991&lt;/ref&gt; a College of Business &amp; Economics was added in 1910. Lehigh's business curriculum was unique&lt;ref name=&quot;Scrapbook&quot;/&gt; in that it combined both the abstract emphasis on Economics seen in the [[Ivy League]] with the practical skills of management seen in more common business administration degrees given by other universities.

A similar emphasis on the well-rounded graduate can be seen in Lehigh's approach to education degrees. Lehigh's respected School of Education started as (and remains) a solely graduate-level program. This is based&lt;ref name=&quot;Scrapbook&quot;/&gt; on the principle that you need to learn primary subject matter well before you can learn how to teach it to others. Thus future teachers at Lehigh often take a five year program earning both a Bachelors Degree in a specialized field and a Masters Degree in Education.

[[Image:Lehigh original seal.jpg|upright|thumb|Lehigh's seal]]
===Presidents of Lehigh===
#[[Henry Coppée]] (1866–1875), soldier, author, and engineer
#[[John McDowell Leavitt]] (1875–1880), Episcopal clergyman
#Robert Alexander Lamberton (1880–1893), lawyer
#[[Thomas Messinger Drown]] (1895–1904), chemistry professor
#Henry Sturgis Drinker (1905–1920), the only alumnus to serve as president
#Charles Russ Richards (1922–1935), presided over the first graduate degrees awarded to women
#Clement C. Williams (1935–1944), civil engineer
#Martin Dewey Whitaker (1946–1960), who worked to develop the atomic bomb
#Harvey A. Neville (1961–1964), the only faculty member ever elected president
#W. Deming Lewis (1964–1982), presided over the admission of undergraduate women
#[[Peter Likins]] (1982–1997), civil engineer
#William C. Hittinger (1997–1998), electrical engineer
#[[Gregory C. Farrington]] (1998–2006), chemist
#[[Alice P. Gast]] (2006–present), Lehigh's first female president, chemical engineer

===The Clery Act===
{{Main|Clery Act}}
On April 5, 1986, a 19-year-old Lehigh freshman was raped and murdered in her dorm room; the culprit was later sentenced to death. The backlash against unreported crimes on numerous campuses across the country led to the Jeanne Clery Disclosure of Campus Security Policy and Campus Crime Statistics Act. The Clery Act requires that colleges reveal information regarding crime on their campuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gross |first=Ken |url=http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20116872,00.html |title=After Their Daughter Is Murdered at College, Her Grieving Parents Mount a Crusade for Campus Safety |publisher=People.com |date=1990-02-19 |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.securityoncampus.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=271&amp;Itemid=60 |title=Complying With The Jeanne Clery Act |publisher=Securityoncampus.org |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
{{Main|List of Lehigh University buildings}}
[[Image:Lehigh University Alumni Building.jpg|upright|thumb|Alumni Memorial Building on the Asa Packer campus]]
Located in the [[Lehigh Valley]], the university is a {{convert|70|mi|km|adj=on}} drive from [[Philadelphia]], and an {{convert|85|mi|km|adj=on}} drive from New York City.&lt;ref name=&quot;location&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&amp;source=s_d&amp;saddr=new+york+city,+ny&amp;daddr=27+Memorial+Dr+W,+Bethlehem,+PA+18015+(Lehigh+University)+to:philadelphia,+pa&amp;geocode=FR1AbQIdK8KW-yk7CD_TpU_CiTFi_nfhBo8LyA%3BFbKdawIdy8uB-yEgs29k7emwXQ%3BFc-fYQIdcxeF-ylfd6CC9qjGiTHBWD6M2BT1iQ&amp;hl=en&amp;mra=ls&amp;sll=40.34549,-74.789725&amp;sspn=1.080165,2.403259&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=h&amp;z=9 |title=Driving Directions to Lehigh from New York, Philadelphia |publisher=Maps.google.com |date=1970-01-01 |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lehigh encompasses {{convert|1600|acre|km2}}, including {{convert|180|acre|km2}} of recreational and playing fields and 150 buildings comprising four million square feet of floor space. It is organized into three contiguous campuses on and around [[South Mountain (eastern Pennsylvania)|South Mountain]]:
*the Asa Packer Campus, built into the Northern slope of the mountain, is Lehigh's original and predominant campus;
*the Mountaintop Campus, atop South Mountain, featuring an [[intramural sports]] field as well as Iacocca Hall; and
*the Murray H. Goodman Campus, immediately south, where a 16,000-seat stadium and other sports facilities are located.
[[Image:Lehigh_University_Mountain_Top_Campus.jpg|left|thumb|Iacocca Hall on the Mountaintop Campus.]]

==Academics==
Lehigh's average class size is 27 students; 80% of classes have fewer than 35 students. The undergraduate student-to-faculty ratio is 10:1.&lt;ref name=&quot;lufacts&quot;/&gt;

The 2010 edition of ''[[US News &amp; World Report]]'''s ''Best Colleges'' ranked Lehigh in its &quot;Most Selective&quot; admissions category and 37th in the &quot;National Universities (Doctoral)&quot; category.&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews&quot;&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_3289_brief.php Lehigh University at a Glance] from ''[[US News &amp; World Report]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Princeton Review]]'' classifies it among the &quot;Best Northeastern Colleges.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;princeton_review&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/LehighUniversity.aspx |title=Lehigh University on the Princeton Review |publisher=Princetonreview.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lehigh University offers undergraduate enrollment in all colleges but the College of Education: the P.C. Rossin School of Engineering and Applied Science, the College of Business and Economics, and the College of Arts and Sciences. Students are able to take courses or major/minor in a subject outside of their respective college.&lt;ref name=&quot;enrollment-data&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www4.lehigh.edu/admissions/undergrad/glance/academics.aspx#Enrollment |title=Chart Showing Undergraduate Enrollment |publisher=.lehigh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===P.C. Rossin College of Engineering and Applied Science===
{{See also|Lehigh University engineering highlights}}

Graduates of Lehigh's engineering programs invented the [[escalator]]&lt;ref name=&quot;escalator&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.terrastories.com/bearings/stairways-to-heaven-escalators-in-the-vernacular |title=Stairways to Heaven: Escalators in the Vernacular |publisher=Terrastories.com |date=2007-05-16 |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and founded [[Packard|Packard Motor Car Company]]&lt;ref name=&quot;packard&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://heritage.web.lehigh.edu/index.php/Packard,_James_Ward |title=Packard, James Ward – Lehigh Engineering Heritage Initiative |publisher=Heritage.web.lehigh.edu |date=2011-04-20 |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the companies that built the locks and lockgates of the [[Panama Canal]]. Other notable alumni include [[Roger Penske]] and [[Lee Iacocca]]. [[Tau Beta Pi]], the renowned engineering [[honors society]], was founded at Lehigh.&lt;ref name=&quot;taubetapi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tbp.org/pages/About/History/Founder.cfm |title=Tau Beta Pi Founder, Dr. Edward Higginson Williams, Jr |publisher=Tbp.org |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===College of Business and Economics===
In 2011, ''[[BusinessWeek]]'' ranked Lehigh's College of Business and Economics 24th in the nation among undergraduate business programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;BusinessWeek Undergrad B-School Rankings&quot;&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/bschools/07/undergrad/ BusinessWeek rankings].&lt;/ref&gt; Lehigh's accounting program is particularly strong, ranked as the number one undergraduate accounting program in the nation by BusinessWeek. The finance program is also strong, ranked as the 18th best undergraduate program in the nation by BusinessWeek.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bwnt.businessweek.com/bschools/undergraduate/07rankings/specialty.asp?rankcatid=9 BusinessWeek Undergrad B-School Specialty Rankings: Accounting Rankings]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accounting and finance majors at Lehigh are heavily recruited by [[Big Four auditors]] and many consulting firms. Additionally, BusinessWeek ranked Lehigh's part-time MBA fifth in the nation and first in the region in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;businessweek&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bwnt.businessweek.com/interactive_reports/bschool_ptmba_2007/ |title=The Best Part-Time MBA Programs |publisher=Bwnt.businessweek.com |date=2009-12-08 |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===College of Arts and Sciences===
Based in Maginnes Hall,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cas.lehigh.edu/casweb/default.aspx?id=1 |title=College of Arts &amp; Sciences |publisher=Cas.lehigh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lehigh offers a variety of humanities courses and visual arts programs. In particular, it has many music programs, including its [http://www3.lehigh.edu/admissions/marching97.asp Marching 97],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marching97.org/ |title=The Marching 97 website |publisher=Marching97.org |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Wind Ensemble and the Philharmonic orchestra. It has a dedicated Humanities Center, which is the site for many literature and other arts-based programs, including the DWS, or Drown Writers Series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lehigh.edu/~indrown/ugrad/activities.html |title=Department of English |publisher=Lehigh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Vague|date=March 2008}}&lt;!-- What is meant by an &quot;active center for discussions&quot;? --&gt;

Lehigh also has a program called ArtsLehigh,&lt;ref&gt;[http://cas.lehigh.edu/artslehigh ArtsLehigh] from the Lehigh website&lt;/ref&gt; oriented towards enhancing interest in the arts on campus.

===College of Education===
The College of Education offers graduate programs in [[Counseling Psychology]], [[Educational Leadership]], [[School Psychology]], [[Special Education]], &quot;Teaching, Learning, and Technology&quot;, and &quot;Comparative and International Education&quot; (see [[comparative education]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lehigh.edu/education/academics/academics.html COE Academic Programs] from Lehigh's website&lt;/ref&gt;  More than 6000 students have received one of these degrees as of 2007, with some of them going on to receive awards such as MetLife/NASSP National Middle Level Principal of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lehigh.edu/education/alumni/index.html |title=COE Alumni page |publisher=Lehigh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Faculty===
{{See also|Lehigh University faculty}}
As of 2010, Lehigh has 666 instructional faculty. Over 99% of the faculty hold a Ph.D. or the highest terminal degree in their field. About 69% of all full-time faculty are tenured.&lt;ref name=&quot;lufacts&quot;/&gt; About three-quarters (74%) are male.  Faculty members are required to have a minimum of four office hours per week.

==Athletics==
{{Main|Lehigh Mountain Hawks}}
[[Image:LehighMountainHawks.png|thumb|left|upright|Lehigh University Mountain Hawks logo]]
Called the Engineers until 1995, Lehigh's teams are now officially known as [[Lehigh Mountain Hawks|the Mountain Hawks]]. Teams prior to 1995  may be referred to by the historic title, Lehigh Engineers, after the Lehigh railroad.

As a member of the [[Patriot League]], Lehigh competes in 25 different [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]] sports. Lehigh's 2006 student-athlete graduation rate of 97% ranked 12th among all 326 NCAA Division I institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;lehighsports1&quot;&gt;http://www.lehighsports.com/info/graduation/default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2002, it won the inaugural ''[[USA Today]]''/NCAA Foundation Award for having the nation's top graduation rate of all Division I institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;lehighsports1&quot;/&gt; Lehigh student-athletes' success on the field and in the classroom has resulted in Lehigh being one of the 20 Division I schools included in ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'''s &quot;America's Best College Sports Programs.&quot; Lehigh graduates have gone on to professional careers in the [[National Football League]], [[Major League Baseball]], [[Major League Soccer]],and the [[National Basketball Association]] as players, scouts, coaches and owners.  Lehigh graduates have competed in the [[Super Bowl]] and won gold medals for the USA at the Olympics.

[[Image:Goodman_Stadium.JPG|right|thumb|Goodman Stadium in the Murray H. Goodman Campus.]]

===Wrestling===
The most storied athletic program at Lehigh is its wrestling team. Over the past several decades it has turned out several All-Americans and had numerous squads finish with Top 20 NCAA national rankings. Under coach Greg Strobel, recent teams have dominated the [[EIWA]] league. On April 15, 2008, the athletic department announced the hiring of former assistant coach and two-time national champion [[Pat Santoro]] as Lehigh's next head coach.

===&quot;The Rivalry&quot;===
{{Main|Lehigh-Lafayette football games (The Rivalry)}}
Lehigh University is notable for its rivalry in sports and academics with nearby [[Lafayette College]]. Since 1884, the two football teams have met 146 times, making [[Lehigh-Lafayette football games (The Rivalry)|&quot;The Rivalry&quot;]] the most played in the history of college football. It is also the longest uninterrupted rivalry in college football, with the teams playing at least once every year since 1897. The Rivalry is considered one of the best in all of college athletics and [[ESPNU]] recently ranked The Rivalry #8 in their Top Ten College Football Rivalries. This game is sold out long before gameday each year.

==Greek life==
{{Prose|section|date=September 2010}}
Nearly all of Lehigh's fraternities and sororities have their own houses which are owned by the university; most of the fraternities and sororities are located on the &quot;Hill&quot; along Upper and Lower Sayre Park Roads. Approximately 34% of undergraduates are members of a Greek organization.  There are currently 22 fraternities, 16 of which are on campus, and 10 sororities, 9 of which are on campus: &lt;ref name=&quot;greek-life&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alumni.lehigh.edu/greekheritage/index.cfm |title=List of all Greek Life at Lehigh |publisher=.lehigh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-12-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fraternities===

{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Alpha Epsilon Pi]] (non-residential)
*[[Alpha Tau Omega]]
*[[Chi Phi]]
*[[Chi Psi]]
*[[Delta Chi]] (non-residential)
*[[Delta Phi]]
*[[Delta Upsilon]]
*[[Kappa Alpha Society|Kappa Alpha]]
*[[Kappa Alpha Psi]] (non-residential)
*[[Kappa Sigma]]
*[[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
*[[Lambda Sigma Upsilon]] (non-residential)
*[[Omega Psi Phi]] (non-residential)
*[[Pi Kappa Alpha]] (non-residential)
*[[Phi Gamma Delta]]
*[[Phi Kappa Theta]]
*[[Phi Sigma Kappa]]
*[[Psi Upsilon]]
*[[Sigma Chi]]
*[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]
*[[Theta Chi]]
*[[Theta Xi]]
{{div col end}}

===Sororities===
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Alpha Chi Omega]]
*[[Alpha Gamma Delta]]
*[[Alpha Omicron Pi]]
*[[Alpha Phi]]
*[[Delta Gamma]]
*[[Gamma Phi Beta]]
*[[Kappa Alpha Theta]]
*[[Lambda Theta Alpha]] (non-residential)
*[[Pi Beta Phi]]
*[[Zeta Tau Alpha]]
{{div col end}}

==Spirit and traditions==
Lehigh students have several lasting traditions: Lehigh's school colors, brown and white, date back to 1874, and the school newspaper of the same name was first published in 1894.

Following the death of Asa Packer in May 1879, the University established &quot;Founder's Day&quot; to be held in October  to remember and recognize those have contributed to the success of the University. The event remains an annual tradition.

Freshmen are traditionally inducted into the University in a convocation in the [[Zoellner Arts Center]] and welcomed at a Freshman-Alumni Rally where their class flag is given to them by the class from fifty years before.

Until the 1970s, freshmen wore small brown hats with their class numbers called &quot;dinks&quot; from the beginning of the fall semester until the Lafayette football game. The week leading up to the big game was full of festivities created to unite the students and fuel spirit. In one of these events, &quot;The Pajama Parade,&quot; the freshmen were led across the penny toll bridge in their pajamas singing &quot;We Pay No Tolls Tonight&quot; to the [[Moravian College]] dormitories where they would serenade the women. The week before the game still involves decoration of the Greek houses, a bonfire, parties, rallies and the Marching 97 performing unexpectedly during classes the Friday before the game.

While the riots to rip down the goal posts in Taylor Stadium are a thing of the past, many alumni return for the Lafayette game (which is usually sold out three months in advance) to root Lehigh on, to attend parties at their former fraternities and sororities, and to see old friends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scrapbook&quot;/&gt;

===Beirut===
{{Main|Beer pong}}
Lehigh University is credited with coining the phrase &quot;Beirut&quot; to represent the popular drinking game Beer pong. The name most likely originated from the 1982 Lebanon War. At Lehigh University, Beer Pong is considered to be the drinking game played with paddles and Beirut is the more common version of throwing a ping pong ball into a cup. There are myriad rules utilized across Lehigh's campus, with the most prevalent rule being &quot;house rules&quot;. Each fraternity has their own style of game play. Another difference between the game played at Lehigh compared to other schools is that at Lehigh the common cup used is a plastic 9oz cup versus the classic Solo cup seen elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playbeirut.com/history.aspx |title=National Beirut League™ - Up the Stakes. Play for Real |publisher=Playbeirut.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rankings==
The 2008 edition of ''Best Colleges'' from ''US News &amp; World Report'''s ranked Lehigh as &quot;Most Selective&quot; in admissions and 31st in the &quot;National Universities (Doctoral)&quot; category. It ranked as follows among the 126 top-tier universities:&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews&quot;/&gt;

*8th in alumni giving.
*16th in classes with fewer than 20 students.
*28th in best value.
*30th in retention rate.
*32nd in student selectivity.
*32nd in graduation rate.
*36th in percentage of students in the top 10 percent of their high school class.
*36th in average standardized test scores.

The magazine also included Lehigh in its &quot;America's Best College Sports Programs &quot; list&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews&quot;/&gt;

''BusinessWeek'' ranked Lehigh's undergraduate College of Business &amp; Economics 25th overall in the nation in 2007. The school was ranked 1st in accounting, 11th in median starting salaries for its graduates, and 21st in academic quality.&lt;ref name=&quot;BusinessWeek Undergrad B-School Rankings&quot;/&gt; In BusinessWeek's 2008 ranking of Which College Grads Earn the Most, Lehigh ranked #14.

''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' in June 2010 ranked Lehigh as number 12 in the nation for return on investment (ROI) when comparing the average career earnings of a graduate to the cost of an education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Zhao |first=Emmeline |url=http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2010/06/30/top-20-colleges-that-offer-best-return-on-investment |title=Top 20: Colleges That Offer Best Return on Investment - Real Time Economics - WSJ |publisher=Blogs.wsj.com |date=2010-06-30 |accessdate=2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
{{Main|List of Lehigh University alumni}}

{{Alumni|date=November 2011}}
*[[Ali Al-Naimi]] (BS [[geology]], 1962), [[CEO]], [[Saudi Aramco]], formerly Arabian American Oil Company, 1984–1995, Minister of Petroleum and Mineral Resources, [[Saudi Arabia]], 1995–present.
*[[William Amelio]] (BS [[chemical engineering]], 1979), former CEO, [[Lenovo]] Group Limited.
*[[John-David F. Bartoe]] (BS [[physics]], 1966), [[Space Shuttle]] [[astronaut]] and [[ISS]] research manager for [[NASA]].
*[[Steven J. Burakoff]], cancer specialist and the author of both ''Therepeutic Immunology'' (2001) and ''Graft-Vs.-Host Disease: Immunology, Pathophysiology, and Treatment'' (1990).
*Congressman [[Charlie Dent]], Member of U.S. House of Representatives.
*[[Peter D. Feaver]], (BA, 1983), member of the [[United States National Security Council|National Security Council]] in the Clinton and Bush administrations and professor at [[Duke University]].
*[[Eugene Grace]] (1899), former president, [[Bethlehem Steel]].
*[[Richard Hayne]] (BA [[anthropology]], 1969), co-founder, [[Urban Outfitters]], [[Anthropologie]] and [[Free People]].
*[[Al Holbert]], legendary American race car driver.
*[[Lee Iacocca]] ([[industrial engineering]], 1945, Hon [[Doctor of Engineering|D.Eng.]] 1965), former chairman, [[Chrysler Corporation]].
*Daniel C. Keefe, former CEO [[Ingersol-Rand]].
*Donald Bryant, President &amp; CEO Hopunion LLC, 1977 BS Finance, 1979 MBA International Economics.
*Philip Kent (BS business &amp; economics, 1976), chairman &amp; CEO, [[Turner Broadcasting]].
*Warren Klawitter  (BS &amp; MS mathematics), vice president &amp; chief [[actuary]], [[GEICO]].
*[[Zhou Ming-Zhen]], Chinese palentologist, academican of the [[Chinese Academy of Sciences]], recipient of the [[Romer-Simpson Medal]].
*Harold Mohler (BS [[Chemical Engineering|chemical engineering]], 1948), former president and CEO, [[Hershey Foods]].
*Donny Most (actor, Happy Days)
*[[Joe Morgenstern]] (BA [[English studies|English]], 1953), 2005 [[Pulitzer Prize]] winner.
*[[Robert J. Myers (politician)|Robert J. Myers]], co-creator of the American [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] program, who set the retirement age at 65.
*[[James Ward Packard|James W. Packard]] ([[Mechanical Engineering|mechanical engineering]], 1884), co-founder of [[Packard]] Motor Company. Funded Lehigh's Packard Lab, named after him.
*[[Roger Penske]] (1959), [[NASCAR]] and [[Indy Racing League|IRL]] team owner and member of [[International Motorsports Hall of Fame]].
*[[Joseph R. Perella]] (BS business &amp; economics, 1964), former chairman of [[investment banking]], [[Morgan Stanley]].
*[[Will Rackley]], professional football player, [[Jacksonville Jaguars]].
*Douglas Rogers (1982), president, [[Wyeth|Wyeth Consumer Healthcare]].
*[[Andrea Tantaros]], [[Fox News]] political analyst, writer and columnist for the ''[[New York Daily News]]''.

==Photo gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Gymnasium (Coppee Hall) 1896.jpg|Coppee Hall Gymnasium (built 1882).
Image:Lehigh_University_Packard_Lab.jpg|Packard Laboratory, home of the P.C. Rossin College of Engineering and Applied Science
Image:Lehigh_University_Rauch.jpg|Rauch Business Center
Image:Fairmart.jpg|The Fairchild-Martindale Library
Image:Lehigh_University_Packard_Windows.jpg|Packard Lab windows
Image:Lehigh_University_Christmas_Saucon.jpg|Christmas Saucon Hall, home of the Department of Mathematics
Image:Lehigh_University_Admissions_Stairs.jpg|Stairs Leading to Alumni Memorial Building

Image:Packer_Memorial_Church_Side_Entrance.jpg|Above an entrance to [[Packer Memorial Church]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Lehigh University Press]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Lehigh University}}
*[http://www.lehigh.edu/ Official website]
*[http://www.lehighsports.com/ Official athletics website]
*{{Cite NIE|year=1905|Lehigh University}}

&lt;!-- {{Geolinks-US-streetscale|40.671525|-75.363464}}--&gt;
{{Coord|40|36.43|N|75|22.74|W|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Patriot League}}
{{Colleges and universities in the Lehigh Valley}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[Category:Lehigh University| ]]
[[Category:Eastern Pennsylvania Rugby Union]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1865]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:National Football League summer camp sites]]
[[Category:Patriot League]]
[[Category:Technical universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Bethlehem, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Northampton County, Pennsylvania]]

[[cs:Lehigh University]]
[[de:Lehigh University]]
[[fr:Université Lehigh]]
[[id:Universitas Lehigh]]
[[ko:리하이 대학교]]
[[nl:Lehigh-universiteit]]
[[no:Lehigh University]]
[[fi:Lehighin yliopisto]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยลีไฮ]]
[[zh:理海大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
