<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4319919" ns="0" title="Linda Vista University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name = Linda Vista University
|image =  
|motto = 
|established = 
|endowment =  
|type = [[Private school|Private]]
|president= 
|city = [[Chiapas]] in southern [[Mexico]]. 
|state = 
|country = 
|campus = 
|students= 
|staff= 
|website= [http://www.adventist.org/ www.adventist.org]
}}


'''Linda Vista University''' ([[Spanish language|Spanish]]: '''''Universidad Linda Vista''''') is a private [[university]] in the state of [[Chiapas]] in southern [[Mexico]].  Linda Vista is affiliated with the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]].

==History==
Linda Vista began as a high school, '''Colégio Linda Vista''' or '''Linda Vista High School''', located in the city of [[Villahermosa, Tabasco|Villahermosa]], [[Tabasco]], in 1901.  A few years later, it moved to the mountains of Chiapas, near the town of [[Pueblo Nuevo Solistahuacán]], commonly known as Pueblo Nuevo.  The first tertiary classes offered at Linda Vista were offered in conjunction with [[Montemorelos University|Universidad de Montemorelos]] (Montemorelos University), another Adventist university in Mexico, located in [[Montemorelos, Mexico|Montemorelos]], [[Nuevo León]].  This continued for several years, but Linda Vista is ({{As of|2006|lc=on}}) finishing the process of making all of its majors independent from Montemorelos.  Linda Vista now has its own &quot;Colégio Linda Vista,&quot; with many students in its elementary (primaria), junior high (secundaria), and high school (preparatorio).

==Linda Vista today==
In 2005, Linda Vista made the decision to accept a public school in [[Mérida, Mexico|Mérida]], [[Yucatán]], as a secondary campus.  Also in 2005, Colégio Linda Vista made the decision to officially and administratively separate itself from Universidad Linda Vista.  This separation will ultimately take the form of separate buildings dedicated exclusively to its use.  Linda Vista also has integrated a new campus in the state capital of [[Tuxtla Gutiérrez]].  Today, Linda Vista offers bachelor's degrees in the areas of Educational Sciences (5 specializations), Administrative Sciences, Theology, Nursing, Computer Systems Administration, an engineering degree in Computer Systems Administration, and a master's degree in Education (in association with Montemorelos University).

==External links==
*[http://www.ulv.edu.mx The official site of Universidad Linda Vista] (in Spanish)

==See also==
*[[List of Seventh-day Adventist colleges and universities]]


{{Seventh-day Adventists Colleges and Universities in North America}}

{{Mexico-edu-stub}}
{{SeventhdayAdventist-stub}}

{{coord missing|Mexico}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the Seventh-day Adventist Church|Linda Vista, Universidad]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Chiapas|Linda Vista, Universidad]]

[[es:Universidad Linda Vista]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
