<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4327868" ns="0" title="Walk for Hunger"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:WalkForHunger2011.png|thumb|The logo of the 2011 Walk for Hunger]]'''Project Bread's Walk for Hunger''' is the oldest continual [[Walkathon|pledge walk]] in the [[United States]] and the largest annual one-day fundraiser to alleviate local hunger in [[Massachusetts]]. 

==Project Bread - The Walk for Hunger==
Project Bread is an antihunger organization creating and promoting programs to help end hunger in Massachusetts.  With the Chefs in Schools Initiative, the organization is changing school food. The Initiative is a joint effort with Project Bread and the City of Boston to change what kids eat in the school cafeteria. First piloted in the Boston Public Schools, the &quot;Chef in Resident,&quot; Chef Kirk Conrad, is now working in Lawrence and Salem School districts.&lt;ref&gt;McCabe, Kathy. [http://www.boston.com/community/moms/articles/2011/01/23/a_new_way_of_looking_at_school_lunches_is_bringing_professional_chefs_into_the_mix/ Stirring it up: A new way of looking at school lunches is bringing professional chefs into the mix], ''[[Boston Globe]]''. Published January 23, 2011. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lynds, John. [http://www.eastietimes.com/2011/01/26/project-bread-applauds-changes-to-meal-guidelines/ Project Bread Applauds Changes to Meal Guidelines], ''East Boston Times-Free Press''. Published January 26, 2011. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Child Nutrition Outreach Program at Project Bread has partnered with the U.S. Department of Agriculture to promote participation the Summer Food Service Program and the National School Breakfast Program, both federally funded programs. Making sure kids don’t go hungry when they're not in school, sites around the state allow low-income children the opportunity for free or reduced priced meals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thereminder.com/localnews/springfield/projectbreadhelpst/ Project Bread helps to fund summer food programs], ''[[Springfield, Massachusetts#Newspapers|Springfield Reminder]]''. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedailyitemoflynn.com/articles/2009/06/10/news/news10.txt Project Bread to fund summer meals], ''[[The Daily Item (Lynn)|The Daily Item]]''. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Project Bread's 2010 status report, 660,000 people in Massachusetts are hungry.&lt;ref&gt;Nawar, Alex. [http://dailyfreepress.com/2011/02/03/boston-ranked-third-in-u-s-for-creating-new-jobs/ Boston ranked third in U.S. for creating new jobs], ''[[The Daily Free Press]]''. Published February 3, 2011. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Project Bread is trying to eliminate the number of food insecure people with the FoodSource Hotline, where people can find out how to get the help they need.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.capecodonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20110130/LIFE/110129811/-1/NEWSMAP Parent education and support calendar: FoodSource Hotline of Project Bread], ''[[Cape Cod Times]]''. Published January 30, 2011. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Project Bread has also created an easy website to help residents apply for food stamps.&lt;ref&gt;Lynds, John. [http://www.eastietimes.com/2010/12/16/project-bread-report-highlights-problems-and-offers-solutions/ Project Bread report highlights problems and offers solutions], ''East Boston Times-Free Press''. Published December 16, 2010. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.north-attleboro.ma.us/boh/massachusetts_food_and_nutrition.htm Massachusetts Food and Nutrition Program], [[North Attleborough, Massachusetts|Town of North Attleboro]]. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Boston Red Sox]] player [[Jacoby Ellsbury]] came out with &quot;ZinfandEllsbury&quot; Wine in 2010, with proceeds benefitting Project Bread.&lt;ref&gt;Grillo, Thomas. [http://www.bostonherald.com/business/general/view/20100512red_sox_tip_glass_to_charity_jacoby_ellsbury_josh_beckett_uncork_collectible_wines Red Sox tip glass to charity: Jacoby Ellsbury, Josh Beckett uncork collectible wines], ''[[Boston Herald]]''. Published May 12, 2010. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:WalkForHunger38.jpg|thumb|The logo of the 2009 Walk for Hunger]]The first Walk was held in [[1969]] by a group of activists from the Paulist Center, led by Patrick Hughes. An estimated 2,000 people walked and raised $26,000 to help fund two hunger projects. At the 2009 Walk for Hunger, 44,000 people came to the Boston Common to raise millions for the hungry. The 20-mile pledge Walk attracted over 1,000 religious organizations, as well as 1,200 corporate teams, 1,200 schools, 2,000 volunteers, and 700 friends and family groups who all came together to help feed hungry people in Massachusetts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://massnonprofit.org/news.php?artid=1933&amp;catid=12 Project Bread Raises $3.8M in Its Annual “Walk for Hunger”], Massnonprofit.org. Published May 16, 2010. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 20-mile Walk occurs annually on the first Sunday in May and weaves through [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]], [[Brookline, Massachusetts|Brookline]], [[Newton, Massachusetts|Newton]], [[Watertown, Massachusetts|Watertown]] and [[Cambridge, Massachusetts|Cambridge]], and includes entertainment and free snacks along the way. The 43rd annual Walk for Hunger will take place on Sunday, May 1, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://calendar.boston.com/boston-ma/events/show/166732885-project-breads-43rd-annual-walk-for-hunger Project Bread's 43rd Annual Walk for Hunger], ''[[The Boston Globe]]''. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in 2010, the new leadership sponsor for the event is Friehofer's Baking Company.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milforddailynews.com/business/x1060312173/Business-Digest Walk for Hunger takes place May 2], ''[[The Milford Daily News]]''. Published April 13, 2010. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Heart &amp; Sole Walkers and Volunteers ==
Unlike regular Walkers, The Heart &amp; Sole Walkers must raise at least $500 to become part of the Heart &amp; Sole Circle. The group raises more than $1 million to help hungry people annually. These special Walkers are between the ages of 9 and 90. Their help is what makes it possible to raise one third of the money given to help the hungry. Special T-shirts are given to these individuals.

Volunteers at the Walk help assist Walkers. At each checkpoint, volunteers help check off mile sheets, hand out cold water, assist Walkers by helping them cross the streets safely and motivating the participants.&lt;ref&gt;[http://volunteerboston.org/IND/ProjBread.shtml Project Bread (Walk For Hunger)], Volunteer Boston. Retrieved February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.projectbread.org/ Project Bread]
*[http://www.projectbread.org/site/PageServer?pagename=walk_main The Walk for Hunger]

[[Category:Recurring events established in 1969]]
[[Category:Annual events in Boston, Massachusetts]]
{{charity-org-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
