<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="43373" ns="0" title="Clint Eastwood"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox person
| image        = ClintEastwoodSept10TIFF.jpg
| caption      = Eastwood at the [[2010 Toronto International Film Festival]]
| alt          = A headshot of an older man is looking to the left while smiling
| birth_name   = Clinton Eastwood, Jr.
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1930|5|31}}
| birth_place  = [[San Francisco]], [[California]], U.S.
| nationality  = [[United States|American]]
| occupation   = Actor, director, producer, composer, politician
| years_active = 1955–present 
| spouse       = Maggie Johnson (1953–84; two children)&lt;br&gt;[[Dina Eastwood|Dina Ruiz]] (1996–present; one child)
| children     = Kimber Tunis&lt;br&gt;[[Kyle Eastwood]]&lt;br&gt;[[Alison Eastwood]]&lt;br&gt;[[Scott Eastwood|Scott Reeves]]&lt;br&gt;Kathryn Reeves&lt;br&gt;Francesca Fisher-Eastwood&lt;br&gt;Morgan Eastwood
}}
{{Clint Eastwood sidebar}}
'''Clinton''' &quot;'''Clint'''&quot; '''Eastwood, Jr.''' (born May&amp;nbsp;31, 1930) is an American film actor, director, producer, composer and politician. Eastwood first came to prominence as a supporting cast member in the TV series ''[[Rawhide (TV series)|Rawhide]]'' (1959&amp;ndash;1965). He rose to fame for playing the [[Man with No Name]] in [[Sergio Leone]]'s [[Dollars Trilogy|''Dollars'' trilogy]] of [[spaghetti western]]s (''[[A Fistful of Dollars]]'', ''[[For a Few Dollars More]]'', and ''[[The Good, the Bad and the Ugly]]'') during the 1960s, and as [[San Francisco Police Department]] Inspector [[Harry Callahan (character)|Harry Callahan]] in the ''[[Dirty Harry (film series)|Dirty Harry]]'' films (''[[Dirty Harry]]'', ''[[Magnum Force]]'', ''[[The Enforcer (1976 film)|The Enforcer]]'', ''[[Sudden Impact]]'', and ''[[The Dead Pool]]'') during the 1970s and 1980s. These roles, along with several others in which he plays tough-talking no-nonsense police officers, have made him an enduring [[cultural icon]] of [[masculinity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer, Landy &amp; Smith&quot;&gt;Fischer, Landy &amp; Smith, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kitses, p. 307&lt;/ref&gt; 

Eastwood won Academy Awards for [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] and Producer of the [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]], as well as receiving nominations for [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]], for his work in the films ''[[Unforgiven]]'' (1992) and ''[[Million Dollar Baby]]'' (2004). These films in particular, as well as others including ''[[Play Misty for Me]]'' (1971), ''[[The Outlaw Josey Wales]]'' (1976), ''[[Pale Rider]]'' (1985), ''[[In the Line of Fire]]'' (1993), ''[[The Bridges of Madison County (film)|The Bridges of Madison County]]'' (1995), and ''[[Gran Torino]]'' (2008), have all received commercial success and critical acclaim. Eastwood's only comedies have been ''[[Every Which Way but Loose (film)|Every Which Way but Loose]]'' (1978), its sequel ''[[Any Which Way You Can]]'' (1980), and ''[[Bronco Billy]]'' (1980); despite being widely panned by critics, the &quot;Any Which Way&quot; films are the two highest-grossing films of his career after adjusting for inflation.

In addition to directing most of his own [[star vehicles]], Eastwood has also directed films in which he did not appear, such as ''[[Mystic River (film)|Mystic River]]'' (2003) and ''[[Letters from Iwo Jima]]'' (2006), for which he received Academy Award nominations, and ''[[Changeling (film)|Changeling]]'' (2008). He has received considerable critical praise in France in particular, including for several of his films which were panned in the United States, and was awarded two of France's highest honors: in 1994 he received the [[Ordre des Arts et des Lettres]] medal and in 2007 was awarded the [[Légion d'honneur]] medal. In 2000 he was awarded the Italian [[Venice Film Festival]] [[Golden Lion]] for lifetime achievement.

Since 1967, Eastwood has run his own production company, [[Malpaso Productions|Malpaso]], which has produced the vast majority of his films. He also served as the nonpartisan mayor of [[Carmel-by-the-Sea, California]], from 1986 to 1988. Eastwood has seven children by five different women, and has married twice.

==Early life==
{{Main|Early life and work of Clint Eastwood}}
Eastwood was born in [[San Francisco]] to Clinton Eastwood, Sr. (1906&amp;ndash;70), a steelworker and migrant worker, and Margaret Ruth (née Runner; 1909&amp;ndash;2006), a factory worker.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot13&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; He was nicknamed &quot;Samson&quot; by the hospital nurses as he weighed {{convert|11|lb|6|oz|kg}} at birth.&lt;ref name=&quot;At80&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/news/eastwood-at-80-1986872.html|title=Eastwood at 80|last1=Amara|first1=Pavan|last2=Sundberg|first2=Charlotte|date=May&amp;nbsp;30, 2010 |work=independent.co.uk|work=[[The Independent]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vnYapQvw|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;16, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian 08&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Day|first=Elizabeth|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2008/nov/02/clint-eastwood-drama|title=Gentle Man Clint|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=November&amp;nbsp;2, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vnYkOYuP|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;16, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; After his father died in 1970, Eastwood's mother remarried to John Belden Wood (1913&amp;ndash;2004) in 1972, and they remained married until his death 32 years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2004-02-22/news/17413417_1_stone-youngberg-pebble-beach-death | work=The San Francisco Chronicle | title=BRETTEVILLE, Frances Mein De | date=February 22, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood is of English, Irish, Scottish, and Dutch ancestry&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot13&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; and was raised in a [[American middle class|middle class]] home with his younger sister, Jean (born 1934).&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Zmi12&quot;&gt;Zmijewsky, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; His family relocated often as his father worked at different jobs along the [[West Coast of the United States|West Coast]], including at a pulp mill.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot15&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Leung|first=Rebecca|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/02/03/Sunday/main671541.shtml|title=Two Sides Of Clint Eastwood: Lesley Stahl Talks To Oscar-Nominated Actor And Director|work=[[CBS Evening News]]|date=February&amp;nbsp;6, 2005|archiveurl=
http://www.webcitation.org/5vnYqoTvt|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The family settled in [[Piedmont, California]], where Eastwood attended [[Piedmont Middle School|Piedmont Junior High School]] and [[Piedmont High School (California)|Piedmont Senior High School]], taking part in sports such as basketball, football, gymnastics, and competitive swimming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cah123&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 123 (interviewer Tim Cahill)&lt;/ref&gt; He later transferred to [[Oakland Technical High School]] where the drama teachers encouraged him to enroll in school plays, but he was not interested. As his family moved to different areas he held a series of jobs including lifeguard, paper carrier, grocery clerk, forest firefighter, and golf caddy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot17&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1950, Eastwood began a one-year stint as a lifeguard for the United States Army during the [[Korean War]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot1819&quot;&gt;Eliot, pp. 18–19&lt;/ref&gt; and was posted to [[Fort Ord]] in California.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot23&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; While on leave in 1951 Eastwood was a passenger onboard a [[Douglas A-1 Skyraider|Douglas AD bomber]] that ran out of fuel and crashed into the ocean near [[Point Reyes]].&lt;ref&gt;Frank (1982), p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; After escaping from the sinking aircraft he and the pilot swam {{convert|3|mi|km|0}} to safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot25&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood later moved to Los Angeles and began a romance with Maggie Johnson, a college student.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot26&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; He managed an apartment house in [[Beverly Hills]] by day and worked at a gas station by night.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG556&quot;&gt;McGilligan, pp. 55–56&lt;/ref&gt; He enrolled at [[Los Angeles City College]] and married Johnson shortly before Christmas 1953 in [[South Pasadena, California|South Pasadena]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG556&quot;/&gt;

==Film career==
===1950s===
{{Main|Early life and work of Clint Eastwood#Early work:1950s|l1=Clint Eastwood in the 1950s}}

====Early career struggles====
According to the [[CBS]] press release for ''[[Rawhide (TV series)|Rawhide]]'', [[Universal Studios]], known then as the Universal-International film company, was shooting in Fort Ord when an enterprising assistant spotted Eastwood and arranged a meeting with the series' director.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG52&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; According to Eastwood's official biography the key figure was a man named Chuck Hill, who was stationed in Fort Ord and had contacts in Hollywood.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG52&quot;/&gt; Later, in Los Angeles, Hill became reacquainted with Eastwood and managed to sneak him into one of Universal's studios, where he showed him to cameraman [[Irving Glassberg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG52&quot;/&gt; Glassberg arranged for an audition with [[Arthur Lubin]] who, although impressed with Eastwood's appearance and {{convert|6|ft|4|in|adj=on}} frame,&lt;ref&gt;Baldwin, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; initially questioned his acting skills remarking, &quot;He was quite amateurish. He didn't know which way to turn or which way to go or do anything&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG60&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; Lubin suggested he attend drama classes and arranged for his initial contract in April&amp;nbsp;1954 at $100 (US${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|100|1954}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) per week.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG60&quot;/&gt; After signing Eastwood was initially criticized for his stiff manner, his squint and with hissing his lines through his teeth, a feature that would become a life-long trademark.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CinemaInstitute1972&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=University of Southern California. Division of Cinema|author2=American Film Institute|author3=Center for Understanding Media|title=Filmfacts|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NuIvAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011|year=1972|publisher=Division of Cinema of the University of Southern California|page=423}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Press, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stillman, pp. 130–132&lt;/ref&gt;

In May&amp;nbsp;1954 Eastwood auditioned for his first role in ''[[Six Bridges to Cross]]'', but was rejected by [[Joseph Pevney]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG63&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; After many unsuccessful auditions he eventually landed a minor role as a laboratory assistant in director [[Jack Arnold (director)|Jack Arnold's]] ''[[Revenge of the Creature]]'', a sequel to ''[[The Creature from the Black Lagoon]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG64&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; He then worked for three weeks on Lubin's ''[[Lady Godiva of Coventry]]'' in September&amp;nbsp;1954, then won a role in February&amp;nbsp;1955 as a sailor in ''[[Francis in the Navy]]'' as well as appearing uncredited in another Jack Arnold film, ''[[Tarantula (film)|Tarantula]]'', in which he played a squadron pilot.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzgerald &amp; Magers, p. 264&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; In May&amp;nbsp;1955 Eastwood had a brief appearance in the film ''[[Never Say Goodbye (1956 film)|Never Say Goodbye]]'', during which he shared a scene with [[Rock Hudson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG81&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; Universal presented him with his first television role on July&amp;nbsp;2, 1955, in [[NBC]]'s ''Allen in Movieland'', which starred [[Tony Curtis]] and [[Benny Goodman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG86&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; Although he continued to develop as an actor Universal terminated Eastwood's contract on October&amp;nbsp;23, 1955.&lt;ref&gt;Eliot, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, p. xxi&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood then joined the Marsh Agency and although Lubin landed him his biggest role to date in ''[[The First Traveling Saleslady]]'' (1956) and later hired him for ''[[Escapade in Japan]]'', without a formal contract Eastwood struggled.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG85&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; He met financial advisor [[Irving Leonard (accountant)|Irving Leonard]], who would later arguably take most responsibility for launching his career in the late 1950s and 1960s, whom Eastwood described as being &quot;like a second father to me&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 185&lt;/ref&gt; On Leonard's advice Eastwood switched talent agencies to the Kumin-Olenick Agency in 1956 and to Mitchell Gertz in 1957. He landed several small roles in 1956 as a temperamental army officer for a segment of [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]'s ''Reader's Digest'' series, and as a motorcycle gang member on a ''[[Highway Patrol (TV series)|Highway Patrol]]'' episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG85&quot;/&gt; Eastwood had a minor uncredited role as a ranch hand in his first western film, ''[[Star in the Dust|Law Man]]'', in June&amp;nbsp;1956.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG81&quot;/&gt; The following year he played a cadet in the ''[[The West Point Story (TV series)|West Point]]'' television series and a suicidal gold prospector in ''[[Death Valley Days]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG87&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; In 1955 he played a Navy lieutenant in a segment of ''[[Navy Log]]'' and in early 1959 he made a notable guest appearance on ''[[Maverick (TV series)|Maverick]]'', opposite [[James Garner]], as a cowardly villain intent on marrying a rich girl for money.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG87&quot;/&gt; Eastwood had a small part as an aviator in the French picture ''[[Lafayette Escadrille (film)|Lafayette Escadrille]]'' and took on a major role as an ex-Confederate renegade in ''[[Ambush at Cimarron Pass]]'', a film which Eastwood viewed as disastrous and the lowest point of his career.&lt;ref&gt;Frayling, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Brien, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG93&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

====Rawhide====
{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=left|quote=&quot;Lazy, and would cost you a morning. I never started a day with Clint Eastwood in the first scene, because you knew he was gonna be late, at least a half hour or an hour.&quot;|source=—''[[Rawhide (TV series)|Rawhide]]'' director [[Thomas Carr (director)|Thomas Carr]] on Eastwood.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG111&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
In a long sought-after career breakthrough, Eastwood was cast as Rowdy Yates for the CBS hour-long western series ''Rawhide'' in 1958,&lt;ref name=&quot;McG95&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot45&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; although he was not especially happy with his role. By now, aged almost 30, he felt that his character Rowdy was too young and too cloddish for him to feel comfortable with the part.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Miller, Kenneth|url=http://www.readersdigest.com.au/content/rd-face-to-face-clint-eastwood/|title=RD Face to Face: Clint Eastwood|work=[[Reader's Digest|Reader's Digest Australia]]|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080726195125/http://www.readersdigest.com.au/content/rd-face-to-face-clint-eastwood/|archivedate=July&amp;nbsp;26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Filming began in Arizona in the summer of 1958&lt;ref&gt;O'Brien, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; and on release it took just three weeks for ''Rawhide'' to reach the top&amp;nbsp;20 in the TV ratings. Although the series never won an [[Emmy]] it was a major success for several years, reaching its peak at number six in the ratings between October&amp;nbsp;1960 and April&amp;nbsp;1961.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG110&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Rawhide'' years (1959&amp;ndash;65) were some of the most grueling of Eastwood's career. He often filmed for six days a week at an average of twelve hours a day, yet some directors still criticized him for not working hard enough.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG111&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG110&quot;/&gt; By late 1963 ''Rawhide'''s popularity had declined. Lacking freshness in the scripts, it was canceled in the middle of the 1965&amp;ndash;66&amp;nbsp;television season.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 125&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood made his first attempt at directing when he filmed several trailers for the show, although he was unable to convince producers to let him direct an episode.&lt;ref&gt;Emery, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; In the show's first season Eastwood earned $750 (US${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|750|1958}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) an episode. At the time of its cancellation he received a $119,000 (US${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|119000|1965}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) compensation package.&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, p. xxvi&lt;/ref&gt;

===1960s===
{{Main|Clint Eastwood in the 1960s}}
[[File:Almeria.jpg|thumb|right|Set of ''The Good, Bad and the Ugly'' in Almería in 2009]]
In late 1963 Eastwood's co-star on ''Rawhide'', [[Eric Fleming]], rejected an offer to star in an Italian-made western called ''[[A Fistful of Dollars]]'', to be directed in a remote region of Spain by [[Sergio Leone]], who was relatively unknown at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG126&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt; Other actors, including [[Charles Bronson]], [[Steve Reeves]], [[Richard Harrison (actor)|Richard Harrison]], Frank Wolfe, [[Henry Fonda]], [[James Coburn]], and [[Ty Hardin]], were also considered for the role. Knowing that he could play a cowboy convincingly Harrison suggested Eastwood, who in turn saw the film as an opportunity to escape from ''Rawhide''. He signed a contract for $15,000 (US${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|15000|1964}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) in wages for eleven&amp;nbsp;weeks' work with a bonus of a [[Mercedes-Benz|Mercedes]] automobile upon completion and arrived in Rome in May&amp;nbsp;1964&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot59&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG128&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood later spoke about the transition from a television western to ''A Fistful of Dollars'': &quot;In ''Rawhide'' I did get awfully tired of playing the conventional white hat. The hero who kisses old ladies and dogs and was kind to everybody. I decided it was time to be an anti-hero.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hughes, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood was instrumental in creating the [[Man with No Name]] character's distinctive visual style and, although a non-smoker, Leone insisted he smoke cigars as an essential ingredient of the &quot;mask&quot; he was attempting to create with the loner character.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG131&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 131&lt;/ref&gt;

Some interior shots for ''A Fistful of Dollars'' were done at the [[Cinecittà]] studio on the outskirts of Rome, before production moved to a small village in [[Andalusia]], [[Spain]].&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 134&lt;/ref&gt; The film became a benchmark in the development of [[spaghetti western]]s, with Leone depicting a more lawless and desolate world than in traditional westerns; meanwhile challenging stereotypical American notions of a western hero by replacing him with a morally ambiguous [[antihero]]. The film's success meant Eastwood became a major star in Italy&lt;ref&gt;Mercer, p. 272&lt;/ref&gt; and he was re-hired by Leone to star in ''[[For a Few Dollars More]]'' (1965), the second film of the trilogy. Through the efforts of screenwriter [[Luciano Vincenzoni]], the rights to the film and the final film of the trilogy (''[[The Good, the Bad and the Ugly]]'') were sold to [[United Artists]] for roughly $900,000 (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|900000|1965|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;McG148&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 148&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=left|quote=&quot;I wanted to play it with an economy of words and create this whole feeling through attitude and movement. It was just the kind of character I had envisioned for a long time, keep to the mystery and allude to what happened in the past. It came about after the frustration of doing ''[[Rawhide (TV series)|Rawhide]]'' for so long. I felt the less he said the stronger he became and the more he grew in the imagination of the audience.&quot;|source=—Eastwood, on playing the Man with No Name character&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In January&amp;nbsp;1966 Eastwood met with producer [[Dino De Laurentiis]] in New York City and agreed to star in a non-western five-part anthology production named ''[[Le streghe]]'' (&quot;The Witches&quot;)  opposite De Laurentiis' wife, actress [[Silvana Mangano]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG150&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood's nineteen-minute installment only took a few days to shoot but his performance did not go down well with the critics, with one saying &quot;no other performance of his is quite so 'un-Clintlike'&amp;nbsp;&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG151&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; Two months later Eastwood began work on the third ''Dollars'' film, ''The Good, the Bad and the Ugly'', in which he again played the mysterious Man with No Name. [[Lee Van Cleef]] returned to play a ruthless fortune seeker, while [[Eli Wallach]] portrayed the cunning Mexican bandit Tuco. The storyline involves the search for a cache of [[Confederate gold]] buried in a cemetery. One day during filming of a scene where a bridge was to be dynamited Eastwood, suspicious of explosives, urged Wallach to retreat to the hilltop saying, &quot;I know about these things. Stay as far away from special effects and explosives as you can.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG156&quot;&gt;McGillagan, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; Minutes later crew confusion, over the word &quot;Vaya!&quot;, resulted in a premature explosion which could have killed the co-star, while necessitating rebuilding of the bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG156&quot;/&gt; 

The ''Dollars'' trilogy was not shown in the United States until 1967 when ''A Fistful of Dollars'' opened in January, ''For a Few Dollars More'' in May, and ''The Good, the Bad and the Ugly'' in December.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG157&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 157&lt;/ref&gt; All the films proved successful in cinemas, particularly ''The Good, the Bad and the Ugly'' which eventually earned $8&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|8000000|1967|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) in rental earnings and turned Eastwood into a major film star.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG157&quot;/&gt; All three films received generally bad reviews and marked the beginning of Eastwood's battle to win the respect of American film critics.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG158&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; [[Judith Crist]] described ''A Fistful of Dollars'' as &quot;cheapjack&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Crist|first=Judith|title=Plain Murder All the Way|work=[[New York World Journal Tribune]]|date=February&amp;nbsp;2, 1967}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ''[[Newsweek]]'' considered ''For a Few Dollars More'' as &quot;excruciatingly dopey&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG158&quot;/&gt; [[Renata Adler]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'' remarked that ''The Good, the Bad and the Ugly'' was &quot;the most expensive, pious and repellent movie in the history of its peculiar genre&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Adler|first= Renata|title=The Screen:Zane Grey Meets the Marquis de Sade|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50F16FE3D5C147493C7AB178AD85F4C8685F9|format=Fee required|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=January&amp;nbsp;25, 1968|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that it is now widely considered one of the finest films in the history of cinema.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inc.2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Active Interest Media, Inc.|title=American Cowboy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=c-oCAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA10|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011|date=2005-09–2005–10|publisher=Active Interest Media, Inc.|page=10|id={{ISSN|10793690}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston, p. 277&lt;/ref&gt; [[Time (magazine)|''Time'' magazine]] highlighted the film's wooden acting, especially Eastwood's, although critics such as [[Vincent Canby]] and [[Bosley Crowther]] of ''The New York Times'' praised Eastwood's coolness in playing the tall, lone stranger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Crowther|first=Bosley|title=A Fistful of Dollars (1964)|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F40910FC3F5D107B93C0A91789D85F438685F9&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=A+Fistful+of+Dollars&amp;st=p|format=Fee required|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=February&amp;nbsp;2, 1967|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leone's unique style of cinematography was widely acclaimed, even by some critics who panned the acting.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG158&quot;/&gt;

Stardom brought more &quot;tough guy&quot; roles for Eastwood. He signed for the American revisionist western ''[[Hang 'Em High]]'' (1968), in which he featured alongside [[Inger Stevens]], [[Pat Hingle]], [[Dennis Hopper]], [[Ed Begley]], [[Bruce Dern]], and [[James MacArthur]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG159&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 159&lt;/ref&gt; A cross between ''Rawhide'' and Leone's westerns, the film brought him a salary of $400,000 (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|400000|1968|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) and 25% of its net earnings.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG159&quot;/&gt; He plays a man who seeks revenge after being lynched by vigilantes and left for dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG160&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; Using money earned from the ''Dollars'' trilogy Leonard helped establish Eastwood's production company,  [[Malpaso Productions]], named after the [[Malpaso Creek]] on Eastwood's property in [[Monterey County, California]]. Leonard arranged for ''Hang 'Em High'' to be a joint production with United Artists&lt;ref name=&quot;McG162&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; and, when it opened in July&amp;nbsp;1968, the film became the biggest United Artists opening in history — its box office receipts exceeding all the James Bond films of the time.&lt;ref&gt;''Clint Eastwood's Stock Hits New High'', [[United Artists]] press release, 1968&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG165&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 165&lt;/ref&gt; It was widely praised by critics; including Archer Winsten of the ''[[New York Post]]'' who described ''Hang 'Em High'' as, &quot;a western of quality, courage, danger and excitement&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zmi12&quot;/&gt;

Before the release of ''Hang 'Em High'' Eastwood had already begun work on the film ''[[Coogan's Bluff (film)|Coogan's Bluff]]'', about an Arizona deputy sheriff tracking a wanted psychopathic criminal ([[Don Stroud]]) through the streets of New York City. He was reunited with Universal Studios for the project after receiving an offer of $1&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|1000000|1967|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}})&amp;mdash;more than double his previous salary.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG165&quot;/&gt; [[Jennings Lang]] arranged for Eastwood to meet [[Don Siegel]], a Universal contract director who later became one of Eastwood's close friends, with the two forming a close partnership that would last for more than ten years over five films.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG167&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 167&lt;/ref&gt;  Filming began in November&amp;nbsp;1967, before the full script had been finalized.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG169&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; The film was controversial for its portrayal of violence,&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd and Robinson, p. 417&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Slocum, p. 205&lt;/ref&gt; with Eastwood's role creating the prototype for what would later become the [[machismo|macho]] cop of the ''Dirty Harry'' films. ''Coogan's Bluff'' also became the first collaboration with Argentine composer [[Lalo Schifrin]], who would later compose the jazzy score to several of Eastwood's films in the 1970s and 1980s, particularly the [[Dirty Harry (film series)|''Dirty Harry'' film series]].

Eastwood was paid $850,000 (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|850000|1968|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) in 1968 for the war epic ''[[Where Eagles Dare]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;McG172&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; about a World War II squad parachuting into a [[Gestapo]] stronghold in the mountains. [[Richard Burton]] played the squad's commander with Eastwood as his right-hand man. He was also cast as [[Two-Face]] in the [[Batman (TV series)|''Batman'']] television show, but the series was canceled before filming could commence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot83&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood then branched out to star in the only [[musical film|musical]] of his career, ''[[Paint Your Wagon (film)|Paint Your Wagon]]'' (1969). Eastwood and fellow non-singer [[Lee Marvin]] play gold miners who share the same wife (portrayed by [[Jean Seberg]]). Bad weather and delays plagued the production while its budget eventually exceeded $20&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|20000000|1969|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}), extremely expensive for the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG173&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 173&lt;/ref&gt; The film was not a critical or commercial success, although it was nominated for a [[Golden Globe Award for Best Motion Picture&amp;nbsp;– Musical or Comedy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Paint Your Wagon (1969)|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/37096/Paint-Your-Wagon/details|work=[[The New York Times]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vcZqgkCy|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1970s===
{{Main|Clint Eastwood in the 1970s}}
In 1970, Eastwood starred in the western ''[[Two Mules for Sister Sara]]'' with [[Shirley MacLaine]] and directed by [[Don Siegel]]. The film follows an American mercenary who gets mixed up with a whore disguised as a nun and ends up helping a group of Juarista rebels during the reign of Emperor [[Maximilian I of Mexico]].&lt;ref&gt;Frayling, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, p. 76&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood once again played a mysterious stranger&amp;mdash;unshaven, wearing a serape-like vest, and smoking a cigar.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; Although the film received moderate reviews&lt;ref name=&quot;McG182&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kauffman|first= Stanley|title=Stanley Kauffman on Films|work=[[The New Republic]]|date=August&amp;nbsp;1, 1970}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;the film is listed in ''The New York Times Guide to the Best 1,000&amp;nbsp;Movies Ever Made''.&lt;ref&gt;Canby, Maslin, and Nichols&lt;/ref&gt; Later the same year Eastwood starred as one of a group of Americans who steal a fortune in gold from the [[Nazi]]s in the World War II film ''[[Kelly's Heroes]]'' with [[Donald Sutherland]] and [[Telly Savalas]]. ''Kelly's Heroes'' was the last film in which Eastwood appeared that was not produced by his own Malpaso Productions.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG184&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; Filming commenced in July&amp;nbsp;1969 [[Filming location|on location]] in [[Yugoslavia]] and in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG183&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 183&lt;/ref&gt; The film received mostly a positive reception and its anti-war sentiments were recognized.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG184&quot;/&gt; In the winter of 1969&amp;ndash;70, Eastwood and Siegel began planning his next film, ''[[The Beguiled]]'', a tale of a wounded Union soldier held captive by the sexually repressed matron of a southern girl's school.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG185&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 185&lt;/ref&gt; Upon release the film received major recognition in France and is considered one of Eastwood's finest works by the French.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG190&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 190&lt;/ref&gt; However, it grossed less than $1&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|1000000|1970|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) and, according to Eastwood and Lang, flopped due to poor publicity and the &quot;emasculated&quot; role of Eastwood.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG189&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=right|quote=&quot;Dustin Hoffman and Al Pacino play losers very well. But my audience like to be in there vicariously with a winner. That isn't always popular with critics. My characters have sensitivity and vulnerabilities, but they're still winners. I don't pretend to understand losers. When I read a script about a loser I think of people in life who are losers and they seem to want it that way. It's a compulsive philosophy with them. Winners tell themselves, I'm as bright as the next person. I can do it. Nothing can stop me.&quot;|source=—Eastwood, on his role in ''[[The Beguiled]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;McG189&quot;/&gt;}}
Eastwood's career reached a turning point in 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG196&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt; Before Irving Leonard died he and Eastwood had discussed the idea of Malpaso producing ''[[Play Misty for Me]]'', a film that was to give Eastwood the artistic control he desired and his debut as a director.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG192&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 192&lt;/ref&gt; The script was about a jazz disc jockey named Dave (Eastwood) who has a casual affair with Evelyn ([[Jessica Walter]]), a listener who had been calling the radio station repeatedly at night asking him to play her favorite song&amp;mdash;[[Erroll Garner]]'s &quot;[[Misty (song)|Misty]]&quot;. When Dave ends their relationship the fan becomes violent and murderous.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG193&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt; Filming commenced in [[Monterey]] in September&amp;nbsp;1970 and included footage of that year's [[Monterey Jazz Festival]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG194&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 194&lt;/ref&gt; The film was highly acclaimed with critics such as [[Jay Cocks]] in ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', [[Andrew Sarris]] in the ''[[Village Voice]]'', and Archer Winsten in the ''[[New York Post]]'' all praising the film, as well as Eastwood's directorial skills and performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG195&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; Walter was nominated for a Golden Globe Best Actress Award (Drama) for her performance in the film.

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=left|quote=&quot;I know what you're thinking&amp;nbsp;— 'Did he fire six shots or only five?' Well, to tell you the truth, in all this excitement, I've kinda lost track myself. But, being as this is a .44 Magnum, the most powerful handgun in the world and would blow your head clean off, you've got to ask yourself one question: 'Do I feel lucky?' Well, do ya, punk?&quot;|source=—Eastwood, in ''[[Dirty Harry]]''}}

The script for ''[[Dirty Harry]]'' (1971) was written by [[Harry Julian Fink]] and Rita M. Fink. It is a story about a hard-edged New York City (later changed to San Francisco) police inspector named [[Harry Callahan (character)|Harry Callahan]] who is determined to stop a psychotic killer by any means.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG205&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 205&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dirty Harry'' is arguably Eastwood's most memorable character and has been credited with inventing the &quot;loose-cannon cop genre&quot;, which is still imitated to this day.&lt;ref&gt;Mathijs and Mendik, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cardullo, p. 51&lt;/ref&gt; Author Eric Lichtenfeld argues that Eastwood's role as Dirty Harry established the &quot;first true archetype&quot; of the action film genre.&lt;ref&gt;Lichtenfeld, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; His lines (quoted at left) have been cited as among the most memorable in cinematic history and are regarded by firearms historians, such as Garry James and Richard Venola, as the force which catapulted the ownership of [[.44 Magnum]] pistols to unprecedented heights in the United States; specifically the [[Smith &amp; Wesson Model 29]] carried by Harry Callahan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Communications2003&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Communications|first=Emmis|title=Orange Coast Magazine|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=TAQEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA23|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011|date=March&amp;nbsp;2003|publisher=Emmis Communications|page=23|id={{ISSN|02790483}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sweeney, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dirty Harry'' proved a phenomenal success after its release in December&amp;nbsp;1971, earning some $22&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|22000000|1971|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) in the United States and Canada alone.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 272&lt;/ref&gt; It was Siegel's highest-grossing film and the start of a series of films featuring the character of Harry Callahan. Although a number of critics praised his performance as Dirty Harry, such as [[Jay Cocks]] of ''Time'' magazine who described him as &quot;giving his best performance so far, tense, tough, full of implicit identification with his character&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;McG210&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; the film was widely criticized and accused of [[fascism]].&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 273&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 281&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Baker, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt;

Following [[Sean Connery]]'s announcement that he would not play [[James Bond]] again Eastwood was offered the role but turned it down because he believed the character should be played by an English actor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Boucher|first=Geoff|title=Clint Eastwood as Superman or James Bond? 'It could have happened,' he says|work=[[Los Angeles Times]] Hero Complex|date=September&amp;nbsp;7, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uuAyMleF|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010|url=http://herocomplex.latimes.com/2010/09/07/clint-eastwood-as-superman-or-james-bond-it-could-have-happened-he-says/}}&lt;/ref&gt; He next starred in the loner Western ''[[Joe Kidd]]'' (1972), based on a character inspired by [[Reies Lopez Tijerina]] who stormed a courthouse in [[Tierra Amarilla]], [[New Mexico]], in June&amp;nbsp;1967. Filming began in [[Old Tucson]] in November&amp;nbsp;1971 under director [[John Sturges]]. During the filming, Eastwood suffered symptoms of a bronchial infection and several panic attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG219&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; ''Joe Kidd'' received a mixed reception, with [[Roger Greenspun]] of ''The New York Times'' writing that the film was unremarkable, with foolish symbolism and sloppy editing, although he praised Eastwood's performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;GreenNYT&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Greenspun|first=Roger|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=950DE6D71F31E73BBC4851DFB1668389669EDE|title=Joe Kidd (1972)|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=July&amp;nbsp;20, 1972|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1973 Eastwood directed his first western, ''[[High Plains Drifter]]'', in which he starred alongside [[Verna Bloom]], [[Marianna Hill]],
[[Billy Curtis]], ''Rawhide'''s [[Paul Brinegar]] and [[Geoffrey Lewis (actor)|Geoffrey Lewis]]. The film had a moral and supernatural theme, later emulated in ''Pale Rider''. The plot follows a mysterious stranger (Eastwood) who arrives in a brooding Western town where the people hire him to defend the town against three felons who are soon to be released. There remains confusion during the film as to whether the stranger is the brother of the deputy, whom the felons lynched and murdered, or his ghost. Holes in the plot were filled with black humor and [[allegory]], influenced by Leone.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG221&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; The revisionist film received a mixed reception from critics, but was a major box office success. A number of critics thought Eastwood's directing was &quot;as derivative as it was expressive&quot;, with [[Arthur Knight (film critic)|Arthur Knight]] of the ''[[Saturday Review (US magazine)|Saturday Review]]'' remarking that Eastwood had &quot;absorbed the approaches of Siegel and Leone and fused them with his own paranoid vision of society&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG223&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 223&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Wayne]], who had declined a role in the film, sent a letter of disapproval to Eastwood some weeks after the film's release saying that &quot;the townspeople did not represent the true spirit of the American pioneer, the spirit that made America great&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 291&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:ClintEastwood1970.jpg|thumb|alt=A man stands next to a girl as they both face to the left, smiling.|left|Eastwood with a fan circa 1970]]
Eastwood next turned his attention towards ''[[Breezy]]'' (1973), a film about love blossoming between a middle-aged man and a teenage girl. During casting for the film Eastwood met [[Sondra Locke]] for the first time, an actress who would play major roles in many of his films for the next ten years and would become an important figure in his life.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG229&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 229&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kay Lenz]] was awarded the part of Breezy because Locke, at 28, was considered too old. The film, shot very quickly and efficiently by Eastwood and [[Frank Stanley (cinematographer)|Frank Stanley]], came in $1&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|1000000|1973|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) under budget and was finished three days ahead of schedule.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG230&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; ''Breezy'' was not a major critical or commercial success; it barely reached the Top&amp;nbsp;50 before disappearing and was only made available on video in 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG231&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 231&lt;/ref&gt;

Once filming of ''Breezy'' had finished, Warner Brothers announced that Eastwood had agreed to reprise his role as Detective Harry Callahan in ''[[Magnum Force]]'' (1973), a sequel to ''Dirty Harry'', about a group of rogue young officers (among them [[David Soul]], [[Robert Urich]] and [[Tim Matheson]]) in the San Francisco Police Force who systematically exterminate the city's worst criminals.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG233&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 233&lt;/ref&gt; Although the film was a major success after release, grossing $58.1&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|58100000|1973|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) in the United States alone and a new record for Eastwood, it was not a critical success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot153&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG236&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; ''The New York Times'' critic [[Nora Sayre]] panned the often contradictory moral themes of the film, while the paper's [[Frank Rich]] called it &quot;the same old stuff&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG236&quot;/&gt;

In 1974 Eastwood teamed up with [[Jeff Bridges]] and [[George Kennedy]] in the buddy action caper ''[[Thunderbolt and Lightfoot]]'', a road movie about a veteran bank robber Thunderbolt (Eastwood) and a young con man drifter, Lightfoot (Bridges). On its release, in spring 1974, the film was praised for its offbeat comedy mixed with high suspense and tragedy but was only a modest success at the box office, earning $32.4&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|32400000|1974|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;McG241&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 241&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood's acting was noted by critics but was overshadowed by Bridges who was nominated for an [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor]]. Eastwood reportedly fumed at the lack of Academy Award recognition for him and swore that he would never work for United Artists again.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG241&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG240&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 240&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood's next film ''[[The Eiger Sanction (film)|The Eiger Sanction]]'' (1975) was based on [[Trevanian]]'s [[The Eiger Sanction|critically acclaimed spy novel]] of the same name. Eastwood plays Jonathan Hemlock in a role originally intended for [[Paul Newman]],  an assassin turned college art professor who decides to return to his former profession for one last sanction in return for a rare [[Pissarro]] painting. In the process he must climb the north face of the [[Eiger]] in [[Switzerland]] under perilous conditions. Once again Eastwood starred alongside George Kennedy. [[Mike Hoover]] taught Eastwood how to climb during several weeks of preparation at [[Yosemite]] in the summer of 1974 before filming commenced in [[Grindelwald]] on August&amp;nbsp;12, 1974.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 314&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McG244&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 244&lt;/ref&gt; Despite prior warnings about the perils of the Eiger the film crew suffered a number of accidents, including one fatality.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 315&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zmijewsky, p. 176&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of the danger Eastwood insisted on doing all his own climbing and stunts. Upon its release in May&amp;nbsp;1975 ''The Eiger Sanction'' was a commercial failure, receiving only $23.8&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|23800000|1975|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) at the box office, and was panned by most critics.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG253&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; Joy Gould Boyum of the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' dismissed the film as &quot;brutal fantasy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG253&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 316&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood blamed [[Universal Studios]] for the film's poor promotion and turned his back on them to make an agreement with [[Warner Brothers]], through [[Frank Wells]], that has lasted to the present day.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG256&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 256&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Outlaw Josey Wales]]'' (1976), a western inspired by [[Asa Carter]]'s eponymous 1972&amp;nbsp;novel,&lt;ref name=&quot;McG257&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 257&lt;/ref&gt; has lead character Josey Wales (Eastwood) as a pro-Confederate guerilla who refuses to surrender his arms after the [[American Civil War]] and is chased across the old southwest by a group of enforcers. Eastwood cast his young son [[Kyle Eastwood]], [[Chief Dan George]], and Sondra Locke for the first time, against the wishes of director [[Philip Kaufman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG261&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 261&lt;/ref&gt; Kaufman was notoriously fired by producer Bob Daley under Eastwood's command, resulting in a fine reported to be around $60,000 (US${{Formatnum:{{Inflation|US|60000|1976}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) from the [[Directors Guild of America]]&amp;mdash;who subsequently passed new legislation reserving the right to impose a major fine on a producer for discharging a director and taking his place.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG264&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 264&lt;/ref&gt; The film was pre-screened at the [[Sun Valley, Idaho|Sun Valley]] Center for the Arts and Humanities in [[Idaho]] during a six-day conference entitled ''Western Movies: Myths and Images''. Invited to the screening were: some 200 esteemed film critics, including [[Jay Cocks]] and [[Arthur Knight (film critic)|Arthur Knight]]; directors such as [[King Vidor]], [[William Wyler]], and [[Howard Hawks]]; along with a number of academics.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG266&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; Upon release in August&amp;nbsp;1976 ''The Outlaw Josey Wales'' was widely acclaimed, with many critics and viewers seeing Eastwood's role as an iconic one that related to America's ancestral past and the destiny of the nation after the American Civil War.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG266&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; [[Roger Ebert]] compared the nature and vulnerability of Eastwood's portrayal of Josey Wales with his Man with No Name character in the ''Dollars'' westerns and praised the film's atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19760101/REVIEWS/601010306/1023|last=Ebert|first=Roger|authorlink=Roger Ebert|title=The Outlaw Josey Wales|work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]]|date=January&amp;nbsp;1, 1976|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vy3Pz9eG|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film would later appear in ''Time''{{'}}s &quot;Top 10 Films of the Year&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McGilligan267&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 267&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood was then offered the role of [[Benjamin L. Willard]] in [[Francis Coppola]]'s ''[[Apocalypse Now]]'', but declined as he did not want to spend weeks on location in the [[Philippines]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McG268&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 268&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kitses, p. 305&lt;/ref&gt; He also refused the part of a platoon leader in [[Ted Post]]'s [[Vietnam War]] film ''[[Go Tell the Spartans]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;McG268&quot;/&gt; and instead decided to make a third ''Dirty Harry'' film ''[[The Enforcer (1976 film)|The Enforcer]]''. The film had Harry partnered with a new female officer ([[Tyne Daly]]) to face a San Francisco Bay area group resembling the [[Symbionese Liberation Army]]. The film, culminating in a shootout on [[Alcatraz]] island, was considerably shorter than the previous ''Dirty Harry'' films at 95&amp;nbsp;minutes,&lt;ref name=&quot;McG273&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 273&lt;/ref&gt; but was a major commercial success grossing $100&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|100000000|1976|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) worldwide to become Eastwood's highest-grossing film to date.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG278&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 278&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1977 he directed and starred in ''[[The Gauntlet (film)|The Gauntlet]]'' opposite Locke, [[Pat Hingle]], [[William Prince (actor)|William Prince]], [[Bill McKinney]], and [[Mara Corday]]. He portrays a down-and-out cop who falls in love with a prostitute that he is assigned to escort from Las Vegas to Phoenix, to testify against the mob. Although a moderate hit with the viewing public critics had mixed feelings about the film, with many believing it was overly violent. Eastwood's longtime nemesis [[Pauline Kael]] called it &quot;a tale varnished with foul language and garnished with violence&quot;. Roger Ebert, on the other hand, gave it three stars and called it &quot;...classic Clint Eastwood: fast, furious, and funny.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ebert|first=Roger|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19770101/REVIEWS/701010304/1023|title=The Gauntlet|work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]]|date=January&amp;nbsp;1, 1977|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uuCeuD0o|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1978 Eastwood starred in ''[[Every Which Way but Loose (film)|Every Which Way but Loose]]'' alongside Locke, Geoffrey Lewis, [[Ruth Gordon]] and [[John Quade]]. In an uncharacteristic offbeat comedy role, Eastwood played Philo Beddoe, a trucker and brawler who roams the American West searching for a lost love accompanied by his brother and an [[orangutan]] called Clyde. The film proved a surprising success upon its release and became Eastwood's most commercially successful film at the time. Panned by the critics it ranked high amongst the box office successes of his career and was the second-highest grossing film of 1978.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG302&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 302&lt;/ref&gt; 

Eastwood starred in the atmospheric thriller ''[[Escape from Alcatraz (film)|Escape from Alcatraz]]'' in 1979, the last of his films to be directed by Don Siegel. It was based on the true story of [[Frank Morris (prisoner)|Frank Lee Morris]] who, along with [[John Anglin|John]] and [[Clarence Anglin]], escaped from the notorious [[Alcatraz]] prison in 1962. The film was a major success and marked the beginning of a period of praise for Eastwood from the critics; [[Stanley Kauffmann]] of ''[[The New Republic]]'' lauding it as &quot;crystalline cinema&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 307&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Frank Rich]] of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' describing it as &quot;cool, cinematic grace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Zmijewsky, p. 213&lt;/ref&gt;

===1980s===
{{Main|Clint Eastwood in the 1980s}}
Eastwood directed the 1980 comedy ''[[Bronco Billy]]'' as well as playing the lead role in alongside Locke, [[Scatman Crothers]], and [[Sam Bottoms]].&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 317&lt;/ref&gt; His children, [[Kyle Eastwood|Kyle]] and [[Alison Eastwood|Alison]], also had small roles as orphans.&lt;ref&gt;Munn, p. 174&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood has cited ''Bronco Billy'' as being one of the most affable shoots of his career and biographer Richard Schickel has argued that the character of Bronco Billy is Eastwood's most self-referential work.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 362&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 365&lt;/ref&gt; The film was a commercial failure&lt;ref name=&quot;Maslin 1280&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Maslin|first= Janet|title=Any Which Way You Can (1980): Screen: Clint and Clyde|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9E03E7DB1339F934A25751C1A966948260|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=December&amp;nbsp;17, 1980|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vckh1zY1|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; but was appreciated by critics. [[Janet Maslin]] of ''The New York Times'' believed the film was &quot;the best and funniest Clint Eastwood movie in quite a while&quot;, praising Eastwood's directing and the way he intricately juxtaposes the old West and the new.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Maslin|first= Janet|title=Bronco Billy (1980): Eastwood Stars and Directs 'Bronco Billy'|work=[[The New York Times]]|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9C01E5D61638F932A25755C0A966948260|date=June&amp;nbsp;11, 1980|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vckcsP1W|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later in 1980 Eastwood starred in ''[[Any Which Way You Can]]'', the sequel to ''Every Which Way but Loose''. The film received a number of bad reviews from critics, although Maslin described it as &quot;funnier and even better than its predecessor&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maslin 1280&quot;/&gt; The film became another box office success and was among the top five highest-grossing films of the year.

[[File:Eastwood1981.jpg|thumb|right|Eastwood in 1981]]
In 1982 Eastwood directed and starred alongside his son Kyle in ''[[Honkytonk Man]]'', based on the eponymous [[Clancy Carlile]]'s [[Great Depression|depression-era]] novel. Eastwood portrays a struggling western singer Red Stovall who suffers from [[tuberculosis]], but has finally been given an opportunity to make it big at the [[Grand Ole Opry]].  He is accompanied by his young nephew (Kyle) to [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]], [[Tennessee]] where he is supposed to record a song. Only ''Time'' gave the film a good review in the United States, with most reviewers criticizing its blend of muted humor and tragedy.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 383&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless the film received critical acclaim in France, where it was compared to [[John Ford]]'s ''[[The Grapes of Wrath (film)|The Grapes of Wrath]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 384&lt;/ref&gt; and it has since acquired the very high rating of 93% on ''Rotten Tomatoes''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/honkytonk_man/|title=Honkytonk Man (1982)|publisher=Rotten Tomatoes|accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that same year Eastwood directed, produced, and starred in the [[Cold War]]-themed ''[[Firefox (film)|Firefox]]'' alongside [[Freddie Jones]], [[David Huffman]], [[Warren Clarke]] and [[Ronald Lacey]]. Based on a 1977 [[Firefox (novel)|novel with the same name]] written by [[Craig Thomas (author)|Craig Thomas]], the film was shot before ''Honkeytonk Man'' but was released after it. Russian filming locations were not possible due to the [[Cold War]], and the film had to be shot in [[Vienna]] and other locations in [[Austria]] to simulate many of the Eurasian story locations. With a production cost of $20&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|20000000|1982|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) it was Eastwood's highest budget film to date.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schickel378&quot;&gt;Schickel, p. 378&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[People (magazine)|People]]'' magazine likened Eastwood's performance to &quot;[[Luke Skywalker]] trapped in Dirty Harry's Soul&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schickel378&quot;/&gt;

''[[Sudden Impact]]'', the fourth ''Dirty Harry'' film, was shot in the spring and summer of 1983 and is widely considered to be the darkest and most violent of the series.&lt;ref&gt;Zmijewsky and Pfeiffer, p. 232&lt;/ref&gt; By this time Eastwood received 60% of all profits from films he starred in and directed, with the rest going to the studio.&lt;ref&gt;Munn, p. 194&lt;/ref&gt; ''Sudden Impact'' was the last film which he starred in with Locke. She plays a woman raped, along with her sister, by a ruthless gang at a fairground and seeks revenge for her sister's now vegetative state by systematically murdering her rapists. The line &quot;[[Go ahead, make my day]]&quot;, uttered by Eastwood during an early scene in a coffee shop, is often cited as one of cinema's immortal ones; famously quoted by [[President of the United States|President]] [[Ronald Reagan]] in a speech to Congress and used during the [[United States presidential election, 1984|1984 presidential elections]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afi.com/Docs/100Years/quotes100.pdf|title=Frankly, My Dear, I Don't Give A Damn|publisher=[[AFI's 100 Years... 100 Movie Quotes]], [[American Film Institute]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x1HnwHWc|archivedate=March&amp;nbsp;7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rogin, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; The film was the highest-earning of all the ''Dirty Harry'' films earning $70&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|70000000|1983|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}). It received rave reviews with many critics praising the feminist aspects of the film, through its explorations of the physical and psychological consequences of rape.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 352&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Tightrope (film)|Tightrope]]'' (1984) had Eastwood starring opposite his daughter Alison, [[Geneviève Bujold]], and [[Jamie Rose]] in a provocative thriller, inspired by newspaper articles about an elusive Bay Area rapist. Set in [[New Orleans]], to avoid confusion with the ''Dirty Harry'' films,&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 389&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood played a single-parent cop drawn into his target's tortured psychology and fascination for [[sadomasochism]].&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 361&lt;/ref&gt; He next starred in the period comedy ''[[City Heat]]'' (1984) alongside [[Burt Reynolds]], a film about a private eye and his partner who get mixed up with gangsters in the [[prohibition]] era of the 1930s. It grossed around $50&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|50000000|1984|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) domestically, but was overshadowed by [[Eddie Murphy]]'s ''[[Beverly Hills Cop]]'' and failed to meet expectations.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 400&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=left|quote=&quot;Westerns. A period gone by, the pioneer, the loner operating by himself, without benefit of society. It usually has something to do with some sort of vengeance; he takes care of the vengeance himself, doesn't call the police. Like Robin Hood. It's the last masculine frontier. Romantic myth. I guess, though it's hard to think about anything romantic today. In a Western you can think, Jesus, there was a time when man was alone, on horseback, out there where man hasn't spoiled the land yet.&quot;|source=—Eastwood, on the philosophical allure of portraying western loners&lt;ref&gt;Munn, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Eastwood made his only foray into TV direction with the 1985 ''[[Amazing Stories]]'' episode &quot;Vanessa In The Garden&quot;, which starred [[Harvey Keitel]] and Sondra Locke. This was his first collaboration with [[Steven Spielberg]], who later co-produced ''[[Flags of Our Fathers (film)|Flags of Our Fathers]]'' and ''[[Letters from Iwo Jima]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Halbfinger|first=David M.|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/21/movies/21flag.html?ref=movies|title=The Power of an Image Drives Film by Eastwood|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=September&amp;nbsp;21, 2006|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uuiqkSBy|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood revisited the western genre when he directed and starred in ''[[Pale Rider]]'' (1985) opposite [[Michael Moriarty]] and [[Carrie Snodgress]]. The film is based on the classic 1953&amp;nbsp;western ''[[Shane (film)|Shane]]'' and follows a preacher descending from the mists of the Sierras to side with the miners during the [[California Gold Rush]] of 1850.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 371&lt;/ref&gt; The title is a reference to the [[Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse]], as the rider of the pale horse is Death, and shows similarities to Eastwood's 1973&amp;nbsp;western ''High Plains Drifter'' in its themes of morality and justice as well as its exploration of the supernatural.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 375&lt;/ref&gt; ''Pale Rider'' became one of Eastwood's most successful films to date. It was hailed as one of the best films of 1985 and the best western in years with [[Gene Siskel]] of the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' remarking, &quot;This year (1985) will go down in film history as the moment Clint Eastwood finally earned respect as an artist&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 378&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1986 Eastwood co-starred with [[Marsha Mason]] in the military drama ''[[Heartbreak Ridge]]'', about the 1983&amp;nbsp;United States [[invasion of Grenada]]. He portrays an aging [[United States Marine Corps|United States Marine]] [[Gunnery Sergeant]] and [[Korean War]] veteran. The production and filming of ''Heartbreak Ridge'' were marred by internal disagreements, between Eastwood and long-time friend and producer Fritz Manes as well as between Eastwood and the [[United States Department of Defense]] who expressed contempt for the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG398&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 398&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 406&lt;/ref&gt; At the time the film was a commercial rather than a critical success, only becoming viewed more favorably in recent times.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 421&lt;/ref&gt; The film was released in 1,470&amp;nbsp;theaters and grossed $70&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|70000000|1986|r=2}}}}) domestically.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 407&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood starred in ''[[The Dead Pool]]'' (1988), the fifth and final Dirty Harry film in the series. It co-starred [[Liam Neeson]], [[Patricia Clarkson]], and a young [[Jim Carrey]] who plays Johnny Squares, a drug-addled rock star and the first of the victims on a list of celebrities drawn up by horror film director Peter Swan (Neeson) who are deemed most likely to die, the so-called &quot;Dead Pool&quot;. The list is stolen by an obsessed fan, who in mimicking his favorite director, systematically makes his way through the list killing off celebrities, of which Dirty Harry is also included. ''The Dead Pool'' grossed nearly $38&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|38000000|1988|r=2}}}}), relatively low receipts for a ''Dirty Harry'' film and it is generally viewed as the weakest film of the series, although Roger Ebert perceived it to be as good as the original.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Film journal&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Film journal|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hAnsAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=1 May 2011|date=1 July 1988|publisher=Pubsun Corp.|page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert1992&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Ebert|first=Roger|title=Roger Ebert's movie home companion|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lTshz3206kYC|accessdate=1 May 2011|year=1992|publisher=Andrews and McMeel|isbn=9780836262438}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood began working on smaller, more personal projects, and experienced a lull in his career between 1988 and 1992. Always interested in jazz he directed ''[[Bird (film)|Bird]]'' (1988), a biopic starring [[Forest Whitaker]] as jazz musician [[Charlie Parker|Charlie &quot;Bird&quot; Parker]]. Alto saxophonist [[Jackie McLean]] and [[Spike Lee]], son of jazz bassist [[Bill Lee (musician)|Bill Lee]] and a long time critic of Eastwood, criticized the characterization of Charlie Parker remarking that it did not capture his true essence and sense of humor.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG433&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 433&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood received two [[Golden Globes]] for the film, the [[Golden Globe Cecil B. DeMille Award|Cecil B. DeMille Award]] for his lifelong contribution, and the [[Golden Globe Award for Best Director|Best Director award]]. However, ''Bird'' was a commercial disaster earning just $11&amp;nbsp;million, which Eastwood attributed to the declining interest in jazz among black people.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 435&lt;/ref&gt;

Carrey would again appear with Eastwood in the poorly received comedy ''[[Pink Cadillac (film)|Pink Cadillac]]'' (1989) alongside [[Bernadette Peters]]. The film is about a [[bounty hunter]] and a group of white supremacists chasing an innocent woman who tries to outrun everyone in her husband's prized pink [[Cadillac]]. The film was a disaster, both critically and commercially,&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 442&lt;/ref&gt; earning barely more than ''Bird'' and marking the lowest point in Eastwood's career in years.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 437&lt;/ref&gt;

===1990s===
{{main|Clint Eastwood in the 1990s}}
Eastwood directed and starred in ''[[White Hunter Black Heart]]'' (1990), an adaptation of [[Peter Viertel]]'s ''[[roman à clef]]'', about [[John Huston]] and the making of the classic film ''[[The African Queen (film)|The African Queen]]''. Shot on location in [[Zimbabwe]] in the summer of 1989,&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 452&lt;/ref&gt; the film received some critical attention but with only a limited release earned just $8.4&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|8400000|1990|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;McG461&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 461&lt;/ref&gt; Later the same year Eastwood directed and co-starred with [[Charlie Sheen]] in ''[[The Rookie (1990 film)|The Rookie]]'', a [[buddy cop]] action film. Critics found the macho jiving between Eastwood and Sheen unconvincing and passed the film off as &quot;blatant racial Hispanic stereotyping&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 460&lt;/ref&gt; An ongoing lawsuit filed by Stacy McLaughlin resulted in no Eastwood films showing in cinemas in 1991&amp;mdash;the third time in his career.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG467&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 467&lt;/ref&gt; The suit was in response to Eastwood allegedly ramming McLaughlin's car while backing out of his parking space at Malpaso.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 466&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood won the suit and agreed to pay McLaughlin's court fees if she did not appeal.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG467&quot;/&gt;

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=right|quote=&quot;...if possible, he looks even taller, leaner and more mysteriously possessed than he did in Sergio Leone's seminal ''Fistful of Dollars'' a quarter of a century ago. The years haven't softened him. They have given him the presence of some fierce force of nature, which may be why the landscapes of the mythic, late 19th-century West become him, never more so than in his new ''Unforgiven''. ... This is his richest, most satisfying performance since the underrated, politically lunatic ''Heartbreak Ridge''. There's no one like him.&quot;|source=—[[Vincent Canby]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'', on Eastwood's performance in ''Unforgiven''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9E0CE7DB103EF934A3575BC0A964958260|last=Canby|first=Vincent|title=Unforgiven (1992)|work=[[The New York Times]]|format=Registration required|date=August&amp;nbsp;7, 1992|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
In 1992 Eastwood revisited the western genre in the self-directed film ''[[Unforgiven]]'', where he played an aging ex-[[gunfighting|gunfighter]] long past his prime opposite [[Gene Hackman]], [[Morgan Freeman]], [[Richard Harris]], and his then girlfriend [[Frances Fisher]]. Scripts existed for the film as early as 1976 under titles such as ''The Cut-Whore Killings'' and ''The William Munny Killings'' but Eastwood delayed the project, partly because he wanted to wait until he was old enough to play his character and to savor it as the last of his western films.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG467&quot;/&gt; By re-envisioning established genre conventions in a more ambiguous and unromantic light the picture laid the groundwork for later westerns such as ''[[Deadwood (TV series)|Deadwood]]''. ''Unforgiven'' was a major commercial and critical success, with nominations for nine [[Academy Award]]s&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 475&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]] for Eastwood and Best Original Screenplay for David Webb Peoples. It won four, including [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]] and [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] for Eastwood. Jack Methews of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' described it as &quot;the finest classical western to come along since perhaps [[John Ford]]'s 1956 ''[[The Searchers (film)|The Searchers]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG473&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 473&lt;/ref&gt; In June&amp;nbsp;2008 ''Unforgiven'' was acknowledged as the fourth best American film in the western genre, behind ''[[Shane (film)|Shane]]'', ''[[High Noon]]'', and ''The Searchers'', in the [[American Film Institute]]'s &quot;[[AFI's 10 Top 10]]&quot; list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=American Film Institute|title=AFI Crowns Top 10 Films in 10 Classic Genres|publisher=ComingSoon.net|date=June&amp;nbsp17, 2008|url=http://www.comingsoon.net/news/movienews.php?id=46072|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;17, 2011|authorlink=American Film Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Top Western|url=http://www.afi.com/10top10/western.html|publisher=[[American Film Institute]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5w8ldkIqa|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Clint Eastwood Cannes 1993.jpg|thumb|right|Clint Eastwood at the [[1994 Cannes Film Festival]]]]
Eastwood played Frank Horrigan in the [[United States Secret Service|Secret Service]] thriller ''[[In the Line of Fire]]'' (1993) directed by [[Wolfgang Petersen]] and co-starring [[John Malkovich]] and [[Rene Russo]]. Horrigan is a guilt-ridden [[United States Secret Service|Secret Service]] agent, haunted by his failure to react in time to save [[John F. Kennedy]]'s life.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 471&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2011 it is the last time he acted in a film that he did not direct himself. The film was among the top&amp;nbsp;10 box office performers in that year, earning a reported $200&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|200000000|1993|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) in the United States alone.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 480&lt;/ref&gt; Later in 1993 Eastwood directed and co-starred with [[Kevin Costner]] in ''[[A Perfect World]]''. Set in the 1960s,&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 481&lt;/ref&gt;Eastwood plays a Texas Ranger in pursuit of an escaped convict (Costner) who hits the road with a young boy ([[T.J. Lowther]]). Janet Maslin of ''The New York Times'' remarked that the film was the highest point of Eastwood's directing career&lt;ref name=&quot;costner&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Maslin|first= Janet|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1D61738F937A15752C1A965958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2|title=A Perfect World; Where Destiny Is Sad and Scars Never Heal|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=November&amp;nbsp;24, 1993|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uuk657Hg|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it has since been cited as one of his most underrated directorial achievements.&lt;ref name=&quot;wpostreview&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Hinson|first=Hall|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/movies/videos/aperfectworldpg13hinson_a0a8b5.htm|title='A Perfect World' by Hal Hinson|work=[[Washington Post]]|date=November&amp;nbsp;24, 1993|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uukCDFSx|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, pp. 485–6&lt;/ref&gt; 

At the May&amp;nbsp;[[1994 Cannes Film Festival]] Eastwood received France's [[Ordre des Arts et des Lettres]] medal&lt;ref name=&quot;McG491&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 491&lt;/ref&gt; then on March&amp;nbsp;27, 1995, he was awarded the [[Irving G. Thalberg Memorial Award]] at the [[67th Academy Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;Verlhac and Bogdanovich, p.144&lt;/ref&gt; His next appearance was in a cameo role as himself in the 1995 children's film ''[[Casper (film)|Casper]]'' and continued to expand his repertoire by playing opposite [[Meryl Streep]] in the romantic picture ''[[The Bridges of Madison County (film)|The Bridges of Madison County]]'' in the same year. Based on a best-selling novel by [[Robert James Waller]] and set in [[Iowa]],&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 492&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Bridges of Madison County'' relates the story of Robert Kincaid (Eastwood), a photographer working for ''[[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]]'', who has a love affair with middle-aged Italian farm wife Francesca (Streep). The film was a hit at the box office and highly acclaimed by critics, despite unfavorable views of the novel and a subject deemed potentially disastrous for film.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG503&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 503&lt;/ref&gt; Roger Ebert remarked that &quot;Streep and Eastwood weave a spell, and it is based on that particular knowledge of love and self that comes with middle age.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19950602/REVIEWS/506020301/1023|title=The Bridges of Madison County|publisher=''Chicago Sun Times''|date=June&amp;nbsp;2, 1995|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5w8lXwsll|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Bridges of Madison County'' was nominated for a [[Golden Globe]] for Best Picture and won a [[César Award]] in France for Best Foreign Film. Streep was also nominated for an Academy Award and a Golden Globe.

As well as directing the 1997 political thriller ''[[Absolute Power (film)|Absolute Power]]'', Eastwood once again appeared alongside co-star Gene Hackman. Eastwood played the role of a veteran thief who witnesses the Secret Service cover up of a murder. The film received a mixed reception from critics and was generally viewed as one of his weaker efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/absolute_power/|title=Absolute Power (1997)|publisher=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Maitland McDonagh]] of ''[[TV Guide]]'' remarked, &quot;The plot turns are no more ludicrous than those of the average political thriller, but the slow pace makes their preposterousness all the more obvious. Eastwood's acting limitations are also sorely evident, since Luther is the kind of thoughtful thief who has to talk, rather than maintaining the enigmatic fortitude that is Eastwood's forte. Disappointing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://movies.tvguide.com/absolute-power/review/131933|title=Absolute Power review|work=[[TV Guide]]|last=McDonagh|first=Maitland|archiveurl=
http://www.webcitation.org/5vkCHZSAS|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later in 1997 Eastwood directed ''[[Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil (film)|Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil]]'', based on the novel by [[John Berendt]] and starring [[John Cusack]], [[Kevin Spacey]], and [[Jude Law]], a film which received a mixed response from critics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19971121/REVIEWS/711210303/1023|last=Ebert|first= Roger|title=Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil|publisher=Chicago Sun Times|date=November&amp;nbsp;21, 1997|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uukTSo1h|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=left|quote=&quot;The roles that Eastwood has played, and the films that he has directed, cannot be disentangled from the nature of the American culture of the last quarter century, its fantasies and its realities.&quot;|source=—Author Edward Gallafent, commenting on Eastwood's impact on film from the 1970s to 1990s&lt;ref name=&quot;Gallafent10&quot;&gt;Gallafent, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Eastwood directed and starred in ''[[True Crime (1999 film)|True Crime]]'' (1999), which also featured his young daughter Francesca Fisher-Eastwood. He plays Steve Everett, a journalist recovering from [[alcoholism]] given the task of covering the execution of murderer Frank Beechum ([[Isaiah Washington]]). The film received a mixed reception with Janet Maslin of ''The New York Times'' writing, &quot;''True Crime'' is directed by Mr. Eastwood with righteous indignation and increasingly strong momentum. As in ''A Perfect World,'' his direction is galvanized by a sense of second chances and tragic misunderstandings, and by contrasting a larger sense of justice with the peculiar minutiae of crime. Perhaps he goes a shade too far in the latter direction, though.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9807EFD61731F93AA25750C0A96F958260|last=Maslin|first= Janet|title=True Crime|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=March&amp;nbsp;19, 1999|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; If some reviews for ''True Crime'' were positive, commercially it was a box office bomb&amp;mdash;earning less than half its $55&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|55000000|1999|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) budget&amp;mdash;and easily became Eastwood's worst performing film of the 1990s aside from ''White Hunter Black Heart'', which only had limited release.&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 539&lt;/ref&gt;

===2000s===
{{main|Clint Eastwood in the 2000s}}
In 2000 Eastwood directed and starred in ''[[Space Cowboys]]'' alongside [[Tommy Lee Jones]], Donald Sutherland, and [[James Garner]] as one of a group of veteran &quot;ex-test pilots&quot; who are sent into space to repair an old [[Soviet]] satellite. The original music score was composed by Eastwood and [[Lennie Niehaus]]. ''Space Cowboys'' was well-received and holds a 79% rating at Rotten Tomatoes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Space Cowboys (2000)|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/space_cowboys/|publisher=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film received a moderately favorable review from Roger Ebert, &quot;it's too secure within its traditional story structure to make much seem at risk &amp;mdash; but with the structure come the traditional pleasures as well.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ebert|first=Roger|coauthor=[[Roger Ebert]]|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20000804/REVIEWS/8040306/1023|title=Space Cowboys|work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]]|date=August 4, 2000|accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film grossed over $90 million in its United States release, more than Eastwood's two previous films combined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hughes152&quot;&gt;Hughes, p.152&lt;/ref&gt; The following year he played an ex-[[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] agent on the track of a sadistic killer ([[Jeff Daniels]]) in the thriller ''[[Blood Work (film)|Blood Work]]'', loosely based on the 1998 [[Blood Work (novel)|novel of the same name]] by [[Michael Connelly]]. The film was a failure, grossing just $26.2&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|26200000|2002|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) on an estimated budget of $50&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|50000000|2002|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}), and received mixed reviews with a consensus at [[Rotten Tomatoes]] calling it &quot;well-made but marred by lethargic pacing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Blood Work (2002)|publisher=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/blood_work/|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood did, however, win the Future Film Festival Digital Award at the [[Venice Film Festival]]. 

{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=right|quote=&quot;Clint is a true artist in every respect. Despite his years of being at the top of his game and the legendary movies he has made, he always made us feel comfortable and valued on the set, treating us as equals.&quot;|source=—[[Tim Robbins]], on working with Eastwood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian 08&quot;/&gt;}}

Eastwood directed and scored the crime drama ''[[Mystic River (film)|Mystic River]]'' (2003), a film about murder, vigilantism, and sexual abuse, set in [[Boston]]. Starring [[Sean Penn]], [[Kevin Bacon]], and [[Tim Robbins]], ''Mystic River'' was lauded by critics and viewers alike. The film won two Academy Awards, [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]] for Penn and [[Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]] for Robbins, with Eastwood garnering nominations for [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] and [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/lifestyle/news/article.cfm?c_id=6&amp;objectid=3552323|title=Acclaim flows for 'Mystic River' at Oscars|date=March&amp;nbsp;2, 2004|agency=[[Reuters]]|publisher=''[[The New Zealand Herald]]''|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vxrmou7Z|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood was named Best Director of the Year by the [[London Film Critics Circle]] and the [[National Society of Film Critics]]. The film grossed $90&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|90000000|2003|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) domestically on a budget of $30&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|30000000|2003|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=mysticriver.htm|title=Mystic River|work=[[Box Office Mojo]]|accessdate=September&amp;nbsp;4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following year Eastwood found further critical and commercial success when he directed, produced, scored, and starred in the boxing drama ''[[Million Dollar Baby]]'', playing a cantankerous trainer who forms a bond with female boxer ([[Hilary Swank]]) who he is persuaded to train by his lifelong friend ([[Morgan Freeman]]). The film won four Academy Awards: Best Picture, Best Director, Best Actress (Swank), and Best Supporting Actor (Freeman).&lt;ref&gt;Roberts and Skutt, p. 689&lt;/ref&gt; At age 74 Eastwood became the oldest of eighteen directors to have directed two or more Best Picture winners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Directing: Directors with 2 or More Directing Awards|publisher=[[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]]|url=http://awardsdatabase.oscars.org/ampas_awards/help/helpMain.jsp?helpContentURL=statistics/indexStats.html|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=D'Angelo|first=Jennifer|title='Million Dollar Baby' Wins Best Picture Oscar|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,148881,00.html|publisher=[[Fox News Channel|FOX News]]|date=February&amp;nbsp;28, 2005|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5veO4O7bn|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also received a nomination for Best Actor and a [[Grammy]] nomination for his score.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot313&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 313&lt;/ref&gt; [[A. O. Scott]] of ''The New York Times'' lauded the film as a &quot;masterpiece&quot; and the best film of the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Scott|first=A. O.|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/2004/12/15/movies/15baby.html|title=3 People Seduced by the Bloody Allure of the Ring|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=December&amp;nbsp;14, 2004|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5w8lLMJ4g|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 Eastwood directed two films about World War II's [[Battle of Iwo Jima]]. The first, ''[[Flags of Our Fathers (film)|Flags of Our Fathers]]'', focused on the men who raised the American flag on top of [[Mount Suribachi]] and was followed by ''[[Letters from Iwo Jima]]'', which dealt with the tactics of the Japanese soldiers on the island and the letters they wrote home to family members. ''Letters from Iwo Jima'' was the first American film to depict a war issue completely from the view of an American enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot320&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 320&lt;/ref&gt; Both films received praise from critics and garnered several nominations at the [[79th Academy Awards]], including [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]],  [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]], and [[Academy Award for Best Original Screenplay|Best Original Screenplay]] for ''Letters from Iwo Jima''. At the [[64th Golden Globe Awards]] Eastwood received nominations for [[Golden Globe Award for Best Director|Best Director]] in both films. ''Letters from Iwo Jima'' won the award for [[Golden Globe Award for Best Foreign Language Film|Best Foreign Language Film]].
[[File:ClintEastwoodCannesMay08.jpg|thumb|left|alt=An older man is at the center of the image smiling and looking off to the right of the image. He is wearing a white jacket, and a tan shirt and tie. The number 61 can be seen behind him on a background wall.|Eastwood in 2008]]
Eastwood next directed ''[[Changeling (film)|Changeling]]'' (2008), based on a true story set in the late 1920s. [[Angelina Jolie]] stars as a woman who is reunited with her missing son only to realize that he is an impostor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot327&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 327&lt;/ref&gt; After its release at several film festivals the film grossed over $110&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|110000000|2008|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}), the majority of which came from foreign markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Pamela |last=McClintock|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118001053|title=Clint mints overseas box office|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=March&amp;nbsp;10, 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uulP7r2V|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was highly acclaimed, with Damon Wise of ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' describing ''Changeling'' as &quot;flawless&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.empireonline.com/features/cannes2008/Post.asp?id=145|title=Clint Eastwood's Changeling Is The Best Of The Festival So Far|first=Damon|last=Wise|work=[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]|date=May&amp;nbsp;20, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vixRGLeV|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Todd McCarthy of ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' described it as &quot;emotionally powerful and stylistically sure-handed&quot; and stated that ''Changeling'' was a more complex and wide-ranging work than Eastwood's ''Mystic River'', saying the characters and social commentary were brought into the story with an &quot;almost breathtaking deliberation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/index.asp?layout=festivals&amp;jump=review&amp;id=2531&amp;reviewid=VE1117937210|title='Changeling' review|first=Todd|last=McCarthy|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=May&amp;nbsp;20, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vixO021b|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Film critic Prairie Miller said that, in its portrayal of female courage, the film was &quot;about as feminist as Hollywood can get&quot; whilst [[David Denby (film critic)|David Denby]] argued that, like Eastwood's ''Million Dollar Baby'', the film was &quot;less an expression of feminist awareness than a case of awed respect for a woman who was strong and enduring.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2010/03/08/100308fa_fact_denby?currentPage=all#ixzz0hnyNNTgl|title=Out of the West|first=David|last=Denby|work=[[The New Yorker]]|date=March&amp;nbsp;8, 2010|archiveurl=
http://www.webcitation.org/5vixWshcE|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood received nominations for [[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score|Best Original Score]] at the [[66th Golden Globe Awards]], [[BAFTA Award for Best Direction|Best Direction]] at the [[62nd British Academy Film Awards]] and director of the year from the London Film Critics' Circle.

After four years away from acting Eastwood ended his &quot;self-imposed acting hiatus&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Turan|first= Kenneth|url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/reviews/la-et-torino12-2008dec12,0,2314630.story|title=Review: 'Gran Torino'|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=December&amp;nbsp;12, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uulSk9Xj|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; with ''[[Gran Torino]]'', which he also directed, produced, and partly scored with his son Kyle and [[Jamie Cullum]]. Biographer Marc Eliot called Eastwood's role &quot;an amalgam of the Man with No Name, Dirty Harry, and William Munny, here aged and cynical but willing and able to fight on whenever the need arose.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot329&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 329&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood has said that the role will most likely be the last time he acts in a film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jamieson|first= Alistair|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/celebritynews/3507352/Clint-Eastwood-to-retire-from-acting.html|title=Clint Eastwood to retire from acting|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=November&amp;nbsp;23, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uulXVx6S|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; It grossed close to $30&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|30000000|2008|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) during its wide release opening weekend in January&amp;nbsp;2009, the highest of his career as an actor or director.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=[[Reuters]]|title=Clint Eastwood leads box office with 'Gran Torino'|url=http://www.forbes.com/feeds/afx/2009/01/11/afx5905250.html|date=January&amp;nbsp;11, 2009|work=[[Forbes]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5veOXhNju|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gran Torino'' eventually grossed over $268&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|268000000|2008|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}})  in theaters worldwide becoming the highest-grossing film of Eastwood's career so far, without adjustment for [[inflation]]. 

His 30th directorial outing came with ''[[Invictus (film)|Invictus]]'', a film based on the story of the [[South Africa]]n team at the [[1995 Rugby World Cup]], with [[Morgan Freeman]] as [[Nelson Mandela]] and [[Matt Damon]] as rugby team captain [[François Pienaar]]. Freeman had bought the film rights to John Carlin's book on which the film is based.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Keller|first=Bill|title=Entering the Scrum|date=August&amp;nbsp;15, 2008|work=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/17/books/review/Keller-t.html|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x9EZJdD0|archivedate=March&amp;nbsp;12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film met with generally positive reviews; Roger Ebert gave it three and a half stars and described it as a &quot;very good film... with moments evoking great emotion&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Invictus|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20091209/REVIEWS/912099994|work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]]|last=Ebert|first=Roger|authorlink=Roger Ebert|date=December&amp;nbsp;9, 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x9EHZO6u|archivedate=March&amp;nbsp;12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ''Variety''{{'}}s Todd McCarthy wrote, &quot;Inspirational on the face of it, Clint Eastwood's film has a predictable trajectory, but every scene brims with surprising details that accumulate into a rich fabric of history, cultural impressions and emotion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Invictus|url=http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117941681.html?categoryid=31&amp;cs=1|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|last=McCarthy|first=Todd|date=November&amp;nbsp;27, 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x9EMigMz|archivedate=March&amp;nbsp;12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood was nominated for [[Golden Globe Award for Best Director|Best Director]] at the [[67th Golden Globe Awards]].

===2010s===
{{quote box|width=30em|bgcolor=#c6dbf7|align=right|quote=&quot;Everybody wonders why I continue working at this stage. I keep working because there's always new stories. ... And as long as people want me to tell them, I'll be there doing them.&quot;|source=—Eastwood, reflecting on his later career&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|title=The Eastwood Factor (Extended Edition)|medium=DVD|publisher=[[Warner Home Video]]|time=1:26:15|date=June&amp;nbsp;1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
In 2010, Eastwood directed the drama ''[[Hereafter (film)|Hereafter]]'', again working with Damon, who portrayed a psychic. The film had its world premiere on September&amp;nbsp;12, 2010 at the [[2010 Toronto International Film Festival]] and was given a limited release on October&amp;nbsp;15, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Punter|first=Jennie|title=Eastwood, Boyle among new Toronto entries|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118023009.html?categoryId=13&amp;cs=1|date=August&amp;nbsp;17, 2010|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|publisher=[[Reed Business Information]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vePTu6Dn|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Mercer|first=Benjamin|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/culture/archive/2010/10/eastwoods-hereafter-matt-damon-shines-despite-schmaltz/64236/|title=Eastwood's 'Hereafter': Matt Damon Shines, Despite Schmaltz|work=[[The Atlantic]]|date=October&amp;nbsp;11, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vePm3J0V|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Hereafter'' received mixed reviews from critics, with the consensus at [[Rotten Tomatoes]] being, &quot;Despite a thought-provoking premise and Clint Eastwood's typical flair as director, ''Hereafter'' fails to generate much compelling drama, straddling the line between poignant sentimentality and hokey tedium.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/hereafter/|title=Hereafter Movie Reviews, Pictures – Rotten Tomatoes|work=[[Rotten Tomatoes]]|accessdate=October&amp;nbsp;30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, Eastwood served as executive producer for a [[Turner Classic Movies]] (TCM) documentary about jazz pianist [[Dave Brubeck]], ''[[Dave Brubeck: In His Own Sweet Way]]'', to commemorate Brubeck's 90th birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Mergner|first=Lee|date=November&amp;nbsp;29, 2010|url=http://jazztimes.com/articles/26871-in-dave-brubeck-s-own-sweet-way|title=In Dave Brubeck's Own Sweet Way|work=[[JazzTimes]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vixgEhO4|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood directed the 2011 biopic of [[J. Edgar Hoover]], ''[[J. Edgar]]'', focusing on the former FBI director's scandalous career and controversial private life. It starred [[Leonardo DiCaprio]] as Hoover,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rosenberg|first=Adam|url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1641867/20100618/story.jhtml|title=Leonardo DiCaprio To Star In J. Edgar Hoover Biopic|publisher=[[MTV.com]]|date=June 18, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vvv3yla4|archivedate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Armie Hammer]] as [[Clyde Tolson]], and [[Damon Herriman]] as [[Bruno Hauptmann]]. In January 2011, it was announced that Eastwood is in talks to direct [[Beyoncé Knowles]] in a third remake of the [[List of American films of 1937|1937 film]] ''[[A Star Is Born (1937 film)|A Star Is Born]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Magrath|first=Andrea|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1349280/Beyonce-Clint-Eastwood-team-A-Star-Is-Born-remake.html|title=A Star Is Born... again: Clint Eastwood in talks to direct Beyonce in yet another remake of Hollywood classic|work=[[Daily Mail]]|date=January 21, 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vvubxGeM|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;22, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Production has been delayed due to the pregnancy of Knowles. In October 2011, ''Entertainment Weekly'' indicated that Eastwood was in talks to star in a baseball drama where he would play a veteran baseball scout who travels with his daughter for a final scouting trip. [[Robert Lorenz]], who worked with Eastwood as an assistant director on a few of his films, is in talks to direct the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Breznican|first=Anthony|url=http://insidemovies.ew.com/2011/10/05/clint-eastwood-may-act-again-in-baseball-drama-breaking/|title=Clint Eastwood may act again in baseball drama -- Breaking|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=October 5, 2011|archivedate=October&amp;nbsp;5, 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/62FABoBay}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Directing style===

Beginning with the thriller ''Play Misty for Me'', Eastwood has directed over 30 films in his career; including westerns, action films, and dramas. From the very early days of his career, Eastwood had been frustrated by directors insisting that scenes be re-shot multiple times and perfected, and when he began as a director in 1971, he made a conscious attempt to avoid any aspects of directing he had been indifferent to as an actor. As a result, Eastwood is renowned for his efficient film directing and to reduce filming time and to keep budgets under control. Eastwood usually avoids actors rehearsing and prefers most scenes to be completed on the first take.&lt;ref&gt;Munn, p. 160&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Biskind19697&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, pp. 196–197 (interviewer Peter Biskind)&lt;/ref&gt; In preparation for filming Eastwood rarely uses [[storyboard]]s for developing the layout of a shooting schedule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gentry65&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 65 (interviewer Ric Gentry)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Abb173&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 173 (interviewer Denise Abbott)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pascal235&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 235 (interviewer Pascal Mérigeau)&lt;/ref&gt; He also attempts to reduce script background details on characters to allow the audience to become more involved in the film,&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp678&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, pp. 67–68 (interviewer Ric Gentry)&lt;/ref&gt; considering their imagination a requirement for a film that connects with viewers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp678&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp91&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 91 (interviewer David Thomson)&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood has indicated that he lays out a film's plot to provide the audience with necessary details, but not &quot;so much that it insults their intelligence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp60&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 60 (interviewer Ric Gentry)&lt;/ref&gt;According to ''Life'' magazine, &quot;Eastwood's style is to shoot first and act afterward. He etches his characters virtually without words. He has developed the art of underplaying to the point that anyone around him who so much as flinches looks hammily histrionic.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Inc1971&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Fayard|first=Judy|work=[[Life (magazine)|Life]]|title=Who can stand 32,580 seconds of Clint Eastwood?|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OEAEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA44|accessdate=March&amp;nbsp;8, 2011|date=July&amp;nbsp;23, 1971|publisher=[[Time Inc.]]|page=46|id={{ISSN|00243019}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Interviewers Richard Thompson and Tim Hunter note that Eastwood's films are &quot;superbly paced: unhurried; cool; and [give] a strong sense of real time, regardless of the speed of the narrative&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp45&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 45 (interviewers Richard Thompson and Tim Hunter)&lt;/ref&gt; while Ric Gentry considers Eastwood's pacing to be &quot;unrushed and relaxed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp71&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 71 (interviewer Ric Gentry)&lt;/ref&gt; Many of Eastwood's films rely on low lighting to give his films a [[Film noir|&quot;noir-ish&quot;]] feel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biskind19697&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Milan143&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 143 (interviewer Milan Pavolić)&lt;/ref&gt; Reviewers have pointed out that the majority of his films are based on the male point-of-view, although female characters typically have strong roles as both heroes and villains.&lt;ref name=&quot;Intp45&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cah119&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 119 (interviewer Tim Cahill)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Behar190&quot;&gt;Kapsis and Coblentz, p. 190 (interviewer Henri Béhar)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Munn, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

==Politics==
{{main|Political life of Clint Eastwood}}
{{double image|right|ClintEastwoodReagan.jpg|220|Clint Eastwood DOI 1675.jpg|150|Left: Eastwood with President [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[Lou Gossett, Jr.]] in July 1987&lt;br&gt;Right: Eastwood as a a spokesman for [[Take Pride in America]] in 2005}}
Eastwood registered as a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] to vote for [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] in 1952 and later supported [[Richard Nixon]]'s [[United States presidential election, 1968|1968]] and [[United States presidential election, 1972|1972]]&amp;nbsp;presidential campaigns. However, he later criticized Nixon's handling of the [[Vietnam War]] and his morality during [[Watergate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot115&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;playboy.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playboy.com/articles/clint-eastwood-1974-playboy-interview/index.html|title=Clint Eastwood: 1974 Playboy Interview|work=[[Playboy Magazine]]|date=February&amp;nbsp;1974|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vxsTt7uJ|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He expressed his disapproval of America's wars in [[Korean War|Korea]] (1950&amp;ndash;1953), Vietnam (1964&amp;ndash;1973), and [[Iraq War|Iraq]] (2003&amp;ndash;2011), believing that the United States should not be overly militaristic or play the role of global policeman. He considers himself too individualistic to be either right-wing or left-wing, describing himself as a &quot;political nothing&quot; and a moderate in 1974&lt;ref name=&quot;playboy.com&quot;/&gt; and a [[libertarianism|libertarian]] in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playboy.com/articles/clint-eastwood-1997-playboy%20interview/|title=Clint Eastwood: 1997 Playboy Interview|work=[[Playboy Magazine]]|date=March&amp;nbsp;1997|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5w6fYSuHU|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood has stated that while he does not see himself as conservative, he is not an &quot;ultra-leftist&quot; either.&lt;ref name=&quot;usaweekend&quot;/&gt; At times he has supported [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] in California, including Representative [[Sam Farr]] in 2002 and Governor [[Gray Davis]] in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Cooper|first=Marc|url=http://www.thenation.com/article/left-coast-notes-3|title=Left Coast Notes|work=[[The Nation]]|date=May&amp;nbsp;8, 2003|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vxsipPfq|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A longtime [[libertarian]] on social issues, Eastwood has stated that he is pro-choice on abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.playboy.com/articles/clint-eastwood-1997-playboy%20interview/index.html|title=Clint Eastwood: 1997 Playboy Interview|work=[[Playboy]]|date=March&amp;nbsp;1997|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vxsmHBb6|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has endorsed the notion of allowing gays to marry&lt;ref name=&quot;usaweekend&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=American Icon series&amp;nbsp;– Clint Eastwood|last=McCafferty|first=Dennis|work=[[USA Weekend]]|date=January&amp;nbsp;25, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; and contributed to groups supporting the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] for women.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 380&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:ClintEastwood6.jpg|thumb|left|Eastwood outdoors at a Take Pride in America event.]]
As a politician Eastwood has made successful forays into both local and state government. In April&amp;nbsp;1986 he was elected mayor for one term in his home town of [[Carmel-by-the-Sea, California]] – a small, wealthy town and artist community on the [[Monterey Peninsula]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot227&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt; During his term he tended towards supporting small business interests and advocating environmental protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Economist&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Economist|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=IeftAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;16, 2011|year=1986|publisher=The Economist Newspaper Ltd.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001 Eastwood was appointed to the California State Park and Recreation Commission by Governor Davis,&lt;ref name=&quot;CSPRC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|agency=[[Associated Press]]|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2008-03-20-schwarzeneggar-firings_N.htm|title='Terminator' fires Clint Eastwood, Shriver|work=[[USA Today]]|date=March&amp;nbsp;20, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vcltydlv|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; then reappointed in 2004 by Governor [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CSPRC&quot;/&gt; As the vice chairman of the commission, in 2005 along with chairman [[Bobby Shriver]], he led the movement opposed to a six-lane {{convert|16|mi|km|sing=on}} extension of [[California State Route 241]], a toll road that would cut through [[San Onofre State Beach]]. Eastwood and Shriver supported a 2006&amp;nbsp;lawsuit to block the toll road and urged the [[California Coastal Commission]] to reject the project, which it duly did in February&amp;nbsp;2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;YoungS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Young|first=Samantha|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/state/20080320-1635-schwarzenegger-parks.html|work=[[San Diego Union Tribune]]|title=Schwarzenegger removes his brother-in-law and Clint Eastwood from Calif. parks panel|date=March&amp;nbsp;20, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uumanMoa|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March&amp;nbsp;2008 Eastwood and Shriver's non-reappointment to the commission on the expiry of their terms&lt;ref name=&quot;YoungS&quot;/&gt; prompted the [[Natural Resources Defense Council]] (NDRC) to request a legislative investigation into the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=[[Associated Press]]|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/state/20080322-1416-ca-schwarzenegger-parkscommission.html|work=[[San Diego Union Tribune]]|title=Group wants probe into governor's removal of Eastwood, Shriver|date=March&amp;nbsp;22, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uumlK7Ky|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Governor Schwarzenegger appointed Eastwood to the [[California Film Commission]] in April&amp;nbsp;2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Schwarzenegger to boost Hollywood|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/3631261.stm|publisher=BBC News|date=April&amp;nbsp;16, 2004|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vclQP3k8|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also acted as a spokesman for [[Take Pride in America]], an agency of the [[United States Department of the Interior]] which advocates taking responsibility for natural, cultural, and historic resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inc.2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Go Ahead. Make His Day|work=Boys' Life|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YvwDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA15|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp23, 2011|date=June&amp;nbsp2005|publisher=[[Boy Scouts of America]]|page=15|id={{ISSN|00068608}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[2008 United States Presidential Election]] Eastwood endorsed [[John McCain]], whom he has known since 1973, but nevertheless wished [[Barack Obama]] well upon his subsequent victory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Aguilar|first=Lou|title=Real Men Vote for McCain|work=[[National Review]]|date=July&amp;nbsp;18, 2008|url=http://www.nationalreview.com/articles/225026/real-men-vote-mccain/lou-aguilar#more|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uumBVFUt|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/.../clint-eastwood-on-gran-to_n_149862.html |title=Clint Eastwood On &quot;Gran Torino,&quot; Getting Old And The Spike Lee Feud|publisher=Huffingtonpost.com|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uumHDTD8|archivedate=December 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2010 Eastwood wrote to &lt;!-- The British term uses &quot;the&quot; in the official title--&gt;the British [[Chancellor of the Exchequer]] [[George Osborne]] to protest the decision to close the [[UK Film Council]], warning that the closure could result in fewer foreign production companies choosing to work in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-10911948|title=Clint Eastwood writes plea to save UK Film Council|publisher=BBC News|date=August&amp;nbsp;9, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vxrz1mNV|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
{{main|Personal life of Clint Eastwood}}

===Relationships===
Eastwood has fathered at least seven children by five different women and has been described as a &quot;serial womanizer&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;At80&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian 08&quot;/&gt; According to biographers Eastwood has always had a strong sexual appetite and particularly so during the 1970s. He has had affairs with many women including actresses [[Catherine Deneuve]], [[Peggy Lipton]], [[Jean Seberg]], [[Kay Lenz]], [[Jamie Rose]], [[Inger Stevens]], [[Jo Ann Harris]], [[Jill Banner]], casting director Jane Brolin, script analyst Megan Rose, and swimming champion Anita Lhoest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot211&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; 

Eastwood married Maggie Johnson on December&amp;nbsp;19, 1953, six months after they met on a blind date.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munn19&quot;&gt;Munn, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; While separated from Johnson, Eastwood had an affair with dancer Roxanne Tunis, with whom he had his first child, Kimber (born June&amp;nbsp;17, 1964); he did not publicly acknowledge her until 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot68&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; After a reconciliation, he had two children with Johnson: [[Kyle Eastwood]] (born May&amp;nbsp;19, 1968) and [[Alison Eastwood]] (born May&amp;nbsp;22, 1972). Eastwood filed for divorce in 1979 after a long separation, but the $25&amp;nbsp;million (US${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|25000000|1984|r=2}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} dollars{{inflation-fn|US}}) divorce settlement was not finalized until May&amp;nbsp;1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot176&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot6&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; 

Eastwood entered a relationship with actress [[Sondra Locke]] in 1975, and they lived together for fourteen years despite the fact that she remained married (in name only) to her gay husband, Gordon Anderson.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.annonline.com/interviews/971111/biography.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Locke|first=Sondra|title= The good, the bad, and the very ugly: a Hollywood journey|publisher= Morrow|year= 1997|ISBN=9780688154622|page=45}}&lt;/ref&gt; They co-starred in six films together: ''[[The Outlaw Josey Wales]]'', ''[[The Gauntlet (film)|The Gauntlet]]'', ''[[Every Which Way but Loose (film)|Every Which Way but Loose]]'', ''[[Bronco Billy]]'', ''[[Any Which Way You Can]]'', and ''[[Sudden Impact]]''. Early on in the relationship, Locke had two abortions and a subsequent [[tubal ligation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot193&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AborTub&quot;&gt;{{cite news|agency=[[Associated Press]]|title=Sondra Locke Suing Clint Eastwood|work=[[Sun Journal (Lewiston)|Lewiston Journal]]|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=H70gAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=sWkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4573%2C3414437|date=April&amp;nbsp;28, 1989|accessdate=April&amp;nbsp;29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The couple separated acrimoniously in 1989; Locke filed a [[palimony]] suit against Eastwood after he changed the locks on the home they shared. She sued him a second time, for [[fraud]], regarding an alleged phony directing contract he gave her in settlement of the first lawsuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;FraudSue&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=O'Neill|first=Ann W.|title=Sondra Locke Suing Clint Eastwood|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/16576835.html?dids=16576835:16576835&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Sep+18%2C+1996&amp;author=&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+%28pre-1997+Fulltext%29&amp;desc=Eastwood+Denies+Fraud+in+Film+Deal+for+Former+Lover&amp;pqatl=google|format=Fee required|date=September&amp;nbsp;18, 1996|accessdate=April&amp;nbsp;29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Locke and Eastwood went on to resolve the dispute with a non-public settlement in 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;Settle&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Huffaker|first=Donna|title=Eastwood's Ex Settles With Warner Bros.|work=[[Los Angeles Daily News]]|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-83612488.html|format=Fee required|publisher=[[Highbeam Research]]|date=May&amp;nbsp;25, 1999|accessdate=April&amp;nbsp;29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her memoir ''The Good, the Bad, and the Very Ugly'' includes a harrowing account of their years together.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,290016,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; 

During his cohabitation with Locke, Eastwood had an affair with flight attendant Jacelyn Reeves. According to biographers they met at the premiere of ''Pale Rider'' where they conceived a son, [[Scott Eastwood|Scott Reeves]] (born March&amp;nbsp;21, 1986).&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot226&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; They also had a daughter, Kathryn Reeves (born February&amp;nbsp;2, 1988), although neither of them were publicly acknowledged until years later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot236&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; Kathryn served as [[Miss Golden Globe]] at the [[62nd Golden Globe Awards|2005 ceremony]] where she presented Eastwood with an award for ''Million Dollar Baby''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.goldenglobes.org/miss_golden_globe/&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1990 Eastwood began living with actress [[Frances Fisher]], whom he had met on the set of ''[[Pink Cadillac]]'' (1989).&lt;ref name=&quot;McG434&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 434&lt;/ref&gt; They co-starred in ''[[Unforgiven]]'' and had a daughter, Francesca Fisher-Eastwood (born August&amp;nbsp;7, 1993).&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot289&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 289&lt;/ref&gt; The couple ended their relationship in early 1995,&lt;ref name=&quot;McG501&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 501&lt;/ref&gt; but remain friends and later appeared together in ''True Crime''. 
[[File:Clint and Dina Eastwood.jpg|thumb|right|Eastwood with wife [[Dina Eastwood|Dina]] in 2007]]
Eastwood subsequently began dating [[Dina Eastwood|Dina Ruiz]], an anchorwoman 35 years his junior, whom he had first met when she interviewed him in 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot289&quot;/&gt; They married on March&amp;nbsp;31, 1996, when Eastwood surprised her with a private ceremony at his home on the [[Shadow Creek Golf Course]] in Las Vegas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=[[Reuters]]|title=Clint's wife expecting|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/18702402.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Sep+06%2C+1996&amp;author=&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=Clint%27s+wife+expecting&amp;pqatl=google|format=Fee required|work=[[Toronto Star]]|date=September&amp;nbsp;6, 1996|accessdate=March&amp;nbsp;7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After their wedding, Dina commented &quot;The fact that I am only the second woman he has married really touches me.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot295&quot;&gt;Eliot, p.295&lt;/ref&gt; The couple has one daughter, Morgan Eastwood (born December&amp;nbsp;12, 1996). 

Eastwood has two grandchildren: Clinton (born 1984) and Graylen (born 1994), by Kimber and Kyle respectively.&lt;ref&gt;http://movies.yahoo.com/movie/contributor/1800019744/bio&lt;/ref&gt;

===Leisure===
[[File:Hog Breaths Inn.jpg|thumb|The Hog's Breath Inn in Carmel, once owned by Eastwood]]
Despite appearing to smoke in many of his films, Eastwood is a life-long non-smoker, has been conscious of his health and fitness since he was a teenager, and practices healthy eating and daily [[Transcendental Meditation]].&lt;ref&gt;McGilligan, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Oates, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Corliss|first= Richard|title=The Last Roundup|work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=August&amp;nbsp;10, 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July&amp;nbsp;21, 1970, Eastwood's father died unexpectedly of a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]] at the age of 64. This profoundly altered Eastwood's lifestyle, encouraging him to adopt a vigorous health and exercise regime to ensure his longevity.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG193&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt; He abstained from hard liquor, although he still favored cold beer, and opened an old English-inspired pub called the Hog's Breath Inn in [[Carmel-by-the-Sea, California|Carmel-by-the-Sea]] in 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG204&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood eventually sold the pub and now owns the Mission Ranch Hotel and Restaurant, also located in Carmel-by-the-Sea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Him&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.missionranchcarmel.com/|title=Welcome to Mission Ranch|publisher=Mission Ranch Hotel and Restaurant|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vckpm2bV|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood is a keen golfer and owns the [[Tehàma Golf Club]]. He is also an investor in the world-renowned [[Pebble Beach Golf Links]] and donates his time every year to charitable causes at major tournaments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Him&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://travel.latimes.com/articles/la-trw-pebblebeach14jun14|work=Los Angeles Times|title=California rejects Clint Eastwood's Monterey golf course|first1=Kenneth R.|last1=Weiss|date=June&amp;nbsp;14, 2007|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vckyHPBy|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stroke.org.uk/media_centre/press_releases/clint_eastwood.html|title=Clint Eastwood &quot;Makes Their Day&quot;|publisher=The Stroke Association|date=March&amp;nbsp;18, 2002|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vckuuApv|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood was formerly a licensed pilot and often flew his helicopter to the studios to avoid traffic.&lt;ref&gt;Schickel, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot131&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 131&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
{{main|Discography of Clint Eastwood}}
Eastwood has had a passion for music all his life. He particularly favors jazz and country and western music and is a pianist and composer.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG114&quot;&gt;McGilligan, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt; Jazz has played an important role in Eastwood's life from a young age and, although he never made it as a professional musician, he passed on the influence to his son Kyle Eastwood, a successful jazz bassist and composer. Eastwood developed as a ragtime pianist early on and had originally intended to pursue a career in music by studying for a music theory degree after graduating from high school. In late 1959 he produced the album ''Cowboy Favorites'', released on the Cameo label.&lt;ref name=&quot;McG114&quot;/&gt; 

Eastwood has his own [[Warner Bros. Records]]-distributed imprint Malpaso Records, as part of his deal with Warner Brothers, which has released all of the scores of Eastwood's films from ''The Bridges of Madison County'' onward. Eastwood co-wrote &quot;Why Should I Care&quot; with [[Linda Thompson (singer)|Linda Thompson]] and [[Carole Bayer Sager]], which was recorded by [[Diana Krall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Krall, Eastwood Team For 'crime'|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]|publisher=AllBusiness.com|url=http://www.allbusiness.com/retail-trade/miscellaneous-retail-retail-stores-not/4607056-1.html|date=March&amp;nbsp;11, 1999|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uunYzwbK|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood composed the [[film score]]s of ''Mystic River'', ''[[Grace Is Gone (film)|Grace Is Gone]]'' (2007), ''[[Changeling (2008 film)|Changeling]]'', and ''[[J. Edgar]]'', and the original piano compositions for ''[[In the Line of Fire]]''. He also wrote and performed the song heard over the credits of ''Gran Torino''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Him&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Headlam|first=Bruce|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/14/movies/14head.html?_r=1|title=The Films Are for Him. Got That?|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=December&amp;nbsp;10, 2008|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5veOl9DiK|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The music in ''Grace Is Gone'' received two [[Golden Globe Award|Golden Globe]] nominations by the [[Hollywood Foreign Press Association]] for the [[65th Golden Globe Awards]]. Eastwood was nominated for [[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score|Best Original Score]], while the song &quot;Grace is Gone&quot; with music by Eastwood and lyrics by Carole Bayer Sager was nominated for [[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Song|Best Original Song]].&lt;ref name=65gg&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goldenglobes.org/news/id/81 |title=Hollywood Foreign Press Association 2008 Golden Globe Awards For the Year Ended December&amp;nbsp;31, 2007|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;19, 2011|date=December&amp;nbsp;13, 2007|publisher=goldenglobes.org|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071214020838/http://www.goldenglobes.org/news/id/81|archivedate=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; It won the [[Satellite Award]] for Best Song at the [[Satellite Awards 2007|12th Satellite Awards]]. ''Changeling'' was nominated for Best Score at the 14th Critics' Choice Awards, [[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score|Best Original Score]] at the [[66th Golden Globe Awards]], and Best Music at the 35th Saturn Awards. On September&amp;nbsp;22, 2007, Eastwood was awarded an honorary [[Doctor of Music]] degree from the [[Berklee College of Music]] at the [[Monterey Jazz Festival]], on which he serves as an active board member. Upon receiving the award he gave a speech claiming, &quot;It's one of the great honors I'll cherish in this lifetime.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Clint Eastwood Receives Berklee Degree at Monterey Jazz Festival (news release)|date=September&amp;nbsp;24, 2007|publisher=[[Berklee College of Music]]|url=http://www.berklee.edu/news/2007/09/0924.html|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uuo8sCXG}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and honors==
{{Main|List of awards and nominations received by Clint Eastwood|List of awards and nominations received by Clint Eastwood by film}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable floatright&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 26em;&quot;
|+ Academy Awards
|-
! Year !! Award !! Film !! W/N
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|1992 || [[Academy Award for Best Director|Best Director]] || ''[[Unforgiven]]'' || style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|Won
|-
| [[Academy Award for Best Picture|Best Picture]] || ''Unforgiven'' || style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|Won
|-
| [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]] || ''Unforgiven'' || Nominated
|-
| 1994 || colspan=&quot;2&quot;|[[Irving G. Thalberg Memorial Award]] || style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|Won
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|2003 || Best Director || ''[[Mystic River (film)|Mystic River]]'' || Nominated
|-
| Best Picture || ''Mystic River'' || Nominated
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|2004 || Best Director || ''[[Million Dollar Baby]]'' || style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|Won
|-
| Best Picture || ''Million Dollar Baby'' || style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|Won
|-
| Best Actor || ''Million Dollar Baby'' || Nominated
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|2006 || Best Director || ''[[Letters from Iwo Jima]]'' || Nominated
|-
| Best Picture || ''Letters from Iwo Jima'' || Nominated
|}
Eastwood has been recognized with multiple awards and nominations for his work in film, television, and music.  His widest reception has been in film work, for which he has received Academy Awards, [[Directors Guild of America Award]]s, [[Golden Globe Award]]s, and [[People's Choice Awards]], among others. Eastwood is one of only two people to have been twice nominated for Best Actor and Best Director for the same film (''Unforgiven'' and ''Million Dollar Baby'') the other being [[Warren Beatty]] (''[[Heaven Can Wait (1978 film)|Heaven Can Wait]]'' and ''[[Reds (film)|Reds]]''). Along with Beatty, [[Robert Redford]], [[Richard Attenborough]], [[Kevin Costner]], and [[Mel Gibson]], he is one of the few directors best known as an actor to win an Academy Award for directing. On February 27, 2005, he became one of only three living directors (along with [[Miloš Forman]] and [[Francis Ford Coppola]]) to have directed two Best Picture winners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=French|first=Philip|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2007/feb/25/clinteastwood.oscars|title=Interview: Clint Eastwood, 'I figured I'd retire gradually, just ride off into the sunset ...'|work=[[The Observer]]|publisher=''[[The Guardian]]''|date=February&amp;nbsp;25, 2007|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5w8kkpugi|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;30, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; At age 74, he was also the oldest recipient of the Academy Award for Best Director. Eastwood has directed five actors in Academy Award–winning performances: [[Gene Hackman]] in ''Unforgiven'', [[Tim Robbins]] and [[Sean Penn]] in ''Mystic River'', and [[Morgan Freeman]] and [[Hilary Swank]] in ''Million Dollar Baby''.

[[File:CAHoF Entrance.jpg|thumb|right|Clint Eastwood display in the entrance to the [[California Hall of Fame]]]]
On August&amp;nbsp;22, 1984, Eastwood was honored at a ceremony at Grauman's Chinese theater to record his hand and footprints in cement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliot213&quot;&gt;Eliot, p. 213&lt;/ref&gt; Eastwood received the AFI Life Achievement Award in 1996 and received an honorary degree from AFI in 2009. On December&amp;nbsp;6, 2006, California Governor [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] and First Lady [[Maria Shriver]] inducted Eastwood into the [[California Hall of Fame]] located at [[The California Museum for History, Women, and the Arts]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Matier|first1=Phillip |first2=Andrew |last2=Ross|title=Eastwood to share top billing in Hall of Fame|url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2006-12-06/bay-area/17325327_1_dirty-harry-academy-tests-police-academy|date=December&amp;nbsp;6, 2006|work=[[San Francisco Chronicle]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5veMvotcp|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 2007, Eastwood was presented with the highest civilian distinction in France, [[Légion d'honneur]], at a ceremony in Paris. French President [[Jacques Chirac]] told Eastwood that he embodied &quot;the best of Hollywood&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Eastwood receives French honour|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/6371461.stm|date=February&amp;nbsp;17, 2007|publisher=BBC News|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uuo2v0vq|archivedate=December&amp;nbsp;11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October&amp;nbsp;2009, he was honored by the [[Lumière Award]] (in honor of the [[Auguste and Louis Lumière|Lumière Brothers]], inventors of the [[Cinematograph]]) during the first edition of the [[Lumière Film Festival]] in [[Lyon]], France. This award honors his entire career and his major contribution to the 7th Art. In February&amp;nbsp;2010, Eastwood was recognized by [[President of the United States|President]] [[Barack Obama]] with an arts and humanities award. Obama described Eastwood's films as &quot;essays in individuality, hard truths and the essence of what it means to be American.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Simmons|first=Christine|title=Bob Dylan, Clint Eastwood get White House awards|url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/people/2010-02-25-white-house-awards_N.htm|date=February&amp;nbsp;25, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5voyzN8eE|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;17, 2011|work=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastwood has also been awarded at least three honorary degrees from universities and colleges, including an honorary degree from the [[University of the Pacific (United States)|University of the Pacific]] in 2006, an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters from the [[University of Southern California]] on May&amp;nbsp;27, 2007, and an honorary [[Doctor of Music]] degree from the [[Berklee College of Music]] at the [[Monterey Jazz Festival]] on September&amp;nbsp;22, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bowen|first=Rebecca|title=Berklee awards Clint Eastwood honorary doctorate|date=September&amp;nbsp;13, 2007|work=[[Paste (magazine)|Paste]]|url=http://www.pastemagazine.com/articles/2007/09/berklee-awards-clint-eastwood-honorary-doctorate.html|archivedate=January&amp;nbsp;17, 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vowkQP5o}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=An honorary Trojan|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/1269513241.html?dids=1269513241:1269513241&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=May+12%2C+2007&amp;author=&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;desc=An+honorary+Trojan&amp;pqatl=google|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|format=Fee required|date=May&amp;nbsp;12, 2007|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{Main|Clint Eastwood filmography}}
Eastwood has contributed to over 50&amp;nbsp;films over his career as actor, director, producer, and composer. He has acted in several television series, most notably starring in ''[[Rawhide (TV series)|Rawhide]]''. He started directing in 1971 and made his debut as a producer in 1982 with ''[[Firefox (film)|Firefox]]'', though he had been functioning as uncredited producer on all of his Malpaso Company films since ''[[Hang 'Em High]]'' in 1968. Eastwood also has contributed music to his films, either through performing, writing, or composing. He has mainly starred in western, action, and drama films. According to the box office-revenue tracking website, [[Box Office Mojo]], films featuring Eastwood have grossed a total of more than US$1.68&amp;nbsp;billion domestically, with an average of $37&amp;nbsp;million per film.&lt;ref name=&quot;BOXMOJO&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/people/chart/?id=clinteastwood.htm|title=Clint Eastwood|publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]]|accessdate=January&amp;nbsp;16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book|last=Baker|first=Brian|title=Masculinity in Fiction and Film: Representing Men in Popular Genres, 1945–2000|year=2006|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=9780826486523}}
*{{cite book|last=Baldwin|first=Louis|title=Turning Points: Pivotal Moments in the Careers of 83 Famous Figures|year=1999|publisher=McFarland|isbn=9780786406265}}
*{{cite book|authors=Canby, Vincent; Maslin, Janet; Nichols, Peter|title=The New York Times Guide to the Best 1000 Movies Ever Made|publisher=Times Books|year=1999|isbn=0812930010|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Cardullo|first=Bert|title=Screen Writings: Genres, Classics, and Aesthetics|year=2010|publisher=Anthem Press|isbn=9781843318378}}
*{{cite book|last=Eliot|first=Marc|title=American Rebel: The Life of Clint Eastwood|publisher=[[Harmony Books]]|year=2009|isbn=9780307336880|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Emery|first=Robert J.|title=The Directors: Take 3|publisher=Allworth Press|year=2003|isbn=1581152450}}
*{{cite book|authors=Fischer, Lucy; Landy, Marcia; Smith, Paul|year=2004|title=Stars: The Film Reader: Action Movie Hysteria of Eastwood Bound|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=0415278937|location=London}}
*{{cite book|author=Fitzgerald, Michael G.; Magers, Boyd|title=Ladies of the Western: Interviews With Fifty-One More Actresses from the Silent Era to the Television Westerns of the 1950s and 1960s|publisher=McFarland|year=2002|isbn=0786411406|location=Jefferson, N.C.}}
*{{cite book|last=Frank|first=Alan|title=Clint Eastwood: Screen Greats|publisher=Exeter|year=1982|isbn=0896731359|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Frayling|first=Christopher|title=Clint Eastwood|publisher=Virgin|year=1992|isbn=0863693075|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=Gallafent|first=Edward|title=Clint Eastwood|location=New York|publisher=Continuum|year=1994|isbn=0826406653}}
*{{cite book|last=Hughes|first=Howard|title=Aim for the Heart|publisher=[[I.B. Tauris]]|year=2009|isbn=9781845119027|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnston|first=Robert K.|title=Reframing Theology and Film: New Focus for an Emerging Discipline|year=2007|publisher=Baker Academic|isbn=9780801032400}}
*{{cite book|editor-first=Robert E.; Coblentz, Kathie|editor-last=Kapsis|title=Clint Eastwood: Interviews|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|year=1999|isbn=1578060702|location=Jackson}}
*{{cite book|last=Kitses|first=Jim|title=Horizons West|publisher=British Film Institute|year=2004|isbn=1844570509}}
*{{cite book|last=Lichtenfeld|first=Eric|title=Action Speaks Louder|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|year=2007|location=Middletown, Connecticut|isbn=0819568015}}
*{{cite book|authors=Lloyd, Ann; Robinson, David|title=The Illustrated History of the Cinema|publisher=Macmillan|year=1987|isbn=0029192412|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last1=Mathijs|first1=Ernest|last2=Mendik|first2=Xavier|title=Alternative Europe: Eurotrash and Exploitation Cinema Since 1945|date=July&amp;nbsp;7, 2004|publisher=Wallflower Press|isbn=9781903364932}}
*{{cite book|last=McGilligan|first=Patrick|title=Clint: The Life and Legend|publisher=[[Harper Collins]]|year=1999|isbn=0006383548|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=Mercer|first=Jane|title=Great Lovers of the Movies|publisher=Crescent Books|year=1975|isbn=0517131269|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Munn|first=Michael|title=Clint Eastwood: Hollywood's Loner|publisher=Robson|year=1992|location=London|isbn=9780860517900}}
*{{cite book|author=Oates, Bob|title=Celebrating the Dawn: Maharishi Mahesh Yogi and the TM Technique|publisher=Putnam|year=1976|isbn=0399118152|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=O'Brien|first=Daniel|title=Clint Eastwood: Film-Maker|publisher=B. T. Batsford|year=1996|isbn=071347839X|location=London}}
*{{cite book|author=Ivy Press|title=Heritage Vintage Movie Poster Signature Auction 2005 Catalog #624|date=November&amp;nbsp;1, 2005|publisher=Heritage Capital Corporation|isbn=9781599670041}}
*{{cite book|author=Roberts, James B.; Skutt, Alexander|title=The Boxing Register: International Boxing Hall of Fame Official Record Book|publisher=McBooks Press|year=2006|isbn=1590131215|location=Ithaca, N.Y.}}
*{{cite book|last=Rogin|first=Michael Paul|title=Ronald Reagan, the Movie and Other Episodes in Political Demonology|year=1988|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=9780520064690}}
*{{cite book|last=Schickel|first=Richard|title=Clint Eastwood: A Biography|publisher=Knopf|year=1996|isbn=9780679429746|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Slocum|first=J. David|title=Violence and American Cinema|work=AFI film readers|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2001|isbn=0415928109|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Paul|title=Clint Eastwood: A Cultural Production: Volume 8 of American Culture|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|year=1993|isbn=0816619603|location=Minneapolis}}
*{{cite book|last=Stillman|first=Deanne|title=Getting Back at Dad|year=1981|publisher=Wideview Books|isbn=9780872237254}}
*{{cite book|last=Sweeney|first=Patrick|title=The Gun Digest Book of Smith &amp; Wesson|date=December&amp;nbsp;13, 2004|publisher=Gun Digest Books|isbn=9780873497923}}
*{{cite book|last1=Verlhac|first1=Pierre-Henri|last2=Bogdanovich|first2=Peter|title=Clint Eastwood: A Life in Pictures|date=September&amp;nbsp;1, 2008|publisher=Chronicle Books|isbn=9780811861540}}
*{{cite book|last=Zmijewsky|first=Boris|coauthor=Lee Pfeiffer|title=The Films of Clint Eastwood|publisher=Citadel Press|year=1982|isbn=0806508639|location=Secaucus, New Jersey}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Engel|first=Leonard|title=Clint Eastwood, Actor and Director: New Perspectives|publisher=[[University of Utah Press]]|year=2007|isbn=0874809002|location=Salt Lake City}}
*{{cite book|last=Gabbard|first=Glen O.|title=Psychoanalysis and Film|work=International Journal of Psychoanalysis Key Papers Series|publisher=Karnac Books|year=2001|isbn=1855752751|location=London; New York}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnstone|first=Iain|title=The Man with No Name: The Biography of Clint Eastwood|publisher=Plexus|year=2007|isbn=085965026X|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=Thompson|first=Douglas|title=Clint Eastwood: Billion Dollar Man|publisher=John Blake|year=2005|isbn=9781857825725|location=London}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{IMDb name|142}}
*{{tcmdb name|55386}}
*{{ymovies name|1800019744}}
*[http://www.rottentomatoes.com/celebrity/clint_eastwood/ Clint Eastwood] at [[Rotten Tomatoes]]
*[http://www.charlierose.com/view/interview/82 Charlie Rose show: An hour with Clint Eastwood]

{{good article}}

{{Clint Eastwood}}
{{Navboxes
| title = Awards for Clint Eastwood
| list =
{{AcademyAwardBestDirector 1981-2000}}
{{AcademyAwardBestDirector 2001-2020}}
{{Cecil B. DeMille Award}}
{{Golden Globe Award for Best Director 1966-1990}}
{{Golden Globe Award for Best Director 1991-2015}}
{{Kennedy Center Honorees 2000s}}
{{AFI Life Achievement Award}}
{{Lincoln Center Gala Tribute}}
{{Thalberg Award}}
}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Eastwood, Clint
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES= Eastwood, Clinton
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Actor, director, film producer
|DATE OF BIRTH=May 31, 1930
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[San Francisco]], [[United States]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Eastwood, Clint}}
[[Category:1930 births]]
[[Category:Clint Eastwood| ]]
[[Category:Actors from California]]
[[Category:Akira Kurosawa Award winners]]
[[Category:American actor–politicians]]
[[Category:American aviators]]
[[Category:American composers]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American film directors]]
[[Category:American film producers]]
[[Category:American firefighters]]
[[Category:American libertarians]]
[[Category:American people of Dutch descent]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:American people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:American restaurateurs]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:Best Director Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Best Director Golden Globe winners]]
[[Category:California Republicans]]
[[Category:César Award winners]]
[[Category:Commandeurs of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Eastwood family]]
[[Category:English-language film directors]]
[[Category:Fellini Gold Medalists]]
[[Category:Film directors from California]]
[[Category:Film producers from California]]
[[Category:Kennedy Center honorees]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Mayors of places in California]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Rising Sun]]
[[Category:People from Oakland, California]]
[[Category:People from Piedmont, California]]
[[Category:People from San Francisco, California]]
[[Category:Producers who won the Best Picture Academy Award]]
[[Category:Spaghetti Western actors]]
[[Category:Transcendental Meditation practitioners]]
[[Category:United States Army soldiers]]
[[Category:Western (genre) film actors]]
[[Category:Western (genre) film directors]]
[[Category:United States National Medal of Arts recipients]]
[[Category:Helicopter pilots]]

{{Link GA|sr}}
{{Link FA|fr}}
{{Link FA|pt}}

[[ar:كلينت إيستوود]]
[[an:Clint Eastwood]]
[[az:Klint İstvud]]
[[bn:ক্লিন্ট ইস্টউড]]
[[zh-min-nan:Clint Eastwood]]
[[be:Клінт Іствуд]]
[[be-x-old:Клінт Іствуд]]
[[bg:Клинт Истууд]]
[[bar:Eastwood Clint]]
[[bs:Clint Eastwood]]
[[br:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ca:Clint Eastwood]]
[[cv:Клинт Иствут]]
[[cs:Clint Eastwood]]
[[cy:Clint Eastwood]]
[[da:Clint Eastwood]]
[[de:Clint Eastwood]]
[[et:Clint Eastwood]]
[[el:Κλιντ Ίστγουντ]]
[[es:Clint Eastwood]]
[[eo:Clint Eastwood]]
[[eu:Clint Eastwood]]
[[fa:کلینت ایستوود]]
[[fr:Clint Eastwood]]
[[fy:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ga:Clint Eastwood]]
[[gd:Clint Eastwood]]
[[gl:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ko:클린트 이스트우드]]
[[hy:Քլինթ Իսթվուդ]]
[[hi:क्लिंट ईस्टवुड]]
[[hr:Clint Eastwood]]
[[io:Clint Eastwood]]
[[id:Clint Eastwood]]
[[it:Clint Eastwood]]
[[he:קלינט איסטווד]]
[[sw:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ht:Clint Eastwood]]
[[la:Clint Eastwood]]
[[lv:Klints Īstvuds]]
[[lb:Clint Eastwood]]
[[lt:Clint Eastwood]]
[[hu:Clint Eastwood]]
[[mk:Клинт Иствуд]]
[[ml:ക്ലിന്റ് ഈസ്റ്റ്‌വുഡ്]]
[[mr:क्लिंट ईस्टवूड]]
[[nl:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ja:クリント・イーストウッド]]
[[no:Clint Eastwood]]
[[nn:Clint Eastwood]]
[[pa:ਕਲਿੰਟਨ ਕਲਿੰਟ ਈਸਟਵੁਡ]]
[[nds:Clint Eastwood]]
[[pl:Clint Eastwood]]
[[pt:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ro:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ru:Иствуд, Клинт]]
[[sq:Clint Eastwood]]
[[simple:Clint Eastwood]]
[[sk:Clint Eastwood]]
[[sl:Clint Eastwood]]
[[sr:Клинт Иствуд]]
[[sh:Clint Eastwood]]
[[fi:Clint Eastwood]]
[[sv:Clint Eastwood]]
[[tl:Clint Eastwood]]
[[ta:கிலின்ட் ஈஸ்ட்வுட்]]
[[th:คลินต์ อีสต์วูด]]
[[tr:Clint Eastwood]]
[[uk:Клінт Іствуд]]
[[vi:Clint Eastwood]]
[[zh:克林·伊斯威特]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
