<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4340" ns="0" title="Baltimore Orioles"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the team so named since 1954|others|Baltimore Oriole (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|St. Louis Browns|other teams at some time so named}}
{{ref improve|date=October 2011}}
{{MLB infobox
| name             = Baltimore Orioles
| established      = 1894
| misc             = '''Based in Baltimore since {{by|1954}}'''
| logo             = Orioles new.PNG
| uniformlogo      = BaltimoreOriolescap.PNG
| current league   = American League
| y1               = 1901
| division         = [[American League East|East Division]]
| y2               = 1969
| retirednumbers   = [[Earl Weaver|4]], [[Brooks Robinson|5]], [[Cal Ripken Jr.|8]], [[Frank Robinson|20]], [[Jim Palmer|22]], [[Eddie Murray|33]], [[Jackie Robinson|42]]
| colors           = Black, orange, white
{{color box|#000000}} {{color box|#FB4F14}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
| name             = Baltimore Orioles
| y3               = 1954
| nicknames        = The O's, The Birds
| pastnames        = St. Louis Browns ({{by|1902}}–{{by|1953}})
*Milwaukee Brewers ({{by|1894}}–{{by|1901}})
| ballpark         = [[Oriole Park at Camden Yards]]
| y4               = 1992
| pastparks        = [[Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)|Memorial Stadium]] ({{by|1954}}–{{by|1991}})
*[[Sportsman's Park|Sportsman's Park (III)]] (St. Louis) ({{by|1902}}–{{by|1953}})
**a.k.a. Busch Stadium (I) ({{by|1953}})
*[[Lloyd Street Grounds]] (Milwaukee) ({{by|1895}}–{{by|1901}})
*[[Borchert Field]] (Milwaukee) ({{by|1894}})
| WS               = (3)
| WORLD CHAMPIONS  = [[1983 World Series|1983]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;[[1970 World Series|1970]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;[[1966 World Series|1966]]
| LEAGUE           = AL
| P                = (7)
| PENNANTS         = [[1983 American League Championship Series|1983]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;[[1979 American League Championship Series|1979]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;[[1971 American League Championship Series|1971]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;[[1970 American League Championship Series|1970]]&lt;br&gt;[[1969 American League Championship Series|1969]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1966&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1944
| misc1            =
| OTHER PENNANTS   =
| DIV              = East
| DV               = (8)
| Division Champs  = [[1997 American League Division Series|1997]]&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1983&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1979&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1974 &lt;br&gt; 1973&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1971&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1970&amp;nbsp;•&amp;nbsp;1969
| misc5            =
| OTHER DIV CHAMPS =
| WC               = (1)
| Wild Card        = [[1996 American League Division Series|1996]]
| owner            = [[Peter Angelos]]
| manager          = [[Buck Showalter]]
| gm               = [[Dan Duquette]]
}}
The '''Baltimore Orioles''' are a [[professional baseball|professional baseball team]] based in [[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]] in the [[United States]]. They are a member of the [[American League East|Eastern Division]] of [[Major League Baseball]]'s [[American League]]. One of the American League's eight charter franchises in 1901, it spent its first year as a major league club in [[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, Wisconsin]], as the '''Milwaukee Brewers''' before moving to [[St. Louis]] to become the '''St. Louis Browns'''.[[Category:St. Louis Browns]] After 52 mostly hapless years in St. Louis, the Browns moved to Baltimore in [[1954 Major League Baseball season|1954]] and adopted the Orioles name in honor of the [[Baltimore Oriole|official state bird of Maryland]]. The Orioles name had been used by previous major league baseball clubs in Baltimore, including the [[American League]] Baltimore Orioles franchise from 1901–1902 that became the [[New York Yankees]] and the [[Baltimore Orioles (19th century)|National League Baltimore Orioles]] which won [[National League]] championships under [[Baseball Hall of Fame|Hall-of-Fame]] manager [[John McGraw]], before McGraw took the black and orange team colors to the New York Giants baseball team, which became the [[San Francisco Giants]] after the 1957 season. [[List of baseball nicknames|Nicknames]] for the team include the '''O's''' and the '''Birds.''' The Orioles have been best known for their successful stadium, the trend-setting [[Oriole Park at Camden Yards]], opened in 1992 near the birthplace of Babe Ruth.

The Orioles experienced their greatest success from 1964–1983, winning seven Division Championships (1969–1971, 1973–1974, 1979 and 1983), six pennants (1966, 1969–1971, 1979 and 1983), three World Championships (1966, 1970 and 1983), and four Most Valuable Player awards (3B [[Brooks Robinson]] 1964, OF [[Frank Robinson]] 1966, 1B [[Boog Powell]] 1970 and SS [[Cal Ripken Jr.]] 1983).  The [[1966 World Series|first World Series championship]] [[1966 Baltimore Orioles season|team]] in [[1966 Major League Baseball season|1966]] was led by Hall-of-Famers Frank Robinson (OF), Brooks Robinson (3B), and [[Jim Palmer]] (P).  Frank Robinson won the [[1966 World Series]] [[World Series MVP|MVP award]], as well as the [[Major League Baseball Triple Crown|Triple Crown]] in hitting, in which he led the American League in batting average, home runs, and runs batted in.  The [[1970 World Series|second World Series]] [[1970 Baltimore Orioles season|championship team]] in [[1970 Major League Baseball season|1970]] was led by the previous trio of Hall-of-Famers, Hall-of-Fame manager [[Earl Weaver]], and 1970 AL MVP Boog Powell (1B).  Brooks Robinson won the 1970 World Series MVP award.  The [[1983 World Series|third World Championship]] [[1983 Baltimore Orioles season|team]] was led by Hall-of-Famers [[Cal Ripken, Jr.]] (SS), [[Eddie Murray]] (1B), [[Jim Palmer]] (P) and 1983 World Series MVP [[Rick Dempsey]] (C).  The Orioles' success after 1983 included the following: [[Frank Robinson]] won the American League manager of the year in [[1989 Major League Baseball season|1989]] managing the [[1989 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] to a second-place finish in the AL East Division only two games behind the [[1989 Toronto Blue Jays season|Toronto Blue Jays]]; [[Cal Ripken Jr.]] won the American League Most Valuable Player Award in [[1991 Major League Baseball season|1991]]; Ripken's breaking [[Lou Gehrig]]'s record for consecutive games played in [[1995 Major League Baseball season|1995]]; the Orioles winning their first American League Wild Card playoff appearance in [[1996 Major League Baseball season|1996]] and going wire-to-wire in winning the American League East Division championship in [[1997 Major League Baseball season|1997]], with [[Davey Johnson]] winning the American League Manager of the Year Award. Since the retirement of Cal Ripken Jr. in 2001, the Orioles have continued in a downward spiral, compiling a losing record in every season since 1998.

==History==
{{Main|History of the Baltimore Orioles}}
:''For other uses, see [[Milwaukee Brewers (disambiguation)]]''
[[Image:MilwaukeeBrewers1889.jpg|right|thumb|200px|The 1889 Milwaukee Brewers]]
The modern Orioles franchise can trace its roots back to the original Milwaukee Brewers of the [[minor league|minor]] [[Western League (U.S. baseball)|Western League]], beginning in 1894 when the league reorganized. The Brewers were there when the WL renamed itself the [[American League]] in [[1900 in baseball|1900]].

===Milwaukee Brewers===
At the end of the 1900 season, the American League removed itself from baseball's National Agreement (the formal understanding between the NL and the minor leagues). Two months later, the AL declared itself a competing major league. As a result of several franchise shifts, the Brewers were one of only two Western League teams that didn't fold, move or get kicked out of the league (the other being the [[Detroit Tigers]]). In its first game in the American League, the team lost to the Detroit Tigers 14–13 after blowing a 9-run lead in the 9th inning.[http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1901/04251901.htm] To this day, it is a major league record for the biggest deficit overcome that late in the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://blogs.wsj.com/numbersguy/baseballs-biggest-ninth-inning-comebacks-385/ | work=The Wall Street Journal | title=Baseball's Biggest Ninth-Inning Comebacks | first=Carl | last=Bialik | date=July 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the first American League season in [[1901 in baseball|1901]], they finished last (8th place) with a record of 48–89. During its lone Major League season, the team played at [[Lloyd Street Grounds]], between 16th and 18th Streets in Milwaukee.

===St. Louis Browns===
{{main|History of the St. Louis Browns}}

===Baltimore Orioles===
[[File:Orioles Mascot.jpg|thumb|right]]
As mentioned above, the Miles-Hofberger group renamed their new team the Baltimore Orioles soon after taking control of the franchise. The name has a rich history in Baltimore, having been used by Baltimore baseball teams since the late 19th century.

In the 1890s, a powerful and innovative [[Baltimore Orioles (19th century)|National League Orioles]] squad included several future [[Baseball Hall of Fame|Hall of Famers]], such as [[Willie Keeler|&quot;Wee&quot; Willie Keeler]], [[Wilbert Robinson]], [[Hughie Jennings]], and [[John McGraw (baseball)|John McGraw]]. They won three straight pennants, and participated in all four of the [[Temple Cup]] Championship Series, winning the last two of them. That team had started as a charter member of the [[American Association (19th century)|American Association]] in 1882. Despite its on-field success, it was one of the four teams contracted out of existence by the National League after the 1899 season. Its best players (and its manager, [[Ned Hanlon (baseball)|Ned Hanlon]]) regrouped with the [[Los Angeles Dodgers|Brooklyn Dodgers]], turning that team into a contender.

In 1901, Baltimore and McGraw were awarded an expansion franchise in the growing American League, but again the team was sacrificed in favor of a [[New York City]] franchise, as the team was transferred to New York in 1903. After some early struggles, that team eventually became baseball's most successful franchise&amp;nbsp;— the [[New York Yankees]].

As a member of the high-minor league level [[International League]], the Orioles competed at what is now known as the AAA level from 1903–1953. Baltimore's own [[Babe Ruth]] pitched for the Orioles before being sold to the AL [[Boston Red Sox]] in 1914. The Orioles of the IL won nine league championships, first in 1908, followed by a lengthy run from 1919 to 1925, and then dramatically in 1944, after they had lost their home field [[Oriole Park]] in a disastrous mid-season fire. The huge post-season crowds at their temporary home, [[Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)|Municipal Stadium]], caught the attention of the big league brass and helped open the door to the return of major league baseball to Baltimore. Thanks to the big stadium, that &quot;Junior World Series&quot; easily outdrew the major league World Series which, coincidentally, included the team that would move to Baltimore ten years later and take up occupancy in the rebuilt version of the big stadium.

====Seeds of success (1954–59)====
After starting the [[1954 Major League Baseball season|1954 campaign]] with a two-game split against the [[1954 Detroit Tigers season|Tigers]] in [[Tiger Stadium (Detroit)|Detroit]], the [[1954 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] returned to Baltimore on April 15 to a welcoming parade that wound through the streets of downtown, with an estimated 350,000 spectators lining the route. In its first-ever home opener at [[Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)|Memorial Stadium]] later in the afternoon, they treated a sellout crowd of 46,354 to a 3–1 victory over the [[1954 Chicago White Sox season|Chicago White Sox]]. The remainder of the season would not be as pleasant, with the team enduring 100 losses while avoiding the AL cellar by only three games. With fellow investors both frustrated with his domination of the franchise's business operations and dissatisfied with yet another seventh- place finish, Clarence Miles resigned in early November 1955. Real estate developer [[James Keelty|James Keelty Jr.]] succeeded him as president with investment banker [[Joseph Iglehart]] the new board chairman.

The seeds of long-term success were planted on September 14, 1954, when the Orioles hired [[Paul Richards (baseball)|Paul Richards]] to become the ballclub's manager and general manager. He laid the foundation for what would years later be called the '''''Oriole Way'''''. The instruction of baseball fundamentals became uniform in every detail between all classes within the organization. Players were patiently refined until fundamentally sound instead of being hastily advanced to the next level.

For the remainder of the 1950s, the Orioles crawled up the standings, reaching as high as fifth place with a [[1957 Baltimore Orioles season|76–76]] record in [[1957 Major League Baseball season|1957]]. Richards succeeded in stocking the franchise with a plethora of young talent which included [[Dave Nicholson]], [[Pete Ward]], [[Ron Hansen (baseball)|Ron Hansen]] (1960 AL [[Rookie of the Year (award)|Rookie of the Year]]), [[Milt Pappas]], [[Jerry Adair]], [[Steve Barber]] (20 wins in 1963), [[Boog Powell]], [[Dave McNally]] and [[Brooks Robinson]]. Unfortunately, Richards also had the tendency to recklessly spend money on individuals with dubious baseball skills. This became a major problem as bidding wars between the ballclubs to land the best amateur players escalated signing bonuses.

The solution came on November 5, 1958, when [[Lee MacPhail]] was appointed general manager, allowing Richards to focus on his managerial duties. MacPhail added much needed discipline to the [[scout (sport)|scouting]] staff by establishing cross-checkers who thoroughly evaluated young hopefuls to determine whether they were worthy of being tendered a contract. He also accepted the title of president after Keelty resigned in mid-December, 1959.

====Pennant contenders (1960–65)====
One month prior to the end of the [[1961 Major League Baseball season|1961 season]], Richards resigned as the team's skipper to become the general manager of the expansion [[Houston Astros|Houston Colt 45s]]. A [[1960 Major League Baseball season|year earlier]], he succeeded in establishing the [[1960 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] as a legitimate contender when they stood atop the AL standings as late as early September before finishing in second place at 89–65.

In [[1964 Major League Baseball season|1964]], the [[1964 Baltimore Orioles season|Birds]], piloted by [[Hank Bauer]] in his first year of managing the ballclub, were involved in a tight pennant race against the [[1964 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] and [[1964 Chicago White Sox season|White Sox]]. They ended up in third with a 97–65 record, only two games out. It has been suggested that they would likely have advanced to the [[1964 World Series|Fall Classic]] had it not been for a minor wrist injury that sidelined Powell for two weeks in late August.&lt;ref&gt;Halberstam, David. ''October 1964''. New York: Villard Books, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Robinson enjoyed a breakout season with a league-high 118 RBIs and won the [[Major League Baseball Most Valuable Player Award|AL Most Valuable Player Award]].

[[CBS]]' purchase of a majority stake in the Yankees on September 9 of that same year resulted in a change to the ownership situation in Baltimore. Iglehart, the Orioles' largest shareholder at 32% and owner of a sizable amount of CBS stock, straightened out his conflict of interest issues on May 25, 1965 by selling his 64,000 shares in the ballclub to the [[National Bohemian|National Brewing Company]], an original team investor which finally had controlling interest at 65%. Brewery president [[Jerold Hoffberger]] became the Orioles' new chairman of the board.

With the benefit of a deep talent pool and superior scouts, the franchise continued to make improvements at the major league level. Three months before the start of the [[1963 Major League Baseball season|1963 season]], the [[1963 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] stabilized its infield by acquiring [[Luis Aparicio]] in a transaction that involved sending a trio of homegrown players (Hansen, Nicholson and Ward) to the White Sox. They also scoured the [[minor league baseball|minor leagues]] for selections in the [[Rule 5 draft]] ([[Paul Blair (baseball)|Paul Blair]] from the [[New York Mets|Mets]] in [[1962 Major League Baseball season|1962]], [[Moe Drabowsky]] from the Cardinals in 1965) and claims off [[Major League Baseball transactions|waivers]] ([[Curt Blefary]], 1965 AL Rookie of the Year, from the Yankees in 1963).

====Milt Pappas for Frank Robinson====
On December 9, 1965, the Orioles traded pitcher [[Milt Pappas]] (and several others) to the [[Cincinnati Reds]] in exchange for slugging outfielder [[Frank Robinson]]. The following year, Robinson won the American League Most Valuable Player award, thus becoming the first (and so far only) man to win the MVP in each league (Robinson won the NL MVP in 1961, leading the Reds to the pennant). In addition to winning the 1966 MVP, Robinson also won the [[Triple crown (baseball)|Triple Crown]] (leading the American League in batting average, home runs, and runs batted in), a feat also achieved the following season by [[1962 Boston Red Sox season|Boston's]] [[Carl Yastrzemski]] but never since. The [[1966 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] won their first-ever American League championship in [[1966 Major League Baseball season|1966]], and in a major upset, swept the [[1966 World Series|World Series]] by out-dueling the Los Angeles Dodgers aces [[Sandy Koufax]] and [[Don Drysdale]]. The only home run ball ever hit completely out of Memorial Stadium was slugged by Robinson on Mother's Day in 1966, off [[1966 Cleveland Indians season|Cleveland Indians]] pitcher [[Luis Tiant]]. It cleared the left field single-deck portion of the grandstand. A flag was later erected near the spot the ball cleared the back wall, with simply the word &quot;HERE&quot; upon it. The flag is now in the Baltimore Orioles museum.

Pappas went 30–29 in a little over two years with the Reds before being traded. Although he would go on to have back-to-back 17-win seasons for the [[Chicago Cubs]] in 1971 and 1972, including a [[no-hitter]] in the latter season, this did not help the [[1970 Cincinnati Reds season|Reds]], who ended up losing the [[1970 World Series]] to Robinson and the Orioles. This trade has become renowned as one of the most lopsided in baseball history, including a mention by [[Susan Sarandon]] in her opening soliloquy in the 1988 film ''[[Bull Durham]]'': &quot;Bad trades are a part of baseball. I mean, who can forget Frank Robinson for Milt Pappas?&quot;

====Glory years (1966–1983)====
In the 1960s, the Orioles farm system produced an especially large number of high-quality players and coaches and laid the foundation for two decades of on-field success. This period included eighteen consecutive winning seasons (1968–1985) -- an unprecedented run of success that saw the Orioles become the envy of the league, and the winningest team in baseball.

During this period, the Orioles played baseball the '''''Oriole Way''''', an organizational ethic best described by longtime farm hand and coach [[Cal Ripken, Sr.]]'s phrase ''&quot;'''perfect''' practice makes perfect!&quot;'' The ''Oriole Way'' was a belief that hard work, professionalism, and a strong understanding of fundamentals were the keys to success at the major league level. It was based on the belief that if every coach, at every level, taught the game the same way, the organization could produce &quot;replacement parts&quot; that could be substituted seamlessly into the big league club with little or no adjustment. Elaborations on the Oriole way include pitching coach and manager Ray Miller's maxim &quot;Work fast, change speeds, and throw strikes&quot; and manager Earl Weaver's maxim &quot;Pitching, defense and three-run homers.&quot;

The ''Oriole Way'' began flourishing in 1966 after the Robinson-for-Pappas deal, as Robinson won the Triple Crown Award. His Orioles would easily sweep the [[1966 Los Angeles Dodgers season|Los Angeles Dodgers]] in the [[1966 World Series]]. After a mediocre [[1967 Baltimore Orioles season|1967 season]], [[Hank Bauer]] would be replaced by [[Earl Weaver]] halfway into [[1968 Major League Baseball season|1968]]. The [[1968 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] would finish second in the American League. This would only be a prelude to [[1969 Major League Baseball season|1969]], when the [[1969 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] won 109 games and easily won the newly-created [[American League East]] division title. [[Mike Cuellar]] shared the Cy Young Award with Detroit's [[Denny McLain]]. After sweeping [[1969 Minnesota Twins season|Minnesota]] in the [[1969 American League Championship Series|American League Championship Series]], Baltimore was shocked by losing to the [[1969 New York Mets season|New York Mets]] in a five-game [[1969 World Series|World Series]]. The next year, [[Boog Powell]] won the MVP and the Orioles won another 108 games. After sweeping the [[1970 Minnesota Twins season|Twins]] once again in the [[1970 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], the Orioles won the [[1970 World Series]] by defeating the [[1970 Cincinnati Reds season|Cincinnati Reds]]' [[Big Red Machine]] in five games.

In [[1971 Major League Baseball season|1971]], the [[1971 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] won another division title thanks to four 20-game winners on their pitching staff (Cuellar, [[Jim Palmer]], [[Pat Dobson]], and [[Dave McNally]]). After defeating the young [[1971 Oakland Athletics season|Oakland A's]] in the [[1971 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], the Orioles would lose a heartbreaking seven-game [[1971 World Series|World Series]] to the [[1971 Pittsburgh Pirates season|Pittsburgh Pirates]]. The [[1972 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] would miss the playoffs in [[1972 Major League Baseball season|1972]], but rebounded to win the division in 1973 and 1974. Each time, they would lose to Oakland in the ALCS. During this stretch, the Orioles began to phase out their veteran infield by replacing [[Davey Johnson]] and [[Brooks Robinson]] with younger stars [[Bobby Grich]] and [[Doug DeCinces]], respectively. Johnson would be dealt along with [[Johnny Oates]] to the [[Atlanta Braves]] for catcher and 1971 National League Rookie of the Year [[Earl Williams (1970s catcher)|Earl Williams]]. Although Williams would hit 63 home runs in two seasons with Atlanta, he would only hit 36 homers in two seasons with the Orioles.

In [[1975 Major League Baseball season|1975]], the Birds acquired slugger [[Lee May]] in a trade with Houston, and traded [[Dave McNally]], [[Rich Coggins]] and minor-league pitcher Bill Kirkpatrick to Montreal for star outfielder [[Ken Singleton]], and future 20-game winner [[Mike Torrez]]. Jim Palmer won the Cy Young Award, but the [[1975 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] lost the division title to the [[1975 Boston Red Sox season|Boston Red Sox]] and their mega-rookies [[Fred Lynn]] and [[Jim Rice]]. The [[1976 Major League Baseball season|1976]] season brought [[Reggie Jackson]] and [[Ken Holtzman]] from a trade with Oakland, but the [[1976 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] only won 88 games. It was this season when the Orioles made a trade that brought them players such as [[Tippy Martinez]] and [[Rick Dempsey]]. This young foundation, along with the departures of the unhappy Jackson and Holtzman, would create the basis for [[1977 Major League Baseball season|1977]]. The [[1977 Baltimore Orioles season|&quot;No Name Orioles&quot;]], along with Rookie of the Year [[Eddie Murray]], won 97 games and finished tied for second place with Boston. After finishing fourth in [[1978 Major League Baseball season|1978]], the [[1979 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] finally won the division in [[1979 Major League Baseball season|1979]] thanks to strong play from Ken Singleton and Cy Young Winner [[Mike Flanagan (baseball)|Mike Flanagan]]. The Orioles defeated the [[1979 California Angels season|Angels]] in the [[1979 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], but lost to [[1979 Pittsburgh Pirates season|Pittsburgh]] in another [[1979 World Series|stunning World Series]]. This started a short period of heartbreak for Baltimore that would nevertheless culminate in a championship.

The [[1980 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] won 100 games in [[1980 Major League Baseball season|1980]] thanks to Cy Young Winner [[Steve Stone (baseball)|Steve Stone]], but the [[1980 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] won 103 games. Although [[1981 Baltimore Orioles season|Baltimore]] had the best overall record in the AL East in [[1981 Major League Baseball season|1981]], they finished second in each half. As a result, they were out of the playoffs. The [[1982 Major League Baseball season|1982]] campaign saw Baltimore eliminated on the final weekend of the season by the [[1982 Milwaukee Brewers season|Milwaukee Brewers]]. [[Earl Weaver]] retired and [[Joe Altobelli]] took over for [[1983 Major League Baseball season|1983]]. Altobelli would lead the Orioles to 98 wins and a division title thanks to MVP [[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]. The [[1983 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] defeated the [[1983 Chicago White Sox season|Chicago White Sox]] in the [[1983 American League Championship Series|ALCS]] thanks to a 10th-inning homer by [[Tito Landrum]] in the deciding game. The Orioles won the [[1983 World Series|World Series]] in five games by defeating the [[1983 Philadelphia Phillies season|Philadelphia Phillies]].

During their most productive years, the Orioles saw three of its players named MVP: ([[Frank Robinson]] in 1966; [[Boog Powell]] in 1970; and [[Cal Ripken, Jr.]] in 1983). Additionally, [[Brooks Robinson]] was named Most Valuable Player in 1964, just two years before the 1966–1983 golden era began.  The pitching staff was phenomenal, with four pitchers winning six [[Cy Young Award]]s (Mike Cuellar in 1969; Jim Palmer in 1973, 1975, and 1976; Mike Flanagan in 1979; and [[Steve Stone (baseball)|Steve Stone]] in 1980). In 1971, the team's four starting pitchers, McNally, Cuellar, Palmer, and [[Pat Dobson]], all won 20 games, a feat that has not been replicated. In that year, the Birds went on to post a 101–61 record for their third-straight AL East title.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sportsecyclopedia.com/al/baltios/orioles.html Baltimore Orioles (1954–Present)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Also during this stretch three players were named [[American League Rookie of the Year|rookies of the year]]: [[Al Bumbry]] (1973); Eddie Murray (1977); and Cal Ripken, Jr. (1982).  One might date the glory years of the Orioles dating back to 1964, which would include two 3rd-place seasons, 1964–1965, in which the Orioles won 97 and 94 games, respectively, and a year in which third-baseman [[Brooks Robinson]] won his Most Valuable Player Award (1964).  The glory years of the Orioles effectively ended when the [[1984 Detroit Tigers season|Detroit Tigers]], a divisional rival at the time, went 35–5 to open the [[1984 Major League Baseball season|1984 season]] on the way to winning the World Series, and when Hall-of-Fame pitcher [[Jim Palmer]] retired during the 1984 season.

====Final seasons at Memorial Stadium (1984–1991)====
After winning the [[1983 World Series]], the Orioles spent the next five years in steady decline, finishing [[1986 Major League Baseball season|1986]] in last place for the first time since the franchise moved to Baltimore. The [[1988 Baltimore Orioles season|team]] hit bottom in [[1988 Major League Baseball season|1988]] when it started the season 0–21, en route to 107 losses and the worst record in the majors that year. The Orioles surprised the baseball world the following year by spending most of the summer in first place until September when the [[1989 Toronto Blue Jays season|Toronto Blue Jays]] overtook them and seized the A.L. East title on the final weekend of the regular season. The next two years were spent below the .500 mark, highlighted only by Cal Ripken, Jr. winning his second [[Major League Baseball Most Valuable Player Award|A.L. MVP Award]] in [[1991 Major League Baseball season|1991]]. The [[1991 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] said goodbye to Memorial Stadium, the team's home for 38 years, at the end of the 1991 campaign.

====Camden Yards opens (1992–93)====
{{main|1992 Baltimore Orioles season|1993 Baltimore Orioles season}}
Opening to much fanfare in 1992, [[Oriole Park at Camden Yards]] was an instant success, spawning other retro-designed major league ballparks within the next two decades. The stadium became the site of the [[1993 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1993 All-Star Game]]. The Orioles returned to contention in those first two seasons at Camden Yards, only to finish in third place both times.

=====Angelos takes over=====
Also in 1993, with then-owner [[Eli Jacobs]] forced to divest himself of the franchise, Baltimore-based attorney [[Peter Angelos]] was awarded the Orioles in [[United States bankruptcy court|bankruptcy court]], returning the team to local ownership for the first time since 1979.

====Strike year (1994)====
{{main|1994 Baltimore Orioles season}}
After the 1993 season, the Orioles acquired first baseman [[Rafael Palmeiro]] from the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]]. The Orioles, who spent all of [[1994 Major League Baseball season|1994]] chasing the [[1994 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]], occupied second place in the new five-team AL East when the [[1994 Major League Baseball strike|players strike]], which began on August 11, forced the eventual cancellation of the season.

====Ripken breaks the streak (1995)====
{{main|1995 Baltimore Orioles season}}
The labor impasse would continue into the spring of [[1995 Major League Baseball season|1995]]. Almost all of the major league clubs held [[spring training]] using [[strikebreaker|replacement players]], with the intention of beginning the [[1995 Major League Baseball season|season]] with them. The Orioles, whose owner was a [[trade union|labor union]] [[lawyer]], were the lone dissenters against creating an ersatz team, choosing instead to sit out spring training and possibly the entire season. Had they fielded a substitute team, [[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]'s consecutive games streak would have been jeopardized. The replacements questions became moot when the strike was finally settled.

The Ripken countdown resumed once the season began. Ripken finally broke [[Lou Gehrig]]'s consecutive games streak of 2,130 games in a nationally televised game on September 6. This was later voted the all-time baseball moment of the 20th century by fans from around the country in 1999. Ripken finished his streak with 2,632 straight games, finally sitting on September 20, 1998, against the [[1998 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] at Camden Yards.

The Orioles finished two games under .500 in third place in [[Phil Regan (baseball)|Phil Regan]]'s only season of managing the ballclub.

====Playoff years (1996–97)====
=====1996 season=====
{{main|1996 Baltimore Orioles season}}
Before the [[1996 Major League Baseball season|1996 season]], Angelos hired [[Pat Gillick]] as general manager. Given the green light to spend heavily on established talent, Gillick signed several premium players like [[B.J. Surhoff]], [[Randy Myers]], [[David Wells]] and [[Roberto Alomar]]. Under new manager [[Davey Johnson]] and on the strength of a then-major league record 257 [[home run]]s in a single season, the Orioles returned to the playoffs after a twelve-year absence by clinching the A.L. [[wild card (sports)|wild card]] berth. Alomar set off a firestorm in September when he spat into home plate umpire [[John Hirschbeck]]'s face during an argument in Toronto. He was later suspended for the first five games of the 1997 season, even though most wanted him banned from the postseason. After dethroning the defending A.L. Champion [[1996 Cleveland Indians season|Cleveland Indians]] 3–1 in the [[1996 American League Division Series|Division Series]], the Orioles fell to the [[1996 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] 4–1 in an [[1996 American League Championship Series|ALCS]] infamous for right field umpire [[Rich Garcia]]'s failure to call fan interference, when Yankee fan Jeffrey Maier reached over the outfield wall to catch an in-play hit which was clearly on its path to being caught by right fielder Tony Tarasco.  This failed call was largely blamed for changing the momentum of the series and granting the Yankees another questionable win.

=====1997 season=====
{{main|1997 Baltimore Orioles season}}
The Orioles went &quot;wire-to-wire&quot; (first place from start to finish) in winning the [[American League East|A.L. East]] title in [[1997 Major League Baseball season|1997]]. After eliminating the [[1997 Seattle Mariners season|Seattle Mariners]] 3–1 in the [[1997 American League Division Series|Division Series]], the team lost again in the [[1997 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], this time to the underdog [[1997 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]] 4–2, with each Oriole loss by only a run. Johnson resigned as manager after the season, largely due to a spat with Angelos concerning Alomar's fine for missing a team function being donated to Johnson's wife's charity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/sports/orioles/longterm/memories/davey/articles/poorcomm.htm | work=The Washington Post|title=Poor Communication at Heart of Feud  | date=May 12, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pitching coach [[Ray Miller (baseball manager)|Ray Miller]] replaced Johnson.

====Futility: 14 years and counting (1998–present)====
=====1998 season=====
{{main|1998 Baltimore Orioles season}}
With Miller at the helm, the Orioles found themselves not only out of the playoffs, but also with a losing season. When Gillick's contract expired in 1998, it was not renewed. Angelos brought in [[Frank Wren]] to take over as GM. The Orioles added volatile slugger [[Albert Belle]], but the team's woes continued in the 1999 season, with stars like [[Rafael Palmeiro]], [[Roberto Alomar]], and [[Eric Davis (baseball)|Eric Davis]] leaving in free agency. After a second straight losing season, Angelos fired both Miller and Wren. He named [[Syd Thrift]] the new GM and brought in former Cleveland manager [[Mike Hargrove]].

=====1999 season=====
{{main|1999 Baltimore Orioles season}}
[[File:Baltimore Orioles.svg|150px|left|thumb|Logo from 1999–2008.]]In a rare event on March 28, 1999, the Orioles staged an exhibition game against the [[Cuba national baseball team|Cuban national team]] in [[Havana]]. The Orioles won the game 3–2 in 11 innings. They were the first Major League team to play in Cuba since 1959, when the [[1959 Los Angeles Dodggers season|Los Angeles Dodgers]] faced the [[1959 Baltimore Orioles season|Orioles]] in an exhibition. The game was part of a two-game series, in which the Cuban team visited Baltimore in May 1999. Cuba won the second game 10–6.

=====2000-02 seasons=====
[[File:CamdenYards 2005-05-08.jpg|300px|thumb|[[Oriole Park at Camden Yards]]]]
{{main|2000 Baltimore Orioles season}}
Cal Ripken, Jr. achieved his 3000th hit early in the season.  A fire sale occurred late in the season, where the Orioles traded away many veterans for unproven young players and minor league prospects.  The Orioles called up many of their AAA players to finish the season.  The only acquired player that would have a long-term career with the organization was [[Melvin Mora]].
{{main|2001 Baltimore Orioles season}}
This was Cal Ripken, Jr.'s final season. His number (8) was retired in a ceremony before the final home game of the season.
{{main|2002 Baltimore Orioles season}}

=====2003–04 seasons=====
{{main|2003 Baltimore Orioles season|2004 Baltimore Orioles season}}
In an effort to right the Orioles' sinking ship, changes began to sweep through the organization in {{mlby|2003}}. General manager [[Syd Thrift]] was fired and to replace him, the Orioles hired [[Jim Beattie]] as executive vice-president and [[Mike Flanagan (baseball)|Mike Flanagan]] as the vice president of baseball operations. After another losing season, manager [[Mike Hargrove]] was not retained and Yankees coach [[Lee Mazzilli]] was brought in as the new manager. The team signed powerful hitters in SS [[Miguel Tejada]], C [[Javy López]], and former Oriole 1B [[Rafael Palmeiro]]. The following season, the Orioles traded for OF [[Sammy Sosa]].

=====2005 season=====
{{main|2005 Baltimore Orioles season}}
The team got hot early in [[2005 Major League Baseball season|2005]] and jumped out in front of the AL East division, holding onto first place for 62 straight days. However, turmoil on and off the field began to take its toll as the Orioles started struggling around the All-Star break, dropping them close to the surging [[2005 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] and [[2005 Boston Red Sox season|Red Sox]]. Injuries to Lopez, Sosa, [[Luis Matos]], [[Brian Roberts]], and [[Larry Bigbie]] came within weeks of each other, and the team grew increasingly dissatisfied with the &quot;band-aid&quot; moves of the front office and manager Mazzilli to help them through this period of struggle. Various minor league players such as Single-A Frederick OF [[Jeff Fiorentino]] were brought up in place of more experienced players such as OF [[David Newhan]], who had batted .311 the previous season.

After starting the season 42–28 (.600), the Orioles finished the season with a stretch of 32–60 (.348), ending at 74–88 (.457). Only the [[2005 Kansas City Royals season|Kansas City Royals]] (.346) had a worse winning percentage for the season than did the Orioles for the final 92 games. The club's major off-season acquisition, [[Sammy Sosa]], posted his worst performance in a decade, with 14 home runs and a .221 batting average. The Orioles did not attempt to re-sign him. The Orioles also allowed Palmeiro to file for free agency and publicly stated they would not re-sign him. On August 25, pitcher [[Sidney Ponson]] was arrested for [[DUI]], and on September 1, the Orioles moved to void his contract (on a morals clause) and released him. The [[Major League Baseball Players Association]] filed a grievance on Ponson's behalf and the case was sent to arbitration and was eventually resolved.

=====2006 season=====
{{main|2006 Baltimore Orioles season}}
In the [[2006 World Baseball Classic]], the Orioles contributed more players than any other major league team, with eleven players suiting up for their home nations. [[Erik Bedard]] and [[Adam Loewen]] pitched for [[Canada national baseball team|Canada]]; [[Rodrigo López (pitcher)|Rodrigo López]] and [[Geronimo Gil]] (released before the season began by the club) played for [[Mexico national baseball team|Mexico]]; [[Daniel Cabrera]] and [[Miguel Tejada]] for the [[Dominican Republic national baseball team|Dominican Republic]]; [[Javy López]] and [[Luis Matos]] for [[Puerto Rico national baseball team|Puerto Rico]]; [[Bruce Chen]] for [[Panama national baseball team|Panama]]; [[Ramon Hernandez]] for [[Venezuela national baseball team|Venezuela]]; and [[John Stephens (baseball player)|John Stephens]] for [[Australia national baseball team|Australia]]. The Orioles finished the [[2006 Major League Baseball season|2006 season]] with a record of 70 wins and 92 losses, 27 games behind the AL East-leading Yankees.

=====2007 season=====
{{main|2007 Baltimore Orioles season}}
On June 18, 2007, the Orioles fired [[Sam Perlozzo]] after losing eight straight games. He was replaced on interim basis by [[Dave Trembley]]. On June 22, Miguel Tejada's consecutive-games streak came to an end due to an injury, the fifth-longest streak in major league history. [[Aubrey Huff]] became the first Oriole to hit for the cycle at home, on June 29 against the Angels. On July 7, [[Erik Bedard]] struck out 15 batters in a game against the [[2007 Texas Rangers season|Texas Rangers]] to tie a franchise record held by [[Mike Mussina]]. On July 31, 2007, [[Andy MacPhail]] named Dave Trembley as the Orioles manager through the remainder of the 2007 season, and advised him to &quot;Keep up the good work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.yahoo.com/mlb/news?slug=ap-orioles-perlozzo&amp;prov=ap&amp;type=lgns Yahoo! Sports – Sports News, Scores, Rumors, Fantasy Games, and more&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Facing the Texas Rangers in a doubleheader at Camden Yards on August 22, the Orioles surrendered 30 runs in the first game-a modern-era record for a single game-in a 30–3 defeat. The Orioles led the game 3–0 after three innings of play. Sixteen of Texas' thirty runs were scored in the final two innings. The Orioles would also fall in the nightcap, 9–7.

=====2008 season=====
{{main|2008 Baltimore Orioles season}}
[[File:Baltimore Orioles Script.svg|right|thumb|The script logo.]]The Orioles began the [[2008 Major League Baseball season|2008 season]] in a rebuilding mode under President of Baseball Operations [[Andy MacPhail]]. The Orioles traded away star players [[Miguel Tejada]] to the [[Astros]] and ace [[Erik Bedard]] to the [[Seattle Mariners]] for prized prospect [[Adam Jones (baseball)|Adam Jones]], lefty reliever [[George Sherrill]], and minor league pitchers [[Kam Mickolio]], [[Chris Tillman]], and Tony Butler. The Orioles started off the first couple weeks of the season near the top of their division as players such as [[Nick Markakis]] and newcomer [[Luke Scott]] led the team offensively. Although the Orioles hovered around .500 for much of the season, they had fallen back by September and were over 20 games behind the first place [[2008 Tampa Bay Rays season|Tampa Bay Rays]]. They finished the season losing 11 of their final 12 games and 28 of their final 34. The team finished last for the first time since their [[1988 Major League Baseball season|1988 season]]. After the season ended, the Orioles showcased altered uniforms, with a circular 'Maryland' patch added to the left-hand sleeve of all jerseys and the grey road jerseys displaying Baltimore across the chest for the first time since [[1972 Major League Baseball season|1972]].

=====2009 season=====
{{main|2009 Baltimore Orioles season}}
[[File:Nick Markakis.jpg|thumb|right|2009 Orioles Adam Jones and Nick Markakis]]
On June 30, 2009, the Orioles rallied to score 10 runs against [[2009 Boston Red Sox season|Boston Red Sox]] after facing a 10–1 deficit in the 7th inning, winning the game by 11–10, setting a Major League Baseball record for the largest comeback by a last-place team over a first-place team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20090630&amp;content_id=5618964&amp;vkey=recap&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=mlb |title=O's stage historic comeback vs. Red Sox |publisher=mlb.mlb.com |date= 2009-06-30 |accessdate= 2011-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, the team finished the [[2009 Major League Baseball season|2009 season]] with 64 wins and 98 losses, making it the worst record in the 2009 American League season. Despite this, Manager [[Dave Trembley]] was re-hired for the [[2010 Major League Baseball season|2010 season]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20091002&amp;content_id=7287970&amp;vkey=news_mlb&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=mlb |title=Orioles pick up option on Trembley |publisher= mlb.mlb.com |accessdate=2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Centerfielder Adam Jones was named to the 2009 All Star team and awarded a Gold Glove award for his defensive play.

=====2010 season=====
{{main|2010 Baltimore Orioles season}}

The Orioles started off their 2010 season with newly acquired [[Kevin Millwood]] as their opening day starter.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://baltimore.orioles.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20100329&amp;content_id=8989470&amp;vkey=news_bal&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=bal |title=Millwood gets O's Opening Day nod |publisher=baltimore.orioles.mlb.com |accessdate= 2011-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 12, 2010 the team set a club record for the lowest paid attendance in Camden Yards history, only 9,129 attended the game versus the Tampa Bay Rays
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wbaltv.com/sports/23130983/detail.html |title=Orioles Set Attendance Low, Lose To Rays – Sports News Story |publisher=wbaltv.com |accessdate=2011-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Orioles then went 2–16 to begin the season, one of the worst openings in MLB history. For much of the first half of the season, they had by far the worst record in the league.

On June 4, the Orioles replaced [[Dave Trembley]] as manager with third base coach [[Juan Samuel]]. Samuels's appointment was announced as 'interim'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wbaltv.com/r/23791247/detail.html |title=O's Fire Trembley, Samuel To Replace Him - Baltimore News Story |publisher=wbaltv.com |date=2010-06-04 |accessdate=2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 30, the Orioles hired [[Buck Showalter]] to be the full-time manager.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/dailypitch/post/2010/07/orioles-hire-buck-showalter-as-manager/1 |title=Orioles hire Buck Showalter as manager - Daily Pitch: MLB News, Standings, Schedules &amp; More |publisher= content.usatoday.com |date=2010-07-29 |accessdate=2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was introduced on August 2 and made his debut on August 3, after the Orioles fired [[Juan Samuel]]. Showalter chose to wear the number 26 in honor of his friend and former Oriole's manager [[Johnny Oates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://msn.foxsports.com/mlb/story/Buck-Showalter-to-wear-Johnny-Oates-number-as-Orioles-manager |title=Showalter pays tribute to his old friend and mentor |publisher=msn.foxsports.com |date=2010-08-06 |accessdate= 2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Showalter's arrival produced, or coincided with, a turnaround; the Birds went 34–24 in August, September and October.

[[File:Baseball Catcher.JPG|thumb|left|Baltimore Orioles catcher, Craig Tatum, is preparing for the game]]
[[File:Orioles Win May 13 2010.JPG|left|thumb|The team celebrates after winning a game against the [[Seattle Mariners]] in Oriole Park at Camden Yards on 13th May, 2010]]

=====2011 season=====
{{main|2011 Baltimore Orioles season}}

On February 4, the Orioles signed free agent [[Vladimir Guerrero]] to be the team's designated hitter. Guerrero hit 29 home runs and had a .300 batting average in the 2010 season with the Texas Rangers. He has a career average of .320 and 436 home runs.

The Orioles finished 69-93 to finish with yet another losing season. This makes 14 consecutive losing seasons for this franchise dating back to 1998. The O's have recently hired Dan Duquette as their new GM and president of baseball operations to hopefully help turn the corner.

==Uniform==
The Orioles home uniform is white with the word &quot;Orioles&quot; written across the chest. The Orioles road uniform is gray with the word &quot;Baltimore&quot; written across the chest. An alternate uniform is black with the word &quot;Orioles&quot; written across the chest. The Orioles wear their black alternate jerseys (usually on Fridays) with the alternate &quot;O's&quot; cap, whether at home or on the road.

For 2012, the Orioles unveiled new uniforms. There is a change to the cap insignia, with the cartoon Oriole replacing the current image-based one. Also, they have introduced a new alternate orange uniform to be worn on Saturday home games throughout the 2012 season.

[[File:ALE-Uniform-BAL.PNG|right|thumb|The club's 2010 Uniforms. Left to right: Home, Away, Alternative.]]

==Radio and television==
{{see|List of Baltimore Orioles broadcasters}}

===Current===
====Radio====
Orioles games are broadcast on a 43-station radio network in Maryland and nearby states, anchored by [[Flagship (radio)|flagship station]] [[WBAL (AM)|WBAL]]. [[Fred Manfra]] and [[Joe Angel]] alternate radio announcing duties.

====Television====
As part of the settlement of a television broadcast rights dispute with [[CSN Washington|Comcast SportsNet]] over the Washington Nationals, the Orioles severed their Comcast ties at the end of the 2006 season. All Orioles games are now televised on the Orioles-controlled [[Mid-Atlantic Sports Network|Mid-Atlantic Sports Network (MASN)]], with some games also airing locally on [[WJZ-TV|WJZ-TV (ch. 13)]]. Longtime sportscaster [[Gary Thorne]], who is also recognized for his work as a hockey announcer, is the current lead television announcer for the Orioles, with [[Jim Hunter (sportscaster)|Jim Hunter]] as his backup along with [[National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum|Hall of Fame]] member and former Orioles pitcher [[Jim Palmer]]. Some MASN telecasts in conflict with Washington Nationals' game telecasts air on an alternate MASN2 feed. All Oriole games are televised, as their non-MASN games are televised by [[ESPN Major League Baseball|ESPN]], [[Major League Baseball on Fox|Fox]], or [[Major League Baseball on TBS|TBS]].

===Former===
Six former Oriole franchise radio announcers have received the Hall of Fame's [[Ford C. Frick Award]] for excellence in broadcasting: [[Chuck Thompson]] (who was also the voice of the old [[National Football League|NFL]] [[Indianapolis Colts|Baltimore Colts]]); [[Jon Miller]] (now with the [[San Francisco Giants]]); [[Ernie Harwell]], [[Herb Carneal]]; [[Bob Murphy (announcer)|Bob Murphy]] and [[Harry Caray]] (as a St. Louis Browns announcer in the 1940s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.paperofrecord.com/paper_view.asp?PaperId=834&amp;RecordId=1&amp;PageId=7750536&amp;iZyNetId={2E6BBCCF-5CD0-46CC-A586-07221F6521B4}&amp;iOrder=2&amp;iOrderDir=0&amp;iCurrentBlock=1 |title=About Paper of Record |publisher=paperofrecord.com |accessdate= 2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
). Other former Baltimore announcers include [[Josh Lewin]] (currently with [[Fox Sports (USA)|Fox Sports]]), the late [[Bill O'Donnell (sportscaster)|Bill O'Donnell]], and Baltimore radio veteran [[Tom Marr]], who called the games during the &quot;Oriole Magic&quot; years on the old WFBR-AM (now [[WJZ (AM)|WJZ]]). In 1991, the Orioles experimented with longtime TV writer/producer [[Ken Levine (TV personality)|Ken Levine]] as a play-by-play broadcaster. Levine was best noted for his work on TV shows such as ''[[Cheers]]'' and ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', but only lasted one season in the Orioles broadcast booth.

Other previous flagship radio stations include [[WBAL (AM)|WBAL]] (1090&amp;nbsp;kHz AM) from 1987–2006, the now-defunct [[WFBR (AM)|WFBR]] (1300&amp;nbsp;kHz AM) from 1979 through 1986, and a brief period with [[WCBM]] (680&amp;nbsp;kHz AM) for the 1987 season. Previous to 1979, WBAL had been the flagship station.

Former Oriole television broadcasters include: Thompson, Miller, former [[Baltimore Ravens]] broadcaster Scott Garceau, longtime versatile sportscaster [[Mel Proctor]], former [[Cleveland Cavaliers]] broadcaster [[Michael Reghi]], former major leaguer [[Buck Martinez]] (now with the [[Toronto Blue Jays]] as their play-by-play announcer), as well as former Oriole players including Hall of Fame third baseman [[Brooks Robinson]] and former outfielder [[John Lowenstein]].

Previous Baltimore television flagship stations have included: [[WMAR-TV]] (Channel 2) and [[WNUV|WNUV-TV]] (Channel 54), as well as regional cable network Home Team Sports (HTS) which eventually evolved into Comcast SportsNet.

==Musical traditions==	
===&quot;O!&quot;===	
Since its introduction at games by the &quot;Roar from 34&quot;, led by [[Wild Bill Hagy]] and others, in the late 1970s, it has been a tradition at Orioles games for fans to yell out the &quot;Oh&quot; in the line &quot;Oh, say does that Star-Spangled Banner yet wave&quot; in &quot;[[The Star-Spangled Banner]]&quot;. &quot;The Star-Spangled Banner&quot; has special meaning to Baltimore historically, as it was written during the [[Battle of Baltimore]] in the [[War of 1812]] by [[Francis Scott Key]], a Baltimorean. &quot;O&quot; is not only short for &quot;Oriole&quot;, but the vowel is also a stand-out aspect of the [[Baltimorese|Baltimorean accent]].
	
The tradition is often carried out at other sporting events, both professional or amateur, and even sometimes at non-sporting events where the anthem is played, throughout the [[Baltimore-Washington metropolitan area|Baltimore/Washington area]] and beyond, notably at [[Baltimore Ravens]], [[Washington Capitals]], [[Georgetown Hoyas]], [[Maryland Terrapins]], [[Virginia Cavaliers]], [[Virginia Tech Hokies]], [[West Virginia Mountaineers]], [[Penn State Nittany Lions]] and Aberdeen Ironbirds games. Fans in Norfolk, Virginia, chanted &quot;O!&quot; even before the [[Norfolk Tides|Tides]] became an Orioles affiliate. &quot;O!&quot; has also been shouted during the anthem at [[Washington Redskins]] and [[Washington Capitals]] home games. The &quot;O&quot; Shout has traveled from across the DC Metro Area, from Frostburg, Maryland, to Salisbury, Maryland. The practice caught some attention in the spring of 2005, when some fans performed the &quot;O!&quot; cry at [[Washington Nationals]] games at [[RFK Stadium]]. At [[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]'s induction into the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame]], the crowd, comprising mostly Orioles fans, carried out the &quot;O!&quot; tradition during [[Tony Gwynn]]'s daughter's rendition of &quot;The Star-Spangled Banner&quot;. Additionally, a faint but audible &quot;O!&quot; could be heard on the television broadcast of Barack Obama's pre-inaugural visit to Baltimore as the National Anthem played before his entrance. A resounding &quot;O!&quot; bellowed from the nearly 30,000 Ravens fans that attended the November 21, 2010 away game at the [[Carolina Panthers]]' [[Bank of America Stadium]] in Charlotte, North Carolina.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lee|first=Edward|title='It was like a home game' vs. Panthers, said Ravens quarterback Joe Flacco|url=http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2010-11-22/sports/bs-sp-ravens-notebook-1122-20101121_1_ravens-quarterback-joe-flacco-ed-reed-panthers-fans|publisher=The Baltimore Sun|accessdate=28 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
Some songs from special events include &quot;[[One Moment in Time]]&quot; for Cal Ripken's record-breaking game. For his last game, the theme from ''[[Pearl Harbor (film)|Pearl Harbor]]'', &quot;There You'll Be&quot; by [[Faith Hill]], was featured. The theme from ''[[Field of Dreams]]'' was played at the last game at Memorial Stadium in 1991, and the song &quot;Magic to Do&quot; from the stage musical ''[[Pippin (musical)|Pippin]]'' was used that season to commemorate &quot;Orioles Magic&quot; on 33rd Street. During the Orioles' heyday in the 1970s, a club song, appropriately titled &quot;Orioles Magic&quot;, was composed, and played when the team ran out until Opening Day of 2008. Starting the following game, the song (a favorite among many fans, who appreciated its references to [[Wild Bill Hagy]] and [[Earl Weaver]]) was only played (along with a video featuring several Orioles stars performing the song) after wins.

====&quot;Thank God I'm a Country Boy&quot;====
It has been an Orioles tradition since 1975 to play [[John Denver]]'s &quot;[[Thank God I'm a Country Boy]]&quot; during the [[seventh inning stretch]].

In the July 5, 2007 edition of Baltimore's weekly sports publication ''Press Box'', an article by Mike Gibbons covered the details of how this tradition came to be.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.pressboxonline.com/story.cfm?id=2189 |title=Baltimore’s Seventh-Inning Tradition Within a Tradition |date=July 5, 2007 |first=Mike |last=Gibbons |publisher= pressboxonline.com |accessdate=2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During &quot;[[Thank God I'm a Country Boy]]&quot;, a man in the club level sections puts on overalls and starts dancing around. He also has an orange violin for the violin solos.

==Rex Barney==
For 23 years, [[Rex Barney]] was the [[Public address|PA announcer]] for the Orioles. His voice became a fixture of both Memorial Stadium and Camden Yards, and his expression &quot;Give that fan a contract&quot;, uttered whenever a fan caught a [[foul ball]], was one of his trademarks&amp;nbsp;– the other being his distinct &quot;Thank Yooooou...&quot; following every announcement (He was also known on occasion to say &quot;Give that fan an error&quot; after a dropped foul ball). Barney died on August 12, 1997, and in his honor that night's game at Camden Yards against the Oakland Athletics was held without a public–address announcer.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url=http://www.baseballlibrary.com/baseballlibrary/chronology/1997AUGUST.stm |title=August 1997 |publisher=baseballlibrary.com  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Barney was replaced as Camden Yards' PA announcer by [[Dave McGowan (announcer)|Dave McGowan]], who remains in that capacity today.

==Season-by-season records==
{{main|List of Baltimore Orioles seasons}}

==Post-season appearances==
Of the eight original American League teams, the Orioles were the last of the eight to win the [[World Series]], doing so in [[1966 World Series|1966]] with its four–game sweep of the heavily favored [[1966 Los Angeles Dodgers season|Los Angeles Dodgers]]. When the Orioles were the St. Louis Browns, they played in only one World Series, the [[1944 World Series|1944 matchup]] against their Sportsman's Park tenants, the [[1944 St. Louis Cardinals season|Cardinals]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot;
|-
!Year
!colspan=2|[[American League Division Series|ALDS]]
!colspan=2|[[American League Championship Series|ALCS]]
!colspan=2|[[World Series]]
|-
|[[1944 St. Louis Browns season|1944]] (St. Louis)
|
|
|
|
|[[1944 St. Louis Cardinals season|St. Louis Cardinals]]
|[[1944 World Series|L]]
|-
|[[1966 Baltimore Orioles season|1966]] (Baltimore)
|
|
|
|
|[[1966 Los Angeles Dodgers season|Los Angeles Dodgers]]
|[[1966 World Series|W]]
|-
|[[1969 Baltimore Orioles season|1969]]
|
|
|[[1969 Minnesota Twins season|Minnesota Twins]]
|[[1969 American League Championship Series|W]]
|[[1969 New York Mets season|New York Mets]]
|[[1969 World Series|L]]
|-
|[[1970 Baltimore Orioles season|1970]]
|
|
|[[1970 Minnesota Twins season|Minnesota Twins]]
|[[1970 American League Championship Series|W]]
|[[1970 Cincinnati Reds season|Cincinnati Reds]]
|[[1970 World Series|W]]
|-
|[[1971 Baltimore Orioles season|1971]]
|
|
|[[1971 Oakland Athletics season|Oakland Athletics]]
|[[1971 American League Championship Series|W]]
|[[1971 Pittsburgh Pirates season|Pittsburgh Pirates]]
|[[1971 World Series|L]]
|-
|[[1973 Baltimore Orioles season|1973]]
|
|
|[[1973 Oakland Athletics season|Oakland Athletics]]
|[[1973 American League Championship Series|L]]
|
|
|-
|[[1974 Baltimore Orioles season|1974]]
|
|
|[[1974 Oakland Athletics season|Oakland Athletics]]
|[[1974 American League Championship Series|L]]
|
|
|-
|[[1979 Baltimore Orioles season|1979]]
|
|
|[[1979 California Angels season|California Angels]]
|[[1979 American League Championship Series|W]]
|[[1979 Pittsburgh Pirates season|Pittsburgh Pirates]]
|[[1979 World Series|L]]
|-
|[[1983 Baltimore Orioles season|1983]]
|
|
|[[1983 Chicago White Sox season|Chicago White Sox]]
|[[1983 American League Championship Series|W]]
|[[1983 Philadelphia Phillies season|Philadelphia Phillies]]
|[[1983 World Series|W]]
|-
|[[1996 Baltimore Orioles season|1996]]
|[[1996 Cleveland Indians season|Cleveland Indians]]
|[[1996 American League Division Series|W]]
|[[1996 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]]
|[[1996 American League Championship Series|L]]
|
|
|-
|[[1997 Baltimore Orioles season|1997]]
|[[1997 Seattle Mariners season|Seattle Mariners]]
|[[1997 American League Division Series|W]]
|[[1997 Cleveland Indians season|Cleveland Indians]]
|[[1997 American League Championship Series|L]]
|
|
|}

==Baseball Hall of Famers==
{{main|National Baseball Hall of Fame}}
&lt;center&gt;{{HOFList
|Current Team Name = Baltimore Orioles
|   All Team Names = Orioles or Browns
|          ColorA# = 000000
|          ColorB# = FB4F14
|          ColorC# = FB4F14
|          ColorD# = FFFFFF
|      Team Name 1 = '''Milwaukee Brewers'''
|         List 1.1 = 
|         List 1.2 = 
|         List 1.3 = [[Hugh Duffy]]
|         List 1.4 = 
|         List 1.5 = 
|      Team Name 2 = '''St. Louis Browns'''
|         List 2.1 = [[Jim Bottomley]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Willard Brown (baseball outfielder)|Willard Brown]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jesse Burkett]]
|         List 2.2 = [[Dizzy Dean]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Rick Ferrell]]'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Goose Goslin]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rogers Hornsby]]
|         List 2.3 = [[Tommy Lasorda]] **&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, Fred: ''The Final Season,'' St. Louis Browns Historical Society, 111 pp. (1991) ISBN 1-880629-00-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20090107232458/http://www.bigdunker.com/lasorda.htm |title=1953 San Francisco Seals pre-season scorecard |publisher=bigdunker.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[[Heinie Manush]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Christy Mathewson]] **&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://bioproj.sabr.org/bioproj.cfm?a=v&amp;v=l&amp;bid=1548&amp;pid=19110 |publisher=bioproj.sabr.org |title= The Baseball Biography Project }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Joe Medwick]] **&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/m/medwijo01.shtml |title=Joe Medwick Statistics and History |publisher=baseball-reference.com |accessdate= 2011-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|         List 2.4 = [[Satchel Paige]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eddie Plank]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Branch Rickey]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[George Sisler]]'''*
|         List 2.5 = [[Bill Veeck]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rube Waddell]]*&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Bobby Wallace (baseball)|Bobby Wallace]]'''
|      Team Name 3 = '''Baltimore Orioles'''
|         List 3.1 = [[Roberto Alomar]]&lt;br&gt;[[Luis Aparicio]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pat Gillick]]&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt;
|         List 3.2 = [[Whitey Herzog]]&lt;br&gt;[[Reggie Jackson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[George Kell]]
|         List 3.3 = '''[[Eddie Murray]]'''&lt;br&gt;'''[[Jim Palmer]]'''&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Robin Roberts (baseball)|Robin Roberts]]
|         List 3.4 = '''[[Brooks Robinson]]'''&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Frank Robinson]]'''&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Earl Weaver]]'''
|         List 3.5 = [[Hoyt Wilhelm]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dick Williams]]
|      Team Name 4 = 
|         List 4.1 = 
|         List 4.2 = 
|         List 4.3 = 
|         List 4.4 = 
|         List 4.5 =
|        Footnote1 = * Has no insignia on his cap due to playing at a time when caps bore no insignia.
|        Footnote2 = ** Were property of the St. Louis Browns and were assigned to the team's major league roster, but never appeared in a regulation game.
|        Footnote3 =&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt; – Pat Gillick was elected as an Executive/Pioneer due in part to his contributions to baseball as general manager of the Orioles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Carr|first=Samantha|title=Emotional Election|url=http://baseballhall.org/news/voting-news/emotional-election|publisher=National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum|accessdate=5 January 2011|date=6 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|        Footnote4 =
|}}&lt;/center&gt;

===Ford C. Frick Award recipients (broadcasters)===
&lt;center&gt;{{FCFList
|Current Team Name = Baltimore Orioles
|   All Team Names = Orioles or Browns
|          ColorA# = 000000
|          ColorB# = FB4F14
|          ColorC# = FB4F14
|          ColorD# = FFFFFF
|         List 1   = [[Harry Caray]]
|         List 2   = [[Herb Carneal]]
|         List 3   = [[Milo Hamilton]]&lt;br&gt;'''[[Chuck Thompson]]'''
|         List 4   = [[Ernie Harwell]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jon Miller]]
|         List 5   = [[Bob Murphy (announcer)|Bob Murphy]]
|        Footnote1 =
|        Footnote2 =
|        Footnote3 =
|        Footnote4 =
|}}&lt;/center&gt;

===Retired numbers===
{{see also|List of Major League Baseball retired numbers}}
&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-style:bold; font-size:120%; border:3px;&quot;
|-  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff;&quot;
|[[File:OsRetired4.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Earl Weaver|Earl&lt;br /&gt;Weaver]]&lt;br /&gt;Manager&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 1982&lt;/font&gt;
|[[File:OsRetired5.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Brooks Robinson|Brooks&lt;br /&gt;Robinson]]&lt;br /&gt;3B&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 1977&lt;/font&gt;
|[[File:OsRetired8.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Cal Ripken, Jr.|Cal&lt;br /&gt;Ripken, Jr.]]&lt;br /&gt;SS, 3B&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 2001&lt;/font&gt;
|[[File:OsRetired20.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Frank Robinson|Frank&lt;br /&gt;Robinson]]&lt;br /&gt;RF, Mgr&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 1972&lt;/font&gt;
|[[File:OsRetired22.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Jim Palmer|Jim&lt;br /&gt;Palmer]]&lt;br /&gt;P&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 1985&lt;/font&gt;
|[[File:OsRetired33.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Eddie Murray|Eddie&lt;br /&gt;Murray]]&lt;br /&gt;1B&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 1998&lt;/font&gt;
|[[File:OsRetired42.PNG|95px|]]&lt;br /&gt;'''[[Jackie Robinson|Jackie&lt;br /&gt;Robinson]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2B&lt;br /&gt;&lt;font size=1&gt;Retired 1997&lt;/font&gt;
|}
&lt;/center&gt;
'''Note:''' [[Cal Ripken, Sr.]]'s number 7 and [[Elrod Hendricks]]' number 44 have not been retired, but a moratorium has been placed on them and they have not been issued by the team since their deaths.

&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;''Jackie Robinson's number 42 is retired throughout Major League Baseball''

==Current roster==
{{Baltimore Orioles roster}}

==Minor league affiliates==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Level
! Team
! League
! Location
|-
| ''AAA''
| [[Norfolk Tides]]
| [[International League]]
| [[Norfolk, Virginia|Norfolk, VA]]
|-
| ''AA''
| [[Bowie Baysox]]
| [[Eastern League (U.S. baseball)|Eastern League]]
| [[Bowie, Maryland|Bowie, MD]]
|-
| ''High-A''
| [[Frederick Keys]]
| [[Carolina League]]
| [[Frederick, Maryland|Frederick, MD]]
|-
| ''Low-A''
| [[Delmarva Shorebirds]]
| [[South Atlantic League]]
| [[Salisbury, Maryland|Salisbury, MD]]
|-
|''Short Season A''
| [[Aberdeen IronBirds]]
| [[New York-Penn League]]
| [[Aberdeen, Maryland|Aberdeen, MD]]
|-
|rowspan=3|''Rookie''
| [[Gulf Coast League Orioles|GCL Orioles]]
| [[Gulf Coast League]]
| [[Sarasota, Florida|Sarasota, FL]]
|-
| [[Dominican Summer Orioles|DSL Orioles]]
| [[Dominican Summer League]]
| [[Dominican Republic]]
|}

==Franchise records and award winners==
{{main|Baltimore Orioles team records|List of Baltimore Orioles awards}}

===Season records===
* Highest batting average: .340, [[Melvin Mora]] (2004)
* Most games: 163, [[Brooks Robinson]] (1961, 1964) and [[Cal Ripken]] (1996)
* Most runs: 132, [[Roberto Alomar]] (1996)
* Most hits: 214, [[Miguel Tejada]] (2006)
* Highest slugging %: .646, [[Jim Gentile]] (1961)
* Most doubles: 56, [[Brian Roberts]] (2009)
* Most triples: 12, [[Paul Blair (baseball)|Paul Blair]] (1967)
* Most home runs: 50, [[Brady Anderson]] (1996)
* Most RBIs: 150, [[Miguel Tejada]] (2004)
* Most stolen bases: 57, [[Luis Aparicio]] (1964)
* Most wins: 25, [[Steve Stone (baseball)|Steve Stone]] (1980)
* Lowest ERA: 1.95, [[Dave McNally]] (1968)
* Strikeouts: 221, [[Erik Bedard]] (2007)
* Complete games: 25, [[Jim Palmer]] (1975)
* Saves: 45, [[Randy Myers]] (1997)

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* {{MLBTeam|Baltimore|Orioles|BAL}}
* [http://www.baltimoresun.com/sports/baseball/bal-sp.os5001aug01,0,2972162.story Waldman, Ed. &quot;Sold! Angelos scored with '93 home run,&quot; ''The Baltimore Sun'', August 1, 2004.]
* {{Whmc stl photodb|keywords=browns|title=St. Louis Browns}}

==Bibliography==
* Bready, James H. ''The Home Team''. 4th ed. Baltimore: 1984.
* Eisenberg, John. ''From 33rd Street to Camden Yards''. New York: Contemporary Books, 2001.
* Hawkins, John C. ''This Date in Baltimore Orioles &amp; St. Louis Browns History''. Briarcliff Manor, NY: Stein &amp; Day, 1983.
* Miller, James Edward. ''The Baseball Business''. Chapel Hill, NC: The University of North Carolina Press, 1990.
* Patterson, Ted. ''The Baltimore Orioles''. Dallas: Taylor Publishing Co., 1994.

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach|ach}}
{{succession box | title=World Series Champions | years=[[1966 World Series|1966]]&lt;br/&gt;[[1970 World Series|1970]]&lt;br/&gt;[[1983 World Series|1983]] | before=[[Los Angeles Dodgers]]&lt;br/&gt;[[New York Mets]]&lt;br/&gt;[[St. Louis Cardinals]] | after=[[St. Louis Cardinals]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Pittsburgh Pirates]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Detroit Tigers]]
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Baltimore Orioles}}
{{Navboxes | titlestyle=background:#000000; color:#FB4F14; | list1=&lt;/span&gt;
{{MLB Orioles franchise}}
{{MLB}}
{{Orioles Retired Numbers}}
{{Navboxes | title=[[World Series]] Championship Navigation Boxes | list=
{{1966 Baltimore Orioles}}
{{1970 Baltimore Orioles}}
{{1983 Baltimore Orioles}}
}}
{{Maryland Sports}}
{{Baltimore}}
{{Grapefruit League}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Baltimore Orioles}}
[[Category:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball teams]]
[[Category:Professional baseball teams in Maryland]]
[[Category:Sports clubs established in 1894]]
[[Category:Bankruptcy in the United States]]
[[Category:Fictional passerine birds]]

[[ca:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[cs:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[da:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[de:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[es:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[fr:Orioles de Baltimore]]
[[ko:볼티모어 오리올스]]
[[id:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[it:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[he:בולטימור אוריולס]]
[[hu:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[nl:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[ja:ボルチモア・オリオールズ]]
[[pl:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[pt:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[ru:Балтимор Ориолс]]
[[simple:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[fi:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[sv:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[tr:Baltimore Orioles]]
[[uk:Балтимор Оріолс]]
[[zh:巴尔的摩金莺]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
