<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="434157" ns="0" title="University of Regina"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|50|24|55.99|N|104|35|16.63|W|display=title|type:edu}}
{{Infobox University
|name            ='''University of Regina'''
|image           =[[File:UofRegina Logo.svg|230px]]
|motto           = As one who serves
|established     = Regina College, 1911
University of Regina, 1974 
|type            = [[Public university|Public]]
|endowment       =$25.9 million
|president       =Dr. Vianne Timmons
|chancellor      =Dr. William F. Ready
|staff           =1,283
|students        =12,270&lt;ref name=&quot;AUCCJul2011&quot;/&gt;
|undergrad       =10,740
|postgrad        =1,530
|profess         =
|city            =[[Regina, Saskatchewan|Regina]]
|state          = [[Saskatchewan]]
|country        = [[Canada]]
|campus          = Urban
|colours         = {{color box|#00502F}} Green&lt;br /&gt; {{color box|#FDD017}} Gold
|free_label      =Newspaper
|free            =[[The Carillon]]
|former_names    = Regina College (1911-1961)
University of Saskatchewan (1961-1974)
|mascot          = Reggie the Cougar and Ram-page
|athletics       =[[Regina Cougars]] and [[Regina Rams]]
|nickname        =
|affiliations    =[[L'Association des universités de la francophonie canadienne|AUFC]], [[Canadian Association of Research Libraries|CARL‎]], [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport|CIS]], [[Canadian University Society for Intercollegiate Debate|CUSID]], [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|UACC]], [[Canada West Universities Athletic Association|CWUAA]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]], [[Canadian University Press|CUP]]
|footnotes       =
|website         =[http://www.uregina.ca/ www.uregina.ca]
|coor            =
|logo            =
}}
The '''University of Regina''' is a [[public university|public]] [[research university]] located in [[Regina, Saskatchewan]], [[Canada]]. Founded in 1911 as a private denominational high school of the [[Methodist Church of Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;later the [[United Church of Canada]], at the time there were also in Regina denominational private schools operated by the [[Anglican Church of Canada|Church of England]], the [[Roman Catholic]] Sisters of Our Lady of the Missions and [[Jesuit Order]], and some few years later, the Lutherans. ''Vide infra''.&lt;/ref&gt; it began an association with the [[University of Saskatchewan]] as a junior college in 1925, and was disaffiliated by the Church and fully ceded to the University in 1934; in 1961 it attained degree-granting status as the Regina Campus of the [[University of Saskatchewan]]. It became an autonomous university in 1974.&lt;ref&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/university_of_regina.html James M. Pitsula, &quot;University of Regina,&quot; ''Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan''.] Retrieved 19 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The enabling legislation is ''An Act Respecting the University of Regina, Chapter U-5.'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.qp.gov.sk.ca/publications/index.cfm?fuseaction=details&amp;c=2036&amp;id=2  ''An Act Respecting the University of Regina, Chapter U-5''&lt;/ref&gt; The University of Regina has an enrolment of over 12,000 full and part-time students&lt;ref name=&quot;AUCCJul2011&quot;&gt;http://www.aucc.ca/publications/stats/enrol_e.html Retrieved July 9, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;. The university's student newspaper, The Carillon, is a member of [[Canadian University Press|CUP]].

The University of Regina is well-reputed for having a focus on experiential learning&lt;ref&gt;Guide to Canadian Universities (2011 Edition). Maclean's 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and offers internships, professional placements and practicums in addition to cooperative education placements in 41 programs&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/servicesForStudents/ugcal_103.shtml#coopProgram&lt;/ref&gt;. This experiential learning and career-preparation focus was further highlighted when, in 2009 the University of Regina launched the UR Guarantee Program, a unique program guaranteeing participating students a successful career launch after graduation. Partnership agreements with provincial crown corporations, government departments and private corporations have helped the University of Regina both place students in work experience opportunities and help gain employment post-study.

==History==
===Origins===
[[Image:Regina College at 16th Avenue (now College Avenue) and Broad Street, 1913. Building under construction..jpg|left|thumb|225px|Regina College, designed by James Henry Puntin (architect), under construction on 16th Avenue (now College Avenue), 1913]]

The University of Regina is a non-denominational university, which grew out of Regina College, founded in 1911.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0008257 Nancy Brown Foulds, &quot;University of Regina,&quot; ''The Canadian Encyclopedia''] Retrieved 18 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In direct response to the award of the University of Saskatchewan to Saskatoon rather than Regina, the [[Methodist Church of Canada]] established Regina College in 1911 on College Avenue in Regina, Saskatchewan, starting with an enrollment of 27 students; it was adjacent to the now long-defunct St Chad's College (a theological seminary for the training of Anglican clergy) and Qu'Appelle Diocesan School, also on College Avenue. James Henry Puntin (architect) designed several buildings on campus including: Regina Methodist College (1910); East &amp; West Towers (1914); Ladies Residence (1914); Gymnasium (1925); Power Plant (1927); Music &amp; Arts Building (1928). &lt;ref&gt; http://dictionaryofarchitectsincanada.org/architects/view/622 James Henry Puntin (architect) &lt;/ref&gt;

In 1934 Regina College became part of the University of Saskatchewan.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;Foulds, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[University of Saskatchewan]] a single, public provincial university created in 1907 was modeled on the American state university, with an emphasis on extension work and applied research.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0008242 P. Anisef and J. Lennards, &quot;University,&quot; ''The Encyclopedia of Canada''.] Retrieved 18 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The governance was modeled on the ''University of Toronto Act'', 1906 which established a bicameral system of university government consisting of a senate (faculty), responsible for academic policy, and a board of governors (citizens) exercising exclusive control over financial policy and having formal authority in all other matters. The president, appointed by the board, was to provide a link between the 2 bodies and to perform institutional leadership.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;Anicef and Lennards, op. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early part of this century, professional education expanded beyond the traditional fields of theology, law and medicine. Graduate training based on the German-inspired American model of specialized course work and the completion of a research thesis was introduced.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

Regina College commenced a formal association with the University of Saskatchewan as a junior college offering accredited university courses in 1925&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/university_of_regina.html Jim Pitsula, &quot;University of Regina,&quot; in Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan.] Retrieved 14 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; though continuing as a denominational college of the now-[[United Church of Canada]], the successor to the Methodist Church. Regina College continued as a Junior College until 1959, when it received full degree granting status as a second campus of the University of Saskatchewan.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; 

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Normal school.jpg|right|thumb|Regina Normal School, 1914.]] --&gt;Methodist patrons of Regina College contributed amply to its development: [[Francis Nicholson Darke]], a pioneer of early Regina, financed the building of Darke Hall, the concert venue of the old Regina College Campus, built in 1929. (See [[Regina's historic buildings and precincts]].) However, in 1934, the United Church was financially hard pressed by the [[Great Depression]] and in any case its history from the great [[Egerton Ryerson]] of urgent advocacy of universal free public education made its involvement in private schools anomalous. It accordingly fully surrendered Regina College to the [[University of Saskatchewan]]. Regina College and its successor Regina Campus of the University of Saskatchewan and University of Regina have — possibly unawares — retained the Methodist motto &quot;as one who serves&quot; (Luke 22.27). 

The policy of university education initiated in the 1960s responded to population pressure and the belief that higher education was a key to social justice and economic productivity for individuals and for society.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; In 1961 the College was renamed the University of Saskatchewan, Regina Campus. In 1974 it became the independent University of Regina. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title='Fitzhenry and Whiteside Book of Canadian Facts and Dates'  |last=Pound |first=Richard W. |publisher=Fitzhenry and Whiteside |year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The original United Church affiliation is, however, symbolically commemorated in the convocation furniture, resumed by the university for ceremonial use from one of the last downtown United Churches, which closed in the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;It was Carmichael United Church in the East End of Regina, which closed in 1996, whose chancel furniture is now used by the University of Regina at formal ceremonies.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Junior college of the University of Saskatchewan===
[[File:Regina College Building.JPG|thumb||left|Regina College Building]]
With the transfer of control to the University of Saskatchewan the range of courses offered was somewhat broadened. During this period [[Campion College, Regina|Campion]] and Luther Colleges, which maintained private high schools in Regina under the auspices respectively of the Roman Catholic and Lutheran churches, also retained junior college status in affiliation with the University of Saskatchewan; the Anglican Church, whose St Chad's College had operated a theological training facility in Regina, meanwhile merged with Emmanuel College in Saskatoon and withdrew from tertiary education in Regina. 

The upgrading process accelerated in 1961 when the college was granted full-degree granting status as the Regina Campus of the University of Saskatchewan and students completing degrees at Regina Campus were granted degrees of the University of Saskatchewan.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

===Regina Campus===
[[Image:UofR campus.jpg|thumb||right|300px|U of R campus as seen from the Saskatchewan Science Centre. From left: La Residence, Administration-Humanities Building, North Residence, Archer Library.]]
The arts and sciences programs evolved with the growth of Regina Campus, which held its first [[convocation]] in 1965. The new campus was begun in 1966 to the southwest of the old campus whose buildings, however, remain in use: the old Girls' Residence is now used by the Regina Conservatory of Music; the Normal School, having at various times housed not only the teacher-training facility that is now the University's Department of Education but the [[Royal Saskatchewan Museum|Saskatchewan Museum of Natural History]], war-training facilities during World War II when it was temporarily resumed by the federal crown and latterly the University's Fine Arts Department, is now the [[Canada-Saskatchewan Soundstage]]. The original design of Regina Campus (as of [[Wascana Centre]] itself) and its initial buildings, in a stark concrete [[modernist]] style, were by [[Minoru Yamasaki]],&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; the architect of the original [[World Trade Center]] in New York. 

Yamasaki's original vision was that:
:[the buildings] would be located close enough together that passage between them in the winter could be provided through connecting corridors in the &quot;podium&quot; or first [ground] floor of all buildings in the central instructional complex. Each podium would be larger than the remaining floors of the buildings rising above it, thereby creating the impression of separate buildings rising from a common base. The buildings would be constructed around sunken, landscaped courts which would be accessible visually and physically by generous windows and doors from the corridors located along these enclosing walls.&lt;ref&gt;Fletcher, Tom. &quot;The Work of Minoru Yamasaki,&quot; ''New York Architecture Images and Notes''. Internet: http://www.nyc-architecture.com/GON/GON001G.htm.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:University of Regina Library viewed from the Oval.jpg|left|thumb|300px|Dr. John Archer Library, Main Campus]]Yamaski's vision of the new university campus as part of the wider [[Wascana Centre]] involved the eventual [[Saskatchewan Centre of the Arts]] as an adjacent convocation hall, which informed its placement on the south shore of Wascana Lake, some distance from the city centre, to the serious detriment of the city centre at a time when issues of inner-urban decay did not yet appear likely to affect Regina. {{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} It was not immediately apparent that the development of the new campus would quickly stall: after an initial spate of development in the mid-60s and early 70s, building substantially lapsed for some years.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} The [[Dr. John Archer Library]], the main library of the university, was opened in 1967, one of the original three buildings of the new campus (the others being the classroom and laboratory buildings), and named after [[John Hall Archer|Dr. John Archer]] in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;It was the first building on the new campus to be named after an individual, Darke Hall on the Regina College campus having been named in 1929 after Francis Nicholson Darke, an early benefactor of Regina College.&lt;/ref&gt; Further building has been substantially in accord with Yamasaki's vision, notwithstanding some controversy over the years as to the suitability of its austere style for the featureless Regina plain; by 1972 with the demolition of Yamasaki's 1955 [[Pruitt–Igoe]] housing project in St. Louis, Missouri — such demolition being considered by some to be the beginning of postmodern architecture — Yamasaki's modernist aesthetic was already somewhat passé in the view of many architects.

[[Campion College, Regina|Campion College]] and later Luther College, which like Regina College had also been denominational junior colleges affiliated with the University of Saskatchewan, established &quot;federated college&quot; status on the model of [[Victoria University in the University of Toronto|Victoria]], [[University of Trinity College|Trinity]], [[University of St. Michael's College|St Michael's]] and [[University College, University of Toronto|University]] Colleges at the [[University of Toronto]] (and ultimately the collegiate system of [[Oxford]] and [[Cambridge]]) and built facilities at the new campus. (St Chad's, a fourth denominational college in Regina, operated by the [[Anglican Church of Canada]] on the former Anglican diocesan property on College Avenue immediately to the east of Regina College, merged with Emmanuel College on the Saskatoon campus in 1964 and, after a period of continuing to operate its private girls' high school closed its Regina facilities in 1970.&lt;ref&gt;Neither the United nor the Anglican Church now maintains any continuing official involvement with the University despite their pioneering work in tertiary education in Regina. After the Anglicans closed their tertiary facility St Chad's girls' school continued to be run by the Sisters of St John the Divine, a Canadian Anglican religious order. During this period the Canadian Roman Catholic religious order the Sisters of Our Lady of the Missions also closed their Marian High School and Sacred Heart Academy as did the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]] their Campion High School when they moved their tertiary educational activities in Regina to their new Campion College on the new campus.&lt;/ref&gt;) 

As with other rapidly expanding universities in the late 1960s, the Regina Campus of the University of Saskatchewan was able to benefit from a significant outflow of academics from American universities during the [[Vietnam War]] era of U.S. history at a time when the supply of Canadian PhDs could not yet keep up with demand {{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}; it was labelled by a deputy commissioner of the [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police]] (RCMP, the Canadian federal police force) as one of the three most radical campuses in Canada {{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}, along with Burnaby's [[Simon Fraser University]] and Sir George Williams University (now part of [[Concordia University (Montreal)|Concordia University]]) in Montreal.

===University of Regina===
[[Image:Riddell Building, New Campus.jpg|thumb|left|387px|The Terrace, Regina Research Park. South Residence and La Résidence visible above.]]Disappointment as to the non-fulfilment of plans by the University of Saskatchewan to situate various faculties at the Regina rather than the Saskatoon campus and a range of other issues of discontent led to the formation of a Faculty Council with the goal of making the campus an autonomous institution {{Citation needed|date=December 2008}}; a Royal Commission under the chairmanship of former Chief Justice of Saskatchewan and Supreme Court of Canada Justice [[Emmett Matthew Hall|Emmett Hall]] found there to be &quot;two campus groups warring within the bosom of a single university.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;Pitsula.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result the University of Regina was established as an independent institution on 1 July 1974&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; and the first University of Regina degrees were conferred at the spring convocation in 1975 — although its development was slow until the 21st century, when a renewed burst of building and expansion occurred. That being said, numerous of the university's faculties are significantly smaller in the 21st century than they were in the 1970s as priorities have shifted from liberal arts to vocational training. 

The original Regina College buildings on College Avenue continue in use; the old Girls' Residence is now the Regina Conservatory of Music; in 1997 the Fine Arts Department moved from the old Normal School building to the new W.A. Riddell Centre&lt;ref&gt;Pitsula&lt;/ref&gt; and the Normal School was substantially renovated to become the [[Canada-Saskatchewan Soundstage]].

In the summer of 2005 the University of Regina hosted the [[2005 Canada Games]]. Many events took place in the newly completed state-of-the-art Centre for [[Kinesiology]], Health and Sport. The administration of the games proceeded from the University of Regina Students Union offices and various other locations across campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/canadagames/newsletter/sept04.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Lab, classroom and library buildings.jpg|right|thumb|275px|Classroom Building, Archer Library, and Research &amp; Innovation Centre (under construction), viewed from South Residence]]The campus has experienced a recent spurt of growth and expansion, having been static for some two decades after the construction of the Language Institute at the end of the 1970s. Since the late 1990s, several new buildings have been added including the Dr. William A. Riddell Centre; the North and South Residences; the Centre for Kinesiology, Health &amp; Sport; [[First Nations University of Canada]] and Research &amp; Innovation Centre; along with a significant expansion of the Education Building. The building of the North and South Residences also involved a significant redevelopment of the landscaping of the campus around a new oval&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uregina.ca/campusgrowth/projects/completed/academicgreen.shtml &quot;The Dr Lloyd Barber Academic Green.&quot;] Retrieved 17 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; as an aesthetic and community hub of campus. Future plans include construction on the east side of the Ring Road. The goal is to accommodate an enrolment of 25,000.  

The [[Regina Research Park]] is located immediately adjacent to the main campus and conducts many of its initiatives in conjunction with university departments. In recent years, local benefactors have substantially endowed the university with scholarships and chairs in various disciplines.&lt;ref&gt;For example, the Dr. Morris C. Shumiatcher Graduate Fellowship in English, endowed by Morris Shumiatcher's widow Dr. Jacqui Shumiatcher in 2006.[http://www.uregina.ca/campaign/news/Shumiatcher%20donates%20$225,000%20to%20support%20English%20graduate%20students_Oct5_06.shtml Shumiatcher donates $225,000 to support English graduate students] Retrieved 14 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Federated Colleges, Regional Colleges and Associates==
The University has three federated colleges:
* [[Campion College, Regina|Campion College]]
* [[First Nations University of Canada]]
* [[Luther College (Saskatchewan)|Luther College]]&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.luthercollege.edu/ Luther College website]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:First Nations University, University of Regina.jpg|left|thumb|275px|First Nations University of Canada]]Campion and Luther colleges had been high schools offering junior college courses accredited by the University of Saskatchewan on the same basis as the old Regina College, out of premises located elsewhere in Regina. [[Campion College, Regina|Campion College]] became a junior college of the University of Saskatchewan like Regina College in 1923, later severed that association in favour of one with St Boniface College in Manitoba, and returned to federated college status with the University of Saskatchewan in 1964. It built its facilities on the new Regina Campus in 1968&lt;ref&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/campion_college_university_of_regina.html Joanne Kozlowski, Kenneth McGovern, &quot;Campion College,&quot; ''The Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan''] retrieved 12 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and subsequently vacated its original high school premises on 23rd Avenue. Its Regina Campus building was designed in accordance with [[Minoru Yamasaki]]'s original plan for the campus, with a &quot;podium,&quot; contemplated as eventually being joined with the campus-wide ground floor. Thus far this has not occurred and Campion's building remains isolated.

Luther College opened its building on the new Regina Campus in 1971 but continues to operate its high school on Royal Street,&lt;ref&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/luther_college_university_of_regina.html &quot;Luther College,&quot; ''Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan''], retrieved 12 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; on the site of the first [[Government House (Saskatchewan)|Government House of the North-West Territories]]. By this point the original Yamasaki plan for the campus was being reconsidered and the Luther College complex is isolated to the east of the principal campus buildings, though it is connected by an all-weather corridor via Campion College.

The [[First Nations University of Canada]] grew out of the Saskatchewan Indian Federated College, established in 1976, which was an original foundation at the University of Regina. Its new building to the east of Luther College replaced its original facilities to the west of College West and was opened by [[Prince Edward, Earl of Wessex|Prince Edward]] in 2003 and visited by the Queen in 2005 when she installed a commemorative stone to symbolise the special relationship between Canada's First Nations and the sovereign.

The United Church, having vacated tertiary education in Regina when it ceded Regina College to the University of Saskatchewan,&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/university_of_regina.html &quot;University of Regina,&quot; Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan.] Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Anglican Church, having removed its St Chad's College from Regina to Saskatoon,&lt;ref&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/anglican_church_of_canada.html &quot;Anglican Church of Canada,&quot; ''Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan''.] Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; do not maintain any presence at the University of Regina. The Christian and Missionary Alliance Church formerly maintained the residential Canadian Bible College in Regina and offered some of its courses for accreditation with the University of Regina but was unable to obtain university status in Saskatchewan and vacated to Calgary in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/canadian_bible_college__canadian_theological_seminary.html &quot;Canadian Bible College/Canadian Theological Seminary,&quot; Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan.] Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, the University of Regina has two &quot;Affiliated Colleges:&quot; The [[Gabriel Dumont Institute]] and the [[Saskatchewan Institute of Applied Science and Technology]] (SIAST).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/affiliatedAssociatedColleges/index.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; The university also has two &quot;Associated Colleges:&quot; [[Athol Murray College of Notre Dame]] and [[Briercrest College and Seminary]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/affiliatedAssociatedColleges/index.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; These institutions offer collaborative, associated, or articulated programs in conjunction with the University of Regina.

Saskatchewan's network of Regional Colleges further extend program delivery across the province. The University of Regina offers courses through Cumberland College, Northlands College, North West Regional College, Great Plains College, Carlton Trail Regional College, Parkland College, and the South East Regional College.

==Faculties==
The University of Regina has ten faculties and one school that offer a variety of programs at the certificate, diploma, undergraduate and graduate degree levels.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Faculty
! Overview
! Degrees Offered
|-
| Faculty of Arts
| The U of R's largest faculty and is home to the social sciences, languages, and humanities.&lt;ref&gt;http://arts.uregina.ca/general-public&lt;/ref&gt; The Faculty of Arts offers the country's only Police Studies program.
| Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Human Justice, Bachelor of Fracophone Studies, Bachelor of Health Studies (jointly with Kinesiology), Bachelor of Journalism&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/glossary/ugcal_410.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Business Administration&lt;ref name=&quot;uregina.ca&quot;&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/orp/FactBrochure/FactsBrochure2009.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| The Faculty encompasses both the Paul J. Hill School of Business (undergraduate programs&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/admin/academic/business_school/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;) and the Kenneth Levene Graduate School of Business (graduate degree/certificate programs&lt;ref&gt;http://levene.uregina.ca/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| Bachelor of (Business) Administration,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; (Executive) Master of Business Administration, Master of Human Resource Management, Master of Administration&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gradstudies/calendar/programs_overview.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Education
| Offers undergraduate and graduate-level level for primary and secondary-level teaching. One of the U of R's quota (competitive entry) programs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/admissionTransfer/ugcal_13.shtml#facultyEducation&lt;/ref&gt;
| Bachelor of Education, Bachelor of Human Resource Development, Bachelor of Dance, Bachelor of Music Education (jointly with Fine Arts),&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Master of (Adult) Education, Master of Human Resource Development&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Engineering &amp; Applied Science
| Engineering programs offered: Electronic Systems Engineering, Environmental Systems Engineering, Industrial Systems Engineering, Petroleum Systems Engineering, and Software Systems Engineering.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cemf.ca/Engineering/UniversityList.htm Canadian Engineering Memorial Foundation - University List&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Students may add a specialization in the following disciplines: Communications Engineering, Controls, Digital Design, Power Electronics, Manufacturing Engineering, and Process Engineering.
| Bachelor of Applied Science,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Master of Applied Science, Master of Engineering&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Fine Arts
| Home to the U of R's fine and performing arts and art study programs in the arts of visual art, theatre, music, and media production and studies.
| Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Fine Arts, Bachelor of Music, Bachelor of Music Education (jointly with Education),&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Master of Arts, Master of Fine Arts, Master of Music&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Graduate Studies &amp; Research
| Offers masters and doctoral study programs in conjunction with all other faculties.
| Various masters and PhD/doctoral programs&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Kinesiology &amp; Health Studies
| 
| Bachelor of Kinesiology, Bachelor of Sport &amp; Recreation Studies, Bachelor of Health Studies (jointly with Arts),&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Master of Science&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Nursing&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/facultyofNursing/index.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
| Accepting its first intake in Fall 2011, offers a degree-track nursing program jointly with [[SIAST]].
| Bachelor of Science in Nursing&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Science
| Departments and programs include geology, biology, physics, math and statistics, chemistry and biochemistry, computer science, and actuarial science.
| Bachelor of Science, Bachelor of Medical Imaging, Bachelor of Medical Laboratory Science,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Master of Arts, Master of Science&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Faculty of Social Work
| With primary campuses in Regina and Saskatoon, and satellite campuses across Saskatchewan &lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/facultyofSocialWork/ugcal_346.shtml#campuses&lt;/ref&gt; offers practice and research based programs of study.
| Bachelor of Social Work, Bachelor of Indian Social Work,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Master of Social Work, Master of Aboriginal Social Work&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
|}

The University of Regina also has one school, the [[Johnson-Shoyama Graduate School of Public Policy]]. It delivers Masters and Doctoral programs in conjunction with the [[University of Saskatchewan]]. 

The University of Regina also offers a number of pre-professional transfer programs with other universities and professional colleges: Agriculture and Bioresources, Chiropractic, Dentistry, Law, Medicine, Nutrition, Occupational Therapy, Optometry, Pharmacy, Physical Therapy, and Veterinary Medicine.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uregina.ca/gencal/ugcal/transferPrograms/index.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

===Co-operative Education===
The University of Regina is the one of the universities with [[co-operative education]] in Saskatchewan.  Many of the university undergraduate students are enrolled in the co-op program with the highest percentage being in the faculties of science and engineering. The Faculty of Arts offers an innovative internship program for its undergraduate students.

==Residences==
[[Image:College West.jpg|thumb|left|237px|College West viewed from the South Residence, across the Barber Academic Green.]]Regina College originally housed male and female student residences which were converted to academic use when the College became affiliated with the University of Saskatchewan in 1934. (The old Girls' Residence now accommodates the Regina Conservatory of Music.) 

The Main (Wascana) Campus has residence space for about 1,200 students on-campus. Each bedroom is single-occupant, but many spaces on campus are designed to facilitate double occupancy, increasing capacity if required to address high demand without building additional residence space. The University of Regina residences have enlivened campus life from the somewhat bleak atmosphere of its founding days:
*College West, the first on-campus residential accommodation, constructed in 1972.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; Offers apartment-style residence living. The building also houses classrooms, academic and business offices and The Bookstore.
*La Résidence in the Language Institute, gives priority to francophone students and those studying international languages. Offers dorm-style residence living. It maintains a French-speaking student atmosphere.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;
*North and South Residences, completed in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uregina.ca/campusgrowth/ University of Regina Campus Growth: Residence Buildings.] Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Two symmetrical, twelve-floor towers housing apartment, studio, and dorm-style residences. These buildings form the centre pinnacle for the campus and also house both External/Alumni Relations and the Faculty of Graduate Studies &amp; Research.
*[[Luther College (Saskatchewan)|Luther College Residences]], part of Luther College (the University's second federated college and second on-campus residence), opened in 1971.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; Luther offers more traditional dorm-style residences with some shared facilities.

The University of Regina internally designates a significant portion of spaces annually to incoming (first year) students in an effort to facilitate the growing number of non-resident (international, out-of-province, rural) students choosing to live on-campus.

==Notable faculty and alumni==
{{Expand list|date=January 2010}}.
* [[Lee Ward, PhD.]], noted political scientist
* [[Gordon Barnhart]], [[SOM]], author, former secretary of the House of Commons, and current Lieutenant Governor of Saskatchewan
* [[Gordon Asmundson]], professor of psychology, Fellow of Royal Society of Canada.
* [[Roy Bonisteel]], [[Laurier LaPierre]], [[Knowlton Nash]], Bill Cunningham, [[Val Sears]], [[Myrna Kostash]], [[Walter Stewart (journalist)|Walter Stewart]], [[John Sawatsky]] and [[Maggie Siggins]], ''inter alios'', have been visiting professors in the School of Journalism.
* [[Robert Boyer (artist)|Bob Boyer]] (1948–2004), visual artist, Professor and Head of Indian Fine Arts, SIFC.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0010115&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lorne Calvert]], Premier of Saskatchewan (2001–2007)
* [[Sylvain Charlebois]], food and agriculture expert
* [[Jason Clermont]], Canadian Football Player
* [[Saros Cowasjee]], novelist, short story writer, critic, anthologist, screenwriter&lt;ref&gt;''Goodbye to Elsa'' (1974); ''Mulk Raj Anand: Coolie : an assessment'' (1976); ''Nude therapy'' (1978); ''So Many Freedoms: Major Fiction of Mulk-Raj Anand '' (1978); ''The last of the maharajas: A screen play based on Mulk Raj Anand's Private life of an Indian Prince'' (1980); ''Modern Indian Fiction'' (1981); ''Suffer little children'' (1982); ''Stories from the Raj'' (1983); ''Women Writers of the Raj '' (1990); ''Studies in Indian and Anglo-Indian Fiction'' (1995); ''The Assistant Professor'' (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jonathan Denis]], Alberta MLA and Minister of Housing and Urban Affairs (1997)
* [[Shadia Drury|Shadia B. Drury]], professor of political science and philosophy; [[Canada Research Chair]] in [[Social justice|Social Justice]]
* [[Chris Getzlaf]], Canadian Football Player
* [[Joan Givner]], biographer, novelist and short story writer&lt;ref&gt;''Half Known Lives'' (2000); ''In the Garden of Henry James'' (1996); ''Scenes from Provincial Life'' (1991); ''Unfortunate Incidents'' (1988); ''Tentacles of Unreason'' (1985)); biographer (''Katherine Anne Porter: A life'' (1982) ''Mazo de la Roche: The Hidden Life'' (1989); essayist and memoirist (''Thirty-Four Ways of Looking at Jane Eyre'' (1998); ''The Self-Portrait of a Literary Biographer'' (1993); Room of One's Own (1992)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Glenda Goertzen]], children's author
* [[Ralph Goodale]], Member of Parliament, former Minister of Finance
* [[Thomas Hadjistavropoulos]], professor of psychology, RBC Senior Research Fellow, former president Canadian Psychological Association, Fellow of Canadian Academy of Health Sciences
* [[John Hewson]], former Australian federal opposition leader
* [[Gregory Marchildon]], Executive Director, The [[Romanow Report]]
* [[Imp labs|Charity Marsh]], assistant professor of Media Production and Studies, Canada Research Chair in Interactive Media and Performance
* [[Ken Mitchell]], novelist and playwright&lt;ref&gt;''Stones of the Dalai Lama'' (1993); ''The plainsman'' (1992); ''Rebels in time: three plays'' (1991); ''Witches and idiots: poems'' (1990); ''The shipbuilder'' (1990); ''Through the Nan Da Gate: a China journey'' (1986); ''Gone the burning sun'' (1984); ''Chautauqua girl: a musical show for young people'' (1982); ''The great cultural revolution: a play'' (1980); ''The con man: a novel'' (1979); ''Davin, the politician: a play'' (c1979); ''Everybody gets something here: stories'' (1977); ''The Meadowlark Connection: A Saskatchewan thriller'' (1975); ''Wandering Rafferty: a novel'' (1972)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Zenon Pylyshyn]], Rutgers University, leading authority in cognitive science, Ph.D. (1963) University of Saskatchewan (Regina Campus)
* [[Jon Ryan]], CFL and NFL punter
* [[Ann Saddlemyer]], literary critic, Master of [[Massey College]], [[University of Toronto]]
* [[Christine Selinger]], Canadian paracanoe gold medalist
* [[Jordan Sisco]] CFL wide receiver
* [[Dione Taylor]] (BFA), a noted jazz singer
* [[Guy Vanderhaeghe]], novelist&lt;ref&gt;''My Present Age'' (1984);  ''Homesick'' (1989); ''The Englishman's Boy'' (1996); ''The Last Crossing'' (2001)); short story writer (''Man Descending'' (1982); ''The Trouble With Heroes'' (1983); ''Things As They Are?'' (1992)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Senator [[Pamela Wallin]], former national broadcaster and Canadian Consul in New York

==Sports==
[[Image:UofR Athletic.jpg|thumb|300px|U of R Athletic Wall of Excellence]]
The University of Regina is a member of [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]] and fields men and women's teams in various sports. Its teams bear the name &quot;[[Regina Cougars|Cougars]]&quot; in all sports, except the [[Regina Rams]], which were originally a community junior football team competing in PJFC football without affiliation with the University, and who joined University ranks in 1999 as a member of the Canada West Conference of Canadian Interuniversity Sport. The University sports teams are: the Regina Rams (football); men's basketball; women's basketball; men's volleyball; women's volleyball; men's hockey; women's hockey; women's soccer; track and field; swimming; cross country; wrestling; and cheerleading. In the summer of [[2005 Canada Games|2005]], the University hosted the [[Canada Summer Games]].

==Media==
The university's [[student newspaper]] is ''[[The Carillon]]''. It for many years was an organ of radical student dissent and in the 60s and 70s frequently had a very high community profile as its editorial postures occasioned vigorous denunciation by university administration figures and in the conservative general press. As student mores in subsequent generations have become less disputatious the ''Carillon'' has evolved into a less political paper which currently is a somewhat conventional newsletter of campus affairs.

The university is home to the School of Journalism, which was one of the first established in western Canada. The School publishes a student periodical, ''The Crow'', and hosts the annual Minifie lecture, in honour of one of Canada's most illustrious journalists, James M. Minifie (1900–1974).

The University of Regina does not have its own [[campus radio]] station, although the independent [[community radio]] station [[CJTR-FM]] actively solicits volunteers among the school's student body.

The school launched [http://www2.uregina.ca/yourblog Your Official University of Regina blog (YOURblog)] in October 2010, a place where the U of R community and the public can read, discuss and share ideas and experiences with each other and the connection between campus and the world. YOURblog strives to be interesting, informative and above all collaborative. In that spirit, the site and its content are shaped by site visitors’ [http://www2.uregina.ca/yourblog/?page_id=19 input and participation].

The University of Regina is home to the Interactive Media and Performance Labs ([[IMP Labs]]), which includes programming for the student body as well as members of the community. The Labs have been particularly recognized through the IMP Labs Hip Hop Project with [[Scott Collegiate]]. The directors of this program, Dr. Charity Marsh and Chris Beingessner, received the Lieutenant Governor's Arts Awards for Arts and Learning through the [[Saskatchewan Arts Board]].

==Aboriginal==

The University of Regina provides services to Aboriginal people in more remote communities. The University of Regina’s SUNTEP program was developed in partnership with specific Aboriginal communities to meet specific needs within Aboriginal communities. Aboriginal Elders are present on campus at University of Regina to provide social supports. Through the University of Regina’s Kâspohtamatâtân Mentorship Program Aboriginal students act as role models to younger students still in their home communities. The University of Regina has established an Aboriginal Career Centre to assist with the transition to a fulfilling career.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uwinnipeg.ca/index/cms-filesystem-action?file=pdfs/conferences/2007/aboriginal-rt-spring-report.pdf. Michael Mendelson and Alex Usher, &quot;The Aboriginal University Education Roundtable,&quot; May 24, 2007, The University of Winnipeg.] Retrieved 18 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
*[[Regina Public Library]]
*[[List of agricultural universities and colleges]]
*[[List of universities with industrial engineering faculty]]
*[[Higher education in Saskatchewan]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* James Pitsula 'As One Who Serves: The Making Of The University Of Regina' (Montreal:  McGill-Queen's University Press, June 1, 2006)
* James Pitsula. 'An Act of Faith: The Early Years of Regina College.' (Regina: Canadian Plains Research Center, 1988).

==External links==
{{Commons}}
* {{Official website|http://www.uregina.ca/}}
* [http://www.uregina.ca/urprofile.shtml University of Regina profile with ample photos]
* [http://www2.uregina.ca/yourblog/ Your Official University of Regina blog (YOURblog)]
* [http://www.uregina.ca/residences/ University of Regina Residence Services]
* [http://www.uregina.ca/esl English as a Second Language Program, University of Regina]
* [http://scratchpost.cc.uregina.ca/gspp/index.html The Graduate School of Public Policy]
* [http://www.usask.ca/english/EnglishStudentBooks.htm Books by Former University of Regina Department of English students]
* [http://www.innovationplace.com/ReginaResearchPark/HTML/about.htm Regina Research Park]
* [http://www.uregina.ca/home/web/pdf/CampusMap.pdf Campus Map]
* [http://www.ccee.ca/ Canadian Centre for Environmental Education]

{{Sask Uni}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Regina, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Regina| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Saskatchewan]]
[[Category:Canadian Interuniversity Sport football teams]]
[[Category:Association of Commonwealth Universities]]
[[Category:Consortium for North American Higher Education Collaboration]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1974]]

[[fr:Université de Régina]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยรีไจนา]]
[[uk:Реджайнський університет]]
[[zh:里贾纳大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
