<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="434166" ns="0" title="Rosy Cross"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=August 2011}}

[[Image:Rose Cross Lamen.svg|thumb|300px|The Rosy Cross Lamen as worn by Adepts in the Rosae Rubae et Aureae Crucis, the inner order of the [[Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]].]]
The '''Rosy Cross''' (also called '''Rose Cross''' and '''''Rose Croix''''') is a symbol largely associated with the semi-mythical [[Christian Rosenkreuz]], [[Alchemy|alchemist]] and founder of the [[Rosicrucianism|Rosicrucian Order]].&lt;ref&gt;[[German language]] original: 'Die Bruderschaft des Ordens der Rosenkreuzer', [[Fama Fraternitatis]], 1614 [in circulation ca. 1610]; 'Bruderschaft Rosenkreuz', [[Confessio Fraternitatis]], 1615&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Max Heindel]], ''[http://rosicrucianzine.tripod.com/christian_rosenkreuz.htm Christian Rosenkreuz and the Order of Rosicrucians]'', 1909 [1908&amp;ndash;1919]&lt;/ref&gt; The Rose Cross is said to be a [[cross]] with a [[white]] [[rose]] at its centre&lt;ref&gt;[[Albert Pike]] (1872). ''[[Morals and Dogma of the Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite of Freemasonry]], [http://www.phoenixmasonry.org/morals_and_dogma/knight_kadosh.htm XXX: Knight Kadosh]''. p.&amp;nbsp;822.&lt;br&gt;&quot;Commentaries and studies have been multiplied upon the ''Divine Comedy'', the work of DANTE, and yet no one, so far as we know, has pointed out its especial character. (...) His Hell is but a negative Purgatory. His Heaven is composed of a series of Kabalistic circles, divided by a cross, like the Pantacle of Ezekiel. In the centre of this cross blooms a rose, and we see the symbol of the Adepts of the Rose-Croix for the first time publicly expounded and almost categorically explained.&quot;
:[[Dante Alighieri]], ''[[The Divine Comedy]]'', [[wikisource:en:The Divine Comedy/Paradiso/Canto XXXI|Paradiso, Canto XXXI]], ''circa'' 1308&amp;ndash;1321:&lt;br&gt;&quot;In fashion then as of a snow-white rose&lt;br&gt;Displayed itself to me the saintly host,&lt;br&gt;Whom Christ in his own blood had made his bride,&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and symbolizes the teachings of a tradition formed within the [[Christian]] tenets{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}:

{{quote|What think you, loving people, and how seem you affected, seeing that you now understand and know, that we acknowledge ourselves truly and sincerely to profess Christ, condemn the Pope, addict ourselves to the true Philosophy, lead a Christian life, and daily call, entreat and invite many more unto our Fraternity, unto whom the same Light of God likewise appeareth?&lt;ref&gt;in ''[[Confessio Fraternitatis]]'', the second [[Rosicrucian Manifestos|Rosicrucian Manifesto]] printed in 1615&lt;/ref&gt;}}

It has several meanings, depending on the source. Some groups, such as the [[Ancient and Mystical Order Rosae Crucis]], from a non-sectarian or non-religious view, suggest that the rosy cross predates [[Christianity]], where &quot;the cross represents the human body and the rose represents the individual's unfolding consciousness.&lt;ref&gt;[[AMORC]]. ''[http://www.rosicrucian.org/about/mastery/mastery08history.html Our Traditional and Chronological History].''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[The Rosicrucian Fellowship]] and kindred groups of rosicrucianists, promulgating an [[Esoteric Christian]] viewpoint, hold that the Rosicrucian Brotherhood was founded in the early 14th century, or between the 13th and 14th centuries,&lt;ref&gt;[[Rudolf Steiner|Steiner, Rudolf]] (founder of [[Anthroposophy]]). [http://books.google.pt/books?id=MLjh70BLqLUC ''Christian Rosenkreutz&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; The Mystery, Teaching and Mission of a Master''].&lt;/ref&gt; as an [[Invisible College]] of mystic sages, by a highly evolved entity having the symbolic name of [[Christian Rosenkreuz]] in order &quot;to prepare a new phase of the Christian religion to be used during the [[Age of Aquarius|coming age]] now at hand, for as the world and man evolve so also must religion change&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/pamen010.htm The Rosicrucian Interpretation of Christianity] by The [[Rosicrucian Fellowship]].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Paracelsus]], who was called the &quot;Luther of Medicine&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Debus, Allen G. (1993). ''[http://www.nlm.nih.gov/hmd/pdf/paracelsus.pdf ''Paracelsus and the Medical Revolution of the Renaissance&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; A 500th Anniversary Celebration''].  [[National Library of Medicine]].  p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; describes these mystics sages as &quot;persons who have been exalted (verzueckt) to God, and who have remained in that state of exaltation, and have not died (...) nobody knew what became of them, and yet they remained on the earth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;cited by [[Franz Hartmann]] in ''[http://books.google.pt/books?id=zBB4EmRiyqQC Life &amp; Prophecies of Paracelsus (1493&amp;ndash;1541)]'', p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; Modern groups and researchers of the &quot;Rosicrucian Enlightenment&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Frances Yates|Yates, Frances A.]] (1972), ''The Rosicrucian Enlightenment'', London&lt;/ref&gt; suggest that there is much evidence that the Rosicrucian Order not only has made herself known in the early 17th century through the [[Rosicrucian Manifestos]], but has been active since the beginning of the [[Renaissance]] period, not only as an [[Hermetism|hermetic]] Order, but also through forerunners&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[genius]]es of the [[western world]], sometimes also known to be [[Freemasonry|Freemasons]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; in the literary,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/pamen041.htm &quot;Shakespeare&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; The Lay Bible&quot;].  [[Rosicrucian Fellowship]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Manly Palmer Hall|Hall, Manly Palmer]] (1928). ''The Secret Teachings of All Ages: [http://www.phoenixmasonry.org/secret_teachings_of_all_ages/bacon_shakspere_and_the_roscrucians.htm Bacon, Shakespeare, and the Rosicrucians]'', pp. 165&amp;ndash;168.&lt;/ref&gt; cultural, ethical, political, religious and scientific fields.

In the late 18th century, [[Karl von Eckartshausen]], a German [[Christian mystic]], describes the true Adepts of the Rose Cross in the following terms: &quot;These sages, whose number is small, are children of light, and are opposed to darkness. They dislike mystification and secrecy; they are open and frank, have nothing to do with secret societies and with external ceremonies. They possess a spiritual temple, in which God is presiding&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Karl von Eckartshausen|von Eckartshausen, Karl]] (1790).  ''Aufschlüsse über Magie''. [Explanations Concerning Magic.] München [Munich], 1790; cited by [[Franz Hartmann]] in [http://books.google.pt/books?id=zBB4EmRiyqQC ''Life &amp; Prophecies of Paracelsus (1493&amp;ndash;1541)''], p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the early 20th century, [[Max Heindel]], a Rosicrucian [[Initiation#Religious and other spiritual initiations|Initiate]], emphasizes that the roots of the Brothers of the Rose Cross, immersed in the [[western mystery tradition]], are almost impossible to be traced as &quot;theirs is a work which aims to encourage the [[spiritual evolution|evolution]] of humanity, they have labored far back into antiquity--under one guise or another&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/magen103.htm The Brothers of the Rose Cross]'' by The Rosicrucian Fellowship&lt;/ref&gt;

It has also been suggested that the rose represents silence while the cross signifies &quot;salvation, to which the Society of the Rose-Cross devoted itself by teaching mankind the love of God and the beauty of brotherhood, with all that they implied.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Baxter, James. ''[http://svmmvmbonvm.org/crc/bacon.htm Sir Francis Bacon and The Rosy Cross]''&lt;/ref&gt; Others saw the Rosy Cross as a symbol of the human process of reproduction elevated to the spiritual: &quot;The fundamental symbols of the Rosicrucians were the rose and the cross; the rose female and the cross male, both universal phallic [...] As generation is the key to material existence, it is natural that the Rosicrucians should adopt as its characteristic symbols those exemplifying the reproductive processes. As regeneration is the key to spiritual existence, they therefore founded their symbolism upon the rose and the cross, which typify the redemption of man through the union of his lower temporal nature with his higher eternal nature.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Hall, 1928, p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is further a symbol of the [[Philosopher's Stone]], the ultimate product of the alchemist.&lt;ref&gt;[[Max Heindel|Heindel, Max]].  [http://www.rosicrucian.com/frc/frceng01.htm ''Freemasonry and Catholicism''] (Part VII). ISBN 0-911274-04-9. [http://www.archive.org/details/freemasonryandca017137mbp www2]. [http://www.archive.org/details/freemasonaryandc001552mbp www3].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Freemasonry and the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn==
The Rosy Cross is also a symbol found in some [[Rosicrucian#Modern groups|Masonic Christian]] bodies&lt;ref&gt;See image: [[:Image:Bijou fm 18eme.jpg|The &quot;18° Knight of the Rose Croix&quot; degree of the Scottish Rite]].&lt;/ref&gt; and employed by individuals and groups formed during the last centuries for the study of Rosicrucianism and allied subjects,&lt;ref&gt;See image:  [[:Image:Rosy Cross of the Golden Dawn.png|Rosy Cross lamen of the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]].&lt;/ref&gt; but derived from the adoption of a red rose.

===Freemasonry===
{{main|Freemasonry}}
Within the Southern Jurisdiction of the [[Scottish Rite]] [[Masonic appendant bodies|concordant body]] of [[Freemasonry]], the Eighteenth Degree is specifically concerned with the rose cross and confers the title of &quot;Knight Rose Croix&quot;. Of one version of the degree, [[Albert Pike]] wrote in 1871,

{{quote|The Degree of Rose Cross teaches three things;—the unity, immutability and goodness of God; the immortality of the Soul; and the ultimate defeat and extinction of evil and wrong and sorrow, by a Redeemer or Messiah, yet to come, if he has not already appeared.&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot;&gt;Pike (1871), pp. 290&amp;ndash;291.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

He goes on to give an explanation of what he believes to be the symbolism of the Rose Cross in that degree:

{{quote|But [the cross's] peculiar meaning in this Degree, is that given to it by the Ancient Egyptians. ''[[Thoth]]'' or ''[[Ptah|Phtha]]'' is represented on the oldest monuments carrying in his hand the ''Crux Ansata'', or ''Ankh'', (a Tau cross, with a ring or circle over it). [...] It was the hieroglyphic for ''life'', and with a triangle prefixed meant ''life-giving''. To us therefore it is the symbol of ''Life''—of that life that emanated from the Deity, and of that Eternal Life for which we all hope; through our faith in God's infinite goodness.

The ROSE, was anciently sacred to [[Aurora (mythology)|Aurora]] and the Sun. It is a symbol of ''Dawn,'' of the resurrection of Light and the renewal of life, and therefore of the dawn of the first day, and more particularly of the resurrection: and the Cross and Rose together are therefore hieroglyphically to be read, ''the Dawn of Eternal Life'' which all Nations have hoped for by the advent of a Redeemer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pike&quot; /&gt;}}

===Golden Dawn===
{{main|Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn}}
The Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn made use of the rosy cross as well, including 'The Ritual of the Rose Cross,&quot; designed for spiritual protection and as preparation for meditation. Based on the [[Rosicrucian]] symbolism of the Red Rose and the Cross of Gold, it is also a key symbol of the Golden Dawn's Second Order. According to Regardie, the Golden Dawn rosy cross contains attributes for the Elements, Planets, [[Zodiac]], [[Hebrew alphabet]], alchemical principles, the [[hexagram]] and [[pentagram]], the sephiroth of the Tree of Life, and the formula of INRI. On the back side of the rosy cross is inscribed the motto of the Zelator Adeptus Minor at the bottom, &quot;The master Jesus Christ, God and Man&quot; between four Maltese crosses, and in the center, written in Latin, &quot;Blessed be the Lord our God who hath given us the Symbol Signum.&quot;

Regardie says of the rosy cross in ''The Golden Dawn'':

{{quote|Established in 2004 the temple of &quot;The Rose-Cross&quot; is a Lamen or badge synthesizing a vast concourse of ideas, representing in a single emblem the Great Work itself—the harmonious reconciliation in one symbol of diverse and apparently contradictory concepts, the reconciliation of divinity and manhood. It is a highly important symbol to be worn over the heart during every important operation. It is a glyph, in one sense, of the higher Genius to whose knowledge and conversation the student is eternally aspiring. In the Rituals it is described as the Key of Sigils and Rituals.}}

====Symbolism of the Golden Dawn Rosy Cross====
This lamen is a complete synthesis of the masculine, positive, or rainbow scale of color attributions, which is also called the Scale of the King. The four arms of the cross belong to the four elements and are colored accordingly. The white portion belongs to the Holy Spirit and the planets.

The petals of the rose refer to the twenty-two paths on the Tree of Life and the Twenty-two letters of the Hebrew alphabet. It is the cross in Tiphareth, the receptacle and the center of the forces of the [[Sephiroth (Kabbalah)|Sephiroth]] and the paths. The extreme center of the rose is white, the reflected spiritual brightness of [[Kether]], bearing upon it the Red Rose of Five Petals and the Golden Cross of Six Squares; four green rays issue from around the angles of the cross. Upon the white portion of the lamen, below the rose, is placed the hexagram, with the planets.

Around the pentagrams, which are placed one upon each elemental colored arm, are drawn the symbols of the spirit and the four elements. Upon each of the floriated  (the arms) of the cross are arranged the three alchemical principles of sulfur, salt, and mercury. The white rays issuing from behind the rose at the inner angles between the arms of the cross are the rays of the divine light issuing and coruscating from the reflected light of Kether in its center; and the letters and symbols on them refer to the analysis of the Key Word - [[I.N.R.I.]]

==Aleister Crowley and Ordo Templi Orientis==
{{main|Thelema|Thelemic mysticism}}
The symbol of the rosy cross played a substantial role within the system of [[Thelema]] as developed by [[Aleister Crowley]]. In a cosmological context, the rose is [[Nuit]], the infinitely expanded goddess of the night sky, and the cross is [[Hadit]], the ultimately contracted atomic point. For Crowley, it was the job of the adept to identify with the appropriate symbol so to experience the mystical conjunction of opposites, which leads to attainment. In this sense, the rose cross is a grand symbol of the [[Great Work]]:

{{quote|The [[Tau]] and the circle together make one form of the Rosy Cross, the uniting of subject and object which is the Great Work, and which is symbolized sometimes as this cross and circle, sometimes as the [[Lingam]]-[[Yoni]], sometimes as the [[Ankh]] or Crux Ansata, sometimes by the Spire and Nave of a church or temple, and sometimes as a marriage feast, mystic marriage, spiritual marriage, &quot;chymical nuptials,&quot; and in a hundred other ways. Whatever the form chosen, it is the symbol of the Great Work.&lt;ref&gt;Crowley, Aleister. ''Magick, Book 4''.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Crowley also makes clear that this process is reflected in the sexual act as well:

{{quote|So we need not be surprised if the Unity of Subject and Object in Consciousness which is [[samādhi]], the uniting of the Bride and the Lamb which is Heaven, the uniting of the Magus and the god which is Evocation, the uniting of the Man and his [[Holy Guardian Angel]] which is the seal upon the work of the Adeptus Minor, is symbolized by the geometrical unity of the circle and the square, the arithmetical unity of the 5 and the 6, and (for more universality of comprehension) the uniting of the Lingam and the Yoni, the Cross and the Rose.  For as in earth-life the sexual ecstasy is the loss of self in the Beloved, the creation of a third consciousness transcending its parents, which is again reflected into matter as a child; so, immeasurably higher, upon the Plane of Spirit, Subject and Object join to disappear, leaving a transcendent unity.  This third is ecstasy and death; as below, so above.&lt;ref&gt;Crowley, Aleister. ''The Equinox'' I(4), &quot;The Big Stick&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The rosy cross is further symbolic of the grade of Adeptus Minor in the [[A.'.A.'.]], the [[Qabalah|Qabalistic]] sphere of [[Tiphareth]] on the [[Tree of Life]], the magical formula [[INRI]], and the concepts of Light (LVX) and Life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scarletwoman.org/docs/docs_lege.html De Lege Libellum]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ordo Templi Orientis===
{{main|Ordo Templi Orientis}}
The rose cross also has a place in the system of Ordo Templi Orientis. It is associated with the Fifth Degree, the title of which is &quot;Sovereign Prince Rose-Croix, and Knight of the Pelican and Eagle.&quot; Of it, Crowley writes in &quot;An Intimation with Reference to the Constitution of the Order&quot;:

{{quote|The members of the Fifth Degree are responsible for all that concerns the Social welfare of the Order. This grade is symbolically that of beauty and harmony; it is the natural stopping-place of the majority of men and women; for to proceed farther, as will appear, involves renunciation of the sternest kind. Here then is all joy, peace, well-being on all planes; the Sovereign Prince Rose Croix is attached equally to the higher and the lower, and forms a natural link between them. Yet let him look to it that his eyes are set on high!&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| volume = III
| issue = 1
| author = Crowley, Aleister
| title = Liber CXCIV OTO&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash;An Intimation with Reference to the Constitution of the Order
| journal = [[The Equinox]]
| accessdate = March 8, 2011
| date = 1919
| url = http://hermetic.com/crowley/equinox/iii/i/eq0301239.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Fellowship of the Rosy Cross==
[[Image:The Rose Cross.jpg|upright|thumb|'''The Winged Self''' symbol of the Rosy Cross consists of a cross of [[light]], with a white [[rose]] at the centre.]]
The Fellowship of the Rosy Cross was a [[Christian]] [[mystical]] organization established by [[Arthur Edward Waite]] in [[England]] in 1915. It developed out of the breakdown of [[Isis-Urania Temple#Independent and Rectified Rite of the Golden Dawn|Independent and Rectified Rite of the Golden Dawn]]. It was based on Waite's complicated ideas and its rites reflected his interest in the history of the [[Rosicrucian Order]], [[Freemasonry]], and Christian mystical teachings through the ages. Most of its members were Freemasons or theosophists. One of its most noted members was the novelist [[Charles Williams (UK writer)|Charles Williams]] who was a member from 1917 to at least 1928 and possibly later. There were plans to establish a branch in the [[United States]] but they appear never to have been fulfilled. The order ended with Waite's death in 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert, Robert A (1983). ''The Golden Dawn: Twilight of the Magicians''.  [[Aquarian Press]].  pp. 76&amp;ndash;77. ISBN 0-85030-278-1.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Arthur Edward Waite]] wrote also a book entitled ''[[The Brotherhood of the Rosy Cross]]'' which presents the brotherhood as a Christian order dating from the Middle Ages.

==Modern forms==
{{main|Rosicrucian Fellowship|Lectorium Rosicrucianum|Esoteric Christianity|Ancient and Mystical Order Rosae Crucis}}
One modern form of the ''Rosie Cross'' is found in a [[Rosicrucian#Modern groups|Rosicrucian Christian]] symbol that places a crown of [[red]] roses ennobling a [[white]] rose at the centre of the cross; radiating behind is the golden five-pointed star, an allusion also to 'the Five Points of Fellowship'.&lt;ref&gt;See image [[:Image:Rosicrucian fellowship-emblem2.jpg|The Rosicrucian Fellowship (emblem)]].&lt;/ref&gt; It is the symbol of [[Rosicrucian Fellowship|the fraternity]] that has prepared a [[Mount Ecclesia|great lodge]] for the [[Brethren of Purity|Brethren]] to be gathered.&lt;ref&gt;See image:  [[:Image:MountEcclesia 002entr.jpg|The Ecclesia (portico)]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Another version used by the [[Ancient and Mystical Order Rosae Crucis]] suggests that &quot;together, the rose and cross represent the experiences and challenges of a thoughtful life well lived.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;AMORC. [http://www.rosicrucian.org/about/mastery/mastery08history.html Our Traditional and Chronological History].&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal box|Mythology|Religion}}
* [[Sir Francis Bacon]]
{{clear}}

==References==
{{cleanup-link rot|date=August 2011}}
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.hermetic.com/browe-archive/achad/misc/inri.htm I. N. R. I.—De Mysteriis Rosae Rubeae et Aureae Crucis], by Charles Stansfeld Jones

[[Category:Cross symbols]]
[[Category:Magic (paranormal)]]
[[Category:Masonic symbolism]]
[[Category:Rosicrucianism]]
[[Category:Thelema]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
