<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4344236" ns="0" title="Saint Mary&#039;s University (Halifax)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name            ='''Saint Mary's University'''
|native_name     =
|latin_name      =
|image           =[[Image:Saint Mary's University (Halifax) crest.png]]
|motto           =''Age Quod Agis'' ([[Latin language|Latin]]:What you do, do well)
|established     =1802
|type            =Public
|endowment       =[[$]]16.9 million
|staff           =393
|faculty         =246
|president       =[[Dr. J. Colin Dodds]]
|principal       =
|rector          =
|chancellor      =[[Robert P. Kelly]]
|vice_chancellor = Dr. J. Colin Dodds
|dean            =
|head_label      =
|head            =
|students        =7,281&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atlanticuniversities.ca/Download.aspx?serverfn=./files/drm/9cb318ea-60f6-41d8-8913-4ff9e09b1852.pdf&amp;downloadfn=Full%20+%20Part-time%202009.pdf&amp;contenttype=|title=Full-time plus Part-time Enrollment|date=October 14, 2009|publisher=Association of Atlantic Universities|accessdate=December 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       =
|postgrad        =
|doctoral        =89
|city            =[[Halifax Urban Area|Halifax, Nova Scotia]]
|Province        =[[Nova Scotia]]
|country         =Canada
|campus          =[[Urbanization|Urban]]
|free_label      =
|free            =
|colors          =[[Maroon (color)|Maroon]] {{color box|#800000}} and [[White (color)|White]]  {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
|colours         =
|mascot          =[[Husky]]
|nickname        =[[Saint Mary's Huskies|Huskies]]
|affiliation     =None
|affiliations    =[[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[International Association of Universities|IAU]], [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport|CIS]], [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]], [[Canadian University Society for Intercollegiate Debate|CUSID]], [[Atlantic University Sport|AUS]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]]
|website         =http://www.smu.ca/
|logo            =[[Image:SaintMarysU Logo.png|center|220px]]
}}

{{Coord|44|37|54.07|N|63|34|47.09|W|region:CA_type:landmark|display=title}}
'''Saint Mary's University''' (SMU) is located in [[Halifax (former city), Nova Scotia|Halifax]], [[Nova Scotia]] Canada. The school is best known{{by whom|date=May 2011}} for having nationally lead programs in Business, Astronomy and International Development Studies{{citation needed|date=May 2011}} as well, one of the best [[Canadian football|football]] and Men's hockey programs in Canada {{citation needed|date=May 2011}}.

The campus is situated in Halifax's South End and covers approximately {{convert|40|acre|ha|0}}.

== History ==

Founded in 1802 by Reverend Edmund Burke, Saint Mary's is the second oldest English-speaking and first Roman Catholic initiated university in Canada. With meagre resources Burke initiated instruction for young men at Glebe House, located on the corner of Halifax’s Spring Garden Road and Barrington Street.

The [[Roman Catholic]] church founded St. Mary's University at [[City of Halifax|Halifax, Nova Scotia]] in 1840.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext04/tlctd10.txt The Project Gutenberg] EBook #6466 of 'The Intellectual Development of the Canadian People, A historical review' by John George Bourinot, House of Commons, Ottawa, February 17, 1881&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1841 the Nova Scotia Legislature bestowed the degree granting charter to Saint Mary’s and eleven years later granted the University formal legal status. After a great deal of uncertainty, in 1913 the Christian Brothers of Ireland were asked by the Archdiocese of Halifax to direct the college and academic programs. With this change of leadership the University's reputation thrived as a Liberal Arts Institution and expanded its undergraduate programs, with the most notable being the Faculty of Commerce in 1934 (now known as the Sobey School of Business), which was the first of its kind in Canada. In 1940 the Upper Province of the Society of Jesus (the [[Jesuits]]) was invited to succeed the Christian Brothers as both administrators and faculty.

The next 30 years would see the University flourish under the Jesuit supervision, with such advancements as the formal recognition of the &quot;college&quot; as a University in 1952 and purchasing the first computer in Atlantic Canada (a [[Royal McBee]] [[LGP-30]]) in 1959. In 1970 the Jesuits formally incorporated the University under the &quot;Acts of Incorporation&quot; which gave all administrative and academic duties to the Board of Governors and [[Saint Mary's University Academic Senate|Academic Senate]]. Saint Mary's University was established by the Saint Mary's University Act, 1970.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smu.ca/ug/documents/UniversityActDec2007.pdf Saint Mary's University Act]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Saint Marys HFX.jpg|thumb|left|Main entrance]]Since then the University has continued expansion of its academic programs with the most notable being the offerings of doctoral level studies in Astronomy and Business and the accreditation of the business school with the AACSB ([[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business]]). At the same time the University has expanded its campus facilities with noted additions of the Burke-Gaffney Observatory in the 1970s and the Sobey Building in 1998.

In 1992, the Faculty of Commerce was renamed the [[Sobey School of Business]], after [[Frank H. Sobey]], founder of [[Sobeys]].

In 2001, SMU's Huskies were the first Atlantic Canadian university team to advance to the world finals in the [[ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest]] World Finals.

In March 2005, Saint Mary’s started the “Science Building Renewal Project” which was estimated to cost $25.5 million. This project is part of the larger project the “University’s Strategic Directions and Academic Plan” which was developed by meeting with Students, Faculty and local Citizens in order to meet both the needs of the University and local community over the next decade. The first stage of the project focused on:
* Modernization and expansion of the Science Facility's resources
* Renew the architectural, mechanical and electrical infrastructures of the Science building and its surroundings
* Provide additional office and research space to every faculty member
* Improve lab layout for hands-on teaching purposes
* Integrate flawlessly with future projects in both function and appearance

The University completed construction of the Atrium and Global Commons project in late 2009. The three-storey $17.5 million dollar complex links the Science Centre, the Burke Building and the Patrick Power Library. The space features a common area, theater style classrooms, offices and study spaces. The project also features advanced green environmental technologies, has fully integrated hard and Wi-Fi systems, a food outlet and a three storey &quot;living wall&quot;.

The 62-year old McNally Building is undergoing a $27 million dollar renewal thanks in large part to the Canadian governments Infrastructure Renewal Programme. Estimated to be completed by March 2011, most of the interior of the 4 floor, 4 wing complex is being rebuilt.

Construction of the new Homburg Centre for Health and Wellness began in October 2010. This complex will house new space for community health and wellness activities and become the new home for the Centre for the Study of Sport and Health. The $8 million project was funded by a donation from real estate developer and manager Richard Homburg and the University's capital campaign.

== Faculties ==
Saint Mary's comprises four faculties:
{{Div col}}
* [http://arts.smu.ca Arts]
Dean: Dr. Esther Enns
* [http://sobey.smu.ca Sobey School of Business]
Dean: Dr. David Wicks
* [http://science.smu.ca/ Science]
Dean: Dr. Steven Smith
* [http://fgsr.smu.ca/ Graduate Studies and Research]
Dean: Dr. Kevin Vessey
 {{Div col end}}

==Campus Life==
===Huskies Football===
{{main|Saint Mary's Huskies}}
The Huskies won back-to-back [[Vanier Cup|Canadian University Football Championships]] (2001 &amp; 2002), the third university to do so (after [[Manitoba Bisons|Manitoba]] and [[Western Ontario Mustangs|Western]]).

===Huskie Hockey===

In 2010, the men Huskies won their first CIS University Hockey Cup by defeating the Alberta Golden Bears 3-2 in overtime.

===Saint Mary's University Students' Association===
The Saint Mary's University Students' Association (SMUSA) is the official representation of the students of Saint Mary's University. The association was incorporated in 1966, however, unofficially has represented students for many years previous. The Association main offices are located on the top floor of the student centre at the heart of campus.

SMUSA provides such services as a safe drive program, tutor database, online book exchange, health and dental plans and the Gorsebrook Lounge. SMUSA also operates many departments that help in the mission of serving students and making their lives at Saint Mary's the best possible. These departments include the volunteer department, events and programming, marketing and communications, the yearbook, the information desk and husky patrol.

The Saint Mary's University Students Association is represented federally by the [[Canadian Alliance of Student Associations]] and provincially by the [[Alliance of Nova Scotia Student Associations]].

==Notable alumni==
* [[Steve Armitage]], CBC Sportscaster
* [[Alan Abraham]], former Lieutenant Governor of Nova Scotia
* [[Noah Cantor]], Canadian Football League player
* [[Karen Casey]] (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Colchester North)
* [[Zach Churchill]], (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Yarmouth)
* [[Patrick H. Curran]], Chief Judge of the Provincial Court of Nova Scotia
* [[Chris d'Entremont]] (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Argyle)
* [[Wayne Gaudette]] (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Clare)
* [[Glenn Graham (fiddler)|Glenn Graham]], Celtic musician
* [[Paul Hollingsworth]] (CTV Atlantic and TSN Newscaster and Sportscaster)
* [[Peter J. Kelly]] (Mayor of Halifax, Nova Scotia)
* [[Robert P. Kelly]], [[Former CEO]] of the [[Bank of New York Mellon]]
* [[Becky Kent]] (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Cole Harbour – Eastern Passage)
* [[Joseph Phillip Kennedy]], Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Nova Scotia
* [[Steven Landry]], CEO of [[DaimlerChrysler]] Canada
* [[William Linton]], [[CFO]] of [[Rogers Communications]]
* [[Terry Mercer]] (Canadian Government, Senator – Northend Halifax)
* [[Boris Mirtchev]], CEO of Hamachi Restaurants in Halifax, NS
* [[Wilfred Moore]] (Canadian Government, Senator – Stanhope St./Bluenose)
* [[Steve Morley]] (CFL Player and Former NFL Player)
* [[William Njoku]], Basketball player drafted in the 2nd round of the 1994 NBA Draft who played professionally for 10 years for various clubs in Europe.
* [[Gerald Regan]] (Nova Scotia Government, Former Premier)
* [[Mat Whynott]] (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Hammonds Plains – Upper Sackville)
* [[John MacDonnell]] (Nova Scotia Government, MLA – Hants East)

== Saint Mary's University Academic Senate ==
The '''Saint Mary's University Academic Senate''' is the part of a [[bicameral]] university governance structure responsible for academic decisions at the University. It is paired with a [[board of governors]] responsible for administrative and financial decisions.

The Senate has ten ex-officio members: the President, Vice-Presidents, Deans, Registrar, Director of Student Services, Director of Continuing Education, and University Librarian.  Fifteen faculty members are elected to three year terms and five students are elected by the general university population to one year terms.

=== Function ===
The academic senate is governed by the [[Saint Mary's University Act]]. It is subject to the powers of the university's Board and is responsible for the educational policy of the University in addition to:
* May create, maintain and discontinue such faculties, departments, schools or institutes and establish such chairs as it may determine and may fix the duties of those employed therein
* May recommend to the Board the affiliation or discontinuance of the affiliation of or with other universities
* May determine courses of study, admission standards, qualifications for diplomas, certificates and degrees, examinations, scholarships and bursaries and may issue university calendars and other official publications
* Shall be responsible for the library
* Shall be responsible for student discipline
* May create such committees as it deems necessary or useful
* May make regulations governing the matters that are assigned to it by this Section

== See also ==
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
{{Div col}}
* [[Canadian government scientific research organizations]]
* [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]]
* [[Canadian industrial research and development organizations]]
* [[Canadian university scientific research organizations]]
* [[Higher education in Nova Scotia]]
* [[Huskies Stadium]]
* [[List of universities in Nova Scotia]]
* [[loyola Residence Tower]]
* [[Master of Management: Co-operatives and Credit Unions]]
* [[Saint Mary's Huskies]]
* [[Saint Mary's University Students' Association]]
 {{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.smu.ca/ Saint Mary's University]
* [http://www.smu.ca/academic/science/ap/bgo.html Burke-Gaffney Observatory]
* [http://www.smuhuskies.ca Saint Mary's University Huskies]
* [http://www.smusa.ca Saint Mary's University Students' Association]
* [http://www.smu.ca/registrar/calendar.html Saint Mary's University Academic Calendar]
* [http://www.smu.ca/administration/businessoffice/governance/SMUAct.pdf Saint Mary's University Act {{Dead link|date=July 2011}}]
* [http://www.smu.ca/administration/facman/sci.html Saint Mary's University Science Building Renewal Project]
* [http://www.smu.ca/administration/facman/atrium.html Saint Mary's University Atrium Project]
{{Commons}}
{{Universities in Canada}}
{{NS Uni}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in Nova Scotia]]
[[Category:Saint Mary's University (Halifax)|*]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1802]]
[[Category:2011 Canada Games]]

[[de:Saint Mary’s University Halifax]]
[[fr:Université Saint Mary]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
