<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4360630" ns="0" title="Winnie the Pooh (Disney)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About||the character|Winnie-the-Pooh|the book|Winnie-the-Pooh (book)|}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Winnie the Pooh'' (Disney)}}
{{Refimprove|date=December 2008}}

'''''Winnie the Pooh'''''  is an American [[The Walt Disney Company|Walt Disney Company]] [[Media franchise|franchise]], based on animated [[fictional characters]] who have been featured as part of the [[List of Disney characters|Disney character line-up]].  The ''Winnie the Pooh'' franchise is based on [[A. A. Milne]]'s books ''[[Winnie-the-Pooh]]'' (1926), and ''[[The House at Pooh Corner]]'' (1928).  

Disney's Pooh was originally voiced by [[Sterling Holloway]] in the three original Winnie the Pooh featurettes that were later used as segments to 1977's ''[[The Many Adventures of Winnie the Pooh]]''. [[Hal Smith (actor)|Hal Smith]] took over for the 1981 short ''[[Winnie the Pooh Discovers the Seasons]]'', and would mantain the role until [[Jim Cummings]] began voicing Pooh in ''[[The New Adventures of Winnie-the-Pooh]]'' (1988-1991). Cummings continues to voice Pooh (as well as [[Tigger]]) to this day.

==Adaptation and development by Disney==
In 1961, [[The Walt Disney Company|Walt Disney Productions]] licensed certain film and other rights to the characters, stories and trademarks from [[Stephen Slesinger|Stephen Slesinger, Inc.]], and The Estate of [[A. A. Milne]] and made a series of cartoon films about him.  The early cartoons were based on several of the original stories and the distinctive images made popular by Stephen Slesinger, Inc. during the 1930s through 1960s. Alongside the cartoon versions, which Disney adapted from Slesinger, Slesinger's simplified lines and pastel color adaptations of Shepard's classical drawings are now marketed under the description &quot;Classic Pooh&quot;.

In 1977, Disney released the animated feature ''[[The Many Adventures of Winnie the Pooh]]'', introducing a new character named Gopher, which Disney acknowledged by having Gopher proclaim, &quot;I'm not in the book, you know!&quot;  This movie features three segments that were originally released separately as featurettes: ''[[Winnie the Pooh and the Honey Tree]]'' (1966), ''[[Winnie the Pooh and the Blustery Day]]'' (1968), and ''[[Winnie the Pooh and Tigger Too!]]'' (1974). This feature version featured new bridging material and a new ending, as it had been [[Walt Disney]]'s original intention to make a feature.  In 1983, a fourth featurette, ''[[Winnie the Pooh and a Day for Eeyore]]'', was released.

The live-action series ''[[Welcome to Pooh Corner]]'' ran on the [[Disney Channel]] from 1983 to 1986. In 1988, Disney launched the animated series ''[[The New Adventures of Winnie the Pooh]]'', which aired from 1988 to 1991 with a total of 83 episodes.

In 2000, Disney released the full-length film ''[[The Tigger Movie]]'' in which the character of Tigger played the leading role. Due to its success, two more feature-length Pooh movies based on other characters were released to theaters: ''[[Piglet's Big Movie]]'' in 2003 and ''[[Pooh's Heffalump Movie]]'' in 2005.

In 2001, Playhouse Disney, along with Shadow Projects, produced a puppet TV series for preschoolers called, ''[[The Book of Pooh]]'', which aired from 2001 to 2003.

''[[Winnie the Pooh (film)|Winnie the Pooh]]'' was the next Pooh feature film to be released, on July 15, 2011.

Disney has also changed Pooh's world a bit, by changing the characters' clothes and adding many new characters, such as Gopher.

==Ownership controversy and drastic changes==
During his lifetime, Milne was liberal with his grant of rights. At times he licensed the same exclusive rights to more than one entity.

In the United States, Dutton publishers acquired exclusive volume publication rights and Stephen Slesinger, Inc., acquired sole and exclusive rights to virtually all uses outside of the Dutton books as well as rights to any sorts of future uses. Beginning in 1930 Stephen Slesinger created all of the distinctive and colorful images of Pooh outside of the books. Under license from Slesinger, Pooh made his debuts in radio, film, animation, children's theatre, advertising and a host of consumer products and services protected by trademark. Outside of the U.S. and Canada, Milne retained most of his literary copyright rights which he left to four beneficiaries of his trust:  The [[Garrick Club]], [[Westminster School]], [[The Royal Literary Fund]] and the A. A. Milne Family. By direction of Milne's will, the Pooh Properties Trust was formed. Mrs. Milne, trustee of the Milne Estate and Spencer Curtis Brown, Trustee, licensed certain exclusive film rights to Disney in 1961. Christopher Robin Milne sold his rights to the other copyright holders, in order to raise money to support his daughter, before his death in 1996.

Sometime around 2000, the Pooh Properties Trust licensed additional rights to Disney and accepted a buyout from of their claims to royalties as defined in a 1991 lawsuit brought by Stephen Slesinger, Inc. Although Slesinger's rights are arguably more valuable, the combined value paid by Disney to The Pooh Properties Trust is said to be approximately $300 million for Milne's portion of those rights.

To further minimize Disney's legal exposure to Slesinger, Disney paid money to the Pooh Properties attorneys and trusts to use the name of Clare Milne, daughter of Christopher Robin, in an attempt to terminate certain of the copyright rights of Stephen Slesinger Inc, in the wake of the [[Sonny Bono]] [[Copyright Term Extension Act]] of 1998. The district court found in favour of Stephen Slesinger, Inc., and as did the [[United States Court of Appeals|U.S. Court of Appeals]] for the Ninth Circuit.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seattlepi.com/national/1154AP_Scotus_Pooh.html&lt;/ref&gt; On Monday, June 26, 2006, the U.S. Supreme Court refused to hear the case, thus sustaining the Appeals Court ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/2006/LAW/06/26/scotus.pooh.ap/index.html }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2005, Disney announced that Pooh's friend and owner [[Christopher Robin]] would be replaced by a six-year-old &quot;tomboyish&quot; [[red hair|red-haired]] girl named [[List of Winnie-the-Pooh characters#Darby|Darby]] for the [[Disney Channel]] [[animated television series]], ''[[My Friends Tigger &amp; Pooh]]''. Christopher Robin appeared intermittently in the series.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1449283/ Winnie-the-Pooh (2011)] at [[Internet Movie Database]]

{{Winnie-the-Pooh}}
{{DisneyConsumer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Winnie The Pooh (Disney)}}
[[Category:Disney franchises]]
[[Category:Winnie-the-Pooh]]
[[Category:Kingdom Hearts characters]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
