<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="436657" ns="0" title="(What&#039;s the Story) Morning Glory?"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?''}}
{{Infobox album &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Albums --&gt;
| Name    = (What's the Story) Morning Glory?
| Type    = Studio album
| Artist   = [[Oasis (band)|Oasis]]
| Cover    = Oasis - (What's The Story) Morning Glory album cover.jpg
| Released  = 2 October 1995
| Recorded  = March 1995, May&amp;nbsp;– June 1995, [[Rockfield Studios]] in [[Monmouth]], Wales
| Mixed    = [[Miloco Studios]], London
| Genre    = [[Rock music|Rock]], [[Britpop]]
| Length   = 50:05
| Label    = [[Creation Records|Creation]]
| Producer  = [[Owen Morris]], [[Noel Gallagher]]
| Last album = ''[[Definitely Maybe]]''&lt;br /&gt;(1994)
| This album = '''''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?'''''&lt;br /&gt;(1995)
| Next album = ''[[Be Here Now (album)|Be Here Now]]''&lt;br /&gt;(1997)
| Misc    =
 {{Singles
 | Name      = (What's the Story) Morning Glory?
 | Type      = studio
 | single 1    = [[Some Might Say]]
 | single 1 date = 30 April 1995
 | single 2    = [[Roll with It (Oasis song)|Roll with It]]
 | single 2 date = 14 August 1995
 | single 3    = [[Morning Glory (Oasis song)|Morning Glory]]
 | single 3 date = 15 September 1995
 | single 4    = [[Wonderwall (song)|Wonderwall]]
 | single 4 date = 30 October 1995
 | single 5    = [[Don't Look Back in Anger]]
 | single 5 date = 19 February 1996
 | single 6    = [[Champagne Supernova]]
 | single 6 date = 13 May 1996
 }}
 }}

'''''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?''''' is the second [[studio album]] by the English [[Rock music|rock]] band [[Oasis (band)|Oasis]]. It was released on 2 October 1995 through [[Creation Records]]. The album was Oasis' most enduring commercial success, charting at number one in the UK (staying there for 10 weeks) and number four in the U.S. The album sold 346,000 copies in its first week in the UK&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p. 254&quot;&gt;Harris, p. 254&lt;/ref&gt; and has sold approximately 14 million copies worldwide,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oasisinet.com/NewsArticle.aspx?n=787 |title=Oasis News |publisher=Oasisinet.com |date= |accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/&lt;/ref&gt; although several sources estimate that it has sold in excess of 20 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Nick Pisa |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/worldnews/article-1250950/Brit-Pope-Vatican-puts-Oasis-albums-time.html |title=Brit Pope: Vatican puts Oasis in its top ten albums of all time &amp;#124; Mail Online |work=The Daily Mail |location=London |date=14 February 2010 |accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Simon Hattenstone |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2008/dec/06/noel-gallagher-oasis |title=Interview: Noel Gallagher talks Oasis past and present &amp;#124; Music |work=The Guardian |location=UK |date= 6 December 2008|accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of June 2009, it was the [[List_of_best-selling_albums_in_the_United_Kingdom|fourth biggest-selling album]] in UK chart history, with 4.4&amp;nbsp;million copies sold.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bpi.co.uk/assets/files/top%2040%20albums.pdf BPI Top 40 albums]&lt;/ref&gt; The album has gone 4× platinum (3.9 million copies) in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;English Beat&quot;&gt;Trust, Gary. [http://www.billboard.com/bbcom/thisday/ask-billboard-mariah-carey-abba-oasis-the-1003934063.story &quot;Ask Billboard: &quot;English Beat&quot;]. [[billboard.com]]. 23 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?resultpage=1&amp;table=SEARCH_RESULTS&amp;action=&amp;title=Morning%20Glory&amp;artist=Oasis&amp;format=&amp;debutLP=&amp;category=&amp;sex=&amp;releaseDate=&amp;requestNo=&amp;type=&amp;level=&amp;label=&amp;company=&amp;certificationDate=&amp;awardDescription=&amp;catalogNo=&amp;aSex=&amp;rec_id=&amp;charField=&amp;gold=&amp;platinum=&amp;multiPlat=&amp;level2=&amp;certDate=&amp;album=&amp;id=&amp;after=&amp;before=&amp;startMonth=1&amp;endMonth=1&amp;startYear=1958&amp;endYear=2009&amp;sort=Artist&amp;perPage=25
| title=Gold and Platinum Database Search
| accessdate=1 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Album singles &quot;[[Some Might Say]]&quot;, &quot;[[Roll with It (Oasis song)|Roll With It]]&quot;, &quot;[[Wonderwall (song)|Wonderwall]]&quot; and &quot;[[Don't Look Back in Anger]]&quot; were big hits in the UK, with &quot;Some Might Say&quot; and &quot;Don't Look Back in Anger&quot; both reaching the number one spot in the UK singles chart. &quot;Wonderwall&quot; and &quot;[[Champagne Supernova]]&quot; both went No. 1 on the U.S. [[Alternative Songs|Modern Rock Tracks]] chart, eventually being certified gold in the United States,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?resultpage=1&amp;table=SEARCH_RESULTS&amp;artist=Oasis&amp;startMonth=1&amp;endMonth=1&amp;startYear=1958&amp;endYear=2008&amp;sort=Artist&amp;perPage=25 RIAA - Gold &amp; Platinum - OASIS]&lt;/ref&gt; whilst &quot;Wonderwall&quot; also topped the Australian ARIA charts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Steffen Hung |url=http://australian-charts.com/showitem.asp?interpret=Oasis&amp;titel=Wonderwall&amp;cat=s |title=Oasis&amp;nbsp;— Wonderwall |publisher=australian-charts.com |date= |accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album won Best British Album at the 1996 [[Brit Awards]], and won the award for the best British Album of the last 30 Years at the 2010 [[Brit Awards]].&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/8517579.stm |title=Lady Gaga wins Brit Awards triple |publisher=BBC News |date=16 February 2010 |accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background and recording==
Oasis achieved commercial success with the release of their debut album ''[[Definitely Maybe]]'' in 1994. That November after a performance in [[Hamburg]], Germany, guitarist and songwriter [[Noel Gallagher]] performed all the songs he intended the group to record for its next album on his acoustic guitar. Guitarist [[Paul Arthurs]] said he was so awed by the quality of Gallagher's songs that he cried.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 213&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1995, Oasis began recording their next album at Rockfield Studios, near [[Monmouth]]. The band recorded quickly; early on, the group averaged recording close to one song every 24 hours. Tension arose between Noel and his younger brother, singer [[Liam Gallagher]] when the former told the latter that he wanted to sing lead vocals on either &quot;Wonderwall&quot; or &quot;Don't Look Back in Anger&quot;. The younger Gallagher considered this tantamount to a temporary exile from his own group. The issue dissipated momentarily as Noel was pleased with Liam's vocal take of &quot;Wonderwall&quot;. However, tension rose due to Liam's strained attempts to sing the high notes on &quot;Champagne Supernova&quot;. When Noel subsequently took his turn to record his vocals for &quot;Don't Look Back in Anger&quot;, Liam went to a local pub and came back accompanied by a crowd of people while his brother was recording. The siblings then began fighting viciously; Arthurs described it as &quot;a proper fight&quot;. As a result of the brawl, Arthurs said that Noel instructed the group to leave for London at four in the morning. At seven A.M., Arthurs called the group's management company, Ignition, to tell them that the album was cancelled. Ignition did not believe Arthurs at first and hung up on him; the company soon after realised that Arthurs was serious. Producer [[Owen Morris]] was &quot;gutted&quot; that sessions were called off, however, the rest of the band was not as concerned. Arthurs said he told Morris, &quot;It'll be all right. Give [Noel] a week at home. By then it was just, 'Oh - ''another'' fight'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 226-27&lt;/ref&gt;

The Gallagher brothers reconciled three weeks later. The group spent another two weeks working on the album, followed by post-production work in London. Morris claimed the album was recorded in 15 days; he said once the album was finished, &quot;This album will wipe the field with any competition [. . .] It's astonishing. It's the [[Never Mind the Bollocks, Here's the Sex Pistols|bollocks]] for this decade.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;

==Composition==
[[John Harris (critic)|John Harris]] commented in his music history ''Britpop!: Cool Britannia and the Spectacular Demise of English Rock'' that much of the music on ''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?'' &quot;seemed to reveal little more inspired than a string of musical hand-me-downs&quot;. Among the musical cues Harris noted on the album were [[Gary Glitter]]'s &quot;Hello, Hello I'm Back Again&quot; (&quot;Hello&quot;), [[John Lennon]]'s &quot;[[Imagine (song)|Imagine]]&quot; (&quot;Don't Look Back in Anger&quot;), the theme to the 1970s children's programme ''You and Me'' and [[The Beatles]]' &quot;[[While My Guitar Gently Weeps]]&quot; (&quot;She's Electric&quot;), and the [[R.E.M.]] song &quot;[[The One I Love (R.E.M. song)|The One I Love]]&quot; (&quot;Morning Glory&quot;). One song, &quot;Step Out&quot;, bore such a close resemblance to the song &quot;[[Uptight (Everything's Alright)]]&quot; by [[Stevie Wonder]] that it was removed from the album shortly before release due to the threat of legal action.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 253-54&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite critics who derided Noel Gallagher's appropriation of other songs, Harris commented &quot;the fact that [Gallagher's] songs contained so many musical echoes seemed to couch the album in an air of homely reassurance&quot;. Harris believed that the &quot;ordinary&quot; nature of some of the album's songs &quot;turned out to be part of its deeply populist appeal&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p. 254&quot; /&gt;

Despite initial criticism from the press, the album's reputation has grown significantly since its release, with singles such as &quot;Don't Look Back In Anger&quot;, &quot;Wonderwall&quot; and &quot;Champagne Supernova&quot; still receiving critical acclaim and being voted in numerous music polls. The album has a notable anthemic theme to its songs, differing from the rawness and edged rock of ''Definitely Maybe''. In the BBC documentary ''[[Seven Ages of Rock]]'', former NME chief editor Steve Sutherland noted that &quot;with ''Morning Glory'', [Noel] began to take seriously the notion of being the voice of a generation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{BBC Online|id=music/sevenages/|title=''Seven Ages''}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of string arrangements and instrumental accompaninces on the album was a significant departure from the band's debut.

==Release and reception==
{{Album reviews
| rev1 = [[Allmusic]]
|rev1Score = {{rating|5|5}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url={{Allmusic|class=album|id=whats-the-story-morning-glory-r224033/review|pure_url=yes}}|title=(What's the Story) Morning Glory? review&amp;nbsp;— Oasis|last=Erlewine|first=Stephen Thomas|publisher=Allmusic|accessdate=25 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev2 = ''[[The Austin Chronicle]]''
|rev2Score = {{Rating|4|5}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Austin Chronicle review&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Mindy |last=LaBernz |title=Review: OASIS - (What's the Story) Morning Glory? (Epic) |url=http://www.austinchronicle.com/gyrobase/Issue/review?oid=oid:530246 |date=16 November 1995 |publisher=Nick Barbaro |accessdate=5 August 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5iwEh7v1v|archivedate=10 August 2009|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev3 = [[BBC]]
|rev3Score = (favourable)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/music/reviews/fqw6|title=(What's the Story) Morning Glory? review&amp;nbsp;— Oasis|last=Smith|first=Sid|publisher=BBC|accessdate=25 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev4 = ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]''
|rev4Score = (A-)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,299002,00.html|title=(What's the Story) Morning Glory? review&amp;nbsp;— Oasis|last=Flaherty|first=Mike|work=Entertainment Weekly |accessdate=25 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev5 = ''[[Rolling Stone]]''
|rev5Score = {{rating|5|5}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/music/artists/oasis/albumguide|title=Album Guide|accessdate=13 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| rev6 = [[Sputnikmusic]]
|rev6Score = {{rating|5|5}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sputnikmusic.com/album.php?albumid=396|title=Oasis: Album Guide|accessdate=18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}&lt;!--List Automatically Moved by DASHBot--&gt;

The album was preceded by two singles. The first, &quot;[[Some Might Say]]&quot;, was released 6 months prior to the album's issue and gave the group its first [[List of number-one singles from the 1990s (UK)|number one single]]. The second single from the album, and its lead track, &quot;[[Roll with It (Oasis song)|Roll with It]]&quot;, was issued on 14 August . The single had a tentative release date of October 1995, to bring it close to the issue of its parent album, but its move to August 1995 led to the key moment of the [[Britpop]] movement, the chart showdown, dubbed &quot;[[The Battle of Britpop]]&quot;. Oasis' Britpop rivals [[Blur (band)|Blur]], assuming Oasis would follow music industry protocol and release the single three weeks before the album, had originally planned to release the lead single for their new album ''[[The Great Escape (Blur album)|The Great Escape]]'', entitled &quot;[[Country House]]&quot;, on 21 August 1995. Blur later learned that Oasis moved up &quot;Roll with It&quot;'s release to the 14th and reacted by changing the release date of &quot;Country House&quot; to be the same week.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; In the event &quot;Country House&quot; outsold &quot;Roll with It&quot; by 270,000 copies to 220,000, and topped the singles chart for a fortnight. Overall singles sales that week were up by 41 percent.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 235&lt;/ref&gt;

''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?'' was eventually released on 2 October 1995. The album sold quickly; the ''[[Daily Mirror]]'' reported the day after release that central London [[HMV]] stores were selling copies of the album at a rate of two per minute. At the end of the first week of sales, ''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?'' had sold 347,000 copies, making it (at the time) the third-fastest-selling album in [[UK Albums Chart|UK chart]] history, behind [[Michael Jackson]]'s ''[[Bad (album)|Bad]]'' and [[U2]]'s ''[[Rattle and Hum]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris, p. 254&quot; /&gt; It was knocked off of the top spot after just one week, by [[Simply Red]]'s ''[[Life (Simply Red album)|Life]]''. However, sales remained consistent and the album returned to the top spot for six weeks from 13 January 1996, before being temporarily knocked off the top spot for one week by [[The Bluetones]] ''[[Expecting to Fly (album)|Expecting to Fly]]'', and then a three week run from 2 March 1996. In total, the album spent 10 weeks at number one and was the second best selling album of 1995 and 1996, behind [[Robson &amp; Jerome]] and [[Alanis Morissette]] respectively. The album's prolonged chart success is, at least partially, attributed to &quot;[[Wonderwall (song)|Wonderwall]]&quot;, which was released three weeks after its parent album, and the [[Mike Flowers Pops]] cover version released two months later. The Oasis single peaked at number two, but went on to be the band's best selling single in the UK, passing sales of 1&amp;nbsp;million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=everyHit.com&amp;nbsp;— Best Selling Singles Of All Time&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|url=http://www.everyhit.com./bestsellingsingles.html|work=|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5iwEhisRc|archivedate=10 August 2009|deadurl=no|accessdate=5 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and reached number one on the US Modern Rock chart (for a then-unprecedented 10 consecutive weeks), as did &quot;[[Champagne Supernova]]&quot;, which was not issued as a single in the UK. &quot;Wonderwall&quot; also achieved number one status on the Australian singles chart. &quot;[[Morning Glory (Oasis song)|Morning Glory]]&quot; was issued as a radio-only single in the U.S. and a physical release in Australia. The last UK single from the album, &quot;[[Don't Look Back in Anger]]&quot;, was released in February 1996, becoming the group's second UK Number One, going platinum,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bpi.co.uk/platinum/platinumright.asp?rq=search_plat&amp;r_id=21174 BPI website]&lt;/ref&gt; and reached number 10 on the US Modern Rock Charts.

''Morning Glory'' sold in excess of 4.4&amp;nbsp;million copies in the UK alone which propelled it to being the second biggest-selling album of all time in the UK until a July 2007 update by the [[British Phonographic Industry|BPI]] placed it third behind [[Queen (band)|Queen]]'s Greatest Hits and [[The Beatles]]' ''[[Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band]]''.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.rockonthenet.com/artists-o/oasis_main.htm Rock The Net: Oasis]&lt;/ref&gt; This (as noted by [[John Harris (critic)|John Harris]] in ''Britpop!'') equated to one in four households in Britain owning a copy of the album; an example of Oasis' prominence in their home country.&lt;ref&gt;Harris, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; The album was commercially successful worldwide reaching No. 1 in Australia, New Zealand, Sweden and Switzerland and No. 4 in the U.S., and going Top 10 in a further seven countries. It was certified 14 times platinum by the BPI, four times platinum by the RIAA, eight times platinum by the CRIA and six times platinum by the Australian Recording Industry Association.

''[[NME]]'' gave the album seven out of 10,&lt;ref name=&quot;NME Review&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=John |last=Robinson |title=Review: Oasis - (What's The Story) Morning Glory |journal=[[NME]] |publisher=[[IPC Media]] |issue=30 September 1995 |page=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Q (magazine)|Q]]'' gave it 3 stars out of 5. In its original review ''[[Rolling Stone]]'', gave the album 4 out of 5 stars, stating that &quot;Oasis have discovered their feminine side&quot; and adding &quot;that doesn't mean they can't still rock&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rolling stone 95&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Music Reviews: (What's the Story) Morning Glory?|journal=[[Rolling Stone]]|first=Jon|last=Wiederhorn|date=1995-10-19|accessdate=2011-05-23|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20081103075321/http://www.rollingstone.com/reviews/album/213321/review/5946311/whatsthestorymorningglory}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in an update of its ''Album Guide'' in 2010, it re-rated it with 5 stars.&lt;ref name=&quot;rolling stone albumguide&quot;&gt;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/artists/oasis/albumguide&lt;/ref&gt; It was ranked number 376 in ''Rolling Stone''{{'}}s list of &quot;[[The 500 Greatest Albums of All Time]]&quot;. Allmusic gave the album a perfect rating of 5 stars.

The success of ''Morning Glory'' resulted in Oasis being one of the biggest bands in the United Kingdom, with substantial and considerable press coverage in the mainstream music press. The band played several large open air concerts in the UK during 1996, including two famous gigs at [[Manchester City]] football stadium [[Maine Road]] in front of their home town fans, and two nights at [[Concerts at Knebworth House|Knebworth]] in front of a combined audience of 250,000 people (125,000 each night);&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nme.com/news/oasis/23794 Oasis mark Knebworth anniversary]&lt;/ref&gt; at the time, they were the biggest gigs ever held for a single band on UK soil and to date remains the largest demand ever for a British concert; with reportedly over 2.6&amp;nbsp;million applications for tickets.

The album is also considered a starting point in the [[loudness war]], with its heavy use of compression.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stylusmagazine.com/articles/weekly_article/imperfect-sound-forever.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Packaging==
The cover photo was taken on [[Berwick Street]] in [[Soho, London]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musicpilgrimages.com/album/index.php?alias=album_cover__whats_the_story_morning_glory.html musicpilgrimages.com]&lt;/ref&gt; a London street known for its independent record shops. The cover features two men walking&amp;nbsp;— art director [[Brian Cannon]], and DJ [[Sean Rowley]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nme.com/photos/revealed-%E2-the-real-life-stars-of-famous-album-sleeves/152747/9/1 NME Oasis What's The Story Morning Glory album sleeve] nme.com, September 2009. Accessed 18 September 2009. [http://www.webcitation.org/5jxwWKUpT Archived] 21 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Track listing==
{{Track listing
| all_writing = [[Noel Gallagher]], except where noted
| title1      = Hello
| length1     = 3:21
| note1       = Gallagher, [[Gary Glitter]], [[Mike Leander]]
| title2      = [[Roll with It (Oasis song)|Roll with It]]
| length2     = 3:59
| title3      = [[Wonderwall (song)|Wonderwall]]
| length3     = 4:18
| title4      = [[Don't Look Back in Anger]]
| length4     = 4:48
| title5      = Hey Now!
| length5     = 5:41
| length6     = 0:44
| note6       = aka &quot;The Swamp Song&amp;nbsp;— Excerpt 1&quot;
| title7      = [[Some Might Say]]
| length7     = 5:29
| title8      = Cast No Shadow
| length8     = 4:51
| title9      = She's Electric
| length9     = 3:40
| title10     = [[Morning Glory (Oasis song)|Morning Glory]]
| length10    = 5:03
| length11    = 0:39
| note11      = aka &quot;The Swamp Song&amp;nbsp;— Excerpt 2&quot;
| title12     = [[Champagne Supernova]]
| length12    = 7:27
}}

{{Track listing
| headline    = Vinyl Edition
| collapsed   = yes
| title1      = Hello
| length1     = 3:21
| note1       = Gallagher, [[Gary Glitter]], [[Mike Leander]]
| title2      = [[Roll with It (Oasis song)|Roll with It]]
| length2     = 3:59
| title3      = [[Wonderwall (song)|Wonderwall]]
| length3     = 4:18
| title4      = [[Don't Look Back in Anger]]
| length4     = 4:48
| title5      = Hey Now!
| length5     = 5:41
| length6     = 0:44
| note6       = aka &quot;The Swamp Song&amp;nbsp;— Excerpt 1&quot;
| title7      = Bonehead's Bank Holiday
| length7     = 3:47
| note7       = Gallagher, [[Paul Arthurs]]; Vinyl-only bonus track
| title8      = [[Some Might Say]]
| length8     = 5:29
| title9      = Cast No Shadow
| length9     = 4:51
| title10     = She's Electric
| length10    = 3:40
| title11     = [[Morning Glory (Oasis song)|Morning Glory]]
| length11    = 5:03
| length12    = 0:39
| note12      = aka &quot;The Swamp Song&amp;nbsp;— Excerpt 2&quot;
| title13     = [[Champagne Supernova]]
| length13    = 7:27
}}

===Singles box set===
{{Main|Morning Glory (singles box)}}

{{Infobox album &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Albums --&gt;
| Name    = (What's the Story) Morning Glory?
| Type    = box
| Artist   = [[Oasis (band)|Oasis]]
| Cover    = 200841469;encoding=jpg;size=300.jpg
| Released  = 4 November 1996
| Recorded  = 1995
| Genre    = Rock, [[Britpop]]
| Length   = 81:59
| Label    = [[Creation Records|Creation]]
| Producer  = [[Owen Morris]], [[Noel Gallagher]]
| Reviews   =
| Last album = ''[[Definitely Maybe (singles box) (EP)|Definitely Maybe]]'' (box set)&lt;br /&gt;(1996)
| This album = '''''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?''''' (box set)&lt;br /&gt;(1996)
| Next album = ''[[Be Here Now (album)|Be Here Now]]''&lt;br /&gt;(1997)
}}
The '''''(What's the Story) Morning Glory?''''' [[box set]] was released on 4 November 1996, featuring four discs of singles, including B-sides, and one disc of interviews. The album charted at number 24 on the [[UK Albums Chart]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theofficialcharts.com/artist/_/oasis/#albums|title=Featured Artists: Oasis|publisher=[[The Official Charts Company]]|accessdate=11 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All songs written by [[Noel Gallagher]], except &quot;Cum on Feel the Noize&quot; by [[Noddy Holder]] and [[Jim Lea]]; &quot;Step Out&quot; co-written by [[Stevie Wonder]], [[Henry Cosby]] and [[Sylvia Moy]].

{{Track list
| all_writing   =
| collapsed     = no
| headline      = Disc One
| title1        = Interviews
| length1       = 18:22
}}
{{Track list    
| all_writing   = 
| collapsed     = no
| headline      = Disc Two
| title1        = [[Some Might Say]]
| length1       = 5:28

| title2        = [[Talk Tonight]]
| length2       = 4:21

| title3        = [[Acquiesce]]
| length3       = 4:24

| title4        = Headshrinker
| length4       = 4:38
}}
{{Track list
| all_writing   = 
| headline      = Disc Three
| collapsed     = no
| title1        = [[Roll with It (Oasis song)|Roll with It]]
| length1       = 4:00

| title2        = [[It's Better People]]
| length2       = 3:59

| title3        = Rockin' Chair
| length3       = 4:36

| title4        = [[Live Forever]]
| note4         = Live at [[Glastonbury Festival]], 1995
| length4       = 4:40
}}
{{Track list
| all_writing   =
| headline      = Disc Four
| collapsed     = no
| title1        = [[Wonderwall (Oasis song)|Wonderwall]]
| length1       = 4:19

| title2        = Round Are Way
| length2       = 5:42

| title3        = The Swamp Song
| length3       = 4:15

| title4        = [[The Masterplan (song)|The Masterplan]]
| length4       = 5:23
}}
{{Track list
| all_writing   =
| headline      = Disc Five
| collapsed     = no
| title1        = [[Don't Look Back in Anger]]
| length1       = 4:47

| title2        = Step Out
| length2       = 3:40

| title3        = Underneath the Sky
| length3       = 3:20

| title4        = [[Cum On Feel the Noize]]
| length4       = 5:09
}}

==Personnel==
;Oasis
* [[Liam Gallagher]]&amp;nbsp;– lead vocals, [[tambourine]]
* [[Noel Gallagher]]&amp;nbsp;– [[lead guitar|lead]] and [[acoustic guitar]], vocals (lead on &quot;Don't Look Back in Anger&quot;), piano, [[mellotron]], [[e-bow]], production
* [[Paul Arthurs|Paul &quot;Bonehead&quot; Arthurs]]&amp;nbsp;– [[rhythm guitar|rhythm]] and acoustic guitar, piano, mellotron
* [[Paul McGuigan (musician)|Paul McGuigan]]&amp;nbsp;– bass guitar
* [[Alan White (Oasis drummer)|Alan White]]&amp;nbsp;– drums, percussion (except on &quot;[[Some Might Say]]&quot;)
* [[Tony McCarroll]]&amp;nbsp;– drums on &quot;[[Some Might Say]]&quot;

;Additional musician
* [[Paul Weller]]&amp;nbsp;– lead guitar and backing vocals on &quot;Champagne Supernova&quot; and harmonica on track 6 and 11.

;Additional personnel
* [[Owen Morris]]&amp;nbsp;– production
* Neil Dorfsman&amp;nbsp;– [[Audio mixing (recorded music)|multichannel mixing (SACD version)]]
* David Swope&amp;nbsp;– assistant mixing (SACD version)
* Barry Grint&amp;nbsp;– original audio mastering at Abbey Road Studios (now at Alchemy Soho)
* Vlado Meller&amp;nbsp;– [[Audio mastering|mastering]] (SACD version)
* Michael Spencer Jones&amp;nbsp;– [[photography]]
* [[Brian Cannon]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Cover art|artwork]], [[Graphic design|design]]
* Mathew Sankey&amp;nbsp;– assistant design

==Chart positions==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Year !! Chart !! Peak
|-
|1995 || [[UK Albums Chart]] || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
|1995 || US [[Billboard 200|''Billboard'' 200]]&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic charts&quot;&gt;&quot;[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=oasis-p44888/charts-awards|pure_url=yes}} Oasis - Billboard Albums]&quot;. ''[[Allmusic]]''. Retrieved 29 October 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 4
|-
|1996 || Australian [[Australian Recording Industry Association|ARIA]] Albums Chart || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
|1996 || [[Canadian Albums Chart]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/rpm/028020-119.01-e.php?&amp;file_num=nlc008388.2876&amp;type=1&amp;interval=50&amp;PHPSESSID=c6btf3r8hs459qqt5ln3o3dcv5|title=Top Albums/CDs&amp;nbsp;— Volume 62, No. 25, February 05 1996|publisher=''[[RPM (magazine)|RPM]]''|accessdate=2010-10-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
|1996 || New Zealand Albums Chart || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
|1996 || Spanish Albums Chart || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|}

==Certifications==
* United Kingdom ([[British Phonographic Industry|BPI]]): 14x Platinum (24 September 2004)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bpi.co.uk/platinum/platinumright.asp?rq=search_plat&amp;r_id=32163 (What's the Story) Morning Glory? 14x Platinum]&lt;/ref&gt; (4,421,505)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.bpi.co.uk/assets/files/top%2040%20albums.pdf | title=Top 40 Best Selling Albums 28 July 1956 – 14 June 2009 | format=PDF| publisher=[[British Phonographic Industry]] | accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* United States ([[Recording Industry Association of America|RIAA]]): 4x Platinum (8 November 1996)&lt;ref name=&quot;English Beat&quot;/&gt; (4&amp;nbsp;million)
* Canada ([[Canadian Recording Industry Association|CRIA]]): 8x Platinum (800,000)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.musiccanada.com/GPSearchResult.aspx?st=(What's%20The%20Story)%20Morning%20Glory&amp;ica=False&amp;sa=Oasis&amp;sl=&amp;smt=0&amp;sat=-1&amp;ssb=Artist|title=Gold Platinum Database: (What's The Story) Morning Glory|publisher=[[Canadian Recording Industry Association]]|accessdate=2011-09-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Australia ([[ARIA Charts]]): 6x Platinum (420,000)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ARIA Charts&amp;nbsp;— Accreditations - 1999 Albums|url=http://www.aria.com.au/pages/aria-charts-accreditations-albums-1999.htm|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5iPw4q5W5|archivedate=20 July 2009|deadurl=no|accessdate=30 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Spain ([[SGAE]]) : 2X Platinum (250,000)
* Germany ([[IFPI]]): Gold (250,000)
* France ([[SNEP]]): Platinum (585,900)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.infodisc.fr/CDCertif_P.php?debut=600&lt;/ref&gt;
* Netherlands ([[NVPI]]): Gold (1996) (30,000)
* Norway ([[IFPI]]) : Platinum (1997) (30,000)
* Switzerland: Gold (15.000)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Steffen Hung |url=http://www.swisscharts.com/search_certifications.asp?search=oasis |title=The Official Swiss Charts and Music Community |publisher=Swisscharts.com |date= |accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Finland ([[IFPI]]) : Gold (27.540)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ifpi.fi/tilastot/artistit/oasis |title=IFPI&amp;nbsp;— Tilastot&amp;nbsp;— Kulta- ja platinalevyt |publisher=Ifpi.fi |date= |accessdate=10 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of best-selling albums worldwide]]
* [[List of best-selling albums in the United Kingdom]]
* [[List of best-selling albums in the United Kingdom#Top best-selling albums by UK Chart|Top best-selling albums by UK Chart]]

==References==
* Harris, John. ''Britpop!: Cool Britannia and the Spectacular Demise of English Rock''. Da Capo Press, 2004. ISBN 0-306-81367-X

==References==
{{cleanup-linkrot|date=August 2011}}
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Oasis}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2010}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Whats The Story Morning Glory?}}
[[Category:1995 albums]]
[[Category:Oasis (band) albums]]
[[Category:Albums released in Super Audio]]
[[Category:Creation Records albums]]
[[Category:Epic Records albums]]
[[Category:English-language albums]]

[[bg:(What's The Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[da:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[de:(What’s the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[et:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[es:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[fr:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[gl:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[ko:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[is:(What's The Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[it:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[he:(What's The Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[ka:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[hu:(What’s the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[nl:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[ja:モーニング・グローリー]]
[[no:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[pl:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[pt:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[ru:(What’s the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[simple:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[sk:(What’s The Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[fi:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[sv:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[tr:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]
[[uk:(What's the Story) Morning Glory?]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
