<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="43815" ns="0" title="Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect6|TMNT|the 2007 film|TMNT (film)||Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (disambiguation)}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2009}}
{{Infobox comics organization
|image = Tmnt_7.jpg
|imagesize= 198
|caption= Clockwise from top: ''Leonardo'', ''Michelangelo'', ''Donatello'', and ''Raphael''
|publisher=[[Mirage Studios]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Heroes in a Half Shell Turn the Big 2-5 |work= The New York Times|date=2009-04-20|url= http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/04/20/heroes-n-a-half-shell-turn-the-big-2-5/?scp=4&amp;sq=ninja%20turtles%20reviews&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|debut= [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (Mirage Studios)|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]] #1 &lt;br&gt;(May 1984)
|creators=[[Kevin Eastman]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Peter Laird]]
|base= '''[[Manhattan]]'''
|members=[[Leonardo (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Leonardo]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Raphael (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Raphael]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Donatello (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Donatello]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Michelangelo (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Michelangelo]] &lt;br/&gt;
|memberlist=
|cat=teams
|subcat=
|hero=y
|sortkey=Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles
}}

The '''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles''' (or simply ''Ninja Turtles'') are a fictional team of four teenage [[anthropomorphic]] [[turtle]]s, who were trained by their anthropomorphic rat [[sensei]] in the art of [[ninjutsu]] and named after four Renaissance artists. From their home in the storm sewers of [[New York City]], they battle petty criminals, evil [[megalomania]]cs, and [[alien invader]]s, all while remaining isolated from [[society]] at large. The characters initially appeared in [[comic book]]s before being licensed for toys, cartoons, video games, films, and other merchandise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Just How Powerful Are Those Turtles?|work= The New York Times|date=1990-04-15|url= http://www.nytimes.com/1990/04/15/movies/just-how-powerful-are-those-turtles.html?scp=8&amp;sq=ninja%20turtles&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2010-08-07 | first1=Harvey R. | last1=Greenberg}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the peak of its popularity in the late 1980s through early 1990s, the franchise gained considerable worldwide success and fame.

==History==
''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles'' Was created in an American [[comic book]] published by [[Mirage Studios]] in 1984 in [[Dover, New Hampshire]]. The concept arose from a humorous drawing sketched out by [[Kevin Eastman]] during a casual evening of [[brainstorming]] with his friend [[Peter Laird]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ezine.kungfumagazine.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title= TMNT: The {{Typo|Rennaissance}} &amp;#91;sic&amp;#93; Reptiles Return|work= Kung Fu Magazine|date=|url=http://ezine.kungfumagazine.com/ezine/article.php?article=703|accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Using money from a [[tax refund]] together with a loan from Eastman's uncle, the young artists [[Self-publishing|self-published]] a single issue comic intended to [[parody]] four of the most popular comics of the early 1980s: [[Marvel Comics]]' ''[[Daredevil (Marvel Comics)|Daredevil]]'' and ''[[New Mutants]]'', [[Dave Sim]]'s ''[[Cerebus the Aardvark|Cerebus]]'', and [[Frank Miller (comics)|Frank Miller]]'s ''[[Ronin (DC Comics)|Ronin]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heavymetal.com/index.php?id=260|title=I Was a Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtle |date=2007-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Much of the Turtles' mainstream success began when a [[license|licensing]] agent, Mark Freedman, sought out Eastman and Laird to propose wider [[merchandise|merchandising]] opportunities for the offbeat property. In 1986, Dark Horse Miniatures produced a set of 15&amp;nbsp;mm [[figurine|lead figurines]]. In January 1987, they visited the offices of [[Playmates Toys Inc]], a small [[California]] [[toy]] company who wished to expand into the [[action figure]] market. Development initiated with a creative team of companies and individuals: Jerry Sachs, ad man of Sachs-Finley Agency, brought together the animators at Murakami-Wolf-Swenson, headed by award-winning animator Fred Wolf. Wolf and his team combined concepts and ideas with Playmates marketing crew, headed by Karl Aaronian and then VP of Sales, Richard Sallis and VP of Playmates, Bill Carlson. Aaronian brought on several designers and concepteer and writer John Schulte and worked out the simple backstory that would live on toy packaging for the entire run of the product and show. Sachs called the high-concept pitch &quot;Green Against Brick&quot;. The sense of humor was honed with the collaboration of MWS's writers. Playmates and their team essentially served as associate producers and contributing writers to the miniseries that was first launched to sell-in the toy action figures. Phrases like &quot;Heroes in a Half Shell&quot; and many of the comical catch phrases and battle slogans (&quot;Turtle Power!&quot;) came from the writing and conceptualization of this creative team. As the series developed, veteran writer Jack Mendelsohn came on board as both a story editor and scriptwriter. David Wise, Michael Charles Hill, and Michael Reaves wrote most of the scripts, taking input via Mendelsohn and collaborating writer Schulte and marketing maven Aaronian.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

The miniseries was repeated three times before it found an audience. Once the product started selling, the show got syndicated and picked up and backed by Group W, which funded the next round of animation. The show then went network, on [[CBS]]. Accompanied by the popular [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)|''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles'' 1987 TV series]], and the subsequent [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles action figures|action figure line]], the TMNT were soon catapulted into [[pop culture]] history. At the height of the frenzy, in the late 1980s and early 1990s, the Turtles' likenesses could be found on a wide range of children's merchandise, from [[Pez dispenser]]s to [[skateboard]]s, breakfast cereal, video games, school supplies, linens, towels, cameras, and even toy shaving kits.

On October 21, 2009 it was announced that cable channel [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] (a subsidiary of [[Viacom]]) had purchased all of Mirage's rights to the ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles'' property. Mirage retains the rights to publish 18 issues a year, though the future involvement of Mirage with the Turtles and the future of Mirage Studios itself is unknown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Laird| first = Peter| title = palblog: Musings about the sale| date = 2009-10-21| url = http://plairdblog.blogspot.com/2009/10/musings-about-sale.html| accessdate = 2009-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nickelodeon plans to develop a new CGI-animated TMNT television series and will partner with fellow Viacom company [[Paramount Pictures]] to bring a new TMNT movie to theaters. Both are expected to debut in 2012.&lt;ref name=Reuters&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS136562+21-Oct-2009+PRN20091021 The Mirage Group Sells Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles to Nickelodeon | Reuters]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Main characters==
::''For supporting characters see [[List of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles characters]]''

*'''[[Leonardo (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Leonardo]]''' (Leo) — The courageous leader and devoted student of martial arts, Leonardo wears a blue mask (red in the Mirage/Image/IDW comics) and wields two [[katana]].&lt;!--Do not change to ninjato. Leo's swords have always been called katana in the fiction. Even if they shouldn't have been, we have to stick with what's written.--&gt; He is the oldest of the four and the most skilled fighter of the turtles. Leonardo was named after the Italian polymath, scientist, engineer, inventor, anatomist, and painter, [[Leonardo da Vinci]].
*'''[[Raphael (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Raphael]]''' (Raph) — The team's bad boy, Raphael wears a red mask and wields a pair of [[Sai (weapon)|sai]]. He has an aggressive nature and seldom hesitates to throw the first punch. He is an intense fighter. He would usually speak in a Brooklyn accent. His personality can be alternately fierce and sarcastic, and oftentimes delivers deadpan humor. Still, he is intensely loyal to his brothers and sensei. Raphael is good friends with Casey Jones. He is named after the Italian painter and architect of the High Renaissance, [[Raphael]].&lt;ref name=Origin&gt;[http://www.ninjaturtles.com/origin/origin.htm TMNT Origin Story], official site. Retrieved 2007-11-16.&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Michelangelo (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Michelangelo]]''' (Mike or Mikey) — Easy-going and free-spirited, Michelangelo wears an orange mask (red in the Mirage/Image/IDW comcis) and wields a pair of [[nunchaku]]. Michelangelo provides much of the [[comic relief]]. Most of the time, he is youngest of the four Turtles. While he loves to relax and eat pizza, this Turtle also has an adventurous and creative side. He's something of the &quot;surfer&quot; boy, speaking usually in a Southern California accent. He is named after the Italian Renaissance painter, sculptor, architect, poet, and engineer [[Michelangelo|Michelangelo Buonarroti]]. His name was originally misspelled &quot;Michaelangelo&quot; by Peter Laird and Kevin Eastman.&lt;ref name=Origin/&gt;
*'''[[Donatello (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Donatello]]''' (Don or Donnie) — The knowledgeable scientist, inventor, engineer, and technological genius, Donatello wears a purple mask (red in the Mirage/Image/IDW comics) and wields the [[bō]] staff. Donatello is perhaps the least violent Turtle, preferring to use his knowledge to solve conflicts. He is named after the sculptor [[Donatello]].
*'''[[Splinter (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Splinter]]''' — The Turtles' [[sensei]] and adoptive father, Splinter is a Japanese mutant [[rat]] who learned the ways of ninjutsu from his owner and master, [[Hamato Yoshi]]. In the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)|1987 TV series]] and [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Adventures|Archie Comics series]], Splinter was Hamato Yoshi mutated into a rat instead of being just Yoshi's pet.
*'''[[Shredder (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Shredder]]''' — A villainous ninjutsu master called Oroku Saki. In every incarnation of the TMNT franchise, he has been the archenemy of Splinter and the Turtles. Shredder prefers to use his armor instead of weapons in some versions. He is also the leader of the [[Foot Clan]].
*'''[[April O'Neil]]''' — A former lab assistant to the [[mad scientist]] [[Baxter Stockman]], April is the plucky human companion of the Turtles. April first met up with the Turtles when they saved her from Baxter's Mouser robots. She embarks on many of the Turtles' adventures and aids them by doing the work in public that the Turtles can not. In the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)|1987 TV series]], [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Adventures|Archie Comics series]] and subsequent three films, April was a television news reporter.
*'''[[Casey Jones (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Casey Jones]]''' — A [[vigilante]] who has become one of the Turtles' closest allies as well as a love interest to April. Casey first met up with the Turtles after having a fight with Raphael. Casey fights crime with an assortment of sporting goods ([[baseball bat]]s, [[golf club (equipment)|golf clubs]], [[ice hockey stick]]s, [[cricket bat]], etc.) while wearing a [[hockey mask]] to protect his identity.

==Comics==
{{Main|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (Mirage Studios)}}
[[File:Tmnt1cover.jpg|right|thumb|200px|The cover of TMNT #1]]
Eastman and Laird's ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles'' premiered in May, 1984, at a comic book convention held at a local Sheraton Hotel in [[Portsmouth, New Hampshire]]. It was published by [[Mirage Studios]] in an oversized magazine-style format using black &amp; white artwork on cheap newsprint, limited to a print run of only 3,000 copies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= DYNAMIC DUO: Kevin Eastman and Peter Laird; Turning Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Into a Monster|work= The New York Times|date=1988-12-25|url= http://www.nytimes.com/1988/12/25/business/dynamic-duo-kevin-eastman-peter-laird-turning-teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles-into.html?scp=1&amp;sq=ninja%20turtles&amp;st=cse&amp;pagewanted=2|accessdate=2010-08-07 | first=Douglas C. | last=McGill}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through a clever media kit that included an ad placed in Comic Buyer's Guide #545, the public's interest was piqued and thus began the Turtle phenomenon. The small print runs made these early comics and trade magazines instant collector items, and within months they were trading for over fifty times their cover price. The name &quot;Mirage Studios&quot; was chosen because of Eastman and Laird's lack of a professional art studio at the start of their career, before their creation made them both multi-millionaires.

Mirage also published a bi-monthly companion book entitled ''[[Tales of the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]'', featuring art by [[Ryan Brown (comics)|Ryan Brown]] and [[Jim Lawson]], which was designed to fill in the gaps of continuity in the TMNT universe. This put the original series and ''Tales'' in the same mainstream continuity, and the two are thus canon to each other. The title's first volume was from 1987–1989, released in alternating months with the regular Eastman and Laird book. All seven issues of Volume One have been collected in trade paperback form twice, and twenty-five issues of Volume Two have been collected in trades of five issues each.

As the TMNT phenomenon proliferated to other media, Eastman and Laird would find themselves administrating an international merchandising juggernaut. However, this prevented the two creators from participating in the day-to-day work of writing and illustrating a monthly comic book. For this reason, many guest artists were invited to showcase their unique talents in the TMNT universe. The breadth of diversity found in the various short stories gave the series a disjointed, [[anthology|anthology-like]] feel. Fans stuck with the series, and what was originally intended as a one-shot became a continuing series that lasted for 104 issues spanning four separate volumes. 
 
In June, 1996, [[Image Comics]] revived the title in what is considered &quot;Volume 3&quot; of the comics. It was a slightly more action-oriented TMNT series and although notable for inflicting major physical changes on the main characters, Peter Laird, co-creator of the TMNT, has said this volume is no longer in canon as he began publishing Volume 4 at Mirage Publishing. As an explanation, he offered in the pages of Volume 4's letter column: &quot;It just didn't feel right.&quot;

After taking back the series from Image Comics, Mirage Studios resumed publication of a fourth volume in December, 2001, under the simple title ''TMNT''. After the publication of issue #28, writer Peter Laird placed the series on an eight-month hiatus to devote himself to production of the recent TMNT movie. However, after that eight months had passed Mirage's official website went on to list the series as in &quot;indefinite hiatus&quot;. In January 2008 Mirage had finally confirmed that the series would return in May 2008. Issues 29 and 30 had a limited printing of 1,000 copies each, and were available through the official TMNT website. Although the purchase agreement with Nickelodeon allows Laird to produce up to 18 comics a year set in the original Mirage continuity, no new material has been released since the sale. 

In April 2011, [[IDW Publishing]] announced that they had acquired the license to publish new collections of Mirage storylines and a new ongoing series.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.idwpublishing.com/news/article/1677/ IDW Announces New Comic Series Based on the Original Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles] [[IDW Publishing]] April 1, 2011 Accessed April 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The first issue of [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (IDW Publishing)|the new series]] was release on August 24, 2011. Turtles co-creator Kevin Eastman and Tom Waltz write, with Eastman and Dan Duncan handling art chores.

''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Adventures]]'' was a comic book series published from August 1988 to October 1995 by [[Archie Comics]]. The initial storylines were close adaptations of the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)|1987 TV series]], but with the fifth issue Eastman and Laird decided to hand the series over to Mirage Studios employees [[Ryan Brown (comics)|Ryan Brown]] and [[Stephen Murphy (comics)|Stephen Murphy]] who immediately abandoned the animated series adaptations and took the title in a decidedly different direction with all-new original adventures.

In 1989, Kevin Eastman and Peter Laird created a special three-issue series of full-color mini comics for the [[Ralston-Purina]] Company. These comics were offered for kids to collect and were only available as premiums in boxes of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles cereal.

A monthly comic inspired by the 2003 TV series was published by [[Dreamwave Productions]] from June to December 2003. It was written by [[Peter David]] and illustrated by [[LeSean Thomas]]. In the first four issues, which were the only ones directly adapted from the TV series, the story was told from the perspectives of April, Baxter, Casey, and a pair of NYC cops, instead of the Turtles.

The Turtles have also appeared in many [[manga]] series: {{Nihongo|''Mutant Turtles''|ミュータント・タートルズ|Myūtanto Tātoruzu}} was a 15-issue series by Tsutomu Oyamada, Zuki mora, and Yoshimi Hamada that simply adapted episodes of the original American animated series. ''Super Turtles'' (スーパータートルズ ''Sūpā Tātoruzu'') was a three-issue miniseries by Hidemasa Idemitsu, Tetsurō Kawade, and Toshio Kudō that featured the &quot;TMNT Supermutants&quot; Turtle toys that were on sale at the time. The first volume of Japan's [[anime]] miniseries followed this storyline. Next was {{Nihongo|''Mutant Turtles Gaiden''|ミュータント・タートルズ外伝|Myūtanto Tātoruzu Gaiden}} by Hiroshi Kanno, which was a re-interpretation of the Turtles story with no connection to the previous manga. Also of note was ''Mutant Turtles III'', an adaptation of the third feature film by Yasuhiko Hachino.

A [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles comic strip|daily comic strip]] written and illustrated by [[Dan Berger]] featured an adventure story Monday through Friday and activity puzzles on weekends (with fan art appearing later). The comic strip was published in [[Print syndication|syndication]] until its cancellation in December, 1996. At its highest point in popularity, it was published in over 250 newspapers.

==Television series==
===First animated series (1987–1996)===
{{Main|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)}}
[[File:TMNT1987Series.png|right|thumb|The TMNT logo of the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)|1987 animated series]].]]
When little known Playmates Toys Inc. was approached about producing a TMNT action figure line, they were cautious of the risk and requested that a television deal be acquired first.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tmnt25.com/turtle_power/about_the_creators.html#4 About the Creators] TMNT25.com (January 2009). Retrieved on 1-31-09.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Show Business: Lean, Green and on the Screen
|work= Time|date=April 2, 1990|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,969727-2,00.html#ixzz0h91fnBrj
|accessdate=2010-03-03 | first=Janice C. | last=Simpson}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 28, 1987, the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles' first cartoon series began, starting as a 5-part miniseries and becoming a regular Saturday morning syndicated series on October 1, 1988 with 13 more episodes. The series was produced by Murakami-Wolf-Swenson Film Productions Inc. Mirage Studios does not own the rights to this cartoon series. The show places a much stronger emphasis on humor than the comics do. Here, the Ninja Turtles are portrayed as four wise-cracking, pizza-obsessed superheroes who fight the forces of evil from their sewer hideout, and make their first appearance in masks color-coded to each turtle, where previously they had all worn red.&lt;ref name=&quot;Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles On TV&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title= Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles On TV|work= IGN|date=|url=http://uk.tv.ign.com/articles/774/774796p1.html|accessdate=2010-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cast included new and different characters like [[Bebop and Rocksteady]] and the Neutrinos. Original characters like [[Splinter (TMNT)|Splinter]], [[Shredder (TMNT)|Shredder]], and the [[Foot Clan|Foot Soldiers]] stayed true to the comics in appearance and alignment only. Instead of being Hamato Yoshi's mutated pet rat, [[Splinter (TMNT)|Splinter]] was a mutated Hamato himself. The Foot Soldiers changed from human ninja to an endless supply of robotic grunts, allowing large numbers of them to be destroyed without anyone dying (this was a very important decision in terms of the show's child audience; excessive violence would have alienated parents of children, the show's target demographic). [[Krang]], one of the series' most memorable villains, was inspired by the design of the Utrom, a benign alien race from the Mirage comics. The animated Krang, however, was instead an evil warlord from [[Dimension X (TMNT)|Dimension X]]. [[Baxter Stockman]], whose race was changed from [[black people|black]] to [[white people|white]] either due to apprehension toward depicting a villanous [[African American]] character in a children's cartoon or that for Shredder to boss around a black Stockman would be perceived as racist. Either way, Stockman was rewritten as a shy and meek lackey to Shredder, later mutating into an anthropomorphic [[housefly]].

Starting on September 25, 1989, the series was expanded to weekdays and had 47 more episodes for the new Season. There were 28 new syndicated episodes for Season 4 and only 13 of those episodes aired in 1990. The &quot;European Vacation&quot; episodes were not seen in the United States until [[USA Network]] started showing reruns in late 1993 and the &quot;Awesome Easter&quot; episodes were not seen until 1991. These episodes were delayed because of animation or schedule problems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0131613/trivia &quot;Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles&quot; (1987/I) - Trivia] IMDB.com (February 2019). Retrieved on 2-21-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 21, 1990 a drug prevention television special was broadcast on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]], [[NBC]], and [[CBS]] named ''[[Cartoon All-Stars to the Rescue]]'' that featured some of the most popular cartoons at the time; representing TMNT was Michelangelo, voiced by Townsend Coleman.

The turtles are also well known for their use of idiomatic expressions characteristic of the surfer lingo of the time, especially by Michelangelo. Words and phrases, such as &quot;bummer,&quot; &quot;dude,&quot; &quot;bogus,&quot; &quot;radical,&quot; &quot;far-out,&quot; &quot;tubuloso,&quot; &quot;bodacious,&quot; and possibly the most recognized, &quot;cowabunga.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tmnt25.com/turtle_power/ninja_pedia.html The Official TMNT Web Site!&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting on September 8, 1990 (with a different opening sequence), the show began its run on CBS. The CBS weekend edition ran for a full hour, initially airing a couple of Saturday exclusive episodes back to back. There would also be a brief &quot;Turtle Tips&quot; segment in between the two episodes which served as PSA about the environment or other issues.

The series ran until November 2, 1996 when it aired its final episode. Its enormous popularity gave rise to its numerous imitators, including the ''[[Battletoads]]'', ''[[Cheetahmen]]'', ''[[Wild West C.O.W.-Boys of Moo Mesa]]'', ''[[Stone Protectors]]'', ''[[Street Sharks]]'', ''[[Extreme Dinosaurs]]'', and ''[[Biker Mice from Mars]]''.

Currently, 178 episodes are available on [[DVD]].

===Live-action series (1997–1998)===
[[File:Ninja Turtles, The Next Mutation.png|right|thumb|The [[Ninja Turtles: The Next Mutation]] logo.]]
{{Main|Ninja Turtles: The Next Mutation}}

In 1997–1998, the Turtles starred in a live-action television series called ''Ninja Turtles: The Next Mutation'' that follows the events of the movies. A fifth turtle was introduced, a female named &quot;[[Venus (Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles)|Venus de Milo]]&quot; who was skilled in the mystical arts of the [[ninja|shinobi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles On TV&quot;/&gt;
The series seemed to be a loose continuation of the movie franchise, as Shredder had been defeated and the Ninja Turtles encountered new villains. Other connections to the feature films include the fact that Splinter's ear was cut, the Foot Soldiers were humans, and the Turtles lived in the abandoned subway station seen in the second and third movies. ''The Next Mutation'' Turtles made a guest appearance on ''[[Power Rangers in Space]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles On TV|work= IGN|date=|url=http://uk.tv.ign.com/articles/774/774796p2.html|accessdate=2010-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was canceled after one season of twenty-six episodes. Since its cancellation, Peter Laird has disavowed the character Venus de Milo, while Kevin Eastman is more open to talk about her.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

===Second animated series (2003–2009)===
[[File:TMNT03TVLOGO.png|thumb|right|The TMNT logo of the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (2003 TV series)|2003 animated series]].]]
{{Main|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (2003 TV series)}}
In 2003, a new Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles series produced by [[4Kids Entertainment]] began airing on the &quot;[[FoxBox]]&quot; programming block. It later moved to &quot;[[The CW4Kids]]&quot; block. The series was co-produced by [[Mirage Studios]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= TMNT Celebrates 25 Years, III - Peter Laird |publisher= Newsarama|date=|url= http://www.newsarama.com/comics/080610-TMNT25-Laird.html|accessdate=2010-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Mirage owned one-third of the rights to the series. Mirage's significant stake in creative control resulted in a cartoon that hews more closely to the original comics, creating a darker and edgier feel than the 1987 cartoon, but still remaining lighthearted enough to be considered appropriate for children. This series lasted until 2009, ending with a feature-length television movie titled ''[[Turtles Forever]]'', which was produced in conjunction with the 25th anniversary of the TMNT franchise and featured the Turtles of the 2003 series teaming up with their counterparts from the 1987 series.

[http://www.4kidstv.com/ 4Kidstv.com] featured all the episodes of the series, up until September 2010.  As of that date, 4Kids no longer owns the license to the show, meaning that it can no longer be viewed at 4Kidstv.com. [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] will soon be airing the show on [[Nicktoons (TV channel)|Nicktoons]].

===Third animated series (2012)===
[[File:TMNT-2012-logo.png|thumb|right|The TMNT logo of the 2012 animated series.]]
[[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] has acquired the global rights to Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles from the Mirage Group and 4Kids Entertainment, Inc. and have announced that they are moving forward on development on a new CGI-animated TMNT television series consisting of at least 26 half-hour episodes, and which will premiere the fourth quarter (or summer) 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;TMNT Nickelodeon Animated Series 1&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.toonzone.net/news/articles/36887/
|title=WonderCon 2011 - PR: IDW to Publish New Ninja Turtles Series Based on Original Comics
|publisher=toonzone news
|author=Eileen Cruz
|date=2011-04-04
|accessdate=2011-04-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TMNT Nickelodeon Animated Series 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/115/1154603p1.html
|title=TMNT Gets a Makeover
|publisher=IGN TV
|author=David McCutcheon
|date=2011-03-09
|accessdate=2011-04-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TMNT Nickelodeon Animated Series 3&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/103/1037171p1.html
|title=New Ninja Turtles TV Series and Film Coming
|publisher=IGN TV
|author=Eric Goldman
|date=2009-10-21
|accessdate=2011-04-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A teaser for the upcoming 2012 Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles animated series is available.&lt;ref name=&quot;TMNT Nickelodeon Animated Series 4&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://insidetv.ew.com/2011/03/10/teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles-nickelodeon/
|title=First Look: Nickelodeon unveils 'Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles' -- EXCLUSIVE VIDEO
|publisher=Inside TV | EW.com
|author=Jeff Labrecque
|date=2011-03-10
|accessdate=2011-04-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The video hints at some changes, namely the two Turtles who traditionally carry blunt weapons have had their weapons changed to similar bladed versions. Donatello uses a [[naginata]] instead of a bo, and Michelangelo uses a [[kusarigama]] instead of nunchaku.

At the Nickelodeon Upfront Conference, it was announced that actor [[Jason Biggs]] will voice Leonardo and [[Rob Paulsen]], who voiced Raphael in the 1987 series, will now voice Donatello in the upcoming series.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x8hoofcWI1Y&amp;feature=feedu&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2011, it was confirmed that [[Sean Astin]] would voice Raphael and [[Greg Cipes]] would voice Michelangelo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://insidetv.ew.com/2011/06/14/teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles-sean-astin/ Sean Astin voicing Raphael in new 'Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles' -- EXCLUSIVE]&lt;/ref&gt; On August 8, 2011, it was revealed that [[Mae Whitman]] will be the voice for April O'Neil. In July 2011, it was revealed that Hoon Lee will be the voice of Master Splinter. In October 2011, it was revealed that [[Kevin Michael Richardson]] will be the voice of the Shredder.

==Anime==
[[File:metal raphael toy.jpg|right|thumb|Metal Mutant Raphael]]
{{Main|Mutant Turtles: Choujin Densetsu-hen}}
In addition to the American series, a [[Japan]]ese exclusive two-episode [[anime]] [[Original video animation|OVA]] series was made in 1996, titled ''Mutant Turtles: Choujin Densetsu-hen''. The OVA was similar in tone to the 1987 TV series and uses the same voices from the Japanese dub of the 1987 TV series.

The first episode was made to advertise the ''TMNT Supermutants'' toys. It featured the Turtles as [[superhero]]es, who gained costumes and superpowers with the use of Mutastones, while [[Shredder (TMNT)|Shredder]] and [[Bebop and Rocksteady]] gained supervillain powers with the use of a Dark Mutastone. As with the ''[[Super Sentai]]'' and ''[[Power Rangers]]'' franchises, the four Turtles could combine to form the giant ''Turtle Saint''.

The second episode was created to advertise the ''Metal Mutants'' toys in which the characters gain ''[[Saint Seiya]]''-esque mystical metal armor that can transform into beasts. The seven Japanese Mutanite stones encased in a magic mirror that control the Metal Beasts are based on the sun, moon, and the [[Wu Xing|Five Elements]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

==Feature films==
{{Main|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (film series)}}
The Turtles have featured in four feature films. The first three, produced in the early 90s and released by [[New Line Cinema]], feature live-action, with the Turtles played by various actors in costumes featuring [[animatronic]] heads. The [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (film)|first live-action film]] was distributed by [[Golden Harvest]] overseas, whereas the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles II: The Secret of the Ooze|second]] and [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles III|third]] films were distributed by [[20th Century Fox]] outside [[North America]]. The [[TMNT (film)|fourth]], released in 2007 by [[Warner Bros.]], was an all-CGI animated film.

A new feature film is expected in 2012 as part of the acquisition of the franchise by Viacom. It was announced on May 27, 2010 that [[Michael Bay]]'s [[Platinum Dunes]] production company had landed the rights to the new film. It is expected that Bay, [[Bradley Fuller]] and Andrew Form will serve as executive producers. TMNT will be a co-production between Paramount and Nickelodeon.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theibug.com/articles/teenage-mutant-ninja-turtles-is-coming-with-nunchucks-and-michael-bay|title=Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Is Coming With Nunchucks and Michael Bay}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it will be a [[Reboot (fiction)|reboot]] film as opposed to another sequel.

==Merchandise==

Among the first licensed products to feature the Ninja Turtles was a pen and paper [[Role-playing game|RPG]] titled ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles &amp; Other Strangeness]]'', published by [[Palladium Books]] in 1985 and featuring original comics and illustrations by Eastman and Laird themselves. The game features a large list of animals, including pandas and sparrows, that are available as mutant [[player character]]s. There were several more titles in this genre, including ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Adventures (role-playing game supplement)|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Adventures]]'', ''[[Truckin' Turtles]]'', ''[[Turtles Go Hollywood]]'', ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Guide to the Universe]]'', and ''[[Transdimensional Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]''. In 1986, Dark Horse Miniatures in Boise, Idaho produced an attendant set of [[figurines|lead figurines]]; unlike later incarnations the bandanas on the store's display set were painted all black before the multicolored versions were released to help younger readers distinguish between the four characters other than their weaponry. Palladium allowed the license to lapse in 2000, in part due to declining sales stemming from the &quot;kiddification&quot; of the animated and live-action incarnations to that point. However, Palladium's publisher, [[Kevin Siembieda]], has indicated a potential willingness to revisit the license given the franchise's recent moves closer to its roots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://recordings.talkshoe.com/TS-9655.mp3 |title=Kevin Siembieda Interview, Part 2|date=2007-02-19 |last=Meadows |first=Chris |accessdate=2007-02-20 |format=mp3 |work=Space Station Liberty}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Toys===
{{Main|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles action figures}}
During the run of the 1987 TV series, Playmates Toys produced hundreds of TMNT [[action figure]]s, along with vehicles, [[playset]]s, and accessories, becoming one of the top collectibles for children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Rapid-Paced Turtle Sales Starting to Slow Down : Toys: Rival manufacturers see a cooling of the 'Ninja' fad as a chance to regain a larger share of the market. |work= The Los Angeles Times|date=1991-12-23|url= http://articles.latimes.com/1991-12-23/business/fi-809_1_toy-manufacturers|accessdate=2010-11-09|first=Carla|last=Lazzareschi}}&lt;/ref&gt; Staff artists at Northampton, Massachusetts-based [[Mirage Studios]] provided conceptual designs for many of the figures, vehicles, and playsets and creator credit can be found in the legal text printed on the back of the toy packaging. The line featured many different variants of the TMNT, such as &quot;Farmer Mike&quot; and &quot;Classic Rocker Leo&quot;. In addition, Playmates produced a series of TMNT/[[Star Trek]] crossover figures, due to Playmates holding the Star Trek action figure license at the time. Playmates employed many design groups to develop looks and styles for the ongoing toy line, including Bloom Design, White Design, Pangea, Robinson-Clarke, and McHale Design. Comic reality was maintained by visual artists at each of the firms, creating a wide range of compelling styles. The writing on the packaging came predominately from Pangea and White Design. Ancillary in-pack items, like the Turtle Maps and joke books were also wildly popular. All in all, the shows were often inspired by the collaboration of all these visual and written elements coming together. The Marketing VP of Playmates, Karl Aaronian, was largely responsible for assembling the talented team of designers and writers, which in turn, helped germinate continued interest in the toy line. Never before in toy history did an action figure line have such an impact for over two decades, generating billions of dollars in licensing revenue.

The series was highly popular in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] where, in the run-up to Christmas, the [[Army &amp; Navy Stores (United Kingdom)|Army &amp; Navy Store]] in [[London]]'s [[Lewisham]] devoted its entire basement to everything Turtle, including games, videos, costumes, and other items.

Playmates continues to produce TMNT action figures based on the 2003 animated series. The 2007 film, ''TMNT'', also gave Playmates a new source from which to make figures. And in September 2007, [[National Entertainment Collectibles Association|NECA]] announced that they would produce figures based on character designs from the original Mirage comics. As of April 2008 there have been toys released of the four turtles with their weapons, a piece of an interhooking platform, a can of ooze, an unmutated turtle toy, and two alternate hands. It features a detailed color/design job as well as 20 points of articulation. August 2008, NECA announced a second wave, featuring Shredder, Casey Jones, and a Foot Soldier, but the future of the NECA line is unknown with Playmates releasing 25th anniversary TMNT toys.

==Video games==
{{Main|List of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles video games}}
The first Famicom/[[Nintendo Entertainment System|NES]] TMNT game was the single-player ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (NES game)|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]'', released by [[Konami]]/Ultra in 1989. It was unique in that at any point, the player could switch from one turtle to the next to take advantage of each Turtle's strengths. In addition, the player starts off in a strategic map where the player may explore sewer holes as well as engage patrolling enemy foot soldiers before entering any in-game portals. The game was also released on the many home computers, but these conversions were hastily made and got negative reviews. Years later the game was released for the [[Wii]] on the [[Virtual Console]].

Also released by Konami in 1989 was the first [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (arcade game)|TMNT arcade game]], also titled simply ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles''. This [[Side-scrolling game|side-scrolling]] &quot;[[beat 'em up]]&quot; was ported to the NES as ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles II: The Arcade Game''. This led to an NES-only sequel, entitled ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles III: The Manhattan Project]]'', which used the look of the arcade game, as opposed the first NES game. The next Turtles console game, ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Turtles in Time]]'', was released in 1991 as an arcade game, and was later ported to the [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|Super Nintendo]] in 1992. ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: The Hyperstone Heist]]'' was also created for the [[Sega Genesis]] in the same year, and used many of the art assets from ''TMNT IV''.

There was also a trilogy of TMNT video games for the original [[Game Boy]] system made by Konami, consisting of: ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Fall of the Foot Clan]]'', ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles II: Back from the Sewers]]'', and ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles III: Radical Rescue]]''.

As the video game series progressed, programmers began to incorporate unique signature moves for each Turtle, as well as game features such as &quot;Versus mode&quot; and &quot;Time Attack mode&quot;. When the Ninja Turtles' popularity began to decline in the mid-nineties, the video games changed direction. ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Tournament Fighters]]'' was released as a one-on-one [[fighting game]] similar to the [[Street Fighter|''Street Fighter'' series]]. It is of note that, whilst this game would see release on both the Mega Drive/Genesis and Super Nintendo consoles using similar art assets, the games are essentially different (a common occurrence for 16-bit licensed titles of the era, such as ''[[Disney's Aladdin (video game)|Disney's Aladdin]]'').

Konami also acquired the license to adapt the 2003 TV series into a video game franchise, resulting in a new series of games with the same [[button mashing]] gameplay as the old TMNT &quot;beat 'em ups&quot; (''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (2003 video game)]]'', ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles 2: Battle Nexus]]'', and ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles 3: Mutant Nightmare]]''). In 2006, [[Ubisoft]] acquired the rights of TMNT games, beginning with [[TMNT (video game)|a game based on the 2007 animated feature film]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.starpulse.com/news/index.php/2006/01/11/ubisoft_to_create_video_game_based_on_20 Ubisoft to create video game based on 2007 TMNT movie]&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[beat 'em up]], ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Arcade Attack'', was released for the [[Nintendo DS|DS]] in November 2009, to coincide with the series' 25th anniversary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ds.ign.com/articles/102/1021102p1.html Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles:Arcade Attack hands-on] ign.com&lt;/ref&gt;

==In other media==
===Food tie-ins===
{{Main|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles food tie-ins}}
During the height of their popularity (1987–1996) the Turtles had a number of food tie-ins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= 'Turtles' Tapes Being Served at Burger King|work= The Los Angeles Times|date=1990-04-13|url= http://articles.latimes.com/1990-04-13/entertainment/ca-1355_1_burger-king|accessdate=2010-11-09|first=Dennis|last=Hunt}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Among the most notable of these products was Ninja Turtles Cereal, produced by [[Ralston-Purina]] as a kind of &quot;Chex with TMNT-themed marshmallows&quot; which also came with a small pouch of Pizza Crunchabungas, pizza flavored corn snacks in the shape of pizzas (the commercial starred the Ninja Turtles as [[Will Vinton]]-created claymations); [[Hostess (brand)|Hostess]] Ninja Turtles Pudding Pies, featuring a green sugar crust and vanilla pudding inside; and Royal OOZE Gelatin Desserts, distributed by [[Nabisco]] under &quot;Royal Gelatin&quot; in three different flavors: orange, strawberry, and lime. [[Shreddies]] used to give out TMNT toys in their boxes when the cereal advertising was still geared toward children. One example of a TMNT prize was rings featuring a character on the cartoon (1992). There was also green Ninja Turtle ice cream with different toppings according to which turtle flavour one ordered. [[Chef Boyardee]] also released a canned pasta with the pasta in the shapes of the four turtles themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Mutant Merchandise|publisher= [[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=|url= http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,317055,00.html|accessdate=2010-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Concert tour===
To further add to the Turtles' popularity, a concert tour was held in 1990, premiering at [[Radio City Music Hall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Music news for August 17, 1990 -- Prince and the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles made news this week|publisher= [[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=|url= http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,317967,00.html|accessdate=2010-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Review/Music; After the Hype, an Elaborate High-Tech Show for the Ninja Turtles Set |work= The New York Times|date=1990-09-28|url= http://www.nytimes.com/1990/09/28/arts/review-music-after-hype-elaborate-high-tech-show-for-ninja-turtles-set.html?scp=4&amp;sq=ninja%20turtles%20review&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2010-11-09|first=Jon|last=Pareles}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;Coming Out of Their Shells&quot; tour featured live-action turtles playing music as a band (Donatello; keyboards, Leonardo; bass guitar, Raphael; drums &amp; sax, Michelangelo; guitar) on stage around a familiar plotline: April O'Neil is kidnapped by the Shredder, the turtles have to rescue her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Turtles Shell Out Ninja Concert Fun |publisher= The Los Angeles Times|date=1990-11-30|url= http://articles.latimes.com/1990-11-30/entertainment/ca-5464_1_ninja-turtle-sheets|accessdate=2010-08-27|first1=Ted|last1=Granberry|first2=Nancy|last2=Churnin}}&lt;/ref&gt; The story had a very [[Bill &amp; Ted's Excellent Adventure|Bill-n'-Ted]]-esque feel, with its theme of the power of [[rock n' roll]] literally defeating the enemy, in the form of the Shredder (who only rapped about how he hates music) trying to eliminate all music. A pay-per-view special highlighting the concert was shown, and a studio album was also released. Stylistically, the music's genre was closest to [[hair metal]]/[[power rock]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Shell Schlocked|publisher= [[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=|url= http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,318331,00.html|accessdate=2010-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The track listing is as follows:
{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
# &quot;Coming Out of Our Shells!&quot;
# &quot;Sing About It&quot;
# &quot;Tubin'&quot;
# &quot;Skipping Stones&quot;
# &quot;Pizza Power&quot;
# &quot;Walk Straight&quot;
# &quot;No Treaties&quot;
# &quot;Cowabunga&quot;
# &quot;April Ballad&quot;
# &quot;Count on Us&quot;
|}

Since the tour was sponsored by [[Pizza Hut]] in real life, there are many references to their pizza. Empty Pizza Hut boxes are seen onscreen during the &quot;Behind The Shells&quot; VHS. As part of a cross-marketing strategy, Pizza Hut restaurants gave away posters, audio cassettes of &quot;Coming Out of Their Shells&quot;, and &quot;Official Tour Guides&quot; as premiums.

The original show of the tour was released on video with a making of video also released. The song &quot;Pizza Power&quot; was later used by [[Konami]] for the second arcade game ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles: Turtles in Time]]''.

===At the Disney-MGM Studios Theme Park===
[[File:MGMTMNT.jpg|right|thumb|The TMNT as they appeared at Disney-MGM Studios.]]
On June 30, 1990 the TMNT appeared in the &quot;New York Street&quot; section of [[Disney's Hollywood Studios|Disney-MGM Studios]] theme park in [[Orlando, Florida|Orlando]]. Emerging from their Turtle Party Wagon, they would &quot;ninja dance&quot; across the stage while April performed the theme song to the show. After the main show was done they would pose for pictures and sign autographs.

The Turtles made appearances in Walt Disney's &quot;Very Merry Christmas Parade&quot; to sing their own rendition of &quot;Santa Claus is Coming to Town&quot;. They also appeared during the Easter parade dancing to their single &quot;Pizza Power!&quot; The Turtles' live shows and appearances ceased production in 1996.

==Parodies==
[[File:Cracked Issue 255.jpg|right|thumb|140px|Cover of ''Cracked'' #255, Aug 1990]]

Although the TMNT had originated as something of a parody, the comic's explosive success led to a wave of small-press, black &amp; white comic parodies of ''TMNT'' itself, including ''[[Adolescent Radioactive Black Belt Hamsters]]'', ''[[Pre-Teen Dirty-Gene Kung Fu Kangaroos]]'', and a host of others. Dark Horse Comics' ''[[Boris the Bear]]'' was launched in response to these TMNT clones; its first issue was titled &quot;Boris the Bear Slaughters the Teenage Radioactive Black Belt Mutant Ninja Critters.&quot;
Once the Turtles broke into the mainstream, parodies also proliferated in other media, such as in satire magazines ''[[Cracked (magazine)|Cracked]]'' and ''[[MAD Magazine]]'' and numerous TV series of the period.

==Controversy==
===Departure from origins===

In keeping with the &quot;grim 'n gritty&quot; feel of Frank Miller's Ronin/Elektra material, the Turtles engaged in a greater amount of overt [[violence]] in the pages of the early Mirage comic book series. As the TMNT were introduced into the [[mainstream]], they were radically redesigned for a younger audience in the children's spinoff universes beginning with the first cartoon. Some fans of the independently-published comic series were disappointed that the artistic tone had shifted.{{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}  In issue #19 of ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles'', the creators published an [[editorial]] addressing these concerns. It stated, in part: &quot;We've allowed the wacky side to happen, and enjoy it very much. All the while, though, we've kept the originals very much ours – forty pages of what we enjoy and want to see in our books, whether it comes from our own hands or from those of the talented people we work with.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (Mirage Studios)|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]] vol. 1 #19, March, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the film ''[[Turtles Forever]]'', the original Mirage Turtles refer to their descendents as &quot;sell-outs,&quot; in reference to their colorful accessories (the originals are conveyed in black and white).

===Teenage Mutant &quot;Hero&quot; Turtles===
[[File:TMNTCensoredTitle.jpg|frame|right|The title screen from the TMHT version, altered due to censorship.]]
Upon TMNT's first arrival in the [[United Kingdom]], [[Ireland]], [[Sweden]], [[Norway]], [[Finland]], [[Poland]], [[Austria]], [[Germany]], and some other countries in [[Europe]], the name was changed to &quot;Teenage Mutant ''Hero'' Turtles&quot; (or TMHT, for short), since local [[censorship]] policies deemed the word ''ninja'' to have excessively violent connotations for a children's program (in Ireland, however, the first season aired as &quot;Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles&quot; before changing to &quot;Teenage Mutant Hero Turtles&quot;).&lt;ref name=cohen&gt;{{cite news| first= Susan| last= Cohen| title= Teenage Mutant Ninja Television: Who's winning the battle over kids' TV?| publisher= Washington Post Magazine| date= 1991-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, everything related to the Turtles had to be renamed before being released in these nations (comic books, video games, toys, etc.) The lyrics were also changed, such as changing &quot;Splinter taught them to be ''ninja'' teens&quot; to the &quot;Splinter taught them to be ''fighting'' teens.&quot;

The policies also had other effects, such as removing use of Michelangelo's [[nunchaku]] (which were at the time banned from appearing in [[Rated 18|18-rated movies]]) and generally toning down the usage of all the turtles' weapons.&lt;ref name=FAQ&gt;[http://www.ninjaturtles.com/html/faq.htm NinjaTurtles.com FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; After many seasons of never using his nunchaku, they eventually disappeared entirely, replaced by a turtle shell shaped [[grappling hook]] called the &quot;Turtle Line&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ezine.kungfumagazine.com&quot;/&gt; In [[Italy]], [[Spain]] and [[Portugal]], they kept Michelangelo's Nunchakus and kept the same title but translated. Also, The [[Italian language|Italian]] and [[European Portuguese|Portugese]] dubs had few edits. In Spain the cartoon had different dubs depending on the region, as well as [[Spanish language|Castillian Spanish]], for example [[Galician language|Galician]], [[Catalan language|Catalan]] and [[Valencian]] language, among others.

However, when the [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (film)|live-action movie]] came out in 1990, the &quot;Ninja&quot; of the title was kept even in the UK. In time, nunchaku scenes were retained in previously-censored movies such as those of [[Bruce Lee]]. The same went for the PAL releases of the early video games, which had Michelangelo's weapon of choice fully visible and usable.

By the time of the 2003 TV series, these censorship policies had been abolished, and no changes have occurred in the content of the show. The name &quot;Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles&quot; remained unchanged for the 2003 TV series. As a result, in the UK, the 1987 TV series is still called ''Teenage Mutant Hero Turtles'' and the 2003 TV series is called ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles'', hence a disambiguation between the two TV series.

On May 25, 2009, [[Lionsgate]] Home Entertainment released the 25th Anniversary Collectors Edition on Region 2 DVD in the UK. This 3-Disc set contains all the episodes of Seasons 1 and 2 and 4 episodes from the final season, as well as a 1-Disc DVD with the first few episodes of Season 1. This release features the original, unedited episodes under the Ninja Turtles title, and also marks the first time the show has been released uncensored in the UK.

==Ownership rights==
Due to various movie and television deals, the various TMNT films &amp; television series have split between various companies, with Mirage Studios having retained copyright and trademark until October 19, 2009, at which point the rights for the entire TMNT franchise were sold by co-creator Peter Laird to [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nickelodeon&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Hall|first=Peter |url=http://amazon.imdb.com/news/ni1106749/ |title=So Much for a Dark and Twisted 'Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles' Movie |publisher=amazon.imdb.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===TV series===

The original animated series (1987–1996) was produced by [[Fred Wolf Films Dublin]] (as '''Murakami Wolf Swenson''' ('''MWS''') and '''Murakami Wolf Dublin''' ('''MWD''') during earlier seasons), and syndicated by [[Westinghouse Broadcasting|Group W]]. The series itself is owned by Wolf Films, home entertainment rights reside with [[Lionsgate]], and until recently, syndication rights belonged to former [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] corporate sibling [[CBS Television Distribution]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

''[[Ninja Turtles: The Next Mutation]]'' was produced by [[Saban Entertainment]], and as of September 2011, is owned by [[Saban Capital Group|Saban Brands]] and distributed by [[MarVista Entertainment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Programming Catalog: Ninja Turtles: The Next Mutation|url=http://www.marvista.net/programing-catalog.php?n=2&amp;id=313&amp;cat=1|work=MarVista Entertainment|accessdate=September 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cynopsis: Kids!  09/19/11|url=http://www.cynopsis.com/editions/kids/091911/|accessdate=September 19, 2011|newspaper=Cynopsis|date=September 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pickard|first=Michael|title=MarVista picks up live Turtles|url=http://www.c21media.net/news/detail.asp?area=4&amp;article=62705|accessdate=September 19, 2011|newspaper=C21Media|date=September 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The second animated series (2003–2009) was a co-production between Mirage Studios and 4Kids Entertainment. Nickelodeon's October 19, 2009 buyout of the TMNT franchise included an approximate $9.75 million payment to 4Kids to terminate its right to serve as the merchandise licensing agent prior to the scheduled expiration of the representation agreement in 2012.&lt;ref name=Reuters/&gt; Due to the buyout, all future TMNT film and television series rights are owned by Nickelodeon.&lt;ref name=Nickelodeon/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Comics}}
*[[Table of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles character appearances]]
*[[List of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987) episodes]]
*[[List of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (2003) episodes]]
*[[List of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles video games]]
*[[List of anthropomorphic animal superheroes]]

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
*Eastman, Kevin (2002). ''Kevin Eastman's Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Artobiography''. Los Angeles: Heavy Metal. ISBN 1-882931-85-8.
*Wiater, Stanley (1991). ''The Official Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Treasury''. New York: Villard. ISBN 0-679-73484-8.

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
*[http://www.ninjaturtles.com Official Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles Website]
*[http://tmnt.wikia.com TMNTPedia]
*[http://www.toonopedia.com/turtles.htm ''Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles''] at [[Don Markstein's Toonopedia]]


&lt;!-- this article has its own category. If you'd like to add new ones
then please add them to the main category itself. thx --&gt;
{{Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles}}

[[Category:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles| ]]
[[Category:1984 introductions]]
[[Category:1984 comic debuts]]
[[Category:Animal superheroes]]
[[Category:Anthropomorphic martial artists]]
[[Category:Comics characters introduced in 1984]]
[[Category:Fictional ninja]]
[[Category:Fictional turtles]]
[[Category:Superhero teams]]
[[Category:Mirage Studios titles]]
[[Category:MTV Networks]]
[[Category:Nickelodeon]]
[[Category:Ninja parody]]
[[Category:Teens in fiction]]

[[ar:سلاحف النينجا]]
[[az:Nindza tısbağalar]]
[[bg:Костенурките нинджа]]
[[ca:Tortugues Ninja]]
[[cs:Želvy Ninja]]
[[da:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[de:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[el:Χελωνονιντζάκια]]
[[es:Tortugas Ninja]]
[[fa:لاک‌پشت‌های نینجا]]
[[fr:Les Tortues ninja]]
[[ko:닌자 거북이]]
[[hr:Nindža kornjače]]
[[id:Kura-kura Ninja]]
[[is:Ninjaskjaldbökurnar]]
[[it:Tartarughe Ninja]]
[[he:צבי הנינג'ה]]
[[ka:კუ-ნინძები]]
[[kw:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[lv:Bruņurupuči nindzjas]]
[[hu:Tini Nindzsa Teknőcök]]
[[ms:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[nl:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[ja:ティーンエイジ・ミュータント・ニンジャ・タートルズ]]
[[no:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[uz:Ninza Toshbaqalar]]
[[pl:Wojownicze Żółwie Ninja]]
[[pt:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[ru:Черепашки-ниндзя]]
[[simple:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[sr:Нинџа корњаче]]
[[fi:Teini-ikäiset mutanttininjakilpikonnat]]
[[sv:Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]
[[th:เต่านินจา]]
[[tg:Cанг‌пуштҳои Нинҷа Навҷавон Чаҳишёфта]]
[[tr:Ninja Kaplumbağalar]]
[[uk:Черепашки Ніндзя]]
[[zh:忍者龜]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
