<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4455408" ns="0" title="Anaconda Road Massacre"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Anaconda Road Massacre''' was a deadly incident that occurred on April 21, 1920 during a miners strike in [[Butte, Montana]]'s copper mines. A group of striking miners who were picketing near a mine of the [[Anaconda Copper Mining Company]] were fired upon by company guards, killing a miner named Tom Manning and injuring sixteen other miners. During the inquest into Manning's death, no one was found guilty, and his murder still remains officially unsolved.

==Strike and massacre==

On April 19, 1920, the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] (IWW) and the [[Metal Mine Workers Industrial Union]] called for a strike in the mines around Butte. They hoped the strike would help secure higher wages, an eight hour day, and end the use of the [[rustling card]], a system that allowed employers to blacklist employees involved in union organizing, among other goals.&lt;ref name=&quot;murphy&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Murphy | first = Mary | title = Mining Cultures | publisher = University of Illinois Press | date = 1997 | pages = 33 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Fpcb4vjVAk8C | isbn = 9780252065699}}&lt;/ref&gt; The strike came at a weak point for the union movement in Butte. World War I had undermined the power of the [[Butte Miners Union]] and the mines around the town were [[open shop]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Malone&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Malone | first = Michael P. | coauthors = Roeder, Richard B. and Lang, William L. | title = Montana: A History of Two Centuries | publisher = University of Washington Press | date = 1991 | pages = 328 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=p-P59FkOPg0C | isbn = 9780295971292}}&lt;/ref&gt; Only six years earlier, in 1914, the Butte Miners Union Hall had been destroyed. Rising copper prices, fatal mining accidents, and recruitment by the IWW had further exacerbated tensions in the town. Three years before the strike, an IWW organizer named Frank Little was beaten and hanged from a railroad trestle by unknown assailants. Thus, the strike began in an atmosphere of tension.&lt;ref name=&quot;walter&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Walter | first = David | title = More Montana Campfire Tales | publisher = Farcountry Press | date = 2002 | pages = 211–224 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=E_EEwRc9vi8C | isbn = 9781560372363}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The day the strike was called, picketers began blocking roads to mines in the area, including the Anaconda Road. These picketers turned non-striking miners away from the mines. By the second day of the strike, the picketers had succeeded in shutting down nearly all mining in Butte. The same day, a local newspaper called the Butte Daily Bulletin reported that the head of the [[Anaconda Copper Mining Company]] had suggested killings and hangings to help end the strike. On the 21st, the local sheriff deputized the Anaconda mine guards in an attempt to contain the strike.&lt;ref name=walter/&gt;

That afternoon, a few hundred picketers gathered outside the Anaconda company's Neversweat Mine. The sheriff arrived and apparently attempted to mediate the dispute.&lt;ref name=walter/&gt; However, the Anaconda mine guards opened fire on the picketers, although the reason why the shooting began is unclear. Sixteen miners were hit, and one, Tom Manning, was killed. All were shot in the back as they tried to flee.&lt;ref name=murphy/&gt; 

Federal troops arrived on the 22nd, ostensibly to prevent further violence.&lt;ref name=Malone/&gt; A labor newspaper that wrote about the strike was suppressed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Goldstein | first = Robert Justin | title = Political Repression in Modern America from 1870 to 1976 | publisher = University of Illinois Press | date = 2001 | pages = 158 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=2Za8lifq1mYC | isbn = 9780252069642}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three weeks later, the strike collapsed completely and the miners returned to work.&lt;ref name=murphy/&gt; No one was found guilty as a result of the massacre, despite an inquest into the death of Tom Manning. During the inquest, Anaconda employees testified that a shot had been fired at them from a boarding house across the street, something which residents of the boarding house disputed. Cross-examination of witnesses by union attorneys suggested that the Anaconda employees had received coaching to make their stories align. Anaconda attorneys attempted to undermine their accusers by pointing out that some of the miners had recently immigrated to the United States.&lt;ref name=walter/&gt; In the end, the jury declared that Manning had been killed by a bullet but that the bullet had been fired by unknown persons,&lt;ref name=murphy/&gt; and his murder  is still officially unsolved.&lt;ref name=walter/&gt;

The strike and massacre were the last major labor conflict in the area until the 1934 passage of the [[National Recovery Act]] allowed outside support to help rebuild the weakened Butte Miners Union.&lt;ref name=murphy/&gt;

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Conflicts in 1920]]
[[Category:Labor disputes in the United States]]
[[Category:Industrial Workers of the World]]
[[Category:Miners' labor disputes]]
[[Category:Butte, Montana]]
[[Category:Protest-related deaths]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
