<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4473608" ns="0" title="June Peppas"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox baseball biography
| name          = June Peppas 
| image         = June Peppas.jpg
| image_size         = 200px
| team          = [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League]] 
| position      = [[First base]]&lt;br&gt;[[Pitcher]]
| birth_date= {{Birth date and age|1929|6|16|mf=y}} 
| birth_place= [[Kansas City, Missouri]]
| death_date= 
| death_place= 
| bats          = Left
| throws        = Left
| debutyear     = 
| debutteam     =
| finalyear     = 
| finalteam     =
| stat1label    = [[Batting average]]
| stat1value    = .273
| stat2label    = [[Home run]]s
| stat2value    = &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; 21
| stat3label    = [[Runs batted in]]
| stat3value    = &amp;nbsp;257
| teams         =&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[Fort Wayne Daisies]] (1948-1949)
*[[Racine Belles]] (1949-1950)
*[[Battle Creek Belles]] (1951)
*[[Kalamazoo Lassies]] (1951-1954)
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*Two-time [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League All-Star Team|All-Star Team]] (1953-1954)
*[[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League#League Champions|AAGPBL Championship Title]] (1954)
*Ranks in the All-Time list in batting average (9th)&lt;br&gt;and home runs (14th)
*Women in Baseball – AAGPBL Permanent Display&lt;br&gt;Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum (1988)
}}

'''June Peppas''' (born June 16, 1929) is a former [[first base]]woman and [[pitcher]] who played from {{by|1948}} through {{by|1954}} in the [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League]]. Listed at 5' 5&quot;, 145&amp;nbsp;lb., she batted and threw [[left-handed]].

==Early life==
Peppas was born in [[Kansas City, Missouri]] and grew up in [[Fort Wayne, Indiana]]. As a student she was always involved in athletics, predominantly [[Pitch (baseball)|underhand]] [[fast-pitch softball|fast pitch softball]]. She graduated from [[Elmhurst High School]] in 1947, and from 1942 to 1947 played for a championship team sponsored by [[Harold Greiner]], owner of the Bob-Inn Restaurant in Fort Wayne. The team won state titles in 1944 and 1945, while Greiner, who [[scout (sport)|scouted]]  for the All-American  Professional Baseball League, recommended Peppas for the league's tryouts. She received contract offers from a professional softball league and the AAGPBL, but decided to join the All-Americans. She had a mother who had a bad cold all the time and had to use the money she earned to take care of her

==AAGPBL career==
In 1948, Peppas attended to [[spring training]] at [[Opa-locka, Florida]] and was assigned to the [[Fort Wayne Daisies]], playing for them one and a half year before joining the [[Racine Belles]] (1949-'50), [[Battle Creek Belles]] (1951) and [[Kalamazoo Lassies]] (1951-'54). She spent most of her time at first base and pitching, eventually appearing at [[outfield]]. 

According to the new league's regulations, Peppas had to make the transition from underhand to overhand pitching. Her unfamiliarity with the style and the ball size caused her negative results. 

In her [[rookie]] season, Peppas posted a 4-12 record with 39 [[strikeout]]s and 91 [[base on balls|walks]] in 113 innings for the Daisies, including a lousy 4.62 [[earned run average|ERA]] which ranked her near last place between the league pitchers. Nevertheless, she still had a respectable .264 [[batting average]]. In 1949, she played more games at first base and overcame her pitching control problems, going 3-4 with a 2.25 ERA while hitting .150 in 50 games, though she was bothered by two knee injuries.

In 1950, once Peppas overcame her injuries, her career blossomed. She hit .268 with a career-high 52 [[runs batted in]], including 11 [[Double (baseball)|doubles]], five [[Triple (baseball)|triples]], and four [[home run]]s. As a pitcher, she had a decent 4-4 record with a 4.57 ERA. But her control problems returned, as she walked more hitters than she struck out in 1950 (41-to-20) and 1951 (31-to-20). Her most productive seasons came with the Lassies, when she was selected at first base for the [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League All-Star Team|All-Star Team]] in 1953 and 1954, even though she often pitched. 

From 1952 to 1953, Peppas improved her batting averages from .262 to .271. In 1954 she drove in 54 runs and posted career-numbers with a .333 average, 16 home runs, and her only pitching winning season with a 6-4 record and a 3.32 ERA in 13 appearances. Her .333 average was a team’s best and the league’s fifth highest mark for girls who played at least 80 games. When Kalamazoo had to face the [[Fort Wayne Daisies]] for the AAGPBL Championship Title, Peppas  came through with a stellar performance.

==1954 Championship Title==
In Game 1 of the AAGPBL Series, the Lassies defeated the Daisies 17-9 behind a four-hit, seven strong innings from Peppas, who also helped herself by hitiing 2-for-4, including one home run. Her teammates [[Carol Habben]], [[Fern Shollenberger]] and [[Chris Ballingall]], who hit a [[Grand slam (baseball)|grand slam]], also slugged one each. [[Katie Horstman]] connected two home runs for the Daisies in a lost cause, and her teammate [[Joanne Weaver]] slugged one. [[Maxine Kline]], who had posted an 18-7 record with 3.23 ERA during the regular season, gave up 11 runs in six innings and was credited with the loss.

The Daisies evened the Series against the Lassies winning Game 2, 11–4, after hitting five home runs off two pitchers. Horstman started the feat with a two-run home run to open the score in the first inning. In the rest of the game, [[Betty Foss|Betty Weaver Foss]] added two homers with five RBI, while her sister Joanne and Geissinger added solo shots. [[Nancy Mudge]] and [[Dorothy Schroeder]] homered for Kalamazoo, while Peppas, who played first base, hit a solo homer in three at-bats.

In Game 3, the Daisies won the Lassies,  8–7, fueled fueled again by a heavy hitting by Joanne Weaver, who hit a double, a triple and a three-run home run in five at bats, driving in four runs. Peppas went 1-for-4 to spark a seventh inning three-run rally, but Fort Wayne came back in the bottom of the inning with two two runs that marked the difference.  
 
In other close score, the Lassies evened the Series in Game 4 with a victory over the Daisies, 6-5, behind a strong pitching effort by [[Gloria Cordes]], who hurled a [[complete game]]. Peppas contributed with a single, a double and one RBI in four at-bats.

In decisive Game 5, Peppas pitched a clutch complete game and went 3-for-5 with an RBI against her former Daisies team, winning by a 8–5 margin to gave the Lassies the Championship title in the AAGPBL's last ever game. She received support from Balingall (3-for-4) and Schroeder, who drove in the winning run in the bottom of the eight. Peppas finished with a .450 average and collected two of the three Lassies victories, to become the winning pitcher of the last game in the league's history.

==Private life==
Following her AAGPBL career, Peppas earned bachelor's and master's degrees in arts from the [[Western Michigan University]] during the late 1960s. She later taught vocational-education graphic arts and operated her own printing business, retiring in 1988. 

Since 1980, Peppas and a group of friends began assembling a list of names and addresses of former AAGPBL players. Her work turned into a newsletter that resulted in the league’s first-ever reunion in [[Chicago, Illinois]] in 1982. Starting from that reunion, a Players Association was formed five years later and many former AAGPBL players continued to enjoy reunions, which became annual events in 1998.

June Peppas is living currently in [[Jensen Beach, Florida]].

==Facts==
* The AAGPBL folded in 1954, but there is now a permanent display at the [[Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum]] at  [[Cooperstown, New York]] since November 5, {{by|1988}} that honors those who were part of this unique experience. Peppas, along with the rest of the league's girls, is now enshrined in the Hall.

* The AAGPBL Players Association helped to bring the league story to the public eye. The association was largely responsible for the opening of the aforementioned exhibition. As it is said, all began with the newsletter published by Peppas in 1980. Of the approximately 560 women who had played in the league, most had lost touch with the others; at least not until the first reunion held in Chicago two years later.
 
*''[[A League of Their Own]]'' is a [[1992 film]] about the first season of the All-American Girls Professional Baseball League. While the film does not use real names, [[filmmaker]] [[Penny Marshall]] seemed to be aiming for realism, as her film includes fake newsreel footage and pseudo-documentary ''present day'' scenes at the beginning and end of the [[fiction|fictitious]] story. ''A League of Their Own'' itself was inspired by the 1987 documentary of the same title, written and produced by [[Casey Candaele#Personal life|Kelly Candaele]], one of the five sons of [[Helen Callaghan]], who in 1945 won the AAGPBL batting championship with a .299 average. Like many of her colleagues, Peppas was relatively unknown until the Marshall's film was exhibited for the first time.

==Sources==
*''All-American Girls Professional Baseball League Record Book'' – W. C. Madden. Publisher: McFarland &amp; Company, 2000. Format: Paperback, 294pp. Language: English. ISBN 0-7864-3747-2

* ''Encyclopedia of women and baseball''' – Leslie A. Heaphy, Mel Anthony May. Publisher: McFarland &amp; Company, 2006. Format: Paperback, 438pp. Language: English. ISBN	0786421002

* ''The Guide to U.S. Popular Culture'' – Ray B. Browne, Pat Browne. Publisher: Popular Press 3, 2001. Format: Hardcover, 1010pp. Language: English. ISBN 0-87972-821-3

*''Women of the All-American Girls Professional Baseball League: A Biographical Dictionary'' - W. C. Madden. Publisher:  McFarland &amp; Company, 2005. Format: Paperback, 295 pp.&amp;nbsp;Language: English. ISBN 0-7864-3747-2

{{All-American Girls Professional Baseball League}}

==External links==
*[http://www.aagpbl.org/ All-American Girls Professional Baseball League Website]
*[http://bioproj.sabr.org/bioproj.cfm?a=v&amp;v=l&amp;bid=2389&amp;pid=19589 SABR Biography Project] –  [http://www.aagpbl.org/articles/biographies.cfm?ID=1 Jim Sargent]
*[http://www.thediamondangle.com/archive/aug01/junepeppas.html The Diamond Angle Interview] – [http://www.thediamondangle.com/parrotta/ Lou Parrotta]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Peppas, June
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =All-American Girls Professional Baseball League player
| DATE OF BIRTH     = June 16, 1929
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Kansas City, Missouri]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Peppas, June}}
[[Category:All-American Girls Professional Baseball League players]]
[[Category:American people of Greek descent]]
[[Category:Baseball players from Missouri]]
[[Category:People from Kansas City, Missouri]]
[[Category:1929 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
