<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4550" ns="0" title="Bikini"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the women's bathing suit}}
[[File:Bikini Model Jassi 3.jpg|thumb|175px|Woman wearing a bikini]]

The '''bikini''' is typically a women's two-piece [[swimsuit]]. One part of the attire covers the [[breast]]s and the other part covers the [[crotch]] and part of or the entire [[buttocks]], leaving an uncovered area between the two. ''[[Merriam–Webster]]'' describes the bikini as &quot;a woman's scanty two-piece bathing suit&quot; or &quot;a man's brief swimsuit&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;merriam-webster.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Bikini|publisher=''[[Merriam-Webster]]''|date=June 25, 2011|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/bikini}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is often worn in hot weather, while swimming or sunbathing. The shapes of both parts of a bikini resemble women's underwear, and the lower part can range from revealing [[thong (clothing)|thong]] or [[g-string]] to briefs. 

While two-piece bathing suits had been worn on the beach before, the modern bikini was invented by French engineer [[Louis Réard]] in 1946. He named it after [[Bikini Atoll]] in the Pacific, the site of the [[Operation Crossroads]] nuclear weapon tests in July that year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.swimsuit-style.com/bikini.html Swimsuit Trivia – The Surprising History of the Bikini]. Swimsuit-style.com. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.omg-facts.com/view/Facts/9262 The 'bikini' was named after Bikini Island in the Bikini Atoll where they used to test nuclear bombs.]. OMG Facts (2010-07-09). Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LalFortune2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Brij V. Lal|author2=Kate Fortune|title=The Pacific Islands: an encyclopedia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=T5pPpJl8E5wC&amp;pg=PA259|accessdate=5 July 2011|year=2000|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|isbn=9780824822651|page=259}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Foster2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Ruth Foster|title=Nonfiction Reading Comprehension: Social Studies, Grade 5|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5bWfeLfg_FoC&amp;pg=PA130|accessdate=5 July 2011|date=June 2007|publisher=Teacher Created Resources|isbn=9781420680300|page=130}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bikini is perhaps the most popular female beachwear around the globe, according to French fashion historian Olivier Saillard due to &quot;the power of women, and not the power of fashion&quot;. As he explains, &quot;The emancipation of swimwear has always been linked to the emancipation of women.&quot;&lt;ref name=BBCW&gt;Kathryn Westcott, &quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/5130460.stm The Bikini: Not a brief affair]&quot;, BBC News, 2006-06-05&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid 2000s, bikinis had become a $811 million business annually, according to the [[NPD Group]], a consumer and retail information company.&lt;ref name=SFC&gt;Sylvia Rubin, &quot;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/07/02/BIKINI.TMP&amp;type=printable Fashion shocker of '46: the naked belly button]&quot;, ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'', 2006-07-02&lt;/ref&gt; The bikini has boosted spin-off services like [[bikini wax]]ing and the suntanning industries.&lt;ref name=AgeL&gt;Lorna Edwards, &quot;[http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2006/06/02/1148956539436.html?page=fullpage#contentSwap1 You've still got it, babe], ''[[The Age]]'', 2006-06-03&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{main|History of the bikini}}
[[File:Casale Bikini.jpg|thumb|287px|The &quot;Bikini girls&quot; mosaic showing women exercising, first quarter of the 4th century AD. [[Villa Romana del Casale]], Sicily]]

Predecessors of the bikini date to [[Ancient history|antiquity]], in [[Çatalhöyük]]&lt;ref&gt;Prithvi Kumar Agrawala, ''Goddessess in Ancient India'', page 12, Abhinav Publications, 1984, ISBN 0391029606&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Greco-Roman world]].&lt;ref&gt;Peter J. James, I. J. Thorpe &amp; Nick Thorpe, ''Ancient Inventions'', page 279, Ballantine Books, 1994, ISBN 0345401026&lt;/ref&gt;  Art dating from the [[Diocletianic Persecution|Diocletian period]] (286–305 AD) in [[Villa Romana del Casale]], [[Sicily]] depicts women in garments resembling bikinis in mosaics on the floor.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt;&lt;ref name=VilCas&gt;[http://www.valdinoto.com/english/villa_romana_del_casale.htm Villa Romana del Casale], Val di Noto&lt;/ref&gt; The images of ten women, dubbed the &quot;Bikini Girls&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Allen Guttmann, ''Women's Sports: A History'', page 38, Columbia University Press, 1991, ISBN 023106957X&lt;/ref&gt; exercising in clothing that would pass as bikinis today are the most replicated mosaic among the 37 million colored tiles at the site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldheritagesite.org/sites/villaromanadelcasale.html Villa Romana del Casale], World Heritage Sites&lt;/ref&gt; Archeological finds, particularly in [[Pompeii]], show the Roman goddess [[Venus (mythology)|Venus]] wearing a bikini. A statue of Venus in a bikini was found in a cupboard in the southwest corner in Casa della Venere, others were found in the front hall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stoa.org/gallery/allison Pompeian Households], [http://www.stoa.org/gallery/albums.php Stoa Image Gallery], [http://www.stoa.org/ The Stoa Consortium]&lt;/ref&gt; A statue of Venus was recovered from the ''[[tablinum]]'' of the [[House of Julia Felix]],&lt;ref&gt;Mary Beard &amp; John Henderson, ''Classical Art'', page 116, Oxford University Press, 2001, ISBN 0192842374&lt;/ref&gt; and another from an [[Atrium (architecture)|atrium]] at the garden at [[House of Loreius Tiburtinus|Via Dell'Abbondanza]].&lt;ref&gt;Elisabeth B. MacDougall, Wilhelmina Mary Feemster Jashemski &amp; Dumbarton Oaks, ''Ancient Roman Gardens'', page 38, Dumbarton Oaks, 1979, ISBN 0884021009&lt;/ref&gt;

The groundwork for the modern bikini began to be laid in 1907, when Australian swimmer and performer [[Annette Kellerman]] was arrested on a [[Boston]] beach for wearing a form-fitting one-piece swimsuit, which became an accepted beach attire for women by 1910. In 1913, inspired by the introduction of women into Olympic swimming, designer [[Carl Jantzen]] made the first functional two-piece [[swimwear]], a close-fitting one-piece with shorts on the bottom and short sleeves on top.&lt;ref name=heritage&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/web/20060705-bikini-swimming-suit-louis-reard-micheline-bernardini-paris-brigitte-bardot.shtml|accessdate=2007-11-13|publisher=American Heritage Inc.|title=60 Years of Bikinis|author=Hoover, Elizabeth D.|date=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1930s, necklines plunged at the back, sleeves disappeared and sides were cut away. Hollywood endorsed the new glamour with films such as ''[[Neptune's Daughter (1949 film)|Neptune's Daughter]]'' in which [[Esther Williams]] wore provocatively named costumes such as &quot;Double Entendre&quot; and &quot;Honey Child&quot;.&lt;ref name=notting&gt;David Sandhu, &quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/sunandsea/728059/Nottingham-Bathed-in-nostalgia.html Nottingham: Bathed in nostalgia]&quot;, ''The Telegraph'' (UK), 2003-08-04&lt;/ref&gt; With new materials like [[latex]] and [[nylon]], by 1934 the swimsuit started hugging the body and had shoulder straps to lower for tanning.&lt;ref name=carnival&gt;[http://www.carnaval.com/bikini/#In%20Brazil History of the Bikini], Carnival&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MichelineBernardini.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Micheline Bernardini]] modeling the first modern bikinis]]

By the early 1940s two-piece swimsuits were frequent on American beaches. [[Hollywood]] stars such as [[Ava Gardner]], [[Rita Hayworth]] and [[Lana Turner]] tried similar swimwear or beachwear.&lt;ref name=3X24&gt;James Kitchling, [http://www.3x24.com/short-history-of-bikinis-and-swimsuits/801764 Short History of Bikinis and Swimsuits], 3X24 News Magazine&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pin up]]s of Hayworth and [[Esther Williams]] in the costume were widely distributed.&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt;

Finally, the modern bikini was introduced by French engineer [[Louis Réard]] and fashion designer [[Jacques Heim]] in Paris in 1946.  Réard was a car engineer but by 1946 he was running his mother's lingerie boutique near [[Folies Bergère|Les Folies Bergères]] in Paris.&lt;ref name=TimA&gt;Adam Sage, &quot;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article705414.ece Happy birthday: the 'shocking and immoral' bikini hits 60]&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 2006-04-16&lt;/ref&gt; Heim was working on a new kind of beach costume. It comprised two pieces, the bottom large enough to cover its wearer's navel. In May 1946, he advertised the bathing suit, known as the &quot;Atome,&quot; as the world's &quot;smallest bathing suit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, Thomas G., II, [http://www.genders.org/g53/g53_cole.html &quot;(The) Bikini: EmBodying the Bomb&quot;] ''Genders Journal''. para. 8&lt;/ref&gt; Réard named his swimsuit the &quot;bikini&quot;, taking the name from the [[Bikini Atoll]], one of a series of islands in the South Pacific where testing on the new atomic bomb was occurring that summer.  Historians assume Reard termed his swimsuit the &quot;bikini&quot; because he believed its revealing style would create reactions among people similar to those created by America’s atomic bomb in Japan just one summer earlier.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.randomhistory.com/1-50/002bikini.html Tiny Swimsuit That Rocked the World: A History of the Bikini]. Randomhistory.com (2007-05-01). Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt; Réard sliced the top off the bottoms and advertised it as &quot;smaller than the smallest swimsuit&quot;.&lt;ref name=Guard&gt;Paula Cocozza, &quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/travel/2006/jun/10/sttropez.filminspiredtravel.france.culturaltrips?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=travel A little piece of history]&quot;, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 2006-06-10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lil&gt;[http://www.lilith-ezine.com/articles/2006/The-Bikini.html The Bikini Turns 60], 1946 to 2006: 60 Years of Bikini Bathing Beauties, ''Lilith E-Zine''&lt;/ref&gt; Réard could not find a model to wear his design. He ended up hiring [[Micheline Bernardini]], a [[stripper|nude dancer]] from the Casino de Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bikiniscience.com/chronology/1945-1950_SS/LR4601_S/LR4601.html | title = Michele Bernadini: The First Bikini | first = Judson | last = Rosebush | work = Bikini Science | date = | accessdate = 2007-09-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; That bikini, a [[#String bikini|string bikini]] with a [[g-string]] back of {{convert|30|sqin|cm2|0}} of cloth with newspaper type printed across, was introduced on July 5 at [[Piscine Molitor]], a public pool in Paris.&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt;&lt;ref name=HistC&gt;[http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history.do?action=VideoArticle&amp;id=6949 Bikini Introduced], This Day in History, ''[[History Channel]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Heim's design was the first worn on the beach, but clothing was given its name by Réard.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt;

From a 1949 ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' report: &quot;The bathing beauty queen—blond [[BeBe Shopp|Bebe Shopp]], 18, of Hopkins, Minn.—got an enthusiastic welcome in Paris, but she said she hasn't changed her mind about French swim suits. ... 'I don't approve of Bikini suits for American girls,' Bebe told her French interviewers. 'The French girls can wear them if they want to, but I still don't approve of them on American girls.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Miss America Stops in Paris—Traffic, Too.&quot; ''Los Angeles Times''. August 7, 1949. p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brigitte Bardot]] is recognized for popularizing bikini swimwear in early films such as ''[[Manina, the Girl in the Bikini|Manina (Woman without a Veil)]]'' (1952) in her appearances at Cannes and in many photo shoots.&lt;ref name=menkes&gt;Suzy Menkes, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D81430F93BA25754C0A965958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2 Runways: Remembrance of Thongs Past]&quot;, ''The New York Times'', 1993-07-18&lt;/ref&gt; with Bardot identified as the original Cannes bathing beauty.&lt;ref&gt;Cari Beauchamp &amp; Henri Béhar, '' Hollywood on the Riviera: The Inside Story of the Cannes Film Festival‎'', page 165, W. Morrow and Co., 1992, ISBN 0-688-11007-X&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vanessa R. Schwartz, '' It's So French!: Hollywood, Paris, and the Making of Cosmopolitan Film Culture‎'', page 79, University of Chicago Press, 2007, ISBN 0-226-74243-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James Peterson, ''The Century of Sex'', page 184, Grove Press, 1999, ISBN 0-8021-1652-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bikini variants==
{{main|Bikini variant}}
[[File:Woman in black thong bikini with tattoo and wearing bracelets and wrist cuff.jpg|thumb|left|187px|String bikini]]

The bikini has spawned many stylistic variations. A regular bikini is defined as a two pieces of garments that cover the groin and buttocks at the lower end and the breasts in the upper end. Some bikinis can offer a large amount of coverage, while other bikinis provide only the barest minimum. Topless variants may still be considered bikinis, although technically no longer two-piece swimsuits.&lt;ref name=SStyle&gt;[http://www.swimsuit-style.com/bikini-swimsuit.html Bikini], Swimsuit Styles&lt;/ref&gt; Along with a variation in designs, the term ''bikini'' was followed by an often hilarious lexicon including the monokini (top part missing), seekini (transparent bikini), tankini ([[tank top]], bikini bottom), camikini ([[camisole]] top and bikini bottom) and hikini.&lt;ref&gt;Barry J. Blake, ''Playing with Words: Humour in the English Language'', page 59, Equinox, 2007, ISBN 1845533305&lt;/ref&gt; Since fashions of different centuries exist beside one another in early 21st century, though it is possible to imagine a woman combining a bikini and a 1910 bathing costume.&lt;ref&gt;Jacques Laurent &amp; Cécil Saint-Laurent, ''A History of Ladies Underwear'', page 214, Joseph, 1968, ISBN 0718106245&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Red polka tankini.jpg|thumb|167px|Tankini]]

Bikini tops come in different styles and cuts, including a halter-style neck that offers more coverage and support, a strapless [[bandeau]], a rectangular strip of fabric covering the breasts that minimizes large breasts, a top with cups similar to a [[Brassiere designs#&quot;Push-up&quot; bras|push-up bra]], and the more traditional triangle cups that lift and shape the breasts. Bikini bottoms vary in style and cut and in the amount of coverage they offer, coverage ranging anywhere from complete underwear-style coverage, as in the case of more modest bottom pieces like briefs, shorts, or briefs with a small skirt-panel attached, to almost full exposure, as in the case of the thong bikini. Skimpier styles have narrow sides, including V-cut (in front), French cut (with high-cut sides) and low-cut string (with string sides).&lt;ref name=SStyle/&gt; In just one major fashion show in 1985 were two-piece suits with [[Crop top|cropped tank tops]] instead of the usual skimpy bandeaux, suits that are bikinis in front and one-piece in back, [[Suspenders|suspender straps]], [[ruffle]]s, and daring, navel-baring cutouts.&lt;ref&gt;Fashion Correspondent, &quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=PI&amp;s_site=philly&amp;p_multi=PI&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EB29A230AE055D5&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM Swimsuits take some inspiration from the past]&quot;, ''Philadelphia Inquirer'', 1985-11-10&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent variations on the theme include the monokini, tankini, string bikini, thong, slingshot, minimini, teardrop, and micro.&lt;ref&gt;David Diefendorf &amp; James Randi, ''Amazing... But False!: Hundreds of &quot;Facts&quot; You Thought Were True, But Aren't'', page 33, Sterling, 2007, ISBN 1402737912&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bikini underwear===
Types of underwear worn by both men and women are identified as '''bikini underwear''', similar in size and revealing nature to the bottom half of a bikini bathing suit. For women, bikini underwear can refer to virtually any tight, skimpy, or revealing undergarment that provides less coverage to the midsection than traditional underwear, [[panties]] or knickers. For men, a bikini is a type of undergarment that is smaller and more revealing than men's briefs.

[[File:Floé Kühnert cropped.jpg|thumb|left|225px|German pole vaulter [[Floé Kühnert]]]]

==Sports bikini==
There is evidence of ancient Roman women playing ''Expulsim Ludere'', an early version of [[Team handball|handball]].&lt;ref&gt;John Anthony Cuddon, ''The Macmillan Dictionary of Sports and Games'', page 393, Macmillan, 1980, ISBN 0333191633&lt;/ref&gt; Female athletes who play [[beach volleyball]] professionally usually wear two-pieces. These bikinis are designed with functionality rather than fashion in mind.

[[File:Beach Volleyball 2007 (1436878831).jpg|thumb|right|167px|Sports bikini in [[Beach Volleyball]]]]

===Beach volleyball===
In 1994, the bikini became the official uniform of women's Olympic [[beach volleyball]], sparking controversy, with some sports officials considering it exploitative and unpractical in colder weather,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/sport/591787.stm Aussies opt for bikini cover-up]. BBC News (2000-01-05). Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt; and athletes admitting that the regulation uniform is intended to be &quot;sexy&quot; and to draw attention.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/sport/olympics/article4357036.ece?print=yes&amp;randnum=1151003209000 Denise Johns: There is more to beach volleyball than girls in bikinis]. Timesonline.co.uk. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt; Dancers, sex appeal and bikinis worn by women players as much as athletic ability made beach volleyball the fifth largest television audience of all the sports at the Games at [[Bondi Beach, New South Wales|Bondi Beach]] in Australia in 2000 Olympics.&lt;ref&gt;Stuff Writer, &quot;[http://sports.espn.go.com/oly/summer04/gen/news/story?id=1860176 Beach volleyball a popular spectator sport]&quot;, ''ESPN'', 2004-08-16&lt;/ref&gt; The popularity of ''[[Dead or Alive: Xtreme Beach Volleyball]]'', a video game for [[Xbox]], was attributed to the scantily clad women.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Harold, [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DD1731F934A3575BC0A9659C8B63 GAME THEORY; It's Hot-Potato Season: Call In the String Bikinis], New York Times, 2003-08-07; Retrieved: 2008-03-12&lt;/ref&gt;

===Athletics===
Often the women in [[athletics (sport)|athletics]] also wear bikinis, not much larger than in beach volleyball. [[Amy Acuff]], a US high-jumper, wore a black leather bikini instead of a track suit, at Sydney [[2000 Summer Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;Staff Correspondent, &quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=ST&amp;s_site=dfw&amp;p_multi=ST&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EAF9290227B1DAA&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM Hype Hopes Today's Olympians need more than athletic prowess to win gold]&quot;, ''Fort Worth Star-Telegram'', 2000-08-06&lt;/ref&gt; Runner [[Florence Griffith-Joyner]] mixed bikini bottoms with one-legged [[tights]] in Seoul [[1988 Summer Olympics]], which earned her more attention than her record breaking in Women's 200 meters.&lt;ref&gt;Anne Marie Balsamo, ''Technologies of the gendered body'', page 46, Duke University Press, 1996, ISBN 0822316986&lt;/ref&gt; Towns like [[Porto Seguro]] in Brazil has become an attraction for beach athletics in bikini for the tourists.&lt;ref&gt;James Brooke, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE103DF933A25750C0A967958260 In the Land of Lambada]&quot;, 1991-03-10&lt;/ref&gt;

===Controversy===
Skimpy bikinis have been a major component of marketing women's sports, raising some objections.&lt;ref&gt;Laura Grae Kilborn, &quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=DP&amp;p_theme=dp&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EAF44E9A0508C03&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM The Marketing Of Female Athletes]&quot;, ''Denver Post'', 1998-08-11&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, fans voted for contestants in the [[WWE Diva]] contest after watching them playing beach volleyball in skimpy bikinis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.propeller.com/viewstory/2007/09/18/wwe-diva-contestants-playing-bikini-beach-volleyball-who-is-your-favorite/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.gnewsworld.com%2FWWEDivaSearch&amp;frame=true WWE Diva Search], Propeller News, 2007-09-18; Retrieved: 2008-03-12&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2004 and 2008 [[Olympic Games]], inclusion of bikini-clad athletes raised eyebrows, while a controversy broke out around bikini-clad [[cheerleaders]] performing at a beach volleyball match.&lt;ref&gt;Phil Gordos, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/olympics_2004/volleyball/3596738.stm Bikini girls making waves], BBC, 2004-08-25; Retrieved: 2008-03-12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press, [http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/5705620/ Beach volleyball’s bikini cheerleaders stir up a storm], NBC sports, 2004-08-17; Retrieved: 2008-03-12&lt;/ref&gt; Bikinis stirred up a controversy at the 2006 [[Asian Games]] at Doha, Qatar, and the Iraqi teams refused to wear such clothing.&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press, [http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3335511,00.html In Doha, beach volleyball bikinis create cultural clash], Ynet News, 2006-03-12; Retrieved: 2008-03-12&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2007 [[South Pacific Games]], players were made to wear shorts and cropped sports tops instead of bikinis.&lt;ref&gt;Staff Correspondent, [http://www.news.com.au/story/0,23599,22339200-23109,00.html No bikinis for beach volleyball players], The News, 2007-08-31; Retrieved: 2008-03-12&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[West Asian Games]] 2006, bikini-bottoms were banned for female athletes, who were asked to wear long shorts.&lt;ref&gt;Staff Correspondent, &quot;[http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/articleshow/661034.cms Unveiling the spirit of the sporting women]&quot;, ''The Economic Times'', 2006-12-01&lt;/ref&gt; String bikinis and other skimpy clothes are also common in [[surfing]], paving the way for some [[hooliganism]] in the past.&lt;ref&gt;Matt Krantz, &quot;[http://www.usatoday.com/money/advertising/2001-08-03-surf.htm Sponsors get gnarly idea: Surf sells, dude]&quot;, ''USA Today'', 2001-08-06&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2011, [[Barcelona]], [[Spain]] made it illegal to wear bikinis in public except in areas near the beaches. Violators face fines of between 120 and 300 euros.&lt;ref&gt;Fiona Govan, &quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/spain/8548124/Barcelona-bans-bikinis-on-its-streets.html Barcelona bans bikinis on its streets]&quot;, ''The Telegraph'', 2011-05-31&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:František Huf.jpg|thumb|175px|left|Posing brief in a [[bodybuilding]] contest]]

==Men's bikini==
The term '''men's bikini''' is used to describe types of [[Swim briefs|men's swimsuits]], men's underwear, or similar garments. Men's bikinis can have both high or low side panels, string sides or tie sides, and most lack a button or flap front. Many do not have a visible waistband like briefs. Suits less than 1.5&amp;nbsp;inches wide at the hips are less common for sporting purposes and are most often worn for recreation, [[fashion]], and [[sun tanning]]. An example of this style, known as the posing brief, is the standard for competitions in the sport of [[bodybuilding]]. Male [[punk rock]] musicians have performed on the stage wearing women's bikini briefs.&lt;ref&gt;A. W. Richard Sipe, ''A Secret World'', page 25, Psychology Press, 1990, ISBN 0876305850&lt;/ref&gt; The 2000 [[Bollywood]] film ''[[Hera Pheri (2000 film)|Hera Pheri]]'' shows men sunbathing in bikinis, who were mistakenly believed to be girls from a distance by the protagonist.&lt;ref&gt;Ruth Vanita, ''Queering India'', page 207, Routledge, 2002, ISBN 0415929504&lt;/ref&gt;

Swimsuits shown in men's wear collections by [[Giorgio Armani]], [[Dolce &amp; Gabbana]] or [[Paul Smith (fashion designer)|Paul Smith]] have tended to be black and snug fitting, throwbacks to the designs of the 1930s and '40s, while [[Gianni Versace]]'s ads with their heroic depictions of Miami bathers in contrast to popular, sports-inspired beach wear—bright and baggy Bermudas or boxer shorts. The Greek designer [[Nikos Apostolopoulos]] put a different spin on his bathing suits (for both sexes, but with the focus on the male), making them anatomical creations, cut and stitched to outline the body and its sexual characteristics.&lt;ref name=menkes&gt;Suzy Menkes, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D81430F93BA25754C0A965958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2 Runways: Remembrance of Thongs Past]&quot;, ''The New York Times'', 1993-07-18&lt;/ref&gt;
Bikini tops for men are seen as an amusement factor.&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Karnasiewicz, [http://www.salon.com/mwt/broadsheet/2006/01/19/mr_saugus/ Here she comes, &quot;Mr. Saugus High School&quot;], Salon.com&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mankini (cropped).jpg|thumb|right|80px|Mankini]]

===Mankini===
'''Mankini''' is a type of sling bikini worn by men. It was popularized by [[Sacha Baron Cohen]] when he donned one in the film ''[[Borat]]''. The buzz around the film started building during the [[Cannes Film Festival]] in May 2006, when Baron Cohen posed in character on the beach in a neon green mankini, alongside four models.&lt;ref&gt;Josh Friedman &amp; Lorenza Munoz, &quot;[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/1150656071.html?dids=1150656071:1150656071&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Oct+25%2C+2006&amp;author=Josh+Friedman+and+Lorenza+Munoz&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;desc=Fox+scales+back+%60Borat%27+movie%27s+opening%3B+The+comedy+will+first+be+shown+in+800+theaters%2C+down+from+2%2C000%2C+amid+a+lack+of+awareness.&amp;pqatl=google Fox scales back `Borat' movie's opening; The comedy will first be shown in 800 theaters, down from 2,000, amid a lack of awareness]&quot;, ''The Los Angeles Times'', page C1, 2006-10-25&lt;/ref&gt; A [[garden gnome]] in the 2011 film ''[[Gnomeo and Juliet]]'' was also shown wearing a mankini, which gets referred to as a Borat-Mankini by newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digg.be/movie.php?id=2332 Gnomeo and Juliet film bespreking Digg* filmbespreking]. Digg.be. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/ent/movies/mobile/7422124.html Gnomeo &amp; Juliet – Houston Chronicle]. Chron.com (2011-02-10). Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
* [[Bikini in popular culture]] {{nb10}}
* [[Bikini waxing]]
* [[Burqini]]
* [[Men's bikini]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Monokini]]
* [[Swimsuit]]
* [[Tankini]]
* [[White bikini of Ursula Andress]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Bikini}}
&lt;!-- Do not add links to shops or other commercial sites here, they will just be removed. Wikipedia is not a marketing channel, advertising service or web directory. --&gt;
* [http://www.freezonal.com/weird-history-of-bikini.html Weird History of Bikini]
* [http://www.bikiniscience.com/bsmain.html Bikini Science: A comprehensive site on the bikini]
* [http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/biki/hd_biki.htm Bikini exhibition]

{{Navboxes
|title=Articles and topics related to Bikini
|state=collapsed
|list1=
{{Clothing}}
{{Lingerie}}
{{men's undergarments}}
}}

[[Category:History of fashion]]
[[Category:1946 introductions]]
[[Category:Bikini Atoll]]
[[Category:Bikinis|*]]

[[af:Bikini]]
[[als:Bikini]]
[[ar:بكيني]]
[[bn:বিকিনি]]
[[br:Bikini (dilhad)]]
[[bg:Бикини]]
[[ca:Biquini]]
[[cs:Bikiny]]
[[cy:Bicini (dilledyn)]]
[[da:Bikini]]
[[pdc:Bikini]]
[[de:Bikini]]
[[et:Bikiinid]]
[[es:Bikini]]
[[eo:Bikino]]
[[eu:Bikini]]
[[fa:بیکینی]]
[[fr:Bikini (vêtement)]]
[[ko:비키니]]
[[hi:बिकनी]]
[[hr:Bikini]]
[[ilo:Bikini]]
[[id:Bikini]]
[[it:Bikini]]
[[he:ביקיני]]
[[lv:Bikini]]
[[lt:Bikinis]]
[[hu:Bikini (fürdőruha)]]
[[mk:Бикини (костим за капење)]]
[[arz:بيكينى]]
[[nl:Bikini (kleding)]]
[[ja:ビキニ (水着)]]
[[no:Bikini (klesplagg)]]
[[nrm:Bikini]]
[[pl:Bikini]]
[[pt:Biquíni]]
[[ksh:Bikini]]
[[ro:Bikini]]
[[ru:Бикини]]
[[simple:Bikini]]
[[sl:Bikini]]
[[sr:Бикини]]
[[sh:Bikini]]
[[fi:Bikinit]]
[[sv:Bikini]]
[[tl:Bikini]]
[[th:บิกินี]]
[[tr:Bikini]]
[[uk:Бікіні (одяг)]]
[[vi:Bikini]]
[[yi:ביקיני]]
[[zh:比基尼泳衣]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
