<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4554716" ns="0" title="Collaboration with the Axis Powers during World War II"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{WorldWarIISegmentUnderInfoBox}}

Within nations occupied by the  [[Axis Powers]], some citizens, driven by [[nationalism]], [[ethnic hatred]], [[anti-communism]], [[anti-Semitism]] or [[opportunism]], knowingly engaged in '''collaboration with the Axis Powers during World War II'''. Some of these [[collaborationist]]s committed the worst crimes and atrocities of the [[Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ushmm&quot;/&gt;

Collaboration ranged from urging the civilian population to remain calm and accept foreign occupation without conflict, organizing trade, production, financial and economic support to joining various branches of the armed forces of the [[Tripartite Pact|Axis powers]] or special &quot;national&quot; military units fighting under their command.

==Requirements for collaboration==
The Nazis did not consider everyone equally fit for cooperation. Even people from closely related nations were often valued differently in accordance with [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|Nazi racial theories]].
The [[Jew]]s were considered to be worst of all nations and thus unfit for cooperation, although some were used in [[concentration camp]]s as [[Kapo (concentration camp)|Kapos]] to report on other prisoners and enforce order. Others governed [[Ghettos in occupied Europe 1939 - 1944|ghettos]] and helped organize [[deportation]]s to [[extermination camp]]s ([[Jewish Ghetto Police]]).

==By country==
===Albania===
{{See also|Axis-Cham Albanian collaboration}}

In April 1943, ''Reichsfuhrer''-SS [[Heinrich Himmler]] created the [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)]] manned by [[Albanians|Albanian]] and [[Kosovar Albanian]] [[volunteer]]s . By June 1944, the military value was deemed low in lieu of partisan aggression and by November 1944 it was disbanded. The remaining cadre, now called Kampfgruppe Skanderbeg, was transferred to the Prinz Eugen Division where they successfully participated in actions against Tito's partisans in December 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;williamson&quot;/&gt; The emblem of the division was a black Albanian eagle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson&quot;/&gt;

===Belgium===
The 373rd [[infantry]] [[battalion]] of [[Wehrmacht]], manned by Walloon Belgians, took part in anti-guerrilla actions in the occupied territory of the [[USSR]] from August 1941-February 1942. In May 1943, the battalion was transformed into the 5th SS Volunteer Sturmbrigade Wallonien and sent to the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. In the autumn, the brigade had been transformed into [[28th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Wallonien]]. Its remnants surrendered to British troops in the final days of war. Flemish Belgian collaborators were organized first into the [[6th SS Volunteer Sturmbrigade Langemarck|6th SS Volunteer Brigade]] and later the 27th SS Infantry (''Grenadier'') Division. Belgians served in the German forces from mid-1941 until the end of the war.

===China===
The Japanese set up several puppet regimes in occupied Chinese territories. The first of which was [[Manchukuo]] in 1932, followed by the [[East Hebei Autonomous Council]] in 1935. Similar to [[Manchukuo]] in its supposed ethnic identity, [[Mengjiang]] (Mengkukuo) was set up in late 1936. [[Wang Kemin]]'s collaborationist [[Provisional Government of the Republic of China]] was set up in [[Beiping]] in 1937 following [[Second Sino-Japanese War|the start of full-scale military operations between China and Japan]], another puppet regime was the [[Reformed Government of the Republic of China]], setup in [[Nanjing]] in 1938. The [[Wang Jingwei]] collaborationist government, established in 1940, &quot;consolidated&quot; these regimes, though in reality neither Wang's government nor the constituent governments had any autonomy, although the  military  of the [[Wang Jingwei Government]] was equipped by the Japanese with planes, cannons, tanks, boats, and German-style [[stahlhelm]] (already widely used by the [[National Revolutionary Army]], the &quot;official&quot; army of the [[Republic of China (1912–1949)|Republic of China]]).

The military forces of these puppet regimes, known collectively as the [[Collaborationist Chinese Army]], numbered more than a million at their height, with some estimates that the number exceeded 2 million conscripts. Great number of collaborationist troops were men originally serving in warlord forces within the National Revolutionary Army who had defected when facing both Communists and Japanese as enemies. Although its manpower was very large, the soldiers were very ineffective compared to NRA soldiers due to low morale for being considered as &quot;[[Hanjian]]&quot;. Although certain collaborationist forces had limited battlefield presence during the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]], most were relegated to behind-the-line duties.

The Wang Jingwei government was disbanded after Japanese surrender to Allies in 1945, and Manchukuo and Mengjiang were destroyed by Soviet troops in the [[Soviet invasion of Manchuria|invasion of Manchuria]].

===Denmark===
{{Main|Occupation of Denmark}}

At 04:15 on 9 April 1940 (Danish standard time), German forces crossed the border into [[neutral country|neutral]] Denmark, in direct violation of a German-Danish treaty of non-aggression signed the previous year. After two hours the Danish government [[Surrender (military)|surrendered]], believing that resistance was useless and hoping to work out an advantageous agreement with Germany.

As a result of the cooperative attitude of the Danish authorities, German officials claimed that they would &quot;respect Danish sovereignty and territorial integrity, as well as neutrality.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;resistance&quot;/&gt; The German authorities were inclined towards lenient terms with Denmark for several reasons. These factors allowed Denmark a very favorable relationship with Nazi Germany. The government remained intact and the [[parliament]] continued to function more or less as it had before. They were able to maintain much of their former control over domestic policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;collaboration&quot;/&gt; Danish public opinion generally backed the new government, particularly after the fall of France in June 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;danskerne&quot;/&gt; There was a general feeling that the unpleasant reality of German occupation must be confronted in the most realistic way possible, given the international situation. Newspaper articles and news reports &quot;which might jeopardize German-Danish relations&quot; were outlawed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scandinavian&quot;/&gt; After the assault on the Soviet Union, [[Operation Barbarossa]], Denmark joined the [[Anti-Comintern Pact]], together with the fellow [[nordic countries|Nordic]] state of [[Finland]]; the [[Communist Party]] was banned in Denmark. [[Industry|Industrial production]] and trade was, partly due to geopolitical reality and economic necessity, redirected toward Germany. Many government officials saw expanded trade with Germany as vital to maintaining social order in Denmark.&lt;ref name=&quot;voorhis&quot;/&gt; Increased [[unemployment]] and poverty was feared to lead to more of open revolt within the country, since Danes tended to blame all negative developments on the Germans. It was feared that any revolt would result in a crackdown by the German authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;historie&quot;/&gt;

In return for these concessions, the Danish cabinet rejected German demands for legislation discriminating against Denmark's Jewish minority. Demands to introduce the death penalty were likewise rebuffed and so were German demands to allow German military courts jurisdiction over Danish citizens. Denmark also rejected demands for the transfer of Danish army units to German military use. Throughout the years of its hold on power, the government consistently refused to accept German demands regarding the Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;grundtvigian&quot;/&gt; The authorities would not enact special laws concerning Jews, and their civil rights remained equal with those of the rest of the population. German authorities became increasingly exasperated with this position but concluded that any attempt to remove or mistreat Jews would be &quot;politically unacceptable.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;flender&quot;/&gt; Even the [[Gestapo]] officer Dr. [[Werner Best]], plenipotentiary in Denmark from November 1942, believed that any attempt to remove the Jews would be enormously disruptive to the relationship between the two governments and recommended against any action concerning the Jews of Denmark.

On 29 June 1941, days after the [[Operation Barbarossa|invasion of the USSR]], ''[[Frikorps Danmark]]'' (Free Corps Denmark) was founded as a corps of Danish volunteers to fight against the Soviet Union. ''Frikorps Danmark'' was set up at the initiative of the [[SS]] and [[National Socialist Workers' Party of Denmark|DNSAP]] who approached Lieutenant-Colonel [[Christian Peter Kryssing|C.P. Kryssing]] of the Danish army shortly after the invasion of the USSR had begun. The Nazi paper ''Fædrelandet'' proclaimed the creation of the corps on 29 June 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lidegaard2003_p461&quot;/&gt; According to Danish law, it was not illegal to join a foreign army, but active recruiting on Danish soil was illegal. The SS disregarded this law and began recruiting efforts — predominantly recruiting Danish Nazis and members of the German-speaking minority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lidegaard2003_p461&quot;/&gt;

===Estonia===
{{See also|Estonian war crimes trials|Estonian International Commission for Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity}}

Although the [[Estonian Self-Administration]] did not have complete freedom of action, it exercised a significant measure of autonomy, within the framework of German policy, political, racial and economic. Thus, the Directors exercised their powers pursuant to the laws and regulations of the Republic of Estonia, but only to the extent that these had not been repealed or amended by the German military command. The Director's position was voluntary. The Self-Administration’s autonomy enabled it to maintain police structures that
cooperated with the Germans in rounding up and
killing  [[Jews in Estonia|Jews]] and [[Romani people|Roma]], and in seeking out
and killing Estonians deemed to be opponents of the
occupiers, and which were ultimately incorporated
into the [[Estonian Security Police and SD]]. It also extended to the
unlawful [[conscription]] of Estonians for [[forced labor]]
or for [[military service]] under German command.&lt;ref name=historycommission/&gt; 

The Estonian Security Police and SD,&lt;ref name=&quot;cambridge&quot;/&gt; the 286th, 287th and 288th [[Estonian Auxiliary Police]] Battalions, and 2.5–3% of Estonian [[Omakaitse]] (Home Guard) [[militia]] units (approximately between 1000 and 1200 men) were directly involved in criminal acts, taking part in the round-up, guarding or killing of 400–1000 Roma people and 6000 Jews in the concentration camps of [[Pskov region]] in Russia and the [[Jägala]], [[Vaivara concentration camp|Vaivara]], [[Klooga concentration camp|Klooga]], and [[Lagedi]] camps in Estonia. Guarded by the above listed formations, 15,000 Soviet POW died in Estonia, part of them because of neglect and mistreatment and part executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;historycommission&quot;/&gt;

===France===
[[Image:French SS recruitment poster.jpg|right|thumb|French Waffen SS recruitment poster. The text reads: &quot;You, too!  Your comrades await you in the French division of the ''[[Waffen-SS]]''&quot;.]]
{{Main|Vichy France}}

The Vichy government, headed by Marshall [[Philippe Pétain]] and [[Pierre Laval]], actively collaborated in the extermination of the European Jews. It also participated in [[Porrajmos]], the extermination of Rom people, and in the extermination of other &quot;undesirables.&quot; Vichy opened up a series of [[internment camps in France|concentration camps in France]] where it interned Jews, Gypsies, homosexuals, political opponents, etc. Directed by [[René Bousquet]], the [[French police]] helped in the deportation of 76,000 Jews to the extermination camps. In 1995, President [[Jacques Chirac]] officially recognized the responsibility of the French state for the deportation of Jews during the war, in particular the more than 13,000 victims the [[Vel' d'Hiv Roundup]] of July 1942, during which Laval decided, by his own, to deport children along with their parents. Only 2,500 of the deported Jews survived the war. The 1943 [[Battle of Marseille]] was another event during which the French police assisted the Gestapo in a massive raid, which included an urban reshaping plan involving the destruction of a whole neighbourhood in the popular Old Port. Some few collaborators were tried in the 1980s for crimes against humanity ([[Paul Touvier]], etc.), while [[Maurice Papon]], who had become after the war prefect of police of Paris (a function in which he illustrated himself during the [[1961 Paris massacre]]) was convicted in 1998 for crimes against humanity. He had been Budget Minister under President [[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]]. Other collaborators, such as [[Emile Dewoitine]], managed to have important functions after the war (Dewoitine was eventually named head of [[Aérospatiale]], the firm which created the Concorde plane). Debates concerning state collaboration remain, in 2008, very strong in France.

The French volunteers formed the [[Legion of French Volunteers Against Bolshevism]] and the [[Legion Imperiale]], in 1945 the [[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)]], which was among the final defenders of [[Battle of Berlin|Berlin]].

====Brittany====
{{Main|Breton nationalism and World War II}}

Breton nationists such as [[Olier Mordrel]] and [[François Debeauvais]] had longstanding links with Nazi Germany because of the their fascist and [[Nordicism|Nordicist]] ideologies, linked to the belief that the Bretons were a &quot;pure&quot; Celtic branch of the Aryan-Nordic race. At the outbreak of the war they left France and declared support for Germany. After 1940, they returned and their supporters such as [[Célestin Lainé]] and [[Yann Goulet]] organized militias that worked in collaboration with the Germans. Lainé and Goulet later took refuge in Ireland.

===Greece===
After the [[Germany|German]] invasion of Greece, a Nazi-held government was put in place. All three [[quisling]] prime ministers, ([[Georgios Tsolakoglou]], [[Konstantinos Logothetopoulos]] and [[Ioannis Rallis]]), cooperated with the Axis authorities. Although their  administrations did not directly assist the occupation forces, they did instigate suppressive measures, the most significant of which was the encouragement and, with the consent of the German forces, the creation of armed &quot;anti-communist&quot; and &quot;anti-gangster&quot; paramilitary organisations such as  [[Organization of National Resistance of the Interior X (Chi)|X]], the [[Security Battalions]] and others. Moreover, small but active Greek National-Socialist parties, like the [[Greek National Socialist Party]], or openly anti-semitic organisations, like the [[National Union of Greece]],  helped German authorities fight the [[Greek Resistance|Resistance]], and identify and [[Nazi concentration camps|deport]] Greek Jews.

About one thousand Greeks from Greece and more from the Soviet Union, ostensibly avenging their ethnic persecution from Soviet authorities, joined the Waffen-SS, mostly in Ukrainian divisions. A special case was that of the infamous Ukrainian-Greek [[Sevastianos Foulidis]], a fanatical anti-communist who had been recruited by the [[Abwehr]] as early as 1938 and became an official of the Wehrmacht, with extensive action in intelligence and agitation work in the Eastern front.&lt;ref name=&quot;hondromatidis&quot;/&gt;

{{See also|Axis-Cham Albanian collaboration}}

During the Axis occupation, a number of [[Cham Albanians]] set up their own administration and militia in [[Thesprotia]], Greece, subservient to the fascist [[Balli Kombetar]] organization, and actively collaborated first with the Italian and, subsequently, the German occupation forces, committing a number of atrocities.&lt;ref name=&quot;King&quot;/&gt; In one incident, on 29 September 1943, [[Nuri Dino|Nuri]] and [[Mazzar Dino]], Albanian paramilitary leaders, instigated the mass execution of all [[Paramythia executions|Greek officials and notables]] of [[Paramythia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;/&gt;

===Hungary===
[[Hungary]] was a war ally and then puppet state of Nazi Germany. The Hungarians played an active role in the murder of about 23,600 Jews (14,000–18,000 of whom were from Hungary) in [[Kamenets-Podolsk]] in late August 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem&quot;/&gt; and in the [[1942 raid in Novi Sad]].
Radical Hungarian governments—mainly the puppet government of [[Döme Sztójay]], appointed after the German occupation—actively participated in the Holocaust.

The [[Arrow Cross Party]] was a Hungarian Nazi party led by [[Ferenc Szálasi]] which ruled Hungary from 15 October 1944-January 1945 following [[Operation Panzerfaust|the German SS coup]] in [[Budapest]]. During its short rule, 80,000 Jews were deported from Hungary to their deaths. Out of 825,000 Hungarian Jews before the war, only 260,000 survived.

===India===
The ''[[Legion Freies Indien]]'', or ''Indische Freiwilligen Infanterie Regiment 950'' (also known as the ''Indische Freiwilligen-Legion der Waffen-SS'') was created in August 1942, chiefly from disaffected Indian soldiers of the [[British Indian Army]], captured by the [[Axis Powers|Axis]] in [[North Africa]]. Many, if not most, of the Indian volunteers who switched sides to fight with the German Army and against the British were strongly nationalistic supporters of the exiled, anti-British, former president of the [[Indian National Congress]], ''Netaji'' (the Leader) [[Subhash Chandra Bose]]. A Japanese supported [[sovereign state|sovereign]] and [[autonomous]] state- the [[Provisional Government of Free India|Azad Hind (Free India)]] was also established with the [[Indian National Army]] as its military force. ''See also the [[Tiger Legion]].''

===Indonesia===
{{Main|Japanese occupation of Indonesia}}

Among Indonesians to receive Japanese imperial honours from [[Hirohito]] in November 1943 were [[Sukarno]] and [[Mohammad Hatta]]. [[Sukarno]] actively recruited and organised Indonesian [[Romusha]] forced labour.&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica&quot;/&gt; They succeeded respectively to become the founding [[President of the Republic of Indonesia]] and [[Vice President of the Republic of Indonesia]] in August 1945.

===Italy===
{{Main|Italian Social Republic}}

The Italian Social Republic (''Repubblica Sociale Italiana'' or RSI) was a [[client state]] of [[Nazi Germany]] led by the &quot;Leader of the Nation&quot; (''Duce'') and &quot;Minister of Foreign Affairs&quot; [[Benito Mussolini]]. The RSI exercised official [[sovereignty]] in [[northern Italy]] but was largely dependent on the [[Wehrmacht Heer|German Army]] (''[[Wehrmacht Heer]]'') to maintain control. The state was informally known as the &quot;Salò Republic&quot; (''Repubblica di Salò'') because the RSI's Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Mussolini) was headquartered in [[Salò]], a small town on [[Lake Garda]]. The Italian Social Republic was the second and last incarnation of a [[Fascist]] Italian state.

===Latvia===
Having occupied [[Latvia]] in summer 1941, German command, capitalizing on Latvian anti-Soviet sentiments, created the local voluntary troops (''Schutzmannschaft'' or ''Schuma''), to fight the [[Soviet partisan]]s and serve as guards in [[concentration camp]]s for Jews and [[Soviet union|Soviet]] [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]]. The group of the Latvian [[auxiliary police]] known as [[Arajs Commando|Arājs Commando]] murdered about 26,000 Jews, mainly in November and December 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;indianapolis&quot;/&gt;

===Lithuania===
====Part 1====&lt;!--This part needs a better title!--&gt;
Prior to the German invasion, some leaders in [[Lithuania]] and in exile believed Germany would grant the country autonomy along the lines of the status of the [[Slovak Republic (1939–1945)|Slovakia protectorate]]. German intelligence [[Abwehr]] believed it had control of the [[Lithuanian Activist Front]], a pro-German organization based in the Lithuanian embassy in [[Berlin]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} The German Nazis allowed Lithuanians to form the [[Provisional Government of Lithuania|Provisional Government]], but did not recognize it diplomatically and did not allow Lithuanian ambassador [[Kazys Škirpa]] to become the Prime Minister. Once German military rule in Lithuania was replaced by a German civil authority, the Provisional Government was disbanded.
[[Rogue (vagrant)|Rogue]] units organised by [[Algirdas Klimaitis]] and led by [[SS]] ''[[Brigadeführer]]'' [[Walter Stahlecker]] started [[pogrom]]s in and around [[Kaunas]] on June 25, 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys-Hol&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Oshry&quot;/&gt; Lithuanian collaborators would become involved in the murders of hundreds of thousands of Jews and Poles.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPN-Ponary&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WSP-Ponary&quot;/&gt;

In 1941, the [[Lithuanian Security Police]] (''Lietuvos saugumo policija''), subordinate to Nazi Germany's Security Police and Nazi Germany's Criminal Police, was created.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys&quot;/&gt; Of the 26 local police battalions formed, 10 were involved in systematic extermination of Jews known as [[the Holocaust]]. The [[Ypatingasis būrys|Special SD and German Security Police Squad]] in [[Vilnius]] killed tens of thousands of Jews and ethnic Poles in [[Paneriai]] (see [[Ponary massacre]]) and other places.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys&quot;/&gt; In Minsk, the 2nd Battalion shot about 9,000 Soviet prisoners of war, in Slutsk it massacred 5,000 Jews. In March 1942 in Poland, the 2nd Lithuanian Battalion carried out guard duty in the [[Majdanek]] extermination camp.&lt;ref name=Piotr165166/&gt; In July 1942, the 2nd Battalion participated in the deportation of Jews from the [[Warsaw ghetto]] to a death camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;buffalo&quot;/&gt; In August–October 1942, the police battalions formed from Lithuanians were in Ukraine: the 3rd in [[Molodechno]], the 4th in [[Donetsk]], the 7th-в in Vinnitsa, the 11th in [[Korosten]], the 16th in [[Dnepropetrovsk]], the 254th in [[Poltava]] and the 255th in [[Mogilyov]] (Belarus).&lt;ref name=&quot;kiev&quot;/&gt; One of the battalions was also used to put down the [[Warsaw Ghetto Uprising]] in 1943.&lt;ref name=Piotr165166/&gt;

====Lithuanian Territorial Defense Force====
{{main|Lithuanian Territorial Defense Force}}

The [[Lithuanian Territorial Defense Force]] was formed of volunteers in 1944. Its leadership was Lithuanian, whereas arms were provided by Germans. The purpose of the Lithuanian Territorial Defense Force was to defend Lithuania against approaching Soviet Army and to defend civilian population in the territory of Lithuania form actions of partisans. In practice, it was primarily engaged in suppressing the Polish population and the anti-Nazi Polish resistance of [[Armia Krajowa]]; LTDF has self disbanded after it was ordered to act under Nazi command.&lt;ref name=&quot;bubnys&quot;/&gt; Shortly before it was disbanded, LTDF suffered a major defeat from Polish partisans in the [[battle of Murowana Oszmianka]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotr165166&quot;/&gt;

The participation of the local populace was a key factor in the [[Holocaust in Nazi-occupied Lithuania]]&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;/&gt; which resulted in the near total destruction of [[Lithuanian Jews]]{{Ref label|a|a|none}} living in the [[Occupation of the Baltic states by Nazi Germany|Nazi-controlled]] Lithuanian territories that would, from July 17, 1941, become the ''Generalbezirk Litauen'' of ''[[Reichskommissariat Ostland]]''. Out of approximately 210,000&lt;ref name=&quot;MacQueen_context&quot;/&gt; Jews, (208,000 according to the Lithuanian pre-war statistical data)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys_vanished219&quot;/&gt; an estimated 195,000–196,000 perished before the end of [[World War II]] (wider estimates are sometimes published); most from June to December 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;MacQueen_context&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Porat161&quot;/&gt; The events that took place in the western regions of the USSR occupied by [[Nazi Germany]] in the first weeks after the [[Operation Barbarossa|German invasion]] (including Lithuania - [[:Image:Coffinmap.jpg|see map]]) marked the sharp intensification of [[The Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Browning&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Porat159&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kwiet&quot;/&gt;

===Netherlands===
[[Image:Ssnederland.jpg|right|thumb|[[SS]] Recruiting Poster for the [[Netherlands]], urging Dutch people to &quot;join the fight against [[communism|Bolshevism]].&quot;]]

Thousands of Dutch volunteers joined the [[11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nordland]] (created in February 1943). The division participated in fighting against the Soviet army and was crushed in the [[Battle of Berlin]] in April–May 1945.

This was also the case for the [[5th SS Panzergrenadier Division Wiking]]. It was involved in several major battles on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]].

SS-Freiwilligen Legion Niederlande, manned by Dutch volunteers and German officers, battled the Soviet army from 1941. In December 1943, it gained brigade status after fighting on the front around Leningrad. It was at Leningrad that the first European volunteer, a Dutchman, earned the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]]: [[Gerardus Mooyman]]. In December 1944, it was transformed into the [[23rd SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nederland]] and fought in [[Courland]] and [[Pomerania]].&lt;ref name=Williamson/&gt; It found its end scattered across Germany. 49. SS-''Freiwilligen-Panzergrenadier-Regiment'' &quot;de Ruyter&quot; fought at the Oder and surrendered on 3 May 1945 to the Americans. 48. ''SS-Freiwilligen-Panzergrenadier-Regiment'' &quot;General Seyffardt&quot; however was split up into two groups. The first of these fought with ''Kampfgruppe Vieweger'' and went under in the fighting near [[Halbe]]. The few remaining survivors were captured by the Soviets. The other half of &quot;General Seyffart&quot; fought with ''[[Hans von Tettau|Korpsgruppe Tettau]]'' and surrendered to the western Allies.
During the war famous actor and singer [[Johannes Heesters]] made his career in Nazi-Germany, befriending high-ranking Nazis such as [[Joseph Goebbels]] and living in houses stolen from wealthy Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movienews&quot;/&gt;

===Norway===
In [[Norway]], the [[Quisling regime|national government]], headed by [[Vidkun Quisling]], was installed by the Germans as a puppet regime [[Occupation of Norway by Nazi Germany|during the occupation]], while king [[Haakon VII]] and the previous [[Nygaardsvold's Cabinet|government were in exile]]. He encouraged [[Norwegians]] to serve as volunteers [[5th SS Panzer Division Wiking|in the Waffen-SS]], collaborating in the deportation of Jews, and was responsible for the executions of [[Norwegian resistance movement|Norwegian patriots]].

About 45,000 Norwegian collaborators joined the pro-Nazi party ''[[Nasjonal Samling]]'' (National Union), and some police units helped arrest many of Norway's Jews. It had very little support among the population at large and Norway was one of few countries where [[resistance during World War II]] was widespread before the turning point of the war in 1942/43. After the war, [[Legal purge in Norway after World War II|Quisling and other collaborators were executed]]. Quisling's name has become an international [[eponym]] for [[traitor]].

===Palestine===
A [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] [[Arab nationalism|Arab nationalist]] and a [[Muslim]] religious leader, the [[Grand Mufti]] of [[Jerusalem]] [[Mohammad Amin al-Husayni]] worked for the Nazi Germany as a propagandist and a recruiter of Muslim volunteers for the [[Waffen SS]] and other units.

On November 28, 1941, Hitler officially received al-Husayni in Berlin. Hitler made a declaration that after &quot;...the last traces of the Jewish-Communist European hegemony had been obliterated... the German army would... gain the southern exit of Caucasus... the Führer would offer the Arab world his personal assurance that the hour of liberation had struck. Thereafter, Germany's only remaining objective in the region would be limited to the ''Vernichtung des... Judentums'' ['destruction of the Jewish element', sometimes taken to be a euphemism for 'annihilation of the Jews'] living under British protection in Arab lands..&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;hitler-fleming&quot;/&gt;

The Mufti spent the remainder of the war assisting with the formation of Muslim Waffen SS units in the [[Balkans]] and the formation of schools and training centers for [[imam]]s and [[mullah]]s who would accompany the Muslim SS and Wehrmacht units. Beginning in 1943, al-Husayni was involved in the organization and recruitment of [[Bosniaks|Bosnian Muslims]] into several divisions. The largest of which was the [[13th Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Handschar (1st Croatian)|13th &quot;Handschar&quot; division]] of 21,065 men.

In 1944, al-Husayni sponsored an unsuccessful [[chemical warfare]] assault on the Jewish community in Palestine. Five parachutists were supplied with maps of [[Tel Aviv]], canisters of a German–manufactured &quot;fine white powder,&quot; and instructions from the Mufti to dump chemicals into the Tel Aviv [[Water well|water system]]. District police commander Fayiz Bey Idrissi later recalled, &quot;The laboratory report stated that each container held enough poison to kill 25,000 people, and there were at least ten containers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;korn&quot;/&gt;{{Additional citation needed|date=September 2011}}

The German [[Zionist]] organization concluded an economic agreement called the Haavara (Transfer in Hebrew) Agreement with Nazi Germany in 1933.  The [[Haavara agreement]] would last by most accounts until 1941.  PBS states: &quot;Haavara (Transfer) was a company established in 1935 as the result of an agreement between the Jewish Agency (the official Jewish executive in Palestine) and the Nazi regime. The agreement was designed to facilitate Jewish emigration to Palestine. Though the Nazis had ordered Jewish emigrants to surrender most of their property before leaving Germany, the [[Haavara Agreement|Ha'avara agreement]] let them retain some of their assets by transferring them to Palestine as German export goods. Approximately 50,000 Jews emigrated to Palestine under this arrangement.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs&quot;/&gt;  The Nazi German official Baron von Mildenstein was a guest of Jews in Palestine in 1933 and a commemorative medal was struck marking the occasion for the Nazi propaganda publication &quot;Der Angriff&quot;; wherein one side of the medal coin featured the Nazi swastika and other side featured the Star of David.&lt;ref name=&quot;blogspot&quot;/&gt;

In 1940, [[Lehi (group)|Lehi]], a militant [[Zionism|Zionist]] group founded by [[Avraham Stern|Avraham (&quot;Yair&quot;) Stern]], proposed intervening in World War II on the side of Nazi Germany. It offered assistance in transferring the Jews of Europe to Palestine, in return for Germany's help in expelling Britain from Mandatory Palestine. Late in 1940, Lehi representative [[Naftali Lubenchik]] went to [[Beirut]] to meet German official [[Werner Otto von Hentig]] (who also was involved with the [[Haavara Agreement|Haavara or Transfer Agreement]], which had been transferring German Jews and their funds to Palestine since 1933). Lubenchik told von Hentig that Lehi had not yet revealed its full power and that they were capable of organizing a whole range of anti-British operations. This proposed alliance with Nazi Germany cost Lehi and Stern much support.&lt;ref name=&quot;marxists&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;/&gt;

===Poland===
[[Image:German Poster - Chodzmy na roboty rolne do Niemiec.jpg|right|thumb|300px|German Recruitment Poster: &quot;Let's do agricultural work in Germany. Report immediately to your [[Vogt]]&quot;]]
{{Main|Occupation of Poland (1939–1945)|Blue Police}}

Unlike in most European countries [[German–occupied Europe|occupied by Nazi Germany]]{{mdash}}where the Germans sought and found true collaborators among the locals{{mdash}}in [[occupied Poland]] there was no official collaboration either at the political or at the economic level.&lt;ref name=&quot;CT&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KPF&quot;/&gt; Poland also never officially surrendered to the Germans. Under German occupation, the Polish army continued to fight underground, as [[Armia Krajowa]] and forest partisans – [[Leśni]]. The [[Polish resistance movement in World War II]] in German-occupied Poland was the largest resistance movement in all of occupied Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;hippocrene&quot;/&gt; As a result, Polish citizens were unlikely to be given positions of any significant authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;CT&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KPF&quot;/&gt; The vast majority of the pre-war citizenry collaborating with the Nazis was the [[German minority in Poland]] which was offered one of several possible grades of the German citizenship.&lt;ref name=&quot;google2&quot;/&gt; In 1939, before the [[German invasion of Poland]], 800,000 people declared themselves as members of the German minority in Poland mostly in [[Pomerania]] and Western [[Silesia]]. During the war there were about 3 million former Polish citizens of German origin who signed the official list of ''[[Volksdeutsche]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;KPF&quot;/&gt; People who became ''Volksdeutsche'' were treated by Poles with special contempt, and the fact of them having signed the ''[[Volksliste]]'' constituted high treason according to the [[Polish Underground State|Polish underground law]].

There is a general consensus among historians that there was very little collaboration with the Nazis among the Polish nation as a whole, compared to other German-occupied countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;CT&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KPF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JC&quot;/&gt; Depending on a definition of collaboration (and of a Polish citizen, based on ethnicity and minority status), scholars estimate number of &quot;Polish collaborators&quot; at around several thousand in a population of about 35 million (that number is supported by the Israeli War Crimes Commission).&lt;ref name=&quot;Lukas&quot;/&gt; The estimate is based primarily on the number of death sentences for [[treason]] by the [[Special Courts]] of the [[Polish Underground State]]. Some estimates are higher, counting in all members of the German minority in Poland and any former Polish citizens declaring their German ethnicity (''[[Volksdeutsche]]''), as well as conscripted members of the [[Blue Police]], low-ranking Polish bureaucrats employed in German occupational administration, and even workers in [[forced labor in Nazi Germany|forced labor camps]] (ex. [[Zivilarbeiter]] and [[Baudienst]]). Most of the [[Blue Police]] were forcibly drafted into service; nevertheless, a significant number acted as spies for Polish resistance movement [[Armia Krajowa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JC&quot;/&gt; John Connelly quoted a Polish historian ([[Leszek Gondek]]) calling the phenomenon of Polish collaboration &quot;marginal&quot; and wrote that &quot;only relatively small percentage of Polish population engaged in activities that may be described as collaboration when seen against the backdrop of European and world history&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;JC&quot;/&gt;

The anti-Jewish actions of [[szmalcownik|szmalcownicy]] were very harmful to the Polish Jews as well as the gentile Poles aiding them. Anti-Jewish collaboration of Poles was particularly widespread and effective in the rural areas.{{Fact|date=September 2011}} It is estimated that some 200 thousand hiding Jews died in 1942-1945 in direct result of this collaboration.{{fact|date=September 2011}} The collaboration by some Polish Jews, who belonged to [[Żagiew]], was also harmful to both Jewish and ethnic [[Polish Underground]].

In October 1939, the Nazis ordered the [[mobilization]] of the pre-war [[Polish police]] to the service of the occupational authorities. The policemen were to report for duty or face death penalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hempel_2&quot;/&gt; [[Blue Police]] was formed. At its peak in 1943, it numbered around 16,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;encholo&quot;/&gt; Its primary task was to act as a regular [[police]] force and to deal with criminal activities, but were also used by the Germans in combating smuggling, resistance, and in measures against the Polish (and [[Polish Jewish]]) population: for example, it was present in [[łapanka]]s (rounding up random civilians for labor duties) and patrolling for Jewish escapees from the [[ghetto]]s. Nonetheless many individuals in the Blue Police followed German orders reluctantly, often disobeyed German orders or even risked death acting against them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotrowski&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paulsson&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hempel&quot;/&gt; Many members of the Blue Police were in fact [[double agent]]s for the [[Polish resistance in World War II|Polish resistance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Paczkowski-2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PWN&quot;/&gt; Some of its officers were ultimately awarded the [[Righteous among the Nations]] awards for saving Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;IAR&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem3&quot;/&gt;

Following Nazi Germany's [[Operation Barbarossa|attack on the Soviet Union]] in June 1941, German forces quickly overran the territory of Poland controlled by the Soviets since their joint invasion of Poland in accordance with the [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]]. A number of people collaborating with the Soviets before [[Operation Barbarossa]] were killed by local people. Belief in the ''[[Żydokomuna]]'' stereotype, combined with the German Nazi encouragement for expression of anti-Semitic attitudes, was a principal cause of massacres of Jews by gentile Poles in Poland's northeastern [[Łomża]] province in the summer of 1941, including the massacre at [[Jedwabne pogrom|Jedwabne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;google4&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;google5&quot;/&gt;

In 1944 Germans clandestinely armed a few regional [[Armia Krajowa]] (AK) units operating in the area of [[Vilnius]] in order to encourage them to act against the [[Soviet partisans in Poland|Soviet partisans]] in the region; in [[Nowogrodek]] district and to a lesser degree in Vilnius district (AK turned these weapons against the Nazis during [[Operation Ostra Brama]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;zizas19421944&quot;/&gt; Such arrangements were purely tactical and did not evidence the type of ideological collaboration as shown by [[Vichy regime]] in France or [[Quisling regime]] in Norway.&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotrowski&quot;/&gt; The Poles main motivation was to gain intelligence on German morale and preparedness and to acquire much needed equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Radzilowski&quot;/&gt; There are no known joint Polish-German actions, and the Germans were unsuccessful in their attempt to turn the Poles toward fighting exclusively against Soviet partisans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotrowski&quot;/&gt; Further, most of such collaboration of local commanders with the Germans was condemned by AK headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotrowski&quot;/&gt; [[Tadeusz Piotrowski (sociologist)|Tadeusz Piotrowski]] quotes [[Joseph Rothschild]] saying &quot;The Polish Home Army was by and large untainted by collaboration&quot; and adds that &quot;the honor of AK as a whole is beyond reproach&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotrowski&quot;/&gt;

One partisan unit of Polish right-wing [[National Armed Forces]], the [[Holy Cross Mountains Brigade]], decided to tacitly cooperate with the Germans in late 1944. It ceased hostile actions against the Germans for a few months, accepted logistic help and withdrew from Poland into Czechoslovakia with German approval (where they resumed hostilities against the Germans) in late stages of the war in order to avoid capture by the Soviets.&lt;ref name=&quot;underground&quot;/&gt;

===Romania===
{{Main|History of the Jews in Romania#The_Holocaust}}

===Slovakia===
{{Main|Slovak Republic (1939–1945)}}

The Slovak Republic (''Slovenská republika'') was an independent national [[Slovak people|Slovak]] state which existed from 14 March 1939 to 8 May 1945 as an ally and [[client state]] of [[Nazi Germany]]. The Slovak Republic existed on roughly the same territory as present-day [[Slovakia]] (with the exception of the southern and eastern parts of present-day Slovakia). The Republic bordered Germany, the [[Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia]], [[Poland]], and [[Hungary]].

[[Image:Nazi poster.jpg|right|thumb|&quot;I live in a German family and feel wonderful&quot;: propagandistic recruitment poster for the Eastern worker program]]

===The Soviet Union===
Nazi Germany terminated the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact|Non-Aggression Pact]] signed by [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]] and [[Vyacheslav Molotov]] with its invasion of the Soviet Union at 3:15 am on June 22, 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars82&quot;/&gt; Large areas of the European part of the [[Soviet Union]] would be placed under German occupation between 1941 and 1944. Soviet collaborators included numerous Russians and members of other ethnic groups.

The Germans attempted to recruit Soviet citizens (and to a lesser extent other Eastern Europeans) voluntarily for the [[OST-Arbeiter]] or Eastern worker program; originally this worked, but the news of the terrible conditions they faced dried up the volunteers and the program became forcible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gregorovich&quot;/&gt;

====Belarus====
{{Main|Belarusian collaborationism with the Axis powers|Belarusian Central Rada}}
Belarusian collaborators participated in various massacres of [[Belarusians|Belarusian]] villagers. Many of these collaborators retreated with German forces in the wake of the [[Red Army]] advance, and in January 1945, formed the [[30th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Belarussian)]].

====Caucasus====
{{Main|Turkic, Caucasian, Cossack, and Crimean collaborationism with the Axis powers}}

[[Armenians|Armenian]], Turkic and Caucasian forces deployed by the Nazis consisted primarily of Red Army POWs, assembled into ill-trained legions. Among these battalions were 18,000 Armenians, 13,000 Azerbaidjanis, 14,000 Georgians and 10,000 men from the &quot;North Caucasus.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ailsby&quot;/&gt; American historian Alexander Dallin notes that [[Armenische Legion|Armenian Legion]] and [[The Georgian Legion (1941-1945)|Georgian battalions]] were sent to the Netherlands as a result of Hitler's distrust for them, [[Georgian Uprising of Texel|many of which deserted]].&lt;ref name=&quot;alexander&quot;/&gt; According to military historian Christopher Ailsby, the Turkic and Caucasian forces formed by the Germans were &quot;poorly armed, trained, and motivated,&quot; and were &quot;unreliable and next to useless.&quot;&lt;ref name=ailsby /&gt;

Armenian Revolutionary Federation (The Dashnaks) was conquered by the Russian [[Bolshevik]]s in 1920, and ceased to exist. During World War II, some of the Dashnaks saw an opportunity in the collaboration with the Germans to regain those territories. The legion participated in the occupation of the [[Crimea]]n Peninsula and the [[Caucasus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auron238&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;google6&quot;/&gt; On December 15, 1942, the Armenian National Council was granted official recognition by [[Alfred Rosenberg]], the [[Reich Ministry for the Occupied Eastern Territories]]. The president of Council was Professor [[Ardasher Abeghian]], its vice-president [[Abraham Guilkhandanian]] and it numbered among its members [[Garegin Nzhdeh]] and [[Vahan Papazian]]. Until the end of 1944 it published a weekly journal, Armenian, edited by Viken Shantn who also broadcast on Radio Berlin with the aid of Dr. [[Paul Rohrbach]].&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher&quot;/&gt;

====Russia====
{{Main|Russian collaborationism with the Axis powers|Russian Liberation Army|Russian Liberation Movement|Lokot Republic|Kaminski Brigade|Russian Corps}}

In [[Russia]] proper, ethnic Russians were allowed to govern the [[Lokot Republic]], an autonomous sector in Nazi-occupied Russia. Military groups under Nazi command were formed, such as the notorious [[Kaminski Brigade]], infamous because of its involvement in atrocities in Belarus and Poland, and the [[30th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (2nd Russian)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;panzer-reich&quot;/&gt;

Ethnic Russians also enlisted in large numbers into the many German auxiliary police units. Local civilians and Russian [[POW]]s, as well as [[Red Army]] defectors were encouraged to join the Wehrmacht as &quot;[[Hiwi (volunteer)|hilfswillige]]&quot;. Some of them also served in so-called [[Ost battalion]]s which, in particular, defended the French coastline against the expected Allied invasion.

The [[Kalmykian Voluntary Cavalry Corps]] was a unit of about 5,000 [[Kalmyk people|Kalmyk]] [[Mongol]] volunteers who chose to join the ''Wehrmacht'' in 1942 rather than remain in [[Kalmykia]] as the German Army retreated before the [[Red Army]].

In May 1943, German General [[Helmuth von Pannwitz]] was given authorization to create a [[Cossack]] Division consisting of two brigades primarily from [[Don Cossacks|Don]] and [[Kuban Cossacks]], including former exiled [[White Army]] commanders such as [[Pyotr Krasnov]] and [[Andrei Shkuro]]. The division however was then not sent to fight the Red Army, but was ordered, in September 1943, to proceed to [[Yugoslavia]] and fight [[Josip Broz Tito]]'s [[Partisans (Yugoslavia)|partisans]]. In the summer of 1944, the two brigades were upgraded to become the [[1st Cossack Division|1st Cossack Cavalry Division]] and 2nd Cossack Cavalry Division. From the beginning of 1945, these divisions were combined to become [[XVth SS Cossack Cavalry Corps]].

Pro-German Russian forces also included the anti-communist [[Russian Liberation Army]] (ROA, {{lang-ru|POA: Русская Освободительная Армия}}), which saw action as a part of the [[Wehrmacht]]. On May 1, 1945, however, ROA turned against the SS and fought on the side of [[Czechs|Czech]] [[Insurgency|insurgents]] during the [[Prague Uprising]].

====Ukraine====
{{Main|Ukrainian collaborationism with the Axis powers}}
&lt;!-- this section needs tidying up and is in need of a little NPov--&gt;

Before World War II, [[Ukraine]] was divided primarily between the [[Ukrainian SSR]] of the [[Soviet Union]] and the [[Second Polish Republic]]. Smaller regions were administered by [[Romania]] and [[Czechoslovakia]]. Only the Soviet Union recognised Ukrainian autonomy, and large numbers of Ukrainians, particularly from the East, fought in the [[Red Army]].

The negative impact of Soviet policies implemented in the 1930s were still fresh in the memory of Ukrainians. These included the [[Holodomor]] of 1933, the Great Terror, the persecution of intellectuals during the [[Great Purge]] of 1937-38, the massacre of Ukrainian intellectuals after the annexation of [[Ukraine|Western Ukraine]] from Poland in 1939, the introduction and implementation of [[Collectivisation]].

As a result, the population of whole towns, cities and villages, greeted the Germans as liberators which helps explain the unprecedented rapid progress of the German forces in the occupation of Ukraine.

Even before the German invasion, the [[Nachtigall Battalion|Nachtigall]] and [[Roland Battalion|Roland]] battalions were set up and trained as Ukrainian battalions in the ''Wehrmacht'', and were part of the initial invading force.

With the change in regime ethnic, Ukrainians were allowed and encouraged to work in administrative positions. These included and the auxiliary police, post office, and other government structures; taking the place of Poles, Russians and Jews.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

Soviet citizens had a page in their [[internal passport]]s with information regarding their ethnicity, party status, military rank, service in the Soviet Army reserve, and information as to where they were to assemble in case of war. This document also contained markings regarding a citizens social status and reliability, (i.e. son of a [[kulak]], party or [[Komsomol]] membership. Soviet POWs who were able to demonstrate Soviet unreliability i.e. non membership in the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union|CPSU]], Komsomol or be of a discriminated class were quickly released from the POW camps. Often they were offered administrative and clerical positions or encouraged to join local police units. Some were trained as camp guards, while others were encouraged (in some cases forced) to enlist to fight in anti-Soviet military divisions.

During the period of occupation, Nazi-controlled Ukrainian newspaper Volhyn wrote that &quot;The element that settled our cities (Jews)... must disappear completely from our cities. The Jewish problem is already in the process of being solved.&lt;ref name=&quot;neveragain&quot;/&gt;

There is evidence of some Ukrainian participation in the [[Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;holocausttaskforce&quot;/&gt; The auxiliary police in Kiev participated in rounding up of Jews who were directed to the [[Babi Yar]] massacre.

Ukrainians participated in crushing the [[Warsaw Ghetto Uprising]] of 1943&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica7&quot;/&gt; and the [[Warsaw Uprising]] of 1944 where a mixed force of German SS troops, Russians, Cossacks, Azeris and Ukrainians, backed by German regular army units — killed up to 40,000 civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;warsawuprising&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;/&gt;

In [[Zhytomyr]] on September 18, 1941, 3,145 Jews were murdered with the assistance of Ukrainian militia (Operational Report 106) and [[Korosten]] where Ukrainian militia rounded up 238 Jews for liquidation (Operational Report 80). At times the assistance was more active. Operational Report 88, for example, reports that on September 6, 1941, 1,107 Jewish adults were shot while the Ukrainian militia unit assisting them({{?}}) liquidated 561 Jewish children and youths.&lt;ref name=&quot;holocaust-history&quot;/&gt;

On April 28, 1943 German Command anounced the estblishment of the [[14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Galizien (1st Ukrainian)|SS-Freiwilligen-Schützen-Division «Galizien»]].&lt;ref name=&quot;williamson8&quot;/&gt; It has been accounted  that approximately 83,000 people volunteered for service in the Division.&lt;ref name=&quot;ukrainische&quot;/&gt; The Division,  was used in [[Anti-partisan operations]] in [[Poland]], [[Czechoslovakia]] and [[Yugoslavia]].  During  the [[Lvov–Sandomierz Offensive|Brody offensive]] and [[Vienna Offensive]] to fight the Soviet forces. Those that survived surrendered to the Allies and the bulk emigrated to the West, primarily England, Australia and Canada.

===Yugoslavia===
Prior to being invaded by [[Nazi Germany]], the Yugoslav government was working on forging a pact with Germany. That pact was rejected by Yugoslav antifascists, who guided by general [[Dušan Simović]] demonstrated on March 26, 1941, and forced the government to withdraw. Angered by what he perceived as treason, Hitler invaded [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] without warning on April 6, 1941. Eleven days later Yugoslavia capitulated.

====Bosnia====
The 13th Waffen Mountain Division of the SS (also known as the 1st Croatian or Handschar division), manned by [[Bosniaks]] and [[Croats]], but commanded by German officers, was created in February 1943. The division participated in anti-guerrilla operations in Yugoslavia.&lt;ref name=Williamson/&gt; The division operated until 1945 with considerable strength, although by that time many tried to leave Bosnia along with the SS Prinz Eugen, Ustase, Serbian Volunteer Corps, Serbian State Guard, and Chetniks. They were massacred at Bleiburg all together.

====Croatia====
{{Main|Independent State of Croatia}}

[[Ante Pavelić]]'s Croatian puppet state was an ally of Nazi Germany. The Croatian extreme [[nationalists]], [[Ustaše]], killed 700 thousands of Serbs and other victims in the [[Jasenovac concentration camp]].

The 13th Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Handschar (1st Croatian), created in February 1943, and the [[23rd Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Kama]], created in January 1944, were manned by Croats and Bosniaks as well as local Germans.

====Serbia====
Serbian collaborationist organizations [[Serbian State Guard]], [[Serbian Volunteer Corps]] (party militia of the extreme right-wing [[ZBOR|Yugoslav National Movement &quot;Zbor&quot;]]
had a few thousand members and helped guard and run concentration camps.

====Albanians====
In April 1943, [[Heinrich Himmler]] created [[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)]] manned by [[Albanians|Albanian]] and [[Kosovar Albanian]] [[volunteer]]s. By June 1944, the military value was deemed low in lieu of partisan aggression and by November 1944 it was disbanded. The remaining cadre, now called Kampfgruppe Skanderbeg, was transferred to the Prinz Eugen Division where they successfully participated in actions against Tito's partisans in December 1944. The emblem of the division was a black Albanian eagle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson&quot;/&gt; [[Balli Kombëtar]] was an [[Albanians|Albanian]] nationalist and anti-communist organization which collaborated with the [[Axis Powers]] during their [[Axis occupation of Greece during World War II|occupation of Greece]] and [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. Their agenda was the creation of &quot;[[Great Albania]].&quot;

====Slovenia====
{{Main|Slovensko domobranstvo}}

''Slovensko domobranstvo'' (English: Slovene Home Guard, German: ''Slowenische Landeswehr,'') or SD for short, was a collaborationist force, formed in September 1943 in the area of  [[Province of Ljubljana]] (then a part of [[Yugoslavia]]). An individual member was a ''Domobranec,'' the plural of which was ''Domobranci.'' The SD functioned like most collaborationist forces in [[Axis powers of World War II|Axis]]-occupied Europe during World War II, but had limited autonomy, and at first functioned as an auxiliary police force that assisted the Germans in anti-[[Partisans (Yugoslavia)|Partisan]] actions. Later, it gained more autonomy and conducted most of the anti-partisan operations in the [[Province of Ljubljana]]. Much of the SD equipment was [[Italy|Italian]] (confiscated when Italy dropped out of the war in 1943), although German weapons and equipment were used as well, especially later in the war. Similar, but much smaller units were also formed in [[Littoral]] (''Primorska'') and [[Upper Carniola]] (''Gorenjska'').

===United Kingdom===
The [[British Free Corps]] reached a maximum size of 27 troops in 1945.

====Channel Islands====
{{Main|Occupation of the Channel Islands}}

The [[Channel Islands]] were the only [[British Empire|British territory]] in Europe occupied by Nazi Germany during World War II. The policy of the Island governments, acting under instructions from the British government communicated before the occupation, was one of ''passive co-operation,'' although this has been criticised,&lt;ref name=&quot;occupation&quot;/&gt; particularly in the treatment of Jews in the islands. These measures were administered by the Bailiff and the Aliens Office.&lt;ref name=&quot;jerseyheritagetrust&quot;/&gt; &quot;In Britain the administrators and the police in the Channel Islands who had helped with the deportation of Jews continued to work in their old positions, and some of them even received the [[Order of the British Empire]] for the bravery they had shown in the war years.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;

Following the liberation of 1945 allegations against those accused of collaborating with the occupying authorities were investigated. By November 1946, the UK Home Secretary was in a position to inform the UK House of Commons&lt;ref name=&quot;hansard&quot;/&gt; that most of the allegations lacked substance and only 12 cases of collaboration were considered for prosecution, but the [[Director of Public Prosecutions]] had ruled out prosecutions on insufficient grounds. In particular, it was decided that there were no legal grounds for proceeding against those alleged to have informed to the occupying authorities against their fellow-citizens.&lt;ref name=&quot;cruickshank&quot;/&gt;

In [[Jersey]] and [[Guernsey]], laws&lt;ref name=&quot;profits&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;guernsey&quot;/&gt; were passed to retrospectively confiscate the financial gains made by war profiteers and black marketeers, although these measures also affected those who had made legitimate profits during the years of military occupation.

During the occupation, cases of women fraternising with German soldiers had aroused indignation among some citizens. In the hours following the liberation, members of the British liberating forces were obliged to intervene to prevent revenge attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;occupation9&quot;/&gt;

===Volunteers===
Volunteers joined the ''Wehrmacht'', the auxiliary police (''Schutzmannschaft'') and the [[Waffen SS]] from most occupied countries and even a small number from some [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries ([[British Free Corps]]). Overall, almost 600,000 of Waffen-SS members were non-German [http://www.scrapbookpages.com/DachauScrapbook/DachauLiberation/BuechnerAccount.html] with some countries as Belgium and the Netherlands contributing thousands of volunteers.
Various collaborationalist parties in occupied [[France]] and the [[Vichy]] government assisted in establishing the [[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)|Légion des volontaires français contre le bolchevisme (LVF)]]. This volunteer army initially counted some 10,000 volunteers and would later become the 33rd Waffen SS division and one of the first SS divisions comprising mostly foreigners.

Following is a list of the 18 largest Waffen SS division composed mostly or totally of foreign volunteers (note that there were other foreign Waffen SS divisions composed mostly of forced conscripts).
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
*[[5th SS Panzergrenadier Division Wiking|Wiking]]
*[[11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nordland|Nordland]]
*[[13th Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Handschar (1st Croatian)|1st Croatian]]
*[[14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Galizien (1st Ukrainian)|1st Ukrainian]]
*[[21st Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Skanderbeg (1st Albanian)|1st Albanian]]
*[[23rd Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Kama|Kama]]
{{col-break}}

*[[23rd SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nederland|Nederland]]
*[[25th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Hunyadi (1st Hungarian)|1st Hungarian]]
*[[26th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (2nd Hungarian)|2nd Hungarian]]
*[[27th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Langemarck (1st Flemish)|1st Flemish]]
*[[28th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Wallonien|Wallonien]]
*[[29th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Russian)|1st Russian]]
{{col-break}}
*[[29th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Italian)|1st Italian]]
*[[30th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (2nd Russian)|2nd Russian]]
*[[30th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Belarussian)|1st Belarussian]]
*[[33rd Waffen Cavalry Division of the SS (3rd Hungarian)|3rd Hungarian]]
*[[33rd Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Charlemagne (1st French)]]
*[[34th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Landstorm Nederland|Landstorm Nederland]]
{{col-end}}

Apart from frontline units volunteers played another important role notably in the large ''Schutzmannschaft'' units in the German occupied territories in Eastern Europe. After [[Operation Barbarossa]] recruitment of local forces began almost immediately mostly by initiative of [[Himmler]]. These forces were not members of the regular armed forces and were not intended for frontline duty but were instead used for rear echelon activities including maintaining peace, fighting [[Partisans (Yugoslavia)|partisans]], acting as police and organizing supplies for the front lines. In the later years of the war, these units numbered almost 200,000.

By the end of World War II, 60% of the [[Waffen SS]] was made up of non-German volunteers from occupied countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;sbp&quot;/&gt; The predominantly Scandinavian ''11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nordland'' division along with remnants of [[France|French]], [[Italy|Italian]], [[Spanish people|Spanish]] and [[Dutch people|Dutch]] volunteers were last defenders of the [[Reichstag (building)|Reichstag]] in [[Berlin]]{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}.

The [[Nuremberg Trials]], in declaring the [[Waffen SS]] a criminal organisation, explicitly excluded [[conscripts]], who had committed no crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;yale&quot;/&gt; In 1950, The [[U.S. High Commission in Germany]] and the [[U.S. Displaced Persons Commission]] clarified the U.S. position on the Baltic Waffen SS Units, considering them distinct from the German SS in purpose, ideology, activities and qualifications for membership.

===Collaboration of Governments===
The most significant support of Germany came from the European [[Axis powers]] of the [[Balkans]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}. [[Albania]], having an Italian puppet state, declared war on the Allies along with the [[Italy|Kingdom of Italy]] in 1940, although the resistance movements and the peoples were against this. Later that year [[Slovakia]] declared war on [[Great Britain]] and the [[United States]]. Slovakian, Croatian and Albanian{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} collaborators fought with the German forces against the [[Soviet Union]] on the eastern front throughout the war. [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]] and [[Soviet invasion of Poland]] in 1939 should also be mentioned.

However, significant support was also given by many countries initially at war with Germany but which subsequently elected to adopt a policy of co-operation.

The [[Vichy France|Vichy]] government in France is one of the best known and most significant examples of collaboration between former enemies of Germany and Germany itself. When the French Vichy government emerged at the same time of the [[Free French]] in [[London]] there was much confusion regarding the loyalty of French overseas colonies and more importantly their overseas armies and naval fleet. The reluctance of Vichy France to either disarm or surrender their naval fleet resulted in the British [[destruction of the French Fleet at Mers-el-Kebir]] on 3 July 1940. Later in the war French colonies were frequently used as staging areas for invasions or airbases for the Axis powers both in [[Indo China]] and [[Syria]]. This resulted in the invasion of Syria and [[Lebanon]] with the capture of [[Damascus]] on June 17 and later the [[Battle of Madagascar]] against Vichy French forces which lasted for seven months until November the same year.

Many other countries cooperated to some extent and in different ways. Denmark's government cooperated with the German occupiers until 1943 and actively helped recruit members for the ''Nordland'' and ''Wiking'' Waffen SS divisions and helped organize trade and sale of industrial and agricultural products to Germany. In Greece, the three quisling prime ministers ([[Georgios Tsolakoglou]], [[Konstantinos Logothetopoulos]] and [[Ioannis Rallis]]) cooperated with the Axis authorities. Agricultural products (especially tobacco) were sent to Germany, Greek &quot;volunteers&quot; were sent to work to German factories, and special armed forces (such as the [[Security Battalions]] were created to fight along German soldiers against the Allies and the Resistance movement. In Norway the government successfully managed to escape to [[London]] but [[Vidkun Quisling]] established a puppet regime in its absence—albeit with little support from the local population.

==See also==
*''[[Collaboration: Japanese Agents and Local Elites in Wartime China]]''
*[[Collaborationism]]
*[[Responsibility for the Holocaust]]
*[[Schutzmannschaft]]
*[[Axis Powers]]
*[[Resistance during World War II]]
*[[Pursuit of Nazi collaborators]]
*[[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]]
*[[Blue Division]]

==Notes and references==
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;encholo&quot;&gt;''[http://motlc.learningcenter.wiesenthal.org/text/x25/xr2513.html Encyclopedia of the Holocaust]'' entry on the Blue Police, Macmillan Publishing Company, New York NY, 1990. ISBN 0028645278.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Browning&quot;&gt;Christopher R. Browning, with contributions by Jürgen Matthäus, &quot;The Origins of the Final Solution: The Evolution of Nazi Jewish Policy, September 1939-March 1942&quot;, [[University of Nebraska Press]], 2007, ISBN 0803259794, section 7 by Jürgen Matthäus, &quot;Operation Barbarossa and the onset of the Holocaust&quot;, pp. 244-294&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys&quot;&gt;{{lt icon}} {{cite book|author=Arūnas Bubnys|coauthors=|title=Vokiečių ir lietuvių saugumo policija (1941–1944) (German and Lithuanian security police: 1941–1944)|year=2004|publisher=[[Lietuvos gyventojų genocido ir rezistencijos tyrimo centras]]|location=Vilnius|url=http://www.genocid.lt/Leidyba/1/arunas1.htm|accessdate=2006-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys-Hol&quot;&gt;[http://www.genocid.lt/Leidyba/13/bubnys.htm {{lt icon}} Arūnas Bubnys. ''Lithuanian Security Police and the Holocaust (1941–1944)'']&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bubnys_vanished219&quot;&gt;Arūnas Bubnys, ''Holocaust in Lithuania: An Outline of the Major Stages and Their Results'' in Alvydas Nikžentaitis, Stefan Schreiner, Darius Staliūnas, ''The Vanished World of Lithuanian Jews'', Rodopi, 2004, ISBN 9042008504, [http://books.google.com/books?id=mdXRKbcyi5oC&amp;pg=PA219&amp;vq=is+the+worst+tragedy+of+Lithuania's&amp;dq=Holocaust+1941+Lithuania&amp;as_brr=3&amp;source=gbs_search_s&amp;sig=ZtduokysVV6MqLWS7I9uw7tMUFE Google Print, p.219]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;CT&quot;&gt;Carla Tonini, ''The Polish underground press and the issue of collaboration with the Nazi occupiers, 1939-1944'', European Review of History: Revue Europeenne d'Histoire, Volume 15, Issue 2 April 2008 , pages 193 - 205&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gregorovich&quot;&gt;[http://www.infoukes.com/history/ww2/page-12.html Andrew Gregorovich - World War II in Ukraine]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hempel&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} {{cite book|first=Adam|last=Hempel|title=Pogrobowcy klęski: rzecz o policji &quot;granatowej&quot; w Generalnym Gubernatorstwie 1939-1945|year=1990|publisher= [[Państwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe]]|location=Warsaw|isbn=8301092912|url=http://books.google.com/?id=sy0iAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=#search|accessdate=|page=435}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hempel_2&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} {{cite book|first=Adam|last=Hempel|title=Policja granatowa w okupacyjnym systemie administracyjnym Generalnego Gubernatorstwa: 1939–1945|year=1987|publisher= Instytut Wydawniczy Związków Zawodowych|location=Warsaw|page=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;IAR&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} {{cite news|author=IAR (corporate author)|title=Sprawiedliwy Wśród Narodów Świata 2005|url=http://www.forum-znak.org.pl/index.php?t=wydarzenia&amp;id=3139|work=Forum Żydzi - Chrześcijanie - Muzułmanie|publisher=Fundacja Kultury Chrześcijańskiej Znak|date=2005-07-24|accessdate=2007-02-20|language=Polish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;IPN-Ponary&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} [http://www.ipn.gov.pl/portal.php?serwis=pl&amp;dzial=194&amp;id=3327 Śledztwo w sprawie masowych zabójstw Polaków w latach 1941–1944 w Ponarach koło Wilna dokonanych przez funkcjonariuszy policji niemieckiej i kolaboracyjnej policji litewskiej] (Investigation of mass murders of Poles in the years 1941–1944 in Ponary near Wilno by functionaries of German police and Lithuanian collaborating police). [[Institute of National Remembrance]] documents from 2003 on the ongoing investigation]. Last accessed on 10 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;JC&quot;&gt;John Connelly, ''Why the Poles Collaborated so Little: And Why That Is No Reason for Nationalist Hubris'', Slavic Review, Vol. 64, No. 4 (Winter, 2005), pp. 771-781, [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3649912 JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;KPF&quot;&gt;Klaus-Peter Friedrich. ''Collaboration in a &quot;Land without a Quisling&quot;: Patterns of Cooperation with the Nazi German Occupation Regime in Poland during World War II.'' Slavic Review, Vol. 64, No. 4, (Winter, 2005), pp. 711-746. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3649910 JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;King&quot;&gt;Russell King, Nicola Mai, and Stephanie Schwandner-Sievers. ''The New Albanian Migration''. Sussex Academic Press, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kwiet&quot;&gt;Konrad Kwiet, ''Rehearsing for Murder: The Beginning of the Final Solution in Lithuania in June 1941'', Holocaust and Genocide Studies, Volume 12, Number 1, pp. 3-26, 1998, [http://hgs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/12/1/3]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Lidegaard2003_p461&quot;&gt;Bo Lidegaard (ed.) (2003): ''Dansk Udenrigspolitiks historie'', vol. 4, p. 461&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Lukas&quot;&gt;Richard C. Lukas, [http://books.google.ca/books?id=lz9obsxmuW4C&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=%22&amp;sig=ACfU3U0SGgyvqSbL4bypepYoO_CbYc_N_w ''Out of the Inferno: Poles Remember the Holocaust''] University Press of Kentucky 1989 - 201 pages. Page 13; also in Richard C. Lukas, ''The Forgotten Holocaust: The Poles Under German Occupation, 1939-1944'', University Press of Kentucky 1986 - 300 pages&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MacQueen_context&quot;&gt;Michael MacQueen, ''The Context of Mass Destruction: Agents and Prerequisites of the Holocaust in Lithuania'', Holocaust and Genocide Studies, Volume 12, Number 1, pp. 27-48, 1998, [http://hgs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/12/1/27]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Movienews&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.movienewz.nl/rudicarrell/?sub=extern&amp;waid=36728|title=Nederlanderse-entertainer-sin-Duitsland|work=[[Die Welt]]|date=17 April 2010|accessdate=7 April 2011|language=Dutch }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Oshry&quot;&gt;Oshry, Ephraim, ''Annihilation of Lithuanian Jewry'', Judaica Press, Inc., New York, 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PWN&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} {{cite encyclopedia|year=2005| title=Policja Polska Generalnego Gubernatorstwa|encyclopedia=Encyklopedia Internetowa PWN|url= http://encyklopedia.pwn.pl/haslo.php?id=3959423|publisher=[[Państwowe Wydawnictwa Naukowe]]| location=Warsaw}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Paczkowski-2&quot;&gt;Paczkowski (op.cit., [http://books.google.com/books?id=WoKQWem2yl4C&amp;pg=PA54&amp;lpg=PA54&amp;sig=vajOBIBsbx6RYJ24eRN86w_21CY#PPA60,M1 p.60]) cites 10% of policemen and 20% of officers&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Paulsson&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Gunnar S. Paulsson|coauthors=|title=The Holocaust: Critical Concepts in Historical Studies|year=2004|chapter=The Demography of Jews in Hiding in Warsaw|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=0415275091|url=http://books.google.com/?id=7xC5wNo0edoC&amp;pg=PA118&amp;lpg=PA118#PPA118,M1|page=118}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotr165166&quot;&gt;{{en icon}} {{cite book|author=[[Tadeusz Piotrowski (sociologist)|Tadeusz Piotrowski]]| coauthors=|title=Poland's Holocaust: Ethnic Strife, Collaboration with Occupying Forces and Genocide...|year=1997|editor=|pages=165–166|chapter=|chapterurl=|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company| location=|isbn=0-7864-0371-3|url=http://books.google.com/?id=A4FlatJCro4C&amp;pg=PA166&amp;vq=Murowana&amp;dq=1939+Soviet+citizenship+Poland|format=| accessdate=2008-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Piotrowski&quot;&gt;[[Tadeusz Piotrowski (sociologist)|Tadeusz Piotrowski]], ''Poland's Holocaust'', McFarland &amp; Company, 1997, ISBN 0-7864-0371-3. [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0786403713&amp;id=A4FlatJCro4C&amp;pg=PA88&amp;lpg=PA88&amp;dq=holocaust+in+Poland&amp;vq=wilno&amp;sig=8H45HLJILfGXRoOg3WdVDDjJ9Q4 Google Print, p.88], [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0786403713&amp;id=A4FlatJCro4C&amp;vq=wilno&amp;dq=holocaust+in+Poland&amp;lpg=PA88&amp;pg=PA89&amp;sig=LHllmtARMayj58PX49-zSFPXcXI p.89], [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0786403713&amp;id=A4FlatJCro4C&amp;pg=PA90&amp;lpg=PA90&amp;dq=holocaust+in+Poland&amp;vq=%22only+a+third+of+the+available+AK+forces%22&amp;sig=6wXjIU3xa5VvtLvquNZcIXLi2VA p.90]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Porat159&quot;&gt;Dina Porat, ''“The Holocaust in Lithuania: Some Unique Aspects”'', in David Cesarani, ''The Final Solution: Origins and Implementation'', Routledge, 2002, ISBN 0415152321, [http://books.google.com/books?id=3N9Xxc8wdu0C&amp;pg=PA159&amp;dq=%22The+Holocaust+in+Lithuania:+Some+Unique+Aspects%22&amp;ei=GV_ZR7zhEba4igGM06zRAQ&amp;sig=BC8nnQzADrvUtKwXXJ53qMJo480 Google Print, p. 159]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Porat161&quot;&gt;Dina Porat, ''“The Holocaust in Lithuania: Some Unique Aspects”'', in David Cesarani, ''The Final Solution: Origins and Implementation'', Routledge, 2002, ISBN 0415152321, [http://books.google.com/books?id=3N9Xxc8wdu0C&amp;pg=PA161&amp;vq=most+of+the+lithuanian+jews&amp;dq=%22The+Holocaust+in+Lithuania:+Some+Unique+Aspects%22&amp;source=gbs_search_s&amp;sig=Q51GxOA40aEQ_rhazg2g7VJpPWE Google Print, p. 161]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Radzilowski&quot;&gt;Review by [[John Radzilowski]] of [[Yaffa Eliach]]'s ''[[There Once Was a World: A 900-Year Chronicle of the Shtetl of Eishyshok]]'', [[Journal of Genocide Research]], vol. 1, no. 2 (June 1999), City University of New York.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;WSP-Ponary&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Czesław Michalski, [http://www.wsp.krakow.pl/konspekt/konspekt5/ponary.html Ponary — Golgota Wileńszczyzny] (Ponary — the Golgoth of Wilno Region). ''Konspekt'' nº 5, Winter 2000–2001, a publication of the [[Academy of Pedagogy in Kraków]]. Last accessed on 10 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson&quot;&gt;Williamson, G. ''The SS: Hitler's Instrument of Terror''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ailsby&quot;&gt;Ailsby, Christopher. ''Hitler's renegades''. 2004, page 123-4&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;alexander&quot;&gt;Dallin, Alexander. ''German Rule in Russia: 1941-1945.'' Octagon Books: 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auron238&quot;&gt;Auron. ''The Banality of Denial'', p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3527848.stm Warsaw's failed uprising still divides] (BBC) 2 August 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;blogspot&quot;&gt;[http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_FKUpGU_Jbp0/TRlhS6uhMyI/AAAAAAAAFm8/_McZEbvYa0o/s1600/Zionist%2BNazi%2Bcoin.jpg image of Angriff commemorative medallion]&lt;!-- another image here: http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_oCEwFr2yk_g/RjtpcsqrysI/AAAAAAAAAF0/Uo7X1ErPlwk/s1600-h/ZioNazi.jpg from this blog post: http://randompottins.blogspot.com/2007/05/coin-with-two-sides.html --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica&quot;&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-22819/Indonesia Indonesia :: Japanese occupation], [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica7&quot;&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/holocaust/article-9076148 Warsaw Ghetto Uprising] ([[Encyclopædia Britannica]])&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bubnys&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bubnys|first=Arūnas|authorlink=Arūnas Bubnys|title=Vokiečių okupuota Lietuva (1941-1944)|publisher=[[Lietuvos gyventojų genocido ir rezistencijos tyrimo centras]]|year=1998| location=Vilnius|pages=|isbn=9986-757-12-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;buffalo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Peter Gessner |url=http://info-poland.buffalo.edu/exhib/ghetto2/exit.html |title=Life and Death in the German-established Warsaw Ghetto |publisher=Info-poland.buffalo.edu |date=1942-07-29 |accessdate=2011-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cambridge&quot;&gt;[http://journals.cambridge.org/production/action/cjoGetFulltext?fulltextid=81766 Birn, Ruth Bettina] (2001), Collaboration with Nazi Germany in Eastern Europe: the Case of the Estonian Security Police]. ''[[Contemporary European History]]'' 10.2, 181-198&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;christopher&quot;&gt;Christopher J. Walker's &quot;Armenia —The Survival of a Nation,&quot; page 357&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;collaboration&quot;&gt;Phil Giltner, “The Success of Collaboration: Denmark’s Self-Assessment of its Economic Position after Five Years of Nazi Occupation,” ''Journal of Contemporary History'' 36:3 (2001) p. 486.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cruickshank&quot;&gt;''The German Occupation of the Channel Islands,'' Cruickshank, London 1975 ISBN 0192850873&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;danskerne&quot;&gt;Henning Poulsen, “Hvad mente Danskerne?” ''Historie'' 2 (2000) p. 320.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia&quot;&gt;Laqueur, Walter: ''Holocaust Encyclopedia'', Yale University Press, New Haven and London, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;flender&quot;&gt;Harold Flender, Rescue in Denmark, (New York: 1963) p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;Hermann Frank Meyer. [http://books.google.com/books?id=_Hpr-PK39UkC&amp;dq= Blutiges Edelweiß: Die 1. Gebirgs-division im zweiten Weltkrieg Bloodstained Edelweiss. The 1st Mountain-Division in WWII Ch. Links Verlag, 2008.] ISBN 9783861534471, p. 469-471&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;&gt;Dov Levin. [http://books.google.com/books?id=U6KVOsjpP0MC&amp;pg=PA325&amp;dq=Lithuania,+levin+The+World+Reacts+to+the+Holocaust&amp;ei=z-ehSJqJEJycjgHQ3oX7BA&amp;sig=ACfU3U1aPcNzGcAek5M93T4XXDEWHLn-nw Lithuania.] In: David S. Wyman, Charles H. Rosenzveig. The World Reacts to the Holocaust. Johns Hopkins University Press, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google2&quot;&gt;http://google.com/search?q=cache:0IQ986AcKo4J:www.polishresistance-ak.org/PR_WWII_texts_En/26_Article_En.rtf&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google4&quot;&gt;Joanna B. Michlic. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=t6h2pI7o_zQC&amp;pg=PA90&amp;dq=judeo-communism&amp;lr=#PPA180,M1 Poland's Threatening Other: The Image of the Jew from 1880 to the Present.]'' University of Nebraska Press, 2006. Pages 170-180.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google5&quot;&gt;Richard Levy. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=Tdn6FFZklkcC&amp;pg=RA1-PA556&amp;dq=holocaust+jedwabne&amp;lr=&amp;ei=qL7_SKD8HY6OzQShqri0Dg#PRA1-PA366,M1 Antisemitism: A Historical Encyclopedia of Prejudice and Persecution.]'' ABC-CLIO, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google6&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=8STgD_e0vKcC&amp;pg=PA238&amp;dq=drastamat+kanayan,+nazi&amp;ei=TOrOSseLCZW-zATlidChBg#v=onepage&amp;q=drastamat%20kanayan%2C%20nazi&amp;f=false The banality of denial: Israel and the Armenian genocide], Yair Auron, p. 238&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;grundtvigian&quot;&gt;Andrew Buckser, “Rescue and Cultural Context During the Holocaust: Grundtvigian Nationalism and the Rescue of Danish Jews”, ''Shofar'' 19:2 (2001) p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;guernsey&quot;&gt;War Profits (Guernsey) Law 1945&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hansard&quot;&gt;[[Hansard]] (Commons), vol. 430, col. 138&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hippocrene&quot;&gt;Zamoyski, Adam. [[The Polish Way]]. New York: Hippocrene Books, 1987&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;historie&quot;&gt;Poulsen, Historie, 320.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;historycommission&quot;&gt;[http://www.mnemosyne.ee/hc.ee/pdf/conclusions_en_1941-1944.pdf Conclusions of the Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity. Phase II - The German Occupation of Estonia, 1941 - 1944]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hitler-fleming&quot;&gt;official transcript, trans. Fleming&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;holocaust-history&quot;&gt;[http://www.holocaust-history.org/intro-einsatz An Introduction to the Einatzgruppen] Accessed January 14, 2006 /&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;holocausttaskforce&quot;&gt;[[Yehuda Bauer|Bauer, Yehuda]]: ''[http://www.holocausttaskforce.org/speeches/details/2006-07-04/document.pdf The Holocaust in its European Context]'' p.14. Accessed January 14, 2006.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hondromatidis&quot;&gt;Hondromatidis, Iakovos ''I Mavri Skia Stin Ellada'' (&quot;The Black Shadow Over Greece&quot;), Athens 1978 (in Greek)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;indianapolis&quot;&gt;Arad, Yitzhak. Belzec, Sobibor, Treblinka — The Operation Reinhard Death Camps, Indiana University Press, Bloomington and Indianapolis, 1987&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jerseyheritagetrust&quot;&gt;[http://www.jerseyheritagetrust.org/collections/collections.html Jersey Heritage Trust archive*]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kiev&quot;&gt;http://www.holocaust.kiev.ua/bulletin/vip7/vip7_3.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;korn&quot;&gt;[http://www.wymaninstitute.org/articles/2003-03-chemical.php  Arab Chemical Warfare Against Jews - in 1944] by Benyamin Korn. (The David S. Wyman Institute for Holocaust Studies)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;marxists&quot;&gt;David Yisraeli, ''The Palestine Problem in German Politics, 1889–1945'', Bar Ilan University, Ramat Gan, Israel, 1974. Verified web copies: [http://www.marxists.de/middleast/ironwall/irgunazi.htm German] [http://www.marxists.de/middleast/brenner/irgunazi.htm English]. Also see Otto von Hentig, ''Mein Leben'' (Goettingen, 1962) pp 338–339&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;neveragain&quot;&gt;''Volhyn'' on September 1, 1941 [http://www.neveragain.org/1941.htm NAAF Holocaust Timeline Project 1941]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;occupation&quot;&gt;Bunting, Madelaine (1995) ''The Model Occupation: the Channel Islands under German rule, 1940-1945'', London: Harper Collins, ISBN 0-00-255242-6&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;occupation9&quot;&gt;''Occupation Diary,'' Leslie Sinel, Jersey 1945&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;panzer-reich&quot;&gt;[http://www.panzer-reich.co.uk/30th-waffen-grenadier-division-of-the-ss-2nd-russian.htm 30th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (2nd Russian)]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs&quot;&gt;[[PBS]] - [http://www.pbs.org/wnet/heritage/episode8/documents/documents_11.html Haavara (Transfer) Agreement Documents]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;profits&quot;&gt;War Profits Levy (Jersey) Law 1945&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;resistance&quot;&gt;Jørgen Hæstrup, Secret Alliance: A Study of the Danish Resistance Movement 1940–45. Odense, 1976. p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;sbp&quot;&gt;Dachau Scrapbook: [http://www.scrapbookpages.com/DachauScrapbook/DachauLiberation/BuechnerAccount.html &quot;Col. Howard A. Buechner's account of execution of Waffen-SS soldiers during the liberation of Dachau&quot;]. ''By the end of the war, 60% of the Waffen-SS consisted of volunteers from other countries; some of the soldiers at Dachau that day were Hungarian''. Accessed July 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;scandinavian&quot;&gt;Jerry Voorhis, “Germany and Denmark: 1940–45,” Scandinavian Studies 44:2 (1972) p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars82&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=82}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ukrainische&quot;&gt;Rolf Michaelis: Ukrainer in der Waffen-SS. Die 14. Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS (ukrainische Nr. 1). Winkelried-Verlag, Dresden 2006, ISBN 978-3-938392-23-2&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;underground&quot;&gt;Stefan Korbonski, &quot;The Polish Underground State&quot;, pg. 7&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;&gt;&quot;Stern Gang&quot; ''The Oxford Companion to World War II''. Ed. I. C. B. Dear and M. R. D. Foot. Oxford University Press, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ushmm&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005466 |title=Collaboration |publisher=Ushmm.org |date=2011-01-06 |accessdate=2011-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;voorhis&quot;&gt;Voorhis, 175.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;warsawuprising&quot;&gt;[http://www.warsawuprising.com/witness/atrocities10.htm Central Commission for Investigation of German Crimes in Poland.] Excerpts from: German Crimes in Poland. Howard Fertig, New York, 1982.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;williamson&quot;&gt;The Waffen-SS (3): 11. to 23. Divisions  By Gordon Williamson, Stephen Andrew&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;williamson8&quot;&gt;Williamson, G: ''The SS: Hitler's Instrument of Terror''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem&quot;&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_holocaust/chronology/1939-1941/1941/chronology_1941_24.html August 27–28: Massacre at Kamenets-Podolsk]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem3&quot;&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%206755.pdf The Righteous Among The Nations - Polish rescuer Waclaw Nowinski]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yale&quot;&gt;[[Nuremberg Trial|Nuremberg Trial Proceedings]], [http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/imt/proc/09-30-46.htm Volume 22, September 1946]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;zizas19421944&quot;&gt;{{lt icon}} Rimantas Zizas. ''Armijos Krajovos veikla Lietuvoje 1942–1944 metais'' (Acitivies of Armia Krajowa in Lithuania in 1942–1944). Armija Krajova Lietuvoje, pp. 14–39. A. Bubnys, K. Garšva, E. Gečiauskas, J. Lebionka, J. Saudargienė, R. Zizas (editors). Vilnius – Kaunas, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
*Arad, Yitzhak. Belzec, Sobibor, ''Treblinka — The Operation Reinhard Death Camps'', Indiana University Press, Bloomington and Indianapolis, 1987
*Peter Suppli Benson, Bjørn Lamnek and Stig Ørskov: ''Mærsk · manden og magten'', Politiken Bøger, 2004 (''&quot;Maersk · The Man and Power&quot;'', in Danish)
*Christian Jensen, Tomas Kristiansen and Karl Erik Nielsen: ''Krigens købmænd'', Gyldendal, 2000 (''&quot;The Merchants of War&quot;'', in Danish)
*Chuev, Sergei Gennadevic: ''Prokliatye soldaty'', [Damned soldiers], ĖKSMO, 2004, ISBN 5699059709
*Williamson, Gordon: ''The SS: Hitler's Instrument of Terror'', Brown Packaging Limited, 1994
*Gerlach, Christian: ''Kalkulierte Morde'', Hamburger Edition, Hamburg, 1999
*Klaus-Peter Friedrich ''Collaboration in a &quot;Land without a Quisling&quot;: Patterns of Cooperation with the Nazi German Occupation Regime in Poland during World War II'' — ''[[Slavic Review]]'' Vol. 64, No. 4 (Winter, 2005), pp.&amp;nbsp;711–746
*Jeffrey W. Jones ''&quot;Every Family Has Its Freak&quot;: Perceptions of Collaboration in Occupied Soviet Russia, 1943–1948'' — [[Slavic Review]] Vol. 64, No. 4 (Winter, 2005), pp.&amp;nbsp;747–770
*Birn, Ruth Bettina, Collaboration with Nazi Germany in Eastern Europe: the Case of the Estonian Security Police. ''Contemporary European History'' 2001, 10.2, 181–198.
*Simon Kitson, ''The Hunt for Nazi Spies, Fighting Espionage in Vichy France'', Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 2008.

==External links==
*[http://www.feldgrau.com Feldgrau]

{{World War II}}
{{The Holocaust (end)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Collaboration With The Axis Powers During World War Ii}}
[[Category:Collaborators with Nazi Germany| ]]
[[Category:The Holocaust]]
[[Category:Collaboration during World War II]]
[[Category:Occupation of the Baltic states]]

[[fr:Collaboration dans l'Europe occupée par les nazis]]
[[id:Kolaborasi selama Perang Dunia II]]
[[lt:Kolaboravimas su trišalį paktą pasirašiusiomis šalimis antrojo pasaulinio karo metu]]
[[pl:Kolaboracja pod okupacją niemiecką podczas II wojny światowej]]
[[ro:Colaborarea cu Puterile Axei în timpul celui de al doilea război mondial]]
[[ru:Коллаборационизм во Второй мировой войне]]
[[sv:Kollaboration med axelmakterna under andra världskriget]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
