<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="457343" ns="0" title="6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 6th Airborne Division
|image= 
|caption= 
|dates= [[Second World War]]&lt;br&gt; 3 May 1943 - 1 April 1948
|country= [[Great Britain]]
|allegiance=
|branch= [[British Army]]
|type=Airborne
|role=Parachute Infantry
|size=12,148 men&lt;ref&gt;Joslen, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|This figure is the war establishment, the on-paper strength of the division for 1944/1945.|group=nb}}
|command_structure=
|garrison=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|current_commander=
|ceremonial_chief=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|notable_commanders= Maj.Gen. [[Richard Nelson Gale]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:British Airborne Units.svg|200px]]
|identification_symbol_2=British airborne forces insignia
&lt;!-- Culture and history --&gt;
|nickname=''Red Devils'' {{#tag:ref|The 1st Parachute Brigade had been called the &quot;Rote Teufel&quot; or &quot;Red Devils&quot; by the German troops they had fought in North Africa. The title was officially confirmed by General [[Harold Alexander]] and henceforth applied to all British airborne troops.&lt;ref&gt;Otway, p.88&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}
|patron=
|motto=''Go To It'' &lt;ref&gt;Saunders, p.189&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors=
|march=
|mascot=
|battles= [[Operation Deadstick]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Tonga]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Mallard]]&lt;br&gt;[[6th Airborne Division advance to the River Seine|Advance to the River Seine]]&lt;br&gt;[[Battle of the Bulge]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Varsity]]&lt;br&gt;[[6th Airborne Division in Palestine|Mandate of Palestine]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours= 
}}

The '''6th Airborne Division''' was an [[airborne forces|airborne]] [[division (military)|division]] in the [[British Army]] during the [[Second World War]]. It took part in [[Operation Tonga]], the airborne landings on the left flank of the invasion beaches in the [[Operation Overlord|Normandy Landings]]. It played a small part in the [[Battle of the Bulge]] and was involved in [[Operation Varsity]], the Allied assault across the [[Rhine river]]. At the end of the war in [[Europe]] it was planned to send the Division to the [[Far East]] for operations against [[Japan]], but these plans were cancelled after the [[Atomic bomb]]s were dropped on the Japanese mainland. The Division was instead sent to [[British Mandate for Palestine|Palestine]] on [[internal security]] duties, where it remained until being disbanded in April 1948.

==Background==
Impressed by the success of German airborne operations during the [[Battle of France]], the British [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]], [[Winston Churchill]], directed the [[War Office]] to investigate the possibility of creating a force of 5,000 parachute troops.&lt;ref&gt;Otway, p.21&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, on 22 June 1940, [[No. 2 Commando]] assumed parachute duties, and on 21 November was re-designated the 11th Special Air Service Battalion, with a parachute and [[Military glider|glider wing]].&lt;ref&gt;Shortt and McBride, p.4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Moreman, p.91&lt;/ref&gt;

On 21 June 1940 the [[No.1 Parachute Training School RAF|Central Landing Establishment]] was formed at [[RAF Ringway|Ringway airfield]] near [[Manchester]]. Although tasked primarily with training parachute troops, it was also directed to investigate the use of gliders to transport troops into battle.&lt;ref&gt;Otway 1990, pp. 28–29&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith7&quot;&gt;Smith, p.7&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the Ministry of Aircraft Production contracted [[General Aircraft Ltd]] to design and produce a glider for this purpose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flint73&quot;&gt;Flint, p.73&lt;/ref&gt; The result was the [[General Aircraft Hotspur]], an aircraft capable of transporting eight soldiers, that was used for both assault and training purposes.&lt;ref&gt;Lynch, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

The success of the first British airborne raid, [[Operation Colossus]], prompted the War Office to expand the airborne force through the creation of the [[Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)|Parachute Regiment]], and to develop plans to convert several infantry battalions into parachute and glider battalions.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; On 31 May 1941, a joint [[British Army|army]] and [[Royal Air Force|air force]] memorandum was approved by the [[Chiefs of Staff Committee|Chiefs-of-Staff]] and Winston Churchill; it recommended that the British airborne forces should consist of two parachute brigades, one based in England and the other in the [[Middle East]], and that a glider force of 10,000 men should be created.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell p.123&lt;/ref&gt;


==Formation==
On 23 April 1943, the British [[War Office]] ordered that a second airborne division be raised to supplement the original [[1st Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 1st Airborne Division]]. The new division consisted initially of key personnel reassigned from 1st Airborne. This included several officers who had fought in North Africa with the [[1st Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Parachute Brigade]]. For example, [[Richard Nelson Gale|Richard Gale]] had raised and commanded the 1st Parachute Brigade. [[James Hill (soldier)|James Hill]] had commanded 1st Parachute [[Battalion]]. [[Alastair Pearson]] had been his second-in-command. [[Richard Geoffrey Pine-Coffin|Geoffrey Pine-Coffin]] had been second-in-command of 2nd Battalion.

The core of the new 6th Airborne Division was formed from the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]] and two battalion's  from the [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]]. The two new division formations were the [[6th Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|6th Airlanding Brigade]] and the [[5th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|5th Parachute Brigade]]. Divisional troops included [[Pathfinders (military)|pathfinders]], engineer, anti-tank, reconnaissance, medical, and signals units.

==D-Day==
{{see|Operation Tonga|Operation Deadstick|Operation Mallard|Battle of Merville Gun Battery}}
[[Image:Operation Tonga.jpg|thumb|left|200px|British [[Pathfinders (military)|Pathfinders]] synchronising their watches in front of an Armstrong Whitworth Albemarle.]]

During the last hours of 5 June 1944 as part of [[Operation Tonga]], [[Military transport aircraft|transport aircraft]] and towed [[military glider|gliders]] carried units of the 6th Airborne to Normandy where they would land just prior to the [[Normandy Landings|D-Day]] landings that took place on the morning of 6 June. They were to land behind [[Sword Beach]] and secure the eastern flank. Some of the objectives included the seizure of two bridges over the [[Canal de Caen à la Mer|Caen Canal]] (later renamed &quot;[[Pegasus Bridge]]&quot;) and the bridge over the [[Orne River]] (later renamed &quot;[[Horsa Bridge]]&quot;) by D Company, 2nd Ox &amp; Bucks (commanded by Major [[John Howard (soldier)|John Howard]]). And also the destruction of the [[Merville Battery]] by Lieutenant-Colonel [[Terence Otway]]'s 9 PARA, both of whom were some of the first units to land and achieve their objectives. The landings proved successful, although many units were scattered across much of Normandy. The area around Pegasus and Horsa were successfully defended until they were eventually relieved, having repulsed numerous German counter-attacks, later on 6 June by [[Simon Fraser, 15th Lord Lovat|Lord Lovat's]] [[British 1st Special Service Brigade|1 Special Service Brigade]], followed by elements of the [[British 3rd Infantry Division]].

On 12 June, during the [[Battle of Breville]], British artillery was bombarding the German positions when a stray shell fell short and hit a group of British officers, killing Lieutenant-Colonel A.P. &quot;Johnny&quot; Johnson ([[Commanding Officer|CO]] 12 PARA) and badly wounding Brigadiers [[Hugh Kindersley, 2nd Baron Kindersley|Kindersley]] (CO 6 Airlanding Brigade) and [[Simon Fraser, 15th Lord Lovat|Lord Lovat]] (CO 1st Special Service Brigade).

===Advance to the River Seine===
{{see|6th Airborne Division advance to the River Seine}}

In August 1944, the division was ordered to prepare to advance.  Their objective was the mouth of the River Seine a distance of 45 miles (72 km). To assist them in carrying out their mission, the division was reinforced by two British Commando, a Belgian and a Dutch infantry brigade, and increased artillery support. To reach the Seine, the division had to cross three rivers, which had been flooded by the Germans, with only two roads available for transport.

When the German Army started to withdraw on 17 August, the division attacked. Fighting several small battles, by the end of the month they reached their objective at the River Seine. Here the division halted until early in September, when they returned to England to prepare for further airborne operations later in the war.

==Ardennes Offensive==
On 16 December the Germans launched [[Ardennes Offensive|Operation Wacht am Rhein]], a last-ditch offensive against the Allies via the [[Ardennes]] forest. The division was rushed to Belgium shortly afterward to assist in repulsing the attack. The fighting took place in awful weather conditions and ended in mid-January 1945.

==The Rhine crossings==

===Preparation===
By March 1945, the Allies had advanced into Germany and had reached the River [[Rhine]]. The Rhine was a formidable natural obstacle to the Allied advance,&lt;ref name=&quot;Armyhistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.armyhistory.org/armyhistorical.aspx?pgID=1017&amp;id=139&amp;exCompID=177 |title= Operation Varsity: The Last Airborne Deployment of World War II |accessdate=2008-05-01 |author= Matthew J. Seelinger|year= 2007|work= |publisher=Army Historical Research}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; but if breached would allow the Allies to access the [[North German Plain]] and ultimately advance on Berlin and other major cities in Northern Germany. Following the 'Broad Front Approach' laid out by [[General of the Army (United States)|General]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], the [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force|Supreme Allied Commander of the Allied Expeditionary Force]], it was decided to attempt to breach the Rhine in several areas.&lt;ref&gt;Saunders, Tim, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt; [[Field Marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] [[Bernard Montgomery]], commanding the British [[21st Army Group]] devised a plan to allow the forces under his command to breach the Rhine. To ensure that the operation was a success, Montgomery insisted that airborne forces support the operation. The airborne operation was code-named [[Operation Varsity]].&lt;ref&gt;Devlin, p. 258-259&lt;/ref&gt;

The division's objective was to seize the high ground east of the town of [[Bergen, North Holland|Bergen]], to attack and capture the town of [[Hamminkeln]], and finally to take control of several bridges over the River [[Oude IJssel|Issel]]. It would then hold the territory it had captured until it linked up with units from the American [[17th Airborne Division]], which would land to the south of them.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p. 553&lt;/ref&gt; Once these objectives were taken, the airborne troops would consolidate their positions and await the arrival of Allied ground forces, defending the territory captured against the German forces known to be in the area. The division would then advance alongside the 21st Army Group once the Allied ground forces had made contact with them.

To avoid the heavy casualties incurred by the [[British 1st Airborne Division]] that had occurred during [[Operation Market-Garden]], both Allied airborne divisions would only be dropped after Allied ground units had crossed the Rhine and secured crossings; the two divisions would also be dropped only a relatively short distance behind German lines, to ensure that reinforcements would be able to link up with them after only a few hours and they would not be isolated.&lt;ref&gt;Jewell, p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;

===The battle, 24 March 1945===
{{See also|Operation Varsity}}

The first element of the division to land was the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]], commanded by Brigadier James Hill.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Devlin, p. 624&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade actually jumped nine minutes earlier than it was scheduled, but despite this the unit was successfully delivered to Drop-Zone A, where it was engaged by heavy small-arms and 20&amp;nbsp;mm anti-aircraft fire. A number of casualties were suffered as it engaged German forces in the Diersfordter Wald, but by 1100 hours the drop-zone was practically clear of enemy forces and all battalions of the brigade had formed up.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway307&quot;&gt;Otway, p. 307&lt;/ref&gt; The key town of Schnappenberg was captured by the 9th Parachute Battalion in conjunction with the 1st Canadian Parachute Battalion, the latter unit having lost its commanding officer to German small-arms fire only moments after he had landed.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Despite taking casualties the brigade cleared the area of German forces and by 1345 hours Brigadier Hill reported that the brigade had secured all of its objectives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway307&quot;/&gt;

The next formation to land was the [[5th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|5th Parachute Brigade]] commanded by Brigadier [[Nigel Poett]].&lt;ref&gt;Ministry of Information, p. 139&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade was designated to land on Drop-Zone B and achieved this, although not as accurately as 3rd Parachute Brigade due to poor visibility around the drop-zone, which also made it more difficult for paratroopers of the brigade to rally. The drop-zone came under heavy fire from German troops stationed nearby and was subjected to artillery and mortar fire which inflicted casualties in the battalion rendezvous areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway308&quot;&gt;Otway, p. 308&lt;/ref&gt; However 7th Parachute Battalion soon cleared the drop-zone of German troops, many of whom were located in farms and houses. The 12th and 13th Parachute Battalions rapidly secured the rest of the brigades' objectives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway308&quot;/&gt; The brigade was then ordered to move due east and clear the area near Schnappenberg, as well as engaging German forces who were gathered to the west of a farmhouse, which had been taken over as the headquarters for the division. By 1530 hours Brigadier Poett reported that the brigade had secured all of its objectives and linked up with other units of the division.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway308&quot;/&gt;

The [[6th Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|6th Airlanding Brigade]], commanded by Brigadier R. H. Bellamy,&lt;ref&gt;Otway, p. 302&lt;/ref&gt; was tasked with landing in company-sized groups and capturing several objectives, including the town of Hamminkeln.&lt;ref&gt;Otway, pp. 302-303&lt;/ref&gt; The gliders landed in landing-zones P, O, U and R under considerable anti-aircraft fire, the landing being made even more difficult due to the presence of a great deal of haze and smoke. This caused a number of glider pilots to mis-identify their landing areas and lose their bearings, resulting in a number of gliders landing in the wrong areas or crashing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway308&quot;/&gt; The majority of the gliders survived, allowing the battalions of the brigade to secure three bridges over the IJssel that they had been tasked with capturing intact, as well as the town of Hamminkeln with the aid of the US [[513th Parachute Infantry Regiment]], which had been dropped by mistake near the town. The brigade secured all of its objectives shortly after capturing Hamminkeln.&lt;ref name=&quot;Otway308&quot;/&gt;

==Later operations==
{{see|6th Airborne Division in Palestine}}

The division was moved to [[Palestine]], starting on 15 September 1945 and finishing on 6 November.&lt;ref name=wilsond4&gt;{{cite book |title=With 6th Airborne Division in Palestine 1945-48 |last=Wilson |first=Dare |year=2008 |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books Ltd |isbn=9781844157716 |page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the aim of the move was to allow the division to make use of the air training facilities in southern Palestine.&lt;ref name=wilsond4 /&gt; The deteriorating security situation resulted in the division taking part in internal security duties against [[Zionist]] organisations known as [[Irgun]], [[Haganah]], and the [[Lehi (group) |Lehi]], who were attempting to expel the British. The 6th Division continued to carry out operations against the groups in very difficult circumstances until they were disbanded on 1 April 1948 just before the termination of the British Mandate and the independence of the State of Israel.

==Order of battle==
{{see|6th Airborne Division order of battle}}

;Commander
*May 1943 Major-General [[Richard Nelson Gale|Richard Gale]] 
*December 1944 Major General [[Eric Bols]] 
*March 1946 Major-General [[James Cassels (British Army officer)|James Cassels]] 
*December 1946 Major General [[Eric Bols]] 
*August 1947 Major-General [[Hugh Stockwell]] 

;Units
&lt;small&gt;The division order of battle for the invasion of Normandy was as follows:&lt;/small&gt;
*[[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]]
**[[8th (Midlands) Parachute Battalion]]
**[[9th (Eastern and Home Counties) Parachute Battalion]]
**[[1st Canadian Parachute Battalion]]

*[[5th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|5th Parachute Brigade]]
**[[7th (Light Infantry) Parachute Battalion]]
**[[12th (Yorkshire) Parachute Battalion]]
**[[13th (Lancashire) Parachute Battalion]]

*[[6th Airlanding Brigade]]
**12th [[Devonshire Regiment]]
**2nd [[Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry]]
**1st [[Royal Ulster Rifles]]

*Divisional troops
**[[6th Airborne Armoured Reconnaissance Regiment]]
**[[53rd (Worcester Yeomanry) Airlanding Light Regiment]], [[Royal Artillery]]
**2nd Forward Observer Unit, Royal Artillery
**3rd Airlanding Anti-Tank Battery, Royal Artillery
**4th Airlanding Anti-Tank Battery, Royal Artillery
**2nd Airlanding Light Anti-Aircraft Battery, Royal Artillery
**3rd Parachute Squadron, [[Royal Engineers]]
**591st Parachute Squadron, Royal Engineers
**249th Field Company. Royal Engineers
**286th Field Park Company, Royal Engineers
**6th Airborne Divisional Signals
**21st Independent Parachute Company ([[Pathfinder (military)|Pathfinders]])
**[[127th (Parachute) Field Ambulance]]
**[[224th (Parachute) Field Ambulance]]
**[[195th (Airlanding) Field Ambulance]]
**63rd Company, [[Royal Army Service Corps]]
**398th Company, Royal Army Service Corps
**716th Company, Royal Army Service Corps
**6th Airborne Division Ordnance Field Park
**6th Airborne Division Workshop
**6th Airborne Division Provost Company &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 July 2011|title=The British Airborne Assault|publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)]]||url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://www.mod.uk/aboutus/dday60/airborne.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Portal|World War II}}

==Notes==
; Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=nb}}
; Citations
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
*{{cite book
  | last = Bernage
  | first = Georges
  | authorlink =
  | title = Red Devils In Normandy
  | publisher = [[Heimdal]]
  | year = 2002
  | pages =
  | doi =
  | isbn = 2840481596}}
*{{cite book | last = Devlin | first = Gerard M. | title = Paratrooper: The Saga of Parachute and Glider Combat Troops During World War II | publisher = Robson Books | year = 1979 | isbn = 0-31259-652-9}}
*{{cite book | last = Harclerode | first = Peter | title = Wings Of War: Airborne Warfare 1918–1945 | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson | year = 2005 | isbn = 0-30436-730-3}}
*{{cite web
  | last = Hickman
  | first = Mark
  | title = Pegasus Archive
  | url=http://www.pegasusarchive.org
  | accessdate = 2006-12-07 }}
*{{cite book | last = Jewell | first = Brian | title = &quot;Over the Rhine&quot;: The Last Days of War in Europe | publisher = Spellmount | year = 1985 | isbn = 0-87052-128-4}}
*{{cite book |first=Lieutenant-Colonel H.F |last=Joslen |title=Orders Of Battle Second World War 1939–1945 |location= |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |year=1960 |isbn=978-184342-474-1}}
*{{cite web
  | last = Mills
  | first = T.F.
  | title = Land Forces of Britain, the Empire, and Commonwealth
  | url=http://www.regiments.org
  | accessdate = 2006-12-09 }}
*{{cite book | last = Ministry of Information | title = By Air to Battle: The Official Account of the British Airborne Divisions | publisher = P. Stephens | year = 1978 | isbn = 0-85059-310-7}}
*{{cite book | last = Otway | first = Lieutenant-Colonel T. B. H. | title = The Second World War 1939–1945 Army - Airborne Forces | publisher = Imperial War Museum | year = 1990 | isbn = 0-90162-75-77}}
*{{cite book
  | last = Saunders
  | first = Hilary
  | authorlink =
  | title = The Red Beret: The Story of the Parachute Regiment at War 1940–1945
  | publisher = Battery Press
  | year = 1985
  | pages =
  | doi =
  | isbn = 0898390877}}
*{{cite book| first=Tim|last=Saunders|title=Operation Plunder: The British &amp; Canadian Rhine Crossing|publisher=Leo Cooper |year=2006|isbn=1-84415-221-9}}

==External links==
* [http://history.6th.org.uk/ history.6th.org.uk] 6th Airborne articles, history and forum
* [http://www.paradata.org.uk/units/6th-airborne-division 6th Airborne Division | Paradata] 6th Airborne articles and historical documents
* [http://www.remuseum.org.uk/campaign/rem_campaign_6adiv.htm Royal Engineers Museum]—6th Airborne Divisional Engineers - D Day 1944


{{British parachute units of the Second World War}}
{{British Divisions in World War II}}

[[Category:Airborne divisions of the United Kingdom|6th Airborne Division]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1943]]
[[Category:Airborne units and formations of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)]]


[[ca:6a Divisió Aerotransportada (Regne Unit)]]
[[de:6. Britische Luftlandedivision]]
[[es:6ª División Aerotransportada (Reino Unido)]]
[[fr:6e division aéroportée (Royaume-Uni)]]
[[it:6th Airborne Division (British Army)]]
[[he:הדיוויזיה המוטסת הבריטית השישית]]
[[nl:6e Luchtlandingsdivisie]]
[[sl:6. zračnoprevozna divizija (Združeno kraljestvo)]]
[[uk:6-а повітряно-десантна дивізія (Великобританія)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
