<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="457803" ns="0" title="Yusuf al-Qaradawi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Quote farm|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox Muslim scholars
|notability       = [[Islamic scholar]]
|era              = [[Modern]]
|image            = Qardawi.JPG|250px
|caption          =
|name             = '''Yusuf 'Abdullah al-Qaradawi'''&lt;br /&gt;يوسف عبد الله القرضاوي
|title            = Shaykh
|birth_date       = {{Birth date and age|1926|09|09}}
|death_date       =
|ethnicity        =
|region           = [[Egypt]]
|Madhhab          =
|school_tradition = [[Sunni]]
|main_interests   =
|notable_ideas    =
|works            = Fiqh az Zakat, The Lawful and Prohibited in Islam, Fiqh al Jihad, and others
|influences       = [[Hassan al Banna]]
|influenced       = [[Rashid Al-Ghannushi]]
}}

'''Yusuf al-Qaradawi''' ({{lang-ar|يوسف القرضاوي ''Yūsuf al-Qaraḍāwiy''}}; born September 9, 1926) is a controversial&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3874893.stm Controversial preacher with 'star status'] BBC article, by agdi Abdelhadi on 7 July, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; [[Egyptians|Egyptian]] [[Islamic theologian]]. He is best known for his programme, ''ash-Shariah wal-Hayat'' (&quot;[[Shariah]] and Life&quot;), broadcast on [[Al Jazeera]], which has an estimated audience of 60 million worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Influential 500&quot;&gt;No.9 Sheikh Dr Yusuf al Qaradawi, Head of the International Union of Muslim Scholars – &quot;The 500 most influential muslims in the world 2009&quot; ,Prof John Esposito and Prof Ibrahim Kalin – Edmund A. Walsh School of Foreign Service, Georgetown University&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;spiegel&quot;&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/0,1518,745526,00.html The Voice of Egypt's Muslim Brotherhood] article in Spiegel, by Alexander Smoltczyk on 15 February, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  He is also well-known for [[Islamonline.net|IslamOnline]], a popular website he helped found in 1997 and for which he now serves as chief religious scholar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/islamonline.net# |title=Alexa site info IslamOnline.net Ranking#3880 Mar 1 2010 |publisher=Alexa.com |date=2010-02-16 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Al-Qaradawi has published more than 120 books,&lt;ref name=&quot;spiegel&quot;/&gt; including ''[[The Lawful and the Prohibited in Islam]]'' and ''Islam: The Future Civilization''.  He has also received eight international prizes for his contributions to Islamic scholarship,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?c=Article_C&amp;cid=1260257992606&amp;pagename=Zone-English-News/NWELayout &quot;Qaradawi Wins Hijra Award&quot;] ION, December 15, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; and is considered one of the most influential such scholars living today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Influential 500&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/1850659397 |title=Product Description: The Global Mufti: The Phenomenon of Yusuf Al-Qaradawi (Paperback)by Bettina Graf (Author, Editor), Jakob Skovgaard-Petersen (Editor) C Hurst &amp; Co Publishers Ltd (20 July 2009) |publisher=Amazon.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Raymond William Baker, Islam Without Fear: Egypt and the New Islamists (2003), p.4&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Qaradawi has long had a prominent role within the intellectual leadership of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = The Cartoon Jihad:  The Muslim Brotherhood's project for dominating the West
| author = Olivier Guitta
| date=  February 20, 2006
| pages = Volume 11, Issue 22
| url = http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/006/704xewyj.asp
| publisher = [[The Weekly Standard]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; an Egyptian political organization, but twice (in 1976 and 2004) turned down offers for the official role in the organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Influential 500&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.cesnur.org/2004/qaradawi.htm
| title = Al-Qaradawi Turns Down Offer to Assume Leadership of the Muslim Brotherhood
| date=  January 12, 2004
| publisher = [[al-Jazeera]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of al-Qaradawi's views have been controversial in [[Western world|the West]], and he was refused an entry visa to the [[United Kingdom]] in 2008.&lt;ref name='BBC 2008-02-07'/&gt; In 2004, 2,500 Muslim academics from [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Iraq]] and from the Palestinian territories condemned Qaradawi, and accused him of giving &quot;[[Islam]] a bad name.&quot;&lt;ref name=arabnews1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabnews.com/?page=4&amp;section=0&amp;article=53683&amp;d=30&amp;m=10&amp;y=2004 |title=Stop Terror Sheikhs, Muslim Academics Demand |publisher=Arabnews.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Be merciful to Qaradawi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=15874 |title=Be merciful to Qaradawi |publisher=Ikhwanweb.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11| name=&quot;be merciful&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2004, al-Qaradawi was a trustee of the [[Oxford University]] Center for Islamic Studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Owen Bowcott and Faisal al Yafai |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2004/jul/09/religion.immigrationpolicy |title=Scholar with a streetwise touch defies expectations and stereotypes |publisher=Guardian |date= 2004-07-09|accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also served as a technical consultant for an epic movie in English on [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;zawya.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zawya.com/Story.cfm/sidZAWYA20091102120242/Qatar%20Firm%20Plans%20Film%20On%20Prophet/ |title=Qatar firm plans film on Prophet |publisher=Zawya.com |date=2009-12-17 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GuardianBiopic&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Xan Brooks and agencies |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2009/nov/02/matrix-producer-plans-muhammad-biopic |title=Matrix producer plans Muhammad biopic |publisher=Guardian |date= 2009-11-02|accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
[[Image:Yusuf al-Qaradawi.jpg|thumb|left|Al-Qaradawi, during his days at Azhari Institute at Tanta]]

Al-Qaradawi was born in Safat Turab village in the [[Nile Delta]], [[Egypt]], in a poor family of devout Muslim peasants. He became an orphan at the age of two, when he lost his father. Following his father's death, he was raised by his uncle. He read and memorized the entire Qur'an by the time he was nine years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;DubaiAward&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quran.gov.ae/en/DIHQAPrograms/IslamicPersonality/Pages/FourthSession.aspx |title=Home &gt; English &gt; DIHQA Programs &gt; The Islamic Personality &gt; Fourth Session |publisher=Quran.gov.ae |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He then joined the Institute of Religious Studies at [[Tanta]], and graduated after nine years of study. He moved on to study Islamic Theology at the [[Al-Azhar Theological Seminary|Al-Azhar University]] in [[Cairo]], from which he graduated in 1953.
He earned a diploma in [[Arabic]] Language and [[Literature]] in 1958 at the Advanced Arabic Studies Institute.
He enrolled in the graduate program in the Department of [[Qur'an]] and [[Sunnah]] Sciences of the Faculty of Religion's Fundamentals (Usul al-Din), and graduated with a Masters degree in Quranic Studies in 1960.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aawsat.com/english/news.asp?section=3&amp;id=13430 Al Qaradawi in Al Azhar] Asharq Aawsat 17/7/2008&lt;/ref&gt; In 1962, he was sent by Al-Azhar University to Qatar to head the Qatari Secondary Institute of Religious Studies. He completed his PhD thesis titled ''Zakah and its effect on solving social problems'' in 1973 with First Merit, and was awarded his PhD degree from Al Azhar.

In 1977, he laid the foundation for the Faculty of [[Shari'ah]] and [[Islamic Studies]] in the [[University of Qatar]] and became the faculty's dean. In the same year he founded the Centre of Seerah and Sunna Research.&lt;ref name=&quot;DubaiAward&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Abdelhadi |first=Magdi |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3874893.stm |title=BBC World News Profile of Sheikh Yusuf Qaradawi |publisher=BBC News |date=2004-07-07 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Al Qaradawi in Al Azhar&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Hamed |first=Ayman |url=http://www.aawsat.com/english/news.asp?section=3&amp;id=13430 |title=Al Qaradawi in Al Azhar |publisher=Aawsat.com |date=2008-07-17 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alowaisnet.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alowaisnet.org/en/winnersbio/abijjffgihfdfhfbej.aspx |title=Dr. Yousef Al Qaradhawi winner Cultural &amp; Scientific Achievements Sixth Circle 1998–1999 |publisher=Alowaisnet.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He also served at the Institute of Imams, Egypt under the [[Ministry of Awqaf (Egypt)|Egyptian Ministry of Religious Endowments]] as supervisor before moving back to Doha as Dean of the Islamic Department at the Faculties of Shariah and Education in [[Qatar]], where he continued until 1990.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quran.gov.ae/en/News/Lists/News%20Center/DispForm.aspx?ID=82 |title=Profile of Qaradawi |publisher=Quran.gov.ae |date=2009-08-26 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; His next appointment was in Algeria as Chairman of the Scientific Council of Islamic University and Higher Institutions in 1990–91. He returned to Qatar once more as Director of the Seerah and Sunnah Center at Qatar University, a post he still occupies today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Al Qaradawi in Al Azhar&quot;/&gt;
Al-Qaradawi is the head of the [[European Council for Fatwa and Research]],an Islamic scholarly entity based in Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.e-cfr.org/en/ECFR.pdf The European Council for Fatwa and Research]&lt;/ref&gt; He also serves as the chairman of International Union for Muslim Scholars (IUMS).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iumsonline.net/about-us/head.html IUMS About us]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He was imprisoned under [[Farouk of Egypt|King Farouq]] in 1949, then three times during the reign of former President [[Gamal Abdul Nasser]], until he left Egypt for Qatar in 1961.&lt;ref name=&quot;Al Qaradawi in Al Azhar&quot; /&gt; He returned to Egypt in 2011 in the wake of the [[2011 Egyptian Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0218/Egypt-revolution-unfinished-Qaradawi-tells-Tahrir-masses |title=Egypt Revolution Unfinished, Qaradawi Tells Tahrir Masses |publisher=[[Christian Science Monitor]] |date=2011-02-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Al-Qaradawi is a principal shareholder and former [[Sharia]] adviser to Bank Al-Taqwa, a member bank of the Lugano-Switzerland Al-Taqwa group, a bank that the U.S. states finances terrorism and that the UN Security Council had listed as associated with Al Qaeda.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brusselsjournal.com/node/1898 Islamic Banking in Britain]&lt;/ref&gt; On August 2, 2010, the bank was removed from a list of entities and individuals associated with Al Qaeda maintained by the Security Council.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.asiaone.com/News/AsiaOne%2BNews/World/Story/A1Story20100803-230121.html 10 Taliban taken off UN terror list]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/sc/committees/1267/consolidatedlist.htm The UN -The Consolidated List September 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

Al-Qaradawi has three sons and four daughters,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://translate.google.com/translate?js=y&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;layout=1&amp;eotf=1&amp;u=http://www.el-wasat.com/persons.php%3Fperson%3D11&amp;sl=ar&amp;tl=en |title=Google Translate |publisher=Translate.google.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; three of whom hold doctorates from British Universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2005-01/11/article05.shtml |title=Livingstone Demands UK Media Apology for Qaradawi |publisher=Islamonline.net |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AnaSoage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalpolitician.com/24328-islam |title=SHAYKH YUSUF AL-QARADAWI: PORTRAIT OF A LEADING ISLAMIC CLERIC Ana Belén Soage* Middle East Review of International Affairs, Vol. 12, No. 1 (March 2008) Page 59 |publisher=Globalpolitician.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
His daughter, Ilham Yousef Al-Qaradawi, is an internationally recognized [[nuclear physics|nuclear]] scientist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.world-nuclear-university.org/about.aspx?id=25736&amp;terms=ilham |title=Advisory Committee to the WNU RI School Al-QARADAWI Ilham |publisher=World-nuclear-university.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.qu.edu.qa/artssciences/mathphysta/documents/CVs/Ilham_AlQaradawi_2008.pdf |title=Curriculum Vitae Ilham AlQaradawi |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; While his son, Abdurrahman Yusuf al-Qaradawi, is a [[poet]] and a political activist in [[Egypt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Abdurrahman Yusuf al-Qaradawi: new branches of National Association for Change Will open soon in Europe and the United States&quot;&gt;[http://www.masrawy.com/News/Egypt/Politics/2010/april/17/baradei.aspx?ref=moreclip Abdurrahman Yusuf al-Qaradawi: new branches of National Association for Change Will open soon in Europe and the United States]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, in an open online poll, Yusuf al-Qaradawi was voted the 3rd most intellectual person in the world on the list of [[Top 100 Public Intellectuals Poll|Top 100 Public Intellectuals]] by ''[[Prospect (magazine)|Prospect Magazine]]'' ([[UK]]) and ''[[Foreign Policy (magazine)|Foreign Policy]]'' ([[US]]).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.prospectmagazine.co.uk/prospect-100-intellectuals/&lt;/ref&gt;

===2011 return to Egypt===
After the [[2011 Egyptian Revolution]] Qaradawi made his first public appearance in Egypt after 1981.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2011/02/17/138093.html&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Tahrir Square]] he led Friday prayers on February 18, addressing an audience estimated to exceed two million Egyptians.&lt;ref&gt;For a complete English translation, see: ''The Tahrir Square Sermon of Shaykh Yûsuf al-Qaradâwî''. Translation by Yahya M. Michot with the collaboration of Samy Metwally, on http://www.hartsem.edu/&lt;/ref&gt; It began with an address of “Oh Muslims and Copts,” referring to Egypt’s Coptic Christian minority instead of the customary opening for Islamic Friday sermons “Oh Muslims”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/19/world/middleeast/19egypt.html | work=The New York Times | first=David D. | last=Kirkpatrick | title=After Long Exile, Sunni Cleric Takes Role in Egypt | date=2011-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was reported to have said,“Egyptian people are like the [[genie]] who came out of the lamp and who have been in prison for 30 years.” He also demanded the release of political prisoners in Egyptian prisons, praised the [[Copts]] for protecting Muslims in their Friday prayer, and called for the new military rulers to quickly restore civilian rule.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0218/Egypt-revolution-unfinished-Qaradawi-tells-Tahrir-masses Egypt revolution unfinished, Qaradawi tells Tahrir masses]&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 21, 2011, he talked about the [[2011 Libyan civil war|protests in Libya]] and issued a [[fatwa]] against [[Muammar Gaddafi]]:&lt;ref&gt;For a complete English translation, see: ''The fatwa of Shaykh Yûsuf al-Qaradâwî against Gaddafi''. Translation by Yahya M. Michot with the collaboration of Samy Metwally, on http://www.scribd.com/doc/51219918/Qadhafi/&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|...To the officers and the soldiers who are able to kill Muammar Gaddafi, to whomever among them is able to shoot him with a bullet and to free the country and [God’s] servants from him, I issue this fatwa (uftî): Do it! That man wants to exterminate the people (sha‘b). As for me, I protect the people (sha‘b) and I issue this fatwa: Whoever among them is able to shoot him with a bullet and to free us from his evil, to free Libya and its great people from the evil of this man and from the danger of him, let him do so! It is not permissible (lâ yajûzu) to any officer, be he a officer pilot, or a ground forces officer, or an air forces officer, or any other, it is not permissible to obey this man within disobedience (ma‘siya) [to God], in evil (sharr), in injustice (zulm), in oppression (baghî ‘alâ) of [His] servants.}}

He also called on Libyan ambassadors around the world to distance themselves from Gaddafi’s regime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iol.co.za/news/africa/sunni-cleric-says-gaddafi-should-die-1.1030016 Sunni cleric says Gaddafi should die], ''IOL News'', February 21, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.presstv.ir/detail/166411.html Egyptian cleric: Kill Gaddafi], ''PressTV'', February 22, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''[[Jerusalem Post]]'', [[Barry Rubin]] drew a parallel between Qaradawi's sermon and the [[Ayatollah Khomeini]] returning to [[Iran]]. He also said that Qaradawi was encouraging the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] to suppress opposition when he made reference to [[Munafiq|hypocrites]] in his sermon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/Opinion/Columnists/Article.aspx?id=209102 The Region: Egypt gets its Khomeini]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Brookings Institution]] member Shadi Hamid says that Qaradawi is in the mainstream of Egyptian society, and that he also has appeal among Egyptians who are not [[Islamist]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0218/Egypt-revolution-unfinished-Qaradawi-tells-Tahrir-masses/(page)/1 Egypt revolution unfinished, Qaradawi tells Tahrir masses]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''[[Eurasia Review]]'', [[Princeton University]] Professor Aaron Rock dismisses claims that Qaradawi is the Khomeini of Egypt, but he does see his influence as a sign that Islam will play a significant role in the shaping of Egypt's politics. He writes, &quot;Neither Qaradawi’s popularity nor his rhetoric should distract from the fact that Egyptian revolution’s grievances were based on a desire for political liberty and economic opportunity. That said, Islam remains an important framework for public debate and a reservoir of political symbolism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rock|first=Aaron|title=Qaradawi's Return And Islamic Leadership in Egypt|url=http://www.eurasiareview.com/qaradawis-return-and-islamic-leadership-in-egypt-analysis-20032011/|accessdate=20 March 2011|newspaper=Eurasia Review|date=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Views and statements==
===Religious and sectarian views===
====Muslim sects====
Al-Qaradawi has written about the danger of extremist groups of Islam, especially when done through blind obedience. He released a [[dissertation]] on the subject. He listed indications of extremism:
#The 1st indication of extremism include [[bigotry]] and intolerance, which make a person adamantly devoted to his own opinions and prejudices, as well as rigidity, which deprives him of clarity of vision regarding the interests of other human beings, or the purposes of [[Shariah]], or the circumstances of age. Such a person does not allow any opportunity for dialogue with others so that he may compare his opinion with theirs, and chooses to follow what appears to him most sound.&lt;ref name=&quot;witness-pioneer.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_RE/ch1pre.htm#3.%20Manifestations%20of%20Extremism &quot;Islamic Awakening between Rejection and Extremism&quot;] www.witness-pioneer.org&lt;/ref&gt;
#The 2nd indication of extremism manifests in a continuous commitment to excessiveness, and in attempts to force others to do likewise, despite the fact that Allah has not commanded it, and the existence of good reasons to make things easy. A person motivated by piety and caution may however, if he so wishes, choose a hard-line opinion in some matters and on certain occasions. But this should not become so habitual that he rejects advice when he needs it.&lt;ref name=&quot;witness-pioneer.org&quot;/&gt;
#The 3rd indication of extremism is the out-of-time and out-of-place religious excessiveness and overburdening of others, ''i.e.'' when applying Islamic principles to people in non-Muslim countries or to people who have only recently converted to Islam, as well as to newly committed Muslims. With all these, emphasis should not be put on either minor or controversial issues, but on fundamentals. Endeavours should be made to correct their concepts and understanding of Islam before anything else.&lt;ref name=&quot;witness-pioneer.org&quot;/&gt;
#The 4th indication of extremism manifests itself in harshness in the treatment of people, roughness in the manner of approach, and crudeness in calling people to Islam, all which are contrary to the teachings of the Qur'an and Sunnah.&lt;ref name=&quot;witness-pioneer.org&quot;/&gt;

;Sufism
Al-Qaradawi has been an avid caller to what he calls &quot;Islamic [[Sufism]]&quot;, praising those who practice it as pious.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sunnah.org/tasawwuf/scholr39.htm |title=On Tassawuf Shaykh Yusuf al-Qaradawi |publisher=Sunnah.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also been a staunch defender of the [[Ashari]] school of belief within Islam, going so far as to claim that the whole Muslim world follows this school as well as all Muslim religious schools in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youngmuslims.ca/biographies/display.asp?ID=3 Al Ghazaly Man of Da'wah]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Shi'ites
Al-Qaradawi has also described [[Shi'ites]] as [[heresy|heretics]] (&quot;mubtadi'oun&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2008/916/eg5.htm |title=The politics of sects |publisher=Weekly.ahram.org.eg |date=2008-10-05 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fellow member of International union of Muslim Scholars, [[Mohammad Salim Al-Awa]] criticized Qaradawi for promoting divisions among Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;ibid.&lt;/ref&gt; In response, the [[Iranian Press Agency]] has described Qaradawi as &quot;a spokesman for “international [[Freemasonry]] and [[rabbi]]s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/research/backgrounders/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12305381 Try to be nice about each other, A Sunni preacher upsets the Shias] Sep 25th 2008, CAIRO, From The Economist print edition&lt;/ref&gt;

Qaradawi accused what he called &quot;heretical&quot; Shias of &quot;invading&quot; Sunni countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Inflential Sunni cleric speaks of Shiite 'invasion'|author=(AFP)|url=http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5g-I5N5oznQqpvBVxaDnjD-uJyswA|newspaper=AFP|date=Sep 18, 2008|accessdate=February 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Non-Muslims====

Al-Qaradawi has strongly pressed for dialogue with Non-Muslims. He also puts emphasis on conversations with the West, including Jews, Christians, and [[secularists]]. He writes that this effort should differentiate itself from a [[debate]], for the latter does not often result in mutual cooperation. In his book titled ''Priorities of The Islamic Movement in The Coming Phase'', he recounts his experience:

{{bquote|I will never forget what one of the participants, a [[Christian nationalism|nationalist Christian]], said to me at the lunch table. He said, &quot;We have changed our opinion about you completely&quot;. I asked, &quot;And what was your opinion?&quot; He replied, &quot;that you are a hard-liner and a fanatic&quot;. I said, &quot;Where did you get this idea about me? He answered, &quot;I don't know, but, frankly, that was our impression about you&quot;. I asked &quot;And now?&quot; He said, &quot;Now we have learned through seeing, hearing, discussion and direct contact what has changed this unfair idea about you completely. We now see you as a man who respects logic, refers to reason and knows how to listen to the other opinion as a man who is not stubborn or adamant, but extremely flexible and tolerant&quot;.

What I want to convey by telling this story is that direct contact and reasonable, quiet dialogue that is held on equal footing is in the interest of the Islamic Movement, which stands to gain from it and will lose nothing at all in it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_Priorities/ch4p1-1.htm#The%20Dialogue%20With%20Rational%20Secularists &quot;Qaradawi's on Dialogue with Others&quot;] www.witness-pioneer.org&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Regarding the rights and citizenship of non-Muslim minorities, Qaradawi has said:
{{cquote|those people who live under the protection of an Islamic government enjoy special privileges. They are referred to as &quot;the Protected People&quot; (ahl al-dhimma or [[dhimmi]]s), meaning that [[Allah]], [[Muhammad|His Messenger]] ... and the community of Muslims have made a covenant with them that they may live in safety and security under the Islamic government. In modern terminology, dhimmies are &quot;citizens&quot; of the Islamic state. From the earliest period of Islam to the present day, Muslims are in unanimous agreement that they enjoy the same rights and carry the same responsibilities as Muslims themselves, while being free to practice their own faiths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_LP/ |title=Non-Muslim Residents of an Islamic State |publisher=Witness-pioneer.org |date=2002-09-16 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In his book titled ''The Lawful and Prohibited in Islam'', al-Qaradawi wrote:
{{bquote|Islam does not prohibit Muslims to be kind and generous to peoples of other religions, even if they are [[idolatry|idolaters]] and [[polytheism|polytheists]], ... it looks upon the People of the Book, that is, [[Jew]]s and [[Christian]]s, with special regard, whether they reside in a Muslim society or outside it. The Qur'an never addresses them without saying, &quot;O People of the Book&quot; or &quot;O You who have been given the Book,&quot; indicating that they were originally people of a revealed religion. For this reason there exists a relationship of mercy and spiritual kinship between them and the Muslims, all having in common the principles of the one true religion sent by Allah through his prophets ...: He has ordained for (the Muslims) the same religion which He enjoined on Noah, and that which We have revealed to thee (Muhammad) and that which We enjoined on Abraham, Moses, and Jesus: that you should establish the faith and make no division in it. (Qur'an 42:13)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_LP/ |title=Special Consideration for the People of the Book |publisher=Witness-pioneer.org |date=2002-09-16 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In May 2008, al-Qaradawi told visiting Rabbis from [[Neturei Karta]] movement,
{{cquote|There is no enmity between Muslims and Jews....Jews who believe in the authentic [[Torah]] are very close to Muslims.}}

He also added that relations between Muslims and Jews only became strained with the emergence of [[Zionism]] and the establishment of [[Israel]].{{cquote|Muslims are against the expansionist, oppressive Zionist movement, not the Jews.}} He also said that Muslims and Jews were subjected to the same persecution following the fall of Islamic rule in [[Andalusia]], now [[Spain]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?c=Article_C&amp;pagename=Zone-English-News/NWELayout&amp;cid=1209357181004 &quot;Qaradawi: Muslims Anti Zionists Not Jews&quot;] ION News&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

However, al-Qaradawi has also made statements that some critics charge are [[anti-Semitic]]. In a January 9, 2009, sermon during the [[Gaza War]], shown on [[Al-Jazeera]], Qaradawi prayed (as translated by [[MEMRI]]):{{cquote|Oh Allah, take your enemies, the enemies of Islam. Oh Allah, take the Jews, the treacherous aggressors. Oh Allah, take this [[profligate]], cunning, arrogant band of people. Oh Allah, they have spread much tyranny and corruption in the land. Pour Your wrath upon them, oh our God. Lie in wait for them. Oh Allah, You annihilated the people of [[Thamoud]] at the hand of a tyrant, and You annihilated the people of 'Aad with a fierce, icy gale, and You destroyed the [[Pharaoh]] and his soldiers — oh Allah, take this oppressive, tyrannical band of people. Oh Allah, take this oppressive, Jewish Zionist band of people. Oh Allah, do not spare a single one of them. Oh Allah, count their numbers, and kill them, down to the very last one.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=archives&amp;Area=sd&amp;ID=SP218309 Sheikh Yousef Al-Qaradhawi On Al-Jazeera Incites Against Jews, Arab Regimes, and the U.S.; Calls on Muslims to Boycott Starbucks and Others; Says 'Oh Allah, Take This Oppressive, Jewish, Zionist Band of People... And Kill Them, Down to the Very Last One'], MEMRI – Special Dispatch No. 2183 January 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Also, in August 2005, the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' reported that the [[Dublin]]-based [[European Council for Fatwa and Research]], of which al-Qaradhawi is president, had used the anti-semitic ''[[Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' in its theological deliberations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zmo.de/pressekit/material/Wall_Street_BG.pdf Islamic Justice Finds a Foothold In Heart of Europe] Wall street Journal, 4 August 2005, Vol nr. 24&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Qaradawi's remarks were sharply criticized by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] (ADL), which accused him of inciting violence against Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/NR/exeres/788C5421-70E3-4E4D-BFF4-9BE14E4A2E58%2CDB7611A2-02CD-43AF-8147-649E26813571%2Cframeless.htm Sheik Yusuf al-Qaradawi: Theologian of Terror], Anti-Defamation League, August 4, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/main_Terrorism/qaradawi_gaza_threats.htm Muslim Brotherhood Ideologue Incites Violence Against Jews and Israel], Anti-Defamation League (ADL), February 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lfpress.com/comment/columnists/rory_leishman/2009/10/31/11588271-sun.html Multiculturalists diminish 'rough beast' ravaging Islam] by By Rory Leishman, IFPress.com, October 31, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/opinion/the-bond-between-nazis-and-islam/story-e6frg6zo-1225890936552 The bond between Nazis and Islam] by Paul Berman, The Australian, July 13, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Apostasy====

Al-Qaradawi says that [[apostasy]] &amp;mdash; Muslims leaving Islam &amp;mdash; is a grave danger to the Muslim community and that it is the duty of all Muslims &quot;is to combat apostasy in all its forms and wherefrom it comes, giving it no chance to pervade in the Muslim world.&quot;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:n6vYB-lD6-wJ:www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite%3Fc%3DArticle_C%26cid%3D1178724001992%26pagename%3DZone-English-Living_Shariah/LSELayout+site:islamonline.net+%22Apostasy%22+qaradawi&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=ca&amp;source=www.google.ca |title=Source of the Punishment for Apostasy |publisher=Islamonline.net |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With regards to the punishment of apostasy, al-Qaradawi supports the classical Islamic tradition on some points but differs on others. He considers [[execution]] as a penalty in principle, but the only apostates that are to be executed are those that combine other crimes with apostasy (e.g. &quot;incit[ing] a [[war against Islam]]&quot;). He also advocates that the apostates to be executed should be given a chance to repent. Finally, he believes that &quot;hidden apostasy&quot; (where the apostate does not &quot;proclaim&quot; his conversion) may be left to the judgement of God in the [[Hereafter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite article|title=Apostasy and its Classification in Yusuf Al-Qardawi's View|url=http://www.islamopediaonline.org/fatwa/apostasy-and-its-classification-yusuf-al-qardawis-view|publisher=[[Islamopedia]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While al-Qaradawi believes that the Muslim community is not allowed to punish &quot;intellectual apostasy&quot;, where the apostates do not &quot;swagger&quot; about their conversion, he still strongly condemns it. He says &quot;These people are not noticed when they invade or begin to disseminate their falsehood, but they are mostly felt when they affect the minds. They do not use guns in their attacks, however, their attacks are fierce and cunning.&quot; Nevertheless, he concedes that &quot;Erudite scholars and well versed jurists ... can not take an action in face of such professional criminals who have firmly established themselves and have not left a chance for law to be enforced on them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.onislam.net/english/ask-the-scholar/crimes-and-penalties/apostasy/175287.html| title=Fatwa on Intellectual Apostasy |publisher=OnIslam.net|accessdate=2011-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political views===
====Freedom and democracy====
Al-Qaradawi has spoken in favor of [[democracy]] in the Muslim world,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimnews.co.uk/news/news.php?article=11311 Muslim world needs democracy, says Qaradawi] – The Muslim News – Saturday, July 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; speaking of a need for reform of political climates in the Middle East specifically.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/English/archive/archive?ArchiveId=3779 Reform according to Islam]{{dead link|date=April 2010}}. [http://english.aljazeera.net/ Al Jazeera English]&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 22, 2011, he held an exclusive interview with OnIslam.net, dismissing the allegation that he wanted a religious state established in Egypt:
{{cquote|On the contrary, my speech supported establishing a civil state with a religious background, I am totally against [[theocracy]]. We are not a state for [[mullah]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.onislam.net/english/news/africa/451164-govt-pressures-ban-qaradawi-from-egypt-tv.html] Govt pressure bans Qaradawi&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Terrorism====
After the [[September 11 attacks]], al-Qaradawi urged Muslims to donate blood for the victims and stated,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sept 11 Response&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islam-online.net/English/News/2001-09/13/article25.shtml |title=Qaradawi Condemns Attacks Against Civilians: Forbidden in Islam |publisher=Islam-online.net |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{bquote|Islam, the religion of tolerance, holds the human soul in high esteem, and considers the attack against innocent human beings a grave sin; this is backed by the [[Qur'an]]ic verse which reads:
::Who so ever kills a human being for other than manslaughter or corruption in the earth, it shall be as if he has killed all mankind, and who so ever saves the life of one, it shall be as if he had saved the life of all mankind,&quot; (Al-Ma'dah:32).
The Prophet, peace and blessings be upon him, is reported to have said, 'A believer remains within the scope of his religion as long as he doesn't kill another person illegally'
Islam never allows a Muslim to kill the innocent and the helpless.}}

He denies that Palestinian suicide bombing attacks constitute terrorism, claiming that &quot;when Palestinians face such unjust aggression, they tend to stem bloodletting and destruction and not to claim the lives of innocent civilians&quot;, but qualifies that with &quot;I do agree with those who do not allow such martyr operations to be carried out outside the Palestinian territories.&quot;

Al-Qaradawi has suggested the legitimate use of (defensive) [[suicide bombings]] against enemy combatants in modern times if the defending combatants has no other means of self-defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

The [[Islam in Malaysia|Malaysian Islamic]] Scholar, [[Afifi al-Akiti|Dr.Muhammad Afifi al-Akiti]], rules that there is no [[Fiqh|Islamic legal]] for this view and that female soldiers can only be killed in direct combat. With regards to suicide bombings he says that they are &quot;breaching the [[Ijma|scholarly consensus]] . . . because to endanger one's life is one thing and to commit suicide during the attack is obviously another&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hasan|first=Mehdi|title=Suicide attacks are un-Islamic|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/religion/2009/11/mehdi-hasan--islam-suicide|accessdate=8 May 2011|newspaper=New Statesman|date=5 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With regards to male soldiers he states, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;it goes without saying that they are considered combatants as soon as they arrive on the battlefield even if they are not in direct combat - provided of course that the remaining conventions of war have been observed throughout, and that all this is during a valid war when there is no [[Hudna|ceasefire]]...&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Afifi al-Akiti|first=Muhammad|title=Al-Akiti of Oxford University and author at Living Islam prohibits targeting Israeli civilians, permits attacking soldiers in times of no recognized cease fire in Palestine|url=http://www.islamopediaonline.org/fatwa/al-akiti-oxford-university-and-author-living-islam-prohibits-targeting-israeli-civilians-permi|publisher=Islamopedia Online|accessdate=8 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Western governments have met al-Qaradawi to request release of European civilians kidnapped in Iraq and have thanked him officially, praising his cooperation. The [[French Foreign Minister]] [[Michel Barnier]] wrote to al-Qaradawi: &quot;With such a clear condemnation of the abduction of the French hostages you have sent a clear-cut message demonstrating respect for the tenets of Islam.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatnextjournal.co.uk/Pages/Politics/Welcome.html |title=Qaradawi Is Welcome Peter Roberts Labour Left Briefing, December 2004 |publisher=Whatnextjournal.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Israeli-Palestinian conflict====
Al-Qaradawi condones [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] attacks on [[Israeli people|Israelis]]. A  resolution issued by The Islamic Fiqh Council affiliated to the [[Muslim World League]] in its 14th session, held in [[Doha]] ([[Qatar]]) on 11–16 January 2003 has upheld his views on the matter. Defending bombings against Israeli civilians, al-Qaradawi told ''[[BBC Newsnight]]'' in 2005 that:
* &quot;An Israeli woman is not like women in our societies, because she is a soldier.&quot;
* &quot;I consider this type of martyrdom operation as an evidence of God's justice.&quot;
* &quot;Allah Almighty is just; through his infinite wisdom he has given the weak a weapon the strong do not have and that is their ability to turn their bodies into bombs as Palestinians do&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

He supports suicide attacks on all Israelis, including women&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Mark Oliver and Anushri Patel |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2005/jul/19/july7.uksecurity3 |title=Controversy over cleric's visit grows |publisher=Guardian |date= 2005-07-19|accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2004/07_july/07/newsnight.shtml |title=Yusuf Al-Qaradawi tells BBC Newsnight that Islam justifies suicide bombings |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; since he views the Israeli society as a &quot;completely military&quot; society that did not include any civilians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2001-12/05/article6.shtml |title=Qaradawi Criticizes Al-Azhar for Condemning Jerusalem Attacks |publisher=Islamonline.net |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also considers pregnant women and their unborn babies to be valid targets on the ground that the babies could grow up to join the [[Israeli Army]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.arabnews.com/?page=4&amp;section=0&amp;article=53683&amp;d=30&amp;m=10&amp;y=2004 |title=Stop Terror Sheikhs, Muslim Academics Demand |publisher=Archive.arabnews.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the press conference held by the organizations sponsoring his visit to [[London]], al-Qaradawi reiterated his view that [[suicide attack]]s are a justified form of resistance to Israeli occupation of the rightfully [[Palestinian Territories]]. He has also justified his views by stating that all Israeli civilians are potential soldiers, since Israel is a &quot;militarized society.&quot; Because of these views, al-Qaradawi has been accused by Western countries and Israel of supporting [[terrorism]].

Al-Qaradawi is opposed to attacks outside of the Palestinian Territories and Israel, and against non-Israeli targets.  For example, on March 20, 2005, he condemned a car bombing that had occurred in Doha, Qatar the previous day. One Briton, Jon Adams was killed. Al-Qaradawi issued a statement&lt;ref name=&quot;www_islam_online_net8&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.islam-online.net/English/News/2005-03/20/article04.shtml | title = Islam-online.net | accessdate = 2007-06-18 | publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt; that said{{bquote|Such crimes are committed by insane persons who have no religious affiliation and play well into the hands of the enemies... I urge all Qataris to stand united in facing such an epidemic and uproot it to nip the infection in the bud, otherwise it will spread like wildfire. I, in the name of all scholars in Qatar, denounce such a horrendous crime and pray that it would be the last and implore God to protect this secure country.}}

According to IslamOnline, Qaradawi released a fatwa on April 14, 2004 stating boycott of American and Israeli products was an obligation for all who are able.&lt;ref name=&quot;www_islamonline_net14&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?cid=1119503545220&amp;pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar/FatwaE/FatwaEAskTheScholar | title = islamonline.net | accessdate = 2007-06-18 | publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;www_islamonline_net9&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar/FatwaE/FatwaE&amp;cid=1119503543874 | title = islamonline.net | accessdate = 2007-06-18 | publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The fatwa reads in part :

{{bquote|If people ask in the name of religion we must help them. The vehicle of this support is a complete boycott of the enemies' goods. Each [[riyal]], [[dirham]] …etc. used to buy their goods eventually becomes bullets to be fired at the hearts of brothers and children in Palestine. For this reason, it is an obligation not to help them (the enemies of Islam) by buying their goods. To buy their goods is to support tyranny, oppression and aggression. Buying goods from them will strengthen them; our duty is to make them as weak as we can. Our obligation is to strengthen our resisting brothers in the Sacred Land as much as we can. If we cannot strengthen the brothers, we have a duty to make the enemy weak. If their weakness cannot be achieved except by boycott, we must boycott them.... American goods, exactly like &quot;Israeli&quot; goods, are forbidden. It is also forbidden to advertise these goods. America today is a second Israel. It totally supports the Zionist entity. The usurper could not do this without the support of America. &quot;Israel's&quot; unjustified destruction and vandalism of everything has been using American money, American weapons, and the American veto. America has done this for decades without suffering the consequences of any punishment or protests about their oppressive and prejudiced position from the Islamic world.}}

=====Statements on Adolf Hitler and the Holocaust=====
In a statement which aired on [[Al-Jazeera]] TV on 28 January 2009 during the [[Gaza war]], al-Qaradawi said the following regarding [[Adolf Hitler]] and the [[Holocaust]]:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/2005.htm #2005 - Sheik Yousuf Al-Qaradhawi: Allah Imposed Hitler upon the Jews to Punish Them - &quot;Allah Willing, the Next Time Will Be at the Hand of the Believers&quot;], MEMRITV.org, Clip no. 2005, Al-Jazeera TV (Qatar) - January 28–30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Analysis: Yusuf al-Qaradawi – a ‘man for all seasons’|url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?ID=208978&amp;R=R|work=[[Jerusalem Post]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.investigativeproject.org/992/qaradawis-extremism-laid-bare Qaradawi's Extremism Laid Bare], Investigative Project on Terrorism, IPT News, February 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishworldreview.com/people/emerson050610.php3 Intellectual Double Standards on Islamists] by Steve Emerson, Jewish World Review, May 6, 2010 / 22 Iyar 5770.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{bquote|Throughout history, Allah has imposed upon the Jews people who would punish them for their corruption...The last punishment was carried out by [[Adolf Hitler|[Adolf] Hitler]]. By means of all the things he did to them – even though they exaggerated this issue – he managed to put them in their place. This was [[divine punishment]] for them...Allah willing, the next time will be at the hand of the believers.}}

====Iraq war====
In an address aired on Qatar TV on January 5, 2007, al-Qaradawi questioned the trial of [[Saddam Hussein]] under American supervision in Iraq, but agreed to it if it were conducted by the Iraqi people &quot;after liberating Iraq from American colonialism&quot;. He also suggested that the trial was &quot;an act of vengeance by the Americans&quot; for his missile attacks on Israel. He strongly criticized the way Saddam was hanged:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=countries&amp;Area=iraq&amp;ID=SP142707 |title=Middle East Media Research Institute |publisher=MEMRI |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{cquote|A human soul must be respected. These people did not respect the human soul. The man was calm and kept his cool. He refused to be blindfolded, and insisted upon facing death with open eyes.. and said the two parts of the [[shahada]]....The man died saying: 'There is no God but Allah'....Anybody whose last words are 'There is no God but Allah' goes to Paradise. The thing that improves [the record] of Saddam Hussein is that in his final years – as the brothers in Iraq tell us – he was a changed man. He began to strictly observe the prayers, to read the Quran, and to do charitable work. He would hasten to do anything that may help people. He would help build mosques, and would say that if anybody wants to build a mosque, the government should pay half the cost of the building materials. When they entered his secret hideout and caught him, they found a prayer carpet and an open Quran.}}

====Hezbollah====
In response to Muslim scholar [[Abdullah Ibn Jibreen]]'s fatwa declaring that it was forbidden for Muslims to support or pray for [[Hezbollah]] because they are [[Shia]], al-Qaradawi issued a contrary fatwa, stating that it was mandatory for all Muslims to support Hezbollah in its fight against [[Israel]], claiming that &quot;Shias agree with the Sunnis in the main principles of Islam while the differences are only over the branches.&quot;  In this fatwa, he also called upon the Sunnis and Shia of [[Iraq]] to end the civil war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=99984&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=36&amp;parent_id=16 Qaradawi urges Muslims to support Hezbollah]. Gulf Times&lt;/ref&gt;

====2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests====
Qaradawi declared his support for the rebels led by the [[National Transitional Council]] in the [[2011 Libyan civil war]], urging Arab nations to recognize them and “to confront the tyranny of the regime in Tripoli&quot;. He suggested weapons be sent to the rebels to assist the, and said “Our Islamic nation should stand against injustice and corruption and I urge the Egyptian government to extend a helping hand to Libyan people and not to Gaddafi.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Recognise Libyan rebels: Qaradawi|author=|url=http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=421411&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=36&amp;parent_id=16|newspaper=Gulf Times|date= March 11, 2011|accessdate=March 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the [[2011 Bahrain protests]], Qaradawi was reluctant to give support claiming that,&quot; The protests in Bahrain are sectarian in nature. The Shias are revolting against the Sunnis,&quot;. He claimed that Shia protesters attack Sunnis and occupied their mosques. He acknowledged that the Shia majority had legitimate concerns in regards to fairness with the Sunnis saying that,&quot;I want them to be real citizens of their country&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bharaini Sunnis, Shias should talk to resolve issues: Qaradawi|url=http://www.thepeninsulaqatar.com/qatar/146271-bharaini-sunnis-shias-should-talk-to-resolve-issues-qaradawi.html|accessdate=30 March 2011|newspaper=The Peninsula|date=20 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Qaradawi said all Arabs should back up the protesters in the [[2011 Syrian uprising]], saying &quot;Today the train of revolution has reached a station that it had to reach: The Syria station&quot;, and &quot;It is not possible for Syria to be separated from the history of the Arab community&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Protests in Syria's Daraa city, journalists banned|author=|url=http://www.monstersandcritics.com/news/middleeast/news/article_1628710.php/Protests-in-Syria-s-Daraa-city-journalists-banned|newspaper=Deutsche Presse-Agentur|date=Mar 25, 2011|accessdate=March 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He declared his support for the protests against what he called Syria's &quot;oppresive regime&quot;, claiming &quot;atrocities&quot; were committed by it. He called for victory against the ruling Ba'ath party and claimed the army would be the major factor in the revolt. He claimed that when he offered to mediate negotiations between the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] and the Syrian regime,someone deliberately sabotaged it. Qaradawi also expressed his support for the [[2011 military intervention in Libya|No Fly zone put in place by western nations over Libya]], saying &quot;The operation in Libya is to protect the civilians from Gaddafi’s tyranny&quot;, and slamming the Arab League leader [[Amr Moussa]] for criticism of it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Qaradawi condemns ‘atrocities’ against protesters in Syria|author=Nour Abuzant|url=http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=424384&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=57&amp;parent_id=56|newspaper=Gulf Times|date=26 March 2011|accessdate=March 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women and gender issues===
Commenting on the role women played in social active issues: &lt;blockquote&gt;Although over sixty year have passed since the Movement emerged into existence, no women leaders have appeared that can confront secular and [[Marxist]] trends single-handedly and efficiently. This has come about as a result of men's unrelenting attempts to control women's movement, as men have never allowed women a real chance to express themselves and show special leadership talents and abilities that demonstrate their capability of taking command of their work without men's dominance.

I believe that women's Islamic work will succeed and prove itself in the arena of the Islamic Movement only when it gives birth to female Islamic leaders in the fields of Call, thought, science, literature and education.

Accordingly, women as well as men can dedicate themselves to Allah, and serve as a jihad human bomber.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.palestine-info.info/arabic/fatawa/alamaliyat/qaradawi1.htm Advisory opinion of the scholar Dr. Yusuf al-Qaradawi on women's participation in martyrdom operations]&lt;/ref&gt;

I do not think that this is impossible or even difficult. There are genius women just as there are genius men. Ingenuity is not a monopoly for men. It is not in vain that the Holy Quran tells us the story of a woman who led men wisely and bravely and made her people fare the best end: it is the [[Queen of Sheba]], whose story with [[Solomon]] is told in Surat Al­ Naml. I have observed in the University of Qatar that girls make better students than boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_Priorities/ch2p1.htm#The%20Islamic%20Movement%20And%20Women%20Activity |title='When Will Women's Islamic Work Succeed?' |publisher=Witness-pioneer.org |date=2002-09-16 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Rape====
In 2004 ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' reported that [[IslamOnline]] was asked the following question &quot;Are [[rape]]d women punished in Islam?&quot;, and a panel headed by Qaradawi replied: &quot;To be absolved from guilt, the raped woman must have shown some sort of good conduct... Islam addresses women to maintain their modesty, as not to open the door for evil... The Koran calls upon Muslim women in general to preserve their dignity and modesty, just to save themselves from any harassment... So for a rape victim to be absolved from guilt, she must not be the one that opens... her dignity for [[deflower]]ing...If, after trying her best to resist the attack, she gets overcome by the assailants, she is totally absolved from punishment... any woman, who, despite doing her utmost to resist these thugs and their ilk, is raped, is not guilty of any sin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Syal |first=Rajeev |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1466715/For-her-to-be-absolved-from-guilt-a-raped-woman-must-have-shown-good-conduct.html |title=For her to be absolved from guilt, a raped woman must have shown good conduct |work=The Telegraph|date=2004-07-11 |accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The report by the ''Telegraph'' was sought challenged by the [[Muslim Association of Britain]], who believed the article to be false from &quot;[[right-wing]] media&quot; attempting to &quot;stoke up the flames of hate&quot; against al-Qaradawi. It demanded that the ''Telegraph'' issue a full apology as well as resignation of the two writers of the article. [[IslamOnline]] denied that al-Qaradawi wrote the answer, and claimed that they clearly stated raped women were not punished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.turks.us/article.php?story=20040715063807607 |title=UK Group To Sue Telegraph Over &quot;False&quot; Qaradawi Story |date= July 15, 2004  |work=Daily News |accessdate=March 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Wife Beating====
Al-Qaradawi told ''[[The Guardian]]'' that [[domestic violence|wife-beating]] was neither &quot;obligatory nor desirable&quot; but that he &quot;accepts it as a method of last resort – though only ''lightly''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Madeleine Bunting |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/oct/29/religion.uk1 |title=Friendly fire Madeleine Bunting meets Sheikh Yusuf al-Qaradawi in Qatar |publisher=Guardian |date= 2005-10-29|accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; He stated on Channel 4 News that it was justifiable in certain circumstances&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Ken and the Conservative Cleric&quot;/&gt; but &quot;The ideal was for Muslim men never to beat their wives, and if husbands wrongly beat their wives, they have the right to fight back.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LondonDossier&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://legacy.london.gov.uk/news/docs/qaradawi_dossier.pdf |title=Why the Mayor of London will maintain dialogues with all of London’s faiths and communities – Page 14 – Women's rights |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The British newspaper [[The Daily Telegraph]] writes that al-Qaradawi, in his book ''The Lawful and Prohibited in Islam'', states that wife-beating is permissible after the failure of all other means of persuasion. In such circumstances, a husband may beat his wife &quot;lightly with his hands, avoiding her face and other sensitive areas.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Ken and the Conservative Cleric&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatnextjournal.co.uk/Pages/Politics/Brettlock.html |title=Red Ken and the Conservative Cleric |publisher=Whatnextjournal.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=McCartney |first=Jenny |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/columnists/jennymccartney/3608294/Livingstone-lauds-the-man-who-defends-the-killing-of-gays.html |title=Livingstone lauds the man who defends the killing of gays |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=2004-07-11 |accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Syal |first=Rajeev |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1466715/For-her-to-be-absolved-from-guilt-a-raped-woman-must-have-shown-good-conduct.html |title='For her to be absolved from guilt, a raped woman must have shown good conduct' |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=2004-07-11 |accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Al-Qaradawi, Yusuf. The Lawful and the Prohibited in Islam, Chapter 3:The Halal And The Haram In Marriage And Family Life -&gt; Divorce -&gt; Rebelliousness and Strife&lt;/ref&gt;

====Female Circumcision====
While stating that [[female circumcision]] is &quot;not required&quot; in his book, ''Modern Fatwas''&quot;, he adds: &quot;whoever finds it serving the interest of his daughters should do it, and I personally support this under the current circumstances in the modern world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatnextjournal.co.uk/Pages/Politics/Brettlock.html |title=The Odd Couple: Red Ken and the Conservative Cleric |publisher=Whatnextjournal.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?pagename=Islamonline-English-Ask_Scholar/FatwaE/FatwaE&amp;cid=1119503543886 |title=Ruling on Female Circumcision |publisher=Islamonline.net |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, he does believe that it becomes prohibited when it harms females physically or psychologically.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=19661 Qaradawi Calls On Ending Female Circumcision, Considers It Banned In Islamic Law]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Homosexuality====
Al-Qaradawi believes that [[homosexuality]] should be punishable by death.&lt;ref name=&quot;islamonline.ne&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = islamonline.ne| accessdate = 2010-02-03| publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In his online site, Al-Qaradawi says, &quot;it should be clear that this man committed two heinous crimes: 1) homosexuality, and 2) murder. Each crime is sufficient to warrant [[death penalty]]. In addition, this man has severed ties of kinship by seducing and killing his nephew.&quot;

On June 5, 2006, on the Al Jazeera program ''Sharia and Life'', al-Qaradawi (a regular on the program) reiterated orthodox views on homosexuality.&lt;ref name=&quot;www_aljazeera_net4&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/E3A7EEFB-4016-485A-8D6A-7AA9FD75CBD9.htm | title = aljazeera.net | accessdate = 2007-06-18 | publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked about the punishment for people who &quot;practise liwaat ([[sodomy]]) or sihaaq ([[lesbian]] activity)&quot;, al-Qaradawi replied: &quot;The same punishment as any sexual pervert – the same as the adulterer.&quot; ([[Middle East Media Research Institute|MEMRI]] translation).&lt;ref name=&quot;www_memritv_org5&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.memritv.org/search.asp?ACT=S9&amp;P1=1170# | title = memritv.org | accessdate = 2007-06-18 | publisher = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061002053939/http://www.memritv.org/search.asp?ACT=S9&amp;P1=1170# |archivedate = October 2, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The punishment for adultery is [[stoning]].&lt;ref name=&quot;islamonline.ne&quot;/&gt;

In an interview with ''[[Der Spiegel]]'', Qaradawi said that his attitude towards homosexuality is the same as that found in [[Christianity]]. In the interview he stated, &quot;One year ago, there was a demonstration against me in London because I spoke out against homosexuality. People seem to have forgotten that it wasn't me who came up with this mindset. It's part of God's order spoken of by [[Moses]] and even mentioned by [[Jesus]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,376954,00.html | title = SPIEGEL Interview with Al-Jazeera Host Yusuf Al-Qaradawi | accessdate = 2011-03-01 | publisher = SPIEGEL International}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other Views===
;Wailing wall
On the subject of the [[Wailing Wall]], Qaradawi said:

{{cquote|The Jews' claim to Al-Buraq Wall dates back only to recent times. The longest reign of the Jews lasted for 434 years. Their reign in Palestine dates back to the times of Kings [[Saul]], [[King David|David]] and [[King Solomon|Solomon]]. Solomon’s sons split after his decease: [[Saint Jude|Jude]] headed for Jerusalem while the state of Israel was established in [[Shechem]], that is [[Nablus]]. The Jewish state in Nablus lasted for 298 years and the former for 434. This is the longest period that the Jews reigned. So those who claim that they have a long history in Israel are liars. That history lasted for only 434 years. The Arabs, on the other hand, have been present in Palestine since the days of the [[Jebusites]] and the [[Canaanites]], that is 30 centuries before the birth of Christ. Their history under the umbrella of Islam lasted for more than 14 centuries or even longer. Before the advent of Islam, there had been no Jews in Palestine because since 70 C.E. there had been no trace of Jews or Israelis in Palestine.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar/FatwaE/FatwaE&amp;cid=1119503543546&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;}}

;Mecca Time
In April 2008, at a conference in [[Qatar]] titled &quot;Mecca: the Center of the Earth, Theory and Practice&quot;, al-Qaradawi advocated the implementation of [[Mecca Time]] to replace the [[Greenwich Meridian]] as the basis of the world [[time zone]] system.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Abdelhadi |first=Magdi |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7359258.stm |title=BBC:Muslim call to adopt Mecca time |publisher=BBC News |date=2008-04-21 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Muhammed Cartoon Controversy
Al-Qaradawi called for a &quot;Day of Anger&quot; over the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|cartoons]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rennie |first=David |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2006/02/03/wcart03.xml |title=Daily Telegraph |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=2006-02-03 |accessdate=2010-04-11 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; but condemned violent actions in response to them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2006-02/06/article01.shtml Qaradawi Condemns Violent Cartoon Protests]. IslamOnline.net&lt;/ref&gt;

;Salman Rushdie
Al-Qaradawi endorsed [[Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini]]'s call to execute novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] for [[blasphemy]] in regared to his novel ''[[The Satanic Verses]]'', stating that &quot;Rushdie disgraced the honor of the Prophet and his family and defiled the values of Islam.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,376954,00.html |title=&quot;Spiegel Interview with Al-Jazeera Host Yusuf Al-Qaradawi: God Has Disappeared&quot;([[Der Spiegel]], September 27, 2005) |date=2005-09-27 |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Muslim Brotherhood
Al-Qaradawi was a follower of Hasan al-Banna during his youth and a longtime member of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]].&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt; He has twice turned down offers to be its leader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=moreorless |url=http://www.cesnur.org/2004/qaradawi.htm |title=&quot;Al-Qaradawi Turns Down Offer to Assume Leadership of the Muslim Brotherhood&quot;(al-Jazeera, January 12, 2004) |publisher=Cesnur.org |date=2004-01-12 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview on the [[Dream channel]], al-Qaradawi states the following about his relationship with the Muslim Brotherhood (MB):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=3537 |title=Qaradawi: &quot;MB asked me to be a chairman&quot; – |publisher=Ikhwanweb.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{cquote|I joined the Muslim Brotherhood Group and worked with Imam al-Banna. I was influenced by al-Banna’s moderate thoughts and principles ...(Later) MB asked me to be a chairman, but I preferred to be a spiritual guide for the entire nation... MB consider me their [[Mufti]], but I don’t have a relation with the organization, because being an MB chairman is something difficult requiring a highly sophisticated wisdom, and I prefer to be devoted to the entire nation, and I feel comfortable with this decision. I like MB and consider them the nearest group to be righteous.}}

==Views of Other Scholars==
===From Muslim Academics===

In 2004, 2,500 Muslim academics from [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Iraq]] and from the Palestinian territories condemned al-Qaradawi, and accused him of giving &quot;[[Islam]] a bad name.&quot; with regard to his views on the rights of Palestinians to defend themselves against Israelis.&lt;ref name=&quot;arabnews1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Be merciful to Qaradawi&quot;/&gt;

===From Islamic Scholars===

Qaradawi's methodology has been analysed by other [[Islamic Scholars|Ulama]]. The Pakistani Scholar, [[Muhammad Taqi Usmani]] has stated that &quot;There is no doubt that I—as the lowest student of Islamic Fiqh—with my benefitting from the books of the outstanding Dr al-Qaradāwī to a very large extent, and my supreme wonderment at the majority of [his works], have found myself, in some particular issues, not in agreement with him in the results the he has arrived at, but these sorts of differences (ikhtilāf) in views based on juristic judgement (ijtihādī) are natural, and cannot be the [sole] basis for judging [their author] so long as the people of knowledge do not deem [the bearers of such opinions] to be weak intellectually, or in religion, and [in any case] the importance of these books and their value in scholarship and da‘wa are not affected by this to even the slightest, most insignificant degree.&quot;

In addition, he refers to some modern scholars by writing &quot;What we see today, very unfortunately,is that the one who brings forward elevated ideas in his writings and lofty theories in his speech and his sermons often does not rise&quot;, &quot;above the level of the layman&quot; but exempts Qardawi by saying &quot;As for the outstanding, erudite scholar, Dr Yūsuf al-Qaradāwī, may God (Most High) preserve him, God (Most High) has indeed made me fortunate enough to accompany him in travels and in residence, and sit with him and closely associate with him in long and repeated meetings. [From this] I found him manifest in his personality exemplary Islamic qualities, for he is a human being before he is a Muslim, and a devoted Muslim before he is a caller to Islam (dā‘iya), and a caller to Islam before he is a scholar and jurist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Uthmani|first=Muhammad Taqi|title=Yūsuf al-Qaradāwī, as I Have Known Him|url=http://www.suhaibwebb.com/islam-studies/yusuf-al-qaradawi-as-i-have-known-him-by-mufti-taqi-uthmani-h/|publisher=SuhaibWebb.com|accessdate=28 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
===Disagreement with Muhammad Sayyid Tantawy===

&quot;But, the Sheikh [[Muhammad Sayyid Tantawy|Tantawy]] entered, or was pushed to enter, the area of Fiqh [[Islamic jurisprudence]]. He did not prepare himself for the task. He did not study, practise, or write in Fiqh. He did not train himself in navigating through the deep waters of Fiqh. Therefore, he was not successful in many of his hard-hitting opinions. This was the reason of my disagreement with him despite the old friendship between us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=&amp;nbsp;By Alaa Bayoumi |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/focus/2010/03/201031763554123901.html |title=Focus - The battle for Al-Azhar |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2010-03-17 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Entry into western countries===

Al-Qaradawi has been banned from entering the [[United States]] since 1999 and the [[United Kingdom]] since 2008,&lt;ref name='BBC 2008-02-07'&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Muslim cleric not allowed into UK | date=2008-02-07 | publisher= | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/7232398.stm | work =BBC News | pages = | accessdate = 2008-02-08 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; though he visited London in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;miausma&quot;&gt;[http://ctc.usma.edu/atlas/Atlas-ResearchCompendium.pdf Militant Ideology Atlas], Combating Terrorism Center, West Point&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2003 he visited [[Stockholm]], [[Sweden]], for a conference at the [[Stockholm Mosque]] arranged by the [[Muslim Association of Sweden]]. During the conference al-Qaradawi expressed his support for suicide attacks against Israeli civilians, calling the fight against the Israeli occupation of the Palestinian Territories a &quot;necessary [[Jihad]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=DN&gt;{{cite news |first = Fredrik |last = Malm |authorlink = Fredrik Malm |title = Massmordspredikan i svensk moské |url = http://www.dn.se/DNet/jsp/polopoly.jsp?d=572&amp;a=172705 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20041104021932/http://www.dn.se/DNet/jsp/polopoly.jsp?d=572&amp;a=172705 |archivedate = 2004-11-04 |publisher = [[Dagens Nyheter]] |date = August 21, 2003 |language = Swedish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fatwa controversy with MEMRI===

The [[Middle East Media Research Institute]] (MEMRI) (citing [[Asharq Al-Awsat]]), alleges that al-Qaradawi issued a Fatwa following the [[Iraqi insurgency]], saying,
&lt;blockquote&gt;
All of the Americans in Iraq are combatants, there is no difference between civilians and soldiers, and one should fight them, since the American civilians came to Iraq in order to serve the occupation. The abduction and killing of Americans in Iraq is a [religious] obligation so as to cause them to leave Iraq immediately. The mutilation of corpses [however] is forbidden in Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;www_memri_org11&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=subjects&amp;Area=jihad&amp;ID=SP79404#_edn1 | title = memri.org | accessdate = 2007-06-18 | publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Al-Qaradawi, however, denies this allegation:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I have not published a Fatwa on this issue. At the Egyptian Journalists' Union a few days ago I was asked about the permissibility of fighting against the occupation in Iraq, and I answered that it is permitted. Afterwards I was asked concerning the American civilians in Iraq and I merely responded with the question – are there American civilians in Iraq? It is a matter of common knowledge that in Fatwas such as these I do not use the word &quot;killing&quot; but rather I say &quot;struggle,&quot; which is a more comprehensive word than the word &quot;killing&quot; and whose meaning is not necessarily to kill. In addition, I have condemned the taking of hostages on a number of occasions in the past and have demanded that they be released and that their lives not be threatened.&lt;ref&gt;MEMRI as above, citing [[al-Hayat]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Shaker Al-Nabulsi]], a former Muslim&lt;ref name=&quot;www_memri_org12&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=subjects&amp;Area=jihad&amp;ID=SP79404#_edn20 | title =Reactions to Sheikh Al-Qaradhawi's Fatwa Calling for the Abduction and Killing of American Civilians in Iraq | accessdate = 2008-10-13 | publisher = memri.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; who writes for the liberal site Ethal, called for the creation of a petition to the [[UN]] calling to put Qaradawi and his like on trial for incitement and support of [[terrorism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;www_memri_org12&quot;/&gt;

===Alcohol fatwa controversy===

Al-Qaradawi issued a fatwa in 2008 stating that the consumption of tiny amounts of [[alcohol]] (&lt;0.5% concentration or 5/1000) was acceptable for Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Harrison |first=Frances |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7342425.stm |title=Alcohol fatwa sparks controversy |publisher=BBC News |date=2008-04-11 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statement was made regarding [[energy drink]]s, where fermentation occurs naturally as part of the production process. This does not contradict with the widespread view that consuming alcohol is totally forbidden to Muslims. (chapter 5: verses 90–91). The fermentation in this process is natural and unavoidable, similarly it is an extremely small proportion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/quran/005.qmt.html#005.090 |title=Qur'an Chapter 50: Al Maeda, verse 90 |publisher=Usc.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and recognition==

[[Image:Book on qaradawi.png|thumb|right|''The Global Mufti: The Phenomenon of Yusuf al-Qaradawi'',a book on Qaradawi published by Columbia Press]]
Al-Qaradawi has been awarded by various countries and institutions for his contributions to Islamic society. Among them are
* [[King Faisal Foundation#King Faisal International Prize|King Faisal International Prize]] for Islamic Studies – 1994&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.menofia.edu.eg/announcements/faisal/files/PDF_Files/English/KFIP-Winners-per-Years.pdf |title=Winners |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Development Bank|Islamic Development Bank (IDB)]] Prize in Islamic Economics – 1991&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.isdb.org/irj/go/km/docs/documents/IDBDevelopments/Internet/English/IRTI/CM/About%20IRTI/IDB_Prize.html |title=The IDB Prize in Islamic Economics and Islamic Banking |publisher=Isdb.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sultan Al Owais Award for Cultural &amp; Scientific Achievements – 1998–1999&lt;ref name=&quot;alowaisnet.org&quot;/&gt;
* Sultan Hassanal Bolkiah (Sultan of Brunei) Award for Islamic Jurisprudence – 1997&lt;ref name=&quot;DubaiAward&quot;/&gt;
* [[Dubai International Holy Quran Award]] for Islamic Personality of the Year – 2000&lt;ref name=&quot;DubaiAward&quot;/&gt;
* Tokoh Ma'al Hijrah (Hijra of the Prophet) award by the Malaysian Government −2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2009/12/19/nation/5334691&amp;sec=nation |title=Work together to enhance cooperation, Sultan Abdul Halim tells Muslims |publisher=Thestar.com.my |date=2009-12-19 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The State Acknowledgement Award  for contributions in the field of Islamic Studies from the Government of Qatar – 2008&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diwan.gov.qa/english/the_amir/the_amir_activities_88.htm |title=H.H. The Amir presents the State Acknowledgement Award to Dr. Sheikh Yusuf Al Qaradawi for his contributions in the field of Islamic Studies |publisher=Diwan.gov.qa |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Qatar Faculty of Islamic Studies, part of the [[Qatar Foundation|Qatar Foundation for Education, Science and Community Development]], instituted the &quot;Sheikh Yusuf Al Qaradawi Scholarships&quot; in 2009, awarding them to five students each year for post-graduate studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.qfis.edu.qa/files/pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%20QFIS_Scholarships%202009-2010.pdf Qatar Faculty of Islamic Studies (QFIS)]&lt;/ref&gt; It also named after him its newly established research centre, The Qaradawi Center for Islamic Moderation and Renewal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabianbusiness.com/572720-qatar-centre-spreads-moderate-islam-dialogue |title=Qatar centre spreads moderate Islam, dialogue |publisher=Arabianbusiness.com |date=2009-11-07 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=314242&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=57 |title=Qaradawi centre vows to fight extremism |publisher=Gulf-times.com |date=2009-12-09 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He is a trustee of the [[Oxford University]] Center for Islamic Studies&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian.co.uk&quot;/&gt; and has been named as the technical consultant for a multi-million dollar [[English-language]] film about [[Prophet Muhammed]] produced by [[Barrie Osborne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;zawya.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GuardianBiopic&quot;/&gt;
A 2008 ''[[Foreign Policy]]'' poll put him at No.3 in the list of the Top 20 Public Intellectuals worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;foreignpolicy.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2008/06/16/the_world_s_top_20_public_intellectuals |title=The World’s Top 20 Public Intellectuals |publisher=Foreignpolicy.com |date=2008-06-16 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
===Fiqh az Zakat===

Al -Qaradawi has authored more than 80 books and his academic style and objective thought are considered to be some of the main characteristics of his works.&lt;ref name=&quot;AnaSoage&quot;/&gt; His most famous work is ''The Lawful and Prohibited in Islam''. Professor Mustafa al-Zarqa declared that owning a copy of it was &quot;the duty of every Muslim family.&quot; His book ''Fiqh al-Zakat'' is considered by some as the most comprehensive work in the area of [[zakat]]. [[Abul Ala Maududi]] commented on it as &quot;the book of this century in Islamic jurisprudence (fiqh)&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DubaiAward&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AnaSoage&quot;/&gt;
The prominent [[Deobandi]] [[Islamic scholar]] [[Muhammad Taqi Usmani]], said this about the work:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suhaibwebb.com/islam-studies/yusuf-al-qaradawi-as-i-have-known-him-by-mufti-taqi-uthmani-h/ Yūsuf al-Qaradāwī, as I Have Known Him]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The first book that read in its entirety of his works is his valuable book Fiqh al-Zakat, and I benefitted much from this great, encyclopedic, rewarding work through which the author did a great service to the second of the pillars of Islam, in a way that the umma needs today, when it comes to the application of zakat at the level of the individual and the group. Indeed this work manifested the genius of its author, and his inventive methodology, not only in the clarification of issues pertaining to zakat and their compilation, but in stimulating research in contemporary topics that no one before him had touched upon, and basing them upon the principles fiqh and its jurisprudential theory.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Fiqh al Jihad===

His book ''Fiqh al-Jihad'' has been widely commented on. ''[[The Guardian]]''{{'}}s writes:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/belief/2009/aug/17/islam-jihad-qaradawi Yusuf Qaradawi's jihad]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{bquote|Instead Qaradawi encourages a &quot;middle way&quot; conception of [[jihad]]: &quot;solidarity&quot; with the Palestinians and others on the front line, rather than violence, is an obligatory form of jihad. Financial jihad, which corresponds with the obligation of alms giving ([[zakat]]), counts as well. And Muslims should recognise that technological change means that media and information systems are as much a part of the jihadist repertoire as are guns. Indeed, as long as Muslims are free to use media and other resources to press their case, there is no justification for using force to &quot;open&quot; countries for Islam.}}

This book has also been analyzed by [[University of Michigan]] professor [[Sherman Jackson]] and Tunisian reformer [[Rachid Ghannouchi]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.casaw.ac.uk/conf/rj2009/documents/ReThinkingJihad2009Report.pdf Rethinking Jihad: Ideas, Politics and Conflict in the Arab World and Beyond Conference Report]&lt;/ref&gt;

His views on jihad have attracted criticism from some hard line groups:

{{bquote|Now, any Sunni knows that the purpose of jihaad is to make the word of Allaah supreme, and that is none other than worshipping Him alone, and establishing and spreading Tawheed. So if the Qaradawite think tank and its theoreticians claim that this is not the motive and reason, and it is but land, then the land in the view of Qaradawite Thought, is more lofty and more noble and more worthy than the Islamic aqidah.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamicweb.com/beliefs/misguided/qaradawi.htm Some Mistakes Of Yusuf Al-Qaradawi]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Major works==
Some of al-Qaradawi's major works are:
* [http://www.newvision.tc/?zSystem=eShop&amp;Lang=&amp;sc=E083 ''Time in the life of the Muslim]
* [http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_Priorities/index.htm ''Priorities of the Islamic Movement in the Coming Phase]
* [http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_awake/index.htm ''Towards a Sound Awakening]
* [http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_WI/default.htm ''The Status of Women in Islam]
* [http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_RE/index.htm ''Islamic Awakening between Rejection and Extremism]
* [http://www.witness-pioneer.org/vil/Books/Q_LP/ ''The Lawful and Prohibited in Islam'']
* [http://www.returntoislam.com/wiki/index.php/Diversion_and_Arts_In_Islam ''Diversion and Arts In Islam''] (in progress)
* ''Islam: Modern Fatwas on Issues of Women and the Family'' (Fatawa Mu'asira fi Shu'un al-Mar'a wa al-Usrah) (Dar al-Shihab, Algeria, 1987)

He has also published some excerpts of his poetry in the book ''Nafahat wa Lafahat''.

Al-Qaradawi has also been the subject of the book ''The Global Mufti: The Phenomenon of Yusuf al-Qaradawi'' published by Columbia University Press.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/0231700709 |title=The Global Mufti: The Phenomenon of Yusuf al-Qaradawi (Columbia/Hurst) |publisher=Amazon.com |date=2009-09-09 |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is also profiled as one of the leading liberal voices in contemporary Islam in [[Charles Kurzman]]'s book ''Liberal Islam: A Sourcebook'', published by [[Oxford University Press]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/0195116224 |title=Liberal Islam, 1998 Edition, Chapter 22 Yusuf Al-Qaradawi |publisher=Amazon.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Abdullah bin Bayyah]]
* [[Khurshid Ahmad (Islamic scholar)|Khurshid Ahmad]]
* [[Qur'an]]
* [[Template:Islam|Quick list on Islam]]

==Notes==
{{Ibid|date=February 2011}}
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.islamonline.net/ Islam Online]
* [http://www.qaradawi.net/ Personal website] (in Arabic)
* {{Worldcat id|lccn-n82-164852}}
* [http://www.newvision.tc/ Al-Qaradawi's books translated into English and French]
* [[Wolfgang G. Schwanitz]]: ''Global Mufti al-Qaradawi'', Webversion [http://www.trafoberlin.de/pdf-dateien/2011_04_26/Bettina%20Graef%20Jakob%20Skovgaard-Petersen%20Global%20Mufti.pdf 12-2010]
* [http://meria.idc.ac.il/journal/2008/issue1/pdf/5.pdf &quot;Shaykh Yusuf Al-Qaradawi: Portrait of a leading Islamist cleric&quot;], Ana Belén Soage, ''[[Middle East Review of International Affairs]]'', 12/1 (March 2008), pp.&amp;nbsp;51–65
* [http://en.qantara.de/webcom/show_article.php/_c-478/_nr-1007/i.html Yusuf al-Qaradawi and Minorities: Learned Intolerance], ''[[Qantara.de]]
* [http://www.london.gov.uk/moderngov/Data/London%20Assembly%20(Mayor's%20Question%20Time)/20050914/Minutes/Transcript%20PDF.pdf Daily Assembly 14 September 2005], Mayor of London about Qardawi and Pope John XXIII, pp.&amp;nbsp;12–13, [[Greater London Authority]]

{{Islamism}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Qaradawi, Yusuf Al-
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1926-09-09
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Gharbia]] [[Egypt]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Qaradawi, Yusuf al-}}
[[Category:1926 births]]
[[Category:Egyptian religious leaders]]
[[Category:Egyptian imams]]
[[Category:Egyptian Sunni Muslims]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Egyptian Islamists]]
[[Category:Islamic democracy activists]]
[[Category:Egyptian television personalities]]
[[Category:Sunni imams]]
[[Category:Egyptian Muslims]]
[[Category:Personae non gratae]]
[[Category:21st-century imams]]
[[Category:Muslim Brotherhood figures]]
[[Category:Muslim theologians]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]

{{Link FA|he}}

[[ar:يوسف القرضاوي]]
[[az:Yusif əl-Qərdavi]]
[[cs:Jusúf al-Karadáví]]
[[de:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[fa:یوسف قرضاوی]]
[[fr:Youssef al-Qaradâwî]]
[[id:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[it:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[he:יוסוף אל-קרדאווי]]
[[ml:യൂസുഫ് അൽ ഖറദാവി]]
[[ms:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[nl:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[ja:アル・カラダウィ]]
[[no:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[ps:يوسف عبدالله القرضاوي]]
[[pl:Jusuf al-Kardawi]]
[[pt:Yusuf Al-Qaradawi]]
[[ru:Кардави, Юсуф]]
[[sq:Jusuf El-Kardavi]]
[[so:Sh. Yuusuf Alqardaawi]]
[[sv:Yusuf al-Qaradawi]]
[[tt:Йосыф әл-Кардави]]
[[th:ยูซุฟ ก็อรฏอวี]]
[[tr:Yusuf el Karadavi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
