<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4578009" ns="0" title="Arizona State Sun Devils"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
| name             = Arizona State Sun Devils
| logo             = Asu.png
| university       = Arizona State University
| conference       = [[Pacific-12 Conference]]
| division         = Division I
| director         = [[Lisa Love (coach)|Lisa Love]]
| city             = Tempe
| state            = Arizona
| stateabb         = AZ
| teams            = 20
| stadium          = [[Sun Devil Stadium]]
| arena            = [[Wells Fargo Arena (Tempe)|Wells Fargo Arena]]
| baseballfield    = [[Packard Stadium]] 
| mascot           = [[Sparky the Sun Devil|Sparky]]
| nickname         = Sun Devils
| color1           = ASU Maroon
| color2           = ASU Gold
| hex1             = 800000
| hex2             = FFD700
| pageurl          = http://thesundevils.cstv.com
| pagename         = www.thesundevils.com
}}

The '''Arizona State Sun Devils''' are the athletic teams representing [[Arizona State University]].  ASU has nine men's and eleven women's [[Varsity team|varsity]] teams competing in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Pacific-12 Conference]].  The men compete in [[baseball]], [[basketball]], [[Cross country running|cross country]], [[American football|football]], [[golf]], [[diving]], [[Track and field|track]], and [[collegiate wrestling|wrestling]]. Women compete in basketball, cross country, golf, gymnastics, soccer, softball, swimming/diving, tennis, track, volleyball, and water polo.

Athletes at ASU are known as &quot;Sun Devils.&quot; The mascot was adopted in 1946; earlier nicknames were the Normals or the Owls and, later, the Bulldogs. The Sun Devil mascot, [[Sparky (Arizona State Mascot)|Sparky]], was designed by former [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] illustrator Bert Anthony.  ASU's chief rival is the [[University of Arizona]] [[Arizona Wildcats|Wildcats]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/trads/asu-trads-sparky.html|title=Let's call them Sun Devils}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable athletic achievements==
ASU has 23 NCAA team national championships, including baseball (five times), women's tennis (three times), men's gymnastics (one), men's track and field (one), men's indoor track and field (one), women's outdoor track and field (two times), women's indoor track and field (one), wrestling (one), men's golf (two times), women's golf (thirteen times), softball (two times), and women's swimming and diving (seven times). These combine for a total of 133 team national championships. ASU also has numerous individual NCAA national champions in different sports. Additionally, the baseball team has appeared in the [[College World Series]] 22 times, the men's basketball team has participated in 13 [[NCAA]] tournaments, including 3 Elite Eight appearances, and the ASU football team won the [[Rose Bowl Game|Rose Bowl]] in [[1987 Rose Bowl|1987]] and the [[Fiesta Bowl]] in 1971, 1972, 1973, 1975, and 1982.

ASU won national championships in men's archery 15 times, women's archery 21 times, mixed archery 20 times, men's badminton 13 times, women's badminton 17 times and mixed badminton 10 times, all which are not recognized by the NCAA.

==Sports==
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Sparky.png|thumb|right|Sparky the Sun Devil]] --&gt;

===Football===
{{Main|Arizona State Sun Devils football}}
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Sundevil_stadium.jpg|thumb|300px|left|''Sun Devil Stadium'']] --&gt;
The Sun Devils played in the [[Border Intercollegiate Athletic Association|Border Conference]] between 1931 and 1961, before joining the [[Western Athletic Conference]]. Led by legendary head coach [[Frank Kush]], the Sun Devils posted a remarkable 62–9 record between 1970 and 1975, culminating in a 17–14 upset of the [[University of Nebraska-Lincoln|Nebraska Cornhuskers]] in the 1975 Fiesta Bowl.

In 1978, both ASU and the [[University of Arizona]] joined the Pacific-8 Conference, causing the conference to become the Pacific-10 (which grew again in 2011 to become the Pacific-12). The Sun Devils suffered some down years due to a number of head coaching changes, but were still able to make it to the 1983 Fiesta Bowl and 1987 Rose Bowl winning both. 

After the [[2006 Arizona State Sun Devils football team|2006]] season, [[Dirk Koetter]] was fired after six seasons, and on December 6, 2006, athletic director [[Lisa Love (coach)|Lisa Love]] hired [[Dennis Erickson]] to become the head coach at ASU. Erickson, in his first year as coach of the Arizona State Sun Devils, led the team to 10 wins, a share of the Pac-10 title with USC, and the Holiday Bowl against the University of Texas Long Horns.

Notable football alumni include [[Jim Jeffcoat]], [[Jake Plummer]], [[Todd Heap]], [[J.R. Redmond]], [[Danny White]], [[Terrell Suggs]], [[Randall McDaniel]], [[David Fulcher]], [[Darren Woodson]], [[Pat Tillman]], [[Eric Allen]], [[Zach Miller]], [[Shaun McDonald]], [[John Jefferson]], [[Paul Justin]], [[Jimmy Verdon]], [[Mike Haynes (cornerback)|Mike Haynes]], [[Al Harris (defensive lineman)|Al Harris]] and [[Ryan Torain]].

===Men's Basketball===
{{Split|Arizona State Sun Devils men's basketball|date=February 2010}}
[[File:20090117 James Harden makes contact with Alfred Aboya inside.jpg|thumb|[[James Harden (basketball)|James Harden]] makes contact with [[Alfred Aboya]] inside.]]
The Arizona State Sun Devils have appeared in the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|NCAA Tournament]] 13 times, including 3 Elite Eights (1961, 1963, 1975). They have won 8 conference championships (4 WAC and 4 BOR) and finished in the final AP rankings 7 times. The highest national ranking the Sun Devils have achieved was #3 under [[Ned Wulk]] during the 1980–81 season when the starting lineup included [[Byron Scott (basketball)|Byron Scott]], [[Fat Lever]], and [[Alton Lister]]. [[Ned Wulk]] was the men's basketball coach from 1958 to 1982 and remains the most successful coach in the history of the program with a record of 406 – 272 (.599). 

Arizona State appeared in the [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]] Men's Basketball [[NAIA national men's basketball championship|National Tournament]] two years ([[1948 NAIA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|1948]] and [[1953 NAIA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|1953]]). Both years losing in the second round, leaving the NAIA with a tournament record of 2–2.

[[Herb Sendek]] is the current head coach of the Sun Devils. Sendek stepped down as head coach of the [[North Carolina State Wolfpack]] and accepted the head coaching job at Arizona State in 2006. During a successful career in Raleigh, Sendek took the Wolfpack to five consecutive NCAA Tournaments and also won [[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC]] coach of the year in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hsendek&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herb_Sendek|title=Herb Sendek}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sendek was credited for bringing a &quot;basketball atmosphere&quot; and level of excitement to the ASU campus that had been absent for years. In his first four seasons at ASU, Sendek led the Sun Devils to three consecutive 20 win seasons, the 2009 Pac-10 conference tournament finals, and the second round of the NCAA tournament.

Thirty-six ASU Sun Devils have been selected in the [[NBA Draft]], including [[James Harden (basketball)|James Harden]], [[Byron Scott (basketball)|Byron Scott]], [[Isaac Austin]], [[Lafayette Lever]], [[Alton Lister]], [[Lionel Hollins]], Sam Williams, [[Jeff Pendergraph]], [[Stevin Smith|Stevin &quot;Hedake&quot; Smith]], [[Mario Bennett]], [[Tommy Smith (basketball)|Tommy Smith]], [[Ike Diogu]], [[Eddie House]]. [[Freddie Lewis]], and [[Joe Caldwell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Devils drafted&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/archive/062305aab.html|title=ASU players drafted into the NBA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Baseball===

[[File:Ike Davis cropped.jpg|thumb|left|[[Ike Davis]], first baseman for&lt;br&gt;the New York Mets]]
{{Main|Arizona State Sun Devils baseball}}
ASU is one of the most successful baseball programs in the country. The Sun Devils have won five national championships ([[1965 College World Series|1965]], [[1967 College World Series|1967]], [[1969 College World Series|1969]], [[1977 College World Series|1977]], [[1981 College World Series|1981]]), the fourth most by any school, and have the third most [[College World Series]] victories with 61.&lt;ref name=&quot;baseballws&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/sports/m-basebl/spec-rel/061202aaa.html|title=Baseball World Series history}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

ASU baseball has won 21 conference championships (including four consecutive Pac-10 titles from 2007–2010) and reached the [[College World Series]] 22 times. The Sun Devils have also reached the NCAA tournament 34 times, most recently in 2011. 

Starting with [[Rick Monday]] as the #1 pick of the first ever [[Major League Baseball]] draft in '65, ASU leads all schools with 368 total picks. ASU also has the third most alumni to ever play in [[Major League Baseball]]. Notable baseball alumni include [[Barry Bonds]], [[Paul Lo Duca]], [[Fernando Viña]], [[Dustin Pedroia]], [[Mike Leake]], [[Andre Ethier]], [[Willie Bloomquist]], [[Bob Horner]], [[Sal Bando]], [[Ike Davis]], [[Jason Kipnis]], [[Brett Wallace]], [[Ian Kinsler]], [[Hubie Brooks]], and Hall of Famer [[Reggie Jackson]].

===Softball===
{{Main|Arizona State Sun Devils Softball}}

One of the nation's founding programs, the two-time NCAA national champion Sun Devils are in their 45th season on the diamond. ASU has recorded twenty-seven seasons of 30 or more wins and twelve with 40 or more, including an all-time high of 66 wins in 2008. The Sun Devils have appeared in 23 NCAA tournaments (33 postseason bids overall) and have made nine trips to the [[Women's College World Series]]. Prior to the current NCAA format, ASU went to seven WCWS, claiming back-to-back national tiles in 1972 and 1973. Arizona State's storied tradition of softball excellence continues to flourish under head coach Clint Myers, who has led the Sun Devils to two NCAA national championships. Myers joined Linda Vollstedt (women’s golf – 7), Greg Kraft (women’s track &amp; field indoor – 2, women’s track &amp; field outdoor – 1, men’s indoor track &amp; field – 1), [[Bobby Winkles]] (baseball – 3) and [[Jim Brock]] (baseball – 2) as Sun Devil coaches with more than one NCAA title. 

The Sun Devils capped off the 2008 season with their first WCWS NCAA national championship on June 3, 2008. [[Kaitlin Cochran]] hit a three-run home run, [[Katie Burkhart]] pitched a four-hitter and Arizona State routed Texas A&amp;M 11–0 to win the title. Cochran slammed the first pitch from Megan Gibson over the left field fence in the fifth inning to give the sixth-seeded Sun Devils a 4–0 lead in the fifth inning. The margin ended up matching the second-most lopsided game in Women's College World Series history.

On June 7, 2011, the Sun Devils captured their second NCAA national championship by defeating the Florida Gators. ASU pitcher, Dallas Escobedo, became the first freshman pitcher to lead a team to the NCAA title since 1990.

===Golf===
Notable golf alumni include [[Phil Mickelson]], [[Billy Mayfair]], [[Paul Casey]], [[Bob Gilder]], [[Howard Twitty]], [[Tom Purtzer]], [[Jeff Quinney]], [[Matt Jones (golfer)|Matt Jones]], [[Chez Reavie]], [[Grace Park (golfer)|Grace Park]], [[Heather Farr]], [[Anna Nordqvist]], [[Wendy Ward]], and [[Azahara Muñoz]].

===Wrestling===
ASU has had a very successful wrestling team. The Sun Devils have captured one NCAA team national championship (1988), eight individual championships, and 100 total All American honors.&lt;ref name=&quot;wrestlinginfo&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/sports/m-wrestl/stats/082904aaf.html|title=ASU wrestling championships}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable alumni include several MMA stars, such as [[Dan Severn]], [[Cain Velasquez]], [[Ryan Bader]], [[Aaron Simpson]], [[Dan Henderson]], [[Clifford Starks]] and [[C.B. Dollaway]].

Eight Sun Devils have participated in the Olympic games, most recently in the 1996 Olympic games in Atlanta. There have been two silver medalists; Zeke Jones and Townsend Saunders.&lt;ref name=&quot;wrestlingolympics&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/asu/sports/m-wrestl/auto_pdf/olympians.pdf|format=PDF|title=ASU Olympians PDF }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Six Sun Devils have participated in the World Championships of Wrestling since 1985 (a total of 16 entries). those wrestlers placed in the top 10 a total of ten times, including Zeke Jones, the 1991 champion at 114.5 pounds.
 
During the 1992–1993 season ASU set a Pacific-10 Conference record for most points in a championship meet.&lt;ref name=&quot;wrestling&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/sports/m-wrestl/archive/asu-m-wrestl-yearbyyear.html|title=ASU wrestling}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 13, 2008, the university announced it will drop the sport of Wrestling as well as Men's Tennis and Men's Swimming to save more than $1 million in operational costs. Just 10 days after the announcement to drop three sports, Arizona State announced it was reinstating the varsity wrestling program. The announcement came as local and civic sponsorship was announced as the reason to bring the sport back.

==Championship history==
===National championships===
Arizona State has 23 [[NCAA]] team national championships &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|Pac 10 record book|url=http://www.pac-10.org/portals/7/images/PDFs/RecordBook/ncaa-sport.pdf|title=2010–11 Basketball PAC-10 NCAA Championships}}&lt;/ref&gt; :

{{Div col}}
:'''Baseball''' (5)
:*1965, 1967, 1969, 1977, 1981&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ncaa.com/history/default.aspx?id=87920|title=Division I Baseball Champions}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Men's Golf''' (2)
:*1990, 1996&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ncaa.com/history/default.aspx?id=87970|title=Division I Men's Golf Champions}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Men's Gymnastics''' (1)
:*1986&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ncaa.com/history/default.aspx?id=87982|title=National Collegiate Men's Gymnastics}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Men's Indoor Track and Field''' (1)
:*2008&lt;ref name=itaf&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ncaa.com/history/default.aspx?id=88064|title=Division I Indoor Track &amp; Field – Team Champions}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Men's Outdoor Track and Field''' (1)
:*1977&lt;ref name=taf&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ncaa.com/history/default.aspx?id=88070|title=Division I Outdoor Track &amp; Field – Team Champions}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Wrestling''' (1)
:*1988
:'''Women's Golf''' (7)
:*1990, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1997, 1998, 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ncaa.com/history/default.aspx?id=87976|title=Division I Women's Golf Champions}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''Women's Indoor Track and Field''' (2)
:*2007, 2008&lt;ref name=itaf/&gt;
:'''Women's Outdoor Track and Field''' (1)
:*2007&lt;ref name=taf/&gt;
:'''Softball''' (2)
:*[[2008 Women's College World Series|2008]], [[2011 Women's College World Series|2011]]
 {{Div col end}}

==Rivalries==
A strong academic and athletic rivalry exists between the [[University of Arizona]] and Arizona State University. Arizona leads the all-time record against ASU in men's basketball 139–79 as of January 2010. 

Arizona State University fields the more accomplished baseball team with five [[College World Series]] national championships (1965, 1967, 1969, 1977 and 1981). As of May 2010, the schools have met 432 times on the baseball diamond, dating back over 100 years to the first contest in 1907. Arizona, recognizing victories against club teams (ASU did not adopt varsity baseball until 1959)&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://asunews.asu.edu/20100510_Baseball_vsBYU_UA |title=Baseball hosts BYU before facing UA &amp;#124; ASU News |publisher=Asunews.asu.edu |date=May 10, 2010 |accessdate=February 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; claims the all-time series 233–198–1.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArizonaASUBaseball&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.arizonawildcats.com/sports/m-basebl/spec-rel/031808aaa.html|title=Arizona vs. ASU Baseball Record }}&lt;/ref&gt; ASU, recognizing only varsity baseball competition (beginning in 1959), claims a 179–115 edge in the all-time series (as of May 2010).&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

The annual football rivalry game between the two schools is known as &quot;The Duel in the Desert.&quot; It is one of the most heated rivalries in college football. The [[University of Arizona]] has the all-time series lead with a record of 46–37–1 dating back to the time when ASU was the Tempe Normal Owls and Teacher's College Bulldogs. The school adopted the moniker, the Sun Devils, on November 20, 1946.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/trads/asu-trads-sparky.html |title=Arizona State Official Athletic Site – Traditions |publisher=Thesundevils.cstv.com |date=November 8, 1946 |accessdate=February 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since Arizona State became a university in 1958, the Sun Devils lead the rivalry series over the [[University of Arizona Wildcats]] by a record of 29–23–1. The trophy awarded after each game, the [[Territorial Cup]], is one of the nation's oldest rivalry trophies. It is currently held by Arizona. 

In 2009, State Farm introduced the sponsored &quot;State Farm Territorial Cup&quot; for the two schools. Arizona won the inaugural season of the series 10.5 points to 7.5.

The ASU wrestling team has been dominant over the UA Wildcats with a record of 28–8 all time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ASUwrestleingrecord&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thesundevils.cstv.com/sports/m-wrestl/archive/asu-m-wrestl-series.html|title=ASU's all time record (wrestling)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The University of Arizona no longer has a wrestling program.

==ASU athletic facilities==
[[Mona Plummer Aquatic Center]] 
*The Mona Plummer Aquatic Center, located on the campus of Arizona State University, is regarded as one of the country's finest outdoor swimming and diving facilities.

[[Karsten Golf Course]]
*At the ASU Karsten Golf Course, challenge is inherent. Many touring professionals have honed their skills on the fairways and greens of this classic Pete Dye, Scottish links course. The course is home to the ASU Golf Program, which turns out winning teams year after year.

[[Packard Stadium]]
*Packard Stadium, the home of Arizona State baseball since 1974, is one of the nation's most beautiful ballparks. The outfield wall is lined with orange trees and just beyond the left field fence lies the Salt River which winds its way through the Valley of the Sun. The field is named in honor of [[College Baseball Hall of Fame]] coach [[Bobby Winkles]]. In 2006, Bobby Winkles Field-Packard Stadium at Brock Ballpark was dedicated to the memory of another College Baseball Hall of Fame coach [[Jim Brock]].

[[Arizona State University Soccer Stadium]]
*On April 1, 2000, Arizona State University unveiled the latest amenity in its sports facilities, the Soccer Stadium. The Soccer Stadium features chair-back bleachers and individual seats with a capacity for 1,051 fans.

[[Alberta B. Farrington Softball Stadium]]
*On April 8, 2000, Arizona State University unveiled the Alberta B. Farrington Softball Stadium. It is the latest amenity among the sports facilities of Sun Devil Athletics. Farrington Stadium features chair-back bleachers and individual seats with a capacity for 1,535 fans.

[[Sun Angel Stadium, Joe Selleh Track]]
*Arizona State University's men's and women's track and field teams compete at Sun Angel Stadium/Joe Selleh Track, which opened in 1976. The stadium was completed in 1975 at an estimated cost of $3 million.

[[Sun Devil Stadium]]
*Arizona State University's Sun Devil Stadium has played host to football games for more than four decades. On September 21, 1996, the school held [[Frank Kush]] Day and announced that the playing field at Sun Devil Stadium would be named &quot;Frank Kush Field&quot; in his honor.

[[Wells Fargo Arena (Tempe)|Wells Fargo Arena]]
*Wells Fargo Arena is the home for Sun Devil men's and women's basketball as well as volleyball, gymnastics and wrestling. Constructed in the spring of 1974, the 14,198-seat facility also plays host to graduation ceremonies and a variety of concerts and shows.

[[Whiteman Tennis Center]]
*The Whiteman Tennis Center serves as the home to Arizona State's nationally ranked women's tennis teams. The original complex was dedicated May 8, 1976. It featured eight fully lit asphalt-based courts with a seating capacity of 1,200.

==See also==
* [[2008–09 Pacific-10 Conference men's basketball season]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://thesundevils.cstv.com/index-main.html Arizona State Sun Devils – Official Site]
* [http://thesundevils.cstv.com/facilities/asu-facilities.html Arizona State University Athletic Facilities]
* [http://www.azcentral.com/sports/asu/ ASU sports coverage on The Arizona Republic/azcentral.com]

{{ASU}}
{{Pacific-12 Conference}}
{{Arizona Sports}}

[[Category:Arizona State Sun Devils| ]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]
[[Category:College sports teams in Arizona]]

[[es:Arizona State Sun Devils]]
[[fr:Arizona State Sun Devils]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
