<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4579092" ns="0" title="Vodafone Egypt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{POV-check|date=June 2008}}
{{Refimprove|date=January 2011}}
{{Advert|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox Company   
| company_name     = Vodafone Egypt
| company_logo     = &lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here without complying with WP:NFCC #10c --&gt;
| company_type     = [[Privately held company|Private]]
| company_slogan   = power to you
| foundation       = 1998
| location_city    = [[Cairo]]
| location_country =  [[Egypt]]
| industry         = [[Telecommunication]]s
| products         = Mobile phone services
| parent           = [[Vodafone Group]] (54.9%)
                     [[Telecom Egypt]] (44.7%)
| CEO              = Hatem Dowidar
| homepage         = [http://www.vodafone.com.eg www.vodafone.com.eg]
}}
'''Vodafone Egypt''' is [[Egypt]]'s largest [[mobile network operator]]. It was launched in 1998 and was formerly known as '''Click GSM'''. 
==About Vodafone Egypt==   
Vodafone Egypt is a telecommunications service and product provider. It was established in 1998. It covers various voice and data exchange services, as well as 3G, ADSL and broadband Internet services.
Vodafone Egypt General Assembly voted in September 2006 in favor of the acquisition of 51% of Raya Telecom shares,,so as to expand corporate communication services. A further acquisition of up to 97.52% of Raya Telecom shares followed in 2008. Vodafone secured a stronger share when Telecom Egypt pushed for a major increase of its own Vodafone corporate share from 25.5% to 44.7% in a massive stock acquisition move. Today, Vodafone still owns a 54.9% share of Vodafone Egypt.

Another step for Vodafone Egypt was its close matching of its own corporate policy with local government policy through the provision of job opportunities for young graduates, exporting products and the launch of its call center in Egypt. In 2006 Vodafone Egypt signed call center contracts with Vodafone Australia, New Zealand and lately the UK to provide customer and technical support for customers in these countries.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

Vodafone Egypt is Egypt’s largest mobile operator serving 31.8 million customers (March 2011) all over Egypt. Vodafone Egypt’s roaming communication services are supported by agreements with 564 partners in 188 countries.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

==Vodafone Egypt products and services==
Vodafone Egypt provides a wide range of voice and data exchange services, as well as 3G, ADSL and broadband Internet services.
Vodafone Egypt provide its services for both consumer and businesses in Egypt focusing on Total telecommunication services from Voice to Data and Internet services.

==Vodafone Egypt International Services (VIS)==
Vodafone International Services is a subsidiary of Vodafone Egypt delivering outsourcing &amp; off-shoring [[solution]]s and services. It is an international operation providing global off-shoring services for customers in locations all over the world that are seeking to outsource contact centers, business processes, and IT software development and support.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

==Vodafone Egypt corporate social responsibility==
In 1998, Vodafone Egypt pioneered the practice of corporate social responsibility and initiated national awareness on the importance of corporate social responsibility and sustainability as integral key part of corporate development. Since 2003, the concept continued to evolve along with the commitment to apply higher levels of social and environmental compliance while increasing the financial expenditure to support social investment, which totaled to EGP150 Million (2010).

Through various CSR initiatives, Vodafone Egypt contributed to development efforts in education, health, environment, emergency relief as well as philanthropic work throughout Egypt.

==Vodafone Egypt Foundation ==
Vodafone Egypt Foundation makes long term social investments and was registered in 2003 as a Corporate Donor in the Egyptian Ministry of Social Solidarity.

The Foundation is registered as a separate legal entity from Vodafone Egypt, governed by an independent Board of Trustees that includes a number of prominent figures in the area of development and social work in Egypt.

Vodafone Egypt Foundation is among 23 Vodafone Foundations around the world and is part of Vodafone's commitment to be a responsible global citizen and member of society.

The Foundation is driven by Vodafone's strategic goal of being a leading responsible business by engaging in various forms of social investment aiming at improving the livelihood for marginalized people in Egypt.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

Vodafone Egypt Foundation implements all its projects through NGOs by granting funds to implement projects in addition to in-kind and volunteering support by Vodafone Egypt employees.

In February 2011, Vodafone Egypt Foundation launched a national literacy initiative under the slogan &quot;Knowledge is Power&quot; to eradicate the illiteracy of 17 million Egyptian by 2017.

==Vodafone Egypt sponsorships ==
'''Al Ahly Sponsorship'''
Vodafone is the official partner of Egypt’s El Ahly Club, the African Club of the Century. Vodafone’s partnership with El Ahly’s football team began in 2002, and in 2005 Vodafone went beyond football and took on El Ahly teams for nine other sports Including team sports like basketball, handball, and volleyball, as well as individual games like gymnastics, tennis, table tennis, karate and swimming. Vodafone also extended the partnership by sponsoring El Ahly centennial celebration.&lt;br /&gt;

==Subsidiaries of Vodafone Egypt==
'''Vodafone International Services'''
Vodafone International Services is a subsidiary of Vodafone Egypt delivering outsourcing &amp; off-shoring solutions and services.

'''Sarmady'''
Established in 2001, Sarmady dominates the Egyptian fixed and mobile internet with a range of locally relevant content and services spanning sports, film, music, city-guides, directories, classifieds, social networks and automotive.
Sarmady invested heavily in building some destination websites and mobile internet portals in the region.
Acquired by Vodafone Egypt in 2008, Sarmady became Vodafone's digital arm.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
Vodafone Egypt website www.Vodafone.com.eg 
Google+ Page :[https://plus.google.com/u/0/105247430930290514671/posts Google+]

==External links==
* [http://www.vodafone.com.eg Vodafone Egypt]
* [http://www.vodafone.com Vodafone Group]
* [http://www.telecomegypt.com.eg Telecom Egypt]
* [http://www.sarmady.net Sarmady, a Vodafone company]

{{Egyptian mobile operators}}
{{Vodafone}}

[[Category:Vodafone]]
[[Category:Mobile phone companies of Egypt]]
[[Category:Privately held companies]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1998]]
[[Category:1998 establishments in Egypt]]

[[ar:فودافون مصر]]
[[de:Vodafone Egypt]]
[[es:Vodafone Egipto]]
[[fr:Vodafone Égypte]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
