<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="458133" ns="0" title="Thompson Twins"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist| &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name                = Thompson Twins
| image                 = Thompson Twins Feb84.JPG  
| caption            = Alannah Currie and Joe Leeway, 1984
| image_size            = 200
| background          = group_or_band
| alias               = 
| origin              = [[United Kingdom]]
| instrument          = 
| genre               = [[Pop music|Pop]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Dance music|Dance]]&lt;br/&gt;[[New wave music|New wave]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Synthpop]]
| years_active        = 1977–1993
| label               = [[Tee Records]]&lt;br&gt;[[Arista Records]]&lt;br&gt;[[Warner Bros. Records]]
| associated_acts     = [[Babble (band)|Babble]]&lt;br/&gt;[[International Observer]]
| website                 = 
| current_members     = 
| past_members        =  [[Tom Bailey (musician)|Tom Bailey]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Alannah Currie]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Joe Leeway]]&lt;br/&gt;Pete Dodd&lt;br/&gt;John Roog&lt;br/&gt;[[Matthew Seligman]]&lt;br/&gt;Chris Bell&lt;br/&gt;Jane Shorter&lt;br/&gt;[[Andrew Edge]]&lt;br/&gt;Jon Podgorski&lt;br/&gt;[[Roger O'Donnell]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Boris Williams]]
}}

The '''Thompson Twins''' were a [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Pop music|pop]] [[musical ensemble|group]] that were formed in April 1977&lt;ref name=&quot;Guinness Rockopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 1998
| title= Guinness Rockopedia
| edition= 1st
| publisher= Guinness Publishing Ltd.
| location= London
| page= 448
| isbn= 0-85112-072-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and disbanded in May 1993. They achieved considerable popularity in the mid 1980s, scoring a string of hits in the [[United Kingdom]], the [[United States]] and around the globe. The band was named after the two bumbling detectives [[Thomson and Thompson]] in [[Hergé]]'s [[comic strip]], ''[[The Adventures of Tintin (TV series)|The Adventures of Tintin]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; A predominantly [[synthpop]] [[trio (music)|trio]], they were joined on stage at [[Live Aid]] by [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] and were at the forefront of the so-called [[Second British Invasion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt;

==Career==
===Early days===
In 1977, the original Thompson Twins line-up consisted of [[Tom Bailey (musician)|Tom Bailey]] (born 18 January 1954, [[Halifax, West Yorkshire|Halifax]], [[Yorkshire]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spock.com/Tom-Bailey-(Thompson-Twins) Spock.com]&lt;/ref&gt;) on bass and vocals, Pete Dodd on guitar and vocals, John Roog on guitar, and Jon Podgorski (known as &quot;Pod&quot;) on drums.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first= |last= |url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p5644/biography|pure_url=yes}}|title=Biography by Stephen Thomas Erlewine |publisher=Allmusic.com |accessdate=27 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dodd and Roog first met when they were both 13 years old.

Arriving in [[London]] with very little money, they lived as [[Squatting|squatters]] in Lillieshall Road, London. Future Thompson Twins member [[Alannah Currie]] lived in another squat in the same street &amp;mdash; which is how she met Bailey. It was in this ramshackle and run-down house that they found an illegal way of &quot;borrowing&quot; electricity from the house next door. Bailey described themselves (laughingly) as spongers (meaning that they were on the dole—unemployed) back then, as they were living on very little and scavenging everything they could lay their hands on. He even said that the only instruments they had were bought, or had been stolen or borrowed. Dodd managed to get a [[Council house|council flat]] not far away. Their [[Road crew|roadie]] at that time was John Hade, who lived in the same house, and who later became their manager. 

As Podgorski had decided to stay in the north, the group auditioned for drummers at the Point Studio in [[Victoria, London]].  [[Andrew Edge]] joined them on drums for less than one year, and went on to join [[Savage Progress]], who later toured with the Thompson Twins as their support act on the 1984 UK tour.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birthdays&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first= |last= |url=http://nfo.net/calendar/oct27.htm |title=Diary of Notable Musical Events |publisher=info net calendar |accessdate=12 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Membership changes===
By 1981, the line-up was Bailey, Dodd, Roog and three new members: Chris Bell on drums, former band roadie [[Joe Leeway]] on congas and percussion, and Jane Shorter on saxophone. This line-up recorded the first Thompson Twins album ''[[A Product of ... (Participation)]]'', documented in the [[film]], ''Listen to London'' (1981).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.listentolondon.net Listen To London]&lt;/ref&gt; Currie, who had been associated with the band for a few years, played and sang on the first album, but was not yet a full member.  

After the first album, the band's line-up shifted yet again. Saxophonist Jane Shorter left, percussionist Currie was made an official member, and bassist [[Matthew Seligman]], a former member of [[The Soft Boys]] and [[The Fallout Club]], joined.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; Bailey moved to keyboards and guitar in addition to serving as lead vocalist, with Leeway handling vocals on a few tracks.   

The band signed to [[Arista Records]] and released the album ''[[Set (Thompson Twins album)|Set]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; [[Thomas Dolby]] played some keyboards on ''Set'' and some live gigs, as Bailey had little experience with synthesizers before then. ''Set'' contained the single &quot;In the Name of Love&quot;, sung and largely written by Bailey. It became a #1 dance club hit in the US,&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p5644/charts-awards/billboard-singles|pure_url=yes}}|title=Allmusic ((( Thompson Twins &gt; Charts &amp; Awards &gt; Billboard Singles )))}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an album entitled ''In the Name of Love'' (consisting mainly of tracks from ''Set'', with two others from ''A Product Of... (Participation)'') was released in the US to capitalize on the song's popularity. It entered the US [[Billboard 200]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Albums&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p5644/charts-awards/billboard-albums|pure_url=yes}}|title=Allmusic ((( Thompson Twins &gt; Charts &amp; Awards &gt; Billboard Albums )))}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reduction to a trio===
After the success of &quot;In the Name of Love&quot;, Bailey, Currie and Leeway, wanting to pursue the single's different sound, toyed with the idea of starting a new band on the side, which they planned to call 'The Bermuda Triangle'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost&quot;&gt;[http://www.lostidols.com/files/t/twins.html Now and Then] lostidols.com - Retrieved 8 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  When &quot;In The Name Of Love&quot; (and the parent album ''Set'') failed to make a substantial impact in the UK [[record chart|charts]], this plan was abandoned.  However, at the same time, manager Hade convinced Bailey, Leeway and Currie to downsize the Thompson Twins to a core of the three in April 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost&quot;/&gt; Accordingly, the other four members of the band were notified that they were being let go; they were each paid £500 and were allowed to keep their instruments and equipment.  

All the former members are still on friendly speaking terms with each other, and with Bailey, Currie and Leeway — although Dodd once had the job of delivering a [[keyboard instrument|keyboard]] to Thompson Twins session keyboard player Thomas Dolby some time later, but (to Dodd's irritation) Dolby failed to recognise him. 

The Thompson Twins decided to go abroad to free themselves of any UK influence, as well as to combine the songwriting for their first album as a trio with a long holiday. They first went to [[Egypt]] and then to the [[Bahamas]] where they recorded at the [[Compass Point Studios]] in [[Nassau, Bahamas|Nassau]] with the [[record producer|producer]], [[Alex Sadkin]].

===International success===
The band broke into the [[UK Singles Chart]] and the US [[Billboard Hot 100]] chart at the beginning of 1983 with &quot;[[Lies (Thompson Twins song)|Lies]]&quot; and &quot;Love On Your Side&quot;, which became the band's first UK Top 10 single.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited 
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 557}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; They then released their third album, ''[[Quick Step and Side Kick]]'' (called simply ''Side Kicks'' in the US&lt;ref name=&quot;Albums&quot;/&gt;), which peaked at number 2 in the UK and was later certified platinum there. Further singles followed with &quot;We Are Detective&quot; (another Top 10 UK hit) and &quot;Watching&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; All three received songwriting credits, though the band publicly acknowledged Bailey as the songwriter, with Currie contributing [[lyrics]] and Leeway focusing on the stage show.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheAge&quot;/&gt; During 1983, the band had the opening spot on [[The Police]] concert tour in the US.

A new single, &quot;[[Hold Me Now (Thompson Twins song)|Hold Me Now]]&quot;, was released towards the end of 1983. The song was an international chart success, peaking at #4 in their native UK where it became the band's biggest seller earning a [[Music recording sales certification|gold disc]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bpi.co.uk/platinum/platinumright.asp?rq=search_plat&amp;r_id=20357 BPI Gold award certification for &quot;Hold Me Now&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and reached #3 in the US in the spring of 1984 becoming their biggest American hit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; The band's new album, ''[[Into the Gap]]'', was released in early 1984 and became one of the year's biggest sellers, selling five million copies worldwide. It topped the [[UK Albums Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; and was later certified double platinum there. Further hit singles from the album followed with &quot;Doctor! Doctor!&quot; (UK #3) and &quot;You Take Me Up&quot; (UK #2, their highest UK singles chart placing&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; and which earned a [[Music recording sales certification|silver disc]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bpi.co.uk/platinum/platinumright.asp?rq=search_plat&amp;r_id=20359 BPI Silver award certification for &quot;You Take Me Up&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Other singles included a new version of the album track &quot;Sister of Mercy&quot; (UK #11), and &quot;The Gap&quot; (though this was not released in the UK). The band embarked on a world tour in support of the album, which had also made the US top ten.

A new single, &quot;Lay Your Hands On Me&quot;, was released in the UK in late 1984 and reached #13 in the UK charts.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; However, while working on the follow-up album to ''Into The Gap'', Bailey suffered a nervous breakdown. The band's planned next single, &quot;Roll Over&quot;, was then cancelled at the last minute. The band had already parted company with their producer [[Alex Sadkin]], and [[Nile Rodgers]] was subsequently called in to help finish the album. Released in September 1985, ''[[Here's To Future Days]]'' reached the Top 5 in the UK and the Top 20 in the US&lt;ref name=&quot;Albums&quot;/&gt;), though failed to come close to the success of ''Into The Gap''. It spawned the single &quot;King For A Day&quot;, which peaked at #22 in the UK,&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; but reached #8 on the US chart&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; Other singles included a new US version of &quot;Lay Your Hands On Me&quot; (US #6),&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; the anti-drug song &quot;Don't Mess With Doctor Dream&quot; (UK #15&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt;) and an unsuccessful [[cover version|cover]] of [[The Beatles]]' 1968 hit &quot;[[Revolution (song)|Revolution]]&quot; which became the band's first single to fail to make the UK Top 40 in three years. 

Prior to the album's release, the Thompson Twins made headlines when they performed on the American leg of [[Live Aid]] in July 1985 and were joined onstage by [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]].&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; The planned 1985 tour of the UK had to be cancelled due to Bailey's breakdown (fans with tickets received a free live album as compensation), though international dates were re-scheduled and the latter half of 1985 saw sell out tours for the band in the US and [[Japan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NME Rock 'N' Roll Years&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= John
| last= Tobler
| year= 1992
| title= NME Rock 'N' Roll Years
| edition= 1st
| publisher= Reed International Books Ltd 
| location= London
| page= 408
| id= CN 5585}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final years===
Leeway left the band in 1986, and the remaining duo of Bailey and Currie carried on making music for another seven years.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; 1987 saw the release of ''[[Close to the Bone (Thompson Twins album)|Close to the Bone]]'' and the single &quot;Get That Love&quot;, which climbed to #31 in the US&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; but failed in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; &quot;In the Name of Love&quot; was given a new lease on life in 1988, after a remix by [[Shep Pettibone]] made the Top 50 in the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; 1989 saw the release of another album, ''[[Big Trash]]'', and a new [[recording contract]] with [[Warner Bros. Records]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; The single &quot;[[Sugar Daddy (Thompson Twins song)|Sugar Daddy]]&quot; peaked at #28 in the US&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; and would be their last brush with mainstream chart success.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; 1991's ''[[Queer (Thompson Twins album)|Queer]]'' would be the band's swansong, and was supported by various [[techno]] inspired singles under the moniker of [http://www.discogs.com/artist/Feedback+Max Feedback Max] (in the UK) to disguise the identity of the band to [[nightclub|club]] [[Disc jockey|DJs]]. The single &quot;[[Come Inside (Thompson Twins song)|Come Inside]]&quot; reached #7 in the US [[Hot Dance Club Songs|Dance Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Singles&quot;/&gt; and #1 in the [[UK Dance Chart]]. However, once it was discovered that the Thompson Twins were behind the record, sales dropped and the album never had a UK release {{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}. 

Prior to this, Bailey and Currie (who were now a couple) had their first child together in 1988,&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; and in the following years they spent a lot of time writing material for other artists including the hit single &quot;I Want That Man&quot; for [[Debbie Harry]] in 1989. In 1990, Bailey and Currie contributed the song &quot;[[Who Wants to Be a Millionaire? (song)|Who Wants To Be A Millionaire?]]&quot; to the [[Cole Porter]] tribute album ''&quot;[[Red Hot + Blue]]&quot;'' produced by the [[Red Hot Organization]].  In 1991, Bailey and Currie were married in [[Las Vegas, Nevada|Las Vegas]] and the following year moved to [[New Zealand]] with their two children. In 1992, the Thompson Twins contributed the song &quot;Play With Me&quot; to the [[Songs from the Cool World|soundtrack]] of the [[Ralph Bakshi]] film ''[[Cool World]]''; Bailey alone contributed a second track, &quot;Industry and Seduction&quot;. The following year, the duo formally teamed up with engineer Keith Fernley &amp; changed their band name to Babble.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; 

The Thompson Twins declined to follow the examples of many of their contemporaries and reform to tie-in with a nostalgic rebirth of the 1980s, although Bailey, Currie and Leeway appeared together on the UK [[Channel 4]] show ''Top Ten Electro Bands'' in 2001. The Thompson Twins were placed ninth.

==Critical response==
The British [[music journalism|musical press]] regularly criticised the Thompson Twins. The ''[[NME]]'' called them, &quot;1984's most instantly kitsch mass program of monosodium glutamation of the brain&quot;. ''[[City Limits (magazine)|City Limits]]'' said they were &quot;candy-floss art capitalists&quot;, whilst ''[[The Guardian]]'' dubbed them &quot;The three haircuts&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheAge&quot;/&gt;

==After the Twins==
Babble released two albums—''[[The Stone (album)|The Stone]]'' (1993)&lt;ref name=&quot;AMG&quot;/&gt; and ''[[Ether (Babble album)|Ether]]'' (1996)—with songs featured in the films ''[[Coneheads (film)|Coneheads]]'' and ''[[With Honors (film)|With Honors]]''. Three quarters of a third album was recorded, but it remains unreleased.

In 1999, Bailey produced and played keyboards on the hit album ''[[Mix (Stellar* album)|Mix]]'' by the New Zealand band [[Stellar*]], and won the 'producer of the year' award at the New Zealand equivalent of the [[Grammy Award]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thebubbleburst.co.uk/bb.php?entry=Thompson+Twins Thebubbleburst.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; He has also arranged soundtracks and has provided instrumental music for several films. In the mid 1990s, Currie gave up the music business to set up her own glass-casting studio in [[Auckland]]. 

After her sister died of [[Creutzfeldt–Jakob disease]], Currie founded a group in New Zealand called Mothers Against Genetic-Engineering in Food and the Environment (also known as MADGE), which soon had thousands of members.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheAge&quot;/&gt; Currie described this group as a &quot;rapidly growing network of politically non-aligned women who are actively resisting the use of genetically-engineered material in our food and on our land&quot;. An advert for this group featuring a young woman with four [[breast]]s  hooked up to a [[milking machine]] became famous after appearing on [[billboard]]s across New Zealand.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheAge&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2004/01/10/1073437513674.html|title=Hear Me Now by Gilbert Wong |publisher=Theage.com.au |accessdate=27 October 2009 |location=Melbourne |date=11 January 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Bailey and Currie split up in 2003, and are now divorced. They both left New Zealand to live separately in Britain, but are still close friends. In 2011, Currie married [[Jimmy Cauty]] (formerly of [[The KLF]]) and currently is a trained [[upholstery|upholsterer]] known professionally as &quot;Miss Pokeno&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2008/apr/26/homes|title=To Die For - She was the crazy-haired singer in 80s synth-pop band the Thompson Twins. Now Alannah Currie is back, in a new incarnation as artist-upholsterer|publisher=Guardian.co.uk |accessdate=27 October 2009 | location=London | date=26 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The earlier members went on to do other things: 
*Dodd and Roog formed a band called Big View (with Edge on drums) and recorded a single called, &quot;August Grass&quot;, which was released on Point Records (owned by Merton, the Thompson Twins publisher) in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;BigViewAugustGrass&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first= |last= |url=http://www.discogs.com/release/1331606 |title=BigViewAugustGrass |publisher=Discogs |accessdate=11 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dodd is now living back in [[Chesterfield]] working as a freelance journalist &amp;mdash; and has released his own ''History of Rock'' album billed as Peter &amp; the Wolves. Dodd still sees Podgorski on a regular basis.
*Roog lives in London and is in a senior position in [[Tower Hamlets]] Adult Services.
*Seligman worked for a law firm in London, and has played in [[The Soft Boys]] reunions as well as releasing his own albums,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bassplayer.com/article/soft-return/Feb-03/582 Bassplayer.com - accessed October 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;   but has moved to [[Japan]] with his Japanese wife and their daughter.  In 2009, he has been contributing to the new Thomas Dolby album.
*Bell moved from London to [[Bath, Somerset|Bath]], and played in or for [[Spear of Destiny (band)]], [[Gene Loves Jezebel]] and [[Hugh Cornwell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first= |last= |url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p20664|pure_url=yes}}|title=Biography by Dave Thompson|publisher=Allmusic.com |accessdate=27 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He also works as a [[Landscape architecture|landscape gardener]].
*Booth is, reportedly, living in [[Shanghai]] and is the general manager of a music [[publishing]] company.
*Podgorski still lives in Chesterfield.
*Edge has a singing career with [[Drumsing]], as well as being an English Conversation teacher in Linz, Austria.

Bailey continues to make music under the moniker [[International Observer]]. His albums ''[[Seen (album)|Seen]]'', and ''[[All Played Out]]'' both received positive reviews.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}} The most recent outing was ''Felt'', released on 8 September 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r1643293|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic.com - accessed October 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;  He also performs with the [http://www.holiwater.com/ Holiwater] group from [[India]]. Remarried (to artist Lauren Drescher), he currently resides in London.

==Discography==
{{Main|Thompson Twins discography}}

===Thompson Twins albums===
====Original studio albums====
*''[[A Product of ... (Participation)]]'' (1981)
*''[[Set (Thompson Twins album)|Set]]'' (1982)
*''[[Quick Step and Side Kick]]'' (1983) (a.k.a. ''Side Kicks'' in North America/Japan)
*''[[Into the Gap]]'' (1984)
*''[[Here's to Future Days]]'' (1985)
*''[[Close to the Bone (Thompson Twins album)|Close to the Bone]]'' (1987)
*''[[Big Trash]]'' (1989)
*''[[Queer (Thompson Twins album)|Queer]]'' (1991)

====Compilation albums====
*''[[In the Name of Love (Thompson Twins album)|In the Name of Love]]'' (U.S. only release compiling tracks from the first two albums) (1982)
*''[[The Best of Thompson Twins: Greatest Mixes]]'' (1988)
*''[[Greatest Hits (Thompson Twins album)|Thompson Twins - Greatest Hits]]'' (1990)
*''Hold Me Now (Thompson Twins album)'' (1993)
*''[[Love on Your Side - The Best of Thompson Twins]]'' (2007)

===Babble albums===
*''[[The Stone (album)|The Stone]]'' (1993)
*''[[Ether (Babble album)|Ether]]'' (1996)
&lt;ref name=&quot;Babble&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first= |last= |url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p37187|pure_url=yes}}|title=Biography by William Ruhlmann |publisher=Allmusic.com |accessdate=27 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
*''The Thompson Twins - An Odd Couple (The Official Biography)'' by Rose Rouse. [[Virgin Books]], 1985.
*''Thompson Twin - An '80's Memoir'' by [[Michael White (author)|Michael White]]. Publisher: Little, Brown (4 May 2000).

==See also==
*[[List of number-one dance hits (United States)]]
*[[List of artists who reached number one on the U.S. Dance chart]]
*[[List of Second British Invasion Artists]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p5644|pure_url=yes}} Biography at Allmusic.com]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Thompson Twins}}
[[Category:British New Wave musical groups]]
[[Category:Music from Sheffield]]
[[Category:Arista Records artists]]
[[Category:Warner Bros. Records artists]]
[[Category:English pop music groups]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1977]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 1993]]

[[de:Thompson Twins]]
[[es:Thompson Twins]]
[[fr:Thompson Twins]]
[[it:Thompson Twins]]
[[nl:Thompson Twins]]
[[ja:トンプソン・ツインズ]]
[[no:Thompson Twins]]
[[pl:Thompson Twins]]
[[pt:Thompson Twins]]
[[sv:Thompson Twins]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
