<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="45812" ns="0" title="Pim Fortuyn"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name        = Pim Fortuyn
| residence   = 
| other_names = 
| image       = Pim Fortuyn - May 4.jpg
| image_size  = 220px
| caption     = Pim Fortuyn, 4 May 2002, two days before his assassination
| birth_name  = Wilhelmus Simon Petrus Fortuijn
| birth_date  = {{Birth date|1948|02|19|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Driehuis]], Netherlands
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|2002|05|06|1948|02|19|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[Hilversum]], Netherlands
| death_cause = [[Assassination|Assassinated]]
| known       = [[Assassination of Pim Fortuyn|Assassination]] during [[Dutch general election, 2002|Dutch Election of 2002]]
| occupation  = [[Politician]], [[Civil service|civil servant]], [[Sociology|sociologist]], [[author]], [[columnist]], [[professor]]
| alma_mater  = [[Vrije Universiteit]]&lt;br&gt;[[University of Groningen]]
| title       = [[Doctor of Philosophy]]
| salary      = 
| term        = 
| predecessor = 
| successor   = 
| party       = &lt;small&gt;[[Labour Party (Netherlands)|Labour Party]] (1974-1989)&lt;br&gt;[[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy]] (mid 90's)&lt;br&gt;[[Livable Netherlands]] (2001-2002)&lt;br&gt;[[Pim Fortuyn List]] (2002)&lt;/small&gt;
| boards      = 
| religion    = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]
| spouse      = 
| partner     = 
| children    = 
| relations   = 
| website     = 
| footnotes   = 
| employer    = 
| height      = 
| weight      = 
}}
'''Wilhelmus Simon Petrus Fortuijn''', known as '''Pim Fortuyn''' ({{IPA-nl|ˈpɪm fɔrˈtœyn}}; February 19, 1948 – May 6, 2002) was a  [[Dutch people|Dutch]] politician, civil servant, sociologist, author and professor who formed his own party, ''[[Pim Fortuyn List]]'' (Lijst Pim Fortuyn or LPF).&lt;ref name=&quot;Margry&quot;&gt;Margry, Peter Jan: ''The Murder of Pim Fortuyn and Collective Emotions. Hype, Hysteria, and Holiness in the Netherlands?'' published in the Dutch magazine ''Etnofoor: Antropologisch tijdschrift'' nr. 16 pages 106-131, 2003,[http://www.meertens.knaw.nl/meertensnet/file/edwinb/20050420/PF_webp_Engels_lang.pdf English version available online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Fortuyn provoked controversy with his stated views about immigrants and [[Islam]]. He called Islam &quot;a backward culture&quot;, and said that if it were legally possible he would close the borders for Muslim immigrants.&lt;ref name=&quot;controversy&quot;&gt;{{nl icon}} [http://web.archive.org/web/20020212063049/http%3a//www.volkskrant.nl/nieuws/denhaag/1013147690985.html ''Volkskrant'' newspaper interview (summary)]&lt;/ref&gt; He was labelled a [[Far right|far-right]] [[populism|populist]] by his opponents and in the media, but he fiercely rejected this label&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/1966979.stm Cf. this BBC interview] . Retrieved July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and explicitly distanced himself from &quot;far-right&quot; politicians such as the Belgian [[Filip Dewinter]], the Austrian [[Jörg Haider]], or Frenchman [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] whenever compared to them. While Fortuyn compared his own politics to centre-right politicians such as [[Silvio Berlusconi]] of Italy, he also admired former Dutch [[Prime Minister]] [[Joop den Uyl]], a [[socialist]]. Fortuyn however repeatedly described himself and [[Pim Fortuyn List|LPF]]'s ideology as [[pragmatism]] and not [[populism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ODW8uQTbhGw|title=Interview with Belgium news agency}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fortuyn was [[Coming out|openly homosexual]].

Fortuyn was [[Assassination of Pim Fortuyn|assassinated]] during the [[Dutch general election, 2002|2002 Dutch national election campaign]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Simons |first=Marlise |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/07/international/europe/07DUTC.html |title=Rightist in Netherlands Is Slain, and the Nation Is Stunned |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2002-05-07 |accessdate=2010-06-13}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=James |first=Barry |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/07/news/07iht-dutch_ed3_.html |title=Assailant shoots gay who railed against Muslim immigrants: Rightist in Dutch election is murdered |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2002-05-07 |accessdate=2010-06-13}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Simons |first=Marlise |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/08/world/elections-to-proceed-in-the-netherlands-despite-killing.html |title=Elections to Proceed in the Netherlands, Despite Killing |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2002-05-08 |accessdate=2010-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Volkert van der Graaf]].  In court at his trial, van der Graaf said he murdered Fortuyn to stop him from exploiting Muslims as &quot;scapegoats&quot; and targeting &quot;the weak members of society&quot; in seeking political power.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/netherlands/1425944/Fortuyn-killed-to-protect-Muslims.html Fortuyn killed 'to protect Muslims'], [[The Daily Telegraph]], 28 March 2003:
:[van der Graaf] said his goal was to stop Mr Fortuyn exploiting Muslims as &quot;scapegoats&quot; and targeting &quot;the weak parts of society to score points&quot; to try to gain political power.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn&quot;&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/europe/03/27/netherlands.fortuyn.trial/ Fortuyn killer 'acted for Muslims'], [[CNN]], 27 March 2003:
:Van der Graaf, 33, said during his first court appearance in Amsterdam on Thursday that Fortuyn was using &quot;the weakest parts of society to score points&quot; and gain political power.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;newcriminologist&quot;&gt;[http://www.newcriminologist.com/article.asp?nid=870 Jihad Vegan], Dr Janet Parker 20 June 2005, New Criminologist&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early life and education===
Fortuyn was born on 19 February 1948 in [[Driehuis]], as the third child to a [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] family. In 1967 he began to study [[sociology]] at the [[University of Amsterdam]] but transferred after a few months to the [[Vrije Universiteit]] in [[Amsterdam]]. In 1971 he ended his study with the [[Academic degree]] [[Doctorandus]]. In 1981 he received a [[doctorate]] in [[sociology]] at the [[University of Groningen]] as a [[Doctor of Philosophy]].

==Career==
Fortuyn worked as a lecturer at the ''[[Nyenrode Business Universiteit]]'' and as an associate professor at the [[University of Groningen]], where he taught [[Marxist]] [[sociology]]. He was a confessed Marxist at the time.  Later, he joined the [[Dutch Labour Party]].

In 1989 Fortuyn became director of a [[Politics of the Netherlands|government]] organisation administering student transport cards. In 1990 he moved to [[Rotterdam]].  From 1991 to 1995, he was an extraordinary professor at the [[Erasmus University Rotterdam]], appointed to the Albeda-chair in &quot;employment conditions in public service&quot;. 

When his contract ended, he made a career of public speaking and writing books and press columns, gradually becoming involved in [[politics]].  Fortuyn was openly [[gay]], and said in a 2002 interview that he was [[Catholic Church|Catholic]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.katholieknieuwsblad.nl/actueel19/kn1920a.htm Mark Eyck, &quot;Interview: Pim Fortuyn&quot;], ''[[Katholiek Nieuwsblad]]'' (Catholic Newspaper), 15 Februari 2002 &lt;br&gt;&quot; Question: U beschouwt zichzelf nog wel als katholiek? Answer: Ja, daar ontkom je niet aan. [..] Question: Toch noemt u zich ondanks uw homoseksualiteit nog steeds katholiek. Answer: Ik bén katholiek! Ik ben nota bene gedoopt! Ik noem me niet zo, ik ben het!&quot; (''Question: Do you still consider yourself a Catholic?  Answer: Yes, you can't escape from that.  [..] Question: But in spite of your homosexuality you still call yourself a Catholic.  Answer: I ''am'' a Catholic.  I have, after all, been baptised!  I don't call myself one, I am one!'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political career===
[[Image:Pim Fortuyn.png|thumb|left|Pim Fortuyn in 1991]]

In 1992 Fortuyn wrote &quot;Aan het volk van Nederland&quot; (To the people of the Netherlands), declaring he was the successor to the charismatic but controversial 18th-century Dutch politician [[Joan van der Capellen tot den Pol]].  A one-time [[Communist Party of the Netherlands|communist]] and former member of the [[social-democratic]] [[Dutch Labour Party]], Fortuyn was elected &quot;[[lijsttrekker]]&quot; of the newly formed [[Livable Netherlands]] party by a large majority on 26 November 2001, prior to the [[Dutch general election, 2002|Dutch general election of 2002]].

On 9 February 2002, he was interviewed by the ''[[Volkskrant]]'', a Dutch newspaper (see below). His statements were considered so controversial that the party dismissed him as ''lijsttrekker'' the next day. Fortuyn had said that he favoured putting an end to [[Muslim]] [[immigration]], if possible. Having been rejected by Livable Netherlands, Fortuyn founded his own party '''LPF''' ([[Pim Fortuyn List]]) on 11 February 2002. Many Livable Netherlands supporters transferred their support to the new party.

As lijsttrekker for the [[Livable Rotterdam]] party, a local issues party, he achieved a major victory in the [[Rotterdam]] district council elections in early March 2002. The new party won about 36% of the seats, making it the largest party in the council. For the first time since the [[Second World War]], the [[Dutch Labour Party]] was out of power in [[Rotterdam]].

Fortuyn's victory made him the subject of hundreds of [[interviews]] during the next three months, and he made many [[News release|statements]] about his [[political ideology]]. In March he released his book ''The Mess of Eight Purple Years'' (''Puinhopen Van Acht Jaar Paars''), which he used as his [[political agenda]] for the upcoming [[Dutch general election, 2002|general election]].

===Assassination===
[[Image:Palazzo di Pietro Rotterdam.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Fortuyn's house in [[Rotterdam]] where he lived from 1998 until his death]]
{{main|Assassination of Pim Fortuyn}}

On 6 May 2002, at age 54, Fortuyn was [[Assassination of Pim Fortuyn|assassinated]] in [[Hilversum]], [[North Holland]], by [[Volkert van der Graaf]]. The attack took place in a parking lot outside a radio studio where Fortuyn had just given an interview. This was nine days before the [[Dutch general election, 2002|general election]], for which he was running. The attacker was pursued by Hans Smolders, Fortuyn's driver, and was arrested by the police shortly afterward, still in possession of a [[handgun|gun]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/dutch-farright-leader-shot-dead-650464.html |title=Dutch far-right leader shot dead |publisher=Independent.co.uk |date=2002-05-07 |accessdate=2010-06-13 | location=London | first=Isobel | last=Conway}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Months later, van der Graaf confessed in court to the Netherlands' first modern-age political assassination (excluding WW II events). He was sentenced to 18 years in prison.

The [[Assassination of Pim Fortuyn|assassination]] shocked many residents of the Netherlands and highlighted the cultural clashes within the country. Politicians from all parties suspended campaigning. After consultation with LPF, the government decided not to postpone the elections. As Dutch law did not permit modifying the ballots, Fortuyn became a posthumous candidate. The [[Pim Fortuyn List|LPF]] made an unprecedented debut in the [[House of Representatives of the Netherlands|House of Representatives]] by winning 26 seats (17% of the 150 seats in the house). By the following year, the party had lost support, winning only eight seats.  It won no seats in the [[Dutch general election, 2006|2006 elections]], and consequently the party had no seats left in the [[States-General of the Netherlands|parliament]].

During the last months of his life, Fortuyn had become closer to the [[Catholic Church]]. To the surprise of many commentators and Dutch TV hosts, Fortuyn insisted on Fr. Louis Berger, a [[curate|parish priest]] from [[The Hague]], accompanying him in some of his last TV appearances. According to the ''[[New York Times]]'', Berger had become his &quot;friend and [[sacrament of penance|confessor]]&quot; during the last weeks of his life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4DD1430F934A35756C0A9649C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all &quot;Rightist politician is slain and the Nation is stunned&quot;], ''New York Times,'' Archive, 7 May 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;

Fortuyn was initially buried in [[Driehuis]] in the Netherlands. He was re-interred on 20 July 2002, at [[San Giorgio della Richinvelda]], in the [[province of Pordenone]] in Italy, where he had owned a house.

==Views on Islam and immigration==
In August 2001, Fortuyn was quoted in the ''Rotterdams Dagblad'' newspaper saying, &quot;I am also in favour of a [[cold war]] with Islam. I see Islam as an extraordinary threat, as a hostile religion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}} Original quote in {{lang-nl|Ik ben ook voor een koude oorlog met de islam. De islam zie ik als een buitengewone bedreiging, als een ons vijandige samenleving.}} (''&quot;I also favor a cold war against Islam. I see Islam as being an exceptional threat, as a society hostile to ours&quot;.'')&lt;/ref&gt;  In the TV program, ''Business class'', Fortuyn said that Muslims in The Netherlands did not accept Dutch society.  He appeared on the program several times.  It was moderated by his friend Harry Mens.  Since his death, commentators have suggested Fortuyn's words were interpreted rather harshly, if not wrongly. For instance, he said that Muslims in the Netherlands needed to accept living ''together'' with the Dutch, and that if this was unacceptable for them, then they were free to leave. His concluding words in the TV program were &quot;...I want to live together with the Muslim people, but [[wikt:it takes two to tango|it takes two to tango]].&quot;

[[Image:Rotterdam kunstwerk beeld Pim Fortuyn.jpg|thumb|left|220px|After his death a statue was placed at his home in [[Rotterdam]]]]

On 9 February 2002, additional statements made by him were carried in the ''[[Volkskrant]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;controversy&quot; /&gt; He said that the Netherlands, with a population of 16 million, had enough inhabitants, and the practice of allowing as many as 40,000 asylum-seekers into the country each year had to be stopped. (This figure was higher than the actual numbers, and immigrants were decreasing at the time.).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbs.nl/en-GB/menu/themas/bevolking/publicaties/artikelen/archief/2002/2002-1019-wm.htm Asylum Immigration Statistics] and [http://statline.cbs.nl/StatWeb/table.asp?LYR=G1:0&amp;LA=en&amp;DM=SLEN&amp;PA=03740eng&amp;D1=a&amp;D2=a,!1-39&amp;D3=4,9,14,19,24,29,(l-8)-l&amp;STB=G2&amp;HDR=T Asylum Requests Statistics], Netherlands Bureau of Statistics&lt;/ref&gt; He claimed that if he became part of the next government, he would pursue a restrictive immigration policy while also granting citizenship to a large group of illegal immigrants.

He said that he did not intend to &quot;unload our Moroccan hooligans&quot; onto the Moroccan [[Hassan II of Morocco|King Hassan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}}[http://www.volkskrant.nl/den_haag/article153195.ece/De_islam_is_een_achterlijke_cultuur Volkskrant interview, 2 February 2002, full text]. Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Hassan had died three years earlier.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hassan II of Morocco]]&lt;/ref&gt; He considered Article 7 of the constitution, which asserts [[freedom of speech]], of more importance than Article 1, which forbids [[discrimination]] on the basis of religion, life principles, political inclination, race, or sexual preference. Fortuyn distanced himself from [[Hans Janmaat]] of the [[Centre Democrats (Netherlands)|Centrum Democraten]], who in the 1980s wanted to remove all foreigners from the country and was repeatedly convicted for discrimination and [[hate speech]].

Fortuyn proposed that all people who already resided in the Netherlands would be able to stay, but he emphasized the need of the immigrants to adopt Dutch society's consensus on human rights as their own. He said &quot;If it were legally possible, I'd say no more Muslims will get in here&quot;, claiming that the influx of Muslims would threaten freedoms in the liberal Dutch society. He thought Muslim culture had never undergone a process of [[modernisation]] and therefore still lacked acceptance of democracy and women's, gays', lesbians' and minorities' rights. He feared Muslims would try to replace the Dutch legal system with the [[Sharia|shari'a law]].

He said he was concerned about intolerance in the Muslim community. In a televised debate in 2002, &quot;Fortuyn baited the Muslim cleric by flaunting his homosexuality. Finally the ''[[imam]]'' exploded, denouncing Fortuyn in strongly [[homophobia|anti-homosexual]] terms. Fortuyn calmly turned to the camera and, addressing viewers directly, told them that this is the kind of [[Trojan horse]] of intolerance the Dutch are inviting into their society in the name of [[multiculturalism]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted from &quot;Murder in Holland&quot;, [[Rod Dreher]], ''National Review,'' 7 May 2002 [http://www.nationalreview.com/dreher/dreher050702.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;

When asked by the Dutch newspaper ''[[Volkskrant]]'' whether he hated Islam, he replied:

{{cquote|I don't hate Islam. I consider it a backward culture. I have travelled much in the world. And wherever Islam rules, it's just terrible. All the hypocrisy. It's a bit like those old [[Dutch Reformed Church|reformed protestants]]. The Reformed lie all the time. And why is that? Because they have standards and values that are so high that you can't humanly maintain them. You also see that in that Muslim culture. Then look at the Netherlands. In what country could an electoral leader of such a large movement as mine be openly homosexual? How wonderful that that's possible. That's something that one can be proud of. And I'd like to keep it that way, thank you very much.&lt;ref&gt;Original quote in Dutch: &quot;Ik haat de islam niet. Ik vind het een achterlijke cultuur. Ik heb veel gereisd in de wereld. En overal waar de islam de baas is, is het gewoon verschrikkelijk. Al die dubbelzinnigheid. Het heeft wel iets weg van die oude gereformeerden. Gereformeerden liegen altijd. En hoe komt dat? Omdat ze een normen- en waardenstelsel hebben dat zo hoog ligt dat je dat menselijkerwijs niet kunt handhaven. Dat zie je in die moslimcultuur ook. Kijk dan naar Nederland. In welk land zou een lijsttrekker van een zo grote beweging als de mijne, openlijk homoseksueel kunnen zijn? Wat fantastisch dat dat kan. Daar mag je trots op zijn. En dat wil ik graag effe zo houden&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Fortuyn used the word ''achterlijk'', literally meaning &quot;backward&quot;, but commonly used as an insult in the sense of &quot;retarded&quot;.  After his use of &quot;achterlijk&quot; caused an uproar, Fortuyn said he had used the word with its literal meaning of &quot;backward&quot;.

Fortuyn wrote  ''Against the Islamization of Our Culture'' (1997) (in [[Dutch language|Dutch]]).&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.amazon.com/dp/9022983382 Tegen de islamisering van onze cultuur: Nederlandse identiteit als fundament]'', A.W. Bruna, 1997, ISBN 90-229-8338-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other views==
He held liberal views favouring the [[drug policy of the Netherlands]], [[Same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|same-sex marriage]], [[Euthanasia in the Netherlands|euthanasia]], and related positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/fortuyn_p,2.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Fortuyn, Pim |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2010-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
[[File:RotterdamGWBurgerPlein060502.png|thumb|Anti-Fortuyn poster of the [[International Socialists (Netherlands)|International Socialists]] with the slogan &quot;Stop de Hollandse Haider&quot; (English: &quot;Stop the Dutch Haider&quot;) near Fortuyn's house in Rotterdam on 6 May 2002]]

Fortuyn was compared with the politicians Jörg Haider and Jean-Marie Le Pen in the foreign press. These comparisons were often referred to by Dutch reporters and politicians. An explicit comparison with Le Pen was made by [[Ad Melkert]], then ''[[lijsttrekker]]'' of the Dutch Labour Party, who said in [[Emmen, Netherlands|Emmen]] on 24 April 2002: 

{{cquote|&quot;If you flirt with Fortuyn, then in the Netherlands the same thing will happen as happened in [[France]]. There they woke up with Le Pen, soon we will wake up with Fortuyn.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{nl}}: &quot;Als je flirt met Fortuyn, dan gebeurt er in Nederland straks hetzelfde als in Frankrijk. Daar zijn ze wakker geworden met Le Pen, straks worden wij wakker met Fortuyn.&quot; quote from article in [[Het Financieele Dagblad]], 25 April 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 5 May, the day before the assassination, Fortuyn debated with Melkert in a debate organized by the [[Algemeen Dagblad]] newspaper about [[demonization]] of himself. In it he said that he often had to tell journalists that the image created of him in the media was incorrect.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl}} [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kCupE2LlFoo&amp;feature=related &quot;Het laatste debat&quot;] Nova, 18 juni 2002&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Columnist [[Jan Blokker]] wrote: 

{{cquote|&quot;After reading (...) I realized once again that Professor Pim may really be called the Jean-Marie Le Pen, the Filip Dewinter, the Jörg Haider and the new Hans Janmaat of the Netherlands.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{nl}}: Na lezing (...) was ik er eens te meer van overtuigd dat Professor Pim wel degelijk de Jean-Marie Le Pen, de Filip Dewinter], de Jörg Haider en de nieuwe Hans Janmaat van Nederland mag heten.&quot;, de Volkskrant, 25 March 2002&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Legacy==
[[Image:Beeld Pim Fortuyn Rotterdam.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Pim Fortuyn monument in [[Rotterdam]]]]

Fortuyn changed the Dutch political landscape and political culture.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1974184.stm BBC impression] for an early evaluation. Retrieved July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The 2002 elections, only weeks after Fortuyn's death, were marked by large losses for the [[liberalism|liberal]] [[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy|VVD]] and especially the [[social democracy|social democratic]] [[Dutch Labour Party|PvdA]] (whose parliamentary group was halved in size); both parties replaced their leaders shortly after their losses. The election winners were the [[Pim Fortuyn List]], and the [[Christian democracy|Christian democratic]] [[Christian Democratic Appeal|CDA]]. Some commentators think that Fortuyn's perceived martyrdom created greater support for the LPF, which seems likely given its quick later decline.

The Netherlands has made its asylum policy more strict.  Some have objected to what they think is a harsher political and social climate, especially towards immigrants and Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/2680881.stm &quot;Fortuyn ghost stalks Dutch politics&quot;], (BBC News)&lt;/ref&gt;

Contemporary Dutch politics is more polarized than it has been in recent years, especially on the issues for which Fortuyn was best known. People debate the success of their [[multiculturalism|multicultural society]], and whether they need to better [[Assimilation (sociology)|assimilate]] newcomers. The government's decision to expel numerous asylum seekers whose applications had failed was controversial.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3494627.stm Dutch MPs approve asylum exodus] (BBC News)&lt;/ref&gt; Fortuyn had advocated an amnesty for asylum seekers' already residing in the Netherlands.

The [[coalition government|coalition]] cabinet of [[Christian Democratic Appeal|CDA]], [[Pim Fortuyn List|LPF]] and [[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy|VVD]] fell within three months, due to infighting within the LPF. In the following elections, the LPF was left with only 8 seats in parliament (out of 150) and was not included in the new government.  Political commentators speculated that discontented voters might vote for a non-traditional party, if a viable alternative was at hand. In recent times the right-wing [[Party for Freedom]], which has a strong stance on immigration and integration, won 9 (out of 150) seats in the 2006 elections and 24 in 2010.

In 2004, in a TV show, Fortuyn was chosen as [[De Grootste Nederlander]] (&quot;Greatest Dutchman of all-time&quot;), followed closely by [[William I of Orange|William of Orange]], the leader of the independence war that established the precursor to the present-day Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}} [http://www.planet.nl/planet/show/id=106882/contentid=525037/sc=5ce917 Greatest Dutchman]&lt;/ref&gt; The election was not considered representative, as it was held by viewers' voting through the internet and by phoning in.
[[Theo van Gogh (film director)|Theo van Gogh]] had been murdered a few days before by a Muslim, which likely affected people's voting in the TV contest for Fortuyn.  The program later revealed that William of Orange had received the most votes, but many could not be counted until after the official closing time of the television show (and the proclamation of the winner), due to technical problems. The official rules of the show said that votes counted before the end of the show would be decisive, but it was suggested that all votes correctly cast before the closing of the vote would be counted. Following the official rules, the outcome was not changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nu.nl/algemeen/443284/pim-fortuyn-toch-niet-de-grootste-nederlander.html |title=nu.nl/algemeen &amp;#124; 'Pim Fortuyn toch niet de Grootste Nederlander' |publisher=Nu.nl |date= |accessdate=2010-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Plek moord Pim Fortuyn.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Parking lot in [[Hilversum]] where Fortuyn was assassinated]]

Fortuyn's political career and popularity suggested a change in the Dutch people's views of their society as tolerant with integrated multiple cultures. 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;First of all, one can conclude that criticism on political correctness and on the ideal of the multicultural society has broken through for real relatively late.... In the end it was Pim Fortuyn, the electoral success of the LPF and namely the murder on Fortuyn which led to the definitive breakthrough.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tegenwicht.org/24_fund_nl/prins.htm Quote from Prins, Baukje &amp; Slijper, Boris - 'Integratie zorgt in veel landen voor controverses', De Helling, winter 2002]: &quot;Ten eerste kan men stellen dat de kritiek op de politieke correctheid en het ideaal van de multiculturele samenleving relatief laat echt is doorgebroken. [...] Uiteindelijk waren het Pim Fortuyn, het electorale succes van de LPF en met name de moord op Fortuyn die tot de definitieve doorbraak hebben geleid.&quot; (Tegenwicht)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Although Fortuyn did not advocate [[racial segregation|segregation]], he brought it up as a debatable issue. 

[[Right-wing politics|Right-wing politicians]] gained power after Fortuyn's death, such as former [[Ministry of Justice (Netherlands)|Minister for Integration &amp; Immigration]] [[Rita Verdonk]] and the prominent [[Criticism of Islam|critic of Islam]], [[House of Representatives of the Netherlands|Member of the House of Representatives]] [[Geert Wilders]]. These politicians often focused on the debate over [[cultural assimilation]] and [[Integration law for new immigrants to the Netherlands|integration]].

==Accusations of sexual misconduct==
In 2005, three years after Fortuyn's death, the Dutch journalist [[Peter R. de Vries]] obtained and publicized a secret report of the intelligence department of the Rotterdam police. Fortuyn and several other members of his party had been the subject of an investigation by the intelligence services.  An anonymous informant claimed that Fortuyn had engaged in sex with [[Morocco|Moroccan]] youths aged between 16 and 21; this was legal under Dutch law.  The Ministry of the Interior informed parliament that the report contained factual inaccuracies, and that the trustworthiness of the original source could not be verified.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}} [http://www.minbzk.nl/actueel/kamerstukken?ActItmIdt=69617 Explanation from the Minister of the Interior to Parliament] (in Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
*''[http://www.amazon.com/dp/9022983382 Tegen de islamisering van onze cultuur: Nederlandse identiteit als fundament]'' (Against the Islamisation of Our Culture), (A.W. Bruna, 1997), (ISBN 90-229-8338-2)
*''[http://www.amazon.com/dp/9022984079 50 jaar Israel, hoe lang nog?: Tegen het tolereren van fundamentalisme]'' (Fifty Years Israel, how much left?) (Bruna, 1998), (ISBN 90-229-8407-9)
*''[http://www.amazon.com/dp/9061129117 De Puinhopen Van Acht Jaar Paars: de Wachtlijsten in de Gezondheidszorg, de Zorgwekkende Staat Van Het Onderwijs, de Problemen Met Betrekking Tot de V]'' (The rubble of eight purple years), (Karakter Uitgevers, 2002), (ISBN  9-0611-2911-7)

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{nl icon}} [http://www.parlement.com/9291000/biof/02312 Official Parliamentary Biography]
* {{imdb name|id=1989556|name=Pim Fortuyn}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[Party leader]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Livable Netherlands]]
| years  = 2001-2002
| before = ''First''
| after  = [[Fred Teeven]]
}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[Party leader]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Pim Fortuyn List]]
| years  = 2002
| before = ''First''
| after  = [[Mat Herben]]
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Persondata 
| NAME              = Fortuyn, Pim
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Fortuijn, Wilhelmus Simon Petrus
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Dutch politician, civil servant, sociologist, author and professor. Assassinated during the 2002 Dutch national election campaign.
| DATE OF BIRTH     = February 19, 1948
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Driehuis, Netherlands
| DATE OF DEATH     = May 6, 2002
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Hilversum, Netherlands
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Fortuyn, Pim}}
[[Category:1948 births]]
[[Category:2002 deaths]]
[[Category:Dutch civil servants]]
[[Category:Dutch academics]]
[[Category:Dutch sociologists]]
[[Category:Dutch political scientists]]
[[Category:Dutch educators]]
[[Category:Dutch writers]]
[[Category:Dutch non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Dutch political writers]]
[[Category:Dutch columnists]]
[[Category:Dutch activists]]
[[Category:Dutch political pundits]]
[[Category:Dutch republicans]]
[[Category:Dutch Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Dutch municipal councillors]]
[[Category:Free speech activists]]
[[Category:Livable Netherlands politicians]]
[[Category:Pim Fortuyn List politicians]]
[[Category:Gay politicians]]
[[Category:Gay writers]]
[[Category:LGBT people from the Netherlands]]
[[Category:LGBT politicians from the Netherlands]]
[[Category:LGBT rights activists from the Netherlands]]
[[Category:LGBT television personalities]]
[[Category:LGBT Christians]]
[[Category:Islam in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Islam critical scholars]]
[[Category:Opposition to Islam in Europe]]
[[Category:Criticism of Islam]]
[[Category:Critics of the European Union]]
[[Category:Vrije Universiteit alumni]]
[[Category:University of Groningen alumni]]
[[Category:University of Groningen faculty]]
[[Category:Maastricht University faculty]]
[[Category:Erasmus University Rotterdam faculty]]
[[Category:People from Velsen]]
[[Category:People from Rotterdam]]
[[Category:Murdered educators]]
[[Category:Murdered writers]]
[[Category:Assassinated activists]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:People murdered in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Assassinated Dutch politicians]]

[[br:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[da:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[de:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[es:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[fr:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[fy:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[ga:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[it:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[he:פים פורטאון]]
[[nl:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[ja:ピム・フォルタイン]]
[[no:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[pl:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[pt:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[ro:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[ru:Фортёйн, Пим]]
[[simple:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[ckb:پیم فۆرتاین]]
[[fi:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[sv:Pim Fortuyn]]
[[uk:Пім Фортейн]]
[[vo:Pim Fortuyn]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
