<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4593836" ns="0" title="Sandy Thomas"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{In-universe|date=October 2009}}

{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|image=[[Image:Sandy Thomas.png|220px]]
|name=Sandy Thomas
|caption=Freddie Jones as Sandy in 2009.
|introducer=[[Kathleen Beedles]] (2005)&lt;br /&gt;[[Gavin Blyth]] (2009)
|portrayer=[[Freddie Jones]]
|years=2005–08, 2009—
|classification=[[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|home=Mulberry Cottage
|occupation=[[Retirement|Retired]]
|born=22 March 1934 
|sons = [[Ashley Thomas]]&lt;br&gt;Luke Thomas
|granddaughters =[[Jasmine Thomas]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gabby Thomas]]
|grandsons=[[Arthur Thomas (Emmerdale)|Arthur Thomas]]
|first=6 November 2005
|last= 
}}

'''Sandy Thomas''' is a [[fictional character]] on the [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]''. He is played by [[Freddie Jones]] and made his first appearance on the show 6 November 2005. The character left in March 2008, but returned to the show in February 2009.

==Creation and development==
===Departure (2008)===
Jones announced his decision to quit in January 2008, remaining on-screen until March, however in October 2008, 7 months after deciding to quit, it was announced that he was to return to Emmerdale&lt;ref&gt;http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a133980/sandy-to-make-emmerdale-return.html&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Storylines==
===2005–08===
Sandy arrived in [[Emmerdale]] on Ashley and Laurel's wedding day. Ashley and Laurel found him in their bedroom and Ashley introduced him as his father.

Ashley and Sandy were estranged, due to Sandy helping Ashley's mum die of a terminal illness. However, Ashley's new wife [[Laurel Thomas|Laurel]] and granddaughter [[Jasmine Thomas|Jasmine]] were pleased to have him around. Sandy made friends with [[Daz Eden]] and [[Shadrach Dingle]] but made an enemy of [[Edna Birch]]. He was accused of kidnapping [[Belle Dingle]] at Christmas 2005 after she went missing.

After a major fall-out with his son, Sandy moved in with [[Alan Turner (Emmerdale)|Alan Turner]] and [[Betty Eagleton]]. Father and son reconciled but Sandy stayed with Alan and Betty.

===2009—===
Sandy returned in February 2009, when it was revealed that Jasmine had visited him when she left Emmerdale. He and his lady friend helped Jasmine find a flat but she went on the run again after Marlon, Eli, Ashley and Laurel Thomas came looking for her.

Jasmine told Sandy what had happened to Shane and that Debbie was on remand for manslaughter. She felt guilty and wanted to confess but Debbie and Sandy insisted she go on the run. She returned to Emmerdale briefly to collect some money Sandy promised her and witnessed Danielle Hutch being arrested. She went to Debbie's court hearing and confessed - just as Debbie was about to plead guilty to manslaughter. She was charged with manslaughter and pleaded guilty. She was sentenced to four years in prison, leaving Debbie and her family devastated.

Sandy stayed at the vicarage but overcrowding meant he and Doug had to share a room. Unhappy, he tried blackmailing Nicola to move out by telling her his age....it didn't work. Resorting to desperate measures, Sandy and Doug wrote Nicola a love letter, apparently from Jimmy, including an invitation to move into Mill Cottage. She accepted, easing the overcrowding but Ashley threw Sandy out after his preoccupation with Jasmine led to Gabby damaging the computer in Cafe Hope. Ashley was furious when Gabby told him that she thought if she was naughty, she would be sent to prison and could ask the governor to let Jasmine go because it was making her grandad very sad. Debbie found him sleeping in the shed in her garden. Sandy and Ashley reconciled but Sandy, seeing Diane was lonely, asked if he could move into the Woolpack and she agreed.

Sandy stayed living at the Woolpack until December 2009 when, in disgust at Ashley choosing Sally over her, Laurel and the children left the village. Doug was equally disgusted and moved into the Woolpack himself so Sandy returned to the vicarage, wanting to support his son. He was thrilled when Ashley and Laurel managed to patch up their marriage, returning to the village with the children.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/Soaps/emmerdale/newsandgossip/FreddieleavestheDales/default.html Freddie leaves the Dales] at [[itv.com]]
*[http://www.itv.com/Soaps/emmerdale/newsandgossip/Sandyscomingback999/default.html Freddie return Dales] at itv.com

{{Emmerdale}}
{{EDThomas}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Thomas, Sandy}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional sailors]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2005]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
