<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4634432" ns="0" title="Goa&#039;uld technology in Stargate"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|notability=December 2009|primarysources=December 2009|in-universe=December 2009|fiction=December 2009}}
This is a '''list of Goa'uld technologies''' in the ''[[Stargate]]'' franchise. The [[Goa'uld]] are the main adversaries for most of the run of ''Stargate SG-1''. They scavenged or conquered most of their advanced technologies from other races. However, there are innovators amongst the Goa'uld; [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] and [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] in particular have been depicted with a great deal of technological ingenuity. Rather than being designed as practical, many Goa'uld devices, such as the [[staff weapon]], are designed to have higher visual impact, meant to intimidate and reinforce their position as gods to their followers.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Warrior&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Warrior|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some pieces of Goa'uld technology, such as the hand device and the healing device, respond only to mental commands and require naqahdah in the bloodstream of the user to operate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thor's Chariot|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Seth&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Seth|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cloaking and shielding ==

* '''Cloaking device''' – The existence of Goa'uld cloaking technology is first revealed in {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, when [[Nirrti (Stargate)|Nirrti]] uses a personal cloaking device based on Reetou phase-shifting. [[Yu (Stargate)|Yu]] is outraged that she has not shared this technology with the [[System Lord]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fair Game|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Personal cloaking devices have also been used by Hathor,&lt;ref name=&quot;Out of Mind&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Out of Mind|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an ash'rak assassin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allegiance&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Allegiance|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cloaking devices first appear on a Goa'uld cargo ship in {{sgcite|Deadman Switch}}, and in later episodes become commonplace for [[Tel'tak]]s and [[Al'kesh]]. In {{sgcite|The Serpent's Venom}}, [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] cloaks an entire fleet of [[Ha'tak]]s, a feat that [[Selmak]] says has never before been accomplished.

* '''Force Shield''' – A energy barrier, also called a force-field or simply a shield. Goa'uld force shields work on a frequency oscillation principle, so a fast moving object can bypass it at the right moment. Goa'uld motherships are protected by force shields,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;/&gt; as are some ground-based facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Into the Fire&quot;/&gt; Force shields are also installed inside ships to restrict access to certain areas,&lt;ref name=&quot;Upgrades&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Upgrades|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to contain hull breaches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Descent&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Descent|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some powerful Goa'uld are equipped with personal force shields activated with a button on their hand device. These shields react proportionally to the amount of kinetic energy of incoming matter, blocking fast-moving objects like bullets but not slower objects like an object thrown by hand. This is so the shield does not stop air from getting in.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Nox&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Nox|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tok'ra]] have made force shield technology available to the [[Stargate Command|SGC]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prototype|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Lucian Alliance has also obtained shield technology, and it appears to block any solid object, regardless of velocity.

* '''Gate Shield''' – A force field that blocks a [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] from unauthorized access, functioning similarly to [[Earth]]'s [[Iris (Stargate)|Iris]], though it does not impede the energy-absorbing armor of a [[Kull Warrior]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot;/&gt; It can be deactivated remotely by a specific code. Planets with shielded Stargates include Tartarus&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot; /&gt; and Erebus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orpheus&quot;/&gt;

* '''Sun shield''' – A pair of devices on P3X-513 designed to generate a massive force-field that protects the area below from [[ultraviolet radiation]]. It turns the sky orange as a side-effect. The device is reactivated by [[SG-1]], in the process disproving former SGC officer Jonas Hanson's claim of divinity that he had used to seize power on the planet.&lt;ref name=&quot;The First Commandment&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The First Commandment|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Weapons and military ==

* '''AG-3''' – A weapons satellite design supposedly buried within the Goa'uld genetic memory, capable of detecting enemy ships thousands of light-years away and destroying [[Ha'tak]] motherships. They are powered by heavy liquid [[naqahdah]] fuel cells and work in groups of six. In a dream state created by the Harcesis [[Shifu (Stargate)|Shifu]], [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] oversees the construction of an AG-3 defense network for Earth, but eventually tries to use it to dominate the world. The dream serves to demonstrate how Goa'uld knowledge is inherently corrupting even to those with the best intentions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Absolute Power&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Absolute Power|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This is almost certainly not an actual device as this only appeared as a plot device in a dream sequence, and no weapon like it was ever exhibited by the Goa'uld, as it would have changed the balance of power significantly between the System Lords.

[[Image:Goauldhanddevice.png|frame|Goa'uld hand device]]
* '''Kara kesh''' – Also known as a &quot;ribbon device&quot;, the hand device is a metal, glove-like object with a large red gem set in the palm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;&gt;''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]''&lt;/ref&gt; It is the personal weapon of the [[Goa'uld]] and requires [[naqahdah]] in the bloodstream to operate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seth&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Seth|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They utilize a modified version of a staff weapon's power source channeled through amplification crystals, and are thought-controlled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forever in a Day&quot;/&gt; The hand device can generate a shockwave that throws back anyone in its path with great force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; The [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] attribute the Goa'uld ability to hurl people through the air as a sign of their divine power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Threshold&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Threshold|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hand device can also generate an energy stream to a person's head that causes severe pain and eventual death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; This function creates a mental link between Goa'uld and victim, which may allow the Goa'uld host to send a message through.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forever in a Day&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Forever in a Day|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hand devices can also be used to block zat blasts,&lt;ref name=&quot;Double Jeopardy&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Double Jeopardy|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have buttons on the wrist for controlling Goa'uld technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Secrets&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Secrets|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Enemies|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Hara'kesh''' – A device shaped like an elaborate ring, worn by Goa'uld ashrak assassins. It is both a weapon and a torture device, capable of inflicting incredible pain before killing. It can also generate an energy field that causes suggestibility and memory loss, allowing the ashrak to gain access to the target.&lt;ref name=&quot;In the Line of Duty&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|In the Line of Duty|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sokar (Stargate)|Sokar]] tortured [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] with a hara'kesh.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serpent's Song&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Serpent's Song|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Intar''' – A weapon used for training purposes. Intars can be built into many different types of weapons, including Earth firearms, and fire a red energy burst that stuns the target. [[SG-1]] first encounters intars in a training camp of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rules of Engagement&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Rules of Engagement|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Stargate Command|SGC]] adopts intars for training purposes as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Proving Ground&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Proving Ground|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Kor mak''' – Paired bracelets that connect the wearers and kills them if they are separated from one another for too long. They are nearly impossible to cut through or otherwise remove except with a key. They were once used by the Goa'uld [[Cronus (Stargate)|Cronus]] in transporting prisoners to prevent escape. [[Vala Mal Doran]] uses one to connect her to [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] in order to ensure a share of Ancient treasure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Avalon|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their connection lasts even after she removes the bracelets due to the effects of an Ancient long-range communications device, but it eventually wears off.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Ties That Bind|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Pain stick''' – A torture device shaped like a rod with a three-pronged tip. The pain stick inflicts excruciating pain when applied to a person, and causes light to emanate from their eyes, ears, and mouth. Extended exposure is lethal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Point of View&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Point of View|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the later seasons of ''SG-1'', pain sticks are used by members of the Free Jaffa&lt;ref name=&quot;Ex Deus Machina&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Ex Deus Machina|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Lucian Alliance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Company of Thieves&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Company of Thieves|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an alternate universe, they are also seen used by [[United States Secret Service|Secret Service]] agents to subdue a protestor.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Road Not Taken&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Road Not Taken|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Reconnaissance drone''' – A hovering reconnaissance device equipped with sensors, shields, an energy weapon, and a long-range subspace communicator. One alerts [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] to SG-13's presence on P3X-666,&lt;ref name=&quot;Heroes&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Heroes|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and another is found scanning a Repository of the Ancients on P3X-439.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Lost City|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Shock Grenade''' – A reusable spherical device that emits a blinding light and a deafening sound, rendering all individuals in its vicinity unconscious. Exposure to the device can cause temporary blindness.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Serpent's Lair|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are often deployed in advance of an attack force to neutralize opposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orpheus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Orpheus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:SGStaffWep.jpg|frame|A staff weapon held by Col. Jack O'Neill]]
* '''Ma'Tok staff''' {{anchor|Staff Weapon}}– More commonly known as the &quot;Staff Weapon&quot;, the standard weapon used by the [[Goa'uld|Goa'uld army]] and their [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]], consisting of a metal quarterstaff with an almond-shaped head that splits open to fire a powerful energy blast. There is a counterbalancing club on the back end, allowing the weapon to be used in melee combat at close ranges.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; It is powered by liquid [[naqahdah]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Fifth Race|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In skilled hands it can be quite effective,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bloodlines&quot;/&gt; but it is less accurate and slower to fire than Earth-made firearms; [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] describes it as a &quot;weapon of terror&quot; rather than of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Warrior&quot;/&gt; Heavier models of the weapon can be slung at the waist by a strap,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Man&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Fifth Man|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;48 Hours&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|48 Hours|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; or mounted on fixed or mobile platforms to act as artillery support.&lt;ref name=&quot;Into the Fire&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Into the Fire|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Goa'uld ships are equipped with large-scale versions of these weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; The [[Mythology of Stargate#Jaffa|Sodan]] use a variant of the staff weapon with the back half removed, making it light and easier to carry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babylon&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Babylon|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This gives the Sodan staff the advantage of being able to be used one-handed, and it allows the weapon to be slung over the back, although it removes the weapon's melee ability.

* '''Starship''' – The [[Goa'uld]] operate a [[Starships in Stargate#Goa'uld starships|variety of starships]], including [[Ha'tak]] motherships, [[Al'kesh]] bombers, and [[death glider]] fighters. The control systems of Goa'uld ships are based on crystals,&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;/&gt; a feature copied by the Earth ship ''Prometheus''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prometheus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prometheus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the collapse of the Goa'uld order in {{sgcite|Reckoning}}, most of their fleet have fallen into the hands of the [[Free Jaffa Nation]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Stronghold&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Stronghold|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Lucian Alliance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;/&gt;

* '''Tacluchnatagamuntoron (Tac)''' – A heat-seeking automated weapon shaped like a sphere, which fires bolts of energy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deadman Switch&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Deadman Switch|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Transphase eradication rod (TER)''' – A device designed to illuminate the Reetou, enemies of the Goa'uld who are normally invisible because they exist 180 degrees out of phase. The TER also incorporates an energy weapon that can kill a Reetou in one shot. The [[Tok'ra]] provide TERs to [[Stargate Command]] after it is infiltrated by Reetou rebels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Show and Tell&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Show and Tell|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, the SGC maintains a cache of TERs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rite of Passage&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Rite of Passage|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; A TER is also capable of penetrating a Goa'uld personal cloaking device, as they are based on Reetou phase-shifting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;/&gt; The prototype of the Kull disruptor is based on a modified TER.&lt;ref name=&quot;Death Knell&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Death Knell|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Za'tarc weapon''' – A small but extremely powerful energy weapon worn as a ring. It is first seen used by za'tarc assassins, who can vaporize themselves after completing their mission with a self-destruct on the weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Divide and Conquer&quot;/&gt; The weapon has also been used by [[Osiris (Stargate)|Osiris]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Chimera&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Chimera|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by bounty hunters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bounty&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Bounty|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:SGZatGun.jpg|frame|A zat held in its open configuration, ready to fire]]
* '''Zat'nik'tel (Zat)''' {{anchor|Zat'nik'tel|Zat}} – A zat'nik'tel (pronounced &quot;ZAT-nik-a-tel&quot;, usually shortened to &quot;zat&quot;) is commonly used sidearm shaped like a small snake curved into an &quot;S&quot; shape, that springs forward when activated. One shot from the zat stuns (though its effectiveness varies with different people), a second shot kills, and a third shot disintegrates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Within the Serpent's Grasp&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Within the Serpent's Grasp|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers eventually regretted introducing the disintegration feature and [[retcon]]ned it out of existence after season 3; an in-joke is made of this in the episode {{sgcite|Wormhole X-Treme!}}, where [[Martin Lloyd]] suggests it and a character replies &quot;that's the quite possibly the stupidest thing I've ever heard you say.&quot; Zat blasts can be transmitted through conductive materials like metals,&lt;ref name=&quot;Memento Mori&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Memento Mori|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and can also be used to either destroy electronic equipment&lt;ref name=&quot;Into the Fire&quot;/&gt; or as a power source.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot;/&gt;  The SGC is ultimately able to acquire a fairly large supply of Zat guns by taking them from dead Jaffa, or raiding Goa'uld weapons caches.

== Other technology ==
* '''Argosian nanocyte''' – A self-replicating microscopic devices created by the Goa'uld Pelops to experiment on the people of Argos. The nanocytes accelerate aging, such as that the Argosians live only 100 days. [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] is infected by the nanocytes and appears to age rapidly, but since they are not designed to start the aging process in adults, the effect wears off after [[SG-1]] deactivates the nanocytes' control signal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brief Candle&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Brief Candle|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Blood of Sokar''' – A hallucinogenic substance used by [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] in an unsuccessful attempt to extract information from [[SG-1]] and [[Martouf]] on the prison moon Ne'tu.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Devil You Know&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Devil You Know|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Brainwashing device''' - A device that allows the Goa'uld to brainwash their foes to believe what they wish them to believe and to act as agents for them.  Used by Apophis to turn Teal'c on the Tau'ri, broken by the Rite of Mal'Sharan where Teal'c was brought to the brink of death and then back during which he viewed his life.  Also used by Ba'al on the Jaffa High Council in order to take over the Free Jaffa Nation.  One member managed to break the brainwashing, but died in the attempt, but left a clue that led to Ba'al.  Ba'al tried to brainwash Teal'c but failed due to Teal'c being able to resist thanks to his previous experience and pretend to brainwashed.  Afterwards, the brainwashing over the High Council was broken.  Was later used to brainwash Malcom Barret as part of Ba'al's plan to get Stargate Command's gate list.  Broken through an unknown method.  The technology at some point fell into the hands of the [[Lucian Alliance]] who used it to brainwash Colonel [[David Telford]] into becoming a spy for them for about a year.  Broken when the air was vented from his room, suffocating him and then he was revived.  Victims of this technology seem to retain all of their memories of their actions when the brainwashing is broken.

* '''Brain interlink device''' – A small sphere with extending spikes, developed by the Goa'uld [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] using [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancient]] knowledge. When implanted into a subject's brain, it allows the subject's memories to be directly downloaded into a computer. Anubis uses the device to download Thor's mind, gaining access to [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]] technologies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Revelations|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also uses the device on [[Jonas Quinn]] and learns of Langara and [[naqahdriah]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fallen|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Homecoming|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Drydock''' – A floating anti-gravity platform used to construct Goa'uld [[Ha'tak]]s. [[SG-1]] disables a drydock on Erebus, causing it to crash to the ground, as a distraction for liberating a [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] forced labor camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Orpheus&quot;/&gt;

* '''The Eye of Ra''' – A powerful artifact shaped like a circular crystal. There are six Eyes in all, held by Ra, [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]], [[Osiris (Stargate)|Osiris]], Tiamat, and others. Each eye is powerful individually, but combined their power increases tenfold, creating a weapon of mass destruction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Full Circle|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Eye shown onscreen is the Eye of Tiamat, which is buried inside the Goa'uld Marduk's [[ziggurat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tomb&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Tomb|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] eventually collects five of the six Eyes and receives the Eye of Ra from [[SG-1]] in exchange for sparing Abydos. Once he has the superweapon, Anubis defeats the combined fleet of the [[System Lord]]s and then breaks the agreement and destroys Abydos.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot;/&gt; The weapon is later destroyed by a [[F-302]] flown by [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] and [[Samantha Carter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;/&gt;

* '''Healing device''' – A circular device worn over the palm that can heal most diseases and injuries. It requires [[naqahdah]] in the blood of the user to operate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thor's Hammer|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nirrti (Stargate)|Nirrti]] uses a healing device in conjunction with another instrument to return Cassandra's physiology to normal in {{sgcite|Rite of Passage}}. [[Jacob Carter]] unsuccessfully attempts to use a healing device to heal [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] from [[naqahdriah]] [[radiation poisoning]] in {{sgcite|Meridian}}. [[Vala Mal Doran]] is proficient with the healing device and uses one to assist the [[Stargate Command|SGC]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Powers That Be&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Powers That Be|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Uninvited&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Uninvited|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''[[Holographic projector]]''' – Small device that projects a three-dimensional image above it. It is first seen used by the [[Tok'ra]] in {{sgcite|Seth}} and appears again in several episodes to provide a visual aid for important plot points.&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Exodus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;/&gt; It was invented by the Goa'uld Nerus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beachhead&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Beachhead|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Jaffa converter''' – A device that changes ordinary humans into [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]], rewriting [[DNA]] and creating a symbiote pouch. The conversion can be reversed with a sarcophagus if done soon enough.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hathor&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Hathor|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Long-range communications device''' – A featureless metallic sphere enabling communication over many light-years. When in use, the face of the other person ripples onto its surface. Introduced as a large sphere floating within an inactive Stargate,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;/&gt; it has since appeared as a smaller, hand-held version.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tok'ra&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Tok'ra (Stargate SG-1)|The Tok'ra]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tok'ra]] do not use them because the system is not secure.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tok'ra&quot;/&gt; [[Harry Maybourne]] obtains one with which to communicate with his rogue NID teams off-world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shades of Grey&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Shades of Grey|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jack O'Neill has variously called them &quot;Goa'uld TV&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Within the Serpent's Grasp&quot;/&gt; &quot;teleball dealies&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tok'ra&quot;/&gt; and &quot;Goa'uld communication balls&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shades of Grey&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:jaffa mask.jpg|thumb|A Jaffa Serpent Guard.]]

* '''Mask''' – In the [[Stargate (film)|original movie]], Ra wears a complex mask resembling an Egyptian pharaoh's [[death mask]] (also seen in {{sgcite|Moebius}}), and his guards wear animal-headed masks evoking the Egyptian gods [[Anubis]] and [[Horus]]. The masks are made from many metallic plates that can be retracted into the collar, and serve to reinforce the perception that they are gods to Ra's slaves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; In ''Stargate SG-1'', [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] and his Serpent Guards wear masks,&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Children of the Gods|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; as do Heru-ur and his Horus Guards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;/&gt; Some of [[Sokar (Stargate)|Sokar]]'s Jaffa wear demon-headed masks,&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Jolinar's Memories|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and reference is made to a [[Setesh]] Guard in {{sgcite|Seth}}. The masks contain an internal [[Head-up display|HUD]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Bloodlines&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Bloodlines|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its eyes glow while the wearer is alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;/&gt;

* '''Memory device''' – A disc-shaped device that stimulates and amplifies the memory centers of the brain, aiding in recall. It is applied to the temple, causing a moment of pain, and can be connected to a visual display to allow a person's memories to be viewed directly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Out of Mind&quot;/&gt; The Goa'uld use memory devices for interrogation;&lt;ref name=&quot;Out of Mind&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Devil You Know&quot;/&gt; [[Osiris (Stargate)|Osiris]] uses one to gain access to [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]]'s dreams.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chimera&quot;/&gt; [[Jacob Carter]] uses a memory device on a [[Kull Warrior]] to learn its origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Evolution|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; A memory device is part of the [[Tok'ra]] za'tarc detector.&lt;ref name=&quot;Divide and Conquer&quot;/&gt;

* '''Nish'ta''' – An artificial organism in the form of a green gas, that once absorbed into a body's tissues opens the subject to mind control. [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] uses it to turn [[Rya'c]] against his father [[Teal'c]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Family&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Family|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Seth uses it to brainwash humans into loyal cultists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seth&quot;/&gt; Nish'ta can only be killed by an electrical shock, such as from a zat gun,&lt;ref name=&quot;Family&quot;/&gt; but once it has been eradicated a person cannot be reinfected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seth&quot;/&gt; The breath of Hathor is a less potent version of nish'ta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hathor&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Stargate sarcophagus.jpg|thumb|SG-1 inspects a sarcophagus.]]
* '''Sarcophagus''' – A coffin-like chamber capable of vastly extending life, healing almost any illness, repairing grievous injuries, and even reviving the recently dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; However, frequent use of the sarcophagus becomes addictive and has a deleterious effect on the mind;&lt;ref name=&quot;Need&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Need|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is a main factor in why the Goa'uld are evil, and why the [[Tok'ra]] refuse to use the sarcophagus.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tok'ra&quot;/&gt; Sarcophagi are sometimes used to preserve individuals for thousands of years,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tomb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hathor&quot;/&gt; although there is a limit to how long a sarcophagus can extend a person's life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;/&gt; The first sarcophagus was created by the Goa'uld Telchak, using a less potent version of the energy emitted by an Ancient healing device.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot;/&gt;

* '''Stasis jar''' – A container resembling a [[canopic jar]], which in the show are primitive copies of these devices made by the ancient Egyptians. The jar is filled with fluid that contains a dissolved sedative, and has life support and a [[naqahdah]] power source sufficient to keep a single [[Goa'uld]] symbiote alive at minimal metabolism for thousands of years. Stasis jars were used to imprison [[Osiris (Stargate)|Osiris]] and his queen Isis thousands of years ago. However, Isis died after the seal of her jar was broken.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Curse&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Curse|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Tablet''' – A database storage and display device resembling a metal plate with raised letters. It is paired with a '''page-turning device''', which changes the text to the next &quot;page&quot; when passed over the tablet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brief Candle&quot;/&gt; [[Ma'chello]] used a weapon hidden inside a page-turning device to assassinate the Linvris.&lt;ref name=&quot;Legacy&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Legacy|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tok'ra]] use a similar device but without the page-turner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Divide and Conquer&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Divide and Conquer|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Vocuum''' – A small, spherical Goa'uld device that projects an enormous three-dimensional [[hologram]], used by the Goa'uld to issue public pronouncements. [[SG-1]] encounters a vocuum at training camp of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rules of Engagement&quot;/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Stargate}}

[[Category:Stargate technology]]

[[ar:تكنولوجيا الغواؤلد]]
[[cs:Goa'uldské technologie ve Hvězdné bráně]]
[[hu:Goa'uld technológia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
