<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="465754" ns="0" title="Loyola University New Orleans"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|image_name= Loyolaseal.png
|image_size= 150px
|name=Loyola University New Orleans
|motto=''Deo et Patriae -(For God and country) - [[Ad Majorem Dei Gloriam]]''
|established=Founded 1904, chartered July 10, 1912
|type=[[Roman Catholic]], [[Jesuit]], [[Private university|Private]]
|endowment=[[United States dollar|US $]]257 [[1000000 (number)|million]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2011/schools/loyola-university-of-new-orleans&lt;/ref&gt;
|president=Rev. [[Kevin Wildes|Kevin Wm. Wildes]], S.J.
|city            = [[New Orleans]]
|state           = [[Louisiana]]
|country         = [[United States]]
|coor            = {{Coord|29.934236|N|90.121685|W|region:US-LA_type:edu|display=inline,title}}
|campus=[[urban area|Urban]], 24 acres
|undergrad=2,655&lt;ref name=&quot;unique&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.loyno.edu/vivid_descriptors/ |title=What Makes Us Unique? |accessdate=2008-04-12 |format= |publisher=Loyola University New Orleans}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad=2,203&lt;ref name=&quot;unique&quot; /&gt;
|staff=240
|colors= [[Maroon (color)|Maroon]] and [[Gold (color)|Gold]]
{{Color box|maroon}}{{Color box|gold}}
|mascot=[[Wolfpack]]
|affiliations=[[AJCU]]
|website=[http://www.loyno.edu/ www.loyno.edu]
|logo= [[Image:Loyolaneworleanslogo.svg|250px]]
|}}

'''Loyola University New Orleans''' is a [[Private university|private]], [[co-educational]] and [[Jesuit]] university located in [[New Orleans]], [[Louisiana]], United States. Originally established as Loyola College in 1904, the institution was chartered as a university in 1912. It bears the name of the Jesuit patron, [[Ignatius of Loyola|Saint Ignatius of Loyola]]. Loyola is one of 28 member institutions that make up the [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities]] and, with its current enrollment of approximately 5000 students, is among the larger Jesuit universities in the southern United States. Loyola University New Orleans is ranked fifth best institution among Southern regional universities offering masters and undergraduate degrees in the 2008 issue of the annual America's Best Colleges issue and guidebook published by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = America's Best Colleges 2008: Universities-Master's (South): Top Schools
  | work = US News and World Report
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/t1univmas_s_brief.php
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2008-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Princeton Review]]'' also features Loyola New Orleans in the most recent editions of its annual book, ''The Best 371 Colleges.''&lt;ref name=&quot;The Best 371 Colleges&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/rankingsbest.aspx| title=The Best 371 Colleges|year=2010|accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the past, the school has been called ''Loyola of the South'', ''Loyola New Orleans'', ''Loyola University, New Orleans'', and ''Loyola University of New Orleans''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loyno.edu/ia/publications/graphicidentityguide/index.html Graphic Identity Guide to Loyola], Loyola University New Orleans, April 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Founding===
[[Image:LoyolaCollege1904.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Loyola College, circa 1904]]In the early 18th century Jesuits first arrived among the earliest settlers in New Orleans and Louisiana.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://history.furman.edu/~benson/hst11/group6/test3.htm| title=French Jesuits, Missions in Louisiana|year=2005|accessdate=2007-06-13 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071228234816/http://history.furman.edu/~benson/hst11/group6/test3.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Loyola University New Orleans was founded by the [[Society of Jesus]] in 1904 as Loyola College on a section of the Foucher Plantation bought by the Jesuits in 1886. A young Jesuit, Fr. Albert Biever, was given a [[nickel]] for [[Tram|street car]] fare and told by his [[Jesuit]] superiors to travel [[Uptown New Orleans|Uptown]] on the [[Streetcars in New Orleans#St. Charles Avenue Line|St. Charles Streetcar]] and found a university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Hawkins, S.J., Donald A. | year = 1987 | title = Church on the Park: Holy Name of Jesus | url = | chapter = The Parish | chapterurl = | pages = 12 | publisher  = Laborde Printing Co. | isbn = | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; As with many Jesuit schools, it contained both a college and preparatory academy. The first classes of Loyola College were held in a residence behind [[Most Holy Name of Jesus Church]]. Fr. Biever was the first president. The first of Loyola's permanent buildings was undertaken in 1907, with Marquette Hall completed in 1910.

In 1911, the [[Jesuit]] schools in [[New Orleans]] were reorganized. The [[College of the Immaculate Conception (New Orleans)|College of the Immaculate Conception]], founded in 1847 in downtown [[New Orleans]], split its high school and college divisions and became solely a secondary institution, now known as [[Jesuit High School, New Orleans|Jesuit High School]]. Loyola was designated as the collegiate institution and was chartered as Loyola University on July 10, 1912.&lt;ref name=Whelan&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Whelan, S.J.
 | first = James F.
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | date = 1946-11
 | month = November
 | title = Loyola University, New Orleans
 | journal = The Southern Association Quarterly
 | volume = 10
 | issue = 4
 | pages = 538, 540–542
 | publisher = Duke University Press
 | issn = 0890-7145
 | pmid =
 | pmc =
 | doi =
 | bibcode =
 | url =
 | accessdate = 
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Growth===
[[Image:Loyarchdoor.JPG|thumb|left|160px|Entrance to the Memorial Library (1950), dedicated to Loyolans killed in [[World War II]]]]Loyola grew steadily over the years on its uptown campus. By the end of its first decade, the university not only included the College of Arts and Sciences, but also a School of Law (1914), a School of Dentistry (1914), and a College of Pharmacy (1919).{{Ref|Dentistry and Pharmacy|a}} Several years later, a School of Music was added to the growing curriculum.&lt;ref name=Whelan/&gt; At the time, the university's campus consisted mainly of Marquette and Bobet Halls, with large athletic fields extending back towards the end of the campus at Freret St. Loyola has the distinction of transmitting the first [[Radio programming|radio broadcast]] in the Deep South, when [[WWL (AM)|WWL]] began operation as a laboratory experiment on March 31, 1922.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/newsandcalendars/loyolatoday/2002/03/wwl.html| title=Loyola and WWL Radio celebrate 80th anniversary|year=2002|accessdate=2007-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the discontinuance of the football program in the 1930s, more space became available for construction of new facilities. Stallings Hall, built as a dedicated building for the College Of Business Administration, and the Memorial Library (now known as the &quot;Old Library&quot;)&lt;ref name=campconfid&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.loyolamaroon.com/media/storage/paper542/news/2008/04/18/News/Campus.Confidential-3332632.shtml| title=Campus Confidential|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; were constructed in the post [[World War II]] years, accommodating the growth of the student population.

[[Norman Francis]] entered the Law School in 1952, becoming the first [[African-American]]
admitted to the university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/?id=rcO5WhAJsFgC&amp;dq=black+white+and+catholic |title=Black, White, and Catholic: New Orleans interracialism, 1947-1956 |accessdate= |author=R. Bentley Anderson |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2005 |month= |work=  |publisher=Vanderbilt University Press |pages= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |isbn=9780826514837 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

More expansion continued in 1964, with the addition of the Joseph A. Danna [[Student activity center|Student Center]]; Albert Biever Hall, a [[Dormitory|student residence]] hall named after the first [[Academic administration|university president]]; and a central heating/cooling plant. Built soon after in 1967 was Henrietta Buddig Hall, a student residence that is Loyola's tallest building at twelve stories. The last building to be added in the 1960s was the J. Edgar Monroe Science Building (now known as Monroe Hall), the largest academic building erected to date.

During the 1970s, Loyola began to make many changes, especially regarding Jesuit governance and in the academic curriculum, reflective of many universities during the same period. Reflecting the precedent for reform established by [[Vatican II]], governance of the university shifted from a Jesuit regulated Board of Regents to a combined lay and clerical Board of Trustees. During this period, the Common Curriculum was developed to give students a wide breadth of knowledge in certain core areas, including [[Science]], [[Math]], [[History]], and [[English studies|English]]. A broader trend was seen in the growth of the university during this period, seeing it gradually transform from a regional, largely commuter college to a higher national profile school that attracted students from across the [[United States]].

In 1984 Loyola purchased the facilities of [[St. Mary’s Dominican College]], a nearby Catholic women's college which was closing down, and transformed it into the Broadway campus (after the name of its street location).  Today, the Broadway campus includes Loyola's School of Law, Cabra Residence Hall, and a Department of Visual Arts.

Expansion in recent years has seen the addition of Mercy Hall, purchased in 1993, a former girl's preparatory academy; construction of Carrollton Hall, an upperclassman residence; and the J. Edgar and Louise S. Monroe Library, the latter two completed in 1999.

In 1996, the Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities granted exclusive branding rights to [[Loyola University Chicago]] to call itself ''Loyola University''. This resulted in Loyola New Orleans' current trademark, ''Loyola University New Orleans''.

===Hurricane Katrina and Aftermath===
In August 2005, Loyola closed its campus and evacuated its students in anticipation of [[Hurricane Katrina]].  The campus sustained minimal wind damage including broken windows but floodwaters did not breach any buildings.  Following cleanup, classes resumed on Monday, January 9, 2006.  Despite the displacement of the entire student body during the fall 2005 semester, 91 percent of Loyola’s undergraduate students returned for the spring 2006 semester.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://loyno.edu/news/story/2005/12/9/924| title=Majority of Students to Return in Spring|year=2006|accessdate=2008-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Loyola held commencement ceremonies for the Class of 2006 on April 28–29, becoming the first New Orleans college to do so post-Katrina.

On April 10, 2006, President [[Kevin Wm. Wildes]], S.J. unveiled ''PATHWAYS - Toward Our Second Century'', Loyola's strategic post-Katrina plan.  The plan restructured the University's colleges and eliminated several academic programs and faculty positions to reduce operating costs and revitalize the University.  The Board of Trustees unanimously approved and passed the plan on May 19, 2006.  In response, the faculty of the College of Arts and Sciences produced a [[Motion of no confidence|vote of no-confidence]] in both President Wildes and Provost Walter Harris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.loyolamaroon.com/media/storage/paper542/news/2006/10/06/News/A.Lack.Of.Confidence-2334353.shtml| title=A Lack of Confidence|year=2006|accessdate=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In fall 2006, Loyola welcomed the class of 2010, the first post-Katrina freshman class, with 555 new students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/newsandcalendars/release.php?id=1082|title=Loyola Welcomes Freshmen One Year After Katrina|year=2006|accessdate=2007-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the storm, Loyola has completed all physical repairs that were caused by the hurricane, and its enrollment is on a steady rise to pre-Katrina numbers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/news/story/2008/5/15/1495|title=Loyola’s 100th graduating class steps on campus this fall|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.loyolamaroon.com/media/storage/paper542/news/2008/05/02/News/Freshmen.Commitments.Highest.Since.Katrina-3369951.shtml|title=Freshmen commitments highest since Katrina|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===University Presidents===
There have been seventeen presidents since the establishment of Loyola College in 1904.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.loyolamaroon.com/media/storage/paper542/news/2003/10/10/News/Chronology.Of.Loyolas.Presidents-524994.shtml| title=Chronology of Loyola's Presidents |year=2004|publisher= loyolamaroon.com| accessdate=2007-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break}}
# Albert H. Biever, S.J. (1904–1913)
# Alphonse E. Otis, S.J  (1913–1919)
# Edward A. Cummings, S.J. (1919–1924)
# Francis X. Twellmeyer, S.J. (1924–1925)
# Florence D. Sullivan, S.J. (1925–1931)
# John W. Hynes, S.J. (1931–1936)
# Harold A. Gaudin, S.J. (1936–1939)
# Percy A. Roy, S.J. (1939–1945)
# Thomas J. Shields, S.J. (1945–1952)
# W. Patrick Donnelly, S.J. (1952–1961)
# Andrew C. Smith, S.J. (1961–1966)
# Homer R. Jolley, S.J. (1966–1970)
# [[Michael Kennelly|Michael F. Kennelly]], S.J. (1970–1974)
# James C. Carter, S.J. (1974–1995)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://loyno.edu/news/story/2008/8/1/1532| title=Happy Birthday to Loyola President Emeritus Rev. James Carter, S.J.!|year=2008|accessdate=2008-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Bernard P. Knoth, S.J. (1995–2003)
# [[William J. Byron]], S.J. (2003-2004 (acting))
# [[Kevin Wm. Wildes]], S.J. (2004–present)

{{Col-end}}

==University Seal==
[[Image:Loyolaseal.png|thumb|left|250px|Seal of Loyola University New Orleans]]The seal, which was adopted by the university in 1929, features the [[coat of arms]] of the house of Loyola with the emblem of the Society of Jesus at the top. Central to the seal are two wolves and a golden pot, which come from [[St. Ignatius Loyola]]'s [[Crest (heraldry)|family crest]] and symbolize generosity (having enough to give to the wolves).  Above the figures of the wolves appears the [[fleur-de-lis]], which represents the French origin of New Orleans and Louisiana. Beneath it is a [[Brown Pelican|pelican]] feeding its young with her own blood; this ancient symbol of Christianity (Christ feeding the Church with his body and blood through the [[Eucharist]]) depicts Loyola as an institution of the state of Louisiana.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/ia/publications/graphicidentityguide/| title=Graphic Identity Guide to Loyola|year=2006|accessdate=2008-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:Loyola nola monroe library.JPG|thumb|right|300px|The south-west side of J. Edgar and Louise S. Monroe Library]]

===Profile===
Loyola is home to 5,000 students, including 3,000 undergraduates. The student to faculty ratio is 11 to 1. [[The Princeton Review]] features Loyola New Orleans in the 2010 edition of its annual book, ''The Best 371 Colleges.''&lt;ref name=&quot;The Best 371 Colleges&quot;/&gt; Loyola University New Orleans ranks #8 (South) in 2012 U.S. News &amp; World Report Best College Ranking. &lt;ref&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/loyola-university-new-orleans-2016&lt;/ref&gt;
The New York-based education services company says Loyola New Orleans offers students an outstanding undergraduate education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/newsandcalendars/release.php?id=1078| title=Loyola University featured in 2008 edition of the Princeton Review Annual College Guide – The Best 366 Colleges|year=2007|accessdate=2008-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nearly all classes are taught by full-time faculty, 91 percent of whom hold doctoral or equivalent degrees in their areas of expertise. Loyola professors have been recognized nationally and internationally by the [[Pulitzer Prize|Pulitzer Committee]], the [[National Science Foundation]], the [[National Endowment for the Humanities]], and by numerous other associations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://loyno.edu/vivid_descriptors/| title=What Makes Us Unique?|year=2008|accessdate=2008-01-30 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071227090819/http://www.loyno.edu/vivid_descriptors/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges===
Loyola is organized into colleges specializing in the [[liberal arts]], [[social science|social]] and [[physical science|physical]] [[science]]s and certain [[professions]]. The colleges at Loyola include:
*College of Humanities and Natural Sciences
*College of Social Sciences
*The Joseph A. Butt, S.J., College of Business
*College of Music and Fine Arts
*College of Law

====College of Humanities and Natural Sciences====
The College of Humanities and Natural Sciences focuses on areas concerning the natural sciences and liberal arts programs. It contains the departments of English, history, languages, philosophy, religious studies, psychology, biology, liberal studies, chemistry, mathematics, and physics. Also under the college's supervision is the Loyola Institute for Ministry (LIM).[http://loyno.edu/strategicplan/documents/pathways051906finaledited.pdf] Students have been awarded British Marshall, Fulbright, Goldwater, Mellon, Mitchell, and Rhodes scholarships, and have been included as USA Today's top students.

====College of Social Sciences====
The College of Social Sciences specializes in areas that deal with [[Human condition|the human condition]]. The College of Social Sciences contains the departments of counseling, criminal justice, human and organizational development, sociology, and political science. The college also includes the Schools of Nursing and Mass Communication.[http://loyno.edu/strategicplan/documents/pathways051906finaledited.pdf] The School of Mass Communication houses award winning programs in public relations, journalism and advertising. This includes the Loyola Bateman team which won the 1997, 2000, 2003, 2005 and 2008 national competitions sponsored by the Public Relations Student Society of America.[http://www.princetonreview.com/LoyolaUniversityNewOrleans.aspx]

====Joseph A. Butt, S.J., College of Business====
The College of Business began as an outgrowth of the College of Arts and Sciences and became a full fledged college in 1947. In 1983, the College of Business was renamed in honor of Joseph A. Butt, S.J., a longtime Jesuit professor in the business college. The College of Business is accredited by the [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business]] (AACSB), a prestigious honor awarded to only 450 business schools worldwide. The college offers programs in the fields of economics, finance, international business, management, marketing, accounting and the business of music.

====College of Music and Fine Arts====
The College of Music was established when the [[New Orleans]] Conservatory of Music and Dramatic Art was incorporated into the university in 1932. The College of Music gives students the chance to combine liberal arts with professional music courses. It is the only [[Jesuit]] college of music in the [[United States]]. The college offers programs in Jazz Studies, Music Education, Music Therapy, Music Industry Studies, Instrumental Performance, Vocal Performance, Ballet, Theatre Arts, and Visual Arts. In April 2007, the [[Thelonious Monk]] Institute of Jazz Performance announced its relocation to the College of Music and Fine Arts from the campus of the [[University of Southern California]]. The Music Industry program was one of the first in the country, and combines both the performing and technical aspects of the music business. ''[[The Princeton Review]]'' called it the &quot;second best program in the nation&quot; for music business.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}

====College of Law====
{{Main|Loyola University New Orleans College of Law}}
Loyola's [[law school]] opened in 1914. [[Colocation (business)|Co-located]] for many years on the main campus of Loyola, the Law School moved to the new Broadway campus in 1986, after Loyola purchased the closed campus of [[St. Mary’s Dominican College]] in 1984. The School of Law was renamed the College of Law with the passage of the PATHWAYS Plan on May 19, 2006.

===Centers and Institutes===
The University houses institutes in many different disciplines:
*[[Thelonious Monk Institute of Jazz|Thelonious Monk Institute of Jazz Performance]]
*Center for Environmental Communications
*Center for the Study of Catholics in the South
*Gillis Long Poverty Law Center
*Jesuit Center
*Jesuit Social Research Institute
*Lindy Boggs National Center for Community Literacy
*Loyola Institute of Politics
*Loyola Institute for Ministry (LIM)
*Shawn M. Donnelley Center for Nonprofit Communications
*Twomey Center for Peace Through Justice

==Campus==
Loyola is located in the historic [[Audubon, New Orleans|Audubon Park District]] on [[St. Charles Avenue]]. Its original campus, now called the Main Campus, was founded on a tract of land purchased by the New Orleans Jesuits in 1889. The purchased portion of land was much larger than the current day campus; in fact, the original land purchase contained the land now occupied by both Loyola and [[Tulane University|Tulane]] universities and Audubon Place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/discover/what-makes-us-unique/loyola-history.php|title=Loyola History|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through the next twenty years, portions of the original land purchase were sold to different entities to raise money for the new university, resulting in the current Main Campus area of 19 [[acre]]s.

By the 1950s, most of the original campus had been developed and the university looked around for areas where it could expand. In the 1960s, J. Edgar Monroe, a major benefactor of the university, donated to Loyola a large undeveloped tract of land in [[Metairie]] where the university could either expand or move its entire location. After reviewing its options, including the sale of the original campus to [[Tulane University]], the university decided to remain on [[St. Charles Avenue]], subsequently selling off its property in Metairie in ten years as a condition of the donation.

The Louis J. Roussel, Jr., Performance Hall on the Loyola campus, which stages symphony concerts, is named for the late New Orleans businessman [[Louis J. Roussel, Jr.]]

The closure of [[St. Mary's Dominican College]] in 1984 provided an opportunity for Loyola to expand its campus. After renovation of the closed college and some new construction, the Broadway Campus was opened in 1986, with several university offices and programs, the school of law most significantly, moving to the new campus.

===Main Campus===
Loyola's first campus, the Main Campus is located on [[St. Charles Avenue]] across from [[Audubon Park, New Orleans|Audubon Park]] and adjacent to [[Tulane University]], which also fronts St. Charles. The [[Streetcars in New Orleans#St. Charles Avenue Line|St. Charles Streetcar]] passes in front of the main campus. According to [[The Princeton Review]] Loyola students get along well with members of the local community. It is ranked #11 out of 371 Best Colleges for Great Town-Gown Relations.

The Main Campus contains the majority of the undergraduate academic divisions on campus, as well as serves as the hub of campus activities. Fronting St. Charles is Marquette Hall, the oldest campus building, which serves as the iconic image of the university. Several [[Quadrangle (architecture)|quadrangles]] organize the campus proceeding from the front of campus to its northern border at Freret Street, including the Academic quad, the Plaza De Los Martires De La Paz, or Peace Quad, named after the Salvadoran martyrs of 1989,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.loyno.edu/discover/what-makes-us-unique/loyola-history.php|title=Loyola History |accessdate=2008-07-23 |publisher=Loyola University New Orleans|quote=The Activities Quad, between Bobet Hall and the Danna Center, was renamed the Plaza De Los Martires De La Paz in 1989 to honor the six Jesuits, their cook, and her daughter who were slain in El Salvador. The Jesuits taught at the University of San Salvador. Eight trees were planted in the Peace Quad as a permanent memorial to these contemporary martyrs.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Residential Quad. Other notable buildings include the Joseph Danna Student Center, J. Edgar and Louise S. Monroe Library, Bobet Hall, J. Edgar Monroe Hall, the Music and Communications Building, and Branch Knox Miller Hall.

====Marquette Hall====
[[Image:Marquettehall.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Marquette Hall, Built 1910, as seen from the front of the campus on St. Charles Ave.]]Named after the Jesuit explorer Fr. [[Jacques Marquette]], S.J., Marquette Hall is one of the most prominent buildings on campus. Begun in 1907, it was finished in 1910. After its completion, most of the classes of the college and later, the university were conducted in the building until the construction of Bobet Hall in the late 1920s. The university's first library, the Bobet Library, was located on the third floor of Marquette Hall until the Memorial Library was constructed in the 1950s. When the dentistry school began its operations, the fourth floor of Marquette was used partly as a [[cadaver]] dissection area, and an external [[winch]] was used to hoist the cadavers up the four floors.&lt;ref name=campconfid/&gt; Today, Marquette primarily functions as an administrative building, but some classes are still conducted there. Also, the main [[theatre]] used by the Theatre Arts
program is housed on the third floor of the building. [[Image:Monroe Library.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Monroe Library]]

====J. Edgar and Louise S. Monroe Library====
The J. Edgar and Louise S. Monroe library is the main university library, constructed in 1999, replacing the Memorial Library built in 1950. The {{convert|150000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} library includes 377,000 books and periodicals and online access to 36,000 journals and 27,000 [[e-book]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://loyno.edu/libraries/|title=Libraries|year=2007|accessdate=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=collections&gt;{{cite web|url=http://library.loyno.edu/services_collections/|title=Collections + Services|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its music collection includes over 20,000 scores and recordings, and the special collections and archives include material concerning [[Jesuits]] in [[New Orleans]] and the [[U.S. South]].&lt;ref name=&quot;collections&quot; /&gt;
The library has won numerous awards in its existence, including the Association of College &amp; Research Libraries’ 2003 &quot;Excellence in Academic Libraries Award and the 2004 [[H. W. Wilson Company|H.W. Wilson]] Award for Professional Development. More so, the library ranks 5th in the “Best College Library” category of [[The Princeton Review]]'s 2010 edition of ''The Best 361 Colleges''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/vivid_descriptors/academicexcellence/university.html|title=Loyola Featured In Princeton Review's The Best 361 Colleges|year=2006|accessdate=2008-01-30}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://library.loyno.edu/about_us/faculty_staff/awards.php|title=Awards + Scholarly Activities|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Broadway Campus===
[[Image:LoyolaGreenville.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Greenville Hall, built 1889, faces St. Charles Ave on the Broadway Campus]]The former campus of [[St. Mary's Dominican College]], the {{convert|4|acre|m2|sing=on}} site was purchased by Loyola in 1984. Broadway Street forms its downtown border, and fronts St. Charles Avenue. The campus is located in the Greenville neighborhood, a former plantation and town annexed by New Orleans in the 19th Century. Greenville Hall, a [[National Register of Historic Places|Registered Historic Place]] built in 1889, forms the focus of the small campus, along with the College of Law building.

====Law Library====
Loyola University New Orleans' Law Library is located in the College of Law building on the Broadway Campus. It contains over 286,000 volumes and microfilm for the support of the students and faculty of the College of Law. Due to the unique tradition of civil law in [[Louisiana]], the library has substantial collections from civil law jurisdictions from around the world, including [[France]], [[Scotland]], and [[Quebec]].

===Sustainability===
Loyola's Statement on Environmental Responsibility details the ways in which campus operations strives to maintain its facilities in an environmentally sound and sustainable manner. Currently, 75% of all university classrooms are currently equipped with motion sensor lights and irrigation systems are designed with rain sensors to conserve water, both efforts supporting energy efficiency. The Loyola recycling program includes office paper, aluminum cans, and newspaper.&lt;ref name= &quot;Statement on Environmental Responsibility&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =Statement on Environmental Responsibility
| publisher =Loyola University of New Orleans
| url =http://www.loyno.edu/physicalplant/documents/ser.pdf
| accessdate =2009-06-010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The student-run group Loyola University Community Action Program organizes the Environmental Action Program, which works to educate &amp; advocate for environmental justice on campus and in the Gulf Coast region.&lt;ref name= &quot;LUCAP: Our Projects&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =LUCAP: Our Projects
| publisher =Loyola University of New Orleans
| url =http://www.loyno.edu/~lucapweb/projects.html
| accessdate =2009-06-010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Student Government Association maintains a Sustainability Garden to provide the campus community with gardening space and supplies as well as sustainability information.&lt;ref name= &quot;Sustainability Garden&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =Sustainability Garden
| publisher =Loyola University of New Orleans
| url =http://www.loyno.edu/sga/sustainabilitygarden.html
| accessdate =2009-06-010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
===Danna Student Center===
The epicenter of Loyola's on-campus life is the Dr. Joseph A. Danna Center, built in 1964. The Danna Student Center houses many services, including the campus bookstore, lounges, and student organization and university offices, and all of the university's dining services. The Orleans Room, or as the students call it the O.R., Loyola's main cafeteria, is also housed in the building.  Other dining options include Satchmo's, a jazz-themed eatery serving salads, sandwiches, and other traditional New Orleans foods, a [[Community Coffee|Community Coffee House]], a [[Smoothie King]], and Flambeaux's, a Po-Boy grill.  In 2008, the university completed a [[United States dollar|US$]]3 million renovation of the Danna Student Center under the guidance of Henry R. Muñoz III, improving the organization and services of the building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/news/story/2008/6/13/1503| title=Danna Student Center renovation update|year=2008|accessdate=2008-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student housing===
The university requires all students from outside the metropolitan New Orleans area to live on campus their first two years. Housing options include four on-campus [[residence halls]] for students: Biever Hall, Buddig Hall, Carrollton Hall, and Cabra Hall. Biever and Buddig hall are primarily reserved for freshmen and underclassmen male and female students, respectively. Carrollton and Cabra Halls are for upperclassmen students, offering [[suite (hotel)|suite]] and [[apartment]]-style living. The Department of Residential Life manages the Residence Halls, and provides programming aimed at building community within the residence halls. The Residence Hall Association, made up of residential students, serves as a representative for students to the administration and also allocates funding to student-run projects and activities.

===University Sports Complex===
The University Sports Complex, formerly called the Recreational Sports Complex or Rec Plex, houses all the athletic facilities on Loyola's campus.  It was constructed in 1987 and paid for in full by [[Freeport-McMoRan]].  The complex is situated on the fifth and sixth floors of the Freret Street [[Multi-storey car park|parking garage]].

The Complex features many modern amenities, including a jogging track; indoor tennis, racquetball, and basketball courts; weight rooms; and a six-Lane, Olympic style swimming pool.

===Organizations===
====Student Government====
&lt;!----this is too long. It is ordinary, not unique and shouldn't be here for that reason. Okay to mention ACTUAL stuff that it has done which is not ordinary----&gt;
The student body of Loyola is governed by a [[Students' union|Student Government Association (SGA)]]. The SGA is divided into three cohesive but independent branches—the Executive, Legislative, and Judicial.

The Executive branch is headed by the President, which consists of the Executive Staff: Chief of Staff, Director of Public Relations, Director of Finance, etc. The Chief of Staff organizes and maintains the hired staff and reports to the President. The Director of Finance (in lieu with the Vice President) helps run the Budget Allocations process for chartered student organizations. The Director of Public Relations handles all publicity and advertising associated with all three branches.

The Legislative branch is run and maintained by the Vice President, who oversees all members of Senate: The Senior Senator at Large, Junior Senators at Large, College Presidents, Senators, and First-year (new student) Student Senators. Members of Senate are divided up by the four (4) colleges: College of Business, College of Humanities and Natural Sciences, College of Music and Fine Arts, College of Social Sciences.

The Judicial Branch is headed by the Chief Justice, which consists of the Court of Review: Clerk of Court and Justices of the Court. The Justices of the Court are appointed by an interview process with the President and serve two-year appointments. The Court meets weekly or bi-weekly to judge student cases.

====Service organizations====
The Loyola University Community Action Program, commonly referred to as LUCAP, was founded in 1975 by a student group led by Loyola students Robert Guasco and Mary Baudouin as an organization connecting students with [[community service]], social justice, and advocacy work in New Orleans and abroad. LUCAP is the largest student organization on campus, due largely to its inclusive membership of any current or former project volunteer. LUCAP partners with local [[non-profit organization]]s including [[Habitat for Humanity]], [[Green Light New Orleans]], and the [[Gulf Restoration Network]] to provide students with opportunities to serve in their community. LUCAP successfully organized against [[Freeport-McMoRan]] in 1995 after the company donated money to Loyola University New Orleans to found the Institute for Environmental Communications, build sports facilities, and support the Twomey Center for Peace Through Justice. The organization cited Freeport's history of lack of regard for environmental quality and its history of [[Human rights|human rights violations]]
in the developing world. LUCAP organized [[student protest]] led to Freeport requesting their donation be returned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Fox
 | first = Julia
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | date = 1997-09
 | year =
 | month =
 | title = Leasing the Ivory Tower at a social justice university
 | journal = Organization &amp; Environment
 | volume = 10
 | issue = 3
 | pages = 259
 | publisher = Thousand Oaks
 | pmid =
 | pmc =
 | doi = 10.1177/0921810697103002
 | bibcode =
 | url =
 | accessdate = 
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Other organizations include [[Circle K International]], [[Big Brothers Big Sisters of America|Big Brothers/Big Sisters]], Peers Advocating Wellness (PAWS), and many others. Many students took a lead in rebuilding New Orleans after Hurricane Katrina through these service organizations.

====Greek life====
Loyola is home to 15 different social [[College fraternities and sororities in North America|fraternities and sororities]] that encompass over 20 percent of the undergraduate population. Presently, none of the Greek organizations own official houses. The last Greek organization to own a house was [[Alpha Delta Gamma]], whose house burned in January 2006. Since the burning of the ADG house on Freret Street, it has been demolished, just two blocks from Loyola's Main Campus. Loyola's Greek organizations are governed by three councils, the [[North-American Interfraternity Conference|Interfraternity Council]], the [[National Panhellenic Conference|Panhellenic Association]], and the [[National Pan-Hellenic Council]].
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-1-of-2}}
;Fraternities
*[[Alpha Delta Gamma]] (1932)
*[[Alpha Phi Alpha]] (1988)
*[[Beggars Fraternity|Beggars]] (1923)
*[[Kappa Alpha Psi]] (2005)
*[[Phi Kappa Psi]] (1989)
*[[Phi Beta Sigma]]  (1984)
*[[Sigma Alpha Kappa]] (1923)
*[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]] (1983)

{{Col-2-of-2}}
;Sororities
*[[Alpha Chi Omega]] (1984)
*[[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] (1972)
*[[Delta Gamma]] (1984)
*[[Delta Sigma Theta]] (1977)
*[[Gamma Phi Beta]] (1989)
*[[Zeta Phi Beta]] (1993)
*[[Theta Phi Alpha]] (1959)
{{Col-end}}

===1540 secret society===
1540, a purported secret society, has been subjected to criticism for existing in violation of rules banning unchartered organizations. In 2009, two members of Student Government Association's court were asked to resign due to their alleged membership in 1540.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loyolamaroon.com/news/sga-president-asks-two-justices-to-resign-1.1999949]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus publications===
The student-run weekly newspaper, ''The Maroon'', was established in 1923.  It is published weekly during the spring and fall semesters.  The Maroon has been nominated for the [[Associated Collegiate Press]]' [[National Pacemaker Award]] six times and won the award in 1982, 1983, 1986, 1998, 1999, and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.studentpress.org/acp/winners/npm06.html|title=ACP Contest Winners|year=2006|accessdate=2008-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.loyno.edu/newsandcalendars/loyolatoday/1998/11/maroon.html|title=The Maroon Wins National Award|year=1998|accessdate=2008-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Additional student publications include ''The Wolf,'' Loyola's annual yearbook, ''ReVisions,'' the annual literary arts journal, ''Hyster,'' the Women's Issues Organization's [[zine]], and ''Reader's Response'', which publishes the single best paper from each of the English Department's literature and theory courses. Each semester, a small group of students intern for ''The New Orleans Review'', an international journal of contemporary poetry, fiction, nonfiction, art, photography, film and book reviews, founded in 1968 and published by Loyola University.

==Athletics==
[[Image:Loyola Wolfpack.jpg|thumb|right|Loyola Wolfpack Logo]]
Loyola's sports teams are nicknamed the Wolfpack. They currently participate in the [[Southern States Athletic Conference]]. Loyola's six intercollegiate teams are almost wholly funded through student activity fees per a student referendum passed in 1991. In 1972, Loyola suspended its athletics program, citing &quot;educational and financial&quot; reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.loyolamaroon.com/media/storage/paper542/news/2002/02/01/WebExtra/Looking.Back.The.Day.The.Wolfpack.Died-173975.shtml| title=Looking Back: The day the Wolfpack died|year=2002|accessdate=2008-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1991, the athletics program was reinstituted, amid student appeals for its reinstatement, including the aforementioned referendum.  Since 2003, the athletic department has offered three athletic scholarships in [[basketball]] to attract talent. Locally, Loyola's biggest rival is the adjacent [[Tulane University]], and the annual basketball game between the two teams is one of biggest athletic events at Loyola. [[Spring Hill College]] is also another rival in conference play. The Pack Pride Committee was founded in 2007 to promote athletics and to encourage community members to be &quot;Proud to be Part of the 'Pack'&quot;.

==Notable faculty and alumni==

{{Main|List of Loyola University New Orleans people}}

Many notable [[politicians]], [[entertainers]], and figures in [[United States]] history are alumni of the university. These include current and former members of the [[United States House of Representatives]], members of the [[Louisiana House of Representatives]] and [[Louisiana State Senate]], high ranking Presidential [[United States Cabinet]] officials, a former [[Head of State]], a recipient of the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]], and numerous music celebrities, including opera star [[Norman Treigle]]. The university is also home to a number of high profile professors, including [[Walter Block]], the [[free market]] economist and [[anarcho-capitalist]] associated with the [[Austrian School]].

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Norman Francis awarded 2006 Presidential Medal of Freedom.jpg|'''[[Norman Francis]]''', president of [[Xavier University of Louisiana]], receives [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]], 2006.
Image:Sean O'Keefe.jpg|'''[[Sean O'Keefe]]''', former [[Navy Secretary]], former [[Louisiana State University|LSU]] Chancellor, former [[National Aeronautics and Space Administration]] ([[NASA]]) Administrator.
Image:Harry Connick, Jr..jpg|'''[[Harry Connick, Jr.]]'''
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

==Notes==
{{Refbegin}}
{{Ref|Dentistry and Pharmacy|a}}The College of Pharmacy was closed in 1965, while the School of Dentistry closed in 1970.
{{Refend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|New Orleans}}
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.loyno.edu/ Official website]
* [http://wolfpack.loyno.edu/ Official Athletics website]

{{Private colleges and universities in Louisiana}}
{{Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities}}
{{Archdiocese of New Orleans}}
{{Southern States Athletic Conference navbox}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in Louisiana]]
[[Category:Loyola University New Orleans]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in New Orleans, Louisiana]]
[[Category:Jesuit New Orleans Province]]
[[Category:Jesuit universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1912]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1912]]
[[Category:Uptown New Orleans]]
[[Category:Places affected by Hurricane Katrina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]

[[es:Universidad Loyola Nueva Orleans]]
[[it:Loyola University (New Orleans)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
