<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="465922" ns="0" title="TeleFutura"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2011}}

{{Infobox broadcasting network
|name           = TeleFutura
|logo           = [[Image:Telefutura logo.svg|200px]]
|type           = [[Terrestrial television|Spanish Broadcast Television]] Network
|branding       = 
|airdate        = 
|country        = {{flag|United States}}&lt;p&gt;Headquarters: [[Miami, Florida]]
|available      = National
|founded        = 2002
|founder        =
|slogan         = 
|motto          = 
|market_share   = 
|license_area   = 
|broadcast_area = 
|area           = [[United States]], [[Mexico]] and [[Puerto Rico]]
|erp            = 
|owner          = [[Univision Communications, Inc.]][[Grupo Televisa]]
|key_people     = 
|foundation     = 
|launch_date    = January 14, 2002
|dissolved      = 
|picture format = [[480i]] (SD)&lt;br /&gt;[[720p]]/[[1080i]] (HD)
|former_names   = None
|digital        = 
|analog         = 
|servicename1   = 
|service1       = 
|servicename2   = 
|service2       = 
|servicename3   = 
|service3       = 
|servicename4   = 
|service4       = 
|callsigns      = 
|callsign_meaning = 
|former_callsigns = 
|affiliation    = 
|affiliates     = 
|groups         = 
|former_affiliations = 
|website        = [http://www.telefutura.com/ www.telefutura.com]
|footnotes      = 
}}
{{Infobox TV channel
| name              = 
| logofile          = 
| logosize          = 
| logocaption       = 
| logoalt           = 
| logo2             = 
| launch            = 
| closed date       = 
| picture format    = 
| share             = 
| share as of       = 
| share source      = 
| network           = 
| owner             = 
| slogan            = 
| country           = 
| language          = 
| broadcast area    = 
| affiliates        =
| headquarters      = 
| former names      = 
| replaced names    = 
| replaced by names = 
| sister names      = [[Univision]]&lt;br&gt; [[Galavision (USA)|Galavision]]
| timeshift names   = 
| web               = 
| terr serv 1       = 
| terr chan 1       = 
| sat serv 1        = DirecTV
| sat chan 1        = 408 Telefutura West (SD/HD)
| sat serv 2        = Dish Network
| sat chan 2        = 271, 830 (East)&lt;br&gt; 272, 831 (West)
| cable serv 1      = 
| cable chan 1      = 
| sat radio serv 1  = 
| sat radio chan 1  = 
| iptv serv 1       = [[AT&amp;T U-verse]]
| iptv chan 1       = 3005
| online serv 1     = 
| online chan 1     = 
| 3gmobile serv 1   =
}}

'''TeleFutura''' is a  U.S. [[Spanish language|Spanish-language]] broadcast [[television network]] owned by [[Univision]] with headquarters in [[Miami, Florida]].

==Overview==
TeleFutura Is America’s #2 Spanish-Language Network in [[prime time]]. The network started on January 14, 2002, a month behind [[Telemundo]]'s launch of its cable TV network, the bilingual [[mun2]], with programs such as the 3 hour gossip/Entertainment  show ''Escándalo TV'' (formerly &quot;Escándalo en el Medio Dia&quot;, but later changed due to a similarly named program airing in Mexico by Televisa S.A.) which was designed to compete with similar offerings like ''[[Cotorreando]]'' from [[NBC Universal]]'s Telemundo. Commercials for TeleFutura often air on the Univision network. Most of the stations that carry TeleFutura once aired the [[Home Shopping Network]].  Univision bought the stations from [[Barry Diller]]'s [[USA Broadcasting]] late in 2001.

TeleFutura's programming consists of [[telenovelas]] from Coral Productions, [[Televisa]], [[Venevision]], [[RCTV]], [[RCN TV|RCN]] and [[Rede Globo]] as well as movies often consisting of recent American releases dubbed into Spanish.  Movie titles are announced before the start of the broadcast, using the &quot;CinePlex&quot; (daytime movie, usually weekends), &quot;CineEscape&quot; (late night movie), &quot;Cine Especial&quot; (movie specials), or &quot;Cine de las Estrellas&quot; (prime-time movie) branding. The network also airs the reality courtroom show ''Veredicto Final'', ''Fútbol de la Liga Mexicana'' broadcasts, and sports news (including [[Contacto Deportivo]]).

In late 2005, TeleFutura started airing ''En Vivo y Directo'', a 7&amp;nbsp;pm newscast, opposite the taped 4&amp;nbsp;pm news on [[Galavisión (USA)|Galavisión]]). But the network eventually cancelled &quot;En Vivo y Directo&quot; due to low ratings after only a few weeks and have replaced the newscast with movies.

The network also offers a children programming block called [[Toonturama]] to fulfill the [[E/I]] requirements. Curiously, this block is shown both on Saturdays and Sundays, and includes mostly American and European series dubbed into Spanish, such as ''[[Flight Squad]]'' and ''[[Problem Child (TV series)|Problem Child]]''. An exception is ''[[Toad Patrol]]'', which it needs to dub into English to fix the speech. In the past, [[anime]] such as ''[[Lost Universe]]'', ''[[Tenchi Universe]]'', and ''[[Red Baron (anime)|Red Baron]]'' were shown in the block as well.

TeleFutura is also a part of the Spanish-language coverage of the [[FIFA World Cup]] [[soccer]] tournament, as Univisión owns exclusive US Spanish-language rights. For 2006 it carried eight live games, all in the last days of group play when games are played simultaneously, like [[ESPN2]] did with [[ESPN]] for English-language coverage.  It also had game replays and recap shows.  In addition, and in conjunction, TeleFutura also airs an exclusive [[Major League Soccer]] game of the week on Sunday afternoon/evening.

In late June 2006, Univisión was sold to an investment group including entertainment industry veteran [[Haim Saban]] for $13 billion. There are reports on media message boards that TeleFutura is being phased out and several key on air talents are being shifted to Univisión and Galavisión channels. However these rumors have not been verified, nor will the shutdown of TeleFutura happen anytime soon: According to [[Nielsen Media Research]], in February 2007 TeleFutura made significant gains in viewership at the expense of Telemundo, actually taking over second place among Spanish-language networks in the Adults 18-34, Men 18-34 and Men 18-49 demographics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hispanicprwire.com/news.php?l=in&amp;id=8151&amp;cha=7 |title=TeleFutura Delivers Highest Primetime Performance Ever in February Sweeps Among Key Hispanic Viewers |author=Rosemary Mercedes |publisher=Univision Networks  |accessdate=20 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 2009 TeleFutura launched the daily Gossip Show &quot;La Tijera&quot; with [[Charitin Goyco]], Liliana Rodriguez, [[Paul Bouche]], Carolina Sandoval and [[Augusto Valverde]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.enelbrasero.com/2009/03/10/el-publico-pide-que-corten-con-la-tijera-a-charitin/|title=El Publico Pide}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The cast was gradually modified and incorporated Tanya Charry , Raul Garcia, Anabelle Blum, and Rodolfo Jimenez. The show was cancelled in October 2011. 

On February 26, 2010 TeleFutura, one of the largest Spanish-language networks in the U.S. and the ideal entertainment alternative for Hispanics across the nation, announced today that once again it secured the #2 Spanish-language network position with last night’s  special broadcast of “Buscando La Doble de Selena: La Gran Final” (Search for Selena’s Double) attracting an impressive 1.9 million Total Viewers 2+, 1.0 million Adults 18-49,  over half a million Adults 18-34 and 620,000 Persons 12-34, making it the highest-ranked entertainment special in the history of the network.

On October 10, 2011, TeleFutura will premiere a new daily Gossip Show ''[[Tómbola]]''.

==TeleFutura HD==

In 2010, TeleFutura along with sister network Univisión began airing programming in [[1080i]] [[High-definition television|high definition]] with a [[16:9]] [[Aspect ratio (image)|aspect ratio]]. They were the last major over-the-air networks in the United States to have made the switch. DirecTV added the West Coast feed of the network in HD nationally on April 28, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dtv.client.shareholder.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=464645 DIRECTV Launches Univision and TeleFutura in Crystal-Clear HD] DirecTV Press Release April 28, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Dish Network later added the West Coast feed on May 12, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.multichannel.com/article/452575-Dish_To_Launch_Galavision_HD.php Dish To Launch Galavision HD] ''Multichannel News'' May 12, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Escándalo TV is broadcasting in HD.

==See also==
{{Portalbox|United States|Film}}
*[[List of programs broadcast by Telefutura]]
*[[List of Telefutura affiliates]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://tv.univision.com/telefutura TeleFutura] {{es icon}}

{{Broadcast Television}}
{{Univision Communications}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Telefutura}}
[[Category:TeleFutura television network|*]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 2002]]

[[es:TeleFutura]]
[[fr:TeleFutura Network]]
[[pt:TeleFutura]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
