<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4662249" ns="0" title="Jim Whitehurst"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Jim Whitehurst''' is the Chief Executive Officer at [[Red Hat]]. Prior to that, he was a Chief Operating Officer of [[Delta Air Lines]]. Whitehurst was tapped by former Delta CEO [[Gerald Grinstein]] to lead the airline out of [[bankruptcy]] and played a critical role in Delta's battle for survival against the hostile takeover attempt by US Airways in 2006.  Whitehurst became a very popular figure during the campaign to Keep Delta My Delta because of his transparent honesty and genuine affection for the company and its heritage.  Some have speculated that his fierce defense of Delta worked against him as Delta's Board sought a successor to CEO Grinstein in 2007.  Before his appointment as COO of Delta, Whitehurst served as Senior Vice President and Chief Network and Planning Officer for the company. 

Prior to joining Delta in 2002, he served as Vice President and Director of The [[Boston Consulting Group]] and held various management roles at its [[Chicago]], [[Hong Kong]], [[Shanghai]] and [[Atlanta]] offices.

A native of [[Columbus, GA|Columbus, Georgia]], Whitehurst graduated from [[Rice University]] in [[Houston]], Texas, with a bachelor's degree in Computer Science and Economics. He also attended [[Erlangen Nuremberg University]] in Erlangen, Germany, holds a general course degree from the [[London School of Economics]] and an MBA from [[Harvard Business School]]. 

Whitehurst is married and has two children.

== External links ==
* [http://blogs.cnet.com/8301-13505_1-9839996-16.html On the record with Jim Whitehurst, Red Hat's new CEO: 'I must have a mission'], an interview with Jim Whitehurst
* [http://www.redhat.com/about/companyprofile/management/whitehurst.html Jim Whitehurst's details at redhat.com]

{{Red Hat}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Whitehurst, Jim
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Whitehurst, Jim}}
[[Category:American businesspeople]]
[[Category:Boston Consulting Group people]]
[[Category:Delta Air Lines people]]
[[Category:Harvard Business School alumni]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Columbus, Georgia]]
[[Category:Rice University alumni]]
[[Category:Year of birth missing (living people)]]


{{US-CEO-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
