<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Cheat code" to="Cheating in video games" tofragment="Cheat codes" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="8544406" ns="0" title="Cheating in video games"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Cheatcodes|the gaming website|CheatCodes.com}}
{{Essay-like|article|date=November 2009}}

'''Cheating in video games''' involves a [[video game]] player using non-standard methods for creating an advantage beyond normal gameplay, usually to make the game easier, or may also create unusual effects which do not necessarily make the game easier to play, such as giving characters different appearances, such as large heads. Cheats sometimes may take the form of &quot;secrets&quot; placed by game developers themselves. 

Cheats may be activated from within the game itself (a cheat code implemented by the original game developers); or created by third-party software (a game trainer) or hardware (a [[cheat cartridge]]).

==History==
Cheating in video games has existed for almost their entire history. The first cheat codes were put in place for [[Playtest|play testing]] purposes. Playtesters had to rigorously test the mechanics of a game and introduced cheat codes to make this process easier. An early cheat code can be found in ''[[Manic Miner]]'', where typing &quot;6031769&quot; (based on [[Matthew Smith (games programmer)|Matthew Smith's]] driving licence,&lt;ref&gt;Retro Gamer Magazine issue 48 - Interview with Matthew Smith&lt;/ref&gt;) enables the cheat mode.

In a computer game, all numerical values are stored &quot;as is&quot; in memory. Gamers could reprogram a small part of the game before launching it. In the context of games for many 8-bit computers, it was a usual practice to load games into memory and, before launching them, modify specific memory addresses in order to cheat, getting an unlimited number of lives, currency, immunity, invisibility, etc. Such modifications were performed through [[PEEK and POKE|POKE]] statements. The [[Commodore 64]] and ZX Spectrum also allowed players with the proper cartridges or [[Multiface]] add-on to freeze the running program, enter POKEs, and resume. Some games tried to detect the Multiface, and refused to load if it was present. The earliest models had no ability to &quot;hide&quot;. Later revisions either included a switch, hid if you opened and closed the menu before loading the game, or automatically hid.

For instance, with &quot;&lt;code&gt;POKE 47196,201&lt;/code&gt;&quot; in ''[[Knight Lore]]'' for the ZX Spectrum, immunity is achieved. Magazines such as ''[[CRASH (magazine)|CRASH]]'' regularly featured lists of such [[PEEK and POKE|POKE]] instructions for games. In order to find them a [[software cracker]] had to interpret the [[machine code]] and locate the critical point where the number of lives is decreased, impacts detected, etc. Sometimes the term POKE was used with this specific meaning.

Cheating was exploited by technology-oriented players due to the difficulty of early cheats. However, a cheat industry emerged as gaming systems evolved, through the packaging and selling of cheating as a product.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.atarimagazines.com/v7n10/productreviews.html | title=Celebrity Cookbook, Cheat!|journal=Antic|month=February|year=1989|volume=7|issue=10|page=p.57}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cheat-enablers such as cheat books, game guides, cheat cartridges helped form a cheat industry and cemented cheating as part of gaming culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=11153 | publisher=MIT | accessdate=2007-01-03 | author=Mia Consalvo | title=Cheating:Gaining Advantage in Videogames}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, cheating was not universally accepted in early gaming; gaming magazine ''[[Amiga Power]]'' condemned cheaters, taking the stance that cheating was not part of their philosophy of fairness. They also applied this in reverse; games should also not be allowed to cheat the player.

Later, cheating grew more popular with magazines, websites, and even a television show, [[Cheat!]], dedicated to listing cheats and walkthroughs for consoles and computer systems. POKE cheats were replaced by trainers and cheat codes. Generally, the majority of cheat codes on modern day systems are implemented not by gamers, but by [[video game developer|game developer]]s. Some say that as many people do not have the time to complete a video game on their own, cheats are needed to make a game more accessible and appealing to a casual gamer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://vgstrategies.about.com/od/basicgamingtipstricks/a/whyusecheats.htm | publisher=The New York Times Company | accessdate=2007-01-03 | author=Jason Rybka | title=Why Use Cheats and Codes for Console and PC Games?}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the rise in popularity of gaming, cheating using external software and hardware raised a number of copyright legal issues related to modifying game code.

Many modern games have removed cheat codes entirely, save for uses to unlock certain secret bonuses. The usage of real-time achievement tracking made it unfair for any one player to cheat. In online multiplayer games, cheating is frowned upon and disallowed, often leading to a [[&amp;b|ban]]. However, certain games may unlock single-player cheats if the player fulfills a certain condition. Yet other games, such as those using the [[Source engine]], allow developer consoles to be used to activate a wide variety of cheats in single-player or by server administrators.

==Cheat codes==
The most basic type of cheat code is one created by the game designers and hidden within the [[video game]] itself, that will cause any type of uncommon effect that is not part of the usual game mechanics.&lt;ref name=&quot;sezen&quot;&gt;{{cite paper|title=FROM OZANS TO GOD-MODES: CHEATING IN INTERACTIVE ENTERTAINMENT FROM DIFFERENT CULTURES|author=Sezen, Tonguc Ibrahim|coauthors=Isikoglu, Digdem|url=http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/mit5/papers/sezen_isikoglu.pdf|date=2007-04-27|page=8|accessdate=2009-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Activation methods for cheat codes might include entering a code at a password prompt or a pressing a combination of [[game controller]] buttons,&lt;ref name=&quot;ingame&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Ecology of Games: Connecting Youth, Games, and Learning, Pages|pages=41–46|chapter=In-Game, In-Room, In-World: Reconnecting Video Game Play to the Rest of Kids’ Lives.|url=http://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1162/dmal.9780262693646.041|editor=Katie Salen|series=The John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation Series on Digital Media and Learning|publisher=Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008|doi=10.1162/dmal.9780262693646.041|author=Stevens, Reed, Tom Satwicz, and Laurie McCarthy}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as &quot;[[The Konami Code]]&quot;, or by [[password]]s that can be typed in to get the desired effect or bring up a cheat menu. Other entry points may be a developer console, a code entry dialog, at title screens, or in-game. Effects might include unlocking a character or improving a character's performance: for example providing a car with greater acceleration&lt;ref name=&quot;ingame&quot;/&gt; or the [[God mode]] in [[Doom (video game)|Doom]] which makes the player invulnerable; or visual gags with no practical purpose, such as &quot;Tutu Qwark&quot; in [[Ratchet &amp; Clank: Up Your Arsenal]].

Unlike other cheating methods, cheat codes are implemented by the game developers themselves,&lt;ref name=&quot;sezen&quot;/&gt; often as a tool to playtest certain aspects of the game without difficulty. One of the earliest known examples of this type of cheat is the [[Konami Code]], created in 1986 by Konami developer [[Kazuhisa Hashimoto]] as he worked on [[porting]] the 1985 arcade game ''[[Gradius]]'' for use on the [[Nintendo Entertainment System]]. Hashimoto is quoted as saying &quot;The arcade version of Gradius is really difficult, right? I never played it that much, and there was no way I could finish the game, so I inserted the so-called Konami code.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?cId=3108751&amp;did=1 |title= Cracking the Code: The Konami Code |publisher= 1up.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modification of run time game data==
Cheating can easily be achieved by modifying the game's data while it is running. These methods of cheating are often less reliable than cheat codes included into a game by its creators. This is due to the fact that certain programming styles or quirks of internal game logic, different release versions of a game, or even using the same game at different times or on different hardware, may result in different memory usage and hence the trainer program might have no effect, or stop the game from running altogether.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Game trainers and cheats|url=http://www.gamew0rld.com/category/trainer/}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Memory editing===
Cheating via memory editing involves modifying the memory values where the game keeps its status information. This can be achieved in a range of different ways depending of the game's running environment. The way to achieve this will vary depending on the environment in which the game is running.

====Memory editing hardware====

{{Main|Cheat cartridge}}
A cheat cartridge is attached to an interface port on a home computer or console. It allows a user to modify the game code either before or during its execution. An early example is the [[Multiface]] for the ZX Spectrum, and almost every format since has had a cheat cartridge created for it; such as [[Datel]]'s range of [[Action Replay]] devices. Another popular example of this is [[Game Genie]] for [[Sega Genesis]], [[Nintendo Entertainment System|NES]], [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|Super Nintendo]], [[Game Boy]], and [[Sega Game Gear|Game Gear]] game consoles. Modern disc-based cheat hardware include [[GameShark]] and Code Breaker which modify game code from a large database of cheats. In later generation consoles, cheat cartridges have come to be replaced by cheat discs that usually contain a game loader and, used to boot the console, modify the console's memory environment previous to the loading of the actual game disc.

The legality of this type of devices has been questioned, having raised a particular case named ''[[Lewis Galoob Toys, Inc. v. Nintendo of America, Inc.]]'', in which [[Nintendo]] unsuccessfully sued [[Galoob|Lewis Galoob Toys]] stating that its cheating device, the [[Game Genie]], created [[derivative work]]s of games and violated [[copyright|copyright law]].

====Memory editing software====
The most basic way of achieving this is by means of memory editor software, which allows you to directly edit the numeric values in a certain memory address. This kind of software usually includes a feature that allows you to perform memory searches to aid the user to locate the memory areas where known values (such as the amount of lives, score or health level) are located. Provided a memory address, a memory editor may also be able to &quot;freeze&quot; it, preventing the game from altering the information stored at that memory address.

Game trainers are a special type of memory editor, in which the program comes with predefined functions to modify the [[run time (program lifecycle phase)|run time]] memory of a specific [[computer game]].&lt;ref name = &quot;about&quot;&gt;[http://vgstrategies.about.com/od/strategyglossary/g/Trainers.htm &quot;Trainers&quot;] at About.com's Video Game Strategies&lt;/ref&gt; When distributed, trainers often have a single + and a number appended to their title, representing the number of modifications the trainer has available.&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot;/&gt;

In the 1980s and 1990s, trainers were generally integrated straight into the actual game by [[Software cracking|cracking group]]s. When the game was first started, the trainer would typically show a splash screen of its own, sometimes allowing modifications of options related to the trainer, and then proceed to the actual game. In the cracker group release lists and intros, trained games were marked with one or more plus signs after them, one for each option in the trainer, for example: ''&quot;the Mega Krew presents: '''Ms. Astro Chicken++'''&quot;''. 

Many emulators have built-in functionality that allows players to modify data as the game is running, sometimes even emulating cheating hardware such as [[Game Genie]]. Some emulators take this method a step further and allow the player to export and import data edits. Edit templates of many games for a console are collected and redistributed as cheat packs.

Emulators also frequently offer the additional advantage of being able to save the state of the entire emulated machine at any point, effectively allowing saving at any point in a game even when save functionality is not provided by the game itself. Cheating hardware such as &quot;Instant Replay&quot; also allows such behaviour for some consoles.

===Code injection===
Somewhat more unusual than memory editing, code injection consists of the modification of the game's executable code while it is running, for example with the use of [[PEEK and POKE|POKE]] commands. In the case of ''[[Jet Set Willy]]'' on the ZX Spectrum computer, a popular cheat involved replacing a [[Zilog Z80|Z80]] instruction &lt;code&gt;DEC (HL)&lt;/code&gt; in the program (which was responsible for decrementing the number of lives by one) with a &lt;code&gt;[[NOP]]&lt;/code&gt;, effectively granting the player infinite lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.users.globalnet.co.uk/~jg27paw4/yr06/yr06_21.htm | publisher=Future | journal=Your Spectrum | title=Hacking Away: &quot;Jump To It&quot; | accessdate=2007-01-01|issue=6|month=August|year=1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Saved game editors===
Editing a saved game offers an indirect way to modify game data. By modifying a file in persistent storage, it is possible to effectively modify the run time game data that will be restored when the game attempts to load the save game.

[[Hex editor]]s were the most basic means of editing saved game files (e.g. to give the player a large sum of money in strategy games such as ''[[Dune II]]''). However, as happened with game editors, dedicated game-editing utilities soon became available, including functions to effortlessly edit saved data for specific games, rendering hex editing largely obsolete for this purpose.

===Network traffic forgery===
A similar method for cheating in online games involves editing packets in the outbound network traffic, thus affecting the state of the game. Although this method was more common a few years ago, games are developed with more robustness to prevent network and packet modifications.

==Unusual effects==
Cheat codes may sometimes produce unusual or interesting effects which don't necessarily make the game easier to play. For example, one cheat in ''[[Jurassic Park: Operation Genesis]]'' makes dinosaurs appear '[[undead]]'. In other games, a cheat may make the game harder to play; for instance one could give the enemy special abilities, add a harder difficulty, make neutral bystanders attack the player or grant the player a disadvantage such as low health points or instant death. In a few games the player is humorously penalized if they use cheat codes originally for another game; for example, using cheat codes from ''[[Doom (video game)|Doom]]'' in ''[[Descent (video game)|Descent]]'' would result in a sarcastic message from the programmers on screen. Similar effects also occurred if codes from ''Descent'' were attempted to be used in its sequels. The game ''[[Heretic (computer game)|Heretic]]'' played on ''Doom''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s codes gives the complete opposite of the desired effect, such as instant death instead of invulnerability or stripping weapons instead of providing them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cheats.ign.com/ob2/068/003/003678.html|title=Heretic cheats|publisher=IGN|accessdate=2009-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Doom 3]] if the user types in the cheat &quot;IDDQD&quot; from the original game, a message appears saying &quot;Your memory serves you well.&quot;,
Or,displaying the word BALONGA! on the exit door in portal 1 and 2 with only 30 seconds to turn off the cheat(s) before you die.

Other unusual cheats found regularly in games include &quot;big-head mode&quot; (in ''[[GoldenEye 007 (1997 video game)|GoldenEye 007]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.cheats.ign.com/ob2/068/001/001991.html|title=GoldenEye 007 Cheats|publisher=IGN|accessdate=2008-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; or ''[[Oni (video game)|Oni]]'', for example), switching weapons for other objects, and codes to change the colors of characters.

Some games allow the player to enter a code to change what the character is wearing or to change the character itself, but not enhance the progress of the game. For example, most of the Grand Theft Auto games allow the player to enter a code to make the character change into an [[non-player character|NPC]]. Another unusual cheat code in the Grand Theft Auto games is the ability to make the people of the town start rioting, or hold weapons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://uk.gamespot.com/ps2/action/gta4/hints.html |title=Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas Cheat Codes |accessdate=2007-08-12 |work=Gamespot UK }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Easter egg (virtual)#Computer-related Easter eggs|Easter egg]]s are a related feature, although such hidden content has no impact on gameplay.

==Counter-cheating measures==
In games having attainable achievements or [[high score]] records, or both, cheats by nature allow the player to attain achievements too easily or score point totals not attainable by a non-cheating player. In some games, [[Audio commentary#Video games|developer commentary]] mode can have the same effect because these games, in an effort to make all commented-on scenarios accessible to the player, render a player invulnerable to damage while in commentary mode.

===Barriers to game completion===
* The [[Sega 32X]] version of [[Doom (video game)|Doom]] does not allow the player to finish the game if any cheat codes were used; instead, after a cheating player defeats the game's penultimate level, the game simulates a program exit to [[MS-DOS|DOS]] and displays a mock [[Command-line interface#Command prompt|command prompt]] (&quot;C:\&gt;&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://faqs.ign.com/articles/368/368956p1.html Doom Cheat Codex – IGN FAQs]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Some PC games and most [[Xbox]] games do not record player achievements if they are attained while cheat mode is activated. For example, ''[[Half-Life 2: Episode 2]]'' turns this barrier into a continuing obstacle if a player saves the game with cheats activated: The game will record that fact in the save file and automatically cause subsequent reloads from the relevant save file to reactivate cheat mode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.faqs.ign.com/mail/2006-09-01.html|title=Game Help Q&amp;A 2006 September 1|work=IGN|accessdate=2009-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In Ricochet Infinity, if a player cheats at all, their score will be set to zero, the message &quot;You are Cheating&quot; appears in the message box,and your progress after cheating will not be recorded.

===Penalties to player performance===
* Entry of [[Wolfenstein 3-D]]'s &quot;ILM&quot; code provides a player with the maximum possible lives, weapons, and ammunition but in the process resets a player's score to zero.{{cn|date=April 2011}}
* If a player of [[Battlefield 1942]] makes a mistake while entering a cheat code, the error triggers an algorithm that either makes the player automatically lose or gives the enemy the performance enhancements the player is attempting to obtain. The risk of incurring this cost varies with the player's memory and dexterity.{{cn|date=April 2011}}
* If a player of Raven Software game [[Heretic (video game)|Heretic]] tries to cheat by entering the God code from [[Doom (video game)|Doom]], the game kills the player and displays the message &quot;Trying to cheat, are you? Now you die!&quot;. If the player enters the Weapons Cheat code from Doom, the player loses all weapons acquired, is given a [[Magic wand|Staff]] as its new weapon  with the message &quot;Cheater, you don't deserve any weapons.&quot; displaying on screen. {{cn|date=April 2011}}
* If a player of [[Pokémon Ruby and Sapphire]] uses a cheating device to obtain [[Mew (Pokémon)|Mew]] or Deoxys, the Pokémon will not obey its trainer, no matter how many gym badges the player has.{{cn|date=April 2011}}
* If a player in [[Unreal]] uses an &quot;Admin Set&quot; command, they will need to restart Unreal to enter any online server.

===Disclaimers regarding player achievement===
* If a player of [[Portal (video game)|Portal]] has any cheat(s) activated when s/he completes a chamber in Challenge mode, the game will display &quot;CHEATED!&quot; above the performance summary screen for that level. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cheatcodes.com/portal-pc-cheats/|title=Portal Cheats on CheatCodes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tyrian (video game)|Tyrian]] displays the message &quot;Cheaters always prosper&quot; on the bottom of the score screen.{{cn|date=April 2011}}
* [[MechWarrior 3]] makes its cheat modes readily available as standard game options (as opposed to, ''e.g.'', requiring the entry of a &quot;secret&quot; code) but labels these game options &quot;dishonorable,&quot; a reference to the code of honor shared by the game's rival clans.{{cn|date=April 2011}}
* In [[Grand Theft Auto: Vice City]], entering a cheat code to spawn vehicles will reduce the player's criminal rating. If this drops below zero   cheat-related messages are displayed. Other cheats may render the game extremely difficult, such as enabling the 'pedestrians carry weapons' along with the 'pedestrians hate you' cheat and saving. The game will notify you if you attempt to save with gameplay-altering cheats enabled, as they will remain saved with the game if the player does save.{{cn|date=April 2011}}
* [[Sanctum (2011 video game)|Sanctum]] displays a message after each wave showing you cheated if you use any kind of cheating meassure, and disables scores and achievement until you restart the game.

==Cheating in online games==
{{Main|Cheating in online games}}

Cheating exists in many [[multiplayer game|multiplayer online computer games]]. While there have always been cheat codes and other ways to make single player games easier, developers often attempt to prevent it in multiplayer games. With the release of the first popular internet multiplayer games cheating took on new dimensions. Previously it was rather easy to see if the other players cheated, as most games were played on local networks or consoles. The [[Internet]] changed that by increasing the popularity of multiplayer games, giving the players relative anonymity, and giving people an avenue to communicate cheats.

Examples of cheats in FPS games include the [[aimbot]], which assists the player in aiming at the target, giving the user an unfair advantage, the [[wallhack]], which allows a player to see through solid or opaque objects or manipulate or remove textures, and [[Cheating in online games#ESP|ESP]], with which the information of other players is displayed.

In role-playing games, [[twinking]], the practice of passing on valuable items not normally available at player's character's level, may be considered cheating.

In [[Massively multiplayer online game|online multiplayer games]], players may use [[macro (computer science)|macro scripts]], which automate player actions, to automatically find items or defeat enemies for the player's advantage. The prevalence of [[massively multiplayer online game]]s (MMORPGs) such as ''World of Warcraft'', ''Anarchy Online'', ''EverQuest'', ''Guild Wars'', and ''RuneScape'' has resulted in the trading of in-game currency for real world currency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.cnet.com/2100-1040-832347.html | title=Game exchange dispute goes to court | publisher=CNET | accessdate=2007-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can lead to [[virtual economy|virtual economies]]. The rise of virtual economies has led to cheating where a gamer uses macros to gain large amounts of ingame money which the player will then trade for real cash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.devmaster.net/articles/mmorpg-postmortem/part2.php | title=Eternal Lands' MMORPG Postmortem: Mistakes and Lessons, Part II | publisher=DevMaster | accessdate=2007-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Terms of Service of most modern online games now specifically prohibit the transfer of accounts or sale of in-game items for 'real-world' money.

Whilst games cannot prevent cheating in [[single-player]] modes, cheating in online games is common on public [[game server]]s. Some online games, such as ''[[Battlefield 1942]],'' include specific features to counter [[exploit (online gaming)|cheating exploits]], by incorporating tools such as ''[[PunkBuster]]'', ''[[GameGuard|nProtect GameGuard]]'', or ''VAC'' ([[Valve Anti-Cheat]]). However, much like anti-virus companies; anti-cheat tools are constantly and consistently bypassed until further updates force cheat creators to find new methods to bypass the protection.

== See also ==
* [[Cheating]]
* [[Difficulty level]]
* [[Glitching]]
* [[God mode]]
* [[Twinking]]
* [[Mod (computer gaming)]]
* [[PEEK and POKE#POKEs as cheats|POKEs as cheats]]
* [[Strategy guide]]
* [[Cheat Engine]]

==External links==
*[http://www.GameHacking.org GameHacking.org] A site with some information and resources related to RAM and ROM hacking.
*[http://www.dmoz.org/Games/Video_Games/Cheats_and_Hints/ Open Directory – Games: Video Games: Cheats and Hints] at [[dmoz.org]]
*[http://dir.yahoo.com/Recreation/Games/Video_Games/Cheats__Hints__and_Codes/ Video Game Cheats, Hints, and Codes] at [[yahoo.com]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

[[Category:Video game cheating| ]]

[[de:Cheat]]
[[es:Cheats]]
[[gl:Trainer]]
[[it:Trucco (videogiochi)]]
[[he:צ'יט]]
[[ja:チート]]
[[ru:Трейнер (игры)]]
[[fi:Traineri]]
[[th:การโกงเกม]]
[[zh:游戏作弊]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
