<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="468224" ns="0" title="Catskill Mountains"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Geobox|Range
| name                        =Catskill Mountains
| image                       =Central Catskills from Twin south summit.jpg
| image_size                  =300
| image_caption               =[[Slide Mountain (Ulster County, New York)|Slide Mountain]] and the peaks around it as seen from Twin Mountain in the northern Catskills.
| country                     =United States
| state                       =[[New York]]
| region                      =[[Hudson Valley]]
| region1                     =
| district_type               =[[County (US)|Counties]]
| district                    =[[Ulster County, New York|Ulster]]
| district1                   =[[Greene County, New York|Greene]]
| district2                   =[[Sullivan County, New York|Sullivan]]
| district3                   =[[Delaware County, New York|Delaware]]
| district4                   =[[Schoharie County, New York|Schoharie]]
| city_type                   =Communities
| city                        =[[Hunter (village), New York|Hunter]]
| city1                       =[[Tannersville, New York|Tannersville]]
| city2                       =[[Monticello, New York|Monticello]]
| city3                       =[[Liberty (village), New York|Liberty]]
| unit                        =[[Appalachian Mountains|Appalachian]]
| unit1                       =[[Allegheny Plateau]]
| border                      =[[Pocono Mountains|Poconos]]
| border1                     =[[Shawangunk Ridge]]
| geology                     =[[Sedimentary]]
| geology1                    =
| period                      =[[Devonian]]
| period1                     =[[Mississippian]]
| orogeny                     =
| orogeny1                    =
| area                        =15259
| length_imperial             =111
| length_orientation          =N/S
| width_imperial              =102
| width_orientation           =E/W
| highest                =[[Slide Mountain (Ulster County, New York)|Slide Mountain]]
| highest location            =S of [[Shandaken, New York|Shandaken]]
| highest_country             =
| highest_state               =
| highest_region              =
| highest_district            =[[Ulster County, New York|Ulster]]
| highest_elevation_imperial  =4154
| highest_lat_d               =41
| highest_lat_m               =59
| highest_lat_s               =55
| highest_lat_NS              =N
| highest_long_d              =74
| highest_long_m              =23
| highest_long_s              =11
| highest_long_EW             =W
| lowest                 =
| lowest_location             =
| lowest_country              =
| lowest_state                =
| lowest_region               =
| lowest_district             =
| lowest_elevation_imperial   =
| lowest_lat_d                =
| lowest_lat_m                =
| lowest_lat_s                =
| lowest_lat_NS               =
| lowest_long_d               =
| lowest_long_m               =
| lowest_long_s               =
| lowest_long_EW              =
| free_type                   =
| free                  =
| map                         =NortheastAppalachiansMap.jpg
| map_size                    =300
| map_caption                 =Map of the main regions of the northeast Appalachians, with the Catskills as &quot;C&quot;.
| map_first                   =
}}
The '''Catskill Mountains''', an area in [[New York|New York State]] northwest of [[New York City]] and southwest of [[Albany, New York|Albany]], are a mature [[dissected plateau]], an uplifted region that was subsequently eroded into sharp [[Terrain|relief]]. They are an eastward continuation, and the highest representation, of the [[Allegheny Plateau]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cc-gis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catskillcenter.org/atlas/geomorphology/geo_1_3dtopography.htm|title=REGIONAL TOPOGRAPHY|work=Catskills GIS Atlas|publisher=Catskill Center|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are sometimes considered an extension of the [[Appalachian Mountains]] into [[Upstate New York]], although they are not geologically related. The Catskills are west of the [[Hudson River]] and lie within the bounds of six [[county (US)|counties]] ([[Otsego County, New York|Otsego]], [[Delaware County, New York|Delaware]], [[Sullivan County, New York|Sullivan]], [[Schoharie County, New York|Schoharie]], [[Greene County, New York|Greene]], and [[Ulster County, New York|Ulster]]). The Catskill Mountains are also considered a [[Physiographic regions of the world|physiographic section]] of the larger [[Appalachian Plateau]] province, which in turn is part of the larger [[Appalachian Mountains|Appalachian]] physiographic division.&lt;ref name=&quot;USGS-Water&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Physiographic divisions of the conterminous U. S. | publisher = U.S. Geological Survey | url = http://water.usgs.gov/GIS/metadata/usgswrd/XML/physio.xml | accessdate = 2007-12-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The mountains lie within the [[Allegheny Highlands forests]] [[ecoregion]].

==Geography==

At the eastern end of the range the [[mountains]] begin quite dramatically with the [[Catskill Escarpment]] rising up suddenly from the [[Hudson Valley]]. The western boundary is far less certain, as the mountains gradually decline in height and grade into the rest of the [[Allegheny Plateau]]. Nor is there a consensus on where the Catskills end to the north or south, with it being certain only that by the time one reaches either [[Interstate 88 (east)|I-88]], the [[Delaware River]] or the [[Shawangunk Ridge]] that one is no longer in the Catskills.

In these peripheral regions, whether you are in the Catskills seems to be a matter of personal preference, as an old saying in the region seems to suggest — &quot;When you have two rocks for every dirt, you are in the Catskills.&quot;

Many visitors, including owners of weekend or vacation homes in the region, seem to consider almost anything sufficiently rural west of the Hudson yet within a short drive of New York City to be in the Catskills.

[[The Poconos]], to the immediate southwest in [[Pennsylvania]], are technically a continuation of the Catskills under a different name. The Catskills contain [[Catskill High Peaks|more than thirty peaks above 3,500 feet]] and parts of six important rivers. The highest mountain, [[Slide Mountain (New York)|Slide Mountain]] in Ulster County, has an elevation of 4,180 feet (1,274 m).

Within the range is the [[Catskill Park]], part of [[Forest Preserve (New York)|New York's Forest Preserve]]. Not all the land is publicly owned; about 60% remains in private hands, but new sections are added frequently. Most of the park and the preserve are within Ulster County; however Greene County accounts for a significant portion as well and there are areas in Sullivan and Delaware counties too.

==Geology==
[[Image:Kaaterskill Falls.jpg|thumb|[[Kaaterskill Falls]] on Spruce Creek near Palenville, New York. One of the higher falls in New York. Two separate falls total {{convert|260|ft|m|0|abbr=on}}]]
The history of the Catskill Mountains is a geologic story come full circle, from erosion, deposition and uplift back to erosion. The Catskill Mountains are more of a [[dissected plateau]] than a series of mountain ranges. The sediments that make up the rocks in the Catskills were deposited when the ancient Acadian Mountains in the east were rising and subsequently eroding. The sediments traveled westward and formed a great delta into the sea that was in the area at that time.

The eastern escarpment of the Catskill Mountains is near the former (landward) edge of this delta, as the sediments deposited in the northeastern areas along the escarpment were deposited above sea level by moving rivers and the Acadian Mountains were located roughly where the [[Taconic Mountains|Taconics]] are located today (though significantly larger). The further west you travel, the finer the sediment that was deposited and thus the rocks change from gravel conglomerates to sandstones and shales. Even further west, these fresh water deposits intermingle with shallow marine sandstones and shales until the end in deeper water limestones.

The uplift and erosion of the Acadian Mountains was occurring during the [[Devonian]] and early [[Mississippian]] period (395 to 325 million years ago). Over that time, thousands of feet of these sediments built up, slowly moving the Devonian seashore further and further west. A meteor impact occurred in the shallow sea approximately 375 [[mya (unit)|mya]] creating a {{convert|10|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} diameter crater. This crater eventually filled with sediments and became [[Panther Mountain Crater|Panther Mountain]] through the process of uplift and erosion.

By the middle of the Mississippian period, the uplift stopped and the Acadian Mountains had been eroded so much that sediments no longer flowed across the Catskill Delta.

Over time the sediments were buried by more sediments from other areas until the original Devonian and Mississippian sediments were deeply buried and slowly became solid rock. Then the entire area experienced uplift, which caused the sedimentary rocks to begin to erode. Today, those upper sedimentary rocks have been completely removed, allowing the Devonian and Mississippian rocks to be exposed. Today’s Catskills are a result of the continued erosion of these rocks, both by streams and in the recent past by glaciers.
[[Image:Platte Clove.jpg|thumb|left|[[Platte Clove]], a break in the Escarpment created by glacial action.]]
Some traces of the most recent sedimentary layers remain for the discerning eye to discover, however. Even along the glacially-scoured eastern escarpment and in the upper Hudson Valley just below it—not to mention the glacial till-dumps and occasional terminal moraines of the southern-facing mountain slopes and valleys of the eastern and central Catskills—fragments of quartzite ranging from bright white, banded orange and tan, to deep red and dark gray are found. Many if not most of these are no more than 6&quot; thick, have two flat sides and are without inclusions of other native rock, e.g., gray or blue sandstone (&quot;bluestone&quot;), most likely indicating the presence of a shallow, wave-beaten sandy delta or beach area at the base of the Acadian ranges in the delta's final stages of sedimentation. That sand layer, mostly free of silt (hence less opaque than older layers formed with higher concentrations of silt and mud under deeper water at more remote reaches of the delta) formed one or more upper layers of the delta. With compression and time, thin layers of sandstone formed of which only the here-mentioned fragments of sandstone remain now though in comparative abundance, if one measures their frequency against those of glacial erratics of similar size and shape which are typically metamorphic in origin (e.g., feldspars, granites, basalts), which most likely originated in the geologically complex region of the Adirondacks to the north. Such sandstones and erratics are frequently found collocated in cairns and other anomalous rock arrangements of the Eastern Catskills.

In successive Ice Ages, both valley and continental glaciers have widened the valleys and the notches of the Catskills and rounded the mountains. Grooves and scratches in exposed bedrock provides evidence of the great sheets of ice that once traversed through the region. Even today the erosion of the mountains continue, with the region’s rivers and streams deepening and widening the mountains’ valleys and cloves.

==Transportation==
From 1872, the Catskills were served by the Catskill Mountain Branch of the [[Ulster and Delaware Railroad]] (which was absorbed into the [[New York Central]] railroad in 1932). Passenger rail service continued until 1954. Part of the line still exists but now serves only freight.
[[File:Udmap.jpg|thumb|right|thumb]]

[[New York State Route 28]] serves road vehicle traffic from [[Interstate 87]] at the western edge of [[Kingston, NY|Kingston]]. I-87 opened to road traffic in 1954.&lt;ref&gt;nycroads.com, New York State Thruway: Historic Overview http://www.nycroads.com/roads/thruway/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Name==
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2009}}
[[Image:Catskills beyond Hudson.jpg|thumb|right|Views of the Catskills from the Hudson like this led to the name &quot;Blue Mountains&quot; for a time.]]
The name &quot;Catskills&quot; did not come into wide popular use for the mountains until the mid-19th century — in fact, that name was disparaged by purists as too plebeian, too reminiscent of the area's [[Netherlands|Dutch]] [[Colonialism|colonial]] past, especially since it was used by the local farming population. It may also have been a continuation of the British practice, after taking possession of the colony in the late 17th century, of trying to replace most Dutch [[Knickerbocker]] toponyms in present-day New York with their English alternatives. The locals preferred to call them the '''Blue Mountains''', to harmonize with [[Vermont]]'s [[Green Mountains]] and [[New Hampshire]]'s [[White Mountains (New Hampshire)|White Mountains]]. It was only after [[Washington Irving]]'s stories that Catskills won out over Blue Mountains, and several other competitors.

[[Image:Map-Novi Belgii Novæque Angliæ (Amsterdam, 1685).jpg|thumb|left|A 1656 map of New Netherland showing the locations of the Lands of the Kat Kills and the High Lands of the Esopus]]
Nicolaes Visscher II's 1656 map of New Netherland (left) located the 'Landt van Kats Kill' at the mouth of the Kats Kill ([[Catskill creek]]). The region to the south is identified as 'Hooge Landt van Esopus' (High Lands of the Esopus). This is a reference to a local band northern [[Lenape]] [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] who inhabited the banks of the Hudson and hunted in the high lands along the [[Esopus Creek]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Kudish36–8&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Catskill Forest: A History |last=Kudish |first=Michael |authorlink=Michael Kudish |year=2000 |publisher=Purple Mountain Press |location=[[Fleischmanns, New York|Fleischmanns, NY]] |isbn=1930098022 |pages=47}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the meaning of the name (&quot;cat creek&quot; in [[Dutch language|Dutch]]) and the namer (early Dutch explorers) are settled matters, exactly how and why the area is named is a mystery. [[Mountain lion]]s (catamounts) were known to have been in the area when the Dutch arrived in the 17th century.&lt;ref name=sierraclub&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sierraclub.org/e-files/puma.asp |title=The Elusive Mountain Lion - E-Files - Our History|accessdate=2007-09-17 |work=Sierra Club}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most common, and easiest, is that [[bobcat]]s were seen near [[Catskill creek]] and the present-day [[Catskill (village), New York|village of Catskill]], and the name followed from there. However there is no record of bobcats ever having been seen in significant numbers on the banks of the Hudson, and the name Catskill does not appear on paper until 1655, more than four decades later.

Other theories include:

* A corruption of ''kasteel'', the Dutch sailors' term for the Indian stockades they saw on the riverbank. According to one [[Belgium|Belgian]] authority, ''kat'' occurs in many place names throughout [[Flanders]] and has nothing to do with cats and everything to do with fortifications.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}
* It was named for Dutch poet [[Jacob Cats]], who was also known for his real estate prowess, profiting from [[speculation]] in lands reclaimed from the sea.
* A ship named ''The Cat'' had gone up the Hudson shortly before the name was first used. In nautical slang of the era, ''cat'' could also mean a piece of equipment, or [[catboat|a particular type of small vessel]].
* It has also been suggested that it refers to [[lacrosse]], which Dutch visitors had seen the Iroquois natives play. ''Kat'' can also refer to a [[tennis]] [[racquet|racket]], which a lacrosse stick resembles, and the first place the Dutch saw this, further down the river in the present-day [[Saugerties (town), New York|Town of Saugerties]], they gave the name ''Kaatsbaan'', for &quot;tennis court,&quot; which is still on maps today.
* The [[Mohicans]] roamed the woods of [[New England]] during the 18th century. A Mohican tribe supposedly inhabited the area known as the Catskills today, led by a Mohican chief named Cat.
*When Europeans first arrived in the Catskills, an Native American fort was on the banks of the Catskill. In The [[Netherlands]], the term “Kat” refers to a fortification.

The confusion over the exact origins of the name led over the years to variant spellings such as ''Kaatskill'' and ''Kaaterskill'', both of which are also still used, the former in the regional magazine ''[[Kaatskill Life]]'', the latter as the name of a town, creek, clove, [[Kaaterskill High Peak|mountain]] and [[Kaaterskill Falls|waterfall]].

The supposed Indian name for the range, ''Onteora'' or &quot;land in the sky,&quot; was actually created by a white man in the mid-19th century to drum up business for a resort. It, too, persists today as the name of a school district and as the name of a [[Boy Scout]] summer camp.

==In culture==
[[File:WLA lacma Sanford Robinson Gifford October in the Catskills 1880.jpg|thumb|right|October in the Catskills by [[Sanford Robinson Gifford]].]]
The Catskills are famous in American cultural history for being the site of the so-called [[Borscht Belt]], a [[Jewish]] [[resort]] area where many young Jewish [[Stand-up comedy|stand-up comics]] got their start.

The Catskill mountains and their inhabitants play an important role in the  stories ''[[My Side of the Mountain]]'' and its sequels by [[Jean Craighead George]] and in [[H. P. Lovecraft]]'s &quot;The Lurking Fear&quot; &amp; &quot;Beyond the Wall of Sleep&quot;.

The town of [[Palenville]] located in the Catskills figures in Washington Irving's story as the home of &quot;[[Rip Van Winkle]]&quot;.

The Catskills are mentioned in [[The Band]]'s song &quot;Time to Kill.&quot; The Band was also photographed there for their first album, ''Music from Big Pink'' [http://theband.hiof.no/band_pictures/band_mfbp_back.html The Band in the Catskills].

The Catskills are also mentioned in [[Beck]]'s song &quot;High Five (Rock the Catskills)&quot; on his 1996 album ''[[Odelay]]''.

[[Mercury Rev]]'s song &quot;[[Opus 40]]&quot; on their 1998 album ''[[Deserter's Songs]]'' contains the line &quot;Catskill mansions buried dreams/ I'm alive she cried but I don't know what it means&quot;. The band and their studios are based in the Catskills, and the area is often referred to in interview.

The Catskills are mentioned as well in Pela's song &quot;[[Rooftops (Moth Song Outro)]]&quot; on their 2007 album ''[[Anytown Graffiti]]''.

Much of the [[frame story]] of [[Art Spiegelman]]'s award-winning [[graphic novel]] ''[[Maus]]'' is set in the Catskills.  ''Maus II'' is subtitled ''And Here My Troubles Began (From [[Auschwitz|Mauschwitz]] to the Catskills and Beyond)''.

A [[Home Box Office]] miniseries is planned that will dramatize the a [[New York magazine]] article on [[natural gas]] drillers coming to the region. [[Richard Russo]], a winner of the [[Pulitzer Prize]], is writing a script for the project.&lt;ref name='HBO-gas'&gt;{{cite news | first=Nellie | last=Andreeva | coauthors= |authorlink= | title=HBO taps scribe for Catskills drama | date=2009-09-07 | publisher= | url =http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/television/news/e3i27b2ea26515fca07a4d6673609adfad0 | work =The Hollywood Reporter | pages = | accessdate = 2009-09-12 | language = }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The town of Bethel, New York, located in the Catskills was home to the famous Woodstock Music festival in 1969

The 1973 novel ''Nickel Mountain: A Pastoral Novel'' by [[John Gardner (novelist)|John Gardner]] takes place in the Catskill Mountains.

===Films set, or filmed in, the Catskills===
* UPDATED LIST of FILMS set in the Hudson Valley / Catskills Region: (kept up to date by the Hudson Valley Film Commission): [http://hudsonvalleyfilmcommission.org/films.html]
* The Tears of Julian Po (1997) Christian Slater - filmed in Fleischmanns
*''99 Geiger Road''  [http://www.99geigerroad.com] 2007 - Documentary about a bungalow colony of Holocaust survivors
* ''[[The Cake Eaters]]'' (2007)
*''[[Casper Meets Wendy]]'' (1995) Wendy and her aunts run into Casper and his uncles at a resort in the Catskills.
*''The Catskill Chainsaw Redemption'' (2004) A horror movie.
*The hit [[1987 in film|1987]] film ''[[Dirty Dancing]]'' was set in a Catskills resort in the summer of 1963 (though filmed at [[Mountain Lake (Virginia)|Mountain Lake]] in [[Virginia]] and at [[Lake Lure]] in [[North Carolina]].)
*''[http://fourseasonsdocumentary.com  Four Seasons Documentary]'' (2006 - in production) Follows the lives of [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]] survivors in a [[Borscht Belt]] colony
*''The Gig'' (1985) Director: Frank D. Gilroy, character study, amateur musicians get a gig.
*''[[Goyband]]'' (2008) ''[[Dirty Dancing]]'' meets ''[[My Big Fat Greek Wedding]]'' with a touch of ''[[Fiddler on the Roof]]''.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}
* ''[[Having Wonderful Time]]'' (1938) [[Red Skelton]]'s first movie, set in a Catskills hotel.
* ''Heavy'' (1995) An independent film starring Liv Tyler, Debbie Harry, Pruitt Taylor Vince, Shelley Winters, and Joe Grifasi was filmed partially in the southern Catskills in [[Barryville, New York|Barryville]] and Highland Lake.
*''[[Kaaterskill Falls (film)|Kaaterskill Falls]]'' ([[2001 in film|2001]])  Award-winning independent film about a young urban couple befriending a local hitchhiker.  Mountain country version of [[Roman Polanski]]'s ''[[Knife in the Water (film)|Knife in the Water]]''. (Actually filmed in the Catskills.)
*''[[Manny &amp; Lo]]'' ([[1996 in film|1996]])
*''[[Martha Marcy May Marlene]]'' ([[2011 in film|2011]]) Critically acclaimed film about a young woman who escapes from a cult in the Catskills.
*&quot;[[My Side Of The Mountain]]&quot; A young boy tests his survival skills by living about 2 years in the Catskill Mountains.
*''[[Rip Van Winkle]]'' (1921) Silent film version of the classic story
*''Stagedoor'' (2006) Documentary on life at a teen camp
*''Sweet Lorraine'' ([[1987 in film|1987]]) story of an aging Catskill resort in its last days, filmed at the former Heiden Hotel in [[South Fallsburg, New York|South Fallsburg]].
*''[[Taking Woodstock]]'' (2009) -- The story of how [[Elliot Tiber]] helped bring the [[Woodstock Festival]] to [[Bethel, New York]].
*''[[Magic (1978 film)|Magic]]'', the 1978 film starring Anthony Hopkins is set in the Catskills.
*''[[Tootsie]]'' (1982) - Features scenes in the &quot;Hurley Mountain Inn&quot; located in [[Ulster County, New York|Ulster County]].
* Parts of the movie ''[[Transamerica (film)|Transamerica]]'' (2005) starring [[Felicity Huffman]] were filmed in [[Callicoon (town), New York|Callicoon]] though in the movie it's referred to as Callicoon, Kentucky.
*''[[A Walk on the Moon]]'' ([[1999 in film|1999]]) Set in [[Sullivan County, New York|Sullivan County]], but filmed in [[Quebec]], Canada.
* Part of the movie [[War of the Worlds (2005 film)|''War of the Worlds'']] was filmed in [[Athens (town), New York|Athens]] at the foot of the Catskills (the burning train and ferry scene)
*''WaterFall in the Catskills'' (1897, the Edison Studio)
*''[[Wendigo (film)|Wendigo]]'' (2001) Filmed in West Shokan and [[Phoenicia, New York|Phoenicia]] area. Starred [[Maureen Stapleton]].
*''[[Woodstock (film)|Woodstock]]'', a 1970 documentary about the [[Woodstock Festival]] of 1969, was filmed at the festival in [[Bethel, New York|Bethel]].
*''[[You Can Count on Me]]'' ([[2000 in film|2000]]) Award-winning independent film set in the village of [[Scottsville, New York|Scottsville]], in [[western New York]] near [[Rochester, New York|Rochester]], but filmed in the Catskills, in and around [[Margaretville, New York|Margaretville]] and [[Phoenicia, New York|Phoenicia]].

== See also ==
*[[Helderberg Escarpment]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}
&lt;!--For ease of standardization, use a citation template from http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Template_messages/Sources_of_articles#Citations_of_generic_sources
--&gt;

== Further reading ==
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.2307/198709
| issn = 01905929
| volume = 39
| issue = 4
| pages = 193–201
| last = Heilprin
| first = Angelo
| title = The Catskill Mountains
| journal = Bulletin of the American Geographical Society
| year = 1907
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=rGs9AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA193&amp;lpg=PA193&amp;dq=The+Catskill+Mountains+Angelo+Heilprin#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Catskill%20Mountains%20Angelo%20Heilprin&amp;f=false
| jstor = 198709
}}
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.2307/2422746
| issn = 00030031
| volume = 68
| issue = 2
| pages = 409–23
| last = McIntosh
| first = Robert P.
| title = The forest cover of the Catskill Mountain region, New York, as indicated by land survey records
| journal = American Midland Naturalist
| year = 1962
| jstor = 2422746
}}
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.2307/1942261
| volume = 42
| issue = 2
| pages = 143–61
| last = McIntosh
| first = Robert P.
| title = Forests of the Catskill Mountains, New York
| journal = Ecological Monographs
| year = 1972
| jstor = 1942261
}}
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.2307/1933844
| issn = 00129658
| volume = 45
| issue = 2
| pages = 314–26
| last = McIntosh
| first = R. P.
| coauthors = R. T. Hurley
| title = The spruce-fir forests of the Catskill Mountains
| journal = Ecology
| year = 1964
| jstor = 1933844
}}
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.1086/621285
| issn = 00221376
| volume = 14
| issue = 2
| pages = 113–21
| last = Rich
| first = John Lyon
| title = Local glaciation in the Catskill Mountains
| journal = The Journal of Geology
| year = 1906
}}
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.2307/773655
| issn = 15436322
| volume = 17
| issue = 1
| pages = 30–43
| last = Shepard
| first = Paul
| title = Paintings of the New England landscape: a scientist looks at their geomorphology
| journal = College Art Journal
| year = 1957
| jstor = 773655
}}
*{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.1890/1051-0761(2000)010[0528:TEOLFO]2.0.CO;2
| issn = 10510761
| volume = 10
| issue = 2
| pages = 528–40
| last = Weathers
| first = K. C.
| coauthors = G. M. Lovett, G. E. Likens, R. Lathrop
| title = The effect of landscape features on deposition to Hunter Mountain, Catskill Mountains, New York
| journal = Ecological Applications
| year = 2000
}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Catskill Mountains}}
*[http://www.catskill-3500-club.org/ Hiking Guide to Catskill High Peaks] Catskill 3500 Club
*[http://www.catskillcamps.com History of Catskill Mountains Sleepaway Camps]
*[http://www.catskillmountainclub.org Website for the Catskill Mountain Club hiking]
*[http://www.catskillarchive.com The Catskill Archive - History of the Catskill Mountains]
*[http://www.catskillmtn.org The Catskill Mountain Foundation]
*[http://www.catskillcenter.org The Catskill Center]
*[http://www.cwconline.org The Catskill Watershed Corporation]
*[http://www.catskillsearch.com/site/category/gallery/ Catskill Region Photo Gallery]
*[http://www.catskillmountainkeeper.org/ Catskill Mountainkeeper] Protecting the Six Counties of the Catskills
*[http://www.hvdirectory.com/ Catskill Mountain Businesses listed on Hudson Valley Directory]

{{New York}}
{{Capital District}}

[[Category:Catskills| ]]
[[Category:Physiographic sections]]
[[Category:Dutch loanwords]]
[[Category:Geography of Delaware County, New York]]
[[Category:Geography of Greene County, New York]]
[[Category:Geography of Otsego County, New York]]
[[Category:Geography of Schoharie County, New York]]
[[Category:Geography of Sullivan County, New York]]
[[Category:Geography of Ulster County, New York]]

[[ca:Catskill Mountains]]
[[da:Catskill Mountains]]
[[de:Catskill Mountains]]
[[eo:Katskil-Montaro]]
[[fr:Montagnes Catskill]]
[[id:Pegunungan Catskill]]
[[he:הרי קטסקיל]]
[[ja:キャッツキル山地]]
[[pt:Montanhas Catskill]]
[[ru:Катскилл (горы)]]
[[fi:Catskillvuoret]]
[[sv:Catskillbergen]]
[[yi:קעטסקילס]]
[[zh:卡茲奇山]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
