<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="468899" ns="0" title="Patrick Bateman"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lead too short|date=January 2011}}
{{Original research|date=November 2010}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2010}}
{{Infobox character
| name =
| image       =[[Image:Batemanas.jpg|200px]]
| caption     =[[Christian Bale]] as Bateman in ''[[American Psycho (film)|American Psycho]]''
| first       = ''[[The Rules of Attraction]]''
| last        = ''[[Lunar Park]]''
| creator     = [[Bret Easton Ellis]]
| portrayer   = [[Christian Bale]]&lt;br&gt;(''[[American Psycho (film)|American Psycho]]'') &lt;br&gt;Dechen Thurman&lt;br&gt;(''[[Bret Easton Ellis#Films|This Is Not an Exit]]'')&lt;br&gt;Michael Kremko&lt;br&gt;(''[[American Psycho 2]]'')
| episode     =
| nickname    = &quot;Boy Next Door&quot;
| alias       = Marcus Halberstram&lt;br&gt;Paul Allen
| gender      =
| occupation  = [[Investment banking|Investment banker]]
| title       = [[Vice President]]
| family      = [[The Rules of Attraction#Sean Bateman|Sean Bateman]] (brother)&lt;br&gt;Unnamed mother&lt;br&gt;Unnamed father
| spouse      =
| significantother= Evelyn Williams (''American Psycho'')&lt;br&gt;Jean (&quot;[[American Psycho (film)#Marketing|AmPsycho2000]]&quot; emails)
| children    = Five [[abortion|aborted]], 2 by his own hand.
| relatives   =
| religion    =
| nationality = [[United States|American]]
| lbl21       = Education
| data21      = [[Phillips Exeter Academy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Harvard University]]&lt;br&gt;[[Harvard Business School]]
}}
'''Patrick Bateman''' is a [[fictional character]], the [[antihero]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Patrick Bateman1&quot;&gt;The Toronto Star, Peter Howell; [http://www.fradical.com/psycho_killer_is_no_pop_culture_.htm Psycho killer is no pop culture anti-hero], April 19, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Patrick Bateman2&quot;&gt;Guardian Unlimited; [http://books.guardian.co.uk/authors/author/0,,-61,00.html BRET EASTON ELLIS].&lt;/ref&gt; and [[narrator]] of the novel ''[[American Psycho]]'' by [[Bret Easton Ellis]], and its [[American Psycho (film)|film adaptation]]. He has also briefly appeared in other Ellis novels.

==Biography and profile==
When he is first introduced in Ellis' novel, young [[investment banker]] Patrick Bateman's &quot;mask of sanity&quot; is about to slip, according to his own admission. Bateman works as a specialist in [[mergers and acquisitions]] at the fictional [[Wall Street]] investment firm of Pierce &amp; Pierce (also Sherman McCoy's firm in ''[[The Bonfire of the Vanities]]'') and lives at 55 West 81st Street, [[Upper West Side]] in the American Gardens Building (where he is a neighbor of actor [[Tom Cruise]]). In his &quot;secret life&quot;, however, Bateman  is a [[serial killer]] who murders a variety of people, from colleagues, to [[Homelessness|the homeless]], to [[prostitution|prostitutes]]. His crimes, including [[rape]], [[torture]], [[murder]], [[necrophilia]] and [[cannibalism]], are described in graphic detail in the novel.

Bateman comes from a wealthy family. His parents have a house on [[Long Island]], and he mentions a summer house in [[Newport, Rhode Island|Newport]]. His parents [[divorce]]d sometime earlier, while his mother became sick and now resides at a [[sanatorium]]. His father, who first appeared in the preceding novel ''[[The Rules of Attraction]]'', grew up on an estate in [[Connecticut]], and now owns an apartment in the [[Carlyle Hotel]] in [[Manhattan]], although he was apparently dying in the previous novel and, unlike his ex-wife, is mentioned only in past tense during the novel. His younger brother [[Sean Bateman|Sean]]  attends [[Camden College (fictional college)|Camden College]] (and is a protagonist of ''[[The Rules of Attraction]]''). Bateman attended [[Phillips Exeter Academy]] for prep school.  He graduated from [[Harvard University]] in 1984, and [[Harvard Business School]] two years later and moved to [[New York City]].

==Personality==
As written by Ellis, Bateman is the ultimate [[stereotype]] of [[yuppie]] greed: rich, shallow, and addicted to sex, drugs, and [[conspicuous consumption]]. All of his friends look alike to him, to the point that he often confuses one for another, and they often confuse him for other people. Bateman takes delight in obsessively detailing virtually every single feature of his always designer clothes, workout routine, business cards, alcoholic drinks, as well as his elaborate high end stereo and [[home cinema|home theater]] sound system. He is engaged to an equally rich, shallow woman named Evelyn Williams. They can't stand each other, but they stay together for the sake of their social lives. He has a mistress on the side (the fiancee of a [[gay]] colleague whom he holds in great contempt and who makes repeated, hapless sexual advances towards Bateman) and has regular liaisons with prostitutes and women he encounters at clubs, many of whom end up being his victims. The one woman (and possibly the one person) in his life he has anything approaching feelings for is his secretary, Jean. He just cannot bring himself to seduce, rape or kill her, perhaps because she is the only person in his life who is not completely shallow. Every time he mentions Jean throughout the novel, he casually acknowledges her as &quot;Jean, my secretary who is in love with me&quot; and introduces her in the narration as someone whom he &quot;will probably end up married to someday&quot;.

Bateman kills many of his victims because they make him feel inadequate, usually by having better taste than he does. His friends mock him as the &quot;boy next door&quot;, his own lawyer refers to him as a &quot;bloody ass-kisser... a brown-nosing goody-goody&quot;, and he is often dismissed as &quot;yuppie trash&quot; by people outside of his social circle. 

Bateman often expresses doubts regarding his own [[sanity]], and he has periodic attacks of [[psychosis]], during which he [[hallucination|hallucinates]]. He often experiences feelings of [[depersonalization]]. In his own words, &quot;although I can hide my cold gaze and you can shake my hand and feel my flesh gripping yours and maybe you can even sense our lifestyles are probably comparable: I simply am not there.&quot; Although Bateman often claims that he is devoid of emotion, he also describes experiencing moments of extreme rage, panic or grief - being on the &quot;verge of tears&quot; - often over trivial inconveniences such as remembering to return videotapes or trying to obtain reservations. In the middle of dismembering a victim, he breaks down, sobbing that he &quot;just wants to be loved&quot;. He takes [[psychotropic]]s, like [[Xanax]], to get these attacks under control.

Bateman compensates for these insecurities through obsessive vanity and [[personal grooming]], with unwavering attention to detail. He dresses in and uses the most fashionable, expensive clothing and accessories possible (e.g. [[Salvatore Ferragamo]] and [[Valentino SpA|Valentino suits]], [[Oliver Peoples]] glasses and [[Jean Paul Gaultier]], [[Louis Vuitton]] and [[Bottega Veneta]] leather goods) as a means of affecting some &quot;control&quot; over his otherwise chaotic life. Likewise, he categorizes people by what they wear and how they look because they are more easily &quot;understood&quot; in terms of labels and stereotypes. Bateman's apartment also is firmly controlled in terms of look and taste, with the latest music, food, and art.

Bateman kills more or less indiscriminately, with no preferred type of victim and no consistent or preferred method of killing. Throughout the novel, he kills men, women, a child, and animals. He kills women mostly for [[Sadism and Masochism|sadistic]] sexual pleasure, often during or just after sex, and is also a prolific rapist. He kills men because they anger or annoy him, and the child just to see if he would enjoy it (he does not).

Periodically, he matter-of-factly confesses his crimes to his friends, co-workers, and even complete strangers (&quot;I'm utterly insane&quot;, &quot;I like to dissect girls&quot;) just to see if they are actually listening to him. They either are not, or think he is joking. In the [[climax (narrative)|climactic]] scene Bateman calls his lawyer and leaves a lengthy, detailed message confessing all of his crimes. He later runs into his lawyer, who mistakes him for someone else and dismisses the confession as a joke.

==Outside of ''American Psycho''==
Bateman made his first appearance in Ellis' 1987 novel ''[[The Rules of Attraction]]'' (in which Sean, his brother, is the main character); no indication is given that he is a serial killer. Bateman also makes a short appearance in Ellis' 1998 novel ''[[Glamorama]]'', with &quot;strange stains&quot; on the lapel of his [[Armani]] suit and Victor mentions &quot;He has a coat of arms baby&quot;.

Bateman also appeared in the ''American Psycho 2000'' [[e-mail]]s ([http://www.briankotek.com/psycho/movie/am2000.cfm transcribed here]), which were written as an advertisement campaign for the movie. Although they are often mistakenly credited to Ellis, they were actually written by one or more unnamed author(s) and approved by Ellis before being sent out. ''American Psycho 2000'' served as a sort of &quot;e-quel&quot; to the original novel. The e-mails take place in 2000, a little over a decade since the novel. Bateman is in [[psychotherapy|therapy]] with a Dr. M. He is also married to Jean, his former secretary. They have a son, Patrick Bateman Jr. (P.B.), who is eight years old. In the story, Bateman talks about therapy, trying to get a divorce from Jean, his renewed feelings about murder, and idolizing his son. In the end it is revealed that the 'real' Bateman who 'writes' the e-mails, is the owner of the company that produces the movie.

Bateman appeared in Ellis' 2005 novel ''[[Lunar Park]]'', in which the fictionalised Bret Easton Ellis confesses that writing ''American Psycho'' felt like channeling the words of a violent spirit rather than writing anything himself. This ghost &amp;mdash; Bateman &amp;mdash; haunts Ellis' home. A character also comes to Ellis' [[Halloween]] party dressed as Patrick Bateman, and a copycat killer is seemingly patterning himself on Bateman. Toward the novel's end, Ellis writes the 'last' Bateman story as a way of confronting and controlling the character, as well as the issues Ellis created Bateman as a means of countering.  Bateman, for all intents and purposes, dies in a fire on a boat dock.

==In film==

Though [[Christian Bale]] had been the first choice for the part by both Ellis and Harron, the producers offered the part to [[Keanu Reeves]], [[Edward Norton]], and [[Brad Pitt]]. [[Leonardo DiCaprio]] was set to play the character, but Ellis (as explained in the ''American Psycho'' DVD) decided he was too young, especially immediately after ''[[Titanic (1997 film)|Titanic]]''. Bateman was also portrayed by Dechen Thurman (brother of [[Uma Thurman|Uma]]) in the 2000 [[documentary film|documentary]] ''This Is Not an Exit: The Fictional World of Bret Easton Ellis''. Michael Kremko played Bateman in the [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] ''[[American Psycho 2]]'', in which the character is killed by a would-be victim. This sequel has, however, no connections to the previous film and has been denounced by Ellis.

Scenes with the character were shot for the 2002 [[The Rules of Attraction (film)|film adaptation]] of ''[[The Rules of Attraction]]''. Ellis revealed in an interview that director [[Roger Avary]] asked Bale to reprise the role, but Bale turned down the offer, and Avary asked Ellis himself to portray Bateman. Ellis refused, stating that he &quot;thought it was such a terrible and gimmicky idea&quot;, and Avary eventually shot the scenes with [[Casper Van Dien]]. The scenes, however, were ultimately cut from the final version of the film.

In a 2009 interview with ''Black Book'', director [[Mary Harron]] said, &quot;We talked about how [[Martian]]-like [the character] Patrick Bateman was, how he was looking at the world like somebody from another planet, watching what people did and trying to work out the right way to behave, and then one day [Christian] called me and he had been watching [[Tom Cruise]] on [[David Letterman]], and he just had this very intense friendliness with nothing behind the eyes, and he was really taken with this energy.&quot;

==Chronology==
*October, 1962: Patrick Bateman is born.&lt;ref&gt;The month can be narrowed down by passages where he briefly muses on what it means to be a [[Libra (astrology)|Libra]], as well as wondering what he'll get for his birthday in October. The year is 1962, derived from the fact that the novel begins in April 1989 &lt;!-- 1987 in the movie --&gt; and Patrick mentions in the narration that he is twenty-six years old.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1980: Bateman graduates from [[Phillips Exeter Academy]].
*1984: Bateman graduates from [[Harvard University]].
*1985: Bateman has a short discussion with his estranged brother [[Sean Bateman|Sean]] about his future.
*1986: Bateman graduates from [[Harvard Business School]].
**From the time of his graduation, through the end of ''American Psycho'', Bateman works at Pierce &amp; Pierce.
*ca. 1996: Bateman shows up at Victor's club in ''[[Glamorama]]'' with &quot;strange stains&quot; on his suit.
*2000: Bateman enters therapy with a Dr. M. This appears in the ''American Psycho 2000'' e-mails. In these emails, he is divorcing Jean, to whom he has been married for at least five years, and has a son with. He has started his own brokerage firm and seems to be even richer than he was in the original novel. His tastes are even more rarefied. His homicidal tendencies (or thoughts) seem to have cooled a little with the birth of his son and has generally [[mellow]]ed as he has gotten older, but have not disappeared completely.
*2003: Ellis kills off Patrick Bateman by writing an extraordinary account of the serial killer being trapped in a pier fire. See ''[[Lunar Park]]''.

== References ==
* IMDB, Internet Movie Database, IMDB.com, 1/17/07, Pg. 4 Para 5

{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*{{imdb character|id= 0004406|name=Patrick Bateman}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bateman, Patrick}}
[[Category:Bret Easton Ellis characters]]
[[Category:Fictional bankers]]
[[Category:Fictional cannibals]]
[[Category:Fictional characters from New York City]]
[[Category:Fictional Harvard University people]]
[[Category:Fictional rapists]]
[[Category:Fictional serial killers]]
[[Category:Fictional socialites]]
[[Category:Film characters]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1987]]
[[Category:Characters in American novels of the 20th century]]
[[da:Patrick Bateman]]
[[de:Patrick Bateman]]
[[es:Patrick Bateman]]
[[fr:Patrick Bateman]]
[[it:Patrick Bateman]]
[[nl:Patrick Bateman]]
[[ru:Патрик Бэйтмен]]
[[sv:Patrick Bateman]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
