<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4693250" ns="0" title="New Era High School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''New Era High School''' (or '''NEHS''') is located in [[Panchgani]], a hill station town known as an educational centre, in the state of [[Maharashtra]], [[India]]. It is a private co-educatioinal [[International school|internationalist]] [[Bahá'í school]], drawing students from all over the world and is under the supervision of the [[National Spiritual Assembly]] of the Bahá'ís of India.&lt;ref name=&quot;background&quot;&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/aboutus/background/background.php3 Background statement of the school]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
It was founded in August 1945, and was one of the first [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]] education projects in India.&lt;ref name=&quot;background&quot;/&gt; In the 1970s and 1980s, the school setup programmes to assist the poor and underdeveloped villages in the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;early&quot;&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/aboutus/history/1971_1982/1971_1982.php3 History: 1971-1982]&lt;/ref&gt;  It started as a service project for students and evolved into a separate institution known as the [[New Era Development Institute]] in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;second&quot;&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/aboutus/history/1982_1998/1982_1998.php3 History: 1982-1998]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bahá'í Faith in Norway|National Spiritual Assembly of Norway]] established an institution - Norwegian Agency for International Development Cooperation - and in 1988 it began a working relationship with the institute, with support for a two-year rural community development program. In 1989, funding was extended to cover a one-year community development facilitators course and short courses on agriculture, rural technology, literacy, and domestic science.

NEHS is one of the top boarding schools in India. It did have a higher secondary school(11th-12th) till 1999, but  discontinued it from 2000. The shooting of the film &quot;Taare Zameen Par&quot; took place here. Promonent students include Twinkle and Rinke Khanna - daughters of the Indian actress Dimple. 

The principle Dr. Mehrassa supervises the school from Canada, Mr. Kalmadi is the acting principle. The school regularly reaches district level in sports such as football, basketball and cricket.

&lt;ref name=&quot;involve&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Hansen | first = Holly  | coauthors = Bahá'í International Community | title = Overview of Bahá'í Social and Economic Development | work = 1992-93 edition of ''The Bahá'í World'', pp. 229-245. | publisher = Universal House of Justice | date = 1999 | url =http://info.bahai.org/article-1-8-1-6.html | accessdate = 2008-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Site/facilities==
The present site was moved into in 1953 and consisted of five buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;begin&quot;&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/aboutus/history/1945_1971/1945_1971.php3 History: 1945-1971]&lt;/ref&gt; A play field and several added dormitories in 1980s gave the school the room to add over 500 students bringing the total student population to over 1000.&lt;ref name=&quot;second&quot;/&gt; In the 1990s the campus went through massive infrastructure growth and renovation -  gaining its own power plant, campus fencing, intercom system, phone system for students, parents and staff,  three wells, solar heating for the dining hall and a large garden. Computers handle student records, accounts, maintenance, personnel, and other administrative areas as well as facilitating student-parent communication.&lt;ref name=&quot;third&quot;&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/aboutus/history/1998_2003/1998_2003.php3 History: 1998-2003]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programme==
Special attention is given to academic excellence, moral education, specifically noted by the [[Universal House of Justice]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/aboutus/history/letter_msg/letter_msg.php3 letter from the Universal House Of Justice, 30 October 1995, to the school]&lt;/ref&gt;, values for world citizenship, and social and economic development in rural areas. Subject areas significantly expanded through the 1990s to include advances across the K-12 curriculum with peace and cooperative learning programs, computer training programs and  extracurricular sports clubs and educational field trips.&lt;ref name=&quot;third&quot;/&gt;

==Accreditation and awards==
The school was registered with the state in 1954 and the first students took their external examinations in 1958. Gloria Faizi, [[Abu'l-Qásim Faizi]]'s wife, helped bring the school onto a more financial status by providing leadership and attracting investments.&lt;ref name=&quot;begin&quot;/&gt; The current accreditation includes the standard ten high school exam of the [[Central Board of Secondary Education]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/academics/academics.php3 General Academics]&lt;/ref&gt; though it is increasingly switching to [[Indian Certificate of Secondary Education]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goodschoolsofindia.com/introduction/sbcba.asp School Boards Compete for Better Academics]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Secondary Section in 2007 received top awards for all of [[Panchgani]] (with additional high marks in specific subject areas)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/academics/secondary/secondary_generalinfo/secondary_generalinfo.php3 Secondary: General Information - highlight of CBSE Results 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;
*100% passed result with average score of 73.54%
*Set a new record of highest average 94.6%
*Number of students appeared - 102
*48 students (47%) secured Distinction ( above 75%)
*43 students (42%) secured First Class (above 60%)
*11 students (11%) secured Second Class

The Secondary Science program won awards in 2003 (National Level Science Talent Search Examination and Best Participation Award in the NSTSE)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/academics/science/science.php3 Academics: Science]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Secondary Computer Science curriculum serves the [[International General Certificate of Secondary Education]].&lt;ref name=&quot;computers&quot;&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/beyondbooks/computer/computer.php3 Computers, Information &amp; Communication Technology]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Secondary Arts program can support students reaching for the annual [[Government of Maharashtra Elementary and Intermediate Art Exams]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/beyondbooks/art/art.php3 Arts - Aims, Objectives &amp; Special Programmes]&lt;/ref&gt;

All topic areas have vocational courses&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/beyondbooks/vocation/vocation.php3 Vocational Courses and Admission criteria]&lt;/ref&gt;

The school is ranked 64th across India by a broad range of criteria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gyanbharatischool.net/GBS/UserSpace/UserName/admin/DynamicFolder/popup/SchoolRanking.html India's best schools league table]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005/6, New Era High School two students ranked 857th and 1824th (over 2000 were ranked) across all Indian students competing for the [[Amul Shakti Vidyashree award]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amul.com/Vidyashree_06_India.html Amul Shakti Vidyashree Award] - Academic Year 2005-6  List of Winners (All India)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Primary Section===
Along with standard academic and arts subject areas, and multilingual programs begin&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/academics/secondlanguages/secondlanguages.php3 Academics: Second Languages]&lt;/ref&gt;, a featured area is values education (including Peace Education, Conflict Resolution, and Environmental Education.)

===Secondary Section===
In addition to the awards winning academic and arts subjects areas, most subject areas develop extension programs - poly-lingual plays, student quiz teams, and community outreach.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indicareer.com/India-Residential-Schools/Maharashtra/New-Era-High-School-Panchgani.html India Schools : New Era High School, Panchgani]&lt;/ref&gt;

The computer system, especially present in the Secondary Section, is [[Open Source]] based - highlighting [[Mandriva]] 2007 and [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora Core]] 7, [[OpenOffice]], and [[GIMP]].&lt;ref name=&quot;computers&quot;/&gt;

==School culture==
The school developed a residential [[prefect]]-oriented system. The prefect body consists of thirty-two students who represent four virtues - Peace, Respect, Harmony and Wisdom. One of the senior students is appointed as Head Girl or Head Boy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/valueeducation/familylearningprogram/familylearningprogram.php3 Family Learning Programme - Our School Prefects]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nehsindia.org/studentlife/secondary_student_associations/secondary_student_associations.php3 Student Associations]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Events==
The second half of [[Aamir Khan]]'s film, ''[[Taare Zameen Par]]'' was shot in the school.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apunkachoice.com/scoop/bollywood/20071007-2.html Aamir Khan declined special appearance in 'Om Shanti Om'], 07th Oct 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Education in India]]
*[[Barli Vocational Institute for Rural Women in Indore]]
*[[Bahá'í Faith in India]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

* ''Rowley, Elizabeth Anne''. (1980) New Era High School: an ethnographic study of an International Bahá'í school in India. Thesis (M.A.) -- [[University of Georgia]] (Athens), 1980.

==External links==
*[http://www.nehsindia.org Official Website]
*[http://www.bahai.in/Social-Action/Education Bahá’í Schools in India]

{{coord missing|Maharashtra}}

[[Category:Bahá'í educational institutions]]
[[Category:International schools in India]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1945]]
[[Category:Boarding schools in India]]
[[Category:Schools in Maharashtra]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
