<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="471806" ns="0" title="António Guterres"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Politician
| name          = António Guterres
| image         = António Guterres.jpg
| office        = [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]]
| term_start    = February 20, 2005
| term_end      = 
| predecessor   = [[Ruud Lubbers]]
| successor     = 
| office1       = [[Prime Minister of Portugal]]&lt;br /&gt; &lt;small&gt;Elections: [[Portuguese legislative election, 1995|1995]], [[Portuguese legislative election, 1999|1999]]&lt;/small&gt;
| term_start2   = October 28, 1995
| term_end2     = April 6, 2002
| president2    = [[Mário Soares]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jorge Sampaio]]
| predecessor2  = [[Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
| successor2    = [[José Manuel Barroso]]
| constituency2 = 
| majority2     = 
| office3       = President of the [[Socialist International]]
| term_start3   = 1999
| term_end3     = 2005
| predecessor3  = [[Pierre Mauroy]]
| successor3    = [[George Andreas Papandreou]]
| constituency3 = 
| majority3     =
| office4       = General Secretary of [[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialist Party]]
| term_start4   = [[1992]]
| term_end4     = [[2002]]
| predecessor4  = [[Jorge Sampaio]]
| successor4    = [[Ferro Rodrigues]]
| constituency4 = 
| majority4     = 
| birth_date    = {{Birth date and age|1949|4|30|df=y}}
| birth_place   = [[Lisbon]]
| death_date    = 
| death_place   = 
| party         = [[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialist Party]]
| relations     = 
| spouse        = Luísa Amélia Guimarães e Melo (deceased), Catarina de Almeida Vaz Pinto
| children      = Pedro Guimarães e Melo Guterres, Mariana Guimarães e Melo Guterres
| residence     = 
| alma_mater    = 
| occupation    = 
| religion      = [[Roman Catholicism]]
| signature     = 
| website       = 
| footnotes     = 
}}

'''António Manuel de Oliveira Guterres''', &lt;small&gt;[[Order of Christ (Portugal)|GCC]]&lt;/small&gt; ({{IPA-pt|ɐ̃ˈtɔniu ɡuˈtɛʁɨʃ}}; born 30 April 1949) is a [[Portugal|Portuguese]] politician, a former [[List of Prime Ministers of Portugal|prime minister]] and President of the [[Socialist International]]. Currently he is the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]].

==Early life==
António Guterres was born and raised in Portugal's capital, [[Lisbon]], son of Virgílio Dias Guterres (b. São José, [[Lisbon]], 21 October 1913) and wife Ilda Cândida de Oliveira (b. [[Fundão]], Donas, 12 February 1923). As a young child he already showed the abilities which would later garner him the award for Best High School Student for the year of 1965. He continued his studies at [[Instituto Superior Técnico|IST]], where he pursued degrees in physics and electrical engineering. During his college years Guterres was never involved in the student opposition to the authoritarian regime of [[António de Oliveira Salazar]] and, from 1968, [[Marcelo Caetano]]. Instead, he dedicated himself to his studies and to meetings of the JUC (Catholic University Students Movement). In 1971 he graduated and started an academic career as Assistant Professor.

==Career==
His political career started in 1972, when he joined the [[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialist Party]]. On New Year's Eve that year, at Carnide, [[Lisbon]], he married his first wife, Luísa Amélia Guimarães e Melo (b. [[Porto]], 1 September 1946), by whom he had two children, Pedro Guimarães e Melo Guterres (b. 1977), married to Vanda Lobo and father of Maria Ana Lobo Guterres (b. Lisbon, 11 February 2009), and Mariana Guimarães e Melo de Oliveira Guterres (b. 1985). Shortly thereafter, he quit academic life and became a full-time politician. In the period following the [[Carnation Revolution]] of April 25, 1974, which put an end to [[Marcelo_Caetano#Prime_minister|Caetano's dictatorship]], Guterres was closely involved in the organization of the Socialist Party, especially the Lisbon section. Guterres became one of the party leaders and held the following offices: 

* Head of Office of the Secretary of State of Industry (1974 and 1975)
* Deputy for [[Lisbon]], and later [[Castelo Branco Municipality|Castelo Branco]] in the [[Assembly of the Republic|Portuguese National Parliament]] (1976–1995)
** During this term he was responsible for several parliamentary commissions
* Leader of the parliamentary bench of the Socialist Party, succeeding [[Jorge Sampaio]] (1988)

In 1992, he became president of the Socialist Party and leader of the opposition against [[Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]'s government. He was also nominated vice-president of the [[Socialist International]] in September of the same year. 

Following the retirement of [[Aníbal Cavaco Silva|Cavaco Silva]] in 1995, the Socialist Party won the [[Portuguese legislative election, 1995|general election]] and Guterres became Prime Minister of Portugal. With a style markedly different from that of his predecessor, based on dialogue and discussion with all sections of society, Guterres was a popular prime minister in the first years of his government. Portugal was enjoying a solid economic expansion which allowed the Socialists to increase welfare spending. Also important was the successful staging of [[Expo´98]], which increased Portugal's visibility in the world.

His wife died of [[cancer]] at the [[Royal Free Hospital]] in the [[Greater London]], [[London]], on 28 January 1998.

Guterres was re-elected in [[Portuguese legislative election, 1999|1999]], and from January to July 2000, he occupied the Presidency of the [[European Council]]. This second term in government was not as successful however. Internal party conflicts along with an economic recession and the [[Hintze Ribeiro disaster]] damaged his authority and popularity.

Meanwhile in [[Alcântara (Lisbon)|Alcântara]], [[Lisbon]], at the Chapel of Santo Amaro, on 9 April 2001, he married his second wife Catarina de Almeida Vaz Pinto, born on 15 June 1960, by whom he had no children. He has a stepson, natural son of his second wife by José Carlos da Costa Ramos, named Francisco Vaz Pinto da Costa Ramos, born on 20 May 1998.

In 2002, following a disastrous result for the Socialist Party in the local elections, Guterres resigned, stating that &quot;''I am resigning to prevent the country from falling into a political swamp''&quot;, and President [[Jorge Sampaio]] dissolved the Parliament and called for elections. [[Ferro Rodrigues|Eduardo Ferro Rodrigues]], until then Minister for Social Security, assumed the Socialist Party leadership, but the general election was lost to the [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]] of [[José Manuel Durão Barroso]], the current [[President of the European Commission]]. Guterres retired from Portuguese politics and worked as President of the [[Socialist International]] until 2005.

==Work as High Commissioner for Refugees==
In May 2005 he was appointed [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|High Commissioner for Refugees]] by then [[Secretary-General of the United Nations]] [[Kofi Annan]]. In a 16 February 2007 [[NPR]] interview devoted mainly to the plight of Iraqi refugees, he said that this was the greatest refugee crisis in the Middle East since 1948.  Among poorly publicized refugee crises, he cited those in the [[Central African Republic]] and the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]].&lt;ref&gt;Interview with António Guterres, the United Nations high commissioner for refugees, 16 February 2007, Weekend Edition-Saturday, http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=7466089&lt;/ref&gt;

He is a member of the [[Club of Madrid]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clubmadrid.org The Club of Madrid] is an independent non-profit organization composed of 81 democratic former Presidents and Prime Ministers from 57 different countries. It constitutes the world´s largest forum of former Heads of State and Government, who have come together to respond to a growing demand for support among leaders in democratic leadership, governance, crisis and post-crisis situations. All lines of work share the common goal of building functional and inclusive societies, where the leadership experience of the members is most valuable.&lt;/ref&gt; an independent non-profit organization composed of 81 democratic former Presidents and Prime Ministers from 57 different countries.

{{commons|António Guterres}}

{{start box}}
{{s-off}}
{{succession box|title=[[Prime Minister of Portugal]]|before=[[Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]|after=[[Durão Barroso]]|years=1995-2002|}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{succession box|title=President of the [[Socialist International]]|before=[[Pierre Mauroy]]|after=[[George Papandreou (junior)|George A. Papandreou]]|years=1999-2005|}}
{{end box}}
{{PMPortugal1974}}
{{Presidents of the European Council}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Guterres, Antonio
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =30 April 1949
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Lisbon]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Guterres, Antonio}}
[[Category:1949 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Lisbon]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Portugal]]
[[Category:Portuguese engineers]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Socialist International]]
[[Category:Portuguese Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Portuguese Christian socialists]]
[[Category:United Nations High Commissioners for Refugees]]
[[Category:Socialist Party (Portugal) politicians]]
[[Category:Technical University of Lisbon alumni]]
[[Category:United Nations Under-Secretaries-General]]

[[be:Антоніу Гутэрэш]]
[[bg:Антониу Гутериш]]
[[cs:António Guterres]]
[[da:António Guterres]]
[[de:António Guterres]]
[[es:António Guterres]]
[[fr:António Guterres]]
[[ko:안토니우 구테흐스]]
[[io:António Manuel Guterres]]
[[it:António Guterres]]
[[lt:António Guterres]]
[[mr:अँतोनियो गुतेरेस]]
[[nl:António Guterres]]
[[ja:アントニオ・グテーレス]]
[[no:António Guterres]]
[[oc:António Manuel Guterres]]
[[pl:António Guterres]]
[[pt:António Guterres]]
[[ro:Antonio Manuel de Oliveira Guterres]]
[[qu:António Guterres]]
[[ru:Гутерреш, Антониу]]
[[fi:António Guterres]]
[[sv:António Guterres]]
[[tr:António Guterres]]
[[uk:Антоніу Гутерреш]]
[[zh:安东尼奥·古特雷斯]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
