<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="473086" ns="0" title="King Kong (2005 film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the video game|Peter Jackson's King Kong: The Official Game of the Movie}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = King Kong
| image          = Kingkong bigfinal1.jpg
| border         = yes
| caption        = Theatrical poster
| director       = [[Peter Jackson]]
| writer         = 
| screenplay     = [[Fran Walsh]]&lt;br&gt;[[Philippa Boyens]]&lt;br&gt;[[Peter Jackson]]
| story          = [[Merian C. Cooper]]&lt;br&gt;[[Edgar Wallace]]
| starring       = [[Naomi Watts]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jack Black]]&lt;br&gt;[[Adrien Brody]]&lt;br&gt;[[Thomas Kretschmann]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kyle Chandler]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jamie Bell]]&lt;br&gt;[[Colin Hanks]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lobo Chan]]&lt;br&gt;[[Andy Serkis]]
| producer       = Jan Blenkin&lt;br&gt;{{nowrap|Carolynne Cunningham}}&lt;br&gt;[[Fran Walsh]]&lt;br&gt;[[Peter Jackson]]
| music          = {{nowrap|[[James Newton Howard]]}}
| cinematography = [[Andrew Lesnie]]
| editing        = [[Jamie Selkirk]]
| studio         = WingNut Films
| distributor    = [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]]
| released       = {{filmdate|2005|12|13|New Zealand|2005|12|14|United States}}
| runtime        = 187 min (Theatrical)&lt;br&gt;201 min (Extended DVD)
| country        = {{Film NZ}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Film US}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $207 million
| gross          = $550.5 million 
}}
'''''King Kong''''' is a 2005 [[fantasy film|fantasy]] [[adventure film]] directed by [[Peter Jackson]]. It is a [[remake]] of the [[King Kong (1933 film)|1933 film of the same name]] and stars [[Naomi Watts]], [[Jack Black (actor)|Jack Black]] and [[Adrien Brody]]. [[Andy Serkis]], through [[performance capture]], portrays [[King Kong|Kong]].

The film's budget climbed from an initial US$150&amp;nbsp;million to a record-breaking $207&amp;nbsp;million. The film was released on December&amp;nbsp;14, 2005 and made an opening of $50.1&amp;nbsp;million. While the film performed lower than expectations, ''King Kong'' made domestic and worldwide grosses that eventually added up to $550&amp;nbsp;million,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = ''King Kong''| publisher = BoxOfficeMojo.com| url = http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=kingkong05.htm| accessdate = 2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; becoming the fourth-highest grossing movie in [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]] history. Strong DVD sales also added over $100&amp;nbsp;million to the grosses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = ''King Kong'' – DVD sales| publisher = BlogCritics.org| url = http://blogcritics.org/archives/2006/04/04/122953.php| accessdate = 2007-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also received positive reviews, with some considering it one of the all-round best movies of 2005, though it has been criticised for its length at three hours and seven minutes. It won [[Academy Award]]s for [[Academy Award for Best Visual Effects|Best Visual Effects]], [[Academy Award for Best Sound|Best Sound Mixing]], and [[Academy Award for Best Sound Editing|Best Sound Editing]].

==Plot summary==
In 1933, at the height of the [[Great Depression]] in [[New York City]], Ann Darrow ([[Naomi Watts]]) has lost her job as a [[vaudeville]] actress but is hired by troubled filmmaker [[Carl Denham]] ([[Jack Black]]) to act in his new motion picture. Ann signs on when she learns her favourite playwright [[Jack Driscoll]] ([[Adrien Brody]]) is the screenwriter. As the [[tramp steamer]] SS&amp;nbsp;''Venture'' sails to the mysterious Skull Island, they slowly fall in love. As for Carl, a warrant is out for his arrest and [[Captain Englehorn]] ([[Thomas Kretschmann]]) begins to have second thoughts, following the fears of his crew about Skull Island and its [[Island gigantism|strange creatures that have evolved apart]] from the outside world.  Despite his attempt to turn around, the ship is lost in fog and runs aground on the rocks encircling the island.

Carl and his crew explore the island to film and are attacked by the vicious natives. Mike ([[Craig Hall (actor)|Craig Hall]]), the sound technician, is speared, one of the sailors has his head bashed in, and Jack is knocked out. Ann screams as she is captured, and a roar beyond the wall responds. The matriarch of the tribe vows to sacrifice her to &quot;Kong&quot;, a 25 ft (8m) tall [[gorilla]], and the last of its kind. Englehorn and his crew break up the attack and return to the stranded ship. They lighten their load to steer away, but Jack discovers Ann has been kidnapped. On the island, Ann is hung from a balcony on the side of the wall. The crew comes armed, but is too late as Kong takes Ann into the jungle.

Captain Englehorn organizes a rescue party to find Ann and hunt down the beast. The rescue party is caught up in a [[Dromaeosauridae|Venatosaurus]] pack's hunt of [[Brontosaurus]], and Herb ([[John Sumner (actor born 1951)|John Sumner]]), the cameraman, is killed along with three sailors. The rest of the rescue party come across a swamp where Bruce Baxter ([[Kyle Chandler]]) and two others leave the group. Meanwhile, Ann manages to entertain Kong with juggling and dancing. The survivors stumble across a log, where Kong arrives and attacks, shaking them off the log into a ravine. He returns to rescue Ann from three [[Tyrannosauridae|Vastatosaurus Rex]], and takes her up to his mountain lair. Englehorn and the rest of the crew rescue what is left of the rescue party from the pit of giant insects, and as Jack decides to continue to search for Ann, Carl decides to capture Kong. Jack goes to Kong's lair, waking him. As Kong fights a swarm of flying [[Giant bat|Terapusmordax]], Ann and Jack escape by grabbing the wing of one of the bats and then jumping into a river. They arrive at the village wall with the angry Kong following them, and Ann becomes distraught by what Carl plans to do. Kong bursts through the gate and struggles to get her back, but he is eventually knocked out by [[chloroform]]. 

In New York around [[Christmas]], Carl presents a chained ''Kong&amp;nbsp;— the Eighth Wonder of the World'' on [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]], starring Baxter and an imprisoned Kong. Ann has become an anonymous chorus girl and a double of her is no replacement in Kong's eyes. Camera flashes from photographers enrage the gorilla. Kong breaks free from his [[chrome-steel]] chains and chases Jack across town, where he encounters Ann again. They share a quiet moment on a frozen lake in Central Park, before the army attacks. Kong climbs with Ann onto the [[Empire State Building]], where he fights off planes sent to attack him, downing three of them. Ultimately, Kong is hit by several bursts of gunfire from the surviving planes, and gazes at a distraught Ann for the last time before falling off the building to his death. Ann is greeted by Jack, and the reporters gather around Kong's corpse. Carl takes one last look and says, &quot;It wasn't the airplanes. It was Beauty&lt;!-- please don't change this. It's a quote--&gt; killed the Beast.&quot;

==Cast==
*[[Naomi Watts]] as [[Ann Darrow]]: A struggling vaudville actress who desperate for work.Carl first meets her when she tries to steal an apple form a fruit stand. As the voyage goes on she falls in love with Jack and she forms a special relationship with Kong.
*[[Andy Serkis]] as [[King Kong|Kong]] ([[motion capture]] and voice): A 7.5-meter (25 ft) [[gorilla]] who is around 120–150 years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;Konga&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author= Wloszczyna, Susan| date= June 26, 2005| title=''King Kong'' goes digital| work=USA Today| url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2005-06-26-king-kong_x.htm | accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is the last of his species, ''[[Megaprimatus kong]]''.
*[[Jack Black]] as Carl Denham: A film director who obtained the map to skull island. Due to his situation involing debts Carl starts to lose his moral compass.
*[[Adrien Brody]] as [[Jack Driscoll]]: A scripwriter who falls for Ann. He is on the voyage mistakenly, when he delivers 15 pages of script to Denham and delays him when the venture begins its voyage.
*[[Thomas Kretschmann]] as [[Captain Englehorn]]: The German Captain of the ''Venture''.
*[[Colin Hanks]] as Preston: Denham's neurotic but honest personal assistant. 
*[[Jamie Bell]] as [[Jimmy (King Kong)|Jimmy]]: A boy, found on the ''Venture'', wild and abandoned. He is a [[kleptomania]]c and views Hayes as a father figure.&lt;!-- There is nothing to suggest he is killed when thrown by Kong. Perhaps knocked out, but being killed is speculation.--&gt;
*Andy Serkis as Lumpy: The ship's cook, barber and surgeon. He warns Denham about rumors he has heard about Skull Island and Kong. He joins the search for Ann but is killed in the insect pit.
*[[Evan Parke]] as Ben Hayes: Englehorn's first mate and a friend of Lumpy, who leads Ann's rescue mission due to his army training and combat experience gained during [[World War I]]. He is killed after Kong throws him against a rock wall.
*[[Kyle Chandler]] as Bruce Baxter: An actor who specialises in adventure films. He abandons Ann's rescue mission but brings Englehorn to rescue the search party from the insect pit, and is given credit for rescuing Ann during the Broadway display of Kong.
*[[John Sumner (actor born 1951)|John Sumner]] as Herb: Denham's loyal camera man. He is eaten by a ''Venatosaurus''.
*[[Lobo Chan]] as Choy: Lumpy's best friend and a janitor on the ''Venture'', who falls to his death during the log scene.
*[[Craig Hall (actor)|Craig Hall]] as Mike: Denham's soundman for the journey. He is the first person to be killed when the Skull Island natives spear him.
*William Johnson as Manny: an elderly vaudevillian actor who befriends Ann Darrow at the beginning of the picture.
*[[Mark Hadlow]] as Harry: a struggling vaudevillian actor.
*[[Jed Brophy]] and [[Todd Rippon]] cameoed as crew members.

==Production==
===Development===
[[Peter Jackson]] was a nine-year-old in the New Zealand town of [[Pukerua Bay]] when he first saw the 1933&amp;nbsp;version of ''[[King Kong]]''. He was in tears in front of the TV when Kong slipped off the [[Empire State Building]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Fischer, Paul | date= December 5, 2005| title= Interview: Peter Jackson &quot;''King Kong''&quot; | work=Dark Horizons| url=http://www.darkhorizons.com/news05/kong.php | accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; At age 12 he tried to recreate the film using his parents' super-8 camera and a model of Kong made of wire and rubber with his mother's fur coat for the hair, but eventually gave up on the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot;&gt;{{cite video | title = Recreating the Eighth Wonder: The Making of ''King Kong'' | medium = DVD | publisher = Universal |date = 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1996, he developed a version that was in pre-production for 6–7 months, but the studio cancelled it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Utichi, Joe | year=2005 | title= Interview with Peter Jackson — ''King Kong'' | work=Film Focus| url=http://www.filmfocus.co.uk/lookat.asp?FilmbaseID=42&amp;FeatureID=52 | accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is most likely because of the release of ''[[Mighty Joe Young (1998 film)|Mighty Joe Young]]'' and ''[[Godzilla (1998 film)|Godzilla]]'' the same year.&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot; /&gt; During this time Jackson had achieved the designs of the ''Brontosaurus'' and the ''Venatosaurus''.&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot; /&gt; No casting was ever done, but he had hoped to get [[George Clooney]] and [[Robert De Niro]] for the roles of Jack Driscoll and Carl Denham, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | year=1998 | title= Peter Jackson FAQ (Interview) | work=The Bastards have landed| url=http://tbhl.theonering.net/peter/faq.html#KINGKONG | accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He then began work on [[The Lord of the Rings film trilogy|''The Lord of the Rings'' trilogy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Stratton, David | date= December 13, 2005 | title= Peter Jackson Interview | work=ABC (Australia)| url=http://www.abc.net.au/atthemovies/txt/s1529210.htm | accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  With the overwhelming box office and critical success of ''[[The Lord of the Rings: The Fellowship of the Ring]]'' Universal contacted him during production of [[The Lord of the Rings: The Two Towers|the second film]],&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot;/&gt; and he was paid $20 million [[USD]] to direct this film, the highest salary Hollywood ever paid a director.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Thompson, Anne | date= June 16, 2006| title= Studios learning that A-list isn't everything| work=The Hollywood Reporter| url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/columns/risky_business_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002689404 | accessdate=2006-06-14 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060620022757/http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/columns/risky_business_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002689404 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Screenplay development===
Jackson has stated that the script significantly changed between the 1996 and 2005&amp;nbsp;drafts. He described his first rough draft as a &quot;tongue-in-cheek comedic film with elements of ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]'' and other films&quot;, and in retrospect he is glad that Universal pulled the plug on this version of the film, as he was able to rework the screenplay into something better.&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot; /&gt;

In Jackson's original 1996&amp;nbsp;draft of the script, Ann was the daughter of famed English archaeologist Lord Linwood Darrow exploring ancient ruins in [[Sumatra]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kong&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Stax | date= April 8, 2003| title=The Stax Report: Script Review of ''King Kong''|work=IGN| url=http://filmforce.ign.com/articles/392/392468p1.html| accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; They would come into conflict with Denham during his filming, and they would uncover a hidden Kong statue and the map of [[Skull Island]]. This would indicate that the island natives were the last remnants of a [[cult]] religion that had once thrived on the mainland of Asia. Instead of a playwright, Jack was the first mate and an ex-First World War fighter pilot still struggling with the loss of his best friend, who had been killed in battle during a [[World War I]] prologue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kong&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Stax | date= April 8, 2003| title=The Stax Report: Script Review of ''King Kong''| work=IGN| url=http://filmforce.ign.com/articles/392/392468p1.html| accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Herb the camera-man is the only supporting character in the original draft who made it to the final version. The fight between Kong and the three ''T.&amp;nbsp;rex'' also changed from the original draft. In the draft, Ann is actually caught in the ''T.&amp;nbsp;rex''{{'s}} jaws, where she becomes wedged, and slashed by the teeth; after the fight, Kong gets her out but she is suffering from a fever, from which she then recovers.

The rewriting of the script between 1996 and 2005 involved basing the characters more closely on the 1933 ones, but adding more detail (the screenplay takes no material from the 1976 version).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=| date= February 24, 2004| title=Peter Jackson, filmmaker| work=The Hollywood Reporter| url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/interviews/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000443007 | accessdate=2006-06-14}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The process began with a nine minute animatic created by Jackson and shown to the writing team, causing Philippa Boyens to cry{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}. Jackson, alongside [[Christian Rivers]] and his team, created animatics for all the action sequences which wound up becoming the first stage in animation. The Empire State Building animatic in particular, was completely replicated in the final film.&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot; /&gt;

===Pre-production===
[[Image:Andy Serkis - King Kong.jpg|350px|thumb|[[Andy Serkis]] in his Kong bodysuit]]
Jackson decided early on that he did not want Kong to behave like a human, and so he and his team studied hours of gorilla footage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Epstein, Daniel Robert | year=2005| title=Philippa Boyens Interview| work=Kong UGO| url=http://kingkong.ugo.com/features/philippa_boyens/default.asp# | accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Andy Serkis]], who modelled his movement, went to the [[London Zoo]] to watch the gorillas, but was unsatisfied.  He ended up going to [[Rwanda]] to observe mountain gorillas in the wild with a company called Rainbow Tours.  The resulting Kong is entirely a special effect, who acts and moves very much like a real gorilla.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Fischer, Paul | date= December 5, 2005| title= Interview: Andy Serkis &quot;''King Kong''&quot; | work=Dark Horizons| url=http://www.darkhorizons.com/news05/kong2.php| accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Apart from Kong, [[Skull Island]] is inhabited by [[dinosaur]]s and other large [[fauna]].  Inspired by the works of [[Dougal Dixon]], the designers imagined what 65 million years or more of isolated [[evolution]] might have done to dinosaurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;EE doc&quot; /&gt;

===Difficulties===
The film's budget climbed from an initial US$150&amp;nbsp;million to a record-breaking $207&amp;nbsp;million,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=| date= October 28, 2005| title=''King Kong'' 'goes $32m over budget' | work=BBC| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4384458.stm | accessdate=2006-06-14 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; making it at one point the [[List of most expensive films|most expensive film]] yet made. Universal Pictures only agreed to such an outlay after seeing a screening of the unfinished film, to which executives responded enthusiastically. Marketing and promotion costs were an estimated $60&amp;nbsp;million. The film's length also grew; originally set to be 135 minutes, it soon grew to 200, prompting Universal executives to fly to New Zealand to view a rough cut, but they liked it so their concerns were addressed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Colley, Ed| date= December 8, 2005| title=Jackson: ''King Kong'' is why I'm here | work=The Evening Standard| url= http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/film/article-21146885-details/Jackson%3A+King+Kong+is+why+I%27m+here/article.do| accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other difficulties included Peter Jackson's decision to change composers from [[Howard Shore]] to [[James Newton Howard]] seven weeks before the film opened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=| date= October 18, 2005| title=Jackson drops ''King Kong'' composer| work=BBC| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4352072.stm | accessdate=2006-06-14 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release==
The marketing campaign for ''King Kong'' started in full swing on June&amp;nbsp;27, 2005, when the [[teaser trailer]] made its debut, first online at the official [[Volkswagen]] website at 8:45&amp;nbsp;p.m. EST, then 8:55&amp;nbsp;p.m. EST across media outlets owned by [[NBC Universal]] (the parent of Universal Studios), including [[NBC]], [[Bravo!]], [[CNBC]] and [[MSNBC]]. That trailer appeared in theatres attached to ''[[War of the Worlds (2005 film)|War of the Worlds]]'', which opened on June&amp;nbsp;29.&lt;ref name=&quot;Konga&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author= Wloszczyna, Susan| date= June 26, 2005| title=''King Kong'' goes digital| work=USA Today| url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2005-06-26-king-kong_x.htm|accessdate=2006-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jackson also regularly published a series of 'Production Diaries', which chronicled the making of the film. The diaries started shortly after the [[DVD]] release of ''[[The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King|The Return of the King]]'' as a way to give Jackson's ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]'' fans a glimpse of his next project. These diaries are edited into broadband-friendly installments of three or four minutes each. They consist of features that would normally be seen in a making-of documentary: a tour of the set, a roving camera introducing key players behind the scene, a peek inside the sound booth during last-minute dubbing, or [[Andy Serkis]] doing his ape movements in a motion capture studio.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Abel, Glenn| date= December 19, 2005| title=''King Kong'': Peter Jackson's Production Diaries| work=Hollywood Reporter| url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001700175|accessdate=2006-06-14 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060513134323/http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr/reviews/review_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1001700175 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A novelisation of the movie and a prequel entitled ''The Island of the Skull'' was also written. A multi-platform video game entitled ''[[Peter Jackson's King Kong: The Official Game of the Movie|Peter Jackson's King Kong]]'' was released, which featured an alternate ending. There was a hardback book entitled ''The World of Kong'', featuring artwork from [[Weta Workshop]] to describe the fictional bestiary in the film.

==Reception==
[[Image:KingKongOdeonpremiere.jpg|thumb|The billboard at the [[Odeon Leicester Square]] premiere]]
With a take of $9.7 million on its Wednesday opening day, and with an opening weekend gross of $50.1 million, ''King Kong'''s opening numbers did not meet expectations of [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]] executives.  Its opening weekend of $50.1 million, while good for most movies, fell short of the inflated expectations that preceded the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.the-numbers.com/interactive/newsStory.php?newsID=1641
|title=Kong's King| publisher=the-numbers.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, ''King Kong'' was able to hold its audience in the subsequent holiday weeks and ended up becoming a domestic hit, grossing $218.1&amp;nbsp;million at the North American box office (putting it in the top five grossing films of 2005 domestically).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=2005 Domestic Grosses | work=boxofficemojo.com | url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/chart/?yr=2005&amp;p=.htm | accessdate=2006-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''King Kong'' fared much better in the international market, as it grossed $332.4&amp;nbsp;million outside North America, leading to a worldwide total of $550.5&amp;nbsp;million, that not only put it in the top five grossing films of 2005 worldwide,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/chart/?view2=worldwide&amp;yr=2005&amp;p=.htm |title=Worldwide gross | publisher=BoxOfficeMojo.com | accessdate=2007-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; but also helped the film bring back more than two and half times its production budget.

Other factors also affect a film's profitability besides box office sales, such as the DVD sales. ''King Kong'', sold over $100 million worth of DVDs in the largest six-day performance in Universal Studios history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=| date= April 3, 2006| title='King Kong' DVD scares up $100 mln 1st-week sales | format=| work=Reuters| url=http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/wireStory?id=1802180|accessdate=2006-06-14}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of April&amp;nbsp;3, 2006, ''King Kong'' has sold more than 7.5 million DVDs, accumulating over $140 million worth of sales numbers, domestically alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=King Kong DVD Sales at The-numbers.com | url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2005/KKONG-DVD.php}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of June&amp;nbsp;25, 2006 ''King Kong'' has generated almost $38 million from DVD rental gross.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = ''King Kong''/DVD and Video | publisher = Box Office Mojo | url = http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=homevideo&amp;id=kingkong05.htm | accessdate = 2007-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; As well, in February 2006, Universal received $26.5 million from [[TNT (TV channel)|TNT]]/[[TBS (TV channel)|TBS]] and [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] for the television rights to the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2005/KKONG.php |title=Movie King Kong - Box Office Data, News, Cast Information |publisher=The Numbers |date= |accessdate=2011-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thus, despite the film's inauspicious start at the box office, ''King Kong'' turned out to be very profitable. Ticket and DVD sales combined, the film earned well over $700&amp;nbsp;million,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = ''King Kong''| publisher = BoxOfficeMojo.com| url = http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=kingkong05.htm| accessdate = 2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = ''King Kong'' DVD Sets Sales Record| publisher = Breitbart.com| date = 2006-04-04| url = http://www.breitbart.com/news/2006/04/04/D8GPD9DG6.html| accessdate = 2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; becoming the fourth-highest grossing movie in [[Universal Pictures]] history.

===Critical reaction===
''King Kong'' received a favourable critical response, garnering an 84% &quot;Certified Fresh&quot; approval rating among 'T-Meter Critics', and a 79% rating among 'Top Critics' on Rotten Tomatoes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=''King Kong'' (2005) | work=rottentomatoes.com | url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/king_kong/ | accessdate=2006-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common criticisms of the film were due to excessive length, lack of pace, over-use of slow motion, and some obvious use of [[Computer-generated imagery|CGI]] effects. Positive critical reviews regarded it as one of the few good epics and all-round best movies of 2005. [[Roger Ebert]] gave the movie four stars, and listed it as the 8th best film of 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Ebert, Roger| date= December 18, 2005| title=Ebert's Best 10 Movies of 2005| work=rogerebert.com | url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20051218/COMMENTARY/512180302 | accessdate=2006-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, ''King Kong'' has been included in many critics' Top Ten of 2005 lists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The 2005 Top Ten's | work=Awards Watch | url=http://www.moviecitynews.com/awards/2006/top_tens/critics_01.html|accessdate=2006-05-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060324050559/http://www.moviecitynews.com/awards/2006/top_tens/critics_01.html |archivedate = March 24, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film received four [[Academy Award]] nominations for [[Academy Award for Visual Effects|Visual Effects]], [[Academy Award for Best Sound|Sound Mixing]] ([[Christopher Boyes]], [[Michael Semanick]], [[Michael Hedges (sound engineer)|Michael Hedges]], [[Hammond Peek]]), [[Academy Award for Sound Editing|Sound Editing]], and [[Academy Award for Best Art Direction|Art Direction]], winning all but the last.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oscars2006&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oscars.org/awards/academyawards/legacy/ceremony/78th-winners.html |title=The 78th Academy Awards (2006) Nominees and Winners |accessdate=2011-11-20|work=oscars.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Oscars 2006: The nominees | work=BBC News | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/4665684.stm | accessdate=2008-11-06 | date=2006-01-31 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' called the depiction of Kong the most convincing computer generated character in film in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Our 10 Favorite CG Characters | publisher = ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' | url = http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20041669_20041686_20046918_9,00.html | accessdate=2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some criticised the film for retaining racist stereotypes present in the original film, though it was not suggested that Jackson had done this intentionally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Big black and bad stereotyping | work=Times Online | author= McKenzie, Kwame| date= December 13, 2005| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,6-1922429,00.html | accessdate=2006-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
''King Kong'' ranks 450th on ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine's 2008 list of the 500 Greatest Movies of All Time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.empireonline.com/500/10.asp |title=Empire Features |publisher=Empireonline.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Future==
===Possible 3-D release===
Peter Jackson has expressed his desire to remaster the film in 3-D at some point in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=| date= April 25, 2006| title=Film director 'sees future in 3D'| work=BBC | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4942338.stm | accessdate=2006-06-13 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson was also seen shooting with a 3-D&amp;nbsp;camera at times during the shoot of ''King Kong''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=McLean, Robyn | date= November 12, 2005| title=''King Kong'' movie may go 3D| work=The Dominion Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cinematic and literary allusions==
*Jamie Bell's character is repeatedly shown reading [[Joseph Conrad|Joseph Conrad's]] ''[[Heart of Darkness]]'', a novel about a journey into a primitive land and mankind's exploitation of fellow man. 

*Jack Black and critics have noted Carl Denham's similarity to [[Orson Welles]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Spelling, Ian| month=December | year=2005| title=Interview:Peter Jackson proves with ''King Kong'' that the director, not the beast, is the true eighth wonder of the world | work=Sci Fi.com | url=http://www.scifi.com/sfw/issue452/interview.html|accessdate=2006-06-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060619091002/http://www.scifi.com/sfw/issue452/interview.html |archivedate = June 19, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

*When Jack Driscoll is searching for a place to sleep in the animal storage hold, a box behind him reads ''[[Sumatran Rat Monkey]] — Beware the bite!'' – a reference to the creature that causes mayhem in Peter Jackson's film ''[[Braindead (1992 film)|Braindead]]'' (1992)&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Wloszczyna, Susan| date= December 15, 2005| title=''King Kong'' abounds with fun facts for fanboys| work=USA Today | url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2005-12-15-kong-fanboy-references_x.htm| accessdate=2006-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; (in that film, the rat monkey is described as only being found on [[Skull Island]]).

===References to earlier versions of ''King Kong''===
*[[Fay Wray]], the original [[Ann Darrow]], was asked by Peter Jackson to do a brief cameo in which she would utter the film's final line: &quot;It was beauty killed the beast.&quot; At first she flatly refused, but then seemed to consider the possibility. However, she died shortly after her meeting with Jackson.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Spelling, Ian| month=December | year=2005| title=Interview:Peter Jackson proves with ''King Kong'' that the director, not the beast, is the true eighth wonder of the world | work=Sci Fi.com | url=http://www.scifi.com/sfw/issue452/interview.html | accessdate=2006-06-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060619091002/http://www.scifi.com/sfw/issue452/interview.html |archivedate = June 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The line ultimately went to the character of Carl Denham, as in the original.

* An ad for [[Universal Pictures]] is visible while Kong is tearing up [[Times Square]]. In the original film, an ad for [[Columbia Pictures]] appeared in the same spot, and the production designers replicated it, but Columbia asked for a large amount of money for its use, so effects artists replaced it.&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;/&gt;

* When Denham is considering who to play the part before meeting Ann, he suggests &quot;Fay&quot;, but his assistant Preston replies, &quot;She's doing a [[King Kong (1933 film)|picture]] with [[RKO Pictures|RKO]].&quot;  Music from the 1933&amp;nbsp;original is heard, and Denham mutters, &quot;Cooper, huh? I might have known.&quot;  [[Fay Wray]] starred in the 1933&amp;nbsp;film, which was directed by [[Merian C. Cooper]] and released by RKO.&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Wloszczyna, Susan| date= December 15, 2005| title=''King Kong'' abounds with fun facts for fanboys| work=USA Today|url=http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2005-12-15-kong-fanboy-references_x.htm| accessdate=2006-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* When Carl Denham calls Bruce Baxter and Ann Darrow to film a scene on the deck of the ship, the shot is essentially identical to a scene between Ann and Jack Driscoll in the 1933 version.

* In the original film, [[Merian C. Cooper]] made up an &quot;Arabian proverb&quot; about &quot;beauty and beast&quot;. The 2005 remake repeats the fake proverb.&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;/&gt;

* Kong's New York stage appearance looks very much like a re-enactment of the sacrifice scene of the 1933&amp;nbsp;film, including the posts the 'beauty' is tied to and the nearly identical performance and costumes of the dancers. In addition, the music played by the orchestra during that scene is the original 1933&amp;nbsp;score by [[Max Steiner]].&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;/&gt;

* The 1933 film featured an extended sequence in which several members of the party were devoured by massive spiders and insects after being shaken off a log into a ravine by Kong. This scene was pulled before release when Cooper decided it slowed the film down. Peter Jackson recreated the scene for the 2005&amp;nbsp;remake. He also paid homage to the spider pit sequence by recreating the scene using stop motion photography, which he included as an extra for the deluxe DVD release of the original 1933&amp;nbsp;film.

* The battle between Kong and the final ''T. rex'' is almost move-for-move like the last half of the fight between Kong and the ''T.&amp;nbsp;rex'' in the original 1933&amp;nbsp;film, right down to Kong playing with the dinosaur's broken jaw and then standing, beating his chest and roaring victoriously.&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;/&gt;

*After the crew captures Kong on the beach, Denham speaks a line from the 1933 film: &quot;''The whole world will pay to see this! We're millionaires, boys! I'll share it with all of you. In a few months, his name will be up in lights on Broadway! KONG, THE EIGHTH WONDER OF THE WORLD!''&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;/&gt;

*In the original film, director and co-director [[Merian C. Cooper]] and [[Ernest B. Schoedsack]] appear in cameos as the pilot and rear-gunner who shoot Kong. In the 2005 film, Jackson plays one of the gunners; the pilot is played by [[Richard A. Baker|Rick Baker]], who played Kong (in a rubber suit) in the 1976&amp;nbsp;remake.&lt;ref name=&quot;References&quot;/&gt;

==Soundtrack==
{{Infobox album &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Albums --&gt;
| Name        = King Kong: Original Motion Picture Soundtrack
| Type        = [[Soundtrack]]
| Artist      = [[James Newton Howard]]
| Cover       = KingKong2005Soundtrack.jpg
| Released    = December 6, 2005
| Recorded    = 2005
| Genre       = [[Soundtrack]]
| Length      = 74:27
| Label       = [[Decca Records]]
| Producer    =
| Last album  = [[Batman Begins (soundtrack)|Batman Begins]]&lt;br/ &gt;(2005)
| This album  = King Kong&lt;br/ &gt;(2005)
| Next album  = Freedomland&lt;br/ &gt;(2006)
}}

'''''King Kong: Original Motion Picture Soundtrack''''' was composed by [[James Newton Howard]]. Originally [[Howard Shore]], who worked for Peter Jackson on ''The Lord of the Rings'', was to compose the score for the film and recorded several completed cues before he was removed from the project by Jackson. Shore makes a cameo appearance as the conductor in the theatre from which Kong escapes. The film's record album was nominated for the [[Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

;Track listing
#&quot;King Kong&quot; – 1:09
#&quot;A Fateful Meeting&quot; – 4:16
#&quot;Defeat Is Always Momentary&quot; – 2:48
#&quot;It's In the Subtext&quot; – 3:19
#&quot;Two Grand&quot; – 2:34
#&quot;The Venture Departs&quot; – 4:03
#&quot;Last Blank Space On the Map&quot; – 4:43
#&quot;It's Deserted&quot; – 7:08
#&quot;Something Monstrous… Neither Beast Nor Man&quot; – 2:38
#&quot;Head Towards the Animals&quot; – 2:48
#&quot;Beautiful&quot; – 4:08
#&quot;Tooth and Claw&quot; – 6:17
#&quot;That's All There Is…&quot; – 3:26
#&quot;Captured&quot; – 2:25
#&quot;Central Park&quot; – 4:36
#&quot;The Empire State Building&quot; – 2:36
#&quot;Beauty Killed the Beast (Part I)&quot; – 1:59
#&quot;Beauty Killed the Beast (Part II)&quot; – 2:22
#&quot;Beauty Killed the Beast (Part III)&quot; – 2:14
#&quot;Beauty Killed the Beast (Part IV)&quot; – 4:45
#&quot;Beauty Killed the Beast (Part V)&quot; – 4:13

The music played during the vaudeville sequence at the beginning of the movie is the classic song &quot;I'm Sitting on Top of the World&quot; by [[Al Jolson]]. However, it has not been included in the original soundtrack album.

==Home media==
''King Kong'' was released on DVD on March 28, 2006 in the United States. The three versions that came out were single disc [[fullscreen]], single disc [[widescreen]] and a 2-Disc Widescreen Special Edition. The second disc of the Special Edition contains the remainder of almost all the KongisKing.net production diaries not contained on the ''Peter Jackson's Production Diaries'' DVD set. The only missing episode is ''&quot;13&amp;nbsp;Weeks To Go&quot;'' which contained footage of Howard Shore recording the original score. It is still available on the website. ''King Kong'' was not released on [[VHS]] in the United States, but it was exclusively released on VHS in [[Germany]].

The 3 disc Deluxe Extended Edition was released on November&amp;nbsp;14, 2006 in the [[U.S.A.]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dvdactive.com/news/releases/king-kong3.html ''King Kong'' (US – DVD R1) in News &gt; Releases at DVDActive&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and on November 1 in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ezydvd.com.au/item.zml/789627 ''King Kong'' (2005) – Deluxe Extended Edition (3 Disc Set) @ EzyDVD&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Thirteen minutes were put back into the film, and a further 40&amp;nbsp;minutes presented alongside the rest of the special features. The film was spread onto the first two discs with commentary by Peter Jackson and Philippa Boyens, and some featurettes on Discs 1 and 2, whilst the main Special Features are on Disc&amp;nbsp;3. Another set was released, including a WETA figurine of a bullet-ridden Kong scaling the Empire State Building, roaring at the army with Ann in hand. The extended film amounts to 201&amp;nbsp;minutes in total.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release| title = Official Universal Press Release on the Extended Edition!| publisher = KongisKing.net| date = 2006-07-20| url = http://www.kongisking.net/perl/newsview/17/1153423812| accessdate = 2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A special [[HD DVD]] version of ''King Kong'' was part of a promotional pack for the release of the external HD DVD Drive for the [[Xbox 360]]. The pack contained the HD DVD drive, the Universal Media Remote and ''King Kong'' on HD DVD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xbox.com/en-US/hardware/x/xbox360hddvdplayer/ Xbox.com]&lt;/ref&gt; It was also available separately as a standard HD DVD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hddvd.highdefdigest.com/kingkong2005.html Highdefdigest]&lt;/ref&gt; The film's theatrical and extended cuts were released together on [[Blu-ray Disc]] on January 20, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bluray.highdefdigest.com/news/show/Universal/Disc_Announcements/King_Kong_to_Roar_on_Blu-ray_this_January/2245|title='King Kong' to Roar on Blu-ray this January|date=2008-11-11|accessdate=2008-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikinews|2006 Oscars handed out at Kodak Theatre}}
* {{Official website|http://kingkongmovie.com}}
* {{IMDb title|0360717|King Kong}}
* {{Allmovie title|289249|King Kong}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|king_kong|King Kong}}
* {{mojo title|kingkong05|King Kong}}

{{KingKong}}
{{Peter Jackson}}
{{Empire Award for Best Film}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:King Kong}}
[[Category:2005 films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:New Zealand films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:2000s adventure films]]
[[Category:Best Film Empire Award winners]]
[[Category:Best Sound Editing Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Dinosaur films]]
[[Category:Epic films]]
[[Category:Films about filmmaking]]
[[Category:Fantasy adventure films]] 
[[Category:American comedy-drama films]]
[[Category:Film remakes]]
[[Category:Films directed by Peter Jackson]]
[[Category:Films set in the 1930s]]
[[Category:Films set in 1933]]
[[Category:Films set in New York City]]
[[Category:Empire State Building]]
[[Category:Films that won the Best Sound Mixing Academy Award]]
[[Category:Films that won the Best Visual Effects Academy Award]]
[[Category:King Kong films]]
[[Category:Universal Pictures films]]
[[Category:WingNut Films productions]]
[[Category:Performance capture in film]]

[[ar:كينج كونج (فيلم 2005)]]
[[cs:King Kong (film, 2005)]]
[[cy:King Kong (ffilm 2005)]]
[[da:King Kong (2005 film)]]
[[de:King Kong (2005)]]
[[es:King Kong (película de 2005)]]
[[fa:کینگ کونگ (فیلم ۲۰۰۵)]]
[[fr:King Kong (film, 2005)]]
[[ga:King Kong (scannán 2005)]]
[[gl:King Kong (filme de 2005)]]
[[ko:킹콩 (2005년 영화)]]
[[id:King Kong (film 2005)]]
[[it:King Kong (film 2005)]]
[[hu:King Kong (film, 2005)]]
[[nl:King Kong (2005)]]
[[ja:キング・コング (2005年の映画)]]
[[no:King Kong (2005)]]
[[pl:King Kong (film 2005)]]
[[pt:King Kong (2005)]]
[[ru:Кинг-Конг (фильм, 2005)]]
[[sk:King Kong (film z roku 2005)]]
[[fi:King Kong (vuoden 2005 elokuva)]]
[[sv:King Kong (2005)]]
[[tr:King Kong (film, 2005)]]
[[uk:Кінг-Конг (фільм, 2005)]]
[[zh:金剛 (2005年電影)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
