<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="473073" ns="0" title="The Irresponsible Captain Tylor"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=July 2008}}
{{Infobox animanga/Header
| name            = The Irresponsible Captain Tylor
| image           = [[File:Tylor-p1.jpg|240px]]
| caption         = Tylor (front), Yamamoto (right), Yuriko (left).
| ja_kanji        = 無責任艦長タイラー
| ja_romaji       = Musekinin Kanchō Tairā
| genre           = Adventure, Comedy, Military, Science Fiction, Space Opera
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Print
| type            = light novel
| author          = [[Hitoshi Yoshioka]]
| illustrator     = 
| publisher       = [[Fujimi Fantasia Bunko]]
| publisher_en    = 
| demographic     = 
| label           = 
| magazine        = Dragon Magazine
| first           = June 6, 2003
| last            = 
| volumes         = 11
| volume_list     =
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Video
| type            = tv series
| director        = [[Kōichi Mashimo]]
| producer        = 
| writer          = [[Koichi Mashimo]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hiroyuki Kawasaki]]
| music           = 
| studio          = [[Tatsunoko Production]]
| network         = [[TV Tokyo]]
| licensor        = {{flagicon|United States}} [[The Right Stuf International|Nozomi Entertainment]]
| first           = January 25, 1993
| last            = July 19, 1993
| episodes        = 26
| episode_list    = 
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Video
| type            = ova
| director        = [[Kōichi Mashimo]] (1-2)&lt;br&gt;[[Naoyuki Yoshinaga]] (3-10)
| producer        = 
| writer          = 
| music           = 
| studio          = Yume&lt;br&gt;[[Studio Deen]]
| licensor        = {{flagicon|United States}} [[The Right Stuf International|Nozomi Entertainment]]
| licensor_other  = {{flagicon|Germany}} [[OVA Films]] 2002&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|ROC}} [[MDS Multimedia]]
| first           = October 1, 1994
| last            = August 1, 1996
| runtime         = 
| episodes        = 10
| episode_list    = 
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Print
| type            = manga
| title           = Love &amp; War
| author          = [[Hitoshi Yoshioka]]
| illustrator     = [[Kotaro Mori]]
| publisher       = [[Enterbrain]]
| publisher_other = {{flagicon|Germany}} [[Egmont]] 2004
| demographic     = ''[[Shōnen manga|Shōnen]]''
| magazine        = 
| published       = 2001
| first           = 
| last            = 
| volumes         = 3
| volume_list     = 
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Footer}}

{{nihongo|'''''The Irresponsible Captain Tylor'''''|無責任艦長タイラー|Musekinin Kanchō Tairā}} is an [[anime]] series based on {{nihongo|''The Most Irresponsible Man in Space''|宇宙一の無責任男|Uchū Ichi no Musekinin Otoko}} [[light novel]] series by [[Hitoshi Yoshioka]]. It was produced by some of Japan's larger studios, including [[Big West Advertising|Big West]], [[Tatsunoko Production]], [[King Records (Japan)|King Records]] and [[Video and Audio Project|VAP]].

''Tylor'' consists of a 26-episodes TV series created by [[Kōichi Mashimo]], and a sequel [[Original Video Animation|OVA]] series of 10 episodes directed by Mashimo and [[Naoyuki Yoshinaga]]. The TV show premiered in Japan on [[TV Tokyo]] between January 25, 1993 and July 19, 1993, and was broadcast across [[Latin America]] by the television network, Magic Kids. Both series were broadcast across the United States by [[AZN Television]]. ''Tylor'' is distributed across [[North America]] by [[The Right Stuf International]]. 

It is usually classified as humorous [[space opera]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themanime.org/viewreview.php?id=345 Irresponsible Captain Tylor] review at THEM Anime Reviews&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Enterbrain]] published a 3-volume [[manga]] miniseries in 2001.

== Plot ==
In a distant, highly technological future, Tylor, the title character, is a mysterious young man without a real purpose in life, a state of mind that is very hard to determine, and a knack for accidentally getting out of near-death situations with a childishly cavalier attitude. He sometimes does not even seem to realize when he is in danger, which is actually an asset to him on many occasions.

Tylor stumbles his way into the United Planets Space Force, and soon gains command of a destroyer, after resolving a hostage dispute and saving a retired admiral. Despite being given a decrepit and underpowered ship (the Soyokaze), thanks to brilliant strokes of luck, Tylor manages to destroy a patrol group. This is quickly followed by a sneak attack on another patrol group, performed while Tylor was playing the role of a consummate, professional soldier. The admiralty, attempting to kill Tylor, present him with a medal modified with a device to trick the Raalgon fleet into believing the Soyokaze is an entire fleet. Tylor loses the medal in UPSF HQ, and the Raalgons destroy the admiralty's super-weapon instead. The Soyokaze is then sent to a demotion sector, despite the fervent hopes of its crew. There, Tylor and Yamamoto encounter the ghost of the former Captain, who vanishes due to depression after seeing Tylor's behavior. The Admiral of the Fleet, who actually murdered the prior Captain, rescinds Tylor's demotion after seeing Tylor with the former captains pipe, thinking he is now aware of the admiral's crime. Tylor is then captured by the Raalgon fleet, who plan to execute him to boost morale. After escaping his cell, Tylor encounters the Empress of the Raalgon, Azalyn, in plain dress, and spends the day entertaining her. She stops his execution, and his jailors implant microchip in his brain to control him. Meanwhile, the crew of the Soyokaze has been imprisoned by the brass.  They manage to escape captivity and invade the Melva, the main Raalgon ship, in order to get Tylor back.  During the fight, Tylor saves Azalyn from a bomb that her treacherous Prime Minister Wang had detonated in order to gain power for himself.  Tylor is badly injured, and Azalyn tells the Raalgon that she is going with Tylor back to the Soyokaze in order to make sure he is alright.  After the doctor saves Tylor, Azalyn returns back to her people.  Tylor then rendezvouses with the main fleet, where he is branded a traitor for letting Azalyn return.  He is sentenced to death by a firing squad.  However, Tylor convinces the brass that he can defeat the Raalgon, and they reluctantly allow him to take complete command.  After coming to a stand-off with Dom, Tylor manages to spill no blood and stop the fighting for the time being.  After the death of Admiral Hanner, who Tylor had adored and talked with, Tylor becomes sullen and announces he will leave the military.  Lieutenant Yamamoto is given command of the brand new ship, the Aso.  In the final episode, the former crew of the Soyokaze, who are supposed to be on the Aso, join Tylor on the Soyokaze as they fly out into space.

The two major powers in the story are the ''UPSF'' (United Planets Space Force, or the humans, possibly a reference to the [[Earth Federation|Earth Federation Space Force]] of ''[[Mobile Suit Gundam]]'', or the [[United Federation of Planets]] of ''[[Star Trek]]'', or perhaps both) and the ''Raalgon Empire'' (the [[extraterrestrials]]), who with their pointy ears share a resemblance to either [[elves]] or possibly [[Romulans]].

One of the largest points of dispute within the story is the actual competence of Tylor. Several characters say of Tylor, &quot;I can't decide if he's an idiot or a genius.&quot; Whether he is a genius or an idiot is up to each individual viewer.

==Characters==
{{Main|List of The Irresponsible Captain Tylor characters}}
[[File:Captain Tylor Soyokaze crew.jpg|thumb|right|400px|The main crew of the Soyokaze. Left to right: Beginner Pilots Emi and Yumi Hanner, Second Lt. Kojiro Sakai; First Lt. K. Kim; Sub Lt. Makoto Yamamoto; Lt. Commander Justy Ueki Tylor; Lt. Commander Yuriko Star; First Lt. H. Katori; Master Sgt. M. Cryburn; First Lt. K. B. Andresen; Staff Sgt. Harumi; and Naval Surgeon H. Kitaguchi.]]
{{nihongo|'''Lt. Commander Justy Ueki Tylor'''|ジャスティ・ウエキ・タイラー少佐|Jasuti Ueki Taira-shōsa}} is a mysterious, irresponsible man. Tylor, age 20, joined the United Planets Space Force for what he hoped would be an easy life. Originally assigned to the Pension department, he unwittingly foiled a terrorist plot to kidnap and kill a retired UPSF admiral when he tried to deliver a late check by hand. For saving the war hero's life, Tylor was promoted to Lieutenant Commander and placed in command of the destroyer Soyokaze (the UPSF dumping ground for trouble makers and the unwanted). Tylor has, as his superiors have put it, 'The Devil's own luck' and usually can get out of any situation relatively unscathed, avoiding multiple assassination attempts and defeating enemy groups of vastly superior numbers. He is very laid back and does not really care for the rules, using his authority as captain to change whatever regulations seem too uptight for him. He is also easily led by his crew, who are able to convince him to allow them to wear comfortable clothes on watch, hold a swimsuit competition, and let the surgeon drink while on duty. The UPSF and the Raalgon Empire are constantly debating whether Tylor possesses the most brilliant military mind or whether he is just a lucky moron.&lt;br&gt;
{{anime voices|[[Kouji Tsujitani]]|[[Crispin Freeman]]}}{{-}}

{{nihongo|'''Lt. Commander Yuriko Star'''|ユリコ・スター少佐|Yuriko Sutā-shōsa}} is a very straight-laced, by-the-book officer. Yuriko joined the UPSF to give her life structure and attempts to obey the rules in almost every situation. However, she, unlike Yamamoto, has no problem telling Tylor that he has done something wrong and will even resort to slapping him when he gets too far out of line. Yuriko also tries to downplay her gender, making herself a soldier first, and then a woman. This is a sore subject for her when someone comments about Tylor's obvious attraction to her looks, pointing out that she has never used her appearance to get ahead; an equally sore point for her is her budding attraction to him. Yuriko is one of the most rational and level-headed officers on the Soyokaze. While she is senior to Yamamoto, her speciality as an intelligence officer places her outside the chain of command.&lt;br&gt;
{{anime voices|[[Yuri Amano]]|[[Rachael Lillis]]}}{{-}}

{{nihongo|'''Lieutenant Makoto Yamamoto'''|マコト・ヤマモト大尉|Makoto Yamamoto-taī}} is another very strait-laced, by-the-books military man. Yamamoto is the first officer on the Soyokaze and tried mightily to interject an air of professionalism to the outfit. Constantly enraged by Tylor's lack of discipline and his loose command of the troops, Yamamoto spends much of his free time in the medic's office taking tranquilizers and making use of the neuro-cleanser. Yamamoto sees Tylor for what he is, a bumbling fool, but is torn between the unwritten soldier's code of supporting and obeying your superior officer, and telling the UPSF brass what is REALLY going on. He is always on the lookout for a chance to get some form of command, hoping to get a ship of his own one day.&lt;br&gt;
{{anime voices|[[Sho Hayami]]|J. David Brimmer}}{{-}}

[[File:Azalynzz.jpg|120px|left|Azalyn]]
{{nihongo|'''Azalyn''' |アザリン|Azarin}} is the 16 year old empress of the Holy Raalgon Empire. Azalyn is a child, forced into the unenviable situation of having to assume power of the empire once her parents are murdered. Prompted by her advisors, she gives the command to attack the UPSF (under the assumption that they were behind the assassination plot). Having not had a chance to be a child, Azalyn must now be strong for the entire empire, and it's a task that she is afraid of taking, but even more afraid of failing in.&lt;br&gt;
{{anime voices|[[Hiroko Kasahara]]|Lisa Ortiz}}{{-}}

[[File:Dom01zz.jpg|120px|right|Dom]]
{{nihongo|'''Captain Ru Baraba Dom'''|ル・バラバ・ドム|Ru Baraba Domu}} is the commander of one of the Raalgon fleets. He speaks candidly with the Empress, in stark contrast to the bowing and scraping and lying of the rest of her court. Dom gains Azalyn's trust and becomes one of her more valued advisors. Dom is also very interested in Tylor, feeling that Tylor would be not only a worthy adversary, but also a challenge for anyone to decipher and defeat. It is Dom who assigned Harumi to spy on the Soyokaze's enigmatic captain, but even with the constant data coming in from his valued spy, Dom is still unsure whether Tylor really knows what he is doing or if he is just a fool.&lt;br&gt;
{{anime voices|[[Toshihiko Seki]]|Josh Mosby}}{{-}}

==Light novels==
''The Irresponsible Captain Tylor'' is adapted from the series of light novels ''The Most Irresponsible Man in Space'' by Hitoshi Yoshioka. The series is mainly split into a series of trilogies which cover both the anime story and further onwards. The novels and side stories published so far include:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|date=|title=''The Irresponsible Captain Tylor OVA: Volume IV'' - Liner Notes|url=http://www.tylor.com/|date=August 4, 2009|medium=[[DVD]]|publisher=[[Nozomi Entertainment]]|location=[[Grimes, Iowa|Grimes]], [[Iowa]], [[United States]]|isbn=1-57032-782-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''''The Most Irresponsible Man in Space Series 1''''' (''Uchuuichi no Musekinin Otoko Series 1'')
:1. ''The Irresponsible Captain Tylor'' (''Musekinin Kanchou Tylor'')
:2. ''The Most Irresponsible Man in the Meiji Period'' (''Meiji Ichidai Musekinin Otoko'')
:3. ''Wang Strikes Back!'' (''Wang no Gyakushuu'')

*'''''The Most Irresponsible Man in Space Series 2''''' (''Uchuuichi no Musekinin Otoko Series 2'')
:4. ''The Irresponsible Admiral Tylor'' (''Musekinin Gensui Tylor'')
:5. ''Azalyn, Age 16'' (''Azalyn, 16-sai'')
:6. ''Tylor's Big Turnabout'' (''Tylor no Daigyakuten'')

*'''''The Most Irresponsible Man in Space Series 3''''' (''Uchuuichi no Musekinin Otoko Series 3'')
:7. ''The Irresponsible President Tylor'' (''Musekinin Daitouryou Tylor'')
:8. ''Wind Speed: 40 Light Years!'' (''Fuusoku Yon-Juu Kounen'')
:9. ''The Eternally Irresponsible Man'' (''Eiennare Musekinin Otoko'')

*'''''The Most Irresponsible Man in Space Side Stories''''' (''Uchuuichi no Musekinin Otoko Gaiden'')
:1. ''The Galactic Age of Irresponsiblity'' (''Ginga Musekinin Jidai'')
:2. ''The Samurai of Space'' (''O-zora no Samurai'')
:3. ''The Scarlet Lion'' (''Akaki Shishi'')
:4. ''Rebellion on Ice Planet Horoshiri!'' (''Gentou Wakusei Horoshiri no Hanran'')

*'''''The Irresponsible Kids''''' (''Musekinin Kids'')
:1. ''The Black Sun Belle'' (''Ankoku Taiyou Komachi'')
:2. ''The Storm of &quot;Why?&quot;'' (''Why? no Arashi'')

==Manga==
The [[manga]] ''Love &amp; War'' after a story of [[Hitoshi Yoshioka]] and with the artwork of [[Kotaro Mori]] that was 2001-2002 published by [[Enterbrain]], is set years after the OVA. Tylor is now a Viceadmiral and Captain of the battleship ''Omi''. This time he gets with his fiancée and political officer Lt.Cmdr. Yuriko Star and his staff officer and adjutant Cmdr. Makoto Yamamoto in a timetravel adventure back into the past of Raalgon at the time of the reign of Guze XV.

==Soundtrack==
The soundtrack to both the TV series and the OVA were both released on CD by ADV Films and Right Stuf on June 5, 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rightstuf.com/rsstatic/nozomiEntertainment/pressReleases/archive/rel0501.pdf|title=Release Information: May 2001|publisher=[[Right Stuf]]|format=PDF|date=May 2001|accessdate=August 23rd, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both CDs are no longer for sale.

==Notes and references==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.tylor.com ''The Irresponsible Captain Tylor'' official English site]
*{{imdb title|0106076}}
*{{ann|anime|160}}
*{{ann|OAV|87}}
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20010219065839/j-pop.com/anime/archive/reviews/12_studios/picks.html J-pop.com review]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20040404094119/www.animerica-mag.com/features/tylor_02.html ''Animerica'' review of OVA]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Irresponsible Captain Tylor, The}}
[[Category:Anime of 1993]]
[[Category:Anime of 1994]]
[[Category:Anime of 1995]]
[[Category:Anime of 1996]]
[[Category:Adventure anime and manga]]
[[Category:Anime series]]
[[Category:Comedy anime and manga]]
[[Category:Light novels]]
[[Category:Science fiction anime and manga]]
[[Category:Space opera]]
[[Category:Anime OVAs]]
[[Category:1994 Japanese television series debuts]]
[[Category:1997 Japanese television series endings]]
[[Category:TV Tokyo shows]]

[[de:The Irresponsible Captain Tylor]]
[[es:Irresponsable capitán Taylor]]
[[fr:Irresponsable capitaine Tylor]]
[[ko:무책임 함장 테일러]]
[[it:L'irresponsabile capitano Tylor]]
[[ja:無責任艦長タイラー (アニメ)]]
[[ru:The Irresponsible Captain Tylor]]
[[zh:无责任舰长]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
