<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="475446" ns="0" title="Fedora Project"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Fedora Project logo.png|thumb|The Fedora Project logo]]

The '''Fedora Project''' is an endeavor sponsored by [[Red Hat]] to co-ordinate the development of the [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] [[operating system]]. Founded on September 2003 as a result of a merger between the [[Red Hat Linux]] (RHL) and old Fedora Linux projects. The project consists, not only of Red Hat employees, but community members worldwide which make up 75% of all contributors within the Fedora Project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://press.redhat.com/2008/05/28/ride-the-wave-with-fedora-9/ | title=Ride the Wave with Fedora 9  | accessdate=2009-11-24 | date=2008-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The Fedora project was founded December 2002 by University of Hawaii Computer Science student Warren Togami. When Red Hat decided to split [[Red Hat]] [[Linux]] to [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] (RHEL) and a community-based version, the name [[Fedora (operating system) | Fedora]] was eventually selected&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fedora.us/ | title=Announcement: Red Hat Linux Merging with Fedora Linux | archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20031001204515/http://www.fedora.us/ | archivedate=October 1, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;, it left the existing small business and home users with some uncertainty about what to do. Red Hat Professional Workstation was created at this same time with the intention of filling the niche that RHL had once filled but it was created without a certain future.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url=http://www.linux.com/articles/34346?theme=print | title=linux.com :: Red Hat Professional Workstation:More Expensive,Fewer features |accessdate=2007-12-21 |date= 2004-02-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This option quickly fell to the wayside for non-enterprise RHL users in favor of Fedora.  The Fedora community continues to thrive and the Fedora distribution has a reputation as being a [[FOSS]] distribution that focuses on innovation and close work with upstream Linux communities.

=== Security intrusion ===
In August 2008 several Fedora servers were compromised. Upon investigation it was found that one of the compromised servers was used for signing Fedora update [[Software package (installation)|packages]]. The Fedora Project stated that the attacker(s) did not get the package [[Digital signature#Authentication|signing key]] which could be used  to introduce malicious software onto Fedora users' systems through the update process. Project administrators performed checks on the software and did not find anything to suggest that a [[Trojan horse]] had been introduced into the software. As a precaution the Project converted to new package signing keys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.securityfocus.com/news/11532 |title=Security Breach—securityfocus.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2008-August/msg00012.html |title=Security Breach—Red Hat Mailing list}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fedora published the full details on 30 March 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2009-March/msg00010.html |title=Update and Report on Fedora August 2008 Intrusion—Red Hat Mailing list}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Governance ==
The Fedora Project is not a separate legal entity or organization; Red Hat retains liability for its actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://interviews.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=06/08/17/177220 | title =  Fedora Project Leader Max Spevack Responds to Slashdot Questions | accessdate=2007-02-12 | date = 2006-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Fedora Project Board is responsible for the direction of the Fedora Project and comprises four Red Hat appointed members and five community-elected members.  Additionally, Red Hat appoints a chairman who has veto power over any board decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url = http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Board | title = The Fedora Project Board | accessdate = 2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within Red Hat, this chairman holds the position of &quot;Fedora Project Leader&quot;.  Red Hat at one point created a separate ''Fedora Foundation'' to govern the project,&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url = http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1823403,00.asp | title = Red Hat Creates Fedora Foundation | author = Peter Galli | date = 2005-06-03 | accessdate = 2007-02-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; but after consideration of a variety of issues, canceled it in favor of the board model currently in place.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url = http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Foundation | title = The Fedora Foundation | accessdate = 2007-02-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url = http://www.redhat.com/archives/fedora-announce-list/2006-April/msg00016.html | title = Fedora Foundation | author = Max Spevack | date = 2006-04-04 | accessdate = 2007-02-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The project facilitates online communication amongst its developers and community members through public mailing lists and wiki pages. It also coordinates an annual summit known as the Fedora Users and Developers Conference (commonly called FUDCon).  Additional conferences have taken place in Germany, England and India.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url=http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/FUDCon/ | title = FUDCon | accessdate=2007-02-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071008123509/http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/FUDCon/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Fedora (operating system)]]
* [[Red Hat]]
* [[Rawhide (computing)|Rawhide]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*{{official|http://fedoraproject.org}}

{{Red Hat}}

[[Category:Fedora Project|*]]
[[Category:Free software projects]]

[[es:Proyecto Fedora]]
[[fr:Fedora Project]]
[[ko:페도라 프로젝트]]
[[id:Fedora Project]]
[[he:פרויקט פדורה]]
[[ms:Projek Fedora]]
[[ja:Fedora Project]]
[[uz:Fedora Loyihasi]]
[[pl:Fedora Project]]
[[pt:Projeto Fedora]]
[[ru:Проект Fedora]]
[[simple:Fedora Project]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
