<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4757816" ns="0" title="Bahram Bayzai"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name = بهرام بیضائی&lt;br&gt;Bahrām Beizai
| image =Bahram Bayzai.jpg
| imagesize = 170px
| caption = 
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1938|12|26}}
| birth_place = [[File:Flag of Iran.svg|25px]] [[Tehran]], [[Iran]]
| death_date = 
| death_place = 
| occupation = [[Film director]], [[Theatre director]], [[Screenwriter]], [[Playwright]]
}}

'''Bahrām Beyzāi''' (also spelt '''Bahrām Beizai''', '''Bahrām Beyzaie''', {{lang-fa| بهرام بیضائی}}, born 26 December 1938 in [[Tehran]]) is an [[Iran]]ian [[film director]], [[theatre director]], [[screenwriter]], [[playwright]], [[film editor]], [[film producer|producer]], and [[researcher]]. 

Bahram Beyzai is the son of the poet Ostād Ne'mat'ollāh Beyzāi &lt;ref&gt;Two thousand verse lines by ''Zokā'i Beyzāi'', of a total of six thousand, were published in 1978 (1357 [[Iranian calendar|AH]]) in a book entitled ''Yad-e Bayzā'' (The White Hand); ''Bayzā'' in Persian is the literary word for ''White''. See Arash Fanā'iān, ''Gofteman-e Iran'', January 20, 2008. [http://www.goftman-iran.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=922&amp;Itemid=11].&lt;/ref&gt;  (best known by his literary pseudonym ''Zokā'i Beyzāi'' - ذکائی بیضائی). The celebrated poet Adib Ali Beyzāi, considered as one of the most profound poets of the twentieth-century [[Iran]], is Bahram Beyzai's paternal uncle.&lt;ref&gt;Arash Fanā'iān, ''Gofteman-e Iran'', January 20, 2008. [http://www.goftman-iran.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=922&amp;Itemid=11]. It is noteworthy that Adib Ali Beyzāi's son, Hossein Beyzāi, is also a poet; his literary pseudonym is ''Partow'' (Ray of Light).&lt;/ref&gt; Bahram Beyzai's paternal grandfather, Mirzā Mohammad-Rezā Ārāni (''Ebn Ruh'' -  ابن روح), and paternal great-grandfather, the mulla Mohammad-Faqih Ārāni (''Ruh'ol-Amin'' - روح الامین), were also renown poets.&lt;ref&gt;Arash Fanā'iān, ''Gofteman-e Iran'', January 20, 2008. [http://www.goftman-iran.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=922&amp;Itemid=11].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Beyzai is part of a generation of filmmakers in the [[Iranian New Wave]], a [[Persian cinema]] movement that started in the late 1960s and includes other pioneering directors such as [[Abbas Kiarostami]], [[Forough Farrokhzad]], [[Sohrab Shahid Sales]], and [[Parviz Kimiavi]]. The filmmakers share many common techniques including the use of poetic dialog, references to traditional [[Persian art]] and culture and [[allegorical]] story-telling often dealing with political and philosophical issues.

==Early career==
[[File:YoungBahramBayzai.jpg|thumb|150px|Bahram Beyzai as a young man in the early 1960s during his period of Persian artistic study]]
Beyzai was interested in the arts from a very young age. In high school, [[Dar'ol-Fonoun]],&lt;ref&gt;For an illustrated report on Dar'ol-Fonoun see: Hamid-Reza Hosseini, ''Dar'ol-Fonoun in want of Love'' (&quot;Dar'ol-Fonoun dar hasrat-e eshq&quot;), in Persian, Jadid Online, September 22, 2008, [http://www.jadidonline.com/stry/22092008/frnk/darolfonoon]. The pertinent photographs (15 in total) can be viewed here: [http://www.jadidonline.com/slideshow/695/1]. The following is the photograph of what used to be the [[amphitheatre]] of Dar'ol-Fonoun: [http://www.jadidonline.com/slideshow/695/13].&lt;/ref&gt; he wrote two historical plays which went on to become his preferred method of writing. He studied literature at [[Tehran University]], but started skipping school from around the age of 17 in order to go to movies which were becoming popular in Iran at a rapid pace. This only fed his hunger to learn more about the [[cinema of Iran]] and the visual arts. At the age of 21 he did substantial research on the traditional Persian plays,  ''Book of Kings ([[Shahname]])'' and [[Ta'zieh]] and by 1961 he had already spent a great deal of time studying and researching other ancient [[Persian people|Persian]] and pre-[[Islamic]] culture and literature. This in turn led him to studying Eastern theatre and traditional Iranian theatre and arts which would help him formulate a new non-western identity for Iranian theatre. He also became acquainted with Persian painting.

By late 1961 he had already published numerous articles in various arts and literary journals. In 1962 he made his first short film (4 minutes) in 8&amp;nbsp;mm format. In the next two years he wrote several plays and published &quot;Theatre in Japan&quot;. 

In the next eight or so years of his life throughout the early to late 1960s, Bayzai dedicated to writing in various publications about Eastern art and Persian literature enabled through his extensive study and also wrote a number of essays about Iranian cinema which later became the subject of one of his books. It is during this period that he wrote popular books which are often regarded as masterpieces; ''The Eight Voyage of Sinbad'', ''Banquet'', ''Serpant King'', ''Dolls'', ''The Story of the Hidden Moon'' and many more.

In 1968, Beyzai became one of the first people to join the Iranian Writer's Guild, a highly controversial organization in Iran in the face of [[censorship]], known as the ''Kanun-e Nevisandegan-e Iran''.

==Theatrical career and playwriting==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:TheMarionettes.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The Marionettes puppet play]] --&gt;
Beyzai's early study and interest in [[drama]] and the theatre is well known, but less well-known is his early work as a dramatist. As a young man Beyzai had always been fascinated by the traditions of Iranian [[theatre]], and this included the [[puppet]] theatre. His &quot;Se Nemayeshname-ye 'Arusaki&quot; (&quot;Three Puppet Plays&quot;) was published in 1963, and &quot;The Marionettes&quot; was the first one of these three plays. But for all that it is unmistakably based on the model of the traditional [[puppet]] theatre, &quot;The Marionettes&quot; is shaped by other traditions, too. It is the work of someone au fait with the work of [[Pirandello]] and the [[Theatre of the Absurd]]. In the 1960s, plays by dramatists such as [[Beckett]] and [[Ionesco]] were often translated into the [[Persian language]] and performed in Iran soon after their premieres in the West). Drawing on these varied influences, Beyzai's play is a little-known master-piece of twentieth-century drama. 
Beyzaie's &quot;Drama in Iran&quot; (Namayesh dar Iran), published in late 1960s is still considered the most important text on the history of Iranian theater. Beyzaie is also the first scholar in Iran to publish books on theater in China and Japan.

Some of his plays such as his masterpiece &quot;Marg-e Yazdgerd&quot; (&quot;Death of Yazdgerd&quot;) have been made into films.

===Theatres===
Beyzaie has over 50 published plays, some of which are:
* &quot;Gorob dar Diari Garib&quot; (Sunset in a Strange Land)
* &quot;Chahar Sandoogh&quot; (Four Chests)
* &quot;Hashtomin Safar e Sandbad&quot; ( The Eighth Voyage of Sinbad) 
* ''Ziāfat va Mirās'' (1967 - aka ''Heritage and The Feast'')
* ''Soltān-Mār'' (1969 - aka ''The King Snake'')
* ''[[Death of Yazdgerd|Marg-e Yazdgerd]]'' (1979 - aka ''Death of Yazdgerd'')
* ''Kārnāme-ye Bandār Bidakhsh'' (1997 and 1998)
* ''Bānū Aoi'' (1997 and 1998) (based on [[Aoi no Ue|The Lady Aoi]] by [[Yukio Mishima]])
* ''Shab-e Hezār-o-yekom'' (2003)
* ''[[Afra, or the day passes|Afrā yā Rooz migozarad]]'' (2007 - aka ''Afra, or the day passes'')
نمایشنامه‌ها [ویرایش]مترسک‌ها در شب-۱۳۴۱
سه نمایشنامهٔ عروسکی: 
عروسک‌ها-۱۳۴۱
غروب در دیاری غریب-۱۳۴۱
قصهٔ ماه پنهان-۱۳۴۲
پهلوان اکبر می‌میرد-۱۳۴۲
هشتمین سفر سندباد-۱۳۴۳
دنیای مطبوعاتی آقای اسراری-۱۳۴۵
سلطان‌مار-۱۳۴۵
میراث و ضیافت-۱۳۴۶
چهار صندوق-۱۳۴۶
ساحل نجات-۱۳۴۷
در حضور باد-۱۳۴۷
دیوان بلخ-۱۳۴۷
گمشدگان-۱۳۴۸
راه طوفانی فرمان پسر فرمان از میان تاریکی-۱۳۴۹
ندبه-۱۳۵۶
نوشته‌های دیواری-۱۳۵۷
مرگ یزدگرد-۱۳۵۸
خاطرات هنرپیشهٔ نقش دوم-۱۳۶۰
فتح‌نامه کلات-۱۳۶۱
پرده‌خانه-۱۳۶۴
جنگ‌نامه غلامان-۱۳۶۷
طرب‌نامه-۱۳۷۳
سهراب‌کشی-۱۳۷۳
مجلس بساط برچیدن-۱۳۷۶
افرا یا روز می‌گذرد-۱۳۷۶
مجلس قربانی سنمار-۱۳۷۷
گزارش ارداویراف-۱۳۷۸
مجلس ضربت زدن-۱۳۷۹
شب هزار و یکم-۱۳۸۲
دیوان نمایش (جلد یک و دو)-۱۳۸۲
مجلس شبیه در ذکر مصائب استاد نوید ماکان و همسرش مهندس رخشید فرزین-۱۳۸۳
تاراج نامه -[۴]۱۳۹۰
فیلم‌نامه‌ها [ویرایش]

==Cinematic career==
&lt;!-- This use of this image has no rationale on the image's page. Please read [[Wikipedia:NFCC#10c]] [[File:BashutheLittleStranger.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Bashu, the Little Stranger]] (1989)]] --&gt;
In 1969 he began his film career by directing the short film ''Amu Sibilou'' (Uncle Moustache) followed by &quot;Safar&quot; in 1970.

Immediately after, in 1971, he made his first feature film &quot;Ragbar&quot; (&quot;Downpour&quot;) which is regarded by critics to this day as one of the most successful Iranian films ever made. The successful film addresses the late [[Parviz Fannizadeh]] as its central character and [[protagonist]].

Since then he has produced and directed 8 films including ''Qaribe va Meh (Stranger and the Fog)'' (1974), ''Cherike-ye Tara (Ballad of Tara)'' (1980), ''[[Bashu, the Little Stranger]]'' (1986, released in 1989), ''Shāyad Vaghti digar (Maybe another time)'' (1988) and ''Mosaferan (Travellers)'' (1992). He has also written the screenplay to ''Ruz-e Vaqe'e (The Fateful Day)'' in 1995 and ''Fasl-e Panjom'' (The fifth season) in 1996, whilst also editing ''Borj-e Minu (Minoo Tower)''. 

===Cinematic style===
He is known as the most intellectual and conspicuous “author” in [[Iranian cinema]]. The main theme of his works is the [[history]] and “crisis of identity” which is related to Iranian cultural and mythical symbols and paradigms. 

===Reception and criticism===
Beyzai has made significant contribution to the development of the [[Cinema of Iran]] and theatre and is regarded as an influential director and innovator of the [[Iranian New Wave]] movement of cinema. He is also considered Iran’s most prominent screenwriter in terms of dramatic integrity of his works, many of which have been made into films.

However, despite the value of his films and his substantial knowledge of the arts, like other Iranian film directors such as [[Abbas Kiarostami]], the [[Government of Iran]] has never supported his career, neither before nor after the 1979 [[Iranian Revolution]]. Even after some 20 years, his films such as ''Ballad of Tara'' (1980) and ''Death of Yazdgerd'' (1981) have never received a screening permit in Iran. Both films have been shelved because they are not in accordance with the [[Islamic]] code currently in operation in Iranian motion pictures. Even ''[[Bashu, the Little Stranger]]'' almost saw the same fate in 1986 due to the subject matter of the film, i.e. the story of a little orphaned boy who lost his parents in the Iran-Iraqi war. The film was only legalized after the end of the [[1980-1988 Iran-Iraq War]] and was released in 1989.

===Filmography (as a director)===
* ''Amū Sibilū'' (1969 - short)
* ''Safar'' (1970 - short - aka ''The Journey'')
* ''Ragbār'' (1971 - aka ''Downpour'')
* ''Qaribé va Meh'' (1974 - aka ''The Stranger and the Fog'')
* ''Kalāq'' (1976 - aka ''The Crow'' or ''The Raven'' )
* ''[[Ballad of Tara|Charike-ye Tārā]]'' (1979 - aka ''Ballad of Tara'')
* ''Marg-e Yazdgerd'' (1982 - aka ''Death of Yazdgerd'')
* ''[[Bashu, the Little Stranger]]'' (1986 - aka ''Bashu'' - released 1989)
* ''Shāyad Vaghti digar'' (1988 - aka ''Maybe Some Other Time'')
* ''Mosāferan'' (1992 - aka ''[[Travellers (1992 film)|Travellers]]'')
* ''Goft-o-gū bā Bād'' (1998 - short - aka ''Talking with the Wind'')
* ''Sagkoshi'' (2001 - aka ''Killing Mad Dogs'')
* ''Qāli-ye Sokhangū'' (2006)
* ''Vaqti hame khābim'' (When we are all sleeping) (2009)

==Personal life==
He is the husband of [[actress]] and make-up artist [[Mozhdeh Shamsai]]. His daughter, [[Niloofar Beyzaie]], is a theater director and playwright. He has one son.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|1}}

==References==
{{No footnotes|article|date=February 2008}}
* [[Hamid Dabashi]], ''Masters &amp; Masterpieces of Iranian Cinema'', 451 p. (Mage Publishers, Washington, DC, 2007); Chapter IX, pp.&amp;nbsp;253–280: ''Bahram Beizai; Bashu, the Little Stranger''. ISBN 093421185X

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Travellers'Mosaferan.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Mosaferan (Travellers) (1992)]] --&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.bahrambeyzaie.com/ Official website]
* {{imdb name|id=0067323|name=Bahram Beizai}}
*[http://www.iranchamber.com/cinema/bbeyzai/bahram_beyzai.php Bahram Bayzai's biography on Iran Chamber Society (www.iranchamber.com)]
* ''Speaking with Bahram Bayzai; [Afrā], Day Passes By'', in Persian, BBC Persian,  Sunday 6 January 2008, [http://www.bbc.co.uk/persian/arts/story/2008/01/080105_la-ek-beizaee.shtml]. 
* ''A short talk with Bahram Bayzai, the celebrated director of film and theatre'', in Persian, Deutsche Welle, Wednesday 26 December 2007: [http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,2144,3023108,00.html (Main page)], [http://www.dw-world.de/popups/popup_single_mediaplayer/0,,3023091_type_audio_struct_10005,00.html?mytitle=%25D8%25A8%25D8%25B4%25D9%2586%25D9%2588%25DB%258C%25D8%25AF%253A%2B%25DA%25AF%25D9%2581%25D8%25AA%25E2%2580%258C%25D9%2588%25DA%25AF%25D9%2588%2B%25D8%25A8%25D8%25A7%2B%25D8%25A8%25D9%2587%25D8%25B1%25D8%25A7%25D9%2585%2B%25D8%25A8%25DB%258C%25D8%25B6%25D8%25A7%25DB%258C%25DB%258C (Audio recording of interview &amp;mdash; 4 min 9 sec)].
* Najmeh Khalili Mahani, ''Bahram Baizai, Iranian Cinema, Feminism, Art Cinema'', Off Screen, January 31, 2003, [http://www.horschamp.qc.ca/new_offscreen/baizai.html].

&lt;br /&gt;
{{CinemaofIran}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Beizai, Bahram
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1938-12-26
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Tehran]], [[Iran]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Beizai, Bahram}}
[[Category:Iranian theatre directors]]
[[Category:Iranian film directors]]
[[Category:Iranian screenwriters]]
[[Category:Iranian dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:People from Tehran]]
[[Category:University of Tehran alumni]]
[[Category:1938 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[de:Bahram Bayzai]]
[[eo:Bahram Bejzai]]
[[fa:بهرام بیضایی]]
[[fr:Bahram Beyzai]]
[[tr:Behram Beyzayi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
