<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="477085" ns="0" title="Ford Fiesta"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=November 2011}}
{{Distinguish2|the [[Ford Festiva]]}}
{{Cleanup|date=May 2009}}
{{Infobox automobile
|image = [[File:2009-2011 Ford Fiesta (WS) Zetec 5-door hatchback (2011-08-17).jpg|250px|2009–2011 Ford Fiesta Zetec 5-door hatchback, Australia]]
|name = Ford Fiesta
|manufacturer = [[Ford Motor Company]]
|production = 1976–present
|class = [[Supermini]], [[Subcompact car|Subcompact]]
|layout = [[Front-engine, front-wheel drive layout|Front-engine, front-wheel drive]]
|engine = [[Inline-four engine|Inline-four]]
}}

The '''Ford Fiesta''' is a front wheel drive [[supermini]]/[[subcompact]] manufactured and marketed by [[Ford Motor Company]] and built in Europe, Brazil, Argentina, Mexico, Venezuela, China, India, Thailand and South Africa. The current-generation Fiesta is marketed worldwide.

By 2010, the sixth-generation (Mark VI)&lt;ref name=&quot;30years&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=24102 |title=Still going strong, Ford's youthful-spirited Fiesta is celebrating its 30th birthday |work=Media.Ford.com |date=25 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fiesta had been introduced worldwide, including in the United States and Canada—making it the first Fiesta model to be sold in North America since 1980.

The Fiesta has sold over twelve million units since 1976.&lt;ref name=&quot;30years&quot;/&gt;

==History==
The Fiesta was originally developed under the project name &quot;Bobcat&quot; (later to be used on a badge engineered version of the [[Ford Pinto]] called the Mercury Bobcat) and approved for development by [[Henry Ford II]] in September 1972. Development targets indicated a production cost US$100 less than the current Ford Escort.&lt;ref name='30yr-pdf'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.ford.com/pdf/Fiesta_30th_EN.pdf |title=STILL GOING STRONG, FORD'S YOUTHFUL-SPIRITED FIESTA IS CELEBRATING ITS 30TH BIRTHDAY |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The car was to have a wheelbase longer than that of the Fiat 127, but with overall length shorter than that of Ford's Escort. The final proposal was developed by [[Tom Tjaarda]] at [[Carrozzeria Ghia|Ghia]]. The project was approved for production in autumn 1973, with Ford's engineering centres in Cologne and [[Dunton Wayletts|Dunton (Essex)]] collaborating.

Ford estimated that 500,000 Fiestas a year would be produced, and built an all-new [[Ford Valencia Plant|factory]] near [[Valencia, Spain]]; a transaxle factory near [[Bordeaux, France]]; factory extensions for the assembly plants in Dagenham, UK, and Saarlouis, Germany. Final assembly also took place in Valencia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/4car/ft/feature/retrospective/1186/2 Retrospective: Ford Fiesta: 30th Anniversary]{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Codenames===
{{Refimprove|date=February 2010}}
{{Original research|date=February 2010}}
When Ford of Europe began to design the car, the design proposals were named Iris, Beta, The Deutschlander (from Ford's Cologne studios), Mini-Mite, and the Blue Car (from Ghia). Codenames for the Fiesta prototype included Torino, but it became Project Bobcat.

The shortlisted names for the new car designed by the project Bobcat team (headed by Mr Trevor Erskine) were Amigo, Bambi, Bebe, Bravo, Bolero, Cherie, Tempo, Chico, Fiesta, Forito, Metro, Pony and Sierra. Despite more board votes for &quot;Bravo&quot;, [[Henry Ford II]] personally overruled them and named the car &quot;Fiesta&quot;. Several of the shortlisted names were later used on other cars, including &quot;[[Ford Sierra|Sierra]]&quot;, which was introduced on the [[Ford Cortina|Cortina]] replacement in 1982, and ''[[Ford Tempo|Tempo]]'' which was used on a Ford small car in the United States market. Ironically the &quot;Metro&quot; nameplate was introduced by rival manufacturer [[British Leyland]] for the similar-sized [[Austin Metro]] in 1980.

The name '''Fiesta''' belonged to [[General Motors]] at the time; however, it was freely given for Ford to use on their new B-class car. After years of speculation by the motoring press about Ford's new car, it was subject to a succession of carefully crafted press leaks from the end of 1975. A Fiesta was on display at the [[Le Mans 24 Hour Race]] in June 1976, and the car was launched and on sale in France and Germany in September 1976: to the frustration of UK dealerships righthand drive versions only began to appear in the UK in January 1977.&lt;ref name=Autocar197606&gt;{{cite journal| journal = [[Autocar (magazine)|Autocar]] |volume = 144 (nbr 4155) | authorlink =Peter Garnier (Ed)|title =World wide comment: Fiesta in France|pages = 4–5| date = 26 June 1976}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fiesta Mark I (1976–1983)==
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Mark I
|image = [[File:Ford Fiesta MK1 front 20071023.jpg|250px]]
|production = 1976–1983
|assembly = [[Almussafes]], Spain&lt;br /&gt;[[Dagenham]], United Kingdom&lt;br /&gt;[[Cologne]], [[Saarlouis]], Germany
|body_style = 3-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door [[panel van]]
|platform =
|engine = ''[[Petrol]]'':&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Kent#Valencia|Kent/Valencia]]:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|957|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} 40–45&amp;nbsp;PS (29–33&amp;nbsp;kW),&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1117|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|53|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1298|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|66|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1597|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|84|PS|abbr=on}}
|transmission = [[Ford BC transmission|Ford BC4]] 4-speed [[manual transmission|manual gearbox]]
|wheelbase = {{convert|2286|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|length = {{convert|3565|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|width = {{convert|1567|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|height = {{convert|1360|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|weight =
|fuel_capacity = {{convert|7.5|impgal|L usgal|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=Autocar1976&gt;
{{cite journal
| authorlink = Unsigned
| title = Autotest Ford Fiesta 1000L
| journal = [[Autocar (magazine)|Autocar]]
| volume = 145 (nbr 4172)
| pages = pages 68–73
| date = 23 October 1976
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|designer =
}}

Mechanically, the '''Ford Fiesta''' followed tradition, with an end-on four-speed [[manual transmission]] mounted to a new version of the [[Ford Kent engine|Ford Kent]] [[Overhead valve|OHV]] engine, dubbed &quot;Valencia&quot; after the brand new Spanish factory in [[Almussafes]], [[Valencia (autonomous community)|Valencia]], developed especially to produce the new car. Ford's plants in [[Dagenham]], England, and [[Saarlouis]] and [[Cologne]] (from 1979) in Germany, also manufactured Fiestas. To cut costs and speed up the research and development, many modified [[Ford Kent engine|Kent engines]] destined for the Fiesta were tested in [[Fiat 127]]s – at the time considered the benchmark car in the class, with which the Fiesta shares styling similarities. This also allowed covert road testing across Europe.

Although not the first Ford vehicle to feature [[front wheel drive]] (the 1960s [[Ford Taunus|Taunus]] produced by [[Ford of Germany]] laid claim to that title), the Fiesta is widely credited as being Ford's first globally successful front wheel drive model. UK sales began in January 1977, where it was available from £1,856 for the basic 950&amp;nbsp;cc engined model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.edp24.co.uk/content/edp24/lifestyle/motoring/story.aspx?brand=EDPOnline&amp;category=motoringNews&amp;tBrand=EDPOnline&amp;tCategory=motoringNews&amp;itemid=NOED03%20Sep%202010%2010%3A26%3A32%3A877 |title=Hammond's trip down memory lane – Norfolk Motoring News, Road Tests and more |publisher=EDP24 |date= |accessdate=2010-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was only the second hatchback mini-car to have been built in the UK at this stage, being launched a year after the [[Vauxhall Chevette]], but a year before the [[Chrysler Sunbeam]] and four years before the [[Austin Metro]]. The millionth Fiesta was produced on 9 January 1979.

The car was available in Europe with a {{convert|957|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} [[Inline-four engine|I4]] (high compression and low compression options), either a 1.1 L and 1.3 L OHV [[petrol]] engines and in Base, Popular, L, GL (1978 onward), Ghia and S trim, as well as a [[van]]. The U.S. Mark I Fiesta was built in [[Cologne]], Germany but to slightly different specifications; U.S. models were Base, Decor, Sport, and Ghia, the Ghia having the highest level of trim.&lt;ref name='timeline'&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.ford.com/images/10031/Fiesta_Timeline.pdf |title=Ford Fiesta Global Heritage |work=Media.Ford.com |month=November | year=2009 |accessdate=2010-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; These trim levels changed very little in the Fiesta's three year run in the USA, from 1978–80. All U.S. models featured the more powerful {{convert|1.6|L|cuin|abbr=on}} Kent [[inline-four engine]] (fitted with a catalytic converter and air pump for lower emissions), energy-absorbing bumpers, side-marker lamps, round sealed-beam headlamps, improved crash dynamics and fuel system integrity as well as optional air conditioning (a/c was not available in Europe). In the U.S. market, the [[Ford Escort (North America)|Ford Escort]] replaced both the Fiesta and the compact [[Ford Pinto|Pinto]] in 1981.

A sporting derivative (1.3 L Supersport) was offered in Europe in 1980, effectively to test the market for the similar XR2 introduced one year later, which featured a 1.6 L version of the same engine. Black plastic trim was added to the exterior and interior. The small square headlights were replaced with larger circular ones resulting in the front indicators being moved into the bumper to accommodate the change. With a quoted performance of {{convert|0|-|60|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} in 9.3 seconds and {{convert|105|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} top speed, the XR2 [[hot hatch]] became a cult car beloved of [[boy racer (subculture)|boy racer]]s throughout the 1980s.

Minor revisions appeared across the range in late 1981, with larger bumpers to meet crash worthiness regulations and other small improvements in a bid to maintain showroom appeal ahead of the forthcoming Mk 2.

In 1978, the Fiesta overtook the [[Vauxhall Chevette]] as Britain's best selling supermini, but in 1981 it was knocked off the top spot by [[British Leyland]]'s [[Austin Metro]] and was still in second place at the end of 1982.

{| border=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Mk I specifications
|-
!Engine type(s)
|[[Straight-4|Inline-4]]: [[Petrol]], [[Ford Kent#Valencia|Ford Kent/Valencia]] [[Overhead valve|OHV]]
|-
!Capacity
|{{convert|957|-|1597|cc|cuin|abbr=on}}
|-
!Power
|{{convert|40|-|84|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}
|-
!Max. speed
|{{convert|85|-|106|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}
|-
!Acceleration
|0–{{convert|60|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}: 10.1–17.6 seconds
|}

===Crayford convertibles===
In 1982, coachbuilders [[Crayford Engineering|Crayford]] produced the Fiesta &quot;Fly&quot;—a convertible version of the Mk 1 Fiesta 1300 Ghia, and a total of just fifteen vehicles were produced. The following year the more powerful 1600 Mk 1 Fiesta XR2 was the donor car, and a further seven convertibles were produced. The conversion involved welding the boot shut.

==Fiesta Mark II (1983–1989)==
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Mark II
|image = [[File:Ford Fiesta front 20070920.jpg|250px]]
|production = 1983–1989
|assembly = [[Almussafes]], Spain&lt;br /&gt;[[Dagenham]], United Kingdom&lt;br /&gt;[[Cologne]], [[Saarlouis]], Germany
|body_style = 3-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door [[panel van]]
|platform =
|engine = ''[[Petrol]]'':&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Kent#Valencia|Kent/Valencia]]:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|957|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|45|PS|abbr=on|link=on}},&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1117|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|49|-|53|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1298|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|66|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford CVH engine|CVH]]:&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1298|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|69|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1368|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|71|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1597|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|96|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;''[[Diesel engine|Diesel]]'':&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1608|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|54|PS|abbr=on}}
|transmission = [[Ford BC transmission|Ford BC4 &amp; BC5]] 4- or 5-speed [[manual transmission|manual gearbox]],&lt;br /&gt;[[continuously variable transmission]]
|wheelbase = {{convert|2286|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|length = {{convert|3565|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|width = {{convert|1567|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|height = {{convert|1360|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|weight =
|fuel_capacity =
|designer =
}}

The '''Fiesta Mark II''' appeared towards the end of summer 1983 with a revised front end and interior, and a bootlid mirroring the [[swaging#Car styling swage line|swage lines]] from the sides of the car. The 1.3 L OHV engine was dropped, being replaced in 1984 by a CVH powerplant of similar capacity, itself superseded by the [[lean burn]] 1.4 L two years later. 957 and 1117 cc engines continued with only slight alterations and for the first time a Fiesta [[diesel engine|diesel]] was produced with a 1600&amp;nbsp;cc engine adapted from the Escort.

The new CTX [[continuously variable transmission]], also fitted in the [[Fiat Uno]], eventually appeared early in 1987 on 1.1 L models only. This gearbox provided a quick and economic driving experience, despite the resemblance of the sensation of the continuously variable transmission to that of a slipping clutch.

The Mk 2 featured a different [[dashboard]] on the lower-series trim levels compared to the more expensive variants.

The XR2 model was thoroughly updated with a larger bodykit. It also featured a {{convert|96|bhp|kW|abbr=on}} 1.6 L CVH engine as previously seen in the Ford Escort XR3, and five-speed gearbox (also standard on the 1.3 L CVH models). The engine was replaced by a lean-burn variant in 1986 which featured a revised cylinder head and carburettor; it was significantly cleaner from an environmental viewpoint but was slightly less powerful as a result ({{convert|95|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}).
A truly &quot;hot&quot; Fiesta was never produced by the factory to avoid impacting on sales of performance Ford Escort variants but many aftermarket conversions were available, the best-known being that by the English firm [[Turbo Technics]] boosting power to a well documented {{convert|125|bhp|kW|0|abbr=on}}, which easily outclassed its &quot;standard&quot; rivals. [[Ford]] appreciated the high quality of this conversion and was keen to look after its customers: the installation was undertaken by approved fitting centres and all the warranties remained valid after.
[[Image:Ford Fiesta 2 XR2 1984.jpg|thumb|250px|left|1984 Ford Fiesta Mk2 XR2.]]

The face-lifted, facing competition from the [[Vauxhall Nova]] and [[Austin Metro]], was one of the UK's top supermini. In its best-ever year, 1987, over 150,000 Fiesta models were sold in the UK,&lt;ref name='30yr-pdf'/&gt; though it missed out on first place in the sales charts to the Ford Escort.

The Mk 2 Fiesta lives on as the donor vehicle for Quantum Sports Cars' 2+2 convertible&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.quantumcars.co.uk/showroom/2plus2/ |title=Quantum 2+2 |accessdate=2008-02-15 |work=Quantum Sports Cars Ltd. }}&lt;/ref&gt; with several hundred manufactured at the factory in [[Stourbridge]] before production moved to [[Kingsbridge]].

;Mk II specifications
{| border=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Engine type(s)
|[[Straight-4|Inline-4]]: [[Petrol]], [[Ford Kent#Valencia|Ford Kent/Valencia]][[Overhead valve|OHV]], [[Ford CVH engine|Ford CVH]], and [[Diesel engine|Diesel]]
|-
!Capacity
|{{convert|957|-|1608|cc|cuin|abbr=on}}
|-
!Power
|{{convert|45|-|96|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}
|-
!Max. speed
|{{convert|88|-|101|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}
|-
!Acceleration
|0–{{convert|60|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} 8.7–19.0 seconds
|}

==Fiesta Mark III (1989–1997)==
{{See also|Ford Fiesta RS Turbo}}
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Mark III
|image = [[Image:Ford Fiesta MK3 front 20070926.jpg|250px]]
|production = 1989–1997
|assembly = [[Almussafes]], Spain&lt;br /&gt;[[Dagenham]], United Kingdom&lt;br /&gt;[[Cologne]], [[Saarlouis]], Germany
|body_style = 3-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;5-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door [[panel van]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door 'high cube' [[panel van]]
|platform = [[Ford B platform]]
|engine = ''[[Petrol]]'':&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford HCS|Kent/HCS]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|999|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|45|PS|abbr=on|link=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1118|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|50|-|55|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1289|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|60|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford CVH engine|CVH]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1392|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|71|-|75|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1596|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|104|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1596|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} [[Turbocharger|Turbo]] {{convert|133|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford Zetec engine|Zetec]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1598|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|90|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1796|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|105|-|130|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
''[[Diesel engine|Diesel]]'':&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1753|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|60|PS|abbr=on}}
|transmission = [[Ford IB transmission|Ford IB4 &amp; IB5]] 4- or 5-speed [[manual transmission|manual gearbox]],&lt;br /&gt;[[continuously variable transmission]]
|wheelbase =
|length =
|width =
|height =
|weight =
|fuel_capacity =42 L
|designer =
|related = [[Ford Ka]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Courier]]
}}

The third generation '''Fiesta Mark III''', codenamed ''BE-13'' was unveiled at the end of 1988 and officially went on sale in the February of the following year.  Although it was essentially a reskin of the Mk.II (which in turn was a facelift of the 1976 original), it looked radically different, and did address the principal weakness of the previous generation – the lack of a 5-door derivative, something that was by then available in its major rivals such as the [[Fiat Uno]], [[Peugeot 205]] and [[Opel Corsa]].  The other main change was to the running gear – the improved HCS (High Compression Swirl) version of the Kent/Valencia powerplant.  The CVH units from the Mk II were carried over largely unmodified.  The diesel engine was enlarged to a 1.8L capacity.  

This model had the longest production life of any Fiesta to date, achieved the highest yearly sales of any Fiesta in the early 1990s – achieving a sales volume of 1 million units inside the first two years of production, and underwent numerous changes in its life. For example, the car had four different versions of standard steering wheels during its lifetime (the launch wheel, then updated in 1992, 1994 and 1995) and the most changes to standard UK trim levels of any Fiesta (examples across the years show the large line-up: Popular, Popular Plus, L, LX, Ghia, 1.6S, XR2i, RS Turbo, RS1800, Fiesta, Louisiana, DL, SX, Azura, Si, Classic, Classic Quartz, Classic Cabaret, Saphire). A Fiesta-derived van, the Ford Courier, was launched in 1991.

Fuel injection engines became available in 1991. Major changes were introduced to the range in 1994. Major structural improvements were made to improve safety, as well as a new immobiliser being fitted to petrol models. The UK trim line-up was also simplified to Fiesta, LX, Si (which also had a new bumper and seat designs) and Ghia. Revised door mirrors were also fitted, as were a line-up of fresh wheel trim designs.

As for sports models, the XR2i was launched in 1989&lt;ref name=&quot;30years&quot;/&gt; with an 8v CVH (compound valve-angle hemispherical combustion chamber) engine but was replaced by a Zetec 16v version in 1992, which also saw the RS Turbo being supplanted by the RS1800—as the CVH engine was being phased out, the RS1800 shared its 1.8 L [[Ford Zetec engine|Zetec]] [[fuel-injected]] engine with the {{convert|130|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} version of the then-current [[Ford Escort (Europe)|Ford Escort]] XR3i and had a top speed of {{convert|125|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}. The XR2i name was also dropped in early 1994, and the insurance-friendly &quot;Si&quot; badge appeared in its place on a slightly less sporty-looking model with either the 1.4 L PTE (a development of the CVH) or the 1.6 L Zetec engine.

From 1995 the vehicle was built and sold at the same time as the new Mark IV. To distinguish the car, trim levels were revised, and it was marketed as the &quot;Fiesta Classic&quot;. This continued until production finally ceased in 1997.

;Mk III specifications;
{| border=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Engine type(s)
|[[Straight-4|Inline-4]]: [[Petrol]], [[Ford Kent#HCS|Ford Kent/HCS]] ([[Overhead valve|OHV]]), [[Ford CVH engine|Ford CVH]] ([[OHC]]), [[Ford Zetec engine|Ford Zetec]] (OHC), and [[Diesel engine|Diesel]] (OHC)
|-
!Capacity
|{{convert|999|-|1796|cc|cuin|abbr=on}}
|-
!Power
|{{convert|45|-|133|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}
|-
!Max. speed
|{{convert|86|-|129|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}
|-
!Acceleration
|0–{{convert|60|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} 7.9–19.0 seconds
|}

{{anchor|fourth}}

==Fiesta Mark IV (1995–2002)==
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Mark IV
|image = [[Image:Ford Fiesta MK4 front 20070926.jpg|250px]]
|production = 1995–2002
|aka = [[Mazda 121]]&lt;br/&gt;Mazda Soho
|assembly = [[Almussafes]], Spain&lt;br /&gt;[[Dagenham]], United Kingdom&lt;br /&gt;[[Cologne]], [[Saarlouis]], Germany&lt;br /&gt;[[São Bernardo do Campo]], Brazil&lt;br /&gt;[[Port Elizabeth]], South Africa
|body_style = 3-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;5-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door [[panel van]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door 'high cube'[[panel van]]
|platform = [[Ford B platform]]
|engine = ''[[Petrol]]'':&lt;br /&gt;
[[Endura-E|Kent/Endura-E]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1299|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|50|-|60|PS|abbr=on|link=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford Sigma engine|Zetec-SE]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1242|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|75|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1388|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|90|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
''[[Diesel engine|Diesel]]'':&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1753|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|60|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford Endura-D engine|Endura-D]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1753|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|75|PS|abbr=on}}
|transmission = [[Ford IB transmission|Ford IB5]] 5-speed [[manual transmission|manual gearbox]],&lt;br /&gt;[[continuously variable transmission]]
|wheelbase =
|length =
|width =
|height =
|weight =
|fuel_capacity =
|related = [[Ford Ka]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Puma]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Ikon]]
|designer =
}}

The all new '''Fiesta Mark IV''' (internal code name was ''BE91'') was launched in 1995&lt;ref name=&quot;30years&quot;/&gt; and became [[United Kingdom|Britain's]] best selling car from 1996–1998.

The model used the chassis of the Mark III car{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}, but most components were heavily revised, including a new [[suspension (vehicle)|suspension]] system, which gave the Fiesta one of the best handling abilities in its class.

The model featured a range of new [[Zetec]] engines, available in 1.25 L and 1.4 L forms, the 1.8 diesel engine was slightly modified for the Mark IV, now marketed as the &quot;Endura DE&quot;. The 1.3 L OHV engine was carried over from the Mark III. As well as the major changes to the chassis, the Mark IV also benefited from a new interior and exterior styling, including a soft painted instrument panel for the first year of production, albeit maintaining a similar dimensions to the Mark III. The RS1800 and RS Turbo models were not carried over to the updated Fiesta range.

The Mark IV Fiesta shared a production line and design with the [[Mazda 121]], which sold in much lower volumes and was not produced for the British market after 1999.

In Brazil a 1.0-litre version was available, in L, LX and GL trim levels; it was sold in Argentina and Chile. The UK trim level line up had relatively few changes over the years: (1995, Encore, LX, Si, Ghia; 1996, Ghia X added as range-topper; 1998, Si replaced by Zetec, petrol LX models briefly renamed Zetec LX, Ghia X models axed; 1999, Finesse added between Encore and Zetec).

In 1997, the Mark IV was introduced into South Africa. This is the first time the Fiesta entered the South African vehicle market. Only one engine was available, the 1.3 L Endura E. It subsequently won the South African Car of the Year award. The 1.3 L engine was replaced with the 1.4 L PTE (CVH) engine in 1999.

The Mark IV was not sold in North America.

The German-built [[Ford Puma]] was based on the Mark IV, sharing its underpinnings. For this reason the 1.7 VCT engine from the Ford Puma has become an extremely popular engine swap into the Mark IV and Mark IV facelift Fiesta. This gives the popular hatchback an extra 100&amp;nbsp;cc over the previous largest engine size available, variable cam timing and better ratio gearbox while still retaining a factory finish as all components are a direct swap.

As an exercise in [[badge engineering]], the Mazda 121 and Ford Fiesta were built on the same production lines and used almost all the same parts. In the JD Power reliability surveys at the time, the Mazda was reported to be significantly more reliable and attracted higher levels of customer satisfaction.

;Mark IV specifications
{| border=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Engine type(s)
|[[Straight-4|Inline-4]]: [[Petrol]], [[Ford Kent#Endura-E|Ford Kent/Endura-E]] ([[Overhead valve|OHV]]), [[Ford Sigma engine|Zetec-SE]] ([[OHC]]), and [[Diesel engine|Diesel]] (OHC)
|-
!Capacity
|Petrol: {{convert|1242|-|1596|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} Diesel: {{convert|1753|cc|cuin|abbr=on}}
|-
!Power
|{{convert|59|-|91|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}
|-
!Max. speed
|{{convert|96|-|112|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}
|-
!Acceleration
|0-{{convert|62|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} -&lt;br /&gt;
1.25: 11.9&amp;nbsp;s&lt;br /&gt;
1.4: 10.8&amp;nbsp;s&lt;br /&gt;
1.8D: 14.7&amp;nbsp;s&lt;br /&gt;
1.8D: 16.2&amp;nbsp;s&lt;br /&gt;
1.4 Zetec: 9.6&amp;nbsp;s
|-
!Fuel efficiency'''
|38–46 mpg-UK (32–38&amp;nbsp;mpg-US or 7.4–6.1 L/100&amp;nbsp;km)&lt;!--miles per imperial gallon per http://www.ford.co.uk/ns7/fiesta/-/fie_0508_spec/-/-/-/-#--&gt;
|}

===Fiesta Mark IV (1999–2002) facelift===
[[Image:Ford Fiesta MK5 front 20090227.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Ford Fiesta Mark IV facelift (2000) 5-door]]
[[Image:Fordfiesta.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Ford Fiesta Mark IV facelift (2000) 3-door]]
[[File:Courier wikipedia.jpg|thumb|200px|Ford Courier Pickup]]
In 1999, the Fiesta received a minor facelift&lt;ref name='timeline'/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;yearsfordfiesta1&quot;&gt;[http://www.fordmedia.eu/presskits/30YearsFordFiesta/htdocs/ Still going strong, Ford's youthful-spired Fiesta is celebrating its 30th birthday] Fordmedia.eu&lt;/ref&gt; aimed at giving the car a [[New Edge]] look, with a Focus-inspired face, new bumpers and wheel designs. Facelift known as Mark V in United Kingdom and elsewhere.

Other changes include 1.6i 16V Zetec engine, fitted to the new Zetec S model, and later available in Ghia and Freestyle trims. New features such as side airbags and (after launch) the reintroduction of leather trim. An environmentally-friendly ''E-Diesel'' model for 2001, with CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions of 120&amp;nbsp;g/km. The Lynx 1.8 TDDi engine (also introduced after launch).

The Mk IV facelift&lt;ref name=&quot;yearsfordfiesta1&quot;/&gt; was the last generation of Fiesta to be built at [[Dagenham]] in England. Its internal code name was still BE91. The UK trim level line-up consisted of: 1999, Encore, Finesse, Zetec, LX, Ghia; 2000, Zetec S added; 2001, E-Diesel added at bottom of range, Flight and Freestyle respectively replace Finesse and Zetec.

In South Africa, the facelift used the Port Elizabeth-built 1.3 L and 1.6 L Rocam engines, instead of the European Sigma 16-valve engines.
This model formed the basis of the [[Ford Ikon]] (code name C195), which is a four-door sedan designed for India, where Ford was now producing cars in a joint venture with [[Mahindra]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} The Ikon was also introduced in other developing countries, such as Brazil (where it is known as the Fiesta [[Sedan (car)|Sedan]]), South Africa, Mexico and China, where sedans are preferred to [[hatchback]]s. They are extremely reliable, and became one of [[Ford]]'s successes. There were also four [[truck]] variants, the simplest being the &quot;Fiesta Van&quot; which was a three-door hatchback with the rear quarter windows blanked over and the rear seat omitted. Another van with a boxy rear body and stretched wheelbase used the Courier nameplate and formed the basis of two [[pick-up truck|pick-up]] models, one with the short doors of the 5-door hatchback and small quarterlights in the style of larger [[extended cab]] pick-ups, made in South Africa; and another with the 3-door's longer doors and no quarter windows, made in Brazil.

The Fiesta was still Britain's best-selling supermini in 2001, by which time it was making use of a design over a decade old (though heavily updated visually and mechanically). In three-door form, it was sold alongside the Mk 5 Fiesta from April to December 2002.

====Zetec S====
The Zetec S was the highest Fiesta trim, and although its 1.6 L 16v Sigma engine was available in other Fiestas (such as the Freestyle) the Zetec S pushed out {{Convert|101|bhp|kW PS|abbr=on}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parkers.co.uk/cars/specs/Detail.aspx?deriv=18633|title=Facts &amp; Figures: Ford Fiesta (99-02) 1.6 Zetec S 3d|work=Parkers.co.uk|publisher=Parkers|accessdate=2011-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and had major alterations to the suspension, with stiffer anti-roll bars and uprated brakes shared with the Puma.

The Zetec S Mk 5 facelift&lt;ref name=&quot;yearsfordfiesta1&quot;/&gt; has a sizeable following, with many websites dedicated to the vehicle. There is also a tuning culture devoted to this model, with reputable companies such as Milltek Sport and Shawspeed developing performance parts solely for the Sigma engine.

===Mk IV facelift specifications===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Engine type(s)
|[[Straight-4|Inline-4]]: [[Petrol]], [[Ford Kent#Endura-E|Ford Kent/Endura-E]] ([[Overhead valve|OHV]]), [[Ford Sigma engine|Zetec-SE]] ([[OHC]]), and [[Diesel engine|Diesel]] (OHC)
|-
!Capacity
|Petrol: {{Convert|1242|-|1596|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} Diesel: {{convert|1753|cc|cuin|abbr=on}}
|-
!Power
|{{convert|59|-|102|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}
|-
!Max. speed
|{{convert|95|-|113|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}
|-
!Acceleration
|0–{{convert|60|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} 9.9–16.9 seconds
|-
!Fuel efficiency'''
|38–53&amp;nbsp;mpg-UK (32–52&amp;nbsp;mpg-US or 7.4–4.6 L/100&amp;nbsp;km)&lt;!--miles per imperial gallon per http://www.ford.co.uk/ns7/fiesta/-/fie_0508_spec/-/-/-/-#--&gt;
|}

==Fiesta Mark V (2002–2008)==
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Mark V
|image = [[File:2006-2008 Ford Fiesta (WQ) LX 3-door hatchback 02.jpg|250px|2006–2008 Ford Fiesta (WQ) LX 3-door hatchback (Australia)]]
|also called = Ford ikon
|production = 2002–2008 (Brazil 2002 on)
|assembly = [[Almussafes]], Spain&lt;br /&gt;[[Cologne]], [[Saarlouis]], Germany&lt;br /&gt;[[Camaçari]], Brazil&lt;br /&gt;[[Valencia, Venezuela]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Chennai]], India
|body_style = 3-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;5-door [[hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt;3-door [[panel van]]&lt;br /&gt;4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]
|platform = [[Ford B3 platform]]
|engine = ''[[Petrol]]'':&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford Duratec engine#Duratec 8v|Duratec]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1299|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|60|PS|abbr=on|link=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford Sigma engine|Zetec-SE]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1242|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|75|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1398|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|80|PS|abbr=on}},&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1596|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|100|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford Duratec engine#Duratec 20|Duratec 20]]:&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1998|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} {{convert|150|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
''[[Diesel engine|Diesel]]'':&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford DLD engine#DLD-414|Duratorq DLD-414]]&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1398|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} TDCi {{convert|68|PS|abbr=on}};&lt;br /&gt;
[[Ford DLD engine#DLD-416|Duratorq DLD-416]]&lt;br /&gt;
{{convert|1560|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} TDCi {{convert|90|PS|abbr=on}} (2005 on)
|transmission = [[Ford IB transmission|Ford IB5]] 5-speed [[manual transmission|manual gearbox]],&lt;br /&gt;4-speed [[automatic transmission]]
|wheelbase = {{convert|2486|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Brazil: {{convert|2488|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|length = {{convert|3918|-|3924|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Brazil Hatchback: {{convert|3930|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Brazil Sedan: {{convert|4221|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Trail: {{convert|4030|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|width = {{convert|1685|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|height = {{convert|1464|-|1468|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Brazil Hatchback: {{convert|1451|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Trail: {{convert|1550|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|weight = {{convert|1096|-|1178|kg|lb|abbr=on}}
|fuel_capacity =
|related =
|designer =
|related = [[Ford Fusion (European)|Ford Fusion]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Ecosport]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ford Figo]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mazda Demio#2002|Mazda2]]
}}
[[Image:2005 Ford Fiesta ST.JPG|thumb|left|200px|2005 Ford Fiesta ST]]

On 1 April 2002, the all new five-generation car was unveiled. Of this '''Fiesta Mark V''', most engines were carried over from the previous Fiesta, but renamed &quot;[[Duratec]]&quot;, as the &quot;[[Zetec]]&quot; name was now solely used for sportier models. The previous push-rod 1.3 L engine was initially available in the UK, but this was quickly replaced with a Rocam 1.3 L, both under the name Duratec 8v.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fiesta 2002|url=http://www.honestjohn.co.uk/carbycar/ford/fiesta-2002/?section=good|work=HonestJohn.co.uk|publisher=Honest John|accessdate=2011-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trim levels available initially were Finesse, LX, Zetec and Ghia, with limited edition variants soon following. The Mk 5 was also the first Fiesta to feature the [[Anti-lock Braking System]] and passenger [[airbags]] as standard. The fifth generation was known as Mark VI in United Kingdom and elsewhere. This generation became the best selling Ford Fiesta generation to date.

Engines available include 1.25 L, 1.3 L, 1.4 L, 1.6 L, 2.0 L petrol, plus 1.4 L 8v and 1.6 L 16v [[Ford Duratorq engine|Duratorq TDCi]] common-rail diesels built in a joint venture with [[PSA Peugeot Citroën|PSA]].

This was also the first Fiesta to be sold in Asia and [[Australasia]] (all 1.6 L LX 3dr/5dr, Zetec 3dr, Ghia 5dr), replacing the [[Kia Motors|Kia]]-based [[Ford Festiva|Festiva]]. In Brazil and [[Argentina]], a Fiesta sedan version was introduced in late 2004. A similar Fiesta sedan model, with a different front end, was released in India in late 2005. This Fiesta generation was [[ergonomical]]ly and mechanically more advanced than any previous generation. The 2005 facelift came with an even improved exterior.
[[Image:FiestaSouthAmerica08.jpg|thumb|left|200px|South American 2008 Fiesta Facelift]]

===Fiesta South America===
In Brazil, the engine options also include 1.0 L 8v Flex and 1.6 L 8v Flex engines called Rocam, that runs on ethanol, petrol or any mixture of both. The internal codename of this model is B256 (5-door) and B257 (3-door). In other [[Mercosur]] countries the Fiesta features a 1.6 L {{convert|98|bhp|kW|abbr=on}} SOHC [[Zetec]] engine has a standard with the choice of either a 4-speed automatic or 5-speed manual transmission. There is also a 1.4 L {{convert|68|bhp|kW|abbr=on}} diesel engine available. For the Colombian market a 1.0 L 8v Rocam engine was sold with a supercharger, producing {{convert|96|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}. This was discontinued on 2009 and replaced by the Mark VI imported from Mexico.

The South American market Fiesta was facelifted in early 2007 as a 2008 model, with new rectangular headlights and grille. And again, in early 2010 the Fiesta was facelifted as a 2011 model, with new headlights and grille, very similar to those on the mark VI Fiesta available in other markets around the world, but keeping all other features nearly the same as the previous model. Its name varies from country to country, called &quot;Fiesta One&quot; in [[Argentina]], &quot;Fiesta Move&quot; in [[Venezuela]], and &quot;Fiesta Rocam&quot; in Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ford.com.ar/ford2010/pdf/fiesta.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ford.com.ve/Carros |title=Ford Motor de Venezuela S.A. - Introducción Fiesta .move |publisher=Ford.com.ve |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ford.com.br/showroom.asp?veiculo=41 |title=Viva o Novo |publisher=Ford |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiesta in India===
In the Indian market Ford produced the [[Ford Ikon]] and Fiesta Mk V in parallel for the sedan market until April 2011. Production of the Ford Ikon was discontinued when the Bharat IV emission requirements came into effect for metropolitan areas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2011-04-07/news/29392445_1_rocam-diesel-variant-tdci Ford Ikon Discontinued]&lt;/ref&gt; Ford then announced its intent to launch the Fiesta Mark VI at a lower price and new features, including dual airbags, bringing the Fiesta in line with competitors such as the [[Honda City]], [[Suzuki SX4]], [[Volkswagen Vento]] and [[Hyundai Verna]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cardekho.com/carmodels/Ford/Ford_Fiesta Ford Fiesta India]&lt;/ref&gt; In July, Ford replaced the Mk V with the Fiesta Mk VI, marketed in India as the Ford Fiesta 2011&lt;ref name=wsj-india2011&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304911104576445281205342402.html |title=Ford launches Fiest sedan in India |publisher=Wall Street Journal |date= 2011-07-14|accessdate=2011-07-14 |first=Eric |last=Yep}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiesta ST/XR4===
The Fiesta ST/XR4 was the performance model of this Fiesta. It includes a 2.0 L [[Ford Duratec engine|Duratec]] [[Four-stroke cycle|petrol engine]] rated at {{convert|150|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} in standard form, with a top speed of {{convert|129|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ford Fiesta ST|url=http://www.parkers.co.uk/cars/specs/Detail.aspx?deriv=32683|work=Parkers.co.uk|publisher=Parkers|accessdate=2011-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Fiesta ST also features {{convert|17|in|cm|abbr=on}} alloy wheels, different front and rear bumpers, side skirts, body colour handles and bump strips, partial leather seats and a ST logo on the steering wheel.

In Australia, the Fiesta ST was sold as the Fiesta XR4. To stay in line with all sports model Fords sold in Australia it received the 'XR' badging, instead of the 'ST' badging used in Europe.

The vehicle was unveiled at the 2004 Geneva Motor Show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carenthusiast.com/geneva2004.html?article=305 |title=Ford Fiesta ST (preview) |publisher=Carenthusiast.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiesta RallyeConcept===
This is a British 3-door concept car designed by Ford RallyeSport and Ford Design Europe, designed for the [[Super 1600]] rally. The 1.6 L Duratec engine was rated {{convert|200|bhp|kW PS|abbr=on}}. It includes four-two-one [[Arvin Meritor]] exhaust, 6-speed Hewland sequential gearbox, MacPherson strut front and twist-beam rear suspensions, 15-spoke magnesium wheels with 18&quot; Pirelli P-Zero tyres.

The car was unveiled at the Birmingham Auto Show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carkeys.co.uk/features/sport/1138.asp |title=Ford's New Fiesta Rally Car |publisher=Carkeys.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiesta RS concept===
This is a concept model based on the 2002 Fiesta RallyeConcept. It includes many of the RallyeConcept Fiesta features such as the cooling vents in the front bumper, deep side rockers, white ceramic-coated brake calipers and exhaust tips, and a large rear spoiler. It also includes 18-inch alloy wheels with low-profile tyres, extended wheel arches, and lowered and stiffened suspension. The engine is rated at over {{convert|180|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/4car/ft/feature/concept+car/1682/1 Concept Car: Ford Fiesta RS]{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiesta Mark V (2005–2008): facelift===
[[Image:fiestamk7zetecs.jpg|thumb|200px|right|2007 Front Facelift Fiesta Zetec-S]]
[[Image:Fiestamk7rear.jpg|thumb|200px|right|2007 Rear Facelift Fiesta Zetec-S]]
[[Image:Ford Fiesta Style.JPG|thumb|200px|right|2007 Front Facelift Fiesta Style]]

In November 2005, a revised version of the Mk 5 Fiesta went on sale, also known as the Mk 5 facelift. A number of cosmetic changes were introduced: front and rear lights featured new detailing, and bumpers, side mouldings and door mirrors were altered. A bright new colour palette was introduced. The facelift is known as the Mk 6.5 in the UK, or Mark 7 elsewhere (mistakenly){{citation needed|date=March 2011}}, as this was simply a revised version of the Mark VI and not a completely new car.

Inside, the dashboard was redesigned with better quality soft touch materials, following criticisms of the hard, cheaply textured original. A new analogue instrument display is included in a style similar to the Mk 2 [[Ford Focus (International)|Ford Focus]]. The facelift also includes new technology, including power folding mirrors, automatic and 'home-safe' headlights, automatic windscreen wipers, [[Bluetooth]] with voice control, [[Trip computer]], [[MP3 player]] connectivity and the [[Electronic Stability Program]].

The changes had immediate effects on sales. After years being outsold by Vauxhall's Corsa, among others, in February 2006 Ford announced sales in the preceding month were up 25% on January 2005 for the previous model. Furthermore, the Fiesta captured the title of Britain's most popular supermini in both 2006 and 2007, for the first time since 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.motortrader.com/26406/New-car-sales-2007-The-results.ehtml |title=New car sales 2007: The results |date=2008-01-07 |accessdate=2008-02-15 |work=motortrader.com |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080309101427/http%3A//www.motortrader.com/26406/New-car-sales-2007-The-results.ehtml |archivedate = 9 March 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the UK, the car is available in Studio, Style, Style Climate, Zetec, Zetec Climate, Zetec S, ST and Ghia trim levels with what was called a 'Tech Pack' available to all trim levels above the Style Climate, this featured the power folding mirrors, automatic wipers, automatic and home safe lights and an advanced trip computer.

In 2007, more limited editions were added—the Fiesta Zetec Blue, and (following on from the hugely successful Fiesta Zetec S &quot;Anniversary&quot; edition), the Fiesta Zetec S 'Celebration'. In 2008, the Fiesta Zetec S Red was added, as well as an ST500 model.

====Limited editions====
The '''Zetec S &quot;Anniversary&quot;''' was a limited edition of 400 cars based on the Zetec S and included a Radian Yellow body, chequered roof, black mirrors and door handles, tinted glass, {{convert|16|in|cm|abbr=on}} alloy wheels, black roof spoiler, sports seats, leather trim, an alarm, and an iPod socket.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2007/02/09/ford-bites-minis-flavour-with-uk-chequered-flag-model/ |title=Ford bites MINI's flavour with UK &quot;chequered flag&quot; model |author=Nunez, Alex |date=9 February 2007 |work=Autoblog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The car went on sale in the UK on March 2007 for £12,595. Despite the name, the Ford Fiesta was 31 years old when the anniversary model was released.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/4car/di/ford/fiesta+st/8094/1 Driven: Ford Fiesta Zetec S 30th Anniversary]{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''Zetec S &quot;Celebration&quot;''' was a limited (400 cars) edition based on the Zetec S and included a Celebration Green body, black and white chequered roof decal, unique identity number, chequered scuff plates and mats, full 'Ebony Haze' leather interior, privacy glass and Panther Black door mirrors, bodyside mouldings, roof spoiler, tailgate handle, {{convert|16|in|cm|abbr=on}} alloy wheels, air conditioning, trip computer, electric windows, CD player with portable music connection socket, sports front seats and lowered sports suspension.

The car went on sale in the UK for £12,595.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2007/10/24/ford-unveils-fiesta-zetec-s-celebration-in-uk/ |title=Ford unveils Fiesta Zetec S 'Celebration' in UK |author=Nunez, Alex |date=24 October 2007 |work=Autoblog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''Zetec S Red''' was a limited (500 cars) edition based on the Zetec S and included a Colorado Red body, black and white chequered roof decal, dark privacy glass on the rear windows, panther black door mirrors, door handles, bodyside mouldings, roof spoiler and tailgate handle; [[Quickclear]] heated front windscreen, ebony leather seats, {{convert|16|in|cm|abbr=on}} alloy wheels, air conditioning and heated electrically-operated door mirrors.

The car went on sale in the UK for £13,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autoblog.com/2008/06/26/ford-uk-offers-red-edition-fiesta-zetec-s/ |title=Ford UK offers Red edition Fiesta Zetec S |author=Joseph, Noah |date=26 June 2008 |work=Autoblog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Fiesta ST====
In 2008, Ford offered Mountune Performance options for Fiesta ST vehicles, available at specialist British Ford dealers beginning in March 2008. These were developed by Roush Technologies Ltd, which owns the Mountune Racing motorsport brand. The Mountune Performance Stage 1 (£1,435) includes a high flow catalyst and tubular manifold, and re-calibration of the engine to produce {{convert|165|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}. The Mountune Performance Stage 2 package (£1,838) adds new camshafts and valve springs to the basic package to deliver {{convert|185|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.conceptcarz.com/vehicle/z14860/Ford-Fiesta-ST-Mountune.aspx |title=2008 Ford Fiesta ST Mountune |publisher=Conceptcarz.com |date=2008-03-01 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''ST 500''' was a limited production (500 vehicles) model of the Fiesta ST. It includes {{convert|17|in|cm|abbr=on}} 11-spoke black alloy wheels, red brake callipers and carbon fibre pattern interior trim. The interior also features a Sony audio system and ebony leather heated seats. The vehicle cost £15,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.automobilesreview.com/auto-news/new-sporty-limited-edition-fiesta-st/2122/ |title=New sporty limited edition Fiesta ST |publisher=Automobilesreview.com |date=2008-06-10 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mk V specifications===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Engine type(s)
|[[Straight-4|Inline-4]]: [[Petrol]], [[Ford Duratec engine#Duratec 8v|Duratec]] ([[Overhead valve|OHV]]), [[Ford Sigma engine|Zetec-SE]] and [[Ford Duratec engine#Duratec 20|Duratec 20]] ([[OHC]]), and [[Diesel engine|Diesel]], [[Ford DLD engine#DLD-414|Duratorq DLD-414]] and [[Ford DLD engine#DLD-416|Duratorq DLD-416]] (OHC)
|-
!Capacity
|{{convert|1242|-|1998|cc|cuin|abbr=on}}
|-
!Power
|{{convert|60|-|150|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}
|-
!Max. speed
|{{convert|94|-|130|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}
|-
!Acceleration
|0–{{convert|60|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} 7.9–18.8 seconds
|}

===Marketing===
Since the launch of the 2005+ model, the advertising motto has been &quot;'''Stupid'''Dogbot, '''Clever'''Fiesta&quot;, with the car showing a new gadget, while the robotic dog does something stupid; e.g., the Fiesta showing MP3 connectivity, while the Dogbot sticks its head into an old record player.

The September 2008 advert for the UK-spec Fiesta used ''Transient'' by [[Pluxus]] as backing track.

==Fiesta Mark VI (2008 on)==
{{Infobox automobile
|image = [[File:2009-2010 Ford Fiesta (WS) Zetec 5-door hatchback 01.jpg|250px|2009–2010 Ford Fiesta (WS) Zetec 5-door hatchback (Australia)]]
|name = Ford Fiesta Mark VI
|aka = Ford New Fiesta (Latin America)
|manufacturer = [[Ford Motor Company]]
|aka =
|production = 2008 on
|assembly = [[Almussafes]], Spain&lt;br /&gt;[[Nanjing]], China&lt;br /&gt;[[Cologne]], Germany&lt;br /&gt;[[Cuautitlán Izcalli]], Mexico&lt;br /&gt;[[Rayong]], [[Thailand]] (2010 on)&lt;br /&gt;[[Valencia, Spain]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Chennai, India]]&lt;ref name=wsj-india2011/&gt;
|body_style = 3-door [[Hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt; 5-door [[Hatchback]]&lt;br /&gt; 4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]]&lt;br /&gt;2-door [[Van]]
|platform = [[Ford B3 platform|Ford global B-car platform]]
|engine =1.4 L [[Inline-four engine|I4]]&lt;br /&gt;1.6 L I4&lt;br /&gt;1.25 L I4&lt;br /&gt;1.4 L [[Diesel engine|Diesel]] I4&lt;br /&gt;1.6 L [[Diesel engine|Diesel]] I4
|transmission = 4-speed [[automatic transmission|automatic]]&lt;br /&gt;5-speed [[manual transmission|manual]]&lt;br /&gt;6-speed [[Ford PowerShift transmission|PowerShift]]
|wheelbase = {{convert|2489|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Van: {{convert|2487|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|length = Sedan: {{convert|173.6|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;2011 on Hatchback: {{convert|160.1|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;2008–2010: {{convert|3950|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Van: {{convert|3917|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|width = {{convert|1722|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Van: {{convert|1683|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|height = 2011 on: {{convert|58.0|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;2008–2010: {{convert|1481|mm|in|abbr=on}}&lt;br /&gt;Van: {{convert|1467|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|weight = 1,041–1,092&amp;nbsp;kg (Petrol), 1,086–1,100&amp;nbsp;kg (Diesel)
|fuel_capacity =
|electric_range =
|related = [[Mazda Demio#2002|Mazda2]]
|designer =
}}
{{See also|Ford Verve concepts}}
[[File:2009-2010 Ford Fiesta (WS) Zetec 5-door hatchback 02.jpg|thumb|left|2009–2010 Ford Fiesta (WS) Zetec 5-door hatchback (Australia)]]

The sixth generation, or '''Ford Fiesta Mark VI''',&lt;ref name=&quot;MK6&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=27699 |title=Geneva global debut for new Fiesta |work=Media.Ford.com |date=15 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; was shown in concept form as the [[Ford Verve]] at the [[Frankfurt Motor Show]] in September 2007 and marketed in principal European markets,&lt;ref name=ADACmotorwelt2008&gt;{{cite book |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= ADAC motorwelt Heft 9 (September 2008) Seite 38|year= |publisher= |location= Muenchen |id=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Australia and the United States. This model is based on Ford's [[Ford B3 platform|new global B-car platform]]. The sixth generation is known as '''Mark VII''' in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mountuneperformance.co.uk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=141&amp;Itemid=58 |title=Fiesta 140ps Upgrade |publisher=Mountuneperformance.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Production started at Ford's Cologne plant in Germany in August 2008. A second plant in Valencia, Spain started production in early 2009. Productions in China, Thailand and Mexico started from late 2008 to 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canadiandriver.com/2008/08/14/ford-fiesta-enters-volume-production.htm |title=Ford Fiesta &quot;global car&quot; begins production |date=2008-08-14 |author= |publisher=Canadian Driver }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fiesta sales for Canada began in June 2010 for model year 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.canadiandriver.com/2010/04/26/first-drive-2011-ford-fiesta.htm |title=First Drive: 2011 Ford Fiesta |date=2010-04-26 |accessdate= |work=Canadian Driver |author=James Bergeron }}&lt;/ref&gt; The 5-door hatchback will also be sold in Mexico starting 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fordvehicles.com/2011fiesta/ |title=Introducing the 2011 Ford Fiesta |work=Ford Motor Company}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The sixth generation sedan was launched in India in July 2011 with both petrol and diesel variants.&lt;ref name=wsj-india2011/&gt;&lt;ref name=toi-fiesta2011&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/business/india-business/Ford-rolls-out-global-Fiesta-at-Rs-823-lakh/articleshow/9229860.cms |title=Ford rolls out global Fiesta at Rs 8.23 lakh |publisher=Times of India |date= |accessdate=2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equipment===
The 2008 Fiesta includes Ford's Convers+ menu system, as seen on the Mondeo, S-MAX and Galaxy, and complemented by steering wheel button controls. Ford initially anticipated that over 85% of Fiesta orders would include this multifunction display. Other new equipment includes keyless entry with a 'Ford Power' starter button, reach and rake adjustable steering wheel, electric power steering, and a USB port for portable music players. Ford Easyfuel, the capless refuelling system recently introduced with the [[Ford Mondeo]], will also be a feature, while 'ambient lighting,' casting a soft red glow over the interior, will be an option. For the 2011 US market model, the [[Ford Sync]] in-car communications and entertainment system will be available as an option.

UK trim levels for the new Fiesta include Studio, Edge, ECONetic, Zetec, Zetec S, Titanium and Titanium Individual.

===ECOnetic model===
{{main|ECOnetic}}
In 2008 Ford revealed details of an ECOnetic model, which Ford stated would emit 98g/km of [[carbon dioxide]]. The car was launched in 2009. It uses the 1.6 [[Ford Duratorq TDCi|Duratorq TDCi]] diesel engine, but with an added diesel particulate filter. The Fiesta ECOnetic achieves its environmental credentials through weight loss and aerodynamic adjustments, and its emission figure exempts the car from UK [[vehicle excise duty]]. The ECOnetic gets an estimated fuel consumption of {{convert|65|mpgus|L/100 km mpgimp|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name='bw'&gt;{{cite web|last=Kiley |first=David |url=http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/08_37/b4099060491065.htm |title=The 65 mpg Ford the U.S. Can't Have |work=BusinessWeek |date=4 September 2008 |accessdate=2009-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; When tested on the highway mileage and emissions test schedules, on which hybrids are designed to perform well,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://autospeed.com/cms/title_Giving-the-Insight-a-Good-Driver/A_110187/article.html |title=Giving the Insight a Good Driver |publisher=AutoSpeed |date= |accessdate=2010-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ECOnetic outperforms the Toyota Prius.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/drive/motor-news/new-fuelmiser-ford-knocks-prius-off-its-perch-20091016-h0ck.html |title=New fuel-miser Ford knocks Prius off its perch |publisher=Smh.com.au |date= 2009-10-16|accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The model will not be available in the U.S. because, as ''Business Week'' noted, the company &quot;doesn't believe it could charge enough to make money on an imported ECOnetic&quot; and doesn't think it would sell enough of the model (350,000/year) to justify the $350 million in upgrades required at their Mexico plant to manufacture it in North America.&lt;ref name='bw'/&gt;

===Fiesta ST===
In 2011 Ford revealed the Fiesta ST concept based on the Fiesta mk7&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=Ford Reveals Fiesta ST Concept at [[Frankfurt Motor Show]]; Previews Future High-Performance Fiesta|publisher=Ford Motor Company Newsroom|url=http://media.ford.com/news/fordrevealsfiestastconceptatfrankfurtpreviewsfuturehighperformancefiesta.htm|date=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;. The High Performance Fiesta is powered by a 1.6-litre Ford Ecoboost Engine to deliver performance while still providing good fuel efficiency. The 1.6-litre Ford [[Ecoboost]] [[Turbocharged]] engine will feature [[Variable valve timing|Twin-independent Variable Camshaft Timing (Ti-VCT)]] and put out {{convert|180|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} with {{convert|240|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} of torque providing an acceleration time of under 7 seconds (0–100&amp;nbsp;km/h) and a top speed exceeding 220&amp;nbsp;km/h. Mated to a 6-speed manual transmission, the car is expected to provide responsible fuel economy while not sacrificing performance. The concept ST features a redesigned front fascia similar to the one seen on its older sibling (Focus ST), LED-laced headlights, Large rear spoiler, aggressive rear diffuser with a twin exit exhaust system, completed with 17-inch wheels. On the inside, the ST provides heavily bolstered [[Recaro]] front seats and sportier décor.

The Fiesta ST Production model is expected to come out in Europe sometime next year, but may also come to the North American market as a five-door hatchback variant instead of the three-door Europe is offered with.

===Body styles===
There are 4 [[car body style|body styles]], including 3 and 5-door [[hatchback]]s, 4-door [[Sedan (automobile)|sedan]], and 2-door [[van]]. They are sold separately depending on the country.
;5-door hatchback: Sold globally except India.
;4-door sedan: Originally available in Chinese and American market, later in other parts of Asia, and then in Australasia.
;3-door hatchback: Sold in Europe, Australasia, and small parts of Asia such as Singapore.
;2-door van: Sold only in Europe. Uses the same bodyshell as the 3-door, modified with solid panels in place of the rear quarter windows and a flat load floor replacing the rear seat.

===Powertrain===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Model !! Years !! Type !! Power, torque@rpm
|-
!colspan=4|Petrol engines&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.config.ford.co.uk/fordconnection/multimedia/gbr_en/00w/yyy/gbr_en00wyyyfuelspc.htm# |title=Fuel, performance and emissions |publisher=Config.ford.co.uk |date=2008-10-09 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1.25 L [[Ford Sigma engine|Duratec]] 60 PS||From 2008||{{convert|1242|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|60|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}, {{convert|109|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}
|-
|1.25 L [[Ford Sigma engine|Duratec]] 82 PS||From 2008||{{convert|1242|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|82|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}, {{convert|114|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}
|-
|1.4 L [[Ford Sigma engine|Duratec]]||From 2008||{{convert|1388|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|96|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}, {{convert|128|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}
|-
|1.6 L [[Ford Sigma engine|Duratec Ti-VCT]]||From 2008||{{convert|1596|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|120|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} @ 6,000&amp;nbsp;rpm, {{convert|152|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} @ 4,050&amp;nbsp;rpm
|-
!colspan=4|Diesel engines
|-
|1.4 L [[Ford Duratorq engine#DLD|Duratorq TDCi]]||From 2008||{{convert|1398|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|68|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} @ 4,500&amp;nbsp;rpm, {{convert|160|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} @ 2,000&amp;nbsp;rpm
|-
|1.6 L [[Ford Duratorq engine#DLD|Duratorq TDCi]]||From 2008||{{convert|1560|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|75|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}, {{convert|185|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}
|-
|1.6 L [[Ford Duratorq engine#DLD|Duratorq TDCi]]||From 2008||{{convert|1560|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|90|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}, {{convert|212|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}
|-
|1.6 L [[Ford Duratorq engine#DLD|Duratorq TDCi]] ECOnetic||From 2008||{{convert|1560|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} I4 ||{{convert|90|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}}, {{convert|200|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}
|}

The 1.6 L Duratorq TDCi with {{convert|75|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} is sold instead of, in some countries alongside with the 1.4 L TDCi.

The 1.6 Duratorq TDCi with {{convert|212|Nm|lbft||abbr=on}} torque is used on non-van models only. Vans with the 1.6 Duratorq TDCi are rated {{convert|200|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} torque.

Transmission choices include a 5-speed manual or 4-speed automatic. The automatic is only offered with the 1.4 L Duratec. The 2011 North American model offers the ''Powershift'' 6-speed dual-clutch as an option in addition to the 5-speed manual, which may be sold with a diesel in Europe in the future.

Thailand is the last plant to start assembling Ford Fiesta for ASEAN countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://paultan.org/2010/07/09/ford-fiesta-starts-to-roll-off-rayong-plant-this-month |title=Ford Fiesta Starts To Roll Off Rayong Plant This Month |publisher=paultan.org |date= |accessdate=2010-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; However 6-speed 'Powershift' dual clutch transmission will be available as standard transmission for 1.6L Ti-VCT engines in Thailand&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ford.co.th |title=Ford Sales &amp; Service (Thailand) |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2010-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Curiously, the Thai-made Fiesta versions – both sedan and five-door hatch – feature a 100 mm pitch circle diameter (PCD) wheel lug mount measurement identical to the Mazda2, as opposed to the 108 mm one as found in other global versions.

In Brazil, the Mexican Fiesta is sold only in 4-door version. The Brazilian-made Sigma 1.6-liter engine is [[flex fuel]], but it does not use [[variable valve timing]]. The power output and torque are {{convert|110|bhp|kW|abbr=on}} and {{convert|155|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} with petrol and {{convert|115|bhp|kW|abbr=on}} and {{convert|159|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} with [[ethanol]].

===Reception===
In late 2008 ''Motor Trend'' called the new generation of Fiesta a &quot;superb little car&quot; whose &quot;greatest problem is that it's still a year away&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Horrell|first=Paul|title=Small Minded|journal=Motor Trend|volume=60|issue=11|pages=44–50|date=November 2008|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; a reference to the fact that the Fiesta would not arrive in the USA until early 2010. British magazine ''Auto Express'' called the car a &quot;new class leader&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;autoexpress2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autoexpress.co.uk/carreviews/grouptests/226986/ford_fiesta_vs_vauxhall_corsa.html |title=Ford Fiesta vs Vauxhall Corsa |month=August | year=2008 |accessdate=2009-02-15 |work=Auto Express }}&lt;/ref&gt; UK's ''Car Magazine'' said it was a &quot;huge achievement&quot; which will &quot;please just about everyone&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carmagazine.co.uk/Drives/Search-Results/First-drives/Ford-Fiesta-2008-CAR-review/ |title=Ford Fiesta 1.6 (2008) CAR review &amp;#124; Road Testing Reviews &amp;#124; Car Magazine Online |publisher=Carmagazine.co.uk |date=2008-08-27 |accessdate=2009-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The February 2009 issue of Britain's ''What Car?'' magazine named the new Fiesta &quot;Car of the Year&quot; and the Ford Mondeo &quot;Best Family Car&quot; and &quot;Best Estate.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;article1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=29750 |title=Fiesta named &quot;Car of the Year&quot; by ''What Car?'', Britain's leading source of new car advice |work=Media.Ford.com |date=22 January 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''What Car?'', there is plenty of space in the front of the cabin, however, the rear knee space is rather limited and the backrests do not fold flat onto the base, making an uneven floor for the expanded boot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatcar.com/car-reviews/ford/fiesta-hatchback/full-review/25846-5 |title=Ford Fiesta Hatchback Full Review |publisher=''What Car?''}}&lt;/ref&gt; This generation draws some criticism for its similarity to [[Peugeot]]s, especially the design of the front end and the headlights. Unlike previous generations, which were more or less gender-neutral, this generation is said to be more appealing to females than males.{{Who|date=January 2011}}

The Fiesta was featured on episode 6 of [[Top Gear (series 12)|series 12]] of ''[[Top Gear (2002 TV series)|Top Gear]]'' in a series of &quot;serious&quot; road tests conducted by presenter [[Jeremy Clarkson]], from escaping 'baddies' driving a [[Chevrolet Corvette C6]] in the [[Festival Place]] [[Basingstoke]] shopping mall, to participating in an amphibious beach assault with the [[Royal Marines]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7e7R3y-qwZ0&lt;/ref&gt;.

In its first two years since the latest generation Fiesta went on sale in October 2008, more than 940,000 Fiestas had been purchased by customers around the world, with 810,000 (86%) being sold in Europe (September, 2010).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://www.at.ford.com/news/cn/Pages/FordRemainsEurope'sNo2Best-SellingCarBrandinAugustandYear-to-Date.aspx
 |title=Ford Remains Europe's No. 2 Best-Selling Car Brand in August and Year-to-Date
 |date=2010-09-16
 |accessdate=2010-09-16
 |publisher=Ford Motor Company
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===North American market===
[[File:2011 Ford Fiesta S sedan front -- 07-10-2010.jpg|thumb|right|2011 Ford Fiesta S sedan (US)]]
[[File:2011 Ford Fiesta SES hatchback -- 02-18-2011.jpg|thumb|right|2011 Ford Fiesta SES 5-door (US)]]

Kevin George directed the adaptation of the Fiesta's design for the North American market, reshaping the front end to comply with federal impact standards, keeping the styling substantially like the European model. &quot;I spent about two years trying to make it look like I did nothing&quot;, George said.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytsame&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
 | title = 2 Cars Separated at Birth
 | work=The New York Times
 | author=Phil Patton
 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2010/09/12/automobiles/12DESIGN.html?hpw
 | date=2010-09-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The North American front fascia includes LED parking lamps, used in a few other markets.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytsame&quot;/&gt;

Unveiled at the [[Los Angeles Auto Show#2009|2009 Los Angeles Auto Show]] in December,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueovalnews.com/index.php?categoryid=12&amp;p2_articleid=760 |title=Ford Forums, Ford News, Ford Motor Company News, Ford Employee Forum, Ford Reviews, Ford Edge Forum, Ford Flex Forum, Ford Fusion Forum, Ford Sales Figures, Ford Eco Boost Forum, Ford Transit Forum, Ford Transit Connect Forum, Lincoln MKS Forum – FORD'S NEW FIESTA TO DEBUT AT L.A. AUTO SHOW; FIESTA AGENTS BEGIN FINAL MONTH OF MISSIONS |publisher=BlueOvalNews |date=2009-10-06 |accessdate=2010-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Fiesta offers Ford's &quot;Powershift&quot; dual-clutch automatic transmission and is offered as a four door sedan and five door hatchback.

Ford dealers in the US will offer optional laminated vinyl graphics applied to the car's exterior, expected to last 3 to 5 years before being replaced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fordfiestagraphics.com/faq.php |title=Car Wrap Designs for the Ford Fiesta |publisher=Ford Fiesta Graphics |date= |accessdate=2010-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, certain dealers partaking in a new Ford Retail program will provide an &quot;unwrapping&quot; digital package loaded with a photograph of the buyer taking delivery of his/her new car. A 19-minute audio description of the car and its features is included, which can be played on the way home, then loaded along with its interactive program into the home computer via its [[USB]] connection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=32841 |title=Ford Fiesta 'Unwraps' Itself With Unique New Interactive Owner Delivery Experience &amp;#124; Ford Motor Company Newsroom |publisher=Media.ford.com |date=2010-06-24 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Preliminary marketing====
For the North American Fiesta, Ford initiated a marketing campaign in the spring of 2009 called the Fiesta Movement, distributing examples of European Fiestas to applicants across the United States—to have the test drivers use popular Internet sites to share their experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.ford.com/wireless_article_display.cfm?article_id=30156 |title=Ford names 100 Fiesta Movement 'agents' to hit the road, find adventure, share experiences |work=Media.Ford.com |date=7 April 2009 |accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently, Ford brought the cars to public venues nationwide to offer 100,000 test drives over eight months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.ford.com/article_display.cfm?article_id=30344 |title=Be part of Ford's Fiesta Movement: 100,000 test drives planned for the new fuel-efficient Fiesta |work=Media.Ford.com |date=11 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such event was offering free shuttle service in Chicago from a site near the [[Union Station (Chicago)|Union Station]] commuter rail terminal to the [[Taste of Chicago]] event in Grant Park the week starting 29 June 2009. Late in July, six European Fiestas arrived in [[Halifax Regional Municipality|Halifax, Nova Scotia]], to begin a similar demonstration tour across Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canadiandriver.com/2009/07/29/new-ford-fiesta-to-make-cross-country-tour.htm |title=New Ford Fiesta to make cross-country tour |publisher=CanadianDriver |date=29 July 2009 |accessdate=2009-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following on the success of Fiesta Movement, Ford initiated Fiesta Movement 2 in December 2009 by calling for video applications to be submitted by the end of January 2010 for activities to begin mid-February.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2009/12/03/ford-accepting-applications-for-fiesta-movement-2/ |title=Ford accepting applications for Fiesta Movement 2 |author=Shunk, Chris |date=3 December 2009 |work=Autoblog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2010, Ford worked with the television series ''[[American Idol]]'' to promote the Ford Fiesta in North America. Working with Ford designers, the final 12 contestants of the show created their own custom graphics on a Ford Fiesta, which were subsequently revealed on the show with fans given the chance to win one of the personalised cars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fastfiesta.com/idol-fiesta.html |title=Custom Ford Fiesta Designs from American Idol Finalists |publisher=Fast Fiesta |date=18 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Launch====
Production of Ford Fiesta for the North American market started in May 2010. Ford planned to have cars available for sale soon after in summer. On 18 June 2010, it was reported that although dealers took deposits from over 2,000 customers for Fiesta and placed large orders as the car was heavily marketed, dealers and customers had not received cars that they expected to have arrived weeks ago in May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autoweek.com/article/20100618/CARNEWS/100619870 |title=Ford Fiesta not yet in dealerships; dealers and customers get antsy Read more: http://www.autoweek.com/article/20100618/CARNEWS/100619870#ixzz0xjouGWWd |date=2010-06-18 |author=Jamie Lareau |publisher=Autonews via Autoweek}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July, Ford said initial shipments were delayed for up to two weeks by Hurricane Alex that hit Northern Mexico in late June, and subsequently by Tropical Storm Bonnie.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autoblog.com/2010/07/13/ford-fiesta-shipments-delayed-due-to-hurricane-damaged-railroad/ |title=Ford Fiesta shipments delayed due to hurricane |date=2010-07-13 |author=Jeremy Korzeniewski |publisher=Autoblog }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the delays, Ford sent out US$50 gift certificates. By August 2010, Ford delayed some shipments because of a 'quality problem'. Ford claimed the issue was fixed and it was unlikely cars with defective parts would reach customers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.autoblog.com/2010/08/26/ford-fiesta-shipments-flowing-again-after-faulty-part-fixed/ |title=Ford Fiesta shipments flowing again after faulty part fixed |date=2010-08-26 |author=Chris Shunk |publisher=Autoblog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Recognition====
The 2011 Fiesta was one of the five finalists for the 2011 [[Green Car of the Year]] awarded by the [[Green Car Journal]] in November 2010, competing with two [[plug-in electric vehicle]]s, the [[Nissan Leaf]] and the [[Chevrolet Volt]] (the winner), and two [[hybrid electric vehicle]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greencar.com/articles/chevrolet-volt-electric-car-2011-green-car-year.php|title=Chevrolet Volt Electric Car is 2011 Green Car of the Year|publisher=[[Green Car Journal]]|date=2010-11-18|accessdate=2010-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indian Launch===
Ford Fiesta for the Indian market has been finalised in both sedan and hatchback versions. It was put on show on 15 April 2011 in a Delhi mall. The model on show was a TDCi 1.6 Fiesta Sedan but the variant was not disclosed. The top model is supposed to come with Bluetooth, Cruise control, Pull control, USB and SYNC as standard features. The other cars it will compete against will include Fiat Linea and Volkswagen Vento both of which have extended wheelbases, which the Fiesta does not.

==Commercial variants==
All six generations of the Fiesta have been available in [[panel van]] format, although not available in all markets. The Mark I, II and III versions feature the standard 3-door bodyshell with the rear side glass replaced by body coloured metal and a flat floorpan instead of the rear seats.

In 1991, a &quot;high-cube&quot; style van based on the Mark III chassis was introduced and was named the [[Ford Courier (Europe)|Ford Courier]]. The Courier continued in the Mark IV style through until 2002, when it was replaced by the [[Ford Transit Connect]].

For the Mark V, the standard Fiestavan version was based on the 3-door bodyshell rather than the taller 5-door version. The Mark VI Fiesta van was first introduced in the European market in the summer of 2009, a year after the original launch.

==Motorsport==
===Rallying===
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Group N rally car
|image = [[Image:Ford Fiesta Rally car.JPG|250px]] ''Ford Fiesta Rally car Group N in Rally Japan 2007, No.102 Kodue Oi.''
|manufacturer = Ford Motors and [[M-Sport]]
}}

Two Ford Fiestas famously starred in the 1979 [[Monte Carlo rally]]—the British entry driven by [[Roger Clark]] and aided by co-driver [[Jim Porter]], and a German entry piloted by [[Ari Vatanen]] and co-driven by [[David Richards (racing)|David Richards]].

Both cars were highly modified with special motorsport components throughout and featured pioneering [[Limited Slip Differential]] (LSD) [[technology]]. The cars were powered by competition tuned versions of the 1600&amp;nbsp;cc Kent crossflow engine—a later version of which appeared in the '''Mk 1 Fiesta XR2'''.

The 2 cars worked well in the arduous ice and snow that year. [[Roger Clark]] did not set any records but the German car achieved 9th position overall—a very encouraging result which sparked demand for sportier Fiestas.

Since this there have been sporting and &quot;[[hot hatch]]&quot; editions. Versions include Supersport, XR2, S(Sport), XR2i, Si, RS Turbo, RS1800, Zetec S, Zetec RS, and ST. All of these were powered by a range of engines from the [[Ford Kent engine]] to the [[Ford Duratec engine]].

The Ford RallyeConcept in 2002 and Fiesta [[JWRC]]. Ford RallyeConcept has been realised through an intensely close collaboration between Ford RallyeSport, the motorsport experts behind the Puma [[Super 1600]] and the Focus [[World Rally Championship|WRC]] rally cars, and Ford Design Europe, the creative team responsible for the new three-door Fiesta on which the RallyeConcept is based. Ford RallyeConcept's marriage of the motorsport engineer's objective for performance functionality with the eye for detail of the designer has been so effective that Ford has committed to an engineering development programme to bring a Fiesta-based rally car to reality. Aiming for FIA homologation by the summer of 2003, Ford RallyeSport is hoping that it will become Ford's next success story in national and international rallying. Fiesta [[Super 1600]] debut Rally Greece 2004.

The &quot;Fiesta Sporting Trophy&quot; is a ''One Make'' Championship; beginning its 1st season in March 2006. It combines keen competition with equal performance and leaves the decision about winning or losing to the drivers and co-drivers capabilities. The driver, co-driver and mechanics work as a team to compete against the toughest adversary of all—the clock.

The Fiesta Sporting Trophy will be based around the Fiesta ST [[Group N]] car. The car has {{convert|165|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} from the 2 L Duratec ST engine which when combined with the conversion kit from [[M-Sport]], has been designed to provide all of the safety equipment and performance upgrades to enable the car to be competitive and reliable at any event around the world.

In March 2007, the Pirtek Rally Team introduced the Ford Fiesta [[Super 2000]] rally car, which will compete in the [[Australian Rally Championship]].

On 18 November 2009, Ford with M-Sport unveiled the Ford Fiesta S2000 Mark VI. Although not due for homologation until January 2010 it is set to make its debut as course car on the final round of the IRC series, Rally Scotland. The car has been built to compete mainly in the [[Super 2000 World Rally Championship]] and [[World Rally Championship]] when the new rules come into place for [[2011 World Rally Championship season|2011]] but it is expected to make appearances in the IRC as well.

====Fiesta ST Group N specifications====
[[File:Rally Finland 2010 - shakedown - Nasser Al-Attiyah 1.jpg|thumb|[[Nasser Al-Attiyah]] driving Ford Fiesta S2000 at [[2010 Rally Finland]].]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
![[Engine]]
| {{convert|1999|cc|cuin|abbr=on}} Duratec engine. Four cylinders in line, [[DOHC]], 16 valves, alloy cylinder head and block.&lt;br /&gt;Electronic multipoint fuel injection.
|-
![[Power (physics)|Power]]
|{{convert|165|PS|kW bhp|abbr=on}} at 5,800&amp;nbsp;rpm
|-
![[Torque]]
|{{convert|202|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}} at 4,500&amp;nbsp;rpm
|-
![[Transmission (mechanics)|Transmission]]
|Five-speed 'dog' engagement gearkit fitted to standard ST road car casing.&lt;br /&gt;Upgraded driveshafts fitted as standard. Plated LSD.
|-
![[Suspension (vehicle)|Suspension]]
|Upgraded suspension of ST road car includes revised front knuckles and strengthened twist beam rear axle.&lt;br /&gt;Reiger dampers, adjustable for rebound, and revised spring rates. Uprated suspension bushes.
|-
![[Brakes]]
|Standard ST road car front and rear disc brakes.
|-
![[Wheel]]s
|Gravel: 15-inch OZ Racing wheels
Asphalt: 17-inch OZ Racing wheels
Wheels manufactured in both Super T and Rally Racing style.
|-
![[Frame (vehicle)|Bodyshell]]
|Multipoint roll cage designed by M-Sport, complying with FIA regulations.&lt;br /&gt;Includes three X braces in rear and twin tube door bars with no cross-over.
|-
![[Electronics]]
|'Piggy back' loom supplements standard loom.&lt;br /&gt;Includes electronic circuit breaker and wiring for additional requirements.
|-
![[Fuel tank]]
|Standard {{convert|45|L|impgal U.S.gal|abbr=on}} tank with Kevlar composite moulded guard.
|-
!Dimensions
|Length: {{convert|3921|mm|in|abbr=on}}.&lt;br /&gt;Width: {{convert|1683|mm|in|abbr=on}}.&lt;br /&gt;Height: {{convert|1468|mm|in|abbr=on}}.&lt;br /&gt;Wheelbase: {{convert|2486|mm|in|abbr=on}}.
|}

===Rallycross===
{{Infobox automobile
|name = Ford Fiesta Div 1 rallycross car
|image = [[Image:GrönholmRallycrossFiesta2008.jpg|250px]]&lt;br /&gt;''The 2008 Ford Fiesta ST ERC (4WD, {{convert|560|bhp|kW PS|abbr=on}}, {{convert|800|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}) of Marcus Grönholm for Rallycross pictured at a press conference in Stockholm.''
|manufacturer = Ford's TeamRS and Swedish rally team MSE
}}

Fiesta [[Rallycross|ERC]] Div 1 is racecar with a 2.0 L [[Duratec]] turbocharged four cylinder engine, running on petrol or [[E85]] (85% ethanol/15% petrol). It produces over {{convert|550|bhp|kW PS|abbr=on}} and {{convert|820|Nm|lbft|abbr=on}}. That propels the {{convert|2600|lb|kg|abbr=on}} rally-prepped Fiesta up to sixty in 2.8 seconds. The car is driven by former champion [[Andreas Erikkson]], double World Rally Champion [[Marcus Grönholm]], X Games medalist [[Tanner Foust]] and several others. The cars are smaller and more powerful than [[World Rally Championship|WRC]] cars.

The Fiesta Rallycross cars made their U.S. debuts in July's Pikes Peak International Hill Climb in Colorado. Swedish Olsbergs Motor Sport Evolution (MSE) team announced the cars would later appear in ESPN's [[X Games]] 15 on 2009-08-02.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Joseph |first=Noah |url=http://www.autoblog.com/2009/07/02/ford-attacking-x-games-with-star-studded-trio-of-fiesta-rally-ca/ |title=Ford attacking X Games with star-studded trio of Fiesta rally cars |publisher=Autoblog.com |date=2009-07-02 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Olsbergs MSE Fiesta Rallycross cars were based on the Fiesta hatchback model road cars, but with all-wheel drive, powered by 2.0 L Duratec Ford engines capable of more than {{convert|800|bhp|kW|abbr=on}}.

===Circuit racing===
In the UK, the Fiesta is commonly used in numerous club level motorsport series but has its national one-make series called the ''Ford Fiesta Championship''. During its peak in the 1980s and 1990s, it had manufacturer support and it even was a support race to the [[British Grand Prix]] and numerous [[British Touring Car Championship]] rounds. The series has gone through numerous name changes including ''Ford Credit Fiesta Championship'', ''Ford Fiesta Zetec Championship'' and ''BRSCC Ford Si Challenge'' and is nowadays run by the BRSCC ([[British Racing and Sports Car Club]]) as a club racing championship. The organisation also run the other series that consists of Fiestas.&lt;ref name=fordracing&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fordracinguk.com/ |title=BRSCC Ford Championships |accessdate=2008-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Ford XR Challenge'', for XR2 and XR2i models, also consists of the Escort XR models.&lt;ref name=fordracing/&gt;
* ''Ford Saloon Championship'', mainly for a wider range of Ford models but Fiestas are mostly seen in classes C and E with a Mk 4 example winning the title outright in 2006 at the hands of Ollie Allen.&lt;ref name=fordracing/&gt;{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

==Popularity==
{{Expand section|date=January 2010}}
In early 2009, total sales of the Fiesta since its launch 33 years earlier passed the 3,500,000 mark in Britain, making it the second most popular car ever sold there after the [[Ford Escort (Europe)|Ford Escort]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://icliverpool.icnetwork.co.uk/motors/advice/tm_headline=recession-proof-wise-buys-revealed&amp;method=full&amp;objectid=23171460&amp;siteid=63127-name_page.html |title=icLiverpool – Recession-proof wise-buys revealed |publisher=Icliverpool.icnetwork.co.uk |date=2009-03-17 |accessdate=2010-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been Britain's most popular new car in 1990, 1991, 1996, 1997, 1998 and 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cardealermagazine.co.uk/publish/ford-fiesta-is-2009-best-seller/28370 |title=Ford Fiesta is top in 09 |publisher=Car Dealer Magazine |date=2010-01-08 |accessdate=2010-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, it was Britain's best selling car for the second year running.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carkeys.co.uk/news/2011/january/7/uk_registrations_2010.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of the MK2 Fiesta's demise in the spring of 1989, just under 1,300,000 had been sold in Britain since its launch 12 years earlier. By early 2007, well over 40,000 (more than 3%) were still in circulation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/motoring/features/nissan-micra-443911.html | location=London | work=The Independent | date=2007-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; though that figure has inevitably declined further since then.

== Sales ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year !! Sales in the UK
|-
| 2001 || 98,221&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2002/01/new-car-sales-seven-record-months-one-record-year/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2002 || 93,591&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2003/01/new-car-market-scores-a-record-breaking-2002/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2003 || 95,887&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2004/01/consumer-confidence-drives-record-year/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2004 || 89,295&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2005/01/new-car-market-in-2004-falls-just-short-of-record-total/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2005 || 83,803&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2006/01/record-december-after-a-tough-year-for-new-car-sales/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2009 || 117,296&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2010/01/2009-ends-year-with-strong-growth-december-up-38-9/&lt;/ref&gt;
|}
In 2002, it was the fifth best selling new car in the UK, but was ranked third in the supermini charts after the [[Vauxhall Corsa]] and [[Peugeot 206]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.smmt.co.uk/2003/01/new-car-market-scores-a-record-breaking-2002/&lt;/ref&gt; It claimed the top spot in its sector in 2006.{{Citation needed|reason=Aug 2010|date=August 2010}}

In the US Ford sold 23,273 Fiestas in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cheersandgears.com/topic/74946-december-2010-sales-ford-motor-company/ |title=Jan–Apr 2011 Sales: Ford Motor Company – Cheers &amp; Gears Forums |publisher=Cheersandgears.com |date= |accessdate=2011-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Fiesta is one of Brazil's best-selling vehicles, selling around 5,000 units per month. From September 2002 to April 2007, more than 336,000 units have been sold, outselling its competitors: Chevrolet Corsa (183,000 in the same period) and Renault Clio (122,267). Ford Brazil also makes a Fiesta Sedan, which has sold 113,000 units since its launch in 2004.{{Citation needed|reason=Aug 2010|date=August 2010}}

==Awards==
* Winner of ''UK [[Design Council]] Efficiency Award'' for &quot;exemplary contribution to the reduction of running and [[Car maintenance|maintenance]] costs&quot; in 1978. The award was presented by [[Prince Philip]].
* Winner ''Australia's Best Small Car'' in 2004.
* Winner of ''[[Business Standard]] [[Motoring]] Jury Award'', 2006.
* [[What Car?|What Car's]] Best Used [[supermini car|Supermini]] for 2006 – 1.4 Zetec 3dr 2003 – Runner Up [[Toyota Yaris]] 1.0 T2 3dr 2003.
* Winner of Brazilian ''Auto Esporte'' magazine ''Car of the Year'' in 2005 (Fiesta Sedan)&lt;!-- http://www.carronovo.com.br/noticiasconteudo.php?NoticiaID=760 --&gt;.
* Named ''Scottish Car of the Year 2008'' at the 11th annual Association of Scottish Motoring Writers (ASMW) awards dinner in St Andrew's, Scotland.
* Named 'Car of the Year 1989' by Britain's [[What Car?]] magazine
* Named 'Car of the Year 2009' by Britain's What Car? magazine&lt;ref name=&quot;article1&quot;/&gt;
* Named 'Semperit Irish Small car of the Year' by tyre mafacturer [[Semperit]]
* Named 'Car of the Year' and 'Best Supermini' in Auto Express magazine's New Car Awards 2009
* Fiesta ECOnetic named 'Least boring green car'of 2009 by Top Gear's James May
* First minicar to achieve Top Safety Pick by the U.S. [[Insurance Institute for Highway Safety#Top Safety Pick Award|Insurance Institute for Highway Safety]] (IIHS) based on front-, side- and rear-impact crash testing and roof-strength.
* Winner of the 2011 [[Automobile Journalists Association of Canada|AJAC]] Car of the year award for Best Small Car under $21,000.

==See also==
* [[Ford Ikon]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Ford Fiesta}}
* [http://www.fordvehicles.com/cars/fiesta/ Ford Fiesta USA official website]
* [http://www.ford.co.uk/fiesta Ford Fiesta UK official website]
* [http://www.ford.co.uk/Commercialvehicles/NewFiestaVan/Overview Ford UK Fiesta van site]
* [http://www.fordmedia.eu/presskits/30YearsFordFiesta/htdocs/ Ford Fiesta official history website (Mark and time line history) Ford of Europe, Media Kits]
&lt;!--
*********************** ({{No More Links}}) ***************************
*Please be cautious in adding more links to this article. Wikipedia  *
*is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. *
*                                                                     *
*           Excessive or inappropriate links Will-Be-Deleted.         *
*See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  *
*                                                                     *
*If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   *
*replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link *
*to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   *
*and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         *
********************** ({{No More Links}}) ****************************
--&gt;

{{Ford vehicles}}
{{FordEurope}}
{{Ford postwar template}}
{{Modern North American Ford vehicles}}
{{Early European Ford vehicles}}
{{Modern European Ford vehicles}}
{{Ford Australia timeline}}
{{Ford Motor Company vehicles}}

[[Category:Vehicles introduced in 1976]]
[[Category:Vehicles introduced in 2008]]
[[Category:Ford of Europe vehicles|Fiesta]]
[[Category:Subcompact cars]]
[[Category:Hatchbacks]]
[[Category:Sedans]]
[[Category:Euro NCAP superminis]]
[[Category:Hot Hatch]]
[[Category:Sports sedans]]
[[Category:Ford B3 platform]]
[[Category:Rally cars]]
[[Category:Cars of Spain]]
[[Category:Vehicles with CVT transmission]]
[[Category:Front-wheel-drive vehicles]]
[[Category:Goods manufactured in Germany]]
[[Category:1970s automobiles]]
[[Category:1980s automobiles]]
[[Category:1990s automobiles]]
[[Category:2000s automobiles]]
[[Category:2010s automobiles]]

[[be:Ford Fiesta]]
[[bg:Форд Фиеста]]
[[cs:Ford Fiesta]]
[[da:Ford Fiesta]]
[[de:Ford Fiesta]]
[[es:Ford Fiesta]]
[[fa:فورد فیستا]]
[[fr:Ford Fiesta]]
[[hr:Ford Fiesta]]
[[id:Ford Fiesta]]
[[it:Ford Fiesta]]
[[lv:Ford Fiesta]]
[[lt:Ford Fiesta]]
[[hu:Ford Fiesta]]
[[nah:Ford Fiesta III]]
[[nl:Ford Fiesta]]
[[ja:フォード・フィエスタ]]
[[no:Ford Fiesta]]
[[pl:Ford Fiesta]]
[[pt:Ford Fiesta]]
[[ro:Ford Fiesta]]
[[ru:Ford Fiesta]]
[[sco:Ford Fiesta]]
[[simple:Ford Fiesta]]
[[sk:Ford Fiesta]]
[[fi:Ford Fiesta]]
[[sv:Ford Fiesta]]
[[ta:ஃபோர்டு ஃபீஸ்டா]]
[[th:ฟอร์ด เฟียสตา]]
[[tr:Ford Fiesta]]
[[uk:Ford Fiesta]]
[[zh:福特嘉年華]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
