<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4801" ns="0" title="BeOS"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS
| name          = BeOS
| screenshot    = [[Image:BeOS Desktop.png|250px]]&lt;!-- Do not change unless you have read &quot;Wikipedia:Software_screenshots&quot;! --&gt;
| caption       = BeOS R4.5
| developer     = [[Be Inc.]]
| family        = BeOS
| source_model  = [[Closed source]]
| frequently_updated = yes
| working_state = Discontinued/Historic
| kernel_type   = [[Modularity (programming)|Modular]] [[Hybrid kernel]]
| supported_platforms = [[IA-32]], [[PowerPC]]
| license       = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website       = [http://www.beincorporated.com/ www.beincorporated.com]
}}
'''BeOS''' is an [[operating system]] for [[personal computer]]s which began development by [[Be Inc.]] in 1991. It was first written to run on [[BeBox]] hardware. BeOS was optimized for digital media work and was written to take advantage of modern hardware facilities such as [[symmetric multiprocessing]] by utilizing modular I/O bandwidth, pervasive multithreading, [[preemptive multitasking]] and a [[64-bit]] [[journaling file system]] known as [[Be File System|BFS]]. The BeOS GUI was developed on the principles of clarity and a clean, uncluttered design. It used [[Unicode]] as the default encoding in the GUI, yet support for input methods, such as bidirectional input was never realized. The [[application programming interface|API]] was written in [[C++]] for ease of programming. It has partial [[POSIX]] compatibility and access to a [[command-line interface]] through [[Bash (Unix shell)|Bash]], although internally it is not a Unix-derived operating system.

BeOS was positioned as a multimedia platform which could be used by a substantial population of desktop users and a competitor to [[Mac OS]] and [[Microsoft Windows]]. However, it was ultimately unable to achieve a significant market share and proved commercially unviable for Be Inc. The company was acquired by [[Palm Inc.]] and today BeOS is mainly used and developed by a small population of enthusiasts.

The open-source OS [[Haiku (operating system)|Haiku]] is designed to start up where BeOS left off. Alpha 3 of Haiku was released in June 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.haiku-os.org/news/2011-06-18_haiku_release_1_alpha_3 |title=Haiku Release 1 Alpha 3 |date=June 18, 2011 |work=Haiku-OS.org }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
Initially designed to run on [[AT&amp;T Hobbit]]-based hardware, BeOS was later modified to run on [[PowerPC]]-based processors: first Be's own systems, later [[Apple Inc.]]'s [[PowerPC Reference Platform]] and [[Common Hardware Reference Platform]], with the hope that Apple would purchase or license BeOS as a replacement for its then aging [[Mac OS#&quot;Classic&quot; Mac OS (1984–2001)|Mac OS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://macreate.net/reloaded/?q=node/view/149  | title=BeOS @ MaCreate | date=2004-11-24 | author=Tom | accessdate=2006-11-16 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050324220739/http://macreate.net/reloaded/?q=node/view/149 |archivedate = 2005-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple CEO [[Gil Amelio]] started negotiations to buy Be Inc., but negotiations stalled when Be CEO [[Jean-Louis Gassée]] wanted $200 million; Apple was unwilling to offer any more than $125 million. Apple's board of directors decided [[NeXTSTEP]] was a better choice and purchased [[NeXT]] in 1996 for $429 million, bringing back Apple co-founder [[Steve Jobs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://macspeedzone.com/archive/art/con/be.shtml Apple Confidential: The Day They Almost Decided To Put Windows NT On The Mac Instead Of OS X!]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, [[Power Computing]] began bundling BeOS (on a CD for optional installation) with its line of PowerPC-based [[Macintosh clone]]s. These systems could [[dual boot]] either the [[Mac OS]] or BeOS, with a start-up screen offering the choice.

Due to Apple's moves and the mounting debt of Be Inc., BeOS was soon ported to the [[X86 architecture|Intel x86]] platform with its R3 release in March 1998. Through the late 1990s, BeOS managed to create a niche of followers, but the company failed to remain viable. As a last-ditch effort to increase interest in the failing operating system, Be Inc. released a stripped-down, but free, copy of [[BeOS R5]] known as BeOS Personal Edition (BeOS PE). BeOS PE could be started from within [[Microsoft Windows]] or [[Linux]], and was intended to nurture consumer interest in its product and give developers something to tinker with.

Be Inc. also released a stripped-down version of BeOS for Internet Appliances ([[BeIA]]), which soon became the company's business focus in place of BeOS. BeOS PE and BeIA proved to be too little too late, and in 2001 Be's copyrights were sold to [[Palm, Inc.]] for some $11 million. BeOS R5 is considered the last official version, but BeOS R5.1 &quot;[[Dano (BeOS)|Dano]]&quot;, which was under development before Be's sale to Palm and included the [[BeOS Networking Environment]] (BONE) networking stack, was leaked to the public shortly after the company's demise.

In 2002, Be Inc. sued&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2002/02/20/be_inc_sues_microsoft/ | title=Be Inc. sues Microsoft | date=2002-02-20 | author=Andrew Orlowski| accessdate=2008-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft claiming that [[Hitachi]] had been dissuaded from selling PCs loaded with BeOS, and that [[Compaq]] had been pressured not to market an Internet appliance in partnership with Be. Be also claimed that Microsoft acted to artificially depress Be Inc.'s [[initial public offering]] (IPO). The case was eventually settled out of court&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.internetnews.com/ent-news/print.php/3073811/ | title=Microsoft Settles Anti-Trust Charges with Be | date=2003-09-08 | author=Mark Berniker| accessdate=2008-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; for $23.25 million with no admission of liability on Microsoft's part.

After the split from Palm, [[PalmSource]] used parts of BeOS's multimedia framework for its failed [[Palm OS#Palm OS Cobalt|Palm OS Cobalt]] product.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.access-company.com/news/press/PalmSource/2004/021004_cobalt.html PalmSource Introduces Palm OS Cobalt], PalmSource press release, 10 February 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; With the takeover of PalmSource, the BeOS rights now belong to [[Access Co.]]

===Continuation===
Despite the end of Be Inc., BeOS has devoted followers. The BeOS community still develops free software and has even released patches, drivers and various updates to BeOS. The main source of BeOS-related software can be found at BeBits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=BeBits&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; The Best Source of BeOS Software | url=http://www.bebits.com | accessdate=2006-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The BeOS user interface was notable at the time for being almost completely [[theme (computing)|unthemeable]], even with third party hacks. The BeOS theme of yellow, changing length [[tab (GUI)|tab]]s on the top of windows, and relatively plain grey interface [[widget (computing)|widget]]s was enforced. This UI remained relatively unchanged from 1995, but had been completely overhauled by the time of the leaked ''Dano'' release. An [[Easter egg (virtual)|Easter egg]] in the OS allowed changing the title bar look-and-feel to a few others (Mac OS 8, [[Workbench (AmigaOS)|Amiga Workbench]], and [[Windows 98]] appearances) and in ''Dano'', this had been extended to be a feature allowing changing of the title bar and scroll bars. No other interface widgets could be changed. There is a pre-Dano third party program WindowShade that allows the colors of the title bar and window frame to be changed, but the appearance remained the same.

The plain BeOS R5 GUI is commonly cloned, for example with themes for the [[GNOME]] or [[KDE]] desktop environment.

===Version history===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Release !! Date !! Hardware
|-
| DR1–DR5
| October 1995
| [[AT&amp;T Hobbit]]
|-
| DR6 (developer release)
| January 1996
| rowspan=&quot;6&quot; | [[PowerPC]]
|-
| DR7
| April 1996
|-
| DR8
| September 1996
|-
| Advanced Access Preview Release
| May 1997
|-
| PR1 (preview release)
| June 1997
|-
| PR2
| October 1997
|-
| R3
| March 1998
| rowspan=&quot;6&quot; | PowerPC and [[Intel x86]]
|-
| R3.1
| June 1998
|-
| R3.2
| July 1998
|-
| R4
| November 4, 1998
|-
| R4.5 (&quot;Genki&quot;)
| June 1999
|-
| [[BeOS R5|R5 PE/Pro (&quot;Maui&quot;)]]
| March 2000
|-
| [[Dano (BeOS)|R5.1 (&quot;Dano&quot;)]]
| November 2001
| rowspan=&quot;1&quot; | Intel x86
|}

== Projects to recreate BeOS ==
BeOS was well respected by a small but loyal user base, which was disappointed when Be Inc. failed commercially and no further enhancement of the operating system would be possible. In the years that followed a handful of projects formed to recreate BeOS or key elements of the OS with the eventual goal of then continuing where Be Inc. left off. To ensure that the OS could not be &quot;taken away&quot; from the Be community again, and to attract the efforts of volunteer programmers, these projects were all [[free and open source software]]. The modular nature of the original BeOS facilitated recreating the operating system a piece at a time, inserting the newly coded modules into a working BeOS system to test compatibility. Eventually, all of the &quot;servers&quot; (interworking modules of code) were to be replaced with original, freely licensed code.

Within a few years, some of these projects lost momentum and were discontinued. The Blue Eyed Os website is back online after being missing for 2 years but hasn't had a release since 2003, the most recent release available on the Cosmoe web site is from 2004 and active development on [[E/OS]] ended in July 2008, BeOS Workstation picked up where Be. Inc left off but that too seems to be dead as well. Development however continues on [[Haiku (operating system)|Haiku]], a complete reimplementation of BeOS. The first alpha release, &quot;Haiku R1 / Alpha 1&quot;, was released on September 14, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haiku-os.org/news/2009-09-13_haiku_project_announces_availability_haiku_r1alpha_1|title=Haiku Project Announces Availability of Haiku R1/Alpha 1|date=2009-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second alpha release, &quot;Haiku R1 / Alpha 2&quot;, was made available on May 9, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haiku-os.org/news/2010-05-10_haiku_project_announces_availability_haiku_r1alpha_2|title=Haiku Project Announces Availability of Haiku R1/Alpha 2|date=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third alpha release, &quot;Haiku R1 / Alpha 3&quot;, was released on June 18, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.haiku-os.org/news/2011-06-18_haiku_release_1_alpha_3 |title=Haiku Release 1 Alpha 3 |date=June 18, 2011 |work=Haiku-OS.org }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Projects to continue BeOS ==
[[Magnussoft ZETA|ZETA]] was a commercially available operating system based on the BeOS R5.1 codebase. Originally developed by [[YellowTAB]], the operating system was then distributed by [[magnussoft]]. During development by YellowTAB, the company received criticism from the BeOS community for refusing to discuss its legal position with regard to the BeOS codebase (perhaps for contractual reasons). [[Access Co.]] (which bought [[PalmSource]], until then the holder of the intellectual property associated with BeOS) has since declared that YellowTAB had no right to distribute a modified version of BeOS, and magnussoft has ceased distribution of the operating system.

== Products using BeOS ==
BeOS (and now Zeta) continue to be used in media appliances such as the Edirol DV-7 video editors from [[Roland corporation]] which run on top of a modified BeOS&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.edirol.com/products/dv7dl/index.html | title=EDIROL by Roland DV-7DL Series Digital Video Workstations | accessdate=2006-11-16 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061110070209/http://www.edirol.com/products/dv7dl/index.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the TuneTracker radio automation software that runs on BeOS and Zeta, but is also sold as a &quot;Station-in-a-Box&quot; with the Zeta operating system included.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.tunetrackersystems.com/products.html | title=TuneTracker Radio Automation Software | accessdate=2006-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tascam SX-1 digital audio recorder runs a heavily modified version of BeOS that will only launch the recording interface software.

iZ Technology sells the [[RADAR (audio recorder)|RADAR 24 and RADAR V]], hard disk-based, 24-track professional audio recorders based on BeOS 5.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://mixonline.com/mag/audio_iz_radar/ | title=iZ RADAR 24 | accessdate=2006-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Magicbox, a manufacturer of signage and broadcast display machines, uses BeOS to power their [[Aavelin]] product line.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://digitalcontentproducer.com/digitalsign/depth/digital_signage_hardware_05012006/ | title=Technology Showcase: Digital Signage Hardware | author=Jay Ankeney | date=2006-05-01 | publisher=Digital Content Producer | accessdate=2006-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Final Scratch]], the 12″ vinyl timecode record-driven DJ software/hardware system, was first developed on BeOS. The &quot;ProFS&quot; version was sold to a few dozen DJs prior to the 1.0 release, which ran on a Linux virtual partition.

== See also ==
* [[Access Co.]]
* [[bootman]]
* [[Comparison of operating systems]]
* [[Gobe Productive]]
* [[Haiku (operating system)]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; an open source continuation of BeOS
* [[Hitachi Flora Prius]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; a computer that shipped with an installation of BeOS, but with Windows as the only boot option
* [[KDL]]
* [[List of BeOS programs]]
* [[NetPositive]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Default web browser of BeOS
* [[OpenTracker]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; File manager from BeOS, officially and freely licensed
* [[Pe (text editor)]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.bebits.com/app/2680 BeOS 5.0 (Personal Edition) as a free download] (Most likely to be documented for early 2000-01 hardware.)
* [http://testou.free.fr/www.beatjapan.org/mirror/www.be.com/ Mirror of the old www.be.com site]
* [http://www.osnews.com/story.php?news_id=7265/ BeOS] Celebrating Ten Years
* [http://www.begroovy.com/ BeGroovy] A blog dedicated to all things BeOS &lt;!-- Linked here, because BeGroovy has the biggest archive of BeOS-related news --&gt;
* [http://www.reghardware.co.uk/2007/01/30/forgotten_tech_beos/ BeOS: The Mac OS X might-have-been], reghardware.co.uk
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9eMGbDJmgv0 YouTube videos] A brief overview of BeOS's features
* [http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/beosprog/book/ Programming the Be Operating System]&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; An O'Reilly Open Book (out of print)
* [http://osvirtual.net/en/beos-5-max-edition/ BeOS 5 Max Edition (OSvirtual)]&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; BeOS 5 Max Edition, installed in VMWare virtual machine
* {{US trademark|78558039}} (BeOS)

{{BeOS}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Beos}}
[[Category:BeOS]]
[[Category:Discontinued operating systems]]
[[Category:X86 operating systems]]

[[ar:بي أو إس]]
[[ca:BeOS]]
[[cs:BeOS]]
[[de:BeOS]]
[[es:BeOS]]
[[eo:BeOS]]
[[fr:BeOS]]
[[ko:BeOS]]
[[ilo:BeOS]]
[[ia:BeOS]]
[[is:BeOS]]
[[it:BeOS]]
[[lt:BeOS]]
[[hu:BeOS]]
[[ms:BeOS]]
[[nl:BeOS]]
[[ja:BeOS]]
[[no:BeOS]]
[[pl:BeOS]]
[[pt:BeOS]]
[[ro:BeOS]]
[[ru:BeOS]]
[[sk:BeOS]]
[[fi:BeOS]]
[[sv:BeOS]]
[[tr:BeOS]]
[[uk:BeOS]]
[[zh:BeOS]]
[[hy:BeOS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
