<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="48189" ns="0" title="Surrey"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{About|the county of England}}
{{Distinguish|Surry (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox England county
 | name = Surrey
 | image = [[File:Surreyflag.gif|150px]]
 | motto =Making Surrey a better place
 | map = [[File:Surrey UK locator map 2010.svg|200px|Surrey within England]] 
 | status = [[Ceremonial counties of England|Ceremonial]] &amp; [[Metropolitan and non-metropolitan counties of England|Non-metropolitan]] county
 | origin = [[Ancient counties of England|Historic]]
 | region = [[South East England]]
 | arearank = [[List of Ceremonial counties of England by Area|Ranked 35th]]
 | area_km2 = 1663
 | adminarearank = [[List of Administrative shire counties of England by Area|Ranked 25th]]
 | adminhq = [[Kingston upon Thames|Kingston]]&lt;br /&gt;(extraterritorially)
 | iso = GB-SRY
 | ons = 43
 | nuts3 = UKJ23
 | poprank = [[List of ceremonial counties of England by population|Ranked {{English cerem counties|RNK=Surrey}}]]
 | popestdate = {{English statistics year}}
 | pop = {{English cerem counties|POP=Surrey}}
 | density_km2 = {{English cerem counties|DEN=Surrey}}
 | adminpoprank = [[List of non-metropolitan counties of England by population|Ranked {{English admin counties|RNK=Surrey}}]]
 | ethnicity = 95.0% White&lt;br /&gt;2.2% S. Asian
 | council = [[File:SurreyCC.png|150px]]&lt;br /&gt;http://www.surreycc.gov.uk/
 | exec = {{English county control|CTY=Surrey}}
 | mps = *[[Sam Gyimah]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Paul Beresford]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Crispin Blunt]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Jeremy Hunt (politician)|Jeremy Hunt]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Anne Milton]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Chris Grayling]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Philip Hammond]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Michael Gove]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Jonathan Lord]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Dominic Raab]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
* [[Kwasi Kwarteng]] [[Conservative Party (UK)|(C)]]
 | subdivmap = [[File:SurreyNumbered.png]]
 | subdivs = #[[Spelthorne]]   
#[[Runnymede (district)|Runnymede]]
#[[Surrey Heath]]
#[[Woking (borough)|Woking]]
#[[Elmbridge]]
#[[Guildford (borough)|Guildford]]
#[[Waverley, Surrey|Waverley]]
#[[Mole Valley]]
#[[Epsom and Ewell]]
#[[Reigate and Banstead]]
#[[Tandridge (district)|Tandridge]]
}}

'''Surrey ''' {{IPAc-en|ˈ|s|ʌr|i}} is a [[counties of England|county]] in the [[South East England|South East]] of [[England]] and is one of the [[Home Counties]]. The county borders [[Greater London]], [[Kent]], [[East Sussex]], [[West Sussex]], [[Hampshire]] and [[Berkshire]].  The historic [[county town]] is [[Guildford]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.guildford.gov.uk/guildfordweb/leisure/guildfordmuseum/guildfordsites/historynotes/medieval+guildford.htm | publisher=Guildford Borough Council |title=Medieval Guildford—''&quot;Henry III confirmed Guildford's status as the county town of Surrey in 1257&quot;'' | accessdate=12 February 2007}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Surrey County Council]] sits at [[Kingston upon Thames]], although this has been part of [[Greater London]] since 1965. The London boroughs of Lambeth, Wandsworth and Southwark were considered part of Surrey until 1889; and Croydon, Kingston, Merton, Sutton, Barnes and Richmond - all now reclassified as part of Greater London - were part of Surrey until 1965.
 
Surrey is divided into 11 [[borough]]s and districts: [[Elmbridge]], [[Epsom and Ewell]], [[Guildford (borough)|Guildford]], [[Mole Valley]], [[Reigate and Banstead]], [[Runnymede (district)|Runnymede]], [[Spelthorne]], [[Surrey Heath]], [[Tandridge (district)|Tandridge]], [[Waverley, Surrey|Waverley]], [[Woking_(borough)|Woking]]. After the elections of 1 May 2008, the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservatives]] are in control of 10 out of 11 councils in Surrey, with Epsom and Ewell in [[Epsom and Ewell Residents Association|Residents Association]] control. The Conservatives hold all [[List of Parliamentary constituencies in Surrey|11 Parliamentary constituencies]] within the county borders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/election2010/results/region/8.stm | work=BBC News | title=BBC NEWS – Election 2010 – South East}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Geography ==
[[File:Boxhill surrey viewfromtop.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Box Hill, Surrey|Box Hill]]]]

Surrey is divided in two by the chalk ridge of the [[North Downs]], running east-west. The ridge is pierced by Surrey's principal rivers, the [[River Wey|Wey]] and the [[River Mole|Mole]], which are tributaries of the [[River Thames|Thames]], the river which constituted the northern border of the county before modern local government reorganisations. To the north of the Downs the land is mostly flat, forming part of the basin of the Thames. The geology of this area is dominated by [[London Clay]] in the east, [[Bagshot Formation|Bagshot Sands]] in the west and [[alluvium|alluvial]] deposits along the rivers. To the south of the Downs in the western part of the county are the sandstone [[Surrey Hills AONB|Surrey Hills]], while further east is the plain of the Low [[Weald]], rising in the extreme south-east to the edge of the hills of the High Weald. The Downs and the area to the south form part of a concentric pattern of geological deposits which also extends across southern Kent and most of Sussex, predominantly composed of [[Wealden Group|Wealden Clay]], [[Lower Greensand]] and the chalk of the Downs. 

Much of Surrey is in the [[Metropolitan Green Belt]]. It contains a good deal of mature [[woodland]] (reflected in the official logo of Surrey County Council, a pair of interlocking oak leaves). Among its many notable beauty spots are [[Box Hill, England|Box Hill]], [[Leith Hill]], [[Frensham Ponds]], [[Newlands Corner]] and [[Puttenham &amp; Crooksbury Commons]]. Surrey is the most wooded county in England, with 22.4% coverage compared to a national average of 11.8%&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.surreycc.gov.uk/sccwebsite/sccwspages.nsf/LookupWebPagesByTITLE_RTF/Surrey's+woodlands?opendocument |title=Surrey's woodlands |publisher=Surrey County Council |accessdate=16 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as such is one of the few counties not to include new woodlands in their strategic plans. Box Hill has the oldest untouched area of natural woodland in the UK, one of the oldest in Europe. Surrey also contains England's principal concentration of lowland [[Heath (habitat)|heath]], on sandy soils in the west of the county.

[[File:Leith hill tower.JPG|thumb|200px|left|[[Leith Hill]] Tower]]
Agriculture not being intensive, there are many [[Common land|commons]] and access lands, together with an extensive network of [[Rights of way in England and Wales|footpaths and bridleways]] including the [[North Downs Way]], a scenic [[long-distance path]]. Accordingly, Surrey provides much in the way of rural leisure activities, with a very large horse population.
    
The highest elevation in Surrey is [[Leith Hill]] near [[Dorking]]. It is either 293,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infobritain.co.uk/Leith_Hill.htm |title=Leith Hill |publisher=Infobritain.co.uk |accessdate=27 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  294&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/local/surrey/hi/people_and_places/newsid_8387000/8387218.stm |work=BBC News  | title=See for miles from Surrey's hills | date=1 December 2009 | accessdate=24 May 2010 | first=Heather | last=Driscoll-Woodford}}&lt;/ref&gt; or 295&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bubl.ac.uk/org/tacit/marilyns/chapter4.htm |title=The Relative Hills of Britain – Chapter 4: The Marilyns by Height |publisher=Bubl.ac.uk |accessdate=27 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; metres (961, 965 or 968&amp;nbsp;ft) above sea level and is the second highest point in southeastern England after [[Walbury Hill]] {{convert|297|m|ft}} in [[West Berkshire]].

== Settlements ==
:''See also [[list of places in Surrey]].''
Surrey has a population of approximately 1.1&amp;nbsp;million people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.surreycc.gov.uk/sccwebsite/sccwspages.nsf/LookupWebPagesByTITLE_RTF/2008+mid-year+estimates+of+population?opendocument |publisher=Surrey City Council |title=2008 mid-year estimates of population |accessdate=15 January 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its largest town is [[Guildford]], with a population of 66,773; [[Woking]] comes a close second with 62,796. They are followed by [[Ewell]] with 39,994 people and [[Camberley]] with 30,155. Towns of between 25,000 and 30,000 inhabitants are [[Ashford, Surrey|Ashford]], [[Epsom]], [[Farnham]], [[Staines]] and [[Redhill, Surrey|Redhill]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.surreycc.gov.uk/sccwebsite/sccwspublications.nsf/591f7dda55aad72a80256c670041a50d/1c602ea59c869c9180256e600054b26c/$FILE/Town%20populations.pdf |publisher=Surrey County Council |title=2001 Census: Town/villages in Surrey with population more than 1000 |format=PDF |accessdate=16 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Guildford is the historic [[county town]], although the county administration was moved to [[Newington, London|Newington]] in 1791 and to [[Kingston upon Thames]] in 1893. The county council's headquarters have been outside the county's boundaries since 1 April 1965 when Kingston and other areas were included within [[Greater London]] by the [[London Government Act 1963]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.visionofbritain.org.uk/relationships.jsp?u_id=10152902 |publisher=Vision of Britain |title=Relationships / unit history of Surrey |accessdate=16 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent plans to move the offices to a new site in Woking have now been abandoned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.surreycc.gov.uk/comm/Press.nsf/0/ac12227d5a45aa6f802570fa00449921?OpenDocument Surrey County Council press release 17 January 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;  Due to its proximity to London there are many [[commuter town]]s and villages in Surrey, the population density is high and the area is one of the richest parts of the UK. Surrey is Britain's most densely populated county, excluding Greater London, the [[Metropolitan county|metropolitan counties]] and [[Bristol]]. Much of the north east of the county is an urban area contiguous to [[Greater London]]. In the west, there is a [[conurbation]] straddling the Hampshire/Surrey border, including in Surrey [[Camberley]] and [[Farnham]].

== History ==
=== British and Roman Surrey ===
[[File:Stane Street.JPG|left|thumb|The Roman [[Stane Street (Chichester)|Stane or Stone Street]] runs through Surrey]]
Before Roman times the area today known as Surrey was very probably occupied by the [[Atrebates]] tribe centred at [[Calleva Atrebatum]] in the modern county of [[Hampshire]]. They are known to have controlled the southern bank of the [[Thames]] from Roman texts describing the tribal relations between them and the powerful [[Catuvellauni]] on the north bank. In about 42AD King [[Cunobelinus]] (''[[Welsh Language|Welsh]]'': [[Cunobelin|Cynfelin ap Tegfan]]) of the Catuvellauni died and war broke out between his sons and King [[Verica]] of the Atrebates. The Atrebates were defeated in the conflict, their capital captured and their lands made subject to the Catuvellauni now led by [[Togodumnus]] ruling from [[Camulodunum]]. Verica fled to [[Gaul]] and appealed for Roman aid. The Atrebates were allies with Rome during their invasion of Britain in 43AD. The area of Surrey was traversed by [[Stane Street (Chichester)|Stane Street]] and other less well known Roman roads. There were Roman temples on [[Farley Green|Farley Heath]] and near [[Wanborough, Surrey|Wanborough]].

=== The Saxon tribes and the sub-kingdom ===
During the 5th and 6th centuries Surrey was conquered and settled by [[Saxons]]. The names of a number of Saxon tribes who may have inhabited different parts of Surrey in this period have been conjectured on the basis of place names. These include the ''Godhelmingas'' (around [[Godalming (hundred)|Godalming]]), ''Tetingas'' (around [[Tooting]]) and ''Woccingas'' (between [[Woking]] and [[Wokingham]] in Berkshire). It has also been speculated that the ''Nox gaga'' and the ''Oht gaga'' tribes listed in the Mercian [[Tribal Hidage]] refer to two distinct groups living in Surrey. They were valued together at 7,000 [[hide (unit)|hides]]. Surrey may have formed part of a larger [[Middlesex|Middle Saxon]] kingdom or confederacy also including areas north of the Thames. The name Surrey is derived from ''Suthrige'', meaning &quot;southern region&quot;, and this may originate in its status as the southern half of the Middle Saxon territory.

If it ever existed, the Middle Saxon kingdom had disappeared by the 7th century, and Surrey became a frontier area disputed between the kingdoms of [[Kingdom of Kent|Kent]], [[Kingdom of Essex|Essex]], [[Kingdom of Sussex|Sussex]], [[Wessex]] and [[Mercia]], until its permanent absorption by Wessex in 825. Despite this fluctuating situation it retained its identity as a coherent territorial unit. During the 7th century Surrey became Christian and initially formed part of the East Saxon [[diocese of London]], indicating that it was under East Saxon rule at that time, but was later transferred to the West Saxon [[diocese of Winchester]]. Its most important religious institution throughout the [[Anglo-Saxon]] period and beyond was [[Chertsey Abbey]], founded in 666. At this point Surrey was evidently under Kentish domination, as the abbey was founded under the patronage of [[Ecgberht of Kent|King Ecgberht]] of Kent. However, a few years later at least part of it was subject to Mercia, since in 673-5 further lands were given to Chertsey Abbey by [[Frithuwald of Surrey|Frithuwald]], a local sub-king (''subregulus'') ruling under the sovereignty of [[Wulfhere of Mercia|Wulfhere]] of Mercia. A decade later Surrey passed into the hands of [[Caedwalla|King Caedwalla]] of Wessex, who also conquered Kent and Sussex and founded a monastery at [[Farnham]] in 686, and it remained under the control of Caedwalla's successor [[Ine of Wessex|Ine]] in the early 8th century. Its political history for most of the 8th century is unclear, although it may have been under South Saxon control around 722, but by 784–5 it had passed into the hands of [[Offa of Mercia|King Offa]] of Mercia. Mercian rule continued until 825, when following his victory over the Mercians at the [[Battle of Ashdown]], [[Egbert of Wessex|King Egbert]] of Wessex seized control of Surrey, along with Sussex, Kent and Essex. It was incorporated into Wessex as a [[shire]] and continued thereafter under the rule of the West Saxon kings, who eventually became kings of all England.

'''Identified sub-kings of Surrey'''   
* [[Frithuwold of Surrey|Frithuwald]] (c.673 – 675)
* Frithuric? (675 – c.686)

=== The West Saxon and English shire ===
In the 9th century England was afflicted, along with the rest of north-western Europe, by the attacks of [[Scandinavians|Scandinavian]] [[Vikings]]. Surrey's inland position shielded it from coastal raiding, so that it was not normally troubled except by the largest and most ambitious Scandinavian armies. In 851 an exceptionally large invasion force of [[Danes]] arrived in the mouth of the Thames on a fleet of about 350 ships, which would have carried over 15,000 men. Having sacked [[Canterbury]] and London and defeated [[Beorhtwulf of Mercia|King Beorhtwulf]] of Mercia in battle, the Danes crossed the Thames into Surrey, but were slaughtered by a West Saxon army led by [[Aethelwulf of Wessex|King Aethelwulf]] in the [[Battle of Aclea]], bringing the invasion to an end. In 892 Surrey was the scene of another important battle when a large Danish army, variously reported at 200, 250 and 350 ship-loads, moved west from its encampment in Kent. It was intercepted and defeated at Farnham by an army led by [[Alfred the Great]]'s son [[Edward the Elder|Edward, the future King Edward the Elder]], and fled across the Thames towards Essex.

Its location and the growing power of the West Saxon, later English, kingdom kept Surrey safe from attack for over a century thereafter. [[Kingston upon Thames|Kingston]] was the scene for the coronation of [[Athelstan of England|Aethelstan]] in 924 and [[Aethelred the Unready]] in 978, and, according to later tradition, of other tenth century Kings of England as well. The renewed Danish attacks during the disastrous reign of Aethelred led to the devastation of Surrey by the army of [[Thorkell the Tall]], which ravaged all of south-eastern England in 1009–11. The climax of this wave of attacks came in 1016, which saw prolonged fighting between the forces of [[Edmund Ironside|King Edmund Ironside]] and the Danish king [[Cnut the Great|Cnut]], including an English victory over the Danes somewhere in north-eastern Surrey, but ended with the Danish conquest of England and the establishment of Cnut as king.

Cnut's death in 1035 was followed by a period of political uncertainty as the succession was disputed between his sons. In 1036 [[Alfred Aetheling|Alfred]], son of Aethelred the Unready, returned from Normandy, where he had been taken for safety as a child at the time of Cnut's conquest of England. It is uncertain what his intentions were, but after landing with a small retinue in Sussex he was met by [[Godwin, Earl of Wessex]], who escorted him in apparently friendly fashion to [[Guildford]]. Having taken lodgings there, Alfred's men were attacked as they slept and massacred by Godwin's followers, while the prince himself was blinded and imprisoned, dying shortly afterwards. This butchery must have contributed to the antipathy between Godwin and Alfred's brother [[Edward the Confessor]], who came to the throne in 1042. That hostility was of critical importance in bringing about the [[Norman Conquest]] of England in 1066.

[[Domesday Book]] records that the largest landowners in Surrey at the end of Edward's reign were Chertsey Abbey and [[Harold Godwinson]], Earl of Wessex and later king, followed by the estates of King Edward himself. Apart from the abbey, most of whose lands were within the shire, Surrey was the not the principal focus of any major landowner's holdings, a tendency which was to persist in later periods. Given the vast and widespread landed interests and the national and international preoccupations of the monarchy and the earldom of Wessex, the Abbot of Chertsey was therefore probably the most important figure in the local elite.

The Anglo-Saxon period saw the emergence of the shire's internal division into 14 [[hundred (division)|hundreds]], which continued until [[Victorian era|Victorian]] times. These were the hundreds of [[Blackheath, Surrey (hundred)|Blackheath]], [[Brixton (hundred)|Brixton]], [[Copthorne (hundred)|Copthorne]], [[Effingham (half hundred)|Effingham Half-Hundred]], [[Elmbridge (hundred)|Elmbridge]], [[Farnham (hundred)|Farnham]], [[Godalming (hundred)|Godalming]], [[Godley (hundred)|Godley]], [[Kingston (hundred)|Kingston]], [[Reigate (hundred)|Reigate]], [[Tandridge (hundred)|Tandridge]], [[Wallington (hundred)|Wallington]], [[Woking (hundred)|Woking]] and [[Wotton (hundred)|Wotton]].

'''Identified ''[[ealdorman|ealdormen]]'' of Surrey'''

* Wulfheard (c.823)
* Huda (? – 853)
* Æðelweard (late 10th century)
* Æðelmær (? – 1016)

=== Later Medieval Surrey ===

After the [[Battle of Hastings]], the [[Norman people|Norman]] army advanced through Kent into Surrey, where they defeated an English force which attacked them at [[Southwark]], before proceeding westwards on a circuitous march to reach London from the north-west. As was the case across England, the native ruling class of Surrey was virtually eliminated by Norman seizure of land. Only one significant English landowner, the brother of the last English Abbot of Chertsey, remained by the time the Domesday survey was conducted in 1086. At that time the largest landholding in Surrey, as in many other parts of the country, was the expanded royal estate, while the next largest holding belonged to [[Richard fitz Gilbert]], founder of the [[de Clare]] family.

[[File:Runnymede-meadow-eghamend.jpg|200px|left|thumb|[[Runnymede]], where the [[Magna Carta]] was sealed]]
In 1088, [[William II of England|King William II]] granted [[William de Warenne, 1st Earl of Surrey|William de Warenne]] the title of [[Earl of Surrey]] as a reward for Warenne's loyalty during the [[Rebellion of 1088|rebellion that followed the death of William I]]. When the male line of the Warennes became extinct in the 14th century the earldom was inherited by the [[Fitzalan]] [[Earls of Arundel]]. The Fitzalan line of Earls of Surrey became extinct in 1415 but the title was revived in the late 15th century for the [[House of Howard|Howard family]] who still hold it. However, Surrey was not the principal focus of any of these families' interests.

[[Image:Guildford castle 1.jpg|250px|thumb|[[Guildford Castle]]]]
[[Guildford Castle]], one of many fortresses originally established by the Normans as part of the process of subjugating the country, was developed as a royal palace in the 12th century. [[Farnham Castle]] was built during the 12th century as a residence for the [[Bishop of Winchester]], while other stone castles were constructed in the same period at [[Bletchingley Castle|Bletchingley]] by the de Clares and at [[Reigate Castle|Reigate]] by the Warennes. During [[John of England|King John]]'s [[First Barons' War|struggle with the barons]], [[Magna Carta]] was issued in June 1215 at [[Runnymede]]. In the following year Surrey was overrun by forces supporting [[Louis VIII of France|Prince Louis]] of France, who passed through on their way from London to [[Winchester]] and back and occupied Guildford and Reigate castles. Guildford Castle later became one of the favourite residences of [[Henry III of England|King Henry III]], who considerably expanded the palace there. In 1264, during the [[Second Barons' War|baronial revolt]] against Henry III, the rebel army of [[Simon de Montfort, 6th Earl of Leicester|Simon de Montfort]] passed southwards through Surrey on their way to the [[Battle of Lewes]] in Sussex. Although the rebels were victorious, soon after the battle royal forces captured and destroyed Bletchingley Castle, whose owner [[Gilbert de Clare, 7th Earl of Gloucester|Gilbert de Clare]] was one of de Montfort's leading supporters. By the 14th century castles were of dwindling military importance, but continued to be a mark of social prestige, leading to the construction of castles at [[Betchworth Castle|Betchworth]] by [[John de Cobham, 2nd Baron Cobham|Lord Cobham]] and at [[Starborough Castle|Starborough]] near [[Lingfield, Surrey|Lingfield]] by [[John Fitzalan, 1st Baron Arundel|John Fitzalan]], whose father had recently inherited the Earldom of Surrey.

Surrey had little political or economic importance in the Middle Ages. It was not the main power-base of any major aristocratic family or the seat of a bishopric, while its agricultural wealth was limited by its generally poor soils. Population pressure in the 12th and 13th centuries led to the beginning of the gradual deforestation and agricultural development of the Weald, an area which had hitherto remained wooded due to the exceptional difficulty of farming its heavy clay soil. Urban development, excepting the London suburb of Southwark, was sapped by the overshadowing predominance of London and the major towns in neighbouring shires, many of which benefited from access to the sea or from political or ecclesiastical eminence. Surrey did however achieve a significant degree of prosperity in the later Middle Ages through its role in the production of woollen cloth, England's main export industry, which in Surrey was centred on Guildford.

[[Image:waverleywindows.jpg|250px|thumb|left|Ruins of the monks' dormitory at [[Waverley Abbey]]]]
One benefit of obscurity was that Surrey largely avoided being seriously fought over in the various rebellions and civil wars of the period, although armies from Kent heading for London passed through what was then north-eastern Surrey during the [[Peasants' Revolt]] of 1381, [[Jack Cade|Cade's Rebellion]] in 1450 and one stage of the [[Wars of the Roses]] in 1460.

In 1082 a [[Cluniac]] abbey was founded at [[Bermondsey Abbey|Bermondsey]] by Alwine, a wealthy English citizen of London. The first [[Cistercian]] monastery in England, [[Waverley Abbey]], was founded in 1128. Over the next quarter-century monks spread out from here to found new houses, creating a network of twelve monasteries descended from Waverley across southern and central England. The 12th and early 13th centuries also saw the establishment of [[Augustinian Order|Augustinian]] priories at [[Merton Priory|Merton]], [[Newark Priory|Newark]], [[Tandridge Priory|Tandridge]], [[Southwark Cathedral|Southwark]] and Reigate. A [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] friary was established at [[Guildford Black Friary|Guildford]] by Henry III's widow [[Eleanor of Provence]], in memory of her grandson who had died at Guildford in 1274. In the 15th century a [[Carthusian]] priory was founded by [[Henry V of England|King Henry V]] at [[Sheen Priory|Sheen]]. These would all perish, along with the still important [[Benedictine]] abbey of [[Chertsey Abbey|Chertsey]], in the 16th-century [[Dissolution of the Monasteries]].

Although now fallen into disuse, some English counties had nicknames for people from that county, such as a [[Yorkshire|Tyke]] from [[Yorkshire]] and a [[Yellowbelly (Lincolnshire)|Yellowbelly]] from [[Lincolnshire]]; the traditional nickname for people from Surrey is 'Surrey Capon', as it was well known in the later Middle Ages as the county where chickens were fattened up for the London meat markets.

=== Early Modern Surrey ===

[[Image:Woodcut of Nonsuch Palace.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Nonsuch Palace]]]]
Under the early [[Tudor dynasty|Tudor]] kings magnificent royal palaces were constructed in northern Surrey, in convenient proximity to London. At [[Richmond Palace|Richmond]] an existing royal residence was rebuilt on a grand scale under [[Henry VII of England|King Henry VII]], who also founded a [[Franciscan]] [[Sheen Friary|friary]] nearby in 1499. The still more spectacular palace of [[Nonsuch Palace|Nonsuch]] was later built for [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] near [[Ewell]]. The palace at Guildford Castle had fallen out of use long before, but a royal hunting lodge existed just outside the town. All these have since been demolished.

During the [[Cornish Rebellion of 1497]] the rebels heading for London briefly occupied Guildford and fought a skirmish with a government detachment on Guildown outside the town, before marching on to [[Blackheath, London|Blackheath]] in Kent where they were crushed by a royal army. The forces of [[Wyatt's Rebellion]] in 1554 passed through what was then north-eastern Surrey on their way from Kent to London, briefly occupying Southwark and then crossing the Thames at Kingston after failing to storm London Bridge.

Surrey's cloth industry declined in the 16th century, and effectively collapsed in the 17th. The introduction of new furnace technology in the early 17th century led to an expansion of the iron industry in the Weald, whose rich deposits had been exploited since prehistoric times, but this hastened the extinction of the business as the mines were worked out. However, this period also saw the emergence of important new industries, centred on the valley of the [[River Tillingbourne|Tillingbourne]]. The production of brass goods and wire in this area was relatively short-lived, but the manufacture of paper and gunpowder proved more enduring. For a time in the mid-17th century the Surrey mills were the main producers of gunpowder in England. The [[Wey and Godalming Navigations|Wey Navigation]], opened in 1653, was one of England's first canal systems.

[[George Abbot (bishop)|George Abbot]], the son of a Guildford clothworker, served as [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] in 1611–33. In 1619 he founded [[Abbot's Hospital]], an [[almshouse]] in Guildford, which is still operating. He also made unsuccessful efforts to revitalise the ailing local cloth industry. One of his brothers, [[Robert Abbot (bishop)|Robert]], became [[Bishop of Salisbury]] and another, [[Maurice Abbot|Maurice]], was a founding shareholder of the [[East India Company]] who became the company's governor and later [[Lord Mayor of London]].

[[Image:George Abbot from NPG cropped.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[George Abbot (bishop)|George Abbot]]]]
[[Bankside]] in Southwark, then part of Surrey, was the principal entertainment district of early modern London. This was due to its convenient location outside the jurisdiction of the government of the [[City of London]], since the social control exercised over this London suburb by the local authorities of Surrey was less effectively restrictive. As a result this was where the city's theatres were located and was the setting for the golden age of [[English Renaissance theatre|Elizabethan and Jacobean theatre]], with the work of playwrights including [[William Shakespeare]], [[Christopher Marlowe]], [[Ben Jonson]] and [[John Webster]] being performed in playhouses along the south bank of the Thames.

Surrey almost entirely escaped the direct impact of fighting during the [[First English Civil War|main phase]] of the [[English Civil War]] in 1642-6. The local [[Roundhead|Parliamentarian]] gentry led by [[Richard Onslow (Parliamentarian)|Sir Richard Onslow]] were able to secure the county without difficulty on the outbreak of war. Farnham Castle was briefly occupied by the advancing [[Cavaliers|Royalists]] in late 1642, but was easily stormed by the Parliamentarians under Sir [[William Waller]]. A new Royalist offensive in late 1643 saw skirmishing around Farnham between Waller's forces and [[Ralph Hopton]]'s Royalists, but these brief incursions into the western fringes of Surrey marked the limits of Royalist advances on the county. During a political crisis in summer 1647 [[Sir Thomas Fairfax]]'s army passed through Surrey on its way to occupy London, and subsequent billeting of troops in Surrey caused considerable discontent. In the brief [[Second English Civil War|Second Civil War]] of 1648 the [[Henry Rich, 1st Earl of Holland|Earl of Holland]] entered Surrey in July hoping to ignite a Royalist revolt. He raised his standard at Kingston and advanced south, but found little support. After confused manoeuvres between Reigate and [[Dorking]] as Parliamentary troops closed in, his force of 500 men fled northwards and was overtaken and routed at Kingston.

Surrey had a prominent role in the development of the radical political movements unleashed by the civil war. In October 1647 the first manifesto of what became known as the [[Leveller]] movement, ''[[The Case of the Army Truly Stated]]'', was drafted at Guildford by the elected representatives of [[New Model Army]] regiments and civilian radicals from London. This document combined the presentation of specific grievances with wider demands for constitutional change on the basis of [[popular sovereignty]]. It formed the template for the more systematic and radical ''[[Agreement of the People]]'', drafted by the same men later that month, and led to the [[Putney Debates]] between its signatories and the army leadership. In 1649 the [[Diggers]] led by [[Gerrard Winstanley]] established their communal settlement at [[St. George's Hill]] to implement egalitarian ideals of common ownership, but were eventually driven out by the local landowners through violence and litigation. A smaller Digger commune was then established near [[Cobham, Surrey|Cobham]], but suffered the same fate in 1650.

=== Modern history ===

Until the late 18th century Surrey, apart from its north-eastern corner, was sparsely populated and somewhat rustic, despite its proximity to the capital. Communications began to improve, and the influence of London to increase, with the development of [[Turnpike trust|turnpike]] roads and a [[stagecoach]] system. A far more profound transformation followed with the arrival of the railways, beginning in the late 1830s. The availability of rapid transportation enabled prosperous London workers to travel daily to homes across Surrey. This phenomenon of commuting brought explosive growth to Surrey's population and wealth, and tied its economy and society inextricably to London. Existing towns like Guildford, Farnham and most spectacularly [[Croydon]] grew rapidly, while new towns such as Woking and [[Redhill, Surrey|Redhill]] emerged beside the railway lines.

[[Image:Woking Crematorium - geograph.org.uk - 161645.jpg|thumb|left|Britain's first crematorium, in [[Woking]]]]
Meanwhile London itself spread swiftly across north-eastern Surrey. In 1800 it extended only to [[Vauxhall]]; a century later the city's growth had reached as far as [[Putney]] and [[Streatham]]. This expansion was reflected in the creation of the [[County of London]] in 1889, detaching the areas subsumed by the city from Surrey. The expansion of London continued in the 20th century, engulfing Croydon, Kingston and many smaller settlements. This led to a further contraction of Surrey in 1965 with the creation of [[Greater London]].

[[Image:Guildford Cathedral.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Guildford Cathedral]]]]
In 1849 [[Brookwood Cemetery]] was established near Woking to serve the population of London, connected to the capital by [[London Necropolis Railway|its own railway service]]. It soon developed into the largest burial ground in the world. Woking was also the site of Britain's [[Woking Crematorium|first crematorium]], which opened in 1878, and its [[Shah Jahan Mosque|first mosque]], founded in 1889. In 1881 Godalming became the first town in the world with a public electricity supply.

The eastern part of Surrey was transferred from the [[Diocese of Winchester]] to that of [[Diocese of Rochester|Rochester]] in 1877. In 1905 this area was detached to form a new [[Anglican Diocese of Southwark|Diocese of Southwark]]. The rest of the county, together with part of eastern Hampshire, was separated from Winchester in 1927 to become the [[Diocese of Guildford]], whose [[Guildford Cathedral|cathedral]] was consecrated in 1961.

During the later 19th century Surrey became increasingly important in the development of architecture in Britain and the wider world. Its traditional building forms were significant in shaping the widespread trend for English [[vernacular architecture]] associated with the [[Arts and Crafts Movement]], and would continue to influence domestic building through the 20th century. The prominence of Surrey peaked in the 1890s, when it was the focus for globally important developments in domestic architecture, in particular the early work of [[Edwin Lutyens]], who grew up in the county and was greatly influenced by its traditional styles and materials.

[[Image:DennisSabre.JPG|thumb|left|Dennis Sabre fire engine]]
The late 19th and early 20th centuries saw the demise of Surrey's long-standing industries manufacturing paper and gunpowder. Most of the county's paper mills closed around the turn of the century and the last survivor shut in 1928. Gunpowder production fell victim to the [[First World War]], which brought about a huge expansion of the British munitions industry, followed by sharp contraction and consolidation when the war ended, leading to the closure of the Surrey powder mills. New industrial developments included the establishment of the vehicle manufacturers [[Dennis Specialist Vehicles|Dennis Brothers]] in Guildford in 1895. Beginning as a maker of bicycles and then of cars, the firm soon shifted into the production of commercial and utility vehicles, becoming internationally important as a manufacturer of fire engines and buses. Though much reduced in size and despite numerous changes of ownership, this business continues to operate in Guildford.

During the [[Second World War]] a section of the [[GHQ Line|GHQ Stop Line]], a system of [[Bunker#Pillbox|pillboxes]], gun emplacements, anti-tank obstacles and other fortifications was constructed along the North Downs. This line, running from [[Somerset]] to [[Yorkshire]], was intended as the principal fixed defence of London and the industrial core of England against the threat of invasion. German invasion plans envisaged that the main thrust of their advance inland would cross the North Downs at the gap in the ridge formed by the Wey valley, thus colliding with the defence line around Guildford.

== Historic architecture and monuments ==

[[Image:Abbotshospital.jpg|thumb|The gate of [[Abbot's Hospital]], Guildford]]
Few traces of the ancient British and Roman periods survive in Surrey. There are a number of [[round barrow]]s and [[bell barrow]]s in various locations, mostly dating to the [[Bronze Age]]. Remains of [[Iron Age]] [[hillfort]]s exist at [[Holmbury Hill]], [[Hascombe Hill]], [[Anstiebury hillfort|Anstiebury]] (near [[Capel, Surrey|Capel]]), [[Dry Hill (Surrey)|Dry Hill]] (near [[Lingfield, Surrey|Lingfield]]), [[St. Ann's Hill, Chertsey]] and [[St George's Hill]], [[Weybridge]]. Most of these sites were created in the 1st century BC and many were re-occupied during the middle of the 1st century AD.&lt;ref&gt;Dyer, James. ''Penguin Guide to Prehistoric England &amp; Wales'', pp. 235–239.&lt;/ref&gt; Only fragments of [[Stane Street (Chichester)|Stane Street]] and [[Ermine Street]], the [[Roman roads]] which crossed the county, remain.

Anglo-Saxon elements survive in a number of Surrey churches, notably at Guildford ([[St. Mary's Church, Guildford|St. Mary's]]), [[Godalming]] ([[Church of St. Peter &amp; St. Paul, Godalming|St. Peter &amp; St. Paul]]), [[Stoke D'Abernon]], [[Thursley]], [[Witley]], [[Compton, Guildford|Compton]] and [[Albury, Surrey|Albury]] (old church).

Numerous medieval churches exist in Surrey, but the county's parish churches are typically relatively small and simple, and have suffered particularly heavily at the hands of [[Victorian restoration]]. Important medieval church interiors are to be found at Stoke D'Abernon, Compton, [[Chaldon]], [[Dunsfold]] and [[Lingfield, Surrey|Lingfield]]. The larger monastic churches fell into ruin after their institutions were dissolved, although some remains of those at Waverley and Newark still exist, while Southwark Priory, no longer in Surrey, has survived intact as a cathedral. Farnham Castle survives in large part and substantial ruins remain at Guildford Castle, while a handful of medieval domestic buildings survive, albeit with considerable later modifications.

The 16th century is the earliest from which a sizeable amount of non-military secular architecture survives in Surrey. Important examples include the grand mid-century country houses of [[Loseley Park]] and [[Sutton Place, Surrey|Sutton Place]] and the old building of the [[Royal Grammar School, Guildford]], founded in 1509. A considerable number of more ordinary houses and commercial buildings of the 16th century are also still standing, and with the 17th century the number of surviving buildings proliferates much further. [[Abbot's Hospital]], founded in 1619, is a grand edifice built in the [[Tudor architecture|Tudor style]], despite its date. More characteristic examples of major 17th-century building include [[West Horsley Place]], [[Slyfield Manor]] and the guildhall in Guildford, as well as [[Ham House]] and [[Kew Palace]], formerly in Surrey but now in Greater London.

== Literature ==

Besides its role in [[English Renaissance theatre|Elizabethan and Jacobean theatre]], many important writers have lived and worked in Surrey.

* [[The Owl and the Nightingale]], one of the earliest [[Middle English]] poems, may have been written by one Nicholas of Guildford, who is mentioned in its text.
* [[John Donne]] (1572–1631) lived and worked for much of his life in [[Pyrford]].
* [[John Evelyn]] (1620–1706) was born at [[Wotton, Surrey|Wotton]] and spent much of his life there.
* [[Daniel Defoe]] (1659/61-1731) was educated in Dorking.
* [[William Cobbett]] (1763–1835) was born in Farnham and is buried there; Surrey features prominently in his ''[[Rural Rides]]''.
* [[Benjamin Disraeli]] (1804–81) wrote ''[[Conningsby]]'' while living in Dorking.
* [[Alfred Tennyson, 1st Baron Tennyson|Alfred Tennyson]] (1809–92) spent the latter part of his life, and died, in [[Haslemere]].
* [[Charles Dickens]] (1812–70) wrote part of ''[[The Pickwick Papers]]'' in Dorking, and refers to the town in the novel.
* [[Robert Browning]] (1812–89) was born in [[Camberwell]], then part of Surrey.
* [[George Eliot]] (1819–80) wrote most of ''[[Middlemarch]]'' while living in Haslemere.
* [[George Meredith]] (1828–1909) lived at Box Hill.
* [[Lewis Carroll]] (1832–98) died and is buried in Guildford, where he had spent much time at his sisters' home.
* [[George Bernard Shaw]] (1856–1950) lived in Woking and later in [[Hindhead]], where he wrote ''[[Caesar and Cleopatra (play)|Caesar and Cleopatra]]''.
* [[Arthur Conan Doyle]] (1859–1930) lived and wrote many of his books in Hindhead and served as [[deputy lieutenant]] of Surrey; the county forms a setting for many of the [[Sherlock Holmes]] stories.
* [[J.M. Barrie]] (1860–1937) lived in [[Tilford]], and based ''[[The Boy Castaways]]'', which later evolved into ''[[Peter Pan]]'', in the nearby countryside.
* [[H.G. Wells]] (1866–1946) wrote ''[[The War of the Worlds]]'' while living in Woking; much of northern Surrey is laid waste in the course of the story.
* [[John Galsworthy]] (1867–1933) was born in Kingston and the ''[[Forsyte Saga]]'' is set in the area.
* [[E.M. Forster]] (1879–1970) lived and wrote in Weybridge.
* [[P.G. Wodehouse]] (1881–1975) was born in Guildford and baptised there in [[St. Nicolas' Church, Guildford|St. Nicolas's church]].
* [[Aldous Huxley]] (1894–1963) was born in Godalming and his remains are interred at Compton; the end of ''[[Brave New World]]'' is set in Surrey.

== Arts and sciences ==

* [[William of Ockham]] (c.1288-c.1348), [[scholasticism|scholastic]] philosopher, most famous for &quot;[[Occam's Razor]]&quot;, came from [[Ockham, Surrey|Ockham]].
* [[Thomas Malthus]] (1766–1834), pioneer of [[demography]], was born and grew up in [[Westcott, Surrey|Westcott]], and later lived in Albury.
* [[Ada Lovelace]] (1815–52), mathematician, lived at [[East Horsley]].
* [[Gertrude Jekyll]] (1843–1932), garden designer, lived for much of her life at Munstead near Godalming, created significant gardens in Surrey and is buried in [[Busbridge]].
* [[Edwin Lutyens]] (1869–1944), architect, grew up in [[Thursley]] and many of his early works were built in west Surrey, including collaborations with Gertrude Jekyll.
* [[Ralph Vaughan Williams]] (1872–1958), composer, grew up at Leith Hill and later lived in Dorking.
* [[Laurence Olivier]] (1907–89), actor, was born in Dorking.
* [[Alan Turing]] (1912–54), mathematician and pioneer of [[computer science]], lived for much of his early life in Guildford.

== Popular music ==
The &quot;Surrey Delta&quot; produced many of the musicians in 60s British blues movements. The Rolling Stones developed their music at Crawdaddy Club in [[Richmond upon Thames|Richmond]].

* [[Jimmy Page]] (born 1944) spent much of his early life in [[Epsom]].
* [[Jeff Beck]] (born 1944) was born in [[Wallington, London|Wallington]], then part of Surrey.
* [[Eric Clapton]] (born 1945) was born and grew up in [[Ripley, Surrey|Ripley]].
* [[The Stranglers]] were formed in [[Guildford]].
* [[Paul Weller]] (born 1958) was born and grew up in Woking, which inspired the song ''[[Town Called Malice]]''. [[The Jam]] were formed at [[Sheerwater Secondary School]] in the town.
* [[Norman Cook]] (born 1963) was born in Surrey.
* [[Hard-Fi]] members [[Richard Archer]] , [[Ross Phillips]] , and [[Kai Stephens]] are from Staines, Surrey.
* [[Justin Hawkins]], lead singer of rock band [[The Darkness (band)|The Darkness]] was born in Surrey.
*[[Mike Rutherford]] guitarist of progressive rock band [[Genesis (band)|Genesis]].
*[[Peter Gabriel]], once lead songwriter of progressive rock band Genesis.

== Sport ==
Surrey was the scene for the earliest appearance in history of cricket being played, a reference to games at the [[Royal Grammar School, Guildford]] in the 16th century (see [[History of English cricket to 1696]]). [[Mitcham Cricket Club]], formed in 1685 and the oldest documented club in the game's history, was within Surrey's borders until 1965.&lt;ref&gt;Phil Shaw, [[The Independent]], 13 July 2003, [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20020713/ai_n12629473 ''Cricket: After 400 years, history is made next to the A323'']. Retrieved on 6 February 2007. Quote: &quot;Mitcham Green has been in continual use as a cricket venue for 317 years&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Surrey County Cricket Club]], founded in 1845, represents the [[Ancient counties of England|historic county]] of Surrey, although its main ground, [[The Oval]] in [[Kennington]], is now in [[Greater London]]. The club also uses [[Whitgift School]], [[South Croydon]] and [[Woodbridge Road]], [[Guildford]] for some games. It was one of the original participants in the [[County Championship]] and has won the competition 18 times, more than any other county except [[Yorkshire County Cricket Club|Yorkshire]].

[[Epsom Downs Racecourse]] is the venue for the most prestigious event in British flat horse-racing, the [[Epsom Derby|Derby]], which has been held there annually since 1780.

[[Brooklands]] near Woking was the world's first purpose-built [[motorsport]] race circuit, opened in 1907. Currently Woking plays host to the headquarters of the [[McLaren]] [[Formula One]] team, giving Surrey the rarity of having a local F1 team. [[James Hunt]], the 1976 Formula 1 World Driver's Champion was born in Belmont, then part of Surrey, in 1947.

Surrey's leading [[Rugby union|rugby]] club, [[Esher RFC|Esher]], currently compete in the [[RFU Championship]], the second tier of English rugby. The county has numerous football teams, but none in the [[Football League]].

Surrey is home to the [[Ice Hockey]] team the [[Guildford Flames]], who compete in the [[English Premier Ice Hockey League|English Premier League]] and the basketball team the [[Guildford Heat]], who play in the top tier of British basketball, the [[British Basketball League]].

== Local government ==
   {{infobox historic subdivision|
   |Name=              Surrey
   |HQ=                [[Newington, London|Newington]] 1889 – 1893&lt;br /&gt;[[Kingston upon Thames]] from 1893
   |Status=            [[Administrative county]]
   |Start=             c.825
   |End=               N/A
   |Replace=           N/A
   |Image=             
   |Civic=             [[File:Surrey arms 1934.png|150px|The arms granted to Surrey County Council in 1934 and used until 1974]]
   |PopulationFirst=     452,218&lt;ref&gt;Census of England and Wales 1891, General Report, Table III: Administrative counties and county boroughs&lt;/ref&gt;
   |PopulationFirstYear= 1891
   |PopulationLast=     1,002,832&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visionofbritain.org.uk/unit_page.jsp?u_id=10152902 ''Surrey'', Vision of Britain, accessed 17 October 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;
   |PopulationLastYear= 1971
   }}

The [[Local Government Act 1888]] reorganised county-level local government throughout England and Wales. Accordingly, the [[administrative county]] of Surrey was formed in 1889 when the Provisional Surrey County Council first met, consisting of 19 [[aldermen]] and 57 [[councillors]]. The county council assumed the administrative responsibilities previously exercised by the county's [[justice of the peace|justices]] in [[quarter sessions]]. The county had revised boundaries, with the north east of the historic county bordering the [[City of London]] becoming part of a new [[County of London]]. These areas now form the London Boroughs of [[London Borough of Lambeth|Lambeth]], [[London Borough of Southwark|Southwark]] and [[London Borough of Wandsworth|Wandsworth]], and the [[Penge Urban District|Penge]] area of the [[London Borough of Bromley]]. At the same time, the [[County Borough of Croydon|borough of Croydon]] became a [[county borough]], outside the jurisdiction of the county council.

For purposes other than local government the administrative county of Surrey and county borough of Croydon continued to form a &quot;county of Surrey&quot; to which a [[Lord Lieutenant]] and [[Custos Rotulorum of Surrey|Custos Rotulorum]] (Chief [[Magistrate]]) and a [[High Sheriff of Surrey|High Sheriff]] were appointed.  

Surrey had been administered from [[Newington, London|Newington]] since the 1790s, and the county council was initially based in the sessions house there. As Newington was included in the County of London it lay outside the area administered by the council, and a site for a new county hall within the administrative county was sought. By 1890 six towns were being considered: Epsom, Guildford, Kingston, Redhill, [[Surbiton]] and Wimbledon.&lt;ref&gt;''The Times'', 27 March 1890&lt;/ref&gt; A decision to build the new [[County Hall (Surrey)|County Hall]] at Kingston was made in 1891, (the building opened in 1893&lt;ref&gt;David Robinson, ''History of County Hall'', Surrey County Council&lt;/ref&gt;) but this site would also became overtaken by the growing London conurbation and by the 1930s most of the north of the county had been built over, becoming [[Outer London|outer suburbs of London]], although continuing to form part of Surrey administratively. 

In 1960 the report of the [[Royal Commission on Local Government in Greater London|Herbert Commission]] recommended that much of north Surrey (including Kingston and Croydon) be included in a new &quot;[[Greater London]]&quot;. The recommendations of the report were enacted in highly modified form in 1965 by the [[London Government Act 1963]]. The areas that now form the London Boroughs of [[London Borough of Croydon|Croydon]], [[Royal Borough of Kingston-upon-Thames|Kingston]], [[London Borough of Merton|Merton]], [[London Borough of Sutton|Sutton]] and that part of [[London Borough of Richmond upon Thames|Richmond]] south of the [[River Thames]] were transferred from Surrey to Greater London. At the same time part of the county of [[Middlesex]], which had been abolished by the legislation, was added to Surrey. This area now forms the borough of [[Spelthorne]]. 
    
Further local government reform under the [[Local Government Act 1972]] took place in 1974. The 1972 Act abolished administrative counties and introduced [[non-metropolitan county|non-metropolitan counties]] in their place. The boundaries of the non-metropolitan county of Surrey were similar to those of the administrative county with the exception of [[Gatwick Airport]] and some surrounding land which was transferred to [[West Sussex]]. It was originally proposed that the parishes of [[Horley]] and [[Charlwood]] would become part of West Sussex, however fierce local opposition led to a reversal of this under the [[Charlwood and Horley Act 1974]].

== Economy ==
[[File:ExportHouse2.JPG|thumb|left|[[Export House]], one of Surrey's tallest buildings]]
Surrey is an affluent county with a service based economy closely tied to that of London. Surrey has the highest GDP per capita of any county in the UK and the highest cost of living in the UK outside of the capital. The county is said to have the highest proportion of millionaires in the UK. The average wage in Surrey is bolstered by the high number of residents who work in financial services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/house-and-home/property/surrey-stockbroker-belt-tops-uk-houseprice-list-581317.html | work=The Independent | location=London | title=Surrey 'stockbroker belt' tops UK house-price list | first=Philip | last=Thornton | date=27 September 2003 | accessdate=24 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Surrey has more organisation and company headquarters than any other county in the UK. Electronic giants [[Nikon]], Whirlpool, [[Canon (company)|Canon]], [[Toshiba]], [[Samsung]] and [[Philips]] are housed here. [[Kia Motors]] and [[Toyota]] UK also have HQs in Surrey, as do drug companies [[Pfizer]] and [[Sanofi-Aventis]] and oil giant [[Esso]]. Some of the largest [[FMCG]] multinationals in the world have their UK and/or European headquarters here, including [[Unilever]], [[Procter &amp; Gamble]], [[Superdrug]], [[Nestle]], [[SC Johnson]], [[Kimberly-Clark]] and [[Colgate-Palmolive]]. NGOs including [[World Wide Fund for Nature|WWF]] UK &amp; [[Compassion in World Farming]] are also based here. Government [[Quango]]s such as [[SEEDA]], SEERA and GOSE are headquartered in Guildford.

== Transport ==
=== Road ===
Three major motorways pass through the county. These are:
* The [[M25 motorway|M25]] (London Orbital). This runs around the North-East of the county. It connects to the [[M1 motorway|M1]], [[M11 motorway|M11]], [[M20 motorway|M20]], [[M26 motorway|M26]] and [[M40 motorway|M40]]. The motorway bypasses [[London Heathrow Airport]], and is easily connected to [[Gatwick Airport]], [[Stanstead Airport]], [[Luton Airport]] and the [[Channel Tunnel]].

*[[M3 motorway|M3]] which runs along the north of the county. It connects London to [[Southampton]] and the [[South West of England]] via [[Camberley]] and [[Sunbury]].

*The [[M23 motorway|M23]]. Runs along the East border, from [[Croydon]], South London, to South of [[Crawley]]. It connects London and Surrey via the M25, to [[Gatwick Airport]].

Other major roads include:

*The [[A3 road|A3]] trunk road is the Old Portmouth Road, which runs from [[Portsmouth]] to London. The road travels through [[Haslemere]], [[Godalming]], [[Guildford]], [[Esher]] and [[Kingston-upon-Thames]]. The [[Hindhead Tunnel]] has bypasses the infamous Hindhead junction and the Devil's Punchbowl.
*The [[A24 road (England)|A24]] runs again from London to [[Littlehampton]] and [[Worthing]]. In Surrey, it passes through [[Ewell]], [[Epsom]], [[Ashtead]], [[Leatherhead]] and [[Dorking]]. It passes past Box Hill, near Dorking. Unlike the A3, which is almost completely dual carriageway, the A24 is generally single carriageway, and has been bypassed around [[Leatherhead]].
*The [[A31 road|A31]] is a trunk road from [[Guildford]] to [[Bere Regis]] via [[Farnham]] and is connected to the M3 by [[Winchester]] or via the A331. It is dual carriageway along the Hog's Back from the A3 to Farnham. It is one of the ancient routes from London to [[Winchester]].
*The A331 connects the A31 to the M3. It runs along the Surrey – Hampshire border, bypassing [[Aldershot]], [[Frimley]] and [[Farnborough, Hampshire|Farnborough]].

=== Rail ===
Surrey is connected to London via the [[South Western Mainline]] and the [[Brighton Mainline]]. The South Western Mainline travels from Weymouth, Southampton, Basingstoke to Farnborough (Main), up through Woking before travelling to Surbiton and onto London Waterloo. Although these routes are used for long distance trains, regular commuter services run along these lines, and Woking, Guildford are main commuter towns for London. As the North – East is heavily built up, and apart of the London Urban Area. There are many commuter routes, including the Chertsey Branch Line, the Hampton Court Line, the New Guildford Line, the Alton Line.

Alternatively, services in the South East terminate in London Bridge, and London Victoria via the Brighton Mainline. It runs from Horley to the [[Merstham Tunnel]], via the major station [[Redhill railway station|Redhill]]. These lines are all electrified, and in Surrey the only main route not electrified is the North Downs Line which runs from Reading to Redhill via Farnborough and Guildford. Services into London Waterloo are run by South West Trains, services to London Victoria and London Bridge are Southern and South Eastern, and services on the North Downs Line are operated by Great First Western. From Guildford, a daily service with CrossCountry runs to [[Manchester Piccadilly Station|Manchester Piccadilly]] via Reading.

Major Stations:

*[[Guildford railway station|Guildford]] (7.8&amp;nbsp;million passengers)
*[[Woking railway station|Woking]] (7.1&amp;nbsp;million passengers)
*[[Epsom railway station|Epsom]] (3.5&amp;nbsp;million passengers)
*[[Redhill railway station|Redhill]] (3.4&amp;nbsp;million passengers)


=== Air ===
Both [[Heathrow]] (in the London Borough of Hillingdon) and [[Gatwick]] (near the Sussex/Surrey border) are close at hand and both are connected to Surrey by the M25 in particular. There is also a National Express Coach from Woking to Heathrow Airport.
[[Fairoaks Airport]] , on the edge of Chobham and Ottershaw is just 2.3 miles from Woking Town centre which operates as a private airfield with two training schools and is home to other aviation businesses.

== Education ==
[[File:RoyalHollowayFoundersLondon-Seabhcan.jpg|thumb|400px|right|[[Royal Holloway, University of London|Royal Holloway College]], [[Egham]]]]

Surrey has a [[Comprehensive school|comprehensive]] secondary education system with 53 state schools (not including [[sixth form college]]s). There are 41 independent schools including [[Preparatory school (UK)|Preparatory schools]] and [[Senior school]]s including the famous [[Charterhouse School]], which along with [[Eton College]] and [[Harrow College|Harrow]] was one of the original nine independent schools defined by the [[Public Schools Act 1868]]. Most secondary schools in Surrey have sixth forms although Reigate, Esher, Egham, Spelthorne, Woking and Waverley districts tend to have separate sixth form colleges.

Private tutor agencies include Southern Tutors Limited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southerntutors.co.uk |title=Southern Tutors Limited |publisher=southerntutors.co.uk |date=2011-12-05 |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Higher education ===
{{see also|List of schools in Surrey|Category:Education in Surrey}}

* The [[University of Surrey]] is based in [[Guildford]] and the University of Creative Arts (UCA) is based in [[Farnham]] and [[Epsom]].
* [[Royal Holloway, University of London]] is based in [[Egham]]

== Emergency services ==
Surrey is served by these emergency services.
* [[Surrey Police]], with twelve police stations in Surrey.
* [[South East Coast Ambulance Service]] as of 1 July 2006. Previously [[Surrey Ambulance Service]] covered Surrey; on 1 July 2006, it merged with [[Sussex Ambulance Service]] and [[Kent Ambulance Service]] to form the South East Coast Ambulance Service. Surrey has twenty-one ambulance stations.
* [[Surrey Fire &amp; Rescue Service]], with twenty-four fire stations in Surrey.
* [[SURSAR]], Surrey Search &amp; Rescue, based in Woking Police Station.

== Places of interest ==
Significant landscapes in Surrey include [[Box Hill, England|Box Hill]] just north of [[Dorking]]; the [[Devil's Punch Bowl]] at [[Hindhead]] and [[Frensham]] Common. [[Leith Hill]] south west of [[Dorking]] in the [[Greensand Ridge]] is the second highest point in south-east England. [[Witley Common]] and [[Thursley Common]] are expansive areas of ancient heathland south of [[Godalming]] run by the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]] and [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]]. The [[Surrey Hills AONB|Surrey Hills]] are an area of outstanding natural beauty ([[AONB]]).

[[File:Lawns at Wisley.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Lawns at [[RHS Garden, Wisley]]]]
More manicured landscapes can be seen at [[Claremont Landscape Garden]], south of [[Esher]] (dating from 1715). There is also [[Winkworth Arboretum]] south east of [[Godalming]] and [[Windlesham Arboretum]] near [[Lightwater]] created in the 20th century. [[Wisley]] is home to the [[Royal Horticultural Society]] [[RHS Garden, Wisley|gardens]]. [[Kew]], historically part of Surrey but now in Greater London, features the [[Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew]], as well as [[The National Archives]] for England &amp; Wales.

There are 80 Surrey Wildlife Trust reserves with at least one in all 11 [[non-metropolitan_district|non-metropolitan districts]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.surreywildlifetrust.org/reserves] Surrey Wildlife Trust reserves&lt;/ref&gt;

Surrey's important country houses include the [[Tudor period|Tudor]] mansion of [[Loseley Park]], built in the 1560s and [[Clandon Park]], an 18th-century [[Palladian]] mansion in [[West Clandon]] to the east of Guildford. Nearby [[Hatchlands Park]] in [[East Clandon]], was built in 1758 with [[Robert Adam]] interiors and a collection of keyboard instruments. [[Polesden Lacey]] south of [[Great Bookham]] is a [[regency architecture|regency]] villa with extensive grounds. On a smaller scale, [[Oakhurst Cottage]] in [[Hambledon, Surrey|Hambledon]] near [[Godalming]] is a restored 16th-century worker's home.

A canal system, the [[Wey and Godalming Navigations]] is linked to the [[Wey and Arun Canal]] with future full reopening expected after 2015. [[Dapdune Wharf]] in [[Guildford]] commemorates the work of the canal system and is home to a restored Wey barge, the Reliance. Furthermore on the [[River Tillingbourne]], [[Shalford Mill]] is an 18th century water-mill. 
   
[[Runnymede]] at [[Egham]] is the site of the sealing of the [[Magna Carta]] in 1215.
  
[[Guildford Cathedral]] is a post-war cathedral built from bricks made from the clay hill on which it stands.   

[[Brooklands]] Museum recognises the motoring past of Surrey. The county is also home to the theme parks [[Thorpe Park]] and [[Chessington World of Adventures]].

== Surrey in film and books ==
[[File:Woking tripod.JPG|thumb|right|Sculpture of a [[H. G. Wells|Wellsian]] Martian tripod in [[Woking]]]]
Much of [[H. G. Wells]]'s 1898 novella ''[[The War of the Worlds]]'' is set in Surrey with many specific towns and villages identified. The Martians first land on [[Horsell Common SSSI|Horsell Common]] on the north side of Woking, outside the Bleak House pub, now called Sands. In the story the narrator flees in the direction of London, first passing [[Byfleet]] and then [[Weybridge]] before travelling east along the north bank of the [[Thames]]. Jane Austen's novel Emma is set in Surrey and the famous picnic where Emma embarrasses Miss Bates takes place on Box Hill. The character [[Ford Prefect (character)|Ford Prefect]] from ''[[The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy]]'' claimed to be from Guildford in Surrey, but in actuality he was from a small planet somewhere in the vicinity of [[Betelgeuse]]. Thomas Paine Kydd, the hero of the [[Kydd]] series of naval adventure novels written by [[Julian Stockwin]], starts off as a young wig-maker from Guildford who is pressed into service and thus begins a life at sea. [[Atonement (novel)|''Atonement'']] is set in Surrey. The late Poet Laureate [[Sir John Betjeman]] mentions [[Camberley]] in his poem &quot;A Subaltern's Lovesong&quot;, while [[Carshalton]] forms the literary backdrop to many of the poems by [[James Farrar]]. In [[J. K. Rowling|J.K. Rowling's]] [[Harry Potter (series)|&quot;Harry Potter&quot; series]], the home of [[Harry Potter|Harry's]] pernicious relatives, [[the Dursleys]], is set in the fictional town of Little Whinging, Surrey. They lived at Number Four Privet Drive, Little Whinging, Surrey in a perfectly ordinary house on a perfectly ordinary street.

The county has also been used as a film location. Part of the movie ''[[The Holiday]]'' was filmed in Godalming and Shere: [[Kate Winslet]]'s character Iris lived in a cottage in Shere and [[Cameron Diaz]]'s character Amanda switched houses with her as part of a home exchange. The final scene of ''[[Bridget Jones: The Edge of Reason]]'' uses the village church, also in Shere, as does the movie ''[[The Wedding Date]]''. In the 1976 film ''[[The Omen (1976 film)|The Omen]]'', the scenes at the cathedral were filmed at [[Guildford Cathedral]].&lt;ref name=&quot;omen&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url = http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,1789988,00.html| title = Church fears return of Omen curse | accessdate =31 August 2007| date =4 June 2004|work=The Observer |location=UK  | first=Rob | last=Sharp}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film ''[[I Want Candy (film)|I Want Candy]]'' follows two hopeful lads from [[Leatherhead]] trying to break into the movies, and was partly filmed in Brooklands College ([[Weybridge]] campus). Surrey woodland represented Germany in the opening scene of ''[[Gladiator (2000 film)|Gladiator]]'', starring [[Russell Crowe]]; it was filmed at the [[Bourne Wood]]s near Farnham in Surrey.
Scenes for the 2009 BBC production of ''[[Emma]]'' by [[Jane Austen]], starring [[Romola Garai]] and [[Michael Gambon]], were filmed at St Mary the Virgin Church [[Send, Surrey|Send]] near [[Guildford]] and at [[Loseley House]].

== See also ==
{{portal}}
* [[Lord Lieutenant of Surrey]]
* [[High Sheriff of Surrey]]
* [[Surrey (carriage)]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite web |url=http://uk.geocities.com/guildfordian2002/AngloSaxon/PrinceAlfred.htm |title=Martyr-Prince Alfred Of England |author=Vladimir Moss |accessdate=16 October 2007|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070225020126/http://uk.geocities.com/guildfordian2002/AngloSaxon/PrinceAlfred.htm|archivedate=25 February 2007}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.btinternet.com/~john.whitbourn/Cornish.htm |title=The Day the Cornish Invaded Guildford |publisher=The Surrey Advertiser |date=2 June 1989 |accessdate=16 October 2007}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Surrey}}
* [http://www.surreycc.gov.uk Surrey County Council]
* [http://www.livinginsurrey.co.uk Living in Surrey – a website that champions local businesses and events.]
* [http://www.surreylife.co.uk Surrey Life – a monthly Surrey based community magazine.]
*{{dmoz|Regional/Europe/United_Kingdom/England/Surrey}}
* [http://surreymaps.surreycc.gov.uk/public/viewer.asp Surrey Interactive Map]
* [http://www.exploringsurreyspast.org.uk Exploring Surrey's Past]
* [http://www.sursar.org.uk Surrey Search &amp; Rescue (SurSAR)]

{{Geographic Location
|title = '''Neighbouring counties'''
|Centre    = Surrey
|North     = [[Berkshire]], Greater London
|Northeast = [[Greater London]]
|East      = [[Kent]]
|Southeast = [[East Sussex]]
|South     = [[West Sussex]]
|Southwest = [[Hampshire]]
|West      = [[Hampshire]]
|Northwest = [[Berkshire]]
}}

{{Surrey}}
{{England counties}}

{{Heptarchy}}

{{coord|51.243|-0.418|display=title}}

[[Category:Surrey| ]]
[[Category:Non-metropolitan counties]]
[[Category:South East England]]

[[af:Surrey]]
[[ang:Sūþrīge]]
[[ar:سري]]
[[ast:Surrey]]
[[zh-min-nan:Surrey]]
[[bg:Съри]]
[[br:Surrey]]
[[ca:Surrey]]
[[cs:Surrey]]
[[cy:Surrey]]
[[da:Surrey]]
[[de:Surrey]]
[[et:Surrey]]
[[el:Σάρρεϋ]]
[[es:Surrey]]
[[eo:Surrey]]
[[eu:Surrey]]
[[fr:Surrey (comté)]]
[[gv:Surrey]]
[[ko:서리 주]]
[[hi:सरी]]
[[io:Surrey]]
[[id:Surrey]]
[[ia:Surrey]]
[[is:Surrey]]
[[it:Surrey]]
[[kn:ಸರ್ರೆ]]
[[kw:Surrey]]
[[la:Surria]]
[[lv:Sareja]]
[[lb:Grofschaft Surrey]]
[[lt:Surėjus]]
[[mr:सरे]]
[[ms:Surrey]]
[[nl:Surrey (graafschap)]]
[[ja:サリー (イングランド)]]
[[no:Surrey]]
[[nn:Surrey]]
[[oc:Comtat de Surrey]]
[[pnb:سرے]]
[[pl:Surrey]]
[[pt:Surrey]]
[[ro:Surrey]]
[[ru:Суррей]]
[[scn:Surrey]]
[[simple:Surrey]]
[[sk:Surrey (Anglicko)]]
[[sl:Surrey]]
[[sh:Surrey]]
[[fi:Surrey]]
[[sv:Surrey]]
[[th:เซอร์รีย์]]
[[tr:Surrey]]
[[uk:Суррей]]
[[vi:Surrey]]
[[vo:Surrey]]
[[yo:Surrey]]
[[zh:薩里郡]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
