<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="482579" ns="0" title=".nfo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{primarysources|date=March 2011}}
{{ infobox file format
| icon                   = 
| logo                   = 
| screenshot             = [[File:Wikipedia-nfo.png|200px]]
| caption                = Screenshot of a .nfo file
| extension              = .nfo
| mime                   = text/x-nfo&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gitorious.org/nfoview/mainline/blobs/raw/master/NEWS|title=NFO Viewer | work = NEWS file|quote=Remove mimetype installation files and use the new 'text/x-nfo' mimetype added with [[freedesktop.org]]'s shared-mime-info 0.30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| type code              = 
| uniform type           = 
| magic                  = 
| owner                  = 
| released               = 
| latest release version = 
| latest release date    = 
| genre                  = [[Plain text]]
| container for          = 
| contained by           = 
| extended from          = 
| extended to            = 
| standard               = 
| url                    = 
}}

'''.nfo''' (also written '''.NFO''' or '''NFO''', a [[abbreviation|contraction]] of &quot;info&quot;, or &quot;[[information]]&quot;) is a commonly used three-letter [[filename extension]] of [[ASCII]] or [[extended ASCII]] text files that accompany other files and contain information about them. Such '''NFO files''' can be viewed with [[text editor]]s or dedicated NFO viewers. They commonly also contain elaborate [[ASCII art]].&lt;ref name=&quot;defacto&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defacto2.net/documents.cfm|title=Defacto2 - Scene Documents, text and NFO files}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Content of NFO files ==

NFO files usually contain release information about a software program. They are commonly associated with [[warez]] groups who include them to declare credit of said release.  Similarly they are often found in [[demoscene]] productions, where the respective groups include them for credits, contact details, and the software requirements.&lt;ref name=&quot;defacto&quot; /&gt;

NFO files were common, and sometimes required, during the era of the [[Bulletin Board System|BBS]]. A typical warez NFO file was elaborate and highly decorated, and usually included a large [[ASCII art]] logo along with software release and warez group information. The designers of these NFO files frequently incorporated [[extended ASCII]] characters from the then near-ubiquitous [[code page 437]] character set in the file.

Before [[Windows 95]] was introduced, NFO files also sometimes used ANSI-escape sequences to generate animated ASCII art ([[ANSI art]]). These animations, however, required [[ANSI.SYS]] to be loaded by the [[COMMAND.COM|DOS shell]]. If the user's computer wasn't already configured to load the ANSI.SYS driver, viewing ANSI art required reconfiguring and rebooting. Because of this, ANSI art was much less common, and getting ANSI art to display correctly on a Windows 95 PC often proved more difficult, leading to a decline of such art in NFO files.

As of 2010, NFO files can still be found in many [[ZIP file format|ZIP]] archives. In modern day warez NFO files, a large ASCII art logo is frequently shown at the top, followed by textual information below. Instead of using the old code page 437 extended ASCII characters, modern ASCII art uses the current [[de-facto]] web standard [[ISO-8859-1]]/[[ISO-8859-15]] or [[Unicode]] [[UTF-8]] characters.

=== Compatibility problems ===

Because the once-ubiquitous ASCII [[code page 437]] was never common on the [[World Wide Web]] and is poorly supported by most (as of 2007) modern computers, older NFO files are frequently rendered incorrectly in modern [[web browsers]] and on modern [[operating system]]s (which mostly no longer use code page 437). To display old NFO files as intended, a dedicated CP437-capable viewing software or conversion is often required.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.gna.org/nfoview/|title=NFO Viewer|quote=NFO Viewer is a simple viewer for NFO files, which are &quot;ASCII&quot; art in the CP437 codepage. The advantages of using NFO Viewer instead of a text editor are preset font and encoding settings, automatic window size and clickable hyperlinks.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An added problem lies in the fact that many modern web browsers and [[text editing]] programs often use [[proportional font]]s, whereas the ASCII art included in both old and new NFO files is heavily dependent on the file being viewed with a [[fixed width]] font.
As a workaround, simply using a [[text editor]] and selecting a monospace font may, in the absence of incompatible extended ASCII characters, sometimes be sufficient. In this case, the only difference might be that the text in GUI text editors will often be black on a white background (rather than white on a black background as seen when viewing in [[MS-DOS]] or Unix console), thus making some of the art appear to be &quot;inverse&quot;, like a [[film negative]].

== Canonical origins ==

NFO files were first introduced by &quot;Fabulous Furlough&quot; of the [[IBM PC|PC]] organization [[The Humble Guys]], or THG.&lt;ref name=textfiles /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.textfiles.com/piracy/HUMBLE/|title=NFO files by THG}} Evidence of the very first NFO files by The Humble Guys.&lt;/ref&gt; Such organizations are also known as [[warez|warez group]]s or [[software cracking|crack groups]]. The first use came in 1989 on the THG release of the PC game [[Bubble Bobble]]. This file was used in lieu of the more common [[readme|README.TXT]] or README.1ST file names.&lt;ref name=textfiles&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.defacto2.net/documents.cfm?id=183 |title=Online Software Piracy of the Last Millennium |first=Ben |last=Garrett |date=2004-04-27 |publisher=defacto2.net |format=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The perpetuation of this file extension legacy was carried on by warez groups which followed after THG and is still in use to this day. Hence its strong presence on [[Usenet]] newsgroups that carry binaries and on [[P2P file sharing|P2P file trading]] networks.

The Humble Guys later became a [[demogroup]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pouet.net/groups.php?which=1673|title=Demo's from The Humble Guys}}&lt;/ref&gt; thus bringing the .nfo file tradition into the [[demoscene]].

== File association ==

On [[Microsoft Windows]], the NFO filename extension is associated with a Microsoft software tool called ''System Information'' (msinfo32.exe).&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web|url=http://www.fileinfo.com/extension/nfo|title=.NFO File Extension |quote=Windows may unsuccessfully attempt to use the Microsoft Help program in order to open the file; instead open the file directly with a text editor.}}&lt;/ref&gt; System Information provides a general overview of a computer's system specifications as well as detailed information on the system's hardware components. It even includes information about the Windows environment. NFO files that are meant for System Information simply contain all of the information that System Information displays and are saved in an XML format.

== See also ==

* [[README]]
* [[FILE ID.DIZ]]
* [[The iSONEWS]]

== References ==

{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://nfomation.net/ NFO Uploader and Viewer]
* [http://www.defacto2.net/nfo-files.cfm List of NFO utilities]

{{DEFAULTSORT:nfo}}
[[Category:ASCII art]]
[[Category:Warez]]

[[de:NFO]]
[[es:.nfo]]
[[fr:.nfo]]
[[nl:NFO-bestand]]
[[ru:NFO]]
[[sl:NFO]]
[[sv:.nfo]]
[[tr:.nfo]]
[[uk:.nfo]]
[[zh:.nfo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
