<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="485487" ns="0" title="M&amp;M&#039;s"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{About|the candy|other uses|M&amp;M (disambiguation)}}
{{for|the rapper|Eminem}}
{{prose|date=April 2011}}
{{refimprove|date=May 2010}}
{{infobox brand
| logo                   =
| name                   = M&amp;M
| image                  = [[File:Plain-M&amp;Ms-Pile.jpg|280px|Milk Chocolate M&amp;M's]]
| type                   = [[Candy]]
| currentowner           = [[Mars, Incorporated]]
| origin                 = United States
| introduced             = 1941
| discontinued           =
| related                = [[Minstrels (chocolate)|Minstrels]], [[Revels (confectionery)|Revels]], [[Skittles (confectionery)|Skittles]], [[Treets]] &lt;!-- similar products from the same company --&gt;
| markets                = Worldwide (over 100 countries)&lt;ref name=&quot;usat03&quot;&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/money/advertising/2003-12-30-mm-bw_x.htm M&amp;M's candy fades to black and white], a December 30, 2003 [[Reuters]] article via ''[[USA Today]]''&lt;/ref&gt;
| previousowners         =
| trademarkregistrations =
| website                = http://www.mms.com/
}}
'''M&amp;M's''' (named after the surnames of Forrest Mars, Sr., &amp; Bruce Murrie of [[The Hershey Company|Hershey's]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/mars.html Inventor of the Week Archive]&lt;/ref&gt;) are [[dragée]]-like ''&quot;colorful button-shaped candies&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;usat03&quot;/&gt; produced by [[Mars, Incorporated]]. The [[Sugar panning|candy shells]], each of which has the letter &quot;m&quot; printed in [[lower case]] on one side, surround a variety of fillings, including [[milk chocolate]], [[dark chocolate]], [[crisped rice]], [[mint chocolate]], [[peanut]]s, [[almond]]s, [[orange chocolate]], [[coconut]], [[pretzel]], [[wild cherry]], and [[peanut butter]].  M&amp;M's originated in the United States in 1941, and are now sold in over 100 countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;usat03&quot;/&gt; They are produced in different colors, some of which have [[#Color changes in chocolate M&amp;M's|changed over the years]].  

==History==
[[File:M&amp;Ms-Wrapper-Small.jpg|thumb|right|Plain/Milk Chocolate M&amp;M's]]

===1930s and 1940s===
[[Forrest Mars, Sr.]], the founder of the Mars Company, got the idea for the confection in the 1930s during the [[Spanish Civil War]] when he saw soldiers eating chocolate pellets with a hard shell of tempered chocolate surrounding the inside, preventing the candies from melting. Mars received a patent for his own process on March 3, 1941.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/mars.html |title=Inventor of the Week: Archive |publisher=Web.mit.edu |date= |accessdate=June 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Production began in 1941 in a factory located at 285 Badger Avenue in [[Clinton Hill, Newark, New Jersey]]. One M was for Forrest E. Mars Sr., and one for Bruce Murrie, the son of Hershey's Chocolate president William F. R. Murrie.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hersheyarchives.org/essay/details.aspx?EssayId=28&amp;Rurl=%2fresources%2fsearch-results.aspx%3fType%3dBrowseEssay Murrie, William F.R.; 1873–1950] - hersheyarchives.com - Retrieved January 22, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Murrie had 20 percent interest in the product. The arrangement allowed the candies to be made with Hershey chocolate which had control of the [[ration]]ed chocolate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.mit.edu/invent/iow/mars.html |title=Inventor of the Week: Archive |publisher=Web.mit.edu |date= |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; When operations were started, the hard-coated chocolates were made in five colors: red, yellow, brown, green, and violet. They were served in a cardboard tube (similar to [[Smarties]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;virtualnewarknj.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.virtualnewarknj.com/memories/newark/bodianmm.htm |title=Looking Back at Newark Origins of World-Famous M&amp;M Chocolates - virtualnewarknj.com - Retrieved August&amp;nbsp;28, 2008 |publisher=virtualnewarknj.com |date=April 12, 1981 |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn0620&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=M&amp;M lovers pick purple|url=http://money.cnn.com/2002/06/20/news/companies/mandms/|work=[[CNNMoney.com]]|publisher=[[Time Warner]]|date=June 20, 2002|accessdate=June 14, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The practicality of the candies during [[World War II]] caused an increase in production and its factory moved to bigger quarters at 200 North 12th Street in [[Newark, New Jersey]] where they remained until 1958 when it moved to a bigger factory at [[Hackettstown, New Jersey]]. During the war, the candies were exclusively sold to the military.&lt;ref name=&quot;virtualnewarknj.com&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Candy-Peanut-MMs-Wrapper-Small.jpg|thumb|Peanut M&amp;M's, introduced in 1954.]]

===1950s and 1960s===
In 1950, a black &quot;M&quot; was imprinted on the candies. It was changed to white in 1954.&lt;ref name=&quot;virtualnewarknj.com&quot;/&gt;

In the early 1950s, the [[Midwest Research Institute]] in [[Kansas City, Missouri]], working for M&amp;M's, perfected a process where by {{convert|3300|lb}} of chocolate centers could be coated every hour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mriresearch.org/AboutMRI/Breakthroughs.asp |title=MRI Breakthroughs |publisher=Mriresearch.org |date=September 11, 2001 |accessdate=January 15, 2010 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080702054645/http://www.mriresearch.org/AboutMRI/Breakthroughs.asp |archivedate = July 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Peanut M&amp;M's were introduced in 1954, but first appeared only in the color tan.
In 1960, Peanut M&amp;M's added the yellow, red, green, and orange colors.

===1970s and 1980s===
Red candies were eliminated in 1976&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://us.mms.com/us/about/history/story/|title=The Story of M&amp;M'S Brand|accessdate=June 14, 2008|work=mms.com|publisher=[[Mars, Incorporated]]|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080409043530/http://us.mms.com/us/about/history/story/ |archivedate = April 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to health concerns over the dye [[amaranth (dye)|amaranth]] ([[FD&amp;C]] Red #2), which was a suspected [[carcinogen]], and were replaced with orange-colored candies. This was done despite the fact that M&amp;M's did not contain the dye; the action was purely to satisfy worried consumers. Red candies were reintroduced later, but they also kept the orange colored M&amp;M's. They currently contain [[Allura Red AC]] (FD&amp;C Red #40, E129). In Europe, Allura Red AC is not recommended for consumption by children. It is banned in Denmark, Belgium, France, Germany, Switzerland, Sweden, Austria, and Norway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ukfoodguide.net/e129.htm|title=E129 Allura Red AC, FD&amp;C Red 40|accessdate=June 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, [[Cochineal dye|Cochineal]] (E120) is used in the red shells. 

In 1980, M&amp;M's were introduced internationally to Australia, Canada, Europe, Hong Kong, Japan, Malaysia and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mms.com/us/about/mmshistory/&lt;/ref&gt;

Although they were marketed and then withdrawn in the 1960s, in 1988, almond-centered M&amp;M's hit stores again in limited release, with appearances only during [[Christmas]] and [[Easter]] times; they became a standard part of the product line in 1992.

Also in 1986, M&amp;M's launched HOLIDAYS Chocolate Candies for Easter and Christmas, with the Easter candies having bunny, chick, and egg symbols on pastel-colored shells, and the Christmas candies having pine tree and candle symbols on red and green shells. By 1993, the holiday symbols were replaced with the trademark &quot;M&quot;.

===1990s===
In 1990, Mars Snackfood US signed up to be a sponsor for NASCAR. Drivers for the M&amp;M car through the years have included [[Ernie Irvan]], [[Ken Schrader]], [[Eliott Sadler]], [[Ricky Rudd]], [[David Gilliland]] and [[Kyle Busch]].

In 1991, Peanut Butter M&amp;M's were released. These candies have [[peanut butter]] inside the chocolate center and the same color scheme as the other brands.

In 1995, Mars ran a promotion in which consumers were invited to vote on which of blue, pink, or purple would replace the tan M&amp;M's. Blue was the winner, replacing tan in early 1995. Consumers could vote by calling 1-800-FUN-COLOR. (The introduction of blue M&amp;M's to Australia in 1997 was controversially promoted by the [[Carlton Football Club]] of the [[Australian Football League]] [AFL] who, for one game, swapped their trademark dark blue [[guernsey (clothing)#Use in Australian rules football|guernseys]] for pale blue guernseys — their first change since the early 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afl.com.au/The%20Clubs/tabid/10297/default.aspx |title=The Clubs |publisher=AFL.com.au |date= |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;)

[[File:M&amp;M's spokecandies.jpg|200px|right|thumb|Red and Yellow, two of M&amp;M's &quot;spokescandies&quot;]]
[[File:Green M spokescandy.png|200px|right|thumb|The Green &quot;spokescandy&quot;]]
[[File:Blue M spokecandy.jpg|200px|right|thumb|The Blue &quot;spokescandy&quot;]]
Concurrent with the Blue M&amp;M campaign, M&amp;M's introduced computer animated [[mascot|&quot;spokescandies&quot;]] in their [[television commercial]]s. These include the team of the [[cynicism|cynical]] and [[sarcasm|sardonic]] &quot;[[Red]]&quot; (originally voiced by [[Jon Lovitz]], thereafter [[Billy West (voice actor)|Billy West]]) who is the mascot for milk chocolate M&amp;M's, and the [[happiness|happy]] and [[humor|gullible]] &quot;[[Yellow]]&quot; (originally [[John Goodman]], thereafter [[J.K. Simmons]]), who is the mascot for peanut M&amp;M's. Other mascots include the &quot;cool one&quot;, Blue ([[Phil Hartman]], thereafter Robb Pruitt); the [[Sexual attraction|seductive]] Green ([[Cree Summer]]) (Green is the only female M&amp;M's mascot); and the slightly [[neurosis|neurotic]] Orange (Eric Kirchberger) for crispy and pretzel M&amp;M's. 

In 1996, Mars introduced &quot;M&amp;M's Minis&quot;, smaller candies usually sold in plastic tubes instead of bags.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} A video game, ''[[M&amp;M's: The Lost Formulas]]'', was also eventually released, based on this candy. It was released on September 28, 2000.

In 1998, M&amp;M's became &quot;The Official Candy of the [[New Millennium]]&quot;, since MM is the roman numeral for 2000. A year later, Crispy M&amp;M's were released. They were slightly larger than the milk chocolate variety and featured a crispy rice center. They were discontinued in the United States in 2005. They are still available in Europe, Australia, and southeast Asia.

In 1990, an M&amp;M's exhibit at New York's Erie County Fair, promoting the company's nutrition awareness campaign, became the precursor to Cow Parade, the whimsical phenomenon where municipalities and museums display decorated cattle at convenient traffic intersections. The M&amp;M's display was a life size fiberglass cow covered with 66,000 M&amp;M candies, each adhered by hand with the &quot;m&quot; logo on each candy facing outward. Candy the Cow was the first-ever decorated bovine, and earned M&amp;M Mars $1&amp;nbsp;million in free publicity. The chocolate marvel, created by designer [[Michael Adams (graphic designer)|Michael Adams]], was reported on by ''[[Newsweek]]'' magazine (&quot;udderly amazing&quot;) as well as the ''[[New York Post]]'', [[UPI]] and [[WABC-TV]]. Candy then appeared as a live &quot;guest&quot; on ''[[Live with Regis]]'', where Regis Philbin &quot;interviewed&quot; her and affirmed the nutritional value of milk chocolate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.behindthescenesmarketing.com/events-tshws-props/01_cow.html |title=Events - M&amp;M Candy Cow |publisher=Behindthescenesmarketing.com |date= |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2000–2005===
In 2000, &quot;Plain&quot; M&amp;M's (a name introduced in 1954 when Peanut M&amp;M's were introduced) were renamed &quot;Milk Chocolate&quot; M&amp;M's, and pictures of the candy pieces were added to the traditional brown and white packaging&lt;ref&gt;http://www.collectorcafe.com/article_archive.asp?article=10&amp;id=1877&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2000/06/29/business/media-business-advertising-m-m-mars-concludes-after-46-years-that-plain-does-not.html |title=THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING; M&amp;M/Mars concludes, after 46 years, that 'Plain' does not do justice to the original M&amp;M's candy. |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date= |accessdate=June 29, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

In July 2001, [[Dulce de Leche]] M&amp;M's were introduced in five markets with large Hispanic populations: [[Los Angeles, CA]], [[San Diego, CA]], [[Miami, FL]], [[McAllen, Texas|Mcallen]]-[[Brownsville, TX]], and [[San Antonio, TX]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allbusiness.com/food-beverage/food-industry-food-mfg-sugar/6097035-1.html |title=M&amp;M/MARS Woos Latinos With New ``M&amp;M's'&amp;#39; Dulce de Leche-Caramel Chocolate Candies; New Flavor to Premiere in Markets With Highest Concentration of Latinos. &amp;#124; Food &amp; Beverage &gt; Food Industry from |publisher=AllBusiness.com |date= |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flavor never became popular with the Hispanic community, who preferred existing M&amp;M's flavors, and it was discontinued in most areas by early 2003.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nuintelligence.net/Manager/anmviewer.asp?a=9{{Dead link|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flavor was widely panned for containing 36&amp;nbsp;grams of fat per serving.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailycandy.com/new-york/article/17516/La+Dulce+Vita |title=Dulce de Leche M&amp;M's &amp;#124; New York |publisher=DailyCandy.com |date=February 13, 2002 |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Mars solicited votes in their first ever &quot;M&amp;M's Global Color Vote&quot; to add a new color from three choices:  aqua (turquoise), pink, and purple. This time, purple won and was featured for a limited time.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn0620&quot;/&gt;

Since 2005 M&amp;M's have been available online in 17 colors, with personalized phrases on each candy on the opposite side from the &quot;m&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mymms.com/|title=Custom Printed MY M&amp;M'S|work=mms.com|publisher=[[Mars, Incorporated]]|accessdate=June 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Released around Christmas, these custom-printed M&amp;M's were originally intended for [[holiday greetings]], but are now available all year round.

In April 2005 M&amp;M's ran the &quot;mPire&quot; promotion to tie in with the ''[[Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith]]'' movie release. M&amp;M's were offered in dark chocolate varieties (Regular and Peanut) for the first time after a string of [[Addams Family]] M&amp;M's commercials.

In May 2004, M&amp;M's ran a ''Shrek 2'' promotion to tie in with the movie's release. M&amp;M's were offered &quot;ogre-sized&quot; (65% larger) in swamp/ogre colors. They were sold at many stores displayed in huge cardboard cutout ogre displays.

In the summer of 2005, Mars added &quot;Mega M&amp;M's&quot; to the lineup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=M&amp;M's get mega-sized|url=http://money.cnn.com/2005/08/04/news/funny/m_and_ms/|work=[[CNNMoney.com]]|publisher=[[Time Warner]]|date=August 4, 2005|accessdate=June 14, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These candies, at 55% larger than the traditional M&amp;M's, were a little smaller than the ogre-sized version. They were available in milk chocolate and peanut varieties. The colors for Mega M&amp;M's were changed to less-bright colors – teal (replacing green), beige (orange), maroon (red), gold (yellow), blue-gray (blue), and brown to appeal to a more adult consumer.

===2006–present===
[[File:MandM Times Square.JPG|left|thumb|220px|Outside of the M&amp;M store in [[Times Square]], [[New York City]].]]In July 2006, Dark Chocolate M&amp;M's reappeared in a purple package, followed in 2007 by Dark Chocolate Peanut M&amp;M's. Also in 2006, the company piloted White Chocolate M&amp;M's as a tie-in with their ''Pirates of the Caribbean'' promotion. The company also offered eight new flavors of M&amp;M's via online sales, as well as at [[M&amp;M's World]] locations: &quot;All That Razz&quot;; &quot;Eat, Drink, &amp; Be Cherry&quot;; &quot;A Day at the Peach&quot;; &quot;Orange-U-Glad&quot;; &quot;Mint Condition&quot;; &quot;AlmonDeeLicious&quot;; &quot;Nut What You Think&quot; and &quot;Cookie Minster&quot;.  Mars also released a &quot;Crispy Mint&quot; variety in Australia that year.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

Also in 2006, M&amp;M's became the official chocolate of NASCAR.

In 2007, M&amp;M's introduced a limited-edition raspberry flavor called &quot;M&amp;M's Razzberry Chocolate Candies.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

Also in 2007, M&amp;M's produced a 50-foot, smiling Lady Liberty M&amp;M statue to kick off a campaign encouraging Americans to create their own M&amp;M characters at mms.com. The website allows for people to log in and create their own character from scratch. They choose everything from the color and shape to hair and accessories.

For the 2008 Valentine's Day season Mars introduced all-green bags of M&amp;M's. This was due to common urban folklore that says green M&amp;M's are an [[aphrodisiac]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=M&amp;M'S Chocolate Candies go green just in time for Valentine's Day|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/mnr/mars/31278/|publisher=PRNewswire|date=January 16, 2008|accessdate=August 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were brought back for 2009 alongside the &quot;Ms. Green Heats Up Valentine's Day&quot; contest.

In 2008, two new limited-edition varieties of the candy were introduced – &quot;Wildly Cherry&quot; M&amp;M's, and, as a marketing tie-in with the film ''[[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]'', &quot;Mint Crisp&quot; M&amp;M's.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

M&amp;M's also introduced another new product called &quot;M&amp;M's Premiums&quot; in 2008. They come in five flavors – chocolate almond, mint chocolate, mocha, raspberry almond and triple chocolate (milk, dark, and white chocolate), which are sold in small upright cartons with a plastic bag inside. M&amp;M's Premiums do not have a candy shell, but are coated with carnauba wax and color. Dark Chocolate was added in 2009, replacing Mocha.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

During summer of 2008, My M&amp;M's launched 'Faces,' which allows consumers to print the faces of loved ones on M&amp;M's chocolate candies at mymms.com.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

In February 2009, M&amp;M's launched the &quot;M&amp;M’s Colour Break-Up&quot; promotion in Australia where M&amp;M's were sold in separate packs (one for each color): the packs included a code to win prizes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=M&amp;M'S Color Break Up|url=http://www.colourbreakup.com.au/html/default.aspx| publisher=Mars |date=February 18, 2009 | accessdate=February 18, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Summer 2009, M&amp;M's launched a limited-edition &quot;Strawberried Peanut Butter&quot; variant to tie in with the release of ''[[Transformers: Revenge of the Fallen]]''. In addition, M&amp;M's launched a limited edition &quot;Coconut M&amp;M's,&quot; which became a permanent item in 2010.

In July 2009, a study showed that a dye similar to that in blue M&amp;M's showed benefits in helping paralyzed rats to walk again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://featuresblogs.chicagotribune.com/features_julieshealthclub/2009/07/can-blue-mms-cure-paralysis.html |title=Julie's Health Club: Dye found in blue M&amp;Ms may improve spinal injuries |publisher=Featuresblogs.chicagotribune.com |date=July 28, 2009 |accessdate=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2010, M&amp;M's launched a new pretzel variety. Pretzel M&amp;M's do not have any yellow M&amp;M's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.m-ms.com/us/about/products/pretzel/|title=About M&amp;MS®: Products: Pretzel|accessdate=March 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 2010, M&amp;M's Bare All were released as part of a competition in Australia and New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;http://m-msbareall.com.au/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; M&amp;M's Bare All winning packs were ordinary M&amp;M's, but without shells (and hence had no colours). An official website, http://m-msbareall.com.au/, was launched, along with television advertisements.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1b1R0BEFc7w M&amp;M's Bare All TV commercial] from [[YouTube]]&lt;/ref&gt;

About the time pretzel M&amp;M'S came out, the M&amp;M'S wrapper designs in the U.S. were redone, from the old design, used from 2004-early 2010.

==Color changes in chocolate M&amp;M's== &lt;!-- change section ref in intro if section is renamed --&gt;
The following is a summary of the changes to the colors of the flagship ([[milk chocolate]]) flavor of M&amp;M's, the only filling manufactured since the beginning of the brand.  From 1941 until 1987, each package contained M&amp;M's in five different colors; when red M&amp;M's were reintroduced in 1987, they were added as a sixth color instead of replacing any of the existing colors.
&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;timeline&gt;
ImageSize = width:800 height:200
PlotArea = left:50 bottom:60 top:0 right:50
Alignbars = justify
DateFormat  = yyyy
Period = from:1940 till:2010
TimeAxis = orientation:horizontal format:yyyy

ScaleMajor = unit:year increment:5 start:1940

Colors =
  id:brown   value:rgb(0.5, 0.25, 0)

LineData =
  at:1945 color:black layer:back
  at:1955 color:black layer:back
  at:1965 color:black layer:back
  at:1975 color:black layer:back
  at:1985 color:black layer:back
  at:1995 color:black layer:back
  at:2005 color:black layer:back
BarData =
  bar:mmbrown  text:&quot;Brown&quot;
  bar:mmyellow text:&quot;Yellow&quot;
  bar:mmgreen  text:&quot;Green&quot;
  bar:mmred1   text:&quot;Red&quot;
  bar:mmviolet text:&quot;Violet&quot;
  bar:mmtan    text:&quot;Tan&quot;
  bar:mmorange text:&quot;Orange&quot;
  bar:mmblue   text:&quot;Blue&quot;

PlotData =
  width:10 textcolor:black align:left anchor:from shift:(10,-4)
  bar:mmbrown  from:1941 till:end color:brown
  bar:mmyellow from:1941 till:end color:yellow
  bar:mmgreen  from:1941 till:end color:green
  bar:mmviolet from:1941 till:1949 color:lightpurple
  bar:mmred1   from:1941 till:1976 color:red
  bar:mmred1   from:1987 till:end color:red
  bar:mmtan    from:1949 till:1995 color:tan1
  bar:mmorange from:1976 till:end color:orange
  bar:mmblue   from:1995 till:end color:blue
&lt;/timeline&gt; 1941-2011
&lt;/div&gt;

[[File:M&amp;M's World Las Vegas.jpg|right|thumb|224px|[[M&amp;M's World]] on the [[Las Vegas Strip]].]]

==Related brands==
Related candy brands from Mars include [[Minstrels (chocolate)|Minstrels]], [[Revels (confectionery)|Revels]], [[Skittles (confectionery)|Skittles]], and [[Treets]]; similar products from other companies include [[Smarties]], Pebbles and several products from [[The Hershey Company]]: [[Hershey's Drops]], [[Reese's Pieces]], [[Hershey's Dark]] Chocolate Pieces, [[York Peppermint Pattie|York]] Pieces, [[Almond Joy]] Pieces and the long-discontinued [[Hershey-ets]].  Similar candies are used as an ingredient in some brands of [[trail mix]].

[[M&amp;M's World]] specialty shops have been established in some locations.  Several [[M&amp;M's video games|M&amp;Ms-themed]] video games have been created.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|M&amp;M's}}
*[http://www.mms.com/ Official website]
*[http://us.mms.com/us/about/mmshistory/ The History of M&amp;M's Chocolates] from us.mms.com
*[http://www.mymms.com/ Personalized M&amp;M's] from mymms.com

{{Mars brands}}
{{Portal|United States}}
[[Category:Mars confectionery brands]]
[[Category:1941 introductions]]
[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]

[[cs:M&amp;M's]]
[[da:M&amp;M's]]
[[de:M&amp;M’s]]
[[es:M&amp;M's]]
[[fr:M&amp;M's]]
[[ko:M&amp;M's]]
[[id:M&amp;M's]]
[[it:M&amp;M's]]
[[he:M&amp;M's]]
[[la:M&amp;M's]]
[[lt:M&amp;M's]]
[[nl:M&amp;M's]]
[[ja:M&amp;M's]]
[[no:M&amp;M's]]
[[nn:M&amp;M’s]]
[[pl:M&amp;M's]]
[[pt:M&amp;M's]]
[[ru:M&amp;M's]]
[[simple:M&amp;M's]]
[[fi:M&amp;M’s]]
[[sv:M&amp;M's]]
[[zh:M&amp;M's]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
