<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="486709" ns="0" title="Browser wars"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Timeline of web browsers.svg|thumb|right|A timeline of web browsers.]]
[[File:Wikimedia browser share pie chart.png|frameless|right]]
'''Browser wars''' is a [[metaphor]]ical term that refers to competitions for dominance in [[Usage share of web browsers|usage share]] in the [[web browser]] marketplace. The term is often used to denote two specific rivalries: the competition that saw [[Microsoft]]'s [[Internet Explorer]] replace [[Netscape]]'s [[Netscape Navigator|Navigator]] as the dominant browser during the late 1990s and the erosion of Internet Explorer's market share since 2003 by a collection of emerging browsers including [[Mozilla Firefox]], [[Google Chrome]], [[Safari (web browser)|Safari]], and [[Opera (web browser)|Opera]].

== Background ==
{{update|section|date=March 2010|reason=This time is often referred as &quot;Mosaic Wars&quot;}}
[[File:Layout engine usage share-2009-01-07.svg|thumb|300px| Usage share as of Q2 2009 by percent of layout engines/web browsers]]

The [[World Wide Web]] is an [[Internet]]-based [[hypertext]] system invented in the late 1980s and early 1990s by [[Tim Berners-Lee]]. Berners-Lee wrote the first web browser [[WorldWideWeb]], later renamed Nexus, and released it for the [[NeXTstep]] platform  in 1991.

By the end of 1992 other browsers had appeared, many of them based on the [[libwww]] library. These included [[Unix]] browsers such as [[Line Mode Browser]], [[ViolaWWW]], [[Erwise]] and [[MidasWWW]], and [[MacWWW]]/Samba for the Mac. This created choice between browsers and hence the first real competition, especially on Unix.

== Mosaic wars ==
{{cquote|There are two ages of the Internet - before Mosaic, and after. The combination of Tim Berners-Lee's Web protocols, which provided connectivity, and Marc Andreesen's browser, which provided a great interface, proved explosive. In twenty-four months, the Web has gone from being unknown to absolutely ubiquitous
|4=A Brief History of Cyberspace
|5=Mark Pesce, ZDNet, October 15, 1995
}} 
Further browsers were released in 1993, including [[Cello (web browser)|Cello]], [[Arena (web browser)|Arena]], [[Lynx (web browser)|Lynx]], [[tkWWW]] and [[Mosaic (web browser)|Mosaic]]. The most influential of these was Mosaic, a multiplatform browser developed at [[National Center for Supercomputing Applications]] (NCSA). By October 1994, Mosaic was &quot;well on its way to becoming the world's standard interface&quot;, according to Gary Wolfe of ''[[Wired magazine|Wired]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/2.10/mosaic.html |title=The (Second Phase of the) Revolution Has Begun |month=October |year=1994 |accessdate=2006-12-16 |last=Wolfe |first=Gary |publisher=Wired Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several companies licensed Mosaic to create their own commercial browsers, such as [[AirMosaic]] and [[Spyglass Mosaic]]. One of the Mosaic developers, [[Marc Andreessen]], founded Mosaic Communications Corporation and created a new web browser named Mosaic Netscape. To resolve legal issues with NCSA, the company was renamed [[Netscape Communications Corporation]] and the browser Netscape Navigator. The Netscape browser improved on Mosaic's usability and reliability and was able to display pages as they loaded. By 1995, helped by the fact that it was free for non-commercial use, the browser dominated the emerging World Wide Web.

Other browsers launched during 1994 included [[IBM Web Explorer]], [[Navipress]], [[SlipKnot (web browser)|SlipKnot]], [[MacWeb]], and [[Browse (web browser)|Browse]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Berghel|first=Hal|title=Hal Berghel's Cybernautica|url=http://berghel.net/col-edit/cybernautica/jan-feb96/pcai961.php|accessdate=14 November 2010|date=2 April 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1995, Netscape faced new competition from [[OmniWeb]], [[WebRouser]], [[UdiWWW]], and Microsoft's [[Internet Explorer 1.0]], but continued to dominate the market.

==The first browser war==
&lt;!-- The below content is also available at
http://hljournal.blogspot.com/2008/01/browser-wars_21.html.
However, this is not copyright infringement; the content below existed on December 15, 2008, prior to the creation of said website. The website content is actually an un-cited extended quote from Wikipedia, not the other way around--&gt;
[[Image:Browser Wars.png|thumb|300px|Market share for several browsers between 1995 and 2010]]

By mid-1995 the World Wide Web had received a great deal of attention in [[popular culture]] and the [[mass media]]. Netscape Navigator was the most widely used web browser and [[Microsoft]] had licensed Mosaic to create Internet Explorer 1.0,&lt;ref name=&quot;bw&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/bwdaily/dnflash/january/new0122d.htm|title=MICROSOFT'S $8 MILLION GOODBYE TO SPYGLASS|accessdate=9 February 2011|first=Peter|last=Elstrom|date=22 January 1997|publisher=[[Bloomberg Businessweek]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;win&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.windowsitpro.com/article/news2/microsoft-and-spyglass-kiss-and-make-up.aspx|title=Microsoft and Spyglass kiss and make up|publisher=[[WindowsITPro]]|last=Thurrott|first=Paul|authorlink=Paul Thurrott|date=22 January 1997|accessdate=9 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; which it had released as part of the Microsoft [[Windows 95]] [[Microsoft Plus!|Plus!]] Pack in August.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windows/WinHistoryIE.mspx |title=Windows History: Internet Explorer History |publisher=Microsoft.com |date=2003-06-30 |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Internet Explorer 2.0]] was released as a free download three months later. Unlike Netscape Navigator it was available to all Windows users for free, even commercial companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/1996/apr96/iemompr.mspx|title=Microsoft Internet Explorer Web Browser Available on All Major Platforms, Offers Broadest International Support|publisher=Microsoft|date=30 April 1996|accessdate=9 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other companies later followed and gave their browsers away for free.&lt;ref name=&quot;pcgo&quot; /&gt; Both Netscape Navigator and competitor products like [[InternetWorks]], [[Quarterdeck Browser]], [[InterAp]], and [[WinTapestry]] were bundled with other applications to full [[internet suite]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;pcgo&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.well.com/user/oink/oinkxweb/snippets/g7-bxls/webwar3.htm|accessdate=25 February 2011|title=Web-Wars|journal=[[PC Week]]|date=20 February 1995|first=Jesse|last=Berst}}&lt;/ref&gt; New versions of Internet Explorer and Netscape (branded as [[Netscape Communicator]]) were released at a rapid pace over the following few years.

Development was rapid and new features were routinely added, including Netscape's [[JavaScript]] (subsequently replicated by Microsoft as [[JScript]]) and proprietary HTML tags such as &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;[[Blink element|blink]]&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;[[Marquee tag|marquee]]&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.

Internet Explorer began to approach feature parity with Netscape with version 3.0 (1996), which offered scripting support and the market's first commercial [[Cascading Style Sheets]] (CSS) implementation.

In October 1997, [[Internet Explorer 4.0]] was released. The release party in San Francisco featured a ten-foot-tall letter &quot;e&quot; logo. Netscape employees showing up to work the following morning found the giant logo on their front lawn, with a sign attached that read &quot;From the IE team ... We Love You&quot;. The Netscape employees promptly knocked it over and set a giant figure of their [[Mozilla]] dinosaur mascot atop it, holding a sign reading &quot;Netscape 72, Microsoft 18&quot; representing the market distribution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.snafu.de/tilman/mozilla/stomps.html |title=Mozilla stomps IE |publisher=Home.snafu.de |date=1997-10-02 |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Internet Explorer 4 changed the tides of the browser wars. It was integrated into Microsoft Windows, which IT professionals{{Who|date=October 2011}} and industry critics{{Who|date=October 2011}} considered technologically disadvantageous and an apparent exploitation of Microsoft's monopoly on the PC platform. Users were discouraged from using competing products because IE was &quot;already there&quot; on their PCs.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

During these releases it was common for web designers to display 'best viewed in Netscape' or 'best viewed in Internet Explorer' logos.  These images often identified a specific browser version and were commonly linked to a source from which the stated browser could be downloaded.  These logos generally recognized the divergence between the standards supported by the browsers and signified which browser was used for testing the pages. In response, supporters of the principle that web sites should be compliant with [[World Wide Web Consortium]] standards and hence viewable with any browser started the &quot;Viewable With Any Browser&quot; campaign, which employed its own logo similar to the partisan ones.

===Internet Explorer 5 &amp; 6===
{{Refimprove|section|date=October 2009}}
Microsoft had three strong advantages in the browser wars.

One was resources: Netscape began with about 80% market share and a good deal of public goodwill, but as a relatively small company deriving the great bulk of its income from what was essentially a single product (Navigator and its derivatives), it was financially vulnerable.  Netscape's total revenue never exceeded the interest income generated by Microsoft's cash on hand.  Microsoft's vast resources allowed IE to remain free as the enormous revenues from Windows were used to fund its development and marketing. Netscape was commercial software for businesses but provided for free for home and education users; Internet Explorer was provided as free for Windows users, cutting off a significant revenue stream: As it was told by Jim Barksdale, President and CEO of Netscape Communications: &quot;Very few times in warfare have smaller forces overtaken bigger forces...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.netvalley.com/cgi-bin/intval/net_history.pl?chapter=4 |title=Roads and Crossroads of the Internet History |work=NetValley.com|date= |accessdate=2011-02-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another advantage was that Microsoft Windows had over 90% share of the desktop operating system market. IE was bundled with every copy of Windows; therefore Microsoft was able to dominate the market share easily as customers had IE as a default.  In this time period, many new computer purchases were first computer purchases for home users or offices, and many of the users had never extensively used a web browser before, so had nothing to compare with and little motivation to consider alternatives; the great set of features they had gained in gaining access to the Internet and the World Wide Web at all made any modest differences in browser features or ergonomics pale in comparison.

During the [[United States Microsoft antitrust case]] in 1998, [[Intel]] vice president [[Steven McGeady]], a witness called by the government, said on the stand that a senior executive at Microsoft told him in 1995 of his company's intention to &quot;cut off Netscape's air supply&quot;. Microsoft attorney said that McGeady's testimony is not credible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/business/longterm/microsoft/stories/1998/microsoft111398.htm |title=Microsoft Attacks Credibility of Intel Exec |month=November |year=1998 |accessdate=2009-12-01 |last=Chandrasekaran |first=Rajiv |publisher=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; That same year, Netscape, the company, was acquired by [[AOL|America Online]] for [[USD]] $4.2&amp;nbsp;billion. Internet Explorer became the new dominant browser, attaining a peak of about 96% of the [[usage share of web browsers|web browser usage share]] during 2002, more than Netscape had at its peak.

The first browser war ended with Internet Explorer having no remaining serious competition for its market share.  This also brought an end to the rapid innovation in web browsers; until 2006 there was only one new version of Internet Explorer since [[Internet Explorer 6|version 6.0]] had been released in 2001. Internet Explorer 6.0 Service Pack 1 was developed as part of [[Windows XP SP1]], and integrated into [[Windows Server 2003]].  Further enhancements were made to Internet Explorer in [[Windows XP SP2]] (released in 2004), including a pop-up blocker and stronger default security settings against the installation of ActiveX controls.

===Consequences===
The browser wars encouraged three specific kinds of behavior among their combatants.

# ''Adding new features instead of fixing bugs:'' A web browser had to have more new features than its competitor, or else it would be considered to be &quot;falling behind.&quot; But with limited manpower to put towards development, this often meant that quality assurance suffered and that the software was released with serious bugs.
# ''Adding proprietary features instead of obeying standards:'' A web browser is expected to follow the standards set down by standards committees (for example, by adhering to the HTML specifications) in order to assure interoperability of the Web for all users.  But competition and innovation led to web browsers &quot;extending&quot; the standards with proprietary features (such as the HTML tags &amp;lt;font&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;[[marquee tag|marquee]]&amp;gt;, and &amp;lt;[[blink tag|blink]]&amp;gt;) without waiting for committee approval.  Sometimes these extensions produced useful features that were adopted by other browsers, such as the [[XMLHttpRequest]] technology that resulted in [[Ajax (programming)|Ajax]].
# ''Inadvertently creating security loopholes:'' In the race to add development features, the line between document and application is crossed, and the Active Content Exploit is born. This is because, whenever applications have been allowed to masquerade as documents (e.g. Master Mode, Office macros, etc.) anyone can slip malicious code into what is otherwise a trustworthy format. As a virus scanner can only detect a virus that is old enough to be catalogued (usually more than 48 hours), it cannot protect against a [[zero day attack]]. Thus this blurring of the boundary between application and document creates an easy access point that is the basis for delivery of nearly all of today's [[drive-by download]]s and auto-loading [[malicious code]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

Support for web standards was severely weakened. For years, innovation in web development stagnated as developers had to use obsolete and unnecessarily complex techniques to ensure their pages would render properly in Netscape Navigator and Internet Explorer. Netscape Navigator 4 and IE6 lacked full compliance with several [[W3C|standards]], including [[Cascading Style Sheets|CSS]] and the [[Portable Network Graphics|PNG]] image format.

On February 2, 2008 the last update to [[Netscape Navigator 9]] was released, based on [[Mozilla Firefox 2]]. However, it never regained its market share. Netscape was discontinued on March 1, 2008.

==The second browser war==
[[File:Usage share of alternative web browsers (Source StatCounter).svg|thumb|Usage share of non-IE web browsers according to [[StatCounter]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser-ww-monthly-200807-201106  Usage share of non-IE web browsers according to [[StatCounter]]]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Wikipedia Main Page in Firefox 2.0.0.12.png|thumb|Firefox 2.0, shown here was released in October 2006]]

After the defeat of Navigator by [[Internet Explorer]], Netscape open-sourced their browser code, and entrusted it to the newly formed non-profit Mozilla Foundation—a primarily community-driven project to create a successor to Netscape. Development continued for several years with little widespread adoption until a stripped-down browser-only version of the full suite was created, which included features, such as tabbed browsing and a separate search bar, that had previously only appeared in [[Opera (web_browser)|Opera]]. The browser-only version was initially named ''Phoenix'', but because of trademark issues that name was changed, first to ''Firebird'', then to ''Firefox''. This browser became the focus of the Mozilla Foundation's development efforts and Mozilla Firefox 1.0 was released on November 9, 2004. Since then it has continued to gain an increasing share of the browser market, until a peak in [[2010]], after which it has remained largely stable.

In 2003, Microsoft announced that Internet Explorer 6 Service Pack 1 would be the last [[standalone software|standalone]] version of its browser. Future enhancements would be dependent on [[Windows Vista]], which would include new tools such as the [[Windows Presentation Foundation|WPF]] and [[Extensible Application Markup Language|XAML]] to enable developers to build extensive Web applications.

In response, in April 2004, the [[Mozilla Foundation]] and [[Opera Software]] joined efforts to develop new open technology standards which add more capability while remaining backward-compatible with existing technologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.w3.org/2004/04/webapps-cdf-ws/papers/opera.html |title=Position Paper for the W3C Workshop on Web Applications and Compound Documents |publisher=W3.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The result of this collaboration was the [[Web Hypertext Application Technology Working Group|WHATWG]], a working group devoted to the fast creation of new standard definitions that would be submitted to the [[World Wide Web Consortium|W3C]] for approval.

===2006–2007===

On February 15, 2005, Microsoft announced that [[Internet Explorer 7]] would be available for Windows XP SP2 and later versions of Windows by mid-2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.msdn.com/ie/archive/2005/02/15/373104.aspx |title=IEBlog : IE7 |publisher=Blogs.msdn.com |date=2005-02-15 |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The announcement introduced the new version of the browser as a major upgrade over Internet Explorer 6 SP1.

Opera had been a long-time small player in the browser wars, known for introducing innovative features such as tabbed browsing and mouse gestures, as well as being lightweight but [[feature-rich]]. The software, however, was commercial, which hampered its adoption compared to its free rivals until 2005, when the browser became [[freeware]]. On June 20, 2006, Opera Software released [[Opera 9]] including an integrated source viewer, a [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]] client implementation and widgets. It was the first Windows browser to pass the [[Acid2]] test. [[Opera Mini]], a mobile browser, has significant mobile market share as well as being available on the [[Nintendo DS]] and [[Wii]].

On October 18, 2006, Microsoft released Internet Explorer 7. It included tabbed browsing, a search bar, a [[phishing]] filter, and improved support for Web standards — all features already familiar to Opera and Firefox users. Microsoft distributed Internet Explorer 7 to [[Windows Genuine Advantage|genuine Windows users]] (WGA) as a high priority update through [[Windows Update]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Evers |first=Joris |url=http://news.com.com/Microsoft+tags+IE+7+high+priority+update/2100-7350_3-6098500.html |title=Microsoft tags IE 7 'high priority' update &amp;#124; CNET News.com |publisher=News.com.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Typical market share analysis showed only a slow uptake of Internet Explorer 7 and Microsoft decided to drop the requirement for WGA and made Internet Explorer 7 available to all Windows users in October 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.msdn.com/ie/archive/2007/10/04/internet-explorer-7-update.aspx |title=IEBlog: Internet Explorer 7 Update |publisher=Blogs.msdn.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 24, 2006, Mozilla released Mozilla Firefox 2.0. It included the ability to reopen recently closed tabs, a session restore feature to resume work where it had been left after a crash, a phishing filter and a spell-checker for text fields.

In 2002 Apple created a [[software fork|fork]] of the open-source [[KHTML]] and [[KJS (KDE)|KJS]] layout and javascript engines from the [[KDE]] project [[Konqueror]] browser, explaining that those would provide easier development than other technologies by virtue of being small (fewer than 140,000 [[lines of code]]), cleanly designed and standards compliant,&lt;ref name=&quot;macport&quot;&gt;KDE KFM-Devel mailing list &quot;[http://lists.kde.org/?l=kfm-devel&amp;m=104197092318639&amp;w=2 (fwd) Greetings from the Safari team at Apple Computer]&quot;, January 7, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;  now known as [[WebKit]] project. A  Safari browser was first shipped with [[Mac OS X v10.3]]. On June 13, 2003 Microsoft  said it was discontinuing their browser on the Mac platform. On June 6, 2007, Apple released their initial beta version of Safari for Microsoft Windows.

On December 19, 2007, Microsoft announced that an internal build of Internet Explorer 8 has passed the [[Acid2]] CSS test in &quot;IE8 standards mode&quot; – the last of the major browsers to do so.

On December 28, 2007, Netscape announced that support for its Mozilla-derived Netscape Navigator would be discontinued on February 1, 2008, suggesting its users migrate to Mozilla Firefox.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://blog.netscape.com/2007/12/28/end-of-support-for-netscapeweb-browsers/|title= The Netscape Blog|accessdate=2007-12-28 |work= Netscape, AOL}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, on January 28, 2008, Netscape announced that support would be extended to March 1, 2008, and mentioned [[Flock (web browser)|Flock]], alongside Firefox, as an alternative to its users.

===2008–2010===
{{Browser marketshare|align=right}}
[[File:Usage share of web browsers (Source StatCounter).svg|left|thumb|[[Usage share of web browsers]] according to [[StatCounter]].]]
[[File:INT BROWSERS USED.png|thumb|left|International usage share of web browsers, 2002–2011.]]
Mozilla released [[Mozilla Firefox 3|Firefox 3.0]] on June 17, 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://developer.mozilla.org/devnews/index.php/2008/06/11/coming-tuesday-june-17th-firefox-3/
|title=Coming Tuesday, June 17th: Firefox 3
|publisher=Mozilla Developer Center
|accessdate=2009-10-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt; with performance improvements, and other new features. [[Mozilla Firefox 3.5|Firefox 3.5]] followed on June 30, 2009 with further performance improvements, native integration of audio and video, and more privacy features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.mozilla-europe.org/en/press/2009/06/30/1293-mozilla-advances-the-web-with-firefox-35
|title=Mozilla Advances the Web with Firefox 3.5
|publisher=Mozilla Europe and Mozilla Foundation
|accessdate=2009-10-12
}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Countries by most used web browser.png|thumb|Most used web browser by country in September 2011:&lt;br&gt;
{{Legend|blue|[[Internet Explorer]]}}
{{Legend|orange|[[Firefox]]}}
{{Legend|#00ff00|[[Google Chrome]]}}
{{Legend|red|[[Opera (web browser)|Opera]]}}according to [http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser-ww-monthly-201103-201103-bar Statcounter] ]]

[[Google]] released the [[Google Chrome|Chrome]] browser for Microsoft Windows on December 11, 2008, using the same WebKit rendering engine as Safari and a faster JavaScript engine called V8. An open sourced version for the Windows, Mac OS X and Linux platforms was released under the name [[Chromium (web browser)|Chromium]].  According to Net Applications, Chrome had gained a 3.6% usage share by October 2009. After the release of the beta for Mac OS X and Linux, the market share had increased rapidly.&lt;ref name=&quot;market-share&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://marketshare.hitslink.com/browser-market-share.aspx?qprid=0
| title = Browser market share
| accessdate = 2009-12-30
| date= December 30, 2009
| publisher = Net Applications
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 19, 2009, Microsoft released [[Internet Explorer 8]], which added [[Selection-based search|accelerators]], improved privacy protection, a compatibility mode for pages designed for Internet Explorer 7&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/newsroom/windows/factsheets/ie8fs.mspx |title=Window Internet Explorer 8 Fact Sheet |date=March 2009|publisher=[[Microsoft]]|accessdate=26 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and improved support for various web standards.

During December 2009 and January 2010, ''[[StatCounter]]'' reported that its statistics indicated that Firefox 3.5 was the most popular browser, when counting individual browser versions, passing Internet Explorer 7 and 8 by a small margin.&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;[http://blog.seattlepi.com/microsoft/archives/188906.asp?from=blog_last3 Firefox 3.5 is world's most popular browser, StatCounter says], Nick Eaton. seattlepi blogs. 2009-12-21. Retrieved 2009-12-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser_version-ww-monthly-200902-201006|title=StatCounter global stats – Top 12 browser versions|publisher=StatCounter|accessdate=12 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is the first time a global statistic has reported that a non-Internet Explorer browser version has exceeded the top Internet Explorer version in usage share since the fall of Netscape Navigator. This feat, which GeekSmack called the &quot;dethron[ing of] Microsoft and its Internet Explorer 7 browser,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://geeksmack.net/internet/910-firefox-35-surpasses-ie7-market-share |title=Firefox 3.5 surpasses IE7 market share |publisher=Geeksmack.net |date=2009-12-22 |accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; can largely be attributed to the fact that it came at a time when IE 8 was replacing IE 7 as the dominant Internet Explorer version. No more than two months later IE 8 had established itself as the most popular browser version, a position which it still holds as of March 2011. It should also be noted that other major statistics, such as [[Net Applications]], never report any non-IE browser version as having a higher usage share than the most popular Internet Explorer version, although Firefox 3.5 was reported as the third most popular browser version between December 2009 and February 2010, to be replaced by Firefox 3.6 since April 2010, each ahead of IE7 and behind IE6 and IE8.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://marketshare.hitslink.com/browser-market-share.aspx?qprid=3 |title=Browser market share trend |publisher=Marketshare.hitslink.com |accessdate=2010-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 21, 2010, Mozilla released [[Mozilla Firefox 3.6]], which allows support for a new type of theme display, 'Personas', which allows users to change Firefox's appearance with a single click. Version 3.6 also improves JavaScript performance, overall browser responsiveness and startup times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/3.6/releasenotes/ |title=Mozilla Firefox 3.6 Release Notes |publisher=Mozilla.com |date=2010-01-21 |accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2010, StatCounter reported that Internet Explorer had for the first time dropped below 50% market share to 49.87% in their figures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser-ww-monthly-200909-201009|title=Microsoft Internet Explorer browser falls below 50% of worldwide market for first time|publisher=StatCounter|accessdate=7 october 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, StatCounter reported Internet Explorer 8's first drop in usage share in the same month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser_version-ww-monthly-200910-201010|title=StatCounter Browser Versions form Oct 09 to Oct 10|publisher=StatCounter|accessdate=9 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Race to HTML5===

On February 3, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 9]]. New features introduced include: support for [[WebGL]], Chrome Instant, and the Chrome Web Store.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://chrome.blogspot.com/2011/02/dash-of-speed-3d-and-apps.html |title=Google Chrome Blog |publisher=chrome.blogspot.com |date=2011-02-03 |accessdate=2010-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''StatCounter'' global market share figures were as follows for February 2011. Internet Explorer 45%, Firefox 30%, Chrome 17%, Safari 5%, and Opera 2%, leaving all the others sharing the remaining 1%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser-ww-monthly-201003-201102|title=StatCounter global stats – Top 5 browsers|publisher=StatCounter|accessdate=7 March 2011|quote=Hover mouse on the data points for figures}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 8, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 10]]. New features can be found on the blogspot release.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://googlechromereleases.blogspot.com/2011/03/chrome-stable-release.html |title=Google Chrome Blog |publisher=chrome.blogspot.com |date=2011-03-08 |accessdate=2011-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 14, 2011, Microsoft released [[Internet Explorer 9]].

On March 22, 2011, Mozilla released [[Firefox 4.0]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://groups.google.com/forum/?pli=1#!topic/mozilla.dev.planning/GKNHlW5Gk-s/|title=Damon Sicore announces possible Firefox 4.0 final launch date in the official Mozilla Google Groups page.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 4, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 11]]. 

On June 7, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 12]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://googlechromereleases.blogspot.com/2011/06/chrome-stable-release.html|title=Chrome Stable}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 21, 2011, Mozilla released [[Firefox 5.0]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.mozilla.com/blog/2011/06/21/mozilla-delivers-new-version-of-firefox-first-web-browser-to-support-do-not-track-on-multiple-platforms/|title=Mozilla Delivers New Version of Firefox – First Web Browser to Support Do Not Track on Multiple Platforms}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 2, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 13]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://googlechromereleases.blogspot.com/2011/08/stable-channel-update.html|title=Google Chrome Releases - Stable Channel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 16, 2011, Mozilla released [[Firefox 6.0]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/firefox-6-release-date-2011-8|title=Firefox 6 Is Launching Tuesday, Here's What You Need To Know}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 15, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 14]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://googlechromereleases.blogspot.com/2011/09/stable-channel-update_16.html|title=Chrome Stable Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 27, 2011, Mozilla released [[Firefox 7.0]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/heres-whats-new-in-firefox-7-2011-9|title=Here's What's New In Firefox 7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 25, 2011, Google released [[Chrome 15]].

On November 8, 2011 Mozilla released [[Firefox 8]].

===In development===

Microsoft's [[Internet Explorer 10]] which supports [[Windows 7]] or later.

Google's [[Google Chrome#Release history|Chrome]] 16 and Chrome 17, in Beta and Dev respectively.

Mozilla's [[Firefox 9]], [[Firefox 10]], and [[Firefox 11]], in Beta, Aurora (Alpha 2), and Nightly (Alpha 1) respectively.

Opera Software's Opera 12, in pre-Alpha.

==Other browser competition==
===Microsoft Windows===
Although its usage share has been dropping since the mid-2000s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Browser Stats|url=http://www.thecounter.com/stats/2004/June/browser.php|work=The Counter.Com|publisher=QuinStreet|accessdate=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Internet Explorer still has, as of January 2011, the largest [[usage share of web browsers|usage share]] on Microsoft Windows, with Mozilla Firefox the second most used web browser. Google Chrome, released in September 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/chrome/intl/en/why.html |title=Google Chrome |publisher=Google.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; is gaining ground in third place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net Applications&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Top Browser Share Trend|url=http://marketshare.hitslink.com/browser-market-share.aspx?qprid=1&amp;qptimeframe=M&amp;qpsp=121&amp;qpnp=25#|publisher=Net Applications|accessdate=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2008, [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] released Safari 3.1, began including it as a pre-selected update in the Apple Software Update program&lt;ref name=&quot;safari&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/26/technology/26firefox.html
| title = Browsers Are a Battleground Once Again
| accessdate = 2008-05-29
| date= created May 26, 2008
| publisher = The New York Times
| first=Brad
| last=Stone
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its market share on Windows tripled.&lt;ref name=&quot;safari-market-share&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://marketshare.hitslink.com/report.aspx?sample=13&amp;qprid=22&amp;qpdt=1&amp;qpct=5&amp;qptimeframe=M&amp;qpsp=100&amp;qpnp=12
| title = Apple's Gamble: Push Safari to Windows Users via Software Updates. Did it Work?
| accessdate = 2008-05-30
| date= created May 30, 2008
| publisher = Net Applications
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; It is now in fourth place followed by Opera.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net Applications&quot;/&gt; Other browsers based on Internet Explorer's [[Trident (layout engine)|Trident]] [[layout engine]], such as [[Maxthon]], included features like tabbed browsing and were once popular but fell out of use when IE began adding such features itself from version 7 onwards.

===Linux and Unix===
The Unix-based [[Konqueror]] browser is part of the [[KDE]] project and is the primary competitor against Mozilla-based browsers ([[Firefox]], Mozilla Application Suite/[[SeaMonkey]], [[Epiphany (web browser)|Epiphany]], [[Galeon]], etc.) for market share on Unix-like systems.
Konqueror's [[KHTML]] engine is an API for the KDE desktop. Derivative browsers and web-browsing functionality (for example, [[Amarok (audio)|Amarok]] has a Wikipedia sidebar that gives information about the current artist) based on KDE use KHTML.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://developer.kde.org/documentation/library/kdeqt/kde3arch/khtml/ |title=KDE 2 Architecture Overview – KDE's HTML Library |publisher=Developer.kde.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mac OS X===
Safari is Apple's web browser for Mac OS X, and also has the highest usage share on Mac OS X.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://weblogs.mozillazine.org/asa/archives/2008/12/market_share_by.html|title=market share by platform|last=Dotzler|first=Asa|date=December 6, 2008|publisher=Mozilla|accessdate=26 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The web browser is based on [[WebKit]], a derivative of the [[KHTML]] engine. Other Mac browsers including [[iCab]] (since 4.0), [[OmniWeb]] (since 4.5), and [[Shiira]], use the [[WebKit]] API, and many other Macintosh programs add web-browsing functionality through [[WebKit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macdevcenter.com/pub/a/mac/2004/01/23/webkit.html |title=BYOB: Build Your Own Browser |publisher=MacDevCenter.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mozilla Firefox and Opera Browser also have high usage on Mac OS X.

[[Camino]] is a Mozilla-based [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko]] browser for the Mac OS X platform, and uses Mac's native [[Cocoa (API)|Cocoa]] interface like Safari does, instead of Mozilla's [[XUL]] which is used in Firefox. It was initially developed by [[Dave Hyatt]], until he was hired by Apple to develop Safari.

===Embedded devices===
[[Opera Mini]] is a popular web browser on mobile devices such as most [[Java ME]] enabled internet connected phones and [[smartphone]]s because of its small [[Memory-footprint|footprint]]. It has also recently been released for the iPhone and iPod Touch. Opera Mobile for smartphones main competition is from [[Netfront]]. Sony developed a mobile browser for their [[PlayStation Portable|PSP]], using Netfront's codebase. Sony's [[PlayStation 3]] also includes a web browser. PC Site Viewer, the web browser included on many Japanese cellular phones, is based on Opera. In February, 2006 it was announced that [[Nintendo]] &quot;will release an add-on card&quot; with a version of Opera for the [[Nintendo DS]] ([[Nintendo DS Browser]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/4719570.stm |title=Technology &amp;#124; Nintendo DS looks beyond gamers |publisher=BBC News |date=2006-02-16 |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; This DS browser has since been criticized for its lack of Flash support and slowness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/802/802002p1.html |title=IGN: Nintendo DS Browser Review |publisher=Ds.ign.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opera is also used as a web browser on the [[Wii]] console.

[[Nokia]] released a [[WebKit]]-based browser in 2005,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.s60.com/life/newsevents/pressreleases/archive?action=archiveNews&amp;whatshot=0&amp;appweek=0&amp;hotNewsId=206 s60.com]&lt;/ref&gt; which comes with every [[Symbian]] [[S60 platform]]-based smartphone. On Nokia's N900 is MicroB, a Firefox derivate, preinstalled. It competes with Opera for the N900.

[[Windows Phone 7]] comes with a version of [[Internet Explorer Mobile]] with a rendering engine which [[Steve Ballmer]] said to be &quot;somewhere between Internet Explorer 7 and Internet Explorer 8&quot;. Microsoft plans to update the layout engine to that of Internet Explorer 9.

[[Windows Mobile]] comes with [[Internet Explorer Mobile]] by default and competes with Opera Mobile, Netfront, Iris, and Mozilla's [[Minimo]], and lately the [[Skyfire (web browser)|Skyfire]] browser (also available for [[Android (operating system)|Android]] and [[Symbian]]).

MobileSafari, Apple's browser based on WebKit/KHTML, comes with [[iPhone]], [[iPod Touch]] and the [[iPad]].

[[Android (operating system)|Android]], Google's open-source OS for mobile devices, uses a browser based on [[WebKit]]. Since March 2010, Opera Mini has been available for Android.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://my.opera.com/chooseopera/blog/2010/03/11/opera-mini-5-beta-for-android |title=Opera Mini 5 beta for Android |publisher=my.opera.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other browsers include Opera Mobile and Firefox 4.

== See also ==
* ''[[After the Software Wars]]''
* [[Comparison of web browsers]]
* [[Usage share of web browsers]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==

{{refbegin}}
* '''DOJ/Antitrust''': U.S. Department of Justice Antitrust Division. [http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/f1700/1763.htm Civil Action No. 98-1232 (Antitrust) Complaint, United States of America v. Microsoft Corporation]. May 18, 1998. Press release: [http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/public/press_releases/1998/1764.htm Justice Department Files Antitrust Suit Against Microsoft for Unlawfully Monopolizing Computer Software Markets]
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.w3schools.com/browsers/browsers_stats.asp Browser Statistics] – Month by month comparison spanning from 2002 and onward displaying the usage share of browsers among web developers.
* [http://www.upsdell.com/BrowserNews/stat.htm Browser Stats] – Chuck Upsdell's Browser Statistics
* [http://marketshare.hitslink.com/ Browser Stats] – Net Applications' Browser Statistics
* [http://gs.statcounter.com/ StatCounter Global Stats] – tracks the market share of browsers including mobile from over 4 billion monthly page views.
* [http://www.w3avenue.com/2009/03/24/browser-war-ria-future-of-web-development/ Browser war, RIA and future of web development]
* [http://www.evolt.org/article/Browser_Wars_II_The_Saga_Continues/25/60181/ Browser Wars II: The Saga Continues] – an article about the development of the browser wars
* [http://www.tomandmaria.com/tom/Writing/ProtocolsForProfitDRAFT.pdf Thomas Haigh, &quot;Protocols for Profit: Web and Email Technologies as Product and Infrastructure&quot; in The Internet &amp; American Business, eds. Ceruzzi &amp; Aspray, MIT Press, 2008]– business &amp; technological history of web browsers, online preprint
* [http://stephenbrooks.org/games/browserwars/ stephenbrooks.org – browserwars] – a multiplayer browser game, shows the logo of the browsers used

{{Early web browsers}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Browser Wars}}
[[Category:Web browsers]]
[[Category:Software wars]]

[[ar:حرب المتصفحات]]
[[ca:Guerra de navegadors]]
[[de:Browserkrieg]]
[[es:Guerra de navegadores]]
[[fr:Évolution de l'usage des navigateurs Web]]
[[ko:브라우저 전쟁]]
[[id:Perang peramban web]]
[[it:Guerra dei browser]]
[[he:מלחמת הדפדפנים]]
[[ka:ბრაუზერების ომი]]
[[hu:Böngészőháborúk]]
[[ml:ബ്രൗസർ യുദ്ധങ്ങൾ]]
[[nl:Browseroorlog]]
[[ja:ブラウザ戦争]]
[[pl:Historia przeglądarek internetowych]]
[[pt:Guerra dos navegadores]]
[[ru:Война браузеров]]
[[sl:Vojna brskalnikov]]
[[fi:Selainsodat]]
[[tr:Tarayıcı savaşları]]
[[zh:浏览器大战]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
