<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4892961" ns="0" title="Richard Whitney (artist)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:self portrait e.jpg|thumb|right|200px|&quot;Self Portrait&quot;, oil, 26 x 20, 1973.  Collection: [[Newark Museum]]]]
''' Richard Whitney''' ([[1946]]) is an [[United States|American]] painter born in [[New Hampshire]]. Whitney is a [[portrait]] and [[landscape art|landscape]] painter; his paintings currently hang in over 650 fine art collections worldwide.

==Background==
Whitney graduated [[Phi Beta Kappa]] from the [[University of New Hampshire]] in 1968.  He studied with [[Sidney F. Willis]] and [[R. H. Ives Gammell]].  He has been called &quot;a living master of the classical tradition&quot; by [[Sotheby’s]].

==Professional organizations==
[[Image:matinee.jpg|thumb|right|170px|Matinee]]
*[[Allied Artists of America]]
*[[American Artists' Professional League]]
*[[American Society of Portrait Artists]]
*[[American Society of Classical Realism]]
*[[Copley Society]]
*[[The Guild of Boston Artists]]
*[[National Arts Club]]
*[[Portrait Society of America]]
*[[Society of Illustrators]]

==Awards, honors==
''1970 - 1973''
*Three Grants - Elizabeth T. Greenshields' Memorial Foundation – Montreal

''1975''
*Third Gold Medal - Jordan Marsh Show - Boston

''1976''
*Merit Award – Springfield (MA) Art League National Exhibition
*Merit Award for Drawing – Sharon (NH) Arts Center Regional Exhibition
*Excellence Award in Traditional - Cape Cod Art Association All New England
*Exhibition Three Awards – Ogunquit (ME) Art Center National Exhibition
*Architects Award - New Hampshire Art Association Annual Exhibition
*Anonymous Award in Oil - Knickerbocker Artists National Exhibition – New York City

''1977''
*First Prize - Fitchburg (MA) Art Museum Regional Exhibition
*Best of Show, People's Choice Award - Sharon Arts Center Regional Exhibition
*[[Grumbacher]] Award in Oils - Academic Artists National Exhibition – New York City
*First in Oil - Cape Cod Art Association All New England Exhibition

''1978''
*Honorable Mention - Fitchburg Art Museum Regional Exhibition
*People's Choice Award - Sharon Arts Center Regional Exhibition
*Finalist - American Artist Magazine National Art Competition – New York City

''1979''
*First Prize - Fitchburg Art Museum Regional Exhibition
*Ezekial A. Straw Memorial Award - New Hampshire Art Association Exhibition

''1980''
*Yankee Sagendorph Award - Copley Society of Boston
*Honorable Mention - Jubilee 350 Competition for New England Artists - Boston
*The Crescent Gallery, Ltd. Award - Allied Artists National Exhibition – New York City

''1982''
*The [[Margaret Fitzhugh Browne]] Memorial Portrait Award - Copley Society of Boston

''1983''
*Grumbacher Gold Medal - Guild of Boston Artists Competition

''1984''
*Gold Medal - American Artist Professional League Grand National Exhibition – NYC
*Copley Master Award - Copley Society of Boston
*Juror's Choice Award – Springville (Utah) Museum of Art National Salon Show
*American Portrait Society Certification - Los Angeles

''1986''
*Juror's Choice Award - Springville Museum of Art National Salon Show
*Dole Award - American Artists Professional League Grand National Exhibition

''1987''
*Silver Medal - The Society of Illustrators' 29th Annual Exhibition – New York City
*A. Lassell Ripley Award - Guild of Boston Artists Competition
*Medal &quot;Benemerito&quot; - Catholic University of Portugal

''1989''
*Highest Bid - Copley Society of Boston Fundraising Auction

''1990''
*Commendation - Governor and Executive Council of New Hampshire
*Second Highest Bid - Copley Society of Boston Fundraising Auction

''1991''
*Ken Gore Memorial Award - Guild of Boston Artists Competition

''1992''
*Second Highest Bid – Copley Society of Boston Fundraising Auction
[[Image:rbreich.jpg|thumb|right|170px|The official portrait of Robert Reich hangs in the [[United States Department of Labor|Department of Labor]]]]
''1994''
*Merit Award for Painting – Sharon Arts Center Regional Exhibition

''1998''
*Highest Bid – Peterborough (NH) Arts Auction

''1999''
*R. H. Ives Gammell Award – Guild of Boston Artists Competition
*[[Robert B. Reich]] - Official Portrait

==Exhibits==
{{Empty section|date=May 2008}}

==Gallery of Work==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Gov_Hugh_Gallen.jpg|[[Hugh Gallen]]
Image:Gov_Judd_Gregg.jpg|[[Judd Gregg]]
Image:Nancyharrington1.jpg|[[Salem State College|Nancy D. Harrington]]
Image:Gov_John_King.jpg|John W. King
Image:Lkirkland.jpg|[[Lane Kirkland]]
Image:Michael J McGivney.jpg|[[Michael J. McGivney]]
Image:Sen_Thomas_J_McIntyre.jpg|[[Thomas J. McIntyre]]
Image:Cardinalhm.jpg|[[Humberto Sousa Medeiros]]
Image:Rbreich.jpg|[[Robert Reich]]
File:Romney portrait.jpg|[[Mitt Romney]]
Image:GovJohnSununu1.jpg|[[John H. Sununu]]
Image:Jwebb.jpg|[[James H. Webb]]
Image:Monadorch.jpg|Monadnock Orchard
Image:Matinee.jpg|Matinee
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==External links==
{{commons category|Richard Whitney}}
*[http://www.crescentpond.com Personal Website]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Whitney, Richard
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1946
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Whitney, Richard}}
[[Category:American painters]]
[[Category:Portrait artists]]
[[Category:Contemporary painters]]
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:University of New Hampshire alumni]]
[[Category:Artists from New Hampshire]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
