<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="490007" ns="0" title="Hot Autumn"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{oneref|date=June 2010}}
The '''Hot Autumn''' (''autunno caldo'' in Italian) of 1969–1970 was a massive series of strikes in the factories and industrial centers of [[Northern Italy]], during which workers demanded better pay and better conditions. Between 1969-1970 there were over 440 million hours of strikes alone. The decrease in flow of labour [[Human migration|migration]] from the [[Southern Italy|South]] had resulted in nearly [[full employment]] levels in the North, meaning that the previously under-paid and unhappy workforce started to flex its muscles.

Due to increased literacy levels and student discontent, students started agitating for reform and increased class consciousness. Workers joined in on this, and began to demand better pay. Many of them were being laid off because of increased efficiencies in factories. Higher class consciousness was not achieved, but more basic demands such as a 40 hour work week, and increased pay were. &lt;ref&gt;A History of Contemporary Italy: Society and Politics, 1943-1988
 By Paul Ginsborg&lt;/ref&gt;

The reasons for discontent varied - while the usual pay and conditions were a factor, it's fair to say that tensions were increased by the fact that much of the workforce had migrated from the much poorer south. They were generally unhappy at the society that had forced them to leave their homes in search of work and wanted to get back at the employers that had exploited the low average wages for so many years.

The phrase &quot;hot autumn&quot; has since been applied in the [[Italy|Italian]] [[Mass media|press]] to describe other autumns with significant amounts of strikes. In the later years, such season strikes have more often been directed against the government's budget.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Workerism]]
* [[Autonomism]]
* [[Lotta Continua]]
* [[Potere Operaio]]

'''Similar periods in other countries around the same time:'''
* [[Long Hot Summer of 1967]]
* [[Winter of Discontent]]
* [[May 1968 in France]]

==External Links==
[http://libcom.org/gallery/photo-gallery-hot-autumn-italy-1969 Italy Hot Autumn Photo Gallery]

[http://libcom.org/tags/italy-60s-70s Italy 60s-70s collection at the Libertarian Communist Library]

[[Category:20th century in Italy]]
[[Category:Labor disputes in Italy]]
[[Category:1969 in Italy]]
[[Category:1970 in Italy]]
[[Category:Years of Lead (Italy)]]


{{Italy-hist-stub}}
{{Labor-dispute-stub}}

[[it:Autunno caldo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
