<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="49069" ns="0" title="Pope Eugene IV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Christian leader | type = Pope|
English name=Eugene IV|
image=PapstEugen.jpg|
birth_name=Gabriele Condulmer|
term_start=March 3, 1431|
term_end=February 23, 1447|
predecessor=[[Pope Martin V|Martin V]]|
successor=[[Pope Nicholas V|Nicholas V]]
| ordination = 
| ordinated_by =
| consecration =1408
| consecrated_by = 
| cardinal =9 May, 1408|
birth_date=1383|
birth_place= [[Venice]], [[Republic of Venice]] |
dead=dead|death_date={{death date|1447|2|23|mf=y}}&lt;/br&gt;(aged 63-64)|
death_place=[[Rome]], [[Papal States]]|
other=Eugenius}}
{{Infobox popestyles
|image      = C o a Eugenio IV.svg 
|dipstyle   = [[His Holiness]]
|offstyle   = Your Holiness
|relstyle   = Holy Father
|deathstyle = None
|}}

'''Pope Eugene IV''' (1383 &amp;ndash; February 23, 1447), born '''Gabriele Condulmer''', was pope from March 3, 1431, to his death.

==Biography==
He was born in [[Venice]] to a rich merchant family, a [[Correr]] on his mother's side. Condulmer entered the [[Order of Saint Augustine]] at the monastery of St. George in his native city. At the age of twenty-four he was appointed by his uncle [[Pope Gregory XII]] (1406&amp;ndash;15), as [[Bishop of Siena]], and came into prominence. In Siena, the political class objected to a 24-year old bishop who was a foreigner. Therefore, the issue was not pressed, and he resigned the appointment, becoming instead his uncle's papal treasurer, [[protonotary]] and [[Cardinal Priest]] of [[Basilica of San Clemente|San Clemente]]. [[Pope Martin V]] named him Cardinal Priest of [[Basilica di Santa Maria in Trastevere]]. 

He made himself useful to [[Pope Martin V]] (1417&amp;ndash;31) and was [[Papal conclave, 1431|quickly elected to succeed him]]. Eugene was crowned as Eugene IV at [[St. Peter's Basilica|St. Peter's]], March 11, 1431. By a written agreement made before his election he agreed with the cardinals to distribute to them one-half of all the revenues of the Church and promised to consult with them on all questions of importance, both spiritual and temporal. Upon taking the Papal Chair, Eugene IV took violent measures against the numerous [[Colonna]] relations of his predecessor, Pope Martin V (Ottone Colonna), who had rewarded his numerous clan with castles and lands. This at once involved him in a serious contest with the powerful house of Colonna that nominally supported the local rights of [[Rome]] against the interests of the Papacy. A truce was soon arranged. 

===Conciliar reform===
{{refimprove section|date=March 2011}}
{{Main|The Council of Florence}}
[[File:Pio Joris - La fuga di Papa Eugenio IV.jpg|200px|thumb|right|Painting of Pope Eugene rowing down the Tiber escaping Rome]]
But by far the most important feature of Eugene IV's pontificate was the great struggle between the Pope and the [[Council of Basel]] (1431&amp;ndash;39), the final embodiment of the [[Conciliar movement]]. On July 23, 1431, his legate, [[Giuliano Cesarini]], opened the council, which had been convoked by Martin V, but, distrustful of its purposes and emboldened by the small attendance, the pope issued a bill on December 18, 1431, dissolving the council and calling a new one to meet in eighteen months at [[Bologna]]. The council resisted this premature expression of papal prerogative, as it appeared to the majority of them. Eugene IV's action gave some weight to the contention that the [[Curia]] was opposed to any authentic measures of reform. The council refused to dissolve; instead they renewed the resolutions by which the [[Council of Constance]] had declared a council superior to the Pope, and cited Eugene IV to appear at Basel. A compromise was arranged by [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor]], who had been crowned emperor at Rome on May 31, 1433. By its terms the Pope recalled his [[papal bull|bull]] of dissolution, and, reserving all the rights of the [[Holy See]], acknowledged the council as [[ecumenical]] (December 15, 1433) except for the initial unapproved sessions which contained [[canon law|canons]] which exalted conciliar authority above that of the pope. The pope agreed to name presidents to lead the council.

These concessions also were due to the invasion of the [[Papal States]] by the former Papal [[condottiero]] [[Niccolò Fortebraccio]] and the troops of [[Filippo Maria Visconti]] led by [[Niccolò Piccinino]], in retaliation to Eugenius's support to Florence and Venice against Milan (see also [[Wars in Lombardy]]). This situation led also to establishment of an insurrectionary [[republic]] at Rome, controlled by the [[Colonna family]]. In early June, disguised in the robes of a Benedictine [[monk]], he was rowed down the center of the [[Tiber]], pelted by stones from either bank, to a [[Florence|Florentine]] vessel waiting to pick him up at [[Ostia Antica (archaeological site)|Ostia]]. The city was restored to obedience by [[Giovanni Vitelleschi]], the militant Bishop of [[Recanati]], in the following October. In August 1435 a peace treaty was signed at Ferrara by the various belligerents. The Pope moved to [[Bologna]] in April 1436. His condottieri [[Francesco Sforza]] and Vitelleschi in the meantime reconquered much of the Papal States. Traditional papal enemies such as the [[Prefetti di Vico]] were destroyed, while the Colonna were reduced to obedience after the destruction of their stronghold in [[Palestrina]] (August 1436).

[[File:Portrait du pape Eugène IV.jpg|thumb|left|Portrait of Pope Eugenius IV, after [[Jean Fouquet]].]]

Meanwhile the struggle with the council sitting at Basel broke out anew. Eugene IV at length convened a rival council at [[Ferrara]] on January 8, 1438, and [[excommunicated]] the [[prelate]]s assembled at Basel. The result was that the Council of Basel suspended him on January 24, 1438, then formally deposed him as a [[heresy|heretic]] on June 25, 1439, and in the following November elected the ambitious [[Amadeus VIII of Savoy|Amadeus VIII, Duke of Savoy]], [[antipope]] under the name of [[Felix V]]. The conduct of [[France]] and [[Germany]] seemed to warrant this action, for [[Charles VII of France]] had introduced the decrees of the Council of Basel, with slight changes, into France through the [[Pragmatic Sanction of Bourges]] (July 7, 1438), and the [[Diet of Mainz]] had deprived the Pope of most of his rights in the Empire (March 26, 1439). 

At Florence, where the council of Ferrara had been transferred as a result of an outbreak of the plague, a union with the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] was effected in July 1439, which, as the result of political necessities, proved but a temporary bolster to the papacy's prestige.

This union was followed by others of even less stability. Eugene IV signed an agreement with the [[Armenia]]ns on November 22, 1439, and with a part of the [[Jacobite (Orthodox)|Jacobites]] in 1443, and in 1445 he received the [[Nestorian Church|Nestorians]] and the [[Maronites]]. He did his best to stem the [[Ottoman Empire|Turkish]] advance, pledging one-fifth of the papal income to the [[crusade]] which set out in 1443, but which met with overwhelming defeat at the [[Battle of Varna]]. Cardinal Cesarini, the papal legate, perished in the rout. 

His rival, Felix V, meanwhile, obtained small recognition, even in the Empire. Eventually Frederick III, king of the Romans, moved toward acceptance of Eugenius. The king's ablest adviser, the humanist Aeneas Sylvius Piccolomini, who was later to be [[Pope Pius II]], made peace with Eugene IV in 1442. The Pope's recognition of the claim to [[Naples]] of King [[Alfonso V of Aragon]] (treaty of [[Terracina]], signed by Eugenius at Siena somewhat later) withdrew the last important support from the council of Basel. In 1442 Eugenius, Alfonso and Visconti sent [[Niccolò Piccinino]] to reconquer the March of [[Ancona]] from Francesco Sforza, but the defeat of the allied army at the [[battle of Montolmo|Montolmo]] pushed the Pope to reconcile with Sforza.

So enabled, Eugene IV made a victorious entry into Rome on September 28, 1443, after an exile of nearly ten years. 

His protests against the Pragmatic Sanction of Bourges were ineffectual, but by means of the [[Concordat of the Princes]], negotiated by Piccolomini with the electors in February 1447, the whole of [[Germany]] declared against the antipope. This agreement was completed only after Eugene's death.

===Slavery===
Christianity had gained many converts in the [[Canary Islands]] by the early 1430s. However, the ownership of the lands had been the subject of dispute between [[Portugal]] and the [[Kingdom of Castille]]. The lack of effective control had resulted in periodic raids on the islands to procure slaves. Pope Eugene IV was concerned that the enslavement of newly baptized Christians would impede the spread of Christianity and therefore issued a Papal Bull, &quot;Creator Omnium&quot;, on December 17, 1434.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Raiswell, p. 260&quot;&gt;Richard Raiswell, p. 260&lt;/ref&gt;

Eugenius excommunicated anyone who enslaved newly converted Christians but no protection was offered to those who declined to become Christians. Historian Richard Raiswell&lt;ref&gt;http://www.upei.ca/history/rraiswell&lt;/ref&gt; sees this as a significant turning point because before this Canon Law had only sanctioned slavery in the context of a just war and un-baptized captives, but with the issuing of this bull the only protection offered was if the person became a Christian. 

Portuguese soldiers continued to raid the islands during 1435 and Eugene issued a further edict [[Sicut Dudum]] that prohibited wars being waged against the islands and affirming the ban on enslavement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard Raiswell, p. 260&quot;/&gt; Eugenius condemned the enslavement of the peoples of the newly colonized Canary Islands and, under pain of excommunication, ordered all such slaves to be immediately set free.&lt;ref&gt;Cardinal Avery Dulles, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Joel S Panzer (2008) views &quot;Sicut Dudum&quot; as a significant condemnation of slavery, issued sixty years before the Europeans found the New World.&lt;ref&gt;Panzer, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The prohibitions and ecclesiastical sanctions of Sicut Dudum related to the newly converted.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''Slavery and the Catholic Church&quot;'', John Francis Maxwell, p. 51, Barry Rose Publishers, 1975&lt;/ref&gt; Eugene tempered Sicut Dudum with another bull (15 September 1436) due to the complaints made by [[Edward of Portugal|King Edward of Portugal]], now allowing the Portuguese to conquer any unconverted parts of the Canary Islands. According to Raiswell (1997) any Christian would be protected by the earlier edict but the un-baptized were implicitly allowed to be enslaved.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Raiswell, p. 260 &amp; Sued-Badillo, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

Following the arrival of the first African slaves in Lisbon during 1441, [[Henry the Navigator|Prince Henry]] asked Eugenius to designate Portugal's raids along the West African coast as a crusade, a consequence of which would be the legitimization of enslavement for captives taken during the crusade. On December 19, 1442, Eugene replied by issuing &quot;Illius qui&quot; in which he granted full remission of sins to those who took part in any expeditions against the Saracens.&lt;ref&gt;Raiswell, p. 261&lt;/ref&gt; Davidson (1961) asserts that &quot;In Christianity as in Islam...the heathen was expendable.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The African Slave Trade&quot;, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

Richard Raiswell argues that the bulls of Eugene helped in some way the development of thought which perceived the enslavement of Africans by the Portuguese and later Europeans  &quot;as dealing a blow for Christendom&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The Historical encyclopedia of world slavery&quot;, Richard Raiswell, p. 261&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death and legacy===
[[File:Papa Eugenio IV.jpg|right|200px|thumb|Statue of Pope Eugene at the [[Florence Cathedral]]]]
Although his pontificate had been so stormy and unhappy that he is said to have regretted on his deathbed that he ever left his [[monastery]], nevertheless Eugene IV's victory over the council of Basel and his efforts on behalf of church unity contributed greatly to the breakdown of the conciliar movement and restored the papacy to a semblance of the dominant position it had held before the [[Western Schism]] (1378&amp;ndash;1417).  This victory had been gained, however, by making concessions to the princes of Europe.  Thereafter, the papacy had to depend more for its revenues on the [[Papal States]].

Eugene IV was dignified in demeanour, but inexperienced and vacillating in action and excitable in temper. Bitter in his hatred of [[heresy]], he nevertheless displayed great kindness to the poor. He laboured to reform the [[monasticism|monastic]] orders, especially the [[Franciscan]]s, and was never guilty of [[nepotism]]. Although austere in his private life, he was a sincere friend of [[art]] and learning, and in 1431 he re-established the [[university]] at Rome. He also consecrated the [[Florence Cathedral]] in  March 25, 1436. Eugene was buried at Saint Peter's by the [[list of papal tombs|tomb of Pope Eugenius III]], the former pupil of [[Bernard of Clairvaux]]. Later his tomb was transferred in [[San Salvatore in Lauro]] - a parish church on the other bank of the [[Tiber River]].

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==References==
*{{1911}}
*{{Catholic|wstitle=Pope Eugene IV}}
*{{cite book|first=Claudio|last=Rendina|title=I capitani di ventura|publisher=Newton Compton|location=Rome|year=1994|pages=355}}
* ''The Historical Encyclopedia of World slavery'', Contributor Richard Raiswell, Editor Junius P. Rodriguez, ABC-CLIO, 1997, ISBN 0874368855
* ''Christopher Columbus and the enslavement of the Amerindians in the Caribbean. (Columbus and the New World Order 1492&amp;ndash;1992).'', Sued-Badillo, Jalil, Monthly Review. Monthly Review Foundation, Inc. 1992. HighBeam Research. 10 August 2009
*''Development or Reversal?'', Cardinal Avery Cardinal Dulles, S.J., First Things Magazine, October 2005 [http://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/01/development-or-reversal-37]
*''The Popes and Slavery'' Father Joel S Panzer, The Church In History Centre, 22 April 2008 [http://www.churchinhistory.org/pages/booklets/slavery.pdf], retrieved 9 August 2009
*''A violent evangelism'', Luis N. Rivera, Luis Rivera Pagán [http://www.synodne.org/article.php/20070507103958523/print], Westminster John Knox Press, 1992, ISBN 0664253679
*''The African Slave Trade'', Basil Davidson, James Currey Publishers, 1961, ISBN 0852557981
*''A successful defeat. Eugenius IV's Struggle with the Council of Basel for Ultimate Authority in the Church, 1431/1449'', M. Decaluwe, Brepols Publishers, 2010, ISBN 978-90-74461-73-3

==External links==
{{Commons category|Eugenius IV}}
{{wikisource author|Eugenius IV}}
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05601a.htm Pope Eugenius IV in the Catholic Encyclopaedia]

{{s-start}}
{{s-rel|ca}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Pope Martin V|Martin V]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Pope]]|years=1431&amp;ndash;47}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Pope Nicholas V|Nicholas V]]}}
{{end}}

{{Popes}}
{{Catholicism}} 
{{History of the Catholic Church}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Eugenius 4
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1383
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Venice]], [[Republic of Venice]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = February 23, 1447
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Rome]], [[Papal States]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Eugenius 4}}
[[Category:Popes]]
[[Category:Italian popes]]
[[Category:15th-century Roman Catholic bishops]]
[[Category:15th-century Italian people]]
[[Category:Augustinian friars|Eugenius 4, Pope]]
[[Category:People from Venice (city)]]
[[Category:1383 births]]
[[Category:1447 deaths]]
[[Category:Cardinal-nephews]]
[[Category:Renaissance Papacy]]
[[Category:Christians of the Crusade of Varna]]

[[af:Pous Eugenius IV]]
[[be:Яўген IV, Папа Рымскі]]
[[br:Ujan IV]]
[[bg:Евгений IV]]
[[ca:Eugeni IV]]
[[cs:Evžen IV.]]
[[de:Eugen IV.]]
[[et:Eugenius IV]]
[[es:Eugenio IV]]
[[eu:Eugenio IV.a]]
[[fa:اوژن چهارم]]
[[fr:Eugène IV]]
[[gl:Uxío IV, papa]]
[[ko:교황 에우제니오 4세]]
[[hr:Eugen IV.]]
[[id:Paus Eugenius IV]]
[[it:Papa Eugenio IV]]
[[jv:Paus Eugenius IV]]
[[ka:ევგენიუს IV]]
[[sw:Papa Eugenio IV]]
[[la:Eugenius IV]]
[[lt:Eugenijus IV]]
[[hu:IV. Jenő pápa]]
[[mk:Папа Евгение IV]]
[[mr:पोप युजेनियस चौथा]]
[[nl:Paus Eugenius IV]]
[[ja:エウゲニウス4世 (ローマ教皇)]]
[[oc:Eugèni IV]]
[[pl:Eugeniusz IV]]
[[pt:Papa Eugênio IV]]
[[ro:Papa Eugen al IV-lea]]
[[ru:Евгений IV]]
[[scn:Eugeniu IV]]
[[sl:Papež Evgen IV.]]
[[fi:Eugenius IV]]
[[sv:Eugenius IV]]
[[tl:Eugenio IV]]
[[th:สมเด็จพระสันตะปาปายูจีนที่ 4]]
[[tr:Papa IV. Eugenius]]
[[uk:Євгеній IV]]
[[vi:Giáo hoàng Êugêniô IV]]
[[war:Papa Eugenio IV]]
[[yo:Pope Eugene IV]]
[[zh:尤金四世]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
