<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4908812" ns="0" title="Ankur Group"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=June 2007}}

{{Infobox Company
| company_name = Ankur Group
| company_logo = [[Image:Ektara.png|100px]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Logo of Ankur Group&lt;/small&gt;
| company_type = [[Non-profit organization]]
| foundation = January 2003
| founder = [[Taneem Ahmed]] 
| location_country = [[Bangladesh]]
| key_people = [[Taneem Ahmed]], Kaushik Ghosh, Sayamindu Dasgupta, Deepayan Sarkar, Jamil Ahmed, Progga, Anirban Mitra
| industry = [[Open Source Software]]
| homepage = http://ankurbangla.org/
}}

'''Ankur''' is working toward supporting [[Bengali language]] (Bangla) on [[GNU]]/[[Linux]] operating system. Most of Ankur's projects are focused on [[XFree86]].org's XServer. Some of its projects are in fact platform independent and add language support to other operating systems.

The group is also working on providing Bangla support for some major [[XServer]] applications such as office suites, databases, development tools and desktop environments such as [[GNOME]] and [[KDE]]. Ankur's intention is to help develop and maintain open source/free software targeted towards the Bangla speaking user and to provide a completely functional, user intuitive localised desktop that is easily usable and easily deployable.

==History==

Initially, Ankur started as the bengalinux-core mailing list. This later worked as the nucleus for forming Ankur.

[[Taneem Ahmed]] of Bangladesh, the founder of Ankur, was developing and maintaining the http://www.BengaLinux.Org website - a one stop mall for Unix based Bangla Free Software. He was also the author of the bn_BD [[locale]] for the [[GNU C library]]. This established his identity as major figure in the Bangla open source community. In October 2002, he launched the bengalinux-core mailing list. 

This list became a focus of Bangla related Open Source enthusiasts. In January, 2003, Taneem Ahmed announced the [[GNOME]] Bangla Translation Project and began recruiting for the project. The recruitment call was taken seriously and the project began to expand. After some discussion on a group name of discussion, 'Ankur', proposed by Kaushik Ghosh. On 3 March 2003, the name ''Ankur'' was officially adopted.

==Major achievement==

* Creation of the first Bangla graphical Desktop in any [[Linux distribution]].
* Design and release of the first Open Type font (Akash) which made possible the  use of Unicode-based Bangla.
* Organising the Bangla-speaking open-source developers (Unix-based) under a single platform.
* Release of the first Bangla OS (i.e. Ankur [[Live CD]]) in 2004.
* Best .org project at LinuxAsia 2006

==Current projects==

* [[GUI]] (Graphical User Interface) translation (or localization in short [[L10n]]),
* Font designing/maintenance,
* Archiving copyright-expired literature,
* Maintaining a Linux [[Live CD]] with Bangla-specific add-ons,
* Developing various Bangla-language-processing software,
* English-to-Bangla translator ''Anubadok'',
* Bangla [[OCR]],
* Bengali Dictionary

==See also==
*[[IndLinux]]
*[[BOSS Linux]]

==External links==
* [http://www.ankurbangla.org  Ankur Bangla]
* [http://www.bengalinux.org Bengalinux]
* [http://www.ankur.org.bd Ankur Bangladesh]

[[Category:Bengal]]
[[Category:Indic computing]]


{{linux-stub}}

[[bn:অঙ্কুর গ্রুপ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
