<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4917428" ns="0" title="Global Impact"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the wrestling event|TNA Global Impact!}}
{{Orphan|date=February 2009}}

'''Global Impact''' was founded in 1956 as the Federal Service Joint Crusade to serve as the umbrella group for international health and welfare agencies participating in Federal government employee fund-raising campaigns. With the inception of the [[Combined Federal Campaign]] (CFC) in 1964, the organization became known as International Service Agencies (ISA). Until 1980, ISA was one of four approved federations participating in the CFC. After that time, the campaign was opened to include many more agencies and federations.  In 2003, ISA changed its name to Global Impact to align with the organization’s evolving mission.

Global Impact represents more than 58&lt;ref name=&quot;charities&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.charity.org/Member_Charities |title=Member Charities |author=Global Impact |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=February 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; of America's most respected international development and relief charities, including [[Heifer International]], [[Lutheran World Relief]], [[CARE (relief agency)|CARE]], [[Médecins Sans Frontières]], [[Save the Children]], and [[Women for Women International]].  Global Impact’s member charities work in developing countries around the globe providing a wide range of services to the poor including: feeding the hungry; teaching effective farming techniques; providing prenatal care and education for expectant mothers; supplying clean water, medicines, and disease prevention programs; building schools and training teachers; promoting entrepreneurial opportunities through microloans; and providing assistance following natural and man-made disasters.

==Key Dates==
*'''1956''': The Federal Service Joint Crusade (FSJC) is organized as an umbrella group for international health and welfare agencies. It is at first made up of two member agencies primarily interested in overseas assistance programs: [[CARE (relief agency)|CARE]] and [[Radio Free Europe]]. In this first year, the organization raises a total of $698,203.
*'''1966''': At the suggestion of U.S. Civil Service Commissioner Vernon Gill, FSJC changes its name to International Service Agencies.
*'''1981''': International Service Agencies has 11 member charities.
*'''1983''': International Service Agencies has more than doubled its roster of member charities to 23.
*'''1993''': Renée S. Acosta begins her tenure as president and CEO to further the organization's commitment to a strategic transformation.
*'''1996''': International Service Agencies named as the Principal Combined Fund Organization (PCFO) to administer the Combined Federal Campaign–Overseas.
*'''2003''': International Service Agencies changes its name to Global Impact in order to better illustrate its mission and its member agencies.
*'''2003''': Global Impact named as the Principal Combined Fund Organization (PCFO) of the Combined Federal Campaign of the National Capital Area (CFCNCA).
*'''2005''': Global Impact launches Global Alert, an electronic crisis response program that gives corporations and their employees a tool to respond to crises. In its initial launch, $1.1 million was raised for relief following the [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake|South Asia tsunami]].
*'''2005''': Global Impact begins offering [[donor advised fund]] management services to assist corporations with distribution of charitable gifts raised in private workplace giving campaigns.
*'''2006''': Global Impact marks 50 years of assuring help for people in need.
*'''2006''': Global Impact selected as the lead charity partner for the Central America and Mexico Hurricane Relief Fund.
*'''2006''': Global Impact selected as the lead charity partner for the [http://www.lebanonpartnership.org/ U.S.-Lebanon Partnership Fund]. 
*'''2007''': Global Impact awards [[Microsoft Corporation]] the ''Global Citizen Award'' for their commitment to international philanthropy. 
*'''2007''': Global Impact is awarded the [http://www.aaiusa.org/foundation/kahlil-gibran-awards ''Kahlil Gibran Spirit of Humanity Award for International Achievement''] by the [http://www.aaiusa.org/foundation Arab American Institute Foundation].
*'''2007''': Global Impact appears on the [http://philanthropy.com/ Chronicle of Philanthropy’s] annual ''Philanthropy 400'' list. 
*'''2008''': Global Impact programs are highlighted as [http://www.conference-board.org/workingGroups/wkgGrpDescribe.cfm?Council_ID=219 models for international disaster response] by [http://www.conference-board.org/ The Conference Board]. 

== Programs and Partnerships ==
*'''Campaign Management''': Created to assist companies wanting to offer workplace giving campaigns.  Services include collection and distribution of funds. 

*'''Charitable Fund Management''': Designed to assist with the distribution of charitable gifts raised through private workplace giving campaigns or in response to special requests. 

*'''Global Alert''': Web-based crisis fundraising tool designed for companies to provide employees with a means of making donations following a disaster or crisis. 

== Members ==
* [[Educational Concerns For Hunger Organization]], a network of agriculturalists working to provide sustainable options for the poor. ECHO's programs include research, training, network maintenance, seed banking and supply, and agricultural technical support.

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.charity.org www.charity.org Official web site]

[[Category:Development charities]]
[[Category:Humanitarian aid organizations]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:Non-profit organizations based in Virginia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
