<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="493706" ns="0" title="Fairfield University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox university
 | name            = Fairfield University
 | image           = [[Image:Fairfield Seal.png]]
 | motto           = ''Per Fidem ad Plenam Veritatem'' ([[Latin]])
 | mottoeng        = Through Faith to the Fullness of Truth
 | established     = 1942
 | type            = [[private university|Private]], [[Coeducational]]
 | affiliation     = Roman Catholic,&lt;br&gt;[[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]]
 | endowment       = $218 million&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
 | president       = [[Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]]
 | vice-president  = Dr. William Weltzer&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/about/about_evp_weitzer.html Biography: Dr. William Weitzer, Senior Vice President]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | provost         = Paul J. Fitzgerald, S.J.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/about_exec_avp.html |title=Senior Vice President for Academic Affairs Paul J. Fitzgerald, S.J |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | chairman        = Paul J. Huston '82&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/pres_trustees.html |title=Fairfield University Board of Trustees |publisher=Fairfield University |date=February 28, 2011 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | city            = [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Fairfield]]
 | state           = [[Connecticut]]
 | country         = USA {{flagicon|USA}}
 | coor            = {{Coord|41.18153|-73.29029|region:US_type:city|display=inline,title}}
 | undergrad       = 3,500&lt;ref name=FUgeoeroll&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/ir_geoenroll.html |title=Fairfield University Enrollment by Geographic Distribution|publisher=Fairfield University |date=Oct 13, 2009 |accessdate=August 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; (455 at UC) (2009)
 | postgrad        = 1231&lt;ref name=FUgeoeroll/&gt; (2009)
 | faculty         = 329 full-time equivalent&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/about/ir_faculty.html University Faculty Statistics] Updated: May 26, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; (13-to-1)
 | campus          = Suburban 212 acres (809,000 m²)
 | sports          = 21 Varsity Teams&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaa.com/schools/220_Fairfield.html |title=The Official Web Site of the NCAA |publisher=NCAA.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | colors	   = Cardinal, White
 | nickname	   = [[Fairfield Stags|Stags]]
 | mascot	   = Lucas The [[Stag]]
 | athletics	   = [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;
 | affiliations    = [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities|AJCU]] &lt;br&gt; [[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference|MAAC]]&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;&lt;br&gt; [[New England Association of Schools and Colleges|NEASC]]
 | free_label      = Newspaper
 | free            = [[Fairfield Mirror]]
 | website         = [http://www.fairfield.edu/ www.fairfield.edu]
 | logo            = [[Image:Fairfield University.svg|200px]]
}}

[[Image:Fairfield Entrance.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Main Entrance and Alumni House]]

'''Fairfield University''' is a private, co-educational undergraduate and master's level teaching-oriented university located in [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Fairfield]], Connecticut, in the [[New England]] region of the United States. It was founded by the [[Society of Jesus]] in 1942, and today is one of 28 member institutions of the [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities]]. The primary objectives of a Fairfield University education are to develop the creative intellectual potential of its students and to foster in them [[ethics|ethical]] and [[Philosophy of religion|religious]] [[values]] and a sense of [[social responsibility]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/about_mission.html |title=Fairfield University: Mission Statement |publisher=Fairfield University |date=March 4, 1983 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; All schools of the university are committed to a liberal [[Humanism|humanistic]] approach to education, which encourages interdisciplinary learning.

About 3,500 undergraduate and 1,200 graduate students&lt;ref name=FUgeoeroll/&gt; study in Fairfield's six schools and colleges: The [[Fairfield College of Arts and Sciences]], The [[Charles F. Dolan School of Business]], The [[Fairfield University School of Engineering|School of Engineering]], The [[Fairfield University School of Nursing|School of Nursing]], The [[Fairfield University Graduate School of Education and Allied Professions|Graduate School of Education and Allied Professions]], and The [[Fairfield University - Academic Programs#The University College|University College]]. Fairfield academics are notable for its science programs which have produced a [[MacArthur Fellow]] and a [[Guggenheim Fellow]] and its international programs which have produced fifty-nine [[Fulbright Scholars]] since 1993.  In addition, two Fairfield faculty members were named consecutive Connecticut Professors of the Year by the [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] in 2009 and 2010 in recognition of their extraordinary dedication to undergraduate teaching.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.fairfield.edu/web_features/?p=2471 Dr. Betsy Bowen Named 2010 Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching Connecticut Professor of the Year], accessed November 24, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History and tradition==
===History===
[[Image:Bellarmine 3.jpg|thumb|150px|left|[[St. Robert Bellarmine|St. Robert Bellarmine, S.J.]], [[Patron Saint]] of Fairfield University]]

Fairfield University was founded in 1942 by the [[Society of Jesus]] when the Jesuits acquired the two contiguous estates of the [[Brewster Jennings]] and Walter Lashar families. In the same year the [[James H. Dolan, S.J.|Rev. James H. Dolan, S.J.]], the Provincial Superior of the New England Jesuit Province appointed the [[John J. McEleney, S.J.|Rev. John J. McEleney, S.J.]] the first President of the &quot;Fairfield University of [[St. Robert Bellarmine|Saint Robert Bellarmine, S.J.]]&quot; and Vicar of the [[Fairfield College Preparatory School]]. In 1944, the Rev. James H. Dolan, S.J. became the second President. During his tenure, Fairfield University was chartered by the State of Connecticut to grant degrees in 1945; the first class of 303 male students was admitted to the College of Arts and Sciences in 1947; the College of Arts and Sciences was accredited by the State of Connecticut and the first summer session of undergraduate courses was held in 1949.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:16pt;margin-top:2pt;float:right;&quot;
|-
!colspan=3|Presidents of Fairfield
|-
! '''Years''' !! '''President'''
|-
| '''1942–1944''' || [[John J. McEleney, S.J.|Rev. John J. McEleney, S.J.]]
|-
| '''1944–1951''' || [[James H. Dolan, S.J.|Rev. James H. Dolan, S.J.]]
|-
| '''1951–1958''' || [[Joseph D. FitzGerald, S.J.|Rev. Joseph D. FitzGerald, S.J.]]
|-
| '''1958–1964''' || [[James E. FitzGerald, S.J.|Rev. James E. FitzGerald, S.J.]]
|-
| '''1964–1973''' || [[William C. McInnes, S.J.|Rev. William C. McInnes, S.J.]]
|-
| '''1973–1979''' || [[Thomas R. Fitzgerald, S.J.|Rev. Thomas R. Fitzgerald, S.J.]]
|-
| '''1979–2004''' || [[Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J.|Rev. Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J.]]
|-
| '''2004 -''' || [[Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]]
|}

In 1971, Fairfield University won a significant legal victory at the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] in ''Tilton vs. Richardson'' establishing an important legal precedent concerning the [[Establishment Clause of the First Amendment]] and government financial assistance to religious-based colleges and universities.&lt;ref name=&quot;oyez.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oyez.org/cases/1970-1979/1970/1970_153/ |title=Tilton vs. Richardson, 403 U.S. 672 (1971) |publisher=Oyez |date=June 28, 1971 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This landmark court case questioned the legality of Fairfield and three other Connecticut religious-based institutions securing federal construction grants under the Higher Education Facilities Act of 1963. An appeal by the plaintiffs was denied by the Supreme Court on June 28, 1971, ensuring Fairfield a significant amount of federal money which contributed to the construction of the [[DiMenna-Nyselius Library|Nyselius Library]] (1968) and Bannow Science Center (1971).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.fairfield.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/fuhp&amp;CISOPTR=227&amp;CISOBOX=1&amp;REC=8 |title=Rev. William C. McInnes, S.J., 5th President of Fairfield University (1964–1973) |publisher=Digital.fairfield.edu |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the majority opinion, the Court upheld, 5–4, the federal construction grants as long as the facilities were not to be used for sectarian instruction or places of worship.&lt;ref name=&quot;oyez.org&quot;/&gt;  The Court held that the church-related institutions in question had not used their federally funded facilities for religious activities, and that the facilities were &quot;indistinguishable from a typical state university facility.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;oyez.org&quot;/&gt;

Fairfield has been a frequent stop of candidates for President of the United States throughout several Presidential campaigns.  During the [[United States presidential election, 1984|1984 presidential election]],  President of the United States [[Ronald Reagan]] visited Fairfield on October 26, 1984.  During the [[United States presidential election, 1988|1988 Presidential election]],   [[George H. Bush]] visited the university and delivered a speech in [[Alumni Hall (Fairfield University)|Alumni Hall]] attacking the tax-and-budget policies of then Massachusetts Governor [[Michael Dukakis]] days before being elected the 41st [[President of the United States|President]]. Alumnus [[J. Michael Farren|J. Michael Farren '77]] served as deputy director to President-elect [[George H. Bush]]'s transition team and later served as deputy campaign manager for the Bush-Quayle Re-election Committee during the [[United States presidential election, 1992|1992 presidential election]]. During the [[United States presidential election, 2000|2000 United States Presidential Election]],   Texas Governor [[George W. Bush]] scheduled and controversially cancelled at the last moment a large student rally at Fairfield following a visit to [[Bob Jones University]], a school which has been characterized as anti-Catholic. Alumnus [[Thomas J. Josefiak]] served as general counsel to both the [[George W. Bush presidential campaign, 2004|55th Presidential Inaugural Committee]] and later served as general counsel to [[George W. Bush presidential campaign, 2004|the Bush presidential campaign]] during the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 election]].

A detailed account of the history of Fairfield University was written by the late Rev. Joseph MacDonnell, S.J. in his book entitled '''If these Stones Could Speak.'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://faculty.fairfield.edu/jmac/fu/FU1ur.htm If These Stones Could Speak]&lt;/ref&gt;  Further, a brief history of '''The Jesuits in Fairfield''' can be found on The Fairfield Jesuit Community website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.faculty.fairfield.edu/jesuit/history_1.html |title=The Jesuits in Fairfield |publisher=Faculty.fairfield.edu |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[American Revolutionary War]] in 1779, the &quot;Battle of Round Hill&quot; took place on the present day Bellarmine Hill on the campus of the university where the Americans under the command of Colonel Samuel Whiting (whose third-generation grandson Andrew Whiting graduated in 2005) repelled the British invaders under the command of Major-General [[William Tryon]], but not before the British laid ruin to the Town of Fairfield.

===Recent history===
In September 2000, [[Charles Dolan|Charles F. Dolan H'04]], founder of [[HBO]] and chairman of [[Cablevision]], donated $25 million to the renamed [[Charles F. Dolan School of Business]], which still represents one of the largest donations from a single source to a [[business school]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aacsb.edu/members/communities/interestgrps/donors.asp Business School Donations]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2004, the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]], a graduate of [[Princeton University]], former Chair of the History Department at [[Georgetown University]], and former Dean of [[Fordham University|Fordham College at Rose Hill]], became the eighth Jesuit President of Fairfield University succeeding the [[Aloysius P. Kelley|Rev. Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J.]], the longest tenured and most accomplished President of the University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/about_pres_apkelley.html |title=Fairfield University inaugurates its first president in 25 years |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Fairfield Kelley Center.PNG|thumb|right|300px|Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J. Center]]

In September 2004, the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]] announced that the capital campaign, &quot;Our Promise: The Campaign for Fairfield University,&quot; launched and led by the [[Aloysius P. Kelley|Rev. Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J.]], raised a record $137.9 million. The capital raised resulted in the construction and renovation of seven buildings, the creation of four new academic chairs, and the significant increase in the University's endowment.

In October 2006, the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]], the [[Aloysius P. Kelley|Rev. Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J.]], and Paul J. Huston '82, chairman of the Board of Trustees, dedicated the Aloysius P. Kelley. S.J. Center, a new [[environmentally friendly]], state-of-the-art welcoming center for prospective students and a &quot;one-stop shopping&quot; administrative center for current students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20070322214926/http://www.workstage.com/kelleycenter/ |title=Fairfield University honors former President with green, hi-tech administration and welcome center |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=March 22, 2007 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2008, the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]], announced the Bridgeport Tuition Plan offering full tuition scholarships to admitted students who are graduates of a [[Bridgeport, Connecticut#High Schools|Bridgeport, Connecticut high school]] whose family earns less than $50,000 a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2009 |title=Fairfield University announces Bridgeport Tuition Plan for students with family incomes under $50,000 |publisher=Fairfield University |date=March 31, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roman Catholic and Jesuit tradition===

As one of 28 Jesuit colleges and universities in the United States, Fairfield belongs to an elite group that continues the dedication [[Ignatius of Loyola|Saint Ignatius of Loyola]] (1491–1556)  to developing the whole person. The university's   environment invites students of all traditions to a maturing of faith, self knowledge, respect for the dignity of themselves and others, a devotion to justice, a commitment to serving the poor, and a passion for truth, reflection, and lifelong learning.

===Alma Mater===
[[Image:Fairfield Egan Chapel.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Egan Chapel of St. Ignatius Loyola]]

::::'''''Fairfield! See the stag with cross of Gold'''''
::::'''''Rears once more its undefeated head.'''''
::::'''''Fair our field, as any field of old,'''''

::::'''''Bids our banners, like our blood, be red.'''''
::::'''''&quot;Through faith, unto total truth,&quot; our cry'''''
::::'''''Swells from the sea to spire and sky;'''''
::::'''''Hear, Alma Mater, hear! Fairfield, hail!'''''

::::'''''Mem'ries fold away the thought of thee:'''''
::::'''''Autumn roses crimson on the bough,'''''
::::'''''Bright snow breaking to the dogwood tree'''''

::::'''''Keeps spring singing, then as now.'''''
::::'''''&quot;Through faith, unto total truth,&quot; our cry'''''
::::'''''Swells from the sea to spire and sky;'''''
::::'''''Hear, Alma Mater, hear! Fairfield, hail!'''''

::::Alma Mater of Fairfield University by Rev. John L. Bonn, S.J.

*Listen to the [http://www.fairfield.edu/documents/arts/arts_almamater.mp3 Alma Mater], as performed by the [[Fairfield University Glee Club]].

===Seal of the University===
[[Image:Fairfield Seal.png|frame|left]]
Fairfield's seal combines elements of its several traditions. The gold pinecones come from the coat of arms of the family of [[St. Robert Bellarmine|Saint Robert Bellarmine, S.J.]], for whom the university was originally named. Superimposed on the cones is the badge of the [[Society of Jesus]] – the letters IHS surmounted by the cross and surrounded by the instruments of Christ's passion – to indicate that the University is in the care of members of the same religious family.

There are three compartments in the upper portion of the shield, because &quot;the school is dedicated and exists in the name of the father, and of the son, and of the holy spirit.&quot; The central compartment portrays a hart crossing a ford, a part of the coat of arms of the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Hartford|Diocese of Hartford]], whose boundaries encompassed the [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Town of Fairfield]], when the University was founded. Finally, the two outer compartments show clusters of grapes, charges taken from the town seal and symbolic of the fertility of the verdant fields of the Town and County of Fairfield.
When the University was founded in 1942, the official name of the University was &quot;Fairfield University of St. Robert Bellarmine&quot;. Three of the original seals with this name still exist on campus – in the main lobby of Alumni Hall, on the exterior of the Barone Campus Center, and on the glass front of Regis Hall facing the Quad.

==Academics==
===Academic programs===
{{Main|Fairfield University - Academic Programs}}

Fairfield's Jesuit ethos trains students in scholarship, prepares them for leadership, encourages them to engage in service projects; and develops graduates with strong social concerns for the common good. The university is an intellectual, social, spiritual, and cultural destination of choice for students and faculty from a   diversity of backgrounds.
[[Image:Fairfield McAuliffe Hall.JPG|thumb|right|300px|McAuliffe Hall, School of Engineering]]
Fairfield University offers 35 undergraduate majors and 16 interdisciplinary minors, 35 graduate programs leading to a Master's degree or certification, as well as more than 350 credit and 250 non-credit courses in University College. The Fiske Guide to Colleges recognized Fairfield's strongest programs to include [[Biology]], [[International Studies]], [[Art History]], [[Religious Studies]], [[Sociology]], Accounting and Finance, and [[Mechanical Engineering]]. The innovative [[New Media]] major is the first of its kind among Jesuit universities and features [[Cinefest Fairfield]], an annual film festival showcasing student work created in production courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/cas/nm_index.html |title=Film, Television and Radio major led by three Jesuits |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; And Fairfield's new 5-Year Bachelor's/Master's Teacher Program allows students to begin their teacher education program requirements as undergraduates and complete them as graduate students in the University's graduate degree programs in [[Secondary education in the United States|secondary]], [[Primary education in the United States|elementary]], or [[English as a foreign or second language|TESOL education]].

*The [[Fairfield College of Arts and Sciences]]
*The [[Charles F. Dolan School of Business]]
*The [[Fairfield University School of Engineering|School of Engineering]]
*The [[Fairfield University School of Nursing|School of Nursing]]
*The [[Fairfield University Graduate School of Education and Allied Professions|Graduate School of Education and Allied Professions]]
*The [[Fairfield University - Academic Programs#The University College|University College]]

===Academic achievement===

{{Main|Fairfield University - Fellows and Scholars}}

Fairfield students and graduates have been the recipients of numerous nationally acclaimed fellowships and scholarships including the [[MacArthur Fellowship]], [[Guggenheim Fellowship]], [[Fulbright Scholarship]], [[Goldwater Scholarship]], [[Clare Booth Luce]] Scholarship, McGowan Scholarship and Udall Scholarship.

*'''Phi Beta Kappa''': Fairfield is the second youngest institution to gain membership in [[Phi Beta Kappa]] (ΦΒΚ), the nation's oldest and most prestigious academic honor society. When the Zeta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa was chartered at the university in 1994, Fairfield joined a select company of 262 colleges and universities. Nationwide, only one percent of college seniors are invited to join Phi Beta Kappa annually. As of 2007, forty-three faculty and staff members on campus, including University President Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, are members of Phi Beta Kappa.

*'''USA Today All-USA College Academic Team''': Two Fairfield students, Chris Pilkerton '95 and Michael Franz '99, were selected to the USA Today All-USA College Academic Team which honors full-time undergraduates who   excel in scholarship and also extend their intellectual abilities beyond the classroom to benefit society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/education/2004-08-12-2005-colllege-team_x.htm |title=All-USA College Academic Team: About and advice |work=USA Today  |date=September 23, 2005 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Centers of distinction===
*The '''Center for Catholic Studies''' promotes an understanding and appreciation of the Catholic intellectual tradition by supporting academic programming exploring the Catholic and Jesuit mission and identity and the Minor in Catholic Studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Center for Catholic Studies&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/cs/index.html |title=Center for Catholic Studies |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center sponsors the ''Voices of Others'' video series in which [[Paul Lakeland|Dr. Paul Lakeland]] sits down with scholars, theologians and social activists to discuss issues surrounding the theme “Listening to the Voices of Others.” Past special guests include [[Loung Ung]], [[Gregory Boyle|Rev. Gregory Boyle, S.J.]], [[Paul Farmer|Dr. Paul Farmer]] and [[Archbishop Demetrios of America]]. The Center is directed by the holder of the Aloysius P. Kelley, S.J. Chair in Catholic Studies, currently Dr. Lakeland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Center for Catholic Studies&quot;/&gt;

*The '''Center for Faith and Public Life''' provides a cross-disciplinary forum for students, scholars, policy makers, and religious leaders to converse and reflect on issues where religion intersects with civic life. Through academic research, teaching, publications and public initiatives, the Center provides a  focus for viewing the role of religion in the public square.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/cfpl/index.html |title=Center for Faith and Public Life |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center sponsors the ''Politics Meets Faith'' video series in which American politicians such [[Joseph Lieberman|U.S. Senator Joseph Lieberman]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1991 |title=Senator Joseph Lieberman answers questions about faith and politics posed by Fairfield University students |publisher=Fairfield University |date=March 14, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Christopher Shays|U.S. Representative Christopher Shays]] and [[Jim McGovern|U.S. Representative Jim McGovern]] have gone on record in front of an audience of students for such  conversations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/cfpl/cfpl_politics_meets_faith.html |title=Politics Meets Faith Series |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center is home to the '''Office of Service Learning''' which incorporates the [[service learning]] teaching methodology into the Fairfield curriculum,  providing   opportunities to combine   academics studies with active [[community service]] to local organizations in nearby [[Bridgeport, Connecticut]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/service/index.html |title=Office of Service Learning |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For example, education and psychology students can participate in the Adrienne Kirby Family Literacy Project,&lt;ref name=&quot;query.nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1D71130F935A35755C0A96F958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all |title=Literacy Program Teaches the Teachers |work=New York Times |date=June 6, 1999 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; business students can participate in the [[IRS Volunteer Income Tax Assistance Program|Volunteer Income Tax Assistance (VITA)]] program,&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.fairfieldmirror.com/media/storage/paper148/news/2007/03/22/News/Taxes.Teaching.Lessons-2784396.shtml Taxes Teaching Lessons]&lt;/ref&gt; and nursing students can work at the Health Promotion Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/son/son_affiliations.html |title=Fairfield University School of Nursing Health Promotion Center |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/osl/osl_partners.html |title=Office of Service Learning Community Partners |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The center is   the current home for the '''Connecticut Campus Compact''', providing state level support for the [[Campus Compact]], a national coalition of more than 1,100 colleges and universities promoting [[community service]], [[civic engagement]], and [[service learning]] in higher education.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/currents/stories/08_02/cc_upclose_feb08.html Fairfield Welcome Campus Compact]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center for Faith and Public Life was founded in 2005 and is directed by the [[Richard Ryscavage|Richard Ryscavage, S.J.]]

*The '''Carl and Dorothy Bennett Center for Judaic Studies''' provides students and the local community exposure to  Jewish ideas, culture, and thinking. The Bennett Center has brought several   lecturers to the University, including Nobel Prize-winner [[Elie Wiesel]], Former Ambassador [[Dennis Ross]], and New York Times columnist [[Thomas Friedman]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/judaic/index.html |title=Carl &amp; Dorothy Bennett Center for Judaic Studies at Fairfield University |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The  center was founded in 1994 with an initial endowment of $1.5 million from Carl and Dorothy Bennett of Greenwich, Connecticut and is directed by Dr. [[Ellen Umansky]].

*The '''Center for Microfinance''' is engaged in the [[microfinance]] movement working to help develop self-sustaining business operations in developing countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/dsb/dsb_cmac.html |title=Center for Microfinance |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dr. [[Winston Tellis]] and Dr. Michael Tucker co-founded the Center in 2001, with a program in which the faculty and business students   helped develop self-sustaining businesses in poor rural areas of Haiti and Nicaragua.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=85 |title=Business students investigating viability of sun ovens for Haiti |publisher=Fairfield University |date=February 1, 1998 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The center was honored for its work for Haiti's poor by FONKOZE USA (F/USA) which supports Fonkoze (Fondasyon Kole Zepol), Haiti's only alternative bank for the poor. F/USA is one of only five non-profit organizations approved by the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission to solicit U.S. investments for foreign organizations.{{cite}}

===International programs===
The International Studies Program at the  Fairfield College of Arts and Sciences  and the International Business Program at the  Dolan School of Business  are associated with several programs:

[[File:Fairfield Dolan House.JPG|thumb|300px|right|Dolan House, International Programs Center]]

*'''Fulbright Scholars Program''': Fairfield   students have been   successful in garnering [[Fulbright Scholarships]], which fund students to go abroad for one year after graduation to engage in independent research, study and work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/about_international.html |title=Fairfield University: International Presence |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1993, 59 Fairfield students have been awarded these scholarship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/academic/prest_fulbrights.html |title=Fairfield University Academic Office of Prestigious Fellowships and Scholarships |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fairfield has been ranked No. 1 among universities that grant master's degrees in the  Fulbright 's list of colleges and universities that produced U.S. Fulbright Scholars since 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iienetwork.org/?p=FulbrightRankings |title=Fulbright Rankings 2006–2007 |publisher=Iienetwork.org |date=October 20, 2006 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was the fifth time in six years that Fairfield had the largest number of awards in its category.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1881 |title=Fairfield University once again tops in its class in Fulbrights awarded |publisher=Fairfield University |date=October 23, 2007 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the last nine years, eight faculty members have been awarded Fulbright Scholar Grants for postdoctoral research. Fairfield faculty members have published hundreds of scholarly articles and books in the past two years.
* '''The Study Abroad Program:''' Fairfield   offers summer, semester and year-long study abroad options in [[Florence, Italy]] at the Florence University of the Arts; [[Syracuse, Italy]] at the Mediterranean Center for Arts and Sciences; [[Galway]], Ireland at the [[National University of Ireland, Galway]]; [[Brisbane, Australia]] at the [[Australian Catholic University]]; [[Managua, Nicaragua]] at the [[Universidad Centroamericana]]; [[Granada, Spain]] at the [[University of Granada]]; [[Madrid, Spain]] at the [[Complutense University of Madrid]]; and [[Seville, Spain]] at the [[University of Seville]].  In addition, MBA students can participate in the ''Doing Business in Europe'' program hosted by the [[École supérieure de commerce de Rouen|ESC Rouen – Rouen School of Management]] in [[Rouen]], France.

*'''The Beijing Center for Chinese Studies:''' Fairfield University students regularly study at the [[University of International Business and Economics]] in [[Beijing, China]] through a partnership with [[The Beijing Center for China Studies|The Beijing Center for Chinese Studies]], a Jesuit consortium program for study in China. Many of these students are winners of Freeman Awards for Study in Asia and ASIANetwork Freeman Student-Faculty Fellowships.

===Rankings and ratings===

[[BusinessWeek]] ranks Fairfield 63rd in the United States and 2nd in  Connecticut for Value based on the [[return on investment]] (ROI) it provides to its students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/interactive_reports/bs_collegeROI_0621.html |title=Bloomberg BusinessWeek: What's Your College Degree Worth? |work=Bloomberg BusinessWeek   |date=December 8, 2009 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center for College Enrollment Studies includes Fairfield in annual Guide to 101 of the Best Values in Colleges and Universities. The Fiske Guide to Colleges profiles Fairfield as one of the &quot;country's best and most interesting&quot; colleges and universities, stating that &quot;Fairfield is one of the up-and-coming schools in the Roman Catholic universe&quot; and &quot;is moving into the same class as older, more revered East Coast Jesuit institutions.&quot; The guide    ranks the Fairfield and its School of Business among &quot;Small Colleges and Universities Strong in Business.&quot;

[[The Princeton Review]] ranks Fairfield amongst the &quot;Best 361 Colleges;&quot; and the Dolan School of Business among the &quot;Best 237 Business Schools&quot; and one of the top 15 accounting programs in the country based on &quot;Student Opinion Honors for Business Schools&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/student-opinion-honors-accounting.aspx Princeton Review's &quot;Student Opinion Honors for Business Schools&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; It ranks Fairfield among the &quot;Best Northeast Colleges;&quot; among &quot;America's Best Value Colleges&quot; in 2005 (the only Connecticut school and among 77 schools nationwide); and among &quot;Top 25 Most Connected Campuses&quot; in 2004.  [[U.S. News &amp; World Report|U.S. News America's Best Colleges]] ranked Fairfield at number 2 on its Northeast Regional Universities chart for 2012; and amongst &quot;Great Schools, Great Prices&quot; based on academic ranking and the net cost of attendance for a student who receives the average level of need-based financial aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/masters-north-search/c_final_tier+1 |title=Master's Universities (North) Rankings – Best Colleges – Education – US News and World Report |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arts and enrichment==
===Quick Center For the Arts===
[[Image:Fairfield Quick Center.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Regina A. Quick Center for the Arts]]
The [[Regina A. Quick Center for the Arts]] is the major center of theatre and the arts at Fairfield and recognized as the &quot;cultural epicenter of Fairfield County&quot; by Westport Magazine.{{cite}} The center opened in 1990 and hosts events such as popular and classical music, dance, theatre, and programs for young audiences. It houses the 740-seat Kelley Theatre, the 150-seat Lawrence A. Wien Experimental (Black Box) Theatre, and the Thomas J. Walsh, Jr. Art Gallery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20060904190916/http://www.faculty.fairfield.edu/psarawit/vtour/quickcenter.htm |title=Regina A. Quick Center for the Arts |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=September 4, 2006 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The  center is home to the '''Open VISIONS Forum''', which under the direction   of Dr. Philip Eliasoph brings a wide range of speakers to campus to participate in an   dialogue about topical issues. Past guests have included two-time [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning historian [[David McCullough]], prize-winning [[NBC Nightly News]] anchor [[Brian Williams]], former prime minister of Pakistan [[Benazir Bhutto]]; documentary filmmaker [[Ken Burns]]; Forbes CEO and former presidential candidate [[Steve Forbes]]; former U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations [[Richard Holbrooke]]; United States Poet Laureate [[Robert Pinsky]]; Broadway legend [[Stephen Sondheim]]; and former hostage and author [[Terry Waite]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfieldmirror.com/news/1.475117-1.475117 Eliasoph Brings Headliners To Fairfield]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cinefest Fairfield===
[[Cinefest Fairfield]] is an annual film festival held in association with the [[Fairfield Community Theatre]] featuring short films by students, alumni and faculty. The film festival is sponsored by the Department of Visual and Performing Arts and showcases its innovative New Media major. &quot;CineFest Fairfield will become a notable annual event for the University and for Fairfield County,&quot; Fr. James Mayzik, S.J., Director of the New Media major and Media Center said. &quot;Fairfield students will emerge as leaders within the region and the nation for their creativity and talent in film, television and radio within this exciting new program.&quot;

===Bellarmine Museum of Art===
[[Image:Fairfield Kress.jpg|thumb|left|125px|&quot;Madonna and Child&quot;, c. 1525]]
The '''[[Bellarmine Museum of Art]]''', opened in October 2010, is located the University's signature 1920s Tudor mansion and features four galleries with about {{convert|2700|sqft|m2}} of space.  Its main gallery, The Frank and Clara Meditz Gallery, is named in honor of the parents of the lead donor to the project, University Trustee John Meditz '70. Its evocative footprint – which resembles an early Christian basilica in plan – makes the Meditz Gallery an ideal space for displaying ten paintings from the Italian Renaissance and Baroque periods, works gifted to the University by the [[Samuel H. Kress Foundation]] via Bridgeport's [[Discovery Museum and Planetarium|Discovery Museum]]. In a smaller side gallery, highlights from the University's collection of plaster casts after exemplary works from ancient Rome and Greece (including eight recently donated to the University by the [[Acropolis Museum]] in Athens) are displayed. The corridor adjacent to the Meditz gallery holds casts of significant pieces from the [[Parthenon]]. In addition to these objects, the museum houses a range of non-Western art artifacts (including pre-Columbian vessels, 19th-century South East Asian sculptures and African masks), and has  pieces from the Celtic, Byzantine, Medieval and Romanesque periods on loan from the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]'s Department of Medieval Art and [[The Cloisters]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/arts/bell_opening.html Bellarmine Museum Opens October 25, 2010]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theatre Fairfield===
Theatre Fairfield is the resident [[production company]] of the [[Theatre|Theatre Program]] of the Department of [[Visual Arts|Visual]] &amp; [[Performing Arts]] at the university. Theatre Fairfield's season includes professionally directed and designed productions; a '''Festival''' of student-written, directed, and designed plays; performances by '''On the Spot''', an [[Improvisational theatre|improv company]]; '''Director's Cut''' or '''A Class Act''' which features the work of advanced directing and acting students; and independent projects created by junior and senior theatre majors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/arts/arts_theatreffld.html |title=Theater Fairfield |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The '''PepsiCo Theatre''', a renovated 1922 [[carriage house]], is the home to Theatre Fairfield. This [[Theater (structure)|theatrical facility]] includes a 70-seat flexible [[black box theatre]], [[coffeehouse]], [[dance studio]], {{Disambiguation needed|Design studio|design studio|date=June 2011}}, and costume shop/[[dressing room]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faculty.fairfield.edu/psarawit/vtour/pepsico.htm The PepsiCo Theatre]{{Dead link|date=June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fairfield on the screen===
Five locations on the Fairfield University campus including McAuliffe Hall were utilized in the filming of [[All Good Things (film)|All Good Things]], an upcoming mystery-romance film written and directed by [[Andrew Jarecki]]. Among the actors and actresses present on campus June 2 through June 5, 2008 were [[Academy Award]]-nominated actor [[Ryan Gosling]] and actress [[Kirsten Dunst]]. The movie is scheduled to be released in theaters nationally in 2009.&lt;ref name=Mirror&gt;{{cite web| url = http://media.www.fairfieldmirror.com/media/storage/paper148/news/2008/05/01/SummerOnlineUpdate/Movie.To.Be.Filmed.At.Fairfield.Next.Week-3375401.shtml| title = Movie to be filmed at Fairfield next week|work=[[Fairfield Mirror]]| date = May 1, 2008| accessdate = 2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two locations on the Fairfield University campus including Loyola Hall were utilized in the filming of [[Oprah Winfrey Presents: Mitch Albom's For One More Day]], an [[Oprah Winfrey|&quot;Oprah Winfrey Presents&quot;]] adaptation of [[Mitch Albom|Mitch Albom's]] New York Times best-selling book, ''[[For One More Day]]''. Among the actors and actresses present on campus on July 23 and 24, 2007 were Emmy Award-winning actor [[Michael Imperioli]] and Academy Award-winning actress [[Ellen Burstyn]]. The made-for-television movie aired nationally on the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] television network on December 9, 2007.

A team of four Fairfield students won three consecutive matches on the [[GE College Bowl]], a popular quiz game show broadcast live nationally on the [[NBC]] television network. The wins brought national recognition to the University along with a total grant of $5,000. In the first match broadcast on September 29, 1963, the Fairfield four defeated a team from [[Creighton University]], 215–140. In the second match, broadcast on October 6, 1963, the Fairfield four defeated a team from [[Southern Illinois University Carbondale]], 220–190. In the third match, broadcast on October 14, 1963, the Fairfield four defeated a team from [[Clemson University]], 245–200. The four finally were defeated in their fourth match broadcast on October 20, 1963, falling to [[Polytechnic University (New York)|Polytechnic University]], 145–160.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.collegebowl.com/gecollegebowlresultrpt.asp |title=GE College Bowl TV Show History: Fairfield University |publisher=Collegebowl.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Fairfield four included John Horvath, John Kappenberg, Joseph Kroll and George Greller; and were coached by the Rev. Donald D. Lynch, S.J.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.fairfield.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/fuhp&amp;CISOPTR=236&amp;CISOBOX=1&amp;REC=7 |title=College Bowl 1963, Fairfield University vs. Brooklyn Polytechnic |publisher=Digital.fairfield.edu |date=October 20, 1963 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kurt C. Schlichting|Dr. Kurt C. Schlichting '70]], the [[E. Gerald Corrigan]] Endowed Chair in the Humanities and Social Sciences at Fairfield,  and a Fairfield alumnus, appeared as an on-screen interviewee and served as an Academic Advisor to the [[American Experience]] documentary, &quot;[[Grand Central Terminal|Grand Central]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/grandcentral/program/a.html |title=Grand Central &amp;#124; American Experience |publisher=PBS |date=March 29, 1905 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The documentary aired nationally on the [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] television network on February 4, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.fairfieldmirror.com/media/storage/paper148/news/2008/02/21/News/Schlichtings.Stint.On.The.Silver.Screen-3221634.shtml Schlichting's stint on the silver screen]&lt;/ref&gt;  The documentary was based on his book ''Grand Central Terminal: Railroads, Architecture and Engineering in New York'' (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001), for which he received the 2002 Best Professional /Scholarly Book: Architecture &amp; Urbanism Award from the [[Association of American Publishers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hamill |first=Pete |url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/0801865107 |title=Grand Central Terminal: Railroads, Engineering, and Architecture in New York City: Books: Kurt C. Schlichting |publisher=Amazon.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Tony Micelli, the lead fictional character played by actor [[Tony Danza]] in the television sitcom [[Who's the Boss?]], which was set and filmed in [[Fairfield, Connecticut]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wtbr.com/articles/fairfield_citizen/001/ |title=Fairfield and Fantasy Mix on 'Who's the Boss? |publisher=Wtbr.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; attended Fairfield and wore an official  university sweatshirt during the Season 5 &quot;Winter Break&quot; episode.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ULG8i9gr1U Season 5 &quot;Winter Break&quot; episode]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[List of Who's the Boss episodes|episode]] aired nationally on the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] television network on February 14, 1989.

==Athletics==
{{Main|Fairfield Stags}}
[[Image:Fairfield Stags alternate logo.svg|thumb|right|150px|[[Fairfield Stags]] alternate logo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sportslogos.net/team.php?id=673 |title=Fairfield Stags Logos – NCAA Division I (d-h) (NCAA d-h) – Chris Creamer's Sports Logos Page |publisher=SportsLogos.Net |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Fairfield University  is a member of the [[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference]] (MAAC) and is classified as Division 1 in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] for a majority of its athletic programs. it sponsors 20 varsity sports – baseball, men's and women's basketball, men's and women's crew, men's and women's cross country, field hockey, men's and women's golf, men's and women's lacrosse, men's and women's soccer, softball, men's and women's swimming and diving, men's and women's tennis, and women's volleyball. Men's lacrosse is a member of the [[ECAC Lacrosse League]] and field hockey is an associate member of the [[America East Conference]].

===Scholar-athletes===
Fairfield athletes are among the most academically successful in the nation, according to the NCAA's [[Academic Progress Rate]] (APR). In the past several years the NCAA has honored many Fairfield sports teams for their academic performance with Public Recognition Awards. These teams posted multi-year APR scores in the top 10 percent of all squads in their respective sports nationwide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncaa.org/wps/portal/home?WCM_GLOBAL_CONTEXT=/wps/wcm/connect/NCAA/Media+and+Events/Press+Room/News+Release+Archive/2008/Awards+and+Scholarships/20080424_d1_academichonors_rls.html NCAA Honors Division I Teams for Academic Performance]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006–07, eight teams, and in 2007–08, seven teams received these awards. In recent years, twelve Fairfield student-athletes have been honored as Academic All-Americans or National Scholar-Athletes in recognition of their academic and athletic achievements.{{cite}}

===Athletic success===
The Stags' most notable success in athletics has been in [[Fairfield Stags basketball|basketball]], [[Fairfield Stags men's lacrosse|lacrosse]], soccer and volleyball. The [[Fairfield Stags basketball|men's basketball team]] held a half time lead over the number 1 seed University of North Carolina Tar Heels before falling short in the 1997 [[NCAA Men's Basketball Championship]] tournament. [[Darren Phillip|Darren Phillip '00]] was the nation's top rebounder averaging 14 rebounds per game in 1999–00 and [[Deng Gai|Deng Gai '05]] was the nation's top shot blocker averaging 5.5 blocks per game in 2004–05. On March 16, 2010, during the first round of the 2010 [[CollegeInsider.com Postseason Tournament]] (CIT) [[Fairfield Stags men's basketball|men's basketball]] set the national record for the largest comeback in division I college basketball postseason history by overcoming a 27-point deficit with under 16 minutes to play to defeat [[George Mason Patriots men's basketball|George Mason]] in overtime, 101–96. The Stags were led by Mike Evanovich who finished with a career-high 32 points and a school record nine three-pointers including one with 0.9 seconds in regulation to send the game into overtime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.collegeinsider.com/macy/ |title=Historical Comeback |publisher=Collegeinsider.com |date=March 17, 2010 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  And at the conclusion of 2010 season, head coach [[Ed Cooley]] was named the [[Ben Jobe Award|Ben Jobe National Coach of the Year]]. The former women's basketball head coach, Diane Nolan, achieved her 500th career win in 2005–06 and led the Stags to four post-season bids to the [[NCAA Women's Basketball Championship]] in 1988, 1991, 1998 and 2001.

[[Image:Fairfield Alumni Stadium.JPG|thumb|left|300px|Alumni Field and Thomas J. Walsh Athletic Center]]

The [[Fairfield Stags#Lacrosse|men's lacrosse team]] earned berths to the 2003 and 2005 [[NCAA Men's Lacrosse Championship]] tournaments while the women won 6 MAAC Regular Season Titles in the last decade and earned a berth to the 2009 [[NCAA Women's Lacrosse Championship]]. On March 13, 2010, [[Fairfield Stags men's lacrosse|men's lacrosse]] set the school record for the defeat of the highest ranked opponent when the Stags upset the then no. 3 nationally ranked (and eventual [[2010 NCAA Division I Men's Lacrosse Championship|2010 NCAA tournament runner-up]]) [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish men's lacrosse|Notre Dame Fighting Irish]] 10–8 while competing in the inaugural 'Beating Cancer With A Stick Classic' at [[The Kinkaid School]] in [[Houston]], Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.laxpower.com/laxnews/news.php?story=17749 |title=Fairfield Upsets No. 3 Notre Dame in Texas Match |publisher=Laxpower.com |date=March 13, 2010 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Fairfield Stags men's soccer|men's soccer]] team won the 2005 and 2006 MAAC Regular Season Championship as well as the 1999, 2006 and 2008 MAAC Tournament Championship. The 2006 MAAC Championship earned the team a First round NCAA Tournmant Game at in-state rival [[University of Connecticut]]. Prior to the game, UConn had never lost an NCAA Tournament game on its home field. Fairfield secured a 2–1 first round victory, thanks to a late goal by star player James Gaughan. During the years of 2000, 2001, 2005, 2006 and 2007, the team was nationally ranked, rising as high as No. 15 in several polls. In 2007, the Men's Soccer team defeated national champion St. John's University 2–1. No other Fairfield athletic program has ever defeated a former National Championship team.The women's soccer team has advanced to the [[NCAA Women's Soccer Championship]] five times, most recently in 2005 and 2008, and has won the MAAC Championship seven times since 1993. And the women's volleyball team was nationally ranked in 1998 (24th) and 1999 (32nd) and competed in five straight [[NCAA Women's Volleyball Championship]]s between 1997 and 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfieldstags.com |title=Fairfield Stags website |publisher=Fairfieldstags.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sport clubs===
Sport Clubs offer a competitive athletic opportunity for students including baseball, equestrian, men's and women's ice hockey, martial arts, men's and women's rugby, sailing, men's and women's skiing and snowboarding, men's and women's soccer, men's and women's track and [[Fairfield University Men's Volleyball Club|men's]] and women's volleyball.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/athletics/rec_philosophy.html |title=Sport Clubs |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The '''[[Fairfield University Men's Rugby Football Club|Men's Rugby Football Club]]''' or '''Red Ruggers''', established in 1963, is the longest continuously running sport club at Fairfield University.  The Red Ruggers won the 2008 [[Metropolitan New York Rugby Union|MET NY Rugby Football Union]] Division II Title and have produced two [[USA Rugby]] Collegiate All-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/athletics/rec_mensrugby.html |title=Men's Rugby Football Club |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Former Red Ruggers [[Paul Sheehy]] '81 competed for the [[USA Eagles]] at the [[1991 Rugby World Cup]] and [[Will Brazier]] '05 competed for the [[USA Tomahawks]] at the 2004 Liberty Bell Cup.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.life.com/image/51807459 Life Photo: Will Brazier, Philips Kangaroos v USA Tomahawks], accessed March 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The '''Equestrian Club''' was Regional Champions in 1996, 1997, 1999, 2000, 2002, &amp; 2003 and in 2007 seven Fairfield riders were invited to the elite Tournament of Champions, a horse show for the nation's top collegiate [[equestrianism|equestrian]] teams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/athletics/rec_equestrian.html |title=Equestrian Club |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The '''Men's Hockey Club''' (formerly an NCAA level Division I program of the now-defunct MAAC) competed in the 2007 [[Metropolitan Collegiate Hockey Conference|MCHC]] Championship game and the 2008 [[American Collegiate Hockey Association|ACHA]] National Tournament.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfieldhockey.net/ Men's Hockey Club]&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Fairfield University Men's Volleyball Club|'''Men's Volleyball Club''']] won the 2006 and 2007 New England Collegiate Volleyball League Division II Championship and competed in the 2001, 2002, 2005, 2006 and 2008 National Intramural-Recreational Sports Association (NIRSA) Volleyball Championships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/athletics/rec_mvball.html |title=Men's Volleyball Club |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Historically, the 1979 '''Football Club''' led by All-America quarterback Craig Leach '81 played in the National Collegiate Football Association's championship game where the Stags fell 60–40 to the University of Massachusetts-Lowell. The 1980 Football Club started the season ranked No. 1 in the pre-season NCFA Polls.  The men's club baseball team was officially recognized as a sports club during the 2007–2008 academic year.  The team competes in the New England Club Baseball Association.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fairfield.edu/athletics/rec_baseball.html |title=Fairfield University Athletics Club Baseball Team |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus and region==
[[File:Bellarmine Hall (three-quarter view) - Jan 2011.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Bellarmine Hall]]
The university is situated on a pastoral campus offering scenic views of [[Long Island Sound]] and all the amenities of a major, comprehensive university in a setting of rolling hills, sprawling lawns, picturesque ponds, and bucolic wooded areas-a setting ideal for education.  Fairfield's {{convert|200|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus consists of 35 buildings anchored by the three manor homes of the original estates: Bellarmine Hall (1921), formerly the Lashar's 'Hearthstone Hall', re-named to honor [[St. Robert Bellarmine|Saint Robert Bellarmine, S.J]],; McAuliffe Hall (1896), originally O.G. Jennings' 'Mailands', re-named for Bishop [[Maurice F. McAuliffe]], who sanctioned the creation of Fairfield University; and David J. Dolan House, Lawrence Jenning's 'Larribee', dedicated to honor the uncle of [[Charles Dolan|Charles F. Dolan]] who made the 1989 acquisition of Dolan Campus possible.  Along with Bellarmine Hall, named in honor of [[St. Robert Bellarmine|Saint Robert Bellarmine, S.J]], many of the buildings on the campus   are named in honor of Jesuit priests. Behind each building name is a story of a Jesuit priest who was an exemplar of the Jesuit mission and their pursuit of educational and intellectual contributions, human rights and social justice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/about/about_map.html |title=Fairfield University About Fairfield Campus maps, parking and directions |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Main|List of Fairfield University buildings}}

===Campus safety===
The university received the 2008 [[Jeanne Clery]] Campus Safety Award, presented each year by Security On Campus Inc. (SOC). The national award, established in 1994 by Howard and Connie Clery in memory of their daughter who was murdered on a college campus in 1986, honors schools and individuals “that have done extraordinary things to make college and university students safer.” Fairfield was selected for the award based on &quot;...its innovative programs, comprehensive emergency response plan, and overall commitment to...peer education and prevention programming, and a unique study abroad travel safety program.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2201 |title=Fairfield University to receive the national 2008 Jeanne Clery Campus Safety Award |publisher=Fairfield University |date=November 4, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===DiMenna-Nyselius Library===
[[Image:Fairfield Library.JPG|thumb|300px|left|DiMenna-Nyselius Library]]
Built in 1968, the [[DiMenna-Nyselius Library]] originally was named the Nyselius Library in honor of benefactors Gustav and Dagmar Nyselius. They were Swedish immigrants who had settled in Stamford and wanted to make a donation to Fairfield University to repay in part the kindness of their adoptive country. In 2001, the Library underwent a major renovation and expansion and was renamed the DiMenna-Nyselius Library in recognition of a   donation from alumnus Joseph A. DiMenna, Jr. '80.

The Library contains an extensive   collection of [[printing|print]] and [[Computer file|electronic resources]] which include over 300,000 bound volumes, 1800 [[Academic journal|journals]] and newspapers, over 11,000 [[audiovisual]] items and the equivalent of 92,000 volumes in [[microform]]. Its electronic resources provide online access to a wide variety of [[World Wide Web]] subscription databases that bring full text journals and statistical information to the desktop anywhere on campus. Throughout the Library, [[wireless network|wireless access]] is available in designated areas. The Library also contains two open access computer labs featuring [[Macintosh]] and [[Dell]] computers (one with 24-hour access for students), two dozen [[multimedia]] [[workstations]], an [[electronic classroom]], a 90-seat [[multimedia]] [[auditorium]], and study rooms.

In March 2010, a strong [[Nor'easter]] storm peeled back a roughly 120’ x 30–40’ section of the roof along the parking lot side of the library building, destroying 2,583 books—some of which were out of print. The worst-damaged sections were the ones on Shakespeare, film, modern languages, science and social science. The minimum estimated value of the books was $88,519.41.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://fairfieldmirror.com/2010/03/30/library-loses-books-at-high-cost/ |title=Library Loses Books At High Cost |author=Schelzi, Meghan |date=March 30, 2010 |work=The Fairfield Mirror |accessdate=August 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Environmental Sustainability===
In recent years, the university has implemented an institution-wide Green Movement, taking major steps to reduce its impact on the [[natural environment]] and improve [[sustainability]].   The university now builds facilities with an eye to [[Efficient energy use|energy efficiency]], [[recycling]], and receives high marks from [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]] (LEED), a rating system of the [[U.S. Green Building Council]] that promotes responsible building practices and [[sustainable design]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/green/green_fairfield_doing.html What is Fairfield doing?]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; These efforts have earned the university recognition as one of the nation's &quot;Cool Schools&quot; from the [[Sierra Club]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sierraclub.org/sierra/200909/coolschools/allrankings.aspx |title=Sierra Club Cool Schools: The Third Annual List |publisher=Sierraclub.org |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a &quot;C-&quot; grade on the Sustainable Endowments Institute's 2009 College Sustainability Report Card.&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 College Sustainability Report Card&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2009/schools/fairfield-university |title=Fairfield University – Green Report Card 2009 |publisher=Greenreportcard.org |date=June 30, 2007 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  And in 2010, the Princeton Review and U.S. Green Building Council included Fairfield   in the &quot;Guide to 286 Green Colleges&quot;

In October 2007, [[Samuel Bodman|U.S. Secretary of Energy Samuel Bodman]] and [[Chris Shays|U.S. Representative Christopher Shays]] joined the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]] in unveiling the University's new [[environmentally friendly]] [[Cogeneration|Combined Heat and Power Plant]] (CHP) designed to reduce strain on the region's [[power grid]] and reduce the University's overall [[carbon footprint]] by more than 10,000 [[metric tons]] per year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1879 |title=United States Secretary of Energy Samuel Bodman and Congressman Christopher Shays help unveil The university's eco-friendly Combined Heat and Power Plant |publisher=Fairfield University |date=October 22, 2007 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] (EPA) honored the university with a 2010 [[Energy Star]] CHP Award for its energy smart CHP.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2659 |title=Fairfield University wins a 2010 Energy Star CHP Award from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency for its environmentally-friendly power plant |publisher=Fairfield University |date=March 1, 2010 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2008, the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]] signed the American College &amp; University Presidents Climate Commitment, a high-visibility effort to address [[global warming]] by garnering institutional commitments to neutralize [[greenhouse gas emissions]], and to accelerate the research and educational efforts of higher education to equip society to re-stabilize the Earth's [[climate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2043 |title=Fairfield University President commits to 'climate neutral' campus |publisher=Fairfield University |date=May 1, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[Earth Day]] 2008, a ground breaking took place for the new Fairfield Jesuit Community Center, an [[environmentally friendly]] home and retreat and meeting center that will feature a [[roof garden]] and a [[Geothermal heat pump|geo-thermal heating and cooling system]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2036 |title=Fairfield University's Jesuit Community Center groundbreaking ceremony set for Earth Day |publisher=Fairfield University |date=April 17, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Fairfield is also in the process of replacing its 125-vehicle fleet with [[biodiesel|biodiesel-powered buses]] and [[hybrid vehicles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/green/green_fairfield_conservation.html What is Fairfield Doing?: Conservation]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most recently, in August 2009, Fairfield University became the first university in the United States to install [[Tomra]] [[reverse vending machine|UNO reverse vending machines (RVM)]], an all-in-one recycling machine, allowing students to deposit plastic, glass and aluminum beverage containers for a rebate of a nickel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2505 |title=Fairfield University first university in nation to install UNO machines |publisher=Fairfield University |date=September 23, 2009 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Fairfield Beach Postcard 1932.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Fairfield Beach, Connecticut]]

===Region===
The [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Town of Fairfield]] was rated the ninth &quot;best place to live&quot; in the United States and the best place to live in the Northeast by [[Money Magazine]] offering students [[Fairfield Beach, Connecticut|Fairfield Beach]] along the scenic shoreline of [[Long Island Sound]] and a vibrant downtown area which are both located just five minutes from campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://money.cnn.com/magazines/moneymag/bplive/2006/snapshots/CS0926620.html |title=Money Magazine Top Ten Best Place to Live in 2006: Fairfield, CT |publisher=CNN  |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The University runs a shuttle between campus and downtown where students can catch a dinner and a [[Fairfield community theatre|movie]] or hop on a [[Fairfield (Metro-North station)|Metro-North Train]] bound for [[Grand Central Terminal|Grand Central Station]] and New York City.

The [[Black Rock (Bridgeport)|Black Rock]] neighborhood of the [[Bridgeport, Connecticut|City of Bridgeport]] bordering on the [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Town of Fairfield]] is located just ten minutes from campus and provides students a metropolitan village-like atmosphere that boasts some of the best restaurants and entertainment in [[Fairfield County, Connecticut|Fairfield County]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackrockrocks.com/ |title=Black Rock Entertainment District |publisher=Blackrockrocks.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Fairfield University students frequent the &quot;Acoustic Cafe&quot; which has been named &quot;Best Place to Hear Alternative Music&quot; three years in a row by Fairfield County Weekly's reader poll and helped launch Fairfield University's own award-winning [[Indie rock]] band, [[The Alternate Routes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.acousticafe.com/ |title=Acoustic Cafe |publisher=Acousticafe.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==People==
===Notable alumni===
{{Main|List of Fairfield University people}}
Fairfield has approximately 40,000 living alumni. Despite the relative youth of the institution, the alumni are achieving considerable success   in  [[academia]], business, finance, journalism, law, government, medicine, science and [[social justice]].
*In  [[academia]] and education, Fairfield alumni include: [[Donald Preziosi]], an art historian and former Slade Professor of Fine Art at Oxford University; [[Charles E. Schaefer]], a  psychology professor considered the &quot;Father of Play Therapy&quot;; [[Katherine Lapp]], Executive Vice President of Harvard University; [[David J. McCarthy, Jr.]], Dean Emeritus of the Georgetown University Law Center; [[Francis J. Tedesco]], President Emeritus of the Medical College of Georgia.
*In  business and finance, alumni include: [[E. Gerald Corrigan]], the 7th President of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York; [[William P. Egan]], venture capitalist; [[Kathleen Murphy]], one of Fortune Magazine's 50 Most Powerful Business Women; [[Joseph DiMenna]], hedge fund manager; [[Christopher McCormick]], president &amp; CEO of L.L.Bean; [[Eileen Rominger]], Director of Investment Management at the U.S. Securities &amp; Exchange Commission.
*In journalism and literature, alumni include: [[Pat Jordan (author)|Pat Jordan]], leading sports writer and acclaimed author of ''A False Spring''; [[Bob Sullivan (journalist)|Bob Sullivan]], two time New York Times Best Seller author and founding member of MSNBC.com.
*In  law  and  government, alumni include: [[Raymond J. Dearie]], Chief Judge of the United States District Court for the Eastern District of New York; [[Joseph P. Flynn]] and [[William J. Lavery]], Chief Judges of the Connecticut Appellant Court; James G. Gilbert, Chief Administrative Law Judge, [[United States Postal Service]]; [[Buddy Cianci]], mayor of Providence, Rhode Island; [[Martin Looney]], the Connecticut Senate Majority Leader; [[Jorge E. Pérez-Díaz]], Attorney General and Solicitor General of the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.
*In  medicine  and  science, alumni include: [[James Lewis Abbruzzese]], Chairman of the Department of Gastrointestinal Medical Oncology at the University of Texas M. D. Anderson Cancer Center; [[Peter Pronovost]], a 2008 Time 100 World's Most Influential People and MacArthur Fellow; [[John T. Lis]], a Guggenheim Fellow and Barbara McClintock Professor of Molecular Biology &amp; Genetics at Cornell University; [[Brian Monahan]], the Attending Physician of the United States Congress.
*In  [[social justice]], alumni include: [[G. Simon Harak]], a Pax Christi National Peacemaker of the Year; [[Paula Donovan]], the founding executive director of AIDS-Free World; [[Joseph Moylan]], founder and president of Durham Nativity School.
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
Image:E_Gerald_Corrigan.gif|[[E. Gerald Corrigan]], &lt;br&gt; [[Federal Reserve Bank of New York|7th President of Federal Reserve Bank of New York]]
File:Brian Monahan.JPG|[[Brian Monahan]], &lt;br&gt; [[Attending Physician of the United States Congress|Attending Physician of the U.S. Congress]]
Image:Kathleen Murphy.jpg|[[Kathleen Murphy]], &lt;br&gt; [[Fortune (magazine)|''Fortune'' 50 Most Powerful Women in Business]]
File:Joseph Russoniello.jpg|[[Joseph Russoniello]], &lt;br&gt; [[U.S. Attorney for the Northern District of California|U.S. Attorney, Northern District of California]]
File:Donatella Arpaia.jpg| [[Donatella Arpaia]],&lt;br/&gt;New York's 50 Most Powerful Women&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

*''See also:'' ''[[:Category:Fairfield University alumni|Fairfield University alumni]]''

===Notable benefactors===
Among the large donors  are: Rudolf F. Bannow, Swedish-American industrialist and namesake of the Rudolf F. Bannow Science Center.;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vasaorden.se/en/index.htm?page=/en/asa/1960.asp Vasa Order of America: Rudolf F. Bannow Profile]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[E. Gerald Corrigan|E. Gerald Corrigan '63]], former 7th President [[Federal Reserve Bank of New York]] and namesake of the E. Gerald Corrigan Endowed Chair in the Humanities and Social Sciences; [[Charles Dolan|Charles F. Dolan '04]], founder of HBO and Cablevision and namesake of the [[Charles F. Dolan School of Business]] and Dolan Campus; [[Joseph DiMenna|Joseph A. DiMenna, Jr. '80]], founding Managing Director of Zweig-DiMenna Associates; namesake of the [[DiMenna-Nyselius Library]]; [[William P. Egan|William P. Egan '67]], founding Partner at [[Alta Communications]]; namesake of the Egan Chapel of St. Ignatius of Loyola; Steve Lessing '80, Managing Director of Barclays and namesake of [[Lessing Field]]; Roger Lynch '63, former Partner of Goldman Sachs and namesake of the Roger M. Lynch Professor of Economics; Gustav Nyselius, Swedish-American Industrialist and namesake of the [[DiMenna-Nyselius Library]].;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vasaorden.se/en/index.htm?page=/en/asa/1971.asp Vasa Order of America: Gustav Nyselius Profile]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leslie C. Quick Jr.|Leslie C. Quick Jr. H'99]], founder of Quick &amp; Reilly and namesake of the Leslie C. Quick Jr. Recreational Complex and [[Regina A. Quick Center for the Arts]]; [[Fay Vincent|Fay Vincent Jr. '08]], former Commissioner of [[Major League Baseball]] and creator of the need-based Alice Lynch Vincent Scholarship.;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=30 |title=Fay Vincent gives Fairfield University $2 million for scholarships |publisher=Fairfield University |date=December 1, 1996 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Thomas J. Walsh Jr., former President &amp; Chairman of Colonial Wire and Cable and namesake of the Thomas J. Walsh, Jr. Athletic Center and Thomas J. Walsh Art Gallery.

==Publications and media==
*''Campus Currents'' – The Official News Publication of Fairfield University&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/publications/cc_index.html |title=Campus Currents |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Fairfield Now'' – The Magazine of Fairfield University&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/publications/fn_index.html |title=Fairfield Now |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Press Room'' – Fairfield University's Electronic News Room&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/index.html |title=Fairfield University's Electronic News Room |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''In The News'' – News media highlights featuring Fairfield University&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.fairfield.edu/inthenews/ |title=In The News |publisher=Blog.fairfield.edu |date=November 8, 2011 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Fairfield University News'' – Fairfield University's YouTube news and information video center
*''[[Fairfield Mirror|The Mirror]]'' – The Independent Student Newspaper of Fairfield University
*''The Reluctant Environmentalist'' – Blogging about Earth-friendly living at Fairfield University&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.fairfield.edu/redtogreen/ The Reluctant Environmentalist]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[WVOF]]'' – Student operated radio station featuring the best blend of public radio and college programming
*''[[The HAM Channel (Fairfield University Student Television)|The Ham Channel]]'' – Fairfield University's student run television on YouTube

===Academic journals===
*''[[Mezzo Cammin]]'' – An online journal devoted to [[New Formalism|New Formalist]] poetry by women, as well as to bringing renewed attention to female poets of the past who wrote in [[Verse forms|form]]. This journal was associated with Fairfield university until 2010, when its editor-in-chief and former Fairfield professor [[Kim Bridgford]] took a position at another university.
*'' Mason's Road'' – An online literary and arts journal sponsored by Fairfield University's MFA in Creative Writing, accepting submissions in fiction, poetry, creative nonfiction, drama, art, and audio.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.masonsroad.com/ |title=Mason'Road – An online literary and arts journal |publisher=Masonsroad.com |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media Center===
The Media Center is a {{convert|15000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} facility located on the ground floor of Xavier Hall that houses the New Media: Film, Television, and Radio major, the Campus Television Network and the student run HAM Channel. It operates a {{convert|32|ft|m|sing=on}} television production [[Communications satellite|satellite]] [[uplink]] truck that can transmit and receive digitally encoded television signals from [[geostationary]] domestic [[satellites]]. Fairfield   is one of few colleges in the nation to have this technology allowing campus programming and international news organizations including [[CNN]], [[MSNBC]], [[Fox News]] and [[Bloomberg Television]] to be broadcast worldwide from the University.

The Media Center staff and New Media students have won national recognition for their  programs and production of multimedia presentations for the university. The Media Center has received  a Bronze [[Telly Award]] in 2001&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=478 |title=Media Center wins Telly Award for video production |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one Silver Telly Award and three Bronze Telly Awards in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1076 |title=Fairfield University Media Center wins three Telly Awards, Student video secures a fourth Telly |publisher=Fairfield University |date=March 22, 2004 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other recent honors have included the Crystal Award of Distinction from the Communicator Awards 2005 Print Competition; two Awards of Excellence from the Videographer 2005 Awards; and the Platinum BEST of Show from The Aurora 2005 Awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1436 |title=Fairfield University Media Center wins Platinum BEST of Show in major film and video competition |publisher=Fairfield University |date=November 15, 2005 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1333 |title=Fairfield University Media Center wins four awards in international competitions |publisher=Fairfield University |date=May 19, 2005 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Residence life==
===Residence halls===
[[Image:Fairfield Dolan Hall.JPG|thumb|left|300px|John C. Dolan Hall]]
Fairfield University guarantees first year students four years of campus housing and provides several housing options depending on their class. Most underclassman live on campus and live the typical [[residence hall]] life in the '''Quad''' or '''The Orient''' sections of campus. '''The Quad''' is located in the northwest corner of campus and consists of Campion Hall, Joques Hall, Gonzaga Hall, Loyola Hall, and Regis Hall. Students typically choose to live in The Quad in order to be close to the classroom buildings and to enjoy the annual battle of dorms water fights; and frisbee and wiffleball games during the warm weather. '''The Orient''' is located in the southeast corner of campus and consists of Kostka Hall and Claver Hall which is suite style living, and also the apartments, the newest on campus housing. This section earned its nickname because the original names of the residence halls located in that area were &quot;Southeast&quot; (now Kostka) and &quot;Far East&quot; (now Claver). Though the names were changed in the 1980s, the nickname survived as a non sequitur.  '''Dolan Hall''' is located in the northeast corner of campus is the primary residence hall for students who request to live in singles housing. This building also holds some freshman doubles.

===Residential Colleges===
Loyola Hall is home to the '''Ignatian Residential College''', which offers a unique [[residential college]] experience for Fairfield sophomores. Funded by a $2 million grant from the [[Lilly Endowment]], the program provides over 200 students with the opportunity to study and live together while pondering questions of identity, faith and purpose. In addition to living together and taking two classes together students meet once per month in groups of ten with a mentor, hear from weekly speakers, attend one overnight retreat per semester, and take cultural trips.

St. Ignatius House, the former Jesuit community house, will be home to the '''Just-Us Residential College'''. The program will allow up to 140 sophomores,   committed to community service and social justice, to go beyond the small community service groups at Campus Ministry and live with a group of individuals concerned with life outside of Fairfield County. The program is not inherently religious, but should attract students of all faiths, races and socioeconomic backgrounds who want to do something to help the Fairfield community and beyond.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfieldmirror.com/editorial_just-us-1.1314693 Editorial: Just-Us]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Upperclassmen alternatives===
Upperclassmen   choose between living at the  Townhouse Complex ,  the Apartment Village, or [[Fairfield Beach, Connecticut|Fairfield Beach]]. The 10 unit  Townhouse Complex is a series of 104 two-story student townhouses for 469 juniors and seniors. There are between five and seven students living in each townhouse which has two or three bedrooms upstairs, a living and dining area, a kitchen and two bathrooms. In 2007, townhouse basements have been closed off to students, after an incident in which the administration and Fairfield fire department deemed the basements a fire hazard. During the warmer weather students enjoy their back porches and lawns with an occasional barbecue and wiffleball game. The  Apartment Village   was opened in September 2000. These apartment-style residences house 192 juniors and seniors. Each apartment contains four single bedrooms, two full bathrooms, a kitchen and a living room.   Fairfield Beach is  a unique Fairfield living experience for 200 eligible students to rent beach houses along the Long Island Sound. It historically has been the center of off-campus social life hosting such Fairfield traditions as the Clam Jam and Mock Weddings. However, as it  has evolved from a part-time summer beach community into a more permanent residential community, Fairfield Beach has become a source of strain on town-gown relations leading to greater controls over student social life including a ban on large gatherings at Lantern Point since 2001 due to a court injunction.{{cite}}

==Student life==
===Community service===
The goal of Jesuit education is ''homines pro aliis'', “men and women for others”. As a result, Fairfield students are involved in many [[community service]] opportunities.  Fairfield was among just 119 colleges in the nation named to the Carnegie Classification for Community Engagement in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/descriptions/community_engagement.php?key=1213 The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching: Community Engagement Classification Elective], accessed December 4, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  Further, the University was named to the 2009 and 2010 President's Higher Education Community Service Honor Roll by the [[Learn and Serve America]] Program of the [[Corporation for National and Community Service]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.learnandserve.gov/about/programs/higher_ed_honorroll.asp President's Higher Education Community Service Honor Roll], accessed December 4, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Locally, the award-winning '''Annual Hunger Clean Up''' is a one-day service-a-thon where the entire university community joins together to work at 40-plus local agency sites throughout Fairfield County  and to raise money for local and national [[hunger]] and [[homelessness]] causes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfield.edu/student/cmsj_hunger.html Annual Hunger Clean Up]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Fairfield chapter of '''Colleges Against Cancer''' hosts an annual [[American Cancer Society]] [[Relay for Life]], an overnight event designed to spread awareness of cancer prevention, treatments and cures, celebrate [[cancer survivors]] and raise money for [[cancer research]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.fairfieldmirror.com/media/storage/paper148/news/2008/04/24/CampusLife/All-Aboard.For.Relay.For.Life-3342805.shtml All aboard for Relay for Life!]&lt;/ref&gt;  The '''[[Family literacy|Adrienne Kirby Family Literacy Project]]''', recognized as a model program by the [[Corporation for National and Community Service]], involves about 175 Fairfield student-volunteers a year in providing individual tutoring to preschool children  at the Action for Bridgeport Community Development's [[Head Start Program|Early Learning/Head Start Program]].&lt;ref name=&quot;query.nytimes.com&quot;/&gt;

Internationally, '''Ignatian Solidarity Corps''' volunteers annually participate in two-week international service trips during their spring and winter breaks traveling to [[Ecuador]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zwire.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=19365140&amp;BRD=1653&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=12717&amp;rfi=6 Fairfield students provide aid in Ecuador]{{Dead link|date=June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mexico]], Jamaica, [[Belize]] and [[Haiti]].  In 2004, Mikaela Conley '06 and Aamina Awan '07 founded '''The Afghan Children's Project''' to raise awareness and funds for children who have suffered the effects of war, violence, and poverty in the heart of [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://afghanchildrensproject.org/background.html |title=The Afghan Children's Project: Background |publisher=Afghanchildrensproject.org |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Both were interviewed on [[CNN Daybreak]] in August 2005 for their work in funding the building of a [[water well]] for Aloudine, a small village outside [[Kabul]], desperate for clean drinking water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/documents/publications/fn_fall05.pdf |title=A Well That Runs Deep |format=PDF |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  And in 2008, nine Fairfield students, inspired by 2006 [[Nobel Peace Prize]] recipient [[Muhammad Yunus]] and the [[Grameen Bank]], started '''Sustainable Equity for Women''', a [[micro-lending]] project designed to raise and invest money in small businesses run by women in [[developing countries]] in conjunction with
[[Kiva (organization)|Kiva Microfunds]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2049 |title=Fairfield University seniors leave legacy of micro-lending project, Sustainable Equity for Women (SEW) |publisher=Fairfield University |date=May 14, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diversity===
In total, the   student body hails from 32 states, Washington, D.C., [[Puerto Rico]], the [[U.S. Virgin Islands]], and 45 foreign countries. 13% of undergraduate students are African American, [[Hispanic]], Asian American, Native American ([[AHANA]]), or [[multiracial]]. Valuing a mix of experiences in the classroom and on campus, increasing [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] at Fairfield is a major goal of the University's Strategic Vision,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/documents/publications/fn_winter06.pdf |title=Fairfield's Strategic Vision: Windows to the Future |format=PDF |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2005, during the University's [[Martin Luther King, Jr. Day|Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Holiday Celebration and Convocation]], the [[Jeffrey P. von Arx|Rev. Jeffrey P. von Arx, S.J.]], called on the university   to join him in efforts to increase [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] at the institution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=1237 |title=Fairfield President pledges campus-wide effort to increase diversity |publisher=Fairfield University |date=January 27, 2005 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  For this reason, the '''Office of Institutional Diversity Initiatives''' and the '''Office of Student Diversity Programs'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/student/sd_about.html |title=Office of Student Diversity Programs |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; were created to pursue a number of initiatives to increase [[Race and ethnicity in the United States Census|racial]] and [[socioeconomic]] [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]]. These [[Diversity (politics)|diversity]] initiatives are helped annually by the Fairfield Awards Dinner held in New York City in which funds are raised for '''The Alumni Multicultural Scholarship Fund'''. The 2008 Fairfield Awards Dinner raised a record-breaking $1.1 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2035 |title=Record-breaking $1.1 million raised by Fairfield University for drive to increase diversity |publisher=Fairfield University |date=April 17, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Fairfield Barone Campus Center.JPG|thumb|left|300px|John A. Barone Campus Center]]

===Fairfield University Student Association===
The Fairfield University Student Association (FUSA) is the official student association for full-time undergraduate students and is the largest student organization on campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/fusa/ |title=Fairfield University Student Association (FUSA) |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The association exists to represent student issues and concerns to the faculty and administration and to sponsor a multitude of student programs and activities. All full-time undergraduate students are members. The association is organized into three branches –  legislative', executive, and  judicial. The  legislative branch  consists of the '''Student Senate''', comprising 40 elected representatives (10 from each undergraduate class year). The  executive branch  is headed by the popularly elected  President  of FUSA, who serves as the official spokesperson for undergraduate students in addition to administering the student association on a daily basis. In 2002, Karen Donoghue '03 became the first women elected President of FUSA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3DD133BF932A05750C0A9649C8B63&amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fOrganizations%2fF%2fFairfield%20University Kenneth Best, &quot;Fairfield University's B.W.O.C.,&quot; [[New York Times]], March 31, 2002.]&lt;/ref&gt; The FUSA President is assisted by a popularly elected Vice President, elected class officers, and a number of other appointed officers, including the Executive Director of Programming and the Executive Director of Clubs &amp; Organizations. The  judicial branch,  known as the Student Court,  serves as a hearing body in certain student conduct cases, as well as performing the judicial functions required for the student association.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/documents/student/sl_sthandbook.pdf |title=Fairfield University Student Handbook |format=PDF |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student activism===
A central tenet of a [[Jesuit]] education is the promotion of the [[values]] of [[peace]] and [[social justice]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/cas/pj_index.html |title=Program in Peace and Justice Studies |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Fairfield University students have embraced and reflected these values in their own [[student activism]]. In 1988, 1989 and 1990, the '''Coalition for a Better World''' constructed &quot;Cardboard City&quot; and held a 36 hour vigil,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.fairfield.edu/u?/fuhp,240 |title=Cardboard City on the patio of Barone Campus Center |publisher=Digital.fairfield.edu |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and again in 2008, the '''Students for Social Justice''' similarly constructed &quot;Homeless Village&quot; and hosted the [[Oxfam|&quot;Oxfam Hunger Banquet&quot;]] to raise awareness of the plight of the [[homeless]] in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.fairfieldmirror.com/media/storage/paper148/news/2008/01/31/News/Food-For.Thought.Students.For.Social.Justice.Host.Hunger.Banquet-3176960.shtml Food for thought: Students for Social Justice host Hunger Banquet]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1999, students staged an 11-hour sit-in at the home of the university president and later a [[hunger strike]] to protest a contracting company used by the university that the students said was anti-union and paid janitors poorly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D9143DF930A25752C1A96F958260 |title=Six Students End Hunger Strike After Fairfield Drops Contractor |work=New York Times |date=November 13, 1999 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Each year, the Students for Social Justice travel to [[Columbus, Georgia]] for the annual [[School of the Americas Watch]] protest at a combat training school for Latin American soldiers now known as the [[Western Hemisphere Institute for Security Cooperation]]. The date of the protest marks the anniversary of the murder of six [[Jesuit]] priests, their maid, and her daughter in [[El Salvador]] at the hands of soldiers trained at the School of the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/student/cmsj_social_justice.html |title=Fairfield University: Social Justice: School of the Americas Protest |publisher=Fairfield University |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  And in 2008, '''Fairfield for Peace NOW''' created &quot;Hope Trail&quot;, a pathway of flags around campus symbolizing the cost in life and casualties from the [[Iraq War]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=2019 |title=Fairfield University students erect symbols of Iraq war casualties |publisher=Fairfield University |date=April 8, 2008 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;A Cry For Peace&quot;, a play written and performed with Theatre Fairfield demonstrating the toll of the [[Iraq War]] on the families of soldiers back in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.fairfieldmirror.com/media/storage/paper148/news/2008/05/01/Commentary/Editorial.Fairfield.Shows.Activism-3357368.shtml Fairfield shows activism]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student clubs &amp; organizations===
All student clubs and organizations comprise the Student Organization Board of Governors (SOBOG), which is governed by a board of governors and administered by a chairperson selected by members of student organizations. SOBOG exists to encourage student involvement and participation in approximately 80 clubs and organizations each year including the Glee Club, Jazz Ensemble, Pep Band, Dance Team, Stag in the Stands, Habitat for Humanity, Asian Student Association, mission volunteer trips, and Theater Fairfield. The oldest club on campus is the [[Fairfield University Glee Club]] which celebrated its 60th anniversary in 2007. The Fairfield University Debate Team of Jason LaRue '99 and Courtney Darts '01 won first place at the 1998 Columbia University [[Parliamentary debate|Parliamentary Debate Tournament]] beating 69 other teams, including teams from Harvard, Johns Hopkins, Princeton, Yale and Williams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fairfield.edu/press/pr_index.html?id=126 |title=Debate Team wins major tournament |publisher=Fairfield University |date=December 1, 1998 |accessdate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student media===
[[Image:Fairfield Ham Channel logo.png|frame|right|125px]]
*''The Cream Filling'' – The Student Artistic, Literary, and Cultural Special-Interest Magazine of Fairfield University
*''Dogwood'' – A Journal of Poetry and Prose
*[[The HAM Channel]] – The Student Television Station of Fairfield University
*[[Fairfield Mirror|The Mirror]] – The Independent Student Newspaper of Fairfield University
*''The Mirror Sports Blog'' – The Independent Student Sports Blog of Fairfield University Athletics
*''The Sound'' – The Student Literary Magazine of Fairfield University
*[[WVOF]] – The Voice of Fairfield University

===Traditions===
Student life at the Fairfield is marked by a number of unique traditions and celebrations:
*'''The Floating Naut''' – The Floating Naut is a weekly gathering of beach residents at student houses on the beach.  The location rotates each week.
*'''Stagstock''' – Stagstock is an all day, outdoor concert organized by the HAM Channel and WVOF each year. Stagstock brings together local bands, along with bigger, nationally recognized acts, and showcases them in a free concert. The concert is traditionally held in the Quad on the first weekend of the new school year.
*'''Mock Weddings''' – Mock Wedding, created by Chris Tucker '96 and Steve Xeller '96, is a long standing Fairfield tradition in which senior class members select peers to be part of a faux wedding ceremony at The Point at [[Fairfield Beach, Connecticut|Fairfield Beach]] followed by a wedding party at a local reception hall late in their final spring semester.
*'''Powder Puff''' – Powder Puff is a senior beach event that usually takes place in early November each year.
*'''Spring Week''' – Spring Week is a week full of Spring Events sponsored by various clubs and organizations culminating in May Day.  Coordinated by IRHA (Inter-Residential Housing Association)
*'''May Day''' – May Day sponsored by IRHA and is the last of Spring Week.  Free food, cheap drinks, music and fun events take over Lessing Field for the day long event.
*'''Clam Jam''' – Clam Jam is one of the final events held at the beach in late April.  The Point at [[Fairfield Beach, Connecticut|Fairfield Beach]] is jam packed with students celebrating the end of the school year.

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Fairfield University}}
*[http://www.fairfield.edu/ Official website]
*[http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=1073+n+benson+rd,+fairfield,+ct+06824+(fairfield+university)&amp;sll=39.352618,-76.707058&amp;sspn=0.007815,0.02105&amp;g=wabash+ave+%26+patterson+ave,+baltimore,+md+21215&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=1073+N+Benson+Rd,+Fairfield,+Connecticut+06824&amp;ll=41.161185,-73.253971&amp;spn=0,0.014613&amp;t=h&amp;z=17&amp;layer=c&amp;cbll=41.161267,-73.254019&amp;panoid=xLWJAHqHaGefcORSDODGNg&amp;cbp=12,249.45,,0,1.96 Fairfield University entrance on Google Maps]

{{Fairfield University}}
{{Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities}}
{{Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#FFFFFF;color:#C41E3A;border:1px solid #C41E3A;
|list =
{{ECAC Lacrosse League}}
{{America East}}
{{Colleges and universities in Connecticut}}
|state =autocollapse
}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1942]]
[[Category:Fairfield, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Fairfield University| ]]
[[Category:Jesuit universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Diocese of Bridgeport]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Fairfield County, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Telly Awards]]

[[de:Fairfield University]]
[[es:Universidad de Fairfield]]
[[zh:费尔菲尔德大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
