<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4939444" ns="0" title="The Simpsons (season 5)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox tvseason |
  | season_name = The Simpsons'' Season 5
  | bgcolour = #FD9D83
  | show_name = The Simpsons
  | image = [[File:Simpsons s5.png|200px]]
  | caption = ''The Simpsons'' Season 5 DVD
  | country = [[United States]]
  | network = [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]]
  | first_aired = September 30, 1993
  | last_aired = &lt;br&gt;May 19, 1994
  | region_1 = December 21, 2005
  | region_2 = March 21, 2005
  | region_4 = March 23, 2005
  | region_5 = May 27, 2010
  | num_episodes = 22
  | prev_season = [[The Simpsons (season 4)|Season 4]]
  | next_season = [[The Simpsons (season 6)|Season 6]]
  | episode_list = [[List of The Simpsons episodes|List of ''The Simpsons'' episodes]]
|}}
'''''The Simpsons''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt; fifth season''' originally aired on the [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] network between September 30, 1993 and May 19, 1994. The [[Showrunner|show runner]] for the fifth production season was [[David Mirkin]] who executive produced 20 episodes. [[Al Jean]] and [[Mike Reiss]] executive produced the remaining two, which were both hold overs that were produced for the [[The Simpsons (season 4)|previous season]]. The season contains some of the series' most acclaimed episodes, including &quot;[[Cape Feare]]&quot; and &quot;[[Rosebud (The Simpsons)|Rosebud]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;EW&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,417748~3~0~25bestand1,00.html|title=The Family Dynamic|accessdate=2008-04-06|date=2003-01-29|publisher=Entertainment Weekly}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also includes the 100th episode, &quot;[[Sweet Seymour Skinner's Baadasssss Song]]&quot;. The season was nominated for two [[Primetime Emmy Awards]] and won an [[Annie Award]] for Best Animated Television Program as well as an [[Environmental Media Award]] and a [[Genesis Award]]. The DVD box set was released in [[Region 1]] on December 21, 2004, Region 2 on March 21, 2005, and Region 4 on March 23, 2005.

==Production==
[[Image:Conan O'Brien - Simpsons (cropped).jpg|left|thumb|[[Conan O'Brien]] left the writing staff halfway through the season.]]
The season was the first to be executive produced by [[David Mirkin]], who would also run [[The Simpsons (season 6)|the following season]]. Several of the show's original writers who had worked on ''The Simpsons'' since the [[The Simpsons (season 1)|first season]] had left following the completion of season four. &quot;[[Cape Feare]]&quot;, which was the final episode to be produced by the &quot;original team&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;vitti&quot;/&gt; aired during this season as a hold over.&lt;ref name=&quot;vitti&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Vitti, Jon|date=2004|title=Commentary for the episode &quot;Cape Feare&quot;. The Simpsons: The Complete Fifth Season| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jay Kogen]], [[Wallace Wolodarsky]], [[Sam Simon]] and [[Jeff Martin (writer)|Jeff Martin]] wrote their final episodes for the season four production run. Show runners [[Al Jean]] and [[Mike Reiss]] left to produce their own series, ''[[The Critic]]'' but returned in subsequent seasons to produce more ''Simpsons'' episodes, and Jean again became the show runner starting with [[The Simpsons (season 13)|season thirteen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jean&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Jean, Al|date=2004|title=The Simpsons season 5 DVD commentary for the episode &quot;Cape Feare&quot;| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[George Meyer]] and [[John Swartzwelder]], [[Conan O'Brien]], [[Frank Mula]] and future show runners [[Bill Oakley]] and [[Josh Weinstein]] all stayed with the show following the previous season. O'Brien would leave the series halfway through the production of the season to host his own show, ''[[Late Night with Conan O'Brien]]''. He had been working on &quot;[[Homer Goes to College]]&quot; when he found out he was chosen to host ''Late Night'' and was forced to walk out on his contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;jean&quot;/&gt; He later had a cameo appearance in &quot;[[Bart Gets Famous]]&quot;. He recorded his part while ''Late Night'' was on the air, but O'Brien thought that his show might be canceled by the time the episode aired.&lt;ref name=&quot;BGF&quot;/&gt;

A whole new group of writers were brought in for this season. [[Jace Richdale]] was the first to be hired by Mirkin and others to receive their first writing credits were [[Greg Daniels]] and [[Dan McGrath]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Mirkin, David|date=2004|title=The Simpsons season 5 DVD commentary for the episode &quot;Burns' Heir&quot;| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mike Scully]] wrote &quot;[[Lisa's Rival]]&quot;, which was produced for this season, but aired the next. Two freelance writers wrote episodes: [[David Richardson (writer)|David Richardson]] wrote &quot;[[Homer Loves Flanders]]&quot; while Bill Canterbury received two writing credits. [[Bob Anderson (director)|Bob Anderson]] and [[Susie Dietter]], who had previously worked on the show as part of the animation staff, would direct their first episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;BGF&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Groening, Matt; Brooks, James L.; Mirkin, David; O'Brien, Conan; Dietter, Susie; Silverman, Davis|date=2004|title=Commentary for the episode &quot;Bart Gets Famous&quot;. The Simpsons: The Complete Fifth Season| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Anderson, Bob|date=2004|title=Commentary for the episode &quot;Bart's Inner Child&quot;. The Simpsons: The Complete Fifth Season| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Davidmirkin.jpg|right|200px|thumb|[[David Mirkin]] was the show runner for this season.|alt=A seated man wearing a cap smiles as he looks into the distance. His hands are crossed.]]
The season started off with &quot;[[Homer's Barbershop Quartet]]&quot; which was chosen as the season premiere because it guest starred [[George Harrison]]. The [[Fox Network]] executives had wanted to premiere with &quot;Homer Goes to College&quot; because it was an ''[[Animal House]]'' parody, but the writers felt &quot;Homer's Barbershop Quartet&quot; would be a better episode because of Harrison's involvement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Groening, Matt; Reiss, Mike; Jean, Al; Martin, Jeff; Azaria, Hank; Lovitz, Jon; Kirkland, Mark |date=2004|title=The Simpsons season 5 DVD commentary for the episode &quot;Homer's Barbershow Quartet&quot;| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though the episode aired during the beginning of the fifth season, &quot;[[Cape Feare]]&quot; was the last episode written by the original team of writers and guest starred [[Kelsey Grammer]] as [[Sideshow Bob]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vitti&quot;/&gt; Compared to previously produced episodes, the episode featured several elements that could be described as cartoonish.&lt;ref name=&quot;EW&quot;/&gt; This was a result of the staff's careless attitude towards the end of season four as the majority of them were leaving which, combined with the shortness of the episode, led to the creation of the [[rake (tool)|rake]] sequence, became a memorable moment for this episode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Jean, Al|date=2004|title=Commentary for the episode &quot;Cape Feare&quot;. The Simpsons: The Complete Fifth Season| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Cape Feare&quot; and &quot;[[Rosebud (The Simpsons)|Rosebud]]&quot; were both broadcast early in the season and are amongst the series' most acclaimed episodes, both having placed highly on ''Entertainment Weekly''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s list of the top 25 episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;EW&quot;/&gt; The episode &quot;[[Deep Space Homer]]&quot; was the only episode to be written by David Mirkin and was controversial amongst the show's writing staff when the episode was in production. Some of the writers felt that having Homer go into space was too &quot;large&quot; of an idea. [[Matt Groening]] felt that the idea was so big that it gave the writers &quot;nowhere to go&quot;. As a result, every aspect of the show was worked on to make the concept work. The writers focused more upon the relationship between Homer and his family and Homer's attempts to be a hero.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Groening, Matt; Mirkin, David; Silverman, David; Kirkland, Mark|date=2004|title=Commentary for the episode &quot;Cape Feare&quot;. The Simpsons: The Complete Fifth Season| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Sweet Seymour Skinner's Baadasssss Song]]&quot; was the series' 100th episode. It was chosen because it heavily featured Bart and was promoted as &quot;Bart's biggest prank ever,&quot; even though Bart did not actually pull any pranks in the episode;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Groening, Matt; Mirkin, David; Silverman, David; Oakley, Bill; Weinstein, Josh; Anderson, Bob|date=2004|title=Commentary for the episode &quot;Cape Feare&quot;. The Simpsons: The Complete Fifth Season| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; rather, Bart accidentally let his dog loose, eventually resulting in Principal Skinner's firing.  [[Cletus Spuckler]] and [[List of recurring characters from The Simpsons#Rich Texan|the Rich Texan]] were the only recurring characters to be introduced this season, first appearing in &quot;[[Bart Gets an Elephant]]&quot;, and &quot;[[$pringfield (Or, How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love Legalized Gambling)|$pringfield]]&quot; respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;BGE&quot;/&gt; Other minor characters who first appeared this season were [[List of recurring characters in The Simpsons#Luigi Risotto|Luigi]] and [[List of recurring characters from The Simpsons#Baby Gerald|Baby Gerald]]. Two more episodes, &quot;[[Bart of Darkness]]&quot; and &quot;[[Lisa's Rival]]&quot; were produced as part of the season five (1F) production run, but both aired [[The Simpsons (season 6)|the following season]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, pp. 148–150&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
''The Simpsons'' won an [[Annie Award]] for [[Annie Award for Best Animated Television Production|Best Animated Television Production]], while [[David Silverman]] received a nomination for &quot;Best Individual Achievement for Creative Supervision in the Field of Animation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;A22&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://annieawards.org/22ndwinners.html|title=Legacy: 22nd Annual Annie Award Nominees and Winners (1994)|accessdate=2008-04-06|publisher=Annie Awards}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Bart Gets an Elephant]]&quot; won both an [[Environmental Media Award]] for &quot;Best Television Episodic Comedy&quot; and a [[Genesis Award]] for &quot;Best Television Comedy Series&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDB&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096697/awards|title=Awards for &quot;The Simpsons&quot;|accessdate=2008-04-06|publisher=Internet Movie Database}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hsus.org/about_us/offices_and_affiliates/hsus_hollywood_office/the_genesis_awards/genesis_award_winners_and_memorable_moments/1995_genesis_awards.html|title=1995 Genesis Awards|accessdate=2008-04-06|publisher=Humane Society of the United States |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080224095632/http://www.hsus.org/about_us/offices_and_affiliates/hsus_hollywood_office/the_genesis_awards/genesis_award_winners_and_memorable_moments/1995_genesis_awards.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the [[Primetime Emmy Awards]], [[Alf Clausen]] and [[Greg Daniels]] received a nomination in the &quot;Outstanding Individual Achievement in Music and Lyrics&quot; category for the song &quot;Who Needs The Kwik-E-Mart?&quot; from the episode &quot;[[Homer and Apu]]&quot;. Clausen also was nominated for &quot;Outstanding Individual Achievement in Music Composition for a Series (Dramatic Underscore)&quot; for the episode &quot;[[Cape Feare]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.emmys.org/awards/awardsearch.php |title=Primetime Emmy Awards Advanced Search|publisher=Emmys.org|accessdate=2008-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers submitted episodes for &quot;[[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Comedy Series|Outstanding Comedy Series]]&quot; category rather than the &quot;[[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Animated Program (For Programming less than One Hour)|Outstanding Animated Program]]&quot; as they had previously done and were not nominated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jean&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Jean, Al|date=2004|title=The Simpsons season 4 DVD commentary for the episode &quot;[[Mr. Plow]]&quot;| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Casting about for an Emmy - Bart Simpson and Tim Allen aren't in the running for TV's big awards |date=1994-07-22|accessdate=2008-04-06|page=1|publisher=[[The Tampa Tribune]]|author=Walt Belcher}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The series was also nominated for a [[Saturn Award]] for &quot;Best Genre Television Series&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDB&quot;/&gt;

==Ratings==
Like the previous three seasons, ''The Simpsons'' aired Thursday at 8:00 pm in the United States and was coupled with the series ''[[The Sinbad Show]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Fox adds 6 hours of new shows in fall |date=1993-05-26|accessdate=2008-04-22|page=F2|publisher=''[[Waterloo Region Record|The Record]]''|author=Verne Gay}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Homer's Barbershop Quartet]]&quot;, the season premiere, finished 30th in the ratings with a [[Nielsen rating]] of 12.7.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nielsen ratings / Sept. 27 - Oct. 3|date=1993-10-06|accessdate=2008-04-22|page=D5|publisher=''[[Press-Telegram]]''|author=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Treehouse of Horror IV]]&quot;, which was broadcast on October 28, was the highest rated episode of the season, finishing 17th with a Nielsen rating of 14.5&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nielsen ratings / Oct. 26-Nov. 1|date=1993-11-03|accessdate=2008-04-22|page=C6|publisher=''[[Press-Telegram]]''|author=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; and finishing ninth in terms of viewers, being seen by approximately 24 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,308686,00.html|title=The Ratings - Off into the 'Sunset'|accessdate=2008-04-22|date=1993-11-12|publisher=''Entertainment Weekly''}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Secrets of a Successful Marriage]]&quot;, the season finale, aired during the week of May 16–22, 1994 and finished 43rd with a Nielsen rating of 9.8.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nielsen ratings / May 16–22 |date=1994-05-25|accessdate=2008-04-22|page=4E|publisher=[[Press-Telegram]]|author=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Episodes==
{{see also|List of The Simpsons episodes}}

;Key
* In the # column:
** The first number refers to the order it aired during the entire series.
** The second number refers to the episode number within its season.
*The production code refers to the code assigned to the episode by the production team. The first two characters refer to the season the episode was made for: 9F for season four, 1F for season five. The second number is the order the episode was produced, not the airing order. For example, 1F02 aired before 1F01.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turner&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Turner| first = Chris| title =[[Planet Simpson: How a Cartoon Masterpiece Documented an Era and Defined a Generation]]| isbn = 0-679-31318-4| page =4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:98%;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;| # !! style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;| Title !! style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;| Directed by !! style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;| Written by !! style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;|Original airdate !! style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;|Prod. code
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=82 - 1
 |Title=[[Homer's Barbershop Quartet]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|9|30}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[Jeff Martin (writer)|Jeff Martin]]
 |ProdCode=9F21
 |ShortSummary=In a flashback, [[Homer Simpson|Homer]] recounts his time with a barbershop quartet called The Be Sharps that also featured [[Seymour Skinner|Principal Skinner]], [[Apu Nahasapeemapetilon|Apu]] and [[Chief Wiggum]] who was later replaced with [[Barney Gumble|Barney]]. The group became music stars with their hit song &quot;Baby on Board&quot; and won a Grammy. Eventually, Homer started missing his family and the group began to lose its popularity, so it broke up.&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[George Harrison]], [[David Crosby]] and [[The Dapper Dans]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=83 - 2
 |Title=[[Cape Feare]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|10|7}}
 |Aux1=[[Rich Moore]]
 |Aux2=[[Jon Vitti]]
 |ProdCode=9F22
 |ShortSummary=[[Bart Simpson|Bart]] starts receiving threatening letters in the mail and it is soon revealed that they were sent to him by [[Sideshow Bob]]. Bob is released from prison, so Bart is placed in the [[Witness Protection Program|Witness Relocation Program]] and the [[Simpson family]] is moved to Terror Lake. However, Bob follows the Simpsons there and sneaks onto the family's [[house boat]] and tries to kill Bart. Cornered, Bart asks Bob to sing the entire score of ''[[HMS Pinafore]]'' as a last request. Bob does so, and during his performance the boat drifts through Springfield and Bob is caught.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Kelsey Grammer]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=84 - 3
 |Title=[[Homer Goes to College]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|10|14}}
 |Aux1=[[Jim Reardon]]
 |Aux2=[[Conan O'Brien]]
 |ProdCode=1F02
 |ShortSummary=After failing a test at the nuclear plant, Homer's lack of a college degree is revealed and he is sent back to pass a nuclear physics class. Homer, having seen too many bad ''[[Animal House]]'' knock-off movies, goofs off, so he is sent to a group of boys for tutoring. The boys, who are stereotypical nerds, try to help Homer, but he instead tries to help them party and decides to pull a prank on another college. They steal Springfield A&amp;M's mascot, but his friends are caught and expelled. Homer invites them to live with him, but his family soon become angered by their new housemates, so Homer decides to try to help them get back into college. He succeeds, but fails his final exam, so Marge convinces him to return to college for another year.&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 122&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=85 - 4
 |Title=[[Rosebud (The Simpsons episode)|Rosebud]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|10|21}}
 |Aux1=[[Wes Archer]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=1F01
 |ShortSummary=After a disastrous birthday party, [[Montgomery Burns|Mr. Burns]] pines for his long-lost childhood toy, a teddy bear named Bobo. The bear ends up in the hands of [[Maggie Simpson|Maggie]] and when Homer discovers this, he tries to use the bear to get a large reward from Burns. When Burns agrees, Homer tries to hand the bear over, but is stopped by Maggie. Homer, seeing that Maggie has become attached to the bear, decides not to give it back to Mr. Burns, who promises that Homer will regret the decision. Mr. Burns later returns and talks to Maggie and she eventually gives it back to him.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Ramones|The Ramones]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=86 - 5
 |Title=[[Treehouse of Horror IV]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|10|28}}
 |Aux1=[[David Silverman]]
 |Aux2=[[Greg Daniels]] &amp; [[Dan McGrath]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bill Oakley]] &amp; [[Josh Weinstein]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bill Canterbury]] and [[Conan O'Brien]]
 |ProdCode=1F04
 |ShortSummary=In a parody of ''[[Night Gallery]]'', Bart tells three scary stories based on paintings:&lt;br/&gt;'''The Devil and Homer Simpson''' – Homer sells his soul to the Devil ([[Ned Flanders]]) for a doughnut.&lt;br&gt;'''Terror at 5½ Feet''' – While riding the bus to school, Bart discovers that there is a Gremlin on the side of the bus.&lt;br&gt;'''Bart Simpson's Dracula''' – The Simpsons are invited to a dinner with Mr. Burns, where Bart and [[Lisa Simpson|Lisa]] discover that Mr. Burns is a vampire.&lt;br&gt;Guest stars: [[Frank Welker]] and [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 124–125&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=87 - 6
 |Title=[[Marge on the Lam]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|11|4}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[Bill Canterbury]]
 |ProdCode=1F03
 |ShortSummary=[[Marge Simpson|Marge]] and neighbor [[List of recurring characters from The Simpsons#Ruth Powers|Ruth Powers]] have a girls' night. Meanwhile, Homer tries to have fun without Marge and [[Lionel Hutz]] is hired as Bart, Lisa, and Maggie's babysitter. Homer hitches a ride home with Chief Wiggum, who is following behind Marge and Ruth and decides to pull them over. However, Ruth speeds her car up and reveals to Marge that she stole it from her ex-husband. Marge decides to stay with Ruth, but eventually the police catch up with them and the charges are dismissed.&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[George Fenneman]], [[Pamela Reed]] and [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=88 - 7
 |Title=[[Bart's Inner Child]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|11|11}}
 |Aux1=[[Bob Anderson (director)|Bob Anderson]]
 |Aux2=[[George Meyer]]
 |ProdCode=1F05
 |ShortSummary=Marge realizes that she is no fun because of her constant nagging and seeks help from self-help guru Brad Goodman, who then uses Bart's irreverent attitude as a new example of how people should behave. The entire town of [[Springfield (The Simpsons)|Springfield]] begins to act like Bart, who at first enjoys things but begins to feel that his role as a troublemaker is usurped. During the inaugural &quot;Do what you feel&quot; festival, several things go wrong and the town decides to stop acting like Bart.&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[James Brown (musician)|James Brown]], [[Albert Brooks]] and [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=89 - 8
 |Title=[[Boy-Scoutz N the Hood]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|11|18}}
 |Aux1=[[Jeffrey Lynch]]
 |Aux2=[[Dan McGrath]]
 |ProdCode=1F06
 |ShortSummary=Bart and Milhouse find $20.00 on the street and buy a Squishee made entirely of syrup. After a night of bingeing and carousing, Bart wakes up to discover that he has joined a Boy Scouts-esque troupe called &quot;The Junior Campers&quot;. Bart initially hates the group, then enjoys it, until Homer agrees to participate in their river-rafting trip. In a boat with Ned and [[List of recurring characters in The Simpsons#Rod Flanders|Rod Flanders]], Homer loses their map and the boat gets lost in the ocean. After being stuck out at sea for several days, they discover an oil rig with a Krusty Burger and are saved.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Ernest Borgnine]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 128–129&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=90 - 9
 |Title=[[The Last Temptation of Homer]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|12|9}}
 |Aux1=[[Carlos Baeza]]
 |Aux2=[[Frank Mula]]
 |ProdCode=1F07
 |ShortSummary=Mr. Burns hires a female worker named Mindy Simmons in accordance with government policy and Homer is worried that his crush on her will ruin his marriage with Marge. Both Mindy and Homer have feelings for each other, but in the end Homer decides not to cheat on Marge. Meanwhile, Bart becomes a nerd after doctors find several things physically wrong with him and apply treatments that make him look like a nerd.&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Michelle Pfeiffer]], [[Werner Klemperer]] and [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 130&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=91 - 10
 |Title=[[$pringfield (Or, How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love Legalized Gambling)]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1993|12|16}}
 |Aux1=[[Wes Archer]]
 |Aux2=[[Bill Oakley]] &amp; [[Josh Weinstein]]
 |ProdCode=1F08
 |ShortSummary=After the local economy stalls, everyone in town votes for gambling to be legalized, prompting Mr. Burns to open a casino. Homer becomes a blackjack dealer, and Marge becomes so addicted to gambling that she forgets about her family life. Meanwhile, Bart opens up his own casino after being kicked out of Mr. Burns's and Lisa struggles to have her costume done for a school pageant. Homer agrees to help her, but does a terrible job, so he decides to go to the casino to get Marge back.&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Robert Goulet]] and [[Gerry Cooney]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 131&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=92 - 11
 |Title=[[Homer the Vigilante]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|1|6}}
 |Aux1=[[Jim Reardon]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=1F09
 |ShortSummary=A crime wave hits Springfield, caused by the elusive cat burglar and Lisa's saxophone is stolen, so Homer agrees to try to get it back. The police are ineffective, so Flanders creates a neighborhood watch group, which Homer takes charge of. However, Homer's incompetence causes the vigilante group to commit more crimes than it prevents, and they are unsuccessful in catching the cat burglar. With the help of [[Abraham Simpson|Grampa]], Homer discovers that the burglar is a charming senior named Malloy. Malloy is arrested, but he tricks the citizens of Springfield into thinking he's hidden millions of dollars and escapes during the ensuing rush to find the money.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Sam Neill]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=93 - 12
 |Title=[[Bart Gets Famous]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|2|3}}
 |Aux1=[[Susie Dietter]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=1F11
 |ShortSummary=After sneaking away from a school trip to a box factory, Bart sneaks onto the set of the [[Krusty the Clown]] show. He gets a job as Krusty's production assistant and soon becomes sick of the job. One day, he is close to quitting, but Krusty runs up and says he needs to use Bart in a sketch. Bart becomes an accidental star when he says, &quot;I didn't do it&quot; during the botched sketch. He becomes famous but soon becomes tired of being known for one line. Marge convinces him that the main thing is to make people happy, so Bart decides to continue, but the audience soon becomes tired of Bart's act and forgets about him.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Conan O'Brien]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=94 - 13
 |Title=[[Homer and Apu]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|2|10}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[Greg Daniels]]
 |ProdCode=1F10
 |ShortSummary=After twice getting food poisoning from expired food sold at the [[Kwik-E-Mart]], Homer teams up with [[Kent Brockman]] to report Apu. Apu is fired from his job and comes to stay with the Simpsons, and he is replaced by actor [[James Woods]]. Homer resolves to help Apu get his old job back, and the two travel to India to talk to the owner of the Kwik-E-Mart, but are unsuccessful. Apu decides to visit his old Kwik-E-Mart and saves James Woods' life. Woods is so grateful that he helps Apu get re-hired.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[James Woods]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 134&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=95 - 14
 |Title=[[Lisa vs. Malibu Stacy]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|2|17}}
 |Aux1=[[Jeffrey Lynch]]
 |Aux2=[[Bill Oakley]] &amp; [[Josh Weinstein]]
 |ProdCode=1F12
 |ShortSummary=Lisa protests against the phrases on her new Talking Malibu Stacy doll, which she finds demeaning to women. She tracks down the reclusive creator Stacy to make a more politically correct doll. Meanwhile, Grampa is worried that he is getting old, so he takes a job at Krusty Burger. Lisa and Stacy create &quot;Lisa Lionheart&quot; which gets a lot of positive buzz, but is a flop when the Malibu Stacy executives release a new doll that comes with a hat.&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Kathleen Turner]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 135&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=96 - 15
 |Title=[[Deep Space Homer]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|2|24}}
 |Aux1=[[Carlos Baeza]]
 |Aux2=[[David Mirkin]]
 |ProdCode=1F13
 |ShortSummary=[[NASA]] decides that they need to hire average joes in order to get higher television ratings. They recruit Homer and Barney to train to be the first average American in space. Homer, who wants to be respected, is the winner by default, and goes into space with [[Buzz Aldrin]]. While there, he causes a lot of havoc and eventually breaks the handle on the space shuttle's hatch. Homer inadvertently seals the door shut with an inanimate carbon rod, and the shuttle returns to Earth. The rod is hailed as a hero, but Homer gains the respect of Aldrin and his family.&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Buzz Aldrin]] and [[James Taylor]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 136–137&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=97 - 16
 |Title=[[Homer Loves Flanders]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|3|17}}
 |Aux1=[[Wes Archer]]
 |Aux2=[[David Richardson (writer)|David Richardson]]
 |ProdCode=1F14
 |ShortSummary=Homer begins to like Flanders after being invited to a football game. However, Homer's constant presence around Flanders and his family causes Ned to feel hate for Homer. One day while trying to drive away from Homer, Flanders is arrested and charged with drunk driving. Flanders begins to lose the respect of the church congregation until Homer sticks up for him. Flanders thanks Homer and the two remain friends.&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 138&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=98 - 17
 |Title=[[Bart Gets an Elephant]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|3|31}}
 |Aux1=[[Jim Reardon]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=1F15
 |ShortSummary=While stuck cleaning the house, Bart wins a radio contest and chooses a gag prize, an [[elephant]], instead of the real prize, $10,000 cash. The radio station eventually gets Bart his elephant, which is named Stampy. When taking care of Stampy gets too expensive Homer decides to sell him to an ivory dealer rather than turn him over to a non-profit Animal Refuge. Bart tries to run away with Stampy, but the elephant escapes. They track him down, and Homer agrees to give him to the Animal Refuge.&lt;ref name=&quot;BGE&quot;&gt;Richmond, p. 139&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=99 - 18
 |Title=[[Burns' Heir]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|4|14}}
 |Aux1= [[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2= [[Jace Richdale]]
 |ProdCode=1F16
 |ShortSummary=Mr. Burns has a near-death experience which prompts him to find an heir to inherit his wealth after he dies. Bart is rejected, but Burns soon decides to choose him after seeing that Bart is &quot;a creature of pure malevolence&quot;. Marge convinces Bart to go spend some time with Burns, and soon becomes more disruptive than normal to his own family and decides to go live with Mr. Burns. Bart eventually starts to miss his family, but Burns manipulates him into staying. Burns tries to have Bart prove his loyalty by firing Homer, but Bart instead decides to go back to living with his family.&lt;br&gt;Guest star: [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 140&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=100 - 19
 |Title=[[Sweet Seymour Skinner's Baadasssss Song]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|4|28}}
 |Aux1=[[Bob Anderson (The Simpsons director)|Bob Anderson]]
 |Aux2=[[Bill Oakley]] &amp; [[Josh Weinstein]]
 |ProdCode=1F18
 |ShortSummary=Bart accidentally gets Principal Skinner fired after he brings [[Santa's Little Helper]] to school for show and tell. Bart feels guilty for what he did, and befriends Skinner. Meanwhile, Ned Flanders is hired as principal and the school goes to pot. Bart decides that while he enjoys having Skinner as a friend, he needs him as an enemy, but discovers that he returned to the Army to be a sergeant. Bart convinces Skinner to return and they get Flanders fired so that Skinner can get his old job back.&lt;br&gt;Guest star: [[Frank Welker]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 141&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=101 - 20
 |Title=[[The Boy Who Knew Too Much]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|5|5}}
 |Aux1=[[Jeffrey Lynch]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=1F19
 |ShortSummary=
Bart plays hooky from school and ends up at the birthday party of Freddy Quimby, the Mayor's nephew, where Freddy is accused of assaulting a waiter. Bart knows the truth, but would have to admit that he was playing hooky if he testifies. Meanwhile, Homer is chosen for jury duty in the assault case against Freddy Quimby and takes advantage of being sequestered in a hotel.&lt;br&gt;Guest star: [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 142–143&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=102 - 21
 |Title=[[Lady Bouvier's Lover]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|5|12}}
 |Aux1=[[Wes Archer]]
 |Aux2=[[Bill Oakley]] &amp; [[Josh Weinstein]]
 |ProdCode=1F21
 |ShortSummary=While attending Maggie's first birthday party, Grampa falls for Marge's mother Jackie. Grampa and Jackie start dating, but he is soon pushed aside in favor of Mr. Burns. Burns and Jackie are soon engaged to be married, much to the chagrin of Marge and [[Waylon Smithers|Smithers]]. Grampa [[Wedding crashing|crashes the wedding]] and tries to get Jackie back, but she decides that she doesn't want to be married. Meanwhile, Bart steals Homer's credit card to buy a piece of Itchy and Scratchy memorabilia that turns out to be a rip-off.&lt;br&gt;Guest star: [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 144&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=103 - 22
 |Title=[[Secrets of a Successful Marriage]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1994|5|19}}
 |Aux1=[[Carlos Baeza]]
 |Aux2=[[Greg Daniels]]
 |ProdCode=1F20
 |ShortSummary=Tired of being called &quot;slow,&quot; Homer signs up to teach a class on keeping a successful marriage at a learning annex. He is an unsuccessful teacher and finds that the only way he can keep the class interested is to tell racy secrets about Marge and their bedroom antics. Marge soon gets fed up with Homer telling their secrets and kicks him out. Homer starts living in Bart's treehouse and becomes so lost without Marge that he begs her to take him back, and she eventually agrees.&lt;br&gt;Guest star: [[Phil Hartman]].&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, p. 145&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=FD9D83
}}
|}

==DVD release==
[[Image:The Simpsons - Season 5 DVD menu.png|200px|right|thumb|The menu for the first disk of The Complete Fifth Season; the new format of menus has since been used in the rest of the released season box sets]]
The DVD boxset for season five was released by [[20th Century Fox]] in the United States and Canada on December 21, 2004, ten years after it had completed broadcast on television. As well as every episode from the season, the DVD release features bonus material including [[deleted scene]]s, [[Animatics]], and commentaries for every episode. The menus are a different format than the previous seasons, and that format would be used in every set after.&lt;ref name=&quot;Season 5 DVD&quot;&gt;{{cite video |date=2004|title=The Simpsons season 5 DVD boxset| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 1em 0 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 95%;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#EFEFEF&quot;
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #FD9D83;&quot;| '''The Complete Fifth Season'''
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
| align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;| '''Set details'''&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/releases/Simpsons-Complete-5th-Season/4113|title=Simpsons, The - The Complete 5th Season|accessdate=2008-03-07|publisher=TVShowsonDVD.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs52&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thesimpsonsshop.com/detail.php?p=12533&amp;v=simfandvd |title=The Simpsons Season 5 DVD |accessdate=2008-03-07 |publisher=The Simpsons Shop}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| width=&quot;300&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Special features'''&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs5&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs52&quot;/&gt;
|-valign=&quot;top&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;400&quot;|
* 22 episodes
* 4-disc set
* [[Aspect ratio (image)#4:3 standard|1.33:1 aspect ratio]]
* Languages:
** English ([[Dolby Digital]] 5.1, with subtitles)&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs5&quot; /&gt;
** Spanish (Dolby Digital 2.0 Stereo, with subtitles)&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs5&quot; /&gt;
** French (Dolby Digital 2.0 Stereo)&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs5&quot; /&gt;
** Special language feature for &quot;[[Sweet Seymour Skinner's Baadasssss Song]]&quot; (Czech, Italian, Polish and Hungarian)
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;|
* Optional commentaries for all 22 episodes
* Introduction from [[Matt Groening]]
* Animation Showcases
* &quot;A Look Back&quot; with [[James L. Brooks]]
* Deleted Scenes for 14 episodes
* Commercials
* Illustrated commentaries
* Audio outtakes
* Original sketches
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | '''Release dates'''
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; | [[DVD region code|Region 1]]
|align=&quot;center&quot; | [[DVD region code|Region 2]]
|align=&quot;center&quot; | [[DVD region code|Region 4]]
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; | December 21, 2004
|align=&quot;center&quot; | March 21, 2005
|align=&quot;center&quot; | March 23, 2005
|}

==References==
;General
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Richmond |first=Ray|coauthors=Antonia Coffman|title=The Simpsons: A Complete Guide to our Favorite Family |year=1997 |publisher=Harper Collins Publishers|isbn=0-00-638898-1}}
{{refend}}

;Specific
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* {{cite web|url=http://www.thesimpsons.com/#/recaps/season-5_episode-1 |title=Season 5|publisher=The Simpsons.com}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/simpsons/episodeguide/season5/index.shtml |title=Season 5|publisher=[[BBC]]}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.tv.com/the-simpsons/show/146/episode_guide.html?season=5 |title=Season 5|publisher=[[TV.com]]}}

{{The Simpsons}}

{{featured list}}

{{DISPLAYTITLE:''The Simpsons'' (season 5)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Simpsons (season 5)}}
[[Category:The Simpsons seasons|Simpsons season 05]]
[[Category:1993 television seasons]]
[[Category:1994 television seasons]]

{{Link GA|fr}}
[[da:The Simpsons (sæson 5)]]
[[es:Anexo:Quinta temporada de Los Simpson]]
[[fr:Saison 5 des Simpson]]
[[it:Episodi de I Simpson (quinta stagione)]]
[[pl:Simpsonowie (sezon 5)]]
[[pt:The Simpsons (quinta temporada)]]
[[ru:Симпсоны (сезон 5)]]
[[fi:Simpsonit (5. tuotantokausi)]]
[[sv:Simpsons (säsong 5)]]
[[tr:Simpsonlar (5. sezon)]]
[[uk:Сімпсони (сезон 5)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
