<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4939240" ns="0" title="The Simpsons (season 11)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox tvseason |
  | season_name = The Simpsons'' Season 11
  | bgcolour = #8CB4D5
  | show_name = [[The Simpsons]]
  | image = [[File:Simpsons s11.png|200px]]
  | caption = ''The Simpsons'' Season 11 DVD
  | country = [[United States]]
  | network = [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]]
  | first_aired = September 26, 1999
  | last_aired = &lt;br&gt;May 21, 2000
  | region_1 = October 7, 2008
  | region_2 = October 6, 2008
  | region_4 = November 5, 2008
  | num_episodes = 22
  | prev_season = [[The Simpsons (season 10)|Season 10]]
  | next_season = [[The Simpsons (season 12)|Season 12]]
  | episode_list = [[List of The Simpsons episodes|List of ''The Simpsons'' episodes]]
|}}

'''''The Simpsons''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt; 11th season''' originally aired between September 1999 and May 2000, beginning on Sunday, September 26, 1999, with &quot;[[Beyond Blunderdome]]&quot;. The [[show runner]] for the 11th production season was [[Mike Scully]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Krusty&quot;&gt;Groening, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; The season contained four hold-over episodes from the [[The Simpsons (season 10)|season 10]] (AABF) production line.

==Production==
Towards the end of the production of season 10, voice actress [[Maggie Roswell]], who voiced Helen Lovejoy, Maude Flanders and Miss Hoover, among others,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cast&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|McCann|2005|pp=118&amp;ndash;119}}&lt;/ref&gt; left the show because of a contract dispute.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Cartwright|2000|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; She returned to the show in [[The Simpsons (season 14)|season 14]]. As a result of Roswell's leaving, however, it was decided to kill off her primary role of [[Maude Flanders]] in the episode &quot;[[Alone Again, Natura-Diddily]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MF&quot;/&gt; Roswell's roles, including that of Maude Flanders until her death, were taken over by [[Marcia Mitzman Gaven]] starting from hold-over season 10 episode &quot;[[Brother's Little Helper]]&quot;.

Writers credited with episodes in the 11th season include [[Al Jean]], [[Dan Greaney]], [[Donick Cary]], [[Tim Long]], [[Ian Maxtone-Graham]], [[Carolyn Omine]], [[Mike Scully]], [[Matt Selman]], [[John Swartzwelder]] and [[George Meyer]]. Animation directors included [[Bob Anderson (director)|Bob Anderson]], [[Mike B. Anderson]], [[Mark Kirkland]], [[Lance Kramer]], [[Nancy Kruse]], [[Lauren MacMullan]], [[Pete Michels]], [[Steven Dean Moore]], [[Matthew Nastuk]], [[Michael Polcino]] and [[Jim Reardon]]. The main cast consisted of [[Dan Castellaneta]] ([[Homer Simpson]], [[Abraham Simpson|Grampa Simpson]], [[Krusty the Clown]] amongst others), [[Julie Kavner]] ([[Marge Simpson]]), [[Nancy Cartwright]] ([[Bart Simpson]], [[Ralph Wiggum]], [[Nelson Muntz]]), [[Yeardley Smith]] ([[Lisa Simpson]]), [[Hank Azaria]] ([[Moe Syzlak]], [[Apu Nahasapeemapetilon|Apu]], [[Chief Wiggum]], amongst others) and [[Harry Shearer]] ([[Ned Flanders]], [[Montgomery Burns|Mr. Burns]], [[Seymour Skinner|Principal Skinner]], amongst others).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cast&quot;/&gt; Other cast members included [[Marcia Wallace]] ([[Edna Krabappel]]), [[Pamela Hayden]] ([[Milhouse Van Houten]], amongst others), [[Tress MacNeille]] (Agnes Skinner, amongst others), [[Russi Taylor]] ([[Martin Prince]]) and [[Karl Wiedergott]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cast&quot;/&gt;

==Reception==

===Awards===
Aside from winning several awards in 2000, The Simpsons family themselves were awarded on January 14, 2000, their own star on Hollywood's [[Hollywood Walk of Fame|Walk of Fame]] at 7021 [[Hollywood Boulevard]]. The 11th season itself gathered an [[Emmy Award]] for [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Animated Program (For Programming less than One Hour)|Outstanding Animated Program]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Jean&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Jean, Al|date=2004|title=The Simpsons season 4 DVD commentary for the episode &quot;[[Mr. Plow]]&quot;| medium=DVD|publisher=20th Century Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as an [[Annie Award]] for Outstanding Achievement in a Primetime or Late Night Animated Television Program,&lt;ref name=&quot;A28&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://annieawards.org/28thwinners.html|title=Legacy: 28th Annual Annie Award Nominees and Winners (2000)|accessdate=2007-10-16|publisher=Annie Awards}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[British Comedy Award]] for Best International Comedy TV Show.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.britishcomedyawards.com/pastwinners00.html&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alf Clausen]] also received a 2000 Annie Award for Outstanding Individual Achievement for Music in an Animated Television Production for his work on the episode &quot;[[Behind the Laughter]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;A28&quot;/&gt; In the same year, &quot;[[Treehouse of Horror X]]&quot; won the [[CINE|CINE Golden Eagle Award]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cine.org/directories/2000-CINE-Winner-Directory.pdf CINE Golden Eagle Film &amp; Video Competition 2000 Winner Directory]. CINE.org. Retrieved on 2007-10-20.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2000, the two music editors Bob Beecher and Chris Ledesma were each nominated for the [[Golden Reel Award]] for &quot;[[Treehouse of Horror X]]&quot; and respectively for &quot;[[Wild Barts Can't Be Broken]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GR&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mpse.org/goldenreels/pastawards.html|title=Past Golden Reel Awards|accessdate=2007-10-17|publisher=Motion Picture Sound Editors}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At the [[Entertainment Industries Council#Prism Awards|Prism Awards]], &quot;[[Days of Wine and D'oh'ses]]&quot; received a commendation in the Comedy Series Episode category in 2001 for its frank depiction of alcoholism and drug rehabilitation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prism&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://prismawards.com/winners/ |title=Prism Awards Winners|accessdate=2008-04-27|publisher=[[Entertainment Industries Council]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The show was also nominated for a Blimp Award in the Favorite Cartoon category at the 2000 Kids' Choice Awards,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/Sections/Awards/Kids_Choice_Awards_USA/2000&lt;/ref&gt; as well as for the [[Teen Choice Award]] in the category Choice TV Show - Comedy.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/Sections/Awards/Teen_Choice_Awards/2000&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nielsen Rating===
The show ranked 41st in the seasonal ratings making it the second highest rated show on [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] that season after ''[[Malcolm in the Middle]]'', getting an 18-49 [[Nielsen Rating]] of 8.2//13.&lt;ref&gt;http://fbibler.chez.com/tvstats/recent_data/1999-00.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Critical Reception==
The season has received generally mixed to negative reviews. Mark Oakley of Den of Geek said that &quot;Once the programmes had a heart, as viewers were taken on a journey with the show’s characters. Here instead episodes are loaded with ever wackier and zanier gags&quot; and said that &quot;The Simpsons has well and truly jumped the shark&quot;.

==Episodes==
{{see also|List of The Simpsons episodes}}

;Key
* In the # column:
** The first number refers to the order it aired during the entire series.
** The second number refers to the episode number within its season.
*The production code refers to the code assigned to the episode by the production team. The first two characters refer to the season the episode was made for: AABF for Season 10, BABF for Season 11. The second number is the order the episode was produced, not the airing order.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;onlyinclude&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:98%;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font color&gt; 
! style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;Title&lt;/font color&gt;
! style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;Directed by&lt;/font color&gt; 
! style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;Written by&lt;/font color&gt; 
! style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;Original airdate&lt;/font color&gt; 
! style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;Prod. code&lt;/font color&gt;
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=227 - 01
 |Title=[[Beyond Blunderdome]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|9|26}}
 |Aux1=[[Steven Dean Moore]]
 |Aux2=[[Mike Scully]]
 |ProdCode=	AABF23
 |ShortSummary=After destroying an &quot;Elec-Taurus&quot; electric car in a test run, the Simpsons are given free tickets to [[Mel Gibson]]'s new film, a remake of ''[[Mr. Smith Goes to Washington]]''. Mel Gibson, however, laments his current role without violence and wants someone to give him criticism. When Homer sees Mel talking with Marge, he gives Mel a brutal review, leading Mel to believe that Homer is the only man brave enough to give suggestions. As a result, he hires him to create a better ending. However, when the ending proves to be too controversial, Mel and Homer end up on the run from studio executives with the film.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Mel Gibson]] and [[Jack Burns]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=228 - 02
 |Title=[[Brother's Little Helper]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|10|3}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[George Meyer]]
 |ProdCode=AABF22
 |ShortSummary=After getting in trouble for flooding the school gym during Fire Prevention Day, Bart is revealed to be diagnosed with [[Attention Deficit Disorder]] and prescribed a Ritalin-esque drug called Focusyn. At first, the drug makes Bart well-behaved and intellectual, but soon, Bart becomes paranoid, claiming that there are satellites owned by [[Major League Baseball]] that are spying on the town. When ordered to stop, Bart refuses, devours a few hundred, and proves his theory right by destroying the satellite with a tank. All is restored when Bart goes back to his ordinary pills.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, pp. 14-15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Mark McGwire]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{ Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=229 - 03
 |Title=[[Guess Who's Coming to Criticize Dinner]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|10|24}}
 |Aux1=[[Nancy Kruse]]
 |Aux2=[[Al Jean]]
 |ProdCode=AABF21
 |ShortSummary=Homer becomes a food critic for a Springfield newspaper and ends up annoying the restaurant owners of Springfield after he makes negative reviews just to be mean, advice he took from fellow critics. Springfield's restaurant owners then attempt to kill Homer by feeding him a poisoned [[éclair (pastry)|éclair]].&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Edward Asner]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=230 - 04
 |Title=[[Treehouse of Horror X]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|10|31}}
 |Aux1=[[Pete Michels]]
 |Aux2=[[Donick Cary]], [[Tim Long]] and [[Ron Hauge]]
 |ProdCode=BABF01
 |ShortSummary='''Intro''': The Simpsons (all dressed as characters from previous Treehouse of Horror episodes, save Lisa, who is an axe murder victim) watch Kang and Kodos's lame attempt at a Halloween variety show.

'''I Know What You Diddily-Iddily Did''' – Marge accidentally runs over Ned Flanders and is haunted by claims that someone knows what she did, only to realize that Ned survived because he became a [[werewolf]].

'''Desperately Xeeking Xena''' – Bart and Lisa gain super powers after a freak accident at school and must save [[Lucy Lawless]] (dressed as [[Xena]]) from the Collector ([[Comic Book Guy]]).

'''Life's A Glitch, Then You Die''' – When the [[Y2K bug]] causes everything electronic and computer generated in the world to go haywire, the family searches for a way out. &lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Dick Clark (entertainer)|Dick Clark]], [[Tom Arnold (actor)|Tom Arnold]] and [[Lucy Lawless]]&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=231 - 05
 |Title=[[E-I-E-I-(Annoyed Grunt)]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|11|7}}
 |Aux1=[[Bob Anderson (director)|Bob Anderson]]
 |Aux2=[[Ian Maxtone-Graham]]
 |ProdCode=AABF19
 |ShortSummary=Inspired by a cheesy &quot;Zorro&quot; movie, Homer begins slapping people with a glove and challenging them to duels (with the victims giving Homer whatever he wants instead of accepting the challenge), but when a real Southern gentleman accepts Homer's request for a duel, the Simpsons run off to the old farm Homer lived in with his parents (as seen in the season six episode [[Grampa vs. Sexual Inadequacy]]) and breed a dangerously addictive but successful tobacco/tomato hybrid called &quot;[[tomacco]]&quot;. Just when they are about to gain a hundred million dollars from the hybrid, dangerously addicted animals ruin their plan. Homer proceeds to duel, only to get shot in the arm.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[The B-52's]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=232 - 06
 |Title=[[Hello Gutter, Hello Fadder]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|11|14}}
 |Aux1=[[Mike B. Anderson]]
 |Aux2=[[Al Jean]]
 |ProdCode=BABF02
 |ShortSummary=Homer becomes a local celebrity after bowling a 300 game, but his fame quickly fades as &quot;yesterday's news&quot;. After a botched suicide attempt foiled by Otto, Homer decides to spend time with Maggie after seeing [[Ron Howard]] spend time with his children. When Homer tries to teach Maggie swimming, he fails due to her mistrust of him, and has to pulled out the beach by Maggie. Eventually, Homer brings Maggie to a bowling game, where she bowls a perfect game.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Ron Howard]], [[Pat O'Brien (television)|Pat O'Brien]], [[Nancy O'Dell]] and [[Penn &amp; Teller]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=233 - 07
 |Title=[[Eight Misbehavin']]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|11|21}}
 |Aux1=[[Steven Dean Moore]]
 |Aux2=[[Matt Selman]]
 |ProdCode=BABF03
 |ShortSummary=After Manjula gives birth to octuplets that were the result of fertility drugs, she and Apu unintentionally allow a zookeeper to exploit their babies in exchange for help after corporate sponsors abandon them for a mom that has given birth to nontuplets in Shelbyville. After a failed rescue attempt by Homer and Apu, the zoo keeper agrees to return the babies only if [[Butch Patrick]] and Homer ride a tricycle dressed as [[Eddie Munster]] on stage while attacked by cobras.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, pp. 21-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Garry Marshall]] and [[Butch Patrick]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=234 - 08
 |Title=[[Take My Wife, Sleaze]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|11|28}}
 |Aux1=[[Neil Affleck]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=BABF05
 |ShortSummary=Homer wins a [[Harley-Davidson]] motorcycle at a fifties dancing contest and starts his own biker gang, naming it &quot;Hell's Satans&quot;. However, this attracts the real biker gang called &quot;Hell's Satans&quot; to crash at their house. However, after a while, they begin to appreciate Marge, who takes care of them, and kidnaps her. Homer tracks them down and scuffles with Meathook, the leader. At Marge's suggestion, the gang settles down and lives normal lives.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[John Goodman]], [[Henry Winkler]], [[Jay North]] and [[NRBQ]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=235 - 09
 |Title=[[Grift of the Magi]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|1999|12|19}}
 |Aux1=[[Matthew Nastuk]]
 |Aux2=[[Tom Martin (writer)|Tom Martin]]
 |ProdCode=BABF07
 |ShortSummary=Principal Skinner hires Fat Tony's construction company to build wheelchair ramps for the school. These ramps promptly break down, forcing Skinner to close down [[Springfield Elementary School|Springfield Elementary]]. However, a toy company led by Jim Hope takes over the school; in school, the children are only taught to provide marketing schemes and suggestions. Soon, a new toy called Funzo that mysteriously resembles the children's ideas is invented. After a brief showdown [[Gary Coleman]] and the Funzo, things return to normal as Burns decides to fund the school after a visit from the three Christmas spirits.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Gary Coleman]], [[Tim Robbins]] and [[Clarence Clemons]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=236 - 10
 |Title=[[Little Big Mom]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|1|9}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[Carolyn Omine]]
 |ProdCode=BABF04
 |ShortSummary=While the Simpson family goes skiing, Marge remains at the ski lodge due to her fear of skiing, only to break her leg from a falling clock. As a result, while hospitalised, Marge leaves Lisa to deal with the slovenly Bart and Homer, who do nothing but take their toll on their house. However, in an attempt to motivate them, she pulls a prank suggested by the ghost of [[Lucille Ball]] on Bart and Homer by making it look like they have [[leprosy]]. At [[Ned Flanders|Ned Flanders']] suggestion, Bart and Homer end up in Hawaii; with them gone, Lisa finishes cleaning the house as Marge arrives home, her cast off. The pair then go to retrieve Homer and Bart, who are enjoying themselves despite the shock therapy.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, pp. 26-27.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Elwood Edwards]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=237 - 11
 |Title=[[Faith Off]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|1|16}}
 |Aux1=[[Nancy Kruse]]
 |Aux2=[[Frank Mula]]
 |ProdCode=BABF06
 |ShortSummary=Bart believes he has the power to heal others through faith after removing a bucket glued to Homer's head. However, when Bart knocks Milhouse's glasses off in order to cure his [[myopia]], Milhouse is nearly run over by a truck that he thinks is a dog as he cannot see without his glasses. Consequently, Bart, feeling guilty, ends his career as a faith healer. Meanwhile, Homer creates a homecoming game float for Springfield University. However, he soon forgets about it, and accidentally injures the star player, Anton Lubchenko. After getting in trouble with Fat Tony, Homer is saved when Lubchenko sacrifices his leg to win the game; the leg is surgically reattached by Doctor Hibbert, who is relieved at the end of Bart's healing career.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Don Cheadle]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=238 - 12
 |Title=[[The Mansion Family]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|1|23}}
 |Aux1=[[Michael Polcino]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=BABF08
 |ShortSummary=[[Montgomery Burns|Mr. Burns]] goes to the [[Mayo Clinic]] for a checkup after being declared the oldest man in Springfield, leaving the Simpsons to house-sit for him and Homer to take advantage of living as a rich man. However, when Homer wants to throw a party, he goes to Moe's, where he must buy the alcohol in international waters as it is Sunday before 2 PM. There, they are captured by Chinese pirates. Later, Burns discovers that as a result of having all the existing diseases, he is perfectly healthy as all the germs simply cancel each other out. Consequently, he returns and kicks out the Simpsons, who haven't even enjoyed being rich, causing Homer to be extremely bitter and resentful.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Britney Spears]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=239 - 13
 |Title=[[Saddlesore Galactica]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|2|6}}
 |Aux1=[[Lance Kramer]]
 |Aux2=[[Tim Long]]
 |ProdCode=BABF09
 |ShortSummary=The Simpsons rescue a diving horse named Duncan from abuse and keep it as a pet (despite The Comic Book Guy's protest that [[Lisa's Pony|the Simpsons have done this before]]), but when the cost of upkeeping the horse rises, Homer and Bart train Duncan to be a racing horse. Meanwhile, Lisa is upset over her school losing the band competition to Ogdenville unfairly at the state fair and writes a letter to Bill Clinton in protest.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Bachman–Turner Overdrive]] and [[Jim Cummings]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=240 - 14
 |Title=[[Alone Again, Natura-Diddily]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|2|13}}
 |Aux1=[[Jim Reardon]]
 |Aux2=[[Ian Maxtone-Graham]]
 |ProdCode=BABF10
 |ShortSummary=Maude Flanders is killed in a freak accident during a stock car race, devastating Ned and prompting Homer to find a new woman for his grieving neighbor. However, Ned begins losing his faith in God before being prompted back by a Christian rock band.&lt;ref name=&quot;MF&quot;&gt;Groening, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Shawn Colvin]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=241 - 15
 |Title=[[Missionary: Impossible]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|2|20}}
 |Aux1=[[Steven Dean Moore]]
 |Aux2=[[Ron Hauge]]
 |ProdCode=BABF11
 |ShortSummary=Homer gets in trouble with PBS after confessing he doesn't have $10,000 to give them for their pledge drive--and ends up a missionary on a South Pacific island.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Betty White]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=242 - 16
 |Title=[[Pygmoelian]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|2|27}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[Larry Doyle (writer)|Larry Doyle]]
 |ProdCode=BABF12
 |ShortSummary=After getting his face censored out on the Duff Calendar for not being photogenic, Moe gets plastic surgery and becomes the star of a popular soap opera. Meanwhile, Bart and Lisa go after Maggie's pink elephant balloon after it floats away.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=243 - 17
 |Title=[[Bart to the Future]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|3|19}}
 |Aux1=[[Michael Marcantel]]
 |Aux2=[[Dan Greaney]]
 |ProdCode=BABF13
 |ShortSummary=After their vacation in the woods is cut short due to a mosquito infestation, The Simpsons stop by at an Indian casino, where Bart tries to sneak in and ends up in the office of an Indian mystic who shows Bart's future in the year 2030 as a washed-up rock star living with Ralph Wiggum while Lisa is the President of the United States trying to get the country out of financial trouble.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=244 - 18
 |Title=[[Days of Wine and D'oh'ses]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|4|9}}
 |Aux1=[[Neil Affleck]]
 |Aux2=[[Dan Castellaneta]] and [[Deb Lacusta]]
 |ProdCode=BABF14
 |ShortSummary=Barney realizes how much of a pathetic drunk he is after watching his birthday party video and decides to give up alcohol forever, which doesn't sit well with Homer. Meanwhile, Bart and Lisa work together to take a memorable photo for a new phone book cover contest.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, pp. 39-40.&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=245 - 19
 |Title=[[Kill the Alligator and Run]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|4|30}}
 |Aux1=[[Jen Kamerman]]
 |Aux2=[[John Swartzwelder]]
 |ProdCode=BABF16
 |ShortSummary=Homer has a nervous breakdown when it's revealed on a quiz that he only has three years left to live. To calm him down, the family goes to Florida for vacation--and end up in the middle of a raucous spring break, where Homer joins in on the party and ends up getting himself and his family in trouble for killing the county's beloved mascot: an alligator named Captain Jack.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Kid Rock]], [[Joe C.]], [[Robert Evans (film producer)|Robert Evans]], [[Charlie Rose]] and [[Diedrich Bader]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=246 - 20
 |Title=[[Last Tap Dance in Springfield]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|5|7}}
 |Aux1=[[Nancy Kruse]]
 |Aux2=[[Julie Thacker]]
 |ProdCode=BABF15
 |ShortSummary=Inspired by a movie about a girl who enters a tango contest and wins, Lisa decides to sign up for dance lessons -- and ends up taking tap lessons from a former child star. Meanwhile, Bart and Milhouse hide out at the mall to escape going to summer camp.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, pp. 43-44.&lt;/ref&gt;
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=247 - 21
 |Title=[[It's a Mad, Mad, Mad, Mad Marge]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|5|14}}
 |Aux1=[[Steven Dean Moore]]
 |Aux2=[[Larry Doyle (writer)|Larry Doyle]]
 |ProdCode=BABF18
 |ShortSummary=Otto dumps his fiancee, Becky, at the altar, leaving her to become the Simpsons' latest houseguest, prompting Marge to go insane when Patty and Selma scare Marge with thoughts of Becky replacing Marge as a wife and mother. Meanwhile, Springfield Elementary gives Bart's fourth grade class videocameras (after slashing geography out of the budget) and Bart sets out to create a movie.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Guest star: [[Parker Posey]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
{{Episode list
 |EpisodeNumber=248 - 22
 |Title=[[Behind the Laughter]]
 |OriginalAirDate={{Start date|2000|5|21}}
 |Aux1=[[Mark Kirkland]]
 |Aux2=[[Tim Long]], [[George Meyer]], [[Mike Scully]] and [[Matt Selman]]
 |ProdCode=BABF19
 |ShortSummary=In a parody of [[VH1]]'s ''[[Behind The Music]]'', viewers take an inside look at The Simpsons' rise to fame--and the many scandals, feuds and break-ups that threatened to end the show and split up the family.&lt;ref&gt;Groening, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Guest stars: [[Jim Forbes (journalist)|Jim Forbes]] and [[Willie Nelson]]
 |LineColor=8CB4D5
}}
|}&lt;/onlyinclude&gt;

==DVD release==
[[Image:Simpsons s11 - Krusty.png|175px|right|thumb|''The Simpsons'' season 11 DVD digipak, special Krusty head edition]]
The DVD [[boxset]] for Season 11 was released by [[20th Century Fox]] in the United States and Canada on October 7, 2008, eight years after it had completed broadcast on television, in the UK on October 6, 2008, and in Australia on November 5, 2008. The special features include [[deleted scenes]], [[storyboards]]/[[animatic]]s, and commentaries. 

This is the first season release following the series of five Simpson family member shaped boxes. The character-themed packaging continues and, as with those seasons, this set was released in two different packagings: A &quot;Collector's Edition&quot; plastic packaging molded to look like [[Krusty the Clown]]'s head, and a standard rectangular cardboard box featuring Krusty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/releases/Simpsons-Complete-11th-Season-Limited-Edition-Krusty-Head/8086 |title=The Simpsons - The Complete 11th Season (Lisa Head) |accessdate=2009-04-11 |publisher=[[TVShowsOnDVD.com]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the previous seasons, the Collector's Edition packaging is a removable molded face attached to a cardboard sleeve, as opposed to a fully plastic clamshell. Both versions have changed from a [[digipak]] style of disc tray in previous seasons, to an accordion-style series of cardboard sleeves into which the discs slide. Following the release of the set there were a number of complaints regarding the style of packaging; David Lambert of [[TVShowsOnDVD.com]] described the set as &quot;functionally defective.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Simpsons - Editorial: Season 11: Worst... Packaging... Ever! |url= http://tvshowsondvd.com/news/Simpsons-Season-11-Box-Art/10740|author=Lambert, David|accessdate=2009-01-13|date=2008-10-21|publisher=[[TVShowsOnDVD.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 1em 0 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 95%;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#EFEFEF&quot;
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;background:#8CB4D5;&quot;| '''The Complete Eleventh Season'''
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; width:400px;&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot;| '''Set details'''&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs11&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Simpsons-Season-11-Press-Release/10451 |title=Here's Krusty... The Simpsons: The Complete Eleventh Season DVD collection |author=David Lambert|accessdate=2008-09-02|publisher=[[TVShowsOnDVD.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|  style=&quot;width:300px; text-align:center;&quot;|'''Special features'''&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs11&quot;/&gt;
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; width:400px;&quot;| 
* 22 episodes
* 4-disc set
* [[4:3|1.33:1 aspect ratio]]
* Languages:
** English ([[Dolby Digital]] 5.1, with subtitles)&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs11&quot;/&gt;
** Spanish (Dolby Digital, with subtitles)&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs11&quot;/&gt;
** French (Dolby Digital)&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDs11&quot;/&gt;
** Special Language Feature for &quot;Beyond Blunderdome&quot; (Italian, Brazilian Portuguese, Czech, German)
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; width:300px;&quot;|
* Optional commentaries for all 22 episodes
* Introduction from [[Matt Groening]]
* Deleted scenes with optional commentaries
* Featurette: &quot;The Many Faces of Krusty&quot;
* Featurette: &quot;A Star on Hollywood Boulevard&quot;
* Extra: &quot;And Then There Were Menus&quot;
* Sketch gallery
* Animation Showcases
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| '''Release dates'''
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[DVD region code|Region 1]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[DVD region code|Region 2]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| [[DVD region code|Region 4]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; 
|| October 7, 2008
|| October 6, 2008
|| November 6, 2008
|}

==References==
;General
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Groening|first=Matt|coauthors=Richmond, Ray; Antonia Coffman|title= Simpsons: Beyond Forever!: a Complete Guide to Our Favorite Family...Still Continued|publisher=Bt Bound|year=2003|isbn=0613621603, 9780613621601|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vuPxAQAACAAJ&amp;dq=The+Simpsons+Beyond+Forever!:+A+Complete+Guide+to+Our+Favorite+Family+...Still+Continued}}
{{Refend}}
;Specific
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.thesimpsons.com/#/recaps/season-11_episode-1 Season 11] at The Simpsons.com

{{The Simpsons}}

{{DISPLAYTITLE:''The Simpsons'' (season 11)}}
[[Category:The Simpsons seasons|Simpsons season 11]]
[[Category:1999 television seasons]]
[[Category:2000 television seasons]]
{{DEFAULTSORT:Simpsons (season 11)}}

[[da:The Simpsons (sæson 11)]]
[[es:Anexo:Undécima temporada de Los Simpson]]
[[fr:Saison 11 des Simpson]]
[[it:Episodi de I Simpson (undicesima stagione)]]
[[fi:Simpsonit (11. tuotantokausi)]]
[[ru:Симпсоны (сезон 11)]]
[[sv:Simpsons (säsong 11)]]
[[tr:Simpsonlar (11. sezon)]]
[[uk:Сімпсони (сезон 11)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
