<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="4944616" ns="0" title="Hanbury Hall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{no footnotes|date=March 2010}}

{{Geobox|stately home
| name = Hanbury Hall
| category =stately home
| image = Hanbury Hall front.JPG
| image_caption = Frontage of Hanbury Hall
| flag =
| symbol =  
| country = [[England]]
| state = [[Worcestershire]]
| region = [[English Midlands|Midlands]]
| district = [[Worcestershire]]
| municipality = [[Worcester]] 
| location = 
| elevation =
| prominence =
| lat_d = 
| lat_m =
| lat_s =
| lat_NS =
| long_d =
| long_m =
| long_s =
| long_EW =
| length = 
| length_orientation = 
| width = 
| width_orientation = 
| height =
| depth = 
| volume =
| area = 
| author =
| style = 
| material =
| established =1701
| date =
| owner = in the care of the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]]
| public =
| visitation =accessible to the public with a fee 
| visitation_date = All year round
| access =
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free =
| free_type = 
&lt;!-- *** Maps *** --&gt;
| map =
| map_caption = 
| map_background = 
| map_locator =
| map_locator_x =
| map_locator_y = 
&lt;!-- *** Website *** --&gt; 
| website = [http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/main/w-vh/w-visits/w-findaplace/w-hanburyhall/ www.nationaltrust.org.uk]
&lt;!-- *** Footnotes *** --&gt;
| footnotes =
}}
[[File:Hanbury Hall 1701.JPG|left|thumb|The disputed date above the entrance.]]
[[File:Hanbury Hall parterre 01.JPG|left|thumb|The rear of the hall, viewed across the [[parterre]].]]
[[File:Hanbury Hall staircase - finding of Achilles.JPG|left|thumb|[[Odysseus]] finds [[Achilles]] among the daughters of [[Lycomedes]]. This [[mural]] painting by Thornhill commands the main staircase.]]
[[File:Hanbury Hall 011.jpg|right|thumb|Hanbury Hall as seen through the entry gates]]
'''Hanbury Hall''' was built by the chancery lawyer [[Thomas Vernon (lawyer)|Thomas Vernon]] in the early 18th century. Thomas Vernon was the great grandson of the first Vernon to come to [[Hanbury, Worcestershire]], Rev Richard Vernon (1549–1628). Rev Richard and his descendants slowly accumulated land in Hanbury, including the manor, bought by Edward Vernon in 1630, but it was Thomas through his successful legal practice who added most to estates, which amounted to nearly {{convert|8000|acre|km2}} in his successor Bowater Vernon’s day. 

Hanbury Hall is thought to stand on the site of the previous mansion, [[Spernall Hall]], and Thomas Vernon first describes himself as ‘of Hanbury Hall’ in 1706, and this and other evidence leads to a likely completion date of about 1706. The date of 1701 above the front door is thought to be a [[Victorian era|Victorian]] embellishment, but no building accounts are known to exist. 

Although Hanbury Hall appears to be of a very uniform style, the rear wall is clearly of a different and rather earlier style, and may mark the first phase of a building campaign when Thomas Vernon and his wife Mary first came into possession of Spernall Hall in 1692 when his bachelor uncle John Vernon died. 

A notable feature of Hanbury Hall is the painting of the staircase, hall ceiling, and other rooms by the English painter Sir [[James Thornhill]]. They include a small representation of Rev [[Henry Sacheverell]] being cast to the furies – this relates to an incident in 1710 when Sacheverell, a [[Tory]], was put on trial for sedition by the [[Whig (British political party)|Whig]] government, and dates the paintings to that year. The focus of the paintings around the stairwell is the life of the Greek hero [[Achilles]], as told by a range of classical sources. They are surmounted by a large representation of the [[Olympian gods]] on the ceiling.

The original plan of the Hall had a large undivided central hall with the main staircase leading off it, with many rather small rooms in the corner pavilions and north range – the south range was given over mainly to service rooms. The 18th century Worcestershire historian [[Treadway Nash]], in his ''Collections for the History of Worcestershire'', wrote “Here is a large handsome house built by Counsellor Vernon about the year 1710 when a bad style of architecture prevailed; many windows and doors, rooms small, many closets, few arched cellars, large stables and offices in full view, are marks of that time”. 

When the heiress Emma Vernon (1754–1818) married [[Henry Cecil, 1st Marquess of Exeter]] in 1776, Cecil clearly was of the same opinion, as he remodelled the interior (other than the great hall) creating larger rooms and enlarging the north east pavilion. On the south façade, having removed a doorway he repositioned all the windows to lie under their first floor equivalent. On the south side there had been large formal gardens, clearly shown in Dougharty’s perspective drawing contained in the estate maps of the 1730s, and Cecil swept all these away (including the farm buildings in front of the Hall) and landscaped the park in the fashion of the time – he would have had contact with [[Capability Brown]] when being brought up by his uncle 9th [[Earl of Exeter]] at [[Burghley House]]. 

Following Henry and Emma’s divorce in 1791 the contents were all sold, and the house remained empty until Henry’s death in 1804, when Emma and her third husband, John Phillips, were able to regain possession. As the house had lain unoccupied for so long, many repairs had to be carried out at that time. Emma died in 1818 and left her second cousin, Thomas Shrawley Vernon (1759-1825), as the heir to her estate after the death of her husband John Phillips. Phillips married again and had two daughters in Hanbury before finally moving out in 1829. From then, the eldest son of Emma's heir, Thomas Tayler Vernon (1792–1835), was able to occupy it. His grandson Harry Foley Vernon (1834–1920) M.P., was created 1st Baronet of Hanbury in 1885, and was succeeded by his son Sir (Bowater) George Hamilton Vernon (1865–1940), 2nd Bart. Sir George led an unhappy life, separating from his wife Doris, and spending his last 10 years living with his secretary and companion Ruth Horton, who later changed her name by deed poll to Vernon. During this time the agricultural depression led to a reduction in rental income, and Hanbury Hall suffered a lack of care. 

In poor health, Sir George Vernon took his own life in 1940, after which his estranged wife was able to move back in, dieing there in 1962. In the meantime, negotiations had led to the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]] having the reversion, and after making essential repairs on Lady Doris’s death, the hall was let to tenants and opened on a restricted basis. But in more recent times the hall has been managed more commercially, and is now open most of the year, and is very popular with visitors. 

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Hanburyhallmorris edited.jpg|Hanbury Hall circa 1880
File:Hanbury orangery.JPG|The orangery, in the gardens to the south-west of the hall.
File:Hanbury Hall orchard.JPG|The walled orchard at Hanbury, containing a wide range of traditional English fruit varieties.
File:Hanbury Hall parterre 02.JPG|The parterre, viewed from a first floor window of the hall.‎ 
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Sources==
* Vernon archives in the Worcestershire Record Office BA 7995.

{{commons category|Hanbury Hall}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/main/w-vh/w-visits/w-findaplace/w-hanburyhall/ National Trust profile]
*[http://www.thornber.net/england/htmlfiles/hanburyhall.html Photographs of Hanbury Hall]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/herefordandworcester/features/360/worcester/hanbury_hall_index.shtml BBC Hereford &amp; Worcester feature including 360 panoramic of Hanbury Hall]
*[http://www.pbase.com/belvedere/hanbury_hall Hanbury Hall on pbase.com]
*[http://www.geograph.org.uk/search.php?i=3757595 photos of Hanbury Hall and surrounding area on geograph]
{{coord|52.271788|-2.083261|display=title}}

[[Category:Country houses in Worcestershire]]
[[Category:National Trust properties in Worcestershire]]
[[Category:Houses completed in 1706]]
[[Category:Historic house museums in Worcestershire]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
