<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="494785" ns="0" title="Towson University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name=Towson University
|image_name= Towson University seal.png
|type=[[Public university|Public]]
|endowment= $33.2 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2010 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2009 to FY 2010| work = 2010 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = May 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|established=1866&lt;ref name=&quot;AtAGlance&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/abouttu/glance/index.asp
|title=Towson At a Glance |accessdate=2007-09-11 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president=[[Marcia G. Welsh]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Admins&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/abouttu/admingov/
|title=Administration &amp; Governance |accessdate=2009-10-26 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|provost=Terry Cooney&lt;ref name=&quot;Admins&quot;/&gt;
|faculty= 1,588&lt;ref name=&quot;AtAGlance&quot;/&gt;
|students= 
|undergrad= 17,529&lt;ref name=&quot;AtAGlance&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USNewsRank&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_2099_brief.php |title=Towson University school profile |accessdate=2011-03-17 |publisher=U.S. News and World Report}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad= 4,311&lt;ref name=&quot;AtAGlance&quot;/&gt;
|staff-ratio=17:1&lt;ref name=&quot;AtAGlance&quot;/&gt;
|city=[[Towson, Maryland|Towson]]
|state=[[Maryland]]
|country=[[United States]]
|coor={{Coord|39|23|34|N|76|36|17|W |region:US-MD_type:edu |display=inline,title}}
|campus=[[Suburban]], 328 acres (1.33 km²)&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/abouttu/glance/campus/index.asp
|title=Campus - Towson At a Glance |accessdate=2007-09-11 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors = Black and Gold&lt;br&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:black;width:50px;border:1px solid #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:gold;width:50px;border:1px solid #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;|
|nickname=[[Towson Tigers]]
|mascot = [[Doc (mascot)|Doc]]
|fightsong=[[Towson Tigers#Fight song|Towson Fight Song]]
|athletics=[[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Athletics&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/athletics/
|title=Athletics - Towson University |accessdate=2007-09-11 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|logo=
|website=[http://www.towson.edu www.towson.edu]
}}

'''Towson University''', often referred to as '''TU''' or simply '''Towson''' for short, is a [[public university]] located in [[Towson, Maryland|Towson]] in [[Baltimore County, Maryland|Baltimore County]], [[Maryland]], [[United States|U.S.]] It is a part of the [[University System of Maryland]].

Founded in 1866 as Maryland's first [[normal school|training school]] for teachers, Towson University has evolved into a 4-year degree granting institution consisting of 8 colleges with over 20,000 students enrolled. Towson is also the second largest public university in Maryland, and still produces the most teachers of any university in the state.

The ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' ranked Towson University 8th in the Public Universities-Master’s (North) category for its 2010 America's Best Colleges issue.&lt;ref&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/masters-universities-north-rankings/page+2&lt;/ref&gt; Forbes included Towson University in its 2009 list of the top 100 public colleges and universities in the United States. Kiplinger's Personal Finance magazine named Towson University one of the top 100 best values in public colleges for the 2008-2009 academic year.

==History==
{{See also|Chronology of Towson University}}
[[Image:TUSeals.png|center|700px]]

===Maryland State Normal School===
[[Image:TUNewell.jpg|right|thumb|[[McFadden Newell|McFadden Alexander Newell]]|125px]]
The [[Maryland General Assembly|Maryland Legislature]] established what would become Towson University in 1865, with the allocation of funds directed toward Maryland’s first teacher-training school, or [[normal school]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TUHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.towson.edu/main/abouttu/glance/history.asp |title=History - Towson At a Glance |accessdate=2007-09-11 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 15, 1866, this institution, known as the Maryland State Normal School (MSNS), officially opened its doors.&lt;ref name=&quot;MDEN&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mdoe.org/towson_u.html |title=Towson University |accessdate=2007-09-11 |publisher=Maryland Online Encyclopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Located then at Red Man's Hall in [[Baltimore, Maryland|Baltimore]], the school originally enrolled eleven students and fostered three faculty members.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tower1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.thetowerlight.com/media/storage/paper957/news/2002/04/29/News/Renovations.Build.On.History.Of.University-2197491.shtml?sourcedomain=www.thetowerlight.com&amp;MIIHost=media.collegepublisher.com  |title=Renovations build on history of Towson University |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last=Bridge |first=James |year=2002 |month=April |publisher=The Towerlight}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chronicle&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://chronicle.com/jobs/profiles/1621.htm |title=Employer Profile |accessdate=2007-08-02 |publisher=Chronicle Careers}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[McFadden Alexander Newell]] served as the school's first principal as well as the State Superintendent of Public Instruction and oversaw the first graduating class of sixteen students in June 1866.&lt;ref name=&quot;MDEN&quot;/&gt;

As time passed, the enrollment in the school grew exponentially. The school soon outgrew its facilities in Red Man's Hall and moved to a temporary location, later known as the Athenaeum Club, in 1873.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chrono&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cooklibrary.towson.edu/archives/chronology.cfm |title=Chronology of Towson University History |accessdate=2007-09-11 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, the General Assembly appropriated money to construct an exclusive building to house the burgeoning school. In 1876, the school moved its faculty and 206 students to this new facility located in West Baltimore on Carrollton &amp; Lafayette Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tower1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chronicle&quot;/&gt;

===Move to Towson===
The demand for qualified teachers became overwhelming by the turn of the century. The Maryland Department of Education reported an annual need for 350 new teachers, but the Maryland State Normal School was graduating fewer than 100.&lt;ref name=&quot;MDEN&quot;/&gt; The facilities in West Baltimore were now inadequate to meet state demands. Principal [[Sarah Richmond]], one of the original eleven graduates, began a campaign to establish a campus where the school could function more appropriately.[[Image:TUStephConstr.jpg|left|thumb|125 px|Stephens Hall, under construction in 1914.]] In 1910, the General Assembly formed a committee to oversee site selection, budget, and design plans for the new campus. [[John Charles Linthicum]] was appointed president of the committee, alongside State Superintendent Dr. M. Bates Stephens and Sarah Richmond. The committee surveyed locations at [[Roland Park, Baltimore|Roland Park]], [[Lutherville-Timonium, Maryland|Lutherville-Timonium]], [[Mount Washington, Baltimore|Mount Washington]], [[Pimlico, Baltimore|Pimlico]], Glencoe, and many other areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chronicle&quot;/&gt; Eventually, the committee settled on an {{convert|80|acre|m2|adj=on}} site in Towson and the General Assembly financed the $600,000 move in 1912.&lt;ref name=&quot;TUHistory&quot;/&gt; Construction began in 1913 on the Administration Building, now known as Stephens Hall. In September 1915, the new campus, comprising Stephens Hall, Newell Hall, and the power plant, began classes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chrono&quot;/&gt;

===Name changes===
In 1934, the state decreed that new public school teachers must have [[Bachelor's degree|baccalaureate degrees]] instead of two-year teaching certificates, and the school retooled its curriculum to issue [[Bachelor of Science]] degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;TUHistory&quot;/&gt; The following year, the school changed its name to '''Maryland State Teachers College at Towson'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;MDEN&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chrono&quot;/&gt; As the name implied, the college's single purpose was to train teachers. In 1946, however, the institution established a junior college to offer two years of college work on a transfer basis. This expansion lay the foundation of what was later to become the art and sciences program. In 1958, the college offered its first graduate program leading to a [[Master of Education]] degree. In 1960, the college expanded the art and science programs into four-year courses and began awarding Bachelor degrees in these fields. Due to this change in focus, the name changed once more to '''Towson State College'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;TUHistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MDEN&quot;/&gt;

Beginning in 1964, the college enrollment rates began a dramatic increase as the [[baby boomer]] generation began applying to colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;MDEN&quot;/&gt; Within a decade, Towson State's enrollment climbed from 3,537 to 13,399.&lt;ref name=&quot;TUHistory&quot;/&gt; This expansion led to the construction of the Center for the Arts, University Union, Cook Library, and many other new facilities. Under the presidency of James L. Fisher, the college expanded the courses offered to meet the demands of the growing student body. In 1976, the school's name changed again to '''Towson State University'''. In 1988, TU joined 10 other public institutions in the newly created [[University of Maryland System]]. On July 1, 1997, another name change took effect. Towson dropped the designation &quot;state&quot; from its name and became ''[http://www.towson.edu Towson University]''. The new name recognized shifts in funding and the development and growth of Towson as a [[Metropolitan area|metropolitan]] university.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chronicle&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:TURedMan'sHall.jpg|&lt;center&gt;'''Red Man's Hall'''&lt;/center&gt;
Image:TUAthenaneumBuilding.jpg|&lt;center&gt;'''The Athenueum Club'''&lt;/center&gt;
Image:TUCarroltonSt.Building.jpg|&lt;center&gt;'''Carrollton &amp; Lafayette Street'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

==Academics==
Towson University is accredited by the [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools#Commission on Higher Education|Middle States Commission on Higher Education]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MSCHE&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.msche.org/institutions_view.asp?idinstitution=473 |title=Middle States Commission on Higher Education |accessdate=2007-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Maryland State Department of Education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dance&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.towson.edu/dance/facacc.htm |title=Towson University Facilities and Accreditation |accessdate=2007-09-12 |publisher=Towson University}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the Fall 2010 freshmen class, Towson accepted about 57% of their applicants.&lt;ref name=&quot;College Board&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=685&amp;profileId=1 |title=Towson University - Facts &amp; Figures |accessdate=2011-03-17 |publisher=[[Peterson's]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The average [[Grade (education)|grade point average]] was a 3.45 and the middle 50% of matriculating students had [[ACT (test)|ACT]] composite scores between 21-25.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBoard&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=685&amp;profileId=6 |title=College Search - Towson University |accessdate=2011-03-17 |publisher=[[College Board]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Towson educates undergraduate and graduate students in thirty academic departments which are subdivided into eight colleges:

{| width=&quot;auto&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#FFCC00&quot; 
!| Name of College
!| Dean
|-
|[[Towson University College of Business and Economics|College of Business and Economics]]
|Shohreh A. Kaynama
|-
|[[Towson University College of Education|College of Education]]
|Raymond Lorion
|-
|[[Towson University College of Fine Arts and Communication|College of Fine Arts and Communication]]
|Susan E. Picinich
|-
|[[Towson University College of Health Professions|College of Health Professions]]
|Charlotte E. Exner
|-
|[[Towson University College of Liberal Arts|College of Liberal Arts]]
|Terry A. Cooney
|-
|[[Towson University Jess and Mildred Fisher College of Science and Mathematics|Jess and Mildred Fisher College of Science and Mathematics]]
|David Vanko
|-
|[[Towson University Honors College|Honors College]]
|Joseph McGinn
|-
|[[Towson University College of Graduate Studies and Research|College of Graduate Studies and Research]]
|Lawrence Shirley
|-
|}

The university provides 64 undergraduate majors, 37 master's degree programs and 4 doctoral programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/academics/degreeprograms/index.asp |title=Degree Programs |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/academics/ugrad/index.asp |title=Undergraduate Studies |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Once students have determined a program of study, they become a member of the academic college administering the program.

As a side note, Towson also has a [[gerontology|gerontology program]] which is one of only 100 undergraduate programs offered in the United States. They're also the only public university in the United States that offers an undergraduate degree in [[e-Business]].

==Enrollment==
More than 20,000 full-time and part-time students are enrolled in the University. Their numbers include over 800 international students from 100 nations. There are more than 17,000 undergraduates; approximately 13% are non-white. Also, in 2006 Towson achieved more enrollment in its business school than any college in the state of Maryland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.thetowerlight.com/media/storage/paper957/news/2006/11/09/News/College.Of.Business.Passes.College.Park-2448699.shtml?sourcedomain=www.thetowerlight.com&amp;MIIHost=media.collegepublisher.com
 |title=Increased enrollment results in 2,995 undergraduates in CBE for Fall 2006 |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last=Leff |first=Sharon |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year=2006 |month=November |format= |work= |publisher=The Towerlight |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
[[Image:TURezTower.JPG|thumb|TU's high rise dorm, the Residence Tower.]]

===Housing===
About 77% of the freshman class, and over 4,400 students among all four classes, reside on campus. The University has 15 residence halls, which include apartment complexes, modern high-rise towers, and more traditional two- and three-story residential buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/housing/ |title=Housing and Residence Life |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Students can also choose from five special housing options on campus, including: International House, Honors College, Wellness, Alcohol-free, and Special Quiet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.towson.edu/main/admissions/freshman/studentlife/ Student Life - Towson University] Towson University. Retrieved on 2009-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt; While on campus, students have access to a counseling center, an academic advising center, a health center, and a career center.

===OneCard===
[[Image:TUOneCard.jpg|150px|left|thumb|An example of a OneCard]]
Students get access to their meal plan, dorm buildings, and computer labs through the use of their [http://www.towson.edu/adminfinance/auxservices/onecard/ OneCard]. They can also go to all of the school sporting events (which are many times free of charge to students) and several on campus events with the use of their card. It also serves dually as identification on campus.

===Transportation===
TU has its own on campus shuttle system that operates free of charge to students. The on-campus shuttle travels to most sections of the school, while the off-campus shuttles travel to housing complexes (The Fairways at Towson, University Village, The Colony, Donnybrook) that students live in that are on the outskirts of the campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/adminfinance/auxservices/parking/shuttle/index.asp |title=Shuttle Services |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
There is also direct access to the [[Maryland Transit Administration|MTA Maryland]] buses with services connecting to the [[light rail]].

===Towson UnPlugged===
[[Image:TUUnplugged.png|right]]
Towson Unplugged is one of the largest wireless networks in the Baltimore metro area, and spans the campus’ {{convert|328|acre|km2}} including residence halls.

The value of the updated wired network and new wireless network is $3.2 million. Wireless coverage extends across majority of the size of the TU campus, including 28 academic and administrative buildings that are wireless with approximately 400 access points in those buildings, with each access point having a range of {{convert|300|ft|m}}.

TU Unplugged uses [[IEEE 802.11|802.11 b/g standard]] [[Wi-Fi]] protocols with 11 Mbit/s is the approximate shared connection speed for Towson Unplugged users with 802.11b wireless adapters and 54 Mbit/s is the approximate shared connection speed for Towson Unplugged users with 802.11 g [[Wireless LAN|wireless networking]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/adminfinance/OTS/towsonunplugged/index.asp |title=Towson UnPlugged |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 11, 2007, [[Baltimore County]] officials announced that they may provide wireless internet access throughout the county. However, they will first pilot the program in the [[Towson]] area, using donated bandwidth from Towson University to send signals to the Towson area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.examiner.com/printa-667352~Towson_gets_free_wireless_Internet.html |title=Towson gets free wireless Internet |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last=Malarkey |first=Jaime |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year=2007 |month=April |work= |publisher=Baltimore Examiner |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus Police===
The Towson University Police Department (TUPD) is the primary law enforcement agency servicing the students, faculty, and visitors within the campus limits and adjacent streets and roadways. The TUPD is aided by the [[Baltimore County Police Department]] as directed by authority. The current chief of police is Bernard Gerst.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.towson.edu/adminfinance/facilities/police/ University Police - Towson University&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The TUPD is divided into several units such as the Patrol Unit and the Community Crime Reduction Unit. It also includes emergency communications.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.new.towson.edu/adminfinance/facilities/police/documents/BOLO07-00134.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
{{Main|Towson University Buildings and Structures}}

===Campus Master Plan===
As a response to the University System of Maryland’s (USM) desire for Towson University to grow its enrollment, a new Campus Master Plan was developed for the university and approved by the USM, Board of Regents in December 2003. The university found that in the past, it has been guided by master plans that focused inward, resulting in disjointed campus development that was disconnected from the larger Towson community.

The resulting vision, called ''TU:2010''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://realsrv.towson.edu/ramgen/static/masterplan.rm |title=Video of the campus master Plan |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.towson.edu/main/abouttu/strategic/ |title=TU 2010: Mapping the Future |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; addresses both [[University System of Maryland]] requirements and community concerns. It contains over 70 specific initiatives that range from growing diversity to increasing student involvement in service learning projects. Perhaps its most visible development is the creation of academic and student life buildings, as well as roads, parking, utilities and landscapes to support those buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/main/abouttu/glance/campus/masterplan.asp |title=Campus Master Plan |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of this vision, Towson's campus is undergoing many construction projects set into different phases with staggered completion dates. 

&lt;center&gt;
'''COMPLETED CONSTRUCTION PROJECTS'''
&lt;/center&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Name of Project
!Cost
!Completion Date
!Description
|-
|Union Third Floor Conference Rooms  
|$760,000
|August 2006
|Conversion of existing patio space on the third floor of the University Union into conference rooms for use by student organizations. 
|-
|Cook Library Lobby Renovation and Starbucks Cafe
|$1 million 
|September 2006
|Complete renovation of the lobby area to include new inner and outer storefronts with [[Starbucks|Starbucks Cafe]] replacing the vending area.
|-
|Burkshire Marriott Pub
|$1 million
|January 2007
|The patio outside of Nathan T's at the Burkshire Marriott was enclosed and the interior of Pub Smedley was renovated and expanded to create the newly named University Club. The University Club boasts new interior finishes, bar, and bathrooms.
|-
|Childcare Center
|$4.5 million
|January 2007
|Formerly housed in the Lida Lee Tall Education Building, TU's Childcare Center now has its own newly constructed building located on Auburn Drive.
|-
|Campus Memorial Garden
|$200,000
|Summer 2007
|Construction of a memorial garden between the University Union and the Glen Towers was completed 2007. The garden is open to all students, faculty and staff and is designed to provide visitors with a peaceful place where the lives of members of the Towson University community may be remembered and celebrated. 
|-
|Towsontown Garage Expansion
|$10.6 million
|December 2007
|Expansion of the garage to add 500 parking spaces for use by students, faculty, staff and visitors. Construction was completed in December 2007.
|-
|West Village Housing - Phase I
|$36 million
|Fall 2008
|Delivery of 668 additional beds in the West Village sector was completed before the fall 2008 semester.
|-
|College of Liberal Arts - Phase I
|$51.5 million
|April 2009
|Design and construction of the first {{convert|100000|sqft|m2}} of the {{convert|250000|sqft|m2}} academic building houses the College of Liberal Arts. The university broke ground on the building's construction in September 2007 completing the first phase in Fall of 2009.
|-
|}

&lt;center&gt;
'''FUTURE CONSTRUCTION PROJECTS'''
&lt;/center&gt;
{{Out of date|date=August 2009}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Name of Project
!Cost
!Estimated Completion Date
!Description
|-
|College of Liberal Arts - Phase II
|$72 million
|Summer 2011
|Design and construction of the second of the academic building that will house the remainder of the College of Liberal Arts. The university broke ground on the building's construction in 2009 with the building set to open in summer 2011.
|-
|West Village Housing - Phase II
|N/A
|Summer 2011
|Phase II of the West Village housing project encompasses the construction of two residential facilities in the university’s West Village precinct. The buildings will consist of nearly 160,000 total gross square feet of space and contain 651 beds for freshman and sophomore students. They will be constructed as mirror images of Paca and Tubman Halls, located just west of these buildings which comprised phase one of the West Village housing project.
|-
|West Village Commons
|$30 million
|Summer 2011
|When it opens in summer 2011, the West Village Commons building will be an 85,000 gross square foot mixed-use facility that supports the residential population of the campus's West Village precinct. The building will offer dining, retail, meeting, office and other student service spaces that will enhance the area ’s living and learning environment, contribute to the development of its community, and serve as a central gathering space for current and future residential students.
|-
|West Village Parking Garage
|$27 million
|Summer 2011
|The West Village Garage is a {{convert|489000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} parking facility being constructed west of Towson Run Apartments in the university’s West Village precinct. Construction on the garage began in August 2010 and is anticipated to culminate in August 2011. At that time, the six-story garage will contain 1,500 parking spaces for TU students, faculty/staff and visitors. It will also feature LED lighting, which consumes 50% less electricity than standard garage fixtures.
|-
|Campus Gateway
|$11 million
|Winter 2012
|The new gateway will be located near Burdick Hall. Marked by brick pillars and a large, open plaza, the gateway will serve as a major campus access route, giving Towson University’s campus the main entrance that it’s always lacked. The gateway is designed to give campus visitors a sense of arrival and serving as an entry point for the entire campus community. 
|-
|Tiger Arena
|$68 million
|Spring 2013
|A 5,200-plus seat multi-use arena facility complete with state-of-the-art video screens, entertainment suites/boxes, and expanded lobbies. Towson University will have a new arena with the added benefit of preserving the Towson Center and keeping it operational in a redeveloped form for a basketball/volleyball practice facility, gymnastics facility and newly developed areas for sports medicine, strength &amp; conditioning and a comprehensive academic and life skills area. Moreover, classes and events can continue in the old arena while Tiger Arena is being developed. Construction has begun and will be complete as early as May 2013.  Follow the construction of this project at www.TigerArena.com
|}

===Campus Sustainability===
Towson University is committed to social and environmental responsibility. The school is achieving this goal by promoting recycling initiatives and green dining. Students partake in “Trayless Tuesdays” and receive incentives for using reusable mugs. Sustainability has also been incorporated into first year orientation so that students can begin a dialogue on environmental stewardship in their daily lives. Towson looks forward to having its initiatives analyzed for the 2010 College Sustainability Report Card.&lt;ref name=&quot;The College Sustainability Report Card&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The College Sustainability Report Card|url=http://www.greenreportcard.org//|accessdate=2009-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Go Green&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Go Green|url=http://www.towson.edu/adminfinance/facilities/recycling/howtogogreen/programs.asp#prp/|accessdate=2009-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Towson Tiger===
{{Main|Doc (mascot)}}
Before the 1960s, the name of the sports teams at Towson were known as the &quot;Towson College Knights&quot;. Towson student [[John Schuerholz]] pushed for a new mascot, and the tiger was officially adopted in 1962. Schuerholz later became general manager of the [[Atlanta Braves]] and is the team's president as of 2008. The university's present baseball complex is named in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://presidentcaret.org/blog/?p=24 |title=The Meaning of a Mascot |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last=Caret |first=Robert |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=President's Caret's Blog |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to school newspaper ''[[The Towerlight]]'', when the Student Government Association first bought the tiger statue that sits outside Cook Library in 1996, the organization hoped to boost school spirit. Instead, it became subject to vandalism and disrepair. In March 2006, after several acts of vandalism, the statue was completely removed from in front of the library.

In September 2006, the Towerlight reported that a new bronze tiger statue had been unveiled as the centerpiece of the university's &quot;Capital Campaign&quot; to raise $50 million dollars. The primary difference between the new statue and previous one is that the new one is made of bronze and all of the legs are on the ground and the tail is wrapped around its legs rather than raised, so it won't get damaged by vandals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thetowerlight.com/media/storage/paper957/news/2006/11/06/News/New-Tiger.Statue.Debuts-2440106.shtml?norewrite200611101151&amp;sourcedomain=www.thetowerlight.com |title=Tiger Statue Debuts |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last=Funderburk |first=Kristi |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year=2006 |month=November |format= |work= |publisher= |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The new statue is outside Stephens Hall and was unveiled on February 8, 2007 where Caret said it would be  &quot;visible to passersby on York Road as well as students&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thetowerlight.com/media/storage/paper957/news/2006/12/11/CrystalBall/In.With.2007.The.Future.Of.Towson.University-2531535-page4.shtml?norewrite200612111128&amp;sourcedomain=www.thetowerlight.com |title=The Future of Towson University |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year=2006 |month=December |format= |work= |publisher=The Towerlight |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/baltsun/access/1213298171.html?dids=1213298171:1213298171&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Feb+9%2C+2007&amp;author=Julie+Scharper&amp;pub=The+Sun&amp;desc=BRONZE+MASCOT+SHOULD+STAND+UP+TO+PROWLING+VANDALS+ |title=Towson's new Tiger built to last |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last=Scharper |first=Julie |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year=2007 |month=December |format= |work= |publisher=Baltimore Sun |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===A President's Blog===
Towson University is one of the first colleges in the United States to have a president who has his own [[blog]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.presidentcaret.org |title=President Caret's Blog |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=President Caret's Internet Blog |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[podcast]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://phobos.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=122399125&amp;s=143441 |title=President Caret's Podcast |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher= |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Caret created the blog and  podcast to convey different messages to TU students.

===Smoke Free Campus===
Towson is the first four year institution in Maryland to enact a campus-wide smoke-free policy starting August 1, 2010. All Towson University buildings and exterior grounds are now designated as non-smoking areas.

==Athletics==
{{Main|Towson Tigers}}
[[File:TowsonRugby.jpg|thumb|right|Towson's club Rugby team in action, October 2005.]]
The [[Towson Tigers]], formerly the Towson College Knights, are the athletics teams of Towson University. All of the major athletic teams compete in the [[Colonial Athletic Association]] with 20 Division I athletic teams (13 in women's sports, 7 in men's sports).

Under the leadership of President Bob Caret the University placed a greater emphasis on the athletics program.  In September 2010 Caret hired a new Director of Athletics, Michael P. Waddell, who has significant program building experience at the highest levels of college sports.  

Towson University offers the most comprehensive sports program in the metropolitan Baltimore area, fielding 20 varsity teams that compete in the Colonial Athletic Association. Since joining the league in 2001-02, the Tigers have won CAA titles in men’s and women’s lacrosse, women’s swimming, men’s soccer and men’s golf. During an athletics history that traces its roots to the 1920s, Towson has sent teams and individual student-athletes to NCAA post-season competition in baseball, basketball, football, golf, gymnastics, lacrosse, soccer, swimming, track &amp; field and volleyball. 

Tiger student-athletes have distinguished themselves in the classroom as well as on the field of competition. Eleven Tigers have been named CAA Scholar-Athlete Award Winners for their respective sports, including the 2010 cross country recipient, Brandi Gervais, a senior Biology/Pre-Dentistry Major with a perfect 4.0 GPA. A number of student-athletes have gone on to enjoy professional careers, including most recently Jermon Bushrod, the starting left offensive tackle for the 2010 Super Bowl Champion New Orleans Saints; outfielder Casper Wells with the Detroit Tigers; and shooting guard Gary Neal with the San Antonio Spurs. Saint's Associate head coach Joe Vitt is also a prominent alumnus as well as a major contributor to the Athletics Department.  Current Atlanta Braves' President John Schuerholz is also a Towson alumnus and a member of the school's Board of Visitors.

In May 2011, the department broke ground on the future of Towson Athletics as it began construction of Tiger Arena, a new 5,200-seat, state-of-the-art arena for basketball, volleyball and gymnastics, slated to open in the Spring of 2013.

==Traditions==
===Tigerfest===
Tigerfest is TU's annual spring festival that features interactive activities for students, as well as live musical entertainment. Tigerfest, which is also open to the public (not just TU students), occurs in late April and is held on Burdick Field. The event has become increasingly popular throughout its history, mainly because mainstream music acts headline Tigerfest each year.  Artists such as [[Third Eye Blind]], [[Dashboard Confessional]], [[The Used]], and [[Yellowcard]] have appeared at Tigerfest in the past. [[The Roots]], [[Immortal Technique]], and [[Alex Band]] of [[The Calling]] performed at the 2008 Tigerfest. The 2009 Tigerfest featured [[The All-American Rejects]] as the headliner. The concert also featured [[Shiny Toy Guns]], [[Vedera]], and [[Ace Enders]] as opening acts.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=1227840442&amp;ref=profile#/event.php?eid=67012473435&amp;ref=mf&lt;/ref&gt;[[N.E.R.D.]] headlined the 2010 festival and [[Brand New (band)|Brand New]], [[Reel Big Fish]], and [[Far East Movement]] will be playing the 2011 Tigerfest.

==Community Outreach==
===Division of Economic and Community Outreach===
Towson University, Maryland’s Metropolitan University, is committed to addressing education, economic development and broad social issues. To further Towson’s role as a premier metropolitan university, the Division of Economic and Community Outreach (DECO) was established in 2004 as an initiative of President Robert L. Caret. DECO’s charge is to provide a focus for engagement with the external community and to provide a path into the university's research and project talent.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.towson.edu/outreach/&lt;/ref&gt; DECO includes over 130 experts in the following areas: IT Solutions, Mapping Solutions (GIS), Technical Training, Applied Economics and Human Services, Information Assurance, and Business Growth.

===The Cherry Hill Learning Zone===
The initiative is a partnership among the [[Baltimore City Public School System]], Baltimore City government, Towson University and Cherry Hill's community organizations. Together, the programs are trying to rebuild the Cherry Hill neighborhood in southern Baltimore. The program interacts with Cherry Hill’s civic leaders, community organizations and citizens, the Learning Zone hopes to serve as a resource for the academic progress of Cherry Hill’s young residents and improvement of the overall environment in the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/cherryhill/index.asp |title=The Cherry Hill Learning Zone |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/cherryhill/videos.asp |title=Cherry Hill Learning Zone video |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Baltimore Urban Debate League===
{{See also|Baltimore Urban Debate League}}
The [[Towson University Speech and Debate|Towson Speech and Debate]] team has close ties with the [[Baltimore Urban Debate League]] and often volunteers people from the team and the university to judge and facilitate the running of the tournaments.

&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:BUDL Logo.jpg|right|200px]] --&gt;

The university often acts as a host for league tournaments at least once a year.

Towson also has what they call an ''Urban Debate Scholar'' award that they give to one graduating senior every year. The scholarship pays for full tuition and fees at TU. They also offer varying awards between $2,000 - $4,000 to other graduating seniors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/speechanddebate/pages/scholarships.html |title=Scholarship Opportunities |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=Towson Speech and Debate |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Adopt-A-Campus===
President Caret has also established a program called ''Adopt-A-Campus'', which gives local businesses, organizations and others an opportunity to help beautify the TU campus. Every group will be assigned a certain section of the campus, and will be encouraged to pick up litter and help keep the area clean of trash and debris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwnew.towson.edu/adminfinance/resources/adopt-a-campus.asp |title=Adopt-A-Campus |accessdate=2007-07-25 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |format= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
===Free Speech policy===

The school newspaper, ''[[The Towerlight]]'', announced that in February 2008, the school administration was planning to implement a &quot;Free Speech Policy&quot;. Within the policy, it defines several things that would be considered [[free speech]], and that students would be restricted to where they could assemble and have demonstrations or protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;FreeSpeechPolicy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.thetowerlight.com/media/storage/paper957/news/2008/02/07/News/Tu.Administration.Reworking.Free.Speech.Policy-3193819.shtml |title=TU administration reworking free speech policy |accessdate=2007-02-15 |last=Leff |first=Sharon |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=The Towerlight |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; This has caused serious backlash from the students, and has solicited various protests on campus and vocal dissent from the Student Government Association as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;FreeSpeechPolicy&quot;/&gt; Jenny Haley, the SGA president at the time, said the policy was not discussed nor negotiated with the SGA and that she feels it is a mistake to exclude students from the decision making process.&lt;ref name=&quot;FreeSpeechPolicy&quot;/&gt; It was also noted that during a meeting with the administration to discuss the policy, several administrators said that the only input initially solicited from students for the Free Speech policy was from a committee called the ''Student Leadership Council'' that consists of student leaders who are in charge of large student groups. Several of the students contested that not only did they not know who was on this committee, but that most of them did not even know that kind of committee even existed.

The administration has reworked the policy and named it the ''Time, Place and Manner policy''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://inside.towson.edu/generalcampus/tupolicies/documents/06-04.11%20Policy%20on%20Time,%20Place%20and%20Manner.pdf |title=Time Place and Manner Policy |accessdate=2011-04-06 |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=Towson University |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media and publications==
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:WTMD.jpg|right]] --&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Television
!Radio
!Print
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
*''[[WMJF]]'' – The university's student-run TV station
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
*''[[WTMD]]'' – Alternative music FM public radio
*''[[XTSR]]'' – Student-run Internet radio station; also played on campus television (formerly ''WTSR'').
|valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*''[[The Towerlight]]'' - Towson's bi-weekly student newspaper [http://www.thetowerlight.com/]
*''[[Grub Street (literary magazine)|Grub Street Literary and Arts Magazine]]''
*''Journal of Philosophical Ideas'' - The Philosophy Forum's Undergraduate Journal
*''The Prelaw Society Journal''
*''Journal of Historical Studies''
|}

==Student organizations==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!SGA Affiliated
!Cultural Organizations
!Recreation and Sport Clubs
!Religious Organizations
!Community Service
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*Active Minds
*Actuary Club
*[[Alpha Kappa Psi]] Business Fraternity [http://www.akpsiok.com/]
*American Advertising Federation
*American College of Health-care Executives
*Pakistan Student Association
*American Marketing Association
*Amnesty International
*Anime Club
*Arts and Crafts Club
*Athletic Training Club
*Ballroom Dance Club [http://www.towson.edu/ballroomdance/]
*Campus Greens [http://www.towson.edu/campusgreens/]
*College Democrats [http://www.towson.edu/collegedems/]
*College Libertarians [http://www.towson.edu/clt/]
*Communications Society
*Computer and Technology Club
*Council for Exceptional Children, TU Student Chapter
*E-business Association
*English Club
*Excelsior
*Financial Management Association
*Geography Club
*Hillel
*Honors College Student Council
*Lambda Kappa Tau [http://www.lambdakappatau.com/]
*Mathematics Club
*Minority Science and Technology
*National Association of Future Doctors of Audiology
*National Science Teacher’s Association
*National Student Speech Language and Hearing Association
*Nursing Student Association
*Philosophy Forum [http://wwwnew.towson.edu/philosophyforum/]
*Physical Education Majors Club
*Prelaw Society [http://wwwnew.towson.edu/polsci/prelawsociety/]
*Psychology Club
*Public Relations Group
*Sign-Up Club
*Society of Physics Students
*Society of Professional Journalists
*Speech and Debate Team
*Sport Business Association
*Student Affiliates of the American Chemical Society
*Student Council on Family Studies
*Student Education Association
*Students for Ron Paul
*Students for a Sensible Drug Policy
*Towson Economics Society [http://www.towsonecon.tk]
*Towson Republicans
*Towson University Feminist Collective
*Wall$treet Investors Investment Club [http://www.towson.edu/wiic/]
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*African Diaspora Club [http://www.towson.edu/adc] est.2000
*Black Student Union
*Caribbean Students’ Association
*Chinese Student and Scholarship Association
*Delta Phi Omega
*Hillel
*Queer Student Union [http://www.towson.edu/qsu/]
*Groove Crew
*Filipino Cultural Association
*International Student Association
*Japanese Association
*Latin American Student Organization
*South Asian Student Association
*Towson Zionist Organization of America
*Zeta Sigma Chi Multicultural Sorority
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*Chess Club
*Dance Team
*Baseball
*Badminton
*Bowling
*Cycling
*Dodgeball
*Golf
*Field Hockey
*Figure Skating
*Ice Hockey
*Men's &amp; Women's Lacrosse
*Martial Arts
*Adventure Pursuits
*Pom Squad
*Rock Climbing Club
*Roller Hockey
*Rugby (Men's &amp; Women's)
*Men's &amp; Women's Soccer
*Ski and Snowboard
*Stunt
*Surf
*Tennis
*Track &amp; Field
*Men's &amp; Women's Ultimate Frisbee
*Men's &amp; Women's Volleyball, Wrestling
*Triple T (Towson’s Tapping Tigers)
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*Athletes in Action
*Baptist Student Ministry
*BASIC
*Campus Crusade for Christ
*Collegelife
*Episcopal Campus Fellowship
*Gospel Choir (Infinite Praise Ministries)
*Korean Campus Ministry
*Lutheran Student Movement
*Muslim Student Association
*Newman Club
*Reformed University Fellowship
*University Bible Fellowship
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*[[American Red Cross|American Red Cross Corps]]
*Best Buddies
*Choice Tutoring
*[[Circle K International|Circle K]]
*Dance Marathon
*[[Habitat for Humanity]]
*Leaders of a Beautiful Struggle [http://www.towson.edu/lbs]
*NonProfit Leadership Alliance
*Proud Athletes Who Serve (PAWS)
*Project L.O.U.
*Sisterhood
*Students Helping Honduras
*SWING PHI SWING Social Fellowship,INC
*Towson Volunteer Board
|}

==Greek life==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Interfraternity Council (IFC)
!National Pan-Hellenic Council (NPHC)
!Unified Greek Council (UGC)
!Panhellenic Association (PHA)
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*[[Alpha Epsilon Pi]] fraternity
*[[Delta Sigma Phi]] fraternity
*[[Lambda Chi Alpha]] fraternity
*[[Phi Sigma Kappa]] fraternity
*[[Pi Kappa Alpha]] fraternity
*[[Pi Lambda Phi]] fraternity
*[[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]] fraternity
*[[Sigma Pi]] fraternity
*[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]] fraternity
*[[Zeta Beta Tau]] fraternity
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|

*[[Alpha Phi Alpha]] fraternity
*[[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] sorority
*[[Delta Sigma Theta]] sorority
*[[Kappa Alpha Psi]] fraternity
*[[Zeta Phi Beta]] sorority
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|

*[[Alpha Nu Omega]] sorority &amp; fraternity
*[[Zeta Sigma Chi]] multicultural sorority
*[[Sigma Lambda Gamma]] sorority
*[[Lambda Theta Phi]] Latin fraternity
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller;&quot;|
*[[Delta Delta Delta]] sorority
*[[Alpha Gamma Delta]] sorority
*[[Alpha Omicron Pi]] sorority
*[[Alpha Phi]] sorority
*[[Alpha Xi Delta]] sorority
*[[Kappa Delta]] sorority
*[[Phi Mu]] fraternity for Women
*[[Phi Sigma Sigma]] sorority
*[[Zeta Tau Alpha]] sorority
|}

==Notable attendees and faculty==
{{Main|List of Towson University people}}

==See also==
*[[List of presidents of Towson University]]
*[[:Category:Towson University colleges|Towson University colleges]]

==References==
&lt;sub&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}
&lt;/sub&gt;
==External links==
*[http://www.towson.edu Towson's Official website]
*[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0738541877&amp;id=HZ1KeUXAAucC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=iNdjIM1pDg&amp;dq=%22towson+university%22&amp;sig=093Ak_uuQLH0sbjBcJsIwEP4DTU ''Towson University''] By Dean Esslinger, Lori Armstrong, Angie Brickhouse
*[http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Wabash+Ave+%26+Patterson+Ave,+Baltimore,+MD+21215&amp;sll=37.0625,-95.677068&amp;sspn=33.352165,60.46875&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=39.396607,-76.615133&amp;spn=0.015885,0.029526&amp;z=15&amp;layer=c&amp;cbll=39.392962,-76.604476&amp;panoid=xw360Fh-MYjgWnfA5TgHIw&amp;cbp=12,271.93222882977267,,0,-7.1656976744186105 Towson campus on Google Street View]


{{Colleges and Universities in Maryland}}
{{University System of Maryland}}
{{Colonial Athletic Association}}
{{ECHA}}

{{Towson University}}

[[Category:Towson University]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1866]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Maryland]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Baltimore County, Maryland]]
[[Category:Baltimore County, Maryland landmarks]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Coalition of Urban and Metropolitan Universities]]

[[de:Towson University]]
[[no:Towson University]]
[[simple:Towson University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
