<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="496361" ns="0" title="Sacred Heart University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}

{{Infobox University
|name		= Sacred Heart University
|image_name	= Sacred Heart University seal.svg
|image_size	= 200px
|motto		= Where Personal Attention Leads to Personal Achievement
|established	= 1963
|type		= [[Private school|Private]]
|president	= [[John J. Petillo]]
|city		= [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Fairfield]]
|state		= [[Connecticut]]
|country	= [[United States|USA]]
|endowment      = $82 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = GuideStar.org| work = SHU FY '09-'10 Form 990 financials | publisher = Sacred Heart University | url = www.guidestar.org| format = PDF | accessdate = May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad	= 4,192
|postgrad	= 1,831
|postgrad_label	= graduate
|full-time faculty=212
|free_label	= Student to faculty ratio
|free		= 12:1
|campus		= [[Suburban]] 67 acres
|sports         = 31 Varsity Teams&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncaa.com/schools/590_Sacred_Heart.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/br&gt;17 women's; 14 men's
|colors		= [[Red (color)|Red]] and [[White]] {{color box|#990000}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
|nickname	= Pioneers
|mascot		= &quot;Big Red&quot; the Pioneer
|athletics	= [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|affiliations	= [[Northeast Conference|NEC]]; [[Colonial Athletic Association|CAA]]; [[Eastern College Athletic Conference|ECAC]]; [[Atlantic Hockey|AHA]]; [[Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association|EIVA]]
|website	= [http://www.sacredheart.edu/ www.sacredheart.edu]
|logo           = [[Image:Sacred Heart University wordmark.svg|225px|Sacred Heart University]]

}}

'''Sacred Heart University''' is a Roman Catholic university located in suburban [[Fairfield, Connecticut|Fairfield]], [[Connecticut]], [[United States]]. Sacred Heart was founded in 1963 by the Most Reverend [[Walter W. Curtis]], Bishop of the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Bridgeport|Diocese of Bridgeport]], Connecticut. Sacred Heart University was the first Catholic university in the [[United States]] to be staffed by the [[laity]].&lt;ref&gt;
http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/1916_mission_commitment.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. John J. Petillo is the current President of the University.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ctpost.com/local/article/SHU-president-resigns-to-pursue-other-interests-735414.php&lt;/ref&gt;

SHU is the second largest Catholic university in [[New England]], behind [[Boston College]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/3353_shu_at_a_glance.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;, and offers more than 40 degree programs to over 6,000 students at the bachelor's, master's and doctoral levels.

Sacred Heart is included in ''The Princeton Review's Best 371 Colleges 2010''[http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/29732_shu_ranked_among_america_s_best_schools_by_the_princeton_review_us_news_world_report.cfm], the ''Best 301 Business Schools 2010''[http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/30356_shu_among_princeton_review_s_best_business_schools.cfm], as well as ''U.S. News and World Report's Best Colleges''.[http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/29732_shu_ranked_among_america_s_best_schools_by_the_princeton_review_us_news_world_report.cfm]

==History==
Sacred Heart University was founded in 1963 by the Most Reverend Walter W. Curtis, Bishop of the Diocese of Bridgeport.  It was established to provide the community with an affordable, quality education at a local Catholic university.  The University was to be led and staffed by the laity independent and locally oriented, serving the needs of the diocese and of southwestern Connecticut.

Enrollment has risen from the original class of 173 to over 6,000 full and part-time undergraduate and graduate students, and the faculty has increased from 9 to 212 full-time professors and over 350 adjunct professors.

The University has enhanced the undergraduate student experience in several notable ways.  In 1990, it accepted for the first time students who wanted the residential experience.  The first dorms, Scholars Commons (previously known as J-Hill), were built 1991. It now has 10 residential buildings with 70% of the full-time undergraduates residing in university housing.   

New degree programs and majors in relevant disciplines are regularly added to the curriculum.  The University offers Division I athletics with 31 varsity teams. The $17.5 million William H. Pitt Health and Recreation Center is available to all students and to the community at large.  Recognizing the importance of technology, Sacred Heart University provides all undergraduate students with a laptop computer.  The University campus is a wireless environment.   

The University consists of four colleges:  College of Arts &amp; Sciences, John F. Welch College of Business, College of Education and Health Professions, and University College.  University College is committed to the adult learner, and its evening, weekend and accelerated courses earn praise for their diversity and relevance to changing lifestyles.

On January 25, 2006, [[Jack Welch]] gave a large sum of money and his name to Sacred Heart University's College of Business, which is now known as the &quot;John F. Welch College of Business.&quot;[http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/12142_sacred_heart_university_names_college_of_business_for_legendary_ge_chairman_jack_welch.cfm]

On Sunday, September 27, 2009, Sacred Heart University dedicated and opened its new chapel. The worship space, following the teachings of Vatican Council II has been named the ''Chapel of the Holy Spirit.''

== Campus ==
The main campus is located in suburban Fairfield, {{convert|50|mi|km}} north of [[New York City]] and {{convert|150|mi|km}} south of [[Boston]].

=== Additional campuses ===
* Cambridge Campus (Trumbull, CT)
* Oakview Campus (Trumbull, CT)
* Stamford Campus (Stamford, CT)
* Griswold Campus (Griswold, CT)
* Luxembourg Campus (Luxembourg)
* Dingle, County Kerry Campus (Ireland)

== Student body ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2009}}

* Enrollment:	        4192
* Female: 	        60%
* Out of State:	        74%
* International:        1%
* African American:	5%
* Asian:	        4%
* Caucasian:	        84%
* Hispanic:	        7%
* Native American:	0%

* The top four states in which first-year undergraduate students and their families permanently reside are New York, Connecticut, New Jersey and Massachusetts.
* 40% of the Class of 2009 had a high school GPA of 3.5 or higher.

== Student life ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2008}}

===Theatre Arts Program===
The Theatre Arts Program began in 2009 with the premiere of Sacred Heart University's first musical production: ''Rent''.  Other productions include ''Little Shop of Horrors'' in spring 2011 and ''Spring Awakening'' premiering in the spring of 2012.  The Theatre Arts Program also features two student-produced, student-written, and student-performed Theatre Festivals in both the fall and spring semesters and is the home of Sacred Heart's own improv team: Awkward Handshake.

=== The Spectrum ===
The Spectrum is a student-run newspaper printed and distributed to students each Wednesday and made available online.

=== Community service ===
More than 1,200 students and members of the faculty and staff volunteer in excess of 31,000 hours each year largely within the City of Bridgeport, but also regionally, nationally, and internationally. In Spring 2008, SHU finished third in the nation in the &quot;ONE Campus Challenge&quot;, a campaign that seeks to raise public awareness about the issues of global poverty, hunger, and disease. In Fall 2007, SHU's Habitat for Humanity Campus Chapter was named one of the Top Five Campus Chapters in the nation, for their work in the Bridgeport community, and around the country with alternative spring break service trips.

===Study abroad===
SHU has the only American-accredited MBA program in the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg and a residential study-abroad program in the Irish-speaking community of Dingle, County Kerry, Ireland. International experiences are available to SHU students worldwide through study abroad programs located at the American University of Rome, in Italy, the University of Notre Dame in Fremantle, Australia, and the University of Granada, in Spain, as well as programs in Bermuda and the Bahamas.

SHU also allows students to participate in CCIS programs, programs affiliated with other schools across the U.S. These programs include, but are not limited to: France, Argentina, Germany, Belgium, and Japan.

===Athletics===
{{see also|Sacred Heart Pioneers men's ice hockey|Sacred Heart Pioneers women's ice hockey}}
The Pioneers compete in [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] of the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA) in the [[Northeast Conference]] (NEC) [[Atlantic Hockey]], [[Colonial Athletic Association]] (CAA) [[Eastern College Athletic Conference]] (ECAC), [[Eastern Intercollegiate Wrestling Association]] EIWA (Wrestling) and the [[Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association]] (EIVA).

Nearly 800 students participate in the university's 31 athletic teams (17 female teams and 14 male teams) along with more than 500 students who participate in 23 Club Sports.

In March 2009, the Women's Basketball team won the NEC Title and earned their second trip to the NCAA Tournament in the last four years. The team faced the Ohio State Buckeyes in the first round of the tournament on March 21, 2009, and lost 77-63. The [[Sacred Heart Pioneers women's ice hockey]] program competes as an independent in NCAA Division I women's ice hockey.

The men's golf team won the NEC Title in May of 2008, 2009 and 2011.

===Club sports===
Currently there are twenty-six club sports active on campus.  

The active clubs are:
*Baseball
*Men's Basketball
*Women's Basketball
*Men's Bowling
*Curling
*Dance Team
*Field Hockey
*Figure Skating
*Gymnastics
*Golf
*[[Sacred Heart Pioneers men's ice hockey|Men's Ice Hockey]]
*[[Sacred Heart Pioneers women's ice hockey|Women's Ice Hockey]]
*Men's Lacrosse
*Women's Lacrosse
*[[Sacred Heart University Men's Rugby Football Club|Men's Rugby]]
*Women's Rugby
*Running
*Men's Soccer
*Women's Soccer
*Softball
*Men's Swimming
*Tennis
*Track and Field
*Ultimate Frisbee
*Women's Volleyball
*Weightlifting

=== Greek life ===
There are 5 national sororities and 3 national fraternities. With one local fraternity and sorority. With over 650 members it is one of the fastest growing organizations on campus.

Sororities:
'''5 National:''' [[Kappa Delta]], [[Phi Sigma Sigma]], [[Zeta Tau Alpha]], [[Theta Phi Alpha]], [[Chi Omega]] and '''1 Local:''' Kappa Phi

Fraternities: 
'''3 National:''' [[Pi Kappa Phi]], [[Delta Tau Delta]], [[Kappa Sigma]] and '''1 Local:''' Omega Phi Kappa

== Honors ==
* “America’s Best Colleges&quot; by U.S.News &amp; World Report, Tier I institution [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/29732_shu_ranked_among_america_s_best_schools_by_the_princeton_review_us_news_world_report.cfm]
* &quot;The Best 371 Colleges&quot; by Princeton Review [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/29732_shu_ranked_among_america_s_best_schools_by_the_princeton_review_us_news_world_report.cfm]
* &quot;Best Physical Therapy Program in Connecticut&quot; [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/23473_physical_therapy_program_ranks_best_in_state.cfm]
* &quot;Best Graduate Schools 2009,” ranked its physical therapy program 52nd nationally, placing it as one of the top 5 programs in New England [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/23473_physical_therapy_program_ranks_best_in_state.cfm]
* &quot;Best 301 Business Schools&quot; by Princeton Review [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/1948_more_news.cfm]
* SHU named to the President's Higher Education Community Service Honor Roll 2008-09 [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/26664_shu_named_to_presidential_honor_roll_for_community_service.cfm]
* Habitat for Humanity campus chapter among the top five collegiate chapters in the nation [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/19711_shu_habitat_chapter_among_top_5_in_u_s_.cfm]
* &quot;SHU Ranked #11 in Intel's Most Unwired Campuses&quot; [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/3967_shu_ranks_11th_in_the_nation.cfm?searchterm=]
* &quot;Named one of Princeton Reviews and GamePro's Top 50 Game Design Program&quot; [http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/32309_game_design_program_named_top_50.cfm]

==Notable alumni==
*[[Kevin Nealon]] - ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' cast member
*[[John Ratzenberger]] - Actor
*[[Lydia Hearst-Shaw]] - American model &amp; Actress
*[[Jon Corto]] - Linebacker for [[Buffalo Bills]]
*[[Romeo Roselli]] - Professional Wrestler &amp; Actor
*[[Jeff LeBlanc]] - Singer/Songwriter from the class of 2008

==Notable members of the Board of Trustees==
*[[Linda McMahon]]&lt;ref name=boardoftrustees&gt;{{cite news|title=Administration and Board of Trustees|publisher=Sacred Heart University|url=http://www.sacredheart.edu/pages/18846_administration_and_board_of_trustees.cfm|accessdate=2008-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[John Ratzenberger]]&lt;ref name=&quot;boardoftrustees&quot;/&gt;
*[[Rosanne Badowski]]&lt;ref name=boardoftrustees /&gt;
*[[Peter Terpeluk, Jr.]]&lt;ref name=boardoftrustees /&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.sacredheart.edu/ Official website]
* [http://sacredheartpioneers.cstv.com/ Official Athletics website]
* [http://www.ctpost.com/local/article/SHU-president-resigns-to-pursue-other-interests-735414.php]

{{Colleges and universities in Connecticut}}
{{Northeast Conference}}
{{Atlantic Hockey}}
{{Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association}}

{{coord|41.22139|-73.24194|display=title}}

[[Category:Sacred Heart University]]
[[Category:Fairfield, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1963]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Diocese of Bridgeport]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Fairfield County, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Connecticut]]

[[no:Sacred Heart University]]
[[simple:Sacred Heart University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
