<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5001420" ns="0" title="Montana Grizzlies"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
|name             = Montana Grizzlies
|logo             = Montana UM logo.gif
|logo_width       =
|university       = [[University of Montana – Missoula|University of Montana]]
|conference       = [[Big Sky Conference]]
|division         = [[Division I FCS]]
|director         = Jim O'Day
|city             = Missoula
|state            = Montana
|stateabb         = MT
|teams            = 14
|stadium          = [[Washington-Grizzly Stadium]]
|soccerstadium    = [[Montana_Grizzlies#Athletic_facilities|South Campus Stadium]]
|arena            = [[Dahlberg Arena]]
|mascot           = [[Monte (mascot)|Monte]]
|nickname         = Grizzlies, Griz, Lady Griz
|fightsong        = [[Montana Grizzlies#School Fight Song|Up With Montana]]
|color1           = Maroon
|color2           = Silver
|hex1             = 660033
|hex2             = 999999
|hex3             = 
|pageurl          = http://www.gogriz.com/
|pagename         = gogriz.com 
|altlogo          = 
}}
'''Montana Grizzlies''' is the nickname given to the athletic teams of the [[University of Montana – Missoula|University of Montana]].  The women's basketball team, however, uses the moniker '''Lady Griz'''. The university is a member of the [[Big Sky Conference]] and competes in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], fielding 6 men's teams (Basketball, Football, Cross Country, Tennis, Indoor Track &amp; Field, and Outdoor Track &amp; Field) and 8 women's teams (Basketball, Cross Country, Golf, Soccer, Tennis, Indoor Track &amp; Field, Outdoor Track &amp; Field, and Volleyball).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/&lt;/ref&gt; The football team has won the university's only two NCAA Championships.

==History==
===Nickname and Mascot===
Originally known as the Bears with a live black bear named Teddy as the mascot, the university's football team officially became the Grizzlies (sometimes called the Silvertips) in 1923 when they were admitted to the [[Pacific Coast Conference]] (PCC).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.montanagrizzlies.com/user/pages/MBasketball/2010-11/Section1.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  That same year Montana became the first state in the nation to designate grizzlies as a protected game animal.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nrmsc.usgs.gov/files/norock/products/StateOfTheGrizzly.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  This name change would later prove problematic, however, for their new PCC conference-mate [[UCLA]] who had also recently changed their name to the Grizzlies.  When UCLA petitioned to join the conference in 1926, Montana claimed rights to the name and the UCLA Grizzlies became the [[UCLA Bruins]] when they were admitted to the conference in 1928.&lt;ref&gt;Stadium Stories: UCLA Bruins. Roberts, Chris. Globe Pequot. (2005). p. 7 &lt;/ref&gt;

The Grizzlies continued to use live bears as mascots until the early 1960's.  In addition to Teddy, there was a Cocoa, Chester, and three different Fessy's named after former football coach Doug Fessenden, among several others.  In the 1970's and 80's costumed mascots were introduced, but as mascots of local sponsors, not the University.  This included the [[Hamm's Beer bear]], a chicken from a local radio station, and even Ronald McDonald.&lt;ref&gt;http://nwda-db.wsulibs.wsu.edu/ark:/80444/xv80682&lt;/ref&gt;  Later in the 1980's, a costumed mascot by the name of Grizzly Otto (after local sponsor Grizzly Auto) was introduced as part of the Montana cheer squad.  The current mascot, [[Monte (mascot)|Monte]] (short for Montana), was introduced in 1993 and in 2002 became the first winner of the [[Capital_One_Bowl#Mascot_contest|Capital One Bowl's &quot;Mascot of the Year&quot;]] contest.  He won again in 2004 and was nominated three other times.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.umt.edu/montanan/f06/artifacts.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.capitalonebowl.com/history#2002&lt;/ref&gt;
{{See also|Monte (mascot)}}

===Colors===
''(1893-1967), (1997-Present) Maroon &amp; Silver {{colorbox|#660033}}&amp;nbsp;{{colorbox|silver}}&lt;br&gt; 
(1968-1996) Copper &amp; Gold {{colorbox|#CC5500}}&amp;nbsp;{{colorbox|#FFCC00}}''&lt;br&gt;
The University of Montana's official colors are copper, silver and gold, and were chosen as such in recognition of the state of Montana's mining history.  Contrary to popular perception, these colors have never changed with the confusion stemming from the University's decision to represent &quot;copper&quot; with either ''maroon'' {{colorbox|#660033}} or ''Texas orange'' {{colorbox|#CC5500}} at various times in its history.  In 1893 when the University was founded and its colors chosen a lack of copper dye led the school to use maroon and occasionally other colors to represent the copper.  This had the effect of having the schools athletic teams not always being represented across the board by the same uniform colors.  In 1967, then football coach and athletic director Jack Swarthout, who personally preferred the maroon and silver used by the football team, sought to make the schools colors more consistent and held a vote among UM coaches.  They selected ''Texas orange'' (to represent copper) and gold to be used on the school's uniforms and it would remain so for the next 30 years.  In 1993, the maroon was brought back as part of the University's centennial celebrations and a student survey in 1995 showed support for a return to maroon and silver uniforms.  Despite some vocal opposition, by 1997 the colors began to phase into the maroon and silver that continues to be used.&lt;ref&gt;http://filemanager.montanagrizzlies.com/mtgriz3/custom_pages/files/pdfs/fb/features/coaching_legends/jack_swarthout.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.umt.edu/montanan//wint96/oval.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.montanakaimin.com/arts-culture/why-we-bleed-maroon-and-silver-1.2622129&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programs==
===Football===
{{main|Montana Grizzlies football}}
The Grizzlies won national champs in 1995 and 2001 and have qualified for a record 16 consecutive playoffs. They have played football from 1897 to present.

The Grizzlies rank among the all time playoff appearance leaders, with appearances in 1982, 1988, 1989, 1993-2009. The Grizzlies playoff streak is the record at the I-AA level, now known as the NCAA Division I Championship Subdivision.&lt;ref&gt;Source: College Football Data Warehouse&lt;/ref&gt;  The team's continuous streak ended in 2010 with a loss to the Montana State University Bobcats ending their season with 7-4 record an no invitation to the post-season for the first time in 17 years.

The Grizzlies have won (105-27) games this decade (1998–2008) – the most wins by any FCS or Football Bowl Subdivision team in the nation. Currently from (1999–2009) they are (104-23) with an .819 winning percentage.
The stadium opened on October 18, 1986, and the Griz have racked up a home record of 142-20 (.876).

The Grizzlies won the national championship in 1995 under Don Read when [[Dave Dickenson]] led the team to a victory over [[Marshall University]] in the national championship game. In 2001, coach [[Joe Glenn]] led the Montana Grizzlies to another national championship, defeating [[Furman University]] by a score of 13-6.

The Grizzlies play in the [[Brawl of the Wild]] every year, a rivalry game against [[Montana State University - Bozeman]]. The Griz lead the series 68-35-5 ties. The Griz used to play a rivalry game against the [[University of Idaho]] Vandals for the [[Little Brown Stein]]. The Griz trail the all-time series 27-55-2. However, the Griz won the last four meetings between 2000–2003

Two players currently play for the Atlanta Falcons

===Men's Basketball===
{{Main|Montana Grizzlies men's basketball}}
The Men's Basketball team plays its home game at [[Dahlberg Arena]]. They have been to the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament]] 7 times and the [[National Invitation Tournament|NIT]] 3 times.
====Career leaders====
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=150px
!Points
|-
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0; width:100%;&quot;
!Player !! Points
|-
| McCloud, Trenton||2,017
|-
| [[Micheal Ray Richardson | Richardson, Micheal Ray]] ||1,827
|-
| Cope, Bob||1,810
|-
| Criswell, Kevin||1,663
|-
| Strait, Andrew||1,617
|-
| [[Wayne Tinkle | Tinkle, Wayne]]||1,500
|-
| Hasquet, Jordan||1,396
|-
| McKenzie, Ken||1,321
|-
| Samuelson, Shawn||1,293
|-
| Pope, Derrick||1,289
|-
| Rocheleau, Lou||1,235
|-
| Engellant, Daren||1,224
|-
| Davis, Charles||1,214
|-
| Kempfert, Matt||1,131
|-
| Spoja, Chris||1,111
|-
| Argenbright, Ed||1,100
|-
| Zanon, Craig||1,071
|-
| Zanon, Scott||1,070
|-
| Fasting, Roger||1,047
|-
| Warhank, Mike||1,046
|-
| Lake, Jeremy||1,036
|-
| Balko, Dan||1,025
|-
| Martin, Matt||1,021
|-
| Selvig, Doug||1,000
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=150px
!Rebounds
|-
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0; width:100%;&quot;
!Player !! Rebounds
|-
| [[Larry Krystkowiak | Krystkowiak, Larry]]||1105
|-
| Engellant, Daren||874
|-
| McKenzie, Ken||859
|-
| [[Wayne Tinkle | Tinkle, Wayne]]||836
|-
| Samuelson, Shawn||791
|-
| Sheriff, Russell||788
|-
| Lowry, Steve||763
|-
| Hasquet, Jordan||718
|-
| Strait, Andrew||711
|-
| Pope, Derrick||675
|-
| [[Micheal Ray Richardson | Richardson, Micheal Ray]] ||670
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=150px
!Assists
|-
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
!Player !! Assists
|-
| DeCuire, Travis||435
|-
| [[Shane Christensen | Christensen, Shane]]||431
|-
| Zanon, Scott||411
|-
| [[Micheal Ray Richardson | Richardson, Micheal Ray]] ||372
|-
| Glass, Marc||369
|-
| Camel, J.||365
|-
| Fastings, Roger||363
|-
| Selvig, Doug||361
|-
| Reed, Tony||339
|-
| Martin, Matt||317
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=150px
!Steals
|-
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
!Player !! Steals
|-
| Camel, J.||215
|}
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=150px
!Blocked Shots
|-
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
!Player !! Blocked Shots
|-
| Engellant, Daren||212
|}
|}

===Women's basketball===

The Lady Griz, as the women's basketball team is known, is one of the most successful women's basketball programs in the country. As of the end of the 2008-2009 season they have compiled a 757-252 (.750) record and a 388-85 (.820) conference record. Their head coach is Robin Selvig, who is now in in his 32 year, having compiled a record of 725-204 (.780). They play their games at [[Dahlberg Arena]].

The Lady Griz have made the [[NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship]] tournament 18 times, compiling a 6-18 record. They've also have 3 [[WNIT]] appearances. Through all of their success, the Lady Griz have never advanced past the second round, having reach it 7 times (1984, 1986, 1988, 1989, 1992, 1994, 1995). They have also won 22 regular season conference championships (Northwest Women's Basketball League (2), Mountain West Conference (5), Big Sky Conference (15).

==Athletic facilities==
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''Adams Center Auxiliary Gymnasiums'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-west-auxiliary-gym.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt; (Volleyball)
|-
|
* Built 1998
* Part of main facility Adams Center which opened in the fall of 1999 after nearly two years and $15 million of renovation.
* Divided into two separate venues (West and East).  
**West Auxiliary Gymnasium (WAG) - playing venue for volleyball program
*** WAG capacity (1218)
*** The WAG features a permanent maple wood floor and a high-intensity lighting system. A scoreboard from Dahlberg Arena was mounted on the south side of the WAG and permanent shot clocks for basketball were mounted behind the backstops. A state-of-the-art public-address system is in place, and eight speakers were installed at ceiling height to provide sound throughout the facility.
**East Auxiliary Gymnasium (EAG) - used as a practice facility for all UM sports programs, including basketball, cross country, golf, football, soccer, tennis, track &amp; field, and volleyball.
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''Athletic Performance Center'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-athletic-performance-center.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
* Built 1998-99 as part of the Adams Center renovation
* 7000 square feet

* Athletic Performance Center was created as part of the recent renovation to the Adams Center in 1999. The current facility is approximately twice as large as the previous weight room used in the Adams Center over the years.

The Athletic Performance Center staff designs, implements and evaluates strength and conditioning programs for all Grizzly athletes including sport-specific weight training, coupled with movement-specific conditioning.  The center features numerous free-weight stations and several weight-training machines.

Sport-specific weight training, coupled with movement-specific conditioning results in a greater overall training effect that transfers to the court during the season. Lifting is also a focus during the season. The student-athletes focus on several core lifts to maintain their strength levels during the long and grueling season.
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''[[Dahlberg Arena]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-dahlberg-arena.html&lt;/ref&gt; (Basketball)
|-
|
* Basketball Arena
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''[[Dornblaser Field]]'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-dornblaser-field.html&lt;/ref&gt; (Track and Field)
|-
|
* Built 1967
* Track and Field

* Off-campus facility bearing the same name as a former on-campus facility it replaced in 1967.  The Dornblaser fields successively fielded the Montana football team until a new facility (Washington-Grizzly Stadium) was completed on campus in 1986.
* Located next to the Soccer Stadium, the newly renovated Dornblaser Field recently received a complete reconstruction, including a resurfaced track, new field, new event equipment, and new bleachers.
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''Jacobsen Academic Center'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-jacobsen-academic-center.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
*The Jacobson Academic Center provides UM student-athletes access to a computer lab and a study room. A small conference room is available for group studying, as well as 10 desktop computer stations and free printing.  Both student-athletes and Athletic Academic Services use the facilities for programming. 

The Jacobson Academic Center, open Monday-Friday, 7:30 am - 6:00 pm, is located on the Adams Center’s ground floor, down the hall from the Athletic Performance Center. 
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''Rhinehard Athletic Training Center'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-rhinehart-athletic-training-center.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
* Completed 1999
* 7200 square feet
* The RATC provides numerous ways to treat injuries: electrical stimulation units, whirlpools, free weights and balance boards. The primary goal of the athletic training staff is to provide quality care for student-athletes while helping them safely return to competition.

* In an addition to an enlarged rehabilitation area, the center also includes athletic trainers’ offices, six hydrotherapy units and a consulting office where nutritionists and doctors can meet with athletes. There are also classrooms for the athletic training curriculum.

The RATC provides numerous ways to treat injuries: electrical stimulation units, whirlpools, free weights and balance boards. The primary goal of the athletic training staff is to provide quality care for student-athletes while helping them safely return to competition.

When a student-athlete is injured, an athletic trainer evaluates the severity of the injury and renders whatever care is needed. Depending on the extent of the injury, the student-athlete visits the center daily, at least two to three times, for treatment and rehabilitation exercises. The athletic training staff works together with the Athletic Performance staff to monitor the student-athlete's strengthening exercises. Once student-athletes have regained strength and function, they are allowed to return to the playing field or court.

Although athletic trainers provide injury care, they also promote injury prevention. Preventative maintenance occurs in the form of injury-screening processes, flexibility, taping and strengthening exercises.
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''Robert O. Lindsay Tennis Center'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-robert-o-lindsay-tennis-center.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
* Includes 9 courts
* Dedicated to Dr. Robert O. Lindsay, former faculty representative for athletics, in 1996.
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot; width=350px
!'''South Campus Stadium'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-south-campus-stadium.html&lt;/ref&gt; (Soccer)
|-
|
* Soccer Stadium
* Capacity (1000)

*Located at the corner of South and Higgins avenues, South Campus Stadium was constructed partly from volunteer funds and services donated by the Missoula soccer community. Irrigation, water and power lines, a grass field, a chain link fence surrounding the property, a scoreboard, and permanent seating for 1,000 spectators
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot;  width=350px
!'''[[Washington-Grizzly Stadium]]'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gogriz.com/facilities/mont-washington-grizzly-stadium.html&lt;/ref&gt; (Football)
|-
|
* Football Stadium
* Built 1986 (Expansions in 1995, 2003, and 2007)
** Current capacity (25,217)

* In August of 1985 Missoula businessman Dennis R. Washington and the employees of Washington Corporations provided a gift of $1 million and the stadium has since been the named Washington-Grizzly Stadium. The cost of the stadium was around $3.2 million.

There are 49 private boxes located on the east and west sides of the stadium, and they are individually decorated and furnished.

*Stadium Additions
** 1986 - Original layout had 12,500 permanent seats, and seating was available, weather-permitting, in the grass end zones, which made the capacity around 15,000.

** 1995 - In the spring of 1995 the stadium underwent its first expansion in the north and south end zones.  The cost of that expansion was about $2.5 million and brought seating to 19,000.

** 2001 - Sprinturf was added prior to the 2001 season at a cost of about $1 million, which was paid for by an anonymous donor, but with the request that the field be named “John Hoyt Field” in honor of John Hoyt, a long-time Grizzly booster, who passed away in March of that year. A new Sprinturf playing surface was installed prior to the 2008 season

** 2002 - GrizVision, a state-of-the-art video and message center, was added in 2002. GrizVision displays game statistics, player profiles, digital replays, and shots of the crowd. The screen is one of the largest in the FCS, measuring 26 feet by 36 feet, and it came from New York City and Times Square.

** 2003 - The second expansion occurred in the spring and summer of 2003, and approximately 4,000 seats were added to the north end zone section, increasing the stadium capacity to 23,183, with a cost around $3.5 million.

** 2007 - The third expansion, at a cost of approximately $6.5 million, occurred prior to the 2008 football season. The eastside expansion now houses a 500-seat “Stadium Club” with two membership levels: the “Canyon Room” has 125 seats inside and 125 seats outside, and the “Hellgate Terrace,” which has 250 seats.  This expansion increased the current seating capacity of Washington- Grizzly Stadium to 25,217.
|}

==University Marching Band==
{{Main|University of Montana Grizzly Marching Band}}

The band has its origins in the late 19th Century and has since continued its tradition into the new millennium. Marching in contemporary corps-style, the program endeavors to stay on the cutting edge of trends in outdoor music performances. The program is also one of the most visible organizations on the University of Montana campus, performing at all Grizzly football home games in the 25,500-seat [[Washington-Grizzly Stadium]]. The group also travels to several conference games throughout the Northwest and has accompanied the football team to four Division I-AA National Championships in recent years.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.umt.edu/music/ensembles/grizzly-marching-band School of Music's Grizzly Marching Band website&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fight song===
'''''&quot;Up With Montana&quot;''''' 
{{Quote box
| quote  = . . . and the squeal of the pig will float on the air; from the tummy of the Grizzly bear.
| source =''closing line of &quot;Up With Montana&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umt.edu/urelations/mainhall/0899/song.htm &quot;And it's 'Up with Montana' Folks&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
| font   = 120%
| width  = 26em
| align  = right
}}

The lyrics to &quot;Up with Montana&quot; are credited to Dick Howell, a Law student and member of the glee club in the 1910's, “to commemorate the rivalry” for game number twenty-one between UM and Montana State University, in 1914.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umt.edu/montanan/s07/artifacts.shtml Montana Magazine ''Artifacts'']&lt;/ref&gt; The origin of the tune itself, however, is disputed.  [[The Stanford Jonah]] is a fight song of the [[University of California, Berkeley]] written in 1913 by Ted Haley as an entry into a song contest held by the Daily Californian. The song continues to be a hit at most sporting events, but specifically at events between the [[California Golden Bears]] and their rival, the [[Stanford Cardinal]]. [[Georgia Institute of Technology|Georgia Tech's]] &quot;White And Gold&quot; and The [[Navy_Midshipmen|Naval Academy's]] &quot;Up With The Navy&quot; (which gives credit to the University of Montana&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usna.edu/USNABand/groups/marchingband.htm US Naval Academy Band]&lt;/ref&gt;)also share a similar tune as well.

==See also==
* [[List of college athletic programs in Montana]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{University of Montana}}
{{Montana Sports}}

[[Category:Montana Grizzlies|*]]
[[Category:College sports teams in Montana]]
[[Category:Sports in Missoula, Montana]]

[[es:Montana Grizzlies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
