<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="501393" ns="0" title="Wasim Akram"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox cricketer
|          playername = Wasim Akram&lt;br&gt;{{Nastaliq|وسیم اکرم}}
|              female =
|               image = Wasim_Akram.jpg
|             country = Pakistan
|            fullname = Wasim Akram Chaudhry
|            nickname = Sultan of Swing, The Two W's (with [[Waqar Younis]]), King Of Swing
|              living = true
|        partialdates =
|          dayofbirth = 3
|        monthofbirth = 6
|         yearofbirth = 1966
|        placeofbirth = [[Lahore]], [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]]
|      countryofbirth = Pakistan
|          dayofdeath =
|        monthofdeath =
|         yearofdeath =
|        placeofdeath =
|      countryofdeath =
|             batting = Left hand bat
|             bowling = Left arm [[Fast bowling|fast]]
|                role = ([[All-rounder]]) [[Bowler (cricket)|bowler]] and [[batsman]]
|       international = true
|       testdebutdate = 25 January
|       testdebutyear = 1985
|    testdebutagainst = New Zealand
|             testcap = 102
|        lasttestdate = 9 January
|        lasttestyear = 2002
|     lasttestagainst = Bangladesh
|        odidebutdate = 23 November
|        odidebutyear = 1984
|     odidebutagainst = New Zealand
|              odicap = 53
|         lastodidate = 4 March
|         lastodiyear = 2003
|      lastodiagainst = Zimbabwe
|            odishirt = 3
|               club1 = [[Hampshire County Cricket Club|Hampshire]]
|               year1 = 2003
|         clubnumber1 =
|               club2 = [[Lahore cricket team|Lahore]]
|               year2 = 2000–2001
|         clubnumber2 =
|               club3 = [[Lahore cricket team|Lahore]]
|               year3 = 1997–1998
|         clubnumber3 =
|               club4 = [[Pakistan International Airlines cricket team|Pakistan International Airlines]]
|               year4 = 1992–2002
|         clubnumber4 =
|               club5 = [[Lancashire County Cricket Club|Lancashire]]
|               year5 = 1988–1998
|         clubnumber5 =
|               club6 = [[Lahore cricket team|Lahore]]
|               year6 = 1986–1987
|         clubnumber6 =
|               club7 = [[Lahore cricket team|Lahore]]
|               year7 = 1985–1986
|         clubnumber7 =
|               club8 = [[Pakistan Automobiles Corporation cricket team|Pakistan Automobiles Corporation]]
|               year8 = 1984–1986
|         clubnumber8 =
|
|             columns = 4
|             column1 = [[Test cricket|Test]]
|            matches1 = 104
|               runs1 = 2898
|            bat avg1 = 22.64
|           100s/50s1 = 3/7
|          top score1 = 257[[not out|*]]
|         deliveries1 = 22627
|            wickets1 = 414
|           bowl avg1 = 23.62
|            fivefor1 = 25
|             tenfor1 = 5
|       best bowling1 = 7/119
|  catches/stumpings1 = 44/0
|             column2 = [[One Day International|ODI]]
|            matches2 = 356
|               runs2 = 3717
|            bat avg2 = 16.52
|           100s/50s2 = 0/6
|          top score2 = 86
|         deliveries2 = 18186
|            wickets2 = 502
|           bowl avg2 = 23.52
|            fivefor2 = 6
|             tenfor2 = 0
|       best bowling2 = 5/15
|  catches/stumpings2 = 88/0
|             column3 = [[First-class cricket|FC]]
|            matches3 = 257
|               runs3 = 7161
|            bat avg3 = 22.73
|           100s/50s3 = 7/24
|          top score3 = 257[[not out|*]]
|         deliveries3 = 50278
|            wickets3 = 1042
|           bowl avg3 = 21.64
|            fivefor3 = 70
|             tenfor3 = 16
|       best bowling3 = 8/30
|  catches/stumpings3 = 97/0
|             column4 = [[List A cricket|LA]]
|            matches4 = 594
|               runs4 = 6993
|            bat avg4 = 18.90
|           100s/50s4 = 0/17
|          top score4 = 89[[not out|*]]
|         deliveries4 = 29719
|            wickets4 = 881
|           bowl avg4 = 21.91
|            fivefor4 = 12
|             tenfor4 = 0
|       best bowling4 = 5/10
|  catches/stumpings4 = 147/0
|                date = 11 January
|                year = 2008
|              source = http://cricketarchive.com/Archive/Players/1/1774/1774.html CricketArchive
}}

'''Wasim Akram''' ({{lang-pa|{{Nastaliq|وسیم اکرم}}}}; born 3 June 1966) is a former [[Pakistani people|Pakistani]] left arm [[fast bowling|fast bowler]] and left-handed [[batsman]] in [[cricketer]] and [[Model (person)|model]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Wasim Akram Catwalk|url=http://www.pakmates.com/showthread.php?t=2024|publisher=PakMates.com|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; who represented the [[Pakistan national cricket team]] in [[Test cricket]] and [[One Day International]] (ODI) matches.

Akram is regarded as one of the best fast bowlers in the history of cricket. He holds the world record for most wickets in [[List A cricket]] with 881 and is second only to [[Sri Lanka national cricket team|Sri Lankan]] [[off-spin]] bowler, [[Muttiah Muralitharan]] in terms of ODI wickets with 502. He is considered to be one of the founders and perhaps one of the finest exponents of [[Reverse_swing#Reverse_swing|reverse swing]] bowling.&lt;ref name = &quot;wasim_cricinfo&quot;&gt;[http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/pakistan/content/player/43547.html Wasim Akram]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;odi_wkts&quot;&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/ODIS/BOWLING/ODI_BOWL_MOST_WKTS.html ODI Career Bowling – Most Wickets]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;lista_wkts&quot;&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/LISTA/BOWLING/LISTA_MOST_WKTS_CAREER.html List A Limited-Overs Most Wickets in Career]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

He was the first bowler to reach the 500-wicket landmark in ODI cricket during the 2003 World Cup. In 2002 Wisden released its only and final list of best players of all time. Wasim was ranked as the best bowler in ODI of all time with a rating of 1223.5, ahead of Allan Donald, Imran Khan, Waqar Younis, Joel Garner, Glen McGratt and Murali.

Wasim has taken 23 4-wicket hauls in ODI in 356 matches he played.  On 30 September 2009, Akram was one of five new members inducted into the [[ICC Cricket Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sports.in.msn.com/cricket/article.aspx?cp-documentid=3261064 |title=Wasim Akram, Steve Waugh inducted into ICC Hall of Fame |publisher=MSN Sports|accessdate=6 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early and personal life==

Akram was born in [[Lahore]], Pakistan on 3 June 1966, to a moderately affluent middle-class family.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.webcitation.org/5rgRJCtgc | title=Akram biography |accessdate=2 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was educated at [[Islamia College (Lahore)|Islamia College]] in Lahore, where he played as an opening bowler and batsman.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt; Like several other Pakistani cricketers during the 1980s, his inclusion into the national side was at the behest of a senior player in the team, which in Akram's case, was [[Javed Miandad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.webcitation.org/5rgbZgFMr | title=Wasim Akram; talkcricket Legend |accessdate=2 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Akram was diagnosed with [[diabetes]] at the peak of his career but despite the initial psychological blow, he managed to regain his form and went on to produce fine cricketing performances. Since then he has actively sought to be involved in various awareness-raising campaigns for diabetes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsline.com.pk/NewsDec2004/health1dec.htm Dealing With Diabetes]. ''[[Newsline]].'' Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was married to Huma in 1995. They had two sons Taimur and Akbar&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/DesiLife/article/203952 The Sultan swings by]. ''[[Toronto Star]].'' Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; from their marriage of fifteen years. Huma died of [[multiple organ failure]] at [[Apollo Hospital]] in [[Chennai]], India on 25 October 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.cricinfo.com/pakistan/content/story/431079.html | title=Pakistan / News – Akram's wife dies at the age of 42 | publisher=ESPN Cricinfo |accessdate=25 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== International career ==
===First-class cricket===
In 1988 he signed for [[Lancashire County Cricket Club]] in England and went on to become their most successful overseas players. From 1988 to 1998, he opened their bowling attack in their [[ECB Trophy]], Benson &amp; Hedges Cup and [[National League (cricket)|National League]] tournaments. He was a favourite of the local British fans who used to sing a song called &quot;Wasim for England&quot; at Lancashire's matches. In 1998, with Akram as captain, Lancashire won the ECB Trophy and [[Pro40|Axa League]] and finished second in the championship tournament despite losing only five matches in all competitions throughout the season. Apart from the National League second division title in 2003, this was the last time Lancashire won a trophy.&lt;ref name=&quot;brink&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/countycricket2007/content/story/311431.html |title=Lancashire on the brink of history |author=Cricinfo staff |publisher=ESPNcricinfo  |date=18&amp;nbsp;September 2007}} Retrieved on 11&amp;nbsp;October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Test cricket===
Akram made his [[Test cricket]] debut for Pakistan against [[New Zealand cricket team|New Zealand]] in 1985 and in only his second Test match, he claimed 10 wickets. A few weeks prior to his selection into the Pakistan team, he was an unknown club cricketer who had failed to make it even to his college team. He came to the trials at [[Gaddafi Stadium]] in Lahore in Pakistan, but for the first two days he did not get a chance to bowl. On the third day he got a chance; his performance convincing [[Javed Miandad]] to insist upon his inclusion in the national team. Akram was hence given an opportunity to play for Pakistan, without any significant domestic experience. Later that season he opened the bowling attack with [[Imran Khan]], who became his mentor at and after the [[World Championship of Cricket]] in Australia.

In the [[1987 Cricket World Cup]], when Pakistan played against the [[West Indies cricket team|West Indies]], Akram bowled to [[Viv Richards]] in the late overs of the innings but Richards, who is regarded as the best batsman during that period, struggled against Akram's bowling performances.

Akram's rise in international cricket was rapid during the late 1980s. When Pakistan toured the West Indies in 1988, he looked to be the fastest bowler between the two sides. However, a groin injury impeded his career in the late 1980s. Following two surgeries, he re-emerged in the 1990s as a fast bowler who focused more on swing and accurate bowling.

=== One Day International ===

Akram started his ODI career against New Zealand in Pakistan in 1984 under the Captaincy of Zaheer Abaass. He rose to prominence taking 5 wickets in his just 3rd ODI against an awesome Australian side in 1985 Benson &amp; Hedges World Championship who would be future winners of 1987 World Cup.His wickets included that of Kepler Wessels, Dean Jones and Captain Border. 
 
=== Rise to prominence (1983- Dec 1991)===

In 1984-85 Rothmans Four-Nations Cup and 1985-86 Rothmans Sharjah Cup he took 5 wickets with a run rate of under 3.50, which was consided to be magnificient even in that times.He started improving his bowling with the passage of time taking help from Senior Pakistani member Imran Khan.

In 1985-1986 [[Austral-Asia Cup|Austral-Asia Cup]] which involved [[Australia cricket team|Australia]], [[India cricket team|India]], [[New Zealand cricket team|New Zealand]], [[Pakistan cricket team|Pakistan]], [[Sri Lanka cricket team|Sri Lanka]] playing in [[United Arab Emirates|UAE]] Sharjah. Wasim Akram with the help of Abdul Qadir destroyed New Zealand batting line up for just 64 in the Second Semi final of Cup.Pakistan won that game with more than 27 overs to spare obtaining one of the biggest wins in Pakistani history.In Final against India he and Imran(Captain at that time) shared 5 wickets between them. His scalps included [[Dilip Vengsarkar|Dilip Vengsarkar]] and [[Ravi Shastri|Ravi Shastri]].Akram was becoming the darling of swing in Sharjah. His bowls were at times diffcult to read at the later half of innings making batsman busy in problems

In [[1987 World Cup |1987 Reliance World Cup ]]held for the 1st time in Sub Continent, Akram really struggled in Pakistani Pitches were he managed only 7 wickets with an average of 40+ in 7 matches. Akram played [[West Indies cricket team|West Indies]], [[Sri Lanka cricket team|Sri Lanka]] and [[England cricket team|England]] twice. All group matches were played in Pakistan.

In [[World Series Cup|1988-89 Benson and Hedges World Series]] he managed well 4-25 against powerful Australia.[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Players/PlayerProgressBowl_ODI.asp].He got his hundredth wicket at CA Sharjah in 1989-1990 Champions Trophy - 2nd Match against West Indies. His 100th wicket was of Ambrose.In that match he took 5 wickets only second time in his career.

On October 14, 1989 at [[Sharjah Cricket Association Stadium |Sharjah]] he took his 1st hat-trick against [[West Indies cricket team|West Indies]]. All 3 batsman were bowled. Again on 4 May 1990in Sharjah, Akram took his second ODI hat-trick against [[Australia cricket team|Australia]]. All 3 batsmen were bowled this time also.[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_One_Day_International_cricket_hat-tricks]. 
His best years in late 1980s were from 1986-1989 when which he took 100 wickets at 22.71 apiece and economy rate of less than 3.9 run/over with 4 4-wicket hauls. His first two 4-wicket hauls against Sri Lanka and Bangladesh came in bowler friendly conditions of Sri Lanka in 1986.[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Players/PlayerProgressBowl_ODI.asp?PlayerId=0029&amp;Year=1986].

Overall in this time period Akram rose from a young ordinary fast bowler to a dangerous wicket-taker who would move ball on any wicket he wanted to. Till Dec 1991 Akram took 143 wickets in 107 matches with an average of almost 24 and economy rate of 3.84. He took 5 4-wicket hauls. [http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/457149.html].

=== Peak Time (Jan 1992- Dec 1997)===

Akram was a significant figure in the [[1992 Cricket World Cup]] held in Australia, when Pakistan won the tournament. In the final against [[England national cricket team|England]], his batting performance during his innings of 33 runs off 19 balls, pushed Pakistan to a respectable score of 249 runs for 6 wickets. Akram then took the important wicket of [[Ian Botham]] early on the English batting innings and when brought back into the bowling attack later on, with the ball reverse swinging, he produced a devastating spell of bowling which led to [[Allan Lamb]] and [[Chris Lewis (cricketer)|Chris Lewis]] being bowled in successive deliveries in one over. His excellent performances earned him the [[Man of the Match]] award for the final.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/wc2007/content/story/284428.html Double jeopardy]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/wc2007/engine/match/65156.html Benson &amp; Hedges World Cup – Final, England v Pakistan]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;. In 1993 Akram took 2 consecutive 4-wicket hauls against Sri Lanka in Sharjah in which 7 out of 8 wickets were either lbw or bowled.[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Players/PlayerProgressBowl_ODI.asp].
In 1992-1993 Total International Series in South Africa (Involving Pakistan, West Indies and South Africa) his magic was destructive where he took 5 wickets against South Africa and got his 200th wicket in 143rd match. He now emerged as a dangerous bowler in bowler friendly pitches of [[South Africa cricket team|South Africa]].[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Matches/MatchScorecard_ODI.asp?MatchCode=0868].[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Players/PlayerBowlGraph_ODI.asp?PlayerID=0029].Akram took 46 wickets in calender year 1993 certainly his best year ever in ODI.Another astonishment was average which was less than 19 with an economy rate of less than 3.8 runs / over. He took 6 4-wicket hauls in 1993 most by him in any year. This was the year when he and Waqar were truly mesmerizing.[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Players/PlayerYears_ODI.asp?PlayerID=0029].In [[1996 Cricket World Cup|1996 World Cup]] he struggled as he missed crucial quarter final match against India which Pakistan lost and went out of the World Cup. From 1994 till 1996 he took 84 wickets in 39 matches. This time period was his golden time

[http://www.howstat.com.au/cricket/statistics/Players/PlayerYears_ODI.asp?PlayerID=0029].
From Jan 1992 - Dec 1997 Akram played 131 matches took 198 wickets at mere 21.86 apiece with 14 4-wicket hauls in ODIs.Run rate was also fantastic with less than 3.8 per over. Definitely his best era in ODI cricket.[http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/457149.html].

=== A tough Period with some joys (Jan 1998 till 2003 world cup)===

In 1999, he led Pakistan to the brink of victory in the World Cup before they capitulated and was defeated by Australia in the final, by eight wickets with almost 30 overs to spare. This was the start of the match fixing controversies, as critics believed Akram had set up the match for Australia. However, none of the allegations could be proved.

He was Pakistan's best bowler in the [[2003 Cricket World Cup]] taking 19 wickets in 6 matches. However, Pakistan failed to reach the &quot;Super Six&quot; phase of the tournament and Akram was one of the eight players to be sacked by the [[Pakistan Cricket Board]] as a result.

==Records==

He finished with 22 Man-of-the-Match awards in ODIs. In fact, Akram and Shaun Pollock (who also has 22) have the highest number of awards among players whose major suit isn't batting.[http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/457149.html].Out of 356 ODI matches he played Pakistan won 199 of them and 66 under his captaincy(He captained Pakistan in ODIs in 109 matches and has one of the best win ratio as a captain).In 199 win matches he took 326 wickets at fantastic 18.86 apiece with a run rate of 3.70 and took 18 4-wicket hauls.[http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/457149.html].

===Captaincy===

Wasim Akram captained Pakistan in 109 ODI matches out of 356 he played. Pakistan won 66 matches of them. So he has a win loss ratio of 1.60 which more than [[Imran Khan|Imran's]]1.27 , [[Waqar Younis|Waqar's]] 1.60. [http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/457149.html].Under his captaincy Pakistan played.He also captained Pakistan with some success. The high points of his captaincy was the 1996–1997 victory in the [[World Series Cricket]] in Australia, two Test match wins in India in 1998–1999 and in 1999, when Pakistan reached the [[1999 Cricket World Cup]] final. The low point was the [[1996 Cricket World Cup]] in Pakistan and India, when he had to pull out of the quarter final match against [[India cricket team|India]], citing injury. After Pakistan's defeat, there were angry protests outside his home and riots across the country from angry fans who accused the team of throwing the match and a government inquiry was launched into the failure.

===Retirement===
On 18 May 2003, at the age of 36, Akram abruptly announced his retirement from international cricket, ending a career which spanned 19 years. He had suggested that he was ready to quit several times towards the end of his career, but Pakistan's sub-par performance in the [[2003 Cricket World Cup|World Cup]] proved to be the deciding factor.

Prior to his retirement, he was one of eight senior players dropped for the Sharjah Cup in April 2003, and was then omitted from the Pakistan squad for the subsequent Bank Alfalah Cup triangular series.&lt;ref name=&quot;retirement&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.webcitation.org/5rgTcsNCa
| title = Akram announces retirement
| date = 18 May 2003
| accessdate =2 August 2010
| publisher=[[Cricinfo]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Due to his omission from the team, he did not participate in a farewell match.

Akram fulfilled his contract play for Hampshire until the end of the English season.

==Post retirement==
===Media career===
Since retiring from cricket, Akram has worked and taken up commentary for television networks and can currently be seen as a sports commentator for [[ESPN Star Sports]] and [[ARY Digital]] among others. He did commentary on a variety of sporting tournaments including the 2009 [[Women's Cricket World Cup]] in Australia, the [[2009 ICC World Twenty20]] in England, the [[2009 ICC Champions Trophy]] in South Africa, and the [[2011 ICC World Cup]] in India, Sri Lanka and Bangladesh.

===Coaching career===
In 2010, Akram was appointed the bowling coach consultant of [[Kolkata Knight Riders]], the [[Indian Premier League]] team for [[Kolkata]]. [[Sourav Ganguly]] was always keen to have Akram as the bowling coach for India, during the former's stint as Indian captain. Although this never happened, his dreams were realised to some extent, when Akram was appointed as the bowling coach for the franchise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=KKR can win IPL’s 3rd edition: Wasim Akram|url=http://www.thenews.com.pk/updates.asp?id=95819|publisher=The News International|accessdate=3 July 2010|date=11 January 2010}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
While working for the [[Kolkata Knight Riders]], he was also responsible for the signing of Pakistani domestic left-arm fast-bowler [[Mohammad Irfan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Pakistan's Mohammad Irfan in line for IPL contract|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/pakistan/content/current/story/471812.html|publisher=Cricinfo|accessdate=11 August 2010|date=10 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Akram has also been coaching in Pakistan fast bowling camps; his most notable discovery being the teenage Pakistani bowler Muhammad amir.

== Skills in cricket ==
{{rquote|left|Over my 15 or 16 years of playing international cricket in Tests and One Day Internationals, Wasim Akram is definitely the most outstanding bowler I've ever faced.| Former West Indies batsman [[Brian Lara]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smh.com.au/news/Sport/Lara-rates-Akram-better-than-McGrath/2007/03/29/1174761627979.html Lara rates Akram better than McGrath]. ''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]].'' Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
During his professional career he bowled with genuine speed and hostility. Akram was a man possessed of accurate control of line and length, accompanied by [[seam bowling|seam]] and [[swing bowling]] skills, extended to both [[inswinger]]s and [[outswinger]]s. With a very quick bowling action, he could bowl equally well from both sides of the wicket. His mastery of [[reverse swing]] with the cricket ball meant he was at his most dangerous towards a bowling innings, and earned him the nickname of one of the &quot;Sultans of Swing&quot;, the other one being Waqar Younis.

As well as often being able to find the edge of the bat, Akram would also focus his bowling attack on the [[stump (cricket)|stumps]] and had a particularly lethal inswinging [[yorker]]. Of his 414 Test wickets, 193 were taken [[caught]], 119 were taken [[leg before wicket]] and 102 were [[bowled]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BOWLING/TRIVIA/MOST_TEST_CAUGHT.html Tests – Most Wickets Taken Caught]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BOWLING/TRIVIA/MOST_TEST_LBW.html Tests – Most Wickets Taken LBW]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BOWLING/TRIVIA/MOST_TEST_BOWLED.html Tests – Most Wickets Taken Bowled]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In partnership with [[Waqar Younis]], he intimidated international batsmen in the 1990s. Together Wasim and Waqar, known as &quot;the two Ws&quot; of the Pakistani team, were one of the most successful bowling partnerships in cricket.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/217157.html Home truths, and the greatest fast-bowling pairs]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Akram was also skilled with the bat and was regarded as a bowling [[all-rounder]]. He was especially effective against spin bowlers. However, he liked to slog and was criticised for his lack of high scores and giving away his wicket too cheaply for a player of his talent. He did silence his critics and the media in October 1996 when he scored 257 runs not out, of the team's total of 553 against [[Zimbabwe cricket team|Zimbabwe]] at [[Sheikhupura]]. He also achieved good scores for the Pakistan team such as his scores of 123 and 45* against Australia to take Pakistan to victory in a low scoring match. His batting was also valuable to the Pakistan ODI side, such as his match winning performance in the [[Nehru Cup (cricket)|Nehru Cup]], when needing six runs and two balls to win the match; he hit the first delivery he faced for six runs and secured the cup.

===Modeling===
He had walked in the [[Pantene Bridal Couture Week 2011]] which was an event of [[Style 360]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Waseem Akram also runs at Ramp|url=http://www.awomensclub.com/pantene-bridal-couture-week-2011.php|publisher=A Women's Club|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Wasim Akram at Pantene Bridal Couture Week 2011|url=http://www.zimbio.com/Pakistan/articles/_oSLqyNh3Ih/Pantene+Bridal+Couture+Week+2011|publisher=Zimbo.com|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

== Award and records ==
{{see also|List of international cricket five-wicket hauls by Wasim Akram }}

Akram was awarded [[Wisden Cricketer of the Year]] in 1993 for his sporting achievements.

*In his [[Test cricket|Test]] career, Akram took 414 wickets in 104 matches, a Pakistani record, at an [[bowling average|average]] of 23.62 and scored 2,898 runs, at an [[batting average|average]] of 22.64.&lt;ref name = &quot;test_wkts&quot;&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BOWLING/TEST_BOWL_MOST_WKTS.html Test Career Bowling – Most Wickets]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

*In [[One Day International]]s, Akram took 502 wickets in 356 appearances, at an average of 23.52 and scored 3,717 runs, at an average of 16.52.&lt;ref name = odi_wkts/&gt;

*Akram was the first bowler in international cricket to take more than 400 wickets in both forms of the game and only [[Muttiah Muralitharan]] has since achieved this.&lt;ref name = odi_wkts/&gt;&lt;ref name = test_wkts/&gt;

*Akram also held the record for the most wickets in [[Cricket World Cup]]s, a total of 55 in 38 matches. [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]]'s [[Glenn McGrath]] broke the record during the [[2007 Cricket World Cup]], ending with a final tally of 71 from 39 matches.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/WC/BOWLING/WC_BOWL_MOST_WKTS.html World Cup Bowling – Most Wickets]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; On passing Wasim's record, McGrath said, &quot;Wasim Akram, to me, is one of the greatest bowlers of all time. Left-armer, swung it both ways with the new ball and he was so dangerous with the old ball. To go past him is something I will always remember. Probably the other side of the coin is that if you play long enough, you're going to break records here and there.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.smh.com.au/sport/archives/2007/04/pigeon_v_wasim_whos_the_best.html Pigeon v Wasim – who's the best?]. ''[[The Sydney Morning Herald]].'' Retrieved on 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

*Akram took four [[hat-trick]]s in international cricket, two each in Tests matches and One Day Internationals. He is the only bowler in cricket to have achieved four hat-tricks. He was the third of only three bowlers to have taken two [[Test cricket hat-tricks]], the others being [[Hugh Trumble]] and [[Jimmy Matthews]]. Akram was also the first of only five bowlers to have taken two [[One Day International cricket hat-tricks]]. Akram's Test hat-tricks are significant, since they were taken in consecutive Test matches in the same series, a game played against Sri Lanka in the [[1998-99 Asian Test Championship]]. Akram is also one of only two bowlers to have taken both a Test match and One Day International hat-trick, the other being Pakistan fast bowler, [[Mohammad Sami]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BOWLING/TEST_HAT-TRICKS.html Hat Tricks in Test Matches]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/ODIS/BOWLING/ODI_BOWL_HAT-TRICKS.html One Day Internationals – Hat Tricks]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

*Playing in a Test series against the [[West Indies national cricket team|West Indies]] at Lahore in 1990–1991, he became one of only six players to have taken four wickets in an over during a Test match. In Akram's case, these achievement was not part of a hat-trick, the third ball he delivered to the batting opposition was a dropped catch, which allowed a single run.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content-uk.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/287834.html Four wickets in an over, and who's the Cockroach?]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/ARCHIVE/1990-91/WI_IN_PAK/WI_PAK_T3_06-11DEC1990.html Pakistan v West Indies, 1990/91, 3rd Test]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

*Akram has also achieved the highest score by a number eight batsman in Test cricket when he scored 257 runs not out from 363 balls against [[Zimbabwe national cricket team|Zimbabwe]] at [[Sheikhupura]]. The innings contained 12 [[six (cricket)|six]]es which is also a world record for Test cricket.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BATTING/HIGHEST_BATTING_POSITION.html Tests – Highest Score at Each Batting Position]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/BATTING/TRIVIA/BAT_MOST_SIXES_TEST.html Tests – Most Sixes in an Innings]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

*He also has the third highest number of Man of the Match awards in Test cricket, with seventeen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/STATS/TESTS/INDIVIDUAL/TEST_MOST_MOM.html Tests – Most Man of the Match Awards]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

*He has scored the record number of runs in One Day International matches by a player who has never scored a One Day International hundred. His highest score was 86 runs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/ci/content/records/284205.html | title=Records / One Day Internationals / Batting records / Most runs in a career without a hundred | publisher=ESPN cricinfo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cricket controversies ==
In 1992, after he had been successful against the English batsmen, accusations of [[ball tampering]] began to appear in the English media, though no video evidence of foul play was ever found. Akram and Younis had been able to obtain prodigious amounts of movement from both new and old cricket balls. The skill of the [[reverse swing]] delivery was relatively unknown in England and around the cricketing world during that period.

A far larger controversy was created when critics alleged that he was involved in match fixing. An inquiry commission was set up by the Pakistan Cricket Board headed by a Pakistan high court judge, [[Malik Mohammad Qayyum]]. The judge wrote in his report that:&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.cricinfo.com/db/NATIONAL/PAK/NEWS/qayyumreport/qayyum_report.html Justice Qayyum's Report]. ESPNcricinfo. Retrieved on 1 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|''This commission feels that all is not well here and that Wasim Akram is not above board. He has not co-operated with this Commission. It is only by giving Wasim Akram the benefit of the doubt after [[Ata-ur-Rehman]] changed his testimony in suspicious circumstances that he has not been found guilty of match-fixing. He cannot be said to be above suspicion.''|}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{Cricinfo | ref = pakistan/content/player/43547.html}}
* {{Cricketarchive | ref = Archive/Players/1/1774/1774.html}}
* {{Yahoo!_Cricket| ref= player-profile/Wasim-Akram_3154}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-sports}}
{{succession box|
before= [[Aamer Sohail]]|
title= [[Pakistani national cricket captains|Pakistan Cricket Captain]]|
years= 1999–2000|
after= [[Moin Khan]]
}}
{{s-ach}}
{{succession box | title=[[Wisden Leading Cricketer in the World]]|before=[[Curtly Ambrose]]|after=[[Shane Warne]]|years=1992}}
{{s-end}}

{{Bowlers who took 300 wickets in Test cricket}}
{{5WI 25 times}}
{{All-rounders-Double}}
{{Bowlers who have taken 400 wickets in ODI}}
{{Pakistan Squad 1987 Cricket World Cup}}
{{Pakistan Squad 1992 Cricket World Cup}}
{{Pakistan Squad 1996 Cricket World Cup}}
{{Pakistan Squad 1999 Cricket World Cup}}
{{Pakistan Squad 2003 Cricket World Cup}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME= Wasim Akram
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES= Akram, Wasim
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Pakistani cricketer
|DATE OF BIRTH=3 June 1966
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Lahore]], [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]], Pakistan
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Wasim Akram}}
[[Category:Pakistan One Day International cricketers]]
[[Category:Pakistan Test cricketers]]
[[Category:Pakistani cricket captains]]
[[Category:Hampshire cricketers]]
[[Category:Lahore cricketers]]
[[Category:People from Lahore]]
[[Category:Lancashire cricketers]]
[[Category:Lancashire cricket captains]]
[[Category:Pakistan Automobiles Corporation cricketers]]
[[Category:Pakistan International Airlines cricketers]]
[[Category:Wisden Cricketers of the Year]]
[[Category:Wisden Leading Cricketers in the World]]
[[Category:Test cricket hat-trick takers]]
[[Category:One Day International hat-trick takers]]
[[Category:Cricket commentators]]
[[Category:Cricketers at the 1987 Cricket World Cup]]
[[Category:Cricketers at the 1992 Cricket World Cup]]
[[Category:Cricketers at the 1996 Cricket World Cup]]
[[Category:Cricketers at the 1999 Cricket World Cup]]
[[Category:Cricketers at the 2003 Cricket World Cup]]
[[Category:1966 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Pakistani Sunni Muslims]]
[[Category:Punjabi people]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from Lahore]]
[[Category:International Cricket Council Hall of Fame inductees]]

[[bn:ওয়াসিম আকরাম]]
[[de:Wasim Akram]]
[[fr:Wasim Akram]]
[[kn:ವಾಸಿಂ ಆಕ್ರಮ್]]
[[ml:വസീം അക്രം]]
[[mr:वासिम अक्रम]]
[[pnb:وسیم اکرم]]
[[ta:வசீம் அக்ரம்]]
[[ur:وسیم اکرم]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
