<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="501636" ns="0" title="Unix wars"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=December 2009}}

[[Image:Unix history.svg|thumb|450px|Unix genealogy tree]]
The '''Unix wars''' were the struggles between [[vendor]]s of the [[Unix]] [[computer]] [[operating system]] in the late 1980s and early 1990s to set the standard for Unix thenceforth.

== Origins ==

In the mid-1980s, the two common versions of Unix were [[BSD]], from the [[University of California, Berkeley]], and [[UNIX System V|System V]], from [[AT&amp;T]]. Both were derived from the earlier [[Version 7 Unix]], but had diverged considerably. Further, each vendor's version of Unix was different to some degree.

A group of vendors formed the [[X/Open]] [[open standard|standard]]s group in 1984, with the aim of forming compatible [[open system (computing)|open system]]s. They chose to base their system on Unix.

X/Open caught AT&amp;T's attention. To increase the uniformity of Unix, AT&amp;T and leading BSD Unix vendor [[Sun Microsystems]] started work in 1987 on a unified system. (The feasibility of this had been demonstrated a few years earlier by the [[US Army]] [[Ballistic Research Laboratory]]'s System V environment for BSD Unix.)  This was eventually released as ''System V Release 4'' (SVR4).

While this decision was applauded by customers and the trade press, certain other Unix licensees feared Sun would be unduly advantaged. They formed the [[Open Software Foundation]] (OSF) in 1988.  The same year, AT&amp;T and another group of licensees responded by forming [[UNIX International]].  Technical issues soon took a back seat to vicious and public commercial competition between the two &quot;open&quot; versions of Unix, with X/Open holding the middle ground.

== The move towards open source code ==

In March 1993 the major participants in UI and OSF formed the [[Common Open Software Environment]] (COSE) alliance, effectively marking the end of the most significant era of the Unix wars.  In June, AT&amp;T sold its UNIX assets to [[Novell]], and in October Novell transferred the Unix brand to X/Open. 

In 1996, X/Open and the new OSF merged to form the [[Open Group]].  COSE work such as the [[Single UNIX Specification]], the current standard for branded Unix, is now the responsibility of the Open Group. However, the damage to Unix's market reputation had been done.

Since then, occasional bursts of Unix factionalism have broken out, such as the [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]]/SCO &quot;[[3DA]]&quot; alliance in 1995, and [[Project Monterey]] in 1998, a teaming of [[IBM]], [[Santa Cruz Operation|SCO]], [[Sequent Computer Systems|Sequent]] and [[Intel Corporation|Intel]] which was followed by litigation ([[SCO v. IBM]]) between IBM and the [[The SCO Group|new SCO, formerly Caldera]].

The [[Berkeley Software Distribution]] emerged as an independent Unix-like operating system, with the purging of code copyrighted by AT&amp;T, in the period 1989-1994. During this time various open-source BSD derivatives took shape, starting with [[386BSD]], which was soon succeeded by [[FreeBSD]] and [[NetBSD]]. [[OpenBSD]] emerged in 1995 as a fork of NetBSD.

=== Rise of GNU and Linux ===

During BSD's period of legal turmoil, the nearly-complete [[GNU]] operating system was made operational by the inclusion of the [[Linux]] kernel, and countless operating systems, lumped together under the label &quot;GNU/Linux&quot;, emerged that were based on this combination. Linux derivatives are not compatible enough to qualify for the Unix trademark. On the other hand, BSD systems can at least claim direct ancestry to [[Version 7 Unix]]. Or, according to Open Source advocate [[Eric Raymond]], BSD systems can be considered &quot;genetic Unix&quot;, if not &quot;trademark Unix&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.internetnews.com/dev-news/print.php/2208691&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Mac OS X v10.5]] is the first operating system with open source BSD code to be certified as fully Unix compliant.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opengroup.org/comm/press/19-2-nov07.htm Mac OS X Leopard Achieves UNIX 03 Product Standard Certification]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Editor war]]

==References==
{{Citation style|date=September 2009}}
*[http://livinginternet.com/i/iw_unix_war.htm Unix Wars] (Living Internet)
*[http://www.bell-labs.com/history/unix/wars.html The UNIX Wars] (Bell Labs)
*[http://www.unix.org/what_is_unix/history_timeline.html The UNIX System&amp;nbsp;— History and Timeline] (The Open Group)
*[http://www.faqs.org/docs/artu/ch17s02.html Unix Standards] ([[Eric S. Raymond]], ''[[The Art of Unix Programming]]'')
*[http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20050601125916588 Chapter 11. OSF and UNIX International] ([[Peter H. Salus]], ''The Daemon, the GNU and the Penguin'')
&lt;references /&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Unix Wars}}
[[Category:Unix history]]
[[Category:Software wars]]

[[ar:حروب يونكس]]
[[cs:Unixové války]]
[[hu:Unix-háborúk]]
[[ja:UNIX戦争]]
[[pt:Guerras do Unix]]
[[sl:vojne Unixov]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
