<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="502336" ns="0" title="Trinity College, Hartford"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name            = Trinity College
|image_name      = Trinity College Connecticut Seal.svg
|image_size      = 200px
|motto           = Pro Ecclesia Et Patria
|mottoeng          = For Church and Country
|established     = May 1823
|type            = Private
|affiliation = [[Nonsectarian]]
|endowment       = $441 million&lt;ref&gt;http://softlaunch.trincoll.edu/AboutTrinity/offices/president/whitepaper/Documents/ToReweaveTheHelicesWcover.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|faculty         = 267
|president       = [[James F. Jones|James F. Jones, Jr.]]
|dean            = Rena Fraden
|undergrad       = 2,144
|postgrad        = 104 (includes post-doctoral students and visiting scholars)
|city            = [[Hartford, Connecticut|Hartford]]
|state           = [[Connecticut]]
|country         = [[United States|USA]]
|campus          = Urban
|sports          = 29 varsity teams&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncaa.com/schools/713_Trinity_Conn.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors		 = [[Blue (color)|Blue]] and [[Gold (color)|Gold]] {{color box|#1E388C}} {{color box|#FFC424}}
|nickname	 = Bantams
|mascot		 = [[Bantam (chicken)|Bantam]]
|athletics	 = [[NCAA]] [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]]
|affiliations	 = [[New England Small College Athletic Conference|NESCAC]]
|website         = [http://www.trincoll.edu www.trincoll.edu]
|logo            = [[File:Trinity College Connecticut.svg]]
}}

'''Trinity College''' is a private, [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States|liberal arts college]] in [[Hartford, Connecticut]]. Founded in 1823, it is the second-oldest college in the state of Connecticut after [[Yale University]]. The college enrolls 2,300 students and has been coeducational since 1969. Trinity offers 38 majors and 26 minors, and has a student to faculty ratio of 10:1. The college is also known as one of the few [[Little Ivies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hclib.org/pub/search/fff/FullDisplay.cfm?ID=232&amp;Term=universities |title=Hennepin County Library – Fugitive Fact File – LITTLE IVY LEAGUE (COLLEGES) |publisher=Hclib.org |date=February 19, 2009 |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trinity's stated mission is to &quot;foster critical thinking, free the mind of parochialism and prejudice, and prepare students to lead examined lives that are personally satisfying, civilly responsible, and socially useful&quot;.

== History ==

[[File:Burgesplan.jpg|left|thumb|200px|[[William Burges (architect)|William Burges]]'s original plan for the campus of Trinity College]]
[[File:trincollchapel.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Trinity College Chapel, Hartford]]
[[File:Trincolllibrarysnow2003.JPG|thumb|200px|The $35 million Raether Library, completed in 2003, shown during a snow storm]]
[[File:Seabury Hall.jpg|thumb|Seabury Hall, part of a $32.9 million renovation and restoration of the Long Walk buildings]]
[[File:Trinity College Clock Tower.jpg|thumb|The Downes Memorial clock tower during the spring semester]]

=== Early history ===

Trinity was founded in the spring of 1823 as Washington College, in downtown Hartford, receiving its current name in 1845. Because of the social dominance of rival [[Congregationalists]] in Connecticut and because Trinity's founder and first president, the [[Thomas Church Brownell|Rt. Rev. Thomas Brownell]], was an [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal]] [[bishop]], the college had some early difficulties obtaining its charter from the state.  A condition imposed by the charter was that, despite its Episcopal roots, the college must prohibit any imposition of religious standards on students, faculty members, or other members of the college. A year after opening, Trinity moved to its first campus, which consisted of two Greek Revival-style buildings, one housing a chapel, library, and lecture rooms and the other a dormitory.  Within a few years the student body grew to nearly one hundred, a size that was rarely exceeded until the 20th century.

=== A new campus ===

In 1872 Trinity College was persuaded by the State of Connecticut to move from its downtown “College Hill” location (now Capitol Hill, the site of the state capitol building) to its current {{convert|100|acre|ha|sing=on}} campus a mile to the southwest.  Although the college sold its land overlooking the [[Park River]] and [[Bushnell Park]] in 1872, it did not complete its move to its Gallows Hill campus until 1878.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trincoll.edu/AboutTrinity/CollegeHistory.htm |title=Trinity College |publisher=Trincoll.edu |date= |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Trinity’s first plan for the Gallows Hill site proved to be too ambitious (and too expensive) to be completely built.  Only one section of the proposed campus plan, the [[Trinity College Long Walk|Long Walk]], was completed.

=== Trinity in the twentieth century ===

Trinity ended the nineteenth century as an institution primarily serving the Hartford area.  The founding of the [[University of Hartford]] in 1877, however, allowed Trinity to focus on becoming a regional institution rather than a local one.  The early years of the century were primarily growth years for Trinity.  Enrollment was increased to 500 men.  In 1932 under President Remsen Ogilby, the Gothic chapel was completed, becoming the symbol of Trinity College.  It replaced the Seabury chapel which had become too small for the student body.

In 1968 the trustees of Trinity College voted to make a commitment to enroll (with financial aid as needed) more minority students.  This decision was preceded by a siege of the administrative offices in the Downes and Williams Memorial buildings during which Trinity students would not allow the president or trustees to leave until they agreed to the resolution. 

Less than one year later Trinity College became co-educational and admitted its first female students, as transfers from [[Vassar College]].  Today, women make up about 50 percent of Trinity's student body.

== Traditions ==
=== Matriculation ===
The matriculation ceremony, sometimes referred to as the &quot;signing of the books,&quot; first started in 1826 and is the oldest continuously observed tradition at Trinity. First year students formally join Trinity College as students by signing the matriculation register. By signing the register, students agree to the declaration found in The Charter and Standing Rules that reads: &quot;I promise to observe the Statutes of Trinity College; to obey all its Rules and Regulations; to discharge faithfully all scholastic duties imposed upon me; and to maintain and defend all the rights, privileges, and immunities of the College according to my station and degree in the same.&quot; Symbolic of Trinity's becoming coeducational in 1969, the first student to sign the matriculation register was a woman.&lt;ref&gt;http://library.trincoll.edu/research/watk/archives/trinitytraditions.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Bantam ===
Trinity's mascot, the bantam, was conceived by Hon. Joseph Buffington, Class of 1875, who was a federal judge and trustee of the College. He was a noted speaker, and gave an address during an 1899 dinner with alumni of other prestigious colleges. Giving his view on what a Trinity student is, and supporting his view that Trinity students are different from the &quot;collegiate barnyard&quot; consisting of Harvard and Yale (amongst others such as Amherst), Buffington said: &quot;But I tell you, my fellow chanticleers, that the Trinity bantam has been brought up in the Trinity barnyard on different principles, and the most marked outcome of his collegiate training is the fostering of a habit which leads him to size things from his own standpoint, and not have somebody else size them for him.&quot; He continued, saying: &quot;You will therefore understand, gentlemen, the spirit in which the Trinity bantam, game from comb to spur, crows at your door, hops in, shakes his tail feathers, and with a sociable nod to the venerable John, and a good natured &quot;How d'ydo&quot; to the ponderous old Elihu steps into the collegiate cock pit, makes his best bow to the tiger, says he is glad to be here, is not a whit abashed at your hugeness, [and] is satisfied with himself and his own particular coop.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://library.trincoll.edu/research/watk/archives/trinitytraditions.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;

Subsequent to this address, word spread throughout campus, and newspapers began to refer to the Trinity athletic teams as the &quot;bantams.&quot; Soon after, the bantam became accepted at Trinity and at fellow colleges as the mascot and has been so ever since.

== Alma Mater ==
Trinity's alma mater is &quot;’Neath the Elms.&quot; It was written in 1882 by Trinity student Augustus P. Burgwin to the tune of a song that his butler often sang. When &quot;'Neath the Elms&quot; was written, the College had been planting elm trees on the quad, which remain today. Trinity alumni use this as a motto when referencing Trinity; for example, a Trinity alumnus would say to another: &quot;I'll see you 'neath the elms.&quot; The alma mater of Trinity College is also the basis for other terms used on campus, such as &quot;Ol' Trin.&quot;

:’Neath the elms of our old Trinity, 
:’Neath the elms of our dear old Trinity, 
:No more shall we meet,
:Our classmates to greet,
:’Neath the elms of our old Trinity.
: &amp;nbsp;
:’Neath the elms of our old Trinity. 
:’Neath the elms of our dear old Trinity 
:Oh it’s seldom we’ll meet,
:In the moonlight so sweet,
:’Neath the elms of our old Trinity.
: &amp;nbsp;
:On the hills of our old Trinity,
:In the halls of our dear old Trinity, 
:There is bright merry cheer,
:There are friends true and dear,
:In the halls of our old Trinity.
: &amp;nbsp;
:College days are from care and sorrow free. 
:And oft will we seek in memory
:Those days that are past,
:Far too joyous to last,
:’Neath the elms of our old Trinity.
: &amp;nbsp;
:Then we’ll sing to our old Trinity, 
:To our dear old Alma Mater, Trinity; 
:We’re together today,
:And tomorrow away,
:Far away from our old Trinity.

&lt;ref&gt;http://www.trincoll.edu/AboutTrinity/commencement/Documents/185thCommencement.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Hartford Campus ==

The first buildings completed on the current campus were Seabury and Jarvis halls in 1878. Together with Northam Towers, these make up what is known as the &quot;[[Trinity College Long Walk|Long Walk]]&quot;. These buildings are the earliest examples of [[Collegiate Gothic]] architecture in the United States, built to plans drawn up by [[William Burges (architect)|William Burges]], with [[Francis Kimball|F.H. Kimball]] as supervising architect.  The Long Walk has been expanded and is connected with several other buildings.  On the northernmost end there is the Chapel, whose western side is connected to the Downes and Williams Memorial building. Heading south, the next building is Jarvis.  Jarvis becomes Northam Towers heading south, then Seabury Hall.  Seabury Hall, named for [[Samuel Seabury (1729–1796)]], is connected to Hamlin Hall.  To Hamlin's east is Cook, then Goodwin and then Woodard.  The dormitories on the Long Walk end there, and the terminal building on the south end of the long walk is Clement/[[Cinestudio]].  Clement is the chemistry building; [[Cinestudio]] a student run movie theater. If one travels to the south of Hamlin there will be Mather Hall and the Dean of Students Office.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.trincoll.edu/NR/rdonlyres/49EA971F-5F57-43DA-A0F0-A276AE77F148/0/CampusMap2009.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Trinity's other landmark is its distinctive chapel. The Trinity College Chapel was built in the 1930s to replace Trinity's original chapel, located in Seabury Hall (now a lecture hall).  The Chapel's facade is made almost entirely of limestone and therefore blends into the adjacent Downes Memorial Clock Tower.  Its primary architect was [[Philip Hubert Frohman]], of [[Frohman, Robb and Little]], who was also responsible for the [[National Cathedral]] in Washington, DC. There are two dormitories named after these three people.  The first is the Frohman-Robb dormitory known colloquially as &quot;Frobb.&quot;  There is another dormitory called Little in honor of the third architect.  The two dormitories are adjacent and are on the south side of campus, behind the Life Science Center (LSC).

Another feature of Trinity's campus is its central green known as the Main Quad, which is bound on the west by the Long Walk, on the east by the Lower Long Walk, on the north by the Chapel, and on the south by the Cook, Goodwin and Woodard dormitories..  While a central green is a feature of many college campuses, Trinity's is notable for its unusually large size, running the entire length of the Long Walk and with no paved or unpaved walkways traversing it. Trees on the Quad have been planted in a 'T' configuration (for Trinity) with the letter's base located at the statue of Bishop Brownell and its top running the length of the Long Walk.  Tradition holds that the trees were intended to distinguish Trinity's campus from Yale's.  Also located on the Quad are two cannons used on the ''USS Hartford'', flagship of Admiral [[David Farragut]] during the [[American Civil War]].

The whole of Trinity's campus is set out on a {{convert|100|acre|ha|sing=on}} parcel of land that is bound on the south by New Britain Avenue, on the west by Summit Street, on the east by Broad Street, and on the north by Allen Place. Trinity's former northern border, Vernon Street, has been transferred from the city of Hartford to Trinity College and closed off at one end (Broad Street), creating a cul-de-sac within Trinity's borders. Completed in 2001, and located on what was formerly an abandoned bus depot adjacent to Trinity's campus, the Learning Corridor is a collection of K-12 public magnet schools co-created by Trinity and the governments of Hartford and Connecticut.

Crescent Street is the only through street on Trinity's campus. The only other exception until its recent closure was Vernon Street, at the north end of the campus. Since the street was transferred to the school from the city, Trinity widened and repaved it, as well as installing light posts about every ten feet and adding granite crosswalks, curbs, benches, and fenceposts.  Vernon Street is the location of most of the campus' cultural houses and Greek organizations, as well as Vernon Social Center.  There are also various residences on that street, including the President's house and the Smith House for visitors.

=== Important buildings on campus ===

* '''Albert C. Jacobs Life Sciences Center''' – Built in 1967 in the architectural style of [[Brutalism]], the Life Science Center, or LSC, was designed to be an abstract representation of the Long Walk. The building houses Trinity's departments of Biology and Psychology. It contains several classrooms, an auditorium, teaching labs, research labs, and a greenhouse. Trinity's first dedicated neuroscience lab is to be built in LSC in 2011. Fund raising is underway to construct a neuroscience suite and a music rehearsal hall on the north side of LSC.
* '''Austin Arts Center''' – The AAC was designed in the 1960s, and contains art exhibition spaces, two theaters (Garmany and Goodwin) , a few classrooms, and is home to the offices of Theater and Dance and Music professors.
* '''Clement''' - The Clement Center, is home to the Chemistry department. Clement contains four teaching laboratories, eight research laboratories, instrument rooms, computer rooms, and classrooms. It also offers its own library, conducive to scholarly pursuits and thoughtful concentration. During the summer of 2011, the building will undergo of $750,000 renovation of five of its laboratories through funds provided by the National Science Foundation. Clement is also home to [[Cinestudio]], the on campus movie theater.
* '''Facilities''' (Formerly Buildings and Grounds)  The facilities building is the home of various departments that relate to the maintenance of the physical (as opposed to the academic) aspects of the College.  Included in this building is the Director of Facilities, the Superintendent of Grounds, the Superintendent of Construction Trades (who is also the Superintendent of Access Control), various engineers, electricians, painters, carpenters and mechanics.
* '''Ferris Athletic Center'''*- Ferris Athletic Center includes a field house, an eight-lane, 37-meter swimming pool with a movable bulkhead, 16 international-size squash courts, two basketball courts, 2 weight rooms, one of which that is new and used for varsity team athletes, two crew tanks, a wrestling room and a 1/10-mile indoor track. Adjacent to Ferris are 19 acres of playing fields for soccer, lacrosse, field hockey, and baseball as well as the  multi- purpose Robin L. Sheppard Field and the 6,500- seat [[Jessee/Miller Field|Dan Jessee/Don Miller Football Field and Track]].
* '''Jarvis Hall''' – This section of the Long Walk contains single, double and quad dorms, primarily for juniors and seniors.  It is rumored that the doubles were originally designed for students while the singles across the hallway were intended for their servants. In actuality, the single rooms were single bedrooms, which opened into living areas, which are currently the doubles and the hallway, and six rooms retain this layout. As of the 2008 school year, the massive Long Walk Reconstruction project has been completed, and the dorms are built in a classic style.
* '''Mather Hall''' – located just south of Hamlin Hall (the southern terminus of the long walk), Mather Hall is the main student center of Trinity College.  The building contains the main dining hall as well as &quot;The Cave&quot; dining hall, a post office and student mail boxes, a coffee house, as well as meeting rooms and a large auditorium.
* '''Math, Computing, and Engineering Center''' – also known as the MCEC, is located on the Life Sciences Quad (named for the Life Sciences Center, which dominates the eastern side of the quad) it is made of brick and sandstone.
* '''Northam Towers''' – This central tower on the Long Walk, flanked by the Fuller archway, connects Jarvis and Seabury Halls.  It contains upperclassman housing. The National Fraternity of Alpha Chi Rho was founded in a room within Northam Towers.
* '''Raether Library and Information Technology Center''' – Trinity's main library was originally built at the southeast corner of the main quad in the 1950s to replace the library in Williams Memorial. Additional wings were constructed in the 1970s, and a major renovation and restoration took place in 2002, at which time the building was given its present name. The Watkinson Library, which houses rare books and manuscripts, occupies an annex of the first floor. The latest renovations, which enlarged the facility to {{convert|172000|sqft|m2|-2}} and more than 1 million volumes, include an atrium, grand reading room, three new computing centers, a multimedia development studio, a music and media center, private study rooms, and a cafe. Though a private academic library, more than 2,800 outside visitors were recorded between November, 2006 and March, 2007.
* '''Seabury Hall''' – This section of the Long Walk contains classrooms, professor's offices, and four dance studios. Its recent $32.7 million renovation project was completed in 2008.  In addition, the old Seabury chapel was renovated into a classroom, maintaining the pews for student seating.
* '''Trinity Commons''' * – Located on the south end of campus on New Britain and Summit St., Trinity Commons is the new arts mecca on campus. It is contains 4 studio classrooms and the newly constructed Performance Lab. The Performance Lab is a massive black box theater that can sit at least 100 people, but can accommodate much more with standing room. It has a set lighting plot with about 100 lights and is the new performance venue for most new student and faculty shows. It also houses many offices on the other side of the building. It is one of the newest buildings on campus and only houses Theater and Dance classes and administrative offices.
* '''Vernon Social Center''' – Vernon Social Center, located on Vernon Street, is a multipurpose auditorium used on campus for various events, including concerts and lectures. It is attached to Vernon Place, a dormitory, and makes up the quad housing North Campus Hall and High Rise Hall.

=== Sustainability Initiatives ===

Trinity is a signatory of the American College and University Presidents Climate Commitment. Students are involved with programs such as Green Campus, ConnPIRG, and The TREEhouse (Trinity Recreational and Environmental Education House). Students also have access to Zipcars, UPass bus passes.

== Academics ==
Trinity offers three types of degrees: B.A.'s, B.S.'s, as well as M.A.'s in a few subjects. Trinity offers 38 majors. Students also have the option of creating a self-designed major or adding an interdisciplinary or departmental minor. Trinity is one of the only liberal arts schools to offer a degree in engineering. Trinity has a student to faculty ratio of 10:1.

=== Admission ===

Admission to Trinity has been increasingly competitive in recent years; this may be attributed to a large increase in admission applications as of late. For the class of 2015, the acceptance rate was 26.70%.  In January 2011, Trinity's Dean of Admissions reported a  45% application increase, one of the highest ever. A ''[[The New York Times|New York Times]]'' article in January 2011 noted a 47.38% increase, the highest increase of the nation's most selective colleges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://thechoice.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/01/31/total-apps-2011/?scp=2&amp;sq=application%20increase&amp;st=cse | work=The New York Times | first1=Jacques | last1=Steinberg | first2=Eric | last2=Platt | title=Applications Rise (Yet Again) at Dozens of Selective Colleges | date=January 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.trincoll.edu/AboutTrinity/leadership/jones/letters/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/06/30/the-trendiest-colleges_n_887602.html#s299970&amp;title=Trinity_College_Trendiest&lt;/ref&gt;  Trinity's President [[James F. Jones]] commented saying, &quot;The 48.4 percent increase in completed apps is unprecedented: at Trinity or anywhere else for that matter as far as we know. Trinity has become a very hot school because of the vast opportunities we offer, all of which are being better publicized through our new admissions materials, the new website, and our ever-evolving use of social media.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.4legs.org/2011/03/number-of-trinity-applicants-skyrockets&lt;/ref&gt;  ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' ranked Trinity as one of the top 50 best &quot;feeder schools&quot; for top graduate school programs.&lt;ref&gt;http://wsjclassroom.com/pdfs/wsj_college_092503.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  Data compiled by the [[National Science Foundation]] lists Trinity as a liberal arts college that graduates disproportionately high numbers of future scientists.

''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' ranked Trinity #36 among liberal arts colleges in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/hartford-ct/trinity-college-1414 |title=Trinity College – Best College – Education – US News |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=August 17, 2010 |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In August 2007, however, the college joined the &quot;[[Annapolis Group]]&quot;, an organization of more than 100 of the nation's liberal arts schools, in refusing to participate in the magazine's rankings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trincoll.edu/AboutTrinity/News_Events/trinity_news/070816_usnews.htm |title=Trinity College |publisher=Trincoll.edu |date=August 16, 2007 |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, ''The Princeton Review'' gave Trinity a 95 (out of 100) for selectivity. In 2011 &quot;The Princeton Review&quot; named Trinity as a best value college for 2011.Also in 2011, Forbes Magazine listed Trinity College among the top 100 colleges in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/pictures/eidm45jjk/trinity-college | work=Forbes | first=Michael | last=Noer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2011 ''[[Huffington Post]]'' article named Trinity one of the top 10 Trendiest Schools in America, along with other exclusive schools such as Yale and Columbia. The article noted Trinity's &quot;drastic application increases and soaring student reviews&quot; and &quot;close-knit student body.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/06/30/the-trendiest-colleges_n_887602.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== Student life ==
=== Fraternities and sororities ===

Officially, approximately 18% of the student body are affiliated with a Greek organization.  During the late 1980s and 1990s, under pressure from the college administration, many of the single-sex fraternities and sororities merged and formed co-educational Greek organizations. Among those currently on campus are:
[[File:PictureHartfordCTTrinityCollegePanorama1909.jpg|thumb|600px|Trinity College in 1909, showing the Long Walk and three attached buildings: Northam (center), Jarvis (right), Seabury(left)]]
* [[Alpha Chi Rho]] (Crow) founded at Trinity College in 1895.
* [[Alpha Delta Phi]]
* [[Cleo of Alpha Chi|Cleo Literary Society]]
* [[Ivy Society]]
* [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]]
* [[Psi Upsilon]]
* [[St. Anthony Hall]]
* [[Zeta Omega Eta]]: founded at Trinity College in 2003.

Several other Greek organizations, while active, are not officially affiliated with the school.  They include:
* [[Kappa Sigma]] Colony established in 2011.
* [[Pi Kappa Alpha]] (Pike).  The Epsilon Alpha chapter was established in 1953, and has been unaffiliated with the school since 1993.
* [[Theta Delta Sigma]] A national co-ed, multicultural Greek society was colonized in 2005.
* [[Cha Ki Ryan]] the Alpha chapter was founded at Trinity College in 2005.
*National Pan-Hellenic Council (Historically Black)
** [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] sorority
** [[Alpha Phi Alpha]] fraternity
** [[Delta Sigma Theta]] sorority
** [[Phi Beta Sigma]] fraternity

=== Coffee Houses ===

* '''The Underground Coffee House''': Located below Mather dining hall, The Underground is a spot for students to relax, study, and participate in cultural events. It is the only completely student-run business on campus.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

* '''Peter B's Cafe''': Located on the first floor of the library.

=== A cappella groups ===

Trinity's [[a cappella]] groups are:
* The Accidentals: The Accidentals were founded in 1993 as an all-male a capella singing group. Their repertoire includes classic rock, R&amp;B, barbershop, jazz and pop.
* The Dischords: The Dischords are Trinity’s newest co-ed a cappella group, organized in 2005. They sing a wide variety of music ranging from old classics to the soulful one-hit wonders of the 80’s to contemporary hits of today and tomorrow.
* The Trinitones: The Trinitones are Trinity's first all-female vocal group. The Trinitones sing a cappella music in close harmony, in styles ranging from jazzy 1920's music to current popular songs.
* The Trinity Pipes: The Trinity Pipes are Trinity's oldest a cappella group. They are a small, coed singing group, which was founded in 1938 by four men from St. Anthony Hall and sings a wide variety of music from 1940s close harmony to modern pop and rock arrangements.
* [http://www.TrinityCollegeQuirks.com The Quirks]: The Quirks are Trinity’s newest all-female a capella group.  Founded by two students in 2003 as their Tutorial College project, the Quirks' repertoire includes close harmony arrangements of a wide range of musical genres, including jazz, rock, R&amp;B, and pop.

=== Athletics ===
{{see also|Trinity College Bantams}}
[[File:Trinity Bantams.gif|thumb|The Bantams logo.]]The Trinity College Department of Athletics currently sponsors Men's Intercollegiate Baseball, Basketball, Cross Country, Soccer, Swimming, [[Trinity Bantams football|Football]], Lacrosse,  Golf, Tennis, Track &amp; Field, Wrestling, Rowing, Squash and Ice Hockey along with Women's Intercollegiate Softball, Basketball, Cross Country, Soccer, Swimming, Volleyball, Field Hockey, Ice Hockey, Squash, Tennis, Track &amp; Field and Rowing. They compete in the NCAA Division III in most sports.

The Trinity Bantams squash team holds the record for the longest winning streak in any inter-collegiate sport in the nation, at 244 consecutive victories.  The Bantams have won 13 consecutive national titles since 1998, when they first took home the Potter Trophy.  They have also garnered attention and praise from major media outlets such as ESPN, Sports Illustrated, and USA Today, among others.  

The Trinity Baseball team won the Division III national title in 2008, after having started the season 44–0, shattering numerous records in the process. After having been handed their first loss of the year by Johns Hopkins (to fall to 44–1), the Bantams clinched the national title by beating Johns Hopkins in the bottom of the ninth of the championship game.  They finished the season with a 45–1 record.  

The Trinity Football team has gone undefeated in several recent seasons (2003–2005, 2008) and has won the [[NESCAC]] championship in five of the past seven seasons (2002–2005, 2008).  

Both the men's and women's rowing teams are consistently ranked within the top five teams in NCAA Division III competition. In 2008, the women's Varsity 8+ won the Division III [[NCAA Rowing Championship]] title and placed second as a team and later went on to win the Jeffries Cup at [[Henley Women's Regatta]].

=== Student publications ===

* ''[[The Trinity Tripod]]''
* ''[[4legs.org]]''
* ''Slate Literary Magazine''

=== Student clubs and organizations===
Student clubs are a huge part of the Trinity experience. There are more than 100 student-run organizations representing the full spectrum of student life at the College. Clubs are categorized by: community service organizations, cultural organizations, special interest groups, club sports and recreation, media organizations, musical organizations, and student government. A few of the student clubs offered at Trinity are:
 {{Div col }}
* Amnesty International: Trinity College Chapter
* Anime Club
* Asian American Student Association
* Bantam Brew Club
* BBQ Club
* Caribbean Students Association
* Chapel Singers
* Club Tennis Team
* Green Campus
* Habitat for Humanity
* Hillel
* Investment Club
* M.D. Fox Mentoring Program
* Mock Trial Team
* Society of Physics Students
* Trap and Skeet Shooting Club
* Trinity College Black Women's Organization
* Trinity College Democrats
* Trinity College Emergency Response Team
* Trintity College Gospel Choir
* Trinity College Republicans
* UMOJA- black student organization
 {{Div col end}}

=== Residence halls ===

Trinity College houses its students in 27 dorms organized into four &quot;areas&quot;, each with a local area coordinator, who is responsible for administering the area.
 {{Div col }}
* Area 1 (&quot;Crescent Street&quot;):
** Stowe
** Clemens
** Anadama
** Wiggins
** Little - First Year
** Frohman-Robb - First Year

* Area 2 (&quot;South Campus&quot;):
** Summit North
** Summit South
** Summit East (The Fred)
** Jackson- First Year
** Smith
** Wheaton
** Funston

* Area 3 (&quot;The Long Walk&quot;):
** Jarvis
** Northam Towers
** Cook
** Goodwin-Woodward
** Jones- First Year
** Elton- First Year
(Note that Jones and Elton are not part of the same structure as the Long Walk proper, but are in the same general vicinity.)

* Area 4 (&quot;Vernon Street&quot;):
** Boardwalk
** Park Place
** Vernon
** High Rise
** North Campus- First Year
** Hansen
** Doonesbury
** Ogilby
 {{Div col end}}

==Study Away==

Study away is an integral part of the Trinity experience and is also a critical component of Trinity’s urban/global focus. Approximately 70 percent of Trinity undergraduates study abroad or in another U.S. city before graduating. In addition to the Trinity College, Rome Campus, Trinity has programs in Paris, Barcelona, Vienna, Trinidad and Tobago, Cape Town, and Buenos Aires that are partially staffed by Trinity professors. In addition there are many other study abroad programs which Trinity students are approved to take part in. In 2012 Trinity will establish a program in Shanghai through a partnership with [[Fudan University]].

=== Trinity College, Rome Campus ===

Trinity College, Rome Campus (TCRC) is a study abroad campus of Trinity College. It was established in 1970 and is located in a residential area of Rome on the [[Aventine Hill]] close to the [[Basilica of Santa Sabina]] within the precincts of a convent run by an order of nuns. 

The program usually consists of 50–70 students from different American colleges and universities.  Students can either attend TCRC for a semester or for their summer program.  Each semester, there are usually a range of courses from economics to art history.  Most courses make use of the city of Rome by conducting numerous walking tours and trips.  Every student enrolled in the program is required to take the appropriate level of study of [[Italian language]].  The program also regularly makes trips to other parts of Italy, such as [[Florence]], [[Venice]], and [[Capri]].

== Notable people ==

[[File:Trinity College, Connecticut, in 1905 Postcard.jpg|thumb|right|250px|1905 postcard to a Miss Irene Jackson (Message: &quot;Here's where you find interesting specimens to analize [sic]. Very promising.&quot;)]]

{{main|List of Trinity College (Connecticut) people}}
* [[Edward Albee]], playwright
* [[Charles McLean Andrews]], [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning historian and professor
* [[James Roosevelt Bayley]], [[Archdiocese of Baltimore|Archbishop of Baltimore]]
* [[Jonah Bayliss]], [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher
* [[Tucker Carlson]], journalist, editor and founder of ''The Daily Caller'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dailycaller.com/ |title=Breaking News, Opinion, Research, and Entertainment |publisher=The Daily Caller |date=January 20, 2011 |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; former host of ''[[Tucker (television program)|Tucker]]''
* [[Thomas M. Chappell]], co-founder and CEO of [[Tom's of Maine]]
* [[Moe Drabowsky]], Major League Baseball pitcher
* [[Edward Miner Gallaudet]], founder of [[Gallaudet University]]
* [[Stephen Gyllenhaal]], film producer and director
* [[Dean Hamer]], discoverer of the controversial &quot;[[gay gene]]&quot; and &quot;[[God gene]]&quot;
* [[Alfred Harding (bishop)|Alfred Harding]], [[Episcopal Diocese of Washington|Episcopal]] [[Bishop]] of [[Washington, D.C.|Washington]].
* [[Barbara B. Kennelly]], [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. Representative]]
* [[Mickey Kobrosky]], College Football Hall of Fame Member (2001), Former NFL, MLB athlete
* [[Ernest de Koven Leffingwell]] geologist and Arctic explorer
* [[Mary McCormack]], American actress
* [[Thomas Joseph Meskill]], [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. Representative]] and [[Governor of Connecticut]]
* [[Roy Nutt]], Co-Founder [[Computer Sciences Corporation]], co-creator of [[FORTRAN]].
* [[Jane M. Swift]], Class of 1987, [[Governor of Massachusetts]] (2001–2003)
* [[J. H. Hobart Ward]], [[American Civil War]] general
* [[George Will]], [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning newspaper columnist, author, and [[ABC News]] political journalist
* [[George A. Woodward]], [[U.S. Army]] general

===Faculty===
* [[Michael C. FitzGerald]], Picasso scholar and art historian .
* [[William Woodruff Niles]], A.B. 1857, professor of Latin, 1864–70, Episcopal Bishop of New Hampshire, 1870–1914.

== Trinity College and Hartford ==

Trinity is located in urban Hartford, within walking distance of the state capital of Connecticut. The main campus is bordered by Summit Street, Allen Place, Broad Street and New Britain Avenue.

=== Trinity and the community ===

Along with Trinity, the Learning Corridor, [[Hartford Hospital]], and [[The Institute of Living]] make up the Southside Institutions Neighborhood Alliance, or SINA.  SINA aims to create affordable housing in Hartford's Frog Hollow and Barry Square neighborhoods as well as in the creation of the Learning Corridor and the Trinity College [[Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of America|Boys and Girls Club]].

Trinity's library, computer resources and the new Community Sports Complex are available to Hartford residents. The new sports complex functions both as a rink for Trinity’s [[ice hockey]] teams and as a public skating rink. Trinity also runs the Trinfo Café which provides Hartford residents with internet and computer access as well as  computing services/education. 

Trinity has recently entered into a partnership with the [[Hartford Magnet Middle School]] located across the street. Trinity will now advise the school with academic affairs, provide professors to lead summer courses and will open up some Trinity courses to qualified seniors at Hartford Magnet Middle School which is in the process of adding grades 9–12.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.trincoll.edu/NewsEvents/NewsArticles/pages/Trinity-College-and-Hartford-Public-Schools-Join-Forces-.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer months, when not in session, the college opens its campus to the community for its Plumb Memorial Carillon Concerts that are held on Wednesday nights. Trinity's 49-bell Carillon is one of approximately 200 such instruments in North America.

=== Contributions to the arts ===

[[File:Eyeball film festival poster.jpg|thumb|right|200px|A student run film festival.]]

[[Cinestudio]] is an art cinema with 1930s-style design. An article in the ''Hartford Advocate'' described this non-profit organization, which depends solely on grants and the efforts of volunteer workers who are paid in free movies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cinestudio.org/about |title=About |publisher=Cinestudio |date=September 25, 2008 |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cinestudio has been located in the Clement Chemistry Building since it was founded in the 1970s.

Cinestudio is host to the annual Eyeball Film Festival, in which young film makers premier their latest works in front of their peers. The festival has judges, each schooled in film from a different perspective, who judge the students' films.

Trinity also hosts the annual [[Trinity International Hip Hop Festival]].  A three-day celebration of global hip hop culture, the festival features lectures, panel discussions, workshops and live performances.  The festival was founded in 2006 with the goal of unifying Trinity with the city of Hartford.

Trinity has a strong faculty in fine arts, including Picasso scholar and art historian [[Michael C. FitzGerald]].

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:TrinCollChapelHartford.jpg|Trinity College Chapel Doorway
Image:TrinCollChapelHartfrd.jpg|Trinity College Chapel
Image:TrinCollHartfordChap.jpg|Trinity College Chapel
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Trinity College presidents ==

{{Div col}} 
* [[James F. Jones|James Fleming Jones, Jr.]], 2004–present
* [[Evan Dobelle]] H'01 1995–2001
* [[Tom Gerety]] 1989–1994
* [[John Barrett Kerfoot]] H'65 1864–1866
* [[John Williams (bishop of Connecticut)|John Williams]] '35 1848–1853
* [[Thomas Church Brownell]] 1824–1831
 {{Div col end}}

== Trinity in modern culture==
* In the opening sequence of the 1975 film ''[[Jaws (film)|Jaws]]'', the male character Cassidy mentions that he attends Trinity.  When Police Chief Brody asks, &quot;Do you live here?&quot;, Cassidy replies, &quot;Na, Hartford, I go to Trinity. My folks live in Greenwich.&quot;

* Trinity is mentioned several times in Lisa Birnbach's 2010 book ''True Prep,'' as well as in her 1980 bestseller ''[[The Official Preppy Handbook]]'', where Trinity is listed among the preppiest colleges. In 2010, Birnbach described Trinity as &quot;a hot school that everyone wants to go to&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.trinitytripod.com/opinions/trinity-s-preppy-culture-defined-1.2175839#.TrCtdWD2Lw4&lt;/ref&gt;

* It is believed that [[Edward Albee]] in his play ''[[Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?]]'' based the college in the play on Trinity College. Trinity was also the set for the film version of the play.

* Rt. Rev. Lyman C. Ogilby, whose father was Trinity president Remsen Brinckerhoff Ogilby, named [[Trinity University of Asia]] after Trinity College.

* In a 1963 article written by Gene Hawes titled, &quot;The Colleges of America's Upper Class,&quot; which measured the social standing of alumni, Trinity was cited among the exclusively Ivy League group. Trinity ranked fifth behind Harvard, Princeton, Yale, and Pennsylvania; was ahead of Dartmouth, Brown, Columbia and Cornell.

*In a 2011 Bollywood film, ''Desi Boyz'', the main character attends a fictitious Trinity College in the UK. However, Trinity's seal and school colors are used.

== Notes and references ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.trincoll.edu/ Official website]

{{Trinity College}}
{{Colleges and universities in Connecticut}}
{{NESCAC}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{Oberlin Group}}
{{CLAC}}

{{coord|41.74740|N|72.69001|W|source:placeopedia|display=title}}

[[Category:A cappella musical groups]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:Education in Hartford, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1823]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:New England Small College Athletic Conference]]
[[Category:Posse schools]]
[[Category:Trinity College, Hartford|*]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Connecticut]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Hartford County, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Hartford, Connecticut]]

[[ja:トリニティ・カレッジ (コネチカット州)]]
[[pnb:ٹرنیٹی کالج، ہارٹفورڈ]]
[[sv:Trinity College (Connecticut)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
