<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="50372" ns="0" title="Paul Revere"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the 18th-century American activist and artisan}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox person
| name        = Paul Revere
| image       = J S Copley - Paul Revere.jpg
| caption     = Portrait of Paul Revere by [[John Singleton Copley]], c. 1768–70
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1735|1|1}}&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Old Style and New Style dates|O.S.]]: December 21, 1734)&lt;/small&gt;
| birth_place = [[Boston]] ([[North End, Boston|North End]])
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1818|5|10|1735|1|1}}
| death_place = [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]]
| occupation  = [[silversmith]], [[Minutemen|colonial militia officer]]
| networth =
| spouse      = Sarah Orne (1757–73) (her death)&lt;br /&gt;Rachel Walker (1773–1813) (her death)
| children    = 8 with Sarah Orne (6 survived)&lt;br /&gt;8 with Rachel Walker (5 survived)
| residence   =
| alma_mater  =
| website     =
| signature   =
}}

'''Paul Revere''' ({{OldStyleDate|January 1, 1735||December 21, 1734}}{{ndash}} May 10, 1818){{#tag:ref|Revere's date of birth is confused by the conversion between the [[Julian calendar|Julian]] and [[Gregorian calendar]]s, which offsets the date by 11 days.  While the birth was recorded on December 21, adjusting for the conversion between Julian and Gregorian calendars changes the date to January 1.|group=N}} was an American [[silversmith]] and a [[Patriot (American Revolution)|patriot]] in the [[American Revolution]]. He is most famous for alerting Colonial militia of approaching [[UK Army|British forces]] before the [[battles of Lexington and Concord]], as dramatized in [[Henry Wadsworth Longfellow]]'s poem, [[Paul Revere's Ride]]. As a result, his &quot;midnight ride&quot; is a legendary part of [[United States]] history.

Revere was a prosperous and prominent [[Boston]] silversmith, who helped organize an [[intelligence in the American Revolutionary War|intelligence and alarm]] system to keep watch on the [[Kingdom of Great Britain|British]] military.
Revere later served as an officer in the [[Penobscot Expedition]], one of the most disastrous campaigns of the [[American Revolutionary War]], for which he was absolved of blame.

==Early years==
Paul Revere was born in the [[North End, Boston|North End]] of [[Boston]] on December 21, 1734, according to the [[Old Style]] calendar then in use, or January 1, 1735, in the modern calendar.{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=7}} His father, a French [[Huguenot]] born Apollos Rivoire, came to Boston at the age of 13 and was apprenticed to the silversmith [[John Coney (silversmith)|John Coney]].{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=7-9}} By the time he married Deborah Hitchborn, a member of a long-standing Boston family that owned a small shipping wharf, in 1729, Rivoire had anglicized his name to Paul Revere. Their son, Paul Revere, was the third of 12 children and eventually the eldest surviving son.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=297}} Revere grew up in the environment of the extended Hitchborn family, and never learned his father's native language.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=9}}  At 13 he left school and became an apprentice to his father. The silversmith trade afforded him connections with a cross-section of Boston society, which would serve him well when he became active in the [[American Revolution]].{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=14–16}}  As for religion, although his father attended [[Puritan]] services, Revere was drawn to the [[Church of England]].{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=21}} Revere eventually began attending the services of the political and provocative [[Jonathan Mayhew]] at the [[Old West Church, Boston, Massachusetts|West Church]].{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=21}}  His father did not approve, and as a result father and son came to blows on one occasion.  Revere relented and returned to his father's church, although he did become friends with Mayhew.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=25}}

[[File:PaulReveredentaltools.jpg|left|thumb|upright|Revere's dentistry tools]]
His father died in 1754, and Paul was legally too young to officially be the master of the family silver shop.{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=21}} In February 1756, during the [[French and Indian War]] (the North American theater of the [[Seven Years' War]]), he enlisted in the provincial army. Possibly he made this decision because of the weak economy, since army service promised consistent pay.{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=21–22}} Commissioned a second lieutenant in a provincial artillery regiment, he spent the summer at [[Fort William Henry]] at the southern end of [[Lake George (New York)|Lake George]] in New York as part of an abortive plan for the capture of [[Fort St. Frédéric]]. He did not stay long in the army, but returned to Boston and assumed control of the silver shop in his own name. On August 4, 1757, he married Sarah Orne (1736–1773); their first child was born eight months later.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=33}} He and Sarah had eight children, but three died young, and only one survived, Paul.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=}} Revere would later remarry.

==Business and political connections==
Over the next few years Revere provided for not only his growing family, but his mother and unmarried older sister.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=33–34}} One of the skills that distinguished him from other silversmiths was that he was also a skilled engraver, so he could decorate his own pieces.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} Revere's silver work quickly gained attention in Boston. Surviving documents show that among more than 5,000 products crafted by his shop during his lifetime there were many small and affordable items such as buckles, buttons, rings and beads.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=242}}

In 1760 Revere became one of the founding members of the [[Freemasonry|Masonic Lodge]] of Boston. Possibly introduced to freemasonry by [[Richard Gridley]], his commanding officer during the 1756 expedition, he may have been further exposed to it during evenings in which he frequented Boston's [[public house]]s.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=41}} The lodge provided an environment where social classes mixed, which was beneficial to Revere's business.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=44}} The lodge would later be seen by some royal governors of Massachusetts as a principal source of resistance to British authority.{{sfn|Forbes|1999|p=61}}

==1765–1774: the gathering storm of revolution==
{{main|Sons of Liberty}}
Revere's business began to suffer when the British economy entered a recession in the years following the Seven Years' War, and declined further when the [[Stamp Act 1765|Stamp Act of 1765]] resulted in a further downturn in the Massachusetts economy.{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=38–43}} Business was so poor that an attempt was made to attach his property in late 1765.{{sfn|Fischer|1998|p=20}} To help make ends meet he even took up [[dentistry]], a skill set he was taught by a practicing surgeon who lodged at a friend's house.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=104}}

Although Revere was not one of the &quot;Loyal Nine&quot;—organizers of the earliest protests against the Stamp Act—he was well connected with its members, who were laborers and artisans.{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=43}} Revere did not participate in some of the more raucous protests, such as the attack on the home of Lieutenant Governor [[Thomas Hutchinson (governor)|Thomas Hutchinson]].{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=46–47}} In 1765, a group of militants who would become known as the &quot;[[Sons of Liberty]]&quot; formed. Revere was one of them.{{sfn|Goss|1891|pp=112–115}}{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=36, 42}} From 1765 on, in support of the dissident cause, he produced engravings with political themes and other artifacts. Among these engravings are a depiction of the arrival of British troops in 1768 (which he termed &quot;an insolent parade&quot;) and a famous depiction of the March 1770 [[Boston Massacre]] (see illustration). Although the latter was engraved by Revere and he included the inscription, &quot;Engraved, Printed, &amp; Sold by Paul Revere Boston&quot;, it was modeled on a drawing by [[Henry Pelham (engraver)|Henry Pelham]], and Revere's engraving of the drawing was colored by a third man and printed by a fourth.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=22}} Revere also produced a bowl commemorating the Massachusetts assembly's refusal to retract the [[Massachusetts Circular Letter]]. (This letter, adopted in response to the 1767 [[Townshend Acts]], called for united colonial action against the acts.  [[George III of Great Britain|King George III]] had issued a demand for its retraction.){{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=22}}

[[File:Boston Massacre high-res.jpg|right|thumb|&quot;''The Bloody Massacre Perpetrated in King Street Boston on March 5th, 1770''&quot;. Copper engraving by Paul Revere modeled on a drawing by Henry Pelham,{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=24 and note 53}} 1770.]]

In 1770 Revere purchased a house on [[North Square (Boston, Massachusetts)|North Square]] in Boston's North End.  Now [[Paul Revere House|a museum]], the house provided space for his growing family while he continued to maintain his shop at nearby Clark's Wharf.{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=71–72}}  Sarah died in 1773, and on October 10 of that year Revere married Rachel Walker (1745–1813). They had eight children, three of whom died young.{{sfn|Forbes|1999|pp=485–487}}

In November 1773 the merchant ship, ''Dartmouth'' arrived in Boston harbor carrying the first shipment of tea that would be subject to the taxes of the [[Tea Act]].  Revere and Warren, as members of the informal &quot;North End Caucus&quot;, organized a watch over the ''Dartmouth'' to prevent the unloading of the tea. Revere took his turns on guard duty,{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=163}} and was one of the ringleaders in the [[Boston Tea Party]] of December 16, when colonists disguised as Indians dumped tea from the ''Dartmouth'' and two other ships into the harbor.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=165}}

From December 1773 to November 1775, Revere served as a courier for the Boston [[Committee of Safety (American Revolution)|Committee of Public Safety]], traveling to New York and Philadelphia to report on the political unrest in Boston. Research has documented 18 such rides. Notice of some of them was published in Massachusetts newspapers, and British authorities received further intelligence of them from Loyalist Americans.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|pp=27; 54; Appendix C}} In 1774, his cousin John on the island of [[Guernsey]] wrote to Paul that John had seen reports of Paul's role as an &quot;express&quot; (courier) in London newspapers.{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=101}}

In 1774, the military governor of Massachusetts, General [[Thomas Gage]], [[Massachusetts Government Act|dissolved the provincial assembly]] on orders from Britain. Governor Gage also [[Boston Port Act|closed the port]] of Boston and all over the city forced private citizens to quarter (provide lodging for) soldiers in their homes.{{#tag:ref|Forcing private citizens to quarter soldiers in their homes would be one of the grievances enumerated in the [[United States Declaration of Independence]]—[The King] &quot;has combined with others to subject us to a Jurisdiction foreign to our Constitution, and unacknowledged by our Laws; giving his Assent to their Acts of pretended Legislation: For quartering large Bodies of Armed Troops among us:...&quot;—and the framers of the [[United States Constitution]] restricted the practice in Article III of the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]].|group=N}}

During this time, Revere and a group of 30 &quot;mechanics&quot; began meeting in secret at his favorite haunt, the ''Green Dragon'', to coordinate the gathering and dissemination of intelligence by &quot;watching the Movements of British Soldiers&quot;, as he would write in an account of his April 18, 1775 ride. Around this time Revere contributed engravings to the patriot monthly, ''[[Royal American Magazine]]''.{{sfn|Goss|1891|p=}}{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=181}}

He rode to [[Portsmouth, New Hampshire]] in December 1774 upon rumors of an impending landing of British troops there, a journey known in history as the [[Powder Alarm#Portsmouth Alarm|Portsmouth Alarm]]. Although the rumors were false, his ride sparked a rebel success by provoking locals to [[Fort William and Mary#1774 raid|raid Fort William and Mary]], defended by just six soldiers, for its gunpowder supply.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|pp=52–57}}

==&quot;Midnight Ride&quot;==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Lexington, Massachusetts]] --&gt;
{{main|Battles of Lexington and Concord}}
When British Army activity on April 7, 1775, suggested the possibility of troop movements, [[Joseph Warren]] sent Revere to warn the [[Massachusetts Provincial Congress]], then sitting in [[Concord, Massachusetts|Concord]], the site of one of the larger caches of Patriot military supplies. After delivering the warning, Concord residents began moving the military supplies away from the town.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=186}}

One week later, General Gage received instructions from [[Secretary of State (United Kingdom)|Secretary of State]] [[William Legge, 2nd Earl of Dartmouth|William Legge, Earl of Dartmouth]], to disarm the rebels, who were known to have hidden weapons in Concord, among other locations, and to imprison the rebellion's leaders, especially [[Samuel Adams]] and [[John Hancock]]. Dartmouth gave Gage considerable discretion in his commands.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|pp=75–76}}{{sfn|Brooks|1999|pp=37–38}} Gage issued orders to Lieutenant Colonel [[Francis Smith (British officer)|Francis Smith]] to proceed from Boston &quot;with utmost expedition and [[Military secret|secrecy]] to Concord, where you will seize and destroy... all Military stores.... But you will take care that the soldiers do not plunder the inhabitants or hurt private property.&quot; Gage did not issue written orders for the arrest of rebel leaders, as he feared doing so might spark an uprising.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=85}}

Between 9 and 10 p.m. on the night of April 18, 1775, Joseph Warren told Revere and [[William Dawes]] that the king's troops were about to embark in boats from Boston bound for Cambridge and the road to Lexington and Concord. Warren's intelligence suggested that the most likely objectives of the regulars' movements later that night would be the capture of Adams and Hancock. They did not worry about the possibility of regulars marching to Concord, since the supplies at Concord were safe, but they did think their leaders in Lexington were unaware of the potential danger that night. Revere and Dawes were sent out to warn them and to alert colonial militias in nearby towns.{{sfn|Brooks|1999|pp=41–42}}{{sfn|Boatner|1975|p=622}}

In the days before April 18, Revere had instructed [[Robert Newman (sexton)|Robert Newman]], the [[sexton]] of the [[Old North Church|North Church]], to send a signal by lantern to alert colonists in [[Charlestown, Massachusetts|Charlestown]] as to the movements of the troops when the information became known. In what is well known today by the phrase &quot;one if by land, two if by sea&quot;, one lantern in the steeple would signal the army's choice of the land route while two lanterns would signal the route &quot;by water&quot; across the [[Charles River]].{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=99}} Revere first gave instructions to send the signal to Charlestown. He then crossed the Charles River by rowboat, slipping past the British warship [[HMS Somerset (1748)|HMS ''Somerset'']] at anchor. Crossings were banned at that hour, but Revere safely landed in Charlestown and rode to Lexington, avoiding a British patrol and later warning almost every house along the route. The Charlestown colonists dispatched additional riders to the north.{{sfn|Boatner|1975|p=622}}{{sfn|Brooks|1999|pp=42–44}}

Riding through present-day [[Somerville, Massachusetts|Somerville]], [[Medford, Massachusetts|Medford]], and [[Arlington, Massachusetts|Arlington]], Revere warned patriots along his route, many of whom set out on horseback to deliver warnings of their own. By the end of the night there were probably as many as 40 riders throughout [[Middlesex County, Massachusetts|Middlesex County]] carrying the news of the army's advance. Revere did not shout the phrase later attributed to him (&quot;The British are coming!&quot;): His mission depended on secrecy, the countryside was filled with British army patrols, and most of the Massachusetts colonists (who were predominantly [[English people|English]] in ethnic origin&lt;ref name=&quot;1790census&quot;&gt;According to the 1790 census, Massachusetts was 89% English, Scots, and Northern Irish.&lt;/ref&gt;) still considered themselves British.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=110}} {{sfn|McDonald|McDonald|1980|p=180}} Revere's warning, according to eyewitness accounts of the ride and Revere's own descriptions, was &quot;The [[Regular Army|Regulars]] are coming out.&quot;{{sfn|Revere|1961}} Revere arrived in Lexington around midnight, with Dawes arriving about a half hour later. They met with Samuel Adams and John Hancock, who were spending the night with Hancock's relatives (in what is now called the [[Hancock-Clarke House]]), and they spent a great deal of time discussing plans of action upon receiving the news. They believed that the forces leaving the city were too large for the sole task of arresting two men and that Concord was the main target.{{sfn|Brooks|1999|p=50}} The Lexington men dispatched riders to the surrounding towns, and Revere and Dawes continued along the road to Concord accompanied by [[Samuel Prescott]], a doctor who happened to be in Lexington &quot;returning from a lady friend's house at the awkward hour of 1 a.m.&quot;{{sfn|Boatner|1975|p=622}}{{sfn|Murrin|2002|p=205}}

Revere, Dawes, and Prescott were detained by a British Army patrol in [[Lincoln, Massachusetts|Lincoln]] at a roadblock on the way to Concord.{{sfn|Boatner|1975|p=622}} Prescott jumped his horse over a wall and escaped into the woods; he eventually reached Concord. Dawes also escaped, though he fell off his horse not long after and did not complete the ride.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|pp=131–132, 144}}

[[File:Paul Revere Statue by Cyrus E. Dallin, North End, Boston, MA.JPG|thumb|right|This Paul Revere Statue in [[North End, Boston]] was made by [[Cyrus Dallin]] and unveiled on September 22, 1940.]]
Revere was captured and questioned by the British soldiers at gunpoint. He told them of the army's movement from Boston, and that British army troops would be in some danger if they approached Lexington, because of the large number of hostile militia gathered there. He and other captives taken by the patrol were still escorted east toward Lexington, until about a half mile from Lexington they heard a gunshot. The British major demanded Revere explain the gunfire, and Revere replied it was a signal to &quot;alarm the country&quot;. As the group drew closer to Lexington, the town bell began to clang rapidly, upon which one of the captives proclaimed to the British soldiers &quot;The bell's a'ringing! The town's alarmed, and you're all dead men!&quot;{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=136}} The British soldiers gathered and decided not to press further towards Lexington but instead to free the prisoners and head back to warn their commanders.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|pp=133–136, 142–148}} The British confiscated Revere's horse and rode off to warn the approaching army column. Revere walked to Rev. [[Jonas Clarke]]'s house, where Hancock and Adams were staying. As the battle on [[Lexington Green]] unfolded, Revere assisted John Hancock and his family in their escape from Lexington, helping to carry a trunk of Hancock's papers.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=198–200}}

The ride of the three men triggered a flexible system of &quot;alarm and muster&quot; that had been carefully developed months before, in reaction to the colonists' impotent response to the [[Powder Alarm]] of September 1774. This system was an improved version of an old network of widespread notification and fast deployment of local militia forces in times of emergency. The colonists had periodically used this system all the way back to the early years of [[American Indian Wars|Indian wars]] in the colony, before it fell into disuse in the [[French and Indian War]]. In addition to other express riders delivering messages, bells, drums, alarm guns, bonfires, and a trumpet were used for rapid communication from town to town, notifying the rebels in dozens of eastern Massachusetts villages that they should muster their militias because the regulars in numbers greater than 500 were leaving Boston with possible hostile intentions. This system was so effective that people in towns {{convert|25|mi|km}} from Boston were aware of the army's movements while they were still unloading boats in Cambridge.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|pp=138–145}} Unlike in the Powder Alarm, the alarm raised by the three riders successfully allowed the militia to repel the British troops in Concord, after which the British were harried by the growing colonial militia all the way back to Boston.

==War years==
Because Boston [[Siege of Boston|was besieged]] after the battles at Lexington and Concord, Revere could not return to the city, which was now firmly in British hands.  He boarded in [[Watertown, Massachusetts|Watertown]], where he was eventually joined by Rachel and most of his children (Paul Jr., then 15, remained in Boston to mind the family properties).{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=115}}  After he was denied a commission in the [[Continental Army]], he tried to find other ways to be useful to the rebel cause.  He was retained by the provincial congress as a courier, and to print local currency, which the congress used to pay the troops around Boston.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=201–208}}

[[Image:Massachusetts 12 pence 1776 front.png|thumb|left|A 12 pence bill printed by Revere in 1776]]
Since there was a desperate shortage of gunpowder, the provincial congress decided in November 1775 to send him to [[Philadelphia]] to study the working of the only [[powder mill]] in the colonies, in the hopes that he might be able to build a second one in Massachusetts.  Revere called on the mill's owner, [[Oswald Eve]], armed with a letter from Continental Congressmen [[Robert Morris (financier)|Robert Morris]] and [[John Dickinson (delegate)|John Dickinson]] asking Eve to &quot;Chearfully &amp; from Public Spirited Motives give Mr. Revere such information as will inable him to Conduct the business on his return home.&quot;{{sfn|Martello|2010|p=62}}{{sfn|Gettemy|1905|p=169}}  Eve showed Revere around the mill, but refused to give him detailed drawings unless he was first paid a substantial bribe.  Despite this chilly reception, Revere was able to discern useful information from the visit.  He also acquired, through the work of Samuel Adams, plans for another powder mill.  This information enabled Revere to set up a powder mill at Stoughton (present-day [[Canton, Massachusetts|Canton]]).{{sfn|Martello|2010|p=62}}{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=148}}  The mill produced tons of gunpowder for the Patriot cause.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=214}}

Revere's friend and compatriot Joseph Warren was killed during the [[Battle of Bunker Hill]] on June 17, 1775.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=208}} Because soldiers killed in battle were often buried in mass graves without ceremony, Warren's grave was unmarked. On March 21, 1776, several days after the British army left Boston, Revere, Warren's brothers, and a few friends went to the battlefield and found a grave containing two bodies.{{citation needed|date=June 2011|reason=composition of search party, number of bodies}} After being buried for 10 months, Warren's face was unrecognizable, but Revere was able to identify Warren's body because he had placed a false tooth in Warren's mouth, and recognized the wire he had used for fastening it.  Warren was given a proper funeral and reburied in a marked grave.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=215}}

===Militia service===
Upon returning to Boston in 1776, Revere was commissioned a [[major]] of [[infantry]] in the Massachusetts militia in that April, and transferred to the [[artillery]] a month later.{{sfn|Martello|2010|p=80}}  In November he was promoted to [[lieutenant colonel]], and was stationed at [[Castle William]], defending Boston harbor.  He was generally second or third in the chain of command, and on several occasions he was given command of the fort.{{sfn|Martello|2010|p=80}}  He applied his engineering skills to maintaining the fort's armaments, even designing and building a [[caliper]] to accurately measure cannon balls and cannon bore holes.{{sfn|Martello|2010|p=80}}  The service at Castle William was relatively isolated, and personality friction prompted some men to file complaints against Revere.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=217}}  The boredom was alleviated in late August 1777 when Revere was sent with a troop of soldiers to escort prisoners taken in the [[Battle of Bennington]] to Boston, where they were confined on board prison ships,{{sfn|Gettemy|1906|pp=148–151}}{{sfn|Drake|1899|p=128}} and again in September when he was briefly deployed to [[Rhode Island]].{{sfn|Gettemy|1906|pp=152–153}}

In August 1778 Revere's regiment served in a combined Franco-American expedition whose objective was to capture the British base at [[Newport, Rhode Island]].{{sfn|Forbes|1999|p=343}}  His regiment was responsible for erecting and maintaining artillery batteries on [[Aquidneck Island]].{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=132}}  The attempt was abandoned by the French when their fleet was scattered in a storm, and Revere's regiment returned to Boston before the British sortied from Newport to force the [[Battle of Rhode Island]].

===Penobscot disaster===
{{main|Penobscot Expedition}}
The British in June 1779 established a new base on [[Penobscot Bay]] in present-day [[Maine]] (which was then part of Massachusetts).{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=220}}  Massachusetts authorities called out the militia, pressed into service available shipping, and organized [[Penobscot Expedition|a major expedition]] to dislodge the British.{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=134–135}}  The expedition was a complete fiasco: its land and naval commanders could not agree on strategy or tactics, and the arrival of British reinforcements led to the destruction of the entire Massachusetts fleet.{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=135–136}}  Revere commanded the artillery units for the expedition, and was responsible for organizing the artillery train.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=224–225}}  He participated in the taking of Bank's Island, from which artillery batteries could reach the British ships anchored before [[Fort George (Castine, Maine)|Fort George]].  He next oversaw the transport of the guns from Bank's Island to a new position on the heights of the Bagaduce Peninsula that commanded the fort.  Although Revere was in favor of storming the fort, Brigadier General [[Solomon Lovell]] opted for a siege instead.  After further inconsequential exchanges, and disagreements on how to proceed between Lovell and fleet commander [[Dudley Saltonstall]], Lovell, a decision supported by Revere, decided to return to the transports on August 12.

Late the next day British sails were spotted.  A mad scramble ensued, and on the 14th the fleet was in retreat heading up the [[Penobscot River]].  Revere and his men were put ashore with their stores, and their transports destroyed.  At one point Brigadier General [[Peleg Wadsworth]] ordered Revere to send his barge in an attempt to recover a ship drifting toward the enemy position.  Revere at first resisted, but eventually complied, and Wadsworth told him to expect formal charges over the affair.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=234–236}}  The incident separated Revere from his men.  Moving overland, he eventually managed to regroup most of his troops, and returned to Boston on August 26.  A variety of charges were made against Revere, some of which were exaggerated assignments of blame{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=136–138}} made by enemies he had made in his command at Castle William.  The initial hearings on the matter in September 1779 were inconclusive, but he was asked to resign his post.{{sfn|Triber|1998|pp=136–138}}  He repeatedly sought a full [[court martial]] to clear his name, but it was not until February 1782 that a court martial heard the issue, exonerating him.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=238–239}}{{sfn|Triber|1998|p=139}}

==Later years==
[[File:PaulRevereByGilbertStuart.jpeg|thumb|left|upright|1813 portrait of Revere by [[Gilbert Stuart]]]]
After the war, finding the silver trade difficult in the ensuing depression, Revere opened a hardware and home goods store, and later became interested in metal work beyond gold and silver. By 1788 he had opened an iron and brass foundry in Boston's North End.  As a foundryman he recognized a burgeoning market for church bells in the religious revival known as the [[Second Great Awakening]] that followed the war. He became one of the best-known metal casters of that instrument, working with sons Paul Jr. and [[Joseph Warren Revere]] in the firm Paul Revere &amp; Sons. This firm cast the first bell made in Boston and ultimately produced more than 900 bells. A substantial part of the foundry's business came from supplying shipyards with iron bolts and fittings for ship construction. In 1801, Revere became a pioneer in the production of [[copper plating]], opening North America's first copper mill south of Boston in [[Canton, Massachusetts|Canton]], near the [[Canton Viaduct]]. Copper from the [[Revere Copper Company]] was used to cover the original wooden dome of the [[Massachusetts State House]] in 1802.

His business plans in the late 1780s were stymied by a shortage of adequate money in circulation. His plans rested on his entrepreneurial role as a manufacturer of cast iron, brass, and copper products. [[Alexander Hamilton]]'s national policies regarding banks and industrialization exactly matched his dreams, and he became an ardent [[Federalist Party|Federalist]] committed to building a robust economy and a powerful nation. His copper and brass works eventually grew, through sale and corporate merger, into a large national corporation, Revere Copper and Brass, Inc.

Despite advancing age, Revere remained active.  He continued to discuss the issues of the day, and in 1814 circulated a petition offering the government the services of Boston's artisans in protecting Boston during the [[War of 1812]].{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=257}}  Revere died on May 10, 1818, at the age of 83, at his home on Charter Street in Boston.{{sfn|Miller|2010|p=258}} He is buried in the [[Granary Burying Ground]] on Tremont Street.{{sfn|PRMA|1988|p=33}}

==Legacy==
[[File:Paul Revere 1958 Issue-25c.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Revere on 1958 U.S. stamp.]]
[[File:Paul Revere Memorial, Granary Burying Ground, Boston, Massachusetts.jpg|upright|thumb|right|Paul Revere's grave site in the [[Granary Burying Ground]]]]
After Paul Revere's death, the family business was taken over by his oldest surviving son, Joseph Warren Revere.{{sfn|Miller|2010|pp=255, 260}}  The copper works founded in 1801 continues today as the [[Revere Copper Company]], with manufacturing divisions in [[Rome, New York]] and [[New Bedford, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reverecopper.com/about.html|title=About the Revere Copper Company|publisher=Revere Copper Company|accessdate=April 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 25-cent 1958 U.S. [[postage stamp]] in the [[Liberty Issue|Liberty Series]] honors Paul Revere, featuring the portrait by [[Gilbert Stuart]].  He also appears on the $5,000 [[United States Treasury security#Series EE|Series EE U.S. Savings Bond]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.treasurydirect.gov/images/instit/savbond/mat/clipart/maree5000.gif|publisher=United States Treasury|title=U.S. Savings Bond Images|accessdate=April 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Revere's original silverware, engravings, and other works are highly regarded today, and can be found on display in the [[Museum of Fine Arts, Boston]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.org/collections/search_art.asp?coll_accession=&amp;coll_name=&amp;coll_artist=Paul+Revere+Jr&amp;coll_medium=&amp;coll_culture=&amp;coll_classification=&amp;coll_credit=&amp;coll_provenance=&amp;coll_keywords=&amp;coll_sort=2&amp;coll_sort_order=0&amp;submit=Search|title=Boston Museum of Fine Arts Search for Paul Revere|publisher=Boston Museum of Fine Arts|accessdate=April 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other museums.

The communities of [[Revere, Massachusetts]]{{sfn|Schmidt|2002|p=7}} and [[Revere, Minnesota]],{{sfn|Upham|1920|p=451}} bear his name, as do [[Revere Beach]]{{sfn|Schmidt|2002|p=7}} in Revere, Massachusetts, Revere Avenue in [[The Bronx]], [[New York City]],{{sfn|McNamara|1978}} and Paul Revere Road in Arlington Heights in [[Arlington, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;National Lancers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nationallancers.org/pday.html|title=Patriot's Day Events|publisher=National Lancers Foundation|accessdate=June 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ride===
In 1861, over 40 years after Revere's death, [[Henry Wadsworth Longfellow]] made the midnight ride the subject of his poem &quot;[[Paul Revere's Ride]],&quot; which opens:

{{quote |Listen, my children, and you shall hear&lt;br /&gt;Of the midnight ride of Paul Revere,&lt;br /&gt;On the eighteenth of April, in Seventy-Five;&lt;br /&gt;Hardly a man is now alive&lt;br /&gt;Who remembers that famous day and year}}

Longfellow's poem is not historically accurate, but his &quot;mistakes&quot; were deliberate. He had researched the historical event, using such works as [[George Bancroft]]'s ''History of the United States'', but he manipulated the facts for poetic effect.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=331}}  He was purposely trying to create American legends, much as he did with works like ''[[The Song of Hiawatha]]'' (1855) and ''[[The Courtship of Miles Standish]]'' (1858).{{sfn|Ruland|Bradbury|1991|p=109}} Longfellow was successful in creating a legend: Revere's stature rose significantly in the years following the poem's publication.{{sfn|Fischer|1994|p=333}}

Parts of the ride route in Massachusetts are now posted with signs marked &quot;Revere's Ride&quot;. The route follows Main Street in [[Charlestown, Massachusetts|Charlestown]], Broadway and Main Street in [[Somerville, Massachusetts|Somerville]], Main Street and High Street in [[Medford, Massachusetts|Medford]], Medford Street to [[Arlington, Massachusetts|Arlington]] center, and [[Massachusetts Avenue (Boston)|Massachusetts Avenue]] the rest of the way through Lexington and into Lincoln.  Revere's ride is reenacted annually.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Lancers&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
*[[Jack Jouett]], rode to warn [[Thomas Jefferson]] and the [[Virginia]] legislature of a British raid
*''[[Johnny Tremain]]'', 1943 children's novel by [[Esther Forbes]] set in Boston prior to and during the outbreak of the Revolution
*[[Israel Bissell]], who rode to [[Philadelphia]] to warn the colonists there
*[[Sybil Ludington]], who performed a similar ride in [[New York]]
*[[Laura Secord]], &quot;[[Canada]]'s Paul Revere&quot; in the [[War of 1812]]

==References==
===Notes===
{{reflist|group=N}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|4}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Boatner
|first1= Mark Mayo, III
|year= 1975
|origyear= 1964
|title= Encyclopedia of the American Revolution
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=-r6sNI9dUfYC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|location= New York
|publisher= David McKay
|series= Library of Military History
|isbn= 978-0618001941
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Brooks
|first1= Victor
|year= 1999
|title= The Boston Campaign: April 1775–March 1776
|url=
|location= Conshohocken, Pennsylvania
|publisher= Combined Publishing
|isbn= 978-0585234533
}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last1=Drake|first=Samuel Adams|title=Historic Mansions and Highways Around Boston|publisher=Little, Brown|year=1899|location=Boston|oclc=1838072|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=iPUMAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA128#v=onepage&amp;f=false}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Fischer
|first1= David Hackett
|authorlink= David Hackett Fischer
|year= 1994
|title= Paul Revere's ride
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=knC-kTFI9_gC
|location=New York
|publisher= Oxford University Press
|isbn= 0-19-508847-6
}} This work is extensively footnoted, and contains a voluminous list of primary resources concerning all aspects of the Revere's ride and the battles at Lexington and Concord.
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Forbes
|first1= Esther
|authorlink= Esther Forbes
|year= 1999
|origyear= 1942
|title= Paul Revere and the World He Lived in
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=-r6sNI9dUfYC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|location= Boston
|publisher= Houghton Mifflin
|isbn= 978-0618001941
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Gettemy
|first1= Charles
|year= 1905
|title= The True Story of Paul Revere
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=SlUSAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover
|location= Boston
|publisher= Little, Brown
|oclc=1375230
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Goss
|first1= Elbridge Henry
|year= 1891
|title= The Life of Colonel Paul Revere
|location= Boston
|publisher= J. G. Cupples
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=HEtgrZJmu9oC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|oclc=3589045
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Martello
|first1= Robert
|year= 2010
|title= Midnight Ride, Industrial Dawn: Paul Revere and the Growth of American Enterprise
|location= Baltimore
|publisher= The Johns Hopkins University Press
|series= Johns Hopkins Studies in the History of Technology
}}
*{{cite journal
|ref= harv
|last= McDonald
|first= Forrest
|last2= McDonald
|first2= Ellen
|date=
|year= 1980
|month= April
|title= The Ethnic Origins of the American People, 1790
|journal= The William and Mary Quarterly
|volume= 37
|series= Third
|issue= 2
|pages=179–199
|jstor= 1919495
}}
*{{cite book
|last1= McNamara
|first1= John
|year= 1978
|title= History in Asphalt: The Origin of Bronx Street and Place Names, Borough of the Bronx, New York City
|location= Fleischmanns, New York
|publisher= Harbor Hill Books}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Miller
|first1= Joel J.
|year= 2010
|title= The Revolutionary Paul Revere
|location= Nashville, Tennessee
|publisher= Thomas Nelson
|isbn=978-1595550743
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Murrin
|first1= John M.
|last2=  et al.
|year= 2002
|origyear= 1996
|title= Liberty, Equality, Power: A History of the American People, Volume I: To 1877
|location= Florence, Kentucky
|publisher= Wadsworth-Thomson Learning
}}
*{{cite book|ref={{harvid|PRMA|1998}}|title=Paul Revere, Artisan, Businessman and Patriot: The Man Behind the Myth|location=Boston|publisher=Paul Revere Memorial Association (PRMA)|year=1988}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Revere
|first1= Paul
|others= Introduction by Edmund Morgan
|year= 1961
|title= Paul Revere's Three Accounts of His Famous Ride
|location= Boston
|publisher= Massachusetts Historical Society
|isbn=978-0961999902
}}
*{{cite book
|last1= Ruland
|first1= Richard
|last2= Bradbury
|first2= Malcolm
|year= 1991
|title= From Puritanism to Postmodernism: A History of American Literature
|location= New York
|publisher= Viking}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last1=Schmidt|first1=Leah A|title=Revere Beach|location=Mount Pleasant, SC|publisher=Arcadia Publishing|year=2002|isbn=978-0738510309}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Steblecki
|first1= Edith J.
|year= 1985
|title= Paul Revere and Freemasonry
|location= Boston
|publisher= Paul Revere Memorial Association (PRMA)
|oclc=17485269
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Triber
|first1= Jayne
|year= 1998
|title= A True Republican: The Life of Paul Revere
|location= Amherst, Massachusetts
|publisher= University of Massachusetts Press
|isbn=978-1558491397
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= United States
|first1= National Archives and Records Service
|title= Papers of the [[Continental Congress]], 1774–1789
|publisher= [[National Archives]] and Records Service, [[General Services Administration]]
}}
*{{cite book
|ref= harv
|last1= Upham
|first1= Warren
|year= 1920
|title= Minnesota Geographic Names: Their Origin and Historic Significance
|location= St. Paul, Minnesota
|publisher= Minnesota Historical Society
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ShcLAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover
|oclc=34232868
}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Paul Revere}}
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Revere, Paul}}
*[http://www.paul-revere-heritage.com/ Paul Revere Heritage Project]
*[http://www.paulreverehouse.org/ The Paul Revere House]
**[http://www.paulreverehouse.org/ride/ An interactive map showing the routes taken by Revere, Dawes, and Prescott]
*[http://www.sec.state.ma.us/arc/arcidx.htm Original copper engravings and other documents in collections of the Massachusetts State Archives]
*{{Worldcat id|lccn-n80-37041}}
*[http://revererollingmill.googlepages.com/ Revere Rolling Mill] (about the endangered original Revere copper works site in Canton, MA)

{{Persondata
| NAME              =Revere, Paul
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =American patriot and silversmith
| DATE OF BIRTH     =December 21, 1734
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Boston]] ([[North End, Boston, Massachusetts|North End]]), [[Province of Massachusetts Bay]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =May 10, 1818
| PLACE OF DEATH    =[[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Revere, Paul}}
[[Category:American businesspeople]]
[[Category:American engravers]]
[[Category:American people of French descent]]
[[Category:American Revolution spies]]
[[Category:American silversmiths]]
[[Category:Foundrymen]]
[[Category:British military personnel of the Seven Years' War]]
[[Category:Massachusetts Federalists]]
[[Category:Massachusetts militiamen in the American Revolution]]
[[Category:Patriots in the American Revolution]]
[[Category:People from Boston, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:People of Massachusetts in the American Revolution]]
[[Category:1734 births]]
[[Category:1818 deaths]]
[[Category:18th-century people]]

[[ar:بول ريفير]]
[[ca:Paul Revere]]
[[da:Paul Revere]]
[[de:Paul Revere (Freiheitskämpfer)]]
[[es:Paul Revere]]
[[fr:Paul Revere]]
[[ga:Paul Revere]]
[[ia:Paul Revere]]
[[it:Paul Revere]]
[[he:פול רוויר]]
[[nl:Paul Revere]]
[[ja:ポール・リビア]]
[[pl:Paul Revere]]
[[pt:Paul Revere]]
[[ro:Paul Revere]]
[[ru:Ревир, Пол]]
[[simple:Paul Revere]]
[[fi:Paul Revere]]
[[sv:Paul Revere]]
[[uk:Пол Ревір]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
