<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="50591" ns="0" title="United States Postal Service"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{About|the government agency|individual post offices|U.S. Post Office (disambiguation)|the cycling team|Discovery Channel Pro Cycling Team}}
{{Redirect|USPS|the non-profit boating safety and education organization|United States Power Squadrons}}
{{Cleanup|date=October 2010}}
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Infobox company
|company_name   = United States Postal Service|100px
|company_logo   = [[File:United States Postal Service Logo.svg|200px]]
|company_type   = [[Independent agencies of the United States government|Independent agency of the United States government]]
|company_slogan = We Deliver For You.
|key_people     = [[Patrick R. Donahoe]], [[United States Postmaster General]]
|num_employees  = 574,001(2011 Career Employees)&lt;ref name=&quot;postalfacts-2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web | coauthors = | title = 2011 Postal Facts | publisher=U.S. Postal Service | year = 2011 | url = http://about.usps.com/future-postal-service/postalfacts-2011.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate =November 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|foundation     = July 26, 1775&lt;br&gt;[[Philadelphia, PA]]
|location       = 475 [[L'Enfant Plaza]] SW&lt;br /&gt;Washington, D.C. 20260-2202
|industry       = [[Courier]]
|products       = [[First-class mail|First-class]] and [[mail|domestic mail]], [[logistics]]
|revenue        = {{decrease}} US$ 65.71&amp;nbsp;billion (2011)&lt;ref name=&quot;form10k2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web | coauthors = | title = 2011 Form 10-K | publisher=U.S. Postal Service | year = 2011 | url = http://about.usps.com/who-we-are/financials/10k-reports/fy2011.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate =November 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|operating_income = {{decrease}} US$ −4.92&amp;nbsp;billion (2011)
|net_income       = {{decrease}} US$ −5.1&amp;nbsp;billion (2011)
|parent           = [[Federal government of the United States|Government of the United States]]
|homepage         = [http://www.usps.com/ USPS.com]
}}
[[File:Uspslogo.png|thumb|300px|Full eagle logo, used in various versions from 1970 to 1993]]

The '''United States Postal Service''' (also known as '''USPS''', the '''Post Office''' or '''U.S. Mail''') is an independent agency of the United States government responsible for providing [[mail|postal service]] in the United States. It is one of the few government agencies [[Postal Clause|explicitly authorized by the United States Constitution]].

The USPS traces its roots to 1775 during the [[Second Continental Congress]], where [[Benjamin Franklin]] was appointed the first [[Postmaster General of the United States|postmaster general]]. The [[United States Cabinet|cabinet-level]] [[United States Post Office Department|Post Office Department]] was created in 1792 from Franklin's operation and transformed into its current form in 1971 under the [[Postal Reorganization Act]].

The USPS has not directly received taxpayer-dollars since the early 1980s with the minor exception of subsidies for costs associated with the disabled and overseas voters. Revenue in the 2000s has been dropping sharply due to declining mail volume,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/08/12/news/economy/post_office_layoffs/ | work=CNN | first=Jennifer | last=Liberto | title=Clock ticking on Postal Service budget crisis | date=August 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; prompting the postal service to look to other sources of revenue while cutting costs to reduce its budget deficit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/2009/05/08/news/economy/postal_service/index.htm |publisher=CNN | title=U.S. Postal Service find ways to save money | date=May 11, 2009 | accessdate=May 26, 2010 | first=Aaron | last=Smith}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The USPS employs over 574,000 workers and operates over 218,000 vehicles. It is the 48th-largest employer in the United States.  The USPS is the operator of the largest [[vehicle fleet]] in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Postal Facts 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Postal Facts 2010| publisher=U.S. Postal Service | year = 2010| url = http://www.usps.com/strategicplanning/_pdf/PostalFacts_03_17_2010.pdf|accessdate =September 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The USPS is legally obligated to serve all Americans, regardless of geography, at uniform price and quality. The USPS has exclusive access to [[letter box]]es marked &quot;U.S. Mail&quot; and personal letterboxes in the United States, but still competes against private [[package delivery]] services, such as [[United Parcel Service|UPS]] and [[FedEx]].

==History==
{{Main|Postage stamps and postal history of the United States}}
[[File:United States Department of the Post Office Seal.svg|thumb|left|Running pony logo used by the U.S. Post Office Department before the creation of the USPS]]
The first postal service in America arose in February 1692, when a grant from [[William and Mary|King William &amp; Queen Mary]] empowered [[Thomas Neale]] &quot;to erect, settle and establish within the chief parts of their majesties' colonies and plantations in America, an office or offices for the receiving and dispatching letters and pacquets, and to receive, send and deliver the same under such rates and sums of money as the planters shall agree to give, and to hold and enjoy the same for the term of twenty-one years.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/40066939 ''Our Postal System''] Francis C. Huebner. Records of the Columbia Historical Society, Washington, DC Vol. 9 (1906), pp. 126–74. Historical Society of Washington, DC.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''United States Post Office'' (USPO) was created in [[Philadelphia]] under [[Benjamin Franklin]] on Wednesday, July 26, 1775, by decree of the [[Second Continental Congress]]. Based on the [[Postal Clause]] in [[Article One of the United States Constitution]], empowering [[United States Congress|Congress]] &quot;To establish [[Post office|post offices]] and [[Post road|post roads]]&quot;, it became the '''[[United States Post Office Department|Post Office Department]]''' (USPOD) in 1792. Until 1971, it was part of the Presidential cabinet and the [[United States Postmaster General|Postmaster General]] was the last person in the [[United States presidential line of succession]].

The Post Office Department was enlarged during the tenure of President [[Andrew Jackson]]. As the Post Office expanded, difficulties were experienced due to a lack of employees and transportation. The Post Office's employees at that time were still subject to the so-called &quot;spoils&quot; system, where faithful political supporters of the executive branch were appointed to positions in the post office and other government corporations as a reward for their patronage. These appointees rarely had prior experience in postal service and mail delivery. This system of political patronage was replaced in 1883, after passage of the [[Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.classbrain.com/artteenst/publish/article_130.shtml | title = Classbrain | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ten years before waterways were declared post roads in 1823, the Post Office used steamboats to carry mail between post towns where no roads existed.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}  Once it became clear that the postal system in the United States needed to expand across the entire country, the use of the railroad to transport the mail was instituted in 1832, on one line in Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;postalmuseum1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.postalmuseum.si.edu/exhibits/2c1_railwaymail.html |title=National Postal Museum |publisher=SI |accessdate=October 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; All railroads in the United States were designated as post routes, after passage of the Act of July 7, 1838. Mail service by railroad increased rapidly thereafter.&lt;ref&gt;History of the United States Postal Service 1775–1993, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:First US Stamps 1847 Issue.jpg|right|thumb|300px|&lt;center&gt;''~ [[Benjamin Franklin]] ~ [[George Washington]] ~''&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;The First U.S. Postage Stamps&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:10pt&quot;&gt;Issued 1847&lt;/center&gt;The first stamp issues were authorized by an act of Congress and approved on March 3, 1847.&lt;ref&gt;USPS, [http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/stampsandpostcards.htm?from=PostalHistory&amp;page=Center_StampsandPostcards#hosp United States Postage Stamps]&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest known use of the Franklin 5c is July 7, 1847, while the earliest known use of the Washington 10c is July 2, 1847. Remaining in postal circulation for only a few years, these issues were declared invalid for Postage on July 1, 1851.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scotts US Postage Stamp Catalogue&lt;/ref&gt;]]

An Act of Congress provided for the issuance of stamps on March 3, 1847, and the Postmaster General immediately let a contract to the New York City engraving firm of Rawdon, Wright, Hatch, and Edson. The first stamp issue of the U.S. was offered for sale on July 1, 1847, in NYC, with Boston receiving stamps the following day and other cities thereafter. The 5 cent stamp paid for a letter weighing less than {{convert|1|oz|abbr=on}} and travelling less than 300 miles, the 10 cent stamp for deliveries to locations greater than 300 miles, or twice the weight deliverable for the 5 cent stamp.

In 1847, the [[U.S. Mail Steamship Company]] acquired the contract to carry the U.S. mails from New York, with stops in New Orleans and [[Havana]], to the [[Isthmus of Panama]] for delivery in California. The same year, the [[Pacific Mail Steamship Company]] had acquired the right to transport mail under contract from the United States Government from the Isthmus of Panama to California. In 1855, [[William Henry Aspinwall]] completed the [[Panama Canal Railway|Panama Railway]], the first transcontinental railroad, providing service from the east coast across the Isthmus to California in three weeks for the mails, passengers and goods, and remained an important route until the completion of the transcontinental railroad in 1869. Railroad companies greatly expanded mail transport service after 1862, and the [[Railway Mail Service]] was inaugurated in 1869.&lt;ref name=&quot;postalmuseum1&quot;/&gt;  Rail cars designed to sort and distribute mail while rolling were soon introduced.&lt;ref name=&quot;postalmuseum1&quot;/&gt;  RMS employees sorted mail 'on the fly' during the journey, and became some of the most skilled workers in the postal service. An RMS sorter had to be able to separate the mail quickly into compartments based on its final destination, before the first destination arrived, and work at the rate of 600 pieces of mail an hour. They were tested regularly for speed and accuracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.postalmuseum.si.edu/exhibits/2c1a_insiderms.html |title=National Postal Museum |publisher=Postalmuseum.si.edu |accessdate=October 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The advent of [[rural free delivery]] in the U.S. in 1896, and the inauguration of [[parcel post]] service in 1913 greatly increased the volume of mail shipped nationwide, and motivated the development of more efficient postal transportation systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sil.si.edu/ondisplay/parcelpost/cf/view.cfm |title=Parcel Post: Delivery of Dreams |publisher=Sil.si.edu |accessdate=October 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 12, 1918, the Post Office Department took over [[air mail]] service from the [[U.S. Army Air Service]] (USAAS). Assistant Postmaster General, Otto Praeger, appointed Benjamin B. Lipsner to head the civilian-operated [[Airmails of the United States|Air Mail Service]]. One of Lipsner's first acts was to hire four pilots, each with at least 1,000 hours flying experience, paying them an average of $4,000 per year. The Post Office Department used mostly World War I military surplus [[de Havilland DH-4]] aircraft. During 1918, the Post Office hired an additional 36 pilots. In its first year of operation, the Post Office completed 1,208 airmail flights with 90 forced landings. Of those, 53 were due to weather and 37 to engine failure. By 1920, the Air Mail service had delivered 49 million letters.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Centennial of Flight Commission, [http://www.centennialofflight.gov/essay/Government_Role/1918-1924/POL3.htm ''The Post Office Flies The Mail'']&lt;/ref&gt; Domestic [[Airmails of the United States|air mail]] became obsolete in 1975, and international air mail in 1995, when the USPS began transporting First-Class mail by air on a routine basis.

The Post Office was one of the first government departments to regulate [[obscenity|obscene]] materials on a national basis. When the U.S. Congress passed the [[Comstock laws]] of 1873, it became illegal to send through the U.S. mail any material considered obscene, [[decency|indecent]] or which promoted abortion issues, [[contraception]], or [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]] consumption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law.jrank.org/pages/5508/Comstock-Law-1873.html |title=Comstock Law of (1873) |publisher=Law.jrank.org |accessdate=October 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Postal Reorganization Act]] signed by President [[Richard Nixon]] on August 12, 1970, replaced the cabinet-level [[United States Post Office Department|Post Office Department]] with the independent United States Postal Service. The Act took effect on July 1, 1971.

On May 11, 2009, the price of a First-Class Mail stamp rose to 44 cents.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com usps.com]. usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current operations==
[[File:United States Postal Service Truck.jpg|thumb|left|USPS service delivery truck]]
The United States Postal Service employs some 574,000 workers, making it the second-largest&lt;ref name=&quot;Postal Facts 2010&quot;/&gt; civilian employer in the United States (excluding the federal government), following only Wal-Mart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://walmartstores.com/download/2230.pdf| format=PDF| title=Corporate Fact Sheet| publisher=Wal-Mart| date=July 17, 2008| accessdate=August 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In a 2006 [[U.S. Supreme Court]] decision, the Court noted: &quot;Each day, according to the Government's submissions here, the United States Postal Service delivers some 660 million pieces of mail to as many as 142&amp;nbsp;million delivery points.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Dolan v. United States Postal Service]]'', {{ussc|546|481|2006}}. Update: In February 2011, the figure for number of delivery points was stated as &quot;more than 150 million nationally&quot; (See citation name=DelOn20110220).&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 2011, the USPS operates 31,000 post offices and locations in the U.S., and delivers 177&amp;nbsp;billion pieces of mail annually.&lt;ref name=&quot;Postal Facts 2010&quot;/&gt;

The USPS operates the largest civilian [[vehicle fleet]] in the world, with an estimated 218,684 vehicles, the majority of which are the easily identified [[Chevrolet]]/[[Grumman LLV]] (Long-Life Vehicle), and the newer Ford/Utilimaster FFV (Flex-Fuel Vehicle), originally also referred to as the &quot;CRV&quot; (Carrier Route Vehicle).&lt;ref name=&quot;Postal Facts 2010&quot;/&gt; For every penny increase in the national average price of gasoline, the USPS spends an extra $8&amp;nbsp;million per year to fuel its fleet.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.wjla.com/news/stories/0608/529721.html| title=High Gas Prices Affecting USPS Drivers| date=June 19, 2008| publisher=[[WJLA-TV]]| work=[[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]| accessdate=August 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of gallons of fuel used in 2009 was 444 million, at a cost of {{USD|1.1}} billion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Postal Facts 2010&quot;/&gt; The fleet is notable in that many of its vehicles are [[Right- and left-hand traffic|right-hand drive]], an arrangement intended to give drivers the easiest access to roadside mailboxes. Some [[Rural Letter Carrier]]s use personal vehicles. Standard postal-owned vehicles do not have [[license plate]]s. These vehicles are identified by a seven digit number displayed on the front and rear.

[[File:GriffithStationHoustonvehicles.JPG|thumb|Fleet of post office vehicles at the James Griffith Station in [[Spring Branch, Houston]]]]

The Department of Defense and the USPS jointly operate a postal system to deliver [[Military mail#United States Military Postal Services|mail for the military]]; this is known as the '''Army Post Office''' (for [[United States Army|Army]] and [[United States Air Force|Air Force]] postal facilities) and the '''Fleet Post Office''' (for [[United States Navy|Navy]], [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] and [[United States Coast Guard|Coast Guard]] postal facilities).

===Revenue decline===
Declining mail volume is a symptom of the weak national economy{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}, particularly related to the financial and housing industries, and to trends toward the use of electronic mail. In addition to the weak or contracting economy and the diversion of mail to electronic means, the pre-funding of retiree health benefits continues to have a significant impact on Postal Service finances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usps.com/financials/| title=Financials | publisher=USPS| year=2009|accessdate=August 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;strategicplanning&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.usps.com/strategicplanning/cs08/chpt1_pg5.htm| title=Comprehensive Statement on Postal Operations 2008| publisher=USPS| year=2008| accessdate=August 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; First-Class mail volume (which is protected by legal monopoly) peaked in 2001&lt;ref&gt;[http://about.usps.com/who-we-are/postal-history/first-class-mail-1926-2010.pdf First Class Mail Volume, 1926-2010]&lt;/ref&gt;and has declined 29% from 1998 to 2008, due to the increasing use of email and the World Wide Web for correspondence and business transactions.&lt;ref name=&quot;amp&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.usps.com/all/amp.htm| title=USPS – Area Mail Processing| publisher=USPS| year=2009| accessdate=August 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Lower volume means lower revenues to support the fixed commitment to deliver to every address once a day, six days a week. In response, the USPS has increased productivity each year from 2000 to 2007,&lt;ref name=&quot;strategicplanning&quot;/&gt; through increased automation, route re-optimization, and facility consolidation.&lt;ref name=&quot;amp&quot;/&gt;  Despite these efforts, the organization saw an $8.5&amp;nbsp;billion budget shortfall in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;McElhatton, Jim [http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/nov/12/postal-service-reports-8-billion-losses/ &quot;Postal Service Reports $8 billion in Losses&quot;], ''The Washington Times'', November 12, 2010, accessed August 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

To cut costs, the U.S. Postal Service proposes to close as many as 3,700 small post offices and replacing some of them as 'village post offices' to offer the most basic mail services at lower costs inside such places as grocery stores and drugstores with signs -'Village Post Office'- in the window since August 2011. The Postal Service will pay Mini-mart about $2,000 a year. One benefit of the new policy is service hours which are longer than the old post office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/story/2011-09-14/village-post-office-closing/50408934/1?csp=34news&amp;utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+usatoday-NewsTopStories+%28News+-+Top+Stories%29 |title=Post office turns to small-town mini-mart for savings |accessdate=September 15, 2011 | work=USA Today |date=September 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other plans===
In October 2008, the Postal Service released ''Vision 2013'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://about.usps.com/transforming-business/vision2013.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; a five-year plan required by law starting in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;Government Performance and Results Act 0f 1993, P.L. 103-62, ([http://www.usps.com/strategicplanning/govtperfact.htm USPS.com])&lt;/ref&gt; One planned improvement is the introduction of the [[Intelligent Mail Barcode]], which will allow pieces of mail to be tracked through the delivery system, as competitors like UPS and FedEx currently do.

==Governance and organization==
[[File:Uspsheadquartersatlenfantplaza.jpg|thumb|USPS headquarters at [[L'Enfant Plaza]] in Washington, D.C.]]
The [[Board of Governors of the United States Postal Service]] sets policy, procedure, and postal rates for services rendered, and has a similar role to a corporate board of directors. Of the eleven members of the Board, nine are appointed by the President and confirmed by the [[United States Senate]] (see {{usc|39|202}}). The nine appointed members then select the [[United States Postmaster General]], who serves as the board's tenth member, and who oversees the day to day activities of the service as Chief Executive Officer (see {{usc|39|202|203}}). The ten-member board then nominates a Deputy Postmaster General, who acts as Chief Operating Officer, to the eleventh and last remaining open seat.

The USPS is often mistaken for a government-owned corporation (e.g., [[Amtrak]]) because it operates much like a business, but as noted above, it is legally defined as an &quot;independent establishment of the executive branch of the Government of the United States&quot;, ({{usc|39|201}}) as it is controlled by Presidential appointees and the Postmaster General. As a [[quasi-governmental agency]], it has many special privileges, including [[sovereign immunity]], [[eminent domain]] powers, powers to negotiate [[Universal Postal Union|postal treaties]] with foreign nations, and an exclusive legal right to deliver first-class and third-class mail. Indeed, in 2004, the U.S. Supreme Court ruled in a unanimous decision that the USPS was not a government-owned corporation, and therefore could not be sued under the [[Sherman Antitrust Act]].&lt;ref&gt;''United States Postal Serv. v. Flamingo Indus. (USA) Ltd.'', {{ussc|540|736|2004}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. Supreme Court has also upheld the USPS's statutory monopoly on access to letter boxes against a [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] [[Freedom of speech in the United States|freedom of speech]] challenge; it thus remains illegal in the U.S. for ''anyone'', other than the employees and agents of the USPS, to deliver mailpieces to letter boxes marked &quot;U.S. Mail.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''United States Postal Serv. v. Greenburgh Civic Ass'ns'', {{ussc|453|114|1981}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Postal Service also has a [[Mailers' Technical Advisory Committee]] and local Postal Customer Councils, which are advisory and primarily involve business customers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/strategicplanning/cs08/chpt2_pg10.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (September 17, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Universal service obligation and monopoly status==
{{Unbalanced|date=October 2010}}
{{Importance-section|date=October 2010}}
{{Generalize-section|date=October 2010}}
{{Incoherent|date=October 2010}}
{{Refimprove|section|{{subst:November 2011}}|date=November 2011|talk=y}}
[[Postal Clause|Article I, section 8, Clause 7]] of the [[United States Constitution]] grants Congress the power to establish post offices and post roads, which has been interpreted as a de facto Congressional monopoly over the delivery of mail. Accordingly, no other system for delivering mail – public or private – can be established, absent Congress's consent.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}} Congress has delegated to the Postal Service the power to decide whether others may compete with it, and the Postal Service has allowed an exception to its monopoly for extremely urgent letters.

The mission of the Postal Service is to provide the American public with trusted universal postal service at affordable prices. While not explicitly defined, the Postal Service's [[universal service obligation]] (USO) is broadly outlined in statute and includes multiple dimensions: geographic scope, range of products, access to services and facilities, delivery frequency, affordable and uniform pricing, service quality, and security of the mail. While other carriers may claim to voluntarily provide delivery on a broad basis, the Postal Service is the only carrier with a ''legal obligation'' to provide all the various aspects of universal service at affordable rates.

Proponents of universal service principles claim that since any obligation must be matched by the financial capability to meet that obligation, the postal monopoly was put in place as a funding mechanism for the USO, and it has been in place for over a hundred years. It consists of two parts: the [[Private Express Statutes]] (PES) and the mailbox access rule. The PES refers to the Postal Service's monopoly on the delivery of letters, and the mailbox rule refers to the Postal Service's exclusive access to customer mailboxes.

Proponents of universal service principles further claim that eliminating or reducing the PES or mailbox rule would have an impact on the ability of the Postal Service to provide affordable universal service. If, for example, the PES and the mailbox rule were to be eliminated, and the USO maintained, then either billions of dollars in tax revenues or some other source of funding would have to be found. As the operating environment of the Postal Service continues to change, additional flexibilities will likely be necessary to fulfill the USO.

Some proponents of universal service principles suggest that private communications that are protected by the veil of government promote the exchange of free ideas and communications. This separates private communications from the ability of a private organization or company motivated by profit to corrupt. Security for the individual is in this way protected by the United States Post Office, maintaining confidentiality and anonymity, as well as government employee's being much less likely to be instructed by superiors to engage in nefarious action related to communications between persons, organizations or competitors in all nature of associations.  It is seen by some as a dangerous step to extract the universal service principle from the post office, as the untainted nature of private communications is preserved as assurance of the protection of individual freedom of privacy. 

Critics of universal service principles include several professional economists advocating for the privatization of the mail delivery system, or at least a relaxation of the universal service model that currently exists.&lt;ref&gt;Geddes, Rick. &quot;Do Vital Economists Reach a Policy Conclusion on Postal Reform?&quot; (April 2004).
[http://www.econjournalwatch.org/pdf/Geddes%20Do%20Economists%20April%202004.pdf econjournalwatch.org]&lt;/ref&gt;  Rick Geddes argued in 2000:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoover.org/publications/digest/3484126.html Neither Snow nor Sleet... Can Dampen This Monopoly] Rick Geddes from the Hoover Institution talks about rural subsidies&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''First, basic economics implies that rural customers are unlikely to be without service under competition; they would simply have to pay the true cost of delivery to them, which may or may not be lower than under monopoly.''
* ''Second, basic notions of fairness imply that the cross-subsidy should be eliminated. To the extent that people make choices about where they live, they should assume the costs of that decision.''
* ''Third, there is no reason why the government monopoly is necessary to ensure service to sparsely populated areas. The government could easily award competitive contracts to private firms for that service.''
* ''Fourth, early concerns that rural residents of the United States would somehow become isolated without federally subsidized mail delivery today are simply unfounded. ... Once both sender and receiver have access to a computer, the marginal cost of sending an electronic message is close to zero.''
However, as the recent notice of a termination of mail service to residents of the [[Frank Church—River of No Return Wilderness]] indicates, mail service has been contracted to private firms such as Arnold Aviation for many decades. KTVB-TV reported:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ktvb.com/news/local/64242462.html Postal Service to renew Idaho back country mail route] Alyson Outen, KTVB-TV, April 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
:'&quot;We cannot go out every week and pick up our mail....it's impossible&quot;, said Heinz Sippel. &quot;Everyone gets their mail. Why can't we?&quot; said Sue Anderson. Getting mail delivered, once a week, by airplane is not a luxury, it's a necessity for those who live in Idaho's vast wilderness – those along the Salmon and Selway rivers. It's a service that's been provided to them for more than half a century – mostly by Ray Arnold of Arnold Aviation.

The decision was reversed; U.S. Postmaster General John Potter indicated that acceptable service to back country customers could not be achieved in any other fashion than continuing an air mail contract with Arnold Aviation to deliver the mail.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://minnick.house.gov/2009/05/idaho-delegation-gets-reversal-on-backcountry-mail-delivery-decision.shtml Idaho delegation gets reversal on back country mail delivery decision]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Postal Act of 2006 required the [[Postal Regulatory Commission]] (PRC) to submit a report to the President and Congress on universal postal service and the postal monopoly in December 2008. The report must include any recommended changes. The Postal Service report supports the requirement that the PRC is to consult with and solicit written comments from the Postal Service. In addition, the Government Accountability Office is required to evaluate broader business model issues by 2011.

On October 15, 2008, the Postal Service submitted a report&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postallaw/universalpostalservice.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; to the PRC on its position related to the Universal Service Obligation (USO). It said no changes to the USO and restriction on mailbox access were necessary at this time, but increased regulatory flexibility was required to ensure affordable universal service in the future.

Obligations of the USO include uniform prices, quality of service, access to services, and six-day delivery to every part of the country. To assure financial support for these obligations, the postal monopoly provides the Postal Service the exclusive right to deliver letters and restricts mailbox access solely for mail. The report argued that eliminating or reducing either aspect of the monopoly &quot;would have a devastating impact on the ability...to provide the affordable universal service that the country values so highly.&quot; Relaxing access to the mailbox would also pose security concerns, increase delivery costs, and hurt customer service, according to the Post Office. The report notes:
:''It is somewhat misleading to characterize the mailbox rule as a &quot;monopoly,&quot; because the enforcement of {{UnitedStatesCode|18|1725}} leaves customers with ample alternative means of delivering their messages. Customers can deliver their messages either by paying postage, by placing messages on or under a door or a doormat, by using newspaper or non-postal boxes, by telephoning or emailing, by engaging in person-to-person delivery in public areas, by tacking or taping their notices on a door post, or by placing advertisements in local newspapers. These methods are comparable in efficacy to communication via the mailbox.''

The Postal Service said that the USO should continue to be broadly defined and there should be no changes to the postal monopoly. Any changes would have far-reaching effects on customers and the trillion dollar mailing industry. &quot;A more rigidly defined USO would … ultimately harm the American public and businesses,&quot; according to the report, which cautions that any potential change must be studied carefully and the effects fully understood.

During hearings held earlier this year, the PRC also heard from mailers, mailing associations, and postal unions and management associations. Comments generally indicated that changes are not currently needed.

===Competitors===
[[File:U.S. Post Office - Los Angeles Terminal Annex.jpg|thumb|USPS [[Terminal Annex]] building in Los Angeles]]
[[FedEx]] and [[United Parcel Service]] (UPS) directly compete with USPS express mail and package delivery services, making nationwide deliveries of urgent letters and packages. Due to the postal monopoly, they are not allowed to deliver non-urgent letters and may not directly ship to U.S. Mail boxes at residential and commercial destinations. However both companies have transit agreements with the USPS in which an item can be dropped off with either FedEx or UPS who will then provide shipment up to the destination post office serving the intended recipient where it will be transferred for delivery to the US Mail destination, including Post Office Box destinations. These services also deliver packages which are larger and heavier than USPS will accept. [[DHL Express]] was the third major competitor until February 2009, when it ceased domestic delivery operations in the United States.

A variety of other [[:Category:Transportation companies of the United States|transportation companies in the United States]] move cargo around the country, but either have limited geographic scope for delivery points, or specialize in items too large to be mailed. Many of the thousands of [[courier]] companies focus on same-day delivery, for example, by [[bicycle messenger]].

===Alternative transmission methods===
The Post Office Department owned and operated the first public [[telegraph]] lines in the United States, starting in 1844 from Washington to Baltimore, and eventually extending to New York, Boston, Buffalo, and Philadelphia. In 1847 the telegraph system was privatized, except for a period during World War I, when it was used to accelerate the delivery of letters arriving at night.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_pdf/Telegraph.pdf Telegraph]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1942 and 1945 &quot;[[V-Mail]]&quot; (for &quot;Victory Mail&quot;) service was available for [[military mail]]. Letters were converted into [[microfilm]] and reprinted near the destination, to save room on transport vehicles for military cargo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_pdf/VMail.pdf V-Mail]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1982 to 1985 Electronic Computer Originated Mail was accepted for bulk mailings. Text was transmitted electronically to one of 25 post offices nationwide. The Postal Service would print the mail and put it in special envelopes bearing a blue ECOM logo. Delivery was assured within 2 days.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_pdf/ECOM.pdf ECOM]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Law enforcement agencies==
===Postal Inspection Service===
The [[United States Postal Inspection Service]] (USPIS) is one of the oldest [[law enforcement agencies]] in the U.S. Founded by [[Benjamin Franklin]], its mission is to protect the Postal Service, its employees, and its customers from crime and protect the nation's mail system from criminal misuse.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://www.usps.com/websites/depart/inspect/missmore.htm
|title= Who We Are
|accessdate=March 31, 2008
|work=USPS.com |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071223101540/http://www.usps.com/websites/depart/inspect/missmore.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = December 23, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Postal Inspectors enforce over 200 federal laws providing for the protection of mail in [[Criminal procedure|investigations of crimes]] that may adversely affect or fraudulently use the U.S. Mail, the postal system or postal employees.

The USPIS has the power to enforce the USPS monopoly by conducting search and seizure raids on entities they suspect of sending non-urgent mail through overnight delivery competitors. According to the [[American Enterprise Institute]], a private conservative [[think tank]], the USPIS raided [[Equifax]] offices in 1993 to ascertain if the mail they were sending through [[FedEx|Federal Express]] was truly &quot;extremely urgent.&quot; It was found that the mail was not, and Equifax was fined $30,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.aei.org/paper/17488|title= Opportunities for Anticompetitive Behavior in Postal Services|accessdate=August 11, 2009|last= Geddes|first= Rick|date= June 1, 2003|work=AEI Online|doi=|quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lastly, the PIS oversees the activities of the [[United_States_Postal_Inspection_Service#Postal_Police_Force|Postal Police Force]] who patrol in and around selected high-risk postal facilities in major metropolitan areas in the United States and its territories.

===Office of Inspector General===
The [[United States Postal Service Office of Inspector General]] (OIG) was authorized by law in 1996. Prior to the 1996 legislation, the Postal Inspection Service performed the duties of the OIG. The Inspector General, who is independent of postal management, is appointed by and reports directly to the nine [[List of positions filled by presidential appointment with Senate confirmation|presidentially-appointed]], [[United States Senate|Senate]]–[[Advice and consent|confirmed]] members of the [[Board of Governors of the United States Postal Service]].

The primary purpose of the OIG is to prevent, detect and report fraud, waste and program abuse, and promote efficiency in the operations of the Postal Service. The OIG has &quot;oversight&quot; responsibility for all activities of the Postal Inspection Service.

==Elements of addressing and preparing domestic mail==
All mailable articles (e.g., letters, flats, machinable parcels, irregular parcels, etc.) shipped within the United States must comply with an array of standards published in the USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM).&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/600_tab.htm Mailing Standards of the United States Postal Service Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – § 600: Basic Standards For All Mailing Services]. Pe.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Before addressing the mailpiece, one must first comply with the various mailability standards relating to attributes of the actual mailpiece such as: minimum/maximum dimensions&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/100_tab.htm USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – § 101: Physical Standards]. Pe.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; &amp; weight, acceptable mailing containers, proper mailpiece sealing/closure, utilization of various markings, and restrictions relating to various hazardous (e.g., explosives, flammables, etc.) &amp; restricted (e.g., cigarettes, smokeless tobacco, etc.) materials, as well as others articulated in § 601 of the DMM.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/601.htm USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – § 601: Mailability]. Pe.usps.com (August 20, 1912). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The USPS specifies the following key elements when preparing the face of a mailpiece:

# '''Proper Placement''': The Delivery Address should be left-justified and located roughly in the center of mailpiece's largest side. More precisely, on a letter-size piece, the recommended address placement is within the optical character reader (OCR) read area, which is a space on the address side of the mailpiece defined by these boundaries: Left – 1/2&amp;nbsp;inch (13&amp;nbsp;mm) from the left edge of the piece; Right – 1/2&amp;nbsp;inch (13&amp;nbsp;mm) from the right edge of the piece; Top – 2-3/4&amp;nbsp;inches (70&amp;nbsp;mm) from the bottom edge of the piece; Bottom – 5/8&amp;nbsp;inch (16&amp;nbsp;mm) from the bottom edge of the piece.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/102.htm#wp1034636 USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – Section 102.2.1: Exhibit 2.1 OCR Read Area]. Pe.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Preferred placement of a return address is in the upper left portion of the mailpiece—on the side of the piece bearing postage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/602.htm#wp1078946 USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – § 602.1.5: Elements of Addressing – Return Address]. Pe.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, postage (e.g., stamps, meter imprints, information-based indicia [IBI], etc.) is to be affixed in the upper right corner of the address side of the mail cover. It should be noted that any stamp/indicia partly concealed or otherwise obscured by an overlapping stamp/indicia may not be counted as valid postage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/604.htm#wp1156173 USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – Section 102.2.1: Exhibit 2.1 OCR Read Area]. Pe.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Delivery Address (party receiving mail)''': The mail piece must have the address of the intended recipient, visible and legible, only on the side of the mail piece bearing postage. Generally, the name of the addressee should be included above the [[address (geography)|address]] itself. A [[ZIP+4 code]] will facilitate delivery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm100/addressing.htm A Customer's Guide to Mailing]{{dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- Please note if there is any difference in a local versus international address for mailing, Thanks --&gt;
# '''Return Address (party sending mail)''': A return address tells the USPS where the sender wants the mail returned if it is undeliverable. Usage of a return address is required for most all postal services (e.g., all parcel services, Priority Mail, Express Mail, Periodicals in envelopes or wrappers, Insured Mail, Registered Mail, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.com/text/dmm300/602.htm#wp1078946 USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – § 602.1.5.3 Addressing—Required Use of Return Addresses]. Pe.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Postage Payment''': All mailpieces must include appropriate valid postage. Postage payment may be in the form of stamps, stamped stationery, precanceled stamps, postage meter imprints &amp; PC Postage products (&quot;Postage Evidencing Systems&quot;), or permit imprint (indicia).&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.gov/text/dmm300/604.htm USPS Domestic Mail Manual (DMM) – § 604 Postage Payment Methods]. Pe.usps.gov. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the U.S. Congress, among others, have [[franking|franking privilege]]s, which only require a signature.
Domestic first-class mail costs 44¢ for [[envelope]]s (29¢ for [[postcard|post cards]]) and upwards, depending on the weight and dimensions of the letter and the class.

Undeliverable mails that cannot be readily returned, including those without return addresses, are treated as [[dead mail]]s at a Mail Recovery Center in [[Atlanta, Georgia]] or [[Saint Paul, Minnesota]].
[[File:UseZipCode.JPG|thumb|right|Sticker promoting ZIP code use.]]
;The formatting of the address is as follows:
:Line 1: Name of recipient
:Line 2: Street address or [[P.O. Box]]
:Line 3: City State ([[ISO 3166-2:US|ISO 3166-2:US code]] or APO/FPO code) and ZIP+4 code

;Example:
:[[John Q. Public]]
:789 UNIVERSAL DR
:PORTLAND OR 97086-1234

The USPS maintains a list of proper abbreviations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/ncsc/lookups/usps_abbreviations.htm USPS list of abbreviations]. Usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
Commented out as dubious:
The city and state designations are a redundant safety measure used in the case that the printed ZIP code is illegible or ambiguously written. Since the ZIP code system is such that there is only one street of any name for any ZIP code (ex. there is only one Johnson Street in the 10036 ZIP area), it is possible to exclude the city and state from a mailing label and still have the package delivered, assuming the label is legible.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010|comment=False: Several times communities have requested (and sometimes been denied, and sometimes been given) separate ZIP Codes for the exact reason that there were duplicate streets in a ZIP Code, and had been for decades.}}
--&gt;

The formatting of a return address is identical. Though some [[style manual]]s do recommend using a comma between the city and state name when typesetting addresses in other contexts, for optimal automatic character recognition, the Post Office does not recommend this when addressing mail. The official recommendation is to use all upper case block letters with appropriate formats and abbreviations, and leave out all punctuation except for the [[hyphen]] in the ZIP+4 code. If the address is unusually formatted or illegible enough, it will require hand-processing, delaying that particular item. The USPS publishes the entirety of their postal addressing standards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.gov/text/pub28/welcome.htm USPS postal addressing standards]. Pe.usps.gov. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Customers can look up ZIP codes on usps.com, and purchase postage if they have an account.

==Paying postage==
The actual postage can be paid via:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/all/postagepayoptions/welcome.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Stamps purchased online, at a Post Office, from a stamp vending machine or &quot;Automated Postal Center&quot; which can also handle packages, or from a third party (such as a grocery store)
* [[Pre-cancelled stamps]] for bulk mailings&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/send/postagepermitimprintsandmeters/precancelledstamps.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Postal meter
* Prepaid envelope
* Shipping label purchased online and printed by the customer on standard paper (e.g. with [[Click-N-Ship]], or via a third-party such as [[Paypal]] or [[Amazon.com|Amazon shipping]])

All unused [[U.S. postage stamps]] issued since 1861 are still valid as postage at their indicated value. Stamps with no value shown or denominated by a letter are also still valid, although the value depends upon the particular stamp. For some stamps issued without a printed value, the current value is the original value. But some stamps beginning in 1988 or earlier, including &quot;Forever Stamps&quot; that were issued beginning in April 2007, and all 1st class mail 1st ounce stamps beginning 2011-01-21, the value is the current value of a 1st class mail 1st ounce stamps. (The USPS calls these &quot;Forever Stamps&quot;. The generic name is [[non-denominated postage]].)

Forever stamps are sold at the first-class mail postage rate at the time of purchase, but will always be valid for first-class mail (1 oz and under), no matter how rates rise in the future.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsmax.com/archives/articles/2007/3/19/190818.shtml Postal Rates Set to Go Up on May 14]. March 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/prices/ New Prices Coming May 12, 2008]. Usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Britain has had a similar stamp since 1989. However, one of the tenets of the [[Universal Postal Union]] is having a single flat rate to mail a letter anywhere in the world, which is true for Britain (since 1995), but not the U.S. The cost of mailing a {{convert|1|oz|abbr=on}} First-Class letter increased to 44 cents on May 11.

===Postage meters===
{{Main|Postage meter}}
A postage meter is a mechanical device used to create and apply physical evidence of postage (or franking) to mailed matter. Postage meters are regulated by a country's postal authority; for example, in the United States, the United States Postal Service specifies the rules for the creation, support, and use of postage meters. A postage meter imprints an amount of postage, functioning as a postage stamp, a cancellation and a dated postmark all in one. The meter stamp serves as proof of payment and eliminates the need for adhesive stamps.

===PC postage===
In addition to using standard stamps, postage can now be printed in the form of an electronic stamp, or e-stamp, from a personal computer using a system called [[Information Based Indicia]]. This online PC Postage method relies upon application software on the customer's computer contacting a postal security device at the office of the postal service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | first=Henk C. A. | last=van Tilborg | year=2005 | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of cryptography and security | title=Electronic Postage | publisher=Springer | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=m-9Zj-e-HDsC&amp;pg=PA177 | isbn=038723473X | accessdate=May 6, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Authorized providers of PC Postage are listed below (many others--such as Amazon--are secondary providers, which use one of the authorized providers to do the actual service):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Online Postage|url=http://www.usps.com/onlinepostage/welcome.htm|publisher=USPS|accessdate=September 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Click-N-Ship]] (USPS)
* [[eBay]]
* [[Dymo Endicia|Endicia]]
* [[Pitney Bowes]]
* [[Stamps.com]]

===Other electronic postage payment methods===
Electronic Verification System (eVS)&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.gov/text/dmm300/705.htm#wp1179335 Advanced Preparation and Special Postage Payment Systems – Manifest Mailing System – Electronic Verification System]. Pe.usps.gov. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; is the Postal Service's integrated mail management technology that centralizes payment processing and electronic postage reports. Part of an evolving suite of USPS electronic payment services called PostalOne!,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/memotomailers/2006/aug2006.htm USPS Memo To Mailers – August 2006 &quot;Making It E-Easy For High-Volume Shippers&quot;]{{dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; eVS allows mailers shipping large volumes of parcels through the Postal Service a way to circumvent use of hard-copy manifests, postage statements and drop-shipment verification forms. Instead, mailers can pay postage automatically through a centralized account and track payments online.

Beginning in August 2007, the Postal Service began requiring mailers shipping Parcel Select packages using a permit imprint to use eVS for manifesting their packages.

===Stamp copyright and reproduction===
All U.S. postage stamps issued under the former [[United States Post Office Department]] and other postage items that were released before 1978 are not subject to copyright, but stamp designs since 1978 are copyrighted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://shop.usps.com/webapp/wcs/stores/servlet/ContentUpload1View?status=i&amp;langId=-1&amp;storeId=10001&amp;catalogId=10152&amp;HTMLName=stampcollecting.html&amp;pagetitle=S_Collecting#asc8 |title=Stamp Collecting: What other stamp materials can I collect? |publisher=United States Postal Service |accessdate=December 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the creation of the United States Postal Service, the [[United States Copyright Office]] in section 206.02(b) of the [[Compendium II: Copyright Office Practices]] holds that &quot;Works of the U.S. Postal Service, as now constituted, are not considered U.S. Government works.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ipmall.info/hosted_resources/CopyrightCompendium/chapter_0200.asp |title=U.S Copyright Office Practices section 206.02(b) |publisher=[[United States Copyright Office]] |accessdate=August 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Here, the U.S. Copyright Office has clarified that works of the U.S. Postal Service, of the [[government of the District of Columbia]], or of the [[government of Puerto Rico]] are ''not'' &quot;works of the U.S. government&quot; and thus ''are'' subject to copyright. Thus, postal service holds copyright to such materials released since 1978 under Title 17 of the [[United States Code]]. Written permission is required for use of copyrighted postage stamp images, although under USPS rules, permission is &quot;generally&quot; not required for &quot;educational use&quot;, &quot;news reporting&quot; or &quot;philatelic advertising use,&quot; but users must cite USPS as the source of the image and include language such as &quot;© United States Postal Service. All rights reserved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usps.com/rightsandpermissions/fair-use-exceptions.htm|title=Rights and Permission Overview |accessdate=June 18, 2010 |publisher=United States Postal Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service level choices==
=== General domestic services ===
[[File:TyvekExpressMailEnvelope.jpg|thumb|[[Tyvek]] envelope for Express Mail]]
Domestic postage includes Monday through Saturday delivery (excepting federal holidays) to any address, Post Office Box, or general delivery Post Office in the United States, or any U.S. [[military mail]] destination.

The Post Office will not deliver packages heavier than 70&amp;nbsp;lb (31.8&amp;nbsp;kg) or if the two largest dimensions (length and width) are greater than 108&amp;nbsp;inches (274&amp;nbsp;cm) combined. Other carriers handle packages that do not meet these conditions. Mail sent at a level other than First-Class (such as Second Class or Third Class), will not be forwarded or returned to sender, unless an additional fee is paid; &quot;return service requested&quot; may need to appear on the outside of the item. Deliveries outside the [[contiguous United States]] may take longer.

As of April 2011, domestic postage levels for low-volume mailers include:

* [[Express Mail]] – &quot;Overnight Guaranteed&quot; to most locations&lt;ref name=&quot;usps_times&quot;&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view%28%29=c{12adaeb0-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Domestic Classes of Mail Estimated Delivery Time]. Faq.usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
** Sunday and holiday delivery available for additional charge
** $100 insurance included
** Tracking included
** Flat rate envelope available. Otherwise, [[variable pricing]] by weight, size, and ZIP code.
* Priority Mail – 2 or 3-day service (not guaranteed)&lt;ref name=&quot;usps_times&quot; /&gt;
** Flat rate envelope and boxes (various sizes) available. Otherwise, variable pricing by weight, size, and ZIP code.
* [[First class mail#First-class|First-Class Mail]]
** Fast service (2–3 days)&lt;ref name=&quot;usps_times&quot; /&gt; for letters and small packages
** Flat rate depending on size and weight
*** Postcards (5&quot; x 3.5&quot; x 0.007 to 6&quot; x 4.25&quot; x 0.016&quot; [127 x 89 x 0.18 to 152 x 108 x 0.4&amp;nbsp;mm]): 29¢
*** Letters (up to 11.5&quot; x 6.125&quot; x 0.25&quot;, 3.5 oz [292 x 156 x 6.4&amp;nbsp;mm, 100 g]): 44¢ + 20¢ each additional ounce
*** Large Envelope or Flat (up to 15&quot; x 12&quot; x 0.75&quot;, 13 oz [381 x 305 x 19&amp;nbsp;mm, 370 g]): 88¢ + 20¢ each add'l ounce (28 g). Must be rectangular, uniformly thick, and not too rigid.
*** Package/Parcel (Up to 108&quot; [274&amp;nbsp;cm] length + width, 13 oz [370 g]): $1.71 + 17¢ each add'l ounce (28 g) over 3 ounces (84 g)
* [[Parcel Post]]
** Slowest but cheapest service for packages – uses [[surface transport]]
** 2-9-day service to contiguous U.S., 4–14 days internal to AK/HI/territories, 3–6 weeks between mainland and outlying areas (travels by ship)&lt;ref name=&quot;usps_times&quot; /&gt;
** Variable pricing by weight and ZIP code
** Free forwarding if recipient has filed change-of-address form, or return if the item is undeliverable
* Media Mail (formerly &quot;Book Rate&quot;)
** Books and recorded media only
** No advertising
** Flat rate pricing by weight only
** Transit time similar to Parcel Post
** Cheaper than Parcel Post but only due to increased restrictions on package contents.
* Library Mail
** Similar to Media Mail, but cheaper and restricted to academic institutions, public libraries, museums, etc.

=== Bulk mail ===
{{See also|Bulk mail}}
[[File:USPS Dodge CV.JPG|thumb|USPS [[Dodge Caravan]] used for residential delivery in [[Omaha, Nebraska]]]]
Discounts are available for large volumes of mail. Depending on the postage level, certain conditions might be required or optional for an additional discount:
* Minimum number of pieces
* Weight limits
* Ability for the USPS to process by machine
* Addresses formatting standardized
* USPS-readable barcode
* Sorted by 3-digit ZIP code prefix, 5-digit ZIP code, ZIP+4, or 11-digit delivery point
* Delivered in trays, bundles, or pallets partitioned by destination
* Delivered directly to a regional Bulk Mail Center, destination SCF, or destination Post Office
* Certification of mailing list accuracy and freshness (e.g. correct ZIP codes, purging of stale addresses, processing of change-of-address notifications)

In addition to bulk discounts on Express, Priority, and First-Class Mail, the following postage levels are available for bulk mailers:

* Periodicals
* Standard Mail (A)
** Automation
** Enhanced Carrier Route
** Regular
* Standard Mail (B)
** Parcel Post
** Bound [[Printed matter|Printed Matter]] – Cheaper than Media Mail, for advertising catalogs, phone books, etc. up to 15&amp;nbsp;lb&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Postage Payment for Bound Printed Matter Limited to Permit Imprint | publisher=USPS | date =September 11, 2008 | url =http://pe.usps.com/Bound_Printed_Matter.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Special Standard Mail
** Library Mail
** [[Nonprofit]]

===Add-on services===
[[File:ASmallUnitedStatesPostalServiceTruckGuam.jpg|thumb|A [[Grumman LLV|Long Life Vehicle]] seen in [[Guam]].]]
Depending on the type of mail, additional services are available for an additional fee:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/all/insuranceandextraservices/welcome.htm?from=household&amp;page=insuranceandextras USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Certificate of Mailing – Proof of the date a package was mailed.
* Delivery Confirmation – Provides proof of delivery to sorting facilities, local post office and destination, but no signature is required.
* Signature Confirmation – Delivery requires a signature, which is kept on file. The online tracking system displays the first initial and last name of the signatory.
* Return Receipt – Actively sends Signature Confirmation information back to the sender by postcard or emailed PDF (as opposed to merely putting this information into the online tracking system).
* Insurance against loss or damage, for the value of the goods mailed. Amount of coverage can be specified, up to $5000.
* Certified Mail – Provides proof of mailing, and a delivery record. Used for serving legal documents and for sending [[Classified information in the United States|U.S. Government classified information]], up to the &quot;confidential&quot; level.
* Restricted Delivery – Requires delivery to a specific person or their authorized agent, not just to a mailbox.
* Collect On Delivery (C.O.D.) – Allows merchants to offer customers an option to pay upon delivery, up to $1000. Includes insurance.
* Special Handling – For unusual items, like live animals.
* Registered Mail – Used for highly valuable or irreplaceable items, and [[Classified information in the United States|classified information]] up to the &quot;secret&quot; level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo10501.htm Executive Order No. 10501]. Fas.org. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Registered mail is transported separately from other mail, in locked containers. Tracking is included and insurance up to $25,000 is available.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/send/waystosendmail/extraservices/registeredmailservice.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Postal money orders===
Postal [[money order]]s provide a safe alternative to sending [[cash]] through the mail, and are available in any amount up to $1000. Like a bank [[cheque|check]] money orders are cashable only by the recipient. Unlike a personal bank check, they are prepaid and therefore cannot be returned because of insufficient funds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/money/sendingmoney/moneyorders/welcome.htm Domestic Money Orders]. USPS (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Money orders are a declining business for the USPS, as companies like [[PayPal]], [[PaidByCash]] and others are offering electronic replacements.

From 1911 to 1966, the Postal Service also operated a savings program, not unlike a [[savings and loan association]] with the amount of the deposit limited.&lt;ref name=&quot;postal savings&quot;&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_pdf/PostalSavingsSystem.pdf USPS.com]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===International services===
In May 2007, the USPS restructured international service names to correspond with domestic shipping options. Formerly, USPS International services&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=International Delivery Options |url=http://www.usps.com/international/deliveryoptions.htm|publisher=USPS|accessdate=September 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; were categorized as Airmail (Letter Post), Economy (Surface) Parcel Post, Airmail Parcel Post, Global Priority, Global Express, and Global Express Guaranteed Mail. The former Airmail (Letter Post) is now First-Class Mail International,&lt;ref&gt;[http://pe.usps.gov/text/imm/immc2_019.htm USPS International Mail Manual, Issue 35]. Pe.usps.gov. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/international/airmailinternational.htm First-Class Mail International]. USPS (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and includes small packages weighing up to four pounds (1.8&amp;nbsp;kg). Economy Parcel Post was discontinued for international service, while Airmail Parcel Post was replaced by Priority Mail International. Priority Mail International Flat-Rate packaging in various sizes was introduced, with the same conditions of service previously used for Global Priority. Global Express is now Express Mail International, while Global Express Guaranteed is unchanged. The international mailing classes with a tracking ability are Express, Express Guaranteed, and Priority (except that tracking is not available for Priority Mail International Flat Rate Envelopes or Priority Mail International Small Flat Rate Boxes).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/shipping/trackandconfirm.htm USPS.com]. Retrieved November 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; One of the major changes in the new naming and services definitions is that USPS-supplied mailing boxes for Priority and Express mail are now allowed for international use. These services are offered to ship letters and packages to almost every country and territory on the globe. Ironically, the USPS provides much of this service by contracting with a private parcel service, [[FedEx]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/communications/news/press/2004/pr04_040.htm USPS press release, June 8, 2004, Release No. 40, FedEx to deliver premium postal int'l service]. Retrieved October 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 14, 2007, the USPS canceled all outgoing international [[surface mail]] (sometimes known as &quot;sea mail&quot;) from the United States, citing increased costs and reduced demand due to competition from airmail services such as FedEx and UPS.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/mailpro/2007/janfeb/page6.htm USPS International Mail – Frequently Asked Questions]. Retrieved October 10, 2007. {{Wayback | url=http://www.usps.com/mailpro/2007/janfeb/page6.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; | date=20070929150924 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The decision has been criticized by the Peace Corps and military personnel overseas, as well as independent booksellers and other small businesses who rely on international deliveries.

The USPS provides an '''{{visible anchor|M-bag}}'''&lt;ref&gt;Styling for &quot;M-bag&quot; is inconsistent – the term is styled both as ''M-bag'' (with a [[hyphen]]) and ''M–bag'' (with an [[en-dash]]).&lt;/ref&gt; service for international shipment of [[printed matter]];&lt;ref name=&quot;IMM260&quot;&gt;Postal Explorer &gt; IMM Issue 37 – International Mail Manual &gt; 2 Conditions for Mailing &gt; [http://pe.usps.com/text/imm/immc2_022.htm 260 Direct Sacks of Printed Matter to One Addressee (M–bags)]&lt;/ref&gt; previously surface M-bags existed, but with the 2007 elimination of surface mail, only airmail M-bags remain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/international/mbags.htm Airmail M-Bags]. Usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;M-bag&quot; is not expanded in USPS publications; M-bags are simply defined as &quot;direct sacks of printed matter ... sent to a single foreign addressee at a single address&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;IMM260&quot; /&gt; however, the term is sometimes referred to informally as &quot;media bag&quot;, as the bag can also contain &quot;discs, tapes, and cassettes&quot;, in addition to books, for which the usual umbrella term is &quot;media&quot;; some also refer to them as &quot;mail bags&quot;.

[[Military mail]] is billed at domestic rates when being sent from the United States to a military outpost, and is free when sent by deployed military personnel. The overseas logistics are handled by the [[Military Postal Service Agency]] in the Department of Defense.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?session={f63181e0-1fa8-11de-627c-000000000000}&amp;event=1&amp;view()=c{26b65060-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000}&amp;objectId=&amp;eksObjectId=&amp;objectType=Case&amp;isJumpEnabled=false&amp;isContentJumpEnabled=false&amp;vendorKey=&amp;objTitle=&amp;versionId=1921&amp;searchProperties=type:natural&amp;naturalAdvance=false&amp;allStr=&amp;phraseStr=&amp;anyStr=&amp;noneStr=&amp;keywordStr=&amp;tTitle=&amp;topicFromSub=&amp;topicsORSubUrl=&amp;report(0000)=p{e521dc60-6973-11dd-e6c4-000000000000}&amp;bcobjectId={e4ae5a10-6973-11dd-e6c4-000000000000}&amp;search=military&amp;topicAndSubtopic=Buying$ALL USPS FAQ – Mailing to military personnel]. Faq.usps.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Outside of forward areas and active operations, military mail First-Class takes 7–10 days, Priority 10–15 days, and Parcel Post about 24 days.&lt;ref name=&quot;usps_times&quot; /&gt;

===Airline and rail division===
The United States Postal Service does not directly own or operate any aircraft or trains. The mail and packages are flown on airlines with which the Postal Service has a contractual agreement. The contracts change periodically. Depending on the contract, aircraft may be painted with the USPS paint scheme.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}  Contract airlines have included: [[United Parcel Service|UPS]], [[Emery Worldwide]], [[Ryan International Airlines]], [[FedEx Express]], [[Rhoades Aviation]], [[American Airlines]], [[United Airlines]], and [[Express One International]]. The Postal Service also contracts with [[Amtrak]] to carry some mail between certain cities such as [[Chicago]] and [[Minneapolis – Saint Paul]].

The last air delivery route in the continental U.S., to residents in the [[Frank Church—River of No Return Wilderness]], was scheduled to be ended in June 2009. The weekly [[bush plane]] route, contracted out to an [[air taxi]] company, had in its final year an annual cost of $46,000, or $2400/year per residence, over ten times the average cost of delivering mail to a residence in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;idaho&quot;&gt;[http://www.idahostatesman.com/localnews/story/727644.html Air mail route grounded for Central Idaho backcountry], an April 2009 article from the ''[[Idaho Statesman]]''&lt;/ref&gt;  This decision has been reversed by the U.S. Postmaster General.&lt;ref&gt;[http://minnick.house.gov/2009/05/idaho-delegation-gets-reversal-on-backcountry-mail-delivery-decision.shtml Idaho delegation gets reversal on backcountry mail delivery decision], Senators Mike Crapo and Jim Risch and Representative Walt Minnick press release, May 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sorting and delivery process==
[[File:USPS mail flow through national infrastructure.svg|right|thumb|400px|Mail Flow through National Infrastructure]]

Processing of standard sized envelopes and cards is highly automated, including reading of handwritten addresses. Mail from individual customers and public postboxes is collected by mail carriers into plastic tubs. The tubs are taken to a '''Processing and Distribution Center''' (P&amp;DC).
There are approximately 275 such centers across the United States, which sort mail for a given region (typically a radius of around 200 miles) and connect with the national network for interregional mail.&lt;ref name=&quot;bard&quot;&gt;[http://www.allbusiness.com/marketing/direct-marketing-direct-mail/316648-1.html Allbusiness.com]. Allbusiness.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the P&amp;DC, mail is emptied into hampers which are then automatically dumped into a Dual Pass Rough Cull System (DPRCS). As mail travels through the DPRCS, large items, such as packages and mail bundles, are removed from the stream. As the remaining mail enters the first machine for processing standard mail, the [[Advanced Facer-Canceler System]] (AFCS), pieces that passed through the DPRCS but do not conform to physical dimensions for processing in the AFCS (i.e. large envelopes or overstuffed standard envelopes) are automatically diverted from the stream. Mail removed from the DPRCS and AFCS is manually processed or sent to parcel sorting machines.

In contrast to the previous system, which merely canceled and postmarked the upper right corner of the envelope, thereby missing any stamps which were inappropriately placed, the Advanced Facer-Canceler System locates [[indicia (philately)|indicia]] (stamp or metered [[postage]] mark), regardless of the orientation of the mail as it enters the machine, and cancels it by applying a [[postmark]]. Detection of indicia enables the AFCS to determine the orientation of each mailpiece and sort it accordingly, rotating pieces as necessary so all mail is sorted right-side up and faced in the same direction in each output bin. Mail is output by the machine into three categories: mail already affixed with a [[bar code]] and addressed (such as business reply envelopes and cards), mail with machine printed (typed) addresses, and mail with handwritten addresses. Additionally, machines with a recent [[Optical Character Recognition]] (OCR) upgrade have the capability to read the address information, including handwritten, and sort the mail based on local or outgoing ZIP codes.

Mail with typed addresses goes to a [[Multiline Optical Character Reader]] (MLOCR) which reads the ZIP Code and address information and prints the appropriate bar code onto the envelope. Mail (actually the scanned image of the mail) with handwritten addresses (and machine-printed ones that are not easily recognized) goes to the [[Remote Bar Coding System]]. It also corrects spelling errors and, where there is an error, omission, or conflict in the written address, identifies the most likely correct address. When it has decided on a correct address, it prints the appropriate bar code onto the envelopes, similarly to the MLOCR system. RBCS also has facilities in place, called [[Remote Encoding Center]]s, that have humans look at images of mail pieces and enter the address data. The address data is associated with the image via an ID Tag, a [[fluorescent]] [[Barcode]] printed by mail processing equipment on the back of mail pieces.

If a customer has filed a change of address card and his or her mail is detected in the mailstream with the old address, the mailpiece is sent to a machine that automatically connects to a Computerized Forwarding System database to determine the new address. If this address is found, the machine will paste a label over the former address with the current address. The mail is returned to the mailstream to forward to the new location.

Mail with addresses that cannot be resolved by the automated system are separated for human intervention. If a local postal worker can read the address, he or she manually sorts it out according to the ZIP code on the article. If the address cannot be read, mail is either returned to the sender (first-class mail with a valid return address) or is sent to the Mail Recovery Center in Atlanta, Georgia (formerly known as Dead Letter Offices, originated by Benjamin Franklin in the 1770s{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}) where it receives more intense scrutiny, including being opened to determine if any of the contents are a clue. If no valid address can be determined, the items are held for 90 days in case of inquiry by the customer; and if they are not claimed then they are either destroyed or auctioned off at the monthly Postal Service Unclaimed Parcel auction to raise money for the service.

Once the mail is bar coded, it is automatically sorted by a [[delivery bar code sorter|Delivery Bar Code System]] that reads the bar code and determines the destination of the mailpiece to postal stations.

Regional mail is trucked to the appropriate local post office or kept in the building for carrier routes served directly from the P&amp;DC. Out-of-region mail is trucked to the airport and then flown, usually as baggage on commercial airlines, to the airport nearest the destination station. At the destination P&amp;DC, mail is once again read by a [[delivery bar code sorter|DBCS]] which sorts the items into their local destinations, including grouping them by individual mail carrier.

At the carrier route level, 95% of letters arrive pre-sorted;&lt;ref name=&quot;bard&quot; /&gt; the remaining mail must be sorted by hand. The Post Office is working to increase the percentage of automatically sorted mail, including a pilot program to sort &quot;flats&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/strategicplanning/cs08/chpt4_pg46.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Types of postal facilities===
[[File:OldPostOfficeTomahWI.JPG|thumb|right|Historic main post office in [[Tomah, Wisconsin]].]]
[[File:LongPointStationHouston.JPG|thumb|A typical post office station in the [[Spring Branch, Houston|Spring Branch]] area of [[Houston]], Texas]]&lt;!--Used to show the new &quot;generic&quot; post offices--&gt;
[[File:Galveston Federal Building 2009.jpg|thumb|Combined [[Galveston United States Post Office and Courthouse|Post Office, Customs House, and Federal Court House]] in [[Galveston, Texas]].]]&lt;!--Photo used to show example of post offices that are tenants in other governmental buildings--&gt;
Although its customer service centers are called post offices in regular speech, the USPS recognizes several types of postal facilities, including the following:
* A '''main post office''' (formerly known as a '''general post office''') is the primary postal facility in a community.
* A '''station''' or '''post office station''', a postal facility that is not the main post office, but that is within the corporate limits of the community.
* A '''branch''' or '''post office branch''', a postal facility that is not the main post office and that is outside the corporate limits of the community.
* A '''classified unit''', a station or branch operated by USPS employees in a facility owned or leased by the USPS.
* A '''contract postal unit''' (or '''CPU'''), a station or branch operated by a contractor, typically in a store or other place of business.&lt;ref name=&quot;glossary&quot; /&gt;
* A '''community post office''' (or '''CPO'''), a contract postal unit providing services in a small community in which other types of post office facilities have been discontinued.
* A '''finance unit''', a station or branch that provides window services and accepts mail, but does not provide delivery.
* A '''processing and distribution center''' ('''P&amp;DC''', or '''processing and distribution facility''', formerly known as a '''General Mail Facility'''), a central mail facility that processes and dispatches incoming and outgoing mail to and from a designated service area. (275 nationwide.)&lt;ref name=&quot;bard&quot; /&gt;
* An '''international service center (ISC)''', an international mail processing facility. There are only five such USPS facilities in the United States, located in Chicago, New York, Miami, Los Angeles and San Francisco.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usps.com/communications/newsroom/2008/pr08_063.htm |title=USPS Postal News Release No. 08-063 |publisher=usps.com |date=June 5, 2008 |accessdate=September 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A '''[[sectional center facility (SCF)]]''', a P&amp;DC for a designated geographical area defined by one or more three-digit [[ZIP code]] prefixes.
* A '''network distribution center''', formerly known as a [[bulk mail]] center (BMC), a central mail facility that processes bulk rate parcels as the hub in a [[hub and spoke network]].
* An '''auxiliary sorting facility''' ('''ASF'''), a central mail facility that processes bulk rate parcels as spokes in a hub and spoke network.
* A '''remote encoding center''' ('''REC'''), a facility at which clerks receive images of problem mail pieces (those with hard-to-read addresses, etc.) via secure Internet-type feeds and manually type the addresses they can decipher, using a special encoding protocol. The mail pieces are then sprayed with the correct addresses or are sorted for further handling according to the instructions given via encoding. The total number of RECs is down from 55 in 1998 to just 5 centers in April 2009. In 2010, there will be just two remaining RECs open, in [[Salt Lake City]], [[Utah]] and [[Wichita, Kansas]]. More closures will occur as computer software becomes more able to read most addresses, but a few centers are expected to remain open (see '''Evolutionary Network Development''' below).
[[File:APC 77598 Webster Texas.jpg|thumb|left|upright|A 24-hour Automated Postal Center kiosk inside the [[Webster, Texas]] Main Post Office]]&lt;!--Used to show an example 24-hour &quot;APC&quot; kiosk--&gt;
* A '''village post office''' ('''VPO'''), a post office concept beginning in 2011, village post offices are an integral part of the USPS plan to close low volume post offices. Many of these will be replaced with village post offices that will fill the role of the post office within that zip code and be located in local business or government centers and operated by those entities as specified in the contract negotiated between the entity and USPS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://about.usps.com/news/electronic-press-kits/expandedaccess/assets/pdf/vpo-fact-sheet-110726.pdf |title=USPS VPO Fact Sheet |publisher=usps.com |date=July 26, 2011 |accessdate=November 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While common usage refers to all types of postal facilities as &quot;substations&quot;, the USPS Glossary of Postal Terms does not define or even list that word.&lt;ref name=&quot;glossary&quot;&gt;[http://www.usps.com/cpim/ftp/pubs/pub32.pdf Publication 32 – Glossary of Postal Terms]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Post Offices often share facilities with other governmental organizations located within a city's central business district. In those locations, often Courthouses and Federal Buildings, the building is owned by the [[General Services Administration]] while the U.S. Postal Services operates as a [[tenement (law)|tenant]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gsa.gov/Portal/gsa/ep/contentView.do?contentType=GSA_BASIC&amp;contentId=18257|work=General Services Administration|title=Texas Federal Buildings:Galveston U.S. Post Office and Courthouse|accessdate=December 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=[http://www.nr.nps.gov/nomination/01000438.pdf|work=National http://www.nr.nps.gov/nomination/01000438.pdf|work=National]{{NRIS dead link}} Park Service|title=National Register of Historic Places Registration Form|accessdate=December 20, 2009}}{{NRIS dead link}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are approximately 36,000 post offices, stations, and branches in the USPS retail system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/strategicplanning/cs08/chpt4_pg38.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Temporary stations are also set up for applying [[pictorial cancellation]]s.

====Automated Postal Centers====
In 2004 the USPS began deploying Automated Postal Centers '''(APC)'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lunewsviews.com/sspcplans.htm Lunewsviews.com]&lt;/ref&gt; APCs are unattended kiosks that are capable of weighing, [[franking]], and storing packages for later pickup as well as selling domestic and international postage stamps. Similarly, traditional [[vending machine]]s are available at many post offices to purchase stamps, though these are being phased out in many areas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/alternateaccess/selfserve.htm USPS.com]. USPS.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Due to increasing use of Internet services, as of June, 2009, no retail post office windows are open 24 hours; overnight services are limited to those provided by an Automated Postal Center.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=105040498 Chicago's 24-Hour Postal Service Comes To An End] by Cheryl Corley. ''All Things Considered'', National Public Radio. June 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

===Evolutionary Network Development (END) program===
In February 2006, the USPS announced that they plan to replace the nine existing facility-types with five processing facility-types:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lunewsviews.com/consolidations.htm Lunewsviews.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Regional Distribution Centers''' (RDCs), which will process all classes of parcels and bundles and serve as Surface Transfer Centers;
* '''Local Processing Centers''' (LPCs), which will process single-piece letters and flats and cancel mail;
* '''Destination Processing Centers''' (DPC), sort the mail for individual mail carriers;
* '''Airport Transfer Centers''' (ATCs), which will serve as transfer points only; and
* '''Remote Encoding Centers''' (RECs).

Over a period of years, these facilities are expected to replace Processing &amp; Distribution Centers, Customer Service Facilities, Bulk Mail Centers, Logistic and Distribution Centers, annexes, the Hub and Spoke Program, Air Mail Centers, and International Service Centers.

The changes are a result of the declining volumes of single-piece first-class mail, population shifts, the increase in drop shipments by advertising mailers at destinating postal facilities, advancements in equipment and technology, redundancies in the existing network, and the need for operational flexibility.

==Final delivery==
[[File:Usmailcontractor.jpg|thumb|USPS contractor-driven [[semi-trailer truck]] seen near [[Mendota, California]]]]
[[File:USPS Van.JPG|thumb|USPS [[Ford Windstar]] used for residential delivery in [[Olympia, Washington]]]]

===Delivery days===
Until 1912, mail was delivered seven days a week. As the postal service grew in popularity and usage in the 19th century, local religious leaders noticed a decline in Sunday-morning church attendance because of local post offices' doubling as gathering places. These leaders appealed to the government to intervene and close post offices on Sundays.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://atheism.about.com/b/a/242048.htm About.com, &quot;Sunday Mail Service in a Christian Nation&quot;, Austin Cline, February 19, 2006]. Retrieved October 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USPSHistory&quot;&gt;[http://www.usps.com/cpim/ftp/pubs/pub100.pdf &quot;The United States Postal Service: An American History 1775 – 2006&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of this intervention by the government, U.S. Mail (with the exception of Express Mail)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/serviceperformance/dayofmailing.htm USPS – Express Mail Delivery Chart]. Retrieved October 10, 2007. {{Wayback | url=http://www.usps.com/serviceperformance/dayofmailing.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; | date=20070929150736 }}&lt;/ref&gt; is not delivered on Sunday, except in a few towns in which the local religion has had an effect on the policy, such as [[Loma Linda, California]], which has a significant [[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventist]] population&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; and where U.S. Mail is delivered Sunday through Friday, with the exception of observed federal holidays.

Saturday delivery was temporarily suspended in April 1957, because of lack of funds, but quickly restored.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyorb.com/events/april/13 Historyorb.com], events April 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyorb.com/events/april/15 Historyorb.com], events April 15&lt;/ref&gt; On January 28, 2009, [[United States Postmaster General|Postmaster General]] [[John E. Potter]] testified before the Senate&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hsgac.senate.gov/public/_files/Potter.pdf|title=Postmaster General/CEO John E. Potter Before the Subcommittee on Federal Financial Management|accessdate=January 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; that, if the Postal Service could not readjust its payment toward the pre-funding of retiree health benefits, as mandated by the Postal Accountability &amp; Enhancement Act of 2006,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usps.com/postallaw/_pdf/PostalServiceNetworkPlan.pdf|title=Postal Accountability &amp; Enhancement Act of 2006|accessdate=February 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; the USPS would be forced to consider cutting delivery to five days per week during June, July, and August.

H.R. 22, addressing this issue, passed the House of Representatives and Senate and was signed into law on September 30, 2009. However, PMG Potter has continued to unveil a plan to eliminate Saturday mail delivery. The universal service obligation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usps.com/postallaw/universalpostalservice.htm|title=Report on Universal Postal Service and the Postal Monopoly|accessdate=February 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and six day delivery are upheld by Congressional language within Appropriations legislation, so a reduction in service would require action from the House and Senate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrlca.org/membershipUpdates/selectedMembershipUpdate.cfm/memUpID/124|title=NRLCA President Don Cantriel &amp; the entire National Board fully support 6-Day Delivery &amp; oppose 5-Day Delivery which could further erode the Postal Service's dwindling customer base|accessdate=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 10, 2009, the [[NRLCA]] was contacted for its input on the USPS's current study of the impact of five-day delivery along with developing an implementation plan for a five-day service plan. A team of postal service headquarters executives and staff has been given a time frame of sixty days to complete the study. The current concept examines the impact of five-day delivery with no business or collections on Saturday, with Post Offices with current Saturday hours remaining open.

Chairman [[José Enrique Serrano|José Serrano]] ([[Democratic Party (United States)|D]]–[[New York|NY]]), of the House Appropriations subcommittee on Financial Services and General Government, which oversees language mandating six day service, said &quot;While I understand the seriousness of the Postal Service's fiscal issues, I remain supportive of a six day delivery schedule. I will be in conversations in coming weeks with the senior postal leadership and the postal unions in an effort to avoid service cuts.&quot;

On Thursday, April 15, 2010, the House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform held a hearing to examine the status of the Postal Service and recent reports on short and long term strategies for the financial viability and stability of the USPS entitled &quot;Continuing to Deliver: An Examination of the Postal Service's Current Financial Crisis and its Future Viability.&quot; At which, PMG Potter testified that by the year 2020, the USPS cumulative losses could exceed $238&amp;nbsp;billion, and that mail volume could drop 15 percent from 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oversight.house.gov/images/stories/Hearings/Committee_on_Oversight/2010/041510_Postal_Service/TESTIMONY-Potter-USPS.pdf|title=Statement of Postmaster General/CEO John E. Potter Before the Committee on Governmant on Oversight &amp; Government Reform United States House of Representatives &amp; Subcommittee on Federal Workforce, Postal Service, and the District of Colombia|accessdate=April 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Direct delivery vs. customer pickup===
Originally, mail was not delivered to homes and businesses, but to post offices. In 1863, &quot;city delivery&quot; began in urban areas with enough customers to make this economical. This required streets to be named, houses to be numbered, with sidewalks and lighting provided, and these street addresses to be added to envelopes.&lt;ref name=&quot;city delivery&quot;&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_pdf/CityDelivery.pdf City Delivery]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The number of routes served expanded over time. In 1891, the first experiments with [[Rural Free Delivery]] began in less densely populated areas.

To compensate for high mail volume and slow long-distance transportation which saw mail arrive at post offices throughout the day, deliveries were made multiple times a day. This ranged from twice for residential areas to up to seven times for the central business district of [[Brooklyn]], New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;deliveries per day&quot;&gt;[http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_pdf/DeliveriesperDay.pdf Deliveries per Day]. (PDF) . Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the late 19th century, mail boxes were encouraged, saving carriers the time it took to deliver directly to the addressee in person; in the 1910s and 1920s, they were phased in as a requirement for service.&lt;ref name=&quot;city delivery&quot; /&gt;  In the 1940s, multiple daily deliveries began to be reduced, especially on Saturdays. By 1990, the last twice-daily deliveries in New York City were eliminated.

Today, mail is delivered once a day on-site to most private homes and businesses. The USPS still distinguishes between city delivery (where carriers generally walk and deliver to mailboxes hung on exterior walls or porches, or to commercial reception areas) and rural delivery (where carriers generally drive).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/receive/businesssolutions/cityruralandgeneraldelivery.htm?from=receiveyourmail&amp;page=homedelivery Home Delivery]. USPS (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  With &quot;curbside delivery&quot;, mailboxes are at the ends of driveways, on the nearest convenient road.  &quot;Central point delivery&quot; is used in some locations, where several nearby residences share a &quot;cluster&quot; of individual mailboxes in a single housing.

Some customers choose to use [[post office box]]es for an additional fee, for privacy or convenience. This provides a locked box at the post office to which mail is addressed and delivered (usually earlier in the day than home delivery). Customers in less densely populated areas where there is no city delivery and who do not qualify for rural delivery may only receive mail through post office boxes. High-volume business customers can also arrange for special pick-up.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view()=c{15ca7f10-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Caller Service], multiple pickups for a fee&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view()=c{1624ad00-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Firm Holdout Service], free pickup once a day&lt;/ref&gt;

Another option is the old-style [[general delivery]], for people who have neither post office boxes nor street addresses. Mail is held at the post office until they present identification and pick it up.

Some customers receive free post office boxes if the USPS declines to provide door-to-door delivery to their location or a nearby box.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view()=c{0d389670-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Do I qualify for free box service?]. Faq.usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  People with medical problems can request door-to-door delivery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view()=c{03a36ea0-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Hardship / Medical Problems]. Faq.usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Homeless]] people are also eligible for post office boxes at the discretion of the local postmaster, or can use general delivery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view()=c{0a4e47c0-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Mail service available for the homeless]. Faq.usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Special delivery===
From 1885 to 1997, a service called [[special delivery (postal service)|special delivery]] was available, which caused a separate delivery to the final location earlier in the day than the usual daily rounds.

===Forwarding and holds===
Residential customers can fill out a form to forward mail to a new address, and can also send pre-printed forms to any of their frequent correspondents. They can also put their mail on &quot;hold&quot;, for example, while on vacation. The Post Office will store mail during the hold, instead of letting it overflow in the mailbox. These services are not available to large buildings and customers of a [[commercial mail receiving agency]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?create=kb:USPSFAQ&amp;view()=c{11d2df10-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000} USPS FAQ – Commercial Mail Receiving Agency (CMRA)]. Faq.usps.com (November 26, 2008). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; where mail is subsorted by non-Post Office employees into individual mailboxes.

==Employment in the USPS==
[[File:RLC.jpg|thumb|A Rural Letter Carrier from [[Fort Myers, Florida]]]]
The Postal Service is the nation's second-largest civilian employer, after Wal-Mart.&lt;ref name=&quot;Postal Facts 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Postal Facts 2011| publisher=U.S. Postal Service | year = 2011| url = http://about.usps.com/who-we-are/postal-facts/welcome.htm|accessdate =August 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{As of|2011}}, it employed 574,000 personnel, divided into offices, processing centers, and actual post offices.

[[trade union|Labor unions]] representing USPS employees include the [[National Association of Letter Carriers]] (NALC), which represents city letter carriers, the [[National Rural Letter Carriers' Association]] (NRLCA), which represents rural letter carriers, the [[National Postal Mail Handlers Union]] (NPMHU), which represents mail handlers, and the [[American Postal Workers Union]] (APWU), which represents clerks, maintenance employees, and motor vehicle service workers. While union membership is voluntary, city carriers are organized near 90% nationally.

USPS employees are divided into three&lt;!-- ?! --&gt; major crafts according to the work they engage in:
*'''[[Mail carrier]]s''', also referred to as mailmen or letter carriers, prepare and deliver mail and parcels.  They are divided into two categories: '''City Letter Carriers''', who are represented by the NALC, and '''[[Rural Letter Carrier]]s''', who are represented by the NRLCA. City carriers are paid hourly with the potential for overtime. City Carriers are also subject to &quot;undertime&quot; on a daily basis{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}. &quot;Pivoting&quot; is when a Carrier's assigned route will take less than 8 hours to complete.  Management may &quot;pivot&quot; the Carrier to work on another route to fill that Carrier up to 8 hours.  Pivoting is a tool postal management uses to redistribute and eliminate overtime costs, based on consultation with the Carrier about his/her estimated workload for the day and mail volume projections from the DOIS (Delivery Operations Information System) computer program. City Carrier routes are adjusted and/ or eliminated based on information (length, time, and overall workload) also controlled by this program, consultations with the Carrier assigned to the route, and a current PS Form 3999 (street observation by a Postal supervisor to determine accurate times spent on actual delivery of mail).
*'''Rural carriers''' are under a form of salary called &quot;evaluated hours&quot;, usually with overtime built in to their pay. The evaluated hours are created by having all mail counted for a period of two or four weeks, and a formula used to create the set dollar amount they will be paid for each day worked until the next time the route is counted.
*'''Mail handlers and processors''', prepare mail and parcels, by delivery route, for the mail carrier.
*'''Clerks''', who directly handle customer needs and sort standard and bulk-rate mail. Data Conversion Operators, who encode address information at Remote Encoding Centers, are also members of the clerk craft.

Other non-managerial positions in the USPS include:
* '''Maintenance and custodians''', who see to the overall operation and cleaning of mail sorting machines, work areas, public parking and general facility operations.
* '''Transitional employees''' (TEs), who are hired for terms of 360 days (with the option of appointment to another 360 day term after a 5 day break), are given the same hourly base pay as a Part Time Flexible carrier, but receive no benefits other than annual leave. Transitional employees may be released by the USPS upon completion of their 360 day term, lack of work, or for &quot;just cause&quot; and can be represented by the NALC.
* '''Career, Part Time Flexible and Transitional employees''' (Career, PTF &amp; TE DCOs) at a remote encoding center are still under clerks category but under a different contract than a plant worker or mail carrier and, therefore, are also under a different union (APWU) than the above mentioned Career, TEs and PTFs. There are several differences between working as a carrier or plant worker VS. working at a REC. Even pay is different.

Though the USPS employs many individuals, as more Americans send information via email, fewer postal workers are needed to work dwindling amounts of mail. Post offices and mail facilities are constantly downsizing, replacing craft positions with new machines and consolidating mail routes through the MIARAP (Modified Interim Alternate Route Adjustment Process) agreement. A major round of job cuts, early retirements, and a construction freeze were announced on March 20, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/US/03/20/post.office.cuts/index.html |publisher=CNN | title=Postal service to slash more than 3,000 jobs, offer early retirements | date=March 20, 2009 | accessdate=May 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Violence as &quot;going postal&quot;==
In the early 1990s, widely publicized workplace shootings by disgruntled employees at USPS facilities led to a postal regulation that prohibits the possession of firearms in all postal facilities. Due to media coverage, postal employees gained a reputation among the general public as more likely to be [[Mental disorder|mentally ill]]. The USPS Commission on a Safe and Secure Workplace found that &quot;Postal workers are only a third as likely as those in the national workforce to be victims of homicide at work.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usps.com/communications/news/press/2006/pr06_0131commission.htm USPS Commission on a Safe and Secure Workplace, January 31, 2006]. Retrieved October 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

This stereotype in turn has influenced American culture, as seen in the slang term &quot;[[going postal]]&quot; (see [[Patrick Sherrill]] for information on his August 20, 1986, rampage) and the computer game ''[[Postal (video game)|Postal]]''. Also, in the opening sequence of ''[[Naked Gun 33⅓: The Final Insult]]'', a yell of &quot;Disgruntled postal workers&quot; is heard, followed by the arrival of postal workers with machine guns. In an episode of ''[[Seinfeld]]'', the character [[Newman (Seinfeld)|Newman]], who is a mailman, explained in a dramatic monologue that postal workers &quot;go crazy and kill everyone&quot; because the mail never stops. In ''The Simpsons'' episode ''[[Sunday, Cruddy Sunday]]'', [[Nelson Muntz]] asks Postmaster Bill if he has &quot;ever gone on a killing spree&quot;, with a reply of, &quot;The day of the disgruntled postman went out with the [[Macarena (song)|Macarena]]&quot;.

==In fiction==
* In the 1947 film ''[[Miracle on 34th Street]]'', the identity of Kris Kringle (played by [[Edmund Gwenn]]) as the one and only &quot;Santa Claus&quot; was validated by a state court, based on the delivery of 21 bags of mail (famously carried into the courtroom) to the character in question. The contention was that it would have been illegal for the United States Post Office to deliver mail that was addressed to &quot;Santa Claus&quot; to the character &quot;Kris Kringle&quot; unless he was, in fact, the one and only Santa Claus. Judge Henry X. Harper (played by [[Gene Lockhart]]) ruled that since the US Government had demonstrated through the delivery of the bags of mail that Kris Kringle was Santa Claus, the State of New York did not have the authority to overrule that decision.
* In the TV series ''[[Seinfeld]]'', [[Newman (Seinfeld)|Newman]] is an employee at the USPS, which is portrayed in the series as a powerful, nefarious organization. He claims that [[ZIP code]]s are meaningless;{{episode|date=June 2011}} no mail carrier has successfully delivered more than 50% of their mail (a feat he compares to the 3-minute mile);{{episode|date=June 2011}} and that several postal workers go on killing sprees because, as he puts it, &quot;the mail never stops&quot;.{{episode|date=June 2011}} In one episode, [[Cosmo Kramer]] is abducted by Post Office security men for running an anti-mail campaign after he realizes the Postal Service has become obsolete.{{episode|date=June 2011}}
* The TV series ''[[Cheers]]'' featured [[John Ratzenberger]] as [[Cliff Clavin]], a USPS worker and a regular in the bar. Ratzenberger, along with the rest of the show's cast, appears in an induction video for U.S. Postal Services staff.{{fact|date=June 2011}}

==See also==
{{Portal box|Government of the United States|Philately}}
* [[Administrative law judge]]
* [[American Letter Mail Company]]
* [[Canada Post]]
* [[History of United States postage rates]]
* [[Indian Post]] – Indian Postal Service
* [[Philately]] – stamp collecting
* [[Royal Mail]] – United Kingdom Postal Service
* [[Section of Painting and Sculpture]] – WPA post-office murals
* [[U.S. Postal Exams]]
* [[Trade union|Union]]s of the U.S. Postal Service:
** [[American Postal Workers Union]]
** [[National Association of Letter Carriers]]
** [[National Postal Mail Handlers Union]]
** [[National Rural Letter Carriers' Association]]

* [[United States postal abbreviations]]
* [[United States Postal Service creed]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{PDFlink|[http://www.usps.com/cpim/ftp/pubs/pub542.pdf Understanding the Private Express Statutes]|146&amp;nbsp;KB}} USPS Publication 542 (June 1998)
* [http://www.uniformsmag.com/issues/0907/feat2.htm USPS Employee Uniform Program] – feature article at ''Uniforms'' magazine, September 2007{{Dead link|date=September 2010}}
* [http://www.lysanderspooner.org/STAMP2.htm ''&quot;Father of 3-cent Stamp&quot; Spooner fought Post Office''] Account of Lysander Spooner's fight against USPS monopoly
* [http://www.lysanderspooner.org/PrivateMail.htm ''The Unconstitutionality of the Laws of Congress Prohibiting Private Mails''] by [[Lysander Spooner]]
* [http://flag.blackened.net/daver/anarchism/tucker/tucker38.html ''The Post Office and Private Mail Service''] 19th century [[American individualist anarchist]] [[Benjamin Tucker]] opposes USPS monopoly
* [http://www.cato.org/dailys/12-07-99.html ''America's Post Office Challenges The Digital Age''] An argument in support of ending the government monopoly
* [http://www.fee.org/publications/the-freeman/article.asp?aid=3976 ''Time for the Mail Monopoly to Go'']
* [http://www.cato.org/testimony/ct-eh043096.html Postal Service Privatization] Dr. Edward L. Hudgins, of the Cato Institute, speaks to Appropriations Subcommittee on Treasury, Postal Service, and General Government
* [http://thefederalregister.com/b.p/department/POSTAL_SERVICE/ Postal Service Meeting Notices and Rule Changes] from The Federal Register [http://thefederalregister.com/rss/department/POSTAL_SERVICE/ RSS Feed]

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*{{official website|http://www.usps.com|mobile=http://mobile.usps.com/iphone/}}
*[http://www.prioritymail.com/ USPS Priority Mail] official website
*{{PDFlink|[http://www.usps.com/cpim/ftp/pubs/pub32.pdf USPS Glossary of Postal Terms (Publication 32)]|519&amp;nbsp;KB}}
*[http://postalinspectors.uspis.gov/ U.S. Postal Inspection Service] official website
*[http://www.uspsoig.gov/ USPS Office of the Inspector General] official website
*[http://www.prc.gov/ Postal Regulatory Commission] official website
*[http://www.uspsvideo.com U.S. Postal Service Media Center]
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=%22postal+service%22&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form US Postal Service] [[Congressional Research Service]] Reports
*{{YouTube|8aF6LhrafR0&amp;feature=channel|An Examination of the USPS Delivery Route Adjustments Panel 3}}

{{Postal administrations of North America}}
&lt;!-- major reorg not establishment--&gt;

[[Category:United States Postal Service| ]]
[[Category:Independent agencies of the United States government|Postal Service]]
[[Category:Postal organisations]]
[[Category:Communications in the United States]]
[[Category:1775 establishments]]
[[Category:1971 establishments]]

[[ast:United States Postal Service]]
[[ca:United States Postal Service]]
[[da:United States Postal Service]]
[[de:United States Postal Service]]
[[es:Servicio Postal de los Estados Unidos]]
[[fa:خدمات پستی ایالات متحده آمریکا]]
[[fr:United States Postal Service]]
[[ga:United States Postal Service]]
[[gl:Servizo Postal dos Estados Unidos]]
[[ko:미국 우편 공사]]
[[it:United States Postal Service]]
[[ro:United States Postal Service]]
[[nl:United States Postal Service]]
[[ja:アメリカ合衆国郵便公社]]
[[no:United States Postal Service]]
[[pl:United States Postal Service]]
[[pt:United States Postal Service]]
[[ro:United States Postal Service]]
[[ru:Почтовая служба США]]
[[simple:United States Postal Service]]
[[fi:Yhdysvaltain postilaitos]]
[[sv:United States Postal Service]]
[[tr:United States Postal Service]]
[[zh:美國郵政署]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
