<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5072040" ns="0" title="ImageShack"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Website
| name = ImageShack
| logo = [[Image:Imageshack.png|center|ImageShack Logo]]
| screenshot =
| caption = ImageShack Frontpage
| url = [http://www.imageshack.us ImageShack.us]
| commercial = Yes
| type = [[image hosting service|Image Hosting Service]]
| registration = Optional
| owner = ImageShack Corp.
| author = Alexander Levin
| language = English
| launch date = November 2003
| current status = Active
| revenue =
| alexa = {{decrease}} 135 ({{as of|2011|11|2|alt=November 2011}})&lt;ref name=&quot;alexa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/ImageShack.us |title= Imageshack.us Site Info | publisher= [[Alexa Internet]] |accessdate= 2011-11-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Updated monthly by OKBot.--&gt;
}}

'''ImageShack''' is a free [[image hosting service|image hosting]] website. ImageShack has a subscription service but the majority of its revenue is produced from advertising related to its free image hosting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mashable.com/2006/12/18/divshare-launches-imageshack-wannae-imageshack-launches-profiles/ |title=DivShare Launches ImageShack Wannabe, ImageShack Launches Profiles |accessdate=2007-02-27 |publisher=[[Mashable]].com}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The imageshack.us [[Alexa Internet|Alexa]] ranking in September 25, 2007 was one of the top 40, but now as of September 25, 2011 it's dropped to 135.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/imageshack.us |title=Related info for: imageshack.us |accessdate=2007-09-25 |publisher=Alexa}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[Nielsen ratings|Nielsen//NetRatings]], ImageShack was the fourth fastest growing web brand in July 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imediaconnection.com/news/10801.asp |title=MySpace Tops List of Hottest Sites |accessdate=2007-02-27 |publisher=I Media Connection}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Image hosting==

The site debuted in November 2003 and has since grown greatly in popularity. The main page has a file selection field, where the user may select the image file to upload. The [[image file format]] must be either [[JPEG]] (JPG), [[Portable Network Graphics|PNG]], [[GIF]], [[Tagged Image File Format|TIFF]] (TIF), [[Windows bitmap|BMP]], and the file must be smaller than or equal to 5 megabytes. Uploaded BMP and TIFF (TIF) images are automatically converted to PNG format.

After the file is uploaded, the user is redirected to a page containing different versions of [[Uniform Resource Locator|URL]]s to the uploaded image. These URLs are preformatted in a variety of [[HTML]] and [[BBCode|Bulletin Board code]] snippets, which can be used to hotlink them on websites and message boards. These URLs are not listed publicly, therefore only the user and the people to whom the user shares the URL can know the file location.  In mid-2008, Imageshack began 'hiding' the direct link to images, in an attempt to reduce the number of directly-linked images, as they provide no advertising revenue. After receiving feedback from users Imageshack discontinued 'hiding' the direct links and placed them on the top of the page. However, it now claims&lt;ref name=&quot;imageshack.us&quot;&gt;http://imageshack.us/content.php?page=faq&lt;/ref&gt; you must register to see the direct link (viewing the image directly or reading the url from the source code also works).

Images are stored on ImageShack indefinitely unless the image or the user who uploaded it abuses the [[Terms of Service]]. The image will be rendered inaccessible if the image uses over 200 megabytes of bandwidth in a one-hour period. If the image in question is not accessed a single time in one year, they will remove it.&lt;ref name=&quot;imageshack.us&quot;/&gt;

There is also a free registration service that gives the user the ability to see and delete their previously uploaded images.

In May 2006 it was reported that ImageShack serves 100,000 concurrent user requests during peak operation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.biosmagazine.co.uk/article.php?id=3421 |title=ImageShack Simplifies Image Sharing |accessdate=2007-02-27 |publisher=Bios Magazine}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ImageShack also provides a standalone [[open-source]] application for users to upload images and videos. The ImageShack uploader is available for Windows, Mac, and Linux.

==yfrog==
{{Main|yfrog}}
Yfrog is a service run by ImageShack that is designed specifically for uploading photographs and videos to [[Twitter]]. It was launched in February 2009, and allows uploads via [[email]] or a website interface.&lt;ref name = &quot;launch&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/02/19/AR2009021900369.html|title=ImageShack Launches Mediocre TwitPic Alternative|author=Wauters, Robin |date=February 18, 2009 |work=[[The Washington Post]] |publisher=|accessdate=June 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hack by Anti-Sec==
[[File:Anti-sec manifesto.png|thumb|256px|The [[Antisec Movement]]'s manifesto which had replaced a number of pictures hosted by ImageShack]]
On July 10, 2009, at 7:34pm PST, ImageShack's services were compromised by the [[Antisec Movement]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://it.slashdot.org/story/09/07/11/1430249/ImageShack-Hacked-Security-Groups-Threatened|title=Slashdot IT Story &amp;#124; ImageShack Hacked, Security Groups Threatened|accessdate=2009-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; a group with the goal of eradicating the publication of security exploits. The group had gained control of the way images were being displayed, and as a result some images hosted by ImageShack were temporarily [[redirected]] to an image detailing the manifesto of the movement. The message adds that “no images were harmed in the making of this … image”, implying that ImageShack images were not lost. Normal functionality was restored less than two hours later, and ImageShack asserted that no user data or content had been damaged or lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://toolbar.imageshack.us/blog/imageshack/?p=83|title=Your media is secure|accessdate=2009-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Photo sharing]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://imageshack.us/ ImageShack website]
* [http://news.imageshack.us/blog/ ImageShack - Blog]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Imageshack}}
[[Category:Image hosting]]
[[Category:Internet properties established in 2003]]

[[ar:إيميج شاك]]
[[ca:ImageShack]]
[[de:ImageShack]]
[[es:ImageShack]]
[[fr:ImageShack]]
[[it:ImageShack]]
[[nl:ImageShack]]
[[ja:ImageShack]]
[[pl:ImageShack]]
[[pt:ImageShack]]
[[ru:ImageShack]]
[[tr:ImageShack]]
[[uk:Imageshack]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
