<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="509227" ns="0" title="Bentley University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|news release = August 2011|refimprove = August 2011}}
{{coord|42.387633|-71.22061|display=title}}

{{Infobox university
|name=Bentley University
[[File:Bentleyuniversityseal.png]]

|Established=1917
|Type=[[Private university|Private]]
|endowment=[[United States dollar|U.S. $]]158 [[1000000 (number)|million]]&lt;ref&gt;National Association of College and University Business Officers, [http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf &quot;2009 Public Tables Endowment Market Values&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|president=[[Gloria Cordes Larson]]
|faculty=484
|undergrad=4,269
|postgrad=1,405
|doctoral=40
|campus=[[Suburban]], 163 acres
|free_label= Athletics
|free= 23 varsity teams
|nickname=Falcons
|colors=[[Blue]] and [[Gold]]
|mascot= Flex the Falcon
|website=[http://www.bentley.edu/ www.bentley.edu]
|city=[[Waltham, Massachusetts|Waltham]]
|state=[[Massachusetts|MA]]
|country=[[United States|USA]]
}}

'''Bentley University''' is a private co-educational university in [[Waltham, Massachusetts|Waltham]], [[Massachusetts]], {{convert|10|mi|km}} west of [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]]. Founded in 1917 as a school of accounting and finance in Boston's [[Back Bay, Boston|Back Bay]] neighborhood, Bentley moved to Waltham in 1968. In late 2010, Bentley University was ranked one of the top 20 undergraduate business schools by Business Week and was ranked #6 in Best Career/Job Placement Services by Princeton Review.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/interactive_reports/bschools_undergraduate_10rankings.html |title=Top Undergraduate Business Programs 2010 - Business Week |publisher= BLOOMBERG L.P.  |accessdate=2011-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a business university, Bentley University's mission is to create new knowledge within and across business and the arts and sciences and to educate creative, ethical, and socially responsible organizational leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://about.bentley.edu/mission-statement |title=Mission Statement &amp;#124; Bentley University |publisher=About.bentley.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bentley University provides a focused undergraduate business curriculum with bachelor of science degrees in 11 business fields and bachelor of arts degrees in six arts and sciences disciplines. The graduate school emphasizes the impact of technology on business practice and offers PhD programs in Business and Accountancy, the Bentley MBA with 16 areas of concentration, an integrated MS+MBA, seven Master of Science degrees, and custom executive education programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://about.bentley.edu/facts-about-bentley |title=Facts About Bentley &amp;#124; Bentley University |publisher=About.bentley.edu |date=2008-10-02 |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

Bentley University was founded in 1917 as the Bentley School of Accounting and Finance by Harry C. Bentley who served as the school’s president until 1953. In 1961, the college was accredited to confer four-year Bachelor of Science degrees under President Morison, who moved the college from its Boylston Street address in Boston to its current day location in Waltham, Massachusetts. Gregory H. Adamian, a major driving force in the college's development, became the fourth president in 1970. Under his guidance, the college became accredited to confer four-year Bachelor of Arts degrees in 1971 and graduate degrees in 1973. During this time, the school also changed its name to Bentley College. In the late 1990s, Bentley College became a pioneer{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} of incorporating information technology into its core business curriculum. In 2002, Bentley College opened up a campus in the Middle Eastern country of [[Bahrain]] in partnership with the Bahrain Institute of Banking and Finance. The college was accredited to confer its first doctoral degrees in the fields of business and accountancy in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/news-events/pr_view.cfm?id=2163 |title=We're sorry, but we can not find the page you're looking for. &amp;#124; Bentley University Newsroom |publisher=Bentley.edu |date=2011-02-24 |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=August 2011}} A main fixture of the campus, The Bentley Library, underwent a sweeping renovation in 2006 during which time the school's logo was changed to showcase the clock tower that sits atop the building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/news-events/pr_view.cfm?id=2258 |title=We're sorry, but we can not find the page you're looking for. &amp;#124; Bentley University Newsroom |publisher=Bentley.edu |date=2011-02-24 |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=August 2011}} One year later, [[Gloria Cordes Larson]], a former state and federal government official and Boston-based lawyer became the first female president of Bentley College. In 2008, the school changed its name to Bentley University after being authorized by the state board of higher education to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/university/ |title=university : Bentley |publisher=Bentley.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=August 2011}}

==Mobile Computing Program==
All entering students receive a new notebook computer during their First Week sessions that familiarizes them with the computing resources available on campus. Students keep this computer until the beginning of their third year of study when they may exchange it for a new model.  The Mobile Computing Program is mandatory, helping Bentley maintain hardware and software uniformity among all students and faculty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/ugcatalogue/resources/mobile_computing_program.cfm |title=Mobile Computing Program : Bentley |publisher=Bentley.edu |date=2011-02-24 |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tomorrow25==
Launched in 2005 to identify exemplary leaders of the future, the Tomorrow25 program honors 25 outstanding high school juniors with a series of special events on the Bentley campus. The winners receive national recognition and interact with high-profile business leaders at the annual Bentley Leadership Forum in cooperation with [[TIME magazine]]. The Tomorrow25 students also appear in an ad in [[TIME magazine]] as part of Bentley’s national recruitment campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tomorrow25.bentley.edu/home |title=Tomorrow 25: Bentley University honors outstanding high school juniors |publisher=Tomorrow25.bentley.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Hughey Center for Financial Services (HCFS)==
The Hughey Center for Financial Services (HCFS) named in honor of Bentley College alumnus David A. Hughey ’55 (retired executive vice president of Dean Witter Inter-capital), was established in 1997. The HCFS has earned a national reputation{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} and has been featured on CNBC.

The mission of the center is to extend the educational goals of Bentley University through innovative classroom pedagogy, cutting-edge financial research, and real-world applications.

The mission is translated into three broad strategies:
* To integrate the Trading Room into the graduate and undergraduate curricula in an effort to enhance student learning, professional development, and success
* To create a positive, collegial, and collaborative environment that is supportive of faculty and student research activities
* To strengthen external relations with the investment management community

The center is dedicated to providing world-class education through the integration of the multi-million-dollar Trading Room. Supporting more than 40 graduate and undergraduate courses and providing faculty, students, and staff to an unrivaled{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} collection of financial technologies valued at more than $3.5 million in annual licensing fees, the Hughey Center serves as a model{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} for other colleges and universities around the globe.

==The Center for Business Ethics (CBE)==
The Center for Business Ethics is one of the world’s leading{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} research and educational institutes in the field of business ethics. It is also among the oldest, having been established in 1976, when the field was in its infancy.

CBE is guided by its mission to promote integrity and trust in business by encouraging the establishment of ethical cultures in businesses everywhere. The center staff pursues this through the application of expertise, research, education and a collaborative approach to the dissemination of best practices.

For over three decades, CBE has demonstrated unsurpassed leadership in advancing knowledge, stimulating public discourse and fostering an appreciation for the importance of business ethics among a global network of executives, ethics and compliance professionals, academics, researchers and students of business.

==Campus==
In 1968, Bentley moved from downtown Boston to Waltham, Massachusetts, to accommodate an increasing number of students. The first buildings on the Waltham campus were built between 1965 and 1968. Today, the campus stretches across {{convert|163|acre|km2}} of land.

Bentley University's campus is divided into three parts: Upper Campus, Lower Campus and North Campus.

===Upper Campus===

Upper Campus contains most of the school's academic buildings and all of its classrooms. It is located on the North side of Beaver Street. Below is a list of the major buildings found on Upper Campus.

====Non-Residence Hall Buildings====
* Bentley Library: opened 1968
[[Image:Bentley College Library.jpg|thumb|right|175px|Bentley Library]]
* Jennison Hall: opened 1968
* LaCava Campus Center: opened 1968
* Morison Hall: opened 1968
* Lindsay Hall: home of the Koumantzelis Auditorium; opened 1969
* Adamian Academic Center: opened 1983
* President's House: opened 1983
* Rauch Administration Center: opened 1986
* Smith Academic Technology Center: opened 2000
* Student Center: opened 2002

====Residence Halls====
* Tree Dorms (Alder, Birch, Cedar, Elm, Maple, Oak, Spruce): opened 1968
* Boylston Apartments (A and B): opened 1972
* Rhodes Apartments: opened 1973
* Kresge Hall: opened 1975
* Forest Hall: opened 1976
* Slade Hall: opened 1977
* Miller Hall: opened 1979
* Collins Hall: opened 1980
* Falcone Apartments (North, West, East): opened 1985

===Lower Campus===

Lower Campus contains all of the school's athletic facilities and some of its newest dormitories. It is located on the South side of Beaver Street. Below is a list of the major buildings found on Lower Campus.

====Non-Residence Hall Buildings====
* Lewis Hall: originally built in the 1800s, acquired by Bentley College in 1968
* Dana Athletic Center: opened 1973

====Residence Hall Buildings====
* The Castle: opened 1975
* The Cape: opened 1986
* Orchard North &amp; South: opened 1988
* Copley North &amp; South: opened Summer 2001
* Fenway Hall: opened Fall 2004

===North Campus===

North Campus is located 1/2 mile North of the main entrance to Upper Campus on Forest Street. Transportation to and from North Campus is provided via shuttle bus. North Campus contains only residence hall buildings named: A, B, C and D. Residence halls A and B were opened in 2005 while C and D were opened in 2007 making North Campus the most recent addition to Bentley's facilities. Each building has 3 floors and include an elevator and 2 stairwells. Originally North Campus was intended to be graduate student housing but due to the sharp growth of enrollment it is occupied mostly by undergraduates.

==Rankings and Recognition by Major Media==

''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''
* Ranked 62 - MBA Top Graduate Business Schools '2009
* Ranked 14 - MSIT program in the United States
* Ranked 18 - Information System Schools&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscollegeranking.org/business/information-system/best-information-system-schools-ranking-in-2011.html|title=Information System School Rankings|publisher=|year=2011|accessdate=2011-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Top 20 Accounting Program in the US, Tied for #1 in New England
* Top 50 Undergraduate Business Programs (Nationally, 2010)
* Top 10 Master's Universities (North,2010)

''[[The Princeton Review]]''
* Ranked among the &quot;361 Best Colleges and Universities for 2006&quot;
* # 3 in the Top 25 Most Connected Campuses (2004)
* #6 in Best Career/Job Placement Services (2011)
* #14 Best College Library (2011)
* #18 Dorms Like Palaces (2011)

''[[Kaplan, Inc.|Kaplan]]/[[Newsweek]]''
* Named one of the &quot;12 Hot Schools of 2004&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/about/facts.cfm |title=Bentley University |publisher=Bentley.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[BusinessWeek]]''
* Top Undergraduate Business Programs 2010, Ranking 21st&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bwnt.businessweek.com/bschools/undergraduate/10rankings/ |title=Top Undergraduate Business Programs 2010 - Businessweek |publisher=Bwnt.businessweek.com |date=2009-12-08 |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A in facilities and services
* A in teaching quality
* A in job placement

==Athletics==
{{see also|Bentley Falcons men's ice hockey}}
[[File:Dana Gym 015-web.jpg|thumb|right|Bentley University Basketball Gymnasium located in the Dana Athletic Center]]
Bentley's mascot is &quot;Flex the Falcon.&quot; The university has 23 men's and women's varsity teams. All of the teams compete in the [[Northeast Ten Conference]] at the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division II level, with the exception of the men's hockey program, which was one of the original six founding teams of [[Atlantic Hockey]] at the Division I level.

Bentley is also home to one of the best rugby programs in the Northeast winning two national Division III titles as well as winning the 2008 Beast of the East tournament.

After beating [[Saint Michael's College]] by a score of 85-65 on February 23, 2008, Bentley University Men's Basketball team set the record for the longest regular season winning streak in Division II history.  Additionally, Bentley has men's, women's, and co-ed intramural programs for the fall, winter, and spring semesters.

===Club Sports At Bentley University===
In addition to the intercollegiate and intramural programs, the university offers a number of club sports for students to take part in.  These clubs are operated within the Student Activities department, and are financially supported by the student's activity fees. Club Sports include: cheerleading, dance team, men’s rugby, women’s rugby, Ultimate Frisbee, and sailing.

==Campus media==
* ''BS-TV'': student-produced monthly television segment
* ''The Vanguard'': student-produced weekly on-campus newspaper
* ''Piecework'': student-produced annual literary magazine
* ''Bentley Observer'': staff-produced quarterly magazine for alumni&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/alumni/publications/index.cfm |title=Publications : Bentley |publisher=Bentley.edu |date=2011-02-24 |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[WBTY - Radio Bentley]]'': on-campus radio station, operating at 105.3 [[FM broadcasting|FM]]

==Fraternity and Sorority Life==
===Mission===
The Office of Fraternity and Sorority Life is a division of Student Activities that directly supports recognized social Greek-Lettered fraternities and sororities at Bentley University.  Scholarship, Leadership, Service, and Brotherhood/Sisterhood are the pillars that strengthen the development of each individual member and all chapters.  The Office of Fraternity and Sorority Life partners with campus administrators, local and national volunteers as well as alumni/alumnae members to encourage purposeful campus programming and service learning opportunities that promote lifelong friendships.

===Sororities===
There currently are five recognized women’s sororities at Bentley University.  These chapters are governed by the National Panhellenic Conference or the National Association of Latina/Latino Fraternal Organizations, Inc.  For additional information on each of the organizations please see their individual websites:

*[[Alpha Phi]]: Alpha Phi is a sisterhood of outstanding women supporting one another in lifelong achievement.
:Motto: Union Hand in Hand
:Established at Bentley in 1982

*[[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]]: Delta Phi Epsilon develops a social consciousness and a commitment to think and act for the greater good. We assure continuous development and achievement for women through individual attention and smart strategic growth.
:Motto: To Be Rather Than Seem to Be
:Established at Bentley in 1987

*[[Gamma Phi Beta]]: To foster a nurturing environment that provides women the opportunity to achieve their potential through lifelong commitment to intellectual growth, individual worth and service to humanity.
:Motto: Founded Upon a Rock
:Established at Bentley in 1975

*[[Sigma Iota Alpha|Hermandad de Sigma Iota Alpha]]: SIA strives to promote education and unity among women. We endeavor to foster a sense of pride for our heritage, and in doing so hope to abolish ignorance, prejudice, and racism in society at large.
:Motto: Always One and Inseparable
:Established at Bentley in 2009

*[[Phi Sigma Sigma]]: To inspire the personal development of each sister and perpetuate the advancement of womanhood.
:Motto: Aim High
:Established at Bentley in 1991

===Fraternities===
There currently are six recognized men’s fraternities at Bentley University.  Four chapters are inter/national and are governed by the North American Interfraternity Conference. Two of the men’s organizations are local groups which mean that Bentley University is the only institution that house these chapters. For additional information on each of the organizations please see their individual websites.

*[[Alpha Epsilon Pi]] Alpha Epsilon Pi was founded to provide opportunities for the Jewish college man seeking the best possible college and fraternity experience.
:Motto: Developing Leadership for the Jewish Community
:Established at Bentley in 2005

*Alpha Gamma Pi: As a local fraternity, Alpha Gamma Pi realizes the benefit of giving back to the community. We believe that donating our time to help others not only improves their standard of living, but also adds tremendous value to our lives.
:Motto: Brotherhood Through Fraternity Forever
:Established at Bentley in 1924

*[[Alpha Sigma Phi]]: To Better the Man, through the creation and perpetuation of Brotherhood founded upon the virtues of character… Silence, Purity, Charity, Honor, Patriotism.
:Motto: To Better the Man
:Established at Bentley in 2000

*[[Delta Kappa Epsilon]]: The Cultivation of General Literature and Social Culture, the Advancement and Encouragement of Intellectual Excellence, the Promotion of Honorable Friendship and Useful Citizenship, the Development of a Spirit of Tolerance and Respect for the Rights and Views of Others, the Maintenance of Gentlemanly Dignity, Self-Respect, and Morality in All Circumstances, and the Union  of Stout Hearts and Kindred Interests to Secure to Merit its Due Reward.
:Motto: Friends from the Heart Forever
:Established at Bentley in 1991

*Sigma Gamma Delta: Our purpose is to promote goodwill and friendship between its members, acquaintances, the college community, and the community at large. We also have the objective of increasing the social relationships and activities of its members through a distinct vision of friendship. We aim to create a cohesive brotherhood that will stand the test of time while giving back to the world in which we live through charity. In unity is strength!
:Motto: In Unity Is Strength (Unis Veris)
:Established at Bentley in 1965

*[[Sigma Pi]]: To build and support chapters and alumni organizations for the purpose of maintaining a Fellowship of kindred minds united in Brotherhood.
:Motto: A New Generation of Leaders
:Established at Bentley in 2008

==Notable alumni==
* [[Mackenzy Bernadeau]], '08, professional [[American football|football]] player with Carolina Panthers; drafted 250th overall in [[2008 NFL Draft]].
* [http://eatfeats.com/the-great-moomsi-to-be-adam-richmans-pizza-partner.html Greg Maloomian], '07, &quot;The Great Moomsi&quot;, Competitive Eater, guest-starred on the Travel Channel's Man vs Food season 2 finale.
* J. Terence Carleton, '77, Executive Vice President of Technology, [[Hill Holliday|Hill, Holliday, Connors, Cosmopulos, Inc.]]
* Richard Caturano, '72, Co-Founder of Caturano and Company, [[McGladrey]] Northeast Managing Director
* R. Marcelo Claure, '93, Chairman, CEO and President, [[Brightstar Corporation]]
* Charles Dockendorff, Chief Financial Officer and Executive Vice-President of [[Covidien]].
* Thomas M. Feeley,  '82, Managing Partner of Feeley &amp; Driscoll, PC &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bentley.edu/alumni/publications/archive-issues/03_sum_class_notes.pdf |title=Welcome Message from Leigh Gaspar &amp;#124; Alumni |publisher=Bentley.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Taylor Fisher, '76, CPA for the [[Boston Red Sox]] (retired).
* William C. Freda,  Managing Partner of Clients &amp; Markets at [[Deloitte &amp; Touche]] USA LLP.
* Michael Gilburd, '78, businessman and valuation expert, President of ValuCorp International, Inc.; former managing director of corporate finance of American Express.
* Andrew Henshaw, '88, Chief Financial Officer of Novatec, Inc.
* [[Edward J. King]], '53, professional football player with Buffalo Bills and Baltimore Colts 1948-1950; Governor of Massachusetts 1979-1983 (deceased).
* Bud Lacava, '78, [[KPMG]] Northeast Managing Partner.
* [[Mike Malin (Big Brother contestant)|Mike Malin]], owner of the Dolce Group and contestant on both ''[[Big Brother 2 (U.S.)|Big Brother 2]]'' and ''[[Big Brother: All Stars]]''.
* [[Mike Mangini]], Current drummer of [[Dream Theater]]; former drum teacher at [[Berklee College of Music]]
* Elkin B. McCallum, '67, Chairman and CEO (retired), [[Jo-Ann Stores|Jo-Ann Fabrics Corporation]].
* Matthew McKay, '52, Chief Operating Officer of Belleview Corporation (retired).{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}
* Robert F. Smith, '53, Chairman and CEO (retired), American Express Bank.
* [[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]], '77, Prominent war criminal; African Warlord; 22nd President of Liberia
* Daniel Welbeck, '84, Chief Operation Officer and board member of [[Radio Shack]].
* Robert J. Wentworth, '76, Partner, [[Platinum Equity]].
* Joe Wickwire, '93, Manager of the Fidelity Select Gold Portfolio Fund.
* Richard F. Zannino, '80, Former CEO, Dow Jones, Delphi Group.
*[[Michael Jingozian]], '91, Founder &amp; CEO, AngelVision, TV Producer
Also of note: Comedian [[Jay Leno]] attended Bentley for one semester but dropped out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://collegeprowler.com/bentley-university/the-inside-scoop/ |title=Bentley University - Inside Scoop |publisher=College Prowler |date= |accessdate=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bentley.edu Official website]
* [http://www.bentley.edu/athletics Official athletics website]

{{Northeast Ten Conference}}
{{Atlantic Hockey}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Boston}}

[[Category:Business schools in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Association of Independent Colleges and Universities in Massachusetts members]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1917]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Waltham, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Bentley University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Middlesex County, Massachusetts]]

[[fr:Bentley College]]
[[ko:벤틀리 대학교]]
[[id:Universitas Bentley]]
[[no:Bentley College]]
[[pnb:بینٹلے یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Bentley University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
