<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="512318" ns="0" title="State University of New York at Fredonia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name=State University of New York at Fredonia
|image_name= 2004logo.png
|motto= |&quot;Where Success is a Tradition.&quot;
|established=1826
|type=Public coeducational
|endowment= $17.41 million (FY 2007)&lt;ref&gt;SUNY Fredonia Facts, Media Relations Office, http://www.fredonia.edu/academicaffairs/facts.asp&lt;/ref&gt;|
|president= [[Dennis L. Hefner]]
|city=[[Fredonia, New York|Fredonia]]
|state=[[New York]]
|country=[[United States|USA]]
|coor= {{Coord|42|26|27|N|79|20|02|W|type:edu}}
|campus= Small Town, &lt;br/&gt;249 acre campus
|undergrad=5,043
|postgrad=389
|faculty=405
|postgrad_label=graduate
|nickname= Blue Devils
|athletics= [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division III, [[State University of New York Athletic Conference|SUNYAC]]&lt;br/&gt;17 varsity teams
|website=[http://www.fredonia.edu/ www.fredonia.edu]
|colors= Blue and White{{color box|Blue}}{{color box|White}}}}
The '''State University of New York at Fredonia''' (also known as '''SUNY Fredonia''', '''Fredonia State University''' and formerly '''SUNY College at Fredonia''') is a four-year liberal arts college located in [[Fredonia, New York|Fredonia]], [[New York]], [[United States]]; it is a constituent college of the [[State University of New York]]. The college's motto is &quot;Where Success is a Tradition.&quot;

SUNY Fredonia was one of the state [[normal school|teachers' colleges]] traditionally specializing in music education, but now offers a large number of programs in many areas, including a growing graduate division. The most popular areas include Communication, Music, Education, and programs of the Social Sciences. There are 82 majors and 41 minors.

The SUNY Fredonia campus, located in [[Chautauqua County, New York|Chautauqua County]] (southwest of [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]]) was designed by prominent architects [[I.M. Pei]] and [[Henry N. Cobb]] in 1968.&lt;ref&gt;Six buildings on campus have stamp of I.M. Pei, SUNY Fredonia Office of Media Relations Campus Report, Accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/prweb/releases/impei.asp&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pei, Cobb, Freed &amp; Partners Projects, Accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.pcf-p.com/a/i/&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Fredonia Academy (1826–1867)===
Originally opened in 1826 as Fredonia Academy under its first principal Austin Smith, the academy enrolled eight students. The first classes began on October 4, 1826. Within one year the Academy had 136 students, 81 boys and 55 girls.&lt;ref&gt;Academy to State University: Fredonia's Story
Written by William Chazanof, Accessed 6/16/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/175thanniversary/history.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Academy reached peak enrollment in 1856 with 217 students. The school was plagued by financial shortages, and was forced to close its doors in 1867.

===Normal School (1867–1948)===
In 1867, the college emerged in its second phase of existence as a New York State Normal School. On December 2, 1867, the Normal (as it became commonly known) began classes with 147 students, 62 boys and 85 girls. For students preparing to be teachers, no tuition was charged, books were supplied, and travel costs were reimbursed; in return, students had to promise to teach after graduation. Those students not studying for the teaching profession paid tuition and provided their own textbooks.

During its 82 years of existence, Fredonia Normal had a tumultuous existence. With a fluctuating student enrollment and threats of state funding reductions, the school seemed to be in constant jeopardy of closing.

Nonetheless, gradually the school was upgraded. In 1930, {{convert|58|acre|m2}} of land west of Central Avenue in the Village of Fredonia were bought to house a future campus. In 1938 a music building was constructed on the Central Avenue site. New York State Governor Herbert Lehman signed the Feinberg Law in 1942 that changed the Normal Schools into Teacher Colleges.

===State University System (1948–present)===
With the formation of the State University of New York on March 13, 1948, the college created a Division of the Humanities in 1958 and in 1960 Fredonia was selected by State University to grant the A.B. degree. Previously, Fredonia's curriculum was restricted for teacher training only.

In 1968, the master plan for the central avenue campus was drafted by the highly respected architectural firm of I.M. Pei &amp; Partners of New York at the request of then-president Oscar E. Lanford. A complex came into being that consisted of Jewett Hall (science), Dods Hall (health and physical education), Rockefeller Arts Center (building for fine arts), administration, library and an infirmary. In 1970, Pei and Cobb returned to the SUNY Fredonia campus to complete the Erie Dining Hall and the suite-style residence halls.&lt;ref&gt;Six buildings on campus have stamp of I.M. Pei, SUNY Fredonia Office of Media Relations, Accessed 6/16/07, http://www.fredonia.edu/prweb/releases/impei.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

==Architecture==
Architects I.M. Pei and Henry Cobb, who designed the master plan for the modernized campus in 1968.

Many of the buildings are listed in architectural guides as examples of exceptional modern architecture. Some are described in architectural history books. The National Building Museum listed the SUNY Fredonia campus as one of I.M. Pei's ideal places to visit in its 1991 journal &quot;Blueprints.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Campus bears unique stamp of I.M. Pei's vision, SUNY Fredonia News Services, Accessed 6/16/07, http://www.fredonia.edu/news/News/Archives/tabid/1101/ctl/ArticleView/mid/1878/articleId/84/Campus-bears-unique-stamp-of-IM-Peis-vision.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

Pei is credited with designing Maytum Hall, Williams Center, Reed Library, Rockefeller Arts Center, McEwen Hall, and Houghton Hall as well as its characteristic circular perimeter, aptly named Ring Road. The design of Daniel Reed Library earned Henry Cobb and I.M. Pei the 1969 Prestressed Concrete Institute Award.
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image: Fredonia_2005.jpg|Maytum Hall
Image:Williams_Center.jpg|Williams Center
Image:Reed Library Fredonia.jpg|Daniel A. Reed Library with the addition built in 1992
Image: Rockefeller_Arts_Center.jpg|Rockefeller Arts Center
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Academic and administrative buildings on campus==
*'''Reed Library''' was constructed in 1969.  It is approximately the size of a regulation football field, provides seating for over 850 readers, and houses over 250,000 books.  It is named for the late [[Daniel A. Reed]] (1875–1959), [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. Representative]] from the Fredonia area for over 40 years. The four story addition to Reed Library was constructed in 1992, and consists of several study areas, a scholarship center, atrium, elevators, tower study lounge which leads to a fifth story, and the Tutoring Center.
*'''Michael C. Rockefeller Arts Center''', constructed in 1968, is named after the youngest son of former [[Governor]] [[Nelson A. Rockefeller]], who disappeared in 1961 during an anthropological expedition in [[New Guinea]].  The Rockefeller Arts Center includes King Concert Hall (a 1,200-seat concert hall), Marvel Theatre (a 400 seat proscenium theatre), Alice E. Bartlett Theatre (a 200-seat maximum black box theatre), an art gallery, and 24 classrooms. This building houses the Departpment of Theatre and Dance, and the Department of Visual Arts and New Media.  The arts center was opened in 1968 by Clint Norton as its first Managing Director.  He was followed by Robert B. D'Angelo who served from 1970-1974 while he also served as a speech writer and advisor to then Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller.  Jefferson Westword has served as director since the mid-1970's.
*'''Fenton Hall''' was named for the late [[Reuben Fenton]], U.S. Senator, and Governor, who was born in Carroll, Chautauqua County. Fenton Hall houses the office of the University President, the Graduate Studies office, as well as classrooms, academic departments and the Gazebo Cafe (part of Signature Cafe). Computer Science, Modern Languages, English, and Philosophy are some of the departments located in Fenton.
*'''Mason Hall''' is home to the School of Music and was named after American music education pioneer [[Lowell Mason]].  This hall is actually three buildings, &quot;Old Mason,&quot; &quot;New Mason,&quot; and the recent addition of two rehearsal rooms, which are all connected together.  Mason Hall includes over 100 personal practice rooms, several small ensemble practice rooms, and large ensemble rooms.  Both Juliet J. Rosch Recital Hall and Diers Recital Hall are located here, as well as two state-of-the-art MIDI technology labs, and an extensive Studio Recording Department.
*'''Maytum Hall''' is an eight-story semi-circular office building and computer center, and was named after Arthur Maytum (1866–1953).  He served as Chairman of the Board of Visitors of the Fredonia Normal School and Teachers college from 1928 to 1953.  He also served as supervisor of the Town of Pomfret from 1931 to 1938. There is much speculation as to how many stories Maytum hall contains. Many contend that the central offices, along with the elevator stop at floor eight, and so should the floor count. However, the original president office was to be on the constructed ninth floor, but was moved due to lack of handicap access, along with a fear of riots shutting the president in. When walking from Thompson or Fenton, you can see the very large patio window of the ninth floor. The building is currently closed for major renovations and upgrades, and is expected to reopen sometime during the Fall 2011  semester.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fredonia.edu/admin/facilities/construction.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Offices usually in Maytum are temporarily distributed between Gregory Hall and the Williams Center.
*'''Steele Hall''' is mainly used as a sports center with a basketball court and an ice rink which are used for both campus and community events. It also contains classrooms, a newly constructed natatorium, raquetball courts, dancing practice rooms, and many other facilities.
*'''The Williams Center''', previously the Campus Center, houses the Office of Campus Life, the Student Association, Signature Cafe, the Campus Grind, the newly renovated Centre Pointe dining facility (Operated by FSA), Trendz (organic, vegan style food) and is the meeting location for most of the SA clubs and groups.
*'''Thompson Hall''' is the largest academic building at SUNY Fredonia. It houses the departments of Multicultural Affairs, Psychology, Political Science, Speech Pathology, Sociology, and History, among others, plus the College of Education. The building is designed as riot proof. It has narrow stairwells, dimly lighted hallways, and no operable windows.
*'''Houghton Hall and Jewett Hall''' are the two science buildings at SUNY Fredonia. They house the departments of Geology, Physics, Chemistry, and Biochemistry, and the 3-2 Cooperative Engineering Program.
*'''LoGrasso Hall''' On campus medical services, along with counseling, and the office of international education.
*'''McEwen Hall''' Four level building, Contains lecture halls, Sheldon Media Labs, and Fredonia Radio Systems.
*'''Erie Hall''' Dining facility located in the center of the four-dormitory Kirkland Complex.

==Residential halls==
SUNY Fredonia has two different type of residential buildings: Corridor and Suite-style. Corridor style dorms are long, staggered hallways with no sections. Whereas suites are short corridors with either staggered hallways extending from the main corridor, or doors leading into the individual suites.

===Corridor halls===
*'''University Commons''' which opened for the Fall Semester 2006 is an expansion and renovation on the former Cranston Dining Hall. Originally opened in 1969, Cranston served as one of the two cafeteria style dining halls at SUNY Fredonia (the other being Marketplace at Erie Dining Center). Currently, University Commons is split between a four-story upperclassmen co-ed 124 bed Residence Hall. And the second part, of two stories which contains the dining hall Cranston Marche (all you can eat, made to order dining facility), the University Bookstore and Convenience Store, offices for FSA management, and a [[Starbucks]].
*'''Gregory Hall''' is a multi-purpose building consisting of a 200-bed upperclassmen dormitory, substance free living, the offices for the Faculty-Student Association (Bookstore, Foodservice), Residence Life, University Police, the Campus Print Shop, and the Career Development Office. Before its current uses, Gregory Hall previously housed the campus radio station WCVF AM/FM and the Student Association offices.
*'''Nixon Hall''' is a 200-bed dormitory named for Samuel Frederick Nixon of Westfield.  He was a member of the Fredonia College Council (1932–1952).  He was one of the nation's leading independent telephone executives and was the President of the Chautauqua and Erie and the Dunkirk and Fredonia Telephone Companies. A 200-bed dorm for freshman women. Corridor style.
*'''Alumni Hall''' is a 200-bed dorm for freshman women. Corridor style. Originally a men's dormitory.
*'''McGinnies Hall''' 200-bed dorm for upperclassman. Corridor style.
*'''Chautauqua Hall''' 200-bed dorm for freshman men. Corridor style.

===Suite style halls===
Suite style dorms are placed into ''''Quads''''. Or as students call them ''''the far/near Quad''''. They are groups of four dorms either in an L pattern (in the case of Andrews) or a square pattern (in the case of Kirkland). The buildings are connected by floor, but residents can not go through the doors, except for emergencies. Only Residence life staff, janitorial staff and University officials have round-the-clock access. Suites are set up in a 'Suite:room' fashion. For Example: 212-A is Suite 212, room A. &quot;310-C&quot; is Suite 310-C. There is an A, B, C, D room, Common room and bathroom for each suite.

====Kirkland complex====
Kirkland has private common rooms contained within the suite. Eisenhower and Disney Hall house the highly coveted ''''Kitchen Suites'''' meant for upperclassmen. There is a fee associated with moving into a kitchen suite, however a student does not need a meal plan. Kitchen suites take up the 'D' room of a suite, and the common room is connected to the kitchen. Therefore only six people live in a kitchen suite.

*'''Disney Hall''' 200-bed dorm for upperclassmen, Suite-style. Contains some Kitchen Suites. (&quot;the near quad&quot;).
*'''Eisenhower Hall''' 200-bed dorm for upperclassmen. Suite style. Contains some Kitchen Suites(&quot;the near quad&quot;.)
*'''Grissom Hall''' 200-bed dorm for freshman men. Suite style. (&quot;the near quad&quot;) new windows, scheduled to have lobby renovated in the summer of 2011.
*'''Kasling Hall''' 200-bed dorm for freshman women. Suite style. Newly renovated lobby, new windows.(&quot;the near quad&quot;).

====Andrews complex====
Andrews buildings have shared common areas, and private suites. The shared common areas are open to all other residents, but the bathroom, bedroom and suite-hallway are separated from the open areas. Andrews has its own dedicated parking lot next to Igoe and Hendrix. Those two halls have exclusive rights to using that parking lot.

*'''Igoe Hall''' is a 200-bed dorm for upperclassmen. It is named after Jimmy Igoe who died on Lake Erie. It is a co-ed building. Sexes are separated by suite, and/or floor. Part of the Andrews Complex (&quot;The far-quad&quot;)
*'''[https://sites.google.com/a/fredonia.edu/hendrix-hall/ Hendrix Hall]''' is a 200-bed dormitory for upperclassmen, situated next to Igoe Hall and across from Hemmingway Hall. Hendrix is home to one of the last independently student-run television stations in America, [[WNYF-TV]]. Part of the Andrews Complex (&quot;the far-quads&quot;).
*'''Schulz Hall''' 200-bed dorm for upperclassmen, Suite-style. Part of the Andrews Complex (&quot;the far-quads&quot;).
*'''Hemingway Hall''' 200-bed dorm for upperclassman, Suite style. Part of the Andrews Complex (&quot;the far-quads&quot;).

==''The Leader''==
''The Normal Leader'' was created in September 1899 by the Zetesian society, an all-male literary organization. ''The Normal Leader'' was a monthly newspaper, costing ten cents a copy or fifty cents for a yearly subscription.

On September 28, 1936 ''The Normal Leader'' became what we know today as [http://www.fredonialeader.com ''The Leader''] on its Vol. XXXVI article No. 3 even though the school would not change its name to [http://www.fredonia.edu SUNY Fredonia] until 1948.  ''The Leader'' is produced by a team of Fredonia students, some of whom receive stipends from the Student Association.  ''The Leader'' is printed by the [http://www.corrypa.com/journal/ ''Corry Journal''] in Corry, Pennsylvania and is distributed free on campus and in the surrounding community.

==A cappella groups==

Fredonia is home to five collegiate a cappella groups: Premium Blend (co-ed), the Riveters (female), Some Like It Hot (female), Much More Chill (all-male), and [[SUNY Fredonia Guerrillas|The Guerrillas]] (all-male).

==Greek life==
While there are no physical fraternity or sorority houses on campus due to a local ordinance prohibiting them, Fredonia State has an active Greek culture with one local and eight national recognized organizations as well as numerous Greek letter honor societies.

*[[Alpha Phi Omega]] (Chi Pi)
*[[Delta Chi]] (SUNY Fredonia chapter)
*[[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]] (Epsilon Eta)
*[[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]] (Rho Chi)
*[[Sigma Alpha Iota]] (Delta Lambda)
*[[Sigma Kappa]]
*[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]] (New York Iota)
*[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]] (Colony 817)

==Notable alumni==
===Business===
*[[Benjamin Goodrich|Dr. Benjamin Franklin Goodrich]] 1857- Founder of [http://www.bfgoodrichtires.com B.F.Goodrich tire company]
*[[James H. McGraw]] 1884 - Founder of [http://www.mcgraw-hill.com McGraw-Hill Companies]  Set a higher standard for industrial journalists.&lt;ref&gt;Biographical Dictionary of American Business Leaders, Accessed 11/4/2007, http://books.google.com/books?id=J9nXHgKQ49EC&amp;pg=PA903&amp;lpg=PA903&amp;dq=james+herbert+mcgraw+fredonia&amp;source=web&amp;ots=nfoAZFd2JC&amp;sig=9LmTPN3IOSBwDp0ADNL9HnNB84Q#PPA903,M1&lt;/ref&gt;
*Louis Boyer '65 - Owner of Polyloom Corporation of America, was the first to develop artificial turf&lt;ref&gt;In Addition, College and University Profiles, Accessed 6/17/2007, http://www.collegeprofiles.com/suny-fredonia.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Entertainment===
*[[Peter Michael Goetz]] '65 - Actor&lt;ref&gt;Biography for Peter Michael Goetz at IMDB, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0324533/bio&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Famous Alumni State University of New York College at Fredonia at College.com, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.colleges.com/admissions/collegesearch/college_search.taf?_function=detail&amp;Type=4&amp;school_id=1100143&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mary McDonnell]] '74 - Academy Award-nominated actress&lt;ref&gt;Mary McDonnell Biography at Yahoo Entertainment, accessed 6/14/2007, http://tv.yahoo.com/mary-mcdonnell/contributor/30520/bio&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Brian Frons]] '77 - President, Daytime, Disney-ABC Television Group&lt;ref&gt;Frons Biography at Disney-ABC Television, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.disneyabctv.com/bios/bio_frons.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Andrea Romano]] '77 - Peabody Award winner. Seven time Emmy award winner. Casting and voice director&lt;ref&gt;Outstanding Achievement Award SUNY Fredonia News Services, Accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/news/tabid/1101/ctl/ArticleView/mid/1878/articleId/194/Homecoming-Weekend-will-bring-back-the-best.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
*Marc Calixte '93- Screenwriter ([[The Perfect Holiday]])
*Evan Harrington- Actor&lt;ref&gt;Evan Harrington Website, accessed 1/24/2008, http://www.evanharrington.com&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jennifer Cody]] '91- actress
*Rich Ceisler '78 - Stand-up Comedian, Actor, Writer [http://www.richcomedy.com]
*Stan Rogers '59 - Songwriter, Multi-instrumentalist. Composer of &quot;Barrett's Privateers&quot; and &quot;Northwest Passage&quot;.
*[[Kevin Sylvester (broadcaster)|Kevin Sylvester]] '95 - Television Analyst for the Buffalo Sabres.
*Joshua Gregory '96 - Edge of the Unknown Radio Talk Show Host (as Mark Henry) in Buffalo, NY

===Music===
*[[James Houlik]] '64 - American Tenor Saxophonist&lt;ref&gt;James Houlik Biography at Duquesne University, Accessed 6/16/2007, http://www.music.duq.edu/fasBioHoul.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Roberta Guaspari]] '69 - Internationally renowned Music Educator&lt;ref&gt;Biography for Roberta Guaspari at IMDB, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0345461/bio&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Allan Dennis|Dr. Allan Dennis]] '70 - Music educator and conductor&lt;ref&gt;Allan Dennis Faculty Biography at Midwest Young Artists, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.mya.org/people/&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Onaje Allan Gumbs]] '71 - Pianist, Composer, and Bandleader&lt;ref&gt;SUNY Fredonia Alumni Outstanding Achievement Award, Accessed 11/4/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/alumni/achievement.asp&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Don Menza]] - Saxophonist, Arranger, Composer, Jazz Educator
*Barbara Kilduff '81 - Soprano&lt;ref&gt;NY Times Archives, Barbara Kilduff, Accessed 6/14/2007, http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DE1738F931A25754C0A965958260&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Clint Holmes]] - Singer&lt;ref&gt;http://www.netwebsite.com/clintholmes/biography.html, Accessed 9/7/2008&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Kevin Moore]] - Keyboardist for Dream Theater, Chroma Key, and O.S.I., attended briefly in 1985
*[[Dave Fridmann]] - American record producer and musician

===Politics, government and law===
*[[Marcus M. Drake]] 1852 - Mayor of Buffalo, 1882&lt;ref name=&quot;bflo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.buffalonian.com/history/industry/mayors/Drake.htm|title=Marcus M. Drake|date=2009-05-27|work= Through The Mayor's Eyes, The Only Complete History of the Mayor's of Buffalo, New York, Compiled by Michael Rizzo|publisher=The Buffalonian is produced by The Peoples History Union}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Reuben Fenton]] - U.S. Senator and Governor of New York State from 1865 to 1868 (Attended part of a term at Fredonia Academy)&lt;ref&gt;Academy to State University: Fredonia's Story Written by William Chazanof, Accessed 6/16/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/175thanniversary/history.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reuben Fenton, Fenton History Center, Accessed 6/16/2007, http://www.fentonhistorycenter.org/civilwar/fenton/fentontimeline.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ozra Amander Hadley]] - Governor of the State of Arkansas from 1871 to 1873&lt;ref&gt;Ozra Amander Hadley Biography at Anything Arkansas Directory, Accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.anythingarkansas.com/arkapedia/pedia/Ozra_Hadley/&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Paul Cambria]] '69 - Leading first-amendment lawyer&lt;ref&gt;Paul J. Cambria, West Legal Directory, accessed 6/14/2007, http://pview.findlaw.com/view/1910880_1?channel=LP&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Robert Spitzer (political scientist)|Robert Spitzer]] '75 - Political Scientist&lt;ref&gt;Robert Spitzer Biography at SUNY Cortland, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.cortland.edu/polsci/default.asp?page_id=19&lt;/ref&gt;
*James B. Foley '79 - Diplomat, U.S. Ambassador to the Republic of Croatia&lt;ref&gt;James B. Foley Biography at U.S. State Department, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/biog/25992.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Literature and education===
*[[Neil Postman]] '53 - Educator and author&lt;ref&gt;Neil Postman &quot;Outstanding Achiever&quot; at Homecoming, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/prweb/releases/postman.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lucille Clifton]] '55 - American Poet&lt;ref&gt;Lucille Clifton Biography at The Poetry Center, accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.smith.edu/poetrycenter/poets/lclifton.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[http://www.wendylindstrom.com/ Wendy Lindstrom] '71- Famous romance writer, 2003 RITA award
*[[Gaelen Foley]] '91 - Author&lt;ref&gt;About the Author: Gaelen Foley, Powell Books, Accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.powells.com/cgi-bin/biblio?inkey=92-0345494105-0&lt;/ref&gt;
*[http://www.wendycorsistaub.com/ Wendy Corsi Staub] '86- ''The New York Times'' best-selling suspense author

===Science===
*Diane Pennica '73 - Biologist and researcher, Genetech&lt;ref&gt;Researcher Profiles: Diane Pennica at Genentech, Inc., accessed 6/14/2007, http://www.gene.com/gene/research/sci-profiles/molecularoncology/pennica/index.jsp?q=Diane+Pennica+&amp;rls=com.microsoft:en-us:IE-SearchBox&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;sourceid=ie7&amp;rlz=1I7RNWE&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Michael Marletta]] '73 - Chemist and MacArthur Fellow&lt;ref&gt;Michael Marletta Biography at UC Berkeley, accessed 6/14/2007, http://chem.berkeley.edu/people/faculty/marletta/marletta.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Presidents==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! width=&quot;150px&quot;|President
! width=&quot;90px&quot;|Tenure
!Notes
|-
|Joseph A. Allen
|1867–1869
|Born on April 25, 1819, Allen was the first &quot;President&quot; of The Fredonia Normal School. Prior to coming to Fredonia he was the Principal of both Syracuse Academy and The State Reform School and at Westboro where he was principal for seven years. He died on July 17, 1904.
|-
|J.W. Armstrong
|1869–1898
|
|-
|Francis B. Palmer
|1898–1907
|
|-
|Myron T. Dana
|1908–1922
|
|-
|Howard Griffth Burdge
|1922–1928
|
|-
|Herman Cooper
|1929–1931
|
|-
|Leslie R. Gregory
|1931–1948
|
|-
|Harry W. Porter
|1953–1961
|
|-
|Oscar Lanford
|1961–1971
|
|-
|Dallas K. Beal
|1971–1984
|
|-
|Donald A. MacPhee
|1985–1996
|
|-
|[[Dennis L. Hefner]]
|1997–Present
|Hefner received his Bachelor's degree in economics from California State University and both his Masters in economics and Ph. D from Washington State University.  Prior to coming to Fredonia he worked for the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare in Washington, D.C. and also as Vice President of Academic Affairs at California State University in San Bernardino from 1990 to 1994.  He also worked as Vice Chancellor of Academic Affairs for Minnesota State Colleges and Universities from 1994 to 1996.
|}
*Note: Earlier Presidents were Principals and are not included list

==History of the athletic team name==
Fredonia athletic teams compete as the Blue Devils.

When SUNY Fredonia was first known as the Fredonia Normal School; the athletics team were known as the &quot;Normalites&quot;. On January 27, 1936, ''The Leader'' issued an article which publicized a contest to come up with a new name for the teams. There were two names the committee had chosen, Blue Jackets and Blue Devils. The name Blue Devils seemed to be used more than Blue Jackets. In the issue of ''The Leader'' on September 30, 1952; the name Blue Devils was used officially for the first time.

===Alma mater===
&lt;poem&gt;
Near the shores of old Lake Erie
Stands our Alma Mater true.
Fredonia State we proudly honor,
With its colors white and blue.

Sing its glory and its praises
Let them ring forever true.
Beloved is our Alma Mater.
Fredonia State, all hail to you.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fredonia.edu/alumni/Alma.asp SUNY Fredonia Alma Mater]
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/poem&gt;

==Resources==
*Archive and Special Collections, SUNY Fredonia, Daniel E. Reed Library
**Building Naming Committee - Correspondence, lists of names.
**College History Buildings - Nixon Hall.
**History of the College at Fredonia.
**General History of Buildings.
**&quot;F.N.S Squad Needs Catchy Nickname&quot; The Leader, 27 January 1936
*&quot;The Historical Development of State University of New York College...&quot; (PH.D diss. John Ford Ohles) State University of New York at Buffalo, 1964

*President's List: College History Reference Files, Archives and Special Collections, Daniel A. Reed Library, Suny Fredonia

*The Normal Leader. Vol. I, No. 1, September, 1899, p.&amp;nbsp;1

*The Leader. Vol. CXIV, No. 2, September 13, 2006, p.&amp;nbsp;5

*From Academy to State University: Fredonia's Story, by William Chazanof (1967). Accessed 6/16/2007, http://www.fredonia.edu/175thanniversary/history.htm

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.fredonia.edu SUNY Fredonia]
* [http://www.cs.fredonia.edu SUNY Fredonia Computer Science Department]
* [http://sa.fredonia.edu SUNY Fredonia Student Association]
*[http://www.fredonialeader.com The Leader]
*[http://www.fredoniaradio.com Fredonia Radio Systems]
*[http://www.fredonia.edu/music SUNY Fredonia School of Music]
*[http://www.fredoniabluedevils.com/ Fredonia State Athletics]

{{State University of New York Athletic Conference}}
{{SUNY}}

[[Category:Education in Buffalo, New York]]
[[Category:State University of New York university colleges|Fredonia]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Education in Chautauqua County, New York]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
