<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5123945" ns="0" title="WERC (AM)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=October 2008}}
{{Infobox radio station
| name             = WERC
| image            = [[File:WERC1055.png|WERC-FM logo]]
| city             = [[Birmingham, Alabama]]
| area             = 
| branding         = {{nowrap|'''News Radio 105.5 WERC'''}}
| slogan           = 
| airdate          = [[May 25]], [[1925 in radio|1925]]
| frequency        = '''960''' ([[kilohertz|kHz]])&lt;br&gt;{{HD Radio}}
| format           = [[Talk radio|News/talk]]
| power            = 5,000 [[watt]]s
| class            = B 
| facility_id      = 2112
| coordinates      = {{coord|33|32|02|N|86|51|07|W}}
| callsign_meaning = '''W'''-B'''E'''ll '''R'''adio '''C'''orporation&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(derived from [[WBRC]] calls)&lt;/small&gt;
| former_callsigns = 2011: '''WVVB''' &lt;small&gt;(149 days)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;1972-2011: '''WERC'''&lt;br&gt;1925-1972: '''WBRC'''
| affiliations     = [[Fox News Radio]]&lt;br&gt;[[Premiere Radio Networks]]&lt;br&gt;[[WBRC-TV]]
| owner            = [[Clear Channel Communications]]
| licensee         = Capstar TX LLC
| sister_stations  = [[WDXB]], [[WERC-FM]], [[WMJJ]], [[WQEN]]
| webcast          = {{listenlive|http://www.wercfm.com/mediaplayer/}}
| website          = [http://www.wercfm.com wercfm.com]
}}

'''WERC''' (960 [[AM broadcasting|AM]]) — branded '''News Radio 105.5 WERC''' — is a [[talk radio|news/talk]] [[radio station]] licensed to [[Birmingham, Alabama]], and serving the Birmingham market as a complete simulcast of sister station [[WERC-FM]]. It operates at unlimited hours with 5,000 [[watt]]s.

WERC originated the talk format currently heard on WERC-FM from 1982 until 2011, and was the first station in Birmingham to carry an all-talk format. The format - and the WERC calls - migrated to the 105.5 facility in 2010 before both returned to the AM station in July 2011.

WERC is owned by [[Clear Channel Communications]].  Other stations in the Birmingham market owned by Clear Channel include [[WMJJ]] (96.5 FM), [[WDXB]] (102.5 FM), [[WQEN]] (103.7 FM), and WERC-FM (105.5 FM). Clear Channel also programs W276BQ (103.1), a translator owned by Red Mountain Broadcasting, LLC. W276BQ rebroadcasts the programming of the HD2 channel of WQEN, branded as &quot;103.1 The Vulcan&quot; (and was also relayed on this facility from January to June 2011 under the WVVB calls).

==Programming==
Like most Clear Channel talk stations, WERC airs several local programs, as well as nationally syndicated programs such as ''[[The Glenn Beck Program]]'', ''[[The Rush Limbaugh Show]]'', ''[[The Schnitt Show]]'', ''[[The Savage Nation]]'', ''[[America Now with Andy Dean (radio program)|America Now with Andy Dean]]'' and ''[[The Mutual Fund Show]]'' with [[Adam Bold]]. In addition, WERC simulcasts the audio feed of [[WBRC-TV]]'s early morning and late night newscasts, along with breaking news/weather coverage (in effect continuing the linkage between WERC and its' onetime sister TV station). Overnight, the station broadcasts the syndicated ''[[Coast to Coast AM]]'' hosted by [[George Noory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c2c&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Coast to Coast AM |title=Alabama Affiliates |url=http://www.coasttocoastam.com/affiliates/alabama |accessdate=January 28, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The station also broadcasts the syndicated Saturday night program ''Somewhere In Time'', which consists of reruns of [[Art Bell]]-hosted editions of ''Coast to Coast AM''.&lt;ref name=&quot;c2c&quot;/&gt;

== History ==
The forerunner of WERC was the first radio station in Birmingham, and the second station in Alabama.  In May 1925, '''WBRC''' (for the '''B'''ell '''R'''adio '''C'''orporation)&lt;ref name=&quot;bob&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Call Letter Origins |url=http://nelson.oldradio.com/origins.call-list.html |publisher=The Broadcast Archive |last=Nelson |first=Bob |date=2008-10-18 |accessdate=2008-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; signed on, broadcasting with 50 watts power at 1210 AM.  Throughout the 1920s the station increased its broadcast power several times as well as its broadcast frequency.  By 1935, the station was affiliated with the [[NBC]] network.

In 1946, WBRC introduced the first FM station in Birmingham.  Due to the lack of FM radios in Birmingham, WBRC-FM was not very successful, and was taken off the air two years later.  In 1949, the owners of WBRC launched the second television station in Birmingham, as [[WBRC|WBRC-TV]] made its debut on channel 4.  The local owners of WBRC and WBRC-TV sold the stations to [[Storer Broadcasting]] in 1953, and four years later, the stations were sold to [[Taft Broadcasting]].

The advent of television in the 1950s caused network radio programming to decline.  By the early 1960s, WBRC was one of two &quot;[[middle of the road (music)|middle of the road]]&quot; music stations in Birmingham.  It continued in that format until 1972, when Taft Broadcasting sold WBRC and a revived WBRC-FM (106.9 FM) to Mooney Broadcasting.  Taft retained ownership of WBRC-TV until 1987; as [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) regulations at that time prohibited non-commonly owned stations from sharing call letters, Mooney changed the call letters of the radio stations to '''WERC''' and '''WERC-FM'''.  WERC was christened “96-ERC”, and launched an all-out assault on the market’s leading [[top 40]] station, WSGN (now [[WAGG]]). 

For much of the 1970s, WERC and WSGN were two of the most listened-to stations in Birmingham.  The beginning of WERC's demise as a top 40 powerhouse came in 1977, when its own FM sister station was relaunched as top 40 station WKXX, “Kicks 106” (now [[WBPT]]).  By 1980, WERC modified its format to [[adult contemporary]] music and was known as ”News Plus 960, WERC”.  An afternoon drive sports call-in show hosted by future University of Alabama football announcer [[Eli Gold]] was launched in 1981.  Competing unsuccessfully against WSGN and [[WAPI (AM)|WAPI]] as an adult contemporary station, WERC dropped music in 1982 and changed to a news-talk format, which it continued with until January 2011.  The station was an early affiliate for [[Rush Limbaugh]]'s radio network.

For much of the 1990s the WERC line-up featured TC and John Ed as morning hosts, [[Paul Finebaum]] in the afternoons, and Russ and Dee Fine hosting evenings.   

During a 1993 snowstorm that paralyzed the Birmingham area, WERC became the primary source of information and assistance for hundreds of thousands of residents that were stranded by the weather without power (in some cases, for weeks).

WERC began to transition its format to the FM dial on July 6, 2009, when a new incarnation of [[WERC-FM]] replaced [[modern rock]] station WVVB (”The Vulcan”) at 105.5 FM.  960 AM simulcast with 105.5 FM until January 7, 2011, when it began originating the programming being broadcast on a new FM translator, W276BQ, that began broadcasting on the 103.1 frequency.  After [[stunting (broadcasting)|stunting]] with several formats, ranging from [[oldies]] to [[classic country]] to [[adult album alternative]] to urban, the station settled on a permanent format on January 13, 2011, reviving the ”Vulcan” branding with an [[active rock]] format.  In addition to broadcasting on 960 AM and 103.1 FM, &quot;The Vulcan&quot; also broadcast on [[WQEN]]-HD2 103.7-2.  The transition was completed on February 15, 2011, when the WERC call letters were replaced with 105.5's former '''WVVB''' call letters.

On June 23, 2011, WVVB changed their format back to news/talk, simulcasting WERC-FM (105.5 FM). On July 14, 2011 WVVB changed their call letters back to '''WERC'''. 103.1 continues to broadcast the active rock format from WQEN-HD2. 

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{official|http://www.wercfm.com/}}
*{{AM station data|WERC}}

{{Birmingham Radio}}
{{News/Talk Radio Stations in Alabama}}

[[Category:Radio stations in Birmingham, Alabama|ERC]]
[[Category:Clear Channel radio stations]]
[[Category:News and talk radio stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Radio stations established in 1925]]
[[Category:Jefferson County, Alabama]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
