<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="514888" ns="0" title="Woolworths Limited"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Australian retail company|retailers of a similar name|Woolworth's (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}
{{Infobox company
| name              =  Woolworths Limited
| logo              =  [[File:WoolworthsLimited.svg|250px]]
| company_type      =  Public 
| traded_as  = {{asx|WOW}}
| foundation        =  1924
| location_city     =  [[Bella Vista, New South Wales]]
| location_country  =  [[Australia]]
| area_served       =  [[Australia]]&lt;br&gt;[[New Zealand]]&lt;br&gt;[[India]]
| key_people        =  [[James Strong (businessman)|James Strong]], [[Chairman]]&lt;br&gt;[[Grant O'Brien]], [[CEO]]
| num_employees     =  188,000
| industry          =  [[Retail]]
| divisions         =  Supermarkets ([[Woolworths (supermarkets)|Woolworths]], [[Safeway (Australia)|Safeway]], Food For Less, Woolworths/Safeway Liquor, [[Flemings (supermarkets)|Flemings]]), Petrol (Caltex Woolworths/Safeway), Liquor ([[BWS]], [[Dan Murphy's]]), General Merch([[Big W]]), Consumer Electronics ([[Dick Smith Electronics]], Dick Smith PowerHouse, [[Tandy (Australia)|Tandy]])
| revenue           =  {{profit}} [[Australian Dollar|A$]]54.28 billion &lt;small&gt;(2011)&lt;/small&gt;
| net_income        =  {{profit}} [[Australian Dollar|A$]]2.14 billion &lt;small&gt;(2011)&lt;/small&gt;
| homepage          =  [http://www.woolworthslimited.com.au/ woolworthslimited.com.au]
| intl              =  yes
}}

[[File:Woolworths Limited Headquarters.jpg|thumb|right|260px|Woolworths Limited headquarters in the [[Norwest Business Park]]]]

'''Woolworths Limited''' is a major [[Australia]]n company with extensive [[retailer|retail]] interest throughout Australia and [[New Zealand]]. It is the:
* largest retail company in Australia and New Zealand by [[market capitalisation]] and sales{{citation needed|date=August 2011|reason=wesfarmers 2011 sales were higher}}
* largest food retailer in Australia&lt;ref name = &quot;IRIS&quot;&gt;{{cite web  | date = 9 November 2007 | url =  http://www.iris.tas.gov.au/major_comp/woolworths | title = Woolworths Limited Group | work = IRIS Tasmania | publisher = Department of Infrastructure, Energy and Resources, State of Tasmania | accessdate = 23 November 2007|quote = The company is Australia's largest food retailer and second largest private employer, with 13 million customers each week.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the second largest in New Zealand&lt;ref name = &quot;NZHerald26Oct2007&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last = NZPA | date = 26 October 2007 | url =  http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/3/story.cfm?c_id=3&amp;objectid=10472143 | title = Commission: Red Shed takeover would create a 'pure duopoly'| work =  Business story| publisher = New Zealand Herald | accessdate = 23 November 2006 |quote = Commerce Commission lawyer Stephen Kos told the court the market essentially consisted of a single acknowledged price leader and other price followers. &quot;The effect of the merger would be a creation of a pure duopoly.&quot; ... Now Woolworths and Foodstuffs had roughly equal market shares, Kos said.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* largest takeaway liquor retailer in Australia&lt;ref name = &quot;CorbettItrvw20060305&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last = Moore  | first =  Ali | authorlink =   | coauthors =   | date = 5 March 2006 | url =  http://businesssunday.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=89566 | title = Man of the Moment (Interview with Woolworths' boss Roger Corbett)  | work = Business Sunday | publisher = Ninemsn | accessdate = 23 November 2007 | quote = This is a very personal question but it is probably going to be the last chance we get to speak to with you on Business Sunday. You are now the biggest pokies operator, the biggest pub owner, the biggest liquor retailer in Australia, how does that sit with your very well known personal Christian beliefs? }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* largest hotel and poker machine operator in Australia&lt;ref name = &quot;CorbettItrvw20060305&quot;/&gt;
* 19th largest retailer in the world (may change from time to time)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=14 January 2008 12:00AM |url=http://www.news.com.au/business/story/0,23636,23049940-462,00.html |title=Woolies makes top 25 global retailer list |publisher=News.com.au |date=14 January 2008 |accessdate=11 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australian Divisions==
===Supermarkets===
*[[Woolworths (supermarket)|'''Woolworths''']] – The company's premier supermarket chain, which operates in every Australian state and territory. The supermarkets are often colloquially known as &quot;Woolies&quot; and have used the slogan 'The Fresh Food People' since 1987.
*'''[[Woolworths online]] (Homeshop)''' – An online Woolworths supermarket store. Homeshop allows users to purchase their groceries online and have them delivered to their front door. The groceries are packed in special warehouses located around the country specific for homeshop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.homeshop.com.au/|title=Woolworths online|accessdate=11 June 2010 |work= |date=11 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Safeway (Australia)|'''Safeway''']] – In 1985 Woolworths Limited acquired Safeway and used it as the trading name for Woolworths supermarkets in Victoria.  In August 2008, Woolworths announced it would be rebranding these stores as ''Woolworths''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=The Age, Melbourne|date=21 August 2008|accessdate=21 August 2008| title=Woolies shelves Safeway brand|url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/woolies-shelves-safeway-brand-20080820-3ywj.html | first=Ari | last=Sharp}}&lt;/ref&gt; As at December 2008 Safeway remained by far the dominant brand in Victoria, with only a handful of Woolworths' branded stores. However the Woolworths brand will be slowly rolled out throughout Victoria as the stores are refurbished.
*'''[[Food For Less]]''' – Discount supermarket chain located in Queensland and New South Wales. Rumored to be rebranded to Woolworths over time as stores are refurbished.
*[[Flemings (supermarkets)|'''Flemings''']] – Group of four supermarkets located in Sydney and the Central Coast (the remnants of a chain purchased in the 1960s). Rumored to be rebranded to Woolworths over time as stores are refurbished.
*'''[[Thomas Dux Grocer]]''' – Upmarket supermarket / deli chain launched in 2008
*'''[[Macro Wholefoods Market]]''' – Organic Food and produce chain, purchased in 2009 and due to be rebranded to [[Thomas Dux Grocer]]. The Macro Wholefoods branded organic products (100 line items) will be sold through [[Woolworths (supermarket)|'''Woolworths''']] and [[Thomas Dux Grocer]].

===Liquor===
*'''[[Safeway Liquor]]''' – A department of Safeway supermarket stores.
*'''[[BWS]]''' – (Beer Wine Spirits) Liquor stores located away from the company's supermarkets.
*'''[[Dan Murphy's]]''' – Large liquor barns often referred to as Liquor Supermarkets. Dan Murphy's is one of the company's best growth performers, with plans for up to 100 stores (from the current 55) to exist within the next 2–3 years.
*'''[[Woolworths (supermarket)|Woolworths Liquor]]''' – A department of Woolworths supermarket stores. They are not located in [[Queensland]] and [[Tasmania]], as State law there prohibits liquor sales at supermarkets. These stores were formerly known as &quot;Mac's Liquor&quot;.
*'''[[Cellarmasters]]'''

===Hotels===
* '''[[ALH Group]]'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alhgroup.com.au |title=Home |publisher=ALH Group |date= |accessdate=11 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; – Hotel and Poker Machine operator, which is 75% owned by Woolworths Limited.

===Petrol===
*'''[[Caltex Woolworths|Caltex Woolworths/Safeway]]''' – Petrol stations located both free standing and adjacent to Woolworths and Safeway supermarkets

===General merchandise===
*'''[[Big W]]''' – Discount Department Store chain, which sell a wide range of general merchandise. BIG W represents about 8% of group sales and reputedly has aggressive expansion plans compared with competitors [[Kmart (Australia)|Kmart]] and [[Target (Australia)|Target]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Consumer electronics===
*'''[[Dick Smith (retailer)|Dick Smith]]''' – Sell a wide range of consumer goods such as computer products. (Formerly 'Dick Smith Electronics')
*'''[[Dick Smith Large]]''' – Larger Dick Smith stores with a focus on consumer entertainment products (Formerly 'Dick Smith Powerhouse').
*'''[[Tandy (Australia)|Tandy]]''' – Similar to Dick Smith Electronics stores, but smaller and lacking the hobbyist components (Tandy brand is being phased out, becoming smaller Dick Smith stores).

===''Everyday'' Services===
*'''[[Everyday Rewards (Australia)|Everyday Rewards]]''' – Loyalty program offering customers fuel saving offers, [[Qantas]] Frequent Flyer points, and personalised shopping offers. As of February 2010, there were 4.6 million Everyday Rewards cards registered, with 2.1 million linked with Qantas Frequent Flyer memberships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.asx.com.au/asx/statistics/displayAnnouncement.do?display=pdf&amp;idsId=01041760|format=PDF|title=Woolworths Limited – Half Year Presentation HY10 |accessdate=23 March 2010 |work= |date=28 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Everyday Money]]''' – First product is the Everyday Money Credit Card. Points are earned for purchases made at Woolworths Limited stores, points are converted to shopping vouchers. Second product launched in June 2010 is the Everyday Money Prepaid MasterCard.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.everydaymoney.com.au/edm/wps/portal/!ut/p/c1/04_SB8K8xLLM9MSSzPy8xBz9CP0os3ijIAs_X-9gYwMDb38DA89gXw-PUGMnAwNfA6B8JB55IxTdFi5ezkBZczNHT2dLoGIDfT-P_NxU_YLciHIAWWtU1g!!/dl2/d1/L2dJQSEvUUt3QS9ZQnB3LzZfMlI4Tk1LUzMwR0oyRDBJMlRRTFNERTEwVjc!/&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Everyday Mobile]]''' – Pre-paid mobile service running on the [[Optus]] network – $2 SIM cards are purchased in stores and recharge is available in store or online.

===Home Improvement===
*'''[[Masters Home Improvement]]''' – In 2009, Woolworths announced a joint venture with US home improvement retailer [[Lowe's]] to enter the home improvement market.&lt;ref&gt;http://media.corporate-ir.net/media_files/irol/14/144044/asx/753818.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Based on documents submitted to the government, Woolworths' hardware chain will be named Masters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.smh.com.au/business/woolies-out-to-nail-hardware-20100406-rph3.html | work=The Sydney Morning Herald | title=Woolies out to nail hardware | date=7 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was confirmed on 2 May 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.insideretailing.com.au/IR/IRNews/Woolies-confirms-home-improvement-name-708.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; The first store will be located in [[Braybrook]], Victoria and is scheduled to open in September 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://phx.corporate-ir.net/External.File?item=UGFyZW50SUQ9MTUzMzB8Q2hpbGRJRD0tMXxUeXBlPTM=&amp;t=1&lt;/ref&gt; [[Springfield Central]], Queensland is also scheduled to open in late 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.qt.com.au/story/2010/06/24/ipswich-diy-store-wars-Woolworths-hardware-store&lt;/ref&gt; As of November 2011, they have opened 5 stores, 18 more under construction and plans to take it to 150 sites in 5 years.&lt;ref&gt;http://media.corporate-ir.net/media_files/IROL/14/144044/woolworths.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Zealand Divisions==
===Progressive Enterprises===
[[Progressive Enterprises]] (PEL) runs the following supermarket chains: 

*'''[[Countdown (supermarket)|Countdown]]''' – Progressive Enterprises' and Woolworths' New Zealand flagship supermarket chain – 104 full-service discount supermarkets, operating across the North and South Islands of New Zealand.
** '''[[Woolworths Supermarkets (New Zealand)|Woolworths]]''' – 28 full-service supermarkets, operating across the North Island of New Zealand, plus [[Waiheke Island]] – all stores rebranding to Countdown by late 2012.
** '''[[Foodtown]]''' – 20 full-service supermarkets, operating in Auckland, Hamilton, and Tauranga – all stores rebranding to Countdown by late 2012.
* '''[[Supervalue|SuperValue]]''' – franchised convenience supermarket
* '''[[Fresh Choice Supermarkets|Freshchoice]]''' – franchised full-service supermarket
* '''Woolworths @ Gull''' – 22 Woolworths Quickstop and Woolworths Micro convenience supermarkets, operating in the North Island on [[Gull Petroleum]] fuel sites.
PEL also operates internet grocery stores in the name of Woolworths Home Shopping&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.woolworths.co.nz/homeshopping/default.asp],&lt;/ref&gt; and Foodtown Online.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.foodtown.co.nz/homeshopping/default.asp Online Food Shopping – Online Food Recipes – Foodtown Online Supermarket New Zealand&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dick Smith Electronics NZ===
*'''[[Dick Smith Electronics]]''' – sell a wide range of hobby electronic products and consumer goods such as computer products.
*'''Dick Smith Powerhouse''' – Large stores with a focus on consumer entertainment products.

==India==
*'''Croma/Tata Group Venture''' – In 2006 Woolworths and the [[Tata Group]] of [[India]] announced an electronics retailing venture on the subcontinent. Due to the legal framework, foreign companies are prevented from operating retail businesses in [[India]]. Due to this, Woolworths will act as a wholesaler to the [[Tata Group]]. The stores are based on the Dick Smith Powerhouse format.

Tata Group ends deal with Woolworths. According to the report in The Economic Times of India, Woolworths was surprised that the deal had a time limit on it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=The Sydney Morning Herald |date=25 October 2011|accessdate=25 October 2011| title=Blow for Woolies as Tata ends Indian venture|url=http://www.smh.com.au/business/blow-for-woolies-as-tata-ends-indian-venture-20111024-1mgcc.html | first=Kruger| last=Collin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Former chains and brands==
*'''[[Woolworths Food Fair]]''' – The name given to the company's growing food-retailing interests in the 1960s to differentiate them from the variety-based stores. This name was absorbed when the decision was made to use the original Woolworths name for the company's food stores and supermarkets instead of its variety stores.
*'''[[Woolworths Variety]]''' – The name given to the company's traditional variety stores to differentiate them from the company's food-retailing interests, when the decision was made to use the original Woolworths name for the company's food stores and supermarkets instead of its variety stores. These variety stores were progressively divested as Woolworths focused on food retailing and developed large-scale discount department stores.
*'''[[Woolworths Family Centre]]''' – Woolworths opened its first [[hypermarket]] at [[Booval, Queensland|Booval]] near [[Ipswich, Queensland]] in November 1969 under the [[Big W]] name. A second hypermarket was opened in 1970 in [[Indooroopilly, Queensland|Indooroopilly]], [[Brisbane]], under the Woolworths Family Centre name. The early popularity of these stores led to Woolworths establishing hypermarkets around Australia using the Woolworths Family Centre name. However the concept failed to perform, and the hypermarkets were re-established as separated [[Woolworths (supermarkets)|Woolworths]] supermarkets and [[Big W]] discount department stores in the late 1970s to early 1980s.
*'''[[Crazy Prices]]''' – A variety store chain that sold discounted merchandise. These stores were sold to (and formed part of) rival [[Go-Lo]] in 2001, although the last store with Crazy Prices branding didn't close until 2005 in [[Port Macquarie]]. Its slogan was &quot;The Bargains are Better&quot;.
*'''[[Rockmans]]''' – Women's clothing retailer acquired by the group in 1960 and was a major operating division until its sale in 2000.
*'''[[Woolworths Plus Petrol]]''' – The original name of the petrol sites owned by Woolworths before the joint venture with [[Caltex]].
*'''[[Woolworths Metro]]''' – Inner-urban convenience stores located in the key metropolitan areas of Sydney and Brisbane selling a range of pre-prepared meals for the 'time poor' customer. Woolworths Metro was also the name of Woolworths' flagship five-storey store at Town Hall in Sydney until 2003 when it reverted back to the Woolworths supermarket brand.

*'''[[Roelf Vos]]''' and '''[[Purity]]''' supermarkets – Two Tasmanian supermarkets located in the north and south respectively. Bought out by Woolworths (Purity in 1981 and Roelf Vos in 1982) however they continued to trade under these names until being rebranded as Woolworths in 2000. The stores adopted the standard Woolworths look and feel of their mainland counterparts but with the 'Purity' or 'Roelf Vos' text in the logo in place of Woolworths.

==History==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Woolworth's]] --&gt;
[[Image:Woolworthssyd.jpg|thumb|right|191px|Woolworths in the Sydney CBD]]
Woolworths opened its first store, the Woolworths Stupendous Bargain Basement, in the old Her Majesty's Arcade [[Pitt Street, Sydney]], where Centrepoint now stands, on 5 December 1924. Its nominal capital was just £25,000 and although 15,000 shares were offered to the public, only 11,707 shares were subscribed for by 29 people, including the five founders – Percy Christmas, Stanley Chatterton, Cecil Scott Waine, George Creed and Ernest Williams. One of the foundation investors was [[Preston Lanchester Gowing]], the then chairman of [[Gowings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://esvc000089.wic034u.server-web.com/downloads/2002%20Annual%20Report.pdf |title=GOW372_Annual(pg1-14) |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=11 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name on the draft prospectus drawn up by Cecil Scott Waine was &quot;Wallworths Bazaar&quot; – a play on the [[F.W. Woolworth Company|F.W. Woolworth]] name (the owner of the Woolworth's chain in the United States and United Kingdom). However, according to Ernest Robert Williams, Percy Christmas dared him to register the name Woolworths instead, which he succeeded in doing after finding out the name was available for use in [[New South Wales]]. Accordingly, Woolworths Ltd in Australia has no connection with the [[F.W. Woolworth Company]] in the United States. 

The new Woolworths store was innovative; it was the first variety store in the world to use cash registers that print receipts for customers.

Christmas set up a New Zealand general merchandise operation in Wellington in 1929. Woolworths New Zealand opened its first food store in Auckland in 1956, and supermarkets in 1971. Woolworths New Zealand was sold to the company that is now Lion Nathan in 1979, then sold to Dairy Farm International in 1990, now owned by [[Progressive Enterprises]], a subsidiary of Foodland Associated Limited of Australia. In 2005 Woolworths Limited and Metcash Holdings ([[IGA (Australian supermarket group)|IGA]]) agreed to purchase a demerged Foodland, and [[Progressive Enterprises]] and 23 of Foodland's [[Action (supermarket chain)|Action]] supermarkets came under Woolworths' ownership. This acquisition brought total store numbers in Australia to near 750.

During the late 1920s the company grew, with a second store in Sydney and stores in [[Brisbane]] and [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]]. It grew further in the 1930s, despite the depression, until by the end of 1933 it had 23 stores. In 1933 the first store in [[Melbourne]] was opened. On 1 April 1936 the company bought eight stores from Edments Ltd and opened its first store in [[Adelaide]]. 

[[World War II]] slowed the growth of Woolworths and the Australian and United States military used Woolworths' warehouses in Sydney for storage. After the war expansion was rapid and in 1955 Woolworths opened its 200th store, in the Civic Centre in [[Canberra]] (since closed). At this point Woolworths was still mainly a variety chain and had not moved into the food sector that uses the &quot;Woolworths&quot; brand today. This move began in 1955 when it opened its first supermarket at [[Beverly Hills, Sydney|Beverly Hills]], south-west of Sydney. The company bought the Rockmans chain of women's clothing stores in 1960. 

In the 1970s, the company started to open Big W discount department stores and the slow removal of many variety products from the supermarket and variety stores began. This process finished in 1989 when the last of the Woolworths Variety stores was closed (except the one in [[Rundle Mall]]) and the &quot;Family Centres&quot; were split into separate Big W and Woolworths supermarket stores. Woolworths acquired the Dick Smith Electronics consumer electronics chain in 1981 and expanded the consumer electronics arm of its business with the purchase of the Tandy chain in Australia from InterTan Inc in 2001. The company sold the Rockmans chain in 2000.

In 1985 the acquisition of the 126 Safeway stores in eastern Australia made Woolworths the largest food retailer in Australia. Safeway stores were in Victoria, New South Wales and Queensland and included Food Barns in Queensland and northern New South Wales. The stores were acquired following an agreement whereby [[Safeway Stores Inc.|Safeway]] acquired a 19.99% interest in Woolworths Limited. Woolworths and Safeway supermarkets in Victoria traded under the Safeway brand, and Safeway's Food Barns in Queensland and New South Wales became part of Woolworths.

Around this time the supermarket chain had run eight small supermarket chains including the Queensland-based [[Food For Less]] and the Sydney-based Flemings, both of which survive.

In 1989 the company was acquired by [[Industrial Equity Limited]] and was a wholly owned subsidiary until 1993, when it was floated in the biggest share sale (at that time) in Australia's history. 

In 1996 Woolworths entered the petrol market, initially with wholly owned &quot;Plus Petrol&quot; outlets located in shopping centre parking lots. In 2004, as part of a loyalty program aimed at attracting customers to supermarkets through the lure of four cent a litre discounts, Woolworths entered into an agreement with Caltex to co-brand some Caltex outlets as [[Caltex Woolworths]]. These joint venture outlets are supplied with fuel by Caltex and with groceries by Woolworths, and accept Woolworths cards and discount dockets.

In 1999, Woolworths began a joint venture with the Commonwealth Bank called Woolworths Ezy Banking, but was scaled back by 2006.  In 2005 the company reached an agreement with the ANZ Banking Group to install ATMs at Woolworths locations. Additionally, by 2008 it had invested in financial services infrastructure and expertise, building a team of 50 staff for this purpose.&lt;ref name = &quot;AFR&quot;&gt;{{Cite document| publisher=Australian Financial Review |title=Retailers take on the banks…again| date=30 January 2008|pages=1, 61| postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997 Woolworths opened its first Metro convenience store, in [[Sydney]], converting their premier variety store for 32 years to this format with the lower ground floor specialising in a large range of ‘prepared meals’ to cater for the increasing numbers of city dwellers. Subsequent stores opened in [[Coogee]], [[Boronia Park]] and [[West Pennant Hills]] in Sydney and [[Ascot, Queensland|Ascot]] in [[Brisbane]]. Stores that have since been sold or re-branded are [[Newtown]], [[Waterloo, New South Wales|Waterloo]] and its Sydney city store (all in Sydney).

Woolworths started to expand into liquor businesses with the acquisition of [[Dan Murphy's]] in 1998. By 2001, the [[BWS]] chain had been established.  With [[Queensland]] licensing laws dictating that retail outlets must be operated by a hotelier, Woolworths moved into the hotel industry in 2005 in a joint venture with experienced hotel operator Bruce Mathieson, purchasing hotelier Australian Leisure and Hospitality Group (ALH). Later in 2005 the ALH Group expanded its portfolio to 250 hotels by acquiring the Taverner Hotel Group and the Bruce Mathieson Group.  The ALH Group is 25% owned by Bruce Mathieson and 75% owned by Woolworths. Statistics provided during the acquisition of the Taverner group showed that over one third of sales are made up of gaming/poker machine takings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.woolworthslimited.com.au/resources/taverners+analyst+presentation.pdf Woolworths Limited taverners analyst presentation]{{Dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of poker machines owned by Woolworths and Bruce Mathieson after ALH acquisitions was 10,722.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/news/business/retail-giants-place-side-bet-on-pokies/2006/03/28/1143441151233.html &quot;Retail Giants Place Side Bet on Pokies&quot;], theage.com.au, 28 March 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 the company had three major events: 
*in June it opened a buying office in Hong Kong to cut out the intermediary in sourcing foreign-produced items;
*it announced a venture with the Tata Group in India to introduce Dick Smiths Electronics stores to that country;
*in September it announced that it had taken a 10% strategic stake in the [[The Warehouse Group]] in New Zealand.

In 2006, Woolworths rolled out new Retalix [[point of sale]] systems running on [[IBM]] POS hardware with [[liquid crystal display|LCD]] touchscreens throughout all its stores.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Australia's Woolworths Meets Store Service Strategy with Retalix StoreLine|accessdate=14 October 2007|publisher=Internet Retailer|url=http://www.internetretailer.com/internet/marketing-conference/66458-australias-woolworths-meets-store-service-strategy-retalix-storeline.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2007 Woolworths announced that it was planning to launch a general purpose credit card in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Now it's Woolworths the credit card people|date=27 August 2007|accessdate=6 September 2007|publisher=Sydney Morning Herald|url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/national/now-its-woolworths-the-credit-card-people/2007/08/27/1188067034518.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is expected to offer credit cardholders reward vouchers redeemable through its store network.&lt;ref name = &quot;AFR&quot;/&gt;  [[HSBC]] was subsequently named as its credit card partner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Woolies way ahead at checkout|date=27 February 2008|accessdate=27 February 2008|publisher=Melbourne Herald Sun|url=http://www.news.com.au/heraldsun/story/0,21985,23282036-664,00.html}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Woolworths subsequently announced that the ''Woolworths Everyday Money MasterCard'' would be launched on 26 August 2008 and allows customers to earn shopping cards redeemable at Woolworths group retailers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=news.com.au|title=Woolworths launches new credit card|url=http://www.news.com.au/business/story/0,,24199187-462,00.html|date=18 August 2008|accessdate=18 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=The Sheet|title=Woolies MasterCard debuts in two weeks|date=15 August 2008|accessdate=18 August 2008|url=http://www.thesheet.com/nl05_news_selected.php?act=2&amp;stream=1&amp;selkey=7022&amp;hlc=2&amp;hlw=}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was suggested Woolworths could earn approximately $20m from credit cards in three years and that it was targeting 100,000 to 150,000 cardholders in the first year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|publisher=Australian Financial Review|title=Woolies makes move into credit cards|date=19 August 2008|pages=13|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Into 2008, a [http://www.wakeupwoolworths.com/ ''Wake Up Woolworths''] campaign, largely funded by the [[Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union]], was pushing Woolworths to sever its relationship with Asia Pulp &amp; Paper over claims of deforestation of Indonesian rainforests. Asia Pulp &amp; Paper supplies Woolworths' ''Select Brand'' tissue products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=The Age, Melbourne|date=5 June 2008|accessdate=14 July 2008|title=Woolies under fire over pulp products|url=http://business.theage.com.au/woolies-under-fire-over-pulp-products-20080604-2lx4.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Woolworths Limited (Australia)}}
*[http://www.woolworthslimited.com.au/ Woolworths Limited]

{{Woolworths}}
{{S&amp;P/ASX 50}}
{{Business in Australia}}
{{Supermarkets Companies of Australia}}

[[Category:Woolworths Limited| ]]
[[Category:Woolworth companies]]

[[de:Woolworths (Australien)]]
[[fr:Woolworths]]
[[id:Woolworths Limited]]
[[ja:ウールワース]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
