<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5161996" ns="0" title="Uganda–Tanzania War"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
| conflict    = Uganda-Tanzania War
| image       = [[File:LocationUganda&amp;Tanzania.png|300px]]
| date        = October 30, 1978 – April 11, 1979
| place       = [[Uganda]]
| result      = Tanzanian victory; overthrow of [[Idi Amin]] in Uganda
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Uganda}} [[Uganda under Idi Amin|Uganda]] &lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|Libyan Arab Jamahiriya|1977}} [[History of Libya under Muammar Gaddafi#Great Socialist People.27s Libyan Arab Jamahiriya|Libya]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[PLO]]&lt;ref name=loc1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field%28DOCID+ug0140%29 |title=Idi Amin and Military Rule |work=Country Study: Uganda |publisher=[[Library of Congress]] |date=December 1990|quote=By mid-March 1979, about 2,000 Libyan troops and several hundred Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) fighters had joined in the fight to save Amin's regime |accessdate=5 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flag|Tanzania}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Uganda}} [[Uganda National Liberation Army|UNLA]]
| commander1  = '''Uganda''':
* {{flagicon|Uganda}} [[Idi Amin]]
'''Libya''':
* {{flagicon|Libya|1977}} [[Muammar Gaddafi]]
| commander2  = '''Tanzania''':
* {{flagicon|Tanzania}} [[Julius Nyerere]]
* {{flagicon|Tanzania}} [[Abdallah Twalipo]]
* {{flagicon|Tanzania}} [[Tumainiel Kiwelu]]
'''UNLA''':
* {{flagicon|Uganda}} [[Tito Okello]]
* {{flagicon|Uganda}} [[Yoweri Museveni]]
* {{flagicon|Uganda}} [[David Oyite-Ojok]]
| strength1   = 70,000+ Ugandan Army troops&lt;br&gt;3,000 Libyan troops&lt;br&gt;200+ Palestinian troops
| strength2   = 100,000 Tanzanians&lt;br&gt;6,000 Ugandan resistance troops
| casualties1 = ~1,500 Ugandans&lt;br&gt;~500 Libyans&lt;ref name=erols&gt;[http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat3.htm Secondary Wars and Atrocities of the Twentieth Century]&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = ~1,000&lt;ref name=erols/&gt;
| notes       = 
}}
{{History of Uganda}}
{{History of Tanzania}}

The '''Uganda–Tanzania War''' (usually referred to in [[Uganda]] as '''the Liberation War''') was fought between Uganda and [[Tanzania]] in 1978–1979, and led to the overthrow of [[Idi Amin]]'s regime. Idi Amin's forces included thousands of troops sent by [[Muammar Gaddafi]], and some [[Palestine|Palestinian]] support.

==Events leading to the war==
Relations between [[Tanzania]] and [[Uganda]] had been strained for several years before the war started. After Amin seized power in a [[1971 Ugandan coup d'état|military coup in 1971]], the Tanzanian leader [[Julius Nyerere]] offered sanctuary to Uganda's ousted president, [[Milton Obote]]. Obote was joined by 20,000 refugees fleeing Amin's attempts to wipe out opposition. A year later, a group of exiles based in Tanzania attempted, unsuccessfully, to invade Uganda and remove Amin. Amin blamed Nyerere for backing and arming his enemies. The relationship between Uganda and Tanzania remained strained for many years.

In early October 1978, dissident troops ambushed Amin at the presidential lodge in [[Kampala]], but he escaped with his family in a helicopter.&lt;ref name=time_nov_1978&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,946151-2,00.html &quot;An Idi-otic Invasion&quot;], ''[[Time (magazine)|TIME]]'' magazine, Nov. 13, 1978.&lt;/ref&gt; This was during a period when the number of Amin's close associates had shrunk significantly, and he faced increasing dissent from within Uganda. When General [[Mustafa Adrisi]], Amin's Vice President, was injured in a suspicious car accident, troops loyal to Adrisi (and other soldiers who were disgruntled for other reasons) [[mutiny|mutinied]]. Amin sent troops against the mutineers (which included members of the elite Simba Battalion), some of whom had fled across the Tanzanian border.&lt;ref name=loc1/&gt;&lt;ref name=time_nov_1978/&gt; The rebellion spilled over into Tanzania, where Tanzania-based anti-Amin exiles joined the fighting against Amin's troops.

Uganda declared a state of war against Tanzania, and sent troops to invade and [[annexation|annex]] part of the [[Kagera Region|Kagera]] region of Tanzania, which Amin claimed belonged to Uganda.

==The war==
Nyerere mobilized the [[Tanzania People's Defence Force]] and counterattacked. In a few weeks, the Tanzanian army was expanded from less than 40,000 troops to over 100,000 including members of the [[police]], [[prison|prison services]], [[national service]], and the [[militia]]. The Tanzanians were joined by several anti-Amin groups consisting of Ugandan exiles, who at a conference in [[Moshi]] ([[Moshi Conference]]) had united as the [[Uganda National Liberation Army]] (UNLA). These included [[Kikosi Maalum]] commanded by [[Tito Okello]] and [[David Oyite Ojok]], [[FRONASA]] commanded by [[Yoweri Museveni]], and [[Save Uganda Movement]] commanded by [[Akena p'Ojok]], [[William Omaria]], and [[Ateker Ejalu]]. 

The Tanzanian Army acquired a Russian [[Katyusha rocket launcher|BM Katyusha]] rocket launcher (known in Uganda as ''saba saba''), with which they started to fire on targets in Uganda.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationaudio.com/News/EastAfrican/15042002/Features/Magazine3.html &quot;Fighting for Amin&quot;], ''The East African'', April 8, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; The Ugandan Army retreated steadily. [[Libya]]'s [[Muammar Gaddafi]] sent 2,500 troops to aid Amin, equipped with [[T-54]] and [[T-55]] tanks, BTR APCs, BM-21 Katyusha MRLs, artillery, [[MiG-21]]s, and a [[Tu-22]] bomber.&lt;ref name=pollack&gt;Kenneth M. Pollack, ''Arabs at War: Military Effectiveness 1948–91'', University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 2002, p.369-373, ISBN 0-8032-3733-2&lt;/ref&gt; However the Libyans soon found themselves on the front line, while Ugandan Army units were using supply trucks to carry their newly plundered wealth in the opposite direction.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.onwar.com/aced/chrono/c1900s/yr75/ftanzaniauganda1978.htm OnWar.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Libyan troops were a mix of regular Libyan Army units, People's Militia, and sub-Saharan Africans of the [[Islamic Legion]], a further force created by Libya for this type of expeditionary mission.&lt;ref name=pollack/&gt; The Tanzanians, joined by UNLA dissidents, moved north for Kampala but halted at the vast deep-water swamp north of [[Lukaya]]. The Tanzanians decided to send the 201st Brigade directly across the causeway over the swamp while the better-quality 208th Brigade skirted the western edge of the swamp as an alternative in case the causeway was blocked or destroyed. A planned attack by a brigade-sized Libyan force with fifteen T-55s, a dozen APCs, and BM-21 MRLs, intended to reach [[Masaka]], instead collided with the Tanzanian force at Lukaya on 10 March and sent the 201st Brigade reeling backwards in disarray. However, a Tanzanian counter-attack on the night of 11–12 March from two directions, involving a reorganised 201st Brigade attacking from the south and the 208th Brigade from the north-west, was successful, with many Libyan units, including the militia, breaking and retreating at a run. Libyan casualties were reported at 200 plus another 200 allied Ugandans.

Tanzanian and UNLA forces met little resistance after the Battle of Lukuya and carried on west toward Kampala, first taking the Entebbe airfield after some fighting, and then [[The Liberation of Kampala|taking Kampala]] itself on 10 April 1979. Few Ugandan or Libyan units gave much resistance, and Pollack says the greatest problem for the Tanzanian troops was their own lack of maps of the city.&lt;ref name=pollack/&gt; Amin fled, first to Libya and later to Saudi Arabia. The Libyan forces retreated to [[Jinja, Uganda|Jinja]] and then were repatriated finally through Kenya and Ethiopia. The Tanzanian army remained in Uganda to maintain peace while the UNLF (the political wing of the UNLA) organized elections to return the country to civilian rule.

The Tanzanian Government struck and distributed a [[campaign medal]], known as the ''Nishani ya Vita''.  The [[obverse]] bears the inscriptions '''''Vita-1978-1979''''' (top) and '''''Tanzania''''' (bottom). The [[reverse]] is plain.

==Aftermath==
===Uganda===
{{Main|Uganda since 1979}}
The period following the ousting of Amin proved to be a time of intense competition and fighting for power among different groups made up of political and ethnic rivals. [[Yusuf Lule]] had been installed as president by Tanzania. In June 1979, following a dispute over the extent of presidential powers, the [[National Consultative Commission]] (NCC), which was then the supreme governing body of the UNLF, replaced Lule with [[Godfrey Binaisa]]. Binaisa was himself removed on 12 May 1980 by the Military Commission, a powerful organ of the UNLF headed by the [[Paulo Muwanga]], and whose deputy was [[Yoweri Museveni]] (then leader of [[Uganda Patriotic Movement]]). The country was then led by the [[Presidential Commission of Uganda]] with among others [[Paulo Muwanga]], [[Yoweri Museveni]], [[Oyite Ojok]] and [[Tito Okello]]. The Presidential Commission governed Uganda until the December 1980 general elections which were won by [[Milton Obote]]'s [[Uganda Peoples Congress]]. The elections were bitterly disputed. Yoweri Museveni alleged [[electoral fraud]] and declared an armed rebellion against the government of Obote, plunging the country into the civil war which came to be known as the [[Ugandan Bush War]].

===Tanzania===
Tanzania, on the other hand, received no help from other countries in the [[Organization of African Unity]], which had denounced Tanzania's invasion (and for its role as a backer of the 1977 coup in the [[Seychelles]] which brought [[France-Albert René]] to power) as a breach of respect for national sovereignty. As a result, the government in [[Dar es Salaam]] had to foot the bill for the invasion and subsequent peacekeeping role from its own coffers, further driving the country into poverty; Tanzania would not fully recover from the cost of the war until Uganda paid back Tanzania's debt in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://allafrica.com/stories/200704110882.html Uganda: Country Pays Tanzania Shs120 Billion Amin War Debt]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}
*[http://www.iss.co.za/pubs/ASR/10No1/Lupogo.html Tanzania Civil-military Relations and Political Stability]
*[http://www.idiamindada.com/A_Daring_Rescue.html Details of TPDF brigade movement during invasion] (half way down page)
*{{loc}}—[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/ugtoc.html Uganda]

==Further reading==
*Mambo, Andrew; Julian Schofield (2007-12-01). &quot;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3719/is_200712/ai_n24394498 Military Diversion in the 1978 Uganda-Tanzania War]&quot;. Journal of Political and Military Sociology.

[[Category:Idi Amin]]
[[Category:Wars involving Tanzania]]
[[Category:Wars involving Uganda]]
[[Category:Wars involving Libya]]
[[Category:Muammar Gaddafi]]
[[Category:Military history of Tanzania]]
[[Category:Wars involving the states and peoples of Africa]]
[[Category:1978 in Uganda]]
[[Category:1978 in Tanzania]]
[[Category:1979 in Uganda]]
[[Category:1979 in Tanzania]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1978]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1979]]

[[ar:حرب أوغندا-تنزانيا]]
[[bg:Угандийско-танзанийска война]]
[[de:Uganda-Tansania-Krieg]]
[[es:Guerra Uganda-Tanzania]]
[[fr:Guerre ougando-tanzanienne]]
[[id:Perang Uganda-Tanzania]]
[[it:Guerra ugandese-tanzaniana]]
[[hu:Ugandai–tanzániai háború]]
[[no:Krigen mellom Uganda og Tanzania]]
[[pl:Wojna ugandyjsko-tanzańska]]
[[pt:Guerra Uganda-Tanzânia]]
[[ru:Угандийско-танзанийская война]]
[[sr:Угандско-танзанијски рат]]
[[sv:Kriget mellan Uganda och Tanzania]]
[[vec:Guera ugandexe tanzaniana]]
[[yo:Ogun láàrin Ùgándà àti Tànsáníà]]
[[zh:烏坦戰爭]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
