<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="517620" ns="0" title="Tom Seaver"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other persons|Thomas Seaver}}
{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Tom Seaver
|image=Tom Seaver's Last Pitch.jpg
|caption=Tom Seaver on September 28, 2008.
|position=[[Pitcher]]
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|1944|11|17}}
|birth_place=[[Fresno, California]]
|debutdate=April 13
|debutyear=1967
|debutteam=New York Mets
|finaldate=September 19
|finalyear=1986
|finalteam=Boston Red Sox
|stat1label=[[Win–loss record (pitching)|Win–loss record]]
|stat1value=311–205
|stat2label=[[Earned run average]]
|stat2value=2.86
|stat3label=[[Strikeout]]s
|stat3value=3,640
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[New York Mets]] ({{By|1967}}–{{By|1977}})
* [[Cincinnati Reds]] ({{By|1977}}–{{By|1982}})
* [[New York Mets]] ({{By|1983}})
* [[Chicago White Sox]] ({{By|1984}}–{{By|1986}})
* [[Boston Red Sox]] ({{By|1986}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* 12× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] ([[1967 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1967]], [[1968 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1968]], [[1969 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1969]], [[1970 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1970]], [[1971 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1971]], [[1972 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1972]], [[1973 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1973]], [[1975 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1975]], [[1976 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1976]], [[1977 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1977]], [[1978 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1978]], [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1981]])
* [[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1969}})
* 3× [[NL Cy Young Award]] winner (1969, 1973, 1975)
* 1967 [[NL Rookie of the Year]]
* 2× [[NL TSN Pitcher of the Year]] (1969, 1975)
* Pitched a [[no-hitter]] on June 16, 1978
*[[New York Mets#Retired numbers|New York Mets #41]] retired
|hofdate={{By|1992}}
|hofvote=98.8% (first ballot)
}}
'''George Thomas &quot;Tom&quot; Seaver''' (born November 17, 1944), nicknamed '''&quot;Tom Terrific&quot;''' and '''&quot;The Franchise&quot;''', is a former [[Major League Baseball]] [[pitcher]]. He pitched from 1967-1986 for four different teams in his career, but is noted primarily for his time with the [[New York Mets]]. During a 20-year career, Seaver compiled 311 [[win (baseball statistics)|wins]], 3,640 [[strikeout]]s, 61 [[shutouts]] and a 2.86 [[earned run average]]. In {{By|1992}}, he was inducted into the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame]] by the highest percentage ever recorded (98.84%), and has the only plaque at [[Cooperstown]] wearing a New York Mets hat. As of 2010, Tom Seaver and [[Gil Hodges]] (played for the Mets in 1962-63) are the only Met players to have their jersey numbers retired by the team (Gil Hodges' number was retired as a manager even though he also played for the Mets).

He won the [[National League]] [[MLB Rookie of the Year award|Rookie of the Year Award]] in 1967, and three NL [[Cy Young Award]]s as the league's best pitcher. Seaver is the Mets' all-time leader in wins, and is considered by many baseball experts as one of the best [[starting pitcher]]s in the history of baseball.

==Early life &amp; development==
Seaver was born in [[Fresno, California]] to Betty Lee Cline and Charles Henry Seaver.&lt;ref&gt;[http://freepages.genealogy.rootsweb.com/~battle/celeb/seaver.htm Baseball Hall Of Fame&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Pitching for [[Fresno High School]], Seaver compensated for his lack of size and strength by developing great control on the mound. Despite being an All-City [[basketball]] player, he hoped to play baseball in college.

He joined the [[United States Marine Corps Reserves]] on June 28, 1962. He served with AIRFMFPAC 29 Palms, California through July {{By|1963}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usmc-mccs.org/sports/hof/2003-seaver.cfm Marine Corps Sports Hall of Fame], Retrieved July 1, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; After six months of active duty in the Reserves, Seaver enrolled at [[Fresno City College]]. 

In anticipation of the following season, he was being recruited to pitch for the [[University of Southern California]] by legendary Trojan coach [[Rod Dedeaux]].  Unsure as to whether Seaver was worthy of a scholarship, he was sent to pitch for the [[Alaska Goldpanners]] of [[Fairbanks, Alaska]], in 1964. After a stellar season &amp;mdash; in which he pitched and won a game in the national tournament with a [[Grand slam (baseball)|grand slam]] &amp;mdash; he was awarded a scholarship to USC. As a sophomore, Seaver posted a 10-2 record, and he was drafted in the tenth round of the [[1965 Major League Baseball Draft]] by the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]].  When Seaver asked for $70,000, however, the Dodgers passed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Golenbock 2002 187&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Golenbock|first=Peter|title=Amazin': The Miraculous History of New York's most Beloved Baseball Team|publisher=St. Martin's Griffin|year=2002|location=New York|pages=187|isbn=0-312-30992-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1966, he signed a contract with the [[Atlanta Braves]], who had drafted him in the first round of the secondary June draft (20th overall). However, the contract was voided by [[Baseball Commissioner]] [[William Eckert]] because his college team had played two exhibition games (although Seaver hadn't played). Seaver intended, then, to finish the college season, but because he had signed a pro contract, the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] ruled him ineligible. After Seaver's father complained to Eckert about the unfairness of the situation, and threatened with a lawsuit, Eckert ruled that other teams could match the Braves' offer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Golenbock 2002 187&quot;/&gt;  The Mets were subsequently awarded his signing rights in a lottery drawing among the three teams (the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] and [[Cleveland Indians]] being the two others) that were willing to match the Braves' terms.

==Professional playing career==
===New York Mets===
====Rookie of the Year====
Seaver spent one season with the [[Jacksonville Suns]] of the [[International League]], then joined [[New York]] in 1967. He won 16 games for the last-place Mets, with 18 complete games, 170 strikeouts, and a 2.76 ERA, all Mets records to that point, and was named the National League Rookie of the Year. He was also named to the [[1967 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1967 All-Star Game]], and got the save by pitching a scoreless 15th inning. In {{By|1968}}, he won 16 games again, and recorded over 200 strikeouts for the first of nine consecutive seasons, but the Mets moved up only one spot in the standings, to ninth.

====1969 Championship season====
In {{By|1969}}, Seaver and the [[1969 New York Mets season|Mets]] won their first [[1969 World Series|World Series]] championship. Seaver won a league-high 25 games and his first National League Cy Young Award. He also finished runner-up to [[Willie McCovey]] for the League's Most Valuable Player Award.

On July 9, before a crowd of over 59,000 at New York's [[Shea Stadium]], Seaver threw {{frac|8|1|3}} perfect innings against the division-leading [[1969 Chicago Cubs season|Chicago Cubs]]. Then, rookie backup outfielder [[Jim Qualls|Jimmy Qualls]] lined a clean single to left field, breaking up Seaver's [[perfect game]].

In the first-ever [[1969 National League Championship Series|NLCS]] game, Seaver outlasted [[1969 Atlanta Braves season|Atlanta]]'s [[Phil Niekro]] for a sloppy 9-5 victory. Seaver was also the starter for the Mets' first [[World Series]] game, but lost a 4-1 decision to the [[1969 Baltimore Orioles sseason|Baltimore Orioles]]' [[Mike Cuellar]]. Seaver then pitched a 10-inning complete-game for a 2-1 win in Game Four to put the Mets on the cusp of their first championship.

At year's end, Seaver was presented with both the [[Hickok Belt]] as the top professional athlete of the year, and ''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' magazine's &quot;[[Sportsman of the Year]]&quot; award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hickock Belt Tom Seaver|url=http://hickokbelt.com/winners/past-winners/winners/tom-seaver/|work=Hickokbelt.com|accessdate=19 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Leggett|first=William|title=TOM SEAVER - 12.22.69|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1083193/index.htm?eref=sisf|work=Sportsillustrated.cnn.com|publisher=Time Inc.|accessdate=19 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Continued excellence====
On April 22, {{By|1970}}, Seaver set a major league record by striking out the final 10 batters of the game in a 2-1 victory over the [[1970 San Diego Padres season|San Diego Padres]] at Shea Stadium.  Al Ferrara, who had homered in the second inning for the Padres' run, was the final strikeout victim of the game. In addition to his 10 consecutive strikeouts, Seaver tied [[Steve Carlton]]'s major league record with 19 strikeouts in a nine-inning game,&lt;ref name=&quot;baseball-reference.com&quot;&gt;http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NYN/NYN197004220.shtml Box Score of 19-strikeout game, April 22, 1970&lt;/ref&gt;. The Mets also won the game in which Carlton struck out 19, with Carlton victimized by Ron Swoboda's pair of 2-run homers in a 4-3 Mets victory in St. Louis on September 15, 1969.  (The record was later eclipsed by 20-strikeout games by [[Kerry Wood]], [[Randy Johnson]], and twice by [[Roger Clemens]].)  By mid-August, Seaver's record stood at 17-6 and he seemed well on his way to a second consecutive 20-victory season.  But he only won one of his last ten starts, including four on short rest, to finish 18-12. Nonetheless, Seaver led the National League in both ERA and strikeouts.

[[File:Tom Seaver at Shea Stadium 1974.jpg|thumb|Seaver at [[Shea Stadium]], 1974.]]
His {{By|1971}} season was arguably Seaver's finest year, when he led the league in ERA (1.76) and strikeouts (289 in 286 innings) while going 20-10.  However, he finished second in the Cy Young balloting to [[Ferguson Jenkins]] of the Chicago Cubs, due to Jenkins' league-leading 24 wins, 325 innings pitched, and exceptional control numbers. Seaver himself has said that 1971 was his best season.

Seaver had four more twenty-win seasons (20 in {{By|1971}}, 21 in {{By|1972}}, 22 in 1975 and 21 in {{By|1977}} (7 wins for the Mets, then 14 more after being traded to the Reds). He won two more Cy Young Awards ({{By|1973}} and 1975, both with the Mets).

During his tenure with the Mets, Seaver made 108 starts in which he pitched 9 or more innings and allowed 1 run or less. His record in those starts is 93 - 3 with 12 no-decisions. In seven of the 12 no-decisions, he pitched 10 or more innings. In the 12 no-decisions, he pitched a total of 117 innings, allowing 56 hits and 5 earned runs, compiling a 0.38 ERA.

Between 1970 and 1976, Seaver led the [[National League]] in strikeouts five of the seven seasons, finishing second in {{By|1972}} and third in {{By|1974}}. Seaver also won three ERA titles as a Met. A famous quote about Seaver is attributed to [[Reggie Jackson]]: &quot;Blind men come to the park just to hear him pitch.&quot;  Seaver was perhaps the foremost latter-day exponent of &quot;drop and drive&quot; overhand delivery, but his powerful legs protected his arm, and ensured his longevity. Seaver was frequently compared to fellow Hall of Fame pitcher Christy Mathewson.

====1977 trade====
By 1977, the [[Free agent|free agency]] period had begun and contract negotiations between Mets ownership and Seaver were not going well. Seaver wanted to renegotiate his contract to bring his salary in line with what other top pitchers were making, but chairman of the board [[M. Donald Grant]], who by this time had been given [[wikt:carte blanche|carte blanche]] by Met management to do what he wished, refused to budge. Longtime ''[[New York Daily News]]'' columnist [[Dick Young (sportswriter)|Dick Young]] regularly wrote negative columns about Seaver's &quot;greedy&quot; demands. As for Seaver, he attempted to resolve the impasse by going to then-team owner Lorinda de Roulet, who along with then-GM Joe McDonald, had negotiated in principle a three-year contract extension by mid-June. But before the contract could be signed, Young wrote an unattributed story in the Daily News claiming that Seaver was being goaded by his wife to ask for more money because she was jealous of the fact that [[Nolan Ryan]] was making more money with the [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim|California Angels]]. Upon being informed of the story, Seaver informed de Roulet that he immediately wanted out, and asked McDonald to immediately trade him, feeling that he could not co-exist with M. Donald Grant.&lt;ref name=MM&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/baseball/mets/2007/06/17/2007-06-17_the_true_story_of_the_midnight_massacre-1.html?print=1&amp;page=all|title=The true story of The Midnight Massacre - How Tom Seaver was run out of town 30 years ago|author=Madden, Bill|newspaper=[[New York Daily News]]|date=June 17, 2007|accessdate=May 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In one of two trades that New York's sports reporters dubbed &quot;the Midnight Massacre&quot; (the other involved struggling outfielder [[Dave Kingman]]),  Seaver was traded to the Cincinnati Reds on June 15, {{By|1977}} (the trading deadline for that year) for [[Pat Zachry]], [[Steve Henderson]], [[Doug Flynn]], and [[Dan Norman]]. Seaver would go 14-3 with [[1977 Cincinnati Reds season|Cincinnati]] and win 21 games that season,, including an emotional 5-1 win over the Mets in his return to Shea Stadium.  Seaver struck out 11 in the return, and also hit a double. Seaver, who was immensely popular in New York, also received a lengthy ovation at the [[1977 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1977 All-Star Game]], which was held in New York's [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]].  His departure from New York sparked sustained negative fan reaction, as the Mets became the league's worst team, finishing in last place the next 3 seasons. Combined with the Yankees' resurgence in the market, attendance dipped in {{By|1978}}, and plunged in {{By|1979}} to 9,740 per game. M. Donald Grant was fired after the [[1978 New York Mets season|1978 season]], and Joe McDonald was fired after the [[1979 New York Mets season|1979 season]] following a sale of the team to publishing magnate [[Nelson Doubleday, Jr.]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.baseball-almanac.com/teams/metsattn.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; In a sardonic nod to the general manager, Shea Stadium acquired the nickname &quot;[[Grant's Tomb]]&quot;.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

===Cincinnati Reds===
After having thrown five one-hitters for New York, including two no-hitters that were broken up in the 9th inning, Seaver finally recorded a 4-0 [[no-hitter]] against the [[1978 St. Louis Cardinals season|St. Louis Cardinals]] on June 16, 1978 at [[Cinergy Field|Riverfront Stadium]]. It was the only no-hitter of his professional career.

Seaver was 75-46 during his time in Cincinnati. He led the Cincinnati pitching staff notably in 1979, when the Reds won the Western Division crown and (along with [[Mario Soto (baseball)|Mario Soto]]) in the strike-shortened 1981 season, when the Reds posted the best record in the major leagues. He was a close runner-up to [[Fernando Valenzuela]] for the {{By|1981}} Cy Young Award, a year in which he was 14-2, and was voted third and fourth in two other seasons. He suffered through an injury-ridden {{By|1982}} campaign, finishing 5-13.

===Return to New York===
On December 16, 1982, Seaver was traded back to the Mets, for [[Charlie Puleo]], [[Lloyd McClendon]], and [[Jason Felice]]. On April 5, {{By|1983}}, he tied [[Walter Johnson]]'s major league record of 14 Opening Day starts, shutting out the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] for six innings in a 2-0 Mets win. (He made two more such starts with the [[Chicago White Sox]] in {{By|1985}} and {{By|1986}} for a record total of 16 opening day assignments.) Despite a 9-14 record that season, Seaver had high expectations going into {{By|1984}} and intended to finish his career where he started it.

===300 wins===
Seaver and the Mets were stunned on January 20, 1984 when he was claimed in a free-agent compensation draft by the Chicago White Sox. The team (especially GM [[Frank Cashen]]) had incorrectly assumed that no one would pursue a high-salaried, 39-year-old starting pitcher, and left him off the protected list. Faced with either reporting to the White Sox or retiring, Seaver chose the former. The result for the Mets was an opening in the starting rotation that allowed [[Dwight Gooden]] to be part of the team.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

Seaver pitched two and a half seasons in Chicago, crafting his last [[shutout]] on July 19, [[1985 Chicago White Sox season|1985]] against the visiting [[1985 Cleveland Indians season|Indians]]. In an anomaly, Seaver won two games on May 9, 1984; he pitched the 25th and final inning of a game suspended the day before, picking up the win in [[relief pitcher|relief]], before starting and winning the day's regularly scheduled game. This unexpected win set up one of Seaver's most memorable moments.

After Seaver's 298&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; win, a reporter had pointed out to White Sox catcher [[Carlton Fisk]] that following his upcoming start in [[1985 Boston Red Sox season|Boston]], Seaver's next scheduled start would be in New York, and that the possibility existed that he might achieve the mark there. Fisk emphatically stated that Seaver ''would'' win in Boston, and then ''would'' win his 300&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;.

On August 4, 1985, Seaver recorded his 300&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; victory at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|New York]] against the [[1985 New York Yankees season|Yankees]], throwing a complete game. Coincidentally, it was [[Phil Rizzuto]] Day &amp;ndash; Seaver would later become Rizzuto's broadcast partner for Yankee games. [[Lindsey Nelson]], a Mets radio and TV announcer during Seaver's Mets days, called the final out for Yankees TV flagship [[WPIX]].

===Final season===
Late in 1985, his next-to-last season, Seaver almost returned to the Mets, as general manager Frank Cashen was poised to make a late-season trade. However, manager [[Davey Johnson]] vetoed the idea, and Seaver instead ended his career with the [[Boston Red Sox]] in [[1986 Boston Red Sox season|1986]] after being traded for [[Steve Lyons (baseball)|Steve Lyons]] in mid-season. Seaver's 311th and last win came on August 18, 1986 against the [[1986 Minnesota Twins season|Minnesota Twins]]. At the time of his retirement, Seaver was third on the all-time strikeout list (3,640), trailing only [[Nolan Ryan]] and [[Steve Carlton]]. No major league pitcher ever has matched his feat of striking out ten consecutive batters.&lt;ref name=&quot;baseball-reference.com&quot;/&gt; His career average of 6.85 strikeouts per nine innings is second only to Nolan Ryan (9.55)of any Hall of Famer with at least 300 wins. Seaver's lifetime ERA of 2.86 was third among starting pitchers in the [[Live Ball Era]], behind only [[Whitey Ford]] (2.73) and [[Sandy Koufax]] (2.76). ([[Jim Palmer]] and [[Andy Messersmith]] both have a career [[earned run average]] of 2.86 as well.) Seaver also holds the record for consecutive 200-strike-out seasons with nine (1968–1976).  Seaver's 61 career shutouts are second only to Warren Spahn (63) in the [[Live Ball Era]].  His career [[win–loss record (pitching)|win-loss record]] percentage of .603 is one of the highest of any Hall of Fame pitcher with 300 wins in the [[Live Ball Era]], and his record of 7.84 hits per nine innings is second only to [[Nolan Ryan]] (6.56) for all Hall of Fame pitchers with at least three hundred wins, and first among all HOF pitchers in any era with 300 wins, 3000 strikeouts, and a winning percentage of .600 or better. A knee injury prevented him from appearing against the Mets in the 1986 [[World Series]] between the Mets and Red Sox, but Seaver received among the loudest ovations during player introductions prior to Game 1. Roger Clemens attributes the time he shared with Seaver as 1986 Red Sox teammates as instrumental in helping him make the transition from thrower to pitcher. The Red Sox did not offer Seaver a contract to his liking for the {{By|1987}} season. His 1986 salary was $1 million; the Red Sox offered $500,000, which Seaver declined. When no new contract agreement was reached, Seaver was granted free agency on November 12, 1986.

In 1987, with their starting rotation decimated by injury, the [[1987 New York Mets season|Mets]] sought help from Seaver. Though no actual contract was signed, Seaver joined the club on June 6, and was hit hard in an exhibition game against the Triple-A [[Tidewater Tides]] on June 11. After similarly poor outings on the 16th &amp; 20th, he announced his retirement, saying, ''&quot;I've used up all the competitive pitches in my arm!&quot;'' The Mets retired his uniform number 41 in {{By|1988}} in a special Tom Seaver Day ceremony.  As of 2010, Seaver remains the only Met player to have his uniform number retired.  [[Casey Stengel]] and [[Gil Hodges]] had their numbers retired as Met managers, and Jackie Robinson had his number retired by all teams.  Their numbers—14 (Hodges), 37 (Stengel), 41 (Seaver), and 42 (Jackie Robinson) -- were posted in large numerals on the outfield fence at Shea Stadium, and are posted on the left field corner wall at Citi Field.

==Hall of Fame==
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = Metret41.PNG
|Name   = Tom Seaver
|Number = 41
|Team   = New York Mets
|Year   = 1988
|}}
Seaver was elected to the Baseball Hall of Fame on January 7, [[Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 1992|1992]].  He received the highest-ever percentage of votes with 98.84% (on 425 of 430 ballots), higher than [[Nolan Ryan]]'s 98.79% (491 of 497), and [[Ty Cobb]]'s 98.23% (222 of 226).  Reportedly, three of the five ballots that had omitted Seaver were blank, cast by writers protesting the Hall's decision to make [[Pete Rose]] ineligible for consideration.  Seaver is the only player enshrined in the Hall of Fame with a Mets cap on his plaque.  He was also inducted into the [[New York Mets Hall of Fame]] in {{By|1988}}, the Marine Corps Sports Hall of Fame in 2003 and the [[Cincinnati Reds Hall of Fame]] in 2006.

In {{By|1999}}, Seaver ranked 32nd on ''[[The Sporting News]]''' list of the 100 Greatest Baseball Players, the only player to have spent a majority of his career with the Mets to make the list. That year, he was also a nominee for the [[Major League Baseball]] [[Major League Baseball All-Century Team|All-Century Team]].  Baseball purists often compare him to Christy Mathewson for his combination of raw power, pinpoint control, intelligence, and intense scrutiny of his performance. Seaver was the foremost latter-day exponent of &quot;drop and drive&quot; overhand delivery that utilitized his powerful legs, took strain off of his arm, and helped ensure his longevity. He always credited the training he received in the Mets organization, citing the long careers of teammates Jerry Koosman, Nolan Ryan and Tug McGraw as further proof.  Seaver could also help himself at the plate. A good-hitting pitcher and proficient bunter, Seaver hit 12 home runs during his career, along with a relatively solid lifetime average for a pitcher of .154.

[[Hank Aaron]] stated that Seaver was the toughest pitcher he ever faced.  Seaver approached Aaron before his first All-Star Game in 1967 and asked Aaron for his autograph. Seaver felt the need to introduce himself to Aaron, as he was certain &quot;Hammerin' Hank&quot; would not know who he was. Aaron replied to Seaver, &quot;Kid, I know who you are, and before your career is over, I guarantee you everyone in this stadium will, too.&quot;  In an [[ESPN]] poll among his peers, [[Bob Gibson]], [[Juan Marichal]], [[Jim Palmer]], [[Nolan Ryan]], [[Steve Carlton]], [[Bert Blyleven]], and [[Don Sutton]] all agreed Seaver was &quot;the best&quot; of their generation of pitchers.

On September 28, {{By|2006}}, Seaver was chosen as the &quot;Hometown Hero&quot; for the Mets franchise by ESPN.  Seaver made a return to Shea Stadium during the &quot;Shea Goodbye&quot; closing ceremony on September 28, {{By|2008}}, where he threw out the final pitch in the history of the stadium to [[Mike Piazza]]. He and Piazza then opened the Mets' new home, [[Citi Field]] with the ceremonial first pitch on April 13, 2009.

==Broadcasting career==
Since retirement, Seaver has sometimes been a television [[color commentator]], working variously for the Mets, the [[New York Yankees]], and with [[Vin Scully]] in {{By|1989}} for [[Major League Baseball on NBC|NBC]]. Seaver replaced [[Joe Garagiola, Sr.|Joe Garagiola]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=NBC plans innovative ways to fill baseball void|date=January 31, 1989|first=Rudy|last=Martzke|newspaper=USA Today|page=3C}}&lt;/ref&gt; as NBC's lead baseball color commentator. He is one of three sportscasters to be regular announcers for both the [[Mets–Yankees rivalry|Mets and Yankees]]; the others are [[Fran Healy (baseball)|Fran Healy]] and [[Tim McCarver]]. He has also worked as a part-time scout, and as a [[spring training]] pitching coach. Seaver's TV experience dates back to his playing career, when he was invited into the TV booths for the {{wsy|1977}} and {{wsy|1978}} World Series on [[Major League Baseball on ABC|ABC]] and NBC, respectively.

==Personal life==
Seaver married the former Nancy Lynn McIntyre on June 9, 1966. They are parents of two daughters. They live in [[Calistoga, California]], where he started his own his {{convert|3.5|acre|m2|adj=on}} vineyard, Seaver Family Vineyards,. Seaver Family Vineyard
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seaverfamilyvineyards.com]&lt;/ref&gt; on his {{convert|116|acre|km2|adj=on}} estate in 2002.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/28/dining/28seav.html | work=The New York Times | title=Warming Up in the Vineyard, Tom Terrific | first=Eric | last=Asimov | date=December 28, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; His first vintage was produced in 2005. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
  | last = Lindbloom
  | first = John
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = St. Helena gets a taste of Seaver and Sinatra
  | journal = [[St. Helena Star]]
  | volume = 
  | issue = 
  | pages = 
  | publisher = Lee Enterprises, Inc.
  | location = Napa, CA
  | date = August 26, 2010
  | url = http://napavalleyregister.com/star/business/st-helena-gets-a-taste-of-seaver-and-sinatra/article_0bcc08a9-c1b7-5b4b-b3ff-5e5d3aae92ec.html
  | issn = 
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
  | last = James
  | first = Marty
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Tom's terrific life after baseball
  | journal = [[Napa Valley Register]]
  | volume = 
  | issue = 
  | pages = 
  | publisher = Lee Enterprises, Inc.
  | location = Napa, CA
  | date = October 8, 2009
  | url = http://napavalleyregister.com/calistogan/sports/tom-s-terrific-life-after-baseball/article_1cd6a4b7-4daa-5294-97b3-810e20721b30.html
  | issn = 
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;He presented his two cabernets, &quot;Nancy's Fancy&quot; and &quot;GTS&quot;, in an April 2010 wine-tasting event in [[SoHo]] to positive reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://bats.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/04/26/seavers-tales-of-wine-and-roses/ | work=The New York Times | first=Ken | last=Belson | date=April 26, 2010 | title=Seaver's Tales of Wine and Roses}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His media nickname referred to the cartoon character [[Tom Terrific]].

==See also==
* [[List of MLB individual streaks]]
* [[300 win club]]
* [[3000 strikeout club]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career wins]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball ERA champions]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball strikeout champions]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball wins champions]]
* [[List of pitchers who have struck out 18 or more batters in a nine-inning MLB game]]
* [[Top 100 strikeout pitchers of all time]]
* [[Major League Baseball titles leaders]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball no-hitters]]
* [[Shutouts in baseball]]
* [[List of celebrities who own wineries and vineyards]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Baseballstats |mlb= |espn= |br=s/seaveto01 |fangraphs=1011708 |cube=s/tom-seaver}}
{{bbhof|seaver-tom}}

{{s-start-collapsible|header={{s-ach}}}}
{{succession box | before = [[Tommy Helms]] | title = [[MLB Rookie of the Year Award|National League Rookie of the Year]]| years = 1967 | after = [[Johnny Bench]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Bob Gibson]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Carlton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mike Marshall (baseball pitcher)|Mike Marshall]] | title = [[Cy Young Award|National League Cy Young Award]] | years = 1969&lt;br&gt;1973&lt;br&gt;1975 | after = [[Bob Gibson]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mike Marshall (baseball pitcher)|Mike Marshall]]&lt;br&gt;[[Randy Jones (baseball player)|Randy Jones]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Joe Namath]] | title = [[Hickok Belt|Hickok Belt Winner]] | years=[[1969 in sports|1969]] | after = [[Brooks Robinson]]}}
{{succession box| title  = [[List of Major League Baseball wins champions|National League Wins Champion]]| years  = 1969&lt;br&gt;1975&lt;br&gt;1981| before = [[Juan Marichal]]&lt;br&gt;[[Andy Messersmith|A. Messersmith]] &amp; [[Phil Niekro]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Carlton]]| after  = [[Bob Gibson]] &amp; [[Gaylord Perry]]&lt;br&gt;[[Randy Jones (baseball player)|Randy Jones]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Carlton]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball ERA champions|National League ERA Champion]] | before= [[Juan Marichal]] | years=1970-1971 | after= [[Steve Carlton]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball strikeout champions|National League Strikeout Champion]] | before= [[Ferguson Jenkins]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Carlton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Carlton]] | years=1970-1971&lt;br&gt;1973&lt;br&gt;1975-1976 | after= [[Steve Carlton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Steve Carlton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Phil Niekro]]}}
{{Succession box|title=[[No-hitter]] pitcher |before=[[Bob Forsch]]| years= June 16, {{by|1978}} |after=[[Ken Forsch]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{New York Mets Hall of Fame}}
{{1969 New York Mets}}
{{NL Rookie of the Year}}
{{NL Cy Young}}
{{300 win club}}
{{3000 strikeout club}}
{{SI Sportsman of the Year}}
{{SN Sportsman of the Year}}
{{Associated Press Male Athlete of the Year navbox}}
{{Mets Retired Numbers}}
{{1992 Baseball HOF}}
{{Pitchers in the Baseball Hall of Fame}}
{{Major League Baseball on NBC}}
{{New York Mets Opening Day Starting Pitchers}}
{{Chicago White Sox Opening Day starting pitchers}}

{{Persondata         &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
| NAME              = Seaver, Tom
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = 
| DATE OF BIRTH     = November 17, 1944
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Fresno, California
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Seaver, Tom}}
[[Category:1944 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Baseball players from California]]
[[Category:Boston Red Sox players]]
[[Category:Chicago White Sox players]]
[[Category:Cincinnati Reds players]]
[[Category:Cy Young Award winners]]
[[Category:Jacksonville Suns players]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball pitchers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball Rookie of the Year Award winners]]
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:National League ERA champions]]
[[Category:National League strikeout champions]]
[[Category:National League wins champions]]
[[Category:New York Mets broadcasters]]
[[Category:New York Mets players]]
[[Category:People from Fresno, California]]
[[Category:University of Southern California alumni]]
[[Category:USC Trojans baseball players]]
[[Category:People from Napa County, California]]

[[de:Tom Seaver]]
[[es:Tom Seaver]]
[[fr:Tom Seaver]]
[[ja:トム・シーバー]]
[[simple:Tom Seaver]]
[[sh:Tom Seaver]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
