<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="519012" ns="0" title="Télé-Québec"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox broadcast|
  call_letters             = CIVM-TV|
  city                     = [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]]|
  station_logo             = [[Image:Télé-Québec Logo.svg|220px]]|
  station_slogan           = ''L'esprit ouvert''&lt;br&gt;(&quot;The Open Mind&quot;)|
  station_branding         = |
  analog                   = [[#Stations|see below]]|
  digital                  = [[#Stations|see below]]|
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = |
  network                  = |
  airdate                  = January 19, 1975&lt;br&gt;''(first appeared on cable in 1972)''|
  location                 = Provincewide [[Quebec]]|
  callsign_meaning         = |
  former_callsigns         = |
  former_channel_numbers   = |
  owner                    = [[Government of Quebec]]|
  licensee                 = Société de télédiffusion du Québec|
  sister_stations          = |
  former_affiliations      = |
  effective_radiated_power = 889.5 [[kilowatt|kW]]|
  HAAT                     = 300 m|
  coordinates              = {{Coord|45|30|19|N|73|35|29|W|type:landmark}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.telequebec.tv/ Télé-Québec] {{fr}}|
}}
'''Télé-Québec''' is a [[French language]] [[public television|public]] [[education]]al [[television network]] in the [[Canada|Canadian]] province of [[Quebec]]. Known legally as ''' Société de télédiffusion du Québec''' ''(Quebec Television Broadcasting Corporation)'', it is a provincial [[crown corporation]] owned by the Government of Quebec. The network's main studios and general offices are located in [[Montreal]], at the corner of [[Saint Catherine Street|Saint Catherine]] and Fullum Streets in [[Ville-Marie, Montreal|Ville-Marie]].

Télé-Québec is equivalent to [[Ontario]]'s [[TVOntario]] and [[TFO]], [[British Columbia]]'s [[Knowledge (TV channel)|Knowledge]] and [[Saskatchewan]]'s [[Saskatchewan Communications Network|SCN]], and similar to the US [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] network, in that it is somewhat modest in scope, runs mostly educational or cultural programming, and does not try to compete with privately owned television networks or with the [[Télévision de Radio-Canada|Radio-Canada]] television network owned and operated by the [[government of Canada|federal government]]. The network also runs commercials during its programming, not unlike its federal counterparts Radio-Canada and [[CBC Television]]. The latter, by contrast, does strongly compete with private networks and overlaps with their programming categories.

All programming on Télé-Québec is in [[French language|French]], though there are a few shows and movies that are presented in the original language (predominantly English), with French subtitles.

Télé-Québec operates local offices in [[Val-d'Or]], [[Trois-Rivières]], [[Rimouski]], [[Gatineau]], [[Sept-Îles, Quebec|Sept-Îles]], [[Quebec City]], [[Sherbrooke]], [[Saguenay, Quebec|Saguenay]] and [[Carleton-sur-Mer, Quebec|Carleton]].

Télé-Québec is one of the partners in the [[TV5 Québec Canada]] and [[TV5MONDE]] consortiums. They also had a 25% stake in the French-Canadian arts specialty channel, [[ARTV]], which they sold to the CBC in 2010.

==History==
[[Image:Radio-Quebec.png|right|150px|thumb|Logo while under the name '''Radio Québec''']]
The genesis of Télé-Québec was created on April 20, 1945, when the [[Legislative Assembly of Quebec]], under the mandate of Premier [[Maurice Duplessis]], passed a law allowing Quebec to create and run a public broadcasting network, as a provincial counterpart to the [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]].

A public broadcasting scheme in Quebec was formerly established on February 22, 1968, when the [[Daniel Johnson, Sr.]] administration created a new public broadcasting agency, &quot;Radio-Québec&quot;, under the auspices of the [[Ministry of Education, Recreation and Sports (Quebec)|Ministry of Education]]. Shortly afterward, the first Radio-Québec program, a radio program on the history of Canada called ''En montant la rivière'', was produced. Produced later that year was its first television program, ''[[Les Oraliens]]'', where space aliens taught kids how to properly pronounce French words and phrases.

In 1969, a new law was passed by the [[National Assembly of Quebec]], creating ''l’Office de radio-télédiffusion du Québec'' (&quot;Quebec Office of Radio and Television Broadcasting&quot;), where Radio-Québec was placed.

Radio-Québec began broadcasting on its own in 1972 as a cable channel, which broadcasted evenings on [[Community channel (Canada)|community channels]] in Montréal and Quebec City, then expanded in 1973 to Hull, Gatineau and Sherbrooke. As a cable network, Radio-Québec was generally on the air weeknights from 8PM to 10PM.&lt;ref&gt;[http://boards.radio-info.com/smf/index.php?topic=161389.0 Radio-Info: &quot;Retro: Southern Quebec Fri, Jan 24, 1975&quot;, January 26, 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt; The network of over-the-air transmitters was launched on January 19, 1975 with the sign-ons of '''CIVM-TV''' in Montreal and '''CIVQ-TV''' in Quebec City, making its programming available to an even wider audience. In its early days after the terrestrial network began, Radio-Québec would provide week-delay videotapes of its programming line-up to cable systems in communities not served by a Radio-Québec station. Some Radio-Québec programs were also seen on most Radio-Canada stations, not only in Quebec, but throughout Canada as well; this arrangement continued into the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://boards.radio-info.com/smf/index.php/topic,156292.0.html Western British Columbia ''TV Guide'' listings at Radio-Info.com: &quot;Retro: Vancouver/Victoria/Seattle Wed, Nov 9, 1977&quot;, November 6, 2009]; listings for CBUFT included ''Les Oraliens'' and ''[[Les 100 tours de Centour]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1977, Radio-Québec opened its third station, '''CIVO-TV''' in [[Hull, Quebec|Hull]], serving the greater [[Ottawa]] area—the station was built after acquiring the license and facilities of a failed [[TVA (TV network)|TVA]] affiliate, [[CFVO-TV]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.php?url=http%3A//www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php%3Fid%3D180%26historyID%3D195 Canadian Communications Foundation: CFVO-TV]. Note: This article contradicts with the [http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/index3.php?url=http%3A//www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php%3Fid%3D107%26historyID%3D125 CCF's page for Télé-Québec], which states that the closedown of CFVO-TV and its conversion to CIVO-TV happened in 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;

Radio-Québec was off the air during most of 1978, due to a [[Lockout (industry)|lockout]] of its employees in a labour dispute.

In 1979, Radio-Québec's agency was restructured as a provincial crown corporation, ''Société de radio-télévision du Québec'' (&quot;Quebec Radio and Television Broadcasting Corporation&quot;). The network had also adopted the slogan, ''L'autre télévision'' (&quot;The other television&quot;).

On January 1, 1985, Radio-Québec began providing its programming to its stations and cable systems via satellite, using [[Anik (satellite)|Anik C-3]]. Also that year, the CRTC granted Radio-Québec permission to show commercials during some of its programming, initially for a two-year trial run. This authorisation would eventually become permanent—by the 2002-2003 fiscal year, Télé-Québec's revenues from advertising would account for 45.8% of its total revenue.

In 1994, the Quebec government announced budget cuts for Radio-Québec, in which its budget was reduced by $10 million. In 1995, Radio-Québec president Jean Fortier announced that the network was virtually bankrupt. As a result, over 150 staffers were laid off (out of over 750 people employed), with plans for further layoffs to trim the employee count to 300 staffers. Programming produced in-house would either be cancelled or transferred to independent companies. In addition, the network would adopt the current &quot;Télé-Québec&quot; name the following year, in 1996,&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cbc.ca/IDC-0-72-1968-12712-11/index_souvenirs/arts_culture/radio_quebec_uhf Radio-Québec diffusée sur UHF - Souvenirs - Les Archives de Radio-Canada&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; with the crown corporation renamed as &quot;Société de télédiffusion du Québec&quot;. Plans for the new Télé-Québec to carry strictly educational programming was also called for, but was never carried out, opting to retain its mixed educational-entertainment schedule.

The monetary shortfall would be short-lived, as, by 1997, Télé-Québec would eventually resume productions on its own and increase its amount of original programming.

==Programming==
[[File:Montréal - Télé-Québec.jpg|thumb|left|The Montreal offices of Télé-Québec.]]
Over 40% of Télé-Québec’s programming is children's programming. In 2005, ''Ramdam'' was a popular show for 2 to 11 year-olds. Other children's shows have included ''Cornemuse'', ''[[Zoboomafoo]]'', and [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] series ''[[Dora the Explorer|Dora l'exploratrice]]'' and ''[[Bob the Builder|Bob le bricoleur]]''. Animated shows include ''IDragon'', ''[[Les Mélodilous]]'', ''Le Petit tracteur rouge'', and ''Toupie et Binou''. For 6 to 8 year-olds, shows have included ''Macaroni tout garni'', Nickelodeon's ''[[Rocket Power]]'', ''Esprits-fantômes'', and ''Le Petit roi Macius''. ''Ramdam'' and ''Banzaï'' are both aimed at pre-teens (9 to 12), and ''ADN-X'' is a teens show that provides practical solutions to everyday problems.

Télé-Québec's cultural programming reflects Quebec's diverse cultural expression in fiction, songs, music, cinema, visual art, and drama. Télé-Québec shows such as ''Belle et Bum'', ''M’as-tu lu?'' and ''Pulsart'' help to promote Quebec artists and creators and their works. ''Belle et Bum'' is a music show that invited 160 performers or groups in 2005–2006, who performed 230 songs by Quebec songwriters or composers. ''M'as-tu lu?'' is a book show that covers books of all genres and for all audiences; in 2005–2006, 260 books were presented, 124 of which were by Quebec authors. ''Pulsart'' is a magazine show on cultural activities taking place all over Quebec.

A new weekly cultural magazine-style show,'' Libre échange'', deals with a ranges of different creative arts, including dance, cinema, literature, sculpture, painting, television, music, and theatre. As well, a new series of &quot;living portraits&quot; will profile notable living creators such as authors, filmmakers, architects and thinkers.

Télé-Québec presents a range of films, including &quot;[[auteur theory|auteur]]&quot; films by notable [[Film director|director]]s, feature-film length [[documentary film|documentaries]], [[premiere|premiere showings]], and [[Cinema of Quebec|Quebec films]]. All films are shown without commercial interruptions. During the last five years, Télé-Québec showed over 959 hours of documentaries, which made up 18% of its programming. Documentary topics included socio-political, cultural, historic, scientific, and travel. Between 2000 and 2006, 137 documentaries and 39 series were produced.

Télé-Québec also hosts debate and discussion-oriented shows that allow for an exchange of ideas and perspectives on social and political issues. ''Points chauds'' is a show on international political issues. ''Méchant contraste!'' is a pan-Quebec magazine show on social, political, and economic issues. ''Dussault-Débat'' is a debate show.

As a community service, Télé-Québec has a number of shows that present a regional perspective, such as ''Méchant contraste!'', ''À la di Stasio'', ''les Francs Tireurs'', ''M'as-tu lu?'', ''Une pilule'', and ''Pulsart''. Télé-Québec also has an Internet strategy, as part of its educational and cultural mission. In 2003, the extremis.tv website won a Gémeaux prize for the best Internet site. In 2004, du missionarctique.tv won the same award. The website for the teen-oriented show ''ADN-X'' has interactive activities including a comic strip-creating activity.

===Programming in English===
The only Télé-Québec program that was entirely in English was ''Quebec School Telecasts'', a weekday, hour-long block of English-language instructional programming. The series was first telecasted on [[CBC Television]] outlets in Quebec in the early-1960s. Radio-Québec picked up the program in 1981; it was telecasted on Radio-Québec and the later Télé-Québec until the early-2000s.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

In 1985, Radio-Québec and [[TVOntario]] signed an exchange arrangement, in which English-language TVO programming would be seen on Radio-Québec, and Radio-Québec's French-language programming would be seen on TVO—it is unknown if either network actually carried the other network's programming.

==Télé-Québec HD and digital conversion==
[[Image:Tele Quebec HD.png|right|175px|thumb|Télé-Québec HD logo]]
On June 12, 2008, Télé-Québec launched an HD simulcast of its Montréal station CIVM-TV called '''Télé-Québec HD'''. It signed on over the air on channel 27 ([[Virtual channel|PSIP]] 17.1) from [[Olympic Stadium (Montreal)|Olympic Stadium]] in Montreal in January [[2009 in Canadian television|2009]], making CIVM-DT the first educational television station in [[Canada]] to broadcast digitally. After the [[DTV in Canada|analogue shutdown and digital conversion]] in [[Canada]], scheduled for August 31, 2011, CIVM-DT will move to channel 26.

A digital terrestrial television transmitter requested and authorized for construction in Quebec City for CIVQ-TV did not sign on until August 2010,{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} weeks before the September 25, 2010 deadline to sign on or file an extension.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2008/db2008-268.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2008-268, 25 September 2008, Société de télédiffusion du Québec, CIVM-DT Montréal - New transmitter in Québec]&lt;/ref&gt; That transmitter broadcasts from [[Edifice Marie-Guyart]] in downtown Quebec City on channel 25 ([[Virtual channel|PSIP]] 15.1). After the digital conversion in 2011, CIVQ moved its digital signal to channel 15.

Télé-Québec intended on converting all of its transmitters to digital by the digital transition deadline of August 31, 2011, including its transmitters that are not required to transition by this deadline.

==Stations==
{{kml}}

Télé-Québec's network currently consists of 12 stations and five repeaters, originating at CIVM-TV in [[Montreal]].  

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse&quot;
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: center;&quot;
| '''Station'''
| '''[[City of licence]]'''
| '''[[Channel (broadcasting)|Channel]] (analog / [[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])'''
| '''[[Channel (broadcasting)|Channel]] (digital)'''&lt;ref name=&quot;TQC-Digital&quot;&gt;[http://www.ic.gc.ca/eic/site/smt-gst.nsf/vwapj/DTV_PLAN_Dec08-e.pdf/$file/DTV_PLAN_Dec08-e.pdf Industry Canada: &quot;DTV Post-Transition Allotment Plan&quot;, December 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
| '''[[effective radiated power|ERP]]'''
| '''[[height above average terrain|HAAT]]'''
| '''Transmitter Coordinates'''
| '''Notes'''
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVA-TV'''
| [[Val-d'Or]]
| 12 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])
| 12
| 169.47&amp;nbsp;kW
| 204.5 m
| {{Coord|48|25|17|N|77|50|49|W|type:landmark|name=CIVA-TV}}
| Signed on January 18, 1980
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVA-TV-1'''
| [[Rouyn-Noranda]]
| 8 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])
| 8
| 256.5&amp;nbsp;kW
| 232.9 m
| {{Coord|48|15|52|N|79|2|38|W|type:landmark|name=CIVA-TV-1}}
| Signed on January 18, 1980, as CIVN-TV
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVB-TV'''
| [[Rimouski]]
| 22 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 22
| 1674.9&amp;nbsp;kW
| 460.5 m
| {{Coord|48|28|2|N|68|12|39|W|type:landmark|name=CIVB-TV}}
| Signed on November 3, 1981 as CIVR-TV
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVB-TV-1'''
| [[Grand-Fonds, Quebec|Grand-Fonds]]
| 31 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 31
| 686.25&amp;nbsp;kW
| 508 m
| {{Coord|47|46|47|N|70|9|8|W|type:landmark|name=CIVB-TV-1}}
| Serving [[La Malbaie]] and [[Baie-Saint-Paul, Quebec|Baie-Saint-Paul]]; signed on in 1985
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVC-TV'''
| [[Trois-Rivières]]
| 45 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 46
| 1500&amp;nbsp;kW
| 398.1 m
| {{Coord|46|29|33|N|72|39|7|W|type:landmark|name=CIVC-TV}}
| Signed on October 6, 1981; originally broadcasted from the old [[CBC Tower (Mont-Carmel)|CBC Tower at Mont-Carmel]] until the plane crash on April 23, 2001&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fybush.com/sites/2004/site-040325.html fybush.com Tower Site of the Week: Quebec City and Trois-Rivieres, Quebec, 3/25/2004.]&lt;/ref&gt;
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVF-TV'''
| [[Baie-Trinité, Quebec|Baie-Trinité]]
| 12 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])
| 12
| 155&amp;nbsp;kW
| 148.2 m
| {{Coord|49|23|28|N|67|28|15|W|type:landmark|name=CIVF-TV}}
| Also covers [[Baie-Comeau]]; signed on Fall 1982
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVG-TV'''
| [[Sept-Îles, Quebec|Sept-Îles]]
| 9 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])
| 9
| 246&amp;nbsp;kW
| 218.9 m
| {{Coord|50|10|18|N|66|44|16|W|type:landmark|name=CIVG-TV}}
| Signed on Fall 1982
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVK-TV'''
| [[Carleton-sur-Mer|Carleton]]
| 15 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 15
| 1061.7&amp;nbsp;kW
| 459 m
| {{Coord|48|8|8|N|66|6|58|W|type:landmark|name=CIVK-TV}}
| Signal also covers [[Campbellton, New Brunswick]]; signed on in 1984
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVK-TV-1'''
| [[Port-Daniel–Gascons|Gascons]]
| 32 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 32
| 1390&amp;nbsp;kW
| 203.1 m
| {{Coord|48|12|41|N|64|52|14|W|type:landmark|name=CIVK-TV-1}}
| Signal also covers the [[Acadian Peninsula]]; signed on in 1984
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVK-TV-2'''
| [[Percé, Quebec|Percé]]
| 40 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 40
| 8.55&amp;nbsp;kW
| 405.4 m
| {{Coord|48|31|38|N|64|14|37|W|type:landmark|name=CIVK-TV-2}}
| Signed on in 1984
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVK-TV-3'''
| [[Gaspé, Quebec|Gaspé]]
| 35 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 35
| 8.43&amp;nbsp;kW
| 424.5 m
| {{Coord|48|50|1|N|64|15|24|W|type:landmark|name=CIVK-TV-3}}
| Signed on in 1984
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVM-TV'''
| [[Montreal]]
| 17 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 26
| 889.5&amp;nbsp;kW (analog)&lt;br&gt;15&amp;nbsp;kW (digital)
| 300 m (analog)&lt;br&gt;170.6 m (digital)
| {{Coord|45|30|19|N|73|35|29|W|type:landmark|name=CIVM-TV}}&lt;br&gt;[[Mount Royal]] ''(analog)''&lt;br&gt;
{{Coord|45|33|28.48|N|73|33|6.39|W|type:landmark|name=CIVM-TV}}&lt;br&gt;[[Olympic Stadium (Montreal)|Olympic Stadium]] ''(digital)''
| [[flagship station]]; signed on January 19, 1975 with CIVQ-TV
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVO-TV'''
| [[Gatineau]]
| 30 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 30
| 1774.2&amp;nbsp;kW
| 353.2 m
| {{Coord|45|30|9|N|75|50|59|W|type:landmark|name=CIVO-TV}}
| Broadcasts from [[Ryan Tower]]; signed on in 1977; was licensed to [[Hull, Quebec|Hull]] prior to 2002
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVP-TV'''
| [[Chapeau, Quebec|Chapeau]]
| 23 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 23
| 8.65&amp;nbsp;kW
| 98.8 m
| {{Coord|45|55|29|N|77|4|22|W|type:landmark|name=CIVP-TV}}
| Signal also covers [[Pembroke, Ontario]]
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVQ-TV'''
| [[Quebec City|Quebec]]
| 15 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 15
| 970&amp;nbsp;kW (analog)&lt;br&gt;15&amp;nbsp;kW (digital)
| 191.4 m (analog)&lt;br&gt;153.0 m (digital)
| {{Coord|46|48|29|N|71|13|3|W|type:landmark_region:CA|name=CIVQ-TV}}
| Broadcasts from [[Edifice Marie-Guyart]]; signed on January 19, 1975 with CIVM-TV
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVS-TV'''
| [[Sherbrooke]]
| 24 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 24
| 549&amp;nbsp;kW
| 583.6 m
| {{Coord|45|18|43|N|72|14|30|W|type:landmark|name=CIVS-TV}}
| Signed on in early 1982 on channel 14; would move to channel 24 later that year
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CIVV-TV'''
| [[Saguenay, Quebec|Saguenay]]
| 8 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])
| 8
| 325&amp;nbsp;kW
| 593.8 m
| {{Coord|48|36|7|N|70|49|48|W|type:landmark|name=CIVV-TV}}
| Broadcast from [[Mount Valin]]; Signed on in Fall 1982; Was licensed to [[Chicoutimi]] prior to 2002
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
|}

It can also be seen nationwide on [[Bell TV]] Channel 138 and [[Shaw Direct]] Channel 722. On terrestrial cable, however, it is generally seen only in Quebec and in communities in Ontario and New Brunswick which are within the broadcast range of a Télé-Québec transmitter. Outside of this area, few cable systems, such as [[Manitoba Telecom Services|MTS]] in [[Winnipeg]], carry Télé-Québec in their digital tiers.

Télé-Québec (and its predecessor, Radio-Québec) was also assigned channel 2 in [[Rivière-du-Loup]], channel 10 in Lithium Mines and channel 21 in [[Mont-Laurier, Quebec|Mont-Laurier]]. As of 2009, service has yet to begin in these communities; in addition, it had later lost its channel 2 slot at Rivière-du-Loup, after that channel was reallocated to Quebec City ([[CFAP-DT|CFAP-TV]]) and Rimouski ([[CJBR-DT|CJBR-TV]]).

==See also==
*[[List of Quebec television channels]]
*[[List of Quebec television series]]
*[[Television of Quebec]]
*[[Culture of Quebec]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.telequebec.tv/ Télé-Québec] {{fr icon}}
**[http://www.telequebec.tv/corporatif/?section=historique Télé-Québec: Histoire] {{fr icon}}
*[http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php?id=107&amp;historyID=125 Canadian Communications Foundation - CIVM-TV History]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20091027123937/http://geocities.com/tvhatton/mtl-local/civm.html  Montreal affiliate CIVM at TV Hat]
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVM-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVF-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVK-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVP-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVO-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVQ-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVB-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVA-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVV-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVG-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVS-TV}}
*{{RecnetCanada|CIVC-TV}}

&lt;br clear=all&gt;
{{Educational Television Stations in Canada}}
{{Montreal TV}}
{{Ottawa-Gatineau TV}}
{{Quebec City TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tele-Quebec}}
[[Category:Crown corporations of Quebec]]
[[Category:Public television in Canada]]
[[Category:Canadian broadcast television networks]]
[[Category:Educational television networks in Canada]]
[[Category:French-language television networks in Canada]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1972]]
[[Category:Organizations based in Montreal]]

[[es:Télé-Québec]]
[[fr:Télé-Québec]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
