<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="51974" ns="0" title="Mountain Dew"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Hatnote|For the songs with &quot;Mountain Dew&quot; in the title, see [[The Rare Old Mountain Dew]] or [[Good Old Mountain Dew]].}}
{{Hatnote|For the homemade alchoholic drink, see [[moonshine]] and for the Juhuro, see [[Mountain Jew]].}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Non-free-overuse|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox Beverage
|name         = Mountain Dew
|image        = [[File:Mountain Dew logo.svg|200px]]
|type         = [[Citrus]] [[soft drink]]
|manufacturer = [[PepsiCo]]
|distributor  =
|origin       = [[United States]]
|introduced   = 1948
|color        = Green, Blue, Red, Orange, Purple, White, Yellow, Black, and Gold
|main flavor       = Citrus blend
|variants     =
Regular&lt;br /&gt;Diet&lt;br /&gt;Caffeine-Free&lt;br /&gt;Caffeine-Free Diet&lt;br /&gt;Code Red&lt;br /&gt;Diet Code Red&lt;br /&gt;LiveWire&lt;br /&gt;Baja Blast&lt;br /&gt;Voltage&lt;br /&gt;Throwback&lt;br /&gt;White Out&lt;br /&gt;Game Fuel Citrus-cherry&lt;br /&gt;Game Fuel Tropical&lt;br /&gt;Grape (Japan only)
|related      = [[Vault (soft drink)|Vault]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mello Yello]]
|website      = [http://www.mountaindew.com/ mountaindew.com]
}}

'''Mountain Dew''' (currently stylized as '''MTN Dew''') is a citrus-flavored carbonated [[soft drink]] brand produced and owned by [[PepsiCo]]. The original formula was invented in the 1940s by Tennessee beverage bottlers Barney and Ally Hartman and was first marketed in [[Marion, VA]], Knoxville and [[Johnson City, Tennessee]]. A revised formula was created by Bill Bridgforth in 1958. The Mountain Dew brand and production rights were acquired by the Pepsi-Cola company in 1964, at which point its distribution expanded more widely across the [[United States]].&lt;ref name=pep1964&gt;{{cite news|last=Collins|first=Glenn|title=Coca-Cola, in Direct Attack on Pepsi, to Introduce Challenger to Mountain Dew|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/16/business/coca-cola-in-direct-attack-on-pepsi-to-introduce-challenger-to-mountain-dew.html|accessdate=12 January 2011|newspaper=The New York Times|date=16 December 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between the 1940s and 1980s, Mountain Dew consisted of a single [[citrus]]-flavored version. Diet Mountain Dew was introduced in 1988,&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot; /&gt; followed by Mountain Dew Red which was introduced - and discontinued - in 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewhistbook&quot; /&gt; While Mountain Dew Red was short-lived, it represented the beginning of a long-term trend of Mountain Dew being produced in different flavor variations. This product line extension trend has continued in the 2000s, with expansion into specialty, limited time production, and retailer-specific ([[Taco Bell]], [[7-Eleven]]) variations of Mountain Dew.

Production was first extended to the [[United Kingdom|UK]] in 1996, though this initial debut was short-lived as it was phased out in 1998. The product returned to the UK under the name &quot;Mountain Dew Energy&quot; in 2010 and returned to the [[Republic of Ireland]] in Spring 2011.&lt;ref name=ukdewlaunch&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kimberley|first=Sara|title=Mountain Dew returns (to UK) with social media push|journal=Brand Republic (U.K.)|date=18 May 2010|url=http://www.brandrepublic.com/News/1003874/Mountain-Dew-returns-social-media-push|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2009, Mountain Dew represented a 6.7 percent share of the overall carbonated soft drinks market in the U.S.&lt;ref name=bevdigest2009top&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sicher|first=John|title=Top-10 Carbonated Soft Drink Brands for 2009|journal=Beverage Digest|date=24 March 2010|url=http://www.beverage-digest.com/pdf/top-10_2010.pdf|accessdate=27 January 2011|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its competition includes [[Vault (soft drink)|Vault]], [[Mello Yello]], and [[Sun Drop]]; Mountain Dew accounts for eighty percent of [[citrus]] soft drinks sold within the U.S.&lt;ref name=80mktcitrus&gt;{{cite news|title=Branded Entertainment Could Boost PepsiCo|url=http://seekingalpha.com/article/211464-branded-entertainment-could-boost-pepsico|accessdate=21 January 2011|newspaper=Seeking Alpha|date=23 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Packaging==
The name “Mountain Dew” was first trademarked by Ally and Barney Hartman in the 1940s, who coined the name from a [[colloquial]] term for [[moonshine]] whiskey. Early bottles and signage carried the reference forward by showing a [[cartoon]]-stylized mountaineer. The first sketches of the original Mountain Dew bottle labels were devised in 1948 by John Brichetto, and the representation on product packaging has changed at multiple points in the history of the beverage.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewhistbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bridgforth|first=Dick|title=Mountain Dew: The History|url=http://books.google.com/?id=78HnGAAACAAJ&amp;dq=mountain+dew+book|accessdate=30 January 2011|edition=4|year=2007|publisher=BookSurge Publishing|isbn=1-4196-6087-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Logo===
[[File:Mountain Dew sign Tonto Arizona.jpg|thumb|right|1950's Mountain Dew advertisement sign in Tonto, Arizona]]
[[PepsiCo]] (known then as The Pepsi-Cola Company) acquired the Mountain Dew brand in 1964, and shortly thereafter in 1973 the [[logo]] was modified as the company sought to shift its focus to a “younger, outdoorsy” generation. This direction continued as the logo remained the same through the 1970s, 80s and into the late 1990s. Later updates to the logo were made in 1999 and again in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewhistbook&quot; /&gt; On October 15, 2008, the Mountain Dew logo was redesigned to ''&quot;Mtn Dew&quot;'' within the U.S. market, as a result of a PepsiCo rebranding of its core carbonated soft-drink products.&lt;ref name=&quot;logo2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://money.ca.msn.com/investing/gallery.aspx?cp-documentid=27219769&amp;page=2|title=The Best and Worst Logo Redesigns|date=16 January 2011|work=MSN Money|page=2|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the variant flavors continued to use the previous design until May 2011, when it was revealed that the &quot;Code Red&quot;, &quot;LiveWire&quot;, &quot;Voltage&quot;, and &quot;Baja Blast&quot; flavor variants would be given redesigned packaging, including new logos to correspond with the &quot;Mtn Dew&quot; style. The returning flavors &quot;Pitch Black&quot; &quot;Supernova&quot; &quot;Typhoon&quot; and &quot;Game Fuel&quot; were given redesigned packaging and logos for their re-release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bevnet.com/news/2008/10-13-2008-pepsi_redesign.asp |title=Pepsi to redesign core products icon |publisher=BevNET.com |date=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marketingmagazine.co.uk/news/855193/Pepsi-rolls-700m-global-brand-makeover|title=News: PepsiCo's &quot;Sidekick&quot; Bottle for Mountain Dew|publisher=BevReview|accessdate=2009-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sidekick Bottles===
Beginning in summer 2010, a secondary type of Mountain Dew bottles began appearing on select U.S. shelves. The bottles featured a sleeker design, smaller packaging labels, and a built-in grip. This design was dubbed &quot;Sidekick bottles&quot; and was said to be in testing in [[North Carolina]], [[South Carolina]], and [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] markets. Currently, the bottles are being found more and more in the south-east region, and could potentially replace the standard bottle design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2011/08/18/pepsicos-sidekick-bottle-for-mountain-dew/|title=News: PepsiCo's &quot;Sidekick&quot; Bottle for Mountain Dew|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=18 August 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=20 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ingredients==
In its primary market of the United States, the ingredient composition of Mountain Dew is listed as: “[[carbonated water]], [[High-fructose corn syrup]] (in much of the U.S.), concentrated [[orange juice]], [[citric acid]], natural flavors, [[sodium benzoate]], [[caffeine]], [[Trisodium citrate|sodium citrate]], [[erythorbic acid]], [[gum arabic]], [[calcium disodium EDTA]], [[brominated vegetable oil]], and [[Tartrazine|yellow 5]].”&lt;ref name=dewingredientlist&gt;{{cite web|title=Pepsi Product Facts - Mountain Dew Ingredient List|url=http://pepsiproductfacts.com/infobyproduct.php?prod_size=20&amp;brand_fam_id=1049&amp;brand_id=1000&amp;product=Mountain+Dew&amp;prod_type=1026|publisher=PepsiCo, Inc.|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ingredient makeup of Mountain Dew varies based on the country of production. For example, in [[Canada]], the sweetener listed is &quot;fructose/sucrose&quot; and it is caffeine-free by default.&lt;ref name=dewcanadaingred&gt;{{cite news|last=Tanner|first=Steve|title=Mountain Dew Throwback (December 2009 Rerelease)|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/01/07/mountain-dew-throwback-december-2009-rerelease/|accessdate=28 January 2011|newspaper=BevReview|date=7 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to consumer insistence on a more natural product, PepsiCo in 2009 released a limited run production of Mountain Dew Throwback, a variation consisting of [[sugar]] in place of high fructose corn syrup.&lt;ref name=hfcs&gt;{{cite news|last=Engber|first=Daniel|title=The decline and fall of high-fructose corn syrup|url=http://www.slate.com/id/2216796/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=Slate|date=28 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mountain Dew Throwback has since been re-released for brief periods (generally 8–12 weeks at a time), including a 2nd wave from December 2009 - February 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;throwback2nd&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/01/07/mountain-dew-throwback-december-2009-rerelease/|title=Mountain Dew Throwback » December 2009 Rerelease|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=7 January 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a 3rd wave in Summer/Fall 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;throwback3rd&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/06/16/throwback-thirds-pepsi-dew-throwback-to-return-for-3rd-run-in-august-for-5-weeks/|title=Pepsi, Dew Throwback to return for 3rd run in August for 5 weeks|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=16 June 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 4th limited production run began in March 2011, lasting for a total of eight weeks before becoming a permanent addition to the Mountain Dew flavor line-up.&lt;ref name=limitedreleasestatus&gt;{{cite news|last=Tanner|first=Steve|title=Pepsi, Dew Throwback return in 2011 for 4th limited run, perhaps extended beyond 8 weeks|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2011/01/07/pepsi-dew-throwback-return-in-2011-for-4th-limited-run-perhaps-extended-beyond-8-weeks/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=BevReview|date=7 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two unfounded urban legends about Mountain Dew ingredients exist. One is that it causes shrunken testicles and/or penis size. The other is that it lowers sperm count.&lt;ref name=dewsp&gt;{{cite news|last=Mayer|first=Heather|title=Fact or Myth: Mountain Dew lowers sperm count|url=http://www.dailyorange.com/2.8656/fact-or-myth-mountain-dew-lowers-sperm-count-1.1234394|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=The Daily Orange (Syracuse, NY)|date=6 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both myths are typically attributed to the dye Yellow #5 ([[tartrazine]]). Yellow #5 has never been scientifically linked to any of the alleged effects in the legends; nor has any other component of the drink. Thus, there is no evidence that Mountain Dew is any more hazardous (or beneficial) to health than other caffeinated, sugar-sweetened soft drinks, provided one is not allergic to Yellow #5.&lt;ref name=dewyellow5&gt;{{cite news|last=Pelisek|first=Christine|title=Offbeat: Mr. Happy Does the Dew|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=Los Angeles Weekly News|date=19 April 2000|url=http://laweekly.com/news/offbeat/mr-happy-does-the-dew/11480/ |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071016184218/http://laweekly.com/news/offbeat/mr-happy-does-the-dew/11480/ |archivedate = 16 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For information on the health effects of consuming large quantities of brominated vegetable oil, see [[brominated vegetable oil]].

Caffeine Content: 54&amp;nbsp;mg/12 fl oz.

==Historical Meanings==
[[File:Oldmtdewbottle.jpg|thumb|180px|An old 10 ounce Mountain Dew bottle (date unknown): &quot;It'll tickle yore innards!&quot; This design has been used for Mountain Dew Throwback since 2010.]]

'''Mountain Dew''' was originally Southern and/or Irish slang for [[moonshine]] (homemade whiskey), or [[poitín]] as it is called in [[Ireland]].
An [[1882]] song from Ireland &quot;[[The Rare Old Mountain Dew]]&quot; (Words by Edward Harrigan. Music by Dave Braham) begins:

:Let grasses grow and waters flow
:In a free and easy way,
:But give me enough of the rare ould stuff,
:That's made near Galway Bay,
:Come gougers all from Donegal, Sligo and Leitrim too,
:And we'll give them the slip and we'll take a sip,
:Of the rare ould Mountain Dew.

A [[1947]] version by [[Grandpa Jones]] ([[1913]]-[[1998]]) may be better-known to Americans:

:There's a big holler tree down the road here from me
:where you lay down a doller er two.
:When you come round the bend and when you come back again
:there's a jug full of good old Mountain Dew
:Oh they call it that old mountain dew and them that refuse it are few.
:I'll shut up my mug if you fill up my jug with some good old Mountain Dew.

==Promotions==
===AMP Energy===
[[AMP Energy]] is an energy drink distributed by PepsiCo under the Mountain Dew brand. Launched in 2001, AMP was originally known as &quot;Mountain Dew AMP&quot;. From 2007–2008, several additional flavors of AMP were introduced.

===Taco Bell's Mountain Dew Baja Blast===
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2011}}
Since 2004, Mountain Dew has offered Taco Bell stores the exclusive right to sell Mountain Dew Baja Blast, a tropical-lime-flavored variety of the popular soft drink. Since then, rumors have appeared on the internet saying that Baja Blast was going to be bottled and sold in stores. This has been confirmed as a hoax, as a contract existed between PepsiCo (owner of Mountain Dew) and Yum! brands (owner of Taco Bell) prohibiting its distribution anywhere outside of Taco Bell stores, giving Taco Bell the privilege of being the only provider of Baja Blast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2004/07/30/review-mountain-dew-baja-blast/|title=Review: Mountain Dew Baja Blast|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=30 July 2004|work=BevReview|accessdate=20 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, however, videos began appearing on the Dew Labs website of members finding Baja Blast in fountains at small markets outside of Taco Bell, meaning the contract is no longer valid. While this is still unconfirmed, it is a possible step towards Baja Blast joining the other flavors on shelves.

===DEWmocracy===

====Dewmocracy 1: People's Dew====
[[File:MtnDewmocracyRevolutionVoltageSupernova.jpg|thumb|right|Original Dewmocracy (2008) flavor finalists: Revolution, Voltage and Supernova]]Beginning in 2007, Mountain Dew began a promotion entitled “DEWmocracy”,&lt;ref name=&quot;officialtitle&quot;&gt;officially stylized as '''DEWmocracy'''&lt;/ref&gt; which involved fans of the beverage brand electing new flavors, colors, names, packaging graphics and advertisements for upcoming Mountain Dew products.&lt;ref name=dewmocracyoverv&gt;{{cite news|last=Tanner|first=Steve|title=Overview: Mountain Dew DEWmocracy 2 Campaign|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/04/21/mountain-dew-dewmocracy-2-campaign/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=BevReview|date=21 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign has been the subject of recognition within the advertising industry,&lt;ref name=cnetdewm&gt;{{cite news|last=Rosenberg|first=Dave|title=Mountain Dew drinks up social media|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13846_3-10419047-62.html|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=CNet News|date=18 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; cited as one of the earliest and longest-running examples of a [[Consumer packaged goods|consumer product]] brand employing [[crowdsourcing]] to make decisions which are traditionally made internally by employees.&lt;ref name=12sec&gt;{{cite news|last=Parr|first=Ben|title=You Have 12 Seconds to Choose Mountain Dew’s New Flavor|url=http://mashable.com/2009/07/18/mountain-dew-crowdsourcing/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=Mashable|date=18 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its initial phase, Dewmocracy participation and voting was conducted via an online game.&lt;ref name=dewmocracyprom&gt;{{cite journal|title=Online Game lets Players Create a New Dew|journal=Promo Magazine|date=8 November 2007|url=http://promomagazine.com/interactivemarketing/news/online_game_mountain_dew/|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Television advertisements at the time featured actor [[Forest Whitaker]] asking people to decide the next new flavor of Mountain Dew. Online voters selected from three choices: Supernova (a strawberry-melon flavor), Revolution (a berry flavor), and Voltage (a raspberry-citrus flavor). Each included [[ginseng]]. On August 17, 2008, Voltage was announced as the winning flavor. It was released on December 29, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewmocracyfaq&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dewmocracyvoltage.com/faq.html |title=DEWmocracy FAQ|publisher=Dewmocracyvoltage.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Beverage Digest]], sales of Dewmocracy flavors totaled 25 million cases in 2008.&lt;ref name=2008cases&gt;{{cite journal|last=Zmuda|first=Natalie|title=New Pepsi 'Dewmocracy' push threatens to crowd out shops|journal=Advertising Age|date=2 November 2009|pages=1, 52|url=http://adage.coverleaf.com/advertisingage/20091102?pg=52#pg52|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Dewmocracy 2: Collective Intelligence====
[[File:WhiteOutDistortionandTyphoonDew.jpg|thumb|right|Dewmocracy 2 (2010) flavor finalists: White Out, Distortion and Typhoon]]Mountain Dew announced the continuation of the Dewmocracy campaign –referred to as “Dewmocracy 2”&lt;ref name=dewm2&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cirillo|first=Jennifer|title=DEWmocracy 2 Continues to Buzz|journal=Beverage World|date=11 March 2010|url=http://www.beverageworld.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=37525:dewmocracy-2-continues-to-buzz&amp;catid=34|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; – which launched in July 2009. A marked difference between Dewmocracy 2 and its predecessor is the involvement of a broader range of online components to conduct voting, expanding beyond the Dewmocracy website to include [[Facebook]], [[Twitter]], [[YouTube]],&lt;ref name=dewmocracybook&gt;{{cite book|last=Weber|first=Larry|title=Marketing to the Social Web: How Digital Customer Communities Build Your Business|year=2009|publisher=Wiley|isbn=978-0470410974|pages=137|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OLXuSpdKeNEC&amp;lpg=PA137&amp;dq=%22Mountain%20Dew%22%20flavors&amp;pg=PA137#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Mountain%20Dew%22%20flavors&amp;f=false|edition=2nd|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and what is referred to as the “Dew Labs Community” – a private, online forum for the “most passionate Dew fans.”&lt;ref name=dewmoccomm&gt;{{cite news|last=Sullivan|first=Laurie|title=Mountain Dew Crowd Sources Ad Media Buying|url=http://www.mediapost.com/publications/?fa=Articles.showArticle&amp;art_aid=128827|accessdate=26 January 2011|newspaper=MediaPost News|date=24 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2009, Dew Labs sampling trucks distributed [[product sample]]s of seven potential flavor variations. At the same time, 50 “Dew fanatics” were chosen based on their video submissions to the video website 12seconds.tv, and were shipped boxes of the seven prototype flavors.&lt;ref name=12sec /&gt; From the initial seven flavors, taste testers were asked to elect three final flavors for later release at [[retail store]]s. The three new candidate flavors were Mountain Dew Typhoon (red-orange), a tropical [[strawberry]]-[[pineapple]] flavor, Mountain Dew White Out (white), described as a smooth [[citrus]] flavor, and Mountain Dew Distortion (green), a [[Lime (fruit)|lime]] flavor. The three new candidate flavors were released on April 19, 2010 and voting continued until June 14. The following day, White Out was announced as the winner. Mountain Dew White Out was officially released for sale on October 4, 2010. A limited production White Out [[Slurpee]] (Mtn Dew White Out Freeze) was made available at [[7-Eleven]] beginning in January 2011.&lt;ref name=dewslurpee2011&gt;{{cite news|first=Marvo|title=New Mountain Dew White Out Slurpee Might Be Less Xtreme Than An Actual Mountain Dew White Out|url=http://www.theimpulsivebuy.com/wordpress/2011/01/04/news-new-mountain-dew-white-out-slurpee-might-be-less-xtreme-than-an-actual-mountain-dew-white-out/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=The Impulsive Buy|date=4 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Future====
Mountain Dew Marketing Director Brett O'Brien said in an interview that since the first two dewmocracy increased many sales, a third one may occur during the summer of 2012. This is of yet unconfirmed.

===Game Fuel===
====2007 Halo 3 edition====
In 2007, after using the term &quot;Game Fuel&quot; to direct their sodas to the video-gaming subculture, Mountain Dew officially announced a new flavor variant with the title. Coinciding with the release of the [[Xbox 360]] game [[Halo 3]], Mountain Dew Game Fuel sported a label that was almost entirely image-based, showing promotional artwork for the game and featuring the game series' main character [[Master Chief]] prominently. This variant remained on shelves for 12 weeks, and was discontinued afterwards.

====2009 World of Warcraft editions====
Two years later, the website for the popular [[MMORPG]] [[World of Warcraft]] was updated to reveal two Mountain Dew Game Fuel flavors would be coming to shelves in June 2009 and would promote the online video game. Shortly afterwards, official bottle art was released, and showed that one of the Game Fuel flavors would promote a certain player class in the game, while the other would promote a different class. It was also revealed that one of the two World of Warcraft Game Fuel flavors was exactly the same drink from the original Halo 3 promotion, with updated packaging. Both drinks were given World of Warcraft-based packaging, and sported the newly-updated &quot;MTN Dew&quot; logo. Like their precursor, these two flavors lasted for 12 weeks and were discontinued.

====2011 Modern Warfare 3 editions====
In early August 2011, an [[eBay]] auction was set up by a Pepsi employee for two unreleased flavors of Mountain Dew Game Fuel. Images of these two flavors showed that they were to promote the upcoming game [[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3]], that one of them would once again be the original Halo 3 flavor with updated packaging while the other would be a new, tropical-flavored drink (indicating it may be the Mystery flavor tested by Dew Labs members), and that they would be in stores in the near future. The auction ended on August 17, with the winning bid at $49.00 (plus $5.65 shipping charges). The status of these two flavors remained unconfirmed until August 24, when Mountain Dew officially announced the two flavors on their Facebook page, stating that they will return in October 2011 and will feature codes that grant players double experience points in-game. Both flavors were mailed out to Dew Labs members in early September 2011, a month before the planned release date. Later that same month, it was revealed through the Facebook page that Game Fuel would be arriving to the public in mid-October, though it would vary by market. Just as promised, Game Fuel began appearing as early as the first week of October, and was officially released as of October 10th.

===Green Label===
[[File:MtnDew16ozbottlespecialeditionartdesign.jpg|thumb|90px|right|A limited edition bottle featuring Green Label art]]Mountain Dew’s Green Label promotion originated in 2007 with “Green Label Art”,&lt;ref name=art07&gt;{{cite news|last=Miller|first=Yael|title=Green Label Art - Mountain Dew|url=http://www.thedieline.com/blog/2007/6/3/green-label-art-mountain-dew.html|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=The Dieline|date=3 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; which entails individual [[artist]]s submitting their own Mountain Dew can and bottle designs to be chosen by popular vote for actual production and distribution.&lt;ref name=thart&gt;{{cite web|last=Butty|first=Christina|title=Pop Surrealism Packaging: Mountain Dew's Green Label Art|url=http://www.trendhunter.com/trends/mountain-dews-green-label-art-volume-3|publisher=Trend Hunter|accessdate=27 January 2011|doi=25 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mountain Dew brand has been featuring limited edition works of art on its bottles and cans since 2007 and as of 2011 this campaign has remained active; however the Green Label concept has since branched out into four specific categories: ''art'', ''sound'' (music), ''sports'' and ''gaming''.&lt;ref name=glart&gt;{{cite news|last=Bott|first=Quinn|title=Mountain Dew announces Green Label Art Series|url=http://huntnewsnu.com/2010/07/mountain-dew-announces-green-label-art-series/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=The Huntington News|date=6 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====History====
Beginning in 2007, Mountain Dew put a small line of limited edition [[aluminum bottle]]s into limited-release production, featuring artwork from a range of [[tattoo artist]]s and other artists. This initial series marked the first use of the term''Green Label Art'' to describe the use of artistic works on Mountain Dew [[Packaging and labeling|product packaging]].&lt;ref name=arten&gt;{{cite news|title=Mountain Dew Limited Edition: Green Label Art|url=http://www.energyfiend.com/2007/05/mountain-dew-limited-edition-green-label-art|accessdate=19 January 2011|newspaper=Energy Fiend|date=18 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2010, a contest entitled “Green Label Art: Shop Series” was announced,&lt;ref name=heralddewtour&gt;{{cite news|last=Hammecker|first=Mike|title=Dew Tour: Green Label Shop Series|url=http://www.bostonherald.com/blogs/entertainment/art_scene/index.php/2010/06/24/dew-tour-green-label-shop-series/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=The Boston Herald|date=24 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; involving 35 independent [[skateboard]] retail store owners who partnered with artists local to their areas in order to design and submit future can artwork designs.&lt;ref name=artdub&gt;{{cite news|title=Green Label Art, Volume 3, Presented by Mountain Dew|url=http://www.dubdaily.com/?p=14649|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=DUB Daily|date=21 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately one million votes were submitted by the conclusion of this contest in October of the same year, with Street Science Skate Shop – a store in [[Tracy, California|Tracy]], [[California]] – being named the winner of a cash prize. This winning can design is scheduled to appear on Mountain Dew cans at some point in 2011, according to [[Skateboarder magazine]].&lt;ref name=artskmag&gt;{{cite journal|title=Green Label Art Shop Series Winners|journal=SkateBoarder Magazine|date=19 October 2010|url=http://www.skateboardermag.com/features/green-label-art-shop-series-winners/|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Green Label Sound====
In 2008, a Mountain Dew-sponsored [[music label]] was launched under the name ''Green Label Sound''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sisario&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/10/arts/music/10brand.html|title=Looking to a Sneaker For a Band's Big Break|last=Sisario|first=Ben|date=10 October 2010|work=The New York Times|page=1|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The label releases exclusive [[Single (music)|singles]] which it makes available for free download, with the intent of providing a broader exposure to emerging [[Musician|recording artists]]. Bands involved include [[Matt and Kim|Matt &amp; Kim]], [[The Cool Kids]] and [[Chromeo]], among others. According to Mikey Rocks of The Cool Kids, “Green Label Sound is giving artists like ourselves an opportunity to get to a different scale than we were previously on.”&lt;ref name=thillgrsound&gt;{{cite journal|last=Thill|first=Scott|title=Tastes Like Selling Out? Mountain Dew Launches Singles-Only Label|journal=Wired Magazine|date=21 August 2008|url=http://www.wired.com/listening_post/2008/08/caffeine-ocalpy/|accessdate=27 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2010, a Mountain Dew Code Red [[television advertisement]] was produced, incorporating the hip-hop artist [[Jay Electronica]] performing his song titled “The Announcement”.&lt;ref name=jayelectr&gt;{{cite news|title=Jay Electronica remakes 'The Announcement' for Mountain Dew Code Red|url=http://www.missinfo.tv/index.php/exclusive-jay-electronica-remixes-the-announcement-for-mountain-dew-code-red/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=Miss Info|date=23 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The advertisement concludes with the tagline: “Hip Hop is different on the mountain”, representing continued incorporation of [[Hip hop music|hip hop]] (along with other music genres) into Mountain Dew promotional campaigns.&lt;ref name=jayelect2&gt;{{cite news|last=Burgess|first=Omar|title=Jay Electronica Lands Mountain Dew Endorsement|url=http://www.hiphopdx.com/index/news/id.13451/title.jay-electronica-lands-mountain-dew-endorsement/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=Hip Hop DX|date=23 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Dew Tour/Green Label experience====
[[File:Salt Lake City Dew Tour BMX Start Ramp.jpg|thumb|left|2007 Dew Tour BMX in [[Salt Lake City]], [[Utah]] ]]Sponsorship of individual athletes who participate in professional [[action sports]] has been a part of the Mountain Dew brand since the late 1990s, with present sponsorship including [[Eli Reed]] (skateboarder), [[Paul Rodriguez Jr.|Paul Rodriguez]] (skateboarder), and [[Danny Davis (snowboarder)|Danny Davis]] (snowboarder).&lt;ref name=fueltv&gt;{{cite news|title=Fuel TV and Mountain Dew Announce 'Mountain Dew's Green Label Experience' TV Show|url=http://www.malakye.com/asp/front/CMSPage.asp?TYP_ID=4&amp;ID=2915|accessdate=23 January 2011|newspaper=Malakye News|date=16 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mountain Dew also sponsors its own namesake festival, &quot;The Dew Tour,&quot; which is an action sports tour made up of multiple events held in five U.S. cities over the course of several months.&lt;ref name=dewtour1&gt;{{cite web|title=Tour Info, Dew Tour 2010|url=http://www.allisports.com/winter-dew-tour/tour-info|publisher=Alli Sports|accessdate=24 January 2011|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Dew Tour was held in the summer of 2005 with events in [[skateboarding]], [[BMX]] and [[Freestyle Motocross]]. In 2008 it expanded to add a “Winter Dew Tour” as well, comprising [[snowboarding]] and [[Skiing#Freestyle_skiing|snow skiing]] competitions. It is ''“the most watched and attended action sports event in the world,”'' according to [[Transworld Snowboarding]] magazine.&lt;ref name=dewtourathl&gt;{{cite journal|title=Winter Dew Tour Athletes For 2010-2011 Season|journal=Transworld Snowboarding|date=28 October 2010|url=http://snowboarding.transworld.net/1000136497/news/winter-dew-tour-athletes-for-2010-2011-season/|accessdate=24 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dewtourutah&gt;{{cite news|last=Donaldson|first=Amy|title=Dew Tour review: Utah has emerged as a pretty great place for action sports|url=http://www.deseretnews.com/article/700067637/Dew-Tour-review-Utah-has-emerged-as-a-pretty-great-place-for-action-sports.html|accessdate=24 January 2011|newspaper=The Desert News (Salt Lake City, Utah)|date=22 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In coordination with its Dew Tour sponsorship, a sponsored television show entitled ''Mountain Dew’s Green Label Experience'' premiered on [[FUEL TV|Fuel TV]] in July, 2010, for the primary purpose of broadcasting interviews with action sports athletes from each of the stops on the Dew Tour.&lt;ref name=glexp&gt;{{cite news|first=Mike|title=Mountain Dew’s Green Label Experience|url=http://www.lat34.com/2010/06/16/mountain-dew%E2%80%99s-green-label-experience/|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=Lat 34|date=16 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Green Label Gaming====
Under the term ''Green Label Gaming'' – coined in 2007 – Mountain Dew has broadened its sponsorship of independent [[Video_game_designer#Game_designer|video game designers]] and [[Gamer|players]]. The brand is often the subject of media attention for its popularity among video game enthusiasts, as several flavors of Mountain Dew have been produced in partnership with video games such as [[Halo (series)|Halo]]&lt;ref name=dewhalo1&gt;{{cite news|last=Deleon|first=Nicholas|title=You &amp; Your Noble Team Buddies Can Win Some Mountain Dew Halo Goodies|url=http://www.crunchgear.com/2010/09/30/you-your-noble-team-buddies-can-win-some-mountain-dew-halo-goodies/|accessdate=26 January 2011|newspaper=CrunchGear|date=30 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[World of Warcraft]].&lt;ref name=nightelf&gt;{{cite news|last=McWhertor|first=Michael|title=World Of Warcraft Flavored Mtn Dew Ad Features Night Elf On Orc Action|url=http://kotaku.com/5293129/world-of-warcraft-flavored-mtn-dew-ad-features-night-elf-on-orc-action|accessdate=26 January 2011|newspaper=Kotaku|date=16 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2008, Mountain Dew produced a 30-minute television special which documented independent gamers in Japan and the U.S., which aired on the [[Spike TV]] network.&lt;ref name=gamehampp&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hampp|first=Andrew|title=Mountain Dew Sets Its Sights on Video-Game Market|journal=Advertising Age|date=11 December 2008|url=http://adage.com/madisonandvine/article?article_id=133193|accessdate=26 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Mountain Dew sponsored two prominent gaming events: the [[Independent Games Festival]] and the [[Game Developers Conference]].&lt;ref name=igfgreen&gt;{{cite news|title=Green Label Gaming Signs Up For IGF|url=http://www.igf.com/2009/02/green_label_gaming_signs_up_fo.html|accessdate=26 January 2011|newspaper=Independent Games Festival|month=February|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gamas2&gt;{{cite news|title=Competition Reminder: Imagine The Games Of 2020|url=http://www.gamasutra.com/php-bin/news_index.php?story=22493|accessdate=26 January 2011|newspaper=Gamasutra|date=4 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=indie&gt;{{cite news|last=Carless|first=Simon|title=Green Label Gaming Competition|url=http://www.indiegames.com/blog/2009/02/competition_imagine_the_games.html|accessdate=26 January 2011|newspaper=Indie Games|date=27 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Doritos Quest===
In 2008, [[Doritos]] debuted a mystery flavor known as &quot;Quest,&quot; featuring a campaign of online puzzles and prizes to identify the Quest flavor. The flavor was later identified as Mountain Dew.&lt;ref name=&quot;AV Club&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Koski|first=Genevieve|url=http://www.avclub.com/content/feature/taste_test_mountain_dew_quest|title=Taste Test: Mountain Dew &quot;Quest&quot; Doritos |publisher=The A.V. Club |date=|accessdate=2010-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===FanDEWmonium===
In October 2010, Mountain Dew announced a new promotion that was called &quot;FanDEWmonium&quot;,&lt;ref name=dietdewchallenge&gt;{{cite news|last=Gibbons|first=Lauren|title=MSU samples new Mountain Dew|url=http://statenews.com/index.php/article/2010/11/msu_samples_new_mountain_dew_|accessdate=27 January 2011|newspaper=State News|date=7 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; a Dewmocracy with eight diet semi-finalist flavors in which Diet Dew drinkers could go online and fill out a bracket style survey, indicating which top two flavors they would like to see later released in stores. Two variant flavors were current flavors that were introduced in diet form, four variant options were previously released flavors that were brought back in diet form, and two entirely new flavors and names were introduced: Diet Mountain Dew Flare (a berry citrus flavor) and Diet Mountain Dew Crave (a sweet and sour [[apple]] flavor). The two current flavors were Dewmocracy winners being introduced in diet form, Diet Mountain Dew White Out (a smooth citrus flavor) and Voltage (a raspberry-citrus flavor with a shot of ginseng for flavor enhancement), and the four returning flavors were Diet Mountain Dew Supernova (a strawberry-melon flavor), Distortion (a lime-citrus flavor), Typhoon (a strawberry-pineapple flavor), and Ultraviolet (a mixed berry flavor). Except for Ultraviolet (a former limited release flavor), the 3 other returning flavors were all previous Dewmocracy flavors that did not win. After many votes were cast, the finalists were diet versions of two of the three diet flavors that were newly introduced in the first DEWmocracy-Diet Voltage and Diet Supernova. The voting for these top two began March 6, 2011, when they were released in U.S. stores, pit stops, gas stations, and pharmacies for a limited duration of eight weeks.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewsupernovavoltagemarch11&quot; /&gt; Diet Mountain Dew Supernova was the eventual winner and thus, it became a permanent Diet Mountain Dew flavor. This new flavor of Diet Mountain Dew will be returning to stores full-time pending a further announcement that shall be outlining exact dates.

===Back by Popular DEWmand===
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2011}}
====Pre-release====
On January 7, 2011, Mountain Dew posted on their Facebook that Pitch Black would return to the shelves on May 2011. It stated that this may be the start of many re-releases of old favorites. The Company promoted Pitch Black's return heavily with giveaways and contests. About a month before the planned release date, a photo was released on a Mountain Dew Company worker's Pongr, which showed Pitch Black and 2008's Supernova. Two weeks before the release, Dew Labs announced the return of 2010's Typhoon in 2-Liter bottles exclusively at Walmart Supercenters.

====Release====
The 3 flavors were officially rereleased to stores on the second of May in 2011 and continued until July. At the same time, Mtn Dew announced the Throwback Shack, which contained Mtn Dew Revolution, a flavor long gone. It was widely spectated by DEW fans that Revolution would return next year. The spectation ended in July 25th, when the Back by Popular Dewmand promotion ended.

====End====
It was officially stated by the official &quot;Back By Popular DEWmand&quot; Facebook page on July 25 that the promotion had ended. The promotional advertisements were then taken down from the official Mountain Dew website. On a later date, Mountain Dew then confirmed via tweet that there would not be any more flavors returning 'by Popular DEWmand' for now, as it was only intended to be a summer program. They also stated that there were currently no plans to re-release Revolution, but they also had the quote &quot;we never say never&quot;.

==Flavors and varieties==
Following the success of Code Red in 2001, over 30 subsequent flavors bearing the &quot;Mountain Dew&quot; name have been introduced, such as LiveWire, an [[Orange (fruit)|orange]]-flavored variation, Pitch Black, a [[grape]]-flavored variation that was produced seasonally prior to [[Halloween]], and Typhoon, a strawberry-pineapple flavored variation that came in second in DEWmocracy 2: Collective Intelligence. This is a table covering them all.

[[File:DewFlavorsinCooler.jpg|600px|thumb|center|Eight flavors of Mountain Dew in a grocery store display cooler.]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; width:100%;&quot;
|+ Mountain Dew Soda Flavors
|-
|
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;15%&quot; | Dates of production
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; | Notes
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; | Picture
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; | Mountain Dew
|1948 – Present
|The original flavor. A yellow-green-colored, lemon-citrus-flavored soda that was developed in the 1940s by Barney and Ally Hartman, who were beverage bottlers in Tennessee. A revised formula was created by Bill Bridgforth in the year 1958.
|[[File:MountainDew-can.jpg|75px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Caffeine-Free Mountain Dew
|1976 – Present
|Non-caffeinated Mountain Dew. Available in various parts of the United States. In Canada and Australia, it is sold as regular Mountain Dew as neither country sell the original Mountain Dew.
|[[File:Caffeine free mountain dew.jpg|75px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew
|1988 – Present
|A no-calorie Mountain Dew that was first introduced in 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Andrew|title=Encyclopedia of junk food and fast food|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4jIOEZ5F9fAC&amp;lpg=PA188&amp;dq=%22Diet%20Mountain%20Dew%22%201988&amp;pg=PA188#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Diet%20Mountain%20Dew%22%201988&amp;f=false|year=2006|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Conn|isbn=0-313-33527-3|page=188}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was formerly known as “Sugar-Free Mountain Dew” until 1986, when it was given its current name. In 2006 Diet Mountain Dew was reformulated with a new “Tuned Up Taste”, using a blend of sucralose, aspartame, and acesulfame potassium as sweeteners. The previous formulation was sweetened exclusively with aspartame.&lt;ref name=&quot;dietdew06&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|title=A New Tuned Up Taste Changes How Dew Does Diet|publisher=PR Newswire|date=8 March 2006|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/a-new-tuned-up-tastetm-changes-how-dew-does-diet-55282307.html|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In limited areas in the United States, Diet Mountain Dew has treated water instead of carbonated water as a fountain drink.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Red
|1988
|Simply known to be Fruit-flavored Mountain Dew, Red was the first Mountain Dew flavor variation, and was discontinued the same year it was released. Its legacy lives on as Mountain Dew Code Red, but the two are entirely different flavors. It was only available from Alabama.
|
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Red
|1988
|Simply known to be a zero-calorie version of Mountain Dew Red. Like the original version, it was also discontinued in the same year it was introduced and was only available from Alabama.
|
|- 
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Caffeine-Free Diet Mountain Dew
|1989 – Present
|A no-calorie, non-caffeinated Mountain Dew. Available in limited locations in the United States. In Canada it is simply labeled as “Diet Mountain Dew.”&lt;ref name=&quot;caffreedietdew&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pepsimidamerica.com/consumer/pages/product_detail.php?ID=32|title=Caffeine Free Diet Mountain Dew|publisher=Pepsi MidAmerica|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|-

! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Sport
|1989–1991
|Following initial test marketing in 1989, this Mountain Dew-flavored sports drink was released in a limited number of U.S. regions in 1990. A 2-calorie variant was released, as well as a Diet version. They were all short-lived, being discontinued in 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;Janice Jorgensen1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Janice Jorgensen|first=|title=Encyclopedia of consumer brands|url=http://books.google.com/?id=r5cYAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Mountain+Dew+Sport%22+1991&amp;dq=%22Mountain+Dew+Sport%22+1991|year=1994|publisher=St. James Press|location=London|isbn=1-55862-336-1|page=206}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|- 
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Sport
|1989–1991
|A zero-calorie version of Mountain Dew Sport. Like the original version, it was also discontinued in 1991.
|
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Code Red
|2001 – Present
|A cherry-flavored Mountain Dew. Introduced in 2001, it was the first widely successful flavor extension; In its first year of production, Code Red increased overall sales of Mountain Dew by 6%.&lt;ref name=&quot;CodeRed&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/money/general/2002/05/07/pepsi-blue.htm|title=USATODAY.com -Marketers of colorful drinks dye for big sales|last=Howard|first=Theresa|date=8 May 2002|work=[[USA Today]]|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later released in [[New Zealand]] in 2009.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Code Red
|2002 – Present
|A no-calorie, no-sugar cherry-flavored Mountain Dew. Available in limited areas only, it was first introduced in late 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;livewirecodereddiet&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|title=Pepsi to Electrify Summer with 'Mountain Dew Livewire'|publisher=PR Newswire|date=25 February 2003|url=http://www.pepsicollector.com/pressrelease/020203MtDewLivewire.htm|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew LiveWire
|2003 – Present
|An orange-colored, orange-flavored Mountain Dew. LiveWire was initially introduced in 2003 as a limited-edition flavor for the summer.&lt;ref name=&quot;livewirecodereddiet&quot; /&gt; In 2005, after two years of limited summer releases, LiveWire became a permanent addition to the Mountain Dew product line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Livewire05&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2005/03/29/review-mountain-dew-livewire-2/|title=Update: Mountain Dew LiveWire|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=29 March 2005|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It appears that LiveWire became region-specific in 2011, as many areas across the U.S. began noticing its disappearance from shelves. It was also released in [[New Zealand]] in 2011.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Pitch Black
| 2004, 2011
|A dark purple-colored, grape-flavored Mountain Dew released for the 2004 Halloween season.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewtimeline1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mountaindew.com/#/products/timeline.php|title=Mountain Dew Product Timeline|publisher=PepsiCo, Inc.|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because [[Canada]] has restrictions, Pitch Black was released as a [http://www.flickr.com/photos/xpectations/3308030271 caffeine-free drink] in Canada. Pitch Black was re-released in 2011 as a part of the &quot;Back by popular DEWmand&quot; promotion in the United States and was also released New Zealand. The US version stayed on shelves through May and July.&lt;ref name=&quot;bevrev&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Tanner|first=Steve|title=News: Mountain Dew Pitch Black is &quot;Back By Popular DEWmand&quot; and stayed on shelves through June and July. |url=http://www.bevreview.com/2011/01/07/mountain-dew-pitch-black-is-back-by-popular-dew-mand-in-2011/|publisher=BevReview|accessdate=10 January 2011|doi=07 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Baja Blast
|2004 – Present
|A sea green-colored, tropical lime-flavored Mountain Dew introduced in 2004, available exclusively as a fountain drink at [[Taco Bell]] restaurants. Beginning in January 2006, internet hoaxes began spreading, claiming that Baja Blast would be available in 20 oz. bottles and sold in stores. In 2011, however, videos began surfacing online of people finding this flavor in fountain drinks in convenience stores outside of Taco Bell restaurants, revealing that the drink was no longer exclusive Taco Bell exclusive. Beverage reviewers have noted a similarity in taste between the Mountain Dew Game Fuel Alliance Blue limited edition flavor and Baja Blast.&lt;ref name=&quot;bajablast&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2004/07/30/review-mountain-dew-baja-blast/|title=Mountain Dew Baja Blast|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=30 July 2004|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Pitch Black II
|2005
|A dark purple-colored, sour grape-flavored Mountain Dew, released as a limited edition flavor for Halloween in 2005. Referred to as the &quot;sequel” to the original Pitch Black, which was released in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;pitchblacktwo&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2005/08/26/review-mountain-dew-pitch-black-ii/|title=Mountain Dew Pitch Black II|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=26 August 2005|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[File:Mountain Dew Pitch Black 2.jpg|150px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Game Fuel (Halo 3 Edition)
|2007
|A red-orange-colored, citrus-cherry-flavored Mountain Dew first released in August 2007 for a total of 12 weeks to promote the release of [[Halo 3]], an [[Xbox 360]] game. Two years later, this flavor saw a limited return to shelves promoting the MMORPG [[World of Warcraft]]. It was sold under the name &quot;Mountain Dew Game Fuel Horde Red&quot; with redesigned packaging and a new counterpart flavor. It was officially announced that this flavor would once again return to shelves to coincide with the upcoming game [[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3]]. Its taste has been compared to &quot;LiveWire&quot;, &quot;Code Red&quot; and the energy drink AMP Overdrive (another drink sold under the Mountain Dew brand name).&lt;ref name=&quot;GameFuel07&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2007/08/12/review-mountain-dew-game-fuel/|title=Mountain Dew Game Fuel » Citrus Cherry Mountain Dew based on Halo 3|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=12 August 2007|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Revolution
|2008
|A sky blue-colored, wild berry fruit-flavored Mountain Dew with [[ginseng]] for flavor enhancement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revolution10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2008/06/11/review-mountain-dew-revolution/|title=Mountain Dew Revolution|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=11 June 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the three “candidate flavor” finalists for DEWmocracy's “People’s Dew” national vote. Revolution held the majority amount of votes until the end of the promotion, when dropped to 3rd place and lost to Mountain Dew Voltage.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewmocracy2008results&quot; /&gt; In 2011, The &quot;Mountain Dew Throwback Shack&quot; began to have a prize of &quot;A Hidden Stash of Dew&quot; which was then revealed to be glass bottles of Revolution with lab labels on them. Demand for Revolution has increased since Pitch Black, Typhoon, and Supernova were returning to shelves, but Mountain Dew said that there were currently no plans to rerelease Revolution.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Supernova
|2008, 2011
|A magenta-colored, strawberry-melon-flavored Mountain Dew with [[ginseng]].&lt;ref name=&quot;supernova10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2008/05/22/review-mountain-dew-supernova/|title=Mountain Dew Supernova|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=22 May 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the three “candidate flavor” finalists for DEWmocracy's “People’s Dew” national vote, it lost to Mountain Dew Voltage. It had held the least amount of votes until the end, when it ended up coming in 2nd place.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewmocracy2008results&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2008/08/19/news-mountain-dew-voltage-wins-dewmocracy-vote/|title=News: Mountain Dew Voltage wins DEWmocracy vote|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=19 August 2008|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This flavor was re-released as a part of the &quot;Back by popular DEWmand&quot; promotion in early May 2011 and stayed on shelves through July.&lt;ref name=bevrev /&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Voltage
|2008 – Present 
|A deep blue-colored, raspberry-citrus-flavored Mountain Dew with [[ginseng]] for flavor enhancement. A part of the first DEWmocracy promotion, it was released in stores on May 19, 2008 as a limited edition flavor so that people could taste test which flavor they like best before voting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Voltage10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2008/05/28/review-mountain-dew-voltage/|title=Mountain Dew Voltage|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=28 May 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Voltage was announced to be the winner with 42% of all votes on August 17, 2008. It was officially released as a permanent flavor on December 29, 2008.
A Diet Voltage was released in 2011 as a part of the &quot;FanDEWmonium&quot; promotion&lt;ref name=&quot;dietdewchallenge&quot; /&gt; and made it to the finals with Diet Mountain Dew Supernova, meaning it had a limited release in U.S. stores while voting took place, until Diet Supernova was revealed to be the winner.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewsupernovavoltagemarch11&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.waltonbeverage.com/content/products/new_products.asp|title=New Products -Mountain Dew fanDEWmonium|publisher=Walton Beverage|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It came in second in voting, against Diet Mountain Dew Supernova with 45% out of all votes.
It was later released in [[New Zealand]] in 2011 under the name &quot;Electro Shock&quot; and described as a &quot;charge of wild berry flavor.&quot;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Game Fuel Horde Red
|2009
|In 2009, the original &quot;Game Fuel&quot; flavor returned to shelves for 10 weeks under this name in connection with the [[World of Warcraft]] video game. The name and label design were updated to reflect the World of Warcraft theme.&lt;ref name=&quot;HordeRed09&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2009/06/09/mountain-dew-game-fuel-horde-red/|title=Mountain Dew Game Fuel Horde Red » World of Warcraft Mtn Dew citrus cherry|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=9 June 2009|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was rereleased on October 2011 with updated packaging to promote the video game &quot;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3&quot;.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Game Fuel Alliance Blue
|2009
|A blue-colored, wild fruit punch-flavored Mountain Dew flavor released alongside &quot;Mountain Dew Game Fuel Horde Red&quot; for a 10-week period in 2009. Like Horde Red, Alliance Blue was a promotional flavor for the video game [[World of Warcraft]].&lt;ref name=&quot;allianceblue09&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2009/06/15/mountain-dew-game-fuel-alliance-blue/|title=Mountain Dew Game Fuel Allliance Blue » World of Warcraft Mtn Dew wild fruit Alliance Blue soda|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=15 June 2009|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Ultra Violet
|2009–2010
|A lavender-colored, mixed berry-flavored Mountain Dew. It was originally available for three months in 2009; and was the first Mountain Dew flavor available exclusively in Diet. It was released on August 3, 2009 at a first taste party in Brooklyn, New York. This flavor returned for the &quot;FanDEWmonium&quot; promotion, but ultimately lost to Diet Mountain Dew Supernova, coming in sixth place and not making it into the final round. Its flavor is sometimes compared to that of &quot;Revolution&quot; due to their berry-themed flavoring.&lt;ref name=&quot;dietultraviolet2009&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2009/08/10/diet-mtn-dew-ultra-violet-mountain-dew-ultraviolet/|title=Diet Mtn Dew Ultra Violet » Limited edition berry-flavored Diet Mountain Dew UltraViolet with zero calories|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=10 August 2009|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Throwback
|2009 – Present
|A variation of Mountain Dew in the U.S. consisting of natural sugar in place of high fructose corn syrup, first released in a limited production run during the summer of 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;hfcs&quot; /&gt; Mountain Dew Throwback has since been re-released for brief periods (generally 8–12 weeks at a time), including a 2nd wave from December 2009 - February 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;throwback2nd&quot; /&gt; and a 3rd wave in Summer/Fall 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;throwback3rd&quot; /&gt; A fourth limited production run began in March 2011, lasting for a total of eight weeks before becoming a permanent addition.&lt;ref name=&quot;limitedreleasestatus&quot; /&gt;
|[[File:Mountain Dew Throwback.jpg|80px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Cherry Fusion
|2009 – Present
|A red-colored, cherry-flavored fountain drink only available at Wienerschnitzel restaurants in the [[Western United States]]. It has a stronger cherry flavor in comparison to ''Code Red''.&lt;ref name=&quot;cherryfusion&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wienerschnitzel.com/Wienerschnitzel-Nutrition-Guide-12-2010.pdf|title=Wienerschnitzel Menu - Nutritional Information|date=November 2010|publisher=Galardi Group, Inc.|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cherryfusiontrademark&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trademarkia.com/mtn-dew-cherry-fusion-85166448.html|title=MTN DEW CHERRY FUSION- Trademark by PEPSICO, INC. PURCHASE, NY - Serial Number: 85166448|date=7 January 2011|publisher=Trademarkia|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Distortion
|2010
|A dark green-colored, lime-flavored Mountain Dew. Part of the second Mountain Dew &quot;DEWmocracy: Collective Intelligence&quot; promotion. It lost to Mountain Dew White Out and came in 3rd place with only 16% out of all votes. Due to its similarity in color to the original Mountain Dew, Distortion was packaged in a clear bottle with a black label (as opposed to the green-plastic bottle with a green label used in the original Mountain Dew) in an attempt to avoid confusion.&lt;ref name=&quot;distortion10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/04/26/mountain-dew-distortion/|title=Mountain Dew Distortion » Lime Blasted Mtn Dew DEWmocracy Flavor|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=26 April 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Diet Distortion was created for the FanDEWmonium promotion, which came in eighth place, not making it to the final round.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Typhoon
|2010, 2011
|A red-orange-colored, strawberry-pineapple flavored Mountain Dew. Part of the second Mountain Dew &quot;DEWmocracy: Collective Intelligence&quot; promotion. It lost to Mountain Dew White Out and came in 2nd place with 40% of all votes. A Diet Typhoon was created for the FanDEWmonium promotion, which came in fifth place, not making it to the final round. It was announced on April 15, 2011 that Typhoon would return in May 2011 as part of the &quot;Back by Popular DEWmand&quot; promotion and it stayed on shelves in 2-Liter bottles exclusively at Walmart Supercenters through July.&lt;ref name=&quot;typhoon10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/05/04/mountain-dew-typhoon/|title=Mountain Dew Typhoon » Punch of Tropical Mtn Dew DEWmocracy Flavor|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=4 May 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew White Out
|2010 – present
|A white-colored, smooth citrus-flavored Mountain Dew. Part of the second Mountain Dew &quot;DEWmocracy: Collective Intelligence&quot; promotion. It was released in stores on April 19 as a limited edition flavor so that people could taste test which flavor they like best before voting. Voting ended on June 14, and it was announced  that White Out had won the campaign with 44% of the votes. It became a permanent flavor and was officially for sale on October 4, 2010. A Diet White Out was created for the FanDEWmonium promotion, which came in third place, not making it to the final round. It has been available in slurpee form since January 2011 and was later released in [[New Zealand]] in 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;whiteout10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2010/04/28/mountain-dew-white-out/|title=Mountain Dew White Out » Smooth Citrus Mtn Dew DEWmocracy Flavor|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=28 April 2010|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[File:Mountain dew whiteout.jpg|80px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Flare
|2011
|A deep yellow-colored, berry-citrus-flavored Diet Mountain Dew. Part of &quot;FanDEWmonium&quot; promotion series of flavors but it lost to Diet Mountain Dew Supernova and came in fourth place, making it into the final round.
|[http://a5.sphotos.ak.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ak-ash1/182883_10150089595296395_349910341394_6376962_6023875_n.jpg]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Crave
|2011
|A light green-colored, sweet and sour apple-flavored Diet Mountain Dew. Part of &quot;FanDEWmonium&quot; promotion series of flavors but it lost to Diet Mountain Dew Supernova, coming in seventh place and not making it to the final round.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Diet Mountain Dew Supernova
|2011
|A magenta-colored, strawberry-melon-flavored Diet Mountain Dew with a &quot;shot of [[ginseng]]&quot; for flavor enhancement. This flavor began as one of the &quot;FanDEWmonium&quot; promotion series of flavors.&lt;ref name=&quot;dietdewchallenge&quot; /&gt; Diet Supernova was released in U.S. stores alongside Diet Mountain Dew Voltage on March 6, 2011 for a duration of eight weeks as a limited edition diet flavor so that people could taste test which flavor they preferred before voting.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewsupernovavoltagemarch11&quot; /&gt; It won FanDEWmonium with 55% out of all votes, and this flavor became a permanent addition to the Diet Mountain Dew flavor line-up.&lt;ref name=dietsupernova&gt;{{cite news|last=Tanner|first=Steve|title=Review: Diet Mountain Dew Supernova|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2011/03/22/diet-mountain-dew-supernova/|accessdate=4 May 2011|newspaper=BevReview|date=22 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dietdewsupernovaperm&gt;{{cite news|title=Diet Dew Supernova Chosen As Brand's Newest Flavor|url=http://www.beverageworld.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=39060&amp;catid=3&amp;Itemid=173|accessdate=4 May 2011|newspaper=Beverage World|date=6 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It will be returning to stores full-time pending a further announcement that shall outline exact dates.
|[[File:Diet mountain dew supernova.jpg|75px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew X-treme
|2010 – Present
|A Grape-flavored Mountain Dew similar to &quot;Pitch Black&quot;. It was released in Kuwait during December 2010 and has so far made its way into Saudi Arabia.
|
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Grape
|2011 – Present
|A deep purple-colored, Grape-flavored Mountain Dew. Since its introduction in mid-2011, it has only been available in Japan exclusively in Pepsi and Boss vending machines.  It is only offered in {{convert|12|oz|abbr=on}} cans and not available in stores in Japan. Its taste has often been compared to that of Grape flavored [[Jolly Rancher]] candies.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Game Fuel Cherry-Citrus 
(Call of Duty: MW3 Edition)
|October 2011 – Present
|The same red-orange-colored, cherry-citrus formula used for the original Game Fuel in 2007 and for Game Fuel Horde Red in 2009. For its 2011 release, its packaging was redesigned to promote the video game [[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3]]. Though this drink's concept was leaked in early August 2011 by means of an eBay auction, it was officially announced on Mountain Dew Facebook page on August 24, 2011 and was officially released to US stores on October 10 that year.
|[[File:Mtn Dew Game Fuel Red.jpg|75px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Game Fuel Tropical
(Call of Duty: MW3 Edition)
|October 2011 – Present
|A dark green-colored, Tropical-flavored Mountain Dew flavor to coincide with the release of the video game [[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3]]. Like its counterpart, its concept was leaked in early August 2011 by means of an eBay auction, and was officially announced on Mountain Dew Facebook page on August 24, 2011 and was officially released to US stores on October 10 that year. It was originally tested by 500 Dew Labs members as a &quot;Mystery&quot; flavor, and was described by many to resemble the taste of &quot;Baja Blast&quot; and &quot;Distortion&quot;.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; width:100%;&quot;
|+ Mountain Dew Slurpee &amp; Energy Variations
|-
|
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;15%&quot; | Dates of production
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; | Notes
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; | Picture
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; | Mountain Dew Blue Shock
|2001 – present
|Berry-citrus flavored Mountain Dew.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/dallas/stories/2002/05/27/daily35.html |title=7-Eleven launches Mountain Dew Blue Shock Slurpee – Dallas Business Journal:|publisher=Bizjournals.com|date=2002-05-31 |accessdate=2010-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blue Shock was initially test-marketed in [[Chicago, Illinois|Chicago]] in can and bottle formats, but sales did not meet expectations and as a result, it was released in 2002 in the U.S. exclusively in [[Slurpee]] form at [[7-Eleven]] stores. As of 2011, it remains listed as a current flavor according to 7-Eleven.&lt;ref name=&quot;blueshockfreeze&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slurpee.com/Flavors/|title=Slurpee flavors and nutrition information|publisher=7-Eleven, Inc.|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was once available at select Marcus Theatres in Icee form.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Dew Fuel
|2002–2007
|A caffeinated version of Mountain Dew produced in [[Canada]]. Marketed as a natural health product and not as a soft drink, due to Health Canada regulations that only allow caffeine in 'dark-colored' varieties of soft drinks such as cola and root beer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shea2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Shea|first=Kitty|title=Teens in Canada|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=r3eO9ChGWfAC&amp;pg=PA31|accessdate=1 February 2011|date=2008-01-01|publisher=Compass Point Books|isbn=9780756533038|pages=31–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally called “Mountain Dew Energy” until given its present name in 2006. In early 2007, Pepsi-QTG Canada cited that Dew Fuel is out of production.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Dew Fuel Sugar Free
|2002–2007
|No-calorie Dew Fuel. The caffeinated version of Diet Mountain Dew offered in Canada. Was originally called “Mountain Dew Energy Sugar-Free” until 2006.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Darth Dew
|2005
|A limited production tangy grape flavored Mountain Dew [[Slurpee]] flavor.&lt;ref name=&quot;darth1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://x-entertainment.com/updates/2005/05/15/the-darth-dew-star-wars-slurpee/|title=The 'Darth Dew' Star Wars Slurpee|first=Matt|date=15 May 2005|work=X-Entertainment|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was available exclusively at 7-Eleven stores as part of a promotion for the theatrical release of ''[[Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith|Star Wars Episode III]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.starwars.com/episode-iii/release/promo/news20050505.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060307230025/http://www.starwars.com/episode-iii/release/promo/news20050505.html|archivedate=2006-03-07|title=Star Wars: Episode III &amp;#124; Revenge is a Sith Best Served Cold: Pepsi's New Darth Dew|publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2005-05-05 |accessdate=2010-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[http://www.x-entertainment.com/updates/pics/vaderdew/3.jpg]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Mountain Dew MDX]]
|2005–2007
|A Mountain Dew-flavored energy soda introduced in 2005 in {{convert|14|USfloz|ml|adj=on}} bottles.&lt;ref name=&quot;mdx2005&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2005/11/21/review-mountain-dew-mdx/|title=Mountain Dew MDX|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=21 November 2005|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 its packaging format was transitioned to {{convert|20|USfloz|ml|adj=on}} bottles.&lt;ref name=&quot;MDX2006&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bevreview.com/2006/11/12/review-mountain-dew-mdx-20-oz/|title=Mountain Dew MDX 20 oz.|last=Tanner|first=Steve|date=12 November 2006|work=BevReview|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its production was discontinued in 2007.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Pitch Black Freeze
|2006
|A re-release of Pitch Black in [[Slurpee]] form produced as a limited edition flavor during the 2006 Halloween season.&lt;ref name=&quot;pitchblackfreeze&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.x-entertainment.com/halloween/2006/september18/|title=2006 Halloween Countdown: Mountain Dew Pitch Black Freeze|first=Matt|date=18 September 2006|work=X-Entertainment|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Maximum Cream Slush
|2004–2008
|A frozen, no-sugar, no-carbonation fruit slush sold in participating 7-11 convenience stores.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Arctic Burst
|2006
|A Mountain Dew [[Slurpee]] flavor available exclusively at [[7-Eleven]] stores as part of a promotion for the theatrical release of ''[[Superman Returns]]''. The Slurpee is blue in color and said to taste like blueberry. The official name was “Arctic Burst”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.x-entertainment.com/updates/pics/superslurp/1.jpg|title=&quot;Mountain Dew Arctic Burst&quot; labeled Slurpee Machine}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Kryptonite Ice
|2006
|A Mountain Dew [[Slurpee]] flavor available exclusively at [[7-Eleven]] stores as part of a promotion for the theatrical release of ''[[Superman Returns]]''. The Slurpee is green in color and had a tropical, mango taste.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Sugar-Free Mountain Dew MDX
|2005–2006
|No-calorie Mountain Dew flavored energy soda which was short-lived, being discontinued one year after entering production in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;mdxsf05&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/28/business/28adco.html|title=ADVERTISING; If It's After Midnight, Then It's Time to Market to Young Men|last=Bosman|first=Julie|date=28 November 2005|work=The New York Times|page=11|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Dew Iced
|2007–2008
|A Mountain Dew flavored [[smoothie]] that was available exclusively at [[Cold Stone Creamery]] stores in 2007 and 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewiced&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Cold Stone Creamery Unveils New Frozen Treat Innovations For The Love of It|url=http://www.coldstonecreamery.com/assets/pdf/news/Summer_Treats_05_15_07.pdf|publisher=Cold Stone Creamery (Press Release)|accessdate=10 January 2011|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Game Fuel (slurpee)
|August 2007
|A red-orange colored, cherry citrus flavored slurpee that is available only at participating 7-11 convenience stores. Like the original version, it was introduced in August 2007 and was used to promote the Xbox 360 game &quot;Halo 3&quot;.
|[http://www.freewebs.com/bringbackthedew/Game%20fuel%20slurpee.bmp]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Blue Shock Freeze
|2008 – Present
|A blueberry Slurpee flavor only available at 7-Eleven stores.&lt;ref name=&quot;blueshockfreeze&quot; /&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Thin Ice Freeze
|2009 – Present
|A blueberry-flavored [[Slurpee]] that is distributed only at 7-Eleven stores.&lt;ref name=&quot;blueshockfreeze&quot; /&gt;
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew White Out Freeze
|2011 – Present
|A smooth citrus, limited edition Slurpee flavor only available at 7-Eleven stores.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Voltage Freeze
|2011 – Present
|A deep-blue colored [[Slurpee]] that is distributed only at 7-Eleven stores. It has a raspberry-citrus flavor and a hint of [[ginseng]] for flavor enhancement.
|&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here, per WP:NFTABLE --&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Coolata
|2011 – Present
|In 2011, Dunkin' Donuts announced a new Mountain Dew-flavored Coolata
|[http://gothamist.com/attachments/jsaxena/050211dewlatta.jpg]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Mountain Dew Energy
|2010 – present
|A new line of Mountain Dew released in the [[UK]] in June, 2010, originally in 500ml bottles, but as of February 2011 it has expanded to 440ml cans (Normal and sugar free) and 1 Litre bottles. Mountain Dew Energy was released in [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]] in April 2011. Produced in a lemon and lime flavor, it has a higher caffeine content as Mountain Dew sold in the [[U.S.]], at 18&amp;nbsp;mg per 100ml,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tesco.com/groceries/Product/Details/?id=267482964 Tesco - Mountain Dew Energy&lt;/ref&gt; versus 91&amp;nbsp;mg per 20 fl oz in the U.S. version&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pepsicobeveragefacts.com/infobyproduct.php?prod_type=1026&amp;prod_size=20&amp;brand_fam_id=1049&amp;brand_id=1000&amp;product=Mountain+Dew PepsiCo beverage facts - Mtn Dew&lt;/ref&gt; (which is ~15.385&amp;nbsp;mg per 100ml). The UK version is produced with real sugar instead of high-fructose corn syrup, as with most other soft drinks in the UK. Mountain Dew did initially launch in the UK and the Republic of Ireland in 1996; however it was discontinued in 1998 due to low sales volumes at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ukdewlaunch&quot; /&gt;  Mountain Dew Energy has been designed specifically for periods of mental and physical exertion, just like the original Mountain Dew distributed in the US.  The high (compared to regular soft drinks) level of caffeine and sugar gives much the same &quot;boost&quot; as other caffeine-heavy energy drinks, making the drink particularly popular with 16-24 year olds. The drink is produced by [[Britvic]] in the UK. The original Mountain Dew is only available either from eBay, Amazon, Selfridges or other specialist importers such as [http://www.americansweets.co.uk Stateside Candy].
|[[File:MDE-Bottle-and-Can.jpg|120px]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | Adrenaline Mountain Dew
|2010 – present
|In August 2010, this new flavor was released to [[Poland]] and possibly other polish-speaking countries. Much like previous attempts, Adrenaline is marketed as a Mountain Dew energy drink, and contains things such as [[caffeine]], [[taurine]], [[guarana]] extract, [[ginseng]], and vitamins B2 and B12. The drink is available in 250 ml cans, and also in an undetermined size of black-tinted bottles (similar to Mountain Dew Energy's green-tinted bottles). Because the drink is fairly recent and not available in English-speaking countries, not much is known of it as of yet.

|}

==See also==
* [[Mello Yello]]
* [[Sun Drop]]
* [[Generic citrus sodas]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{ external media
| align  = 
| width  = 
| audio1 = [http://www.springbokradio.com/ADSMOUNTAINDEW.html 1968 Mountain Dew advert] from the South African [[Springbok Radio]] preservation society (''in Afrikaans'').
}}
*{{Official website|http://mountaindew.com/}}
*[http://www.britvic.co.uk/en/Our-Brands/Mountain-Dew-Energy.aspx Official UK website]
*[http://www.dewbajablast.com/ Mountain Dew Baja Blast official website]
*[http://www.dewmocracy.com/ Dewmocracy]
*[http://www.mariettasodamuseum.com/MtDew%20Facts.htm Marietta Soda Museum]
{{PepsiCo}}
{{citrus sodas}}

[[Category:Mountain Dew|*]]
[[Category:1948 introductions]]
[[Category:PepsiCo brands]]
[[Category:PepsiCo soft drinks]]

[[ar:ماونتن ديو]]
[[cs:Mountain Dew]]
[[da:Mountain Dew]]
[[de:Mountain Dew]]
[[es:Mountain Dew]]
[[fr:Mountain Dew (boisson)]]
[[ko:마운틴 듀]]
[[nl:Mountain Dew]]
[[ja:マウンテンデュー]]
[[no:Mountain Dew]]
[[nn:Mountain Dew]]
[[pl:Mountain Dew]]
[[pt:Mountain Dew]]
[[ro:Mountain Dew]]
[[ru:Mountain Dew]]
[[simple:Mountain Dew]]
[[fi:Mountain Dew]]
[[sv:Mountain Dew]]
[[zh:激浪]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
