<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="520451" ns="0" title="Hoyt Vandenberg"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the man|the USNS General Hoyt S. Vandenberg|USS General Harry Taylor (AP-145)}}
{{Refimprove|date=July 2009}}

{{Infobox military person
|name=Hoyt Sanford Vandenberg
|birth_date= {{birth date|1899|01|24}}
|death_date= {{death date and age|1954|04|02|1899|01|24}}
|birth_place=[[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, Wisconsin]]
|death_place=[[Walter Reed Medical Center]], Washington D.C.
|image=[[File:Hoyt S Vandenberg.jpg|250px|Hoyt Vandenberg]]
|caption=
|nickname=
|allegiance=[[United States|United States of America]]
|branch= [[United States Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt;[[United States Army]]
|serviceyears=1923–1953
|rank=[[File:US-O10 insignia.svg|35px]] [[General (United States)|General]]
|commands= [[12th Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt; [[9th Air Force]]
|battles=[[World War II]]
|awards=[[Distinguished Service Medal (United States)|Distinguished Service Medal]] (2) &lt;br/&gt; [[Silver Star]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Legion of Merit]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Air Medal]] (5)
|laterwork=
}}
'''Hoyt Sanford Vandenberg''' (January 24, 1899 &amp;ndash; April 2, 1954) was a [[United States Air Force|U.S. Air Force]] [[List of United States Air Force four-star generals|general]], its second [[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force|Chief of Staff]], and second [[Director of Central Intelligence]].

During [[World War II]], Vandenberg was the commanding general of the [[Ninth Air Force]], a tactical air force in England and in France, supporting the Army, from August 1944 until V-E Day. [[Vandenberg Air Force Base]] on the central coast of [[California]] is named for General Vandenberg. In 1946, he was briefly the U.S. Chief of Military Intelligence. He was also the nephew of [[Arthur H. Vandenberg]], a former U.S. Senator from Michigan.

==Military career==
Vandenberg was born in [[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, Wisconsin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/vitalrecords/index.asp?id=3261327&amp;record_type=b|title=Birth Record Details|publisher=Wisconsin Historical Society|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; He grew up in [[Lowell, Massachusetts]], spending his teenage years there. He graduated from the [[United States Military Academy]] on June 12, 1923, and was commissioned a second lieutenant in the [[United States Army Air Service|Air Service]].

General Vandenberg graduated from the Air Service Flying School at [[Brooks Air Force Base|Brooks Field, Texas]], in February 1924, and from the Air Service Advanced Flying School at [[Kelly Air Force Base|Kelly Field, Texas]], in September 1924.

His first assignment was with the [[90th Fighter Squadron|90th Attack Squadron]], part of the [[3d Operations Group|3d Attack Group]] at Kelly Field. Vandenberg was appointed commander of the 90th AS on January 1, 1926. In 1927, he became an instructor at the Air Corps Primary Flying School at [[March Air Reserve Base|March Field]], Calif. He went to [[Wheeler Army Airfield|Wheeler Field]], [[Hawaii]], in May 1929, to join the [[6th Night Fighter Squadron|6th Pursuit Squadron]], and assumed command of it the following November.

Returning in September 1931, he was appointed a flying instructor at [[Randolph AFB|Randolph Field]], Texas, and became a flight commander and deputy stage commander there in March 1933. He entered the [[Air Corps Tactical School]] at [[Maxwell AFB|Maxwell Field]], Alabama, in August 1934, and graduated the following June. Two months later he enrolled in the [[Command and General Staff College|Command and General Staff School]] at [[Fort Leavenworth, Kansas]], and completed the course in June 1936. He then became an instructor in the Pursuit Section of the Air Corps Tactical School, where he taught until September 1936, when he entered the [[U.S. Army War College|Army War College]], where he specialized in air defense planning for the Philippines.

After graduating from the War College in June 1939, General Vandenberg was assigned to the Plans Division in the Office of the Chief of Air Corps, selected personally by its head, Brig. Gen. [[Carl Spaatz|Carl A. Spaatz]], whom he had met at the Command and General Staff College. In September 1939 and the autumn of 1940, Vandenberg developed two air plans for the Philippine Department, the second based on [[Royal Air Force]] interceptor operations in the [[Battle of Britain]], but neither was adopted by the War Department when the Roosevelt Administration reaffirmed its long-standing opposition to any plan that called for extensive reinforcement of the defenses in the Philippines.&lt;ref name=&quot;dec24&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author= Bartsch, William H.| chapter= | title=December 8, 1941: MacArthur's Pearl Harbor| editor=| publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press | isbn= 1-58544-246-1| year=2003| pages=}}, pp. 50-54.&lt;/ref&gt;

A few months after the United States entered [[World War II]], he became operations and training officer of the Air Staff. For his services in these two positions he received the Distinguished Service Medal.
[[File:American World War II senior military officials, 1945.JPEG|thumb|Eisenhower (seated, middle) with other US Army officers, 1945. From left to right, the front row includes Simpson, Patton, Spaatz, Eisenhower, Bradley, Hodges, and Gerow. Vandenberg is second from the left in the second row.]]

In June 1942, General Vandenberg was assigned to the United Kingdom and assisted in the organization of the Air Forces in North Africa. While in Great Britain he was appointed the chief of staff of the [[Twelfth Air Force]], which he helped organize. On February 18, 1943, General Vandenberg became the chief of staff of the [[Northwest African Strategic Air Force]] (NASAF) which was under the command of Major General [[Jimmy Doolittle|James Doolittle]]. NASAF was the strategic arm of the new [[Northwest African Air Forces]] (NAAF) under Lieutenant General [[Carl Spaatz]]. With NASAF, Vandenberg flew on numerous missions over Tunisia, Pantelleria, Sardinia, Sicily, and Italy. He was awarded both the Silver Star and the Distinguished Flying Cross for his services during this time. For his organizational ability with the [[12th Air Force]] and his work as chief of staff of the NASAF he was awarded the [[Legion of Merit]].

In August 1943, Vandenberg was assigned to Air Force headquarters as Deputy Chief of Air Staff. In September 1943, he became head of an air mission to Russia, under Ambassador Harriman, and returned to the United States in January 1944. In March 1944, he was transferred to the European theater, and in April 1944, was designated the Deputy Air Commander in Chief of the Allied Expeditionary Forces and the Commander of its American Air Component.

In August 1944, General Vandenberg assumed command of the [[Ninth Air Force]]. On November 28, 1944, he received an oak leaf cluster to his [[Distinguished Service Medal (United States)|Distinguished Service Medal]] for his part in planning the Normandy invasion. He was promoted to Lieutenant General in March 1945.

He was appointed the Assistant Chief of Air Staff at the Army Air Forces ([[USAAF]]) headquarters in July 1945. In January 1946, he became director of Intelligence on the War Department general staff where he served until his appointment in June 1946, as [[Director of Central Intelligence]], a position he held until May 1947.&lt;ref&gt;Curt Gentry, ''J. Edgar Hoover: The Man and the Secrets'' (NY: W.W. Norton, 1991), 391&lt;/ref&gt;

General Vandenberg returned to duty with the Air Force in April 1947, and on June 15, 1947, became the Deputy Commander in Chief of the Air Staff. Following the division of the [[United States Department of War]] into the [[United States Department of the Army|Departments of the Army]] and [[United States Department of the Air Force|the Air Force]], Lieutenant General Vandenberg was designated the Vice Chief of Staff of the Air Force on October 1, 1947, and promoted to the rank of General.
[[File:Gen Vandenberg 1945.jpg|thumb|left|upright|On the January 15, 1945, cover of [[Time (magazine)|''Time'' magazine]]]]
Even when he was at the pinnacle of his military career, General Vandenberg’s boyish good looks and outgoing personality often made him the target of attacks on his credibility and experience. But the attention that his appearance brought on was not all bad, having appeared on the covers of [[Time (magazine)|''Time'']] and ''[[LIFE]]'' magazines. The [[Washington Post]] once described him as “the most impossibly handsome man on the entire Washington scene,” and [[Marilyn Monroe]] once named Vandenberg, along with [[Joe DiMaggio]] and [[Albert Einstein]], as one of the three people with whom she would want to be stranded on a deserted island.

On April 30, 1948, General Vandenberg became the [[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force]], succeeding General [[Carl Spaatz]]. He was renominated by President [[Harry S. Truman]] for a second term as Air Force Chief of Staff on March 6, 1952. The nomination was confirmed on April 28, 1952, with Vandenberg serving until June 30, 1953.

A controversy arose while he was the Air Force Chief of Staff, when he opposed the [[Secretary of Defense]] [[Charles Erwin Wilson]] on a proposed $5 billion budget reduction for the Air Force. General Vandenberg maintained that the cut backed by Wilson would reduce U.S. military aviation to a &quot;one-shot Air Force&quot;, inferior to that of the Soviet Union. He said it was another instance of &quot;start-stop&quot; planning of a kind that had impeded Air Force development in previous years. The cut in appropriations went into effect in July 1953, immediately after his retirement from the Air Force.

==Post-military life==
A scratch golfer, General Vandenberg spent every free moment on the golf courses, but he was also a lover of movies, Westerns, and scotch. Unfortunately, his last months in uniform were painful, unhealthy ones. General Vandenberg retired from active duty as a result of major illness on June 30, 1953, and died nine months later at the [[Walter Reed Army Medical Center]] from [[prostate cancer]] at the age of 55. His remains are buried in Section 30 of the [[Arlington National Cemetery]].

His wife, Gladys Rose Vandenberg, started the concept of the [[Arlington Ladies]] while he was Air Force Chief of Staff. The program provides that a military lady of the appropriate service represents the service chief at all military funerals at Arlington Cemetery.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSNBC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=O'Neill|first=Helen|title=Special lady for each Arlington soldier-Volunteers honor troops and make sure none is buried alone|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/37416579/ns/us_news-life/|publisher=[[MSNBC]].com|accessdate=30 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was buried alongside her husband in Arlington National Cemetery upon her death on January 9, 1978. They are survived by their children, Gloria Miller, and retired Major General [[Hoyt S. Vandenberg, Jr.]], USAF.

On October 4, 1958, the missile and aerospace base at Camp Cooke in [[Lompoc]], California, was renamed [[Vandenberg Air Force Base]]. In July 1963, the instrument ship [[USS General Harry Taylor (AP-145)|USAF ''General Hoyt S. Vandenberg'' (T-AGM-10)]] was renamed at [[Cape Canaveral]], Florida, for duty on the Eastern Space and Missile Range in the Atlantic.  One of the two cadets' dormitories at the [[United States Air Force Academy]], Vandenburg Hall, is also named in his honor. In addition, a popular enlisted &quot;hangout&quot; for technical school Airmen at [[Keesler AFB]], Mississippi, is named in his honor.  The Vandenberg Esplanade, located along the Merrimack River in Lowell, Massachusetts and part of the Lowell Heritage State Park, is named in his honor.

==Decorations==
General Vandenberg was awarded the Distinguished Service Medal with one oak leaf cluster, the [[Silver Star]], the [[Legion of Merit]], the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]], the [[Air Medal]] with four oak leaf clusters, the [[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]], the [[World War II Victory Medal]], the [[American Campaign Medal]], the [[American Defense Service Medal]], and the [[European-African-Middle East Campaign Medal]].

His foreign decorations include the Mexican Military Order of Merit; Netherlands [[Order of Orange Nassau]] (Grand Officer with Swords); Brazilian Cruzeiro do Sul (Grand Officer), and Medal of War; Luxembourg [[Order of Adolphe of Nassau]] (Grand Cross), and Croix de Guerre; [[Order of Leopold (Belgium)]] (Grand Officer with Palms); and French [[Croix de Guerre]] with Palms; British [[Order of the Bath]] (Knight Commanders Cross); Polish [[Order of Polonia Restituta]] (Commander's Cross with Star); Portuguese [[Order of Aviz]], Gra Cruiz; Egyptian [[Order of the Nile]], Grand Cordon; Chinese [[Order of Pao Ting]] (Tripod with Grand Cordon); Chilean Medallia Militar de Primerera Clase; Argentine General Staff Emblem and the Grand Cross of the [[Military Order of Italy]].

The Manuscript Collection of Hoyt S. Vandenberg at the Library of Congress as of November 2005 is [[Classified information]].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Biography|United States Air Force}}
{{commons}}
*[http://www.af.mil/information/heritage/person.asp?dec=&amp;pid=123006497 Public domain biography provided by the United States Air Force]
*{{cite book| chapterurl = http://www.history.army.mil/books/Last_Salute/Ch10.htm| title = The Last Salute: Civil and Military Funeral, 1921-1969| chapter = CHAPTER X, Former Air Force Chief of Staff General Hoyt S. Vandenberg, Special Military Funeral, 2–5 April 1954| first1 = B.C.| last1 = Mossman| first2 = M.W.| last2 = Stark| url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/Last_Salute/index.htm| publisher = [[United States Army Center of Military History]]| id = CMH Pub 90-1| year = 1991| origyear = 1971}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-gov}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Director of Central Intelligence]] |before=Rear Admiral [[Sidney Souers]] |after=Rear Admiral [[Roscoe H. Hillenkoetter]] |years=June 10, 1946 - May 1, 1947}}
{{S-mil}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force]] |before=General [[Carl Spaatz]] |after=General [[Nathan Farragut Twining]] |years=1948&amp;ndash;1953}}
{{S-end}}

{{DCIA}}
{{CSUSAF}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Vandenberg, Hoyt
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = 
| DATE OF BIRTH     = January 24, 1899
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, Wisconsin]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = April 2, 1954
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Walter Reed Medical Center]], Washington D.C.
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Vandenberg, Hoyt}}
[[Category:United States Air Force generals]]
[[Category:Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:Chiefs of Staff of the United States Air Force]]
[[Category:Directors of the Central Intelligence Agency]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Star]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Medal]]
[[Category:Légion d'honneur recipients]]
[[Category:Grand Officers of the Order of Leopold (Belgium)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (France)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (Luxembourg)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Medal of Military Merit (Mexico)]]
[[Category:Grand Officers of the Order of Orange-Nassau]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Sun (Brazil)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Medal of War (Brazil)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Adolphe of Nassau]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (Belgium)]]
[[Category:Honorary Knights Commander of the Order of the Bath]]
[[Category:Commanders with Star of the Order of Polonia Restituta]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Aviz]]
[[Category:Grand Cordons of the Order of the Nile]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Sacred Tripod]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Medal (Chile)]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Military Order of Savoy]]
[[Category:Deaths from prostate cancer]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:People from Milwaukee, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:People from Lowell, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:American people of Dutch descent]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:1899 births]]
[[Category:1954 deaths]]
[[Category:United States Army Command and General Staff College alumni]]
[[Category:Air Corps Tactical School alumni]]

[[de:Hoyt S. Vandenberg]]
[[fr:Hoyt S. Vandenberg]]
[[nl:Hoyt Vandenberg]]
[[ja:ホイト・ヴァンデンバーグ]]
[[pl:Hoyt Vandenberg]]
[[ru:Ванденберг, Хойт Сенфорд]]
[[sl:Hoyt Sanford Vandenberg]]
[[fi:Hoyt Vandenberg]]
[[sv:Hoyt Vandenberg]]
[[uk:Ванденберг Хойт Сенфорд]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
