<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5204825" ns="0" title="Elizabeth Cosson"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military person
|name         = Elizabeth Cosson
|birth_date         = {{birth year and age|1958}}
|birth_place =
|death_place =
|image=
|caption      =
|nickname     = Liz
|allegiance   = {{flagicon|Australia}} [[Australia]]
|serviceyears = 1979 -
|rank         = [[Major General (Australia)|Major General]]
|branch       = [[Australian Army]]
|commands     = National Operations
|unit         =
|battles      = [[East Timor]]
|awards       = [[Member of the Order of Australia]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Conspicuous Service Cross (Australia)|Conspicuous Service Cross]]
|laterwork=
}}
[[Major General (Australia)|Major General]] '''Elizabeth Cosson''' [[Order of Australia|AM]], [[Conspicuous Service Cross (Australia)|CSC]]  (born 1958) is Australia's most senior female army officer, and the first woman to reach the rank of Major General in the [[Australian Army]]. In December 2010, she took the position of General Manager of the Executive Division of the Department of Veterans Affairs.&lt;ref name=DVA/&gt;

==ADF Service==
Elizabeth (Liz) Cosson joined the Australian Army in 1979 as an [[officer cadet]] and was commissioned in the [[Royal Australian Army Ordnance Corps]].  During the early part of her career she held a number of appointments as a supply and administrative officer.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;&gt;[http://www.defence.gov.au/media/download/2006/Apr/20060427/Bio%20-%20Brigadier%20Cosson%202006.doc Brigadier Elizabeth Cosson, CSC], Biography, 27 April 2006. Media Release on Australian Department of Defence website.&lt;br /&gt;[http://www.defence.gov.au/leaders/other/elizabethCosson/index.htm Major General Elizabeth Cosson, CSC]{{Dead link|date=April 2011}}, Biography, Defence Leaders, Media Release on Australian Department of Defence website. Both accessed 28 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991 she was appointed to a position at the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] Logistics Command where she was responsible for the [[logistics]] support to army aviation aircraft. For her work in improving the availability of the [[UH-60 Black Hawk]] helicopter fleet and supporting the fleet deployment to [[Cambodia]], she received a commendation from the Air Officer Commanding Logistics.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;

In 1995 Cosson served in a number of appointments within Land Command, including a regimental appointment with the 11th Brigade and a logistics staff officer appointment at Headquarters Land Command.  During this appointment her responsibilities included logistics planning in support of the 1999 operations in [[International Force for East Timor|East Timor]]. In November 1999 she deployed as the Chief of Staff of the Peace Monitoring Group, [[History of Bougainville|Bougainville]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;

She was awarded the  [[Conspicuous Service Cross (Australia)|Conspicuous Service Cross]] in the 2001 [[Australia Day]] Honours List &quot;for outstanding achievement as the Chief of Staff, Peace Monitoring Group, Bougainville, and in logistic planning and management of the Combat Force as the Staff Officer Grade One Logistics, Land Headquarters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=914415&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true Conspicuous Service Cross], Australian honours site.&lt;/ref&gt;

On her return from Bougainville she served with Defence Corporate Services before being seconded to the Joint Standing Committee for Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade in the [[Australian House of Representatives|House of Representatives]]. In 2002, Cosson commenced a three year appointment in strategic logistics planning and was responsible for logistics policy and for developing concepts to improve logistics information systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;

In December 2005 she became the first woman to be promoted to the rank of [[Brigadier]] in the Australian Army.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

She served in the Corporate Services and Infrastructure Group of the Defence Department as the Director General Regions and Bases.&lt;ref&gt;Brendan Nicholson and Misha Schubert [http://www.theage.com.au/news/national/handpicked-officer-devastated-by-bungle/2006/05/18/1147545456346.html ''Hand-picked officer devastated by bungle''], ''[[The Age]]'', 19 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In this position she was responsible for the management of integrated service delivery to Defence bases across Australia.

In March 2007 she assumed the role of Head Defence Support Operations in an acting capacity. In November 2007, the role was confirmed and she became the first woman to be promoted to the rank of major general in the Australian Army. She is the second female to be promoted to [[two-star rank]] in the [[Australian Defence Force]], the first being [[Air Vice Marshal]] [[Julie Hammer]], who retired in 2005. Cosson, as head of National Operations within the Defence Support Group, became responsible for the management of 80 ADF bases and garrisons across the country.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Dodd, [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22744588-31477,00.html ''First female two-star general named''], ''[[The Australian]]'', 12 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, although about 13% of the ADF were women, there were only four at the one-star level: Commodore Robyn Walker, Commodore Vicki McConachie, Brigadier [[Lyn McDade]] and Air Commodore [[Margaret Staib]].&lt;ref&gt;David McLennan, ''Historic Promotion Despite Kovco Bungle'', ''[[The Canberra Times]]'', 12 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Cosson was appointed a [[Member of the Order of Australia]] in the 2011 [[Australia Day]] Honours List as a result of her &quot;exceptional service&quot; in the positions of Director General Regions and Bases, and as Head Defence Support Operations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gg.gov.au/res/file/2011/honours/ad11/Media%20Notes%20AM(Mil)%20(final).pdf 2011 Australia Day Honours List - Member (AM) in the Military Division of the Order of Australia]&lt;/ref&gt;  In December 2010 it was announced that she had been appointed General Manager of the Executive Division of the Department of Veterans Affairs.&lt;ref name=DVA&gt;[http://www.dva.gov.au/aboutDVA/publications/corporate/vetaffairs/2010/Documents/Vol26No4_2.pdf New General Manager - Executive Division], ''Vetaffairs'', Vol 26, No.4, December 2010, pg.2, Department of Veterans Affairs. Accessed 7 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kovco affair===
Cosson was appointed in April 2006 to investigate the circumstances surrounding the repatriation of the body of [[Jacob Kovco]]. On 15 May 2006, following a meeting with the Victorian Coroner, she left a [[CD ROM]] containing a draft copy of her confidential report in a public computer in the [[Qantas Club]] lounge of [[Melbourne Airport]].&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Walters, [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,20867,19185266-31477,00.html ''Bungle brigadier taking it very hard''], ''[[The Australian]]'', 19 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Parts of the report were subsequently broadcast by [[Derryn Hinch]].&lt;ref&gt;Rachel Carbonell, [http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/content/2006/s1641193.htm ''Defence admits losing report''], ''[[Lateline]]'', 17 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; This incident was the subject of a Defence Department inquiry.&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Walters, [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,20867,19185268-31477,00.html ''Nelson sets limits for Kovco team''], ''[[The Australian]]'', 19 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

== Education ==
Major General Cosson is a graduate of the [[Army Command and Staff College]] at [[Fort Queenscliff]] (1994) and the [[Centre for Defence and Strategic Studies]] (2005). She holds a Graduate Diploma in Management Studies, a Bachelor of Social Sciences and a Master of Arts in Strategic Studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt;

==Personal life==
She is married to Brigadier James Baker,&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot; /&gt; who is also currently serving in the Australian Army.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defence.gov.au/opEx/global/opastute/bios/baker.htm  Brigadier James Baker]{{Dead link|date=April 2011}}, Biography on Department of Defence website.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* Photographs of the [http://www.defence.gov.au/media/download/2007/Nov/20071112a/index.htm Promotion ceremony for Major General Liz Cosson], 12 November 2007. Includes [http://www.defence.gov.au/media/download/2007/Nov/20071112a/20071112adf9901_014_lo.jpg this photo] with then [[Chief of Army]] Lt Gen [[Peter Leahy]], and her husband, then Colonel James Baker.
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Cosson, Elizabeth
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1958
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Cosson, Elizabeth}}
[[Category:1958 births]]
[[Category:Australian generals]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Members of the Order of Australia]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Conspicuous Service Cross (Australia)]]
[[Category:Women in 21st-century warfare]]
[[Category:Women in the Australian military]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
