<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5206799" ns="0" title="List of rapid application development tools"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">
==Cross-platform RAD tools==
* [[Accelerator (Software)|Accelerator Development Solutions]] provides end-to-end RAD generation and other productivity frameworks for C#  and for cross platform support C. 
* [[Smartface|Smartface Platform]]: A cross platform tool for Windows used to create mobile applications for J2ME, Symbian S60, BlackBerry and Android, using [[Drag and drop|drag-and-drop]] tools and action editing.
* [[Code::Blocks]] is a cross-platform C/C++ RAD IDE using wxWidgets; the latest developmental builds have a built-in form designer wxSmith, so it's similar to Embarcadero C++ Builder and Microsoft Visual C++/MFC now.
* [[HyperNext]] is a freeware cross-platform software development system for Mac OS X &amp; Mac OS 9, and Microsoft Windows XP &amp; Vista. It has many similarities with [[HyperCard]] and can compile to both stand alone applications and stacks for the cross-platform HyperNext Player.
* [[Ebase Xi]] is a commercial [[rapid application development]] [[computing platform | platform]]  that combines [[web browser]]-based [[user interface]] development, [[business process management]] and [[data integration]] into a single-technology [[Integrated development environment|IDE]].
* [[IBM Rational Business Developer Extension]] is a cross-platform, Rapid Application Development IDE for creating enterprise and web applications and services for Windows, Linux, Unix (Solaris, HPUX, AIX), System z and System i
* [[IBM Rational Application Developer]] is a cross-platform, Rapid Application Development IDE for creating enterprise and web applications and services for Windows, Linux and Unix (Solaris, HPUX, AIX)
* [[LANSA (development environment)|LANSA]] is a development environment for generating applications on multiple platforms. One of the main features of LANSA is its high level programming language, called RDML (Rapid Development and Maintenance Language). It is classified as a 4GL (4th generation language). LANSA-developed applications run on many systems including MS Windows, IBM i and Linux. 
* [[Lazarus (software)|Lazarus]] is a cross-platform IDE similar to Embarcadero Delphi.
* [[m-Power]] is a Software Development tool which automates application development and rapidly creates enterprise-class Web applications over any database or platform.
* [[MyEclipse]] is a Rapid Application Development environment, focusing on enterprise Java and Web application development. The specialty MyEclipse &quot;Blue Edition&quot; is most similar to [[IBM Rational Application Developer]].
* [[NetBeans]] is a cross-platform, RAD IDE for creating visual desktop, mobile, web, and SOA applications for Linux, Windows and Mac OS X. The IDE officially supports Java, PHP, JavaScript and C/C++ programming languages.
* [[Omnis Studio]] is a cross-platform, Rapid Application Development tool or IDE for creating enterprise and web applications for Windows, Linux, Solaris, and Mac OS X.
* [[OpenROAD]]  is a cross-platform IDE for Linux/Unix, Windows with embedded SQL support
* [[Panther (development tool)|Panther]] (and its [[open source]] version [[POSSL]]) is a cross-platform ([[Microsoft windows|Windows]], [[Unix]], [[Linux]]; [[Text user interface|TUI]], [[GUI]], [[World Wide Web|Web]]), cross-database RAD toolset for development of [[client–server]] and [[n-tier|''n''-tier]] database-oriented applications.
* [[Real Studio]] is a cross-platform IDE for creating desktop applications for Windows, Linux and Mac OS X. The language is similar to both VB and Java. It compiles to machine code, uses native controls and produces native executables.
* [[RadRails]] is a cross-platform IDE for creating Ruby on Rails web applications.
* [[Servoy]] Servoy is a cross-platform application development and deployment environment. Servoy consists of a GUI designer, is event-driven and runs scripts through JavaScript. Servoy allows applications to be deployed to both a native Smart client / Rich client and to a pure HTML Web client from the same codebase and user interface
* [[Squeak]] is an open-source, cross-platform Smalltalk system which can be used to develop applications for desktop, mobile, server-based, and web platforms. Squeak supports Windows, Linux, Mac OS X, Mac OS Classic, many flavors of Unix, and a handful of other operating systems. Squeak is the home of the Seaside RAD web app framework and multiple GUI toolkits, some of which allow the building of GUIs by drag and drop.
* [[Visual FoxPro]] With its local cursor engine, tight coupling between language and data, and various features, Visual FoxPro 9.0 can be used for building database solutions of all sizes. Its data-centric, object-oriented language offers developers a set of tools for building database applications for the desktop, client–server environments, or the Web. Developers will have tools to manage data, from organizing tables of information, running queries, and creating an integrated relational database management system (DBMS) to programming a fully developed data management application for end users. &lt;small&gt;Note: Manufacturer announced in 2007 that there would be no future releases of this product.&lt;/small&gt;
* [[VisualWorks]] is a cross-platform Smalltalk RAD for creating desktop, mobile, enterprise, and web-based applications for Windows, Linux, Mac OS X, Mac OS Classic, and a number of Unix systems. The system supports popular protocols and frameworks like ODBC, Seaside, and GemStone/S. Commercial and free non-commercial versions available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Baum|first=David|title=Client/server delivers revolution for resellers|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fzoEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA65&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=H3nETreDH4bc0QGovMnhDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwAjhu#v=onepage&amp;q=visualworks&amp;f=false|accessdate=17 November 2011|newspaper=[[InfoWorld]]|date=18 September 1995|page=65}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Web Dynpro]] is SAP's RAD to create web applications connected to function modules in mySAP ERP.
* [[WideStudio]] is an open source integrated development environment for desktop applications purely made in Japan.
* [[XVT]] is a cross-platform, Rapid Application Development IDE for creating enterprise and desktop applications in C/C++ on Windows, Linux, Unix (Solaris, HPUX, AIX), and Mac
* [[XPower++]] is a cross-platform IDE for Windows, Linux, Mac OSX, and Mobile operating systems.
* [[CA Technologies|CA]] Plex, a software development tool that combines the techniques of model-based development, patterns and code generation to accelerate the delivery and maintenance of multi-platform, distributed business applications
* Jdeveloper - Oracle Java Develpment IDE.
* [[XDEV]] is a cross-platform, Java RAD IDE for creating visual desktop and web applications for Linux, Windows and Mac OS X.
* [[Philasmicos Entwickler Studio]] is a cross-platform C/C++ RAD IDE for wxWidgets.

==Cloud Based RAD tools==
*[[Coghead]] (is out of business as of 2009)
*[[Wavemaker]] is an open-source, visual, drag and drop development studio that runs in a browser and generates standard Java applications for deployment.
*[[Zoho Office Suite]]

== Desktop Rapid Application Development Tools ==
* [[Accelerator (Software)|Accelerator for .NET]] provides end-to-end RAD generation and other productivity frameworks for .NET, including support for [[MVVM]], [[Windows Communication Foundation|WCF]], and [[Windows_Workflow_Foundation|WF]]. 
* [[Qt (framework)|Qt]] is a cross-platform application and UI framework. It includes a cross-platform class library, integrated development tools and a cross-platform IDE. Using Qt, you can write web-enabled applications once and deploy them across many desktop and embedded operating systems without rewriting the source code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Linux Rapid Application Development|year=2000|publisher=[[IDG]]|isbn=0764547402, 9780764547409|pages=616|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MMqAPgAACAAJ&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tGvETr_MKOTm0QGdkeGSDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwADgK|author=Cameron Hughes|coauthors=Tracey Hughes|accessdate=17 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[C++Builder]] 
* [[Clarion (programming language)|Clarion]] is a data-centric Advanced Rapid Application Development (ARAD) tool featuring roundtrip code generation that preserves all of your own hand-written code while allowing you to re-generate your application as often as needed. It provides reusable metadata to quickly create &quot;corporate quality&quot; applications to manage business data
* [[Code::Blocks]]
* [[CodeGear Delphi|Delphi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Beginning Programming for Dummies&quot; /&gt; 
* [[Dolphin Smalltalk]] is a Smalltalk development environment for Windows with advance RAD features. Proprietary, with a free Community Edition.
* [[Delphi for PHP]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Beginning Programming for Dummies&quot; /&gt; 
* [[Ebase Xi]] is a commercial [[rapid application development]] [[computing platform | platform]]  that combines [[web browser]]-based [[user interface]] development, [[business process management]] and [[data integration]] into a single-technology [[Integrated development environment|IDE]].
* [[Gambas]] Basic, Open source, Linux
* [[Gupta Technologies|Gupta]] Team Developer / SQLWindows
* [[Habanero.NET|Habanero]]
* Microsoft [[Visual Basic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McMahon|first=David|title=Rapid application development with Visual Basic 6|year=2000|publisher=[[McGraw-Hill]]|isbn=0071354220, 9780071354226|pages=424|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OSxqQgAACAAJ&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development+with+Visual+Basic+6&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0GrETtfLHOrx0gGmoIDcDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwAA}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Lazarus (software)|Lazarus]] Pascal, Open Source, Multi-platform
* [[Runtime Revolution|LiveCode]]
* [[Panther (development tool)|Panther]]
* [[PowerBASIC|PowerBASIC Forms (PBForms)]]
* [[Real Studio]] from [[REAL Software]] is a cross-platform, drag and drop development tool that compiles to machine code, uses native controls and produces native executables for Mac OS X, Windows, Linux and the web.
* [[Softwell Maker]] is a desktop IDE with a cross-platform deployment component allowing publish application into almost any Java enable system.
* [[wxDev-C++]]
* Microsoft [[Visual Foxpro]]
* [[WinDev]]
* [[XVT]]
* [[GNAVI]]

== Database Rapid Application Development Tools ==
*[[AppFlower]] [[open source]] application builder using [[Propel (PHP)|Propel]] with a visual designer for Model Add/Edit/View.
* [[Base One Foundation Component Library|Base One Foundation Component Library (BFC)]] is a RAD framework for building [[.NET Framework|.NET]] applications using [[Microsoft SQL Server|SQL Server]], [[Oracle Database|Oracle]], [[IBM DB2|DB2]], [[Adaptive Server Enterprise|Sybase]], and [[MySQL]] databases.
* [[Clarion (programming language)|Clarion]] is a data-centric Advanced Rapid Application Development (ARAD) tool featuring roundtrip code generation that preserves all of your own hand-written code while allowing you to re-generate your application as often as needed. It provides reusable metadata to quickly create &quot;corporate quality&quot; applications to manage business data
* [[CodeCharge Studio]] is a visual rapid application development environment for web-based database driven application development. CodeCharge Studio places emphasis on code generation technology to provide [[ASP.NET]], [[PHP]], [[JavaServer Pages|JSP]], Servlets, [[ColdFusion]] and [[Perl]] language support.
* [[Ebase Xi]] is a commercial [[rapid application development]] [[computing platform | platform]]  that combines [[web browser]]-based [[user interface]] development, [[business process management]] and [[data integration]] into a single-technology [[Integrated development environment|IDE]].
* [[IBM Rational Business Developer Extension]] supports database application development for [[IBM DB2]], [[IBM Informix]], [[Oracle database]], [[Microsoft SQL Server]] and other JDBC compliant relational databases
* [[IBM Rational Application Developer]] supports database application development for [[IBM DB2]], [[IBM Informix]], [[Oracle database]], [[Microsoft SQL Server]] and other JDBC compliant relational databases
* [[IBM Lotus Notes]] is a RAD environment for collaboration and document management tasks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoskins|first=Jim|title=Gaining a Competitive Advantage with IBM Lotus Collaboration Software|year=2010|publisher=[[Maximum Press]]|isbn=http://books.google.com/books?id=1I4c8gAyOgcC&amp;pg=PA109&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tGvETr_MKOTm0QGdkeGSDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CHEQ6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Rapid%20Application%20Development&amp;f=false|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1I4c8gAyOgcC&amp;pg=PA109&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tGvETr_MKOTm0QGdkeGSDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CHEQ6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Rapid%20Application%20Development&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Iron Speed Designer]] is an application generator that builds database-driven web [[Web 2.0]] applications for .NET.  It creates application Web pages [[ASPX]], user interface code and data access logic (C#, [[Visual Basic .NET]]; and [[SQL]] queries) without programming.
* [[FileMaker]]  is a cross-platform database application from FileMaker Inc. (a subsidiary of Apple Inc.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Feiler|first=Jesse|title=FileMaker Pro 10 In Depth|year=2009|publisher=[[Que Publishing]]|isbn=0768688132, 9780768688139|pages=696|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2pXkCFbL4TsC&amp;pg=PT48&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tGvETr_MKOTm0QGdkeGSDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CE8Q6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Rapid%20Application%20Development&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[OpenOffice.org Base]] is an [[open source]] database-driven RAD development environment for building client (desktop) based applications. 
* [[Kexi]] is an [[open source]] database-driven RAD development environment for building desktop applications. It is considered an alternative to Open Office Base in the Open Source environment and provides similar features to commercially available RAD development environments such as [[FileMaker]], [[Alpha Five]] and [[Microsoft Access]].
* [[m-Power]] is a Software Development tool which automates application development and rapidly creates enterprise-class Web applications over any database or platform.
* [[Oracle Forms]]
* [[Oracle Application Express]] (Oracle APEX) is software development environment based on the Oracle database. It allows a very fast development cycle to be achieved to create web based applications.
* [[Outsystems|Outsystems Platform]]
* [[Panther (development tool)|Panther]] (and its [[open source]] version [[POSSL]]) is a cross-platform ([[Microsoft windows|Windows]], [[Unix]], [[Linux]]; [[Text user interface|TUI]], [[GUI]], [[World Wide Web|Web]]), cross-database RAD toolset for development of C/S and [[n-tier]] database oriented applications.
* [[Real Studio]] from [[REAL Software]] is a cross-platform, visual, drag and drop development tool with an object-oriented language that has a report editor and supports database connectivity to SQLite, Oracle, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server (Windows only), Postgres and ODBC.
* [[Sybase]] [[PowerBuilder]] is data-driven development tool for creating client/server, distributed, Web and Smart Clients applications for JEE, Win32, and .NET platforms.
* [[Softwell Maker]] is a ultra RAP data-centric IDE with a cross-platform deployment component allowing publish application into almost any Java enable system.
* [[Visual DataFlex]] is a Windows based development environment for creating Windows and web-based database applications. Object oriented, database neutral, 3-tier model (database - business rules - user interface).
*[[Wavemaker]] is an open-source, visual, drag and drop development studio that runs in a browser and generates standard Java applications for deployment. Runs on Windows/Linux/MacOS.
* [[WinDev]]

== Embedded Control Rapid Application Development Tools ==
* [[VisSim]] is a block diagram language for model based embedded system development
* [[LabVIEW]] is a graphical programming language that allows you to program embedded off-the-shelf systems, FPGAs, custom designs
* [[EICASLAB]] is a [[Visual programming language]] that allows you to design embedded control architectures, providing assistance in modelling, simulation, rapid control prototyping and automatic code generation for the final target.

== Notification/Communication Rapid Application Development Tools ==
* [[Boomerang Software Framework]] – Boomerang is a notification/communication framework for professional developers that provides a service oriented infrastructure and a rapid development interface. The infrastructure supports e-mail out, printers, fax servers, file/ftp servers and incoming e-mail (e-mail to database). 

==Web Based Rapid Application Development Tools==
* [[AppFlower]] is a very rapid application development framework for creating enterprise application without the need of coding. Advanced users can extend AppFlower applications using [[PHP]], the [[Symfony]] framework and [[ExtJS]].
* [[Active Agenda]]'s code generator is a RAD development framework using [[XML]] specification files and the [[PHP]] development language. 
* [[Alpha Five]] is a commercial RAD development environment for both client and web-server based database driven applications. This tool is typically classified with commercial packages such as [[Microsoft Access]] and [[FileMaker]]. 
* [[Base One Foundation Component Library|BFC]] is a RAD framework for both client and server-side development in the .NET environment.
* [[CakePHP]] is a RAD development framework using the [[PHP]] development language. 
* [[CakeApp]] is a RAD online service to build applications based on an online editable DB schema.
* [[Caspio]] is a platform-as-a-service framework that uses wizards instead of coding for RAD.
* [[CodeCharge Studio]] is a visual RAD development environment for web-based database driven application development. CodeCharge Studio places emphasis on code generation technology to provide [[ASP.NET]], [[PHP]], [[JavaServer Pages|JSP]], Servlets, [[ColdFusion]] and [[Perl]] language support.
* [[Zend Framework]] is an open source, object-oriented web application framework licensed under the New BSD License.
* [[Django (web framework)|Django]] is an open source web application framework, written in Python, which loosely follows the model-view-controller design pattern.&lt;ref name='ReadWriteWeb &quot;Alphabet Soup&quot;'&gt;{{cite web|last=Joe|first=Brockmeier|title=Alphabet Soup in the Cloud: Understanding 'aaS'|url=http://www.readwriteweb.com/cloud/2011/10/alphabet-soup-in-the-cloud-und.php|work=[[ReadWriteWeb]]|quote=Ruby on Rails and Django are enormously popular rapid application development frameworks.|accessdate=16 November 2011|date=31 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ebase Xi]] is a commercial [[rapid application development]] [[computing platform | platform]]  that combines [[web browser]]-based [[user interface]] development, [[business process management]] and [[data integration]] into a single-technology [[Integrated development environment|IDE]].
* [[IBM Rational Business Developer Extension]] is a cross-platform, Rapid Application Development IDE for creating enterprise and web applications and services for Windows, Linux, Unix (Solaris, HPUX, AIX), System z and System i
* [[Grails (framework)|Grails]] is an open-source [[Groovy (programming language)|Groovy]]-based high-productivity framework inspired by [[Ruby on Rails]] and following the [[Convention over configuration|&quot;coding by convention&quot;]] paradigm.  Grails applications can run in standard Java servlet containers.
* [[Iron Speed Designer]] is an application generator that builds database-driven web [[Web 2.0]] applications for .NET.  It creates application Web pages [[ASPX]], user interface code and data access logic (C#, [[Visual Basic .NET]]; and [[SQL]] queries) without programming.
* [[LibreSource]]
* [[Morfik]] is a Windows web RAD tool with cross platform deployment.
* [[m-Power]] is a Software Development tool which automates application development and rapidly creates enterprise-class Web applications over any database or platform.
* [[Pario]] is a web-based rapid application development environment for creating, deploying, and maintaining online database applications.
* [[nuBuilder]] is an open source browser based database development tool which stores all forms, reports, data and any custom code in MySQL and displays the content dynamically.
* [[OpenXava]] is a [[Domain-driven design|domain-driven]] Java framework for rapid development of [[AJAX]] applications. It's [[open source]].
* [[Oracle ADF|Oracle Application Development Framework]] uses Oracle's [[JDeveloper]] a FREE IDE that supports ADF's J2EE based framework.
* [[Panther (development tool)|Panther]] (and its [[open source]] version [[POSSL]]) is a cross-platform ([[Microsoft windows|Windows]], [[Unix]], [[Linux]]; [[Text user interface|TUI]], [[GUI]], [[World Wide Web|Web]]), cross-database RAD toolset for development of [[client–server]] and [[n-tier|''n''-tier]] database oriented applications.
* [[Pylons (web framework)|Pylons]] is an open source web application framework, written in Python, which makes extensive use of the [[Web Server Gateway Interface|Web Server Gateway Interface (WSGI)]] standard to promote re-usability and to separate functionality into distinct modules.
* [[radPHP]] commercial, visual, rapid application development IDE for PHP by Embarcadero (formerly Delphi or PHP)&lt;ref name=&quot;Beginning Programming for Dummies&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Wang|first=Wallace|title=Beginning Programming for Dummies|year=2007|publisher=[[John Wiley &amp; Sons]]|isbn=0470099682, 9780470099681|pages=432|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8wUjousS2EwC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=Rapid+Application+Development&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tGvETr_MKOTm0QGdkeGSDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CFkQ6AEwBDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Rapid%20Application%20Development&amp;f=false|edition=4|accessdate=17 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Real Studio]] Web Edition is a rapid application development environment for the web. The language is object oriented and is similar to both VB and Java. Applications are uniquely compiled to binary code.
* [[Ruby on Rails]] sponsored by [[37signals]]&lt;ref name='ReadWriteWeb &quot;Alphabet Soup&quot;' /&gt; 
* [[Scriptcase]] is a powerful tool to increase web development productivity. It supports most databases available generating highly customizable PHP code, AJAX and JQUERY.
* [[Spring Roo]] is an [[open source]] rapid application development tool that produces [[Java (programming language)|Java]]-based [[Spring Framework|Spring]] applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Spring Persistence with Hibernate|year=2010|publisher=[[Apress]]|isbn=1430226323, 9781430226321|pages=246|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OkKJ2JGMcCAC&amp;pg=PA215&amp;lpg=PA215&amp;dq=SpringSource+roo+rad&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=L-mTp371s6&amp;sig=ij6Scj_WVVN1NqC3NwAC269G33M&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Qa7DTtOrGOTt0gGD_pXfDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwBDgU#v=onepage&amp;q=SpringSource%20roo%20rad&amp;f=false|author=Paul Tepper Fisher|coauthors=Brian D. Murphy|accessdate=16 November 2011|page=215}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Symfony]]
* Thoroughbred T-WEB is a Web RAD tool
* [[Visual DataFlex]] is a Windows based development environment for creating advanced web-based database applications using AJAX. Object oriented, database neutral, 3-tier model (database - business rules - user interface).
* [[Web2py]] is a RAD framework for web-based database driven applications with key features including in-browser coding support, admin/design interface, DAL ([[database abstraction layer]]), and translation support.
* [[WebDev]]
* [[Wavemaker]] visual, drag and drop development, standard Java deployment, open source (Windows/Linux/MacOS)
* [[Wolf Frameworks]] is a 100% AJAX, XML &amp; .NET based Platform for designing and delivering cross platform web applications using a browser.
* [http://sculpture.codeplex.com/ Sculpture] is a 100% free .NET based Platform for designing and delivering cross platform web applications.
* [[Yii Framework]] Yii is a high-performance PHP framework best for developing Web 2.0 applications.

== Components based on Rapid Application Development paradigm ==
* [[Add-in Express]] – Visual RAD tool for developing COM add-ins, smart tags, RTD servers and Excel user defined functions in Visual Studio .NET and Delphi.
* [[Panther (development tool)|Panther]] is a cross-platform ([[Microsoft windows|Windows]], [[Unix]], [[Linux]]; [[Text user interface|TUI]], [[GUI]], [[World Wide Web|Web]]), cross-database RAD toolset for development of [[n-tier]] component based database oriented applications. It builds native components employing the same visual paradigm used for client screens. Editions for [[middleware]] from [[IBM WebSphere|IBM]], [[Tuxedo (software)|BEA]] and [[Component Object Model|Microsoft]] exist (and can be combined).

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rapid Application Development Tools}}
[[Category:Computer programming tools]]
[[Category:Lists of software]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
