<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5235776" ns="0" title="Pink Taco"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:PinkTaco.png|230px|right|alt=the words &quot;pink taco&quot; in pink, Gothic font]]
'''Pink Taco''' is a restaurant in [[Los Angeles, California]]. It calls itself a chain, but currently only has one location open after previously having had several locations. It serves [[Mexican cuisine|Mexican food]]. The chain has earned notoriety due to its name, which is a [[slang]] term for the human [[vulva]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Pink Taco Restaurant Name Causes Stir | date=May 16, 2006 | publisher=CBS | url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/05/16/ap/strange/mainD8HKJQH81.shtml }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the restaurant, the name comes from a dish it serves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Lesley | last=Wright | title=Council gives OK for eatery liquor license | date=May 16, 2006| publisher=The Arizona Republic | url=http://www.azcentral.com/arizonarepublic/local/articles/0516netaco0516.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Locations ==
The first Pink Taco restaurant was opened in 1999 at the [[Hard Rock Hotel and Casino (Las Vegas)|Hard Rock Hotel and Casino]] in [[Las Vegas metropolitan area|Las Vegas]], Nevada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = John | last = Katsilometes |title = Columnist John Katsilometes: Eateries need the right name | date = May 30, 1999 | publisher = Las Vegas Sun | url=http://www.lasvegassun.com/sunbin/stories/sun/1999/may/30/508860108.html?%5C%22pink%20taco&amp;quot }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Megan | last = Finnerty |title = Suggestive name puts eatery, city at odds | date = April 22, 2006 | publisher = The Arizona Republic | url=http://www.azcentral.com/ent/dining/articles/0422pinktaco.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; A second location in [[Scottsdale, Arizona]] met with [[Pink_Taco#Name_controversy|controversy]] and remained open for less than three years, between 2006 and 2009. A third location opened on June 28, 2007 in [[Century City, Los Angeles, California]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OfficialWebsite&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Pink Taco | url=http://www.pinktaco.com/ | accessdate=2007-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the restaurant's website, planned future locations include [[Hollywood, California]], [[San Diego, California]], and [[Miami, Florida]]. As of September 2010, only a single [[Los Angeles]], location, at [[Westfield Century City]] mall, was listed on that website.

== Name controversy ==
The name has caused controversy in [[Scottsdale, Arizona]], where the restaurant attempted to open a second location. In response, the city government received four [[emails]] complaining about the name. This generated a complaint from Mayor [[Mary Manross]] who said she was offended, although she did not see the name in a sexual way until the complaints were raised. She asked the owner to change the name, but he refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS&quot; /&gt;

On May 15, 2006, the Scottsdale [[City Council]], by a unanimous vote, recommended the restaurant for a [[liquor]] [[license]] from the Arizona Department of Liquor Licenses and Control. One resident raised an objection at the meeting, saying the name &quot;demeans and degrades women.&quot; The state agency said it had not received any complaints.&lt;ref name=&quot;EastValleyTribune&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=Jonathan | last=Athens | title=Restaurant name spurs TV interest | date=May 18, 2006 | publisher=East Valley Tribune | url=http://www.eastvalleytribune.com/index.php?sty=65818}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Scottsdale location closed its doors on April 1, 2009.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

The restaurant quickly gained the attention of the media, and was soon contacted by representatives from ''[[The Daily Show with Jon Stewart]]'' and ''[[Mind of Mencia]]'' with requests for interviews, which were initially turned down.&lt;ref name=&quot;EastValleyTribune&quot; /&gt; President and CEO [[Harry Morton]] appeared on the June 27, 2006 episode of ''The Daily Show'', which also featured a story on the controversy by reporter Ed Helms. During his interview, Morton explained that the name comes from a menu item, and that if the restaurant were truly &quot;vagina-themed&quot;, there would be &quot;vaginas all over the walls&quot;.&lt;ref name=thedailyshow&gt;''The Daily Show''. &quot;Box Lunch.&quot; Ed Helms. Produced by Bronwen Epstein. Edited by Einar Westerlund.&lt;/ref&gt; Pink Taco was also mentioned during the May 20, 2006 showing of ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' as part of its &quot;[[Weekend Update]]&quot; skit.&lt;ref name=&quot;SNL&quot;&gt;{{Cite video | people=Fey, Tina (Cast), Amy Poehler (Cast) |date=2006 | title=Saturday Night Live | medium=TV-Series | location=United States | publisher=National Broadcasting Company}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2006, Morton announced a [[United States Dollar|$]]30 million bid for the naming rights to the [[Arizona Cardinals]]' new [[University of Phoenix Stadium|stadium]] in [[Glendale, Arizona]].&lt;ref&gt;Villalobos, Louie. &quot;[http://www.azcentral.com/sports/special5/articles/0821stadium21-ON.html Pink Taco's owners make bid to name Cards stadium].&quot; ''[[Arizona Republic]].'' August 21, 2006. Retrieved on August 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The offer was rejected by the Cardinals, who dismissed the announcement as a joke and a publicity stunt. On September 28, 2006, Pink Taco launched a similar bid to rename the [[Louisiana Superdome]] in [[New Orleans]] to the &quot;Pink Taco Dome&quot;. As the State of Louisiana owns the Superdome, any name change must be approved by the [[Louisiana State Legislature]].&lt;ref&gt;Mackel, Fletcher. &quot;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/wdsu/20060929/lo_wdsu/9956336 Pink Taco Wants Naming Rights to Superdome].&quot; ''[[WDSU]].'' September 28, 2006. Retrieved on September 29, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Live animal controversy==
On May 5, 2011 in honor of Cinco de Mayo the Pink Taco in Century City, CA painted a donkey pink and wrote &quot;Pink Taco&quot; on both its sides. Critics claimed the donkey was shaved, painted pink and left outside in 90 °[[Fahrenheit|F]] heat. Spokesman for the animal rental company said the animal was treated fairly and two trainers were on site to care for it. The restaurant manager refused to comment. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ktla.com/news/landing/ktla-pink-taco-donkey-outrage,0,7749811.story |title=Pink Taco Restaurant: Angry Community Members Call for Boycott Over Pink Taco's Pink Donkey Display for Cinco de Mayo - ktla.com |author=klta news|work=ktla.com |year=2011 |accessdate=9 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Hooters]], another restaurant which has met with controversy for its themes

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.pinktaco.com/ Pink Taco website]

[[Category:Regional restaurant chains in the United States]]
[[Category:Mexican restaurants]]
[[Category:Restaurants established in 1999]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
