<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="524237" ns="0" title="Winston-Salem State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
 |name              = Winston-Salem State University
 |native_name       =
 |image_name        = WSSU-logo.jpg
 |image_size        = 150px
 |caption           =
 |latin_name        =
 |motto             = ''Enter to Learn, Depart to Serve.''
 |mottoeng          =
 |established       = 1892
 |closed            =
 |type              = [[Public school (government funded)|Public]], [[Historically black colleges and universities|HBCU]]
 |affiliation       =
 |endowment         = $19.6 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web| title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge =
 |chairman          =
 |chancellor        = Donald J. Reaves
 |president         =
 |vice-president    =
 |superintendent    =
 |provost           =
 |vice_chancellor   =
 |rector            =
 |principal         =
 |dean              =
 |director          =
 |head_label        =
 |head              =
 |faculty           =
 |staff             = 200
 |students          = 6,000
 |undergrad         =
 |postgrad          =
 |doctoral          =
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Winston-Salem, North Carolina|Winston-Salem]]
 |state             = [[North Carolina|NC]]
 |province          =
 |country           = [[United States|USA]]
 |coor              =
 |campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]]
 |former_names      =
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            =
 |colors            =
 |colours           =
 |nickname          = WSSU
 |mascot            =[[Sheep|Ram]]
 |athletics         = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]]
 |affiliations      = [[Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association]]
 |website           = [http://www.wssu.edu/ www.wssu.edu]
 |logo              =
 |footnotes         =
}}
'''Winston-Salem State University''' ('''WSSU'''), a constituent institution of the [[University of North Carolina]], is a [[Historically black colleges and universities|historically black]] [[Public university|public]] research university located in [[Winston-Salem, North Carolina]], [[United States]]. It is a member school of the [[Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund]]. 

Winston-Salem State has been ranked #27 by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' in the Top Public Comprehensive Baccalaureate Colleges of the South for the last nine years (2001–2009).category.&lt;ref&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/winston-salem-nc/winston-salem-state-2986&lt;/ref&gt; WSSU is a recognized regional institution offering baccalaureate and graduate programs to a diverse student population.

==History==
Dr. Simon Green Atkins distinguished himself in his home state of North Carolina as an advocate of teacher-training programs for African Americans. He founded a small school, Winston-Salem Teachers College, that he developed into Winston-Salem State University, a four-year institution, and oversaw its transition from private to state control. His abiding interest in teacher-training also led him to become a founder of the North Carolina Negro Teachers Association.

The oldest child of a brick layer and former slaves Allen and Eliza Atkins, Simon Green Atkins was born on June 11, 1863, in the village of Haywood, in [[Chatham County, North Carolina]], between [[Sanford, NC|Sanford]] and [[Raleigh, NC|Raleigh]]. His town flourished during the period just after the [[Revolutionary War]], but by the late 19th century the railroad and the neighboring town of [[Moncure, NC|Moncure]] had overshadowed it. At one time the area was considered as a location for the state capital as well as the state university. As a child, Atkins worked on a farm with his grandparents.

Atkins studied in the town school under pioneer black educators who came from St. Augustine’s Normal and Collegiate Institute (later [[St. Augustine's College (Raleigh)|St. Augustine’s College]] in Raleigh). One of these was [[Anna J. Cooper|Anna Julia Cooper]], later prominent for her work as an activist, scholar, feminist, and school administrator in [[Washington, D.C]]. This cadre of educators went out into remote communities to teach rural blacks. Atkins also taught at the town school for a while before his college years, and in 1880 he enrolled in St. Augustine’s. He spent summers teaching in the rural schools of Chatham and [[Moore County, North Carolina|Moore]] counties. 

After he graduated with distinction in 1884, renowned educator and orator Joseph Charles Price, president of [[Livingstone College]], an [[African Methodist Episcopal Zion]] church-supported institution in [[Salisbury, North Carolina]], invited Atkins to join his faculty. Atkins agreed and became grammar school department head. He spent six years at Livingstone (1884–90) and spent the last two years of his tenure there in the dual role as educator and treasurer of the college. During summer months he conducted institutes for black teachers in various counties.

The town educators of Winston (before its merger in 1913 with Salem to become Winston-Salem) lured Atkins to the post as principal of the Depot Street School, where he remained from 1890 to 1895. This was the state’s largest public school for African Americans. His work with the North Carolina Negro Teachers’ Association (NCNTA), which he helped to organize about 1881, had stimulated his interest in teacher-training schools for blacks. He directed this group as it established the foundation for a standard black teachers’ college in the state. 

Soon after he began his duties at Depot Street, he intensified his efforts to build such a school for African Americans and sought assistance from the Winston Board of Trade, Chamber of Commerce, and local white residents. By then, the state had begun plans to fund an agricultural college for its African American residents; hearing this, Atkins sought funds to locate the new college in Winston. Local support for this move was good, as the black community donated $2,000, [[R. J. Reynolds]] of tobacco fame contributed $500, and Atkins obtained {{convert|50|acre|m2}} of land along with the backing of the Chamber of Commerce. Although Atkins lobbied the state legislature in Raleigh on behalf of this plan, Winston and its residents lost out to nearby [[Greensboro, NC|Greensboro]], where citizens offered {{convert|14|acre|m2}} of land and $11,000.

The university was established by Dr. Simon Green Atkins in 1892 with funds donated by industrialist [[John Fox Slater]]. Chartered by the state of North Carolina in 1897 as Slater Industrial and State Normal School and renamed Winston-Salem Teachers College in 1925, it was the first African American institution in the United States to grant degrees in elementary teacher education.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} The name was changed to Winston-Salem State University in 1969, and it merged into the [[University of North Carolina]] system in 1972.

==Academics==
Winston-Salem State offers over 40 academic majors and 7 graduate degrees. The school enrolls approximately 6,400 students and employs over 200 staff members.
* Average high school GPA: 3.15 (weighted), 2.92 (unweighted) {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}
* Average SAT scores: 950, 25% lower and 25% higher {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}
* 65% of freshman applicants are accepted {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

==Campus==
{{Expand section|date=September 2010}}
The campus covers {{convert|117|acre|km2}}.

==Student activities==
=== National fraternities and sororities ===
All of the [[National Pan-Hellenic Council]] organizations currently have chapters at Winston-Salem State University except Delta Sigma Theta sorority, who were recently suspended for a 10-year period in April 2010. The remaining organizations are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Organization
! Symbol
! Chapter
! Chapter Symbol
|-
|[[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] sorority
|ΑΚΑ
|Gamma Lambda
|ΓΛ
|-
|[[Alpha Phi Alpha]] fraternity
|ΑΦΑ
|Beta Iota
|BI
|-
|[[Iota Phi Theta]] fraternity
|ΙΦΘ
|Kappa
|Κ
|-
|[[Kappa Alpha Psi]] fraternity
|ΚΑΨ
|Delta Chi
|ΔΧ
|-
|[[Omega Psi Phi]] fraternity
|ΩΨΦ
|Mu Epsilon
|ΜΕ
|-
|[[Phi Beta Sigma]] fraternity
|ΦΒΣ
|Delta Alpha
|ΔΑ
|-
|[[Sigma Gamma Rho]] sorority
|ΣΓΡ
|Rho
|Ρ
|-
|[[Zeta Phi Beta]] sorority
|ΖΦΒ
|Omega
|Ω
|-
|}

Other National fraternities and sororities with registered chapters are members of the Council of Independent Greek Organizations. The current members on campus include:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Organization
! Symbol
! Chapter
! Chapter Symbol
|-
|[[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]] fraternity
|ΦΜΑ
|Mu Beta
|ΜΒ
|-
|[[Tau Beta Sigma]] honorary band sorority
|ΤΒΣ
|Theta Upsilon
|ΘΥ
|-
|[[Kappa Kappa Psi]] honorary band fraternity
|ΚΚΨ
|Kappa Lambda
|ΚΛ
|-
|[[Pi Sigma Epsilon]] professional sales, marketing, and management fraternity
|ΠΣΕ
|Zeta Lambda
|ΖΛ
|-
|[[Alpha Nu Omega]] christian sorority
|ΑΝΩ
|Pi
|Π
|-
|[[Kappa Omicron Tau]] sorority
|ΚΟΤ
|Beta Lambda
|BΛ
|-
|[[Chi Eta Phi]] nursing sorority
|ΧΗΦ
|Chi Chi Beta
|ΧΧΒ
|-
|[[Alpha Phi Omega]] service fraternity
|ΑΦΩ
|Tau Chi
|ΤΧ
|-
|[[Swing Phi Swing]] social fellowship
|SΦS
|Groove
|
|}
===Athletics===
[[File:Athletic ram color full.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]
Winston-Salem State University is currently a part of the [[Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association|CIAA]] in NCAA Division II. From the 2007-08 season through the 2009-10 season, it competed in the NCAA's Division I [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference]] (MEAC) .

Its colors are red and white and the university mascot is a ram.

In 1967, Winston-Salem State became the first Historically Black College to win an NCAA Basketball Championship. The Rams won the College Division Championship with a 31-1 record. They were led by high-scoring guard [[Earl Monroe]], who averaged an amazing 41.5 points per game that season before being selected second overall in the NBA Draft by the Baltimore Bullets.

==Notable alumni==
{{Dynamic list}}
&lt;!-- NOTICE TO EDITORS: DO NOT ADD PEOPLE TO THIS LIST WITHOUT A VERIFIABLE CITATION. Additions without a citation are subject to removal. If a citation link is broken, please replace it with one that works.

PLEASE DO NOT ADD NON NOTABLE PEOPLE TO THIS LIST. A good rule of thumb is to check whether the person has an article on Wikipedia. If not, consider starting an article on the subject before adding him/her to this list.
--&gt;
{{AlumniStart}}

{{Alum|name=[[Donald Evans (football player)|Donald Evans]]|year=1987|nota=former NFL player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Louis Farrakhan]]|year=|nota=leader of the [[Nation of Islam]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Oronde Gadsden]] |year=|nota=former [[NFL]] player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Cleo Hill]]|year=|nota=former professional basketball player; first person from a [[Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association|CIAA]] school to be drafted in the first round of the National Basketball Association|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Richard Huntley]]|year=|nota=former NFL player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Earl Monroe|Earl &quot;the Pearl&quot; Monroe]]|year=1967|nota=former National Basketball Association player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Timmy Newsome]]|year=|nota=former NFL player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Monte Ross]]|year=|nota=Head Basketball Coach [[University of Delaware]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Louise Smith]]|year=|nota=Educator, helped to establish the first kindergarten program in N.C.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Stephen A. Smith]]|year=1989|nota=[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]]'' sports columnist and host of [[ESPN|ESPN's]] ''[[Quite Frankly with Stephen A. Smith]]''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Yancey Thigpen]]|year=|nota=former all-pro National Football League player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Luke Torian]]|year=1980|nota=Member of the Virginia House of Delegates from the 35th District|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Theodore &quot;Ted&quot; Blunt]]|year=|nota=[[Wilmington, Delaware]] City Council President|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[William Hayes (American football)|William Hayes]]|year=2008|nota=professional football player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jim Reid (basketball)|Jim Reid]]|year=|nota=former [[NBA]] player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Earl Williams (basketball player)|Earl &quot;the Twirl&quot; Williams]]|year=|nota= professional basketball player|ref=}}
|}
====Notable faculty and staff====
{{FacultyStart}}
{{Faculty|name=[[Clarence Gaines|Clarence &quot;Bighouse&quot; Gaines]]|dept=Athletics|nota=During his 47-year tenure at WSSU as coach, professor and athletic director, his men's basketball team compiled a record of 828-447. Gaines was inducted into the Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame in 1982.|ref=}}
{{FacultyEnd}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.wssu.edu/ www.wssu.edu] -- Official web site

{{Winston-Salem State University}}
{{University of North Carolina}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund}}

{{Coord|36.0894545|-80.2251603|display=title}}

[[Category:Winston-Salem State University| ]]
[[Category:University of North Carolina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in North Carolina]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Winston-Salem, North Carolina]]

[[no:Winston-Salem State University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
