<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5256396" ns="0" title="Wvdial"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:WvDial}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = WvDial
| logo                   =
| screenshot             =
| caption                =
| author                 = Dave Coombs / Avery Pennarun
| developer              =
| released               =
| latest release version = 1.61
| latest release date    = September 19, 2009
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date    =
| operating system       = [[Linux]]
| platform               =
| language               = [[C++]]
| genre                  = [[Internet]]
| license                = [[GNU Lesser General Public License]]
| website                = [http://alumnit.ca/wiki/index.php?page=WvDial alumnit.ca]
}}
'''WvDial''' (pronounced 'weave-dial' &lt;ref&gt;[http://freshmeat.net/projects/wvdial/ freshmeat.net: Project details for WvDial&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;) is a utility that helps in making [[modem]]-based connections to the Internet that is included in some important Linux distributions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://alumnit.ca/wiki/index.php?page=WvDial Wv Dial - open.alumnit.ca&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; WvDial is a [[Point-to-Point Protocol]] [[dialer]]: it dials a modem and starts [[pppd]] in order to connect to the [[Internet]].

When WvDial starts, it first loads its configuration from &lt;tt&gt;/etc/wvdial.conf&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;~/.wvdialrc&lt;/tt&gt;, which contain basic information about the modem port, speed, and init string, along with information about your ISP, such as the phone number, your user name, and your password.&lt;ref name=&quot;wvdial&quot;&gt;[http://www.linuxcommand.org/man_pages/wvdial1.html WvDial]&lt;/ref&gt;

Then it [[modem initialization|initializes your modem]] (strings are sent to the modem) and [[dialer|dials]] the server and waits for a connection (a ''[[CONNECT]]'' string from the  modem). Any time after connecting, WvDial will start PPP if it sees a PPP sequence from the server or, alternatively, tries to start PPP. If all of this fails, WvDial just runs  [[Point-to-Point Protocol daemon|pppd]] and hopes for the best.&lt;ref name=&quot;wvdial&quot; /&gt;

The connection started with WvDial can be dropped by switching back to the terminal from where it was started and pressing Ctrl-C.

WvDial uses the [[wvstreams]] library.&lt;ref&gt;[http://alumnit.ca/wiki/index.php?page=WvStreams Wv Streams - open.alumnit.ca&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== WvDial and chat ==
It uses heuristics to guess how to dial and log into your server rather than forcing you to write a login script.&lt;ref&gt;[http://linux.die.net/man/8/chat chat(8) - Linux man page&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== wvdialconf utility ==
If &lt;tt&gt;/etc/wvdial.conf&lt;/tt&gt; is not present, the easiest way to create it is to use configuration utility '''wvdialconf''' .

It helps in generating the configuration file needed by WvDial. wvdialconf detects your modem, and fill in automatically the Modem, maximum Baud rate, and a good [[initialization string]] (Init options)  and generates or updates the WvDial configuration file (/etc/wvdial.conf) based on this information.

It is safe to run wvdialconf if a configuration file already exists. In that case, only the Modem, Baud, Init, and Init2 options are changed in the [Dialer Defaults] section, and only if autodetection is successful.

wvdialconf is a non-interactive utility ( that means that you  still  need to edit /etc/wvdial.conf to specify the phone number, login name, and  password of your internet account in order for WvDial to work).

Example:
 wvdialconf /etc/wvdial.conf

Here, /etc/wvdial.conf is the path of the file that needs to be created or updated with the details that wvdialconf detects.

The configuration file built by wvdialconf still needs to be updated with the details like your phone number, username, password for your internet connection in order for WvDial to work.

== Files ==
* /dev/ttyS ([[serial port]] modems) and  /dev/ttyUSB ([[USB modem]]s).

* /etc/ppp/peers/wvdial :  required  for  correct  authentication  in pppd version 2.3.0 or    newer.

* /etc/ppp/{[[Password authentication protocol|pap]], [[Challenge-Handshake Authentication Protocol|chap]]}-secrets : Contains a list of usernames and  passwords  used  by  pppd  for authentication.  WvDial maintains this list automatically.

=== wvdial.conf ===
When WvDial starts, it first loads its configuration from '''/etc/wvdial.conf'''. The configuration file /etc/wvdial.conf is the equivalent to the Windows &quot;ini&quot; file format, with '''section'''s named in square brackets and a number of variable = value pairs within each section.

Here is a sample configuration file:

 [Dialer Defaults]
 Modem = /dev/ttyACM0
 Baud = 460800
 Init = ATZ
 Init2 = ATQ0 V1 E1 S0=0 &amp;C1 &amp;D2 +FCLASS=0
 ISDN = 0
 Modem Type = USB Modem
 Phone = #777
 Username = internet
 Password = internet
 stupid mode = 1

This example that uses Init3 to turn the modem's speaker off. The default is &quot;ATZ&quot; for Init(1).

When WvDial is in Stupid Mode, it does not attempt to interpret any prompts from the terminal server. It starts pppd immediately after the modem connects. Apparently there are ISP's that actually give you a login prompt, but work only if you start PPP, rather than logging in.

== Log ==
If WvDial fails to establish the communication, type the following commands:
 script wvdial.log
 wvdial
 exit

== Ready ==
After starting wvdial you can know if your session is ready with `&lt;code&gt;/sbin/ip addr&lt;/code&gt;` which, if OK, will show a [[pppX|pppd]] interface entry.

==Graphical frontends==

There are some GUI tools which allows using WvDial:
* [[x-wvdial]], that uses [[xmessage]].&lt;ref&gt;http://osx.freshmeat.net/projects/x-wvdial/ , http://www.xfree86.org/4.4.0/xmessage.1.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[gnome-ppp]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://gnomefiles.org/app.php/GNOME_PPP GNOME PPP at GnomeFiles]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[QtWvDialer]]

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Hayes command set]]
* [[ifconfig]]
* [[NetworkManager]]
* [[kppp]] - An automated tool that features a [[GUI]], instead of the daemon's [[command-line]].
* [[pppconfig]]
* [[Point-to-Point Protocol daemon]]
* [[USB modem]]
* [http://www.opennms.org/index.php/Configuring_notifications#Simple_Phone_Call OpenNMS Notification usage example]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [http://alumnit.ca/wiki/index.php?page=WvDialFAQ WvDial FAQ]
* [http://tardus.net/securIDdialup.html Using wvdial with a SecurID one-shot password]
* {{man|1|wvdial}}
* {{man|1|wvdialconf}}
* {{man|5|wvdial.conf}}

==External links==
* {{Official|1=http://alumnit.ca/wiki/index.php?page=WvDial}}
* [http://alumnit.ca/wiki/index.php?page=MailingLists&amp;redirect_from=MailingList wvdial Email list]
* {{Freshmeat|wvdial|wvdial}}
* {{Freshmeat|x-wvdial|x-wvdial}}

[[Category:Free network-related software]]
[[Category:Unix software]]

[[ar:ويف دايل]]
[[es:Wvdial]]
[[it:Wvdial]]
[[krc:Wvdial]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
