<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="526016" ns="0" title="University of Cincinnati"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
| name=University of Cincinnati
| logo=[[File:UC-logo-500.png|110px|University of Cincinnati current logo]]
| image=[[File:UC Seal.svg|125px|University of Cincinnati Seal]]
| motto=''Juncta Juvant''&lt;br&gt;([[Latin language|Latin]] for &quot;Strength in Unity&quot;)
| established=1819
| type=[[State university system|Public (state university)]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Space-grant university|Space grant]]
| endowment=[[United States dollar|$]]1.004 billion (September 2011)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/president/reportcard/2011/economy.html|title=UC 2019 September 2011 Report Card|date=September 23, 2011 |accessdate=September 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| president=[[Gregory H. Williams]]
| provost=[[Santa J. Ono]]
| students=42,421 (all campuses)&lt;ref name=&quot;UC Facts, University of Cincinnati&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/about/ucfactsheet.html|title=UC Facts, University of Cincinnati|publisher=Uc.edu|date=September 20, 2010|accessdate=January 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 32,000 (uptown)
| undergrad=31,523 (all campuses) 22,449 (uptown)&lt;ref name=&quot;UC Facts, University of Cincinnati&quot;/&gt;
| postgrad=9,834&lt;ref name=&quot;UC Facts, University of Cincinnati&quot;/&gt;
| alumni=252,964&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/content/dam/uc/foundation/docs/annual_reports/uc_annual_rpt_alluc_2010.pdf |title=University of Cincinnati Alumni Association Annual Report, Fall 2010|publisher=UC.edu|date=September 1, 2010|accessdate=January 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| faculty=5,928&lt;ref name=&quot;UC Facts, University of Cincinnati&quot;/&gt;
| staff=3,889&lt;ref name=&quot;UC Facts, University of Cincinnati&quot;/&gt;
| city=[[Cincinnati]]
| state=[[Ohio]]
| country=U.S.
| campus=Urban; All Campuses: 473 [[acres]] (1.91 km²)
                Uptown Campus (Main and Medical): {{convert|194|acre|km2}}
|free_label      = Athletics
|free            = 18 Division I / IA NCAA teams
| colors=Red &amp; Black {{color box|#e00122}}{{color box|black}}|
nickname= [[Cincinnati Bearcats|Bearcats]]
| mascot= [[Binturong|The Bearcat]]
| affiliations=[[Big East Conference]],&lt;br /&gt;[[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Oak Ridge Associated Universities]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Great Cities' Universities]]
| website=[http://www.uc.edu/ www.uc.edu]
}}

The '''University of Cincinnati''' (commonly referred to as '''UC''', '''Cincinnati''', or '''Cincy''') is a comprehensive [[public university|public]] [[research university]] in [[Cincinnati, Ohio]], and a part of the [[University System of Ohio]].

UC was founded in 1819, and has an annual enrollment of over 40,000 students, making it one of the largest universities in the U.S. In the 2010 survey by ''Times Higher Education (UK)'', the university was ranked in the top 100 universities in North America and as one of the top 200 in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/north-america.html |title=Top Universities in North America 2010–2011|publisher=Timeshighereducation.co.uk|accessdate=September 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html|title=Top 200 – The Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2010–11|publisher=Timeshighereducation.co.uk|accessdate=September 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2012 edition of ''US News and World Report'', the University of Cincinnati was ranked as a Tier One university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-universities-rankings|title=Best Colleges 2011 – National Universities Rankings|publisher=http://www.usnews.com/rankings|date=September 19, 2010|accessdate=January 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The university garners nearly $500 million per annum in research funding, ranking 22nd among public universities in the US.  Numerous programs across the university are nationally ranked, including: aerospace engineering, anthropology, architecture, classics, composition, conducting, cooperative education, criminal justice, design, environmental science, law, medicine, music, musical theater, neurology, opera, otolaryngology, paleontology, pediatrics and pharmacy.

The school offers over 100 bachelor degrees, over 300 degree granting programs, and over 600 total programs of study, ranging from certificates to doctoral and first professional education. With an economic impact of over $3.5 billion per year, it is the largest single employer in [[Greater Cincinnati]]. After extensive renovations through the implementation of the 1989 Master Plan, the university has been recognized by campus planners and architects as one of the most distinguished campus settings in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Pascale Le Draoulec|url=http://www.forbes.com/2010/03/01/most-beautiful-campus-lifestyle-college_slide.html|title=The World's Most Beautiful College Campuses|publisher=Forbes.com|date=August 31, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/News/NR.aspx?ID=3884|title=University of Cincinnati Master Plan|publisher=UC.edu|date=April 27, 2006|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ratha Tep|url=http://travel.yahoo.com/p-interests-40718209|title=America's Most Beautiful College Campuses|publisher=Travel Magazine|date=October 7, 2011|accessdate=October 7,2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Pt3 3a.jpg|thumb|left|Original Cincinnati College building, 1874]]

===Cincinnati College===
In 1819, Cincinnati College and the Medical College of Ohio were founded in Cincinnati. Local benefactor Dr. [[Daniel Drake]]
founded and funded the Medical College of Ohio. William Lytle of the [[Lytle family]] donated the land, funded the Cincinnati College and Law College, and served as its first president. The college survived only six years before financial difficulties forced it to close. In 1835, Daniel Drake reestablished the institution, which eventually joined with the [[Cincinnati Law School]]. {{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===McMicken University===
In 1858 Charles McMicken died of pneumonia and in his will he allocated $1 million to the City of [[Cincinnati]] to found a university, and after several controversies and delays, the University of Cincinnati was officially chartered by the Ohio legislature in 1870.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.libraries.uc.edu/liblog/2010/05/13/mcmicken-will-notice-found-in-cincinnati-german-newspaper|title=McMicken Will Notice Found in Cincinnati German Newspaper – LiBLOG |publisher=Libraries.uc.edu|date=May 13, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally known as McMicken University, a month after the college's founding, the university's board of directors changed the institution's name to the University of Cincinnati.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=813|title=University of Cincinnati – Ohio History Central – A product of the Ohio Historical Society|publisher=Ohio History Central|date=July 1, 2005|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Move up the hill===
[[File:University of Cincinnati, Ohio c. 1904.jpg|thumb|University of Cincinnati, Ohio, ca. 1904]]
By 1893 the University had outgrown its old home on Clifton Ave. and moved to its current location in the [[CUF, Cincinnati|Heights]] neighborhood, which was formally part [[Burnet Woods]]. As the university continued to grow it merged with the Cincinnati Law School which become the [[University of Cincinnati College of Law]] in 1896 and while the Medical College of Ohio was loosely affiliated with UC from about 1896, it joined with a splinter medical school, Miami Medical College, to form the Ohio-Miami Medical Department of the University of Cincinnati in 1909. As the need for higher education grew, the university also created colleges such as a Teacher's College in 1905 and a Graduate School in the College of Arts and Sciences in 1906. In 1962 the [[University of Cincinnati College-Conservatory of Music|Cincinnati College-Conservatory of Music]] joined the university as well. UC became a &quot;municipally-sponsored, state-affiliated&quot; institution in 1968. During this time, UC was the second oldest and second-largest municipal university in the country. It became one of Ohio's [[state universities]] in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=813|title=University of Cincinnati History |publisher=Libraries.uc.edu|date=June 19, 2011|accessdate=June 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus Master Plan and UC|21===
In 1989 university president [[Joseph A. Steger]] and Hargreaves Associates unveiled a Master Plan for the university.&lt;ref&gt;[http://carlsterner.com/files/research/Main_Street_and_the_Urban_Campus.pdf carlsterner.com (PDF)]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over this time the university invested nearly $2 billion in campus construction, renovation, and expansion ranging from the student union to a new recreation center to the medical school. This has been amended in both 2000 and 2005 but has helped create one of the most beautiful university campuses in the world. [[File:UC MainStreet.jpg|thumb|left|MainStreet looking past the Steger Student Life Center towards the student union and McMicken Hall]]It included renovation and construction of multiple buildings, adding dozens of acres of green-space to the campus, and adding MainStreet, which is a central path through campus highlighting all of the most frequented buildings on campus. After becoming president of the university in 2005, [[Nancy L. Zimpher]] implemented a plan named UC|21. This was designed to help redefine UC as the &quot;new urban research university&quot; for the 21st century. This included putting students at the center, increasing research funding, expanded involvement in the surrounding city, and making UC the &quot;premier&quot; urban research university.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uc.edu/president25/uc21/ataglance.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===UC2019===
As the university approaches its [[Anniversary|bicentennial]] and after Dr. Zimpher left in 2009, [[Gregory H. Williams]] was named the 27th president of the University of Cincinnati. He has begun an aggressive plan to increase outside validation of the university. The plan was designed to catapult UC into its bicentennial and continue increasing academic profile and the size and academic quality of the university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/content/dam/uc/president/media/StrategicPlan_2010.pdf |title=2010 Strategic Plan for UC |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He and Provost [[Santa J. Ono]] are focusing on the academic master plan for the university, placing the academic programs of UC at the core of the strategic plan.  They have invested in scholarships, funding for study abroad experiences, the university's highly regarded Honors Program and the advising program. Additionally, the university has begun work on an academic master plan slated for completion in fall of 2011 that will outline the next generation of programs at UC.

==Campuses==
===Uptown campus===
The Uptown campus includes the West (main), Medical, and Victory Parkway campuses.[[File:Outside 040-edit.jpg|thumb|right|Entrance to main campus at UC]]
*West (main) Campus:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uc.edu/content/dam/common/docs/maps/campus_map_west.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; This campus includes 62 buildings on {{convert|137|acre|km2}}. The university moved to this location in 1893. Most of the undergraduate colleges at the university are located on main campus. The exceptions are part of the [[University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center]] on the Medical campus. In spring of 2010 the University of Cincinnati was honored by being one of only 13 colleges and universities named by [[Forbes]] as one of &quot;The World's Most Beautiful College Campuses&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Pascale Le Draoulec|url=http://www.forbes.com/2010/08/31/beautiful-campuses-lifestyle-education-colleges-10-university-architecture_slide_12.html|title=The World's Most Beautiful College Campuses|publisher=Forbes.com|date=August 31, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Medical Campus:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uc.edu/content/dam/common/docs/maps/campus_map_medical.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; this campus contains nineteen buildings on {{convert|57|acre|m2}}. It is caddy corner to West campus on Martin Luther King Jr. Blvd. The undergraduate colleges of Allied Health Sciences and Nursing and graduate colleges of Medicine and the James L. Winkle College of Pharmacy are located there. The hospitals located there include University Hospital, [[Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center]], Cincinnati VA Medical Center, and the Shriners Hospital for Children.
*Victory Parkway Campus: this campus was formally home to the [[University of Cincinnati College of Applied Science|College of Applied Science]]. It is roughly {{convert|3|mi|km}} from main campus in the [[Walnut Hills]] neighborhood of Cincinnati and overlooks the [[Ohio River]]. When it merged with the College of Engineering to become the College of Engineering and Applied Science many of the classes were moved to main campus, however limited courses are still taught there. There is a shuttle that runs between this and main campus throughout the day.

===Branch campuses===
* '''Blue Ash College (UCBA)''' (regional campus, located in [[Blue Ash, Ohio]])&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rwc.uc.edu|title=Raymond Walters College|publisher=RWC.uc.edu|date=October 18, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[University of Cincinnati Clermont College|Clermont College]] (CLER)''' (regional campus, located in [[Batavia, Ohio]])
* '''UC East''' (located in a renovated Ford plant in Batavia, OH, this facility serves as expansion space for Clermont College and select programs in the College of Nursing and the College of Education, Criminal Justice, and Human Services)&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucclermont.edu/Students/uceast/about_east.html|title=About UC East|publisher=ucclermont.edu|date=September 2010|accessdate=July 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research facilities===
*Center Hill Research Facility
*UC Reading Campus &amp; UC Metabolic Diseases Institute
*Cincinnati Center for Field Studies&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.artsci.uc.edu/biology/cfs|title=Center for Field Studies|publisher=University of Cincinnati|date=May 1, 2011|accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Cincinnati Observatory (university owns the facility and the nonprofit [[Cincinnati Observatory]] Center operates it)

===Architecture===
[[Image:050819 011 Vontz.jpg|thumb|right|Vontz Center for Molecular Studies, designed by [[Frank Gehry]] in conjunction with [[BHDP Architecture]], is part of the [[University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center|medical campus]].]]
[[File:Engineering Research Center.jpg|thumb|The Engineering Research Center, designed by UC Alumnus [[Michael Graves]], was designed to look like a 4-cylinder engine.]]
The university has had a strategic plan for the last decade for new architecture to be built by &quot;signature architects.&quot; UC itself has an outstanding architecture and design program, and the efforts to have these famous architects design new campus buildings have encouraged students to attend the [[University of Cincinnati College of Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning|College of Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning]] (DAAP). In recent years, the university has received attention from architects and campus planners as one of the most beautiful in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Pascale Le Draoulec|url=http://www.forbes.com/2010/03/01/most-beautiful-campus-lifestyle-college_slide.html|title=In Pictures: The World's Most Beautiful Campuses|publisher=Forbes.com|date=August 31, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Engineering Research Center, [[Michael Graves]] (UC alumnus) (1994)
*Aronoff Center for Art and Design, [[Peter Eisenman]] (1996)
*College-Conservatory of Music, [[Henry N. Cobb|Pei Cobb Freed and Partners (Henry Cobb)]] (1999)
*Vontz Center for Molecular Studies, [[Frank O. Gehry]] (1999)
*Tangeman University Center, [[Gwathmey Siegel &amp; Associates Architects]] (2004)
*Steger Student Life Center, [[Charles Willard Moore|Moore Ruble Yudell]] (2005)
*Campus Recreation Center, [[Morphosis]] ([[Thom Mayne]]) (2006)
*Lindner Athletic Center, [[Bernard Tschumi]] (2006)
*Care/Crawley Building, STUDIOS Architecture (2008)

===Sustainability===
In recent years the University of Cincinnati has made significant strides to include more green initiatives and encourage sustainability among students, faculty, and staff. In autumn of 2010 the University of Cincinnati maintained its position in green and sustainability initiatives by being named one of only 286 &quot;Green Colleges&quot; by [[The Princeton Review]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/green-schools-by-state.aspx|title=286 Green Colleges (by State) |publisher=Princetonreview.com|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; UC was the only public university in Ohio and the only university in the Southern Ohio region included on this list. Some of the programs that helped achieve this distinction include a bike share program where UC students can rent bikes from the university, an expanded recycling program, improved and expanded campus transportation options, greatly decreased energy and water use throughout campus, and the addition of 6 [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]] (LEED) certified buildings since 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=UC Sustainability gets high marks|url=http://www.newsrecord.org/news/uc-sustainability-gets-high-marks-1.2393670|publisher=Newsrecord.org |date=November 4, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, former university president Nancy Zimpher signed the [[The American College &amp; University Presidents' Climate Commitment]] which confirms the university's dedication to reducing its environmental impact and take the necessary steps to become climate neutral.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/af/pdc/sustainability/campus_initiatives.html|title=President signs charter to join 'The American College &amp; University Presidents' Climate Commitment (ACUPCC)|publisher=UC.edu|date=April 2007|accessdate=March 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 UC opened up a new $14 million privately funded athletic practice facility and Women's Lacrosse stadium named the Sheakley Athletic Complex. As a continued effort to go green, a chilled water [[thermal energy storage]] tank will be placed under the fields and at night the water will be chilled and then used to air-condition buildings on campus. The storage tank will help the university to reach annual energy savings of about $1 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gobearcats.com/sports/w-lacros/spec-rel/031610aaa.html|title=UC Breaks Ground On Jefferson Avenue Sports Complex – University of Cincinnati Official Athletics Site|publisher=Gobearcats.com|date=March 16, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, in Autumn of 2010, the university began placing ''All Recycling'' containers throughout campus. This expansion of recycling efforts and receptacles provides a greater opportunity for students, staff, and visitors to participate in recycling a broader range of materials. In 2010 UC recycled just over 4,600 tons of material, which was a 23 percent increase over the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.uc.edu/News/NR.aspx?id=13485|title=Recycling Grows at UC – By Tons at a Time|publisher=UC.edu|date=May 2, 2011|accessdate=May 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Professional Practice Program==
[[File:Steger.jpg|thumb|left|Joseph A. Steger Student Life Center]]

UC is the originator of the [[co-operative education]] (co-op) model. The concept was invented at UC in 1906 by [[Herman Schneider]], Dean of the College of Engineering at the time. The program generally consists of alternating quarters of coursework on campus and outside work at a host firm, giving students over one year of relevant work experience by the time they graduate. All programs in the College of Engineering and Applied Science, as well as Architecture and all design programs in the College of Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning, require co-operative education experience to graduate. Programs in the McMicken College of Arts and Sciences, College of Business, and other colleges offer optional co-op opportunities. For a number of years, this system was referred to as &quot;The Cincinnati Plan.&quot; Ranked fourth in the U.S., UC's Professional Practice (Co-op) Program is the largest co-op program at a public institution in the United States with over 3,000 participating students at over 1,500 companies in 25 countries. The office of Professional Practice is housed in the Steger Student Life Center. The Division of Professional Practice is broken up into three units:

===Cooperative Education Program===
For over 100 years the Division lead has provided students with the opportunity to alternate full-time classroom time and work to provide them with a solid base of experience and professional development. This unit is the largest and modern successor of the original &quot;Cincinnati Plan&quot;.

===Academic Internship Program===
In 2010, the Division launched the Academic Internship Program, which provides access to opportunities for part time internships to students.

===The Center for Cooperative Education Research and Innovation===
This unit seeks to drive the development and implementation of cooperative education at UC as well as serve as an incubator for research and new thinking about approaches to experiential education. An example of this in action is the &quot;Live Well Collaborative&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fastcodesign.com/1663402/na-ve-innovation-college-students-show-mega-corporations-like-pg-how-to-design-for-the-elder|title=To Innovate for Boomers, P&amp;G and LG Are Tapping... College Kids?!|publisher=Fast Company Magazine|date=March 14, 2011|accessdate=March 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Formed in 2008, this is a collaborative effort between private companies such as Procter &amp; Gamble, Boeing, General Mills, LG Electronics, and Kraft and the colleges of Business, DAAP, and Engineering and Applied Science at UC to help create living solutions for the U.S.'s aging population.

==Academic profile==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| GUR                  =
| ARWU_W               = 201–300
| ARWU_N               = 90-110
| ARWU_SCI             =
| ARWU_ENG             =
| ARWU_SOC             =
| USNWR_NU             = 143
| USNWR_PU             = 73
| USNWR_Bus            =
| USNWR_Law            =
| USNWR_Medr           =
| USNWR_Eng            =
| USNWR_Ed             =
| QS_W                 = 339
| THES_W               = 190
| Wamo_NU              = 191
| Forbes               = 516
}}

The University of Cincinnati aims to be the premier urban research university, and currently offers 304 programs of study which include 49 Associate, 103 Baccalaureate, 85 Master's, 67 Doctoral, and 4 First Professional (MD, JD, etc.) degrees. The university is divided into 13 colleges.

===Rankings===
The university has dozens of highly ranked programs. The Princeton Review listed the university in its &quot;Best 373 Colleges&quot; in 2011 and the London (UK) Times ranked the University of Cincinnati 190th among all the universities in the world, 69th among United States universities and 28th among public U.S. universities in 2011. Additionally, the influential Academic Ranking of World Universities, published by Shanghai Jiaotong University, ranks the University of Cincinnati in the top 300 of more than 2,500 ranked worldwide and the top 100 of American universities. In the 2012 US News and World Report, UC was ranked as the 143rd best university in the US and as the 73rd best public institution.
{|
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Colleges''':
*[[Cooperative Education]], 4th in the U.S.
*[[College of Pharmacy]], 32nd in the U.S.
*[[College of Medicine]] 42nd in the U.S.
*[[College of Nursing]] (Undergraduate), 48th in the U.S
*[[College of Law]], 61st in the U.S.
*[[College of Business]], 71st in the U.S.
*[[College of Nursing]] (Graduate), 72nd in the U.S.
*[[College of Engineering]], 78th in the U.S.
*[[School of Education]] (CECH), 55th in the U.S.
*[[School of Criminal Justice]] (CECH), 3rd in the U.S.
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Music and Arts Programs''':
*Musical Theatre, 1st in the U.S.
*Opera/Voice, 3rd in the U.S
*[[Interior Design]], 3rd in the U.S.
*[[Musical Conducting]], 5th in the U.S.
*Masters of Architecture, 6th in the U.S.
*[[Industrial Design]], 6th in the U.S.
*Music, 6th in the U.S.
*[[Music Composition]], 9th in the U.S.
*[[Orchestra/Symphony]], 9th in the U.S.
*[[Drama]], Top 10 in the U.S.
*Master of fine arts, 45th in the U.S.
*Creative Writing 46th in the U.S.
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Science, Engineering, and Business Programs''':
*[[Paleontology]], 6th in the U.S.
*[[Environmental Engineering]], 20th in the U.S.
*[[Aerospace Engineering]], 31st in the U.S.
*[[Industrial Engineering]], 37th in the U.S.
*[[Civil Engineering]], 48th in the U.S.
*[[Materials Engineering]], 50th in the U.S.
*[[Mechanical Engineering]], 60th in the U.S.
*[[Masters of Business Administration]] (Full-time), 75th in the U.S.
*[[Masters of Business Administration]] (Part-time), 93rd in the U.S.
*[[Accounting]] (undergraduate), 10th in the U.S.
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Medical and Human Service Programs''':
*[[Pediatrics]], 3rd in the U.S.
*Nursing, Anesthesia, 11th in the U.S.
*[[Otolaryngology]], 18th in the U.S.
*AIDS Center, 26th in the U.S.
*[[Neurology]], 28th in the U.S.
*[[Geriatrics]], 29th in the U.S.
*Pulmonary Disease, 32nd in the U.S.
*Cancer Center, 33rd in the U.S.
*[[Rheumatology]], 35th in the U.S.
*Speech and Language Pathology, 38th in the U.S.
*[[Endocrinology]], 39th in the U.S.
*[[Cardiology]], 43rd in the U.S.
*[[Audiology]], 44th in the U.S.
|}

===Colleges and schools===
The university is broken-up into the 13 colleges and schools listed below.
* '''[[University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center|College of Allied Health Sciences]] (CAHS)'''
** '''School of Social Work''' (Part of the College of Allied Health Sciences as of Autumn 2010)[[File:CampusJuly14 54.jpg|thumb|right|McMicken Hall, home of the McMicken College of Arts and Sciences on main campus.]]
* '''[[McMicken College of Arts and Sciences]] (A&amp;S)''', as the largest and most diverse college, A&amp;S is the academic heart of UC and is home to twenty-one departments, eight co-op programs, and several interdisciplinary programs. The [http://classics.uc.edu/ Classics Department] is one of the most active centers for the study of [[Bronze Age]] and [[Classical antiquity]] in the United States. UC's Creative Writing PhD program was ranked 6th in the nation by [http://www.pw.org Poets and Writers'] magazine. McMicken's paleontology program is ranked 7th in the nation by U.S. News &amp; World Report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/news/NR.asp?id=3780 |title=It's a 'Threepeat' for UC's Paleontology Program|publisher=Uc.edu |date=April 23, 2009|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Carl H. Lindner College of Business]] (LCB)''', one of the top business schools in southern Ohio, particularly known for its programs in [[operations management]], [[accounting]], information systems and [[marketing]] as well as the prestigious Carl H. Lindner Honors-PLUS and the Kolodzik Business Scholars programs which consist of some of the top future business professionals in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Undergraduate B-School Profiles&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessweek.com/bschools/07/undergrad/index.html|title=Undergraduate B-School Profiles|publisher=Businessweek.com|date=August 15, 2007|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; UC is the fifth most influential real estate research institution in the U.S., based on the quality of faculty research and literary citations in journals and has tenth ranked undergraduate accounting program in the U.S.
* '''[[University of Cincinnati Clermont College|Clermont College]] (CLER)''' (regional campus)
* '''[[University of Cincinnati College-Conservatory of Music|College-Conservatory of Music]] (CCM)''', a prestigious performing arts school, ranked 6th nationally by ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' and particularly renowned for its voice, composition, piano, musical theater, orchestra, wind studies, drama, and Theater Design departments.
[[File:Schneider Quad.jpg|thumb|right|Schneider Quadrangle with Baldwin Hall anchoring it, home of the College of Engineering and Applied Science]]
* '''[[University of Cincinnati College of Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning|College of Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning]] (DAAP)''', a highly internationally-ranked design school,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uc.edu/about/ucfactsheet.html#rankings UC website citation] of [[I.D. Magazine]]&lt;/ref&gt; particularly known for its programs in [[interior design]] (ranked best in the nation), [[architecture]], and [[industrial design]] (both ranked second), as well as [[graphic design]] and [[urban planning]] (both ranked in the top 20).
* '''[[University of Cincinnati College of Education Criminal Justice and Human Services|College of Education, Criminal Justice, and Human Services]] (CECH)''', its criminal justice program is ranked 3rd nationally by ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]''
* '''[[University of Cincinnati College of Engineering and Applied Science|College of Engineering and Applied Science]] (CEAS)''', as of June 2009, the College of Applied Science and the College of Engineering officially merged to form the new college. The college is regularly ranked as one of the top 75 engineering colleges in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/cas|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20051215073256/http://www.uc.edu/cas|archivedate=December 15, 2005|title=College of Engineering &amp; Applied Science, University of Cincinnati|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** '''College of Engineering (ENGR)''', recognized as having the first co-operative education program in the United States. [[Winston Koch]] invented the first [[electronic organ]] here.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/about/ucfactsheet.html#firsts|title=College of Engineering &amp; Applied Science, University of Cincinnati|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** '''College of Applied Science (CAS)''', organized as the Ohio Mechanics Institute (OMI) in 1828, it merged with UC in 1969 and was renamed the OMI College of Applied Science in 1979.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://omicas175.uc.edu/index.asp|title=OMI CAS 175th Anniversary|publisher=Omicas175.uc.edu|date=August 30, 2007|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Referred to as the College of Applied Science, CAS offered programs in the engineering technologies and related areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.omicas175.uc.edu/histtimel.asp|title=OMI CAS 175th Anniversary|publisher=Omicas175.uc.edu|accessdate=September 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''The Graduate School''', a collaborative unit of all the university's colleges responsible for providing centralized administrative services for all postgraduate programs.
* '''[[University of Cincinnati College of Law|College of Law]]''', the fourth oldest continually running law school in the country and alma mater of [[William Howard Taft]], the only person to serve both as [[U.S. President]] and as [[Chief Justice of the Supreme Court]]. Taft also served as the college's dean when it integrated with the University of Cincinnati in 1896. Cincinnati is one of only six law schools in America to have matriculated a U.S. President and a Supreme Court justice. A statue of the former president stands near the campus law building.[[File:2008-10-05 05 Cincinnati architecture the University of Cincinnati's CARECrawley Building.jpg|thumb|right|CARE/Crawley building on the University of Cincinnati's Medical campus]]
* '''[[University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center|College of Medicine]]''', ranked among the best 40 medical schools by ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-medical-schools/university-of-cincinnati-04090|title=Top Medical Schools|publisher=grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date= |accessdate=July 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; it includes both a leading [[teaching hospital]] and several biomedical research laboratories. In the 1950s [[Albert Sabin]] developed the live [[polio]] [[vaccine]] at the College of Medicine. [[Diphenhydramine]] ([[Benadryl]]) was developed here by [[George Rieveschl]] in 1946. UC also established the first [[emergency medicine]] residency program. UC offers a dual-admissions program known as ''Connections'' to high school students applying for undergraduate studies at the University of Cincinnati.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.med.uc.edu/hs2md/ |title=Page Title |publisher=Med.uc.edu |date= |accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center|College of Nursing]]''', recognized as having the first bachelor’s degree program in nursing.
* '''[[University of Cincinnati Academic Health Center|James L. Winkle College of Pharmacy]]''', is one of the most prestigious and competitive pharmacy programs in the US and is ranked 32rd nationally by U.S. News and World Report.  It was founded in 1850 as the first pharmacy school west of the Alleghenies, and its graduates have a 100% placement rate prior to graduation.
* '''Blue Ash College (UCBA)''' (regional campus, located in [[Blue Ash, Ohio]])&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

UC is also the home of the '''Institute for Policy Research''', a multidisciplinary research organization which opened in 1971. The center performs a variety of [[opinion poll|surveys and polls]] on public opinion throughout Ohio, Kentucky, and Indiana, primarily through telephone surveys.

===Honors program===
Each year UC brings in roughly 300 students to the '''University Honors Program''' and usually includes the top 5%-8% of students that apply to UC each year. The average credentials for an UC Honors students is an ACT score of 32 or higher, an SAT score of 1400 or higher (critical reading and math combined), a class rank in the top 10%, and an unweighted high school GPA of 3.8.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/honors/prospective/freshmen.html|title=Page Title |publisher=uc.edu/honors|date= |accessdate=July 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The program emphasizes experiential learning and engages students in curricular and co-curricular learning opportunities. The program enriches the UC experience of academically talented and motivated students through coursework and out-of-class experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/honors/abouthonors.html|title=Page Title |publisher=uc.edu/honors|date= |accessdate=July 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Honors Program focuses on the four pillars of honors:

*Community Engagement
*Global studies
*Leadership
*Research &amp; Creative Arts

'''Curriculum &amp; Seminars'''
*Honors courses mesh with major and general education requirements so students can graduate from University Honors without completing extra courses and provide students with priority registration, smaller class sizes, and more academically strenuous expectations from professors. Honors seminars allow honors students to broaden their intellectual horizons regardless of the discipline in which they are majoring. Students may also fulfill honors requirements through experiential learning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/honors/academics.html|title=Page Title |publisher=uc.edu/honors|date= |accessdate=July 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Housing'''
*On-campus Honors housing provides honors students with a close-knit environment of like minded students. Honors housing provides students a network of students taking similar classes and begins fostering long-term relationships.

'''Organizations and activities'''
*The UC LeaderShape Institute is an opportunity for new honors students to spend six days creating a comprehensive and powerful vision for the future that defines a bold change for your community, group, cause, or organization and prepares them for their time at UC. Other ways to get involved in the Honors Program are the University Honors Association (UHA), Honor Societies, Mid-East Honors Association (MEHA), and the [[National Collegiate Honors Council]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/honors/activities.html|title=Page Title |publisher=uc.edu/honors|date= |accessdate=July 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==International activities==
The university has a large, diverse international student body, with approximately 2,500 students drawn from over 110 countries. The largest number of foreign students are from India and China with a significant number from France as well. Most international students study at the graduate level, although the university is now aggressively recruiting more talented students into undergraduate fields. To this end, UC is now creating a network of official representatives to assist interested students throughout the world.

A number of new international activities are positioning UC as a leading international innovator among US universities. UC is the first American university to benchmark its international student services, using an instrument known as the International Student Barometer (ISB). In the Fall 2006 survey, UC benchmarked with the highest overall international student satisfaction score among the 40 participating institutions. UC is also among the first universities to pilot the new Standards of Good Practice for Education Abroad, created by the [[Forum on education abroad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forumea.org|title=Forum on Education Abroad|publisher=Forumea.org|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International collaboration===
UC recently initiated a strategy of &quot;comprehensive engagement&quot; with key foreign institutions. The first of these with which a formal agreement was signed was Shandong University, of Jinan, China. In addition to developing a range of activities across their many colleges, the two universities have agreed to create a Joint Center for Urban Research, with offices on both campuses. UC's new COSMIC database (Cincinnati Online System for Managing International Collaboration) provides a view of its international relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/international/cosmic|title=UCosmic: UC Online System for Managing International Collaboration|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Study and co-op abroad===
UC has offered the opportunity to study or work abroad in over 80 countries since 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/webapps/ucosmic/students/abroad.aspx|title=UC Students Abroad|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are four types of study abroad opportunities at UC:

*Exchange programs: These are run in collaboration with UC's partner institutions. They offer short-term and long-term options and they cost the same amount of tuition as UC.
*External programs: These offer packaged costs, meaning students pay a general fee that typically includes; housing, tuition, meals, excursions, books, health insurance, on-site advising, and a host of other services.
*UC Faculty-Led programs: These are organized and led by the university's very own professors.
*College-specific programs: These offer students the opportunity to study abroad with their cohort. For example, the College of Business has a program in Nantes, France and the College of Nursing has a clinical program in Honduras.

The university offers additional opportunities such as international co-op, internships, research, and service learning abroad and can last anywhere from a week over spring break to a full academic year spent abroad. UC International is the office that oversees these programs and offers several scholarships and grants to help fund international experience as well. The programs offered can be program or college specific and apply directly towards degree completion, or used to satisfy area studies or minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/international/programs/students/programs.html|title=UC Students Abroad|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=July 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
The University of Cincinnati has a long history of both undergraduate and graduate research and in 2010 received the most research funding in the history of the university at more than $443 million, which is a 17% percent increase over 2009. Additionally, corporate research topped $15.2 million, an increase of 21% over the previous year. The university was first classified by The [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education]] as a &quot;Research 1&quot; university, since renamed &quot;RU/VH: Research Universities (very high research activity)&quot;. Recently, The Center at [[Arizona State University]] placed the University of Cincinnati as a &quot;Public University Ranking in the Top 20 public research universities in the United States&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mup.asu.edu/research.html|title=Research- The Center for Measuring University Performance|publisher=Mup.asu.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[The Chronicle of Higher Education]] named UC as a &quot;Research Heavyweight&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/news/NR.aspx?id=11785 |title=Chronicle of Higher Education: UC Identified as &quot;Research Heavyweight&quot;|publisher=UC.edu|date=April 22, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research at the University of Cincinnati is not just limited to labs. Students have the opportunity to take part in opportunities from medical research, to engineering labs, to creating sustainable technologies and designing buildings. UC has dozens of research centers across all 13 colleges at UC and offers research opportunities in more than 250 programs while faculty and students are awarded an average of 11 patents each year. As recently as April 2010, the University of Cincinnati has been mentioned as a possible candidate for the prestigious [[Association of American Universities]] and has secured more research funding in recent years than several current members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://chronicle.com/article/Chart-Many-Universities/65199|title=Chart: Many Universities Outside the AAU Receive More Research Dollars Than Its Members – Administration – The Chronicle of Higher Education|publisher=Chronicle.com|date=April 21, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ohio Centers of Excellence===
[[File:University of Cincinnati Solar Decathlon 2007.jpg|thumb|right|University of Cincinnati Solar Decathlon House 2007]]
The Ohio Centers of Excellence&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com/ |title=Ohio Centers of Excellence |publisher=Ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com |date=December 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; were designed to recognize the extensive research at universities in Ohio and encourage the development of new technologies and techniques to help retain and create Ohio jobs. Most recently the College-Conservatory of Music was honored for its excellence in Cultural &amp; Societal Transformation and is the only performing arts program in Ohio to earn the designation:
* Advanced Energy: Sustaining the Urban Environment&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com/page/sustaining-the-urban|title=Sustaining the Urban Environment – Ohio Centers of Excellence|publisher=Ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Advanced Transportation and Aerospace: Intelligent Air &amp; Space Vehicle Energy Systems&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com/page/intelligent-air-space-vehicle|title=Intelligent Air &amp; Space Vehicle Energy Systems – Ohio Centers of Excellence|publisher=Ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Biomedicine and Health Care: Transforming Health Care in the 21st Century&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com/page/transforming-health-care-in |title=Transforming Health Care in the 21st Century – Ohio Centers of Excellence |publisher=Ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com |date= |accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Cultural &amp; Societal Transformation: Music and Theater Arts&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com/page/music-and-theatre-arts|title=Cultural &amp; Societal Transformation – Ohio Centers of Excellence|publisher=Ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com|accessdate=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Cultural &amp; Societal Transformation: Center for Design and Innovation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/cincinnati/news/2011/10/20/university-of-cincinnati-gets-another.html|title=University of Cincinnati gets another Center of Excellence designation|publisher=Cincinnati Business Courier|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Enabling Technologies: Materials and Sensors, Nanoscale Sensor Technology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com/page/nanoscale-sensor-technology|title=Nanoscale Sensor Technology – Ohio Centers of Excellence|publisher=Ohiocentersofexcellence.ning.com|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Discoveries===
There have been several discoveries, inventions, accomplishments, and &quot;firsts&quot; at the University of Cincinnati and by its graduates.
{|
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
*'''First [[co-operative education]] program''' – [[Herman Schneider]]
*'''First oral [[polio vaccine]]''' – [[Albert Sabin]]
*'''First observations leading to the National Weather Service''' – [[Cleveland Abbe]]
*'''First antihistamine ([[Benadryl]])''' – [[George Rieveschl]]
*'''Designer of the [[Golden Gate Bridge]]''' - [[Joseph B. Strauss]]
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
*'''First electronic organ''' – Winston Kock
*'''First use of YAG laser to remove brain tumor'''
*'''First bachelor’s degree program in [[nursing]]'''
*'''First emergency medicine residency program'''
*'''First degree program offered via satellite'''
|}

===Libraries===
[[File:UC Langsam Library.jpg|thumb|Walter C. Langsam library, the main library at UC.]]The University of Cincinnati has 14 libraries, which are housed in 11 different facilities. This also includes the Digital Projects Department. The university library system has holdings of over 4 million volumes and 70,000 periodicals. The average circulation is around 451,815 items and 116,532 reference transactions. The University of Cincinnati is a member of the [[Association of Research Libraries]]. This is a collection of 123 libraries at research-intensive institutions in the US and Canada. UC is also part of [[OhioLINK]] which gives students access to libraries across 16 public universities, 23 community/technical colleges, and 49 private colleges with tens of millions of volumes at their fingertips.

*[[Walter C. Langsam Library]] (main library)
**Named after a former president of the university, Langsam Library is the main and largest library on campus. It offers a 24/7 computer lab named UCIT@Langsam which is available to students for computer, printing, copying and study use. It is also a [[Federal Depository Library Program]], allowing students free access to thousands of federal publications.
* Donald C. Harrison Health Sciences Library (formerly AIT&amp;L)
* Archives and Rare Books Library
* Business &amp; Economics Library (Langsam)[[File:VanWormerLibrary.jpeg|thumb|Van Wormer Library, the first library on campus]]
* Ralph E. Oesper Chemistry-Biology Library
* John Miller Burnam Classical Library
* Albino Gorno Memorial Music (CCM) Library
* Robert A. Deshon and Karl J. Schlachter Library for Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning (DAAP)
* College of Education, Criminal Justice, and Human Services
* College of Engineering and Applied Science (CEAS) Library
* Geology-Mathematics-Physics Library
* Robert S. Marx Law Library
* Henry R. Winkler Center for the History of the Health Professions
* Clermont College Library
* Raymond Walters College Library

==Athletics==
{{main|Cincinnati Bearcats}}
[[Image:Cincinnati Bearcats.svg|left|The current University of Cincinnati Bearcats logo.]]
The university competes in 18 [[Division I (NCAA)]] sports and its athletics teams are known as the &quot;[[Binturong|Bearcat]]s&quot;. Since July 1, 2005, they have been members of the [[Big East Conference]]. They were previously members of [[Conference USA]], of which they were a founding member, the [[Great Midwest Conference]], the Metro Conference, and the [[Mid-American Conference]], among others.

The university's most well-known rivalries are with [[Miami RedHawks|Miami University]], the [[Louisville Cardinals|University of Louisville]] and [[Xavier Musketeers|Xavier University]]. The Bearcats lost to their arch rival, the Musketeers, in 2010 but defeated them in 2011 and now hold a 48 to 30 lead in their annual contest, the [[Crosstown Shootout]]. UC is known for its rich tradition in basketball, but have enjoyed recent a successful decade in football which is the fifth oldest program in college football, having started collegiate play in 1885 in the first collegiate football game in the State of Ohio. Besides its varsity sports, the university also has a diverse number of intercollegiate club sports teams and has recently passed legislation to distinguish some clubs as Club Varsity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/sald/club_sports.html|title=Club Sports Board, University of Cincinnati|publisher=UC.edu|date=October 5, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some include the Wrestling club and the club Rowing team, which produced 2004 Olympian Kelly Salchow.

===National championships===
[[File:Sandy Koufax.jpg|thumb|180px|Hall of Famer [[Sandy Koufax]]]]
The university has four individual and six team championships. The Bearcats won the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship]] in 1961 and 1962, both times against [[Ohio State Buckeyes men's basketball|Ohio State]]. [[Charles Keating]] won the 1946 200m butterfly national title for UC as a member of the men's swimming team and most recently, [[Josh Schneider]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://magazine.uc.edu/issues/0810/sports.html|title=University of Cincinnati swimmer Josh Schneider won national championship. Next up? Olympics, University of Cincinnati|publisher=Magazine.uc.edu|date=August 18, 2010|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; did the same in the {{convert|50|yd|m|adj=on}} freestyle in 2010. In women's diving, Pat Evans (3 m Dive – 1989) and Becky Ruehl (10 m dive – 1996) have brought home titles for the Bearcats. The UC Dance Team has won 4 National Championships from 2004 through 2006 and again in 2009. They are the first team in UC history to ever capture three consecutive national titles. They remain one of the top dance programs in the country and are the winningest team in University of Cincinnati history. In 2009 the dance team was also selected to represent the United States of America in the first ever world dance championships where they won the gold medal in all three dance categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gobearcats.com/sports/c-dance/spec-rel/042509aaa.html|title=World Champions!|publisher=Gobearcats.com |date= |accessdate=July, 27 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:KevinYouklis.jpg|thumb|left|150px|All Star [[Kevin Youkilis]]]]

Notable athletics alumni include: [[Baseball]] Hall of Famers [[Sandy Koufax]] and [[Miller Huggins]]; Basketball Hall of Famers [[Oscar Robertson]] and [[Jack Twyman]]; [[Boston Red Sox]] first baseman [[Kevin Youkilis]]; [[Colorado Rapids]] forward [[Omar Cummings]]; [[Denver Nuggets]] forward [[Kenyon Martin]]; and tennis great [[Tony Trabert]].

===Student athletes===
In May 2006, Athletic Director (AD) Thomas introduced his vision for Bearcat Athletics, aptly titled CATAPULT. Thomas's five-year vision for UC's 18-sport intercollegiate program was launched six months after his hiring as AD. The plan focuses on three main initiatives: winning BIG EAST team championships, high-level academic achievement, and a comprehensive integration with the greater Cincinnati community. This action initiative tracks UC's 18 teams towards BIG EAST Championships in every sport within the next five years, encourages continued leadership by UC student-athletes in academics, and stresses community engagement. CATAPULT —an acronym for Championships, Academics, and Together— sets the goal that in the next five years UC will win a BIG EAST championship in every sport; UC's student-athletes will lead the general student body in graduation rate and grade point average; and UC's student-athletes and coaches will engage the Cincinnati community in service.
During the 2006 Fall Quarter, the first under the CATAPULT plan, UC's sports teams made major improvements in academics, achieving an overall grade point average (GPA) of 2.938. Additionally, 11 of the 17 squads posted team GPAs higher than the general UC student body GPA of 2.965.
*The Bearcat men's basketball team made the greatest improvement in the classroom, as its 2.875 team GPA a half a grade point better than that of last year's squad for Fall Quarter. Five Bearcats had GPAs of 3.0 or above with two student-athletes making the Dean's List.
*The Bearcat women's soccer team also earned a national Team Academic Award from the National Soccer Coaches Association of America for having a team GPA of at least 3.2 for the 2005–06 school year.
*A total of 247 student-athletes from UC's athletic squads were named to either the Bearcat or the Topcat Honor Roll. To qualify for the Bearcat Honor Roll, a student-athlete must have earned a grade point average between 3.0 and 3.49 for the quarter, while Topcat honorees must maintain between a 3.5 and a 4.0 GPA.

In 2006, four of the six UC fall sports teams improved their finish in the final BIG EAST conference standings over that of Fall 2005. The Bearcat teams collectively posted an improvement of three places. UC's men's soccer team became the first Bearcat squad to claim a BIG EAST title, winning the Red Division of the league's regular season race. Most recently, football won the Big East Championship in 2008 and 2009 and women's volleyball won the Big East regular season title in 2010.

In December 2007 [[ESPN]] stated that if academics and athletics Achievement were factored in, that Cincinnati team would be playing in the BCS Championship game. UC finished the season with a 10–3 record and a #17 national ranking. {{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Athletic facilities===
All of the athletic facilities (with the exception of Fifth Third Arena and Marge Schott Stadium) are open 24/7 for student use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gobearcats.com/facilities/cinn-facilities.html |title=University of Cincinnati Official Athletic Site |publisher=Gobearcats.com |date= |accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Richard E. Lindner Varsity Village
**Commissioned as part of UC's entrance into the Big East and serves as the centerpiece of UC's athletic facilities. It opened in 2006 and includes the Richard E. Lindner Center, which provides training, meeting, studying, and classroom space, as well as the George and Helen Smith Athletics Museum. Also located here is the Sheakley Lawn, which is reserved for students and club sports.
*[[Marge Schott Stadium]]
**Home to the UC Baseball team. It is named for the former owner of the [[Cincinnati Reds]], [[Marge Schott]], and replaced Johnny Bench Field. Shortly after this facility opened in 2006, it was named by Big East coaches and players as the best baseball facility in the conference.
*[[Armory Fieldhouse]]
[[File:NippertStadium.JPG|thumb|right|Nippert Stadium]]
**Home of UC indoor Track and Field teams and former home of the men's and women's Basketball teams
*[[Fifth Third Arena]]
**Home to UC Men's and Women's Basketball teams
*[[Nippert Stadium]]
**Home to UC's Football and Women's Lacrosse teams
*Ben and Dee Gettler Stadium
**Home to UC Men's and Women's Soccer and Track and Field teams
*Trabert-Talbert Tennis Center
**Home to UC Women's Tennis teams
*Keating Aquatics Center
**Home to UC Men's and Women's Swimming and Diving teams
*Sheakley Athletic Complex
**New facility constructed in 2010 that provides one full and one half football field field for varsity teams to practice on and after phase two finishes, a permanent home for the Women's Lacrosse team. From November to February a temporary bubble is inflated over the facility to provide teams practice space during cold months.

==Student life==
===Center for First Year Experience===
[[File:Mick &amp; Mack.jpg|thumb|right|Mick and Mack, stone lions at McMicken Hall]]
The Center for First-Year Experience provides leadership for each student's first-year experience and related academic program. The center serves as a resource for all the university’s undergraduate colleges and programs. This collaboration between UC colleges, academic programs, and students groups allow freshman to continue the transition from high school to college. The program is designed to help freshmen and their faculty to develop relationships that will continue and grow throughout their time at the University of Cincinnati.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.uc.edu/fye.html|title=Center for First Year Experience|accessdate=March 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Learning communities===
Many students at the University of Cincinnati have the opportunity to participate in learning communities. These are diverse groups of students and faculty in which 20–25 students have at least two classes together throughout their first year on campus. Students have the opportunity to join these based on their major or area of study. There are nearly 120 learning communities to chose from. They are offered in the following colleges: College of Allied Health Sciences, College of Business, College of Education, Criminal Justice, and Human Services, College of Engineering &amp; Applied Sciences, College of Nursing, and the McMicken College of Arts &amp; Sciences. Many of these groups have specialized courses taught by their academic adviser.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/fye/Learning_Communities/default.html|title=Learning Communities|accessdate=January 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:060429086 usoh uc tuc jpg.jpg|thumb|left|Students and Cincinnati residents gather for the American Cancer Society's Relay For Life event on UC's campus, one of the top Relay For Life events in the nation.]]

===Organizations===
Student Activities &amp; Leadership Development (SALD)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/sald.html|title=SALD, University of Cincinnati|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; oversees over 300 registered student organizations ranging from student government to religious organizations to student government. Housed in the Steger Student Life Center, the divisions overseeing these groups include Club Sports Board, Diversity Education, Greek Life, Leadership Development, Programming, RAPP, and Student Government. Additionally, there are several other Student Life Offices on campus, such as the African American Cultural &amp; Resource Center, Bearcat Bands (the largest and oldest student group at UC), Early Learning Center, Ethnic Programs &amp; Services, University Judicial Affairs, Resident Education &amp; Development, Wellness Center, and the Women's Center.

===Service learning===
Each year students at the University of Cincinnati log tens thousands of hours of community service on campus and in the surrounding city and communities. The University of Cincinnati was one of the first universities in the country to be classified by the [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] as a [[Community Engagement]] focused university and was one of only 35 research universities on this list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/descriptions/community_engagement.php?key=1213 |title=Community Engagement Elective Classification |publisher=carnegiefoundation.org |date= |accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the hundreds of events that take place annually, two of the largest and most successful student run community service events are the 18-hour Relay for Life and the 24-hour Cincinnati Dance Marathon. In support of the American Cancer Society’s education, advocacy and research programs, UC’s Relay for Life raised more than $126,000 in 2010 when over 1,800 students and 170+ teams participated by collecting pledges and walking the relay route through McMicken Commons on main campus. The event was recognized as one of the top 10 collegiate Relay for Life events in the nation and the largest Relay for Life in their region, which includes Ohio and Pennsylvania.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://magazine.uc.edu/issues/0411/philanthropy.html|title=Student philanthropy after hours ... way after hours|publisher=UC Magazine|accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Cincinnati Dance Marathon at UC has only been taking place in the Campus Recreation Center for a few years, in 2010 500 students danced all night to raise $13,500 in donations and then in 2011 raised nearly $24,000 for Cincinnati Children’s Hospital Medical Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cincinnatidm.org/?page_id=4|title=CDM Raises $23,300 for Cincinnati Children's medical Center|publisher=Cincinnatidm.org|accessdate=July 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Campus Green.jpg|thumb|left|Campus Green, which is green and activity space for students at UC. To the left is the Lindner College of Business and to the right are residence halls]]

===Fraternity and sorority life===
Fraternities and Sororities have been a part of the university since 1870. Currently, there are over 1,400 students participating in fraternities and sororities, which represents approximately 6% of the undergraduate population. 50 chapters have called UC home over the years, and currently includes 36 social [[fraternities]] and [[sororities]]: 19 Interfraternity Council fraternities, 8 Panhellenic Council sororities, 7 National Pan-Hellenic Council (3 fraternities and 4 sororities), and 2 non-affiliated (Delta Phi Lambda and Phi Sigma Rho&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/greeklife |title=Greek Life, University of Cincinnati |publisher=Uc.edu |date=2011-07-19 |accessdate=2011-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;) organizations.

===Student media===
There are several media outlets for university students. The student newspaper is ''The News Record'' and has been in production for more than 130 years, taking its current name in 1936.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.libraries.uc.edu/libraries/arb/archives/collections/newsrecord.html|title=News Record|publisher=Libraries.uc.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is an independent, student run newspaper and not attached to any academic program and therefore any student, regardless of program, is able to apply and work for the newspaper. There is a student-run radio station, named ''Bearcast'' that is housed in the College-Conservatory of Music on campus. The programming streams online as opposed to a traditional radio station and, like the News Record, is open to any student attending the university. There is also a television station called ''UCast''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ccm.uc.edu/emedia/major/activities/ucast.html|title=News Record|publisher=ccm.uc.edu|accessdate=July 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dining===
UC Housing &amp; Food Services&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/food.html|title=Food, University of Cincinnati|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=January 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; runs three award winning dining centers: Center Court, MarketPointe, and Stadium View Café. Meal plans are purchased at the beginning of each year and students living in residence halls are required to purchase one. There are also independent meal plans that students not living in residence halls may purchase. There is also a food court in the Tangeman University Center (student union) and many other restaurants and cafes are also available on campus.

UC is regularly recognized for excellent dining centers and restaurants and they have been awarded multiple awards since 2005. CenterCourt has received the greatest acclaims for UC dining, winning for best concept in 2007 and Grand Prize in 2006 [[National Association of College and University Food Services']] awards. CenterCourt and Market Pointe Dining Program received the honorable mention award in 2009 and Market Pointe@Siddal received an honorable mention in 2008 and a Silver Award in 2005. In 2011, UC's Mick and Mack's Contemporary Café, one of the full service restaurants on campus, received the bronze award with Brown University's Blue room. UC placed third in the category of 'Retail sales – Single concept'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsrecord.org/news/mick-and-mack-s-wins-national-award-1.2608948|title=Mick and Mack's wins national award|publisher=UC.edu|accessdate=August, 5 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Housing===
[[Image:UC Rec Center.jpg|thumb|Campus Recreation Center Housing, designed by [[Thom Mayne]], opened in 2006.]]
Nearly 4,000 students live on campus in eight residence halls that offer both traditional and suite style options. Students also have the option to live in themed housing which include (among others) honors, business, engineering, etc. specific floors. UC Housing &amp; Food Services&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uc.edu/uchousing.html |title=UC Housing, University of Cincinnati |publisher=Uc.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; manages eight undergraduate [[residence halls]]:
* Calhoun Hall
* Campus Recreation Center Housing (CRC is only available to students who are sophomores or older)
* Dabney Hall
* Daniels Hall
* Siddall Hall
* Jefferson Complex which consists of Schneider Hall and Turner Hall. (JCSH, JSTH)
* Stratford Heights (as of Summer 2009)
* Morgens Hall (after renovation, re-opening as undergraduate housing in Autumn 2013)
* Scioto Hall (scheduled to re-open in the future as undergraduate housing)

Two off-campus university-affiliated (but not university-managed) housing options were introduced in 2005: Stratford Heights and University Park Apartments. All leases in the Stratford Heights housing area have been terminated, and control of the housing complex reverted to University control as residence hall in Summer 2009.

==References==
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
  See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how
  to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags, and the template below
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.uc.edu/ Official website]
*[http://gobearcats.cstv.com/ Official Athletics website]
*[http://www.uc.edu/content/dam/uc/president/media/StrategicPlan_2010.pdf Strategic Plan, UC|2019, Accelerating our Transformation]
*[http://www.uc.edu/reportcard/sept10/2010reportcard.pdf 2010 Strategic Plan Report Card]
{{coord|39.132024|-84.515548|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}
{{University of Cincinnati}}
{{Colleges and universities in Ohio}}
{{Big East Conference}}
{{Public universities in Ohio}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Cincinnati, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Cincinnati| ]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Big East Conference schools]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1819]]
[[Category:Greater Cincinnati Consortium of Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Cincinnati, Ohio]]
[[Category:Urban 13 universities]]

[[cs:University of Cincinnati]]
[[de:University of Cincinnati]]
[[es:Universidad de Cincinnati]]
[[fa:دانشگاه سینسینتی]]
[[fr:Université de Cincinnati]]
[[id:Universitas Cincinnati]]
[[it:Università di Cincinnati]]
[[ja:シンシナティ大学]]
[[no:University of Cincinnati]]
[[ksh:Universität va Cincinnati]]
[[simple:University of Cincinnati]]
[[fi:Cincinnatin yliopisto]]
[[sv:University of Cincinnati]]
[[ta:சின்சினாட்டி பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยซินซินแนติ]]
[[zh:辛辛纳提大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
