<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="526702" ns="0" title="Gary Carter"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Gary Carter
|image=Gary Carter OC.JPG
|caption=Carter on the field prior to Game 1 of the 2008 [[Golden Baseball League]] Championship Series.
|position=[[Catcher]]
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{birth date and age|1954|4|8}}
|birth_place=[[Culver City, California]]
|debutdate=September 16
|debutyear=1974
|debutteam=Montreal Expos
|finaldate=September 27
|finalyear=1992
|finalteam=Montreal Expos
|stat1label=[[Batting average]]
|stat1value=.262
|stat2label=[[Home run]]s
|stat2value=324
|stat3label=[[Runs batted in]]
|stat3value=1,225
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[Montreal Expos]] ({{by|1974}}–{{by|1984}})
*[[New York Mets]] ({{by|1985}}–{{by|1989}})
*[[San Francisco Giants]] ({{by|1990}})
*[[Los Angeles Dodgers]] ({{by|1991}})
*[[Montreal Expos]] ({{by|1992}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1986}})
*11× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] ([[1975 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1975]], [[1979 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1979]], [[1980 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1980]], [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1981]], [[1982 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1982]], [[1983 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1983]], [[1984 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1984]], [[1985 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1985]], [[1986 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1986]], [[1987 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1987]], [[1988 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1988]])
*3× [[Gold Glove Award]] winner (1980, 1981, 1982)
*5× [[Silver Slugger Award]] winner (1981, 1982, 1984, 1985, 1986)
*2× [[MLB All-Star Game MVP]] (1981, 1984)
*1989 [[Roberto Clemente Award]]
*[[Montreal Expos#Retired numbers|Montreal Expos #8]] retired
|hofdate=2003
|hofvote=78.02%
}}
'''Gary Edmund Carter''' (born April 8, 1954), nicknamed '''&quot;Kid&quot;''' and '''&quot;Kid Carter&quot;''', is an [[United States|American]] former [[Major League Baseball]] [[catcher]]. During a 19-year baseball career, mostly with the [[Montreal Expos]] and the [[New York Mets]], Carter established himself as one of the premier catchers in the [[National League]], winning three [[Gold Glove]] awards and five [[Silver Slugger]] awards. He was inducted in the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum]] in 2003 wearing the Expos cap.

==Montreal Expos==
Carter was drafted by the [[Montreal Expos]] as a [[shortstop]] in the third round of the [[1972 Major League Baseball Draft]]. Prior to signing with the Expos, he had signed a letter of intent to play football at [[UCLA]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.garycarter.org/|title=The Official Website of Gary Carter |accessdate=2007-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carter recalled how he got his nickname, saying,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1992/09/20/sports/sports-of-the-times-another-september-for-kid.html?partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss|title=Sports of The Times; Another September For Kid|accessdate=1992-09-20 | work=The New York Times | first=Dave | last=Anderson | date=1992-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|I got that nickname my first [[spring training]] camp with the Expos in 1974. [[Tim Foli]], [[Ken Singleton]] and [[Mike Jorgensen]] started calling me Kid because I was trying to win every sprint. I was trying to hit every pitch out of the park.}}

===Rookie season===
The Expos converted Carter to a catcher in the minor leagues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historicbaseball.com/players/c/carter_gary.html|title=Historic Baseball|accessdate=2009-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1974, he clubbed 23 [[home run]]s and drove in 83 [[run (baseball)|runs]] for the Expos' triple-A affiliate, the [[Memphis Blues (baseball)|Memphis Blues]]. Following a September call-up, Carter made his major league debut in [[Jarry Park]] in [[Montreal]] in the second game of a [[Doubleheader (baseball)|double header]] against the [[New York Mets]] on September 16. Despite going 0-4 in that game, Carter's hitting improved dramatically after that. For the season, Carter batted .407 (11-27), hitting his first major league home run on September 28 against [[Steve Carlton]] in a 3-1 victory over the [[Philadelphia Phillies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/MON/MON197409280.shtml|title=Montreal Expos 3, Philadelphia Phillies 1|accessdate=1974-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carter split time between right field and catching his rookie season ({{by|1975}}), and was selected for the [[1975 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|National League All-Star team]] as a [[right fielder]]. Though he did not get an at bat during the game, he came into the game as a defensive replacement for [[Pete Rose]] in the ninth inning, and caught [[Rod Carew]]'s fly ball for the final out of the NL's 6-3 victory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/ALS/ALS197507150.shtml|title=1974 All-Star Game|accessdate=1975-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carter hit .270 with 17 home runs and 68 [[runs batted in]], and finished second to [[San Francisco Giants]] [[pitcher]] [[John Montefusco]] for the [[National League]] [[Rookie of the Year award]] and receiving [[The Sporting News Rookie of the Year Award]].

===Expos catcher===
Carter again split time in the outfield and behind the plate in {{by|1976}}, however, a broken finger limited him to just 91 games, in which he batted .219 with six home runs and 38 RBIs. For {{by|1977}}, new Expos manager [[Dick Williams]] gave promising young stars [[Warren Cromartie]], [[Ellis Valentine]] and [[Andre Dawson]] outfield jobs. On June 15, the Expos traded starting catcher [[Barry Foote]] to the Phillies, and Carter was given a permanent home behind the plate. He responded with 31 home runs and 84 RBIs.

In {{by|1980}}, Carter clubbed 29 home runs, drove in 101 runs, and earned the first of his three consecutive [[Gold Glove Award]]s. He finished second to [[third baseman]] [[Mike Schmidt]] in NL [[Most Valuable Player Award|MVP balloting]], whose Phillies took the [[National League East]] by one game over the Expos.

===First post season===
Carter caught [[Charlie Lea]]'s [[no-hitter]] on May 10, 1981,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1981/B05102MON1981.htm&lt;/ref&gt; during the first half of the [[1981 Major League Baseball strike|strike shortened season]]. Following the two month strike, the season resumed on Sunday, August 9, 1981 with the [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star Game]]. Carter was elected to start his first [[All Star Game]] over perennial NL starting catcher [[Johnny Bench]], and responded with two home runs and being named the game's [[MLB All-Star Game MVP|MVP]]. Carter was the fifth (and latest to date) player to hit two home runs in an All-Star Game, joining [[Arky Vaughan]] ({{by|1941}}), [[Ted Williams]] ({{by|1946}}), [[Al Rosen]] (1954) &amp; [[Willie McCovey]] ({{by|1969}}).

MLB team owners decided to split the 1981 season into two halves, with the first-place teams from each half in each division meeting in a best-of-five divisional playoff series. The four survivors would then move on to the two best-of-five [[League Championship Series]]. It was the first time that Major League Baseball used a split-season format since {{by|1892}}. The Expos won the NL East's second half with a 30-23 record.

In his first post season, Carter batted .421, clubbed two home runs and drove in six in the Expos' three games to two victory over the Phillies in the division series. Carter's average improved to .438 in the [[1981 National League Championship Series]], however, he had no home runs or RBIs, and his Expos lost to the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] in five games.

==={{by|1984}} season===
Carter hit a second inning home run in the [[1984 Major League Baseball All-Star Game]] to give the NL a 2-1 lead that they would not relinquish, and earn Carter his second All-Star game MVP award. Carter's 159 [[games played]], .294 [[batting average]], 175 [[hit (baseball)|hits]] and 290 [[total bases]] were all personal highs, as was his league leading 106 RBIs.

Despite these numbers from Carter, the [[1984 Montreal Expos season|1984 Expos]] finished fifth in the NL East with a 78-83 record. Needing to rebuild, the Expos traded Carter at the end of the season to the New York Mets for [[Hubie Brooks]], [[Mike Fitzgerald (catcher)|Mike Fitzgerald]], [[Herm Winningham]] and [[Floyd Youmans]].

==New York Mets==
In his first game as a Met on April 9, 1985, he hit a tenth inning [[walk-off home run]] off [[Neil Allen]] to give the Mets a 6-5 [[Opening Day]] victory over the [[St. Louis Cardinals]]. The Mets and Cardinals became embroiled in a heated rivalry atop the National League East, with Carter and [[first baseman]] [[Keith Hernandez]] leading the charge for the Mets. The season came down to the wire as the Mets won 98 games that season, however, they narrowly lost the division to a [[1985 St. Louis Cardinals season|Cardinals team]] that won 101 games. Carter clubbed a career high 32 home runs and drove in 100 runs his first season in New York. The Mets had three players finish in the top ten in NL MVP balloting that season ([[Dwight Gooden]] 4th, Carter 6th and Hernandez 8th). Meanwhile, the &quot;Redbirds&quot; placed four players in the top ten ([[Tommy Herr]] 5th, [[John Tudor (baseball)|John Tudor]] tied Hernandez at 8th, [[Jack Clark (baseball)|Jack Clark]] 10th and winner [[Willie McGee]]), as well as having the eleventh place finisher ([[Vince Coleman]]).

Something of a rivalry developed between the Mets and Expos as well as a result of Carter's departure from Montreal. On July 30, while facing the Expos at Shea, Montreal pitcher [[Bill Gullickson]] sailed a pitch over Carter's head in the fifth inning, which drew boos from the [[Shea Stadium]] crowd. Though he denied it was retaliation, Gooden did the same to Gullickson in the bottom of the inning. Interestingly, Carter caught the ball as if he knew exactly where the pitch was going to end up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1985-07-31/sports/sp-5428_1|title=National League Roundup - Gooden Improves Record to 16-3 With His 10th Straight Victory, 2-0|accessdate=1985-07-31 | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Dan | last=Hafner | date=1985-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1986 World Series Champions===
{{Main|1986 New York Mets season}}
Carter and the Mets would not be denied in {{by|1986}}, winning 108 games and taking the National League East convincingly by 21.5 games over the Phillies. The Mets won the [[1986 World Series]] in seven games over the [[Boston Red Sox]]. Carter batted .276 with nine RBIs in his first [[World Series]], and crushed two home runs over [[Fenway Park]]'s [[Green Monster]] in Game Four, giving him the distinction of being the only player to date to have hit two home runs in All-Star Game (1981) and two home runs in a World Series game.

Determined not to be the last out of the World Series, Carter started a two-out rally in the tenth inning of Game Six, coming around to score the first of three Mets runs that inning on a [[single (baseball)|single]] by [[Ray Knight]]. He also hit an eighth-inning [[sacrifice fly]] that tied the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NYN/NYN198610250.shtml|title=1986 World Series Game Six|accessdate=1986-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carter finished third on the NL MVP ballot in 1986.

===300 career home runs===
Carter batted only .235 in {{by|1987}}, and ended the season with 291 career home runs. He seemed determined to hit 300 career home run immediately, clubbing eight home runs by May 16 {{by|1988}}. However, it would take him until August 11 against the [[Chicago Cubs]] at [[Wrigley Field]] to reach the milestone. During his home run drought, Carter was named co-captain of the team with Hernandez, who had been named captain the previous season.

Carter ended the season with eleven home runs and 46 RBIs—both the lowest totals he'd put up in either category going back to his [[sophomore]] season in 1976. He also ended the season with 10,360 career putouts as a catcher, breaking [[Detroit Tigers]] catcher [[Bill Freehan]]'s career mark (9941).

The Mets won 100 games [[1988 New York Mets season|that season]], taking the NL East by fifteen games over the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]]. However, both Hernandez and Carter were in the twilights of their careers, and the heavily favored Mets lost to the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] in the [[1988 National League Championship Series]]. Carter batted only .183 in fifty games for the Mets in {{by|1989}}. On November 13, the Mets released Carter — a day after Keith Hernandez was granted free agency. Carter would play five seasons with the Mets hitting 89 home runs and driving in 349 runs.  His first hit as a Met was a double into the left field corner at Shea Stadium on Opening Day, 1985.  His last hit as a Met was a double into the left field corner at Shea Stadium on September 27, 1989.

==Return to Montreal==
After leaving the Mets, Carter enjoyed something of a resurgence in a platoon role with [[Terry Kennedy]] on the San Francisco Giants in {{by|1990}}, batting .254 with nine home runs. Carter found himself again in a pennant race in {{by|1991}}, signing with the Los Angeles Dodgers. His club finished 93-69, one game behind the [[Atlanta Braves]] in the [[National League West]].

At the end of the season, Carter returned to Montreal for his [[Swan song]] when the Expos selected Carter off waivers from the Dodgers. Carter was still nicknamed &quot;Kid&quot; by teammates despite his age of 38. The Expos 23-year-old [[second baseman]] [[Delino DeShields]] told Carter, &quot;I grew up on you, man. You were like [[Wheaties]] to me. Eat my Wheaties and watch Gary Carter play baseball.&quot; 37 games into the {{by|1992}} season, the Expos fired manager [[Tom Runnells]] and replaced him with [[Felipe Alou]]. With Alou at the helm, the Expos went 70-55 and finished second behind the Pittsburgh Pirates in the National League East.

&lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot;
|Seasons
|Games
|Games caught
|AB
|Runs
|Hits
|2B
|3B
|HR
|RBI
|SB
|BB
|SO
|HBP
|Avg.
|Slg.
|-
|19
|2295
|2056
|7971
|1025
|2092
|371
|31
|324
|1225
|39
|848
|997
|68
|.262
|.439
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
Carter had a .991 [[fielding percentage]] as a catcher and 11,785 career putouts. He ranks sixth all-time in career home runs by a catcher with 298.

==Post-playing career==
After his retirement, Carter served as an [[List of Florida Marlins broadcasters|analyst]] for [[Florida Marlins]] television broadcasts from 1993-1996. He appeared in the movie ''[[The Last Home Run]]'' which was filmed in {{by|1996}} and released in {{by|1998}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0158719/|title=The Internet Movie Database|accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hall of Fame===
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = Carter 8.png
|Name   = Gary Carter
|Number = 8
|Team   = Montreal Expos
|Year   = 2003
|}}
Carter was inducted into the [[New York Mets Hall of Fame]] in {{by|2001}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newyork.mets.mlb.com/nym/history/nym_history_halloffame.jsp|title=Mets Hall of Fame|accessdate=2009-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{by|2003}}, Carter was elected into the [[Canadian Baseball Hall of Fame]] along with [[Kirk McCaskill]], and his number eight was retired by the Expos (and is tacitly recognized on the facade of [[Nationals Park]]).

In his sixth year on the ballot, Gary Carter was elected to the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] along with [[Eddie Murray]] on January 7, 2003. Carter had originally requested if he could have the plaque as half an Expo and half a Met, and though the media took it as one of his jokes, it was a legitimate debate as to with which team he would be associated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/08/sports/sports-of-the-times-put-an-expos-cap-on-carter-s-plaque.html?sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=1|title=Sports of The Times; Put an Expos Cap On Carter's Plaque|accessdate=2003-01-08 | work=The New York Times | first=George | last=Vecsey | authorlink=George Vecsey | date=2003-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carter himself had expressed a preference to be inducted as an Expo during his final season; however, given the uncertainty of the Expo franchise, and Carter's having worked for the Mets organization since retiring as a player, winning his only World Series title with the Mets, and becoming a media celebrity during his stint in New York, Carter had changed his mind by the time the moment arrived, and expressed a preference toward the Mets. The final decision rested with the Hall of Fame, and Hall president [[Dale Petroskey]] declared that Carter's achievements with the Expos over twelve season had earned his induction, whereas his play during his five seasons with the Mets by itself would not have.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20030116&amp;content_id=191990&amp;vkey=news_mlb&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=null|title=Kid catches Cooperstown spotlight: Carter 'happy' to go into Hall as an Expo|accessdate=2003-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mets fans pointed to the induction of [[Reggie Jackson]] with a [[New York Yankees]] cap, despite playing the majority of his career with the [[Oakland A's]] as precedent, but Carter ultimately was inducted with the Expos cap.  At the induction ceremony, Carter spoke a few words of French, thanking fans in Montreal for the great honor and pleasure of playing in that city.

After the Expos moved to Washington, D.C. following the {{by|2004}} season, a banner displaying Carter's number along with those of Andre Dawson, [[Tim Raines]] and [[Rusty Staub]] was hung from the rafters at the [[Bell Centre]], home of the [[National Hockey League|NHL's]] [[Montreal Canadiens]]. While the Mets have not retired number eight, it has remained unused since Carter's election to the Hall of Fame.

===Coaching===
Carter was named Gulf Coast League Manager of the Year his first season managing the [[Gulf Coast Mets]] in {{by|2005}}. A year later, he was promoted to the A-level [[St. Lucie Mets]], and guided his team to the {{by|2006}} [[Florida State League]] championship, again earning Manager of the Year honors. In recent years, Carter has been criticized, most notably by former co-captain Keith Hernandez, for twice openly campaigning for the Mets' managerial position while it was still occupied by incumbents [[Art Howe]] in 2004, and in {{by|2008}} [[Willie Randolph]].

In 2008, he managed the [[Orange County Flyers]] of the [[Golden Baseball League]], and again guided his team to the GBL Championship and was named Manager of the Year.

For the following season Carter was named manager of the [[Long Island Ducks]] of the independent [[Atlantic League of Professional Baseball]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liducks.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=coach&amp;coachId=11|title=Long Island Ducks|accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ducks won the 2009 second half Liberty Division title, however, they were defeated by the [[Southern Maryland Blue Crabs]] in the Liberty Division playoffs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liducks.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=gameRecaps&amp;newsID=1666|title=Ducks Fight to the End|accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next season Carter was named head baseball coach for the [[NCAA Division II]] [[Palm Beach Atlantic University]] Sailfish.

==Personal life==
Carter is an alumnus of [[Sunny Hills High School]] in [[Fullerton, CA]].

Carter has been married to his wife, Sandy, since 1975. They have three children,Christy, Kimmy and D.J.; and three grandchildren. They reside in [[Palm Beach Gardens, Florida]].

His daughter Kimmy is the head [[softball]] coach at Palm Beach Atlantic&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pba.edu/media/news-releases/carter-baseball.cfm|title=Hall-of-Fame Catcher Gary Carter to Lead Sailfish Baseball|accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was a  softball catcher for [[Florida State Seminoles|Florida State]] from {{by|1999}}-{{by|2002}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seminoles.com/sports/w-softbl/mtt/carter_kimmy00.html|title=Official Athletic Site of Florida State University|accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Carter also has been a very active philanthropist. Through The Gary Carter Foundation, of which Carter is the president, Carter and his staff support 8 Title I schools in Palm Beach County whose students live in poverty. Typically, these schools have 90% or more students eligible for free or reduced lunches. The Foundation seeks to &quot;better the physical, mental and spiritual well being of children.&quot; To accomplish this, they advocate &quot;school literacy by encouraging use of the Reading Counts Program, a program that exists in the Palm Beach County School District.&quot;

Since its inception, The Gary Carter Foundation has placed over $622,000 toward charitable purposes, including $366,000 to local elementary schools for their reading programs.

In May 2011, Carter was diagnosed with four [[malignant]] tumors in his brain after complaining of headaches and forgetfulness. Doctors confirmed that he has Stage 4 [[glioblastoma]], an extremely aggressive cancer. Doctors say that it is inoperable and Carter will undergo other treatment methods to shrink his tumor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hardballtalk.nbcsports.com/2011/05/21/gary-carter-diagnosed-with-small-tumors-on-his-brain/|title=Gary Carter diagnosed with small tumors on his brain|accessdate=2011-05-21|date=2011-05-21|author=D.J. Short}}{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/baseball/mets/2011/05/27/2011-05-27_doctors_tell_new_york_mets_great_gary_carter_that_brain_tumors_are_likely_malign.html|title=Doctors tell New York Mets great Gary Carter that brain tumors are likely malignant|accessdate=2011-05-27|date=2011-05-27|author=Bill Madden|work=Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/new-york/mlb/news/story?id=6613002|title=Gary Carter has glioblastoma|publisher=sports.espn.go.com|date=2011-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A special web site has been set up where fans can leave messages of support for Carter and his family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://getwellgary.mlblogs.com/2011/06/02/24/|title=The WELL WISHES FOR GARY Official Greeting Card|accessdate=2011-06-06|date=2011-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Canadian Baseball Hall of Fame]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball retired numbers]]
*[[List of top 300 Major League Baseball home run hitters]]
*[[List of major league players with 2,000 hits]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 runs]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 RBI]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball RBI champions]]
*[[DHL Hometown Heroes]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{bbhof|carter-gary}}
{{baseballstats |mlb=112061|espn=56|br=c/cartega01|fangraphs=1002015|cube=gary-carter}}
*[http://www.leukemia-lymphoma.org/hm_lls Leukemia &amp; Lymphoma Society]
*[http://www.garycarter.org/home.html The Official Website of the Gary Carter Foundation]
*[http://www.ultimatemets.com/profile.php?PlayerCode=0375 Ultimate Mets Database: Gary Carter]

{{S-start}}
{{s-ach}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Dale Murphy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Willie McGee]] | title = [[Player of the Month|National League Player of the Month]]| years = September 1980&lt;br&gt;September 1985 | after = [[Dave Concepción]]&lt;br&gt;[[Johnny Ray]]}}
{{Succession box| title=[[Major League Baseball All-Star Game]]&lt;br&gt; Most Valuable Player| before= [[Ken Griffey, Sr.]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fred Lynn]] | years=1981&lt;br&gt;1984 | after= [[Dave Concepción]]&lt;br&gt;[[LaMarr Hoyt]]}}
{{Succession box| title=[[List of Major League Baseball RBI champions|National League RBI Champion]] | before= [[Dale Murphy]]| years=1984&lt;br&gt;(with [[Mike Schmidt]]) | after= [[Dave Parker]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{New York Mets Hall of Fame}}
{{NL C Gold Glove Award}}
{{NL C Silver Slugger Award}}
{{Major League Baseball All-Star Game MVPs}}
{{1986 New York Mets}}
{{Roberto Clemente Award}}
{{2003 Baseball HOF}}
{{Baseball Hall of Fame catchers}}
{{Expos Retired Numbers}}
{{Florida Sports Hall of Fame}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Carter, Gary
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1954-04-08
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Culver City, California
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Carter, Gary}}
[[Category:1954 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American Christians]]
[[Category:American expatriate baseball people in Canada]]
[[Category:Baseball players from California]]
[[Category:Canadian Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Cocoa Expos players]]
[[Category:Florida Marlins broadcasters]]
[[Category:Gold Glove Award winners]]
[[Category:Los Angeles Dodgers players]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball All-Star Game MVPs]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball announcers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball catchers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers]]
[[Category:Memphis Blues players]]
[[Category:Montreal Expos broadcasters]]
[[Category:Montreal Expos players]]
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:National League RBI champions]]
[[Category:New York Mets players]]
[[Category:Peninsula Whips players]]
[[Category:Québec Carnavals players]]
[[Category:San Francisco Giants players]]
[[Category:Tidewater Tides players]]
[[Category:West Palm Beach Expos players]]

[[fr:Gary Carter]]
[[ja:ゲーリー・カーター]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
