<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="530869" ns="0" title="Youngstown State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University |
name = Youngstown State University |
image =  [[File:Youngstown State University wm.svg|200px]]|
image size = 172px
caption = The Seal of Youngstown State University
motto = ''Animus Liberatus'' ('The mind freed', or 'The spirit freed') |
established = 1908 |
|city={{flagicon|USA}} [[Youngstown, Ohio|Youngstown]]
|state=[[Ohio]]
|country=[[United States|U.S.]] |
campus = {{convert|140|acre|km2}} |
athletics = [[NCAA Division I]] |
undergrad = 11,803 (Fall 2010)|
postgrad = 3,391 (Fall 2010)|
faculty = 2,105 (Fall, 2005, all campuses)|
mascot =   Pete the Penguin|
colors = Red and White|
website = [http://www.ysu.edu/ www.ysu.edu] |
image =  [[File:Youngstown State University wm.svg|200px]]|
}}

'''Youngstown State University''', founded in 1908, is an urban research [[university]] located in [[Youngstown, Ohio|Youngstown]], [[Ohio]], [[United States]].  As of fall 2010, there were 15,194&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vindy.com/news/2010/sep/08/ysu-enrollment-is-at-highest-point-since/?newswatch &quot;YSU enrollment is at highest point since 1990&quot;], ''The Vindicator'', 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; students and a student-faculty ratio of 19:1. It is recognized as being one of the premier schools in the country, comparable to Ivy League schools.  The fall 2010 enrollment figure is the highest since 1990, when the number of students on campus was 15,454. Records show that 11,803 of the students are undergraduates.  Beyond its current student body, YSU claims more than 84,000 alumni.

==History==
The university's origins trace back to 1908, when the local branch of the [[YMCA]] established a school of law within the Youngstown Association School.&lt;ref name=&quot;vindy-10-14-07&quot;&gt;{{cite news
  | first = Harold
  | last = Gwin
  | title = Unofficial historian: Y gave YSU its start
  | work = The Vindicator
  | page = B-1
  | date = October 14, 2007
  | accessdate = 2007-10-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1921, the school became known as the '''Youngstown Institute of Technology''' and offered its first evening courses.&lt;ref name=&quot;vindy-10-14-07&quot;/&gt; In 1928, a year after establishing the College of Arts and Sciences, the institute once again changed its name to '''Youngstown College'''.  In 1955, Youngstown College was renamed as '''Youngstown University''', an indication of the school's broadening curriculum.(note: A private for profit Youngstown College was formed in 1987 and had no affiliation with YSU. The college closed its doors in mid 2000 due to financial issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;vindy-10-14-07&quot;/&gt;)

On September 1, 1967, after becoming a public institution, Youngstown University became officially known as '''Youngstown State University'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;vindy-10-14-07&quot;/&gt;  The following spring, YSU opened a Graduate School and College of Applied Science and Technology. In 1974, the College of Fine and Performing Arts was established.

===Presidents===
* Dr. Howard W. Jones (1931–1966)
* Dr. Albert L. Pugsley (1966–1973)
* Dr. John J. Coffelt (1973–1984)
* Dr. Neil D. Humphrey (1984–1992)
* Dr. Leslie H. Cochran (1992–2000)
* Dr. David C. Sweet (2000—2010)
* Dr. Cynthia Anderson (2010— )

==Statistics==
As of fall 2010, the student body totaled 15,194. YSU has approximately 2,100 full and part-time employees, and 426 full-time faculty with 543 part-time faculty.  165 faculty members boast full-professor rank, with 79% of the instructors holding [[doctorate]]s or [[terminal degree]]s. The university boasts a student to faculty ratio of 19:1.

Tuition for undergraduate students living in Ohio is $7,199, $7,399 for undergraduate students coming from western Pennsylvania (Allegheny, Beaver, Butler, Crawford, Erie, Lawrence, Mercer, Venango, PA), $9,891 for undergraduate students from the regional service area (Chautauqua, NY; Armstrong, Clarion, Fayette, Forest, Greene, Indiana, Jefferson, Warren, Washington, and Westmoreland, PA; Brooke, Hancock, Marshall, and Ohio, WV), and $12,871 for all other out-of-state undergraduate students, including international students. Graduate tuition is $7,337/academic year for Ohio residents, while all other graduate students (including international students) pay just $150 per academic year ($8.34 per credit hour) in addition to the in-state tuition. Room and board cost an additional $7,600. YSU will often note that these tuitions are the lowest of any public university in Ohio.
[[Image:Jones maag.jpg|thumb|right|250 px|Area between Jones Hall and Maag Library (on right)]]YSU is primarily a commuter school, with most students living at home or in residence off campus, but approximately 1,000 students live in residence halls on campus. Another 400 live in the University Courtyard apartment complexes just off campus. About 1.5% of the student body are international students from approximately 45 countries.

YSU is currently trying to get more students to live on campus, with initiatives such as mandatory on-campus housing for students in the Leslie H. Cochran University Scholars program, which is Youngstown State's full ride academic scholarship program.  One of the goals for the university's centennial in 2008 is to have 20 percent of the student body living on campus.

There are over 500,000 volumes at the campus' '''William F. Maag Library''', and participation in the [[OhioLINK]] program gives access to the collections of 84 other Ohio institutions.  The Wilcox Curriculum Resource Center in '''Beeghly Hall''' complements the resources available at Maag.

YSU is participating in the [[Youngstown Early College]] program, through which students from the [[Youngstown City School District]] can take courses for college credit while in high school. The program is in its fifth year, and has approximately 290 students in the ninth through twelfth grades. Youngstown Early college has also had their first graduating class in Spring 2008. YSU is currently phasing out its affiliation with Youngstown Early College, with [[Eastern Gateway Community College]] taking over full operations away from YSU by 2013.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wkbn.com/content/news/local/story/Compromise-Gives-New-Life-to-Youngstown-Early/XHpudYM0SkKWhBxeuJMMNg.cspx Compromise Gives New Life to Youngstown Early College - WKBN - 27 First News - Local News - Youngstown, Warren, Columbiana, Ohio - Sharon, Pennsylvania&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
YSU lies on a {{convert|140|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus just north of [[downtown Youngstown]].  Although it is not located near any outstanding geographical features, that has not stopped Youngstown State's campus from being noted for its landscaping, which is dissimilar from that of many other urban universities.  YSU's geographical center has a park-like atmosphere, featuring a rather-hilly terrain and a variety of trees and plant life, as well as tables and chairs that surround a campus fountain.

Most buildings on campus have been built within the last half-century, making them newer than most buildings in downtown Youngstown, where most buildings were constructed before the [[Great Depression]].

===Buildings===
[[Image:JonesHall.jpg|thumb|right|230 px|Jones Hall]]
Jones Hall, often the building that welcomes people coming onto the YSU campus, is also one of the campus's oldest buildings, having been built in 1931, when YSU was known as Youngstown College.  Its history as the &quot;main building&quot; of the campus continues today, as it is perhaps the best-known and most photographed building of the whole campus.  The building was renamed Jones Hall in honor of the institutions first president, Dr. Howard Jones.  Today, the building is used as mainly administrative office space.

The Rayen College of Engineering and Technology is housed in Moser Hall, completed in 1967. The university's geological and environmental sciences department shares the space, and also sponsor the Clarence R. Smith Mineral Museum.

[[Image:AndrewsCtr.jpg|thumb|left|175 px| Andrews Wellness and Recreation Center]]
The newer addition to YSU is the '''Andrews Wellness and Recreation Center'''.  Completed in time for the fall 2005 semester, the Andrews Center gave YSU a complete gym facility, as well as a climbing wall and racquetball courts.

'''Bliss Hall''', completed in 1977 and featuring two auditoriums, is the home of the College of Fine and Performing Arts, including the Departments of Art, Communication (including communication studies and telecommunication studies), Theater &amp; Dance, and the [[Dana School of Music]]. Next door to Bliss Hall is the [[McDonough Museum of Art]], YSU's University Art Museum and the Mahoning Valley's center for contemporary art.  The Museum has regular changing exhibitions by regional, national and international artists and provides public access to the work of students, faculty and alumni from the Department of Art.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://mcdonoughmuseum.ysu.edu/htmlpgs/information.html |title = McDonough Museum of Art |publisher=Youngstown State University |accessdate = 28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Beeghly Hall''' was completed in 1998 at a cost of $14 million. The Beeghly College of Education resides there, and it also hosts several programs open to the community, such as the Community Counseling Center.  Beeghly, which is located away from the campus proper, is planned to be linked to the rest of the campus through a main pedestrian pathway, a plan that ran into trouble.&lt;ref&gt;Gwin, Harold. [http://www.vindy.com/content/local_regional/304323948627028.php &quot;Some plan to fight YSU and city&quot;], ''The Vindicator'', 2 April 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:YSUArbys.jpg|thumb|right|180px|[[Arby's]] location inside Kilcawley Center. Arby's originated in nearby [[Boardman, Ohio|Boardman]] in 1964 and maintains a major presence in the Mahoning Valley.]]
Kilcawley Center is primarily a resource and community center on campus. It features reading and study rooms, computer labs, a copying center, YSU's bookstore, a variety of restaurants (including a full-service [[Arby's]] and a [[KFC|KFC Express]]), and many student-affairs offices. There are also many meeting and seminar rooms, which can be rented out for events by the community.

'''Williamson College of Business Administration''' is the newest building on campus.  It was completed for Fall semester 2010.  It houses all of the business classrooms and offices.  It was previously housed in the Lincoln Building.  The building itself has LEED standard, making it a green build.  It was one of the most expensive additions to campus, with a large portion of the funding coming from donations.  The building is off of Rayen Ave and was built to purposely connect downtown businesses to the college and to the campus core.  Recently access to the building improved when the Hazel Street Extension opened creating access for vehicle and pedestrian traffic and better connecting the central business district to the university.

YSU has six housing facilities. '''Lyden House''', completed in 1990, and '''Cafaro House''' residential honors facility, completed in 1995, can accommodate a combined 574 students.  '''Christman Dining Commons''', YSU's main residential dining hall, is located in the Anne K. Christman Campus Green between these buildings.  '''Kilcawley House''' is attached to '''Kilcawley Center''' in the middle of campus. '''Wick House''' and '''Weller House''', off Wick Avenue, also houses a small number of students in an apartment setting.  The University Courtyard Apartments, on the east side of the campus (behind '''Bliss Hall'''), were built in 2004.  These are commonly known as '''the Courtyards'''.  They are actual apartments and are not affiliated with housing services at YSU, instead they are managed by an outside company, Ambling Leasing.  '''Buechner Hall''' is an independently owned and operated women's residence hall located on Bryson Street and operated by the Beuchner Foundation. The '''Flats at Wick''', also a privately owned and operated apartments were built and opened in Fall of 2010 on the corner of Madison Ave and Elm Street.  

Other buildings on campus include:
*'''Meshel Hall''' (Department of Computer Science and Information Systems)
*'''Fedor Hall''' (housing student newspaper ''The Jambar'', student magazine ''The Yo'', student literary magazine ''The Penguin Review'', the Rich Center for Autism, and the Youngstown Early College)
*'''Cushwa Hall''' (College of Health and Human Services, WYSU-FM)
*'''Lincoln Hall''' (Mathematics, part of STEM)
*'''Phelps Building''' (Geography, Urban and Regional Studies)
*'''Maag Library'''
*'''Tod Hall''' (administrative offices)
*'''DeBartolo Hall''' (College of Liberal Arts and Social Sciences, a.k.a. CLASS)
*'''Sweeney Hall''' (Undergraduate Admissions)
*'''the E.J. Salata Complex''' (maintenance services)
*'''Clingan-Waddell Hall''' (YSU Police Department)
*'''Alumni House''' (Alumni and Events Management and The YSU Foundation); the oldest building on campus
*'''Lincoln Building''' (Department of Mathematics &amp; Statistics)

Current building projects include the Wick Pollock Inn located on Wick Avenue next to Bliss Hall.&lt;ref&gt;Torisk, E. (2009, March 24). &quot;Preserving Pollock: University advances revitalization plan for historic structure.&quot; ''The Jambar'', News: 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ward Beecher Planetarium==
The university's planetarium, located in '''Ward Beecher Hall''', opened in 1967 and was recently renovated. The $750,000 upgrade included new seats (145), a SciDome fulldome video projector from Spitz, Inc., as well as a Chronos star projector from GOTO. The star projector, which replicates the night sky onto the planetarium's {{convert|40|ft|m|sing=on}} diameter dome, cost $489,000.

The planetarium is the location of the introductory astronomy courses at YSU, which registers almost 1,000 students every year. It has housed over 500,000 students, as well as 750,000 visitors as of 2007. Organized shows are available for groups during the week, and scheduled shows available Friday and Saturday evenings (with a show geared toward a younger crowd Saturday afternoons). All shows are free of charge. For a schedule, go to [http://www.wbplanetarium.org their website].

==Academics==
The University comprises the following colleges as of the Summer 2007 academic reorganization:
*[http://www.as.ysu.edu/ The College of Liberal Arts and Social Sciences (a.k.a. CLASS)]
*[http://www.coe.ysu.edu/ The Beeghly College of Education]
*[http://stem.ysu.edu/ The College of Science, Technology, Engineering &amp; Mathematics (a.k.a. STEM)]
*[http://www.fpa.ysu.edu/ The College of Fine and Performing Arts]
*[http://bchhs.ysu.edu/ The Bitonte College of Health and Human Services]
*[http://www.wcba.ysu.edu/ The Williamson College of Business Administration]
*[http://www.ysu.edu/GradSchool/index.shtml The School of Graduate Studies]

YSU offers doctoral degrees in educational leadership and physical therapy, as well as a doctorate in mathematics in cooperation with [[Rhodes University]].  Together with the [[University of Akron]] and [[Kent State University]], YSU sponsors the [[Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine|Northeastern Ohio Universities College Of Medicine (NEOUCOM)]], a BS-MD program. YSU engineering students may pursue [[doctorate|doctoral]] studies in cooperation with the University of Akron and [[Cleveland State University]]. In addition, YSU has 35 masters programs and over 100 undergraduate majors.

'''The Dana School of Music''' at Youngstown State University was deemed an &quot;All-[[Steinway &amp; Sons|Steinway]]&quot; school in 2004. The Dana School of Music is one of the oldest non-conservatory schools of music in the United States.{{Citation needed|year=September 2008|date=February 2011}} It is housed in '''Bliss Hall'''.  Additionally, the Youngstown State University Symphonic Wind Ensemble performed in March 2005 at New York City's [[Carnegie Hall]].  The ensemble's performance was highly praised, and they received a standing ovation.

Youngstown State University is also home to the Center for Working Class Studies and offers a Regional and [[American Studies]] program, which was the first of its kind in the United States.  The school assisted the [[University of Chicago]] in developing a similar program.  The center is operated by John Russo and Sherry Lee Linkon.

YSU is also known as one of the few universities to have [[Professor|college professors]], rather than [[Teaching assistant|graduate assistants]], directly teach undergraduate students, as it is more common at large universities to use graduate assistants.{{Citation needed|reason=This seems biased and overstated|date=September 2011}} This is because YSU has few doctoral programs and a relatively high standard teaching load (four courses per semester).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ysu.edu/institutional-research/perfreport.doc&lt;/ref&gt; In most colleges, graduate assistants teach courses to undergraduate students.{{Citation needed|reason=&quot;most colleges?&quot; Not true|date=September 2011}} while full-time professors focus on graduate courses, limiting their direct involvement in undergraduate education to lecturing in large sections of introductory courses and supervising graduate assistants, and by grading exams (especially [[Final examination|final exams]]) and [[term paper]]s if those classes necessitate it.

About one-third of the classes, including all of the senior capstone courses for each major, utilize [[e-learning]] through [[Blackboard Inc.|Blackboard]]. Before using Blackboard, YSU utilized [[WebCT]], which Blackboard acquired in 2006 but didn't convert to its own software until 2010, with YSU running both programs during the Spring 2010 semester.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.thejambar.com/media/storage/paper324/news/2010/03/18/News/Webct.To.Convert.To.Blackboard.By.July-3891570.shtml WebCT to convert to Blackboard by July - News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Both WebCT and Blackboard have been criticized by YSU students and professors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.thejambar.com/media/storage/paper324/news/2010/09/14/News/Students.Staff.Struggle.With.Blackboard-3930910.shtml Students, staff struggle with Blackboard - News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Departments=={{news release section}}
YSU has Departments that cover most of the topics one would expect to see at a university of its type.{{By whom|date=September 2011}} Some cover single academic disciplines/programs while others serve as administrative units to consolidate several related disciplines and programs. Some of the larger Departments have over a dozen full-time faculty and support both undergraduate and graduate degrees while others are much smaller and only participate in undergraduate programs. Each of the Departments offers strong educational opportunities and most offer many research and service activities to their students. Contributions have been growing rapidly, such that many of the departments, (e.g., English, Chemistry, Mathematics &amp; Statistics) are at or near the top of national rankings for departments of their type.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} This has resulted in the growth in external funding to YSU from organizations such as the National Science Foundation that has increased consistently at a double digit rate for the last decade and a half(amongst the strongest growth trajectory in the country) and total external funding to support these student-centered companies now exceeds twelve million dollars annually.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

==Youngstown Institute of Software and Design==
As of 2011, Youngstown State University has added the YIS program to host and complement software related startup companies in the Youngstown metro area.  The local business incubator encourages an entrepreneurial approach to education. 

The YIS program has launched its own Licence agreement students and prospective companies can use to design, develop and distribute their products.  This is known as the Youngstown Institute of Software License.

In June 2011, at the regional venture capital estate and presentation show, it was announced that over 10 billion in seed money will be given out over the next 5 years.  Interested parties can contact the YSU Computer Science Department for upcoming events.

==Athletics==
{{main|Youngstown State Penguins}}

==Greek life==
Youngstown State University is home to 10 fraternities and 7 sororities. They are:

'''Interfraternity Council'''

*[[Alpha Phi Delta]]
*[[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]]
*[[Phi Kappa Tau]]
*[[Sigma Tau Gamma]]
*[[Sigma Chi]]
*[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]

'''Panhellenic Conference'''

*[[Alpha Omicron Pi]]
*[[Zeta Tau Alpha]]
*[[Delta Zeta]]
*[[Alpha Xi Delta]]

'''Pan-Hellenic Council'''

Fraternities:
*[[Iota Phi Theta]]
*[[Kappa Alpha Psi]]
*[[Omega Psi Phi]]

Sororities:
*[[Alpha Kappa Alpha]]
*[[Delta Sigma Theta]]
*[[Zeta Phi Beta]]

==Labor relations==
Labor Unions are very active at YSU and include most non-administrative faculty and staff on campus. In August 2005, just before the start of the 2005–06 academic year, two of four campus unions were on strike. Following the conclusion of the strike, relations have remained strained, with some faculty and staff calling for resignation of YSU President David Sweet in May 2007.&lt;ref&gt;Gwin, Harold. [http://www.vindy.com/content/local_regional/305063643397964.php &quot;60 YSU workers call for Pres. Sweet to resign&quot;], ''[[Youngstown Vindicator]]'', 11 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Others on campus thought some individuals on both sides were engaged in less than professional behaviors. Due to the animosity between the parties, a special committee was set up to examine labor relations. This committee recommended that the negotiations teams for all sides be replaced before the next round of contract negotiations. Subsequent to these recommendations the Vice President for Administration was replaced as well as the Executive Director of Human Resources.

Relations have improved since that time and are now typical of what one would expect of a unionized campus in a region that has always been at the center of US union activism.

==Famous alumni==
*[[Tony Aiello]], former National Football League player, Brooklyn Tigers and Detroit Lions
*[[Dr. Cindy Anderson]], First female president of Youngstown State University
*[[Thomas Bopp]], [[astronomer]]; co-discoverer of [[Comet Hale-Bopp]]
*[[Al Campana]], former National Football League running back, Chicago Bears
*[[Billy Clapper]], college basketball head coach, Penn State Altoona
*[[Craig Cotton]], former National Football League tight end, Chicago Bears and Detroit Lions
*[[Mark Dailey]], Canadian newscaster for [[City TV]]
*[[Bob Davie (coach)|Bob Davie]], former [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame]] football coach, current [[ESPN]] commentator
*[[Lorenzo Davis]], former National Football League wide reviver, Pittsburgh Steelers
*[[Pat DiCesare]], [[entrepreneur]] and [[rock and roll]] [[concert promoter|promoter]]
*[[Dave Dravecky]], former MLB All-Star pitcher, 1982–89
*[[Sloko Gill]], former National Football League center, Detroit Lions
*[[Ralph Goldston]], former National Football League running back, Philadelphia Eagles
*[[John Goode]], former National Football League tight end, Philadelphia Eagles and St. Louis Cardnials
*[[Linda Gooden]], Executive Vice President - Lockheed Martin (Ranked 33rd Most Powerful Businesswomen of 2010)
*[[Brad Hennessey]], MLB pitcher, currently with the [[Baltimore Orioles]]
*[[Philip Larmon]], Arena Football Player 2005-2006, Co-Producer of &quot;Magic Valley&quot; an Official 2011 Tribeca Film Festival selection and &quot;Ass Backwards&quot;.
*[[Nanette LePore]], noted fashion designer
*[[Evelyn G. Lowery]], American civil rights activist and leader; marched in the historic Selma to Montgomery March
*[[Quentin Lowry]], Former NFL linebacker for the Washington Redskins
*[[Ron Jaworski]], former NFL All-Pro and sports commentator, [[color commentator]] for Monday Night Football
*[[Tim Johnson]], former National Football League linebacker, Baltimore Ravens and Oakland Raiders
*[[Bobby Jones]], former National Football League wide receiver, New York Jets and Cleveland Browns
*[[Donald Jones (American football)|Donald Jones]], NFL Wide Receiver for the Buffalo Bills
*[[Nathaniel R. Jones]], federal judge
*[[Sean Jones (trumpeter)|Sean Jones]], jazz recording artist and lead trumpeter for the [[Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra]]
*[[Rich Kasunic]], Pennsylvania State Senator
*[[JJ Kincaid]], Afternoon DJ on Z100
*[[Don Leshnock]], Former Major League Baseball pitcher for the Detroit Tigers
*[[Mark Mangino]], college football head coach, formerly at the University of Kansas
*[[Riyad Mansour]], Permanent Representative to the United Nations from Palestine
*[[Vince Marrow]], former National Football League tight end, Buffalo Bills
*[[Marcus Mason]], professional football player, NFL running back, [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Ed Mcglasson]], former National Football League Center, New York Jets, LA Rams and New York Giants
*[[Christopher Moriarty]], Emmy winning television production engineer
*[[Martin Moore]], scientist at the [[Naval Research Laboratory]] known for his pioneering work on novel polymers
*[[Ed O'Neill]], actor, most famous as [[Al Bundy]] on ''[[Married With Children]]''
*[[Ron Parise]], NASA astronaut, sts-35 and sts-37
*[[Amit Patel]], cardiothoracic surgeon and world pioneer of stem cell therapy for heart failure.
*[[Frank Pokorny]], former National Football League wide receiver, Pittsburgh Steelers
*[[Carmen Policy]], NFL executive, San Francisco 49ers &amp; Cleveland Browns
*Milan Puskar, founder of Fortune 500 company [[Mylan Laboratories Inc.|Mylan Laboratories]]
*[[Matt Quinn]], former ABC News reporter
*[[Ed Rosenthal]], author and noted criminal defendant (did not graduate)
*[[Chris Sainato]], [[Pennsylvania House of Representatives|Pennsylvania state representative]]
*[[Cliff Stoudt]], former National Football League quarterback, Pittsburgh Steelers, St. Louis Cardinals, Arizona Cardinals and Miami Dolphins
*[[Russell Stuvaints]], former National Football League defensive back, Pittsburgh Steelers
*[[Justin Thomas]], Major League Baseball relief pitcher
*[[James Traficant]], former [[United States House of Representatives|US Congressman]]
*[[Sonny Vaccaro]], founder of ABCD Basketball Camp. Marketing executive for [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]], [[Reebok]] and [[Adidas]]
*[[Jeff Wilkins]], professional football player, record-setting NFL kicker of the St. Louis Rams
*[[Jay Williams (politician)|Jay Williams]], currently appointed presidential cabinet position in the Office of Recovery for Auto Communities and Workers, by President Barack Obama, former mayor, city of Youngstown
*E.J. Parker, bassist, recording artist, composer and educator.

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
*[http://www.ysu.edu/ Official website]
**[http://www.ysu.edu/sports YSU Sports]
**[http://www.ysu.edu/reccenter YSU Rec Center]
**[http://maag.ysu.edu Maag Library]
*[http://www.ysubookstore.com YSU Bookstore]
*[http://www.ysubands.org YSU Bands website]
*[http://www.ysu.edu/greeklife YSU Greek Life Website]
* [http://www.youngstownsource.com Youngstown Source]- Youngstown's alternative news resource. Covers campus life

{{Horizon League}}
{{Missouri Valley Football Conference}}
{{CHMA}}
{{Public universities in Ohio}}

{{coord|41.106759|N|80.646674|W|source:dewiki_region:US-OH_type:landmark|format=dms|display=title}}

[[Category:Youngstown State University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Ohio]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Education in Mahoning County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Youngstown, Ohio]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1908]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Public universities in the United States]]
[[Category:Public universities]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Mahoning County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Mahoning County, Ohio]]

[[de:Youngstown State University]]
[[fr:Youngstown State University]]
[[no:Youngstown State University]]
[[simple:Youngstown State University]]
[[zh:楊斯鎮州立大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
