<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5309160" ns="0" title="Caloyers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{orphan|date=March 2010}}

The '''Caloyers''' (from the [[Greek language|Greek]] ''kalos ghérôn'', &quot;good old men&quot;), also spelled '''Calogers''' or '''Calogeri''', were [[Greece|Greek]] [[monk]]s who followed the rule of Saint [[Basil of Caesarea]]. Both male and female, they inhabited [[Mount Athos]] (only men), and disseminated throughout many of the churches of the East. They lived either in monasteries, as at Mount Athos and [[Meteora]] or insulated in [[hermit]]ages, devoted to [[agriculture]] and [[prayer]].

There was never any reform among them; they retained their original institution and former habits, with minute exactness. [[Jean-Baptiste Tavernier|Tavernier]] observed that they lived an isolated, austere life, eating no meat, and maintained four [[lent]]s, besides numerous other fasts, with great strictness: they ate no food till they had earned it by the labor of their hands. During their lents, some did not eat more than once in three days, others only twice in seven.

They were divided into three ranks or degrees: the novices, called ''Archari''; the moderately accomplished, called ''Microschemi'' (Μικρόσχημοι); and the perfect, called ''Megaloschemi'' (μεγαλόσχημοι). This last rank was divided into the following: ''[[Coenobites]]'', who spent the day reciting their offices, from midnight to sunset; ''[[Anchorites]]'', who left the community to live alone, only going outside on Sundays and holidays to perform devotions at monasteries; and ''Recluses'', who lived alone in grottos and caverns, on the mountains, and survived on [[alms]] furnished to them by the monasteries.

==See also==
* [[Hesychasm]]
* [[Monk#Eastern Christianity|Eastern Orthodox Monks]]

==References==
*McClintock, John and James Strong. &quot;Caloyers&quot;. ''Cyclopedia of Biblical, Theological &amp; Ecclesiastical Literature''. Baker Academic. 1982. ISBN 0-8010-6123-7.
*Gardner, James. ''Faiths of the World''. Kessinger Publishing. 2003. ISBN 0-7661-4303-1. [http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0766143031?v=search-inside&amp;sitb-query-encoding=&amp;url=stripsearch&amp;keywords=Caloyers Page 248]
*Webster, Noah. ''American Dictionary of the English Language''. 1828.
*{{1728}}

[[Category:Ascetics]]
[[Category:Christianity in Greece]]
[[Category:Greek Christian monks]]

[[el:Μοναχισμός]]
[[fr:Caloyers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
