<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="533596" ns="0" title="Defiant class starship"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Fictional Spacecraft
| name           = ''Defiant'' Class
| image          =  &lt;!-- Screen caps ONLY, publicity images will be deleted --&gt;
| caption        =  
| first          = &quot;[[The Search (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Search]]&quot;
| last           = &quot;[[Endgame (Star Trek: Voyager)|Endgame]]&quot;
| status         = Active
| affiliation    = [[United Federation of Planets]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Starfleet]]
| launched       = 2366
| decommissioned =
| class          =
| registry       =
| maxspeed       = Warp 9.5
| fighters       =
| auxcraft       = [[Shuttlecraft (Star Trek)|Shuttlecraft]]
| armaments=[[List of weapons in Star Trek#Phasers|Phaser]]s&lt;br&gt; [[List of weapons in Star Trek#Photon torpedoes|Photon torpedoes]]&lt;br&gt; [[List of weapons of Star Trek#Quantum torpedoes|Quantum torpedoes]]
| defense        = [[Shields (Star Trek)|Deflector shields]]&lt;br&gt; [[Cloaking device]]&lt;br&gt; [[Ablative armor]]
| propulsion     = [[Warp drive (Star Trek)|Warp]], [[Impulse drive|Impulse]]
| power          = Class 7 Warp Drive 
| length         = 170 meters
| width          = 90 meters
| height         = 25 meters
| primeref       =
}}

The '''''Defiant-Class''''' is a fictional class of [[starship]] in the television series ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'', ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'' and the [[feature film]] ''[[Star Trek: First Contact]]''. The Defiant-class was designed by James Martin under the direction of Herman Zimmerman and Gary Hutzel and introduced to the TV series [[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]] in its third season.

==History and design==
{{In-universe|date=October 2009}}
The ''Defiant'' class vessel is one of Starfleet's most advanced ship designs, conceived in response to the [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] threat. In the Episode &quot;[[The Search (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Search]]&quot;, the Defiant Class is officially designated as an &quot;escort&quot; ship, which Captain Sisko noted was due to Starfleet policy of not operating warships.

Starfleet's Advanced Starship Design Bureau at the [[Utopia Planitia]] Fleet Yards began the project in 2366. [[Benjamin Sisko]] was also part of the project. After the Borg threat was deemed lower, research and production for these vessels slowed. Engineering problems &amp;ndash; particularly in regard to the small ship's overpowered engines &amp;ndash; led Starfleet to mothball the project. However, in 2371 Starfleet put the class into full-scale production as a response to the [[Dominion War]].

The design is a semi-saucer fore with a squared-off aft section and measures 120 meters in length with 4 decks, making it much smaller than most Federation starships. A short, rectangular extension houses the [[Shields (Star Trek)|navigational deflector]] and the main docking port at the bow. The 1.5 megacochrane [[warp drive (Star Trek)|warp nacelles]] are housed on either side of the ship. Unusual for Starfleet vessels, the ''Defiant'' class' nacelles are not parallel; their axes intersect less than a ship-length aft of the starship. The Defiant class was also described as &quot;overpowered&quot; for her size during her trials. 

Another trait distinguishing this class is that it was specifically designed for war, boasting among its armaments distinctive [[List of weapons in Star Trek|phaser]] pulse cannons seemingly unique to the class. [[Ablative armor|Ablative hull armor]], added to the design after its launch, allows ''Defiant'' class ships to take a considerable beating even after the incapacitation of its active [[shields (Star Trek)|deflector shields]]. (''DS9'' &quot;[[The Way of the Warrior]]&quot;, &quot;[[Paradise Lost (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Paradise Lost]]&quot;)) 

The ship has few of the creature comforts that are normally found on most Starfleet vessels and has small racked bunk-styled quarters. The [[Sick bay|infirmary]] is small and the design does not include science labs. The standard crew complement for the Defiant class is forty-six personnel.

==Known ''Defiant'' class starships==
;[[USS Defiant|USS ''Defiant'' (NX-74205)]] : The class pathfinder built at the Antares Fleet Yards. The ''Defiant'' is assigned to [[space station]] [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]] in 2371 to help protect the [[Galactic quadrant|Alpha Quadrant]] from the growing threat from the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]]. The [[Romulan|Romulan Star Empire]] equipped the ship with a [[cloaking device]] for use on intelligence-gathering missions in the Gamma Quadrant. In addition to engaging the Dominion's [[Jem'Hadar]], the ''Defiant'' also sees action against [[Breen (Star Trek)|Breen]], [[Cardassian]] and [[Klingon]] vessels. The ship is severely damaged while fighting the Borg at the [[Star Trek: First Contact|Battle of Sector 001]] in 2373 and is destroyed in 2375 after attempting to stop the Dominion and Breen from retaking the Chin'toka system during the [[Dominion War]].

:The ''Defiant'' retains &quot;NX&quot; in its [[Starfleet ship registry and classes in Star Trek|registry]] even after the class enters mainstream production. This may be due to the continued presence of the Romulan cloaking device, a feature not shared with the ''Defiant'''s sister ships.

; [[USS Defiant|USS ''São Paulo'' (NCC-75633)]] : Assigned to Deep Space Nine after the ''Defiant'''s destruction and rechristened as the USS ''Defiant''. The studio did not wish to spend the time or money to redo stock effects shots of the ''Defiant'' used to depict this new vessel. As such, exterior shots of the ship include the registry number &quot;NX-74205&quot;.

; USS ''Valiant'' (NCC-74210) : Used by Starfleet cadets of Red Squad and destroyed by the Dominion in 2374. The only survivors are [[Jake Sisko]], [[Nog (Star Trek)|Nog]], and Cadet Dorian Collins (''DS9'': &quot;[[Valiant (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Valiant]]&quot;).

*Four unnamed ''Defiant'' class ships are among the task force that the IKS ''Rotarraan'' and the USS ''Defiant'' join following Starfleet's withdrawal from DS9. (''DS9'' &quot;[[Call to Arms (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Call to Arms]]&quot;)
*Two unnamed ''Defiant'' class ships are among the task force sent to recapture the starship [[Prometheus class starship|''Prometheus'']] in ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'''s &quot;[[Message in a Bottle (Star Trek: Voyager)|Message in a Bottle]]&quot;.
*Two unnamed ''Defiant'' class ships are among the task force sent to intercept a Borg sphere emerging from a transwarp aperture near Earth. Following the emergence of the USS Voyager from the debris, the unnamed Defiant-class starships assisted in escorting Voyager back to Earth in the series finale of [[Star Trek: Voyager]], &quot;[[Endgame (Star Trek: Voyager)|Endgame]]&quot;

==See also==
*&quot;[[The Search (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Search]]&quot; &amp;ndash; Episode in which the ''Defiant'' class first appears.

==External links==
*[http://lcarscom.net/defiantclass.htm &quot;Defiant class&quot; at LCARScom.Net]
*[http://memory-alpha.org/wiki/Defiant_class &quot;Defiant class&quot; at Memory Alpha]
*[http://ex-astris-scientia.org/articles/defiant-problems.htm &quot;Defiant problems&quot; at Ex Astris Scientia]

{{Star Trek starships}}
{{Star Trek}}

[[Category:Starfleet ship classes]]
[[Category:Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]

[[cs:Třída Defiant]]
[[it:Astronavi di Star Trek#Classe Defiant]]
[[ja:ディファイアント級]]
[[pl:Klasa Defiant]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
