<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5335922" ns="0" title="Blakeney Point"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Geobox|Geographic feature
| name = Blakeney Point
| category = [[Spit (landform)|Spit]] 
| image = Blakeney point lifeboat station.jpg|250px
| image_caption = The visitor centre, formerly a lifeboat station
| official_name = Blakeney Point
| flag = 
| symbol = 
| country = [[England]] 
| state =     [[Norfolk]]
| region =   [[East of England]]
| district =  [[North Norfolk]]
| municipality = [[Blakeney, Norfolk|Blakeney]] 
| location =  
| elevation =
| prominence =
| lat_d = 
| lat_m = 
| lat_s = 
| lat_NS = 
| long_d = 
| long_m = 
| long_s = 
| long_EW =
| length = 
| length_orientation = 
| width = 
| width_orientation = 
| height =
| depth = 
| volume =
| weight =
| geology =Shingle Ridge
| orogeny =
| period = 
| biome =
| plant =
| animal =
| author =
| style = 
| material =
| established = 
| date = 
| management = National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty
| owner =  National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty
| public = Open all year round
| visitation = 
| visitation_date =
| access =
| ascent = 
| ascent_date =
| discovery = 
| discovery_date =
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free = 
| free_type = 
&lt;!-- *** Maps *** --&gt;
| map = Norfolk outline map with UK.png
| map_caption = 
| map_background =
| map_locator =
| map_locator_x =51
| map_locator_y =4
&lt;!-- *** Websites *** --&gt; 
| commons =
| statistics =
| website =[http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/blakeney/ National Trust Blakeney Point]
&lt;!-- *** Footnotes *** --&gt;
| footnotes =
}}

'''Blakeney Point''' is a shingle [[Spit (landform)|spit]] on the coast of [[North Norfolk]] north of the village of [[Blakeney, Norfolk|Blakeney]] in the [[England|English]] county of [[Norfolk]].&lt;ref&gt; ''OS Explorer Map 24” – Norfolk Coast Central. ISBN 0-319-21726-4 &lt;/ref&gt; It is managed by the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]] as part of its '''Blakeney [[National Nature Reserve]]''' and within the [[Norfolk Coast AONB|Norfolk Coast]] [[Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty]].
==Description==
[[Image:The Shingle spit.jpg||thumb|left|180px|The shingle spit]]
Blakeney Point spit runs East to West and is tied at its eastern end to the cliff line at [[Weybourne, Norfolk|Weybourne]]. The spit is approximately 9.6 miles (15.5 kilometres) in length but is subject to change all the time. The spit is composed of a shingle bank which in places is 65 feet (20 m) in width and at some points, 33 feet (10 m) high. It has been estimated that there are {{convert|82|Mcuft|m3}} of shingle in the spit.&lt;ref&gt;North Norfolk Coast by EM Bridges. The Geographical Association, page 39  ISBN 1-899085-53-X&lt;/ref&gt; At the point on the western end [[Dune|sand dunes]] have accumulated. Between the shingle spit arm and the raised [[coastline]] there are [[salt marshes]]. The spit was formed by [[longshore drift]] and this continues westward. At the western point the shingle curves laterally south towards the land. This feature has occurred several times over the years giving the impression on the map of the teeth of a comb. Between Weybourne and [[Cley next the Sea]] work has taken place to maintain an even height of the bank and to repair it as a natural [[Coastal management|sea defence]] for the villages behind and the [[A149 road|A149]] coast road that runs parallel with the [[Shingle beach|shingle]] spit. From Cley the [[River Glaven]] flows to the landward southern side of the spit, where it abruptly turns west and flows into the sea at Blakeney Point. At the end of the spit is a visitor information centre which is housed in an old [[Lifeboat (rescue)|lifeboat]] station.

==Access==
Blakeney Point can be accessed on foot or by boat. At the end of the lane that runs from Cley to Cley Eye behind the shingle bank there is a car park (charges apply). From here it is possible to walk westwards along the spit to Blakeney Point. To reach the [[headland]] and visitor centre you may also catch one of the several boat trips that operate from Blakeney and [[Morston]] [[harbour]]s. Entry to the sensitive nesting ground on the point is restricted during the breeding season. There are also many facilities for [[Birdwatching]] on the salt marshes and spit. Groups of visitors are requested to contact the warden to make prior arrangements for their visit.

==Seal watching==
[[Image:Seals Blakney Point.jpg|thumb|right|The Seals on Blakeney Point]]
Blakeney Point is one of the best places in [[Great Britain]] to watch and study [[seal (mammal)|seals]]. The seal  colony is made up of [[Common Seal|Common]] and [[Grey Seal|Grey]] Seals and numbers are around 500. The Common Seals have their young between June and August, the Grey Seals between November and January. Both suckle their pups for about three weeks, during which time they grow very quickly, putting on between 1&amp;nbsp;kg and 1.6&amp;nbsp;kg a day, due to the very rich and fatty milk they are fed. The seals usually bask on the sandbanks at the far end of the spit. The grey seals are the larger of the two species and have large speckles on their coats and longer pointed heads with parallel nostrils. The common seals have a more rounded face with ‘v’ shaped nostrils. The best way of viewing the seals is to catch one of several boat trips which are run from Blakeney and Morston harbours. Between April and October the trips operate on a daily basis, although they also run throughout the winter months. Times of trips depend on the [[tide]] and are posted on [[Public transport timetable|timetable]] boards at both harbours. The seals are very inquisitive and often pop up alongside the boats.

==Bird life==
The spit is also teeming with birds. During the summer months you can spot [[Common Tern]]s, [[Sandwich Tern]]s, [[Little Tern]]s and [[Arctic Tern]]s. Other species to be seen are [[Oyster Catcher]], [[Ringed Plover]], [[Turnstone]] and [[Dunlin]]. In the winter months large numbers of ducks and geese, including [[Mallard]], [[Wigeon]], [[Teal]], [[Northern Pintail|Pintail]], [[Pink-footed Goose]]. [[Greylag]] and [[Brent Goose|Brent Geese]], can be seen, especially on the salt marshes.

==Wildlife Gallery==
{{gallery
|lines=1
|Image:Kuestenseeschwalbe-Kniepsand.jpg|Nesting Arctic Tern
|Image:Sterna sandvicensis Brandseeschwalbe.jpg|Sandwich Tern feeding its young
|Image:Little Tern with Crested Terns.jpg|Little Tern
|Image:Austernfischer01.jpg|Oyster Catcher
|Image:Charadrius hiaticula He.jpg|Ringed Plover
|Image:Arenaria interpres.jpg|Turnstone
|Image:Dunlin 800.jpg|Dunlin wading
|Image:Chroicocephalus ridibundus.jpg|Black Headed Gull
}}

==Gastronomy==
[[Image:Norfolk Samphire.jpg|alt=Norfolk Samphire|Norfolk Samphire|upright|thumb]]
A famous local delicacy is [[Samphire]], or [[Glasswort]]. The scientific name for this is ''Salicornia europaea'' and locally it is sometimes called poor man's asparagus. Samphire is a fleshy edible plant, which grows in the intertidal mudflats and salt marshes in the areas around Blakeney Point. A traditional way to eat it is first to boil it lightly, then drag through peppered butter, then 'suck' the flesh of the stalk. When it is in season, many locals sell bunches from small stalls outside their cottages at very reasonable prices. In recent times it has become a very fashionable delicacy served in top restaurants in London and Europe, where the tiny plant fetches inflated prices.
{{clear}}

==The Spit in 1649==
{{Wide image|Salthouse ancient channel map.jpg|600px|The spit and [[Salthouse]] ancient channel map made by Surveyor John Hunt in 1649|100%|left}}
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{commonscat}}

{{coord|52.9772|0.9778|type:landmark_region:GB|display=title}}

[[Category:North Norfolk]]
[[Category:Coastal feature of Norfolk]]
[[Category:National Trust properties in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Geography of Norfolk]]
[[Category:Spits of England]]
[[Category:Special Protection Areas in England]]
[[Category:National Nature Reserves in England]]
[[Category:Nature reserves in Norfolk]]

[[nn:Blakeney Point]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
