<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5345266" ns="0" title="Wadsworth Falls State Park"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Geobox Protected Area
&lt;!-- *** Name section *** --&gt;
| name                        = Wadsworth Falls State Park
| native_name                 = 
| other_name                  = 
| other_name1                 = 
&lt;!-- *** Category *** --&gt;
| category_local              = [[List of Connecticut state parks|Connecticut State Park]]
| category_iucn               = IV
&lt;!-- *** Image *** --&gt;
| image                       =  
| image_caption               = Wadsworth Falls
&lt;!-- *** Etymology *** ---&gt;
| etymology_type              = Named for
| etymology                   = Clarence C. Wadsworth
&lt;!-- *** Country etc. *** --&gt;
| country                     = United States
| state                       = Connecticut
| region_type                 = County
| region                      = [[Middlesex County, Connecticut|Middlesex]]
| district_type               = Towns
| district                    = [[Middlefield, Connecticut|Middlefield]]
| district1                   = [[Middlefield, Connecticut|Middlefield]]
| district2                   = [[Middletown, Connecticut|Middletown]]
| district3                   = | city                        = 
| city1                       =
&lt;!-- *** Geography *** --&gt;  
| location                    =
| lat_d                       = 41       
| lat_m                       = 32
| lat_s                       = 8
| lat_NS                      = N
| long_d                      = 72       
| long_m                      = 40
| long_s                      = 34
| long_EW                     = W
}}

'''Wadsworth Falls State Park''', or simply '''Wadsworth Falls''', is a Connecticut [[state park]] located in the towns of Middletown and  [[Middlefield, Connecticut|Middlefield]].  The park lies in the northeast corner of Middlefield, and extends across the town border into  [[Middletown, Connecticut|Middletown]] with the main entrance on [[Route 157 (Connecticut)|Route 157]]. The park itself consists of a series of marked trails covering {{convert|285|acre|km2}} and is intersected by the [[Coginchaug River]], a tributary of the [[Connecticut River]].

There is also a swimming and picnicking area in the park grounds. The [[swimming pool]] is paved with [[soil cement]] to prevent leakage. Water is pumped from [[water well]]s located near the [[Coginchaug River]]. Through the [[hiking trail]]s there is a small brown [[bridge]] leading to the falls. Wadsworth Falls is 30 feet (9.1 m) high, with 52 feet (16 m) of water trickling over [[sandstone]] along the trail.

==History==
The falls are named after Clarence C. Wadsworth, a [[colonel]] in the [[New York National Guard]] who   owned the property where the park now exists. He had a fine reputation in academics, and studied [[linguistics]] avidly. He settled in [[Middletown, Connecticut]], home of [[Wesleyan University]], it became his passion for 45 years to preserve Wadsworth Falls. His will established the Rockfall Corporation, which is tasked to maintain the protection of the land, plants, and animals in his estate. In [[1942]] {{convert|267|acre|km2}} of the estate were given to the State of Connecticut.[http://dep.state.ct.us/STATEPARKS/parks/wadsworth.htm] The park is now operated by the  Department of Environmental Protection and is open every day until sunset.  

==Features==
This park features a pond with a sandy beach with lifeguard supervision in the summer.  Amenities include picnic tables and grills for use in cook outs, flush toilets, a river stocked for fishing and a network of hiking trails.

Dogs are allowed in the park while on a leash.

==The Falls==
Wadsworth Falls are located at the opposite side of the park from the main entrance and may be reached by car (parking on Cherry Hill Road).  They may also be reached by an easy hike, approximately 1.25 miles in length, from the main entrance on [[Route 157 (Connecticut)|Route 157]].  

==The Mansion==
While not a part of the state park property, the Long Hill Estate mansion once belonging to Clarence C. Wadsworth is adjacent to the park, near {{coord|41|32|8|N|72|40|34|W}}, and may be reached by taking the purple-blazed hiking trail across Laurel Grove Road.  The mansion is now privately owned, and after undergoing extensive renovations, is used as a reception hall.  There are public walking trails around its grounds.

==External links==
*[http://www.ct.gov/dep/cwp/view.asp?a=2716&amp;q=325274&amp;depNav_GID=1650 Wadsworth Falls State Park Official Site]
*[http://dep.state.ct.us/STATEPARKS/parks/wadsworth.htm Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection]
*[http://www.wadsworthmansion.com/ Long Hill Estate]

{{Protected Areas of Connecticut}}

[[Category:Middlefield, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Connecticut state parks]]
[[Category:Parks in Middlesex County, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Waterfalls of Connecticut]]
[[Category:Landforms of Middlesex County, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Protected areas established in 1942]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
