<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5352478" ns="0" title="Burnsview Secondary School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox education in Canada
|name=          Burnsview Secondary School
|image=         
|imagesize=     
|motto=         &quot;We Share, We Care, We Dare to Succeed!&quot;
|motto_translation= 
|streetaddress= 7658 112 Street
|city=          [[Delta, British Columbia|Delta]]
|province=      [[British Columbia]]
|postalcode=    V4C 4V8
|coordinates =  {{Coord|49.141791|-122.911607|region:CA-BC}}
|url=           http://www.deltasd.bc.ca/bu/
|schoolnumber=  3737034
|schoolboard=   [[School District 37 Delta]]
|superintendent=
|trustee=       
|affiliation=   
|principal=     Ms. C Rizzardo
|viceprincipal= Mr. D. Eichorn
|administrator=     
|staff=	44
|fundingtype=	[[Public school (government funded)|Public]]
|schooltype=    [[High school#Canada|high school]]
|grades=        8-12
|language= English, French      
|area=         [[North Delta, British Columbia|North Delta]] 
|mascot= Griffin        
|teamname=      Burnsview Griffins
|colours=Red, navy blue, white     
|founded=       1972
|enrollment=    753
|enrollment_as_of=  18 May 2011
|lastupdate= 18 May 2011
}}

'''Burnsview Secondary School''' is a public [[High school#Canada|high school]] in [[North Delta, British Columbia]], [[Canada]]. Burnsview Secondary School is part of [[School District 37 Delta]]. It was originally a junior high school when it was built in the 1970s, but now accommodates grades 8 through 12.  

==History==
Burnsview Secondary School opened in 1972 as a junior high school, accommodating grades 8 through 10.&lt;ref name=&quot;rollo&quot; /&gt;  In 1992, at its 20th anniversary celebration, a time capsule was created by students and will be sealed until its opening in 2012. &lt;ref name=&quot;rollo&quot;&gt;Archibald Rollo (1992, November 5). Column One :[1* Edition]. The Vancouver Sun,p. B1.  Retrieved February 17, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 182743821).&lt;/ref&gt;  It suffered a fire in the summer of 1997, in which a whole school wing was destroyed.  The rebuilding took over a year.&lt;ref&gt;School board takes on local issues: Members say their biggest challenges for the coming year are to balance the books, deal with contracts, cope with Bill 39, and lobby for new schools while always putting students first :[Richmond / Ladner / Tsawwassen Edition]. (1998, August 31). The Vancouver Sun,p. B3.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 222818711).&lt;/ref&gt; The school was part of the Delta School District's reconfiguration project, and accepted Grade 11 students in 2005 and Grade 12 students in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;General briefs. (18  March). Sterling News Service,1.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from CBCA Current Events database. (Document ID: 314755401).&lt;/ref&gt; It is the only French Immersion secondary school in North Delta and houses one of the few hockey academies in British Columbia.&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite news 
  | last = Booth
  | first = Michael 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Playing by the rules; Coaches adapt to changing landscape, where parents shop for the right school
  | pages =  28
  | publisher = Now
  | date = 2007-12-21}} Burnsview as a magnet school has developed a special hockey academic to attract new students.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite news 
  | last = Fabritius-Brzozowski.
  | first = Kirsten 
  | title = 'Grassroots' means people choose, pay of own free will
  | pages = 14
  | publisher = Now
  | date = 2007-07-06}} Burnsview secondary is the only North Delta high school offering French immersion and it has a hockey academy&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite news 
  | last = Gyarmati
  | first = Sandor 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Two specialty programs in works for September; District looks at equestrian academy, traditional school
  | pages = 12
  | publisher = Delta Optimist
  | date = 2008-02-09}} Hockey academy considered example for future expansion of specialty programs Also, the school is currently under construction, undergoing seismic upgrading to meet provincial standards.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite news 
  | last = Gyarmati
  | first = Sandor 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Delta secondary at top of district's seismic list; $1.6 million project at Ladner high school among five submitted to Ministry of Education
  | pages = 6
  | publisher = Delta Optimist
  | date = 2007-07-21}} Burnsview receives funding for seismic upgrade to meet provincial requirements&lt;/ref&gt;

==World Vision 30 Hour Famine==
Burnsview has actively participated in the World Vision 30 Hour Famine since the early 1990s. In 1992 students raised $10,000 for people in Somalia. &lt;ref&gt;Charlie Anderson (1992, November 22). In Somalia, even tears die :[1* Edition]. The Province,p. A27.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 238831251).&lt;/ref&gt; In 1995, the student body managed to increase donations to $12,000, and sent this money to Rwanda. Students also gave up junk food for three weeks to add to their collection totals.&lt;ref&gt;TANIA LO,  TJ JHEETA. (1995, March 20). Burnsview students send help to Rwanda :[FINAL Edition]. The Vancouver Sun,p. C.6.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 21137304).&lt;/ref&gt; The total money raised placed Burnsview as the second top fundraising school in Canada, just behind [[Collingwood School]]. 

In 1997, Canadian rocker [[Tom Cochrane]] performed a private concert for participants at the 30 Hour Famine. 150 students raised over $11,000, giving the school the highest per student average in Canada for that year. &lt;ref&gt;Glen Schaefer, Staff Reporter (1997, May 30). Cochrane says thanks :[Final Edition]. The Province,p. A2.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 231089521).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Prayer chain for Hong Kong to circle the globe :[Final Edition]. (1997, July 12). Toronto Star,p. L.14.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 12963843).&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, before the start of the famine, students had raised over $18,500.&lt;ref&gt;School Notes :[Final Edition]. (1998, March 8). The Province,p. A14.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 228441991).&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2003 famine raised $20,000 for AIDS in Africa.&lt;ref&gt;Natalia Toronchuk (2004, April 28). Famine prompts feast of generosity: $20,000 raised for hungry kids :[Final Edition]. Now,p. 8.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Pacific database. (Document ID: 628151951).&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, students raised over $30,000 in an effort to regain the title as top fund raising school in Canada. In 2008, students raised over $40,000 for World Vision. &lt;ref&gt;*{{cite news 
  | last = Booth
  | first = Michael 
  | title = Students cope with empty stomachs in annual event
  | pages = 23
  | publisher = Now
  | date = 2007-03-03}} The 30-hour Famine is an annual fundraiser for World Vision Canada. Burnsview has been staging the event for over a decade now and has a reputation as one of the top fundraising schools in the country. &quot;We are just under $30,000 and we're still counting,&quot; she said. &quot;Our goal this year was $40,000 and we still haven't counted all the online donations. We'll definitely catch up with last year's number but will we get the 40? No.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Enrichment Programs==
In 2003, Burnsview was host for a district wide Aboriginal Education program to educate Aboriginal students about their history. This program only accepts Aboriginal students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jan Westell 2003, p. 13&quot;&gt;Jan Westell (2003, January 29). Program instills pride in aboriginal students: :[Final Edition]. Delta Optimist,p. 13.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Pacific database. (Document ID: 328332301).&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2003, Burnsview was awarded part of the Delta School District's $300,000 to purchase computers for students in Grade 8 English classes. This was part of a multi-year project to improve student achievement in literacy, specifically in proofreading, editing, and revising.&lt;ref&gt;Delta goes for laptop learning :[Final Edition]. (2005, March 2). Now,p. 10.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Pacific database. (Document ID: 802450421).&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Prime Minister's Award for Teaching Excellence==
Four teachers have won this award while they have taught at Burnsview Secondary. They are: 

# Shain Chisholm, a French Immersion and Humanities teacher, in 1999. &lt;ref&gt;Janet Steffenhagen (1999, May 14). Chretien lauds Burnaby teacher as hero: Top educator takes students beyond classroom :[Final Edition]. The Vancouver Sun,p. B1 / FRONT.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 223194701).&lt;/ref&gt;
# John Westlake in 2000. &lt;ref&gt;Janet Steffenhagen (2000, May 16). Vancouver teacher wins national award :[Final Edition]. The Vancouver Sun,p. B8.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 223720021).&lt;/ref&gt;
# Wendy Van Haastregt, a science teacher, in 2001. &lt;ref&gt;Janet Steffenhagen (2001, May 10). Three B.C. teachers win awards for classroom skills: They are among 15 from across the country honoured by the prime minister :[Final Edition]. The Vancouver Sun,p. B7.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Major Dailies database. (Document ID: 224886471).&lt;/ref&gt;
# Angelika Hedley, a special education teacher, in 2002. &lt;ref name=&quot;Jan Westell 2003, p. 13&quot; /&gt;

==Notable alumni==
*[[Jeff Francis]]  &amp;mdash; pitcher for the [[Colorado Rockies]].&lt;ref&gt;Tom Zillich (2007, October 26). Parents still proud after Francis battered :[Final Edition]. Now,p. 9.  Retrieved February 18, 2008, from Canadian Newsstand Pacific database. (Document ID: 1373662851).&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jim Robinson]]  &amp;mdash; founding CEO of [[TuneCardz]].
*[[Tyler Connolly]]  &amp;mdash; lead singer of [[Theory of a Deadman]].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.deltasd.bc.ca/bu/ School Website]
*[http://web.deltasd.bc.ca/ourschools/SecondarySchools.asp?ReportID=40354 School District's Page about the school]

[[Category:High schools in Delta, British Columbia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
