<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5378591" ns="0" title="Sinclair family (Emmerdale)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=September 2008}}

'''The Sinclair family''' were a fictional family in ''[[Emmerdale]]''. 

== About the Sinclairs ==

The Sinclairs are [[upper class]] [[aristocracy|aristocrat]] family. They were introduced one by one. 

Later at a dinner party, we met Alasdair's older brother [[Grayson Sinclair|Grayson]] and Grayson's wife, [[Perdita Hyde-Sinclair|Perdy]]; they were revealed as the new residents of Oakwell Hall, previously occupied by [[Lady Tara Thornfield]]. 	

At Alasdair and Sadie's wedding, we were introduced to the matriarch of the Sinclair family, the ruthless and formidable [[Rosemary Sinclair]] who took an instant dislike to her youngest son's wife-to-be. After [[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew King]] burst in trying to stop the wedding, it was too late; Alasdair and Sadie were already married but Sadie left Alasdair at the church, going off with Matthew. Rosemary vowed revenge on the woman who had broken her son's heart. 

Rosemary made a deal with Sadie: in exchange for the Sinclair business with the most sentimental value to Rosemary, Sadie would have the marriage annulled. Rosemary got her revenge: once the business was signed over, Rosemary revealed that it was worthless. She also told Sadie that the meal she had been served prior to the signings was Sadie's horse Cossack (this was a lie, but Sadie believed it).

Rosemary and Alasdair soon left, possibly to another grand Sinclair home, while Grayson and Perdy became involved with village life. It appeared that Grayson and Perdy's marriage was on shaky ground following his infidelities and her inability to carry a baby full term.

At a recent shooting party at Home Farm, Perdy suffered a miscarriage which turned out to be her sixth. After Rosemary found out, from the family doctor, she made a point of saying the lack of a child was a danger to the family name. Perdy, furious with Rosemary's cruelty, forced Grayson to find them a house away from Oakwell Hall, and the two moved into Mill Cottage, [[Rodney Blackstock]]'s old house. 

Rosemary, meanwhile, is hiding a huge secret from the rest of the family. She's broke and only her loyal servant, [[Susie Carter|Susie]], knows this. She got her claws into [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]] in a bid to secure some financial backing, but didn't know that he, too, was broke and was using the Sinclair matriarch for exactly the reason. Rosemary is told that the Oakwell Hall has been one of her own family (Oakwells), for centuries. It has only once been owned by someone else, she meaning Lady Tara. 

&lt;!-- missing image [[Image:Emmerdaleks.PNG|thumb|right|Tom announces that he and Rosemary are a couple]] --&gt;
While Tom got sucked into Rosemary's world, his son, Matthew, developed an attraction to Rosemary's daughter-in-law, Perdy, and during a recent ball at Home Farm, in Grayson's absence, Perdy and Matthew slept together. Perdy even thought she was pregnant with Matthew's child but that turned out to be a false alarm.

The Kings were unable to stop the wedding between Rosemary and Tom. However, Tom died hours after getting married to Rosemary on Christmas Day 2006. Rosemary committed suicide a year later on what would have been the first anniversary and of her and Tom's wedding.

Finally came a new baby Sinclair, son of Perdy and Grayson with [[Katie Sugden]] as surrogate mother. However, just after giving birth, Katie told Perdy to take the baby and run. They left on 22 July 2008.

==Main Plots==
{{Cleanup|section|date=September 2010}}
Sadie gets engaged to Alasdair Sinclair (2006)

Sadie jilts Alasdair at the church (2006)

Sadie Annuls the marriage (2006)

Perdy miscarries Grayson's baby (2006)

Grayson and Perdy move out of Oakwell Hall (2006)

Rosemary gets involved with Tom King (2006)

Rosemary loses Oakwell Hall and her businesses (2006)

Rosemary gets engaged to Tom King (2006)

Grayson is revealed to be gay (2006)

Rosemary and Tom get married hours before his death (2006)

Rosemary goes on holiday and returns to ruin the Kings plans for Tom's Funeral (2007)

Rosemary blackmails Hari into lying about Tom's murderer (2007)

Rosemary falls off the balcony and is then made to sell Home Farm Estate's back to the kings (2007)

Rosemary moves into Mill Cottage and starts poisoning Perdy which results her into getting sectioned (2007)

Grayson finds out that Rosemary was behind Perdy's illness (2007)

Rosemary fakes her death and frames Matthew King (2007)

Perdy Begins an affair with Matthew King (2007)

Katie becomes Grayson and Perdy's surrogate (2007)

Rosemary is revealed to be alive but she kills herself with a gun (Christmas Day 2007)

Grayson and Perdy's marriage breaks down (2008)

Grayson starts a relationship with Katie which ends after her deception (2008)

Perdy leaves with her and Grayson's child

Grayson returns and kidnaps the Kings to get answers about Perdy and leaves (2008)

* Raymond Sinclair (deceased) - Rosemary's first husband. He committed suicide, because Rosemary made his life a hell.
* [[Rosemary King|Rosemary Venitia King]] (née '''Oakwell''', previously '''Sinclair''') (deceased) - Matriarch of the family - Suicide by Gun Shot [[Christmas Day]] [[2007]], first anniversary of her second husband's Tom King wedding day. Played by [[Linda Thorson]] 2006-2007.
* [[Grayson Sinclair]] - Eldest Son of Rosemary and Raymond. Played by [[Christopher Villiers]] 2006-2008
* [[Alasdair Sinclair]] - Youngest son of Rosemary and Raymond. Played by [[Ray Coulthard]] 2006, 2008.
* [[Perdita Hyde-Sinclair]] - Grayson's wife. Played by [[Georgia Slowe]] 2006-2008
* [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Thomas Albert King]] (Deceased) - Rosemary's second husband. Played by [[Ken Farrington]] 2004-2006.
* Baby Hyde-Sinclair - Perdy and Grayson's son, left with Perdy. 2008 (1 episode)

==See also==
*[[Sinclair (surname)]] ''the real surname with list of famous Sinclairs''.
*[[Clan Sinclair]] ''the origins of the surname''.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==

{{Emmerdale}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sinclair Family (Emmerdale)}}
[[Category:Emmerdale families|Sinclair Family, The]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
