<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="53939" ns="0" title="Euro coins"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--
'One euro is 100 cent' is a legislative usage; 'One euro is 100 cents' with the natural plural is recommended by the Commission for general use, as on the Wikipedia... please read [[Linguistic issues concerning the euro#English]]
--&gt;
There are eight '''[[euro]] coin''' denominations, ranging from one cent to two euros (the euro is divided into a hundred cents). The coins first came into use in 2002. They have a common [[Obverse and reverse|reverse]], portraying a map of [[Europe]], but each country in the [[eurozone]] has its own design on the [[Obverse and reverse|obverse]], which means that each coin has a variety of different designs in circulation at once.&lt;ref name=ECB&gt;[http://www.ecb.int/euro/coins/html/index.en.html Euro coins]. [[European Central Bank]].&lt;/ref&gt; Three [[European microstates]] which use the euro as their currency also have the right to mint coins with their own designs on the obverse side.

The coins, and various [[€2 commemorative coins|commemorative coins]], are minted at numerous national mints across the [[European Union]]&lt;!--note use of mints outside eurozone--&gt; to strict national quotas. Obverse designs are chosen nationally, while the reverse and the currency as a whole is managed by the [[European Central Bank]] (ECB).

==Common side==
All coins have a common [[obverse and reverse|reverse]] side showing how much the coin is worth, with a design by [[Belgium|Belgian]] designer [[Luc Luycx]].&lt;ref name=ECB/&gt; The design of the 1-, 2-, and 5-cent coins symbolises Europe's place in the world as a whole.

===Current design===
In 2007, a new design was introduced to reflect the enlargement in 2004. The design still retains all elements of the original designs, including the twelve stars, however the map of the fifteen states is replaced by one showing the whole of Europe as a continent, without borders. The vertical ridges only appear over the sea.

[[Cyprus]] is shown several hundred kilometres north west of its real position in order to include it on the map. On the €1 and €2 coins, the island is shown to be directly east of mainland [[Greece]]; on the 10-, 20-, and 50-cent coins, it appears directly below [[Crete]]. The original proposal from the [[European Commission]] was to include [[Turkey]] on the map; however this design was rejected by the [[Council of the European Union|Council]].

The first issue of these coins were minted in 2006, by the Mint of Finland, for the [[Slovenian euro coins]]. These coins came into circulation in 2007 and have been compulsory for existing members since 2008. The one-, two-, and five-cent coins remained unchanged, with the Commission stating that they remained unaffected as they show Europe's place in the world, even though the EU 15 are still highlighted on the map. It is unknown how soon [[Iceland]] would be added to the map if [[Accession of Iceland to the European Union|it becomes an EU member]] in the next few years.

===1999–2006 design===
The original designs of the 10-, 20-, and 50-cent coins showed the outline of each of the [[EU-15]] member states. This meant that each state was shown as separate from the others, thus giving Europe the appearance of an archipelago. EU member states outside the eurozone (the [[United Kingdom]], [[Sweden]], and [[Denmark]]) were also depicted. Non-EU states were not depicted, for example giving the impression that [[Sweden]] had a large west coast (as Norway was not on the map).

On the €1 and €2 coins, the landmass appeared more cohesive although borders were indicated. The vertical ridges also passed through some non-participating countries. As in current issues, all coins featured 12 stars in their design.

The year featured in the coins can date back to 1999, when the currency was formally established (only [[Belgium|Belgian]], [[Finland|Finnish]], [[France|French]], [[Netherlands|Dutch]], and [[Spain|Spanish]] coins have 1999). These countries traditionally stamp the coin with the year of being minted rather than the year of being put into circulation.

==National sides==
{{See also|Identifying marks on euro coins}}

The [[obverse and reverse|obverse]] side varies from state to state, with each member allowed to choose its own design. Each of the eight coins can have the same design (such as [[Belgian euro coins|Belgian coins]]), or can vary from coin to coin (such as [[Italian euro coins|Italian coins]]). In monarchies, the national side usually features a portrait of the country's monarch, often in a design carried over from the former currency (e.g. Belgium). Republics tend to feature national monuments, symbols, or stylised designs (such as [[French euro coins|French coins]]). Engravings on the edge of the €2 coin are also subject to national choice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guide nat&quot;/&gt;

There are, however, some restrictions on the design: it must include twelve stars, the engraver's initials, and the year of issue. New issues must also include the name of the issuing country (a rule currently breached by [[German euro coins|Germany]] and [[Greek euro coins|Greece]], while [[Belgian euro coins|Belgium]], [[French euro coins|France]] and [[Italian euro coins|Italy]] use an abbreviation rather than the full name). It may not repeat the denomination of the coin or the word ''euro'' unless it is in a different alphabet (such as on [[Greek euro coins|Greek coins]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Guide nat&quot;&gt;[http://europa.eu/scadplus/leg/en/lvb/l25089.htm Common guidelines: the national sides of euro coins], [[Europa (web portal)]]&lt;/ref&gt; This rule is flouted by [[Austrian euro coins|Austria]]. The national side was also to remain unchanged until the end of 2008, unless a monarch depicted on a coin died or abdicated (such as in the case of the [[Vatican euro coins|Vatican's coins]]).

There are at present no plans to abolish the national designs in favour of a common European one. However the Commission has proposed that the one-, two-, and five-cent coins have a common design to keep costs down.&lt;ref name=&quot;125stand&quot;/&gt;

Though they are not members of the EU, [[Monaco]], [[San Marino]], and the [[Vatican City]] also have euro coins featuring a national side, but these coins are not put into general circulation by the authorities who instead sell them to collectors for prices higher than their face value. [[Andorra]] has reached an agreement with the EU to mint its own coin design, probably from 2013, but subject to ratification by the Andorran Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/euro/world/outside_euro_area/index_en.htm |title=The euro outside the euro area |work=ec.europa.eu |date=5 July 2011 [last update] |accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Future changes to national sides===
&quot;The national sides of all denominations of the euro circulation coins should bear an indication of the issuing Member State by means of the Member State’s name or an abbreviation of it.&quot;

&quot;The national side should not repeat any indication on the denomination, or any parts thereof, of the coin neither should it repeat the name of the single currency or of its subdivision, unless such indication stems from the use of a different alphabet.&quot;

&quot;This Recommendation should apply to national sides and edge letterings of both normal and commemorative euro circulation coins. It should not apply to the national sides and edge letterings of both normal and commemorative euro circulation coins which have been first issued prior to the adoption of this Recommendation.&quot;

The above paragraphs, from a European Commission [[Recommendation (European Union)|Recommendation]] of 19 December 2008, in essence, exhorted five eurozone members to change their national designs. Finland was the first state to do so, in 2007, Belgium did so in 2008 while Austria or Germany will not change their current designs for the time being.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title = No design change for Austrian and German euro coins (in German)|publisher = |date = 2008-02-01|url = http://www.zwei-euro.com/2-euro/|accessdate = 2008-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Greece is still pending.

==Small-denomination coins==
{{Multiple image|direction=vertical|align=right|image1=|image2=|width=150|caption2=The one and two cent coins are not used in Finland and the Netherlands, but remain legal tender there.}}
The one- and two-cent coins were initially introduced in order to ensure that the introduction of the euro was not used as an excuse by retailers to heavily round up prices. However, due to the cost of maintaining a circulation of low value coins, by business and the mints, [[Finland]] and the [[Netherlands]] round prices to the nearest five cents ([[Swedish rounding]]) if paying with cash, while producing only a handful of those coins for collectors, rather than general circulation.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC 101007&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/economy/penny.html Save the penny or leave the penny?], [[CBC News]] 2007-10-10&lt;/ref&gt;  The coins are still legal tender and produced outside these states.&lt;ref name=&quot;BW 230904&quot;/&gt; Despite this, many shops in the Netherlands refuse to accept them.

The [[Swedish rounding]] law in Finland was issued in January 2002 and thus before the coins were put into circulation. The Netherlands followed suit in September 2004, with [[Belgium]] making moves to follow in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;BW 230904&quot;/&gt; The Netherlands did so under pressure from retail businesses, which claimed that dealing with 1- and 2-cent coins was too expensive. After a successful experiment in the little town of [[Woerden]] in May 2004, retailers in the whole of the [[Netherlands]] have been permitted to round cash transactions to the nearest five-cent since September 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Stephen |last=Castle   |title=Smallest Euro coins dropped by two nations |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20040916/ai_n12808602 |work=Independent, The (London) |date=September 16, 2004 |accessdate=2008-07-15 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070124003944/http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20040916/ai_n12808602 |archivedate = January 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This is in part due to factors such as rising metal prices: [[De Nederlandsche Bank]] calculated it would save $36 million a year by not using the smaller coins. Other countries such as [[Germany]] favoured retaining the coins due to their desire for €1.99 prices, which appear more attractive to the consumer than a €2 price.&lt;ref name=&quot;BW 230904&quot;&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/bwdaily/dnflash/sep2004/nf20040923_2592_db017.htm Small Change, Big Annoyance in Europe], [[Business Week]] 2004-09-23&lt;/ref&gt; This is echoed by the [[European Central Bank]] itself which supports the coins, stating it allows businesses to calculate prices more exactly to attract consumers, such as 99 cents.&lt;ref name=&quot;1&amp;2 cent FAQ&quot;&gt;[http://www.ecb.int/bc/faqbc/circulation/html/index.en.html#q11 What is the benefit of issuing low-denomination (1 and 2-cent) coins?], [[European Central Bank]]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a [[Eurobarometer]] survey of EU citizens, Germans are most sceptical about the removal of the one- and two-cent coins from complete circulation in the eurozone, however on average there is a majority for their removal (58% for the one cent coin and 52% for the two cent coin in 2005). The Belgians are most supportive of their removal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/flash/fl175_en.pdf The euro, 4 years after the introduction of the banknotes and coins] (PDF), [[Eurobarometer]] 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1-, 2-, and 5-cent coins account for approximately 80% of all new coins minted in the eurozone. Due to the expense of producing such low value coinage, the Commission with some member states have proposed that costs could be cut by having a common design on both sides of these coins, rather than minting numerous different designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;125stand&quot;&gt;[http://europa.eu/scadplus/leg/en/lvb/l25087.htm Five years of Euro banknotes and coins], [[Europa (web portal)]] 2007-01-17&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features for persons with impaired sight==
[[File:Eurocent edges (2,10,20).jpg|thumb|2c, 10c and 20c coins,&lt;br /&gt; showing their unique edges.]]
Euro coins were designed in cooperation with organisations representing [[blindness|blind]] persons, and as a result they incorporate many features allowing them to be distinguished by touch alone. In addition, their visual appearance is designed to make them easy to tell apart for persons who cannot read the inscriptions on the coins.

The coins increase in size and weight with value.  Of the eight denominations of euro coins, the three lowest denominations are small, resemble copper in colour and are quite thin and light.  The next three denominations resemble gold in colour and are thicker as well as heavier.  The highest two denominations are bimetallic, being generally larger and thicker than the lower denominations.

In general, the greater the value, the heavier and larger the coin. Copper colour identifies low value; gold colour identifies medium value; two different metals identify high value.

* The €0.01 is the smallest of all coins, and size is probably the best description.  Its diameter is about the size of the thumb-nail of an average adult.  The edge of the coin is smooth and it is copper in colour.
* The €0.02 is slightly larger than the one-cent coin and is of the same copper colour.  A distinctive groove runs circumferentially around its edge, easily felt by a finger; the groove gives the visual and tactile impression that it consists of two coins pressed into one, though this is not the case.
* The €0.05 is the largest of the copper coins, but is only slightly larger than the two-cent coin.  It has a smooth edge.
* The €0.10 is gold in colour. It is very slightly smaller than the five-cent piece, but is much thicker, and has a coarse serration around the edge. It is heavier than any of the copper coins.
* The €0.20 is larger than the ten-cent coin and is also gold in colour.  It has a unique group of seven notches (forming a [[spanish flower]] shape) around its otherwise smooth edge, making it easy to recognise by touch.
* The €0.50 is also gold in colour and is noticeably thicker, heavier, and larger than the coins of smaller denominations; it also has a coarsely serrated edge.
* The €1 has a silver-coloured interior and a gold-coloured perimeter.  The edge is distinctively marked with alternating smooth and finely serrated sections. It is of about the same thickness and weight as the fifty-cent piece, but its edge markings readily distinguish it from that coin.
* The €2 is of the same colours as the one-euro coin, but they are reversed: the perimeter is silver coloured whilst the interior is gold coloured. It has the largest diameter of any euro coin. Its edge has a fine, continuous serration which is embossed with stars and letters differing between nations. Whilst this is difficult to detect by touch, this may not be necessary in order to distinguish it from other coins, given its size.

Although there have been other currencies predating the euro that were specifically designed in similar ways (different sizes, colours, and ridges) to aid the visually impaired, the introduction of the euro constitutes the first time that authorities have consulted associations representing the blind and visually impaired before the release of a currency.

==Counterfeit coins==
Approximately 100,000 counterfeit euro coins are taken from circulation annually, and a similar number is seized before it can be released. Given a total circulation of 56 billion coins, counterfeit coins are relatively rare. About half the counterfeits feature the German national design, but counterfeits have been detected for every issuing country. The great majority of counterfeit coins are €2 (87% in 2004), with most of the rest being €1, and a few 50-cent coins.

Seized coins from circulation (totals):
:2010 – 186 000&lt;ref name=EuroCounterfeiting2010&gt;{{cite web|url=http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=IP/11/47 |title=EUROPA - Press Releases - Euro coin counterfeiting in 2010 |publisher=Europa.eu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:2009 – 172,100&lt;ref name=EuroCounterfeiting2009&gt;{{cite web|url=http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/10/2 |title=EUROPA - Press Releases - Euro coin counterfeiting in 2009 |publisher=Europa.eu |date= |accessdate=2011-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:2008 – 195,900&lt;ref name=EuroCounterfeiting2009/&gt;
:2007 – 211,100&lt;ref name=AntiFraud2007&gt;{{cite web|url=http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/08/10 |title=EUROPA - Press Releases - Euro coin counterfeiting in 2007 |publisher=Europa.eu |date= |accessdate=2011-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:2006 – 163,800&lt;ref name=AntiFraud2007/&gt;
:2005 – 100,500&lt;ref name=AntiFraud2007/&gt;
:2004 – 75,564
:2003 – 26,339&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coinauthentication.co.uk/newsletter8.html#circul |title=The euro counterfeit coins withdrawn from circulation in 2006. |publisher=Coinauthentication.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The European Technical and Scientific Centre estimates that up to two million counterfeit coins were put into circulation in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ec.europa.eu/anti_fraud/pages_euro/etsc2002_en.pdf European Technical &amp; Scientific Centre. Activity in 2002] European Commission. European Anti-Fraud Office&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent investigations by the European Commission have shown that the level of sophistication in the counterfeits is increasing, making prompt detection even more difficult.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.eux.tv/article.aspx?articleId=20053 | title='Most sophisticated' fake euro coin network uncovered in Italy}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Irish [[Member of the European Parliament|MEP]] [[Eoin Ryan, Jnr|Eoin Ryan]] called for tighter regulation over tokens and medals that are being increasingly used for small purchases mainly in vending machines across Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/public/story_page/043-43307-336-12-49-907-20081201STO43283-2008-01-12-2008/default_en.htm Euro Coins need protection] Last retrieved 01-12-08&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commemorative issues==
{{main|€2 commemorative coins}}

Each state allowed to issue coins may also mint one [[commemorative coin]] each year. Only €2 coins may be used in this way (for them to be legal tender) and there is a limit on the number that can be issued. The coin must show the normal design criteria, such as the twelve stars, the year and the issuing country.

Greece was the first country to issue a commemorative coin, and was followed by all but Cyprus, Estonia and Ireland. However, in 2007 every eurozone state participated in the [[Treaty of Rome]] programme, where all member states issued a coin of similar design to commemorate the signing of the Treaty of Rome, the only difference being the name of the issuing country and the language of the text.

This was repeated in 2009 in commemoration of the 10th anniversary of the [[introduction of the euro]]. The design was selected by electronic voting by EU citizens{{dead link|url=http://www.eurodesigncontest.eu/index.cfm|date=August 2009}}.

In 2006, Germany began issuing a series of coins, the [[German Bundesländer commemorative coin|German Bundesländer series]], showing each of the [[states of Germany]] on its coins; this will last until 2021.

[[Spain]] started a commemorative coin series ''{{lang|es|Patrimonio de la Humanidad de la UNESCO}}'' (UNESCO World Heritage) in 2010, commemorating all of Spain's [[UNESCO World Heritage Sites in Spain|UNESCO World Heritage Sites]], which could continue until 2050. The order in which the coin for a specific site is issued coincides with the order in which they were declared a UNESCO World Heritage site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | date=2010-01-19 | url=http://www.zwei-euro.com/news/artikel/a/2010/01/19/article/weitere-ausgaben-der-2-euro-gedenkmuenzenserie-unesco-weltkulturerbestaetten.html | title=''{{lang|de|Spanien: Weitere Ausgaben der 2-Euro-Gedenkmünzenserie „UNESCO-Weltkulturerbestätten“}}'' | accessdate=2010-01-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Malta will issue a series of five €2 commemorative coins, all related to the Maltese constitutional history. The first coin will be released in 2011 and the last coin will be minted in 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/euro/cash/commemorative/2011_en.htm&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/euro/cash/commemorative/2011_en.htm |title=Commemorative coins 2011 - ECFIN - European Commission |publisher=Ec.europa.eu |date= |accessdate=2011-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gold and silver commemorative issues===
{{main|Euro gold and silver commemorative coins}}

A legacy of old national practice is the minting of silver and gold commemorative coins. Unlike normal issues, these coins ''are not [[legal tender]] throughout the eurozone'', but only in the country where they are issued. For instance, a €10 [[Finland|Finnish]] commemorative coin cannot be used in [[Portugal]].

However, these gold coins are intended for collectors as their bullion value vastly exceeds their face value. Some silver coins, such as the German €10 commemoratives, are often available at banks and some retailers at face value. These coins, however, generally do not circulate but are kept by collectors.

It is uncertain whether the [[Council of the European Union|Council of Ministers]] will grant them legal tender status elsewhere outside national boundaries, as [[San Marino]], [[Monaco]], and the [[Vatican City]] also issue these kind of coins.

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{commons cat}}
* [http://www.ecb.int European Central Bank]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/theeuro The Euro - Information Website]
* [http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/site/en/oj/2005/l_186/l_18620050718en00010002.pdf Common guidelines for the national sides of euro circulation coins]

{{Euro topics|state=expanded}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Euro Coins}}
[[Category:Coins of the Eurozone| ]]

[[frp:Piéces en erô]]
[[cs:Euromince]]
[[da:Euromønter]]
[[de:Euromünzen]]
[[et:Euromünt]]
[[el:Κέρματα ευρώ]]
[[es:Monedas de euro]]
[[eo:Eŭro-moneroj]]
[[ext:Moneas d'euru]]
[[fr:Pièces en euros destinées à la circulation]]
[[ga:Boinn euro]]
[[gl:Moedas de euro]]
[[ko:유로 동전]]
[[is:Evrumynt]]
[[it:Monete euro]]
[[lb:Euromënzen]]
[[lt:Euro monetos]]
[[hu:Euróérmék]]
[[nl:Euromunten]]
[[ja:ユーロ硬貨]]
[[no:Euromynter]]
[[pt:Moedas de euro]]
[[ro:Monede euro]]
[[ru:Монеты евро]]
[[sq:Monedhat Euro]]
[[sk:Eurominca]]
[[sl:Evrokovanci]]
[[fi:Eurokolikot]]
[[sv:Euromynt]]
[[uk:Монети євро]]
[[zh:歐元硬幣]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
