<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="539600" ns="0" title="Don Imus"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
|name        = Don Imus 
|image       = 
|birth_name  = John Donald Imus, Jr.
|birth_date  = {{Birth date and age|mf=yes|1940|07|23}}
|birth_place = [[Riverside, California|Riverside]], [[California]], U.S.
|occupation  = [[Radio]] and [[television]] [[talk show host]], writer, [[humorist]], [[Minister (Christianity)|Minister]](Universal Life Church)
|spouse      =  Harriet Showalter (1st)&lt;br/&gt;[[Deirdre Imus|Deirdre Coleman]] (2nd)
|URL         = 
|agent       =
|allegiance  = United States of America
|rank        = 
|branch      = [[United States Marine Corps]]
|serviceyears= 1957 to 1960 
|commands    = 
|battles     = 
|awards      = 
}}
'''John Donald &quot;Don&quot; Imus, Jr.''' (born July 23, 1940) is an American [[radio personality|radio host]], [[humorist]], philanthropist and writer. His [[radio syndication|nationally-syndicated]] [[talk radio|talk show]], ''[[Imus in the Morning]]'', is broadcast throughout the United States by [[Citadel Media]] and relayed on television by the [[Fox Business Network]].

==Personal life==
Imus was born in [[Riverside, California]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.biography.com/search/article.do?id=9542196|title=Don Imus Biography|publisher=''Biography Channel'' |date=April 14, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; the son of Frances E. (née Moore) and John Donald Imus, Sr.,&lt;ref name=&quot;bookref1&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Reed|first=Jim|title=Everything Imus: all you ever wanted to know about Don Imus|publisher=Carol Publishing Group|year=1999|pages=10, 197|id=ISBN 1559725044}}&lt;/ref&gt; older brother of [[Fred Imus]]. He was raised on a sprawling cattle ranch called The Willows near [[Kingman, Arizona]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://affiliates.abcradionetworks.com/abcradionetworks/imusbio.pdf|format=PDF|title=Don Imus Bio|publisher=''Citadel Media'' |date=November 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; He served in the [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] as a bugler from 1957 to 1960. 
 
Imus battled [[alcoholism]] during his early career in New York, but in 1987 finally pursued effective treatment. (As of 2008, he has remained sober for 20 years).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/wireStory?id=1481976&amp;CMP=OTC-RSSFeeds0312 |title=Don Imus still sober after 21 years|publisher=''Associated Press'' |date=April 14, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988, with his [[drug addiction|cocaine]] and alcohol addictions now legendary in show business, Imus reshaped his show from strictly comedy into a forum for political issues, charitable causes and news-based [[parody|parodies]].

In 1979, he divorced his first wife, Harriet.  He married his second wife, [[Deirdre Imus|Deirdre Coleman]] on December 17, 1994.  He has two stepdaughters that he adopted from his first marriage, two daughters from that marriage, and one son, Frederick Wyatt ([[nickname]]d Wyatt, born July 3, 1998), from his current marriage. Both Don and Deirdre Imus are [[Vegetarianism|vegetarian]]s.

In 1999, Imus and his wife founded the [[Imus Ranch]], a working {{convert|4000|acre|km2|sing=on}} cattle ranch near [[Ribera, New Mexico]], {{convert|50|mi|0}} southeast of [[Santa Fe, New Mexico|Santa Fe]], for children with [[cancer]], as well as siblings of [[Sudden infant death syndrome|SIDS]] victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Don Imus has prostate cancer|agency=Associated Press|date=March 16, 2009|url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/entertainment/news/bal-don-imus-cancer-0316,0,777443.story|accessdate=March 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between [[Memorial Day]] and [[Labor Day]] each year, the Imus family volunteers their time at the Imus ranch. Imus continues his broadcasts from a studio there, while the rest of his cast broadcast from New York. In 2000, Imus suffered serious injuries after a fall from a horse at his ranch, and broadcast several shows from a hospital.

Imus maintains three residences; an apartment in [[Manhattan]], a waterfront mansion valued at $25 million, in [[Westport, Connecticut]], and the Imus Ranch in Ribera, New Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.westportnow.com/index.php?/v2/comments/donahue_and_thomas_put_westport_house_on_market_for_25_million/ |title=Donahue and Thomas put Westport house on market for $25 million|publisher=''Westport Now.com'' |date=August 16, 2005 |accessdate=July 4, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 16, 2009, Imus announced on his radio show that he had been diagnosed with [[Prostate cancer staging|stage two]] [[prostate cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,509347,00.html |title=Don Imus Suffering From Stage II Prostate Cancer |work=Fox News |date=March 16, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early career==
Imus was a [[brakeman]] on the [[Southern Pacific Railroad]].&lt;ref&gt;Late Night with Davis Letterman; Episode #118; February 24, 1994; Note: He had previously attended broadcasting school in LA&lt;/ref&gt;  After hearing a morning disc-jockey, he went to the nearby radio station and persuaded the owner to hire him. Thus he began his career as a radio [[disc jockey]] on June 28, 1968 at radio station [[KUTY]] in [[Palmdale, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://imonthe.net/imus/nfaq.htm#3 |title=Imonthe.Net |publisher=Imonthe.Net |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He stayed at the station until 1969&lt;ref&gt;Imonthe.net&lt;/ref&gt; when he left for a job at KJOY, a small radio station in [[Stockton, California]].  He was later fired for saying &quot;hell&quot; on air.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18081950/|author= |title= Controversy has often dogged Don Imus |publisher=''msnbc.com'' |date=April 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; After being fired in Stockton, he went to [[KXOA]] in [[Sacramento, California]]. His on-air pranks, such as calling up a restaurant and ordering 1200 hamburgers to go, made his show immensely popular and boosted ratings. He was inspired to pursue a career in radio by listening to California radio personality [[Don MacKinnon]].

==''Imus in the Morning''==
{{Main|Imus in the Morning}}

After a stint at [[WHKW|WGAR]] radio in [[Cleveland, Ohio]], Imus moved to New York City and [[WNBC (AM)|WNBC radio]] in December 1971. During this first stint at WNBC, Imus recorded three record albums, two for the [[RCA Records|RCA Victor]] label (''1200 Hamburgers to Go'', including some of his more popular &quot;humor&quot; from KXOA, WGAR and WNBC broadcasts, and ''One Sacred Chicken to Go with Anthrax'', a primarily studio-created album centering on his satirical character, The Right Rev. Dr. Billy Sol Hargus) and one for the [[Bang Records|Bang]] label (''This Honky's Nuts'', an album of his stand up comedy act at the Manhattan nightclub &quot;Jimmy's&quot;). There was also a 1973 RCA Victor single, &quot;Son of Checkers,&quot; issued by Imus.

Imus was fired from WNBC in August 1977 along with several of the station's other personalities, in an effort to revamp the station's sound and boost ratings.  In 1978 he returned to Cleveland radio as afternoon drive host on [[WHK]], making the front page of the ''[[Cleveland Plain Dealer]]'' on his first day back in town.  During that year, Imus commuted between Cleveland and New York to tape a TV talk show, ''Imus Plus'' at [[WNYW|WNEW-TV]]. (The show was nationally syndicated by [[Metromedia]], which owned both WHK and WNEW-TV at the time.)   

In a surprise change of fortune Imus was rehired by WNBC in September 1979, and revived his morning drive show.  From 1982 to 1985, the station also employed talk-radio host [[Howard Stern]], and WNBC heavily promoted the pair in print and television ads, which often featured the slogan &quot;If We Weren't So Bad, We Wouldn't Be So Good.&quot;  Although Stern's show aired later in the day, Imus and Stern often made brief appearances on each other's shows, giving the audience an occasional glimpse of an on-and-off-air rivalry that continued for many years.

During this period, Imus was best known for character ''Billy Sol Hargus'', a radio [[Evangelism|evangelist]] whose name was a cross between infamous real-life radio and television preacher [[Billy James Hargis]] and real-life Texas fertilizer [[swindler]] [[Billie Sol Estes]]. As Hargus, Imus touted on-air the merits of the &quot;First Church of the Gooey Death and Discount House of Worship&quot;. Imus published the 1981 best-selling novel ''God's Other Son'' that further depicted Hargus's adventures. The novel was republished in 1994 by popular demand and spent seven weeks on the [[New York Times bestseller list|''New York Times'' bestseller list]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.hawes.com/1995/1995-01-08.pdf |title=The York Times Best Seller List-January 8, 1995|publisher='' www.hawes.com'' |date=April 13, 2007|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other regular Imus characters included the supposed general manager &quot;Geraldo Santana Banana&quot; (played by doo-wop singer [[Larry Chance]]), and &quot;Moby Worm&quot;, a monstrous creature who devoured local schools (which was reported on the show's &quot;breaking news updates&quot;).

Imus was also the utility announcer for [[Geraldo Rivera]]'s monthly TV series ''[[Good Night, America]]'', which aired as a recurring segment of [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]'s ''[[Wide World of Entertainment]]'' program, and he was one of the inaugural [[VJ (media personality)|video jockeys]] for the launch of the [[VH-1]] cable network in 1985.

In 1988, WNBC radio was sold to [[Emmis Broadcasting]]; on October 7, 1988, WNBC permanently signed off the air and Emmis' WFAN was moved from 1050 AM to WNBC's former spot, 660 AM. ''Imus in the Morning'' remained at 660 AM among WFAN's sports programs with his music and comedy bits as the staples of the program and the beginnings of a political forum.

The radio show became nationally syndicated in 1993, and began [[simulcast]]ing on [[MSNBC]] in 1996. He wore his signature [[cowboy hat]] during his broadcasts.

Imus’s behavior has often drawn the attention of the press. He famously called [[Rush Limbaugh]] &quot;a fat, pill-popping loser&quot; and a &quot;drug-addled gas bag&quot;, and [[Lesley Stahl]] a &quot;gutless, lying weasel.&quot; His comedic exchange of quips (&quot;fat pig&quot;) regarding his show’s former news reader, [[Contessa Brewer]], made news, as did Brewer's response (&quot;cantankerous old fool&quot;). When [[Tucker Carlson]] brought up Brewer on the program in 2005, Imus hung up on him, calling him &quot;a bowtie-wearing little pussy.&quot; 

While on the air during the attacks of September 11, 2001, the ''Imus in the Morning'' program was among the few live American broadcasts to continue airing commercials well after the first reports of the attack. While speaking live with famed sportscaster [[Warner Wolf]], who was being interviewed by Imus from his high-rise apartment with direct sight to the World Trade Center, the second plane hit the towers with Mr. Wolf literally giving play-by-play. The commercials that continued to air included one for a major airline, Continental, along with a jeweler based in the World Trade Center, and a spot read &quot;live&quot; on the air for a broadcasting school, in which it was said careers in broadcasting were &quot;exploding.&quot; Imus noted the irony, but continued reading the spot. His production staff of 13 years also had great difficulty in simulcasting live TV news coverage when requested by Imus. This staff stayed with Imus after the MSNBC debacle and moved with him to the new ABC/RFD-TV arrangement. Imus is still plagued by technical difficulties, which have become part of his daily comedy diatribe.

Imus was instrumental in raising over $60 million for the [[Center for the Intrepid]], a Texas rehabilitation facility for soldiers wounded in the [[Iraq War]]. The largest technological center of its kind in the country, it is designed to help treat disabled veterans and help them with their transition back into the community.  Imus has also taken on the cause of the living conditions at the [[Walter Reed Army Medical Center]], visiting wounded veterans at the hospital to boost morale. Imus's reporting preceded Army resignations, including that of Lieutenant General [[Kevin Kiley]], then Army Surgeon General. Imus had earlier criticized Kiley's personal fitness for military duty and dedication to wounded soldiers.

==Rutgers women's basketball controversy==
On April 4, 2007, during a discussion about the [[NCAA Women's Basketball Championship]], Imus characterized the [[Rutgers University]] [[Athletics at Rutgers University#Women's basketball|women's basketball team]] players as &quot;rough girls&quot; commenting on their tattoos.  His executive producer [[Bernard McGuirk]] responded by referring to them as &quot;hardcore hos&quot;. The discussion continued with Imus describing the girls as &quot;nappy-headed hos&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NappyHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/nation/20070412-1500-nappyhair.html |author=Deepti Hajela |title=Don Imus' 'nappy' remark has long, hurtful history in describing African-American hair |agency=Associated Press |date=April 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;demean&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.insidebayarea.com/ci_5649549 |title=Imus' remarks demean women of all colors |author=Brenda Payton|publisher=Inside Bay Area (ANG Newspapers)|date=April 12, 2007|accessdate=April 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and McGuirk remarking that the two teams looked like the &quot;jigaboos versus the wannabes&quot; mentioned in [[Spike Lee]]'s film, ''[[School Daze]]''; apparently referring to the two teams' differing appearances.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/industryNews/idUSN1237895620070412|title=Furor over Imus puts heat on other broadcasters|author=Daniel Trotta|publisher=Reuters|date=April 12, 2007|accessdate=April 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Imus called women's basketball team &quot;nappy-headed hos&quot; |url=http://mediamatters.org/items/200704040011 |publisher=mediamatters.org |date=April 4, 2007 |accessdate=April 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; At 6:00 p.m. that evening, [[Media Matters for America]] released recorded transcripts to the news media highlighting the brief exchange:

{{bquote |IMUS: That's some rough girls from Rutgers. Man, they got tattoos and—&lt;p&gt;McGUIRK: Some hard-core hos.&lt;p&gt;IMUS: That's some nappy-headed hos. I'm gonna tell you that now, man, that's some—whew. And the girls from [[Tennessee Lady Volunteers basketball|Tennessee]], they all look cute, you know, so, like—kinda like—I don't know.&lt;p&gt;McGUIRK: A [[Spike Lee]] thing.&lt;p&gt;IMUS: Yeah.&lt;p&gt;McGUIRK: The [[School Daze|Jigaboos vs. the Wannabes]]—that movie that he had.}}

After some outrage from the initial repeated reports, Imus dismissed the incident as &quot;some idiot comment meant to be amusing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Networks Condemn Remarks by Imus |publisher=The New York Times |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/arts/television/07imus.html?hp |date=April 7, 2007 |accessdate=April 8, 2007 | first=David | last=Carr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070407/ap_en_bu/imus_apology;_ylt=AhHk5jL1T6SiLGVyVKPGcE2mG78C |title = Despite apology, critics want Imus out |accessdate = April 7, 2007 |last = McShane |first = Larry  |date = April 7, 2007 |publisher = ''Yahoo! News'' |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070426214259/http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070407/ap_en_bu/imus_apology;_ylt=AhHk5jL1T6SiLGVyVKPGcE2mG78C &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = April 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/page2/index?archive=070406 |title = Imus should be fired |accessdate =April 7, 2007 |last = Hill |first = Jemele |date = April 6, 2007 |publisher = ''ESPN.com: Page 2'' }}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, he tried to rationalize his words by saying that &quot;nappy-headed hoes&quot; is a term that rap artists use to refer to African-American women.&lt;ref&gt;Hill, Simona J. And Dave Ramsaran. [http://books.google.com/books?id=09F-6Tl-HkoC&amp;pg=PA85 Hip Hop and Inequality: Searching for the &quot;Real&quot; Slim Shady]. Amherst, N.Y.: Cambria Press, 2009, ISBN 978-1-60-497651-9, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; He said: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;That phrase [nappy-headed ho] didn't originate in the White Community. That phrase originated in the Black community. Young Black women all through that society are demeaned and disparaged and disrespected by their own Black men, and they are called that name in Black [[Hip Hop music|hip hop]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Don Imus quoted in [http://books.google.com/books?id=g4K0QW_FLSMC&amp;pg=PA41 ''Cultural Codes: Makings of a Black Music Philosophy: An Interpretive History from Spirituals to Hip Hop''], William C. Banfield, Lanham: Scarecrow Press, 2010, ISBN 978-0-81-087286-8, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In response to mounting public censure, Imus issued a statement of apology:
{{bquote|I want to take a moment to apologize for an insensitive and ill-conceived remark we made the other morning regarding the Rutgers women's basketball team, which lost to Tennessee in the [[NCAA]] championship game on Tuesday.  It was completely inappropriate and we can understand why people were offended. Our characterization was thoughtless and stupid, and we are sorry.}}

On April 9, Imus appeared on [[Al Sharpton]]'s syndicated radio talk show, ''[[Keepin It Real with Al Sharpton]]'' to address the controversy. Sharpton called the comments &quot;abominable&quot;, &quot;[[racism|racist]]&quot;, and &quot;[[sexism|sexist]]&quot;, and repeated his earlier demand that Imus be fired.  Imus said, &quot;Our agenda is to be funny and sometimes we go too far. And this time we went way too far. Here's what I've learned: that you can't make fun of everybody, because some people don't deserve it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/I/IMUS_PROTESTS?SITE=FLSTU&amp;SECTION=HOME&amp;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT |title=Imus takes his lumps on Sharpton's show |publisher=''[[Associated Press]]'' |date=April 9, 2007 |accessdate=April 9, 2007}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly thereafter Imus was suspended.  Media commentators were divided on the suspension: on MSNBC's ''Scarborough Country'' on April, 10,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18056324/ |title=Transcript of Scarborough Country April 10, 2007|publisher=MSNBC|date=April 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; for example, [[Pat Buchanan]] said that Imus is &quot;a good guy... [who] made a bad mistake and apologized for it&quot; and that the show should stay on the air. Comedian [[Bill Maher]] said that if a comedian apologizes for stepping over a line, that should suffice.  Steve Adubato, an MSNBC media analyst, disagreed, saying that this incident was &quot;not isolated&quot;. [[Joe Klein]] made the same charge, referring to Imus's comment about ''[[New York Times]]'' reporter [[Gwen Ifill]] 14 years before as evidence of a pattern of offensive comments.  On ''[[The View (U.S. TV series)|The View]]'', [[Rosie O'Donnell]] spoke out in support of keeping Imus on the air on [[free speech]] grounds,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsbusters.org/node/11976|title=Rosie on Imus: 'Thought Police' Are Coming
|publisher=[[NewsBusters]], Exposing and Combating Liberal Media Bias|author=Justin McCarthy|date= April 10, 2007 |accessdate=September 15, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; while [[Emil Steiner]] of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' argued that [[Al Sharpton]] used the issue to further divide America along racial lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://blog.washingtonpost.com/offbeat/2007/04/al_sharpton_don_imus_a_distrac.html/ |title=Al Sharpton, Don Imus &amp; A Distracted Nation|publisher=The Washington Post|date=April 14, 2007}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Rutgers basketball team held a news conference at which coach [[C. Vivian Stringer]] stated that the team would meet with Imus to discuss his comments. Several of the players expressed their outrage over his remarks. Team captain Essence Carson said Imus' remarks had &quot;stolen a moment of pure grace from us&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heraldstandard.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=18193723&amp;BRD=2280&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=468632&amp;rfi=6|
title=Rutgers team to meet with Imus; Stringer calls comments 'deplorable'|publisher=The Herald Standard,PA |date=April 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courant.com/sports/college/hc-rutgers0411.artapr11,0,1279931.story?coll=hc-headlines-sports-college |publisher=The Hartford Courant |title=Imus' remark Despicable|date=April 11, 2007|author=David Heuschkel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

African American ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' columnist [[Clarence Page]], at one time a frequent guest, once had confronted Imus about his characterization of certain black athletes and got Imus to take a pledge to stop. After the Rutgers team incident, Page said he would not appear on the show again and said of the original two-week suspension:  

{{bquote|I know other stations... some shock jock who lost his job for less than this, or been at least suspended for a month or two. Why does Don, a repeat offender, keep getting away with it? I want to know.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=NewsHour with Jim Lehrer |url=http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/media/jan-june07/imus_04-09.html |title=Clarence Page of the '&amp;#39;Chicago Tribune'&amp;#39; on PBS' NewsHour April 9,007 |publisher=Pbs.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} CBS board member and former [[NAACP]] president [[Bruce S. Gordon]] said that Imus should not be allowed to come back even after the suspension, claiming that his remarks &quot;crossed the line, a very bright line that divides our country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= MSNBC pulls 'Imus in the Morning' |publisher=CNN|date=April 11, 2007 |url= http://www.cnn.com/2007/SHOWBIZ/TV/04/11/imus.rutgers/index.html |accessdate=April 11, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 11, 2007, Steve Capus of NBC News, announced that MSNBC would no longer [[simulcast]] ''Imus in the Morning'', effective immediately. While the decision came on the same day that a few advertisers left Imus, the network also said employee concerns played a role. Sen. (and at the time presidential candidate) Barack Obama, and several high-profile NBC African-American personalities, including [[Al Roker]] previously a friendly guest on the show, opposed Imus's return. The absence and silence from Imus's frequent NBC guests [[Brian Williams]], [[Andrea Mitchell]], [[David Gregory (journalist)|David Gregory]], [[Chris Matthews]] and close friend [[Tim Russert]] was too obvious to ignore and foreshadowed NBC's future action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tim Russert Abandons Don Imus: Leads the Cowardly Suits at NBC |url=http://www.nationalledger.com/cgi-bin/artman/exec/view.cgi?archive=11&amp;num=12700|author=[[Cliff Kincaid]] |date=April 12, 2007 |publisher = The National Ledger |accessdate=September 15, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In announcing the decision, [[Steve Capus]], President of NBC News, said: 

{{bquote|These comments were deeply hurtful to many, many people. And we've had any number of employee conversations, discussions, emails, phone calls.  And when you listen to the passion and the people who come to the conclusion that there should not be any room for this sort of conversation and dialogue on our air, it was the only decision we could reach.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= NBC News: 'Only decision we could reach' |publisher=[[MSNBC]]|date=April 11, 2007 |url= http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18063461/ |accessdate=April 11, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The next day, [[CBS Radio]] canceled ''Imus in the Morning'', effective immediately.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ST0y1mt9ufE Breaking News From MSNBC – Don Imus Fired From CBS Radio] (From [[YouTube]])&lt;/ref&gt;  CBS President and Chief Executive Officer [[Leslie Moonves]] stated: 

{{bquote|From the outset, I believe all of us have been deeply upset and revulsed by the statements that were made on our air about the young women who represented Rutgers University in the NCAA Women's Basketball Championship with such class, energy and talent. There has been much discussion of the effect language like this has on our young people, particularly young women of color trying to make their way in this society. That consideration has weighed most heavily on our minds as we made our decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= Newly fired Imus meets with Rutgers players|publisher=CNN|date=April 13, 2007 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/SHOWBIZ/TV/04/12/imus.rutgers/index.html |accessdate=April 13, 2007 }} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= CBS fires Don Imus from radio show|agency=Associated Press|date=April 13, 2007 |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18072804/ |accessdate=April 13, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
   
The day before, CBS chairman [[Sumner Redstone]] said he trusted Moonves would &quot;do the right thing,&quot; but didn't elaborate. Moonves had met with Sharpton and [[Jesse Jackson]] shortly before the announcement was made.&lt;ref name=&quot;CartSteinTimes&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/13imus.html|title=Off the Air: The Light Goes Out for Don Imus|author=Bill Carter and Jacques Steinberg|publisher=The New York Times |date=April 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In an internal memo, Moonves said that employee concerns were a factor in the decision to cancel Imus's show, but also said that the decision was &quot;about a lot more than Imus.&quot; Moonves said that CBS had to take Imus off the air in order to change &quot;a culture that permits a certain level of objectionable expression that hurts and demeans a wide range of people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Racist remarks cost Imus CBS radio job|agency=Associated Press |author=David Bauder|date=April 12, 2007 |url=http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2007/04/12/msnbc_drops_imus_simulcast/ |accessdate=April 12, 2007 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seven sponsors had either pulled their ads outright or suspended advertising on Imus's show to protest his remarks — [[General Motors]] (Imus's biggest advertiser), [[Staples Inc.]], [[GlaxoSmithKline]], [[Sprint Nextel]], [[1800Petmeds|PetMeds]]
, [[American Express]] and [[Procter &amp; Gamble]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Apology&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title= Rutgers coach says Imus' apology accepted|publisher=CNN |author=|date=April 13, 2007 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/SHOWBIZ/TV/04/13/imus.rutgers/index.html |accessdate=April 13, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070417140252/http://www.cnn.com/2007/SHOWBIZ/TV/04/13/imus.rutgers/index.html |archivedate = April 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; One other advertiser, [[Bigelow Tea Company|Bigelow Tea]], expressed uncertainty at renewing their ads with Imus's show.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bigelow Tea and other advertisers response&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601087&amp;sid=a0rvIotudMc8&amp;refer=home |publisher=Bloomberg News |title=Staples, P&amp;G Halt Advertising Over Imus's Remarks (Update3) |date=April 10, 2007|author=Mary Jane Credeur and Don Jeffrey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Just hours after the announcement of his firing, Imus met with Stringer and her team at [[Drumthwacket]], the New Jersey governor's mansion. The three-hour meeting was arranged by [[Buster Soaries]], the former New Jersey Secretary of State and Stringer's pastor. New Jersey governor [[Jon Corzine]] planned to attend the meeting but was injured in a car accident on the way to the meeting.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= N.J. Gov. Corzine in car accident, leg broken|publisher=Reuters |author=Jon Hurdle|date=April 13, 2007 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/04/13/AR2007041300795.html |accessdate=April 13, 2007 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Imus left without commenting, but Stringer said the meeting went well.  She later commented that they had accepted Imus's apology, and &quot;It would sadden me for anyone to lose their job,... And he came [to the meeting] in spite of the fact that he lost his job. So let's give him credit for that.&quot;  She also emphasized that the basketball team had not called for Imus to be fired.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apology&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= Host meets with players he insulted, but it's not enough to save program|publisher=[[New York Daily News]] |author=Adam Nichols and Corky Siemaszko|date=April 13, 2007 |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/news/2007/04/13/2007-04-13_youre_don_for_cbs_tells_imus-1.html |accessdate=April 13, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

CBS was criticized by some as being too harsh for canceling Imus's show. Senator [[John Kerry]] said a &quot;long suspension&quot; would be &quot;appropriate to pay a price on the airwaves but I’m not sure that it was appropriate to say you’re off forever.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerry&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title= John Kerry Says Don Imus Shouldn't Have Been Fired |publisher=NY1 (tv channel) |date=April 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subsequent litigation===
By May 2, 2007, Imus had hired prominent attorney [[Martin Garbus]] to pursue a wrongful termination lawsuit against CBS for the remaining $40 million on his five-year contract. The contract contained a clause indicating CBS hired and supported Imus to exhibit &quot;irreverent&quot; and &quot;controversial&quot; programming.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=  Imus hires attorney, will likely sue CBS |author=Ed Payne|publisher=CNN|date=May 3, 2007 |url= http://www.cnn.com/2007/SHOWBIZ/05/03/imus.cbs/index.html |accessdate=May 3, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On August 14, 2007, CBS announced a settlement with Imus on his $40 million contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBSsettle&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title= CBS says settles with fired shock jock Don Imus |author=Daniel Trotta|publisher=Reuters|date=August 14, 2007 |url=http://ca.today.reuters.com/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=entertainmentNews&amp;storyID=2007-08-14T170103Z_01_WEN0418_RTRIDST_0_ENTERTAINMENT-IMUS-CBS-COL.XML |accessdate=September 12, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the same day, Rutgers basketball player [[Kia Vaughn]], one of the women involved in the controversy, filed suit against Don Imus, [[NBC Universal]], [[CBS Corporation]], MSNBC, CBS Radio, [[Viacom]], [[Westwood One]] radio, and Bernard McGuirk, citing slander, libel, and defamation of character. Vaughn was the only player to pursue legal damages brought on by the controversy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://abcnews.go.com/TheLaw/story?id=3479449&amp;page=1 |title=ABC News:Rutgers' Player sues Imus, NBC, CBS|publisher=''ABC News'' |month=August | year=2007 |accessdate=August 14, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vaughn dropped the lawsuit against Imus on September 11, 2007, citing her desire to concentrate on her studies and basketball training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Rutgers' Vaughn withdraws lawsuit against Imus, CBS|agency=Associated Press |publisher=[[USA Today]]|date=September 12, 2007 |url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/womensbasketball/bigeast/2007-09-12-rutgers-imus-suit-withdrawn_N.htm |accessdate=September 12, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= Rutgers Player Drops Imus Suit |author=Josh Grossberg|publisher=[[E! Online]]|date=September 12, 2007 |url=http://www.eonline.com/news/article/index.jsp?uuid=ce95e851-0d3b-4e3c-b59a-ca80288e62b6&amp;sid=fd-news |accessdate=September 14, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Return to radio and television==
On July 8, 2007, the ''[[Drudge Report]]'' indicated that Imus would return to the air before the [[United States presidential election, 2008|2008 presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://drudgereport.com/flash2ii.htm &quot;Imus Plots January Comeback&quot;], ''The Drudge Report'', July 8, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The ''New York Post'' reported on July 16, 2007, that Imus was in search of a black comedian to join the show upon its return to help cushion racially insensitive comments he might say on the air.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/seven/07162007/gossip/pagesix/not_done_yet_pagesix_.htm Not Done Yet], ''New York Post'', July 16, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The same paper reported on July 27, 2007, that CBS was close to a buyout of Imus's contract. The report also said Imus's representatives had contacted [[Buckley Broadcasting]], [[Citadel Broadcasting]], and [[Clear Channel Communications]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.nypost.com/seven/07272007/business/talk_show_settlement_business_peter_lauria.htm |author=Peter Lauria |title= Talk Show Settlement: Sources say Imus, CBS are Close to Contract buyout|publisher=''New York Post'' |date=July 27, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 14, Imus reached a settlement with CBS Radio over his contract, leaving him free to pursue other media opportunities.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBSsettle&quot;/&gt; 

On November 1, Citadel announced they had agreed to what was reportedly a multi-year syndication contract with Imus. The new ''Imus in the Morning'' program would be distributed nationally by [[Citadel Media]], and would be based at Citadel-owned [[WABC (AM)|WABC]] in New York City, beginning in December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wabcradio.com/Article.asp?id=504979&amp;spid= |title=The Biggest News Talk Radio Station in America Just Got Bigger |publisher = ''77WABC'' |date =November 1, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 14, the ''New York Times'' reported that Imus had agreed to terms with cable network [[RFD-TV]] to air a video simulcast of the new radio program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/14/arts/television/14imus.html?ref=television |author=Jacques Steinberg |title=Source: Rural channel will carry Imus show |publisher=''The New York Times'' |date=November 14, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charles McCord]] and [[Bernard McGuirk]] have joined Imus in the new version of the show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newsday.com/entertainment/ny-spimus1009,0,1049766.story |author=Neil Best |title=Source: Imus back on air in early December |publisher=''Newsday'' |date=October 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 3, Imus returned to the airwaves on ABC Radio and [[RFD-TV]].  When asked about Imus's return to radio, [[Al Sharpton]] said in an interview, &quot;We’ll monitor him; I’m not saying I’m going to throw a banquet for him and say welcome home. He has the right to make a living, but because he has such a consistent pattern with this we are going to monitor him to make sure he doesn’t do it again.&quot;&lt;ref name=DS&gt;[[n:Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics|Interview with Al Sharpton]], David Shankbone, ''[[Wikinews]]'', December 3, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; On April 4, 2008, [[Jesse Jackson]] appeared on &quot;Imus in the Morning&quot; to discuss the 40th anniversary of the assassination of [[Martin Luther King]]--a booking that would have seemed impossible nearly a year before, when Reverend Jackson joined 50 demonstrators in Chicago demanding that &quot;Imus Must Go.&quot; Many media commentators declared Don Imus's rehabilitation complete.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The resurrection of Don Imus has been almost as complete as his crash and burn&quot;: David Hinkley, &quot;Year after stirring racism storm &amp; ranch exile, Don Imus back in saddle at WABC,&quot; ''New York Daily News'' (April 6, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, [[Little Richard]] appeared as a guest artist on &quot;The Imus Ranch Record,&quot; to help raise funds to benefit sick and dying children, as well as to debunk the notion that Imus was racist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=nl&amp;u=http://www.musicmeter.nl/album/158774&amp;ei=FErjSsC6CIuo8Ab_t53nAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=translate&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CB0Q7gEwCA&amp;prev=/search%3Fq%3Dlittle%2Brichard%2B-%2Bimus%2Branch%2Brecord%2B-%2Bdiscography%26hl%3Den%26rls%3Dcom.microsoft:en-ca:IE-SearchBox%26rlz%3D1I7GGLJ_en |title=Google Translate |publisher=Translate.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In September of that year, Imus signed a multi-year deal with [[Fox Business Network]] to simulcast his radio show Imus in the Morning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxbusiness.com/story/markets/industries/media/fox-business-network-secures-deal-don-imus-simulcast-morning/ |title=Roger Ailes, FOX Business Network Secure Deal With Don Imus |publisher=FOXBusiness.com |date=2009-09-03 |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The program airs Monday through Friday from 6–9 AM ET and was first broadcast on October 5, 2009.

==Cancer diagnosis==
In March 2009, Imus was diagnosed with stage 2 Prostate cancer. Although a report stating his condition was released and a story about his condition was reported in the national media outlets, no further information has been made available or has been reported to the public as of late 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nydailynews.com/lifestyle/health/2009/03/16/2009-03-16_don_imus_cancer_diagnosis_what_is_stage_.html |title=Imus cancer diagnosis | location=New York | work=Daily News | first=Corky | last=Siemaszko | date=March 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/tv/2009/03/16/2009-03-16_radio_host_don_imus_announces_on_morning-1.html | location=New York | work=Daily News | first1=Richard | last1=Huff | first2=Corky | last2=Siemaszko | title=Radio host Don Imus announces on morning show he has stage 2 prostate cancer | date=March 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/03/16/don-imus-i-have-prostate_n_175203.html | title=huffingtonpost.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reaction from presidential candidates==
On January 11, 2007, Sen. [[Chris Dodd]] (D-CT), an occasional guest on ''Imus in the Morning'', announced his candidacy in the 2008 Presidential Election while speaking with Imus on his daily program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/11/AR2007011100311.html |title=Democratic Sen. Dodd Enters Presidential Race |publisher=''The Washington Post'' |month=January | year=2007|accessdate=January 12, 2007 | first=Dan | last=Balz}}&lt;/ref&gt; Less than three months later, Dodd would publicly chastise Imus during the Rutgers controversy. Dodd later returned and appeared on-air for Imus's first broadcast following his return on WABC, though nothing was mentioned of his prior criticism of Imus. In addition to Dodd, the first week of Imus's return to broadcasting also saw the return of presidential candidates [[Rudy Giuliani]], Sen. [[John McCain]], Governor [[Mike Huckabee]], and Governor [[Bill Richardson]] to his show. 2004 Democratic presidential nominee [[John Kerry]] also appeared. A politician notably lacking in support was [[Harold Ford, Jr.]], whom Imus had supported during Ford's losing 2006 Senate campaign. Democratic candidates [[Hillary Clinton]] and [[Barack Obama]] have both voiced their distaste for Imus's remarks, and both publicly supported his firing.

==Adam &quot;Pacman&quot; Jones controversy==
On June 23, 2008, controversy again surrounded Imus when he made the following statements regarding the suspension of Cowboys' cornerback, [[Pacman Jones|Adam Jones]].

{{bquote|[[Warner Wolf|WARNER WOLF]]: Defensive back Adam &quot;Pacman&quot; Jones, recently signed by the Cowboys, here's a guy suspended all of 2007, following a shooting in a Vegas nightclub.&lt;p&gt;DON IMUS: Well, stuff happens. You're in a nightclub, for God's sake. What do you think is gonna happen in a nightclub. People are drinking, and doing drugs. There are women there and people have guns. So there, go ahead.&lt;p&gt;WARNER WOLF: Also, he's been arrested six times since being drafted by Tennessee in 2005.&lt;p&gt;DON IMUS: What color is he?&lt;p&gt;WARNER WOLF: He's African-American.&lt;p&gt;DON IMUS: Well there you go, now we know.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.americablog.com/2008/06/don-imus-makes-racist-comment-again.html | title = Don Imus makes a racist comment, again | publisher = ''Americablog.com'' | month = June | year = 2008 | accessdate = June 23, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In response, Jones said, &quot;I'm truly upset about the comments. Obviously Mr. Imus has problems with African-Americans. I'm upset, and I hope the station he works for handles it accordingly. I will pray for him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Watkins, Calvin. [http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/spt/football/cowboys/stories/062408dnspocowbrief.31b5ac75.html  Dallas Cowboys' Adam Jones upset with Imus' comments].  ''Dallas Morning News''. 2008-06-24.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Imus said his comments were misinterpreted.&lt;ref name=newquestions&gt;Gross, Samantha. [http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2008/jun/24/imus-faces-new-questions-over-on-air-race-remar-1/  Imus faces new questions over on-air race remarks]. ''The Washington Times''. 2008-06-24.&lt;/ref&gt; Through his spokesman, Imus said, &quot;I meant that he was being picked on because he's black.&quot;&lt;ref name=newquestions/&gt; 

Phil Boyce, vice president of WABC and Citadel Broadcasting Corp., said it was unlikely that disciplinary action would be pursued against Imus, and none was.&lt;ref name=newquestions/&gt;

==Other controversies==
===Howard Stern===
Imus has a long-standing rivalry with [[Howard Stern]], dating back to when they both worked at WNBC.&lt;ref name=bbc_stern&gt;{{cite news|title=Bumpy career of original 'shock jock'|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/6552155.stm|work=BBC.co.uk|accessdate=25 May 2011|date=April 13, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Joe Barton===
For two weeks in the Fall of 2006, Imus delivered ongoing 'rants' against [[Texas]] Congressman [[Joe Barton]], describing him as &quot;a lying fat little skunk from Texas&quot;, a &quot;pipsqueak&quot; and a &quot;coward and a crybaby&quot;.  Imus also called Barton a &quot;congressional dirtbag&quot;, because Barton used his position as a committee chair to prevent passage of the [[Combating Autism Act]], which would authorize funds for [[autism]] research.  In the weeks before Congress recessed on September 29, 2006, Barton used his chairmanship to prevent the legislative proposal from coming to a vote in the House, rousing the ire of Imus and his wife, staunch supporters of autism research.  The bill already had been passed unanimously by the Senate, but Barton opposed the Senate bill's stipulation that centers of excellence investigate environmental factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Maria Recio|title=Talk show host Imus levels blasts at Texas congressman|date=October 16, 2006|url=http://www.mcclatchydc.com/staff/maria_recio/story/14842.html|accessdate=July 28, 2007|publisher=McClatchy Washington Bureau}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lawsuits===
Imus was sued by the wife of ''[[Boston Herald]]'' columnist and radio talk show host [[Howie Carr]] in 1998 after Imus made sexually explicit remarks about her and boxer [[Riddick Bowe]].  Imus reportedly made the remarks after being told that Carr had said that Imus &quot;would die before his kid got out of high school&quot;; Carr denies making those remarks.  Carr, represented by [[Alan Dershowitz]], received an out of court settlement from Imus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bostonherald.com/columnists/view.bg?articleid=194039|author=Howie Carr |title=Imus’ demise no surprise|publisher=Boston Herald |date=April 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Imus also attracted public attention due to two lawsuits.  On November 29, 2004, a former nanny, Nichole Mallette, sued Imus for wrongful termination and [[defamation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thesmokinggun.com/archive/1130041imus1.html |title=Nanny Sues Imus Over Ranch Wrangle |publisher=thesmokinggun.com |date=November 30, 2004 |accessdate=April 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; after a [[Thanksgiving]] 2003 incident in which she was allegedly fired and escorted off his property at 4:15 AM. Don and Deirdre Imus were allegedly upset over Mallette's possession of a cap-gun and pocket knife on ranch property.

On July 8, 2005, Dr. Howard Allen Pearson sued Imus for [[slander]] and civil assault. Pearson accused Imus of threatening him during a July 13, 2004 confrontation at the ranch, and Imus subsequently referred to him on air as &quot;an arrogant fucking doctor who doesn't mind letting a child suffer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Doctor Files Lawsuit Against Don Imus |url=http://www.katv.com/news/stories/0705/242479.html |publisher=www.katv.com |date=July 11, 2005 |accessdate=April 10, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071017171335/http://katv.com/news/stories/0705/242479.html |archivedate = October 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Radio and Television Correspondents Dinner speech===
On March 21, 1996, Imus delivered a speech at the [[Radio and Television Correspondents' Association|Radio and Television Correspondents Dinner]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], which Imus later called &quot;The Speech From Hell&quot;.

The dinner was attended by [[President]] [[Bill Clinton]] and [[First Lady]] [[Hillary Clinton]]. The initial line of Imus's speech was considered a direct reference to Hillary Clinton, who was at the time involved in a specific aspect of the [[Whitewater (controversy)|Whitewater scandal]] concerning billing records that were discovered just a few weeks before on a table in the resident section of [[The White House]].

{{bquote|(audience applause) Thank you very much.&lt;p&gt;Um...this is kind of interesting, these don't appear to be my notes. [picking up papers from the lectern] You still have the folder I gave you?  Where did this come from? [gesturing with the papers]&lt;p&gt;Well, nobody just leaves stuff like this just layin' around. [audience laughter, then slowly looks at Hillary, audience laughs]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://imonthe.net/imus/ispeech.htm |title=Imus' speech to the Radio &amp; TV Correspondent's dinner transcript |publisher=''imonthe.net'' |accessdate=September 28, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Later on, Imus commented on the President saying &quot;Go baby!&quot; while doing radio play-by-play at an Orioles game, and added, &quot;I remember commenting at the time, I bet that's not the first time he's said that.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= Imus Clout Prompts Political Support |author=John Hendren|publisher=[[ABC News]]|date=April 11, 2007 |url= http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/story?id=3031440&amp;page=1 |accessdate=April 11, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accusations of defamatory speech===
As &quot;shock jocks&quot;, Imus and his crew, mainly Bernard McGuirk, repeatedly made controversial remarks through skits and character impersonations in what they considered a comical format which critics labeled as [[racist]], [[misogynist]], [[homophobic]] and [[anti-semitic]].  He has also been accused of making offensive remarks off the air.  Some examples include:

*In a 1984 interview, answering a question about Howard Stern, Don Imus said: &quot;yes, Howard's a slut too, Lloyd...Plus a Jew bastard, and should be castrated... put in an oven.&quot; A clip of this interview was played by Howard Stern in the news section of his November 5, 2007 show.{{Cite quote|date=October 2008}}
*Imus referred to African-American sports columnist [[William C. Rhoden|Bill Rhoden]] as a &quot;''New York Times'' quota hire&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/09/business/media/09carr.html?bl&amp;ex=1176436800&amp;en=8d8812abb96e5775&amp;ei=5087%0A | title = With Imus, They Keep Coming Back | author = David Carr | date=April 9, 2007 | accessdate = April 12, 2007 | publisher = The New York Times }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1993, Imus referred to PBS anchor [[Gwen Ifill]] (then with the ''New York Times'') as a &quot;cleaning lady.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | url = http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3613/is_200007/ai_n8921227 | author = Philip Nobile | title = In the kingdom of Imus, the courtiers are quiet | publisher = Columbia Journalism Review | date = July/August 2000 | accessdate = April 12, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061123125719/http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3613/is_200007/ai_n8921227 |archivedate = November 23, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/10/opinion/10ifill.html | author = Gwen Ifill | title = Trash Talk Radio | publisher = The New York Times | date = April 10, 2007 | accessdate = April 12, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.newsmax.com/archives/ic/2007/4/10/120304.shtml | title = Gwen Ifill: Imus Called Me 'Cleaning Lady' | author = NewsMax.com Staff | date = April 10, 2007 | accessdate = May 10, 2007 | publisher = NewsMax.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*As reported by ''New York Times'' columnist [[Bob Herbert]],&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Paying the Price | publisher = The New York Times | url = http://select.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/opinion/12herbert.html?hp  | date = April 12, 2007 | accessdate = April 12, 2007 | first=Bob | last=Herbert}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the course of a 1998 interview with [[Mike Wallace (journalist)|Mike Wallace]] on ''[[60 Minutes]]'', Imus told a producer off-camera that McGuirk was hired to perform &quot;nigger jokes.&quot;
*[[Robin Quivers]] claimed that when she worked with Imus at WNBC, he called her a &quot;nigger&quot; to her face.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=om een reactie te plaatsen! |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=krfLh5PJjiU&amp;mode=related&amp;search= |title=YouTube – Howard Stern talks about racist Imus |publisher=Youtube.com |date=2007-04-14 |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Howard Stern and Quivers have also claimed that he screamed &quot;Nigger, nigger!&quot; at a black secretary named Brenda during their time at WNBC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.starmuscle.com/2006/12/11/don-imus-is-anti-semitic/ |title=Don Imus Is Anti Semitic And A Racist |publisher=Starmuscle.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Imus has also repeatedly referred to [[Arab]]s as &quot;ragheads.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.annoy.com/editorials/doc.html?DocumentID=100700 | author = Clinton Fein | title = Imus and the Flies | publisher = ''annoy.com'' | date = March 24, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*He has berated many female newsreaders, most recently [[Contessa Brewer]], which caused her to leave the show. After she left the show, Imus went on a tirade, saying, &quot;With that fat ass she's got, she wouldn't be one of 'em,&quot; [a news 'babe'.]. Imus said on the air, &quot;That skank has to spend three hours with makeup in the morning.&quot; The tirade was allegedly tied to comments overheard from Contessa's calling Imus &quot;a cantankerous old fool&quot; at a 2005 dinner in a restaurant when she was still a newsreader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.outsidethebeltway.com/archives/2005/05/don_imus_berates_contessa_brewer | author = James Joyner | title = Don Imus Berates Contessa Brewer | publisher = outside the beltway'' | date = May 1, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During a show a producer also made fun of poet [[Maya Angelou]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Imus Wants to Apologize to Women's Basketball Team in Person | publisher = [[ABC News]] | date = April 9, 2007 | url = http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/story?id=3022039&amp;page=1 }} Retrieved on April 9, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The show's routines sometimes contained derogatory epithets for homosexuals, including &quot;[[faggot (epithet)|faggot]]&quot; and various terms describing homosexuality.&lt;!--Leave these in footnote - they are necessary as citation for the text, not here as quotes--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Some have been compiled at Philip Nobile's &quot;Imus Watch&quot;. See: {{cite web | url = http://tompaine.com/Archive/scontent/3067.html | title=Imus Watch I | publisher = TomPaine.com | date = May 16, 2000 | accessdate = April 12, 2007 }} Samples include:

:''Imus: We're poised to support this bogus tennis [team] thing of yours.
:''McEnroe: That's hurtful. That's hurtful.
:''Imus: The new Hampton Homos or whatever. [laughter]

:''Imus: How about best actress?
:''O'Brien: I think that's going to be [[Annette Bening]], although [[Hilary Swank]], it's a very tight race. I know you like [[Janet McTeer|Jane[t] McTeer]], but I like Annette Bening or Hilary Swank.
:''Imus: Hilary Swank's the lesbo in ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]''?
:''O'Brien: She's getting married to [[Chad Lowe]].
:''Imus: Beard deal. [laughter]
:''O'Brien: What a nightmare.

:''Imus: It sounds like another one of these deals of his [i.e. Dietl's]. We'll hear about two weeks from now the guy suddenly is a fagatation situation...
:''Bo Dietl: You don't do that with [[Tim Russert|Russert]]. You listen to these fagaloons talking to you, 'O Donnie, Donnie, Donnie.''&lt;/ref&gt;
*Imus has also made fun of [[Irish people|Irish]], [[Jew]]s, [[Italians]], other ethnicities and all political positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title = Networks Condemn Remarks by Imus | publisher = New York Times | date = April 7, 2007 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/arts/television/07imus.html?_r=1&amp;hp&amp;oref=slogin | first=David | last=Carr | accessdate=May 1, 2010}} Retrieved on April 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business interests==
Don Imus was also a part owner of Autobody Express stores with his brother, [[Fred Imus|Fred]] (a frequent caller to the radio show, commenting on [[NASCAR]] races, the [[NFL]] and related pop culture matters). The Autobody Express stores were located in Santa Fe, and inside the [[Mohegan Sun]] Native American Casino in [[Montville, Connecticut|Uncasville, Connecticut]]. In 2003, the company failed and both stores closed.

Imus still owns a small coffee/pastry store also located in the Mohegan Sun casino. The Autobody Express became Imus Ranch Foods, which offers its signature chips and [[salsa (sauce)|salsa]] via online sales and in [[Northeastern United States|Northeastern]] stores. The proceeds from Imus Ranch Foods help fund the work of the Imus Ranch.

==Honors==
Imus won four [[NAB Marconi Radio Awards|Marconi Awards]], three for Major Market Personality of the Year (1990,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nab.org/documents/events/awards/marconiAwards/1990Winners.asp |title=1990 Marconi Radio Award Winners |publisher=Nab.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; 1992&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nab.org/documents/events/awards/marconiAwards/1992Winners.asp |title=1992 Marconi Radio Award Winners |publisher=Nab.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 1997&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nab.org/documents/events/awards/marconiAwards/1997Winners.asp |title=1997 Marconi Radio Award Winners |publisher=Nab.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one for Network Syndicated Personality (1994).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nab.org/documents/events/awards/marconiAwards/1994Winners.asp |title=1994 Marconi Radio Award Winners |publisher=Nab.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Imus was named one of the 25 Most Influential People in America in ''Time'' magazine (April 21, 1997).

He was inducted into the [[National Radio Hall of Fame]] in 1989. In 2002, ''[[Talkers Magazine|Talkers]]'' magazine ranked Imus as one of the 25 greatest radio talk show hosts of all time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.talkers.com/greatest/ |title=The 25 greatest radio talk show hosts of all time|publisher=''Talkers Magazine'' |month=September | year=2002 |accessdate=September 27, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
*Awkward, Michael. ''Burying Don Imus''. Minneapolis: [http://www.upress.umn.edu/Books/A/awkward_burying.html University of Minnesota Press], 2009. 
**What the furor surrounding Don Imus shows us about unresolved race relations in the United States.
*Imus, Donald.  ''God's Other Son''.  Simon &amp; Schuster, 1994.  (ISBN 0-684-80166-3).  (Originally published in 1981 (ISBN 0-671-22537-5).)
*Imus, Donald, and Imus, Fred.  ''Two Guys Four Corners: Great Photographs, Great Times, and a Million Laughs''.  Villard, 1997.  (ISBN 0-679-45307-5).
*Imus, Deirdre.  ''The Imus Ranch: Cooking for Kids and Cowboys''.  Rodale Press, 2004.  (ISBN 0-87596-919-4).
*Reed, Jim.  ''Everything Imus: All You Ever Wanted to Know About Don Imus''.  Birch Lane Press, 1999.  (ISBN 1-55972-504-4).
*Tracy, Kathleen.  ''Imus: America's Cowboy''.  Carroll &amp; Graf, 1999.  (ISBN 0-7867-0608-2).

{{Portal box|Biography|United States Marine Corps}}

{{-}}

==Comedy Albums==

* ''1200 Hamburgers to Go'' 
* ''One Sacred Chicken to Go with Anthrax'' 
* ''This Honky's Nuts''

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://www.imus.com/ Official Web site]
*[http://www.wabcradio.com/default.asp 77WABC Radio-New York]
*[http://www.1450wkip.com/pages/onair.html?feed=219650&amp;article=3813623 Imus on WKIP]
*{{C-SPAN|donimus}}
*{{Imdb name|id=0408320}}
*{{Worldcat id|lccn-n81-68704}}
*{{NYTtopic|people/i/don_imus}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Don Imus
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=John Donald Imus, Jr.
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[Radio personality]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=July 23, 1940
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Riverside, California]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Imus, Don}}
[[Category:1940 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American DJs]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American talk radio hosts]]
[[Category:American vegetarians]]
[[Category:Radio personalities from New York City]]
[[Category:National Radio Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:People from Mohave County, Arizona]]
[[Category:People from New York City]]
[[Category:People from Riverside, California]]
[[Category:People from Westport, Connecticut]]
[[Category:People with cancer]]
[[Category:United States Marines]]
[[Category:People self-identifying as alcoholics]]

[[de:Don Imus]]
[[ja:ドン・アイマス]]
[[pl:Don Imus]]
[[fi:Don Imus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
