<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="539794" ns="0" title="CHCH-DT"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|CHCH|the [[New Zealand]] city abbreviated &quot;ChCh&quot;|Christchurch}}
{{Infobox broadcast
|call_letters             = CHCH-DT
|city                     = [[Hamilton, Ontario]]
|station_logo             = [[File:CHCH2010.svg|210px]]
|station_slogan           = ''Your Superstation'' &lt;small&gt;(primary)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;''Great Movies Every Night'' &lt;small&gt;(secondary)&lt;/small&gt;
|station_branding         = CHCH &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;CHCH News &lt;small&gt;(news)&lt;/small&gt;
|digital                  = 11 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])&lt;br&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 11 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
|other_chs                = [[#Transmitters|see below]]
|airdate                  = June 7, 1954
|affiliations             = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (1961-2001, 2009-present)
|callsign_meaning         = '''C''' '''H'''amilton's '''CH'''annel
|former_callsigns         = CHCH-TV (1954-2011)
|former_channel_numbers   = '''Analog''':&lt;br&gt;11 ([[very high frequency|VHF]], 1954-2011)&lt;br&gt;'''Digital''':&lt;br&gt;18 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]], 2008-2011)
|owner                    = [[Channel Zero Inc.|Channel Zero]]
|licensee                 = 2190015 Ontario Inc.
|former_affiliations      = [[CBC Television|CBC]] (1954-1961)&lt;br/&gt;[[E! (Canadian TV system)|CH / E!]] (2001-2009)
|effective_radiated_power =  6 kW|
HAAT                     = 361.0 m
|location                 = [[Hamilton, Ontario|Hamilton]], [[Regional Municipality of Halton|Halton]], [[Regional Municipality of Niagara|Niagara]], and [[Greater Toronto Area]]
|coordinates              = {{Coord|43|12|27|N|79|46|31|W|type:landmark}}
|homepage                 = [http://www.chch.com/ CHCH]|
}}

'''CHCH-DT''', channel 11, is a [[television station]] originating in [[Hamilton, Ontario]], [[Canada]], with transmitters located throughout [[Ontario]]. CHCH currently operates as an [[independent station (North America)|independent station]], having previously served as a [[CBC Television]] affiliate, and more recently as the flagship station of the now-defunct [[E! (TV system)|CH / E!]] system.

Owned and operated by [[Channel Zero (company)|Channel Zero]], it is the oldest privately-owned television station in the Hamilton-Toronto area, having launched in 1954.  CHCH's programming schedule features a weekday [[News broadcasting|rolling news]] format geared primarily to southern Ontario's Golden Horseshoe, along with feature movies on weeknights and weekends; some American entertainment series were added to the evening schedule in the fall of 2010.

==History==
===CBC affiliation===
CHCH-TV was founded by [[Ken Soble]]. A leader of Hamilton's urban renewal movement, and owner of [[CHML]] radio, Soble was regarded as a pioneer in all of his endeavours.&lt;ref name=GREATHAM2&gt;{{Cite web| title = Hamilton Spectator: &quot;The Greatest Hamiltonian&quot;. (II)| url=http://www.hamiltonspectator.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=hamilton/Layout/Article_Type1&amp;c=Article&amp;cid=1143499813048&amp;call_pageid=1020420665036&amp;col=1014656511815| accessdate = 2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The station began broadcasting in [[1954 in television|1954]] as a [[CBC Television|Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]] (CBC) affiliate from the [[CHCH Television Tower]], a transmitter located at 481 First Road West in [[Stoney Creek, Ontario|Stoney Creek]]. At the time, all private stations were required to be CBC affiliates. In [[1961 in television|1961]], CHCH disaffiliated from the CBC and became an independent.  The reason for the disaffiliation from CBC was threefold.  Toronto's [[CBLT]] already provided full network service to some of CHCH's viewing area, and a power increase and change of channels at CBLT (from Channel 9 to Channel 6 and eventually Channel 5) would result in an overlap of nearly all of the CHCH and CBLT coverage areas.  Additionally, the station's managers wanted to produce a larger amount of local programming, instead of being forced to carry CBC programming.

===Superstation CHCH===
[[File:Chch1986.png|thumb|left|130px|CHCH-TV's logo from the 1960s to the late 1980s]]
CHCH became the first (and for over a decade, the only) television station in Canada not to have any network affiliation, as the other private stations (which signed on the air in [[1960 in television|1960]] or early [[1961 in television|1961]]) that were not affiliated with the CBC had formed the [[CTV Television Network|CTV]] network in 1961. CHCH became a nationwide [[superstation]] on January 1, 1982, when [[Shaw Broadcast Services|Cancom]] began carrying the station and three others to cable television operators in remote regions of the country that had access only to the CBC.
[[File:CHCH1990s.png|thumb|left|100px|This was the last logo used by CHCH before re-branding to ONtv]]
The station also produced a number of important Canadian [[Broadcast syndication|syndicated]] series, including ''[[The Hilarious House of Frightenstein]]'', ''[[Me &amp; Max]]'', ''[[Party Game (game show)|Party Game]]'' and ''[[Smith &amp; Smith]]'', and was the original TV home of ''[[The Red Green Show]]''. Hamilton native [[Martin Short]] also had his television debut on the station. CHCH also produced local broadcasts such as ''Tiny Talent Time''.

For a time, CHCH broadcast local mid-week telecasts of the [[National Hockey League|NHL]]'s [[Toronto Maple Leafs]]. It also produced a wrestling show called Ringside Wrestling.  It was originally filmed in the Telecentre, later moving to the Hamilton Forum.  They later reproduced [[World Wrestling Entertainment|World Wrestling Federation]] programming for Canadian audiences before the company's focus shifted entirely to cable.

===ONtv era===
[[File:CHCH ONTV.svg|100px|thumb|CHCH-TV's logo as &quot;ONtv&quot;, (1997-2001) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ic.gc.ca/app/opic-cipo/trdmrks/srch/vwTrdmrk.do;jsessionid=0000aenbY60hwSqnoT0TelSyHFN:1247nfca5?lang=eng&amp;fileNumber=0832824&amp;extension=0&amp;startingDocumentIndexOnPage=1 ONtv trademark data on Canadian Trademark Database]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In 1990, [[Western International Communications]] (WIC) purchased CHCH. Although CHCH had been available on cable in many Ontario markets for years, the station's broadcast signal coverage was expanded throughout Ontario with repeaters in 1997, in an effort to compete with the reach of [[Global Television Network|Global]]'s Ontario station [[CIII-TV|CIII]], as well as the [[Baton Broadcast System]], a group of mostly [[CTV Television Network|CTV]]-affiliated stations which served most of the province. In turn, WIC renamed the station '''ONtv''', as in &quot;Ontario Television&quot;, in line with the naming pattern of many of its other stations (such as [[CHAN-TV|BCTV]], [[CITV-TV|ITV]], and [[CHCA-TV|RDTV]]).

Local news shifted focus from the station's core market, the Hamilton area, toward Ontario as a whole, in an attempt to challenge what was then a regional news service provided by Global. However, with Hamilton now being largely an afterthought, and other local stations (in Toronto and elsewhere) already strong in the ratings, the shift was unsuccessful, and CHCH's ratings actually dropped. During the ONtv years, the station also aired WIC's nightly ''[[Canada Tonight]]'' newscast.

===Canwest ownership===
In 2000, [[Canwest]] purchased WIC's television assets. Since Global already served the Hamilton area through flagship [[CIII-TV]]'s transmitter in [[Paris, Ontario|Paris]], Canwest rebranded the station '''CH''' (or '''CH Hamilton''') on February 12, 2001 and subsequently launched the [[E! (Canadian TV system)|CH television system]] in September of that year. This move launched a secondary television system for Canwest's stations in medium-sized markets near larger markets. Local news coverage was revamped and re-focused on the Hamilton/[[Regional Municipality of Halton|Halton]]/[[Regional Municipality of Niagara|Niagara]] region.

Despite the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]] (CRTC)'s current TV station ownership restrictions (one station per owner per language per market), Canwest was permitted to maintain CHCH's coverage of other markets throughout most of Ontario. However, it could not broadcast to [[Thunder Bay]], [[Peterborough, Ontario|Peterborough]], or [[Kingston, Ontario|Kingston]] due to opposition by local stations. Some cable systems outside of [[Ontario]] also continue to carry CHCH as a form of &quot;superstation&quot;.  Additionally, its over-the-air signal easily covers [[Buffalo, New York]] and [[Erie, Pennsylvania]].

On June 7, 2004, at 8:00 p.m., CHCH-TV celebrated exactly 50 years on the air. At this precise time, the station aired a documentary profiling the station history, entitled ''The First 50 Years: A Half Century of CH'' and hosted by Matt Hayes.

It was announced that the CH brand would change starting in 2007, however, it remained in use until September 7, 2007 when Canwest rebranded CHCH's local programming from CH Hamilton to '''CHCH News''' after the following the relaunch of the national CH service as [[E! (Canadian TV system)|E!]].

[[File:Chchnewslogo.svg|thumb|150px|The logo used for newscasts from 2007-2010. It was used as the de facto branding of the station from 2007-2009|170px|right]]
In late 2008, Canwest retired CHCH's longest serving news anchors, Connie Smith (last day on air November 28, 2008) and Dan McLean (last day on air December 12, 2008), blaming money troubles and having to cut budgets. After their departures, Annette Hamm began handling anchoring duties on a shortened CHCH News at Noon, as well as co-hosting Morning Live with Bob Cowan, while Nick Dixon took over anchoring duties on CHCH News at 6:00. Since being taken over by Channel Zero on August 31, 2009, Annette Hamm and Bob Cowan have co-hosted a restored hour long newscast at noon.

In January 2009, CHCH's ''Morning Live'' program began to be simulcast on former sister station [[CIII-TV]] due to low ratings leading to the cancellation of its own [[Global News Morning]]. The simulcast on [[CIII-TV]] was dropped at the end of August after Channel Zero officially took control of CHCH.  While the station continued to share helicopter traffic services provided by the Canadian Traffic Network, the arrangement between Canwest and CHCH ended on December 31, 2009 as Canwest held the exclusive rights to CTN services in the [[Greater Toronto Area]].

===Channel Zero era===
On February 5, 2009, Canwest (CHCH's parent company at the time) announced it would explore &quot;strategic options&quot;, including possible sale or closure, for CHCH and its other stations in the E! system, saying &quot;a second conventional TV network is no longer key to the long-term success&quot; of the company.&lt;ref name=sale&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/canada/british-columbia/story/2009/02/05/canwest.html &quot;Canwest may sell TV stations&quot;]. [[CBC.ca|cbc.ca]], February 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A grassroots group, fronted by ''Live @ 5:30'' co-host Donna Skelly, surfaced with an intent to purchase CHCH from Canwest and return the station to its former local focus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thespec.com/News/Business/article/520615 &quot;CHCH staff launch bold bid&quot;] ''[[The Hamilton Spectator]]'' (2009-02-26)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/Entertainment/Television/article/602302 &quot;Will townsfolk save the House of Frightenstein?&quot;] From ''[[Toronto Star]]'', March 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2009, paperwork to the CRTC for a one-year renewal of CHCH's licence revealed that the station is projected to lose nearly $30 million during the 2010 fiscal year, which begins September 1, 2009—the station would make $41 million, but the profits would be outpaced by costs of $69 million. John Douglas, a spokesperson for Canwest, said that CHCH, and its other stations in the E! group, were money losers during the last decade, coupled with the Canadian broadcasters' dependency on American programming for profits.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadcastermagazine.com/issues/ISArticle.asp?id=97502&amp;issue=03182009 Broadcaster Magazine: &quot;CHCH-TV, Hamilton Projected to Lose $30-million&quot;, 3/18/2009.]&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 30, 2009, [[Channel Zero Inc.|Channel Zero]] announced that it would purchase CHCH and [[CJNT-TV|CJNT]] in [[Montreal]] from Canwest in exchange for $12 in cash and the assumption of various station liabilities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newswire.ca/en/releases/archive/June2009/30/c3204.html Channel Zero Inc. agrees to purchase CHCH-TV Hamilton and CJNT-TV Montreal from Canwest ] ''[[CNW Group]]'' (2009-06-30)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-uBbCJIJ1HE Channel Zero Inc. agrees to purchase CHCH-TV Hamilton and CJNT-TV Montreal from Canwest (Video News Coverage) ] (2009-06-30)&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission|CRTC]] approved the sale on August 28, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2009/2009-536.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2009-536]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2009/2009-537.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2009-537]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:CHCH News Movies.svg|150px|thumb|left|Logo used by CHCH from 2009-2010.]]
Channel Zero took control of the station's programming at midnight EDT on the morning of August 31, beginning its tenure with a film from the 1980s&lt;!-- appears to be ''[[Deadline (film)|Deadline]]'', to be confirmed --&gt;. CHCH disaffiliated from E! (which shut down at the end of that day), adopted a new format consisting of local news all day on weekdays and movies at night (all day on weekends), and reverted to branding itself as simply CHCH. The first film broadcast in primetime that night was ''[[Rocky]]'', signifying the new ownership's come-from-behind spirit.  CHCH would add, in sparse amounts, additional programming during the 2009-2010 season, including ''Let's Get It On'', a [[mixed martial arts]] program; [[Ed the Sock]]'s ''[[This Movie Sucks!]]'', a movie show featuring the former [[MuchMusic]] character alongside co-host [[Liana Kerzner]] and comedian [[Ron Sparks (comedian)|Ron Sparks]]; and [[infomercial]]s.

In September 2010, CHCH, for the first time since its purchase by Channel Zero, began airing American network television series; many of the added shows, including ''[[Smallville]]'', ''[[Supernatural (TV series)|Supernatural]]'', ''[[Jimmy Kimmel Live!]]'', ''[[48 Hours Mystery]]'', ''[[20/20 (US television series)|20/20]]'', ''[[Chuck (TV series)|Chuck]]'', and ''[[60 Minutes]]'' were previously seen in the Toronto-Hamilton market on [[CKXT-TV]] (that station's owner, [[Quebecor]], was in the process of replacing it with [[Sun TV News Channel|an all-news cable channel]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/television/news/e3ib6a55e024fd8d087caed238a236d8333 Channel Zero loads up on U.S. network series], THR, 2010-06-14&lt;/ref&gt; CHCH also debuted additional original local programs ''Sportsline'' with Mark Hebscher &amp; Clint &quot;Bubba&quot; O'Neil, and will launch a second series with Ed the Sock, the entertainment newsmagazine spoof ''I Hate Hollywood''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.edthesock.com ed the sock]&lt;/ref&gt; Coinciding with the schedule changes was a return to an updated version of the classic CHCH multi-coloured logo used from the 1960s to the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chch.com/Fall2010%20PressRelease.pdf Source: CHCH Fall 2010 press release]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fftVYSiHMs CHCH 2010 Fall Preview - New shows, new logo and more]&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 10, 2011 [[Green Party of Canada|Green party]] leader [[Elizabeth May]] participated in a panel interview on CHCH, which she was invited to attend, as were the leaders of the Bloc, Liberals, NDP and Conservatives, by [[Channel Zero]], whose president was disappointed by May's exclusion from the [[Canadian federal election, 2011#Leaders' debates|2011 election leaders' debates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=CHCH-TV to Broadcast &quot;Elizabeth May, For the Record&quot; Live this Sunday, April 10, 2011 - 8pm ET |url=http://www.newswire.ca/en/releases/archive/April2011/08/c2709.html |accessdate=April 10, 2011 |publisher=CNW Group |date=April 8, 2011 |agency=CNW}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 18, 2011, [[CKXT-TV]] Toronto switched from a independent station to a simulcast of the [[Sun News Network]], leaving CHCH the only independent station in the Toronto/Hamilton area.

On June 8, 2011, at Channel Zero's upfront presentation for advertisers, the company announced they would be adding the series ''[[Hart of Dixie]]'' and ''[[The Secret Circle]]'', both of which will premiere on [[The CW]] in the United States for the 2011-12 Fall television season, on the CHCH primetime schedule, as well as the entertainment news show ''[[The Insider (TV series)|The Insider]]'' (the same show that was last aired when the station was under the E! moniker between 2007-2009).

The company also announced a programming deal with [[Twentieth Century Fox]], that will allow Channel Zero's CHCH and Metro 14 TV stations to show first-run exclusive broadcast movie premieres, most notably ''[[Avatar (film)|Avatar]]'', scheduled to air in Spring 2012 on both stations. The station will be airing the director's cut version of the film not shown in theatres. Other debut titles include ''[[Crazy Heart]]'', ''[[Taken (film)|Taken]]'' and ''[[X-Men Origins: Wolverine]]''.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadcastermagazine.com/issues/story.aspx?aid=1000467638 CHCH and Metro 14 Announce Fall Line-Up]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Newscasts and other local programming==
[[File:CHCH 2010.jpg|thumb|right|upright|CHCH and Channel Zero signs are up on the side of 163 Jackson St. West. Previously, both E! and CHCH News logos were placed up in 2007. The red E! logo was removed after Channel Zero took control of CHCH in 2009, and has replaced the previous E! era newscast logo the following year.]]
CHCH currently airs 84 hours of local news content every week,&lt;ref&gt;[http://chch.com/index.php/community-calendar CHCH schedule]&lt;/ref&gt; more than any local television station in Canada or the United States. In contrast, [[CHAN-DT|CHAN in Vancouver]] broadcasts 45 hours of local news a week, [[WSVN|WSVN in Miami]] airs 55.5 hours, [[WDAF-TV|WDAF in Kansas City]] runs 57.5 hours, [[WTVT|WTVT in Tampa]] carries 60 hours and [[KRON|KRON in San Francisco]] does 60.5 hours of local programming each week. CHCH broadcasts 15.5 hours of local programming every weekday (4 a.m.-5 p.m., 5:30-7:30 p.m. and 11-11:30 p.m.) and two hours a night (6-7 p.m. and 11 p.m.-12 a.m.) on weekends.

On September 12, 2011, CHCH increased its local news programming by launching a 90-minute extension of ''Morning Live'', called ''Morning Live First Edition'', airing weekdays from 4-5:30 a.m.&lt;ref name = &quot;Morning&quot;&gt;[http://www.broadcastermagazine.com/issues/story.aspx?aid=1000466200 CHCH-TV To Launch Canada's Earliest Morning Show]&lt;/ref&gt;

===News/station presentation===
====Newscast titles====
*''Newsroom 11'' (1970s–1982)
*''TV 11 Newsroom'' (1982–1997)
*''On-TV News (Source)'' (1997–2001)
*''OnTV News First Edition'' (6 p.m. newscast; 1997–2001)
*''CH News'' (2001–2007)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nGXb0mE7i70 CHCH Hamilton - &quot;CH&quot; News at Six Open]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Live @ 5:30'' (2005–2010; debate &amp; talk program)
*''CHCH News'' (2007–present)
**''News Now'' (2009–present; late morning and afternoon newscasts)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J4bsh8oXZ6A CHCH News Now Open - Monday, August 1, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;
**''News Now Midday'' (2010–present; noon newscast)
**''Square Off'' (2010–present; 5:30 pm debate &amp; talk program)
**''Evening News'' (2010–present; weeknights and weekends 6 p.m. and 11 p.m. newscasts)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dMcWFEIc1cA CHCH Evening News At 11 Open - Thursday, July 14, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Station slogans====
*''Serving Hamilton, Toronto and the Niagara Peninsula. This is CHCH TV 11'' (1970–1988?)
*''Join Us'' (1988?)
*''Together, We're the Ones'' (1988–1997)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tfW3vtTmxjs CHCH Hamilton 11 Together We're The Ones 1988]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''There's Always Something ONtv'' (1997–1999)
*''ONtv: Where You Are'' (1999–2001)
*''Closer to Home'' (2001)
*''Closer to You!'' (2001–2010)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b2MvEUR1bog CHCH Closer to you Station ID Set of 5 extended Aug 31 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''In Hamilton, Halton, Niagara, CH News is Closer to You!'' (2001–2007; news slogan)
*''CH Has It All'' (2001–2007; general slogan)
*''The Most Dependable Name in Local News'' (2007–2009)
*''Everything Entertainment'' (2007–2009; localized version of E! ad campaign)
*''Canada's Superstation'' (2009–2010)
*''Your Superstation'' (2010–present; general slogan)
*''Great Movies Every Night'' (2011–present; slogan for movie programming)

===News team&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chch.com/index.php/personalities Our On-Air Staff]&lt;/ref&gt;===
[[Image:Nick Dixon of CHCH News crop.jpg|thumb|right|175px|upright|Nick Dixon at the Burlington Music Festival]]
'''Anchors'''
* Taz Boga - ''News Now'' (weekdays 11 a.m.-12 p.m. and 2-5 p.m.)
* Tim Bolen - ''Morning Live First Edition'' (weekday mornings, 4-5:30 a.m.) and ''News Now AM'' (weekday mornings, 9-11 a.m.)
* Kate Carnegie - ''Evening News'' (Sundays at 6 and 11 p.m.)
* Bob Cowan - ''Morning Live'' (weekday mornings, 5:30-9 a.m.), and ''News Now Midday'' (weekdays at noon)
* [[Nick Dixon (Canadian journalist)|Nick Dixon]] - ''Evening News'' (weeknights at 6 and 11 p.m.)
* [[Annette Hamm]] - ''Morning Live'' (weekday mornings, 5:30-9 a.m.), and ''News Now Midday'' (weekdays at noon)

'''Weather team'''
* Matt Hayes - lead weather anchor; ''News Now Midday'' (weekdays at noon), ''News Now PM'' (weekday afternoons 4:30-5 p.m.) and ''Evening News'' (weeknights at 6 and 11 p.m.), also noon community reporter and 6 p.m. entertainment reporter
* Jaclyn Colville - weather and traffic anchor; ''Morning Live First Edition'' (weekday mornings 4-5:30 a.m.) and  traffic anchor; ''Morning Live'' (weekday mornings, 6-9 a.m.)
* Nicola Jones - weather anchor; ''Morning Live'' (weekday mornings, 6-9 a.m.)
* Steve Ruddick - weather anchor; ''Evening News'' (weekends at 6 and 11 p.m.)
* Brian Wood ([[Canadian Meteorological and Oceanographic Society|CMOS]]-endorsed weathercaster) - weather and traffic anchor; weekday mornings ''News Now AM'' (9 a.m.-12 p.m.), and weekday afternoons ''News Now PM'' (2-4:30 p.m.)

'''Sports team'''
* Ken Welch - lead sports anchor; ''Evening News'' (weeknights at 6 and 11 p.m.)
* Jeff Leyland -  sports anchor; ''Evening News'' (weekends at 6 and 11 p.m.)
* Natalie Marconi - sports reporter

'''Reporters'''
* Adam Atkinson - video journalist
* Sean Cowan - video journalist
* Cindy Csordas - video journalist
* Lori De Angelis - ''Morning Live'' community reporter
* Maria Hayes - health reporter
* Lisa Hepfner - general assignment reporter; also fill-in news anchor
* Lisa Knap - general assignment reporter
* Melissa Raftis - video journalist
* Alex Reynolds - entertainment reporter, film and theatre critic and host of ''The Movie Lounge'' (Saturday afternoons)
* Lauran Sabourin - Niagara Bureau reporter
* Lesley Stewart - fill-in news anchor/reporter
* Al Sweeney - general assignment reporter; also fill-in news anchor
* Cristina Tenaglia - video journalist; also fill-in news anchor
* Scot Urquhart - general assignment reporter

'''''Square Off'''''
* Mark Hebscher - host
* Liz West - co-host
* Lawrence Diskin - producer and fill-in co-host

'''''Sportsline'''''
* Mark Hebscher - host
* Clint &quot;Bubba&quot; O'Neil - co-host and producer
* Robin Sawh - field producer
* Candace Devai - feature reporter

==Transmitters==
On August 28, 1996, CHCH received [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission|CRTC]] approval to add new transmitters across most of Ontario.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/1996/DB96-544.HTM Decision CRTC 96-544]&lt;/ref&gt; Their launch in 1997 coincided with the rebranding to ONtv.

{{kml}}
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse&quot;
| '''Station'''
| '''[[city of license|City of licence]]'''
| '''[[channel (broadcasting)|Channel]]'''
| '''[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]'''
| '''[[effective radiated power|ERP]]'''
| '''[[height above average terrain|HAAT]]'''
| '''Transmitter Coordinates'''
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-DT-1'''
| [[Ottawa]]
| 22 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 11.1 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
| 25&amp;nbsp;kW
| 216 m
| {{Coord|45|13|2|N|75|33|49|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-1}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-DT-2'''
| [[London, Ontario|London]]
| 51 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 51.1 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
| 190&amp;nbsp;kW 
| 296.5 m
| {{Coord|42|50|27|N|81|51|29|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-2}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-DT-3'''
| [[Muskoka District Municipality, Ontario|Muskoka]]
| 23 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 67.1 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
| 63&amp;nbsp;kW
| 306.7 m
| {{Coord|44|58|14|N|79|46|57|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-3}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-TV-4'''
| [[Greater Sudbury|Sudbury]]
| 41 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| N/A
| 35&amp;nbsp;kW
| 171.9 m
| {{Coord|46|25|29|N|81|0|53|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-4}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-TV-5'''
| [[Sault Ste. Marie, Ontario|Sault Ste. Marie]]
| 38 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| N/A
| 5&amp;nbsp;kW
| 112.5 m
| {{Coord|46|35|50|N|84|16|53|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-5}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-TV-6'''
| [[North Bay, Ontario|North Bay]]
| 32 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| N/A
| 5&amp;nbsp;kW
| 116 m
| {{Coord|46|18|10|N|79|24|39|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-6}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''CHCH-TV-7'''
| [[Timmins]]
| 11 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])
| N/A
| 3.3&amp;nbsp;kW
| 142.2 m
| {{Coord|48|28|12|N|81|17|49|W|type:landmark|name=CHCH-TV-7}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
|}

During the [[Digital television in Canada|analog television shutdown and digital conversion]] in August 2011, CHCH's transmitters in Ottawa, London, and Muskoka (serving [[Barrie, Ontario|Barrie]], part of the Toronto market) converted to digital since transmitters in or near markets that were mandated to do so. However, the transmitters broadcast in [[Standard-definition television|standard-definition]] [[480i]] since they receive the CHCH signal via [[Shaw Broadcast Services]], which does not carry CHCH HD.

==Digital television and high definition==
CHCH currently broadcasts a digital signal on channel 11. The station's pre-transition digital transmitter on channel 18 in Hamilton was launched on April 18, 2008 by previous owners [[Canwest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.canwest.com/media/viewNews.asp?NewsroomID=804| title=Canwest Broadcasting Launches Three New High Definition Transmitters In Major Canadian Markets| date=2008-04-10| work=Canwest Broadcasting| accessdate=2008-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Digital television in Canada|analog television shutdown and digital conversion]], which mandated stations in mandatory markets to shut down their analog signals before August 31, 2011,&lt;ref name=&quot;Analog to Digital&quot;&gt;http://www.ic.gc.ca/epic/site/oca-bc.nsf/en/ca02336e.html&lt;/ref&gt; CHCH-DT moved from its pre-transition channel number, 18, to the channel position formerly occupied by its analog channel, 11, on August 15, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;YouTube video of transition&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EoF7jVAgg2g&lt;/ref&gt; The analog signal was discontinued immediately preceding the switch. CHCH-DT is available on digital cable as well as for free [[Digital terrestrial television|over the air]] using a regular TV antenna and a digital tuner, included in most new TVs. Reception of CHCH-DT on channel 11 has been difficult for some people in the GTA.

As of September 12, 2011, CHCH is now offered in HD on [[Bell TV]] via channel 1057.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.chch.com CHCH]
*[http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php?id=9&amp;historyID=28 Canadian Communications Foundation - CHCH-TV History]
*{{RecnetCanada|CHCH-TV}}
*{{TV Fool|CHCH}}

{{Toronto TV}}
{{CanindTVstations}}
{{News and information television channels in Canada}}
{{LocalCableNews}}
{{ChannelZero}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chch-Tv}}
[[Category:Television stations in Hamilton, Ontario|HCH]]
[[Category:Channel Zero (company)]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1954]]
[[Category:Channel 11 TV stations in Canada]]
[[Category:Independent television stations in Canada|HCH]]

[[fr:CHCH-DT]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
