<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="541324" ns="0" title="Bethune-Cookman University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|29.2102556|-81.0306086|display=title}}
{{Infobox University
 |name              = Bethune-Cookman University
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Bethune-CookmanSeal.png
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = Enter to Learn, Depart to Serve&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Student Handbook|url=http://www.cookman.edu/documents/studAffrs/studenthandbook.pdf|publisher=Bethune-Cookman University|accessdate=May 14, 2011|page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = 1904
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Private university|Private]], [[Historically black colleges and universities|HBCU]]
 |endowment         = $34.0 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2010 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2009 to FY 2010| work = 2010 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf|page=16| format = PDF | accessdate = May 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |affiliation       = [[United Methodist Church]]&lt;br /&gt;[[United Negro College Fund|UNCF]]
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = Trudie Kibbe Reed
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 3,594&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Education: Bethune-Cookman University|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/bethune-cookman-university-1467|publisher=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]|accessdate=May 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Daytona Beach, Florida|Daytona Beach]]
 |state             = [[Florida]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = &lt;br /&gt;[[United States]]
 |coor              = 
 |campus            = [[urban area|Urban]], 82 acres (0.29 km²)
 |former_names      = 
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = [[Maroon (color)|Maroon]] and [[Gold (color)|Gold]]&lt;br /&gt; {{color box|#6A3547}} {{color box|#E4A41D}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = [[Bethune-Cookman Wildcats|Wildcats]]|
 |mascot            = Wil D Cat
 |athletics         = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Championship Subdivision|Div I FCS]]
 |affiliations      = [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference]]
 |website           = [http://www.Cookman.edu/ www.cookman.edu]
 |logo              = [[Image:B-cc cat.png|150px]]
 |footnotes         = 
}}'''Bethune-Cookman University''' or '''B-CU''' is a private [[historically black university]] in [[Daytona Beach, Florida]].

== History ==
[[Mary McLeod Bethune]] founded the Daytona Educational and Industrial Training School in 1904.&lt;ref name=impact&gt;{{cite journal|last=Collier-Thomas|first=Bettye|title=The Impact of Black Women in Education: An Historical Perspective|journal=[[The Journal of Negro Education]]|year=1982|month=Summer|volume=51|issue=3|jstor=2294687|page=179|publisher=[[Howard University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The school underwent several stages of growth and development through the years and in 1923, it merged with the Cookman Institute of Jacksonville, Florida and became a co-ed high school. A year later in 1924, it became affiliated with the Methodist Church. By 1931, the school had become a junior college.

The school became a four-year college in 1941 when the [[Florida Board of Education]] approved a 4-year baccalaureate program in Liberal Arts and Teacher Education. The name was changed to Bethune-Cookman College.

On February 14, 2007, the Board of Trustees approved the name Bethune-Cookman University after the institution established its first graduate program.

In October 2010 the [[American Association of University Professors]] accused the university administration of improperly dismissing tenured members of the faculty—some for alleged sexual harassment (but, in the opinion of the AAUP, without due process), others for &quot;budgetary reasons&quot; but without a declaration of &quot;financial exigency&quot;.  The university responded saying that the AAUP report contained errors and a one-sided view.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Schmidt, [http://chronicle.com/article/AAUP-Accuses-Bethune-Cookman/125088/ &quot;AAUP Accuses Bethune-Cookman U. of Denying Due Process to 7 Dismissed Professors&quot;], ''The Chronicle of Higher Education'', 25 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Presidents ===
Bethune retired in 1942 at which time [[James A. Colston]] became president until 1946 when Bethune resumed the presidency for a year.

Richard V. Moore, Sr. became president in 1947. Under his tenure the college was accredited by the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] in 1970, joined the [[United Negro College Fund]] and other academic and professional organizations. The curriculum expanded, student enrollment increased and new buildings were constructed for residential housing and classrooms.

Oswald P. Bronson, Sr.(B-CU alumnus) served as the fourth president of the college from 1975 to 2004. During his tenure increased student enrollment led to continuous development and expansion of the college. A rapidly increasing student enrollment led to construction of more student housing, classroom buildings and the Mary Mcleod Bethune Auditorium. Major fields of study increased from 12 in 1974 to 37 by 2003. In addition, seven continuing education centers for students began operating throughout the state. While maintaining accreditation by SACS, Florida Board of Education, and the United Methodist Church Board of Higher Education the college added new accreditations in the Nursing and the Teacher Education programs.

Trudie Kibbe Reed was appointed to the presidency in August 2004 by the Board of Trustees. Reed is the first woman to serve in this capacity since Bethune. Since beginning her tenure, the university has a number of campus improvements including construction of the Center for Civic Engagement, the L. Gale Lemerand School of Nursing, the creation of the Alexis Pugh and Eugene Zimmerman Scholarship houses, and the provision of a university-owned house as an alumni center. Reed also established the university's first graduate program under the School of Graduate &amp; Professional Studies. The new program is a Master of Science in Transformative Leadership.

== Academics ==
Bethune-Cookman University is a small, private, co-educational, and residential institution. The university meets its commitment to excellence through expanding and modifying academic programs and innovative curricular offerings by preparing students to meet the demands of the future. 

The academic program of the university is conducted within seven schools&lt;ref&gt;2008 - 2009 College Catalog&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-3}}
* School of Arts &amp; Humanities
* School of Business
* School of Education
{{Col-3}}
* School of Nursing
* School of Graduate &amp; Professional Studies
{{Col-3}}
* School of Science, Engineering and Mathematics
* School of Social Sciences
{{Col-end}}

== Student activities ==
===Athletics ===
{{Main|Bethune-Cookman Wildcats}}
Bethune-Cookman University is a member of the [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference]] and participates in [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division 1-AA]].  The school sponsors basketball, bowling, baseball, cross country, football, track and field and volleyball. The Wildcats joined the Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference in 1979. The Wildcats have 29 MEAC titles; 13 in baseball, 1 in bowling, 1 in men's cross country, 2 in women's cross country, 3 in football, 2 in women's indoor track and field, 5 in softball and 2 in women's tennis.

B-CU has an intense in-state rivalry with Florida A&amp;M University.  Today, they meet annually in the [[Florida Classic]], a regular-season, neutral-Bethune-Cookman's first win came a year later, 12-0 in 1926. 
In 2000, Mervyl S. Melendez, (B-CU alumnus) was named as the head coach for the Wildcats' baseball program. He's the first B-CU head coach to win a MEAC title in his first season, and under his tutelage, the Wildcats baseball team has won seven conference championships in the last eight years (2000–2004, and 2006–2007). In 2007, the Wildcats finished the regular season with a record of 33-25, with notable wins against both University of Tennessee and Stetson University, as well as ranking #1 in the 2007 Black College Baseball poll.

====Football====
Brian Jenkins (Native Floridian) was named the tenth head football coach at Bethune-Cookman University on December 21, 2009. He comes to B-CU from Rutgers where he served as an Assistant Coach.
In 2010, Bethune-Cookman, Florida A&amp;M and South Carolina State all shared a piece of the 2010 [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference|MEAC]] Football Title; with each team posting an identical 7-1 conference record.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MEAC Highlights|url=http://www.meacsports.com//pdf8/726852.pdf?DB_OEM_ID=20800|publisher=Mid Eastern Athletic Conference|accessdate=5 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; B-CU has won 2 MEAC football championships outright in 1984 and 2002.

== Marching band ==
[[Image:Bbband.jpg|thumb||left|The Marching Wildcats (The Pride)of Bethune-Cookman create the &quot;BCU&quot; formation while playing before a packed Citrus Bowl Stadium at the [[Florida Classic]].]]The Marching Wildcats are a 325 member unit that includes instrumentalists, the Sophisticat Flag Corps and the 14 Karat Gold dancers. Known as &quot;''The Pride'',&quot; the band is under the direction of a Bethune-Cookman alumnus and former Marching Wildcat, Donovan Wells.

The 14 Karat Gold dancers are featured performers in all engagements of the Marching Wildcats and occasionally perform as a solo act. The 14 Karat Gold dancers can be seen frequently in BET video clips promoting Black colleges. The Sophisticat Flag Corps blends traditional flag techniques with innovative choreography to create highly entertaining presentation.

;Performances
The Marching Wildcats perform pre-game and halftime shows at all home games of the Fighting Wildcats football team. Games played in neutral sites where Bethune-Cookman University is deemed the home team, ''The Pride'' also performs a traditional pre-game show.

{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot; 
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; |'''''The Pride's'' leadership'''
|-
|Donovan Wells
|Director of College Bands
|-
|James Poitier
|Associate Director and Arranger
|-
|Pedro Orey
|Assistant Director and Percussion Instructor
|-
|Ernest Hamilton
|Auxiliary Instructor
|-
|Horatio Walker
|Announcer
|}''The Pride'' has been featured in numerous events, including televised performances. On January 26, 2008, the band performed in its fifth Honda Battle of the Bands showcase of HBCU bands in the [[Georgia Dome]] in [[Atlanta, Georgia]] as the Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference representative. In December 2005, a small group of ''The Pride'''s percussion section filmed a commercial unveiling the new Cadillac DTS. The commercial made its debut in February 2006 and continued air play throughout the rest of the year. Immediately following the band's January 2005 performance at the Honda Battle of the Bands, the event's producers nominated ''The Pride'' to be featured in the Super Bowl special episode of the Emmy-winning ''[[Ellen DeGeneres Show]]''. &quot;The Pride&quot; also made an appearance in the 2002 film Drumline.

== See also ==
* [[List of Bethune-Cookman University Alumni]]
* [[Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.Cookman.edu/ www.cookman.edu] -- Official web site

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Navboxes
|title=Articles and topics related to Bethune-Cookman University
|state=collapsed
|list1=&lt;/span&gt;
{{Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida}}
{{MethodistColleges}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference}}
{{Divison1floridacolleges}}
}}

[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Bethune-Cookman University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Volusia County, Florida]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1904]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Daytona Beach, Florida]]

[[no:Bethune-Cookman College]]
[[simple:Bethune-Cookman University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
