<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5416" ns="0" title="Capitalism"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Liberal market economy|the ideology behind this economic system|Economic liberalism}}
{{Redirect|Free enterprise|the 1999 film|Free Enterprise (film)}}
{{Other uses}}
{{Capitalism}}

'''Capitalism''' is an [[economic system]] that became dominant in the [[Western world]] following the [[History of capitalism|demise of feudalism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Capitalism|publisher=Encyclopedia Britannica|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no consensus on the precise definition nor on how the term should be used as a historical category.&lt;ref&gt;Critical Issues in History. Lanham, Md: Rowman and Littlefield, 1999, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; There is general agreement that elements of capitalism include [[Private property|private ownership]] of the [[means of production]], creation of goods or services for [[profit (economics)|profit]] or [[income]], [[competitive markets]], [[voluntary exchange]], and [[wage labor]].&lt;ref&gt;Heilbroner, Robert L. ''Capitalism''. New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics, Secound Edition (2008): http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_C000053&amp;edition=current&amp;q=state%20capitalism&amp;topicid=&amp;result_number=2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tormey, Simon. Anti-Capitalism. One World Publications, 2004. p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; The designation is applied to a variety of historical cases, varying in time, geography, politics and culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;/&gt;

Economists, [[political economy|political economists]] and [[history|historians]] have taken different perspectives on the analysis of capitalism. Economists usually emphasize the degree that government does not have control over markets ([[laissez faire]]), and on [[property]] rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Tucker, Irvin B.|title=Macroeconomics for Today|pages=553|year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Case, Karl E.|title=Principles of Macroeconomics|publisher=Prentice Hall|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most political economists emphasize private property, [[Economic power|power]] relations, wage labour, [[Economic class|class]] and emphasize capitalism as a unique historical formation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stilwell&quot;/&gt; Capitalism is generally viewed as encouraging [[economic growth]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Economic systems&quot;. Encyclopedia Britannica 2007 Ultimate Reference Suite. (Chicago: Encyclopædia Britannica, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The extent to which different markets are free, as well as the rules defining private property, is a matter of politics and [[policy]], and many states have what are termed [[mixed economy|mixed economies]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stilwell&quot;&gt;Stilwell, Frank. “Political Economy: the Contest of Economic Ideas.” First Edition. Oxford University Press. Melbourne, Australia. 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Capitalism gradually spread throughout Europe, and in the 19th and 20th centuries, it provided the main means of [[industrialization]] throughout much of the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Industrialism: A Dictionary of Sociology|author=Scott, John|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and early usage==
{| align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;box&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:1em;text-align: left; border: 4px solid #aaaaaa; padding: 2px; font-size: 100%; width: 30%;&quot;
|bgcolor=&quot;#dbeaff&quot;|
Other terms sometimes used for capitalism:
* [[Capitalist mode of production]]
* [[Economic liberalism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Adam Smith and His Legacy for Modern Capitalism|author=Werhane, P.H.|journal=The Review of Metaphysics|volume=47|year=1994|publisher=Philosophy Education Society, Inc.|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Free-enterprise economy&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rogetfreeenterprise&quot;&gt;&quot;free enterprise.&quot; Roget's 21st Century Thesaurus, Third Edition. Philip Lief Group 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Free market]]&lt;ref name=&quot;rogetfreeenterprise&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mutualist&quot;&gt;[http://www.mutualist.org/ Mutualist.org]. &quot;...based on voluntary cooperation, free exchange, or mutual aid.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* Laissez-faire economy&lt;ref name=Barrons&gt;Barrons Dictionary of Finance and Investment Terms. 1995. p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Market economy]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://unabridged.merriam-webster.com/cgi-bin/unabridged?va=market%20economy &quot;Market economy&quot;], Merriam-Webster Unabridged Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Market liberalism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cato.org/about.php |title=About Cato |publisher=Cato.org |date= |accessdate=6 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cato.org/university/module10.html |title=The Achievements of Nineteenth-Century Classical Liberalism }} &lt;blockquote&gt;Although the term &quot;liberalism&quot; retains its original meaning in most of the world, it has unfortunately come to have a very different meaning in late twentieth-century America. Hence terms such as &quot;market liberalism,&quot; &quot;classical liberalism,&quot; or &quot;libertarianism&quot; are often used in its place in America.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
* Self-regulating market&lt;ref name=&quot;rogetfreeenterprise&quot;/&gt;
|}

''Capital'' evolved from ''capitale'', a late [[Latin]] word based on [[proto-Indo-European language|proto-Indo-European]] ''caput'', meaning &quot;head&quot; — also the origin of ''[[chattel]]'' and ''[[cattle]]'' in the sense of movable property (only much later to refer only to livestock). Capitale emerged in the 12th to 13th centuries in the sense of funds, stock of merchandise, sum of money, or money carrying interest.&lt;ref name=&quot;Braudel on capitalism&quot;&gt;Braudel p.232&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=cattle Etymology of &quot;Cattle&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;&gt;James Augustus Henry Murray. &quot;Capital&quot;. [http://www.archive.org/details/oedvol02 A New English Dictionary on Historical Principles]. ''Oxford English Press''. Vol 2. page 93.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1283 it was used in the sense of the capital assets of a trading firm. It was frequently interchanged with a number of other words — wealth, money, funds, goods, assets, property and so on.&lt;ref name=&quot;Braudel on capitalism&quot;&gt;Braudel p.233&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''capitalist'' refers to an owner of capital rather than an economic system, but shows earlier recorded use than the term ''capitalism'', dating back to the mid-seventeenth century. The ''Hollandische Mercurius'' uses it in 1633 and 1654 to refer to owners of capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Braudel on capitalism&quot;&gt;Braudel p.234&lt;/ref&gt; In French, [[Étienne Clavier]] referred to ''capitalistes'' in 1788,&lt;ref&gt;e.g. &quot;L'Angleterre a-t-elle l'heureux privilège de n'avoir ni Agioteurs, ni Banquiers, ni Faiseurs de services, ni Capitalistes?&quot; in [Etienne Clavier] (1788) ''De la foi publique envers les créanciers de l'état: lettres à M. Linguet sur le n ° CXVI de ses annales'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=ESMVAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA19#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false p.19]&lt;/ref&gt; six years before its first recorded English usage by [[Arthur Young (writer)|Arthur Young]] in his work ''Travels in France'' (1792).&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Young. [http://books.google.com/books?id=l10JAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage#PPA529,M1 Travels in France]&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Ricardo]], in his ''[[Principles of Political Economy and Taxation]]'' (1817), referred to &quot;the capitalist&quot; many times.&lt;ref&gt;Ricardo, David. Principles of Political Economy and Taxation. 1821. John Murray Publisher, 3rd edition.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Samuel Taylor Coleridge]], an English poet, used ''capitalist'' in his work ''Table Talk'' (1823).&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Taylor Coleridge. [http://books.google.com/books?id=ma-4W-XiGkIC&amp;printsec=titlepage&amp;dq=%22capitalists+for+having+labour+at+demand Tabel The Complete Works of Samuel Taylor Coleridge]. page 267.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] used the term ''capitalist'' in his first work, ''[[What is Property?]]'' (1840) to refer to the owners of capital. [[Benjamin Disraeli]] used the term ''capitalist'' in his 1845 work ''[[Sybil (novel)|Sybil]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;/&gt; [[Karl Marx]] and [[Friedrich Engels]] used the term ''capitalist'' (''Kapitalist'') in ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]'' (1848) to refer to a private owner of capital.

According to the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (OED), the term ''capitalism'' was first used by novelist [[William Makepeace Thackeray]] in 1854 in ''[[The Newcomes]]'', where he meant &quot;having ownership of capital&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;&gt;James Augustus Henry Murray. &quot;Capitalism&quot; page 94.&lt;/ref&gt; Also according to the OED, [[Carl Adolph Douai]], a [[German-American]] [[Socialism|socialist]] and [[Abolitionism|abolitionist]], used the term ''private capitalism'' in 1863.

The initial usage of the term ''capitalism'' in its modern sense has been attributed to [[Louis Blanc]] in 1850 and Pierre-Joseph Proudhon in 1861.&lt;ref&gt;Braudel, Fernand. The Wheels of Commerce: Civilization and Capitalism 15–18 Century, Harper and Row, 1979, p.237&lt;/ref&gt; Marx and Engels referred to the ''capitalistic system'' (''kapitalistisches System'')&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx. Chapter 16: Absolute and Relative Surplus-Value. ''[[Das Kapital]]''.
&lt;blockquote&gt;''{{lang|de|Die Verlängrung des Arbeitstags über den Punkt hinaus, wo der Arbeiter nur ein Äquivalent für den Wert seiner Arbeitskraft produziert hätte, und die Aneignung dieser Mehrarbeit durch das Kapital – das ist die Produktion des absoluten Mehrwerts. Sie bildet die allgemeine Grundlage des '''kapitalistischen Systems''' und den Ausgangspunkt der Produktion des relativen Mehrwerts.}}''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The prolongation of the working-day beyond the point at which the labourer would have produced just an equivalent for the value of his labour-power, and the appropriation of that surplus-labour by capital, this is production of absolute surplus-value. It forms the general groundwork of the '''capitalist system''', and the starting-point for the production of relative surplus-value.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx. Chapter Twenty-Five: The General Law of Capitalist Accumulation. ''Das Kapital''.
* ''{{lang|de|Die Erhöhung des Arbeitspreises bleibt also eingebannt in Grenzen, die die Grundlagen des '''kapitalistischen Systems''' nicht nur unangetastet lassen, sondern auch seine Reproduktion auf wachsender Stufenleiter sichern.}}''
* ''{{lang|de|Die allgemeinen Grundlagen des '''kapitalistischen Systems''' einmal gegeben, tritt im Verlauf der Akkumulation jedesmal ein Punkt ein, wo die Entwicklung der Produktivität der gesellschaftlichen Arbeit der mächtigste Hebel der Akkumulation wird.}}''
* ''{{lang|de|Wir sahen im vierten Abschnitt bei Analyse der Produktion des relativen Mehrwerts: innerhalb des '''kapitalistischen Systems''' vollziehn sich alle Methoden zur Steigerung der gesellschaftlichen Produktivkraft der Arbeit auf Kosten des individuellen Arbeiters;}}''&lt;/ref&gt; and to the capitalist mode of production (''kapitalistische Produktionsform'') in ''Das Kapital'' (1867).&lt;ref&gt;Saunders, Peter (1995). ''Capitalism''. University of Minnesota Press. p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the word &quot;capitalism&quot; in reference to an economic system appears twice in Volume I of ''Das Kapital'', p.&amp;nbsp;124 (German edition), and in ''Theories of Surplus Value'', tome II, p.&amp;nbsp;493 (German edition). Marx did not extensively use the form ''capitalism'', but instead those of ''capitalist'' and ''capitalist mode of production'', which appear more than 2600 times in the trilogy ''Das Kapital''.

Marx's notion of the capitalist mode of production is characterised as a system of primarily private ownership of the means of production in a mainly market economy, with a legal framework on [[commerce]] and a physical [[infrastructure]] provided by the state. No legal framework was available to protect the labourers, so exploitation by the companies was rife.&lt;ref&gt;Karl Marx. ''Das Kapital''.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=August 2010}} Engels made more frequent use of the term ''capitalism''; volumes II and III of ''Das Kapital'', both edited by Engels after Marx's death, contain the word &quot;capitalism&quot; four and three times, respectively. The three combined volumes of ''Das Kapital'' (1867, 1885, 1894) contain the word ''capitalist'' more than 2,600 times.

An 1877 work entitled ''Better Times'' by Hugh Gabutt and an 1884 article in the ''[[Pall Mall Gazette]]'' also used the term ''capitalism''.&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;/&gt; A later use of the term ''capitalism'' to describe the production system was by the German economist [[Werner Sombart]], in his 1902 book ''The Jews and Modern Capitalism'' (''Die Juden und das Wirtschaftsleben''). Sombart's close friend and colleague, [[Max Weber]], also used ''capitalism'' in his 1904 book ''[[The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism]]'' (''Die protestantische Ethik und der Geist des Kapitalismus'').

==Economic elements==
{{Ref improve section|date=May 2010}}
Capitalist economics developed out of the interactions of the following elements.

A [[Product (business)|product]] is any good produced for exchange on a market. &quot;Commodities&quot; refers to standard products, especially raw materials such as grains and metals, that are not associated with particular producers or brands and trade on organized exchanges.

There are two types of products: [[capital good]]s and [[Final goods|consumer goods]]. Capital goods (i.e., raw materials, tools, industrial machines, vehicles and factories) are used to produce consumer goods (e.g., televisions, cars, computers, houses) to be sold to others. The three inputs required for production are labour, land (i.e., natural resources, which exist prior to human beings) and capital goods. Capitalism entails the private ownership of the latter two — natural resources and capital goods — by a class of owners called capitalists, either individually, collectively or through a state apparatus that operates for a profit or serves the interests of capital owners.

Money was primarily a standardized medium of exchange, and final means of payment, that serves to measure the value all goods and commodities in a standard of value. It eliminates the cumbersome system of [[barter]] by separating the transactions involved in the exchange of products, thus greatly facilitating specialization and trade through encouraging the exchange of commodities. Capitalism involves the further abstraction of money into other exchangeable assets and the accumulation of money through ownership, exchange, interest and various other financial instruments. However, besides serving as a medium of exchange for labour, goods and services, money is also a store of value, similar to precious metals.

[[Labour (economics)|Labour]] includes all physical and mental human resources, including entrepreneurial capacity and management skills, which are needed to produce products and services. [[Manufacturing|Production]] is the act of making products or services by applying [[labour power]] to the means of production.&lt;ref&gt;Ragan, Christopher T.S., and Richard G. Lipsey. Microeconomics. Twelfth Canadian Edition ed. Toronto: Pearson Education Canada, 2008. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robbins, Richard H. Global problems and the culture of capitalism. Boston: Allyn &amp; Bacon, 2007. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of capitalism==
{{Economics sidebar}}
There are many variants of capitalism in existence. All these forms of capitalism are based on production for profit, at least a moderate degree of market allocation and capital accumulation. The dominant forms of capitalism are listed here.

===Mercantilism===
{{Main|Mercantilism}}
{{See also|Protectionism}}
A nationalist form of early capitalism where national business interests are tied to state interests, and consequently, the state apparatus is utilized to advance national business interests abroad. Mercantilism holds that the wealth of a nation is increased through a positive balance of trade with other nations.

===Free-market capitalism===
{{Main|Free market}}
{{See also|Laissez-faire}}
Free market capitalism consists of a free-price system where supply and demand are allowed to reach their point of equilibrium without intervention by the government. Productive enterprises are privately owned, and the role of the state is limited to protecting [[property rights]].

===Social market economy===
{{Main|Social market}}
A social market economy is a nominally free-market system where government intervention in price formation is kept to a minimum but the state provides significant social security, unemployment benefits and recognition of labour rights through national collective bargaining laws. The social market is based on private ownership of businesses.

===State capitalism===
{{Main|State capitalism}}
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2011}}
State capitalism consists of state ownership of profit-seeking enterprises that operate in a capitalist manner in a market economy. Examples include [[Corporatization|corporatized]] government agencies or partial state ownership of shares in publicly listed firms. The term ''state capitalism'' has also been used to refer to an economy consisting of mainly private enterprises that are subjected to comprehensive [[Indicative planning|national economic planning]] by the government, wherein the state intervenes in the economy to protect specific capitalist businesses (although this is usually referred to as ''[[state monopoly capitalism]]'' or ''[[corporate capitalism]]''). Many socialists and [[anti-Stalinist left|anti-Stalinist leftists]] argue that the [[Soviet Union]] was state capitalist instead of socialist, since the state owned all the means of production, functioned as an enormous corporation, and exploited the [[working class]].

===Corporate capitalism===
{{Main|Corporate capitalism}}
{{See also|State monopoly capitalism}}
Corporate capitalism is a free or mixed market characterized by the dominance of hierarchical, bureaucratic corporations, which are legally required to pursue profit. State monopoly capitalism refers to a form of corporate capitalism where the state is used to benefit, protect from competition and promote the interests of dominant or established corporations.{{Fact|date=September 2011}}

===Mixed economy===
{{Main|Mixed economy}}
A largely market-based economy consisting of both public ownership and private ownership of the means of production. In practice, a mixed economy will be heavily slanted toward one extreme; most capitalist economies are defined as &quot;mixed economies&quot; to some degree and are characterized by the dominance of private ownership.{{Fact|date=September 2011}}

===Other===
Other variants of capitalism include:
{{Col-begin|width=100%}}
{{Col-1-of-3}}
*[[Crony capitalism]]
*[[Finance capitalism]]
*[[Financial capitalism]]
{{Col-2-of-3}}
*[[Late capitalism]]
*[[Market economy]]
*[[Neo-Capitalism]]
{{Col-3-of-3}}
*[[Post-capitalism]]
*[[Technocapitalism]]
{{col-end}}

==History==
{{Main|History of capitalism}}

Economic trade for profit has existed since the second millennium BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;WarburtonDavid&quot;&gt;Warburton, David, Macroeconomics from the beginning: The General Theory, Ancient Markets, and the Rate of Interest. Paris: Recherches et Publications, 2003.p49&lt;/ref&gt; However, capitalism in its modern form is usually traced to the Mercantilism of the 16th-18th Centuries. 

===Mercantilism===
{{Main|Mercantilism}}
[[File:Lorrain.seaport.jpg|right|250px|thumb|A painting of a French seaport from 1638 at the height of [[mercantilism]].]]
The period between the sixteenth and eighteenth centuries is commonly described as [[mercantilism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Burnham&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|author=Burnham, Peter|title=Capitalism: The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Politics|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; This period, the [[Age of Discovery]], was associated with geographic exploration being exploited by merchant overseas traders, especially from England and the [[Low Countries]]; the [[European colonization of the Americas]]; and the rapid growth in overseas trade. Mercantilism was a system of trade for profit, although commodities were still largely produced by non-capitalist production methods.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot; /&gt;

While some scholars see mercantilism as the earliest stage of capitalism, others argue that capitalism did not emerge until later. For example, [[Karl Polanyi]], noted that &quot;mercantilism, with all its tendency toward commercialization, never attacked the safeguards which protected [the] two basic elements of production—labour and land—from becoming the elements of commerce&quot;; thus mercantilist attitudes towards economic regulation were closer to feudalist attitudes, &quot;they disagreed only on the methods of regulation.&quot;

Moreover Polanyi argued that the hallmark of capitalism is the establishment of generalized markets for what he referred to as the &quot;fictitious commodities&quot;: land, labour, and money. Accordingly, &quot;not until 1834 was a competitive labour market established in England, hence industrial capitalism as a social system cannot be said to have existed before that date.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Polanyi, Karl. The Great Transformation. Beacon Press, Boston.1944.p87&lt;/ref&gt;

Evidence of long-distance merchant-driven trade motivated by profit has been found as early as the second millennium BC, with the Old Assyrian merchants.&lt;ref name=&quot;WarburtonDavid&quot; /&gt; The earliest forms of mercantilism date back to the [[Roman Empire]]. When the Roman Empire expanded, the mercantilist economy expanded throughout Europe. After the [[decline of the Roman Empire|collapse of the Roman Empire]], most of the European economy became controlled by local [[feudal]] powers, and mercantilism collapsed there. However, mercantilism persisted in [[Arabia]]. Due to its proximity to neighboring countries, the Arabs established trade routes to [[Egypt]], [[Persia]], and [[Byzantium]]. As [[Islam]] spread in the seventh century, mercantilism spread rapidly to Spain, Portugal, [[Northern Africa]], and Asia. Mercantilism finally revived in Europe in the fourteenth century, as mercantilism spread from Spain and Portugal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.howstuffworks.com/european-history/capitalism3.htm The Rise of Capitalism]&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the major tenets of mercantilist theory was [[bullionism]], a doctrine stressing the importance of accumulating [[precious metals]]. Mercantilists argued that a state should export more goods than it imported so that foreigners would have to pay the difference in precious metals. Mercantilists asserted that only raw materials that could not be extracted at home should be imported; and promoted government [[subsidy|subsidies]], such as the granting of monopolies and protective [[tariff]]s, were necessary to encourage home production of manufactured goods.

[[File:Clive.jpg|thumb|250px|right|[[Robert Clive]] after the [[Battle of Plassey]]. The battle began [[East India Company]] rule in India.]]
European [[merchant]]s, backed by state controls, subsidies, and [[monopoly|monopolies]], made most of their profits from the buying and selling of goods. In the words of [[Francis Bacon]], the purpose of mercantilism was &quot;the opening and well-balancing of trade; the cherishing of manufacturers; the banishing of idleness; the repressing of waste and excess by sumptuary laws; the improvement and husbanding of the soil; the regulation of prices…&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Sir George Clark, ''The Seventeenth Century'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 1961), p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar practices of economic regimentation had begun earlier in the medieval towns. However, under mercantilism, given the contemporaneous rise of [[Absolute monarchy|absolutism]], the state superseded the local [[guild]]s as the regulator of the economy. During that time the guilds essentially functioned like [[cartels]] that monopolized the quantity of craftsmen to earn above-market wages.&lt;ref&gt;Mancur Olson, The rise and decline of nations: economic growth, stagflation, and social rigidities (New Haven &amp; London 1982).&lt;/ref&gt;

At the period from the eighteenth century, the commercial stage of capitalism originated from the start of the British East India Company and the [[Dutch East India Company]].&lt;ref name=Banaji&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Banaji, Jairus|year=2007|title=Islam, the Mediterranean and the rise of capitalism|journal=Journal Historical Materialism|volume=15|pages=47–74|publisher=Brill Publishers|doi=10.1163/156920607X171591}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Economic system :: Market systems|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/178493/economic-system/61117/Market-systems#toc242146|publisher=Encyclopedia Britannica|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; These companies were characterized by their [[colonialism|colonial]] and [[expansionism|expansionary]] powers given to them by nation-states.&lt;ref name=&quot;Banaji&quot; /&gt; During this era, merchants, who had traded under the previous stage of mercantilism, invested capital in the East India Companies and other colonies, seeking a [[return on investment]]. In his &quot;History of Economic Analysis,&quot; Austrian economist [[Joseph Schumpeter]] reduced mercantilist propositions to three main concerns: exchange controls, export monopolism and balance of trade.&lt;ref&gt;Schumpeter, J.A. (1954) History of Economic Analysis&lt;/ref&gt;

===Industrialism===
{{See also|Industrial Revolution}}
[[File:Maquina vapor Watt ETSIIM.jpg|250px|thumb|A [[Watt steam engine]]. The [[steam engine]] fuelled primarily by [[coal]] propelled the [[Industrial Revolution]] in [[United Kingdom|Great Britain]].&lt;ref&gt;Watt steam engine image: located in the lobby of into the Superior Technical School of Industrial Engineers of a the UPM ([[Madrid]])&lt;/ref&gt;]]
A new group of economic theorists, led by [[David Hume]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Hume, David|title=Political Discourses|location=Edinburgh|publisher=A. Kincaid &amp;amp; A. Donaldson|year=1752}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Adam Smith]], in the mid 18th century, challenged fundamental [[mercantilist]] doctrines as the belief that the amount of the world’s wealth remained constant and that a state could only increase its wealth at the expense of another state.

During the Industrial Revolution, the industrialist replaced the merchant as a dominant actor in the capitalist system and effected the decline of the traditional handicraft skills of [[artisan]]s, guilds, and [[journeyman|journeymen]]. Also during this period, the surplus generated by the rise of commercial agriculture encouraged increased mechanization of agriculture. Industrial capitalism marked the development of the [[factory]] system of manufacturing, characterized by a complex [[division of labor]] between and within work process and the routine of work tasks; and finally established the global domination of the capitalist mode of production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burnham&quot; /&gt;

Britain also abandoned its [[protectionist]] policy, as embraced by mercantilism. In the 19th century, [[Richard Cobden]] and [[John Bright]], who based their beliefs on the [[Manchester capitalism|Manchester School]], initiated a movement to lower tariffs.&lt;ref name=&quot;laissezf&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=laissez-faire|url=http://www.bartleby.com/65/la/laissezf.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1840s, Britain adopted a less protectionist policy, with the repeal of the [[Corn Laws]] and the [[Navigation Acts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Burnham&quot; /&gt; Britain reduced [[tariffs]] and [[import quota|quotas]], in line with Adam Smith and David Ricardo's advocacy for [[free trade]].

Karl Polanyi argued that capitalism did not emerge until the progressive commodification of land, money, and labour culminating in the establishment of a generalized labour market in Britain in the 1830s. For Polanyi, &quot;the extension of the market to the elements of industry – land, labour and money – was the inevitable consequence of the introduction of the factory system in a commercial society.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Polanyi, Karl. The Great Transformation, Beacon Press. Boston. 1944. p.78&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources argued that mercantilism fell after the repeal of the Navigation Acts in 1849.&lt;ref name=&quot;laissezf&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Navigation Acts
|url=http://www.bartleby.com/65/na/NavigatA.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mercantilism&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|last=LaHaye|first=Laura|title=Mercantilism|url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/Mercantilism.html|work=[[Concise Encyclepedia of Economics]]|publisher=Fortune Encyclopedia of Economics|year=1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Keynesianism and neoliberalism===
{{Main|Keynesianism|Neoliberalism}}
In the period following the global depression of the 1930s, the state played an increasingly prominent role in the capitalistic system throughout much of the world.

[[File:NY stock exchange traders floor LC-U9-10548-6.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The New York [[stock exchange]] [[trading room|traders' floor]] (1963)]]

After [[World War II]], a broad array of new analytical tools in the [[social sciences]] were developed to explain the social and economic trends of the period, including the concepts of [[post-industrial society]] and the [[welfare state]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Burnham&quot; /&gt; This era was greatly influenced by [[Keynesian]] economic stabilization policies. The postwar boom ended in the late 1960s and early 1970s, and the situation was worsened by the rise of [[stagflation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Barnes, Trevor J.|title=Reading economic geography|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|isbn=063123554X|pages=127|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Exceptionally high [[inflation]] combined with slow output growth, rising unemployment, and eventually [[recession]] to cause a loss of credibility in the Keynesian welfare-statist mode of regulation. Under the influence of [[Friedrich Hayek]] and [[Milton Friedman]], Western states embraced policy prescriptions inspired by [[laissez-faire]] capitalism and [[classical liberalism]].

In particular, [[monetarism]], a theoretical alternative to Keynesianism that is more compatible with laissez-faire, gained increasing prominence in the capitalist world, especially under the leadership of [[Ronald Reagan]] in the US and [[Margaret Thatcher]] in the UK in the 1980s.  Public and political interest began shifting away from the so-called [[collectivist]] concerns of Keynes's managed capitalism to a focus on individual choice, called &quot;remarketized capitalism.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;Fulcher, James 2004&quot;&gt;Fulcher, James. Capitalism. 1st ed. New York: Oxford University Press, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the eyes of many economic and political commentators, the collapse of the [[Soviet Union]] brought further evidence of the superiority of market capitalism over communism.

===Globalization===
{{Main|Globalization}}
Although [[international trade]] has been associated with the development of capitalism for over five hundred years, some thinkers argue that a number of trends associated with [[globalization]] have acted to increase the mobility of people and capital since the last quarter of the 20th century, combining to circumscribe the room to maneuver of states in choosing non-capitalist models of development. Today, these trends have bolstered the argument that capitalism should now be viewed as a truly [[world government|world system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Burnham&quot; /&gt; However, other thinkers argue that globalization, even in its quantitative degree, is no greater now than during earlier periods of capitalist trade.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=After the New Economy |last=Henwood |first=Doug |publisher=New Press |date=1 October 2003 |isbn=1-56584-770-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Neoclassical economic theory==
{{Ref improve section|date=June 2010}}
Neoclassical economics explain capitalism as made up of individuals, enterprises, markets and government. According to their theories, individuals engage in a capitalist economy as [[consumer]]s, [[laborer|labourers]], and [[investor]]s. As labourers, individuals may decide which jobs to prepare for, and in which markets to look for work. As investors they decide how much of their income to save and how to invest their savings. These savings, which become investments, provide much of the money that businesses need to grow.

Business firms decide what to produce and where this production should occur. They also purchase inputs (materials, labour, and capital). Businesses try to influence consumer purchase decisions through marketing and advertisement, as well as the creation of new and improved products.
Driving the capitalist economy is the search for profits (revenues minus expenses). This is known as the [[profit motive]], and it helps ensure that companies produce the goods and services that consumers desire and are able to buy. To be profitable, firms must sell a quantity of their product at a certain price to yield a profit. A business may lose money if sales fall too low or if its costs become too high. The profit motive encourages firms to operate more efficiently. By using less materials, labour or capital, a firm can cut its production costs, which can lead to increased profits.

An economy grows when the total value of goods and services produced rises. This growth requires investment in infrastructure, capital and other resources necessary in production. In a capitalist system, businesses decide when and how much they want to invest.

Income in a capitalist economy depends primarily on what skills are in demand and what skills are being supplied. Skills that are in scarce supply are worth more in the market and can attract higher incomes. Competition among workers for jobs — and among employers for skilled workers — help determine wage rates. Firms need to pay high enough wages to attract the appropriate workers; when jobs are scarce, workers may accept lower wages than they would when jobs are plentiful. [[Trade union]] and governments influence wages in capitalist systems. Unions act to represent their members in negotiations with employers over such things as wage rates and acceptable working conditions.

===The market===
[[File:Supply-and-demand.svg|thumb|right|240px|The price (P) of a product is determined by a balance between production at each price (supply, S) and the desires of those with [[purchasing power]] at each price (demand, D). This results in a market equilibrium, with a given quantity (Q) sold of the product. A rise in demand would result in an increase in price and an increase in output.]]

Supply is the amount of a good or service produced by a firm and which is available for sale. Demand is the amount that people are willing to buy at a specific price. Prices tend to rise when demand exceeds supply, and fall when supply exceeds demand. In theory, the market is able to coordinate itself when a new equilibrium price and quantity is reached.

Competition arises when more than one producer is trying to sell the same or similar products to the same buyers. In capitalist theory, competition leads to innovation and more affordable prices. Without competition, a monopoly or [[cartel]] may develop. A monopoly occurs when a firm supplies the total output in the market; the firm can therefore limit output and raise prices because it has no fear of competition. A cartel is a group of firms that act together in a monopolistic manner to control output and raise prices.

===Role of government===
{{See|Competition regulator|Consumer protection|Competition law}}
In a capitalist system, the government does not prohibit private property or prevent individuals from working where they please. The government does not prevent firms from determining what wages they will pay and what prices they will charge for their products. Many countries, however, have minimum wage laws and minimum safety standards.

Under some versions of capitalism, the government carries out a number of economic functions, such as issuing money, supervising public utilities and enforcing private contracts. Many countries have [[competition law]]s that prohibit monopolies and cartels from forming. Despite anti-monopoly laws, large corporations can form near-monopolies in some industries. Such firms can temporarily drop prices and accept losses to prevent competition from entering the market, and then raise them again once the threat of entry is reduced. In many countries, public utilities (e.g. electricity, heating fuel, communications) are able to operate as a monopoly under government regulation, due to high economies of scale.

Government agencies regulate the standards of service in many industries, such as airlines and broadcasting, as well as financing a wide range of programs. In addition, the government regulates the flow of capital and uses financial tools such as the interest rate to control factors such as inflation and unemployment.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Capitalism.&quot; World Book Encyclopedia. 1988. 194. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Democracy, the state, and legal frameworks==
{{Main|History of capitalist theory}}

===Private property===
The relationship between the [[state (polity)|state]], its formal mechanisms, and capitalist societies has been debated in many fields of social and political theory, with active discussion since the 19th century. [[Hernando de Soto (economist)|Hernando de Soto]] is a contemporary economist who has argued that an important characteristic of capitalism is the functioning state protection of property rights in a formal property system where ownership and transactions are clearly recorded.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2001/03/desoto.htm |title=The mystery of capital|author=Hernando de Soto|accessdate=26 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to de Soto, this is the process by which physical assets are transformed into capital, which in turn may be used in many more ways and much more efficiently in the market economy. A number of Marxian economists have argued that the [[Enclosure Acts]] in England, and similar legislation elsewhere, were an integral part of capitalist [[primitive accumulation]] and that specific legal frameworks of private land ownership have been integral to the development of capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1867-c1/ch27.htm |title=Capital, v. 1. Part VIII: primitive accumulation|author=Karl Marx|accessdate=26 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=N. F. R. Crafts |title=Enclosure and labor supply revisited |journal=Explorations in economic history |issue=15 |month=April |year=1978 |pages=172–183 |doi=10.1016/0014-4983(78)90019-0 |volume=15}}.we the say yes&lt;/ref&gt;

===Institutions===
[[New institutional economics]], a field pioneered by [[Douglass North]], stresses the need of a legal framework in order for capitalism to function optimally, and focuses on the relationship between the historical development of capitalism and the creation and maintenance of political and economic institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=North, Douglass C.|title=Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; In new institutional economics and other fields focusing on public policy, economists seek to judge when and whether governmental intervention (such as [[tax]]es, [[Welfare (financial aid)|welfare]], and [[Regulatory economics|government regulation]]) can result in potential gains in efficiency. According to [[Gregory Mankiw]], a [[New Keynesian economics|New Keynesian economist]], governmental intervention can improve on market outcomes under conditions of &quot;[[market failure]]&quot;, or situations in which the market on its own does not allocate resources efficiently.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Principles of Economics|publisher=Harvard University|year=1997|pages=10|issue=Gregory|unused_data=Mankiw,}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Market failure occurs when an [[externality]] is present and a market will either under-produce a product with a positive externalization or overproduce a product that generates a negative externalization. Air pollution, for instance, is a negative externalization that cannot be incorporated into markets as the world’s air is not owned and then sold for use to polluters. So, too much pollution could be emitted and people not involved in the production pay the cost of the pollution instead of the firm that initially emitted the air pollution. Critics of market failure theory, like [[Ronald Coase]], [[Harold Demsetz]], and [[James M. Buchanan]] argue that government programs and policies also fall short of absolute perfection. Market failures are often small, and government failures are sometimes large. It is therefore the case that imperfect markets are often better than imperfect governmental alternatives. While all nations currently have some kind of market regulations, the desirable degree of regulation is disputed.

===Democracy===
The relationship between [[democracy]] and capitalism is a contentious area in theory and popular political movements. The extension of universal adult male [[suffrage]] in 19th century Britain occurred along with the development of industrial capitalism, and democracy became widespread at the same time as capitalism, leading many theorists to posit a causal relationship between them, or that each affects the other. However, in the 20th century, according to some authors, capitalism also accompanied a variety of political formations quite distinct from liberal democracies, including [[fascism|fascist]] regimes, absolute monarchies, and single-party states,.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burnham&quot; /&gt;

While some thinkers argue that capitalist development more-or-less inevitably eventually leads to the emergence of democracy, others dispute this claim. Research on the [[democratic peace theory]] indicates that capitalist democracies rarely make war with one another&lt;ref&gt;For the influence of capitalism on peace, see Mousseau, M. (2009) &quot;The Social Market Roots of Democratic Peace&quot;, ''International Security'' 33 (4)&lt;/ref&gt; and have little internal violence. However critics of the democratic peace theory note that democratic capitalist states may fight infrequently and or never with other democratic capitalist states because of political similarity or stability rather than because they are democratic or capitalist.

Some commentators argue that though economic growth under capitalism has led to democratization in the past, it may not do so in the future, as [[authoritarian]] regimes have been able to manage economic growth without making concessions to greater political freedom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Mesquita, Bruce Bueno de|url=http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20050901faessay84507/bruce-bueno-de-mesquita-george-w-downs/development-and-democracy.html|title=Development and Democracy|date=2005-09|accessdate=26 February 2008|publisher=Foreign Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Single, Joseph T.|url=http://www10.nytimes.com/cfr/international/20040901facomment_v83n4_siegle-weinstein-halperin.html?_r=5&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin|title=Why Democracies Excel|date=2004-09|accessdate=26 February 2008|publisher=[[New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
States that have highly capitalistic economic systems have thrived under authoritarian or oppressive political systems. Singapore, which maintains a highly open market economy and attracts lots of foreign investment, does not protect civil liberties such as freedom of speech and expression. The private (capitalist) sector in the People's Republic of China has grown exponentially and thrived since its inception, despite having an authoritarian government.  [[Augusto Pinochet]]'s rule in Chile led to economic growth by using authoritarian means to create a safe environment for investment and capitalism.

In response to criticism of the system, some proponents of capitalism have argued that its advantages are supported by empirical research. [[Indices of Economic Freedom]] show a correlation between nations with more economic freedom (as defined by the indices) and higher scores on variables such as income and life expectancy, including the poor, in these nations.

==Advocacy for capitalism==
===Economic growth===
[[File:Gdp chart.png|thumb|World's [[GDP]] per capita shows exponential growth since the beginning of the Industrial Revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective |author=Angus Maddison |publisher=[[OECD]] |location=Paris |year=2001 |isbn=92-64-18998-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Prc1952-2005gdp.gif|thumb|Capitalism and the economy of the [[People's Republic of China]]]]

Many theorists and policymakers in predominantly capitalist nations have emphasized capitalism's ability to promote economic growth, as measured by [[Gross Domestic Product]] (GDP), [[capacity utilization]] or [[standard of living]]. This argument was central, for example, to Adam Smith's advocacy of letting a free market control production and price, and allocate resources. Many theorists have noted that this increase in global GDP over time coincides with the emergence of the modern world capitalist system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.minneapolisfed.org/pubs/region/04-05/essay.cfm |title=The Industrial Revolution: Past and Future |author=Robert E. Lucas Jr. |work=Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis 2003 Annual Report |accessdate=26 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.j-bradford-delong.net/TCEH/1998_Draft/World_GDP/Estimating_World_GDP.html |title=Estimating World GDP, One Million B.C. – Present |author=J. Bradford DeLong |accessdate=26 February 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In years 1000–1820 world economy grew sixfold, 50 % per person. After capitalism had started to spread more widely, in years  1820–1998 world economy grew 50-fold, i.e., 9-fold per person.&lt;ref name=wolf44/&gt; In most capitalist economic regions such as Europe, the United States, Canada, Australia and New Zealand, the economy grew 19-fold per person even though these countries already had a higher starting level, and in Japan, which was poor in 1820, to 31-fold, whereas in the rest of the world the growth was only 5-fold per person.&lt;ref name=wolf44&gt;[[Martin Wolf]], ''[[Why Globalization works]]'', p. 43-45&lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents argue that increasing GDP (per capita) is empirically shown to bring about improved standards of living, such as better availability of food, housing, clothing, and health care.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/IndustrialRevolutionandtheStandardofLiving.html |title=Industrial Revolution and the Standard of Living |author=Clark Nardinelli |accessdate=26 February 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The decrease in the number of hours worked per week and the decreased participation of children and the elderly in the workforce have been attributed to capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Barro, Robert J.|title=Macroeconomics|publisher=MIT Press|year=1997|isbn=0262024365}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mises.org/article.aspx?Id=1481|title=Morality and Economic Law: Toward a Reconciliation|publisher=Ludwig von Mises Institute|accessdate=26 February 2008|author=Woods, Thomas E.|date=5 April 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Proponents also believe that a capitalist economy offers far more opportunities for individuals to raise their income through new professions or business ventures than do other economic forms. To their thinking, this potential is much greater than in either traditional [[feudal]] or [[tribal]] societies or in socialist societies.

===Political freedom===
Milton Friedman stated that the [[economic freedom]] of capitalism is a requisite of [[political freedom]]. Friedman stated that centralized operations of economic activity is always accompanied by [[political repression]]. In his view, transactions in a market economy are voluntary, and the wide diversity that voluntary activity permits is a fundamental threat to repressive political leaders and greatly diminish power to coerce. Friedman's view was also shared by [[Friedrich Hayek]] and John Maynard Keynes, both of whom believed that capitalism is vital for freedom to survive and thrive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Friedrich Hayek|title=The Road to Serfdom|publisher=University Of Chicago Press|year=1944|isbn=0-226-32061-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Bellamy, Richard|title=The Cambridge History of Twentieth-Century Political Thought|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2003|isbn=0-521-56354-2|pages=60}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Self-organization===
Austrian School economists have argued that capitalism can organize itself into a complex system without an external guidance or central planning mechanism. Friedrich Hayek considered the phenomenon of [[self-organization]] as underpinning capitalism. Prices serve as a signal as to the urgent and unfilled wants of people, and the promise of profits gives entrepreneurs [[incentive]] to use their knowledge and resources to satisfy those wants. Thus the activities of millions of people, each seeking his own interest, are coordinated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Walberg, Herbert|title=Education and Capitalism|publisher=Hoover Institution Press|year=2001|pages=87–89|isbn=0-8179-3972-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticisms of capitalism==
{{Main|Criticism of capitalism|Anti-capitalism|Capitalist mode of production}}
[[File:Anti-capitalism color.jpg|right|thumb|250px|An [[Industrial Workers of the World]] poster (1911)]]

Critics of capitalism associate it with: unfair [[distribution of wealth]] and power; a tendency toward market monopoly or [[oligopoly]] (and government by [[oligarchy]]); [[imperialism]], [[counter-revolutionary]] wars and various forms of economic and cultural [[exploitation]]; repression of workers and trade unionists; [[social alienation]]; [[economic inequality]]; [[unemployment]]; and economic instability.

Notable critics of capitalism have included: [[socialism|socialists]], [[anarchism|anarchists]], [[communism|communists]], [[Nazism|national socialists]], [[Social democracy|social democrats]], [[Technocracy|technocrats]], some types of [[conservatism|conservatives]], [[Luddite]]s, [[Narodnik]]s, [[Shakers]] and some types of [[nationalism|nationalists]].

[[Marxism|Marxists]] have advocated a revolutionary overthrow of capitalism that would lead to socialism, before eventually transforming into communism. Many socialists consider capitalism to be irrational, in that production and the direction of the economy are unplanned, creating many inconsistencies and internal contradictions.&lt;ref&gt;Brander, James A. Government policy toward business. 4th ed. Mississauga, Ontario: John Wiley &amp; Sons Canada, Ltd., 2006. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Labor history (discipline)|Labor historians]] and scholars such as [[Immanuel Wallerstein]] have argued that [[Unfree labour|unfree labor]] — by [[Slavery|slaves]], [[indentured servant]]s, prisoners, and other coerced persons — is compatible with capitalist relations.&lt;ref&gt;That unfree labour is acceptable to capital was argued during the 1980s by Tom Brass. See ''Towards a Comparative Political Economy of Unfree Labor'' (Cass, 1999). {{Cite web|url=http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/llt/52/linden.html |title=&quot;Labour History as the History of Multitudes&quot;, ''Labour/Le Travail'', 52, Fall 2003, p. 235-244 |author=Marcel van der Linden |accessdate=26 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many aspects of capitalism have come under attack from the [[anti-globalization movement]], which is primarily opposed to [[corporate capitalism]]. [[environmentalism|Environmentalists]] have argued that capitalism requires continual economic growth, and that it will inevitably deplete the finite natural resources of the Earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = McMurty |first = John |title = The Cancer Stage of Capitalism |publisher = [[PLUTO PRESS]] |year = 1999 |isbn = 0745313477}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many religions have criticized or opposed specific elements of capitalism. Traditional [[Judaism]], [[Christianity]], and Islam forbid [[Usury|lending money at interest]], although alternative methods of banking have been developed. Some Christians have criticized capitalism for its [[Economic materialism|materialist]] aspects&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P8C.HTM#-2FX|title=III. The Social Doctrine of the Church|publisher=The Vatican|accessdate=26 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its inability to account for the wellbeing of all people.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Gubleton, archbishop of Detroit speaking in &quot;Capitalism: A love story&quot;{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;priest Peter Dougherty, speaking in &quot;Capitalism: A love story&quot;{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Multicol}}
'''People'''
* [[Andrew Carnegie]]
* [[Ayn Rand]]
* [[Eugen von Böhm-Bawerk]]
* [[Frederic Batista]]
* [[Ravi Batra]]
* [[Friedrich Engels]]
* [[Friedrich Hayek]]
* [[John D. Rockefeller]]
* [[John Maynard Keynes]]
* [[John Locke]]
* [[John Stuart Mill]]
* [[P.R. Sarkar]]
* [[Joseph Schumpeter]]
* [[Joseph Stiglitz]]
* [[J. P. Morgan]]
* [[Karl Marx]]
* [[Ludwig Von Mises]]
* [[Milton Friedman]]
* [[Murray Rothbard]]
* [[Thorstein Veblen]]

{{Multicol-break}}
'''Concepts'''
* [[Accumulation of capital]]
* [[Business]]
* [[Capital (economics)]]
* [[Chicago school]]
* [[Classical Economics]]
* [[Consumption (economics)]]
* [[Economics]]
* [[Economic calculation problem|Calculation Problem]]
* [[Economic equilibrium]]
* [[Economic liberalism]]
* [[Economic interventionism]]
* [[Entrepreneurship]]
* [[Factors of production]]
* [[Family in advertising]]
* [[Financial market]]
* [[Free price system]]
* [[Gains from trade]]
* [[History of Economic Thought]]
* [[Industrial Revolution]]
* [[Invisible hand]]
* [[Institutional economics]]
{{Multicol-break}}

* [[Keynesianism]]
* [[Laissez-faire]]
* [[Macroeconomics]]
* [[Marginalism]]
* [[Market]]
* [[Market Economy]]
* [[Mass production]]
* [[Means of production]]
* [[Microeconomics]]
* [[Monetarism]]
* [[Neoclassical economics]]
* [[Perspectives on Capitalism]]
* [[Private property]]
* [[Privatization]]
* [[Positive non-interventionism]]
* [[Profit (economics)]]
* [[Social market economy]]
* [[Spontaneous order]]
* [[State capitalism]]
* [[Supply and demand]]
* [[Supply-side economics]]
* [[Trickle down economics]]
* [http://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/truecosteconomics.asp True-cost economics]
{{Multicol-break}}
{{Portal box|Capitalism|Economics}}

'''Works'''
* ''[[Capitalism and Freedom]]''
* ''[[Capitalism, Socialism and Democracy]]''
* ''[[Das Kapital]]''
* ''[[Free to Choose]]''
* ''[[Grundrisse]]''
* ''[[Individualism and Economic Order]]
* ''[[Man, Economy, and State]]''
* ''[[The Accumulation of Capital]]''
* ''[[The Anti-Capitalistic Mentality]]''
* ''[[The Communist Manifesto]]''
* ''[[The Law (1850 book)|The Law]]''
* ''[[The Road to Serfdom]]''
* ''[[The Theory of Business Enterprise]]''
* ''[[The Wealth of Nations]]''
{{Multicol-end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* [[Christian Bacher|Bacher, Christian]] (2007) ''[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=w_6PqBp64y0C Capitalism, Ethics and the Paradoxon of Self-exploitation]'' Grin Verlag. p.&amp;nbsp;2
* [[Richard T. De George|De George, Richard T.]] (1986) ''Business ethics'' p.&amp;nbsp;104
* [[Scott Lash|Lash, Scott]] and [[John Urry (sociologist)|Urry, John]] (2000). ''Capitalism''. In [[Nicholas Abercrombie]], S. Hill &amp; BS Turner (Eds.), ''The Penguin dictionary of sociology'' (4th ed.) (pp.&amp;nbsp;36–40).
* {{Cite book|title=Profit Theory and Capitalism|author=Obrinsky, Mark|authorlink=Mark Obrinsky|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|url=http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=4995059|year=1983|pages=1}}
* [[Eric Wolf|Wolf, Eric]] (1982) ''[[Europe and the People Without History]]''
* [[Ellen Meiksins Wood|Wood, Ellen Meiksins]] (2002) ''[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=FZPyKjVguVoC The Origins of Capitalism: A Longer View]'' London: Verso
* [[Thomas K. McCraw]], [http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/The-current-crisis-and-the-essence-of-capitalism.php ''&quot;The Current Crisis and the Essence of Capitalism&quot;''], The Montreal Review (August, 2011)

==Further reading==
* Abu-Lughod, Janet L. ''Before European Hegemony The World System A.D. 1250–1350''. New York: Oxford UP, USA, 1991.
*{{Cite book|last=Ackerman |first=Frank |authorlink= |coauthors=Lisa Heinzerling |title=Priceless: On Knowing the Price of Everything and the Value of Nothing |publisher=New Press |date=24 August 2005 |location= |pages=277 |url= |doi= |id= |isbn=1565849817}}
* {{Cite book|title=Politics Without Romance|author=Buchanan, James M.}}
* {{Cite book|title=Civilization and Capitalism: 15th – 18 Century|author=[[Fernand Braudel|Braudel, Fernand]]}}
* {{Cite book|title=Theories of Modern Capitalism|author=Bottomore, Tom|year=1985}}
* {{Cite journal|author=H. Doucouliagos and M. Ulubasoglu |title=Democracy and Economic Growth: A meta-analysis |journal=School of Accounting, Economics and Finance Deakin University Australia |year=2006 }}
* {{Cite book|author=Coase, Ronald|year=1974|title=The Lighthouse in Economics}}
* {{Cite book|author=Demsetz, Harold|year=1969|title=Information and Efficiency}}
* {{Cite book|author=Fulcher, James|title=Capitalism|year=2004}}
* {{Cite book|author=Friedman, Milton|title=Capitalism and Freedom|year=1952}}
* {{Cite book|author=[[John Kenneth Galbraith|Galbraith, J.K.]]|title=American Capitalism|year=1952}}
* {{Cite book|author=Böhm-Bawerk, Eugen von|title=Capital and Interest: A Critical History of Economical Theory|location=London|publisher=Macmillan and Co.|year=1890}}
* {{Cite book|author=Harvey, David|title=The Political-Economic Transformation of Late Twentieth Century Capitalism.|location=Cambridge, MA|publisher=Blackwell Publishers|year=1990|isbn=0-631-16294-1}}
* {{Cite book|author=Hayek, Friedrich A.|title=The Pure Theory of Capital|location=Chicago|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1975|isbn=0-226-32081-2}}
* {{Cite book|author=Hayek, Friedrich A.|title=Capitalism and the Historians|location=Chicago|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1963}}
* {{Cite book|author=Heilbroner, Robert L.|title=The Limits of American Capitalism|year=1966}}
* {{Cite book|author=Heilbroner, Robert L.|title=The Nature and Logic of Capitalism|year=1985}}
* {{Cite book|author=Heilbroner, Robert L.|title=Economics Explained|year=1987}}
* {{Cite book|author=Cryan, Dan|title=Capitalism: A Graphic Guide|year=2009}}
* [[Matthew Josephson|Josephson, Matthew]], ''The Money Lords; the great finance capitalists, 1925–1950'', New York, Weybright and Talley, 1972.
* {{Cite book|author=[[Rosa Luxemburg|Luxemburg, Rosa]]|title=The Accumulation of Capital|year=1913}}
* {{Cite book|author=Marx, Karl|title=Capital: A Critical Analysis of Capitalist Production|year=1886}}
* {{Cite book|author=Mises, Ludwig von|title=Human Action: A Treatise on Economics|publisher=Scholars Edition|year=1998}}
* {{Cite book|author=Rand, Ayn|title=[[Capitalism: The Unknown Ideal]]|publisher=Signet|year=1986}}
* {{Cite book|author=Reisman, George|year=1996|title=Capitalism: A Treatise on Economics|location=Ottawa, Illinois|publisher=Jameson Books|isbn=0-915463-73-3}}
* {{Cite book|author=Resnick, Stephen|year=1987|title=Knowledge &amp; Class: a Marxian critique of political economy|location=Chicago|publisher=University of Chicago Press}}
* {{Cite book|author=Rostow, W. W.|title=The Stages of Economic Growth: A Non-Communist Manifesto|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1960}}
* {{Cite book|author=[[Joseph Schumpeter|Schumpeter, J. A.]]|title=Capitalism, Socialism, and Democracy|year=1983}}
* {{Cite book| last = Scott | first = Bruce | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = The Concept of Capitalism | publisher = Springer | year = 2009 | location = | pages = 76 | url =  | doi = | id = | isbn = 3642031099 | oclc =  }}
*[[Historical GDP of the People's Republic of China|China GDP]] – Dr. [[Fengbo Zhang]] introduced the Western economics, GDP and SNA system to China, replaced Soviet Union's MPS system.
* {{Cite book|author=Scott, John|title=Corporate Business and Capitalist Classes|year=1997}}
* {{Cite book|author=Seldon, Arthur|year=2007|title=Capitalism: A Condensed Version|location=London|publisher=Institute of Economic Affairs}}
* {{Cite book|author=Sennett, Richard|title=The Culture of the New Capitalism|year=2006}}
* {{Cite book|author=Smith, Adam|title=An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations|year=1776}}
* {{Cite book|author=De Soto, Hernando|year=2000|title=The Mystery of Capital: Why Capitalism Triumphs in the West and Fails Everywhere Else|location=New York|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=0-465-01614-6}}
* {{Cite book|author=Strange, Susan|title=Casino Capitalism|year=1986}}
* {{Cite book|author=Wallerstein, Immanuel|title=The Modern World System}}
* {{Cite book|author=[[Weber, Max]]|title=[http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/The-protestant-ethic-and-the-spirit-of-capitalism.php The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism]|year=1926}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Capitalism}}
{{EB1922 Poster}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary}}

* {{In Our Time|Capitalism|p00545kv|Capitalism}}
* [http://capitalism.columbia.edu/ Center on Capitalism and Society] at [[Columbia University]]

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[nan:Chu-pún-chú-gī]]

[[Category:Capitalism| ]]
[[Category:Capitalist systems| ]]
[[Category:Economic systems]]
[[Category:Economic ideologies]]
[[Category:Economies]]
[[Category:Economic liberalism]]
[[Category:Ideologies]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Individualism]]

{{Link GA|zh}}
[[af:Kapitalisme]]
[[ar:رأسمالية]]
[[an:Capitalismo]]
[[arc:ܪܫܡܠܘܬܐ]]
[[ast:Capitalismu]]
[[az:Kapitalizm]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chu-pún-chú-gī]]
[[be:Капіталізм]]
[[be-x-old:Капіталізм]]
[[bs:Kapitalizam]]
[[bg:Капитализъм]]
[[ca:Capitalisme]]
[[cs:Kapitalismus]]
[[cy:Cyfalafiaeth]]
[[da:Kapitalisme]]
[[de:Kapitalismus]]
[[et:Kapitalism]]
[[el:Καπιταλισμός]]
[[es:Capitalismo]]
[[eo:Kapitalismo]]
[[eu:Kapitalismo]]
[[fa:سرمایه‌داری]]
[[hif:Punjiwaad]]
[[fo:Kapitalisma]]
[[fr:Capitalisme]]
[[fy:Kapitalisme]]
[[ga:Caipitleachas]]
[[gl:Capitalismo]]
[[gan:資本主義]]
[[gu:મૂડીવાદ]]
[[hak:Chṳ̂-pún chú-ngi]]
[[ko:자본주의]]
[[hi:पूंजीवाद]]
[[hr:Kapitalizam]]
[[io:Kapitalismo]]
[[id:Kapitalisme]]
[[is:Kapítalismi]]
[[it:Capitalismo]]
[[he:קפיטליזם]]
[[jv:Kapitalisme]]
[[kn:ಬಂಡವಾಳಶಾಹಿ]]
[[ka:კაპიტალიზმი]]
[[kk:Капитализм]]
[[ku:Kapîtalîzm]]
[[krc:Капитализм]]
[[la:Capitalismus]]
[[lv:Kapitālisms]]
[[lt:Kapitalizmas]]
[[ln:Kapitalismɛ]]
[[hu:Kapitalizmus]]
[[mk:Капитализам]]
[[ml:മുതലാളിത്തം]]
[[mr:भांडवलशाही]]
[[arz:راسماليه]]
[[ms:Kapitalisme]]
[[mwl:Capitalismo]]
[[mn:Капитализм]]
[[my:အရင်းရှင်ဝါဒ]]
[[nl:Kapitalisme]]
[[ja:資本主義]]
[[no:Kapitalisme]]
[[nn:Kapitalisme]]
[[oc:Capitalisme]]
[[uz:Kapitalizm]]
[[pnb:کیپیٹلزم]]
[[pl:Kapitalizm]]
[[pt:Capitalismo]]
[[ro:Capitalism]]
[[qu:Kapitalismu]]
[[rue:Капіталізм]]
[[ru:Капитализм]]
[[sah:Капитализм]]
[[scn:Capitalismu]]
[[si:ධනවාදය]]
[[simple:Capitalism]]
[[sk:Kapitalizmus]]
[[sl:Kapitalizem]]
[[sr:Капитализам]]
[[sh:Kapitalizam]]
[[fi:Kapitalismi]]
[[sv:Kapitalism]]
[[ta:முதலாளித்துவம்]]
[[te:పెట్టుబడిదారీ విధానం]]
[[th:ทุนนิยม]]
[[tr:Kapitalizm]]
[[uk:Капіталізм]]
[[ur:سرمایہ داری نظام]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa tư bản]]
[[fiu-vro:Kapitalism]]
[[war:Kapitalismo]]
[[yi:קאפיטאליזם]]
[[zh-yue:資本主義]]
[[diq:Qapitalizm]]
[[bat-smg:Kapėtalėzmos]]
[[zh:资本主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
