<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="542952" ns="0" title="The Secret of the Unicorn"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the film adaptation|The Adventures of Tintin (film)}}
{{Graphicnovelbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
englishtitle=The Secret of the Unicorn
|foreigntitle=Le Secret de la Licorne
|image=Tintin cover - The Secret of the Unicorn.jpg
|caption=Cover of the English edition
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=1943
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=''[[Le Soir]]''
|origdate=June 11, 1942 - January 14, 1943
|origisbn=2-203-00110-0
|transtitle=The Secret of the Unicorn
|transpublisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]]
|transdate=1959
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''
|transisbn=1-4052-0622-5
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[The Shooting Star]]'', 1942
|nextissue=''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]'', 1944
}}

'''''The Secret of the Unicorn''''' (in the original French, '''''Le Secret de la Licorne''''') is the eleventh title in the comic book series ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', written and illustrated by Belgian cartoonist [[Hergé]]. Designed to be the first volume in a two-part story, the plot of ''The Secret of the Unicorn'' was continued in the twelfth Tintin adventure, ''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]''. The comic was serialised from 11 June 1942 through to 14 January 1943 in the Belgian newspaper ''[[Le Soir]]'', before being published in book form later that year. Written in the midst of the [[Second World War]], at a time when Belgium was occupied by [[Nazi Germany]], ''The Secret of the Unicorn'' is the first book in the ''Adventures of Tintin'' to avoid political themes, instead focusing purely on an adventure story, and for this reason has been described as being the first book in Hergé's middle period. It is also known for being one of only two books in the series set entirely in Belgium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 113&quot;&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt;

The comic's plot revolves around young reporter [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]], his dog [[Snowy]], and his friend [[Captain Haddock]], who discover a riddle left by Haddock's ancestor, the 17th century Sir Francis Haddock, which could lead them to the hidden treasure of the pirate Red Rackham. In order to unravel the riddle, Tintin and Haddock must obtain three identical models of Sir Francis' ship, the ''[[Unicorn (ship)|Unicorn]]'', but discover that criminals are also after these model ships, and are willing to kill in order to obtain them.

Hergé heavily researched the background to his story, ensuring that the various ships, buildings, and other features illustrated in it were based upon real life counterparts. ''The Secret of the Unicorn'' would remain Hergé's favourite of his Tintin adventures until he wrote ''[[Tintin in Tibet]]'' (1960), which would replace it in his affections.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 113&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peeters 1989. p. 75&quot;&gt;[[#Pee89|Peeters 1989]]. p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; The comic has been adapted into various other media, including for a radio series (1992), two animated television series, Belvision's ''[[Hergé's Adventures of Tintin]]'' (c.1960) and Nelvana's ''[[The Adventures of Tintin (TV series)|The Adventures of Tintin]]'' (1991), and the performance-capture 3D film produced by [[Peter Jackson]] and directed by [[Steven Spielberg]], ''[[The Adventures of Tintin (film)|The Adventures of Tintin]]'' (2011).

==Synopsis==
[[File:Haddock with sword (100x68).jpg|thumb|left|200px|Captain Haddock reenacting the adventures of his ancestor, Sir Francis Haddock]]

Whilst browsing in a market in Brussels, Tintin purchases an old [[model ship]] which he wishes to give to his friend [[Captain Haddock]] as a gift. Two strangers, the model ship collector [[Ivan Ivanovitch Sakharine]] and a mysterious figure known as Barnaby, then unsuccessfully try to independently convince Tintin to sell the model to them. Returning with the model to his flat, Snowy knocks it over and its [[mainmast]] is broken. Repairing it, and showing the ship to Haddock, the latter is amazed that it is actually a model of the ''[[Unicorn (ship)|Unicorn]]'', a 17th-century warship captained by his ancestor, [[Sir Francis Haddock]]. The model ship is subsequently stolen, and it is revealed that Sakharine owns an identical model of the ''Unicorn'', although this is also soon stolen. Returning to his flat, Tintin discovers a rolled-up parchment hidden under furniture, on which is a part of a riddle that points to the location of treasure, and he realises that this must have been hidden in the mast of the model which Snowy had broken.

Informing Haddock about the riddle, the captain tells him of how Sir Francis Haddock battled with the pirate Red Rackham somewhere in the [[West Indies]], before killing him in single combat and blowing up his ship. Haddock gets somewhat carried away in his telling of the story: destroying his flat while re-enacting the battle scenes.

Barnaby then turns up at Tintin's doorstep but is shot down by unknown assailants. Later Tintin is kidnapped by the perpetrators of the shooting. They are revealed to be [[the Bird brothers]], two unscrupulous antique dealers who own a third model of the ''Unicorn''. They are behind the theft of Tintin's model and Sakharine's parchment, knowing that only with all three parchments can the location of the treasure be found.

Tintin escapes from the Bird brothers' country estate, [[Marlinspike Hall]], whilst the Captain arrives with the police officers [[Thompson and Thomson]] to arrest them. However, it is found that they do not have two of the parchments. These are found to have been stolen by [[Aristides Silk]], a [[kleptomania]]c specialising in wallet-snatching. As the pickpocket is cornered, his cache of stolen wallets is found, amongst which are the Bird Brothers' wallets containing the missing two parchments. By combining the three parchments, Tintin and Haddock discover the coordinates of the hidden treasure, and begin to plan for an expedition to find it.

==History==
===Background===

The Belgian comic book creator Georges Remi – who would become better known under his pen name of Hergé – first came up with the character of Tintin, a young boy reporter, whilst working at the right wing Belgian newspaper ''[[Le XXe Siècle]]'' (''The 20th Century''). Pioneering this new character in the story ''[[Tintin in the Land of the Soviets]]'', this comic, which involved Tintin battling the socialist authorities in the [[Soviet Union]], was serialised in ''Le XXe Siècle'''s supplement for children, ''[[Le Petit Vingtième]]'' (''The Little Twentieth''), from 10 January 1929 until 11 May 1930.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof92|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. pp. 22&amp;ndash;23.&lt;/ref&gt; Proving a success, Hergé went on to pen a string of new ''Adventures of Tintin'', sending his character to real locations such as the Belgian Congo, the United States, Egypt, India, China and the United Kingdom, and also to fictional countries of his own devising, such as the Latin American republic of [[San Theodoros]] and the East European kingdom of [[Syldavia]].

As he produced these works, his political approach to the world began to change; the earliest books reflected the [[Social conservatism|socially conservative]], [[fascism|fascist]] and [[imperialism|imperialistic]] attitudes of those for whom he worked.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; Later he became critical of the militaristic expansionist foreign policy of Germany and Italy, with the eighth Tintin adventure, ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'' (1939), involving Tintin battling the forces of fictional state [[Borduria]], whose leader, named Müsstler, was a combination of Nazi German leader [[Adolf Hitler]] and Italian Fascist leader [[Benito Mussolini]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; He continued this anti-German sentiment in his subsequent work, ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'', in which the main antagonist, Dr Müller, is a German intent on sabotaging the oil supply in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 91-92&quot;&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 90-91.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[World War II]] broke out across Europe in 1939, and Germany invaded Belgium in 1940. Although Hergé initially considered fleeing into a self-imposed exile, he ultimately decided to stay in his occupied homeland.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 91-92.&lt;/ref&gt; Although it had reflected political sympathies with the Nazi regime, the occupying forces closed down ''Le XXe Siècle'' in order to secure their own dominance over the Belgian media, leaving Hergé unemployed and his story ''Land of Black Gold'' unfinished.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 91-92&quot;/&gt; In search of employment, he was given a job as an illustrator by [[Raymond de Becker]], an executive of the popular newspaper ''[[Le Soir]]'' (''The Evening''), which was allowed to continue publication under German management.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 92-93.&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 October 1940 he was made editor of the paper's children's supplement, ''Le Soir Jeunesse'', in which he set about producing new Tintin adventures, ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]'' (1941) and then ''[[The Shooting Star]]'' (1942).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 98-99.&lt;/ref&gt; In this new, more repressive political climate, Hergé could no longer explore political themes in his ''Adventures of Tintin''. As Tintinologist [[Harry Thompson]] noted, Tintin's role as a reporter came to an end, to be replaced by his new role as an explorer, something which was not a politically sensitive topic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 112&quot;&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; 

With the culmination of ''The Shooting Star'', Hergé began work on a new Tintin adventure, which would appear as ''The Secret of the Unicorn''. Revolving around the &quot;ultra-romantic theme&quot; of the treasure hunt, Tintinologist [[Benoit Peeters]] would later describe it as &quot;an act of sheer escapism from the rigours of occupation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Pee89|Peeters 1989]]. p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt; His decision to write a story that would span the length of two books was something which he had tried before, with the ''Tintin in the East'' story arch that was found in both ''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'' (1934) and ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'' (1936). He considered it to be sufficiently successful that he repeated it over the next four books, ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'' (1948), ''[[Prisoners of the Sun]]'' (1949), ''[[Destination Moon]]'' (1953) and ''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'' (1954).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Far01|Farr 2001]]. p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Influences===
[[File:Sir Francis Haddock.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Sir Francis Haddock fighting Red Rackham's pirates.]]

To produce the varied backgrounds and other illustrations for ''The Secret of the Unicorn'', Hergé drew on a much wider variety of pictorial sources, such as newspaper clippings, than he had done for any of the earlier Tintin adventures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 112&quot;&gt;[[#Far01|Farr 2001]]. p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; He went to particular effort in order to depict the ''Unicorn'' as a historically accurate 17th century warship, studying the plans of naval vessels from that period which were found in the Naval Museum in Paris. As his primary influence for the fictional craft, he chose a ship named ''Le Brillant'' which had been constructed in [[Le Havre]] in 1690 by the shipwright [[Salicon]] and then decorated by [[Jean Bérain the Elder]]. He also however studied other vessels from the period, such as the ''Le Soleil Royal'', ''La Couronne'', ''La Royale'' and ''Le Reale de France'', in order to better understand 17th century ship design. It was from the latter vessel that he gained a basis for his design for the ''Unicorn'''s jollyboat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 111&quot;&gt;[[#Far01|Farr 2001]]. p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peeters 1989. p. 75&quot;/&gt; No ship named the ''Unicorn'' had ever been listed in the annals of the [[French navy]], so Hergé instead took the name, and also figurehead, for Sir Francis Haddock's fictional vessel from a British frigate which had been active in the mid-18th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 111&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peeters 1989. p. 75&quot;/&gt; 

====Red Rackham and Sir Francis Haddock====

There was a historic pirate with a similar name to Red Rackham, [[Calico Jack|John Rackham]], best known as the captain of the ship on which sailed the women pirates [[Anne Bonny]] and [[Mary Read]]. John Rackham was also known for his bright clothes.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

[[File:Sir Richard Haddock.jpg|thumb|left|150px|A 17th century engraving of Sir Richard Haddock.]]

Tintinologist [[Michael Farr]] believed that the introduction of Sir Francis Haddock (François de Haddoque in the original French) was what made the book &quot;most remarkable&quot; due to the fact that both visually and in his mannerisms, he is &quot;scarcely distinguishable from the captain&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 108&quot;&gt;[[#Far01|Farr 2001]]. p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; By introducing the character, Hergé made Captain Haddock the only character in the series (with the exception of [[Jolyon Wagg]], who would be introduced later) to have a family and an ancestry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 115&quot;&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peeters 1989. p. 75&quot;/&gt;

After publishing the book, Hergé learned that there had actually been an Admiral Haddock who had served in the [[British navy]] during the late 17th and early 18th centuries: [[Sir Richard Haddock]] (1629–1715). This Haddock was in charge of the ''Royal James'', the flagship of the [[Earl of Sandwich]] during the [[Battle of Solebay]] of 1672, the first naval battle of the [[Third Anglo-Dutch War]]. During the fighting, the ''Royal James'' was set alight, and Haddock escaped with his life but had to be rescued from the sea, following which his bravery was recognised by the British monarch, [[Charles II of England|King Charles II]]. He subsequently took command of another ship, the ''Royal Charles'', before becoming a naval administrator in later life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 111&quot;/&gt;

Historians have also highlighted the existence of another Captain Haddock who lived in this period, one who had commanded a [[fire-ship]], the ''Anne and Christopher''. It was recorded by David Ogg that this captain and his ship had got separated from their squadron whilst out at sea and so docked at [[Malaga]] to purchase goods that could be taken back to Britain and sold for a profit. For this action, Haddock was brought before an admiralty tribunal in 1674, where he was ordered to forfeit all profits from the transaction and suspended from his command for six months.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 111&quot;/&gt;

====Marlinspike Hall====

The name ''Moulinsart'' was an anagram of the real village of [[Sarmoulin]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof02|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Publication===
''Le Secret De La Licorne'' was initially serialised on a daily basis in the Belgian newspaper ''Le Soir'' from 11 June 1942, whilst the French newspaper ''Coeurs Vaillants'' began to subsequently serialise it from 19 March 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lofficier 2002. p. 52&quot;/&gt; In Belgium, it was then published in a 62 page book format by [[Casterman|Editions Casterman]] in 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lofficier 2002. p. 52&quot;&gt;[[#Lof02|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1952, [[Casterman]] published English language translations of both ''The Secret of the Unicorn'' and ''Red Rackham's Treasure'', in which Moulinsart (later Marlinspike Hall) was referred to as Puckeridge Castle.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Far01|Farr 2001]]. p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt;

The series' Danish publishers, [[Carlsen]], later located a model of an early 17th-century Danish ship called the ''Enhjørnigen'' (''The Unicorn'') which they gifted to Hergé. Constructed in 1605, ''Enhjørnigen'' had been wrecked in an attempt to navigate the [[Northwest Passage]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Farr 2001. p. 111&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 115&quot;/&gt;

==Analysis==
''The Secret of the Unicorn'' resembled the earlier ''Tintin'' adventures in its use of style, colour and content, leading Harry Thompson to remark that it &quot;unquestionably&quot; belongs to the 1930s, believing it to be &quot;the last and best of Hergé's detective mysteries.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 113&quot;/&gt; 

In his analysis of the ''Adventures of Tintin'', the academic Jean-Marie Apostolidès characterised the ''Secret of the Unicorn''-''Red Rackham's Treasure'' arc as being about the characters going on a &quot;treasure hunt that turns out to be at the same time a search for their roots.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Apo10|Apostolidès 2010]]. p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adaptations==
===Belvision animation, 1957===
In 1957, the animation company [[Belvision]] produced a string of colour adaptations based upon Hergé's original comics, adapting eight of the ''Adventures'' into a series of daily five-minute episodes. ''The Secret of the Unicorn'' was the seventh such story to be adapted, being directed by Ray Goossens and written by [[Michel Greg]], himself a well known comic book writer and illustrator who in later years would become editor-in-chief of the ''Journal De Tintin''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof02|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. pp. 87-88.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ellipse/Nelvana animation, 1991===
In 1991, a second animated series based upon ''The Adventures of Tintin'' was produced, this time as a collaboration between the French studio [[Ellipse]] and the Canadian animation company [[Nelvana]]. Adapting 21 of the stories into a series of episodes, each 42 minutes long, ''The Secret of the Unicorn'' was the ninth story to be produced into the series, with the story spanning two episodes. Directed by Stéphane Bernasconi, the series has been praised for being &quot;generally faithful&quot;, with compositions having been actually directly taken from the panels in the original comic book.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof02|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motion capture film and video game, 2011===
A [[motion capture]] [[film]] titled ''[[The Adventures of Tintin (film)|The Adventures of Tintin: Secret of the Unicorn]]'' directed by [[Steven Spielberg]] and produced by [[Peter Jackson]] was released in most of the world October - November 2011, and is slated for a US release on December 21, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite|url=http://www.timeout.com/film/reviews/89602/the-adventures-of-tintin-the-secret-of-the-unicorn.html|title=The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn Movie Review|publisher=Time Out Magazine|author=Tom Huddleston|date=27 October 2011|accessdate=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn (video game)|video game tie-in to the movie]] has also been made.

== References ==
;Footnotes
{{reflist||colwidth=30em}}

;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |title= The Metamorphoses of Tintin, or Tintin for Adults |last= {{aut|Apostolidès, Jean-Marie}} |year= 2010 |publisher= Stanford University Press |location= Stanford |isbn= 978-0804760317 |ref=Apo10}}
* {{cite book |title= Hergé, the Man Who Created Tintin |last= {{aut|Assouline, Pierre}} |year= 2009 |publisher= Oxford University Press |location= Oxford and New York |isbn= 978-0195397598 |ref=Ass09}}
* {{cite book |title= Tintin: The Complete Companion |last= {{aut|[[Michael Farr|Farr, Michael]]}} |year= 2001 |publisher= John Murray |location= London |isbn= 978-019555220 |ref=Far01}}
* {{cite book |title= The Art of Hergé, Inventor of Tintin: Volume II, 1937-1949 |last= {{aut|[[Philippe Goddin|Goddin, Philippe]]}} |year= 2009 |publisher= Last Gasp |location= San Francisco |isbn= 978-086719-724-2 |ref=God09}}
* {{cite book |title= The Pocket Essential Tintin |last= {{aut|Lofficier, Jean-Marc and Lofficier, Randy}} |year= 2002 |publisher= Pocket Essentials |location= Harpenden, Hertfordshire |isbn= 978-1904048176 |ref=Lof92}}
* {{cite book |title= Tintin and the Secret of Literature |last= {{aut|[[Tom McCarthy (writer)|McCarthy, Tom]]}} |year= 2006 |publisher= Granta |location=London |isbn= 978-1862078314 |ref=McC06}}
* {{cite book |title= Tintin and the World of Hergé |last= {{aut|[[Benoît Peeters|Peeters, Benoît]]}} |year= 1989 |publisher= Methuen Children's Books |location= London |isbn= 978-0416148824 |ref=Pee89}}
* {{cite book |title= Tintin: Hergé and his Creation |last= {{aut|[[Harry Thompson|Thompson, Harry]]}} |year= 1991 |publisher= Hodder and Stoughton |location= London |isbn= 978-0340523933 |ref=Tho91}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/11secret.html The Secret of the Unicorn] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Secret of the Unicorn, The}}
[[Category:1943 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books]]
[[Category:Pirate books]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Le Soir]]
[[Category:Literature first published in serial form]]

[[ca:El secret de l'Unicorn]]
[[cs:Tajemství Jednorožce]]
[[de:Das Geheimnis der „Einhorn“]]
[[es:El secreto del Unicornio]]
[[eu:Adarbakarraren sekretua]]
[[fa:راز اسب شاخدار]]
[[fr:Le Secret de La Licorne]]
[[gl:O segredo do alicorno]]
[[id:Rahasia Unicorn]]
[[he:תעלומת ה&quot;חד-קרן&quot;]]
[[nl:Het geheim van de Eenhoorn]]
[[ja:なぞのユニコーン号]]
[[pl:Tajemnica jednorożca]]
[[pt:Le secret de la Licorne]]
[[ru:Тайна «Единорога»]]
[[fi:Yksisarvisen salaisuus]]
[[sv:Enhörningens hemlighet]]
[[tr:Tekboynuzun Esrarı]]
[[zh:獨角獸號的秘密]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
