<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="543894" ns="0" title="Texas Southern University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
 |name              = Texas Southern University
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Texas Southern University seal.png
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = 
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = March 7, 1927
 |closed            
 |type              = [[Public university|Public]]&lt;br&gt;[[Historically black colleges and universities|Historically black]]
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = 
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = John Rudley
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = Sunny E. Ohia
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 
 |staff             = 350
 |students          = 10,026
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Houston]]
 |state             = [[Texas]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = &lt;br&gt;[[United States]]
 |coor              = {{Coord|29.722179|N|95.360534|W|source:dewiki_region:US-TX_type:landmark|format=dms|display=inline, title}}

 |campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]], {{convert|150|acre|km2|sing=on}} 
 |former_names      = Texas State University for Negroes (1927-?)&lt;br&gt;Houston College for Negroes (?-1947)
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = [[Maroon (color)|Maroon]] and [[Gray (color)|Gray]]&lt;br&gt;{{color box|maroon}} {{color box|gray}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = Tigers or Lady Tigers
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Championship Subdivision|Division I Football Championship Subdivision]]
 |affiliations      = [[Southwestern Athletic Conference]]
 |website           = [http://www.tsu.edu/ www.tsu.edu]
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = 
}}'''Texas Southern University''' (shortened to '''Texas Southern''', or simply '''TSU''') is a [[Historically black colleges and universities|historically black university]] located in [[Houston]], [[Texas]], [[United States]]. 

TSU was established in 1927 as the Houston Colored Junior College, through its private college phase as Houston Colored College. On March 3, 1947, the state declared this to be the first state university in Houston, Texas State University for Negroes. In 1951, the name changed to Texas Southern University.

Texas Southern is one of only four independent public universities in Texas (those not affiliated with any of Texas' six public university systems) and is one of the largest and most comprehensive HBCUs in the nation.

{{As of|2009|10|df=US}}, about 85% of TSU's students were [[African American]]. Fifty-four percent of law school students and 43% of pharmacy students were African American. During that year, the university's president, John Rudley, said that he would try to court [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic]]s as students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kever|first=Jeanne|url=http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/hotstories/6646207.html|title=TTradition changing at black colleges|work=[[Houston Chronicle]]|date=2009-10-01|accessdate=2009-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The beginnings of Texas Southern University can be traced to the March 7, 1927 resolution by the [[Houston Independent School District]] school board to establish junior colleges for each race.  The resolution created Houston Junior College (now the [[University of Houston]]) and Houston Colored Junior College. The Houston Colored Junior College first held classes in [[Yates High School]] during the evenings.  It later changed its name to Houston College for Negroes. In February 1946, [[Heman Marion Sweatt]], an [[African American]] man, applied to the [[University of Texas School of Law]].  He was denied admission because of race, and subsequently filed suit. (See ''[[Sweatt v. Painter]]'' (1950).)   The state had no law school for African Americans.  Instead of granting Sweatt a ''[[mandamus|writ of mandamus]]'', the Texas trial court continued the case for six months to allow the state time to create a law school for blacks. 

As a result, the state founded Texas Southern University under [[Texas Senate Bill 140|Senate Bill 140]] by the [[Fiftieth Texas Legislature]] on March 3, 1947 as a [[State university system|state university]] to be located in Houston.  Originally named Texas State University for Negroes, the school was established to serve [[African Americans]] in Texas and offer them fields of study comparable to those available to white Texans.  The state took over the Houston Independent School District (HISD)-run Houston College for Negroes as a basis for the new university.  At the time, Houston College just moved to the present site (adjacent to the University of Houston) donated by [[Hugh Roy Cullen]] and had one permanent building and an existing faculty and students.  The new university was charged with teaching &quot;pharmacy, dentistry, arts and sciences, journalism education, literature, law, medicine and other professional courses.&quot;  The legislature stipulated that &quot;these courses shall be equivalent to those offered at other institutions of this type supported by the State of Texas.&quot;

Given the differences in facilities and intangibles such as the distance of the new school from Austin and other law students, the Supreme Court ruled it did not satisfy &quot;separate but equal&quot; provisions, and that African Americans must also be admitted to the University of Texas Law School at Austin.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

In the early 1990s, of all Texas universities, TSU had the most incidents of violent crime on its campus. Crime became an issue in the campus during the 14 years leading to 2005.&lt;ref&gt;Secret, Mosi. &quot;Books, Bullets and Guns.&quot; ''[[Houston Press]]''. March 17, 2005. [http://www.houstonpress.com/2005-03-17/news/books-bullets-and-guns/ 1]. Retrieved on January 15, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[Image:TexasSouthernUniversityHouston.JPG|thumb|Texas Southern University]]
The university has a {{convert|150|acre|km2|sing=on}} urban campus in the middle of Houston's [[Third Ward, Houston|Third Ward]] (immediately southeast of [[Downtown Houston]]).
===Jesse H. Jones School of Business===
Jesse H. Jones School of Business is one of the ten colleges and schools at Texas Southern University. Named as one of the &quot;Best 300 Business Schools&quot; by the Princeton Review[1], the Jesse H. Jones School of Business is accredited by the Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business (AACSB)[2].[3] Jesse H. Jones School of Business currently have bachelor's degree major in Accounting, Finance, Management, Management Information Systems and Marketing, and MIS, MBA and eMBA for Master program.The Jesse H. Jones School of Business at Texas Southern University has approximately 1,600 students enrolled in undergraduate and graduate studies.[4] The School was recognized as one of the nation’s “Best Business Schools” by the U.S. News &amp; World Report in 2010 and as one of the “Best 290 Business Schools” by the Princeton Review in 2008[5].
===School of Science and Technology===
One of the newer facilities on the campus this building is home to several scholastic programs such as the Houston Louis Stokes Alliance Minority Program (H-LSAMP) and the Thomas Freeman Honors College. It is also home to several research programs like the NASA University Research Center for Bio-Nanotechnology and Environmental Research (NASA URC C-BER)and Maritime Transportation Studies and Research as well as the STEM research program
The College of Science and Technology offers extensive research experiences through various centers, partnerships and collaborations designed to strengthen the overall collegiate experience, and meet critical social needs. TSU’s NASA University Research Center (C-BER) addresses important human health concerns related to manned exploration of space. Programs such as TSU’s NASA University Research Center (C-BER) and participation in The Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Preparation Program (LSAMP) support undergraduate, graduate and faculty development while helping to increase the number of US citizens receiving degrees in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) fields.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tsu.edu/about&lt;/ref&gt;

===University Museum===
The {{convert|11000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} exhibition space displays a variety of historical and contemporary art and was designated the permanent home of the ''Web of Life'' mural by [[John T. Biggers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/museum.asp|title=University Museum|publisher=Texas Southern University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sterling Student Life Center===
Centrally located on Tiger Walk, the Ernest S. Sterling Student Life Center (SSLC) is the nucleus of campus life at TSU. It provides cultural, social, recreational, educational and religious programs and services for students, faculty, staff, alumni and guests, as it creates constructive leisure and educational activities.  The Student Center is home to the Student Government Association (SGA), University Program Council (UPC), ''Herald'' Newspaper, Tiger Yearbook, Office of Campus Organizations, TSU Cheerleaders, Student Activities administrative offices and Office of Events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/pages/2526.asp|title=Sterling Student Center|publisher=Texas Southern University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Granville M. Sawyer Auditorium===
Recently renovated, the Sawyer Auditorium is Texas Southern University’s historical landmark. Sawyer Auditorium features split level seating for up to 1,800 guests for hosting university sponsored events. It also has an adjacent drama playhouse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/pages/1674.asp|title=Sawyer Auditorium}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Residential facilities===
The school has two residence halls for first-year and returning students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/student/housing/residence.asp|title=The Residence Halls|publisher=Texas Southern University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Lanier East Hall, a co-ed for males and females
* Lanier West Hall, for female students

Other housing options include:
* Apartments with utilities included&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/student/housing/uc.asp|title=University Courtyard Apartments/ Tierwester Oaks/Richfield Manor|publisher=Texas Southern University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** University Courtyard Apartments
** Tierwester Oaks
* The Greystone Apartments (utilities not included)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/student/housing/greystone.asp|title=The Greystone Apartments|publisher=Texas Southern University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Postal services===
*The [[United States Postal Service]] Texas Southern Post Office is located at 3100 Cleburne Street, 77004-4575.

===Athletic facilities===
*[[Dynamo Stadium (Houston)|Dynamo Stadium]]
A new soccer stadium has been approved for the east
side of downtown with construction projected to be complete in 2012. With 22,000 seats, the stadium that has been provided through an agreement with the [[Houston Dynamo]] will serve a permanent home for Tiger football. After a logo campaign that spanned six
months, a new logo designed by Byron Byers was
selected to officially represent TSU athletic teams.
Athletics Director Charles McClelland also selected
two additional winning logos, designed by Daniel
Anderson and Walter Land that will be used for
additional marketing and merchandising efforts.

*[[Health and Physical Education Arena]]
*[[TSU Recreation and Wellness Center]]

===Barbara Jordan – Mickey Leland School of Public Affairs===
An extensive set of curricular offerings is provided through the Barbara Jordan-Mickey Leland School of Public Affairs that includes courses in Administration of Justice (AJ), Political Science (POLS), Public Affairs (PA), and Military Science (MSCI), as well as three undergraduate degrees and five graduate degrees.

==Academics==
Starting in fall 2010, Texas Southern University will offer college courses in partnership with Lone Star College at its new campus in northwest Houston. And thanks to a new partnership with the City of Houston and Houston Public Library, Texas Southern will offer fine arts classes as well as theatre and dance performances in the historic Deluxe Theater in Houston’s Fifth Ward district, which the city is currently renovating.

[[File:TSUHISDLabSchoolHoustonTX.JPG|thumb|left|Texas Southern University/[[Houston Independent School District]] Charter Laboratory School]]The university currently comprises ten schools and colleges along with several scholastic and research programs: 

*The [[Barbara Jordan /Mickey Leland School of Public Affairs]]: Mickey Leland Center, Barbara Jordan Institute

*The College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences: RCMI Institute for Biomedical and Health Disparities Research, Center for Cardiovascular Diseases, Center for Human Performance and Material Science,
Center of Excellence in Health Disparities Research: Cardiovascular Disease and Stroke

*The [[Thurgood Marshall School of Law]]: Earl Carl Institute for Legal and Social Justice,
Center for Legal Pedagogy,
Institute for International and Immigration Law (IIIL),
Center for Government,

*The College of Education

*The College of Continuing Education

*The College of Science and Technology: National Transportation Security Center of Excellence for Petro-Chemical Transportation (NTSCOE-P), Center for Transportation Training and Research (CTTR), TSU NASA University Research Center for Bionanotechnology and Environmental Research (TSU NASA C-BER), Innovative Transportation Research Institute (ITRI), Houston National Summer Transportation Institute (HNSTI), Research Center in Minority Institution (RCMI) Computational Core: Advanced Computational Simulation Center, Research Center in Minority Institution (RCMI) Computational Core: Data Analysis and Visualization Center, NASA C-BER Fellows Program, NASA C-BER Scholars Program, Houston Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (H-LSAMP) Program, Science &amp; Engineering Summer Program  Science Technology and Enhancement Program (STEP)

*The [[Jesse H. Jones School of Business]] ([[AACSB]] accredited): Economic Development Center, Gerald B. Smith Center for Entrepreneurship and Executive Development, JPMorgan Chase Center for Financial Education, Kase Lawal Center for Global Trade,

*The Graduate School

*The School of Communication: The Center for the Radio, Television and Print Media Professional Studies

and the recently established

*The Thomas F. Freeman Honors College (formerly the Frederick Douglass Honors Program); The Thomas F. Freeman Center for Forensic Excellence established in the College of Liberal Arts and Behavioral Sciences.

===Library===
The university main library is the [[Robert J. Terry Library]].The Brown Foundation re-invested in Texas Southern University with a two-year $1.2 million commitment to the Robert J. Terry Library
to improve its Urban Learning Center. The Urban Learning Center is an integral part of a new era of initiatives at Texas Southern and will provide critical support to the currently planned Academic Village. The new improvements will enhance the ability of the RJT Library to address
the literary and academic needs of our students.
TSU will offer classes at a brand new northwest campus location starting in fall 2010.
19 The [[Thurgood Marshall School of Law]] is one of four public [[List of law schools|law schools]] in [[Texas]] and it also houses a library.

==Student activities==
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot; 
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; |'''The Alma Mater'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tsu.edu/pdffiles/athletics/mens-sports/baseball/tsu.pdf|format=PDF|title=Texas Souther University History and Alma Mater}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|
The air is filled as our voices ring
&lt;br/&gt;From earth to the heav’ns above.
&lt;br/&gt;With voices raised; we’re singing praise,
&lt;br/&gt;To the school we dearly love.
&lt;br/&gt;Hail, Hail, Hail! to Texas South-ern
&lt;br/&gt;Hail, to our dear Maroon and Gray
&lt;br/&gt;Undivided we will stand
&lt;br/&gt;By the greatest in the land,
&lt;br/&gt;T-S-U, T-S-U, we love you.
&lt;br/&gt;All roads lead to Texas South-ern,
&lt;br/&gt;Paved with light for one and all.
&lt;br/&gt;T-S-U’s a shining star
&lt;br/&gt;And we’re proud of what you are,
&lt;br/&gt;T-S-U, T-S-U, we love you.
&lt;br/&gt;Hail, Hail, Hail! To Texas South-ern
&lt;br/&gt;Hail to our Chiefs in reverence we sing.
&lt;br/&gt;In our hearts you’ll always stay
&lt;br/&gt;As you lead us on our way,
&lt;br/&gt;T-S-U, T-S-U, we love you.
|-
|&lt;small&gt;''Words and Music by C.A. Tolbert''&lt;/small&gt;
|}


==Music==
The University's marching band the [[Ocean of Soul]] has won numeral awards, performed at Super Bowls&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/sports/2376503.html|title=Houston Bands March at Super Bowl XXXVIII |publisher=CHRON |accessdate=2009-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; , The Stellar Awards&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gospelflava.com/stellar/stellartapingrecap2005.html|title=RECAP:Stellar Award 20th Anniversary Taping 2005 |publisher=Gospel Flava |accessdate=2009-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 300+ Band has Alumni Such as,Grammy award-winning jazz saxophonist [[Kirk Whalum]].

===Athletics===
[[File:TexasSouthernTigers.png|thumb|left|Athletics logo]]
Texas Southern University's school colors are [[Maroon (color)|maroon]] and [[Grey|gray]] and the school's mascot is the Tiger. Texas Southern sports teams participate in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] (Championship Subdivision for football) in the [[Southwestern Athletic Conference]] (SWAC).

Men's varsity sports include baseball, basketball, football, golf, tennis, and track and field. Women's varsity sports include basketball, bowling, cross country, golf, soccer, softball, tennis, track and field, and volleyball.

TSU's best known rivals are [[Prairie View A&amp;M University|Prairie View A&amp;M]], [[Southern University]], [[Jackson State University]] and [[Grambling State University]].

===Tiger football===
On December 11, 2010, Texas Southern University won their FIRST Football SWAC Championship in 42 Years. TSU defeated Alabama State 11-6 at Legion Field in the 2010 Farmers Insurance SWAC Football Championship Game.
Led by SWAC Defensive Player of the Year and SWAC Championship Game Defensive MVP, Dejuan Fulghum, Texas Southern had the toughest defense in the SWAC in 2010, and #2 ranked in the nation (FCS).

Texas Southern Head coach Johnnie Cole was named the SWAC Football Coach of the Year as announced by the SWAC league office for the 2010 season.

Cole led his alma mater to its first-ever SWAC Championship Game berth and the first 8-win season at Texas Southern since 2000. The Tigers tied the school record with a 9th win Saturday, Dec. 11, 2010 after winning the [[SWAC Championship Game]]. Cole is finishing his 3rd season at TSU with a record of 19-16 with the Tigers. He is 34-32 in his 6th season as head coach for his career.

===KTSU 90.9 FM===
{{Main|KTSU}}

In addition to serving as a training unit for TSU students, the station was also established to serve the University at the program level as well as the community by presenting various types of educational, TSU athletic, cultural and social programs to a primarily listening area within a {{convert|10|mi|km|adj=on}} radius of the University. A 1973 survey indicated that radio was generally the preferred source of information of African Americans, particularly those with less than a high school education. By the late 70's, the station had secured an ample audience and programming increased in scope. At the same time, the station increased its power range from 10 watts to 18,500 watts. According to the Arbitron Rating Service (ARS), KTSU has an audience of 244,700 listeners and is number one over all of Houston/Galveston stations for its Sunday format and its Friday format of Golden Oldies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ktsufm.org/history.html|title=KTSU|KTSU FM}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Alumni==

{{alum/start
|ilist=
|alist=

{{Alum|name=Honorable [[Barbara Charline Jordan]]|year=|nota=Congresswoman in the United States House of Representatives from Texas from 1973 to 1979|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=J000266 |title=JORDAN, Barbara Charline - Biographical Information |work=bioguide.congress.gov |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Alum|name=[[Mickey Leland]]|year=|nota=Anti-poverty activist and later became a congressman from the Texas 18th District and chair of the Congressional Black Caucus|ref=.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=L000237 |title=LELAND, George Thomas (Mickey) - Biographical Information |work=bioguide.congress.gov |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Alum|name=[[Yolanda Adams]]|year=|nota=American Grammy and Dove-award winning Gospel music singer and radio show host. She has sold 4.5 million albums since 1991 according to Soundscan|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://christianmusic.about.com/od/alprofiles/p/yolandaadams.htm |title=Yolanda Adams – Biography of Urban Gospel Artist Yolanda Adams |work=about.com |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Alum|name=[[Michael Strahan]]|year1993=|nota=former NFL defensive end for the New York Giants. Currently a football analyst on Fox NFL Sunday, and also a host for Pros vs. Joes alongside fellow Fox football analyst Jay Glazer|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.tvguide.com/celebrities/michael-strahan/bio/258383 |title=Michael Strahan Biography|work=tvguide.com |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Alum|name=[[Rocky Williform]]|year=|nota=American entrepreneur and founder of HipHopBlog.com, the [[microblogging]] network for [[hip-hop]]. The one-time New York investment banker also founded StreetCred, the social network for hip-hop culture, and is the creator of the Hip-Hop Emblem.|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Harry E. Johnson]]|year=|nota= current President of the Washington, D.C. Martin Luther King, Jr. National Memorial Project Foundation, Inc|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.pbs.org/kcet/tavissmiley/archive/200704/20070404_johnson.html |title=Tavis Smiley . Shows . Harry Johnson . April 4, 2007 |work=pbs.org |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Alum|name=[[Ronald C. Green]]|year=|nota=current City Controller of Houston and a former member of the Houston City Council|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.houstontx.gov/controller/index.html |title=City of Houston &gt; Office of the City Controller |work=houstontx.gov |accessdate=30 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Alum|name=[[Rodney Ellis]]|year=|nota=Member of the [[Texas Senate, District 13]]|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Jarvis Johnson]]|year=|nota=Member of the [[Houston City Council]] from the B District|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Kase Lukman Lawal]]|year=|nota=chairman and chief executive officer of CAMAC International Corporation and chairman of Allied Energy Corporation in Houston, Texas, Chairman/Chief Executive Officer, CAMAC HOLDINGS;[1] vice chairman, Port of Houston Authority Commission|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Senfronia Thompson]]|year=|nota=Member of the Texas House of Representatives from the 141st district|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Lloyd C. A. Wells]]|year=|nota=Sports photographer and civil rights activist on the behalf of black athletes|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Robert Taylor (athlete)|Robert Taylor]]|year=|nota=winner of gold medal in 4x100 m relay at the 1972 Summer Olympics, and was a member of gold medal winning 4x400 m relay team at the 1975 Pan American Games,.|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Brett Maxie]]|year=|nota=former NFL defensive back and current NFL assistant coach|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Lloyd Mumphord]]|year=|nota=former NFL defensive back|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Julius Adams]]|year=|nota=former NFL defensive lineman|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Cortez Hankton]]|year=|nota=former NFL wide receiver |ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.databasefootball.com/players/playerpage.htm?ilkid=HANKTCOR01|title=Cortez Hankton, Past Statistics History Awards|work=databasefootball.com |accessdate=13 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Alum|name=[[Oliver Celestin]]|year=|nota=former NFL defensive back |ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.databasefootball.com/players/playerpage.htm?ilkid=CELESOLI01|title=Oliver Celestin, Past Statistics History Awards|work=databasefootball.com |accessdate=13 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Alum|name=[[Don Narcisse]]|year=|nota=former CFL wide receiver, held record of 216 Consecutive games with a catch |ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://leaderpost.specialsections.shoplocal.com/canwest/ss/index.aspx?webstoryid=15308430&amp;area=SS&amp;type=page&amp;AdgroupID=133082&amp;Locations=reginaleaderpost |title=Canwest |work=leaderpost.specialsections.shoplocal.com |accessdate=30 August 2010|quote=... your alma mater, Texas Southern University...}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Alum|name=[[Warren Bone]]|year=|nota=former NFL player |ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/B/BoneWa20.htm|title=Warren Bone|publisher=Pro-Football-Reference.com|accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Alum|name=[[Belvin Perry]]|year=|nota=Chief Judge of the Ninth Judicial Circuit in [[Orlando, Florida]] and was involved in the [[Death of Caylee Anthony|Casey Anthony trial]]. |ref=&lt;ref&gt;              {{cite web | url = http://belvinperry.com/biography/ | title = Biography | accessdate = 2011-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

Lonnie Hepburn. A former Defensive back who played got the Baltimore Colts, Clevland Browns and Denver Broncos.

==External links==
{{Portal box|Houston|University|African American}}
* [http://www.tsu.edu/ www.tsu.edu] -- Official web site
* [http://www.tsulaw.edu/ www.tsulaw.edu] -- Official Thurgood Marshall School of Law Web Site
* [http://www.tsuball.com/ www.tsuball.com] -- athletics web site
* [http://www.tsunaa.com/ www.tsunaa.com] -- Official National Alumni Association web site
* {{Handbook of Texas|id=TT/kct27|name=Texas Southern University}}

{{Public universities in Texas}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund}}
{{Southwestern Athletic Conference}}

[[Category:Texas Southern University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1947]]

[[de:Texas Southern University]]
[[no:Texas Southern University]]
[[simple:Texas Southern University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
