<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5442405" ns="0" title="Google Docs"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Google Docs
| logo                   = [[File:Googlelogo.png|200px]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Google Docs.png|center|300px]]
| caption                = Google Docs homepage   
| developer              = Writely Team (originally)&lt;br/&gt;[[Google Inc.]]
| release_date            = March 9, 2006
| latest_release_version =
| latest_preview_date    =
| operating_system       = Web-based application
| programming language   = front end: [[JavaScript]] &lt;br&gt; back end: [[Java (programming language)|Java]]&lt;ref&gt;http://computer.howstuffworks.com/internet/basics/google-docs5.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
| platform               = [[Internet Explorer]] 6+&lt;br/&gt;[[Mozilla Firefox]] 2+&lt;br/&gt;[[Google Chrome]] 1+&lt;br/&gt;[[Safari (web browser)|Safari]] 3+
| language               = Multilingual (53)&lt;ref&gt;[http://googledocs.blogspot.com/2010/07/translation-and-undo-smartquotes-in.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
| genre                  = Online spreadsheet, Presentations, Word processor, Drawing application, Form creator
| license                = 
| website                = [http://docs.google.com/ docs.google.com]
}}
[[File:Google Docs - example document.png|300px|thumb|An example of a document in Google Docs]]
'''Google Docs''' is a free, Web-based office suite, and data storage service offered by [[Google]].  It allows users to create and edit documents online while collaborating in real-time with other users. Google Docs combines the features of Writely and Spreadsheets with a [[presentation program]] incorporating technology designed by Tonic Systems. Data storage of files up to 1&amp;nbsp;GB total in size was introduced on January 13, 2011, documents created inside Google Docs do not count towards this quota.

==History==
[[File:Writely logo.PNG|frame|Writely's beta logo|left]]
Google Docs originated from two separate products, Writely and Google Spreadsheets.  Writely was a [[World Wide Web|web]]-based [[word processor]] created by the software company Upstartle and launched in August 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://emilychang.com/ehub/app/ehub-interviews-writely/ Emily Chang - eHub Interviews Writely&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Spreadsheets, launched as Google Labs Spreadsheets on June 6, 2006,&lt;ref name=&quot;google.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/intl/en/press/annc/spreadsheets.html Google Press Center: Google Announces limited test on Google Labs: Google Spreadsheets]&lt;/ref&gt; originated from the acquisition of the XL2Web product by [[2Web Technologies]]. Writely's original features included a [[Collaborative software|collaborative]] text editing suite and [[access control]]s. Menus, keyboard shortcuts, and dialog boxes are similar to what users may expect in a desktop word processor such as [[Microsoft Word]] or [[OpenOffice.org Writer]].

On March 9, 2006, Google announced that it had acquired Upstartle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Google Blog: Writely so&quot;&gt;[http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2006/03/writely-so.html Official Google Blog: Writely so&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of acquisition, Upstartle had four employees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cooltechzone.com/News_Reports/Media/Google_Acquires_Online_Word_Processing_Company_200603112224/ CoolTechZone.com - Google Acquires Online Word Processing Company&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Writely closed registration to its service until the move to Google servers was complete.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Google Blog: Writely so&quot;/&gt;  In August 2006, Writely sent account invitations to everyone who had requested to be placed on a waiting list, and then became publicly available on August 23.  Writely continued to maintain its own user system until September 19, 2006, when it was integrated with [[Google Accounts]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://writely.blogspot.com/2006/09/google-account-sign-in-live.html The Writely Blog: Google Account Sign-in LIVE&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, Google developed Google Spreadsheets using the technology it had acquired from 2Web Technologies in 2005 and launched Google Labs Spreadsheets&lt;ref name=&quot;google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2006/06/its-nice-to-share.html Official Google Blog: Its Nice to Share]&lt;/ref&gt; on June 6, 2006 as the first public component of what would eventually become Google Docs. It was initially made available to only a limited number of users, on a first-come, first-served basis. The limited test was later replaced with a beta version available to all Google Account holders, around the same time as a press release was issued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.google.com/intl/en/press/annc/docsspreadsheets.html |title=Google Announces Google Docs &amp; Spreadsheets|date=2006-10-11 |accessdate=2008-10-18|publisher=Official Google Press Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2007, Google Docs was made available to [[Google Apps]] users.

In June 2007, Google changed the front page to include folders instead of labels, organized in a side bar.

On September 17, 2007, Google released their [[presentation program]] product for Google Docs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2007/09/our-feature-presentation.html |title=Our feature presentation |date=2007-09-17 |accessdate=2007-09-17 |publisher=Official [[Google]] Blog |author=Attila Bodis}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 6, 2009, Google announced on their official blog that Google Docs along with other Google Apps would be taken out of beta.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2009/07/google-apps-is-out-of-beta-yes-really.html |title=Google Apps is out of beta (yes, really) |date=2009-07-07 |accessdate=2009-07-07 |publisher=Official [[Google]] Blog |author=Matthew Glotzbach, Director, Product Management, Google Enterprise}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 13, 2010, Google announced on their official blog that Google Docs would allow any file type, including 1GB of free space and $0.25/GB for additional storage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crn.com/storage/222300732;jsessionid=YUYB043111X0NQE1GHOSKH4ATMY32JVN Google Docs any file type]&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 7, 2010, DocVerse, an online document [[Collaborative software|collaboration]] company, was acquired by [[Google]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://phandroid.com/2010/03/05/google-buys-docverse-for-office-collaboration-chrome-android-wave-implications/ Google buys DocVerse]&lt;/ref&gt; It allows multiple user online collaboration on [[Microsoft Office]] compatible document formats such as [[Microsoft Word|Word]], [[Microsoft Excel|Excel]], and [[Microsoft PowerPoint|PowerPoint]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.docverse.com/ Docverse.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Improvements based on DocVerse were announced and deployed in April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://googledocs.blogspot.com/2010/04/rebuilt-more-real-time-google-documents.html A rebuilt, more real time Google documents]&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2010, it was reported that access to Google Docs had been blocked in [[Turkey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/06/08/turkey_bans_google_services/ | title=Turkey bans Google Books, Google Docs, Google Translate... | date=2010-06-08 | accessdate=2010-06-28 | publisher=The Register}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Google employee confirmed the problem saying that it &quot;appear[ed] to be linked to the ongoing ban on [[YouTube]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.google.com/support/forum/p/Google+Docs/thread?tid=23d6143a842bb5ea&amp;hl=en | title=Has Turkey blocked docs.google.com? Is anything being done about it? | date=2010-06-04 | publisher=Google Docs Help Forum}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of September 29, 2011, Google Docs supports offline viewing through an opt-in beta [[HTML 5]] web app.&lt;ref name=&quot;offline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/offline|title=Google Docs Offline|accessdate=2011-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features==

Google Docs is Google's &quot;[[software as a service]]&quot; office suite. Documents, spreadsheets, presentations can be created with Google Docs, imported through the web interface, or sent via email. Documents can be saved to a user's local computer in a variety of formats ([[OpenDocument|ODF]], [[HTML]], [[Portable Document Format|PDF]], [[Rich Text Format|RTF]], [[Formatted text|Text]], [[Microsoft Office]]). Documents are automatically saved to Google's servers to prevent data loss, and a revision history is automatically kept so past edits may be viewed (although this only works for adjacent revisions, and there is currently no way to find and isolate changes in long documents.). Documents can be tagged and archived for organizational purposes. The service is officially supported on recent versions of the [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]], [[Microsoft Internet Explorer|Internet Explorer]], [[Safari (web browser)|Safari]] and [[Google Chrome|Chrome]] browsers running on Microsoft Windows, Apple OS X, and Linux operating systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoogleDocsSYSREQ&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=37560|title=Getting to know Google Docs: System requirements|publisher=Google.com|accessdate=2009-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

1&amp;nbsp;GB of storage is included for free. Currently additional storage costs per year are: 20&amp;nbsp;GB-$5, 80&amp;nbsp;GB-$20, etc. up to 16&amp;nbsp;TB. &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/accounts/b/0/PurchaseStorage Additional Storage]&lt;/ref&gt; Individual documents may not exceed 1&amp;nbsp;GB {{asof|2010|01|13|lc=1}}, embedded images must not exceed 2&amp;nbsp;MB each, and spreadsheets are limited to 256 columns, 200,000 rows, and 99 sheets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/web/news/2010/01/google-docs-gets-file-uploading-but-no-direct-desktop-sync.ars Arstechnica.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://docs.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=37603&amp;topic=15119 |title=Google Docs Help: Size limits}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2009, an equation editor was added which allows rendering in [[LaTeX]] format. However, Google Docs lacks an equation numbering feature. Find and Replace is available and in the original release, there was no ability to do the search in a reverse direction; the newest version of Google Docs allows reverse search and reverse replace.

Google Docs serves as a collaborative tool for editing amongst in real time. Documents can be shared, opened, and edited by multiple users at the same time. Users cannot be notified of changes, but the application can notify users when a comment or discussion is made or replied to, facilitating collaboration. There is no way to highlight changes made by a particular editor in real time during a writing session, nor a way to jump to the changes made. However, users can usually see where in the document or file a particular editor is currently writing, since in most of the suite's products, an editor's current position is represented with an editor-specific color/cursor. Also, the revision history included in the service allows users to see the changes made to a document, distinguished by editor, using their specific color. The application supports two [[ISO]] standard document formats: [[OpenDocument]] (for both opening and exporting) and [[Office Open XML]] (for opening only). It also includes support for proprietary formats such as [[DOC (computing)|.doc]] and [[.xls]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/google-d-s/tour1.html Google Docs Tour]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://docs.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=50092&amp;hl=en List of supported file types]&lt;/ref&gt;

Google Docs is one of many [[cloud computing]] document-sharing services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/188173/should_you_move_your_small_business_to_the_cloud.html PC World: Should you move your business to the cloud?]&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of document-sharing services require user fees, whereas Google Docs is free. Its popularity amongst businesses is growing due to enhanced sharing features and accessibility.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sparxoo.com/2009/05/18/top-5-ways-to-collaborate/ Top 5 Ways to Collaborate]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Google Docs has enjoyed a rapid rise in popularity among students and educational institutions.&lt;ref&gt;Firth, Mark &amp; Mesureur, Germain. [http://jaltcall.org/journal/articles/6_1_Firth_Abstract.html &quot;Innovative uses for Google Docs in a university language program&quot;], ''The JALT CALL Journal''. Retrieved on 2010-06-30.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Google Cloud Connect]] is a plug-in for [[Windows]] [[Microsoft Office]] 2003, 2007 and 2010 that can automatically store and synchronize any for [[Microsoft Word]] document, [[PowerPoint]] presentation, or [[Excel]] spreadsheet to Google Docs in Google Docs or Microsoft Office formats. The Google Doc copy is automatically updated each time the Microsoft Office document is saved. Microsoft Office documents can be edited offline and synchronized later when online. Google Cloud Sync maintains previous Microsoft Office document versions and allows multiple users to collaborate by working on the same document at the same time. &lt;ref&gt;[http://googledocs.blogspot.com/2011/02/google-cloud-connect-for-microsoft.html Google Cloud Connect for Microsoft Office available to all]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mashable.com/2011/02/24/google-cloud-connect-2/ Mashable: Now Anyone Can Sync Google Docs &amp; Microsoft Office]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Google Spreadsheets]] and [[Google Sites]] also incorporate [[Google Apps Script]] to write code within documents in a similar way to [[Visual Basic for Applications|VBA]] in [[Microsoft Office]]. The scripts can be activated either by user action or by a trigger in response to an event &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Meyer|first=David|title=Google Apps Script gets green light|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1001_3-10314002-92.html|accessdate=28 March 2011|date=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Finley|first=Klint|title=Google Apps Now Offers Business Process Automation on Google Sites with Scripts|url=http://www.readwriteweb.com/enterprise/2010/10/google-apps-scripts.php|accessdate=28 March 2011|newspaper=ReadWriteWeb|date=October 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Offline viewing is available as an opt-in beta [[HTML 5]] web app.&lt;ref name=&quot;offline&quot; /&gt;

=== Supported file formats ===
Google Docs supports 15 file formats:&lt;ref&gt;[http://docs.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=1189935]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Microsoft Word (.DOC and .DOCX)
* Microsoft Excel (.XLS and .XLSX)
* Microsoft PowerPoint (.PPT and .PPTX)
* OpenDocument Format (.ODT and .ODS)
* Adobe Portable Document Format (.PDF)
* Apple Pages (.PAGES)
* Adobe Illustrator (.AI)
* Adobe Photoshop (.PSD)
* Tagged Image File Format (.TIFF)
* Autodesk AutoCad (.DXF)
* Scalable Vector Graphics (.SVG)
* PostScript (.EPS, .PS)
* TrueType (.TTF)
* XML Paper Specification (.XPS)
* Archive file types (.ZIP and .RAR)

==Data safety and privacy==
[[Data security]] issues and [[national interests]] mean that on-line document storage, and processing can be unsuitable for use by governments or commercial organisations.  Especially so where sensitive or confidential data is being stored, edited or shared, etc. on systems and infrastructure that are outsourced and shared with many other organisations, individuals, users.

On March 10, 2009, Google reported, for example, that a bug in Google Docs had allowed unintended access to some private documents. It was believed that 0.05% of all documents stored via the service were affected by the bug.  Google claims the bug has now been fixed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.breitbart.com/article.php?id=CNG.54c3200989573ae4c9282658f91276df.481&amp;show_article=1 Google software bug shared private online documents], AFP, March 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mobile access==
The [[Android (operating system)|Android]] Google Docs app, which is available for free on the android market, &lt;ref&gt;https://market.android.com/details?id=com.google.android.apps.docs&amp;hl=en&lt;/ref&gt; allows users to view, edit, and create Google Docs documents, spreadsheets, and presentations. The Android Google Docs app can also take a photo of a document, sign, or other text and use [[Optical Character Recognition]] to convert to text that can be edited. ([http://docs.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=1257518 Help], [http://www.google.com/google-d-s/tour1.html Overview])&lt;ref&gt;[http://googlemobile.blogspot.com/2011/04/introducing-new-google-docs-app-for.html Introducing the new Google Docs app for Android]&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[iPhone]] and [[iPad]] [[Safari (web browser)|Safari Browser]] also allows users to view documents, spreadsheets, and presentation and to edit and create Google Docs documents and spreadsheets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.appsafari.com/utilities/1343/google-docs/ Appsafari: Google Docs]&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, the Google App for iPhone and iPad allows users to view and edit Google Docs. Most other [[mobile devices]] can also view and edit Google Docs documents and spreadsheets  using a [[mobile browser]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/mobile/docs/ Docs.Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt; [[PDF]] files can be viewed but not edited.

==See also==
* [[List of word processors]]
* [[Comparison of word processors]]
* [[Google Cloud Connect]] to sync from Microsoft Office Documents
* [[Google Picasa]] for image storage
* [[Comparison of office suites]]
* [[Docs.com]]
* [[File hosting service]]
* [[:Category:Presentation software|List of presentation software]]
* [[Formula editor|List of equation editors]]
* [[Online word processors|List of online word processors]]
* [[List of online spreadsheets]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | last = Conner | first = Nancy | title = Google Apps: The Missing Manual | publisher = Pogue Press | location = Sebastopol | year = 2008 | isbn = 9780596515799 }}

==External links==
{{Commonscat}}
* [http://docs.google.com/ Google Docs]
* [http://googledocs.blogspot.com/ Official Google Docs Blog] on [[Blogger (service)|Blogger]]
* [http://www.tonicsystems.com/ Tonic Systems web page] (with a few details on Google acquisition)
* [http://www.google.com/google-d-s/tour5.html Some examples of how Google Docs is used]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eRqUE6IHTEA Video: Collaboration in Google Docs]
* [http://office2.0project.net/recommendations/google-docs/ Google Docs Pros and Cons]
* [https://docs.google.com/document/pub?id=1LuaiLkTnAiBTWbKX2Df7Qlzvf1SCsOn50kzep4Cb0MQ Free Google Docs Press Release Template With Company Logo and PDF Output]

{{Google Inc.}}
{{Office suites}}
{{Digital Distribution Platforms}}

[[Category:Cloud applications]]
[[Category:Google services|Docs &amp; Spreadsheets]]
[[Category:Ajax (programming)]]
[[Category:Collaboration]]
[[Category:File hosting]]
[[Category:Presentation software]]
[[Category:Web 2.0]]
[[Category:Web applications]]
[[Category:Online word processors]]
[[Category:Online spreadsheets]]
[[Category:Online office suites]]
[[Category:Collaborative real-time editors]]

[[ar:جوجل دوكس]]
[[be-x-old:Google Docs]]
[[ca:Google Docs &amp; Spreadsheets]]
[[da:Google Docs]]
[[de:Google Text &amp; Tabellen]]
[[et:Google Docs]]
[[es:Google Docs]]
[[eu:Google Docs]]
[[fa:گوگل داکس]]
[[fr:Google Documents]]
[[ko:구글 문서도구]]
[[hi:गूगल डॉक्स]]
[[id:Google Docs]]
[[it:Google Documenti]]
[[he:Google Docs]]
[[lt:Google Docs]]
[[hu:Google Dokumentumok]]
[[mr:गूगल डॉक्स]]
[[nl:Google Docs]]
[[ja:Google ドキュメント]]
[[no:Google Docs]]
[[pl:Dokumenty Google]]
[[pt:Google Docs]]
[[ru:Google Docs]]
[[sk:Google Dokumenty]]
[[fi:Google Docs &amp; Spreadsheets]]
[[sv:Google Docs]]
[[ta:கூகிள் டாக்ஸ்]]
[[uk:Google Docs]]
[[yi:גוגל דאקומענטן]]
[[zh:Google文件]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
