<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="544733" ns="0" title="LabVIEW"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Software
| name = LabVIEW
| logo = [[Image:Labview-logo.png|right|300px|LabVIEW logo.]]
| screenshot =
| caption =
| developer = [[National Instruments]]
| latest_release_version = 2011
| latest_release_date = {{release date|2011|08|04}}
| operating_system = [[Cross-platform]]: [http://ni.com/labview/requirements Windows, Mac OS X, Linux]
| genre = [[Data acquisition|Data Acquisition]], [[Instrument control|Instrument Control]], [[Test automation|Test Automation]], [[Signal processing|Analysis and Signal Processing]], [[Industrial Control Systems|Industrial Control]], [[Embedded system|Embedded Design]]
| license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website = [http://www.ni.com/labview/ ni.com/labview]
}}
'''LabVIEW''' (short for Laboratory Virtual Instrumentation Engineering Workbench) is a system design platform and development environment for a [[visual programming language]] from [[National Instruments]]. LabVIEW provides engineers and scientists with the tools needed to create and deploy measurement and control systems.  
 

The graphical language is named &quot;G&quot; (not to be confused with [[G-code]]). Originally released for the [[Apple Macintosh]] in 1986, LabVIEW is commonly used for [[data acquisition]], [[instrument control]], and [[Automation|industrial automation]] on a variety of platforms including [[Microsoft Windows]], various versions of [[Unix|UNIX]], [[Linux]], and [[Mac OS X]]. The latest version of LabVIEW is version LabVIEW 2011, released in August 2011.

== Dataflow programming ==
The programming language used in LabVIEW, also referred to as G, is a [[dataflow programming]] language. Execution is determined by the structure of a graphical block diagram (the LV-source code) on which the programmer connects different function-nodes by drawing wires. These wires propagate variables and any node can execute as soon as all its input data become available. Since this might be the case for multiple nodes simultaneously, G is inherently capable of parallel execution. [[Multi-processing]] and [[Thread (computer science)|multi-threading]] hardware is automatically exploited by the built-in scheduler, which [[multiplexing|multiplexes]] multiple [[Operating System|OS]] threads over the nodes ready for execution.

== Graphical programming ==
[[File:WikipediaFPandBD.png|thumb|Screenshot of a simple LabVIEW program]]
LabVIEW ties the creation of user interfaces (called front panels) into the development cycle. LabVIEW programs/subroutines are called virtual instruments (VIs). Each VI has three components: a block diagram, a front panel and a connector panel. The last is used to represent the VI in the block diagrams of other, calling VIs. Controls and indicators on the front panel allow an operator to input data into or extract data from a running virtual instrument. However, the front panel can also serve as a programmatic interface. Thus a virtual instrument can either be run as a program, with the front panel serving as a user interface, or, when dropped as a node onto the block diagram, the front panel defines the inputs and outputs for the given node through the connector pane. This implies each VI can be easily tested before being embedded as a subroutine into a larger program.

The graphical approach also allows non-programmers to build programs by dragging and dropping virtual representations of lab equipment with which they are already familiar. The LabVIEW programming environment, with the included examples and documentation, makes it simple to create small applications. This is a benefit on one side, but there is also a certain danger of underestimating the expertise needed for high-quality G programming. For complex algorithms or large-scale code, it is important that the programmer possesses an extensive knowledge of the special LabVIEW syntax and the topology of its memory management. The most advanced LabVIEW development systems offer the possibility of building stand-alone applications. Furthermore, it is possible to create distributed applications, which communicate by a client/server scheme, and are therefore easier to implement due to the inherently parallel nature of G.

The image above is an illustration of a simple LabVIEW program showing the dataflow source code in the form of the block diagram in the lower left frame and the input and output variables as graphical objects in the upper right frame. The two are the essential components of a LabVIEW program referred to as a Virtual Instrument.

==  Benefits ==
=== Interfacing ===

A key benefit of LabVIEW over other development environments is the extensive support for accessing instrumentation hardware. Drivers and abstraction layers for many different types of instruments and buses are included or are available for inclusion. These present themselves as graphical nodes. The abstraction layers offer standard software interfaces to communicate with hardware devices. The provided driver interfaces save program development time. The sales pitch of National Instruments is, therefore, that even people with limited coding experience can write programs and deploy test solutions in a reduced time frame when compared to more conventional or competing systems. A new hardware driver topology (DAQmxBase), which consists mainly of G-coded components with only a few register calls through NI Measurement Hardware DDK (Driver Development Kit) functions, provides platform independent hardware access to numerous data acquisition and instrumentation devices. The DAQmxBase driver is available for LabVIEW on Windows, Mac OS X and Linux platforms.

Although not a .NET language, Labview also offers an interface to .NET Framework assemblies, which makes it possible to use, for instances, databases and XML files in automation projects.

=== Code compilation ===

In terms of performance, LabVIEW includes a [[compiler]] that produces native code for the CPU platform. The graphical code is translated into executable machine code by interpreting the syntax and by compilation. The LabVIEW syntax is strictly enforced during the editing process and compiled into the executable machine code when requested to run or upon saving. In the latter case, the executable and the source code are merged into a single file. The executable runs with the help of the LabVIEW [[Run-time system|run-time]] engine, which contains some precompiled code to perform common tasks that are defined by the G language. The run-time engine reduces compile time and also provides a consistent interface to various operating systems, graphic systems, hardware components, etc. The run-time environment makes the code portable across platforms. Generally, LabVIEW code can be slower than equivalent compiled C code, although the differences often lie more with program optimization than inherent execution speed.

=== Large libraries ===

Many [[Library (computing)|libraries]] with a large number of functions for data acquisition, signal generation, mathematics, statistics, signal conditioning, analysis, etc., along with numerous graphical interface elements are provided in several LabVIEW package options. The number of advanced mathematic blocks for functions such as integration, filters, and other specialized capabilities usually associated with data capture from hardware sensors is immense. In addition, LabVIEW includes a text-based programming component called MathScript with additional functionality for signal processing, analysis and mathematics. MathScript can be integrated with graphical programming using &quot;script nodes&quot; and uses a syntax that is generally compatible with [[MATLAB]] {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}.

=== Code re-use ===

The fully modular character of LabVIEW code allows code reuse without modifications: as long as the data types of input and output are consistent, two sub VIs are interchangeable.

The LabVIEW Professional Development System allows creating stand-alone executables and the resultant executable can be distributed an unlimited number of times. The run-time engine and its libraries can be provided freely along with the executable.

A benefit of the LabVIEW environment is the platform independent nature of the G code, which is (with the exception of a few platform-specific functions) portable between the different LabVIEW systems for different operating systems (Windows, Mac OS X and Linux). National Instruments is increasingly focusing on the capability of deploying LabVIEW code onto an increasing number of targets including devices like [[Phar Lap (company)|Phar Lap]] or [[VxWorks]] OS based LabVIEW Real-Time controllers, [[FPGA]]s, PocketPCs, PDAs,  [[Wireless sensor network]] nodes, and even [[LEGO MINDSTORMS NXT]]

=== Parallel Programming ===
With LabVIEW it is very easy to program different tasks that are performed in parallel by means of multithreading. This is, for instance, easily done by drawing two or more parallel while loops. This is a great benefit for test system automation, where it is common practice to run processes like test sequencing, data recording, and hardware interfacing in parallel.

=== User community ===

There is a low-cost LabVIEW Student Edition aimed at educational institutions for learning purposes. There is also an active community of LabVIEW users who communicate through several e-mail groups and [[Internet forum]]s.

==Criticism==

LabVIEW is a [[proprietary software|proprietary]] product of [[National Instruments]]. Unlike common programming languages such as [[C Programming Language|C]] or [[FORTRAN]], LabVIEW is not managed or specified by a third party standards committee such as [[American National Standards Institute|ANSI]], IEEE, ISO, etc.

=== Licensing ===
Building a stand-alone application with LabVIEW requires the Application Builder component which is included with the Professional Development System but requires a separate purchase if using the Base Package or Full Development System.&lt;ref name=&quot;Building a Stand-Alone Application&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url= http://zone.ni.com/reference/en-XX/help/371361B-01/lvhowto/building_a_stand_alone_app/ | publisher=National Instruments |title= Building a Stand-Alone Application }}&lt;/ref&gt;
There is no LabView 2011 student license for Linux.

=== Runtime environment ===

Compiled [[executable]]s produced by the Application Builder are not truly standalone in that they also require that the LabVIEW run-time engine be installed on any target computer on which users run the application.&lt;ref name=&quot;Using the LabVIEW Run-Time Engine&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url= http://zone.ni.com/reference/en-XX/help/371361B-01/lvhowto/using_the_lv_run_time_eng/ | publisher=National Instruments |title= Using the LabVIEW Run-Time Engine }}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of standard controls requires a [[runtime library]] for any language and all major operating system suppliers supply the required libraries for common languages such as C. However, the runtime required for LabVIEW is not supplied with any operating system and is required to be specifically installed by the administrator or user. This requirement can cause problems if an application is distributed to a user who may be prepared to run the application but does not have the inclination or permission to install additional files on the host system prior to running the executable.

=== Copyright notice ===

According to the [[National Instruments]] [[license agreement]] an executable built with LabVIEW should contain a note that the software is written in LabVIEW.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ni.com/pdf/legal/us/software_license_agreement.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote box4
 |quote  = 1.) You include the following copyright notice &quot;Copyright © [insert year] National Instruments Corporation. All Rights Reserved.&quot; in (a) the Authorized Application′s About Box (if applicable) and (b)(i) any applicable written documentation or, (ii) if no such documentation exists, in a &quot;read me&quot; or other .txt file distributed with each copy of the Authorized Application (you may include your own copyright notice with the notice(s) required above).
|source = 
|width  = 98%
|align  = center
-}}

There is some debate as to whether LabVIEW is really a general purpose programming language (or in some cases whether it is really a programming language at all) as opposed to an application-specific development environment for measurement and automation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://zone.ni.com/devzone/cda/tut/p/id/5313  Is LabVIEW a general purpose programming language?]&lt;/ref&gt; Critics point to a lack of features, common in most other programming languages, such as, until version 2009, native [[recursion]] and, until version 8.20, native object oriented features.

=== Formal testing ===

For an environment targeted for repetitive application, especially in process automation, LabVIEW includes no built-in functions for formally testing limits, reading a limits file, and conveniently tracking the passing or failing results. 

Due to such constraints in effect with formal and dynamic testing, the recommended usage potentially will not cover the required scope for production or therapy processes, especially when these are subject of risk and security auditing, e.g. according to FDA 21 C.F.R. §820 et seq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://zone.ni.com/devzone/cda/pub/p/id/364#toc4 Best Practices When Developing with NI LabVIEW for FDA-Validated Medical Devices]&lt;/ref&gt;

Companies tend to build their own proprietary functions for this basic feature if they choose not to use National Instruments' product line ''TestStand''.

== Timing system ==
LabVIEW uses the January 1, 1904 [[Epoch (reference date)|epoch]] as its &quot;zero&quot; time.  Other programs that use the January 1, 1904 epoch are [[Apple Inc.]]'s [[Mac OS]] through version 9, [[Palm OS]], [[MP4]], and Microsoft Excel (optionally).[13]

== Release history ==

Starting with LabVIEW 8.0, a minor release is released around the first week of August to coincide with the National Instruments conference NI Week, followed by a bug-fix release in February.
In 2009 National Instruments names the releases after the year they are released in. The bug-fix is called a Service Pack (for instance the 2009 service pack 1 is released in February 2010).
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%; text-align: left; &quot;
|-
! Name/Version !! Build Number !! Date
|-
| LabVIEW project begins
| 
| April 1983
|-
| LabVIEW 1.0 (for Macintosh)
| ??
| October 1986
|-
| LabVIEW 2.0
| ??
| January 1990
|-
| LabVIEW 2.5 (first release for Sun &amp; Windows)
| ??
| August 1992
|-
| LabVIEW 3.0 (Multiplatform)
| ??
| July 1993
|-
| LabVIEW 3.0.1 (first release for Windows NT)
| ??
| 1994
|-
| LabVIEW 3.1
| ??
| 1994
|-
| LabVIEW 3.1.1 (first release with &quot;application builder&quot; capability)
| ??
| 1995
|-
| LabVIEW 4.0
| ??
| April 1996
|-
| LabVIEW 4.1
| ??
| 1997
|-
| LabVIEW 5.0
| ??
| February 1998
|-
| LabVIEW RT (Real Time)
| ??
| May 1999
|-
| LabVIEW 6.0 (6i)
| 6.0.0.4005
| 7/26/2000
|-
| LabVIEW 6.1
| 6.1.0.4004
| 12/4/2001
|-
| LabVIEW 7.0 (Express)
| 7.0.0.4000
| April 2003
|-
| LabVIEW PDA module first released
| ??
| May 2003
|-
| LabVIEW FPGA module first released
| ??
| June 2003
|-
| LabVIEW 7.1
| ??
| 2004
|-
| LabVIEW Embedded module first released
| ??
| May 2005
|-
| LabVIEW 8.0 
| ??
| September 2005
|-
| LabVIEW 8.20 (native Object Oriented Programming)
| ??
| August 2006
|-
| LabVIEW 8.2.1
| 8.2.1.4002
| 2/21/2007
|-
| LabVIEW 8.5
| 8.5.0.4002
| 2007
|-
| LabVIEW 8.6
| 8.6.0.4001
| 7/24/2008
|-
| LabVIEW 8.6.1
| 8.6.0.4001
| 12/10/2008
|-
| LabVIEW 2009 (32 and 64-bit)
| 9.0.0.4022
| 8/4/2009
|-
| LabVIEW 2009 SP2
| 9.0.1.4011
| 1/8/2010
|-
| LabVIEW 2010
| 10.0.0.4032
| 8/4/2010
|-
| LabVIEW 2010 f2
| 10.0.0.4033
| 9/16/2010
|-
| LabVIEW 2010 SP1
| 10.0.1.4004
| 5/17/2011
|-
| LabVIEW for LEGO MINDSTORMS (2010 SP1)
| 
| August 2011
|-
| LabVIEW 2011
| 11.0.0.4029
| 6/22/2011
|}

==Repositories and libraries==

[[OpenG]], as well as [http://lavag.org/files/ LAVA Code Repository (LAVAcr)], serve as repositories for a wide range of Open Source LabVIEW applications and [[Library (computing)|libraries]].
[[SourceForge]] has LabVIEW listed as one of [https://sourceforge.net/search/?&amp;fq%5B%5D=trove%3A545 the possible languages] in which code can be written.

[[VI Package Manager]] has become the standard [[package manager]] for LabVIEW libraries. It is very similar in purpose to Ruby's [[RubyGems]] and Perl's [[CPAN]], although it provides a graphical user interface similar to the [[Synaptic Package Manager]].  VI Package Manager provides access to a repository of the OpenG (and other) libraries for LabVIEW.

Tools exist to convert G code into [[MathML]].&lt;ref&gt;https://decibel.ni.com/content/docs/DOC-13859&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related software==

National Instruments also offers a product called [http://www.ni.com/mstudio/ Measurement Studio], which offers many of the test, measurement and control capabilities of LabVIEW, as a set of classes for use with [[Microsoft]] [[Visual Studio]]. This allows developers to harness some of LabVIEW's strengths within the text-based [[.NET framework]]. National Instruments also offers [http://www.ni.com/lwcvi/ LabWindows/CVI] as an alternative for ANSI C programmers.

When applications require sequencing, users often use LabVIEW with [http://www.ni.com/teststand/ TestStand] test management software, also from National Instruments.

The [[Ch interpreter]] is a C/C++ Interpreter that can be embedded into LabVIEW for Scripting.&lt;ref name=&quot;chlabview&quot;&gt;[http://iel.ucdavis.edu/projects/chlabview/ Embedding a C/C++ Interpreter Ch into LabVIEW for Scripting]&lt;/ref&gt;

The TRIL Centre Ireland [http://biomobius.org/ BioMobius platform] and DSP Robotics' [http://www.dsprobotics.com/flowstone.html FlowStone DSP] also use a form of graphical programming similar to LabVIEW, but are limited to the biomedical and robotics industries respectively.

LabVIEW has a direct node with [http://www.modefrontier.com/ modeFRONTIER], a multidisciplinary and multi-objective optimization and design environment, written to allow coupling to almost any computer aided engineering (CAE) tool. Both can be part of the same business process and can be virtually driven by the optimization technologies available in [http://www.modefrontier.com/ modeFRONTIER].

== See also ==
* [[Comparison of numerical analysis software]]
* [[Dataflow programming]]
* [[Fourth-generation programming language]]
* [[Graphical programming]]
* [[Graphical system design]]
* [[LabWindows/CVI]]
* [[Lego Mindstorms|Lego Mindstorms NXT]], whose programming environment is based on LabVIEW.
* [[MATLAB]]/[[Simulink]]
* [[Virtual instrumentation]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Peter A. Blume: ''The LabVIEW Style Book'', February 27, 2007, Prentice Hall. Part of the National Instruments Virtual Instrumentation Series series. ISBN 0-13-145835-3
* Jeffrey Travis, Jim Kring: ''LabVIEW for Everyone: Graphical Programming Made Easy and Fun, 3rd Edition'', July 27, 2006, Prentice Hall. Part of the National Instruments Virtual Instrumentation Series. ISBN 0-13-185672-3

===Articles on specific uses===
*{{cite journal
  | last = Desnica V, Schreiner M
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = A LabVIEW-controlled portable x-ray fluorescence spectrometer for the analysis of art objects
  | journal = X-Ray Spectrometry
  | volume = 35
  | issue = 5
  | pages = 280–286
  | publisher =
  | month = October | year = 2006
  | url = http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/cgi-bin/abstract/112748693/ABSTRACT
  | doi = 10.1002/xrs.906
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = Vladan
  | last2 = Schreiner
  | first2 = Manfred  }}

*{{cite journal
  | last = Keleshis C, Ionita C, Rudin S
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Labview &lt;nowiki&gt;[sic]&lt;/nowiki&gt; graphical user interface for micro angio-fluoroscopic high resolution detector
  | journal = Medical Physics
  | volume = 33
  | issue = 6
  | pages = 2007
  | publisher =
  | month = June | year = 2006
  | url = http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=MPHYA6000033000006002007000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=Yes
  | doi = 10.1118/1.2240285
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = C
  | last2 = Ionita
  | first2 = C
  | last3 = Rudin
  | first3 = S  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Fedak W, Bord D, Smith C, Gawrych D, Lindeman K
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Automation of the Franck-Hertz experiment and the Tel-X-Ometer x-ray machine using LABVIEW
  | journal = American Journal of Physics
  | volume = 71
  | issue = 5
  | pages = 501–506
  | publisher = AAPT
  | month = May | year = 2003
  | url = http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=AJPIAS000071000005000501000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=Yes
  | doi = 10.1119/1.1527949
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = W.
  | last2 = Bord
  | first2 = D.
  | last3 = Smith
  | first3 = C.
  | last4 = Gawrych
  | first4 = D.
  | last5 = Lindeman
  | first5 = K.  }}

===Articles on education uses===
*{{cite journal
  | last = Belletti A, Borromei R, Ingletto G
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =

  | last2 = Borromei
  | first2 = R.
  | last3 = Ingletto
  | first3 = G.| title = Teaching physical chemistry experiments with a computer simulation by LabVIEW
  | journal = Journal of Chemical Education
  | volume = 83
  | issue = 9
  | pages = 1353–1355
  | publisher = ACS
  | month = September | year = 2006
  | url = http://jchemed.chem.wisc.edu/Journal/Issues/2006/Sep/abs1353.html
  | doi = 10.1021/ed083p1353
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = A.  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Moriarty PJ, Gallagher BL, Mellor CJ, Baines RR
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Graphical computing in the undergraduate laboratory: Teaching and interfacing with LabVIEW
  | journal = American Journal of Physics
  | volume = 71
  | issue = 10
  | pages = 1062–1074
  | publisher = AAPT
  | month = October | year = 2003
  | url = http://scitation.aip.org/getabs/servlet/GetabsServlet?prog=normal&amp;id=AJPIAS000071000010001062000001&amp;idtype=cvips&amp;gifs=Yes
  | doi = 10.1119/1.1582189
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = P. J.
  | last2 = Gallagher
  | first2 = B. L.
  | last3 = Mellor
  | first3 = C. J.
  | last4 = Baines
  | first4 = R. R.  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Lauterburg
  | first = Urs
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = LabVIEW in Physics Education
  | journal = A white paper about using LabVIEW in physics demonstration and laboratory experiments and simulations.
  | volume =
  | issue =
  | pages =
  | publisher =
  | month = June | year = 2001
  | url = http://www.lauterburg.ch/UrsLPublications/LV-PhysicsWPPrint.pdf
  | doi =
  | id =
  | accessdate =  |format=PDF}}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Drew SM
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Integration of National Instruments' LabVIEW software into the chemistry curriculum
  | journal = Journal of Chemical Education
  | volume = 73
  | issue = 12
  | pages = 1107–1111
  | publisher = ACS
  | month = December | year = 1996
  | url = http://jchemed.chem.wisc.edu/Journal/Issues/1996/Dec/abs1107.html
  | doi = 10.1021/ed073p1107
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = Steven M.  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Muyskens MA, Glass SV, Wietsma TW, Gray TM
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =

  | last2 = Glass
  | first2 = Samuel V.
  | last3 = Wietsma
  | first3 = Thomas W.
  | last4 = Gray
  | first4 = Terry M.| title = Data acquisition in the chemistry laboratory using LabVIEW software
  | journal = Journal of Chemical Education
  | volume = 73
  | issue = 12
  | pages = 1112–1114
  | publisher = ACS
  | month = December | year = 1996
  | url = http://jchemed.chem.wisc.edu/Journal/Issues/1996/Dec/abs1112.html
  | doi = 10.1021/ed073p1112
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = Mark A.  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Ogren PJ, Jones TP
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =

  | last2 = Jones
  | first2 = Thomas P.| title = Laboratory interfacing using the LabVIEW software package
  | journal = Journal of Chemical Education
  | volume = 73
  | issue = 12
  | pages = 1115–1116
  | publisher = ACS
  | month = December | year = 1996
  | url = http://jchemed.chem.wisc.edu/Journal/Issues/1996/Dec/abs1115.html
  | doi = 10.1021/ed073p1115
  | id =
  | accessdate =
  | first1 = Paul J.  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Trevelyan
  | first = J.P.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = 10 Years Experience with Remote Laboratories
  | journal = International Conference on Engineering Education Research
  | volume =
  | issue =
  | pages =
  | publisher = ACS
  | month = June | year = 2004
  | url = http://telerobot.mech.uwa.edu.au/Information/Trevelyan-INEER-2004.pdf
  |format=PDF| doi =
  | id =
  | accessdate =  }}

== External links ==
* [http://www.ni.com/labview/ Official Home Page] - The National Instruments web site for the LabVIEW product line.
** [http://zone.ni.com/reference/en-XX/help/371361G-01/ LabVIEW Help] - NI's entire set of online help documentation for LabVIEW 2010.
** [http://zone.ni.com/reference/en-XX/help/371361F-01/ LabVIEW Help] - NI's entire set of online help documentation for LabVIEW 2009.
** [http://zone.ni.com/reference/en-XX/help/371361B-01/ LabVIEW Help] - NI's entire set of online help documentation for LabVIEW 8.20.
** [http://www.ni.com/labviewzone Official LabVIEW Community Home Page] - NI's &quot;LabVIEW Zone&quot; web site.
* [http://lavag.org/ LAVA (LabVIEW Advanced Virtual Architects)] - Independent community, with discussion forums and a code repository.
* [http://www.info-labview.org Info-LabVIEW] - A LabVIEW [[electronic mailing list]]
* [http://openg.org/ OpenG] - [[Open-source]] LabVIEW utilities.
* [http://www.gangoflabview.ch/ Gang of LabVIEW] - GOOP by Reference LabVIEW OOP.
* [http://labviewwiki.org/ The LabVIEW Wiki] - A user editable LabVIEW knowledge base powered by [[MediaWiki]].
* [http://cnx.org/content/col10241/latest/ Free, online LabVIEW programming course] - This course was authored by NI, and is hosted by [[Connexions]].
* [http://www.labviewportal.eu/  International multi-language (mostly Russian and German) forum and site dedicated to LabVIEW]
* [http://itpointed.com/  ITpointed LabVIEW Forum]
* [http://www.lvug.nl/  Dutch-language based user group dedicated to LabVIEW]
{{Numerical analysis software}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Labview}}
[[Category:Numerical software]]
[[Category:Visual programming languages]]
[[Category:Numerical programming languages]]
[[Category:Linux numerical analysis software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:Pedagogic integrated development environments]]

[[bg:LabVIEW]]
[[ca:LabVIEW]]
[[de:LabVIEW]]
[[es:LabVIEW]]
[[fa:لب‌ویو]]
[[fr:LabVIEW]]
[[hy:ԼաբՎԻՈՒ]]
[[id:LabVIEW]]
[[it:LabVIEW]]
[[he:LabVIEW]]
[[kk:LabVIEW]]
[[nl:LabVIEW]]
[[ja:LabVIEW]]
[[pl:LabVIEW]]
[[pt:LabVIEW]]
[[ro:LabVIEW]]
[[ru:LabVIEW]]
[[fi:LabVIEW]]
[[sv:Labview]]
[[tr:LabVIEW]]
[[uk:LabVIEW]]
[[vi:LabVIEW]]
[[zh:LabVIEW]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
