<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="544916" ns="0" title="Project Looking Glass"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the airplane|Operation Looking Glass}}
{{For|the United States Postal Service sting operation|Jacobson v. United States}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = Project Looking Glass
| screenshot             = [[File:LG3D.jpg|250px]]&lt;br/&gt;Demonstrating existing 2D applications and a 3D CD selector demo application are coexisting inside the 3D desktop environment
| developer              = LG3D developers
| status                 = Inactive
| latest release version = 1.0.1
| latest release date    = {{release date|2007|01|29}}
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| genre                  = [[Desktop environment]]
| programming language   = [[Java (programming language)|Java]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website                = https://lg3d-core.dev.java.net
}}
'''Project Looking Glass''' is a now inactive [[free software]] project under the [[GNU General Public License|GPL]] to create an innovative [[3D computer graphics|3D]] [[desktop environment]] for [[Linux]], [[Solaris Operating System|Solaris]], and [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]. It was sponsored by [[Sun Microsystems]].

Looking Glass is programmed in the [[Java (programming language)|Java]] language using the [[Java 3D]] system to remain platform independent. Despite the use of graphics acceleration features, the desktop explores the use of 3D windowing capabilities for both existing application programs and ones specifically designed for Looking Glass.

There is a [[Live CD]] available from Project Looking Glass. The Looking Glass environment is also included on a Live DVD (FunWorks 2007 edition) from the [[Granular Linux]] project.

== History ==
Looking Glass was first developed by [[Hideya Kawahara]], a Sun [[programmer]] who wrote it in his spare time on a small [[Linux]] [[laptop]].  After demonstrating an early version to Sun executives, he was assigned to it full-time with a dedicated team and open-sourced the project.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url = http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1895,1617822,00.asp
 |title = Sun Opens Its 3-D 'Looking Glass' Linux Desktop
 |publisher = eWEEK
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was first demonstrated publicly by [[Jonathan I. Schwartz|Jonathan Schwartz]] at LinuxWorld Expo 2003 in San Francisco, and since then has gathered momentum in development.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.granularlinux.com/en/Looking_Glass Granular Linux Documentation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
After unveiling the prototype, [[Steve Jobs]] called Schwartz's office and told him that Apple would sue Sun if Sun moved forward to commercialize it.  Jobs claimed that the project is infringing Apple's [[Intellectual property|IP]].
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last = Schwartz
 |first = Jonathan
 |url = http://jonathanischwartz.wordpress.com/2010/03/09/good-artists-copy-great-artists-steal/
 |title = Good Artists Copy, Great Artists Steal
 |date = March 9, 2010
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Regardless of the threat, Sun determined that the project was not of priority and decided not to put more resource to develop it further into product quality.  The project thus had been continuing in an experimental mode. However, as Sun's financial situation became tighter and the management determined they had higher priority projects on their hand, the project became inactive (practically dead) since late 2006.
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 |last = Kawahara
 |first = Hideya
 |url = http://forums.java.net/jive/ann.jspa?annID=252
 |title = Announcement: INACTIVE (PRACTICALLY DEAD) since late 2006
 |date = September 18, 2009
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Features ==
[[File:Lg3d-ss-config-2.jpg|thumb|250px|Configuring an application using its backside of the window represented as a 3D slate in the 3D space]]

[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SMWd1FOgr18 This movie clip] well summarizes the features it implemented.

One of its most notable features is the creation of reversible [[Window (computing)|windows]]. This capability can be used for features like allowing the user to write notes and comments on the windows' backs, or displaying application dialogs without risking their being detached from the application they relate to. All windows start by looking like a normal [[2D computer graphics|2D]] or [[2.5D]] window, but can be manipulated as thin slate-like 3D objects which can be set at any angle or turned completely around by the user.

[[File:LG3D-slanted-windows.jpg|thumb|250px|Tilting all the windows to assist the user to pick up a desired window]]
Other features include tilting all the window to assist the user to pick up a desired window, provision of a panning virtual desktop, icons that reflect the live status of the window they represent and zooming of a window when it receives focus.

For more details about the features and its underlying technologies, refer to the technical document:
[http://lg3d.dev.java.net/files/documents/1833/149353/LG3D-Overview.pdf Project Looking Glass: A Comprehensive Overview of the Technology]

There are a few designs that Looking Glass implemented and appeared in other products in later years.
A technique became popular by [[Apple Inc.|Apple]]'s [[Dashboard (Mac OS)|Dashboard]] [[Widget engine|widgets]] is configuration of an application (widget) by flipping its visual and performing updates on the backside of it.
The visual of [[Apple Inc.|Apple]]'s [[Mac OS X|OS X]] [[Dock (Mac OS X)|Dock]] became similar to Looking Glass's look when [[Mac OS X Leopard|Leopard]] was released.
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 |url = http://www.engadget.com/2007/06/12/leopard-dock-resembles-suns-project-looking-glass/
 |title = Leopard dock resembles Sun's Project Looking Glass?
 |date = June 12 2007
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Microsoft Windows 7]] implements a feature for window selection that hides other windows than the one that the user placed the mouse cursor on a thumbnail above the taskbar.  It resembles Looking Glass's usage of transparency for window selection using window thumbnails on the taskbar.
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
 |url = http://www.dev.java.net/files/documents/1833/149353/LG3D-Overview.pdf
 |title = Project Looking Glass: A Comprehensive Overview of the Technology
 |date = March 14, 2006
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Similar projects ==
Looking Glass is similar to the [http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/dcr/work/TaskGallery/ TaskGallery] prototype from [[Microsoft]] Research and the open source [[Croquet project]] based on [[Squeak]] in terms of allowance for the user to manipulate applications (including existing 2D applications) in a 3D space.  However, user interaction models of TaskGallery and Croquet are base on [[Virtual Reality]]-like experience where the user moves inside the 3D space to perform tasks, whereas Looking Glass retains the operational model of today's desktop (i.e. no walking around inside the 3D space) and uses 3D effects selectively where they are thought to be effective. Also, these three are similar as they are meant to work on adapted or enhanced versions of existing desktops rather than re-designing the entire [[graphical user interface]] from scratch, an approach taken by many [[Zooming User Interface]] projects such as the one created by the late [[Jef Raskin]].

While many window managers (such as Microsoft's [[Desktop Window Manager]], the [[X Window System]] based [[Compiz]], and [[Mac OS X]] through [[Core Animation]]) can utilize 3D effects, these merely augment a conventional 2D environment.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Compiz]]
* [[Compiz Fusion]]
* [[Metisse]]
* [[Open Wonderland]]
* [[Microsoft Bob]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.sun.com/software/looking_glass/ Product home] - Official Demo Video and Animated Screenshots can be found around the bottom of the page.
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JXv8VlpoK_g#t=1m52s Official Demo Video on Youtube]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SMWd1FOgr18 Another demo movie clip on Youtube] - Without marketing speeches, but in lower quality.
* [http://lg3d.dev.java.net/files/documents/1833/149353/LG3D-Overview.pdf Project Looking Glass: A Comprehensive Overview of the Technology]
* [http://lg3d.dev.java.net/ Development home]
* [http://lg3d-livecd.dev.java.net/ LG3D Live CD]
* [http://today.java.net/pub/a/today/2004/07/06/3ddesktop.html Interview with Hideya Kawahara]

{{Sun Microsystems}}

[[Category:Free desktop environments]]
[[Category:Sun Microsystems software]]
[[Category:Java platform software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

[[de:Project Looking Glass]]
[[es:Proyecto Looking Glass]]
[[fr:LG3D]]
[[it:Project Looking Glass]]
[[nl:Project Looking Glass]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
