<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="546875" ns="0" title="Prisoners of the Sun"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Tintin book|the 1990 Australian film|Blood Oath (film)|the 2010 upcoming film|Prisoners of the Sun (film)}}
{{Graphicnovelbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; englishtitle=Prisoners of the Sun
|foreigntitle=Le Temple du Soleil
|image=Tintin cover - Prisoners of the Sun.JPG
|caption=Cover of the English edition
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=[[1949]]
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin]]''
|origdate=September 26, 1946 - April 22, 1948
|origisbn=2-203-00113-5
|transtitle=Prisoners of the Sun
|transpublisher=[[Methuen Publishing]]
|transdate=1962
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' 
|transisbn=1-4052-0625-X
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'', [[1948]]
|nextissue=''[[Land of Black Gold]]'', [[1950]]
}}
'''''Prisoners of the Sun''''' ({{lang-fr|'''Le Temple du Soleil'''}}) is the fourteenth of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a series of classic comic-strip albums written and illustrated by Belgian writer and illustrator [[Hergé]], featuring young reporter [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] as a hero. It is a continuation of ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'', and is one of very few Tintin books to directly carry on the story of the preceding title.  The two books were adapted into a [[1969]] film, ''[[Tintin and the Temple of the Sun]]'' by [[Belvision]]. It has been also adapted into two episodes of the 1990s television series ''[[The Adventures of Tintin (TV series)|The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a [[Prisoners of the Sun (video game)|video game]], and a musical stage production.

==Synopsis==
In the previous adventure, ''The Seven Crystal Balls'', [[Sanders-Hardiman Expedition Members|seven explorers]] have been afflicted with a mysterious illness after unearthing the tomb of the mummified [[Inca]], [[Rascar Capac]]. [[Professor Calculus]] has been kidnapped by a band of men including the Indian [[Chiquito (Tintin character)|Chiquito]], one of the last descendants of the Incas. Tintin and [[Captain Haddock]] discover their friend is on board the cargo ship ''Pachacamac'' bound for [[Callao]], [[Peru]] and are on a flight to rescue him.

When Tintin and Haddock intercept the ship, Tintin encounters Chiquito and learns Calculus is to be put to death for wearing the bracelet belonging to the Inca mummy. Unable to rescue Calculus, Tintin and the Captain must set off on the trail of the natives who have taken him. It leads them through the small town of Santa Clara, to the mountain town of Jauga, where a train is sabotaged in an attempt to kill them. They find both the authorities and the locals extremely unwilling to help them track Calculus' kidnappers because of the wrath of the Inca.

Tintin encounters a young Indian boy named [[Zorrino]], whom he protects from two bullying men of white descent. For that, a mysterious Indian gives Tintin a medallion, telling him it will save him from danger. Zorrino then offers to take them to the Temple of the Sun, where he claims their friend is being held prisoner by the Inca. &quot;The Inca, in these days?&quot; asks Tintin. &quot;White men not know, señor.&quot; replies Zorrino. &quot;Only you know.&quot; The Temple lies deep in the [[Andes]], and the journey there is long and eventful, involving hindrance from natives and the Captain being terrorised by local wildlife.

Finally, Tintin, Haddock, and Zorrino come upon the Temple of the Sun—and stumble right into a group of Inca who have survived until modern-day times. They are brought before the noble Prince of the Sun; on the left stands Chiquito, on the right stands [[Huascar (Tintin character)|Huascar]], the mysterious Indian Tintin encountered in Jauga. Zorrino is saved from harm when Tintin gives him Huascar's medallion, but Tintin and Haddock are sentenced to death for their sacrilegious intrusion. The Inca prince tells them they may choose the hour that the Sun himself will set alight the [[pyre]] for which they are destined.

Tintin and Haddock end up on the same pyre as Professor Calculus. Tintin has, however, chosen the hour of their death to coincide with a [[solar eclipse]], and the terrified Inca believe Tintin can command [[Pachacamac]], their god, the Sun. The Inca prince implores Tintin to make the Sun show his light again. At Tintin's command, the Sun obeys, and the three are quickly set free. 

Afterwards, the Prince of the Sun tells them the seven crystal balls used against the explorers who had excavated Rascar Capac's tomb contained a &quot;mystic liquid&quot; obtained from [[coca]], which plunged the seven explorers into a deep sleep. Each time the Inca high priest cast his spell over seven wax figures he could use them as he willed, as punishment for their sacrilege. Tintin convinces the Inca prince the explorers wished only to make known to the world the splendours of their civilisation. The Inca prince orders Huascar to destroy the wax figures and at that moment in Europe the seven explorers awaken.

After swearing on their own accord to keep the colony's existence secret, Tintin, Captain Haddock and Professor Calculus are bestowed with a gift of gold and jewels, only a sample of the treasure of the Incas for which the [[Spanish colonization of the Americas|Spanish conquerors]] searched in vain for so long. Zorrino decides to stay with the Incas; his new friends return safely to Europe.

== Publication history ==

''Prisoners of the Sun'' was the first Tintin adventure to be published in the newly-created ''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin Magazine]]'' in [[1946]]. The pages were published in a landscape design crossing two central pages rather than the standard portrait way.
The original version begins with Tintin on his way to [[Marlinspike Hall|Marlinspike]] following his visit to the hospital where he witnessed the mass panic attack of the explorers in ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]''.

In order to fit the story into 62 pages when published in book form, many scenes had to be edited out.

The edited or deleted scenes included:

*Tintin, walking to Marlinspike, is so engrossed by a newspaper report of recent events that he misses a plank of wood and falls into a river. (The story then proceeds to Haddock and Tintin setting off for the city port and on to Peru. These events were ultimately published in the book ''The Seven Crystal Balls''.)

*When Tintin meets Alcazar at the port and Chiquito on board the ship, the three men act as if the meeting at the theatre in ''The Seven Crystal Balls'' had never taken place. Those scenes had originally been published in 1943 and Hergé may have felt that readers needed more than just a reminder.

*While waiting for Zorrino near the bridge in Peru, Tintin and Haddock meet the mysterious Indian who gave Tintin the medallion. He smiles at Haddock's insults with the words &quot;Anger is bad for one's health, señor.&quot;

*While walking through the mountains, Haddock discovers a skull mounted on a pole. A terrified Zorrino says that it is a warning that he is under sentence of death for guiding foreigners to the Temple of the Sun.

*During their trek through the jungle, Tintin shoots a [[jaguar]] as it leaps towards them, and Zorrino strikes a [[snake]] with a stick when it attempts to bite Haddock.

*Haddock discovers and pockets gold in the Inca's cave behind the waterfall. He is later forced to give up the gold in order to get through the hole into the Inca tomb.

This original version was published in book form in France and Belgium in [[2003]].

==Inspiration==
The plot of the book comes largely from the 1912 novel by [[Gaston Leroux]], ''[[The Bride of the Sun]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Sadoul
  | first = Numa
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Tintin et Moi.  Entretiens avec Hergé.
  | publisher = Casterman
  | year = 1975
  | location = 
  | pages = 
  | url = 
  | doi = 
  | id = 
  | isbn = 2203017171}}

&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pachacamac]], the name of both the cargo ship and the Inca Sun god, is an ancient Peruvian temple in the vicinity where the story is set.  

The trick used by Tintin to fool the Inca into believing that he could control the Sun (involving a solar eclipse) was inspired by [[Christopher Columbus]]'s account of his own encounters with [[Arawak peoples|Arawak]] Indians in Jamaica in the early 16th century. While Columbus claimed to have performed a similar ruse, it would have been unlikely that the Inca, a civilization with considerable expertise in astronomy, would have been unaware of the true nature of an eclipse.

In addition, in [[Mark Twain]]'s ''[[A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur's Court]],'' Hank, the main character, avoids being burned at the stake in a similar manner as Tintin. He remembers that on the day he is about to be executed a solar eclipse occurred, and thus he makes the members of King Arthur's court believe he can control the sun.

==Spinoffs==
A [[Prisoners of the Sun (video game)|video game]] and an [[Tintin and the Temple of the Sun|animated film]] were made based on this book.

A [[Kuifje - De Zonnetempel (De Musical)|stage musical]] was also made and premiered in [[Antwerp]] on the 15th of September [[2001]] [http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/stage/temple.html].

==External links==
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/14prisoners.html Prisoners of the Sun] at Tintinologist.org

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Prisoners Of The Sun}}
[[Category:1949 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books]]
[[Category:Peru in fiction]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Tintin (magazine)]]
[[Category:Literature first published in serial form]]

[[ca:El Temple del Sol]]
[[de:Der Sonnentempel]]
[[es:El templo del Sol]]
[[eu:Eguzkiaren Tenplua (Tintin)]]
[[fa:معبد خورشید]]
[[fr:Le Temple du Soleil]]
[[gl:O templo do sol]]
[[hy:Արևի տաճարը]]
[[id:Di Kuil Matahari]]
[[is:Fangarnir í sólhofinu]]
[[nl:De zonnetempel]]
[[pl:Świątynia Słońca]]
[[pt:Le temple du soleil]]
[[ru:Храм Солнца (Тинтин)]]
[[fi:Auringon temppeli (Tintti-sarjakuva)]]
[[sv:Solens tempel]]
[[zh:太陽的囚徒]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
