<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="547055" ns="0" title="XFM London"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Radio station|
 name=Xfm|
 image=[[Image:Xfm London.gif]]|
 airdate= 1 September 1997|
 slogan= ''Music That Rocks&quot;|
 frequency = 104.9 [[megahertz|MHz]], RDS: &lt;code&gt;__XFM__&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br/&gt;[[Digital audio broadcasting|DAB]]&lt;br /&gt; 12A (London, Central Lancashire, Yorkshire) &lt;br/&gt; 12C (Severn Estuary)&lt;br/&gt; 11C (Birmingham, Exeter &amp; Torbay, Cambridge, Kent, Swindon, Tyne &amp; Wear)&lt;br/&gt; 12D (Berkshire &amp; North Hampshire, Coventry, Essex, Peterborough, Wiltshire)&lt;br/&gt; 11B (Cornwall, Leicester, Liverpool, Norwich, Teesside, Sussex, Wolverhampton) &lt;br/&gt; 12C (Nottingham) &lt;br/&gt;  Channel 0113 ([[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]]) &lt;br /&gt; Channel 723 [[Freesat]] &lt;br /&gt; Channel 621 (TalkTalk TV) &lt;br /&gt; Channel 965 ([[Virgin Media]]) &lt;br /&gt; Channel 923 ([[UPC Ireland]])|area=[[London]]|
 share     = 1.3%|
 share as of = August 2011|
 share source = [http://www.rajar.co.uk/listening/quarterly_listening.php]|
 format=[[Modern Rock]]|
 owner=[[Global Radio]]|
 website=[http://www.xfm.co.uk www.xfm.co.uk]
}}
'''Xfm London''' is a commercial [[radio station]] in the [[United Kingdom]] owned by [[Global Radio]] and broadcasts on 104.9 [[FM broadcasting|FM]] in [[London]], on [[Digital radio in the United Kingdom|digital radio]] via 30 [[Digital Audio Broadcasting|DAB]] multiplexes across the country, Sky, TalkTalk TV and Virgin Media.

[[Xfm]] built its reputation on playing a wide range of [[alternative music]], particularly [[indie (music)|indie]], [[hip-hop]], [[rock (music)|rock]] and a wide range of [[dance music]], but since the merger between [[GWR Radio]] and [[Capital Radio Group]], which led to the creation of its parent [[Gcap Media]], the range of music it plays has narrowed markedly and the station now focuses primarily upon commercially successful [[indie (music)|indie]].

==History==
The station's roots go back to 1989 and a pirate-turned-[[Restricted Service Licence|Restricted Service Licence (RSL)]] London station called &quot;Q102&quot;, which was famed for launching the career of [[BBC Radio 1]] DJ [[Steve Lamacq]].

Following further RSLs under the Xfm moniker, the station became full time on 1 September 1997, under the management/marketing directorship of Chris Parry and programming director/founder Sammy Jacob (who subsequently launched [[NME Radio]] in 2007). During the following year the station played a diverse range of music from its studios in [[Charlotte Street]], but mass appeal was thwarted by the lack of awareness due to a poor marketing campaign which was compounded by the [[Death of Diana, Princess of Wales|death]] of [[Diana, Princess of Wales|Princess Diana]] the day before its launch.

It was taken over by the then [[Capital Radio]] group in 1998, and on 23 August of that year was abruptly closed down for four days (during which a test tape featuring mainstream soft-rock acts was looped). The station subsequently relaunched with a vastly more mainstream format, and a new advert featuring a friendly cartoon radio saying &quot;Don't be afraid!&quot; (referring to the perceived inaccessibility of its old format). However the soft-rock revamp did not prove a success, culminating in listener-led protests outside the Capital Radio studios. Listeners also lodged objections with the radio authority, which found Xfm to be acting in a manner contrary to its licence requirements, and a degree of alternative output was eventually restored, particularly through night-time playlists and cutting-edge specialist shows.

The station found itself in hot water again the following year. Since the take-over by Capital, the station had become more male-orientated and featured [[football (soccer)|football]] coverage and &quot;laddish&quot; output. This came to an abrupt end when the Radio Authority fined Xfm £50,000 for breakfast presenter [[Tom Binns]] joking about [[bestiality]] on air. No one complained about the comedian's comments until the station re-edited his remarks and rebroadcast them for a &quot;Best of Binns&quot; compilation show.

Capital Radio set about increasing Xfm's listening figures, recruiting famous DJs such as [[Zoë Ball]], former [[BBC Radio 1]] presenter [[Kevin Greening]], and re-recruiting comedians [[Ricky Gervais]] and [[Stephen Merchant]] who took voluntary redundancy when [[Capital Radio]] bought the station, after the pair rose to fame with the first airing of [[The Office]].  This yielded good results for the station in a period in which it could boast growing listening figures and talent such as [[Zane Lowe]] and [[Christian O'Connell]]. The music was still tightly a playlisted mix of popular indie and soft rock, not what the original station set out to do, and this continues to the present day.

In May 2007, as an attempt to cut costs, the parent company of XFM, [[GCap Media]] (now [[Global Radio]]) announced that they would be removing all presenters from the daytime (10am-4pm) lineup and replacing them with a jukebox based upon listener requests through their websites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.radiotoday.co.uk/news.php?extend.1967 | title = Radio Today: XFM drops daytime jocks | accessdate = 2007-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has since been reversed and new presenters have been hired and networked across the stations.&lt;ref name=&quot;radiotoday.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://radiotoday.co.uk/news.php?extend.3134.2 | title = Radio Today: DJs return to Xfm daytime | accessdate = 2008-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 March 2008 an announcement was made to reverse the decision to remove daytime presenters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.musicweek.com/story.asp?sectioncode=1&amp;storycode=1033420&amp;c=1 | title = Music Week - Xfm brings back daytime DJs | accessdate = 2008-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; From Tuesday 25 March 2008 a new schedule restoring daytime schedules was put in place.&lt;ref name=&quot;radiotoday.co.uk&quot; /&gt;

A new schedule was launched on the 12 January 2009. Changes at this date included the returning Ian Camfield taking over the ''Afternoon Show, including Afternoon X List'' from [[Jo Good]], and new signing [[Richard Skinner]] taking over the ''Morning Show'' from [[Rick Shaw]]. The times of the shows were also adjusted, with the morning show only becoming an 2 hour show (previously an 3 hour show) and the afternoon show becoming a 4 hour show (previously a 3 hour show). The weekend schedule was also adjusted at this time, with [[Rick Shaw]] moving to present the ''Weekend Morning Show'' on a Saturday and Sunday from 10 am - 2 pm. This led to other changes in the weekend schedule,  such as [[Marsha Shandur]]'' Sunday Brunch'' ending, and the air times of [[Marc Haynes]] ''Certificate X'' changing (from 1 pm - 3 pm to 6 pm - 8 pm). [[Jo Good]] left the station during these changes.

In January 2010 it was announced that Ian Camfield was to swap timeslots with [[Dave Berry]]. Dave remained on Breakfast until May 2011 when he announced his resignation. This was followed by a period of months in which Ian Camfield covered breakfast while new signing Eoghan McDermott took over drivetime. On July 4th it was revealed that [[Danny Wallace]] was to start as the new Breakfast presenter from August 1st&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2011/jul/04/yes-man-danny-wallace-joins-xfm | title = Yes Man author Danny Wallace joins Xfm London as breakfast host | accessdate = 2011-07-04 | work=The Guardian | first=Jason | last=Deans | date=4 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2011 the XFM schedule had a reshuffle with Ian Camfield moving to networked mid-mornings, Eoghan Mcdermott to a new networked drivetime slot and [[Mary Anne Hobbs]] moving to a re-launched evening show 'Music:Response', . The new local afternoon slot will be hosted by Dan O'Connell with [[Richard Skinner]] leaving the station after two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;radiotoday.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://radiotoday.co.uk/2011/08/hobbs-goes-nightly-in-xfm-shuffle/?utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;utm_medium=facebook&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+radiotoday+%28Radio+Today+-+News%29&amp;utm_content=FaceBook | title = to Hobbs goes nightly in Xfm shuffle | accessdate = 2011-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Former Magazine==
''X-Ray'' was Xfm's short lived sister publication. Initially a free quarterly magazine, it later changed format and became commercially available. The magazine was issued monthly, in an unusually small format, now associated with &quot;[[handbag]] size&quot; women's magazines and came bundled with a CD demoing various signed and unsigned artists. After what seemed like a dispute with the publishers, the magazine went out of print, although Xfm still offer readers reassurance of its return on their website. [http://www.xfm.co.uk/xray]

==Programming==

{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
===Monday - Friday===
*0200 - 0630 Overnights with Rich Walters
*0630 - 1000 The XFM Breakfast Show with [[Danny Wallace (humourist)|Danny Wallace]]
*1000 - 1400 Ian Camfield  
*1400 - 1700 Dan O'Connell
*1700 - 2000 Drivetime with Eoghan McDermott  
*2000 - 2300 Music:Response with [[Mary Anne Hobbs]]  
*2300 - 0200 Xposure with John Kennedy

===Friday Variants===
*2000 - 2200: Import:Export with [[KROQ-FM]]
*2200 - 0200: The Remix with [[Eddy Temple Morris]]
{{col-2}}

===Saturday===
*0200 – 0800: Overnights with Shak
*0800 – 1200: Rick Shaw
*1200 – 1500: Re-Fried Breakfast with [[Danny Wallace (humourist)|Danny Wallace]]
*1500 – 1800: Steve Harris
*1800 – 1900: The [[Mix Master Mike]] Show
*1900 – 2200: [[Mary Anne Hobbs]]
*2200 - 0200: The Remix Reloaded with [[Eddy Temple Morris]]

===Monday Variants===
*0000 - 0200: The Remix with [[Eddy Temple Morris]]
{{col-end}}

{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}

===Sunday===
*0200 – 0800: Overnights with Shak
*0800 – 1200: Rick Shaw
*1200 – 1500: Smart on Sunday with [[Gordon Smart]]
*1500 – 1800: Steve Harris
*1800 – 2200: The Weekender with Sunta Templeton
*2200 – 0000: The XFM Rock Show with Ian Camfield

{{col-end}}
Xfm London airs 43 hours of exclusive London only programmes (per week), and the rest shared with [[XFM Manchester]].

==Notable Former Xfm presenters==
{{div col|colwidth=15em}}
* [[Alex Zane]]
* [[Rick Edwards]]
* [[Russell Brand]]
* [[Adam Buxton|Adam]] and [[Joe Cornish (comedian)|Joe]]
* [[Jimmy Carr]]
* [[Bob Geldof]]
* [[Paul Tonkinson]]
* [[Jane Gazzo]]
* [[Christian O'Connell]]
* [[Arthur Baker (musician)|Arthur Baker]]
[[Alex_Lowe_(actor)|* [Alex Lowe (actor)]]]
* [[Jo Good]]
* [[DJ Greenpeace]]
* [[Kevin Greening]]
* [[Ricky Gervais]]
* [[Stephen Merchant]]
* [[Karl Pilkington]]
* [[Zoë Ball]]
* [[Dermot O'Leary]]
* [[Zane Lowe]]
* [[Lauren Laverne]]
* [[Phil Clifton]]
* [[Simon Amstell]]
* Katie Parsons
* [[Guy Garvey]]
* [[Iain Baker (DJ)|Iain Baker]]
* [[Nick Luscombe]]
* [[Shaun Keaveny]]
* [[Iain Lee]]
* [[Claire Sturgess]]
* [[James Hyman]]
* [[Tom Binns]]
* [[Steven Taylor|Steve Taylor]]
* [[Martin Bate]]
* [[Jon Hillcock]]
* [[Johnny Borrell]]
* Adrian Gibson
* [[Marsha Shandur]]
* [[Richard Skinner (broadcaster)| Richard Skinner]]
{{div col end}}

==See also==
*[[List of radio stations in the United Kingdom]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.xfm.co.uk Official site]
* [http://www.mediauk.com/the_knowledge/i.muk/XFM Detailed account of Xfm's history from Media UK's ''The Knowledge'' wiki]
{{GCap Media}}
{{London radio}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Xfm London}}
[[Category:Former pirate radio stations]]
[[Category:GCap Media]]
[[Category:Modern rock radio stations]]
[[Category:Radio stations in London]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
