<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="54933" ns="0" title="The Red Sea Sharks"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Graphicnovelbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; 
englishtitle=The Red Sea Sharks
|foreigntitle=Coke en stock
|image=Tintin Cover - The Red Sea Sharks.JPG
|caption=Cover of the English edition
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=[[1958]]
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin]]''
|origdate=October 31, 1956 - January 1, 1958
|origisbn=2-203-00118-6
|transtitle=The Red Sea Sharks
|transpublisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]]
|transdate=1960
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' 
|transisbn=0-316-35848-7
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[The Calculus Affair]]'', [[1956]]
|nextissue=''[[Tintin in Tibet]]'', [[1960]]
}}

'''''The Red Sea Sharks''''' is the nineteenth of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a series of classic comic-strip albums written and illustrated by [[Hergé]], featuring young reporter [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] as a hero. Its original French title is '''''Coke en stock''''' (&quot;[[coke (fuel)|coke]] in stock&quot;) a codename used by the villainous antagonists of the story for [[Africa]]n slaves.

''The Red Sea Sharks'' is notable for bringing together a large number of characters from previous Tintin adventures, going all the way back to ''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'':

*[[General Alcazar]] (''[[The Broken Ear]]'' and ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'');
*[[Emir]] [[Ben Kalish Ezab and Abdullah]] (''[[Land of Black Gold]]'');
*[[Rastapopoulos]] (''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'' and ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'');
*[[Oliveira da Figueira]] (''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'' and ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'');
*[[Dr. J.W. Müller|Doctor Müller]] (''[[The Black Island]]'' and ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'');
*Dawson (''[[The Blue Lotus]]'');
*[[Allan Thompson]] (''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'' and ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]'');
*[[Bianca Castafiore]] (''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'', ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'' and ''[[The Calculus Affair]]'');
*[[Jolyon Wagg]] (''[[The Calculus Affair]]'').

Additionally, Patrash Pasha (''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]''), [[Sheikh]] [[Bab El Ehr]] (''[[Land of Black Gold]]'') and General Tapioca (referred to in ''[[The Broken Ear]]'' and appearing later in ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'') are all referred to but don't appear.

==Storyline==
''The Red Sea Sharks'' is an adventure in which Tintin investigates the supporters of [[Sheikh]] [[Bab El Ehr]]'s overthrow of [[Ben Kalish Ezab and Abdullah|Mohammed Ben Kalish Ezab]], the [[Emir]] of Khemed.

After watching a movie, Tintin and Captain Haddock round a corner and bump into [[General Alcazar]], who drops his [[wallet]]. Tintin attempts to return it, but the [[hotel]] he claimed to be staying at has never heard of him, and when Tintin calls a phone number found in his wallet, the man refuses to talk to him. When Tintin and Haddock return home, they discover that the Emir's bratty, incorrigibly spoiled son [[Ben Kalish Ezab and Abdullah|Abdullah]] has been sent there for protection, along with a colorful entourage of servants and dignitaries who have established a [[bedouin]]-bivouac in the great hall of [[Marlinspike Hall]]. Abdullah proceeds to cause chaos at Marlinspike with his practical jokes.

[[Thomson and Thompson]] inform Tintin that they know of his meeting with Alcazar due to their investigation of an arms dealer called Dawson. They then tell him the name of the real hotel where the General is staying. At the hotel, Tintin and Haddock see Alcazar talking with Dawson, whom Tintin recognises as the corrupt police chief of the international settlement in the blue lotus who he exposed and sent to prison guilty of mingling with opium dealers.

Haddock returns the wallet to Alcazar, while Tintin follows Dawson and overhears him discussing how successful his sale of [[de Havilland Mosquito]]es were in starting a [[coup d'état]] in Khemed. Tintin decides to go to Khemed and rescue the emir, who has been overthrown by [[Sheikh]] [[Bab El Ehr]]. Reluctantly, as usual, the Captain agrees to go along, partly because he knows it is his only chance of getting rid of Abdullah, whose practical jokes are getting too much for him. Meanwhile, Dawson, realizing that Tintin is once again meddling in his affairs, resolves to take drastic measures.

At Wadesdah Airport in Khemed, Tintin and Haddock are turned back by customs, while someone (presumably an agent of Dawson) plants a bomb on the plane to &quot;take care of them&quot;. The bombing is [[Deus Ex Machina|foiled by an engine fire]], which forces the plane to crash-land minutes before the bomb goes off. Realizing that they best take a lower profile, Tintin and Haddock walk away from the crash site and slip in unobserved at night into Wadesdah. There they meet another old friend, the loquacious [[Portugal|Portuguese]] merchant [[Oliveira da Figueira]]. He helps them escape the city by dressing up as [[burqa|veil]]-wearing women. Once outside they meet a guide with horses and ride to the Emir's hideout (modelled on the ancient [[Jordan]]ian city of [[Petra]]). 

Their escape is reported however, and a leading figure in the new regime sends out a squad of armored cars and Mosquitoes to intercept them. The officer, Mull Pasha, is in fact [[Dr. J.W. Müller|Doctor Müller]], an enemy whom Tintin fought against in ''[[The Black Island]]'' and ''[[Land of Black Gold]]''. Thanks to a military misinterpretation, the Mosquitoes attack their own armored cars instead of Tintin and his friends. 

The Emir tells them about the ongoing [[slave trade]] run by the [[Rastapopoulos|Marquis di Gorgonzola]], an international businessman with whom the Emir had a tiff several months ago. The Marquis uses the [[Hajj|pilgrimage to Mecca]] to capture and enslave [[Islam in Africa|African Muslim]] travellers. Tintin and Haddock leave for the [[Red Sea]] coast and board a boat for Mecca to investigate. They are attacked by the Mosquitoes again, but Tintin manages to down one with a German [[StG 44]]. But their schooner receives critical damage and they end up shipwrecked aboard a raft, along with [[Piotr Skut]], the pilot of the downed plane. They are then picked up by di Gorgonzola's yacht, the ''Scheherazade'' (named after the [[Scheherazade|Arab princess]] and storyteller of ''[[One Thousand and One Nights]]''), which happens to pass by, but di Gorgonzola isolates them from his guests and offloads them the next night to the SS ''Ramona'', a [[tramp steamer]]. Unbeknownst to Tintin and Haddock, the Ramona is one of di Gorgonzola's own ships, used in the slave trade.

That night they are locked into their cabin by [[Allan Thompson|Allan]], Haddock's [[The Crab with the Golden Claws|former first mate]], who commands the ''Ramona''. A fire breaks out on the ''Ramona'' and the crew abandons ship. Tintin and Haddock force their cabin door open and manage to put out the fire, not realizing that the front of the ship was loaded with munitions. They then free a number of black African men,who speak [[Yoruba language|Yoruba]], from a rear hold and discover that they had paid for the voyage to [[Mecca]], but were intended to be sold as slaves instead. Haddock attempts to explain the situation to them. Initially, many of them don't understand, or refuse to, stubbornly insisting on still going to Mecca. After some discussion, the men come around: an older member of the group recalls how some men from his village never returned from the ''[[Hajj]]''. The Africans agree to help Haddock sail the ship to neutral territory in [[Djibouti]], while Tintin and Skut attempt to fix the radio, which had been smashed.

Tintin finds a slip of paper in the radio room with an order to deliver &quot;coke&quot;, and is puzzled. In shipping, &quot;[[coke (fuel)|coke]]&quot; would normally refer to a [[coal]]-derived fuel, but none is being carried.&lt;ref&gt;The story predates the use of &quot;coke&quot; to mean &quot;[[cocaine]]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; They are then approached by a [[dhow]] and take aboard an [[Arab]] who wishes to inspect the [[coke (fuel)|coke]], puzzling Haddock, who claims they have none. The man then turns about and starts examining the physical strength of one of the [[Africans]]. With the nature of the term coke, a codename for slaves, clear to him now, Haddock furiously confronts the Arab. The inspected [[Black African]] manages to thwart the Arab's attempt to stab the Captain, and the slaver is ordered away from the ship, the outraged Haddock yelling insults to him until he is out of earshot, even from a [[megaphone]].

Di Gorgonzola (who is actually [[Rastapopoulos]], a member of the international [[opium]] smugglers from ''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'' and ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'') finds out from the Arab that Haddock has taken control of the ship, and sends a [[Type VII U-Boat]] to attack them. Tintin spots the submarine by accident just prior to attack because of its periscope sticking out. Haddock manages to outmaneuver a number of [[torpedo]]es, but all appears lost when the engines of the ship get stuck in half reverse. At this point the ''Ramona'' is saved by the arrival of combat aircraft from a nearby US Navy cruiser, the [[USS Los Angeles (CA-135)|USS ''Los Angeles'']], whose crew had been radioed by Tintin. The submarine makes one more attempt to destroy the ''Ramona'' by attaching a [[limpet mine]] to the front of the boat beside the explosives, but this is foiled when the diver is hit by the ''Ramona'''s anchor. A shark swallows the mine and swims away, exploding some time afterwards.

When the ''Los Angeles'' attempts to arrest di Gorgonzola afterwords, he fakes his own death by allowing a motorboat which he steers from his yacht to the cruiser to sink while he escapes in an inbuilt mini-submarine. Thinking him dead, Tintin, Haddock and Skut return to Europe to international renown for their efforts in exposing the slave traders. Soon afterwards, the Emir recaptures control of Khemed and recalls Abdullah home. Tintin and the Captain return home to find [[Nestor (Tintin character)|Nestor]] emaciated from Abdullah's stay and an exploding firework in the Captain's chair as a parting gift. And no sooner have they got rid of one pest when another arrives - [[Jolyon Wagg]].

==Notes==
*When Haddock falls asleep in the desert and won't wake up, Tintin takes a flask of [[rum]] from out of his bag. This wakes Haddock up and, after drinking the lot, he agrees to press on. Tintin remarks that the rum is for &quot;emergencies&quot; &amp;mdash; but it is not specified if it is for [[medicinal]] purposes or getting Haddock to co-operate. Tintin, on occasion, does use alcohol to invigorate Haddock's morale and bring him round to his way of thinking in ''[[The Shooting Star]]'' and ''[[Tintin in Tibet]]''.

*When Tintin asks Senhor [[oliveira de Figueira|Oliveira]] about why the Emir got angry with Arabair, Oliveira stumbles a bit, probably hiding the rather embarrassing reason. It turns out that Abdullah wanted to see the Arabair planes loop-the-loop before landing and Arabair refused for reasons that Abdullah's naive father, the Emir, saw as trivial. This prompted him to threaten to end Arabair's use of the flight path and expose their involvement in the slave trade. Tintin resolves to bring Arabair down anyway because of its involvement in slave trading.

*The character Mull Pasha that is played by [[Dr. J. W. Müller]] is loosely based on the real life European military leader who served on one Middle country: [[John Bagot Glubb]] also known as &quot;Glubb Pasha&quot; who led the [[Arab Legion]] in [[Jordan]].

==Alleged racism==
''The Red Sea Sharks'' has been criticised for stereotypical portrayal of Africans; although obviously good-hearted, the black characters are shown as being somewhat simple. However, it should also be noted that foreign Europeans, throughout the Tintin series, also display a similarly ungrammatical accents (e.g. Skut). Others have criticised Haddock's calling them &quot;addle-pated lumps of anthracite,&quot; but Hergé did not intend to be racist - Captain Haddock is well known for his frequently colourful language, which comprises [http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/lists/curses.html almost 200 insults in total]. Hergé obviously had a strong contempt for slavery, as evidenced by strongly negative emphasis placed on the villainy of slave traders (supplemented by the scene in which Captain Haddock hurls his peculiar brand of expletives at a slaver leaving their ship).

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/19redsea.html The Red Sea Sharks] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Red Sea Sharks, The}}
[[Category:1958 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books]]
[[Category:Middle East in fiction]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Tintin (magazine)]]
[[Category:Literature first published in serial form]]

[[ca:Stoc de coc]]
[[cs:Koks na palubě]]
[[de:Kohle an Bord]]
[[es:Stock de coque]]
[[fa:کوسه‌های دریای سرخ]]
[[fr:Coke en stock]]
[[gl:Stock de coque]]
[[id:Petualangan Tintin, Laut Merah]]
[[nl:Cokes in voorraad]]
[[pl:Koks w ładowni]]
[[pt:Coke en stock]]
[[fi:Seikkailu Punaisella merellä]]
[[sv:Koks i lasten]]
[[tr:Ambardaki Kömür]]
[[zh:紅海鯊魚]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
