<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="55494" ns="0" title="Bábism"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Room-bab.jpg|thumb|200px|The room where The Báb declared his mission on 23 May 1844, in his house in Shiraz.]]
'''The Babi Faith''' ({{lang-fa|بابی ها}} ''{{transl|Bahai|Bábí há}}'' ) is a religious movement that flourished in [[Persian Empire|Persia]] from 1844 to 1852, then lingered on in exile in the [[Ottoman Empire]] (especially [[Cyprus]]) as well as underground.  Its founder was '''Siyyid `Alí Muhammad Shirazi''', who [[Persian names|took the title]] [[Báb]]—meaning &quot;Gate&quot;—from a [[Shi'a Islam|Shi'a]] theological term.  Unlike other Islamic messianic movements, the Bábí movement signalled a break with [[Islam]] and attempted to start a new religious system. While the Bábí movement was violently opposed and crushed by the clerical and government establishments in the country in the mid 1850s, the Bábí movement led to the founding of the [[Bahá'í Faith]] which sees the religion brought by the Báb as a predecessor to their own religion, and gives a renewed significance to the Bábí movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_babism&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |encyclopedia= Encyclopædia Iranica |year= 1989 |article=Babism | first = Dennis | last = MacEoin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Antecedents==
Within [[Shi'a Islam]] exists a large group known as the [[Twelvers]] who regard the twelfth [[Imam]] as the last of the Imams.&lt;ref name=&quot;oneworld&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Shi'ism |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |pages= 312–313}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They contend that the [[Muhammad al-Mahdi|twelfth Imám]] went into concealment or occultation in 874 AD, at which time communication between the Hidden Imam and the people could only be performed through mediators called Bábs (gates) or Na'ibs (representatives).&lt;ref name=&quot;saiedi&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Gate of the Heart | first = Nader | last = Saiedi | publisher = Wilfrid Laurier University Press | location = Waterloo, ON | page = 15 | isbn = 978-1-55458-035-4 | year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 940 AD, the fourth of the representatives claimed that the Hidden Imam had gone into an indefinite &quot;Grand Occultation&quot;, and that he would cease to communicate with the people.  According to Twelver belief, the Hidden Imam is alive in the world, but in concealment from his enemies, and that he would only emerge shortly before the [[Day of Judgement]].  At that time, acting as the [[Al-Qa'im (person)|Qá'im]] (He who will arise), also known as the [[Mahdi]] (He who is rightly guided), the Hidden Imam would start a holy war against evil, would defeat the unbelievers, and would start a reign of justice.&lt;ref name=&quot;saiedi&quot;/&gt;

In 1830s in Persia, [[Sayyid Kazim Rashti]] was the leader of the [[Shaykhism|Shaykhis]], a sect of Shi'a Islam. The Shaykhis were a group expecting the imminent appearance of the [[Al-Qa'im (person)|Qá'im]]. At Siyyid Kázim's death in 1843, he had counselled his followers to leave their homes to seek the Lord of the Age whose advent would soon break on the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Islam | year = 1999 | article = Bāb | publisher = Koninklijke Brill NV | location = Leiden, The Netherlands | first = A.| last = Bausani}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin==
On 22 May,&lt;ref name=&quot;dawn&quot;&gt;{{cite book  |first=R. |last=Mehrabkhani |year= 1987 |title=Mullá Ḥusayn: Disciple at Dawn |publisher=Kalimat Press |location=Los Angeles, CA, USA |isbn=0933770375 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=wDYnPNwuwtcC&amp;pg=PA121&amp;lpg=PA121 | pages = 58–73}}&lt;/ref&gt;  1844 [[Mullá Husayn]] of [[Boshruyeh]] in [[Greater Khorasan|Khorasan]], a prominent disciple of Siyyid Kázim, entered [[Shiraz, Iran|Shiraz]] following the instruction by his master to search for the promised Qa'im.  Soon after he arrived in Shiraz, Mullá Husayn came into contact with the Báb.  On the night of 22 May 1844 Mullá Husayn was invited by the Báb to his home; on that night Mullá Husayn told him that he was searching for the possible successor to Siyyid Kázim, the Promised One, and the Báb told Mullá Husayn privately that he was Siyyid Kázim's successor and the bearer of divine knowledge.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_bab&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |encyclopedia= Encyclopædia Iranica |year= 1989 |article=Bāb, Sayyed `Ali Mohammad Sirazi | first = Dennis | last = MacEoin}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through the night of the 22nd to dawn of the 23rd, Mullá Husayn became the first to accept the Báb's claims as the gateway to Truth and the initiator of a new prophetic cycle;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;iranica_bab&quot;/&gt; the Báb had replied in a satisfactory way to all of Mullá Husayn's questions and had written in his presence, with extreme rapidity, a long commentary of [[Yusuf (sura)|Surih of Joseph]], which has come to be known as the [[Selections from the Writings of the Báb#Qayyúmu'l-Asmá'|Qayyúmu'l-Asmá']] and is considered the Báb's first revealed work.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot; /&gt; After Mullá Husayn accepted the Báb's claim, the Báb ordered him to wait until 17 others had independently recognized the station of the Báb before they could begin teaching others about the new revelation.

Within five months, seventeen other disciples of Siyyid Káẓim had independently recognized the Báb as a Manifestation of God.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = The Time of the Báb | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/bahai/history/bab_2.shtml | publisher = [[BBC]] | accessdate = 2006-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among them was one woman, Zarrín Táj Bara&lt;u&gt;gh&lt;/u&gt;áni, a poetess, who later received the name of [[Táhirih]] (the Pure). These 18 disciples were later to be known as the [[Letters of the Living]] and were given the task of spreading the new faith across Iran and Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_bab&quot; /&gt; The Báb emphasized the spiritual station of these 18 individuals, who along with himself, made the first &quot;Unity&quot; of his religion&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat191&quot;&gt;Amanat, ''Resurrection and Renewal'', 191.&lt;/ref&gt;

After his declaration Siyyid `Alí-Muhammad soon assumed the title of the Báb.  Within a few years the movement spread all over Iran, causing controversy.  His claim was at first understood by some of the public at the time to be merely a reference to the Gate of the Hidden Imám of Muhammad, but this understanding he publicly disclaimed.  He later proclaimed himself, in the presence of the Heir to the Throne of Persia and other notables, to be the Promised One or [[Al-Qa'im (person)|Qá'im]] to Shí'a Muslims. In the Báb's writings, the Báb appears to identify himself as the gate (báb) to the [[Muhammad al-Mahdi|Hidden Twelfth Imam]], and later he begins to explicitly proclaim his station as that of the Hidden Imam and a new messenger from God.&lt;ref name=&quot;saiedi19&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Gate of the Heart | first = Nader | last = Saiedi | publisher = Wilfrid Laurier University Press | location = Waterloo, ON | page = 19 | isbn = 978-1-55458-035-4 | year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Saiedi states the exalted identity the Báb was claiming was unmistakable, but due to the reception of the people, his writings appear to convey the impression that he is only the gate to the Hidden Twelfth Imam.&lt;ref name=&quot;saiedi19&quot;/&gt; To his circle of early believers, the Báb was equivocal about his exact status, gradually confiding in them that he was not merely a gate to the Hidden Imam, but the Manifestation of the Hidden Imam and the [[Al-Qa'im (person)|Qa'im]] himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoA&quot;&gt;{{cite book | chapter = Resurgence of Apocalyptic in Modern Islam | first = Abbas | last = Amanat | editor = Stein, Stephen J. | title = The Encyclopedia of Apocalypticism, vol. III: Apocalypticism in the Modern Period and the Contemporary Age. | location = New York | publisher = Continuum | year = 2000 | pages = 241–242 | isbn = 0826412556}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his early meetings with [[Mullá Husayn]], the Báb described himself as the Master and the Promised One; he did not consider himself just [[Sayyid Kazim Rashti|Siyyid Kazim's]] successor, but claimed a prophetic status, with a sense of deputyship delegated to him not just from the Hidden Imam, but from Divine authority;&lt;ref&gt;Amanat, Resurrection and Renewal, 171.&lt;/ref&gt; His early texts, such as the Commentary on the Surih of Joseph, used Quranic language that implied divine authority and identified himself effectively with the Imam.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_bab&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat230&quot;&gt;Amanat, ''Resurrection and Renewal'', 230-31.&lt;/ref&gt; When Mullá `Alí Basṭámí, the second Letter of the Living, was put on trial in [[Baghdad]] for preaching about the Báb, the clerics studied the [[Selections from the Writings of the Báb#Qayyúmu'l-Asmá'|Commentary on the Surih of Joseph]], recognized in it a claim to divine revelation, and quoted from it extensively to prove that the author had made a messianic claim.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat230&quot; /&gt;

==Spread==
The Báb's message was disseminated by the ''Letters of the Living'' through Iran and southern [[Iraq]].  After some time, preaching by the Letters of the Living led to opposition by the Islamic clergy, prompting the Governor of Shiraz to order the Báb's arrest.  The Báb, upon hearing of the arrest order, left [[Bushehr]] for Shiraz in June 1845 and presented himself to the authorities. He was placed under house arrest at the home of his uncle, and was restricted in his personal activities, until a cholera epidemic broke out in the city in September 1846.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_bab&quot; /&gt; The Báb was released and departed for [[Isfahan (city)|Isfahan]]. There, many came to see him at the house of the imám jum'ih, head of the local clergy, who became sympathetic. After an informal gathering where the Báb debated the local clergy and displayed his speed in producing instantaneous verses, his popularity soared.&lt;ref&gt;Amanat, ''Resurrection and Renewal'', 257.&lt;/ref&gt;  After the death of the Governor of Isfahan, who had become his supporter, pressure from the clergy of the province led to the Shah, [[Mohammad Shah Qajar]], ordering the Báb to [[Tehran]] in January, 1847.&lt;ref&gt;Amanat, ''Resurrection and Renewal'', 258.&lt;/ref&gt; After spending several months in a camp outside Tehran, and before the Báb could meet the Shah, the Prime Minister sent the Báb to [[Tabriz]] in the northwestern corner of the country, and later [[Maku, Iran|Maku]] and [[Chihriq]], where he was confined.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_bab&quot; /&gt; During his confinement, the communication between him and his followers was not completely severed, but was quite difficult, and he was not able to elucidate his teachings to the public.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_babism&quot; /&gt; Thus much of the Bábí teachings were spread by his followers, and led to their persecution.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica_babism&quot; /&gt;

One of the most important events of the Bábí movement was a [[Conference of Badasht|conference held in Badasht]] in 1848 where the split from [[Islam]] and [[Sharia|Islamic law]] was made clear.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt; Three key individuals who attended the conference were [[Bahá'u'lláh]], [[Quddús]], and [[Táhirih]].  Táhirih, during the conference, was able to persuade many of the others about the Bábí split with Islam. She appeared at least once during the conference in public without a [[chador|veil]], heresy within the Islamic world of that day, signalling the split.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt;  During the same month the Báb was brought [[Báb#Trial|to trial]] in Tabriz and made his claim to be the [[Mahdi]] public to the Crown Prince and the Shi'a clergy.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Báb |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |pages= 55–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several sources agree that by 1848 or 1850 there were 100,000 converts to Babism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Smith | first = Peter | title = Research Note; A note on Babi and Baha'i Numbers in Iran | journal = Iranian Studies | volume = 17 | issue = 2–03 | pages = 295–301 | publisher =  International Society for Iranian Studies | date = Spring-Summer 1984 | jstor = 4310446| doi =10.1080/00210868408701633  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uprisings and massacres==
By 1848 the increased fervour of the Bábís and the clerical opposition had led to a number of confrontations between the Bábís and their government and clerical establishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith&quot;/&gt;  After the death of [[Mohammad Shah Qajar]], the shah of Iran, a series of armed struggles and uprisings broke out in the country, including at Tabarsi.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith&quot;/&gt; These confrontations all resulted in Bábí massacres; Bahá'í authors give an estimate of 20,000 Bábís killed from 1844 to present, with most of the deaths occurring during the first 20 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;MacEoin 1983 pp. 219–55&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal  | last = MacEoin  | first = Denis  | authorlink = Denis MacEoin  | title = From Babism to Baha'ism: Problems of Militancy, Quietism, and Conflation in the Construction of a Religion  | journal = Religion  | volume = 13  | issue = 1983  | pages = pp. 219–55  | publisher =   | year = 1983  | url = http://bahai-library.com/maceoin_babism_militancy| doi =   10.1016/0048-721X(83)90022-2   | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Professor of Islamic Studies [[Denis MacEoin]] studied documented deaths, both for individuals and for round figures, from Bábí, Bahá'í, European, and Iranian sources, and confirmed at most two to three thousand.&lt;ref name=&quot;MacEoin 1983 pp. 219–55&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MacEoin 1983 pp. 68–72&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal  | last = MacEoin  | first = Denis  | authorlink = Denis MacEoin  | title = A Note on the Numbers of Babi and Baha'i Martyrs  | journal = Baha'i Studies Bulletin  | volume = 02  | issue = 3–1983  | pages = pp. 68–72  | publisher =   | year = 1983  | url =   | doi =      | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MacEoin 1983 pp. 84–88&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal  | last = MacEoin  | first = Denis  | authorlink = Denis MacEoin  | title = A Note on the Numbers of Babi and Baha'i Martyrs in Iran  | journal = Baha'i Studies Bulletin  | volume = 02  | issue = 2–1983  | pages = pp.  84–88  | publisher =   | year = 1983  | url =   | doi =      | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt; He stated that he could not find evidence for any higher figures.&lt;ref name=&quot;MacEoin 1983 pp. 68–72&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MacEoin 1983 pp. 84–88&quot;/&gt; Supporters of the Bábís paint their struggle as basically defensive in nature; Shi'i writers on the other hand point to this period as proof of the subversive nature of Bábísm. MacEoin has pointed out that the Bábís did arm themselves, upon the Báb's instructions, and originally intended an uprising, but that their eventual clashes with state forces were defensive, and not considered an offensive jihad. In mid 1850 a new prime-minister, [[Amir Kabir]], was convinced that the Bábí movement was a threat and ordered the [[execution of the Báb]] which was followed by the killings of many Bábís.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Shaykhtabarsi 2008.jpg|right|thumb|upright=1|Shrine of Shaykh Ṭabarsí&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]

===Fort Tabarsi===
{{Main|Shaykh Tabarsi}}
Of the conflicts between the Bábís and the establishment, the first and best known took place in [[Mázandarán]], at the remote shrine of [[Shaykh Tabarsí]], about 22 kilometres southeast of Bárfarúsh ([[Babol]]). From October 1848 until May 1849, around 300 Bábís (later rising to 600), led by Mullá Muhammad ‘Alí of Bárfarúsh, surnamed [[Quddús]], and [[Mullá Husayn|Mullá Husayn-i-Bushru'i]], defended themselves against the attacks of local villagers and members of the shah's army under the command of Prince Mihdí Qulí Mirzá.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith2&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Tabarsi, Shaykh |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |page= 331}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were, after being weakened through attrition and starvation, subdued through false promises of safety, and put to death or sold into slavery.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith2&quot;/&gt;

===Zanjan upheaval===
The revolt at the fortress of 'Ali Mardan Khan in [[Zanjan province|Zanjan]] in the north-west of Persia, was by far the most violent of all the conflicts. It was headed by Mulla Muhammad-‘Aliy-i-Zanjani, surnamed [[Hujjat]], and also lasted seven or eight months (May 1850–January 1851).  The Bábí community in the city had swelled to around 3000 after the conversion of one of the town's religious leaders to the Bábí movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith3&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Zanjan |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |pages= 368–369}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict was preceded by years of growing tension between the leading Islamic clergy and the new rising Bábí leadership. The city governor ordered that the city be divided into two sectors, with hostilities starting soon thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith3&quot;/&gt; The Bábís faced resistance against a large number of regular troops, and led to the death of several thousand Bábís.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith3&quot;/&gt; After Hujjat was killed, and the Bábí numbers being greatly reduced, the Bábís surrendered in January 1851 and were massacred by the army.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith3&quot;/&gt;

===Nayriz upheaval===
Meanwhile a serious but less protracted struggle was waged against the government at [[Nayriz]] in [[Fars (province)|Fars]] by [[Vahid Darabi|Aga Siyyid Yahyá]], surnamed Vahid, of Nayriz.  Vahid had converted around 1,500 people in the community, and had thus caused tensions with the authorities which led to an armed struggle in a nearby fort.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith4&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Nayriz |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |page= 260}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bábís resisted attacks by the town's governor as well as further reinforcements.  After being given a truce offer on 17 June 1850, Vahid told his followers to give up their positions, which led to Vahid and the Bábís being killed; the Bábí section of the town was also plundered, and the property of the remaining Bábís seized.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith4&quot;/&gt; Later, in March 1853 the governor of the city was killed by the Bábís.  These further events led to a second armed conflict near the city where the Bábís once again resisted troop attacks until November 1853, when a massacre of Bábís happened, with their women being enslaved.&lt;ref name=&quot;PSmith4&quot;/&gt;

==After the execution of the Báb==
{{See also|Execution of the Báb}}
[[File:Haifa Shrine and Port.jpg|thumb|260 px|The [[Shrine of the Báb]] in Haifa]]
The revolts in Zanjan and Nayriz were in progress when in 1850 the Báb, with one of his disciples, was brought from his prison at Chihriq to Tabriz and publicly shot in front of the citadel.  The body, after being exposed for some days, was recovered by the Bábís and conveyed to a shrine near [[Tehran]], whence it was ultimately removed to [[Haifa]], where it is now [[Shrine of the Báb|enshrined]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gpb_18&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Effendi |last=Shoghi |authorlink=Shoghi Effendi |year=1944 |title=God Passes By |publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location=Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn=0877430209 |url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/se/GPB/gpb-19.html | pages=273–289}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the next two years comparatively little was heard of the Bábís,  but on  15 August 1852 three of them, acting on their own initiative, attempted to assassinate [[Nasser-al-Din Shah]] as he was returning from the chase to his palace at Niyávarfin. Notwithstanding the assassins' claim that they were working alone, the entire Bábí community was blamed, and a slaughter of several thousand Bábís followed, including on the 31 August 1852 some thirty Bábís, including [[Táhirih]], were put to death in Tehran.  Many of the Bábís who were not killed, including [[Bahá'u'lláh]], were imprisoned in the [[Síyáh-Chál]] (Black Pit), an underground dungeon of Tehran.&lt;ref name=&quot;eor&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia| last = Hutter | first = Manfred | editor = Ed. Lindsay Jones | encyclopedia = Encyclopedia of Religion | title = Bahā'īs | edition = 2nd | year = 2005 | publisher = Macmillan Reference USA | volume = 2 | location = Detroit | isbn = 0028657330 | pages = 737–740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Succession==
{{Main|Bahá'í/Bábí split}}
In most of his prominent writings, the Báb alluded to a Promised One, most commonly referred to as &quot;[[He whom God shall make manifest]]&quot;, and that he himself was &quot;but a ring upon the hand of Him Whom God shall make manifest.&quot; Within 20 years of the Báb's death, over 25 people claimed to be the Promised One, most significantly [[Bahá'u'lláh]].

Shortly before the Báb's execution, a follower of the Báb, Abd al-Karim, brought to the Báb's attention the necessity to appoint a successor; thus the Báb wrote a certain number of tablets which he gave to Abd al-Karim to deliver to Subh-i-Azal and Bahá'u'lláh.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat384&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first = Abbas | last = Amanat | title = Resurrection and Renewal: The Making of the Babi Movement in Iran | publisher =  Cornell University Press | location = Ithaca | year = 1989 | page = 384}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These tablets were later interpreted by both Azalis and Bahá'ís as proof of the Báb's delegation of leadership.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat384&quot; /&gt; Some sources state that the Báb did this at the suggestion of Bahá'u'lláh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = `Abdu'l-Bahá |authorlink = `Abdu'l-Bahá |editor = Browne, E.G. (Tr.) |origyear = 1886 |year = 2004 |title = A Traveller's Narrative: Written to illustrate the episode of the Bab |publisher = Kalimát Press |location = Los Angeles, USA |edition = 2004 reprint, with translator's notes |isbn = 1-890688-37-1 |url = http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/ab/TN/ | page = 37}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  |author = Taherzadeh, Adib  |authorlink= Adib Taherzadeh  |year = 1976  |title = The Revelation of Bahá'u'lláh, Volume 1  |publisher = George Ronald  |location = Oxford, UK  |isbn = 0853982708 | page = 37 | url = http://www.peyman.info/cl/Baha%27i/Others/ROB/V1/p018-044Ch03.html#p37}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one of the tablets, which is commonly referred to as the Will and Testament of the Báb, Subh-i-Azal is viewed to have been appointed as leader of the Bábis after the death of the movement's founder; the tablet, in verse 27, also appears to order Subh-i-Azal &quot;...to obey Him Whom God Shall Make Manifest.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Manuchehri (2004)&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author = Manuchehri, S. |title = The Primal Point's Will and Testament |journal = Research Notes in Shaykhi, Babi and Baha'i Studies |year = 2004 |volume =  7 |issue =  2 |url = http://www.h-net.org/~bahai/notes/vol7/BABWILL.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the apparent appointment Subh-i-Azal was still a teenager, had never demonstrated leadership in the Bábí movement, and was still living in the house of his older brother, Bahá'u'lláh. All of this lends credence to the Bahá'í claim that the Báb appointed Subh-i-Azal the head of the Bábí Faith so as to divert attention away from Bahá'u'lláh, while allowing Bábís to visit Bahá'u'lláh and consult with him freely, and allowing Bahá'u'lláh to write Bábís easily and freely.

Subh-i-Azal's leadership was controversial. He generally absented himself from the Bábí community spending his time in [[Baghdad]] in hiding and disguise; and even went so far as to publicly disavow allegiance to the Báb on several occasions.&lt;ref name=&quot;cole_bio&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = A Brief Biography of Baha'u'llah | last = Cole| first = Juan| accessdate=2006-06-22 | url=http://www-personal.umich.edu/~jrcole/bahabio.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |encyclopedia= Encyclopædia Iranica |year= 1989 |article=Azali Babism | first = Dennis | last = MacEoin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Barrett p. 246&quot;&gt;{{cite book  | last = Barrett  | first = David  | title = The New Believers  | publisher = Cassell &amp; Co  | year = 2001  | location = London, UK  | isbn = 0304355925 |page=246}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subh-i-Azal gradually alienated himself from a large proportion of the Bábís who started to give their alliance to other claimants.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica&quot; /&gt; During the time that both Bahá'u'lláh and Subh-i-Azal were in Baghdad, since Subh-i-Azal remained in hiding, Bahá'u'lláh performed much of the daily administration of the Bábí affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;cole_bio&quot;/&gt;

[[Bahá'u'lláh]] claimed that in 1853, while a prisoner in Tehran, he was visited by a &quot;[[Maid of Heaven]]&quot;, which symbolically marked the beginning of his mission as a Messenger of God. Ten years later in Baghdad, he made his first public declaration to be [[Him Whom God Shall Make Manifest]], the messianic figure in the Báb's writings, to a small number of followers, and in 1866 he made the claim public.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica&quot; /&gt;  Bahá'u'lláh's claims threatened Subh-i-Azal's position as leader of the religion since it would mean little to be leader of the Bábís if &quot;Him Whom God Shall Make Manifest&quot; were to appear and start a new religion.&lt;ref name=&quot;cole_bio&quot;/&gt; Subh-i-Azal responded by making his own claims, but his attempt to preserve the traditional Bábísm was largely unpopular, and his followers became the minority.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica&quot; /&gt;

Eventually Bahá'u'lláh was recognized by the vast majority of Bábís as &quot;He whom God shall make manifest&quot; and his followers began calling themselves [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'ís]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cole_bio&quot;/&gt; By 1908 there were probably from half a million to a million Bahá'ís, and at most only a hundred followers of Subh-i-Azal. Subh-i Azal died in [[Famagusta]], [[Cyprus]] in 1912, and his followers are known as [[Azalis]] or Azali Bábis. MacEoin notes that after the deaths of those Azali Babis who were active in the [[Iranian Constitutional Revolution|Constitutional Revolution]] in Iran, the Azali form of Babism entered a stagnation from which it has not recovered as there is no acknowledged leader or central organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;iranica&quot; /&gt; Current estimates are that there are no more than a few thousand.&lt;ref name = &quot;Barrett p. 246&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | title = Azali | encyclopedia = Britannica Concise Encyclopedia | volume = 2006 | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica | url = http://concise.britannica.com/ebc/article-9356264/Azali | accessdate = 2006-12-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently there are five to seven million Bahá'ís.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Religion, second edition, vol 2, pg. 739, (ISBN 0-02-865733-0)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also [[Bahá'í statistics]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writings==
:''See also [[Báb#Writings|Writings of the Báb]]
The Báb's major writings include the [[Selections from the Writings of the Báb#Qayyúmu'l-Asmá'|Qayyúmu'l-Asmá']] (a commentary on the [[Yusuf (sura)|Sura of Joseph]]), and the [[Persian Bayán]], which the Bábís saw as superseding the [[Qur'an]].  The latter has been translated into [[French language|French]]; only portions exist in [[English language|English]]. Unfortunately, most of the writings of the Báb have been lost. The Báb himself stated they exceeded five hundred thousand verses in length; the Qur'an, in contrast, is 6300 verses in length. If one assumes 25 verses per page, that would equal 20,000 pages of text.&lt;ref&gt;MacEoin, ''Sources for Early Bābī Doctrine and History'', 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Nabíl-i-Zarandí, in ''The Dawn-breakers'', mentions nine complete commentaries on the Qur'an, revealed during the Báb's imprisonment at Máh-Kú, which have been lost without a trace.&lt;ref&gt;Denis MacEoin, ''The Sources for Early Bābī Doctrine and History'' (Leiden: Brill, 1992), 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Establishing the true text of the works that are still extant, as already noted, is not always easy, and some texts will require considerable work. Others, however, are in good shape; several of the Báb's major works are available in the handwriting of his trusted secretaries.&lt;ref&gt;MacEoin, ''Sources for Early Bābī Doctrine and History'', 12-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most works were revealed in response to specific questions by Bábís. This is not unusual; the genre of the letter has been a venerable medium for composing authoritative texts as far back as the Apostle Paul. Three quarters of the chapters of the New Testament are letters, were composed to imitate letters, or contain letters within them.&lt;ref&gt;On letters as a medium of composition of the New Testament, see Norman Perrin, ''The New Testament: An Introduction, Proclamation and Parenesis, Myth and History'' (New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovitch, 1974), 96-97.&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes the Báb revealed works very rapidly by chanting them in the presence of a secretary and eye-witnesses.

The Archives Department at the [[Bahá'í World Centre]] currently holds about 190 [[Tablet (religious)|Tablets]] of the Báb.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author = Unpublished letter from the Universal House of Justice |title = Numbers and Classifications of Sacred Writings Texts |url = http://bahai-library.com/uhj_numbers_sacred_writings |accessdate = 2006-12-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Excerpts from several principal works have been published in the only English language compilation of the Báb's writings: ''[[Selections from the Writings of the Báb]]''. Denis MacEoin, in his ''Sources for Early Bābī Doctrine and History'', gives a description of many works; much of the following summary is derived from that source. In addition to major works, the Báb revealed numerous letters to his wife and followers, many prayers for various purposes, numerous commentaries on verses or chapters of the Qur'an, and many khutbihs or sermons (most of which were never delivered). Many of these have been lost; others have survived in compilations.&lt;ref&gt;MacEoin, ''Sources for Early Bābī Doctrine and History'', 15-40.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Teachings==
{{Main|Teachings of the Báb}}
The Báb's teachings can be grouped into three broad stages which each have a dominant thematic focus.  His earliest teachings are primarily defined by his interpretation of the [[Qur'an]] and other [[Hadith|Islamic traditions]].  While this interpretive mode continues throughout all three stages of his teachings, a shift takes place where his emphasis moves to philosophical elucidation and finally to [[legislation|legislative]] pronouncements.  In the second philosophical stage, the Báb gives an explanation of the [[metaphysics]] of being and creation, and in the third legislative stage his mystical and historical principles are explicitly united.&lt;ref name=&quot;saiedi27&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Gate of the Heart | first = Nader | last = Saiedi | publisher = Wilfrid Laurier University Press | location = Waterloo, ON | pages = 27–28 | isbn = 978-1-55458-035-4 | year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
An analysis of the Báb's writings throughout the three stages shows that all of his teachings were animated by a common principle that had multiple dimensions and forms.&lt;ref name=&quot;saiedi49&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Gate of the Heart | first = Nader | last = Saiedi | publisher = Wilfrid Laurier University Press | location = Waterloo, ON | page = 49 | isbn = 978-1-55458-035-4 | year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hidden Imam===

In [[Twelver]] [[Shi'a Islam]]ic belief there were twelve [[Imams]], the last of which, known as [[Imam Mahdi]], who communicated with his followers only through certain representatives.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot;&gt;{{cite book | url = http://bahai-library.com/browne_babism | title =  Bábism | first = Edward G. | last = Browne | authorlink = E.G. Browne | year = 1889}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[Twelver]]'s belief, after the last of these representatives died, the Imam Mahdi went into a state of Occultation; while still alive, he was no longer accessible to his believers.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot; /&gt; Shi'a Muslims believe that when the world becomes oppressed, the Imam Mahdi (also termed the [[Al-Qa'im (person)|Qa'im]]) will come out of occultation and restore true religion on Earth before the cataclysmic end of the world and judgement day.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat1&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title = The Resurgence of Apocalyptic in Modern Islam | first= Abbas | last = Amanat |editor= Stephen J. Stein, ed. | journal = The Encyclopedia of Apocalypticism | volume =  III |location = New York | publisher =  Continuum | year = 2000 | pages = 230–254 | url = http://bahai-library.com/amanat_resurgence_apocalyptic_islam | doi = 10.1016/0048-721X(89)90077-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Bábí belief the [[Báb]] is the return of the Imam Mahdi, but the doctrine of the Occultation is implicitly denied; instead the Báb stated that his manifestation was a symbolic return of the Imam, and not the physical reappearance of the Imam Mahdi who had died a thousand years earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot; /&gt; In Bábí belief the statements made from previous revelations regarding the Imam Mahdi were set forth in symbols.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot; /&gt; The Báb also stated that he was not only the fulfillment of the Shi`i expectations for the Qá'im, but that he also was the beginning of a new prophetic dispensation.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat1&quot; /&gt;

===Resurrection, Judgment Day and cyclical revelation===

The Báb taught that his revelation was beginning an apocalyptic process that was bringing the Islamic dispensation to its cyclical end, and starting a new dispensation.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat1&quot; /&gt; He taught that the terms &quot;resurrection&quot;, &quot;Judgement Day&quot;, &quot;paradise&quot; and &quot;hell&quot; used in Shi'a prophecies for the end-times are symbolic.&lt;ref name=&quot;esslemont&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author= Esslemont, J.E. |authorlink=John Esslemont |year= 1980 |title= Bahá'u'lláh and the New Era |edition= 5th |publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location=Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn= 0877431604 |url= http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/je/BNE/}}&lt;/ref&gt; He stated that &quot;Resurrection&quot; means that the appearance of a new revelation, and that &quot;raising of the dead&quot; means the spiritual awakening of those who have stepped away from true religion.&lt;ref name=&quot;esslemont&quot; /&gt; He further stated that &quot;Judgement Day&quot; refers to when a new [[Manifestation of God]] comes, and the acceptance or rejection of those on the Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;esslemont&quot; /&gt; Thus the Báb taught that with his revelation the [[end times]] ended and the age of resurrection had started, and that the end-times were symbolic as the end of the past prophetic cycle.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat1&quot; /&gt;

In the [[Persian Bayán]], the Báb wrote that religious dispensations come in cycles, as the seasons, to renew &quot;pure religion&quot; for humanity.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat1&quot; /&gt; This notion of continuity anticipated future prophetic revelations after the Báb.&lt;ref name=&quot;amanat1&quot; /&gt;

===He whom God shall make manifest===

While the Báb claimed a station of revelation, he also claimed no finality for his revelation.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot; /&gt; One of the core Bábí teachings is the great Promised One, whom the Báb termed [[He whom God shall make manifest]], promised in the sacred writings of previous religions would soon establish the Kingdom of God on the Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;farah&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Islam: Beliefs and Observances | first = Caesar E. |last= Farah |location= Woodbury, NY | publisher= Barron's Educational Series |year = 1970 | url = http://bahai-library.com/farah_islam_beliefs_observances}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the books written by the Báb he constantly entreats his believers to follow He whom God shall make manifest when he arrives and not behave like the Muslims who have not accepted his own revelation.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne&quot; /&gt;

===Religious law===
The Báb abrogated Islamic law and in the Persian Bayán promulgated a system of Bábí law, thus establishing a separate religion distinct from Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;eor&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | last = Hutter | first = Manfred | title = Babis  |encyclopedia =Encyclopedia of Religion |editor= Lindsay Jones |volume= Vol. 2 | edition= 2nd |location= Detroit |publisher= Macmillan Reference USA |year= 2005 |pages= 727–729}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;walbridge&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Essays and Notes on Bábí and Bahá'í History | first = John |last = Walbridge | publisher = H-Bahai Digital Library | location = East Lansing, Michigan | year = 2002 | chapter = Chap. 3 |url = http://www.h-net.org/~bahai/bhpapers/vol6/waless/chap3.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the new laws included changing the direction of the [[Qibla]] to the [[Bahá'í pilgrimage#House of the Báb, Shiraz|Báb's house]] in [[Shiraz, Iran]] and changing the calendar to a solar calendar of nineteen months and nineteen days (which became the basis of the [[Bahá'í calendar]]) and prescribing the last month as a month of fasting.&lt;ref name=&quot;eor&quot; /&gt;

The Báb also created a large number of rituals and rites which remained largely unpracticed.&lt;ref name=&quot;mceoin&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Deconstructing and Reconstructing the Shari'a: the Bábí and Bahá'í Solutions to the Problem of Immutability | first = Denis |last = MacEoin | url = http://bahai-library.com/maceoin_deconstructing_sharia| accessdate = 2006-07-11 | date = 2006-03-23 | publisher = bahai-library.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of these rituals include the carrying of arms only in times of necessity, the obligatory sitting on chairs, the advocating of the cleanliness displayed by Christians, the non-cruel treatment of animals, the prohibition of beating children severely, the recommendation of the printing of books, even scripture and the prohibition on the study of logic or dead languages.&lt;ref name=&quot;mceoin&quot; /&gt; While some statements in the Bayan show tolerance, there are  other very harsh regulations in regards to relations with non-believers. For example, non-believers are forbidden to live in five central Iranian provinces, the holy places of previous religions are to be demolished, all non-Bábí books should be destroyed, believers are not to marry or sit in the company of non-believers, and the property of non-believers can be taken from them.&lt;ref name=&quot;mceoin&quot; /&gt; Some further ritual include elaborate regulations regarding pilgrimage, fasting, the manufacture of rings, the use of perfume, and the washing and disposal of the dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;mceoin&quot; /&gt;

[[Denis MacEoin]] writes, regarding the Bayán: &quot;One comes away from the Bayan with a strong sense that very little of this is to be taken seriously. It is a form of game, never actually intended to be put into practice.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mceoin&quot; /&gt; Instead he states that &quot;the Bábí shari'a made an impact... it stated very clearly that the Islamic code could be replaced.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mceoin&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
*[[Selections from the Writings of the Báb]]
*[[Persian Bayan]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
* {{cite book
  | last = Amanat
  | first = Abbas
  | title = Resurrection and Renewal: The Making of the Bábí Movement in Iran 1844–1850
  | publisher = Cornell University Press
  | location = Ithaca, NY
  | year = 1989
  | isbn = 0-8014-2098-9
  | ref = harv
}}
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Bábíism}}
*{{cite book|author=Esslemont, J. E.|year=1980|edition=5th|title=Bahá'u'lláh and the New Era, An Introduction to the Bahá'í Faith|publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location= Wilmette, Illinois |isbn=0877431604 |ref = harv}}
* {{cite book
 |first = Denis
 |last = MacEoin
 |authorlink = Denis MacEoin
 |year = 1994
 |title = Rituals in Babism and Baha'ism
 |publisher = British Academic Press and Centre of Middle Eastern Studies, University of Cambridge
 |location = Cambridge, UK
 |isbn = 1850436541
 |url = http://books.google.com/?id=4Bpd0xhUKewC
 |ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
 |first = Denis
 |last = MacEoin
 |authorlink = Denis MacEoin
 |year = 1992
 |title = The Sources for Early Bābī Doctrine and History: A Survey
 |publisher = Brill
 |location = Leiden, The Netherlands
 |isbn = 9004094628
 |url = http://books.google.com/books?id=xqV9-zmMxsUC
 |ref = harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 |author=Nabíl-i-Zarandí
 |authorlink=Nabíl-i-A`zam
 |year=1932
 |title=The Dawn-Breakers: Nabíl’s Narrative
 |publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust
 |location=Wilmette, Illinois
 |isbn=0-900125-22-5
 |url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/nz/DB/
 |ref = harv
 |others=trans. Shoghi Effendi
 }}
*{{cite book
 |last = Saiedi
 |first = Nader
 |year = 2008
 |title = Gate of the Heart: Understanding the Writings of the Báb
 |publisher = Wilfrid Laurier University Press
 |location = Canada
 |isbn = 9781554580569
 |url = http://books.google.com/?id=XTfoaK15t64C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Understanding+the+Writings+of+the+B%C3%A1b&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=
 |ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Smith
  | first = Peter
  | title = The Bábí and Bahá'í Religions: From Messianic Shi'ism to a World Religion
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | location = Cambridge, UK
  | year = 1987
  | isbn = 0-521-30128-9
 |ref = harv
}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book
 |first = Denis
 |last = MacEoin
 |authorlink = Denis MacEoin
 |year = 2009
 |title = The Messiah of Shiraz: Studies in Early and Middle Babism
 |publisher = Brill
 |location = Leiden, The Netherlands
 |isbn = 9004170359
 |url = http://books.google.com/books?id=LgOPsxZofrkC
 |ref = harv
 }}

{{Bahá'í-2}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Babism}}
[[Category:Bábism| ]]
[[Category:Monotheistic religions]]
[[Category:1844 introductions]]

{{Link FA|eo}}
[[af:Babisme]]
[[ar:بابية]]
[[az:Babilik]]
[[ca:Fe babí]]
[[cs:Bábismus]]
[[da:Babisme]]
[[de:Babismus]]
[[es:Babismo]]
[[eo:Babismo]]
[[fr:Babisme]]
[[ko:바브교]]
[[id:Babisme]]
[[it:Bábismo]]
[[he:באביזם]]
[[arz:بابيه]]
[[ms:Bábisme]]
[[nl:Bábisme]]
[[ja:バーブ教]]
[[pl:Babizm]]
[[pt:Babismo]]
[[ro:Bábism]]
[[ru:Бабизм]]
[[scn:Babbismu]]
[[sl:Babizem]]
[[sr:Бабизам]]
[[fi:Baabilaisuus]]
[[sv:Bábísm]]
[[tr:Babi]]
[[tk:Babizm]]
[[uk:Бабізм]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
