<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="55490" ns="0" title="Roald Dahl"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name        = Roald Dahl
| image       = Roald Dahl.jpg
| caption     = Roald Dahl in 1954
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|1916|9|13|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Llandaff]], [[Llandaff]], [[Wales]],&lt;br/&gt; United Kingdom
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1990|11|23|1916|9|13|df=y}}
| death_place  = [[Oxford]], [[Oxfordshire]], [[England]], United Kingdom
| occupation  = Novelist, poet, screenwriter
| nationality = British
| period = 1942–1990
| genre       = Children's, adults' literature, horror, mystery, fantasy
| movement    =
| notableworks = ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'', ''[[James and the Giant Peach]]'', ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]'', ''[[Matilda (novel)|Matilda]]'', ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'', ''[[The Twits]]'', ''[[Charlie and the Great Glass Elevator]]'', ''[[The BFG]]'', ''[[The Gremlins]]'', ''[[The Enormous Crocodile]]'', ''[[Esio Trot]]'', ''[[George's Marvellous Medicine]]'', ''[[Danny, the Champion of the World]]'', ''[[The Giraffe and the Pelly and Me]]'', ''[[The Minpins]]'', ''[[The Vicar of Nibbleswicke]]'', ''[[The Magic Finger]]'', ''[[The Wonderful Story of Henry Sugar and Six More]]''
| spouse      = [[Patricia Neal]] (1953–1983; divorced; 5 children)&lt;br /&gt;Felicity Ann d'Abreu Crosland (1983–1990; his death)
| influences  = [[Charles Dickens]], [[William Thackeray]], [[Rudyard Kipling]], [[Frederick Marryat]], [[Jonas Lie]], Sofie Dahl (mother)&lt;ref name=&quot;infloox.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.infloox.com/person?id=6a5f6877 Roald Dahl Literary Influences] infloox.com&lt;/ref&gt;
| influenced  =
| signature   =
| website = http://www.roalddahl.com
}}
'''Roald Dahl''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|r|oʊ|.|ɑː|l|_|ˈ|d|ɑː|l}},&lt;ref&gt;[http://inogolo.com/pronunciation/d1324/Roald_Dahl Pronunciation of Roald Dahl : How to pronounce Roald Dahl] inogolo.com&lt;/ref&gt; {{IPA-sv|ˈɾuːɑl dɑl|langno}}; 13 September 1916{{ndash}} 23 November 1990) was a British novelist, short story writer, [[fighter pilot]] and screenwriter.

Born in [[Wales]] to Norwegian parents, he served in the [[Royal Air Force]] during the Second World War, in which he became a [[flying ace]] and intelligence agent, rising to the rank of [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]]. Dahl rose to prominence in the 1940s with works for both children and adults, and became one of the world's best-selling authors.&lt;ref name=INT/&gt;&lt;ref name=BDC/&gt; He has been referred to as &quot;one of the greatest storytellers for children of the 20th century&quot;.&lt;ref name=IND/&gt; In 2008 ''[[The Times]]'' placed Dahl 16th on its list of &quot;The 50 greatest [[British literature|British writers]] since 1945&quot;.&lt;ref name=TIM&gt;[http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/books/article3127837.ece The 50 greatest British writers since 1945]. ''[[The Times]]''. 5 January 2008. Retrieved on 1 February 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; His short stories are known for their unexpected endings, and his children's books for their unsentimental, often very [[black comedy|dark humour]].

Some of his notable works include ''[[James and the Giant Peach]]'', ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'', ''[[George's Marvellous Medicine]]'',  ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]'', ''[[Matilda (novel)|Matilda]]'', ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'' and ''[[The BFG]]''.

==Early life==
Roald Dahl was born at Villa Marie, Fairwater Road in [[Llandaff]], [[Cardiff]], Wales in 1916, to Norwegian parents, Harald Dahl and Sofie Magdalene Dahl (''née'' Hesselberg).&lt;ref&gt;Philip Howard, &quot;Dahl, Roald (1916–1990)&quot;, Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl's father had moved from [[Sarpsborg]] in Norway and settled in Cardiff in the 1880s. His mother came over to marry his father in 1911. Dahl was named after the [[polar explorer]] [[Roald Amundsen]], a national hero in Norway at the time. He spoke Norwegian at home with his parents and sisters, Astri, Alfhild, and Else. Dahl and his sisters were christened at the [[Norwegian Church, Cardiff]], where their parents worshipped.&lt;ref&gt;Colin Palfrey (2006) [http://books.google.com/books?id=pOfJeCs0cDIC&amp;pg=PA76&amp;dq=ROALD+DAHL+BAPTISED+Norwegian+Church&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=uRINTZLKKNG4hAfvt9i3Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDkQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=ROALD%20DAHL%20BAPTISED%20Norwegian%20Church&amp;f=false Cardiff Soul: An Underground Guide to the City]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1920, when Dahl was three years old, his seven-year-old sister, Astri, died from [[appendicitis]]. Weeks later, his father died of [[pneumonia]] at the age of 57 while on a fishing trip in the Antarctic. With the option of returning to Norway to live with relatives, Dahl's mother decided to remain in Wales because her husband Harald had wished to have their children educated in British schools, which he considered the world's best.&lt;ref&gt;Jill C. Wheeler (2006) ''Roald Dahl'' p.9. ABDO Publishing Company, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Dahl first attended [[The Cathedral School, Llandaff]]. At the age of eight, he and four of his friends (one named Thwaites) were [[Corporal punishment|caned]] by the headmaster after putting a dead mouse in a jar of gobstoppers at the local sweet shop,&lt;ref name=IND/&gt; which was owned by a &quot;mean and loathsome&quot; old woman called Mrs Pratchett.&lt;ref name=IND/&gt; This was known amongst the five boys as the &quot;[[Boy (book)|Great Mouse Plot of 1924]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Michael D. Sharp (2006) [http://books.google.com/books?id=8d-nHl6bZtgC&amp;pg=PA516&amp;dq=roald+dahl+great+mouse+plot&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=PYwiTdLLHsOChQeNsKG4Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=roald%20dahl%20great%20mouse%20plot&amp;f=false Popular Contemporary Writers] p.516. Marshall Cavendish, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Thereafter, he transferred to a [[boarding school]] in England: Saint Peter's in [[Weston-super-Mare]]. Roald's parents had wanted him to be educated at an English [[Independent school (United Kingdom)|public school]] and, because of a then regular ferry link across the Bristol Channel, this proved to be the nearest. His time at Saint Peter's was an unpleasant experience for him. He was very homesick and wrote to his mother every week, but never revealed to her his unhappiness, being under the pressure of school censorship. Only after her death in 1967 did he find out that she had saved every single one of his letters, in small bundles held together with green tape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/arts/sites/roald-dahl/pages/media-2000-school.shtml | title= Roald Dahl's School Days | publisher=BBC Wales | accessdate=24 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl wrote about his time at St. Peter's in his autobiography ''[[Boy (book)|Boy: Tales of Childhood]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title= [[Boy (book)|Boy: Tales of Childhood]] | authorlink= Roald Dahl | first= Roald | last= Dahl | publisher=Puffin Books| year= 1984 | isbn= 9780141303055}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1929, he attended [[Repton School]] in Derbyshire, where, according to ''Boy: Tales of Childhood'', a friend named Michael was viciously caned by headmaster [[Geoffrey Fisher]], the man who later became the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] and went on to crown [[Queen Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|the Queen]] in 1953. (However, according to Dahl's biographer [[Jeremy Treglown]],&lt;ref&gt;Jeremy Treglown, ''Roald Dahl: A Biography'' (1994) , Faber and Faber, page 21. Treglown's source note is as follows: &quot;Several people who were at the top of Priory House at the time have discussed it with me, particularly B.L.L. Reuss and John Bradburn.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; the caning took place in May 1933, a year after Fisher had left Repton. The headmaster concerned was in fact J.T. Christie, Fisher's successor.) This caused Dahl to &quot;have doubts about religion and even about God&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;boy&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=[[Boy (book)|Boy: Tales of Childhood]] |last=Dahl |first=Roald |year=1984 |publisher=[[Jonathan Cape]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was never seen as a particularly talented writer in his school years, with one of his English teachers writing in his school report &quot;I have never met anybody who so persistently writes words meaning the exact opposite of what is intended,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/rdahl.htm |title=Roald Dahl |publisher=Kirjasto.sci.fi |date=23 November 1990 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl was exceptionally tall, reaching {{height|ft=6|in=6}} in adult life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.penguin.co.uk/nf/Author/AuthorPage/0,,1000008184,00.html Roald Dahl&amp;nbsp;– Penguin UK Authors]&amp;nbsp;– Penguin UK&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; He excelled at sports, being made captain of the school [[fives]] and [[Squash (sport)|squash]] teams, and also playing for the [[Association football|football]] team.&lt;ref&gt;Shavick, Andrea (1997) [http://books.google.com/books?id=DovoRMkvxjUC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;dq=roald+dahl+at+school+-+football+team&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=4Av5TfzHIoa48gODmbHRCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CF4Q6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Roald Dahl: the champion storyteller] p.12. Oxford University Press, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; As well as having a passion for literature, he also developed an interest in photography&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/arts/sites/roald-dahl/pages/biography.shtml Roald Dahl biography] BBC Wales. Retrieved 15 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; and often carried a camera with him. During his years at Repton, [[Cadbury plc|Cadbury]], the chocolate company, would occasionally send boxes of new chocolates to the school to be tested by the pupils. Dahl apparently used to dream of inventing a new chocolate bar that would win the praise of Mr. Cadbury himself, and this proved the inspiration for him to write his third book for children, ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'' (1963) and include references to chocolate in other books for children.&lt;ref name=DahlChocolate&gt;{{Cite book|year=2005|author=Roald Dahl (derivative work) and [[Quentin Blake]]|isbn=0-141-31959-3|title=Roald Dahl's Incredible Chocolate Box}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout his childhood and adolescent years, Dahl spent his summer holidays with his mother's family in Norway. His childhood and first job selling kerosene in [[Midsomer Norton]] and surrounding villages in [[Somerset]], [[South West England|south West]] England are subjects in ''Boy: Tales of Childhood''.&lt;ref&gt;Dahl, Roald (1984) ''Boy: tales of childhood'' p.172. Puffin Books, 1984&lt;/ref&gt; The main child character in his 1983 book ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'' is a British boy of Norwegian descent, whose grandmother is still living in Norway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TheWitches |title=The Witches: A 1983 Roald Dahl book, was made into a 1990 film starring Anjelica Huston |publisher=Tvtropes.org |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After finishing his schooling, he spent three weeks hiking through [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]] with the Public Schools' Exploring Society (now known as [[BSES Expeditions]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/149746/Roald-Dahl Roald Dahl (British author)] ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'.' Retrieved 4 January 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 1934, Dahl joined the [[Royal Dutch Shell|Shell Petroleum]] Company. Following two years of training in the United Kingdom, he was transferred to [[Dar-es-Salaam]], [[Tanganyika]] (now [[Tanzania]]). Along with the only two other Shell employees in the entire territory, he lived in luxury in the Shell House outside Dar-es-Salaam, with a [[cook (profession)|cook]] and personal [[servant (domestic)|servants]]. While out on assignments supplying oil to customers across Tanganyika, he encountered [[black mamba]]s and lions, amongst other [[wildlife]].&lt;ref name=&quot;boy&quot; /&gt;

==Fighter ace==
{{Infobox military person
|nickname=
|allegiance= {{flag|United Kingdom}}
|branch= [[British Army]] (August–November 1939)&lt;br /&gt;{{air force|United Kingdom}} (November 1939–1945)
|serviceyears= 1939–1945
|rank= [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]]
|unit=
|commands=
|battles=World War II
|awards=
|relations=
}}

In August 1939, as World War II loomed, plans were made to round up the hundreds of Germans in [[Dar-es-Salaam]]. Dahl was made an officer in the [[King's African Rifles]], commanding a platoon of [[Askari]]s, indigenous troops serving in the colonial army.&lt;ref&gt;Donald Sturrock [http://books.google.com/books?id=udN6caZEJesC&amp;pg=PA116&amp;dq=roald+Dahl+-+King's+African+Rifle&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=7RMNTazoEIqEhQfuk8S3Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Storyteller: The Authorized Biography of Roald Dahl] p.116. Simon and Schuster, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1939, Dahl joined the [[Royal Air Force]] as an [[Aircraftman]]. After a {{convert|600|mi|km|sing=on}} car journey from Dar-es-Salaam to [[Nairobi]], he was accepted for flight training with 16 other men, of whom     only two others survived the war. With seven hours and 40 minutes experience in a [[De Havilland Tiger Moth]], he flew solo;&lt;ref&gt;Sturrock (2010: 120)&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl enjoyed watching the wildlife of [[Kenya]] during his flights. He continued to advanced flying training in [[Iraq]], at [[RAF Habbaniya]], {{convert|50|mi|km}} west of [[Baghdad]]. He was promoted to [[Leading Aircraftman]] on 24 August 1940.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/34964/pages/5907 The London Gazette, 8 October 1940]''&lt;/ref&gt; Following six months' training on [[Hawker Hart]]s, Dahl was made an [[Acting Pilot Officer]].

He was assigned to [[No. 80 Squadron RAF]], flying obsolete [[Gloster Gladiator]]s, the last [[biplane]] [[fighter aircraft]] used by the RAF. Dahl was surprised to find that he would not receive any specialised training in [[aerial combat]], or in flying Gladiators. On 19 September 1940, Dahl was ordered to fly his Gladiator from Abu Sueir in [[Egypt]], on to Amiriya to refuel, and again to Fouka in [[Libya]] for a second refuelling. From there he would fly to 80 Squadron's forward [[airstrip]] {{convert|30|mi|km}} south of [[Mersa Matruh]]. On the final leg, he could not find the airstrip and, running low on [[fuel]] and with night approaching, he was forced to attempt a [[Accidents and incidents in aviation#Causes|landing]] in the desert. The undercarriage hit a boulder and the aircraft crashed, fracturing his skull, smashing his nose, and temporarily blinding him.&lt;ref name=WRN&gt;Alan Warren (1988) [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=X5BaAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=dahl+fractured+his+skull&amp;dq=dahl+fractured+his+skull&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=iYsHTZO5N86ChQfgj4ntBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAw Roald Dahl] pp.12, 87. Starmont House, 1988&lt;/ref&gt; He managed to drag himself away from the blazing wreckage and passed out. Later, he wrote about the crash for his first published work.&lt;ref name=WRN/&gt;

Dahl was rescued and taken to a [[first aid|first-aid]] post in Mersa Matruh, where he regained consciousness, but not his sight, and was then taken by train to the Royal Navy hospital in [[Alexandria]]. There he fell in and out of love with a nurse, Mary Welland. An RAF inquiry into the crash revealed that the location to which he had been told to fly was completely wrong, and he had mistakenly been sent instead to the [[no man's land]] between the Allied and Italian forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;solo&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=[[Going Solo]] |last=Dahl |first=Roald |year=1986 |publisher=Jonathan Cape}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1941, Dahl was discharged from hospital and passed fully fit for flying duties. By this time, 80 Squadron had been transferred to the [[Battle of Greece|Greek campaign]] and based at [[Eleusina]], near [[Athens]]. The squadron was now equipped with [[Hawker Hurricane]]s. Dahl flew a replacement Hurricane across the Mediterranean Sea in April 1941, after seven hours flying Hurricanes. By this stage in the Greek campaign, the RAF had only 18 combat aircraft in Greece: 14 Hurricanes and four [[Bristol Blenheim]] light bombers. Dahl saw his first aerial combat on 15 April 1941, while flying alone over the city of [[Chalcis]]. He attacked six [[Junkers Ju-88]]s that were bombing ships and shot one down. On 16 April in another air battle, he shot down another Ju-88.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Thomas [http://books.google.com/books?id=4u-QXw2bjwUC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=roald+dahl+-+16+April+Ju-88&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=BOQQTY7-KYOWhQeUl424Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Hurricane Aces 1941–45] Osprey Publishing, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 April 1941, Dahl took part in the &quot;Battle of Athens&quot;, alongside the highest-scoring British Commonwealth ace of World War II, [[Marmaduke Pattle|Pat Pattle]] and Dahl's friend [[David Coke]]. Of 12 Hurricanes involved, five were shot down and four of their pilots killed, including Pattle. Greek observers on the ground counted 22 German aircraft downed, but because of the confusion of the aerial engagement, none of the pilots knew which plane they had shot down. Dahl described it as ''&quot;an endless blur of enemy fighters whizzing towards me from every side&quot;.''&lt;ref&gt;Roald Dahl [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=weZxpJUHuPUC&amp;q=an+endless+blur+of+enemy+fighters+whizzing+towards+me+from+every&amp;dq=an+endless+blur+of+enemy+fighters+whizzing+towards+me+from+every&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=FYUHTbzIDoSYhQfI5azuBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAg Going Solo] p.151. Scholastic, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

In May, as the Germans were pressing on Athens, Dahl was evacuated to Egypt. His squadron was reassembled in [[Haifa]]. From there, Dahl flew sorties every day for a period of four weeks, shooting down a [[Vichy French Air Force]] [[Potez 63]] on 8 June and another Ju-88 on 15 June, but he then began to get severe headaches that caused him to [[G-LOC|black out]]. He was invalided home to Britain. Though at this time Dahl was only an [[Acting Pilot Officer]], in September 1941 he was simultaneously confirmed as a [[Pilot Officer]] and promoted to [[Flying Officer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/35292/pages/5664 |title=Viewing Page 5664 of Issue 35292 |publisher=London-gazette.co.uk |date=30 September 1941 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dahl began writing in 1942, after he was transferred to Washington, D.C. as Assistant [[Air Attaché]]. His first published work, in 1 August 1942 issue of ''[[The Saturday Evening Post]]'', was &quot;Shot Down Over Libya&quot; which described the crash of his Gloster Gladiator. [[C. S. Forester]] had asked Dahl to write down some RAF anecdotes so that he could shape them into a story. After Forester read what Dahl had given him, he decided to publish the story exactly as Dahl had written it. The original title of the article was &quot;A Piece of Cake&quot; but the title was changed to sound more dramatic, despite the fact that he was not actually shot down.&lt;ref name=&quot;solo&quot; /&gt;

Dahl was promoted to [[Flight Lieutenant]] in August 1942.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/35791/supplements/5037 |title=Viewing Page 5037 of Issue 35791 |publisher=London-gazette.co.uk |date=17 November 1942 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the war, Forester worked for the British Information Service and was writing propaganda for the Allied cause, mainly for American consumption.&lt;ref&gt;''Cambridge Guide to Literature'' (Cambridge University Press, 1989) ISBN 0-521-26751-X.&lt;/ref&gt; This work introduced Dahl to espionage and the activities of the Canadian spymaster [[William Stephenson]], known by the codename &quot;Intrepid&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ellen Schoeck [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=-JbF6kwRZiMC&amp;pg=PA221&amp;dq=roald+dahl+-+intrepid+william+stevenson&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=9eIQTdHMO8G4hAeW4Ni3Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=roald%20dahl%20-%20intrepid%20william%20stevenson&amp;f=false I was there: a century of alumni stories about the University of Alberta, 1906–2006] University of Alberta, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

During the war, Dahl supplied intelligence from Washington to Stephenson and his organisation known as [[British Security Coordination]], which was part of [[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]]. He was revealed in the 1980s to have been serving to help promote Britain's interests and message in the United States and to combat the &quot;[[America First Committee|America First]]&quot; movement, working with such other well known agents as [[Ian Fleming]] and [[David Ogilvy (businessman)|David Ogilvy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Irreg&quot;&gt;The book &quot;''The Irregulars''&quot; (by [[Jennet Conant]], Simon and Schuster 2008) describes this era of Dahl's life and those with whom he worked.&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl was once sent back to Britain by [[British Embassy]] officials, supposedly for misconduct&amp;nbsp;– &quot;I got booted out by the big boys,&quot; he said. Stephenson promptly sent him back to Washington—with a promotion to [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]].&lt;ref&gt;Bill Macdonald&amp;nbsp;– ''The True Intrepid'' p249 (Raincoast 2001)ISBN 1-55192-418-8 Dahl also speaks about his espionage work in the documentary ''The True Intrepid''&lt;/ref&gt; Towards the end of the war, Dahl wrote some of the history of the secret organisation and he and Stephenson remained friends for decades after the war.&lt;ref&gt;Macdonald&amp;nbsp;– ''The True Intrepid'' p243 ISBN 1-55192-418-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon the war's conclusion, Dahl held the rank of a temporary [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]] (substantive [[Flight Lieutenant]]). Owing to his accident in 1940 having left him with excruciating headaches while flying, in August 1946 he was invalided out of the RAF. He left the service with the substantive rank of [[Squadron Leader]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/37681/supplements/4054 |title=The London Gazette |publisher=The London Gazette |date=9 August 1946 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His record of five aerial victories, qualifying him as a [[flying ace]], has been confirmed by post-war research and cross-referenced in Axis records, although it is most likely that he scored more than that during 20 April 1941 when 22 German aircraft were shot down.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Shores and Clive Williams&amp;nbsp;– ''Aces High: A Tribute to the Most Notable Fighter Pilots of the British and Commonwealth Air Forces in WWII'' (Grub Street Publishing, 1994) ISBN 1-898697-00-0.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Postwar life==
[[Image:Dahlneal.jpg|thumb|right|[[Patricia Neal]] and Roald Dahl]]
Dahl married American actress [[Patricia Neal]] on 2 July 1953 at [[Trinity Church, New York|Trinity Church]] in New York City. Their marriage lasted for 30 years and they had five children: Olivia, [[Tessa Dahl|Tessa]], Theo, [[Ophelia Dahl|Ophelia]] and [[Lucy Dahl|Lucy]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/biographyandmemoirreviews/7930232/Dad-also-needed-happy-dreams-Roald-Dahl-his-daughters-and-the-BFG.html 'Dad also needed happy dreams': Roald Dahl, his daughters and the BFG] ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'' (6 August 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 December 1960, four-month-old Theo Dahl was severely injured when his baby carriage was struck by a taxicab in New York City. For a time, he suffered from [[hydrocephalus]], and as a result, his father became involved in the development of what became known as the &quot;[[Wade-Dahl-Till valve|Wade-Dahl-Till]]&quot; (or WDT) valve, a device to alleviate the condition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medgadget.com/archives/2005/07/water_on_the_br.html|title=Water on the Brain|date=15 July 2005|accessdate=11 May 2006|work=MedGadget: Internet Journal of Emerging Medical Technologies}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=larner&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.acnr.co.uk/mar_apr_2008/ACNRMA08_nerolit.pdf|author=Dr Andrew Larner
|title=Tales of the Unexpected: Roald Dahl's Neurological Contributions
|publisher=Advances in Clinical Neuroscience and Rehabilitation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1962, Olivia Dahl died of [[Subacute sclerosing panencephalitis|measles encephalitis]] at age seven. Dahl subsequently became a proponent of immunisation&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.childalert.co.uk/absolutenm/templates/newstemplate.asp?articleid=291&amp;zoneid=2 childalert&amp;nbsp;– first for child safety and wellbeing&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and dedicated his 1982 book ''The BFG'' to his daughter.&lt;ref&gt;Singh, Anita (7 August 2010) [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/7930637/Roald-Dahls-secret-notebook-reveals-heartbreak-over-daughters-death.html Roald Dahl's secret notebook reveals heartbreak over daughter's death] ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'.' Retrieved 4 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1965, wife Patricia Neal suffered three burst [[cerebral aneurysm]]s while pregnant with their fifth child, Lucy; Dahl took control of her rehabilitation and she eventually relearned to talk and walk, and even returned to her acting career,&lt;ref name=farrell&gt;{{Cite book
|author=Barry Farrell
|title=Pat and Roald|publisher=Kingsport Press
|year=1969}}&lt;/ref&gt; an episode in their lives which was dramatised in the film ''The Patricia Neal Story'', in which the couple were played by [[Glenda Jackson]] and [[Dirk Bogarde]].

Dahl married [[Clare McLaren-Throckmorton#Personal life|Felicity &quot;Liccy&quot; Crosland]] at [[London Borough of Lambeth#Landmarks|Brixton Town Hall]], [[South London]], following a divorce from Neal in 1983. Dahl and Crosland had previously been in a relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roalddahl.com/|title=Roald Dahl Official website|accessdate=13 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to biographer Donald Sturrock, Liccy gave up her job and moved into 'Gipsy House', [[Great Missenden]] in [[Buckinghamshire]], which had been Dahl's home since 1954.&lt;ref&gt;Lynn F. Pearson [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=9IaHTin6y2wC&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=roald+dahl+gipsy+house&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tPAQTfzrGNCwhQeJi5W4Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEsQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=roald%20dahl%20gipsy%20house&amp;f=false Discovering Famous Graves] Osprey Publishing, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1983, Dahl was quoted as saying: &quot;There's a trait in the Jewish character that does provoke animosity ... I mean there is always a reason why anti-anything crops up anywhere; even a stinker like Hitler didn't just pick on them for no reason.&quot;&lt;ref name=treg&gt;''Roald Dahl: A biography,'' Jeremy Treglown (Farrar, Straus, Giroux, 1994), pp. 255–256.&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl stated that he was anti-Israel rather than anti-Semitic, and he maintained friendships with a number of Jews, including philosopher [[Isaiah Berlin]], who said, &quot;I thought he might say anything. Could have been pro-Arab or pro-Jew. There was no consistent line.&quot;&lt;ref name=treg /&gt;

Dahl is the father of author [[Tessa Dahl]], and grandfather of author, cookbook writer, and former model [[Sophie Dahl]] (after whom Sophie in ''[[The BFG]]'' is named&lt;ref&gt;Martin Chilton (18 November 2010) [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/booknews/8143303/The-25-best-childrens-books.html The 25 best children's books] ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]''&lt;/ref&gt;).

==Death and legacy==
[[File:RoaldDahlgrave.jpg|thumb|230px|right|Dahl's gravestone, [[St. Peter and St. Paul's Church]], [[Great Missenden]], Buckinghamshire]]
Roald Dahl died on 23 November 1990, at the age of 74 of a blood disease, [[myelodysplastic syndrome]], in [[Oxford]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.findmypast.com/BirthsMarriagesDeaths.jsp |title=Deaths England and Wales 1984–2006 |publisher=Findmypast.com |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was buried in the cemetery at [[St. Peter and St. Paul's Church]] in [[Great Missenden]], Buckinghamshire, England. According to his granddaughter, the family gave him a &quot;sort of [[Viking funeral]]&quot;. He was buried with his [[snooker cue]]s, some very good [[Burgundy wine|burgundy]], chocolates, [[No. 2 pencil|HB pencils]] and a [[circular saw|power saw]]. In his honour, the [[Roald Dahl Children's Gallery]] was opened in November 1996, at the [[Buckinghamshire County Museum]] in nearby [[Aylesbury]].&lt;ref&gt;Sharron L. McElmeel (1999)[http://books.google.co.uk/books?ei=2sMHTcizC8XIhAfj5oztBw&amp;ct=result&amp;id=5VkjAQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=Roald+Dahl+Children%27s+Gallery+23+november+1996&amp;q=Buckinghamshire+County+Museum+ 100 most popular children's authors: biographical sketches and bibliographies] Libraries Unlimited, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, one of [[Cardiff Bay]]'s modern landmarks, the historic Oval Basin plaza, was re-christened &quot;[[Roald Dahl Plass]]&quot;. &quot;Plass&quot; means &quot;place&quot; or &quot;square&quot; in Norwegian, referring to the acclaimed late writer's Norwegian roots. There have also been calls from the public for a permanent statue of him to be erected in the city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walesonline.co.uk/news/wales-news/2009/03/27/roald-dahl-and-the-chinese-chip-shop-91466-23243373/ Roald Dahl and the Chinese chip shop], WalesOnline, 27 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dahl's charitable commitments in the fields of [[neurology]], [[haematology]] and [[literacy]] have been continued by his widow since his death, through Roald Dahl's Marvellous Children's Charity, formerly known as the Roald Dahl Foundation.&lt;ref name=TELG/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marvellouschildrenscharity.org/ |title=Roald Dahl's Marvellous Children's Charity |publisher=Marvellouschildrenscharity.org |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2005, the [[Roald Dahl Museum and Story Centre]] opened in [[Great Missenden]] to celebrate the work of Roald Dahl and advance his work in literacy education.&lt;ref&gt;Clarie Heald (11 June 2005) [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4079720.stm Chocolate doors thrown open to Dahl] ''[[BBC News]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David Hurst (20 June 2005) [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/travel/holidaytypeshub/article-593996/Roald-Dahls-fantasy-factory.html Roald Dahl's fantasy factory] ''[[The Daily Mail]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the UK charity Booktrust and [[Children's Laureate]] [[Michael Rosen]] inaugurated '''The Roald Dahl Funny Prize''', an annual award to authors of humorous children's fiction.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-11340344 David Walliams up for Roald Dahl award] ''[[BBC News]]'.' Retrieved 4 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roalddahlprize.org |title=The Roald Dahl Funny Prize |publisher=Roalddahlprize.org |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 September 2009 (the day after what would have been Dahl's 93rd birthday) the first [[blue plaque]] in his honour was unveiled in [[Llandaff]], Cardiff, Wales.&lt;ref name=CDF/&gt; Rather than commemorating his place of birth, however, the plaque was erected on the wall of the former sweet shop (and site of &quot;The Great Mouse Plot of 1924&quot;) that features in the first part of his autobiography ''[[Boy (book)|Boy]]''. It was unveiled by his widow Felicity and son Theo.&lt;ref name=CDF&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/south_east/8253467.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; Wales &amp;#124; South East Wales &amp;#124; Blue plaque marks Dahl sweet shop |publisher=BBC News |date=14 September 2009|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In honour of Roald Dahl, Gibraltar Post issued a set of four stamps in 2010 featuring [[Quentin Blake]]'s original illustrations for four of the children's books written by Dahl during his long career; ''[[The BFG]]'', ''[[The Twits]]'', ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'' and ''[[Matilda (novel)|Matilda]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldstampnews.com/2010/05/gibraltar-will-launch-a-roald-dahl-set-of-stamps/#more-213 |title=&quot;UK world's best selling children author on Gibraltar stamps&quot; '&amp;#39;World Stamp News'&amp;#39; |publisher=Worldstampnews.com |date=15 May 2010 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl's influence has extended beyond literary figures, and he connected with film director [[Tim Burton]] with his &quot;mixture of light and darkness, and not speaking down to kids, and the kind of politically incorrect humour that kids get&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Tim Burton, Mark Salisbury, Johnny Depp (2008) [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=-GY9R1c_kKgC&amp;pg=PA223&amp;dq=gene+wilder+charlie+and+the+chocolate+factory&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=4FgNTcGLGYaEhQfP26y4Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwBTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=gene%20wilder%20charlie%20and%20the%20chocolate%20factory&amp;f=false Burton on Burton] Macmillan, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Regarded as &quot;one of the greatest storytellers for children of the 20th century&quot;,&lt;ref name=IND&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/commentators/once-upon-a-time-there-was-a-man-who-liked-to-make-up-stories-2158052.html Once upon a time, there was a man who liked to make up stories ...] ''[[The Independent]]'' (Sunday, 12 December 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl was listed as one of the greatest British writers since 1945.&lt;ref name=TIM/&gt; He ranks amongst the [[List of best-selling fiction authors|world's best-selling fiction authors]] with sales estimated at over 100&amp;nbsp;million,&lt;ref name=INT&gt;[http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/14817244/from/ET/38893930 Britain celebrates first Roald Dahl Day] ''[[msnbc]]'': &quot;Dahl's books, many of them darkly comic and featuring villainous adult enemies of the child characters, have sold over 100&amp;nbsp;million copies.&quot; (13 September 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BDC&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/5341084.stm Fans gather for Dahl celebration] ''[[BBC News]]'': &quot;Exhibitions and children's reading campaigns are being held to commemorate the life of Dahl, who died in 1990 and has sold more than 100&amp;nbsp;million books.&quot; (13 September 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; and his books have been published in almost 50 languages.&lt;ref name=guard/&gt; In 2003, the UK survey entitled ''[[The Big Read]]'' carried out by the [[BBC]] in order to find the &quot;nation's best loved novel&quot; of all time, four of Dahl's books were named in the Top 100, with only works by [[Charles Dickens]] and [[Terry Pratchett]] featuring more.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/arts/bigread/top100.shtml BBC&amp;nbsp;– The Big Read&amp;nbsp;– Top 100 Books]. Retrieved 15 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The anniversary of Dahl's birthday on 13 September is celebrated as &quot;Roald Dahl Day&quot; in Africa, the United Kingdom, and Latin America.&lt;ref name=guard&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2010/sep/13/roald-dahl-day-september-events Roald Dahl Day expands into full month of special treats] ''[[The Guardian]]'.' Retrieved 1 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roalddahlmuseum.org/whatson/roalddahlday.aspx Roald Dahl Day celebrations], Roald Dahl Museum and Story Centre . Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.randomhouse.co.uk/childrens/roalddahl/day/ Roald Dahl's 90th Birthday!], Random House UK . Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writing==
[[Image:Deviousdahl.jpg|right|thumb|Roald Dahl's story &quot;The Devious Bachelor&quot; was illustrated by [[Frederick Siebel]] when it was published in ''[[Collier's Weekly|Collier's]]'' (September 1953).]]
Dahl's first published work, inspired by a meeting with [[C. S. Forester]], was &quot;A Piece Of Cake&quot; on 1 August 1942. The story, about his wartime adventures, was bought by ''The Saturday Evening Post'' for US$1000 (a substantial sum in 1942) and published under the title &quot;Shot Down Over Libya&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Frances E. Ruffin [http://books.google.com/books?id=Cb6dtVe5VeYC&amp;pg=PA17&amp;dq=Saturday+Evening+Post+Shot+Down+Over+Libya&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=d-UQTd_6EMiHhQe04pG3Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Saturday%20Evening%20Post%20Shot%20Down%20Over%20Libya&amp;f=false Meet Roald Dahl] The Rosen Publishing Group, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

His first children's book was ''[[The Gremlins]]'', about mischievous little creatures that were part of [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] folklore.&lt;ref name=dong&gt;Donald, Graeme [http://books.google.com/books?id=QlmwkeBINiYC&amp;pg=PA147&amp;dq=RAF+pilots+blamed+gremlins&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=wuwQTeKBNsaJhQfrho23Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Sticklers, Sideburns &amp; Bikinis: The Military Origins of Everyday Words and Phrases] Osprey Publishing, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; All the RAF pilots blamed the [[gremlin]]s for all the problems with the plane. The book, which First Lady of the US [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] read to her grandchildren,&lt;ref name=dong/&gt; was commissioned by [[Walt Disney]] for a film that was never made, and published in 1943. Dahl went on to create some of the best-loved children's stories of the 20th century, such as ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'', ''[[Matilda (novel)|Matilda]]'', ''[[James and the Giant Peach]]'', ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'', ''[[Charlie and the Great Glass Elevator]]'', ''[[The BFG]]'', ''[[George's Marvellous Medicine]]'' and ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]''.

Dahl also had a successful parallel career as the writer of macabre adult short stories, usually with a dark sense of humour and a surprise ending.&lt;ref name=arwd/&gt; The [[Mystery Writers of America]] presented Dahl with three [[Edgar Awards]] for his work, and many were originally written for American magazines such as ''[[Collier's Weekly|Collier's]]'', ''[[Ladies Home Journal]]'', ''[[Harper's Magazine|Harper's]]'', ''[[Playboy]]'' and ''[[The New Yorker]]''. Works such as ''[[Kiss Kiss (book)|Kiss Kiss]]'' subsequently collected Dahl's stories into anthologies, gaining worldwide acclaim. Dahl wrote more than 60 short stories; they have appeared in numerous collections, some only being published in book form after his death (See [[List of Roald Dahl short stories]]). His three Edgar Awards were given for: in 1954, the collection ''Someone Like You''; in 1959, the story &quot;[[The Landlady]]&quot;; and in 1980, the episode of ''[[Tales of the Unexpected (TV series)|Tales of the Unexpected]]'' based on &quot;[[Skin (short story)|Skin]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=arwd&gt;Andrew Maunder [http://books.google.com/books?id=Px9s1oIjj88C&amp;pg=PA96&amp;dq=roald+dahl+edgar+award&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=_eYQTd2UMY2IhQen4PS2Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=roald%20dahl%20edgar%20award&amp;f=false The Facts On File companion to the British short story] Infobase Publishing, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

One of his more famous adult stories, &quot;The Smoker&quot; (also known as &quot;[[Man from the South|Man From the South]]&quot;), was filmed twice as both 1960 and 1985 episodes of ''[[Alfred Hitchcock Presents]]'', and also adapted into [[Quentin Tarantino]]'s segment of the 1995 film ''[[Four Rooms]]''.&lt;ref name=quet/&gt; This oft-anthologised classic concerns a man in Jamaica who wagers with visitors in an attempt to claim the fingers from their hands. The 1960 Hitchcock version stars [[Steve McQueen (actor)|Steve McQueen]] and [[Peter Lorre]].&lt;ref name=quet&gt;James Mottram [http://books.google.com/books?id=-GZvT_iUIhkC&amp;pg=PA95&amp;dq=roald+dahl+man+from+the+south+-+hitchcock&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=IvQQTdGMGcHDhAf86523Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CFQQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=roald%20dahl%20man%20from%20the%20south%20-%20hitchcock&amp;f=false The Sundance kids: how the mavericks took back Hollywood] Macmillan, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

His short story collection ''Tales of the Unexpected'' was adapted to a successful [[Tales of the Unexpected (TV series)|TV series of the same name]], beginning with &quot;Man From the South&quot;.&lt;ref name=totu&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Px9s1oIjj88C&amp;pg=PA417&amp;dq=dahl+tales+of+the+unexpected&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=B_UQTcK8CYyGhQe2zsy3Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=dahl%20tales%20of%20the%20unexpected&amp;f=false The Facts On File companion to the British short story] p.417.&lt;/ref&gt; When the stock of Dahl's own original stories was exhausted, the series continued by adapting stories by authors that were written in Dahl's style, including the writers [[John Collier (writer)|John Collier]] and [[Stanley Ellin]].

He acquired a traditional [[Romanichal]] [[Vardo (gypsy wagon)|Gypsy wagon]] in the 1960s, and the family used it as a playhouse for his children. He later used the ''vardo'' as a writing room, where he wrote the book ''[[Danny, the Champion of the World]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gypsywaggons.co.uk/varsuk.htm |title=English Gypsy caravan, Gypsy Wagon, Gypsy Waggon and Vardo: Photograph Gallery 1 |publisher=Gypsywaggons.co.uk |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of his short stories are supposed to be extracts from the diary of his (fictional) Uncle Oswald, a rich gentleman whose sexual exploits form the subject of these stories.&lt;ref name=OSW/&gt; In his novel ''[[My Uncle Oswald]]'', the uncle engages a temptress to seduce 20th century geniuses and royalty with a love potion secretly added to chocolate truffles made by Dahl's favourite chocolate shop, [[Prestat]] of Piccadilly.&lt;ref name=OSW&gt;Darrell Schweitzer (1985) [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=YTL_YsSp4r8C&amp;pg=PA125&amp;dq=fictional+my+Uncle+Oswald&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ZNYHTZKgEdSAhAePpJTBAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=fictional%20my%20Uncle%20Oswald&amp;f=false Discovering modern horror fiction, Volume 2] Wildside Press LLC, 1985&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Memories with Food at Gipsy House]]'', written with his wife Felicity and published posthumously in 1991, was a mixture of recipes, family reminiscences and Dahl's musings on favourite subjects such as chocolate, onions, and claret.&lt;ref name=TELG&gt;Sally Williams (12 Sep 2006) [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/foodanddrink/recipes/3334427/A-plateful-of-Dahl.html A plateful of Dahl] ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'.' Retrieved 4 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=mMDjAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Memories+with+Food+at+Gipsy+House&amp;dq=Memories+with+Food+at+Gipsy+House&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=YdUHTfnoBIPOhAfh24zuBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CFAQ6AEwCA Books magazine, Volumes 5–7] p.35. Publishing News Ltd., 1991&lt;/ref&gt;

===Children's fiction===
Dahl's children's works are usually told from the point of view of a child. They typically involve adult [[villain]]s who hate and mistreat children, and feature at least one &quot;good&quot; adult to counteract the villain(s). These stock characters are possibly a reference to the abuse that Dahl stated that he experienced in the [[boarding school]]s he attended.&lt;ref name=IND/&gt; They usually contain a lot of [[black comedy|black humour]] and grotesque scenarios, including gruesome violence. ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'', ''[[George's Marvellous Medicine]]'' and ''[[Matilda (novel)|Matilda]]'' are examples of this formula. ''[[The BFG]]'' follows it in a more analogous way with the good giant (the BFG or &quot;Big Friendly Giant&quot;) representing the &quot;good adult&quot; archetype and the other giants being the &quot;bad adults&quot;. This formula is also somewhat evident in Dahl's film script for ''[[Chitty Chitty Bang Bang (film)|Chitty Chitty Bang Bang]]''. Class-conscious themes&amp;nbsp;– ranging from the thinly veiled to the blatant&amp;nbsp;– also surface in works such as ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]'' and ''[[Danny, the Champion of the World]]''.

Dahl also features in his books characters who are very fat, usually children. [[Augustus Gloop]], Bruce Bogtrotter, and Bruno Jenkins are a few of these characters, although an enormous woman named Aunt Sponge is featured in ''[[James and the Giant Peach]]'' and the nasty farmer Boggis in ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]'' is an enormously fat character. All of these characters (with the possible exception of Bruce Bogtrotter) are either villains or simply unpleasant gluttons. They are usually punished for this: Augustus Gloop drinks from [[Willy Wonka]]'s chocolate river, disregarding the adults who tell him not to, and falls in, getting sucked up a pipe and nearly being turned into fudge. Bruce Bogtrotter steals cake from the evil headmistress, Miss Trunchbull, and is forced to eat a gigantic chocolate cake in front of the school. Bruno Jenkins is turned into a mouse by witches who lure him to their convention with the promise of chocolate, and, it is speculated, possibly disowned or even killed by his parents because of this. Aunt Sponge is flattened by a giant peach. Dahl's mother used to tell him and his sisters tales about trolls and other mythical Norwegian creatures and some of his children's books contain references or elements inspired by these stories, such as the giants in ''[[The BFG]]'', the fox family in ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]'' and the trolls in ''[[The Minpins]]''.

In his poetry, Dahl gives a humorous re-interpretation of well-known nursery rhymes and [[fairy tales]], providing surprise endings in place of the traditional happily-ever-after. Dahl's collection of poems ''[[Revolting Rhymes]]'' is recorded in [[audio book]] form, and narrated by actor [[Alan Cumming]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?ei=lDYYTeqYKcfPhAfYudS4Dg&amp;ct=result&amp;id=Y7aeAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=audio+book+dirty+beasts&amp;q=alan+cumming AV guide, Volumes 77–82] Scranton Gillette Communications, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

===Screenplays===
For a brief period in the 1960s, Dahl wrote screenplays. Two, the [[James Bond]] film ''[[You Only Live Twice (film)|You Only Live Twice]]'' and ''[[Chitty Chitty Bang Bang]]'', were adaptations of novels by [[Ian Fleming]], though both were rewritten and completed by other writers. Dahl created the [[Child Catcher]], the supporting antagonist in ''Chitty Chitty Bang Bang'', and in a 2005 poll, it was voted the scariest villain in children's literature.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/cbbcnews/hi/newsid_4520000/newsid_4529100/4529175.stm Childcatcher is scariest villain] ''[[BBC]]'' Retrieved 31 January 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl also began adapting his own novel ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory'', which was completed and rewritten by [[David Seltzer]] after Dahl failed to meet deadlines, and produced as the film ''[[Willy Wonka &amp; the Chocolate Factory]]'' (1971). Dahl later disowned the film, saying he was &quot;disappointed&quot; because &quot;he thought it placed too much emphasis on Willy Wonka and not enough on Charlie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Liz Buckingham, trustee for the Roald Dahl Museum, quoted in Tom Bishop: &quot;Willy Wonka's Everlasting Film Plot&quot;, BBC News, July 2005 http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4660873.stm&lt;/ref&gt; He was also &quot;infuriated&quot; by the deviations in the plot devised by David Seltzer in his draft of the screenplay. This resulted in his refusal for any more versions of the book to be made in his lifetime.&lt;ref&gt;Tom Bishop (July 2005) [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4660873.stm Willy Wonka's Everlasting Film Plot] ''[[BBC News]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Influences===
A major part of Dahl's literary influences stemmed from his childhood. In his younger days, he was an avid reader, especially awed by fantastic tales of heroism and triumph. Amongst his favourite authors were [[Rudyard Kipling]], [[William Makepeace Thackeray]], [[Frederick Marryat]] and [[Charles Dickens]], and their works went on to make a lasting mark on his life and writing. Dahl was also a huge fan of ghost stories and claimed that ''Trolls'' by [[Jonas Lie]] was one of the finest ghost stories ever written. While he was still a youngster, his mother, Sofie Dahl, would relate traditional Norwegian myths and legends from her native homeland to Dahl and his sisters. Dahl always maintained that his mother and her stories had a strong influence on his writing. In one interview, he mentioned: &quot;She was a great teller of tales. Her memory was prodigious and nothing that ever happened to her in her life was forgotten.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/3559378/Roald-Dahl-young-tales-of-the-unexpected.html Roald Dahl: young tales of the unexpected] ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'' (30 August 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; When Dahl started writing and publishing his famous books for children, he created a grandmother character in ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'' and later stated that she was based directly on his own mother as a tribute.&lt;ref name=&quot;infloox.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infloox.com/influence?id=e00077f Influence of Sofie Dahl on Roald Dahl] infloox.com&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===
In 1961, Dahl hosted and wrote for a science fiction and [[Horror and terror|horror]] television [[anthology series]] called ''[[Way Out (TV series)|Way Out]]'', which preceded the ''[[Twilight Zone]]'' series on the [[CBS]] network for 14 episodes&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0054574/ Way Out (TV Series 1961)] [[IMDB]]&lt;/ref&gt; from March to July. Dahl's comedic monologues rounded off the episodes, frequently explaining exactly how to murder one's spouse without getting caught. In one introduction, Dahl ruminated about the popularity of the crewcut at the time and how it seemed to make some men feel tougher. The former fighter pilot dryly observed that &quot;....it really doesn't help when the chips are down, though, does it?&quot;{{citation needed|date=May 2011}}

One of the last dramatic network shows shot in New York City, the entire series is available for viewing at [[The Paley Center for Media]] in New York City and Los Angeles.

''[[Tales of the Unexpected (TV series)|Tales of the Unexpected]]'' is a British television series that originally aired between 1979 and 1988, made by Anglia Television for [[ITV]]. The series had been released to tie in with Dahl's ''[[Tales of the Unexpected (book)|Tales of the Unexpected]]'', which had introduced readers to many motifs that were common in his writing.&lt;ref name=totu/&gt;

The series was an anthology of different tales, initially based on Dahl's short stories.&lt;ref name=totu/&gt; The stories were sometimes sinister, sometimes wryly comedic, and usually had a twist ending. Dahl introduced on camera all the episodes of the first two series, which bore the full title ''Roald Dahl's Tales of the Unexpected''.&lt;ref&gt;Vincent Terrace (1985) [http://books.google.com/books?id=AKlgjBCPPnsC&amp;pg=PA406&amp;dq=tales+of+the+unexpected+roald+dahl+-+TV&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=9fcQTdHyHIGHhQewq7i3Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Encyclopedia of Television Series, Pilots and Specials: 1974–1984]&lt;/ref&gt; Dahl also chose the stories not written by him to be adapted for the second series, and a small number of additional Dahl stories were adapted for the third series onwards following his departure.

==Bibliography==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}

===Children's stories===
# ''[[The Gremlins]]'' (1943)
# ''[[James and the Giant Peach]]'' (1961)&amp;nbsp;– Film: ''[[James and the Giant Peach (film)|James and the Giant Peach]]'' (live-action/animated) (1996)
# ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'' (1964)&lt;ref name=n1 group=nn&gt;Published in 1978 in an omnibus edition titled ''The Complete Adventures of Charlie and Willy Wonka''&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– Films: ''[[Willy Wonka &amp; the Chocolate Factory]]'' (1971) and ''[[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory (film)|Charlie and the Chocolate Factory]]'' (2005)
# ''[[The Magic Finger]]'' (1 June 1966)
# ''[[Fantastic Mr Fox]]'' (9 December 1970)&amp;nbsp;– Film: ''[[Fantastic Mr. Fox (film)|Fantastic Mr. Fox]]'' (animated) (2009)
# ''[[Charlie and the Great Glass Elevator]]'' (9 January 1972)&lt;ref name=n1 group=nn/&gt; A sequel to ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory''.
# ''[[Danny, the Champion of the World]]'' (30 October 1975)&amp;nbsp;– Film: ''[[Danny the Champion of the World#TV Movie|Danny the Champion of the World]]'' (TV movie) (1989)
# ''[[The Enormous Crocodile]]'' (24 August 1978)
# ''[[The Twits]]'' (17 December 1980)
# ''[[George's Marvellous Medicine]]'' (21 May 1981)
# ''[[The BFG]]'' (14 October 1982)&amp;nbsp;– Film: ''[[The BFG (film)|The BFG]]'' (animated) (1989)
# ''[[The Witches (book)|The Witches]]'' (27 October 1983)&amp;nbsp;– Film: ''[[The Witches (1990 film)|The Witches]]'' (1990)
# ''[[The Giraffe and the Pelly and Me]]'' (26 September 1985)
# ''[[Matilda (novel)|Matilda]]'' (21 April 1988)&amp;nbsp;– Film: ''[[Matilda (film)|Matilda]]'' (1996)
# ''[[Esio Trot]]'' (19 April 1989)
# ''[[The Vicar of Nibbleswicke]]'' (9 May 1990)
# ''[[The Minpins]]'' (8 August 1991)

;Children's poetry
#''[[Revolting Rhymes]]'' (10 June 1982)
#''[[Dirty Beasts]]'' (25 October 1984)
#''[[Rhyme Stew]]'' (21 September 1989)
{{col-2}}

===Adult fiction===
;Novels
# ''[[Sometime Never: A Fable for Supermen]]'' (1948)
# ''[[My Uncle Oswald]]'' (1979)

;Short story collections
# ''[[Over To You: Ten Stories of Flyers and Flying]]'' (1946)
# ''[[Someone Like You (collection)|Someone Like You]]'' (1953)
# ''[[Lamb to the Slaughter]]'' (1953)
# ''[[Kiss Kiss (book)|Kiss Kiss]]'' (1960)
# ''[[Twenty-Nine Kisses from Roald Dahl]]'' (1969)
# ''[[Switch Bitch]]'' (1974)
# ''[[The Wonderful Story of Henry Sugar and Six More]]'' (1977)
# ''[[The Best of Roald Dahl]]'' (1978)
# ''[[Tales of the Unexpected (book)|Tales of the Unexpected]]'' (1979)
# ''[[More Tales of the Unexpected]]'' (1980)
# ''[[Roald Dahl's Book of Ghost Stories]]'' (1983). Edited with an introduction by Dahl.
# ''[[The Roald Dahl Omnibus]]'' (Dorset Press, 1986)
# ''[[Two Fables]]'' (1986). &quot;Princess and the Poacher&quot; and &quot;Princess Mammalia&quot;.
# ''[[Ah, Sweet Mystery of Life: The Country Stories of Roald Dahl]]'' (1989)
# ''[[The Collected Short Stories of Dahl]]'' (1991)
# ''[[The Roald Dahl Treasury]]'' (1997)
# ''[[The Great Automatic Grammatizator]]'' (1997). (Known in the USA as ''The Umbrella Man and Other Stories'').
# ''[[Skin And Other Stories]]'' (2000)
# ''[[Roald Dahl: Collected Stories]]'' (2006)

See the alphabetical [[List of Roald Dahl short stories]]. See also ''[[Roald Dahl: Collected Stories]]'' for a complete, chronological listing.
{{col-end}}
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}

===Non-fiction===
# ''[[The Mildenhall Treasure]]'' (1946, 1977, 1999)
# ''[[Boy (book)|Boy&amp;nbsp;– Tales of Childhood]]'' (1984) Recollections up to the age of 20, looking particularly at schooling in Britain in the early part of the 20th century.
# ''[[Going Solo]]'' (1986) Continuation of his autobiography, in which he goes to work for [[Royal Dutch Shell|Shell]] and spends some time working in [[Tanzania]] before joining the war effort and becoming one of the last [[Allied]] pilots to withdraw from Greece during the German invasion.
# ''Measles, a Dangerous Illness'' (1986)&lt;ref&gt;Source: written for a leaflet published in 1986 by Sandwell Health Authority (now [[Sandwell and West Birmingham Hospitals NHS Trust]]). Reproduced at [http://www.blacktriangle.org/blog/?p=715 http://www.blacktriangle.org/blog/?p=715].&lt;/ref&gt;
# ''[[Memories with Food at Gipsy House]]'' (1991)
# ''[[Roald Dahl's Guide to Railway Safety]]'' (1991)
# ''[[My Year]]'' (1993)
# ''Roald Dahl's Revolting Recipes'' by Felicity Dahl, ''et al.'' (1994), a collection of recipes based on and inspired by food in Dahl's books, created by Roald &amp; Felicity Dahl, and Josie Fison
# ''Roald Dahl's Even More Revolting Recipes'' by Felicity Dahl, ''et al.'' (2001)

===Plays===
# ''[[The Honeys (play)|The Honeys]]'' (1955) Produced at the Longacre Theater on Broadway.
{{col-2}}

===Film scripts===
# ''[[The Gremlins]]'' (1943)
# ''[[36 Hours]]'' (1965)
# ''[[You Only Live Twice (film)|You Only Live Twice]]'' (1967)
# ''[[Chitty Chitty Bang Bang (film)|Chitty Chitty Bang Bang]]'' (1968)
# ''[[The Night Digger]]'' (1971)
# ''[[Willy Wonka &amp; the Chocolate Factory]]'' (1971)

===Television===
# ''[[Way Out (TV series)|Way Out]]'' (1961) Horror series hosted by Roald Dahl and produced by [[David Susskind]]
# ''[[Alfred Hitchcock Presents]]'': &quot;[[Lamb to the Slaughter]]&quot; (1958)
# ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'': &quot;[[Dip in the Pool]]&quot; (1958)
# ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'': &quot;Poison&quot; (1958)
# ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'': &quot;[[Man from the South]]&quot; (1960) with [[Steve McQueen (actor)|Steve McQueen]] and [[Peter Lorre]]
# ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'': &quot;[[Mrs. Bixby and the Colonel's Coat]]&quot; (1960)
# ''Alfred Hitchcock Presents'': &quot;[[The Landlady]]&quot; (1961)
# ''[[Tales of the Unexpected (TV series)|Tales of the Unexpected]]'' (1979–1988), episodes written and introduced by Dahl
{{col-end}}
{{Reflist|group=nn}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Sources==
*Philip Howard, &quot;Dahl, Roald (1916–1990)&quot;, ''[[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]'', Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn, May 2006 http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/39827 accessed 24 May 2006
*Donald Sturrock, ''Storyteller: The Life of Roald Dahl'', Harper Press, 2010. ISBN 9880007254767 (See the link to excerpts in &quot;External Links&quot;, below.)

==External links==
{{Wikiquote|Roald Dahl}}
{{Wikipedia books|Roald Dahl}}
*{{Official website|http://www.roalddahl.com}}
*[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/biographyandmemoirreviews/7930233/Roald-Dahls-darkest-hour.html Roald Dahl's darkest hour (biography excerpt)]
*{{isfdb name|id=Roald_Dahl|name=Roald Dahl}}
*{{IMDb name|id=0001094|name=Roald Dahl}}
*{{OL_author|id=OL34184A}}
*[http://www1.nrk.no/nett-tv/klipp/7365 Radio interview with Dahl in Norwegian by NRK (1975)]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/19/books/review/Heilbrunn-t.html ''The Irregulars, Roald Dahl and the British Spy Ring in Wartime Washington,'' 2008], New York Times Review, 17 October 2008.
*[http://www.voanews.com/learningenglish/home/Patricia-Neal-1926-2010-Actress-Had-Great-Success-and-Personal-Tragedy-116810828.html February 2011 profile of Patricia Neal on V.O.A.]
*[http://www.itnsource.com/shotlist//ITN/1982/11/09/AS091182009/ Footage of Roald Dahl judging at the Whitbread book prize in 1982 ]
{{Roald Dahl}}
{{Charlie and the Chocolate Factory}}
{{early20CBritChildrensLiterature}}
{{World Fantasy Award Life Achievement}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME= Dahl, Roald
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Norwegian and British novelist, short story writer
|DATE OF BIRTH= 13 September 1916
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Llandaff]], [[Cardiff]], Wales
|DATE OF DEATH= 23 November 1990
|PLACE OF DEATH= [[Oxford]], Oxfordshire, England}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dahl, Roald}}
[[Category:1916 births]]
[[Category:1990 deaths]]
[[Category:Absurdist fiction]]
[[Category:British children's writers]]
[[Category:British horror writers]]
[[Category:British novelists]]
[[Category:British people of Norwegian descent]]
[[Category:British short story writers]]
[[Category:British World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in England]]
[[Category:Edgar Award winners]]
[[Category:King's African Rifles officers]]
[[Category:Old Llandavians]]
[[Category:Old Reptonians]]
[[Category:People from Llandaff]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force officers]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Welsh children's writers]]
[[Category:Welsh people of Norwegian descent]]
[[Category:Welsh fantasy writers]]
[[Category:Welsh writers]]
[[Category:Willy Wonka]]
[[Category:Children's poets]]

{{Link GA|zh}}
[[af:Roald Dahl]]
[[ar:روالد دال]]
[[ast:Roald Dahl]]
[[bn:রুয়াল দাল]]
[[br:Roald Dahl]]
[[bg:Роалд Дал]]
[[ca:Roald Dahl]]
[[cs:Roald Dahl]]
[[cy:Roald Dahl]]
[[da:Roald Dahl]]
[[de:Roald Dahl]]
[[et:Roald Dahl]]
[[el:Ρόαλντ Νταλ]]
[[es:Roald Dahl]]
[[eu:Roald Dahl]]
[[fa:رولد دال]]
[[fo:Roald Dahl]]
[[fr:Roald Dahl]]
[[gl:Roald Dahl]]
[[ko:로알드 달]]
[[hr:Roald Dahl]]
[[id:Roald Dahl]]
[[is:Roald Dahl]]
[[it:Roald Dahl]]
[[he:רואלד דאל]]
[[hu:Roald Dahl]]
[[nah:Roald Dahl]]
[[nl:Roald Dahl]]
[[ja:ロアルド・ダール]]
[[no:Roald Dahl]]
[[nn:Roald Dahl]]
[[pl:Roald Dahl]]
[[pt:Roald Dahl]]
[[ro:Roald Dahl]]
[[ru:Даль, Роальд]]
[[sc:Roald Dahl]]
[[sco:Roald Dahl]]
[[simple:Roald Dahl]]
[[sk:Roald Dahl]]
[[sl:Roald Dahl]]
[[fi:Roald Dahl]]
[[sv:Roald Dahl]]
[[ta:ரூவால் டால்]]
[[th:โรอัลด์ ดาห์ล]]
[[tr:Roald Dahl]]
[[uk:Роальд Дал]]
[[vls:Roald Dahl]]
[[zh:羅爾德·達爾]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
