<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5549285" ns="0" title="Monte Ahuja College of Business"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name=Cleveland State University
|image=
|motto=
|established=1964
|city=[[Cleveland]]
|state=[[Ohio]]|
country=[[United States|USA]]
|website=http://www.csuohio.edu/business}} 
The '''Monte Ahuja College of Business''' is the [[business school]] at [[Cleveland State University]] in [[Cleveland]], [[Ohio]]. With more than 3,000 current students and over 19,000 alumni, the Monte Ahuja College of Business ranks among the largest in Ohio.  It is fully accredited by the [[AACSB]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.csuohio.edu/business/prospstudents/nanceatglance.html&lt;/ref&gt; and currently offers two undergraduate degrees with numerous concentrations: Bachelor of Business Administration (BBA) and the Bachelor of Science in Computer &amp; Information Science (BSCIS). It also offers six graduate degree programs, two dual graduate degree programs, and one doctoral degree program.

Formerly the '''Nance College of Business Administration''', the CSU Board of Trustees unanimously voted to rename the school in June 2011 after former CSU Board of Trustees chair Monte Ahuja, who donated $10 million to the school, the largest gift in the University’s 47-year history.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | title= Ahuja donates $10 million to CSU: Business school renamed the Monte Ahuja College of Business | date=2011-06-28| accessdate=2011-06-28 | url=http://www.wtam.com/cc-common/news/sections/newsarticle.html?feed=122520&amp;article=8767368 | }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Location==
Monte Ahuja College of Business is located in [[Downtown Cleveland]]. It is bounded on the East 18th Street of [[Euclid Avenue (Cleveland, Ohio)|Euclid Avenue]] and Chester Avenue.

==Programs and majors==
The college is ranked in the top ten nationwide in performance of its [[Certified Public Accountant]] graduate students.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}  At nearly 1,000 companies around the county, a Cleveland State University graduate is at the helm as CEO, president or chairman.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}  Its Ahuja Accounting Programs are among a select group of only 168 accounting programs worldwide that hold Accounting Accreditation from AACSB International—the hallmark of management education.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.csuohio.edu/business/academics/act&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.csuohio.edu/cba/fin/ Ahuja's Department of Finance] is known nationally and internationally as a leading Center for [[real estate]] research. The department's strength lies in three areas: 

*Corporate Finance and Investment
*Financial Institutions
*Real Estate

The Finance faculty have been widely recognized outside the university for their scholarly achievements. Recent faculty awards and recognition include: 

*An appointment to the National Distinguished Fellows Program of the National Association of Industrial and Office Properties
*[[Fulbright Scholar]] Awards to teach in Bulgaria and Latvia
*A grant from the State of South Carolina to work on Medicare reform

The department is also very active in encouraging many of its finance majors to take and pass the [[Chartered Financial Analyst]] Examinations (CFA). 

===Undergraduate majors===
[[Image:Nance College Of Business Administration1.JPG|thumb|Monte Ahuja Hall, Monte Ahuja College of Business]]
'''BBA'''
*Accounting 
*Business Economics
*Finance 
*Information Systems and Technology 
*International Business 
*Management &amp; Labor Relations 
*Marketing 
*Operations And Supply Chain Management 

'''BSCIS major fields of study'''
*Computer &amp; Information Science 
*Computer Science

===Graduate programs===
[[File:Sanborn-CSU.jpg|thumb|right|''Adam Smith's Spinning Top'', sculpture by [[Jim Sanborn]] outside Monte Ahuja Hall]]
*Master of Accountancy (MACC)
*MBA, Master of Business Administration (Various Concentrations Offered)
*EMBA, Executive Master of Business Administration
*MBA in Health Care Administration (MBA-HCA)
*Master of Computer &amp; Information Science (MCIS)
*Master of Labor Relations/Human Resources (MLRHR)
*Master of Public Health (MPH)
*MBA/Juris Doctor (JD/MBA) 
*MBA/Master of Science in Nursing (MSN/MBA) 
*Doctor of Business Administration (DBA)

===Global Business Center===
The Global Business Center was created to sustain education and training programs in global business. It also promotes the region’s global competitiveness and to expand the presence of the region’s entrepreneurs in the global market.

The Global Business Center relies on the expertise of a cross-functional, interdisciplinary team of faculty, scholars and Advisory Board members to provide the region with innovative International Business education programs, research and related business services.

In addition, the Center has partnered with [[World Trade Center Cleveland]] and the [[Beachwood Business Development Center]] to provide customized services and programs to foreign companies looking to invest in local markets. The partnership also serves domestic companies looking to invest in most foreign markets.

==Honors==
The college was honored on June 21, 2006 with the [[Governor of Ohio|Ohio Governor]]'s Excellence in Exporting Award, presented by then-Governor [[Bob Taft]].&lt;ref&gt;Ohio Department of Development, http://www.development.ohio.gov/newsroom/2006PR/releases/1607.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;
==External links==
*[http://www.csuohio.edu/business/ Monte Ahuja College of Business]
*[http://engagenance.com Engage Nance]

{{coord missing|Ohio}}

[[Category:Business schools in Ohio]]
[[Category:Cleveland State University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
