<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5630655" ns="0" title="Coronji Calhoun"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|date=May 2008}}
{{BLP IMDB refimprove|date=October 2007}}
{{Infobox person
| image =
| caption =
| birth_date = {{birth year and age|1991}}
| birth_place =

}}

'''Coronji Calhoun''' (born 1991) is an [[United States|American]] actor. He portrayed Tyrell, the morbidly obese son of Lawrence and Leticia Musgrove in the 2001 movie [[Monster's Ball]].

&quot;Perhaps one of the most affecting performances of the year was given by a 10-year-old [[Louisiana]] fourth-grader who has never acted before or studied the craft,&quot; commented ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' reporter Christopher Grove. Indeed, many people were particularly moved by&amp;mdash;and concerned with&amp;mdash;the youth who played Tyrell Musgrove. Calhoun was chosen from an open [[Casting (performing arts)|casting call]], and was paid the minimum [[union scale]] for his work. He also suffered demonstrably from [[obesity]]. Tyrell's [[chocolate]] [[Behavioral addiction|addiction]] was based on his hunger for his absent father.

In a [[feature story|feature]] [[interview]] by ''iofilm.co.uk'' columnist Paul Fischer, Berry discussed working with Coronji, including the scene where she as Leticia strikes him for hiding candy. &quot;Marc (the director) and I were talking to him, saying this is just a movie, and I kept saying, everything I do and say, it's not real. I really think you're wonderful. And he said, 'Well, whatever you do to me, Halle Berry, it isn't going to be worse than what the kids at school do to me.'&quot;

On the film's website, which has since been removed, Coronji was described as being a normal child who enjoyed playing basketball and video games and who liked to dance. Still others suggested that something more should have been done for the boy by giving him a scholarship or a commemorative [[trust fund]] for his work. As Tyrell, Coronji poignantly brought his own experience about being fat, sensitive and artistic to the screen.

Coronji Calhoun was listed as missing on a Web site seeking to find and reunite survivors of [[Hurricane Katrina]]. It was later revealed that he was living some 25 miles outside of New Orleans in a town that sustained little damage from the hurricane.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{IMDb name|1017716}}
*{{Amg name|301019}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Calhoun, Coronji
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = American actor
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1991
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Calhoun, Coronji}}
[[Category:1991 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American child actors]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:Actors from Louisiana]]


{{US-film-actor-1990s-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
