<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="563766" ns="0" title="Devils Lake (North Dakota)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Devils Lake (disambiguation)}}

{{Infobox lake
| lake_name = Devils Lake
| image_lake = Devilslake 03 22 2009.jpg|450 px
| caption_lake = View from space (March 2009)
| image_bathymetry =
| caption_bathymetry =
| location = [[Ramsey County, North Dakota|Ramsey]] / [[Benson County, North Dakota|Benson]] counties, [[North Dakota|North Dakota, USA]]
| coords = {{Coord|48|2|5|N|98|56|39|W|region:US-ND_type:waterbody|display=inline,title}}
| type = [[Endorheic]]&lt;br/&gt;Potentially an [[open and closed lakes|open lake]] owing to [[climate change]]
| inflow =
| outflow =
| catchment = {{convert|3810|mi2|abbr=on}}
| basin_countries = United States
| length =
| width =
| area =
| depth =
| max-depth =
| volume =
| residence_time =
| shore =
| elevation = {{convert|1454.20|ft|m|abbr=on}}
| islands =
| cities = [[Devils Lake, North Dakota|Devils Lake]], [[Minnewaukan, North Dakota|Minnewaukan]]
}}

'''Devils Lake''' is a [[lake]] in the [[U.S. state]] of [[North Dakota]].  It is the largest natural body of water and the second-largest body of water in North Dakota after the artificially created [[Lake Sakakawea]]. In 2011, it reached an unofficial historical high elevation of 1454.20 feet.  Additional rises above 1454.20 feet are still possible this spring and summer with rainfall and wave action. The lake can reach 1458.0 before naturally flowing into the [[Sheyenne River]] via the [[Tolna Coulee]]. 
The city of [[Devils Lake, North Dakota]], takes its name from the lake.

==Geography==
Devils Lake is located in [[Ramsey County, North Dakota|Ramsey County]] and [[Benson County, North Dakota|Benson County]] in northeastern North Dakota.  The [[Spirit Lake Tribe]] occupies most of the southern shore.

==Hydrology==
Devils Lake is the [[endorheic]], or closed, lake of a [[drainage basin]] of some 3,800&amp;nbsp;mi² (9,800&amp;nbsp;km²), the Devils Lake Basin. The lake itself collects around 86 percent of the basin's water runoff.&lt;ref name=&quot;DLBJWRB&quot;&gt;Devils Lake Basin Joint Water Resource Board. North Dakota State Water Commission. 2006. ''2006 Devils Lake Basin Water Management Plan.''&lt;/ref&gt; Above a level of some 1,447&amp;nbsp;ft (441 m)(NAVD88) [[AMSL]] the lake spills into neighboring [[Stump Lake, North Dakota|Stump Lake]].  At 1,458&amp;nbsp;ft (444 m) (NAVD88) the combined lake flows naturally into the [[Sheyenne River]], though the lake has not reached this level in approximately 1000&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|title=Prehistoric Water Levels|url=http://www.swc.state.nd.us/4dlink9/4dcgi/GetContentPhoto/PB-218/640/480}}&lt;/ref&gt; years. The Sheyenne River is a tributary to the [[Red River of the North|Red River]], which flows into Canada, with eventual exit into the [[Hudson Bay]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DLBJWRB&quot; /&gt;  Current dike protection is set at 1454&amp;nbsp;ft (443 m)(NAVD88).

Under normal conditions, Devils Lake is shallow, [[salinity|saline]], and [[hypereutrophic]] (very high in nutrients). During periods of excessive precipitation, however, the lake can be quite deep (up to {{convert|60|ft|m}} in places), [[eutrophic]] (rich in minerals, nutrients, and organisms), with decreased salinity due to dilution.&lt;ref name=&quot;DLBJWRB&quot; /&gt;

===Salinity===
Because Devils Lake is [[endorheic]], the lake tends to be much higher in [[salinity]] than are lakes with outlets to river systems. This is similar to the [[Great Salt Lake]] in [[Utah]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg&quot;&gt;Rosenberg, Sheryl A. 2000. &quot;A Canadian Perspective on the Devils Lake Outlet: Towards an Environmental Assessment Model for the Management of Transboundary Disputes.&quot; ''North Dakota Law Review'' 76: 817-59.&lt;/ref&gt; Lower water levels increase salinity threatening fish and wildlife.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg&quot; /&gt; Salinity levels in the lake have been one prominent aspect of the debate over diversion of lake water into the [[Sheyenne River]], with questions of the potential environmental impact of the diverted water on downstream rivers, lakes, and communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollis&quot; /&gt;

===Flooding===
[[Image:Devilslakelevels.jpg|right|thumb|250 px|Historical Elevations of Devils Lake, 1860-2008]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Image:Devilslake 05 24 1984.jpg|left|thumb|350 px| Devils Lake: 1984]]
[[Image:Devilslake 03 22 2009.jpg|left|thumb|350 px|Devils Lake: 2009]]

Devils Lake is well-known for its wide variations in lake levels, with large swings between low and high water levels. This owes in large part to its nature as a [[Endorheic basin|closed-basin]] lake, lacking a natural outlet. The release of water is dependent upon evaporation and seepage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg&quot; /&gt;

The low, flat terrain around Devils Lake consists of various [[coulees]], [[Channel (geography)|channels]], and [[Drainage basin|basins]], which may be separated during times of low water, or connected during high water.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg&quot; /&gt; Thus the boundaries of the lake can vary greatly from year to year, depending on the amount of precipitation.

The conversion of natural flood control mechanisms into agricultural land has had an effect on the flooding at Devils Lake. Drainage of the basin's [[wetlands]] and conversion of the basin's native [[prairie]] to cropland allows water to move more rapidly into the lake, increasing water levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bryn&quot;&gt;Bryn, Eric M. 1996. &quot;Through a Biodiversity Looking-Glass: An Analysis of the Devils Lake Water Management Plan.&quot; ''Great Plains Natural Resources Journal'' 1: 65-96.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the diversion of natural water flows has also been viewed as a contributor to the flooding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bryn&quot; /&gt;

An increase in precipitation between 1993 and 1999 caused the lake to double in size, forcing the displacement of over 300 homes and flooding {{convert|70000|acre|km2}} of farmland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kempf&quot; /&gt; Attempts to mitigate the flooding have reportedly cost [[North Dakota]] and the [[U.S. Government]] over $450 million. Efforts to control flooding include dike construction and moving railroad lines, roads, and power lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;USGSDevils&quot;&gt;Devils Lake Basin in North Dakota. United States Geological Survey Water Science Center. http://nd.water.usgs.gov/devilslake/index.html.&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the flooding, the [[U.S. Congress]] directed the [[Army Corps of Engineers]] to research construction of an outlet in 1997 to control the lake level through methods other than evaporation or natural overflow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollis&quot; /&gt; The Corps' design included mechanisms for filtration and monitoring of the water, and was estimated to cost $186.5 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brouwer&quot;&gt;Brouwer, Greg. 2003. &quot;Corps Approves Devils Lake Diversion.&quot; ''Civil Engineering'': 18-19.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[North Dakota]], objecting to the cost and certain water quality provisions of the plan, declined to participate in construction of the Corps' outlet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollis&quot; /&gt; In 2003, the state constructed its own outlet to divert water from Devils Lake into the [[Sheyenne River]] at a cost of $28 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kempf&quot; /&gt; The outlet was completed in 2005, but was not operated in 2006 due to water quality and [[biota (ecology)|biota]] issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollis&quot; /&gt; The outlet operated at the maximum permitted rate for the first time in July 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.devilslakejournal.com/articles/2009/07/17/news/news01.txt&lt;/ref&gt;

The National Weather Service is the official government agency responsible for observing and predicting water levels at Devils Lake.&lt;ref name=&quot;NWS&quot;&gt;National Weather Service hydrograph for Devils Lake: http://www.crh.noaa.gov/ahps2/hydrograph.php?wfo=fgf&amp;gage=dcbn8&amp;view=1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recreation==
Devils Lake has long been known for [[fishing]] and other [[watersport]]s. It has been named the [[perch]] capital of the world.  There are a number of boat ramps and other facilities around the lake to facilitate recreational activities on the lake.  Recreation in the form of open water and ice fishing is estimated to have generated more than $20 million dollars annually.

[[Sullys Hill National Game Preserve]] is located on the lake's southern shore. [[Grahams Island State Park]] is located on an island in the lake. Other parks on the lake include [[Black Tiger State Recreation Area]] and [[Shelvers Grove State Recreation Area]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.com/maps?oe=utf-8&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;q=Shelvers+Grove+State+Recreation+Area&amp;fb=1&amp;gl=us&amp;hq=Shelvers+Grove+State+Recreation&amp;hl=en&amp;view=map&amp;cid=5515736929829383259&amp;ved=0CBgQpQY&amp;ei=NnsETKrzN5XMNaahwOMI&amp;hnear=&amp;ll=48.073004,-98.796176&amp;spn=0,0.016512&amp;z=17&amp;layer=c&amp;cbll=48.07455,-98.799328&amp;panoid=ZxuR5y20XHCm1t8B5lGfGA&amp;cbp=12,226.11,,0,5 Shelvers Grove State Recreation Area (Possible Speed trap on US 2)]&lt;/ref&gt; which is now closed due to the lake's flooding.

==Issues and controversies==
===Outlet controversy===
[[Image:Devilslakeoutletpump.jpg|right|thumb|250 px|One of two large pumps used in the state constructed outlet.]]
During the most recent wet cycle which began in 1993, the lake rose over 26.5&amp;nbsp;ft (8.1 m), inundating 140&amp;nbsp;mi² (363&amp;nbsp;km²) of primarily agricultural land, necessitating the expenditure of over $400 million in flood protection measures&lt;ref name=&quot;Kempf&quot;&gt;Kempf, Bart. 2007. &quot;Draining Devils Lake: The International Lawmaking Problems Created by the Devils Lake Outlet.&quot; ''Georgetown International Environmental Law Review.''&lt;/ref&gt; and leading some to call for an emergency outlet into the Sheyenne River.

A proposal from the [[Army Corps of Engineers]] would have drawn water from a different point of the lake, included filtration, and been able to discharge a maximum of 300&amp;nbsp;ft³/s (8 m³/s) of water from Devil's Lake, lessening the reliance of drainage on overflow or evaporation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollis&quot;&gt;Hollis, Duncan B. 2007. &quot;Disaggregating Devils Lake: Can Non-State Actors, Hegemony, or Principal-Agent Theory Explain the Boundary Waters Treaty?&quot; In ''Responsibility of Individuals, States and Organizations.''&lt;/ref&gt; The Corps of Engineers estimated project costs to amount to $186.5 million, with the [[United States Congress]] designating $100 million to the project; [[North Dakota]] would have paid the remaining amount.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kempf&quot; /&gt;

The North Dakota government under Governor [[John Hoeven]], objecting to water quality provisions and the amount of necessary funding,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollis&quot; /&gt; instead constructed its own outlet, with approval of the North Dakota Department of Health and the U.S. State Department and Council For Environmental Quality.  Though North Dakota's outlet, which cost $28 million, has a lower maximum discharge than the federal proposal (limited to a maximum of 100&amp;nbsp;ft³/s (2.8 m³/s) by the Section 402 NDPDES Permit) and includes a gravel filter for the removal of larger organisms, it has provided some relief to the flood problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Landers&quot;&gt;Landers, Jay. 2005, Oct. &quot;North Dakota Begins Operating Devils Lake Diversion.&quot; ''Civil Engineering'': 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Construction began in 2003 and was completed as of summer 2005.

The outlet drew opposition from the governments of [[Minnesota]] and [[Manitoba]]. They argue the outlet would create the potential for the transfer of unknown foreign aquatic species and high levels of sulfates into the [[Red River of the North|Red River]] basin and [[Lake Winnipeg]], the world's 10th-largest freshwater lake.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

In March 2004, Manitoba, along with Minnesota and several environmental groups, sued the Department of Health in state court over the Devils Lake Outlet 402 NDPDES Permit.  The court ruled the outlet could proceed in August 2004 and May 2005.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

In addition, though the [[Boundary Waters Treaty of 1909]] established an intermediary, the [[International Joint Commission]] (IJC), through which the United States and Canada can solve cross-boundary water disputes, the IJC has no power to act without invocation by both nations.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWT&quot;&gt;Boundary Waters Treaty of 1909&lt;/ref&gt; Canada attempted to invoke the IJC for purposes of conflict resolution, but the United States did not, effectively preventing the IJC from taking part in the controversy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flanders&quot;&gt;Flanders, Joseph M. 2006. &quot;Transboundary Water Disputes on an International and State Platform: A Controversial Resolution to North Dakota's Devils Lake Dilemma.&quot; ''North Dakota Law Review'' 82, 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Canada|Canadian]] government argues it is a violation of the [[Boundary Waters Treaty of 1909]] and Canada's national sovereignty. The U.S. government contends the diversion will not be harmful or violate the treaty under current conditions.

In November 2005, a joint United States and Canadian study concluded that none of the 13 species Canada classifies as invasive were present in Devils Lake.  The study did find three species of fish parasites that are not currently known to exist in Lake Winnipeg.  However, all three are ubiquitous to the waters of North America and have a wide variety of hosts.  A difficulty inherent in determining what species are in Devils Lake versus Lake Winnipeg results from spatial relationships.  Lake Winnipeg covers approximately 9,400&amp;nbsp;mi² (24,300&amp;nbsp;km²), dozens of times larger than Devils Lake.  In addition, the Devils Lake Basin is significantly smaller than the watersheds feeding Lake Winnipeg, including the Saskatchewan River basin at approximately 56,000&amp;nbsp;mi² (145,000&amp;nbsp;km²).  Drawing conclusions about the biological community already in Lake Winnipeg is difficult, due to the relative lack of biological sampling compared to Devils Lake.

===Carp===
Due to the rising waters of the Devils Lake and its basin, streams can flow in two directions: into the [[Red River Valley]] or the Devils Lake Basin. The Red River Valley basin contains a &quot;rough fish&quot;, the [[common carp]], which the North Dakota Game and Fish Department fears will enter Devils Lake basin waters in the near future, allowing the carp to populate Devils Lake. The carp's fast reproductive growth and the lack of carp predators in the lake will likely help it to dramatically increase in population. This could have drastic consequences for existing populations of game fish such as the [[walleye]] and [[northern pike]], which could greatly harm the sport fishing industry.

Some preventive measures have been proposed, including inserting chemicals in the creeks along the boundary of the Devils Lake Basin and the Red River Valley to kill fish. Biologists did tests in 2005 which conclude that there are currently no carp in the Devils Lake Basin, but some have been found within two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km). The carp appear to have been stalled by the abundant [[cattail]] plants, which makes travel impossible for the fish.

===Railroad Problems===
In 2009, the [[BNSF Railway]] ended freight service between Devils Lake and Church's Ferry, a total of {{convert|19|mi|km}}, in favor of the [[KO Subdivision]], due to the lake's rising waters. [[Amtrak]]'s [[Empire Builder]] currently operates on this route, servicing Grand Forks, Devils Lake, and Rugby, ND. BNSF has offered Amtrak the right to operate over the KO subdivision, and even suggest Amtrak make a station stop at New Rockford, but Amtrak has stated that they will continue using the line. In the next few years, Amtrak will either have to rebuild the bridge that crosses the lake in Church's Ferry, or reroute.&lt;ref&gt;Fred W. Frailey, &quot;Minus its backbone, Amtrak makes a tempting target,&quot; ''Trains'', August 2010, 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 15, 2011, it was announced that BNSF and Amtrak had reached an agreement to each cover one-third of the cost of rebuilding the rail line, with the government left to cover the remaining third.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.grandforksherald.com/event/article/id/206802/&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://nd.water.usgs.gov/devilslake/ Devils Lake] from the [[United States Geological Survey]]
* [http://water.weather.gov//ahps2/hydrograph.php?wfo=fgf&amp;gage=dcbn8&amp;view=1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1 Devils Lake hydrograph] from the [[National Weather Service]]
* [http://www.swc.state.nd.us/4dlink9/4dcgi/GetCategoryRecord/Devils%20Lake%20Flooding Devils Lake] from the North Dakota State Water Commission
* [http://www.ndhealth.gov/WQ/DevilsLake/ Devils Lake Outlet 402 NDPDES Permit] from the North Dakota Department of Health
*  [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=902467 Legal Article/Analysis] Devils Lake, Social Sciences Research Network.  North Dakota Law Review

[[Category:Lakes of North Dakota]]
[[Category:Endorheic lakes of the United States]]
[[Category:Geography of Ramsey County, North Dakota]]
[[Category:Geography of Benson County, North Dakota]]
[[Category:Environment of North Dakota]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
