<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="564971" ns="0" title="African buffalo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Taxobox
| name = African Buffalo
| status = LC|status_system = IUCN3.1
| trend = down
| status_ref = &lt;ref name=iucn&gt;{{IUCN2008|assessors=IUCN SSC Antelope Specialist Group|year=2008|id=21251|title=Syncerus caffer|downloaded=29 March 2009}} Database entry includes a brief justification of why this species is of least concern.&lt;/ref&gt;
| image = Serengeti Bueffel1.jpg
| image_caption = [[Ngorongoro Conservation Area]], Tanzania
| regnum = [[Animal]]ia
| phylum = [[Chordate|Chordata]]
| subphylum = [[Vertebrate|Vertebrata]]
| classis = [[Mammalia]]
| ordo = [[Artiodactyla]]
| familia = [[Bovidae]]
| subfamilia = [[Bovinae]]
| genus = '''''Syncerus'''''
| species = '''''S. caffer'''''
| genus_authority = [[Brian Houghton Hodgson|Hodgson]], 1847
| binomial = ''Syncerus caffer''
| binomial_authority = ([[Anders Sparrman|Sparrman]], 1779)
| subdivision_ranks = Subspecies
| subdivision = 
''S. c. caffer''&lt;br&gt;
''[[African Forest Buffalo|S. c. nanus]]''&lt;br&gt;
''S. c. brachyceros''&lt;br&gt;
''S. c. aequinoctialis''&lt;br&gt;
''S. c. mathewsi''
}}

The '''African buffalo''', '''affalo''', '''nyati''', '''Mbogo''' or '''Cape buffalo''' ('''''Syncerus caffer''''') is a large African [[bovine]]. It is not closely related to the slightly larger [[wild Asian water buffalo]], but its ancestry remains unclear. Owing to its unpredictable nature which makes it highly dangerous to humans, it has not been [[domesticated]], unlike its Asian counterpart, the [[domestic Asian water buffalo]].

==Description==
[[File:African Buffalo Horns.jpg|thumb|left|Skull of African buffalo]]
The African buffalo is a very robust species. Its shoulder height can range from {{convert|1|to|1.7|m|ft|abbr=on}} and its head-and-body length can range from {{convert|1.7|to|3.4|m|ft|abbr=on}}. The tail can range from {{convert|70|to|110|cm|in|abbr=on}} long. Savannah type buffaloes weigh {{convert|500|to|910|kg|lb|abbr=on}}, with males, normally larger than females, reaching the upper weight range. A record-sized savannah-type male weighed {{convert|1000|kg|lb|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iml.jou.ufl.edu/projects/Fall06/Raphael/pages/African%20Buffalo.html] (2011).&lt;/ref&gt; [[African Forest Buffalo|Forest type buffaloes]], at {{convert|250|to|455|kg|lb|abbr=on}}, are only half that size.&lt;ref name=&quot;ultimateungulate&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Brent |last=Huffman|url=http://www.ultimateungulate.com/Artiodactyla/Syncerus_caffer.html |title=Syncerus caffer - African buffalo |publisher=Ultimateungulate.com|date=2010-05-24 |accessdate=2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boitani, Luigi, ''Simon &amp; Schuster's Guide to Mammals''. Simon &amp; Schuster/Touchstone Books (1984), ISBN 978-0671428051&lt;/ref&gt; Its head is carried low, its top located below the backline. The front hooves of the buffalo are wider than the rear, which is associated with the need to support the weight of the front part of the body, which is more powerful than the back

Savannah type buffalo have black or dark brown coats with age. Old bulls have whitish circles around their eyes. Females tend to have more reddish coats. Forest type buffalo are reddish brown in colour with horns that curve out backwards and upwards. Calves of both types have red coats.

The [[Horn (anatomy)|horn]]s of African buffalo are very peculiar. A characteristic feature of them is the fact that the adult bull's horns have fused bases, forming a continuous bone shield referred to as a &quot;boss,&quot; which can not always be penetrated even by a rifle bullet. From the base the horns diverge, then bend down, and then smoothly curve upwards and outwards. The distance between the ends of the horns of large bulls is more than a metre. The young buffalo horn boss forms fully only upon reaching the age of 5–6 years. In cows the horns are, on average, 10-20% less, and the boss is less prominent. Forest buffalo horns are much smaller and weaker than those of the savannah buffaloes and are almost never fused.  They rarely reach a length of even 40&amp;nbsp;cm.

==Subspecies==
[[File:African Forest Buffalo.jpg|thumb|250px|left|African Forest Buffalo at the [[San Diego Zoo]]]]
* ''Syncerus caffer caffer'' (Cape buffalo) - typical subspecies, the largest one, with large males weighing up to {{convert|910|kg|lb|abbr=on}}. It is peculiar to South and East Africa.  Buffalos of this subspecies living in the south of the continent, notably high in size and ferocity - the so-called cape buffalo. Color of this subspecies is the darkest, almost black.
* ''S. c. nanus'' ([[African Forest Buffalo|Forest buffalo]]) - smallest subspecies - the height at the withers less than 120&amp;nbsp;cm and average weight of about {{convert|270|kg|lb|abbr=on}}.  Color dwarf buffalo red, with darker patches on the head and shoulders in the ears form a brush.  Dwarf buffalo is common in forest areas of Central and West Africa.  This subspecies is so different from the standard model, which some researchers consider it still a separate species S.  nanus Between the typical subspecies and dwarf hybrids are not uncommon
* ''S. c. brachyceros'' ([[Sudanese buffalo]]), who is in morphological terms intermediate between those two subspecies.  Occurs in West Africa .  Its dimensions are relatively small, especially  compared to other buffalo, found in Cameroon, which weigh half as the South African subspecies (bull weighing {{convert|600|kg|lb|abbr=on}} is considered to be in these places are already very large).
* ''S. c.  aequinoctialis'' ([[Nile buffalo]]), which is confined to Central Africa . It is similar to the Cape buffalo, but somewhat smaller, and its color is lighter.
* ''S. c. mathewsi'' ([[African Mountain Buffalo|Mountain buffalo]]) (this subspecies is not universally recognized).  It lives in mountainous areas of East Africa.

==Ecology==
[[File:Syncerus caffer01(js).jpg|thumb|left|250px|Buffalo herd in Masai Mara, Kenya]]
The African buffalo is one of the most successful grazers in Africa. It lives in [[swamps]], floodplains as well as [[mopane]] [[grassland]]s and forests of the major mountains of Africa. Buffalo prefer habitat with dense cover such as reeds and thickets.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;&gt;Estes, R. (1991). ''The Behavior Guide to African Mammals, Including Hoofed Mammals, Carnivores, Primates.'' Los Angeles, The University of California Press. pgs. 195-200&lt;/ref&gt; Herds have also been found in open woodland and grassland.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;/&gt; While not particularly demanding with regard to habitat, they require water daily and therefore depend on perennial sources of water. Like the [[Plains zebra]], the buffalo can subsist on tall, coarse grasses. Herds of buffalo will reduce grass level to the height that is preferred by selective grazers. When feeding, the buffalo makes use of its tongue and wide [[incisor]] row to eat grass more quickly than most other African herbivores. Buffalo do not stay on trampled or depleted areas for long.
[[File:309411872 bc3328ac9b o.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Buffalo in water]]
Other than humans, African buffalo have few [[predator]]s and are capable of defending themselves against (and killing) [[lion]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://nature.ca/notebooks/english/capebuff.htm|title = Cape Buffalo|publisher = Canadian Museum of Nature|accessdate=2010-10-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lions do kill and eat buffalo regularly, but it typically takes multiple lions to bring down a single adult buffalo. However there have been several incidents in which lone adult male lions have been able to successfully bring down large bulls.  The [[Nile crocodile]] will typically attack only old solitary animals and young calves.&lt;ref name=&quot;ultimateungulate&quot;/&gt; The [[cheetah]], [[leopard]] and [[spotted hyena]] are a threat only to newborn calves, though spotted hyenas have been recorded to kill full grown bulls on occasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hyena&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last= Kruuk |first= Hans | title=The Spotted Hyena: A study of predation and social behaviour | year= 1979 | page= 335 | isbn= 978-0-226-45508-2 | publisher= University of Chicago Press }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diseases===
Cape Buffalo are susceptible to many diseases including [[Bovine tuberculosis]], [[Corridor disease]] and [[Foot and Mouth]]. Like with many diseases, these problems will remain dormant within a population as long as the health of the animals is good. These diseases do however restrict the legal movements of the animals and fencing infected areas from unaffected areas is enforced. Some wardens and game managers have managed to protect and breed &quot;disease free&quot; herds which become very valuable because they can be transported. Most well known is [[Lindsay Hunt]]'s efforts to source uninfected animals from the [[Kruger National Park]] in [[South Africa]]. Some disease free buffalo in South Africa have been sold to breeders for close to US$130,000.

==Social behavior==
[[Group size measures|Herd size]] is highly variable. The basic herds consist of related females, and their offspring, in an almost linear [[dominance hierarchy]].  The basic herds are surrounded by sub-herds of subordinate males, high-ranking males and females and old or invalid animals. The young males keep their distance from the dominant bull, who is recognizable by the thickness of his horns. 
[[File:Syncerus caffer fight1.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Bulls in position to spar.]]
During the dry season, male buffalo will split from the herd and form bachelor groups.&lt;ref name =&quot;Turner 1995&quot;/&gt; There are two types of bachelor herds: ones made of males aged 4–7 years&lt;ref name= &quot;Ryan 2006&quot;&gt;Ryan, S. J., Knetchtel, Christiane U., getz, Wayne M. (2006). &quot;Range and habitat Selection of African Buffalo in South Africa.&quot; ''Journal of Wildlife Management'' '''Vol. 70'''(No. 3): 764-776.&lt;/ref&gt; and those of males 12 years or older.&lt;ref name= &quot;Ryan 2006&quot;/&gt; During the wet season the younger bulls rejoin a herd to mate with the females. They stay with them throughout the season to protect the calves.&lt;ref name =&quot;Main 1990&quot;&gt;Main, M. B., Coblentz, Bruce E. (1990). &quot;Sexual Segregation among Ungulate: A Critique.&quot; ''Wildlife Society Bulletin'' '''Vol. 18'''(No. 2): pp. 204-210.&lt;/ref&gt; Some older bulls cease to rejoin the herd, as they can no longer compete with the younger, more aggressive males. Males have a linear dominance hierarchy which is based on age and size. Since a buffalo is safer when a herd is larger, dominant bulls may rely on subordinate bulls and sometimes tolerate their copulation.&lt;ref name =&quot;Turner 1995&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Afrikanische Büffel (Syncerus caffer) 1.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Buffalo herd]]
Adult bulls will spar in play, dominance interactions or actual fights. A bull will approach another lowing with his horns down and wait for the other bull to do the same thing. When sparring the bulls twist their horns from side to side.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sinclair 1977&quot;&gt;Sinclair, A. R. E. (1977). ''The African Buffalo''. Chicago, The University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt; If the sparring is for play the bulls may rub each other's faces and bodies during the sparring session. Actual fights are violent but rare and brief. Calves may also spar in play but adult females rarely spar at all. 

African buffalo are notable for their apparent [[Altruism in animals|altruism]]. Female buffalo appear to exhibit some sort of &quot;voting behavior&quot;. During resting time, the females will stand up shuffle around and sit back down again. They will sit in the direction they think that they should move. After an hour of more shuffling, the females will travel in the direction they decide on. This decision is communal and not based on hierarchy or dominance.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, D. S. (1997). &quot;Altruism and Organism: Disentangling the Themes of Multilevel Selection Theory.&quot; ''The American Naturalist'' Vol. 150: pp. S122-S134.&lt;/ref&gt; When chased by [[Predation|predators]] a herd will stick close together and make it hard for the predators to pick off one member. Calves are gathered in the middle. A buffalo herd will respond to the distress call of a captured member and try to rescue it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sinclair 1977&quot;/&gt; A calf's distress call will get the attention of not only the mother but also the herd. Buffalo will engage in [[mobbing behavior]] when fighting off predators.  They have been recorded treeing lions for two hours, after the lions have killed a member of their group. Lion cubs can get trampled and killed. In one videotaped instance, known as the [[Battle at Kruger]], a calf survived an attack by both lions and a crocodile after intervention of the herd.

===Vocalizations===
African buffalo make various vocalizations. Many calls are similar to those of [[domestic cattle]] but are generally of a lower pitch. Buffalo emit low-pitched 2–4 seconds calls repeated at 3-6 second intervals to signal the herd to move. To signal to the herd to change direction, leaders will emit &quot;gritty&quot;, &quot;creaking gate&quot; sounds.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;/&gt; Extended ''maaa''' calls are made by one to a few individuals up to 20 times a minute before and during movements to drinking places. When being aggressive, buffalo make explosive grunts that may be extended into a sequence or become a rumbling growl. Cows emit croaking calls when looking for their calves. Calves will make a similar call of a higher pitch when in distress.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;/&gt; When threatened by predators, buffalo make drawn about ''waaaa'' calls. Dominant individuals make calls to announce their presence and location. A more intense version of the same call is emitted as a warning to an encroaching inferior.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;/&gt; When grazing, buffalo will make various sounds such as brief bellows, grunts, honks and croaks.
[[File:Cape Buffalo calf.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Cape buffalo and her calf]]

===Reproduction===
Buffalo mate and give birth strictly during the rainy seasons. Birth peak takes place early in the season while mating peaks later. A bull will closely guard a cow that comes into heat, while keeping other bulls at bay.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name =&quot;Turner 1995&quot;&gt;Turner, W. C., Jolles, A. E., Owen-Smith, N. (2005). &quot;Alternating Sexual Segregation During the Mating Season By Male African Buffalo (Syncerus caffer).&quot; Journal of Zoology Vol. 267(No. 3): pp. 291-299.&lt;/ref&gt; This is difficult as cows are quite evasive and attract many males to the scene. By the time a cow is in full estrous only the most dominant bull in the herd/subherd is there.&lt;ref name =&quot;Estes 1991&quot;/&gt;

Cows first calve at five years of age, after a [[gestation]] period of 11.5 months. Newly born calves remain hidden in vegetation for the first few weeks while being nursed occasionally by the mother before joining the main herd. Calves are held in the centre of the herd for safety.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url =http://www.bbc.co.uk/nature/species/African_buffalo|title = African Buffalo|publisher = British Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The maternal bond between mother and calf lasts longer than in most bovids. However when a new calf is born the bonding ends and the mother will keep her previous offspring out of the way with horn jabs. Nevertheless the yearling will still tag along for another year or so. Males leave their mothers when they are two years old and join the bachelor groups.

==Relationship with humans==
===Status===
[[File:Cape Buffalo 41 inch Trophy.jpg|thumb|right|Trophy hunter with buffalo prize]]
The current status of African Cape buffalo is dependent on the existence of the animal's value to both trophy hunters and tourists, paving the way for conservation efforts through anti-poaching patrols, village crop damage payouts, and CAMPFIRE payback programs to local areas. 
[[File:African buffalo kenya.jpg|thumb|left|A herd in Kenya at sunset]]
The buffalo is listed as [[Least Concern]] as the species remains widespread, with a global population estimated at nearly 900,000 animals, of which more than three-quarters are in protected areas. While some populations (subspecies) are decreasing, others will remain unchanged in the long term if large, healthy populations continue to persist in a substantial number of national parks, equivalent reserves and hunting zones in southern and eastern Africa.&lt;ref name=iucn/&gt; 

In the past, numbers of African Buffalo suffered their most severe collapse during the great [[rinderpest]] epidemic of the 1890s, which, coupled with [[pleuro-pneumonia]], caused mortalities as high as 95% among livestock and wild ungulates.&lt;ref&gt;Winterbach, H. E. K. 1998. &quot;Research review: the status and distribution of Cape buffalo Syncerus caffer caffer in southern Africa&quot;. ''South African Journal of Wildlife Research'' 28(3): 82-88.&lt;/ref&gt;
  
Being a member of the [[Big Five Game]] family, a term originally used to describe the 5 most dangerous animals to hunt, the Cape Buffalo is a sought after trophy with some hunters paying over $10,000 for the opportunity to hunt one. The larger bulls are targeted for their trophy value although in some areas buffalo are still hunted for meat.

===Attacks===
Known as one of the &quot;[[Big Five Game|big five]]&quot;, &quot;Black Death&quot; or &quot;widowmaker&quot; in Africa, the African buffalo is widely regarded as a very dangerous animal, as it gores and kills over 200 people every year. Buffalo are sometimes reported to kill more 
people in Africa than any other animal, although the same claim is also made of [[Hippopotamus|hippos]] and [[crocodile]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.on-the-matrix.com/africa/buffalo.asp|first=Bruce G. |last=Stumpf  |title = Africa on the Matrix: The Cape Buffalo |accessdate=2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buffalo are notorious among big game hunters as very dangerous animals, with wounded animals reported to ambush and attack pursuers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.safaribwana.com/ANIMALS/animpages/buffalo.htm|title = African Animals Hunting facts and tips - Buffalo Hunting |publisher=safariBwana newsletter |accessdate=2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:African_Buffalo_Drawing_historic.jpg|19th-century drawing
Image:African Buffalo Ngorongoro.jpg|A typical &quot;m'bogo&quot; from [[Ngorongoro Crater]] [[Tanzania]]
Image:CapeBuffalo-Mara.JPG|Cape buffalo herd grazing in [[Maasai Mara]], [[Kenya]]
Image:3241_Buffalo_In_Mud.jpg|African buffalo covered in mud (so it can rub the mud off with its ticks and keep cool) in Phinda, [[South Africa]]
Image:Cape buffalo in the mud.jpg|African buffalo enlarging its mud hole

&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Gaur]]
* [[Anoa]]
* [[Wild Asian water buffalo]]
* [[Domestic Asian water buffalo]]
* [[Zebu]], the common type of cattle from India: Gaur may have contributed to some breeds.

==References==
{{reflist}}
* ''Ecology and Behaviour of the African Buffalo - Social Inequality and Decision Making'' (Chapman &amp; Hall Wildlife Ecology &amp; Behaviour)
* Huffman, B. 2006. [http://www.ultimateungulate.com ''The ultimate ungulate page'']. ''UltimateUngulate.com''. Retrieved January 9, 2007.
* International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN). 2006. [http://www.iucnredlist.org/search/details.php/21251/all ''Syncerus caffer''],
* Nowak, R.M. and Paradiso, J.L. 1983. ''Walker's Mammals of the World''. Baltimore, Maryland, USA: The Johns Hopkins University Press. ISBN 978-0-8018-2525-5

==External links==
{{Commons category|Syncerus caffer}}
{{wikispecies|Syncerus caffer}}
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LU8DDYz68kM Video:Battle Kruger]
* [http://www.wildlife-photo.org/keysearch.php?key=african+buffalo Buffalo images]

{{Artiodactyla|R.4}}

[[Category:Bovines]]
[[Category:Mammals of Africa]]
[[Category:Megafauna of Africa]]
[[Category:Mammals of Zambia]]
[[Category:Mammals of Eritrea]]
[[Category:Mammals of the Central African Republic]]
[[Category:Mammals of Mali]]
[[Category:Mammals of Gabon]]
[[Category:Mammals of Cameroon]]
[[Category:Mammals of Guinea-Bissau]]
[[Category:Mammals of Malawi]]
[[Category:Mammals of Niger]]
[[Category:Mammals of Nigeria]]
[[Category:Mammals of Benin]]
[[Category:Mammals of Ghana]]
[[Category:Mammals of Chad]]
[[Category:Mammals of Burkina Faso]]
[[Category:Mammals of Equatorial Guinea]]
[[Category:Mammals of Sierra Leone]]
[[Category:Mammals of Mozambique]]
[[Category:Mammals of Kenya]]
[[Category:Mammals of Tanzania]]
[[Category:Mammals of South Africa]]
[[Category:Mammals of Sudan]]
[[Category:Mammals of Ethiopia]]
[[Category:Mammals of the Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
[[Category:Mammals of the Republic of the Congo]]
[[Category:Fauna of the Sahara]]
[[Category:Mammals of Angola]]
[[Category:Mammals of Lesotho]]
[[Category:Mammals of Zimbabwe]]
[[Category:Mammals of Botswana]]
[[Category:Mammals of Namibia]]
[[Category:Mammals of Uganda]]
[[Category:Mammals of Rwanda]]
[[Category:Mammals of Burundi]]
[[Category:Herbivorous animals]]
[[Category:Monotypic mammal genera]]
[[Category:Animals described in 1779]]

{{Link FA|af}}
{{Link GA|ru}}

[[af:Buffel]]
[[av:Африкаялъул гамущ]]
[[az:Afrika camışı]]
[[be:Буйвал афрыканскі]]
[[be-x-old:Буйвал афрыканскі]]
[[br:Bual Afrika]]
[[bg:Кафърски бивол]]
[[ca:Búfal africà]]
[[cs:Buvol africký]]
[[tum:Njati]]
[[cy:Byfflo Affricanaidd]]
[[da:Afrikansk bøffel]]
[[de:Afrikanischer Büffel]]
[[nv:Tábąąh ayání]]
[[es:Syncerus caffer]]
[[eo:Afrika bubalo]]
[[ee:To]]
[[fr:Buffle d'Afrique]]
[[ko:아프리카물소]]
[[ha:Ɓauna]]
[[it:Syncerus caffer]]
[[ka:აფრიკული კამეჩი]]
[[rn:Imbogo]]
[[sw:Nyati wa Afrika]]
[[lt:Afrikinis buivolas]]
[[ln:Nzale]]
[[lg:Mbogo]]
[[hu:Kafferbivaly]]
[[nl:Kafferbuffel]]
[[ja:アフリカスイギュウ]]
[[pnb:افریقی مج]]
[[pl:Bawół afrykański]]
[[pt:Búfalo-africano]]
[[ru:Африканский буйвол]]
[[sg:Guagua]]
[[simple:African Buffalo]]
[[sr:Афрички биво]]
[[sn:Nyati]]
[[fi:Kafferipuhveli]]
[[sv:Afrikansk buffel]]
[[tr:Afrika mandası]]
[[uk:Буйвіл африканський]]
[[yo:Ẹfọ̀n Áfríkà]]
[[zh:非洲水牛]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
