<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="566821" ns="0" title="Islamic terrorism"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{terrorism}}

'''Islamic terrorism''' ({{lang-ar|إرهاب إسلامي}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|ʾirhāb ʾislāmī}}'') is acts of [[terrorism]] committed by [[Muslim]]s for the purpose of achieving varying political and/or religious ends. [[Islam]]ic terrorism has been identified as taking place in the [[Middle East]], [[Africa]], [[Europe]], [[Southeast Asia]], and the [[United States]] since the 1970s. One of the most well-known militant organizations is [[al-Qaeda]], which was founded by [[Osama bin Laden]] for the stated goals of ending [[United States|American]] military presence in the Middle East and the [[Arabian Peninsula]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/terrorism/international/fatwa_1998.html Al Qaeda's 1998 Fatwa | PBS NewsHour | Feb. 23, 1998 | PBS]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/terrorism/international/fatwa_1996.html Online NewsHour: Bin Laden's Fatwa]&lt;/ref&gt; overthrowing Arab regimes he considers corrupt and insufficiently religious,&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; ending [[United States|American]] support for [[Israel]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Israel National News 2010&quot;&gt;“[http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/133413 Al-Qaeda Blames 9/11 on US Support for Israel – Defense/Middle East – Israel News – Israel National News.]” Web. 16 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bin Laden|first1=Osama |authorlink1=Osama bin Laden|last2=Lawrence|first2=Bruce|authorlink2=Bruce Lawrence|title=Messages to the world: the statements of Osama Bin Laden|isbn=9781844670451|year=2005|publisher=Verso|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3_fRlEZoaioC&amp;lpg=PA162&amp;pg=PA164#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=28 July 2011|page=164}}&lt;/ref&gt; and returning [[East Timor]] and [[Kashmir]]  to Muslim rule.&lt;ref&gt;Full Text: Bin Laden's Message:  http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/2455845.stm&lt;/ref&gt;  Islamic terrorist organizations have been known to engage in tactics including [[suicide attack]]s, [[Aircraft hijacking|hijacking]]s, [[kidnapping]] and recruiting new members through the [[Internet]].

== History ==
Mark Burgess of the [[Center for Defense Information]] traces the roots of Islamic terrorism back to the 11th-century [[Assassins]], an order of Isma'ili Shi'ism that targeted political and religious opponents who stood in the way of the Assassins' sectarian ideology. In positing a continuity between Islamic terrorism's medieval and modern manifestations, Burgess identifies both a common underlying motive, namely loyalty to a divine imperative, and similar tactics, such as actively seeking out martyrdom. The modern resurgence of Islamic terrorism, Burgess writes, has its roots in three pivotal events circa 1979 – the Iranian Revolution, the post-Cold War global religious revival, and the Soviet withdrawal from Afghanistan. These events, Burgess goes on to argue, were factors that fueled a recourse to religious terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Burgess|first=Mark|title=Explaining Religious Terrorism Part 1|url=http://www.cdi.org/program/issue/document.cfm?DocumentID=2224&amp;IssueID=138&amp;StartRow=1&amp;ListRows=10&amp;appendURL=&amp;Orderby=DateLastUpdated&amp;ProgramID=39&amp;issueID=138|publisher=[[Center for Defense Information]]|accessdate=3 August 2011|date=20 May 2004|quote=This continuity in terrorist motivations is particularly salient with regard to religion.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Burgess|first=Mark|url=http://www.cdi.org/program/document.cfm?documentid=1502&amp;programID=39&amp;from_page=../friendlyversion/printversion.cfm|title=A Brief History of Terrorism|publisher=[[Center for Defense Information]]|accessdate=3 August 2011|date=2 July 2003|quote=While it is impossible to definitively ascertain when it was first used, that which we today call terrorism traces its roots back at least some 2,000 years.  Moreover, today’s terrorism has, in some respects come full circle, with many of its contemporary practitioners motivated by religious convictions – something which drove many of their earliest predecessors.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Motivations and Islamic terrorism==
Former [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] analyst [[Michael Scheuer]], who led the CIA's hunt for [[Osama Bin Laden]], states that terrorist attacks (specifically [[al-Qaeda]] attacks on America) are ''not'' motivated by a religiously inspired hatred of [[Culture of the United States|American culture]] or religion, but by the belief that [[Foreign policy of the United States|U.S. foreign policy]] has oppressed, killed, or otherwise harmed Muslims in the Middle East,&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheuer 2004 9&quot;&gt;
{{cite book | last = Scheuer| first = Michael| authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Imperial Hubris| publisher = Brassey's, Inc.| year = 2004| location = Dulles, Virginia| page = 9| url = | doi =  | isbn = 978-0-9655139-4-4|quote= The focused and lethal threat posed to U.S. national security arises not from Muslims being offended by what America is, but rather from their plausible perception that the things they most love and value—God, Islam, their brethren, and Muslim lands—are being attacked by America.}}&lt;/ref&gt; condensed in the phrase &quot;They hate us for what we do, not who we are.&quot; U.S. foreign policy actions Scheuer believes are fueling Islamic terror include

* [[United States withdrawal from Saudi Arabia|U.S. troops on Muslim 'holy ground']] in [[Saudi Arabia]]
* U.S. support for &quot;[[Apostasy in Islam|apostate]]&quot; [[police state]]s in Muslim nations such as [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Egypt]], [[Pakistan]], [[Algeria]], [[Morocco]], and [[Kuwait]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/front/interviews/scheuer.html|title= Frontline: Al Qaeda's New Front: Interviews: Michael Scheuer|accessdate=March 8, 2008 |work= |quote= Bin Laden has had success because he's focused on a limited number of U.S. foreign policies in the Muslim world, policies that are visible and are experienced by Muslims on a daily basis: our unqualified support for Israel; our ability to keep oil prices at a level that is more or less acceptable to Western consumers. Probably the most damaging of all is our 30-year support for police states across the Islamic world: the Al Sauds and the Egyptians under [Hosni] Mubarak and his predecessors; the Algerians; the Moroccans; the Kuwaitis. They're all police states.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The U.S.-led intervention in [[Afghanistan]] and invasion of [[Iraq]]
* U.S. support for [[United Nations Transitional Administration in East Timor|the creation]] of the Christian state of [[East Timor]] from territory previously held by Muslim [[Indonesia]]
* Perceived U.S. approval or support of actions against Muslim insurgents in [[India]], the [[Philippines]], [[Chechnya]], [[China]] ([[East Turkestan]]), and [[Palestine]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Scheuer| first = Michael| authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Imperial Hubris| publisher = Brassey's, Inc.| year = 2004| location = Dulles, Virginia| pages = 11–13| url = | doi =  | isbn = 978-0-9655139-4-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Historical justification, such as in the [[Crusades]]
* The [[Western world]]'s religious discrimination against Muslim immigrants.

Some other academics argue that terrorism should be seen as a strategic reaction to American power: that America is an [[empire]], and empires provoked resistance in the form of terrorism. The [[Russian Empire|Russian]], [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]], and [[Habsburg Empire|Habsburg]] Empires, for example, all suffered from terrorist attacks and had terrorist organizations – the [[Black Hand]], [[Young Bosnia]], [[Narodnaya Volya]] – spawned from their multiple ethnic groups, religions and national identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Albert J. Bergesen and Omar Lizardo|volume=22|issue=1|title=Theories of Terrorism: A Symposium|journal=Sociological Theory|date=March 2004|pages=38–52|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9558.2004.00203.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic terrorism, according to [[Criticism of Islam|critics of Islam]], is linked to the practice of divinely sanctioned warfare against [[Apostasy in Islam|apostates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/27/opinion/27iht-edpabst.html | work=The New York Times | first1=Phillip | last1=Blond | first2=Adrian | last2=Pabst | title=The roots of Islamic terrorism | date=28 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=International Humanist and Ethical Union |url=http://www.iheu.org/node/1540 |title=The Fate of Infidels and Apostates under Islam &amp;#124; International Humanist and Ethical Union |publisher=Iheu.org |date= |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Muslims{{Weasel-inline|date=July 2011}} argue that references to violence in Muslim sources have been taken out of context.&lt;ref&gt;[http://islam.about.com/od/terrorism/f/terrorism_verse.htm Islam - Verses of Qur'an That Condone &quot;Killing the Infidel&quot;?]&lt;/ref&gt; These [[ayahs]] are only for the situation when non-believers attack the Muslims' life; and only to protect themselves.

[[Robert Pape]], has argued that at least terrorists utilizing suicide attacks — a particularly effective&lt;ref&gt;For example, according to Pape, from 1980 to 2003 suicide attacks amounted to only 3% of all terrorist attacks, but accounted for 48% of total deaths due to terrorism – this excluding 9/11 attacks, from Pape, ''Dying to Win,'' (2005), p.28&lt;/ref&gt; form of terrorist attack—are driven not by Islamism but by &quot;a clear strategic objective: to compel modern democracies to withdraw military forces from the territory that the terrorists view as their homeland.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = McConnell|first = Scott|year = 2005|url = http://www.amconmag.com/2005_07_18/article.html|title = The Logic of Suicide Terrorism|work = The American Conservative magazine|publisher = The American Conservative|accessdate = June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt; However, [[Martin Kramer]], who debated Pape on origins of suicide bombing, countered Pape's position that the motivation for suicide attacks is not just strategic logic but also an interpretation of Islam to provide a moral logic. For example, [[Hezbollah]] initiated suicide bombings after a complex reworking of the [[martyrdom in Islam|concept of martyrdom]]. Kramer explains that the [[South Lebanon conflict (1982–2000)|Israeli occupation of Lebanon]] raised the temperature necessary for this reinterpretation of Islam, but occupation alone would not have been sufficient for suicide terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtoninstitute.org/templateC05.php?CID=2401 |title=Suicide Terrorism in the Middle East: Origins and Response |publisher=Washingtoninstitute.org |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  &quot;The only way to apply a brake to suicide terrorism,&quot; Kramer argues, &quot;is to undermine its moral logic, by encouraging Muslims to see its incompatibility with their own values.&quot;

Scholar [[Scott Atran]], research director and involved in [[NATO]] group studying suicide terrorism, points out that there is no single root cause of terrorism.  Greatest predictors of suicide bombings, Atran concludes, is not religion but group dynamics: &quot;small-group dynamics involving friends and family that form the [[diaspora]] cell of [[fraternity|brotherhood]] and [[camaraderie]] on which the rising tide of martyrdom actions is based&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sitemaker.umich.edu/satran/files/twq06spring_atran.pdf The Moral Logic and Growth of Suicide Terrorism] p.138, 144&lt;/ref&gt;

The Muslim world has been afflicted with economic stagnation for many centuries. In 2011, U.S. President [[Barack Obama]] himself stated that apart from crude oil, the exports of the entire [[Greater Middle East]] with its 400 million population roughly equals that of [[Switzerland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/the-economics-of-obamas-arab-spring-speech/2011/05/19/AFIh0K7G_blog.html | work=The Washington Post | date=19 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been estimated that the exports of [[Finland]], a European country of only five million, exceeded those of the entire 260 million-strong [[Arab world]], excluding oil revenue.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} This economic stagnation is argued{{Who|date=August 2011}} to have commenced with the demise of the [[Ottoman Caliphate]] in 1924, with trade networks being disrupted and societies torn apart with the creation of new nation states; prior to this, the Middle East had a diverse and growing economy and more general prosperity.

Obama gave a major public speech in the United States in response to the 2011 [[Arab Spring]]. In a message to Muslim leaders around the world, Obama urged reform and stated &quot;that in a global economy based on knowledge, based on innovation, no development strategy can be based solely upon what comes out of the ground (oil). He also stated that people can not reach their potential when they cannot start a business without paying a bribe. Throughout the region, many young people have a solid education, but closed economies leave them unable to find a job. Muslim entrepreneurs are brimming with excellent ideas, but corruption, lack of funding, lack of support or inadequate infastructure leaves them unable to develop and profit from those ideas.&quot;

Strong population growth combined with economic stagnation has created urban conglomerations in [[Cairo]], [[Istanbul]], [[Tehran]], [[Karachi]], [[Dhaka]], and [[Jakarta]] each with well over 12 million citizens, millions of them young and unemployed or underemployed. Such a demographic, alienated from the westernized ways of the urban elite,{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} but uprooted from the comforts and more passive traditions of the villages they came from, is understandably favourably disposed to an Islamic system promising a better world – an ideology providing an &quot;emotionally familiar basis for group identity, solidarity, and exclusion]; an acceptable basis for legitimacy and authority; an immediately intelligible formulation of principles for both a critique of the present and a program for the future.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

===Profiles===
Forensic psychiatrist and former foreign service officer [[Marc Sageman]] made an &quot;intensive study of biographical data on 172 participants in the jihad,&quot; in his book ''Understanding Terror Networks''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=SAQ8Oa6zWF4C&amp;printsec=frontcover |title=Understanding terror networks – Google Books |publisher= |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010|isbn=978-0-8122-3808-2|author1=Sageman, Marc|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; He concluded [[social network]]s, the &quot;tight bonds of family and friendship&quot; rather than [[emotional and behavioral disorders]] of &quot;poverty, trauma, madness, [or] ignorance,&quot; inspired [[alienation|alienated]] young Muslims to join the jihad and kill.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upenn.edu/pennpress/book/14036.html |title=Understanding Terror Networks, Marc Sageman |publisher=Upenn.edu |date=September 11, 2001 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Author [[Lawrence Wright]] described the characteristic of &quot;[[displacement]]&quot; of members of the most famous Islamic terrorist group, al-Qaeda:
&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt; What the recruits tended to have in common – besides their urbanity, their [[cosmopolitanism|cosmopolitan]] backgrounds, their education, their facility with languages, and their computer skills – was displacement. Most who joined the jihad did so in a country other than the one in which they were reared. They were [[Algerians]] living in [[expatriate]] enclaves in [[France]], [[Moroccans]] in [[Spain]], or [[Yemenis]] in [[Saudi Arabia]]. Despite their accomplishments, they had little standing in the host societies where they lived.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wright, ''Loming Tower'' (2006), p.304&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

Scholar [[Olivier Roy (professor)|Olivier Roy]] describes the background of the hundreds of ''global'' (as opposed to local) terrorists who were incarcerated or killed and for whom authorities have records, as being surprising for their Westernized background; for the lack of [[Palestinians]], [[Iraqis]], [[Afghanistan|Afghans]] &quot;coming to avenge what is going on in their country&quot;; their lack of religiosity before being &quot;born again&quot; in a foreign country; the high percentage of converts to Islam among them; their &quot;de-territorialized backgrounds&quot; – &quot;For instance, they may be born in a country, then educated in another country, then go to fight in a third country and take refuge in a fourth country&quot;; their nontraditional belief that jihad is permanent, global, and &quot;not linked with a specific territory.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://globetrotter.berkeley.edu/people7/Roy/roy07-con5.html |title=Olivier Roy Interview (2007): Conversations with History; Institute of International Studies, UC Berkeley |publisher=Globetrotter.berkeley.edu |date=May 3, 2007 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This profile differs from that found among recent local Islamist suicide bombers in Afghanistan, according to a 2007 study of 110 suicide bombers by Afghan pathologist Dr. Yusef Yadgari.  Yadgari found that 80% of the attackers studied had some kind of physical or mental disability. The bombers were also &quot;not celebrated like their counterparts in other Arab nations. Afghan bombers are not featured on posters or in videos as martyrs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=15276485 |title=Disabled Often Carry Out Afghan Suicide Missions |publisher=Npr.org |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Daniel Byman, a Middle East expert at the [[Brookings Institute]], and Christine Fair, an assistant professor in peace and security studies at [[Georgetown University]] say that many of the Islamic terrorists are foolish and untrained, perhaps even untrainable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Byman&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2010/07/the-case-for-calling-them-nitwits/8130/|title=The Case for Calling Them Nitwits|author=Daniel Byman and Christine Fair|publisher=Atlantic Magazine|date=July/August 2010|accessdate=July 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ideology===
{{see also|Islamism|Political aspects of Islam}}
{{Islamism sidebar}}

One ideology that plays a role in Islamic terrorism is the principle of [[Jihad]], which broadly means struggle. Militants generally use jihad to mean defensive or retaliatory warfare against actors that have allegedly harmed Muslims.

Transnational [[Islamism|Islamist]] ideology, specifically of the militant Islamists, assert that Western polities and society are actively anti-Islamic, or as it is sometimes described, waging a &quot;[[war against Islam]]&quot;.  Islamists often identify what they see as a historical struggle between Christianity and Islam, dating back as far as the Crusades, among other historical conflicts between practitioners of the two respective religions. Osama bin Laden, for example, almost invariably describes his enemy as aggressive and his call for action against them as defensive. [[Defensive jihad]] differs from offensive jihad in being &quot;[[fard]] al-ayn,&quot; or a personal obligation of all Muslim, rather than &quot;fard al-kifaya&quot;, a communal obligation, which if some Muslims perform it is not required from others. Hence, framing a fight as defensive has the advantage both of appearing to be a victim rather than aggressor, and of giving your struggle the very highest religious priority for all good Muslims.

Many of the violent terrorist groups use the name of jihad to fight against certain Western nations and Israel. An example is bin Laden's al-Qaeda, which is also known as &quot;International Islamic Front for Jihad Against the [[Jews]] and [[Crusaders]]&quot;. Most militant Islamists oppose Israel's policies, and often its existence.

According to the [[U.S. Army]] Colonel Dale C. Eikmeier, “ideology”, rather than any individual or group, is the &quot;center of gravity&quot; of al-Qaeda and related groups, and the ideology is a &quot;collection of violent Islamic thought called [[Qutbism]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;eikmeier&quot;/&gt; He summarizes the tenets of Qutbism as being:
* A belief that Muslims have deviated from true Islam and must return to “pure Islam” as originally practiced during the time of the [[Muhammad|Prophet]].
* The path to “pure Islam” is only through a literal and strict interpretation of the [[Qur'an]] and [[Hadith]], along with implementation of the Prophet’s commands.
* Muslims should interpret the original sources individually without being bound to follow the interpretations of Islamic scholars.
* That any interpretation of the Quran from a historical, contextual perspective is a corruption, and that the majority of Islamic history and the [[Fiqh|classical jurisprudential tradition]] is mere sophistry.&lt;ref name=&quot;eikmeier&quot;&gt;[http://www.carlisle.army.mil/usawc/Parameters/07spring/eikmeier.htm Qutbism, An Ideology of Islamic-Fascism by Dale C. Eikmeier]. Retrieved 17 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The historic rivalry between [[Hinduism|Hindus]] and Muslims in the [[South Asia|Indian subcontinent]] has also often been the primary motive behind some of the most deadly terrorist attacks in India. According to a [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]] report, India topped the list of countries worst affected by Islamic terrorism.

In addition, Islamist militants, scholars, and leaders opposed Western society for what they see as [[Morality|immoral]] [[secularism]]. Islamists have claimed that such unrestricted free speech has led to the proliferation of [[pornography]], [[immorality]], [[secularism]], [[homosexuality]], [[feminism]], and many other ideas that Islamists often oppose. Although bin Laden almost always emphasized the alleged oppression of Muslims by America and Jews when talking about them in his messages, in his &quot;Letter to America&quot; he answered the question, &quot;What are we calling you to, and what do we want from you?,&quot; with
&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt;We call you to be a people of manners, principles, honour, and purity; to reject the immoral acts of fornication, homosexuality, intoxicants, gambling's, and trading with interest (...) You separate religion from your policies, (...) You are the nation that permits Usury, which has been forbidden by all the religions (...) You are a nation that permits the production, trading and usage of intoxicants (...) You are a nation that permits acts of immorality (...) You are a nation that permits gambling in its all forms. (...) You use women to serve passengers, visitors, and strangers to increase your profit margins. You then rant that you support the liberation of women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buzzle.com/editorials/11-24-2002-30919.asp Full text: bin Laden's 'letter to America'] accessed 24 may 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

Given their perceived [[piety]], ''[[The Times]]'' noted the irony when a major&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelondondailynews.com/sexual-perverts-link-islamic-terrorists-p-1584.html  Sexual perverts and the link to Islamic terrorists], ''The London Daily News'',17 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; investigation by their reporters uncovered a link between Islamic Jihadis and [[child pornography]]; a discovery that, according to the London paper, &quot;is expected to improve understanding of the mindsets of both types of criminals and has been hailed as a potentially vital intelligence tool to undermine future terrorist plots.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Times&quot;&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/crime/article4958674.ece Dangerous and depraved: paedophiles unite with terrorists online], Richard Kerbaj, Dominic Kennedy, Richard Owen and Graham Keeley, ''[[The Times]]'', 17 October 2008. Retrieved 30 November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 Britain's then head of [[MI5]] [[Eliza Manningham-Buller]] said of Al-Qaeda that it &quot;has developed an ideology which claims that Islam is under attack, and needs to be defended&quot;. &quot;This&quot; she said &quot;is a powerful narrative that weaves together conflicts from across the globe, presenting the West’s response to varied and complex issues, from long-standing disputes such as Israel/Palestine and Kashmir to more recent events as evidence of an across-the-board determination to undermine and humiliate Islam worldwide.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EM-B&quot;&gt;&lt;[http://www.icjs-online.org/index.php?article=1121 2006 Speech of Eliza Manningham-Buller] Director-General of MI5 on the terrorist threat facing the [[United Kingdom]]&lt;/ref&gt; She said that the video wills of [[United Kingdom|British]] suicide bombers made it clear that they were motivated by perceived worldwide and long-standing injustices against Muslims; an extreme and minority interpretation of Islam promoted by some preachers and people of influence; their interpretation as anti-Muslim of UK foreign policy, in particular the UK’s involvement in Iraq and Afghanistan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EM-B&quot;/&gt; She also cautioned how difficult it was to gain a proper perspective, saying that although there are more important dangers we face daily without feeling so threatened by them such as climate change and road deaths and though terrorist deaths were few the intelligence services had prevented some potentially large threats and that vigilance was needed.&lt;ref name=&quot;EM-B&quot;/&gt;

===Interpretations of the Qur'an and Hadith===
{{POV-section|date=July 2011}} &lt;!-- see the talk page - but I won't be edit warring with this user alone, or anymore --&gt;

The role played by the [[Qur'an]], Islam's sacred text, in opposing or in encouraging attacks on civilians is disputed.

The [[Princeton University]] Middle Eastern scholar [[Bernard Lewis]], states that [[Islamic military jurisprudence|Islamic jurisprudence]] does not allow terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Bernard, 'Islam: The Religion and the People' (2009). Page 53, 145–150&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, Professor Lewis noted:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Bernard Lewis |url=http://www.opinionjournal.com/extra/?id=95001224 |title=Extra - WSJ.com |publisher=Opinionjournal.com |date=September 27, 2001 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt;At no time did the (Muslim) jurist approve of terrorism.  Nor indeed is there any evidence of the use of terrorism (in Islamic tradition).  Muslims are commanded not to kill women, children, or the aged, not to torture or otherwise ill-treat prisoners, to give fair warning of the opening of hostilities, and to honor agreements. Similarly, the laws of Jihad categorically preclude wanton and indiscriminate slaughter. The warriors in the holy war are urged not to harm non-combatants, women and children, &quot;unless they attack you first.&quot; A point on which they insist is the need for a clear declaration of war before beginning hostilities, and for proper warning before resuming hostilities after a truce. What the classical jurists of Islam never remotely considered is the kind of unprovoked, unannounced mass slaughter of uninvolved civil populations that we saw in New York two weeks ago. For this there is no precedent and no authority in Islam.&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

[[Michael Sells]] and Jane I. Smith (a Professor of Islamic Studies) write that barring some extremists like al-Qaeda, most Muslims do not interpret Qura’nic verses as promoting warfare; and that the phenomenon of radical interpretation of scripture by extremist groups is not unique to Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sells&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Michael Sells | title=Understanding, Not Indoctrination | url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?pagename=article&amp;node=&amp;contentId=A57379-2002Aug7&amp;notFound=true |date=August 8, 2002 | publisher=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | author=Jane I. Smith | title=Islam and Christianity | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Christianity | publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2005 | isbn=978-0-19-522393-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Sells, &quot;[Most Muslims] no more expect to apply [the verses at issue] to their contemporary non-Muslim friends and neighbors than most Christians and Jews consider themselves commanded by God, like the Biblical [[Joshua]], to exterminate the [[infidel]]s.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sells&quot;/&gt;

According to [[Robert Spencer (author)|Robert Spencer]], [[Muhammad]] said in one Hadith:&lt;ref&gt;Spencer, Robert, 'The Truth About Muhammad' (2006). Page 165-166: It is one of his most arresting statements. It is true that his Quran is quite brief, especially in comparison to the Old and even the New Testaments; whether its contents truly bear the &quot;widest meaning,&quot; is a matter for the contention of theologians. That he was made &quot;victorious with terror&quot; is undeniable, given the tumultuous history of his prophetic career, with its raids, wars, and assassinations.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Allah's Apostle said, &quot;I have been sent with the shortest expressions bearing the widest meanings, and I have been made victorious with terror (cast in the hearts of the enemy), and while I was sleeping, the keys of the treasures of the world were brought to me and put in my hand.&quot; Abu Huraira added: Allah's Apostle has left the world and now you, people, are bringing out those treasures (i.e. the Prophet did not benefit by them). Narrated in Abu Huraira, [http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/hadith/bukhari/052.sbt.html#004.052.220 Volume 4, Book 52, Number 220]&quot; Furthermore [[Muhammad]] said in another Hadith:&lt;ref&gt;Spencer, Robert, 'The Truth About Muhammad' (2006). Page 115-116: After the Battle of Badr and the attack against the Qaynuqa Jews, the Prophet of Islam directed his anger ant the Jewish poet Ka´b bin Al-Ashraf, who according to Ibn Ishaq, &quot;composed amatory verses of an insulting nature about the Muslim women.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Prophet said, &quot;Who is ready to kill Ka'b bin Al-Ashraf who has really hurt Allah and His Apostle?&quot; Muhammad bin Maslama said, &quot;O Allah's Apostle! Do you like me to kill him?&quot; He replied in the affirmative. So, Muhammad bin Maslama went to him (i.e. Ka'b) and said, &quot;This person (i.e. the Prophet) has put us to task and asked us for charity.&quot; Ka'b replied, &quot;By Allah, you will get tired of him.&quot; Muhammad said to him, &quot;We have followed him, so we dislike to leave him till we see the end of his affair.&quot; Muhammad bin Maslama went on talking to him in this way till he got the chance to kill him. Narrated Jabir bin 'Abdullah [http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/hadith/bukhari/052.sbt.html#004.052.270 Volume 4, Book 52, Number 270] And another Hadith:&lt;ref&gt;Spencer, Robert, 'The Truth About Muhammad' (2006). Page 97-98:From then on, innocent non-Muslim women and children could legitimately suffer the fate of male unbelievers.&lt;/ref&gt;
The Prophet passed by me at a place called Al-Abwa or Waddan, and was asked whether it was permissible to attack the pagan warriors at night with the probability of exposing their women and children to danger. The Prophet replied, &quot;They (i.e. women and children) are from them (i.e. pagans).&quot; I also heard the Prophet saying, &quot;The institution of Hima is invalid except for Allah and His Apostle. Narrated As-Sab bin Jaththama [http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/hadith/bukhari/052.sbt.html#004.052.256 Volume 4, Book 52, Number 256]

===Criticism of Islamic terrorist ideology===
Although &quot;Islamic&quot; terrorism is commonly associated with the [[Salafi]]s (or &quot;[[Wahhabi]]s&quot;), the scholars of the group have constantly attributed this association to ignorance, misunderstanding and sometimes insincere research and deliberate misleading by rival groups.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.salafimanhaj.com/pdf/SalafiManhaj_NYPD.pdf &quot;The Book, &quot;Is Salafiyyah a cause of Terrorism&quot;]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[September 11 attacks]], [[Abdul-Azeez ibn Abdullaah Aal ash-Shaikh]], the [[Grand Mufti]] of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, made an official statement that &quot;the Islamic Sharee'ah (legislation) does not sanction&quot; such actions.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.salafipublications.com/sps/downloads/pdf/CAF020015.pdf &quot;The Mufti of Saudi Arabia on the New York Attacks]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; A Salafi Committee of Major Scholars&quot;in Saudi Arabia has declared that &quot;Islamic&quot; terrorism, such as the May 2003 [[Riyadh compound bombings|bombing in Riyadh]], are in violation of [[Sharia]] law and aiding the enemies of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.salafipublications.com/sps/downloads/pdf/CAF020016.pdf  &quot;The Major Scholars on the Salafi Position Towards the Suicide Bombings by the Khawaarij in Riyadh]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Criticism of Islamic terrorism on Islamic grounds has also been made by Abdal-Hakim Murad ([[Timothy Winter]]):
&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt;Certainly, neither bin Laden nor his principal associate, [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]], are graduates of Islamic universities. And so their proclamations ignore 14 centuries of Muslim scholarship, and instead take the form of lists of anti-American grievances and of Koranic quotations referring to early Muslim wars against Arab idolaters. These are followed by the conclusion that all Americans, civilian and military, are to be wiped off the face of the Earth. All this amounts to an odd and extreme violation of the normal methods of Islamic scholarship. Had the authors of such [[fatwā]]s followed the norms of their religion, they would have had to acknowledge that no school of mainstream Islam allows the targeting of civilians. An insurrectionist who kills non-combatants is guilty of baghy, “armed aggression,” a capital offense in Islamic law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamfortoday.com/murad04.htm |title=Abdal-Hakim Murad, Bin Laden’s Violence is a Heresy Against Islam |publisher=Islamfortoday.com |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

Colonel Eikmeier points out the &quot;questionable religious credentials&quot; of many Islamist theorists, or &quot;Qutbists,&quot; which can be a &quot;means to discredit them and their message&quot;:
&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt;With the exception of [[Abul Ala Maududi]] and [[Abdullah Yusuf Azzam]], none of Qutbism’s main theoreticians trained at Islam’s recognized centers of learning. Although a devout Muslim, [[Hassan al-Banna]] was a teacher and community activist. [[Sayyid Qutb]] was a literary critic. [[Muhammad Abd al-Salam Faraj]] was an electrician. Ayman al-Zawahiri is a physician. Osama bin Laden trained to be a businessman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carlisle.army.mil/usawc/Parameters/07spring/eikmeier.htm Qutbism: An Ideology of  Islamic-Fascism DALE C. EIKMEIER] From ''Parameters'', Spring 2007, pp. 85–98.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

[[Fethullah Gülen]], a prominent Turkish [[Ulema|Islamic scholar]], has claimed that &quot;a real Muslim,&quot; who understood Islam in every aspect, could not be a terrorist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|year = 2005|url = http://www.rumiforum.org/server/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=99&amp;Itemid=35|title = The terrorist attacks in London|publisher = Rumi Forum|accessdate = August 1, 2006|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070626203916/http://www.rumiforum.org/server/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=99&amp;Itemid=35 |archivedate = June 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2004|url = http://www.fethullahgulen.org/a.page/press/interview/interview.with.nuriye.akman.of.zaman.daily/a1727.html|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050311120616/http://www.fethullahgulen.org/a.page/press/interview/interview.with.nuriye.akman.of.zaman.daily/a1727.html
|archivedate = March 11, 2005|title = A Real Muslim cannot be a Terrorist|work = Interview with Nuriye Akman of Zaman Daily|publisher = Fethullah Gülen's Website|accessdate = August 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.fethullahgulenforum.org/articles/12/fethullah-gulen-s-thoughts-on-state-democracy-politics-terrorism
|title = Fethullah Gulen's Thoughts on State, Democracy, Politics, Terrorism|author = Zeki Saritoprak|accessdate=January 1, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many other people with similar points of view&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Power |first=Carla |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1969662,00.html |title=Eminent Pakistani Cleric Issues Fatwa Against Terrorism – TIME |publisher=Time.com |date=March 12, 2010 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as [[Karen Armstrong]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = http://www.time.com/time/archive/preview/0,10987,1000907,00.html|title = The True, Peaceful Face Of Islam|work = Time|publisher = Time Inc.|accessdate = August 1, 2006| date=2001-10-01| first=Karen| last=Armstrong}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prof. Ahmet Akgunduz,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2002|url = http://www.theturkishtimes.com/archive/02/02_15/opinion.html#a_akgunduz|title = A Muslim cannot be a Terrorist and a Terrorist cannot be a Muslim|work = |publisher = Fethulah Gulen's Website|accessdate = August 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adnan Oktar|Harun Yahya]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2006|url = http://www.harunyahya.com/terrorism1.php|title = Islam Denounces Terrorism|publisher = Harun Yahya's Website|accessdate = August 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tahir-ul-Qadri]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamicresearcher.com/fatwa-suicide-bombing-and-terrorism |title=Fatwa: Suicide Bombing and Terrorism |publisher=Islamicresearcher.com |date=July 7, 2005 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Huston Smith]] prominent author on comparative religion noted that the extremists have hijacked Islam, just as has occurred periodically in Christianity, [[Hinduism]] and other religions throughout history. He added that the real problem is that the extremists do not know their own faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jweekly.com/article/full/38467/man-of-faiths-preeminent-religion-scholar-huston-smith-reflects-on-judaism- |title=Man of faiths: Preeminent religion scholar Huston Smith reflects on Judaism and Chasing the Divine &amp;#124; j. the Jewish news weekly of Northern California |publisher=Jweekly.com |date=June 25, 2009 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Identity-based frameworks for analyzing Islamist-based terrorism===
Islamist-based fundamentalist terrorism against Western nations and the U.S. in particular, has numerous motivations and takes place the larger context of a complex and tense relationship between the ‘West' and the Arab and Muslim 'world,'&lt;ref&gt;“The Muslim world and the West: the roots of conflict.” 2005. Web. 16 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; which is highlighted in the previous section on motivations and Islamic terrorism. Identity-based theoretical frameworks including theories of [[social identity]], social categorization theory, and [[psychodynamics]] are used to explain the reasons terrorism occurs.&lt;ref&gt;“Perspectives on Terrorism – Explaining Terrorism: A Psychosocial Approach.” Web. 16 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Social identity]] is explained by Karina Korostelina as a “feeling of belonging to a social group, as a strong connection with social category, and as an important part of our mind that affects our social perceptions and behavior”&lt;ref name=&quot;Korostelina, K. 2007&quot;&gt;Korostelina, K. (2007). Social Identity and Conflict: Structures, Dynamics and Implications. New York: Palgrave Macmillan&lt;/ref&gt; This definition can be applied to the case of [[Osama bin Laden]], who, according to this theory, has a highly salient perception of his social identity as a Muslim, a strong connection to the social category of the Muslim [[Ummah]] or 'community,' which affect his social perceptions and behaviors.&lt;ref&gt;“Osama bin Laden's growing anxiety / The Christian Science Monitor – CSMonitor.com.” Web. 16 Apr. 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Bin Laden's ideology and interpretation of Islam  led to the creation of al-Qaeda in response to perceived threats against the Muslim community by the [[Soviet Union]], the U.S. in particular due to its troop presence in Saudi Arabia, and American support for Israel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Israel National News 2010&quot; /&gt;  The Islamist terrorist group al-Qaeda has a group identity, which includes “shared experiences, attitudes, beliefs, and interests of ingroup members,” and is “described through the achievement of a collective aim for which this group has been created,”&lt;ref&gt;name=Korostelina&lt;/ref&gt; which in this case is to achieve &quot;a complete break from the foreign influences in [[Muslim countries]], and the creation of a new Islamic [[caliphate]].&quot;

Social categorization theory has been discussed as a three-stage process of identification, where “individuals define themselves as members of a [[social group]], learn the stereotypes and norms of the group, and group categories influence the perception and understanding of all situations in a particular context”&lt;ref name=&quot;Korostelina, K. 2007&quot;/&gt; This definition can be applied to the U.S.-led [[war on terror]], in which conflict features such as the phenomenon of [[Anti-Americanism]]&lt;ref&gt;“Understanding Arab anti-Americanism. - By Lee Smith - Slate Magazine.” Web. 30 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and the phenomenon of non-Arab countries like [[Iran]] and [[Afghanistan]] lending support to Islamist-based terrorism by funding or harboring terrorist groups such as [[Hezbollah]]&lt;ref&gt;“Hizballah (Party of God).” Web. 30 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and al-Qaeda&lt;ref&gt;“Analysis Of Al Qaeda In Afghanistan And Pakistan | Eurasia Review.” Web. 30 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; against Western nations, particularly [[Israel]]&lt;ref&gt;“Hezbollah and its Goals.” Web. 30 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[United States]]&lt;ref&gt;“Al-Qaida.” Web. 30 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; are, according to social categorization theory, influenced by a three-stage process of identification. In this three-stage process of identification, the Arab and Muslim world(s) are the social group(s), in which their members learn [[stereotype]]s and [[norm (sociology)|norms]] which categorize their social group vis-à-vis [[Western world|the West]].&lt;ref&gt;“Global Connections. Stereotypes | PBS.” Web. 30 Apr. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; This social categorization process creates feelings of high-level in-group support and allegiance among Arabs and Muslims and the particular context within which members of the Arab and Muslim world(s) social group(s) understand all situations that involve the West. Social categorization theory as a framework for analysis indicates causal relationships between group identification processes and features of conflict situations.&lt;ref&gt;Korostelina, K.(2007)Social Identity and Conflict: Structures, Dynamics and Implications. New York: Palgrave Macmillan&lt;/ref&gt;

==Muslim attitudes toward terrorism ==
{{Main|Muslim attitudes towards terrorism}}

Muslim popular opinion on the subject of attacks on civilians by Islamist groups varies. [[Fred Halliday]], a British academic specialist on the Middle East, argues that most Muslims consider these acts to be egregious violations of Islam's laws.&lt;ref&gt;Halliday, Fred: ''Islam and the Myth of Confrontation: Religion and Politics in the Middle East'' (New York: I.B. Tauris, 2003), 107&lt;/ref&gt; Muslims living in the West denounce the September 11th attacks against [[United States]], while [[Hezbollah]]'s rocket attacks against [[Israel]]i civilian targets are widely supported in the Muslim world and regarded as [[defensive jihad|defensive Jihad]] by a legitimate [[resistance movement]] rather than terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://almashriq.hiof.no/lebanon/300/320/324/324.2/hizballah/statement01.html |title=Statement of purpose |publisher=Almashriq.hiof.no |date=March 20, 1998 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://almashriq.hiof.no/lebanon/300/320/324/324.2/hizballah/hizballah-background.html |title=Hizbullah: Views and Concepts |publisher=Almashriq.hiof.no |date=June 20, 1997 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Statistics compiled by the United States government's Counterterrorism Center present a complicated picture: of known and specified terrorist incidents from the beginning of 2004 through the first quarter of 2005, slightly more than half of the fatalities were attributed to Islamic extremists but a majority of over-all incidents were considered of either &quot;unknown/unspecified&quot; or a secular political nature.&lt;!-- link broken [http://www.tkb.org/NCTC/PerpetratorReportModule.jsp]--&gt; The vast majority of the &quot;unknown/unspecified&quot; terrorism fatalities did however happen in Islamic regions such as [[Iraq]] and [[Afghanistan]], or in regions where Islam is otherwise involved in conflicts such as the [[West Bank]], the [[Gaza Strip]], southern [[Thailand]] and [[Kashmir]].&lt;!-- link broken http://www.tkb.org/NCTC/PerpetratorReportModule.jsp?pagemode=incident_perp&amp;perpType=Unknown/Unspecified&amp;perpId=7&amp;sortby=country&amp;filterMode=0&amp;filterDetails=0&amp;orderBy=DESC&amp;sortByPast=date&amp;startDate=01/01/2004&amp;endDate=03/31/2005 --&gt;

===View of Muslim clerics===
Many Muslim scholars have presented proofs against the religious justification of terrorism, a notable example being that of [[Muhammad ibn al Uthaymeen]] who states regarding killing a non-Muslim:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.answering-extremism.com/trans-pub/ae_misau_10.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;As for a non-Muslim living under Muslim rule and a Mu’āhid (a Non-Muslim ally with whom Muslims have a treaty, trust, peace, or agreement), it’s been authentically established that the prophet (blessings and peace upon him) said: “Whoever kills a Mu’āhid will not even smell the fragrance of paradise and its fragrance can be smelled from the distance of forty years away.” and he also said: “Certainly, one of the most difficult situations for which there is no turning back for whomever casts himself into it - shedding sacred blood without right.”

Another example is that of late scholar [[Abd al-Aziz ibn Abd Allah ibn Baaz|Abd al-Aziz Ibn Baz]] who stated: &quot;It is well-known to anyone with the slightest amount of common sense that hijacking planes and kidnapping embassy officials and similar acts are some of the greatest universal crimes that result in nothing but widespread corruption and destruction. They place such extreme hardships and injuries upon innocent people, the extent of which only Allāh knows.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.answering-extremism.com/trans-pub/ae_aaib_5.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous [[fatwā]] (rulings) condemning terrorism and [[suicide bomber|suicide bombing]] as ''[[haraam|haram]]'' have been published by [[Ulema|Islamic scholars]] worldwide, one of the most extensive being the 600-page ruling by Sheikh [[Tahir-ul-Qadri]], whose fatwa condemned them as ''[[kufr]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sheikh issues fatwa against all terrorists|work=[[The Independent]]|author=Jerome Taylor|date=March 3, 2010|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/sheikh-issues-fatwa-against-all-terrorists-1915000.html|accessdate=April 9, 2010 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 March 2010, Qadri's fatwa was an &quot;absolute&quot; condemnation of terrorism without &quot;any excuses or pretexts.&quot; He said that &quot;Terrorism is terrorism, violence is violence and it has no place in Islamic teaching and no justification can be provided for it, or any kind of excuses or ifs or buts.&quot; Qadri said his fatwa, which declares terrorists and suicide bombers to be unbelievers, goes further than any previous denunciation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalpost.com/news/story.html?id=2634649 |title=Top Islamic scholar issues 'absolute' fatwa against terror |publisher=Nationalpost.com |date=March 3, 2010 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iranian Ayatollah [[Yousef Sanei|Ozma Seyyed Yousef Sanei]] issued a fatwa (ruling) that suicide attacks against civilians are legitimate only in the context of war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2006|url = http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level.php?cat=Terrorism&amp;loid=8.0.245083220&amp;par=0|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070311032307/http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level.php?cat=Terrorism&amp;loid=8.0.245083220&amp;par=0
|archivedate = March 11, 2007|title = Iran: Ayatollah Issues Fatwa Against Suicide Attacks|work = adn kronos international|publisher = adn kronos international|accessdate = June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ruling did not say whether other types of attacks against civilians are justified outside of the context of war, nor whether jihad is included in Sanei's definition of war.

An influential group of Pakistani scholars and religious leaders declared suicide attacks and beheadings as un-Islamic. 'Ulema' (clerics) and 'mushaikh' (spiritual leaders) of the Jamaat Ahl-e-Sunnah, who gathered for a convention, declared suicide attacks and beheadings as un-Islamic in a unanimous resolution. Chairman of the Pakistani Ruet-e-Hilal Committee, Mufti Muneeb-ur-Rehman, said in his address that those who were fighting in the name of implementing Shariah or Islamic law must first abide by these same laws and killing minors is contrary to the teachings of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=PTI, May 17, 2009, 09.33pm IST |url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/World/Pakistan/Top-Pak-clerics-declare-suicide-attacks-un-Islamic/articleshow/4543693.cms |title=Top Pak clerics declare suicide attacks un-Islamic – Pakistan – World – The Times of India |publisher=Timesofindia.indiatimes.com |date=May 17, 2009 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some contemporary scholars who have followed a textual based approach to the study of the Qur'an with an emphasis over the coherence in the Book and the context of situation offered a radical interpretation on the verses and prophetic narratives that are usually quoted by the militants to promote militancy. According to [[Javed Ahmad Ghamidi]] (his [http://www.al-mawrid.org/pages/dl.php?book_id=53 booklet on Jihad] is considered one of his most important contribution towards understanding the religion according to the principles of interpreting the Qur'an introduced by [[Farahi]] and [[Islahi]]) the Qur'an does not allow waging war except for against oppression under a sovereign state. He holds that jihad without a state is nothing but creating nuisance in the land when hijacked by the individuals and groups independent of the state authority defeats the purpose. The principle behind this study of the issue in the basic sources is the principle that there are divine injunctions in the Qur'an which are specific to the age of the Messenger. He says that nobody can be punished for apostasy or being non-Muslim after the Prophet who acted as the divine agent when he punished the disbelievers by sword who had rejected the message of God and his messenger even after the truth was made manifest to them. Ghamidi and his associates have written extensively on the topics related to  these issues. In his book Meezan Ghamidi has concluded that:
# [http://al-mawrid.org/pages/articles_english_detail.php?rid=382&amp;cid=270 Jihad can only waged against persecution] Islamic jihad has only two purposes: putting an end to persecution even that of the non-Muslims and making the religion of Islam reign supreme in the Arabian peninsula. The latter type was specific for the messenger of God and is no more operative.
# [http://al-mawrid.org/pages/questions_english_detail.php?qid=248&amp;cid=270 Under a sovereign state].
# There are strict [http://www.al-mawrid.org/pages/articles_english_detail.php?rid=390&amp;cid=275 ethical limits for jihad] which do not again allow fighting for example non-combatants.
# Seen in this perspective acts of terrorism including [http://www.al-mawrid.org/pages/questions_english_detail.php?qid=253&amp;cid=275 suicide bombing becomes prohibited].

===Opinion surveys===
* [[Gallup]] conducted tens of thousands of hour-long, face-to-face interviews with residents of more than 35 predominantly Muslim countries between 2001 and 2007. It found that – contrary to the prevailing perception in the west that the actions of al-Qaeda enjoy wide support in the Muslim world – more than 90% of respondents condemned the killing of non-combatants on religious and humanitarian grounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;australia.to&quot;&gt;[http://www.australia.to/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=9647:al-qaida-today-a-movement-at-the-crossroads&amp;catid=115:headlines ]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*A 2004, a year after the [[invasion of Iraq]], [[Pew Research Center]] survey found that suicide bombings against Americans and other Westerners in Iraq were seen as &quot;justifiable&quot; by many [[Jordanians]] (70%), [[Pakistanis]] (46%), and [[Turks]] (31%). At the same time, the survey found that support for the U.S.-led [[War on Terror]] had increased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|year = 2004|url = http://people-press.org/reports/display.php3?ReportID=206|title = A Year After Iraq War – Mistrust of America in Europe Ever Higher, Muslim Anger Persists
|work = Survey reports|publisher = The Pew Research Center|accessdate = June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2003|url = http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=story_11-7-2003_pg4_6|title = Bin Laden more popular with Nigerian Muslims than Bush|work = News|publisher = Daily Times of Pakistan|accessdate = June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*A 2005 Pew Research study that involved 17,000 people in 17 countries showed support for terrorism was declining in the Muslim world along with a growing belief that Islamic extremism represents a threat to those countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2005|url = http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?ReportID=248|title = Islamic Extremism: Common Concern for Muslim and Western Publics|work = Pew Global Attitudes Project|publisher = Pew Research Center|accessdate = June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; A ''[[The Daily Telegraph|Daily Telegraph]]'' survey&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last = King|first = Anthony|year = 2005|url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/07/23/npoll23.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2005/07/23/ixnewstop.html|title = One in four Muslims sympathises with motives of terrorists|work = News|publisher = Telegraph Group Limited|accessdate = June 25, 2006| location=London}}{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; showed that 88% of Muslims said the [[7 July 2005 London bombings|July 2005 bombings]] in the London Underground were unjustified, while 6% disagreed.

* In [[Pakistan]], despite the recent rise in the Taliban's influence, a poll conducted by Terror Free Tomorrow in Pakistan in January 2008 tested support for al-Qaeda, the Taliban, other militant Islamist groups and Osama bin Laden himself, and found a recent drop by half. In August 2007, 33% of Pakistanis expressed support for al-Qaeda; 38% supported the Taliban. By January 2008, al-Qaeda's support had dropped to 18%, the Taliban's to 19%. When asked if they would vote for al-Qaeda, just 1% of Pakistanis polled answered in the affirmative. The Taliban had the support of 3% of those polled.&lt;ref name=&quot;australia.to&quot;/&gt;

* Pew Research surveys in 2008 show that in a range of countries – [[Jordan]], Pakistan, [[Indonesia]], [[Lebanon]], and [[Bangladesh]] – there have been substantial declines in the percentages saying suicide-bombings and other forms of violence against civilian targets can be justified to defend Islam against its enemies. Wide majorities say such attacks are, at most, rarely acceptable. The shift of attitudes against terror has been especially dramatic in Jordan, where 29% of Jordanians were recorded as viewing suicide-attacks as often or sometimes justified (down from 57% in May 2005). In the largest majority-Muslim nation, Indonesia, 74% of respondents agree that terrorist attacks are &quot;never justified&quot; (a substantial increase from the 41% level to which support had risen in March 2004); in Pakistan, that figure is 86%; in Bangladesh, 81%; and in [[Iran]], 80%.&lt;ref name=&quot;australia.to&quot;/&gt;

* A poll conducted in Osama bin Laden's home country of [[Saudi Arabia]] in December 2008 shows that his compatriots have dramatically turned against him, his organisation, Saudi volunteers in Iraq, and terrorism in general. Indeed, confidence in bin Laden has fallen in most Muslim countries in recent years.&lt;ref name=&quot;australia.to&quot;/&gt;

* In Iraq, people of all persuasions unanimously reject the terror tactics against Iraqi civilians by the local al-Qaida. An [[ABC News]]/[[BBC]]/[[NHK]] poll revealed that all of those surveyed – Sunni and Shi'a alike – found al-Qaida attacks on Iraqi civilians &quot;unacceptable&quot;; 98% rejected the militants' attempts to gain control over areas in which they operated; and 97% opposed their attempts to recruit foreign fighters and bring them to Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;australia.to&quot;/&gt;

==Examples of organizations and acts==
{{See|List of designated terrorist organizations|History of terrorism}}
[[File:War on terror attack map.svg|thumb|Countries in which Islamist terrorist attacks have occurred between September 11, 2001, and May 2008]]

Some prominent Islamic terror groups and incidents include the following:

===Transnational===
{{Main|Al-Qaeda}}
{{Expand section|date=July 2011}} &lt;!-- more history (essential stuff, like the early merge with the Egyptian Islamic Jihad), and it needs to be explained how it's now more like a franchise --&gt;

[[Al-Qaeda]]'s stated aim is the use of jihad to defend and protect Islam against [[Zionism]], [[Christianity]], [[Hinduism]], the secular West, and Muslim governments such as Saudi Arabia, which it sees as insufficiently Islamic and too closely tied to the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/79C6AF22-98FB-4A1C-B21F-2BC36E87F61F.htm Complete English translation text of 2004 Osama bin Laden videotape on Al-Jazeera].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael, Maggie. ''[http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/nation/terror/20041029-1423-binladentape.html Bin Laden, in statement to U.S. people, says he ordered Sept. 11 attacks]''. The Associated Press. 29 October 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3966817.stm Excerpts] from the BBC. 29 October 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Langhorne, R. (2006), &quot;The Essentials of Global Politics&quot;, Hodder Arnold&lt;/ref&gt; Formed by [[Osama bin Laden]] and [[Muhammad Atef]] in the aftermath of the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan]] in the late 1980s, al-Qaeda called for the use of violence against civilians and military of the United States and any countries that are allied with it.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Al Qaeda&quot;, http://www.answers.com/topic/al-qaeda&lt;/ref&gt;

===America===
====Canada====
{{See also|Terrorism in Canada}}

According to recent government statements Islamic terrorism is biggest threat to [[Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted: Sep 6, 2011 9:02 PM ET |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/story/2011/09/06/harper-911-terrorism-islamic-interview.html |title=Harper says 'Islamicism' biggest threat to Canada - Canada - CBC News |publisher=Cbc.ca |date=2011-09-06 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Canadian Security Intelligence Service|Canadian Security Intelligence Service (CSIS)]] reported that terrorist radicalization at home is now the chief preoccupation of Canada's spy agency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ottawa |first=The |url=http://www.canada.com/ottawacitizen/news/story.html?id=09fe30f3-84ad-458e-b8e7-8add2a9fc8c7 |title=CSIS focuses on homegrown terrorism threat |publisher=Canada.com |date=2008-03-14 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most notorious arrest in Canada's fight on terrorism, was the [[2006 Ontario terrorism plot]] in which 18 Al-Qaeda cell members were arrested for planning a mass bombing, shooting, and hostage taking terror plot throughout [[Southern Ontario]]. There have also been other arrests mostly in [[Ontario]] involving terror plots. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Seymour |first=Andrew |url=http://www.ottawacitizen.com/news/canada-in-afghanistan/RCMP+homegrown+terror+suspects+were+preparing+build+IEDs/3445591/story.html |title=RCMP say homegrown terror suspects were preparing to build IEDs |publisher=Ottawacitizen.com |date=2010-08-26 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States====
{{See also|Terrorism in the United States}}

A [[FBI]] report has shown that a minority of the total number of terrorist attacks in the United States from 1980 to 2005 were carried out by [[Islamic Extremism in the United States|Islamist extremists]]. Between 1993 and 2001, the major attacks or attempts against US interests stemmed from militant Islamic jihad except for the 1995 Oklahoma City bombing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Terrorism 2002–2005|publisher=[[FBI]]|year=2005|url=http://www.fbi.gov/publications/terror/terrorism2002_2005.htm|accessdate=April 9, 2010}}{{Failed verification|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001 nearly 3,000 people were killed in the massive [[September 11 attacks]] organised by al-Qaeda and perpetrated by Saudi nationals, sparking the [[War on Terror]]. Former CIA Director [[Michael Hayden (general)|Michael Hayden]] considers [[homegrown terrorism]] to be the most dangerous threat and concern faced by American citizens today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hayden&quot;&gt;Jordy Yager, &quot;Former intel chief: Homegrown terrorism is a ‘devil of a problem,’&quot; The Hill. July 25, 2010. Available on-line: http://thehill.com/blogs/blog-briefing-room/news/110759-former-intel-chief-homegrown-terrorism-is-a-devil-of-a-problem.&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2011, there have been 51 homegrown jihadist plots or attacks in the United States since the September 11 attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Saslow|first=Eli|title=A one-man mission to stop homegrown Somali terrorism in U.S.|url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2015571420_somali11.html|accessdate=July 12, 2011|newspaper=The Seattle Times|date=July 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
{{See also|Al-Qaeda involvement in Europe}}

Major lethal attacks on civilians in Europe credited to Islamist terrorism include the [[1985 El Descanso bombing]] in [[Madrid]], the [[1995 Paris Metro bombing]]s, 11 March [[2004 Madrid train bombings|2004 bombings of commuter trains in Madrid]], where 191 people were killed, and the [[7 July 2005 London bombings]], also of public transport, which killed 52 commuters. According to EU Terrorism Report, however, there were almost 500 acts of terrorism across the [[European Union]] in 2006, but only one, the [[2006 German train bombing plot|foiled suitcase bomb plot]] in [[Germany]], was related to Islamist terror.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,476599,00.html 500 Terror Attacks in EU in 2006 – But Only 1 by Islamists], [[Der Spiegel|Spiegel Online]], 4 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, a [[Europol]] report also showed that more than 99% of terrorist attacks in Europe over the last three years were, in fact, carried out by non-Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=This tide of anti-Muslim hatred is a threat to us all|author=Seumas Milne|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=February 25, 2010|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/belief/2010/feb/25/anti-muslim-hatred-threat-to-all|accessdate=April 8, 2010 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=EU Terrorism Situation and Trend Report TE-SAT|publisher=[[Europol]]|year=2007–2009|url=http://www.europol.europa.eu/index.asp?page=publications&amp;language=|accessdate=April 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Know your enemy|author=Mehdi Hasan|work=[[New Statesman]]|date=July 9, 2009|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/2009/07/mehdi-hasan-muslim-terrorism-white-british|accessdate=April 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In terms of arrests, out of a total of 1,009 arrested terror suspects in 2008, 187 of them were arrested in relation to Islamist terrorism. The report also showed that the majority of Islamist terror suspects were not [[first generation immigrant]]s, but were rather [[Second generation immigrant|children of immigrants]] who no longer identified with the culture of their parents and at the same time felt excluded from Western society, &quot;which still perceives them as foreigners,&quot; thus they became &quot;more attracted to the idea of becoming ‘citizens’ of the virtual worldwide [[Ummah|Islamic community]], removed from territory and national culture.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Europol-2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=EU Terrorism Situation and Trend Report TE-SAT 2009|publisher=[[Europol]]|year=2009|url=http://www.europol.europa.eu/publications/EU_Terrorism_Situation_and_Trend_Report_TE-SAT/TESAT2009.pdf|accessdate=April 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eurasia===
====Russia====
{{See also|Terrorism in Russia}}

Politically and religiously motivated attacks on civilians in Russia have been traced to separatist sentiment among the largely Muslim population of its [[North Caucasus]] region, particularly in [[Chechnya]], where the central government of the Russian Federation has waged [[Chechen Wars|two bloody wars]] against the local [[Chechen Republic of Ichkeria|secular separatist government]] since 1994. In the [[Moscow theater hostage crisis]] in October 2002, three Chechen separatist groups took an estimated 850 people hostage in the Russian capital; at least 129 hostages died during the storming by Russian special forces, all but one killed by the chemicals used to subdue the attackers (whether this attack would more properly be called a [[nationalism|nationalist]] rather than an Islamist attack is in question). In the September 2004 [[Beslan school hostage crisis]] more than 1,000 people were taken hostage after a school in the [[Republics of Russia|Russian republic]] of [[North Ossetia-Alania]] was seized by a pro-Chechen multiethnic group aligned to [[Riyad-us Saliheen Brigade of Martyrs]]; hundreds of people died during the storming by Russian forces.&lt;ref&gt;''Foreign Affairs'', January/February 2008, p.74, &quot;The Myth of the Authoritarian Model&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2000, Russia has also experienced [[Suicide attacks in the North Caucasus conflict|a string of suicide bombings]] that killed hundreds of people in the Caucasian republics of Chechnya, [[Dagestan]] and [[Ingushetia]], as well as in Russia proper including Moscow. Responsibility for most of these attacks were claimed by either [[Shamil Basayev]]'s Islamic-nationalist rebel faction or, later, by [[Dokka Umarov]]'s pan-Islamist movement [[Caucasus Emirate]] which is aiming to unite most of Russia's North Caucasus as an [[emirate]] since its creation in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/40b2b7e8-3e84-11df-a706-00144feabdc0.html#axzz1QqDmL2UZ FT.com / Europe - Changing face of terror in Russia]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, the U.S. Department of State included the Caucasus Emirate on its list of terrorist organisations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2011/05/164312.htm Designation of Caucasus Emirate - U.S. Department of State]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Turkey====
[[Turkish Hezbollah]] (unrelated to the [[Shia Islam|Shia]] Hezbollah in Lebanon) is a [[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] terrorist group&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John Pike |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/para/hizbullah-t.htm |title=Turkish Hizbullah |publisher=Globalsecurity.org |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; accused of a series of attacks, including the [[2003 Istanbul bombings|November 2003 bombings]] of two synagogues, the British consulate in [[Istanbul]] and HSBC bank headquarters that killed 58.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalreview.com/comment/kohlmann200311250844.asp Terrorized Turkey] by [[Evan Kohlmann]]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- Wikipedia article actually says: &quot;Perpetrator: Al-Qaeda&quot; --&gt;

===Middle East / Southwest Asia ===
====Iraq====
The area that has seen some of the worst terror attacks in modern history has been Iraq as part of the [[Iraq War]]. In 2005, there were 400 incidents of one type of attack (suicide bombing), killing more than 2,000 people – many if not most of them civilians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sitemaker.umich.edu/satran/files/twq06spring_atran.pdf The Moral Logic and Growth of Suicide Terrorism] p.131&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2006, almost half of all reported terrorist attacks in the world (6,600), and more than half of all terrorist fatalities (13,000), occurred in Iraq, according to the [[National Counterterrorism Center]] of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wits.nctc.gov/reports/crot2006nctcannexfinal.pdf Report on Terrorist Incidents – 2006]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}} 6600 out of 14000&lt;/ref&gt; Along with nationalist groups and criminal, non-political attacks, the [[Iraqi insurgency]] includes Islamist insurgent groups, such as [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]], who favor suicide attacks far more than non-Islamist groups. At least some of the terrorism has a transnational character in that some foreign Islamic jihadists have joined the insurgency.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/iraq_insurgency.htm Iraqi Insurgency Groups] the London-based International Institute for Strategic Studies estimates roughly 1,000 foreign Islamic jihadists&lt;/ref&gt;

====Israel and the Palestinian territories====
{{Main|Israeli-Palestinian conflict}}

[[Hamas]] (&quot;zeal&quot; in Arabic and an acronym for Harakat al-Muqawama al-Islamiyya) began support for attacks on military and civilian targets in [[Israel]] at the beginning of the [[First Intifada]] in 1987.&lt;ref&gt;p.154, ''Jihad: The Trail of Political Islam'' by Gilles Kepel (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; The 1988 charter of [[Hamas]] calls for the destruction of [[Israel]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mideastweb.org/hamas.htm |title=The Covenant of the Islamic Resistance Movement (Hamas) |publisher=Mideastweb.org |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it still states its goal to be the elimination of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Nidal al-Mughrabi |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSL1229777020070312 |title=Hamas says still seeks Israel's destruction &amp;#124; International |publisher=Reuters |date=March 12, 2007 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Its &quot;military wing&quot; has claimed responsibility for [[Hamas#Militancy and terrorism|numerous attacks]] in Israel, principally [[List of Palestinian suicide attacks|suicide bombings]] and [[Palestinian rocket attacks on Israel|rocket attacks]]. Hamas has also been accused of sabotaging the Israeli-Palestine peace process by launching attacks on civilians during Israeli elections to anger Israeli voters and facilitate the election of harder-line Israeli candidates.&lt;ref&gt;''Jihad: The Trail of Political Islam'' by Gilles Kepel, The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, (2002), p.331&lt;/ref&gt; Hamas has been designated as a terrorist group by the [[European Union]], Canada, the United States, the United Kingdom, [[Israel]], Australia, Japan, the [[United Nations Commission on Human Rights]] and [[Human Rights Watch]]. It is banned in [[Jordan]]. Russia does not consider Hamas a terrorist group as it was &quot;democratically elected&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3213707,00.html|title=Putin: Hamas not a terror organization|last=Waked |first=Ali   |coauthors=Roee Nahmias|date=2.09.06|publisher=YnetNews.com|accessdate=January 14, 2010|location=Israel}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[second intifada]] (September 2000 through August 2005) 39.9 percent of the suicide attacks were carried out by Hamas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economics.harvard.edu/faculty/benmelech/files/JEP_0807.pdf Human Capital and the Productivity of Suicide Bombers pdf] [[Journal of Economic Perspectives]] Volume 21, Number 3, Summer 2007. Pages 223–238&lt;/ref&gt; The first Hamas suicide attack was the [[Mehola Junction bombing]] in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;Katz, Samuel (2002). The Hunt for the Engineer. Lyons Press. ISBN 978-1-58574-749-8. p.74&lt;/ref&gt; Hamas justifies these attacks as necessary in fighting the Israeli [[Israeli-occupied territories|occupation of Palestinian territory]], and as responses to Israeli attacks on Palestinian targets. The wider movement also serves as a charity organization and provides services to Palestinians.&lt;ref&gt;Humphreys, R. (2005), &quot;Between Memory and Desire: The Middle East in a Troubled Age&quot;, University of California Press&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Islamic Jihad Movement in Palestine]] is a Palestinian Islamist group based in the [[Syria]]n capital, [[Damascus]], and dedicated to waging jihad to eliminate the state of [[Israel]]. It was formed by Egyptian Fathi Shaqaqi in the Gaza Strip following the [[Iranian Revolution]] which inspired its members. From 1983 onward, it engaged in &quot;a succession of violent, high-profile attacks&quot; on Israeli targets.  The intifada which &quot;it eventually sparked&quot; was quickly taken over by the much larger [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] and [[Hamas]].&lt;ref&gt;p.122, Jihad: The Trail of Political Islam by Gilles Kepel)&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in September 2000, it started a campaign of suicide bombing attacks against Israeli civilians. The PIJ's armed wing, the Al-Quds brigades, has claimed responsibility for numerous militant attacks in Israel, including suicide bombings. The group has been designated as a terrorist organization by several Western countries.

====Lebanon====
{{Cleanup|section|date=July 2011}} &lt;!-- too detailed --&gt;

[[Hezbollah]] first emerged in 1982 as a militia during the [[1982 Lebanon War|Israeli invasion of Lebanon]], also known as [[Operation Peace for Galilee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HG20Ak02&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/HG20Ak02.html |title=Hezbollah's transformation |first=Dahr |last=Jamail |publisher=Asia Times |date=2006-07-20 |accessdate=2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc-hi-me&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Who are Hezbollah| first=|last=|publisher=BBC News |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4314423.stm |date=2008-05-21|accessdate=2008-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its leaders were inspired by the [[Ruhollah Khomeini|ayatollah Khomeini]], and its forces were trained and organized by a contingent of [[Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution|Iranian Revolutionary Guards]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nybooks&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nybooks.com/articles/17060|title= In Search of Hezbollah|author=Adam Shatz|publisher=[[The New York Review of Books]]|date=April 29, 2004|accessdate=2006-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah's 1985 manifesto listed its three main goals as &quot;putting an end to any [[colonialist]] entity&quot; in Lebanon, bringing the [[Kataeb Party|Phalangists]] to justice for &quot;the crimes they [had] perpetrated,&quot; and the establishment of an [[Islamic republic|Islamic regime]] in Lebanon.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Hizballah Program&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.standwithus.com/pdfs/flyers/hezbollah_program.pdf |title=The Hizballah Program |publisher=provided by standwithus. com ([[StandWithUs]]) |author=author unknown|accessdate=2007-10-29|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stalinsky&quot;&gt;Stalinsky, Steven.  [http://www.nysun.com/article/37184 &quot;An Islamic Republic Is Hezbollah's Aim.&quot;] ''[[The New York Sun]]''. 2 August 2006. 1 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah leaders have also made numerous statements calling for the destruction of Israel, which they refer to as a &quot;[[Zionist entity]]... built on lands wrested from their owners.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Hizballah Program&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stalinsky&quot;/&gt; Hezbollah, which started with only a small militia, has grown to an organization with seats in the [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] government, a radio and a [[Al-Manar|satellite television-station]], and programs for [[social development]].&lt;ref name=&quot;deeb-hzb-a-primer&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Hizballah: A Primer|last=Deeb|first=Lara|date=2006-07-31|publisher=Middle East Report|url=http://www.merip.org/mero/mero073106.html|accessdate=2006-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah maintains strong support among Lebanon's Shi'a population, and gained a surge of support from Lebanon's broader population ([[Sunni]], [[Christian]], [[Druze]]) immediately following the [[2006 Lebanon War]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Briefing&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.mideastmonitor.org/issues/0609/0609_6.htm|title=Briefing: Lebanese Public Opinion|author=|date=September–October 2006|accessdate=2007-10-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is able to mobilize demonstrations of hundreds of thousands.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4329201.stm &quot;Huge Beirut protest backs Syria.&quot;] ''[[BBC News]]''. 8 March 2005. 7 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah alongside with some other groups began the [[2006–2008 Lebanese political protests]] in opposition to the government of Prime Minister [[Fouad Siniora]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ghattas&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/6200804.stm|title=Political ferment in Lebanon|first=Kim|last=Ghattas|publisher=BBC News|date=2006-12-01|accessdate=2008-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; A later dispute over Hezbollah preservation of its telecoms network led to [[2008 conflict in Lebanon|clashes]] and Hezbollah-led opposition fighters seized control of several [[West Beirut]] neighborhoods from [[Future Movement]] militiamen loyal to Fouad Siniora. These areas were then handed over to the [[Lebanese Army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Haaretz1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title= Lebanese army moves into W. Beirut after Hezbollah takeover |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/981696.html |publisher=[[Haaretz]]|accessdate=2008-05-10}}{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Lebanese government of July 2008|national unity government]] was formed in 2008, giving Hezbollah and its opposition allies control of 11 of 30 cabinets seats; effectively veto power.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cfr.org/publication/9155/hezbollah.html?breadcrumb=%2F |title=Hezbollah (a.k.a. Hizbollah, Hizbu'llah)  |first=|last=|publisher=[[Council on Foreign Relations]]|date=2008-09-13|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah receives its financial support from the governments of [[Iran]] and [[Syria]], as well as donations from Lebanese people and foreign Shi'as.&lt;ref name=&quot;irinnews52494&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=52494&amp;SelectRegion=Middle_East|title=LEBANON: The many hands and faces of Hezbollah|author=UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs|date=2006-03-29|accessdate=2006-08-17}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haaretz 746631&quot;&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/pages/ShArt.jhtml?itemNo=746631 Iranian official admits Tehran supplied missiles to Hezbollah]&lt;/ref&gt; It has also gained significantly in military strength in the 2000s.&lt;ref name=&quot;met&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= MelL |last= Frykberg |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Mideast Powers, Proxies and Paymasters Bluster and Rearm |url= http://www.metimes.com/International/2008/08/29/mideast_powers_proxies_and_paymasters_bluster_and_rearm/5485/ |work= [[Middle East Times]] |publisher= |date=2008-08-29 |accessdate=2008-08-29 |quote= And if there is one thing that ideologically and diametrically opposed Hezbollah and Israel agree on, it is Hezbollah's growing military strength.}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite a June 2008 certification by the [[United Nations]] that Israel had withdrawn from all Lebanese territory,&lt;ref name=&quot;SC/6878&quot;&gt;{{cite web | date=2000-06-18 | publisher=United Nations Security Council | title=Security council endorses secretary-general's conclusion on Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon as of 16 June | url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2000/20000618.sc6878.doc.html | accessdate=2006-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; in August, Lebanon's new Cabinet unanimously approved a draft policy statement which secures Hezbollah's existence as an armed organization and guarantees its right to &quot;liberate or recover [[Shebaa farms|occupied lands]].&quot; Since 1992, the organization has been headed by [[Hassan Nasrallah]], its [[Secretary-General]]. The United States, Canada, Israel and the Netherlands regard Hezbollah as a &quot;[[terrorism|terrorist]]&quot; organization, while the United Kingdom and Australia consider only Hezbollah's external security organization to be a terrorist organization. Many consider it, or a part of it, to be a terrorist group&lt;ref&gt;Roy, Olivier, ''The Failure of Political Islam'', Harvard University Press, (1994), p.115&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pape, Robert, ''Dying to Win'', Random House, 2005, p.129&lt;/ref&gt; responsible for [[1983 United States Embassy bombing|blowing up the American embassy]]&lt;ref&gt;Ranstorp, Magnus, ''Hizb'allah in Lebanon'', St. Martins Press, 1997 p.89-90&lt;/ref&gt; and later its annex, as well as the [[1983 Beirut barracks bombing|barracks of American and French peacekeeping troops]] and a [[Lebanon hostage crisis|dozens of kidnappings of foreigners in Beirut]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Ranstorp, Magnus, ''Hizb'allah in Lebanon'', St. Martins Press, 1997, p.54&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;Kepel, Gilles, Jihad, (2002), p.129&lt;/ref&gt; It is also accused of being the recipient of massive aid from Iran,&lt;ref&gt;Ranstorp, Magnus, ''Hizb'allah in Lebanon'', St. Martins Press, 1997, p.127&lt;/ref&gt; and of serving &quot;Iranian foreign policy calculations and interests,&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; or serving as a &quot;subcontractor of Iranian initiatives&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; Hezbollah denies any involvement or dependence on Iran.&lt;ref&gt;Ranstorp, Magnus, ''Hizb'allah in Lebanon : The Politics of the Western Hostage Crisis,'' p.60&lt;/ref&gt; In the Arab and Muslim worlds, on the other hand, [[Hezbollah]] is regarded as a legitimate and successful resistance movement that drove both Western powers and Israel out of Lebanon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jul 20, 2006 |url=http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/HG20Ak02.html |title=Asia Times Online :: Middle East News – Hezbollah's transformation |publisher=Atimes.com |date=July 20, 2006 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, the Lebanese Prime Minister said of Hezbollah, it &quot;is not a militia. It's a resistance.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn-2005-05-07&quot;&gt;{{cite news|publisher=CNN|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2005/WORLD/meast/05/06/lebanon.report/index.html |title=Hezbollah disarmament unclear|date=May 7, 2005|accessdate=August 5, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fatah al-Islam]] is an Islamist group operating out of the [[Nahr al-Bared]] refugee camp in northern [[Lebanon]]. It was formed in November 2006 by fighters who broke off from the pro-[[Syria]]n [[Fatah al-Intifada]], itself a splinter group of the Palestinian [[Fatah]] movement, and is led by a Palestinian fugitive militant named [[Shaker al-Abssi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;IHT_20070315&quot;&gt;International Herald Tribune (15 March 2007). [http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/03/15/news/lebanon.php &quot;A new face of Al Qaeda emerges in Lebanon&quot;]. Retrieved 20 May 207.&lt;/ref&gt; The group's members have been described as militant [[jihad]]ists,&lt;ref name=&quot;Figaro_20070416&quot;&gt;Le Figaro (16 April 2007). [http://www.lefigaro.fr/english/20070416.WWW000000477_fatah_al_islam_the_new_terrorist_threat_hanging_over_lebanon.html &quot;Fatah Al-Islam: the new terrorist threat hanging over Lebanon&quot;]. Retrieved 20 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and the group itself has been described as a terrorist movement that draws inspiration from [[al-Qaeda]].&lt;ref name=&quot;IHT_20070315&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Figaro_20070416&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters_20070519&quot;&gt;Reuters (19 May 2007). [http://today.reuters.com/news/articlenews.aspx?storyID=2007-05-20T031424Z_01_L20250509_RTRUKOC_0_US-LEBANON-CAMP-FIGHTING.xml &quot;Lebanese army battles militants at Palestinian camp&quot;]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}. Retrieved 20 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Its stated goal is to reform the Palestinian refugee camps under [[Sharia|Islamic sharia law]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters_FactBox&quot;&gt;Reuters (20 May 2007). [http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L20400320.htm &quot;Facts about militant group Fatah al-Islam&quot;]. Retrieved 20 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and its primary targets are [[Israel]] and the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;IHT_20070315&quot; /&gt;

====Saudi Arabia====
{{main|Terrorism in Saudi Arabia}}

====Yemen====
{{Main|Terrorism in Yemen}}

===North Africa===
====Egypt====
{{main|Terrorism in Egypt}}

====Algeria====
The [[Armed Islamic Group]], active in [[Algeria]] between 1992 and 1998, was one of the most violent Islamic terrorist groups, and is thought to have [[takfir]]ed the Muslim population of Algeria. Its campaign to overthrow the Algerian government included [[List of Algerian massacres of the 1990s|civilian massacres]], sometimes wiping out entire villages in its area of operation. It also targeted foreigners living in Algeria, killing more than 100 expatriates in the country. In recent years it has been eclipsed by a splinter group, the Salafist Group for Preaching and Combat (GSPC), now called [[Al-Qaeda Organization in the Islamic Maghreb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John Pike |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/security/library/news/2008/06/sec-080627-cfr01.htm |title=Backgrounder: Armed Islamic Group (Algeria, Islamists) (a.k.a. GIA, Groupe Islamique Armé, or al-Jama'ah al-Islamiyah al-Musallaha) |publisher=Globalsecurity.org |date=June 27, 2008 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kepel, Gilles, ''Jihad'', (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Asia===
====Afghanistan====
According to [[Human Rights Watch]], [[Taliban]] and [[Hezb-e-Islami Gulbuddin]] forces have &quot;sharply escalated bombing and other attacks&quot; against civilians since 2006. In 2006, &quot;at least 669 Afghan civilians were killed in at least 350 armed attacks, most of which appear to have been intentionally launched at civilians or civilian objects.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/reports/2007/afghanistan0407/ The Consequences of Insurgent Attacks in Afghanistan ] April 2007 Volume 19, No. 6(C)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Bangladesh====
In [[Bangladesh]] the group [[Jamaat-ul-Mujahideen Bangladesh]] was formed sometime in 1998 and gained prominence in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;satp&quot;&gt;[http://www.satp.org/satporgtp/countries/bangladesh/terroristoutfits/JMB.htm Jama'atul Mujahideen Bangladesh (JMB)], from South Asia Terrorism Portal&lt;/ref&gt; The organization was officially banned in February 2005 after attacks on [[Non-governmental organization|NGOs]], but struck back in August when 300 bombs were detonated almost simultaneously throughout Bangladesh, targeting [[Shahjalal International Airport]], government buildings and major hotels.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defenddemocracy.org/in_the_media/in_the_media_show.htm?doc_id=358521 The Rising Tide of Islamism in Bangladesh By Maneeza Hossain, [[Hudson Institute]]: [[Current Trends in Islamist Ideology]] vol. 3, February 16, 2006]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Columbia World Dictionary of Islamism'', Columbia University Press (2007), p.69-70&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
{{see also|Terrorism in India}}

Pakistan-based [[Lashkar-e-Taiba]] and [[Jaish-e-Mohammed]] are militant groups seeking accession of [[Kashmir]] to [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=Lashkar-e-Toiba|title = Lashkar-e-Toiba|work = South Asia
|publisher = dictionary.com|accessdate = August 27, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lashkar leadership describes Indian and [[Israel]]i regimes as the main enemies of Islam and Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last = Mir |first = Amir |authorlink = |year = 2005 |url = http://www.atimes.com/atimes/South_Asia/GC11Df07.html
|title = The jihad lives on |work = South Asia |publisher = Asia Times Online Ltd. |accessdate = June 24, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lashkar-e-Toiba, along with [[Jaish-e-Mohammed]], another militant group active in [[Kashmir]] are on the United States’ foreign terrorist organizations list, and are also designated as terrorist groups by the United Kingdom,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.britishhighcommission.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket/Xcelerate/ShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1031627751059|title = Speech by the Prime Minister the Rt Hon Tony Blair MP to the Confederation of Indian Industry Bangalore, India 5 January 2002|work = Indo-UK Relations|publisher = britishhighcommission.gov|accessdate = June 24, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; India, Australia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = Thompson|first = Geoff|year = 2004|url = http://www.abc.net.au/pm/content/2004/s1107792.htm|title = Is Lashkar-e-Toiba still operating in Pakistan?|work = PM|publisher = Australian Broadcasting Corporation|accessdate = June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year = 2002|url = http://www.ppu.org.uk/war/countries/asia/pakistan.html|title = current situation|work = wars and armed conflicts|publisher =  Peace Pledge Union|accessdate = June 25, 2006|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20051219133310/http://www.ppu.org.uk/war/countries/asia/pakistan.html |archivedate = December 19, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jaish-e-Mohammed was formed in 1994 and has carried out a series of attacks all over India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/1804228.stm |title=SOUTH ASIA &amp;#124; Jaish-e-Mohammad: A profile |publisher=BBC News |date=February 6, 2002 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spacewar.com/reports/Attack_May_Spoil_Kashmir_Summit.html |title=Attack May Spoil Kashmir Summit |publisher=Spacewar.com |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group was formed after the supporters of [[Maulana Masood Azhar]] split from another Islamic militant organization, [[Harkat-ul-Mujahideen]]. Jaish-e-Mohammed is viewed by some as the &quot;deadliest&quot; and &quot;the principal terrorist organization in [[Jammu and Kashmir]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;fas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Foreign Terrorist Organizations|url=http://www.fas.org/irp/crs/RL32223.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=fas.org|accessdate=February 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group was also implicated in the kidnapping and murder of American journalist [[Daniel Pearl]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fas&quot;/&gt;

====Pakistan====
{{main|Terrorism in Pakistan}}

===Southeast Asia===
====Indonesia====
{{main|Terrorism in Indonesia}}

====The Philippines====
{{see also|Terrorism in the Philippines}}

The [[Abu Sayyaf|Abu Sayyaf Group]], also known as al-Harakat al-Islamiyya, is one of several militant Islamic-separatist groups based in and around the southern islands of [[Philippines|the Philippines]], in [[Bangsamoro]] ([[Jolo]], [[Basilan]], and [[Mindanao]]) where for almost 30 years various Muslim groups have been engaged in an insurgency for a state, independent of the predominantly [[Christian]] [[Philippines]]. The name of the group is derived from the Arabic ابو, ''[[ab (Semitic)|abu]]'' (&quot;father of&quot;) and ''sayyaf'' (&quot;Swordsmith&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;24threlease&quot;&gt;[http://www.fbi.gov/pressrel/pressrel06/mostwantedterrorists022406.htm FBI Updates Most Wanted Terrorists and Seeking Information – War on Terrorism Lists], ''FBI national Press Release'', 24 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Since its inception in the early 1990s, the group has carried out bombings, [[assassination]]s, [[kidnapping]]s and [[extortion]] in their fight for an independent [[Islamic state]] in western Mindanao and the [[Sulu Archipelago]] with the stated goal of creating a [[pan-Islamic]] superstate across [[southeast Asia]], spanning from east to west; the island of Mindanao, the Sulu Archipelago, the island of [[Borneo]] ([[Malaysia]], [[Indonesia]]), the [[South China Sea]], and the [[Malay Peninsula]] ([[Peninsular Malaysia]], [[Thailand]] and [[Burma|Myanmar]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;TKBAbu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tkb.org/Group.jsp?groupID=204 |title=Abu Sayyaf Group (ASG) |publisher=MIPT Terrorism Knowledge Base |accessdate=20 September 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Department of State|U.S. Department of State]] has branded the group a terrorist entity by adding it to the list of [[U.S. State Department list of Foreign Terrorist Organizations|Foreign Terrorist Organizations]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TKBAbu&quot; /&gt;

==Tactics==
===Suicide attacks===
{{see also|Suicide attack}}

An increasingly popular tactic used by terrorists is suicide bombing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= The_MIPT_Terrorism_Annual|url=http://www.tkb.org/documents/Downloads/2006-MIPT-Terrorism-Annual.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=tkb.org|accessdate=February 6, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071129192403/http://www.tkb.org/documents/Downloads/2006-MIPT-Terrorism-Annual.pdf |archivedate = November 29, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; This tactic is used against civilians, soldiers, and government officials of the regimes the terrorists oppose. The use of suicide bombers is seen by many Muslims{{Weasel-inline|date=July 2011}} as contradictory to Islam's teachings;&lt;ref&gt;[http://islam.about.com/cs/currentevents/a/suicide_bomb.htm Suicide Bombers in Islam]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/8544531.stm | work=BBC News | first=Dominic | last=Casciani | title=Muslim scholar condemns terrorism | date=2 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, groups who support its use often refer to such attacks as &quot;[[Istishhad|martyrdom operations]]&quot; and the suicide-bombers who commit them as &quot;[[martyr]]s&quot; (Arabic: shuhada, plural of &quot;shahid&quot;). The bombers, and their sympathizers often believe that suicide bombers, as martyrs ([[shaheed]]) to the cause of jihad against the enemy, will receive the rewards of [[Jannah|paradise]] for their actions.

===Hijackings===
Islamic terrorism sometimes employs the hijacking of passenger vehicles. The most famous were the [[September 11 attacks|&quot;9/11&quot;]] attacks that killed nearly 3,000 people on a single day in 2001, effectively ending the era of [[aircraft hijacking]].

===Kidnappings and executions===
Along with bombings and hijackings, Islamic terrorists have made extensive use of highly publicised kidnappings and executions, often circulating videos of the acts for use as propaganda. A frequent form of execution by these groups is [[decapitation]], another is shooting. In the 1980s, a series of abductions of American citizens by Hezbollah during the [[Lebanese Civil War]] resulted in the 1986 [[Iran–Contra affair]]. During the chaos of the [[Iraq War]], more than 200 kidnappings [[Foreign hostages in Iraq|foreign hostages]] (for various reasons and by various groups, including purely criminal) gained great international notoriety, even as the great majority (thousands) of victims were Iraqis. In 2007, the [[kidnapping of Alan Johnston]] by [[Army of Islam (Gaza Strip)|Army of Islam]] resulted in the British government meeting a Hamas member for the first time.

===Internet recruiting===
In the beginning of the 21st century emerged a worldwide network of hundreds of web sites that inspire, train, educate and recruit young Muslims to engage in jihad against America and the West, taking less prominent roles in mosques and community centers that are under scrutiny. According to ''[[The Washington Post]]'', &quot;Online recruiting has exponentially increased, with [[Facebook]], [[YouTube]] and the increasing sophistication of people online&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/16/opinion/16friedman.html &quot;www.jihad.com&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples of attacks ==
{{Main|List of Islamic terrorist attacks}}
[[File:WTC3.jpg|thumb|The outer skin of [[World Trade Center]] Tower Two that remained standing after an Islamist terrorist attack orchestrated by [[Al-Qaeda]].]]

* 18 April 1983 - [[1983 United States embassy bombing]] 63 killed, 120 wounded.
* 23 October 1983 - [[1983 Beirut barracks bombing]] 305 killed, 75 wounded.
* 26 February 1993 – [[1993 World Trade Center bombing|World Trade Center bombing]], New York City. Six killed.
* 13 March 1993 – [[1993 Bombay bombings]]. [[Mumbai]], India. 250 dead, 700 injured.
* 28 July 1994 – [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]]. Vehicle [[AMIA bombing|suicide bombing attack]] against [[Asociación Mutual Israelita Argentina|AMIA]] building, the local Jewish community representation. 85 dead, more than 300 injured.
* 24 December 1994 – [[Air France Flight 8969]] hijacking in [[Algiers]] by three members of [[Armed Islamic Group of Algeria]] and another terrorist. Seven killed, including the hijackers.
* 25 June 1996 – [[Khobar Towers bombing]], 20 killed, 372 wounded.
* 17 November 1997 – [[Luxor massacre|Luxor attack]], six terrorists attack tourists at Egypts famous Luxor Ruins. 68 foreign tourists killed.
* 14 February 1998 – [[1998 Coimbatore bombings|Bombing in Coimbatore]], [[Tamil Nadu]], India. 13 bombs explode within a 12&amp;nbsp;km radius. 46 killed and over 200 injured.
* 7 August 1998 – [[1998 United States embassy bombings]] in Tanzania and Kenya. 224 dead. 4000+ injured.
* 4 September 1999 – A series of [[Russian apartment bombings|bombing attacks]] in several cities of Russia, nearly 300 killed.
* 12 October 2000 – Attack on the [[USS Cole bombing|USS cole]] in the Yemeni port of Aden.
* [[September 11 attacks|11 September 2001]] – Four planes [[Aircraft hijacking|hijacked]] and crashed into [[World Trade Center]] and [[The Pentagon]] by 19 hijackers. Nearly 3000 dead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/LAW/04/25/moussaoui.trial/ |title=2006 9/11 Death Toll |date=April 2006|publisher=CNN|accessdate=September 7, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 13 December 2001 – [[2001 Indian Parliament attack|Suicide attack on Indian parliament]] in New Delhi by Pakistan-based Islamist terrorist organizations, Jaish-E-Mohammad and Lashkar-e-Toiba. Aimed at eliminating the top leadership of India and causing anarchy in the country. 7 dead, 12 injured.
* 27 March 2002 – [[Passover massacre|Suicide bomb]] attack on a [[Passover]] Seder in a Hotel in [[Netanya|Netanya, Israel]]. 30 dead, 133 injured.
* 30 March 2002 and 24 November 2002 - [[2002 Raghunath temple attacks|Attacks on the Hindu Raghunath temple]], India. Total 25 dead.
* 24 September 2002 – Machine gun attack on Hindu temple in [[Ahmedabad]], India. 31 dead, 86 injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/cms.dll/html/uncomp/articleshow?msid=153495 |title=Akshardham attack was planned in Riyadh|work=The Times of India|publisher=Times Internet Limited|accessdate=June 25, 2006|date=29 August 2003|deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=September 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=2005|url=http://in.news.yahoo.com/050715/48/5zcxb.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060114194643/http://in.news.yahoo.com/050715/48/5zcxb.html|archivedate=January 14, 2006|title = Akshardham attack &quot;plotted in Riyadh&quot;|work=India news|publisher=Indian Express Newspapers (Bombay) Ltd.|accessdate=June 25, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 12 October 2002 – [[2002 Bali bombings|Bombing in Bali nightclub]]. 202 killed, 300 injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;afp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://afp.gov.au/international/operations/previous_operations/bali_bombings_2002| accessdate=March 18, 2007| publisher=Australian Federal Police |title=Bali bombings 2002| work=International Activities}}{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 16 May 2003 – [[2003 Casablanca bombings|Casablanca Attacks]] – Four simultaneous attacks in [[Casablanca]] killing 33 civilians (mostly Moroccans) carried by [[Salafia Jihadia]].
* 11 March 2004 – Multiple [[2004 Madrid train bombings|bombings]] on trains near Madrid, Spain. 191 killed, 1460 injured (alleged link to Al-Qaeda).
* 1 September 2004 - [[Beslan school hostage crisis]], approximately 344 civilians including 186 children killed.&lt;ref
name=&quot;last_casualty&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date=December 8, 2006|url=http://www.boston.com/news/world/europe/articles/2006/12/08/woman_injured_in_2004_russian_siege_dies/|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080502221257/http://www.boston.com/news/world/europe/articles/2006/12/08/woman_injured_in_2004_russian_siege_dies/|archivedate=May 2, 2008|title=Woman injured in 2004 Russian siege dies|publisher=The Boston Globe|accessdate=January 9, 2007}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/world/04/russian_s/html/1.stm |title=Bbc News |publisher=BBC News |date=September 3, 2004 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2 November 2004 – The murder of [[Theo van Gogh (film director)]] by Amsterdam-born jihadist [[Mohammed Bouyeri]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3974179.stm ''Gunman kills Dutch film director'']&lt;/ref&gt;
* 5 July 2005 - [[2005 Ram Janmabhoomi attack in Ayodhya|Attack at the Hindu Ram temple]] at [[Ayodhya]], India; one of the most holy sites of [[Hinduism]]. 6 dead.
* 7 July 2005 – Multiple [[7 July 2005 London bombings|bombings in London Underground]]. 53 killed by four suicide bombers. Nearly 700 injured.
* 23 July 2005 – [[2005 Sharm el-Sheikh attacks|Bomb attacks at Sharm el-Sheikh]], an Egyptian resort city, at least 64 people killed.
* 29 October 2005 – [[29 October 2005 Delhi bombings]], India. Over 60 killed and over 180 injured in a series of three attacks in crowded markets and a bus, just 2 days before the [[Diwali]] festival.&lt;ref&gt;[http://in.rediff.com/news/2005/oct/30delhi4.htm Delhi blasts toll is 59, 200 injured]- [[rediff.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 9 November 2005 – [[2005 Amman bombings]]. a series of coordinated suicide attacks on hotels in [[Amman|Amman, Jordan]]. Over 60 killed and 115 injured.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestreet.com/_googlen/funds/international-pf/10252100.html?cm_ven=GOOGLEN&amp;cm_cat=FREE&amp;cm_ite=NA Deadly Bombings Hit Jordan] – TheStreet.com, 9 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://aljazeera.com/me.asp?service_ID=10143 Jordan bombings kill 57, wound 300]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}} – [[Al Jazeera]], 9 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Four attackers including a husband and wife team were involved.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4432964.stm Bomber's wife arrested in Jordan] – [[BBC]], 13 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* 7 March 2006 – [[2006 Varanasi bombings]], India. A series of attacks in the Sankath Mochan Hanuman temple and Cantonment Railway Station in the [[Hindu]] holy city of [[Varanasi]]. 28 killed and over 100 injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.atimes.com/atimes/South_Asia/JE15Df02.html|title= South Asia|date= 2008-May-15|publisher=[[Asia Times]]|accessdate= 2010-June-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 11 July 2006 – [[11 July 2006 Mumbai train bombings]], [[Mumbai]], India; a series of seven bomb blasts that took place over a period of 11&amp;nbsp;minutes on the Suburban Railway in Mumbai. 209 killed and over 700 injured.
* 14 August 2007 – [[2007 Qahtaniya bombings|Qahtaniya bombings]]: Four suicide vehicle bombers massacred nearly 800 members of northern Iraq's Yazidi sect in the deadliest [[Iraq war]]'s attack to date.
* 26 July 2008 – [[2008 Ahmedabad bombings]], India.  Islamic terrorists detonate at least 21 explosive devices in the heart of this industrial capital, leaving at least 56 dead and 200 injured. A Muslim group calling itself the Indian Mujahideen claims responsibility.  Indian authorities believe that extremists with ties to Pakistan and/or Bangladesh are likely responsible and are intent on inciting communal violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bedi |first=Rahul |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/india/2463518/India-on-high-alert-as-bombers-sought.html |title=India on high alert as bombers sought – Telegraph |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=July 27, 2008 |accessdate=April 25, 2010 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Investigation by Indian police led to the eventual arrest of a number of terrorists suspected of carrying out the blasts, most of whom belong to a well-known terrorist group, the [[Students Islamic Movement of India]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=(AFP) – Aug 16, 2008 |url=http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5jmWd6R_7NPYZhvm155_PrCKp6g6w |title=AFP: Indian police arrest 10 for serial blasts – August 16, 2008 |publisher=Afp.google.com |date=August 16, 2008 |accessdate=April 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 13 September 2008 – [[13 September 2008 Delhi bombings|Bombing series in Delhi]], India. Pakistani extremist groups plant bombs at several places including [[India Gate]], out of which the ones at Karol Bagh, [[Connaught Place, New Delhi|Connaught Place]] and [[Greater Kailash]] explode leaving around 30 people dead and 130 injured, followed by [[27 September 2008 Delhi blast|another attack]] two weeks later at the congested Mehrauli area, leaving 3 people dead.
* 26 November 2008 – Muslim extremists kill at least 174 people and wound numerous others in a [[2008 Mumbai attacks|series of coordinated attacks]] on India's largest city and financial capital, [[Mumbai]].  The government of India blamed Pakistan based militant group [[Lashkar-e-Taiba]] and stated that the terrorists killed/caught were citizens of [[Pakistan]], a claim which the Pakistani government first refused but then accepted when given proof. [[Ajmal Kasab]], one of the terrorists, was caught alive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/11/26/AR2008112604708.html?hpid=topnews |title=Washington Post – *26 November 2008 – Dozens Die in Mumbai Attacks |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date= 2008-11-27|accessdate=April 25, 2010 | first=Rama | last=Lakshmi}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/12/01/AR2008120100940.html?hpid=topnews |title=Washington Post – 1 December 2008: More Indian Officials Quit in Aftermath of Attacks |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date= 2008-12-01|accessdate=April 25, 2010 | first=Rama | last=Lakshmi}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 25 October 2009. [[Baghdad]], [[Iraq]]. During a [[25 October 2009 Baghdad bombings|terrorist attack]], two bomber vehicles detonated in the Green Zone, killing at least 155 people and injuring 520.
* 28 October 2009 – [[Peshawar]], [[Pakistan]]. A car bomb is [[28 October 2009 Peshawar bombing|detonated]] in a woman exclusive shopping district, and over 110 killed and over 200 injured.
* 3 December 2009 – [[Mogadishu]], [[Somalia]]. A male suicide bomber disguised as a woman detonates in a hotel meeting hall. The hotel was hosting a graduation ceremony for local medical students when the blast went off, killing four government ministers as well as other civilians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/8392468.stm Somalia ministers killed by hotel suicide bomb] . BBC News. December 3. Retrieved December 3.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1 January 2010 – [[Lakki Marwat]], [[Pakistan]]. A suicide [[2010 Lakki Marwat suicide bombing|car bomber]] drove his explosive-laden vehicle into a volleyball pitch as people gathered to watch a match killing more than 100 people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8437114.stm Pakistan volleyball crowd hit by suicide bomber] . BBC News. January 1. Retrieved January 1, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1 May 2010 - New York, New York, USA.  [[Faisal Shahzad]], an [[Islamic]] [[Pakistani American]] who received U.S. citizenship in December 2009, attempted to detonate a [[car bomb]] in [[Times Square]] working with the [[Pakistani Taliban]] or [[Tehrik-i-Taliban Pakistan]].
* 13 May 2011 - [[Tehrik-i-Taliban Pakistan]] claimed attacks on two mosques simultaneously belonging to the [[Ahmadiyya Muslim Community]], killing nearly 100 and injuring many others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/may/13/suicide-bombing-revenge-osama] . The Guardian. May 13, 2011. Retrieved May 13, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 13 July 2011 - [[13 July 2011 Mumbai bombings|Three bombs exploded at different locations in Mumbai]], perpetrated by [[Indian Mujahideen]].

==U.S. State Department list ==
{{Main|U.S. State Department list of Foreign Terrorist Organizations}}
{{Col-begin|width=}}
{{Col-2}}
* [[Abu Sayyaf]], [[Philippines]]
* [[Al-Gama'a al-Islamiyya]], [[Egypt]]
* [[Al-Aqsa Martyrs' Brigades]], [[Gaza Strip]] and [[West Bank]]
* [[Harakat al-Shabaab Mujahideen|Al-Shabaab]], [[Somalia]]
* [[Al-Qaeda]], worldwide
* [[Ansar al-Islam]], [[Iraq]]
* [[Armed Islamic Group of Algeria|Armed Islamic Group]] (GIA), [[Algeria]]
* [[Caucasus Emirate]] (IK), [[Russia]]
* [[East Turkestan Islamic Movement]] (ETIM), [[China]]
* [[Egyptian Islamic Jihad]], Egypt
* [[Great Eastern Islamic Raiders' Front]] (IBDA-C), [[Turkey]]
* [[Hamas]], Gaza Strip and West Bank
* [[Harkat-ul-Mujahideen]] al-Alami, [[Pakistan]]
{{Col-2}}
* [[Hezbollah]], [[Lebanon]]
* [[Islamic Movement of Central Asia]], [[Central Asia]]
* [[Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan]], [[Uzbekistan]]
* [[Jaish-e-Mohammed]], Pakistan and [[Kashmir]]
* [[Jamaat Ansar al-Sunna]], Iraq
* [[Jemaah Islamiyah]], [[Indonesia]]
* [[Lashkar-e-Taiba]], Pakistan and Kashmir
* [[Lashkar-e-Jhangvi]], Pakistan
* [[Moro Islamic Liberation Front]], [[Philippines]]
* [[Moroccan Islamic Combatant Group]], [[Morocco]] and Europe
* [[Islamic Jihad Movement in Palestine|Palestinian Islamic Jihad]], Gaza Strip and West Bank
* [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq|Tawhid and Jihad]], Iraq
{{Col-end}}

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Islam|Terrorism}}
* [[Christian Terrorism]]
* [[Criticism of Islam]]
* [[Criticism of Islamism]]
* [[History of terrorism]]
* [[Homegrown terrorism]]
* [[Islamism]]
* [[Jihad]]
* [[Religious war]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book
|last = Amir
|first = Taheri
|year = 1987
|title = [[Amir Taheri|Holy Terror: Inside the World of Islamic Terrorism]]
|publisher = Adler &amp; Adler
|isbn = 0-917561-45-7
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Atran
|first = Scott
|year = 2010
|title = Talking to the Enemy
|publisher = Ecco Press / HarperCollins, USA; Allen Lane / Penguin, UK
|isbn = 978-0-06-134490-9
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Ayaan
|first = Hirsi Ali
|year = 2007
|title = [[Infidel (book)|Infidel]]
|publisher = Free Press
|isbn = 0-7432-9503-X
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Bostom
|first = Andrew
|year = 2005
|title = [[The Legacy of Jihad]]
|publisher = Prometheus Books
|isbn = 1-59102-307-6
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Dennis
|first = Anthony J.
|year = 1996
|title = The Rise of the Islamic Empire and the Threat to the West
|publisher = Wyndham Hall Press, Ohio, USA
|isbn = 1-556-05268-5
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Dennis
|first = Anthony J.
|year = 2002
|title = Osama Bin Laden: A Psychological and Political Portrait
|publisher = Wyndham Hall Press, Ohio, USA
|isbn = 1-55605-341-X
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Esposito
|first = John L.
|year = 1995
|title = The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality?
|publisher = Oxford University Press, USA
|isbn = 978-0-19-510298-7
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Esposito
|first = John L.
|year = 2003
|title = Unholy War: Terror in the Name of Islam
|publisher = Oxford University Press, USA
|isbn = 978-0-19-516886-0
}}
* Matovic, Violeta, ''[[Suicide Bombers Who's Next]]'', Belgrade, The National Counter Terrorism Committee, ISBN 978-86-908309-2-3
* [[Avner Falk|Falk, Avner]]. (2008). ''Islamic Terror: Conscious and Unconscious Motives.'' Westport, Connecticut, Praeger Security International. ISBN 978-0-313-35764-0.
* {{Cite book
|last = Fregosi
|first = Paul
|year = 1998
|title = Jihad in the West: Muslim Conquests from the 7th to the 21st Centuries
|publisher = Prometheus Books
|isbn = 1573922471 
}}
* [[Brigitte Gabriel|Gabriel, Brigitte]]. (2006). ''Because They Hate: A Survivor of Islamic Terror Warns America.'' St. Martin's Press. ISBN 0312358377.
* [[Mark A. Gabriel|Gabriel, Mark]]. (2005). ''Journey into the Mind of an Islamic Terrorist.'' Frontline. ISBN 1-59185-713-9.
* [[Andrew C. McCarthy|McCarthy, Andrew]]. (2010). ''The Grand Jihad: How Islam and the Left Sabotage America.'' Encounter Books. ISBN 1594033773.
* {{Cite book
|last = Gregory
|first = M.Davis
|year = 2006
|title = Religion of Peace?: Islam's War Against the World
|publisher = World Ahead Publishing
|isbn = 097789844X
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Halliday
|first = Fred
|year = 2003
|title = Islam and the Myth of Confrontation: Religion and Politics of the Middle East
|publisher = I.B. Tauris, New York
|isbn = 978-1-86064-868-7
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Ibrahim
|first = Raymond
|year = 2007
|title = The Al Qaeda Reader
|publisher = Broadway, USA
|isbn = 978-0-7679-2262-3
}}
* [[Gilles Kepel|Kepel, Gilles]]. ''[[Jihad: The Trail of Political Islam]]''.
* [[Gilles Kepel|Kepel, Gilles]]. ''[[The War for Muslim Minds]]''.
* {{Cite book
|last = Spencer
|first = Robert
|year = 2003
|title = [[Onward Muslim Soldiers]]
|publisher = Regnery Publishing, USA
|isbn = 978-0-89526-100-7
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Spencer
|first = Robert
|year = 2005
|title = [[The Politically Incorrect Guide to Islam (And the Crusades)]]
|publisher = Regnery Publishing, USA
|isbn = 978-0-89526-013-0
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Spencer
|first = Robert
|year = 2006
|title = [[The Truth About Muhammad]]
|publisher = Regnery Publishing, USA
|isbn = 978-1-59698-028-0
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Malik
|first = S. K.
|year = 1986
|title = The Quranic Concept of War
|url = http://wolfpangloss.files.wordpress.com/2008/02/malik-quranic-concept-of-war.pdf
|publisher = Himalayan Books
|isbn = 978-81-7002-020-2
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Swarup
|first = Ram
|year = 1982
|title = [[Understanding Islam through Hadis]]
|publisher = Voice of Dharma
|isbn = 978-0-682-49948-4
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Trifkovic
|first = Serge
|year = 2006
|title = [[Defeating Jihad]]
|publisher = Regina Orthodox Press, USA
|isbn = 978-1-928653-26-4
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Phillips
|first = Melanie
|year = 2006
|title = [[Londonistan: How Britain is Creating a Terror State Within]]
|publisher = Encounter books
|isbn = 978-1-59403-144-1
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Warner
|first = Bill
|year = 2006
|title = Mohammed And the Unbelievers
|publisher = CSPI
|isbn = 097855289X
}}
* {{Cite book
|last = Warner
|first = Bill
|year = 2006
|title = Mohammed, Allah, and the Mind of War
|publisher = CSPI
|isbn = 0978552822
}}

{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Islamism}}
{{US War on Terror}}
{{Criticism of religion}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Islamic Terrorism}}
[[Category:Islamic terrorism| ]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]

[[az:İslam və terror]]
[[de:Islamistischer Terrorismus]]
[[es:Yihadismo]]
[[fa:تروریسم اسلامی]]
[[fr:Terrorisme islamiste]]
[[hi:इस्लामी आतंकवाद]]
[[it:Terrorismo islamista]]
[[he:טרור אסלאמי]]
[[arz:ارهاب اسلامى]]
[[ms:Islam Militan]]
[[nl:Moslimextremisme]]
[[ja:イスラーム過激派]]
[[no:Islamistisk terrorisme]]
[[pt:Terrorismo islâmico]]
[[ru:Исламистский терроризм]]
[[sq:Terrorizmi islamist]]
[[simple:Islamic terrorism]]
[[sv:Islamisk terrorism]]
[[tl:Terorismong Islamista]]
[[zh:伊斯蘭恐怖主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
