<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5675967" ns="0" title="Langford, Bedfordshire"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=November 2006}}
{{infobox UK place
|country =                 England
|latitude=                 52.0529
|longitude=                -0.2741
|official_name=             Langford
| population = 2,882
| population_ref = ([[United Kingdom Census 2001|2001 census]])
 |unitary_england=           [[Central Bedfordshire]]
|lieutenancy_england =    [[Bedfordshire]]
|region=                  East of England
|constituency_westminster=      [[North East Bedfordshire (UK Parliament constituency)|North East Bedfordshire]]
|post_town=        [[Biggleswade]]
|postcode_district =       SG18
|postcode_area=            SG
|dial_code=      01462 and 01767
|os_grid_reference=     TL185405
}}

'''Langford''' is a village and [[civil parishes in England|civil parish]] situated alongside the [[River Ivel]] in the county of [[Bedfordshire]].

==Origins==
The village is of Saxon origin, first mentioned in 944AD. and at one time it had one or more fording points across the river. The name is based on the words long ford from the length of the settlement. At the time of the Domesday Book 1086,the population was around one and twenty. The parish church is St. Andrews. Before 1066 the lord of Langford was Lewin, a thane of Edward the Confessor. William the Conqueror granted the village to Walter le Fleming.  In 1142 Walter's descendant Simon de Wahull gave land to the Knights Templar, who established themselves as Lords of the Manor of Langford Rectory. From: 'The People at the Long Ford' by Michael Rutt – pub. Bedfordshire Countu Council 1975.

Langford is three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) south of [[Biggleswade]] and has been a settlement on the east bank of the river Ivel since Saxon times. It is a long straggling village which at one time had two or three fording points over the river, hence its name. The village now starts at the Baulk corner and it is nearly three miles to the Running Waters at the north end of the village.

On the west side of the river Ivel is part of the Ivel Valley countryside project, namely, Henlow common and Langford meadows local nature reserve. This is a {{convert|47|acre|m2|adj=on}} reserve and despite its name, Henlow common is situated in Langford parish. It came to Langford in 1985 after an exchange of land between the two parishes, as a registered common it keeps its original name. Dams ditch, earlier called Adams ditch, runs through the middle of the reserve. It is more like a small river than a ditch.

The village has grown enormously since 1961 when the population was 1,250, then the housing estates were taking over the fields and meadows, so that by 1976 it had doubled to 2,500 and in 2001 it was 4,000.[http://langfordparishcouncil.org.uk/]

==Sport and recreation==

Langford has a [[List of King George V Playing Fields (Bedfordshire)|King George's Field]] in memorial to [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]]

This is the home of Langford Youth the local youth football side, they play here between September and March and during the summer months it is the home of Langford Cricket Team, at the bottom of the field is a cricket score board.
The Bowls club's bowling green is at the bottom of the field next to the village hall.

The Village also has its own football ground, Forde Park, this can be found half way to [[Henlow]]. It is the Home of both the Men's and Women's Football sides. The women's team currently play in the [http://www.secombination.org.uk/index.htm  South East Combination Women League], A few seasons back the women's side was in the FA Nationwide Women's Premier League, playing the likes of [[Chelsea L.F.C.]]. Forde Park is one of the biggest parks in [[England]] along with the likes of the world famous [[Wembley Stadium]].

[http://www.langfordtennisclub.org.uk/index.html Langford Tennis Club] is an active, friendly, village tennis club with two floodlit courts, organised social play, club ladders and league play in the Bedfordshire LTA leagues. Regular coaching courses for all standards are run by Justin Layne our LTA qualified coach. The club also hosts Get Back Into... courses for people wanting to refresh their way back to playing tennis. Members are welcome from all the surrounding villages

==Notable residents==
[[A.W. Lawrence]], Professor of Archaeology at the [[University of Cambridge]] and the youngest brother of [[T. E. Lawrence]] (Lawrence of Arabia).&lt;ref&gt;R. M. Cook, ‘Lawrence, Arnold Walter (1900–1991)’, Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, Sept 2004; online edn, May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Langford, Bedfordshire}}
* [http://langfordparishcouncil.org.uk/ Parish Council website]
* [http://85.12.98.34/BedsCC/xnoteslink/SDimr4.nsf/Web/ThePage/PP-Langford 2001 Census - Parish profile for Langford]

{{Places in Bedfordshire}}

[[Category:Villages in Bedfordshire]]
[[Category:Civil parishes in Bedfordshire]]
[[Category:Biggleswade]]

[[it:Langford (Bedfordshire)]]
[[nl:Langford (Bedfordshire)]]
[[pl:Langford (Bedfordshire)]]
[[vo:Langford (Bedfordshire)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
