<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5708035" ns="0" title="Grande Prairie Regional College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|55|10|35.37|N|118|48|4.67|W|display=title|type:edu}}
{{Infobox University
|name = '''Grande Prairie Regional College'''
|image = [[File:GPRC Crest.svg|200px|GPRC Crest]]
|logo = [[File:GPRC Logo.svg|120px|GPRC Logo]]
|established = [[1966]]
|type = Public University
|campus = Urban
|president = Don Gnatiuk
|student association president = Rory Tarant
|address = 102-10632 102 Avenue Grande Prairie, AB T8V 6J8
|city = [[Grande Prairie]]
|state = [[Alberta]]
|country = [[Canada]]
|students = 2,000+
|nickname = GPRC
|colours= [[Black (color)|black]] {{color box|#000000}} &amp; [[White (color)|White]] {{color box|#FFFFFF}} 
|free_label     = Sports teams 
|free           = GPRC Wolves
|affiliations   = [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[Canadian Colleges Athletic Association]], [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport|CIS]], [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]], [[Alberta Colleges Athletics Conference]], [[Alberta Association of Colleges &amp; Technical Institutes]],
|website = [http://www.gprc.ab.ca/ gprc.ab.ca]
|}}

'''Grande Prairie Regional College''', often abbreviated ''GPRC'', is a comprehensive community college with two campuses [[Grande Prairie]] and [[Fairview, Alberta (town)|Fairview, Alberta]].  Over 2,000 students in credit programs, and over 6,000 in workforce training and recreational programs, attend GPRC and Fairview College Campus annually.  The college offers a number of apprenticeship and academic programs including certificates and diplomas, university studies, academic upgrading, and workforce development courses in various subjects.

==History==
Grande Prairie Regional College was opened as the ''Grande Prairie Junior College'' in 1966. In 1970, the college was renamed to its current version.  

In 1974, classes were first started in a new facility designed by Canadian architect [[Douglas Cardinal]]. In 1991, phase II of the college, designed by architects ''Field, Field, and Field'', was officially opened.

From 1995 to 2005, GPRC offered its own Bachelor of Applied Forest Resource Management degree.

==Academic programs==
Collaborative programs with other institutions such as The [[University of Alberta]] allow for students to complete some bachelor degrees at GPRC including the Bachelor of Science - Agriculture or Food Business Management and the Bachelor of Science - Agriculture. Other degree programs require transferring to another institution to complete their degree after studying at the college.  Some arrangements also allow for a student to start studies at another facility and complete their degree program at the college.  In total, over 20 different routes for University Studies are offered, and 9 degrees can be completed at the college.&lt;ref&gt;http://tools.canlearn.ca/&lt;/ref&gt;

The college offers 13 certificate and diploma programs. Certificate programs usually require students to complete two semesters of courses, while diploma programs usually require four.

Academic upgrading is also offered, which allows individuals to pursue other learning opportunities such as grade 12 equivalency and general studies.

GPRC has an International Education Centre which offers students courses in English as a Second Language (ESL).  Foreign students can also take credit-based college and university courses offered to Canadian residents.

GPRC's Workforce Development offers courses to the general public in a number of areas. Courses primarily focus on personal and professional development, and range from one-day courses to full credit programs.

==Athletics Program==

GPRC's sports teams are collectively known as the &quot;GPRC Wolves&quot;. The Grande Prairie Regional College Wolves, compete in the [[Alberta Colleges Athletic Conference]]. Sports include: badminton, basketball, curling, cross-country running, soccer, swimming, and volleyball.  Each sport includes participation by both men and women, sometimes on separate teams.  The Wolves Men's Volleyball team carries a strong tradition of winning in the ACAC and has received 2 silver and one bronze medal at CCAA Nationals.

==Campus Facilities==
GPRC's campus includes a 500-seat theatre and double gynasium.  Both are often used to host some of the community events in Grande Prairie.  The campus' student lounge, Howlers, also hosts weekend and evening entertainment often arranged by GPRC's student association. The student association runs a radio-style podcast called &quot;The Tap,&quot; which replaced the student newspaper formerly known as The Tapestry.
 
The campus also includes a bookstore, climbing centre, and library with over 60,000 holdings.

===Residence===
GPRC has on-campus student residences.  Anderson Hall has space for 115 students, and the new Student Village currently has space for an additional 72 students.

==See also==
*[[List of agricultural universities and colleges]]
*[[Education in Alberta]]
*[[List of universities and colleges in Alberta]]
*[[Canadian Colleges Athletic Association]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
All facts, unless otherwise stated, are from Grande Prairie Regional College's web site
*[http://www.gprc.ab.ca/ GPRC Website]

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
*[http://www.gprc.ab.ca/ GPRC Website]
*[http://www.gprc.ab.ca/athletics GPRC Wolves Athletics]
{{Ab Uni|college=yes|technical=yes}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in Alberta]]
[[Category:Douglas Cardinal buildings]]
[[Category:Grande Prairie]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
