<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5736766" ns="0" title="Vodafone Portugal"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Company|
| company_name = Vodafone Portugal
| company_logo = 
| company_type = [[Private company]] 
| company_slogan = Viva o momento. NOW. (''Live the moment. NOW.'')
| location =  Avenida D. João II, 1.04.01, 1990 [[Lisbon]], [[Portugal]]
| foundation = 1991
| key_people =
| industry = [[Mobile phone|Mobile]] [[Telecommunications]]
| products = [[Mobile Networks]], [[Telecom Services]], etc.
| parent = [[Vodafone|Vodafone Group Plc]]
| subsid =
| revenue = {{profit}} [[Euro|€]] '''?''' [[1000000000 (number)|billion]] (2006)
| net_income = {{loss}} [[Euro|€]] '''?''' [[1000000000 (number)|billion]] (2006)
| operating_income = {{profit}} [[Euro|€]] '''?''' [[1000000000 (number)|billion]] (2006)
| homepage = [http://www.vodafone.pt Vodafone Portugal website]
| foot_notes =
| num_employees =
}}

[[Image:Logo telecel.jpg|thumb|200px|The previous Telecel brand]]

'''Vodafone Portugal''', a full subsidiary of the Vodafone Group, is the second mobile operator in Portugal, both chronologically and in market share (34% in 2006). Its competitors are [[Optimus Telecomunicações, S.A.|Optimus]] and [[Telecomunicações Móveis Nacionais, SA|TMN]].

==History==
===As Telecel===
Vodafone Portugal was founded in 1991 as '''Telecel, Comunicações Pessoais, S.A.''' (Telecel) as it won the bid for Portugal's second GSM operator (after [[Telecomunicações Móveis Nacionais, SA|TMN]]). 

The network went live in October 1992.

In 1996, the &quot;pre-paid&quot; concept was introduced with the launch of tariff plan ''Vitamina''.
Telecel also held a paging license and was leader in the 4-player paging business, using the brand ''Telechamada''.

In January 2000, the indirect access fixed-line telephone service was launched, using [[Portugal Telecom]]'s infrastrutctures and the 1091 prefix. It used the brands ''toq 1091'' (for the home costumers; now discontinued in favour of ''Vodafone at Home/Vodafone Casa'') and ''Voz Pri'' (for the business costumers; still used as part of the business solutions).

In May of the same year, Telecel entered the [[Internet Service Provider]] and [[web portal]] businesses under the brand ''Netc'' (pronounced &quot;netcetera&quot;). The business model was lifted from successful [[Freeserve]], a British non-subscription ISP.

===From Telecel to Vodafone===
The initial group of shareholders was led by Portuguese investment bank [[Banco Espírito Santo]], Portuguese conglomerate [[Amorim]] and USA's Pacific Telesis, owner of mobile operator PacTel Cellular.

PacTel Cellular was spun off in 1994 as [[AirTouch]], which in turn merged in 1999 with British operator [[Vodafone]]. Thus, Telecel became minority-owned by the Vodafone Group.

Telecel was listed on the [[Euronext]]-Lisbon Stock Exchange. Banco Espírito Santo and Amorim used the IPO and subsequent sales to sell out with considerable gains, and the Vodafone Group eventually took a controlling share. 

In 2003 the Vodafone Group launched a successful tender offer for all outstanding shares not in its possession, thus becoming the full owner of then-called Telecel-Vodafone. The company was definitely renamed Vodafone Portugal and delisted.

The CEO since the start was António Carrapatoso. Now new CEO is Antonio Coimbra.

===As Vodafone===

In 2002, when Telecel was already controlled by the Vodafone Group, the parent company decided to implement the Vodafone brand worldwide, in order to achieve [[Synergy|synergies]] and improve brand awareness. Telecel was the first operator to initiate the process.{{Fact|date=August 2007}} This was achieved in three steps: 1. putting Vodafone after Telecel, thus referring to the company as Telecel Vodafone; 2. after six months, exchanging the order to Vodafone Telecel; and 3. after another six months (already in 2003), dropping the Telecel brand altogether. Throughout the process, market research showed no confusion and no loss of awareness of both the brands and the operator. This had been a concern for Vodafone for Telecel was a top-ten advertiser, which had led to develop a brand with the highest recall indexes. 

In 2002, the Netc ISP and web portal were rebranded [[Vizzavi]], Vodafone's multimedia brand in association with [[Vivendi Universal]].

In 2003, when paging was moribund as mobile phones had become so ubiquitous, the Telechamada business was abandoned and the license was returned to the State.

In 2003, the Vizzavi ISP business was sold to competitor IOL, a unit of Portuguese media group [[Media Capital]], and the web portal was closed down as [[Vodafone live!]] was launched.

In 2006, Vodafone Portugal disconnected the [[Cell Broadcast]] service.

Vodafone Portugal also provides ADSL2+ services, including [[VoIP]] telephone service and [[IPTV]], under the brand Vodafone Casa.

Despite being branded as part of the international Vodafone group Vodafone Portugal share none of the renowned customer service of its UK parent. It remains little more than a rebranded version of Telecel. That is to say they suffer the problems of many bloated, inefficient Portuguese companies with the same short-sighted staff, inflexible, slow processes resulting in often extremely poor customer service. This is a pity as, from a technical standpoint, they have great products and services which, in the main work well.

==Figures==

Like parent company, Vodafone Portugal's fiscal year runs from April to March.

Results 2Q06:
*4,366,000 clients, of which:
**79.6% pre-paid, [[ARPU]] 13 euro
**21.4% post-paid, ARPU 62.20 euro
*Increase of 5.8% in revenues relative to 2Q05.

== External links ==
* [http://www.vodafone.pt Official website]
&lt;br&gt;
{{Vodafone}}
{{Portuguese mobile operators}}

[[Category:Internet service providers of Portugal]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1991]]
[[Category:1991 establishments in Portugal]]

[[fr:Vodafone Portugal]]
[[pt:Vodafone]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
