<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="573942" ns="0" title="Miami-Dade Transit"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Public transit
|name = Miami-Dade Transit
|image2 = Transit at Government Center.jpg
|imagesize2 = 300px
|caption = Metrorail (top), Metromover (middle), and Metrobus (bottom) at Government Center
|locale = [[South Florida metropolitan area|Greater Miami]]
|transit_type = [[Rapid transit]], [[Downtown Miami|Downtown]] [[people mover]], [[bus rapid transit]], [[transit bus]]
|began_operation = August 2, 1960&lt;ref&gt;http://scholar.library.miami.edu/miamidigital/1960s.php&lt;/ref&gt;
|system_length = {{convert|31|mi|km}} ''(Elevated metro; [[2012 in rail transport|2012]])''
|lines = 2 Metrorail lines&lt;br&gt;3 Metromover loops&lt;br&gt;90 [[bus|Metrobus]] routes&lt;br&gt;1 [[bus rapid transit]] line
|stations = [[Miami Central Station]]&lt;br&gt;[[Government Center (MDT station)|Government Center]]&lt;p&gt;23 (Metrorail)&lt;br&gt;22 (Metromover)&lt;br&gt;28 (South Dade Busway)
|ridership = 391,000+ daily
|chief_executive= Ysela Llort (Interim Director)
|headquarters=701 NW 1st Court&lt;br&gt;[[Miami]], [[Florida]], 33132
|vehicles = 893 buses&lt;br&gt; 136 Metrorail cars&lt;br&gt; 42 Metromover cars
|track_gauge = {{RailGauge|sg}} ([[standard gauge]])
|operator = Miami-Dade Transit
}}

'''Miami-Dade Transit''' ('''MDT''') is the primary [[public transit]] authority of [[Miami, Florida]], [[United States]] and the greater [[Miami-Dade County, Florida|Miami-Dade County]] area.  It is the largest transit system in Florida and the 12th-largest transit system in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.contactlessnews.com/2008/07/10/cubic-wins-contract-to-update-miami-dade-transits-aging-fare-collection-system&lt;/ref&gt;

MDT operates the [[rapid transit]] [[Metrorail (Miami)|Metrorail]], the [[Downtown Miami|Downtown]] [[Metromover]] [[people mover]], Metrobus, and Paratransit (STS) systems. Metrorail is composed of two rail lines (Green and Orange lines) with 23 stations radiating from the city center towards outlying neighborhoods north and south of Downtown. Metromover operates throughout the Downtown and [[Brickell]] neighborhoods, and is composed of three rail loops and 22 stations. Metrobus operates over 110 routes, including the [[Bus rapid transit|South Dade Busway]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/rider_busway.asp&lt;/ref&gt; MDT's main transit stations are [[Government Center (MDT station)|Government Center]] in Downtown, and the new [[Miami Central Station]] in [[Grapeland Heights]], near [[Miami International Airport]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.micdot.com/miami_central_station.html&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2011, MDT has a daily passenger ridership of 336,067, and accounts for over 15% of Miamians' daily transportation. MDT has seen growing passenger ridership since 1998, with ridership increasing 79% since then. The opening of the new Metrorail Orange Line in April 2012 is expected to significantly increase usage of the system.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/news_technical_reports.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Although not under the control of MDT, [[Tri-Rail]] is Miami's [[commuter rail]] system, and connects Miami to suburbs north to [[Fort Lauderdale]] and [[West Palm Beach]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tri-rail.com/rider_info/system_map.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, the Interim Director of the authority is Ysela Llort. The MDT headquarters are located in the Overtown Transit Village in [[Downtown Miami]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/contact.asp Contact Us].&quot; Miami-Dade Transit. Retrieved on September 14, 2011. &quot;Miami-Dade Transit Administrative Offices Overtown Transit Village 701 NW 1st Court Miami, Florida 33136&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In [[1960 in rail transport|1960]], the [[Miami-Dade county law and government|Dade County Commission]] passed an ordinance creating the Metropolitan Transit Authority (MTA) to unify the different transit operations into one countywide service. This [[local ordinance|ordinance]] provided for the purchase, development, and operation of an adequate [[mass transit]] system by the County. These companies included the Miami Transit Company, Miami Beach Railway Company, South Miami Coach Lines, and Keys Transit Company on Key Biscayne and would be managed by National City Management Company.  Over the years and under various administrations, MTA evolved into the Metro-Dade Transportation Administration, the Metro-Dade Transit Agency, the Miami-Dade Transit Agency, and is now known simply as Miami-Dade Transit (MDT).  

Miami-Dade Transit, a county department of more than 4,000 employees, is the largest transit agency in the state of Florida and accounts for more than half of the trips taken on public transit in the state. MDT operates an [[accessibility|accessible]], integrated system of 100-plus [[Miami-Dade Transit#Metrobus|Metrobus]] routes; the {{convert|22|mi|km|adj=on}} [[Miami-Dade Metrorail|Metrorail]] [[rapid transit]] system; [[Miami-Dade Metromover|Metromover]], a free [[Downtown Miami|downtown]] [[people mover]] system; and the Paratransit division’s Special Transportation Service. Metrobus routes cover more than 35-million miles annually, including limited service to [[Broward County, Florida|Broward]] and [[Monroe County, Florida|Monroe]] counties. In 2004, MDT's Metrorail, Metromover, and Metrobus transported more than 96 million passengers, compared to 85 million the previous year.

===2011 federal investigation===
[[File:Metro um.jpg|thumb|left|250px|A Metro train entering [[University (Metrorail station)|University Station]]]]
Miami-Dade Transit is undergoing a federal investigation by the [[Federal Transit Administration]] that includes several audits and a criminal investigation of the transit agency due to concerns over money mismanagement within the agency.&lt;ref name=&quot;miamiheraldjuly7&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2011/07/07/2303266/miami-dade-county-commission-to.html|title=
Miami-Dade to weigh $100M loan for ailing Transit Agency|author=Martha Brannigan and Alfonso Chardy|date=July 7, 2011|publisher=The [[Miami Herald]]|accessdate=2011-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; This caused a freezing of federal funds being granted to the county agency. In late 2010 the county manager claimed that it was 'not fraud' but rather accounting errors, poor management, and erroneous information given to the auditors that triggered the investigation, including a withdrawal of $15 million through the [[ECHO]] program that was made by a transit official two hours after a letter arrived in September 2010 from the FTA telling them withdrawals had been restricted.&lt;ref name=&quot;miamiheralddecember8&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/12/08/1962604/miami-dade-transits-federal-funding.html|title=Miami-Dade Transit's federal funding freeze `not fraud'|date=December 8, 2010|author=Alfonso Chardy|publisher=Miami Herald|accessdate=2011-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The investigation and lack of funding let to emergency service cuts to Metrorail, Metrobus, and Metromover being considered by the agency by the middle of 2011, six months into the investigation and lack of funding which began in November 2010, causing MDT to lose $185 million in grant money. Assistant county manager Ysela Llort became responsible for Miami-Dade Transit after director Harpal Kapoor left in April 2011. Additionally, funding for the Metrorail airport link was jeopardized by the funding freeze. The FTA decided to continue funding under strict control in order to keep service cuts from happening.&lt;ref name=&quot;miamiheraldmay10&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2011/05/10/2211021/miami-dade-transit-agency-eyes.html|title=
Miami-Dade transit agency eyes service cuts as feds hold back money|author=Martha Brannigan, Alfonso Chardy and Matthew Haggman|date=May 10, 2011|publisher=Miami Herald|accessdate=2011-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Improvement projects===
*The Miami-Dade County Government has received federal money in order to purchase new and refurbish old Metrorail and Metromover cars, as they have been operating for more than 20 years.
*'''Technology and Corridor Improvements''': Two corridors, totaling {{convert|24.4|mi|km}} of rapid transit, have completed the planning phase and are ready to enter into final design and construction—the '''North Corridor''', '''Earlington Heights-MIC Connection''', and '''East-West Corridor'''.

==Fares==
[[File:Miami Easy Card.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The EASY Card was implemented in 2009, and allows for fast and seamless transfers between [[Miami Metrorail|Metrorail]], [[Tri-Rail]], [[Metromover]] and Metrobus.]]
{{See also|EASY Card (South Florida)}}

''The &quot;EASY Card&quot; system is a regional fare collection system with interoperable smartcards and equipment.  The following information is specific to Miami-Dade Transit:''

Since October 1, 2009, Miami-Dade Transit has used the [[EASY Card (South Florida)|EASY Card]] system&lt;ref name=&quot;miamidade.gov&quot;&gt;http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/library/pdfs/misc/english_easy_card_brochure_july2009.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; for fare collection.

On December 13, 2009 paper-based bus transfers were discontinued, and bus-to-bus transfers are now free only when using an EASY Card or EASY Ticket.

* An EASY Card can be purchased for $2 at EASY Card sales outlets, vending machines in Metrorail stations, calling 3-1-1 in Miami-Dade County, or online. Money can be reloaded on to the card at the same places and locations. The card lasts for 3 years from first use.

* Alternatively an EASY Ticket may be purchased with no sales charge.  However EASY Tickets are limited to the fare type initially loaded onto it, and expire 60 days after purchase.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/easy_card.asp&lt;/ref&gt;  EASY Tickets also may not be purchased online or via telephone.

* With the change, paper transfers are being eliminated on transit. People paying fares in cash will need to pay full fare when transferring.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/library/easy_card/transfers_poster.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Transfers will be available only by paying with an EASY Card or Ticket and using the card again within 3 hours of boarding transit.

The current standard fare is $2 and reduced fare is $1. A standard [[season ticket|monthly pass]] costs $100 and $50 for reduced fare. The monthly Metropass is loaded onto the EASY Card.  [[Turnstile]] equipment at all Metrorail stations does not accept any type of cash,&lt;ref name=&quot;miamidade.gov&quot;/&gt; and require an EASY Card or Ticket to both enter and exit the boarding area.

Reduced fares are available only to [[Medicare (United States)|Medicare]] recipients, people with [[disability|disabilities]], and Miami-Dade students in grades 1-12. 

All Miami-Dade [[senior citizen]]s aged 65 years and older and with [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] benefits ride free with a Golden Passport pass. [[Veteran]]s residing in Miami-Dade and earning less than $22,000 annually ride free with the Patriot Passport pass.

==Passenger ridership==
[[File:Government Center rush hour.png|right|thumb|250px|Passengers at [[Government Center (MDT station)|Government Center]]]]
In February 2011, Miami-Dade Transit ridership totaled 336,067 passengers, including all Metrorail, Metromover and Metrobus lines. With a population of about 2.5 million in Miami-Dade County, Miami-Dade Transit accounts for 15% of the population's daily mode of transportation. Note: This figure does not include [[Tri-Rail]], Miami's [[commuter rail]] operator.

&lt;big&gt;'''Daily passenger ridership averages'''&lt;/big&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
! Year !! Metrobus !! [[Miami Metrorail|Metrorail]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/news_technical_reports_archive.asp&lt;/ref&gt; !! [[Metromover]] !! Total ridership
|-
| 1998 || 207,048 || 44,871 || 13,269 || 265,188
|-
| 1999 || 209,111 || 46,774 || 13,880 || 269,765
|-
| 2000 || 212,927 || 47,256 || 14,383 || 274,566
|-
| 2001 || 211,823 || 46,664 || 16,849 || 275,336
|-
| 2002 || 204,941 || 47,064 || 16,444 || 268,449
|-
| 2003 || 215,306 || 51,248 || 25,521 || 292,076
|-
| 2004 || 234,109 || 55,294 || 28,192 || 317,595
|-
| 2005 || 246,023 || 59,700 || 28,473 || 334,195
|-
| 2006 || 259,375 || 58,358 || 27,042 || 344,775
|-
| 2007 || 264,467 || 59,708 || 28,058 || 352,233
|-
| 2008 || 259,018 || 63,710 || 26,682 || 349,410
|-
| 2009 || 233,858 || 59,992 || 25,883 || 319,733
|-
| 2010 || 227,883 || 59,900 || 27,175 || 314,958
|-
| February 2011 || 243,878 || 65,300 || 29,878 || 336,067
|-
|}

==Metrorail==
{{main|Metrorail (Miami)}}
[[File:Metrorail-Tri-Rail.png|right|250px|thumb|Metrorail is the city's rapid transit rail system]]

Metrorail is an elevated rapid transit heavy rail system similar to a subway train that has one {{convert|22.4|mi|km|0|abbr=on}} main line from [[Hialeah]] to [[Kendall, Florida|Kendall]] and an under construction line known as the Airport Link to [[Miami International Airport]].
===Metrorail line expansions===
*The '''AirportLink''' is a {{convert|2.4|mi|km|adj=on}} extension from Earlington Heights Metrorail Station to the Miami Intermodal Center (north of NW 21st St. and east of NW 42nd Ave. at Miami International Airport).  Construction is scheduled to be completed in late 2011, with Metrorail passenger service on the extension starting in early 2012.
*The '''North Corridor''' is a {{convert|9.5|mi|km|adj=on}} expansion will be a northward extension from the  Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Plaza Metrorail Station, along NW 27th Avenue to NW 215th Street (Miami-Dade/Broward County line); with proposed stations at Northside Shopping Center, MDC-North Campus, City of Opa-locka, Bunche Park, Miami Gardens, [[Sun Life Stadium]] and the [[Calder Race Course]]. The project has been postponed indefinitely and has been deemed not eligible to federal funding.
*The '''East-West Corridor''' is a {{convert|10.6|mi|km|adj=on}} expansion from the Miami Intermodal Center west to the Palmetto Expressway (SR 826) and from the Palmetto, through West-Dade County and [[Florida Turnpike]]/[[Florida International University|FIU]]/117th Avenue.  These sites have been identified as potential station locations: [[Florida International University]], NW 107th Avenue (Avenue of the Americas), NW 97th Avenue, NW 87th Avenue (Galloway Road), NW 72nd Avenue (Milam Dairy Road), the Blue Lagoon area, and Miami Intermodal Center.

==Metromover==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[People mover]] --&gt;
{{main|Metromover}}
[[File:Miami-Dade Metromover.jpg|250px|right|thumb|The Metromover operates three rail loops throughout the greater Downtown area]]
Metromover is a free, elevated, automated mass transit [[people mover]] that runs on three loops: the Downtown Inner Loop, Brickell Loop, and the Omni Loop. The systems totals 4.4 miles with 22 stations at roughly every two blocks in the greater Downtown area. Metromover serves the neighborhoods of [[Downtown Miami|Downtown]], [[Brickell]], [[Omni (Miami)|Omni]], [[Park West (Miami)|Park West]], and [[Overtown (Miami)|Overtown]].

==Metrobus==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Miami, Florida]] --&gt;
{{main|List of Miami Metrobus routes}}

{{Infobox Bus transit
| name            = Metrobus
| logo            =  
| logo_size       =  
| image           = MiamiMetroBus.jpg 
| image_size      = 
| image_caption   = 
| company_slogan  = 
| parent          = 
| founded         = 
| headquarters    =  
| locale          = [[Miami, Florida]]
| service_area    =  
| service_type    = [[bus service]], [[bus rapid transit]]
| alliance        = 
| routes          = 90
| destinations    = 
| stops           = 
| hubs            =
| stations        = 
| lounge          = 
| fleet           = 900+
| ridership       = 293,000  &lt;ref&gt;http://miamitodaynews.com/news/090521/story1.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
| fuel_type       = 
| operator        = Miami-Dade Transit
| ceo             =  
| website         = 
}}

The '''Metrobus''' network provides bus service throughout [[Miami-Dade County, Florida|Miami-Dade County]] 365 days a year.  It consists of about 90 routes and 900 buses, which connect most points in the county and part of southern [[Broward County, Florida|Broward County]] as well.  Seven of these routes operate around the clock: Routes 3, 11, 27, 38, 77, L (No 24 hour Hialeah service)and S. Routes 246 Night Owl &amp; Route 500 Midnight Owl operate from 12am to 5am. Most other routes operate from 5 AM to 11 PM. All Metrobuses are wheelchair accessible, in compliance with the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]].

Bus route 301 (Dade-Monroe Express) extends into [[Monroe County, Florida|Monroe County]], reaching [[Marathon, Florida|Marathon]], where a transfer is available to a Key West Transit bus proceeding further into the Keys.  With the appropriate bus transfers, one can travel all the way from [[Key West, Florida|Key West]] to [[Jupiter, Florida|Jupiter]] entirely on public-transit buses.

===South Miami-Dade Busway===
The '''South Miami-Dade Busway''' (originally the South Dade [[Busway]]) began operating on February 3, 1997 and was extended in April 2005. The final {{convert|6.5|mi|km|adj=on}} segment of the Busway extension to Florida City opened on Sunday, December 16, 2007. It is parallel to US1/ S Dixie Highway, and replaced an abandoned Florida East Coast Railroad line.  It is an alternative to daily traffic congestion. The {{convert|13|mi|km|adj=on}} roadway was built by the [[Florida Department of Transportation]] just for Metrobus routes and emergency vehicles.  Express buses on the exclusive lanes shuttle passengers to and from [[Dadeland South (Metrorail station)|Dadeland South Station]] (see [[#Metrorail|Metrorail]]) in under 40 minutes.

Both full-size buses and minibuses operate on the Busway and in adjacent neighborhoods, entering the exclusive lanes at major intersections. Local and limited-stop service is offered between [[Florida City, Florida|Florida City]] and Dadeland South Metrorail Station. [[Park and ride|Park &amp; Ride]] lots along the busway are located at SW 152d Street (Coral Reef Drive), SW 168th Street (Richmond Drive), SW 200th Street (Caribbean Boulevard), SW 244th Street, and SW 296th Street. At [[Dadeland South (Metrorail station)|Dadeland South Station]], riders transfer to Metrorail. Riders headed downtown can transfer from Metrorail to Metromover, which consists of three shorter downtown loops, at [[Government Center (changeover station)|Government Center Station]].

The South Miami-Dade Busway features 28 stops, all of which have been converted to light-rail style stations.  A [[Segregated cycle facilities|multi-use path]] stretches the length of the Busway.

====South Dade Busway stations====
{| style=&quot;border:1px solid #ddd; background:#fefefe; padding:5px; margin:5px;&quot;
|
*SW 104th Street
*SW 112th Street
*SW 117th Street
*SW 124th Street
*SW 128th Street
*SW 136th Street
*SW 144th Street
*SW 152nd Street (Park-N-Ride)
*SW 160th Street
*SW 168th Street (Park-N-Ride)
| style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;|
|
*SW 173rd Street
*W Indigo Street
*SW 184th Street
*Marlin Road
*SW 200th Street
*SW 212th Street (Park-N-Ride)
*SW 216th Street
*SW 220th Street
*SW 232nd Street
*SW 244th Street
| style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;|
|
*SW 264th Street
*SW 272nd Street
*SW 280th Street
*SW 296th Street (Park-N-Ride)
*SW 312th Street
*Historic Homestead
*SW 324th Street
*SW 328th Street
*SW 344th Street
|}

====Routes that use the Busway====
*1- Serves the station at 173 st and a route that travels through [[Perrine, Florida]] and Quail Roost DR which every bus passes every half hour. 
*31 Busway Local- serves all stations between northern end of the busway and [[Southland Mall (Miami, Florida)|Southland Mall]], before looping to serve [[Cutler Bay, Florida|Cutler Bay]] shopping centers and the South Dade Government Office Complex
*34 Busway Flyer- travels the entire length of the busway, but does not stop at any stations before SW 152nd Street
*38 Busway MAX- travels the entire length of the busway, deviating from the route slightly to serve Southland Mall, and travelling beyond the end of the busway to serve Florida City shopping centers
*52- begins at [[Dadeland North (Metrorail station)|Dadeland North Metrorail Station]], then runs along busway to SW 152nd street, before becoming a Richmond Heights and Goulds local route
*252 Coral Reef MAX- begins at [[Dadeland South (Metrorail station)|Dadeland South Metrorail Station]], then runs along busway to SW 152nd Street, before becoming express route to [[Country Walk, Florida|Country Walk]]
*287 Saga Bay MAX- begins at Dadeland South Metrorail Station, then runs along busway to SW 168th Street, before running as express route through [[West Perrine, Florida|West Perrine]] and [[Saga Bay, Florida|Saga Bay]]

===Busway vs. rail controversy===
The Busway has been the site of many accidents, as some car drivers driving south on US-1 (which runs parallel to the Busway for much of its length), and looking to turn west, do not stop at the red arrows that govern the right turn lane at an intersection that has a Busway crossing adjacent to it. They make a right turn and go right into the path of a bus that is entering the adjacent Busway intersection. Buses currently have to slow down to {{convert|15|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} before crossing the intersection, and the police often patrol the intersections looking for red arrow runners. Surprisingly, even the intersections where the Busway runs as far as 2 blocks west of US-1 suffer the same problem, with car drivers either not seeing or flatly ignoring the red lights at SW 184th and 186th Streets. City planners and residents alike have commented that rather than dismantling the former Florida East Coast Railroad line for the busway, the Metrorail system could have been extended southward over the railway line.

==Paratransit (STS)==
'''Paratransit/Special Transportation Services (STS)''' is available for people with a mental or physical disability that cannot ride Metrobus, Metrorail, or Metromover. For $3.00 per one-way trip, STS offers shared-ride, door-to-door travel in accessible vehicles throughout most of Miami-Dade County, in some parts of south Broward County, and in the middle and northern [[Florida Keys|Keys]] . STS operates 24 hours a day, seven days a week, including most holidays.

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Miami|Transportation}}
*[[Transportation in Miami]]
*[[List of Miami-Dade Transit metro stations]]
*[[Tri-Rail]], Miami's commuter rail system
*[[List of rapid transit systems#North America|List of rapid transit systems]]
*[[List of United States railroads]]
*[[List of Florida railroads]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;
*[http://www.apta.com/research/stats/ridership/riderep/indexus.cfm APTA ridership information]

==External links==
* [http://www.miamidade.gov/transit Miami-Dade Transit]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080411000453/http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/library/pdfs/corridor/ew/ew_route_alignment_map.pdf Planned East-West Corridor Route Alignment Map (PDF)]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080215065512/http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/corridor/ew_corridor/ew_station_locations.asp Planned East-West Corridor Station Locations]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080630173947/http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/corridor/n_corridor/n_9_mile_route_alignment_map.asp Planned North Corridor Route Alignment Map]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080628171917/http://www.miamidade.gov/transit/corridor/n_corridor/n_7_station_locations.asp Planned North Corridor Station Locations]
* [http://www.trafficrelief.com Citizens' Independent Transportation Trust]
* [http://www.TransitMiami.com Transit Miami] (news and information blog)
* [http://lilpony.blogspot.com Public Transit] (MDTA commuter blog)

{{South Florida rail metro system}}
{{USSubway}}
{{FloridaTransSystems}}
{{Miami}}
{{Greater Miami}}

[[Category:Miami-Dade Transit]]
[[Category:Transportation in Miami, Florida| ]]
[[Category:1960 establishments]]
[[Category:Bus rapid transit in Florida]]

[[es:Departamento de Transporte Público de Miami-Dade]]
[[pl:Miami-Dade Transit]]
[[pt:Miami-Dade Transit]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
