<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="575028" ns="0" title="Athabasca University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Inappropriate tone|date=January 2010}}
{{Infobox university
|name            = Athabasca University
|image_name      = AthabascaUniversity.svg
|image_size      = 200px
|motto           = Canada's Open University
|established     = 1970
|type            = [[public university|Public]]
|president       = Dr. [[Frits Pannekoek]]
|students        = 38,464&lt;ref name=&quot;businessplan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.athabascau.ca/aboutau/documents/businessplans/010_2014_Plan.pdf |title=Athabasca University Business Plan 2010-14 |publisher=Athabasca University |accessdate=2010-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       = 34,921&lt;ref name=&quot;businessplan&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad        = 3,543&lt;ref name=&quot;businessplan&quot;/&gt;
|doctoral        = 
|profess         = 
|city            = [[Athabasca, Alberta|Athabasca]]
|province        = [[Alberta]]
|country         = [[Canada]]
|campus          = [[Rural]] and [[Urban area|urban]]
|free_label      = [[Faculty_(academic_staff)|Faculty]] &amp; [[Employment|Staff]]
|free            = 1,382&lt;ref name=&quot;businessplan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.athabascau.ca/aboutau/documents/businessplans/010_2014_Plan.pdf |title=Athabasca University Business Plan 2010-14 |publisher=Athabasca University |accessdate=2010-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|colours         = [[Blue (color)|Blue]] And [[Green (color)|Green]] {{color box|#072B61}}{{color box|#00FF00}}
|mascot          = 
|nickname        = AU
|affiliations    = [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]],  [[Canadian Virtual University|CVU]], [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]], [[Canadian University Press|CUP]], [http://www.cags.ca CAGS].
|footnotes       = 
|website         = http://www.athabascau.ca/
}}
'''Athabasca University''' is a Canadian university in [[Athabasca, Alberta]]. It is an [[School accreditation|accredited]] research institution which also offers [[distance education]] courses and programs. Courses are offered primarily in [[Canadian English|English]] with some [[French language|French]] offerings.  Each year, 32,000 students attend the university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.athabascau.ca/aboutAU/ |title=About Athabasca University |accessdate=2007-09-09 |publisher=Athabasca University}}&lt;/ref&gt; It offers opportunities for professionals to finish undergraduate, graduate and certificate programs.  Canadian athletes, politicians and broadcasters have chosen Athabasca to complete their studies due to the flexibility in the university's schedule.  In 2004, Athabasca's [[Executive MBA]] was rated in the top 75 by the ''[[Financial Times]]'', the only executive MBA on the list that is delivered entirely online.&lt;ref name=&quot;FT&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Byrne
  | first =T.C.
  | authorlink =Tim Byrne
  | coauthors =
  | title =Athabasca University The Evolution of Distance Education
  | publisher = University of Calgary Press
  | year=  1989
  | location = Calgary, Alberta
  | pages = 135
  | isbn = 0-919813-51-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The enabling legislation is the Post-secondary Learning Act &lt;ref&gt;http://www.qp.alberta.ca/574.cfm?page=p19p5.cfm&amp;leg_type=Acts&amp;isbncln=9780779737932 Post-secondary Learning Act&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
The university was created by the [[Alberta]] government in 1970.  It grew out of the development that occurred after the [[University of Alberta]] had long been established, and following the creation of the [[University of Calgary]] after legislation had been changed, and following an order in council creating the [[University of Lethbridge]].&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

In 1967 the [[Ernest Manning|Manning government]] announced its intention to establish a fourth University, but it was later delayed by two to three years. The [[University of Alberta]] wanted to expand rather than see another University open in [[Edmonton]] to compete with it. One proposal favoured establishing a Christian university instead of a secular one to cope with rising enrollment. One early suggestion for an alternative was an &quot;Alberta Academy&quot; that would take credits students had earned at multiple Universities and evaluate them for transfer, and perhaps even award a degree. A department of education ad hoc group favoured the establishment of a fourth University.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

A group of [[University of Alberta]] graduates, which included [[Preston Manning]] helped influence the development of an independent fourth University. In 1970 [[Lieutenant Governor of Alberta]] [[Grant MacEwan]] established the University by an order in council. The name for the new University was a challenge to choose, not wanting to associate the University with a city that already had a University, in a primarily rural province. ''Athabasca Hall'' a student residence at the [[University of Alberta]] was scheduled for demolition, so the name was appropriated for the new University.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

While the school is a traditional research university, it is also renowned for its distance programs.  This began in 1972 when a pilot project was developed. After being considered a success, the university was granted a permanent, self-governing status in 1978. After growing too big for its location, Athabasca University moved 145 kilometres north from [[Edmonton, Alberta|Edmonton]] to the town of [[Athabasca, Alberta]] in 1984 where it is now established. Satellite centers are in [[Calgary]] and [[Edmonton, Alberta|Edmonton]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.athabascau.ca/aboutAU/history.php |title=History of Athabasca University |accessdate=2007-09-09 |publisher=Athabasca University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mandate===
[[Image:AU2.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Front entrance.]]
The initial mandate for the University dictated that it be primarily [[undergraduate]] in scope. Developing new procedures in curriculum was part of the mandate for the University. The initial Governing Authority of the University had eight members, and a broad range of powers to set up the new University. July 2–3, 1970 they met for the first time, and [[Carl W. Clement]] was the first chairman. It was expected by the government of the day that by [[1979]] the University would have 10,000 students. September 1, 1973 was set as the target date to open.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

===First president===
In April 1971 [[Tim Byrne]] was appointed President of the new university and he assumed office in June that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

The administration chose the [[University of California, Santa Cruz|Santa Cruz campus of the University of California]] as its model, deciding that the individual college should serve as the basic planning unit for the new university, which would be organized as a federation of colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt; 
Each of the colleges of the new university was to have 650 students and needed lecture and office space to reflect that. As well they wanted to adopt a learning approach that would have students learning in small tutorials instead of large lectures. Research within the new university was to be limited to a specified region starting around the city of [[Edmonton]]. One criticism was that the university was trying to do too much.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

The government of [[Peter Lougheed]] in 1971 brought a change, which included a cabinet portfolio specifically for post secondary education. The newly-elected [[Progressive Conservative Association of Alberta|Conservative]] government was opposed to building a new University in Edmonton, but architectural plans were permitted to continue. A proposal was made to the government to test the new model for 3 – 5 years, and if that succeeded, they would become a fully independent University. This happened under the chairmanship of [[Merrill Wolfe]]. The proposal was accepted by the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

One of the trends brought out by the new Deputy Minister of Advanced Education in the summer of 1972 was a demand for lifelong continuing education. An identified need was for an &quot;Alberta Academy&quot; which would evaluate University courses that were taken at multiple institutions. The academy would then award a degree. A second proposal came from the University to also serve part time students, and it would not affect the other traditional Universities already established, or the new approach of Athabasca University. An [[open door policy]] was part of this proposal, removing admission requirements.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

In 1972 a new [[Order in Council|order in council]] was issued to include only the new pilot project of distance education.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

November 17, 2009 a revised mandate was approved by the Minister of Advanced Education and Technology. AU's mission and mandate statement are on the [http://www2.athabascau.ca/aboutau/mission.php Athabasca University] website.

===First course===
[[Image:AU books 1.jpg|thumb|250px|left|Study manual/guides from AU courses]]
Trial and error procedures were used during the pilot period, as there was no model to follow in the field and mandate the staff of the university were given. In 1973 the university began to advertise for students to help with course development. A course &quot;World Ecology&quot; was the first course, and was the core of the pilot project. In-house production of the learning packages was important to the staff, so the university developed its own printing process.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

{{cquote|Contrary to much current belief, Athabasca University was not modelled after the [[Open University]], but was developed in its present form during the pilot project. AU became aware of what the Open University was doing when, during the final year of the project. A representative went to [[Milton Keynes]] discover any methods its staff might have devised to speed up production.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;}}

In 1975 plans came together to reach out to students by developing field services tutors, and regional learning centres. In 1976 the first 24 part time telephone tutors were appointed. The tutor role was to facilitate learning, not teach the course. Tutors are assigned blocks of 20 - 40 students each. An unlisted toll-free number is provided to contact the tutor with. All tutors have at least a Masters degree.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

An early test project for a learning resource centre had books and tapes relevant to the courses available at branches of public libraries throughout the province. Although the libraries were keen on the idea, learners preferred to remain in their homes to learn. By 1975 the median age was 35 - 40, and there were 725 students. A minority of students had only completed grade 9.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

{{cquote|Inviting students to register in a course and then forcing them to wait an unconscionable length of time for delivery of units was obviously not a way to establish a reputation as a reliable institution.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;}}

In 1975 at the end of the pilot project, an agency was appointed to evaluate the overall success. A recommendation was made to the government that the University be made a permanent member of the university system. It was to remain an open university. Under the chairmanship of [[Edward Checkland]], the University gained permanency.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

In 1976 [[W. A. Samuel Smith]] took over as president and the university's permanency was established through an act of the [[Alberta Legislature]].&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

The first collaboration the university embarked on was with [[Keyano College]], which eventually led to the opening of a regional learning office in [[Fort McMurray, Alberta]]. [[North Island College]] in 1976 took on the challenge of delivering many courses from the university in its many campuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

{{cquote|In the mid-seventies, two young Canadians, one of whom was the son of a prominent Edmonton family, were indicted in an English court for attempting to smuggle drugs into the country. They were each sentenced to a lengthy prison term and incarcerated in one of [[England]]'s most infamous prisons. Each registered in one of Athabasca University's first three courses, becoming the first two in a long list of [[prison|prison inmates]] to join its student body.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;}}

In 1985 an agreement was reached with the [[Correctional Service of Canada]] regarding the payment of tuition and program delivery fees related to federal inmates taking courses through the University.&lt;ref name=&quot;byrne&quot; /&gt;

==Distance education==
[[Image:AU1.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Water fountain at the University]]
The Athabasca University Centre for Distance Education has programs which are geared to continuing education using modern communications [[technology]] and have attracted students from around the world, using on-line study programs and a special dedicated website for that purpose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.canadianbusinessschools.com/cms/?z=9&amp;a=200 |title=Athabasca University |publisher=Canadian Business Schools |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is home to [[North America]]'s first online [[Doctor of Education]] in Distance Education program, and offers a Masters of Distance Education degree, and a Graduate Diploma in Distance Education. It has ten core faculty members and contracts additional sessional faculty.  Athabasca University supports the publication of the [http://www.irrodl.org International Review of Open and Distance Education] which is indexed in Social Sciences Citation Index (ISI), is arguably the most well known and most frequently cited scholarly joiunral in the filed of distance and open education &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Zawacki--Richter|first=Olaf|coauthors=Terry Anderson,	 Nazime Tuncay|title=The Growing Impact of Open Access Distance Education Journals: A Bibliometric Analysis|journal=Journal of Distance Education|year=2010|volume=24|issue=3|url=http://www.jofde.ca/index.php/jde/article/view/661/1210}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Accreditation ==
Athabasca University reports to the government through the [[Minister of Advanced Education]] and is publicly funded through the Province of [[Alberta]]. The university's governing council is authorized to grant degrees through the [[Post-Secondary Learning Act]] along with governing its own affairs. Members of the governing council are appointed by the [[Lieutenant Governor of Alberta|Lieutenant Governor]] in council.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.canlii.org/ab/laws/regu/2004r.50/20070813/whole.html |title=Athabasca University Regulation, Alta. Reg. 50/2004 |publisher=CanLII |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The university is accredited with the United States by the Commission on Higher Education of the [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chea.org/search/actionInst.asp?CheaID=502 |publisher=Council for Higher Education Accreditation |title=Database of Institutions Accredited By Recognized U.S. Accrediting Organizations |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Select memberships===
* [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada]]
* [[Association of Commonwealth Universities]]
* [http://www.cags.ca Canadian Association for Graduate Studies]
* [[Canadian Virtual University]]
* [[International Council for Open and Distance Education]]
* [[University of the Arctic]]

==Academics==
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Edmonton learning centre.jpg|right|210px|thumb|Edmonton Learning Centre]] --&gt;
AU is [[Canada]]'s only exclusively open University, and [[Maclean's Magazine]] called it Canada's fastest growing university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.macleans.ca/education/universities/article.jsp?content=20070831_192021_1108 |publisher=[[Macleans Magazine]] |title=The chalkboard is dead: researchers |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; 50% of AU's students are between the ages of 25 and 44, and admissions are year round. AU plays host to 3 [[Canada Research Chair]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chairs.gc.ca/web/chairholders/profile_searchresults_e.asp?Province_ID=0&amp;UniversityID=2&amp;SubjectID=&amp;DisciplineID=&amp;Researcher=&amp;Date_Announce=&amp;Keyword= |title=Canadian Research Chairs |publisher=Government of Canada |accessdate=2007-09-09}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; 260,000 students have taken courses since the University was founded.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.athabascau.ca/newsroom/press/facts.php |title=Facts &amp; Statistics |publisher=Athabasca University |accessdate=2007-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

AU has 27,107 [[undergraduate]] students, with 77 undergraduate programs. Of that two are university diplomas, fourteen are university certificates and one is a certificate of completion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.athabascau.ca/programs/outcomes.php |title=Undergraduate Degree Programs List |accessdate=2007-09-16 |publisher=Athabasca University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research===
AU spends over $2 million per year on research.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; The university has four [[Canada Research Chair]]s and one NSERC/Xerox/Markin/ICORE Research Chair. The [[Athabasca University Research Centre|Centre for Research]] is the primary centre at the university, along with the Technology Enhanced Knowledge Research Institute and the Centre for World Indigenous Knowledge and Research.

Noteworthy Faculty
* [[Martin Connors]], Canadian Research Chair, Space Science, discovered Trojan asteroid associated with planet Earth (2011)
* [[Alvin Finkel]], Professor, History, published several significant books on contemporary social and political history
* [[Joseph Pivato]], Professor, Literature, published eight books on ethnic minority writing in Canada
* [[Norman Temple]], Professor, Food Science, published several books on health and nutrition
* [[Tracey Lindberg]], Canadian Research Chair, Indigenous Knowledge and Law, many publications on social and legal questions
* [[Anne Nothof]], Professor Emerita, English, published several books on Canadian theatre 
* [[Michael Gismondi]], Professor, Sociology, books on environmental and social questions in Canada and Central America
* [[Terry Anderson]], Professor, former Canada Research Chair, Distance Education, published seven books, articles on distance education
* [[Kinshuk]], Professor, Zerox Research Chair, Computer and Information Science, IEEE editor and very active research publisher


AU is also a participating member of the [[WestGrid]] Research Network.

===Rankings===
In 2004, Athabasca's [[Executive MBA]] was rated in the top 75 by the [[Financial Times]], the only executive MBA on the list that is delivered entirely online. The EMBA has since fallen from the FT rankings, and doesn't show up in the 2009 FT rankings for EMBA.&lt;ref name=&quot;FT&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rankings.ft.com/rankings/emba/rankings.html |publisher=FT.com |title=EMBA rankings 2009 |accessdate=2009-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005 38% of the students in the MBA program were female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.businessweek.com/bschools/05/emba_profiles/athabasca.htm |title=Athabasca University |publisher=Business Week |accessdate=2007-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; AU has never been included in the annual rankings by [[Macleans Magazine]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gateway.ualberta.ca/view.php?aid=6271 |title=Universities drop out of Maclean's survey |publisher=[[The Gateway]] |accessdate=2007-09-16}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; because of its &quot;special mission.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.universityaffairs.ca/issues/2005/december/_print/letters.html |publisher=University Affairs |title=Time again for Maclean's rankings |accessdate=2007-09-16 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071103060618/http://www.universityaffairs.ca/issues/2005/december/_print/letters.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2008, Athabasca was named one of [[Alberta's Top Employers]] by Mediacorp Canada Inc., which was announced by the [[Calgary Herald]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canada.com/calgaryherald/story.html?id=02b19397-2fdf-4039-ba29-b93eaf908adb|title=Calgary Herald, &quot;Alberta’s top 40 places to work&quot;, October 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Edmonton Journal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canada.com/edmontonjournal/story.html?id=5bc8514a-b0eb-4538-bab4-a63f11f51a16|title=Edmonton Journal, &quot;Alberta's best focus on attracting, keeping staff&quot;, October 31, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eluta.ca/top-employer-athabasca-university|title=Reasons for Selection, 2009 Alberta's Top Employers competition}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:AU books 2.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Athabasca University books]]

===Delivery Models===
AU's classes are taught in several ways: 

* Individual study: Students are provided with the textbooks, computer software, and video material required. A preset recommended schedule comes with each course.  Each course has a professor, as with any university course.  This person publishes creates a series of learning activities, readings and assessments.  That publication becomes additional reading and activity for the student. Assignments are submitted to the professor via email or more commonly via the Moodle assignment drop box..  The final exam is administered by at Athabasca's learning centres or a partner university, college or accredited individual.  Students have up to six months to finish their course, unless they have received a student loan, in which case, they have up to four months. Courses start at the beginning of each month. Most courses are now augmented with additional resources and activities using the Moodle LMS

* Collaborative, online: Courses in the graduate programs are paced, usually beginning three times a year. The primary delivery platform is the [http://moodle.org Moodle] Learning Management System, that is augmented by web conferencing using Adobe Connect and social networking using [http://elgg.org elgg] based [https://landing.athabascau.ca Athabasca Landing]

* Grouped study: Offered primarily to students physically in [[Alberta]], this method allows students to get together with other students in the same course, and study in a manner similar to that of a regular university. Students studying in this method have up to 4 months to complete their course. Courses start in September and January.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.athabascau.ca/aboutAU/distanceeducation.php |title=Who studies at AU |accessdate=2007-09-09 |publisher=Athabasca University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable people==
[[Image:Ralph-Klein-Szmurlo.jpg|thumb|left|130px|In 2004 Alberta Premier [[Ralph Klein]] was accused of plagiarism in a paper he wrote for an Athabasca University course.]]
{{Main|List of Athabasca University people}}
Some notable people have studied through Athabasca University, including Alberta politician [[Debby Carlson]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Centre for Innovative Management Update |url=http://www.mba.athabascau.ca/titan/aucimwebsite.nsf/AllDoc/79C9DA1CAB6FA4D187256DB200738E71/$File/2003FallNewsletter.pdf!OpenElement |publisher=Athabasca University |accessdate=2007-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Olympic bobsleigh racer [[Christian Farstad]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Olympian joins the Canadian Olympic Committee in new role |publisher=Canadian Olymptic Committee |url=http://www.olympic.ca/EN/organization/news/2003/0626.shtml |accessdate=2007-08-22 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070906022106/http://www.olympic.ca/EN/organization/news/2003/0626.shtml &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alberta Premier [[Ralph Klein]], professional hockey player [[Alyn McCauley]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Koshan |first=Terry |title=No end in sight |url=http://slam.canoe.ca/Slam/Hockey/NHL/2004/10/10/664140.html |publisher=CANOE |accessdate=2007-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cross-country skier [[Milaine Thériault]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cccski.com/main.asp?cmd=doc&amp;ID=3079&amp;lan=0 |title=Milaine Thériault |publisher=Cross Country Canada |accessdate=2007-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The University delivers over 60,000 courses per year, and currently has more than 38,000 students.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

==Controversy==

In May 2004 the [[Premier of Alberta]], [[Ralph Klein]], brought public attention to the university due to allegations that he had [[plagiarism|plagiarized]] a paper that he submitted for a communication studies course he took from the school. While speaking before the provincial legislature, he held up a copy of the paper to provide evidence on his views about former [[Chile]]an dictator General [[Augusto Pinochet]]. Afterwards, there was public criticism that portions of five pages of the 13-page paper had been copied from the Internet without proper citations to the sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/1084462799969_79871999/?hub=TopStories |title=Klein accused of lifting info for school essay |publisher=CTV.ca |date=May 14, 2004 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university investigated the matter and told the news media that Klein's instructor had noted the mistake when grading the paper and offered guidance for correcting it. A university spokesman described the failure to properly cite sources as a &quot;relatively minor error, undisputed by [the] student, easily corrected, and not an ongoing or repeated problem.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20040528/klein_plagiarism_040528?s_name=&amp;no_ads= Klein cleared of plagiarism by his university], ''Canadian Press'', May 28, 2004 (on CTV.ca website; accessed November 4, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

==Student representation==
===Undergrad students===
{{main|Athabasca University Students' Union}}
Undergraduate students at Athabasca University are represented by the Athabasca University Students' Union. The AUSU head office is in AU Edmonton, though the students' council may have elected members from any area where AU students reside. 

AUSU was formed in 1993 and was formalized as a registered Alberta society until students' unions in Alberta were granted recognition under the Post-Secondary Learning Act. On 13 September 2004 the Lieutenant Governor of Alberta approved an [[Order in Council|order in council]] which states:
{{cquote|The Lieutenant Governor in council establishes and incorporates a [[students' union|students' association]] to be known as &quot;The Students' Association of Athabasca University&quot; to provide for the administration of students' affairs and the promotion of the [[general welfare]] of students consistent with the purposes of Athabasca University.}}

AUSU has established several clubs for students. Clubs currently sponsored by AUSU include the AU Health Sciences Society, La Société Française d'AU, the AU Literature Club, AU Business Students’ Association, AU Science Students' Society, AU Sports Club, and the AU Student Moms' Club. Student media at Athabasca University is provided by the official publication The Voice Magazine. Previously published on paper, the magazine since 2001 is published exclusively online in HTML and PDF format.

===Graduate students===
Visiting and program students at the graduate level are represented by the [[Athabasca University Graduate Students' Association]].  The organization was founded in 2010, and approved by the [[Alberta Advanced Education and Technology]]{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}.

==See also==
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
*[[List of universities in the Canadian Prairies]]
*[[Higher education in Alberta]]
*[[Canadian government scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian university scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian industrial research and development organizations]]

==Further reading==
* Small, Michael W. &quot;A Case Study of Educational Policy-making: The Establishment of Athabasca University.&quot; Ph.D. diss., University of Alberta, 1980.

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Wikinews|Athabasca University receives 30 million dollars}}
{{Commons}}
* [http://www.athabascau.ca/ Official website]
{{AthabascaU}}
{{Ab Uni|college=yes|technical = January 2010}}
{{DEiC}}
{{Coord|54|43|20.63|N|113|18|12.19|W|display=title|type:edu}}

[[Category:Athabasca University| ]]
[[Category:Athabasca, Alberta|University, Athabasca]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1970]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Nursing schools in Canada]]
[[Category:Distance education in Canada]]
[[Category:Open universities]]
[[Category:Association of Commonwealth Universities]]

[[de:Athabasca University]]
[[fr:Université Athabasca]]
[[no:Athabasca University]]
[[ru:Университет Атабаски]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
