<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="580291" ns="0" title="Wales national football team"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox national football team
| Name               = Wales
| Badge              = Football Association of Wales logo 2011.png
| Badge_size         = 170px
| Nickname           = ''The Dragons''
| Association        = [[Football Association of Wales]] (FAW)
| Confederation      = [[UEFA]] ([[Europe]])
| Coach              = Vacant{{ref|reference_name_A|note}}
| Asst Manager       = [[Raymond Verheijen]]
| Captain            = [[Aaron Ramsey]]
| Most caps          = [[Neville Southall]] (92)
| Top scorer         = [[Ian Rush]] (28)
| Home Stadium       = [[Millennium Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cardiff City Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Liberty Stadium, Swansea|Liberty Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;
| Capacity           = 74,000
| FIFA Trigramme     = WAL
| FIFA Rank          = &lt;!-- Next Release 21 Dec 2011 --&gt; 50&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.fifa.com/worldranking/rankingtable/index.html#|title=FIFA World Ranking|work=FIFA}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 1st ranking date   = August 1993
| FIFA max           = 27
| FIFA max date      = August 1993
| FIFA min           = 117
| FIFA min date      = August 2011
| Elo Rank           = 59
| Elo max            = 3
| Elo max date       = 1876–1885
| Elo min            = 75
| Elo min date       = September 2000
| pattern_la1=_whiteborder |pattern_b1=_walesh2011 |pattern_ra1=_whiteborder |pattern_sh1= | pattern_so1 = _whitetop
| leftarm1=FF0000 |body1=FF0000 |rightarm1=FF0000 |shorts1=FF0000 |socks1=FF0000
| pattern_la2=_redborder |pattern_b2=_walesa2011 |pattern_ra2=_redborder |pattern_sh2= |pattern_so2= _redtop
| leftarm2=35353C |body2=35353C |rightarm2=35353C |shorts2=35353C |socks2=35353C
| First game         = {{fb|SCO}} [[Scotland v Wales (1876)|4–0]] Wales {{flagicon|Wales}} &lt;br/&gt;([[Glasgow]]; 26 March 1876)
| Largest win        = {{flagicon|Wales}} Wales 11–0 {{fb-rt|IRE}}&lt;br/&gt;([[Wrexham]]; 3 March 1888)
| Largest loss       = {{fb|SCO}} 9–0 Wales {{flagicon|Wales}} &lt;br/&gt;([[Glasgow]]; 23 March 1878)
| World cup apps     = 1
| World cup first    = 1958
| World cup best     = Quarter-finals, [[1958 FIFA World Cup|1958]]
| Regional name = [[UEFA European Football Championship|European Championship]]
| Regional cup apps = none
| Regional cup first = 
| Regional cup best  = Quarter-finals, [[1976 UEFA European Football Championship qualifying|1976 (in Qualifying)]]
}}
The '''Wales national football team''' represents [[Wales]] in international [[association football|football]]. It is controlled by the [[Football Association of Wales]] (FAW), the governing body for football in Wales, and the third oldest national football association in the world. The team have only qualified for a major international tournament once in their history, when Wales qualified for the [[1958 FIFA World Cup]]. However, Wales did progress through [[UEFA Euro 1976 qualifying]] to the quarter-final, which was played on a home and away leg basis.

Although part of the [[United Kingdom]], Wales has always had a representative side that plays in all the major professional tournaments, though not in the [[Olympic Games]], as the [[International Olympic Committee|IOC]] has always recognised United Kingdom representative sides. 

Wales were placed in [[2014 FIFA World Cup qualification – UEFA Group A|Group A]] for [[2014 FIFA World Cup qualification|qualification]] for the [[2014 FIFA World Cup]] tournament alongside [[Croatia national football team|Croatia]], [[Serbia national football team|Serbia]], [[Belgium national football team|Belgium]], [[Scotland national football team|Scotland]] and [[Macedonia national football team|Macedonia]].

==History==
===The early years===
Wales played its [[Scotland v Wales (1876)|first competitive match]] on 25 March 1876 against [[Scotland national football team|Scotland]] in [[Glasgow]], making it the third oldest international football team in the world.

Although the Scots won the first fixture 4–0, a return match was planned in Wales the following year, and so it was that the first international football match on Welsh soil took place at The Racecourse Ground, [[Wrexham]] on 5 March 1877. Scotland took the spoils winning 2–0.

Wales' first match against [[England national football team|England]] came in 1879 – a 2–1 defeat at the [[Kennington Oval]], [[London]] and in 1882 Wales faced [[Northern Ireland national football team|Ireland]] for the first time, winning 7–1 in Wrexham.

The associations of the four [[Home Nations]] met in [[Manchester]] on 6 December 1882 to set down a set of worldwide rules. This meeting saw the establishment of the [[International Football Association Board]] (IFAB) to approve changes to the rules, a task the four associations still perform to this day.

The 1883–84 season saw the formation of the [[British Home Championship]], a tournament which was played annually between England, Scotland, Ireland&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishfa.com/the-ifa/history-of-the-ifa/ History of the Irish FA] at ''www.irishfa.com''&lt;/ref&gt; and Wales, until 1983–84. Wales were champions on 12 occasions, winning outright seven times whilst sharing the title five times.

The FAW became members of [[FIFA]], world football's governing body, in 1906, but the relationship between FIFA and the British associations was fraught and the British nations withdrew from FIFA in 1928 in a dispute over payments to [[amateur]] players. As a result, Wales did not enter the first three [[FIFA World Cup|World Cup]]s.

In 1932 Wales played host to the [[Republic of Ireland national football team|Republic of Ireland]], the first time they played against a side from outside the four home nations. A year later, Wales played a match outside the [[United Kingdom]] for the first time when they travelled to [[Paris]] to take on [[France]] in a match which was drawn 1–1.

===Post-war===
Wales, along with the other four home nations, rejoined FIFA in 1946 and took part in the qualifying rounds for the [[1950 FIFA World Cup|1950 World Cup]], the 1949–50 Home Championships being designated as a qualifying group. The top two teams were to qualify for the finals in [[Brazil]], but Wales finished bottom of the group.

The 1950s were undoubtedly a golden age for Welsh football with stars such as [[Ivor Allchurch]], [[Cliff Jones (Welsh footballer)|Cliff Jones]], [[Alf Sherwood]], [[Jack Kelsey]], [[Trevor Ford]] and, of course, [[John Charles]] pulling on the famous red shirt. Wales made its only World Cup appearance in [[1958 FIFA World Cup|1958]] but their qualification was fortunate to say the least. Having finished second to [[Czechoslovakia national football team|Czechoslovakia]] in qualifying Group 4, the Welsh thought their chances of appearing in Sweden were over. But the golden generation of Welsh football had reckoned without the politics of the [[Middle East]].

[[Egypt national football team|Egypt]] and [[Sudan national football team|Sudan]] had refused to play against [[Israel national football team|Israel]] whilst [[Indonesia national football team|Indonesia]] had insisted on meeting Israel on neutral ground. As a result Israel were proclaimed winners of their respective group in the Asian/African zone. 

FIFA were understandably reluctant to allow a team to qualify for the World Cup finals without actually playing a match and so lots were drawn of all the second placed teams in the [[UEFA]] qualifying groups. Belgium were drawn out of the hat but they refused and so then Wales was drawn and awarded a two-legged play-off match against Israel with a place in Sweden for the winners.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;[http://www.rsssf.com/tables/58q.html Qualification for 1958 World Cup] at ''RSSSF''&lt;/ref&gt;

Having beaten Israel 2–0 at the [[Ramat Gan Stadium]] and 2–0 at [[Ninian Park]], [[Cardiff]], Wales went through to the World Cup Finals for the first and, so far, only time.

The strong [[1958 FIFA World Cup squads|Welsh squad]] made their mark in Sweden, drawing all the matches in their group against [[Hungary national football team|Hungary]], [[Mexico national football team|Mexico]] and [[Sweden national football team|Sweden]] before defeating Hungary in a play off match to reach the quarter-finals against [[Brazilian national football team|Brazil]]. However, Wales' chances of victory against Brazil were hampered by an injury to John Charles that ruled him out of the match. Wales lost 1–0 with 17-year-old [[Pelé]] scoring the only goal of the game and Brazil went on to win the championship.

===The 1970s and 1980s===
Wales have never qualified for the final stages of the [[UEFA European Football Championship|European Championships]] since its inception in 1960. However, in 1976, they did reach the last eight of the competition, having finished top of qualifying group 2 ahead of [[Hungary national football team|Hungary]], [[Austria national football team|Austria]] and [[Luxembourg national football team|Luxembourg]].
Prior to 1980, only four countries qualified for the final stages of the competition, and Wales were drawn to play against the winners of group 3 [[Yugoslavia national football team|Yugoslavia]], in a two legged match. Wales lost the first leg 2–0 in [[Zagreb]] and were knocked out of the competition having only managed a 1–1 draw in a bad-tempered return leg at Ninian Park which was marred by crowd trouble. This led to Wales initially being banned from the 1980 tournament, although this penalty was reduced on appeal to a ban on qualifying games being played within 100 miles of Cardiff for four years. 

The following year, Wales defeated England on English soil for the first time in 42 years and secured their only victory to date at [[Wembley Stadium (1923)|Wembley]] thanks to a [[Leighton James]] penalty. Another notable achievement came in 1980, as Wales tore England apart in one of the best performances ever witnessed by a Welsh side. Goals from [[Mickey Thomas (football)|Mickey Thomas]], [[Ian Walsh (footballer)|Ian Walsh]], Leighton James and an own goal by [[Phil Thompson]] saw Wales thrash England 4–1 at The Racecourse Ground, Wrexham, just four days after England had beaten the then-world champions, [[Argentina national football team|Argentina]].

In the [[1982 World Cup]] qualifiers, Wales came extremely close to qualification, a 3–0 defeat against the USSR in their final game meant they missed out on goal difference, but the real damage had been done by their failure to beat Iceland in their last home game, the match eventually finishing 2–2 after several hold-ups due to floodlight failures.

[[Manchester United F.C.|Manchester United]] youngster [[Mark Hughes]] marked his debut for Wales by scoring the only goal of the game as England were defeated once again in 1984. The following season, Hughes was again on target, scoring a wonder goal as Wales thrashed [[Spain national football team|Spain]] 3–0 at The Racecourse during qualification for [[1986 FIFA World Cup|Mexico 86]]. However, despite beating Scotland 1–0 at Hampden Park, it was again Iceland that wrecked Welsh hopes by beating Wales 1–0 in Reykjavik and for the second World Cup in a row Wales missed out on goal difference. Wales had to win their last match at home to Scotland to be guaranteed at least a play-off, but were held to a 1–1 draw in a match marred by the death of Scotland manager [[Jock Stein]] who collapsed from a heart attack at the end of the game.

===1990–2000===
Under [[Terry Yorath]] Wales attained their highest ever FIFA ranking of 27th in August 1993.

Wales came close, once again, to qualifying for a major championship when they came within a whisker of reaching the [[1994 FIFA World Cup]]. Needing to win the final game of the group at home to [[Romania national football team|Romania]], [[Paul Bodin]] missed a penalty when the scores were level 1–1; Romania went on to win 2–1.

Following the failure to qualify Yorath's contract as manager of the national side was not renewed by the FAW and [[John Toshack]], then manager of [[Real Sociedad]], was appointed as a part-time manager. However, Toshack resigned after just one game – a 3–1 defeat to [[Norway national football team|Norway]] – citing problems with the FAW as his reason for leaving, although he was sure to have been shocked at being booed off the pitch at Ninian Park by the Welsh fans still reeling from the dismissal of Yorath.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Time for Toshack to deliver|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/football/internationals/4005591.stm|first=Dewi|last=Hughes|work=BBC Sport|publisher=BBC|date=12 November 2004|accessdate=12 November 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mike Smith (football manager)|Mike Smith]] took the reins for the start of the [[UEFA Euro 96|Euro 96]] qualifiers, which saw Wales slip to embarrassing defeats against [[Moldova national football team|Moldova]] and [[Georgia national football team|Georgia]] before [[Bobby Gould]] was appointed in June 1995.
[[File:C-Fletcher.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Carl Fletcher (Welsh footballer)|Carl Fletcher]] playing for Wales in [[2010 FIFA World Cup qualification – UEFA Group 4]]]]

Gould's time in charge of Wales is seen as a dark period by Welsh football fans. His questionable tactics and public fallings-out with players such as [[Nathan Blake]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Stack on the back|url=http://pubs.socialistreviewindex.org.uk/sr208/stack.htm|first=Pat|last=Stack|work=Socialist Review|date=May 1997|accessdate=May 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robbie Savage]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Wales reprieve for Savage|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/sport/football/165192.stm|work=BBC Sport|publisher=BBC|date=5 September 1998|accessdate=5 September 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Mark Hughes, coupled with embarrassing defeats to club side [[Leyton Orient F.C.|Leyton Orient]] and a 7–1 thrashing by the [[Netherlands national football team|Netherlands]] in 1996 did not make him a popular figure within Wales. Gould finally resigned following a 4–0 defeat to [[Italy national football team|Italy]] in 1999, and the FAW turned to two legends of the national team, [[Neville Southall]] and Mark Hughes to take temporary charge of the game against [[Denmark national football team|Denmark]] four days later, with Hughes later being appointed on a permanent basis.

===2000–2010===
Under Mark Hughes, Wales came close to qualifying for for a place at [[UEFA Euro 2004]] in Portugal, being narrowly defeated by [[Russia national football team|Russia]] in [[UEFA Euro 2004 qualifying play-offs|the play-offs]]. The defeat, however, was not without its controversy as Russian midfield player, [[Yegor Titov]], tested positive for the use of a banned substance after the first qualifying leg,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Wales consider Euro 2004 appeal|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/football/internationals/wales/3425003.stm|work=BBC Sport|publisher=BBC|date=23 January 2004|accessdate=23 January 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; a scoreless draw in Moscow. However, the sport's governing body decided to take no action against the [[Football Union of Russia]] (Российский Футбольный Союз) other than instructing them not to play Titov again, and the Russian team went on to beat Wales in Cardiff 1–0 to qualify for UEFA Euro 2004.

Following a disappointing start to [[2006 FIFA World Cup qualification – UEFA Group 6]], Hughes left his role with the national team to take over as manager of English [[Premier League]] outfit [[Blackburn Rovers F.C.|Blackburn Rovers]]. On 12 November 2004, [[John Toshack]] was appointed manager for the second time. 

In [[UEFA Euro 2008 qualifying]], Wales were drawn in [[UEFA Euro 2008 qualifying Group D|Group D]] alongside [[Germany national football team|Germany]], [[Czech Republic national football team|the Czech Republic]], [[Slovakia national football team|Slovakia]], [[Republic of Ireland national football team|Republic of Ireland]], [[Cyprus national football team|Cyprus]] and [[San Marino national football team|San Marino]]. The team's performance was disappointing, finishing fifth in the group with expected defeat at home to Germany yet an unexpected draw away, a loss away and a goalless draw at home to the Czech Republic, a loss away and 2–2 draw at home to the Republic of Ireland, a 3–0 home win and uninspiring 2–1 away win against minnows San Marino, a 3–1 home win and 3–1 away defeat against Cyprus, and a spectacularly mixed performance against Slovakia, losing 5–1 at home and winning 5–2 away. However, better performances towards the end of the competition by a team containing, of necessity because of injuries and suspensions of senior players, no fewer than five players who were eligible for selection for the Under-21 squad was viewed as a hopeful sign of future progress for the team.

In [[2010 FIFA World Cup qualification – UEFA Group 4]], Wales made a promising start, winning 1–0 and 2–0 against [[Azerbaijan national football team|Azerbaijan]] and [[Liechtenstein national football team|Liechtenstein]], respectively. However, they lost their next game against [[Russia national football team|Russia]] in Moscow, 2–1, after [[Joe Ledley]] had briefly drawn them level. The qualifying campaign showed signs of promise when the team managed to prevent [[Germany national football team|Germany]] from scoring for 74 minutes of their match in [[Mönchengladbach]], but the match eventually finished 1–0 to Germany. Two 2–0 home defeats by [[Finland national football team|Finland]] and Germany in Spring 2009 effectively put paid to Wales' hopes of qualification.

Wales were drawn in [[UEFA Euro 2012 qualifying Group G]] with [[Montenegro national football team|Montenegro]], [[Bulgaria national football team|Bulgaria]], [[Switzerland national football team|Switzerland]] and close rivals [[England national football team|England]]. Wales lost 1–0 away to Montenegro in their opening game and, on 9 September 2010, [[John Toshack]] stood down as manager after being disappointed at previous results in 2010 against [[Croatia national football team|Croatia]] and the opening UEFA Euro 2012 qualifier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=John Toshack stands down as Wales boss|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/football/league_of_wales/8970745.stm|work=BBC Sport|publisher=BBC|date=9 September 2010|accessdate=9 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Wales national under-21 football team|Wales Under-21]] coach [[Brian Flynn]] took over from Toshack as caretaker manager with a view to a possible permanent appointment but a 1–0 home defeat to Bulgaria and 4–1 away loss to Switzerland meant that the FAW passed over Flynn. 
 
===2010s===
[[File:Wales national football team.jpg|thumb|right|325px|The Wales national football team photographed on 11 October 2011 ahead of [[Bulgaria national football team|Bulgaria]] versus Wales in [[UEFA Euro 2012 qualifying]] at [[Vasil Levski National Stadium]] in [[Sofia]]]]

[[Gary Speed]] was appointed as permanent manager on 14 December 2010. Speed's first game as Wales manager was 8 February 2011 in the inaugural [[2011 Nations Cup|Nations Cup]], which the [[Republic of Ireland national football team|Republic of Ireland]] won 3–0.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rte.ie/sport/soccer/2011/0208/ireland_wales_carlingnationscup.html|title=Republic of Ireland 3–0 Wales|date=8 February 2011|work=[[RTÉ Sport]]|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann]]|accessdate=8 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Speed's first competitive match was the Euro 2012 qualifier at home to England 26 March 2011 and Speed appointed twenty year old [[Aaron Ramsey]] captain, making Ramsey the youngest ever Wales captain. Wales lost to England 2–0 and in August 2011 Wales attained their lowest ever FIFA world ranking of 117th. This was followed by a 2–1 home win against Montenegro, a 1–0 away loss to England, a 2–0 home win against Switzerland and a 1–0 away win against Bulgaria. Consequently in October 2011, Wales had rapidly risen to 45th in the FIFA rankings. Speed's last match as Manager of Wales was the 4-1 home win in a friendly match versus Norway on 12 November 2011. 

Speed's tenure as manager ended in tragic circumstances two weeks later when he was found dead at his home on 27 November, having apparently committed suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.faw.org.uk/news/FAW81615.ink|title=The FAW regrets to announce the death of the national team manager Gary Speed|date=27 November 2011|work=FAW|publisher=Football Association of Wales|accessdate=27 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For [[2014 FIFA World Cup qualification (UEFA)|2014 FIFA World Cup qualification]], Wales were placed in the sixth pot and drawn in [[2014 FIFA World Cup qualification – UEFA Group A|Group A]] with [[Croatia national football team|Croatia]], [[Serbia national football team|Serbia]], [[Belgium national football team|Belgium]], [[Scotland national football team|Scotland]] and [[Macedonia national football team|Macedonia]].

==2012 Summer Olympics==
Due to [[London bid for the 2012 Summer Olympic and Paralympic Games|London's successful bid]] for the [[2012 Summer Olympics]], a Great Britain team would qualify as of right of being the host nation. However, the FAW stressed it was strongly against the proposal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Wales oppose GB Olympic football|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/football/internationals/4427504.stm|work=BBC Sport|publisher=BBC|date=6 December 2005|accessdate=6 December 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; A compromise was eventually reached between the four UK associations, whereby a squad of only English players could represent Great Britain.

==Stadium==
[[File:Millennium Stadium Cardiff.jpg|thumb|The [[Millennium Stadium]] in [[Cardiff]]]]
Wales play most of their home matches at the [[Millennium Stadium]], [[Cardiff]]. The stadium was built in 1999 on the site of the old [[National Stadium]], known as [[Cardiff Arms Park]], as the [[Welsh Rugby Union]] (WRU) had been chosen to host the [[1999 Rugby World Cup]]. Prior to 1989, Wales played their home games at the grounds of [[Cardiff City F.C.]], [[Swansea City A.F.C.]] and [[Wrexham F.C.]], but then came to an agreement with the WRU to use Cardiff Arms Park and, subsequently, the Millennium Stadium. 

Wales' first football match at the Millennium Stadium was against [[Finland national football team|Finland]] on 29 March 2000. The Finns won the match 2–1, with [[Jari Litmanen]] becoming the first player to score a goal at the stadium. [[Ryan Giggs]] scored Wales' goal in the match, becoming the first Welshman to score at the stadium.

In recent seasons, some friendly home matches have been played at [[Cardiff City Stadium]], the [[Liberty Stadium, Swansea]] and the [[Racecourse Ground|Racecourse Ground, Wrexham]]. However, with little recent success on the field, the 74,500 capacity Millennium stadium has only been around 20–40% full, leading to calls for some international matches to be held at these smaller stadiums with capacities of 15,500–27,000.

==Players==
===Latest squad===
[[Gary Speed]] named the following Wales squad for the friendly match against [[Norway national football team|Norway]] on 12 November 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.faw.org.uk/news/FAW81320.ink|title=Wales v Norway - Teams for Today|date=12 November 2011|work=FAW|publisher=Football Association of Wales|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lewis Price]] and [[Lewin Nyatanga]] were subsequently added to the squad. 

Caps and goals updated as 13 November 2011.
&lt;!--Clubs, Caps, Goals, Ages shown are at the time the squad is announced. In order to retain the facts of the article, DO NOT CHANGE UNTIL THE NEXT SQUAD IS ANNOUNCED. --&gt;

{{nat fs g start}}
{{nat fs g player |no=1|pos=GK |name=[[Wayne Hennessey]] |age={{birth date and age|1987|1|24|df=y}} |caps=38 |goals=0 |club=[[Wolverhampton Wanderers F.C.|Wolverhampton Wanderers]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=GK |name=[[Boaz Myhill]]*|age={{birth date and age|1982|11|9|df=y}} |caps=10 |goals=0 |club=[[Birmingham City F.C.|Birmingham City]] (loan)  |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=12|pos=GK |name=[[Lewis Price]]|age={{birth date and age|1984|7|19|df=y}} |caps=8 |goals=0 |club=[[Crystal Palace F.C.|Crystal Palace]]  |clubnat=ENG}}
|-
!colspan=&quot;8&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#B0D3FB&quot;|
|- bgcolor=&quot;#DFEDFD&quot;
{{nat fs g player |no=5|pos=DF |name=[[Darcy Blake]] |age={{birth date and age|1988|12|13|df=y}} |caps=8 |goals=1 |club=[[Cardiff City F.C.|Cardiff City]] |clubnat=WAL}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=DF |name=[[Danny Collins]]*| |age={{birth date and age|1980|8|6|df=y}} |caps=12 |goals=0 |club=[[Ipswich Town F.C.|Ipswich Town]] (loan) |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=DF |name=[[James Collins (footballer born 1983)|James Collins]]*| |age={{birth date and age|1983|8|23|df=y}} |caps=39 |goals=2 |club=[[Aston Villa F.C.|Aston Villa]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=2|pos=DF |name=[[Chris Gunter]] |age={{birth date and age|1989|7|21|df=y}} |caps=35 |goals=0 |club=[[Nottingham Forest F.C.|Nottingham Forest]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=3|pos=DF |name=[[Adam Matthews]] |age={{birth date and age|1992|1|13|df=y}} |caps=5 |goals=0 |club=[[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]] |clubnat=SCO}}
{{nat fs g player |no=13|pos=DF |name=[[Lewin Nyatanga]] |age={{birth date and age|1988|8|18|df=y}} |caps=34 |goals=0 |club=[[Bristol City F.C.|Bristol City]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=DF |name=[[Neil Taylor (footballer)|Neil Taylor]] |age={{birth date and age|1989|2|7|df=y}} |caps=8 |goals=0 |club=[[Swansea City A.F.C.|Swansea City]] |clubnat=WAL}}
{{nat fs g player |no=6|pos=DF |name=[[Ashley Williams (footballer)|Ashley Williams]] | |age={{birth date and age|1984|8|23|df=y}} |caps=31 |goals=1 |club=[[Swansea City A.F.C.|Swansea City]] |clubnat=WAL}}
|-
!colspan=&quot;10&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#B0D3FB&quot;|
|- bgcolor=&quot;#DFEDFD&quot;
{{nat fs g player |no=7|pos=MF |name=[[Joe Allen (footballer born 1990)|Joe Allen]] |age={{birth date and age|1990|3|14|df=y}} |caps=6 |goals=0 |club=[[Swansea City A.F.C.|Swansea City]] |clubnat=WAL}}
{{nat fs g player |no=11|pos=MF |name=[[Gareth Bale]] |age={{birth date and age|1989|7|16|df=y}} |caps=33 |goals=6 |club=[[Tottenham Hotspur F.C.|Tottenham Hotspur]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=MF |name=[[Jack Collison]]* |age={{birth date and age|1988|10|2|df=y}} |caps=10 |goals=0 |club=[[West Ham United F.C.|West Ham United]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=4|pos=MF |name=[[Andrew Crofts (footballer)|Andrew Crofts]] |age={{birth date and age|1984|5|29|df=y}} |caps=22 |goals=0 |club=[[Norwich City F.C.|Norwich City]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=14|pos=MF |name=[[David Edwards (footballer)|David Edwards]] |age={{birth date and age|1986|2|3|df=y}} |caps=23 |goals=3 |club=[[Wolverhampton Wanderers F.C.|Wolverhampton Wanderers]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=15|pos=MF |name=[[Andy King (footballer born 1988)|Andy King]] |age={{birth date and age|1988|10|29|df=y}} |caps=11 |goals=1 |club=[[Leicester City F.C.|Leicester City]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=MF |name=[[Joe Ledley]] |age={{birth date and age|1987|1|23|df=y}} |caps=40 |goals=3 |club=[[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]] |clubnat=SCO}}
{{nat fs g player |no=10|pos=MF |name=[[Aaron Ramsey]] ([[Captain (association football)|c]]) |age={{birth date and age|1990|12|26|df=y}} |caps=20 |goals=5 |club=[[Arsenal F.C.|Arsenal]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=|pos=MF |name=[[David Vaughan (footballer)|David Vaughan]]*|age={{birth date and age|1983|2|18|df=y}} |caps=28 |goals=1 |club=[[Sunderland F.C.|Sunderland]]
|clubnat=ENG}}
|-
!colspan=&quot;9&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#B0D3FB&quot;|
|- bgcolor=&quot;#DFEDFD&quot;
{{nat fs g player |no=8|pos=FW |name=[[Craig Bellamy]] |age={{birth date and age|1979|7|13|df=y}} |caps=67 |goals=19 |club=[[Liverpool F.C.|Liverpool]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no= |pos=FW |name=[[Simon Church]]* |age={{birth date and age|1988|12|10|df=y}} |caps=14 |goals=1 |club=[[Reading F.C.|Reading]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=18|pos=FW |name=[[Robert Earnshaw]] |age={{birth date and age|1981|4|6|df=y}} |caps=57 |goals=16 |club=[[Cardiff City F.C.|Cardiff City]] |clubnat=WAL}}
{{nat fs g player |no=9|pos=FW |name=[[Steve Morison]] |age={{birth date and age|1983|8|29|df=y}} |caps=13 |goals=1 |club=[[Norwich City F.C.|Norwich City]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=16|pos=FW |name=[[Hal Robson-Kanu]] |age={{birth date and age|1989|5|21|df=y}} |caps=5 |goals=0 |club=[[Reading F.C.|Reading]] |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs g player |no=17|pos=FW |name=[[Sam Vokes]] |age={{birth date and age|1989|10|21|df=y}} |caps=19 |goals=4 |club=[[Wolverhampton Wanderers F.C.|Wolverhampton Wanderers]]  |clubnat=ENG}}
{{nat fs end}}

* * withdrew from squad

===Most-capped players===
As of ''13 Nov 2011'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rsssf.com/miscellaneous/wal-recintlp.html |title=Wales – Record International Players |first=Luis Fernando Passo |last=Alpuin |publisher=[[Rec.Sport.Soccer Statistics Foundation]] |date=20 February 2009 |accessdate=10 March 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (players still active in '''bold'''):

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|-
!#
!Name
!Career
!Caps
!Goals
|-
|1
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Neville Southall]]
|1982–1998
|92
|0
|-
|2
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Gary Speed]]
|1990–2004
|85
|7
|-
|3
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Dean Saunders]]
|1986–2001
|75
|22
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 4
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Peter Nicholas (footballer)|Peter Nicholas]]
|1979–1991
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 73
|2
|-

|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Ian Rush]]
|1980–1996

|28
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |6
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Mark Hughes]]
|1984–1999
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |72
|16
|-

|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Joey Jones]]
|1975–1986

|1
|-
|8
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Ivor Allchurch]]
|1950–1966
|68
|23
|-
|9
|align=&quot;left&quot; |'''[[Craig Bellamy]]'''
|1998–2011
|67
|19
|-
|10
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Brian Flynn]]
|1974–1984
|66
|7
|}

===Other players with 50 or more caps===
Note: players still active at international level in '''bold''':

{|
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;
| 
*[[Dai Davies (footballer)|Dai Davies]]
*[[Simon Davies (footballer born 1979)|Simon Davies]]
*'''[[Robert Earnshaw]]'''
*[[Ryan Giggs]]
|
*[[John Hartson]]
*[[Barry Horne (footballer)|Barry Horne]]
*[[Leighton James]]
*[[Cliff Jones (Welsh footballer)|Cliff Jones]]
|
*[[Paul Jones (footballer)|Paul Jones]]
*[[John Mahoney (footballer)|John Mahoney]]
*[[Andy Melville]]
*[[Mark Pembridge]]
|
*[[David Phillips (Welsh footballer)|David Phillips]]
*[[Leighton Phillips]]
*[[Kevin Ratcliffe]]
*[[Carl Robinson]]
|
*[[Mickey Thomas (football)|Mickey Thomas]]
*[[Rod Thomas]]
*[[Terry Yorath]]
|}

===Top goalscorers===
As of ''13 Nov 2011'' (players still active in '''bold'''):

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|-
!#
!Name
!Goals
!Caps
|-
|1
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Ian Rush]]
|28
|73
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |2
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Trevor Ford]]
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |23
|38
|-

|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Ivor Allchurch]]

|68
|-
|4
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Dean Saunders]]
|22
|75
|-
|5
|align=&quot;left&quot;|'''[[Craig Bellamy]]'''
|19
|67
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |6
|align=&quot;left&quot;|'''[[Robert Earnshaw]]'''
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |16
|57
|-

|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Cliff Jones (Welsh footballer)|Cliff Jones]]

|59
|-

|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Mark Hughes]]

|72
|-
|9
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[John Charles]]
|15
|38
|-
|10
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[John Hartson]]
|14
|51
|}

===Notable former players===
:''See [[:Category:Wales international footballers|Wales international footballers]] for all Welsh internationals with a Wikipedia article and [[List of Wales international footballers]] for a list of Welsh internationals in sortable-table format. Also see [[List of Wales international footballers with 25 or more caps]].

;[[Welsh Sports Hall of Fame]] inductees:
{|
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;
| 
*[[Ivor Allchurch]]
*[[Horace Blew]]
*[[Ron Burgess (footballer)|Ronnie Burgess]]
*[[John Charles]]
|
|
*[[Trevor Ford]]
*[[Mark Hughes]]
*[[Bryn Jones (footballer born 1912)|Bryn Jones]]
*[[Cliff Jones (Welsh footballer)|Cliff Jones]]
|
|
*[[Fred Keenor]]
*[[Jack Kelsey]]
*[[George Latham (footballer)|George Latham]]
|
|
*[[Billy Meredith]]
*[[Jimmy Murphy (footballer)|Jimmy Murphy]]
*[[Ivor Powell]]
|
|
*[[Ian Rush]]
*[[Alf Sherwood]]
*[[John Toshack]]
|}

;Welsh inductees to the [[English Football Hall of Fame]]:
*2002 [[John Charles]]
*2005 [[Ryan Giggs]]
*2006 [[Ian Rush]]
*2007 [[Mark Hughes]], [[Billy Meredith]]

;Welsh inductees to the [[Football League 100 Legends]]:
{|
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;
| 
* [[Ivor Allchurch]]
* [[John Charles]]
|
|
* [[Trevor Ford]]
* [[Ryan Giggs]]
|
|
* [[Cliff Jones (Welsh footballer)|Cliff Jones]]
* [[Billy Meredith]]
|
|
* [[Ian Rush]]
* [[Neville Southall]]
|}

;Welsh Inductee to the [[PFA Team of the Year|PFA Team of the Year (Top Division)]]:
* [[Leighton James]] (1975)
* [[John Toshack]] (1976)
* [[Ian Rush]] (1983, 1984, 1991)
* [[Kevin Ratcliffe]] (1985)
* [[Mark Hughes]] (1986, 1989, 1991, 1992)
* [[Neville Southall]] (1987, 1988, 1989, 1990)
* [[Gary Speed]] (1993)
* [[Ryan Giggs]] (1996, 1998, 2001, 2007 and 2009)
* [[Gareth Bale]] (2011)

==Managers==
:''See also [[:Category:Wales national football team managers|Wales national football team managers]]
Prior to 1954 the Welsh team was chosen by a panel of selectors with the team captain fulfilling the role of coach.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;
|-
!Name
!Career
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Walley Barnes]]
|1954–1955
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[James Murphy (footballer)|Jimmy Murphy]]
|1956–1964
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Dave Bowen]]
|1964–1974
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Ron Burgess (footballer)|Ronnie Burgess]]
|1965 (caretaker manager for one match due to unavailability of Dave Bowen)
|-
|{{flagicon|ENG}} [[Mike Smith (football manager)|Mike Smith]]
|1974–1979
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Mike England]]
|1979–1987
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[David Williams (Welsh footballer)|David Williams]]
|1988 (caretaker manager for one match)
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Terry Yorath]]
|1988–1993
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[John Toshack]]
|1994
|-
|{{flagicon|ENG}} [[Mike Smith (football manager)|Mike Smith]]
|1994–1995
|-
|{{flagicon|ENG}} [[Bobby Gould]]
|1995–1999
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Mark Hughes]]
|1999–2004
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[John Toshack]]
|2004–2010
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Brian Flynn]] 
|2010 (caretaker manager for 2 matches)
|-
|{{flagicon|WAL}} [[Gary Speed]] 
|2010–2011
|}

===Manager===
*{{note|reference_name_A|note}} The manager's post is currently vacant following the death of Gary Speed.

===Other staff===
* Assistant Manager: [[Raymond Verheijen]]
* Goalkeeping Coach: [[Martyn Margetson]]
* Team Doctors: Dr. Mark Ridgewell and Dr. Mark Davies
* Physiotherapists: [[Mel Pejic]] and Dyfri Owen
* Masseur: David Rowe

== Records ==
{{Main|Welsh national football team records}}

==Competition history==
===FIFA World Cup record===
*[[1930 FIFA World Cup|1930]]–[[1938 FIFA World Cup|1938]] – ''Did not enter''
*[[1950 FIFA World Cup|1950]]–[[1954 FIFA World Cup|1954]] – ''Did not qualify''
*[[1958 FIFA World Cup|1958]] – Quarter-finals
*[[1962 FIFA World Cup|1962]]–[[2010 FIFA World Cup|2010]] – ''Did not qualify''

===UEFA European Football Championship record===

*[[1960 European Nations' Cup|1960]] – ''Did not enter''
*1964–1970 – ''Did not qualify''
*[[UEFA Euro 1976 qualifying|1976]] – Quarter-Final (played on home and away leg basis)
*1980–2012 – ''Did not qualify''

==See also==
{{Portal|Wales}}
*[[1958 FIFA World Cup]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.faw.org.uk Football Association of Wales]
*[http://www.fawtrust.org.uk Football Association of Wales Trust]
*[http://www.rsssf.com/tablesw/wal-intres.html International results of Wales]
*[http://www.welshfootballonline.com Welsh Football Online]
*[http://www.wfda.co.uk/index.php Welsh Football Data Archive]
*[http://www.dragonsoccer.co.uk Dragon Soccer]
*[http://www.sports-council-wales.co.uk/hall_of_fame.cfm?main_nav=news&amp;sub_nav=hall_of_fame Sports Council of Wales Welsh Sports Hall of Fame]
*[http://www.rsssf.com/miscellaneous/wal-recintlp.html RSSSF archive of most capped players and highest goalscorers]

{{Wales national football team}}
{{Football in Wales}}
{{Football in the United Kingdom}}
{{UEFA teams}}
{{International Football}}
{{1958 FIFA World Cup finalists}}
{{National sports teams of Wales}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wales National Football Team}}
[[Category:1876 establishments in Wales]]
[[Category:European national association football teams]]
[[Category:National sports teams of Wales|Football]]
[[Category:Wales national football team| ]]

[[ar:منتخب ويلز لكرة القدم]]
[[az:Uels milli futbol komandası]]
[[bg:Национален отбор по футбол на Уелс]]
[[bs:Nogometna reprezentacija Velsa]]
[[ca:Selecció de futbol de Gal·les]]
[[cs:Velšská fotbalová reprezentace]]
[[cy:Tîm pêl-droed cenedlaethol Cymru]]
[[da:Wales' fodboldlandshold]]
[[de:Walisische Fußballnationalmannschaft]]
[[et:Walesi jalgpallikoondis]]
[[es:Selección de fútbol de Gales]]
[[eu:Galesko futbol selekzio nazionala]]
[[fr:Équipe du pays de Galles de football]]
[[ko:웨일스 축구 국가대표팀]]
[[id:Tim nasional sepak bola Wales]]
[[it:Nazionale di calcio del Galles]]
[[he:נבחרת ויילס בכדורגל]]
[[ka:უელსის ეროვნული საფეხბურთო ნაკრები]]
[[lv:Velsas futbola izlase]]
[[lt:Velso vyrų futbolo rinktinė]]
[[hu:Walesi labdarúgó-válogatott]]
[[mt:Tim nazzjonali tal-futbol ta' Wales]]
[[mr:वेल्स फुटबॉल संघ]]
[[nl:Welsh voetbalelftal]]
[[ja:サッカーウェールズ代表]]
[[no:Wales' herrelandslag i fotball]]
[[pl:Reprezentacja Walii w piłce nożnej]]
[[pt:Seleção Galesa de Futebol]]
[[ro:Echipa națională de fotbal a Țării Galilor]]
[[ru:Сборная Уэльса по футболу]]
[[sq:Kombëtarja uellsiane e futbollit]]
[[simple:Wales national football team]]
[[sr:Фудбалска репрезентација Велса]]
[[fi:Walesin jalkapallomaajoukkue]]
[[sv:Wales herrlandslag i fotboll]]
[[th:ฟุตบอลทีมชาติเวลส์]]
[[tr:Galler Millî Futbol Takımı]]
[[uk:Збірна Уельсу з футболу]]
[[vi:Đội tuyển bóng đá quốc gia Wales]]
[[wuu:威尔士国家足球队]]
[[zh:威爾斯足球代表隊]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
