<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="582163" ns="0" title="Duquesne University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox University
|name            = Duquesne University&lt;br&gt;of the Holy Spirit
|native_name     = 
|image_name      = Seal of Duquesne University.svg
|image_size      = 175px
|caption         = 
|latin_name      = Universitas Spiritus Sancti Duquesnensis
|motto           = {{lang-la|Spiritus est qui vivificat.}}&lt;br&gt;(It is the [[Holy Spirit|Spirit]] that gives life.)
|tagline         = 
|established     = October 1, 1878
|type            = [[Private university|Private]]
|affiliation     = Roman Catholic ([[Spiritans|Spiritan Fathers]])
|endowment       = $121.0 million (2009){{Ref_label|A|a|none}}
|debt            = 
|president       = [[Charles J. Dougherty]]
|chancellor      = [[John E. Murray, Jr.]]
|vice-president  = 
|faculty         = 
|students        = 10,363
|undergrad       = 5,858
|postgrad        = 4,505
|doctoral        = 
|divinity        = 
|residents       = 
|other           = 
|profess         = 
|city            = [[Pittsburgh]]
|state           = [[Pennsylvania]]
|country         = United States|
|address         = 
|campus          = Urban, 49 acres 
|free_label      = Tuition (2009)
|free            = $24,385 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.sites.duq.edu/student-accounts/tuition&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors          = Red and Blue
|nickname        = 
|mascot          = The [[Duquesne Dukes#Mascot|Duke]]
|fightsong       = ''[[Duquesne Dukes#University fight song|The Victory Song]]''
|athletics       = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|affiliations    = [[Atlantic Ten Conference|Atlantic 10 Conference]]&lt;br&gt;[[Northeast Conference]]
|website         = [http://www.duq.edu www.duq.edu]
|logo            = [[Image:Duqlogo.png|center|125px]]
|publictransit   = 
|footnotes       = &lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;a&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;{{Note_label|A|a|none}} According to {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work=2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = March 8, 2010}}
&lt;/div&gt;
}}

'''Duquesne University of the Holy Spirit''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|dj|uː|ˈ|k|eɪ|n}} {{respell|dew|KAYN|'}}) is a private Catholic university in [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]], United States. Founded by members of the [[Holy Ghost Fathers|Congregation of the Holy Spirit]], Duquesne first opened its doors as the Pittsburgh Catholic College of the Holy Ghost in October 1878 with an enrollment of 40 students and a faculty of six. In 1911, the college became a university, the first Catholic institution of higher learning in Pennsylvania to achieve such a distinction. It is the only Spiritan institution of higher education in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;fastfacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Fast Facts | work=Institutional Research and Planning | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.irp.duq.edu/fastFacts.html | accessdate =2007-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Duquesne has since expanded to over 10,000 graduate and undergraduate students within a self-contained {{convert|49|acre|ha|sigfig=3|adj=on}} hilltop campus in Pittsburgh's [[Bluff (Pittsburgh)|Bluff]] neighborhood. The school maintains an associate campus in Rome and encompasses ten schools of study. The university hosts international students from more than 80 countries&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Fact Book 2008-2009 | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.irp.duq.edu/pdf/2008_Fact_Book.pdf |format=PDF| accessdate =2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; although most students—about 80%—are from Pennsylvania or the surrounding region.&lt;ref name=&quot;duqrec&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Student Body | work=Duquesne University | publisher=[[The Princeton Review]] | url =http://www.princetonreview.com/DuquesneUniversity.aspx | accessdate =2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[U.S. News and World Report]]'s annual college rankings place Duquesne in the top tier among national universities, with the school ranking 120th among national universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Duquesne University | work=Best Colleges | publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report  | year = 2008 | url = http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/pittsburgh-pa/duquesne-university-3258 | accessdate = 2009-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Duquesne is one of 98 universities nationwide, and one of nine Catholic universities, to be designated as a [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education|high research activity]] institution by the [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|Carnegie Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://times.duq.edu/2011/02/carnegie-foundation-validates-strength-of-research-at-duquesne/|newspaper=Duquesne University Times|date=February 9, 2011|publisher=Duquesne University|accessdate=February 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Duquesne's [[MBA]] program is ranked eighth in the world by the Aspen Institute.&lt;ref&gt;http://mba.sustainability.duq.edu/reputation/awards-and-recognition.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

Duquesne University can count more than 79,000 living alumni&lt;ref name=&quot;fastfacts&quot;/&gt; including two [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinals]] and the [[David Zubik|current bishop of Pittsburgh]].

The [[Duquesne Dukes]] compete in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]. Duquesne football has won or shared 11 conference titles, including nine in a row and 11 of the past 13. Duquesne [[Duquesne Dukes men's basketball|men's basketball]] appeared twice in national championship games in the 1950s and won the [[National Invitation Tournament|NIT]] championship in 1955.

== History ==
[[Image:DuquesneChapel.JPG|thumb|215px|left|The Duquesne University chapel adjoins the &quot;Old Main&quot; administration building.]]

The Pittsburgh Catholic College of the Holy Ghost was founded on October 1, 1878 by [[Joseph Strub|Fr. Joseph Strub]] and the Holy Ghost Fathers, who had been expelled from Germany during [[Otto von Bismarck|Otto von Bismarck's]] ''[[Kulturkampf]]'' six years earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;nce&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | title =Duquesne University | encyclopedia =[[New Catholic Encyclopedia]] | volume =IV | pages =1111–1112 | publisher=McGraw-Hill Book Company | year =1967}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the college was founded, it had six faculty members and 40 students.&lt;ref name=&quot;duqhis&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = A Brief History | work=About Duquesne University | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.duq.edu/about/history.cfm | accessdate =May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college obtained its state charter in 1882.&lt;ref name=&quot;nce&quot;/&gt; Students attended classes in a rented space above a bakery on Wylie Avenue in downtown Pittsburgh. Duquesne established itself at its current location on the Bluff and built the original five-story red brick &quot;Old Main&quot; in 1885. At the time, it was the highest point on the Pittsburgh skyline.&lt;ref name=&quot;duqhis&quot;/&gt;

On May 27, 1911, under the leadership of [[Martin Hehir|Fr. Martin Hehir]], the College became the first Catholic institution of higher learning in Pennsylvania to become a university. It was subsequently renamed &quot;Duquesne University of the Holy Ghost&quot;, after [[Marquis Duquesne|Ange Duquesne de Menneville, Marquis du Quesne]], the French governor of [[New France]] who first brought [[Mass (liturgy)|Catholic observances]] to the Pittsburgh area. The year 1913 saw the university record its first woman graduate, Sister M. Fides of the [[Sisters of Mercy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Snyder|first=James L|title=Catholic Educational Review|chapter=Duquesne University, 1878–1953|year=December 1952|volume=50|pages=649–665}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1914, the graduate school was established.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt;

The 1920s were a time of expansion for the developing university. The campus grew to include its first single-purpose academic building, Canevin Hall, as well as a gymnasium and a central heating plant. Institutionally, the school grew to include the [[Mylan School of Pharmacy|School of Pharmacy]] in 1925, a [[Mary Pappert School of Music|School of Music]] in 1926, and a [[Duquesne University School of Education|School of Education]] in 1929.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; In 1928 the university celebrated its fiftieth anniversary and was able to rejoice in the fact that it was now both financially solvent and enrollment had reached an all-time high. Hard times, however, came with the [[Wall Street Crash of 1929]]; plans for expansion had to be shelved.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt;

The beloved Fr. Hehir was succeeded in 1931 by [[Jeremiah J. Callahan|Fr. J. J. Callahan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; Through Fr. Callahan was not as able an administration as Fr. Hehir, his tenure did see the university add numerous new programs, a short-lived School for the Unemployed, and, in 1937, the [[Duquesne University School of Nursing|Nursing School]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; The university's sports programs also thrived during the Depression era, with some of the greatest triumphs of the basketball and football teams occurring in that time period—a 6–0 defeat of [[University of Pittsburgh|Pitt]] in 1936 was a high point of student exuberance.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; A university library was completed in 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt;

Some of the darkest years of the university's history passed during [[World War II]], when the university was led by the young [[Raymond V. Kirk|Fr. Raymond Kirk]]. The school's enrollment, which had been 3,100 in 1940, dropped to an all-time low in the summer of 1944, with a mere one thousand students enrolled.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; Fr. Kirk's health broke under the strain of leading the school through such struggles, and he was relieved of his duties by [[Francis P. Smith|Fr. Francis P. Smith]] in 1946.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; After the war, the school faced a wave of veterans seeking higher education. In contrast to the lean war-time years, the 1949 enrollment peaked at 5,500, and space became an issue. Fr. Smith took advantage of the [[Lanham Act]], which allowed him to acquire three barracks-type buildings from Army surplus. The science curriculum was expanded, and the [[Palumbo–Donahue School of Business|School of Business Administration]] saw its enrollment rise to over two thousand.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt; Also during this time, a campus beautification project was implemented and [[WDUQ]], Pittsburgh's first college radio station, was founded.&lt;ref name=&quot;cer&quot;/&gt;

An ambitious campus expansion plan was proposed by [[Vernon F. Gallagher|Fr. Vernon F. Gallagher]] in 1952. Assumption Hall, the first student dormitory, was opened in 1954, and Rockwell Hall was dedicated in November 1958, housing the schools of business and law. It was during the tenure of [[Henry J. McAnulty|Fr. Henry J. McAnulty]] that Fr. Gallagher's ambitious plans were put to action. Between 1959 and 1980, the university renovated or constructed various buildings to form the academic infrastructure of the campus. Among these are College Hall, the music school and the library, as well as a new Student Union and Mellon Hall, along with four more dormitories. Although Fr. McAnulty's years as president saw tremendous expansion, a financial crisis in 1970 nearly forced the closure of the university. Students rallied to the cause, however, and set a goal of raising one million dollars to &quot;Save Duquesne University&quot;. Students engaged in door-to-door fundraising and gathered nearly $600,000, enough to keep Duquesne afloat until the end of the crisis in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last =Rishel  | first =Joseph F. | coauthors=Paul Demilio | title =&quot;The Spirit That Gives Life&quot;: The History of Duquesne University, 1878–1996 | publisher =Duquesne University Press | year =1997 | location =Pittsburgh | isbn =0-8207-0268-4|page = 189}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also during Fr. McAnulty's time as president that Duquesne University played an important role in the shaping of the [[Catholic Charismatic Renewal]], which has its roots in a retreat of several faculty members and students held in February 1967.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Laurentin | first = René | title = Catholic Pentecostalism | publisher=Doubleday | year = 1977}} (Reprinted in {{Cite book | last = Mills | first =  Watson E. (ed.) | title = Speaking in Tongues: A Guide to Research on Glossalalia | publisher=William B. Eerdmans Publishing | year = 1986 | location = Grand Rapids | page = 235}})&lt;/ref&gt;

McAnulty was succeeded by [[Donald S. Nesti|Fr. Donald S. Nesti]]. Fr. Nesti's tenure in the 1980s saw construction begin on the [[A. J. Palumbo Center]], which was dedicated in 1988, as well as an expansion of the law school. It was under the presidency of [[John E. Murray, Jr.|Dr. John E. Murray, Jr.]], the university's first lay president, that the university developed into its modern institutional and physical form.&lt;ref&gt;Rishel (1997), p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1988 and 2001, the University opened its first new schools in 50 years, including the [[Rangos School of Health Sciences]], the [[Bayer School of Natural and Environmental Sciences]], and the [[Duquesne University School of Leadership and Professional Advancement|School of Leadership and Professional Advancement]].&lt;ref name=&quot;duqhis2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =1950-1959 | work=Duquesne through the Decades | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.library.duq.edu/archives/exhibits/decades/dec6.htm | accessdate =2007-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;duqrec2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Recent Years | work=About Duquesne | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.duq.edu/frontpages/aboutdu/historyRecent.html | accessdate =2007-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Duquesne University continues to expand with its completion of the Power Center, a mixed-use development project on Forbes Avenue, and a new residence hall, to be completed in 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;newresidencehall&quot;&gt;{{Cite press release | title = New Residence Hall to be Constructed at Duquesne | publisher=Duquesne University | date = March 10, 2010 | url = http://newsroom.duq.edu/2010/03/10/new-residence-hall/ | accessdate = March 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Insignia and tradition ==
[[Image:DuquesneCrestCanevin.JPG|225px|thumb|right|Duquesne University's coat of arms is carved in high relief above Canevin Hall.]]
[[Image:DUring1.JPG|225px|thumb|right|The Duquesne University class ring is noted for its distinctive design.]]

=== Seal and coat of arms ===
The Duquesne University [[coat of arms]] was modified from that of the family of its namesake, the Marquis du Quesne. A red book was added to adapt the arms of a French governor to that of a university. The coat of arms was designed by a Spiritan father and alumnus, Father John F. Malloy. They were then examined and partly revised by [[Pierre de Chaignon la Rose]], a prominent [[ecclesiastical heraldry|ecclesiastical heraldic artist]] at the time. The design was adopted early in 1923 and used for the first time carved in [[Alto-relievo|high relief]] above Canevin Hall, then under construction. The first time the arms were incorporated into the seal of the university was for the commencement program of 1926.&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =University Coat of Arms and University Seal | work=Student Handbook | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.studentlife.duq.edu/studenthandbook/01_coatofarms.html | accessdate =2007-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The formal [[heraldry|heraldic]] [[blazon]] of the arms is as follows: ''Argent, a lion sable armed and langued gules holding a book of the same edged or; on a chief party per pale azure and of the third, a dove displayed of the first, areoled of the fourth; motto, &quot;Spiritus est qui vivificat.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title =People, programs, and policies | publisher=Duquesne University | date =Spring 1966 | location =[[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alma mater ===
Alumnus [[Joseph Carl Breil]], class of 1888, notable as being the first person to compose a score specifically for a motion picture, also composed the music for Duquesne University's alma mater. Father John F. Malloy, who also designed the university coat of arms, wrote the lyrics. The first performance of the song was in October 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;almamater&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Alma Mater | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.alumni.duq.edu/trad-am.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:''Alma Mater, old Duquesne, guide and friend of our youthful days.''
:''We, thy sons and daughters all, our loyal voices raise.''
:''The hours we spent at thy Mother knee and drank of wisdom's store''
:''Shall e'er in mem'ry treasured be, tho' we roam the whole world o'er.''
:''Then forward ever, dear Alma Mater, o'er our hearts unrivaled reign.''
:''Onward ever, old Alma Mater! All hail to thee, Duquesne!''

=== Class ring ===
The Duquesne University [[class ring]] was first adopted in the 1920s, the same decade as the seal and alma mater. The first incarnation was approved by a 1925 student committee, and was an &quot;octagonal deep blue stone held in place by four corner prongs.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;classring&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =The Duquesne Ring | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.alumni.duq.edu/trad-ring.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two years later, another student committee replaced the blue stone with a [[Ruby#Synthetic and imitation rubies|synthetic ruby]]. The ring's design continued to evolve until 1936, as the prongs were replaced with a continuous metal [[wiktionary:bezel|bezel]]. The words &quot;Duquesne&quot;, &quot;University&quot;, and &quot;Pittsburgh&quot;, accompanied the graduation year around the four sides of the bezel, and the shank on both sides was decorated with a motif adapted from the university's coat of arms. Originally an option, the embossed gold [[Blackletter|Gothic]] initial &quot;D&quot; became standard in the late 1930s. The Duquesne alumni website notes, &quot;The golden initial, oversized stone and octagonal shape make the Duquesne ring stand out from those of other colleges and universities.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;classring&quot;/&gt;

==Campuses==
===Main campus===
[[Image:Duquesneoldcampus.png|240px|left|thumb|An old postcard image of Duquesne's campus shows the Old Main building, the university chapel, and Canevin Hall.]]

Duquesne University has more than tripled in size from its early {{convert|adj=on|sigfig=4|12.5|acre|m2}} site on Boyd's Hill to its present {{convert|adj=on|sigfig=4|49|acre|m2}} main campus in Pittsburgh's [[Bluff (Pittsburgh)|Uptown neighborhood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =An Introduction to Duquesne University | work=Student Handbook | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.studentlife.duq.edu/studenthandbook/08_introDU.html | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 31 buildings that make up the Bluff campus,&lt;ref name=&quot;fastfacts&quot;/&gt; several are recent constructions or renovations, including a health sciences facility (Rangos Hall), two recording studios, two parking garages, a multipurpose recreation center (Power Center), and a theater-classroom complex (Bayer Hall).

The &quot;Old Main&quot; Administration Building was the first structure to be constructed on campus. The [[Victorian Gothic]] structure is still used to house the administrative offices of the University. Canevin Hall, named after bishop of Pittsburgh [[Regis Canevin]], was constructed in 1922 and is the oldest classroom building on campus; it was renovated in 1968 and again in 2009. These two buildings, as well Bayer Hall, the Richard King Mellon Hall of Science (designed by [[Ludwig Mies van der Rohe]]), and the [[Victorian architecture|Victorian]] Laval House, are at the west end of Academic Walk, a thoroughfare that provides pedestrian-only access to most of the campus, including the Student Union. The Union, which houses meeting rooms, three dining facilities, a [[Starbucks]], a [[PNC Financial Services|PNC]] branch, a recreation center, and an art gallery, is the center of campus life and student activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Physical Facilities | publisher=Student Handbook | url =http://www.studentlife.duq.edu/studenthandbook/09_facilities.html | accessdate =2007-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Located on the northern side of campus is the [[Gumberg Library]], a five-story structure opened in 1978 and holding extensive print and electronic collections.

====Forbes and Fifth Avenue expansion====
The newest campus construction is the Power Center, named in honor of [[William Patrick Power|Father William Patrick Power]], the University's first president. The multipurpose recreation facility on Forbes Avenue between Chatham Square and Magee Street, across from the University's [[Forbes Avenue]] entrance, adds to the student fitness facilities on campus. Other spaces include a [[Barnes and Noble]] bookstore containing a Starbucks café, [[Jamba Juice]], Red Ring Restaurant, and a conference center and ballroom.&lt;ref name=&quot;powercenter&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Power Center | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.duq.edu/powercenter/ | accessdate =2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The {{convert|125000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} building was completed in early January 2008, and is the first stage of a development that aims to serve both the campus community and the surrounding neighborhood.&lt;ref name=&quot;duqrec2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Forbes Expansion Project | publisher=Duquesne University | url = http://www.duq.edu/powercenter/pdf/ForbesExpansionProject.pdf |format=PDF| accessdate = 2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In October 2010 the university announced the purchase of the eight story, {{convert|100000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} building at 600 Fifth Avenue from Robert Morris University which had been RMU's Pittsburgh Center.  This adds an additional 87 classrooms, 1,100 seats and new music facilities.  Duquesne plans to utilize this building to allow further expansion of its graduate programs as applications have increased by doubled since 2005.  Duquesne also owns four other buildings along Fifth Avenue bordering on the new Consol Energy Center where the University now plays some of its home basketball games.
University owned WDUQ, NPR and jazz station, has relocated to offices in the Cooper Building and studios in Clement Hall.

=== Capital Region campus ===
Until 2009, Duquesne University had an extension of the [[Duquesne University School of Leadership and Professional Advancement|School of Leadership and Professional Advancement]] in [[Wormleysburg, Pennsylvania|Wormleysburg]].&lt;ref&gt;View the Capital Region campus on [http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=1007+Mumma+Road,+Wormleysburg,+PA+17043&amp;sll=40.258406,-76.908776&amp;sspn=0.009055,0.019784&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;z=16&amp;iwloc=addr&amp;om=1 Google Maps].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Capital Region Campus | work=School of Leadership and Professional Development | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.leadership.duq.edu/home/text/main.cfm?SID=86 | accessdate =2007-09-29 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070801120722/http://www.leadership.duq.edu/home/text/main.cfm?SID=86 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Classes were also available at [[Fort Indiantown Gap]].

=== Italian campus ===
Since 2001, Duquesne has offered an Italian campus program. The facility, part of extensive grounds owned and managed by the [[Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth]], is west of downtown Rome and just beyond [[Vatican City]].&lt;ref&gt;View the Italian campus on [http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Via+Nazareth,+00166+Roma+RM,+Italy&amp;sll=41.902657,12.402507&amp;sspn=0.017663,0.039568&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;z=15&amp;iwloc=addr&amp;om=1 Google Maps].&lt;/ref&gt; University materials describe the campus as &quot;a walled property enclosing beautiful gardens and walkways, [with] classrooms, computer facilities (including Internet), a small library, dining hall, recreational areas, and modernized living quarters complete with bathrooms in each double room.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Description of Property | work=Italian Campus | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.oip.duq.edu/ItalProperty.html | accessdate =2008-09-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The curriculum at the Italian campus includes history, art history, [[Italian language]], philosophy, theology, sociology and economics, appropriate to the historical and cultural setting of Rome. The faculty of the program, largely constituted by visiting professors and resident scholars, is supplemented by a few distinguished professors from the home campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Duquesne University Italian Campus | publisher=Association of American College and University Programs in Italy | url =http://www.aacupi.org/members/duquesne.htm | accessdate =2007-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Academics ==
[[Image:DuquesneMcAnultyCollege.JPG|250px|right|thumb|The McAnulty College and Graduate School of Liberal Arts building borders Duquesne's Academic Walk.]]

Duquesne has a total student enrollment of 10,368 undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;ref name=&quot;fastfacts&quot;/&gt; The University has grown to comprise ten schools and other institutions, offering degree programs at the baccalaureate, professional, masters and doctoral levels in 189 academic programs. It is the only Spiritan institution of higher education in the world,&lt;ref name=&quot;fastfacts&quot;/&gt; and hosts international students from more than eighty different countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;/&gt; The following institutions, along with their dates of founding, comprise Duquesne University:

*[[McAnulty College and Graduate School of Liberal Arts]] (1878)
*[[Bayer School of Natural and Environmental Sciences]] (formally split from College of Arts and Sciences in 1994)
*[[Duquesne University School of Law|Duquesne School of Law]] (1911)
*[[Palumbo-Donahue School of Business|A.J. Palumbo School of Business Administration]] (1913)
*[[Mylan School of Pharmacy]] (1925)
*[[Mary Pappert School of Music]] (1926)
*[[Duquesne University School of Education|School of Education]] (1929)
*[[Duquesne University School of Nursing|School of Nursing]] (1937)
*[[John G. Rangos School of Health Sciences|Rangos School of Health Sciences]] (1990)
*[[Duquesne University School of Leadership and Professional Advancement|School of Leadership and Professional Advancement]] (2001)

== Student life ==
=== Residential life ===
[[Image:DuquesneTowers.JPG|thumb|225px|right|The Duquesne Towers building houses 1,200 students]]

More than 3,600 students live at Duquesne University in five residence halls and one apartment complex. Assumption Hall, built in the 1950s, was the first residential hall on Duquesne's campus, and can accommodate 300 residents. Freshman dormitories include St. Ann's Hall and St. Martin's Hall, which were opened in the 1960s. The largest dormitory facility is Duquesne Towers, which houses 1,200 students, including Greek organizations. Other facilities include Vickroy Hall, built in 1997, and Brottier Hall, which was formerly an apartment complex before its purchase by the university in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Living Learning Centers | work=Office of Residence Life | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.residencelife.duq.edu/livinglearning.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====New residence hall====
On March 10, 2010, the university announced plans to construct a new residence hall. The need for a new residence hall was explained in a news release as being as the result of &quot;retention rates well above national averages and a desire voiced by students to remain on campus during their junior and senior years&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;newresidencehall&quot;/&gt; The new hall will be constructed on the present site of Des Places Hall, an academic building. Demolition of Des Places is slated for November 2010, with construction to begin in the spring of 2011. The new hall, which will likewise be named after [[Claude Poullart des Places]], the founder of the Spiritan congregation, will make available 430 additional beds for upperclassmen, and will be designed to earn [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED certification]].

=== Student groups ===
Duquesne University hosts more than 150 student organizations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Student Organizations | work=Student Activities | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.studentactivities.duq.edu/studentorgs.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; including 19 [[fraternities and sororities]]. Media organizations include a student radio station, WDSR (Duquesne Student Radio). Founded in 1984, it broadcasts solely through the Internet [[streaming audio]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =WDSR | publisher=Duquesne Student Radio | url =http://www.wdsr.org/index.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other student media organizations include ''[[The Duquesne Duke]]'' campus newspaper and ''L'Esprit Du Duc'', the University's yearbook.&lt;ref name=&quot;organizations&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Student Organizations | work=Student Handbook | publisher=Duquesne University | url =
http://www.studentlife.duq.edu/studenthandbook/14_studentorgs.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Duquesne also hosts a Student Government Association, a student-run Program Council, a Commuter Council, a representative Residence Hall Association, an Interfraternity Council, Panhellenic Council, the [[Knights of Columbus]], and numerous departmental Honor Societies.&lt;ref name=&quot;organizations&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:DuquesneStudentUnion.JPG|thumb|225px|left|The Duquesne Student Union is home to student life offices, a ballroom, dining facilities, and a [[Starbucks]].]]

=== Greek life ===
Fraternities on campus include [[Alpha Delta National Fraternity|Alpha Delta]], [[Alpha Phi Delta]], [[Alpha Tau Omega]], [[Delta Chi]], Gamma Phi (a local fraternity formed at Duquesne in 1916), [[Omega Psi Phi]], [[Phi Kappa Theta]], [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], [[Sigma Nu]], [[Sigma Tau Gamma]], and [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]. Sororities include [[Alpha Gamma Delta]], [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]], [[Alpha Phi]], [[Alpha Sigma Tau]], [[Delta Sigma Theta]], [[Delta Zeta]], [[Gamma Phi Beta]], [[Gamma Sigma Sigma]], [[Sigma Kappa]], and [[Zeta Tau Alpha]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Greek Chapters | work=Greek Life | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.greeklife.duq.edu/chapters/index.html | accessdate =2007-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most Duquesne chapters have suites or wings on campus, in the Duquesne Towers building, although there are some chapters on campus which are not housed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Social &amp; Living | work=Greek Life | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.greeklife.duq.edu/soc_liv/index.html | accessdate =2008-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Performance art ===
Duquesne is the home of the [[Duquesne University Tamburitzans|Tamburitzans]], the longest-running multicultural song and dance company in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;tammies&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Tamburitzans | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.tamburitzans.duq.edu/ | accessdate =2007-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their shows feature an ensemble of talented young folk artists dedicated to the performance and preservation of the music, songs, and [[Folk dance|dances]] of Eastern Europe and neighboring folk cultures. The performers are full-time students who receive substantial scholarship awards from the university, with additional financial aid provided by Tamburitzans Scholarship Endowment Funds.&lt;ref name=&quot;tammies&quot;/&gt;

The Mary Pappert School of Music hosts in-house and guest performers on a regular basis. Many music school ensembles also perform at Carnegie Music Hall in Oakland. Instrumental ensembles include the Symphony Orchestra (conductor Jeffrey Turner), the Wind Symphony (conductor Robert Cameron) and Symphony Band (conductor H. Carl Hess), the Contemporary Ensemble (conductor David Cutler), the Jazz Bands (conductors [[Sean Jones (trumpeter)]] and Mike Tomaro) and many other chamber groups. Vocal Ensembles include the Opera Workshop (director Guenko Guechev),the Voices of Spirit (conductor Christine Jordanoff) and the Pappert Women's and Men's chorales. Performances are regular for each ensemble, and tours abroad are common for many.

The University also maintains three theater groups: the [[Red Masquers]], Spotlight Musical Theatre Company, and the Medieval and Renaissance Players. The Masquers annually perform three [[Main stage|main-stage plays]], generally one classical, one modern, and one contemporary. In addition, the group performs two sets of [[One act play|one-act plays]]. &quot;Premieres&quot;, which are student-written, are performed in the winter, while in the spring &quot;One Acts for Charity&quot; are selected from the works of professional playwrights. In recent years, the company has also participated in the Pittsburgh Monologue Project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Red Masquers | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.dutheaterarts.com/redmasquers.asp | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spotlight is a musical theatre company that produces two full-length [[Broadway musicals]] each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Spotlight | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.music.duq.edu/stuOrg.html#spot | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Renaissance and Medieval Players offer audiences a historical [[Medieval theatre|Medieval experience]], performing religious plays, [[morality play]]s, and [[farce]]s from the English Medieval and Early Renaissance periods, sometimes working in conjunction with the Red Masquers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =The Players | publisher=Duquesne University | url =http://www.dutheaterarts.com/players.asp | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Athletics ==
{{main|Duquesne Dukes}}

The [[Duquesne Dukes]] play varsity football, men's and women's basketball, men's and women's [[cross country running|cross country]], men's and women's soccer, women's swimming, men's and women's tennis, men's and women's outdoor track and field, women's indoor track and field, women's [[lacrosse]], women's [[rowing (sport)|rowing]], and women's volleyball at the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] level and in the [[Atlantic Ten Conference|Atlantic 10 Conference]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Sports Finder | publisher=Duquesne University Athletics | url =http://goduquesne.cstv.com/s-finder/duqu-s-finder.html | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =NCAA Compliance | publisher=Duquesne University Athletics | url =http://goduquesne.cstv.com/school-bio/duqu-school-bio-compliance.html | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the Dukes began playing varsity football in the [[NCAA]] Division I [[Northeast Conference]]. In recent years, Duquesne football was a member of the [[NCAA]] Division I [[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference]].&lt;ref name=&quot;goduquesne.cstv.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Duquesne University Football History | publisher=Duquesne University Athletics | url =http://goduquesne.cstv.com/sports/m-footbl/spec-rel/091402aaa.html | accessdate =2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Duquesne has an ACHA Division I ice hockey program.

The fight song for Duquesne is ''Victory Song (Red and Blue)''.

== Sustainability ==
Duquesne was the first university in Pennsylvania to receive the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]]'s Energy Star Combined Heat and Power Award for its [[Gas turbine|natural gas turbine]] located on campus. Duquesne also uses an innovative ice cooling system which cools buildings and reduces peak energy demand. Duquesne's new Power Center facility has also achieved a [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]] Silver Rating.&lt;ref name=&quot;duqsustainability&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Duquesne University Sustainability | publisher=Duquesne University | url = http://www.duq.edu/sustainability/energy-operations.cfm | accessdate = 2010-06-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Duquesne also has a specialized MBA with a focus on sustainability. Furthermore, Duquesne's Center for Environmental Research and Education (CERE) offers undergraduate and graduate degrees in environmental science and management.&lt;ref name=&quot;duqsustainability&quot;/&gt; Duquesne has been evaluated by the 2009 and 2010 College Sustainability Report Card.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Report Card 2010 (Duquesne University) | work=The College Sustainability Report Card | publisher=Sustainable Endowments Institute | year = 2010 | url = http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2010/schools/duquesne-university | accessdate = 2010-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
{{main|List of Duquesne University people}}

Duquesne University's Institutional Research and Planning records list over 79,000 living alumni,&lt;ref name=&quot;fastfacts&quot;/&gt; and the [[Duquesne University School of Law|School of Law]] reports that almost 30 percent of the practicing lawyers in western Pennsylvania are graduates of Duquesne.&lt;ref name=&quot;goduquesne.cstv.com&quot;/&gt;

Duquesne has many alumni in the media and sports fields. These include [[John Clayton (sportscaster)|John Clayton]], a writer and reporter for ESPN; [[Tom Atkins (actor)|Tom Atkins]], an actor ([[Halloween III]], [[Night of the Creeps]], [[My Bloody Valentine (film)|My Bloody Valentine]]); [[Terry McGovern (actor)|Terry McGovern]], the television actor, radio personality, voice-over specialist, and acting instructor; [[Jesse Joyce]], a comedian and writer; and [[World Championship Wrestling]] commentator and writer [[Mark Madden]]. German filmmaker [[Werner Herzog]] attended Duquesne, but did not graduate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Werner Herzog - Biography | publisher=International Movie Database | url =http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001348/bio | accessdate =2007-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sports personalities [[Leigh Bodden]], [[Chip Ganassi]], [[Mike James]], baseball hall-of-famer [[Cumberland Posey]], and [[Chuck Cooper (basketball)|Chuck Cooper]], possibly the first African-American basketball player in the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]], all graduated from Duquesne, as did both the founder and current owner of the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]], [[Art Rooney|Art]] and [[Dan Rooney]]. Singer [[Bobby Vinton]], MLB pitcher [[Joe Beimel]], and big-band composer [[Sammy Nestico]] are also alumni.

[[Norm Nixon]], who holds the all-time assist record for the Duquesne Dukes, is perhaps the most successful alumnus to have played in the NBA. A former All-Star, he also played for the [[Los Angeles Lakers]] championship teams of 1980 and 1982. He ranks among the franchise's top ten in assist, points, steals and games played.

In addition, Duquesne has graduated at least two bishops and two cardinals in the Roman Catholic Church, including Bishops [[Vincent Leonard]], the current ordinary of the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Pittsburgh]], [[David Zubik]], and Cardinals [[Daniel DiNardo]] and [[Adam Maida]]. Figures in politics include [[Donald A. Bailey]], [[James Renshaw Cox|Father James Cox]], former [[Director of the Central Intelligence Agency|Director of the CIA]] [[Michael Hayden (general)|General Michael V. Hayden]], former Lieutenant Governor of Pennsylvania [[Catherine Baker Knoll]], Pennsylvania Representative [[Bud Shuster]], and United States ambassadors [[Thomas Patrick Melady]] and Art Rooney.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|Duquesne University}}
{{Portal|Pittsburgh}}
*[http://www.duq.edu Official website]
*[http://www.goduquesne.com Official Athletics website]

{{coord|40|26|10|N|79|59|35|W|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{DuquesneUniversity}}
{{Atlantic 10 Conference}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Pittsburgh universities}}
{{CHMA}}
{{RCDioPitt}}

[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1878]]
[[Category:Duquesne University| ]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]

[[bg:Дюкейнски университет]]
[[de:Duquesne University]]
[[es:Universidad Duquesne]]
[[la:Universitas Spiritus Sancti Duquesnensis]]
[[ja:デュケイン大学]]
[[pt:Universidade Duquesne]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
