<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5826579" ns="0" title="Aaron Livesy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Emmerdale
|name= Aaron Livesy
|image= [[Image:Aaron-Livesy ED.jpg|200px]]
|caption= Danny Miller as Aaron Livesy (2010)
|image2= [[File:AaronLivesyDWED.jpg|200px]]
|caption2= Danny Webb as Aaron Livesy (2004)
|introducer= [[Steve November|Steve Frost]] (2003, 2004)&lt;br /&gt;[[Kathleen Beedles]] (2006)&lt;br /&gt;Anita Turner (2008)
|portrayer= [[Danny Webb (child actor)|Danny Webb]] (2003–06)&lt;br /&gt;[[Danny Miller (actor)|Danny Miller]] (2008–12)
|years= 2003–06, 2008–12
|first= 24 December 2003
|last=
|born= 5 January 1992
|death=
|classification= [[List of Emmerdale characters#Departing characters|Present; regular (departing)]]
|occupation= [[Mechanic]]
|home= The Woolpack
|family= [[Dingle family|Dingle]]
|father= [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2003)#Gordon Livesy|Gordon Livesy]]
|mother= [[Chas Dingle]]
|grandfathers= [[Shadrach Dingle]]
|grandmothers = [[Faith Dingle]] 
|uncles = [[Cain Dingle]] 
|aunts = [[Genesis Walker]] 
|cousins= [[Debbie Dingle]]
}}
'''Aaron Livesy''' is a [[fictional character]] from the British [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'', played by [[Danny Miller (actor)|Danny Miller]], who took over the role from [[Danny Webb (child actor)|Danny Webb]] in 2008. He made his first on-screen appearance on 24 December 2003. Aaron is the son of [[Chas Dingle|Chastity Dingle]] and [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2003)#Gordon Livesy|Gordon Livesy]]. His storylines have included being involved with the criminal McFarlane family, making a pass at his best friend, [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam Barton]], coming to terms with his [[homosexuality]], and his relationship with [[Jackson Walsh]]. In November 2011, Miller announced that he would be leaving ''Emmerdale'' in 2012.

==Storylines==
===2003–06===
When Aaron was young, his parents, [[Gordon Livesy]] (Gordon Fletcher) and [[Chas Dingle]] ([[Lucy Pargeter]]), separated and Chas left her son to live with his father and Gordon's second wife, [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2006)#Sandra Livesy|Sandra]] (Janet Bamford). Aaron visits his mother in Emmerdale, where he tells her that he resents her for not raising him and explains that he feels that she abandoned him.&lt;ref name=&quot;HolySoap&quot;/&gt; The two begin to bond, before Aaron returns home to his father. Aaron returns to visit Chas, but she reprimands him after she catches him talking to other people about her behind her back. [[Louise Appleton]] ([[Emily Symons]]) witnesses Chas slapping Aaron and tells Gordon when he arrives to collect his son. Gordon tells Chas that her relationship with her son is over and that Aaron will not visit her again. Despite this, Aaron returns to Emmerdale several months later, staying longer than expected as he came into contact with a person who had [[German measles]] and Sandra was pregnant. Aaron returns home to his father and his stepmother, after telling Chas that while she was in the Army, her partner [[Carl King (Emmerdale)|Carl King]] ([[Tom Lister]]) had a one night stand with her cousin, [[Del Dingle]] ([[Hayley Tamaddon]]).

===2008–12===
Aaron returns to the village two years later when arrested by [[Ross Kirk]] ([[Samuel Anderson (actor)|Samuel Anderson]]) for possession of drugs. He is cautioned and meets his mother. Aaron later runs away and Gordon reveals that he threw Aaron out for hitting Sandra. Chas's family learn that Aaron is a drug courier for the McFarlanes and they bring him to Emmerdale, after Gordon refuses to take him back. Aaron clashes with [[Victoria Sugden]] ([[Isabel Hodgins]]), but they eventually become friends and Aaron helps rescue her when she falls into a frozen lake. After Aaron convinces his cousin, [[Belle Dingle]] ([[Eden Taylor-Draper]]), to take the day off school and is caught stealing, her mother [[Lisa Dingle|Lisa]] ([[Jane Cox]]) throws him out. So he and Chas move into Smithy Cottage with [[Paddy Kirk]] ([[Dominic Brunt]]), until he catches Aaron selling drugs. Aaron gets a job at the garage.

Aaron begins dating Victoria and loses his virginity to her but they break up when he discovers her relationship with her foster-brother, Daz Eden. Aaron then dates [[Holly Barton]] ([[Sophie Powles]]) and make friends with her brother, [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam]] ([[Adam Thomas]]). When Aaron ignites a bale of hay at the Bartons' farm, Holly's father, [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John]] ([[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]]), hits him and locks him in a stable. Aaron reports John to the police but drops the charges. Aaron discovers that Chas has resumed her relationship with Carl and he tells her that he wants nothing more to do with her. After Aaron and Adam are involved in a [[run-off-road collision]], Aaron tries to kiss Adam. Aaron is embarrassed and tells Adam that he misunderstood the situation. Aaron sleeps with Holly and Adam tells his family that he thinks Aaron is gay. Adam tells Aaron that he is fine with him being gay, but he does not want his sister to be used. Aaron denies it but Holly ends their relationship.
{{Quote box|quoted=true|bgcolor=#FFFFF0|salign=center|quote=John can't believe that Aaron's gone to the police because as far as he's concerned, this lad has started a fire in his barn and all he's done is dealt with it in an old-school way by putting him in the stable to cool off... John could have gone and phoned the police but he's not that sort of guy. The fact that Aaron reports him for assault and false imprisonment is absolutely shocking to him.|source=[[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]] ([[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]]) discussing a 2009 storyline in which Aaron ignited a bale of hay at the Barton family's farm&lt;ref name=&quot;Soap Insight: Fury at the Farm in 'Emmerdale'&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a172702/soap-insight-fury-at-the-farm-in-emmerdale.html|title=Soap Insight: Fury at the Farm in 'Emmerdale'|last=Green|first=Kris|date=20 August 2009|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=12 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/soaps/2589039/Coming-up-in-Emmerdale.html|title=Coming up in Emmerdale|last=Francis|first=Julia|date=15 August 2009|publisher=''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]''|accessdate=12 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;|align=right|width=25%}}

Aaron visits a gay bar and meets [[Jackson Walsh]] ([[Marc Silcock]]). He leaves his phone behind and Jackson returns it. Aaron returns to the bar to meet Jackson. When Paddy discovers that Aaron visited a gay bar, he asks Aaron if he is gay and Aaron attacks him. Aaron apologises and admits that he is gay but rejects his sexuality. Jackson comes to the village and he and Aaron talk. They go to kiss, but are interrupted. After a night out at the bar, Jackson and Aaron kiss. Jackson comes to [[The Woolpack]] and when he touches Aaron's arm, Aaron punches him. Aaron is charged with [[Assault occasioning actual bodily harm|ABH]] and told he will stand trial. Aaron tries to kill himself by inhaling car fumes, but his uncle, [[Cain Dingle]] ([[Jeff Hordley]]), and Adam drag him outside. During his court case, Aaron admits that he is gay. Aaron gets community service. He meets [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2010)#Wayne Dobson|Wayne Dobson]] (Gary Hanks), who taunts him about his sexuality. Jackson witnesses Aaron being threatened by Wayne and protects him. After talking things through, Aaron and Jackson begin a relationship.

Aaron sells a clocked car to [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2010)#Mickey Hal|Mickey Hall]] (Lee Oakes). Aaron uses his dog, Clyde, to try to intimidate Mickey, but Mickey sets his own dog on Clyde, seriously injuring him, so Clyde has to be put down. Jackson and Aaron argue and Jackson tells Aaron that he loves him. Aaron believe things are becoming too serious for him and the pair do not talk for days. Aaron and Jackson invite Paddy and [[Marlon Dingle]] ([[Mark Charnock]]) on a night out. Jackson is hurt when Aaron does not admit he loves him too and after realising that Aaron will not change his violent tendencies, Jackson drives off. Aaron tries to ring him and later finds Jackson has crashed his van onto a railway and has been hit by a train. Jackson is permanently paralysed from the shoulders down and Aaron tells him that he will not walk again as Jackson's mother, [[Hazel Rhodes|Hazel]] ([[Pauline Quirke]]), cannot do it.

Jackson blames Aaron for the crash and they break up. Aaron then refuses to see Jackson, even when Hazel asks him to. Aaron and Jackson get back together and Aaron helps Jackson and Hazel move into Dale Head. Jackson's mood starts to deteriorate and he pushes Aaron away. Aaron meets [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)#Flynn Buchanan|Flynn Buchanan]] (Ryan Prescott) and he feels like he is cheating on Jackson. Aaron tells Flynn about Jackson and that he cannot forget about him. Aaron then tells Jackson that he loves him. Aaron watches Jackson's video diary and is shocked to hear Jackson admit that he wants to die, he tells Hazel and they try to work out how to help Jackson. Aaron confesses to Jackson that both he and Hazel have watched his video diary. Aaron and Hazel then become determined to show Jackson that he has a life worth living. Jackson is admitted to hospital with a chest infection and it strengthens his resolve to end his life. Jackson, Aaron and Hazel go to Whitby and Aaron books Jackson on a tandem skydive. Aaron thinks Jackson has changed his mind about dying, but he has not. Aaron is shocked to learn that Jackson has managed to convince Hazel to help him end his life. Jackson later promises Aaron that nothing is going to happen until Aaron is ready. Jackson breaks up with Aaron to make the process easier and Aaron agrees to help Jackson end his life. Jackson tells his mother and Aaron how grateful he is for their support and when Hazel cannot give Jackson the pills, Aaron takes the cup and gives it to Jackson. Jackson then dies and Aaron runs through the village. He then tells Adam that Jackson is dead and what he did.

The police investigate Jackson's death and arrest Aaron for murder. Aaron is forced to miss the funeral as he is due in court. He is released on bail and he goes to Jackson's grave to say goodbye. At his trial, Aaron is found not guilty of murder. However, Aaron blames himself for Jackson's death and he starts lashing out at people. Aaron breaks into Carl's house with the intention of getting arrested, but Carl does not press charges. Aaron then begins self harming.

==Character development==
===Casting===
Aaron first appeared in ''Emmerdale'' as a recurring character in 2003 and was played by [[Danny Webb (Emmerdale actor)|Danny Webb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://holysoap.five.tv/emmerdale/cast/debbie-dingle-812|title=Emmerdale Cast - Debbie Dingle|work=Holy Soap|publisher=[[Five (TV channel)|Five]]|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008 the character became a full time member of the cast and the decision was made to recast the part.&lt;ref name=&quot;HolySoap&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://holysoap.five.tv/emmerdale/cast/aaron-livesy-6314|title=Emmerdale Cast - Aaron Livesy|work=Holy Soap|publisher=[[Five (TV channel)|Five]]|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a180710/miller-unfazed-by-emmerdale-attention.html|title=Miller unfazed by 'Emmerdale' attention|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=6 October 2009|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Danny Miller (actor)|Danny Miller]], who previously appeared in [[Grange Hill]], successfully auditioned for the role of Aaron.&lt;ref name=&quot;People&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.people.co.uk/news/tm_headline=emmerdale-actor-danny-tells-of-gay-heartbreak-scenes%26method=full%26objectid=22127362%26siteid=93463-name_page.html|title=Aaron Livesy, Danny In Emmerdale Tells Of Gay Heartbreak Scenes|publisher=[[The People]]|first=Sue|last=Crawford|date=21 March 2010|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller admitted in an interview that he would have quit acting for good if he had not landed the role.&lt;ref name=&quot;People&quot;/&gt;

===Characterisation===
Violent, angry and always in trouble, the character quickly established himself as the 'baddest' of bad boys. Describing Aaron, [[Lucy Pargeter]] ([[Chas Dingle]]) said &quot;Aaron's an absolute pain in the arse for Chas. Danny Miller, who plays him, is brilliant. He gives so much and he's only young&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/scoop/a150441/emmerdales-chas-on-lexi-aaron-and-cain.html|title='Emmerdale's Chas on Lexi, Aaron and Cain|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=24 March 2009|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexuality===
{{Quote_box |width=25%|align=right|quote= &quot;I'd never thought Aaron could be gay - he's probably the most unlikely person in the village to be gay. I saw it as a challenge and said yes, but I was still quite anxious about it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;People&quot;/&gt; |source=— Miller on his reaction to finding out Aaron is gay. (2010)}} 
A high profile storyline for the character was when he began to question his [[sexual orientation]]. As the storyline progressed, Aaron was seen struggling to come to terms with his sexuality, before admitting the truth to his friend and guardian [[Paddy Kirk]] ([[Dominic Brunt]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a209145/miller-enjoying-dales-plot-challenge.html|title=Miller 'enjoying' Dales plot challenge|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=17 March 2010|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller admits that he was apprehensive when the ''Emmerdale'' writers approached him and told him they were making Aaron gay. Miller said &quot;Being a straight actor and having to kiss another lad, I'm not going to lie, I was a bit worried about it, because it's a great test of your acting skills.&lt;ref name=&quot;People&quot;/&gt; Miller's co-star, Dominic Brunt has praised the storyline and told Media and Entertainment website, [[Digital Spy]], that &quot;It's done more realistically than I've seen in a soap.&quot; He went on to describe Aaron as being a [[homophobic]] homosexual, who doesn't like what he is.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a210459/brunt-emmerdale-gay-plot-is-fantastic.html|title=Brunt: 'Emmerdale gay plot is fantastic'|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=24 March 2010|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=13 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller has stated that he is enjoying the challenge presented by the storyline saying &quot;It's definitely been a big challenge - I feel a big responsibility to get this right and portray it in a way that makes it real, because there are so many lads that are going through what Aaron is going through&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://celebrity.uk.msn.com/news/articles.aspx?cp-documentid=152601156|title=Livesy: Gay plot is responsibility|date=16 March 2010|publisher=MSN Celebrity|accessdate=13 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller's co-star [[James Sutton (actor)|James Sutton]], who previously played a gay character in ''[[Hollyoaks]]'', has said that Miller did not need any advice for the role and said, &quot;We've chatted but I've given him no advice - he's a great actor, he doesn't need me to give him any pointers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tv.com/untitled/story/20810.html|title=Dales James: Danny needs no advice|publisher=[[TV.com]]|date=19 January 2010|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Emmerdale'' producer Gavin Blyth explained the gay plotline to Miller saying, &quot;There are hundreds of thousands of teenage lads out there who are struggling with it as we speak - they're sexually confused&quot;. He also added &quot;Aaron keeps it in so much because he's worried about what people think of him&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/interviews/a189197/danny-miller-aaron-livesy-emmerdale.html|title=Danny Miller (Aaron Livesy, 'Emmerdale')|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=1 December 2009|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller has admitted that he felt &quot;awkward&quot; and &quot;strange&quot; when he filmed an intimate moment with his ''Emmerdale'' co-star [[Adam Thomas]], who is his real-life flatmate.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSTwist&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a189242/miller-dales-twist-was-strange-to-film.html|title=Miller: 'Dales twist was strange to film'|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=2 December 2009|accessdate=12 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said &quot;You'd never think yourself to be in the position that these two are in. Knowing myself and knowing Adam and his long-term girlfriend, he's the last person you'd expect in that position.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DSTwist&quot;/&gt;

===Departure===
On 18 November 2011, Miller announced he would be leaving ''Emmerdale'' in 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeaveSoap&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a351625/emmerdale-star-danny-miller-to-leave-soap.html|title='Emmerdale' star Danny Miller to leave soap|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=18 November 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|accessdate=18 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of his decision to leave, Miller said &quot;It has been an incredibly difficult decision but after three years playing Aaron and much soul-searching, I am eager to explore other roles. I am so grateful to ''Emmerdale'' for the opportunity that I have been given and have loved every moment. I will miss everyone enormously but this might not be the last we see of Aaron.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LeaveSoap&quot;/&gt; Series producer Stuart Blackburn said he respected Miller's decision and was grateful for the hard work he had put into the role of Aaron.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeaveSoap&quot;/&gt;

==Reception==
For his portrayal of Aaron, Miller was nominated for the &quot;Best Newcomer Award&quot; at the [[Inside Soap Awards]] in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/tv/eastenders-scoops-7-inside-soap-awards-1794862.html|title=Eastenders clean up at last night's Inside Soap Awards|date=29 September 2009|work=[[The Independent]]|accessdate=12 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller won the &quot;Best Actor&quot; award at the 2011 [[British Soap Awards]], he was also nominated for &quot;Sexiest Male&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/scoop/a307476/british-soap-awards-2011-voting-opens.html|title=British Soap Awards 2011 voting opens|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=7 March 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=7 March 2011&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x0jSLWib|archivedate=7 March 2011 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a319276/british-soap-awards-2011-the-winners.html|title=British Soap Awards 2011: The Winners|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=15 May 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=1 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller was nominated in the category of &quot;Serial Drama Performance&quot; at the 2012 [[National Television Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wightman|first=Catriona|title=National Television Awards 2012: The nominees|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/news/a342357/national-television-awards-2012-the-nominees.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=27 September 2011|date=27 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Holy Soap]] said Aaron's most memorable moment was &quot;His realisation about his sexuality and the emotional scenes where he told Paddy the truth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://holysoap.channel5.com/emmerdale/cast/aaron-livesy-6314|title=Aaron Livesy|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=[[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Danny Miller has said that he has been verbally abused in public for portraying a bad boy and a homosexual. He stated some viewers initially find it difficult to differentiate between character and actor. Miller said, &quot;I get the odd bit of trouble here and there but nothing that I can't handle. I get people shouting stuff, names in the street, but nothing serious.&quot; He added, &quot;There are people who think I'm the character but when they realise you're not they warm to you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a180710/miller-unfazed-by-emmerdale-attention.html|title=Miller unfazed by 'Emmerdale' attention|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=6 October 2009|publisher=Digital Spy|accessdate=12 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of soap operas with LGBT characters]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/soaps/emmerdale/castandcharacters/ftol/aaronlivesy/default.html Character profile] at [[itv.com]]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20090628101709/http://holysoap.five.tv/cast/aaron-livesy-359 Character profile] at [[Holy Soap]]

{{Emmerdale characters|present}}
{{EDDingles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Livesy, Aaron}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional gay males]]
[[Category:Fictional mechanics]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2003]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
