<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="58586" ns="0" title="John Denver"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
| name = John Denver
| image = John Denver portrait.jpg
| caption = John Denver
| background = solo_singer
| birth_name = Henry John Deutschendorf, Jr.
| Born = {{Birth date|1943|12|31| mf=y}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Roswell, New Mexico|Roswell]], New Mexico, U.S.
| Died = {{Death date and age|1997|10|12|1943|12|31|mf=y}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Pacific Grove, California|Pacific Grove]], California, U.S.
| instrument = Vocals, guitar, keyboards, fiddle
| genre = [[Country music|Country]], [[folk music|folk]], pop
| occupation = Singer-songwriter, instrumentalist, record producer, actor, writer, poet, activist
| years_active = 1962–1997
| First album = ''Rhymes &amp; Reasons''
| Latest album = ''Essential''
| Notable albums  ''Poems, Prayers and Promises'', ''Rocky Mountain High'',''An Evening with John Denver'', ''Dreamland Express''
| Notable songs = &quot;Take Me Home, Country Roads&quot;, &quot;Sunshine On My Shoulders&quot;, &quot;Rocky Mountain High&quot; (Colorado State Song since 2007), &quot;Thank God I'm a Country Boy&quot;, &quot;Annie's Song&quot;, &quot;Perhaps Love&quot;, &quot;Calypso&quot;
| label = [[Mercury Records|Mercury]], [[RCA]], [[Bertelsmann Music Group|BMG]], [[Windstar Records|Windstar]], [[Sony Wonder]]
| associated_acts = [[The John Denver Band]], [[The Back Porch Majority]], [[The New Christy Minstrels]], [[Chad Mitchell Trio]], [[The Muppets]], [[Olivia Newton-John]], [[Plácido Domingo]], [[Emmylou Harris]], [[Johnny Cash]], [[Tina Turner]], [[Glen Campbell]]
| website = http://www.johndenver.com/}}

'''Henry John Deutschendorf, Jr.''' (December 31, 1943&amp;nbsp;– October 12, 1997), known professionally as '''John Denver''', was an American singer/songwriter, activist, and humanitarian. After growing up in numerous locations with his military family, Denver began his music career in [[folk music]] groups in the late 1960s. His greatest commercial success was as a solo singer. Throughout his life Denver recorded and released approximately 300 songs, about 200 of which he composed. He performed primarily with an acoustic guitar and sang about his joy in nature, his enthusiasm for music, and relationship trials. Denver's music appeared on a variety of charts including [[country &amp; western]], the [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]], and [[Adult contemporary music|adult contemporary]], in all earning him 12 [[Music recording sales certification|gold]] and 4 platinum albums with his signature songs &quot;[[Take Me Home, Country Roads]]&quot;,  &quot;[[Leaving on a Jet Plane]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rocky Mountain High]]&quot;, &quot;[[Annie's Song]]&quot; and &quot;[[Calypso (song)|Calypso]]&quot;.

Denver further starred in films and several notable television specials in the 1970s and 1980s. In the following decades he continued to record, but also focused on calling attention to environmental issues, lent his vocal support to space exploration, and testified in front of Congress to protest censorship in music. His renown in the state of [[Colorado]], which he sang about numerous times and where he lived in [[Aspen, Colorado|Aspen]], influenced the governor to name him [[Poet Laureate]] of the state in 1974, and for the state legislature to adopt &quot;Rocky Mountain High&quot; as one of its state songs in 2007. He was an avid pilot, and died while flying his personal aircraft at the age of 53. Denver was one of the most popular acoustic artists of the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?table=tblTopArt |title=Gold &amp; Platinum – August&amp;nbsp;17, 2010 |publisher=RIAA |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
===Early years===
Henry John Deutschendorf, Jr., was born in [[Roswell, New Mexico|Roswell]], New Mexico, to Erma Louise Swope and Lt. Col. Henry John Deutschendorf, Sr.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wargs.com/other/denver.html |title='&amp;#39;Ancestry of John Denver'&amp;#39; compiled by William Addams Reitwiesner |publisher=Wargs.Com |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; an [[United States Air Force|Air Force]] Lieutenant Colonel (who set three speed records in the [[B-58 Hustler]] bomber and earned a place in the Air Force Hall of Fame). Henry Sr. was of German ancestry, and met and married his &quot;Oklahoma Sweetheart&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;&gt;[http://www.john-denver.org/default.asp?nc=1168&amp;id=444 John-Denver.org]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Denver's Irish Catholic and German mother's mother, his beloved Grandmother, was the one who imbued Denver with his love of music. In his autobiography, ''Take Me Home'', Denver described his life as the eldest son of a family shaped by a stern father who couldn't show his love for his children.

Because Denver's father was in the military, the family moved often, making it difficult for young John to make friends and fit in with people of his own age. Constantly being the new kid was agony for the introverted child, and he grew up always feeling as if he should be somewhere else, but never knowing where that &quot;right&quot; place was.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/7733036/John-Denver.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | title=John Denver | date=October 14, 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; While living in [[Tucson, Arizona|Tucson]], Arizona, Denver was a member of the Tucson Arizona Boys Chorus for two years. Denver was happy living in Tucson, but his father was transferred to [[Montgomery, Alabama|Montgomery]], Alabama, then in the midst of the [[Montgomery Bus Boycott|Montgomery boycotts]]. The family later moved to [[Fort Worth, Texas|Fort Worth]], Texas, where Denver graduated from [[Arlington Heights High School]]. Attending high school in Fort Worth was a distressing experience for the disenfranchised Denver. In his third year of high school, he borrowed his father's car and ran away to California to visit family friends and begin his music career. His father flew to California to bring him back, and Denver unhappily returned to finish high school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_g1epc/is_bio/ai_2419200301 |title=FindArticles biodata |publisher=Findarticles.com |accessdate=May 9, 2011 |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the age of 11, Denver received an acoustic guitar from his grandmother.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt; He learned to play well enough to perform at local clubs by the time he was in college. He adopted the surname &quot;Denver&quot; after the capital of his favorite state, [[Colorado]], when [[Randy Sparks]], founder of The New Christy Minstrels, suggested that &quot;Deutschendorf&quot; wouldn't fit comfortably on a marquee.&lt;ref name=&quot;sparks&quot;/&gt; Denver attended [[Texas Tech University]] in [[Lubbock, Texas|Lubbock]] and sang in a folk-music group called &quot;The Alpine Trio&quot; while pursuing architecture studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.notablebiographies.com/supp/Supplement-Ca-Fi/Denver-John.html |title=John Denver Biography – life, family, children, name, death, wife, young, son, born, college, contract, marriage, year, Raised in Military Family |publisher=Notablebiographies.com |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}{{Dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;. He was also a member of [[Delta Tau Delta]] Fraternity. Denver dropped out of the Texas Tech School of Engineering in 1963,&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt; and moved to Los Angeles, California, where he sang in the smoky underground folk clubs. In 1965, Denver joined the [[Chad Mitchell Trio]], a folk group that had been renamed &quot;The Mitchell Trio&quot; prior to Chad Mitchell's departure and before Denver's arrival, and then &quot;Denver, Boise, and Johnson&quot; (John Denver, David Boise, and [[Michael Johnson (singer)|Michael Johnson]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt;

===Solo career===
In 1969, John Denver abandoned the band life to pursue a solo career and John released his first album for [[RCA Records]]: ''[[Rhymes &amp; Reasons (John Denver album)|Rhymes &amp; Reasons]]''. Two years prior Denver had made a self-produced demo recording of some of the songs he played at his concerts. He included in the demo a song called &quot;Babe I Hate to Go,&quot; later renamed &quot;Leaving on A Jet Plane.&quot; Denver made several copies and gave them out as presents for Christmas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.johndenver.com/current/current.html john denver: current events]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Mitchell Trio manager Milt Okun brought the unreleased &quot;Jet Plane&quot; song to the high-profile folk group Peter, Paul and Mary. Their version of the song hit number one on the Billboard Hot 100.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Ruhlman | first = William | title = Beginnings| publisher=Goldmine Magazine  | date = April 12, 1996 | url =http://www.peterpaulandmary.com/history/f-ruhlmann3.htm | accessdate =January 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although RCA did not actively promote ''Rhymes &amp; Reasons'' with a tour, Denver himself embarked on an impromptu supporting tour throughout the Midwest, stopping at towns and cities as the fashion took him, offering to play free concerts at local venues. When he was successful in convincing a school, college, American Legion Hall, or local coffee-house to let him play, he would spend a day or so postering the town and could usually be counted upon to show up at the local radio station, guitar in hand, offering himself for an interview. {{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} With his foot-in-the-door of having authored &quot;[[Leaving on a Jet Plane]]&quot;, he was often successful in gaining some valuable promotional airtime, usually featuring one or two songs performed live. Some venues would let him play for the &quot;door&quot;; others restricted him to selling copies of the album at intermission and after the show. After several months of this constant low-key touring schedule, however, he had sold enough albums to convince RCA to take a chance on extending his recording contract. He had also built a sizable and solid fan base, many of whom remained loyal throughout his career.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://johndenver.com/about/biography/ |title=Biography |publisher=john denver |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Denver recorded two more albums in 1970, ''[[Take Me to Tomorrow]]'' and ''[[Whose Garden Was This]]'', featuring songs he had composed while driving the roads of the American Midwest. Although these albums were not as successful as those that followed, they would all be certified gold by the [[RIAA]] and would generally be considered some of his best work.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt;

===Career peak===
His next album, ''[[Poems, Prayers, and Promises]]'' (released in 1971), was a breakthrough for him in the U.S., thanks in part to the single &quot;[[Take Me Home, Country Roads]]&quot;, which went to No.2 on the ''Billboard'' charts despite the first pressings of the track being distorted. Its success was due in part to the efforts of his new manager, future Hollywood producer [[Jerry Weintraub]], who signed Denver in 1970. Weintraub insisted on a re-issue of the track and began a radio-airplay campaign that started in Denver, Colorado. Denver's career flourished from then on, and he had a series of hits over the next four years. In 1972, Denver scored his first Top Ten album with ''[[Rocky Mountain High (album)|Rocky Mountain High]]'', with its title track reaching the Top Ten in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.com/charts/hot-100#/charts/hot-100?chartDate=1973-02-17 |title=Top 100 Music Hits, Top 100 Music Charts, Top 100 Songs &amp; The Hot 100 |work=Billboard  |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1974 and 1975, Denver experienced an impressive chart dominance, with a string of four No.1 songs (&quot;[[Sunshine on My Shoulders]]&quot;, &quot;[[Annie's Song]]&quot;, &quot;[[Thank God I'm a Country Boy]]&quot;, and &quot;[[I'm Sorry (John Denver song)|I'm Sorry]]&quot;) and three No.1 albums (''[[John Denver's Greatest Hits]]'', ''[[Back Home Again (John Denver album)|Back Home Again]]'', and ''[[Windsong]]'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.countrypolitan.com/bio-john-denver.php |title=Artist Biography – John Denver |publisher=Countrypolitan.com |date=October 12, 1997 |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s, Denver's onstage appearance included long blond hair, embroidered shirts emblazoned with images commonly associated with the American West (created by designer &amp; appliqué artist Anna Zapp), and &quot;granny&quot; glasses. His manager, Jerry Weintraub, insisted on a significant number of television appearances, including a series of half-hour shows in [[United Kingdom|England]], despite Denver's protests at the time, &quot;I've had no success in Britain...I mean ''none''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Rocky Mountain Wonderboy,'' James M. Martin, Pinnacle Books 1977&lt;/ref&gt;  Weintraub explained to Maureen Orth of ''Newsweek'' in December 1976, &quot;I knew the critics would never go for John. I had to get him to the people.&quot;

After appearing as a guest on many shows, Denver went on to host his own variety/music specials, including several concerts from [[Red Rocks Amphitheatre]] near [[Denver]]. His seasonal special, ''Rocky Mountain Christmas,'' was watched by more than 60 million people and was the highest-rated show for the ABC network at that time.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
[[Image:John Denver Muppets Christmas Together screen shot.jpg|right|thumb|''John Denver and the Muppets: A Christmas Together''.]]
His live concert special, ''An Evening with John Denver,'' won the 1974–1975 [[Emmy Award|Emmy]] for Outstanding Special, Comedy-Variety or Music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0151551.html |title=Private Tutor |publisher=Infoplease.com |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Denver ended his business relationship because of Weintraub's focus on other projects, Weintraub threw Denver out of his office and called him a Nazi. Denver would later tell Arthur Tobier, when the latter transcribed his autobiography{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}, &quot;...I'd bend my principles to support something he wanted of me. And of course every time you bend your principles – whether because you don't want to worry about it, or because you're afraid to stand up for fear of what you might lose – you sell your soul to the devil.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Take Me Home: An Autobiography,'' John Denver and Arthur Tobier, Harmony Books, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

Denver was also a guest star on ''[[The Muppet Show]],'' the beginning of the lifelong friendship between Denver and [[Jim Henson]] that spawned two television specials with [[The Muppets]]. He also tried his hand at acting, appearing in the ''The Colorado Cattle Caper'' episode of the ''[[McCloud]]'' television movie on February 24, 1974, and starring in the 1977 film ''[[Oh, God!]]'' opposite [[George Burns]]. Denver hosted the [[Grammy Award]]s five times in the 1970s and 1980s and guest-hosted ''The Tonight Show'' on multiple occasions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.answers.com/topic/john-denver |title=John Denver: Biography from |publisher=Answers.com |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1975, Denver was awarded the [[Country Music Association]]'s Entertainer of the Year award. At the ceremony, the outgoing Entertainer of the Year [[Charlie Rich]] presented the award to his successor, but in protest of what he considered the inappropriateness of Denver's selection, Rich set fire to the envelope containing the official notification of the award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cmt.com/shows/dyn/greatest_series/76893/episode_featured_copy.jhtml |title=The Greatest : Features |publisher=CMT.com |date=April 3, 1992 |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Denver's music was defended by country singer [[Kathy Mattea]], who told Alanna Nash of ''[[Entertainment Weekly]],'' &quot;A lot of people write him off as lightweight, but he articulated a kind of optimism, and he brought acoustic music to the forefront, bridging folk, pop, and country in a fresh way.... People forget how huge he was worldwide.&quot;

In 1977, Denver cofounded [[The Hunger Project]] with [[Werner Erhard]] and [[Robert W. Fuller]]. He served for many years and supported the organization until his death. Denver was also appointed by President [[Jimmy Carter]] to serve on the President's Commission on World Hunger, writing the song &quot;I Want to Live&quot; as its theme song. In 1979, Denver performed &quot;Rhymes &amp; Reasons&quot; at the [[Music for UNICEF Concert]]. Royalties from the concert performances were donated to [[UNICEF]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=thepiperchile |url=http://www.abbaontv.com/1979/description-unicef1.html |title=ABBA on TV – Music for UNICEF – A Gift of Song Concert |publisher=Abbaontv.com |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  His father taught him to fly in the mid-1970s, which led to a reconciliation between father and son.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt; In 1980, Denver and his father, Lt. Col. “Dutch” Deutschendorf, co-hosted an award winning television special, &quot;The Higher We Fly: the History of Flight.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt; It won the Osborn Award from the Aviation/Space Writers’ Association, and was honored by the Houston Film Festival.&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;

====Political activism====
Denver became outspoken in politics in the mid-1970s. In 1976, he campaigned for [[Jimmy Carter]], who became a close friend and ally. Denver was a supporter of the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] and of a number of charitable causes for the environmental movement, the homeless, the poor, the hungry, and the [[HIV/AIDS in Africa|African AIDS crisis]]. He founded the charitable [[Windstar Foundation]] in 1976, to promote [[sustainable living]]. His dismay at the [[Chernobyl disaster]] led to precedent-setting concerts in parts of communist Asia and Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt;

During the 1980s, Denver was critical of the [[Ronald Reagan|Ronald Reagan Presidential Administration]], but he remained active in his campaign against hunger, for which Reagan awarded Denver the Presidential World Without Hunger Award in 1985.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt; Denver's criticism of the conservative politics of the 1980s was expressed in his autobiographical folk-rock ballad &quot;[[One World (John Denver album)|Let Us Begin (What Are We Making Weapons For)]].&quot; Denver was also critical of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-dominated [[United States Congress|Congress]] and [[Conservatism in the United States|American Conservatism]] of the 1990s. He denounced the [[National Rifle Association]] (NRA) as a corrupt political machine that could buy off politicians, &lt;!-- Source: The Windstar Foundation publishing of the letter, no longer posted at http://www.wstar.org/ --&gt; and in an open letter to the media, he wrote that he opposed oil drilling in the [[Arctic National Wildlife Refuge]]. Denver had battled to expand the refuge in the 1980s, and he praised President [[Bill Clinton]] for his opposition to the proposed drilling. The letter, which he wrote in the midst of the 1996 presidential election, was one of the last he ever wrote.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt; Denver was also on the Board of Governors of the [[National Space Society]] for many years.

===Later years and humanitarian work===
He had a few more U.S. Top 30 hits as the 1970s ended, but nothing to match his earlier success. He began to focus more on [[Humanitarianism|humanitarian]] and [[sustainability]] causes, focusing extensively on [[Conservation (ethic)|conservation]] projects. He made public expression of his acquaintances and friendships with ecological-design researchers such as [[Buckminster Fuller|Richard Buckminster Fuller]] and [[Amory Lovins]], from whom he said he learned much. He also founded two environmental groups; the Windstar Foundation and Plant-It 2020 (originally Plant-It 2000). Denver had a keen interest in solutions to [[hunger|world hunger]]. He visited Africa during the 1980s to witness first-hand the suffering caused by starvation and to work with African leaders toward solutions.
[[File:John Denver at PMRC Senate Hearing.ogv|thumb|left|John Denver testifies before the US Senate, 1985]]
[[File:John Denver at PMRC Senate Hearing 2.ogv|thumb|left|Testimony continued]]
In 1983 and 1984, Denver hosted the annual [[Grammy Award]]s. In the 1983 finale, Denver was joined on stage by folk-music legend [[Joan Baez]] with whom he led an all-star version of &quot;[[Blowin' in the Wind]]&quot; and [[Let The Sunshine In]], joined by such diverse musical icons as [[Jennifer Warnes]], [[Donna Summer]], and [[Rick James]]. 

In 1984, Roone Arlidge, president of [[ABC Sports]], asked Denver to compose and sing the theme song for the [[1984 Winter Olympics]] in [[Sarejevo]]. Denver worked as both a performer and a skiing commentator (skiing was another avocation of Denver's). He had written &quot;The Gold and Beyond&quot;, and sang it for the Olympic Games athletes, as well as local venues including many schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;  

In 1985, Denver asked to participate in the singing of &quot;[[We Are the World]]&quot; but was turned down. According to [[Ken Kragen]] (who helped to produce the song), the reason that John Denver was turned down was that many people felt his image would hurt the credibility of the song as a pop-rock anthem. &quot;I didn't agree&quot; with this assessment, Kragen said, but reluctantly turned Denver down anyway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.harrychapin.com/circle/winter05/behind.htm |title=Harry Chapin website |publisher=Harrychapin.com |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

For Earth Day 1990, Denver was the on-camera narrator of a well-received environmental TV program, &quot;In Partnership With Earth,&quot; with then–[[Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] Administrator [[William K. Reilly]].

With Denver's innate love of flying he was naturally attracted to [[NASA]] and became dedicated to America’s work in outer space. He conscientiously worked to help bring into being the “Citizens in Space” program. Denver received the [[NASA Public Service Medal]], in 1985 for “helping to increase awareness of space exploration by the peoples of the world,” an award usually restricted to spaceflight engineers and designers. Also in 1985, Denver passed NASA’s rigorous physical exam and was in line for a space flight, a finalist for the first citizen’s trip on the Space Shuttle in 1986. He was not chosen. After the Challenger disaster with teacher Christa McAuliffe aboard, John dedicated his song “Flying for Me”, to all astronauts, and he continued to support NASA.&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;

Denver testified before the Senate Labor and Commerce Committee on the topic of censorship during a [[Parents Music Resource Center]] hearing in 1985. Denver also toured Russia in 1985. His 11 Soviet Union concerts were the first by any American artist in more than 10 years, and they marked a very important cultural exchange that culminated in an agreement to allow other western artists to perform there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Windstar_Russia_CD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wstar.org/windstar/OnlineStore/Products/russiacd.html |title='&amp;#39;Windstar Foundation announcement'&amp;#39; |publisher=Wstar.Com |date=September 11, 2007 |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He returned two years later to perform at a benefit concert for the victims of the [[Chernobyl disaster]]. In October 1992, John undertook a multiple-city tour of the People's Republic of China. He also released a greatest-hits CD, &quot;Homegrown,&quot; to raise money for homeless charities. In 1994, he published his autobiography, ''Take Me Home''. In 1996, he was inducted into the [[Songwriters Hall of Fame]].

In early 1997, Denver filmed an episode for the ''[[Nature (TV series)|Nature]]'' series, centering on the natural wonders that inspired many of his best-loved songs. The episode contains his last song, &quot;Yellowstone, Coming Home,&quot; which he composed while rafting along the [[Colorado River]] with his son and young daughter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/wnet/nature/denver/index.html |title=PBS Nature Website, &quot;John Denver – Let this be a voice&quot; |publisher=Pbs.org |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 1997, Denver recorded a children's train album for [[Sony Wonder]], entitled ''[[All Aboard! (John Denver album)|All Aboard!]]'', produced by long-time friend [[Roger Nichols (recording engineer)|Roger Nichols]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/8580588/Roger-Nichols.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | title=Roger Nichols | date=June 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album consisted of old-fashioned swing, [[big band]], [[Traditional music|folk]], [[bluegrass music|bluegrass]], and [[Gospel music|gospel]] styles of music woven into a theme of railroad songs. This album won a posthumous [[Grammy Award for Best Musical Album for Children|Best Musical Album For Children Grammy]] for Denver, which was his only [[Grammy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rockonthenet.com/artists-d/johndenver_main.htm |title=John Denver |publisher=Rock On The Net |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Personal life===
Denver's first marriage was to Annie Martell of [[St. Peter, Minnesota|St. Peter]], Minnesota. Their wedding was held at the [[Christ Chapel]] at [[Gustavus Adolphus College]]. Annie was the subject of his hit ''[[Annie's Song]]'', which he composed in only ten minutes while on a ski lift in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt;  The couple lived in [[Edina, Minnesota|Edina]], Minnesota from 1968 to 1971. Following the success of &quot;[[Rocky Mountain High]],&quot; Denver purchased a residence in [[Colorado]] and owned one home in Colorado continuously until his death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.midtod.com/98autumn/denver.phtml John Denver: The Baby Boomer's Poet Laureate Of Song].&lt;/ref&gt; He and Annie adopted a son, Zachary, and daughter, Anna Kate, who John would say were “meant to be” theirs.&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt; John once said, &quot;I'll tell you the best thing about me. I'm some guy's dad; I'm some little gal's dad. When I die, Zachary John and Anna Kate's father, boy, that's enough for me to be remembered by. That's more than enough.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Martin, Frank W. [http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20073026,00.html &quot;John Denver's Unsung Story&quot;], ''People'', February 26, 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; Zachary was the subject of &quot;A Baby Just Like You,&quot; a song that included the line &quot;Merry Christmas, little Zachary&quot; and which he wrote for [[Frank Sinatra]]&lt;!--, who also appeared on the ''Muppet Christmas Special''--&gt;. Denver and Martell divorced in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt; She continues to live in [[Aspen, Colorado|Aspen]], Colorado. 

John Denver married Australian actress Cassandra Delaney in 1988. They had a daughter, Jesse Belle. They separated in 1991 and divorced in 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;/&gt;

Denver's talent extended beyond music. He was a painter as well but because of his limiting schedule, he pursued photography. He once said that &quot;photography is a way to communicate a feeling.&quot; Denver was an avid skier and golfer. His love of flying was secondary only to his love for music.&lt;ref name=&quot;People&quot;&gt;Castro, Peter. [http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20123569,00.html &quot;Peaks &amp; Valleys&quot;], ''People.com'', October 27, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; He collected vintage biplanes and in 1974, he bought a [[Learjet]], which he used to fly himself to concerts. He also bought a [[Aviat Eagle II|Christen Eagle]] aerobatic plane, two [[Cessna 210]] and in 1997, the ill-fated [[Rutan Long-EZ]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;People&quot;/&gt;

[[File:NOAA-Long-EZ.jpg|thumb|right|250px|A Long-EZ two seat canard plane similar to Denver's]]

===Death===
On October 12, 1997, Denver was killed at the age of 53 when his experimental [[Rutan Long-EZ]] plane, [[Aircraft registration|aircraft registration number]] N555JD, crashed into the Pacific Ocean near [[Pacific Grove, California|Pacific Grove]], California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.avweb.com/other/ntsb9905.html |title=Closeup: The John Denver Crash |publisher=Avweb.com |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[National Transportation Safety Board]] accident ID is LAX98FA008.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ntsb.gov/aviationquery/brief.aspx?ev_id=20001208X09045&lt;/ref&gt;

A pilot with over 2,700 hours of experience, Denver had single-engine land and sea, multi-engine land, glider, and instrument [[Pilot licensing and certification|rating]]s. He also held a [[type rating]] in his Learjet. He had recently purchased the Long-EZ aircraft, and had taken a half-hour checkout flight with the aircraft the day before the accident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.check-six.com/Crash_Sites/John-Denver-N555JD.htm Check-Six.com] - John Denver's Long-Ez&lt;/ref&gt; The NTSB cited Denver's unfamiliarity with the aircraft and his failure to have the aircraft refueled as causal factors in the accident. Denver was the sole occupant of the aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlwww.ntsb.gov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ntsb.gov/news/1999/990126.htm |title=Press release |author=National Transportation Safety Board (NTSB) |accessdate=December 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the accident, the [[Federal Aviation Administration]] had learned of his failure to abstain entirely from [[alcoholic beverages|alcohol]] after his [[drunk driving]] arrests, and since his medical certification was conditional on this, a determination was made that due to his drinking problem, he was not qualified for any class of medical certification at the time. At least a [[Medical certifications for pilots|third-class medical certification]] was required to exercise the privileges of his pilot certificate. However, there was no trace of alcohol or any other drug in Denver's body at autopsy.&lt;ref name=NTSB&gt;National Transportation Safety Board. [http://dms.ntsb.gov/aviation/GenPDF.aspx?id=LAX98FA008&amp;rpt=fa ''Long-EZ, N555JD, Flight History and Accident Report'', ID= LAX98FA008], October 12, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

Human-interface designer and pilot [[Bruce Tognazzini]] analyzed Denver's fatal crash on his webzine, AskTog,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Tognazzini|first=Bruce|url=http://www.asktog.com/columns/027InterfacesThatKill.html |title=John Denver: When Interfaces Kill |publisher=AskTog |date=October 12, 1997 |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in June 1999.

This particular aircraft had an unusual reconfiguration of the fuel selector valve handle, which had been moved from the instrument panel to behind the left shoulder of the pilot. Apparently it also had a sticky [[O-ring]] and was hard to move. Both factors may have led to Denver pushing the right rudder pedal when he turned to switch fuel tanks by moving the handle. The aircraft then entered an uncontrolled turning descent: a [[spiral dive]] or a [[spin (flight)|spin]]. 
&lt;!--WP should say which one.--&gt;
Flying at an estimated altitude of {{convert|500|ft|m}}, he did not have time to recover. As the wreck badly disfigured Denver's head and body, making identification by dental records impossible, records of his fingerprints taken from his arrests for intoxicated driving were used to confirm that the fallen pilot was indeed the singer.&lt;ref&gt;Kligman, David. [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4413095.html &quot;John Denver Dies In Crash&quot;], ''Chicago Sun Times'', October 13, 1997. reprinted at highbeam.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rockmine.com/Archive/Vault/DeaCert/Denver.html Certificate of Death], October 13, 1997; at rockmine.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon announcement of Denver's death, Colorado governor [[Roy Romer]] ordered all state flags to be lowered to [[half-mast|half staff]] in his honor. Denver was cremated with the 1910 [[Gibson Guitar Corporation|Gibson guitar]] given to him by his grandmother which had inspired much of his career. Funeral services were held at Faith Presbyterian Church in [[Aurora, Colorado|Aurora]], Colorado, on October 17, 1997, being officiated by Pastor Les Felker, a retired Air Force chaplain. Later, Denver's ashes were scattered in the [[Rocky Mountains]]. Further tributes were made at the following Grammys and [[Country Music Association|Country Music Association Awards]].  On September 23, 2007, nearly ten years after his death, his brother Ron witnessed the dedication of a plaque placed near the crash-site in Pacific Grove, California, commemorating the singer.

==Posthumous recognition==
In 2000, CBS presented the television movie ''Take Me Home: The John Denver Story'' loosely based on his memoirs, starring [[Chad Lowe]]. Denver's brother, Ron Deutschendorf, voiced the feelings of many of the singer's fans when he wrote a letter to the ''Los Angeles Times'' criticizing the film's many inaccuracies: multiple chronological errors, exaggerated difficulties in his relationship with his father, and a completely superficial treatment of Denver's commitment to his various causes. As the ''New York Post'' observed, &quot;An overachiever like John Denver couldn't have been this boring.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Buckman, Adam. &quot;Home Movie Disses Denver&quot;, ''[[New York Post]]'', April 29, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Denver's music remains extremely popular around the world. Previously unreleased and unnoticed recordings are now sought-after collectibles in pop, folk and country genres. Also in demand are copies of Denver's many television appearances, especially his one-hour specials from the 1970s and his six-part series for Britain's BBC, ''The John Denver Show''. Despite strong interest in these programs, no sign of &quot;official&quot; release is evident for the vast majority of this material. An anthology musical featuring John Denver's music, ''Back Home Again: A John Denver Holiday'', premiered at the Rubicon Theatre Company in November 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shellworld.net/~emily/jdfriend.html |title=John Denver and Friends Rocky Mountain High WWW Page |publisher=Shellworld.net |date=April 17, 2009 |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On March 12, 2007, Colorado's Senate passed a resolution to make Denver's trademark 1972 hit &quot;Rocky Mountain High&quot; one of the state's two official state songs, sharing duties with its predecessor, &quot;Where the Columbines Grow.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.netstate.com/states/symb/song/co_rocky_mountain_high.htm Accessed 4/16/2009&lt;/ref&gt; The resolution passed 50–11 in the House, defeating an objection by Rep. Debbie Stafford (R-Aurora) that the song reflected drug use, most specifically the line, &quot;Friends around the campfire and everybody's high.&quot; Sen. Bob Hagedorn, the Aurora Democrat who sponsored the proposal, defended the song as nothing to do with drugs, but everything to do with sharing with friends the euphoria of experiencing the beauty of Colorado's mountain vistas. Nancy Todd (D-Aurora) said that &quot;John Denver to me is an icon of what Colorado is.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Denver Post, 3/13/2007&lt;/ref&gt; Similar proposals have also been made to the West Virginia House of Delegates to make &quot;Take Me Home Country Roads&quot; the official song of that particular state, so far without success.
[[File:DSCN2983 johndenvermemorial e 600.jpg|left|250px|thumb|The lyrics to &quot;[[Rocky Mountain High]]&quot;, one of Colorado's official state songs, in Rio Grande Park&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aspenportrait.com/john_denver_sanctuary/denver1-0706.html |title=John Denver Sanctuary, Aspen, Colorado |publisher=Aspenportrait.com |date=October 12, 1997 |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; near Denver's hometown of [[Aspen, Colorado|Aspen]], Colorado.]]
On September 24, 2007, the California Friends of John Denver and The Windstar Foundation unveiled a bronze plaque near the spot where his plane went down near Pacific Grove. The site had been marked by a driftwood log carved (by Jeffrey Pine of Colorado) with the singer's name, but fears that the memorial could be washed out to sea sparked the campaign for a more permanent memorial. Initially the Pacific Grove Council denied permission for the memorial, fearing the place would attract ghoulish curiosity from extreme fans. Permission was finally granted in 1999, but the project was put on hold at the request of the singer's family. Eventually, over 100 friends and family attended the dedication of the plaque, which features a bas-relief of the singer's face and lines from his song &quot;Windsong&quot;: &quot;So welcome the wind and the wisdom she offers. Follow her summons when she calls again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://johndenverclub.org/JohnDenverPlaque/johndenvermemorialplaquepacificgrove.html |title=John Denver Memorial Plaque Pacific Grove |publisher=Johndenverclub.org |accessdate=May 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To mark the 10th anniversary of Denver's death, his family released a set of previously unreleased recordings of Denver's 1985 concert performances in the [[Soviet Union]]. This two-CD set, ''John Denver – Live in the USSR'', was produced by Denver's friend [[Roger Nichols (recording engineer)|Roger Nichols]], and released by AAO Music. These digital recordings were made during 11 concerts, and then rediscovered in 2002. Included in this set is a previously unpublished rendition of &quot;[[Annie's Song]]&quot; in Russian. The collection was released November 6, 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Windstar_Russia_CD&quot; /&gt;

On October 13, 2009, a DVD box set of previously unreleased concerts recorded throughout Denver's career was released by Eagle Rock Entertainment. &quot;Around the World Live&quot; is a 5-disc DVD set featuring three complete live performances with full band from Australia in 1977, Japan in 1981, and England in 1986. These are complemented by a solo acoustic performance from Japan in 1984, and performances at Farm Aid from 1985, 1987 and 1990. The final disc has two hour-long documentaries made by Denver.

On April 21, 2011, John Denver became the first inductee into the [[Colorado Music Hall of Fame]]. A benefit concert was held at Broomfield's [[1STBANK Center]] and hosted by Olivia Newton-John. Other performers participating in the event included [[Nitty Gritty Dirt Band]], [[Lee Ann Womack]] and [[John Oates]]. Both of his ex-wives were in attendance, and the award was presented to his three children.

==Related artists==
{{Main|The John Denver Band}}
Denver began his recording career with a group that had started as the [[Chad Mitchell Trio]]; his distinctive voice can be heard where he sings solo on ''Violets of Dawn'', among other songs. He recorded three albums with the Mitchell Trio, replacing Chad Mitchell himself as high tenor.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt; The group Denver, Boise and Johnson, which had evolved from the Mitchell Trio, released a single before he moved on to a solo career.&lt;ref name=&quot;sparks&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thenewchristyminstrels.com/ |title=The New Christy Minstrels |publisher=Thenewchristyminstrels.com |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bill Danoff]] and [[Starland Vocal Band|Taffy Nivert]], credited as co-writers of Denver's song &quot;[[Take Me Home, Country Roads]]&quot;, were close friends of Denver and his family, appearing as singers and songwriters on many of Denver's albums until they formed the [[Starland Vocal Band]] in 1976. The band's albums were released on Denver's Windsong Records (later known as [[Windstar Records]]) label. Denver's solo recording contract resulted in part from the recording by Peter, Paul and Mary of his song &quot;[[Leaving on a Jet Plane]]&quot;, which became the sole number 1 hit single for the group.&lt;ref name=&quot;bio&quot;/&gt; Denver recorded songs by [[Tom Paxton]], [[Eric Andersen]], [[John Prine]], [[David Mallett]], and many others in the folk scene. His record company, [[Windstar Records|Windstar]], is still an active record label today.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} Country singer [[John Berry (singer)|John Berry]] considers Denver the greatest influence on his own music and has recorded Denver's hit &quot;Annie's Song&quot; with the original arrangement.

[[Olivia Newton-John]], an Australian singer whose across-the-board appeal to pop, [[Middle of the road (music)|MOR]], and country audiences in the mid-1970s was similar to Denver's, lent her distinctive backup vocals to Denver's 1975 single &quot;Fly Away&quot;; she performed the song with Denver on his 1975 ''[[Rocky Mountain Christmas]]'' special. She also covered his &quot;[[Take Me Home, Country Roads]]&quot;, and had a hit in the United Kingdom (#15 in 1973) and Japan (#6 in a belated 1976 release) with it.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} In 1976, John Denver appeared as a guest star, along with [[Olivia Newton-John]], who made a cameo appearance, on [[The Carpenters]] Very First Special, a one-hour TV special broadcast on the ABC television network. A highlight of the program was John singing a duet with [[Karen Carpenter]] of a medley of &quot;[[Through the Rye]]&quot; and &quot;[[Good Vibrations]]&quot;, although the medley was never released commercially as a single or on an album.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

September 2008 saw the premiere of the musical ''Whisper the Wind'' in New Zealand, a tribute presentation covering highlights of Denver's life and career, with the younger Denver played by 21-year-old Dunedin musician Bevan Gardiner, whose vocal impersonation of the late singer was considered so accurate Denver's business manager Harold Thau could not tell them apart.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODT_21673&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.odt.co.nz/entertainment/arts/21673/meet-dunedin039s-own-john-denver |title=Meet Dunedin's own John Denver |author=Benson, Nigel |date=September 10, 2008 |work=[[Otago Daily Times]] |accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and recognition==
'''[[American Music Award|Academy of Country Music]]'''
*[[Academy of Country Music|1974 Album of the Year]] for &quot;[[Back Home Again (John Denver album)|Back Home Again]]&quot;

'''[[American Music Awards]]'''
*[[American Music Award for Favorite Pop/Rock Male Artist|1975 Favorite Pop/Rock Male Artist]]
*[[American Music Award for Favorite Country Album|1976 Favorite Country Album]] for &quot;[[Back Home Again (John Denver album)|Back Home Again]]&quot;
*[[American Music Award for Favorite Country Male Artist|1976 Favorite Country Male Artist]]

'''[[Country Music Association]]'''
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1975 Entertainer of the Year]]
*[[Country Music Association Awards|1975 Song of the Year]] for &quot;[[Back Home Again (song)|Back Home Again]]&quot;

'''[[Emmy Award]]s'''
*1975 Emmy for Outstanding Variety, Music or Comedy Special for &quot;An Evening With John Denver&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;

'''[[Grammy Award]]s'''
*[[Grammy Award for Best Musical Album for Children|1997 Best Musical Album For Children]] for &quot;[[All Aboard! (John Denver album)|All Aboard!]]&quot;
*[[Grammy Hall of Fame Award|1998 Grammy Hall of Fame Award]] for &quot;[[Take Me Home, Country Roads]]&quot;

'''[[Songwriters Hall of Fame]]'''
*[[Songwriters Hall of Fame#1996|Inducted in 1996]]

===Other recognition===
* [[Poet Laureate]] of Colorado, 1977&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;
* [[People's Choice Awards]], 1977&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;
* Ten Outstanding Young Men of America, 1979&lt;ref name=&quot;JD&quot;/&gt;
* [[Carl Sandburg]]’s People’s Poet Award, 1982
* [[NASA]] Public Service Medal, 1985
* [[Albert Schweitzer]] Music Award, 1993
* &quot;Rocky Mountain High&quot; declared state song of Colorado, 2007

==Discography==
{{Main|John Denver discography}}

==Filmography==
{{Main|John Denver filmography}}

==Selected writings==
*''Alfie the Christmas Tree'' (1990) ISBN 0-945051-25-5
*''Take Me Home: An Autobiography'' (1994) ISBN 0-517-59537-0
*''Poems, Prayers and Promises: The Art and Soul of John Denver'' (2004) ISBN 1-57560-617-8

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Sources==
*Flippo, Chet (1998) &quot;John Denver,&quot; ''The Encyclopedia of Country Music,'' Paul Kingsbury, Editor, New York: Oxford University Press. p.&amp;nbsp;143.
*Martin, James M. (1977) &quot;John Denver: Rocky Mountain Wonderboy,&quot; Pinnacle Books. (Out of print) Biography of Denver with insight into Denver's impact of the 1970s music industry.
*Orth, Maureen, &quot;Voice of America,&quot; ''[[Newsweek]],'' December 1976. Includes information on the role of Weintraub in shaping Denver's career, which has since been edited out of later versions of his biography.

==External links==

{{Commons|John Denver}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.johndenver.com/ Official website]
* [http://www.wstar.org/ Windstar Foundation, cofounded by Denver]
* [http://songwritershalloffame.org/exhibits/C155 Clips of his songs] from the [[Songwriters Hall of Fame]] website
* {{IMDb name|id=0000135|name=John Denver}}
&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME= Denver, John
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES= Deutschendorf, Henry John, Jr.
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Singer-songwriter, [[instrumentalist]], [[recording industry|record producer]], actor, writer, poet, activist
|DATE OF BIRTH= 1943-12-31
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Roswell, New Mexico|Roswell]], New Mexico, United States
|DATE OF DEATH= 1997-10-12
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Pacific Grove, California|Pacific Grove]], California, United States}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Denver, John}}
[[Category:American country singers]]
[[Category:American folk singers]]
[[Category:American male singers]]
[[Category:Songwriters from New Mexico]]
[[Category:Songwriters Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:American environmentalists]]
[[Category:The Hunger Project]]
[[Category:People from Roswell, New Mexico]]
[[Category:Musicians from New Mexico]]
[[Category:People from Denver, Colorado]]
[[Category:Musicians from Colorado]]
[[Category:Roaring Fork Valley]]
[[Category:Texas Tech University alumni]]
[[Category:Military brats]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in the United States]]
[[Category:Aviators killed in aviation accidents or incidents in the United States]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:People associated with the Human Potential Movement]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in California]]
[[Category:1943 births]]
[[Category:1997 deaths]]
[[Category:American musicians of German descent]]
[[Category:American musicians of Irish descent]]
[[Category:John Denver| ]]

[[ar:جون دنفر]]
[[ca:John Denver]]
[[cs:John Denver]]
[[da:John Denver]]
[[de:John Denver]]
[[et:John Denver]]
[[es:John Denver]]
[[eo:John Denver]]
[[eu:John Denver]]
[[fa:جان دنور]]
[[fr:John Denver]]
[[ko:존 덴버]]
[[id:John Denver]]
[[it:John Denver]]
[[he:ג'ון דנוור]][[la:Iohannes Denver]]
[[lv:Džons Denvers]]
[[nl:John Denver]]
[[ja:ジョン・デンバー]]
[[no:John Denver]]
[[nds:John Denver]]
[[pl:John Denver]]
[[pt:John Denver]]
[[ro:John Denver]]
[[ru:Джон Денвер]]
[[sq:John Denver]]
[[simple:John Denver]]
[[sk:John Denver]]
[[fi:John Denver]]
[[sv:John Denver]]
[[tl:John Denver]]
[[th:จอห์น เดนเวอร์]]
[[tr:John Denver]]
[[uk:Джон Денвер]]
[[vi:John Denver]]
[[zh:約翰·丹佛]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
