<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5883418" ns="0" title="Army of Islam (Gaza Strip)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Army of Islam''' ({{lang-ar|جَيش الإسلام}} Jaysh al-Islām), also known as '''[[Tawhid]] and [[Jihad]] Brigades''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asiamedia.ucla.edu/article-world.asp?parentid=67903 |title=PALESTINE: Reporter is dead, claims terror group |publisher=Asiamedia.ucla.edu |date=2007-04-17 |accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the name used by the [[Doghmush]] ''Hamula'' ([[clan]]) for their Islamic militant activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gears&quot;&gt;[http://www.gplanet.co.il/prodetailsamewin.asp?pro_id=413 'The Gears' by Dr. Guy Bechor] {{Language icon|he|Hebrew}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is located at the Tzabra neighborhood in the center of the [[Gaza Strip]] bordered by [[Israel]] and [[Egypt]]. It is a [[designated terrorist organizations|designated terrorist organization]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2011/05/163838.htm|title=Designation of Army of Islam|accessdate=2011-5-19|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activities==
Notorious for their capture of Israeli soldier [[Gilad Shalit]] and the [[kidnapping]] of [[BBC]] reporter [[Alan Johnston]], Army of Islam, which appears to draw inspiration from, or is linked to, [[al-Qaeda]], have also conducted at least one bombing of a Palestinian civilian target (an empty school&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/04/21/news/22mideast.php Bombing at U.S.-backed school in Gaza]&lt;/ref&gt;) and a number of other kidnappings. The group has been previously closely related to [[Hamas]], but has been since shunned by both Hamas and [[Fatah]]. The group has also been known as ''The Organization of al-Qaeda in Palestine'' and is linked to [[Abu Qatada]], the British-based Palestinian-[[Jordan]]ian extremist [[Sheikh]] who they demanded be released in exchange for Johnston.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.terrorism-info.org.il/malam_multimedia/English/eng_n/html/islam_troops_e.htm |title=The Army of Islam, a radical Islamic Palestinian terrorist group in the Gaza Strip |publisher=Terrorism-info.org.il |date= |accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 November 2010 senior Army of Islam leader Mohammad Namnam was killed in a [[targeted killing]] when the car he was driving in Gaza City was hit by a missile fired from an Israeli military helicopter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=November 17, 2010&amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; 6:35 pm |url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/babylonbeyond/2010/11/israel-army-targets-army-of-islam-operatives-again.html |title=ISRAEL, GAZA: Security forces target Army of Islam operatives, again &amp;#124; Babylon &amp; Beyond &amp;#124; Los Angeles Times |publisher=Latimesblogs.latimes.com |date=2010-11-17 |accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Israel killed Namnam after Egyptian authorities reportedly tipped-off Israel that Namnam was helping plan a future attack on multinational security forces in [[Sinai]].&lt;ref&gt;Vick, Karl, &quot;Behind An Israeli Strike In Gaza, Help From Egypt,&quot; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', 10 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the November 3 air strike, the [[Israeli Air Force]] killed two other members of the group. Mohammed and Islam Yassif were killed in an air strike, fired from an unmanned [[Unmanned aerial vehicle|drone]], on 17 November 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imemc.org/article/59930 |title=Two Brothers, Members Of the Army of Islam, Killed By Army Airstrike In Gaza – International Middle East Media Center |publisher=Imemc.org |date= |accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The attack, coordinated with Israeli security services, [[Shin Bet]], came around dawn on a busy street in Gaza City, and cited the same security issues as that in the killing of Namnam.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.maannews.net/eng/ViewDetails.aspx?ID=334011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Kidnapping of Alan Johnston==
{{main|Kidnapping of Alan Johnston}}

In 2007 the group kidnapped the BBC correspondent Alan Johnston.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gears&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.news.yahoo.com/rtrs/20070624/tpl-uk-palestinians-bbc-81f3b62.html BBC's Johnston shown in tape wearing explosives]{{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 25, 2007 a video was released by Army of Islam showing Johnston with an explosive belt around his waist,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=b2c_1182727196 |title=BBC Reporter Alan Johnston Wearing Suicide Belt Appeals |publisher=LiveLeak.com |date=2007-06-24 |accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a demands for the release of Muslim prisoners in British custody. The group, which also kidnapped ten members of Hamas, had claimed that they would have killed him if there had been an attempt to rescue him by force. On July 4, 2007, after Gaza authorities arrested several members of Army of Islam including its spokesman, Abu Muthana,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070702/ap_on_re_mi_ea/palestinians_kidnapped_reporter Hamas makes arrest in reporter's case]{{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and following threats of [[execution]], Johnston was handed over to Hamas officials and released after 114 days in captivity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6267928.stm |title=BBC's Alan Johnston is released |publisher=BBC News |date=2007-07-04 |accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alexandria bombing==
The Army of Islam has been linked with the [[2011 Alexandria bombing|2011 bombing of a Coptic church in Alexandria]] that resulted in 23 deaths. Egypt's Interior minister said on 23 January that evidence proved that the group planned and executed the attack. The group quickly denied responsibility, while also reportedly expressing support for the bombing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Egypt blames Gaza group for bombing|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/01/201112311414915283.html|accessdate=2011-01-26|publisher=Al Jazeera|date=2011-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Fatah al-Islam]]
*[[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Army Of Islam (Gaza Strip)}}
[[Category:Al-Qaeda]]
[[Category:Gaza Strip]]
[[Category:Islamist groups]]
[[Category:Palestinian militant groups]]
[[Category:Israel–Gaza conflict]]

[[ar:جيش الإسلام]]
[[de:Dschaisch al-Islam]]
[[he:צבא האסלאם (עזה)]]
[[ru:Армия Ислама (Cектор Газа)]]
[[fi:Islamin armeija]]
[[sv:Islams armé]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
