<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="590852" ns="0" title="Xen"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the virtualization software}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = Xen
| logo                   =
| screenshot             = [[File:Xen screenshot.png|250px]]
| caption                = Xen running [[NetBSD]] and three [[Linux]] distributions
| developer              = The Xen Project&lt;br&gt;XenSource, Inc.
| released               = {{start date|2003}}
| latest release version = 4.1.2&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.xen.org/index.php/2011/10/21/xen-4-1-2-and-4-0-3-released/&lt;/ref&gt;
| latest release date    = {{release date|2011|10|21}}
| operating system       = [[Linux]], and other [[Unix-like]], [[*BSD]], [[OpenSolaris]] as both hosts and guests; [[Microsoft Windows]] as a guest OS.
| genre                  = [[Virtual machine monitor]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License|GNU GPL]] v2
| website                = http://www.xen.org/
}}
'''Xen''' ({{IPA-en|ˈzɛn|pron}}) is a [[Hypervisor|virtual-machine monitor]] providing services that allow multiple computer [[operating system]]s to execute on the same [[computer hardware]] concurrently.

The [[University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory]] developed the first versions of Xen. Since 2010, the Xen community develops and maintains Xen as [[free software]], licensed under the [[GNU General Public License]] (GPLv2). Xen is available for the [[IA-32]], [[x86-64]], [[Itanium]] and [[ARM architecture|ARM]] computer architectures.

In Xen systems the Xen [[hypervisor]] is the lowest and most privileged software layer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/srg/netos/xen/readmes/user/user.html Xen 3.0 User Manual]&lt;/ref&gt; This layer supports one or more guest operating systems, scheduled on the physical CPUs. The first guest operating system, called in Xen terminology ''domain 0'' (dom0) is executed automatically when the hypervisor boots and receives special management privileges and direct access to all physical hardware by default. The system administrator can log into dom0 in order to manage any additional guest operating systems, called user domains (''domU'') in Xen terminology.

The dom0 domain is typically a modified version of [[Linux]], [[NetBSD]] or [[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]]. User domains may either be unmodified copies of open-source or proprietary operating systems, such as  [[Microsoft Windows]], if the host processor supports [[x86 virtualization]], e.g., [[Intel VT-x]] and [[AMD-V]]),&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.xensource.com/xenwiki/OSCompatibility Xen OS Compatibility]&lt;/ref&gt; or modified, ''para-virtualized'' operating system with special drivers that support enhanced Xen features.

== History ==
Xen originated as a research project at the [[University of Cambridge]], led by [[Ian Pratt (computer scientist)|Ian Pratt]], [[lecturer|senior lecturer]] at Cambridge and founder of XenSource, Inc. This company now supports the development of the [[Open-source software|open source]] project and also sells enterprise versions of the software. The first public release of Xen occurred in 2003. [[Citrix Systems]] acquired XenSource, Inc in October 2007 and subsequently renamed Xensource's products under the Citrix brand:

* XenExpress became &quot;XenServer Express Edition&quot; and &quot;XenServer OEM Edition&quot; (embedded hypervisor)
* XenServer became &quot;XenServer Standard Edition&quot;
* XenEnterprise became &quot;XenServer Enterprise Edition&quot;

Subsequently the product lines have been renamed XenServer (Free), Essentials for XenServer Enterprise, and Essentials for XenServer Platinum. 

On 22 October 2007, [[Citrix Systems]] completed its acquisition of XenSource,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Citrix Systems &amp;raquo; Citrix Completes Acquisition of XenSource |publisher=Citrix Systems |date=2007-07-12 |url=http://www.citrix.com/English/NE/news/news.asp?newsID=683171}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Xen project moved to http://www.xen.org/. This move had started some time previously, and made public the existence of the Xen Project Advisory Board (Xen AB), which had members from [[Citrix]], [[IBM]], [[Intel]], [[Hewlett-Packard]], [[Novell]], [[Red Hat]], [[Sun Microsystems]] and [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]. The Xen AB charter assigns it oversight of the project's code-management procedures, and with development of a new trademark policy for the Xen mark, which Citrix intends to freely license to all vendors and projects that implement the Xen [[hypervisor]]; the Xen AB will have sole responsibility for the requirements of licensing.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

On 21 October 2009, Citrix further announced their, now commercial, applications of XenServer would be fully open-source and made freely available to the public under the name Xen Cloud Platform (XCP).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.virtualization.info/2009/10/citrix-to-fully-open-source-xenserver.html&lt;/ref&gt; Simon Crosby, CTO of Virtualization and Management division at Citrix, stated: &quot;XenServer is 100% free, and also shortly fully open sourced. There is no revenue from it at all.&quot;

The product lines were renamed in Spring 2010 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=XenServer features by edition |publisher=Citrix Systems |url=http://www.citrix.com/English/ps2/products/subfeature.asp?contentID=2300456}}&lt;/ref&gt;:

* XenServer [Free edition]
* XenServer Advanced Edition
* XenServer Enterprise Edition
* XenServer Platinum Edition

=== Release history ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; 
|-
! Version
! width=100px| Release date
! Notes
|-
| 1.0
| 2003-10-02&lt;ref&gt;http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/message.php?msg_id=5533663&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://lwn.net/Articles/52033/&lt;/ref&gt;
| 
|-
| 2.0
| 2004-11-05&lt;ref&gt;http://lwn.net/Articles/109789/&lt;/ref&gt;
| 
|-
| 3.0
| 2005-12-05&lt;ref&gt;http://lwn.net/Articles/162841/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archive.org/web/20051210024853/http://www2.getxen.com/news/pr120505b.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|
* Supports the [[X86_virtualization#Intel_virtualization_.28VT-x.29|Intel VT technology]] for hvm guests.
* Support the [[Ia64|Intel IA64]] architecture.

The releases up to 3.0.4 also added:
* Support for the [[X86_virtualization#AMD_virtualization_.28AMD-V.29|AMD SVM virtualization]] extensions.&lt;ref&gt;http://lists.xensource.com/archives/cgi-bin/mesg.cgi?a=xen-users&amp;i=A95E2296287EAD4EB592B5DEEFCE0E9D4BA296%40liverpoolst.ad.cl.cam.ac.uk&lt;/ref&gt;
* Support for the [[Powerpc|PowerPC]] architecture.&lt;ref&gt;http://lists.xensource.com/archives/html/xen-devel/2006-10/msg00733.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Graphical framebuffer support for paravirtualised guests.&lt;ref&gt;http://lists.xensource.com/archives/html/xen-devel/2006-12/msg00889.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 3.1
| 2007-05-18&lt;ref&gt;http://lists.xensource.com/archives/html/xen-announce/2007-05/msg00002.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| 
|-
| 3.2
| 2008-01-17&lt;ref&gt;http://vmblog.com/archive/2008/01/17/xen-3-2-0-officially-released.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
| PCI passthrough and ACPI S3 standby mode for the host system.
|-
| 3.3
| 2008-08-24&lt;ref&gt;http://www.h-online.com/newsticker/news/item/Xen-3-3-0-hypervisor-ready-for-download-737027.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| Improvements for the PCI passthrough and the power management.
|-
| 3.4
| 2009-05-18&lt;ref&gt;http://community.citrix.com/display/ocb/2009/05/18/Xen.org+Announces+Release+of+Xen+3.4+Hypervisor&lt;/ref&gt;
| Contains a first version of the &quot;Xen Client Initiative&quot;, shortly XCI.
|-
| 4.0
| 2010-04-07&lt;ref&gt;http://www.h-online.com/open/news/item/Virtualisation-Xen-is-looking-to-catch-up-by-releasing-version-4-974405.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| Makes it possible to use a dom0 Linux kernel, which has been implemented by using PVOps. A Linux kernel of version 2.6.31 has been modified for this purpose, because the official Linux kernel actually doesn't support the usage as dom0 kernel (date July 2010).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.xen.org/files/Xen_4_0_Datasheet.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 4.1
| 2011-03-25&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.xen.org/index.php/2011/03/25/xen-4-1-releases/&lt;/ref&gt;
| Some of the improvements: Support for more than 255 processors, better stability. Linux kernel v2.6.37 and onward support usage as dom0 kernel (&lt;ref&gt;http://wiki.xensource.com/xenwiki/XenParavirtOps&lt;/ref&gt;).
|}

== Uses ==
Virtual machine monitors (also known as [[hypervisor]]s) often operate on [[Mainframe computer|mainframes]] and large servers running [[IBM]], [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]], and other systems. [[Internet hosting service]] companies increasingly use hypervisors to provide [[virtual private server]]s. [[Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud|Amazon EC2]], [[Fujitsu Global Cloud Platform]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://m.zdnetasia.com/fujitsu-s-global-cloud-launches-in-aus-62207108.htm |title=Fujitsu's global cloud launches in Aus |publisher=ZDNet Australia |author=Suzanne Tindal|date=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Linode]], and [[Rackspace Cloud]] use Xen as the VM hypervisor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rackspace.com/cloud/cloud_hosting_faq/ About The Rackspace Cloud]&lt;/ref&gt;

Server virtualization can provide benefits such as:

* consolidation
* increased utilization
* rapid provisioning
* dynamic [[fault tolerance]] against software failures (through rapid bootstrapping or rebooting)
* hardware fault tolerance (through migration of a virtual machine to different hardware)
* the ability to securely separate virtual operating systems
* the ability to support legacy software as well as new OS instances on the same computer

Xen's support for virtual machine live migration from one host to another allows [[Load balancing (computing)|workload balancing]] and the avoidance of downtime.

Virtualization also has benefits when working on development (including the development of operating systems): running the new system as a guest avoids the need to reboot the physical computer whenever a bug occurs. [[Sandbox (computer security)|Sandboxed]] guest systems can also help in computer-security research, allowing study of the effects of some [[computer virus|virus]] or [[computer worm|worm]] without the possibility of compromising the host system.

Finally, hardware appliance vendors may decide to ship their appliance running several guest systems, so as to be able to execute various pieces of software that require different operating systems.

Xen can run as a virtualization platform, such as Citrix XenServer Enterprise Edition (formerly XenSource's XenEnterprise), or embedded within the host operating system. As an example of the latter configuration, note the inclusion of Xen in:

* [[Novell]]'s [[SUSE Linux|SUSE Linux Enterprise 10]] distribution
* [[Red Hat]]'s RHEL 5/Fedora 7
* [[Sun Microsystems]]' Solaris
* [[Debian]]'s Etch release

In 2007, XenSource announced that Dell would incorporate Citrix XenServer OEM Edition as an embedded hypervisor installed in flash memory as an option on all PowerEdge servers, early in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citrix.com/English/NE/news/news.asp?newsID=683297 Dell and Citrix Partner to Simplify Virtualization Technology], 23 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  By May 2010 however, Citrix and their OEM partners (including Dell) decided to retire the flash memory embedded OEM XenServer editions.  Only the XenServer 5.6 Retail Edition is available for PowerEdge servers from Dell.  Customers currently running the Dell OEM XenServer 5.5 edition (or earlier) can upgrade to preserve their virtual machines' configuration data.&lt;ref&gt; [http://support.citrix.com/article/CTX125196 Migrating from OEM Editions of XenServer 5.5 to XenServer 5.6], Created: May 27, 2010; Updated: May 26, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

XenSource has also started developing a compatibility layer for [[Windows Server 2008]] hypervisor, so that systems modified to run as Xen guests will also function on the 2008 hypervisor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2006/jul06/07-17MSXenSourcePR.mspx Microsoft Press Release], 16 July 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

== Technology ==
=== Types of virtualization ===
==== Paravirtualization, requiring porting of guest systems ====
On most CPUs, Xen uses a form of virtualization known as [[paravirtualization]], meaning that guests run a modified operating system using a special [[hypercall]] [[Application Binary Interface|ABI]] instead of certain architectural features. Through paravirtualization, Xen can achieve high performance even on its host architecture (x86) which has a reputation for non-cooperation with traditional virtualization techniques.&lt;ref&gt;Robin and Irvine, [http://www.usenix.org/events/sec2000/robin.html &quot;Analysis of the Intel Pentium's Ability to Support a Secure Virtual Machine Monitor&quot;], 9th Usenix Security Symposium, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gil Neiger, Amy Santoni, Felix Leung, Dion Rodgers, Rich Uhlig. [http://www.intel.com/technology/itj/2006/v10i3/1-hardware/3-software.htm Intel Virtualization Technology: Software-only virtualization with the IA-32 and Itanium architectures], ''Intel Technology Journal'', Volume 10 Issue 03, August 2006.
&lt;/ref&gt;

On x86, the Xen host kernel code runs in [[ring (computer security)|Ring 0]], while the hosted domains run in [[ring (computer security)|Ring 1]] or in [[ring (computer security)|Ring 3]].

==== Hardware-assisted virtualization, allowing for unmodified guests ====
Both [[Intel]] and [[AMD]] have contributed modifications to Xen to support their respective [[Intel VT-x]] and [[AMD-V]] architecture extensions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intel.com/technology/itj/2006/v10i3/3-xen/1-abstract.htm Extending Xen with Intel Virtualization Technology], ''intel.com''&lt;/ref&gt; Though these technologies differ quite substantially in their implementation and instruction sets, Xen manages them via a common abstraction layer, enabling unmodified guest operating systems to run within Xen virtual machines, starting with Xen 3.0.

This development allows the virtualization of proprietary operating systems (such as Microsoft Windows), since the guest system's kernel does not require modification when the host runs on Intel VT-x or AMD-V hardware.

[[Hardware-assisted virtualization]] (HVM) offers new instructions to support direct calls by a paravirtualized guest/driver into the hypervisor, typically used for I/O or other so-called hypercalls. It also provides additional execution modes: &quot;root mode&quot; and &quot;non-root mode&quot;. Both of these modes have Rings 0-3; the Xen host operates in root mode and has access to the real hardware, while the unmodified guest operates in Rings 0-3 of non-root mode, with its &quot;hardware&quot; accesses under complete control of the hypervisor.

Xen-HVM has device emulation based on the [[QEMU]] project to provide I/O virtualization to the virtual machines. The system emulates hardware via a patched QEMU &quot;device manager&quot; (qemu-dm) daemon running as a backend in dom0. This means that the virtualized machines see as hardware: a PIIX3 IDE (with some rudimentary PIIX4 capabilities), Cirrus Logic or vanilla VGA emulated video, RTL8139 or NE2000 network emulation, [[Physical Address Extension|PAE]], and somewhat limited [[Advanced Configuration and Power Interface|ACPI]] and [[Advanced Programmable Interrupt Controller|APIC]] support and no SCSI emulation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ian.blenke.com/xen/hvm/svm/vtx/qemu Demystifying Xen HVM]&lt;/ref&gt;

Xen 3.0.2 supports the following unmodified guests:

* certain versions of Microsoft Windows (including Windows XP)
* Linux.

=== Virtual machine migration ===
Administrators can &quot;live migrate&quot; Xen virtual machines between physical hosts across a LAN without loss of availability. During this procedure, the LAN iteratively copies the memory of the virtual machine to the destination without stopping its execution. The process requires a stoppage of around 60&amp;ndash;300&amp;nbsp;ms to perform final synchronization before the virtual machine begins executing at its final destination, providing an illusion of seamless migration. Similar technology can serve to suspend running virtual machines to disk and switch to another virtual machine, resuming the first virtual machine at a later date.

=== Host: Unix-like systems ===
Xen under Linux runs on [[x86]], with [[Pentium II]] or newer processors, [[x86-64]] based systems, as well as on [[IA-64]] and [[PowerPC]]. Xen supports up to 64-way [[symmetric multiprocessing]].
Xen boots from a [[bootloader]] such as [[GNU GRUB]], and then usually loads a modified host operating system into the host domain (dom0). {{As of | 2009}}, most Linux distributions had included Xen packages to interact with the Xen hypervisor and start additional domains, but because Xen was not accepted into the mainline Linux kernel and installation required several kernel patches, some distros such as Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 and Ubuntu 8.10 dropped out-of-the-box support for dom0 in subsequent releases.  With the inclusion of the most significant parts of Xen in the Linux 2.6.37 mainline kernel in early 2011, several distributions are again considering dom0 support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url=http://blog.xen.org/index.php/2011/01/14/linux-2-6-37-first-upstream-linux-kernel-to-work-as-dom0/
 | title=Linux 2.6.37: first upstream Linux kernel to work as Dom0
 | work=blog.xen.org
 | date=2011-01-14
 | accessdate=2011-04-03 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url=http://lwn.net/Articles/412164/
 | title=Kernel development
 | work=LWN.net
 | date=2010-11-01
 | accessdate=2011-04-03 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Version 3.0 of the Linux kernel supports dom0 and domU in the mainline kernel.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.xen.org/index.php/2011/06/02/xen-celebrates-full-dom0-and-domu-support-in-linux-3-0/&lt;/ref&gt;

* Novell's [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Server]] release 10 pioneered the first commercial implementation of Xen in this form.
* [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] 5 also offers support for Xen, but in RHEL 6 there is no support for dom0.
* [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] has host support for Xen from the FC4 to Fedora 8 releases, but {{as of | 2010 | September | lc=on }} Fedora doesn't support dom0.&lt;ref&gt;http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Archive:Tools/Xen&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ubuntu Linux|Ubuntu]] included Xen packages from Ubuntu 8.04 ([[Hardy Heron]]), supporting Xen versions 3.2 and 3.1.&lt;ref&gt;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Xen&lt;/ref&gt; Note however that Ubuntu doesn't include or support a dom0-capable kernel from [[Intrepid Ibex]] (Ubuntu 8.10) onward.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archiveorange.com/archive/v/UsR4nzBeS5vYtX5ylWMY&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Xen#Ubuntu's Support of Xen&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Debian]] includes Xen 4.0.1 in its stable release 6.0 (codename &quot;Squeeze&quot;), and Xen 3.2.1 in its oldstable release 5.0 (codename &quot;Lenny&quot;).
* [[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]] and [[Arch Linux]] both have packages available to support Xen.&lt;ref&gt;
http://packages.gentoo.org/package/xen
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
http://aur.archlinux.org/packages.php?ID=14640&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[openSUSE]] 10.x and 11.x includes Xen 3.1 support. [[YaST]] and virt-man offer graphical VM management.&lt;ref&gt;http://wiki.xensource.com/xenwiki/XenDom0Kernels
&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[OpenSolaris]]-based distributions can function as dom0 and domU from Nevada build 75 onwards.
* {{As of | 2009}} support for [[OpenBSD]] self-hosting required the correction of a lock-up bug before its release.&lt;ref&gt;http://marc.info/?l=openbsd-misc&amp;m=116955702618902
&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[NetBSD]] 3.x. includes host support for Xen 2, with host support for Xen 3.0 available from NetBSD 4.0.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.netbsd.org/Ports/xen/
&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Guests ===
==== Unix-like systems as guests ====
Guest systems can run fully virtualized (which requires hardware support) or paravirtualized (which requires a modified guest operating system). The following systems have patches allowing them to operate as paravirtualized Xen guests:

* [[Linux kernel|Linux]], paravirtualization integrated in 2.6.23, patches for other versions exist
* [[Minix]]
* [[Plan 9 from Bell Labs]]
* [[NetBSD]] (NetBSD 2.0 has support for Xen 1.2, NetBSD 3.0 has support for Xen 2.0, NetBSD 3.1 supports Xen 3.0, NetBSD 5.0 features Xen 3.3)
* [[OpenBSD]], announced in a, now dead, blog entry {{wayback|url=http://anil.recoil.org/blog/articles/2006/08/21/openbsd-xen-boots-multi-user|date=20060828073112}} The support has since been discontinued.
* [[FreeBSD]] (Limited, experimental support for Xen 3 in 8-CURRENT [http://wiki.freebsd.org/FreeBSD/Xen])
* [[OpenSolaris]] (See [http://opensolaris.org/os/community/xen/ The Xen Community On OpenSolaris])
* [[NetWare]] (at [http://www.novell.com/brainshare/ Brainshare 2005], [[Novell]] showed a port that can run as a Xen guest)
* [[Hurd|GNU/Hurd/Mach]] (gnumach-1-branch-Xen-branch)
* [[OZONE]] (has support for Xen v1.2)

==== Microsoft Windows systems as guests ====
Xen version 3.0 introduced the capability to run [[Microsoft Windows]] as a guest operating system unmodified if the host machine's processor supports [[x86 virtualization|hardware virtualization]] provided by Intel VT-x (formerly codenamed Vanderpool) or AMD-V (formerly codenamed Pacifica).

During the development of Xen 1.x, [[Microsoft Research]], along with the University of Cambridge Operating System group, developed a port of [[Windows XP]] to Xen — made possible by [[Microsoft]]'s Academic Licensing Program. The terms of this license do not allow the publication of this port, although documentation of the experience appears in the original Xen [[SOSP]] paper.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/srg/netos/papers/2003-xensosp.pdf Xen and the Art of Virtualization], ''University of Cambridge SOSP'03 paper''
&lt;/ref&gt;

James Harper and the Xen open-source community have started developing [http://wiki.xensource.com/xenwiki/XenWindowsGplPv GPL'd Paravirtualisation] drivers for Windows. These provide front-end drivers for the Xen block and network devices, and allow much higher disk and network performance for Windows systems running in HVM mode. Without these drivers all disk and network traffic has to be processed through QEMU-DM.

== Xen Management Consoles ==
Third-party developers have built a number of tools (known as Xen Management Consoles) to facilitate the common tasks of administering a Xen host, such as configuring, starting, monitoring and stopping of Xen guests. Examples include:
* Servarica WHMCS XenServer Module [http://servarica.com/xen/ SWXSM]
* [http://www.solusvm.com/ SolusVM]
* [http://www.xen-tools.org/software/xen-tools/ Xen Tools]
* [http://code.google.com/p/ganeti/ Ganeti]
* the [[Perl]]-based [http://mln.sourceforge.net/ MLN]
* the web-based [[HyperVM]] and [[FluidVM]]
* the web-based [http://www.cloudmin.com/ Cloudmin]
* the [[Graphical user interface|GUI]] applications [http://xenman.sourceforge.net/ Convirture] (formerly [[XenMan]]) and [[Red Hat]]'s Virtual Machine Manager, [http://virt-manager.et.redhat.com/ virt-manager].
* the [[OpenNebula]] cloud management toolkit
* [http://sourceforge.net/projects/openxenmanager/ OpenXenManager] - An open source clone of Citrix's XenCenter.
* [http://www.xvpsource.org/ XVP] - Web-based VM manager for XenServer and Xen Cloud Platform

[[Novell]]'s [[PlateSpin]] Orchestrate also manages Xen virtual machines for Xen shipping in [[SUSE Linux distributions|SUSE]] Linux Enterprise Server.

== Commercial implementations ==
* [[Citrix]] XenServer
* [[Oracle VM]]
* [[Sun xVM]]
* [[Virtual Iron]]
* Thinsy Corporation

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Kernel-based Virtual Machine]] (KVM)
* [[Comparison of platform virtual machines]]
* [[Hyper-V]]
* [[VMware ESX]]
* [[Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization]]
* [[Virtual disk image]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.xen.org}}
* [http://www.citrix.com/xenserver/ Official Citrix product site]
* [http://www.lumbercartel.ca/library/xen/ Step-by-step installation instructions for Xen, with a DomU capable of running Windows XP SP3 and ReactOS]
* [http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/Research/SRG/netos/xen/ University of Cambridge research page for Xen]
* [http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/TechReports/UCAM-CL-TR-553.pdf University of Cambridge, Technical Report Number 553, January 2003]. Early report outlining the architecture of Xen.
* [http://wiki.xensource.com/xenwiki/Xen_on_4_app_servers Xen Guide by Tapas Mishra]
* [http://www.unifiedsessionsmanager.org/doc/en/html/man1/ctys-createConfVM.html UnifiedSessionsManager - An Unofficial Xen configuration file creator]

{{FLOSS}}

[[Category:2003 introductions]]
[[Category:Free virtualization software]]
[[Category:University of Cambridge Computer Laboratory]]

[[ca:Xen]]
[[cs:Xen]]
[[da:Xen]]
[[de:Xen]]
[[es:Xen]]
[[fr:Xen]]
[[ko:젠]]
[[it:Xen]]
[[he:Xen]]
[[nl:Xen]]
[[ja:Xen (仮想化ソフトウェア)]]
[[pl:Xen]]
[[pt:Xen]]
[[ru:Xen]]
[[fi:Xen]]
[[sv:Xen (virtualisering)]]
[[ta:சென்]]
[[zh:Xen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
