<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="59126" ns="0" title="Apostrophe"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect| ' }}
{{Redirect|Apostrophes|the music book|Apostrophes: A Book of Tributes to Masters of Music}}
{{Other uses}}

{{Punctuation marks|’ '}}

The '''apostrophe''' (&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;, often rendered as &amp;nbsp;'&amp;nbsp;) is a [[punctuation]] mark, and sometimes a [[diacritic]] mark, in languages that use the [[Latin alphabet]] or certain other alphabets. In English, it serves three purposes:&lt;ref&gt;Quirk, Geenbaum, Leech &amp; Svartvik, ''A Comprehensive Grammar of the English Language'', p985, Longman, London &amp; New York, ISBN 0-582-51734-6, p 1636&lt;/ref&gt;
* The marking of the omission of one or more letters (as in the [[Contraction (grammar)|contraction]] of ''do not'' to ''don't'').
* The marking of [[possessive case]] (as in ''the cat's whiskers'').
* The marking as [[plural]] of written items that are not [[word]]s established in English [[orthography]] (as in ''P's and Q's'', ''the late 1950's''). (This is considered incorrect by some; see [[#Use in forming certain plurals|Use in forming certain plurals]]. The use of the apostrophe to form plurals of proper words, as in ''apple's'', ''banana's'', etc., is universally considered incorrect.)

According to the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] (OED), the word comes ultimately from [[Greek language|Greek]] {{Polytonic|ἡ ἀπόστροφος [προσῳδία]}} ({{lang|grc-Latn|''hē apóstrophos'' [''prosōidía'']}}, &quot;[the accent of] 'turning away', or elision&quot;), through [[Latin language|Latin]] and [[French language|French]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The English form ''apostrophe'' is due to its adoption via French and its current pronunciation as four syllables is due to a confusion with the rhetorical device [[apostrophe (figure of speech)|''apostrophé'']]&quot; (W. S. Allen, ''Vox Graeca. The pronunciation of classical Greek'', 3rd edition, 1988. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, p.&amp;nbsp;100, note&amp;nbsp;13).&lt;/ref&gt;

The apostrophe is different from the closing single [[quotation mark]] (usually rendered identically but serving a different purpose), from the similar-looking [[prime (symbol)|prime]] (&amp;nbsp;&amp;prime;&amp;nbsp;), which is used to indicate measurement in [[foot (length)|feet]] or [[arcminute]]s, as well as for various mathematical purposes, and from the [[ʻokina]] (&amp;nbsp;{{okina}}&amp;nbsp;), which represents a [[glottal stop]] in Polynesian languages.

==English language usage==
===Historical development===

The apostrophe was introduced into English in the sixteenth century in imitation of French practice.&lt;ref name=Crystal&gt;
{{Cite book
  | last = Crystal
  | first = David
  | authorlink =David Crystal
  | title = The Cambridge Encyclopedia of the English Language, Second Edition
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | year = 2003
  | page = 203
  | isbn = 0 521 53033 4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====French practice====
Introduced by [[Geoffroy Tory]] (1530), the apostrophe was used in place of a vowel letter to indicate [[Elision in the French language|elision]] (as in ''l'heure'' in place of ''la heure''). It was frequently used in place of letter ''e'' when no actual [[vowel sound]] was elided (as in ''un' heure''). Modern French [[orthography]] has restored the spelling ''une heure''.&lt;ref&gt;Alfred Ewert, ''The French Language'', 1933, Faber &amp; Faber, London, p 119&lt;/ref&gt;

====Early English practice====
From the sixteenth century, following French practice, the apostrophe was used when a vowel letter was omitted either because of [[elision]] (as is in ''I'm'' in place of ''I am'') or because the letter no longer represented a sound (as in ''lov'd'' in place of ''loved''). English spelling retained many [[inflection]]s which were often not pronounced as [[syllables]], notably [[verb]] [[suffix]]es ''-est, -eth, -es, -ed'' and [[noun]] [[suffix]] ''-es'' representing either [[plural]]s or [[Possessive case|possessives]] (also known as [[Genitive case|genitives]]). Thus, apostrophe followed by ''s''  was often used to mark [[plural]], especially when the [[noun]] was a [[loan word]] (as in ''the two comma's'').&lt;ref name=Crystal/&gt;

====Standardisation====

The use for [[elision]] has continued to the present day, but significant changes have been made to the [[possessive case|possessive]] and [[plural]] uses. By the 18th century, apostrophe + ''s'' was regularly used for all [[possessive case|possessive]] [[Grammatical number|singular]] forms, even when the letter ''e'' was not omitted (as in ''the gate's height''). This was regarded as representing the [[Old English]] [[genitive]] singular [[inflection]] ''-es''. The [[plural]] use was greatly reduced, but a need was felt to mark [[possessive case|possessive]] [[plural]]. The solution was to use an apostrophe after the [[plural]] ''s'' (as in ''girls' dresses''). However, this was not universally accepted until the mid nineteenth century.&lt;ref name=Crystal/&gt;

=== Possessive apostrophe ===
{{See also|Saxon genitive}}

An apostrophe is used in English to indicate [[Possession (linguistics)|possession]]. The practice ultimately derives from the [[Old English language|Old English]] [[genitive]] case: the &quot;of&quot; case, itself used as a possessive in many languages.{{Clarify| reason = How can the Old English genitive case be used in &quot;many languages&quot;?|date=June 2011}} The genitive form of many nouns ended with the [[inflection]] ''-es'', which evolved into a simple ''-s'' for the possessive ending. An apostrophe was later added to replace the omitted ''e'' (not an omitted ''his'' as is often believed).{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

====General principles for the possessive apostrophe====

;Summary of rules for most situations{{anchor|Summary of rules for most situations}}

*Possessive personal pronouns, serving as either noun-equivalents or adjective-equivalents, do not use an apostrophe, even when they end in ''s''. The complete list of those ending in the letter ''s'' or the corresponding sound /s/ or /z/ but not taking an apostrophe is ''ours, yours, his, hers, its, theirs'', and ''whose''.
*Other pronouns, singular nouns not ending in ''s'', and plural nouns not ending in ''s'' all take '''s'' in the possessive: e.g., ''someone's, a cat's toys, women's''.
*Plural nouns already ending in ''s'' take only an apostrophe after the pre-existing ''s'' when the possessive is formed: e.g., ''three cats' toys''.

;Basic rule (singular nouns){{anchor|Basic rule (singular nouns)}}

For most singular nouns the ending ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s'' is added; e.g., ''the cat's whiskers''.
* If a singular noun ends with an ''s''-sound (spelled with ''-s'', ''-se'', for example), practice varies as to whether to add ''{{'s}}'' or the apostrophe alone. A widely accepted practice is to follow whichever spoken form is judged better: ''the boss's shoes'', ''Mrs Jones' hat'' (or ''Mrs Jones's hat'', if that spoken form is preferred). In many cases, both spoken and written forms differ between writers. (See details [[#Singular nouns ending with an &quot;s&quot; or &quot;z&quot; sound|below]].)
{{anchor|Plural possessive}}
;Basic rule (plural nouns){{anchor|Basic rule (plural nouns)}}
When the noun is a normal plural, with an added ''s'', no extra ''s'' is added in the possessive; so ''pens' caps'' (where there is more than one pen) is correct rather than ''pens's caps''.
* If the plural is not one that is formed by adding ''s'', an ''s'' is added for the possessive, ''after'' the apostrophe: ''children's hats'', ''women's hairdresser'', ''some people's eyes'' (but compare ''some peoples' recent emergence into nationhood'', where ''peoples'' is meant as the plural of the singular ''people''). These principles are universally accepted.
* A few English nouns have plurals that are not spelled with a final ''s'' but end in an /s/ or a /z/ sound: ''mice'' (plural of ''mouse'', and for compounds like ''[[dormouse]]'', ''[[titmouse]]''), ''[[dice]]'' (when used as the plural of ''die''), ''pence'' (a plural of ''penny'', with compounds like ''sixpence'' that now tend to be taken as singulars). In the absence of specific exceptional treatment in style guides, the possessives of these plurals are formed by adding an apostrophe and an ''s'' in the standard way: ''seven [[titmice]]'s tails were found'', ''the dice's last fall was a seven'', ''his few pence's value was not enough to buy bread''. These would often be rephrased, where possible: ''the last fall of the dice was a seven''.&lt;ref&gt;''Pease'' as an old plural of ''pea'' is indeterminate: ''Lentils' and pease'[s] use in such dishes was optional''. Nouns borrowed from French ending in ''-eau'', ''-eu'', ''-au'', or ''-ou'' sometimes have alternative plurals that retain the French ''-x'': ''beaux'' or ''beaus''; ''bureaux'' or ''bureaus''; ''adieux'' or ''adieus''; ''fabliaux'' or ''fabliaus''; ''choux'' or ''chous''. The ''x'' in these plurals is often pronounced. If it is, then (in the absence of specific rulings from style guides) the plural possessives are formed with an apostrophe alone: ''the beaux' [or beaus'] appearance at the ball''; ''the bureaux' [or bureaus'] responses differed''. If the ''x'' is not pronounced, then in the absence of special rulings the plurals are formed with an apostrophe followed by an ''s'': ''the beaux's appearance''; ''the bureaux's responses''; ''their adieux's effect was that everyone wept''. See also [[#Nouns ending with silent &quot;s&quot;, &quot;x&quot;, or &quot;z&quot;|Nouns ending with silent &quot;s&quot;, &quot;x&quot; or &quot;z&quot;]], below, and attached notes.&lt;/ref&gt;

;Basic rule (compound nouns){{anchor|Basic rule (compound nouns)}}
Compound nouns have their singular possessives formed with an apostrophe and an added ''s'', in accordance with the rules given above: ''the Attorney-General's husband''; ''the [[Lord Warden of the Cinque Ports]]' prerogative''; ''this Minister for Justice's intervention''; ''her father-in-law's new wife''.
* In such examples, the plurals are formed with an ''s'' that does not occur at the end: e.g., ''attorneys-general''. A problem therefore arises with the ''possessive'' plurals of these compounds. Sources that rule on the matter appear to favour the following forms, in which there is both an ''s'' added to form the plural, and a separate ''s'' added for the possessive: ''the attorneys-general's husbands''; ''successive Ministers for Justice's interventions''; ''their fathers-in-law's new wives''.&lt;ref&gt;''Style Guide'', [http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/pub/pdf/bjssg.pdf US Department of Justice, Bureau of Justice Statistics]; [http://www.gpoaccess.gov/stylemanual/2000/chapter_txt-8.html ''The United States Government Printing Office Style Manual 2000'']; ''The Chicago Manual of Style'' (CMOS), 5.25: &quot;The possessive of a multiword compound noun is formed by adding the appropriate ending to the last word {parents-in-law's message}.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Because these constructions stretch the resources of punctuation beyond comfort, in practice they are normally reworded: ''interventions by successive Ministers for Justice''.&lt;ref&gt;CMOS, 7.25: &quot;If plural compounds pose problems, opt for ''of''. ... ''the professions of both my daughters-in-law''.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.llc.manchester.ac.uk/subjects/lel/staff/david-denison/papers/Fileuploadmax10Mb,120431,en.pdf ''Is the English Possessive '''''{{'s}}''''' Truly a Right-Hand Phenomenon?]&lt;/ref&gt;

;Joint and separate possession
A distinction is made between ''joint'' possession (''Jason and Sue's e-mails'': the e-mails of both Jason and Sue), and ''separate'' possession (''Jason's and Sue's e-mails'': both the e-mails of Jason and the e-mails of Sue). Style guides differ only in how much detail they provide concerning these.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'', 5.27; ''[[New Hart's Rules]]'', §4.2, p.&amp;nbsp;64; ''Gregg Reference Manual'', §642.&lt;/ref&gt; Their consensus is that if possession is joint, only the last possessor has possessive inflection; in separate possession all the possessors have possessive inflection. If, however, any of the possessors is indicated by a pronoun, then for both joint and separate possession all of the possessors have possessive inflection (''his and her e-mails''; ''his, her, and Anthea's e-mails''; ''Jason's and her e-mails''; ''His and Sue's e-mails''; ''His and Sue's wedding''; ''His and Sue's weddings'').

Note that in cases of joint possession, the above rule does not distinguish between a situation in which only one or more jointly possessed items perform a grammatical role and a situation in which both one or more such items and a non-possessing entity independently perform that role. Although verb number suffices in some cases (&quot;Jason and Sue's dog has porphyria&quot;) and context suffices in others (&quot;Jason and Sue's e-mails rarely exceed 200 characters in length&quot;), number and grammatical position often prevent a resolution of ambiguity:

*Where multiple items are possessed and context is not dispositive, a rule forbidding distribution of the possessive merely ''shifts'' ambiguity: suppose that Jason and Sue had one or more children who died in a car crash and that none of Jason's children by anyone other than Sue were killed. Under a rule forbidding distribution of the joint possessive, writing &quot;Jason and Sue's children [rather than &quot;Jason's and Sue's children&quot;] died in the crash&quot; eliminates the implication that Jason lost children of whom Sue was not the mother, but it ''introduces'' ambiguity as to whether Jason himself was killed.

*Moreover, if only one item is possessed, the rule against distribution of the joint possessive ''introduces'' ambiguity (unless the [[context (language use)|context]] happens to resolve it): read in light of a rule requiring distribution, the sentence &quot;Jason and Sue's dog died after being hit by a bus&quot; makes clear that the dog belonged to Sue alone and that Jason survived or was not involved, whereas a rule prohibiting distribution forces ambiguity as to both whether Jason (co-)owned the dog and whether he was killed.

;With other punctuation; compounds with pronouns{{anchor|With other punctuation; compounds with pronouns}}
If the word or compound includes, or even ends with, a punctuation mark, an apostrophe and an ''s'' are still added in the usual way: &quot;[[Westward Ho!]]'s railway station;&quot; ''Awaye!'s Paulette Whitten recorded Bob Wilson's story'';&lt;ref&gt;This example is quoted from [http://www.abc.net.au/rn/awaye/index/subjects_Music_2007.htm www.abc.net.au]; see ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'', 7.18.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Washington, D.C.'s museums'',&lt;ref&gt;This example is quoted from ''The Gregg Reference Manual'', 10th edition, 2005, paragraph 641.&lt;/ref&gt; assuming that the prevailing style requires full stops in ''D.C.''
* If the word or compound already includes a possessive apostrophe, a double possessive results: ''Tom's sisters' careers''; ''the head of marketing's husband's preference''; ''the [[Fox hunting|master of foxhounds']] best dog's death''. Some style guides, while allowing that these constructions are possible, advise rephrasing: ''the preference of the head of marketing's husband''. If an original apostrophe, or apostrophe with ''s'', occurs at the end, it is left by itself to do double duty: ''Our employees are better paid than McDonald's employees''; ''Standard &amp; Poor's indexes are widely used''; ''the 5uu's first album'' (the fixed forms of ''[[McDonald's]]'' and ''[[Standard &amp; Poor's]]'' already include possessive apostrophes; ''[[5uu's]]'' already has a non-possessive apostrophe before its final&amp;nbsp;''s''). For similar cases involving geographical names, see [[#Possessives in geographic names|below]].
* By extended application of the principles stated above, the possessives of all phrases whose wording is fixed are formed in the same way:
**&quot;[[Us and Them (song)|Us and Them]]&quot;'s inclusion on the album ''[[The Dark Side of the Moon]]''
**[[You Am I]]'s latest CD
** [[The 69'ers]]' drummer, Tom Callaghan (only the second apostrophe is possessive)
**[[His 'n' Hers]]' first track is called &quot;Joyriders&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;This is normal despite the fact that the single word ''hers'' is spelled without an apostrophe, see below in this section; ''His 'n' Hers's first track'' is theoretically possible but unlikely unless an extra sibilant is actually pronounced after ''hrs''.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**Was ''[[She (novel)|She]]''{{'s}} success greater, or ''[[King Solomon's Mines]]''{{'}}?&lt;ref&gt;Most sources{{Who|date=April 2010}} are against continuing the [[italics]] used in such titles to the apostrophe and the ''s''.&lt;/ref&gt;
:For complications with foreign phrases and titles, see [[#Nouns ending with silent &quot;s&quot;, &quot;x&quot;, or &quot;z&quot;|below]].
;Time, money, and similar{{anchor|Time, money, and similar}}
An apostrophe is used in time and money references, among others, in constructions such as ''one hour's respite'', ''two weeks' holiday'', ''a dollar's worth'', ''five pounds' worth'', ''one mile's drive from here''. This is like an ordinary possessive use. For example, ''one hour's respite'' means ''a respite of one hour'' (exactly as ''the cat's whiskers'' means ''the whiskers of the cat''). Exceptions are accounted for in the same way: ''three months pregnant'' (in modern usage, we do not say ''pregnant of three months'', nor ''one month(')s pregnant'').

;Possessive pronouns and adjectives{{anchor|Possessive pronouns and adjectives}}
No apostrophe is used in the following possessive pronouns and adjectives: ''yours'', ''his'', ''hers'', ''ours'', ''its'', ''theirs'', and ''whose''. 

The possessive of ''it'' was originally ''it's'', and many people continue to write it this way, though the apostrophe was dropped in the early 1800s and authorities are now unanimous that ''it's'' can be only a contraction of ''it is'' or ''it has''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=its&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See for example ''[[New Hart's Rules]]''. Not one of the other sources listed on this page supports the use of ''it's'' as a possessive form of ''it''.&lt;/ref&gt;  For example, US President [[Thomas Jefferson]] used ''it's'' as a possessive in his instructions dated 20 June 1803 to Lewis for his preparations for his great expedition.&lt;ref&gt;Frank Bergon,&quot;The Journals of Lewis &amp; Clark&quot;,(Penguin, New York, 1989, pages xxiv foll.&lt;/ref&gt;

All other possessive pronouns ending in ''s'' do take an apostrophe: ''one's''; ''everyone's''; ''somebody's'', ''nobody else's'', etc. With plural forms, the apostrophe follows the ''s'', as with nouns: ''the others' husbands'' (but compare ''They all looked at each other's husbands'', in which both ''each'' and ''other'' are singular).

;Importance for disambiguation{{anchor|Importance for disambiguation}}
Each of these four phrases (listed in [[Steven Pinker]]'s ''[[The Language Instinct]]'') has a distinct meaning:
*My sister's friend's investments ''(the investments belonging to a friend of my sister)''
*My sister's friends' investments ''(the investments belonging to several friends of my sister)''
*My sisters' friend's investments ''(the investments belonging to a friend of several of my sisters)''
*My sisters' friends' investments ''(the investments belonging to several friends of several of my sisters)''

[[Kingsley Amis]], on being challenged to produce a sentence whose meaning depended on a possessive apostrophe, came up with:
*Those things over there are my husband's. (''Those things over there belong to my husband''.)
*Those things over there are my husbands'. (''Those things over there belong to several husbands of mine''.)
*Those things over there are my husbands. (''I'm married to those men over there.'')&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.com.au/couriermail/story/0,23739,21619016-27197,00.html Courier Mail, Little things that matter]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Singular nouns ending with an &quot;s&quot; or &quot;z&quot; sound====
This subsection deals with singular nouns pronounced with a [[sibilant]] sound at the end: /s/ or /z/. The spelling of these ends with ''-s'', ''-se'', ''-z'', ''-ze'', ''-ce'', ''-x'', or ''-xe''.

Many respected authorities recommend that practically all singular nouns, including those ending with a sibilant sound, have possessive forms with an extra ''s'' after the apostrophe so that the spelling reflects the underlying pronunciation. Examples include [[Oxford University Press]], the [[MLA style manual|Modern Language Association]], and ''[[The Economist]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://oxforddictionaries.com/page/punctuationapostrophe Oxford Dictionaries]: &quot;With personal names that end in ''-s'': add an apostrophe plus ''s'' when you would naturally pronounce an extra ''s'' if you said the word out loud&quot;; ''MLA Style Manual'', 2nd edition, 1998, 3.4.7e: &quot;To form the possessive of any singular proper noun, add an apostrophe and an ''s''&quot;; [http://www.economist.com/research/styleGuide/index.cfm?page=841359 The Economist's Style Guide]; ''[[The Elements of Style]]'' makes the same rule, with only sketchily presented exceptions.&lt;/ref&gt; Such authorities demand possessive singulars like these: ''Senator Jones's umbrella''; ''Mephistopheles's cat''. However, some contemporary writers still follow the older practice of omitting the extra ''s'' in all cases ending with a sibilant, but usually not when written ''-x'' or ''-xe''.&lt;ref&gt;According to this older system, possessives of names ending in &quot;-x&quot; or &quot;-xe&quot; were usually spelled without a final &quot;s&quot; even when an /s/ or /z/ was pronounced at the end (e.g. &quot;Alex' brother&quot; instead of &quot;Alex's brother&quot;), but the possessives of nouns (e.g. &quot;the fox's fur&quot;) were usually spelled as today with a final &quot;s&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Some contemporary authorities such as the Associated Press Stylebook&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/brand/styleguide/punctuation.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The Chicago Manual of Style]]'' recommend or allow the practice of omitting the extra &quot;s&quot; in all words ending with an &quot;s&quot;, but not in words ending with other sibilants (&quot;z&quot; and &quot;x&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;''The Chicago Manual of Style''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s text: 7.23 ''An alternative practice.'' Those uncomfortable with the rules, exceptions, and options outlined above may prefer the system, formerly more common, of simply omitting the possessive ''s'' on all words ending in s&amp;nbsp;– hence &quot;Dylan Thomas' poetry,&quot; &quot;Maria Callas' singing,&quot; and &quot;that business' main concern.&quot; Though easy to apply, that usage disregards pronunciation and thus seems unnatural to many.&lt;/ref&gt; The 15th edition of ''The Chicago Manual of Style'' still recommended the traditional practice, which included providing for several exceptions to accommodate spoken usage such as the omission of the extra ''s'' after a polysyllabic word ending in a sibilant. The 16th edition of CMOS no longer recommends omitting the extra &quot;s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/CMS_FAQ/PossessivesandAttributives/PossessivesandAttributives01.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
Rules that modify or extend the standard principle have included the following:
* If the singular possessive is difficult or awkward to pronounce with an added sibilant, do not add an extra ''s''; these exceptions are supported by ''[[The Guardian]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/styleguide/page/0,,184844,00.html The Guardian's Style Guide].&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language|The American Heritage]] Book of English Usage''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/64/82.html The American Heritage Book of English Usage. 8. Word Formation b. Forming Possessives].&lt;/ref&gt; Such sources permit possessive singulars like these: ''Socrates' later suggestion''; ''James's house'', or ''James' house'', depending on which pronunciation is intended.
* Classical, biblical, and similar names ending in a sibilant, especially if they are [[polysyllabic]], do not take an added ''s'' in the possessive; among sources giving exceptions of this kind are ''[[The Times]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2941-560,00.html The Times Online Style Guide].&lt;/ref&gt; and ''The Elements of Style'', which make general stipulations, and [[Vanderbilt University]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vanderbilt.edu/styleguide.pdf Vanderbilt University's Style Guide].&lt;/ref&gt; which mentions only ''[[Moses]]'' and ''[[Jesus]]''. As a particular case, ''Jesus&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''&amp;nbsp; is very commonly written instead of ''Jesus's''&amp;nbsp;– even by people who would otherwise add ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s'' in, for example, ''James's'' or ''Chris's''. ''Jesus&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''&amp;nbsp; is referred to as &quot;an accepted liturgical archaism&quot; in ''[[Hart's Rules]]''.

Similar examples of notable names ending in an ''s'' that are often given a possessive apostrophe with no additional ''s'' include ''Dickens'' and ''Williams''. There is often a policy of leaving off the additional ''s'' on any such name, but this can prove problematic when specific names are contradictory (for example, ''[[St James' Park]]'' in [[Newcastle upon Tyne|Newcastle]] [the football ground] and the area of ''[[St. James's Park]]'' in London). For more details on practice with geographic names, see the relevant section [[Apostrophe#Possessives in geographic names|below]].

Some writers like to reflect standard spoken practice in cases like these with ''sake'': ''for convenience' sake'', ''for goodness' sake'', ''for appearance' sake'', ''for compromise' sake'', etc. This punctuation is preferred in major style guides. Others prefer to add ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s'': ''for convenience's sake''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=DummiesWorld Wide Words|url=http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-app2.htm| accessdate=2007-03-13}}. ''The Chicago Manual of Style'', 7.22: &quot;For...sake expressions traditionally omit the ''s'' when the noun ends in an ''s'' or an ''s'' sound.&quot; ''Oxford Style Manual'', 5.2.1: &quot;Use an apostrophe alone after singular nouns ending in an ''s'' or ''z'' sound and combined with ''sake'': for goodness' sake&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Still others prefer to omit the apostrophe when there is an ''s'' sound before ''sake'': ''for morality's sake'', but ''for convenience sake''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Practice varies widely in ''for conscience' sake'' and ''for goodness' sake'', and the use of an apostrophe in them must be regarded as optional&quot; ''The New Fowler's Modern English Usage'', ed. Burchfield, RW, 3rd edition, 1996, entry for &quot;sake&quot;, p.&amp;nbsp;686.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Nouns ending with silent &quot;s&quot;, &quot;x&quot; or &quot;z&quot;====
The English possessive of French nouns ending in a silent ''s'', ''x'', or ''z'' is rendered differently by different authorities. Some prefer ''Descartes&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' and ''Dumas&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', while others insist on ''Descartes's'' and ''Dumas's''. Certainly a sibilant is pronounced in these cases; the theoretical question is whether the existing final letter is sounded or whether ''s'' needs to be added. Similar examples with ''x'' or ''z'': ''Sauce Périgueux's main ingredient is truffle''; ''His [[pince-nez]]'s loss went unnoticed''; ''&quot;Verreaux('s) eagle, a large, predominantly black eagle, ''Aquila verreauxi'',...&quot;'' ([[OED]], entry for &quot;Verreaux&quot;, with silent ''x''; see [[Verreaux's eagle]]); in each of these some writers might omit the added ''s''. The same principles and residual uncertainties apply with &quot;naturalised&quot; English words, like ''Illinois'' and ''Arkansas''.&lt;ref&gt;In February 2007 Arkansas historian Parker Westbrook successfully petitioned State Representative Steve Harrelson to settle once and for all that the correct possessive should not be ''Arkansas&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' but ''Arkansas's'' ([http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2007/02/27/arkansas_house_to_argue_over_apostrophes/ ''Arkansas House to argue over apostrophes'']). Arkansas's Apostrophe Act came into law in March 2007 (ABC News [USA], 6 March 2007).&lt;/ref&gt;

For possessive ''plurals'' of words ending in silent ''x'', ''z'' or ''s'', the few authorities that address the issue at all typically call for an added ''s'' and require that the apostrophe precede the ''s'': ''The Loucheux's homeland is in the Yukon''; ''Compare the two Dumas's literary achievements''.&lt;ref&gt;An apparent exception is ''The Complete Stylist'', Sheridan Baker, 2nd edition 1972, p.&amp;nbsp;165: &quot;...''citizens' rights'', ''the Joneses' possessions'', and similarly ''The Beaux' Stratagem''.&quot; But in fact the ''x'' in ''beaux'', as in other such plurals in English, is often already pronounced (see a note to [[#Basic rule (plural nouns)|Basic rule (plural nouns)]], above); ''[[The Beaux Stratagem]]'', the title of a play by George Farquhar (1707), originally lacked the apostrophe (see [http://books.google.com/books?id=6AgJAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=%22beaux%27+stratagem%22&amp;num=100#PPA1,M1 the title page] of a 1752 edition); and it is complicated by the following ''s'' in ''stratagem''. Some modern editions add the apostrophe (some with an ''s'' also), some omit it; and some make a compound with a hyphen: ''The Beaux-Stratagem''. Farquhar himself used the apostrophe elsewhere in the standard ways, for both omission and possession.&lt;/ref&gt; The possessive of a cited French title with a silent plural ending is uncertain: &quot;''Trois femmes's'' long and complicated publication history&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Jacqueline Letzter, ''Intellectual Tacking: Questions of Education in the Works of Isabelle de Charrière'', Rodopi, 1998, p.&amp;nbsp;123.&lt;/ref&gt; but &quot;''Les noces&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' singular effect was 'exotic primitive'...&quot; (with nearby sibilants ''-ce-'' in ''noces'' and ''s-'' in ''singular'').&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth A. McAlister, ''Rara!: Vodou, Power, and Performance in Haiti and Its Diaspora'', University of California Press, 2002, p.&amp;nbsp;196.&lt;/ref&gt; Compare treatment of other titles, [[#With other punctuation; compounds with pronouns|above]].

Guides typically seek a principle that will yield uniformity, even for foreign words that fit awkwardly with standard English punctuation.

==== Possessives in geographic names ====&lt;!-- This section is linked from Apostrophe --&gt;
Place names in the United States generally do not use the possessive apostrophe on federal maps and signs.&lt;ref name=TimesGeo&gt;{{cite news |title=Apostrophe Cops: Don't Be So Possessive |author= |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/03/10/magazine/sunday-march-10-1996-apostrophe-cops-don-t-be-so-possessive.html |newspaper=The ''[[New York Times]]'' (Sunday Magazine) |date=March 10, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Board on Geographic Names]], which has responsibility for formal naming of municipalities and geographic features, has deprecated the use of possessive apostrophes since 1890 so as not to show ownership of the place.&lt;ref name=TimesGeo/&gt;&lt;ref name=TheBoard/&gt; Only five names of natural features in the U.S. are officially spelled with a genitive apostrophe (one example being [[Martha's Vineyard]]).&lt;ref name=TheBoard&gt;[http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/faqs.htm#18 U.S. Board on Geographic Names: FAQs]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cavella, C, and Kernodle, RA, &quot;[http://www.american.edu/tesol/wpkernodlecavella.pdf How the Past Affects the Future: the Story of the Apostrophe]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;

On the other hand, the United Kingdom has [[Bishop's Stortford]], [[Bishop's Castle]] and [[King's Lynn]] (but [[St Albans]], [[St Andrews]] and [[St Helens, Merseyside|St Helens]] possibly because their names date to before the use was formalised{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}) and, while [[Newcastle United F.C.|Newcastle United]] play at [[St James' Park]], and [[Exeter City]] at [[St James Park, Exeter|St James Park]], [[London]] has a [[St James's Park]] (this whole area of London is named after [[St James's Church, Piccadilly]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.st-james-piccadilly.org/ St James's Church Piccadilly website]&lt;/ref&gt;). The special circumstances of the latter case may be this: the customary pronunciation of this place name is reflected in the addition of an extra ''-s''; since usage is firmly against a doubling of the final ''-s'' without an apostrophe, this place name has an apostrophe. This could be regarded{{Who|date=August 2011}} as an example of a double genitive: it refers to the park ''of'' the church ''of'' St James.

Omission of the apostrophe in geographical names is becoming standard in some English-speaking countries, including Australia.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The apostrophe has been dropped from most Australian place-names and street names: ''Connells Point''; ''Wilsons Promontory''; ''Browns Lane''.&quot; ''The Penguin Working Words: an Australian Guide to Modern English Usage'', Penguin, 1993, p.&amp;nbsp;41.&lt;/ref&gt; Modern usage has been influenced by considerations of technological convenience including the economy of typewriter ribbons and films, and similar computer character &quot;disallowance&quot; which tend to ignore traditional canons of correctness.&lt;ref&gt;E.g., under [http://support.microsoft.com/kb/909264 Naming conventions in Active Directory for computers, domains, sites, and OUs] at Microsoft Support&lt;/ref&gt; Practice in the United Kingdom and Canada is not so uniform.&lt;ref&gt;''The Cambridge Guide to English Usage'', Ed. Peters, P, 2004, p.&amp;nbsp;43.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Possessives in names of organizations====
Sometimes the apostrophe is omitted in the names of clubs, societies, and other organizations, even though the standard principles seem to require it: ''[[Country Women's Association]]'', but ''International Aviation {{sic|Wom|ens|hide=yes}} Association'';&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iawa.org International Aviation Womens Association]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Magistrates' Court of Victoria]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Spelled both with and without the apostrophe at [http://www.magistratescourt.vic.gov.au the court's own home page]; but spelled with the apostrophe in Victorian legislation, such as [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/vic/consol_act/mca1989214/ Magistrates' Court Act, 1989].&lt;/ref&gt; but ''[[Federated Ship Painters and Dockers Union]]''. Usage is variable and inconsistent. Style guides typically advise consulting an official source for the standard form of the name; some tend towards greater prescriptiveness, for or against such an apostrophe.&lt;ref&gt;''Gregg Reference Manual'', 10th edition, 2003, distinguishes between what it calls ''possessive'' and ''descriptive'' forms, and uses this distinction in analyzing the problem. From paragraph&amp;nbsp;628: &quot;a.&amp;nbsp;Do not mistake a descriptive form ending in ''s'' for a possessive form[:] sales effort (sales describes the kind of effort)... b.&amp;nbsp;Some cases can be difficult to distinguish. Is it ''the girls basketball team'' or ''the girls' basketball team?'' Try substituting an irregular plural like ''women''. You would not say ''the women basketball team''; you would say ''the women's basketball team''. By analogy, ''the girls' basketball team'' is correct&quot; [italics given exactly as in original, including following punctuation]. And then this principle is applied to organizations at paragraph&amp;nbsp;640, where examples are given, including the non-conforming ''Childrens Hospital, (in Los Angeles)'': &quot;The names of many organizations, products, and publications contain words that could be considered either possessive or descriptive terms... c. In all cases follow the organization's preference when known.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; As the case of ''{{sic|wom|ens|hide=yes}}'' shows, it is not possible to analyze these forms simply as non-possessive plurals, since ''women'' is the only correct plural form of ''woman''.

====Possessives in business names====
{{See also|S-form}}
Where a business name is based on a family name it should take an apostrophe, but many leave it out (contrast ''[[Sainsbury's]]'' with ''[[Harrods]]''). In recent times there has been an increasing tendency to drop the apostrophe. Names based on a first name are more likely to take an apostrophe (''Joe's Crab Shack''). Some business names may inadvertently spell a different name if the name with an ''s'' at the end is also a name, such as Parson.
A small activist group called the [[Apostrophe Protection Society]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apostrophe.org.uk Apostrophe Protection Society's website.]&lt;/ref&gt; has campaigned for large retailers such as Harrods, [[Currys]], and [[Selfridges]] to reinstate their missing punctuation. A spokesperson for [[Barclays PLC]] stated, &quot;It has just disappeared over the years. Barclays is no longer associated with the family name.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Times&quot;&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2-2321813.html#Scene_1 Times Online: Harrods told to put its apostrophe back].&lt;/ref&gt; Further confusion can be caused by businesses whose names tend to look like they are pronounced differently without an apostrophe such as [[Paulos Circus]], and other companies that leave the apostrophe out of their logos but include it in written text, such as [[Waterstone's]] and [[Cadwalader's]].

===Apostrophe showing omission===
An apostrophe is commonly used to indicate omitted characters, normally letters:

* It is used in [[contraction (grammar)|contractions]], such as ''can't'' from ''cannot'', ''it's'' from ''it is'' or ''it has'', and ''I'll'' from ''I will'' or ''I shall''.&lt;ref&gt;In reports of very informal speech ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s'' may sometimes represent ''does'': &quot;Where's that come from?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* It is used in [[abbreviation]]s, as ''gov't'' for ''government''. It may indicate omitted numbers where the spoken form is also capable of omissions, as ''{{'}}70s'' for ''1970s'' representing ''seventies'' for ''nineteen-seventies''. In modern usage, apostrophes are generally omitted when letters are removed from the start of a word, particularly for a [[compound word]]. For example, it is not common to write ''{{'}}bus'' (for ''omnibus''), ''{{'}}phone'' (''telephone''), ''{{'}}net'' (''Internet''). However, if the shortening is unusual, dialectal or archaic, the apostrophe may still be used to mark it (e.g., ''{{'}}bout'' for ''about'', ''{{'}}less'' for ''unless'', ''{{'}}twas'' for ''it was''). Sometimes a misunderstanding of the original form of a word results in an incorrect contraction. A common example: ''{{'}}til'' for ''until'', though ''till'' is in fact the original form, and ''until'' is derived from it.
** The spelling ''fo'c's'le'', contracted from the nautical term ''forecastle'', is unusual for having three apostrophes. The spelling ''bo's'n's'' (from ''boatswain's''), as in ''Bo's'n's Mate'', also has three apostrophes, two showing omission and one possession. ''Fo'c's'le'' may also take a possessive ''s''&amp;nbsp;– as in ''the fo'c's'le's timbers''&amp;nbsp;– giving four apostrophes in one word.&lt;ref&gt;[[SOED]] gives ''fo'c's'le'' as the only shortened form of ''forecastle'', though others are shown in [[OED]]. SOED gives ''bo's'n'' as one spelling of ''bosun'', itself a variant of ''boatswain''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* It is sometimes used when the normal form of an inflection seems awkward or unnatural; for example, ''KO'd'' rather than ''KOed'' (where ''KO'' is used as a verb meaning &quot;to knock out&quot;); &quot;''a spare pince-nez'd man''&quot; (cited in [[OED]], entry for &quot;pince-nez&quot;; ''pince-nezed'' is also in citations).
* In certain colloquial contexts, an apostrophe's function as possessive or contractive can depend on other punctuation.
**We rehearsed for Friday's opening night. (''We rehearsed for the opening night on Friday.'')
**We rehearsed, for Friday's opening night. (''We rehearsed because Friday is opening night.'' &quot;Friday's&quot; here is a contraction of &quot;Friday is.&quot;)
* [[Eye dialect]]s use apostrophes in creating the effect of a non-standard pronunciation.

===Use in forming certain plurals===
An apostrophe is used by some writers to form a [[English plural|plural]] for abbreviations, [[acronym]]s, and symbols where adding just ''s'' rather than '''s'' may leave things ambiguous or inelegant. Some specific cases:
* It is generally acceptable to use apostrophes to show plurals of single lower-case letters,{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} such as ''be sure to dot your i's and cross your t's''. Some style guides would prefer to use a change of font: ''dot your'' i''s and cross your'' t''s.''{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} Some style guides rule that upper case letters need no apostrophe (''I got three As in my exams''&lt;ref name=&quot;owl&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Purdue University Online Writing Lab: The Apostrophe |url=http://owl.english.purdue.edu/handouts/grammar/g_apost.html| accessdate=2007-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;) except when there is a risk of misreading, such as at the start of a sentence: ''A's are the highest marks achievable in these exams.''
* For groups of years, the apostrophe at the end may be regarded as unnecessary, since there is no possibility of misreading. For this reason, some style guides prefer ''1960s'' to ''1960's''&lt;ref name=&quot;owl&quot;/&gt; (although the latter is noted by at least one source as acceptable in American usage),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cogs.susx.ac.uk/doc/punctuation/node21.html Guide to Punctuation], Larry Trask, University of Sussex: &quot;American usage, however, does put an apostrophe here: (A) This research was carried out in the 1970's.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and ''90s'' or ''{{'}}90s'' to ''90's'' or ''{{'}}90's''.
* The apostrophe is sometimes used in forming the plural of numbers (for example, ''1000's of years''); however, as with groups of years, it is unnecessary because there is no possibility of misreading.  Most sources are against this usage.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}
* The apostrophe is often used in plurals of symbols. Again, since there can be no misreading, this is often regarded as incorrect.&lt;ref name=&quot;owl&quot;/&gt; ''That page has too many &amp;s and #s on it.''{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

===Use in non-English names===
Names that are not strictly native to English sometimes have an apostrophe substituted to represent other characters (see also [[#As a mark of elision|As a mark of elision]], below).
* Anglicised versions of Irish surnames often contain an apostrophe after an ''O'', for example ''O'Doole''.
* Some [[Scots language|Scottish]] and [[Irish name|Irish]] surnames use an apostrophe after an ''M'', for example ''M'Gregor''. The apostrophe here may be seen as marking a contraction where the prefix ''Mc'' or ''[[Irish surname prefixes|Mac]]'' would normally appear. (In earlier and meticulous current usage, the symbol is actually &lt;span style=font-family:serif&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt; – a kind of reversed apostrophe that is sometimes called a ''turned comma'', which eventually came to be written as the letter ''c'', whose shape is similar.){{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}
* In [[science fiction]], the apostrophe is often used in alien names, sometimes to indicate a [[glottal stop]] (for example [[T'Pau (Star Trek)|T'Pau]] in ''[[Star Trek]]''), but also sometimes simply for decoration.

===Use in transliteration&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;s===
In [[Transliteration|transliterated]] foreign words, an apostrophe may be used to separate letters or syllables that otherwise would likely be interpreted incorrectly. For example:
*in the [[Arabic (language)|Arabic]] word ''[[mus'haf]]'', a transliteration of {{script|Arab|مصحف}}, the syllables are as in ''mus·haf'', not ''mu·shaf''
*in the [[Japanese (language)|Japanese]] name ''[[Shin'ichi]]'', the apostrophe shows that the pronunciation is ''shi·n·i·chi'' ([[hiragana]] {{nihongo2|しんいち}}), where the letters ''n'' ({{nihongo2|ん}}) and ''i'' ({{nihongo2|い}}) are separate [[mora (linguistics)|moras]], rather than ''shi·ni·chi'' ({{nihongo2|しにち}}).
*in the Chinese [[Pinyin]] romanization, when two [[hanzi]] are combined to form one word, if the resulting Pinyin representation can be mis-interpreted they should be separated by an apostrophe.  For example, 先 (xiān) 西安 (xī'ān).
Furthermore, an apostrophe may be used to indicate a [[glottal stop]] in transliterations. For example:
*in the Arabic word ''[[Qur'an]]'', a common transliteration of (part of) {{script|Arab|القرآن}} ''al-qur'ān'', the apostrophe corresponds to the letter [[hamza]], one of the letters in the [[Arabic alphabet]].

===Non-standard English use===
Failure to observe standard use of the apostrophe is widespread and frequently criticised as incorrect,&lt;ref&gt;Truss, Lynne. ''Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves''. p.&amp;nbsp;41, pp.&amp;nbsp;48–54.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=HoBS/&gt; often generating heated debate. The British founder of the [[Apostrophe Protection Society]] earned a 2001 [[Ig Nobel|Ig&amp;nbsp;Nobel]] prize for &quot;efforts to protect, promote and defend the differences between plural and possessive&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/1581086.stm &quot;In praise of apostrophes&quot;], BBC News, 5 October 2001&lt;/ref&gt; A 2004 report by [[OCR (examination board)|OCR]], a British examination board, stated that &quot;the inaccurate use of the apostrophe is so widespread as to be almost universal&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/education/3979765.stm 'Fatal floors' in exam scripts], BBC News, 3 November 2004&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 survey found that nearly half of the UK adults polled were unable to use the apostrophe correctly.&lt;ref name=HoBS&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/3418036/Half-of-Britons-struggle-with-the-apostrophe.html Half of Britons struggle with the apostrophe], ''The Daily Telegraph'', 11 November 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===={{anchor|Greengrocers' apostrophe}}{{anchor|Greengrocers' apostrophes}} Superfluous apostrophes (&quot;greengrocers' apostrophes&quot;)====
[[Image:Green Craig's.jpg|thumb|right|Sign to Green Craigs housing development]]
Apostrophes used in a non-standard manner to form [[noun]] [[plural]]s are known as ''greengrocers' apostrophes'' or ''grocers' apostrophes'', often called (spelled) ''greengrocer's apostrophes''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wordspy.com/words/greengrocersapostrophe.asp]&lt;/ref&gt; and ''grocer's apostrophes''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/styleguide/a#id-3016449]&lt;/ref&gt; They are sometimes humorously called ''greengrocers apostrophe's'', ''rogue apostrophes'', or ''idiot's apostrophes'' (a literal translation of the German word ''Deppenapostroph'', which criticises the misapplication of apostrophes in [[Denglisch]]). The practice, once common and acceptable (see [[#Historical development|Historical development]]), comes from the identical sound of the [[plural]] and [[possessive case|possessive]] forms of most English [[noun]]s. It is often criticised as a form of [[hypercorrection]] coming from a widespread ignorance of the proper use of the apostrophe or of punctuation in general. [[Lynne Truss]], author of ''[[Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves]]'', points out that before the 19th century, it was standard orthography to use the apostrophe to form a plural of a foreign-sounding word that ended in a vowel (e.g., ''banana's'', ''folio's'', ''logo's'', ''quarto's'', ''pasta's'', ''ouzo's'') to clarify pronunciation. Truss says this usage is no longer considered proper in formal writing.&lt;ref&gt;Truss, Lynne. ''Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves''. pp.&amp;nbsp;63–65.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is believed to have been coined in the middle of the 20th century by a teacher of languages working in [[Liverpool]], at a time when such mistakes were common in the handwritten signs and advertisements of [[greengrocer]]s (e.g., ''Apple's [[shilling|1/-]] a pound, Orange's 1/6[[penny|d]] a pound''). Some have argued that its use in mass communication by employees of well-known companies has led to the less literate assuming it to be correct and adopting the habit themselves.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal
| author = Christina Cavella and Robin A. Kernodle
| title = How the Past Affects the Future: The Story of the Apostrophe
| version =
| publisher = American University
| date =
| url = http://www.american.edu/tesol/wpkernodlecavella.pdf
| format = PDF
| accessdate = 2006-10-26}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The same use of apostrophe before [[noun]] [[plural]] -s forms  is sometimes made by non-native speakers of English. For example, in Dutch, the apostrophe is inserted before the ''s'' when pluralising most words ending in a vowel or ''y''' for example, ''baby's'' (English ''babies'') and ''jury's'' (English ''juries''). This often produces so-called &quot;[[Dunglish]]&quot; errors when carried over into English.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Righting English That's Gone Dutch|chapter=Dutch Greengrocers|p=39–40|first=Joy|last=Burrough-Boenisch|edition=2nd|publisher=Kemper Conseil Publishing|year=2004|isbn=9789076542089|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hyperforeignism]] has been formalised in some pseudo-[[anglicism]]s. For example, the French word [[:fr:pin's|pin's]] (from English ''pin'') is used (with the apostrophe in both singular and plural) for [[collectable]] [[lapel pin]]s. Similarly, there is an [[Andorra]]n football club called [[FC Rànger's]] (after such British clubs as [[Rangers F.C.]]), a Japanese dance group called [[Super Monkey's]], and a Japanese [[pop punk]] band called the ''Titan Go King's''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nippop.com/artist/artist_id-155/artist_name-titan_go_king_s Titan Go King's, at nippop.com].&lt;/ref&gt;

The widespread use of apostrophes before the ''s'' of plural nouns has led some {{Who|date=July 2010}} to believe, incorrectly, that an apostrophe is also needed before the ''s'' of the third-person present tense of a verb. Thus, ''he take's'', ''it begin's'', etc.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

====Omission====
There is a tendency to drop apostrophes in many commonly used names such as [[Lytham St Annes|St Annes]], St Johns Lane,&lt;ref&gt;A search on www.multimpap.com for &quot;St Johns Lane&quot; in the UK, with or without apostrophe, finds the apostrophe omitted in 5 instances out of 25&lt;/ref&gt; and so on.

In 2009, a resident in [[Royal Tunbridge Wells]] was accused of [[vandalism]] after he painted apostrophes on road signs that had spelt ''St John's Close'' as ''St Johns Close''.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Colin, [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1207301/Punctuation-hero-branded-vandal-inserting-apostrophes-street-signs.html 'Punctuation hero' branded a vandal for painting apostrophes on street signs], ''[[The Daily Mail]]'', accessed 19 August 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

UK supermarket chain [[Tesco]] omits the mark where standard practice would require it. Signs in Tesco advertise (among other items) {{typo|&quot;mens magazines&quot;, &quot;girls toys&quot;, &quot;kids books&quot; and &quot;womens shoes&quot;}}. In his book ''[[Bryson's Dictionary of Troublesome Words|Troublesome Words]]'', author [[Bill Bryson]] lambasts Tesco for this, stating that &quot;the mistake is inexcusable, and those who make it are linguistic Neanderthals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bill Bryson, &quot;Troublesome Words,&quot; Penguin, second edition 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;177&lt;/ref&gt;

====Advocates of greater or lesser use====
[[File:Greengrocer's apostrophe correction.jpg|thumb|A sign diverting passengers to a temporary [[taxi rank]] at [[Leeds railway station]], [[West Yorkshire]], [[United Kingdom]], with the extraneous apostrophe crossed out by an unknown copy editor]]
[[George Bernard Shaw]], a proponent of English [[spelling reform]] on phonetic principles, argued that the apostrophe was mostly redundant. He did not use it for spelling ''cant'', ''hes'', etc. in many of his writings. He did however allow ''I'm'' and ''it's''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wwnorton.com/nto/20century/topic_4/shaw.htm W. W. Norton &amp; Company]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hubert Selby, Jr.]] used a slash instead of an apostrophe mark for contractions and did not use an apostrophe at all for possessives. [[Lewis Carroll]] made greater use of apostrophes, and frequently used ''sha'n't'', with an apostrophe in place of the elided &quot;ll&quot; as well as the more usual &quot;o&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dace.co.uk/apostrophe.htm The apostrophe&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Neither author's use has become widespread.

====Other misuses====
The British pop group [[Hear'Say]] famously made unconventional use of an apostrophe in its name. Truss comments that &quot;the naming of Hear'Say in 2001 was [...] a significant milestone on the road to punctuation anarchy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dexys Midnight Runners]], on the other hand, omit the apostrophe (though &quot;dexys&quot; can be understood as a plural form of &quot;dexy&quot;, rather than a possessive form).

An apostrophe wrongly thought to be misused in popular culture occurs in the name of [[Liverpudlian]] rock band [[The La's]]. This apostrophe is often thought to be a mistake; but in fact it marks omission of the letter ''d''. The name comes from the [[Scouse]] [[slang]] for &quot;The Lads&quot;.

===Criticism===
Over the years, the use of apostrophes has been criticized. [[George Bernard Shaw]] called them &quot;uncouth bacilli&quot;. In his book, ''American Speech'', linguist Steven Byington stated of the apostrophe that &quot;the language would be none the worse for its abolition.&quot; Adrian Room in his ''[[English Journal]]'' article &quot;Axing the Apostrophe&quot; argued that apostrophes are unnecessary and context will resolve any ambiguity. Again in an ''English Journal'' article, Peter Brodie stated that apostrophes are &quot;largely decorative [and] rarely clarify meaning&quot;. Dr. [[John C. Wells]], Emeritus Professor of Phonetics at [[University College London]], says the apostrophe is &quot;a waste of time&quot;. [[Peter Buck]], guitarist of [[R.E.M.]], claimed, apparently forgetful of ''[[Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band]]'', &quot;We all hate apostrophes. There's never been a good rock album that's had an apostrophe in the title.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grammar.about.com/b/2008/10/29/the-long-campaign-to-abolish-the-apostrophe.htm|title=The Long Campaign to Abolish the Apostrophe|last=Nordquist|first=Richard|date=29 October 2008|publisher=About.com|accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-English use==
=== As a mark of elision ===
In many languages, especially European languages, the apostrophe is used to indicate the [[elision]] of one or more sounds, as in English.
* In [[Afrikaans]] the apostrophe is used to show that letters have been omitted from words. The most common use is in the indefinite article ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;n'', which is a contraction of ''een'' meaning &quot;one&quot; (the number). As the initial ''e'' is omitted and cannot be capitalised, if a sentence begins with ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;n'' the second word in the sentence is capitalised. For example: ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;n Boom is groen'', &quot;A tree is green&quot;. In addition, the apostrophe is used for plurals and diminutives where the root ends with certain [[vowel]]s, e.g. ''foto's'', ''taxi's'', ''Lulu's'', ''Lulu'tjie'', ''garage's'' etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| last =
| author-link = http://www.nb.co.za/listing/taalkommissie-van-die-sa-akademie-vir-wetenskap-en-kuns/676/
| last2 =
| first2 =
| author2-link =
| title = Afrikaanse Woordelys en Spelreëls
| place = Cape Town, South Africa
| publisher = Pharos Woordeboeke
| year = 2002
| volume =
| edition = 9th
| url = http://www.nb.co.za/product/afrikaanse-woordelys-en-spelre-ls----de-uitgawe/7390/
| doi =
| id =
| isbn = 1 86890 034 7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Danish language|Danish]], apostrophes are sometimes seen on [[Advertising|commercial]] materials. One might commonly see ''Ta' mig med'' (&quot;Take me with [you]&quot;) next to a stand with advertisement leaflets; that would be written ''Tag mig med'' in standard orthography. As in [[German language|German]], the apostrophe must not be used to indicate the possessive, except when there is already an ''s'' present in the base form, as in ''Lukas' bog''.
* In [[Dutch language|Dutch]], the apostrophe is used to indicate omitted characters. For example, the indefinite article ''een'' can be shortened to ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;n'', and the definite article ''het'' shortened to ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;t''. When this happens in the first word of a sentence, the ''second'' word of the sentence is capitalised. In general, this way of using the apostrophe is considered non-standard, except in ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s morgens'', ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s middags'', ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s avonds'', ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s nachts'' (for ''des morgens, des middags, des avonds, des nachts'': &quot;at morning, at afternoon, at evening, at night&quot;). In addition, the apostrophe is used for plurals where the singulars end with certain [[vowel]]s, e.g. ''foto's'', ''taxi's''; and for the genitive of proper names ending with these vowels, e.g. ''Anna's'', ''Otto's''. These are in fact elided vowels; use of the apostrophe prevents spellings like ''fotoos'' and ''Annaas''.
* The [[Fundamento de Esperanto]] limits the elision mark to the definite article ''&lt;nowiki&gt;l'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' (from ''la'') and singular nominative nouns (''&lt;nowiki&gt;kor'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' from ''koro'', &quot;heart&quot;). This is mostly confined to poetry. Non-standard ''&lt;nowiki&gt;dank'&lt;/nowiki&gt; al'' (from ''danke al'', &quot;thanks to&quot;) and ''&lt;nowiki&gt;del'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' (from ''de la'', &quot;of the&quot;) are nonetheless frequent. In-word elision is usually marked with a [[hyphen]], as in ''D-ro'' (from ''doktoro'', &quot;Dr&quot;). Some early guides used and advocated the use of apostrophes between word parts, to aid recognition of such [[compound word]]s as ''&lt;nowiki&gt;gitar'ist'o&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', &quot;guitarist&quot;.
* In [[Catalan language|Catalan]], [[French language|French]], [[Italian language|Italian]] and [[Occitan language|Occitan]] word sequences such as ''[[coup d'état|(coup) d'état]]'', ''[[Maître d|(maître) d'hôtel]]'' (often shortened to ''maître d{{'}}'', when used in English), ''[[L'Aquila]]'' and ''[[L'Hospitalet de Llobregat]]'' the final vowel in the first word (''de'' &quot;of&quot;, ''la'' &quot;the&quot;, etc.) is elided because the word that follows it starts with a vowel or a [[H|mute h]]. Similarly, French has ''qu'il'' instead of ''que il'' (&quot;that he&quot;), ''c'est'' instead of ''ce est'' (&quot;it is or it's&quot;), and so on. Catalan, French, Italian and Occitan surnames sometimes contain apostrophes of elision, e.g. ''d'Alembert'', ''D'Angelo''.
* French feminine singular possessive adjectives do not undergo elision, but change to the masculine form instead: ''ma'' preceding ''église'' becomes ''mon église'' (&quot;my church&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;In early French such elisions did occur: ''m'espée'' (''ma''&amp;nbsp;+''espée'', modern French ''mon épée'': &quot;my sword&quot;), ''s'enfance'' (''sa''&amp;nbsp;+''enfance'', ''son enfance'': &quot;his or her childhood&quot;). But the only modern survivals of this elision with apostrophe are ''m'amie'' and ''m'amour'', as archaic and idiomatic alternatives to ''mon amie'' and ''mon amour'' (&quot;my [female] friend&quot;, &quot;my love&quot;); forms without the apostrophe also used: ''mamie'' or ''ma mie'', ''mamour''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] the apostrophe is also used in some few combinations such as ''caixa-d'água'' (&quot;water tower&quot;), ''galinha-d'angola'' (&quot;Helmeted Guineafowl&quot;), ''pau-d'alho'' (&quot;''Gallesia integrifolia''&quot;), etc. Portuguese has many contractions between prepositions and articles or pronouns (like ''na'' for ''en'' + ''a''), but these are written without an apostrophe.  Portuguese uses a grave accent to indicate an unstressed ''a'' has been elided with a following stressed one, so one writes (and says) ''àquela hora'' instead of ''a aquela hora''.
*  Modern [[Spanish language|Spanish]] no longer uses the apostrophe to indicate elision in standard writing, although it can sometimes be found in older poetry for that purpose.&lt;ref&gt;Examples include ''Nuestras vidas son los ríos / que van a dar en la mar, / qu'es el morir.'' meaning &quot;Our lives are the rivers / that flow to give to the sea, / which is death.&quot; (from ''Coplas de Don Jorge Manrique por la muerte de su padre'', 1477) and ''¿ ... qué me ha de aprovechar ver la pintura / d'aquel que con las alas derretidas ...?'' meaning &quot;... what could it help me to see the painting of that one with the melted wings ...?&quot; (from the 12th sonnet of Garcilazo de la Vega, c. 1500–1536).&lt;/ref&gt; Instead Spanish writes out the spoken elision in full (''de enero'', ''mi hijo'') except for the contraction ''del'' for ''de'' + ''el'', which uses no apostrophe. Spanish also switches to the masculine article immediately before a feminine noun beginning with a stressed ''a'' instead of writing (or saying) an elision: ''un águila blanca'', ''el águila blanca'', and ''el agua pura'' but ''una/la blanca águila'' and ''la pura agua''. This reflects the origin of the Spanish definite articles from the Latin demonstratives ''ille/illa/illum''.  Although forms with an apostrophe indicating elision, especially ''m'ijo'' and ''mi'ija'' for ''mi hijo'' and ''mi hija'', can be found in informal writing, this is considered nonstandard.
* [[German language|German]] usage is very similar: an apostrophe is used almost exclusively to indicate omitted letters. It must not be used for plurals or most of the possessive forms (''Max' Vater'' [Max's father] being one of very few exceptions); although both usages are widespread, they are deemed incorrect. The German equivalent of ''greengrocers' apostrophes'' would be the derogatory ''Deppenapostroph'' (&quot;idiots' apostrophe&quot;  (See the article [[:de:Apostrophitis|Apostrophitis]] in German Wikipedia).
* In modern printings of [[Ancient Greek]], apostrophes are also used to mark elision. Certain Ancient Greek words that end in short vowels elide when the next word starts with a vowel. For example, many Ancient Greek authors would write δ’ ἄλλος  (''d'állos'') for δὲ ἄλλος (''dè állos'') and ἆρ’ οὐ (''âr' ou'') for ἆρα οὐ (''âra ou'').
* Initialisms in [[Hebrew]] are denoted with a [[geresh]], often typed as an apostrophe. A double geresh (״), known by the plural form [[gershayim]], is used to denote [[acronyms]]; it is inserted before (i.e., to the right of) the last letter of the acronym.
* In [[Irish language|Irish]], the past tense of verbs beginning with an F or vowel begins with ''d' ''(elision of ''do''), for example ''do oscail'' becomes ''d'oscail'' (&quot;opened&quot;) and ''do fhill'' becomes ''d'fhill'' (&quot;returned&quot;). The copula ''is'' is often elided to '''s'', and ''do'' (&quot;to&quot;), ''mo'' (&quot;my&quot;) etc. are elided before ''f'' and vowels.
* In [[Luganda|Ganda]], when a word ending with a [[vowel]] is followed by a word beginning with a vowel, the final vowel of the first word is [[elision|elided]] and the initial vowel of the second word [[vowel length|lengthened]] in compensation. When the first word is a [[monosyllable]], this elision is represented in the orthography with an apostrophe: in ''taata w'abaana'' &quot;the father of the children&quot;, ''wa'' (&quot;of&quot;) becomes&amp;nbsp;''w&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''; in ''y'ani?'' (&quot;who is it?&quot;), ''ye'' (&quot;who&quot;) becomes&amp;nbsp;''y&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''. But the final vowel of a [[polysyllable]] is always written, even if it is elided in speech: ''omusajja oyo'' (&quot;this man&quot;), not *''omusajj'oyo'', because ''omusajja'' (&quot;man&quot;) is a polysyllable.
* In [[Norwegian (language)|Norwegian]], the apostrophe marks that a word has been contracted, such as &quot;ha'kke&quot; from &quot;har ikke&quot; (have not). Unlike [[English language|English]] and [[French language|French]], such elisions are not accepted as part of standardised orthography but used to create a more &quot;oral style&quot; in writing. The apostrophe is also used to mark the genitive for words that end in an -s sound:  words ending in -s, -x, and -z, some speakers also including words ending in the sound {{IPA-no|ʃ|}}. (As Norwegian forms the plural without -s, there is no need, unlike [[English language|English]], to distinguish between the -s forming the genitive and the -s forming the plural.) Usually the genitive is created by adding an -s to a word, so that &quot;mann&quot; (man) manns (man's). If the word already ends in an s, instead of adding in s, an apostrophe is added: los (naval pilot) los' (naval pilot's). Former American Presidents [[George Bush]] could be seen having the dual genitives Bushs and Bush'.
* [[Welsh language|Welsh]] uses the apostrophe to mark elision of the definite article ''yr'' (&quot;the&quot;) following a vowel (a, e, i, o, u, y, w in Welsh), such as ''i'r tŷ'' &quot;to the house&quot;. It is also used with the particle ''yn'', such as with ''mae hi'n'' &quot;she is&quot;.

===To separate morphemes===
Some languages use the apostrophe to separate the [[root (linguistics)|root]] of a word and its [[affix]]es, especially if the root is foreign and unassimilated. (For another kind of morphemic separation see [[#Miscellaneous uses in other languages|pinyin]], below.)

* In [[Danish language|Danish]] an apostrophe is sometimes used to join the [[enclitic]] [[definite article]] to words of foreign origin, or to other words that would otherwise look awkward. For example, one would write ''IP'en'' to mean &quot;the [[IP address]]&quot;. There is some variation in what is considered &quot;awkward enough&quot; to warrant an apostrophe; for instance, long-established words such as ''firma'' (&quot;company&quot;) or ''niveau'' (&quot;level&quot;) might be written ''firma'et'' and ''niveau'et'', but will generally be seen without an apostrophe. Due to Danish influence, this usage of the apostrophe can also be seen in Norwegian, but is incorrect – a hyphen should be used instead: e.g. CD-en (the CD).
* In [[Finnish language|Finnish]], apostrophes are used in the declension of foreign names or loan words that end in a consonant when written but are pronounced with a vowel ending, e.g. ''show'ssa'' (&quot;in a show&quot;), ''Bordeaux'hun'' (&quot;to Bordeaux&quot;). For Finnish as well as [[Swedish language|Swedish]], there is a closely related [[Colon (punctuation)#Word-medial separator|use of the colon]].
* In [[Estonian language|Estonian]], apostrophes can be used in the declension of some foreign names to separate the stem from any [[declension]] endings; e.g., ''Monet&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' ([[genitive case]]) or ''Monet'sse'' ([[illative case]]) of ''Monet'' (name of the famous painter).
* In [[Polish language|Polish]], the apostrophe is used exclusively for marking inflections of words and word-like elements (but not [[acronyms]] – a hyphen is used instead) whose spelling conflicts with the normal rules of inflection. This mainly affects foreign words and names. For instance, one would correctly write ''Kampania Ala Gore'a'' for &quot;[[Al Gore]]'s campaign&quot;. In this example, ''Ala'' is spelt without an apostrophe, since its spelling and pronunciation fit into normal Polish rules; but ''Gore'a'' needs the apostrophe, because ''e'' disappears from the pronunciation, changing the inflection pattern. This rule is often misunderstood as calling for an apostrophe after ''all'' foreign words, regardless of their pronunciation, yielding the incorrect ''Kampania Al'a Gore'a'', for example. The effect is akin to the greengrocers' apostrophe (see above).
* In [[Turkish language|Turkish]], [[Noun#Proper nouns and common nouns|proper nouns]] are capitalized and an apostrophe is inserted between the noun and any following [[suffix]], e.g. ''İstanbul'da'' (&quot;in [[Istanbul]]&quot;), contrasting with ''okulda'' (&quot;in school&quot;).
* In [[Welsh language|Welsh]] the apostrophe is used with infixed pronouns in order to distinguish them from the preceding word (e.g.  ''a'm chwaer'' &quot;and my sister&quot; as opposed to ''am chwaer'' &quot;about a sister&quot;).

===As a mark of palatalization or non-palatalization===
Some languages and [[transliteration]] systems use the apostrophe to mark the presence, or the lack of, [[palatalization]].

* In [[Belarusian language|Belarusian]] and [[Ukrainian language|Ukrainian]], the apostrophe is used between a consonant and a following &quot;soft&quot; ([[iotation|iotified]]) vowel (е, ё, ю, я; Uk. є, ї, ю,&amp;nbsp;я) to indicate that ''no'' palatalization of the preceding consonant takes place, and the vowel is pronounced in the same way as at the beginning of the word. It therefore marks a morpheme boundary before /j/, and in Ukrainian, is also occasionally as a &quot;quasi letter&quot;. It appears frequently in Ukrainian, as, for instance, in the words: &lt;п'ять&gt; [p&quot;jat'] 'five', &lt;від'їзд&gt; [vid'jizd] 'departure', &lt;об'єднаний&gt; [ob'jednanyj] 'united', &lt;з'ясувати&gt; [z'jasuvaty] 'to clear up, explain', &lt;п'єса&gt; [p'jesa] play (drama),  etc.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Bunčić (Bonn), &quot;The apostrophe: A neglected and misunderstood reading aid&quot; at the [http://homepages.uni-tuebingen.de/daniel.buncic/apostroph/apostrophe.pdf Tübingen University website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://linguistlist.org/issues/13/13-1566.html Linguist List 13.1566, Daniel Bunčić, &quot;Apostrophe rules in languages&quot;], from May 31, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In Russian and some derived alphabets the same function is served by the [[hard sign]] (ъ, formerly called ''yer''). But the apostrophe saw some use as a substitute after 1918, when Soviet authorities enforced an orthographic reform by confiscating type bearing that &quot;letter parasite&quot; from stubborn printing houses in Petrograd.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vladtv.ru/leksikon.shtml?news=131 ГТРК – Владимир :: Главная] {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In some Latin transliterations of certain variants of the [[Cyrillic alphabet]] (for [[Belarusian language|Belarusian]], [[Russian language|Russian]], and [[Ukrainian language|Ukrainian]]), the apostrophe is used to replace the [[soft sign]] (ь, indicating palatalization of the preceding consonant), e.g., ''Русь'' is transliterated ''[[Kievan Rus'|Rus']]'' according to the [[BGN/PCGN system]]. (The [[Prime (symbol)#Use in linguistics|prime symbol]] is also used for the same purpose.)  Some of these transliteration schemes use a double apostrophe (&amp;nbsp;&quot;&amp;nbsp;) to represent the apostrophe in Ukrainian and Belarusian text, e.g. Ukrainian ''слов’янське'' (&quot;Slavic&quot;) is transliterated as ''slov&quot;yans’ke''.
* Some [[Karelian language|Karelian]] orthographies use an apostrophe to indicate palatalization, e.g. ''n'evvuo'' (&quot;to give advice&quot;), ''d'uuri'' (&quot;just (like)&quot;), ''el'vüttiä'' (&quot;to revive&quot;).

===As a glottal stop===
{{See also|Okina|Saltillo (linguistics)}}

Other languages and transliteration systems use the apostrophe or some similar mark to indicate a [[glottal stop]], sometimes considering it a letter of the alphabet:

* In [[Võro language|Võro]], the apostrophe is used in parallel with the letter &quot;q&quot; as symbol of plural.
* [[Guaraní language|Guarani]], where it is called ''puso'' {{IPA|/puˈso/}}, as in the words ''ñe'ẽ'' (language, to speak), ''ka'a'' (grass), ''a'ỹ'' (sterile).
* [[Hawaiian language|Hawaiian]], the ''[[okina|{{unicode|ʻokina}}]]'' ({{unicode|ʻ}}), an inverted apostrophe, is often rendered as ('). It is considered a letter of the alphabet.
* In the [[Tongan language]], the apostrophe is called a ''fakauʻa'' and is the last letter of the alphabet. It is used to represent the glottal stop. Like the ʻokina, it is inverted.
* Various other [[Austronesian languages]], such as [[Samoan language|Samoan]], [[Tahitian language|Tahitian]], and [[Chamorro language|Chamorro]].
* [[Tetum language|Tetum]], one of the official languages of [[East Timor]].
* The [[Brazil]]ian native [[Tupi language]].
* [[Mayan language|Mayan]].
* Several [[fictional languages]] such as [[Klingon language|Klingon]], [[D'ni language|D'ni]], [[Mando'a]] or [[Na'vi language|Na'vi]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zompist.com/kitlong.html Language Construction Kit], refers to the common phenomenon of adding apostrophes to make names appear &quot;alien&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The apostrophe represents sounds resembling the glottal stop in the [[Turkic languages]] and in some [[romanization]]s of [[Arabic language|Arabic]]. In typography, this function may be performed by the closing single [[quotation mark]]. In that case, the Arabic letter ''[[ayin|‘ayn]]'' (ع) is correspondingly transliterated with the opening single quotation mark.

===Miscellaneous uses in other languages===
* In [[Slovak language|Slovak]], the [[caron]] over lowercase ''t'', ''d'', ''l'', and uppercase ''L'' [[consonants]] resembles an apostrophe: ''ď'', ''ť'', ''ľ'', ''Ľ''. This is especially so in certain common typographic renderings. But it is incorrect to use an apostrophe instead of the caron. In Slovak, there is also ''l'' with an acute accent: ''ĺ'', ''Ĺ''. In both languages the apostrophe is properly used only to indicate [[elision]] in certain words (''tys&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', as an abbreviated form of ''ty si'' in Slovak, or ''pad&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' for ''padl'' in Czech); however, these elisions are restricted to poetry. And the apostrophe is also used before a two-digit year number (to indicate the omission of the first two digits): ''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;87''.
* In [[Finnish language|Finnish]], one of the [[consonant gradation]] patterns is the change of a ''k'' into a [[hiatus (linguistics)|hiatus]], e.g. ''keko → keon'' (&quot;a pile → a pile's&quot;). This hiatus has to be indicated in spelling with an apostrophe if a long vowel or a diphthong would be immediately followed by the final vowel, e.g. ''ruoko → ruo'on'', ''vaaka → vaa'an''. (This is in contrast to compound words, where the equivalent problem is solved with a [[hyphen]], e.g. ''maa-ala'', &quot;land area&quot;.) Similarly, the apostrophe is used to mark the [[hiatus (linguistics)|hiatus]] (contraction) that occurs in poetry, e.g. ''miss' on'' for ''missä on'' (&quot;where is&quot;).
* In [[Breton language|Breton]], the combination ''c'h'' is used for the consonant {{IPA|/x/}} (like ''ch'' in English ''Loch Ness''), while ''ch'' is used for the consonant {{IPA|/ʃ/}} (as in French ''chat'' or English ''she'').
* In [[Italian language|Italian]], an apostrophe is sometimes used as a substitute for a [[grave accent|grave]] or an [[acute accent]] after a final vowel: in capitals, or when the proper form of the letter is unavailable. So ''Niccolò'' might be rendered as ''&lt;nowiki&gt;Niccolo'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', or ''&lt;nowiki&gt;NICCOLO'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''; ''perché'', as ''&lt;nowiki&gt;perche'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', or ''&lt;nowiki&gt;PERCHE'&lt;/nowiki&gt;''. This applies only to machine or computer writing, in the absence of a suitable keyboard. This usage is considered incorrect, or at least inelegant, by many.{{Who|date=August 2011}}
* In [[Swahili language|Swahili]], an apostrophe after ''ng'' shows that there is no sound of {{IPA|/ɡ/}} after the {{IPA|/ŋ/}} sound; that is, that the ''ng'' is pronounced as in English ''singer'', not as in English ''finger''.
* In [[Luganda|Ganda]], ''ng{{'}}'' (pronounced {{IPA|/ŋ/}}) is used in place of ''ŋ'' on keyboards where this character is not available. The apostrophe distinguishes it from the letter combination ''ng'' (pronounced {{IPA|[ŋɡ]}}), which has separate use in the language. Compare this with the Swahili usage above.
* In [[Jèrriais]], one of the uses of the apostrophe is to mark [[gemination]], or consonant length. For example, ''t't'' represents {{IPA|/tː/}}, ''s's'' {{IPA|/sː/}}, ''n'n'' {{IPA|/nː/}}, ''th'th'' {{IPA|/ðː/}}, and ''ch'ch'' {{IPA|/ʃː/}} (contrasted with {{IPA|/t/}}, {{IPA|/s/}}, {{IPA|/n/}}, {{IPA|/ð/}}, and {{IPA|/ʃ/}}).
* In the [[pinyin]] (hànyǔ pīnyīn) system of [[romanization]] for [[Standard Chinese]], an apostrophe is often loosely said to separate syllables in a word where ambiguity could arise. Example: the standard romanization for the name of the city ''[[Xī'ān]]'' includes an apostrophe to distinguish it from a single-syllable word ''xian''. More strictly, however, it is correct to place an apostrophe only before every ''a'', ''e'', or ''o'' that starts a new syllable after the first if it is not preceded by a hyphen or a dash. Examples: ''[[Tiān'ānmén]]'', ''[[Yǎ'ān]]''; but simply ''[[Jǐnán]]'', in which the syllables are ''ji'' and ''nan'', since the absence of an apostrophe shows that the syllables are not ''jin'' and ''an'' (contrast ''[[Jīn'ān]]'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pinyin.info/romanization/hanyu/apostrophes.html Pinyin]&lt;/ref&gt; This is a kind of morpheme-separation marking (see [[#To separate morphemes|above]]).
* In the largely superseded [[Wade-Giles|Wade–Giles]] romanization for Standard Chinese, an apostrophe marks [[Aspiration (phonetics)|aspiration]] of the preceding consonant sound. Example: in ''tsê'' (pinyin ''ze'') the consonant represented by ''ts'' is unaspirated, but in ''ts'ê'' (pinyin ''ce'') the consonant represented by ''ts&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' is aspirated.
* In some systems of romanization for the [[Japanese language|Japanese]], the apostrophe is used between [[Mora (linguistics)|moras]] in ambiguous situations, to differentiate between, for example, ''na'' and ''n''&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;''a''. (This is similar to the practice in Pinyin mentioned above.)
* In [[Hebrew]], the [[geresh]] (a diacritic similar to the apostrophe and often represented by one) is adjacent to letters to show sounds that are not represented in the Hebrew alphabet. Sounds such as ''j'', ''th'', and ''ch'' are indicated using ג, ת, and צ with a [[geresh]] (informally &quot;chupchik&quot;). For example, the name ''George'' is spelled ג׳ורג׳ in Hebrew (with ג׳ representing the first and last consonants).
* In the new [[Uzbek alphabet|Uzbek Latin alphabet]] adopted in 2000, the apostrophe serves as a [[Diacritic|diacritical mark]] to distinguish different phonemes written with the same letter: it differentiates ''o&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' (corresponding to Cyrillic ''[[Short U (Cyrillic)|ў]]'') from ''o'', and ''g&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' (Cyrillic ''[[Ghayn|ғ]]'') from ''g''. This avoids the use of special characters, allowing Uzbek to be typed with ease in ordinary [[ASCII]] on any Latin keyboard. In addition, a postvocalic apostrophe in Uzbek represents the glottal stop phoneme derived from Arabic ''[[hamza]]h'' or ''[[Ayin|‘ayn]]'', replacing Cyrillic ''[[Yer|ъ]]''.
* In English [[Yorkshire dialect]], the apostrophe is used to represent the word ''the'', which is contracted to a more glottal (or &quot;unreleased&quot;) /t/ sound. Most users will write ''in t'barn'' (&quot;in the barn&quot;), ''on t'step'' (&quot;on the step&quot;); and those unfamiliar with Yorkshire speech will often make these sound like ''intuh barn'' and ''ontuh step''. A more accurate rendition might be ''in't barn'' and ''on't step'', though even this does not truly convey correct Yorkshire pronunciation as the ''t'' is more like a [[glottal stop]].
* [[Galician cuisine|Galician restaurants]] in [[Madrid (province)|Madrid]] in [[Yellow Pages|Páginas Amarillas]] sometimes use ''&lt;nowiki&gt;O'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' in their names instead of the standard article ''O'' (&quot;The&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paginasamarillas.es/resultados.asp?activ=Restaurantes+gallegos&amp;nomb=O&amp;prov=MADRID&amp;pgpv=1&amp;mode=listadirGalician restaurants with an 'o' in their names in Madrid].&lt;/ref&gt;
* In standard [[lojban]] orthography, it is a letter in its own right (called y'y [ɐhɐ]) that can appear only between two vowels, and is phonemically realized as either [[Voiceless glottal fricative|[h]]] or, more rarely, [[Voiceless dental fricative|[θ]]].

==Typographic form==
The form of the apostrophe originates in [[manuscript]] writing, as a point with a downwards tail curving clockwise. This form was inherited by the ''typographic apostrophe'' (&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;), also known as the ''[[typeset]] apostrophe'', or, informally, the ''curly apostrophe''. Later [[sans-serif]] typefaces had stylized apostrophes with a more geometric or simplified form, but usually retaining the same directional bias as a closing quotation mark.

With the invention of the [[typewriter]], a &quot;neutral&quot; quotation mark form (&amp;nbsp;'&amp;nbsp;) was created to economize on the keyboard, by using a single key to represent the apostrophe, both opening and closing single [[quotation mark]]s, and single [[Prime (symbol)|primes]]. This is known as the ''typewriter apostrophe'' or ''vertical apostrophe''. The same convention was adopted for [[quotation mark]]s. Both simplifications carried over to computer keyboards and the [[ASCII]] character set. However, although these are widely used due to their ubiquity and convenience, they are deprecated in contexts where proper typography is important.&lt;ref&gt;http://apostropheatrophy.com/&lt;/ref&gt; Various applications, such as [[Microsoft Word]] and [[TextEdit]], support auto-correction of straight apostrophes and quotation marks to typographically accurate ones; furthermore, easier access to the latter is provided by keyboard mappings such as that of [[Mac OS X]].

==Computing==
===ASCII encoding===
The typewriter apostrophe (&amp;nbsp;'&amp;nbsp;) was inherited by computer keyboards, and is the only apostrophe [[character (computing)|character]] available in the (7-bit) [[ASCII]] [[character encoding]], at code value 0x27 (39). As such, it is a highly overloaded character. In ASCII, it represents a right single [[quotation mark]], left single quotation mark, apostrophe, vertical line or [[Prime (symbol)|prime]] (punctuation marks), or an [[acute accent]] (modifier letters).

Many earlier (pre 1985) computer displays and printers rendered the ASCII apostrophe as a typographic apostrophe, and rendered the ASCII [[grave accent]] (&amp;nbsp;'''`'''&amp;nbsp;) U+0060 as a matching left single quotation mark. This allowed a more typographic appearance of text: &lt;code&gt;``I&amp;nbsp;can't'&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt; would appear as &lt;code&gt;&amp;lsquo;&amp;lsquo;I&amp;nbsp;can&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/code&gt; on these systems. This can still be seen in many documents prepared at that time, and is still used in the [[TeX]] typesetting system to create typographic quotes.

===Typographic apostrophe in 8-bit encodings===
Support for the typographic apostrophe (&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;) was introduced in a variety of 8-bit character encodings, such as the [[Mac OS|Apple Macintosh]] operating system's [[Mac Roman]] character set (in 1984), and later in the [[CP1252]] encoding of [[Microsoft Windows]]. There is no such character in [[ISO-8859-1]].

Microsoft Windows [[CP1252]] (sometimes incorrectly called ''ANSI'' or ''ISO-Latin'') contains the typographic apostrophe at 0x92. Due to &quot;smart quotes&quot; in Microsoft software converting the ASCII apostrophe to this value, other software makers have been forced to adopt this as a ''de facto'' convention. For instance the HTML 5 standard specifies that this value is interpreted as CP1252. Some earlier non-Microsoft browsers would display a '?' for this and make web pages composed with Microsoft software somewhat hard to read.

===Unicode===
There are several types of apostrophe character in [[Unicode]]:

* (&amp;nbsp;&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;&amp;nbsp;) Vertical ''typewriter apostrophe'' (Unicode name ''apostrophe'' or ''apostrophe-quote''), U+0027, inherited from [[ASCII]].
* (&amp;nbsp;{{unicode|’}}&amp;nbsp;) ''Punctuation apostrophe'' (or ''typographic apostrophe''; ''right single quotation mark''; ''single comma quotation mark''), U+2019. Serves as both an apostrophe and closing single quotation mark. This is the preferred character to use for apostrophe according to the Unicode standard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://unicode.org/Public/UNIDATA/NamesList.txt The Unicode Consortium]&lt;/ref&gt;
* (&amp;nbsp;{{unicode|ʼ}}&amp;nbsp;) ''Letter apostrophe'' (or ''[[modifier letter apostrophe]]''), U+02BC. This is preferred when the apostrophe is not considered punctuation that separates letters, but a letter in its own right. Examples occur in Breton [[cʼh]], the [[Cyrillic]] [[Azerbaijani alphabet]], or in some [[transliteration]]s such as the transliterated Arabic [[glottal stop]], ''hamza'', or transliterated Cyrillic [[soft sign]]. As the letter apostrophe is seldom used in practice, the Unicode standard cautions that one should never assume text is coded thus. The letter apostrophe is rendered identically to the punctuation apostrophe in the Unicode code charts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicode.org/charts/ Unicode code charts]&lt;/ref&gt;
* (&amp;nbsp;{{okina}}&amp;nbsp;) The Hawaiian glottal stop, the [[okina|{{okina}}okina]], has its own Unicode character, U+02BB.
* (&amp;nbsp;{{unicode|ˮ}}&amp;nbsp;) ''Letter double apostrophe'' (Unicode name ''[[modifier letter double apostrophe]]''), U+02EE. One of two characters for glottal stop in [[Nenets languages|Nenets]].
* (&amp;nbsp;{{unicode|՚}}&amp;nbsp;) ''[[Armenian language|Armenian]] apostrophe'', U+055A.
* (&amp;nbsp;{{unicode|Ꞌ ꞌ}}&amp;nbsp;) The [[Tlapanec language|Me'phaa]] glottal stop (and other languages of Mexico), the [[Saltillo (linguistics)|Saltillo]], has its own Unicode characters, U+A78B and U+A78C.

===Entering apostrophes===
Although ubiquitous in typeset material, the typographic apostrophe (&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;) is rather difficult to enter on a computer, since it does not have its own key on a standard keyboard. Outside the world of professional typesetting and graphic design, many people do not know how to enter this character and instead use the typewriter apostrophe (&amp;nbsp;'&amp;nbsp;). The typewriter apostrophe has always been considered tolerable on Web pages because of the egalitarian nature of Web publishing and the low resolution of computer monitors in comparison to print.

More recently, the correct use of the typographic apostrophe is becoming more common on the Web due to the wide adoption of the [[Unicode]] text encoding standard, higher-resolution displays, and advanced [[anti-aliasing]] of text in modern operating systems. Because typewriter apostrophes are now often automatically converted to typographic apostrophes by wordprocessing and desktop-publishing software (see below), the typographic apostrophe does often appear in documents produced by non-professionals.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+How to enter apostrophes on a computer
!
! [[Macintosh]]
! [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]
! [[Linux]]/[[X Window System|X]]
! HTML entity
! HTML decimal
|-
|Typewriter apostrophe
|'
|'
|'
|''none''
|&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;
|-
|Typographic apostrophe
|Option + Shift + ]
|Alt + 0146 on number pad
|AltGr + shift + B ''or'' Compose ' &gt;
|&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;rsquo;&lt;/code&gt;
|&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#8217;&lt;/code&gt;
|}

While XML (and hence [[XHTML]]) defines an &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;apos;&lt;/code&gt; character entity reference for the apostrophe, no such entity is defined in the HTML 4 standard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224/sgml/entities.html|title=Character entity references in HTML 4|publisher=World Wide Web Consortium|date=December 24, 1999|accessdate=October 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt; must be used.

===Smart quotes===
To make typographic apostrophes easier to enter, [[wordprocessing]] and [[publishing]] software often converts typewriter apostrophes to typographic apostrophes during text entry (at the same time converting opening and closing single and double quotes to their correct left-handed or right-handed forms). A similar facility may be offered on web servers after submitting text in a form field, e.g. on weblogs or free encyclopedias. This is known as the ''smart quotes'' feature; apostrophes and quotation marks that are not automatically altered by computer programs are known as ''dumb quotes''.

Such conversion is not always done in accordance with the standards for character sets and encodings. Additionally, many such software programs incorrectly convert a leading apostrophe to an opening quotation mark (e.g., in abbreviations of years: ''&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt;29'' rather than the correct ''&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;29'' for the years ''1929'' or ''2029'' (depending on context); or ''&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;‘&lt;/span&gt;twas'' instead of ''&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;twas'' as the archaic abbreviation of ''it was''. Smart quote features also often fail to recognise situations when a [[Prime (symbol)|prime]] rather than an apostrophe is needed; for example, incorrectly rendering the latitude 49°&amp;nbsp;53′&amp;nbsp;08″ as 49°&amp;nbsp;53&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;’&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;08&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:serif&quot;&gt;”&lt;/span&gt;.

In  [[Microsoft Word]] it is possible to turn smart quotes off (in some versions, by navigating through ''Tools'', ''AutoCorrect'', ''AutoFormat as you type'', and then unchecking the appropriate option). Alternatively, typing Control-Z (for ''Undo'') immediately after entering the apostrophe will convert it back to a typewriter apostrophe. In Microsoft Word for Windows, holding down the Control key while typing two apostrophes will produce a single typographic apostrophe.

===Programming===
Some programming languages, like [[Pascal (programming language)|Pascal]], use the ASCII apostrophe to delimit [[String (computer science)|string constants]]. Often either the apostrophe or the double quote may be used, allowing string constants to contain the other character (but not to contain both without using an [[escape character]]).

The C programming language (and many related languages like [[C++]] or [[Java]]) uses apostrophes to delimit a [[Character (computing)|character constant]]. In C it is seen as a character value only, different from a 1-letter string.

==See also==
* [[Apologetic apostrophe]]
* [[apos]]
* [[Caron]]
* [[Contraction (grammar)]]
* [[Elision]]
* [[Genitive case]]
* [[Modifier letter double apostrophe]]
* [[Possessive case]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Gibaldi |first=Joseph |title=MLA Handbook for Writers of Research Papers |location=New York |publisher=Modern Language Association |year=2003 |isbn= |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}.
*{{Cite book|authorlink=Lynne Truss |last=Truss |first=Lynne |title=[[Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves|Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves: The Zero Tolerance Approach to Punctuation]] |year=2003 |publisher=Gotham Books |location=Toronto |edition=North American |isbn=1592400876 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|apostrophe}}
{{refbegin}}
*[http://www.askoxford.com/asktheexperts/faq/aboutspelling/pizza Is there an apostrophe in the plural of pizza?] Oxford University Press article on apostrophe use in plurals
*[http://stc-carolina.org/newsletter/tiki-index.php?page=Obsessed+with+Possessives &quot;Obsessed with Possessives&quot;] Society for Technical Communication article on apostrophe use with possessives.
*[http://snowball.tartarus.org/texts/apostrophe.html The apostrophe character] Problems representing apostrophes on computers.
*[http://www.apostrophe.org.uk/ The Apostrophe Protection Society]
*[http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/ucs/quotes.html ASCII and Unicode quotation marks]
*[http://www.dreaded-apostrophe.com The Dreaded Apostrophe: An approach using a single rule only]
*[http://theoatmeal.com/comics/apostrophe How to use an apostrophe] The Oatmeal
{{refend}}
*[http://observer.american.edu/cas/tesol/resources/working-paper-2.cfm &quot;How the Past Affects the Future: The Story of the Apostrophe&quot;] by Christina Cavella and Robin A. Kernodle

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Alphabetic diacritics]]
[[Category:Hebrew diacritics]]
[[Category:Punctuation]]
[[Category:English spelling]]

[[az:Apostrof]]
[[bg:Апостроф]]
[[ca:Apòstrof]]
[[cs:Apostrof]]
[[da:Apostrof]]
[[de:Apostroph]]
[[et:Ülakoma]]
[[es:Apóstrofo]]
[[eo:Apostrofo]]
[[eu:Apostrofo]]
[[fa:آپاستروف]]
[[fr:Apostrophe (typographie)]]
[[gd:Asgair]]
[[xal:Цөөлх темдг]]
[[ko:아포스트로피]]
[[hr:Izostavnik]]
[[io:Apostrofo]]
[[id:Tanda penyingkat]]
[[it:Apostrofo]]
[[he:אפוסטרוף]]
[[kn:ಅಪಾಸ್ಟ್ರಫಿ (Apostrophe )]]
[[kk:Апостроф]]
[[sw:Apostrofi]]
[[hu:Aposztróf]]
[[mk:Апостроф]]
[[nl:Apostrof (leesteken)]]
[[ja:アポストロフィー]]
[[no:Apostrof]]
[[uz:' (belgi)]]
[[pl:Apostrof]]
[[pt:Apóstrofo]]
[[ro:Apostrof (simbol)]]
[[ru:Апостроф]]
[[simple:Apostrophe]]
[[sk:Apostrof]]
[[sl:Opuščaj]]
[[sh:Apostrof]]
[[sv:Apostrof]]
[[tl:Kudlit]]
[[th:อะพอสทรอฟี]]
[[tr:Kesme işareti]]
[[uk:Апостроф]]
[[war:Sisep]]
[[zh:撇号]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
