<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="596249" ns="0" title="Banknotes of the Philippine peso"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Cleanup-rewrite|date=July 2011}}
[[File:New PHP200 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|thumb|The front side of a two-hundred peso bill.]]
'''Banknotes of the Philippine peso''' are issued by the [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas]] (Central Bank of the Philippines) for circulation in the [[Philippines]]. The smallest amount of legal tender in wide circulation is 20 [[Philippine peso|peso]] and the largest is 1000 peso. The front side of each banknote features prominent people in the country's history while the reverse side depicts landmarks and events in history. While the 5- and 10-peso denominations have been concurrently offered in coins in recent years, the 5- and 10-peso notes have not been demonetized.

==History of Philippine banknotes==
On May 1, 1852, the first commercial bank of the Philippines, [[Bank of the Philippine Islands|El Banco Español Filipino de Isabel 2A]] issued the following denominations initially 10, 25, 50 and 200 pesos fuertes (strong pesos). They were used until 1896.

===First Philippine Republic===
During the [[First Philippine Republic]], President [[Emilio Aguinaldo]] ordered the issuance of 1, 2, 5, 10, 25, 50, 100 peso banknotes signed by Messrs [[Pedro A. Paterno]], Telesforo Chuidan and Mariano Limjap to avoid counterfeiting. However, only the 1 and 5 pesos banknotes have been printed and circulated to some areas by the end of the short-lived First Republic.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  style=&quot;font-size:90%; width:100%;&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;9&quot;| Banknotes during the First Philippine Republic
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Image !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Value !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Main Colour !!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Description !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Years of Circulation
|-
! Obverse !! Reverse !! style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;|Obverse !! style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;|Reverse
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Un Peso Reverse.jpg|99px]] --&gt;
|style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|
[[File:Un Peso Republica Filipina.jpg|99px]]
| [[Philippine one peso bill|₱1]]
| White
| Official Name
|
Official Name
| 1899–1901
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|
|
| [[Philippine five peso bill|₱5]]
| White
| Official Name
|
Official Name
| 1899–1901
|-
|colspan=&quot;8&quot;|{{Standard banknote table notice}}
|}

By 1903, The American Insular Government issued Silver Certificates in the denominations 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100 and 500 pesos backed by Silver Coin or U.S. Gold at a fixed rate of 2:1. In 1908, the El Banco Español Filipino was allowed to print banknotes in the following denominations with text in Spanish: Cinco (5), Diez (10), Veinte (20), Cincuenta (50), Cien (100) and Dos Cientos (200) Pesos. In 1912, the bank was renamed [[Bank of the Philippine Islands]] (BPI) and henceforth issued the same banknotes in English. In 1918, the Silver Certificates were replaced by the Treasury Certificates issued with government-backing of bonds issued by the United States Government in the following denominations: One, Two, Five, Ten, Twenty, Fifty, One Hundred and Five Hundred Pesos. In 1916, the [[Philippine National Bank]] (PNB) was created to administer the state-holding shares and print banknotes without any quota from the [[Philippine Assembly]]. They printed banknotes in 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 50 and 100 peso denomination. During [[World War I]], the PNB issued emergency notes printed on cardboard paper in the following denominations: 10, 20, 50 centavos and 1 peso. Also overprinted BPI Notes in Five, Ten and Twenty Pesos due to the lack of currency.

The [[Commonwealth of the Philippines]] issued Treasury Certificates with the seal of the new government but still circulated the BPI and PNB banknotes.

===Japanese Government-issued Philippine Fiat Peso===

{{main|Japanese government-issued Philippine fiat peso}}

==Banknotes issued by the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas==

===English series===
The banknotes first issued by today's [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas]] (formerly the &quot;Central Bank of the Philippines&quot;) were the VICTORY-CBP Overprints in 1949, which were merely overprints of older American-era banknotes.  The first official banknote series to be printed were the English Series in 1951.

{{main|English Series}}
===Pilipino series===

{{main|Pilipino Series}}

===''Ang Bagong Lipunan'' series===

{{main|Ang Bagong Lipunan Series}}

===New Design/BSP series===
{{main|New Design series}}

By 1983, the Committee was deciding the issuing of new banknotes to replace the Ang Bagong Lipunan Series by issuing seven new banknotes consisting of 5, 10, 20, 50, 100, 500, and 1000-peso banknotes.

On June 12, 1985, the Central Bank issued the New Design Series starting with a new 5-peso banknote with the face of [[Emilio Aguinaldo]]. The following months, a new 10-peso banknote with the face of [[Apolinario Mabini]]. In early 1986, a new 20-peso banknote appeared. After the 1986 [[People Power Revolution]] and the new [[Constitution of the Philippines|1987 Constitution]] was promulgated, the Central Bank issued a new 50, 100- and for the second time a new 500-peso banknote with the face of [[Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]. In 1991, the Central Bank issued for the first time a new 1000-peso banknote, containing the portraits of [[Jose Abad Santos]], [[Josefa Llanes Escoda]] and [[Vicente Lim]].

After the passage of the New Central Bank Act of 1993, the New Design Series, which was initiated in 1985, was slightly changed because of new seal of the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas. In 1998, the 100,000-peso Centennial banknote, measuring 8.5&quot;x14&quot;, accredited by the [[Guinness Book of World Records]] as the world's largest legal tender note. It was issued in very limited quantity during the celebration of the Centennial of Philippine Independence. In 2001, the Bangko Sentral issued upgraded 1000, 500, and 100-peso banknotes with new hi-tech security features to combat counterfeiting. During the Estrada Administration, the practice in use since the Commonwealth, of reproducing the signature of the [[President of the Philippines]] over the legend &quot;President of the Philippines&quot; was abandoned in favor of explicitly stating the president's name.  In 2002, the Bangko Sentral issued a new 200-peso banknote with the security features found on the upgraded 1000, 500, and 100-peso banknotes and has the face of former President [[Diosdado Macapagal]]. His daughter, [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]], is at the back of the 200-peso banknote which showed her being sworn into office at the [[EDSA Shrine]]. She is the first president whose image has been included in a banknote while in office since emergency currency was issued by various provincial currency boards during World War II.

The series was renamed the '''BSP Series''' in 1993 when the [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas]] was reestablished as the central monetary authority. These banknotes remains legal tender until 2013.

The '''New Design Series''' has less security features. (only the visible fibers, value panel, security thread and watermark.)

The '''BSP Series''' has added more security features such as another glossy security thread, iridescent strip, fluorescent printing, optically variable ink, and microprints.&lt;ref&gt;[http://philmoney.blogspot.com/search/label/Security%20Features Security Features in Present Money]&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Generation Banknote Series===

In 2009, the [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas]] announced that it launched a massive redesign for current banknotes and coins to further enhance security features and improve durability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bsp.gov.ph/publications/media.asp?id=2296 The New Generation Currency Program of the Philippines (Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas)]&lt;/ref&gt; The members of the numismatic committee include Bangko Sentral Deputy Governor Diwa Guinigundo and Dr. Ambeth Ocampo Chairman of the National Historical Institute. The new banknote design  features famous Filipinos and iconic natural wonders. Philippine national symbols will be depicted on coins. The BSP started releasing the initial batch of new banknotes in December 2010 while new coins will be introduced beginning 2012. Current banknotes will remain legal tender for at least three years.

On December 16, 2010, the new design for Philippine banknotes were released.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gmanews.tv/story/208501/cory-ninoy-together-again-on-new-500-peso-bill Cory, Ninoy together again on new 500-peso bill], Jam Sisante, GMANews.TV, December 16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  style=&quot;font-size:90%; width:100%;&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;9&quot;| New Generation Banknote Series
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Image !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Value !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Dimensions !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Main Colour !!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Description !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Year of First Issue
|-
! Obverse !! Reverse !! style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;|Obverse !! style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;|Reverse
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP20 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|130px]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP20 Banknote (Reverse).jpg|130px]]
| [[Philippine twenty peso bill|₱20]]
|rowspan=&quot;6&quot;| 160 × 66&amp;nbsp;mm
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:orange;&quot;|
| Orange
|
[[Manuel Quezon|Manuel L. Quezon]], Declaration of [[Filipino language|Filipino]] as the national language, [[Malacañang Palace]]
|
[[Banaue Rice Terraces]]; ''[[Asian Palm Civet|Paradoxurus hermaphroditus philippinensis]]'', Palm civet; Cordilleras weave design
| 2010
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP50 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|130px]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP50 Banknote (Reverse).jpg|130px]]
| [[Philippine fifty peso bill|₱50]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:Crimson;&quot;|
| Red
|
[[Sergio Osmeña]], [[Philippine Assembly|First Philippine Assembly]], [[Battle of Leyte#Landings|Leyte Landing]]
|
[[Taal Lake]] in [[Batangas]]; ''[[Giant trevally|Caranx ignobilis]]'', ''maliputo'' (Giant trevally); Batangas embroidery design
| 2010
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP100 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|130px]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP100 Banknote (Reverse).jpg|130px]]
| [[Philippine one hundred peso bill|₱100]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:DarkSlateBlue;&quot;|
| Bluish Violet
|
[[Manuel Roxas|Manuel A. Roxas]], Old [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas|BSP]] building in [[Intramuros]], [[Manila]], Inauguration of the [[History of the Philippines (1946–1965)|Third Philippine Republic]]
|
[[Mayon Volcano]] in [[Albay]]; ''butanding'', ''[[Rhincodon typus]]'', whale shark; Bicol textile design
| 2010
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP200 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|130px]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP200 Banknote (Reverse).jpg|130px]]
| [[Philippine two hundred peso bill|₱200]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:LimeGreen;&quot;|
| Green
|
[[Diosdado Macapagal|Diosdado P. Macapagal]], [[EDSA Revolution of 2001|EDSA People Power 2001]], [[Aguinaldo Shrine]] in [[Kawit, Cavite]], [[Barasoain Church]] in [[Malolos]], [[Bulacan]]
|
[[Chocolate Hills]] in [[Bohol]]; ''[[Tarsius syrichta]]'', Philippine tarsier; Visayas weave design
| 2010
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP500 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|130px]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP500 Banknote (Reverse).jpg|130px]]
| [[Philippine five hundred peso bill|₱500]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;|
| Golden yellow
|
[[Corazon Aquino|Corazon C. Aquino]], [[Benigno Aquino, Jr.|Benigno S. Aquino, Jr.]], [[People Power Revolution|EDSA People Power I]], Benigno Aquino monument in [[Makati City]]
|
[[Puerto Princesa Subterranean River National Park|Subterranean Underground River]] in [[Puerto Princesa, Palawan]]; ''[[Tanygnathus lucionensis]]'', blue-naped parrot; Southern Philippines cloth design
| 2010
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP1000 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|130px]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|[[File:New PHP1000 Banknote (Reverse).jpg|130px]]
| [[Philippine one thousand peso bill|₱1000]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:blue;&quot;|
| Blue
|
[[José Abad Santos]], [[Vicente Lim]], [[Josefa Llanes Escoda]]; Centennial celebration of [[Philippine Declaration of Independence|Philippine independence]]; Medal of Honor, which was awarded to Abad Santos, Lim, and Escoda
|
[[Tubbataha Reef|Tubbataha Reefs Natural Park]] in [[Sulu Sea]]; ''[[Pearl oyster|Pinctada maxima]]'', South Sea pearl; Mindanao design for Tinalak (Ikat-dyed abaca)
| 2010
|-
|colspan=&quot;8&quot;|{{Standard banknote table notice}}
|}

====Errors====
Several errors have been discovered on banknotes of the New Generation series and have become the subject of ridicule in [[social networking sites]]. Among these are the exclusion of [[Batanes]] from the Philippine map on the reverse of all denominations, the mislocation of the Puerto Princesa Subterranean Underground River on the reverse of the 500-peso bill and the Tubbataha Reef on the 1000-peso bill, and the incorrect coloring on the beak and feathers of the blue-naped parrot on the 500-peso bill.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abs-cbnnews.com/business/12/19/10/errors-found-new-peso-bills Errors found on new peso bills &amp;#124; ABS-CBN News &amp;#124; Latest Philippine Headlines, Breaking News, Video, Analysis, Features]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/nation/view/20101220-309957/Error-filled-peso-bills-spark-uproar&lt;/ref&gt; The [[scientific name]]s of the animals featured on the reverse sides of all banknotes were incorrectly rendered as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://philmoney.blogspot.com/2010/12/problem-with-scientific-names-in-new.html Philippine Money – Peso Coins and Banknotes: Error in Scientific Names on New Generation Banknotes]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Design Systemat, the designers of the new bills, that drafts prepared by the company of the new 500-peso bill shows a red beak of the Blue-naped parrot. This color was changed by the printers to account for practical printing concerns. The designers further explains that printing banknotes is not like printing brochures. Due to the [[Intaglio (printmaking)|intalgio printing]] and limited printing capability of banknote printers, it can only produce a limited full color reproduction.

The alleged mislocation of the Tubbataha Reef on the one thousand peso note was due to a security feature, a smaller version of the featured species on the bills' reverse (which is also featured on all banknote denominations) was located on top of the exact location of the Tubbataha Reef on the map. Giving the option of either moving the key security feature on the standard position or locating the Tubbataha marker correctly, the bills' French printers, [[Oberthur Technologies]], decided to move the reef marker slightly south on the Philippine map.&lt;ref&gt;[http://business.inquirer.net/money/topstories/view/20110101-312041/The-pesos-makeover-from-an-insiders-view The peso’s makeover from an insider’s view ], Daxim Lucas, [[Philippine Daily Inquirer]], January 1, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Higher denominations==

The Central Bank of the Philippines issued only 300,000 pieces of this 216mmx133mm 2,000 Philippine peso centennial commemorative legal tender banknote.

The obverse side features President Joseph Estrada taking his oath of office on June 30, 1998 in the historic Barasoain Church, the seat of the first democratic republic in Asia shown in the background as well as the scroll of the Malolos Constitution and the seal of the BSP (Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas).

The reverse side depicts the re-enactment of the declaration of Philippine Independence at the Aguinaldo Shrine in Kawit, Cavite on June 12, 1898 by President Fidel V. Ramos and also features the Philippine Centennial Commission logo.

The security features of the note include a 3-dimensional cylinder mold-made portrait watermark of the two presidents and the years 1898–1998, iridescent band, color-shift windowed security thread, latent image and perfect see-through register.

The 100,000-peso centennial note, measuring 8.5&quot;x14&quot;, is accredited by the [[Guinness Book of World Records]] as the world's largest legal tender note in terms of size. 1,000 pieces were issued during the celebration of the centennial of Philippine independence in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bsp.gov.ph/about/history/story8.asp Special Exhibits – Centennial Exhibits]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{refbegin}}

{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://philmoney.blogspot.com Philippine Banknotes and Coins]
* [http://www.filipinonumismatist.com Philippine Coins News &amp; Updates]
* [http://www.guerrilla-money.com Philippine currency during WWII]
{{Philippine peso history}}

[[Category:Banknotes of Asia|Philippine peso]]
[[Category:Economy of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Currencies of the Philippines]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
