<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5987957" ns="0" title="Western saloon"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|refimprove=October 2008|cleanup=October 2008}}

[[Image:Judge Roy Bean.jpg|thumb|275px|right|Judge Roy Bean’s Saloon in [[Langtry, Texas]]]]
[[File:KinmanBar.jpg|thumb|275px|[[Seth Kinman]]'s bar in 1889 in [[Table Bluff, California]]]]

A '''Western saloon''' is a kind of [[bar (establishment)|bar]] particular to the [[American Old West]]. Saloons served customers such as [[fur trapper]]s, [[cowboy]]s, soldiers, gold prospectors, miners, and gamblers. The first saloon was established at Brown’s Hole, [[Wyoming]], in 1822, to serve fur trappers. The popularity of saloons in the nineteenth-century American West is attested to by the fact that even a town of 3,000 residents, such as 1883’s [[Livingston, Montana]], boasted 33 saloons.&lt;ref name=&quot;legendsofamerica&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legendsofamerica.com/WE-Saloons.html |title=Saloons of the Old West |publisher=Legendsofamerica.com |date=2006-11-16 |accessdate=2009-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the more familiar saloons were First Chance Saloon in [[Miles City, Montana]]; the Bull’s Head in [[Abilene, Kansas]]; the Arcade in El Dorado, [[Colorado]]; the Holy Moses in [[Creede, Colorado]]; the Long Branch in [[Dodge City, Kansas]]; the [[Birdcage Theater]] (also a saloon) in [[Tombstone, Arizona]]; the Bucket of Blood Saloon in [[Virginia City, Nevada]]; and [[Judge Roy Bean]]’s Saloon in [[Langtry, Texas]]. Many of these establishments remained open 24 hours a day, seven days a week.&lt;ref name=&quot;legendsofamerica&quot; /&gt;

== Appearance ==
A saloon's appearance varied from when and where it grew. As towns grew, the saloons became more refined. The [[bartender]] prided himself on his appearance and his drink pouring abilities. Early saloons and those in remote locations were often crude affairs with minimal furniture and few decorations. A single wood-burning stove might warm such establishments during the winter months.

A pair of &quot;batwing&quot; doors at the entrance was one of the more distinctive features of the typical saloon. The doors operated on double action hinges and extended from chest to knee level.

As travelers made their way West, some of them sold liquor from their wagons, and saloons were often formed of the materials at hand, including “sod houses. . . . a hull of an old sailing ship“ or interiors “dug into the side of a hill”.

As towns grew, many hotels included saloons, and some stand-alone saloons, such as the Barlow Trail Saloon in [[Damascus, Oregon]], featured a railed porch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legendsofamerica.com/PicturePages/PP-Saloon-8-DamascusOR.html |title=Old West Saloons Vintage Photographs&amp;nbsp;— Damascus, Oregon Saloon |publisher=Legendsofamerica.com |date=2006-11-16 |accessdate=2009-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alcohol==
The earliest saloons were often nothing more than tents or shacks that served homemade [[whiskey]] that included such ingredients as “raw alcohol, burnt sugar and [[chewing tobacco]]” and was known by such names as “Tanglefoot, Forty-Rod, Tarantula Juice, [[Taos]] Lightning, Red Eye, and Coffin Varnish.” Other offerings included “Cactus Wine, made from a mix of [[tequila]] and [[peyote]] tea, and Mule Skinner, made with whiskey and [[blackberry]] liquor. The house rotgut was often 100 [[proof (alcohol)|proof]], though it was sometimes cut by the barkeep with [[turpentine]], [[ammonia]], [[gun powder]] or [[cayenne pepper|cayenne]]”.&lt;ref name=&quot;legendsofamerica&quot; /&gt; A saloon might also be known as a “watering trough, bughouse, shebang, cantina, grogshop, and gin mill”.

Because a copious amount of alcohol was consumed, many cowboys would urinate right at the bar.  The bar rail was attached to the bar so that cowboys could keep their boots out of the &quot;soggy&quot; ground as many of them would urinate while still sitting at the bar.  

However, all that changed once a town began to boom and money rolled in. Saloons were often elaborately decorated, contained [[Bohemian stemware]], and oil paintings hung from the wall. The whiskey was imported from the U.S. and Europe, and &quot;fancy&quot; drinks were served. Some of the top ten drinks in 1881 included claret [[Sangria|sangaree]]s and [[champagne flip]]s.

===Firewater===
Bartenders sometimes poured whiskey on fire to astonish Indians by the flammable properties of the “[[firewater]]”.

===Beer===
Beer, served at room temperature, was also a popular drink, with [[Adolphus Busch]] introducing the artificial [[refrigeration]] and [[pasteurization]] of beer in 1880 with his [[Budweiser (Anheuser-Busch)|Budweiser]] brand.&lt;ref name=&quot;legendsofamerica&quot; /&gt; Some saloons kept the beer in kegs stored on racks inside the saloon.&lt;ref name=&quot;legendsofamerica1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legendsofamerica.com/PicturePages/PP-Saloon-4-OrangeCountyCA.html |title=Old West Saloons Vintage Photographs&amp;nbsp;— Orange County, California |publisher=Legendsofamerica.com |date=2006-11-16 |accessdate=2009-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some saloons prided themselves on homemade beer and it was not always served at room temperature.

== Entertainment ==

By way of entertainment, saloons offered dancing girls, some of whom occasionally or routinely doubled as [[prostitutes]] (these girls were often addressed as &quot;Miss ___&quot;). Many saloons offered [[Faro (card game)|Faro]], [[poker]], [[Three card brag|brag]], [[three-card monte]], and [[dice]] games. Other games were added as saloons continued to prosper and face increasing competition. These additional games included [[billiards]], [[darts]], and [[bowling]]. Some saloons even included [[piano]] players, [[can-can]] girls, and theatrical skits.  A current example of this type of entertainment is the [[Long Branch Variety Show]] that is presented in the recreated [[Long Branch Saloon]] in [[Dodge City]], [[Kansas]].

== The Bull’s Head pizzle ==

Among the anecdotes of the American West, several concern incidents that took place in or outside saloons. One such incident occurred at The Bull’s Head Saloon in [[Abilene, Kansas]]. When the tavern’s owner, [[Phil Coe]], outraged the townspeople by painting a bull, complete with an erect penis, or pizzle, on the outside wall of his tavern, [[Wild Bill Hickok]], the marshal at the time, threatened to burn the saloon to the ground if the offending animal was not painted over. Instead, he hired some men to do the job, which angered Coe. The two became enemies and in a later altercation, Wild Bill Hickok killed Coe.&lt;ref name=&quot;thewildwest1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thewildwest.org/cowboys/badmen/benthompson.html |title=Home &amp;#124; Cowboys, Native American, American History, Wild West, American Indians |publisher=thewildwest.org |date= |accessdate=2009-10-05 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070928135707/http://www.thewildwest.org/cowboys/badmen/benthompson.html |archivedate = September 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Deadwood’s No. 10 Saloon ==

Wild Bill, also a professional [[lawman]], [[gunfighter]], and [[gambler]], was later killed (on August 2, 1876) by [[Jack McCall]], who shot him in the back of the head, in [[Saloon No. 10]], in [[Deadwood, South Dakota]], as Wild Bill was playing cards. His hand—aces and eights, according to tradition—has become known as “the [[dead man’s hand]].”

== Tom Mix, bartender ==

According to the [[Reader's Digest]]'s ''Story of the Great American West'', [[Tom Mix]], who later became an actor starring in a series of [[Hollywood]] films about the Wild West, was a bartender at the Blue Bell Saloon in [[Guthrie, Oklahoma]]. Mix’s fellow residents included fellow actor and comedian [[Will Rogers]]; [[William Wrigley Jr.]], the inventor of Wrigley’s [[chewing gum]]; and prohibitionist [[Carry Nation]].

== Wyatt Earp, saloon owner ==
[[Image:Northern Saloon.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Wyatt Earp's Northern Saloon, Tonopah, Nevada, circa 1902]]

[[Wyatt Earp]], lawman, Faro dealer, and gambler, also owned several saloons, outright or in partnership with others. In 1884, Earp and his brothers Warren and James bought a circus tent in which they “opened a saloon called The White Elephant. An advertisement in a local newspaper suggests gentlemen 'come and see the elephant'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://home.earthlink.net/~knuthco1/Itemsofinterest3/seniorcitsource.htm | title = Wyatt Earp, Senior Citizen | first = S. J. | last = Reidhead }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1899, Earp and C.E. Hoxsie built the Dexter Saloon in [[Nome, Alaska]], and Earp opened the Northern Saloon in [[Tonopah, Nevada]], circa 1902.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.gv.net/~syd/WyattSEarp/history11.html ]{{dead link|date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Earp also owned and operated a saloon and gambling hall in the Gaslamp Quarter of [[San Diego, California]] that has since been converted into a restaurant, Roger’s On Fifth, by its owner, former San Diego mayor [[Roger Hedgecock]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20030815234304/http://www.rogersonfifth.com/about.shtml|title=What is Roger's on Fifth?| archivedate=Aug 15, 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Television Westerns’ saloons ==

[[Television Westerns]], which were especially popular in the 1950s and 1960s, featured such fictional saloons (sometimes based on actual ones) as The Silver Dollar Saloon (''[[Bonanza]]''), The [[Long Branch Saloon]] (''[[Gunsmoke]]''), and The Last Chance Saloon (''[[The Rifleman]]'').

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Saloons}}
* [[Anti-Saloon League]]

== References ==

{{reflist|2}}

{{Wild West}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Western Saloon}}
[[Category:American Old West]]
[[Category:Drinking establishments in the United States|*]]
[[Category:History of alcoholic beverages]]

[[ar:سالوون]]
[[ca:Saloon]]
[[de:Saloon]]
[[es:Saloon]]
[[fr:Saloon]]
[[it:Saloon]]
[[pt:Saloon]]
[[fi:Saluuna]]
[[sv:Saloon]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
