<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="5995136" ns="0" title="Westover, Arlington, Virginia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|name                     = Westover
|official_name            = 
|settlement_type          = [[Neighborhood]]
|nickname                 = 
|motto                    = 

&lt;!-- Images --&gt;
|image_skyline            = 
|imagesize                = 
|image_caption            = 
|image_flag               = 
|image_seal               = 

&lt;!-- Maps --&gt;
|pushpin_map              = Virginia
|pushpin_label_position   = left&lt;!-- the position of the pushpin label: left, right, top, bottom, none --&gt;
|pushpin_map_caption      = Location within the Commonwealth of Virginia
|pushpin_mapsize          =
|image_map                = 
|map_caption              = Location within Arlington county
|image_map1               = 
|mapsize1                 = 
|map_caption1             = 

&lt;!-- Location --&gt;
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[Virginia]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in Virginia|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Arlington County, Virginia|Arlington]]
|government_footnotes     = 
|government_type          = 
|leader_title             =
|leader_name              =
|leader_title1            = 
|leader_name1             = 
|established_title        = 
|established_date         = 

&lt;!-- Area --&gt;
|unit_pref                = Imperial
|area_footnotes           = 
|area_magnitude           = 
|area_total_km2           = 
|area_land_km2            = 
|area_water_km2           = 

&lt;!-- Population --&gt;
|population_as_of         = [[United States Census, 2000|2000]]
|population_footnotes     = 
|population_total         = 
|population_density_km2   = auto

&lt;!-- General information --&gt;
|timezone                 = [[Eastern Time Zone|Eastern (EST)]]
|utc_offset               = -5
|timezone_DST             = EDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -4
|elevation_footnotes      = 
|elevation_ft             = &lt;!-- --&gt;
|coordinates_display = inline,title
|coordinates_type = region:US_type:city
|latd = 38|latm = 53 |lats = 13|latNS = N
|longd = 77|longm = 8|longs = 22|longEW = W

&lt;!-- Area/postal codes &amp; others --&gt;
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 22205
|area_code                = 703
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               =
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              =
|website                  = 
|footnotes                = 
}}
'''Westover''' is a [[neighborhood]] in [[Arlington County, Virginia|Arlington]], [[Virginia]] on the National Register of Historic Places&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dhr.virginia.gov/registers/Counties/Arlington/000-0032_WestoverHD_photographs.htm&lt;/ref&gt; centered around Washington Boulevard between North McKinley Road and North Longfellow Street.  A true model of mid-century [[Urbanism]], Westover remains a pedestrian friendly neighborhood which sees its residents walk to shops, work, and public transportation&lt;ref&gt;http://www.commuterpage.com/art/villages/westover2.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.  The neighborhood is between the Ballston Station and the East Falls Church Stations, both part of the [[Washington DC Metro]] and is serviced by many Metro Buses.

==History==
During the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, the area that was to become Westover was agricultural in nature, not unlike much of Northern Arlington County at the time. In the mid-nineteenth century, the property was owned by Nicholas Febrey, a civic leader in Arlington and one of the largest landholders in the area&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dhr.virginia.gov/registers/Counties/Arlington/000-0032_WestoverHD_2006_NRfinal.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;.

In the 1890s, small communities began to develop along newly-established [[Northern Virginia trolleys|electric railways]] which serviced the area, as real estate developers began subdividing the land&lt;ref&gt;C.B. Rose, Jr., Arlington Virginia, A History (Arlington, Virginia: Arlington Historical Society, 1976)&lt;/ref&gt;.   One such community was Fostoria, developed by the Fostoria Land and Development Company in 1890, which took advantage of the Washington, Arlington, and Falls Church Electric Railway.  The railroad provided passenger service from Rosslyn to East Falls Church and ran along Four Mile Run&lt;ref&gt;Map of Alexandria County, Virginia for the Virginia Title Co., 1900&lt;/ref&gt;.  By 1907, the neighborhood was known as Highland Park - the earliest houses constructed in the Westover area are located within this community&lt;ref&gt;G.M. Hopkins’ Atlas of Fifteen Miles Around Washington, D.C., 1878. Nan Netherton, Donald Sweig, Janice Artemel, Patricia Hickin, and Patrick Reed, Fairfax County, Virginia: A History, commemorative ed. (Fairfax County, Virginia: Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, 1991)&lt;/ref&gt;. 

A measure of the development in the area at the time, the Walter Reed Elementary School was constructed in 1938 on McKinley Road, originally a section of Febrey farmland.  Though Westover had seen significant development over the previous half century, in 1938, when the school was constructed, the area was still largely undeveloped&lt;ref&gt;“New School Dedicated at Highland Park,” The Washington Post, 19 November 1938&lt;/ref&gt;.  By that time, most of Westover was owned primarily by Ashton C. Jones and his wife, Margaret Rucker.  Jones deeded the land to the local development company, Mace Properties, Inc., which was owned by Miles A. Mace.  In turn, Mace Properties developed the majority of the buildings located in the Westover Historic District between 1939 and 1948&lt;ref&gt;Ames and McClelland, “Historic Residential Suburbs”&lt;/ref&gt;.

Following the principles set forth by the [[Federal Housing Administration|FHA]] and responding to the need for affordable housing, Mace developed several neighborhoods in Arlington County in the early twentieth century which provided economical housing to the growing population. Mace, who lived in Arlington County, was a real estate broker&lt;ref&gt;According to the 1930 United States Census, Mace lived on Glebe Road with his wife, father, mother, and mother-in-law&lt;/ref&gt;.  He was just twenty-six years old when he began to play a role in developing the community of Over-Lee Knolls—adjacent to Westover to the northwest and today considered part of greater Westover.  The Over-Lee Knolls neighborhood was advertised in 1926 as “Virginia’s Ideal Suburb” which emphasized value and quality construction&lt;ref&gt;The Washington Post, 10 October 1926&lt;/ref&gt;.

In October 1938, Arlington County approved the rezoning of {{convert|120|acre|km2}}, which allowed Mace Properties to construct large multi-family apartment buildings&lt;ref&gt;“Arlington Zone Changed for Big Apartments,” The Washington Post, 30 October 1938.&lt;/ref&gt;.  In April 1939, Mace Properties announced that it had received FHA approval for low-cost multi-family rental housing.  The first of these constructed was a of 152 unit garden-style apartment building&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arlingtonva.us/Departments/CPHD/Documents/817011.02%20HC%20item%203.1.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; which cost Mace a total cost of $600,000 to build.  In 1940, the FHA-backed Westover Hills project was announced.  Westover Hills was hailed as the “most ambitious building program in Mace Properties’ [sic] history.”  The dwellings, including single-family houses, twin houses, and garden apartments, were designed by Thelander and Washington, D.C. architect Harry E. Ormston&lt;ref&gt;“Westover Hills New Arlington Home Project,” The Washington Post, 16 June 1940&lt;/ref&gt;.

During 1940, the Westover Shopping Center was constructed -- a 13-store retail center along Washington Boulevard between Longfellow and McKinley Streets&lt;ref&gt;The Arlington Journal, February 2, 1978&lt;/ref&gt;.  The shopping center initially included a [[Safeway Inc.|Safeway]] grocery store&lt;ref&gt;Arlington Sun February 7, 1941&lt;/ref&gt;, a &quot;five and dime&quot; store, and a pharmacy.  In 1958, county planners noted that the center's &quot;retail sales per store [were] higher... than in any of the five nearby competing neighborhood or community centers&lt;ref&gt;Advance Planning Section of the Arlington County Office of Planning, A Study of the Westover Shopping Center, April 1958&lt;/ref&gt;.&quot;  However, by the late seventies, the center's physical condition and sales had declined.  In 1978, the Arlington County Board allocated $50,000 in business and neighborhood conservation funds to supplement $250,000 worth of exterior renovation work planned by the center's owners&lt;ref&gt;The Arlington News, February 16, 1978&lt;/ref&gt;.     

Today, Westover is a residential suburban community and its overall character remains predominately unchanged.  The shopping center continues to provide a mix of retail offerings to the community.  Residences in the neighborhood are still composed mostly of modest, pre-World War II single family homes and garden style apartment complexes such as the Westover Apartments.  Like those in most older suburban neighborhoods, the dwellings in Westover have been adapted to fit modern-day needs and growing families.  In many instances, porches have been enclosed and/or enlarged for additional bathrooms&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dhr.virginia.gov/registers/Counties/Arlington/000-0032_WestoverHD_2006_NRfinal.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Transit==
[[Image:East Falls Church Metro Platform.jpg|left|thumbnail|A woman walks along the East Falls Church Metro station platform]]
Westover has access to many modes of transportation, both public and private.  Approximately 22% of people within Westover's Zip Code (22205) use transit other than a private vehicle to get to work&lt;ref&gt;http://www.movoto.com/Neighborhood.aspx?cityName=arlington&amp;zipcode=22205&amp;State=va&lt;/ref&gt;

The central artery in Westover is [[Washington Boulevard (Arlington)|Washington Boulevard]] which serves as a commercial focal point as well as a regional connector.  

Westover is situated between exit's 69 and 71 on [[Interstate 66]].

Also close by is the [http://www.wmata.com/rail/station_detail.cfm?station_id=100 East Falls Church Metro Station], part of the Washington DC Metro's [[Orange Line (Washington Metro)|Orange Line]].  The community is served by [[Metrobus (Washington, D.C.)|MetroBus]], via the [http://www.wmata.com/bus/timetables/view.cfm?line=152&amp;x=30&amp;y=8 2A, 2B, 2C, and 2G lines]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wmata.com/pdfs/bus/VA.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; which run down Washington Boulevard.  The [[Arlington Transit|Art Bus]] line 52, an Arlington-provided bus system, also passes through the community, though it does not travel through what many consider to be central Westover - Washington Boulevard between North Mckinley and Longfellow Streets&lt;ref&gt;http://www.commuterpage.com/art/51-52main.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.

The [[Washington &amp; Old Dominion Railroad Regional Park|Washington &amp; Old Dominion Railroad]] and [[Custis Trail|Custis]] multi use trails also pass through Southern Westover, connecting the community to [[Falls Church, Virginia|Falls Church]] to the West and [[Rosslyn-Ballston_corridor#Development_patterns|The Rosslyn-Ballston corridor]] and [[Washington, D.C.]] to the East&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arlingtonva.us/Departments/EnvironmentalServices/dot/planning/bike/images/pocket05.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Buildings==
===The Reed School===
[[Image:Reed original facade.jpg|right|thumbnail|225px|Walter Reed School, circa 1939]]
Westover is home to the Walter Reed School, which reopened in October 2009 after significant renovations.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.apsva.us/1540108285711560/blank/browse.asp?A=383&amp;BMDRN=2000&amp;BCOB=0&amp;C=55005&amp;1577Nav=|&amp;NodeID=1596&lt;/ref&gt;.

The Walter Reed Elementary School was built in 1938 by contractor T. Calvin Owens on what was farmland at the time&lt;ref&gt;Lois Snyderman and the Couture/Denig Paternship, 18 Early-Mid Twentieth Century School Buildings Arlington Virginia, December 1991, pp 325-348&lt;/ref&gt;.  In 1950, the school was expanded and altered.  A new 8 classroom wing and mechanical room were added to the rear of the building, while lower level rooms were converted to a library, teachers room, clinic and conference room.  To cope with further population growth, in 1966 an octagonal classroom building was constructed.

On May 9, 2008, a Groundbreaking Ceremony was held at the Reed School site for the $21.6M&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arlingtonva.us/departments/libraries/forums/westover/LibrariesForumsWestoverWestoverReedMain.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; Reed School/Westover Library project.  The project included tearing down the entire building, with the exception of the original 1938 shell, and rebuilding in to a {{convert|61000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} building which houses the new Westover Branch Library and Arlington Public School programs&lt;ref&gt;http://www.grunley.com/portfolio/educational/reed.asp&lt;/ref&gt;. The library reopened on October 31, 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Arlington County Newsroom | url = http://www.arlingtonva.us/departments/Communications/PressReleases/page72938.aspx | accessdate = 2009-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;, having been relocated from its former location approximately one block northeast. 

{{Ref improve section|date=June 2009}}
The school ceased functioning as a traditional educational facility in 1984 due to declining enrollment and the view of then-school superintendent Charles M. Nunley.  The closing occurred in spite of a County funded study which predicted that within 20 years, Reed would be desperately needed to meet the needs of the projected population. True to prediction, the elementary schools that absorbed Reed's student population (McKinley and  [[Tuckahoe Elementary School|Tuckahoe]] elementary schools) are currently (as of SY 2007) the most overcrowded in county.  Reed school was the last &quot;walking school&quot; in Arlington, with 90% of the student body walking to school.  After it closed, 100% of those students living in former Walter Reed districts were required to ride buses to their redistricted schools.

It should be noted, however, that the Reed School was entirely unsuited for use as an elementary school according to modern standards. Not only did it contain large amounts of asbestos and lead paint, it also was extremely difficult to heat and cool and was plagued by problems with mold and excessive humidity. It also was not and could not be made ADA compliant. An addition to the Reed school, built in the late 60s, until recently housed &quot;The Children's School&quot;, a head-start and day-care center, and continues to be used as a polling place and community meeting place.

===Swanson Middle School===
Swanson Middle School is located at the intersection Patrick Henry Drive and Washington Boulevard in Westover.  Swanson is the oldest continuously operating junior high in the Commonwealth of Virginia{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}. Originally a 7-9th grade school, it currently serves 6-8th grade students.  

Swanson Junior High School, built by contractor E. A. Pessagnolo for a cost of $200,941&lt;ref&gt;Arlington County School Board Minutes, Book #2, July 1932-October 1941, p. 341&lt;/ref&gt;, opened in 1939 on land formerly occupied by the A. Duke Torreyson family farm.  In 1955, a large addition off the North side was constructed to add classroom space.  In 1963 and 1968, the central courtyard of the original design was filled in via two additions which accommodated a gymnasium, classrooms, a library, and mechanical rooms&lt;ref&gt;Lois Snyderman and the Couture/Denig Paternship, 18 Early-Mid Twentieth Century School Buildings Arlington Virginia, December 1991, pp. 382-398&lt;/ref&gt;.

In 1958, Swanson was the focus of a racial desegregation controversy when it came under court order to admit an African American student.  The student was &quot;one of seven [plaintiffs] who can attempt to enter white schools under a court order.&quot;  State officials threatened to shut the school down in the fall to avoid the desegregation&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ike-Almond Conference on Virginia Schools&quot;, Washington Post, August 7, 1958.&lt;/ref&gt;.  Ultimately, integration did not actually take place until 1959, when several African American Students were admitted to Stratford Junior High School&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arlingtonva.us/Departments/Libraries/history/LibrariesHistoryLocalHistory.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Commerce==
Westover Village, as it is sometimes called, is home to many Arlington institutions:

[http://www.lostdogcafe.com The Lost Dog Cafe], is a pizza and sandwich shop which was established in 1985.  Originally a carry out place with limited seating, the owners took over adjacent space in the late 1990s and opened a sit down restaurant&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lostdogcafe.com/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.  It expanded again in 2009.  The Lost Dog Cafe is also affiliated with the Lost Dog and Cat Rescue Foundation which was established in 2001. The Lost Dog and Cat Rescue Foundation places an average of 1500 animals annually into permanent homes&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lostdogrescue.org/history.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.

[http://lebanesetaverna.com Lebanese Taverna], the original restaurant in the now regionally-popular chain&lt;ref&gt;http://dc.metromix.com/restaurants/lebanese/lebanese-taverna-montgomery-county/831761/content&lt;/ref&gt; calls Westover home&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lebanesetaverna.com/restaurants/arlington/&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Westover Shopping Center===
The Westover Shopping Center along Washington Boulevard is anchored on the Western end by the Preston King Post Office&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usps.com/communications/newsroom/localnews/va/va_2007_0405.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.  Moving Eastward is small a family-owned and run grocery store, [http://www.westovermarket.com/2038472.html Westover Market].  Westover Market's &quot;Great Wall of Beer&quot; is known throughout the Washington Metropolitan area for its selection of over 550 varieties of beer&lt;ref&gt;http://www.westovermarket.com/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.yelp.com/biz/westover-market-arlington&lt;/ref&gt;.  

[http://:www.washingtonpost.com/gog/stores/j.w.-ayers-variety-and-hardware,800422.html J.W.Ayers Variety &amp; Hardware] is a family-owned and operated independent hardware, housewares and notions store which opened in 1947&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arlingtoncountywebsite.com/ayersvariety.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.  It specializes in keeping in stock items needed in the maintenance of older homes in the area.  Further East is [http://www.tobysicecream.com Toby's Homemade Ice Cream &amp; Coffee], an ice cream and coffee shop featuring ice cream made on the premises, locally roasted gourmet coffee and a well-used community bulletin board.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tobysicecream.com/&lt;/ref&gt;.

==External links==
*[http://www.commuterpage.com/art/villages/westover.htm Arlington's Urban Villages- Westover]
*[http://www.westoverbaptist.org/index.php Westover Baptist Church]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Arlington County, Virginia}}

[[Category:Neighborhoods in Arlington County, Virginia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
