<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="600782" ns="0" title="LinuxChix"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''LinuxChix''' is a women-oriented [[Linux]] community. It is designed to provide both technical and social support for women Linux users, although men are encouraged to help and contribute.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;LinuxChix is a community for women who like Linux and Free Software, and for women and men who want to support women in computing. The membership ranges from novices to experienced users, and includes professional and amateur programmers, system administrators and technical writers.&quot; - {{Citation/make link|http://www.linuxchix.org|LinuxChix - Main Page}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the community are referred to as &quot;a Linux chick&quot; (singular) and &quot;LinuxChix&quot; or &quot;Linux Chix&quot; (plural) regardless of gender.

== Foundation ==
LinuxChix was started in 1998-99 by [[Deb Richardson]], who was a technical writer and web-master at an open source consulting firm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url        = http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-515695.html?legacy=zdnn
|title      = She-geeks confess love for Linux
|work       = [[ZDNet]] News
|author     = Lisa Bowman
|date       = September 15, 1999
|accessdate = 2007-07-15
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070625151809/http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-515695.html?legacy=zdnn &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her reason for founding LinuxChix was to create an alternative to the &quot;[[locker room mentality]]&quot; of other [[Linux User Groups]] and forums. LinuxChix discussion is meant to follow two principles:
# Be polite.
# Be helpful.

== Leadership and structure ==
LinuxChix started out as an [[electronic mailing list]], but soon graduated into a community with regional chapters in several places around the world. In 1999 LinuxChix consisted of a single mailing list, ''grrltalk''. The growth of this mailing list led to the establishment of other mailing lists, beginning with ''techtalk'' for technical discussions and ''issues'' for discussion of women's political issues. LinuxChix was first noticed when [[ZDNet]] published an article on it, which was cross-posted on [[Slashdot]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://technology.guardian.co.uk/online/story/0,,267968,00.html | title = Web Watch:Linux lasses | work = [[The Guardian]] | date = September 23, 1999 | author = Karlin Lillington | accessdate = 2007-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Deb Richardson ran LinuxChix until 2001, when she handed over global coordination and hosting to Melbourne programmer and writer Jenn Vesperman.&lt;ref name=&quot;theage&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/03/29/1017206149200.html | title = Linux grrls break free | work = [[The Age]] | author = Adam Turner | date = April 2, 2002 | accessdate = 2007-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Jenn Vesperman ran the community in a mostly hands-off fashion, delegating almost all tasks including mailing list administration and website maintenance to a group of volunteers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://www.usenix.org/events/usenix04/tech/sigs/full_papers/vesperman/vesperman_html/index.html | title = Building and Maintaining an International Volunteer Linux Community | author = Jenn Vesperman, Val Henson | publisher = Proceedings of the 2004 [[USENIX]] Annual Technical Conference, FREENIX Track | date = June 27–July 2, 2004 | accessdate = 2007-04-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During Jenn Vesperman's tenure, the number of mailing lists tripled. Her tenure saw the foundation of the ''newchix'' mailing list for people new to Linux; the ''courses'' mailing list used by Linux Chix to teach each other specific topics; and the ''grrls-only'' mailing list, the only list closed to male subscribers, founded by Val Henson in 2002. At around the same time, a LinuxChix IRC server was created.

The term ''LinuxChix'' refers to the organisation centered around the official website, the mailing lists and the [[IRC]] channels. The organisation has no official status and the name is used by other groups which are comparatively loosely affiliated with the original LinuxChix group, including local LinuxChix chapters which meet in person, and several national and continental groups which operate more or less independently.

In March 2007, Jenn Vesperman announced that she was retiring as the coordinator, and invited nominations for a new LinuxChix coordinator.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mailman.linuxchix.org/pipermail/announce/2007-March/000536.html Time for a new LinuxChix coordinator]&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2007 Mary Gardiner was announced as the new coordinator, and planned to serve as coordinator until 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.computerworld.com.au/index.php/id;153046089 | title = LinuxChix announces new international coordinator | author = Liz Tay ([[LinuxWorld]]) | work = [[Computerworld]] | date = April 4, 2007 | accessdate = 2007-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; however she resigned in June 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://computerworld.com.sg/ShowPage.aspx?pagetype=2&amp;articleid=5479&amp;pubid=3&amp;tab=Home&amp;issueid=113 | title = Girl trouble forces top LinuxChix to quit| date =  June 19, 2007 | author = Naomi Hamilton | work = Computerworld | accessdate = 2007-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Currently it is led by three lead volunteers known as the &quot;Tres Chix&quot; who are elected by popular vote.  The current coordinators from August 2007 onwards are Sulamita Garcia, Akkana Peck, and [http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/au/1909 Carla Schroder].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.linuxchix.org/linuxchix-coordinators.html | title = LinuxChix coordinators| work = LinuxChix homepage | accessdate = 2008-04-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Regional chapters==
LinuxChix allows local groups following its principles to use its name. Currently the regional chapters listed on the Linuxchix website for each country are:

; Africa
* [http://www.africalinuxchix.org/ African Linuxchix homepage] : In 2004 a new chapter started in Africa &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.hindustantimes.com/StoryPage/StoryPage.aspx?id=54f59036-777a-4c3b-9226-ea355788bc34 | title = An African bid to educate women on IT | work = [[Hindustan Times]] | author = [[Indo-Asian News Service]] | date = April 13, 2006 | accessdate = 2007-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

; Asia
* India : In July 2005, Archana Raghupathy started the Indian chapter [http://india.linuxchix.org LinuxChix-India]. Besides the website wiki they have a [http://mailman.linuxchix.org/mailman/listinfo/indichix mailing list] and an IRC channel #indichix hosted on irc.linuxchix.org servers.

* Indonesia

* Malaysia : [http://fosschix.my FOSSchix.my] founded in September 2008, started in a chatroom among OSS enthusiasts when discussing how LinuxChix doesn't have a chapter in Malaysia. Feeling that Linux can be a bit intimidating for newbies, FOSSchix is adopted instead.

* Philippines

; Australasia and Oceania
* Australia &lt;ref name=&quot;theage&quot;/&gt; :  In March 2007, on the [[International Women's Day]], Australia's two LinuxChix chapters united to form a nationwide LinuxChix chapter called &quot;AussieChix&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.linux.com/articles/60660 | title = Australia's LinuxChix unite to form AussieChix | author = Melissa Draper | date = March 7, 2007 | accessdate = 2007-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* New Zealand : In 2007, the New Zealand chapter was established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/SC0702/S00057.htm | title = Announcing Linuxchix New Zealand | author = LinuxChix NZ Press Release | date = 26 February 2007 | accessdate = 2007-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

; Chicas Linux
* [http://chicaslinux.org Chicas Linux] is a community created by women with the goal of offering a meeting space for people with a common interest in Linux and free software.

; Europe
* France
* Italy
* Lithuania
* London, England
* Poland

; North America

* Canada :  Ottawa, Saskatchewan, Sherbrooke/Québec, and  Vancouver/British Columbia.
* United States : Colorado Springs, Colorado ; Dallas–Fort Worth, Texas ; Denver, Colorado ; [http://linuxchixla.org/ Los Angeles, California] ; Madison, Wisconsin ; [http://www.phillychix.org/ Philadelphia, Pennsylvania] ; [http://seattlelinuxchix.org/ Seattle, Washington] ; Silicon Valley, California ; Washington, District of Columbia.

; South America
* Brazil
* Peru

== Events ==
Some local LinuxChix chapters hold regular meetings, others only meet up on special occasions, such as welcoming a Linuxchix member into town, or in conjunction with various technical conferences. In 2007 members of the Sydney chapter organized a [http://lca2007.linux.org.au/Miniconfs/Linuxchix LinuxChix miniconf] at [[linux.conf.au]] at UNSW.&lt;ref&gt;[http://builderau.com.au/news/soa/Women_flock_to_Linux_talkfest/0,339028227,339272778,00.htm Women flock to Linux talkfest], [http://lca2007.linux.org.au/Miniconfs/Linuxchix/Proposal Original proposal]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linux.com/article.pl?sid=07/02/07/1645205 Portrait: LinuxChix Brazil's Sulamita Garcia]&lt;/ref&gt; Many chapters also organize events on special occasions; for eg., in 2005, LinuxChix Africa organized an event to celebrate [[Software Freedom Day]] at [[Wits University]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tectonic.co.za/view.php?src=rss&amp;id=596 Open source message hits Wits University]&lt;/ref&gt;

===LinuxChix labs===
The Indian chapter (aka [http://mailman.linuxchix.org/mailman/listinfo/indichix IndiChix]) which was featured in the Economic Times recently{{when|date=September 2011}} &lt;ref&gt;[http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/Infotech/Software/LinuxChix-India_aims_at_free_software_access_for_women/articleshow/3217080.cms IndiChix featured in the Economic Times]&lt;/ref&gt; has started an initiative for Linux labs in a number of cities in India. This would serve as a space equipped with PCs (or women could bring their laptops) and an internet connection where women can learn more about Gnu/Linux, collaborate and meet each other to contribute to the Libre software community. Currently{{When|date=September 2011}} the labs have gone live in Bangalore, Delhi, Mumbai, and Pune.

==Other &quot;-Chix&quot; named women's groups==
In 2006, LinuxChix inspired the creation of [http://wikichix.org/wiki/WikiChix WikiChix], a wiki and mailing list for female wiki editors to discuss issues of gender bias in wikis, to promote wikis to potential female editors, and for general discussion of wikis in a friendly female-only environment.

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.linuxchix.org LinuxChix website]
* [http://www.linuxchix.org/content/chapters/ LinuxChix regional chapters]

== See also ==
*[[Linux User Group]]

[[Category:Internet properties established in 1999]]
[[Category:Mailing lists]]
[[Category:Linux User Groups]]

[[tl:LinuxChix]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
