<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6011178" ns="0" title="VMware Player"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
|                   name = VMware Player
|                   logo = [[File:VMware Player logo.png|64px]]
|             screenshot = [[File:VMware Player.png|300px]]
|                caption = VMware Player running [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] v8.04.1
|              developer = [[VMware]]
| latest release version = 4.0.1&lt;ref name=&quot;release_notes&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vmware.com/support/player40/doc/releasenotes_player40.html |title=VMware Player 4.0 Release Notes}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|    latest release date = {{release date|2011|11|17}}&lt;ref name=&quot;release_notes&quot; /&gt;
|       operating system = [[Microsoft Windows]]&lt;br&gt;[[Linux]]
|                  genre = [[Virtual machine]]
|                license = [[Freeware]] for personal non-commercial use; distribution requires permission&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=FAQs |url=http://www.vmware.com/products/player/faqs.html |work=VMware Player home page |publisher=VMware, Inc |accessdate=23 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|                website = {{URL|http://www.vmware.com/products/player/}}
}}
'''VMware Player''' is a freeware virtualization software package from [[VMware|VMware, Inc.]]&lt;ref name=&quot;player&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vmware.com/products/player/|title=VMware Player – The Easiest Way to Run a Virtual Machine}}&lt;/ref&gt; (a company which was formerly a division of and whose majority shareholder remains [[EMC Corporation]]). VMware Player can run [[virtual appliance]]s. VMware Player can also create [[virtual machine]]s since version 3.0. It uses the same virtualization core as VMware Workstation, a similar program with more features, and not free of charge. VMware Player is available for personal non-commercial use, or for distribution or other use by written agreement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vmware.com/download/eula/player31.html |title=VMware Player 4.0 EULA |publisher=VMware |accessdate=23 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Features ==
VMware claims the Player offers better graphics, faster performance, and tighter integration for running [[Windows XP]] under Windows Vista or Windows 7 than Microsoft's [[Windows XP Mode]] running on [[Windows Virtual PC]], which is free of charge for all purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;player&quot; /&gt;

Versions earlier than 3 of VMware Player were unable to create virtual machines, requiring the user to download pre-created virtual appliances or create machines for use in Player with the full [[VMware Workstation]], or manually create and edit the plain text &quot;.vmx&quot; file that defines a virtual machine. From version 3.0.0 this limitation no longer applies: users can create virtual machines in the GUI. The features of Workstation not available in Player are now &quot;developer-centric features such as Teams, multiple Snapshots and Clones, and Virtual Rights Management features for end-point security&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vmware.com/products/player/faqs.html |title=VMware Player – Frequently Asked Questions}}&lt;/ref&gt; Player allows a complete virtual machine to be copied at any time by copying a [[directory (file systems)|directory]]; while not a fully featured snapshot facility, this does allow a copy of a machine in a particular state to be stored, and reverted to later if desired, e.g. after a demonstration or a virus infection test.

VMware Player is also supplied with the VMware Workstation distribution, for use in installations where not all client users are licensed to use the full VMware Workstation. An IT administrator can create a virtual machine using Workstation, then deploy it to unlicensed computers using Player without paying for an additional VMware license.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010|Reason=The license says &quot;personal non-commercial use&quot;.}}

==Resources==
Many ready-made virtual machines (VMs) which run on VMWare Player, Workstation, and other virtualization software are available&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vmware.com/appliances/directory/ Directory of VMs on VMWare website with 1539 entries as of 7 January 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bagside.com/bagvapp/index.html Bagside VMware images of various free operating systems]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thoughtpolice.co.uk/ Thoughtpolice VMware images for Linux]&lt;/ref&gt; for specific purposes, either for purchase or free of charge; for example a free [[Linux]]-based &quot;browser appliance&quot; with the [[Firefox]] browser installed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vmware.com/appliances/directory/80 VMWare Browser Appliance page]&lt;/ref&gt; which can be used for safe Web browsing; if infected or damaged it can be discarded and replaced by a clean copy. The appliance can be configured to automatically reset itself after each use so personal information is not stored. VMs distributed legally only have freely distributable [[operating system]], as operating systems on VMs must be licensed; ready-to-use Microsoft Windows VMs, in particular, are not distributed, except for evaluation versions.

== See also ==
* [[Comparison of platform virtual machines]]
* [[List of VMware software]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{Official|http://www.vmware.com/products/player/}}
* [http://open-vm-tools.sourceforge.net/ Open Virtual Machine Tools]
* [http://www.v3.co.uk/vnunet/downloads/2158957/vmware-player/ V3.co.uk Review of VMWare Player 3.1.2]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vmware Player}}
[[Category:VMware]]
[[Category:Virtualization software]]
[[Category:Proprietary cross-platform software]]

[[id:VMware Player]]
[[it:VMware Player]]
[[ru:VMware Player]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
