<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6024874" ns="0" title="Santa Clarita, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Santa Clara, California}}
{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Santa Clarita
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|nickname                 =
|image_skyline            = santaclaritawelcomesign.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            = Santa Clarita Welcome Sign
|image_flag               =
|image_seal               = Current_Santa_Clarita_Seal.jpg
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Santa Clarita highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Santa Clarita in [[California]] and [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          = [[Council-manager government|Council-Manager]]
|leader_title             = Mayor
|leader_name              = Marsha McLean
|leader_title1            = Mayor Pro-Tem
|leader_name1             = Laurie Ender
|leader_title2            = City Council
|leader_name2             = Frank Ferry&lt;br/&gt;Bob Kellar&lt;br/&gt;Laurene Weste&lt;br/&gt;
|leader_title3            = City Manager
|leader_name3             = Ken Pulskamp
|established_title        = Incorporated
|established_date         = December 15, 1987
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 52.781
| area_land_sq_mi         = 52.716
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.065
| area_total_km2          = 136.702
| area_land_km2           = 136.535
| area_water_km2          = 0.168
| area_water_percent      = 0.12
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          = [[U.S. Census, 2010]]
|population_total         = 176320
|population_rank          =[[List of cities in Los Angeles County, California|4th]] in Los Angeles County&lt;br/&gt;[[List of largest California cities by population|24th]] in California&lt;br/&gt;[[List of United States cities by population|132nd]] in the United States
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_blank1_title = [[Demonym]]
|population_blank1 = Santa Claritan
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latd = 34 |latm = 25 |lats = 00 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 30 |longs = 23 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 368
|elevation_ft             = 1207
|website                  = [http://www.santa-clarita.com/ www.santa-clarita.com]
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 91310, 91321-91322, 91350-91351, 91354-91355, 91380-91387, 91390
|area_code                = [[Area code 661|661]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-69088
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1662338
|footnotes                =
}}
[[Image:Santaclaritaintersection.jpg|thumb|right|300px|A typical stretch of Valencia Boulevard in the Valencia part of Santa Clarita. The bridge in the distance carries a ''paseo'' (a type of dedicated pedestrian pathway) over the roadway.]]

'''Santa Clarita''' is the fourth largest city in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]],  [[United States]] and the [[list of cities in California (by population)|twenty-fourth]] largest city in the state of California. The 2010 US Census reported the city's population grew 16.7% from the year 2000 to 176,320 residents. It is located about {{convert|35|mi|km}} northwest of downtown [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]], and occupies most of the [[Santa Clarita Valley]]. It is a notable example of a U.S. [[edge city]] or [[boomburb]]. The [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] rates it as the sixth safest city in the United States with at least 100,000 inhabitants. Santa Clarita was ranked as number 18 of the top 100 places to live by ''[[Money (magazine)|Money]]'' magazine in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://money.cnn.com/magazines/moneymag/bplive/2006/top100/index.html MONEY Magazine: Best places to live 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

Santa Clarita was incorporated in 1987 as the union of several previously existing communities, including [[Canyon Country, Santa Clarita, California|Canyon Country]], [[Newhall, Santa Clarita, California|Newhall]], [[Saugus, Santa Clarita, California|Saugus]], and [[Valencia, Santa Clarita, California|Valencia]], all of which are the land of the former [[Rancho San Francisco]]. Its principal boundaries are the [[Golden State Freeway|Golden State]] (I-5) and [[Antelope Valley Freeway|Antelope Valley]] (SR-14) freeways; their merger in [[Newhall Pass]] at the city's southernmost point gives Santa Clarita a triangular appearance on the map.

Santa Clarita is usually associated with the [[Six Flags Magic Mountain]] [[amusement park]], though the park is located just outside city limits in unincorporated Los Angeles County, and the [[California Institute of the Arts]] (CalArts), located in Valencia.

==History==
'''Santa Clarita''' was only fairly recently incorporated (1987), but its history runs deep. About AD 450, the [[Tataviam]] people arrived, numbering about 2,000 at their zenith.

In 1842, six years before the better-publicized discovery in the Sacramento area, Francisco Lopez made the first documented discovery of gold in California (the document is a mining claim signed by Gov. Juan B. Alvarado in that year). The discovery was made in [http://www.scvhistory.com/scvhistory/placerita.htm Placerita Canyon], an area later used as Hollywood's original back lot.

The community of Newhall is named after [[Henry Mayo Newhall|Henry Newhall]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.newhallfoundation.org/aboutHMN.html | title=About Henry Mayo Newhall | publisher=Henry Mayo Newhall Foundation | year=2000 | accessdate=2007-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; a businessman who made his original fortune during the [[California Gold Rush]] after opening up the H.M. Newhall &amp; Company; an extremely successful auction house in [[San Francisco|San Francisco, CA]]  Newhall's next business interest was railroads. He invested in rail companies that would connect San Francisco to other cities and became president of the [[San Francisco and San Jose Railroad]]. In 1870, he and his partners sold the company to [[Southern Pacific Railroad]], whose board of directors he then sat on.  After railroads, Newhall turned his eye to real estate and ranching. He purchased a number of the old Spanish and Mexican land grants in the state for a total of {{convert|143,000|acre|km2}} between Monterey and Los Angeles counties. The most significant portion was the {{convert|46,460|acre|km2}} [[Rancho San Francisco]] in northern Los Angeles County, which he purchased for $2/acre, and which became known as Newhall Ranch after Newhall's death. Within this territory, he granted a right-of-way to Southern Pacific through what is now Newhall Pass, and he also sold them a portion of the land, upon which the company built a town they named after him: Newhall. The first station built on the line he named for his hometown, [[Saugus, Massachusetts]].  Following his death, Newhall's heirs incorporated the [[Newhall Land and Farming Company]], which oversaw the development of the communities that now make up the city of Santa Clarita.

On September 26, 1876, Charles Alexander Mentry brought in the state's first productive oil well at [[Mentryville]], giving rise to the California oil industry. The oil was brought to a refinery at Newhall; today it is the oldest existing refinery in the world. (It was operational from 1874 to 1888.)

A few days earlier, on September 5, 1876, [[Charles Crocker]] and [[Leland Stanford]] joined their railroads in Canyon Country, linking Los Angeles with the rest of the nation for the first time.

The Saugus Cafe, on Railroad Avenue in [[Saugus, Santa Clarita, California|Saugus]], was established in 1887&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scvhistory.com/scvhistory/sauguscafe.htm &quot;Tales of the Saugus Cafe], at [http://www.scvhistory.com/scvhistory/scvhistory.php ''Santa Clarita Valley History in Pictures''] (retrieved July 22, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; and appears to be, by far, the oldest still-operating restaurant in Los Angeles County.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chowhound.com/topics/62541 &quot;Centenarian (and older) restaurants?&quot;] [[Chowhound]] (post dated August 26, 2004, retrieved July 22, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt;

Filming in Santa Clarita began shortly after the turn of the 20th century with a veritable Who's Who of actors including [[William S. Hart]], [[Tom Mix]], [[Harry Carey (actor)|Harry Carey]] and a young [[John Wayne]]. Hart and Carey made their homes in the Santa Clarita Valley; today both are operated as county parks.

The Santa Clarita Valley was the scene of the second worst disaster in California history &amp;mdash; The History Channel called it the &quot;worst civil engineering failure of the 20th century&quot; &amp;mdash; when, on the night of March 12, 1928, [[William Mulholland]]'s [[St. Francis Dam]] collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scvhs&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.scvhistory.com/scvhistory/stfrancis.htm  | title= SAN FRANCISQUITO CANYON and the ST. FRANCIS DAM | publisher= [[Santa Clarita Valley Historical Society]] | accessdate=2007-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the time the floodwaters reached the Pacific Ocean near Ventura, an estimated 450 people were dead. Within modern Santa Clarita city limits, the site of the future Westfield Valencia Town Center mall was buried beneath muck and mud. Numerous buildings within Santa Clarita became makeshift morgues.

==Geography==
'''Santa Clarita''' is located at {{Coord|34.416561|-118.506443|region:US_type:city|format=dms|display=inline,title}} (34.416561, -118.506443).{{GR|1}}  According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|52.8|sqmi|km2}}.  {{convert|52.7|sqmi|km2}} of it is land and {{convert|0.065|sqmi|km2}} of it (0.12%) is water.

Santa Clarita is situated near the San Fernando fault zone and was affected by the [[1971 San Fernando earthquake]], also known as the Sylmar quake.  The city was also affected by the [[1994 Northridge earthquake]], and many commercial and residential buildings were devastated by its aftermath, including the nearby Newhall pass, the Valencia Mall, and Six Flags Magic Mountain.  The 38 story tall Sky Tower at Magic Mountain swayed 6 feet in each direction during the Northridge earthquake with only minor damages.

===Wildfires===

Santa Clarita is one of the top areas in the nation for wildfire activity. Recent fires in and around the city of Santa Clarita include the Stables (2001), Copper (2002), Bouquet (2002), Simi (2003), Verdale (2003), Foothill (2004), Buckweed (2007), Ranch (2007), Magic (2007), and Sayre (2008) Fires.

===Climate===
Santa Clarita is warm and dry for most of the year with very little rainfall and hot dry summers, due to its close proximity to the Mojave Desert. Characterized by dry hills covered in brush, the months of late summer and early autumn are often referred to as &quot;fire season.&quot; The warmest months of the year are July through September, although it is not unusual for the temperature to reach 100 degrees in early October. Winters are mild, with temperatures dropping below freezing only occasionally on clear winter nights. Rain falls primarily from December through February. Snow has occurred before and was last seen on April 8, 2011 and February 26, 2011, where some areas received a dusting.The area also received measurable snow on January 2, 2011(1-4&amp;nbsp;inches).
{{Weather box
|location = Santa Clarita
|single line = Yes
|Jan high F = 64
|Feb high F = 66
|Mar high F = 68
|Apr high F = 74
|May high F = 79
|Jun high F = 89
|Jul high F = 96
|Aug high F = 94
|Sep high F = 91
|Oct high F = 82
|Nov high F = 72
|Dec high F = 65
|year high F = 78
|Jan low F = 36
|Feb low F = 37
|Mar low F = 38
|Apr low F = 41
|May low F = 45
|Jun low F = 50
|Jul low F = 54
|Aug low F = 55
|Sep low F = 52
|Oct low F = 46
|Nov low F = 39
|Dec low F = 36
|year low F = 44
|Jan precipitation inch = 2.99
|Feb precipitation inch = 3.50
|Mar precipitation inch = 3.03
|Apr precipitation inch = .63
|May precipitation inch = .22
|Jun precipitation inch = .01
|Jul precipitation inch = .01
|Aug precipitation inch = .11
|Sep precipitation inch = .27
|Oct precipitation inch = .36
|Nov precipitation inch = 1.22
|Dec precipitation inch = 1.61
|year precipitation inch = 13.96
|source 1 = &lt;ref name= &gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.weather.com/outlook/health/achesandpains/climatology/monthly/USCA1019?from=36hr_newslinker2 |title=Average weather for Santa Clarita |accessdate=28 March 2008 |publisher=Weather.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=August 2010
}}

==Demographics==
{{Historical Populations
|type=USA
|1990|110642
|2000|151088
|2010|176320
| footnote=source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/index.html
  |title=CENSUS OF POPULATION AND HOUSING (1790-2000)
  |publisher=[[U.S. Census Bureau]]
  |accessdate=2010-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Santa Clarita had a population of 176,320. The [[population density]] was 3,340.6 people per square mile (1,289.8/km²). The racial makeup of Santa Clarita was 125,005 (70.9%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 5,623 (3.2%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 1,013 (0.6%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 15,025 (8.5%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]] (3.4% Filipino, 1.7% Korean, 0.8% Indian, 0.8% Chinese, 0.6% Japanese, 0.3% Vietnamese, 0.9% Other Asian), 272 (0.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 21,169 (12.0%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 8,213 (4.7%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 51,941 persons (29.5%). 

The Census reported that 174,910 people (99.2% of the population) lived in households, 1,281 (0.7%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 129 (0.1%) were institutionalized.  

There were 59,507 households, out of which 24,677 (41.5%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 34,126 (57.3%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 6,888 (11.6%) had a female householder with no husband present, 3,322 (5.6%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 3,134 (5.3%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 484 (0.8%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 11,634 households (19.6%) were made up of individuals and 4,335 (7.3%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.94.  There were 44,336 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (74.5% of all households); the average family size was 3.37.

The population was spread out with 46,180 people (26.2%) under the age of 18, 17,565 people (10.0%) aged 18 to 24, 47,788 people (27.1%) aged 25 to 44, 47,936 people (27.2%) aged 45 to 64, and 16,851 people (9.6%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 36.2 years. For every 100 females there were 97.1 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 94.0 males.

There were 62,055 housing units at an average density of 1,175.7 per square mile (453.9/km²), of which 42,335 (71.1%) were owner-occupied, and 17,172 (28.9%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.4%; the rental vacancy rate was 6.0%.  124,532 people (70.6% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 50,378 people (28.6%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 151,088 people, 50,787 households, and 38,242 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 3,159.1 inhabitants per square mile (1,219.6/km²).  There were 52,442 housing units at an average density of 1,096.5 per square mile (423.3/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 69.02% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 20.50% [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race, 8.54% from [[Race (U.S. Census)|other races]], 5.24% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 3.89% from two or more races, 2.07% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.59% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.15% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/SAFFFacts?_event=&amp;geo_id=16000US0669088&amp;_geoContext=01000US%7C04000US06%7C16000US0669088&amp;_street=&amp;_county=santa+clarita&amp;_cityTown=santa+clarita&amp;_state=&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=160&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=ACS_2006_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= Census 2000 Demographic Profile: Santa Clarita&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

There were 50,787 households out of which 44.4% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 61.0% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 9.8% had a female householder with no husband present, and 24.7% were non-families. 18.7% of all households were made up of individuals and 6.1% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.95 and the average family size was 3.38.

In the city the population was spread out with 30.3% under the age of 18, 8.1% from 18 to 24, 33.6% from 25 to 44, 20.8% from 45 to 64, and 7.1% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 33 years. For every 100 females there were 98.0 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 94.4 males.

According to a 2007 estimate, the median income for a household in the city was $79,004, and the median income for a family was $91,450.&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/STTable?_bm=y&amp;-context=st&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2007_1YR_G00_S1901&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2007_1YR_G00_&amp;-CONTEXT=st&amp;-tree_id=307&amp;-redoLog=false&amp;-_caller=geoselect&amp;-geo_id=16000US0669088&amp;-format=&amp;-_lang=en Santa Clarita city, California - Fact Sheet]&lt;/ref&gt; Males had a median income of $53,769 versus $36,835 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $26,841.  6.4% of the population and 4.7% of families were below the [[poverty line]].   6.7% of those under the age of 18 and 5.9% of those 65 and older were living below the poverty line.

==Government==
===Local government===

According to the city’s most recent Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, the city’s various funds had $190.1 million in Revenues, $143.4 million in expenditures, $1,062.6 million in total assets, $149.8 million in total liabilities, and $222.9 million in cash and investments.&lt;ref name=&quot;City of Santa Clarita CAFR&quot;&gt;[http://www.santa-clarita.com/cityhall/admin/cafr/CAFR08/Financial%20Report.pdf City of Santa Clarita CAFR] Retrieved 2009-08-14&lt;/ref&gt;

The structure of the management and coordination of city services is:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.santa-clarita.com/cityhall/admin/cafr/CAFR08/Financial%20Report.pdf  City of Santa Clarita CAFR] Retrieved 2009-08-14&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! City Department
! Director
|-
|City Manager
|Ken Pulskamp
|-
|Assistant City Manager
|Ken Striplin
|-
|City Attorney
|Joe Montes
|-
|Director of Community Development
|Paul Brotzman
|-
|Director of Parks, Recreation &amp; Community Services
|Richard Gould
|-
|Deputy City Manager / Director of Administrative Services
|Darren Hernández
|-
|Director of Public Works / City Engineer
|Robert Newman
|}

===Politics===
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]], Santa Clarita is located in the 17th and 19th [[California State Senate|Senate]] Districts, represented by Republicans [[Sharon Runner]] and [[Tony Strickland]] respectively, and in the 38th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Republican [[Cameron Smyth]]. Federally, Santa Clarita is located in [[California's 25th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of R +7&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Republican [[Howard McKeon|Buck McKeon]].

===Education===
====School districts====
*[[Castaic Union School District]] [http://www.castaic.k12.ca.us/]
*[[Newhall School District]] [http://www.newhall.k12.ca.us/]
*[[Saugus Union School District]] [http://www.saugus.k12.ca.us/]
*[[Sulphur Springs School District]] [http://www.sssd.k12.ca.us/]
*[[William S. Hart High School District]] [http://www.hart.k12.ca.us/]

====Colleges and universities====
*[[California Institute of the Arts]]
*[[The Master's College]] [http://www.masters.edu]
*[[College of the Canyons]] [http://www.canyons.edu]

===Parks and recreation===
The city of Santa Clarita's leadership has placed a priority on offering recreational facilities and programs since incorporation. Many youth-friendly activities and diversions exist in order to steer the city's children away from crime and gang activity. The city has established many neighborhood parks and maintains a comprehensive recreation program. There is a recreation center in Canyon Country that includes an aquatic park with wading, diving, and Olympic [[swimming pool]]s along with a bicycle/[[skatepark]], community swimming pools in both Newhall and Canyon Country and a community center in downtown Newhall. The city's largest park is located in Saugus and is known as Central Park. There are currently a total of seventeen parks scattered in various neighborhoods throughout the city. Many have lighted [[tennis court|tennis]] and [[basketball court]]s, [[baseball field|baseball]] and [[soccer field]]s. There are over {{convert|3000|acre|km2}} of open space and {{convert|32|mi|km}} of off-street trails within its boundaries.

Over the past several years, the city has cosponsored a summer concert series offering a variety of music in cooperation with various local businesses. These concerts are free of charge and take place on weekends in Central Park.  The city offers a wide variety of fee-based and free classes and programs in a variety of locations throughout the year.  These programs are listed in the quarterly magazine ''Seasons'' which is delivered to all residences within the city limits via [[United States Postal Service|mail]].

The Santa Clarita Marathon is held annually in November. The race was first run in 1995 and is now a qualifying race for the [[Boston Marathon]].

Santa Clarita was picked to be the end of Stage 6 in the AMGEN [[Tour of California]], in 2007. Santa Clarita was also picked to be the end of Stage 6 and the beginning of  the final stage, Stage 7, in 2008.

There are several public and private golf courses in Santa Clarita, including, TPC Valencia, Valencia Country Club, and Vista Valencia. The city is also home to a public ice skating rink called the ''[[Ice Station Valencia]]''.

===Law enforcement and fire protection===
Santa Clarita does not have its own police or fire departments. The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] (LASD) operates the Santa Clarita Valley Station in Santa Clarita and provides local police protection for the city.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for1/scv/index.html Santa Clarita Valley Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The city contracts with the [[Los Angeles County Fire Department]] for fire protection. Currently, the agency has eight fire stations in Santa Clarita, but with the increasing growth in the area new stations are planned.



==Economy==
[[Princess Cruises]] and [[MannKind Corporation|MannKind]] are based in Santa Clarita.

==Largest employers==
[[File:Siege social de la princess cruise et de la cunard.jpg|thumb|right|[[Princess Cruises]] headquarters in Santa Clarita]]
According to the City's 2010 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.santa-clarita.com/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=2404 City of Santa Clarita CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[Six Flags Magic Mountain]]
|3,689
|-
|2
| [[Princess Cruises]]
|2,100
|-
|3
|[[Henry Mayo Newhall Memorial Hospital]]
|1,212
|-
|4
| [[Woodward, Inc.|Woodward HRT]]
|845
|-
|5
|[[The Master's College]]
|755
|-
|6
|[[Quest Diagnostics|Specialty Laboratories]]
|725
|-
|7
|[[arvato services]]
|586
|-
|8
|[[California Institute of the Arts]]
|500
|-
|9
|[[The Marvin Group|Aerospace Dynamics]]
|450
|-
|10
|Market Tech Media
|407
|}

===Enterprise Zone===
On July 1, 2007, to offer new businesses tax incentives to operate inside Santa Clarita, the industrial and commercial areas in northern and western Santa Clarita were zoned as a federally recognized Enterprise Zone. Additional warehousing and office space was also constructed. Presently, the Santa Clarita Enterprise Zone covers 97% of all commercial, business, and industrial zoned land within the city of Santa Clarita. This zoning allows local businesses to claim hiring, sales and use tax credits.

The newly designated Enterprise Zone is now the base of operations for several large companies, including True Position Technologies, Salt Creek Grille, [[Condomman.com]], and Trigg Laboratories.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.santaclaritaenterprisezone.com http://www.santaclaritaenterprisezone.com] ''santaclaritaenterprisezone.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

===New home development===
Santa Clarita has experienced significant new home growth led by various builders such as [[K. Hovnanian Homes]] and [[Lennar]].

*[[Newhall Ranch in Valencia, California|Newhall Ranch]] is a new community that will break ground in 2012 and bring in 70,000 people to Santa Clarita as well as create 20,000 new jobs{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}.

==Media==
The City of Santa Clarita and surrounding communities are served by several local media properties.

===Newspapers===
The primary daily newspaper, The [[Santa Clarita Signal]], was founded in 1919 and enjoys a weekday circulation of [http://www.verifiedaudit.com/results.php?publication_name=&amp;type_of_report=circulation&amp;publisher_name=&amp;city=santa+clarita&amp;state=&amp;type=&amp;Circulation+Report2=Search ''10,454''] and a Sunday circulation of [http://www.verifiedaudit.com/results.php?publication_name=&amp;type_of_report=circulation&amp;publisher_name=&amp;city=santa+clarita&amp;state=&amp;type=&amp;Circulation+Report2=Search ''11,598'']. The newspaper, which focuses almost exclusively on local news, sports, entertainment and features, is owned by [[Morris Multimedia]], Inc., of [[Savannah, Georgia]]. The Signal's offices on Creekside Road serve as the newspaper's newsroom, production office, IT and web design facility, and printing facility.

Additionally, Santa Clarita is served by the [[Los Angeles Daily News]], a subsidiary of the [[Los Angeles Newspaper Group]] which itself is owned by [[MediaNews Group]] of [[Denver]]. The ''Daily News'' primarily focuses on news, sports and entertainment stories in the [[San Fernando Valley]] and Los Angeles, but also covers Santa Clarita periodically.  ''Daily News'' circulation numbers within the Santa Clarita Valley are not known, but the paper enjoys a circulation of some 157,000 in the greater Los Angeles region, according to its website.

===Radio===
The Santa Clarita Valley is exclusively served by one radio station: AM-1220 KHTS. The commercial radio station, operated by long time residents and public servants Carl and Jeri-Seratti Goldman, broadcasts from studios located in Canyon Country.  The station carries local news, traffic, weather, sports, music and talk shows.  The station's transmitter and antennas are located on [[Sierra Highway]] between Soledad Canyon Rd. and Sand Canyon Rd.  The station has been on the air since October, 2003.  Prior to [[KHTS (AM)|KHTS]], AM-1220 was known as KBET until 1999 when the Goldmans sold it to now-Clear Channel Communications, only to buy it back in 2003.

In addition to KHTS, the City of Santa Clarita and its surrounding communities are indirectly served by a number of major market Los Angeles FM and AM radio stations, though residents often complain that radio reception in the valley is poor due to the surrounding hillsides.

There are also several other Internet Based Radio Stations that serve the public in the Santa Clarita Valley.

===Television===
All local programming for Santa Clarita is carried on a single [[Public-access television]] [[cable TV]] channel, which is operated by SCVTV, a tax-exempt 501c3 nonprofit corporation. It is available to [[Time Warner Cable]] customers throughout the Santa Clarita Valley on Channel 20 and to AT&amp;T U-verse customers under local programming (Channel 99/Santa Clarita). SCVTV carries public, educational and government programming, including Santa Clarita City Council and Planning Commission meetings, history shows, high school and college news programs, talk shows, football games and other programs of local interest.

There are no commercial over-the-air [[television station]]s in the Santa Clarita Valley. The city is part of the [[Los Angeles]] [[media market]].  [[Digital television|Digital]] signals from the Los Angeles stations are available on local [[Cable television|cable television systems]], [[DirecTV]] and [[Dish Network]].

===Television and movie production===

From the first decade of the 20th century to the present day, the Santa Clarita Valley has been a favorite location for producers of films, television shows, and commercials. Even before the first permanent movie set was erected in 1922, the areas topography was exploited for its versatility as the prototypical Western setting. As the &quot;A&quot; Western of the 1910s, '20s and '30s gave way to the &quot;B&quot; Western of the 1940s and '50s, the Santa Clarita Valley continued to play its role, most notably at Gene Autry's Melody Ranch Motion Picture Studio in Placerita Canyon and, later, at [[The Walt Disney Company]]'s nearby [[Golden Oak Ranch]]. 

The first motion-picture studio, developed within a high tech Industrial Park across from Magic Mountain, [http://www.valenciastudios.com/ Valencia Studios] was [http://articles.latimes.com/1989-10-24/business/fi-521_1_valencia-studios founded in 1986 by Robert Thompson]. Most industry experts were initially skeptical about locating a studio in such a remote location. The first motion picture to be shot on its stages was [http://www.insidehollywood.info/index.php?pg=address-valencia-studios&amp;mn=sl Return of the Living Dead, part 2]. Since its inauspicious beginnings, it has featured many high budget movies and television shows such as [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0103064/ Terminator 2] and [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0092007/ Star Trek 4] in the early 90s to [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1099212/ Twilight] in 2008 and the CBS Paramount television series NCIS in 2011. Over the years, Santa Clarita Valley became the home to many [http://www.sc-studios.com/ other studios] as well as hundreds of entertainment related businesses, sometimes nicknamed, the &quot;New Hallywood&quot;, after one of its communities NewHall. The [http://www.filmsantaclarita.com/ Santa Clarita film commission] maintains a vast location library of potential movie sites. 

While the area has a long history of doubling for other places, on rare occasions the Santa Clarita Valley is credited as &quot;itself;&quot; as in the opening of ''[[Ocean's Thirteen]]'' when Brad Pitt and crew attempt to rob a [[Toys R Us]] in Valencia.

Santa Clarita's proximity to Hollywood has seen a number of TV shows and movies filmed in the area:

====Select television productions====
* ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]'' (The city was supposedly destroyed by a nuclear bomb in one episode of ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]''.)
* ''[[B. J. and the Bear]]''
* ''[[Big Love]]''
* ''[[Carnivàle]]''
* ''[[Charlie's Angels]]''
* ''[[CHiPs]]'' (several episodes)
* ''[[Christine (1983 film)|Christine]]'' filmed in [[Valencia, Santa Clarita, California|Valencia]].
* ''[[CSI: Crime Scene Investigation|CSI]]''
* ''[[Deadwood (TV series)|Deadwood]]'' (filmed in Placerita Canyon at [[Melody Ranch]] Studios, once owned by [[Gene Autry]])
* ''[[Disney Channel Games]]'' ([[College of the Canyons]])
* ''[[Firefly (TV series)|Firefly]]'' (Many outdoor scenes were filmed in Santa Clarita.)
* ''[[Freaks and Geeks]]'' was filmed at [[William S. Hart High School]] along with its general vicinity.
* ''[[Heroes (TV series)|Heroes]]'', filmed at [[Golden Valley High School (Santa Clarita)|Golden Valley High School]] and [[West Ranch High School]]
* ''[[JAG (TV series)|JAG]]''
* ''[[Knight Rider (1982 TV series)|Knight Rider]]'' (1982 version, filmed in and around the Santa Clarita Valley)
* ''[[Malcolm in the Middle]]'' (Go-kart scene at Mountasia Family Fun Center on Soledad Canyon Road)
* ''[[Melrose Place (1992 TV series)|Melrose Place]]'' (Beginning in the 1990s, studios began to set up in the Santa Clarita Valley, and this was one of the first TV series to be based out of Santa Clarita Studios.)
* ''[[Mighty Morphin Power Rangers]]'' (filmed in parts of Santa Clarita and [[Castaic]])
* ''[[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]]''
* ''[[Ned's Declassified School Survival Guide]]'' (takes place at [[La Mesa Junior High School]])
* ''[[Smith (TV series)|Smith]]'' ('''Bonus:''' The main characters (in-universe) ''lived'' in the city.)
* ''[[Supermarket Sweep]]'' was taped at Santa Clarita Studios when it was revived in 2000, before moving to [[NBC Studios]] in [[Burbank, California]] the following year.
* ''[[The Dukes of Hazzard]]''
* ''[[The Misadventures of Sheriff Lobo]]''
* ''[[The Riches]]''
* ''[[The Secret World of Alex Mack]]'' was filmed at Charles Helmers Elementary School in the Valencia neighborhood of Northbridge.
* ''[[The Unit (TV series)|The Unit]]''
* ''[[Top Shot]]''
* ''[[Weeds (TV series)|Weeds]]'' (filmed in various locations around [[Stevenson Ranch]] and [[College of the Canyons]])
* ''[[Wipeout (2008 U.S. game show)|Wipeout]]''
* ''[[Zoey 101]]''
'''Note:''' [[Golden Oak Ranch]] is a property owned by [[The Walt Disney Company]] located east of State Route 14 in Newhall.  This has been used as a location for several Disney features.  It has also been rented out to other studios and production companies.

====Select films====

* ''[[Bio-Dome]]'' (also partially at Valencia High)
* ''[[Dude, Where's My Car?]]'' (Mountasia Family Fun Center.)
* ''[[Encino Man]]''
* ''[[Faster (2010 film)|Faster]]'' (featuring [[Dwayne Johnson|Dwayne &quot;The Rock&quot; Johnson]] (refer to Santa Clarita Film Office)
* ''[[Fat Albert]]'' (Scene at the Track meet supposedly in Philadelphia filmed at the College of the Canyons stadium)
* ''[[Jay and Silent Bob Strike Back]]'' (Some scenes shot near Interstate 5's 126 interchange, between Castaic and Valencia in Santa Clarita.)
* ''[[King of California]]''
* ''[[Kiss Meets the Phantom of the Park]]''
* ''[[Mr. Woodcock]]'' (the gym at Sierra Vista Junior High)
* ''[[National Lampoon's Vacation]]'' (filmed at [[Six Flags Magic Mountain]])
* ''[[Don't Tell Mom The Babysitter's Dead]]'' (the Crandall residence used in the film)
* ''[[Never Been Kissed]]'' (filmed partially at William S. Hart High School)
* ''[[Pleasantville (film)|Pleasantville]]'' (features Valencia High)
* ''[[Pump Up the Volume (film)|Pump Up the Volume]]'' (filmed at [[Saugus High School (California)|Saugus High School]])
* ''[[Romy and Michele's High School Reunion]]'' (high school flashback scenes filmed at [[Valencia High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Valencia High School]])
* ''[[Sioux City (film)|Sioux City]]''
* ''[[Space Cowboys]]'' ([[The Halfway House]] on Sierra Highway used for an opening scene)
* ''[[Stay Cool]]'' (Some scenes were filmed in Santa Clarita Valley, including West Ranch High School.)
* ''[[The Chumscrubber]]'' (features Rio Norte Junior High)
* ''[[The Gumball Rally]]''
* ''[[Twilight (2008 film)|Twilight]]'' (The Arizona House scene was filmed near Highlands Elementary School in Saugus, CA. The house overlooks Grace Baptist Church, which can been spotted in the movie. Also, Valencia Hyatt was used for Alice, Bella, and Jasper's hideout.)
* ''[[Vacancy (film)|Vacancy]]'' (largely filmed in Santa Clarita)
* ''[[Viva Knievel!]]''

====Select other productions====

* The video for &quot;There Goes My Heart&quot; by Enuff Z'Nuff was filmed at Richard Rioux Park in Stevenson Ranch.
* The video for &quot;1979&quot; by the Smashing Pumpkins was filmed at Valencia High School.
* The video for &quot;Nice Guys Finish Last&quot; by Green Day was filmed at College of the Canyons in Santa Clarita.
* Part of the video for &quot;Long Road to Ruin&quot; by the Foo Fighters was filmed at the Westfield Shopping Center in Santa Clarita.
* The video for &quot;American Honey&quot; by Lady Antebellum was filmed in Santa Clarita in January 2010

==Infrastructure==
===Transportation===
====Freeways====
Santa Clarita is serviced by [[Interstate 5 (California)|Interstate 5]] on the western side of the City.  The east side of the City is serviced by [[California State Route 14|State Route 14]]. [[California State Route 126|State Route 126]] terminates at [[Interstate 5 (California)|Interstate 5]], where is goes west to Ventura, passing through Fillmore and Santa Paula.

*[[Image:I-5.svg|20px|alt=Interstate 5 shield]] [[Interstate 5]]
*[[Image:California 14.svg|20px|alt=California State Highway 14 shield]] [[California State Highway 14]]
*[[Image:California 126.svg|20px|alt=California State Highway 126 shield]] [[California State Highway 126]]

====Bus service====
[[City of Santa Clarita Transit]] provides extensive bus service within the Santa Clarita Valley and to/from North Hollywood in the San Fernando Valley. City of Santa Clarita Transit is operated by MV Transportation, Inc. under contract with the city of Santa Clarita.

On weekdays, City of Santa Clarita Transit operates commuter buses to/from Burbank, downtown Los Angeles, North Hollywood (operates seven days per week), Warner Center, Van Nuys, Century City and Lancaster. Also on weekdays when school is in session, City of Santa Clarita Transit operates supplemental school-day service with routes and scheduled stops designed around various school sites within the Santa Clarita Valley.

City of Santa Clarita Transit also operates Dial-A-Ride service for seniors and the disabled. Dial-A-Ride service is also open to the general public after 6:00 p.m. The service allows for pick-up and drop-off at any address within the City of Santa Clarita and within a three-quarter mile radius of the nearest fixed route bus stop in unincorporated areas.

City of Santa Clarita Transit was formerly known as Santa Clarita Transit.

====Train====
[[Metrolink (Southern California)|Metrolink]] provides commuter passenger train service to the Santa Clarita Valley along its [[Metrolink Antelope Valley Line|Antelope Valley Line]] which runs from Lancaster to [[Union Station (Los Angeles)|Union Station]] in Downtown [[Los Angeles]], where transfers can be made to destinations in Southern California and the rest of the nation. Metrolink services 3 stations in the city, [[Via Princessa (Metrolink station)|Via Princessa Station]] in the Canyon Country community, [[Santa Clarita (Metrolink station)|Santa Clarita Station]] which is centrally located in the city and serves most of the Valencia and Saugus communities, and the [[Newhall (Metrolink station)|Newhall Station]] which serves the community of Newhall. All stations have large parking lots to allow commuters to &quot;park and ride.&quot;

Metrolink service operates 7 days a week, with reduced service on Saturdays and Sundays.

====Bicycle and walking====
There are a series of [[bike trail]]s and walking paths threaded throughout the city.  Bicyclists can ride from the eastern end of the city in Canyon Country along a paved path which is independent from automobile traffic all the way to Valencia on the [[Santa Clara River Trail]].  This path closely follows the [[Santa Clara River (California)|Santa Clara River]] and Soledad Canyon Road.  There are many jumping off points along this route providing access to neighborhoods, Metrolink stations and commerce.  Once in Valencia, there are several pedestrian bridges called ''paseos'' connected to the bike path network.  The paseos keep riders and walkers above and away from automobile traffic.  The neighborhoods in Valencia were planned to include an ample amount of walking and riding paths that connect to this overall network.  In 2007, the [[League of American Bicyclists]] awarded Santa Clarita its &quot;bronze&quot; designation as a &quot;bicycle friendly community.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=McLean|first=Marsha|title=Santa Clarita Named Bicycle Friendly Community|url=http://www.cicle.org/wordpress/2007/10/01/santa-clarita-named-bicycle-friendly-community-2/|accessdate=4/15/2011|newspaper=The Signal|date=September 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notables==

*[[Shawn Barton]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher. Graduated from [[Saugus High School (California)|Saugus High School]]
*[[Kyle Boller]] - [[National Football League]] [[quarterback]]. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Steve Borden]] - [[Professional Wrestler]]. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Bob Brontsema]] - collegiate baseball player and head baseball coach at UC Santa Barbara. Graduated from [[Canyon High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Canyon High School]] and attended [[College of the Canyons]].
*[[Crystl Bustos]] - a two time Olympic gold medalist on the USA Softball team and three times gold medalist at the Pan Am Games. Graduated from [[Canyon High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Canyon High School]]
*[[Anthony Ervin]] - Winner of two [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] medals and two World Championship golds in swimming. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]].
*[[Jon Garland]] - [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher.  Born in Valencia.
*[[Meagan Good]] - Actress. Grew up in Canyon Country.
*[[Jason Gore]] - Professional Golfer.  Attended [[William S. Hart High School]]. Resides in Valencia.
*[[Mark-Paul Gosselaar]] - [[Actor]]. Attended [[William S. Hart High School]].
*[[William S. Hart]] - Silent-era [[Actor]]. Lived in [[Newhall]].
*[[Erik Hiljus]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher. Graduated from [[Canyon High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Canyon High School]]
*[[Bryan Herta]] - Open wheel race car driver.  Attended [[William S. Hart High School]].
*[[Joe Kapp]] - Quarterback for the University of California and Minnesota Vikings. Also played in the Canadian Football League and was the head coach at Cal. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Taylor Lautner]] - Actor. Lives in Santa Clarita. Lautner was a junior at [[Valencia High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Valencia High School]] for the 2008-09 school year, but tested out of high school and is taking college classes.
*[[Andrew Lorraine]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Tessa Ludwick]] - [[Actress]]. Graduated from [[Saugus High School (California)|Saugus High School]]
*[[Kevin Malone (baseball)|Kevin Malone]] - Former baseball executive and [[General Manager]] of the [[Montreal Expos]] and [[Los Angeles Dodgers]].  Co-Owner of the Santa Clarita [[Mercedes Benz]] dealer.
*[[Matt Moore (American football)|Matt Moore]] - [[National Football League]] [[quarterback]]. Attended [[William S. Hart High School]].
*[[Eddie Murray]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] [[first baseman]] and hitting coach.  Co-Owner of the Santa Clarita [[Mercedes-Benz]] dealer. Resides in Santa Clarita.
*[[Jerry Owens]] - [[Major League Baseball]] [[outfielder]].  Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]].  Attended [[UCLA]].
*[[Erin Perperoglou]] - [[Women's National Basketball Association]] player. Attended [[The Master's College]].
*[[Mike Penberthy]] - Former [[National Basketball Association]] [[guard (basketball)|guard]].  Attended [[The Master's College]].
*[[Mackenzie Rosman]] - [[Actress]]. Attended [[Valencia High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Valencia High School]]
*[[Paul Ruebens]] - Actor, aka [[Pee Wee Herman]]. Attended  the [[California Institute of the Arts]] (CalArts), located in Valencia.
*[[John Paul Salapetek]] - Actor, Screen-writer, Teacher. Starred in [[Children of the Corn]] Teacher at 
 [[Golden Valley High School]] 
*[[Roger Salkeld]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher. Graduated from [[Saugus High School (California)|Saugus High School]]
*[[James Shields (baseball)|James Shields]] - [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher.  Born in Newhall. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Cory Snyder]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] [[utility player]].  Graduated from [[Canyon High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Canyon High School]]
*[[Jessica D. Stone]] - [[Actress]].  Born in Valencia.
*[[Kristy Swanson]] - [[Actress]] best known for roles in ''[[Buffy the Vampire Slayer (film)|Buffy the Vampire Slayer]]'', ''[[Big Daddy (1999 film)|Big Daddy]]'' , ''[[Dude, Where's My Car?]]'' &amp; ''[[Higher Learning (film)|Higher Learning]]''.
*[[Ashley Tisdale]] - [[Actress]].  Graduated from [[Valencia High School (Santa Clarita, California)|Valencia High School]].
*[[Bob Walk]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Todd Zeile]] - Former [[Major League Baseball]] [[third baseman]]. Graduated from [[William S. Hart High School]]
*[[Smile Empty Soul]] - Post-Grunge/Rock Band
*[[Tim Burton]] - Film director, producer, writer and artist. Attended  the [[California Institute of the Arts]] (CalArts), located in Valencia.
*[[Tyler Posey]] - Actor - MTV's Teen Wolf, Lives in Valencia.

==Sister cities==
*{{Flagicon|ECU}} [[Tena]], [[Napo]], [[Ecuador]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.santa-clarita.com/Index.aspx?page=306 &quot;Tena, Ecuador&quot;] at City of Santa Clarita official website.&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{Flagicon|PHL}} [[Sariaya]], [[Quezon]], [[Philippines]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.santa-clarita.com/Index.aspx?page=307 &quot;Sariaya, Philippines&quot;] at City of Santa Clarita official website.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
* [http://www.santa-clarita.com OFFICIAL City of Santa Clarita homepage]
* [http://www.visitsantaclarita.com OFFICIAL Santa Clarita Tourism]
* [http://www.filmsantaclarita.com OFFICIAL Santa Clarita Valley Film Office]
* [http://www.scmarathon.org OFFICIAL Santa Clarita Marathon]
* [http://www.cowboyfestival.org OFFICIAL Santa Clarita Cowboy Festival]
* [http://www.facebook.com/CityOfSantaClarita OFFICIAL Santa Clarita Facebook Page]
* [http://www.facebook.com/SantaClarita OFFICIAL Santa Clarita Twitter Page]
* [http://www.the-signal.com The Signal, Santa Clarita Valley's newspaper]
* [http://www.scvtv.com SCVTV] (Official city &amp; community television programming)
* [http://www.scvhistory.com Santa Clarita Valley History In Pictures]
* [http://www.scvparade.com Santa Clarita 4th of July Parade]
* [http://www.santaclaritaguide.com Santa Clarita Guide - OFFICIAL Guide to Santa Clarita as endorsed by LA County]
* [http://scvinsider.angelskies.net SCV Insider - Guide to the Hip Side of Santa Clarita]
* [http://www.scvresources.com Santa Clarita Valley Resources Page]
* [http://lacdcs.com/station-end-page-6.html LA County Disaster Communications Service ( DCS ) Santa Clarita Valley Station]
* [http://www.scvlife.net SCVLife.net - Santa Clarita Community, Life, and Events]
* [http://www.hometownstation.com AM-1220 KHTS - Santa Clarita's Radio Station]
* [http://www.gibboncenter.org Gibbon Conservation Center]
* [http://www.dailynews.com/santaclarita ''Daily News'']

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}
{{California}}
{{California cities and mayors of 100,000 population}}
{{Geographic Location
|Center    = Santa Clarita
|North     = [[Castaic, California|Castaic]]
|Northeast = [[Palmdale, California|Palmdale]]
|East      = [[Victorville, California|Victorville]]
|Southeast = [[San Fernando, California|San Fernando]]
|South     = [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]
|Southwest = [[Simi Valley, California|Simi Valley]]
|West      = [[Fillmore, California|Fillmore]]
|Northwest = [[Santa Maria, California|Santa Maria]]
}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1987]]

[[ar:سانتا كلاريتا، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Санта Кларита (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Santa Clarita]]
[[de:Santa Clarita]]
[[es:Santa Clarita (California)]]
[[fr:Santa Clarita]]
[[hr:Santa Clarita, Kalifornija]]
[[it:Santa Clarita]]
[[he:סנטה קלריטה]]
[[sw:Santa Clarita, California]]
[[ht:Santa Clarita, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Santa Clarita]]
[[ja:サンタクラリタ (カリフォルニア州)]]
[[pnb:سانٹا کلاریٹا]]
[[pl:Santa Clarita]]
[[pt:Santa Clarita]]
[[ro:Santa Clarita, California]]
[[sv:Santa Clarita]]
[[tl:Santa Clarita, California]]
[[vi:Santa Clarita, California]]
[[vo:Santa Clarita]]
[[war:Santa Clarita, California]]
[[zh:聖塔克拉利塔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
