<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="60296" ns="0" title="Kevin Smith"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{sprotect|small=yes}}
{{Other people}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2010}}
{{Infobox person
|image            = 3.4.11KevinSmithByLuigiNovi1.png
|caption          = Smith promoting ''[[Red State (2011 film)|Red State]]'' at&lt;br&gt;[[Midtown Comics]] Grand Central in Manhattan,&lt;br&gt;March 4, 2011.
|birth_name       = Kevin Patrick Smith
|birth_date       = {{Birth date and age|1970|8|2}}
|birth_place      = [[Red Bank, New Jersey|Red Bank]], [[New Jersey]], U.S.
|occupation       = Director, screenwriter, producer, actor, comedian, author, podcaster
|years_active     = 1994–present
|spouse           = [[Jennifer Schwalbach Smith]] (1999–present)
}}
'''Kevin Patrick Smith''' (born August 2, 1970) is an American screenwriter, actor, film producer, and director, as well as a popular [[script (comics)|comic book]] writer, author, comedian/raconteur, and [[internet radio]] personality best recognized by viewers as [[Silent Bob]]. Although primarily known for the ''[[View Askew]]'' film series, Smith also wrote, directed and produced films such as the [[buddy cop]] [[action comedy]] ''[[Cop Out (2010 film)|Cop Out]]'', as well as the horror film ''[[Red State (2011 film)|Red State]]''. His first several films were mostly set in his home state of New Jersey, and while not strictly sequential, they frequently feature crossover plot elements, character references, and a shared [[canon (fiction)|canon]] in what is known by fans as the &quot;[[View Askewniverse]]&quot;, named after his production company [[View Askew Productions]], which he co-founded with [[Scott Mosier]].

Smith is also the owner of [[Jay and Silent Bob's Secret Stash]] comic book and novelty store in [[Red Bank, New Jersey|Red Bank]], New Jersey. He hosts a weekly [[podcast]] with Scott Mosier known as [[SModcast]]. Smith is well-known for participating in long, humorous Q&amp;A sessions that are often filmed for DVD release, beginning with ''[[An Evening with Kevin Smith]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://movies.nytimes.com/person/111916/Kevin-Smith Kevin Smith] at ''[[The New York Times]]'', accessed March 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Kevin Smith was born in [[Red Bank, New Jersey]], the son of Grace, a homemaker, and Donald E. Smith (1936–2003), a postal worker.&lt;ref&gt;Condran, Kevin. [http://www.jerseypride.com/all_jersey_info/NJ_in_the_News/kevin_smith_a_skewed_view.htm ''A Skewed View'']. Jersey Pride.com. 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filmreference.com/film/89/Kevin-Smith.html Film Reference.com].&lt;/ref&gt; He has an older sister, Virginia, and an older brother, Donald Smith, Jr. He was raised in an [[Irish Catholic]] household&lt;ref&gt;As stated in an interview in Clerks 10th Anniversary DVD.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;chriv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianitytoday.com/movies/interviews/kevinsmith.html|title=www.christianitytoday.com/movies/interviews/kevinsmith.html|title=A Warm &amp; Fuzzy Kevin Smith?|author=Jeffrey Overstreet|publisher=Christianity Today|accessdate=April 30, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070413062748/http://www.christianitytoday.com/movies/interviews/kevinsmith.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = April 13, 2007|authorlink= Jeffrey Overstreet}}&lt;/ref&gt; and attended [[Henry Hudson Regional High School]] in [[Highlands, New Jersey|Highlands]].

After high school, he met [[Jason Mewes]], who would later become a recurring actor in his films. He then attended [[The New School]] and the [[Vancouver Film School]], where he met [[Scott Mosier]], his producer for almost every movie he has made. He majored in film, but dropped out of school halfway through his studies, electing to take a partial tuition reimbursement in order to help finance his first film.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

==Career==
===As a filmmaker===
In an interview with [[Robert K. Elder]] for ''[[The Film That Changed My Life]]'', Smith attributes the film [[Slacker (film)|''Slacker'']] as his main inspiration to becoming a director.

&lt;blockquote&gt;It was the movie that got me off my ass; it was the movie that lit a fire under me, the movie that made me think, “Hey, I could be a filmmaker.” And I had never seen a movie like that before ever in my life.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Kevin. Interview by Robert K. Elder. ''The Film That Changed My Life.'' By Robert K. Elder. Chicago: Chicago Review Press, 2011. N. p236. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

His first film, ''[[Clerks]]'', was shot for the sum total of $27,575 in the convenience store where Smith worked. It went to the [[Sundance Film Festival]] in 1994, where it won the Filmmaker's Trophy and was picked up by [[Miramax]] before the festival's end. In May 1994, it went to the [[Cannes International Film Festival]] where it won both the Prix de la Jeunesse and the International Critics' Week Prize. Released in November 1994 in two cities, the film went on to play in 50 markets, never playing on more than fifty screens at any given time. Despite the limited release, it was a critical and financial success, earning $3.1&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=8-MCAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA50&amp;lpg=PA50&amp;dq=register+dogs+clerks+kevin+smith&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=FRtXRs5qtD&amp;sig=Eal4Vyp9rO7MvC9xyRi_dHgHARE&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=41sxTbDuIo74sAPV2PznBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Books.google.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, the film received an [[NC-17]] rating from the [[Motion Picture Association of America|MPAA]], solely for the graphic language. Miramax hired [[Alan Dershowitz]] to defend the film, and at an appeals screening, a jury consisting of members of the National Association of Theater Owners reversed the MPAA's decision, and the film was given an R rating instead.

Smith's second film, ''[[Mallrats]]'', did not fare as well as expected after the remarkable success of ''Clerks''. It received a critical drubbing and earned merely $2.2&amp;nbsp;million at the box office, despite playing on more than 500 screens. The film marked [[Jason Lee (actor)|Jason Lee]]'s debut as a leading man.  Despite failing at the box office during its theatrical run, ''Mallrats'' proved more successful in the home video market.

Widely hailed as Smith's best film, ''[[Chasing Amy]]'' marked what [[Quentin Tarantino]] called &quot;a quantum leap forward&quot; for Smith. Starring ''Mallrats'' alumni Jason Lee, [[Joey Lauren Adams]] and [[Ben Affleck]], the $250,000 film earned $12&amp;nbsp;million at the box office and wound up on a number of critics' year-end best lists, and won two [[Independent Spirit Award]]s (screenplay and supporting actor for Lee).

In 1996, Smith worked on a script for a [[Superman film series#Superman V|Superman movie]]. He did a couple of drafts but his script was dropped when [[Tim Burton]] was hired to direct. Burton brought his own people to work on the project. Smith still sees the whole experience on working on the Superman project as a positive one however; he has said that he was well paid and it was a lot of fun. (In April, 2009, [http://boingboing.net/2009/04/27/kevin-smith-explains.html Smith discussed his ''Superman'' experiences] at Clark University—a youtube video critic A.O. Scott of the ''New York Times'' called &quot;extraordinary.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;A.O. Scott, &quot;Kevin Smith's 'Red State,'&quot; ''The New York Times'', September 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;) In the end, neither Smith's nor Burton's vision for Superman was filmed. In the 2007 Direct-to-DVD animation release of ''[[Superman: Doomsday]]'', Smith has a cameo as an onlooker in a crowd. After Superman defeats [[Toyman (comics)|The Toyman]]'s giant mechanical robot, Smith scoffs, &quot;Yeah, like we really needed him to defeat that giant spider. Heh. ''Lame!''&quot; This was a reference to a giant spider that producer [[Jon Peters]] wanted Smith to put in the [[Superman film series#Superman Lives|Superman movie]] when he was attached, that was later put into the 1999 feature film flop ''[[Wild Wild West]]'', which Peters also produced.

In 1997, Smith was hired by [[New Line]] to rewrite ''[[Overnight Delivery]]'', which was expected to be a blockbuster teen movie. Smith's then-girlfriend [[Joey Lauren Adams]] almost took the role of Ivy in the movie, instead of the female lead in ''[[Chasing Amy]]''. Eventually she lost out to [[Reese Witherspoon]], and ''Overnight Delivery'' was quietly released directly to video in April 1998. Kevin Smith's involvement with the film was revealed on-line,&lt;ref name=&quot;greasy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewaskew.com/press/psycomic/5.html|title=The Unholy Tale of Greasy Reese Witherspoon|work=&quot;Developing the Monkey&quot; [originally] on Psycomic.com|publisher=ViewAskew.com|date=December 1, 2000|accessdate=June 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; but he remains uncredited. He has said that the only scene which really used his dialogue was the opening scene, which includes a reference to long-time Smith friend [[Bryan Johnson (filmmaker)|Bryan Johnson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;greasy&quot;/&gt;

Smith's fourth film, ''[[Dogma (film)|Dogma]]'', featured an all-star cast and found itself mired in controversy. The religious-themed 1999 comedy, which starred a post-''[[Good Will Hunting]]'' Ben Affleck and [[Matt Damon]], as well as [[Chris Rock]], [[Salma Hayek]], [[George Carlin]], [[Alan Rickman]], [[Linda Fiorentino]], and Smith regulars Jason Lee and Jason Mewes, raised criticism by the [[Catholic League (U.S.)|Catholic League]].&lt;ref&gt;Givens, Ron. [http://articles.nydailynews.com/1999-08-17/entertainment/18115795_1_dogma-cannes-new-york-film-festival &quot;Some Controversy Projected For Ny Film Fest 25-movie Bill Includes Kevin Smith's Religious Comedy 'Dogma'&quot;]. ''[[Daily News (New York)|Daily News]]''. August 17, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.cnn.com/1999-11-12/entertainment/9911_12_kevin.smith.chat_1_dogma-director-film-clerks?_s=PM:SHOWBIZ &quot;Kevin Smith on New Jersey, fatherhood and Dogma&quot;]. [[CNN]]. November 12, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/1999/oct/05/news &quot;Dogma screening brings Catholic protests&quot;]. ''[[The Guardian]]''. October 5, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:KevinSmith08TIFF.jpg|thumb|right|Smith at the [[2008 Toronto International Film Festival]]]]
The film debuted at the [[1999 Cannes Film Festival]], out of competition. Released on 800 screens in November 1999, the $10&amp;nbsp;million film earned $30&amp;nbsp;million.

Smith then focused the spotlight on two characters who had appeared in supporting roles in his previous four films, ''[[Jay and Silent Bob Strike Back]]'' featured an all-star cast, with many familiar faces returning from Smith's first four films. Ben Affleck and Matt Damon appear as themselves filming a mock sequel to ''Good Will Hunting''. The $20&amp;nbsp;million film earned $30&amp;nbsp;million at the box office and received mixed reviews from the critics. 

In 2004, Smith wrote a screenplay for a new film version of ''[[The Green Hornet]]'', and announced prematurely that he had originally intended to direct as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.viewaskew.com/news/feb04/1.html 'Hornet' buzzes Smith] News Askew. Retrieved November 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The project, however died after the film was placed into turn around following the poor box office of ''[[Jersey Girl (2004 film)|Jersey Girl]]''. Smith's screenplay was turned into a ''Green Hornet'' comic book miniseries.&lt;ref name=&quot;PopEWGH&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://popwatch.ew.com/popwatch/2009/05/kevin-smith-com.html|title=EW Exclusive: Kevin Smith takes on Batman and the Green Hornet|publisher=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=May 13, 2009|accessdate=July 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Jersey Girl (2004 film)|Jersey Girl]]'' with Ben Affleck, [[Liv Tyler]], George Carlin and [[Raquel Castro]], his first outside of the View Askewniverse, was meant to mark a new direction in Smith's career. However, the film took a critical beating as it was seen as, in Smith's own words, &quot;''[[Gigli]] 2''&quot;, due to the fact that it co-starred Affleck and his then-girlfriend, [[Jennifer Lopez]]. Despite Smith heavily re-editing the film to reduce Lopez's role to just a few scenes, the film did poorly at the box office. Budgeted at $35&amp;nbsp;million, it earned only $36&amp;nbsp;million.

In the 2006 sequel, ''[[Clerks II]]'', Smith revisited the Dante and Randal characters from his first film for what was his final visit to the View Askewniverse. Roundly criticized before its release, the film went on to win favorable reviews as well as two awards (the Audience Award at the Edinburgh Film Festival and the Orbit Dirtiest Mouth Award at the [[MTV Movie Awards]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeout.com/film/news/1364/Time |title=Out London, Kevin Smith Wins in Edinburgh |publisher=Timeout.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; It marked Smith's third trip to the Cannes International Film Festival, where ''Clerks II'' received an eight minute standing ovation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slashfilm.com/article.php/20060530191203542 |title=Video: Clerks 2's 8-Minute Standing Ovation |publisher=Slashfilm.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The $5&amp;nbsp;million film, starring Jeff Anderson, Brian O'Halloran, [[Rosario Dawson]], Jason Mewes, Jennifer Schwalbach and Smith himself – reprising his role as Silent Bob – earned $25&amp;nbsp;million.

That same year, Smith was featured in ''[[This Film Is Not Yet Rated]]'', a 2006 documentary about the [[Motion Picture Association of America]] process of rating films. Smith's interview was in reference to ''[[Jersey Girl (2004 film)|Jersey Girl]]'' receiving an R rating,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spike.com/video/this-film-is-not-yet/2763894 This Film Is Not Yet Rated – Kevin Smith] [[Spike TV]].com Accessed November 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Clerks]]'' originally receiving an NC-17 rating.

''[[Zack and Miri Make a Porno]]'' was originally announced in March 2006 as Smith's second non-Askewniverse comedy.&lt;ref&gt;Sanchez, Robert. [http://www.newsaskew.com/cgi-bin/coranto/iSay.cgi?Page=Comments&amp;ID=EEupEZAZyyiBWjiwgQ News Askew]. February 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  The film, which began shooting on January 18, 2008 in [[Monroeville, Pennsylvania|Monroeville]], Pennsylvania, and wrapped on March 15, 2008, stars [[Seth Rogen]] and [[Elizabeth Banks]] as the title characters who decide to make a low-budget pornographic film to solve their money problems. The film, which was released on October 31, 2008, ran into many conflicts getting an &quot;R&quot; rating, with Rogen stating:
{{cquote|It's a really filthy movie. I hear they are having some problems getting an R rating from an NC-17 rating, which is never good... They [fight against] sex stuff. Isn't that weird? It's really crazy to me that ''[[Hostel (2005 film)|Hostel]]'' is fine, with people gouging their eyes out and shit like that, but you can't show two people having sex – that's too much.&lt;ref&gt;Larry Carroll (June 19, 2008) [http://www.mtv.com/movies/news/articles/1589686/story.jhtml 'Zack And Miri Make A Porno' Having Trouble With Ratings Board] MTV. Retrieved September 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;}} 
Smith took the film through the MPAA's appeals process and received the R rating, without having to make any further edits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nj.com/entertainment/tv/index.ssf/2008/10/kevin_smith_qa_porn_and_life_a.html |author=Stephen Whitty |title=Kevin Smith Q&amp;A: Porn and life after Apatow |publisher=''The Star-Ledger'' |date=October 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Zack and Miri Make a Porno'' was considered a box office &quot;flop&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;whatculture1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whatculture.com/film/quantum-of-solace-sets-new-records-zack-and-miri-make-a-flop.php |title=QUANTUM OF SOLACE sets new records, ZACK AND MIRI make a flop! |publisher=WhatCulture! |date=2008-11-02 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filmschoolrejects.com/news/box-office-zack-and-miri-make-no-money-hsm-3-wins-again.php |title=Box Office: Zack and Miri Make No Money, HSM 3 Wins Again |publisher=Film School Rejects |date=2008-11-02 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; in part because of &quot;tepid media advertising for a movie with the title PORNO&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;whatculture1&quot;/&gt; and, in the aftermath of the film's &quot;flaccid&quot; performance, the business relationship between Smith and producer [[Harvey Weinstein]] became &quot;frayed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/kevin-smith-alarmist-ninnies-misinterpreted-95811|title=Kevin Smith: 'Alarmist Ninnies' Misinterpreted Sundance Outburst|author=Kim Masters|publisher=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=February 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was announced in 2009 that Smith had signed on to direct a buddy-cop comedy starring [[Bruce Willis]] and [[Tracy Morgan]] called ''A Couple of Dicks'' and written by the Cullen Brothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quickstopentertainment.com/2009/03/09/smodcast-79/ |title=SModcast 79 » FRED Entertainment |publisher=Quickstopentertainment.com |date= |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to controversy surrounding the original title, it was changed to ''A Couple of Cops'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2009/03/04/bruce-willis-tracy-morgan-are-a-couple-of-cops-for-kevin-smith/ |title=Bruce Willis, Tracy Morgan Are ‘A Couple of Cops’ For Kevin Smith » MTV Movies Blog |publisher=Moviesblog.mtv.com |date=October 17, 2008 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; before reverting back its original title, ''A Couple of Dicks'', due to negative reaction,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slashfilm.com/2009/03/05/a-couple-of-dicks-warner-bros-doesnt-cop-out/ |title=A Couple Of Dicks: Warner Bros Doesn’t COP Out &amp;#124; /Film |publisher=Slashfilm.com |date=March 5, 2009 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; before finally settling on the title ''[[Cop Out (2010 film)|Cop Out]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thefilmstage.com/2009/12/12/exclusive-smiths-a-couple-of-dicks-new-title-revealed-inception-trailer-for-christmas/ |title=[Exclusive&amp;#93; Smith's 'A Couple of Dicks' New Title Revealed, 'Inception' Trailer For Christmas |publisher=The Film Stage |date= |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film, which was shot between June and August 2009, involved a pair of veteran cops tracking down a stolen vintage baseball card,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ercboxoffice.com/index.php?page=news&amp;news_id=116 |title=Home &amp;#124; Home Page |publisher=erc BoxOffice |date=March 10, 2010 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was released on February 26, 2010 to poor reviews; it was the first film that Smith has directed but not written. With a worldwide domestic gross of $55,583,804, ''Cop Out'' is Smith's highest grossing film to date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=coupleofdicks.htm |title=Cop Out (2010) |publisher=BoxOfficeMojo.com |date=May 20, 2010 |accessdate=October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2010, Smith started work on ''[[Red State (2011 film)|Red State]]'', an independently-financed horror film inspired by the [[Westboro Baptist Church]] and their Pastor [[Fred Phelps]].&lt;ref&gt;Sciretta, Peter. [http://www.slashfilm.com/article.php/20060807kevin-smith-horror-film ''Kevin Smith Announces Horror Film'']. August 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.rottentomatoes.com/news/1648575/ |title=Rotten Tomatoes, RT-UK Exclusive: Kevin Smith's Horror Project Revealed |publisher=Uk.rottentomatoes.com |author=Joe Utichi &amp;#124; April 6, 2007 |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bloody-disgusting.com/news/17813 |title=Kevin Smith Gets Down and Dirty with 'Red State' Details |publisher=Bloody-disgusting.com |date= |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2010, he talked about his project with Cinssu,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cinssu.ca/blog/?p=610 |title=Kevin Smith: Out of the Comfort Zone |publisher=Cinssu.ca |date=February 4, 2010 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bloody-disgusting.com/news/18989 |title=Kevin Smith Asks for 'Red State' Money, Mr. Disgusting Loses It |publisher=Bloody-disgusting.com |date=February 5, 2010 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Film producers and moguls [[Bob Weinstein|Bob]] and Harvey Weinstein who had thus far been involved in the distribution of most of Smith's films, with the exception of ''Mallrats'' and ''Cop Out'', declined to support ''Red State''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dreadcentral.com/news/33921/kevin-smiths-red-state-gets-funding |title=Kevin Smith's Red State Gets Funding? |publisher=DreadCentral.com |accessdate=2010-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bloody-disgusting.com/news/19560|title=Kevin Smith Shooting 'Red State' This July?}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Comic Con: Michael Parks Cast In Kevin Smith's ''Red State'' |first=Eric |last=Eisenberg |url=http://www.cinemablend.com/new/Comic-Con-Michael-Parks-Cast-In-Kevin-Smith-s-Red-State-19818.html |newspaper= |publisher=[[Cinema Blend]] |date=July 24, 2010 |accessdate=July 26, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Kevin Smith|publisher=Twitter|title=Via @CincinnatiGAZzy &quot;is it true that Matt Jones (Badger from BREAKING BAD) is cast in RED STATE?&quot; Yup. He &amp; Parks share a killer scene...|url=http://twitter.com/ThatKevinSmith/status/23065492097|date=September 5, 2010 |accessdate=September 5, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=397&lt;/ref&gt; The film stars [[Michael Parks]], [[John Goodman]], [[Melissa Leo]] and [[Stephen Root]]. Smith had indicated that he would auction off rights to the $4 million film at a controversial event following the debut screening of the film at [[27th Sundance Film Festival|Sundance]] but instead, kept the rights to the film himself with plans to self-distribute the picture &quot;under the Smodcast Pictures&quot; banner. The film was released via [[Video on Demand]] on September 1, 2011 through [[Lionsgate]], will be released in select theaters again for a special one-night only engagement on September 25, 2011 (via Smodcast Pictures), and was released on home video October 18, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nymag.com/daily/entertainment/2011/01/kevin_smith_red_state.html|title=Kevin Smith’s Red State Premiered at Sundance, and Vulture Was There}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Walsh | first = Brendan | title = Sundance 2011: Kevin Smith’s Red State Auction Live From the Eccles With Video | publisher = ScreenCrave | date = January 23, 2011 | accessdate = 2011-01-28 | url = http://screencrave.com/2011-01-23/sundance-2011-kevin-smiths-red-state-auction-live-from-the-eccles/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kevin Smith listed [[Mel Gibson]] as a role-model he looked up to, and his inspiration, for how he planned to distribute this movie, citing Gibson's ''[[The Passion of the Christ]]'' as an example of a successfully self-distributed movie.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Smith | first = Kevin | title = As the Sundance dust settles | publisher = The Red Statement | date = January 26, 2011 | accessdate = 2011-01-28 | url = http://theredstatements.com/2011/01/26/as-the-sundance-dust-settles/}}&lt;/ref&gt; He further explained his decision as a way to return to an era when marketing a film did not cost four times as much as the film itself, a situation he has described as &quot;both decadent and deadening&quot;.&lt;ref name=RedStateEW&gt;Gleiberman, Owen. [http://insidemovies.ew.com/2011/02/10/kevin-smith-says-that-hes-retiring/ &quot;Kevin Smith says he's retiring. So does Steven Soderbergh. Former indie wunderkinds, we hardly knew ye!&quot;]. ''Entertainment Weekly''. February 10, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The film was released in January 2011. The premiere drew protests from a half-dozen members of the church, along with many more who counter-protested Westboro members.&lt;ref&gt;Yuan, Jada. [http://nymag.com/daily/entertainment/2011/01/kevin_smith_red_state.html &quot;Kevin Smith’s Red State Premiered at Sundance, and Vulture Was There&quot;]. ''[[New York Magazine]]''. January 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith will direct a hockey drama-comedy based on the song &quot;[[My Ride's Here|Hit Somebody (The Hockey Song)]]&quot; by [[Warren Zevon]]. The song, which is about a hockey player famous for fighting in the rink, was co-written by ''[[Tuesdays With Morrie]]'' author [[Mitch Albom]], who is working with Smith on the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2009/05/14/exclusive-kevin-smith-making-hockey-movie-with-mitch-albom-based-on-warren-zevon-song-hit-somebody/ |title=EXCLUSIVE: Kevin Smith Making Hockey Movie With Mitch Albom Based On Warren Zevon Song ‘Hit Somebody’|publisher=MTV|date=May 14, 2009|accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although Smith had previously mentioned other projects he had planned,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=322 |title=Silent Bob Speaks |publisher=Silentbobspeaks.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsaskew.com/cgi-bin/coranto/iSay.cgi?Page=Comments&amp;ID=EEupEZAZuZLZgWaazm|title=''Talk Back''|accessdate=March 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filmbuffonline.com/FBOLNewsreel/wordpress/2009/12/07/clerks-iii-in-about-5-or-6-years-maybe// |title=CLERKS III? In About 5 Or 6 Years, Maybe |publisher=FilmBuffOnLine.com |date=December 7, 2009 |accessdate=December 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; he announced at the Sundance premiere of ''[[Red State (2011 film)|Red State]]'' that ''Hit Somebody'' will be the last movie he ever directs, and that he will continue to tell stories in other media.&lt;ref name=NYPost/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Miller, Daniel J. [http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/blogs/risky-business/sundance-red-states-kevin-smith-74829 &quot;SUNDANCE: 'Red State's' Kevin Smith Buys Own Film for $20&quot;]. ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]''. January 23, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In August ''Hit Somebody'' was announced as a two part film titled ''Hit Somebody: Home'' and ''Hit Somebody: Away'' with part one being [[PG-13]] and part 2 being [[Rated R]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Jagernauth  | first = Kevin | title = Kevin Smith Names His Two-Part Films: ‘Hit Somebody: Home’ &amp; ‘Away’; Wants Part 2 To Be R-Rated | publisher = indiewire | date = January 26, 2011 | accessdate = 2011-01-28 | url = http://blogs.indiewire.com/theplaylist/archives/kevin_smith_names_his_two-part_films_hit_somebody_home_away_wants_part_2_to/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith further explained his retirement from directing, citing distribution politics, and the manner in which making films like ''Zack and Miri'' &quot;adulterated&quot; his own identity as a filmmaker, saying, &quot;I don’t have the same passion for it I used to. I don’t have any stories left to tell.&quot; Smith further emphasized that he sees himself as a writer rather than a director, and that Harvey Weinstein developed his career as a celebrity auteur because &quot;my films were never strong enough to stand up on their own.&quot;&lt;ref name=RedStateEW/&gt; ''[[Daily Beast]]'' writer Chris Lee reported in September 2011 that those close to Smith cite the failure of ''Zack and Miri'', and Smith's constant marijuana consumption as a contributing factor to his categorization of those around him into &quot;friendly or enemy camps&quot;, his tendency to sequester himself from those he perceives as being against him, and his retirement from the film industry. Smith states that he is merely reinventing himself as an artist, which he refers to as &quot;Kevin Smith 2.0&quot;, and cites his 70&amp;nbsp;lb. weight loss, his deals for a book and two television pilots, and his starting an online radio station.&lt;ref name=DailyBeast&gt;Lee, Chris. [http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2011/09/02/kevin-smith-burned-out-director-s-retirement-red-state-more.html &quot;Kevin Smith, Burned Out?&quot;]. ''[[The Daily Beast]]''. September 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comics and magazines===
Smith has been a regular contributor to ''[[Arena (magazine)|Arena]]'' magazine. In 2005, [[Miramax Books]] released Smith's first book, ''[[Silent Bob Speaks]]'', a collection of previously published essays (most from ''Arena'') dissecting pop culture, the movie business, and Smith's personal life. His second book, ''My Boring-Ass Life: The Uncomfortably Candid Diary of Kevin Smith'', published by [[Titan Books]], was another collection of previously published essays (this time blogs from Smith's website www.silentbobspeaks.com) and reached #32 on the ''[[New York Times]]'' Best Sellers List.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewaskew.com/news/oct07/1.html |title=Kevin finishes writing &quot;Red State&quot; |work=New York Times |publisher=The View Askewniverse |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Titan released Smith's third book ''Shootin' the Sh*t with Kevin Smith: The Best of the SModcast'' on September 29, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/1845764153 |title=Shootin' the Sh*t with Kevin Smith: The Best of the SModcast (9781845764159): Kevin Smith: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:KevinSmithCC08.jpg|thumb|Smith at the 2008 [[Comic-Con International|Comic-Con]] convention]]
A life-long [[comic book]] fan, Smith's early forays into comic books dealt with previously established View Askew characters, and were published by [[Oni Press]]. He wrote a short [[Jay and Silent Bob]] story about Walt Flanagan's dog in ''Oni Double Feature'' #1, and followed it with a [[Bluntman and Chronic]] story in ''Oni Double Feature'' #12. He followed these with a series of [[Clerks (comic)|''Clerks'' comics]]. The first was simply ''Clerks: The Comic Book'', which told of Randal's attempts to corner the market on ''Star Wars'' toys. The second was ''Clerks: Holiday Special'', where Dante and Randal discover that Santa Claus lives in an apartment between the Quick Stop and RST Video. Third was ''Clerks: The Lost Scene'', showing what happened inside Poston's Funeral Parlor. This story was later animated in the TV series style and included as an extra on the 10th Anniversary ''[[Clerks]]'' DVD.

Smith then wrote the mini-series ''[[Chasing Dogma]]'', which tells the story of Jay and Silent Bob between the films ''[[Chasing Amy]]'' and ''[[Dogma (film)|Dogma]]''. He has also written the trade paperback ''[[Bluntman and Chronic]]'', published by [[Image Comics|Image]], which purports to be a collection of the three issues of the series done by Holden McNeil and Banky Edwards (of ''Chasing Amy''). It includes a color reprinting of the story from ''Oni Double Feature'' #12, purported to be an early appearance by ''Chasing Amy'' characters Holden McNeil and Banky Edwards. These stories have all been collected in ''Tales From the Clerks'' (Graphitti Designs, ISBN 0936211784), which also includes a new &quot;Clerks&quot; story tying in to the ''Clerks 2'' material, and the story from ''Oni Double Feature'' #1. They were previously collected by Image Comics in three separate volumes, one each for ''Clerks'', ''Chasing Dogma'' and ''Bluntman and Chronic''. In 1999, Smith won a [[Harvey Award]], for Best New Talent in comic books.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hahnlibrary.net/comics/awards/harvey99.php &quot;1999 Harvey Award Nominees and Winners&quot;], Comic Book Awards Almanac, accessed March 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, Smith wrote &quot;[[Daredevil: Guardian Devil|Guardian Devil]]&quot;, an eight-issue story arc of ''[[Daredevil (Marvel Comics)|Daredevil]]'' for [[Marvel Comics]], which was illustrated by [[Joe Quesada]]. Kevin Smith followed this by producing a 15-issue tenure on ''[[Green Arrow]]'' for [[DC Comics]] that saw the return of [[Oliver Queen]] from the dead and the introduction of [[Mia Dearden]], a teenage girl who would become Speedy after Smith's run had ended.

Smith returned to Marvel for two mini-series: ''[[Spider-Man/Black Cat: The Evil That Men Do]]'' and ''[[Daredevil/Bullseye: The Target]]'', both of which debuted in 2002. The former was six issues long, but after the third issue was published two months after the initially scheduled release date, the final issues were delayed for at least three years, prompting Marvel to release an &quot;in case you missed it&quot; reprinting of the first three issues as one book prior to the remaining issues' release. The delay in part was due to Smith's movie production schedule (in this case, work on ''Jersey Girl'' and ''Clerks II'') causing him to shelve completion of the mini-series until the films were completed. In 2007 he was announced as the writer of an ongoing ''[[Black Cat (comics)|Black Cat]]'' series&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comicscontinuum.com/stories/0202/24/|title=''Kevin Smith Talks Black Cat''.|accessdate=March 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The Amazing Spider-Man]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comicon.com/cgi-bin/ultimatebb.cgi?ubb=get_topic&amp;f=13&amp;t=001042|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20020601183702/http://www.comicon.com/cgi-bin/ultimatebb.cgi?ubb=get_topic&amp;f=13&amp;t=001042|archivedate=June 1, 2002|title=''Marvel Locks Up JMS/Kevin Smith.''|accessdate=March 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comicbookresources.com/news/newsitem.cgi?id=1129|title=Wednesday Marvel Conference Call Wrap Up.''|publisher=[[Comic Book Resources]]|accessdate=March 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; in early to mid-2002. However, because of the delays on ''Evil That Men Do'' and ''The Target'', the plan was switched so that Smith would start a third Spider-Man title,&lt;ref&gt;Couper, Jonathan. [http://www.comicboards.com/smb/view.php?rpl=030106020056 ''Re: Kevin Smith Question – Reasons...''] Accessdate: March 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; launched in 2004 by [[Mark Millar]] instead. While ''Spider-Man/Black Cat'' was ultimately completed in 2005, ''Daredevil/Bullseye: The Target'' remains unfinished, with one issue published.

Smith wrote the limited series ''[[Batman: Cacophony]]'', with art by friend [[Walt Flanagan]], which ran from November 2008 to January 2009. As announced at the 2008 [[San Diego Comic-Con]], the series featured the villains [[Onomatopoeia (comics)|Onomatopoeia]] (a character created by Smith during his run at Green Arrow), [[Joker (comics)|The Joker]], [[Maxie Zeus]], and [[Victor Zsasz]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://comics.ign.com/articles/893/893741p1.html |title=SDCC 08: Kevin Smith Tackles New Batman Series |publisher=Comics.ign.com |author=Richard George |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[trade paperback]] of ''Batman: Cacophony'' became a [[New York Times Bestseller]] in their Hardcover Graphic Books section.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/18/books/bestseller/bestgraphicbooks.html | work=The New York Times | title=Graphic Books | date=October 18, 2009 | accessdate=May 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 Smith subsequently wrote a six-issue [[Batman]] mini-series called ''[[Batman: The Widening Gyre|The Widening Gyre]]'' for DC, and a [[The Green Hornet|Green Hornet]] story for [[Dynamite Entertainment]], the latter of which was based on an unused script he wrote for a ''Green Hornet'' film project that never came to fruition.&lt;ref name=&quot;PopEWGH&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Kevin. [http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=389 &quot;Me and Comics Sitting in a Tree, F-U-C-K-I- and G! (See? now it’s SFW)&quot;], Silent Bob Speaks, May 13, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2011, Dynamite Entertainment debuted ''[[The Bionic Man]]'' by Smith, which was based on a 1998 script he wrote that was rejected by Universal as being &quot;more like a comic book than a movie.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.comicbookresources.com/?id=32295&amp;page=article &quot;Kevin Smith's 'Bionic Man' Debuts at Dynamite&quot;]. Comic Book Resources. May 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===
In 2000, Smith and Mosier teamed up with television writer [[David Mandel]] to develop an animated television show based on ''Clerks.'' called ''[[Clerks: The Animated Series]]'' that aired on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] in May 2000. It aired only two episodes before being canceled as a result of poor ratings. The six produced episodes were released on DVD in 2001.

During the mid-1990s Smith directed and starred in a series of commercials for MTV, alongside [[Jason Mewes]], in which they reprised their roles as [[Jay &amp; Silent Bob]]. In 1998 he directed best friend Jason Mewes as &quot;Gary Lamb – Ground Activist&quot; in a series of [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]] commercials. That same year, he also shot commercials for Diet Coke. Two years later, he directed &quot;Star Wars&quot; toy commercials for Hasbro. He has also directed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewaskew.com/tv/panasonic/index.html |title=Kevin's Panasonic e-Wear Commercials |publisher=The View Askewniverse |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and starred&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewaskew.com/tv/panasonic/dvdr.html |title=Kevin Smith – Cultural Historian |publisher=The View Askewniverse |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; in commercials for [[Panasonic]]. In 2004 he also shot a [[public service announcement]] for the [[Declare Yourself]] organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewaskew.com/news/jul04/1.html |title=The View Askewniverse – News – KEVIN SHOOTS 'DECLARE YOURSELF' PSA'S |publisher=Viewaskew.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; These advertisements brought [[Jay and Silent Bob]] out of their &quot;semi-retirement.&quot;

On February 27, 2002 Kevin released a short film for ''[[The Tonight Show]]'' called &quot;[[The Flying Car]]&quot;.

===Acting roles and other appearances===
As an actor, Smith is known for his role as [[Jay and Silent Bob|Silent Bob]] in ''[[Clerks]]'', ''[[Mallrats]]'', ''[[Chasing Amy]]'', ''[[Dogma (film)|Dogma]]'', ''[[Jay And Silent Bob Strike Back]]'', and ''[[Clerks II]]''. He made a cameo appearance in the horror film ''[[Scream 3]]'', and was featured along with [[Jason Mewes]] in several ''[[Degrassi: The Next Generation]]'' episodes, including a special, &quot;Jay and Silent Bob Do Degrassi&quot; (also as a fictional version of himself).

Smith also appeared in an [[mtvU]] show titled ''[[Sucks Less With Kevin Smith]]''. The show gives college students ideas for things to do on the weekends. Smith also played the role of Paul, a cynical divorced man, in a [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] television series pilot, &quot;Manchild&quot;, filmed in December 2006. However, it was not picked up by the network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quickstopentertainment.com/?p=4591 |title=SModcast 11 |publisher=Quickstopentertainment.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1995 to 1997, Smith played small roles in the View Askew movies ''[[Drawing Flies]]'', ''[[Vulgar (film)|Vulgar]]'', and ''[[Big Helium Dog]]''.

In 2001, he appeared in friend Jeff Anderson's ''[[Now You Know (film)|Now You Know]]''. After an August 2001 appearance on ''[[The Tonight Show with Jay Leno (1992 TV series)|The Tonight Show with Jay Leno]]'' to promote ''Jay and Silent Bob Strike Back'', Smith returned to the show for monthly segments as a correspondent. The &quot;Roadside Attractions&quot; segments featured Smith traveling to random locations around the country and showcased places like [[Howe Caverns]] in upstate New York and the Fish Market in [[Seattle]]. While five of these segments were included on the ''[[Jersey Girl (2004 film)|Jersey Girl]]'' DVD, at least twelve were aired on the actual show. Smith regularly appeared on the program to introduce the pre-taped pieces.

In 2003, Smith appeared in a cameo role as coroner [[Jack Kirby]] in the film ''[[Daredevil (film)|Daredevil]]''. In 2006, he voiced the Moose in the CGI cartoon ''[[Doogal]]''.

In early 2005, [[Degrassi: The Next Generation#Guest roles|Smith appeared in three episodes]] of the Canadian-made teen drama ''[[Degrassi: The Next Generation]]''. In the episodes, Smith, portraying a fictionalized version of himself, visited the school to work on the (fictional) film ''Jay and Silent Bob Go Canadian, Eh!'' Smith wrote all his dialogue for the shows he appeared in. All three episodes were collected on a DVD entitled ''Jay and Silent Bob Do Degrassi''. Smith and Mewes also appeared in two more episodes the following season, when they returned to Degrassi for the Toronto premiere of the fictional ''Jay and Silent Bob Go Canadian, Eh!'' movie.

From July 2006 on, Smith has guest reviewed on ''[[At the Movies with Ebert &amp; Roeper|Ebert &amp; Roeper]]'', in place of [[Roger Ebert]], who was recovering from [[thyroid cancer]] treatment. These spots have been notable for the arguments between Smith and [[Richard Roeper]] over certain films, with Smith often citing Roeper's poor review of ''Jersey Girl'' to discredit his review of the film at hand. On his most recent appearance, Smith compared [[Craig Brewer]]'s ''[[Black Snake Moan (film)|Black Snake Moan]]'' to the works of [[William Faulkner]].

In addition to appearing on ''Degrassi: The Next Generation'', Smith is an avid fan of the original ''[[Degrassi (franchise)|Degrassi]]'' series, ''[[Degrassi Junior High]]'' and ''[[Degrassi High]]'' and references to the original are present in some of his early films. He also appeared in the 2009 made for TV movie [[Degrassi Goes Hollywood]].

Smith directed the pilot for [[The CW Television Network]] show ''[[Reaper (TV Series)|Reaper]]''. TV.com's summary of the show is &quot;A twenty-something slacker finally scores a job as [[the devil]]'s [[bounty hunter]].&quot; He describes it as &quot;less ''[[Brimstone (TV series)|Brimstone]]'' or ''[[Dead Like Me]]'' and more like ''[[Shaun of the Dead]]'' than anything else&quot;. He went on to say that the reason he took the job was that he has always wanted to direct something he did not write, but never had an interest in doing it on the big screen.

At the 2007 [[Comic-Con International|San Diego Comic-Con]], it was announced that Smith would write and direct an episode of the ''[[Heroes (TV series)|Heroes]]'' spin-off, ''[[Heroes: Origins]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=342|title=The Guy Who Ruined &quot;Heroes&quot; |publisher=My Boring Ass Life |first=Kevin |last=Smith |date=July 30, 2007 |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the project was canceled because of the [[2007 Writers Guild of America strike]]. That year, Smith appeared in a number of films. He co-starred as Sam in the film ''[[Catch and Release (film)|Catch and Release]]'', starring [[Jennifer Garner]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=303 |title=Gimme an Oscar, Dammit! |publisher=Silentbobspeaks.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, he appeared as a hacker called The Warlock in the fourth installment of the [[Die Hard]] franchise, ''[[Live Free or Die Hard]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=334 |title=Live Free or Die Hard Opens Today |publisher=My Boring Ass Life |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; At year's end, he appeared briefly in friend and fellow writer-director [[Richard Kelly (director)|Richard Kelly's]] ''[[Southland Tales]]'', in which he played the legless conspiracy theorist General Simon Theory. That same year, Smith also did voicework for the CGI film ''[[TMNT (film)|TMNT]]'' as a diner chef. He was also seen as Rusty (a friend of lead Jason Mewes) in ''[[Bottoms Up (2006 film)|Bottoms Up]]'' with co-star Paris Hilton.

Smith has also cameoed in the [[Joey and the Big Break (Part I &amp; II)|second season premiere]] of the sitcom ''[[Joey (TV series)|Joey]]'', where he played himself, on an episode of ''[[Law &amp; Order]]'' in 2000 (episode &quot;Black, White and Blue&quot;), ''[[Duck Dodgers]]'' (2003 as [[Hal Jordan]], voice only) and ''[[Yes, Dear]]'' (2004, as himself and Silent Bob). Smith appeared in the second episode of season two of ''[[Driver Ed (Veronica Mars)|Veronica Mars]]'', playing a store clerk. He stated on his Web site that ''Veronica Mars'' is some of the best television work ever produced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=My Boring-Ass Life: Kevin Smith's Online Diary|url=http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=160 |last=Smith|first=Kevin|publisher=silentbobspeaks.com (via Internet Archive)|date=2005-09-03|accessdate=2008-10-20 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060508054854/http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=160 |archivedate = 2006-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith has also done small roles on television in shows such as ''[[Law &amp; Order]]'', ''[[Driver Ed (Veronica Mars)|Veronica Mars]]'', ''[[Joey and the Big Break (Part I &amp; II)|Joey]]'', ''[[Degrassi: The Next Generation]]'', ''[[Phineas and Ferb]]''. In an episode of ''[[Yes, Dear]]'', he appeared as Silent Bob, standing while smoking a cigarette as the end credits rolled.

Smith has appeared in four Q&amp;A documentaries: ''[[An Evening with Kevin Smith]]'', ''[[An Evening with Kevin Smith 2: Evening Harder]]'' and ''[[Sold Out: A Threevening with Kevin Smith]]''. The fourth installment, ''[[Kevin Smith: Too Fat for 40]]'' was broadcast on [[Epix (TV channel)|epix]] on October 23, 2010. The first is a collection of filmed appearances at American colleges, while the sequel was shot at two Q&amp;A shows held in [[Toronto]] and London. The third and fourth were filmed in Red Bank, New Jersey at the Count Basie Theater on Smith's 37th and 40th birthdays, respectively. The first two DVD sets were released by Sony Home Video, while the third was put out by the Weinstein Company. Smith appears with Marvel Comics guru [[Stan Lee]] in ''Marvel Then &amp; Now: An Evening With Stan Lee and Joe Quesada, hosted by Kevin Smith''. The film is similar in tone to the ''Evening with Kevin Smith'' series. Proceeds from the sale of the film benefit [[The Hero Initiative]], a charitable organization that aids ill or aging comic book creators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.thenandnowdvd.org |title = Then and Now DVD |accessdate = January 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public appearances===
Smith's longest Q&amp;A session took place April&amp;nbsp;2, 2005, at the [[Count Basie Theatre]] in [[Red Bank, New Jersey|Red Bank]], New Jersey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsaskew.com/2005/04/03/madness-in-red-bank-kev-packs-the-basie/ |title=Madness In Red Bank: Kev Packs The Basie! |publisher=News Askew |author=Brad |date=April 3, 2005 |accessdate=November 9, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080801065135/http://www.newsaskew.com/2005/04/03/madness-in-red-bank-kev-packs-the-basie/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = August 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sold-out event was over seven hours long, took place from 8&amp;nbsp;pm through 3&amp;nbsp;am (which due to [[daylight saving time]], was actually 4&amp;nbsp;am). Following the Q&amp;A, he opened [[Jay and Silent Bob's Secret Stash]] for a meet-and-greet with the numerous remaining audience members, which ended around 6:30&amp;nbsp;am. Smith then hopped a plane and did another Q&amp;A at the Raue Center For The Arts in [[Crystal Lake, Illinois|Crystal Lake]], Illinois, that night. Planned for two hours, it lasted just over five hours, ending a little after 1&amp;nbsp;am Central time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsaskew.com/cgi-bin/coranto/iSay.cgi?Page=Comments&amp;ID=EEEkVVZEEAyrVjcdhf |title=NewsAskew Talk Back! |publisher=Newsaskew.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 Smith made a sold out appearance at [[Carnegie Hall]]  and the [[Sydney Opera House]] in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bernardin |first=Marc |url=http://popwatch.ew.com/popwatch/2009/06/kevin-smith-carnegie-hall.html |title=On the Scene: Kevin Smith at Carnegie Hall: Hilariously sullying an institution &amp;#124; EW.com |publisher=Popwatch.ew.com |date=June 18, 2009 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Clift |first=Tom |url=http://www.rowthree.com/2011/01/24/kevin-smith-buys-his-own-film-plans-to-self-distribute/ |title=Kevin Smith buys his own film, plans to self distribute |publisher=Row Three|date=September 11, 2011 |accessdate=January 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===On the Internet===
Smith has a website, The View Askewniverse, which opened in late 1995. He also has an online blog, &quot;My Boring-Ass Life&quot;, the contents of which were published in a book by the same name. ''[[Jay and Silent Bob Strike Back]]'''s fictional website MoviePoopShoot.com became real in 2002. It became [[Quick Stop Entertainment]] and was the home of SModcast until it was sold and Smodcast moved to a dedicated website Smodcast.com, which also carries the other Smodcast network [[podcast]]s in early 2010.

On February 5, 2007, Smith and [[Scott Mosier]] began [[SModcast]], a regular comedy podcast. SModcast has since spawned into a podcast network called the SModcast podcast network and its own [[digital radio]] station called SModcast internet radio (S.I.R).

==Secret Stash==
Smith owns and operates [[Jay and Silent Bob's Secret Stash]] in [[Red Bank, New Jersey|Red Bank]], New Jersey, a comic book store largely dedicated to merchandise related to his films and comics. The current location is its second. The store was moved to a defunct ice cream parlor on Broad St. after Smith sold the Monmouth St. property. The New Jersey location is managed by Smith's long time friend [[Walt Flanagan]], who appears frequently in Smith's films. A second Secret Stash in the Westwood section of Los Angeles was opened in September 2004 and was managed by long-time associate Bryan Johnson, who has appeared in Smith's films as Steve-Dave.&lt;ref name=&quot;stash&quot;&gt;Smith, Kevin. [http://silentbobspeaks.com/?p=353 ''Some pity-oral, who is and isn’t “Zack”, and the shuttering of a comic book emporium'']. My Boring Ass Life. September 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Smith had announced that he would close after his lease expired and Johnson wanted to resign, but eventually relocated to Laser Blazer, a DVD store in Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;Lin, Jennifer. [http://www.dailybruin.ucla.edu/news/2007/nov/19/smith-relocates-his-secret-stash/ ''Smith relocates his Secret Stash'']. UCLA Daily Bruin. November 19, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2009 the West Coast Store closed, leaving the east coast store as Smith's only operating store.

==Controversies==
===2010 Southwest Airlines incident===
On February 13, 2010, Kevin Smith was on board a [[Southwest Airlines]] flight in Oakland bound for Burbank when he was removed from the plane, allegedly over concerns he was too obese to fly safely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fox40.com/news/headlines/ktxl-news-silentbob0214,0,579696.story |title=&quot;Silent Bob&quot; Thrown Off Southwest Flight For Being Too Large |publisher=Fox40.com |date=February 14, 2010 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Per Smith, he was able to put both armrests down in accordance with Southwest Airlines policy, and both passengers on either side did not object to his presence. Smith was then removed from the flight after being told he was a safety concern. After being booked on a later flight and being offered a $100 Southwest Airlines voucher, which he turned down, Smith lashed out at Southwest Airlines on his Twitter account.

Southwest Airlines representatives later released two statements regarding the incident via their blog.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blogsouthwest.com/blog/not-so-silent-bob |title=Not So Silent Bob |publisher=Blogsouthwest.com |date=February 14, 2010 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first statement, Southwest claimed that Mr. Smith &quot;has been known to (...) purchase two Southwest seats&quot; and cited its &quot;Customer of Size&quot; policy which requires that customers who cannot put their armrests down purchase two seats. In his podcast, Smith stated that he regularly purchased two seats, and had done so the previous week, because he preferred not having to sit next to anyone, not due to his size. In releasing this statement, Southwest disclosed Smith's personal travel details without his permission. The first statement also claimed that the flight captain has personally determined that Smith was too large to fly. In its second statement, Southwest contradicted this claim, stating that the captain had not singled out Smith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rutherford |first=Linda |url=http://www.blogsouthwest.com/blog/my-conversation-with-kevin-smith-0 |title=Blog &amp;#124; Nuts About Southwest |publisher=Blogsouthwest.com |date=1999-02-22 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith later released an entire episode of [[SModcast]] devoted to the subject, giving a lengthy description of the incident, in which he claimed that he had been able to lower the armrests completely and comfortably and claimed to have been repeatedly lied to by airline personnel. He also referred to the airline as the &quot;[[Greyhound Lines|Greyhound]] of the Air&quot; and vowed to never fly the airline again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smodcast.com/smods/smodcast106.html |title=SModcast 106: Fuck Southwest Airlines |publisher=Smodcast.com |date= |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his podcast, Smith stated that on his return flight a large female passenger was told to ask him if it was all right that she was sitting next to an empty seat he had bought between them, and it was suggested by Southwest staffers that she may need to purchase an additional seat due to her size, even though she had been placed next to an already-purchased empty seat. She was also the subject of an episode of [[SModcast]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smodcast.com/smods/smodcast107.html |title=SModcast 107: Thinicism |publisher=Smodcast.com |date= |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith also released 24 video statements on YouTube further describing the incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/profile?user=SModcaster#p/u |title=Youtube Statement |publisher=Youtube.com |date=April 14, 2009 |accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A year after the incident, he had lost 65 pounds through controlled diet and regular exercise, including walking up and down a hill near his home in the [[Hollywood Hills]].&lt;ref name=NYPost&gt;Stewawrt, Sara. [http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/movies/kevin_can_wait_erGWlh3wkIje6kK6x1TRlL &quot;Kevin can wait&quot;], ''[[The New York Post]]'', March 3, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Cop Out'' controversy===
A talent rep associated with the production of ''Cop Out'' reported conflicts on set between Smith and [[Bruce Willis]], saying of Smith, &quot;He smokes way too much pot. He sat behind his monitor. He didn't interact with the actors. The actors felt they were on their own.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Masters, Kim. [http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/kevin-smith-alarmist-ninnies-misinterpreted-95811 &quot;Kevin Smith: 'Alarmist Ninnies' Misinterpreted Sundance Outburst&quot;]. ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]''. February 3, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Smith defended his use of marijuana while working, claiming &quot;I dealt with every actor who wanted to be dealt with on that set&quot; and pointed to the amount of projects he worked on while making ''Cop Out'' to counter claims he was unproductive because of marijuana.&lt;ref name=red1&gt;{{cite web|last=Smith|first=Kevin|title=Some Questions &amp; Answers About Red State|url=http://theredstatements.com/2011/02/01/some-questions-answers-about-red-state/|work=Blog|publisher=Smodcast|accessdate=20 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith admitted in an interview that heavy marijuana-smoking had become an integral part of his work ethic after claiming that he watched actor [[Seth Rogen]] on the set of ''[[Zack and Miri Make a Porno]]'' use marijuana as a tool to become a more creative and &quot;productive&quot; worker, saying &quot;The moment I start smoking, I start working. ... That way, no one could ever take it away from you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted 2/9/11 |url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1657568/kevin-smith-i-became-stoner-because-seth-rogen.jhtml |title=Kevin Smith: 'I Became A Stoner Because Of Seth Rogen' - MTV Movie News |publisher=MTV |date=2011-02-09 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{rquote|right|Kevin Smith thinks critics should have had to pay to see &quot;Cop Out.&quot; But Kev, then they would REALLY have hated it.|Critic [[Roger Ebert]], responding to Smith&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Roger Ebert|url=http://twitter.com/ebertchicago/status/11199254151|title=Kevin Smith thinks critics should have had to pay to see &quot;Cop Out.&quot; But Kev, then they would REALLY have hated it.|publisher=Twitter|date=March 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}In response to the critical drubbing his 2010 film ''[[Cop Out (2010 film)|Cop Out]]'' received, Kevin Smith lashed out at the community of film critics on his Twitter account saying, &quot;Writing a nasty review for ''Cop Out'' is akin to bullying a retarded kid. All you’ve done is make fun of something that wasn't doing you any harm and wanted only to give some cats some fun laughs.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mtv.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1634755/20100325/story.jhtml |title=Kevin Smith's Online Rant Gets Heated Response From Film Critics |publisher=MTV |date=March 25, 2010|accessdate=August 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.reelloop.com/9374/news/kevin-smith-attacks-critics-writing-nasty-review-cop-out-akin-bullying-retarded-kid/|title=Kevin Smith Attacks Critics: ‘Writing a Nasty Review For ‘Cop Out’ is Akin to Bullying a Retarded Kid’}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith also implied on Twitter that he may charge critics for advance screenings of his films, a service which has typically been provided free; this subsequently ignited a strong response from some critics condemning his stance as &quot;dishonest&quot; and &quot;disingenuous&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;mtv.com&quot;/&gt;

==Personal life==
Smith is married to [[Jennifer Schwalbach Smith]], and photographed her for the magazine ''[[Playboy]]''. Their daughter, Harley Quinn, was born June 26, 1999, and was named after [[Harley Quinn|the character]] from ''[[Batman: The Animated Series]]'', who was created by friend and fellow writer [[Paul Dini]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.viewaskew.com/harley/|title=View Askew Productions – Harley Quinn Smith|accessdate=March 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; They live in the [[Hollywood Hills]],&lt;ref name=NYPost/&gt; in a house Smith purchased from longtime friend Ben Affleck in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;Jarett Wieselman [http://www.nypost.com/p/blogs/popwrap/kevin_smith_reveals_the_inner_workings_Gz6BTHdpJtYJkZhBnq0s7M &quot;Kevin Smith takes you inside Ben Affleck's panic room ... if you buy 'Cop Out'&quot;]. ''[[New York Post]]''. July 20, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although Smith was raised Catholic, he has said on &quot;Back to the Well&quot;, the ''Clerks II'' documentary, that now he only goes to Mass on the day before he starts production of a movie, and the day before it premieres. He never smoked until his debut film, ''Clerks'', in which he used the cigarettes as a prop, but never actually inhaled. In fact, he has said that prior to filming ''Clerks'', he was a staunch non-smoker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.silentbobspeaks.com |title=My Boring Ass Life}}&lt;/ref&gt; He quit smoking cigarettes in 2008 after taking up smoking [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]]. Smith only began smoking pot at age 38 after working with [[Seth Rogen]] on ''[[Zack and Miri Make a Porno]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/09/02/kevin-smith-leno-smoking-pot-video_n_946832.html &quot;Kevin Smith Talks Smoking Weed On Leno (VIDEO)&quot;]. ''[[The Huffington Post]]''. September 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Kevin Smith is a hockey fan and loyal [[New Jersey Devils]] fan. Smith has also expressed an admiration for his second-favorite team, the [[Edmonton Oilers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bigleaguescrew.com/nhl/new-jerseys-kevin-smith-ditches-devils-for-oilers|title=New Jersey's Kevin Smith Ditches Devils for Oilers|publisher=Big League Screw|date=November 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{Main|Kevin Smith filmography}}

==Recognition==
{{Main|List of recognition for Kevin Smith}}

==Bibliography==
===Books===
Books by Smith include:
* ''[[Silent Bob Speaks]]''
* ''[[My Boring Ass Life: The Uncomfortably Candid Diary of Kevin Smith]]''
* ''[[SModcast|Shootin' the Sh*t with Kevin Smith]]''
* ''Tough Shit: Life Advice from a Fat, Lazy Slob Who Did Good''

===Comics===
* ''[[Daredevil: Guardian Devil]]'' (with [[Joe Quesada]], Marvel Comics, 1998–1999)
* ''[[Green Arrow: Quiver]]'' (with [[Phil Hester (comics)|Phil Hester]], DC Comics, 2001–2002)
* ''[[Green Arrow]]: Sounds of Violence'' (with Phil Hester, DC Comics, 2002)
* ''[[Spider-Man/Black Cat: The Evil that Men Do]]'' (with [[Terry Dodson]], Marvel Comics, 2002, 2005–2006)
* ''[[Batman: Cacophony]]'' (with [[Walt Flanagan]], DC Comics, 2008–2009)
* ''[[Batman: The Widening Gyre]]'' (with Walt Flanagan, DC Comics, 2009–2012)
* ''[[The Green Hornet|Green Hornet]]'' (with Jonathan Lau, Dynamite Entertainment, 2010)
* ''[[The Bionic Man]]'' (with Jonathan Lau, Phil hester, Dynamite Entertainment, 2011–2012)

Trade paperback introductions:
* ''[[Hitman (comics)|Hitman]]: 10,000 Bullets'' (by [[Garth Ennis]], DC Comics, 1996)
* ''[[Preacher (comics)|Preacher]]: Until the End of the World'' (by Garth Ennis, Vertigo Comics, 1995)

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Kevin Smith}}
{{Wikiquote}}

* {{wikiaskew}}
* [http://www.viewaskew.com/ View Askew Production]
* [http://silentbobspeaks.com/ Smith's blog]
* {{IMDb name|0003620}}
* {{twitter|thatkevinsmith}}
*[http://boingboing.net/2009/04/27/kevin-smith-explains.html  Kevin Smith explains what happened to his ''Superman'' movie]
* [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kevin-smith Huffington Post blog]
* {{comicbookdb|type=creator|id=124|title=Kevin Smith}}
* {{amg name|111916}}
* {{Charlie Rose view|3236}}

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box| title=''[[Daredevil (Marvel Comics)|Daredevil]]'' writer| before=[[D. G. Chichester|D.G. Chichester]]&lt;br /&gt;([[Daredevil (Marvel Comics)|''Daredevil'' Vol. 1]]) |after=[[David W. Mack|David Mack]] | years=1998–1999}}
{{end}}
{{Kevin Smith}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME= Smith, Kevin Patrick
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Screenwriter, Film director, Film producer, Actor, [[Comic book|Comic book writer]]
|DATE OF BIRTH= August 2, 1970
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Red Bank, New Jersey|Red Bank]], New Jersey US
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Smith, Kevin}}
[[Category:1970 births]]
[[Category:Actors from New Jersey]]
[[Category:American bloggers]]
[[Category:American comics writers]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American film directors]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:American podcasters]]
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:American screenwriters]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:American writers of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Harvey Award winners for Best New Talent]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Monmouth County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People from Red Bank, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Science fiction fans]]
[[Category:The New School alumni]]
[[Category:View Askewniverse]]
[[Category:Writers from New Jersey]]



[[bs:Kevin Smith]]
[[ca:Kevin Smith]]
[[cs:Kevin Smith]]
[[da:Kevin Smith]]
[[de:Kevin Smith]]
[[es:Kevin Smith]]
[[fa:کوین اسمیت]]
[[fr:Kevin Smith (réalisateur)]]
[[hr:Kevin Smith]]
[[is:Kevin Smith]]
[[it:Kevin Smith]]
[[he:קווין סמית']]
[[hu:Kevin Smith]]
[[nl:Kevin Smith (regisseur)]]
[[ja:ケヴィン・スミス]]
[[no:Kevin Smith]]
[[nn:Kevin Smith]]
[[uz:Kevin Smith]]
[[pl:Kevin Smith]]
[[pt:Kevin Smith]]
[[ru:Смит, Кевин]]
[[simple:Kevin Smith]]
[[sr:Кевин Смит]]
[[fi:Kevin Smith]]
[[sv:Kevin Smith]]
[[tr:Kevin Smith]]
[[uk:Кевін Сміт]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
