<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6045065" ns="0" title="South Lebanon conflict (1982–2000)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
| conflict = South Lebanon conflict
| partof   = the [[Israeli–Lebanese conflict]], [[Lebanese Civil War]] and [[Arab–Israeli conflict]]
| image    = [[File:Troepen idf.jpg|250px]]
| caption  = Israeli troops in South Lebanon, June, 1982
| date     = 1982–2000
| place    = [[Southern Lebanon]]
| result   = * PLO withdrawal from Lebanon
* Unilateral withdrawal of Israeli forces from Lebanon as part of a greater peace plan&lt;ref name='bicom_timeline'&gt;{{cite web 
  | url        = http://www.bicom.org.uk/context/timelines/land-for-peace-timeline 
  | title      = Land for Peace Timeline
  | author     = 
  | date       = 2006
  | work       = 
  | publisher  = British-Israeli Communications &amp; Research Centre
  | accessdate = 25 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='jvl_withdrawl'&gt;{{cite web
  | url        = http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Peace/lebwith.html
  | title      = The Israeli Withdrawal from Southern Lebanon
  | author     = 
  | date       = 2011
  | work       = 
  | publisher  = The American-Israeli Cooperative Enterprise
  | accessdate = 25 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Consolidation of Resistance under Hezbollah leadership
* The dissolution of the Lebanese National Resistance Front
* The collapse and surrender of the South Lebanon Army (SLA)
* Reduced significance of other militant forces, including PLO
| combatant2  =[[File:Hezbollah flag.jpg|22px]] '''[[Hezbollah]]''' &lt;br /&gt; [[File:Flag of Syria.svg|22px|border]] '''[[Syria]]''' &lt;br /&gt; [[File:Flag of Lebanon.svg|22px|border]] [[Lebanese National Resistance Front|LNRF]]&lt;br/&gt; [[File:Flag of Palestine.svg|22px|border]] [[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO]] &lt;br /&gt; [[File:Flag of the Amal Movement.svg|22px|border]] [[Amal Movement|Amal]]
| combatant1  = [[File:Flag of Israel.svg|22px|border]] '''[[Israel]]''' &lt;br /&gt; [[File:South Lebanon Army Patch.png|22px|border]] '''[[South Lebanon Army|SLA]]'''
| commander2  = [[File:Flag of Palestine.svg|22px|border]] [[Yasser Arafat]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag of the Lebanese Communist Party.svg|22px|border]] [[George Hawi]] &lt;br /&gt;[[File:Hezbollah flag.jpg|22px]] [[Abbas al-Musawi]] {{KIA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Hezbollah flag.jpg|22px]] [[Hassan Nasrallah]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag of the Amal Movement.svg|22px|border]] [[Nabih Berri]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag of Syria.svg|22px|border]] [[Hafez al-Assad]]
| commander1  = [[File:Flag of Israel.svg|22px|border]] [[Shimon Peres]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag of Israel.svg|22px|border]] [[Ariel Sharon]]&lt;br /&gt; [[File:Flag of Israel.svg|22px|border]] [[Ehud Barak]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:South Lebanon Army Patch.png|22px|border]] [[Saad Haddad]]&lt;br /&gt; [[File:South Lebanon Army Patch.png|22px|border]] [[Antoine Lahad]]
| strength1   = '''SLA:'''&lt;br /&gt;2,500&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/70/israels-security-zone-in-lebanon-a-tragedy]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''IDF:'''&lt;br /&gt;1,000-1,500 troops&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/70/israels-security-zone-in-lebanon-a-tragedy]&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 
| casualties1 = '''IDF:'''&lt;br /&gt;256 killed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/70/israels-security-zone-in-lebanon-a-tragedy]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''SLA:'''&lt;br /&gt;Several hundred killed&lt;br /&gt;
| casualties2 = '''Hezbollah:'''&lt;br /&gt;1,283 killed&lt;br /&gt;'''Syria:'''&lt;br /&gt;1 killed&lt;br /&gt;7 wounded&lt;br /&gt;'''LNRF:'''&lt;br /&gt;Unknown number of casualties
| casualties3 = 272-288 Lebanese civilians killed&lt;br /&gt;90 Israeli civilians killed
| notes       = 
| campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox South Lebanon 1982–2000}}
{{Campaignbox Israel-Lebanon conflict}}
}}
[[File:BlueLine.jpg|thumb|280px|The Blue Line covers the Lebanese-Israeli border; an extension covers the Lebanese-[[Golan Heights]] border]]

The '''South Lebanon conflict''' refers to nearly 20 years of warfare between the [[Israel Defense Force]] and its [[Lebanon|Lebanese]]  [[Proxy war|proxy]] [[militia]]s and Lebanese [[Islam|Muslim]] [[guerrilla]]s led by the [[Iran]]ian-backed [[Hezbollah]] within what was defined by Israelis as the &quot;Security Zone&quot; in South Lebanon.&lt;ref name=&quot;pbsnewshour_2000&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;independent_1993&quot;&gt;''[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/hizbollah-makes-explosive-return-israels-proxy-militia-under-fire-in-south-lebanon-1461794.html Hezbollah makes explosive return: Israel's proxy militia under fire in south Lebanon]''. Charles Richards, The Independent. 18 August 1993. Retrieved 15 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; It can also refer to the longer history of conflict in this region, beginning with [[PLO]] operations transfer to [[South Lebanon]], following the civil war events of 1971 [[Black September]] in the Kingdom of [[Jordan]]. Historical tension between [[Palestinians|Palestinian refugee]] and Lebanese factions fomented the violent Lebanese internal political struggle between many different factions. In light of this, the South Lebanon conflict can be seen as a part of the Lebanese Civil War.

Earlier conflicts prior to [[1982 Lebanon War|1982 Israeli invasion]], including [[Operation Litani]] attempted to eradicate the [[PLO]] bases from Lebanon and support Christian Maronite militias, following [[PLO]]'s constant attacks on civilian population of Galilee (Northern Israel). The 1982 invasion resulted in the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]]'s (PLO) departure from Lebanon. The creation of Security Zone in South Lebanon has benefited civilian Israeli population as Galilee suffered less violent attacks by Hezbollah (44 Israeli civilian casulaties), than previously by PLO in the 1970s (hundreds of Israeli civilian casualties). Despite this Israeli success in eradicating PLO bases and partial withdraw in 1985, the Israeli invasion had actually increased the severity of conflict with local Lebanese militias and resulted in the consolidation of several local Shia muslim movements in Lebanon, including [[Hezbollah]] and [[Amal Movement|Amal]], from a previously unorganized guerrilla movement in the south. Over the years, military casualties of both sides grew higher, as both parties used more modern weaponry, and Hezbollah progressed in its tactics. By the early 1990s, Hezbollah, with support from [[Syria]] and [[Iran]], emerged as the leading group and military power, monopolizing the directorship of the guerrilla activity in South Lebanon.

By the year 2000, following his campaign promise, newly elected Prime Minister [[Ehud Barak]] withdrew Israeli forces from Southern Lebanon within the year.&lt;ref name=&quot;pbsnewshour_2000&quot;&gt;Online NewsHour: ''[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/middle_east/jan-june00/israel_5-24.html Final Pullout - May 24, 2000]'' (Transcript).  &quot;Israelis evacuate southern Lebanon after 22 years of occupation.&quot; Retrieved 15 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; in accordance with [[UN Security Council Resolution 425]], passed in 1978; the withdrawal consequently resulted in the immediate total collapse of the [[South Lebanon Army|SLA]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2000/20000618.sc6878.doc.html UN Press Release SC/6878]. (18 June 2000). ''Security Council Endorses Secretary-General's Conclusion On Israeli Withdrawal From Lebanon As Of 16 June.''&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the Israeli actions, [[Lebanese government]] and Hezbollah consider the withdrawal incomplete until Israel withdraws from [[Shebaa Farms]]. Following the withdrawal, Hezbollah has monopolized its military and civil control of the southern part of Lebanon.

== Background ==
{{See also|Partition of the Ottoman Empire}}
Following the [[1948 Arab Israeli War]], the [[1949 Armistice Agreements]] were signed with United Nations mediation. The Lebanese-Israeli agreement created the armistice line, which coincided exactly with the existing international boundary between Lebanon and Palestine from the Mediterranean to the Syrian [[tri-point]] on the Hasbani River. From this tri-point on the Hasbani the boundary follows the river northward to the village of [[Ghajar]], then northeast, forming the Lebanese-Syrian border. (The southern line from the tri-point represents the Palestine-Syria border of 1923). Israeli forces captured and occupied 13 villages in Lebanese territory during the conflict, including parts of Marjayun, Bint Jubayl, and areas near the Litani River,&lt;ref name=&quot;AruriSacrTer&quot;&gt;Naseer H. Aruri, Preface to the 3rd(?) edition, Israel’s Sacred Terrorism, Livia Rokach, Association of Arab-American University Graduates, ISBN 978-0-937694-70-1&lt;/ref&gt; but withdrew following international pressure and the armistice agreement.

Although the Israel-Lebanon border remained relatively quiet, entries in the diary of [[Moshe Sharett]] point to a continued territorial interest in the area.&lt;ref&gt;Livia Rokach, Israel’s Sacred Terrorism, Association of Arab-American University Graduates, ISBN 978-0-937694-70-1&lt;/ref&gt; On May 16, 1954, during a joint meeting of senior officials of the defense and foreign affairs ministries, Ben Gurion raised the issue of Lebanon due to renewed tensions between Syria and Iraq, and internal trouble in Syria. Dayan expressed his enthusiastic support for entering Lebanon, occupying the necessary territory and creating a Christian regime that would ally itself with Israel. The issue was raised again in discussions at the [[Protocol of Sèvres]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Avi Shlaim]], [http://users.ox.ac.uk/~ssfc0005/The%20Protocol%20of%20Sevres%201956%20Anatomy%20of%20a%20War%20Plot.html  The Protocol of Sèvres,1956: Anatomy of a War Plot], [[International Affairs (journal)|International Affairs]], 73:3 (1997), 509-530&lt;/ref&gt;

The Israeli victory in the 1967 [[Six Day War]] vastly expanded their area occupied in all neighboring countries, with the exception of Lebanon, but this extended the length of the effective Lebanon-Israel border, with the occupation of the [[Golan Heights]].  Although with a stated requirement for defense, later Israeli expansion into Lebanon under very similar terms followed the [[Israeli legislative election, 1977|1977 elections]], which for the first time, brought the more militant, expansionist and [[Revisionist Zionism|Revisionist]] [[Likud]] to power.&lt;ref name=&quot;AruriSacrTer&quot;/&gt;

=== Emerging Conflict between Israel and Palestinian militants===
{{Main|Lebanese Civil War|1978 South Lebanon conflict}}
Beginning with late 1960s and especially in 1970s, following the defeat of PLO in [[Black September in Jordan]], displaced Palestinians, including militants affiliated with the [[Palestinian Liberation Organization]], began to settle in South Lebanon. The unrestrained buildup of Palestinian militia, and the large autonomy they exercised, led to the popular term &quot;[[Fatahland]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;'csi_gawrych'&quot;&gt;''Urban Operations: An Historical Casebook.''  &quot;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/report/2002/MOUTGawrych.htm Siege of Beirut]&quot;, by George W. Gawrych.  US Army [[Combat Studies Institute]], Fort Leavenworth, KS.  October 2, 2002. Available at globalsecurity.org.&lt;/ref&gt; for South Lebanon. Since mid 1970s the tensions between the various Lebanese factions and Palestinians had exploded, resulting in Lebanese Civil War.

Following multiple terrorist attacks launched by Palestinian organizations in the 1970, which increased with the Lebanese Civil War, the Israeli government decided to take action. Desiring to break up and destroy this PLO stronghold, Israel briefly invaded Lebanon in 1978, but the results of this invasion were mixed. The PLO was pushed north of the Litani River and a buffer zone was created to keep them from returning, with the placement of the [[United Nations Interim Force in Lebanon]] (UNIFIL). In addition and despite earlier covert support, Israel established a second buffer with renegade [[Saad Haddad]]’s Christian [[South Lebanon Army|Free Lebanon Army]] enclave (initially based only in the towns of [[Marjayoun]] and [[Qlayaa]]); the now-public Israeli military commitment to the Christian forces was strengthened. For the first time however, Israel received substantive adverse publicity in the world press for its heavy-handed treatment of South Lebanon, in which some 200,000 Lebanese (mostly Shia muslims) fled the area and ended up in the southern suburbs of Beirut; this indirectly resulted in the Syrian forces in Lebanon turning against the Christians in late June and complicated the dynamics of the on-going [[Lebanese Civil War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SollyIsrExp&quot;&gt;Major George C. Solley, [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/report/1987/SGC.htm ''The Israeli Experience in Lebanon, 1982-1985''], US Marine Corps Command and Staff College, [[United States Marine Corps Training and Education Command|Marine Corps Development and Education Command]], Quantico, Virginia. 10 May 1987. Available from [[GlobalSecurity.org]]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Israeli Invasion ===
{{Main|1982 Lebanon War}}
In 1982, the Israeli military began &quot;[[Operation Peace for Galilee]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcnews_1982inv&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7381364.stm 1982 Lebanon Invasion]. [[BBC News]].&lt;/ref&gt; a full scale invasion of Lebanese territory. The invasion followed the 1978 Litani Operation, which gave Israel possession of the territory near the Israeli-Lebanese border. This follow-up invasion attempted to weaken the PLO as a unified political and military force &lt;ref name=&quot;norton2000&quot;&gt;Norton, Augustus Richard; Journal of Palestine, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; and eventually led to the withdrawal of PLO and Syrian forces from Lebanon. By the end of this operation, Israel got control over Lebanon from Beirut southward, and attempted to install a pro-Israeli government in Beirut to sign a peace accord with it. This goal had never realized, partly because of the assassination of President [[Bashir Gemayel]] in September 1982, and the refusal of the Lebanese Parliament to endorse the accord. The withdrawal of the PLO forces in 1982 forced some Lebanese nationalists to start a resistance against the Israeli army led by the Lebanese Communist Party and Amal movement. During this time, some Amal members started the formation of an Islamic group supported by [[Iran]] that was the nucleus of the future &quot;Islamic Resistance&quot;, and eventually become [[Hezbollah]].

== Chronology ==
=== Occupation period 1982-1985 - the emergence of Hizbullah ===
[[File:Civil war Lebanon map 1983a.gif|thumb|Map showing power balance in Lebanon, 1983: Green - controlled by Syria, purple - controlled by Christian groups, yellow - controlled by Israel, blue - controlled by the United Nations]]
Increased hostilities against the US resulted in the April [[1983 United States Embassy bombing]].  In response, the US brokered the [[May 17 Agreement]], in an attempt to stall hostilities between Israel and Lebanon. However, this agreement eventually failed to take shape, and hostilities continued. In October, the United States Marines barracks [[1983 Beirut barracks bombing|in Beirut was bombed]] (usually attributed to the Islamic Resistance groups). Following this incident, the United States withdrew its military forces from Lebanon.

Suicide bombings became increasingly popular at this time, and were a major concern of the Israel Defense Forces (IDF) both near Beirut and in the South. Among the most serious were the two [[Tyre headquarters bombings|suicide bombings]] against the Israeli heaquarters in Tyre, which killed 103 soldiers, border policemen, and [[Shin Bet]] agents, and also killed 49-56 Lebanese. Israel withdrew from the [[Shouf|Shouf Mountains]], but continued to occupy Lebanon south of the [[Awali River]].

An increased number of Islamic militias began operating in South Lebanon, launching guerilla attacks on Israeli and pro-Israel militia positions. Israeli forces often responded with increased security measures and airstrikes on militant positions, and casualties on all sides steadily climbed. In a vacuum left with eradication of PLO, the disorganized Islamic militants in South Lebanon began to consolidate. The emerging [[Hezbollah]], soon to become the preeminent Islamic militia, evolved during this period. However, scholars disagree as to when Hezbollah came to be regarded as a distinct entity. Over time, a number of Shi’a group members were slowly assimilated into the organization, such as Islamic Jihad members, Organization of the Oppressed on Earth, and the Revolutionary Justice Organization.

=== Israeli withdrawal to Security Zone ===
In February 1985, Israel withdrew from [[Sidon]] and turned it over to the Lebanese Army, but faced attacks: 15 Israelis were killed and 105 wounded during the withdrawal. Dozens of SLA members were also assassinated. From mid-February to mid-March, the Israelis lost 18 dead and 35 wounded. On March 11, Israeli forces raided the town of [[Zrariyah]], killing 40 Amal fighters and capturing a large stock of arms. On April 9, a Shiite girl drove a car bomb into an IDF convoy, and the following day, a soldier was killed by a land mine. During that same period, Israeli forces killed 80 Lebanese guerrillas in five weeks. Another 1,800 Shi'as were taken as prisoners. Israel withdrew from the Bekaa valley on April 24, and from [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]] on the 29th, but continued to occupy a security zone in Southern Lebanon.

In 1985 Hezbollah released an open letter to &quot;The Downtrodden in Lebanon and in the World&quot;, which stated that the world was divided between the oppressed and the oppressors.  The oppressors were named to be mainly the United States and Israel.  This letter legitimized and praised the use of violence against the enemies of Islam, mainly the West. The newfound unity among these Shi'a resistance groups in 1985 has been credited{{By whom|date=August 2009}} to the disappearance of [[Musa al-Sadr]]. Fighting the Israeli occupation included hit-and-run guerrilla attacks, suicide bombings, and the [[Katyusha rocket launcher|Katyusha]] rocket attacks on civilian targets in Northern Israel, including [[Kiryat Shmona]]. The Katyusha proved to be an effective weapon and became [[Hezbollah rocket force#Fajr rockets|a mainstay of the resistance]] in South Lebanon. The attacks resulted in both military and civilian casualties. However, a considerable number of Lebanese guerillas were killed fighting Israeli and SLA troops, and many were captured. Prisoners were often detained in Israeli military prisons, or by the SLA in the infamous [[Khiam detention center]], where detainees were often tortured. [[Lebanese prisoners in Israel]] were arrested and detained for participating in guerilla movements, and many were held for long periods of time.

After Israel destroyed Hezbollah's headquarters in the town of [[Marrakeh]], a Hezbollah suicide bomber destroyed an Israeli transport truck carrying soldiers on the Israel-Lebanon border. In response, Israeli forces ambushed two Hezbollah vehicles, killing eight Hezbollah fighters.&lt;ref&gt;Ross, Michael ''The Volunteer: The Incredible True Story of an Israeli Spy on the Trail of International Terrorists'' (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 28, 1989, Israeli commandos captured Sheikh Abdul Karim Obeid, the leader of Hezbollah. This action led to the adoption of [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 638]], which condemned all hostage takings by all sides.&lt;ref name='UN638'&gt;{{cite web
| url        = http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/RESOLUTION/GEN/NR0/557/75/IMG/NR055775.pdf
| title      = The Question of Hostage-Taking and Abduction
| author     = UN Security Council 
| date       = July 31, 1989
| work       = [http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/1989/scres89.htm Security Council Resolutions, 1989]
| publisher  = United Nations
| accessdate = 25 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/UN/unres638.html UN Resolution 638], reprinted by Jewish Virtual Library&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Taif Accord ===
The Lebanese Civil War officially came to an end with the 1989 [[Ta'if Accord]], but the armed combat continued at least until October 1990,&lt;ref name=&quot;norton2000&quot;/&gt; and in South Lebanon until at least 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes_1991&quot;&gt;''[http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/08/world/tension-grows-in-south-lebanon-as-israel-bombs-guerrilla-targets.html Tension grows in South Lebanon as Israel bombs guerrilla targets.]''  New York Times, November 8, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;  In fact, the continued Israeli presence in South Lebanon resulted in continued [[low-intensity warfare]] and sporadic major combat until the Israeli withdrawal in 2000.

=== Post Civil War conflict ===
Though the majority of the Lebanese civil war conflicts ended in the months following the [[Taif Agreement|Ta'if Accord]], Israel kept maintaining a military presence in South Lebanon. Consequently, the Islamic Resistance, by now dominated by [[Hezbollah]], continued operations in the South. On February 16, 1992, Hezbollah leader [[Abbas al-Musawi]] was killed along with his wife, son and four others when Israeli [[AH-64 Apache]] helicopter gunships fired three missiles at his motorcade. The Israeli attack came in retaliation for the killings of three Israeli soldiers two days earlier when their camp was infiltrated. Hezbollah responded with rocket fire onto the Israeli security zone, and Israel then fired back and sent two armored columns past the security zone to hit Hezbollah strongholds in [[Kafra, Lebanon|Kafra]] and [[Yater]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Time Magazine]]: Vengeance is Mine (2 March 1992)&lt;/ref&gt; Musawi was succeeded by [[Hassan Nasrallah]]. One of Nasrallah's first public declarations was the &quot;retribution&quot; policy: If Israel hit Lebanese civilian targets, then Hezbollah would retaliate with attacks on Israeli territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;norton2000&quot;/&gt;  Meanwhile, Hezbollah continued attacks against IDF targets within occupied Lebanese territory.

In 1993, hostilities flared again. After a month of Hezbollah shelling on Israeli towns and attacks on its soldiers, Israel conducted a seven-day operation called [[Operation Accountability]] in order to hit [[Hezbollah]]. One Israeli soldier and 8-50 Hezbollah fighters were killed in the operation, along with 2 Israeli and 118 Lebanese civilians. After one week of fighting in South Lebanon, a mutual agreement mediated by the [[United States]] prohibited attacks on civilian targets by both parts.&lt;ref name='globsec-opacct'&gt;{{cite web 
| url        = http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/lebanon-accountability.htm
| title      = &quot;Operation Accountability&quot;
| author     = John Pike 
| date       = July 30, 2006
| work       = 
| publisher  = [[Global Security]]
| accessdate = 25 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Hezbollah soon broke the cease-fire, and sporadically attacked Israeli positions and its proxy, the [[South Lebanon Army|SLA]].&lt;ref name=&quot;independent_1993&quot;/&gt;

In May 1994, Israeli commandos kidnapped an Amal leader [[Mustafa Dirani]], and in June, an Israeli airstrike against a training camp killed 30-45 Hezbollah cadets. Hezbollah retaliated by firing four barrages of [[Katyusha]] rockets into northern Israel.&lt;ref name='nytimes-1994-06-03'&gt;{{cite news 
| url        = http://www.nytimes.com/1994/06/03/world/dozens-are-killed-as-israelis-attack-camp-in-lebanon.html
| title      = Dozens Are Killed As Israelis Attack Camp in Lebanon
| author     = Clyde Haberman
| date       = June 3, 1994
| work       = 
| publisher  = [[New York Times]]
| accessdate = 25 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Continued hostility in late 1990s ===
[[Operation Grapes of Wrath]] resulted in the deaths of more than 150 civilians and refugees, most of them in the [[1996 shelling of Qana|shelling of a United Nations base]] at [[Qana]]. Within a few days, a [[Israeli–Lebanese Ceasefire Understanding|ceasefire]] was agreed between Israel and Hezbollah, committing to avoid civilian casualties; however, combat continued for at least two months. A total of 14 Hezbollah fighters, 1 Syrian soldier, and 3 Israeli soldiers were killed in the fighting.

On 4 February 1997, [[1997 Israeli helicopter disaster|two Israeli transport helicopters collided]] over [[She'ar Yashuv]] in Northern Israel while waiting for clearance to fly into Lebanon. A total of 73 IDF soldiers were killed in the disaster. On 28 February one Israeli soldier and four Hezbollah guerrillas were killed in a bloody clash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1997-03-01/news/mn-33669_1_southern-lebanon | work=Los Angeles Times | date=1 March 1997 | title=Israeli Soldier, 4 Guerrillas Die in Lebanon Clash}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 August 1997, Israeli soldiers killed five Hezbollah gunmen, including two area commanders, in a clash north of the security zone.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jta.org/news/article/1997/08/06/1754/BIsraelkillsfive&lt;/ref&gt; On September 5th 1997, a raid by 16 Israeli [[Shayetet 13]] naval commandos failed after the troops stumbled into an [[Improvised Explosive Device|IED]] ambush, killing 12.&lt;ref&gt;End of the mystery: the failiure that caused the flotilla disaster. [[Maariv]]. 30.08.2007&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterward, Hezbollah fighter Hadi Nasrallah was killed in a clash with Israeli soldiers. Hadi was the son of Hezbollah leader [[Hassan Nasrallah]].

During 1999, several dozen Hezbollah and Amal fighters were killed. Twelve Israeli soldiers and one civilian were also killed, one of them in accident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jewishvirtualibrary.org/jsource/History/leb99.html&lt;/ref&gt; Hezbollah also captured an Israeli [[M113 armored personnel carrier]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

=== 2000: Israeli withdrawal ===
[[File:south leb army hezbo khomemi.JPG|thumb|A captured SLA Army tank, featuring a wooden portrait of the late [[Ruhollah Khomeini|Ayatollah Khomeini]] now on display in southern Lebanon]]
In July 1999, [[Ehud Barak]] became Israel's Prime Minister, promising Israel would unilaterally withdraw to the international border by July 2000. Prior to his actions, many believed that Israel would only withdraw from South Lebanon upon reaching an agreement with Syria.

In January 2000, Hezbollah assassinated the commander of the South Lebanon Army's Western Brigade, Colonel [[Aql Hashem]], at his home in the security zone. Hashem had been responsible for day to day operations of the SLA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asylumlaw.org/docs/lebanon/ind01b_lebanon_ca.pdf Lebanon Country Assessment]. [[United Kingdom Home Office]], October 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; After this assassination there were doubts about the leadership of the South Lebanon Army (SLA).

During the spring of 2000, Hezbollah operations stepped up considerably, with persistent harassment of Israeli military outposts in occupied Lebanese territory. As preparation for the major withdrawal plan, Israeli forces began abandoning several forward positions within the security zone of South Lebanon. On 24 May, Israel announced that it would withdraw all troops from South Lebanon. All Israeli forces had withdrawn from Lebanon by the end of the next day, more than six weeks before its stated deadline of 7 July.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc_leb_timeline&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/country_profiles/819200.stm Country Profile: Lebanon Timeline], BBC News.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Israeli pullout resulted in the collapse of the SLA and the rapid advance of Hezbollah forces into the area. As the Israeli Defense Forces (IDF) withdrew, thousands of Shi'a Lebanese rushed back to the South to reclaim their properties. This withdrawal was widely considered a victory for Hezbollah and boosted its popularity in Lebanon. The completeness of the withdrawal is still disputed as Lebanese Government and Hizbollah claim Israel still holds [[Shebaa farms]], a small piece of territory on the Lebanon-Israel-Syria border, with disputed sovereignty.

As a Syrian-backed Lebanese government refused to demarcate its border with Israel, Israel worked with UN cartographers led by regional coordinator [[Terje Rød-Larsen]] to certify Israel had withdrawn from all occupied Lebanese territory. On June 16, 2000, UN Security Council concluded that Israel had indeed withdrawn its forces from all of Lebanon, in accordance with [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 425]] (1978).

Israel considered this move as tactical withdrawal since it always regarded the [[Israeli Security Zone|Security Zone]] as a buffer zone to defend Israel's citizens. By ending the occupation, Barak's cabinet assumed it would improve its worldwide image. [[Ehud Barak]] has argued that &quot;Hezbollah would have enjoyed international legitimacy in their struggle against a foreign occupier&quot;, if the Israelis had not unilaterally withdrew without a peace agreement.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.nybooks.com/articles/15501 Camp David and After: An Exchange].''  (An Interview with [[Ehud Barak]]).  New York Review of Books, Volume 49, Number 10.  June 13, 2002.  Retrieved online, 15 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
{{Main|2000–2006 Shebaa Farms conflict|2006 Lebanon War}}
[[File:Israel outpost.JPG|thumb|An [[Israeli Army]] outpost, in 2007, as seen from the Lebanese side of the border]]
Upon Israel's withdrawal, there was increasing fear among the Christian people of the South that Hezbollah would seek vengeance against those thought to have supported Israel.  Hezbollah met with Christian clerics to reassure them that the Israeli withdrawal was a victory for Lebanon as a nation, not just one sect or militia.&lt;ref name=&quot;norton2000&quot;/&gt;

The tentative peace, resulting from the withdrawal, did not last.

On October 7, 2000 [[2000 Hezbollah cross-border raid|Hezbollah attacked Israel]]. In a cross-border raid, three Israeli soldiers who were patrolling the Lebanese border were attacked and abducted. Their bodies were returned to Israel in a 2004 prisoner exchange. During this exchange, it was also agreed that the price for the release of Lebanon's longest-held prisoner [[Samir Kuntar]] would be solid information on the fate of captured Israeli pilot [[Ron Arad (pilot)|Ron Arad]]. As Hezbollah failed to unearth any solid evidence as to Arad's fate, Kuntar remained incarcerated for his crimes.

In July 2006, in response to Israel's failure to release the [[Lebanese prisoners in Israel]], Hezbollah kidnapped two Israeli soldiers and killed eight others. In retaliation Israel began [[2006 Lebanon War|the 2006 Lebanon War]] to rescue the abducted soldiers and destroy Hezbollah.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Hall, ''[http://www.ucis.pitt.edu/ceris/docs/Symp06_HallPaper.pdf  American Myopia]: American Policy on Hizbollah''. The Muslim World: Questions of Policy and Politics. Cornell University undergraduate research symposium. April 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;NPR&quot;&gt;''&quot;...Hezbollah enjoys enormous popularity in Lebanon, especially in southern Lebanon...&quot;'', [[Ted Koppel]] on [[NPR]] report: ''[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5555771  Lebanon's Hezbollah Ties]''. [[All Things Considered]], July 13, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;BBC 05-26&quot;&gt;[[BBC]]: [http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/may/26/newsid_2496000/2496423.stm  On This Day, May 26th].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;CNN-2000-05-24&quot;&gt;[[CNN]] report: ''[http://archives.cnn.com/2000/WORLD/meast/05/24/israel.lebanon.02/index.html  Hezbollah flag raised as Israeli troops withdraw from southern Lebanon]''. May 24, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Lebanese Civil War]]
* [[1978 South Lebanon conflict]]
* [[Syrian occupation of Lebanon]]
* [[Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution]]
* [[2000-2006 Shebaa Farms conflict]]
* [[2006 Lebanon War]]
* [[2008 conflict in Lebanon]]
* [[List of modern conflicts in the Middle East]]
* [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 425]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Arab–Israeli conflict}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:South Lebanon Conflict (1982–2000)}}
[[Category:South Lebanon conflict (1982–2000)]]
[[Category:History of Lebanon]]

[[ar:الصراع في جنوب لبنان (1982-2000)]]
[[cs:Jiholibanonský konflikt]]
[[hr:Južnolibanonski sukob 1982.-2000.]]
[[it:Conflitto del Libano meridionale (1982-2000)]]
[[he:הלחימה בדרום לבנון (1982 - 2000)]]
[[no:Konflikten i Sør-Libanon 1982–2000]]
[[pt:Conflito no sul do Líbano (1982–2000)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
