<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="606113" ns="0" title="CHNU-DT"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = CHNU-DT|
  city                     = [[Fraser Valley Regional District|Fraser Valley]], [[British Columbia]]|
  station_logo             = [[Image:Joytv10.svg|220px]]|
  station_slogan           = It's all good|
  station_branding         = Joytv 10|
  analog                   = |
  digital                  = 47 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]]) &lt;br&gt; [[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 66.1 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]]) |
  other_chs                = 21 CHNU-DT-1 ([[Victoria, British Columbia|Victoria]])&lt;br&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 21.1|
  affiliations             = [[Joytv]]|
  network                  = |
  airdate                  = September 15, 2001|
  location                 = [[British Columbia|Southwest British Columbia]]|
  callsign_meaning         = CH '''N'''OWTV '''U'''HF|
  former_callsigns         = CHNU-TV (2001-2011)|
  former_channel_numbers   = '''Analog:'''&lt;br&gt; 66 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]], 2001-2011) |
  owner                    = [[ZoomerMedia]]|
  licensee                 = Christian Channel Inc.|
  sister_stations          = |
  former_affiliations      = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (2001-2005)&lt;br&gt;[[Omni Television|Omni]] (2005-2007)&lt;br&gt;Independent (2007-2008)|
  effective_radiated_power = '''CHNU-DT:''' 21.4 [[watt|kilowatts]]&lt;br&gt;'''CHNU-TV-1:''' 3.5 kilowatts|
  HAAT                     = '''CHNU-DT:''' 335 metres&lt;br&gt;'''CHNU-DT-1:''' 99.6 metres|
  coordinates              = '''CHNU-DT:'''&lt;br&gt;{{coord|49|3|48|N|122|12|53|W|type:landmark}}&lt;br&gt;'''CHNU-DT-1:'''&lt;br&gt;{{coord|48|25|30|N|123|20|13|W|type:landmark|name=CHNU-DT-1}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.joytv10.ca/home.php Joytv 10]|
}}
'''CHNU-DT''' (known on air as '''Joytv 10''') is an [[English language]] [[television station]] based in [[Surrey, British Columbia]], [[Canada]]. The station is licensed to the [[Fraser Valley Regional District|Fraser Valley]] Region, and also serves [[Metro Vancouver]], [[Victoria, British Columbia|Victoria]] and surrounding areas. CHNU is owned by [[ZoomerMedia]], and is an [[owned and operated]] station of the [[Joytv]] [[television system]]. CHNU broadcasts a variety of multi-faith and family-oriented programming.

CHNU broadcasts on UHF channel 66, and is seen on cable channel 10 in the [[Lower Mainland]], cable 7 in [[Victoria, British Columbia|Victoria]].  The station is not carried on cable outside those areas.

==History==
[[File:NOWTVCurrentLogo.png|thumb|left|The original logo used by CHNU, [[NOWTV]], was used from the station's launch in 2001 until 2005. A television set replaced the &quot;O&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hinto.tripod.com/newswatch/yvr-tv/station.html tv vancouver: station overview]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
CHNU-TV was licensed in July 2000 by the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]] (CRTC) to Trinity Television Inc. Trinity Television initially requested the callsign be &quot;CFVT&quot; (with &quot;FVT&quot; standing for &quot;Fraser Valley Television&quot;); however, this was denied by [[Industry Canada]]. The station went on air on September 15, 2001 using the CHNU callsign instead. In any case, the call letters had not featured prominently in the station's on-air branding, as the station opted to use the on-air brand &quot;[[NOWTV]]&quot;. CHNU relied on television advertisements and donations from viewers for financial support.

On November 1, 2004, Trinity Television announced that it was selling CHNU and the licence for yet to be launched similar television station in [[Winnipeg]], [[CIIT-TV]], to [[Rogers Communications]], subject to CRTC approval. The financial difficulties Trinity experienced with operating CHNU and getting CIIT on the air, combined with the fact that it could not raise capital from outside investors because of its status as a charitable organization, were the main reasons given for the sale. The deal was approved several months later, finally giving Rogers a broadcast television station in the Vancouver market, where it had lost bids to launch one in the past. At the same time, Rogers got approval to place a [[Broadcast relay station|rebroadcaster]] in Victoria on channel 21 with an [[effective radiated power]] of 720 [[watt]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2005/db2005-207.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2005-207]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the transmitter's power was [http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2006/db2006-42.htm increased] to 17.2 [[kilowatt]]s, with the tower height decreasing to compensate.
[[File:OMNI.10.png|thumb|175px|right|After CHNU was bought by Rogers, the NOWTV branding was dropped in favour of Roger's Omni Television brand. This logo was used from 2005 until 2007.]]
After acquiring the station from Trinity Television, Rogers announced in late June 2005 that the station would join the Rogers-owned [[Omni Television]] system. The Omni brand had previously been associated only with multicultural stations. The renaming occurred in September of that year, making CHNU the third station in the Omni television system. 

On September 28, 2007, Rogers' purchase of the [[Citytv]] stations formerly owned by [[CHUM Limited]] was approved (although [[CTVgm]] sold off the stations a year earlier). As a condition of this approval, Rogers had to sell CHNU and CIIT in Winnipeg due to the CRTC's restrictions on owning multiple television stations broadcasting in the same language in a single market. Rogers had a one-year grace period to find a buyer.
[[Image:CHNU10 logo.svg|200px|thumb|left|CHNU's third logo, used from 2007-2008.]]
Rogers subsequently announced plans to purchase Vancouver multilingual station CHNM-TV, which the company argues would not violate any ownership restrictions under the CRTC's exemptions for stations broadcasting in different languages. On October 31, 2007, CHNU was rebranded '''CHNU 10''' in order to limit viewer confusion because Rogers' contemporaneous acquisition of the multilingual [[CHNM-TV]] in Vancouver meant that the Omni Television brand would be transferred to that station in 2008.

On November 6, 2007, Rogers announced that CHNU and CIIT would be sold to [[S-VOX]], with no financial deals being released. The deal was approved by the CRTC on March 31, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2008/db2008-71.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2008-71]&lt;/ref&gt; The sale was finalized on April 30, 2008 and S-VOX assumed control of the station on May 26 of that year.

S-VOX soon announced that both CHNU and CIIT would rebrand as under a newly created television brand, '''Joytv'''. CHNU rebranded on September 1, 2008 using the on-air brand '''Joytv 10'''.

In June 2009, S-VOX announced it would sell its broadcasting assets, including CHNU, to [[ZoomerMedia]], a company controlled by [[Moses Znaimer]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newswire.ca/en/releases/archive/June2009/15/c6600.html VisionTV Board agrees to ZoomerMedia purchase of television properties], VisionTV press release, June 15, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The sale was approved by the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission|CRTC]] On March 30, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2010/2010-193.htm&lt;/ref&gt; ZoomerMedia assumed control of S-VOX's broadcasting assets on June 30, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marketwatch.com/story/zoomermedia-limited-completes-acquisitions-and-financing-2010-06-30?reflink=MW_news_stmp ZoomerMedia Limited Completes Acquisitions and Financing]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programming==
The station airs a very diverse selection of programming, ranging from [[sitcom]]s (such as ''[[Reba (TV series)|Reba]]'', or ''[[My Name Is Earl]]''), [[drama]]s (such as ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'') to classic programs (such as ''[[Matlock]]'' or ''[[Ironside (TV series)|Ironside]]''.  The majority of the station's non-religious programming are syndicated. The station also airs a great deal of multicultural [[religious broadcasting|religious programming]] as well, particularly about [[Christianity]], [[Islam]], [[Hinduism]] and [[Sikhism]].

CHNU also broadcast two American primetime programs, ''[[20/20 (US television series)|20/20]]'' and ''[[48 Hours (TV series)|48 Hours Mystery]]''.

===Local productions===
====''The Standard''====
''The Standard'' was a news and current affairs program launched by CHNU in September of 2005. The show focused on national and international issues, but from a religious and spiritual standpoint.  Canceled for the final time in August 2010, re-runs of ''The Standard'' continue to be seen on CHNU, CIIT and Vision TV, and formerly weekly on [[CFMT-TV|CFMT]] and [[The Biography Channel Canada]].  

The final host of the series was CBS' &quot;60 Minutes&quot; producer Peter Klein. Before him they were done by Randall Mark, Andrew Dawson, Rafe Mair, Mark Schneider, Russ Froese, and Salimah Ebrahim. The field interviewer position was held by Shannon Nelson, and previously Laura-Lynn Tyler.

Following an initial three-year run that included feature interviews with the likes of Zimbabwe President [[Robert Mugabe]], Canadian Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]], author [[Salman Rushdie]], Nobel Peace Prize winner Dr. [[Shirin Ebadi]], and HRH [[Prince Edward, Earl of Wessex|Prince Edward]], the program was replaced in June 2008 with ''The Daily'' when S-VOX took over ownership of the station from Rogers. The last broadcast was June 6, 2008.  It relaunched in September 2009 as a weekly program hosted by Klein.  

The program was co-created in 2005 by producer Jonathan Roth and station general manager Terry Mahoney.  Roth remained as senior producer throughout &quot;The Standard's&quot; run.

====''The Daily''====
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
''The Daily'' is a talk show hosted by [[Mark Washington (Canadian football)|Mark Washington]] and Laura-Lynn Thompson. The show's first broadcast was on June 9, 2008. The Daily is also broadcast nationally on [[VisionTV]]. The Daily was shot using Shaw facilities in [[Downtown Vancouver]]. The show ceased production on April 15, 2009.

==Digital television and high definition==

{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse&quot;
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''Broadcasting in Digital'''
| Yes
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''Programs in HD'''
| No
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''PSIP functioning properly'''
| No
|}


CHNU was approved by the CRTC to broadcast in digital on channel 47 with a stronger transmitter from Abbotsford that would cover most of the Lower Mainland, doubling the population served compared to its analog transmitter. The station did not broadcast in digital until August 31, 2011 as channel 47 was occupied by [[CKVU-TV|CKVU-DT]].  The station was approved to broadcast in digital on channel 21 in Victoria, also with a greater coverage area. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2010/2010-842.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2010-842]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the station is based out of Surrey, BC, the transmitter tower is in Abbotsford, BC and analog broadcasts were at an insufficient power level to be viewed in many Greater Vancouver municipalities, including Vancouver, BC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2007/db2007-102.pdf Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2007-102]&lt;/ref&gt;  According to the station's website, the target station's audience is the Fraser Valley, Vancouver, and Victoria.

==See also==
*[[2007 Canada broadcast TV realignment]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.joytv10.ca/home.php Joytv 10]
*[http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php?id=52&amp;historyID=5 Canadian Communications Foundation - CHNU-TV History]
*{{RecnetCanada|CHNU-TV}}
*{{TV Fool|CHNU}}

{{British Columbia TV}}
{{ZoomerMedia}}
{{Religious television channels in Canada}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:CHNU-TV}}
[[Category:Surrey, British Columbia]]
[[Category:Christian television stations in Canada]]
[[Category:Channel 66 TV stations in Canada]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 2001]]
[[Category:Television stations in Vancouver|HNU]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
