<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6079658" ns="0" title="Arts in Australia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Use Australian English|date=May 2011}}
{{Auculture}}
The '''Arts in Australia''' refers to the art produced in the area of, on the subject of, or by the people of the [[Commonwealth of Australia]] and its preceding [[Indigenous Australian|Indigenous]] and colonial societies. [[Indigenous Australian art]], [[Indigenous Australian music|music]] and story telling attaches to a 40-60,000 year heritage and continues to affect the broader arts and [[culture of Australia]]. During its early [[Western civilisation|western]] history, Australia was a collection of British colonies, therefore, its [[Australian literature|literary]], [[Visual arts of Australia|visual]] and [[Theatre of Australia|theatrical]] traditions began with strong links to the broader traditions of [[English literature|English]] and [[Irish literature]], [[Art of the United Kingdom|British art]] and [[British music|English]] and [[Celtic music]]. However, the works of Australian artists - including Indigenous as well as [[Anglo-Celtic]] and [[multicultural]] migrant Australians - has, since 1788, introduced the character of a new continent to the global arts scene - exploring such themes as [[Aboriginal Australians|Aboriginality]], Australian landscape, migrant and national identity, distance from other Western nations and proximity to Asia, the complexities of urban living and the &quot;beauty and the terror&quot; of life in the [[Australian bush]].

Notable Australian writers have included the Nobel laureate [[Patrick White]], the novelist [[Colleen McCullough]] and the bush poets [[Henry Lawson]] and [[Banjo Paterson]]. Leading Australian performing artists have included [[Robert Helpmann]] of the [[Australian Ballet]], [[Joan Sutherland]] of [[Opera Australia]] and the humourist [[Barry Humphries]]. Prominent Australian musical artists have included the [[Australian country music]] singer [[Slim Dusty]], rising star [[Cody Simpson]], folk-rocker [[Paul Kelly (musician)|Paul Kelly]], &quot;pop princess&quot; [[Kylie Minogue]] and [[rock n roll]] bands the [[Bee Gees]], [[AC/DC]], [[INXS]] and [[Powderfinger]] . Qintessentially Australian art styles include the [[Heidelberg School]] the [[Hermannsburg School]] and the [[Western Desert Art Movement]]. [[Australian cinema]] has a long tradition with a body of work producing popular classics such as ''[[Crocodile Dundee]]'' and ''[[The Man from Snowy River (1982 film)|The Man From Snowy River]]'', and [[arthouse]] successes such as ''[[Picnic at Hanging Rock]]'' and ''[[Ten Canoes]]''. Prominent Australian trained filmed artists include [[Errol Flynn]], [[Mel Gibson]], [[Nicole Kidman]], [[Russel Crowe]] and [[Cate Blanchett]].

Notable institutions for the arts include the [[UNESCO]] listed [[Sydney Opera House]], the [[National Gallery of Victoria]], the  [[National Gallery of Australia]] in [[Canberra]] and the [[National Institute of Dramatic Art]] in Sydney.

==Overview==
[[File:Banjo Patterson.jpg|thumb|left|140px|The [[bush ballad]]eer [[Banjo Paterson]] wrote ''[[Waltzing Matilda]]'' in 1895.]]
[[File:Sydney Opera House - Dec 2008.jpg|thumb|350px|[[Sydney Opera House]].]]

The arts in Australia — [[cinema of Australia|film]], [[music of Australia|music]], [[art of Australia|painting]], [[theatre of Australia|theatre]], [[dance in Australia|dance]] and crafts — have achieved international recognition. While much of Australia's cultural output has traditionally tended to fit with general trends and styles in Western arts, the arts as practiced by [[indigenous Australians]] represent a unique Australian cultural tradition, and Australia's landscape and history have contributed to some unique variations in the styles inherited by Australia's various migrant communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;painters&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |url=http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/painters/
 |title=Australian painters
 |work=Australian Culture and Recreation Portal
 |publisher=Australia Government
 |accessdate=16 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/film/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dfat.gov.au/aib/arts_culture.html&lt;/ref&gt;

At the close of the 19th century, the painters of the [[Heidelberg School]] began to capture the unique colours of the [[Australian bush]], famed writers [[Henry Lawson]] and [[Banjo Paterson]] presented conflicting views of the harshness and romance of life in Australia, and performing artists like Dame [[Nellie Melba]] succeeded internationally in the traditional European arts. During the 20th century, writers and performers like [[C J Dennis]], [[Barry Humphries]] and [[Paul Hogan]] both mocked and celebrated Australian cultural stereotypes, while shifting demographics saw a diversification of artistic output, with writers like feminist [[Germaine Greer]] challenging traditional cultural norms.

Australia's capital cities each support traditional  &quot;[[high culture]]&quot; institutions in the form of major art galleries, ballet troupes, theaters, symphony orchestras, opera houses and dance companies. Leading Australian performers in these fields have included the opera Dames [[Nellie Melba]] and [[Joan Sutherland]], dancers [[Edouard Borovansky]] and [[Robert Helpmann|Sir Robert Helpmann]], and choreographer/dancers such as [[Graeme Murphy]] and [[Meryl Tankard]]. [[Opera Australia]] is based in Sydney at the world renowned [[Sydney Opera House]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/music/opera/&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Australian Ballet]], [[Melbourne Symphony Orchestra|Melbourne]] and [[Sydney Symphony Orchestra|Sydney]] symphony orchestras are also well regarded cultural institutions.

Organisations such as the [[Sydney Theatre Company]] and [[National Institute of Dramatic Art]] have fostered students of theatre, film, and television several of whom have continued to international success, with actors like [[Cate Blanchett]] and [[Geoffrey Rush]] having been associated with both institutions.

Independent culture thrives in all capital cities and exists in most large regional towns. The independent arts of [[music of Australia|music]], [[cinema of Australia|film]], [[art of Australia|art]] and [[street art]] are the most extensive. [[Melbourne]]'s independent music scene, is one of the largest in the world, whilst another can be found in the multitude of international street artists visiting Melbourne and, to a lesser extent, other major cities, to work for a period of time.

==Visual arts==
===Art – painting and sculpture ===
[[File:Roberts-The Australian native.jpg|thumb|left|200px|&quot;The Australian Native&quot;, by [[Tom Roberts]], 1888.]]
[[Image:Sculpture by the Sea 01.JPG|right|thumb|250px|The large crowd at the 2006 [[Bondi Beach]] [[Sculpture by the Sea]].]]
{{Main|Visual arts of Australia}}
{{See also|Indigenous Australian art}}

The visual arts have a long history in Australia and examples of ancient Aboriginal rock artworks can be found throughout the continent - notably in national parks such as those of the [[UNESCO]] listed sites at [[Uluru]] and [[Kakadu National Park]] in the Northern Territory, but also within protected parks in urban areas such as at [[Ku-ring-gai Chase National Park]] in Sydney.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.environment.gov.au/parks/kakadu/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.environment.gov.au/parks/uluru/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.auinfo.com/Ku_Ring_Gai_National_park_Sydney.html&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 1970s, indigenous artists have used acrylic paints - with styles such as that of the [[Western Desert Art Movement]] becoming a globally known 20th century art movement.

Following the arrival of permanent European settlement in Australia in 1788, the story of early Australian painting has been described{{By whom|date=September 2010}} as requiring of artists a shift from a &quot;European sense of light&quot; to an &quot;Australian sense of light&quot;. The origins of distinctly Australian painting is often associated with the [[Heidelberg School]] of the 1880s-1890s. Artists such as [[Arthur Streeton]], [[Frederick McCubbin]] and [[Tom Roberts]] applied themselves to recreating in their art a truer sense of light and colour as seen in Australian landscape. Like the European Impressionists, they painted in the open air. These artists found inspiration in the unique light and colour which characterises the [[Australian bush]].

Among the first Australians artists to gain a reputation overseas was the impressionist [[John Peter Russell]] during the 1880s. Another notable expatriate artist of the era was [[Rupert Bunny]], a painter of landscape, allegory and sensual and intimate portraits. [[Ernst William Christmas]] also made a name internationally.

Among the principle Australian artists of the 20th century are the [[surrealist]]s [[Sidney Nolan]], [[Arthur Boyd]] and [[Russell Drysdale]], the [[avant-garde]] [[Brett Whiteley]], the painter/sculptors [[William Dobell]] and [[Norman Lindsay]], the landscapists [[Albert Namatjira]] and [[Lloyd Rees]], the [[modernist]] photographer [[Max Dupain]], and the Aboriginal artist [[Emily Kame Kngwarreye]]. Each has helped to define the unique character of the visual arts in Australia.&lt;ref name=&quot;painters&quot;/&gt;

Modernism arrived in Australia early in the 20th century. Among the earliest exponents were [[Grace Cossington Smith]] and [[Margaret Preston]]. Humorist [[Barry Humphries]] has been a provocative exponent of [[dadaism]] in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Hughes; ''The Art of Australia''; Penguin; Revised Edition 1970&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Leunig]] has been an Australian artist who has developed renowned style of poetic cartoons.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.leunig.com.au/&lt;/ref&gt;

Popular with the general community have been [[Ken Done]] best known for his design work, [[Pro Hart]] and [[Rolf Harris]], a [[United Kingdom|British]]/[[Australian]] living in the UK is popular as a musician, composer, painter and television host. In the wealthy suburbs of the capital cities there are many more artists that while not household names, show diversity and sophistication. [[Ricky Swallow]], [[Patricia Piccinini]], [[Susan Norrie]], [[Callum Morton]], [[Rover Thomas]] and [[Emily Kame Kngwarreye]] have all represented Australians at the [[Venice Biennale]] using the traditional mediums of sculpture, photography and painting while instilling them with a renewed vigour. Under what may be termed  'post-aboriginal art' also comes a new generation of Aboriginal artists who don't require or desire to be boxed outside the mainstream of the arts community. These artists, while not rejecting the culture of the past, endeavour to move the artistic dialog forward. [[Gordon Bennett (artist)|Gordon Bennett]], [[Rosella Namok]], [[Richard Bell]] and [[Julie Dowling]] to name a few, are pioneers in this regard.

In recent years the art market has been democratised and art is judged on its merits rather than snobbery. A cohort of male artists aged under fifty ([[Dane Lovett]], [[Adam Cullen]], [[Ben Quilty]], [[Anthony Bennett (Australian artist)|Anthony Bennett]] , [[Simon Cuthbert]], [[Rhys Lee]], [[Ben Frost (artist)|Ben Frost]] and [[Alasdair McIntyre]]) have an expressive style and use humour in their work.

In addition [[street art]] is also a prominent feature in major cities such as [[Melbourne]] and [[Sydney]]. Though there is some debate over the legality, some councils have expressed greater recognition of the urban art movement.

Australia has a number of notable museums and galleries, including the [[National Gallery of Victoria]] in [[Melbourne]], the [[National Gallery of Australia]], [[National Portrait Gallery (Australia)|National Portrait Gallery of Australia]] and  [[National Museum of Australia]] in Canberra, and the [[Art Gallery of New South Wales]] in Sydney.

&lt;gallery&gt;

File:Aboriginal Art Australia.jpg|Aboriginal Rock Art, Ubirr Art Site, [[Kakadu National Park]]
File:A holiday at Mentone.jpg|''[[A holiday at Mentone]]'' 1888 by [[Charles Conder]] of the [[Heidelberg School]] 
File:Down on his luck.jpg|''[[Down on His Luck]]'' 1889 by [[Frederick McCubbin]] of the [[Heidelberg School]]
File:Sunbaker maxdupain nga76.54.jpg|''[[Sunbaker]]'' (1937) an iconic photograph by [[Max Dupain]]
|''[[The cricketers]]'' (1948) by [[Russell Drysdale]]
|''[[Collins St., 5 pm]]'' (1955) by [[John Brack]]

&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Cinema===
{{Main|Cinema of Australia}}
[[File:Errol Flynn1.jpg|thumb|130px|left|[[Errol Flynn]] c. 1940.]]

Australia has a long history of film production. Australia's first dedicated film studio, the [[Limelight Department]], was created by The [[Salvation Army]] in Melbourne in 1898, and is believed to have been the world's first.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.salvationarmy.org.au/SALV/STANDARD/PC_60860.html&lt;/ref&gt; The world's first feature-length film was the Australian production ''[[The Story of the Kelly Gang]]'' of 1906.&lt;ref&gt;http://aso.gov.au/titles/features/story-kelly-gang&lt;/ref&gt; After such early successes, Australian cinema suffered from the rise of [[Hollywood]].

[[File:Nicole kidman3cropped.jpg|thumb|130px|[[Nicole Kidman]],  star of ''[[Dead Calm (film)|Dead Calm]]''.]]
[[File:GeoffreyRush08TIFF.jpg|thumb|130px|[[Geoffrey Rush]], star of ''[[Shine (film)|Shine]]''.]]

In 1933, ''[[In the Wake of the Bounty]]'' was directed by [[Charles Chauvel (film maker)|Charles Chauvel]], who cast Tasmanian born [[Erroll Flynn]] as the leading actor.&lt;ref&gt;http://aso.gov.au/titles/features/wake-bounty/&lt;/ref&gt; Flynn went on to a celebrated career in Hollywood. Chauvel directed a number of successful Australian films, the last being 1955's ''[[Jedda]]'', which was notable for being the first Australian film to be shot in colour, and the first to feature Aboriginal actors in lead roles and to be entered at the Cannes Film Festival.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.festival-cannes.com/en/archives/ficheFilm/id/3702/year/1955.html&lt;/ref&gt; It was not until 2006 and [[Rolf De Heer]]'s ''[[Ten Canoes]]'' that a major feature length drama was shot in an indigenous language.

The first Australian Oscar was won by 1942's ''[[Kokoda Front Line!]]'', directed by [[Ken G. Hall]].&lt;ref&gt;http://aso.gov.au/titles/newsreels/kokoda-front-line/&lt;/ref&gt;

During the late 1960s and 1970s an influx of government funding saw the development of a new generation of film makers telling distinctively Australian stories, including directors [[Peter Weir]], [[George Miller (filmmaker)|George Miller]] and [[Bruce Beresford]]. Films such as ''[[Picnic at Hanging Rock]]'' and ''[[Sunday Too Far Away]]'' had an immediate international impact. The 1980s is often regarded{{By whom|date=October 2010}} as a golden age of Australian cinema, with many successful films, from the historical drama of [[Gallipoli (1981 film)|''Gallipoli'']], to the dark science fiction of ''[[Mad Max]]'', the romantic adventure of ''[[The Man from Snowy River (1982 film)|The Man From Snowy River]]'' or the comedy of ''[[Crocodile Dundee]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://wwwmcc.murdoch.edu.au/ReadingRoom/film/Croc.html&lt;/ref&gt;

A major theme of Australian cinema has been survival in the harsh Australian landscape. A number of thrillers and horror films dubbed &quot;outback gothic&quot; have been created, including ''[[Wake in Fright]]'', ''[[Walkabout (film)|Walkabout]]'', ''[[The Cars That Ate Paris]]'' and ''[[Picnic at Hanging Rock (film)|Picnic at Hanging Rock]]'' in the 1970s, ''[[Razorback (film)|Razorback]]'' and ''[[Shame (1988 film)|Shame]]'' in the 1980s, and ''[[Japanese Story]]'', ''[[The Proposition]]'' and the world-renowned ''[[Wolf Creek (film)|Wolf Creek]]'' in the 21st century. These films depict the Australian bush and its creatures as deadly, and its people as outcasts and psychopaths. These are combined with futuristic post-apocalyptic themes in the [[Mad Max (franchise)|Mad Max series]].

The 1990s saw a run of successful comedies such as ''[[Muriel's Wedding]]'', ''[[The Castle (film)|The Castle]]'' and ''[[Strictly Ballroom]]'', which helped launch the careers of [[Toni Collette]], [[P. J. Hogan]], [[Eric Bana]] and [[Baz Luhrmann]]. This group was joined in Hollywood by actors including [[Russel Crowe]], [[Cate Blanchett]] and [[Heath Ledger]] who also rose to international prominence.

The domestic film industry continues to produce a reasonable{{Quantify|date=October 2010}} number of films each year. The industry is also supported by US producers who produce in Australia following the decision by Fox head [[Rupert Murdoch]] to utilise new studios in Melbourne and Sydney where filming could be completed well below US costs. Notable productions include ''[[The Matrix]]'', ''[[Star Wars]]'' episodes [[Star Wars Episode II: Attack of the Clones|II]] and [[Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith|III]], and ''[[Australia (2008 film)|Australia]]'' starring [[Nicole Kidman]] and [[Hugh Jackman]].

==Literature==
{{main| Australian literature}}
[[File:Henry Lawson photograph 1902.jpg|thumb|130px|left|[[Henry Lawson]].]]

Australian writers who have obtained international renown include the [[Nobel Prize for Literature|Nobel winning]] author [[Patrick White]], as well as authors [[Peter Carey (novelist)|Peter Carey]], [[Thomas Keneally]], [[Colleen McCullough]], [[Nevil Shute]] and [[Morris West]]. Notable contemporary expatriate authors include the feminist [[Germaine Greer]], art historian [[Robert Hughes (critic)|Robert Hughes]] and humorists [[Barry Humphries]] and [[Clive James]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/literature/&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dorothea Mackellar.jpg|thumb|130px|[[Dorothea McKellar]].]]
[[File:The Magic Pudding.jpg|thumb|130px|[[The Magic Pudding]] by [[Norman Lindsay]].]]

Among the important authors of classic Australian works are the poets [[Henry Lawson]], [[Banjo Paterson]], [[C J Dennis]] and [[Dorothea McKellar]]. Dennis wrote in the Australian vernacular, while McKellar wrote the iconic patriotic poem'' [[My Country]]''. At one point, Lawson and Paterson contributed a series of verses to ''[[The Bulletin]]'' magazine in which they engaged in a literary debate about the nature of life in Australia. Lawson said Paterson was a romantic and Paterson said Lawson was full of doom and gloom.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/lawson/&lt;/ref&gt; Lawson is widely regarded as one of Australia's greatest writers of short stories, while Paterson's poems  [[The Man from Snowy River (poem)|The Man From Snowy River]] and [[Clancy of the Overflow]] remain amongst the most popular Australian bush poems. Significant political poets of the 20th century included Dame [[Mary Gilmore]] and [[Judith Wright]]. Among the best known contemporary poets are [[Les Murray (poet)|Les Murray]] and [[Bruce Dawe]].

Novelists of classic Australian works include [[Marcus Clarke]] (''[[For the Term of His Natural Life]]''), [[Miles Franklin]] (''[[My Brilliant Career]]'') and [[Ruth Park]] (''[[The Harp in the South]]''). In terms of children's literature,  [[Norman Lindsay]] (''[[The Magic Pudding]]'') and [[May Gibbs]] (''[[Snugglepot and Cuddlepie]]'') are among the Australian classics, while eminent Australian playwrights have included [[Steele Rudd]], [[David Williamson]], [[Alan Seymour]] and [[Nick Enright]].

Although historically only a small proportion of Australia's population have lived outside the major cities, many of Australia's most distinctive stories and legends originate in the [[outback]], in the [[Drover (Australian)|drover]]s and squatters and people of the barren, dusty plains.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seal 1989 50&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Seal|first=Graham|title=The Hidden Culture: Folklore in Australian Society|page=50|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1989|location=Melbourne|isbn=0195549198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Contemporary works dealing with the migrant experience include [[Melina Marchetta]]'s ''[[Looking for Alibrandi]]'' and [[Anh Do]]'s memoir ''[[The Happiest Refugee]]'', which won the Indie Book of the Year Award for 2011 and tells the story of the his  experience as a Vietnamese refugee travelling to and growing up in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2011/03/15/3164087.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

[[David Unaipon]] is known as the first indigenous author. [[Oodgeroo Noonuccal]] was the first [[Australian Aborigine|Aboriginal Australian]] to publish a book of verse.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Oodgeroo Noonuccal.&quot; Encyclopedia of World Biography Supplement, Vol. 27. Gale, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A significant contemporary account of the experiences of Indigenous Australia can be found in [[Sally Morgan (artist)|Sally Morgan]]'s ''[[My Place (book)|My Place]]''. 

[[Charles Bean]] (''The Story of Anzac: From the Outbreak of War to the End of the First Phase of the Gallipoli Campaign May 4, 191''5, 1921) [[Geoffrey Blainey]] (''The Tyranny of Distance'', 1966), [[Robert Hughes (critic)|Robert Hughes]] (''[[The Fatal Shore]]'', 1987), [[Manning Clark]] ''(A History of Australia'', 1962–87), and [[Marcia Langton]] (''First Australians'', 2008) are authors of important Australian histories.

==Performing arts==
{{Main|Performing arts in Australia}}

===Dance===
{{Main|Dance in Australia}}

[[File:1981 event Australian aboriginals.jpg|thumb|[[Australian Aboriginal]] dancers in 1981.]]
[[File:Robert Helpmann.jpg|thumb|150px|Sir [[Robert Helpmann]].]]

Traditional [[Indigenous Australian]] dance was closely associated with song and was understood and experienced as making present the reality of the [[Dreamtime (mythology)|Dreamtime]]. In some instances, they would imitate the actions of a particular animal in the process of telling a story. For the people in their own country it defined to roles, responsibilities and the place itself. These ritual performances gave them an understanding of themselves in the interplay of social, geographical and environmental forces. The performances were associated with specific places and dance grounds were often sacred places. Body decoration and specific gestures related to kin and other relationships (such as to Dreamtime beings with which individuals and groups). For a number of Indigenous Australian groups their dances were secret and or sacred, gender could also be an important factor in some ceremonies with men and women having separate ceremonial traditions.&lt;ref&gt;Dance in ''[[Encyclopaedia of Aboriginal Australia]], Volume 1'' pp. 255-7&lt;/ref&gt;

The term [[Corroboree]] is commonly used in general Australian culture to refer to Australian Aboriginal dances, however this term has its origins among the people of the Sydney region. In a number of places Australian Aboriginal people will perform &quot;corroborees&quot; for tourists.

In the latter part of the 20th century the influence of Indigenous Australian dance traditions has been seen with the development of concert dance, particularly in contemporary dance with the [[National Aboriginal Islander Skills Development Association]] providing training to Indigenous Australians in dance and the Bangarra Dance Theatre. 

[[Bush dance]] has developed in Australia as a form of traditional dance, drawing from English, Irish, Scottish and other European dance. Favourite dances in the community include such as the Irish [[Céilidh]] &quot;Pride of Erin&quot; and the [[quadrille]] &quot;The Lancers&quot;. Locally originated dances include the &quot;Waves of Bondi&quot;, the [[Melbourne Shuffle]] and [[New Vogue (dance)|New Vogue]]. 

[[The Australian Ballet]] is the foremost [[classical ballet]] company in Australia.  It was founded by the English ballerina Dame [[Peggy van Praagh]] in 1962 and is today recognised as one of the world's major international ballet companies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.australianballet.com.au/about_us/history&lt;/ref&gt; It is based in Melbourne and performs works from the classical repertoire as well as contemporary works by major Australian and international choreographers. As of 2010, it was presenting approximately 200 performances in cities and regional areas around Australia each year as well as international tours. Regular venues include: the [[Melbourne Arts Centre]], [[Sydney Opera House]], [[Sydney Theatre]], [[Adelaide Festival Centre]]
and [[Queensland Performing Arts Centre]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.australianballet.com.au/about_us&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Helpmann]] is among Australia's best known ballerinos.

Many immigrant communities continue their own dance traditions on a professional or amateur basis. Traditional dances from a large number of ethnic backgrounds are danced in Australia, helped by the presence of enthusiastic immigrants and their Australian-born families. It is quite common to see dances from the Baltic region, as well as Scottish, Irish, Indian, Indonesian or African dance being taught at community centres and dance schools in Australia.

[[Baz Lurhmann]]'s popular 1992 film [[Strictly Ballroom]], starring [[Paul Mercurio]] contributed to an increased interest in dance competition in Australia, and a number of popular dance shows including [[So You Think You Can Dance (U.S. TV series)|So You Think You Can Dance]] have featured on television in recent years.

===Music===
====Indigenous music====
[[File:Gurrumul.jpg|thumb|left|[[Geoffrey Gurrumul Yunupingu]] is a contemporary indigenous performer who sings in the [[Yolŋu Matha languages]].]]

{{Main|Indigenous Australian music}}

Aboriginal song was an integral part of Aboriginal culture. The most famous feature of their music is the [[didgeridoo]]. This wooden instrument, used amongst the Aboriginal tribes of northern Australia, makes a distinctive droning sound and its use has been adopted by a wide variety of non-Aboriginal performers.

Aboriginal musicians have turned their hand to Western popular musical forms, often to considerable commercial success. Pioneers included [[Lionel Rose]], and [[Jimmy Little]], while notable contemporary examples include [[Archie Roach]], the [[Warumpi Band]], [[NoKTuRNL]] and [[Yothu Yindi]]. [[Geoffrey Gurrumul Yunupingu]] (formerly of Yothu Yindi) has attained international success singing contemporary music in English and in the language of the [[Yolngu]]. [[Christine Anu]] is a successful [[Torres Strait Islander]] singer.

[[Australian country music]] has been popular among indigenous communities, with performers including [[Troy Cassar-Daley]] rising to national prominence.

Amongst young Australian aborigines, [[African American|African-American]] and Aboriginal [[hip hop]] music and clothing is popular.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | title = The New Corroboree
 | first = Tony
 | last = Mitchell
 | url = http://www.theage.com.au/news/music/the-new-corroboree/2006/03/30/1143441270792.html
 | newspaper = [[The Age]]
 | date = 1 April 2006
| location=Melbourne
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aboriginal boxing champion and former rugby league player [[Anthony Mundine]] identified US rapper [[Tupac Shakur]] as a personal inspiration, after Mundine's release of his 2007 single, ''Platinum Ryder''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/music/the-man-must-make-his-music/2007/03/25/1174761263365.html | work=The Sydney Morning Herald | title=The Man must make his music | date=26 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[The Deadlys]] are an annual celebration of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander achievement in music, sport, entertainment and community.

====Folk music and national songs====
[[File:The Old Bush Songs by Banio Paterson.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Cover to Paterson's seminal 1905 collection of bush ballads, entitled ''Old Bush Songs''.]]

The early [[Anglo-Celtic]] immigrants of the 18th and 19th centuries introduced folk ballad traditions which were adapted to Australian themes: &quot;[[Botany Bay (song)|Bound for Botany Bay]]&quot; tells of the voyage of British convicts to Sydney, &quot;[[The Wild Colonial Boy]]&quot; evokes the spirit of the [[bushranger]]s, and &quot;[[Click Go the Shears]]&quot; speaks of the life of Australian shearers. The lyrics of Australia's best known folk song, &quot;[[Waltzing Matilda]]&quot;, were written by the bush poet [[Banjo Paterson]] in 1895.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/05/05/2235263.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Adopted by Australian soldiers during [[World War I]], this song remains popular and is often sung at sporting events, including the closure of the [[Sydney Olympics]] in 2000, by [[Australian country music]] singer [[Slim Dusty]].

Other well known singers of Australian folk music include [[Rolf Harris]] (who wrote &quot;[[Tie Me Kangaroo Down Sport]]&quot;), [[John Williamson (singer)|John Williamson]], and [[Eric Bogle]] whose 1972 song &quot;[[And the Band Played Waltzing Matilda]]&quot; is a sorrowful lament to the [[Gallipoli Campaign]]. [[Bush dance]] is a traditional style of dance from Australia with strong Celtic roots, and influenced [[country music]]. It is generally accompanied by such instruments as the [[fiddle]], [[accordion]], [[concertina]] and [[percussion instruments]].&lt;ref&gt;http://home.hiwaay.net/~lkseitz/Australia/bushdance.html&lt;/ref&gt; A well known Bush band is [[The Bushwackers]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thebushwackers.com.au/&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[national anthem]] of Australia is &quot;[[Advance Australia Fair]]&quot;:

&lt;div style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;&gt;
:Australians all let us rejoice,
:For we are young and free;
:We've golden soil and wealth for toil,
:Our home is girt by sea;
:Our land abounds in Nature's gifts
:Of beauty rich and rare;
:In history's page, let every stage
:Advance Australia fair!
:In joyful strains then let us sing,
:Advance Australia fair!
&lt;/div&gt;

Unofficial pop music anthems of Australia include [[Peter Allen]]'s &quot;[[I Still Call Australia Home]]&quot; and [[Men at Work]]'s &quot;[[Down Under]]&quot;.

====Classical music====
[[File:Nellie Melba by Henry Walter Barnett.jpg|thumb|left|140px|Dame [[Nellie Melba]] (1861-1931).]]

The earliest Western musical influences in Australia can be traced back to two distinct sources: the first free settlers who brought with them the European classical music tradition, and the large body of convicts and sailors, who brought the traditional folk music of England, Ireland, Scotland and Wales.  The practicalities of building a colony mean that there is very little music extant from this early period although there are samples of music originating from [[Hobart]] and Sydney that date back to the early 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford&quot;&gt;Oxford, A Dictionary of Australian Music, Edited by Warren Bebbington, Copyright 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dame Joan Sutherland colour Allan Warren.jpg|thumb|140px|''La Stupenda'' - Dame [[Joan Sutherland]] in 1975]]

[[Nellie Melba]] (1861–1931) travelled to Europe in 1886 to commence her international career as an opera singer. She became among the best know Australians of the period and participated in early gramophone recording and radio broadcasting.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A100464b.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The establishment of choral societies (c. 1850) and symphony orchestras (c. 1890) led to increased compositional activity, although many Australian classical composers attempted to work entirely within European models. A lot of works leading up to the first part of the 20th century were heavily influenced by the folk music of other countries ([[Percy Grainger]]’s ''[[Country Gardens]]'' of 1918 being a good example of this) and a very conservative British orchestral tradition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford&quot;/&gt;

In the war and post-war eras, as pressure built to assert a national identity in the face of the looming superpower of the United States and the &quot;[[Metropole|motherland]]&quot; [[United Kingdom|Britain]], composers looked to their surroundings for inspiration. John Antill&lt;ref&gt;http://www.australianmusiccentre.com.au/artist/antill-john&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Peter Sculthorpe]] began to incorporate elements of Aboriginal music, and [[Richard Meale]] drew influence from [[south-east Asia]] (notably using the harmonic properties of the [[Balinese people|Balinese]] [[Gamelan]], as had Percy Grainger in an earlier generation).&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford&quot;/&gt;

By the beginning of the 1960s, Australian classical music erupted with influences, with composers incorporating disparate elements into their work, ranging from Aboriginal and south-east Asian music and instruments, to American [[jazz]] and [[blues]], to the belated discovery of European atonality and the [[avant-garde]]. Composers like [[Don Banks]], [[Don Kay (composer)|Don Kay]], [[Malcolm Williamson]] and [[Colin Brumby]] epitomise this period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford&quot;/&gt; In recent times composers including [[Liza Lim]], [[Carl Vine]], [[Georges Lentz]], [[Matthew Hindson]], [[Nigel Westlake]], [[Ross Edwards]], [[Graeme Koehne]], [[Elena Kats-Chernin]], [[Richard Mills]] and [[Brett Dean]] have embodied the pinnacle of established [[List of Australian composers|Australian composers]].

Well-known Australian classical performers include: sopranos [[Joan Sutherland|Dame Joan Sutherland]], Dame [[Joan Hammond]], [[Joan Carden]], [[Yvonne Kenny]], [[Sara Macliver]] and [[Emma Matthews]]; pianists [[Roger Woodward]], [[Eileen Joyce]], [[Michael Kieran Harvey]], [[Geoffrey Tozer]], [[Geoffrey Douglas Madge]], [[Leslie Howard (musician)|Leslie Howard]] and [[Ian Munro (pianist)|Ian Munro]]; guitarists [[John Williams (guitarist)|John Williams]] and [[Slava Grigoryan]]; horn player [[Barry Tuckwell]]; oboist [[Diana Doherty]]; violinists [[Richard Tognetti]] and [[Elizabeth Wallfisch]]; cellists [[John Addison (cellist)|John Addison]] and [[David Pereira]]; organist [[Christopher Wrench]]; orchestras like the [[Sydney Symphony Orchestra]], the [[Melbourne Symphony Orchestra]], the [[Australian Chamber Orchestra]] and the [[Australian Brandenburg Orchestra]]; and conductors Sir [[Bernard Heinze]], Sir [[Charles Mackerras]], [[Richard Bonynge]], [[Simone Young]] and [[Geoffrey Simon]]. Indigenous performers like [[didgeridoo]] player [[William Barton (musician)|William Barton]] and immigrant musicians like Egyptian-born [[oud]] virtuoso [[Joseph Tawadros]] have stimulated interest in their own music traditions and have also collaborated with other musicians and ensembles both in Australia and internationally.

====Pop and rock====
[[File:The Bee Gees.png|thumb|left|The [[Bee Gees]] performing in 1968.]]
[[File:Kylie Minogue Cannes.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Kylie Minogue]].]]
[[File:Powderfinger performing September 2007 (b).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Powderfinger]] performing in 2007.]]
{{Main|Australian rock}}

Australia has produced a large variety of popular music from the internationally renowned work of the [[Bee Gees]], [[AC/DC]], [[INXS]], [[Nick Cave]], [[Cody Simpson]] or [[Kylie Minogue]] to the popular local content of [[John Farnham]] or [[Paul Kelly (musician)|Paul Kelly]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/music/pop/&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the brightest stars of early Australian [[rock and roll]] was [[Johnny O'Keefe]], who formed a band in 1956; his hit ''Wild One'' made him the first Australian rock'n'roller to reach the national charts.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A150610b.htm&lt;/ref&gt; While US and British content dominated airwaves and record sales into the 1960s, local successes began to emerge – notably [[The Easybeats]] and the folk-pop group [[The Seekers]] had significant local success and some international recognition, while the bands the [[Bee Gees]] and [[AC/DC]] had their first hits in Australia before going on to international success.

The arrival of the 1961 underground movement into the mainstream in the early 1970s changed Australian music permanently. [[Skyhooks (band)|Skyhooks]] were far from the first people to write songs in Australia by Australians about Australia, but they were the first ones to make good money doing it. The two best-selling Australian albums made up to that time put Australian music on the map. Within a few years, the novelty had worn off and it became commonplace to hear distinctively Australian lyrics and sounds side-by-side with imports{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}.

During the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s Australian performers continued to do well on the local and international music scenes, for example [[Cold Chisel]], [[INXS]], [[Men at Work]] and [[Kylie Minogue]], [[Natalie Imbruglia]], [[Savage Garden]] and [[Silverchair]]. In the early 21st century, bands such as [[Jet (band)|Jet]], [[Wolfmother]], [[Eskimo Joe]], [[Grinspoon]], [[The Vines]], [[The Living End]], [[Pendulum (band)|Pendulum]], [[Delta Goodrem]] and others were enjoying success internationally. 

Domestically, [[John Farnham]] has remained one of Australia's best-known performers, with a career spanning over 40 years.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.johnfarnham.info/biography/biography.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Singer-songwriter [[Paul Kelly (musician)|Paul Kelly]] whose music style straddles folk, rock, and country has been described{{By whom|date=October 2010}} as the ''poet laureate'' of Australian music.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.civicsandcitizenship.edu.au/cce/default.asp?id=15390&lt;/ref&gt;

The national expansion of [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation|ABC]] youth radio station [[Triple J]] during the 1990s has increased the profile and availability of home-grown talent to listeners nationwide. Since the mid 1990s a string of successful alternative Australian acts have emerged; artists to achieve both underground (critical) and mainstream (commercial) success include [[You Am I]], [[Grinspoon]], [[Powderfinger]] and [[Jet (band)|Jet]].

====Country music====
{{Main|Australian country music}}
[[File:Melinda full.jpg|thumb|300px|left|Country yodeller, [[Melinda Schneider]] with folk-rocker [[Paul Kelly (musician)|Paul Kelly]].]] 

Australia has a long tradition of [[country music]], which has developed a style quite distinct from its US counterpart, influenced by Celtic folk ballads and the traditions of Australian bush balladeers like [[Henry Lawson]] and [[Banjo Paterson]]. Pioneers of popular country music in Australia included [[Tex Morton]] in the 1930s and [[Smoky Dawson]] from the 1940s onward. 

[[File:Olivia Newton-John Sydney 2008.jpg|thumb|150px|[[Olivia Newton-John]].]]

[[Slim Dusty]] (1927–2003) was known as the ''King of Australian Country Music''. His successful career spanned almost six decades and his 1957 hit &quot;[[A Pub With No Beer]]&quot; was the biggest-selling record by an Australian to that time, the first Australian single to go [[Music recording sales certification|gold]], and the first and only 78 rpm record to be awarded a gold disc.&lt;ref&gt;Dave&quot; Laing, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/2003/sep/20/guardianobituaries.artsobituaries &quot;Slim Dusty: Country singer famous for A Pub With No Beer&quot;], ''The Guardian (UK)'', 20 September 2003&lt;/ref&gt; Dusty recorded and released his one-hundredth album in the year 2000 and was given the honour of singing ''[[Waltzing Matilda]]'' in the closing ceremony of the [[2000 Summer Olympics|Sydney 2000 Olympic Games]]. Dusty's wife [[Joy McKean]] penned several of his most popular songs.

Other popular performers of Australian country music include: [[John Williamson (singer)|John Williamson]] (who wrote the iconic song &quot;[[True Blue (John Williamson song)|True Blue]]&quot;), [[Lee Kernaghan]], [[Kasey Chambers]] and [[Sara Storer]]. In the United States, Australian country music stars including [[Olivia Newton John]] and [[Keith Urban]] have attained great success.

Country music has also been a particularly popular form of musical expression among the [[Australia]]n [[Australian Aborigine|Aboriginal]] and [[Torres Strait Islander]] peoples. [[Troy Cassar-Daley]] is among Australia's successful indigenous performers.

The [[Tamworth Country Music Festival]] is an annual country music festival held in [[Tamworth, New South Wales]]. It celebrates the culture and heritage of [[Australian country music]]. During the festival the [[Country Music Association of Australia]] holds the [[Country Music Awards of Australia]] ceremony awarding the [[Golden Guitar]] trophies.

===Theatre===
{{Main|Theatre in Australia}}
[[Image:Dame Edna Everage Myer Melbourne.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Dame Edna Everage]], an enduring comic creation of [[Barry Humphries]], had her stage debut in Melbourne in the 1950s and has featured at the [[West End theatre|West End]] and [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]].]]

The ceremonial dances of [[indigenous Australians]] which recount the stories of the [[Dreamtime]], comprise theatrical aspects and have been performed since time immemorial during the 40-60,000 year Aboriginal occupation of Australia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/indigenous/ceremony/&lt;/ref&gt; European traditions came to Australia with the [[First Fleet]] in 1788, with the first production being performed in 1789 by convicts.&lt;ref name=&quot;olioweb.me.uk&quot;&gt;http://www.olioweb.me.uk/plays/&lt;/ref&gt; Two centuries later, the extraordinary circumstances of the foundations of Australian theatre were recounted in ''Our Country's Good'' by [[Timberlake Wertenbaker]]: the participants were prisoners watched by sadistic guards and the leading lady was under threat of the death penalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;olioweb.me.uk&quot;/&gt;

[[File:TheBoyfromOz.png|thumb|150px|[[Hugh Jackman]] in ''[[The Boy From Oz]]''.]]
[[File:Cate Blanchett Berlinale.jpg|150px|thumb|[[Kate Blanchett]] of the [[Sydney Theatre Company]].]]

The [[Theatre Royal, Hobart]], opened in 1837 and it remains the oldest theatre in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theatreroyal.com.au/history.html&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Australian gold rushes]] beginning in the 1850s provided funds for the construction of grand theatres in the Victorian style. A theatre was built on the present site of Melbourne's [[Princess Theatre, Melbourne|Princess Theatre]] in 1854. The present building now hosts major international productions as well as live performance events such as the [[Melbourne International Comedy Festival]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marrinertheatres.com.au/venue_princess.jsp&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Melbourne Athenaeum]] was built during this period and later became Australia's first cinema, screening ''[[The Story of the Kelly Gang]]'', the world's first feature film in 1906. [[Mark Twain]], [[Nellie Melba]], [[Lawrence Olivier]] and [[Barry Humphries]] have all performed on this historic stage.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.melbourneathenaeum.org.au/content/view/20/37/&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Queen's Theatre, Adelaide]] opened with [[Shakespeare]] in  1841 and is today the oldest theatre on the mainland.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.history.sa.gov.au/queens/about.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

After Federation in 1901, theatre productions evidenced the new sense of national identity. ''On Our Selection'' (1912) by [[Steele Rudd]], told of the adventures of a pioneer farming family and became immensely popular. Sydney's grand [[Capitol Theatre, Sydney|Capitol Theatre]] opened in 1928 and after restoration remains one of the nation's finest auditoriums.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.capitoltheatre.com.au/explore.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1955, ''[[Summer of the Seventeenth Doll]]'' by [[Ray Lawler]] portrayed resolutely Australian characters and went on to international acclaim. That same year, young Melbourne artist [[Barry Humphries]] performed as [[Edna Everage]] for the first time at [[Melbourne University]]'s Union Theatre. Humphries left for London in his early 20s and enjoyed success on stage, including in [[Lionel Bart]]'s musical, [[Oliver!]]. His satirical stage creations - notably Dame Edna and later [[Les Patterson]] - became Australian cultural icons. Humphries also achieved success in the USA with tours on [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] and television appearances and has been honoured in Australia and Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/6757531.stm | work=BBC News | title=The man behind Dame Edna Everage | date=15 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Institute of Dramatic Art]] was created in Sydney in 1958. This institute has since produced a list of famous alumni including [[Cate Blanchett]], [[Mel Gibson]] and [[Baz Luhrmann]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nida.edu.au/default.aspx?FolderID=15&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction of the [[Adelaide Festival Centre]] began in 1970 and South Australia's Sir [[Robert Helpmann]] became director of the Adelaide Festiavl of Arts.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adelaidefestivalcentre.com.au/afc/history.php&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.helpmannawards.com.au/default.aspx?s=sir_robert_helpmann&lt;/ref&gt; The new wave{{Clarify|date=September 2010}} of Australian theatre debuted in the 1970s. The [[Belvoir St Theatre]] presented works by [[Nick Enright]] and [[David Williamson]]. In 1973, the [[Sydney Opera House]], which had been based on a design by [[Jørn Utzon]], was officially opened.&lt;ref&gt;http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/166&lt;/ref&gt; [[Opera Australia]] made its home in the building and its reputation was enhanced by the presence of the diva [[Joan Sutherland]].

The [[Sydney Theatre Company]] was founded 1978 becoming one of Australia's foremost theatre companies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sydneytheatre.com.au/about&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bell Shakespeare Company]] was created in 1990.  A period of success for Australian musical theatre came in the 1990s with the debut of musical biographies of Australian music singers [[Peter Allen]] (''[[The Boy From Oz]]'' in 1998) and [[Johnny O'Keefe]] (''[[Shout! The Legend of The Wild One]]'').

In ''The One Day of the Year'', [[Alan Seymour]] studied the paradoxical nature of the [[ANZAC Day]] commemoration by Australians of the defeat of the [[Battle of Gallipoli]]. ''Ngapartji Ngapartji'', by [[Scott Rankin]] and Trevor Jamieson, recounts the story of the effects on the [[Pitjantjatjara people|Pitjantjatjara]] people of nuclear testing in the Western Desert during the [[Cold War]]. It is an example of the contemporary fusion of traditions of drama in Australia with Pitjantjatjara actors being supported by a multicultural cast  of Greek, Afghan, Japanese and New Zealand heritage.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/news/review-ngapartji-ngapartji/story-e6frev39-1111115327660&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Architecture of Australia]]
* [[Arts NSW]]
* [[Performing arts in Australia]]
** [[Performing arts education in Australia]]
* [[South Australian Living Artists Festival]]
* [[Australian Feminist Art Timeline]]

==External links==
*[http://arts.org.au '''ARTS.org.au''' - The Australian Arts Community - &quot;An online resource for artists and arts organisations Australia wide.&quot;]
*[http://www.fondation-bf.ch/ Australian Aboriginal Art Museum &quot;La grange&quot;, Môtiers/NE, Switzerland]
* [http://www.ozco.gov.au Australia Council for the Arts]
* [http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au Culture and Recreation Portal]
* [http://www.australianart.com.au/ Australian Art]
* [http://www.artshub.com.au/ ArtsHub - Australian Arts Networking and Jobs Directory]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Oceania in topic|Arts in}}
{{Australia topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Arts In Australia}}
[[Category:Arts in Australia| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
