<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6084017" ns="0" title="Ewido Networks"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase|ewido networks}}
[[Image:Ewido Anti-Spyware.jpg|thumb|right|Ewido Anti-Spyware 4.0]]
[[Image:AVG Anti-Spyware.png|thumb|right|AVG Anti-Spyware 7.5]]
[[Image:Ewido Anti-Spyware Micro Scanner.jpg|thumb|right|Ewido Anti-Spyware Micro Scanner 4.0]]

'''Ewido Networks''' was a software company based in [[Germany]]  known for creating Ewido Anti-Spyware. Ewido Anti-Spyware is a software used to remove [[malware]], like [[spyware]], [[Trojan horse (computing)|trojan horses]], [[adware]], dialers, and [[Computer worm|worms]]. It also features real-time protection, automatic updates, and other privacy features. Ewido has both a free version, and a paid version which adds realtime protection, and automatic updates.

==History==
Ewido networks was founded in Germany in 2004 by Andreas Rudyk, Peter Klapprodt and Tobias Graf. Their first product was Ewido Security Suite. Ewido was given Digital River's ICE award for &quot;Best newcomer of the year&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

==Grisoft Acquisition==
On April 19, 2006 it was announced that Czech [[Grisoft]] had acquired the German Anti-Malware company Ewido Networks.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.avg.com/press-releases-news.ndi-29396&lt;/ref&gt; This was the birth of Grisoft's AVG Anti Spyware, an anti spyware based on Ewido's engine. Grisoft now includes ewido in many security suites and bundles and antivirus products.

==Ewido Anti-Spyware==
This software began life as Ewido Security Suite and the name was changed to Ewido Anti-malware in December 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilderssecurity.com/showthread.php?t=111485 Name change - Wilders Security Forums&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; With the release of 4.0, it was later changed again to Ewido Anti-Spyware.

Ewido Anti-Spyware included new features such as scheduled scans, file shredder, running process manager, and a new interface. It also included an LSP and BHO viewer. There was a free version with no realtime protection and automatic updates (Users could update manually). The last known price was $29.99.

After Grisoft's acquisition, however, Ewido's Anti-Spyware developments has not stopped. It continues to exist as Ewido Online Scanner or Ewido Micro Scanner, that uses the full Ewido engine and signatures, without excluding heuristic detection options. As of AVG 8.0, AVG Anti-Spyware is integrated into AVG Anti-Virus and is no longer available as a standalone product. That means that AVG Anti-Spyware will not receive updates any more. 

Ewido works with many popular antivirus and other spyware products such as:
* [[AVG Anti-Virus]]
* [[Ad-Aware]]
* [[Avast]] Antivirus
* [[Avira]] Security Software
* [[Comodo Internet Security]]
* [[Counterspy]]
* [[Kaspersky Anti-Virus]]
* [[McAfee]]
* [[Norton AntiVirus]]
* [[Sophos]]
* [[Spybot Search &amp; Destroy]]
* [[Spyware Doctor]]
* [[ZoneAlarm]] Security Suite

==See also==
* [[Grisoft]]
* [[Malware]]
* [[Spyware]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ewido.com Ewido's Official site]

[[Category:Software companies of Germany]]
[[Category:Antivirus software]]
[[Category:Spyware removal]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Windows-only software]]


{{Germany-company-stub}}

[[fi:Ewido]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
