<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="60948" ns="0" title="Airdrie, North Lanarkshire"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|other places called Airdrie|Airdrie (disambiguation)}}
{{infobox UK place
|country =                 Scotland
   |official_name=             Airdrie
   |gaelic_name=            An t-Àrd Ruigh&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gaelicplacenames.org/databasedetails.php?id=462 Ainmean-Àite na h-Alba ~ Gaelic Place-Names of Scotland]&lt;/ref&gt;
   |scots_name=            Airdrie
   |static_image=&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Airdrie1.jpg|240px|{{deletable image-caption|1=Thursday, 16 April 2009}}]] --&gt;
   |static_image_caption=&lt;small&gt;Airdrie town centre&lt;/small&gt;
   |population=        36,326
   |os_grid_reference=     NS761654
   |map_type=              Scotland
   |latitude=55.86
   |longitude=-3.98
   |unitary_scotland=           [[North Lanarkshire]]
   |lieutenancy_scotland=       [[Lanarkshire]]
   |constituency_westminster=       [[Airdrie and Shotts (UK Parliament constituency)|Airdrie and Shotts]]
   |constituency_scottish_parliament=          [[Airdrie and Shotts (Scottish Parliament constituency)|Airdrie and Shotts]]
   |post_town=Airdrie
   |postcode_district=ML6
   |postcode_area=ML
   |dial_code=01236
}}

'''Airdrie''' ({{lang-gd|An t-Àrd Ruigh}}) is a town within [[North Lanarkshire]], [[Scotland]]. It lies on a [[plateau]] roughly 400&amp;nbsp;ft (130 m) above [[sea level]], and is approximately 12 miles (19&amp;nbsp;km) east of [[Glasgow]] city centre. Airdrie forms part of a conurbation with its neighbour [[Coatbridge]], in the former district known as the [[Monklands (district)|Monklands]]. As of 2006, the town had a population of 36,853.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northlan.gov.uk/Your+Council/parliaments/scottish+parliament/airdrie+and+shotts+population+profile.html] North Lanarkshire Population Estimates&lt;/ref&gt; [[Airdriehill]], [[Chapelhall]], [[Calderbank]], [[Caldercruix]], [[Glenmavis]], [[Greengairs]], [[Longriggend]], [[Plains, North Lanarkshire|Plains]], Stand, [[Upperton, North Lanarkshire|Upperton]] and [[Wattston]] are generally considered satellite villages of Airdrie.

==Name==
The origin of Airdrie's name is not known for certain; however, given the topography of the area, the most likely interpretation is that it derives from the Gaelic ''An Àrd Ruigh'' meaning a level height or high pasture land. Another possibility is that it was taken from the Gaelic ''An Àrd Àirighe'' meaning a sheiling or wayside town.

==Geography==
{{Geographic Location
|title     = '''Neighbouring towns, villages and places.'''
|Northwest = [[Glenboig]]
|North     = [[Glenmavis]]
|Northeast = [[Greengairs]],'''[[Falkirk]]'''
|West      = [[Coatbridge]] (Coatdyke), '''[[Glasgow]]'''
|Centre    = Airdrie
|East      = [[Bathgate]], '''[[Livingston, Scotland|Livingston]]'''
|Southwest = [[Coatbridge]] (Carnbroe)
|South     = [[Calderbank]]
|Southeast = [[Chapelhall]], '''[[Lanark]]'''
}}

===Wards===
[[North Lanarkshire Council]] divides Airdrie into the following wards and areas: 

Ward 7 - Airdrie North: Glenmavis, Caldercruix, Plains, Burnfoot, Thrashbush, Rochsoles, Holehills, Clarkston, Greengairs, Longriggend

Ward 8 - Airdrie Central: Airdrie Town Centre, Whinhall, Coatdyke, Gartlea, North Cairnhill, Central Park Area, Rawyards

Ward 11 - Airdrie South: Craignuek, Petersburn, Moffat Mills, Chapelhall, Calderbank, Brownsburn, South Cairnhill, Gartness

===Climate===
{{Weather box
|location = Airdrie, United Kingdom
|metric first = Yes
|single line = Yes
|Jan record high C = 13
|Feb record high C = 12
|Mar record high C = 15
|Apr record high C = 23
|May record high C = 27
|Jun record high C = 29
|Jul record high C = 30
|Aug record high C = 31
|Sep record high C = 25
|Oct record high C = 21
|Nov record high C = 15
|Dec record high C = 13
|Jan record high F = 56
|Feb record high F = 55
|Mar record high F = 59
|Apr record high F = 75
|May record high F = 81
|Jun record high F = 85
|Jul record high F = 86
|Aug record high F = 88
|Sep record high F = 78
|Oct record high F = 70
|Nov record high F = 59
|Dec record high F = 57
|year record high C = 31
|year record high F = 88
|Jan high C = 6
|Feb high C = 6
|Mar high C = 8
|Apr high C = 11
|May high C = 15
|Jun high C = 17
|Jul high C = 18
|Aug high C = 18
|Sep high C = 15
|Oct high C = 12
|Nov high C = 8
|Dec high C = 6
|Jan high F = 43
|Feb high F = 44
|Mar high F = 47
|Apr high F = 52
|Jun high F = 63
|Jul high F = 66
|Aug high F = 65
|Sep high F = 60
|Oct high F = 54
|Nov high F = 48
|Dec high F = 44
|year high C = 12
|year high F = 54
|Jan low C = 1
|Feb low C = 1
|Mar low C = 2
|Apr low C = 3
|May low C = 6
|Jun low C = 8
|Jul low C = 11
|Aug low C = 10
|Sep low C = 8
|Oct low C = 5
|Nov low C = 2
|Dec low C = 1
|Jan low F = 34
|Feb low F = 34
|Mar low F = 36
|Apr low F = 38
|May low F = 43
|Jun low F = 48
|Jul low F = 52
|Aug low F = 51
|Sep low F = 47
|Oct low F = 42
|Nov low F = 37
|Dec low F = 35
|year low C = 5
|year low F = 41
|Jan record low C = -17
|Feb record low C = -12
|Mar record low C = -8
|Apr record low C = -4
|May record low C = -3
|Jun record low C = 0
|Jul record low C = 3
|Aug record low C = 1
|Sep record low C = -2
|Oct record low C = -7
|Nov record low C = -10
|Dec record low C = -17
|Jan record low F = 1
|Feb record low F = 9
|Mar record low F = 16
|Apr record low F = 24
|May record low F = 25
|Jun record low F = 33
|Jul record low F = 38
|Aug record low F = 35
|Sep record low F = 27
|Oct record low F = 19
|Nov record low F = 14
|Dec record low F = 1
|year record low C = -17
|year record low F = 1
|Jan precipitation mm = 86.9
|Feb precipitation mm = 79
|Mar precipitation mm = 74.4
|Apr precipitation mm = 46.5
|May precipitation mm = 33.5
|Jun precipitation mm = 38.6
|Jul precipitation mm = 49.5
|Aug precipitation mm = 52.6
|Sep precipitation mm = 56.6
|Oct precipitation mm = 84.8
|Nov precipitation mm = 84.8
|Dec precipitation mm = 74.9
|Jan precipitation inch = 3.42
|Feb precipitation inch = 3.11
|Mar precipitation inch = 2.93
|Apr precipitation inch = 1.83
|May precipitation inch = 1.32
|Jun precipitation inch = 1.52
|Jul precipitation inch = 1.95
|Aug precipitation inch = 2.07
|Sep precipitation inch = 2.23
|Oct precipitation inch = 3.34
|Nov precipitation inch = 2.62
|Dec precipitation inch = 2.95
|year precipitation mm = 762.1
|year precipitation inch = 30
|source 1 = Weatherbase&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.weatherbase.com/weather/weather.php3?s=4130
| title = Historical Weather for Airdrie, Scotland,  United Kingdom
| publisher = Weatherbase
| accessdate = 23 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=August 2010
}}

==History==
===Early history===
The history of Airdrie might be dated back to AD 577, which was the year of the [[Battle of Arderyth]]&lt;ref&gt;Begg, Ean. &amp; Rich, Deike (1991). ''On the Trail of Merlin''. ISBN 0-85030-939-5&lt;/ref&gt; However, the historicity and location of the battle are the subject of debate and shrouded in myth. The battle was believed to have been between the [[Gododdin]], [[Riderch I of Alt Clut|Rydderych]] ''The Bountiful'', [[King of Strathclyde]], and Aeddam ''The Perfidious'', the [[Scoti]] King of [[Kintyre]]. While few might have heard of the main protagonists, amongst Aeddam's contingent was the legendary [[Celts|Celtic]] [[bard]], [[Merlin]]. The history of Airdrie between the Battle of Arderyth and AD 1162 is unclear, due to the scarcity of written historical records.

===1162 to 1850===
[[File:Pontmap2b.jpg|thumb|right|205px|[[Timothy Pont|Pont's]] &quot;Nether Warde of Clyds-dail&quot; map c.1654 depicting Ardry (Airdrie), Burnfyd (Burnfoot), Carnhil (Cairnhill), Gartly (Gartlea), and Ruchsols (Rochsoles) amongst others.]] Airdrie owes its existence to its location on the 'Hogs Back' - a ridge of land running from east to west. One very important aspect of the town’s history were the [[Cistercian]] monks of [[Newbattle Abbey]], hence a name for the wider area; Monklands. The monks were farmers and most of the land they used is known today as 'The Four Isles' (a housing estate named after four Scottish islands): [[Isle of Mull|Mull]], [[Islay]], [[Iona]] and [[Luing]] in the Petersburn area of modern Airdrie).  The [[monk]]s of Newbattle had numerous establishments throughout the area including a [[farm]] grange at Drumpellier, Coatbridge, a court house at [[Kipps]], a [[chapel]] in the area of Chapelhall and a number of [[maize|corn]] [[Mill (grinding)|mills]]. The Monks were also expert in the [[construction]] of [[road]]s. In the 12th century they established the original Glasgow to [[Edinburgh]] road via Airdrie and [[Bathgate]], to link up with their lands in Newbattle in [[East Lothian]].

In those days travelling was often dangerous. Horses were still very rare and could only be afforded by the rich. Low lying ground was usually extremely difficult to navigate because of the numerous [[bog]]s, forests and [[Burn (topography)|burns]] - not to mention the possibility of [[ambush]] by a [[footpad]] or robber. Hence, it became much more practical to travel on the high ground (the 'High Way') where one could avoid the mud and the robbers. These roads (or rather tracks) became known as the King's Highway.

Definitive evidence of the existence of Airdrie as a tenantry was only made clear in 1503. The old monks' road was via Cliftonhill (an area now in neighbouring Coatbridge), Airdrie House (now the site of [[Monklands Hospital]]), Aitchison Street, High Street, Hallcraig Street, Flowerhill Street and Colliertree Road.  It was along this road that the first houses in Airdrie were built.  Development was slow and it was only around 1650 that evidence of the number of [[population|inhabitants]] was known at around 500 for the Airdrie area. A large contingent of Airdrieonians fought at the [[Battle of Bothwell Brig]] during the Covenanter Rebellion of 1679; their banner can still be viewed at the local library.

A significant event in Airdrie's history was the [[1695]] passing of a special Act of Parliament in the Scottish Parliament allowing Robert Hamilton of Airdrie to hold four fairs yearly and a weekly market in the town of 'Airdry'. This helped develop Airdrie from a 'farm town' into a thriving 'market town'.

However, Airdrie really came to prominence through its [[weaving]] industry. Airdrie Weavers Society was founded in 1781 and [[flax]] was being grown in sixteen farms in and around the [[burgh]]. In the last decade of the eighteenth century, [[coal mining]] was in progress and around thirty [[Coal mining|colliers]] were employed. Weaving continued to flourish making up a substantial part of the population of over 2,500 around the turn of the 19th century. Given its large number of weavers, its geographic location, and a large number of unemployed soldiers following the end of the [[Napoleonic Wars]], Airdrie became a major centre of support for the [[Radical War]] of 1820. The rapid pace of population growth continued and by 1821 there were 4,862 inhabitants.  At this time the number of houses being built increased dramatically and in 1821, by a private [[Act of Parliament]], Airdrie became a free and independent [[Burgh of Barony]]. Due to the fact it was 'independent', it had all the powers of a [[Royal burgh|Royal Burgh]].

[[Voting]] in the early part of the nineteenth century was rather hit or miss as not only locals but residents outside the burgh were allowed to vote. In 1821 the first election of a town council took place and by August it had appointed an assessor, [[Procurator Fiscal|procurator fiscal]], master of police and a [[town crier]].

In 1824 it was decided to build the Town House, which was originally designed by Alexander Baird and is now a local landmark known as the 'town clock'. In 1832 the Town House was used as a hospital due to the [[cholera]] outbreak of this year.

By 1850, the population had grown to 12,418.

===1850 to 1920===
The enormous growth in population was not due to high birthrate, but instead due to an influx of residents from the [[Scottish Highlands|Highlands]] and predominantly [[Ireland]]. This followed the [[Highland Potato Famine|Highland potato famine]] of the mid 1840s and also reflected the change from cottage industry to [[heavy industry]] in the area. Most of the Irish immigrant population were involved with [[mining]] and labouring.
This led to an increase in ironwork [[Foundry|foundries]] around the area. Because of this explosion in industry, [[Rail transport|railway]] links were soon established (circa 1830) and by 1862, the Airdrie and Bathgate Junction Railway provided a direct link to Edinburgh with Airdrie South Station providing the starting point for trains to Glasgow.

In August the [[Public Libraries Act 1850|Public Libraries Act (Scotland) 1853]] was passed, and in November [[Airdrie Public Library]] became the first in Scotland.

The dramatic rise in population and industry prompted the need for more accessible water supplies. Until the mid 1800s, various wells were put in place feeding from surrounding streams in the area. These served to provide many houses with private wells. By 1846 Airdrie and Coatbridge Water Company was founded to construct (along with Forth and Clyde Canal Company) the reservoir at Roughrigg.

Around the mid 1800s, several local [[newspaper]]s began appearing and notably the [[Airdrie &amp; Coatbridge Advertiser]], which is still the most popular local paper today. Also at this time, [[association football|football]] and [[cricket]] began to emerge as popular sports. Following the codification of association football rules a local team called Excelsior was formed in 1878 which would later be renamed [[Airdrieonians F.C.]] Horse race meetings were also held in the town (1851–1870) but this land became the golf course for the newly formed Airdrie Golf Club in 1877.

[[Education]] posed a major problem with severe overcrowding in the few schools available, therefore three new school boards were established. Fees were routinely charged within the schools with the belief they should be self-supporting until a parliamentary act of 1889 relieved some of the infant classes in schools of this burden. [[Airdrie Academy]] was built in 1895 and by 1919 all school boards were dissolved and Lanarkshire Education Authority took over responsibility for education throughout [[Lanarkshire]].

[[Airdrie Public Observatory]], one of only four public observatories in the UK (Second Oldest and Smallest)- all in Scotland, was founded in the first library building in 1896, and is still operated in the present building by the Airdrie Astronomical Association a Scottish [[space exploration|astronautic]] and [[astronomy]] society and registered charity.

By the turn of the century [[variety show]]s were becoming popular in the area and by 1911 the Pavilion in Graham Street was built which after initially being used as a music hall started showing cinematographic pictures. Unfortunately it was destroyed by fire in 1917 but was rebuilt in 1919 and finally closed in 1970. The New Cinema was opened in 1920 in Broomknoll Street but too has since closed. The town had no suitable venue for larger functions so in 1912 the Sir John Wilson Town Hall was opened (following a generous offer from Sir John Wilson covering the total cost of £13,500). This still stands and is used for major events in the town.

===1920 onwards===
At the end of the [[World War I|First World War]], Airdrie was hard hit with many casualties from the war. Many inhabitants also chose to emigrate around this time. Consequently the population only rose by 3% to around 26,000 by 1931. The [[Great Depression|depression]] years had made a great impact on the town and several well known manufacturers ceased to exist and few replaced them. It was reported that 50% of the registered population were [[Unemployment|unemployed]]. Church groups tried to provide some comfort for the poor folk in the area and set up educational and work experience projects to help and by 1936 the Airdrie Churches Council had attracted national interest through their work culminating in a building in Graham Street being provided for them (the Mutual Service Club). This is now Airdrie Community Centre.

The current Airdrie Public Library building was eventually constructed on its present site in 1925 after years of moving from one site to another.  [[Image:ASTRA - Airdrie Library Building Anderson Street.JPG|thumb| right| The first Airdrie Public Library building, a [[Carnegie library]] opened 1894.]]

Conditions in the town did not really improve until well after the [[World War II|Second World War]] but in 1949 the [[Boots Group|Boots]] [[Pharmaceutical industry|pharmaceutical company]] and Banner Textiles Ltd were attracted to the town (between them employing 1200). With this impetus, new companies began to consider Airdrie as a viable option for business and in 1958 [[Pye Ltd.|Pye]] opened employing over 1000 people. The emergence of industrial estates was also prevalent around this time (Newhouse, Chapelhall, and Brownsburn). The Airdrie Arts Centre opened in 1967 in the former Airdrie Library building and remains a popular venue for concerts and plays.

The 1970s saw the opening of [[Monklands Hospital]], which replaced an older hospital on the Airdrie House estate that had been closed in 1962 and demolished in 1964.

===Modern Airdrie===
Airdrie town centre has changed much in the last ten years with a new road scheme and a shift in emphasis with the type of shopping it offers. Graham Street, the main [[pedestrianised]] street, has recently been refurbished and has had the pedestrian precinct area upgraded. New housing complexes are being built around this suitably situated [[commuter town]], notably in Chapelhall, Rochsoles and Glenmavis, the former Boots factory site in Rawyards and the former Imperial Tube Works in Cairnhill.

Airdrie also has signage in the Scots Gaelic language around the town centre, (alongside English) this was first introduced for the 1993 [[Royal National Mod]]. The signs were originally erected by Monklands District Council, but have been maintained by North Lanarkshire Council.

==Sport==

===Angling===
*[http://www.airdrie-angling.co.uk Airdrie &amp; District Angling Club] based at [[Hillend Loch]], one of Scotland's top [[trout]] fishing locations.

===Athletics===
*[http://www.airdrieharriers.com/ Airdrie Harriers], North Lanarkshire's largest athletics club.

===Bowls===
There are a number of bowling clubs in the town. All are members of the Lanarkshire Bowling Association and the [[Scottish Bowling Association]], district 27.
*Airdrie Bowling Club (founded 1852)
*Calderbank Bowling Club - in nearby [[Calderbank]].
*Caldercraig Bowling Club
*Central Bowling Club
*Clarkston Bowling Club
*Springwells Bowling Club

===Football===
The town's major [[association football|football]] club is [[Airdrie United F.C.|Airdrie United]] [http://www.airdriefc.com], who play in the [[Scottish Football League Second Division|Second Division]] of the [[Scottish Football League]], and are based at the [[Excelsior Stadium]]. They were formed as a replacement for [[Airdrieonians F.C.|Airdrieonians]], who folded in 2002.

In addition there are a number of teams competing in the various [[Scottish Amateur Football Association]] leagues.

===Golf===
[http://www.airdriegolfclub.co.uk Airdrie Golf Club] was established in 1877. It is a wooded parkland par 69 course with tight fairways and well protected greens.

===Motor Sport===
The [http://www.mscc.org.uk Monklands Sporting Car Club] runs it events at the [[Forrestburn Hillclimb]] situated about 5 miles east of Airdrie.

===Rugby Union===
Airdrie was home to its own rugby union team called Waysiders RFC. This team was amalgamated to form [http://www.pitchero.com/clubs/waysidersdrumpellier Waysiders Drumpellier RFC] which currently play out of Drumpellier RFC’s traditional home ground in Langloan, Coatbridge.

They presently play in the [[West Regional Leagues (Rugby Union)|West Regional Leagues]] Division One (Level five).

===Sailing===
The [http://www.monklandssailingclub.org.uk Monklands Sailing Club] is based at [[Hillend Loch]] by [[Caldercruix]].

===Skateboarding/Rollerblading/BMX===
*Airdrie Skatepark and BMX track are located at Airdrie Leisure Centre.

===Swimming===
*Airdrie and Monklands ASC, based at the [[John Smith (Labour Party leader)|John Smith]] Pool, Airdrie.

===Tennis===
*Springwells Lawn Tennis Club. A member of the West of Scotland District and LTA County, divisions of [[Tennis Scotland]].

==Culture==
===Places of interest===
*[[Airdrie Arts Centre]] - originally a [[Carnegie library]].
*[[Airdrie Public Library]]
*[[Airdrie Public Observatory]] - with its celebrated [[Thomas Cooke (machinist)|Cooke]] telescope.
*[[Black Hill transmitting station]] - the tallest structure in Scotland.
*[http://www.airdrieparks.org.uk Centenary and West End Parks] - including the Airdrie [[war memorial|Cenotaph]] and a [[Victorian era|Victorian]] railway viaduct.
*Drumbowie [[World War II]] [[Anti-aircraft battery]] - site number N12, part of the Clyde AA defences. Situated just outside [[Glenmavis]].
*[[Monkland Canal]] - where the [[Vulcan (barge)]], the world's first iron boat, was constructed and launched in 1819.
*New Monklands Parish Church
*[http://www.hiddenglasgow.com/forums/viewtopic.php?f=15&amp;t=9017&amp;hilit=wallace+stone+airdrie The Wallace Stone] - legend tells that [[William Wallace]] sharpened his sword on this stone on his way to the [[Battle of Falkirk]].
*Sir John Wilson Town Hall

===Organisations===
*[http://www.airdrieandcoatbridgeaos.co.uk Airdrie and Coatbridge Amateur Operatic Society]

*[http://www.airdriecoatbridgephotographic.co.uk/ Airdrie and Coatbridge Photographic Club]

*Airdrie and District [[Round Table (club)|Round Table]], [http://www.airdrie.roundtable.co.uk/ no.585]

*[[Army Cadet Force]] - Glasgow and Lanarkshire Battalion

*[http://www.airdrieobservatory.com Airdrie Astronomical Association] - A leading Scottish amateur astronomical organisation.

*[http://www.northlanarkshire.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=6212 Beetroot Studios] - full music and video production facilities and services for solo artists or bands.

*[[Boys Brigade]] - Airdrie, Coatbridge and District Battalion, 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 5th, 6th, 7th, 8th and 11th Companies.

*[[Girl Guides]] (and Brownies) - County of North Lanarkshire

*The [[Moira Anderson Foundation]] [http://www.moiraanderson.org] - A national charity providing support for those affected by childhood sexual abuse.

*[http://www.monklandsheritagesociety.org.uk Monklands Heritage Society]

*[http://www.monklandslightopera.com Monklands Light Opera]

*[http://www.monklandsramblers.org.uk Monklands Ramblers]

*Monklands Women's Aid - associated with [http://www.scottishwomensaid.org.uk Scottish Women's Aid]. Based at the One Wellwynd centre. Provides support for women and children suffering from [[domestic abuse]].

* The [[Royal Scottish Geographical Society]] maintains a regional centre at the Airdrie Arts Centre.

*[[The Scout Association]] - Clyde Region, Calder District, 5th Lanarkshire, 88th Lanarkshire and 126th Lanarkshire Troops.

*[[Sea Cadet Corps (United Kingdom)|Sea Cadet Corps]] - T.S. Enterprise

====Community Centres====
These community centres are maintained by [[North Lanarkshire Council]].
*Beechbank CC - located in Whinhall.
*Chapelside CC - includes the Richard Stewart Nursery, North Airdrie Music Project, Chapelside Women's Health Project and an Adult Literacy centre.
*Four Isles CC - located in Petersburn.
*Gartlea CC
*Rochsoles CC
*Springfield CC - located in east-central Airdrie.
*Victoria CC - located in west-central Airdrie.

==Governance==
{{further|[[History of local government in Scotland]]}}

Airdrie is represented by several tiers of elected government. [[North Lanarkshire|North Lanarkshire Council]], the unitary [[Local government|local authority]] for Airdrie, is based at [[Motherwell, North Lanarkshire|Motherwell]], and is the [[Executive (government)|executive]], [[Deliberation|deliberative]] and [[Legislature|legislative]] body responsible for [[local government in Scotland|local governance]]. The [[Scottish Parliament]] is responsible for [[devolution|devolved matters]] such as [[education in Scotland|education]], [[NHS Scotland|health]] and [[Scots law|justice]],&lt;ref name=&quot;devolvedmatters&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scotlandoffice.gov.uk/what-we-do/reserved-and-devolved-matters.html |title=Reserved and devolved matters |publisher=Scotland Office |accessdate=2006-11-14 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061004074305/http://www.scotlandoffice.gov.uk/what-we-do/reserved-and-devolved-matters.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 4 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; while [[reserved matters]] are dealt with by the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]].

===Westminster===
The town forms part of the [[United Kingdom constituencies|burgh constituency]] of [[Airdrie and Shotts (UK Parliament constituency)|Airdrie and Shotts]], electing one [[Member of Parliament]] (MP) to the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]]. In 2005, changes to the constituency boundaries saw part of its area transferred to [[Motherwell and Wishaw (UK Parliament constituency)|Motherwell and Wishaw]], offset by the addition of part of [[Hamilton North and Bellshill (UK Parliament constituency)|Hamilton North and Bellshill]].

[[Pamela Nash]] has been MP for Airdrie and Shotts since the [[United Kingdom general election, 2010|2010 general election]]; currently she is also the youngest member of the House of Commons. The location has been represented by several prominent Labour MPs in recent years:
*[[John Smith (UK politician)|John Smith]], [[Member of Parliament|MP]] for North Lanarkshire 1970–1983 and Monklands East 1983–1994 (Eastern Coatbridge and Airdrie area). Former [[Shadow Chancellor of the Exchequer|Shadow Chancellor]] and then leader of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] until his untimely death in 1994.
*[[Helen Liddell]], MP for Monklands East 1994–1997, Airdrie and Shotts 1997–2005, [[Secretary of State for Scotland]] and subsequently Britain's [[List of High Commissioners from the United Kingdom to Australia|High Commissioner to Australia]].
*[[John Reid (politician)|John Reid]], MP for Airdrie and Shotts 2005–2010, a high profile minister including as the first [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] to be appointed [[Secretary of State for Northern Ireland]].

===Scottish Parliament===
For the purposes of the [[Scottish Parliament]], Airdrie forms part of the [[Airdrie and Shotts (Scottish Parliament constituency)|Airdrie and Shotts]] constituency.  This has slightly different boundaries than that of the UK Parliament constituency of the same name.  The current member of the [[Scottish Parliament]] for [[Airdrie and Shotts (Scottish Parliament constituency)|Airdrie and Shotts]] is [[Alex Neil MSP]] ([[Scottish National Party]]), who won this seat in the 2011 Scottish Parliament from the LAbour Party who had  held the seat since the instatement of the Scottish Parliament in 1999.

In addition to this Airdrie is represented by seven [[Scottish Parliament constituencies and regions|regional MSPs]] from the [[Central Scotland (Scottish Parliament electoral region)|Central Scotland electoral region]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/msp/map/central.html|publisher=scottish.parliament.uk|title=Central Scotland Regional MSPs|accessdate=2008-05-28|date=}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are: [[Linda Fabiani]] ([[Scottish National Party]], SNP), [[Jamie Hepburn]] (SNP), [[Christina McKelvie]] (SNP), [[Margaret Mitchell]] ([[Scottish Conservative Party]]), [[Alex Neil MSP|Alex Neil]] (SNP), [[Hugh O'Donnell (politician)|Hugh O'Donnell]] ([[Scottish Liberal Democrats]]), and [[John Wilson (Scottish politician)|John Wilson]] (SNP).

===Local government===
Up until 1975, Airdrie had its own [[Burgh Council]]. Between 1975 and 1996, Airdrie came under [[Monklands (district)|Monklands District Council]] operating in conjunction with [[Strathclyde|Strathclyde Regional Council]]. Monklands District Council was headquartered in the Coatbridge Municipal Building. Many Airdrieonians felt short-changed by MDC's actions and a significant political scandal known as [[Monklandsgate]] greatly tarnished the Council's reputation. After 1996, it came under the authority of the unitary [[North Lanarkshire|North Lanarkshire Council]]. Currently, the council is in control of the Labour group and the leader of the council is [[Jim McCabe]], councillor for Thorniewood.

==Law==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Airdriesheriffcourt.jpg|thumb|right|Airdrie Sheriff Court|{{deletable image-caption|1=Saturday, 17 October 2009}}]] --&gt;

===Police===
Policing in Airdrie is undertaken by [[Strathclyde Police]]. Airdrie is part of N Division which is headquartered in [[Motherwell]] with [[Chief Superintendent]] Graham Cairns responsible for local strategy. Airdrie also forms part of NA (or Monklands) sub division which includes Coatbridge and the surrounding area. There is one police office in Airdrie and this is open 24 hours.

===Sheriff Court===
[[Airdrie Sheriff Court]] provides a comprehensive local court service for the area including civil actions and criminal cases. It is administered by the [[Scottish Court Service]] and part of the South Strathclyde, Dumfries and Galloway [[Sheriffdom]] headed by a [[Sheriff Principal]].

===Other===
*The [[Crown Office and Procurator Fiscal Service]], responsible for the prosecution of crime in Scotland, maintains an office in the town directly opposite the Court.
*The Airdrie Hearing Centre holds [[Children's Hearings]] within the town. The Centre is part of the Central West Region of the [[Scottish Children's Reporter Administration]].

==Economy==
===Overview===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Airdriesavingsbank.jpg|thumb|right|Airdrie Savings Bank]] --&gt;
As outlined in the history section Airdrie's traditional economic activities of weaving, coal mining, and heavy industry have ceased to exist. Whilst the [[Glenflagler]] Distillery is now closed the town still retains a strong involvement in the [[whisky]] industry. It is fair to say that, given its location near to Glasgow and other commercial or industrial areas, Airdrie might now be considered something of a commuter town. In fact housing construction in Airdrie has been very prominent in recent years with builders developing a number of [[brownfield]] sites following the closure of various factories such as Boots whom closed their factory in 2004. Nonetheless it does retain significant economic activity.

===Notable Airdrie employers===
* Airdrie Business Centre - a fully [[BREEAM]] accredited facility notable for its grass turf roof.

*[[Airdrie Savings Bank]] [http://www.airdriesavingsbank.com], one of the few independent banks in the UK, and the only independent savings bank.

*[http://www.albert-bartlett.co.uk Albert Bartlett &amp; Sons], the leading supplier of [[root vegetables]] in the UK. The Bartlett brothers, Alan, 52, and Ronnie, 44 are jointly ranked in The Sunday Times Rich List 2008 as the 63rd richest persons in Scotland and the 969th richest persons in the UK with a worth valued at £80 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartlettbrothers&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://business.timesonline.co.uk/tol/business/specials/rich_list/article3800679.ece|title=The Bartlett brothers' entry in The Sunday Times Rich List 2008|publisher= timesonline.co.uk|accessdate=2009-01-28 | location=London | date=2008-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Bell Group, the UK's largest commercial and industrial painting firm.

*[http://www.burnstewartdistillers.com/home Burn Stewart Distillers], blending, maturation and warehousing. Products include [[Deanston]], [[Ledaig]] and [[Tobermory Single Malt]].

*[http://www.rockeater.co.uk Caldervale Forge Co. Ltd.], better known by their Rockeater products. World leading manufacturer of [[hydraulic breaker]] steels.

*Donald McLaren Ltd., the first and only independent [[funeral directors]] in Airdrie and Coatbridge since 1912. 

*EFTEE - leading [[dump truck]] body manufacturer.

*GM Mining, a mining and associated industries company operated by a local family (the Gillespies) and [[David Murray (Scottish businessman)|David Murray]].

*[http://www.harrisonfield.co.uk/ Harrison-Field], one of the UK's leading manufacturer and supplier of workwear with headquarters and production facilities in the town.

*[[Inver House Distillers Limited]] [http://www.inverhouse.com], headquarters and warehousing in Airdrie. Products include [[Old Pulteney]], [[Balblair]], [[Heather Cream]] and Coldstream Gin.

*[[Monklands Hospital]]

*[http://www.newlaycivileng.co.uk Newlay] - major civil engineering company specialising in road construction.

*[http://www.onewellwynd.co.uk One Wellwynd] Innovative business and conference centre incorporating the refurbished Old Wellwynd Church building (1847).

*[http://www.rowan-timber.co.uk Rowan Timber], Scotland's leading timber supplier, was established in Airdrie, maintains a major depot in the town and is headquartered in nearby [[Plains, North Lanarkshire|Plains]].

*Scottish Crane and Engineering Services, one of Scotland's leading manufacturer and supplier of cranes and related engineering services.

*[[Teleperformance]], a major leader in [[Telemarketing|telesales]] and [[technical support]]. Formerly operated as [[beCogent]].

*[http://www.terratek.co.uk Terra Tek], one of the UK's foremost companies providing [[site investigation]] and [[geotechnical]] laboratory services.

====Trading Estates====
*Brownsburn Industrial Estate: [http://www.relief-orthotics.co.uk/index.html Relief Orthotics] ([[orthoses]]), [http://www.tomairdrie.co.uk T.O.M.], (motor vehicle services)
*Osprey Trade Park: Ace [[Elevator|Elevators]], [http://www.graham-group.co.uk Graham] (plumbing supplies), [http://www.howdens.com Howdens] (fitted kitchens), [http://www.jewson.co.uk Jewson] (building supplies)

==Demographics==
According to the [[United Kingdom Census 2001|2001 Census]],&lt;ref name=&quot;airdriecensus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scrol.gov.uk/scrol/browser/profile.jsp?profile=Population&amp;mainLevel=CouncilArea&amp;mainArea=North+Lanarkshire&amp;mainText=&amp;mainTextExplicitMatch=null&amp;compLevel=Locality&amp;compText=airdrie&amp;compTextExplicitMatch=false|title=Profile of Airdrie from Scotland's Census 2001 |publisher= scrol.gov.uk|accessdate=2009-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Airdrie's population of 36,326 was:
*47.31 male, 52.69% female.
*20.7% were under 16, 16.67% were pensioners.
*46.61% were married (first marriage), 29.81% were single.
*95.74% were born in Scotland or described their nationality as Scottish.
*only 0.42% spoke [[Scottish Gaelic|Gaelic]].

===Religion===
'''Christian'''
[[Image:Flowerhillchurch.jpg|thumb|right|Flowerhill Church]]
'''[[Church of Scotland]]''' - Airdrie's Church of Scotland churches are part of the [[Presbyterian polity|Presbytery of Hamilton]].
*[http://broomknollchurch.org Broomknoll Church] (1889)
*[http://www.airdrieclarkstonparishchurch.org.uk Clarkston Church] (1837)
*[http://www.flowerhillparishchurch.co.uk Flowerhill Church] (1875)
*[http://www.airdriehighkirk.org.uk High Church]
*Jackson Church
*New Monkland Parish Church (bef. 1698) - In nearby [[Glenmavis]].
*[http://www.newwellwynd.org.uk New Wellwynd] (1834)
*St Columba's Church

'''[[Roman Catholicism in Scotland|Roman Catholic Church]]''' - Airdrie's Roman Cathloic churches are immediately governed by the [[Diocese of Motherwell]], currently led by [[Bishop]] [[Joseph Devine]]. The [[Bishops' Conference of Scotland]] (effectively the Church's headquarters in Scotland) is situated in Airdrie.
*St Andrew's Church
*St Edward's Church
*St Margaret's Church (1839)
*St Serf's Church

'''[[Congregational church|Congregational Church]]''' - Airdrie's Congregational churches are associoated with the [[Congregational Federation]].
*Coatdyke Church
*Ebenezer Church (Broomknoll Street) (1882)
*Pilgrim Church

'''Other'''
*[http://www.airdriebaptist.co.uk Airdrie Baptist Church] (1843) - part of the [[Baptist Union of Scotland]].
*Airdrie Islamic Centre (mosque) - part of the [[UK Islamic Mission]].
*Airdrie Park - part of the [[United Reformed Church]].
*[http://airdrierpcs.org/ Airdrie Reformed Presbyterian Church] - part of the [[Reformed Presbyterian Church of Scotland]], which is largely headquartered in Airdrie.
*The Church of Jesus Christ of the Latter-Day Saints Chapel
*Ebenezer Church (Aitchison Street) - [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical Church]] - Airdrie's Evangelical churches are [[Plymouth Brethren|Brethren]] and associated with the [[Evangelical Alliance]].
*Jehovah's Witnesses' Kingdom Hall
*[[The Salvation Army]], Airdrie Corps
*[http://www.st-andrews-hospice.com St Andrew's Hospice] - operated by the [[Sisters of Charity]].
*St Paul &amp; St John the Baptist - part of the [[Scottish Episcopal Church]], governed by the [[Diocese of Glasgow and Galloway]], currently led by [[Idris Jones]], [[Primate (religion)|Primus]] of the whole Church.

==Transport==
[[Airdrie railway station]] is on the electrified [[North Clyde Line]]. This railway provides a frequent train service to [[Glasgow]] via {{stnlnk|Coatbridge Sunnyside}} and {{stnlnk|Easterhouse}}. In 2010, the [[Airdrie-Bathgate Rail Link]] opened providing Airdrie with a direct commuter train service to {{stnlnk|Bathgate}}, {{stnlnk|Livingston North}} and {{stnlnk|Edinburgh Waverley}}. [[Drumgelloch railway station]] serves the eastern end of the town.

Airdrie has excellent road links to [[Glasgow]], [[Edinburgh]], [[Motherwell]], and [[Cumbernauld]] and is situated close to the [[M8 motorway (Scotland)|M8 motorway]]. Bus services are largely undertaken by local operators, and links to Glasgow are provided by [[First Glasgow]].

Airdrie is connected to the UK [[National Cycle Network]] by [[National Cycle Route 75]]. This route provides a path between Glasgow and Edinburgh.

==Healthcare==
[[File:Monklands Hospital Accident and Emergency entrance - geograph.org.uk - 370541.jpg|thumb|right|Monklands District General Hospital with the medical tower, the surgical tower and the A&amp;E entrance]]
[[NHS Lanarkshire]] is responsible for the healthcare of Airdrie residents. Airdrie is home to [[Monklands Hospital|Monklands District General Hospital]] with a 24-hour [[Emergency department|Accident &amp; Emergency]] department. The hospital has 473 beds and provides a comprehensive service with specialist [[renal]] and [[Otolaryngology|ENT]] departments. Another NHS hospital, Wester Moffat, provides long term care for the elderly. The West Central division of the [[Scottish Ambulance Service]] provides accident and emergency, and patient transport services for the town. Also located in the town is St Andrews's Hospice which is operated by the [[Sisters of Charity]] and partly funded by North Lanarkshire Council. The hospice is a leading palliative care unit in Scotland with a strong emphasis on cancer care. The [http://www.parkinsonselfhelp.org.uk Parkinson's Self Help Group (North Lanarkshire)] is based in the Weavers' Cottages (1780) and provides support for people with [[Parkinson's disease]]. The [http://www.housesforheroes.org.uk SVGCA - Houses for Heroes], a charity providing suitable accommodation for permanently disabled armed forces, police and fire service  personnel, maintains four houses in the town. In addition there are several medical practices, dental surgeries, nursing homes and opticians throughout Airdrie.

==Education==
There are three [[secondary schools]], 13 [[primary schools]], two dedicated [[nursery schools]], and one [[special needs]] school in Airdrie, all of which are run by North Lanarkshire Council.

===Secondary schools===
*[[Airdrie Academy]] [http://www.airdrie.n-lanark.sch.uk] - [[Non-denominational]], [[co-educational]], [[comprehensive school]] 
*[[Caldervale High]] [http://www.caldervale.n-lanark.sch.uk] - [[Non-denominational]], [[co-educational]],  [[comprehensive school]]    
*[[St Margaret's High]] - [[Roman Catholic]], [[co-educational]], [[comprehensive school]]

===Primary schools===
*Alexandra Primary - Roman Catholic, co-educational
*Chapelside Primary - Non-denominational, co-educational,
*Clarkston Primary - Non-denominational, co-educational
*Dunrobin Primary - Non-denominational, co-educational
*Glengowan &amp; St Mary's Primary Schools and Nursery  - [[Joint campus]], non-deominational and Roman Catholic, co-educational - in nearby [[Caldercruix]].
*Golfhill Primary - Non-denominational, co-educational
*Petersburn Primary and Nursery - Non-denominational, co-educational
*New Monkland Primary and Nursery - Non-denominational, co-educational - in nearby [[Glenmavis]].
*Plains &amp; St David's Primary Schools - [[Joint campus]], non-deominational and Roman Catholic, co-educational - in nearby [[Plains]].
*Rochsolloch Primary and Nursery - Non-denominational, co-educational
*St Andrew's Primary and Nursery - Roman Catholic, co-educational
*St Dominic's Primary and Nursery - Roman Catholic, co-educational
*St Edward's Primary and Nursery - Roman Catholic, co-educational
*St Serf's Primary and Nursery - Roman Catholic, co-educational
*Tollbrae Primary and Nursery - Non-denominational, co-educational
*Victoria Primary and Nursery - Non-denominational, co-educational

===Nursery schools===
*Devonview Nursery
*Richard Stewart Nursery

====Private nursery schools====
*Croft Park Nursery
*First Class Nursery
*Grahamshill Private Day Nursery
*[http://www.heathparknursery.co.uk Heathpark Nursery]
*[http://www.steppingstonesnurseryschool.co.uk Steppeing Stones Nursery]
*[http://www.tinytotsacademy.co.uk Tiny Tots Academy]

===Special needs school===
*[[Mavisbank School and Nursery]]

==Volunteering==

[http://www.voluntaryactionnorthlanarkshire.org.uk Voluntary Action North Lanarkshire] (VANL) is headquartered in Airdrie.

It forms a single point of contact for information, advice and support for voluntary and community organisations, their staff and volunteers, and acts as a representative body for the voluntary and community sector. VANL also provides scheduled and bespoke training for staff and volunteers in a wide variety of areas, including finance, funding &amp; sustainability, governance, ICT, employability and personal development.

==Notable people==
*[[Bill Adam]] - Racing driver
*[[Ian Bannen]] - Actor
*[[John Craig (geologist)|John Craig]] - geologist and lexicographer
*[[Hugh de Largie]] - Australian politician
*[[The Big Dish (band)|The Big Dish]] - Pop/rock band
*[[Ryan Dalziel]] - Racing driver
*[[Ross Davidson]] - Actor
*[[Emily Gerard]] - Writer. Works inspired Bram Stoker's [[Dracula]] and coined the term [[Nosferatu]].
*[[John Graham, 1st Viscount of Dundee]] - also known as 'Bluidy Clavers' and 'Bonnie Dundee'. Royalist and [[Jacobitism|Jacobite]] soldier.
*[[Dee Hepburn]] - Actress. Most famous for her role in [[Gregory's Girl]].
*[[Jim Lambie]] - [[Turner Prize]] nominated artist.
*[[David Ross Lauder]] - Soldier and recipient of the [[Victoria Cross]].
*[[George G. Macfarlane|Sir George G. Macfarlane]], engineer, scientific administrator and public servant.
*[[John O'Neill (VC)|John O'Neill]] - Soldier and recipient of the [[Victoria Cross]].
*[[Jim Traynor]] - Sports broadcaster and journalist.
*[[George Ure]] - Actor/Singer. Star of [[West End theatre]] productions [[Wicked (musical)|Wicked]] and [[Hair (musical)|Hair]].
*[[Wilson Baronets|Sir John Wilson]] - [[Baronet]] (Wilson Baronetcy of Airdrie, which continues today with the 5th Baronet).
===Footballers===
Airdrie has produced more than its fair share of good footballers over the years.
*[[John Armstrong (footballer born 1936)|John Armstrong]]
*[[Barry Bannan]]
*[[Dick Black]]
*[[Gary Love]]
*[[George Brown (footballer born 1928)|George Brown]]
*[[Jackie Campbell]]
*[[Sandy Clark]]
*[[Bobby Cumming]]
*[[Torrance Gillick]]
*[[Dick Hendrie]]
*[[Drew Jarvie]] 
*[[Alan Lawrence]] - Nicknamed 'Nipper'.
*[[Brian McClair]]
*[[Bob McFarlane (footballer)|Bob McFarlane]]
*[[John McGregor (footballer born 1963)|John McGregor]]
*[[Ian McMillan (footballer)|Ian McMillan]]
*[[Robert Main (footballer)|Robert Main]]
*[[Alan Morton]] - Nicknamed 'The Wee Blue Devil'.
*[[Jimmy Smith (footballer born 1911)|Jimmy Smith]]
*[[Gardner Speirs]]
*[[James White (Scottish footballer)|James White]]
*[[Martin Woods]]
*[[Paul McGowan (footballer)|Paul McGowan]]
*[[Derek Riordan]]
*[[John Rankin]]

==Twinned Towns==

* {{flagicon|Canada}} [[Airdrie, Alberta|Airdrie]], [[Alberta]], [[Canada]]
* {{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Arnhem]], [[Netherlands]]
* {{flagicon|Falkland Islands}} [[Port Stanley]], [[Falkland Islands]]
* {{flagicon|Austria}} [[Salzburg]], [[Austria]]

==See also==
*[[Scottish Independence Party]] - headquartered in Airdrie
*[[List of places in North Lanarkshire]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*Begg, E. and Rich, D. (1991) ''On the Trail of Merlin''. ISBN 0-85030-939-5
*Geddes, C.M. (1995) ''Airdrie 300:A Souvenir Brochure''. Motherwell: Monklands Library Services. ISBN 0-946120-29-3
*Hutton, G. (1997) ''Lanarkshire's Mining Legacy''. Catrine: Stenlake Publishing. ISBN 1-84033-015-5
*McCutcheon, C. (1994) ''Old Airdrie''. Catrine: Stenlake Publishing. ISBN 1-872074-34-0
*Moir, H. (2001) ''Airdrie''. Stroud: Tempus Publishing Ltd. ISBN 0-7524-2368-1
*Scobbie, J.K. (1985) ''Book of Airdrie'''. Motherwell: Monklands Library Services. ISBN 0-946120-08-0
*Wilson, R. (1997) ''Old Airdrie Villages''. Catrine: Stenlake Publishing. ISBN 1-84033-004-X

==External links==
{{commons category}}
*[http://airdrie.merryston.co.uk/ Airdrie Museum]
*[http://www.airdriescotland.co.uk/ Airdrie Scotland Website]
*[http://www.monklands.com/ Local information portal]
*[http://airdrie.net/ Airdrie web page]
* '' 'Old-fashioned' Scottish bank shrugs off economic crisis'', Aljazeera English, 28 February 2009, [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4_dcCyUerI&amp;feature=ytn%3Amptnews ''YouTube''] (2 min).
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}
* [http://www.ainmean-aite.org/database.asp?intent=details&amp;id=462]

{{North Lanarkshire Settlements}}

[[Category:Airdrie, North Lanarkshire| ]]

[[da:Airdrie (Skotland)]]
[[de:Airdrie (North Lanarkshire)]]
[[fr:Airdrie (North Lanarkshire)]]
[[gd:Àrd Ruigh]]
[[it:Airdrie]]
[[lt:Erdris]]
[[nl:Airdrie (Schotland)]]
[[nn:Airdrie i North Lanarkshire]]
[[pt:Airdrie (Escócia)]]
[[sco:Airdrie]]
[[simple:Airdrie]]
[[uk:Ейрдрі]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
