<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6106350" ns="0" title="Floribella"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=June 2010}}
{{Unreferenced|date=April 2008}}
[[File:Juliana Silveira 2.jpg|thumb|right|250px]]
'''''Floribella''''' is a [[telenovela]] that was produced in [[Brazil]], [[Portugal]] and [[Chile]]. Each of those countries had their own cast, but the show had exactly the same name. Although they had the same name, all of them came from the first and original Argentine soap opera called ''[[Floricienta]]'', created by [[Cris Morena]].

==Plot==
''Floribella'' is based on the classic story, ''[[Cinderella]]''.

Flor is a pretty, young and poor girl who works for Frederico Fritzenwalden, who falls in love with Flor. However, Frederico is engaged with Delfina, who is a very mean and spoiled woman that fights against anything to marry the soonest possible Frederico and get his money.

But like in the fairy tales, the love always wins: Frederico finds out all the truth about Delfina, and all what she did to everyone. Unfortunately, in the very last week of the soap opera, Frederico dies (he dies differently in each country version), and with this ending, a new story starts with Flor and Conde Máximo Augusto, so this way, the second season of ''Floribella'' begins.

==Floribella Brazil==
[[Image:floribellabr.jpg|frame|Floribella, as portrayed in the Brazilian version by [[Juliana Silveira]]]]
''Floribella'' was aired on the [[Rede Bandeirantes]] Channel of Television. The first season started on the April 4th 2005 and ended on the November 21st 2005. The second season began on January 23, 2006 and ended on the August 28th 2006.

''Floribella Brazil'' released its first musical album during the first season, which went double platinum. Also released its first musical [[DVD]] which topped the DVD sales ranking.  Over 40 licensed products with the Floribella brand were released.

Later on, a second album was released (alongside the second season) which received [[Platinum]] certification according to ABPD. Four DVDs were also released: the first season, the second season, a TV special and the live musical.

A paperback novel, ''As Aventuras de Floribella'', was released and it stayed during months on the top of the best-selling children fiction list compiled by [[O Globo]] and [[Epoca]].

The cast also did a sold-out tour which included stops in several cities in [[Brazil]] from August to December 2006.

During the show, [[Juliana Silveira]], who portrayed ''Floribella'', fell in love with [[Roger Gobeth]], who portrayed her romantic interest Frederico. They're engaged and are still together as of June 2009.

===Music, Video, Book===
* CD FLORIBELLA (Floribella ''Album'') - 2005
* DVD FLORIBELLA AO VIVO (Floribella Live ''DVD'') - 2005
* CD FLORIBELLA 2 (Floribella 2nd Season ''Album'') - 2005
* CD DUPLO FLORIBELLA REMIXES &amp; KARAOKÊS (Floribella Remix &amp; Instrumental ''Double Album'')
* BOX FLORIBELLA PRIMEIRA TEMPORADA (Floribella First Season ''DVD BOX'')
* DVD FLORIBELLA: O ESPETÁCULO MUSICAL (Floribella: The Concert ''DVD'')
* LIVRO: AS AVENTURAS DE FLORIBELLA (''Book'': Floribella's Adventures)

==Portugal==
[[Image:floribella.jpg|thumb]]
The show was a huge phenomenon in [[Portugal]]. The show started discrete but after a few weeks it exceeded expectation and became one of the most-watched programs in the country. [[Luciana Abreu]] played the title role.

The first season soundtrack reached 10 times platinum and sold over 200.000 copies, becoming the best-selling album ever in [[Portugal]]. Over 100 licensed products were released and two sold-out tours were made.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.musica.iol.pt/noticia.php?div_id=3114&amp;id=903022&lt;/ref&gt;

The second season of the show could not reach the success of the first.

===Music===
* Floribella soundtrack&lt;ref&gt;[http://sic.sapo.pt/online/programas/floribella/musicas]&lt;/ref&gt; (2006)
* O Melhor Natal (Christmas soundtrack)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.floribella-online.site.vu/]&lt;/ref&gt; (2006)
* DVD &quot;Floribella Karaoke&quot; (2006)
* Floribella 2 (Soundtrack) (2007)
* DVD &quot;RI-FIXE - O Musical da Floribella&quot; (2007)
* DVD &quot;Floribella Karaoke 2&quot; (2007)
* Video game &quot;Floribella&quot; (2007)

==Chile==
In 2006 began the production of the [[Chile]]an version by [[Televisión Nacional de Chile|TVN]], premiering on October of the same year. It reached high levels of rating, defeating its counterpart by [[Canal 13 (Chile)|Canal 13]] ''Charly Tango''. The original name, &quot;Floricienta&quot;, couldn't be used because a private company had registered the trademark previously. It features actress [[Mariana Derderián]] on the role of Florencia and Cristián Arriagada on the role of Federico. It was the most-watched fictional program of 2007 but a second season was not comitioned since [[Televisión Nacional de Chile|TVN]] didn't want to kill the Prince, which was necessary for a second season to happen.

The CD achieved platinum certification.

==Links==
*[http://blogfloribella.weblog.com.pt Official Portuguese Floribella website ]
*[http://www.band.com.br/FLORIBELLA/ Official Brazilian Floribella website]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UYZ0-rmmQQc Opening of Floribella. Mix of three versions: Floribella Portugal, Floribella Brazil and Floricienta Argentina]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BpGFhI_KMYU Opening of the Chilean version]
*[http://teleseries.tvn.cl/floribella/ Official Website of the Chilean version]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:2005 telenovelas]]
[[Category:2005 television series endings]]
[[Category:2006 television series debuts]]
[[Category:Brazilian telenovelas]]
[[Category:Chilean telenovelas]]
[[Category:Portuguese telenovelas]]
[[Category:Portuguese-language telenovelas]]

[[es:Floribella]]
[[pt:Floribella]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
