<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="61114" ns="0" title="Boston University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox university
 |name              = Boston University
 |native_name       =
 |image_name        = Boston University seal.svg
 |image_size        = 200px
 |caption           = [[Seal (device)|Seal]] of Boston University
 |latin_name        = Universitas Bostoniensis
 |motto             = Learning, Virtue, Piety&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/campus-life/2007/09/16/origin-bus-motto-learning-virtue-piety |title=The origin of BU's motto: Learning, Virtue, Piety |publisher=BU Today |accessdate=2009-11-22 |date=2005-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |mottoeng          =
 |established       = 1839&lt;ref&gt;About BU page, with founding date http://www.bu.edu/info/about/&lt;/ref&gt;
 |closed            =
 |type              = [[Private university|Private]]
 |endowment         = US$ 1.194 billion&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/cfo/files/2011/10/Boston-University-Financial-Statement-for-2011.pdf         |title=Boston University Financial Statements June 30, 2011 and 2010|publisher=Boston University |accessdate=November 2, 2011 |date=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge =
 |president         = [[Robert A. Brown]]
 |vice-president    =
 |provost           = Jean Morrison
 |head_label        =
 |head              =
 |faculty           = 3,931
 |staff             = 7,410 (including faculty)
 |students          = 31,766
 |undergrad         = 18,534
 |postgrad          = 13,232
 |doctoral          =
 |city              = Boston
 |state             = [[Massachusetts]]
 |country           = United States
 |campus            = Urban
 |former_names      =
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            =
 |colors            = scarlet and white&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/dbin/infocenter/content/index.php?pageid=873 |title=Boston University Information Center – Quick Facts |accessdate=2009-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 {{colorbox|#CC0000}}{{colorbox|#FFFFFF}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.bu.edu/brand/logo/colors/ |title=Boston University Brand Identity Standards – Master Logo Colors – Boston University Red |accessdate=2009-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |nickname          = [[Boston University Terriers|Terriers]]
 |mascot            = [[Rhett the Boston Terrier|Rhett]] the [[Boston Terrier]]
 |athletics         = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
 |affiliations      = [[New England Association of Schools and Colleges]], [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business]]
 |website           = [http://www.bu.edu/ bu.edu]
 |publictransit     = [[Boston University Central (MBTA station)|BU Central MBTA station]], [[Boston University East (MBTA station)|BU East MBTA station]], [[Boston University West (MBTA station)|BU West MBTA station]]
 |logo              = [[File:Boston University Wordmark.svg|200px]]
 |footnotes         =
}}

'''Boston University''' ('''BU''') is a [[Private university|private]] research university located in Boston, Massachusetts. With more than 4,000 faculty members and more than 31,000 students, Boston University is one of the [[List of largest United States university campuses by enrollment|largest private universities in the United States]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.bu.edu/bulletins/und/item02.html|title=Boston University Undergraduate Bulletin 2009/2010 – The University|accessdate=2009-11-22|date=2009-10-16|publisher=Trustees of Boston University|location=One Silber Way, Boston, MA 02215|quote=Boston University, the fourth-largest independent university in the United States [...] With more than 4,000 faculty members and more than 32,000 students...}}&lt;/ref&gt; and one of Boston's largest employers.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;{{cite web| url=http://www.bostonredevelopmentauthority.org/PDF/ResearchPublications//Boston%20Economy%202008.pdf|title=The Boston Economy 2008 Holding Strong|accessdate=2009-11-22|year=2008|month=September|publisher=Boston Redevelopment Authority – Research Division|page=16|quote=Largest Private Employers in Boston, April, 2006 (With 1,000+ employees, listed alphabetically)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university is [[nonsectarian]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Nonsectarian1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.bu.edu/nisprod/coursedesc/data/archives/200709251128/www.bu.edu/bulletins/cfa/item02.html| title = The College of Fine Arts Introduction|publisher = Boston University|quote=Boston University is coeducational and nonsectarian.|accessdate = 2007-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; but is historically affiliated with [[The United Methodist Church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Boston University - Religious Affiliation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.bu.edu/phpbin/news/releases/display.php?id=381| title = Boston University Names University Professor Herbert Mason United Methodist Scholar/Teacher of the Year|quote=Boston University has been historically affiliated with the United Methodist Church since 1839 when the Newbury Biblical Institute, the first Methodist seminary in the United States was established in Newbury, Vermont.|publisher = Boston University|year=2001|=accessdate = October 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GBHEM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.gbhem.org/atf/cf/%7B0bcef929-bdba-4aa0-968f-d1986a8eef80%7D/EDUC_CEODIRECTORY.PDF| title = United Methodist-Related Schools, Colleges, Universities, and Theological Schools|quote=Boston University&lt;br&gt;
One Silber Way, 8th Floor&lt;br&gt;
Boston, MA 02215&lt;br&gt;
Robert A. Brown&lt;br&gt;
President&lt;br&gt;
(617) 353-2200&lt;br&gt;
fax: (617) 353-3278&lt;br&gt;
e-mail: rabrown@bu.edu|publisher = General Board of Higher Education &amp; Ministry |page=9|=accessdate = October 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

BU is categorized as an RU/VH Research University (very high research activity) in the Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie Foundation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/index.asp?key=63&amp;search_flag=true&amp;ref=783&amp;start=783&amp;BASIC2005=15 |title=Carnegie Foundation |publisher=Carnegie Foundation |date=May 10, 2007 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009–2010, BU had research expenditures of $407.8 million, or $553 million if the research led by the Medical School faculty at Boston Medical Center is included.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/president/letters-writings/letters/2010/10-4/ |title=State of the University |publisher=Boston University |date=October 5, 2010 |accessdate=October 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; BU is a member of the Boston Consortium for Higher Education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boston-consortium.org/about/what_is_tbc.asp |title=The Boston Consortium |publisher=The Boston Consortium |accessdate=2010-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among its faculty and alumni, BU counts 6 Nobel Prize winners, including [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] (PhD '55); 22 [[Pulitzer Prize]] winners, and numerous{{Quantify|date=May 2010}} [[Guggenheim fellowship|Guggenheim]] and [[MacArthur Fellows Program|MacArthur]] fellows.

The university offers [[bachelor's degree]]s, master's degrees, and [[doctoral degree]]s, and medical and dental degrees through 18 schools and colleges on two urban campuses. The main campus is situated along the [[Charles River]] in Boston's [[Fenway-Kenmore]] and [[Allston, Massachusetts|Allston]] neighborhoods, while the [[Boston University Medical Campus]] is in Boston's [[South End]] neighborhood. BU also operates 75 [[study abroad]] programs in over 33 cities in over 20 countries and has internship opportunities in 10 different countries (including the United States and abroad).

The [[Boston University Terriers]] compete in the [[NCAA]]'s [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]. BU athletic teams compete in the [[America East]], [[Hockey East]], and [[Colonial Athletic Association]] conferences, and their mascot is Rhett the Boston Terrier. Boston University is well known for men's hockey, in which it has won five national championships, most recently in 2009.

==History==
{{toolong|section|date=February 2011}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right;&quot;
|+Presidents of Boston University
|-
|[[William Fairfield Warren]] || 1873–1903
|-
|[[William Edwards Huntington|William E. Huntington]] || 1904–1911
|-
|Lemuel H. Murlin || 1911–1924
|-
|&lt;font size=1&gt;[[Edwin Holt Hughes]] (acting) || |&lt;font size=1&gt;May–Sep 1923&lt;/font&gt;
|-
||&lt;font size=1&gt;William F. Anderson (acting) || |&lt;font size=1&gt;1925–1926
|-
|Daniel L. Marsh || 1926–1950
|-
|Harold C. Case || 1950–1967
|-
|Arland Christ-Janer || 1967–1970
|-
||&lt;font size=1&gt;Calvin B.T. Lee (acting) || |&lt;font size=1&gt;1970
|-
|[[John Silber]] || 1971–1996
|-
|[[Jon Westling]] || 1996–2003
|-
|[[John Silber]] || 2003–2004
|-
|[[Aram Chobanian]] || 2004–2006
|-
|[[Robert A. Brown]] || 2006 – present
|}

===Predecessor institutions and University Charter===
Boston University traces its roots to the establishment of the Newbury Biblical Institute in [[Newbury (town), Vermont|Newbury, Vermont]] in 1839, and was chartered with the name &quot;Boston University&quot; by the Massachusetts Legislature in 1869.  The University organized formal Centennial observances both in 1939 and 1969.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/visit/about/history/index.html Boston University | Visitor Center | About the University |History], retrieved May 6, 2006 {{Wayback | url=http://www.bu.edu/visit/about/history/index.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; | date=20060216154448 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 24–25, 1839 a group of [[Methodist]] ministers and laymen at the Old Bromfield Street Church in Boston elected to establish a Methodist theological school.  Set up in Newbury, Vermont, the school was named the Newbury Biblical Institute.

In 1847, the [[Congregational church|Congregational]] Society in [[Concord, New Hampshire]], invited the Institute to relocate to Concord and made available a disused Congregational church building with a capacity of 1200 people. Other citizens of Concord covered the remodeling costs. One stipulation of the invitation was that the Institute remain in Concord for at least 20 years. The charter issued by [[New Hampshire]] designated the school the &quot;Methodist General Biblical Institute&quot;, but it was commonly called the &quot;Concord Biblical Institute.&quot;

With the agreed twenty years coming to a close, the Trustees of the Concord Biblical Institute purchased {{convert|30|acre|m2}} on Aspinwall Hill in Brookline, Massachusetts as a possible relocation site. The Institute moved in 1867 to 23 Pinkney Street in Boston and received a Massachusetts Charter as the &quot;Boston Theological Institute.&quot;

In 1869, three Trustees of the Boston Theological Institute obtained from the Massachusetts Legislature a charter for a university by name of &quot;Boston University.&quot; These three were successful Boston businessmen and Methodist laymen, with a history of involvement in educational enterprises and became the Founders of Boston University. They were [[Isaac Rich]] (1801–1872), [[Lee Claflin]] (1791–1871), and [[Jacob Sleeper]] (1802–1889), for whom Boston University's three [[West Campus]] dormitories are named. Lee Claflin's son, [[William Claflin|William]], was then Governor of Massachusetts and signed the University Charter on May 26, 1869 after it was passed by the Legislature.

As reported by Kathleen Kilgore in her book, &quot;Transformations, A History of Boston University&quot; (see [[Boston University#Further reading|Further Reading]]), the Founders directed the inclusion in the Charter of the following provision, unusual for its time:

:No instructor in said University shall ever be required by the Trustees to profess any particular religious opinions as a test of office, and no student shall be refused admission . . . on account of the religious opinions he may entertain; provided, nonetheless, that this section shall not apply to the theological department of said University.

Every department of the new university was also open to all on an equal footing regardless of sex, race, or (with the exception of the School of Theology) religion.

===Early years (1870–1900)===
The Boston Theological Institute was absorbed into Boston University in 1871 as the [[Boston University School of Theology|BU School of Theology]].

In January 1872 Isaac Rich died, leaving the vast bulk of his estate to a trust that would go to Boston University after ten years of growth while the University was organized. Most of this bequest consisted of real estate throughout the core of the city of Boston and was appraised at more than $1.5 million. Kilgore describes this as the largest single donation to an American college or university to that time.

By December, the [[Great Boston Fire of 1872]] had destroyed all but one of the buildings Rich had left to the University, and the insurance companies with which they had been insured were bankrupt. The value of his estate, when turned over to the University in 1882, was half what it had been in 1872. As a result, the University was unable to build its contemplated campus on Aspinwall Hill and the land was sold piecemeal as development sites. Street names in the area, including Claflin Road, Claflin Path, and University Road, are the only remaining evidence of University ownership in this area.

Boston University established its facilities in buildings scattered through the less fashionable parts of Beacon Hill, and later expanded into the Boylston Street and [[Copley Square]] area before building the Charles River Campus after 1937.

===20th century and establishment of the Charles River campus===
[[Image:Marsh Chapel.jpg|right|300px|thumb|Marsh Plaza and its surrounding buildings were one of the first completed parts of the Charles River Campus.]]
Seeking to unify a geographically scattered school and enable it to participate in the development of the city, school president Lemuel Murlin arranged that the school buy the present campus along the [[Charles River]].  Between 1920 and 1928, the school bought the {{convert|15|acre|m2}} of land that had been reclaimed from the river by the Riverfront Improvement Association.  Plans for a riverside quadrangle with a multistory administrative tower modeled on the &quot;Old Boston Stump&quot; in [[Boston, Lincolnshire|Boston]], England were scaled back in the late 1920s when the State Metropolitan District Commission used [[eminent domain]] to seize riverfront land for [[Storrow Drive]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/visit/about/history/betweenwars.html|title=Between World Wars|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=2008-04-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071212022404/http://www.bu.edu/visit/about/history/betweenwars.html |archivedate = December 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Through a series of fundraising campaigns by Murlin, the school slowly filled in its new campus. By spring 1936, the student body included 10,384 men and women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70C1EFF3D5E167B93C0A8178FD85F428385F9&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=10.384+are+enrolled+at+B.U.&amp;st=p &quot;10.384 are enrolled at B.U.&quot;], ''The New York Times''. April 12, 1936. p. N7.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951, Harold Case became the school's fifth president and under his direction the character of the campus changed dramatically, as he sought to transform the school into a national research university. The campus tripled in size to {{convert|45|acre|m2}}, and added 68 new buildings before Case retired in 1967. The first large dorms, Claflin, Rich and Sleeper Halls in [[West Campus]] were built, and in 1965 construction began on 700 Commonwealth Avenue, later named [[Warren Towers]], designed to house 1800 students. Between 1961 and 1966, the [[Boston University School of Law|BU Law Tower]], the [[George Sherman Union]], and the [[Mugar Memorial Library]] were constructed in the [[Brutalist architecture|Brutalist]] style, a departure from the school's traditional architecture. The College of Engineering and [[Boston University College of Communication|College of Communication]] were housed in a former stable building and auto-show room, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.dailyfreepress.com/media/storage/paper87/news/2006/10/17/News/Activism.Dorm.Construction.Pervade.Campus.In.1950s60s-2371894.shtml|publisher=The Daily Free Press|author=Alex Taylor|accessdate=2008-04-27|title=Activism, dorm construction pervade campus in 1950s–60s}}&lt;/ref&gt; Besides his efforts to expand the sleepy riverside university into a rival for Greater Boston's more prestigious academic institutions, such as Harvard University and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (both in Cambridge across the Charles River from the B.U. campus), Case involved himself in the start of the student/societal upheavals that came to charazcterize the 1960s. When a minisquabble over editorial policy at [[College radio]] WBUR-FM – whose offices were under a tall radio antenna mast in front of the School of Public Relations and Communications (later College of Communications) – started growing in the spring  of 1964, Case persuaded university trustees that the university should take over the widely heard radio station (now a major outlet for National Public Radio and still a B.U.-owned broadcast facility). The trustees okayed the firing of the student managers and clamped down on programming and editorial policy, which had been led by the late Jim Thistle, later a major force in Boston's broadcast news milieu. The oncampus political dispute between Case's conservative administration and the suddenly active and mostly liberal student body led to other disputes over B.U. student print publications, such as the B.U. News and the Scarlet, a fraternity association newspaper.

The Presidency of John Silber also saw much expansion.  In the late 1970s, the [[Lahey Clinic]] vacated its building at 605 Commonwealth Avenue and moved to [[Burlington, Massachusetts]].  The vacated building was purchased by BU to house the [[Boston University School of Education|School of Education]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lahey.org/About/LaheyHistory.asp|publisher=The Lahey Clinic|accessdate=2009-12-28|title=Lahey History}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Then in the late 90s, concerns over lack of a &quot;campusy&quot; feel and the physical divide between the east and the western portion of campus triggered another wave of development.  The [[John Hancock Student Village]] or StuVi was constructed with the intent of unifying the two campuses. This facility includes a new [[Fitness and Recreation Center]] (FitRec), a [[Agganis Arena|large multipurpose arena]], and three new dormitories, one of which opened in 2000, the other two were finished by fall of 2009, including a 26-story new tallest on-campus building (left).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/president/planning/ |title=Boston University Office of the President |publisher=Bu.edu |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 19 and 26-story towers, known as StuV-II, house another 960 students, and have made possible the guarantee of on-campus housing to the 80% of its 16,000 undergrads who opt for it, without shunting overflow into nearby hotels as was the practice in past years.&lt;ref name=globearticle&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2009/09/02/bu_dorm_offers_a_study_in_luxury/?page=1 |title=BU dorm offers a study in luxury – The Boston Globe |work=Boston Globe  |date=2009-09-02 |accessdate=2010-05-31 | first=Tracy | last=Jan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to the John Hancock Student Village, other projects were also completed under Silber.  These projects range from the construction of the Photonics Center for the study of light, to the construction of the Life Science and Engineering Building for interdisciplinary research,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/bridge/archive/2005/04-29/lse.html|title=Life Science and Engineering building: “cathedral to science”|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the renovation of 928 Commonwealth Ave in order to create a permanent home for the School of Hospitality Administration (SHA), were complete under Silber.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/node/1843|title=SHA ready to move|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The 21st century===
[[Image:Stuvi.JPG|thumb|right|300px|The three 1960s dorms of [[West Campus]] on the right are dwarfed by the 26-story tower of 2009, one of three dorms in StuVi.]]Dr. Robert Brown's presidency, which started in 2005, will seek to further the consolidation of campus infrastructure that was commenced by Case and continued by Silber.  In particular, Brown has committed Boston University to investing $1.8 billion in the fulfillment of its 10-year strategic plan, devoting new resources to unlocking cross-college opportunities for undergraduates, improving the campus’s academic and residential facilities, and recruiting new faculty for the University’s largest college.  The strategy, titled &quot;Choosing to Be Great,&quot; sets goals to be carried out over the next decade, and calls for increasing annual expenditures of up to $225 million for support of the plan’s major goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/president/strategic-plan/|title=BU Strategic Plan|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The cornerstone of the plan, which calls for more campuswide collaboration, is a focus on undergraduate education, starting with an effort to encourage cross-registration among schools and colleges and to encourage undergraduate students to take full advantage of both the liberal arts and the professional programs available. In an attempt to strengthen the liberal arts, the College of Arts and Sciences and the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences are slated to hire 100 new tenure-track faculty members over the next decade.  In addition, interdisciplinary research that spans traditional branches of study has also been identified as a current strength with room for growth.  Andrei Ruckenstein, a CAS professor of physics and the newly appointed associate provost and vice president of research, is working with the faculty to identify BU’s current strengths in cross-disciplinary research and to drive the hiring of up to 30 new faculty members to help grow these activities across the University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/node/5671|title=President Launches $1.8 Billion Strategic Initiatives|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several of the University’s professional schools have also been targeted as current strengths and candidates for growth. The School of Management will hire 20 new faculty.  The School of Law will begin its capital campaign for an expanded and fully renovated facility, with a dollar-for-dollar match in funding from the University. The College of Fine Arts, long recognized for integrating its undergraduate and graduate programs with respected arts institutions throughout greater Boston, also has plans for facilities renovation and expansion, with the same financial commitment from the University.

The School of Medicine also is poised for growth. Already with a national reputation in medical education, clinical practice, and research, the school is moving to expand its research efforts, especially in select areas of emphasis. The School of Medicine will also devote substantial resources towards facilities renovation and the development of more affordable student housing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/2008/04/28/med-buys-site-future-student-housing|title=MED Buys Site of Future Student Housing|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initiatives focusing on life outside the classroom are considered key to the plan’s success, and efforts to engage both current students and alumni have already begun. The ongoing construction of the Student Village 2 residence hall is part of a long-range expansion campaign that includes renovations to housing, recreational facilities, and dining halls and a focus on leveraging this commitment to strengthen the campus community.  In order to accommodate this physical expansion, Boston University has declared intentions to procure [[air rights]] over the [[Massachusetts Turnpike|Mass Pike]]. In addition to freeing up land, it's hoped the move will unify the Charles River area with South Campus, as well as bring width to a long narrow campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.dailyfreepress.com/media/storage/paper87/news/2008/05/01/News/Bu.Says.Campus.Future.Is.Up.In.The.Air-3361027.shtml BU says campus future is up in the air – News]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initiatives intended to carry out the plan have already begun.  In the Fall of 2009, in the midst of the financial crisis, $2.5 million revamp of BU's computer services took place.  The initiative involved a complete renovation of Mugar Library’s first floor, the purchase of 200 energy-efficient ThinClient workstations, and the relocation of the computer lab and IT Help Center from 111 Cummington St.  Several thousand books were moved to make way for the computer clusters, a shift that reflects changes in the way students and faculty use and exchange information, says Hudson. This new hub of study and interaction on campus, aptly named BU Common @ Mugar, includes an IT Help Center that occupies the wall that formerly displayed books by BU authors, as well as a reference desk, where students can seek professional help.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/2009/09/03/mugar-fitrec-mind|title=At Mugar, “a FitRec for the Mind”|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition, 888 Commonwealth Ave. has become Boston University’s first geothermal building.  It currently houses the Kidney Center, the University’s Center for English Language and Orientation Programs classrooms, the International Programs offices, and several retail shops and restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/2009/01/13/bu-goes-center-earth|title=BU Goes to the Center of the Earth|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Last but not least, the University is planning to build a six-story, {{convert|106000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} structure housing state-of-the-art dining services and a new home for an expanded Career Services Center and the Educational Resource Center (ERC), as well as the Writing Program, Freshman Advising, and Professional Advising offices from the College of Arts &amp; Sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/president/letters-writings/letters/2010/5-7/|title=Letter: University Update, May 7, 2010|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Construction of the estimated $50 million East Campus Center for Student Services began in Fall 2010, with an opening date set for fall 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/node/10918|title=Student Center Coming to East Campus|publisher=Boston University|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
===Boston campuses and facilities===
[[Image:bu beach.jpg|right|thumb|The &quot;BU Beach&quot;, located behind Marsh Plaza and the College of Arts and Sciences building, is a popular warm weather gathering place between the Charles River Campus and [[Storrow Drive]].]]

The University's main Charles River Campus follows [[Commonwealth Avenue (Boston)|Commonwealth Avenue]] and the [[Green Line (MBTA)#B Line|Green Line]], beginning near [[Kenmore Square]] and continuing for over a mile and a half to its end near the border of Boston's [[Allston, Massachusetts|Allston]] neighborhood. The [[Boston University Bridge]] over the [[Charles River]] into [[Cambridge, Massachusetts|Cambridge]] represents the dividing line between '''Main Campus''', where most schools and classroom buildings are concentrated, and '''[[West Campus]]''', home to several athletic facilities and playing fields, the large West Campus dorm, and the new John Hancock Student Village complex.

[[Image:BU Law Tower.JPG|thumb|left|The School of Law Tower, made in [[Brutalism|Brutalist]] styling, is the tallest academic building on campus.|180px]]As a result of its continual expansion, the Charles River campus contains an array of architecturally diverse buildings. The College of Arts and Sciences, Marsh Chapel (site of the [[Marsh Chapel Experiment]]), and the School of Theology buildings are the university's most recognizable and were built in the late-1930s and 1940s in collegiate gothic style. A sizable amount of the campus is traditional Boston brownstone, especially at [[Bay State Road]] and South Campus where BU has acquired almost every townhouse those areas offer. The buildings are primarily dormitories but many also serve as various institutes as well as department offices. From the 1960s–1980s many contemporary buildings were constructed including the Mugar Library, BU Law School and Warren Towers, all of which were built in the [[brutalist architecture|brutalist]] style of architecture. The [[Metcalf Science Center for Science and Engineering]], constructed in 1983, might more accurately be described as [[Structural Expressionism]]. [[Morse Auditorium]], adjacent, stands in stark architectrual contrast, as it was constructed as a Jewish temple. The most recent additions to BU's campus are the [[Boston University Photonics Center|Photonics Center]], Life Science and Engineering Building, The Student Village (which includes the [[Fitness and Recreation Center|FitRec Center]] and [[Agganis Arena]]), and the [[Boston University School of Management|School of Management]]. All these buildings were built in brick, a few with a substantial amount of brownstone.

====Student housing====
[[Image:WarrenTowersOverCharles.jpg|thumb|250px|Rising over the [[Charles River]], [[Warren Towers]] constitutes the second-largest non-military dorm in the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/bridge/archive/1999/02-19/yesterday.html BU Bridge] Vol II No. February 24, 19 1998 &quot;BU Yesterday: Third time's the dorm&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;]]

{{Main|Boston University Housing System}}

Boston University's housing system is the nation's 10th largest among four year colleges. BU was originally a commuter school, but the university now guarantees the option of on-campus housing for four years for all undergraduate students. Currently, 76% of the undergraduate population lives on campus. Boston University requires that all students living in dormitories be enrolled in a year-long meal plan with several combinations of meals and dining points which can be used as cash in on-campus facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;diningplanrequired&quot;&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/housing/dining/plans/index.html Boston University | Office of Housing | Dining Plans and Convenience Points|Dining Plans], retrieved May 6, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Housing at BU is an unusually diverse melange, ranging from individual 19th-century [[brownstone]] [[town house]]s and apartment buildings acquired by the school to large-scale high-rises built in the 60s and 2000s. 

The large dormitories include the 1800-student [[Warren Towers]], the largest on campus, as well as West Campus and [[Towers (Boston University)|The Towers]].  The smaller dormitory and apartment style housing are mainly located in two parts of campus: Bay State Road and the South Campus residential area. Bay State Road is a tree-lined street that runs parallel to Commonwealth Avenue and is home to the majority of BUs town houses, often called &quot;brownstones&quot;. South Campus is a student residential area south of Commonwealth Avenue and separated from the main campus by the [[Massachusetts Turnpike]]. Some of the larger buildings in that area have been converted into dormitories, while the rest of the South Campus buildings are apartments.

[[Image:Myles Standish Hall.jpg|thumb|left|Built in 1925 as [[Myles Standish]] Hotel, BU acquired and converted the building to dorm space in 1949.]]Boston University's newest residence and principal apartment-style housing area is officially called 33 Harry Agganis Way, StuVi2 unofficially, and is part of The John Hancock Student Village project. The north facing, 26 story building are apartment style while the south facing, 19 story building are in a 8-bedroom dormitory style suite. Total, the building houses 960 resident.

Aside from these main residential areas, smaller residential dormitories are scattered along Commonwealth Avenue.

Boston University also provides [[Boston University Housing System#Specialty housing|specialty houses]] or specialty floors to students who have particular interests.

All large dormitories have 24/7 security and require all students to swipe and show their school identification before entering.

At least one dorm, [[Shelton Hall (Boston University)|Shelton Hall]], is rumored to be haunted by the ghost of playwright [[Eugene O'Neill]]. O'Neill lived in what was originally room 401 (now 419) while the building was a residential hotel. He died in a hospital on November 27, 1953, and his ghost is rumored to haunt both the room and the floor. The fourth floor is now a specialty floor called the Writers' Corridor.

====John Hancock Student Village====
[[File:Student Village II at Boston University.jpg|thumb|Student Village II with Student Village I in the background, as viewed from Nickerson Field]]
{{Main|John Hancock Student Village}}
The Student Village is a large new residential and recreational complex covering {{convert|10|acre|m2}} between Buick Street and [[Nickerson Field]], ground formerly occupied by a [[United States National Guard|National Guard]] [[Armory (military)|Armory]], which had been used by the University for indoor track and field and as a storage facility before its [[demolition]] and the start of construction. The Student Village was designed with the intention of fostering community and bridging the divide between the eastern and western portions of campus. The dormitory of apartment suites at 10 Buick Street (often abbreviated to &quot;StuVi&quot; by students) opened to juniors and seniors in the fall of 2000. In 2002, [[John Hancock Insurance]] announced its sponsorship of the multi-million dollar project. In 2009, Student Village II, the 26 story luxury dorm opened at 33 Harry Agganis Way. 

The [[Agganis Arena]], named after [[Harry Agganis]], was opened to concerts and [[ice hockey|hockey]] games in January 2005. The Agganis Arena is capable of housing 6,224 spectators for [[Boston University athletics#Terrier Hockey|Terrier hockey]] games, replacing the smaller [[Walter Brown Arena]]. It can also be used for concerts and shows. In March 2005, the final element of phase II of the Student Village complex, the [[Fitness and Recreation Center|Fitness and Recreation (FitRec) Center]], was opened, drawing large crowds from the student body.  Construction on the rest of phase II, which included 19- and 26-story residential towers was finished in fall 2009.

====Other facilities====
[[Image:Mugar Memorial Library Exterior.jpg|220px|thumb|[[Mugar Memorial Library]] is BU's primary library|right]]
The [[Mugar Memorial Library]] is the central academic library for the Charles River Campus.  It also houses the Howard Gotlieb Archival Research Center, formerly called the Twentieth Century Archive, where documents belonging to thousands of eminent figures in literature, journalism, diplomacy, the arts, and other fields are housed. Among them are [[Isaac Asimov]]'s personal papers from 1965 onward, documents from distinguished alumnus [[Martin Luther King Jr]], and the recent addition of Mary Louise Parker's personal papers.

The [[George Sherman Union]] (GSU) located next to Mugar Memorial Library provides students with an expansive food court featuring many popular fast-food chains, including [[Panda Express]] (which opened Fall 2006), [[Starbucks]] and [[Jamba Juice]]. The GSU also provides comfortable lounge areas in which to study. The basement of the George Sherman Union is home to the BU Central lounge, which hosts concerts and other activities and events. There is also a [[United States Post Office]] in the basement of the GSU.

[[Image:BUCastle.jpg|left|thumb|200px|&quot;The Castle&quot; located on Bay State Road.]] [[BU Castle|&quot;The Castle&quot;]] located on the West end of Bay State Road is one of the older buildings on campus, and one with an interesting, if not exactly accurate, history. According to lore, the castle was built by millionaire William Lindsay for his daughter Leslie Lindsey Mason as her wedding gift. However, she was killed when her ship, the ''[[RMS Lusitania]]'', was torpedoed and sunk by German submarines on May 7, 1915. In fact the building was commissioned by William Lindsay for his own use in 1905, long before his daughter's honeymoon on the Lusitania.&lt;ref name=&quot;BFH-BBay&quot;&gt;[http://www.bostonfamilyhistory.com/neigh_bbay.html 403 Forbidden] accessed May 8, 2006 {{Wayback | url=http://www.bostonfamilyhistory.com/neigh_bbay.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; | date=20060303034655 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1939, the University acquired the property by agreement with the city to repay all back taxes owed; these funds were raised through donations from, among others, Dr. William Chenery, a University Trustee.&lt;ref name=&quot;castle_aquisition&quot;&gt;Salzman, Nancy Lurie. Buildings and builders : a history of Boston University. Boston : Boston University Press, 1985. (ISBN 0-87270-056-9)&lt;/ref&gt; It served as the residence of the University president until 1967, when President Christ-Janer found it too large for his needs as a residence and turned it to other uses.  It is now a conference space. Underneath the Castle is the [[BU Castle#BU Pub|BU Pub]], the only BU-operated drinking establishment on campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.dailyfreepress.com/media/storage/paper87/news/2004/04/21/News/Permanent.Daylight.Bu.Pub.Offers.College.Experience-666574.shtml BU Pub offers college experience]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parts of the 2008 film [[21 (2008 film)|21]] were filmed at The Castle after undisclosed legal reasons prevented [[Robert Luketic]] from filming at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]]. Other areas around the Boston University campus, including BU's School of Management, Mugar Library and FitRec, also provided production locations for the film.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.dailyfreepress.com/media/storage/paper87/news/2007/02/27/News/Actor.Producer.Spacey.Brings.Filming.To.Bu.Castle-2745647.shtml Dailey Free Press], February 27, 2007 ''Actor, producer Spacey brings filming to BU Castle''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Boston University School of Education]] located at 605 Commonwealth Avenue is housed in the original location of the [[Lahey Clinic]]. It was the merger of two pre-existing buildings, which explains its half floors (3½, 4½, 5½, etc.).

The recently opened Florence and Chafetz Hillel House on Bay State Road is the Hillel facility for the university. With four floors and a basement, the facility includes lounges, study rooms and a kosher dining hall, open during the academic year (including Passover) to students and walk-ins from the community. The first floor also includes the Granby St.Cafe as well as TV's and ping-pong, pool and foosball tables. The Hillel serves as a focal point for BU's large and active Jewish community. It hosts approximately 30 student groups, including social, cultural and religious groups and BU Students for Israel (BUSI), Holocaust Education and the Center for Jewish Learning and Experience. It hosts a plethora of programs and speakers as well as Friday and Saturday shabbat services and meals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/hillel Hillel House] web site&lt;/ref&gt;

Weld House, the office of the president of Boston University, is the former home of [[Charles Goddard Weld]], a member of the wealthy [[Weld family]] of Massachusetts.  The adjoining Dunn House contains the Office of the Chancellor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.harvardmag.com/nd98/welds.html ''Harvard Alumni Magazine''], &quot;The Welds of Harvard Yard&quot; by associate editor Craig A. Lambert&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Barnes and Noble]] at Boston University is the university's bookstore, which is located on Kenmore Square. Consisting of five floors the bookstore holds all BU students' needs ranging from books to clothes to coffee. Materials for others schools such as the Boston Architecture Center are also sold through the store.

====Cultural life====
Located at the junction of [[Fenway-Kenmore]], [[Allston]], and [[Brookline, Massachusetts|Brookline]], the university has long enjoyed these neighborhood's cultural offerings. In the Fenway-Kenmore area are the [[Museum of Fine Arts, Boston|Museum of Fine Arts]], the [[Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum]], and Landsdowne Street. Allston has been Boston's largest bohemian neighborhood since the 1960s. Nicknamed &quot;Allston Rock City,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boston.com/ae/music/articles/2004/08/27/rock_city_revival/ |title='&amp;#39;Boston Globe'&amp;#39;, &quot;Rock City revival&quot;, August 27, 2004 |work=Boston Globe  |date=August 27, 2004 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the neighborhood is home to many artists and musicians, as well as a variety of cafés, and many of Boston's small music halls. Beyond the southern border of the campus in Brookline, Harvard Avenue offers independent and foreign films at Coolidge Corner Theatre, and readings by esteemed authors at the Brookline Booksmith. Other local destinations for campus intellectuals and culture lovers include Symphony Hall, the Beacon Book Annex, Jordan Hall, the main branch of the Boston Public Library in Copley Square, the art and commerce of Newbury Street, and, across the river, the museums, shops, and galleries in Harvard Square and elsewhere in Cambridge. The combined proximity of so many cultural institutions, colleges, public spaces, and performance outlets, with the University's own College of Fine Arts, College of Communication, University Professors Program, and other on-campus sources for cultural energy, has enabled BU to cultivate a thriving creative community. The George Sherman Student Union on Commonwealth Avenue hosts concerts and performers at &quot;BU Central&quot; and Metcalf Hall. There are 12 A'Capella groups on campus. The two most notable being the co-ed group The BosTones and the all male group the Dear Abbeys. Both have performed at numerous events around campus. BU is home to the [http://www.huntingtontheatre.org/index.aspx Huntington Theatre Company] at the BU Theatre as well as [[Boston Playwrights' Theatre]], and hosts campus and non-campus performances in the Tsai Performance Center.  Visiting artists' work are displayed in rotating exhibitions in the University's three galleries.

====Guest and visitor policies====
Prior to September 2007, Boston University had a rather restrictive visitor policy, which limited the ability of students from different dormitories to visit each other at night. This changed when a new policy approved by Brown took effect.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/phpbin/news-cms/news/?dept=4&amp;id=44920&amp;template=4 &quot;President Approves New Guest Policy&quot; ~ ''BU Today''] May 7, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  The new policy allows for students living on campus to swipe into any on-campus dormitory between the hours of 7&amp;nbsp;am and 2&amp;nbsp;am using their ID cards  Student residents can also sign in guests with photo identification at any time, day or night.  Overnight visitors of the opposite sex are no longer required to seek a same-sex &quot;co-host&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/phpbin/news-cms/news/?dept=4&amp;id=43755&amp;template=4&amp;from_email=true &quot;New Guest Policy Means More Power, More Responsibility&quot; ~ ''BU Today''] March 2, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; However during the week before final exams no guests are permitted in the halls overnight, and are expected to be out of the hall by 2&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/dos/documents/GuestPolicy22807.pdf BU Guest Policy]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Accessing Boston University====
[[Image:BUcampustrolley.JPG|thumb|right|The Campus Trolley food truck on the corner of Granby Street and Commonwealth Avenue. The BU College of Arts and Sciences building is visible in the background]]

Most of the buildings of the main campus are located on or near Commonwealth Avenue. The Kenmore Square area of campus (including the Boston University Bookstore, Shelton Hall and Myles Standish Hall) may be accessed using the Kenmore Station Stop on the [[Massachusetts Bay Transportation Authority|MBTA]] Green Line [[Green Line &quot;B&quot; Branch|B]], [[Green Line &quot;C&quot; Branch|C]] and [[Green Line &quot;D&quot; Branch|D]] trains. Most of the rest of the main campus may be accessed using the B trains of the Green Line between the [[Blandford Street (MBTA station)|Blandford Street]] and [[Babcock Street (MBTA station)|Babcock Street]] stops.  The 57 Bus runs along Commonwealth Avenue and into Allston and Brighton. The [[MBTA Commuter Rail]] [[Framingham/Worcester Line]] also stops near campus at Yawkey Station.

The Medical Campus is served by the 1 and CT1 Buses which runs along Massachusetts Avenue as well as the 47 and CT3 buses which connect the Boston University Medical Center with the Longwood Medical Area. The Silver Line Washington Street Branch runs the entire length of the campus, one block north of most parts of the campus; it connects Boston University Medical Center with Tufts/New England Medical Center and downtown Boston. The nearest underground T station is the Massachusetts Avenue station on the Orange Line, located 3 blocks north of the Medical Center.

The Boston University Shuttle (BUS) serves to connect the Charles River Campus, Boston University Theater, and the Medical Campus.

====Sustainability====
Boston University's sustainability committee is working to &quot;reduce energy consumption and decrease waste across the campus by concentrating on four crucial areas: recycling and waste management, energy efficiency, sustainable building development and operations, and communications, education, and outreach.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;A Greener BU: Look, Mom, No Trays!&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =A Greener BU: Look, Mom, No Trays!
| publisher =BU Today
| url =http://www.bu.edu/today/node/7361/
| accessdate = 2009-06-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the University's early steps toward creating a greener campus was implementing tray-free dining, which saved both water and cash.&lt;ref name=&quot;A Greener BU: Look, Mom, No Trays!&quot;/&gt;  Moving forward, BU's newly-hired Director of Sustainability, Dennis Carlberg, will continue to focus the University more intensely on sustainability issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;A Greener BU: Look, Mom, No Trays!&quot;/&gt;

===Other campuses===
====Brussels Campus====
[[Boston University Brussels]], officially named the '''Boston University Brussels Graduate Center''', and also known as BUB, is part of Boston University's Metropolitan College (MET), one of seventeen degree granting colleges that make up Boston University. In 1972 Boston University became the first major American university to offer graduate business management degrees in Europe with the opening of its campus in [[Brussels]], Belgium.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/brussels/about/index.html Boston University Brussels – About Us]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Due to its location in the capital of Europe, home to the [[European Union]] and [[NATO]], the school places a strong emphasis on international business, and the student body comprises a diverse range of nationalities and cultures.

====Dubai Campus====
The University opened a new dental school in Dubai, UAE in 2007.  The new dental program admitted its first group of students in July, 2008. In addition to BU’s dental facilities, the campus will eventually contain a wellness center, private clinics, and a major teaching hospital. &quot;Dubai Healthcare City is a free medical zone within the Emirate of Dubai, has been developed as a world-class, academic medical community, which will be developed around the Harvard Medical School Dubai Center, Boston University Institute for Dental Research and Education, and a major university hospital&quot;, according to Kathi Ferland, director of admissions at GSDM.[http://www.budubai.ae/],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bumc.bu.edu/Dept/Content.aspx?PageID=12667&amp;DepartmentID=522 |title=BU builds dental school in Dubai » Provost, Medical Campus » BUMC |publisher=Bumc.bu.edu |date=2007-10-18 |accessdate=2010-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====London Campus====
Boston University's largest study abroad program is located in London, England.  Boston University British Programmes offers a semester of study and work in London through their London Internship Program (LIP), as well as an adjunct non-internship program at Oxford University, St. Anne's College. Starting in Fall 2008, the programme at Oxford will only be a full academic year term, not just one semester as its been structured in the past.  The LIP program combines a professional internship with coursework that examines a particular academic area in the context of Britain’s history, culture, and society and its role in modern Europe. Courses in each academic area are taught by selected British faculty exclusively to students enrolled in the Boston University program. Upon successful completion of a semester, students earn 16 Boston University credits.  BU British Programmes are headquartered in South Kensington, London.  The campus consists of the main building at 43 Harrington Gardens, as well as six flats that have been converted to house students.  This program is open to Boston University students, as well as students at other American colleges, and enrolls between 650 to 850 students across Fall, Spring and Summer terms each year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/abroad/programs/england/ BU Study Abroad]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu-london.co.uk/ BU British Programmes]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Los Angeles Campus====
In Los Angeles, BU has an internship program for students to study and work in the heart of the film, television, advertising and public relations, and entertainment management and law industries. The program offers three tracks from which undergraduate and graduate students can choose: Advertising and Public Relations, Film and Television, and Entertainment Management. Graduated students have the opportunity to continue their education by enrolling in the Los Angeles Certificate Program, where students can choose either the Acting in Hollywood or the Writer in Hollywood track. Courses are taught by Boston University faculty and alumni who serve as mentors in and out of the classroom. Upon successful completion of a semester students will earn 16 Boston University credits. Students who successfully complete the Los Angeles Certificate Program will receive eight Boston University credits and a certificate from Boston University College of Fine Arts or College of Communication.

====Washington, DC Campus====
In Washington, DC, BU has internship and journalism programs. Students live in the University's building on [[Connecticut Avenue]] in [[Woodley Park]] and take advantage of the city by interning at different locations. The journalism program, run by [[Linda Killian]] allows students to act as Washington, DC correspondents for newspapers and television stations across the Northeast and New England while interning at major news outlets in the city. [http://www.bu.edu/washintern/index.html BU Washington Internship Program], [http://www.bu.edu/washjocenter/ BU Washington Journalism Center]

====Sydney Campus====
In Sydney, BU has internship and management as well as film festival and travel writing programs that vary based on semester. Around 150 students live in the University's newly constructed building in [[Chippendale, New South Wales|Chippendale]] developed by Tony Owen Partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by tonyowenpartners |url=http://tonyowenpartners.blogspot.com/2010/10/boston-university-nears-completion.html |title=tonyowenpartners: Boston University nears completion |publisher=Tonyowenpartners.blogspot.com |date=October 3, 2010 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by tonyowenpartners |url=http://tonyowenpartners.blogspot.com/2011/02/latest-boston-university-shots.html |title=tonyowenpartners: Latest Boston University Shots |publisher=Tonyowenpartners.blogspot.com |date=February 3, 2011 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The unique design of the building uses &quot;fissures to provide maximum solar access to bedrooms as well as natural ventilation throughout the building.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arthitectural.com/tony-owen-partners-boston-university-student-housing/ |title=Tony Owen Partners &amp;#124; Boston University Student Housing |publisher=arthitectural.com |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new building opened in the beginning of 2011 and features underground classrooms, a lecture hall, office space, library, and a roof patio. 

Other internship and study abroad opportunities are available through the International Programs office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/abroad/ |title=Study Abroad » Boston University |publisher=Bu.edu |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Admissions/demographics==
Admission statistics for the Class of 2015 have reached a modern high of 41,760 student applicants. The acceptance rate for the class of 2015 is 48%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/today/node/12659| title = BU Today| accessdate = 2011-4-6
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The incoming freshman class of 2010 was 68% [[White people|white]], 15% [[Asian people|Asian]], 7% foreign students, 7% [[Hispanic]], and 2% [[Black people|black]].  Boston University also has the second highest number of Jews of any private school (after [[New York University|NYU]]) in the country with between 3,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reformjudaismmag.org/_kd/Items/actions.cfm?action=Show&amp;item_id=1278&amp;destination=ShowItem |title=Reform Judaism Magazine |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hillel&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hillel.org/HillelApps/JLOC/Campus.aspx?AgencyId=17234 |title=Hillel.org |publisher=Hillel.org |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 4,000,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hillel.org/about/news/2006/feb/20060216_top.htm |title=Hillel.org |publisher=Hillel.org |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; or roughly 15%&lt;ref name=hillel/&gt; identifying as Jewish.

The international community at Boston University is 18% Chinese, 12% [[Korea]]n, 11% [[India]]n, 6% [[Taiwan]]ese, 6% Canadian, 4% Japanese, 3% [[Turkey|Turkish]], 2% [[Thailand|Thai]], 2% [[Saudi Arabia]]n, and 2% [[Mexico|Mexican]]. Of the 7% of students who are international students, 26% are pursuing undergraduate degrees and 47% are pursuing graduate degrees, with the remaining 27% engaged in other educational activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bu.edu/isso/about/statistics/student/2009/summary.html
|title=International Students Summary
|publisher=Boston University
|accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The plurality of registrants were from Massachusetts (19%), followed by New York (16%), New Jersey (9%), California (8%), Connecticut (4%), Pennsylvania (4%), and Texas (2%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.bu.edu/dbin/infocenter/content/index.php?pageid=909&amp;topicid=12
|title=Freshman Profile
|publisher=Boston University
|accessdate=2008-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:CASSteps.jpg|right|200px|thumb|Students take a break on the steps of the [[Boston University College of Arts and Sciences|College of Arts and Sciences]].]]Boston University offers [[bachelor's degrees]], [[master's degrees]], and [[doctoral degrees]], and medical and dental degrees through its 18 schools and colleges. Each school and college at the university has a three letter abbreviation, which is commonly used in place of their full school or college name. For example, the College of Arts and Sciences is commonly referred to as CAS, the School of Management is SMG, the School of Education is SED, etc.

===Colleges and schools===
Colleges and schools at Boston University include:
:*[[Boston University College of Fine Arts|College of Fine Arts]] (CFA)
:*[[Boston University College of Arts and Sciences|College of Arts and Sciences]] (CAS)
:**Graduate School of Arts and Sciences (GRS)
:*[[Boston University College of Communication|College of Communication]] (COM)
:*[[Boston University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]] (ENG)
:*College of General Studies (CGS)
:*[[Boston University College of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences (Sargent College)|College of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences (Sargent College)]] (SAR)
:*[[Boston University School of Education|School of Education]] (SED)
:*Division of Extended Education
:*School of Hospitality Administration (SHA)
:*[[Boston University School of Law|School of Law]] (LAW)
:*[[Boston University School of Management|School of Management]] (SMG)
:*[[Boston University Metropolitan College|Metropolitan College]] (MET)
:**[[Boston University Brussels]] (BUB)
:**[[Boston University Science and Engineering Program]] (SEP)
:*[[Boston University School of Social Work|School of Social Work]] (SSW)
:*[[Boston University School of Theology|School of Theology]] (STH)
:*[[Boston University School of Medicine|School of Medicine]] (MED)
:**[[Boston University School of Medicine#Division of Graduate Medical Sciences|Division of Graduate Medical Sciences]] (GMS)
:*[[Goldman School of Dental Medicine]] (SDM)
:*[[Boston University School of Public Health|School of Public Health]] (SPH)
:*[[Boston University Academy]]

The College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) was formerly named the College of Liberal Arts (CLA). The College of Communication was formerly named the School of Public Communication (SPC).  The School of Management (SMG) was formerly named the College of Business Administration (CBA). The College of General Studies (CGS) was formerly named the College of Basic Studies (CBS). The School of Nursing (SON) and the College of Practical Arts and Letters (PAL) are units that have been discontinued.

The Department of Cognitive and Neural Systems' technology lab, directed by [[Gail Carpenter]] has software, on topics ranging from remote sensing to text mining, available for download.

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| USNWR_NU             = 53
| USNWR_LA             =
| USNWR_Bus            = 31
| GUR World            =
| USNWR_Law            = 20
| USNWR_Medr           =
| USNWR_Medc           = 35
| USNWR_Eng            =
| USNWR_Ed             =
| USNWR_Ec             = 24
| USNWR_PolSci         =
| USNWR_PSycc          =
| USNWR_Psycr          =
| USNWR_Soc            =
| ARWU_W               = 76
| ARWU_N               = 44
| ARWU_SCI             =
| ARWU_ENG             =
| ARWU_LIFE            =
| ARWU_MED             =
| ARWU_SOC             =
| Newsweek             = 35
| THES_W               = 54
| QS_W                 = 70
| THES_N               = 20
| CMUP                 =
| Forbes               =
}}
''U.S. News &amp; World Report'' ranks Boston University 53rd among national universities for 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-universities-rankings |title=National Universities Rankings – Best Colleges – Education – US News and World Report |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2009-08-19 |accessdate=2010-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boston University was also ranked 11th among public health graduate schools, 22nd among law schools, 22nd among social work schools, 31st among business schools, 34th among medical schools, 42nd among engineering schools, and 56th among education schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools |title=Best Graduate Schools – Education – US News and World Report |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2010-04-15 |accessdate=2010-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

''[[QS World University Rankings]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011?page=1|title=QS World University Rankings 2011 Results}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2011 ranked Boston University 70th overall in the world. It has also received the maximum five stars under the QS Stars evaluation system.

''[[Times Higher Education]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2011-2012/north-america.html|title=Times Higher Education University Rankings 2011 Results}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2011 ranked Boston University 54th overall in the world.

''[[Shanghai Jiao Tong University]]'''s [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] ranks Boston University 44th in the United States, and 76th in the world, in its 2011 list of the Top 500 Universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2011.html |title=ARWU 2011 |publisher=Arwu.org |accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Newsweek]]'' (International Edition), in its list of the Top 100 Global Universities, ranked Boston University the 35th in the United States, and 65th in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsweek&quot;&gt;[http://msnbc.msn.com/id/14321230/site/newsweek/ MSN]. Retrieved September 18, 2006. {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Biomedical Engineering Graduate and Undergraduate Programs are ranked 7th and 8th respectively in the nation and rising by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''. The undergraduate program is also the sixth-largest ABET-accredited program in the nation.

[[File:BU School of Management.JPG|thumb|250px|right|The Rafik B. Hariri Building houses the [[Boston University School of Management|School of Management]].]]''

Additionally, most of the graduate programs in the [[Boston University College of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences (Sargent College)]] ranked within the top 15% in the country. The Occupational Therapy Program ranked 1st out of 152 programs; the Physical Therapy Program ranked 24th out of 199 programs; and the Speech-Language Pathology Program ranked 25th out of 244 programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sargent College&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/sargent/admissions/facts/
| title = Sargent College Facts &amp; Statistics
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Business Week]]'' ranks Boston University's MBA program 38th, and its undergraduate business program 31st.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWUGrad&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://images.businessweek.com/slideshows/20110227/best-undergraduate-business-schools-2011/slides/32
| title = 2011 Undergrad B-School Rankings
| accessdate = September 17, 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Economist'' ranks ''[[Boston University School of Management]]'' 42nd among global MBA programs in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/whichmba/2010/free-ranking-tool |title=2010 Full time MBA ranking |work=The Economist |date=2010-10-15 |accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Financial Times]]'' ranks Boston University's MBA program 68th in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;FTMba&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://rankings.ft.com/businessschoolrankings/global-mba-rankings-2011
| title = FT.com / Business Education
| accessdate = September 17, 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Boston University Talbot Building 01.JPG|thumb|250px|left|The Talbot Building located on the medical campus houses the [[Boston University School of Public Health|School of Public Health]], which is ranked 11th in the nation.]]

[[The Center for Measuring University Performance]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mup.asu.edu/research2010.pdf |title=The Top American Research Universities: 2010 Annual Report |year=2010 |accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ranks Boston University among the top 50 research universities in the country

BU is one of 96 American universities receiving the highest research classification (&quot;RU/VH&quot;) by the Carnegie Foundation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie Foundation&quot;/&gt;

The Sustainable Endowments Institute awarded Boston University a &quot;B-&quot; grade for its efforts in sustainability on the College Sustainability Report Card 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2009/schools/boston-university |title=Report Card 2009 |publisher=The College Sustainability Report Card |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The University's mark on the Report Card has improved steadily since 2007.  In that year it earned a &quot;D&quot;, and in 2008 it earned a &quot;C.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2007/schools/boston-university |title=Report Card 2007 |publisher=The College Sustainability Report Card |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2008/schools/boston-university |title=Report Card 2008 |publisher=The College Sustainability Report Card |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cost===
The 2010–2011 school year full-time tuition totaled $39,314 with exceptions to some schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;Office Registrar tuition info&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/reg/registration/t+f-1011reg.html |title=Tuition and Fees – 2019–2011 |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The total cost (including room and board) averages $52,574. Compared to the previous year, the school has made a 3.65 percent increase in the price of tuition, room and board. It is the smallest percentage increase since 1969. In addition, the increase of tuition resulted to a 12 percent increase in financial aid for students. President Brown said in an e-mail addressed to the student body that &quot;efforts to control costs and maintain quality have been successful.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BU Today Tution March2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/today/node/10638|author=Jahnke, Art |title=Tuition, Room and Board to Rise 3.65 Percent |publisher=BU Today |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The standard on-campus housing component of this cost is approximately $8,000 a year while more premium choices in the newer Student Village residence halls run nearly $13,000 a year.&lt;ref name=globearticle/&gt;  By comparison, the average rent for a two-bedroom apartment in the [[Allston-Brighton]] area is $1300, or $7800 per person per year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allstonbrightoncdc.org/pdfs/AB%20Housing%20Study.pdf |title=page 9, rent as of 2006 |format=PDF |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Grade Deflation===
The independently-run student newspaper at Boston University, ''[[The Daily Free Press]]'', as well as ''[[The New York Times]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTDeflation&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 |first = Samuel G.
 |last = Freedman
 |url = http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/07/education/07education.html
 |title = Can Tough Grades Be Fair Grades?
 |work = The New York Times
 |page = B8
 |date = 2006-06-07
 |accessdate = 2006-06-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt; have published articles exploring the existence of grade deflation. ''The Times'' discovered that administrators have suggested to faculty members deflated ideal grade distributions. Though an article in the staff's ''BU Today'' asserted that &quot;the GPAs of BU undergrads and the percentage of As and Bs have both risen over the last two decades,&quot; the ''New York Times'' has found BU grades rising more slowly with respect to many other schools.

Currently, the average GPA of a BU undergraduate is 3.04, compared to the averages of 3.35 for Boston College, 3.48 for Amherst College, 3.41 for New York University and 3.45 for Harvard University.&lt;ref name=NationalTrendsinGradeInflation&gt;{{Cite news
 |first = Washington
 |last = Post
 |url = http://gradeinflation.com/
 |work = Grade Inflation Across the U.S.
 |accessdate = 2010-10-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
About 81 percent of all grades earned in either the A or B range (75% in the B range).&quot; The article went on to note that although the university attempted to curb grade inflation and inconsistency in the late 1990s both the percentage of &quot;A's&quot; and GPAs have been rising since. They attributed the grade deflation not to teachers' grading policies, but to the increasing quality of each incoming class which leads to more top grades.&lt;ref name=BUTodayGradeDeflation&gt;{{Cite news
 |first = Chris
 |last = Berdik
 |url = http://www.bu.edu/phpbin/news-cms/news/?dept=4&amp;id=40427&amp;template=7
 |title = Grade Deflation or Not?
 |work = BU Today
 |date = 2006-09-14
 |accessdate = 2006-10-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Journals and publications===
Boston University is home to several academic journals and publications. The [[Boston University School of Law|School of Law]] hosts six nationally recognized law journals, including the ''Boston University Law Review'', ''American Journal of Law and Medicine'', ''Review of Banking &amp; Financial Law'', ''Boston University International Law Journal'', ''Journal of Science and Technology Law'', and ''Public Interest Law Journal''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/law/prospective/jd/journals/
| title = BU Law | Prospective Students J.D. Program | Journals
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Boston University School of Education|School of Education]] houses ''The Journal of Education'', which is the oldest continuously published journal in the field of education in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/sed/about-us/journal-of-education/
| title = Journal of Education
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''American Journal of Media Psychology'' and the ''Public Relations Journal'' are currently edited by professors at the [[Boston University College of Communication|College of Communication]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/com/research/index.shtml
| title = Research at the College of Communication
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is also home to the ''New England Center for Investigative Reporting'', which generates numerous publications yearly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://necir-bu.org/wp/
| title = New England Center for Investigative Reporting at Boston University
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Studies in Romanticism'' is housed at the Department of English&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/cas/academics/departments/
| title = Boston University Arts &amp; Sciences
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''The Journal of Field Archeology'' is housed at the Department of Archeology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/jfa/
| title = Index for JFA
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.maney.co.uk/index.php/journals/jfa/
| title = Maney Publishing Journal of Field Archaeology
| accessdate = 2010-07-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Boston University College of Arts and Sciences|College of Arts and Sciences]].

===Special academic programs===
====Core Curriculum====
Offered in the College of Arts and Sciences, the Core Curriculum offers an intensive [[great books]] program for any incoming freshmen who choose to participate.  Occupying two classes a semester during freshman and sophomore years, the program has four humanities sections which start with [[Gilgamesh]] and work their way through [[Plato]], [[Aristotle]], [[Aeschylus]], [[Machiavelli]], [[Shakespeare]], Milton, Dante, Bach and many more.  The Social Sciences part of the program includes Hobbes, [[John Locke]], Rousseau, Adam Smith, Marx, and continues through contemporary works.  Lastly, the science aspect of the program deals with major ideas such as big bang theory, evolution, quantum mechanics and more.  Ultimately, the program seeks to combine science, math, humanities, art, and the social sciences into a cohesive program to give students insight into their world and help them become more refined writers and scholars.

====University Professors Program====
The [[University Professors Program]] (UNI) is an interdisciplinary program that allows students to pursue a broad range of academic interests. With a student to faculty ratio of 4:1, UNI offers students a broad education in a more personalized atmosphere. Students take a common, intimate, &quot;Core&quot; program consisting of liberal arts courses taught by University Professors in small seminar settings. They then work closely with an advisor to craft a course of study which will lead them to an interdisciplinary degree, culminating in a senior thesis.
Based upon the report of an academic review committee, a new University-wide honors program will be developed and the UNI program will be gradually phased out. Students currently enrolled will continue in the program.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.bu.edu/uni
| title = Boston University – UNI Program
| accessdate = 2007-09-24
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Boston University Academy====
{{Main|Boston University Academy}}
[[Boston University Academy]] is as another notable aspect of the university.  Founded in 1993, the Academy is known for its strong academic program, classical curriculum, and its unique connection to university resources.

==Student life==
===Student publications===
Despite a Student Activities policy which prohibits student-run publications from receiving University funding for printing costs, student journals continue to thrive at Boston University as department-sponsored publications, edited by students under the supervision of faculty and staff advisors. The coordinator for undergraduate publications, responsible for acquainting new editors with University guidelines and directing publications staff to campus production and financial resources, has been Zachary Bos of the Core Curriculum since 2006.

Although officially and entirely independent from the University, ''[[Daily Free Press|The Daily Free Press]]'' (often referred to as ''The FreeP''), is the campus student newspaper, and the fourth largest daily newspaper in Boston. Since 1970, it has provided students with campus news, city and state news, sports coverage, editorials, arts and entertainment, and special feature stories. ''The Daily Free Press'' is published every regular instruction day of the University year and is available at BU dorms, classroom buildings and commercial locations frequented by students.

''Synapse'' is the Boston University Undergraduate Science Magazine and is published online every semester. The &quot;Science&quot; focus is on many disciplines ranging from life sciences to physical sciences, engineering to mathematics, and finance to economics. The magazine is peer and faculty reviewed, and is advertised with routine, campus-wide distribution of pamphlets highlighting featured articles. ''Synapse'' was first published in the spring of 2009 and continues to publish articles each semester.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/synapse |title=BU Synapse Website |publisher=Bu.edu |date=October 12, 2011 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Brownstone Journal'' is the longest-running campus publication, having been publishing undergraduate research, scholarly articles and essays, and literary work in translation, since 1982. The Brownstone is currently sponsored by the Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program, but was originally a departmental publication of the University Professors Program. The staff operates from their offices in the former yearbook space in the basement of 10 Lenox Street, beneath the editorial offices of ''Bostonia''.

The literary arts magazine ''[[Clarion (journal)|Clarion]]'' has been printed since 1998. The first issue, titled &quot;?&quot;, was published by the group Students for Literary Awareness with the sponsorship of the Department of English; subsequent issues have been issued by the BU Literary Society. ''Burn Magazine'' is a younger literary magazine, published biannually.

In 2006, the first issue of ''Pusteblume'' journal of translation was published by a group of former and current students of a co-curricular poetry seminar run by Professor George Kalogeris of the Core Curriculum. The journal, jointly sponsored by the Department of Romance Languages, the Department of Modern Languages and Comparative Literatures, and the Core Curriculum, publishes literature in translation and articles concerning translation.

''The Journal of the Core Curriculum'' has been published continuously since 1992 by the College of Arts and Sciences Core Curriculum. Produced by a student editorial staff with the guidance of a faculty advisor, the very interdisciplinary Core Journal publishes academic prose, literary imitations, fictitious encounters between figures from the 'great works', original poetry and creative writing, essays, artwork, translations, and even—in Vol. XVI, Spring 2007—original musical compositions. ''The Back Bay Review'' is a student-run journal of critical writing.

''Arché'' is an annual journal of undergraduate work in philosophy, whose first issue was released in the summer of 2007. It is sponsored by the Department of Philosophy and published by the Undergraduate Philosophy Association.

''[http://buiaa.org/ir-review/ The International Relations Review]'' began in 2009 as a subsidiary publication of The Boston University International Affairs Association. Entirely student-run, ''The IR Review'' is an independent scholarly journal publishing articles from all areas in international affairs. The goal of ''The IRR'' is to unite the many talents and experiences within BU's vast department of international relations.

Even more independent, ''The Student Underground'', focuses on alternative political and cultural activity. Since 1997, issues have been published roughly monthly by a &quot;not-for-profit collective&quot; composed mostly of BU students. In 2007, the paper began operating under the name ''The Boston Underground''; the original editorial focus on campus issues has over the years weakened as the founding editors graduated from BU or left Boston altogether.

''The Sam Adams Review'' was a short-lived monthly student newspaper &quot;providing news for the American Spirit,&quot; geared toward a conservative readership. Its staff was not officially recognized as a registed student activity group but, like the Underground, was entirely student-run.

''[[Boink]]'' was launched in February 2005 by a group of undergrads led by Alecia Oleyourryk, who was then a senior at the College of Communications. The magazine features BU students posing nude, as well as articles on sexuality. At the time of its first issue, the Dean of Students issued a statement explaining that &quot;the University does not endorse, nor welcome, the prospective publication Boink.&quot; The magazine was then, and remains, unaffiliated with the University.

In September 2005, the student paper ''The Source'' began to appear weekly, and was characterized by a predominance of arts and entertainment coverage. No new issues were printed after November 2006, and it appears the publisher Greenline Media is now defunct.

The &quot;[http://buquad.com/ BU Quad]&quot; is an independent, student-run online magazine started in fall of 2009. The magazine features articles and columns on topics including campus news, television, food, politics, and music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://buquad.com/ |title=the Quad &amp;#124; bu's independent online magazine |publisher=Buquad.com |accessdate=2010-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.bucultureshock.com BU Culture Shock] is the official blog of the [[Howard Thurman#Honors and Legacy|Howard Thurman Center]], Boston University's multicultural center. It is dedicated to free expression and open discussion. Culture Shock is notable for its coverage of the 2011 Boston University Union election, inviting contributions from candidates along with other students.

===Community Service Center===
The [http://www.bu.edu/csc/ Boston University Community Service Center] (CSC) is almost entirely student-run. Each semester, the CSC runs [http://www.bu.edu/csc/opportunities/community-service-center-programs/ 13 volunteer programs] related to issues of local, national, or global concern, including hunger, children, elders, disabilities, homelessness and affordable housing, human rights, AIDS awareness, gender issues, and the environment.

The CSC also runs two immensely popular one-week programs.  During the [http://www.bu.edu/csc/opportunities/community-service-center-programs/fysop/ First Year Student Outreach Project] (FYSOP), upperclassmen lead groups of new freshmen in volunteer activities throughout Boston before the start of first semester.  For [http://www.bu.edu/csc/opportunities/community-service-center-programs/asb/ Alternative Spring Break] (ASB), hundreds of students travel by 12-passenger van, bus and fly to locations throughout the country to do service projects in a variety of areas of need.  In the past students camped out, starting the day before signups, to get spots on trips. Starting in 2010 registration process moved on-line.&lt;ref name=&quot;bu.edu&quot;&gt;www.bu.edu/csc&lt;/ref&gt;

The CSC boasts the most student involvement of any organization on campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;bu.edu&quot;/&gt;

===Graduate workshops===
[[Willing suspension productions|Willing Suspension Productions]] provides graduate English students the opportunity to present rare Early modern drama before a Boston audience.  The program was founded in 1993 and produces one play per year.

===ROTC===
[[ROTC]] at BU traces its origins back to August 16, 1919 when the U.S. War Department stood up the Students’ Army Training Corps at Boston University, the predecessor to the current Army ROTC program.&lt;ref name=&quot;rotc&quot;&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/dme/ Boston University – Division of Military Education], retrieved May 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, BU is one of twenty five colleges and universities in the country to host all three ROTC programs – Army, Navy, and Air Force. Students wishing to be commissioned into the Marine Corps study as Navy Midshipmen.

===Other clubs and activities===
* The [[Boston University Dear Abbeys]] is an acclaimed All-Male student a cappella group. In 2005, they won the [[International Championship of Collegiate A Cappella]], a prestigious nation-wide tournament for collegiate a cappella groups.

* Boston University&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.peerhealthexchange.org/phe-sites.html |title=Peer Health Exchange – PHE Sites |publisher=Peerhealthexchange.org |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; is one of the 22 nation-wide college sites where there is a branch of [[Peer Health Exchange]]. Peer Health Exchange trains college students to become PHE Health Educators in neighboring public high schools that lack funding for health education. Health Educators teach the following topics in ninth grade classrooms: Decision-Making and Communication I, Sexual Decision-Making, Pregnancy Prevention, Sexually Transmitted Infections &amp; HIV, Healthy Relationships, Abusive Relationships, Rape &amp; Sexual Assault, Nutrition &amp; Physical Activity, Tobacco, Alcohol, Drugs, Mental Health, and Decision-Making and Communication II.

* [[Boston University Stage Troupe]] is the University's oldest and largest performing arts group. Open to undergrads not majoring in theatre, the group performs many shows a year, and also hosts special events, some of which are coordinated with the Dean of Students.

* The ''Boston University Debate Society'' regularly competes on the [[American Parliamentary Debate Association]] debate circuit. During the 2010–11 season, BUDS fielded debaters who won both &quot;Team of the Year&quot; distinction as well as the 2011 National Championship at West Point, NY. The team hosts an unopposed national tournament on campus each spring, with nearly every APDA college represented.

*The Boston University Figure Skating Club is a team of students who [[figure skating|figure skate]] and [[ice dancing|ice dance]], and a fully fledged member of the [[United States Figure Skating Association]].  It is the reigning two-time U.S. National Intercollegiate Team Champion.  In addition, the &quot;Boston University Terrierettes&quot; compete in Collegiate [[Synchronized skating]], and have routinely placed in the top ten at the [[United States Synchronized Team Skating Championships]].

* The [[Boston University International Affairs Association]] (BUIAA) is the evolution of the Boston University Model United Nations Association (BUMUNA), which was founded in 1973.  This club also hosts two conferences annually, one for high school students and one on the collegiate level.  '''BosMUN''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosmun.org web site] for Boston Model UN VIII&lt;/ref&gt; BUIAA's high school conference, hosts over 1,000 students annually from all across the globe.  Last year, schools came from China, Guatemala, and Canada.  '''BarMUN'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.barmun.org |title=web site |publisher=United Nations  |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Boston Area Model United Nations Conference) is BUIAA's college level conference.  BarMUN stands apart from other college conference in that the conference is a full scale simulation, ranging from 4 to 8 committee joint crises.

* The ''Hug Don't Hate'' grassroots peace-building campaign was founded in 2006 at Boston University with the mission of creating lasting peace through happiness, understanding and respect. All of Hug Don't Hate's activities are focused on helping individuals find common ground. The activities are divided into 4 branches: 'Free Hug Fridays', 'Urban Smiles', 'Connective Kindness' and 'BUNITED'. Hug Don't Hate is also currently expanding to different locations.

*The Greek community&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/sao/features/greek-life.html |title=Student Activities Office Web site about Fraternity/Sorority activities |publisher=Bu.edu |date=June 3, 2011 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; on BU's campus consists of nine sororities (nine Panhellenic chapters), ten fraternities (seven Inter-Fraternity Council chapters) and recently created Multicultural Greek Council (four fraterneties and one sorority). The student population that is enrolled in fraternities and sororities is currently 8% and growing. In 2008, over 560 women went through formal sorority recruitment which occurs the first weekend of 2nd semester.

* The ''Boston University India Club'' is the University's largest student-run organization. Open to students of all ethnic backgrounds, the club sponsors cultural shows, performances and activities that showcase South Asian culture. BUIC also hosts and organizes the annual GarbaFest Competition, a garba raas competition.

*[[Lambda Chi Alpha]] (ΛΧΑ), a member of the [[North-American Interfraternity Conference]] (NIC) and one of the largest men's general [[Fraternities and sororities|fraternities]] in North America, was founded by [[Warren A. Cole]], while he was a student at Boston University, on November 2, 1909.

*Delta Delta Delta ([[Delta Delta Delta|ΔΔΔ]]) was founded at Boston University on [[Thanksgiving|Thanksgiving Eve]], 1888. Sarah Ida Shaw, later known as Ida Shaw Martin, founded Tri Delta without the assistance of a men's fraternity, a unique accomplishment for her time.

*The College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) Dean's Hosts are a premier student volunteer organization where members serve as liaisons between CAS students and faculty members. Most notably, CAS Dean's Hosts along with CAS Student Government throw the Top of the Hub formal in downtown Boston annually.

*The &quot;Boston University Soccer Club&quot; is an athletic-based club that allows members of the BU community to participate in a variety of soccer related events ranging from pick-up [[futsal]] games at the [[Fitness and Recreation Center]], to philanthropic fundraising matches such as the annual &quot;Lose the Shoes&quot; charity tournament, from which all the proceeds go to the GrassrootSoccer campaign. The motto of the club is: &quot;Unifying diversity through the love of the world's beautiful game.&quot;

*CAS Student Government is the University's largest individual student government group.  Each year they work with the administration of the College of Arts and Sciences to deal with multiple student affairs issues within CAS.  They also program many events for the students of CAS including: Celtics Night, Coffee at Finals, Ice Skating at Frog Pond, Senior Reception, and many more.

*Boston University offers nearly 500 student organizations on campus.

==Athletics==
[[Image:Inside Agganis Arena.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Inside [[Agganis Arena]] after a hockey game.]]
{{Main|Boston University Terriers}}
{{See also|Boston University Terriers men's ice hockey}}

Boston University's NCAA [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] Terriers compete in basketball, cross country, golf, ice hockey, [[Sport rowing|rowing]], soccer, swimming, tennis, track, and [[collegiate wrestling|wrestling]], while the Lady Terriers compete in basketball, dance, cross country, field hockey, golf, ice hockey, [[lacrosse]], rowing, soccer, softball, swimming, tennis, and track. [[Boston University athletics]] teams compete in the [[America East Conference|America East]], [[Hockey East]], and [[Colonial Athletic Association]] conferences, and their mascot is Rhett the Boston Terrier.

The Boston University men's hockey team is the most successful on campus, and is a storied college hockey franchise, with five NCAA championships – including the 2009 NCAA title, which was a classic last-minute comeback victory.  The team is coached by hall-of-famer Jack Parker, and is a major supplier of talent to the NHL, as well as to the 1980 U.S.A. Gold Medal-winning men's hockey team.  Boston University's hockey team has won 29 [[Beanpot (ice hockey)|Beanpot]] titles, more than any other team in the tournament, which includes [[Harvard Crimson Tide|Harvard University]], [[Boston College Eagles men's ice hockey|Boston College]], and [[Northeastern Huskies|Northeastern University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaa.com/sports/m-hockey/ncaa-m-hockey-body.html |title=National Collegiate Athletic Association |publisher=Ncaa.com |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Boston University also won the Sun Life Frozen Fenway contest in 2010 against Boston College by a score of 3–2. It was an outdoor [[Hockey East]] college game played at [[Fenway Park]] a week after the [[NHL Winter Classic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/sports/colleges/mens_hockey/articles/2010/01/09/great_outdoors/ |title=Great outdoors – The Boston Globe |work=Boston Globe  |date=2010-01-09 |accessdate=2010-05-31 | first=Nancy | last=Marrapese-Burrell}}&lt;/ref&gt;

BU has also won two national championships in women's rowing, in 1991 and 1992.&lt;ref&gt;[[NCAA Rowing Championships#Prior Championships|Rowing Championships]], on wikipedia&lt;/ref&gt;

Boston University recently constructed the new [[Agganis Arena]], which opened on January 3, 2005 with a men's hockey game between the Terriers and the [[University of Minnesota]] [[Minnesota Golden Gophers|Golden Gophers]]. The Agganis Arena is also used occasionally to host other non-sporting related events.

Boston University disbanded its football team in 1997. The university used the nearly $3 million from its football program to build the multimillion-dollar John Hancock Student Village and athletic complex. Among the biggest benefactors of the decision was BU women, who saw the funding for their teams increased. &quot;By implementing the total plan, we can achieve a much more balanced set of sports programs for both men and women, which is consistent with the philosophy underlying Title IX,&quot; said former BU athletic director Gary Strickler.&lt;ref&gt;Hanson, Gayle M.B. &amp; Berg, Stacie Zoe. Long on losses, short on funds, BU football lets clock run out. Insight on the News (Dec 15, 1997).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Club sports===
Boston University students also compete in athletics at the club level. Thirty six club sports are recognized by the university, including: Synchronized Skating, Baseball;
Inline Hockey; Men's Volleyball; Women's Volleyball; Men's Lacrosse; Snowboard; Ultimate Frisbee; Kung Fu; Fencing; Rugby Football; Synchronized Swimming; Cheerleading; Table Tennis; Women's Water Polo; Men's Water Polo; Women's Rugby; Alpine Ski Racing; Snowboarding; Cycling; Badminton; Ballroom Dance; Figure Skating; Golf; Gymnastics; Jiu Jitsu; Kendo; Shotokan Karate; Sailing; Taekwondo; Triathlon; Dance Theater Group; Squash, Equestrian, and Men's Club Football

The BU Table Tennis team has won the divisional championships a number of times this decade, most recently in 2006 (Men's) and 2007 (Women's). Both Men's and Women's Intervarsity Table Tennis Teams have attended the National Collegiate Table Tennis Tournaments and ranked as high as the top 10 nationwide.

The BU Dinghy Sailors are the most recent BU team to win a national championship for the school at the varsity level, having won the [[Intercollegiate Sailing Association|ICSA]] Collegiate Nationals in 1999.

The BU Figure Skating Team recently won the 2009 Intercollegiate National Figure Skating Championships held in Colorado Springs, CO.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/bostonia/summer09/skating/ |title=The National Champions You Might Not Know, Bostonia Magazine, Summer 2009 |publisher=Bu.edu |date=July 24, 2009 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fight song: &quot;Go B.U.&quot;===
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Go BU, Go BU!&lt;br&gt;
Sing her praises loud and true!&lt;br&gt;
We'll fight for our alma mater,&lt;br&gt;
On to sure victory!!&lt;br&gt;
Fight! Fight! Fight!&lt;br&gt;
Go BU, Go BU!&lt;br&gt;
Down the field to score anew!&lt;br&gt;
Our hearts are with you as you meet the foe.&lt;br&gt;
We hail you, Ole BU!&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Due to the lack of a football team since 1997,  students use the word &quot;ice&quot; instead of &quot;field&quot; in the seventh line at hockey games, and &quot;court&quot; at basketball games.

==Notable alumni and faculty==
{{Main|List of Boston University people}}
[[File:Martin-Luther-King-1964-leaning-on-a-lectern.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] earned a PhD from BU in 1955.]]
There are 285,000 Boston University alumni, representing almost every country in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/alumni/buaa/ |title=Boston University Alumni Association » Alumni Web » Boston University |publisher=Bu.edu |date=2009-10-20 |accessdate=2010-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] is one of BU's most notable alumni. Three other alumni hold historical importance: [[Rebecca Lee Crumpler]] was the first African-American woman and [[Charles Alexander Eastman|Charles Eastman (first named Ohiyesa)]] the first [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|American Indian]] to be certified as doctors, and [[Helen Magill White]] was the first woman in the U.S. to earn a PhD. Other well-known alumni include actors [[Marisa Tomei]], [[Julianne Moore]] and [[Geena Davis]], former Defense Secretary [[William Cohen]], current Commerce Secretary [[Gary Locke]], former Senator [[Judd Gregg]], radio personality [[Howard Stern]], celebrity chef [[Rocco DiSpirito]], J.Crew CEO and former Gap Inc. CEO [[Millard Drexler]], sports writer [[Bill Simmons]], television personality [[Bill O'Reilly (political commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]], Bravo executive [[Andy Cohen (television personality)|Andy Cohen]], former Second Lady [[Tipper Gore]] and cohost of Project Runway and fashion editor for Marie Claire Magazine [[Nina Garcia]]. The former First Vice President of the Federal Reserve Bank of Boston [[Earle O. Latham]]. The American painter [[Franz Kline]] attended BU. The founder of the Albanian Orthodox Church, [[Fan S. Noli]], received a doctorate from BU. [[Infosys]] co-founder [[S. D. Shibulal]] did his MS from BU.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avni Spahiu&quot;&gt;Avni Spahiu, ''Fan Noli's American Years: Notes on a Great Albanian American'' (Houston: Jalifat, 2009), tr. Getoar Mjeku.&lt;/ref&gt;

Current and former faculty of BU include [[Alexander Graham Bell]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/admissions/bu-basics/fast-facts/ |title=About BU: Fast Facts &amp;#124; Boston University Admissions |publisher=Bu.edu |date=May 5, 1922 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Elie Wiesel]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/judaicstudies/faculty/index.html ]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Andre de Quadros]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/cfa/music/faculty/quadros/ |title=André de Quadros » College of Fine Arts &amp;#124; Boston University |publisher=Bu.edu |date=October 13, 2011 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Howard Zinn]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/breaking_news/2010/01/howard_zinn_his.html | work=The Boston Globe | title=Howard Zinn, historian who challenged status quo, dies at 87 | first1=Mark | last1=Feeney | first2=Bryan | last2=Marquard | date=2010-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Isaac Asimov]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.libraries.wvu.edu/exhibits/asimov/ |title=WVU Libraries: Isaac Asimov Online Exhibit |publisher=Libraries.wvu.edu |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Derek Walcott]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/bpt/facstaff/index.html ]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Robert Pinsky]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/english/pinsky.html ]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Bob Zelnick]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/com/about/faculty/robert_zelnick.shtml |title=Faculty » College of Communication » Boston University |publisher=Bu.edu |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  , [[Andrew Bacevich]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bu.edu/ir/faculty/alphabetical/bacevich/ |title=Andrew J. Bacevich » International Relations &amp;#124; Boston University |publisher=Bu.edu |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jhumpa Lahiri]].

==See also==
*[[Boston University Police Department]]
*[[Einstein Papers Project]]

==References==
&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book
 | last = Kilgore
 | first = Kathleen
 | editor =
 | others =
 | title = Transformations: A History of Boston University
 | origdate =
 | origyear =
 | origmonth =
 | url =
 | edition =
 | year = 1991
 | language =
 | isbn = 0-87270-070-4
 | chapter =
 | chapterurl =
 | quote =
 }}
* {{Cite book
 | last = Saltzman
 | first = Nancy
 | editor =
 | others =
 | title = Buildings and Builders: a History of Boston University
 | origdate =
 | origyear =
 | origmonth =
 | url =
 | edition =
 | year = 1985
 | publisher = Boston University Press
 | location = Boston
 | isbn = 0-87270-056-9
 | chapter =
 | chapterurl =
 | quote =
 }}
* Wertheimer, Linda K. [http://www.boston.com/news/education/higher/articles/2007/10/18/bu_to_launch_18b_plan_to_expand_upgrade_faculty/ BU to launch $1.8b plan to expand, upgrade faculty].  ''Boston Globe'', October 18, 2007.
* Boston University strategic plan.  [http://www.bu.edu/president/documents/Strategic-Plan.pdf Choosing to Be Great: A vision of Boston University—past, present, and future], November 19, 2007.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Boston University}}
*{{Official website|http://www.bu.edu}}
* [http://techlab.bu.edu/ CNS Technology Lab website]

{{Boston University}}
{{MethodistColleges}}
{{America East}}
{{Hockey East}}
{{Largest United States universities by enrollment}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Boston}}
{{Eastern Association of Rowing Colleges}}

{{Coord|42.349634|N|71.099688|W|source:dewiki_region:US-MA_type:landmark|format=dms|display=title}}

[[Category:Boston University| ]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Boston, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1839]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Association of Independent Colleges and Universities in Massachusetts members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Fenway–Kenmore]]

[[ar:جامعة بوسطن]]
[[ast:Universidá de Boston]]
[[ca:Universitat de Boston]]
[[cs:Bostonská univerzita]]
[[da:Boston University]]
[[de:Boston University]]
[[et:Bostoni Ülikool]]
[[es:Universidad de Boston]]
[[fa:دانشگاه بوستون]]
[[fr:Université de Boston]]
[[ga:Boston University]]
[[ko:보스턴 대학교]]
[[hi:बोस्टन विश्वविद्यालय]]
[[is:Boston-háskóli]]
[[it:Università di Boston]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת בוסטון]]
[[nl:Universiteit van Boston]]
[[ja:ボストン大学]]
[[no:Boston University]]
[[pnb:بوسٹن یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Boston University]]
[[pt:Universidade de Boston]]
[[ru:Бостонский университет]]
[[fi:Bostonin yliopisto]]
[[sv:Boston University]]
[[ta:பாஸ்டன் பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[uk:Бостонський університет]]
[[ug:بوستون ئۇنىۋېرستېتى]]
[[zh:波士頓大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
