<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="613947" ns="0" title="Reza Pahlavi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|Not to be confused with his younger brother, Prince [[Ali-Reza Pahlavi]] (1966-2011); or his father, [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]] (1919-1980).}}
{{Infobox royalty
| name           = Reza Pahlavi
| website        = http://www.rezapahlavi.org
| title          = Crown Prince of Iran
| image          = Rezapahlavi.jpg
| caption        = 
| spouse         = [[Yasmine Pahlavi]]
| issue          = Princess Noor&lt;br&gt;Princess Iman&lt;br&gt;Princess Farah
| house          = [[House of Pahlavi]]
| father         = [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]]
| mother         = [[Farah Diba]]
| birth_date  = {{Birth date and age|1960|10|31|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Tehran]], [[Iran]]
| succession     = [[Pahlavi dynasty|Head of ''House of Pahlavi'']]
| reign          = 27 July 1980 – present&lt;br&gt;({{age in years and days|1981|07|27}})
| reign-type     = Period
| predecessor    = [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]]
| successor      = [[Ali Patrick Pahlavi]]
| suc-type       = [[Heir presumptive]]
| religion       = [[Shia Islam]]
|}}

Prince '''Reza Pahlavi''' ({{lang-fa|رضا پهلوی}}, born 31 October 1960) is the last crown prince of the former [[Imperial State of Iran]] and current head of the [[House of Pahlavi]]. He is the older son of the late [[Shah of Iran]], [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]], and his [[Shahbanou]] [[Farah Pahlavi]]. In 1979, Reza Pahlavi left Iran at the time of the [[Iranian Revolution]].

==Biography==
[[File:Cyrus small.JPG|thumb|left|Reza Pahlavi in 1973 as Crown Prince of Iran]]
Reza Pahlavi was born in [[Tehran]], [[Iran]], as eldest son of [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]], the last [[Shah of Iran]], and Empress [[Farah Pahlavi]]. Reza Pahlavi's siblings include his sister [[Farahnaz Pahlavi|Princess Farahnaz Pahlavi]] (12 March 1963), brother [[Ali-Reza Pahlavi|Prince Ali-Reza Pahlavi]] (28 April 1966 – 4 January 2011), and sister [[Leila Pahlavi|Princess Leila Pahlavi]] (27 March 1970 – 10 June 2001), as well as a half-sister, [[Shahnaz Pahlavi|Princess Shahnaz Pahlavi]] (27 October 1940).

He left Iran at the age of 17 for air force training. He spent a year at [[Williams College]], but was forced to leave because of the turmoil in Iran. With the monarchy overthrown and an Islamic Republic established, Reza Pahlavi did not return to Iran. He received a [[Bachelor of science|BSc]] degree by correspondence in [[political science]] from the [[University of Southern California]], because Williams did not offer that option.&lt;ref&gt;record.Williams.edu/wp/?p=13293&lt;/ref&gt; A jet fighter pilot, Reza Pahlavi completed the United States Air Force Training Program at the former [[Reese Air Force Base]] in [[Lubbock, Texas]]. In 1980, at the start of the [[Iran–Iraq War]], Pahlavi, a highly-trained fighter pilot, wrote to General [[Valiollah Fallahi]], Chief Commander of the Armed Forces of the Islamic Republic, offering to fight in the air force for Iran in the war. The offer was rebuffed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mideastnews.com/Reza0202.html Middle East News]&lt;/ref&gt;

With the death of his father on 27 July 1980, Reza Pahlavi became the Head of the [[House of Pahlavi]].

Reza Pahlavi has written three books on the state of Iran.

According to Iranian writer Reza Bayegan, Prince Reza Pahlavi is deeply attached to his [[Shia Islam|Shi'ite Muslim]] faith. He has named one of his daughters ''[[Iman]]'' (meaning faith in Arabic), and has performed the [[Hajj]] (pilgrimage) to [[Mecca]].&lt;ref name=payvand&gt;{{cite article|author=Reza Bayegan|title=Reza Pahlavi and the Question of Religion|url=http://payvand.com/news/08/may/1063.html|publisher=Payvand}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family==

Reza married [[Yasmine Pahlavi|Yasmine Etemad Amini]] on June 12, 1986. Yasmine, a graduate of the [[George Washington University]] School of Law, worked for ten years as a lawyer for the Children’s Law Center as a legal advocate for at-risk youth. Yasmine also founded the Foundation for the Children of Iran in 1991, a non-profit foundation that provides health care services to Iranian children or children of Iranian origin.

Reza Pahlavi and his wife Yasmine have three daughters: [[Princess Noor Pahlavi|Noor]] (born April 3, 1992), [[Princess Iman Pahlavi|Iman]] (born September 12, 1993), and [[Princess Farah Pahlavi|Farah]] (born January 17, 2004).

==Politics==
{{Iranian Imperial Family}}
[[File:Crpcairo.jpg|thumb|left|Reza Pahlavi sworn in as Head of [[Pahlavi Dynasty]] in 1980.]]
Reza Pahlavi has used his high profile status as an Iranian abroad to campaign politically for [[human rights]], democracy, and unity among Iranians in Iran and outside it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zenit.org/article-20209?l=german Zenit.org]&lt;/ref&gt; On his website he calls for a separation of religion and state in Iran and for free and fair elections &quot;for all freedom-loving individuals and political ideologies&quot;. He exhorts all groups dedicated to a democratic agenda to work together for a democratic and secular Iranian government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rezapahlavi.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.com/speeches/?english&amp;id=437 Rezapahlavi.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Reza Bayegan, Prince Pahlavi believes in the separation of religion from politics. However, Pahlavi avoids the &quot;[[Islamophobia|Islam bashing]]&quot; that Bayegan writes occurs in some circles of the Iranian opposition. Rather, he believes that religion has a humanizing and ethical role in shaping individual character and infusing society with greater purpose.&lt;ref name=payvand/&gt;

Pahlavi wrote in his book, ''Winds of Change'':&lt;ref&gt;Pahlavi, Winds of Change, pp. 26-28&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|Since the advent of [[Islam]], our clergymen have served as a moral compass. Spirituality has been an inseparable part of our culture...Today, moral guidance has been replaced by clerical censorship and dictatorial fiat.}}

Pahlavi has used media appearances to urge Iran's [[theocratic]] government to accept a [[referendum]] that uses independently verifiable international standards and observation mechanisms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/audiovideo/BBC-radio4.html BBC Radio]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/audiovideo/rte-041406.html Reza Pahlavi interview]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/audiovideo/McLaughlin-One-on-One.html Reza Pahlavi interview]&lt;/ref&gt; He has also urged Iranians to engage in a campaign of non-violent [[civil disobedience]], starting with non-participation in elections of the [[Islamic republic]] (elections he views as undemocratic), followed by peaceful demonstrations and [[Strike action|strikes]]. He is, however, an outspoken opponent of any foreign military intervention for regime change in Iran,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/audiovideo/KRSI-mohri-042306.html Reza Pahlavi interview]&lt;/ref&gt; believing that the people of Iran alone have the power to bring about change in their governmental system and society.

==Human rights==

On March 27, 2010, Reza Pahlavi was invited by the International Society of Human Rights in Bonn, Germany, to speak on the challenge of implementing democracy and human rights in Iran; a sample excerpt from this speech follows:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/details_article.php?english&amp;article=437 Rezapahlavi.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|...democracy and human rights for Iran is not just a slogan; it is our unique hope for salvation and the fundamental element which will bring long term political stability as well as put our nation back on the track of modernity, progress and prosperity. Iranians have come a long way, particularly in this last century. We have paid a heavy price while learning valuable lessons. As such, we are stronger as a society and perhaps clearer in our collective vision of a better future.}}

Other samples of his speeches are in the External Links below.

==Quotes==
* History has repeatedly proven to us that a clear separation between religion and state is imperative in order to have the right circumstances for democratic governance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rezapahlavi.com&quot;/&gt;
* Idealism and realism, behavior change and regime change do not require different policies but the same: empowering the Iranian people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/details_article.php?english&amp;article=104 Hudson Institute Briefing Series]&lt;/ref&gt;
*June 22, 2009: &quot;At worst, fanatical tyrants who know that the future is against them may end their present course on their terms: a nuclear holocaust,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iYRv05ebnzTQWCYSxUmqVfbHcMiw AFP: Police fire tear gas as Iran protesters defy Guards warning]&lt;/ref&gt;

==2011 comments==
In February 2011, Pahlavi said after [[2011 Iranian protests|violence erupted]] in Tehran that Iran’s youth were determined to get rid of an authoritarian government tainted by corruption and misrule in the hope of installing a democracy. “Fundamental and necessary change is long overdue for our region and we have a whole generation of young Egyptian and Iranians not willing to take no for an answer,” Pahlavi told the ''[[Daily Telegraph]]''. “Democratisation is now an imperative that cannot be denied. It is only a matter of time before the whole region can transform itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/middleeast/iran/8328855/Irans-Crown-Prince-calls-on-West-to-support-anti-government-protests.html Iran's Crown Prince calls on West to support anti-government protests]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Monarchy==
Following in a line of Iranian monarchic dynasties stretching back 3000 years, the [[Pahlavi dynasty]] was founded early in the twentieth century. The revolution of 1979 led to the replacement of the Iranian constitutional monarchy (de facto absolute monarchy) with an [[Islamic republic]]. Although he currently lives in exile, Pahlavi is still regarded by some Iranians as the current [[Pahlavi dynasty|Shah of Iran]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} After the death of his father, [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi|Mohammad-Rezā Shāh Pahlavi]], Pahlavi symbolically declared himself ''Shāhanshāh'' (Literally, ''[[King of Kings]]'' in Persian) at the age of 21, but now his press releases refer to him as either &quot;Reza Pahlavi&quot; or &quot;the former Crown Prince of Iran&quot;.

===Succession===
{{See|Line of succession to the Iranian throne}}
Succession is theoretical, as the Iranian monarchy was abolished with the Islamic Constitution in Iran in 1980. He is the current contender in the succession line to his late father and [[Ali Patrick Pahlavi]] is the second in line.

==Titles, styles and honours==
{{infobox hrhstyles|
image=[[Image:Imperial Coat of Arms of Iran.svg|centre|60px]]|
royal name=Crown Prince Reza of Iran|
dipstyle=[[His Imperial Highness]]|
offstyle=Your Imperial Highness|
altstyle=Sir|}}

===Titles and styles===
* ''[[His Imperial Highness]]'' The Crown Prince of Iran (1960–1979)
* ''His Imperial Highness'' Crown Prince Reza of Iran (''[[pretender]]'', 1979–present)
* Reza Pahlavi (''commoner name'', 1979&amp;ndash;present)

===Honours===
* Grand Collar of the [[Order of Pahlavi]] (26 September 1967, Iran)
*Mohammad Rezā Shāh Pahlavi Coronation medal (1967, Iran)
*Knight of the [[Order of the Seraphim]] (November 24, 1970, [[Sweden]])
*25th Anniversary medal (1971, Iran)
*Persepolis medal (1971, Iran)
*Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit of the Italian Republic]] (December 15, 1974, Italy)
*He was awarded the [[Royal Order of the Drum]] by [[King Kigeli V of Rwanda|King Kigeli V]] ([[Rwanda]])
*In 2004, Reza Pahlavi was named as the &quot;unofficial [[godparent|godfather]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The [[Roman Catholic Church]], the Church of the child being baptized, does not accept non-Catholics as godparents, given the religious nature of the role, so Pahlavi's role was downgraded to unofficial, not formal.&lt;/ref&gt; of [[Princess Louise of Belgium]] the eighth granddaughter of [[King Albert II of Belgium]]. The decision to choose him was criticized by the Foreign Ministry of the Islamic Republic of Iran.

==Publications==
*Reza Pahlavi, ''IRAN: L’Heure du Choix [IRAN: The Deciding Hour] (Denoël, 2009)''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.fr/dp/2207261034 Amazon.fr]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Reza Pahlavi, ''[[Winds of Change: The Future of Democracy in Iran]]'', [[Regnery Publishing]] Inc., 2002, ISBN 0-89526-191-X.
*Reza Pahlavi, ''Gozashteh va Ayandeh'', London: Kayham Publishing, 2000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rezapahlavi.org Reza Pahlavi´s Web site]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Constitutionalist Party of Iran]]
*[[Shahriar Shafiq]]

==Footnotes==

&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
 See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how
 to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags, and the template below
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Mohammad Reza Pahlavi}}
*[http://www.rezapahlavi.org/ Reza Pahlavi's Official Website]
*[http://www.pahlavi.org/ Pahlavi Dynasty's Website]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-12115006 Shah's Son Killed himself BBC]

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Pahlavi dynasty]]|31 October|1960||}}
{{s-pre}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Farah Pahlavi]]|as=Shahbanu of Iran}}
{{s-tul|title=[[Pahlavi dynasty|Shah of Iran]]|years=July 27, 1981 – present|reason=[[Iranian Revolution|Monarchy abolished in 1979]]}}
{{s-inc|heir=[[Ali Patrick Pahlavi]]}}
{{end}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Pahlavi, Reza
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Last crown prince of the former [[Imperial State of Iran]]
| DATE OF BIRTH     = October 31, 1960
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Tehran]], [[Iran]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pahlavi, Reza}}
[[Category:Heirs apparent who never acceded]]
[[Category:American people of Iranian descent]]
[[Category:Iranian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Iranian royalty]]
[[Category:Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]]
[[Category:Pahlavi dynasty]]
[[Category:People from Potomac, Maryland]]
[[Category:People from Tehran]]
[[Category:1960 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Iranian democracy activists]]
[[Category:University of Southern California alumni]]
[[Category:Current heirs apparent]]
[[Category:Iranian monarchists]]

[[ar:رضا بهلوي الثاني]]
[[cs:Rezá Pahlaví]]
[[da:Reza Pahlavi]]
[[de:Cyrus Reza Pahlavi]]
[[eo:Reza Pahlavi]]
[[fa:رضا پهلوی (دوم)]]
[[fr:Reza Pahlavi (1960-)]]
[[ko:레자 시루스 팔라비]]
[[it:Reza Ciro Pahlavi]]
[[he:רזא כורש עלי פהלווי]]
[[pl:Cyrus Reza Pahlawi]]
[[pt:Reza Pahlavi (Príncipe Imperial)]]
[[sq:Reza Pahlavi]]
[[fi:Reza Kuruš Pahlavi]]
[[sv:Reza Pahlavi II]]
[[th:เจ้าชายเรซา ปาห์ลาวี มกุฎราชกุมารแห่งอิหร่าน]]
[[ur:رضا پہلوی]]
[[zh:禮薩·巴列維]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
