<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="614284" ns="0" title="Sam&#039;s Club"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the RV organization|Good Sam Club}}
{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}{{Infobox company
| name = Sam's Club
| logo =[[File:Sams Club.svg|100px]]
| type = [[Subsidiary]]
| parent = [[Wal-Mart|Wal-Mart Stores, Inc.]]
| industry = [[Retailer|Retail]] [[warehouse club]]
| foundation = {{Start date|1983}}
| location_city = [[Bentonville, Arkansas]]
| location_country = [[United States|U.S.]]
| key_people = [[Mike Duke|Michael T. Duke]], President and [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] of [[Wal-Mart|Wal-Mart Stores, Inc.]] (parent)&lt;br/&gt;Brian C. Cornell, President/CEO of Sam's Club (Division)&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot; /&gt;
| products = [[Merchandising|Merchandise]]
| locations = 602 (U.S.) (FY 2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot; /&gt;
| operating_income = [[United States dollar|US$]]1.6 billion (FY 2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot; /&gt;
| homepage = [http://www.samsclub.com/ samsclub.com]
}}
'''Sam's Club''' is a chain of membership-only retail [[warehouse club]]s owned and operated by [[Wal-Mart|Wal-Mart Stores, Inc.]], founded in 1983 and named after Wal-Mart founder [[Sam Walton]]. {{As of|2008|df=US}}, the Sam's Club chain serves more than 47 million U.S. members.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Sam's Club ranks second in sales volume among warehouse clubs behind [[Costco|Costco Wholesale]], despite the fact that Sam's has more retail locations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hoovers.com/costco-wholesale/--ID__17060--/free-co-factsheet.xhtml |title=Costco Wholesale company profile |work=[[Hoover's]] |date= |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of|2009|1|31|df=US}}, Sam's Club operated 602 membership warehouse clubs in 47 U.S. states ([[Oregon]], [[Rhode Island]] and [[Vermont]] are the only states without a Sam's Club), as well as the American possession of [[Puerto Rico]] and the three foreign countries of [[Brazil]], [[China]] and [[Mexico]].&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.samsclub.com.br/nossas-lojas/sams-no-mundo.php |title=Sam's Club Brazilian website |date= |accessdate=2010-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Locations typically range in size from {{convert|70000|-|190000|sqft|abbr=on}}, with an average club size of approximately {{convert|133000|sqft|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.fdreports.com/samsclub.pdf F&amp;D Reports-Customer &amp; Market Insights&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{Dead link|date=November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Ref improve section|date=November 2009}}
The first Sam's Club opened on April 7, 1983 in [[Midwest City, Oklahoma]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite press release
| url = http://pressroom.samsclub.com/News/8203.aspx
| title = Sam's Club celebrates 25th anniversary with nationwide open house
| date = April 10, 2007
| publisher = Sam's Club
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1989, Sam's entered [[New Jersey]] with a store in [[Delran Township, New Jersey|Delran]] in a former Two Guys/Jefferson Ward/Bradlees store. This was Walmart's first foray into the Northeast. The first Walmart discount store in New Jersey opened in 1991 in Turnersville. The company entered the [[Pennsylvania]] market in 1990.

In 1993, Walmart acquired [[PACE Membership Warehouse]] from [[Kmart]] and converted many (but not all) PACE locations into Sam's Clubs.

The latest flagship store opening {{as of|2007|9|13|df=US|lc=on}} was in [[Fayetteville, Arkansas]]. The largest Sam's Club store is located in [[Pineville, NC]] with {{convert|185000|sqft|abbr=on}} of retail space that was formerly an Incredible Universe.

On September 24, 2006, Sam's Club received a new logo. The new logo has an updated [[serif]] font and features a green and blue diamond inside the big blue diamond, found above the word 'Sam's'.

Sam's Club's previous slogan was &quot;We Are In Business For Small Business&quot; until 2006, the decision to remove the slogan comes as Sam's Club attempts to remove itself from serving just small businesses and open up to more individual customers.

In December 2007. Sam's Club launched a new slogan, &quot;Enjoy the Possibilities&quot;. Since then it became an official advertising slogan, mentioned in television and radio advertisements, but it is not mentioned on its website. As of early January 2008 the &quot;Enjoy the Possibilities&quot; slogan was no longer in use. Sam's Club launched their latest slogan &quot;Savings Made Simple&quot; in the fourth quarter of 2009.

Starting in April 2007 there was speculation of a possible sale or spinoff of Sam's Club from parent company Walmart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Otte |first=Timothy M. |url=http://www.fool.com/investing/value/2007/05/07/spinoff-in-bentonville-revisited.aspx |title=Spinoff in Bentonville Revisited |work=[[The Motley Fool]] |date=2007-05-07 |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Otte |first=Timothy M. |url=http://www.fool.com/investing/value/2007/04/17/a-spinoff-in-bentonville.aspx?vstest=search_042607_linkdefault |title=A Spinoff in Bentonville? |work=[[The Motley Fool]] |date=2007-04-17 |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; At Walmart's 2007 annual shareholder's meeting in June, management said that Sam's Club is not for sale, although they did not say they are not considering a spinoff.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Halkias
| first = Maria
| url = http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/bus/stories/060207dnbuswalmart.36d6e74.html
| title = Wal-Mart cuts expansion plans, focuses on existing stores
| newspaper = [[The Dallas Morning News]]
| date = 2007-06-01
| accessdate = 2009-11-27
}}{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 26, 2009, [[Walmart Canada]] announced that it would close all six of its Canadian Sam's Club locations.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123568673767887129.html
| title = Wal-Mart Canada to Close Sam's Club Division
| newspaper = [[The Wall Street Journal]]
| date = February 26, 2009
| last = Georgiades
| first = Andy
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite press release
| url = http://micro.newswire.ca/release.cgi?rkey=1702264189&amp;view=73403-0&amp;Start=30&amp;htm=0
| title = Wal-Mart Canada to close six Ontario Sam's Club locations to focus on supercentre expansion
| date = February 26, 2009
| publisher = [[Walmart Canada]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url=http://www.thestar.com/business/article/593651
| title=Wal-Mart to close all Canadian Sam's Club stores
| last=Flavelle
| first=Dana
| work=[[Toronto Star]]
| date=February 26, 2009
| accessdate=February 26, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was part of Walmart Canada's decision to shift focus towards supercentre stores, but some industry observers suggested that the operation was struggling in competition with [[Costco]] and the non-membership [[The Real Canadian Superstore]] (known as [[Maxi (supermarket)|Maxi &amp; Cie]] in [[Quebec]]), that had a well-established history in the country.

In January 2010, it was announced that ten stores would be closed, including four in California. At the same time, Sam's will open six new stores at various locations in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-walmart12-2010jan12,0,7246820.story Sam's Club to close 10 stores, four in California] Retrieved 1/11/10&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 24, 2010, it was announced that approximately 11,200 Sam's Club employees would be laid off. The layoffs resulted from the decision to outsource product sampling duties to an outside company (Rogers, Arkansas-based Shopper Events, which already performs in-store product demonstrations for Walmart) and to eliminate New Business Membership Representative positions throughout the chain. Most of the laid-off employees were part-time and represented about 10% of the total Sam's Club workforce.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/us_wal_mart_sam_s_club Wal-Mart cuts about 11,200 Sam's Club staffers]{{dead link|date=May 2011}} Retrieved 1/24/10&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
{{Ref improve section|date=November 2009}}
[[Image:Sam'sClubStore1.jpg|left|thumb|200px|A Sam's Club store in Maplewood, Missouri, a suburb of St. Louis]]
[[File:SamsClubLerdo.jpg|right|thumb|200px|A Sam's Club store in Ciudad Lerdo, Durango]]

Like other warehouse clubs, Sam's Club sells most of its merchandise in [[bulk]] and directly off [[pallet]]s. The clubs are arranged much like [[warehouse]]s, with merchandise stocked in warehouse-style steel bins. {{As of|2009|1|31|df=US}} there were 602 Sam's Clubs in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://walmartstores.com/download/3661.pdf
| title = Walmart FY 2009 Annual Report
| format = PDF
| publisher = [[Wal-Mart|Walmart]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Products sold include jewelry, designer goods, sunglasses, crystal and collectibles, electronics, floral, apparel, food and meats. Most locations have Pharmacy, Tire and Battery, Photo, Bakery, Optical, Café and Floral departments. Sam's Club markets items under the private labels ''Member's Mark'', ''Bakers &amp; Chefs'', and ''Sam's Club'' &amp;mdash; including products by [[Richelieu Foods]],&lt;ref name=&quot;start&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Richelieu experiences hiring boom, starts expansion
 | publisher = WCFcourier.com, RC Balaban, August 27, 2006
 | url = http://wcfcourier.com/business/local/article_eb9bdbf5-8790-5071-9eab-2e82b2085f28.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; a private label manufacturer of frozen pizza, salad dressing, sauces, marinades, condiments and deli salads. Sam's Club does not sell the ''Sam's Choice'' or ''Great Value'' brands, that are available in Wal-mart stores. However Sam's Club is now changing some of the Member's Mark items, such as baby wipes to the name Simply Right. The Member's Mark Deli products is also changing names to Artisan Fresh. Another notable feature in most locations is the presence of stands at which ''Shopper Events'' employees prepare various food products for members to sample before purchasing.

Sam's Club has more than 47 million U.S. members and operates more than 580 clubs nationwide,{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} as well as more than 100 international locations in [[Brazil]], [[China]], and [[Mexico]].{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} There are also stores in the U.S. commonwealth of [[Puerto Rico]].{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

A typical Sam's Club stands between {{convert|71000|sqft|m2}} and {{convert|130000|sqft|m2}}. The Sam's Club division of Wal-Mart Stores, Inc. had total sales revenue of [[United States dollar|US$]]46.9 billion for the fiscal year ending January 31, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;annual_report&quot; /&gt; Sam's primary competitor is [[Costco|Costco Wholesale]].

==Sam's Business Center==
Sam's Club opened their first Business Center in Houston, Texas, in August 2008. Converted from an existing Sam's location, the Business Center is similar in concept to Costco's Business Centers.

A fleet of private trucks offers delivery service within a {{convert|25|mi|km|adj=on}} radius on orders of at least $250. The trucks are capable of storing frozen, refrigerated and dry items.

The Business Center is open from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m. Monday through Saturday, and unlike the Costco Business Centers, that are closed on Sundays, the Sam's Business Center is open 8 a.m. to 2 p.m. Sunday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.retailingtoday.com/uploadedFiles/RetailingTodaycom/Digital_Studio/Special_reports/2008/SpecialReport_SamsHouston.pdf |title=IT'S ALL BUSINESS AT SAM'S CLUB HOUSTON |format=PDF |publisher=Retailing Today |date= |accessdate=2009-11-27}}{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2010, the company announced it would be closing its Business Center, along with nine other clubs across the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myfoxhouston.com/dpp/business/100112-sams-club-houston-closing Sam's Club Closing Houston Location | MyFoxHouston.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other retail formats==
In Houston, Sam's Club opened [[Más Club]] in August 2009,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite press release
| url = http://pressroom.samsclub.com/News/9323.aspx
| title = Más Club Opens August 6 in Houston
| date = July 21, 2009
| publisher = Sam's Club
}}&lt;/ref&gt; a club geared towards the Hispanic population. Membership in Más Club is separate from membership in Sam's Club.&lt;ref&gt;Discount Store News&lt;/ref&gt;

==Membership==
Membership is required to purchase at Sam's Club (except at the cafe, for [[prescription drugs]] where federal law prohibits sales to members only, as well as liquor and gasoline in some states); however, a one-time day pass may be obtained from many Walmart newspaper ads. A 10% surcharge is added (except where forbidden by local laws) to the prices for non-members, except for optical, pharmacy, cafe, or alcohol items where available. All memberships are 100% refundable at any time for any reason, even on the date that it is to be renewed.

Renewal of memberships can be done via the internet, through the mail, in-club at the Membership Services desk, any cash register, and also at the new ATM/Membership kiosks (the latter only available in select locations).

In the United States, Sam's Club memberships are divided into three categories: Business, Advantage, and Plus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.samsclub.com/|title=Sam's Club membership options |publisher=Sam's Club |date= |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Plus membership offers discounts and deals for a few services and products within Sam's (similar to free 12-month extended warranty for every extended warranty purchased) and more offered for outside goods and services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.samsclub.com/shopping/navigate.do?catg=12754 Sam's Club Business Membership Comparison], Sam's Club&lt;/ref&gt; As with the Advantage and Business memberships, Plus memberships are 100% refundable.

==Payment options and store credit products==
[[Image:Sams Club interior.jpg|thumb|A Sam's Club in California.]]
[[Image:Samsclub gasstation.JPG|thumb|right|Some Sam's Clubs include gas stations]]

===Payment options===
Sam's Club locations accept Sam's Club and Wal-mart Credit Cards,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askmrcreditcard.com/walmartcreditcard.html Review of Wal-mart Credit Card]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Discover Card]], [[MasterCard]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://money.cnn.com/2006/11/09/news/companies/sams_club/index.htm |title=Sam's Club opens door to MasterCard payments |work=CNNMoney.com |date=2006-11-09 |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[debit card]]s, Wal-mart and Sam's Club gift cards, cash or checks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://samshelpcenter.custhelp.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/193 What payment methods do you accept at Sam's Club?]&lt;/ref&gt; {{As of|2009|3|df=US}} [[Electronic Benefit Transfer|EBT]] [[Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program|SNAP]] benefits are accepted.&lt;ref&gt;[http://samshelpcenter.custhelp.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/194 Does Sam's Club accept SNAP (Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program) cards?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://wcco.com/consumer/sams.club.ebt.2.938281.html?detectflash=false Some Sam's Club Stores Now Accepting EBT Cards]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; MasterCard was added as an option on November 9, 2006. [[Visa Inc.|Visa]] credit cards are still not accepted, because of the high processing fees compared with Wal-mart's discounted rates with Mastercard,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitaltransactions.net/newsstory.cfm?newsid=1157 Pricing, Retailing Rivalry Likely Led to Sam's Club's MasterCard Deal]&lt;/ref&gt; although in the past it was accepted during testing periods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-115423782.html |title=SAM'S CLUB WILL STOP ACCEPTING VISA AND MASTERCARD CREDIT CARDS APRIL 21 |work=Highbeam.com |date=2004-04-16 |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; However Visa [[debit card]]s are accepted in most clubs. [[American Express]] is not accepted. Their online website, samsclub.com, accepts Visa, MasterCard, American Express, or Discover Card.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.samsclub.com/shopping/navigate.do?catg=7059 Sam's Club Business Membership rules], Sam's Club&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sam's Club credit ===
Sam's Club offers store credit lines to individuals and businesses linked to the member's membership card. Sam's Club also offers a Sam's Club Discover Card&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.samsclub.com/shopping/navigate.do?catg=11039 |title=Sam's Club credit cards |publisher=Sam's Club |date= |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://creditcards.lovetoknow.com/Sam's_Club_Credit |title=Sam's Club Credit Cards |work=LoveToKnow Credit Cards |date=2008-10-06 |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; that can be used at Sam's Club and anywhere Discover Cards are accepted, Advantage and Business Members can receive up to 1% cash rewards from the Sam's Club Discover and Advantage/Business Plus members can receive up to 2% cash rewards. The Sam's Discover card replaces the member's regular membership card.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://creditshout.com/sams-club-credit-card-review/ |title=Sams Club Credit Card Review |work=CreditShout |date= |accessdate=2009-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Arkansas|Companies|Business and economics}}
*[[Costco|Costco Wholesale]] - national US competitor
*[[BJ's Wholesale Club]] - competitor in eastern US
*[[Wal-Mart|Wal-Mart Stores Inc.]] - owner
*[[Más Club]]
*[[Warehouse club]]

&lt;br /&gt;
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*{{official|http://www.samsclub.com/}}
*[http://www.samsclub.com.mx/ Sam's Club Mexico]
*[http://www.samsclub.com.br/ Sam's Club Brazil]

{{Wal-Mart}}

[[Category:Companies based in Arkansas]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1983]]
[[Category:Discount stores of the United States]]
[[Category:Multinational companies]]
[[Category:Online retail companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Retail companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Supermarkets of the United States]]
[[Category:Walmart]]

[[pt:Sam's Club]]
[[ru:Sam's Club]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
