<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="616842" ns="0" title="Food Network"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about||the website|The Food Channel|the concept in ecological science|food chain|other uses|Food network (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox TV channel
| name           = Food Network
| logofile       = Food Network.svg
| logoalt        = 
| logosize       = 200px
| logocaption    = 
| slogan         = ''Way More Than Cooking''
| launch         = November 23, 1993
| founder        = [[Jack C. Clifford]]
| owner          = [[Scripps Networks Interactive|Scripps Networks]] (70%)&lt;br&gt;[[Tribune Company]] (30%)
| headquarters   = [[New York City|New York City, New York]]
| sister names   = [[Cooking Channel]]&lt;br&gt;[[DIY Network]]&lt;br&gt;[[Great American Country]]&lt;br&gt;[[HGTV]]&lt;br&gt;[[Travel Channel]]
| picture format = [[480i]] (SD)&lt;br&gt;[[1080i]] (HD)
| web            = http://www.foodnetwork.com
| terr avail     =
| terr serv 1    = [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]]&lt;br&gt;(UK)
| terr chan 1    = Channel 49&lt;br&gt;(18:00-22:00 only)
| sat serv 1     = [[DirecTV]]
| sat chan 1     = 231 (SD/HD)&lt;br&gt; 1231 ([[Video on demand|VOD]])
| sat serv 2     = [[Dish Network]]
| sat chan 2     = 110 (SD/HD)&lt;br&gt;9462 (HD)
| sat serv 4     = [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]]&lt;br&gt;(UK &amp; Ireland)
| sat chan 4     = Channel 262 &lt;br&gt; Channel 263 (+1)
| sat serv 5     = [[Freesat]]&lt;br&gt;(UK)
| sat chan 5     = Channel 405 &lt;br&gt; Channel 406 (+1)&lt;br&gt;
| sat serv 6     = [[DStv]]
| sat chan 6     = Channel 185&lt;br&gt;
| cable serv 1   = Available on most cable systems
| cable chan 1   = Check local listings
| cable serv 2   = [[UPC Ireland]]&lt;br&gt;(Ireland)
| cable chan 2   = Channel 508
| online serv 1  = [[Meo (Portugal)|Meo Online]]
| online chan 1  = [http://www.meo.pt/ver/oquee/Pages/oquee.aspx Watch live] (Portugal only)
}}

'''Food Network''' is a television [[specialty channel]]  that airs both one-time and recurring (episodic) programs about food and cooking. [[Scripps Networks Interactive]] owns 70 percent of the network, with [[Tribune Company]] controlling the remaining 30 percent.

The network is seen in more than ninety million households. In addition to [[New York City]], it has offices in [[Atlanta]], [[Los Angeles]], [[San Francisco]], [[Chicago]], [[Detroit]], [[Jersey City]], and [[Knoxville, Tennessee]].

== History ==
Food Network was founded on April 19, 1993 as '''TV Food Network''', and launched on November 23 of that year; its legal name is still Television Food Network, G.P. Within a few years, the network had shortened its on-air brand name. It was created by [[Reese Schonfeld]] (one of the founders of [[CNN]]), under the direction of Trygve Myrhen, President of ''[[The Providence Journal]]''. Its original partners included the Journal itself, [[Adelphia Communications|Adelphia]], [[Scripps-Howard]], [[Continental Cablevision]], [[Cablevision]], and most importantly, Chicago's [[Tribune Company]], which provided the network's technical output.

Schonfeld, who was also a partner in the company, was appointed its Managing Director and sat on its management board along with two [[Providence Journal]] employees. The original lineup for the network included [[Emeril Lagasse]] ([[Essence of Emeril]]), [[Debbi Fields]], [[Donna Hanover]], [[David Rosengarten]],  Curtis Aikens, Dr. Louis Arrone, [[Jacques Pépin]] and [[Robin Leach]]. The next year the network acquired the rights to the [[Julia Child]] library from [[WGBH-TV|WGBH]]. In 1995, Schonfeld resigned as managing director of the network, but remained on its board until 1998, when he sold his interest in the company to Scripps.

The Food Network had been acquired from the [[A. H. Belo Corp.]] Corporation by the [[E. W. Scripps Company]] in 1997, trading [[KRDY|KENS-AM]]/[[KENS-TV|TV]] in [[San Antonio, Texas]], for it. Belo had acquired the network when it purchased The Providence Journal Company in 1996. Myrhen left the Journal company the following year. In March 2009, the Food Network launched a re-purposed Food.com as a bookmarking site that lets users aggregate and search for recipes from different sources online.

Food Network was first launched internationally in the UK on November 9, 2009, and in Asia on July 5, 2010 (on [[StarHub TV]]'s Channel 433 and Channel 468 for the HD version of [[Food Network Asia]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foodbusinessnews.net Food Business News: Schroeder, Eric &quot;Food Network to launch in international markets&quot; November 4, 2009. ''(Registration required to view entire article.)'']&lt;/ref&gt; Since the UK launch on November 9, 2009 on [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/news/a180719/food-network-coming-to-sky.html|title=Food Network coming to Sky|publisher=Digital Spy|date=October 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; the channel has been added to the [[Freesat]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/news/a191318/food-network-launches-on-freesat.html|title=Food Network launches on Freesat|publisher=Digital Spy|date=December 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/news/a328608/food-network-to-launch-on-freeview.html|title=Food Network to launch on Freeview|publishher=Digital Spy|date=July 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; platforms.

==Programming==
{{see|List of programs broadcast by the Food Network}}

Food Network programming is divided into [[Daytime television|daytime]] coverage known as &quot;Food Network in the Kitchen&quot; and [[primetime]] coverage the network calls &quot;Food Network Nighttime&quot;. Generally, &quot;In the Kitchen&quot; is dedicated to instructional cooking programs while &quot;Nighttime&quot; features food-related entertainment programs, such as cooking competitions, food-related travel shows, and reality shows. Promos identify &quot;Food Network Nighttime&quot; programming but not daytime programming. Many of the channel's personalities routinely pull double-duty (or more) &amp;mdash; hosting both daytime and nighttime programming &amp;mdash; and the channel regularly offers specials which typically either follow its personalities on working vacations, or bring together a number of personalities for a themed cooking event. 

[[Image:Food Network 2000.svg|thumb|left|180px|Former logo, used from 1996 to December 31, 2002.]]
[[Mario Batali]] and [[Bobby Flay]] joined the network in 1995.  In 1996 Joe Langhan, an executive producer at The Food Network, created ''[[Emeril Live|Emeril Live!]]'', which became the channel's signature series. Among other duties, Flay and Batali now appear regularly on ''[[Iron Chef America]]'', the channel's well-received remake of the original Japanese series. ''America's'' host, [[Alton Brown]], gained a cult following for his ''[[Good Eats]]'', which mixes science, cooking and offbeat humor. Currently the channel's biggest cross-over star is [[Rachael Ray]], who has parlayed her cable following (primarily through the series ''[[30 Minute Meals]]'' and ''[[$40 a Day]]'') into a ''[[Rachael Ray (TV series)|syndicated talk show]]''.

Beginning in 2005, an annual reality contest, ''[[The Next Food Network Star]]'', has brought viewers to New York to compete for their own show. Previous winners include Dan Smith and Steve McDonagh (''[[Party Line with The Hearty Boys]]''), [[Guy Fieri]] (''[[Guy's Big Bite]]'', ''[[Diners, Drive-Ins and Dives]]'', &quot;Guy Off the Hook,&quot; &quot;Ultimate Recipe Showdown,&quot; &quot;Guy's Big Night,&quot; &quot;Guy's Family Feast&quot;), [[Amy Finley]] (''[[The Gourmet Next Door]]''), [[Aaron McCargo, Jr.]] (''[[Big Daddy's House]]''),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foodnetwork.com/food/show_am/article/0,3201,FOOD_32117_5909447_,00.html|title= Aaron McCargo, Jr.|accessdate=2008-07-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080805013931/http://www.foodnetwork.com/food/show_am/article/0,3201,FOOD_32117_5909447_,00.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Melissa d'Arabian]] (''[[Ten Dollar Dinners]]'') and [[Aarti Sequeira]] (''Aarti Party'').&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Slezak |first=Michael |title='Next Food Network Star' season finale recap: And the winner is... |work=[[Entertainment Weekly]] |date=August 16, 2010 |url=http://popwatch.ew.com/2010/08/16/next-food-network-star-season-finale-recap/ |accessdate=August 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the 2010 season, the Next Food Network Star has relocated to Los Angeles.

In accordance with an agreement between Scripps and [[Chellomedia]], Food Network programs started to air abroad in the fourth quarter of 2009 in the United Kingdom and then in other markets in early 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news |title=Scripps, Chello to launch Food Network overseas |url=http://cincinnati.bizjournals.com/cincinnati/stories/2009/10/05/daily1.html |work=Business Courier of Cincinnati |date=October 5, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Food Network HD==
[[Image:Food Network HD Logo.svg|50px|right|frame|thumb|Food Network HD logo]]'''Food Network HD''' is a [[1080i]] [[High-definition television|high definition]] simulcast of Food Network. It originally aired a different lineup than the SD version, with only HD programs. On March 31, 2008 Food Network (along with [[HGTV]]) relaunched an HD [[simulcast]] of its standard definition feed. As a result, the programming is now identical on both channels, with [[Heterodyne#Up and down converters|upconverted]]  and [[Stretch-o-Vision|stretched]] versions of standard definition programs being shown when no high definition version is available.
Some cable companies broadcast the HD versions of programming on the east coast time slot (similar to satellite practices) with the SD version being broadcast in its normal timeslot. This only impacts cable networks and does not change local programming.

==Food Network video game==
Food Network has released ''[[Food Network: Cook or Be Cooked|Cook or Be Cooked]]'', a video game for the [[Wii]] console. The game, which was developed by [[Namco]], simulates real cooking experiences and was released on November 3, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Nelson, Randy |title=Joystiq impressions: Food Network: Cook or Be Cooked |url=http://www.joystiq.com/2009/04/30/joystiq-impressions-food-network-cook-or-be-cooked/ |work=Joystiq.com | date=April 30, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news |author=Brion, Raphael |title=Upcoming: Food Network's Cook or Be Cooked Video Game |url=http://www.eatmedaily.com/2009/10/upcoming-food-networks-cook-or-be-cooked-video-game/ |work=EatMeDaily.com |date=October 22, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Players can also try out the recipes featured on the game.

==Carriage disputes==
===Dispute with Cablevision===
On January 1, 2010 [[HGTV]] and Food Network were removed from [[Cablevision]], a major cable company with systems serving areas surrounding [[New York City]]. Scripps removed HGTV and Food Network from Cablevision's programming following the expiration of their contract on December 31, 2009. Cablevision and Scripps had been in negotiations for several months to agree on a new contract, but no progress had been made and the two stations remained off the air for Cablevision customers. The discontinuance of Food Network from Cablevision led them to make arrangements with Tribune-owned [[WPIX]] in New York and [[WCCT-TV|WTXX]] in [[Hartford, Connecticut]] to carry a special episode of ''[[Iron Chef America]]'' with First Lady [[Michelle Obama]] on Sunday, January 10, 2010, after that episode enjoyed high ratings on its January 3 Food Network broadcast.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704160504574641202605830242.html?mod=googlenews_wsj Wall Street Journal: &quot;Scripps to Offer Free Show In Fight With Cablevision&quot;, January 6, 2010. ''(Subscription required to view entire article.)'']&lt;/ref&gt;
On January 21, 2010 Cablevision and Scripps came to an agreement and Food Network and HGTV were put back on the air that day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thewrap.com/article/scripps-cablevision-strike-deal-return-food-network-hgtv-subscribers-13344 Scripps, Cablevision Deal Returns Food Network, HGTV to Subscribers], ''The Wrap'', January 21, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dispute with AT&amp;T===
[[AT&amp;T U-verse]] dropped Food Network, [[Cooking Channel]], [[HGTV]], [[DIY Network]] and [[Great American Country]] on November 5, 2010;&lt;ref&gt;[http://leisureblogs.chicagotribune.com/thestew/2010/11/atts-u-verse-drops-food-network-hgtv-and-other-scripps-networks.html AT&amp;T's U-verse Drops Food Network, HGTV and Other Scripps Networks], ''Chicago Tribune'', November 5, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; two days later, on November 7, 2010, the dispute was resolved.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2010-11-07/business/ct-biz-att-uverse-1108-20101107_1_u-verse-customers-at-t-u-verse-scripps-networks Food Network, HGTV, Back on U-verse], ''Chicago Tribune'', November 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.multichannel.com/article/459564-AT_T_U_Verse_Scripps_Reconnect_On_Carriage_Contract.php AT&amp;T U-verse, Scripps Reconnect on Carriage Contract], ''MultiChannel News'', November 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media comment==
In December 2007 ''[[The New York Times]]'' business section published an article on the end of Emeril Lagasse's show ''Emeril Live'' and quoted Brooke Johnson, the president as saying that  Lagasse &quot;remains a valued member of the Food Network family&quot;.&lt;ref name=jensen/&gt;

Derek Baine, senior analyst at the media research firm SNL Kagan, is reported to have commented, &quot;It's not surprising that people move on&quot;. &quot;They pay almost nothing for the people as they are building their careers&quot;.  &quot;That's been their strategy all along&quot;.&lt;ref name=jensen/&gt; 

The article also commented on the declining popularity of the Food Network whose day ratings it reported had fallen &quot;to an average of 544,000 people from 580,000 a year ago&quot;. It noted, &quot;More significant, its signature weekend block of instructional programs, known collectively as 'In the Kitchen,' has lost 15 percent of its audience in the last year, to 830,000 viewers on average. This had left the network owing refunds, known as 'make goods,' to advertisers.&quot;&lt;ref name=jensen&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/17/business/media/17food.html Changing Courses at the Food Network], ''New York Times'', December 17, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Erica Gruen, former president and CEO of the Food Network (1995–1998) who created ''Emeril Live'' during her tenure, was reported to have blamed the decline on increased competition, &quot;There's all sorts of instructional cooking video on the Web&quot;.&lt;ref name=jensen/&gt;

But it reported that, &quot;Bob Tuschman, Food Network's senior vice president for programming and production, said the weekend ratings drop was 'nothing we haven't anticipated'.  He said the network's ratings in that time period grew by double digits in each of the last four years, growth that could not be sustained.&quot;&lt;ref name=jensen/&gt;

It also wrote, &quot;About a year ago, the Food Network began aggressively trying to change that with new deals that were 'way more onerous' from the stars' point of view, said a person who has been affected by the changing strategy, by insisting on a stake in book deals and licensing ventures, and control over outside activities.&lt;ref name=jensen/&gt;

Similar to the departure of Emeril Lagasse was that of [[David Rosengarten]].  In the foreword to his book ''Taste'', Erica Gruen noted that the show had been the very first in-house production at Food Network and had become its most popular show. Yet after her departure at the end of 1998, the show was relegated to a 1:00 am broadcast time resulting in its inevitable drop in ratings and final demise.  This strange and, on the surface, contrary to interest conduct by the network has never been explained.&lt;ref&gt;David Rosengarten (1998), ''Taste: One Palate's Journey through the World's Greatest Dishes'', [[Television Food Network]], [[Random House]] ISBN 0-375-75265-X&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of programs broadcast by the Food Network]]
*[[Food Network (Canada)]]
*[[List of Dish Network channels]]
*[[List of DirecTV channels]]
*[[The Food Network Awards]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{official|http://www.foodnetwork.com}}
*[http://www.foodnetwork.com/food/hdtv/0,2857,FOOD_26756,00.html Food Network HD]
*[http://www.foodtv.ca/ Food Network Canada]
*[http://www.foodnetwork.co.uk/ Food Network UK]

{{SCRIPPS NET}}
{{Tribune Company}}
[[Category:Food Network| ]]
[[Category:Scripps Cable Networks]]
[[Category:Food and drink media]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1993]]
[[Category:English-language television stations in the United States]]

[[cs:Food Network]]
[[de:Food Network]]
[[es:Food Network]]
[[fr:Food Network]]
[[hi:फुड नेटवर्क]]
[[kn:ಫುಡ್ ನೆಟ್ವರ್ಕ್]]
[[pt:Food Network Canada]]
[[simple:Food Network]]
[[te:ఫుడ్ నెట్‌వర్క్]]
[[zh:美食頻道 (美國)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
