<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6173965" ns="0" title="Cannibalism in popular culture"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues | cleanup-reorganize = September 2011 | copy edit = September 2011 | refimprove = September 2011 | lead too short = September 2011}}
{{In popular culture | date = September 2011}}
'''[[Cannibalism]]''' is a recurring theme '''in popular culture''', especially within the [[horror genre]].

==In literature, film and television==
===As a cultural norm===
In many popular culture works that depict cannibalism, the act has been the cultural norm for a tribe or group of people, normally located in [[South America]]. Usually, the cannibalism has been used as an expression of a tribe's primitive savagery. 

An early literary example is provided by [[Herman Melville]]'s ''[[Typee]]'', a semi-factual account of Melville's voyage to the Pacific Island of [[Nuku Hiva]], where he spent several weeks living among the island's cannibal inhabitants before fleeing for of fear of being eaten.

The theme of cannibal tribes has been exploited by many [[horror film]]s, known as [[cannibal films]]. A common premise of these films concerns the discovery of such tribes by documentary filmmakers or [[anthropologists]]. These films were especially popular through the work of Italian filmmakers in the 1970s and 1980s. The first major film of this type was [[Umberto Lenzi]]'s 1972 film ''[[Il Paese del Sesso Selvaggio]]'' (''The Man from the Deep River''). This inspired other filmmakers to create cannibal films, with the genre reaching its peak in [[cannibal boom]] of 1977 to 1981. The most prolific of these films was [[Ruggero Deodato]]'s controversial ''[[Cannibal Holocaust]]'' (1980), which influenced later cannibal movies, some of which adopted the moniker ''Cannibal Holocaust II'' in homage to Deodato's original. Other significant films from the 'cannibal boom' years include ''[[Ultimo mondo cannibale]]'' (1977) and ''[[Cannibal Ferox]]'' (1981).

Other later horror films have also included cannibal tribes or groups. A notable example is [[The Hills Have Eyes (series)|''The Hills Have Eyes'' series]] of films, which features a [[Jupiters Clan|clan]] of cannibalistic savages. ''[[Wrong Turn]]'' and [[Wrong Turn 2|its sequel]] features a cannibalistic group of [[mountain man|mountain men]].

The 1971 film ''Como Era Gostoso o Meu Francês'' (''[[How Tasty Was My Little Frenchman]]'') by [[Nelson Pereira dos Santos]], set in the 16th century, details the alleged cannibalistic practices of the indigenous [[Tupi people|Tupi]]namba warrior tribe against [[French people|French]] and [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] colonizers.

A different example of cannibal culture in literature is found in the science fiction novel ''[[Stranger in a Strange Land]]'' (1961) by [[Robert A. Heinlein]], where some human culture is transformed as a result of the [[Martian]]s practice of eating one's dead friends as an act of great respect. This novel provided the inspiration for [[The Police]] song &quot;Friends&quot;, which appeared as a B-side on the UK single &quot;[[Don't Stand So Close to Me]]&quot; and the US single of &quot;[[De Do Do Do, De Da Da Da]]&quot;.

Some stories with talking animals or other sentient species consider it equivalent to cannibalism to eat another sentient creature, even one of a different species. An example is [[C. S. Lewis]]'s [[The Silver Chair]], in which the protagonists are horrified to discover that a certain group of giants condones the consumption of humans and talking animals.

In the [[Anne Rice]] novel, ''[[The Queen of the Damned]]'', many references are made to an ancient culture who practiced necro-cannibalism from the belief that the eating of their loved ones' remains was a more fitting funeral rite than either burying or burning them.

===As a means of survival===
[[Image:Accidente 1972.jpg|right|thumb|The wreckage of the Uruguayan Air Force Flight 571]]
Historically, cannibalism was sometimes practised as a last resort by people suffering from famine, and this theme has been used in popular culture. Indeed, occasionally, true stories of such acts of cannibalism have been portrayed. One example is of the 
1972 story of the survivors of [[Uruguayan Air Force Flight 571]], who resorted to cannibalism in order to survive. The story of the survivors was chronicled in [[Piers Paul Read]]'s 1974 book, ''[[Alive: The Story of the Andes Survivors]]'', in a 1993 film adaptation of the book, called simply [[Alive (1993 film)|''Alive'']], and in a 2008 documentary:  [[Stranded: I Have Come from a Plane That Crashed in the Mountains|''Stranded: I’ve Come From a Plane That Crashed on the Mountains'']]. 

Two other similar stories that have provided inspiration for popular culture adaptations are the accounts of [[Alferd Packer]] and the [[Donner Party]], both involving people eating human flesh in order to survive snowbound entrapment in the mountains. The 1999 film ''[[Ravenous]]'' combines elements of both stories. The tale of Packer is retold, with artistic liberty, in the 1980 film ''[[The Legend of Alfred Packer]]'' and in [[Trey Parker]]'s black comedy ''[[Cannibal! The Musical]]''.

A slightly different example is that of ''[[Survivor Type]]'', a short story by [[Stephen King]], which follows a shipwrecked victim stranded on a remote island, who is driven to eating his own body parts in order to survive. This story can also be seen in the manga [[One Piece]] where ship's cook Zeff and protagonist Sanji are stranded on a barren cliff in the middle of the sea. Zeff cuts off one leg and eats it while Sanji keeps the food that they managed to salvage from the shipwreck they were sailing on before.

[[Post-apocalyptic]] narratives have also featured cannibalism as a means of survival. The 1991 French film ''[[Delicatessen (film)|Delicatessen]]'' is set in an apartment block led by a butcher who deals with the food crisis by luring new tenants to the apartment, killing them, and serving them as meat to the other residents. In the 2006 post-apocalyptic [[zombie]] horror novel ''[[World War Z]]'' by [[Max Brooks]], many Americans head north into [[Canada]] to escape the [[undead]], the under-prepared survivors are forced into cannibalizing the dead in order to survive the harsh winters. In [[Cormac McCarthy]]'s novel ''[[The Road]]'', some of the survivors in the post-apocalyptic United States practice cannibalism as nearly all other sources of food (animals, plant life), have been destroyed.

===Unaware cannibals===
Sometimes, those eating the flesh of other humans in popular culture depictions are unaware of their cannibalistic acts, having been served it as a meal by a murderous cannibal host.

One of the oldest examples is [[Tantalus]] from [[Greek mythology]], who served the Olympian gods the flesh of his son, [[Pelops]]. None of the gods were fooled except [[Demeter]], who ate part of his shoulder. Pelops was resurrected, and his shoulder replaced with ivory. As for Tantalus, he was famously punished by being placed in a pool of water under a fruit tree. Whenever he tried to eat the fruit or drink the water, they moved away.

Another early example appears in [[William Shakespeare]]'s late sixteenth century play ''[[Titus Andronicus]]'', where the character Tamora is unknowingly served a pie made from the remains of her two sons. Another literary occurrence is in [[Fannie Flagg]]'s novel ''[[Fried Green Tomatoes at the Whistle Stop Cafe]]'', in which investigators are unknowingly fed the [[barbecue]]d ribs of a man whose murder they are investigating.

Lu Xun's Diary of a Madman, is premised on the notion that those who are eating flesh don't know it.  Hence the Madman is mad only insofar as those who participate in cannibalism are unaware of it.

In cinema, the most notable example is in the 1973 science fiction film ''[[Soylent Green]]''. In the movie, the Soylent Corporation produces rations of small green wafers in response to the food crisis. These wafers are advertised as being produced from &quot;high-energy plankton&quot;, but are actually the processed remains of human corpses. This film was parodied in the third segment of ''[[The Simpsons]]'' episode &quot;[[Treehouse of Horror V]]&quot; (&quot;[[Nightmare Cafeteria]]&quot;), in which the teachers at [[Springfield Elementary School]] begin to eat children in response to overcrowding in detention, and serve the students' remains in the cafeteria.

This theme has also been used in parodies and [[black comedies]], for its humorous value of [[dramatic irony]]. In the 1987 film ''[[Eat the Rich (film)|Eat the Rich]]'', a disgruntled waiter and his friends kill the management and arrogant clientele of a restaurant and feed the bodies to unsuspecting customers. The 1975 musical parody ''[[The Rocky Horror Picture Show]]'' also features this form of cannibalism, as Dr. Frank N. Furter kills the character Eddie and serves his flesh to his dinner guests.

In a the Series 7 Episode of the popular British sitcom ''[[Red Dwarf]]'', &quot;[[Tikka to Ride]]&quot;, [[Dave Lister]] and [[Cat (Red Dwarf)|The Cat]] unknowingly (at first) eat the corpse of a dead man, which was cooked for them by the robot [[Kryten]]. His excuse was that &quot;if humans eat chickens, obviously they would eat their own species, otherwise they would just be picking on the chickens&quot;.

The people in ''[[Sweeney Todd (disambiguation)|Sweeney Todd]]'' eat meat pies made of humans killed by [[Sweeney Todd|Benjamin Barker]] (Sweeney Todd) with the aid of [[Mrs. Lovett]].

In [[C. S. Lewis]]'s [[The Silver Chair]], the protagonists (two children and a Marsh-wiggle) stay in a castle of Narnian giants, who serve them [[venison]]. It is revealed that the venison came from a talking stag, which in Narnia is tantamount to cannibalism. Later, the heroes find a cookbook with recipes for Man and Marsh-wiggle, similar to the plot of [[To Serve Man]].

In the 2001 episode of the [[Animation|animated]] [[Situational comedy|sitcom]] ''[[South Park]]'', entitled &quot;[[Scott Tenorman Must Die]]&quot;, a main character named [[Eric Cartman]] feeds a high schooler's (Scott Tenorman) parents to him after getting them killed by a man who kills trespassers as revenge for Tenorman making Cartman buy his pubes for $16.00. Cartman had ground Tenorman's parents into chili, and had him eat it, which he initially enjoyed.

===As an accompaniment to killing===
Sometimes films are influenced by the morbid fascination surrounding real-life cases of cannibal murderers. 

The [[Armin Meiwes]] cannibalism case in Germany provided the inspiration for many feature films. The 2007 film ''[[Rohtenburg]]'' recounts a story of an American [[criminal psychology]] student in Germany, who decides to study cannibal killer Oliver Hartwin for her thesis. Hartwin, who fulfills his dream of eating a willing victim found on the Internet, is modelled on Meiwes, causing the film to initially be banned in Germany when Meiwes complained that his personal rights were being violated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/04/movies/MoviesFeatures/04cann.html?_r=1|title=Cannibal wins ban of film in Germany |last=Landler|first=Mark|date=2006-03-04|work=[[New York Times]]|accessdate=2009-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2006 film ''[[Cannibal (film)|Cannibal]]'', which reconstructed the event, was also banned in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{imdb title|0910548}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other films based on the case include [[Rosa von Praunheim]]'s ''Dein Herz in Meinem Hirn'' (''Your Heart in My Brain'') and [[Ulli Lommel]]'s ''Diary of a Cannibal'' (2006). Brett Leonard's 2005 movie &quot;Feed&quot; references the Meiwes case in its opening scene.

Another murderer who influenced the creation of a fictional cannibal antagonist is [[Ed Gein]], who served as the inspiration for the characters of [[Norman Bates]] in ''[[Psycho (1960 film)]]'', Ezra Cobb in ''[[Deranged]]'' and [[Leatherface]] in ''[[The Texas Chain Saw Massacre]]'' (1974) and its sequels. Although Gein was not actually a cannibal himself, he did make various items out of the remains of humans. Leatherface wears a mask fashioned from human flesh and lives with a family of cannibals.

Another notable cannibalistic serial killer is [[Hannibal Lecter]], a fictional character created by author [[Thomas Harris]]. Lecter appears in the novels ''[[Red Dragon (novel)|Red Dragon]]'' (1981), ''[[The Silence of the Lambs (novel)|The Silence of the Lambs]]'' (1988), ''[[Hannibal (novel)|Hannibal]]'' (1999) and ''[[Hannibal Rising]]'' (2006). When ''Red Dragon'' was first adapted as the film ''[[Manhunter (film)|Manhunter]]'' (1986), Lecter, as portrayed by [[Brian Cox (actor)|Brian Cox]], was not presented as a cannibal. In later adaptations, such as  ''[[The Silence of the Lambs (film)|The Silence of the Lambs]]'' (1991), wherein the character is played by [[Anthony Hopkins|Sir Anthony Hopkins]], Lecter's cannibalistic tendencies are made more explicit, earning him the nickname &quot;Hannibal the Cannibal&quot;.

===In science fiction===
In addition to the aforementioned uses, occasionally works of science fiction include elements of cannibalism that serve another purpose. For example, in ''[[The Book of the New Sun]]'' by [[Gene Wolfe]], cannibalism and drugs are used in order to gain the memories of dead people. In the book ''[[Peeps (novel)|Peeps]]'' by [[Scott Westerfeld]], people become cannibals when they are infected by a parasite. The post-apocalyptic novel ''[[Lucifer's Hammer]]'' by [[Larry Niven]] and [[Jerry Pournelle]], features a band of survivors from a comet impact turning to cannibalism not only as a means of food, but also as a way of binding members to their group.  ''[[Courtship Rite]]'' by  [[Donald Kingsbury]] explores a human culture planted on a world whose biochemistry is toxic to humans.  Cannibalism is an essential part of both social and religious life, as food is a precious commodity and the only significant source of meat are the humans themselves.

==In music==

&quot;Congo Man&quot;, a calypso song recorded in 1965 by [[Mighty Sparrow]], features a &quot;cannibal headhunter&quot; who preys on white people.  The singer envies the titular character, because &quot;he eat until his belly upset,&quot; while &quot;I never eat white meat yet.&quot;

In 1971, a [[Rupert Holmes]]-composed pop song named &quot;[[Timothy (song)|Timothy]]&quot; by [[The Buoys]] cryptically told the tale of two trapped miners who apparently resort to eating their companion.  After being banned on many radio stations, &quot;Timothy&quot; rose to no. 17 on the Billboard charts.  Later that year, [[Grace Slick]] of [[Jefferson Airplane]] explored the concept of cannibalism in a tongue-in-cheek rock song named &quot;Silver Spoon.&quot;  The song appeared on ''[[Sunfighter]],'' a non-group album issued by Slick and bandmate [[Paul Kantner]].     

&quot;Mr. Green Genes&quot; by [[Frank Zappa]] (from the [[The Mothers of Invention|Mothers of Invention]] album ''[[Uncle Meat]]'') makes a humorous reference to cannibalism: ''&quot;Eat the truck &amp; driver / And his gloves / NUTRITIOUSNESS! DELICIOUSNESS! WORTHLESSNESS!&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://globalia.net/donlope/fz/lyrics/Uncle_Meat.html#Green Uncle Meat&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[Heavy metal music|heavy metal]], especially [[death metal]] and [[grindcore]], bands (As well as [[horrorcore]] rappers) discuss cannibalism in their songs, or depict it on the cover art of their albums, because of the act's taboo nature. Sometimes bands are inspired by particular cases of cannibalism.

American death metal band [[Cannibal Corpse]] are one notable example. [[Eaten Back to Life|Their first album]], according to the inlay, was dedicated to &quot;the memory of Alfred Packer, the first American cannibal (R.I.P.)&quot;; their third album, ''[[Tomb of the Mutilated]]'', features quotations from serial killer and cannibal [[Albert Fish]] in the liner notes. Many of their songs make use of cannibalistic imagery, such as &quot;Edible Autopsy&quot;. The band [[Pungent Stench]] have also frequently dealt with cannibalism, most extensively on their 1990 EP ''For God Your Soul...For Me Your Flesh''.

The [[Armin Meiwes]] cannibalism case in Germany provided the inspiration for a number of metal bands. Rammstein's 2004 single &quot;[[Mein Teil]]&quot;, which featured the refrain &quot;you are what you eat,&quot; was based on the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rammsteinniccage.com/media/press/timesonlinejan05en.html|title=Shock'n'roll circus|date=2005-01-29|work=[[The Times]]|accessdate=2009-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vocalist [[Till Lindemann]] explained the fascination with the case that provoked the band to writing the song: &quot;It's so sick that it becomes fascinating and there just has to be a song about it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.gmax.co.za/feel04/08/27-germanycanibal.html|title=German cannibal inspires hard rockers Rammstein to new hit|date=2004-08-24|accessdate=2009-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other songs influenced by Meiwes include &quot;The Wüstenfeld Man Eater&quot; by American [[death metal|death]]/[[thrash metal]] band [[Macabre (band)|Macabre]], &quot;[[Eaten (song)|Eaten]]&quot; by Swedish death metal band [[Bloodbath]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternative-zine.com/interviews/en/33 Interview with: Bloodbath's Jonas Renkse]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Let me Taste your Flesh&quot; by Spanish death metal band [[Avulsed]], as well as &quot;Cannibal Anthem&quot; by German electro-industrial project [[Wumpscut|:wumpscut:]], &quot;Cannibals of Rotenburg&quot; by the dirge-country band Sons of Perdition, and &quot;Menschenfresser [Eat Me]&quot; by electro-industrial act [[Suicide Commando]]. &quot;Human Consumption&quot; by hip-hop artist [[Necro (rapper)|Necro]] also makes reference to the incident, and the title of the 2007 [[Marilyn Manson]] album ''[[Eat Me, Drink Me]]'' was inspired by the case.&lt;ref&gt;Dan Epstein. ''Feeding Frenzy'', ''Revolver'', reported by [http://www.mansonusa.com/php-bin/news/fullnews.php?id=419 The Heirophant] May 2007. Last accessed March 23, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The song &quot;A Little Piece of Heaven&quot; by Avenged Sevenfold is about a man who kills and eats part of his girlfriend after she rejects him.

Rapper [[Brotha Lynch Hung]] has also written many songs concerning cannibalism, as exemplified by his 1994 album ''[[Season of da Siccness]]'', on which he styles himself as &quot;the Ripgut Cannibal&quot;.

The French industrial band [http://www.discogs.com/Nox-Killin-Drive-Power/release/230522 Nox] had a track titled &quot;Cannibal Night&quot; on their 1990 album ''Killin' Drive Power''. It's about a man who kills his whole family and eats the best parts of every member; at last, he eats himself.

The Gothic/Deathrock band Creaming Jesus' song &quot;Celebrity Cannibalism&quot; was inspired by the Jeffrey Dahmer case, with an ending refrain: &quot;You always eat the ones you love.&quot;

&quot;Kiss Me, Hold Me and Eat Me&quot; by [[Ballboy (band)|Ballboy]], an Edinburgh band, features a poignant love affair between two cannibals, who know that their first kiss could prove fatal.

Pop Artist [[Ke$ha]] sings &quot;Cannibal&quot; which is about a literal man eater.

Dark singer [[Voltaire]] sings 'Cannibal Buffet' where he washes up on an island and gets eaten by the locals.

==Literature==
Cannibalism in literature is represented by some significant works:

* [[Poppy Z. Brite]]. ''[[Exquisite Corpse (novel)|Exquisite Corpse]]''. A horror novel about two cannibalistic serial killers in love.
* ''[[Courtship Rite]]'' by [[Donald Kingsbury]], a [[science fiction]] novel in which cannibalism is an essential theme.
* ''The Republic of Wine: A Novel'' by [[Mo Yan]], in which cannibalism is practiced by officials in modern China.
* In [[Bentley Little]]'s short story &quot;The Washingtonians&quot;, the protagonist discovers that [[George Washington]] was a murderer and a cannibal. This story was adapted for an episode of [[The Washingtonians (Masters of Horror episode)|Masters of Horror]] in 2007.
* In ''The Cannibal Within'', by Mark Mirabello, &quot;Ingestion is the ultimate act of domination.... The victim is absorbed by the eater--body and soul are absorbed--and all that remains is excrement.&quot;
* [[Wilson Tucker|Wilson A. Tucker's]] ''[[The Long Loud Silence]]'' takes place in a post-apocalyptic America where people are reduced to cannibalism to survive.
* [[The Enemy (Higson novel)|The Enemy]] by [[Charlie Higson]], in which all adults are turned mad and start eating the children under fourteen.
*[[Thomas Harris]]'s [[Hannibal Lecter]] series, in which the main villain, Hannibal Lecter, is a serial killer known for cannibalism.
* In ''[[American Psycho]]'' by [[Bret Easton Ellis]], [[Patrick Bateman]] eats many of his female victims after murdering them.
* In ''[[Life of Pi]]'', a 2001 novel where a young boy uses metaphor of animals for cannibalism while lost at sea.
*In [[Dennis Cooper]]'s ''The Marbled Swarm'' (2011), the anonymous Parisian gay male Narrator either abducts, rapes and then consumes his underclass teenage gay male victims, or else is experiencing [[dissociative identity disorder]] or acting a role.

==Film==
Cannibalism is not just confined to the horror genre. [[Dark comedy]] has also featured it as a theme, in films such as ''[[Delicatessen (film)|Delicatessen]]'' (1991) or ''[[Eating Raoul]]'' (1982).

* The 1932 film ''[[Doctor X (film)|Doctor X]]'' features a cannibalistic killer.
* In the [[Suddenly, Last Summer (film)|1959 film adaptation]] of [[Tennessee Williams]]' play ''[[Suddenly, Last Summer]]'', the central mystery concerns the death of Sebastian Venable who was torn apart and eaten by a gang of boys.
* The films &quot;[[Blood Feast]]&quot; (1963) and &quot;[[Blood Feast 2: All U Can Eat]]&quot; (2002), both by [[Herschell Gordon Lewis]], feature a cannibal [[caterer]] preparing a feast for the [[goddess]] [[Ishtar]].
* The low-budget film ''[[Messiah of Evil]]'' (1971) has vampire-cannibalism as plot elements.
* The 1973 film ''[[Soylent Green]]'' concerns, among other things, the source of the eponymous food concentrate.
* In the 1975 film ''[[Rocky Horror Picture Show]]'', adapted from the 1973 stage musical ''[[The Rocky Horror Show]]'', Eddie is killed by Dr. Frank-N-Furter and his body parts are served for dinner.
* The 1980 film ''[[Cannibal Holocaust]]'', considered one of history's most gruesome movies, is about a film crew studying cannibalistic tribes in the [[Amazon Rainforest]]. Commonly believed to be a [[snuff film]], the film was directed by Italian [[Ruggero Deodato]], who was arrested on [[obscenity]] charges.
* ''[[The Cook, the Thief, His Wife &amp; Her Lover]]'', a 1989 film written and directed by [[Peter Greenaway]]
* ''[[Parents (film)|Parents]]'', a 1989 [[black comedy]] directed by [[Bob Balaban]] about a disturbed young boy who begins to wonder where the &quot;leftovers&quot; his parents always serve him for dinner are really coming from.
* In the [[Pseudohistory|pseudohistorical]] film, ''[[Rapa Nui (film)|Rapa Nui]]'' (1994), the inhabitants of [[Rapa Nui]] (Easter Island) resort to cannibalism during a rebellion.
* In the 2001 French film ''[[Trouble Every Day (film)|Trouble Every Day]]'', cannibalism is portrayed purely as a sexual act. Director [[Claire Denis]] explores the ability to love as a hunger, with characters seemingly having originated out of a &quot;diseased culture&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://dir.salon.com/story/ent/movies/review/2002/03/06/trouble/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* In ''[[Wrong Turn]]'' (2003), a clan of [[Inbreeding|inbred]] [[Mountain man|mountain men]] practice cannibalism on waylaid teenagers.
* ''[[Dumplings (film)|Dumplings]]'' (2004) by [[Fruit Chan]], wherein [[fetus|foetuses]] are consumed.
* In [[Tim Burton]]'s [[Charlie and the Chocolate Factory (film)|2005 remake]] of ''[[Willy Wonka &amp; the Chocolate Factory]]'', Wonka claims that cannibalism &quot;[[understatement|is frowned upon in most societies]].&quot; The gluttonous character Augustus Gloop also goes up a pipe into a fudge production room and is nearly made into fudge (it is implied that he would subsequently be eaten by unwitting purchasers).
* The [[Black Christmas (2006 film)|2006 remake]] of the film ''[[Black Christmas (1974 film)|Black Christmas]]'' depicts the two main antagonists, Billy and Agnes, engaging in acts of cannibalism.
* In the 2007 film ''[[Welcome to the Jungle (2007 film)|Welcome to the Jungle]]'', tourists are forced to participate in sacred cannibalistic rituals by a native tribe in [[Papua New Guinea]].
* ''[[The Donner Party (film)|The Donner Party]]'' (2009) is based on the true story of the [[Donner Party]], American settlers who turned to cannibalism during the harsh winter of 1846–1847.
* ''[[The Midnight Meat Train]]'' (2009) features a train-driver who eats the tongues of some of his victims.

==Television==
* The episode &quot;Our Town&quot; of ''[[The X-Files]]'' is based on several historical and popular myths about cannibalism. The protagonist FBI agents find that an entire community in [[Arkansas]] have been kidnapping outsiders and eating them for decades, in the belief that it lengthens their lifespans. They have been taught to do this by the town patriarch, Walter Chaco (a reference to [[Chaco Canyon]]), who lived among the [[Korowai]] tribe of [[Papua, New Guinea]] after being shot down in the [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]] during [[World War II]].
* [[Nightmare Cafeteria]], the third and final segment of [[The Simpsons]] [[Treehouse of Horror V]]. To respond to the overwhelming number of students in [[Detention (Academia)|detention]], the teachers at [[Springfield Elementary School]] start to eat all the children. This was a parody of ''Soylent Green''.
*The ''[[Doctor Who]]'' story ''[[Revelation of the Daleks]]'' a villain sells human flesh to famine victims. In &quot;[[The End of Time]]&quot;, the Master's resurrection went wrong as he tries to survive by eating homeless people in scrapyards.
*In an episode of ''[[The Young Ones (TV series)|The Young Ones]]'' the cast decide to eat their least popular member ([[The Young Ones (TV series)#Neil Pye|Neil]]) when they are trapped in their house, submerged in a flood.
* In [[Monty Python]]'s Flying Circus, cannibalism is something of a recurring theme:
** In the ''[[Undertaker's sketch]]'', a dead woman is referred to as &quot;an eater&quot; by an [[undertaker]], suggesting [[cremation]] or [[burial]] is too &quot;nasty&quot;.
** In the ''[[Lifeboat sketch]]'', five sailors in a lifeboat bicker about the menu planning involving who should be eaten first. The skit is followed by the reading of a &quot;protest letter&quot; saying, &quot;As a naval officer I abhor the implication that the [[Royal Navy]] is a haven for cannibalism. It is well known that we now have the problem relatively under control, and that it is the [[RAF]] who now suffer the largest casualties in this area. And what do you think the [[Argyll]]s ate in [[Aden]]. Arabs? Yours etc. Captain B.J. Smethwick in a [[white wine]] sauce with [[shallot]]s, [[mushroom]]s and [[garlic]].&quot;
** In the ''[[Expedition to Lake Pahoe]]'' sketch, Vice Admiral Sir John Cunningham addresses the audience with the ''non sequitur'' &quot;and may I take this opportunity of emphasizing that there is no cannibalism in the British Navy. Absolutely none, and when I say none, I mean there is a certain amount, more than we are prepared to admit, but all new [[Naval rating#Royal Navy|ratings]] are warned that if they wake up in the morning and find toothmarks at all anywhere on their bodies, they're to tell me immediately so that I can immediately take every measure to hush the whole thing up. And, finally, [[necrophilia]] is right out. Now, this expedition is primarily to investigate reports of cannibalism and necrophilia in ... this expedition is primarily to investigate reports of unusual marine life in the as yet uncharted [[Lake Pahoe]].&quot; Later in the skit, Sir John has to block our view of a naval rating about to bite into a human leg.
** In the ''[[Restaurant/Intermission]]'' sketch, two patrons of a &quot;vegetarian restaurant&quot; which serves &quot;no animal flesh of any kind&quot; are confronted by a semi-naked man in a large serving dish, who informs them, &quot;I'm the special. Try me with some rice.&quot; The surprise here is somewhat lessened by the waiter having just asked the couple, &quot;Would you care for a glass of blood? Oh what a giveaway.&quot;
* A fourth season episode of the series ''[[Tales from the Crypt (TV series)|Tales from the Crypt]]'' entitled &quot;What's Cookin'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{imdb title|0716909|What's Cookin'}}&lt;/ref&gt; featured a restaurant that's saved from failure when the owners start serving meat that they are initially unaware is human.
* The 2001 episode of ''[[South Park]]'' called ''[[Scott Tenorman Must Die]]'', is famous among fans of the [[Comedy Central]] show. [[Eric Cartman]] arranged the [[murders]] of the parents of his archnemesis, [[Scott Tenorman]]. He then collected the bodies, ground them up into meat, and fed them to Scott in a chili cookoff but it turns out that scotts father is also Eric's father in the episode ''[[201 (South Park)|201]]''. This is not the first time cannibalism has been seen, in a previous episode, [[Cartman's Mom Is Still a Dirty Slut]], three characters fall victim to cannibalism during the brief period of time that a group of adults became trapped in a television studio during a blizzard.
* In the ''[[Torchwood]]'' episode &quot;[[Countrycide]]&quot; it is discovered that a whole village of cannibals kill and eat travellers every ten years as part of a &quot;harvest&quot;.
* Some deaths in [[Celebrity Deathmatch]] lead to a celebrity eating another celebrity.
* The 2007 ''[[Masters of Horror]]'' episode &quot;[[The Washingtonians]]&quot; portrays [[George Washington]] as a cannibal in a fictional account of alternate history.
* In ''[[Bones (TV series)|Bones]]'', the group searched and caught an infamous serial killer known as &quot;[[The Gormogon]]&quot;, who murdered and cannibalized members of fraternal orders and secret societies.
* In the ''[[It's Always Sunny in Philadelphia]]'' episode &quot;Mac &amp; Dennis: Manhunters,&quot; Charlie and Dee believe they have accidentally consumed human meat, and subsequently come to crave it, though in reality, Frank is tricking them to teach them not to eat his stash of meat.
* Although it has never been confirmed, some people suspect that in the [[BBC]] [[sitcom]] ''[[The League of Gentlemen]]'' the &quot;special stuff&quot; served by butcher Hilary Briss is human meat.
*The ''[[Are You Afraid of the Dark?]]'' episode &quot;The Tale of the Gruesome Gourmets&quot; is about two brothers who suspect that their new neighbors are cannibals.

==Video games==
*[[Digital Devil Saga]] depicts demonic tribe members devouring each other should his or her opponent be defeated.
* In ''[[Grand Theft Auto: Liberty City Stories]]'', media tycoon Donald Love has [[Toni Cipriani]] kill [[Avery Carrington]] and bring him to his private jet in order to eat him on the trip.
* [[Jade Empire]] features cannibals as one of the game's enemies.
* In [[Dragon Age: Origins]], women that have been captured by darkspawn become cannibalistic after being tainted by the dark spawn.
* Mr. Grimm, a main playable character in [[Twisted Metal Black]], is a cannibal.
* In the [[Grand Theft Auto 2]] mission &quot;R. S. L. Bows!&quot; the player is required to collect members of the public in a bus, before driving them to a meat-processing plant to be slaughtered for human consumption by soldiers of the Russian mafia.
* [[Paxton Fettel]], the main enemy in the computer game [[F.E.A.R.]] eats his victims in order to absorb their memories.
* In [[Mortal Kombat (series)|Mortal Kombat]] the [[Tarkatan]] eat their victims after a fight (The only character that actually does that in game is [[Mileena (Mortal Kombat)|Mileena]]).
* In [[World of Warcraft]], players can choose a Horde race called the Forsaken, a faction of sentient undead with a racial ability called &quot;Cannibalize&quot;. The player consumes the corpse of a Humanoid or Undead enemy to regain health. The female Trolls also have a voice emote that states: &quot;If cannibalism is wrong, I don' wanna be right!&quot;
* The Tribesmen from [[Tomb Raider 3]] attempt to eat [[Lara Croft|Lara]]. Fortunately her arsenal vanquished the tribe. They also attempt to eat a castaway pilot - who they are supposed to have eat for the dessert (as white flesh is said to be a delicacy in those parts) of a special feast, named: &quot;The Feast of Spies&quot;. He only had one leg - as he awoke late one night to find &quot;One of those little fuckers snacking on his leg&quot;. He wrapped it in bandages - hoping to survive up to the feast, in which he will be eaten alive.
* Cannibalism is a recurring theme in the game [[Fallout 3]]. An interesting game mechanic in which players can cannibalize corpses to regain health is featured. Heavily radiated wastelanders called feral ghouls also eat flesh to sustain themselves. Likewise, a small yet corrupt settlement of cannibals can be discovered.  (This is partially a take-off of Parents)
* A 1998 canceled PlayStation fighting game entitled [[Thrill Kill]] featured a murderous redneck cannibal from Kentucky named Cleetus.  He was shown carrying a torn leg and used it as a blunt object in fighting.  Cleetus could be seen also eating the leg during fighting, as well as has attacks where he bites the flesh of other fighters.
* In the [[2010]] video game [[Red Dead Redemption]], one stranger mission revolves around the main character searching for missing people in the nearby hills. It turns out it was the work of a cannibal who was kidnapping and eating residents who lived nearby.

== In other media ==
* In the ''[[Forgotten Realms]]'' setting of the ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]'' [[role-playing game]], [[aboleth]]s are said to consume their parents on birth and in so doing receive their parents' memories (this holds true for those of any other races they eat).
* ''[[Underground (role playing game)|Underground]]'', a role-playing game in which a popular restaurant chain called &quot;Tastee Ghoul&quot; serves food made from human flesh.
* The Lintha, a culture of [[Piracy|sea raiders]] in ''[[Exalted]]'', is known for practicing [[endocannibalism]] as a burial rite and intimidation tactic.
* [[Zhu Yu (artist)|Zhu Yu]], a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] [[conceptual artist]], became famous for his staging of many photographs of himself eating a cooked human [[fetus|foetus]]. Though he himself has claimed in interviews that the foetus was real, obtained from an abortion clinic, some reports indicate that it was likely [[duck]] meat mixed with parts from a baby [[doll]]. Yu briefly found himself the subject of a [[chain mail|chain e-mail]] backlash that singled out [[Asian people|Asian]] communities for allegedly taking their &quot;unusual&quot; [[cuisine]] tastes too far. The chain eventually reached the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] and [[Scotland Yard]], both of whom performed full investigations into the pictures.
* [[Long Pig]], a fictional [[fast food]] chain in the [[comic book]] series ''[[Transmetropolitan]]'', for which humans are cloned without brains to be guiltlessly prepared as meals.
* Famed Mexican muralist [[Diego Rivera]] claimed in his autobiography that during a period in 1904, he and his companions ate &quot;nothing but cadavers&quot; purchased from the local morgue. Rivera was fully aware of the shock value of this tale. He claims that he thought cannibalism a way of the future, remarking, &quot;I believe that when man evolves a civilization higher than the mechanized but still primitive one he has now, the eating of human flesh will be sanctioned. For then man will have thrown off all of his superstitions and irrational taboos.&quot; Readers may be reminded of the savage satire of [[Jonathan Swift]]'s ''[[A Modest Proposal]]''.
* [[Oswald de Andrade]]'s ''Cannibal Manifesto'' was an influential work of [[Brazil]]ian [[modernism]], comparing literal cannibalism to the [[postcolonial]] reappropriation of European culture, art, and ideas.

==In multiple media==
* [[Patrick Bateman]], a fictional character created by [[Bret Easton Ellis]] in the 1987 novel ''[[The Rules of Attraction]]'', but most famously depicted in Ellis's ''[[American Psycho]]'', released in 2000.
* ''[[Sweeney Todd]]'', originally a [[penny dreadful]], later a musical, about a barber who kills his customers and sells their flesh as food. This was made into motion pictures in 1936 (original story), 1982 (musical), 1997 (original story), and 2007 (musical).
* ''[[Sin City (film)|Sin City]]'', a film by [[Frank Miller (comics)|Frank Miller]] and [[Robert Rodriguez]] based upon [[Sin City|a graphic novel of the same title]], features a character named [[Kevin (Sin City)|Kevin]] played by [[Elijah Wood]] who eats the bodies of prostitutes, as well as forcing them to watch as he eats their severed limbs.
* The [[Reaver (Firefly)|Reavers]] are a group of cannibals in the television series ''[[Firefly (TV series)|Firefly]]'' and the movie ''[[Serenity (film)|Serenity]]''.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
* [[Child cannibalism]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cannibalism In Popular Culture}}
[[Category:Cannibalism|Popular culture]]
[[Category:Horror fiction]]
[[Category:Topics in popular culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
