<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="618691" ns="0" title="Ancient (Stargate)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|in-universe=December 2009| fiction=December 2009|notable=December 2009|primarysources=December 2009 }}

[[File:SGAncient.jpg|thumb|Oma Desala, an Ascended Ancient.]]
The '''Ancients''' are a [[humanoid]] race in the [[fictional universe|fictional]] [[Stargate]] universe. They are called &quot;Ancients&quot; in the [[Milky Way Galaxy|Milky Way]], but are also known as '''Lanteans''' or Ancestors in the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus galaxy]] and as the '''Alterans''' in their home galaxy, and they sometimes call themselves ''Anquietas'' in [[Ancient Language (Stargate)|their language]]. In the series mythology, they are one of the most advanced races known to have existed, having evolved millions of years prior to the present day and reaching their level of [[technology]] long before humanity evolved on [[Earth]]. They are best known as the builders of the [[Stargate (device)|Stargates]], the giant ring-shaped portals commonly used by Earth-based humans to travel and explore the Milky Way and Pegasus galaxies.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Fifth Race (Stargate SG-1)|The Fifth Race]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ancients have become an important race in all three ''Stargate'' series. They belong to the same race as the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]], the main antagonists in ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' since the show's ninth season, and have played a large role in the series' many story arcs. In ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'', the Ancients built [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], the show's main setting, and are responsible for the emergence of the show's two main villain races: the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] and the [[Asuran]]s. In [[Stargate Universe]] they are the ones that have built and launched the ship ''Destiny'' on its journey.

==History==
===The Ancients and the Ori===
Millions of years ago, the first evolution of humanity, the Alterans (from ''altera'', [[Latin]]: ''the other(s)''), lived in a distant unknown galaxy while proceeding along the evolutionary path to [[Ascension (Stargate)|ascension]]. At the time, those who were later to be known as the Ori and the Ancients were not distinguished from each other, and lived in one society. However, a philosophical division emerged. Over time, the Ori grew more and more fervent in their religious belief, while the Ancients adopted a more scientific outlook. Ultimately, their viewpoints diverged so much that the two groups split apart and began to oppose each other, culminating in the Ori attempting to destroy the Ancients. Instead of going to war, the Ancients decided to leave their galaxy, and began searching for a new home. The Ori later used their departure to their advantage, including their departure in the Book of Origin, claiming that the mountain the Ancients leveled while leaving contained evil and that it was buried as the mountain collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Fourth Horseman (Stargate SG-1)|The Fourth Horseman]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

After much time, believed by [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] to be thousands of years, the Ancients discovered a &quot;great belt of stars&quot;, which they named &quot;Avalon&quot; (Milky Way Galaxy) where they eventually built an impressive empire. The Ancients built ''Astria Porta'' (Stargates), which were spread out throughout the Milky Way. &lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the Ancients sent out &quot;seed ships&quot; to spread Stargates to other galaxies, along with ''Destiny'', which was sent out after the &quot;seed ships&quot; to further investigate a pattern discovered in the Cosmic Background Microwave Radiation ([[Stargate Universe]]). Among the planets they settled was Earth, which they called ''Terra''. The status of Earth in the Ancients' empire is currently unknown. However, as the planet's original Stargate, eventually discovered by [[SG-1]] in [[Antarctica]], was the oldest gate ever encountered, Earth was probably one of their more important worlds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Frozen (Stargate SG-1)|Frozen]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The nine-chevron address that dials the ship Destiny must use Earth as the point of origin, no matter what planet the Stargate is dialing from so Earth must have been very important, possibly central to their empire.  It was also once the location of one of the [[Ancient City Ship|Ancients City Ships]], [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], before it moved to the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]], and it was where their descendants returned to after their defeat by the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Rising (Stargate Atlantis)|Rising]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Other important planets they have colonized were Proclarush Taonas,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dakara]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and Valos Cor.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Pegasus Project (Stargate SG-1)|The Pegasus Project]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Although exiled to another galaxy, the Ancients still remained in contact with their distant cousins, the Ori, evidenced by the discovery of [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Communication Device|long-range communication devices]] in both the Milky Way and their home galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Origin (Stargate SG-1)|Origin]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Still, the two factions remained bitter enemies. Eventually, the Ancients were afflicted with a terrible plague that wiped out most of the civilization they had built in the Milky Way.&lt;ref name=&quot;Window of Opportunity&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Window of Opportunity (Stargate SG-1)|Window of Opportunity]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; It would later be discovered that what was known of this plague is very similar to the disease used by Ori [[Prior (Stargate)|Priors]] against non-believers, which had led Daniel Jackson to speculate that the pre-Ascended Ori might have been responsible for this plague.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Powers That Be&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Powers That Be (Stargate SG-1)|The Powers That Be]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Ancients apparently attempted to travel back through time to escape the plague, without much success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Window of Opportunity&quot;/&gt; Many others left the Milky Way to travel to the Pegasus galaxy.  It has been stated that the Ancients who remained in the Milky Way galaxy either ascended or died out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Window of Opportunity&quot; /&gt; However, according to [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]], the Ancients had attempted to recreate life after the plague in the Milky Way using the [[Dakara Superweapon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Threads (Stargate SG-1)|Threads]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The evolution of humanity on Earth could be the result of this attempt.

===Pegasus Galaxy===

One million years ago, several Ancients departed Earth in their city-sized spaceship, '[[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]]' which at that time was situated on Earth, on the continent Antarctica. The exact reason for their departure is unknown, although [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] speculated that they might have left to escape the plague that was devastating their civilization at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; One known Ancient (later named [[Ayiana]] by the researchers who discovered her perfectly preserved in Antarctica) was left behind. The fact that Ayiana was infected with the Ancients plague when she was revived would seem to confirm Jackson's conjectures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot; /&gt;

After arriving in the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]], the Ancients settled on a planet they named 'Lantea', calling themselves 'Lanteans'&lt;ref name=&quot;The Defiant One&quot;&gt;[[The_Defiant_One#ep12|The Defiant One]] ([[Stargate Atlantis (season 1)]])&lt;/ref&gt; from that time forward (also, they have been referred to as 'Atlanteans' by members of the Atlantis Expedition - a name often used by the peoples of Pegasus to describe the expedition members). Finding Pegasus devoid of sentient life, the Ancients dispersed humans and Stargates across their new home galaxy, protecting the newly-populated planets and occasionally inhabiting them (usually concealing their true identities as Ancients). The humans seeded by the Ancients came to know them as 'the Ancestors'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; At some point they encountered a leech-like organism called the '[[Iratus bug]]', which possessed impressive healing and [[immunological]] capabilities. Through feeding on humans (and processes of evolution), this organism absorbed genetic information from humans and eventually evolved into the vampire-like [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Instinct&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Instinct (Stargate Atlantis)|Instinct]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Although it remains unknown precisely how this evolution occurred, the Ancients have confirmed that they were responsible for the species' emergence.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Return (Stargate Atlantis)|The Return]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

The Wraith, over a vast period, developed into an advanced but violent society (with vestiges of territorialism that were later harshly revived when their prey became scarce) - all the while avoiding the attention of the Ancients. When the sentient Wraith were discovered by the Ancients, it appears their ferocity, belligerence and large population were underestimated. The Ancients sent a delegation protected by their most powerful warships to negotiate with the Wraith, but the ships were ambushed and destroyed. The Ancients and Wraith went to war, and despite the Ancients' technological superiority, the Wraith overwhelmed the Ancients with their sheer numbers. During their war which lasted for centuries, the Wraith eventually conquered every planet in the Pegasus Galaxy until only Atlantis, the capital of their empire, remained protected by its powerful city shield.

The Ancients were able to hold the Wraith back with their superior weapons for a hundred years, until they were forced to submerge the city and to leave the Galaxy, for no matter how long they stalled the destruction of Atlantis, the Lanteans were unable to overcome the endless number of Wraith.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; They started to make more desperate experiments, such as [[Project Arcturus]], a failed attempt to draw [[Zero Point Energy]] from their own universe, instead of from within an artificially created region of subspace as in [[Zero Point Module]]s. However, containing zero point energy in our own space-time caused serious containment issues, killing the Ancients and the people of Doranda, the planet it was based on.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trinity&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Trinity (Stargate Atlantis)|Trinity]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; They also developed nanites designed to fight the Wraith on a cellular level, giving them aggression codes surpassing that of the Wraith. The nanites took human form, becoming a race known as the [[Asuran]]s. They begged to have the aggressive nature removed from their programming, but the Ancients refused. Once it became clear the Asurans would never be the weapon the Ancients hoped for, they were subsequently exterminated by the Ancients. Not wanting anyone to find out their mistakes, the Ancients deleted all references to the Asurans in the Atlantis database, save for the gate address. A few of the nanites survived and brought up a second evolution, re-creating Asuran society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Progeny&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Progeny (Stargate Atlantis)|Progeny]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; 
It is believed that at one point in time the Asurans even created several nano-viruses specifically designed to kill humans, so as to deprive the Wraith of a food supply. One such virus, which causes hallucinations and death caused by a brain aneurysm, was encountered in a lab on Atlantis. Janus, an Ancient scientist, also built a device called the Attero device, which emitted a specific frequency of subspace distortion, causing Wraith ships to explode when attempting to enter hyper-space. It was later shut off and ordered to be destroyed (an order Janus, as usual of him, disregarded), because the same frequency which damaged the Wraith ships also caused an explosive overload in active Stargates.

The Ancients also pursued technological means of accelerating the process of Ascension through a variety of mediums. Before the war reached its final stages, they selected a hospitable planet and enclosed a portion of its surface inside a time-dilation field. Within the field, time passed much more quickly than outside, allowing the humans within to spend many generations undisturbed in seclusion and meditation in order to reach ascension, whilst remaining undisturbed by the Wraith.&lt;ref name=&quot;Epiphany&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Epiphany (Stargate Atlantis)|Epiphany]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; On Atlantis, they built a [[DNA Resequencer (Stargate)|DNA Resequencer]] designed to modify DNA, fulfilling the physiological component of ascension. This had varying results.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tao of Rodney&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Tao of Rodney (Stargate Atlantis)|Tao of Rodney]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually, the Ancients realized that the war was lost, and those who had not already ascended, decided to return to Earth, the planet that had been home to them for millions of years. As they were making the final preparations to leave, Dr. Elizabeth Weir appeared from the future in a modified Jumper. The High Council of Atlantis, fearing further damage to the timeline, ordered the scientist who built the machine, Janus, to dismantle it. They offered Weir the chance to return to Earth with them, forbidding her to return to her time. Janus, in order to help preserve the city in the future, reconfigured Atlantis's three ZPMs to run in sequence instead of in parallel, and left Dr. Weir behind in stasis to rotate them out. The Ancients evacuated the city via the Stargate, hoping it would eventually be rediscovered by their descendants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Before I Sleep&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Before I Sleep (Stargate Atlantis)|Before I Sleep]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; A few isolated groups of Ancients were left stranded in the Pegasus Galaxy and either lived out the rest of their lives with the humans, or found a way to ascend. At least one warship, the Tria, attempted to reach Earth using modified sublight engines that ran at 99.9% of Light Speed after the ship's Hyperdrive was destroyed.

===Return to the Milky Way===
After the Ancients returned to Earth, they found only a harsh environment and [[Tau'ri|primitive inhabitants]]. It was believed that there was no hope of rebuilding their former civilization. So they spread out to distant lands and helped to populate them. Others would depart the planet through the Stargate located in Antarctica, possibly seeking to live out their days on distant worlds within the Milky Way. The remainder chose isolation in which to meditate and seek enlightenment. This would eventually lead to a spiritual ascension for some.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt;

Those Ancients who stayed on Earth and interbred with humans passed on the [[Ancient Technology Activation gene]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; marking the humans of Earth as their &quot;Second Evolution&quot; as well as giving civilization to the people.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt; They would also lay cultural foundations by way of the Indo-European languages of which the [[Latin]] language is one. Through this cultural and linguistic inheritance many Roman myths were also influenced by the Ancients, such as the myth that the &quot;Ancient ones ascended to the Heavens&quot;. According to mythology, the Romans learned how to build roads from gods known as &quot;The Ancient Ones&quot; in mimicry of the &quot;astria porta&quot; constructed by the ancients.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot; /&gt;

The Arthurian Legends were also shown to be influenced by the Ancients, in particular the Ancient Myrddin/Merlin, (Known as Moros, in Atlantis where he headed the Council prior to his Ascension), who appeared to have ascended after returning from Atlantis, but later de-ascended himself in order to create a weapon that can destroy ascended beings, which he hoped would be used against the Ori. Merlin became known as Arthur's wizard counselor in legends, and the weapon he developed became known as the Sangraal or Holy Grail. He also entrusted his secrets to a small group of nobles which consisted of [[King Arthur]] and the [[Knights of the Round Table]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Camelot (Stargate SG-1)|Camelot]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the Ancients, presumably those who left Earth, set up the [[Alliance of Four Great Races]] including themselves, the [[Nox (Stargate)|Nox]], the [[Furling (Stargate)|Furling]]s and the [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]]. Together, they created a &quot;true&quot; universal language. According to writings discovered on Heliopolis, this alliance lasted for centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Torment of Tantalus&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Torment of Tantalus (Stargate SG-1)|The Torment of Tantalus]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Recent History of the Ancients===
After the Ancients' ascension they continued to oppose their former nemesis, the Ori, who had also reached Enlightenment. Although the two factions were deadlocked in strength, the Ori were still bent on destroying the Ancients once and for all. The Ancients probably out numbered the Ori as the ranks of the ascended Ori were not swelled by new ascendants, rather they preferred to hoard the energy they derived from their own mortal worshipers, sapping power from this second evolution of humanity created in their own galaxy to gather enough strength to, ultimately, attack the Ancients. In response, the Ancients chose to hide their own second evolution created in the Milky Way from the Ori&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot; /&gt; with the sole purpose of protecting the Milky Way humans from being coerced into forced religious servitude to the Ori, and thus used as a resource for the Ori to empower themselves. To this end they also probably influenced the association of [[fire]], the central icon of the Ori religion, with demonic imagery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt; Still, they refused to take direct action because of their strict self-imposed edict of self determination.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt;  It is also likely that the ancients knew the slippery slope of addiction to empowerment by way of the worship of `Lowers` and understood that there was a danger in this reliance, giving the Ori and later Adria a weakness despite `God` like powers. There are several examples of &quot;lowers&quot; praying and giving thanks to the Ancients/Ancestors in the Pegasus Galaxy. Such as &quot;[[The Tower (Stargate Atlantis)|The Tower]]&quot;, even an exiled Ancient on a planet where the people worship her as &quot;Athar&quot; in the [[Stargate Atlantis]] episode, [[Sanctuary (Stargate Atlantis)|&quot;Sanctuary.&quot;]]

The first ascended being ever encountered by the Tau'ri was Oma Desala, when [[SG-1]] arrived on the planet Kheb in their search for [[Shifu (Stargate)|Shifu]], the young son of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] and [[Sha're]]. During their stay, the team discovered a [[Buddhist temple]], where a single monk appeared to reside. The monk spoke in riddles, but spoke about a being called ''Oma Desala'', a name [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] translated as &quot;Mother Nature&quot;. Eventually, when the team was preparing to defend the temple from several [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] warriors, Daniel discovered a non-corporeal being living on Kheb.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maternal Instinct&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Maternal Instinct (Stargate SG-1)|Maternal Instinct]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; He eventually formed a personal bond with Oma Desala, who even helped him to ascend on two occasions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meridian&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Meridian (Stargate SG-1)|Meridian]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Three years later, an Ancient woman, [[Ayiana]], was found frozen in [[Antarctica]] near the location of the Antarctica Stargate. She revived herself when thawed, but was still infected with the plague and died exhausted from healing SG-1 and others from the Plague.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot; /&gt; Apparently, she was left behind in the Ancient outpost in Antarctica, for carrying the plague, when Atlantis left for the Pegasus Galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt;

When an [[Aurora class battleship]] was discovered by the [[List of Earth starships in Stargate#Daedalus|Daedalus]], between the Pegasus and Milky Way galaxy, the crew was still alive. As the ship was traversing the inter-galactic expanse between Pegasus and the Milky Way Galaxies, close to [[light speed]], the crew had only experienced a handful of years, because of the time dilation effect of near speed of light travel, since the evacuation of Atlantis. After learning that Atlantis had survived the Wraith, they reclaimed the city. When the [[Asuran]]s returned and captured the city, all the remaining Ancients were executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot; /&gt;

After Daniel Jackson and [[Vala Mal Doran]] inadvertently alerted the Ori to the existence of another galaxy filled with humans, starting the Ori invasion of the Milky Way,&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt; millions of humans were converted to the oppressive Ori religion, feeding them only more power. According to the Ori themselves, the entire conversion of the Milky Way would probably give them enough strength to destroy the Ancients once the crusade was over. Still, most of the Ancients refused to intervene, even though their own existence is threatened. Exceptions include [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Ganos Lal/Morgan le Fey|Morgan le Fey]] and [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Moros/Merlin/Myrddin|Merlin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt;

[[SG-1]] eventually discovered Merlin in stasis inside a cave on a barren planet. He was revived by the team, and assisted them with constructing the [[Sangraal (Stargate)|Sangraal]], the weapon he had designed to combat the Ori. Although he died before he was able to complete the device, he downloaded the necessary information into a [[Repository of the Ancients|Repository of Knowledge]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Quest (Stargate SG-1)|The Quest]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually, when the Sangraal was complete, the Ancients didn't interfere for unknown reasons and allowed it to go to the Ori galaxy. The Sangraal did its job and destroyed, although Daniel Jackson says a better translation would be &quot;cancels out or neutralized&quot;, the Ori.&lt;ref name=&quot;Line in the Sand&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Line in the Sand|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adria, the de facto leader of the Ori army ascended, taking on the full mantle of the dead Ori. When the humans from the Milky Way traveled to the Ori galaxy and discovered the Ark of Truth, Adria's power was significantly reduced when the Ark was used to &quot;show&quot; the truth to the Doci, and subsequently all the Priors in their home galaxy, which enabled Morgan, who was exiled by the Others, to engage Adria in eternal battle.

==Physiology==
===Pre-Ascension===

Although the Ancients appear to be human in appearance their physiology is much more advanced. The main characteristic differentiating the Ancients from ordinary humans is the [[ATA gene]], which occurs naturally in all Ancients. However, due to genetic inheritance from the Ancients who returned to Earth after they were forced to abandon Atlantis, a small percentage of humans on Earth possess the gene.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; Also, the gene has been introduced in others through [[genetic modification]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Hide and Seek (Stargate Atlantis)|Hide and Seek]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been suggested that the Ancients and the Ori evolved in a galaxy far from the [[Milky Way]], and were the ''first'' evolution of humanity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot; /&gt; It is implied that the current human species evolved as such due to the actions of the Ancients, since two species progressing along identical evolutionary paths is extremely improbable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot; /&gt; The Ancients later created the &quot;second evolution&quot; of their species on Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Before I Sleep&quot; /&gt;

Toward the end of their evolutionary development, but still before they ascended, the Ancients developed advanced abilities, such as [[telekinesis]], extraordinary sensory abilities, and the ability to heal others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot; /&gt;

===Ascension===
{{Main|Ascension (Stargate)}}
Eventually, the Ancients were able to ascend, thus shedding their physical form and existing as pure energy on a &quot;higher plane&quot; of existence. Although this new state of being grants them god-like powers, they adhere to a sort of &quot;[[Prime Directive]]&quot; which forbids them from influencing the unascended.

The ability to ascend is not limited to Ancients, as both humans and [[Goa'uld]] have been able to ascend.

==Philosophy==

The Ancients are well known for their fierce belief in [[free will]]. As such, they do not interfere on lower planes of existence at all, not even to save their own kind from being exterminated by the Ori.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt; As punishment for breaking this law, the Ancients have been known to wipe out entire civilizations and abandon the one responsible to correct the grave mistakes caused by one of their people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ascension&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Ascension (Stargate SG-1)|Ascension]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; They have also forced (or tried to force) transgressors to descend back to corporeal form.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Fallen (Stargate SG-1)|Fallen]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Ancients are, by every means, capable of drastically altering courses of events at will.

What exactly constitutes law-breaking is open to debate. Interfering &quot;a little bit&quot;, as [[Vala Mal Doran]] described it, will be tolerated.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt; Examples of this include the killing of several Jaffa troops&lt;ref name=&quot;Maternal Instinct&quot; /&gt; and giving the coordinates of Sahal and Castiana to [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt; Also, some Ancients, like [[Oma Desala]], repeatedly assists &quot;those beneath&quot; in ascending. Those who follow her are forced to walk a very fine line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Full Circle (Stargate SG-1)|Full Circle]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Other Ancients who have been reprimanded for interfering in the mortal planes include [[Orlin]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Ascension&quot; /&gt; and [[Chaya Sar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanctuary&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Sanctuary (Stargate Atlantis)|Sanctuary]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ancients' viewpoints completely oppose those of their distant cousins, the Ori. The Ori religion states that failure to share the secrets of the universe to those on the lower planes of existence is an evil act and that anyone not following it must be eliminated. They also have no rules against taking direct control of living beings or completely changing them to behave as they desire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt;

This difference in beliefs is not without its reasons. According to a de-ascended Ancient, Orlin, ascended beings can be empowered by massive numbers of humans worshiping them. The Ori have fabricated an entire religion based on the false promise of [[ascension (Stargate)|ascension]] to drain power from their followers. The Ancients firmly resent using their powers this way, and therefore refrain from interfering in the lower planes of existence as manipulating and aligning lower life forms in some order could result in exactly this type of abusive corruption.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot; /&gt; As Morgan le Fay said, if they were to interfere, they would be no better than the Ori.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt;

As a result, the Ancients have shielded the second evolution of humans (i.e. current human culture) in the Milky Way from the Ori (and although it has never been stated, they most likely did the same for the seeded humans in the Pegasus Galaxy and Ida galaxy [the Asgard home galaxy]) and still prevent the Ori from taking direct action in the Milky Way. However, as the Ancients will not interfere in the lower planes of existence, the Ori are allowed to send their human followers to the Milky Way in order to convert it, and anyone who wishes to worship the Ori will be allowed to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt;

Even though the Ancients do not believe in interfering in mortal affairs, it is speculated that they are responsible for generating the associations of [[fire]] with [[Demon]]ic imagery in the Milky Way. This would be another method of shielding humans from the Ori, as the central symbols of Origin involve fire. As Daniel Jackson pointed out, there is no immediate illogicality with fire as a symbol of all that is good: it provides warmth, light, etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt;

Also, even before their ascension, the Ancients had strict rules on time travel, although this rule has been broken as well. The Ancient scientist [[Janus (Stargate)|Janus]] developed time travel technology, leading to [[Elizabeth Weir (Stargate)|Elizabeth Weir]] using it to travel back to Atlantis 10,000 years previously,&lt;ref name=&quot;Before I Sleep&quot; /&gt; and to a column containing a history of future events on the Milky Way planet ruled by [[Harry Maybourne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good to Be King&quot;&gt;&quot;[[It's Good to Be King (Stargate SG-1)|It's Good to Be King]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

==Technology==
[[Image:Sg1stargatefront.jpg|thumb|The Stargate network is the Ancients' most well-known creation.|The Stargate network is the Ancients' best-known creation.]]
{{Main|Ancient technology in Stargate}}
Ancient technology is among the most advanced encountered in the Stargate universe rivaled only by the Ori, who are the same race as the Ancients, and the Asgard who revealed some of their most advanced technologies only shortly before their extinction. Among their many achievements, the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]]s and [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] are perhaps their most famous, but they have also developed technology as diverse as [[Ancient City Ship|flying cities]], [[Zero Point Module|advanced power sources]], [[Ancient healing device|advanced healing devices]] and [[DNA Resequencer (Stargate)|DNA Resequencers]]. Much of the Ancients' weapons technology was used or designed for use in the centuries-long war with the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] in the Pegasus Galaxy. 

Much of Ancient technology requires the presence of the [[Ancient Technology Activation gene|ATA gene]] to use, such as the Ancient weapon system in Antarctica, but numerous instances requiring only the gene to activate it, once active anyone can use it regardless, for instance much of the day to day technology of Atlantis.

==Language and writing system==
The Ancients' language appears to be a precursor of [[Latin]], but it is still distinct. There are many similarities between the two languages, and someone with a decent knowledge of Latin may, given time and practice, be able to understand Ancient as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot; /&gt; The [[Athosians]] in the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]] say their prayers in Ancient.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot; /&gt; The Ancient language and writing system is also used by the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] and their followers, who share the same ancestry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot; /&gt; Since the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] were created by the fictional [[Iratus bug]] absorbing Ancient DNA, the Wraith language seems to be a derivative of the Ancient language, and the two use the same writing system; the Wraith language is therefore relatively easy to translate by experienced Ancient speakers.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Gift&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Gift (Stargate Atlantis)|The Gift]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;  

[[Image:Ancient alphabet.png|thumb|The Ancients' alphabet as it appears in the Stargate universe.]]
The Ancient language has a unique writing system that has no analogues with any known Earth alphabet. Ancient characters are squarish, blocky, and dominated by right angles. There are 25 distinct letters ('F' and 'U' are the same character) and 10 numerals in the Ancient-English conversion. It has been mentioned though that the Ancients have an [[Octal]] counting system, meaning based on 8, not like the [[decimal]] system of the [[Tau'ri]], based on 10, although the Stargate Universe symbols include symbols for 8 and 9.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot; /&gt; Exactly how the characters were used by the Ancients is unknown. It has been mentioned that some Ancient characters have different meanings when read upside down.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot; /&gt; The Ancient writing system has been shown to be learnable with moderate difficulty by humans. However, the pronunciation of Ancient words has fluctuated during the millennia the language was used.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot; /&gt;

Passages written in Ancient on the shows can be transliterated into English (there are no characters for spaces and punctuation marks). These [[transliteration]]s show that the in-show writing system rules do not necessarily apply in reality,&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot; /&gt; but they sometimes reveal [[in-jokes]] or offer further ([[non-canon]]) information instead. For example, parts of the writings on Atlantis main screens include the beginning of the nursery rhyme ''[[Where Oh Where Has My Little Dog Gone?]]'', and the text shown on Daniel's laptop in the episode {{sgcite|Affinity}} can be transliterated into &quot;Actual words are hard to deciph(er) so this(')ll work&quot;. Playback supervisor Krista McLean said that when she originally put the graphics together for the Atlantian holo screens, she carelessly used things that were going through her head. When fans translated the language on the internet, she became more careful and tried to not use direct English translations anymore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/02/10/february-10-2009-hey-look-who-wasnt-trapped-under-a-refrigerator-for-the-past-two-months-after-all-stargate-playback-superviser-krista-mclean-finally-drops-in-to-answer-your-questions/ |title=Hey, Look Who Wasn’t Trapped Under A Refrigerator For The Past Two Months After All! Stargate Playback Superviser Krista McLean Finally Drops In To Answer Your Questions. |publisher=Josephmallozzi’s Weblog |date=2009-02-10 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also many examples that are in keeping with what the Ancients and associated races intended &amp;ndash; the writings on the stairs in the gate-room on Atlantis translate into a sort of greeting for travelers; [[Puddle Jumper]] consoles include instructions on how to use the ship; the Ancient wall in {{sgcite|Reckoning}} describes the use of the Ancient object hidden behind, and the responsibilities that go with it. The sign in Harrid and Sallis' house in the Ori galaxy in &quot;[[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon]]&quot; says what Daniel translates it to be (&quot;This is the nuptial home of \\ Harrid and Sallis Cicera&quot;). The engraved [[Serpent guard (Stargate)|Sodan]] flagstones in {{sgcite|Babylon}} give instructions on how to behave in Sodan society.

==Characters==
{{Main|Ancient characters in Stargate}}
Although most of the Ancients had reached ascension long before the dawn of modern civilization on Earth, the [[Tau'ri]] have come in contact with Ancients on several occasions, both in ascended and corporeal form. Most of the corporeal Ancients were encountered in the Pegasus Galaxy, where their empire had collapsed only some 10,000 years ago. Also, some Ancients helped humans on the lower planes of existence ascend, like Oma Desala helped Daniel Jackson.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.gateworld.net/omnipedia/races/links/ancients.shtml &quot;Ancients&quot;] at [[GateWorld]] Omnipedia.
* [http://www.stargate-sg1-solutions.com/wiki/Ancients &quot;Ancients&quot;] at StargateWiki.
* [http://www.archive.org/details/Matthaeum-AncientTextStargate &quot;The Gospel of Matthew, translated into 'Ancient'&quot;] at Archive.org

{{StargateNav}}

[[Category:Stargate races]]
[[Category:Fictional Atlanteans]]
[[Category:Human-derived fictional species]]

[[ar:القدماء (ستارغيت)]]
[[bs:Drevni]]
[[ca:Antics]]
[[cs:Antikové]]
[[es:Antiguos]]
[[fr:Anciens (Stargate)]]
[[hr:Drevni (Zvjezdana vrata)]]
[[it:Antichi (Stargate)]]
[[ka:ძველები (ვარსკვლავთკარიბჭე)]]
[[hu:Ősök]]
[[nl:Ancients]]
[[ja:エンシェントの遺伝子]]
[[pl:Pradawni (Gwiezdne wrota)]]
[[ro:Străbuni (Stargate)]]
[[ru:Древние (Звёздные врата)]]
[[sk:Antik (Stargate)]]
[[sl:Starodavni]]
[[sh:Drevni (Stargate)]]
[[fi:Muinaiset (Tähtiportti)]]
[[sv:De gamla]]
[[tr:Kadimler (Yıldız Geçidi)]]
[[uk:Древні (Зоряна брама)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
