<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="618672" ns="0" title="Asgard (Stargate)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Thorstargate.jpg|250px|thumb|Thor, an Asgard as seen in the ''SG-1'' episode &quot;Small Victories&quot;.]]
The '''Asgard''' are a [[fiction]]al highly advanced race in the [[science fiction]] series ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' and ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''. They are first mentioned in the episode {{sgcite|Thor's Hammer}}, and first seen in {{sgcite|Thor's Chariot}}. In the series, the Asgard gave rise to [[Norse mythology]] on Earth, as well as accounts of the [[Roswell UFO Incident|Roswell]] &quot;[[Grey alien|Greys]]&quot;. Due to their technological prowess, the Asgard are critical allies in Earth's fight against the [[Goa'uld]], and later the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]]. The Asgard characters on the show are realized through a combination of [[puppet]]s and [[computer-generated imagery]].

== Background ==
The episode {{sgcite|The Fifth Race}} establishes that the Asgard inhabit the galaxy of Ida, and that they were once part of an alliance of four great races with the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]], [[Nox (Stargate)|Nox]], and [[Furling (Stargate)|Furlings]]. In ancient times, the Asgard visited Earth, posing as the gods of [[Norse mythology]]. Norse legends tell of how they protected the humans against the &quot;Etins&quot; ([[Goa'uld]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thor's Hammer|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Asgard protect a number of planets in the Milky Way from Goa'uld attack under the Protected Planets Treaty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fair Game|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the time of ''Stargate SG-1'', the Asgard are a dying race. Having lost the capacity for [[sexual reproduction]], they perpetuate themselves by transferring their minds into successive [[cloning|clone]]d bodies. Repeated generations of cloning has led to an irreversible degeneration of the Asgard genome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Revelations|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 30,000-year-old Asgard ancestor is depicted in {{sgcite|Revelations}}, showing a more human-like appearance.

=== Show history ===
In the ninth episode of season 1, {{sgcite|Thor's Hammer}}, [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] speculates on the existence of an advanced, benevolent race in opposition to the Goa'uld by examining Earth mythologies. This leads [[SG-1]] to the planet Cimmeria, which is free from the Goa'uld thanks to an advanced device called &quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;. SG-1 makes direct contact with Thor in {{sgcite|Thor's Chariot}}, sixth episode of season 2, in which his true Asgard form is seen for the first time. The Asgard lend valuable assistance to Earth on several occasions,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot; /&gt; including providing their technology to Earth ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Disclosure&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Disclosure|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the episode {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, where Thor mediates Earth's inclusion into the Protected Planets Treaty, he reveals to [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] that the Asgard do not have the capability to win a galactic war with the Goa'uld at that time, due to a war with a greater enemy. The Goa'uld [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] ultimately nullifies the treaty after developing shields resistant to Asgard weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot; /&gt; After Anubis' defeat in {{sgcite|Lost City}}, there is speculation amongst the Goa'uld System Lords that the Asgard are no longer able to exercise power in the Milky Way.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot; /&gt;

At the end of season 3, the Asgard's enemy is revealed to be the [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]], a race of machines capable of assimilating any technology they come across. In the episodes {{sgcite|Nemesis}} and {{sgcite|Small Victories}}, they are on the verge of overrunning the Asgard homeworld. Thor enlists SG-1's help in combating them, as &quot;crude&quot; human projectile [[firearm]]s are effective against the Replicators, and the technologically-minded Asgard are incapable of developing unorthodox (i.e. &quot;less sophisticated&quot;) strategies like humans can. With [[Samantha Carter]]'s help, the Replicator invasion force is destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Nemesis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Small Victories|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Unnatural Selection}}, the Asgard reveal that using the android Reese, discovered by SG-1 in {{sgcite|Menace}}, they lured every Replicator in the galaxy to the planet [[Halla (Stargate)|Halla]] with the hopes of trapping them inside a time dilation field. SG-1 activates the field, but the Replicators eventually escape in {{sgcite|New Order}} and head for the planet Orilla, where the Asgard are rebuilding their civilization. The Replicators retreat from the Asgard galaxy after Thor finds specifications for the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator disruptor]] from O'Neill's mind. When the Replicators arrive in the Milky Way in {{sgcite|Gemini}} and {{sgcite|Reckoning}}, Thor helps the SGC develop an effective defense.

After the end of the Replicator threat, the Asgard install significant upgrades in Earth's new battlecruiser, ''Daedalus'', and stationed an Asgard engineer, Hermiod, onboard to oversee the new technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege, Part 3&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Siege, Part 3|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Asgard Kvasir provides assistance to Earth in {{sgcite|Ripple Effect}}, {{sgcite|Camelot}}, and {{sgcite|Flesh and Blood}}, stating that Thor and Heimdall are otherwise engaged in another galaxy. In the ''Stargate SG-1'' finale {{sgcite|Unending}}, Thor reveals that the Asgard have been afflicted by a rapid degenerative disease due to repeated cloning. Unable to [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascend]] due to their seeking a technological solution to extending their lives, there is nothing more that can be done and most of the Asgard civilization elects to self-destruct to prevent their technology from falling into the wrong hands. As their final act, the Asgard install their latest technology on the Earth battlecruiser ''Odyssey'', as well as their entire collected knowledge. The Asgard homeworld Orilla explodes just as the ''Odyssey'' comes under [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] attack.

A renegade faction of Asgard is introduced in the fifth season of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]].''&lt;ref name=&quot;The Lost Tribe&quot;&gt;[http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/09/the_lost_tribe_aliens_revealed.shtml   The Lost Tribe]&lt;/ref&gt; These Asgard splintered from the others 10,000 years ago over their belief that they should experiment on humans to solve their cloning problems. They traveled to the Pegasus galaxy and continued their experiments, but were forced into hiding after the Wraith defeated the Ancients. When their planet became too toxic for them, they unsuccessfully tried to use the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Attero device|Attero Device]] to destroy the Wraith.

==Society==
The governing body of the Asgard is the High Council, shown in {{sgcite|Red Sky}}. It has at least seven members, including Thor, Freyr,&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Sky&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Red Sky|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Penegal.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt; The Asgard masquerade themselves [[holographic]]ally as [[Norse gods]] to the primitive peoples under their protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;/&gt; They have placed tests, such as in the Hall of Thor's Might on Cimmeria, to determine when those peoples have advanced enough for the Asgard to reveal their true forms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;/&gt;

===Protected Planets Treaty===
The Protected Planets Treaty is an [[armistice]] between the Goa'uld and the Asgard, first referred to specifically in {{sgcite|Fair Game}} when Earth is included. The treaty covers 27 planets including Earth,&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|New Order|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ensures that those planets remain free from Goa'uld domination. Other planets in the treaty include Cimmeria,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;/&gt; K'Tau,&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Sky&quot;/&gt; PX3-595,&lt;ref name=&quot;Shades of Grey&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Shades of Grey|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the second planet of the Adara system,&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;/&gt; and Galar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collateral Damage&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Collateral Damage|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The System Lords are responsible for enforcing the treaty amongst the lesser Goa'uld. One stipulation of the treaty is that none of the protected planets are allowed to advance to the point of posing a threat to the Goa'uld; the System Lords cite this condition in their original demand that Earth surrender its [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] to be included in the treaty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;/&gt; Another term of the treaty is that the Asgard are forbidden to artificially advance the civilization of any protected planet, even to save them from a natural disaster. This prevents them from acting to help K'Tau in {{sgcite|Red Sky}} and Earth in {{sgcite|Fail Safe}}. Any violation of the treaty will nullify it as a whole, and free the Goa'uld to attack any protected planet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Sky&quot;/&gt;

The Asgard rely on the treaty to do what good they can in the Milky Way, using the threat of their superior technology to cow the System Lords into accepting the arrangement when, in fact, their resources are taxed fighting the Replicators and they would be unable to win a full-scale war with the Goa'uld.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;/&gt; The treaty becomes largely irrelevant after the season 5 finale {{sgcite|Revelations}}, due to the actions of [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]].

===Technology===
{{Main|Technology in Stargate#Asgard technology|l1=Asgard technology|Starships in Stargate#Asgard starships|l2=Asgard starships}}
The Asgard are one of the most technologically advanced races in the ''Stargate'' universe. They were once contemporaries of the Ancients, and learned much from them.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt; Amongst their most significant advancements are beaming technology, intergalactic hyperdrives, and plasma beam weapons, all of which they have shared with Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Unending&quot;/&gt; The Asgard are no longer capable of traditional reproduction and instead perpetuate themselves through [[cloning]], as they have the technology to upload and store Asgard consciousnesses and transfer them to new bodies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt; [[Neutronium]] is a key element of Asgard technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt; Technology is a central aspect of Asgard civilization; they have become so dependent on it that their mindsets are incapable of coming up with more &quot;primitive&quot; solutions to a problem. This weakness proved critical in their war with the [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;/&gt;

The Asgard's military technology is, with a few exceptions, largely superior to that of the [[Goa'uld]], [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] and even [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] and Lantian period [[Asuran (Stargate)|Asuran]] war ships. Their directed plasma beam weapons are highly effective against nearly all kinds of shields. In addition, Asgard shields are shown to take large amounts of damage from Ori, Wraith, Goa'uld and Ancient weapons. They also appear to be the only shields effective against Ancient drone weapons known to penetrate nearly all other kinds of shields including Ancient shields. However, Asgard shields apparently lose integrity under sustained fire.

==Characters==
===Hermiod===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Universal translator]] --&gt;

'''Hermiod''', named after the [[Norse mythology|Norse]] god [[Hermóðr]] and voiced by [[Trevor Devall]], is an Asgard technician assigned to the ''[[Daedalus (Stargate)|Daedalus]]''. He is tasked with operation of the ship's Asgard transporter and hyperdrive engine, working primarily with [[Lindsey Novak]]. Hermiod mutters to himself when he is displeased with the crew's demands, although his Asgard language is actually normal English played backward. The producers gave him &quot;a little bit of an attitude problem&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title = Stargate Atlantis: Season Two Preview |work = [[TV Zone]] Special #64 |publisher = [[Visual Imagination]] |pages = 76–77 |year = 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; being an angry foreigner utterly convinced of his own brilliance above those around him.

Hermiod is introduced during the ''Daedalus''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt; first mission to [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] in &quot;[[The Siege, Part 3]]&quot;. Hermiod expresses resistance to carry out Colonel [[Steven Caldwell (Stargate)|Steven Caldwell]]'s order to transport several [[nuclear weapons]] on board a [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] hive ship because the Asgard prohibit humans from using the shared Asgard technology offensively, but he later reluctantly agrees to do as ordered.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Siege, Part 3]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Hermiod helps remove a Wraith computer virus that interferes with the ship's computer systems in &quot;[[The Intruder (Stargate Atlantis)|The Intruder]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Intruder&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Intruder (Stargate Atlantis)|The Intruder]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and works with Dr. McKay on the Wraith technology during Atlantis' failed alliance with a [[Wraith Hive-Ship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Allies&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Allies (Stargate Atlantis)|Allies]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Thor===

'''Supreme Commander Thor''', voiced by [[Michael Shanks]], is the Supreme Commander of the Asgard Fleet. [[SG-1]] first encounter him as a [[Viking]] holographic recording (played by [[Mark Gibbon]]) on the planet [[Cimmeria (Stargate)|Cimmeria]] in &quot;[[Thor's Hammer (Stargate SG-1)|Thor's Hammer]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Thor's Hammer (Stargate SG-1)|Thor's Hammer]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; They meet the real Thor one season later when he saves Cimmeria from [[Heru-ur (Stargate)|Heru-ur]]'s invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Thor's Chariot (Stargate SG-1)|Thor's Chariot]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; After O'Neill manages to make friendly contact with the Asgard in their galaxy,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Fifth Race (Stargate SG-1)|The Fifth Race]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Thor includes Earth in the [[Protected Planets Treaty]] to safeguard it from a direct Goa'uld attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Fair Game (Stargate SG-1)|Fair Game]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Late in season 3, SG-1 helps to destroy Thor's ship, the ''[[Beliskner class cruiser|Beliskner]]'', which has been overtaken by the [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]], in &quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Impressed by SG-1's primitive but effective tactics, Thor requests SG-1 to help fight the Replicators in his Asgard homeworld soon after, in &quot;[[Small Victories]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Small Victories (Stargate SG-1)|Small Victories]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Anubis captures Thor and probes his mind for [[Asgard technology in Stargate|Asgard technology]], and Thor's body lapses into a coma in &quot;[[Revelations (Stargate SG-1)|Revelations]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Revelations (Stargate SG-1)|Revelations]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; SG-1 retrieve Thor's consciousness from the ship's database a while later, and transfer it into a new body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Descent&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Descent (Stargate SG-1)|Descent]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Thor asks for SG-1's assistance after his people's plan to trap the Replicators inside a time-dilation field on the planet Halla backfired.&lt;ref name=&quot;Unnatural Selection&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Unnatural Selection (Stargate SG-1)|Unnatural Selection]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Thor personally makes an appearance at a secret meeting between the permanent members of Earth's [[UN Security Council]] taking place in [[the Pentagon]], to ensure the [[Stargate Command|SGC]] retains control over the Earth [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Disclosure&quot;/&gt; As the time-dilation device on Halla cannot keep the Replicators bottled up forever, Thor collapses Halla's sun into a [[black hole]], but some Replicators escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;&quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Some weeks later, Thor and Carter modify their Replicator Disruptor, but as the Replicators quickly adapt, they use the [[Dakara Superweapon]] to destroy all Replicators in one strike. Thor gets a new clone body soon after.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Thor summons the ''[[Odyssey (Stargate)|Odyssey]]'' to the Asgard homeworld Orilla and installs the entire knowledge base of the Asgard race on the ship. As attempts to save the Asgard civilization from their genetic difficulties have failed, he informs Lt. Col. Carter that the people of Earth are the fifth race and makes it their turn to preserve the future. Thor perishes along with the rest of the Asgard race when their planet [[self-destruct]]s before the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] can attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Unending&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Unending (Stargate SG-1)|Unending]]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

Six puppeteers were necessary to make the different parts of the Thor puppet work.&lt;ref&gt;[[Andy Mikita]] in the audio commentary for &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Thor originally speaks slower in the first season, but Michael Shanks, who voiced him since the beginning, joked that he is not getting paid by the hour but by the amount of dialog, when commenting on the increased dialog speed in later episodes.&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter DeLuise]] in the audio commentary for &quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning (Part 1)]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; As the Thor puppet is neither able to walk nor stand, the puppet is often put in a chair.&lt;ref name=ac_401_jt&gt;{{cite video |people=[[James Tichenor]] (VisFX supervisor) |date=2001 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;Small Victories&quot; |medium = DVD &amp;ndash; Stargate SG-1: Season 4 |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Minor characters ===
* {{Anchor|Aegir}}'''Aegir''' (voiced by [[Michael Shanks]]) The commander of a small fleet of ships that protects Orilla in {{sgcite|New Order}}, named after the [[Norse mythology|Norse]] god [[Aegir]]. He destroys [[Fifth (Stargate)|Fifth]]'s Replicator ship as it exits hyperspace, but cannot stop massive numbers of Replicator blocks from raining down on Orilla.
* {{Anchor|Freyr}}'''Freyr''' (voiced by [[Brian Jensen (actor)|Brian Jensen]]) A member of the Asgard High Council, named after [[Freyr]], the [[Norse mythology|Norse]] [[fertility]] god and god of love. SG-1 first encounters him on K'Tau, an Asgard protected planet. Freyr is also initially presented through a [[Viking]] hologram. Freyr refuses to help SG-1 because it would be a violation of the Protected Planets Treaty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Sky&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Red Sky (Stargate SG-1)|Red Sky]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; SG-1 meets Freyr and the Asgard High Council again to save Earth from an approaching [[asteroid]], but get no help.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fail Safe&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Fail Safe (Stargate SG-1)|Fail Safe]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Freyr eventually requests SG-1 to rescue one of their scientists. He protects SG-1, the Asgard scientist [[Heimdall (Stargate)|Heimdall]] and his studies with a fleet of three [[O'Neill class battleship]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;/&gt;
* {{Anchor|Heimdall}}'''Heimdall''' (voiced by [[Teryl Rothery]], who also played Dr. [[Janet Fraiser]]) An Asgard scientist based on the [[Heimdallr]] of [[Norse mythology]]. SG-1 encounters Heimdall in &quot;[[Revelations (Stargate SG-1)|Revelations]]&quot; during his research into finding a solution to the Asgard's cloning difficulties. When the Goa'uld attack Heimdall's planet, SG-1 and Heimdall flee together with the saved Thor and Heimdall's research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot; /&gt; Heimdall continues to look for a solution to the flawed genome with Thor,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ripple Effect&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Ripple Effect (Stargate SG-1)|Ripple Effect]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; but the Asgard race existing within the galaxy of Ida dies at the end of season 10, unaware of the renegade faction existing within the Pegasus Galaxy introduced in the Stargate Atlantis episode 'The Lost Tribe'.
* {{Anchor|Kvasir}}'''Kvasir''' (voiced by [[Morris Chapdelaine]]) An Asgard scientist and expert in time-dilation technology. He is named after [[Kvasir]], a [[Norse mythology|Norse]] god and wisest of the [[Vanir]]. As Thor is busy in the Asgard home galaxy in &quot;[[Ripple Effect (Stargate SG-1)|Ripple Effect]]&quot;, Kvasir visits Earth in Thor's stead to help Earth fix a problem with [[Parallel universe (fiction)|alternate realities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ripple Effect&quot; /&gt; Kvasir also assists SG-1 in battling the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] at the end of season 9 of ''SG-1''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Camelot (Stargate SG-1)|Camelot]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Kvasir survives the battle and helps to repair the transporters of the ''[[Odyssey (Stargate)|Odyssey]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flesh and Blood&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Flesh and Blood (Stargate SG-1)|Flesh and Blood]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Anchor|Loki}}'''Loki''' (voiced by [[Peter DeLuise]]) A rogue Asgard scientist working to find a cure for his species' genomic decay. He is based on [[Loki]], the [[Norse mythology|Norse god]] of mischief. His unauthorized experiments on Earth humans have inspired many accounts of [[alien abduction]]s. In {{sgcite|Fragile Balance}}, he is responsible for creating the younger [[cloning|clone]] of Jack O'Neill as a side product of his studies on O'Neill's brain. At the end of the episode, Thor, visibly angry at Loki's actions takes Loki into custody.
* {{Anchor|Penegal}}'''Penegal''' (voiced by [[Michael Shanks]]) A member of the Asgard High Council in &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order, Part II]]&quot;. He informs Thor of the Replicators's attack on Orilla.

==See also==
*[[Nordic aliens]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

{{StargateNav}}

[[Category:Stargate races]]
[[Category:Fictional clones]]
[[Category:Fictional deities]]
[[Category:Fictional endangered and extinct species]]

[[ar:أسغارد (ستارغيت)]]
[[bs:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[ca:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[cs:Asgardi]]
[[es:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[fr:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[hr:Asgard (Zvjezdana vrata)]]
[[it:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[ka:ასგარდი (ვარსკვლავთკარიბჭე)]]
[[hu:Asgard (Csillagkapu)]]
[[nl:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[ja:アスガード (スターゲイト)]]
[[pl:Asgard (Gwiezdne wrota)]]
[[ro:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[ru:Азгарды (Звёздные врата)]]
[[sk:Asgardi]]
[[sl:Asgardci]]
[[sh:Asgard (Stargate)]]
[[fi:Asgard (Tähtiportti)]]
[[sv:Lista över raser i Stargate#Asgard]]
[[tr:Asgard (Yıldız Geçidi)]]
[[uk:Азгарди]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
