<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="618900" ns="0" title="Stargate Program"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:NORADNorth-Portal.jpg|250px|thumb|The entrance to the [[Cheyenne Mountain complex]] in [[Colorado]], home to Earth's Stargate Command in the ''Stargate'' universe.]]
The '''Stargate Program''' is a fictional top-secret program that plays a key role in the ''[[Stargate]]'' franchise: it surrounds the operations of the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] on Earth. The core of the Stargate Program is Stargate Command (SGC), based at the [[Cheyenne Mountain|Cheyenne Mountain Air Force Station]] near [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]]. During the run of ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'', the [[Stargate Program#NID|NID]] is most critical of the Stargate Program, while the program is extended through the establishment of the Department of Homeworld Security and the International Oversight Advisory (IOA). The Atlantis Project as seen in ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' is part of the Stargate Program but works independently during season 1 of the show.

Despite alien attacks such as in &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot; and &quot;[[Ex Deus Machina (Stargate SG-1)|Ex Deus Machina]]&quot;, all attempts are made throughout the series to keep the existence of the Stargate Program secret, assuming there would be mass panic if the public found out. Several alternate-universe episodes address the public reaction to the revelation of the Stargate Program.&lt;ref name=&quot;2010 episode&quot;&gt;&quot;[[2010 (Stargate SG-1)|2010]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Road Not Taken&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Road Not Taken (Stargate SG-1)|The Road Not Taken]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, some conspiracy theorists in the series assume extraterrestrial activity at the highest levels of the military.&lt;ref name=&quot;Covenant&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Covenant (Stargate SG-1)|Covenant]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; A very few select civilians such as [[Pete Shanahan]] and [[Jeannie Miller]] are also aware of the existence of the Program.

==Earth and the Stargate==
{{See also|Mythology of Stargate#Tau'ri|Stargate (device)|l1=Earth in Stargate Mythology}}
Following a backstory spanning millions of years, the modern history of Earth's Stargate Program begins when the Stargate is unearthed in [[Egypt]] in 1928. The device is eventually brought to the [[United States]] in 1939 to keep it out of [[Nazi]] hands and eventually installed in a facility in Creek Mountain, [[Colorado]] ([[Cheyenne Mountain]] in ''Stargate SG-1'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;&gt;''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]''&lt;/ref&gt; In the events of the [[Stargate (film)|''Stargate'' film]], Dr. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] deciphers the workings of the Stargate. A team is sent through to the planet on the other side, where they encounter and defeat the malevolent [[Ra (Stargate)|Ra]], freeing his slaves. Under the belief that there was only one possible destination through the Stargate, no further missions are planned through the Stargate and the program shut down.

The ''Stargate SG-1'' premiere {{sgcite|Children of the Gods}} reveals the existence of another grave extraterrestrial threat to Earth, [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]], and that there are in fact thousands of planets accessible through the Stargate. As a result, the [[United States]] establishes Stargate Command inside Cheyenne Mountain and commissions nine teams (which increases to many more in the later seasons) to travel through the Gate to assess threats, open negotiations with other civilizations, and procure technology to defend Earth. The first SG mission to Apophis' homeworld, Chulak, sees the defection of Jaffa warrior [[Teal'c]] to Earth. In the early seasons of ''Stargate SG-1'', SG teams from Earth fights battles against Apophis and the Goa'uld [[System Lord]]s. Along the way, they make offworld allies including the [[Tok'ra]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tok'ra&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Tok'ra|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Hammer&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thor's Hammer|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; support a growing rebellion amongst the Jaffa,&lt;ref name=&quot;Within the Serpent's Grasp&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Within the Serpent's Grasp|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and encounter a dangerous new threat from another galaxy, the mechanical [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicator]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Nemesis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Stargate Program also endures challenges from its own government; the ambitious Senator [[Robert Kinsey]] seeks to shut down and later control the SGC,&lt;ref name=&quot;Politics&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Politics|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chain Reaction&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Chain Reaction|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the activities of the unscrupulous N.I.D. threatens to destabilize Earth's offworld relations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Touchstone&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Touchstone|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Season eight of ''Stargate SG-1'' sees the final defeat of the System Lords and the Replicators, changing the political face of the galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Reckoning|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] also discovers the address for the Ancients' Lost City of Atlantis in the Pegasus galaxy, and the international Atlantis Expedition is formed. In Pegasus Earth discovers more enemies, including the life-consuming [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] and the nanite [[Asuran]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Rising|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Progeny&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Progeny|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new enemy, the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]], is introduced in the ninth season of ''SG-1''. Their story arc is concluded in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' with the defeat of the last Ori, the Ascended being Adria, and the turning of her armies.

==Stargate Command==
The core of the fictional Stargate Program is '''Stargate Command''' ('''SGC'''), a publicly undisclosed [[military]] unit organized under the [[United States Department of the Air Force|Department of the Air Force]], and based at the [[Cheyenne Mountain|Cheyenne Mountain Air Force Station]] near [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]].&lt;ref name=wire_cracks&gt;{{cite web |last=Adams |first=John Joseph |url=http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/index.php?category=0&amp;id=58573 |title=Exclusive: Wire Cracks Stargate Command |publisher=SciFi Wire |date=August 13, 2008 |accessdate=2008-09-18 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080822101534/http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/index.php?category=0&amp;id=58573 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; (and at Creek Mountain Facility, a fictional name for Cheyenne Mountain in the ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' film). Although on-base support personnel wear patches of [[Air Force Space Command|Air Force Space Command (AFSPC)]], it has not been clarified whether or not Stargate Command itself is a component of that organization or a separate entity. Stargate Command, also referred to by its codename &quot;[[Area 52]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Politics&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Politics|episodelink=Politics (Stargate SG-1)|series=Stargate SG-1|serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; is tasked with operating the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] on Earth and coordinates exploration and diplomatic relationships through the Stargate. Long-term research of alien technology is usually moved from the SGC to [[Area 51]] in Nevada. Stargate Command is constituted and activated in the pilot episode of ''Stargate SG-1'', &quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot;, when the [[Goa'uld]] threat is first recognized. The writers considered replacing ''Stargate SG-1'' with a new show named ''Stargate Command'' after ''SG-1''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; eighth season,&lt;ref name=ac_901&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Robert C. Cooper|Cooper, Robert C.]], [[Andy Mikita|Mikita, Andy]] |date=2006 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon, Part 1]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the [[Sci Fi Channel (United States)|Sci Fi Channel]] decided to continue ''SG-1'' for two more seasons instead.

===Facility===
[[Image:NORADBlast-Doors.jpg|thumb|Footage of Cheyenne Mountain, Colorado, such as the blast doors into the complex, were shown in the ''Stargate'' series.]]
{{See also|Stargate (device)|Earth technology in Stargate}}
The '''SGC''' base, where most episodes of ''SG-1'' begin and end, is the main setting in ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' and occasionally features on ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''. Half a dozen stock shots of Cheyenne Mountain were filmed at the beginning of the series and re-used until season 8, but the producers did not decide until the beginning of season 9 to film new shots, thinking that ''Stargate SG-1'' would be cancelled after each current year.&lt;ref name=ac_904 /&gt; The interior of the SGC base, together with the [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] set, is filmed at stages 5 and 6 at [[The Bridge Studios]] in [[Vancouver]], Canada. In 2009, the sets were redressed to portray Icarus Base from Stargate Universe, after which the sets were finally struck after standing for a dozen years.

Like the real Cheyenne Mountain Air Force Station,&lt;ref name=wire_cracks /&gt; the SGC extends many levels beneath the ground (officially called sub-levels), thus protecting the base from most forms of attack including indirect nuclear detonations. In the ''Stargate'' universe, the base also serves to contain biological, chemical or alien hazards to the outside world by means of a 'lockdown' status.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Lockdown (Stargate SG-1)|Lockdown]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The briefing room and the SGC Commander's office is located at level 27, while the '''Gate Room''' with the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] and an elevated '''Control Room''' are at level 28. A long ramp in the middle of the Gateroom leading up to the Stargate allows vehicles (such as the [[M.A.L.P.]] robot probe) to enter the Stargate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;/&gt; The Stargate may be lifted in and out through a ceiling that can open.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot; /&gt; The real Cheyenne Mountain Air Force Station denies fan theories of the existence of a Stargate in their Command Center.&lt;ref name=wire_cracks /&gt; 

The [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] is equipped with a metallic barrier called the [[Iris (Stargate)|Iris]] to prevent hostile aliens from entering the SGC. Off-world SG teams additionally carry a [[GDO (Stargate)|GDO]] to identify themselves to the SGC. If nevertheless faced with an alien invasion, the facility has a self-destruct mechanism, which has been activated on more than one occasion on the show. According to [[Samantha Carter|Colonel Samantha Carter]], the self-destruct is not powerful enough to destroy the Stargate or to disconnect an active wormhole, but it would bury the gate under 1000 metric tons of rock to stop incoming travelers.{{Episode|date=August 2008}}&lt;!--Maybe season 2's &quot;Matter of Time&quot;--&gt;

===Organizational structure===
The SGC is typically commanded by an active-duty U.S. Air Force commissioned officer with the grade of [[Major general (United States)|Major General]], and is staffed by a mixture of military and civilian subject matter experts, military support personnel (e.g. members of the [[United States Air Force Security Forces|Air Force Security Forces]] and [[United States Air Force Medical Service|Air Force Medical Service]]), and several SG teams, most notably [[SG-1]]. Stargate Command began operations with 9 SG teams;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot;, '''George Hammond:''' &quot;The President of the United States [...] has ordered the formation of nine teams, whose duties will be to perform reconnaissance, determine threats, and if possible to make peaceful contact with the peoples of these worlds. Now, these teams will operate on a covert, top-secret basis. No one will know of their existence except the President and the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff|Joint Chiefs]].&lt;/ref&gt; at the time of season 10's &quot;[[Uninvited (Stargate SG-1)|Uninvited]]&quot;, there were at least 25 SG teams.&lt;ref name=&quot;uninvited&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Uninvited (Stargate SG-1)| title=Uninvited| series=Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the teams are [[United States Air Force|U.S. Air Force]] with some [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marine Corps]], civilians and later [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] as well. Military forces of foreign nations have been included as the existence of the Stargate was revealed to other countries (the first were the Russians, agreed to in &quot;[[Redemption (Stargate SG-1)|Redemption (Part 2)]]&quot;, first seen in &quot;[[The Tomb (Stargate SG-1)|The Tomb]]&quot;). A chosen few [[Extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrials]] ([[Teal'c]], [[Jonas Quinn]], and [[Vala Mal Doran]]) have also been allowed to join the SG teams. These off world teams usually operate as teams of four, although that is not a requirement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Redemption (Stargate SG-1)|Redemption]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first leader of the SGC is [[Major General West]] in the film, followed by Major General [[George Hammond (Stargate)|George Hammond]] from season 1 through 7. Major General Bauer briefly replaces Hammond, who retires under duress in season 4's &quot;[[Chain Reaction (Stargate SG-1)|Chain Reaction]]&quot;. Dr. [[Elizabeth Weir (Stargate)|Elizabeth Weir]] becomes the first civilian commander of the SGC after Hammond's reassignment in season 7's &quot;[[Lost City]]&quot;. When Weir leaves the SGC in season 8's &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot; to be in charge of the [[Atlantis Expedition]] early in Season 8, Brigadier General [[Jack O'Neill]] takes over for season 8 until he replaces Hammond as the commander of the [[Department of Homeworld Security]] in early season 9.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Major General [[Hank Landry (Stargate)|Hank Landry]] is leader of the SGC in seasons 9 and 10 and the two direct-to-DVD ''SG-1'' films.

===Alternative sites===
The last line of defense for the SGC is an off-world base called the '''Alpha Site''', initially established as a settlement to evacuate a select number of the academic elite of the United States to in case of Goa'uld invasion. It later serves as an emergency back-up for the SGC, and off-world [[SG team]]s will contact the Alpha Site if they are unable to make contact with the SGC. As seen in season 6's &quot;[[Allegiance (Stargate SG-1)|Allegiance]]&quot;, several of Earth's allies, mainly the [[Tok'ra]] and [[Jaffa Resistance|Rebel Jaffa]], use this site as a secure location to hide from the [[Goa'uld]]. The Alpha Site also serves as the temporary home for any large groups of people that are evacuated from their own planets,&lt;ref name=tvzones46_43 /&gt; and a testing facility for Earth's new prototype spacecraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Covenant&quot;/&gt; A similar concept exists for the Atlantis Expedition in ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''.

Although the Alpha Site is mentioned in season 2 of ''Stargate SG-1'' (P3X-984),&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Serpent's Lair}}&lt;/ref&gt; the first Alpha Site is only shown in the season 6 episode &quot;[[Allegiance (Stargate SG-1)|Allegiance]]&quot;. The planet designated as P3X-984, in the storyline unknown to the Goa'uld,&lt;ref name=&quot;Allegiance&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Allegiance (Stargate SG-1)|Allegiance]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; was shot in a gravel pit at [[Mount Seymour]] in North Vancouver.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_15&gt;{{Cite journal | last=Eramo | first=Steven | author-link= | title=SG-1 &amp;ndash; Amanda Tapping &amp;ndash; Tapping Aloud | journal=[[TV Zone]] | issue=Special 46 | pages=15 | year=2002 | date=July 2002 | url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The set designers used a number of sets from season 4's &quot;[[Prodigy (Stargate SG-1)|Prodigy]]&quot; for the façade and filled the remaining gaps with the set decorator and transportation tents.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_43&gt;{{Cite journal | last=Eramo | first=Steven | author-link= | title=SG-1 &amp;ndash; The Production Design Team &amp;ndash; The Art of the Design | journal=[[TV Zone]] | issue=Special 46 | pages=43 | year=2002 | date=July 2002 | url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; After [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] probes [[Jonas Quinn]]'s mind in season 7's &quot;[[Fallen (Stargate SG-1)|Fallen]]&quot; and learns of the first Alpha Site, a second Alpha site is built. Some months after its establishment, it falls under attack by several [[Kull Warriors]] in season 7's &quot;[[Death Knell (Stargate SG-1)|Death Knell]]&quot; and is abandoned. [[Peter DeLuise]] came up with this story idea when a large amount of wood was cut down in the [[Seymour River (Burrard Inlet)|Seymour River]] watershed in [[North Vancouver]] (where outside locations of ''Stargate SG-1'' were often filmed), resembling the aftermath of an explosion.&lt;ref name=ac_816&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Peter DeLuise|DeLuise, Peter]] |date=2005 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Death Knell (Stargate SG-1)|Death Knell]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third Alpha Site is built inside a mountain on P4X-650, and has a runway for the [[F-302]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Covenant&quot; /&gt; [[RepliCarter]] visits this facility in &quot;[[Gemini (Stargate SG-1)|Gemini]]&quot;, as part of a ruse to rid herself of [[Fifth (Stargate)|Fifth]] and learn more about the Ancient Replicator disruptor.

Season 7's &quot;[[Death Knell (Stargate SG-1)|Death Knell]]&quot; mentions a '''Beta Site''' on an unknown planet as a back-up facility operated by the SGC. Other Beta sites are mentioned in [[Parallel universe (fiction)|alternate realities]] &amp;ndash; one equivalent to the Alpha Site in season 1's &quot;[[There But For the Grace of God (Stargate SG-1)|There But For the Grace of God]]&quot;, and another is mentioned in season 3's &quot;[[Point of View (Stargate SG-1)|Point of View]]&quot;. A '''Gamma Site''' is shown in season 9's &quot;[[The Scourge (Stargate SG-1)|The Scourge]]&quot; as a research outpost established on a planet with unique radioactive ionosphere 24,000 [[light year]]s from Earth. The base has several [[F-302]]'s attached to it. At any given time more than 30 scientists conduct research in several fields including [[biology]], [[botany]], [[entomology]] and [[physics]]. After the auto-destruct of this Gamma Site, a new Gamma Site relays a message in &quot;[[The Pegasus Project (Stargate SG-1)|The Pegasus Project]]&quot;.

===Area 51===
First mentioned in {{sgcite|Touchstone}}, '''Area 51''' is a top-secret military facility at [[Nellis Air Force Base]] in [[Nevada]] that serves as an alternate research site for the SGC. Many alien technologies brought back through the Stargate are studied or stored at Area 51.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smoke and Mirrors&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Smoke and Mirrors|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The X-301 fighter and its successor the F-302 are developed at Area 51.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Redemption|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tangent&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Tangent|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ancient control chair was moved to [[Area 51]] a month before Stargate Atlantis S05E20 &quot;Enemy at the Gate&quot;, due to it being in violation of international law, during an attack by a Wraith hive-ship powered by a ZPM (Zero-Point Module), at least a portion of the base is destroyed by two kamikaze darts, destroying the Ancient control chair in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemy At The Gate&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Enemy at the Gate|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Atlantis Project==
{{Main|Stargate Atlantis}}
The '''Atlantis Project''', also called the '''Atlantis Expedition''', is Earth's international mission to the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancient]] city of [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] in the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]]. The impetus for the creation of the expedition was the discovery of the [[Drone Weapon|Ancient outpost]] in Antarctica in the episode &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot;. The reason that it is international is that it was felt that a project of such importance could not be the exclusive province of one nation, as well as the fact that according to [[Antarctic Treaty System|American and international law]], Antarctica is international territory and hence it would be technically illegal for the United States to operate any facilities without international participation or at least international knowledge. An international committee, originally called the Atlantis Committee was established, creating the first truly international body for the management of Earth's offworld affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot; /&gt; It is composed of the representatives of several nations, but the leaders of the committee seem to be the United States, the United Kingdom, France, Canada, Russia, and China. However, numerous nations have sent people to Atlantis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Rising (Stargate Atlantis)|Rising]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of the off-world exploration teams are [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marine Corps]] with some [[United States Air Force|U.S. Air Force]] and multi-national civilian members. Multi-national soldiers from at least six countries (Russia, United Kingdom, Canada, Germany, Spain and South Africa) are assigned to the Atlantis base security unit. The Atlantis military component is originally led by Marine Corps Colonel [[List of Tau'ri characters in Stargate Atlantis#Marshall Sumner|Marshall Sumner]], who after his death is replaced by Air Force Major [[John Sheppard (Stargate)|John Sheppard]], the second highest ranking military officer at this time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=Rising |episodelink=Rising (Stargate Atlantis) |series=Stargate Atlantis |serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the personnel who first arrive in Atlantis, at least three teams are established during ''Atlantis'' season one. No official team designations are mentioned in the series.  However, during the first season, director and creative consultant [[Peter DeLuise]] has called the teams 'Atlantis Reconnaissance Team 1', 'Team 2' and 'Team 3' (or AR-1, AR-2 and AR-3), and writer and executive producer [[Joseph Mallozzi]] has called the teams 'First Atlantis Reconnaissance Team', 'Second Atlantis Reconnaissance Team', etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;jmblog1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://josephmallozzi.blogspot.com/2007/04/april-27-2007.html |title=Blog |work=JosephMallozzi.blogspot.com |first=Joseph |last=Mallozzi |date=2007-04-27 |accessdate=2007-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jmforum1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://forum.gateworld.net/showpost.php?p=4387968&amp;postcount=2098 |title=Ask Joe Mallozzi… |work=Gateworld.net |first=Joseph |last=Mallozzi |date=2005-07-27 |accessdate=2007-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of season 2, Sheppard is promoted to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel and instated as military component commander of the expanded Atlantis Expedition.&lt;ref name=&quot;intruder&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=The Intruder |episodelink=The Intruder (Stargate Atlantis) |series=Stargate Atlantis |serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of commissioned officers are established as team leaders, and several specialist teams are put together for single missions.&lt;ref&gt;The [[anthropology|anthropologist]] team in &quot;[[Suspicion (Stargate Atlantis)|Suspicion]]&quot; and the marine teams for search and rescue operations in &quot;[[Runner (Stargate Atlantis)|Runner]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Destiny Expedition==
{{Main|Stargate Universe}}
The '''Destiny Expedition''' is a reconnaissance mission to the previously unmanned [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancient]] vessel [[Destiny (Stargate)#Destiny-class ship|''Destiny'']], which was part of an experiment to seed galaxies with [[Stargate (device)|Stargates]]. Millions of years prior to the expedition – perhaps even before the Ancients' war with the Wraith or Atlantis' move to the Pegasus Galaxy – the Ancients sent several ships across the universe, the first vessels are automated ships sent out to seed various galaxies with Stargates, and the second, ''Destiny'', to follow-up, exploring and possibly colonizing the Stargate-seeded planets. The ninth chevron on a standard Stargate is used to travel to the ''Destiny'', which is still unmanned due to the Ancients' ascension. However, the experiment was abandoned when the Ancients [[Ascension (Stargate)|ascended]], leaving the ship abandoned in the void until the expedition's arrival.

The expedition plans to set off from the '''Icarus Base''', a secret off-world research base set up by the SGC. However, a faction of The Lucian Alliance commanded by Commander Keva who have Colonel Telford under their control and with his help attack the base, forcing the expedition to escape through the Stargate onto the ''Destiny''. Due to their hasty escape, the people find themselves without adequate food, water, or supplies on a old, neglected, decaying ship with air leaks and failing life support. In addition, many people on the ship were never intended to go on the expedition, while others who were supposed to join it never did.

The ''Destiny'' travels on a preprogrammed course, following the first ship's path throughout the universe. Since it is impossible for the team to alter its course, there is no way to return to Earth. At each planet, the ship stops for a fixed amount of time for the crew to explore the world's truly alien landscapes and species. However, if a member of the crew is left behind when the ship leaves, the crew member is stranded, for there is no way for the crew to turn the ship around. Rush is left behind in [[List of Stargate Universe Episodes|Season one]]'s [[Justice (Stargate Universe)|Justice]] on a planet. Although he manages to return to the ship as he is captured by currently unnamed aliens and escapes to Destiny when the Aliens try to take the ship. Lt. Scott, Eli, Chloe and Sgt. Greer are forcibly left behind in [[Human (Stargate Universe)|Human]].
At the end of Season 1 Colonel Telford and some of Commander Keva's Lucian Alliance faction find another power source and manage to 'gate' to Destiny and take control of the ship with devices they brought with them.

==NID {{anchor|NID|Rogue NID|Trust|The Trust}} ==&lt;!--alternate names to serve as anchor--&gt;
The '''NID''' is a shadowy [[intelligence agency]] that appears throughout the run of ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'', but also in the ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' episodes &quot;[[Critical Mass (Stargate Atlantis)|Critical Mass]]&quot;, &quot;[[Miller's Crossing (Stargate Atlantis)|Miller's Crossing]]&quot; and &quot;[[Outcast (Stargate Atlantis)|Outcast]]&quot;. Its official mandate is to provide vital civilian oversight of top secret military operations, but one of their unofficial primary goals is to procure alien technologies. The producers initially wanted to call the organization NRD for &quot;No Real Department&quot;, but its sound and affinity to Joseph Mallozzi, Paul Mullie and Don S. Davis convinced them to rename it to &quot;NID&quot; instead.&lt;ref name=ac_617&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Joseph Mallozzi]], [[Paul Mullie]] and [[Don S. Davis]] |date=2003 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Disclosure (Stargate SG-1)|Disclosure]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the acronym still stands for nothing in particular,&lt;ref name=ac_512&gt;{{cite video |people= |date=2002 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Wormhole X-Treme!]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Stargate SG-1 (roleplaying game)|Stargate SG-1 Roleplaying Game]] says it stands for '''National Intelligence Department'''.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Stargate SG-1 (roleplaying game)|Stargate SG-1 Roleplaying Game]]: Core Rulebook''&lt;/ref&gt; The NID is made up of federal agents like [[Malcolm Barrett (Stargate)|Malcolm Barrett]], bureaucrats like [[Richard Woolsey]], and military personnel such as Colonels [[Tau'ri characters in Stargate SG-1#Colonel Simmons|Simmons]] and [[Harry Maybourne]]. A set of well-resourced illegal cells named the Rogue NID uses unscrupulous methods to achieve the goals of the official NID and is later replaced by the Trust. With the creation of the [[International Oversight Advisory|IOA]], the NID becomes a more legitimate organization, working for the security of the Stargate program and aiding the SGC. 

Throughout the run of ''Stargate SG-1'', the work of the '''Rogue NID''' is associated with Colonel [[Harry Maybourne]]. The group initially uses the second Stargate unearthed in &quot;[[Solitudes (Stargate SG-1)|Solitudes]]&quot;, and later bases their operations off-world or in disused warehouses throughout the Earth. The rogue elements justify their unscrupulous methods as defense from the [[Goa'uld]] attack on Earth regardless of considerations like inter-planetary diplomacy,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Touchstone (Stargate SG-1)|Touchstone]]&quot;. General Hammond recalls &quot;a philosophical skirmish about its mandate. Some people wanted to make sure that any and all discoveries were brought back regardless of considerations like inter-planetary diplomacy.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; criticising the diplomatic contacts and negotiations of the SGC as too slow. The leading shadow group of the rogue NID, &quot;'''The Committee'''&quot;, are made up of various individual businessmen, politicians and corporations who wish to exploit alien technology for financial gain. The more prominent members of the rogue NID are later revealed to be Senator [[Robert Kinsey]] and Colonel [[Frank Simmons]]. The SGC puts an end to the rogue NID in &quot;[[Smoke and Mirrors (Stargate SG-1)|Smoke and Mirrors]]&quot; after arresting and imprisoning the majority of its upper echelon.

'''The Trust''' is a shady interplanetary terrorist group composed of rogue ex-NID operatives and the international business and political [[cabal]] which funds them. The Trust is more radical in their methods and objectives than the Rogue NID, coming into direct conflict with the SGC and the U.S. Air Force several times. When the producers came up with story ideas for this group, they found that ''[[Alias (TV series)|Alias]]'' had used all the names they could think of. It was not until several weeks after they had decided on the name &quot;Trust&quot; that they found out that ''Alias'' had used that name as well. Faced with the choice to either go with the Trust or with what [[Joseph Mallozzi]] called &quot;The Former Rogue Elements of the N.I.D. Now Working for Private Interests Bent on Global Domination&quot;, they chose the first option.&lt;ref name=gw_making_807&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/sg1/s8/making/807.shtml |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |title=In the Making: &quot;Affinity&quot; |publisher=''[[GateWorld]]'' |accessdate=2008-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Vice President Kinsey still shows his strong ties to the rogue ex-NID agents in season 7's &quot;[[Inauguration (Stargate SG-1)|Inauguration]]&quot; and is subsequently forced into resigning, the SGC learns the name &quot;the Trust&quot; in season 8's &quot;[[Covenant (Stargate SG-1)|Covenant]]&quot;. The Trust use a Goa'uld ship in &quot;[[Endgame (Stargate SG-1)|Endgame]]&quot; to launch an all-out attack on the Goa'uld with symbiote poison, without regard to [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] or [[Tok'ra]] life. Season 8's &quot;[[Full Alert (Stargate SG-1)|Full Alert]]&quot; reveals that the Goa'uld have successfully infiltrated and captured some of Trust members, providing an immediate power base for the Goa'uld; [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] has taken control of the Trust by &quot;[[Ex Deus Machina]]&quot;. The Trust last appears in ''Stargate SG-1'' in season 10's &quot;[[Memento Mori (Stargate SG-1)|Memento Mori]]&quot;, capturing Vala to find an infinite treasure, but they also appear in the ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' season 2 episode &quot;[[Critical Mass (Stargate Atlantis)|Critical Mass]]&quot;, planting an explosive device in the City of Atlantis.

==Political oversight==
===Department of Homeworld Security===
The top-secret '''Department of Homeworld Security''' controls the Stargate Program (Stargate Command, including its associated research facility at Area 51 and the [[Alpha Site|Alpha, Beta and Gamma sites]]), which were originally directly overseen by the President and the [[United States Secretary of Defense|Secretary of Defense]] through the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The Department of Homeworld Security also controls the [[F-302]]/[[Daedalus class battlecruiser|BC-304]] program and coordinates the oversight of the Ancient outpost in [[Antarctica]],&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;&quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; while the [[#International Oversight Advisory|International Oversight Authority]] (IOA) holds direct (political) authority over the Antarctic base and the Atlantis expedition. The Department of Homeworld Security was established by President [[Henry Hayes (Stargate)|Henry Hayes]] after the events of &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot;, with Lieutenant General [[George Hammond (Stargate)|George Hammond]] as its first leader. When Hammond retires from [[United States Air Force|USAF]] active service and moves on to another position, Major General [[Jack O'Neill]] takes over in early season 9.

Homeworld Command is located in the Pentagon, as seen in the ''[[Stargate Universe]]'' episode &quot;Earth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Stargate Universe]]'' 1.07 Earth 2:20&lt;/ref&gt;

===International agreements {{anchor|Gate Alliance Treaty}} ===
The [[United States]], by virtue of its control of the Stargate, is largely responsible for Earth's interstellar policy in the ''Stargate'' franchise. More nations gradually come to take part in its use. Following the events of season 3's &quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot;, [[Russia]] briefly establish their own Stargate program based in Siberia, which is terminated and merged with the United States program running out of Cheyenne Mountain shortly after season 4's &quot;[[Watergate (Stargate SG-1)|Watergate]]&quot;. The United States and Russia inform the other three permanent members of the [[UN]] [[Security Council]] (the [[United Kingdom]], [[France]], and the [[People's Republic of China]]) in season 6's &quot;[[Disclosure (Stargate SG-1)|Disclosure]]&quot;, in the hopes of pooling their combined military resources to defend Earth against [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]]'s fleet. The US President also informs long-time ally [[Canada]] about Stargate Command's fleet engagement plans in &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot;. 

After the defeat of Anubis's fleet and the subsequent discovery of the Ancient outpost in Antarctica, an international committee is established to oversee it and the Atlantis expedition. The five permanent members of the UN Security Council and the signatory members of the [[Antarctic Treaty]] (including [[Australia]], [[Jamaica]], [[Philippines]], [[Portugal]], [[Croatia]] and [[Spain]]) sign the '''Gate Alliance Treaty''', which specifies that all acquired alien technology will be shared between the member nations, in exchange for assistance in keeping the program secret. However, in the following three years, the US military interprets the treaty to only apply to non-military technology, which the Chinese delegate mentions as a sore point in &quot;[[The Scourge (Stargate SG-1)|The Scourge]]&quot;. Still, not all nations have been informed about the existence of the Stargate.

===International Oversight Advisory (IOA) {{anchor|IOA|International Oversight Advisory}} ===&lt;!--alternate names to serve as anchor--&gt;
The '''IOA''' (or '''International Oversight Advisory''') is a civilian oversight committee, created after the United States and Russia revealed the existence of the Stargate Program to the other [[UN Security Council#Permanent members|permanent members of the UN Security Council]] in season 6's &quot;[[Disclosure (Stargate SG-1)|Disclosure]]&quot;. The IOA has also been referred to as the &quot;International Oversight Committee&quot; on the show, until producer [[Joseph Mallozzi]] realized during the writing of &quot;[[The Ties That Bind (Stargate SG-1)|The Ties That Bind]]&quot; that the acronym IOC is already used by the [[International Olympic Committee]].&lt;ref name=ac_904&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Joseph Mallozzi|Mallozzi, Joseph]], [[Martin Gero|Gero, Martin]] |date=2006 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[The Ties That Bind (Stargate SG-1)|The Ties That Bind]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The IOA is in control of the [[Atlantis Expedition]] and also of funding, and approves any missions involving [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] or Earth's battle cruisers. Although not having direct authority over [[Stargate Command]], which as a [[List of Major Commands of the United States Air Force|command of the United States Air Force]] is controlled by the [[United States Department of Defense]],&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt; the IOA assigns a representative to the SGC in exchange for further funding in &quot;[[The Ties That Bind (Stargate SG-1)|The Ties That Bind]]&quot;. The writers originally wanted to set up an IOA watchdog character on ''SG-1'' and possibly have [[Richard Woolsey]] on the base all the time, but season 9 already had so many new characters that the writers did not develop this idea.&lt;ref name=ac_904 /&gt;

The most prominent IOA member is [[Richard Woolsey]] as a US representative. Two other American IOA members are James Marrick ([[Currie Graham]]), shown in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', and Coolidge ([[Rob LaBelle]]), shown in &quot;[[Midway (Stargate Atlantis)|Midway]]&quot;. Representatives of other nations are shown in season 9's &quot;[[The Scourge (Stargate SG-1)|The Scourge]]&quot; &amp;ndash; Russel Chapman of the United Kingdom (played by [[Andy Maton]]), Jean Lapierre of France ([[Mark Oliver]]), Chen Xiaoyi of China ([[Tamlyn Tomita]]), and [[Chekov (Stargate)|Col. Chekov]] of Russia ([[Gary Chalk (actor)|Gary Chalk]]). When these representatives review operations at the SGC and Atlantis, members of both the SGC and the Atlantis expedition display a rather low opinion of the IOA. According to Dr. [[Elizabeth Weir (Stargate)|Elizabeth Weir]] in &quot;[[No Man's Land (Stargate Atlantis)|No Man's Land]]&quot;, the IOA's inability to make final decisions is only a strategic maneuver to not take responsibility, therefore having a [[scapegoat]] (such as Weir herself) in case things go wrong. In ''[[Stargate Universe]]'', [[Camile Wray]] is the highest-ranking surviving member of the IOA onboard the ''Destiny'' and acts the ship's de facto civilian leader. In &quot;Life&quot;, the IOA leadership on Earth stated their support for Wray to command the ''Destiny'' instead of Colonel [[Everett Young]].

==Starship program==
{{Main|Earth starships in Stargate}}
Earth's efforts to construct starships of its own using reverse-engineered alien technology begin in the season 4 episode {{sgcite|Tangent}}, with the less-than-successful X-301. In season 6, the X-302 (later F-302), the first spaceworthy Earth fighter, is introduced,&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot;/&gt; along with Earth's first space battlecruiser, the ''Prometheus''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prometheus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prometheus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Squadrons of F-302s are eventually stationed on Earth, [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], the SGC's alternative sites, and its battlecruisers. In season 2 of ''Stargate Atlantis'', the ''Daedalus''-class battlecruiser is introduced, incorporating advancements that were tested on the ''Prometheus''. Thus far, six ''Daedalus''-class battlecruisers have appeared in the series: the ''Daedalus'',&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege, Part 3&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Siege, Part 3|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Odyssey'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Off the Grid&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Off the Grid|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Korolev'' (destroyed in season 9),&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Camelot|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Apollo'',&lt;ref name=&quot;First Strike&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|First Strike|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Sun Tzu'', and the ''George Hammond'' (named the ''Phoenix'' in an alternate timeline).&lt;ref name=&quot;The Last Man&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Last Man|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Except for the ''Korolev'' and the ''Sun Tzu'', which are operated by the Russians and Chinese respectively, all Earth combat spacecraft are operated by the [[United States Air Force]]. The [[United States]] [[Senate Appropriations Committee]] considers the construction of ''Daedalus''-class ships to be its top priority in terms of planetary defense.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Ties That Bind|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of Earth characters in Stargate SG-1]]
* [[List of Earth characters in Stargate Atlantis]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Stargate}}

[[Category:Fictional military organizations]]
[[Category:United States Marine Corps in popular culture]]

[[it:Programma Stargate]]
[[tr:Yıldız Geçidi Programı]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
