<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="622063" ns="0" title="Keith Locke"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox Politician
|honorific-prefix = 
|name             = Keith Locke
| honorific-suffix = &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;MP&lt;small&gt;
|image            = KeithLocke2008b.jpg
|imagesize        = 225px
|caption         = Keith Locke campaigning during the [[New Zealand general election, 2008]]
|constituency_MP = [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand|Green Party]] List
|term_start      = 1999
|parliament      = New Zealand
|predecessor     = 
|successor       =
|majority        =
|birth_date       = {{birth year and age|1944}}
|birth_place      = [[Christchurch]], [[New Zealand]]
|spouse           = 
|occupation       = [[Politician]]
|religion         = 
|party           = [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand|Green Party]]
|signature       =
|}}
'''Keith James Locke'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.nz/en-NZ/PB/Debates/Debates/5/c/4/49HansD_20081208_00000010-Members-Sworn.htm|title=New Zealand Hansard - Members Sworn Volume:651;Page:2|publisher=[[Parliament of New Zealand]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; (born 1944) is a current New Zealand [[Member of Parliament|MP]] representing the [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand|Green Party]] who was first elected to parliament in [[New Zealand general election, 1999|1999]].

{{As of|2011}} he is the Green Party spokesperson on Foreign Affairs, Defence, Ethnic Affairs, Pacific Affairs, Human Rights, Immigration, Police and Auckland Transport. He has announced his intention to retire from politics at the 2011 election.

[[Vernon Small]], deputy political editor of the [[New Zealand Herald]], dubbed him ''Backbencher of the Year'' in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_3048199&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/1/story.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=3048199 |title=''Politics review:'' Oh, what a year it's been |date=21 December 2002 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family and background==
Locke was born and grew up in [[Christchurch]], to Jack and [[Elsie Locke]], prominent life-long political activists for a wide variety of causes. Their four children were brought up in this environment and followed their parents into a life of activism, (as well as Keith, his sister Maire Leadbeater is a well-known activist and former city councillor for [[Auckland City Council]]). Former Prime Minister [[Robert Muldoon]] is said to have described the Lockes as the most &quot;notorious Communist family in New Zealand&quot;. The Lockes lived in the Avon Loop area of the [[Christchurch Central City]] and were very active in the community notably organising [[Avon River, Canterbury|Avon River]] clean-ups and native tree planting and arguing against development of the area, and in favour of retaining the character of the area.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.converge.org.nz/abc/elsobit.htm Obituary Elsie Locke], Murray Horton&lt;/ref&gt;

He attended [[Christchurch Boys' High School]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Keith Locke MP|url=http://www.greens.org.nz/people/keithlocke|publisher=Green Party|accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has a BSc in Psychology from the [[University of Canterbury]] and then went to [[Canada]] for a Masters in Sociology at the [[University of Alberta]]. He studied towards but never completed a Ph.D in Sociology at the University of Toronto, before returning to New Zealand. Locke lectured in Sociology at Victoria University from 1970–72, but then decided to leave academia to work as a full-time editor of the fortnightly socialist paper, Socialist Action, from 1972 to 1976. From 1978 to 1984 he worked as an active socialist and unionist in a car factory, railway workshops and meatworks in the Wellington region. In 1985 he moved to Auckland, working in the Auckland City abattoirs, 1985-86. From 1986 to 1990 Locke worked full-time as the national coordinator of the Philippines Solidarity Network, based in Auckland. From 1990 to 1999 he was manager of One World Books, a non-profit bookshop in Auckland specialising in social, environmental and development issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greens.org.nz/people/locke_k.asp?auth=78 Green Party website bio]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political history==
Politically active all his life, he joined the [[Socialist Action League]] (SAL) in 1970. By 1972 he was both the National Secretary of the SAL and chairman of &quot;Socialists for Labour&quot;. By 1985 Locke had left the SAL but was still involved in various issue movements. These included Latin America, the Philippines and East Timor solidarity movements and the anti-nuclear movement.

In 1989 [[Jim Anderton]] broke away from the Labour Party to form the [[NewLabour Party (New Zealand)|NewLabour Party]] (NLP). Locke as well as several other former SAL members were given roles in the NLP's first National Council. Locke was their foreign affairs spokesperson and stood as the NLP candidate for Eden in the [[New Zealand general election, 1990|1990 election]].

In December 1991 the NLP merged with the [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand|Greens]], [[Mana Motuhake]] and the [[New Zealand Democratic Party|Democrats]] to form the [[Alliance (New Zealand political party)|Alliance Party]]. Locke continued as foreign affairs spokesperson for the Alliance and stood in Eden in the [[New Zealand general election, 1993|1993 election]] and Owairaka in the [[New Zealand general election, 1996|1996 election]].

However, by 1997 the Greens had decided to leave the Alliance. Soon after Locke left the Alliance and joined the Greens where he was made [[foreign affairs]] spokesperson.

===Member of Parliament===
{{NZ parlbox header}}
{{NZ parlbox|term=46th|start=1999|end=2002|electorate=List|list=7|party=Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand}}
{{NZ parlbox|term=47th|start=2002|end=2005|electorate=List|list=7|party=Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand}}
{{NZ parlbox|term=48th|start=2005|end=2008|electorate=List|list=5|party=Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand}}
{{NZ parlbox|term=49th|start=2008|end=2011|electorate=List|list=6|party=Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand}}
{{NZ parlbox footer}}
In the [[New Zealand general election, 1999|1999 election]] he was elected to Parliament at number 7 on the Green [[Party-list proportional representation|Party list]]. He was returned to Parliament in the [[New Zealand general election, 2002|2002 election]] again at number 7 on the Green Party list and in the [[New Zealand general election, 2005|2005 election]] at number 5, and in the 2008 election at number 6. In all four elections he stood in the Epsom electorate.

In 2000, Locke had two member's bills drawn from the ballot.  The first, the Intelligence and Security Committee Act Repeal Bill 2000, attempted to reform oversight of the [[New Zealand Security Intelligence Service]] and [[Government Communications Security Bureau]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.greens.org.nz/speeches/intelligence-and-security-committee-act-repeal-bill |title=Intelligence and Security Committee Act Repeal Bill |publisher=Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand |date=10 May 2000 |accessdate=2009-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was defeated at its first reading.  The second, the International Treaties Bill, attempted to give greater parliamentary oversight of treaty-making.  It was sent to select committee,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.parliament.nz/NR/rdonlyres/F3F6427D-73C4-45DD-BFA1-A647D3CC4640/47806/DBSCH_SCR_2271_2619.pdf |title=Report of the Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Committee on the International Treaties Bill |publisher=New Zealand Parliament |year=2002 |accessdate=2009-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; but ultimately defeated at its second reading in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;''New Zealand Parliamentary Debates'' '''606''' 3589.&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2011 Locke announced that he would retire at that years' election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/PA1101/S00088/locke-to-retire-at-election.htm |title=Locke to retire at election |publisher=Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand |date=26 January 2011 |accessdate=2011-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political viewpoints===
As a Member of Parliament, Locke has established a profile of being an &quot;unofficial civil liberties watchdog&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_3048199&quot;/&gt; Recently, Locke has been involved in campaigns against the [[New Zealand Police]] being armed with [[Taser gun]]s, and repeal of the law of [[sedition]].

{{wikisource|Head of state (Referenda) Bill}}
Locke is a supporter of [[Republicanism in New Zealand|New Zealand becoming a republic]]. In his maiden speech, Locke stated &quot;We should also break free of the British Crown and become a republic. The question is not whether the monarchy has a lot of power over us. In practice it doesn't. The problem is that bowing before the British Queen reflects a colonial mentality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greens.org.nz/docs/speeches/000215kl-maiden.htm Keith Locke's Maiden Speech, 1999]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, Locke put forward the Head of State (Referenda) Bill, which if passed would bring about a referendum on the question of whether New Zealand should become a republic.&lt;ref name=&quot;nzh_republic_bill&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/1/story.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=940393|title=Republic Bill near|accessdate=2007-09-19|publisher=[[New Zealand Herald]]|author=[[NZPA]]|date=21 February 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bill was drawn from the Ballot of members' Bills on 14 October 2009&lt;ref name=&quot;order_paper&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.nz/NR/rdonlyres/7B3B73E3-47FC-456C-83D3-8BA19D6A5BAC/115528/00HOH20091015_orderpaper1.pdf|date=15 October 2009|title=Parliament of New Zealand Order Paper, Thursday 15 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; but defeated at its first reading in April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/national/politics/3609674/Queen-to-be-kept-as-NZ-head-of-state/ |title=Queen to be kept as NZ head of state |publisher=Stuff.co.nz |date=22 April 2010 |accessdate=2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
His political enemies have referred to him during [[question period]] as &quot;[[Pol Pot]]&quot; or &quot;the Honourable Member for [[Cambodia]]&quot; due to supportive articles he wrote while editor of the New Zealand ''Socialist Action'' newspaper about the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime under the headline; ''Cambodia liberated: victory for humanity''. Locke has claimed his initial support for the Khmer Rouge was because &quot;...many people thought the Khmer Rouge were an adjunct of the Vietnamese communist forces&quot; and that he thought they &quot;...would be better than the regimes they replaced&quot;. He also responded that he renounced his support after hearing of their atrocities, while the New Zealand Government of the time continued to express support for the regime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greens.org.nz/searchdocs/speech8860.html People in glass houses should not throw (Pol) Pots], Keith Locke, 22 June 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, while he opposed the [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|2001 war in Afghanistan]] to remove the [[Taliban]], he wrote an article (in ''Socialist Action'') entitled &quot;''Why workers should support [[Soviet war in Afghanistan|Soviet action in Afghanistan]]''&quot; in 1980. This led to accusations of hypocrisy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vdig.net/hansard/content.jsp?id=88622 Parliamentary Debate: Terrorist Attacks---Retaliation against Afghanistan], New Zealand Hansard, 18 September 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Locke explained that his previous support for the Soviet invasion was the position of the [[Socialist Action League]], that he was wrong to have supported it, that he was incorrect in believing it would protect human rights in Afghanistan, and that he now believes it encouraged Islamic extremist groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vdig.net/hansard/content.jsp?id=89249 Personal Explanation - Alleged Support of Soviet Invasion of Afghanistan], New Zealand Hansard, 10 October 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 2005 election he contested the [[Epsom, New Zealand|Epsom]] electorate in [[Auckland]] and at a public meeting he promised to run through the streets of Epsom [[naked]] if the electorate was won by [[ACT New Zealand]]'s leader [[Rodney Hide]]. Hide won the seat. &quot;I'll do it. I have to,&quot; Locke was reported as saying. &quot;I was so confident, but I have turned out to be wrong and I have got to do it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_10346229&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/story.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10346229 |title=Locke really regretting nude run promise |author=Claire Harvey |date=19 September 2005 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Locke's promise made headlines in media around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbr.co.nz/home/column_article.asp?id=12943 Editor's insight] Nevil Gibson&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4260016.stm BBC news]&lt;/ref&gt; On Sunday 25 September 2005 Locke walked [[Nudity (partial and analogous)|near-naked]] down Broadway (a main shopping street in [[Newmarket, Auckland]]) wearing shoes, socks, a [[G-string]], and [[body paint]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_ww.nzherald.co.nz/author/story.cfm?a_id=74&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/author/story.cfm?a_id=74&amp;ObjectID=10347301 |title=Locke learns the art of losing gracefully |author=Claire Trevett |date=26 September 2005 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The paint [[camouflaged]] Locke's skin by depicting a suit and tie from the neck down.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Keith Locke}}
* [http://www.greens.org.nz/people/keithlocke Keith Locke page on Green Party website]
* [http://www.parliament.nz/en-NZ/MPP/MPs/MPs/b/8/e/49MP30711-Locke-Keith.htm Keith Locke bio] (NZ Parliament website)

{{NZ Green Party caucus}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Locke, Keith
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1944
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Christchurch]], New Zealand
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Locke, Keith}}
[[Category:1944 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand MPs]]
[[Category:New Zealand republicans]]
[[Category:New Zealand left-wing activists]]
[[Category:People from Christchurch]]
[[Category:University of Canterbury alumni]]
[[Category:NewLabour Party (New Zealand) politicians]]
[[Category:University of Alberta alumni]]
[[Category:Alliance (New Zealand) politicians]]
[[Category:New Zealand list MPs]]

[[sco:Keith Locke]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
