<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="622884" ns="0" title="Northern Arizona University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
 |name              = Northern Arizona University
 |native_name       =
 |image_name        = NAU Seal.png
 |image_size        = 210px
 |caption           =
 |latin_name        =
 |motto             = The Difference that Matters
 |mottoeng          =
 |established       = 1899
 |closed            =
 |type              = [[public university|Public]]
 |affiliation       =
 |endowment         = [[united states dollar|$]]46.4 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web| title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge =
 |chairman          =
 |chancellor        =
 |president         = John D. Haeger
 |vice-president    = M. J. McMahon&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.nau.edu/president/NAU_orgchart_6_1_09.pdf Organization Chart - NAU]&lt;/ref&gt;
 |superintendent    =
 |provost           = Liz Grobsmith
 |faculty           = 813&lt;ref name=&quot;Key Statistics&quot;&gt;[http://home.nau.edu/about/who-we-are.asp#statistics Key Statistics]&lt;/ref&gt;
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 23,600&lt;ref name=&quot;Key Statistics&quot;/&gt;
 |undergrad         = 18,301&lt;ref name=&quot;Key Statistics&quot;/&gt;
 |postgrad          = 5,299&lt;ref name=&quot;Key Statistics&quot;/&gt;
 |doctoral          =
 |other             =
 |city              = [[Flagstaff, Arizona|Flagstaff]]
 |state             = [[Arizona]]
 |province          =
 |country           = [[United States]]
 |coor              = {{Coord|35.18782|-111.6528|type:edu_region:US-AZ|display=title}}
 |campus            = [[Small town]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|740|acre|m2}}
 |former_names      = Northern Arizona Normal School&lt;br/&gt;Northern Arizona State Teacher's College&lt;br/&gt;Arizona State Teacher's College of Flagstaff&lt;br/&gt;Arizona State College of Flagstaff
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            = 12 varsity teams &lt;ref name=&quot;Northern Arizona Athletics&quot;&gt;[http://www.nauathletics.com/landing/index]&lt;/ref&gt;
 |colors            = [[Blue|Navy]] &amp; [[Green|Sea-foam Green]] {{colorbox|#003366}}{{colorbox|#557565}} Athletics have [[Blue|Navy]] &amp; [[Gold]]
 |colours           =
 |nickname          = [[Northern Arizona Lumberjacks|Lumberjacks]]
 |mascot            = Louie the Lumberjack
 |athletics         = [[NCAA Division I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Big Sky Conference]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Western Athletic Conference]]
 |affiliations      =
 |website           = http://www.nau.edu
 |logo              = [[File:Northern Arizona University Logo.svg|100px]]
 |footnotes         =
}}

'''Northern Arizona University''' ('''NAU''') is a public university located in [[Flagstaff, Arizona]], [[United States]]. It is accredited by the [[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]], and has 39 satellite campuses in the state of Arizona. The university offers both undergraduate and graduate degrees.

As of fall 2010, 25,204 students were enrolled, 17,529 at the Flagstaff campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enrollment&quot;&gt;[http://www4.nau.edu/pair/EnrollmentDegree/EnrollmentHighlights/Enrollment_Highlights.asp ''Enrollment Highlights''] Northern Arizona University Planning, Budget and Institutional Research Office. Retrieved 2010-08-13&lt;/ref&gt; The average cost of tuition for an full-time, Arizona resident undergraduate student for two semesters is $6,964.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.nau.edu/finaid/Active_Matrix_Pages/Apply/Budgets/10-11/UGRD_10-11_Incoming.pdf Northern Arizona University Academic Year Budgets 2010-2011]. Retrieved 2010-08-13&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education]] clasifies NAU as a Research University with High research activity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=105330&amp;start_page=institution.php&amp;clq={%22first_letter%22:%22N%22} The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]&lt;/ref&gt; NAU is governed by the [[Arizona Board of Regents]].

==History==
[[Image:NAU Old Main.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Old Main, site of Northern Arizona Normal School; currently houses an art gallery, museum, and offices]]
Old Main, site of Northern Arizona Normal School; currently houses an art gallery, museum, and offices
Initially named the Northern Arizona Normal School, the institution was formed on September 11, 1899. The first graduating class, in 1901, consisted of four women who received credentials to teach in the Arizona Territory. In 1925, the Arizona State Legislature allowed the school, which was now called the Northern Arizona State Teacher's College, to grant the Bachelor of Education degree. The school became Northern Arizona State Teacher's College.{{cn|date=December 2011}}

Enrollment dropped sharply, however, as World War II dawned. ASTC became a Navy [[V-12 Navy College Training Program |V-12 program]] training site.&lt;ref name=&quot;nauv-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web| author =| date =2011| url = http://www.cba.nau.edu/newbuilding/deans.html | title = The Former Deans of FCB | publisher =[[Flagstaff, Arizona]]: Northern Arizona University | accessdate = September 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campuses==
===Flagstaff campus===
Perched at {{convert|6950|ft|m}} [[AMSL|above sea level]], the main campus is surrounded by the largest contiguous ponderosa pine forest on the North American continent&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpluhna.nau.edu/Biota/ponderosa_forest.htm Biotic Communities of the Colorado Plateau]&lt;/ref&gt; and enjoys a four-season climate. Snow is common in winter, with accumulations most prevalent in December and January. Winter skiing is accessible at [[Arizona Snowbowl]], an alpine ski resort located on the [[San Francisco Peaks]], {{convert|7|mi|km}} northwest of Flagstaff.

===Extended Campuses===
Northern Arizona University maintains campuses throughout Arizona offering alternatives to the traditional learning experience including evening, weekend and accelerated classes. The university offers more than 123 degree, certificate, and endorsement programs in person and/or on the web. Extended Campus students are learning in-person in classrooms across the state at 39 different locations throughout Arizona. One-third of Northern Arizona University students are served through the Extended Campuses program.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nau.edu/extendedcampuses]&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

==Academics==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| USNWR_NU             = NR&lt;!-- Not ranked: Tier 2 --&gt;
| Wamo_NU              = 96
| Forbes               = 460
}}

NAU is ranked 78th on ''[[Forbes Magazine]]'''s &quot;America's Best Public Colleges&quot; list&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/2009/08/06/best-public-colleges-opinions-colleges-09-top.html| title=America's Best Public Colleges |publisher=''[[Forbes Magazine]]'' |accessdate=2009-09-13 |date=August 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is ranked 460th overall on Forbes &quot;America's Best Colleges 2010&quot; list.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2010/94/best-colleges-10_Northern-Arizona-University_94283.html| title=America's Best Colleges 2010 |publisher=''[[Forbes Magazine]]'' |accessdate=2010-12-18|date=August 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has 93 academic programs; and consists of six colleges.

In fall 2010, the top undergraduate degrees by enrollment were elementary education, biology, hotel and restaurant management, nursing, and criminology and criminal justice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.nau.edu/pair/quickfact.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

===College of Arts and Letters===

The College of Arts and Letters (CAL) houses the Asian Studies Program, Cinema Studies, Comparative Cultural Studies (formerly Humanities, Arts, and Religion), English, History, Latin American Studies, Modern Languages, Museum Studies, Philosophy, School of Art, School of Music, and Theatre.  The college also oversees the NAU Art Museum, Martin-Springer Institute (promoting lessons of the Holocaust), Northern Arizona Writing Project, Ardrey Memorial Auditorium, and Ashurst Hall. The College of Arts and Letters Film Series has been providing quality classic films to the NAU and Flagstaff community for more than 9 years, and the NAU International Film Series has recently been established. Department faculty and students share their scholarly work and artistic achievement through more than 300 performances, lectures, films, and exhibitions a year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nau.edu/cal]&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

===College of Education===
The College of Education prepares educators, counselors, school psychologists, and school administrators. Fields of study include teaching and learning (e.g., early childhood, elementary, and secondary), educational leadership, educational psychology, and educational specialties (e.g., bilingual and multicultural education, career and technical education, educational technology, and special education).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nau.edu/coe]&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

===College of Engineering, Forestry, and Natural Sciences===
[[Image:StudentsByEngineeringBuilding_2000x1333.jpg|thumb|right|Engineering Building]]  
The College of Engineering, Forestry, and Natural Sciences has 11 departments and a Quaternary Program; 13 centers and two institutes. It continues to expand its degree programs. Programs include Biological Sciences, Chemistry and Biochemistry, Civil and Environmental Engineering, Computer Science, Construction Management, Electrical Engineering, Environmental Sciences and Education, Geology, Mathematics and Statistics, Mechanical Engineering, Physics and Astronomy, Quaternary Studies, Master of Engineering, and Master of Science in Engineering. NAUTeach is the secondary school teacher preparation program for mathematics and the sciences.

===College of Health and Human Services===
NAU's College of Health and Human Services consists of the School of Nursing, and three departments [http://www.nau.edu/hhs]

===College of Social and Behavioral Sciences===
The College of Social and Behavioral Sciences undergraduate programs include anthropology, applied indigenous studies, criminology and criminal justice, ethnic studies, geography, planning and recreation, political science, psychology, communication, sociology/social work, and women's and gender studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nau.edu/sbs]&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

===The W.A. Franke College of Business===
[[Image:WAFrankeCollegeOfBusiness_2000x1326.jpg|thumb|right|W.A. Franke College of Business]]
The W.A. Franke College of Business' primary focus is undergraduate education, but it also offers a master’s level education and research opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.franke.nau.edu/DegreePrograms/&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

Businessman Bill Franke's commitment of $25 million resulted in the renaming of the college in his honor. The W.A. Franke College of Business was fully re-accredited in fall 2008 by the national accrediting body AACSB International - The Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business. The NAU program is one of about 400 accredited programs among the more than 1,000 throughout the nation. In 2006, the college moved into a new {{convert|111000|sqft|m2|adj=on}}, LEED-certified building.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.franke.nau.edu/leed/&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

==Residence halls==
Northern Arizona University has 21 dorms on its Flagstaff campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nau.edu/reslife/residencehalls.asp Northern Arizona University- Residence Life]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Freshman residence halls===
&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nau.edu/reslife/freshmanconnections.asp List of Freshman Connections Halls]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Sechrist Hall.jpg|thumb|right|Sechrist Hall]]
*Allen Hall (formerly an upperclassmen hall)
*Cowden Learning Community
*McConnell Hall
*Reilly Hall
*Wilson Hall
*Sechrist Hall (an eight-story residence hall, making it the tallest building in Flagstaff)&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nau.edu/reslife/sechrist.asp NAU Residence Life- Communities at a Glance Sechrist Hall]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Tinsley Hall (beginning fall 2011, Tinsley will be a Freshman connections hall) &lt;ref&gt;[http://northernarizonanews.com/blog/2011/02/21/mountain-view-rumors-false-tinsley-to-become-freshman-hall/ Mountain View rumors false, Tinsley to become freshman hall]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Family housing====
These apartment-styled halls are for married couples and students with children.&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nau.edu/reslife/fam2.asp NAU-Family Housing]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Campus Heights has 63 apartments.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://home.nau.edu/reslife/campusheights.asp Campus Heights].&quot; Northern Arizona University. Retrieved on October 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*South Family Apartments has 145 apartments.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://home.nau.edu/reslife/southfamily.asp South Family].&quot; Northern Arizona University. Retrieved on October 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Residents of both family units are within the [[Flagstaff Unified School District]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://nau.edu/uploadedFiles/Global/parking_map.pdf Parking Map].&quot; Northern Arizona University. Retrieved on October 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Residents are zoned to Kinsey Elementary School, Mount Elden Middle School, and [[Flagstaff High School]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.fusd1.org/fusd1/lib/fusd1/_shared/Flagstaff%20USD%202010%20Map.pdf?1927Nav=|207|&amp;NodeID=208 2010/11 Middle (6-8) and High (9-12) School Attendance Areas with Elementary School (K-5) Attendance Area Outlines (Zoomed-In View of the City of Flagstaff].&quot; [[Flagstaff Unified School District]]. Retrieved on October 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
[[Image:NorthernArizonaLumberjacks.png|right|thumb|Northern Arizona Lumberjacks logo]]
Student athletes go on to compete at national, international, and professional levels in football, basketball, baseball, ice hockey, track and field, tennis, swimming and diving. The university participates in 15 intercollegiate sports programs. NAU teams compete at the [[Walkup Skydome]], which is a multipurpose building which provides facilities for football, basketball, indoor track and field, soccer, weight lifting, lacrosse, student recreation, major concert events, commencements, intramurrals, and a variety of other university and community activities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nau.edu/skydome/Dome_Info.html J. Lawrence Walkup Skydome]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Lumberjack]]s compete at the [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]] level in all sports. In football, the Lumberjacks compete at the [[Football Championship Subdivision]] (formerly known as Division I-AA) level. NAU competes in the Big Sky Conference in all sports except swimming and diving, which is part of the [[Western Athletic Conference]].

==On Campus Activities/Student Media==
NAU has more than 180 recognized professional, academic, service and social organizations; an intramural sports program; ''The Lumberjack'' student newspaper; and active residence hall organization.

===''The Lumberjack''===
The university's award-winning, weekly newspaper is an independent, student-run publication called ''The Lumberjack''.  In May 2007, the newspaper won a [[Society of Professional Journalists]] national award in the editorial writing category for articles printed during 2006.&lt;ref name=SPJ&gt;[http://www.spj.org/moe05r11.asp Society of Professional Journalists Mark of Excellence Awards], [[Society of Professional Journalists]], 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=UnivPR&gt;[http://www4.nau.edu/insidenau/bumps/3_30_05/lumberjack.htm NAU's 'Lumberjack' wins 4 awards], Northern Arizona University, March 30, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

=== KJACK, NAZ Today, and UTV62===
[[KJACK]] is available in [[Flagstaff, Arizona|Flagstaff]] on 1680 AM or online. [[KJACK]] reports to the College Music Journal and specializes in new music. NAU's televised news program, ''NAZ Today'' airs Monday through Thursday in Flagstaff on NPG cable channels 4, 59 and UTV 62 on campus at 6pm MST, and on Dish Network's UniversityHouse Channel (9411) 9pm MST. Since the shutdown of Channel 2 news in August 2008, [http://www.naztoday.com ''NAZ Today''] is now the only TV news source for all of Northern Arizona. UTV 62 is NAU's student run and produced television station. [http://utv62.com ''UTV 62''] runs 24 hours a day 7 days a week on channel 62 on campus. 

===The Dark City Times===

In Summer 2010, a group of student journalists previously employed by The Lumberjack created an independent, student-run website called [http://www.darkcitytimes.com ''The Dark City Times''], in response to NAU faculty taking more control in the affairs of the student media outlets. The Dark City Times currently publishes news, life and entertainment stories, along with a variety of blogs covering politics, pop culture and student life. There are efforts being taken to create a print magazine version of the site. The site receives content from both regular contributors or students who want to work as freelance writers, photographers or videographers.

===Choirs===
The Northern Arizona University Choral Union consists of eight ensembles contained within the School of Music: Men's Chorale, Women's Chorale, University Singers, two Vocal Jazz Ensembles: Northern Voices and High Altitude, Vocal Chamber Ensemble, the Harold M. Harter Memorial Handbell Choir, and the Shrine of the Ages Choir, the premier choral ensemble that tours internationally.

===Recreation services===
The NAU Recreation Center provides facilities for all students, including a fully equipped weight room, a two-court basketball/volleyball gymnasium, five glass-back racquetball courts, an aerobic/dance studio, a six-station climbing wall, locker rooms with dry saunas, and conference rooms for meetings, classes, or activities.

In Fall 2011, the remodel of the NAU Recreation Center will be complete, creating the NAU Health and Learning Center in its place. Features include an Indoor jogging track, 38 foot climbing wall, larger weight room, multipurpose gym, and a cardio theatre. The Health and Learning Center will also include all of the on-campus medical services that were previously housed in the Fronske Health Center, a pharmacy, and the offices for Disability Resources on campus. &lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nau.edu/hlc/features.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intramural sports===
Intramural sports are organized for teams and individuals and include flag football, soccer, volleyball, softball, racquetball, and backgammon. Sports clubs include sports such as rugby, soccer, hockey, lacrosse, water polo, and judo.

===Movies and other events===
Unions and Student Activities offers many services and events for the campus community, such as movies and the popular Friday night AfterHours program produced by SUN Entertainment. SUN also presents several concerts and special events each year and coordinates Welcome Week concerts.  The College of Arts and Letters Film Series presents classic films every Tuesday night during the school year, and the College of Arts and Letters presents more than 300 music and theatrical performances, lectures, films and art exhibitions yearly.

==Alumni==
{{Main|Northern Arizona University alumni}}
The NAU Alumni Association represents more than 115,000&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naualumni.com/site/pp.asp?c=evKYLiMSIqG&amp;b=621279#FAQ_statistics Frequently Asked Questions- NAU Alumni Association, September 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; alumni from the U.S.

==Other information==
The [[Arizona Cardinals]] of the [[National Football League|NFL]] conduct their summer training camp at Northern Arizona University's Flagstaff campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://cardinals.nau.edu/about/&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Arizona|Schools}}
* [[Walkup Skydome]]
* [[Wikiversity:Northern Arizona University]]
* [[List of forestry universities and colleges]]
* [http://www.darkcitytimes.com Dark City Times -- Student Based Newspaper]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}

===General===
*[http://home.nau.edu Official site]
*[http://home.nau.edu/asnau/ Student Government]
*[http://www.distance.nau.edu/ Distance Learning]
*[http://www.nauathletics.com/ Official athletics site]
*[http://www.onlinepressroom.net/nau/ University news]
*[http://www.grandcanyonsemester.nau.edu The Grand Canyon Semester: The Oldest Classroom on Earth]
*[http://www.naualumni.com NAU Alumni Association]
*[http://www.naualumni.com/site/pp.asp?c=evKYLiMSIqG&amp;b=709375 History of NAU courtesy of Alumni Association]
*[http://home.nau.edu/recreation/wac/ Wall Aquatic Center]
*[http://www4.nau.edu/marketing/faculty/default.asp List of faculty]
{{col-2}}

===Colleges===
*[http://www.nau.edu/cal College of Arts and Letters]
*[http://www.nau.edu/coe College of Education]
*[http://www.nau.edu/cens College of Engineering, Forestry, and Natural Sciences]
*[http://www.nau.edu/hhs College of Health and Human Services]
*[http://home.nau.edu/sbs College of Social and Behavioral Sciences]
*[http://www.nau.edu/cba The W.A. Franke College of Business]
*[http://www.nau.edu/hrm School of Hotel and Restaurant Management]
*[http://www.nau.edu/sbs/communication/ School of Communication]
{{col-end}}

===Student life===
*[http://www4.nau.edu/stulife/ Student life]
*[http://www.jackcentral.com ''The Lumberjack'' newspaper]
*[http://www.kjack.org KJACK radio online]
*[http://www.naztoday.com ''NAZ Today'']
*[http://www.utv62.com ''UTV 62'' Student run television]
*[http://nau.edu/imsports Intramural sports]
*[http://www.nau.edu/sun SUN Entertainment]

{{Big Sky Conference}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Arizona}}

[[Category:Northern Arizona University| ]]
[[Category:Public universities]]
[[Category:Public universities and colleges in Arizona]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1899]]
[[Category:Arizona Cardinals]]
[[Category:National Football League summer camp sites]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Education in Coconino County, Arizona]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Coconino County, Arizona]]

[[de:Northern Arizona University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه آریزونای شمالی]]
[[no:Northern Arizona University]]
[[pl:Uniwersytet Północnej Arizony]]
[[ro:Northern Arizona University]]
[[simple:Northern Arizona University]]
[[sv:Northern Arizona University]]
[[zh:北亞利桑那大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
