<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6237476" ns="0" title="Edward M. Cotter (fireboat)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:Edward M.Cotter 009.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption= The ''Edward M. Cotter'' berthed.
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=United States
|Ship flag=[[Image:Flag of the United States.svg|100x35px|Civil Ensign of the United States]]
|Ship name=''William S. Grattan'' (Engine 20)
|Ship operator=[[Buffalo Fire Department]]
|Ship ordered=
|Ship awarded=
|Ship original cost=$91,000
|Ship builder=Cresent Shipbuilding of Elizabeth City, New Jersey
|Ship yard number=
|Ship laid down= March 24, 1900
|Ship launched=
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened= September 5, 1900 by Virginia Pearson
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=
|Ship recommissioned=November 30, 1930
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=July 28, 1928 - November 13, 1930 (Rebuilt due to severe fire damage) &lt;br&gt; November 1952 - November 1953 (Refit)
|Ship renamed=''Firefighter'' (1953) &lt;br&gt;''Edward M. Cotter'' (1954)
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=July 28, 1928 - November 13, 1930
Buffalo Dry Dock Company of Buffalo, New York
November 1952 - November 1953 &lt;br&gt; The Sturgeon Bay Shipbuilding &amp; Dry Dock Company of Sturgeon Bay, Wisconsin
|Ship struck=
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honours=
|Ship honors=
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship type=[[Fireboat]]
|Ship tonnage=
* 274 Gross tons (1900)
*178 Gross tons (1953)
|Ship displacement=
|Ship tons burthen=
|Ship length={{convert|118|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|24|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship height=
|Ship draft={{convert|10|ft|10|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship ice class= {{convert|1.5|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} thick belt line of Swedish steel around the icebreaking part of the hull
|Ship sail plan=
|Ship power=
* Two Babcock &amp; Wilcox coal-fired boilers and steam engines &lt;br&gt; 900 horsepower (1900)
* Oil-fired boilers and steam engines (1930)
* Four Caterpillar D-397 diesel V-type 12 cylinder engines (1953)
|Ship propulsion=
* Single [[propeller|screw]] (1900)
* Twin screws (1953)
|Ship speed=
* {{convert|13|kn|km/h|lk=in}} (1900)
* {{convert|11.5|kn|km/h}} (1953)
|Ship range=
|Ship endurance=
|Ship boats=
|Ship capacity=Water Pumping Capacity
* Three double action steam pumps &lt;br&gt; {{convert|9000|usgal|L impgal|sigfig=4}} per minute (1900)
* Four DeLaval Centrifugal Pumps &lt;br&gt; {{convert|15000|usgal|L impgal|sigfig=5}} per minute @ {{convert|160|psi|bar kPa|abbr=on|lk=on}} (1953)
|Ship complement=
|Ship crew=
|Ship time to activate=
|Ship notes=Number of [[fire monitor]]s
* 3 (1900)
* 4 (1930)
* 5 (1953)
}}
|}
'''''Edward M. Cotter''''' is a [[fireboat]] in use by the [[Buffalo Fire Department]] at [[Buffalo, New York]], United States. The original name of the ship was the  '''''William S. Grattan''''', and she was built in 1900 by the [[Crescent Shipyard]] of [[Elizabeth City, New Jersey|Elizabeth Port, New Jersey]].  Due to age she was rebuilt in 1953 and was renamed '''''Firefighter''''' upon her return. The following year she was renamed the ''Edward M. Cotter''.&lt;ref name =&quot;rename&quot;/&gt; Her namesake, Edward Cotter, was a Buffalo firefighter and leader of the local firefighters union who had recently died.

The ''Edward M. Cotter'' is considered to be the oldest active fireboat in the world and was designated a National Historic Landmark in 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Assembly Minority Research Services
  | work =
  | publisher = New York State Assembly
  | date = 2004
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=RCOcAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=%22oldest+active+fireboat%22&amp;q=%22oldest+active+fireboat%22
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =8 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=2190&amp;ResourceType=Structure
|title=Edward M. Cotter|date=2007-09-11|work=National Historic Landmark summary listing|publisher=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|title={{PDFlink|[http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NHLS/Text/96000968.pdf National Historic Landmark Nomination: Edward M. Cotter]|163&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 166932 bytes --&gt;}}|author=James P. Delgado|date=January 27, 1989 |publisher=National Park Service|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}} and {{PDFlink|[http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NHLS/Photos/96000968.pdf Accompanying 11 photos, exterior and interior, from 1920-1989.]|585&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 599390 bytes --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with her firefighting duties, during the winter the ''Edward M. Cotter'' is used as an [[icebreaker]] on Buffalo's rivers. The ''Cotter'' mounts five [[fire monitor]]s that are capable of pumping {{convert|15000|USgal/min|m3/s impgal/min}}.&lt;ref name=MissBuffaloCruise2003&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.penndixie.org/events/03cruise/2/source/12.html
| title=Fireboat Edward M. Cotter
| publisher=Penn Dixie's Miss Buffalo Nature Cruise and Buffalo Lighthouse Tour
| date=June 8, 2003
| accessdate=June 6, 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DingusDay&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.dyngusdaybuffalo.com/worldslargestsquirtgun.html
| title=The World's largest Dyngus Day squirt gun
| date=April 4, 2007
| accessdate=June 6, 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt; She can often be seen sailing out of her berth and south-west to Lake Erie, returning north through the breakwall and firing her fire monitors.

==Construction==
The ship that was to become the ''Edward M. Cotter'' was built in 1900 by the Crescent Shipyard of Elizabeth Port, New Jersey. She was originally named the ''William S. Grattan'' after the first paid fire commissioner for the city of Buffalo.&lt;ref name=pbase20050208&gt;
{{cite web | url=http://www.pbase.com/kjosker/cotter | title=Edward M. Cotter | publisher=pbase | date=February 8, 2005 | accessdate=June 6, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Construction was started on March 24, 1900 and she was [[Ship naming and launching|christened]] on September 5, 1900 by Virginia Pearson, the young daughter of one of the city's fire commissioners. The final construction cost for the ship was $91,000.

The completed ship was {{convert|118|ft|m|abbr=on}} in length, a [[Beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|24|ft|m|abbr=on}} and a [[Draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|10|ft|10|in|m|abbr=on}}. A {{convert|1.5|in|mm|1|abbr=on}} thick belt line of Swedish steel was included around the hull for icebreaking duties. The ''Grattan'' was powered by two [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] coal-fired boilers with steam engines rated at {{convert|900|hp|kW}}. A single [[propeller]] provided propulsion. The rated speed of the ship was {{convert|13|kn|0|km/h|lk=in}}.

The ship was also equipped with three double action steam pumps that supplied water at 9,000 gallons per minute to the three fire monitors used for firefighting. Two of the fire monitors were mounted on the forward section of the ship and one was on the [[stern]] section.

==History==

At the beginning of the twentieth century, Buffalo's waterfront was an extremely busy center of commerce. [[Grain elevators]], warehouses and shipping traffic had overtaxed the two existing fireboats: the ''John T. Hutchinson'' (Engine 23) and the ''George R. Potter'' (Engine 29). Also, the city of Buffalo had shoreline hookups to allow the fireboats to serve as floating pumping stations supplying high pressure water to a [[fire hydrant]] system that covered the downtown area.&lt;ref name=hydrant&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.emcotter.com/1898.htm
| title=1898
| publisher=
| date=2008-06-08
| author=Buffalo Fire Department's Official Edward M. Coter Website
| accessdate=June 8, 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The decision was made by city officials to order a third boat that would also have icebreaking capability along with her normal firefighting duties.

[[Image:Edward M. Cotter 003.jpg|thumb|left]]
Upon completion she traveled up the Atlantic coast, down the [[St. Lawrence River]], across [[Lake Ontario]], through the [[Welland Canal]] and finally across [[Lake Erie]] in an uneventful trip that took 14 days. She was met {{convert|3|mi|km|1}} out of the harbor by her sister fireboats and escorted in.&lt;ref name=enchanted&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4442/is_200602/ai_n17171995/pg_1
| title=BUFFALO'S ENCHANTED FIREBOAT: Edward M. Cotter
| publisher=Sea Classics
| date=February 2006
| author= Guadagna, Sam
| accessdate=June 8, 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1928 fire===
On July 28, 1928 the ''Grattan'' responded to the oil barge ''James F. Cahill'', loaded with 5,000 barrels of crude oil, that was aflame.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maritime History of the Great Lakes&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://images.maritimehistoryofthegreatlakes.ca/62765/data
| title=CAHILL, JAMES F. , (Barge), 1928 , Official No. U165740
| publisher=The Great Lakes Shipwrecks database
| date=June 8, 2008
| author= William R. McNeil and Jack Messmer
| accessdate=June 8, 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt; After burning 17 hours, the barge's mooring lines gave way and the barge began to drift. The ''Grattan''{{'}}s crew attempted to attach tow lines to the drifting barge but it struck a dock at an oil company where the empty [[oil tanker]] ''B.B. McColl'' was moored.&lt;ref name=Scanner&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.maritimehistoryofthegreatlakes.ca/GreatLakes/Documents/Scanner/04/01/default.asp?ID=c008
| title=The McColl Frontenac Oil Company Limited: A Fleet List
| publisher=Toronto Marine Historical Society
| date=Scanner, v. 4, n. 1 (October 1971)
| author=
| accessdate=June 8, 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fumes on the ''McColl'' ignited causing an explosion and fire that engulfed the  ''Grattan''. Captain Thomas Hylant along with his crew abandoned ship and swam through the flames to shore. Chief Engineer Thomas Lynch of the ''Grattan'' lost his life and seven other crew members were injured. The unattended boilers on the ''Grattan'' soon ran dry and exploded, leaving the ship burned out and heavily damaged.

The ''Grattan'' sat boarded up for eighteen months while city and fire department officials decided whether to replace her at a cost of $225,000 dollars or rebuild her for $99,000 dollars, which was $8,000 dollars more than her original cost. The decision was made to rebuild and in 1930 she was rebuilt at the Buffalo Dry Dock Company of Buffalo, New York. During this refit some improvements were made to the ''Grattan''. One improvement was that her [[boilers]] were converted from burning coal to burning oil.&lt;ref name=MissBuffaloCruise2003/&gt; The engines were rebuilt and her firefighting system was updated and could now handle [[fire retardant|foam]]. Also, the [[pilot house]] was raised to the upper boat deck level and a fixed turret tower with a fire monitor was constructed on the stern of the ship. A fourth fire monitor was added to the top of the pilot house of the ship as well. As part of her acceptance ceremony she was recommissioned and participated in a race against the harbor tug ''Kentucky'', which was considered to be one of the fastest tugs on the [[Great Lakes|lakes]].
{{Infobox NRHP | name =''Edward M. Cotter'' (fireboat)
 | nrhp_type = nhl
 | image =
 | caption =
 | location= [[Buffalo, New York]]
 | locmapin = New York
 | area =
 | built =1900
| architect= Crescent Shipbuilding Co.
| architecture=
| designated_nrhp_type = June 28, 1996&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;/&gt;
 | added = June 28, 1996&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|2007a}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | governing_body = Local
 | refnum=96000968
}}

===1953 refit===
In the early 1950s, it was noticed that the ''Grattan'' was showing signs of age. Her boilers were only able to operate at 40 percent capacity and an engine room steam leak in 1951 injured part of her crew. During November 1952, the ''Grattan'' was sent to the Sturgeon Bay Shipbuilding &amp; Dry Dock Company of Sturgeon Bay, Wisconsin for a refit.
During this refit her boilers and [[steam engines]] were replaced by diesel engines, the pumps for the firefighting system were replaced, the single propeller was replaced with twin propellers, the fixed firefighting platform was replaced with a [[hydraulic cylinder|hydraulically]] operated platform and the twin [[chimney|funnels]] were replaced with lower dummy funnels. Upon her return in 1954, she was renamed ''Firefighter''. In 1955 she was renamed again in honor of Edward M. Cotter, a respected Buffalo firefighter and the leader of the local firefighters union, who had recently died.&lt;ref name=rename&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://images.maritimehistoryofthegreatlakes.ca/25585/data?n=1
| title=Vessel Renamings: COTTER, EDWARD M.
| publisher=The Great Lakes Shipwrecks database
| date=2008-06-08
| author=William R. McNeil and Jack Messmer
| accessdate=June 8, 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the refit the ''Cotter'' now mounts five fire monitors that are capable of pumping 15,000 US gallons per minute (950 L/s).&lt;ref name=&quot;MissBuffaloCruise2003&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DingusDay&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Edward M. Cotter 002.jpg|thumb|left|The ''Cotter'' with its station house in the background]]

===International firefighting===
On October 7, 1960 the ''Cotter'' came to the aid of firefighting authorities in [[Port Colborne, Ontario|Port Colborne]], [[Ontario]], Canada.&lt;ref name=PortColborne&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.emcotter.com/1960.htm
| title=1960
| publisher=Buffalo Fire Department's Official Edward M. Coter Website
| date=2008-06-08
| author=Buffalo Fire Department
| accessdate=June 8, 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two days previously, on October 5, 1960, a set of grain elevators caught fire at the eight-story Maple Leaf Milling Company. The Port Colborne Fire Department did not have its own fireboat and they were unable to bring the fire under control. The Buffalo Fire Department was asked to send the ''Edward M. Cotter'' to lend assistance. Escorted by a [[United States Coast Guard]] cutter, because she had never needed navigational equipment of her own, the ''Edward M. Cotter'' proceeded across the international border.  The voyage to Port Colborne took two hours with an additional four hours needed to bring the fire under control. This mission is said to have been the first instance that a United States fire boat had crossed an international border to help authorities in another country.&lt;ref name= &quot;PortColborne&quot;/&gt;

===Notable rescues===
In 1978 the [[USS Little Rock (CG-4)|USS Little Rock]], a retired United States Naval guided missile cruiser on display at the [[Buffalo and Erie County Naval &amp; Military Park]], began taking on water and listing. The ''Cotter'' and several Buffalo Fire Department fire engines pumped water out of the ''Little Rock'' for five days keeping the ship afloat and level while repairs were made.&lt;ref name=enchanted/&gt; The ''Cotter'' also assisted the disabled United States Coast Guard cutter ''Ojibwa'' during the winter of 1983. The ''Ojibwa'', while on [[Lake Erie]], had lost its steering and was taking on water. The ''Cotter'' towed the ''Ojibwa'' to its base in Buffalo and helped keep it afloat while repairs were made.&lt;ref name=enchanted/&gt; Another rescue occurred on July 31, 1984 when the ''Cotter '' towed the Polish [[tall ship]] ''[[Zawisza Czarny (ship)|Zawisza Czarny]]'' off a sand bar during the ships visit to Buffalo.

==Heritage==
[[Image:Edward M. Cotter 001.jpg|thumb|right]]
As commerce declined on Buffalo's waterfront, the ''Cotter'' was transferred from the Buffalo Fire Department to the Public Works Department in 1992 for icebreaking duties. In 1996 the ''Edward M. Cotter'' was designated a [[National Historic Landmark]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv&quot; /&gt; and was transferred back to the Buffalo Fire Department in 1997.

The ''Edward M. Cotter'' is considered to be the oldest active fireboat in the world. Often the ''Cotter'' can be seen sailing out of berth and south-west to Lake Erie and returning north through the [[breakwall]] while firing her fire monitors.

A non-profit group named &quot;Friends of the ''Cotter''&quot;, founded in 2005, has been running fund-raising events to overhaul the ''Cotter''.&lt;ref name=DingusDay/&gt; Along with her normal duties the ''Cotter'' has been sent to various festivals and boat shows around the [[Great Lakes]].&lt;ref name=enchanted/&gt;

==See also==

* [[List of National Historic Landmarks in New York]]
* [[History of Buffalo, New York]]
* [[SS Canadiana]]
* [[USS Sable (IX-81)]]
* [[MV Aquarama]]

{{clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{Commons category-inline|Edward M. Cotter}}
* [http://www.emcotter.com History of the E.M. Cotter]
* [http://www.boatnerd.com/pictures/fleet/cotter.htm Edward Cotter]
* [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4442/is_200602/ai_n17171995/pg_1 Buffalo's Enchanted Fireboat]
* [http://www.emcotter.com/Contact_page.htm Friends of the Cotter Official Website]
{{Registered Historic Places}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Edward M. Cotter (Fireboat)}}
[[Category:Fireboats]]
[[Category:National Historic Landmarks in New York]]
[[Category:History of Buffalo, New York]]
[[Category:Ships on the National Register of Historic Places in New York]]
[[Category:1900 ships]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
