<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="623736" ns="0" title="Guo Moruo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
|name=Guo Moruo
|image=Guomoruo.JPG
|birth_name=Guo Kaizhen 郭開貞
|birth_date={{birth date|1892|11|16|df=y}}
|birth_place=[[File:China Qing Dynasty Flag 1889.svg|20px]] [[Leshan]], [[Sichuan]], [[Qing Empire]]
|death_date={{death date and age|1978|6|12|1892|11|16|df=y}}
|death_place={{flagicon|China}} [[Beijing]], [[People's Republic of China]]
|alma_mater=[[Chengdu Shishi High School]]
|spouse=Zhang Jinghua (1911-1978, m.1912)&lt;br&gt;[[Sato Tomiko]] (1893-1914)&lt;br&gt;Yu Liqun (1916-1979, m.1939)
|children=8 sons and 3 daughters
|awards=1948 Research Fellow of the [[Academia Sinica]]
}}
{{Chinese name|[[Guo]]}}
'''Guo Moruo''' ({{zh|c=郭沫若|p=Guō Mòruò|w=Kuo Mo-jo}}; November 16, 1892 &amp;ndash; June 12, 1978), [[Chinese style name|courtesy name]] Dingtang (鼎堂), was a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] author, poet, historian, [[archaeology|archaeologist]], and government official from [[Sichuan]], China.
==Biography==
===Family history===
Guo, originally named Guo Kaizhen, was born on November 10 or 16, in the small town of [[Shawan District|Shawan]]. Shawan is located on the [[Dadu River (China)|Dadu River]] some 40&amp;nbsp;km southwest from what was then called the city of Jiading (Chia-ting, 嘉定路), and now is the central urban area of the prefecture level city of [[Leshan]] in [[Sichuan Province]].

At the time of Guo's birth, Shawan was a town of some 180 families.&lt;ref name=roy&gt;David Tod Roy, &quot;Kuo Mo-jo: The Early Years&quot;. Harvard University Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts. 1971. No ISBN.&lt;/ref&gt;

Guo's father's ancestors were [[Hakka people|Hakkas]] from [[Ninghua County]] (''[[Counties of the People's Republic of China#History|xian]]'') in [[Tingzhou fu]], near the western border of [[Fujian]]. They moved to Sichuan in the second half of the 17th century, after Sichuan had lost much of its population to the rebels/bandits of [[Zhang Xianzhong]] (ca. 1605-1647). According to family legend, the only possessions that Guo's ancestors brought to Sichuan were things they could carry on their backs. Guo's great-grandfather, Guo Xianlin, was the first in the family to achieve a degree of prosperity. Guo Xianlin's sons established the Guo clan as the leaders of the local river shipping business, and thus important people in that entire region of Sichuan. It was only then that the Guo clan members became able to send their children to school.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

Guo's father, one of whose names may possibly have been Guo Mingxing (1854–1939), had to drop out of school at the age of 13 and then spent six monthe as an apprentice at a salt well. Thereafter he entered his father's business, a shrewd and smart man who achieved some local renown as a [[Chinese medicine|Chinese medical]] doctor, traded successfully in oils, opium, liquor, and grain and operated a money changing business. His business success allowed him to increase the family's real estate and salt well holdings.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

Guo's mother, in contrast, came from a scholar-official background. She was a daughter of Du Zhouzhang, a holder of the coveted ''[[jinshi (imperial examination)|jinshi]] (chin-shih)'' degree. Whilst serving as an acting magistrate in [[Huangping County|Huangping]] [[Zhou (country subdivision)|prefecture (''zhou'')]],&lt;ref&gt;now part of [[Qiandongnan Miao and Dong Autonomous Prefecture]]&lt;/ref&gt; (in eastern [[Guizhou]]), Du died in 1858 while fighting [[Miao people|Miao]] rebels, when his daughter (the future mother of Guo Moruo) was less than a year old. She married into the Guo family in 1872, when she was fourteen.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

===Childhood===
Guo was the eighth child of his mother. Three of his siblings had died before he was born, but more children were born later, so by the time he went to school, he had seven siblings.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

Guo also had the childhood name Guo Wenbao ('Cultivated Leopard'), given due to a dream his mother had on the night he was conceived.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

A few years before Guo was born, his parents retained a private tutor, Shen Huanzhang, to provide education for their children, in the hope of them later passing civil service examinations. A precocious child, Guo started studying at this &quot;family school&quot; in the spring of 1897, at the early age of four and half. Initially, his studies were based on Chinese classics, but with the government education reforms of 1901, mathematics and other modern subjects started to be introduced.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

When in the fall of 1903 a number of public schools were established in Sichuan's capital, [[Chengdu]], the Guo children started going there to study. Guo's oldest brother, Guo Kaiwen (1877–1936), entered one of them, Dongwen Xuetang, a secondary school preparing students for study in Japan; the next oldest brother, Guo Kaizou, joined Wubei Xuetang, a military school. Guo Kaiwen soon became instrumental in exposing his brother and sisters still in Shawan to modern books and magazines that allowed them to learn about the wide world outside.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

Guo Kaiwen continued to be a role model for his younger brothers when in February 1905 he left for Japan, to study law and administration at [[Tokyo Imperial University]] on a provincial government' scholarship.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

After passing competitive examinations, in early 1906 Guo Moruo started attending the new upper-level primary school (高等小学 ''gaodeng xiao xue'')  in [[Leshan|Jiading]]. It was a boarding school located in a former Buddhist temple and the boy lived on premises. He went on to a middle school in 1907, acquiring by this time the reputation of an academically gifted student but a troublemaker. His peers respected him and often elected him a delegate to represent their interests in front of the school administration. Often spearheading student-faculty conflicts, he was expelled and reinstated a few times, and finally expelled permanently in October 1909.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

Guo was glad to be expelled, as he now had a reason to go to the provincial capital [[Chengdu]] to continue his education there.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

In October 1911, Guo was surprised by his mother announcing that a marriage was arranged for him. He went along with his family's wishes, marrying his appointed bride, Zhang Jinghua, sight-unseen in Shawan in March 1912. Immediately, he regretted this marriage, and five days after the marriage, he left his ancestral home and returned to Chengdu, leaving his wife behind. He never formally divorced her, but apparently never lived with her either.&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;

===Study abroad===
[[Image:郭沫若先生顕彰碑.jpg|150px|right|thumb|Dr. Guo Kaizhen memorial at [[Kyushu University]]]]
Following his elder brothers, Guo left China in December 1913, reaching Japan in early January 1914. After a year of preparatory study in Tokyo, he entered Sixth Higher School in [[Okayama]].&lt;ref name=roy/&gt; When visiting a friend of his hospitalized in Sain Luke's Hospital in Tokyo, in the summer of 1916, Guo fell in love with [[Sato Tomiko]], a Japanese woman from a Christian family, who worked at the hospital as a student nurse. Sato would become his common-law wife. They were to stay together for 20 years, until the outbreak of [[Second Sino-Japanese War|the war]], and to have five children together.&lt;ref name=lu&gt;Yan Lu. &quot;Re-understanding Japan: Chinese Perspectives, 1895-1945&quot;. University of Hawaii Press, 2004.
ISBN 0824827309 [http://books.google.com/books?id=smNSTwZ5J_0C Partial text on Google Books]&lt;/ref&gt;

After graduation from the Okayama school, Guo entered in 1918 the Medical School of [[Kyushyu Imperial University]] in [[Fukuoka, Fukuoka|Fukuoka]].&lt;ref name=roy/&gt;  He was more interested in literature than medicine, however. His studies at this time focused on foreign language and literature, namely the works of: [[Spinoza]], [[Goethe]], [[Walt Whitman]], and the [[Bengali literature|Bengali]] poet [[Rabindranath Tagore|Tagore]]. Along with numerous translations, he published his first anthology of poems, entitled ''The Goddesses'' (女神 - ''nǚ shén'') (1921).  He co-founded the ''[[Ch'uang-tsao she]]'' (&quot;[[Creation Society]]&quot;) in Shanghai, which promoted modern and [[Vernacular Chinese|vernacular literature]].

===The war years===
{{Expand section|date=November 2008}}
[[File:Running script of Guo Moruo.jpg|thumb|Running script of Guo Moruo]]
Guo joined the [[Communist Party of China]] in 1927. He was involved in the Communist [[Nanchang Uprising]] and fled to Japan after its failure. He stayed there for 10 years studying Chinese ancient history. During that time he published his work on [[Oracle bone script|inscriptions on oracle bones]] and [[Bronzeware script|bronze vessels]], ''Corpus of Inscriptions on Bronzes from the Two Zhou Dynasties'' (两周金文辞大系考释).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Guo (郭)|first=Moro (沫若)|title=Corpus of Inscriptions on Bronzes from the Two Zhou Dynasties (两周金文辞大系考释)|language=Chinese|isbn= 9787030106568|date=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this work, he attempted to demonstrate, according to the Communist doctrine, the &quot;slave society&quot; nature of ancient China. His theory on the &quot;slave society of China&quot; remains highly controversial, although it was praised by [[Mao Zedong]] and the party.

In the summer of 1937, soon after the [[Marco Polo Bridge]] incident, Guo returned to China to join the anti-Japanese resistance.  His attempt to arrange for Sato Tomiko and their children to join him in China were frustrated by the Japanese authorities,&lt;ref name=lu/&gt; and in 1939 he remarried to Yu Liqun (于立群; 1916–1979), a Shanghai actress.&lt;ref name=lu/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cctv.com/program/e_documentary/20080912/100992_2.shtml The Westernization of Chinese Theatre] (CCTV)&lt;/ref&gt; After the war, Sato went to reunite with him but was disappointed to know that he had already formed a new family.

===As a communist leader===
Along with holding important government offices in the [[People's Republic of China]], Guo was a prolific writer, not just of poetry but also fiction, plays, autobiographies, translations, and historical and philosophical treatises. He was the first President of the [[Chinese Academy of Sciences]] and remained so from its founding in 1949 until his death in 1978. He was also the first president of [[University of Science &amp; Technology of China]] (USTC), a new type of university established by the Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS) after the founding of the People's Republic of China and aimed at fostering high-level personnel in the fields of science and technology.

In 1966 he was one of the first to be attacked during the [[Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution]]. He confessed that he had not properly understood the thought of Mao Zedong and agreed that his works should be burned. However, this was not enough to protect his family. Two of his sons, Guo Minying and Guo Shiying, &quot;committed suicide&quot; in 1967 and 1968 following &quot;criticism&quot; or persecution by [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guards]].&lt;ref name=xu-weixin&gt;[http://www.china-historical-figures.com/bilder_assets/Krev_Ausstellung_Biographien.pdf -  Portraits of China's historical figures] (This article contains portraits of a number of people who participated in the Cultural Revolution - as actors or as victims - painted by Xu Weixin, and biographical comments).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=xinhua&gt;[http://news.xinhuanet.com/book/2004-07/22/content_1622442.htm 《郭沫若的晚年岁月》：郭民英与郭世英] (Guo Moruo's late years: Guo Minying and Guo Shiying). This article is based on the book &quot;郭沫若的晚年岁月&quot; (Guo Moruo's Late Years) by Feng Xigang (冯锡刚). ISBN 750731622X.  {{zh icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
citation re: the death of one of GMR's sons caused by &quot;struggle against&quot; (persecution) by Red Guards during CR:
(via  news.google.com)
&quot;Suicide of Chinese Reported
$3.95 - New York Times - Jul 10, 1968
The Moscow radio reported today that the son of Kuo Mo-jo, Communist China's leading in..... , has committed suicide after systematic attacks on him in the ... &quot;

Also, for one who reads Chinese, this could be one good source:

&lt;ref name=gong&gt; Gong Jimin, Fang Rennian. &quot;Guo Moruo
zhuan&quot;. (Biography of Guo Moruo) &quot;Zhongguo xiandai zuojia zhuanji congshu&quot; (Collected
biographies of modern Chinese writers).  Beijing, Shiyue Wenyi
Chubanshe. 1988. ISBN 7-5302-0020-8. &lt;/ref&gt;
The cultural revolution years are around pp. 450-455.
--&gt;

Unlike others similarly attacked, Guo's life was spared as he was chosen by Mao as &quot;the representative of the rightwing&quot; in the 9th National Congress of the Communist Party of China in 1969. He had regained much of his influence by the seventies.

Guo was awarded the [[Stalin Peace Prize]] in 1951.

==Family==
Guo had five children (four sons and a daughter) with Sato Tomiko and six with Yu Liqun (four sons and two daughters). An article published in the 2000s said that eight out of the eleven were alive, and that three have died.&lt;ref&gt;[http://topic.xywy.com/wenzhang/20030817/16599.html 郭沫若之女细说父亲往事] (Guo Moruo's daughter recalls details about events in her father's life) {{zh icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With Sato Tomiko (listed chronologically in the order of birth):
*son Guo Hefu (郭和夫) (December 12 (or 31, according to other sources) 1917, Okayama - September 13, 1994). A chemist, he moved from Japan to Taiwan in 1946 and to mainland China in 1949. He was the founder of the Institute of Chemical Physics of the Chinese Academy of Sciences.&lt;ref name=wu-dongping&gt;[http://lianzai.china.com/books/html/1440/6937/92317.html 长子郭和夫] (&quot;Guo Hefu - the eldest son&quot;), and following chapters, from the book &quot;现代名人的后代&quot; (''Xiandai Mingrende Houdai'', &quot;The heirs of the famous people of our times&quot;) by 吴东平 (Wu Dongping). Hubei People's Press, 2006. ISBN 7216044762.&lt;/ref&gt;
*son Guo Bo (郭博) (born 1920), a renowned architect and photographer. He came to China in 1955, invited by his father, and worked in [[Shanghai]], where he participated in the design of many of its famous modern buildings.&lt;ref name=wu-dongping/&gt; Guo Bu is also known as a photographer of Shanghai's heritage architecture;&lt;ref name=wu-dongping/&gt; an album of his photographic work has been published as a book.&lt;ref&gt;Guo Bu, &quot;Zheng zai xiao shi de Shanghai long tang (The Fast Vanishing Shanghai Lanes)&quot;. Shanghai Pictorial Publishing House (1996). ISBN 7805302138. (In Chinese and English)&lt;/ref&gt;
*son Guo Fusheng (郭福生).
*daughter Guo Shuyu (郭淑禹), a Japanese-language teacher, now deceased.
*son Guo Zhihong (郭志宏).

With Yu Liqun  (listed chronologically in the order of birth):
*son Guo Hanying (郭汉英) (born 1941, Chongqing). An  internationally published theoretical physicist.&lt;ref name=wu-dongping/&gt;
*daughter Guo Shuying (郭庶英).&lt;ref name=ustc&gt;[http://www.ustc.edu.cn/en/article/49/42ff6a15/ USTC Newsletter 2001 No.2] (2005-08-14)&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- She studied biophysics at [[University of Science and Technology of China]] - the institution that her father had founded in 1958 and was the first president of. --&gt; She published a book about her father.&lt;ref&gt;Guo Shiying (郭庶英), &quot;My father Guo Moruo&quot; (我的父亲郭沫若), Liaoning People's Press (辽宁人民出版社), 2000, ISBN 7205056446. The book's cover and table of contents are available on amazon.cn.&lt;/ref&gt;
*son Guo Shiying (郭世英) (1942 - April 22, 1968). In 1962, while a philosophy student at [[Beijing University]], he created an &quot;underground&quot; &quot;X Poetry Society&quot;. In the summer of 1963 the society was exposed and deemed subversive. Guo Shiying was sentenced to [[re-education through labor]]. While working at a farm in [[Henan]] province, he developed interest in agriculture. Returning to Beijing in 1965, he enrolled at Beijing Agricultural University.  In 1968, kidnapped by [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guards]] and &quot;tried&quot; by their &quot;court&quot; for his poetry-society activity years before he jumped out of the window of the third-floor room where he was held and died at the age of 26. His father in his later writing expressed regret for encouraging his son to return to Beijing from the farm, thinking that it indirectly lead to his death.&lt;ref name=xu-weixin/&gt;&lt;ref name=xinhua&gt;[http://news.xinhuanet.com/book/2004-07/22/content_1622442.htm 《郭沫若的晚年岁月》：郭民英与郭世英] (Guo Moruo's late years: Guo Minying and Guo Shiying). This article is based on the book &quot;郭沫若的晚年岁月&quot; (Guo Moruo's Late Years) by Feng Xigang (冯锡刚). ISBN：750731622X. {{zh icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*son Guo Minying (郭民英), (November 1943, Chongqing  - April 12, 1967). His death is described as an unexpected suicide.&lt;ref name=xinhua/&gt;
*daughter Guo Pingying (郭平英)
*son Guo Jianying (郭建英) (born 1953).

==Commemoration==
*Guo's residence in Beijing, near Shicha Lake ([[Shichahai]]), where he lived after the war with his second (or third, if the arranged marriage is to be counted) wife, Yu Liqun, is preserved as a museum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.china.org.cn/english/features/beijing/31041.htm  Former Residence of Guo Moruo]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Guo and [[Sato Tomiko]]'s house in [[Ichikawa, Chiba|Ichikawa]], Japan, where they lived in 1927-37, is a museum as well.&lt;ref&gt;City of Ichickawa: [http://www.city.ichikawa.lg.jp/cul01/1541000031.html 郭沫若記念館] (Guo Moruo's Memorial House) {{ja icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to  the Guo Moruo connection, Ichikawa chose to establish [[sister city]] relations with [[Leshan]] in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;City of Ichikawa: [http://www.city.ichikawa.chiba.jp/koku/homon/raku_e.htm Leshan City]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Commons category|Guo Moruo}}

==Further reading==
{{Portalbox|China|Biography|Poetry}}
*[[Encyclopædia Britannica 2005 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]], article- &quot;Guo Moruo&quot;
*[http://english.newssc.org/system/2005/12/23/000023835.shtml  Guo Moruo] newssc.org
* Xiaoming Chen, ''From The May Fourth Movement to Communist Revolution: Guo Moruo and the Chinese Path to Communism'' (Albany, NY: State University of New York Press, 2007).

{{S-start}}
{{S-aca}}
{{s-new|rows=2}}
{{s-ttl|title=President of the [[Chinese Academy of Sciences]]|years=1949–1978}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Fang Yi]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Vacant until 1979&lt;/small&gt;}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=President of the [[University of Science and Technology of China]]|years=1958–1978}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Yan Jici]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Vacant until 1980&lt;/small&gt;}}
|-
{{S-end}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Guo, Moruo
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = November 16, 1892
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Leshan]], [[Sichuan]], [[Qing Empire]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = June 12, 1978
| PLACE OF DEATH    =  [[Beijing]], [[People's Republic of China]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Guo, Moruo}}
[[Category:1892 births]]
[[Category:1978 deaths]]
[[Category:Chinese archaeologists]]
[[Category:Republic of China poets]]
[[Category:People's Republic of China poets]]
[[Category:Republic of China historians]]
[[Category:People's Republic of China historians]]
[[Category:Members of the CPPCC National Committee]]
[[Category:Members of the National People's Congress]]
[[Category:Presidents of universities and colleges in China]]
[[Category:Chinese Hakka people]]
[[Category:People from Leshan]]
[[Category:Stalin Peace Prize recipients]]
[[Category:University of Science and Technology of China alumni]]
[[Category:University of Science and Technology of China faculty]]
[[Category:Sichuan University alumni]]
[[Category:Members of Academia Sinica]]

[[br:Guo Moruo]]
[[de:Guo Moruo]]
[[es:Guo Moruo]]
[[fr:Guo Moruo]]
[[ko:궈모뤄]]
[[id:Guo Moruo]]
[[it:Guō Mòruò]]
[[mr:गुओ मोरुओ]]
[[nl:Guo Moruo]]
[[ja:郭沫若]]
[[no:Guo Moruo]]
[[pl:Guo Moruo]]
[[ro:Guo Moruo]]
[[ru:Го Можо]]
[[fi:Guo Moruo]]
[[vi:Quách Mạt Nhược]]
[[zh:郭沫若]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
