<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="624" ns="0" title="Alaska"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vandalism|expiry=November 16, 2012|small=yes}}
{{About|the U.S. state of Alaska}}
{{Redirect|Alaskan}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}{{Infobox U.S. state
| Name                  = Alaska
| Fullname              = State of Alaska
| Flag                  = Flag of Alaska.svg
| Flaglink              = [[Flag of Alaska|Flag]]
| Seal                  = Alaska-StateSeal.svg
| Former                = Alaska Territory
| Map                   = Map of USA AK full.svg
| imagewidth            = 280px
| Nickname              = &quot;Land of the Midnight Sun&quot;
| Motto                 = North to the Future
| Nickname              =  The Last Frontier
| Demonym               = [[Adjectivals and demonyms for U.S. states|Alaskan]]
| Capital               = [[Juneau, Alaska|Juneau]]
| OfficialLang          = None&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090426134135/http://ourworld.compuserve.com/homepages/JWCRAWFORD/langleg.htm |archivedate=2009-04-26 |url=http://ourworld.compuserve.com/homepages/jwcrawford/langleg.htm |publisher=CompuServe.com |title=Language Legislation in the U.S.A.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.rcn.com/crawj/kritz.htm |title=RCN&amp;nbsp;– Digital Cable TV, High-Speed Internet Service &amp; Phone in Boston, Chicago, New York City, Philadelphia, Washington, D.C. and the Lehigh Valley |publisher=Users.rcn.com |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Languages             = English 89.7%,&lt;br /&gt;Native North American 5.2%,&lt;br /&gt;Spanish 2.9%
| LargestCity           = [[Anchorage, Alaska|Anchorage]]
| Governor              = [[Sean Parnell]] (R)
| Lieutenant Governor   = [[Mead Treadwell]] (R)
| Legislature           = [[Alaska Legislature]]
| Upperhouse            = [[Alaska Senate|Senate]]
| Lowerhouse            = [[Alaska House of Representatives|House of Representatives]]
| Senators              = [[Lisa Murkowski]] (R)&lt;br /&gt; [[Mark Begich]] (D)
| Representative        = [[Don Young]] (R) ([[Alaska's At-large congressional district|at-large]])
| PostalAbbreviation    = AK
| AreaRank              = 1st
| TotalArea             = 1,717,854
| TotalAreaUS           = 663,268
| LandArea              = 1,481,346
| LandAreaUS            = 571,951
| WaterArea             = 236,507
| WaterAreaUS           = 91,316
| PCWater               = 13.77
| PopRank               = 47th
| 2000Pop   (old)       = 626,932
| 2005Pop               = 663,661
| 2000Pop               = 710,231 (2010)&lt;ref name=08CenEst&gt;{{cite web | title = Resident Population Data – 2010 Census | publisher=United States Census Bureau | accessdate = 2011-02-27 | url = http://2010.census.gov/2010census/data/apportionment-pop-text.php}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 626,932 (2000)
| DensityRank           = 50th
| 2000Density           = 0.4
| 2000DensityUS         = 1.07
| MedianHouseholdIncome = US$64,333
| IncomeRank            = 4th |
| AdmittanceOrder       = 49th
| AdmittanceDate        = January 3, 1959
| TimeZone              = [[Alaska Standard Time Zone|Alaska]]: [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]-9/[[Daylight saving time|DST]]-8
| TZ1Where              = east of 169° 30'
| TimeZone2             = [[Hawaii-Aleutian Standard Time Zone|Aleutian]]: UTC-10/[[Daylight saving time|DST]]-9
| TZ2Where              = west of 169° 30'
| Latitude              = 51°20'N to 71°50'N
| Longitude             = 130°W to 172°E
| Width                 = 3,639
| WidthUS               = 2,261
| Length                = 2,285
| LengthUS              = 1,420
| HighestPoint = [[Mount McKinley]] ([[Mount McKinley|Denali]])&lt;ref name=USGS&gt;{{cite web|url=http://egsc.usgs.gov/isb/pubs/booklets/elvadist/elvadist.html|title=Elevations and Distances in the United States|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|year=2001|accessdate=October 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| HighestElev           = 6194
| HighestElevUS         = 20,320
| MeanElev              = 580
| MeanElevUS            = 1900
| LowestPoint           = [[Ocean]]&lt;ref name=USGS/&gt;
| LowestElev            = 0
| LowestElevUS          = 0
| ISOCode               = US-AK
| State song            = Alaska's Flag
| Website               = www.alaska.gov
}}

'''Alaska''' {{IPAc-en|audio=en-us-Alaska.ogg|ə|ˈ|l|æ|s|k|ə}} is the largest state in the [[United States]] by area. It is situated in the northwest extremity of the North American continent, with [[Canada]] to the east, the Arctic Ocean to the north, and the Pacific Ocean to the west and south, with [[Russia]] further west across the [[Bering Strait]]. Approximately half of Alaska's 710,231 residents (as per the [[2010 United States Census]]) live within the [[Anchorage metropolitan area]]. Alaska is the least densely populated state of the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/DTTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=04000US02&amp;-ds_name=PEP_2007_EST&amp;-mt_name=PEP_2007_EST_G2007_T001 |title=Census Bureau |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alaska was [[Alaska Purchase|purchased]] from [[Russia]] on March 30, 1867, for $7.2&amp;nbsp;million (${{Formatprice|{{Inflation|US|7200000|1867|r=2}}}} in today's dollars) at approximately two cents per acre ($4.74/km²). The land went through several administrative changes before becoming an [[Territories of the United States|organized (or incorporated) territory]] on May 11, 1912, and the 49th state of the U.S. on January 3, 1959.

The name &quot;Alaska&quot; (Аляска) was already introduced in the Russian colonial period, when it was used only for the [[Alaska Peninsula|peninsula]] and is derived from the [[Aleut language|Aleut]] ''alaxsxaq'', meaning &quot;the mainland&quot; or more literally, &quot;the object towards which the action of the sea is directed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ransom, J. Ellis. 1940. ''Derivation of the Word &quot;Alaska&quot;'. American Anthropologist n.s., 42: pp. 550–551&lt;/ref&gt; It is also known as [[Alyeska]], the &quot;great land&quot;, an Aleut word derived from the same root.

==Geography==
{{Main|Geography of Alaska}}
{{Wikisource|Portal:Alaska|Alaska}}
Alaska has a longer coastline than all the other U.S. states combined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gi.alaska.edu/ScienceForum/ASF14/1404.html |title=Alaska's Size in Perspective |accessdate=2007-11-19 |author=Benson, Carl|date=1998-09-02 |publisher=[[Geophysical Institute]], [[University of Alaska Fairbanks]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the only non-[[contiguous]] U.S. state on continental North America; about {{convert|500|mi|km|-1}} of British Columbia (Canada) separate Alaska from [[Washington (state)|Washington state]]. Alaska is thus an [[exclave]] of the United States. It is technically part of the [[Continental United States|continental U.S.]], but is often not included in colloquial use; Alaska is not part of the contiguous U.S., often called [[Outside (Alaska)|&quot;the Lower 48&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;The other three exclaves of the United States are the [[Northwest Angle]] of [[Minnesota]], [[Point Roberts, Washington]] and [[Alburgh, Vermont]].&lt;/ref&gt;  The capital city, [[Juneau]], is situated on the mainland of the North American continent, but is not connected by road to the rest of the North American highway system.

The state is bordered by the [[Yukon Territory]] and [[British Columbia]] in Canada, to the east, the [[Gulf of Alaska]] and the Pacific Ocean to the south, the [[Bering Sea]], [[Bering Strait]], and [[Chukchi Sea]] to the west and the Arctic Ocean to the north. Alaska's territorial waters touch Russia's territorial waters in the Bering Strait, as the Russian [[Big Diomede Island]] and Alaskan [[Little Diomede Island]] are only {{convert|3|mi|km}} apart.  With the extension of the [[Aleutian Islands]] into the eastern hemisphere, it is technically both the westernmost and easternmost state in the United States, as well as also being the northernmost.

[[File:Alaska area compared to conterminous US.svg|thumb|Alaska's size compared with the [[contiguous United States|48 contiguous states]].]]
Alaska is the largest state in the United States in land area at {{convert|586412|sqmi|km2|0}}, over twice the size of Texas, the next largest state. Alaska is larger than all but 18 sovereign countries.
Counting territorial waters, Alaska is larger than the combined area of the next three largest states: [[Texas]], [[California]], and [[Montana]]. It is also larger than the combined area of the 22 smallest U.S. states.

===Regions===
There are no officially defined borders demarcating the various regions of Alaska, but there are six generally accepted regions:

====South Central====
{{main|South Central Alaska}}
The most populous region of Alaska, containing [[Anchorage]], the [[Matanuska-Susitna Valley]] and the [[Kenai Peninsula]].  Rural, mostly unpopulated areas south of the [[Alaska Range]] and west of the [[Wrangell Mountains]] also fall within the definition of Southcentral, as well as the [[Prince William Sound]] area and the communities of [[Cordova, Alaska|Cordova]] and [[Valdez, Alaska|Valdez]].

====Southeast====
{{main|Southeast Alaska}}
Also known as the Panhandle, this is the region of Alaska closest to the rest of the United States, and hence was where most initial non-Native settlement occurred following the [[Alaska Purchase]]. It contains the state capital, Juneau, the former capital, [[Sitka]], and the large town of [[Ketchikan]].  The road systems leading from these cities are strictly local;  no roads connect these communities to each other or any other communities apart from their own suburbs.  The region is dominated by the [[Alexander Archipelago]] as well as the [[Tongass National Forest]], the largest national forest in the United States.

====Interior====
{{main|Alaska Interior}}
[[File:Denali Mt McKinley.jpg|thumb|right|[[Mount McKinley]] is both the highest peak in Alaska and in all of North America.]]
The largest region of Alaska, much of it uninhabited wilderness.  [[Fairbanks]] is the only community of any significant size.  Small towns and Native villages are scattered throughout, mostly along the highway and river systems.  [[Denali National Park and Preserve]] is located here, home to [[Mount McKinley]] (also widely known by its local name of Denali), the highest point in North America.

====Southwest====
{{main|Southwest Alaska}}
[[File:Grizzly Bear Fishing Brooks Falls.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Grizzly bear]] fishing for [[salmon]] at [[Katmai National Park and Preserve|Brooks Falls]].]]
A sparsely inhabited region stretching some {{convert|500|mi|km}} inland from the Bering Sea. Most of the population lives along the coast. [[Kodiak Island]] is also located in Southwest. The massive [[Yukon–Kuskokwim Delta]], one of the largest river deltas in the world, is here.  Portions of the [[Alaska Peninsula]] are considered part of Southwest, with the remaining portions included with the Aleutian Islands (see below).

====North Slope====
{{main|Alaska North Slope}}
The North Slope is mostly [[tundra]] peppered with small villages. The area is known for its massive reserves of crude oil, and contains both the [[National Petroleum Reserve–Alaska]] and the [[Prudhoe Bay Oil Field]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alaska.com |url=http://www.alaska.com/regions/ |title=Alaska.com |publisher=Alaska.com |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Barrow, Alaska|Barrow]], the northernmost city in the United States, is located here.  The [[Northwest Arctic Borough, Alaska|Northwest Arctic area]], anchored by [[Kotzebue, Alaska|Kotzebue]] and also containing the [[Kobuk River]] valley, is often regarded as being part of this region.  However, the respective [[Inupiat people|Inupiat]] of the North Slope and of the Northwest Arctic seldom think of themselves as one.

====Aleutian Islands====
{{main|Aleutian Islands}}
More than 300 small, volcanic islands make up this chain, which stretches over {{convert|1200|mi}} into the Pacific Ocean. The [[International Date Line]] was drawn west of 180° to keep the whole state, and thus the entire North American continent, within the same legal day.  However, because some of these islands fall in the Eastern Hemisphere, this makes Alaska the northernmost, easternmost and westernmost state in the union, with the southernmost state being Hawaii.  Two of the islands, [[Attu Island|Attu]] and [[Kiska]], were occupied by Japanese forces during World War II.

===Natural features===
[[File:Augustine Volcano Jan 12 2006 edited-1.jpg|right|thumb|[[Augustine Volcano]] erupting on January 12, 2006.]]
With its myriad islands, Alaska has nearly {{convert|34000|mi|km|-1}} of tidal shoreline. The [[Aleutian Islands]] chain extends west from the southern tip of the [[Alaska Peninsula]]. Many active [[volcano]]es are found in the Aleutians and in coastal regions. [[Unimak Island]], for example, is home to [[Mount Shishaldin]], which is an occasionally smoldering volcano that rises to {{convert|10000|ft|m|0}} above the North Pacific. It is the most perfect volcanic cone on Earth, even more symmetrical than Japan's [[Mount Fuji]]. The chain of volcanoes extends to [[Mount Spurr]], west of Anchorage on the mainland. Geologists have identified Alaska as part of [[Wrangellia]], a large region consisting of multiple states and Canadian provinces in the [[Pacific Northwest]] which is actively undergoing [[plate tectonics|continent building]].

One of the world's largest tides occurs in [[Turnagain Arm]], just south of Anchorage&amp;nbsp;– tidal differences can be more than {{convert|35|ft|m|1}}. (Many sources say Turnagain has the second-greatest tides in North America, but several areas in Canada have larger tides.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Porco, Peter|date = June 23, 2003 | title = Long said to be second to Fundy, city tides aren't even close | journal=[[Anchorage Daily News]] | pages = A1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{main|List of lakes in Alaska}}
Alaska has more than three million lakes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Alaska Hydrology Survey | publisher=Division of Mining, Land, and Water; [[Alaska Department of Natural Resources]] | url=http://www.dnr.state.ak.us/mlw/water/hydro/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.knls.org/English/akfact.htm |title=Alaska Facts |publisher=Knls.org |accessdate=2010-06-02|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080228134807/http%3A//www.knls.org/English/akfact.htm |archivedate = February 28, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Marshland]]s and wetland [[permafrost]] cover {{convert|188320|sqmi|km2|0}} (mostly in northern, western and southwest flatlands). Glacier ice covers some {{convert|16000|sqmi|km2|-1}} of land and {{convert|1200|sqmi|km2|-1}} of tidal zone. The [[Bering Glacier]] complex near the southeastern border with Yukon covers {{convert|2250|sqmi|km2|0}} alone. With over 100,000, Alaska has half of the world's glaciers.

===Land ownership===
[[File:Public-Lands-Western-US.png|thumb|300px|Alaska has more public land owned by the federal government than any other state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wildlandfire.com/docs/2007/western-states-data-public-land.htm |title=Western States Data Public Land Acreage |publisher=Wildlandfire.com |date=2007-11-13 |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
According to an October 1998 report by the [[United States Bureau of Land Management]], approximately 65% of Alaska is owned and managed by the [[Federal government of the United States|U.S. federal government]] as public lands, including a multitude of [[United States National Forest|national forests]], national parks, and [[national wildlife refuge]]s. Of these, the [[Bureau of Land Management]] manages  {{convert|87|e6acre|e6ha|abbr=off}}, or 23.8% of the state. The [[Arctic National Wildlife Refuge]] is managed by the [[United States Fish and Wildlife Service]]. It is the world's largest wildlife refuge, comprising {{convert|16|e6acre|e6ha|abbr=off}}.

Of the remaining land area, the state of Alaska owns {{convert|101|e6acre|e6ha|abbr=off}};  its entitlement under the [[Alaska Statehood Act]].  A portion of that acreage is occasionally ceded to organized boroughs, under the statutory provisions pertaining to newly-formed boroughs.  Smaller portions are set aside for rural subdivisions and other homesteading-related opportunities, though these are infrequently popular due to the often remote and roadless locations.  The [[University of Alaska]], as a [[land grant university]], also owns substantial acreage which it manages independently.

Another {{convert|44|e6acre|e6ha|abbr=off}} are owned by 12 regional, and scores of local, Native corporations created under the [[Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act]].  [[Alaska Native Regional Corporation|Regional Native corporation]] [[Doyon, Limited]] often promotes itself as the largest private landowner in Alaska in advertisements and other communications.  Provisions of ANCSA allowing the corporations' land holdings to be sold on the open market starting in 1991 were repealed before they could take effect.  Effectively, the corporations hold title (including subsurface title in many cases, a privilege denied to individual Alaskans) but cannot sell the land.  [[Alaska Native Allotment Act|Individual Native allotments]] can be and are sold on the open market, however.

Various private interests own the remaining land, totaling about one percent of the state.  Alaska is, by a large margin, the state with the smallest percentage of private land ownership when Native corporation holdings are excluded.

===Climate===
{{Main|Climate of Alaska}}
The climate in Juneau and the southeast panhandle is a mid-latitude [[oceanic climate]] ([[Köppen climate classification]] ''Cfb'') in the southern sections and a subarctic oceanic climate (Köppen ''Cfc'') in the northern parts. On an annual basis, the panhandle is both the wettest and warmest part of Alaska with milder temperatures in the winter and high precipitation throughout the year. Juneau averages over {{convert|50|in|mm|-1}} of precipitation a year, while other areas receive over {{convert|275|in|mm|-1}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;AK-YK Precip&quot;&gt;[http://www.ocs.orst.edu/pub/maps/Precipitation/Total/States/AK/ak_ppt.gif Mean Annual Precipitation in Alaska-Yukon]. Oregon Climate Service at [[Oregon State University]]. Retrieved October 23, 2006. {{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is also the only region in Alaska in which the average daytime high temperature is above freezing during the winter months.

The climate of Anchorage and south central Alaska is mild by Alaskan standards due to the region's proximity to the seacoast. While the area gets less rain than southeast Alaska, it gets more snow, and days tend to be clearer. On average, Anchorage receives {{convert|16|in|mm|0}} of precipitation a year, with around {{convert|75|in|cm|0}} of snow, although there are areas in the south central which receive far more snow. It is a subarctic climate (Köppen ''Dfc'') due to its brief, cool summers.

[[File:Barrow beach.jpg|thumb|[[Barrow, Alaska|Barrow]], known colloquially for many years by the nickname &quot;Top of the World,&quot; is the northernmost city in the United States.]]
The climate of Western Alaska is determined in large part by the Bering Sea and the Gulf of Alaska. It is a subarctic oceanic climate in the southwest and a continental subarctic climate farther north. The temperature is somewhat moderate considering how far north the area is. This region has a tremendous amount of variety in precipitation.  An area stretching from the northern side of the Seward Peninsula to the [[Kobuk River]] valley is technically a desert, with portions receiving less than {{convert|10|in|mm|0}} of precipitation annually.  On the other extreme, some locations between Dillingham and Bethel average around {{convert|100|in|mm|-1}} of precipitation.&lt;ref name=&quot;AK-YK Precip&quot;/&gt;

The climate of the interior of Alaska is subarctic. Some of the highest and lowest temperatures in Alaska occur around the area near Fairbanks. The summers may have temperatures reaching into the 90s°F (the low to mid 30s °C), while in the winter, the temperature can fall below {{convert|−60|°F|°C|1}}. Precipitation is sparse in the Interior, often less than {{convert|10|in|mm|0}} a year, but what precipitation falls in the winter tends to stay the entire winter.

The highest and lowest recorded temperatures in Alaska are both in the Interior. The highest is {{convert|100|°F|°C|1}} in [[Fort Yukon, Alaska|Fort Yukon]] (which is just {{convert|8|mi|km|sp=us|disp=or}} inside the arctic circle) on June 27, 1915,&lt;ref name=&quot;NOAA-All Hazards&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = NOAA Weather Radio All Hazards Information&amp;nbsp;— Alaska Weather Interesting Facts and Records | publisher=[[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration]] | format = PDF | url = http://www.arh.noaa.gov/docs/AKWXfacts.pdf | accessdate = 2007-01-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DRI&gt;{{cite web | title = State Extremes | publisher=Western Regional Climate Center, [[Desert Research Institute]] | url = http://www.wrcc.dri.edu/htmlfiles/state.extremes.html | accessdate = 2007-01-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; making Alaska tied with Hawaii as the state with the lowest high temperature in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = SD Weather History and Trivia for May: May 1 | publisher=[[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration]] | url = http://www.crh.noaa.gov/fsd/?n=fsdtrivia05 NOAA&amp;nbsp;– National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration | accessdate = 2007-01-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = FAQ ALASKA&amp;nbsp;— Frequently Asked Questions About Alaska: Weather | publisher=Statewide Library Electronic Doorway, [[University of Alaska Fairbanks]] | date= 2005-01-17 | url=http://sled.alaska.edu/akfaq/aksuper.html#wea | accessdate = 2007-01-03 }}{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lowest official Alaska temperature is {{convert|−80|°F|°C|1}} in [[Prospect Creek, Alaska|Prospect Creek]] on January 23, 1971,&lt;ref name=&quot;NOAA-All Hazards&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=DRI/&gt; one degree above the lowest temperature recorded in continental North America (in [[Snag, Yukon|Snag, Yukon, Canada]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Ned Rozell | title = The Coldest Place in North America | publisher=Geophysical Institute of the [[University of Alaska Fairbanks]] | date= 2003-01-23 | url = http://www.gi.alaska.edu/ScienceForum/ASF16/1630.html | accessdate = 2007-01-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The climate in the extreme north of Alaska is [[polar climate|Arctic]] (Köppen ''ET'') with long, very cold winters and short, cool summers. Even in July, the average low temperature in [[Barrow, Alaska|Barrow]] is {{convert|34|°F|°C|1}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wunderground.com/history/airport/PABR/2006/7/23/MonthlyHistory.html History for Barrow, Alaska. Monthly Summary for July 2006]. [[Weather Underground (weather service)|Weather Underground]]. Retrieved October 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Precipitation is light in this part of Alaska, with many places averaging less than {{convert|10|in|mm|0}} per year, mostly as snow which stays on the ground almost the entire year.

==History==
{{Main|History of Alaska}}

===Alaska natives===
{{see also|Prehistory of Alaska}}
[[File:AlutiiqDancer.jpg|thumb|left|upright|A modern Alutiiq dancer in traditional festival garb]]
Numerous indigenous peoples occupied Alaska for thousands of years before the arrival of European peoples to the area. The [[Tlingit people|Tlingit]] people developed a matriarchal society in what is today Southeast Alaska, along with parts of British Columbia and the Yukon. Also in Southeast were the [[Haida people|Haida]], now well known for their unique arts, and the [[Tsimshian]] people, whose population were decimated by a smallpox epidemic in the 1860s. The Aleutian Islands are still home to the [[Aleut people|Aleut]] people's seafaring society, although they were among the first native Alaskans to be exploited by Russians. Western and Southwestern Alaska are home to the [[Yup'ik]], while their cousins the [[Alutiiq]] lived in what is now Southcentral Alaska. The [[Gwich’in]] people of the northern Interior region are primarily known today for their dependence on the caribou within the much-contested [[Arctic National Wildlife Refuge]]. The North Slope and [[Little Diomede Island]] are occupied by the widespread [[Inuit]] people.

===Colonization===

Some researchers believe that the first Russian settlement in Alaska was established in 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;Свердлов Л. М. Русское поселение на Аляске в XVII в.? «Природа». М., 1992. № 4. С.67–69.&lt;/ref&gt; According to this hypothesis, in 1648 several [[koch]]es of [[Semyon Dezhnyov]]'s expedition were thrown to Alaska by storm and founded this settlement. This hypothesis is based on the message of [[Chukchi]] geographer [[Nikolai Daurkin]] who had visited Alaska in 1764–1765 and reported about village on the [[Kheuveren]] river, populated by &quot;bearded men&quot; who &quot;pray to the icons&quot;. Some modern researchers associate Kheuveren with [[Koyuk River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fartuna.ru/go.php?ad=489047 |title=Онгмюбюрекэмши Пеяспя Псяяйн-Юлепхйюмяйни Йнлоюмхх |publisher=Fartuna.ru |date= |accessdate=2011-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Russian Sloop-of-War Neva.jpg|thumb|The Russian settlement of St. Paul's Harbor, Kodiak Island, 1814.]]
It is usually assumed that the first European boat to reach Alaska was «St. Gabriel» under the authority of the surveyor [[Mikhail Gvozdev|M. S. Gvozdev]] and assistant navigator [[Ivan Fyodorov (navigator)|I. Fyodorov]] on August 21, 1732 during expedition of Siberian cossak [[Afanasiy Shestakov|A. F. Shestakov]] adb Belorussian explorer [[Dmitriy Pavlutskiy|D. I. Pavlutsky]] (1729—1735)&lt;ref&gt;Аронов В. Н. Патриарх Камчатского мореходства. // «Вопросы истории рыбной промышленности Камчатки»: Историко-краеведческий сб. – Вып. 3. – 2000. Вахрин С. Покорители великого океана. Петроп.-Камч.: Камштат, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another European contact with Alaska occurred in 1741, when [[Vitus Bering]] led an [[second Kamchatka expedition|expedition]] for the Russian Navy aboard the ''St. Peter''. After his crew returned to Russia with sea otter pelts judged to be the finest fur in the world, small associations of fur traders began to sail from the shores of Siberia towards the Aleutian islands. The first permanent European settlement was founded in 1784. Between 1774 and 1800 [[Viceroyalty of New Spain|Spain]] sent several [[Spanish expeditions to the Pacific Northwest|expeditions to Alaska]] in order to assert its claim over the Pacific Northwest. In 1789 a Spanish settlement and [[Fort San Miguel|fort]] were built in [[Nootka Sound]]. These expeditions gave names to places such as [[Valdez, Alaska|Valdez]], [[Bucareli Sound]], and [[Cordova, Alaska|Cordova]]. Later, the [[Russian-American Company]] carried out an expanded colonization program during the early-to-mid-19th century.

[[Sitka, Alaska|Sitka]], renamed [[New Archangel]] from 1804 to 1867, on [[Baranof Island]] in the [[Alexander Archipelago]] in what is now [[Southeast Alaska]], became the capital of [[Russian America]] and remained the capital after the colony was transferred to the United States. The Russians never fully colonized Alaska, and the colony was never very profitable.

[[William H. Seward]], the [[United States Secretary of State]], negotiated the [[Alaska Purchase]] (also known as Seward's Folly) with the Russians in 1867 for $7.2&amp;nbsp;million. Alaska was loosely governed by the military initially, and was administered as a [[District of Alaska|district]] starting in 1884, with a governor appointed by the president of the United States, as well as a [[United States territorial court|district court]] headquartered in Sitka.
[[File:Miners climb Chilkoot.jpg|thumb|Miners and prospectors climb the [[Chilkoot Trail]] during the [[Klondike Gold Rush]].]]
For most of Alaska's first decade under the American flag, Sitka was the only community inhabited by American settlers.  They organized a &quot;provisional city government,&quot; which was Alaska's first city government, but not in a legal sense.  Legislation allowing Alaskan communities to legally incorporate as cities did not come about until 1900, and [[Home rule#Home rule in the United States|home rule]] for cities was extremely limited or unavailable until statehood took effect.

===U.S. Territory===
Starting in the 1890s and stretching in some places to the early 1910s, [[Alaska Gold Rush|gold rushes]] in Alaska and the nearby [[Yukon|Yukon Territory]] brought thousands of miners and settlers to Alaska.  Alaska was officially incorporated as an organized territory in 1912.  Alaska's capital, which had been in [[Sitka, Alaska|Sitka]] until the 1900 legislation mandated its transfer to [[Juneau, Alaska|Juneau]] (the actual move took place in 1906, after initial questions arose), begun to take shape with the construction of the [[Alaska Governor's Mansion]] that same year.

[[File:AttuSnow.jpg|thumb|left|upright|U.S. troops negotiate snow and ice during the [[Battle of Attu]] in May 1943.]]
During World War II, the [[Aleutian Islands Campaign]] focused on the three outer Aleutian Islands&amp;nbsp;– [[Attu Island|Attu]], [[Agattu Island|Agattu]] and [[Kiska Island|Kiska]]&lt;ref&gt;these three Aleutian outer islands are about {{convert|460|mi|km}} away from continental USSR, {{convert|920|mi|km}} from continental Alaska (U.S.), {{convert|950|mi|km}} from Japan.&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– that were invaded by Japanese troops and occupied between June 1942 and August 1943. [[Unalaska]]/Dutch Harbor became a significant base for the U.S. Army Air Corps and Navy submariners.

The U.S. [[Lend-Lease]] program involved the flying of American warplanes through Canada to Fairbanks and thence Nome; Soviet pilots took possession of these aircraft, ferrying them to fight the German invasion of the Soviet Union. The construction of military bases contributed to the population growth of some Alaskan cities.

===Statehood===
Statehood for Alaska was an important cause of [[James Wickersham]] early in his tenure as a congressional delegate.  Decades later, the statehood movement gained its first real momentum following a territorial referendum in 1946.  The Alaska Statehood Committee and Alaska's Constitutional Convention would soon follow.  Statehood supporters also found themselves fighting major battles against political foes, mostly in the U.S. Congress but also within Alaska.  Statehood was approved by Congress on July 7, 1958. Alaska was officially proclaimed a state on January 3, 1959.

On April 27, 1964, the massive &quot;[[Good Friday Earthquake]]&quot; killed 133 people and destroyed several villages and portions of large coastal communities, mainly by the resultant [[tsunamis]] and landslides. It was the third most powerful earthquake in the recorded history of the world, with a [[moment magnitude scale|moment magnitude]] of 9.2. It was over one thousand times more powerful than the [[1989 Loma Prieta earthquake|1989 San Francisco earthquake]].  The time of day (5:36&amp;nbsp;pm), time of year and location of the epicenter were all cited as factors in potentially sparing thousands of lives, particularly in Anchorage.

The 1968 discovery of oil at [[Prudhoe Bay]] and the 1977 completion of the [[Trans-Alaska Pipeline]] led to an oil boom.  Royalty revenues from oil have funded large state budgets from 1980 onward.  That same year, not coincidentally, Alaska repealed its state income tax.  In 1989, the ''[[Exxon Valdez]]'' hit a reef in the [[Prince William Sound]], spilling over {{convert|11000000|USgal|m3|sigfig=2}} of crude oil over 1,100&amp;nbsp;miles (1,600&amp;nbsp;km) of coastline. Today, the battle between philosophies of development and conservation is seen in the contentious debate over oil drilling in the [[Arctic National Wildlife Refuge]].

==Demographics==
{{Main|Demographics of Alaska}}
{{USCensusPop
|1880=33426
|1890=32052
|1900=63592
|1910=64356
|1920=55036
|1930=59278
|1940=72524
|1950=128643
|1960=226167
|1970=300382
|1980=401851
|1990=550043
|2000=626932
|2010=710231
|footnote = 1930 and 1940 censuses taken in preceding autumn&lt;br&gt;Sources: 1910–2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://2010.census.gov/2010census/data/apportionment-pop-text.php |title=Resident Population Data – 2010 Census |publisher=2010.census.gov |accessdate=2011-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The [[United States Census Bureau]], as of July 1, 2008, estimated Alaska's population at 686,293,&lt;ref name=08CenEst/&gt; which represents an increase of 59,361, or 9.5%, since the last census in 2000.&lt;ref name=census_cum&gt;{{cite web |title=Cumulative Estimates of the Components of Population Change for the United States, Regions and States: April 1, 2000 to July 1, 2008 (NST-EST2008-04) |url=http://www.census.gov/popest/states/tables/NST-EST2008-04.csv |author=U.S. Census Bureau |authorlink=United States Census Bureau |date=2008-12-15 |accessdate=2009-01-16 |format=CSV}}&lt;/ref&gt; This includes a natural increase since the last census of 60,994 people (that is 86,062 births minus 25,068 deaths) and a decrease due to net migration of 5,469 people out of the state.&lt;ref name=census_cum/&gt; [[Immigration to the United States|Immigration from outside the U.S.]] resulted in a net increase of 4,418 people, and migration within the country produced a net loss of 9,887 people.&lt;ref name=census_cum/&gt;

In 2000 Alaska ranked the 48th state by population, ahead of [[Vermont]] and [[Wyoming]] (and Washington D.C.).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/population/cen2000/phc-t2/tab01.txt |title=Census Bureau |publisher=census.gov |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alaska is the least densely populated state, and one of the most sparsely populated areas in the world, at 1.0 person per square mile (0.42/km²), with the next state, Wyoming, at 5.1 per square mile (1.97/km²). Alaska is the largest U.S. state by [[List of U.S. states by area|area]], and the sixth wealthiest (per capita income).  As of January 2010, the state's unemployment rate is 8.5%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bls.gov/lau/ Bls.gov]; Local Area Unemployment Statistics&lt;/ref&gt;

===Race and ancestry===

According to the [[2010 U.S. Census]], Alaska had a population of 710,231. In terms of race and ethnicity, the state was 66.7% White (64.7% Non-Hispanic White Alone), 14.8% American Indian and Alaska Native, 5.4% Asian, 3.3% Black or African American, 1.0% Native Hawaiian and Other Pacific Islander, 1.6% from Some Other Race, and 7.3% from Two or More Races. Hispanics or Latinos of any race made up 5.5% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_PL_QTPL&amp;prodType=table |title=American FactFinder |publisher=Factfinder2.census.gov |date=2010-10-05 |accessdate=2011-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Languages===
According to the 2005–2007 American Community Survey, 84.7% of people over the age of five speak only English at home. About 3.5% speak Spanish at home. About 2.2% speak another [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European language]] at home and about 4.3% speak an [[Languages of Asia|Asian language]] at home. And about 5.3% speak other languages at home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=American FactFinder, United States Census Bureau |url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ADPTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=04000US02&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2007_3YR_G00_DP3YR2&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2007_3YR_G00_&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-redoLog=false&amp;-_sse=on |title=Census Bureau |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A total of 5.2% of Alaskans speak one of the state's 22 [[Indigenous languages of the Americas|indigenous languages]], known locally as &quot;native languages&quot;. These languages belong to two major language families: [[Eskimo–Aleut languages|Eskimo–Aleut]] and [[Na-Dené languages|Na-Dene]]. As the homeland of these two major language families of North America, Alaska has been described as the crossroads of the continent, providing evidence for the recent settlement of North America by way of the [[Bering land bridge]].

===Religion===
[[File:Russian Orthodox Church.jpg|thumb|right|[[St. Michael's Cathedral (Sitka, Alaska)|St. Michael's Russian Orthodox Cathedral]] in [[Sitka, Alaska|Sitka]].]]
Alaska has been identified, along with Pacific Northwest states Washington and Oregon, as being the least religious in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adherents.com/Na/Na_472.html |title=Adherents.com |publisher=Adherents.com |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090116035021/http://www.adn.com/life/story/463303.html |archivedate=2009-01-16 |url=http://www.adn.com/life/story/463303.html |title=Believe it or not, Alaska's one of nation's least religious states |publisher=Anchorage Daily News |date=2008-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to statistics collected by the Association of Religion Data Archives, about 39% of Alaska residents were members of religious congregations. [[Evangelical Protestant]]s had 78,070 members, Roman Catholics had 54,359, and mainline Protestants had 37,156.&lt;ref name = ARDA&gt;{{cite web | title = Religious Affiliations 2000 | work=Alaska State Membership Report | publisher=Association of Religion Data Archives | url = http://www.thearda.com/mapsReports/reports/state/02_2000.asp | accessdate = 2008-03-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  After Catholicism, the largest single denominations are [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] with 30,169,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsroom.lds.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/statistical-information |title=LDS Newsroom Statistical Information |publisher=Newsroom.lds.org |accessdate=2010-06-02|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080730060850/http%3A//newsroom.lds.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/statistical-information |archivedate = July 30, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Southern Baptists with 22,959.  The large [[Eastern Orthodox]] (with 49 parishes and up to 50,000 followers)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Dixon |first=Martha |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/3531458.stm |title=''Religious legacy lives on in Alaska'' |publisher=BBC News  |date=2004-09-12 |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; population is a result of early [[Russian Alaska|Russian colonization]] and [[missionary]] work among Alaska Natives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sled.alaska.edu/akfaq/akchron.html |title=Welcome to SLED: FAQ Alaska |publisher=Sled.alaska.edu |accessdate=2010-06-02}}{{dead link|date=December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1795, the First [[Russian Orthodox Church]] was established in [[Kodiak Island Borough, Alaska|Kodiak]]. Intermarriage with Alaskan Natives helped the Russian immigrants integrate into society. As a result, an increasing number of Russian Orthodox churches&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vilda.alaska.edu/u?/cdmg11,4904 |title=An early Russian Orthodox Church |publisher=Vilda.alaska.edu |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; gradually became established within Alaska. Alaska also has the largest [[Quaker]] population (by percentage) of any state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thearda.com/mapsReports/maps/map.asp?state=101&amp;variable=201 |title=Association of Religion Data Archive |publisher=Thearda.com |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009 there were 6,000 Jews in Alaska (for whom observance of the [[mitzvah]] [[Jewish law in the polar regions|may pose special problems]]).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.census.gov/compendia/statab/2011/tables/11s0077.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates for the number of Alaskan Muslims range from 2,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090116035850/http://dwb.adn.com/news/alaska/ap_alaska/story/8656236p-8548061c.html |archivedate=2009-01-16 |url=http://dwb.adn.com/news/alaska/ap_alaska/story/8656236p-8548061c.html |title=First Muslim cemetery opens in Alaska}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090215202834/http://engagingmuslims.alaskapacific.edu/ |archivedate=2009-02-15 |url=http://engagingmuslims.alaskapacific.edu/ |title=Engaging Muslim: Religion, Culture, Politics}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 5,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.humanitynews.net/index.php/main/more/alaskan_muslims_avoid_conflict/ |title=Alaskan Muslims Avoid Conflict |publisher=Humanitynews.net |date=2005-07-07 |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the local Muslim community broke ground on the first mosque in the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/video/americas/2010/12/20101225111741183159.html |title=Mosque milestone for Alaska Muslims – Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2010-12-25 |accessdate=2011-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alaskan Hindus often share venues and celebrations with members of other religious communities including [[Sikhism|Sikhs]] and [[Jainism|Jains]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090201151519/http://caia.arctic.us/?Shri_Ganesha_Mandir_of_Alaska |archivedate=2009-02-11 |url=http://www.caia.arctic.us/?Shri_Ganesha_Mandir_of_Alaska |title=Shri Ganesha Mandir of Alaska |publisher=Cultural Association of India Anchorage |last1=Kalyan |first1=Mala}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindumandir.us/west-coast.html#AK |title=Hindu Temples in USA&amp;nbsp;– Hindu Mandirs in USA |publisher=Hindumandir.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090201151459/http://caia.arctic.us/?Holi_%2F_Baisakhi_Celebration%3A |archivedate=2009-02-11 |url=http://www.caia.arctic.us/?Holi_%2F_Baisakhi_Celebration%3A |title=Holi &amp; Baisakhi celebrated by Alaskan Hindus and Sikhs |publisher=Cultural Association of India Anchorage}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
[[File:Prudhoe Bay aerial FWS.jpg|thumb|right|Oilfield facilities at [[Prudhoe Bay]].]]
{{main|Economy of Alaska}}
The 2007 [[gross state product]] was $44.9&amp;nbsp;billion, 45th in the nation. Its [[List of U.S. states by GDP per capita (nominal)|per capita personal income]] for 2007 was $40,042, ranking 15th in the nation. The oil and gas industry dominates the Alaskan economy, with more than 80% of the state's revenues derived from petroleum extraction. Alaska's main export product (excluding oil and natural gas) is seafood, primarily salmon, cod, Pollock and crab.

Agriculture represents only a fraction of the Alaskan economy. Agricultural production is primarily for consumption within the state and includes nursery stock, dairy products, vegetables, and livestock. Manufacturing is limited, with most foodstuffs and general goods imported from elsewhere.

Employment is primarily in government and industries such as natural resource extraction, shipping, and transportation. Military bases are a significant component of the economy in both Fairbanks and Anchorage. Federal subsidies are also an important part of the economy, allowing the state to keep taxes low. Its industrial outputs are crude petroleum, natural gas, coal, gold, precious metals, zinc and other mining, seafood processing, timber and wood products. There is also a growing service and tourism sector. Tourists have contributed to the economy by supporting local lodging.

===Largest employers===
According to the [[Alaska Department of Labor and Workforce Development]], the following were the state's largest [[private sector]] employers in 2010:&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://laborstats.alaska.gov/lgstemp/lgstemp.htm Alaska's 100 Largest Private Sector Employers in 2010 (July 2011 Alaska Economic Trends).&quot; Alaska Department of Labor and Workforce Development (2007).]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bpanchorage.JPG|thumb|right|BP headquarters in Anchorage.]]
[[File:Alaska Airlines, N767AS.jpg|thumb|right|Alaska Airlines [[Boeing 737]]-490 taking off from [[Ted Stevens Anchorage International Airport]].]]
[[File:Fairbanks Memorial Hospital.jpg|thumb|right|Fairbanks Memorial Hospital.]]
[[File:Alyeska Resort.JPG|thumb|right|Alyeska Prince Hotel in [[Girdwood]].]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Rank
! Employer name
! Average monthly&lt;br&gt;employment in 2010
|-
| 1
| [[Providence Health &amp; Services]]
| 4,000+
|-
| 2
| [[Walmart]]/[[Sam's Club]]
| 3,000-3,249
|-
| 3
| [[Carrs Safeway Alaska Division]]
| 2,750-2,999
|-
| 4
| [[Fred Meyer]]
| 2,500-2,749
|-
| 5
| [[Arctic Slope Regional Corporation#Business enterprises|ASRC Energy Services]]
| 2,500-2,749
|-
| 6
| [[Trident Seafoods]]
| 2,250-2,499
|-
| 7
| [[BP|BP Exploration Alaska]]
| 2,000-2,249
|-
| 8
| [[CH2M HILL]]
| 1,750-1,999
|-
| 9
| [[NANA Regional Corporation|NANA Management Services]]
| 1,750-1,999
|-
| 10
| [[Alaska Native Tribal Health Consortium]]
| 1,500-1,749
|-
| 11
| [[Alaska Airlines]]
| 1,500-1,749
|-
| 12
| [[GCI (company)|GCI Communications]]
| 1,250-1,499
|-
| 13
| [[Banner Health]]&lt;br&gt;(includes Fairbanks Memorial Hospital)
| 1,250-1,499
|-
| 14
| [[Southcentral Foundation]]
| 1,250-1,499
|-
| 15
| [[Yukon-Kuskokwim Health Corporation]]
| 1,000-1,249
|-
| 16
| [[FedEx]]
| 1,000-1,249
|-
| 17
| [[ConocoPhillips Alaska]]
| 1,000-1,249
|-
| 18
| [[Alaska USA Federal Credit Union]]
| 1,000-1,249
|-
| 19
| [[United Parcel Service]]
| 1,000-1,249
|-
| 20
| [[McDonald's|McDonald's Restaurants of Alaska]]
| 750-999
|-
| 21
| [[Wells Fargo]]
| 750-999
|-
| 22
| [[Doyon, Limited|Doyon Universal Services]]
| 750-999
|-
| 23
| [[Home Depot]]
| 750-999
|-
| 24
| [[Alaska Regional Hospital]]
| 750-999
|-
| 25
| [[The Alaska Club]]
| 750-999
|-
| 26
| [[Petersburg, Alaska#History|Icicle Seafoods]]
| 750-999
|-
| 27
| [[Southeast Alaska Regional Health Consortium]]
| 750-999
|-
| 28
| [[Hope Community Resources]]
| 750-999
|-
| 29
| [[UniSea]]
| 750-999
|-
| 30
| [[Alaska Commercial Company]]
| 750-999
|-
| 31
| [[Costco]]
| 750-999
|-
| 32
| [[Spenard Builders Supply]]
| 750-999
|-
| 33
| [[Lowe's]]
| 750-999
|-
| 34
| [[Alyeska Pipeline Service Company]]
| 750-999
|-
| 35
| [[Alaska Communications|Alaska Communication Systems]]
| 500-749
|-
| 36
| [[First National Bank Alaska]]
| 500-749
|-
| 37
| [[Central Peninsula Hospital]]
| 500-749
|-
| 38
| [[First Student (United States)|First Student]]
| 500-749
|-
| 39
| [[Westward Seafood]]
| 500-749
|-
| 40
| [[Mat-Su Regional Medical Center]]
| 500-749
|-
| 41
| [[Alaska Consumer Direct Personal Care]]
| 500-749
|-
| 42
| [[Tanana Chiefs Conference]]
| 500-749
|-
| 43
| [[PeterPan Seafoods]]
| 500-749
|-
| 44
| [[Udelhoven Oilfield System Services]]
| 500-749
|-
| 45
| [[Job Ready]]/[[ReadyCare]]
| 500-749
|-
| 46
| [[Schlumberger|Schlumberger Technologies]]
| 500-749
|-
| 47
| [[Maniilaq]] Association
| 500-749
|-
| 48
| [[Carnival Corporation &amp; plc|Alaska Hotel Properties/Princess Hotels]]
| 500-749
|-
| 49
| [[Alyeska Resort]]&lt;br&gt;(includes O'Malley's on the Green)
| 500-749
|-
| 50
| [[Ocean Beauty Seafoods]]
| 250-499
|}

===Energy===
{{See also|Natural gas in Alaska|Energy law#Alaska law}}
[[File:Alaska Pipeline Closeup Underneath.jpg|thumb|right|upright|The [[Trans-Alaska Pipeline]] transports oil, Alaska's most financially important export, from the [[Alaska North Slope|North Slope]] to [[Valdez, Alaska|Valdez]]. Pertinent are the [[heat pipe]]s in the column mounts, which disperses heat upwards and prevents melting of [[permafrost]].]]
[[File:Alaska Crude Oil Reserves.PNG|thumb|right|Alaska oil reserves peaked in 1978 and have declined 60% thereafter.]]
[[File:Alaska Crude Oil Production.PNG|thumb|right|Alaska oil production peaked in 1988 and has declined 65% since.]]
Alaska has vast energy resources. Major oil and gas reserves are found in the [[Alaska North Slope]] (ANS) and Cook Inlet basins. According to the [[Energy Information Administration]], Alaska ranks second in the nation in crude oil production. Prudhoe Bay on Alaska's North Slope is the highest yielding oil field in the United States and on North America, typically producing about {{convert|400000|oilbbl/d|m3/d}}.

The [[Trans-Alaska Pipeline]] can transport and pump up to {{convert|2.1|Moilbbl|m3}} of crude oil per day, more than any other crude oil pipeline in the United States. Additionally, substantial coal deposits are found in Alaska's bituminous, sub-bituminous, and lignite coal basins.  The United States Geological Survey estimates that there are {{convert|85.4|Tcuft|km3}} of undiscovered, technically recoverable gas from natural gas hydrates on the Alaskan North Slope.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usgs.gov/corecast/details.asp?ep=74 |title=Gas Hydrates on Alaska's North Slope |publisher=Usgs.gov |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Alaska also offers some of the highest hydroelectric power potential in the country from its numerous rivers. Large swaths of the Alaskan coastline offer wind and geothermal energy potential as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/state/state_energy_profiles.cfm?sid=AK |title=EIA State Energy Profiles: Alaska |publisher=Tonto.eia.doe.gov |date=2009-08-27 |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alaska's economy depends heavily on increasingly expensive diesel fuel for heating, transportation, electric power and light. Though wind and hydroelectric power are abundant and underdeveloped, proposals for state-wide energy systems (e.g. with special [[single-wire earth return#Use in interties|low-cost electric interties]]) were judged uneconomical (at the time of the report, 2001) due to low (&lt;$0.50/Gal) fuel prices, long distances and low population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080216014031/http://www.dced.state.ak.us/dca/AEIS/PDF_Files/AIDEA_Energy_Screening.pdf |archivedate=2008-02-16 |url=http://www.dced.state.ak.us/dca/AEIS/PDF_Files/AIDEA_Energy_Screening.pdf |title=Screening Report for Alaska Rural Energy Plan |date=2001-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The cost of a US gallon of gas in urban Alaska today is usually $0.30–$0.60 higher than the national average; prices in rural areas are generally significantly higher but vary widely depending on transportation costs, seasonal usage peaks, nearby petroleum development infrastructure and many other factors.

Alaska accounts for one-fifth (20 percent){{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} of domestically produced United States oil production. Prudhoe Bay (North America's largest oil field) alone accounts for 8% of the U.S. domestic oil production.

====Permanent Fund====
The [[Alaska Permanent Fund]] is a constitutionally authorized appropriation of oil revenues, established by voters in 1976 to manage a surplus in state petroleum revenues from oil, largely in anticipation of same from the recently constructed [[Trans-Alaska Pipeline System]].  The fund was originally proposed by Governor [[Keith Harvey Miller|Keith Miller]] on the eve of the 1969 Prudhoe Bay lease sale, out of fear that the legislature would spend the entire proceeds of the sale (which amounted to $900&amp;nbsp;million (US)) at once, and was later championed by Governor [[Jay Hammond]] and [[Kenai, Alaska|Kenai]] [[Alaska House of Representatives|state representative]] Hugh Malone.  It has served as an attractive political prospect ever since, diverting revenues which would normally be deposited into the general fund.

The [[Alaska Constitution]] was written so as to discourage dedicating state funds for a particular purpose.  The Permanent Fund has become the rare exception to this, mostly due to the political climate of distrust existing during the time of its creation.  From its initial principal of $734,000, the fund has grown to $40&amp;nbsp;billion as a result of oil royalties and capital investment programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apfc.org/ Alaska Permanent Fund Corporation]&lt;/ref&gt;  Most if not all the principal is invested conservatively outside Alaska.  This has led to frequent calls by Alaskan politicians for the Fund to make investments within Alaska, though such a stance has never really gained momentum.

Starting in 1982, dividends from the fund's annual growth have been paid out each year to eligible Alaskans, ranging from an initial $1,000.00 in 1982 (equal to three years' payout, as the distribution of payments was held up in a lawsuit over the distribution scheme) to $3,269.00 in 2008 (which included a one-time $1,200.00 &quot;Resource Rebate&quot;). Every year, the state legislature takes out 8 percent from the earnings, puts 3 percent back into the principal for inflation proofing, and the remaining 5 percent is distributed to all qualifying Alaskans. To qualify for the Permanent Fund Dividend, one must have lived in the state for a minimum of 12 months, maintain constant residency subject to allowable absences,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pfd.state.ak.us/dividendamounts/index.aspx |title=State of Alaska Permanent Fund Division |publisher=Pfd.state.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and not be subject to court judgments or criminal convictions which fall under various disqualifying classifications or may subject the payment amount to civil garnishment.

===Cost of living===
The cost of goods in Alaska has long been higher than in the contiguous 48 states. This has changed for the most part in Anchorage and to a lesser extent in Fairbanks, where the cost of living has dropped somewhat in the past five years. Federal government employees, particularly [[United States Postal Service]] (USPS) workers and active-duty military members, receive a Cost of Living Allowance usually set at 25% of base pay because, while the cost of living has gone down, it is still one of the highest in the country.

The introduction of [[big-box store]]s in Anchorage, Fairbanks, and Juneau also did much to lower prices.  [[Wal-Mart]] opened their first Anchorage store in 1993, and debuted in Fairbanks in 2004.  The company currently has locations covering most of the population centers of Alaska, including Juneau, Ketchikan and Kodiak.  However, rural Alaska suffers from extremely high prices for food and consumer goods, compared to the rest of the country due to the relatively limited transportation infrastructure. Many rural residents come into these cities and purchase food and goods in bulk from warehouse clubs like [[Costco]] and [[Sam's Club]]. Some have embraced the free shipping offers&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freeshipping.org/category/alaska-free-shipping-coupons/ FreeShipping.org] for examples of companies offering free shipping to Alaska&lt;/ref&gt; of some online retailers to purchase items much more cheaply than they could in their own communities, if they are available at all.

===Agriculture===
Due to the northern climate and steep terrain, relatively little farming occurs in Alaska. Most farms are in either the [[Matanuska Valley]], about {{convert|40|mi|km}} northeast of [[Anchorage]], or on the [[Kenai Peninsula]], about {{convert|60|mi|km}} southwest of Anchorage. The short 100-day growing season limits the crops that can be grown, but the long sunny summer days make for productive growing seasons. The primary crops are potatoes, carrots, lettuce, and cabbage.  The [[Delta Junction, Alaska|Delta Junction]] area, about {{convert|100|mi|km}} southeast of Fairbanks, also has a sizable concentration of farms, which mostly lie north and east of [[Fort Greely]].  This area was largely set aside and developed under a state program spearheaded by Hammond during his second term as governor.  Delta-area crops consist predominately of barley and hay.

Alaska, with no counties, also lacks county fairs.  However, a small assortment of state and local fairs (with the [[Alaska State Fair]] in [[Palmer, Alaska|Palmer]] the largest), are held mostly in the late summer.  The fairs are mostly located in communities with historic or current agricultural activity, and feature local farmers exhibiting produce in addition to more high-profile commercial activities such as carnival rides, concerts and food.  &quot;Alaska Grown&quot; is used as an agricultural slogan.

[[File:Pacific Halibut Fileting.JPG|thumb|left|upright|[[Halibut]] is important to the state's economy as both a commercial and sport-caught fish.]]
Alaska has an abundance of seafood, with the primary fisheries in the Bering Sea and the North Pacific, and seafood is one of the few food items that is often cheaper within the state than outside it.  Many Alaskans take advantage of salmon seasons to harvest portions of their household diet while fishing for subsistence, as well as sport.  This includes fish taken by hook, net or wheel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adfg.alaska.gov/index.cfm?adfg=fishingPersonalUse.main |title=Alaska Department of Fish and Game |publisher=Adfg.alaska.gov |accessdate=2011-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hunting for subsistence, primarily [[caribou]], [[moose]], and [[Dall sheep]] is still common in the state, particularly in remote [[Bush Alaska|Bush]] communities. An example of a traditional native food is [[Akutaq]], the Eskimo ice cream, which can consist of reindeer fat, seal oil, dried fish meat and local berries.

Alaska's reindeer herding is concentrated on [[Seward Peninsula]] where wild caribou can be prevented from mingling and migrating with the domesticated reindeer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reindeer.salrm.uaf.edu/about_reindeer/seward_peninsula.php |title=Reindeer Herding |publisher=Reindeer.salrm.uaf.edu |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most food in Alaska is transported into the state from [[Outside (Alaska)|&quot;Outside&quot;]], and shipping costs make food in the cities relatively expensive. In rural areas, subsistence hunting and gathering is an essential activity because imported food is prohibitively expensive. The cost of importing food to villages begins at 7¢ per pound (15¢/kg) and rises rapidly to 50¢ per pound ($1.10/kg) or more. The cost of delivering a {{convert|1|USgal|L}} of milk is about $3.50 in many villages where per capita income can be $20,000 or less. Fuel cost can exceed $8.00 per gallon.

==Transportation==
{{Main|Transportation in Alaska}}

===Roads===
[[File:Seward Highway.jpg|thumb|[[Sterling Highway]].]]
{{See also|List of Alaska Routes}}
Alaska has few road connections compared to the rest of the U.S. The state's road system covers a relatively small area of the state, linking the central population centers and the [[Alaska Highway]], the principal route out of the state through Canada. The state capital, Juneau, is not accessible by road, only a car ferry, which has spurred several debates over the decades about moving the capital to a city on the road system, or building a road connection from [[Haines, Alaska|Haines]]. The western part of Alaska has no road system connecting the communities with the rest of Alaska.

[[File:Susitnabridge.JPG|thumb|The [[Susitna River]] bridge on the [[Denali Highway]] is {{convert|1036|ft}} long.]]
One unique feature of the Alaska Highway system is the [[Anton Anderson Memorial Tunnel]], an active [[Alaska Railroad]] tunnel recently upgraded to provide a paved roadway link with the isolated community of [[Whittier, Alaska|Whittier]] on [[Prince William Sound]] to the [[Seward Highway]] about {{convert|50|mi|km}} southeast of Anchorage at [[Portage, Alaska|Portage]]. At {{convert|2.5|mi|km}} the tunnel was the longest road tunnel in North America until 2007.&lt;ref&gt;completion of the 3.5&amp;nbsp;mile (5.6&amp;nbsp;km) [[Interstate 93]] tunnel as part of the &quot;[[Big Dig (Boston, Massachusetts)|Big Dig]]&quot; project in Boston, Massachusetts.&lt;/ref&gt; The tunnel is the longest combination [[List of road-rail tunnels|road and rail tunnel]] in North America.

===Rail===
[[File:AlaskaRailroad.jpg|thumb|Alaska Railroad &quot;[[Glacier Discovery]]&quot; train.]]
Built around 1915, the [[Alaska Railroad]] (ARR) played a key role in the development of Alaska through the 20th century. It links north Pacific shipping through providing critical infrastructure with tracks that run from [[Seward, Alaska|Seward]] to [[Interior Alaska]] by way of [[South Central Alaska]], passing through Anchorage, [[Eklutna, Alaska|Eklutna]], Wasilla, [[Talkeetna, Alaska|Talkeetna]], [[Denali]], and Fairbanks, with spurs to [[Whittier, Alaska|Whittier]], [[Palmer, Alaska|Palmer]] and [[North Pole, Alaska|North Pole]]. The cities, towns, villages, and region served by ARR tracks are known statewide as &quot;The Railbelt&quot;. In recent years, the ever-improving paved highway system began to eclipse the railroad's importance in Alaska's economy.

The railroad, though famed for its summertime tour passenger service, played a vital role in Alaska's development, moving freight into Alaska while transporting natural resources southward (i.e., coal from the Usibelli coal mine near [[Healy, Alaska|Healy]] to Seward and gravel from the Matanuska Valley to Anchorage).

The Alaska Railroad was one of the last railroads in North America to use [[caboose]]s in regular service and still uses them on some gravel trains. It continues to offer one of the last [[Request stop|flag stop]] routes in the country. A stretch of about {{convert|60|mi|km|-1}} of track along an area north of Talkeetna remains inaccessible by road; the railroad provides the only transportation to rural homes and cabins in the area; until construction of the Parks Highway in the 1970s, the railroad provided the only land access to most of the region along its entire route.

In northern Southeast Alaska, the [[White Pass and Yukon Route]] also partly runs through the state from [[Skagway, Alaska|Skagway]] northwards into Canada (British Columbia and Yukon Territory), crossing the border at [[White Pass]] Summit. This line is now mainly used by tourists, often arriving by cruise liner at Skagway. It featured in the 1983 [[BBC]] television series [[Great Little Railways]].

The Alaska Rail network is not connected to Outside. In 2000, the U.S. Congress authorized $6&amp;nbsp;million to study the feasibility of a rail link between Alaska, Canada, and the lower 48.&lt;ref name=&quot;RailLink1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://communities.canada.com/vancouversun/blogs/powerplay/archive/2010/12/13/transporting-oil-across-b-c.aspx | title=Alaska Oil / BC Tar sands via rail | author=Barbara Yaffe | date=2011-01-02 | accessdate=2011-01-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RailLink2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSN2138860820070622| title= Economic study touts Alaska-Canada rail link| author=Allan Dowd   | date=2007-06-27 | accessdate=2011-01-02 |agency=Reuters  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RailLink3&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://alaskacanadarail.com/index.html| title=Alaska Canada Rail Link | author=AlaskaCanadaRail.org | date=2005-01-02 | accessdate=2011-01-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alaska Rail Marine]] provides [[car float]] service between [[Whittier, Alaska|Whittier]] and [[Seattle]].

===Marine transport===
Many cities, towns and villages in the state do not have road or highway access; the only modes of access involve travel by air, river, or the sea.
[[File:Tustumena, Alaska Marine Highway.jpg|right|thumb|The [[MV Tustumena|M/V ''Tustumena'']] (named after [[Tustumena Glacier]]) is one of the state's many ferries, providing service between the [[Kenai Peninsula]] and [[Kodiak Island]].]]
Alaska's well-developed state-owned ferry system (known as the [[Alaska Marine Highway]]) serves the cities of [[Southeast Alaska|southeast]], the Gulf Coast and the Alaska Peninsula. The ferries transport vehicles as well as passengers. The system also operates a ferry service from [[Bellingham, Washington]] and [[Prince Rupert, British Columbia]] in Canada through the [[Inside Passage]] to [[Skagway, Alaska|Skagway]]. The [[Inter-Island Ferry Authority]] also serves as an important marine link for many communities in the [[Prince of Wales Island (Alaska)|Prince of Wales Island]] region of Southeast and works in concert with the Alaska Marine Highway.

In recent years, cruise lines have created a summertime tourism market, mainly connecting the Pacific Northwest to Southeast Alaska and, to a lesser degree, towns along Alaska's gulf coast. The population of [[Ketchikan, Alaska|Ketchikan]] may rise by over 10,000 people on many days during the summer, as up to four large cruise ships at a time can dock, debarking thousands passengers.

===Air transport===
Cities not served by road, sea, or river can be reached only by air, foot, dogsled, or snowmachine accounting for Alaska's extremely well developed [[Alaskan Bush|bush]] air services—an Alaskan novelty. Anchorage itself, and to a lesser extent Fairbanks, are served by [[Ted Stevens Anchorage International Airport#Airlines and destinations|many major airlines]]. Because of limited highway access, air travel remains the most efficient form of transportation in and out of the state. Anchorage recently completed extensive remodeling and construction at [[Ted Stevens Anchorage International Airport]] to help accommodate the upsurge in tourism (in 2000–2001, the latest year for which data is available, 2.4&amp;nbsp;million total arrivals to Alaska were counted, 1.7&amp;nbsp;million by air travel; 1.4&amp;nbsp;million were visitors).&lt;ref&gt;State of Alaska Office of Economic Development. ''[http://www.commerce.state.ak.us/dca/toubus/pub/AVSPSummerArrival111402.pdf Alaska Visitor Arrivals and Profile-Summer 2001]''. November, 2002. Retrieved September 11, 2006. {{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;State of Alaska Office of Economic Development. ''[http://www.commerce.state.ak.us/oed/toubus/pub/AVSPWinterArrival111402.pdf Alaska Visitor Arrivals and Profile-Fall/Winter 2001]''. November, 2002. Retrieved September 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Alaska-737-4QB-YVR.jpg|thumb|left|[[Alaska Airlines]] [[Boeing 737]] airliner]]

Regular flights to most villages and towns within the state that are commercially viable are challenging to provide, so they are heavily subsidized by the federal government through the [[Essential Air Service]] program. [[Alaska Airlines]] is the only major airline offering in-state travel with jet service (sometimes in combination cargo and passenger [[Boeing 737]]-400s) from Anchorage and Fairbanks to regional hubs like [[Bethel, Alaska|Bethel]], [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]], [[Kotzebue, Alaska|Kotzebue]], [[Dillingham, Alaska|Dillingham]], [[Kodiak, Alaska|Kodiak]], and other larger communities as well as to major Southeast and Alaska Peninsula communities.

The bulk of remaining commercial flight offerings come from small regional commuter airlines such as [[Era Aviation]], [[PenAir]], and [[Frontier Flying Service]]. The smallest towns and villages must rely on scheduled or chartered bush flying services using general aviation aircraft such as the [[Cessna Caravan]], the most popular aircraft in use in the state. Much of this service can be attributed to the Alaska bypass mail program which subsidizes bulk mail delivery to Alaskan rural communities. The program requires 70% of that subsidy to go to carriers who offer passenger service to the communities.

Many communities have small air taxi services.  These operations originated from the demand for customized transport to remote areas.  Perhaps the most quintessentially Alaskan plane is the bush seaplane. The world's busiest seaplane base is [[Lake Hood Seaplane Base|Lake Hood]], located next to Ted Stevens Anchorage International Airport, where flights bound for remote villages without an airstrip carry passengers, cargo, and many items from stores and warehouse clubs. Alaska has the highest number of pilots per capita of any U.S. state: out of the estimated 663,661 residents, 8,550 are pilots, or about one in 78.&lt;ref&gt;Federal Aviation Administration. ''[http://www.faa.gov/data_research/aviation_data_statistics/civil_airmen_statistics/2005/ 2005 U.S. Civil Airman Statistics]''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other transport===
Another Alaskan transportation method is the [[dogsled]]. In modern times (that is, any time after the mid-late 1920s), dog [[mushing]] is more of a sport than a true means of transportation. Various races are held around the state, but the best known is the [[Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race]], a 1150-mile (1850&amp;nbsp;km) trail from Anchorage to Nome (although the distance varies from year to year, the official distance is set at {{convert|1049|mi|km}}). The race commemorates the famous [[1925 serum run to Nome]] in which mushers and dogs like [[Togo (dog)|Togo]] and [[Balto]] took much-needed medicine to the [[diphtheria]]-stricken community of [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]] when all other means of transportation had failed. Mushers from all over the world come to Anchorage each March to compete for cash, prizes, and prestige. The &quot;Serum Run&quot; is another sled dog race that more accurately follows the route of the famous 1925 relay, leaving from the community of [[Nenana, Alaska|Nenana]] (southwest of Fairbanks) to Nome.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.serumrun.org/ |title=Norman Vaughan Serum Run |publisher=United Nations  |date=2010-04-15 |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In areas not served by road or rail, primary transportation in summer is by [[all-terrain vehicle]] and in winter by [[snowmobile]] or &quot;snow machine,&quot; as it is commonly referred to in Alaska.

==Law and government==
{{Main|Government of Alaska}}

===State government===
[[File:Juneau, Alaska Downtown.jpg|thumb|The center of state government in [[Juneau]].  The large buildings in the background are, from left to right: the Court Plaza Building (colloquially known as the [[Spam (food)|&quot;Spam Can&quot;]]), the State Office Building (behind), the Alaska Office Building, the [[List of Justices of the Alaska Supreme Court|John H. Dimond]] State Courthouse, and the [[Alaska State Capitol]].  Many of the smaller buildings in the foreground are also occupied by state government agencies.]]
Like all other U.S. states, Alaska is governed as a republic, with three [[separation of powers|branches of government]]: an [[executive branch]] consisting of the [[Governor of Alaska]] and the other independently elected constitutional officers; a [[legislative branch]] consisting of the [[Alaska House of Representatives]] and [[Alaska Senate]]; and a [[judicial branch]] consisting of the [[Alaska Supreme Court]] and lower courts.

The state of Alaska employs approximately 15,000 employees statewide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dop.state.ak.us/employeeOrientation/introduction |title=State of Alaska |publisher=Dop.state.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Alaska Legislature]] consists of a 40-member [[Alaska House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] and a 20-member [[Alaska Senate|Senate]]. Senators serve four year terms and House members two. The [[Governor of Alaska]] serves four-year terms. The [[List of Lieutenant Governors of Alaska|lieutenant governor]] runs separately from the governor in the [[Primary election|primaries]], but during the general election, the nominee for governor and nominee for lieutenant governor run together on the same ticket.

Alaska's court system has four levels: the [[Alaska Supreme Court]], the court of appeals, the superior courts and the district courts.&lt;ref name=&quot;cts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.ak.us/courts/ctinfo.htm |title=About the Alaska Court System |publisher=State.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The superior and district courts are [[trial court]]s. Superior courts are courts of general jurisdiction, while district courts only hear certain types of cases, including misdemeanor criminal cases and civil cases valued up to $100,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;cts&quot;/&gt;  The Supreme Court and the Court Of Appeals are [[appellate court]]s. The Court Of Appeals is required to hear appeals from certain lower-court decisions, including those regarding criminal prosecutions, juvenile delinquency, and [[habeas corpus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cts&quot;/&gt; The Supreme Court hears civil appeals and may in its discretion hear criminal appeals.&lt;ref name=&quot;cts&quot;/&gt;

===State politics===
{{further|[[Political party strength in Alaska]], [[Alaska political corruption probe]]}}

Although Alaska entered&lt;!--&quot;entered&quot;?--&gt; the union as a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] state, since the early 1970s Alaska has been characterized as a [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-leaning state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://election.nationaljournal.com/states/ak.htm |title=National Journal Alaska State Profile |publisher=Election.nationaljournal.com |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Local political communities have often worked on issues related to land use development, fishing, tourism, and individual rights. [[Alaska Native]]s, while organized in and around their communities, have been active within the [[Alaska Native Regional Corporations|Native corporations]]. These have been given ownership over large tracts of land, which require stewardship.

Alaska is the only state in which possession of one ounce or less of marijuana in one's home is completely legal under state law, though the federal law remains in force.&lt;ref name=seattle_times&gt;{{cite news |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/localnews/2003118645_webpot10.html |title=Judge rules against Alaska marijuana law |accessdate=2008-05-22 |last=Volz |first=Matt |date=2006-07-11 |work=[[The Seattle Times]] |publisher=Frank A. Blethen}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The state has an independence movement favoring a vote on secession from the United States, with the [[Alaskan Independence Party]] labeled as one of &quot;the most significant state-level third parties operating in the 20th century&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Doughtery, J. (2001, February 25). Alaska party stumps for independence. World Net Daily. Retrieved from [http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=21840 A Free Press for a Free People]&lt;/ref&gt;

Six [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] and four [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] have served as governor of Alaska.  In addition, Republican Governor [[Walter Joseph Hickel|Wally Hickel]] was elected to the office for a second term in 1990 after leaving the Republican party and briefly joining the Alaskan Independence Party ticket just long enough to be reelected. He subsequently officially rejoined the Republican party in 1994.

===Taxes===
To finance state government operations, Alaska depends primarily on petroleum revenues and federal subsidies. This allows it to have the lowest individual tax burden in the United States,&lt;ref&gt;CNN Money (2005). &quot;How tax friendly is your state?&quot; Retrieved from [http://money.cnn.com/pf/features/lists/taxesbystate2005/index.html CNN website].&lt;/ref&gt; and be one of only five states with no state [[sales tax]], one of seven states that do not levy an individual [[income tax]], and one of two states that has neither. The Department of Revenue Tax Division&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tax.state.ak.us/ |title=Department of Revenue Tax Division |publisher=Tax.state.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  reports regularly on the state's revenue sources. The Department also issues an annual summary of its operations, including new state laws that directly affect the tax division.

While Alaska has no state sales tax, 89 municipalities collect a local sales tax, from 1–7.5%, typically 3–5%. Other local taxes levied include raw fish taxes, hotel, motel, and bed-and-breakfast 'bed' taxes, [[severance tax]]es, liquor and tobacco taxes, gaming (pull tabs) taxes, tire taxes and fuel transfer taxes. A part of the revenue collected from certain state taxes and license fees (such as petroleum, aviation motor fuel, telephone cooperative) is shared with municipalities in Alaska.

[[Fairbanks, Alaska|Fairbanks]] has one of the highest property taxes in the state as no sales or income taxes are assessed in the [[Fairbanks North Star Borough]] (FNSB). A sales tax for the FNSB has been voted on many times, but has yet to be approved, leading law makers to increase taxes dramatically on other goods such as liquor and tobacco.

In 2008 the [[Tax Foundation]] ranked Alaska as having the 4th most &quot;business friendly&quot; tax policy. More &quot;friendly&quot; states were [[Wyoming]], [[Nevada]], and [[South Dakota]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taxfoundation.org/research/topic/11.html |title=Educating Taxpayers Since 1937 |publisher=The Tax Foundation |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Federal politics===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  style=&quot;float:right; font-size:76%; margin:10px&quot;
|+ '''Presidential elections results'''
|- style=&quot;background:lightgrey;&quot;
! Year
! [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
! [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]]
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 2008|2008]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''59.49%''' ''192,631
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|37.83% ''122,485
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 2004|2004]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''61.07%''' ''190,889
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|35.52% ''111,025
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 2000|2000]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''58.62%''' ''167,398
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|27.67% ''79,004
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1996|1996]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''50.80%''' ''122,746
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|33.27% ''80,380
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1992|1992]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''39.46%''' ''102,000
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|30.29% '' ''78,294
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1988|1988]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''59.59%''' ''119,251
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|36.27% ''72,584
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1984|1984]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''66.65%''' ''138,377
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|29.87% ''62,007
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1980|1980]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''54.35%''' ''86,112
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|26.41% ''41,842
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1976|1976]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''57.90%''' ''71,555
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|35.65% ''44,058
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1972|1972]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''58.13%''' ''55,349
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|34.62% ''32,967
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1968|1968]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''45.28%''' ''37,600
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|42.65% ''35,411
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1964|1964]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|34.09% ''22,930
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|'''65.91%''' ''44,329
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1960|1960]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''50.94%''' ''30,953
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|49.06% ''29,809
|}

In presidential elections, the state's [[Electoral College (United States)|electoral college]] votes have been won by the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] nominee in every election since statehood, except for 1964. No state has voted for a Democratic presidential candidate fewer times. Alaska supported [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] nominee [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] in the landslide year of [[U.S. presidential election, 1964|1964]], and the [[U.S. presidential election, 1960|1960]] and [[U.S. presidential election, 1968|1968]] elections were close. Since [[U.S. presidential election, 1972|1972]], however, Republicans have carried the state by large margins. In [[U.S. presidential election, 2008|2008]], Republican [[John McCain]] defeated Democrat [[Barack Obama]] in Alaska, 59.49% to 37.83%.  McCain's running mate was [[Sarah Palin]], the state's governor and the first Alaskan on a major party ticket.

The [[The Bush (Alaska)|Alaska Bush]], central Juneau, midtown and downtown Anchorage, and the area surrounding the [[University of Alaska Fairbanks]] campus have been strongholds of the Democratic Party. Matanuska-Susitna Borough and South Anchorage typically have the strongest Republican showing. As of 2004, well over half of all registered voters have chosen &quot;Non-Partisan&quot; or &quot;Undeclared&quot; as their affiliation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gov.state.ak.us/ltgov/elections/regbypty.htm|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080225223222/http://www.gov.state.ak.us/ltgov/elections/regbypty.htm|archivedate=2008-02-25 |title=State of Alaska |publisher=Gov.state.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite recent attempts to close primaries.

Because of its population relative to other U.S. states, Alaska has only one member in the [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. House of Representatives]]. This seat is currently being held by Republican [[Don Young]], who was re-elected to his 19th consecutive term in 2008.  [[Alaska's At-large congressional district]] is currently the world's second-largest legislative constituency by area, behind only the Canadian territory of [[Nunavut]].

In 2008, Governor [[Sarah Palin]] became the first Republican woman to run on a national ticket when she became [[John S. McCain|John McCain]]'s Vice Presidential running mate.  She continued to be a prominent national figure even after resigning from the governor's job in July 2009.

[[List of United States Senators from Alaska|Alaska's United States Senators]] belong to [[Classes of United States Senators|Class 2 and Class 3]].  In 2008, Democrat [[Mark Begich]], mayor of Anchorage, defeated long-time Republican senator [[Ted Stevens]]. Stevens had been convicted on seven felony counts of failing to report gifts on Senate financial discloser forms one week before the election. The conviction was set aside in April 2009 after evidence of prosecutorial misconduct emerged.

Republican [[Frank Murkowski]] held the state's other senatorial position. After being elected governor in 2002, he resigned from the Senate and appointed his daughter, State Representative [[Lisa Murkowski]] as his successor. She won a full six-year term in 2004 and 2010.

==Cities, towns and boroughs==
[[File:Anchorage1.jpg|thumb|[[Anchorage]], Alaska's largest city.]]
[[File:Fairbanks05.jpg|thumb|[[Fairbanks]].]]
[[File:Mount Juneau Alaska.jpg|thumb|Alaska's capital city, [[Juneau]].]]
[[File:USACE Homer Spit Alaska.jpg|thumb|The [[Homer Spit]] in Homer.]]
{{Clear left}}
{{See also|List of cities in Alaska by population|Alaska locations by per capita income}}
Alaska is not divided into [[County (United States)|counties]], as most of the other U.S. states, but it is divided into ''[[List of boroughs and census areas in Alaska|boroughs]]''. Many of the more densely populated parts of the state are part of Alaska's 16 boroughs, which function somewhat similarly to counties in other states. However, unlike county-equivalents in the other 49 states, the boroughs do not cover the entire land area of the state. The area not part of any borough is referred to as the [[Unorganized Borough, Alaska|Unorganized Borough]].

The Unorganized Borough has no government of its own, but the [[U.S. Census Bureau]] in cooperation with the state divided the Unorganized Borough into 11 [[census area]]s solely for the purposes of statistical analysis and presentation. A ''recording district'' is a mechanism for administration of the [[public record]] in Alaska. The state is divided into 34 recording districts which are centrally administered under a State [[recorder of deeds|Recorder]]. All recording districts use the same acceptance criteria, fee schedule, etc., for accepting documents into the public record.

Whereas many U.S. states use a three-tiered system of decentralization—state/county/township—most of Alaska uses only two tiers—state/borough. Owing to the low population density, most of the land is located in the [[Unorganized Borough]] which, as the name implies, has no intermediate borough government of its own, but is administered directly by the state government. Currently ([[United States Census, 2000|2000 census]]) 57.71% of Alaska's area has this status, with 13.05% of the population.

For statistical purposes the [[United States Census Bureau]] divides this territory into [[census area]]s. Anchorage merged the city government with the Greater Anchorage Area Borough in 1975 to form the Municipality of Anchorage, containing the city proper and the communities of Eagle River, Chugiak, Peters Creek, Girdwood, Bird, and Indian. Fairbanks has a separate borough (the [[Fairbanks North Star Borough]]) and municipality (the City of Fairbanks).

The state's most populous city is [[Anchorage, Alaska|Anchorage]], home to 278,700 people in 2006, 225,744 of whom live in the urbanized area. The richest [[Alaska locations by per capita income|location in Alaska by per capita income]] is [[Halibut Cove, Alaska|Halibut Cove]] ($89,895). [[Yakutat City]], Sitka, Juneau, and Anchorage are the four [[List of U.S. cities by area|largest cities in the U.S. by area]].

; Cities of 100,000 or more people
* [[Anchorage, Alaska|Anchorage]]

; Cities and [[census-designated place]]s of 10,000–100,000 people
* [[Fairbanks, Alaska|Fairbanks]]
* [[Juneau, Alaska|Juneau]] (State Capital)
* [[Knik-Fairview, Alaska|Knik-Fairview]]
* [[College, Alaska|College]]
; Cities and [[census-designated place]]s of 1,000–10,000 people
{{Col-begin|width=auto}}
{{Col-break}}
* [[Sitka, Alaska|Sitka]]
* [[Ketchikan, Alaska|Ketchikan]]
* [[Wasilla, Alaska|Wasilla]]
* [[Kenai, Alaska|Kenai]]
* [[Lakes, Alaska|Lakes]]
* [[Tanaina, Alaska|Tanaina]]
* [[Kalifornsky, Alaska|Kalifornsky]]
* [[Meadow Lakes, Alaska|Meadow Lakes]]
* Steele Creek
* [[Kodiak, Alaska|Kodiak]]
* [[Bethel, Alaska|Bethel]]
* [[Palmer, Alaska|Palmer]]
* [[Chena, Alaska|Chena Ridge]]
* [[Sterling, Alaska|Sterling]]
* [[Gateway, Alaska|Gateway]]
{{Col-break|width=50px}}
&amp;nbsp;
{{Col-break}}
* [[Homer, Alaska|Homer]]
* Farmers Loop
* [[Fishhook, Alaska|Fishhook]]
* [[Nikiski, Alaska|Nikiski]]
* [[Unalaska, Alaska|Unalaska]]
* [[Barrow, Alaska|Barrow]]
* [[Soldotna, Alaska|Soldotna]]
* [[Valdez, Alaska|Valdez]]
* [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]]
* Goldstream
* [[Big Lake, Alaska|Big Lake]]
* [[Butte, Alaska|Butte]]
* [[Kotzebue, Alaska|Kotzebue]]
* [[Petersburg, Alaska|Petersburg]]
* [[Seward, Alaska|Seward]]
{{Col-break|width=50px}}
&amp;nbsp;
{{Col-break}}
* [[Eielson AFB, Alaska|Eielson AFB]]
* [[Ester, Alaska|Ester]]
* [[Wrangell, Alaska|Wrangell]]
* [[Dillingham, Alaska|Dillingham]]
* [[Deltana, Alaska|Deltana]]
* [[Cordova, Alaska|Cordova]]
* [[Prudhoe Bay, Alaska|Prudhoe Bay]]
* [[North Pole, Alaska|North Pole]]
* [[Willow, Alaska|Willow]]
* [[Ridgeway, Alaska|Ridgeway]]
* [[Bear Creek, Alaska|Bear Creek]]
* [[Fritz Creek, Alaska|Fritz Creek]]
* [[Anchor Point, Alaska|Anchor Point]]
* [[Houston, Alaska|Houston]]
* [[Haines, Alaska|Haines]]
{{Col-break|width=50px}}
&amp;nbsp;
{{Col-break}}
* [[Lazy Mountain, Alaska|Lazy Mountain]]
* [[Sutton-Alpine, Alaska|Sutton-Alpine]]
* [[Metlakatla, Alaska|Metlakatla]]
* [[Cohoe, Alaska|Cohoe]]
* [[Kodiak Station, Alaska|Kodiak Station]]
* Susitna North
* [[Tok, Alaska|Tok]]
* [[Craig, Alaska|Craig]]
* [[Diamond Ridge, Alaska|Diamond Ridge]]
* [[Salcha, Alaska|Salcha]]
* [[Hooper Bay, Alaska|Hooper Bay]]
* [[Farm Loop, Alaska|Farm Loop]]
* [[Akutan, Alaska|Akutan]]
* [[Healy, Alaska|Healy]]
{{Col-end}}
; Smaller towns
: Alaska has many smaller towns, especially in the [[Alaska Bush]], which are generally inaccessible by road.

==Education==
[[File:Kachcampus.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Kachemak Bay]] campus of the [[University of Alaska Anchorage]].]]
The Alaska Department of Education and Early Development administers many [[List of school districts in Alaska|school districts]] in Alaska. In addition, the state operates a boarding school, [[Mt. Edgecumbe High School]] in [[Sitka, Alaska|Sitka]]; and provides partial funding for other boarding schools, including [[Nenana Student Living Center]] in [[Nenana, Alaska|Nenana]] and The Galena Interior Learning Academy in [[Galena, Alaska|Galena]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alaskaice.org/material.php?matID=138 |title=Alaska ICE |publisher=Alaska ICE |accessdate=2010-06-02}}{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are more than a dozen [[List of colleges and universities in Alaska|colleges and universities in Alaska]]. Accredited universities in Alaska include the [[University of Alaska Anchorage]], [[University of Alaska Fairbanks]], [[University of Alaska Southeast]], and [[Alaska Pacific University]].&lt;ref&gt;These are the only three universities in the state ranked by [[US News and World Report]]. [http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/rankindex_brief.php]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Alaska Department of Labor and Workforce Development operates [http://avtec.labor.state.ak.us/ AVTEC, Alaska's Institute of Technology].  Campuses in Seward and Anchorage offer 1 week to 11 month training programs in areas as diverse as Information Technology, Welding, Nursing, and Mechanics.

Alaska has had a problem with a &quot;[[brain drain]]&quot;. Many of its young people, including most of the highest academic achievers, leave the state after high school graduation and do not return. The [[University of Alaska]] has attempted to combat this by offering partial four-year scholarships to the top 10% of Alaska high school graduates, via the Alaska Scholars Program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.alaska.edu/scholars/faq.xml#scholars_award |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080309023826/http://www.alaska.edu/scholars/faq.xml |archivedate=2008-03-09 |title=UA Scholars Program&amp;nbsp;– Frequently Asked Questions |accessdate=2009-12-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public health and public safety==
{{See also|Dentistry in rural Alaska}}
The [[Alaska State Troopers]] are Alaska's statewide police force. They have a long and storied history, but were not an official organization until 1941. Before the force was officially organized, law enforcement in Alaska was handled by various federal agencies. Larger towns usually have their own local police and some villages rely on &quot;Public Safety Officers&quot; who have police training but do not carry firearms. In much of the state, the troopers serve as the only police force available. In addition to enforcing traffic and criminal law, wildlife Troopers enforce hunting and fishing regulations. Due to the varied terrain and wide scope of the Troopers' duties, they employ a wide variety of land, air, and water patrol vehicles.

Many rural communities in Alaska are considered &quot;dry,&quot; having outlawed the importation of alcoholic beverages .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dps.state.ak.us/abc/restrictions.aspx |title=AK Dept. of Public Safety Alcoholic Beverage Control Board |publisher=Dps.state.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Suicide rates for rural residents are higher than urban.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hss.state.ak.us/suicideprevention/statistics_pages_sspc/AKsuiciderate_rural_urban_90-00.htm |title=State of Alaska |publisher=Hss.state.ak.us |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Domestic abuse]] and other violent crimes are also at high levels in the state; this is in part linked to alcohol abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://notes3.state.ak.us/pn/pubnotic.nsf/0/8dad412f35cf9ba1892574e30001c413/$FILE/JAG+supplemental+program+narrative.pdf |title=Alaska State Troopers FY 2008 Byrne Grant Application |format=PDF |accessdate=2010-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alaska also has the highest rate of sexual assault in the nation. The average age of sexually assaulted victims is 16 years old. In four out of five cases, the suspects were relatives, friends or acquaintances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2008-01-29-alaska-sexualassaults_N.htm |title=Rural Alaska steeped in sexual violence |work=USA Today |date= 2008-01-30|accessdate=2010-12-31 |first=Rachel |last=D'oro}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culture==
{{see also|List of artists and writers from Alaska}}
[[File:Iditarod Ceremonial start in Anchorage, Alaska.jpg|thumb|right|A dog team in the Iditarod race, arguably the most popular winter event in Alaska.]]
Some of Alaska's popular annual events are the [[Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race]] that starts in Anchorage and ends in Nome, World Ice Art Championships in Fairbanks, the Alaska Hummingbird Festival in [[Ketchikan, Alaska|Ketchikan]], the [[Sitka Whale Fest]], and the Stikine River Garnet Fest in [[Wrangell, Alaska|Wrangell]]. The [[Stikine River]] features the largest springtime concentration of [[American Bald Eagle]]s in the world.

The [[Alaska Native Heritage Center]] celebrates the rich heritage of Alaska's 11 cultural groups. Their purpose is to enhance self-esteem among Native people and to encourage cross-cultural exchanges among all people. The [[Alaska Native Arts Foundation]] promotes and markets Native art from all regions and cultures in the State, both on the internet; at its gallery in Anchorage, 500 West Sixth Avenue, and at the [http://www.alaskahouseny.org/index.aspx?ModuleID=1  Alaska House New York], 109 Mercer Street in SoHo.&lt;ref&gt;www.alaskanativearts.org&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
{{Main|Music of Alaska}}
Influences on music in Alaska include the traditional music of Alaska Natives as well as folk music brought by later immigrants from Russia and Europe. Prominent musicians from Alaska include singer [[Jewel (singer)|Jewel]], traditional Aleut flautist [[Mary Youngblood]], folk singer-songwriter [[Libby Roderick]], Christian music singer/songwriter [[Lincoln Brewster]], metal/post hardcore band [[36 Crazyfists]] and the groups [[Pamyua]] and [[Portugal. The Man]].

There are many established music festivals in Alaska, including the [[Alaska Folk Festival]], the [[Fairbanks Summer Arts Festival]], the [http://anchoragefolkfestival.org/ Anchorage Folk Festival], the [[Athabascan Old-Time Fiddling Festival]], the Sitka Jazz Festival, and the [[Sitka Summer Music Festival]]. The most prominent [[orchestra]] in Alaska is the [[Anchorage Symphony Orchestra]], though the [[Fairbanks Symphony Orchestra]] and [[Juneau Symphony]] are also notable. The [[Anchorage Opera]] is currently the state's only professional opera company, though there are several volunteer and semi-professional organizations in the state as well.

The official [[List of U.S. state songs|state song]] of Alaska is &quot;[[Alaska's Flag]]&quot;, which was adopted in 1955; it celebrates the [[flag of Alaska]].

===Movies filmed in Alaska===
{{see also|List of films set in Alaska}}
[[File:Bow bow.jpg|thumb|left|Films featuring Alaskan wolves usually employ domesticated  [[wolf-dog hybrid]]s to stand in for wild wolves.]]
Alaska's first independent picture all made on place was in the silent years.  ''[[The Chechahcos]]'' was produced by Alaskan businessman [[Austin E. Lathrop]] and filmed in and around Anchorage.  It was released in 1924 by the Alaska Moving Picture Corporation and was the only film the company made.

One of the most prominent movies filmed in Alaska is [[MGM]]'s ''[[Eskimo/Mala The Magnificent]]'', starring Alaska Native [[Ray Mala]].  In 1932 an expedition set out from [[MGM]]'s studios in Hollywood to Alaska to film what was then billed as &quot;The Biggest Picture Ever Made.&quot;  Upon arriving in Alaska, they set up &quot;Camp Hollywood&quot; in Northwest Alaska, where they lived during the duration of the filming.  [[Louis B. Mayer]] spared no expense in spite of the remote location, going so far as to hire the chef from the [[Roosevelt Hotel (Hollywood)|Hotel Roosevelt]] in Hollywood to prepare meals.  When ''Eskimo'' premiered at the [[Astor Theatre (New York)|Astor Theatre]] in New York City, the studio received the largest amount of feedback in its history to that point.  ''Eskimo'' was critically acclaimed and released worldwide; as a result, Mala became an international movie star. ''Eskimo'' won the first Oscar for [[Best Film Editing]] at the Academy Awards, and was also responsible for showcasing and preserving aspects of [[Inupiat people|Inupiat]] culture on film.

The 1983 Disney movie [[Never Cry Wolf (film)|''Never Cry Wolf'']] was at least partially shot in Alaska. The 1991 film [[White Fang (1991 film)|''White Fang'']], starring [[Ethan Hawke]], was filmed in and around Haines, Alaska. [[Steven Seagal]]'s 1994 ''[[On Deadly Ground]]'', starring [[Michael Caine]], was filmed in part at the [[Worthington Glacier]] near [[Valdez, Alaska|Valdez]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filminamerica.com/Movies/OnDeadlyGround/ |title=On Deadly Ground |publisher=Filminamerica.com |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1999 John Sayles film ''[[Limbo (film)|Limbo]]'', starring David Strathairn, Mary Elizabeth Mastrantonio, and Kris Kristofferson, was filmed in Juneau.

The psychological thriller ''[[Insomnia (2002 film)|Insomnia]]'', starring [[Al Pacino]] and [[Robin Williams]], was shot in Canada, but was set in Alaska. The 2007 horror feature ''[[30 Days of Night (film)|30 Days of Night]]'' is set in [[Barrow, Alaska|Barrow]], Alaska, but was filmed in New Zealand. Most films and television shows set in Alaska are not filmed there; for example, ''[[Northern Exposure]]'', set in the fictional town of Cicely, Alaska, was actually filmed in [[Roslyn, Washington]].

The 2007 film directed by Sean Penn, ''[[Into the Wild (film)|Into The Wild]]'', was partially filmed and set in Alaska. The film, which is based on the novel of the same name, follows the adventures of [[Christopher McCandless]], who died in a remote abandoned bus along the [[Stampede Trail]] west of [[Healy, Alaska|Healy]] in 1992.

==State symbols==
{{Main|State symbols of Alaska}}
* State Motto: North to the Future
* Nicknames: &quot;The Last Frontier&quot; or &quot;Land of the Midnight Sun&quot; or &quot;Seward's Icebox&quot;
* State bird: [[Willow Ptarmigan]], adopted by the Territorial Legislature in 1955. It is a small (15–17&amp;nbsp;inches) Arctic grouse that lives among willows and on open tundra and muskeg. Plumage is brown in summer, changing to white in winter. The Willow Ptarmigan is common in much of Alaska.
* State fish: [[King Salmon]], adopted 1962.
* State flower: wild/native [[Forget-me-not|Forget-Me-Not]], adopted by the Territorial Legislature in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090225094636/http://akcf.org/_pages/about_ACF/about_alaska/state_symbols.php |archivedate=2009-02-25 |url=http://www.akcf.org/_pages/about_ACF/about_alaska/state_symbols.php |title=Alaska Conservation Foundation&amp;nbsp;– State Symbols}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a perennial that is found throughout Alaska, from Hyder to the Arctic Coast, and west to the Aleutians.
[[File:2008-05-04 at 18-26-44-Forgetmenot-Flower.jpg|thumb|right|The Forget-me-not is the state's official flower and bears the same blue and gold as the state flag]]
* State fossil: [[Woolly Mammoth]], adopted 1986.
* State gem: [[nephrite|Jade]], adopted 1968.
* State insect: Four-spot skimmer [[dragonfly]], adopted 1995.
* State land mammal: [[Moose]], adopted 1998.
* State marine mammal: [[Bowhead Whale]], adopted 1983.
* State mineral: Gold, adopted 1968.
* State song: &quot;[[Alaska's Flag]]&quot;
* State sport: [[Mushing|Dog Mushing]], adopted 1972.
* State tree: [[Sitka Spruce]], adopted 1962.
* State dog:  [[Alaskan Malamute]], adopted 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ktuu.com/Global/story.asp?S=12473783 |title=It's official: Malamute now Alaska's state dog&amp;nbsp;– KTUU.com &amp;#124; Alaska's news and information source &amp;#124; |publisher=KTUU.com |date=2010-05-12 |accessdate=2010-06-02}}{{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* State soil: [[Tanana (soil)|Tanana]],&lt;ref&gt;[ftp://ftp-fc.sc.egov.usda.gov/NSSC/StateSoil_Profiles/ak_soil.pdf TANANA – ALASKA STATE SOIL] U.S. Department of Agriculture&lt;/ref&gt; adopted unknown.
{{clear}}

==See also==
{{satop|Geography|North America|Northern America|United States|Alaska|Arctic}}
*[[National Register of Historic Places listings in Alaska|List of National Register of Historic Places in Alaska]]
*[[List of people from Alaska]]
*[[List of places in Alaska]]
*[[U.S. state]]
{{clear}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Alaska}}
{{osmrelation|1116270}}
&lt;!-- Please do not add commercial links to this section—they will be removed, as per the external links policy. Thank you. --&gt;
* [http://www.dced.state.ak.us/dca/commdb/CF_COMDB.htm Alaska Community Database System]
* [http://vilda.alaska.edu/index.php Alaska's Digital Archives]
* [http://www.alcnet.org/projects/overview/alaska Alaska], project area of the [http://www.alcnet.org/ American Land Conservancy]
* [http://www.aitc.org/ Alaska Inter-Tribal Council]
* {{dmoz|Regional/North_America/United_States/Alaska}}
* [http://www.life.com/gallery/23236/big-beautiful-alaska#index/0 Big, Beautiful Alaska] – slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''

; U.S. Government
* [http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/state/state_energy_profiles.cfm?sid=AK Energy &amp; Environmental Data for Alaska]
* [http://www.usgs.gov/state/state.asp?State=AK USGS real-time, geographic, and other scientific resources of Alaska]
* [http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/02000.html US Census Bureau]
* [http://www.ers.usda.gov/statefacts/ak.htm Alaska State Facts]
* [http://eisenhower.archives.gov/Research/Digital_Documents/Alaska/Alaska.html Documents on Alaskan Statehood at the Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library]{{dead link|date=December 2011}}
* [http://eisenhower.archives.gov/Research/Subject_Guides/PDFs/Agriculture.pdf Guide to collections containing information on Alaskan statehood at the Eisenhower Presidential Library]{{dead link|date=December 2011}}

; State government
* [http://www.alaska.gov/ State of Alaska website]
* [http://wikis.ala.org/godort/index.php/Alaska Alaska State Databases]&amp;nbsp;– Annotated list of searchable databases produced by Alaska state agencies and compiled by the Government Documents Roundtable of the American Library Association.
* [http://www.dnr.state.ak.us/ssd/recoff/terminology.cfm Alaska Department of Natural Resources, Recorder's Office]
{{Coord|64|N|153|W|region:US-AK_type:adm1st_scale:10000000|display=title}}
{{Geographic location
|Centre    = {{flag|Alaska}}
|North     = {{flag|Russia}} &lt;br /&gt; Arctic Ocean
|Northeast = [[Beaufort Sea]]
|East      = {{flag|Canada}} &lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Yukon}}
|Southeast = {{flag|Canada}} &lt;br /&gt; {{flag|British Columbia}}
|South     = Pacific Ocean &lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Hawaii}}
|Southwest = [[Bering Sea]] &lt;br /&gt; Pacific Ocean &lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Japan}}
|West      = {{flag|Russia}} • [[Bering Strait]] &lt;br&gt; [[Chukotka Autonomous Okrug|Chukotka]]
|Northwest = [[Chuckchi Sea]]
}}
{{succession
|preceded = [[Arizona]]
|office = [[List of U.S. states by date of statehood]]
|years = Admitted on January 3, 1959 (49th)
|succeeded = Hawaii
}}
{{Template group
|title = &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:11pt;&quot;&gt;Articles Related to Alaska&lt;/span&gt; &lt;br /&gt; ''The Last Frontier''
|list =
{{Alaska|expanded}}
{{USPoliticalDivisions}}
{{United States topics}}
}}

[[Category:Alaska| ]]
[[Category:Arctic Ocean]]
[[Category:Exclaves in the United States]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1959]]
[[Category:States of the United States]]
[[Category:West Coast of the United States]]

[[af:Alaska]]
[[ang:Alaska]]
[[ar:ألاسكا]]
[[an:Alaska]]
[[arc:ܐܠܐܣܟܐ]]
[[frp:Alaska]]
[[ast:Alaska]]
[[gn:Alaska]]
[[az:Alyaska]]
[[bn:আলাস্কা]]
[[zh-min-nan:Alaska]]
[[be:Штат Аляска]]
[[be-x-old:Аляска (штат)]]
[[bh:अलास्का]]
[[bcl:Alaska]]
[[bi:Alaska]]
[[bs:Alaska]]
[[br:Alaska]]
[[bg:Аляска]]
[[ca:Alaska]]
[[cv:Аляска]]
[[ceb:Alaska]]
[[cs:Aljaška]]
[[co:Alaska]]
[[cy:Alaska]]
[[da:Alaska]]
[[de:Alaska]]
[[nv:Hakʼaz Dineʼé Bikéyah Hahoodzo]]
[[dsb:Alaska]]
[[et:Alaska]]
[[el:Αλάσκα]]
[[es:Alaska]]
[[eo:Alasko]]
[[eu:Alaska]]
[[fa:آلاسکا]]
[[hif:Alaska]]
[[fo:Alaska]]
[[fr:Alaska]]
[[fy:Alaska]]
[[ga:Alasca]]
[[gv:Alaska]]
[[gag:Alaska]]
[[gd:Alasca]]
[[gl:Alasca - Alaska]]
[[hak:Â-lâ-sṳ̂-kâ]]
[[xal:Аляск]]
[[ko:알래스카 주]]
[[haw:‘Ālaka]]
[[hy:Ալյասկա (նահանգ)]]
[[hi:अलास्का]]
[[hr:Aljaska]]
[[io:Alaska]]
[[ig:Àláskà]]
[[ilo:Alaska]]
[[bpy:আলাস্কা]]
[[id:Alaska]]
[[ia:Alaska]]
[[iu:ᐊᓛᓯᑲ]]
[[ik:Alaska]]
[[os:Аляскæ]]
[[is:Alaska]]
[[it:Alaska]]
[[he:אלסקה]]
[[jv:Alaska]]
[[kn:ಅಲಾಸ್ಕ]]
[[pam:Alaska]]
[[ka:ალასკა (შტატი)]]
[[kk:Аляска штаты]]
[[kw:Alaska]]
[[sw:Alaska]]
[[ht:Alaska]]
[[ku:Alaska]]
[[mrj:Аляска]]
[[lad:Alaska]]
[[la:Alasca]]
[[lv:Aļaska]]
[[lt:Aliaska]]
[[lij:Alaska]]
[[li:Alaska]]
[[lmo:Alaska]]
[[hu:Alaszka]]
[[mk:Алјаска]]
[[mg:Alaska]]
[[ml:അലാസ്ക]]
[[mi:Alaska]]
[[mr:अलास्का]]
[[arz:الاسكا]]
[[ms:Alaska]]
[[mn:Аляска]]
[[my:အလက်စကာပြည်နယ်]]
[[nah:Alaska]]
[[nl:Alaska]]
[[nds-nl:Alaska (stoat)]]
[[new:अलास्का]]
[[ja:アラスカ州]]
[[frr:Alaska]]
[[no:Alaska]]
[[nn:Alaska]]
[[oc:Alaska]]
[[uz:Alaska]]
[[pa:ਅਲਾਸਕਾ]]
[[pnb:الاسکا]]
[[pap:Alaska]]
[[pms:Alasca]]
[[nds:Alaska]]
[[pl:Alaska]]
[[pt:Alasca]]
[[ro:Alaska]]
[[rm:Alasca]]
[[qu:Alaska suyu]]
[[ru:Аляска]]
[[sah:Аляска]]
[[se:Alaska]]
[[sa:अलास्‍का]]
[[sco:Alaska]]
[[stq:Alaska]]
[[sq:Alaska]]
[[scn:Alaska]]
[[simple:Alaska]]
[[sk:Aljaška]]
[[sl:Aljaska]]
[[ckb:ئالاسکا]]
[[sr:Аљаска]]
[[sh:Aljaska]]
[[fi:Alaska]]
[[sv:Alaska]]
[[tl:Alaska]]
[[ta:அலாஸ்கா]]
[[tt:Аляска]]
[[te:అలాస్కా]]
[[th:รัฐอะแลสกา]]
[[tg:Аляска]]
[[tr:Alaska]]
[[udm:Аляска]]
[[uk:Аляска]]
[[ur:الاسکا]]
[[ug:Alyaska Shitati]]
[[vec:Ałasca]]
[[vi:Alaska]]
[[vo:Alaska]]
[[vls:Alaska]]
[[war:Alaska]]
[[wuu:阿拉斯加]]
[[yi:אלאסקע]]
[[yo:Alaska]]
[[zh-yue:阿拉斯加]]
[[diq:Alaska]]
[[bat-smg:Aliaska]]
[[zh:阿拉斯加州]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
