<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="624192" ns="0" title="St. Cloud State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name            =St. Cloud State University
|image           =[[Image:St. Cloud State University seal.svg|200px]]
|established     =1869
|type            =[[Public school (government funded)|Public]]
|endowment       =$21,000,000&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff           =845
|faculty         =904
|president       =Dr. Earl H. Potter III
|students        =17,231  (Fall 2011)
|undergrad       =15,536
|postgrad        =1,695
|doctoral        =
|city            =[[St. Cloud, Minnesota|St. Cloud]]
|state           =[[Minnesota]]
|country         =[[United States]]
|campus          =[[Urban area|Urban]]&lt;br/&gt; {{convert|100|acre|ha}} campus
|nickname        =[[St. Cloud State Huskies|Huskies]]
|mascot          =Blizzard
|colors          = [[Cardinal Red (color)|&lt;font color=#000000&gt;Cardinal Red&lt;/font&gt;]] and [[Black (color)|&lt;font color=#000000&gt;Black&lt;/font&gt;]]
&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:#C41E3A;width:50px;border:1px solid #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:#000000;width:50px;border:1px solid #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;
|athletics       =[[Northern Sun Intercollegiate Conference|NSIC]] ([[Division II (NCAA)|NCAA Division II]]) &lt;br&gt; Men's and women's [[College ice hockey|ice hockey]] [[Western Collegiate Hockey Association|WCHA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]]
|website         = http://stcloudstate.edu and http://m.stcloudstate.edu
|logo            =[[Image:St. Cloud State University wordmark.svg|225px]]
}}

'''St. Cloud State University''' is a four-year public university founded in 1869 on the banks of the [[Mississippi River]] in [[St. Cloud, Minnesota]], [[United States]]. The university is the largest member of the [[Minnesota State Colleges and Universities]] (MnSCU) system which is the largest single provider of higher education in the state of Minnesota.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mnscu.edu/about/index.html|title=About MnSCU|publisher=MnSCU|accessdate=2009-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;  With more than 18,000 students, St. Cloud State has Minnesota's second-highest university enrollment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enrollment jumps 4.5 percent&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/news/newsrelease/default.asp?storyID=29742/|title=Enrollment jumps 4.5 percent |publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2010-03-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  St. Cloud State has more than 100,000 alumni worldwide; Notable alumni include [[John Stumpf]], [[president]] and [[CEO]] of [[Wells Fargo &amp; Company]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.wellsfargo.com/about/corporate/executive_officers/stumpf|title=John Stumpf|publisher=Wells Fargo &amp; Company|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[James B. Bullard]], [[president]] and [[CEO]] of the [[Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stlouisfed.org/newsroom/press_kit/bios/bullard.cfm|title=James Bullard Bio|publisher=St. Louis FED|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

St. Cloud State University opened its doors to students in 1869, under the name '''Third State Normal School'''. The school consisted of one building, the Stearns House, a renovated hotel purchased by the state Legislature for $46,000. Classrooms were on the first floor, the &quot;model school&quot; was on second floor and a women's dormitory was housed on the third floor. The five-member faculty was headed by Principal Ira Moore. Of the 53 original students, 43 were women. In 1898, the school began offering a junior college curriculum.

In 1914, the school dropped its secondary education program entirely. The legislature authorized a name change in 1921, allowing the school to adopt the name '''St. Cloud State Teachers College''' (the word &quot;teachers&quot; was deleted in 1957). The first bachelor's degrees were awarded in 1925, with master's degree programs offered beginning in 1953.

In 1975, St. Cloud State became a university, comprising five colleges and a graduate school. The G.R. Herberger Business School is recognized as one of the top business colleges in the country and is one of only four in the state that is nationally accredited. Within the past decade, the College of Science and Engineering established and gained full accreditation for its Computer Engineering program. It is the only university in Minnesota that offers an ABET accredited Manufacturing Engineering Program. It also offers ABET accredited Electrical and Mechanical Engineering programs, along with Computer Science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abet.org/AccredProgramSearch/AccreditationSearch.aspx|title=Accredited Programs|publisher=ABET Inc.|accessdate=2010-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; St. Cloud State University's Master of Engineering Management is the only program in Minnesota that is certified by the American Society of Engineering Management (ASEM).

In 1987, men's hockey became an NCAA Division I program. Two years later the team moved into a new two-rink arena called the National Hockey Center. In 1998, the university added a women's hockey team at the Division I level. 

In 2010, the university teamed with the private sector to build a welcome center and student housing complex adjacent to campus. The university leases the Welcome Center and Coborn Plaza Apartments.

===Previous school names===
* St. Cloud Normal School 1869–1921
* St. Cloud State Teachers College 1921–1957
* St. Cloud State College 1957–1975
* St. Cloud State University 1975–present

==Academics==
The university was created as a [[Normal school]], then developed college-level programs for teachers. Today it offers more than 200 majors, minors and pre-professional programs in five academic colleges. The School of Graduate Studies offers more than 60 graduate programs and certificates leading to specialist, Master of Arts, Master of Business Administration, Master of Engineering Management, Master of Music, Master of Science degrees and an Ed.D. in Higher Education Administration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bulletin.stcloudstate.edu/ugb/programs.asp|title=Majors and Minors - Majors and Emphasis Areas |publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2008-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new graduate program of note is the master's in regulatory affairs &amp; services, one of five programs offering classes at the university's Twin Cities Graduate Center in Maple Grove, Minn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/news/scsunow/default.asp?pubID=1&amp;issueID=24104&amp;storyID=29077|title=Twin Cities Graduate Center |publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

St. Cloud State has about 20 education-abroad programs, including a year-around program at [[Alnwick Castle]] in northern [[England]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/studyabroad/programs/default.asp|title=Study Abroad: St. Cloud State University |publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges and schools===
St. Cloud State offers more than 200 undergraduate and more than 60 graduate programs of study through two colleges and six schools. The academic structure described below takes effect July 1, 2011.
&lt;center&gt;
{| style='border:1px solid #cccccc; background-color:#fefefe; padding:3px; margin:0px'
|
* [http://www.stcloudstate.edu/cose/ College of Science and Engineering]
* College of Liberal Arts
* [http://www.stcloudstate.edu/coe/ School of Education], [[NCATE]] accredited.
* School of Health and Human Services
* [http://www.stcloudstate.edu/hbs/ G.R. Herberger Business School], [[AACSB]] accredited.
* School of Computers, Engineering and Environment
* School of the Public Affairs
* School of the Arts
| width='20' |
|}

&lt;/center&gt;

==Student life==
At the beginning of each academic year students are invited to &quot;Mainstreet,&quot; an event held on campus, to peruse student organizations and groups as well as those offered by the community.

===Residence Halls===
Nearly 20 percent of St. Cloud State students live in one of the eight traditional [[residence hall]]s or in an apartment-style hall on campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/studentlife/residence/on-campus.asp|title=On-campus Housing| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2010, as a part of Fifth Avenue Live, St. Cloud State opened the Coborn Plaza Apartments, a new residence hall that is capable of housing 455 students in high-amenity apartments with underground parking.

Traditional residence halls:
{{Columns-list|2|
* Benton Hall
* Hill-Case Hall
* W.W. Holes Hall
* Lawrence Hall
* Mitchell Hall
* Sherburne Hall
* Shoemaker Hall
* Stearns Hall
}}
Apartment-style residence halls:
* Stateview
* Coborn Plaza Apartments

===Student organizations===
St. Cloud State allows students to join an array of 250 student organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/studentlife/getinvolved/organizations.asp|title=SCSU Student Organizations| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Click on the following link to access a list of the organizations at St. Cloud State.
* [http://www.stcloudstate.edu/campusinvolvement/studentorganizations/ St. Cloud State Organizations]

===Greek life===

Students can also join one of the nine houses that represent the [[Fraternities and sororities|Greek population]] at St. Cloud State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/csold/greeks/|title=Greek Life|publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!colspan=1|Sororities
!colspan=2|Fraternities
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:small; padding:12px; margin:5px&quot; |
* [[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]]
* [[Delta Zeta]]
* Kappa Phi Omega
|valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;font-size:small; padding:12px; margin:5px&quot; |
* [[Acacia]]
* [[Delta Sigma Phi]]
* [[Phi Kappa Tau]]
* [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]
* [[Theta Chi]]
|}

===Student Media===
KVSC-FM is a public radio station licensed to St. Cloud State University. The station first started on May 10, 1967 and expanded  broadcasting times in September 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kvsc.org/milestones.php|title=KVSC| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The University Chronicle is the student newspaper and is published twice a week. It has been published since 1921.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.universitychronicle.com/|title=University Chronicle| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

University Television Station (UTVS) is a student-run television station, which airs live newscasts and other programming. The station is broadcast on [[Charter Communications]]' cable channel 21 in the greater St. Cloud area. Broadcasts of sporting events, including men's hockey, are also aired on other Charter franchises.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.utvs.com/21/about.asp|title=About UTVS| publisher=UTVS|accessdate=2010-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Student Media Awards====
In the spring of 2009, student-run media outlets received awards from five different competitions that garner national, regional, and state recognition. Husky Productions received the Global Media Award for College Sports &quot;Best Live Game or Live Event&quot; for its telecast of a November hockey game between Wisconsin and St. Cloud State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sportsvideo.org/main/blog/2009/06/09/global-media-awards-for-college-sports-announced-at-inaugural-college-sports-video-summit-2/|title=Global Media Awards for College Sports Announced at Inaugural College Sports Video Summit|publisher=Sports Video Group|accessdate=2009-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the Broadcast Educators Association Awards in Las Vegas, UTVS, Husky Mag, and Husky Productions received three out of the 17 awards recognized.  Husky Mag took first place in the studio competition, two students received first place in the music video category, and Husky Productions took second place in the studio production category.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.beaweb.org/staticcontent/staticpages/2009conv.htm|title=BEA 2009 Convention - Program|publisher=Broadcast Educators Association|accessdate=2009-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2009, KVSC-FM received four awards from the Minnesota Associated Press Broadcasters for work done in 2008.  The honorees were: Aaron Bjokrstrand's &quot;Rage Against Abuse&quot;, received Best in show; &quot;Husky Hockey Review&quot;, first in Sports Reporting; Jenna Wundrow's &quot;SCSU Recycling Program: Green or Guilt?&quot;; first in documentary/investigative; and Peter Tomala and Patrick Sullivan's &quot;Husky Sports Friday&quot;; honorable mention in sports reporting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kxmb.com/news/345639.asp|title=List of 2008 Minnesota AP Broadcast award winners|publisher=KXNet.com North Dakota News|accessdate=2009-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students with the University Chronicle received 11 Better Newspaper Contest awards for their work in 2008 from the Minnesota Newspaper Association; the University Chronicle received second place for its typography and design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mna.org/mna/1571-MNA.html|title=2007-2008 COLLEGE BNC WINNERS|publisher=Minnesota Newspaper Association|accessdate=2009-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Minnesota State University Student Association===
Each student attending St. Cloud State University pays a .43 cent per credit fee to fund the [[Minnesota State University Student Association]], a student-led non-profit that advocates on behalf of all Minnesota state university students.

==Athletics and Activities==
{{Main|St. Cloud State Huskies}}

The university currently sponsors 21 [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] teams and is a member of the [[Northern Sun Intercollegiate Conference]]. The St. Cloud State's men's and women's [[College ice hockey|ice hockey]] teams also compete in [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] as a member of the [[Western Collegiate Hockey Association|WCHA]] division. The mascot is the [[Husky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/athletics/|title=St. Cloud State Athletics |publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

St. Cloud State University provides free admission to all sports for students (including football and hockey).  This is possible through an athletic fee &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/athletics/tickets/StudentTicketPage.asp|title=Student Ticket Info|publisher=St. Cloud State University - Athletics|accessdate=2009-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The school operates a radio station, [[KVSC]] 88.1 [[FM band|FM]]. Students publish a [[newspaper]], the ''University Chronicle''. Students also run a television station known as UTVS, which recently won first place for best student news and productions from the [[Society of Professional Journalists]], as well as honorable mention at a New York competition in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/masscommunications/organizations/default.asp|title=Mass Communications - St. Cloud State|publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The school operates a theatre called Theatre L'homme Dieu. The theatre produces a ten-week season of plays and musicals each summer. The theatre employs professional actors, directors, and designers usually from the [[Twin Cities]] theatre community. The theatre also employs a resident intern company of twenty student apprentices. Most of the student apprentices are theatre majors from SCSU and other Midwestern universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/theatrefilmdance/theatre/lhommedieu.asp |title=Theatre L'Homme Dieu |accessdate=2009-11-01 |work=St. Cloud State University }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Events==
===Coborn Plaza opens in 2010===

Construction of a St. Cloud State welcome center and 455-student housing complex at Coborn Plaza was completed in August 2010. The welcome center and apartment-style housing are part of the first phase of Fifth Avenue Live, a private development adjacent to campus. Student apartments will be on the upper floors of the north and south buildings. Retail will be on the ground floor of the north building. The welcome center is slated for the ground floor of the south building. The university is leasing the apartments and welcome center from the J.A. Wedum Foundation.The two buildings combined are called Coborn Plaza in honor of the community contributions of the Coborn family, whose grocery chain formerly had a store on that site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/news/pressreleases/default.asp?storyID=29086&amp;SIimageID=7551|title=Fifth Avenue Live| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/news/newsrelease/default.asp?storyID=30733|title=Coborn Plaza| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2010-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twin Cities Graduate Center opens===

[[Image:Dex Building-MapleGrove-MN.jpg|thumb|left|The Twin Cities Graduate Center in Maple Grove, Minn., is located on the ground floor of the Dex Building near I-494 and Bass Lake Road.]]
In July 2009, St. Cloud State added a presence in the [[Minneapolis]]/[[St. Paul]] [[metropolitan area]] with a graduate center in [[Maple Grove, MN]]. The Twin Cities Graduate Center uses the cohort instructional model of learning, in which small groups of student proceed through the program together. Classes from programs such as business administration, higher education administration, counseling and regulatory affairs and services are offered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/news/scsunow/default.asp?pubID=1&amp;issueID=24104&amp;storyID=29077|title=Twin Cities Graduate Center| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Riverview Renovated

===Lawrence Hall renovated===

After an extensive restoration project in 2002 and 2003, St. Cloud State reopened the doors to historic Lawrence Hall to host a cultural melting pot of international and American Students studying foreign languages. The hall was first built in 1895 housing women students and later housing men for a few years. After originally being touted as fireproof, the building burned beyond repair and a new Lawrence Hall was built in 1905. It once again served as housing until it was retired in 1974 with exception to the basement floor which was used to facilitate a Math Skills Center. The Math Skills Center was forced out of the hall in 1999 after the structure was deemed unfit. After being distinguished as a campus eyesore efforts began to start a restoration campaign of the hall with funding for the project coming from the state's Legislation's bonding bill in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/news/outlook/story.asp?storyID=11439&amp;issueID=7888|title=Lawrence Hall| publisher=St. Cloud State University|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hockey program to Division I===

In the 1986-1987 season, [[Herb Brooks]], the 1980 USA men's [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] hockey coach, became the coach of the Huskies and helped St. Cloud State hockey team achieve [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] status. He also helped lead efforts to build the [[National Hockey Center]]. A small street near the National Hockey Center was named for Brooks shortly after his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.herbbrooksfoundation.com/news.html|title=St. Cloud Street Honors Brooks |publisher=The Herb Brooks Foundation|accessdate=2008-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
*Van Nelson - 1968 Olympic Track and Field Athlete. 5k and 10k winner at the 1967 Pan American Games.
*[[Tyler Arnason]] - Professional hockey player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=1395|title=Tyler Arnason|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Todd Bouman]] - National Football League quarterback, [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/nfl/players/profile?playerId=1417|title=Todd Bouman|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Dick Bremer]] - [[Minnesota Twins]] television play-by-play&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://minnesota.twins.mlb.com/team/broadcasters.jsp?c_id=min|title=Broadcasters|publisher=Minnesota Twins|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[James B. Bullard]] - President and CEO of the [[Federal Reserve Bank of St Louis]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stlouisfed.org/newsroom/press_kit/bios/bullard.cfm|title=James Bullard, bio|publisher=Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Matt Cullen]] - Professional hockey player, Stanley Cup winner, [[Minnesota Wild]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=182|title=Matt Cullen|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jim Eisenreich]] - Former MLB outfielder/first baseman with [[Tourette syndrome]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tourettes.org/index.php?id=612|title=About Jim|publisher=Jim Eisenreich Foundation|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jeff Finger]] - Professional hockey player, [[American Hockey League|AHL]] [[Toronto Marlies]]
*[[Andrew Gordon (ice hockey)|Andrew Gordon]] - Professional hockey player with the Hershey Bears/Washington Capitals&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=3638|title=Adnrew Gordon|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mark Hartigan]] - Professional hockey player, [[HC CSKA Moscow]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=1427&amp;out|title=Mark Hartigan|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[John Hawkes (actor)|John Hawkes]] - Film and television actor &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0370035/|title=John Hawkes|publisher=Internet Movie Database|accessdate=2010-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Bret Hedican]] - Former professional hockey player, Olympian and Stanley Cup winner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php?pid=2224|title=Bret Hedican|publisher=Internet Hockey Database
|accessdate=2019-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lawrence Heinemi]] - Professional wrestler who competed as Lars Anderson
*[[Matt Hendricks]] - Professional hockey player, [[Washington Capitals]]
*[[Bonnie Henrickson]] - University of Kansas women's basketball head coach&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kuathletics.com/sports/w-baskbl/mtt/henrickson_bonnie00.html|title=Player Bio: Bonnie Henrickson|publisher=University of Kansas - Athletics|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jodi Huisentruit]] - Former television news anchor who went missing June 27, 1995
*[[Bruce Hyde (actor)|Bruce Hyde]] - An actor who played Lt. Kevin Reilly on two episodes of ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]''
*[[Jessica Kresa]] - [[Total Nonstop Action Wrestling|TNA]] professional wrestler known as [[ODB (wrestler)|ODB]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://womensprowrestling.blogspot.com/2007/12/odb-jessica-kresa.html|title=ODB/Jessica Kresa|publisher=Blogspot|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Leo Kottke]] - Fingerstyle acoustic guitar virtuoso with a four-decades long recording career
*[[Ryan Malone]] - Professional hockey player, [[Tampa Bay Lightning]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=2130|title=Ryan Malone|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Bob Motzko]] - Men's hockey head coach at St. Cloud State&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stcloudstate.edu/athletics/sports/hockey-mens/BobMotzko.asp|title=St. Cloud State's Men's Hockey|publisher=St. Cloud State University - Athletics|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Joe Motzko]] - Professional hockey player
*[[Harold J. Nevin, Jr.]], [[U.S. National Guard]] general
*[[Andreas Nödl]] - Professional hockey player, [[Philadelphia Flyers]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=5035&amp;out|title=Andreas Nodl|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mark Parrish]] - Professional hockey player, [[Buffalo Sabres]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=708&amp;out|title=Mark Parrish|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[John Stumpf]] - Chief executive officer of [[Wells Fargo &amp; Company]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.wellsfargo.com/about/corporate/executive_officers/stumpf|title=John G. Stumpf|publisher=Wells Fargo &amp; Company|accessdate=2009-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*David Swanson - former chief executive officer of R.H. Donnelley Publishing/Dex One (Dex Yellow Pages)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.forbes.com/forbes/2006/1002/030.html|title=A Different B.S.|last=Barrett|first=William P.|coauthors=Matthew Rand|date=2006-10-02|publisher=Forbes.com|accessdate=2008-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tim Vakoc|H. Timothy (&quot;Tim&quot;) Vakoc]] – the first U.S. military chaplain to die from wounds received in the Iraq War.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thecatholicspirit.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2035&amp;Itemid=27|title=Father Timothy Vakoc dies|publisher=The Catholic Spirit|accessdate=2010-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Steve Martinson]] - Retired professional hockey player, current professional hockey head coach (Chicago Express)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Martinson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Faculty and Staff==
*[[Herb Brooks]], former St. Cloud State and U.S. Olympic Men's hockey coach
*[[Bruce Hyde (actor)|Bruce Hyde]], original cast member of the American TV show Star Trek
*Christopher Lehman, author of history books on African Americans&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umass.edu/umpress/fall_07/lehman.htm|title=The Colored Cartoon by Christopher P. Lehman|publisher=University of Massachusetts Press|accessdate=2011-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Mary Wingerd, author and Minnesota historian&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://minnesota.publicradio.org/display/web/2010/07/27/midday1/|title=How the land of the Dakota and Ojibwe became the State of Minnesota|publisher=Minnesota Public Radio|accessdate=2011-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*John Harlander, designer of optical spectrometers used in near-space research&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uap-www.nrl.navy.mil/uap/7641/publications/AOarticle.pdf|title=SHIMMER: a spatial heterodyne spectrometer
for remote sensing of Earth’s middle atmosphere|publisher=Applied Optics|accessdate=2011-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Heiko Schoenfuss, expert on the effects of man-made contaminants in lakes and streams&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.startribune.com/sports/outdoors/36549344.html|title=What happens when minnows take a chill pill?|publisher=Minneapolis Star Tribune|accessdate=2011-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Presidents of St. Cloud State==
{{Columns-list|2|
*2007-present Earl H. Potter III
*2000-2007 Roy H. Saigo
*1999-2000 Suzanne R. Williams, Interim President
*1995-1999 Bruce F. Grube
*1992-1995 Robert O. Bess, Interim President
*1982-1992 Brendan J. McDonald
*1981-1982 Lowell R. Gillette, Interim President
*1971-1981 Charles J. Graham
*1965-1971 Robert H. Wick
*1952-1965 George F. Budd
*1947-1952 John W. Headley
*1943-1947 Dudley S. Brainard
*1927-1943 George A. Selke
*1916-1927 Joseph C. Brown
*1915-1916 Isabel Lawrence, Interim President
*1902-1915 Waite A. Shoemaker
*1895-1902 George R. Kleeberger
*1890-1895 Joseph Carhart
*1884-1890 Thomas J. Gray
*1881-1884 Jerome Allen
*1875-1881 David L. Kiehle
*1869-1875 Ira Moore
}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://stcloudstate.edu/ St. Cloud State website]
* [http://m.stcloudstate.edu/ St. Cloud State mobile website]
* [http://www.stcloudstate.edu/athletics/ Home of Husky Athletics]
* [http://www.herbergermba.com// MBA program at St. Cloud State]
* [http://www.universitychronicle.net/ University Chronicle, the student newspaper]
* [http://www.kvsc.org/ 88.1 FM KVSC, a student-run educational public radio station.]
* [http://www.utvs.com/ UTVS-TV, a student-run educational public television station.]
* [http://www.northernsun.org/ Northern Sun Intercollegiate Conference]
* [http://www.wcha.com/ Western Collegiate Hockey Association]

{{Colleges and universities in Minnesota}}
{{Minnesota State Colleges and Universities}}
{{Northern Sun Intercollegiate Conference}}
{{Western Collegiate Hockey Association}}

{{coord|45|33|14|N|94|10|13|W|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Saint Cloud State University}}
[[Category:St. Cloud State University|*]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Minnesota]]
[[Category:St. Cloud, Minnesota]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1869]]
[[Category:Education in Stearns County, Minnesota]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Stearns County, Minnesota]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Stearns County, Minnesota]]

[[de:St. Cloud State University]]
[[eo:Ŝtatuniversitato St. Cloud]]
[[ko:세인트 클라우드 주립 대학교]]
[[no:St. Cloud State University]]
[[simple:St. Cloud State University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
