<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6252744" ns="0" title="Gnome-screensaver"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase}}
{{Multiple issues
| weasel         = July 2008
| primarysources = July 2008
}}
{{Infobox Software
| name = gnome-screensaver
| logo = 
| screenshot = [[Image:Gnome-screensaver.png|300px]]
| caption = A screenshot of gnome-screensaver
| developer = GNOME developers
| latest release version = 2.30.0
| latest release date = {{release date and age|2010|03|30}}
| operating system = [[Cross-platform]]
| genre = [[Screensaver]]
| license = [[GNU General Public License|GPL]]
| website = [http://live.gnome.org/GnomeScreensaver/ live.gnome.org/GnomeScreensaver]
}}

'''gnome-screensaver''' is the [[GNOME]] project's official screen blanking and locking framework. On some GNOME-based [[Linux distribution]]s, it is used instead of the framework that is a part of [[XScreenSaver]]. 

On these systems, the screen savers themselves still come from the [[XScreenSaver]] collection. gnome-screensaver is just the user interface.

The gnome-screensaver interface is designed for improved integration with a GNOME desktop, including themeability, language support, and [[Human interface guidelines]]  compliance.

Compared to the front end included with XScreenSaver, gnome-screensaver has a simplified [[graphical user interface|interface]] but less customizability. For instance, users may not select which screensavers to select at random &amp;ndash; either only one is selected or the program randomly selects from the whole list. In addition, the inability to configure individual screensavers and the developers' response to this issue has been criticized by some users.&lt;ref&gt;http://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=316654&lt;/ref&gt; It also lacks a setting to control cycling through different screensavers.

In recognition that the situation had turned into an organizational deadlock,{{Fact|date=October 2011}} and that the controversy on such an apparently simple but highly visible issue was severely damaging the image of the whole GNOME project,{{Fact|date=October 2011}} the GNOME 3 version of gnome-screensaver has been drastically simplified, supporting only screen blanking but no graphical screen savers. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title=Giovanni Campagna on gnome-shell-list: What is the status of the screensaver in GNOME3?
  | date=2011-03-21
  | url=http://mail.gnome.org/archives/gnome-shell-list/2011-March/msg00340.html
  | accessdate=2011-10-09
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://live.gnome.org/GnomeScreensaver/ gnome-screensaver on GNOME Live!]
*[http://live.gnome.org/GnomeScreensaver/FrequentlyAskedQuestions Frequently Asked Questions]
*[http://www.jwz.org/xscreensaver/toolkits.html XScreenSaver: On Toolkit Dialogs]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gnome-Screensaver}}
[[Category:Screensavers]]


{{GNOME-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
