<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6262054" ns="0" title="Windows Messaging"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Software |
 name = Windows Messaging |
 screenshot = [[Image:Windows Messaging.png|250px]] |
 caption = Windows Messaging running on [[Windows NT 4.0]]. |
 developer = [[Microsoft]] |
 latest_release_version = 4.00.835.1374 (version 5.0) |
 latest_release_date = October 14, 1996 |
 operating_system = [[Microsoft Windows]] |
 genre = [[E-mail client]] |
 license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]] [[EULA]] |
 website = [http://microsoft.com/windows95/downloads/contents/WURecommended/S_WUCommunications/W95ExchUpdate Exchange update for Windows 95]
}}

'''Windows Messaging,''' initially called ''[[Microsoft Exchange Client|Microsoft Exchange]]'', is an [[e-mail client]] that was included with [[Windows 95]] (beginning with OSR2), [[Windows 98|98]] and [[Windows NT 4.0]].

In Windows 98, it is not installed by default, but available as a separate program in the setup CD.

==History==
Microsoft Exchange gained wider usage with the release of Windows 95, as this was the only e-mail client that came bundled with it. Exchange was included throughout later releases of Windows up until the initial release of Windows 98, which by then also included Outlook Express 4.0.
*In 1996, Microsoft Exchange was renamed Windows Messaging, because of Microsoft's release of another [[Microsoft Exchange Server|Exchange]] product, which was meant for servers.
*Windows Messaging had two branches of successors:
**In software bundled with Windows itself, these were [[Internet Mail and News]] in Windows 95 (and bundled with [[Internet Explorer 3]]), which was succeeded by Outlook Express 4.0 in Windows 98 (bundled with [[Internet Explorer 4|Internet Explorer 4.0]] in Windows 95) and throughout newer Windows systems. These did not use the .pst file type.
**[[Microsoft Outlook]] became the professional-grade and more direct successor of MS Exchange Client, which still uses the .pst file type.

==Microsoft Fax==
Microsoft Fax, also called [[Microsoft at Work]] Fax (AWF), is the fax component to provide Send-and-Receive Fax capability; sent and received faxes were stored in the same [[.pst]] file as other messages, first attempt of [[unified messaging]] by Microsoft; also the ability to act as [[fax server]]&lt;ref&gt;http://support.microsoft.com/kb/141292/EN-US/&lt;/ref&gt;, which is not available in later versions of Windows until [[Windows Vista]]

==Criticisms==
*Because Microsoft Outlook used the same basic Windows Messaging profile, account and e-mail settings ([[MAPI]]), MS Exchange users not familiar with it could have been led into thinking that Outlook created a double profile and that it made copies of all their mail while they were just checking to see what the new MS Outlook (ver. 97) looked like. This way some MS Exchange users could have unknowingly deleted all their e-mail that they perceived to be 'double', as MS Outlook did not have any front-end feature to notify users that it was actually using the same MS Exchange or Windows Messaging account.
*The original version lacks support of [[Internet mail]] ([[SMTP]] and [[POP3]] support). They are only available with the other-purchased [[Microsoft Plus!]] pack.&lt;!--AFAIK, the original version in Windows 95 had POP3 support--&gt;
*No support for International characters. Some e-mail that was sent with a non-ASCII or non-7/8-bit character set, was shown in the form of text attachments, which had to be saved and then read in a web browser, with the browser's text encoding set for a specified code page.
*HTML e-mail was shown in such a way that the message contained an *.ATT or *.htm attachment, which had to be saved and then viewed in a browser, as MS Exchange did not have support for HTML-formatted messages.
*In a similar fashion, e-mail that did not use traditional message formatting, was shown the same way: actual message content was delivered in the form of text attachments with the *.ATT extension, which could be opened through Notepad. These files were in turn saved in the active Temp directory and some sensitive e-mail could therefore have been made available for other users to see.

==See also==
*[[.pst]]
*[[Microsoft Internet Mail and News]]
*[[Outlook Express]]
*[[Microsoft Outlook]]
*[[Windows 95]] and [[Windows 98]]

==External links==
* [http://www.indiana.edu/~uits/telecom/messaging/whatexchange.html What is the Microsoft Exchange client?]

{{E-mail clients}}
{{Internet Explorer}}

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Internet Explorer add-ons]]
[[Category:Windows email clients]]
[[Category:Discontinued Microsoft software]]
[[Category:Windows 95]]
[[Category:Windows NT]]
[[Category:Windows 98]]
[[Category:Discontinued Windows components]]
[[Category:Fax]]
[[Category:Fax software]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
