<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="626692" ns="0" title="Star Fox (video game)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Super Nintendo video game|other uses, including other video games|Star Fox (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox video game
|title=Star Fox&lt;br&gt;Starwing
|image=[[Image:Star Fox SNES.jpg|250px|Star Fox]]
|caption=North American box art
|developer=[[Nintendo EAD]]&lt;br&gt;[[Argonaut Software]]
|publisher=Nintendo
|director=[[Katsuya Eguchi]]
|producer=[[Shigeru Miyamoto]]
|composer=Hajime Hirasawa
|series=''[[Star Fox (series)|Star Fox]]''
|platforms=[[Super Nintendo Entertainment System]]
|released={{vgrelease|JP=February 21, 1993|NA=March 1, 1993|EU=June 3, 1993}}
|genre=[[Rail shooter]]
|modes=[[Single-player]]
}}

{{nihongo|'''''Star Fox'''''|スターフォックス|Sutā Fokkusu}}, released as '''''Starwing''''' in [[Europe]] and [[Australia]] due to a [[Star Fox (1983 video game)|game of the same name]] and subsequent trademark issues in those regions, is the first game in the [[Star Fox (series)|''Star Fox'' series]] of [[console game|video games]]. It was released in the spring of [[1993 in video gaming|1993]] for the [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|SFC/SNES]]. It was the first [[3D computer graphics|three-dimensional]] Nintendo game, and it included the [[Super FX]] chip, a [[coprocessor]] used to accelerate graphics display, which became Nintendo's first game to use 3D polygon graphics. The complex display of three-dimensional models with [[Polygon (computer graphics)|polygons]] was still new and uncommon in console [[video game]]s, and the game was much-hyped as a result. ''Star Fox'' featured [[kemono]] character designs by Nintendo artist [[Takaya Imamura]], music composed by Hajime Hirasawa and obstacle course style gameplay. ''Star Fox'' was developed by [[Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development|Nintendo EAD]] with assistance by [[Argonaut Games|Argonaut Software]], and was published by [[Nintendo]].

The storyline involves [[Fox McCloud]] and the rest of the [[List of Star Fox characters#Star Fox Team|Star Fox team]], who must defend their homeworld of Corneria against the attacking forces of [[List of Star Fox characters#Andross|Andross]].&lt;ref name=&quot;booklet&quot;&gt;{{cite book | year=1993 | editor=Argonaut Software | title=Star Fox Instruction Booklet | pages=3, | publisher=Nintendo of America | id=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The game was very successful and started another one of Nintendo's major franchises, with an unreleased sequel, four sequels, and one remake released to this date.

==Gameplay==
''Star Fox'' is a [[rail shooter]] in a third-person and first-person [[3D computer graphics|3D]] perspective. The player must navigate Fox's spacecraft, an [[Star Fox (series)#Arwing|Arwing]], through environments while various enemies (spaceships, robots, creatures, etc.) attack him. Along the way various [[power-up]]s are placed in the stage to help the player. The player receives a score on each level based on how many enemies destroyed and how well the player has defended his/her teammates. At the end of each [[Level (computer and video games)|level]] there is a [[Boss (video games)|boss]] that the player must defeat before progressing to the next level.

''Star Fox'' possesses certain unique elements that differentiate it from the standard scrolling shooter. Most scrolling shooters force the player forward at a constant speed. While this is also true for ''Star Fox'', there are thrusters and retro-rockets on the Arwing that allow the player to temporarily speed up and slow down. These can be used to maneuver around enemy attacks and other obstacles.

The damage model is another difference. In the standard scrolling shooter, touching almost any object results in the immediate destruction of the player's craft. In ''Star Fox'', the Arwing has a certain amount of shield energy that represents how much damage can be absorbed before the destruction of the craft. The game also has a small degree of locational damage detection: If the ship's wings clip against obstacles or the ground too much, they will break off, adversely affecting the craft's handling and the ability to upgrade weapons.

&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:SNES Star Fox.png|right|thumb|200px|In-game screenshot from the first level, Corneria]] --&gt;
The difficulty in ''Star Fox'' is also set in a unique way. Most scrolling shooters, if they have selectable [[difficulty level]]s, allow the player to set the difficulty by choosing an option (e.g. &quot;Easy,&quot; &quot;Normal,&quot; and &quot;Hard&quot;) at the beginning of the game. This option usually affects variables such as the number of lives a player has, the number of enemies encountered in the game, the speed of enemies, and so on. In contrast, at the beginning of ''Star Fox'', the player is given a choice of one of three routes to take through the Lylat system. Each of these routes corresponds with a certain level of difficulty, but each route has its own series of unique levels. This gives ''Star Fox'' somewhat more [[replay value]] than other scrolling shooters that have a fixed series of levels each time the game is played. The three game paths all contain the planet Corneria (the first level) and Venom (the last level), but they each have different versions depending on the path taken.

In each level, the player is accompanied by three computer-controlled wingmen: [[List of Star Fox characters#Peppy Hare|Peppy Hare]], [[Slippy Toad]], and [[Falco Lombardi]]. At certain pre-scripted points, one will fly into the player's view, often either chasing an enemy or being chased and asking for assistance. Ignoring a wingman's pleas will result in him taking damage, or being shot down. They cannot be damaged by the player's own lasers (they will notice it nonetheless). Regardless of their survival, wingmen are not present during boss battles but rejoin the player before the next stage. A player may help his or her wingmen when they ask for assistance, as they will engage some of the enemies not destroyed by the player, and thereby make it easier to achieve maximum score in a given level. If a wingman gets shot down, he will not return for the rest of the game.

==Plot==
===Setting and characters===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Andross SNES.jpg|left|thumb|160px|Andross Face as seen from the last level, Venom]] --&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Andross SNES2.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Andross Cube as seen from the last level, Venom]] --&gt;
{{main|List of Star Fox characters}}
This game takes place in the Lylat system, a stellar system in the fictional ''Star Fox'' universe that is inhabited by [[wikt:anthropomorphic|anthropomorphic]] animal races (i.e. foxes, frogs, dogs, birds, rabbits, apes, etc.). It contains the planets Corneria and Venom, representing good and evil, respectively. One can visit many other planets, asteroid belts, space stations, etc. while going through the course of the game. Which path the player chooses affects what places they will encounter.

===Storyline===
A mad scientist named Doctor Andross, now known as [[List of Star Fox characters#Andross|Emperor Andross]], has fled to Planet Venom after being banished from Planet Corneria, and has now declared war on Corneria and unleashed an enormous army to wreak havoc on the Lylat system. [[List of Star Fox characters#General Pepper|General Pepper]], the commanding officer of Corneria's defense force, has decided to dispatch a prototype high-performance combat ship called &quot;Arwing.&quot; However, lacking in time to train pilots for the new crafts, he summons the elite mercenary unit Star Fox to defeat Andross. [[Fox McCloud]] is the leader of the team, and he is accompanied by his teammates [[Falco Lombardi]], [[List of Star Fox characters#Peppy Hare|Peppy Hare]], and [[Slippy Toad]].

==Development==
The game company [[Argonaut Games|Argonaut]] worked closely with Nintendo during the early years of the NES and SNES. They developed a prototype on the NES, initially codenamed &quot;NesGlider&quot;, which was inspired by their earlier 8-bit game ''[[Starglider]]'', and then ported this prototype to the SNES. Programmer [[Jez San]] told Nintendo that this was as good as it could get unless they were allowed to design custom hardware to make the SNES better at 3D. Nintendo assented to this, and San hired chip designers to make the [[Super FX]] chip, the first 3D graphics accelerator in a consumer product.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| author = [[Syd Bolton]]
| title = Interview with Jez San, OBE
| publisher = Armchair Empire
| url = http://www.armchairempire.com/Interviews/jez-san-interview.htm
| doi =
| accessdate = 2007-12-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://old.siggraph.org/publications/newsletter/v32n1/contributions/baum.html&lt;/ref&gt; The SuperFX was so much more powerful than the SNES's standard processor that they joked that the SNES was just a box to hold the chip.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title=Interview with Jez San
| publisher=arwinglanding.net
| url=http://www.arwinglanding.net/articles.php?page=writeups/jezsan
| accessdate=2007-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By late 1992, the main game design was done by [[Shigeru Miyamoto]] and [[Katsuya Eguchi]]. Characters were designed by [[Takaya Imamura]], and music was composed by Hajime Hirasawa.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Interview with Shigeru Miyamoto
| publisher = Nintendo Power
| url = http://www.miyamotoshrine.com/theman/interviews/0197.shtml
| accessdate = 2008-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Argonaut brought the idea of using space ships, and Nintendo suggested the &quot;arcade-style shooting&quot; element of the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Interview with Dylan Cuthbert | publisher=emulatorium.com |archiveurl=http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20090111030948/http://www.arwinglanding.net/articles.php?page=writeups/dylan |archivedate=2009-01-11 | accessdate=2007-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yoichi Yamada, a level designer for many Nintendo games, laid out and edited the Star Fox maps.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;/&gt;

Miyamoto stated that he wanted the Star Fox series to star animal characters since he was not interested in making a series with conventional science fiction stories with robots, monsters, and superheroes. In addition Miyamoto himself had been drawing animal characters for a long period, so he asked [[Takaya Imamura]] to make a game series with animal characters. Miyamoto decided to use a fox as a main characters since it reminded him of [[Fushimi Inari Taisha]], about a fifteen minute walk from the [[Nintendo]] corporate headquarters. Miyamoto explained that he had always planned to use the English word &quot;fox&quot; instead of the [[Japanese language|Japanese]] word {{nihongo|&quot;kitsune&quot;|キツネ}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iwataasks&quot;/&gt;

Imamura used [[Japanese folklore]] as an inspiration to add a pheasant and a hare as two other protagonists. Imamura populated the Cornerian army with dogs and the enemy army with monkeys, and made Pepper a dog and Andross a monkey, since there is a Japanese expression about fighting like dogs and monkeys. Imamura added a toad; the inspiration came from a staff member of [[EADS]] who used a toad as his personal mascot. Miyamoto created several puppets and photographed them to use as artwork for the cover of the ''Star Fox'' game; Miyamoto was a fan of English puppet dramas, such as ''[[Thunderbirds (TV series)| Thunderbirds]]'', so he wanted the game cover to feature puppets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iwataasks&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://iwataasks.nintendo.com/interviews/#/3ds/starfox/0/2 Fushimi Inari Taisha and Fox].&quot; Nintendo. Retrieved on August 17, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variant names==
While the game was released in Japan and North America as ''Star Fox'', in Europe the title was changed to &quot;Starwing&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GJBV9jWUZw8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Easter eggs==
{{unreferenced-section|date=June 2009}}
The game features two well-known [[Easter egg (media)|Easter eggs]], which take the player to secret levels. One such level, &quot;The Awesome Black Hole&quot;, can be accessed from the Asteroid Field on Course 1. The Black Hole, which General Pepper states is the place where Fox's father disappeared, consists of a &quot;warped space&quot; that loops over and over again. A spinning ring also appears periodically, allowing the player to escape. The player is then taken to a level (depending on which ring they fly through), and continues from that level's path.

The other Easter egg (found in the Asteroid Field on Course 3) takes the player &quot;Out of This Dimension&quot;. The player flies through a surreal area of space and shoots down [[paper plane]]s for a time. The &quot;boss&quot; of this level is a large slot machine with no life meter, and the boss's theme music includes excerpts from the Japanese folk song &quot;[[Yuki]]&quot;, the chorus from &quot;[[When the Saints Go Marching In]]&quot;, and &quot;[[American folk music|Lightly Row]]&quot;. Shooting parts of the machine (including its arm) cause its rollers to spin and then stop in various configurations. Configurations including an image of Andross cause it to flip over and launch a series of missiles and plasma-balls at the player, and one configuration launches large coins at the player instead (each one acts as a shield recharge).

Getting the winning configuration (three &quot;7&quot;s) &quot;defeats&quot; the slot machine, causing it to explode. The game's ending credits then appear on the screen, followed by the words &quot;THE END&quot; appearing with each letter turned or flipped in a random direction. Shooting a letter causes it to fly away momentarily and then come back in a different direction. The letter turns yellow when it is correctly aligned. If a letter is correct, an enemy may fly towards the letters, changing their position, thus reseting the sequence. When all letters are aligned correctly, the music changes briefly and then goes back to the slot-machine boss music, and the letters re-jumble themselves. Typically, it is easier just to reset the game console or lose all of one's lives and start over from the start. If the player allows their ship to be destroyed, they start over at the beginning of the level and repeat the whole sequence.

Although not an easter egg, the real voices (as opposed to the captioned language) of the Star Fox team can be heard at the end, and when a boss enemy enters the level (near the end).

In some space levels, destroying an enemy ship will sometimes display an enemy pilot ejecting. If the player intercepts the ejected pilot with their ship it earns them a continue.

==Competition version==
A promotional cartridge, '''''Super Star Fox Weekend (Official Competition)''''' (titled '''''Star Wing: Official Competition (Official Competition)''''' in Europe), was released as part of the game's marketing campaign in Europe and the US. It featured time-limited single player mode on modified stages, as well as an exclusive bonus level.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=IGN: Star Fox: Super Weekend (Official Competition Cartridge) | publisher=IGN | url=http://cheats.ign.com/objects/496/496296.html | accessdate=2006-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to IGN, ''&quot;The altered start-up screen displays 'Official Competition Cartridge'. Depending on the points scored, players could win a t-shirt, a jacket, or even trips to international destinations. An estimated 2000 cartridges were made.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;/&gt;

In the United States, the ''Super Star Fox Weekend'' was played by tens of thousands of competitors in malls across the country. Stores such as [[KB Toys]] and [[Suncoast Motion Picture Company|Suncoast Video]] (usually any store that carried Super Nintendo games participated) hosted the event. After the competition, a limited number of the Super Weekend cartridges were sold through the Nintendo Power magazine.

In the [[United Kingdom]], the competition was known as the ''Star Wing Challenge'' and was held in gaming shops across the country on May 29, 1993.

Nintendo Netherlands also held the ''Starwing'' competition at various game selling stores in early 1993. The winner of each day won a large ''Starwing'' poster. ''Starwing'' competition was also used during the Dutch Nintendo Championship in October 1993-1996.

==Reception and legacy==
{{clear}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%; float: right; text-align: center; margin-left: 1em;&quot;
|+'''Reviews and awards'''
!Publication
!Score
|-
| [[Allgame]]
| {{Rating|4.5|5}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Allgame&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Star Fox &gt; Overview| publisher=Allgame | url=http://allgame.com/cg/agg.dll?p=agg&amp;sql=1:2613 | accessdate=2006-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| ''[[Electronic Gaming Monthly|EGM]]''
| 8.75 of 10&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamerankings&quot;/&gt;
|-
| ''[[Famitsu]]''
| 34 of 40&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamestats&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=GameStats: Star Fox Articles | publisher=GameStats | url=http://www.gamestats.com/objects/007/007705/articles.html | accessdate=2006-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| ''[[Nintendo Power]]''
| 4.125 of 5&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamerankings&quot;/&gt;
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Compilations of multiple reviews
|-
| [[Game Rankings]]
| colspan=&quot;1&quot;|86 of 100 (based on 5 reviews)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamerankings&quot;/&gt;
|}

&lt;!-- As of August 2006, ''Star Fox'' has sold 2.99 million units worldwide (1.63 million in the US and 0.8 in Japan). (readd when a figure is found that is not from VGCharts, a site which relies on sales estimates and sales shipments --&gt;
At the time of the game's release, the use of filled, [[3D computer graphics|three-dimensional]] [[Polygon (computer graphics)|polygons]] in a console game was very unusual, beyond a handful of earlier titles, including [[Sega Genesis]] ports of [[Atari]]'s arcade driving game, ''[[Hard Drivin']]'', and their helicopter shooter, ''[[Steel Talons]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=News &amp; Features Team|date= June 27, 2006| title=Essential Games for the Animal Within | publisher=IGN | url=http://xbox360.ign.com/articles/746/746646p2.html | accessdate=2006-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Star Fox'' was awarded Best Shooter of 1993 by [[Electronic Gaming Monthly]].&lt;ref name=&quot;egmbuyersguide1994&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1994 |month= |title=Electronic Gaming Monthly's Buyer's Guide |journal= |volume= |issue= |pages= |id= |url= |accessdate=2009-01-09 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The game took the #115 spot on ''EGM''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s &quot;The Greatest 200 Videogames of Their Time&quot;, and 82nd best game made on a Nintendo System in ''[[Nintendo Power]]''{{'}}s Top 200 Games list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The Greatest 200 Videogames of Their Time from Electronic Gaming Monthly | publisher=EGM | url=http://egm.1up.com/do/feature?pager.offset=3&amp;cId=3147448 | accessdate=2006-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NP Top 200&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|date=February 2006| title=NP Top 200|periodical=Nintendo Power|volume=200|pages=58–66}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It also received a 34 out of 40 from ''[[Famitsu]]'' magazine, and a 4.125 out of 5 from ''[[Nintendo Power]]'' Magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamerankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Star Fox Reviews | publisher=GameRankings | url=http://www.gamerankings.com/htmlpages2/588690.asp?q=star%20fox | accessdate=2006-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Next Gen Magazine'' pointed out Star Fox as helping pioneer the use of 3-D video game graphics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Eric-Jon Rossel Waugh|date= June 27, 2006| title=The Ten Greatest Years In Gaming | publisher=Next Gen Magazine | url=http://www.next-gen.biz/features/ten-greatest-years-gaming | accessdate=2006-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game has been used as an example of how, even with a fully polygon design, the game was still very similar to older games in that there was a set path to travel through each level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Andre Segers|date= May 9, 2006| title=2D to 3D: A Tale of Two Dimensions | publisher=IGN | url=http://xbox360.ign.com/articles/786/786938p1.html | accessdate=2006-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other games in the series===
{{main|Star Fox (series)}}
Due to its success, ''Star Fox'' has become a Nintendo franchise, with five more games and numerous appearances by its characters in other Nintendo games such as ''[[Super Smash Bros. (series)|Super Smash Bros.]]'' series. Originally, a sequel titled ''[[Star Fox 2]]'' was in the works for the Super Nintendo, but it was never released, although according to programmer Dylan Cuthbert, the game was actually completely finished. Although ''Star Fox 2'' was never released, some of the ideas and gameplay were salvaged for [[1997 in video gaming|1997]]'s ''[[Star Fox 64]]'' (released throughout Europe under the title ''Lylat Wars'') for [[Nintendo 64]]. Eventually, a handful of ROM dumps of ''Star Fox 2'' at various stages of its development were leaked onto the internet, and a fan-made translation of ''Star Fox 2'' from Japanese to English was released in the form of a patch that could be applied to one of the ROM dumps.

In [[2002 in video gaming|2002]] ''Star Fox'' made the jump to the [[Nintendo GameCube]], with [[Rare (company)|Rare]]'s ''[[Star Fox Adventures]]''. ''Adventures'' was the first ''Star Fox'' game to incorporate an [[action RPG]] element, where the player took control of [[Fox McCloud]] on the world of Sauria which was also known as Dinosaur Planet. In [[2005 in video gaming|2005]] ''[[Star Fox: Assault]]'' was released for the GameCube, this time developed by [[Namco]]. It incorporates a [[third-person shooter]] aspect into the game, but also makes a return to its roots as a shooter that made the first two games of the series so popular. ''[[Star Fox Command]]'', released for the [[Nintendo DS]] in [[2006 in video gaming|2006]], marks the franchise's first game on a portable system, as well as its first foray into online gaming. It used many features from the unreleased ''[[Star Fox 2]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;command&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Nintendo DS Game of the Month: August 2006|author=Craig Harris|publisher = IGN.com | date = September 6, 2006|url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/731/731088p1.html| accessdate=2006-09-17|authorlink = Craig Harris (journalist)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although not a sequel, there is a ''Star Fox'' micro-game in ''[[WarioWare: Smooth Moves]]'' for the Wii complete with three stages where the player pilots the Arwing with his or her [[Wii Remote]] through Corneria, Sector X, and Titania. At the end of each level, the player fights [[R.O.B.]], who is armed with a large [[NES Zapper]]. In addition, the game's sound test features full versions of the stage themes as well as the boss theme.

During the game's release, Nintendo teamed up with [[Kellogg Company|Kellogg's]] and [[Nelsonic]] to develop and release a promotional ''Star Fox'' [[liquid crystal display|LCD]] game watch to those who bought a box of [[Corn Flakes]] and sent the order form to Kellogg's to receive the ''Star Fox'' game watch for free. In the game watch, there are four levels and the object is to fly towards the Attack Carrier and destroy it while dodging plasma balls and falling structures. The game watch also included a pair of [[earphone]]s and a headphone jack for listening to the game without disturbing anyone nearby due to the game watch missing a volume control.&lt;ref name = &quot;fjgamewatch&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.anthrofox.org/starfox/watch/index.html | title = F.J. McCloud's Star Fox Page - The Star Fox LCD game watch | publisher = F.J. McCloud's Star Fox Page | accessdate = 2009-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nelsonic later released it in stores in a different watch appearance.&lt;ref name = &quot;handheldmuseum&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.handheldmuseum.com/Nelsonic/StarFox.htm | title = Handheld Museum - Nelsonic Star Fox | publisher = Handheld Museum | accessdate = 2009-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portalbox|Nintendo|Video games}}
* [http://www.nintendo.co.jp/n02/shvc/fo/index.html Official Nintendo Japan ''Star Fox'' site]
* {{GameFAQs|id=588690|name=''Star Fox''}}
* [http://www.meanmachinesmag.co.uk/review/406/starfox.php Star Fox SNES review] from [[Mean Machines|Mean Machines Archive]]
* {{moby game|id=/snes/star-fox-|name=''Star Fox''}}
* {{imdb title|0304743|Star Fox}}

{{Star Fox series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Star Fox (Video Game)}}
[[Category:1993 video games]]
[[Category:Argonaut Games games]]
[[Category:Nintendo Entertainment Analysis and Development games]]
[[Category:Rail shooters]]
[[Category:Star Fox video games]]
[[Category:Super FX games]]
[[Category:Super Nintendo Entertainment System games]]
[[Category:Super Nintendo Entertainment System-only games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Shigeru Miyamoto games]]
[[Category:Video games featuring anthropomorphic characters]]

{{Link FA|fr}}

[[es:Star Fox]]
[[fr:Star Wing]]
[[ko:스타폭스]]
[[it:Star Fox]]
[[nl:Star Fox]]
[[ja:スターフォックス]]
[[pt:Star Fox (jogo eletrônico)]]
[[ru:Star Fox]]
[[fi:Starwing]]
[[sv:Starwing]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
