<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6332360" ns="0" title="MTV Latin America"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Expand Spanish|MTV Latinoamérica|topic=culture|date=March 2009}}

{{Infobox TV channel
| name              = MTV Latin America
| logofile          = MTV Logo 2010.png 
| logosize          =  
| logoalt           =
| logo2             =
| launch            = October 1, 1993
| closed date       =
| picture format    = [[480i]] ([[SDTV]])
| share             =
| share as of       =
| share source      =
| network           = 
| owner             = [[MTV Networks]] ([[Viacom]])
| slogan            =
| country           = 
| broadcast area    = [[Latin America]]
| headquarters      = [[Miami Beach, Florida]]
| former names      = MTV en Español
| replaced names    =
| replaced by names =
| sister names      = [[VH1 Latin America]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Nickelodeon (Latin America)]]
| timeshift names   =
| web               = http://www.mtvla.com
| terr serv 1       =
| terr chan 1       =
| sat serv 1        = [[Dish Network Mexico]]
| sat chan 1        = channel 250
| sat serv 2        = [[Directv]] Latin America
| sat chan 2        = channel 264
| cable serv 1      = Inter Venezuela
| cable chan 1      = channel 24 
| sat radio serv 1  =
| sat radio chan 1  =
| adsl serv 1       =
| adsl chan 1       =
| online serv 1     =
| online chan 1     =
}}

'''MTV Latin America''' (also known as '''MTV Latinoamérica''', '''MTV Latino''' or '''MTV Latin''') is a [[cable television]] specialty service aimed at residents in [[Hispanic America]]n countries. It was launched on October 1, 1993 as ''MTV en Español''. The channel is a Hispanic American version from [[MTV]]. The channel is property of [[MTV Networks Latin America]], a subsidiary of [[Viacom]].

MTV Latin America’s principal objective is to broadcast music videos as well as reality shows, series, and films, which may be directly or indirectly related to music. All programming is related in some way to youth culture. MTV Latin America’s programming focuses on certain musical genres, mainly pop, soft rock, [[Latin pop]], and hip hop. Each of these categories includes music in English and Spanish.

The service is headquartered in [[Miami Beach]]. MTV Latin America is distributed via satellite, cable, and other terrestrial distribution through of three different feeds in [[Argentina]], [[Colombia]] and [[Mexico]].

The channel has also their own versions of MTV reality shows like ''[[Room Raiders]]'' or [[Dismissed (TV series)|Dismissed]], but most of the time the bad words are not censored in Latin América Regions (specially during the [[Watershed (television)|watershed]] time). The first video shown was ''[[We are sudamerican rockers|We Are South American Rockers]]'' by the Chilean band [[Los Prisioneros]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.allmusic.com/cg/amg.dll Los Prisioneros], [[Allmusic]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
A few important events in the late 1980s led to the creation of MTV Latin America. Firstly, the program “MTV International” was created in 1988 and led by [[Daisy Fuentes]]. This weekly program was broadcast through Latin American and American channels and presented music videos from both regions. A second catalyst was the rise of the “Spanish Rock fever”, which included artists such as Argentinean rockers [[Miguel Mateos]] and [[Soda Stereo]]. Lastly, during these years the first-ever Spanish rock concert was put on by Miguel Mateos, which created excitement amongst Latino communities in the United States.

With the growing popularity of Latino artists, channel executives began to take notice and realized the increasing quality and popularity of music sung in Spanish. After considering the success of other international MTV channels, such as [[MTV Europe]] and [[MTV Brazil]], MTV Networks launched “MTV in Spanish” in October 1993. The channel had one signal to broadcast to all of Latin America. All programs were recorded and produced in Miami, FL where the studios were located. Daisy Fuentes became one of the first [[VJ (media personality)|VJ]]s for the channel.

As the channel began to experience growing popularity in the early part of 1995,&lt;ref name=&quot;Latinoamérica y negocios&quot;&gt;Medios y mercados de Latinoamérica, ''[http://www.zonalatina.com/Zldata115.htm Latinoamérica y negocios]'', Estados unidos, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; new shows were added to the program. For the first time, shows unrelated to music were broadcast, such as “Beavis and Butthead”. “MTV News” was added, a segment dedicated to news on celebrities, film, politics and social issues, usually combining subjective and objective commentary. Lastly, in this same year the show “Connection” was launched, the most popular show in the channel’s history, which has remained on air for a record length of time and boasts the largest audience of any program in the history of the channel.

Given the channel’s social and economic growth, in April 1996 “MTV in Spanish” was divided into two regional signals, “North”, covering Mexico, Central America, Colombia and Venezuela, and “South”, covering the rest of the region. This division was created in order to cater programming more closely to distinct audiences. As a result, in 1996 MTV became the number one music channel in Latin America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Latinoamérica y negocios&quot;/&gt; The channel also became one of the first US television brands to develop a website for Latin America audiences with the launch MTVLA.com in partnership with the Miami-based company [[Internet Marketing Consultants, Inc.]]

However, during the 1990s the channel began experiencing problems. The musical aspect of “MTV in Spanish” was disorganized and the channel was having trouble catering to distinct regional tastes. Executives decided to segment audiences by dividing the channel into three signals: “MTV Mexico”, “MTV Central” (Colombia) and “MTV Argentina”, with studios and regional offices located in capital cities of each country.

During this time, the channel began to show American MTV programs subtitled in Spanish. As well, in the year 2000, MTV created a new signal directed towards Chile, known as “MTV Southwest”, which repeated programming from MTV Mexico but adjusted to Chilean time. While at first MTV thought about repeating MTV Argentina’s programming for the Chilean signal because of the proximity of the countries, it was decided that considering cultural traits and the difference in accents between Chilean and Argentine Spanish, it would be more suitable to adapt Mexican programming for the Chilean signal. However, in 2004, MTV Southwest was cancelled due to the low number of viewers. Currently, three signals operate in Latin America: “MTV North”, covering Mexico, “MTV Central”, covering Colombia, Bolivia, Chile, Cuba, Ecuador, Peru, Venezuela, and Central American countries and “MTV South”, covering Argentina, Paraguay and Uruguay.

==Programming==
Although MTV’s objective is to broadcast music videos of popular artists, the channel also broadcasts reality shows and other series aimed at youth. While many shows produced and broadcast by the channel have generated controversy for their irreverence, they continue to be popular among their viewers. Such controversy surrounds shows such as “South Park”, for its liberal themes, vulgar language and obscenities. Although these controversial shows are broadcast at night, they are often repeated during daytime scheduling.

In the later part of 2009, MTV began to change. With the incorporation of new reality shows, music videos could now only be seen in the very early morning. The rest of programming was dedicated to American reality shows.

==Audience Demographics==
The majority of viewers are between the ages of 14 and 34. The average age of viewers is 18 years, with the majority of the audience being older.&lt;ref name=ref_duplicada_2&gt;LAMAC, ''[http://www.lamac.org/_es/mtv_1.php The Best Global Brands Study, Business Week , Financial Times &amp; Interbrand]'', Estados Unidos, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003 &amp; 2004&lt;/ref&gt; About 76% of viewers belong to the middle to upper class.&lt;ref&gt;TG1 Latina, ''[http://www.lamac.org/_es/mtv_2.php MTV viewed last 7 days]'', Estados Unidos, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; As well, the channel notes a large number of viewers are university students.&lt;ref&gt;LAMAC, ''[http://www.lamac.org/_es/mtv_2.php TGI Latinoamérica]'', Estados Unidos, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, according to a study conducted by [[TGI Latina]] in 2004, MTV Latin America’s audience is 57% male and 43% female.&lt;ref&gt;TG1 Latina, ''[http://www.lamac.org/_es/mtv_2.php TGI Latina 2004 Wave I+II]'', Estados Unidos, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social issues and MTV==
In addition to broadcasting core MTV programs, MTV Latin America has also produced other non-music-related programs that address social and cultural issues that impact Latin American youth. These programs address issues such as politics, sexually transmitted infections, the environment and sexuality. Some of these shows include:

* Speak out: We are 30 million – Mexican Elections of 2006 (a series promoting the participation of youth in the Presidential elections, and included interviews with each of the candidates)&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, R. (2006). [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/1043671651.html?dids=1043671651:1043671651&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=May+30%2C+2006&amp;author=Reed+Johnson&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=E.1&amp;desc=TELEVISION+%26+RADIO MTV's note to Mexico: Go vote]. Los Angeles Times. [2006]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Xpress (an award-winning documentary on the killing of women in Juarez City, Chihuahua, Mexico)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/spanish/News/fullstorynews.asp?NewsID=12170 Documental de UNICEF y MTV gana premio en Festival Mundial de Medios (Abril 14, 2008).] Centro de Noticias ONU [2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Staying Alive (a co-production with CNN covering the worldwide HIV/AIDS epidemic)

==Other projects==
In 2002, MTV Networks announced the first Latin American MTV Video Music Awards.  For the first three years, the awards were held in Miami. In 2006 and 2007 they were held in Mexico City. In 2008, the Awards were moved to Guadalajara, Mexico. In 2009, the show took place in various cities, including Bogotá, Buenos Aires, Mexico City and Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;EHUI!, ''[http://www.ehui.com/?c=4&amp;a=119976 Premios MTV se transmitirán desde varias ciudades de AL]'', México, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public Reception==
MTV Latin America, like other MTV channels around the world, has been one of the first television channels to receive criticisms, largely from their own viewers. While many criticisms apply to MTV as a whole, some criticisms apply specifically to MTV Latin America. One reason for these criticisms is that certain videos and reality shows on MTV Latin America are not censored.

One of the main criticisms against MTV Latin America is that it is merely a commercial channel, whose broadcasting of videos is based on only economic interests and not on audience requests. MTV has been accused of being excessively commercial and an advertising tool for major music corporations. MTV has undermined the importance of the music itself, replacing it with merely a visual esthetic. This creates a negative public image for MTV.&lt;ref&gt;Emol: El mercurio online, ''[http://www.emol.com/noticias/cultura_espectaculos/detalle/detallenoticias.asp?idnoticia=226475 Hace 25 años nació MTV, la revolución musical de la pantalla chica ]'', Chile, 28 de julio de 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

As well, MTV has recently been criticized for broadcasting too many reality shows, distancing itself from its original purpose, which was to broadcast musical programming.&lt;ref&gt;Fórmula tv, ''[http://www.formulatv.com/1,20060801,2552,1.html La cadena MTV cumplió 25 años de historia musical el 1 de agosto]'', España, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; MTV has argued that these shows include music from current artists in their soundtrack, such as Laguna Beach. This show in particular has caused great controversy among viewers as it offers content completely unrelated to music.

Another criticism against MTV is that the channel spreads and promotes inappropriate behaviour among youth, in both music videos and shows.&lt;ref&gt;Calabozo ''[http://calabozomutante.blogcindario.com/2006/05/00048-no-mires-mtv.html No mires MTV!?!?]'', España, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Some controversial content include sex, early pregnancy, general violence, use of drugs, daily drinking and smoking habits of celebrities and domestic violence.

A final criticism, exclusive to MTV Latin America, relates to the form in which titles are presented on the screen, which usually includes a variety of orthographical errors such as missing accents and use of exclamation and question marks. Critics argue that these errors do not aid in didactic learning for viewers, the majority of which are youth.&lt;ref&gt;De todo hay en la vida del ´señor... ''[http://slavetothepc.wordpress.com/2006/06/29/mtv-y-el-regaeton/ MTV Y EL REGAETON (O como se escriba…)]'', Valencia, Venezuela 29 de junio de 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

However, MTV Latin America has also made many positive achievements. Between 2005 and 2006, MTV broadcast a campaign entitled “Don’t Kill the Music”, which aimed to broadcast a message of awareness to youth about music in general.&lt;ref&gt;Inconciente Colectivo, ''[http://www.inconcientecolectivo.cl/articulos/170 MTV: Don´t Kill the Music]'', Chile, 12 de enero de 2006,&lt;/ref&gt; As well the channel has created various projects to help independent Hispanic bands and musical artists.

==Feeds==
MTV Latin America is divided in the following feeds depending on population, accent and morals:

===Argentina===
* [[Argentina]]
* [[Paraguay]]
* [[Uruguay]]

===Colombia (Central &amp; Caribbean)===
* [[Bolivia]]
* [[Chile]]
* [[Colombia]]
* [[Costa Rica]]
* [[Dominican Republic]]
* [[Ecuador]]
* [[El Salvador]]
* [[Guadeloupe]]
* [[Guatemala]]
* [[Honduras]]
* [[Nicaragua]]
* [[Panama]]
* [[Peru]]
* [[Trinidad &amp; Tobago]]
* [[Venezuela]]

===Mexico===
* [[Mexico]]

Shows currently airing in MTV Latin America include. Some shows are airing only in selected feeds:

==Reality and Animated Shows==
=== Airing===

*''[[16 and Pregnant]]'' (2009–present)
*''[[MTV Cribs]]'' (2003–present)
*''[[Made (TV series)|Made]]''
*''[[True Life]]'' 
*''[[South Park]]'' (2004–present, Previously aired on [[Locomotion (TV channel)|Locomotion]])
*''[[Happy Tree Friends]]''
*''[[Parental Control]]'' (2009–present)
*''[[The City (MTV series)|The City]]'' (2009–present)
*''[[The Hills]]'' (2006–present)
*''[[Drawn Together]]'' (translated in Spanish as ''La Casa de los Dibujos'') (2005–present)
*''[[Chris (Childerns TV)]] 1995 AND 2003-PRESENT For Childern
*''[[Pimp my Ride]]''
*''[[My Super Sweet 16|Super Dulces 16]]'' (2007–present)
*''[[Life of Ryan]]'' (2008–present)
*''[[My Life As Liz]]'' (2010-present)
*''[[Jersey Shore (TV series)|Jersey Shore ]]'' (2010-present)
*''[[Disaster Date]]'' (2009-present)
*''[[Paris Hilton's Dubai BFF|Paris Hilton's My New BFF in Dubai]]'' (begins early 2011) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.tvlatina.tv/articles/display/16592|title = MTV presentó novedades de programación para 2011 |publisher = tvlatina.tv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===No longer airing===
*''[[Pimp my Ride U.K]]''
*''[[Next (TV series)|Next]]'' (2006–2009)
*''[[That's Amoré]]'' (2009)
*''[[From G's to Gents]] (2009)
*''[[Making the Video]]''
*''[[Scarred]]'' (2009)
*''[[Wrestling Society X]]''
*''[[Punk'd]]''
*''[[Wanna Come In?]]''
*''[[Britney &amp; Kevin: Chaotic]]''
*''[[Roomraiders]]'' (translated in Spanish as ''Los Invadecuartos'')
*''[[Fur TV]]'' (translated in Spanish as ''TV de Ciertopelo'') (2009)
*''Rob &amp; Big''
*''[[Exiled (TV series)|Exiled]]'' (2009)
*''[[Scream Queens (TV series)|Scream Queens]]'' (2009)
*''[[My Super Sweet 16]]'' (2009)
*''[[The Real World]]'' (2009; This run is conformed by the Austin, Denver and Sydney seasons all aired as one hour episodes, Season like Back to New York, Chicago, Las Vegas, San Diego and Key West all aired after being screen in the U.S.)
*''[[A Shot at Love]]'' (2008–2009)
*''[[A Double Shot at Love]]'' (2009)
*''[[The X Effect]]''
*''[[Celebrity Deathmatch]]''
*''[[Run's House]]'' (2009)
*''[[MTV's Busted]]''
*''[[Paris Hilton's My New BFF]]'' : ''[[Paris Hilton's My New BFF (season 1)|Season 1]]'' (2009) &amp; ''[[Paris Hilton's My New BFF (season 2)|Season 2]]'' (2010)
*''[[Jackass (TV series)|Jackass]]''
*''[[The Andy Milonakis Show]]'' (2008–2009)
*''[[The Dudesons]]'' (2008–2009)
*''[[Ren &amp; Stimpy]]''
*''[[The Ashlee Simpson Show]]''
*''[[Viva la Bam]]''
*''[[Daddy's Girls]]''
*''[[Dismissed (TV series)|Dismissed]]''
*''[[Beavis &amp; Butt-head]]''
*''[[Tiara Girls]]''
*''[[Popetown]]'' (2007–2008)
*''[[Daria]]''
*''[[Degrassi: The Next Generation]]''
*''[[Instant Star]]'' (translated in Spanish as ''Estrella Instantánea'')
*''[[Striperella]]''
*''[[South of Nowhere]]'' (2007–2008)
*''[[Skins (TV series)|Skins]]'' (2009-2010)
*''[[Fist of Zen]]'' (2008–2010)
*''[[The Osbournes]]'' (Re-launched in January 2010)
*''[[The Inbetweeners]]'' (2010)
*''[[Blue Mountain State]]'' (2010)
*''[[Alejo &amp; Valentina|Alejo y Valentina]]'' (2004–2010)
*''[[Stankervision]]''
*''[[Nitro Circus]]'' (2009–2010)
*''Camp'd Out'' (2010)
*''[[Exposed (MTV series)|Exposed]]'' (2008–2010)
*''[[Newport Harbor: The Real Orange County|Newport Harbor]]'' (2010–present)
*''Pranked'' (2009–2010)
*''The Bedroom Diaries'' (2010)
*''[[Room 401]]'' (2009–present)
*''Becoming''
*''I Bet You Will''
*''Spy Groove''
*''Fanatic''
*''MTV Cine Pop'' (2009–2010)
* ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]'' (current airing on [[Nickelodeon (Latin America)|Nickelodeon]])

==Original Shows==

This shows although they're locally produced in Latin America they only last between 1 or 2 seasons. The only exception is ''Joystickeros'' which has lasted 5 seasons.

*''Rally MTV'' (lasted 1 season)
*''Quiero Mis Quinces'' (Latin American version of &quot;Super Sweet 16&quot;) (Lasted 2 seasons)
*''Los Invadecuartos'' (Latin American version of &quot;Roomraiders&quot;)
*''Rock Dinner'' (Lasted 2 seasons)
*''Joystickeros''
*''Dansin' Ropa''
*''Fan Van''
*''Infiltrados''
*''[[Niñas Mal]]'' (one season, re-airing)
* ''[[Popland]]''

'''Music Shows'''
*''[[MTV Live]]''
*''Videorama''
*''Videosomnia''
*''Asterisco''
*''Playlist''
*''Karaoqué''
*''Pixcelu''
*''Casi +''
*''Los 10 + pedidos''
*''Top 10''
*''El clic''
*''La Zona TV''
*''[[Taking the Stage]]''
*''[[MTV World Stage]]''
*''La Cresta''
*''El Bloque''
*''Contra''
*''2X1''
*''Top 20 MTV''
*''El 20''
*''MTV Decimo''

'''Award Shows'''
*[[Los Premios MTV Latinoamérica|Los Premios MTV]]

==See also==
* [[List of MTV VJs#es:MTV Latin America|List of MTV Latin America VJ's]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{MTV Networks Latin America}}
{{MTV Networks}}
{{Viacom}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mtv Latin America}}
[[Category:MTV Networks]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1993]]
[[Category:Spanish-language television stations]]

{{Link FA|es}}
[[de:MTV Lateinamerika]]
[[es:MTV Latinoamérica]]
[[pl:MTV Ameryka Łacińska]]
[[pt:MTV Latinoamérica]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
