<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="634099" ns="0" title="Della Reese"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-reorganize|date=December 2010}}
{{Copy edit|date=December 2010}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name                = Della Reese
| background          = solo_singer
| image                 = DellaReeseJuly09.jpg
| caption            = Reese in July 2009
| birth_name          = Delloreese Patricia Early
| Born                = {{Birth date and age|1931|07|06}}&lt;ref name=&quot;msn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Andrea LeVasseur|title=Della Reese: Biography|url=http://movies.msn.com/celebrities/celebrity-biography/della-reese|work=All Movie Guide|publisher=MSN|year=2009|accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| origin              = [[Detroit]], [[Michigan]], United States
| genre               = [[Gospel music|Gospel]], [[Pop music|pop]], [[jazz]], [[Rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]], [[traditional pop]]
| occupation          = [[Singer]], [[actress]], [[Ordination|minister]], [[game show]] [[panelist]]
| years_active        = 1953–present
| label               = [[Jubilee Records]] &lt;br&gt; [[RCA Records]]
| associated_acts     = [[Mahalia Jackson]] &lt;br&gt;[[Erskine Hawkins]]
| website                 = [http://www.dellareese.com/ www.DellaReese.com]
}}
'''Delloreese Patricia Early''', known professionally as '''Della Reese''' (born  July 6, 1931),&lt;ref name=&quot;msn&quot;/&gt; is an American [[actress]], [[singer]], [[game show]] [[panelist]] of the 1970s, one-time [[talk-show]] [[presenter|hostess]] and [[ordained minister]]. She started her career in the 1950s as a gospel, pop and [[jazz]] singer, scoring a hit with her 1959 single &quot;[[Don't You Know?]]&quot;.  In her four decades of acting, she  gained a new generation of fans in the 1990s, playing Tess, the leading role on the television show ''[[Touched by an Angel]].'' In the late 1960s, she hosted her own talk show, ''Della,'' which ran for 297 episodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=|title=''Della'' (1969)|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0063892|work=Internet Movie Database|year=2009|accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|subject=Colson Whitehead and Della Reese|interviewer=[[Tavis Smiley]]|title=|url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/video/flv/generic.html?s=tavi08s29c1q9d6|format=Video|program=[[The Tavis Smiley Show|''Tavis Smiley Late Night'']]|callsign=PBS|date=12 June 2009|accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In more recent times, she became an ordained [[New Thought]] minister in the Understanding Principles for Better Living Church in [[Los Angeles, California]].

==Early years==
Reese was born '''Delloreese Patricia Early''' in the historic [[Black Bottom, Detroit|Black Bottom]] neighborhood of [[Detroit, Michigan]] to [[African American]] steelworker, Richard Thaddeus Early, and Nellie Mitchelle, a [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] ([[Cherokee]]) cook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|title=Della Reese Biography|url=http://www.filmreference.com/film/64/Della-Reese.html|work=filmreference|year=2009|accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Hilary de Vries|title=Della Reese: Earning Her Wings|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/14/tv/cover-story-della-reese-earning-her-wings.html|work=The New York Times|date=14 June 1998|accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Delloreese's mother also had several older children, before her birth, all of whom did not live with her, hence, she was an only child.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography.com&quot;&gt;http://www.biography.com/&lt;/ref&gt; At only six years old, she began singing in [[Church building|church]]. From this experience, she became an avid [[Gospel music|gospel]] singer. As a young lady of the 1940s, on the weekends, she and her mother would go to the movies, independently, to watch the likes of: [[Joan Crawford]], [[Bette Davis]] and [[Lena Horne]], each of whom had portrayed glamourous lives on-screen. After each movie, she would act out the scenes taken from every single film. In 1944, she began her career directing the young people's choir, after she'd nurtured acting plus her obvious musical talent. She was often chosen on radio, as a regular singer.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography.com&quot;/&gt; At the age of thirteen, she was hired to sing with [[Mahalia Jackson]]'s gospel group. Upon entering [[Detroit, Michigan|Detroit]]'s popular [[Cass Technical High School]] (where she attended the same high with an unknown star, Edna Rae Gillooly, later known as: [[Ellen Burstyn]]). At Cass Tech, she was a brilliant, no-nonsense student. She also continued with her touring with Jackson. With higher grades, she was the first in her family to graduate from high school in 1947, at only 15.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography.com&quot;/&gt; Afterwards, she formed her own gospel group called the ''[[Meditation Singers]]''. However, due in part to the death of her mother, and her father's serious illness, Reese had to interrupt her schooling at [[Wayne State University]] to help support her family. Faithful to the memory of Deloreese's memory of her mother, she also moved out of her father's house, due to her feuding with her father, who had a new girlfriend. She then took on odd jobs such as truck driver, dental receptionist, even elevator operator, after 1949.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography.com&quot;/&gt;

Performing in clubs, Early soon realized that she had no choice but to shorten her name from '''Delloreese Early''' to '''Della Reese''', knowing that her birth name was too long for a club marquee.

==Musical career==
[[File:Della Reese Jubilee Records.jpg|thumb|130px|Reese in the 1950s.]]
Reese was discovered by the gospel singer [[Mahalia Jackson]], and big break came when she won a contest, which gave her a week to sing at Detroit's well-known and talked-about Flame Show Bar.  Reese remained there for eight weeks.  Although her roots were in [[gospel music]], she now was being exposed to and influenced by such great [[jazz]] artists as [[Ella Fitzgerald]], [[Sarah Vaughan]] and [[Billie Holiday]].  In 1953, she signed a recording contract with [[Jubilee Records]], for which she recorded six albums. Later that year, she also joined the [[Hawkins]] Orchestra. Her first recordings for Jubilee were songs such as &quot;[[In the Still of the Night (1937 song)]],&quot; &quot;[[I've Got My Love to Keep Me Warm]],&quot; and &quot;[[Time after Time (1947 song)]].&quot;  Although the EP did not enter the charts, it sold 500,000 copies, and the songs were later included on the 1959 album &quot;And That Reminds Me.&quot;

In 1957, Reese released a single called &quot;[[And That Reminds Me]].&quot; After years of performing, she gained chart success with this song.  It became a Top Twenty Pop hit and a million-seller record. That year, Reese was voted by ''[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]'', ''[[Cashbox (magazine)|Cashbox]]'', and various other magazines, as &quot;The Most Promising Singer.&quot;

In 1959, Reese moved to a [[RCA Records]], and released her first RCA single called &quot;[[Don't You Know?]],&quot; which was adapted from [[Puccini]]'s music for ''[[La Bohème]];'' specifically, the aria ''[[Musetta's Waltz]].'' It became her biggest hit to date, reaching the #2 spot on the Pop charts, and topping the [[Rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]] charts, which were then called the &quot;Black Singles Charts,&quot; that year. Eventually, the song came to be widely considered the signature song of her early career.

Reese received a Grammy nomination for her 1960 album, ''Della.'' and then released a successful follow-up single called &quot;Not One Minute More&quot; (#16), and she remained on the [[Billboard Hot 100]] chart with the songs &quot;And Now&quot; (#69), &quot;[[Someday (You'll Want Me to Want You)]]&quot; (#56) and &quot;The Most Beautiful Words&quot; (#67).

Reese recorded regularly throughout the 1960s, releasing singles and several albums.  Two of the most significant were ''[[The Classic Della]]'' (1962), and ''Waltz with Me, Della'' (1963), which broadened her fan base internationally. She recorded several jazz-focused albums including ''Della Reese Live'' (1966), ''On Strings of Blue'' (1967), and ''One of a Kind'' (1978). She also performed in [[Las Vegas, Nevada|Las Vegas]] for nine years, and toured across the country.

Reese continued to record albums in the following decades, receiving two more Grammy nominations in the gospel category for the album ''Della Reese and Brilliance'' (1991), and for the live recorded album, ''My Soul Feels Better Right Now'' (1999).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | title=Music | url=http://www.dellareese.com/html/music.html | work=dellareese.com | year=2009 | accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Television career==
[[File:Della Reese 1977.JPG|thumb|200px|Reese did some commercial work for Kraft Foods in 1977.]]
In 1969, Reese began a transition into acting work which would eventually lead to her greatest fame.  Her first attempt at [[television]] stardom was a 1969 eponymously titled variety series, which was canceled after one season.

In 1970, Reese became the first black woman to guest host ''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson]].'' She appeared in several TV movies and miniseries, was a regular on ''[[Chico and the Man]],'' and she played the mother of [[B. A. Baracus]] in ''[[The A-Team]]'' episode &quot;Lease with an Option to Die.&quot; In 1991, she starred opposite [[Redd Foxx]] in his final sitcom, ''[[The Royal Family (TV series)|The Royal Family]],'' but his death halted production of the series for several months. Reese also did voice over for the animated series ''[[A Pup Named Scooby-Doo]].''

In 1989, she starred alongside [[Eddie Murphy]], [[Richard Pryor]], and [[Arsenio Hall]] in the theatrical release movie ''[[Harlem Nights]],'' in which she was seen doing a fight scene with [[Eddie Murphy]].

Reese appeared as a panelist on several episodes of the popular television game show ''[[Match Game]]'' and was featured on ''[[That's So Raven]]'' in The Four Aces. On May 18, 2009, she guest starred on the daytime drama ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'' as Virginia Hamilton.

====No-nonsense character actress====
Reese also had a wide variety of guest-starring roles, beginning with an episode of ''[[The Mod Squad]]''. This led to other roles such as: ''[[The Bold Ones: The New Doctors]]'', ''Getting Together'', ''[[Police Woman (TV series)|Police Woman]]'', ''[[Petrocelli]]'', ''Joe Forrester'', ''[[Police Story (TV series)|Police Story]]'', ''[[The Rookies]]'', ''[[McCloud (TV series)|McCloud]]'', ''[[Sanford and Son]]'' with old friend [[Redd Foxx]], ''[[Vega$]]'', ''[[Insight (TV series)|Insight]]'', 2 episodes of ''[[The Love Boat]]''.  She also had a recurring role on ''It Takes Two'' opposite [[Richard Crenna]] and [[Patty Duke]], 3 episodes of ''[[Crazy Like a Fox (TV series)|Crazy Like a Fox]]'', 4 episodes of ''[[Charlie &amp; Co.]]'' opposite [[Flip Wilson]], ''[[227 (TV series)|227]]'' with best friend [[Marla Gibbs]], ''[[MacGyver]]'', ''[[Night Court]]'', ''[[Dream On (TV series)|Dream On]]'', ''[[Designing Women]]'', ''[[Picket Fences]]''.  She also had a recurring role as Tess, on ''[[Promised Land]]'' with [[Wendy Phillips]] and [[Gerald McRaney]], among many others.

====''Touched by an Angel''====
After coping with the death of one of her best friends, Redd Foxx, in 1991, she was reluctant to have an older female lead in ''Touched by an Angel'', but went ahead and auditioned for Tess. She wanted to have a one-shot agreement between [[Columbia Broadcasting System|CBS]] and producer [[Martha Williamson]], but ordered more episodes. She portrayed the character of Tess on the inspirational television drama ''[[Touched by an Angel]].'' Reese was widely seen as a key component of the show's success.

Already starring on ''Touched by an Angel'' was an unfamiliar [[Irish people|Irish]] actress and future wife of [[reality television show]]s producer ([[Mark Burnett]]), [[Roma Downey]], who played the role of a case worker Tess's angel/employee, Monica. In numerous interviews, there was an on- and off-screen chemistry of both Reese &amp; Downey, as the two clicked as second mother and second daughter of any other 1990s TV series, when Reese was playing the boss whilst Downey played employee.

The character of Tess was the angelic supervisor who sent the other angels out on missions to help people redeem their lives and show them God's love, while at the same time, she was sassy, had no-nonsense, but always had an attitude. The show often featured a climactic monologue delivered by the angel Monica in which she reveals herself as an angel to a human with the words, &quot;I am an angel sent by God to tell you that he loves you.&quot; The character of Tess balanced the emotional tone of the show, and was portrayed by Reese as down to earth, experienced, and direct.

The series introduced Reese to a new young fan base, and added to her appeal with television viewers who remembered her earlier career highlights. Reese also sang the show's theme song, &quot;Walk With You&quot; and was featured prominently on the soundtrack album produced in conjunction with the show.

During its first season in 1994, many critics had been skeptical about the new drama, it being the second prime-time fantasy series (after ''[[Highway to Heaven]]'', being the first) that talked about [[God]]. The program featured kind-hearted angels who appeared on Earth, and helped guide people in their toughest moments. The show also had a rocky start, and was not a ratings winner, hence, they cancelled it after the first season with only 11 episodes, but with the help of die hard fans and massive letter-writing, the show resuscitated, the following season, and became a huge ratings winner for the next seven seasons. The same year, unfamiliar actor [[John Dye]] played Andrew. Though he was a handsome actor, there had been threats to the familiar TV star. At the beginning of the fourth season in 1997, unlike her co-stars making more money, Reese was offered a lesser salary, hence, she threatened to leave the ''Angel'' set. Angry about the imbalance of her paycheck, Reese fought with both [[CBS]] and Williamson, and she continued playing Tess until the end, having raised her salary.&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.biography.com&quot;&gt;http://www.biography.com&lt;/ref&gt;

During its final season in 2002, ''Touched by an Angel'' [[Columbia Broadcasting System|CBS]] decided to cancel the show after nine seasons and 212 episodes. Despite the show being cancelled, it continued re-running heavily into syndication and on [[The Hallmark Channel]].

Roma Downey said of her on- and off-screen relationship with Reese, who had adopted her as a daughter: &quot;She's very wise, she's very loving, she can be a little gruff at times. But she's always adoring and adorable. I lost my mother, when I was very young, and during my whole adolescence and into my twenties, I'd been looking for a mother figure, and I really think I can say with absolute truth and sincerity that I feel that I finally found her in Della Reese.&quot; The last thing Downey said about her TV boss/mother was that she could be as loving as her mentor's Jesus: &quot;I think I'll just always remember the feel of her neck against my cheek when she hugs me, and the love, I know that she has for me, and the love that I feel for her, and the love that she has for God. To know Della is to know that she loves God.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.biography.com&quot;/&gt;

==Personal life==
{{NewThought}}
Reese's mother, Nellie Mitchelle Early, died in 1949 of a cerebral hemorrhage.

Reese's father, Richard Early, died in 1959.

Reese had an adoptive daughter, Deloreese Daniels Owens, in 1961, who died on March 14, 2002, after complications stemming from [[pituitary disease]]. She said about the painful experience, sharing her frustration with the lack of awareness and knowledge of pituitary disorders, &quot;When it happened, I thought, 'It's such an odd thing to die from,' because pituitary problems aren't something you hear about. It makes it harder because you don't understand what happened. It seemed so strange and hard to explain. It still is, to be honest.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cushings-help.com/reese.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, after taping a guest spot for ''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson|The Tonight Show]],'' she suffered a nearly fatal brain [[aneurysm]], but made a full recovery after two operations  by neurosurgeon [[Charles George Drake|Dr. Charles Drake]] at [[University Hospital (London)|University Hospital]] in [[London, Ontario]].

In 1983, she married [[Franklin Thomas Lett, Jr.]], a [[concert]] producer and writer. 

In 2002, Reese announced on ''[[Larry King Live]]'' that she had been diagnosed with type-2 [[diabetes]]. She became a [[spokesman|spokeswoman]] for the [[American Diabetes Association]], traveling around the [[United States]] to raise awareness about this disorder.

In 2005, Reese was honored by [[Oprah Winfrey]] at her [[Legends Ball]] ceremony, along with 25 other women of [[African-American]] descent.

Reese was ordained as a [[Minister (Christianity)|minister]] in 2010, after serving as the senior minister and founder of the Understanding Principles for Better Living Church, an independent &quot;[[Christian]] New Thought&quot; congregation, which currently meets at First Lutheran Church (www.firsting.org) in [[Inglewood, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | title=Ministry | url=http://www.dellareese.com/html/minst.html | work=dellareese.com | year=2009 | accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In her ministerial work, she is known as the Rev. Dr. Della Reese Lett.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | title=Ministry: Biography | url=http://www.upchurch.org/index.php?page=home | publisher=Understanding Principles for Better Living Church | year=2009 | accessdate=2009-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
{{main|Della Reese discography}}

==Filmography==
{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 90%;&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
! Year
! Title
! Role
! Notes
|-
|1968
|''[[The Mod Squad]]''
|Rose
|Episode: &quot;Find Tara Chapman!&quot;
|-
|1970
|''[[The Bold Ones: The New Doctors]]''
|Grace Dayton
|Episode: &quot;Killer on the Loose&quot;
|-
|1971
|''[[Getting Together]]''
|
|Episode: &quot;Singing the Blues&quot;
|-
| rowspan=2|1973
|''Voyage of the Yes''
|Opal Parker
| rowspan=3|TV movies
|-
|''Daddy's Girl''
|Diane
|-
| rowspan=3|1974
|''Twice in a Lifetime''
|Flo
|-
|''[[Police Woman (TV series)|Police Woman]]''
|Tina Thompson
|Episode: &quot;Requiem for Bored Wives&quot;
|-
|''[[McCloud (TV series)|McCloud]]''
|Police Sgt. Gladys Harris
|Episode: &quot;This Must be the Alamo&quot;
|-
| rowspan=7|1975
|''[[Petrocelli]]''
|Angela Damon
|Episode: &quot;Once Upon a Victim&quot;
|-
|''Joe Forrester''
| rowspan=2|
| rowspan=2|Episode: &quot;The Return of Joe Forrester&quot;
|-
|''[[Police Story (TV series)|Police Story]]''
|-
|''Cop on the Beat''
|Claudine
|TV movie
|-
|''[[The Rookies]]''
|Landers
|Episode: &quot;Ladies Day&quot;
|-
|''Psychic Killer''
|Mrs. Gibson
|
|-
|''[[Chico and the Man]]''
|Della Rogers
|1975-1978 (27 episodes)
|-
| rowspan=4|1976
|''[[McCloud (TV series)|McCloud]]''
|Police Sgt. Gladys Harris
|Episode: &quot;The Day New York Turned Blue&quot;
|-
|''[[Medical Center (TV series)|Medical Center]]''
|Captain Sykes
|Episode: &quot;Major Annie, MD&quot;
|-
|''Flo's Place''
|Flo
| rowspan=2|TV movies
|-
|''Nightmare in Badham County''
|Sarah
|-
|1978
|''[[Vega$]]''
|Ernie
|Episode: &quot;Lost Women&quot;
|-
|1979
|''[[Welcome Back, Kotter]]''
|Mrs. Tremaine
|Episode: &quot;Come Back, Little Arnold&quot;&lt;Br&gt;Episode: &quot;The Gang Show&quot;
|-
|1980
|''[[Insight (TV series)|Insight]]''
|The Judge
|Episode: &quot;God in the Dock&quot;
|-
| rowspan=2|1982
|''[[The Love Boat]]''
|Millie Washington
|2 episodes
|-
| rowspan=2|''It Takes Two''
| rowspan=2|Judge Caroline Phillips
|Episode: &quot;Promises in the Dark&quot;
|-
|1983
|Episode: &quot;Looks Bad, Feels Good&quot;&lt;Br&gt;Episode: &quot;Rhythm Blues&quot;&lt;br&gt;Episode: &quot;Instinct&quot;
|-
| rowspan=2|1985
|''[[The A-Team]]''
|Mrs. Baracus
|Episode: &quot;Lease with an Option to Die&quot;
|-
| rowspan=2|''[[Crazy Like a Fox (TV series)|Crazy Like a Fox]]''
| rowspan=2|
|Episode: &quot;A Fox at the Races&quot;
|-
| rowspan=3|1986
|Episode: &quot;Fox Hunt&quot;&lt;br&gt;Episode: &quot;Is There a Fox in the House?&quot;
|-
|''[[Charlie &amp; Co.]]''
|Aunt Rachel
|4 episodes
|-
|''[[ABC Afterschool Specials]]''
|Aunt Faith
|Episode: &quot;The Gift of Amazing Grace&quot;
|-
|1987
|''[[227 (TV series)|227]]''
|Rita
|Episode: &quot;Far from the Tree&quot;
|-
|1988
|''[[A Pup Named Scooby-Doo]]''
|Additional Voices
|TV series
|-
| rowspan=2|1989
|''[[Night Court]]''
|Aunt Ruth
|Episode: &quot;Auntie Maim&quot;
|-
|''[[Harlem Nights]]''
|Vera
|
|-
| rowspan=4|1990
|''[[227 (TV series)|227]]''
|Grace
|Episode: &quot;Where Do We Go from Here?&quot;
|-
|''The Kid Who Loved Christmas''
|Alicia Slater
|TV movie
|-
|''[[The Young Riders]]''
|Stagecoach Sally
|Episode: &quot;Born to Hang&quot;
|-
| rowspan=2|''[[MacGyver]]''
| rowspan=2|Mama Colton
|Episode: &quot;Squeeze Play&quot;
|-
| rowspan=3|1991
|Episode: &quot;The Coltons&quot;
|-
|''[[Married People]]''
|
|Episode: &quot;Dance Ten, Friends Zero&quot;
|-
|''[[The Royal Family (TV series)|The Royal Family]]''
|Victoria Royal
|1991-1992 (15 episodes)
|-
| rowspan=2|1992
|''[[Dream On (TV series)|Dream On]]''
|Receptionist
|Episode: &quot;No Deposit, No Return&quot;
|-
|''[[The Distinguished Gentleman]]''
|Elevator Operator (uncredited)
|
|-
| rowspan=3|1993
|''[[Designing Women]]''
|Mrs. Toussant
|Episode: &quot;Wedding Redux&quot;
|-
|''[[L.A. Law]]''
|Lucille Lake
|Episode: &quot;Vindaloo in the Villows&quot;
|-
|''[[Picket Fences]]''
|Naomi Grand
|Episode: &quot;The Lullaby League&quot;
|-
|1994
|''[[Touched by an Angel]]''
| rowspan=2|Tess
|1994-2003 (212 episodes)
|-
| rowspan=2|1996
|''[[Promised Land (TV series)|Promised Land]]''
|1996-1998 (5 episodes)
|-
|''[[A Thin Line Between Love and Hate]]''
|Ma Wright
|
|-
| rowspan=3|1997
|''[[Happily Ever After: Fairy Tales for Every Child]]''
|The Blues Fairy
|Episode: &quot;Pinocchio&quot;
|-
|''[[A Match Made in Heaven]]''
|Katie Beale
| rowspan=8|TV movies
|-
|''Miracle in the Woods''
|Lilly Cooper
|-
| rowspan=2|1998
|''Emma's Wish''
|Mona Washburn
|-
|''[[Mama Flora's Family]]''
|Nana Fleming
|-
| rowspan=3|1999
|''Chasing Secrets''
|Honey
|-
|''Having Our Say: The Delany Sisters' First 100 Years''
|Martha Logan
|-
|''[[Anya's Bell]]''
|Anya Herpick
|-
| rowspan=2|2000
|''The Moving of Sophia Myles''
|Sophia Myles
|-
|''[[Dinosaur (film)|Dinosaur]]''
|Eema (voice)
|
|-
|2005
|''[[Beauty Shop]]''
|Mrs. Towner
|
|-
|2006
|''[[That's So Raven]]''
|Miss Rhonnie Wilcox
|Episode: &quot;The Four Aces&quot;
|-
|2007
|''[[If I Had Known I Was a Genius]]''
|Nana
|
|-
|2009
|''[[The Young and the Restless]]''
|Aunt Virginia
|2 episodes
|-
|2010
|''[[Expecting Mary]]''
|Doris Dorkus
|
|}

==Awards and nominations==
; Awards
* 1994: [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]]: [[Hollywood Boulevard|7060 Hollywood Boulevard]] – Television
* 1996: [[NAACP Image Award for Outstanding Actress in a Drama Series|Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series]] – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1997: Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1998: Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1999: Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 2000: Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 2001: Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 2002: Image Award for Outstanding Lead Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''

; Nominations
* 1960: Grammy Award – ''Don't You Know''
* 1961: Grammy Award – ''Della'' (Album)
* 1991: Grammy Award – ''Della Reese and Brilliance''
* 1997: [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actress – Drama Series|Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Drama Series]] – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1997: [[Screen Actors Guild Award for Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Drama Series]] – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1998: Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1998: [[Golden Globe Award for Best Supporting Actress – Series, Miniseries or Television Film|Golden Globe Award for Best Performance by an Actress in a Supporting Role in a Made for TV Series]] – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1998: Screen Actors Guild Award for Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Drama Series – ''Touched by an Angel''
* 1999: Grammy Award – ''My Soul Feels Better Right Now''
* 2000: [[Annie Award|Annie Award for Outstanding Individual Achievement for Voice Acting By a Female Performer in an Animated Feature]] – ''[[Dinosaur (film)|Dinosaur]]''

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.dellareese.com/ Della Reese Official Website]
* {{IMDb name|5343}}
* [http://www.emmytvlegends.org/interviews/people/della-reese Della Reese Interview] at [[Archive of American Television|The Archive of American Television]]
* [http://upchurch.org Understanding Principles for Better Living Church]
* [http://www.tvparty.com/mysdella.html Della Reese's Tough TV Career]
*[http://www.visionaryproject.com/reesedella Della Reese's oral history video excerpts] at The National Visionary Leadership Project

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Reese, Della
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =1931-07-06
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Reese, Della}}
[[Category:1931 births]]
[[Category:African American actors]]
[[Category:African American writers]]
[[Category:American Christians]]
[[Category:American evangelists]]
[[Category:American female singers]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American performers of Christian music]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:American television personalities]]
[[Category:American television talk show hosts]]
[[Category:American voice actors]]
[[Category:American people of Cherokee descent]]
[[Category:American people of Native American descent]]
[[Category:American singers of Native American descent]]
[[Category:California Democrats]]
[[Category:Cass Technical High School alumni]]
[[Category:Jubilee Records artists]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Michigan Democrats]]
[[Category:New Thought writers]]
[[Category:People from Detroit, Michigan]]
[[Category:RCA Victor artists]]
[[Category:Stroke survivors]]
[[Category:Traditional pop music singers]]
[[Category:Wayne State University alumni]]
[[Category:American jazz singers]]

[[de:Della Reese]]
[[es:Della Reese]]
[[fr:Della Reese]]
[[ko:델라 리즈]]
[[id:Della Reese]]
[[it:Della Reese]]
[[nl:Della Reese]]
[[pl:Della Reese]]
[[pt:Della Reese]]
[[ru:Делла Риз]]
[[sk:Della Reese]]
[[fi:Della Reese]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
