<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="637662" ns="0" title="Middle Tennessee State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox university
|name            =Middle Tennessee State University
|image           =[[Image:MTSU Wordmark.png|MTSU Wordmark]]
|coordinates       = {{coord|35.846222|-86.369279|display=inline,title|type:edu}}
|motto           =Agriculture and Commerce
|established     =September 11, 1911
|type            =[[Public university]]
|endowment       = $48.2 million (2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;endowment&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf |title=U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009 |work=NACUBO.org |publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers |year=2009 |accessdate=February 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|faculty         =900
|president       =[[Sidney A. McPhee]]
|students        =24,660&lt;ref name=&quot;attendance&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dnj.com/article/20110206/NEWS01/102060323/MTSU-s-spring-enrollment-sets-new-record |title=MTSU's spring enrollment sets new record |work=Daily News Journal |date=February 6, 2011 |accessdate=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       =22,274&lt;ref name=&quot;attendance&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad        =2,386&lt;ref name=&quot;attendance&quot;/&gt;
|city            =[[Murfreesboro, Tennessee|Murfreesboro]]
|state           =[[Tennessee]]
|country         =[[United States|USA]]
|campus          =[[Suburb]]an; {{convert|466|acre|km2|abbr=on}}
|colors          =Royal Blue &amp; White
|free_label      =Athletics
|free            =15 varsity teams
|mascot          =Lightning&lt;ref name=&quot;mascot&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.goblueraiders.com/content.cfm/id/2171 |title=Legend of Lightning |work=GoBlueRaiders.com |date=August 18, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|fightsong       =[http://www.goblueraiders.com/content.cfm/id/2173 Fight Song link]
|nickname        =[[Middle Tennessee Blue Raiders|Blue Raiders]]&lt;ref name=&quot;nickname&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.goblueraiders.com/content.cfm/id/2172 |title=The Blue Raider Nickname |work=GoBlueRaiders.com |date=August 18, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|affiliations    =[[Sun Belt Conference]]
|footnotes       =
|website         =[http://www.mtsu.edu MTSU.edu]
|address         =1301 E Main St &lt;br /&gt; Murfreesboro, TN 37132
|telephone       =(615) 898-2300
|coor            =
|logo            =
|footnotes=
}}
'''Middle Tennessee State University''', commonly abbreviated as '''MTSU''', is a [[public university|public]] [[university]] located in [[Murfreesboro, Tennessee|Murfreesboro]], [[Tennessee]], [[United States]].

Founded in 1911 as an education college, the university is composed of seven undergraduate colleges as well as a college of graduate studies offering more than 80 majors/degree programs through over 35 departments. Total enrollment in Fall, 2010 was 26,430, and in spring 2011 it was 24,660 (Spring enrollment is typically a bit lower than Fall enrollment). Of the Spring, 2011 total, 22,274 were undergraduates, and 2,386 were graduate students. It is currently the largest institution of higher learning in Tennessee by undergraduate enrollment. Fall semester 2011 set a new MTSU record enrollment total of 26,442 students.  In 2009, Middle Tennessee State University was ranked among the top 100 public universities by Forbes. 

MTSU is part of the [[Tennessee Board of Regents]], and is [[accreditation|accredited]] by the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] Commission on Colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;accreditation&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mtsu.edu/about_accreditation.shtml |title=Accreditations |work=MTSU.edu |year=2007 |accessdate=February 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its current president is [[Sidney A. McPhee]].

==History==
[[File:MTSU 1952 Aerial.jpg|thumb|left|1952 aerial photograph of the university]]
In 1909, the General Assembly of the State of [[Tennessee]] moved &quot;to provide for the improvement of the system of Public Education of the State of Tennessee, that is to say, to establish a General Education Fund.&quot; The major thrust of this &quot;improvement&quot; embodied in the legislative act that was to become known as the General Education Bill of 1909 was the establishment of three normals or teacher-training institutions. Following the intent of the act that one was to be located in each of the grand divisions of the state, the State Board of Education assigned the middle Tennessee institution
to Murfreesboro.

Opening on September 11, 1911, with a two-year program for training teachers, Middle Tennessee State Normal School evolved into a four-year teachers' college in 1925 with the power of granting the [[Bachelor of Science]] degree. In 1943, the General Assembly designated the institution a state college. This new status marked a sharp departure from the founding purpose and opened the way for expanding curricular offerings and programs. In 1965, the institution was advanced to university status.

During the progressive movement from a two-year normal to a university, several significant milestones may be identified. In 1936, the [[Bachelor of Arts]] program was added. Responding to the expressed needs of the institution's service area, the Graduate School was established in 1951. To effect better communications and improve administrative supervision, the schools concept was introduced in 1962.

As Middle Tennessee State University developed and grew, the [[Doctor of Arts]] program was added in 1970 and the [[Specialist in Education]] in 1974. These two degree programs became attractive centerpieces for other efforts to improve and enhance institutional roles. Library resources were dramatically increased and sophisticated computer services were developed to aid instruction and administration. A highly trained faculty enabled the University to continue growth in program offerings. In 1991, the University's six schools—five undergraduate and the graduate school—became colleges. In 1998, MTSU's [[Honors course|Honors Program]] became the Honors College, the first in the state. In 2002, approval was granted to redesignate three D.A. programs to Doctor of Philosophy programs, expanding the progressive institution's offerings.  Ph.D. degree offerings now include  Computational Sciences, Mathematics and Science Education (including concentrations in Biology Education, Chemistry Education, Mathematics Education, and Interdisciplinary Science Education), Molecular Biosciences, Economics, English, Human Performance, Public History, and Literacy Studies.

Since 1911, MTSU has graduated more than 100,000 students. Despite the University's growth from a campus of {{convert|100|acre|km2}}, 125 students, and a faculty of 19, to an academic city of over {{convert|500|acre|km2}}, more than 26,000 students, and a faculty of over 900, the institution is still essentially a &quot;people's university&quot; with a concern for the diverse needs of the area that it serves. In the 1980s and 1990s, the institution dedicated resources to become a leader in technology, both in the classroom and in many services to students. In 1986, [[James McGill Buchanan]] ('40) became the first MTSU alumnus to be
awarded the Nobel Prize. Buchanan received the [[Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences]] for his pioneering role in the development of the field of [[public choice]], a way of studying the behavior of politicians and bureaucrats.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://mtsu.edu/rootpage_files/MTSU_DetailedHistory.pdf |title=The History of the University |work=mtsu.edu |accessdate=March 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| Forbes = 234
| USNWR_NU = 203–268
}}
MTSU is divided into eight colleges:
[[Image:MTSU James E Walker Library.JPG|right|230px|thumbnail|[[James E. Walker Library]]]]
*College of Basic and Applied Sciences
*College of Education and Behavioral Science
*College of Graduate Studies
*College of Liberal Arts
*College of Mass Communication
*Jennings A. Jones College of Business
*University College
*University Honors College

The College of Graduate Studies offers Master's degrees in nearly forty different areas, the Specialist in Education degree (Administration and Supervision, Curriculum and Instruction in Educational Leadership, Elementary School Education, and School Psychology), and the Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) degree. MTSU's first Ph.D. was awarded in May 2003, though the university had awarded many Doctor of Arts (D.A.) degrees in the past.

Middle Tennessee State University employs approximately 900 full-time faculty members, with a student-to-faculty ratio of 22:1.

===Department of Recording Industry===
[[Image:MTSU Mass Comm.JPG|150px|thumb|left|The Mass Communications building at MTSU]]
The Department of Recording Industry (often called &quot;RIM&quot; for its former name &quot;Recording Industry Management&quot;) is a department in the College of Mass Communications and the university's most popular program. Due to the large number of students in the program, only a limited number of slots are opened for students to gain candidacy to take upper-division classes. The RIM program is divided into three concentrations: Music Business, Commercial Songwriting, and Production &amp; Technology. Music Business focuses on the marketing, management, and business aspects of the recording, touring, and publishing industries. The Production and Technology concentration focuses on recording, mixing, and mastering techniques, and specific technological trends of the industry. Commercial Songwriting is a blend of music business, songwriting, and music theory classes.

The department boasts five recording studios on campus, each open 24 hours a day.

The ''[[Rolling Stone]] College Guide'' recognized MTSU as having &quot;one of the preeminent music business programs in the country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eliscu2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Schools That Rock: The Rolling Stone College Guide |publisher=Wenner |location=New York |first=Jenny |last=Eliscu |year=2005 |isbn=1932958533}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Department of Aerospace===
The Department of Aerospace offers an aerospace major with five concentrations: professional pilot, administration, technology, flight dispatch, and maintenance management. Each concentration has been accredited by the Aviation Accreditation Board International, and the aerospace program has been accredited since 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;mtsuaero&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mtsu.edu/aerospace/ |title=MTSU Aerospace |work=MTSU.edu |accessdate=March 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Department of Aerospace has a working agreement with the single-runway Murfreesboro Airport to provide many of its classes on-site. A decommissioned [[Boeing 727]] airliner (number N117FE, donated by [[FedEx]]) is housed at the airport as a teaching tool.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=MTSU's 'classroom with wings' about to land |work=The Tennessean |first=Emily |last=Heffter |date=May 6, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Though no longer considered air-worthy, its engines remain functional, and can be restarted for training purposes. [[American Airlines]] has also donated a 727 cockpit procedure trainer to MTSU, which allows students to receive their flight engineer rating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mtsusidelines.com/media/storage/paper202/news/2001/02/26/News/Aerospace.Updates.Boeing.727.Trainer-37040.shtml |title=Aerospace updates Boeing 727 trainer |work=Sidelines |first=Jason |last=Cox |date=February 26, 2001 |accessdate=October 15, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is housed in the Business &amp; Aerospace Building near the center of campus. The aerospace program's training fleet is made up of [[Diamond DA40]] single-engine aircraft featuring [[glass cockpit]]s, with an assortment of other single- and multi-engine aircraft available.&lt;ref name=&quot;mtsuaero-planes&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mtsu.edu/aerospace/airplanes.shtml |title=Airplanes |work=MTSU.edu |accessdate=March 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the Department of Aerospace purchased ten radar simulators as well as a one-of-a-kind 360 degree control tower simulator to enhance training for its air traffic control students. These simulators allow students to experience life-like air traffic control scenarios that will aid in preparing them for training at the FAA Academy in Oklahoma City.&lt;ref name=&quot;sidelines100710&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mtsusidelines.com/news/mtsu-aerospace-program-lands-multi-million-dollar-contract-1.1497806 |title=MTSU aerospace program lands multi-million dollar contract |work=The Sidelines |first=Ryan |last=Glenn |date=July 10, 2010 |accessdate=September 27, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Concrete Industry Management===
The Concrete Industry Management program is a four year bachelor of science degree offered through the Engineering Technology and Industrial Studies department in the College of Basic and Applied Sciences. CIM develops graduates that are broadly educated with technical knowledge in addition to a solid business background. Known for its close industry ties and very high job placement rates, CIM has become the fastest growing major on campus and boasts around 300 students. It was started in 1996 by industry professionals and companies to meet the demand for educated professionals in an expanding and changing industry. CIM at MTSU was the first of its kind in the country. Other CIM programs have since started at [[Arizona State University]] and [[New Jersey Institute of Technology]].

==Campus Information==
[[Image:Walnut Grove at MTSU.jpg|135px|thumb|right|Walnut Grove behind the site of the old library building at MTSU]]
The campus, set on 466 acres (1.9&amp;nbsp;km²), features 109 permanent buildings with 3.8 million square feet (353,000 m²) of space. It is located one mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km) from the geographic center of Tennessee, and 1.3 miles (2&amp;nbsp;km) east of downtown Murfreesboro. The campus is mostly flat, much like the landscape of Murfreesboro.

The campus takes the general shape of a rectangle and automobile traffic is mostly confined to the campus perimeter. Its borders, however, are generally defined by four high-traffic Murfreesboro thoroughfares: Greenland Boulevard on the north, Middle Tennessee Boulevard on the west, Rutherford Boulevard on the east, and East Main Street on the south. Parking lots for students border these streets on the outer perimeter of campus.

MTSU has never been linked directly to [[Interstate 24]], though there are two main arteries from the interstate. One is via Exit 80, which connects to New Salem Highway, intersects with Middle Tennessee Boulevard, and eventually leads to campus.  The other is through Exit 81, which connects to Church Street, intersects with Rutherford Boulevard, and leads to the university's main entrance at MTSU Boulevard.

Middle Tennessee State University is a &quot;dry campus,&quot; meaning alcoholic beverages are prohibited at all times.

===Campus Layout===
[[Image:MTSU Jones Hall.JPG|200px|thumb|left|Jones Hall]]
[[Image:MTSU Naked Eye Observatory.JPG|200px|thumb|right|The Naked Eye Observatory]]
[[Image:MTSU Business and Aerospace Building.JPG|200px|thumb|left|Business and Aerospace Building]]
[[Image:MTSU Paul W Martin Honors Building.JPG|200px|thumb|right|Paul W. Martin Honors Building]]

The western section of campus contains most of the college's original buildings.  The college's oldest classroom building, Kirksey Old Main, lies adjacent to Peck Hall.  The original dormitories - Monohan, Lyon, and Rutledge Halls - line the western edge of campus.  Service buildings such as the James Union Building and the Cope Administration Building are on the western edge of campus.  Liberal arts buildings, such as Peck Hall, Jones Hall, and Saunders Fine Arts, occupy the majority of west campus.  Other structures, such as the Wiser-Patten Science Building and the Uranidrome, a Naked Eye Observatory also lie on the western part of campus.  Athletic facilities such as the [[Murphy Center]], [[Johnny &quot;Red&quot; Floyd Stadium]], the Alumni Memorial Gym, [[Reese Smith Jr. Field]], and the university's tennis courts are also on the western part of campus.

Central campus contains student service buildings and more dormitories.  The Keathley University Center is the student union of MTSU, containing a cafeteria, bookstore, post office, and many student service offices. The new Student Union Building and College of Education Building is currently being erected on the west side of campus between Cummings Hall and the Recreation Center. The Woodmore CyberCafe also contains a cafeteria for students.  Dormitory halls such as Smith, Beasley, Sims, Gracy, and Judd lie central to campus.  Classroom buildings, such as the Boutwell Dramatic Arts Building, Forrest Hall, and the Photography building are also located in the center of campus.

The eastern part of campus houses the main quadrangle of MTSU, encompassing the Learning Resource Center, the Business and Aerospace Building, the Mass Communications Building, and the [[James E. Walker Library]].  East campus is also home to many dorms, including the honors dorm Wood-Felder, Clement, Gore, Nicks, Deere, and the two seven-story dormitories - Cummings and Corlew.  On the far east of campus lies the Paul W. Martin Honors Building, Ezell and Abernathy Halls, the recreation center, and two apartment complexes - Scarlett Commons and Womack Lane.  On the very extreme east of campus facing Rutherford Boulevard lies Greek Row.

&lt;!--- Please leave this space blank for formatting. ---&gt;

==Student life==
===Residences===
There are twenty on-campus dormitories on MTSU's campus, and two apartment complexes. 15% of MTSU's students live in on campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;housing&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://frank.mtsu.edu/~ocss/ocl/ |title=MTSU Blue Raiders Guide to Living Off-Campus |work=MTSU.edu |year=2008 |accessdate=February 23, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; A large majority of students live in apartment complexes surrounding the university. Eight [[Fraternities and sororities|fraternity]] houses are located on Greek Row, and a few other fraternities have off-campus housing locations. No sorority houses have opened at MTSU.

[[Image:Autumn in the library quad at Middle Tennessee State University.jpg|thumb|The quad in front of the [[James E. Walker Library]]]]

===Media outlets===
Due to a significant emphasis on Mass Communication at MTSU, the campus has several mass media outlets. ''Sidelines'' is the campus's editorially independent, student-run newspaper, printed every Monday and Thursday. MTTV, a student-run TV station, is carried locally by [[Comcast]]. The two radio stations on MTSU's campus are [[WMTS-FM|WMTS]], a student-run radio station, and [[WMOT]], a publicly supported jazz radio station.

===Student organizations===
The university is host to approximately 225 student organizations, fraternities, and interest groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;studentorgs&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://frank.mtsu.edu/~camporgs/student.htm |title=MTSU Student Organizations and Community Service |work=MTSU.edu |year=2003 |accessdate=February 23, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, MTSU's Greek Life consists of the following social fraternities and sororities:
&lt;!--- These are in Greek-alphabet order. If you add an organization, please try to uphold that. ---&gt;

Twelve [[North-American Interfraternity Conference|IFC]] fraternities: [[Alpha Gamma Rho]], [[Alpha Tau Omega]], [[Kappa Alpha Order]], [[Kappa Sigma]], [[Pi Kappa Phi]], [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], [[Sigma Nu]], [[Sigma Pi]], [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]], [[Sigma Chi]], and [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]

Six [[National Panhellenic Conference|NPC]] sororities: [[Alpha Delta Pi]], [[Alpha Omicron Pi]], [[Alpha Chi Omega]], [[Zeta Tau Alpha]], [[Kappa Delta]], and [[Chi Omega]]

All Nine [[National Pahellenic Council|NPHC]] organizations: [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]], [[Alpha Phi Alpha]], [[Delta Sigma Theta]], [[Zeta Phi Beta]], [[Iota Phi Theta]], [[Kappa Alpha Psi]], [[Sigma Gamma Rho]], [[Phi Beta Sigma]], and [[Omega Psi Phi]]

Two [[NALFO]] organizations: [[Lambda Theta Alpha]] and [[Lambda Theta Phi]]

One independent fraternity: [[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]]

Professional/Honor organizations: [[Alpha Eta Rho]], [[Alpha Kappa Psi]], [[Alpha Psi Omega]], [[Delta Omicron]], [[Pi Sigma Epsilon]], [[Sigma Alpha Iota]], [[Sigma Theta Tau]], [[Sigma Alpha Lambda]], [[Phi Sigma Pi]], [[Phi Kappa Phi]], [[Order of Omega]], and Omega Delta Psi

==Athletics==
[[File:MTSU Raiders logo.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]
{{main|Middle Tennessee Blue Raiders}}
Middle Tennessee's athletic teams, known as the '''Blue Raiders''', compete in the [[Sun Belt Conference]] of [[NCAA]]'s Division I in the [[Football Bowl Subdivision| Football Bowl Subdivision (FBS, formerly Division I-A)]].  MTSU has won two national championships:  golf in 1965, and men's doubles tennis in 2007.

The MTSU mascot is &quot;Lightning,&quot; a winged horse based on Pegasus from Greek mythology.

==Distinguished Alumni and Faculty==
{{main|List of Middle Tennessee State University people}}
Some of MTSU's most notable alumni include politician [[Albert Gore, Sr.]], Nobel Prize winning economist [[James McGill Buchanan]], NFL quarterback [[Kelly Holcomb]], Nashville Star winner [[Chris Young (singer)|Chris Young]], country music artist [[Hillary Scott (singer)|Hillary Scott]] of [[Lady Antebellum]], and WNBA players [[Alysha Clark]] and [[Amber Holt]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Middle Tennessee State University|MTSU}}
* {{Official website|http://www.mtsu.edu}}
&lt;!-- Do not add any further links. They will be removed. --&gt;

{{Tennessee Board of Regents}}
{{Public universities in Tennessee}}
{{Sun Belt Conference}}
{{coord|35.85222|-86.37|display=title}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1911]]
[[Category:Middle Tennessee State University| ]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Air traffic controller schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Murfreesboro, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Audio engineering schools in the United States]]
[[Category:Education in Rutherford County, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Rutherford County, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Rutherford County, Tennessee]]

[[bn:মিডল টেনেসি স্টেট ইউনিভার্সিটি]]
[[de:Middle Tennessee State University]]
[[ja:ミドルテネシー州立大学]]
[[no:Middle Tennessee State University]]
[[tr:Middle Tennessee Devlet Üniversitesi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
