<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6450525" ns="0" title="Out of India theory"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{sprotected2}}
{{Indo-European topics}}
The '''Out of India theory''' ('''OIT''', also called the '''Indian Urheimat Theory''') is the proposition that the [[Indo-European language family]] [[Indo-European homeland|originated]] in the [[Indian subcontinent]] and spread to the remainder of the Indo-European region through a series of migrations. A notable proponent was [[Karl Wilhelm Friedrich Schlegel|Friedrich Schlegel]] (1772–1829).

Originally proposed in the late 18th century in an attempt to explain connections between [[Sanskrit]] and European languages, it was rapidly marginalized within academic linguistics,&lt;ref&gt;George {{Harvcoltxt|Erdosy|1995|p=x}} describes it as &quot;lunatic [[fringe science|fringe]]&quot; and &quot;devoid of scholarly value&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Witzel | first = Michael | authorlink = Michael E. J. Witzel | editor = Fagan, Garrett G. | title = Archaeological Fantasies: How Pseudoarchaeology Misrepresents the Past and Misleads the Public | year = 2006 | publisher = Routledge | pages = 203–232 | chapter = Rama's realm: Indocentric rewritings of early South Asian archaeology and history}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref  name = &quot;bhatt-2001&quot; &gt;{{Citation | author = Chetan Bhatt | title = Hindu Nationalism: Origins, Ideologies and Modern Myths | publisher = Berg Publishers | year = 2001 | isbn = 1859733484 | page = 205 }}&lt;/ref&gt; particularly those who tend to favor the [[Kurgan hypothesis|Kurgan model]] instead.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Mallory|1989|p=185}}. &quot;The Kurgan solution is attractive and has been accepted by many archaeologists and linguists, in part or total. It is the solution one encounters in the ''Encyclopaedia Britannica'' and the ''Grand Dictionnaire Encyclopédique Larousse''.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Cavalli-Sforza|2000|p=152}} &quot;The Aryan invasions of Iran, Pakistan, and India brought Indo-European languages to Dravidian-speaking areas.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcolnb|Mallory|1989}} &quot;the great majority of scholars insist that the Indo-Aryans were intrusive into northwest India&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; 

Still, the Out of India theory today builds primarily on the idea that [[Indigenous Aryans|Aryans are indigenous to the Indian subcontinent]]&lt;ref&gt;Trautmann, The Aryan Debate p. xiii (2005)  &quot;The indigenous Aryan view is not a recent invention, and there have always been some scholars who supported it.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trautmann, The Aryan Debate pxii (2005) &quot;There are others taking up the indigenous aryan position who are very well qualified, and whose scholarly credentials entitle them to a respectful hearing.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; rather than on the archaeogenetic and other academic developments. The theory's recent revival in [[Hindu nationalist]] writing has made it the subject of a contentious debate in [[Indian politics]].&lt;ref name = &quot;bhatt-2001&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trautmann, The Aryan Debate p. xviii (2005) &quot;unflattering labels such as 'Hindu nationalist' and 'Hindutva' are thrown about as if they were proofs that the arguments of the writers opponent were not true...identifying the social historical location of a piece of history writing does not tell us whether it is true or false.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; These recent &quot;OIT&quot; scenarios posit that the [[Indus Valley Civilization]] was [[Indo-Aryan peoples|Indo-Aryan]] and uses mainly evidence from Sanskrit literature. The hypotheses have been espoused mainly by the radical nationalist sympathizer [[Koenraad Elst]] and Indian author [[Shrikant Talageri]]. These scenarios have also been defended by the archaeologist [[B.B. Lal]].

==History==
{{See also|Aryan Invasion Theory (history and controversies)}}

===Early proposals===
When the finding of connections between languages from India to Europe led to the creation of [[Indo-European studies]] in the late 18th century some Indians and Europeans believed that the [[Proto-Indo-European language]] must be [[Sanskrit]], or something very close to it. A few early Indo-Europeanists, such as [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] pioneers [[Voltaire]],&lt;ref name=&quot;savitri&quot;&gt;[[Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke|Goodrick-Clarke, Nicholas]], ''[[Hitler's Priestess]]: Savitri Devi, the Hindu-Aryan Myth, and Neo-Nazism'' ([[New York University]] Press, 1998, hardcover: ISBN 0-8147-3110-4, paperback: ISBN 0-8147-3111-2)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Immanuel Kant]],&lt;ref name=&quot;savitri&quot;/&gt; and [[Karl Wilhelm Friedrich Schlegel]]&lt;ref&gt;Friedrich von Schlegel: Ueber die Sprache und Weisheit der Indier (1808)&lt;/ref&gt; had a firm belief in this and essentially created the idea that India was the [[Urheimat]] of all Indo-European languages. In a 1775 letter, Voltaire expressed his belief in that the &quot;dynasty of the [[Brahmin]]s&quot; taught the rest of the world: &quot;I am convinced that everything has come down to us from the banks of the [[Ganges]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;savitri&quot;/&gt; The idea intrigued Kant who &quot;suggested that mankind together with all science must have originated on the roof of the world [the [[Himalayas]] ].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;savitri&quot;/&gt; Most scholars, such as [[William Jones (philologist)|William Jones]], however realized from earliest times that instead, Sanskrit and related European languages had a common source, and that no attested language represented this direct ancestor.

The development of [[historical linguistics]], specifically the law of palatals and the discovery of the laryngeals in Hittite,  shattered Sanskrit's preeminent status as the most venerable elder in this reconstructed family.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bryant|2001|p=69}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demotion of Sanskrit to the status of one daughter language among many eroded the remaining support of India as the Indo-European homeland.

The ethnologist and philologist [[Robert Gordon Latham]] was the first to state that, according to the principles of [[natural science]], a language family's most likely point of origin is in the area of its greatest diversity which, in the case of Indo-European, is roughly in Central-Eastern Europe, where the [[Italic languages|Italic]], [[Venetic language|Venetic]], [[Illyrian languages|Illyrian]], [[Germanic languages|Germanic]], [[Baltic languages|Baltic]], [[Slavic languages|Slavic]], [[Thracian language|Thracian]], and [[Greek language|Greek]] branches of the Indo-European language family are attested, as opposed to South Asia, where only the Indo-Aryan branch is.&lt;ref name=jpm152&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Mallory|1989|pp=152–153}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lachhmi Dhar Kalla]] responded by arguing that the greater linguistic diversity of Indo-European in Europe is the result of absorbing foreign linguistic elements, and that a language family's point of origin should be sought in the area of least linguistic change, since it has been least affected by substrate interference. Dhar's line of argument has a history in Western debates in the Indo-European homeland (e.g. Feist 1932 and Pissani 1974 as cited in {{Harvnb|Bryant|2001|pp=142–143}}) where it has been used to locate the Indo-European homeland near the area where the [[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]]{{Clarify|there is no &quot;Lithuanian branch&quot;, should this be &quot;Baltic&quot; or &quot;Balto-Slavic&quot;?|date=June 2009}} and [[Anatolian languages|Anatolian]] branches of Indo-European are attested.

===1999 &quot;revival&quot;===
An Indian Urheimat has been promoted more recently by {{Harvtxt|Elst|1999}} and {{Harvtxt|Talageri|2000}}, which led to an exchange of criticisms with [[Michael Witzel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://www.ejvs.laurasianacademy.com/ejvs0702/ejvs0702article.pdf| title = Westward Ho!: The Incredible Wanderlust of the Ṛgvedic tribes Exposed by S. Talageri| accessdate = 2007-07-17  | last = Witzel | first = Michael| authorlink = Michael E. J. Witzel| year = 2001 | month = April| publisher = Electronic Journal of Vedic Studies| format = PDF }}&lt;br&gt;Talageri 2000:&quot;[http://www.voi.org/books/rig/ch9.htm Chapter 9 (Appendix 2): Michael Witzel - An Examination of Western Vedic Scholarship]&quot;.&lt;br&gt;{{Cite web| url = http://koenraadelst.voiceofdharma.org/articles/fascism/witzelmisattribute.html| title = Petty Professorial Politicking in The Indo-Aryan Controversy| accessdate = 2007-07-17  | last = Elst | first = Koenraad| authorlink = Koenraad Elst| date = 2005-10-19 | work = The Koenraad Elst Site | publisher = Voice of Dharma }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In what its editor J. P. {{Harvtxt|Mallory|2002}} described as a &quot;sense of fair play,&quot; the [[Journal of Indo-European Studies]] waived [[peer review]] in order to publish
Kazanas' ([[Out of India theory#CITEREFKazanas2002|2002]], [[Out of India theory#CITEREFKazanas2003|2003]]) defence of the &quot;Indigenous Indo-Aryan&quot; viewpoint&amp;nbsp;— which cited {{Harvtxt|Elst|1999}} and {{Harvtxt|Talageri|2000}}. Mallory's reasoning for this exceptional omission of peer-review was as follows:
{{cquote|The reasons for the acrimony between the two camps is not purely academic but may involve agendas that are variously associated with Hindu nationalism, western cultural imperialism, communalism, post-colonialism, and just about any other form of -ism that reflects current political frictions. [...] For the editor of a Western peer-reviewed journal, the publication of an article in support of the Indigenous Indo-Aryan camp poses obvious problems.  Many regard the scholarship of the Indigenous Indo-Aryan camp so seriously flawed that it should not be given an airing.  They view the Indigenous Aryan camp as more a religion than an academic position and no amount of scholarly refutation is likely to have the least impact on its adherents. On the other hand, we might also invoke some sense of fair play [...]  I indicated that I thought it would be unlikely that any referee would agree with [Kazanas'] conclusions but that I would consider publication if one of the referees believed that the article had made a case to answer; I requested the referees to view the article in that light.  This is indeed what happened and the authors agreed with my suggestion that we might treat the article in a review format where I would invite a series of relevant scholars to comment upon the article and then provide the author with space to make his final reply to his critics.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Editor's Note&quot; of JIES 30 (2002, n.3&amp;4, p.273-274&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The debate consisted of an article by {{Harvtxt|Kazanas|2002}}, nine highly critical reviews by referees,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | year=2002 | periodical=Journal of Indo-European Studies |volume=30}}.&lt;br&gt;{{Citation | year=2003 | periodical=Journal of Indo-European Studies |volume=31}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Out of India theory#CITEREFKazanas2003|Kazanas' (2003)]] response to those criticisms, and a few further responses available online.&lt;ref name=WitzelReplyToFR&gt;Witzel [http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/~witzel/Kazanas.htm The Kazanas Fiasco]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=KazanasReplyToWitzelReplyToFR&gt;Kazanas [http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/pdf/en/indology/reply_to_witzel.pdf Message to V Agarwal]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Harvcoltxt|Witzel|2003}} warned:
{{cquote|It is certain that Kazanas, now that he is published in JIES, will be quoted endlessly by Indian fundamentalists and nationalists as &quot;a respected scholar published in major peer-reviewed journals like JIES&quot; -- no matter how absurd his claims are known to be by specialist readers of those journals. It was through means like these that the misperception has taken root in Indian lay sectors that the historical absurdities of Kak, Frawley, and even Rajaram are taken seriously by academic scholars.}}

==Chronology==
Neolithic and Bronze Age Indian history is periodized into the [[Pre-Harappan]] (ca. 7000 to 3300 BC), [[Early Harappan]] (3300 to 2600), [[Mature Harappan]] (2600 to 1900) and [[Late Harappan]] (1900 to 1300 BC) periods.

The Indian Urheimat proposal put forward by {{Harvtxt|Elst|1999}}, which he dubs the &quot;emerging non-invasionist model,&quot; is as follows: During the 6th millennium BC, the Proto-Indo-Europeans were living in the [[Punjab region]] of [[North India|Northern India]]. As the result of demographic expansion, they spread into [[Bactria]] as the [[Kambojas]]. The [[Paradas]] moved further and inhabited the [[Caspian Sea|Caspian]] coast and much of [[Central Asia]] while the [[Cina]]s moved northwards and inhabited the [[Tarim Basin]] in northwestern China, forming the [[Tocharians]] group of I-E speakers. These groups were [[Proto-Anatolian]] and inhabited that region by 2000 BC. These people took the oldest form of the Proto Indo-European (PIE) language with them and, while interacting with people of the Anatolian and Balkan region, transformed it into its own dialect. While inhabiting Central Asia they discovered the uses of the [[horse]], which they later sent back to [[Urheimat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Aryan-Non Invasionist Model&quot;&gt;[http://www.voiceofdharma.com/books/ait/ch63.htm The Aryan Non-Invasionist Model] by Koenraad Elst&lt;/ref&gt; Later on during their history, they went on to take [[Western Europe]] and thus spread the Indo-European languages to that region.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Aryan-Non Invasionist Model&quot;/&gt; During the 4th millennium BC, civilization in India was evolving to become the urban [[Indus Valley Civilization]]. During this time, the PIE languages evolved to [[Proto-Indo-Iranian]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Aryan-Non Invasionist Model&quot;/&gt; Some time during this period, the Indo-Iranians began to separate as the result of internal rivalry and conflict, with the Iranians expanding westwards towards [[Mesopotamia]] and [[Persia]], these possibly were the [[Pahlava]]s. They also expanded into parts of [[Central Asia]]. By the end of this migration, India was left with the Proto-Indo-Aryans. At the end of the Mature Harappan period, the Sarasvati river began drying up and the remainder of Indo-Aryans split into separate categories. Some travelled westwards and established themselves as rulers of the [[Hurrian]] [[Mitanni]] kingdom by around 1500 BC (see [[Indo-Aryan superstrate in Mitanni]]).  Others travelled eastwards and inhabited the [[Gangetic basin]] while others travelled southwards and interacted with the [[Dravidian people]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Aryan-Non Invasionist Model&quot;/&gt;

==Linguistics==
:''See also [[linguistics]] or [[historical linguistics]].''

According to {{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|p=75}}, OIT proponents tend to be linguistic dilettantes who either ignore the linguistic evidence completely, dismiss it as highly speculative and inconclusive (e.g. Chakrabarti 1995 and [[N. S. Rajaram|Rajaram]] 1995, as cited in {{Harvcolnb|Bryant|2001|p=74}}, or attempt to tackle it with hopelessly inadequate qualifications; this attitude and neglect significantly minimizes the value of most OIT publications.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|pp=74–107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Edwin F. Bryant, Linguistic Substrata and the Indigenous Aryan Debate (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Harvtxt|Talageri|2000}} and {{Harvtxt|Kazanas|2002}} have adapted the language dispersal model proposed by [[Johanna Nichols]] (in {{Harvnb|Blench|Spriggs|1997}}) to support OIT by moving Nichols' proposed Indo-European point of origin from [[Bactria]]-[[Sogdiana]] to India. These ideas have not been accepted in mainstream linguistics.

{{Harvtxt|Elst|1999}} argues that it is altogether more likely that the Urheimat was in [[satem]] territory.  The alternative from the angle of an Indian Urheimat theory (IUT) would be that India had originally had the [[Centum-Satem isogloss|centum]] form, that the dialects which first emigrated (Hittite, Italo-Celtic, Germanic, Tokharic) retained the centum form and took it to the geographical borderlands of the IE expanse (Europe, Anatolia, China), while the dialects which emigrated later (Baltic, Thracian, Phrygian) were at a halfway stage and the last-emigrated dialects (Slavic, Armenian, Iranian) plus the staybehind Indo-Aryan languages had adopted the satem form.  This would satisfy the claim of the so-called Lateral Theory that the most conservative forms are to be found at the outskirts rather than in the metropolis.&lt;ref&gt;Elst 1999:&quot;[http://voi.org/books/ait/ch32.htm 3.2  Origin of the Linguistic Argument]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparative linguistics===
[[File:Centum Satem map.png|thumb|260px|Diachronic map showing the [[Satem]] [[areal (linguistics)|areal]] in red. The central area of Satemization is shown in darker red, corresponding to the [[Sintashta-Petrovka|Sintashta]]/[[Abashevo culture|Abashevo]]/[[Srubna culture|Srubna]]  cultures.]]There are twelve accepted branches of the [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European family]]. The two [[Indo-Iranian languages|Indo-Iranian]] branches, [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indic]] (Indo-Aryan) and [[Iranian languages|Iranian]], dominate the eastern cluster, historically spanning [[Scythia]], [[Iran]] and [[Northern India]]. While the exact sequence in which the different branches separated or migrated away from a homeland is disputed, linguists generally agree that [[Anatolian languages|Anatolian]]  was the first branch to be separated from the remaining body of Indo-European.

Additionally, [[Graeco-Aryan]] isoglosses seem suggestive that Greek and Indo-Iranian may have shared a common homeland for a while after the splitting of the other IE branches. Such a homeland could be northwestern India (which is preferred by proponents of the OIT) or the [[Pontic steppe]]s (as preferred by the mainstream supporters of the Kurgan hypothesis).

According to [[Hans Henrich Hock|Hock]], if evidence like linguistic isogloss patterns is ignored, then the hypothesis of an Out-of-India migration becomes &quot;relatively easy to maintain&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last=Hock | first=H.H. | author-link=Hans Hock | chapter=Out of India? The linguistic evidence | year=1996 | editor-surname=Bronkhorst | editor-first=J. | editor2-last=Deshpande | editor2-first=M.M. | title=Aryan and Non-Aryan in South Asia: Evidence, Interpretation, and Ideology | publisher=Harvard Oriental Series | publication-date=1999 | isbn=1888789042 }}. On p 14 is Fig 1, the cladistic tree of the IE branches. On p 15 is Fig 2, the diagram of isoglosses. On p 16 he states that if only the model in Fig 1 is accepted, then the hypothesis of an Out-of-India migration would be &quot;relatively easy to maintain&quot;, i.e. provided the evidence of Fig 2 were ignored.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Substratum influences in Vedic Sanskrit===
{{Main|Substratum in Vedic Sanskrit}}

Evidence of a pre-Indo-European linguistic [[substratum]] in South Asia is solid reason to exclude India as a potential Indo-European homeland.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|p=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Thomas Burrow|Burrow]] compiled a list of approximately 500 foreign words in the [[Rigveda|Ṛgveda]] that he considered to be loans predominantly from [[Dravidian languages|Dravidian]]. Kuiper identified 383 Ṛgvedic words as non-Indo-Aryan—roughly 4% of its liturgical vocabulary—borrowed from Old [[Dravidian languages|Dravidian]], Old [[Munda languages|Munda]], and several other languages. [[Paul Thieme|Thieme]] has questioned Dravidian etymologies proposed for Vedic words, for most of which he gives Indoaryan or Sanskrit etymologies, and condemned what he characterizes as a misplaced “[[Zealotry|zeal]] for hunting up [[Dravidian languages|Dravidian]] loans in [[Sanskrit]]”. [[Rahul Peter Das|Das]] contends that there is “''not a single case'' in which a ''communis opinio'' has been found confirming the foreign origin of a Rigvedic (and probably Vedic in general) word”. Burrow in turn has criticized the &quot;resort to tortuous reconstructions in order to find, by hook or by crook, Indo-European explanations for Sanskrit words&quot;. Kuiper reasons that given the abundance of Indo-European comparative material—and the scarcity of Dravidian or Munda—the inability to clearly confirm whether the etymology of a Vedic word is Indo-European implies that it is not. {{Harvtxt|Witzel|1999}} argues that the earliest level of the Rigveda shows signs of para-[[Munda languages|Munda]] influence and only later levels of Dravidian, suggesting—against the older widespread two-century-old belief—that the original inhabitants of Punjab were [[Munda people|speakers of para-Munda]] rather than [[Dravidian people|speakers of Dravidian]], whom the Indo-Aryans encountered only in middle Rigvedic times.&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Thieme|Thieme]], [[Thomas Burrow|Burrow]], and [[Rahul Peter Das|Das]], as cited in {{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|pp=86–88}}&lt;br&gt;Kuiper, as cited in {{Harvcoltxt|Witzel|1999}} and {{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|pp=87}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dravidian and other South Asian languages share with Indo-Aryan a number of [[syntactical]] and [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphological]] features that are alien to other Indo-European languages. [[Phonologically]], there is the introduction of [[retroflex]]es, which alternate with [[Dental consonant|dentals]] in Indo-Aryan; [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphologically]] there are the [[gerund]]s; and [[syntactically]] there is the use of a [[quotative]] [[Marker (linguistics)|marker]] (&quot;iti&quot;). Several linguists, all of whom accept the external origin of the Aryan languages on other grounds, are quite open to considering that various syntactical developments in Indo-Aryan could have been internal developments (Hamp 1996 and Jamison 1989, as cited in {{Harvcolnb|Bryant|2001|pp=81–82}} rather than the result of substrate influences, or have been the result of [[adstratum]] (Hock 1975/1984/1996 and Tikkanen 1987, as cited in {{Harvcolnb|Bryant|2001|pp=80–82}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|pp=78–82}}&lt;/ref&gt; About retroflexion {{Harvcoltxt|Tikkanen|1999}} states that &quot;in view of the strictly areal implications of retroflexion and the occurrence of retroflexes in many early loanwords, it is hardly likely that Indo-Aryan retroflexion arose in a region that did not have a substratum with retroflexes.&quot;

Another concern raised is that there is large time gap between the comparative materials, which can be seen as a serious methodological drawback.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bryant|2001|p=82}} - the syntax of the [[Rigveda]] is being compared with a reconstructed proto-Dravidian. The first completely intelligible, datable, and sufficiently long and complete epigraphs that might be of some use in linguistic comparison are the [[Tamil language|Tamil]] inscriptions of the [[Pallava dynasty]] of about 550 c.e. (Zvelebil 1990), two entire millennia after the commonly accepted date for the Rigveda.  Similarly there is much less material available for comparative [[Munda people|Munda]] and the interval in their case at least is a staggering thirty-five hundred years.&lt;/ref&gt; The latter is however not a cogent argument, if one compares, for example modern Lithuanian (laukas patis) with early Vedic Sanskrit (loka-pati), which too are divided by a  time span of c. 3200 years.

{{Harvtxt|Elst|1999}} proposes that any Dravidian in Sanskrit can still be explained via the OIT. He suggests through David McAlpin's [[Elamo-Dravidian languages|Proto-Elamo-Dravidian theory]], that the ancient homeland for Proto-Elamo-Dravidian was in the Mesopotamia region, from where the languages spread across the coast towards [[Sindh]] and eventually to [[South India]] where they still remain.&lt;ref&gt;D. McAlpin ''Linguistic Prehistory: The Dravidian Situation'' 1979&lt;/ref&gt; According to Elst, this theory would support the idea that Early Harappan culture was possibly bi- or multi-lingual. {{Harvtxt|Elst|1999}} claims that the presence of the [[Brahui language]], similarities between Elamite and Harappan script as well as similarities between Indo-Aryan and Dravidian indicate that these languages may have interacted prior to the spread of Indo-Aryans southwards and the resultant intermixing of races and languages.

Elfenbein (as cited in {{Harvnb|Witzel|2000}}) argues that the presence of Brahui in Baluchistan is explained by a late immigration that took place within the last thousand years.

Elst believes that there is evidence suggesting that Dravidian influences in [[Maharashtra]] and [[Gujarat]] were largely lost over the years. He traces this to linguistic evidence. Some occurrences in [[Sangam literature|Sangam Tamil]], or ancient forms of Tamil, indicate small similarities with [[Sanskrit]] or [[Prakrit]]. As the oldest recognizable form of Tamil have influences of Indo-Aryan, it is possible that they had Sanskrit influence through a migration through the coastal regions of western India.&lt;ref&gt;Elst (1999){{Page needed|date=September 2010}}; Influence of Sanskrit or Prakrit on Sangam Tamil can be seen in some particular terms. For example, ''AkAyam'' (meaning sky) is thought to be derived from ''AkAsha'', while ''Ayutham'' (meaning weapon) is thought to be derived from ''Ayudha''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing specifically about language contact phenomena, {{Harvcoltxt|Thomason|Kaufman|1988}} state that there is strong evidence that Dravidian influenced Indic through &quot;shift&quot;, that is, native Dravidian speakers learning and adopting Indic languages. Even though the innovative traits in Indic could be explained by multiple internal explanations, early Dravidian influence is the only explanation that can account for all of the innovations at once&amp;nbsp;– it becomes a question of [[Occam's razor|explanatory parsimony]]; moreover, early Dravidian influence accounts for the several of the innovative traits in Indic better than any internal explanation that has been proposed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Thomason|Kaufman|1988|pp=141–144}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Harvcoltxt|Erdosy|1995|p=18}} states that the most plausible explanation for the presence of Dravidian structural features in Old Indo-Aryan is that the majority of early Old Indo-Aryan speakers had a Dravidian mother tongue which they gradually abandoned.

===Hydronymy===
[[Indo-Aryan languages]] are the oldest source of place and [[Rivers of India|river names]] in northern India&amp;nbsp;– which [[Shrikant G. Talageri]] sees as an argument in favor of seeing Indo-Aryan as the oldest documented [[Demographics of India|population of that area]].&lt;ref name=talageri&gt;Talageri 2000:&quot;[http://www.voiceofdharma.com/books/rig/ch7.htm Chapter 7: The Indo-European Homeland]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Witzel, river names are conservative, and &quot;in northern India, rivers in general have early Sanskrit names from the Vedic period, and names derived from the daughter languages of Sanskrit later on.&quot;&lt;ref name=witzel&gt;Witzel. &quot;Early Indian history: Linguistic and textual parametres&quot;, in {{Harvtxt|Erdosy|1995}}&lt;/ref&gt; Talageri cites this in support of the Out of India theory,&lt;ref name=talageri/&gt; though Witzel himself would dispute jumping to that conclusion.&lt;ref name=witzel/&gt; Rather, he points out that non-Sanskritic names are common in the &quot;Sarasvati&quot; (Ghaggar) area.

Kazanas argues that this indicates that the [[Indus Valley Civilization|Harappan]] civilization must have been dominated by [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indo-Aryan]] speakers, supposing that the arrival of Indo-Aryan migrants in Late Harappan times to the remnants of a [[Indus Valley Civilization]] formerly stretching over vast area could not have resulted in the suppression of the entire native hydronymy.&lt;ref name = &quot;Kazanas 2001B&quot;&gt;Kazanas, Nicholas 2001b&amp;nbsp;— Indigenous Indoaryans and the Rgveda&amp;nbsp;— Journal of Indo-European Studies, volume 29, pages 257-93&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Witzel argues exactly that: &quot;The failure to preserve old hydronomes even in the Indus Valley (with a few exceptions, noted above) indicates the extent of the social and political collapse experienced by the local population.&quot;&lt;ref name=witzel/&gt;

Paralleling Witzel, {{Harvtxt|Villar|2000}} characterizes place names as the deepest ethnic and linguistic layer, and states that the first network of river and place names in Spain was created by very ancient Indo-European populations, and was dense enough to resist successive language changes. According to {{Harvtxt|Villar|2000}}, even in those areas which are historically Basque (i.e. non-Indo-European), the ancient names of places and people have a prevailing Indo-European character, with very few names of non-Indo-European Basque etymology documented in ancient sources. {{Harvtxt|Alinei|2003}} cites this in support of the [[Paleolithic Continuity Theory]].

===Position of Sanskrit===
Vedic Sanskrit conserves many archaic aspects, in the words of  T. Burrow: &quot;Vedic is a language which in most respects is more archaic and less altered from original Indo-European than any other member of the family&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;T Burrow&amp;nbsp;— The Sanskrit Language (1973): &quot;Vedic is a language which ''in most respects is more archaic and less altered'' from original Indo-European ''than any other member'' of the family&quot; (34: emphasis added); he also states that root nouns, &quot;very much in decline in the earliest recorded Indo-European languages&quot;, are preserved better in Sanskrit, and later adds, &quot;Chiefly owing to its antiquity the Sanskrit language is more readily analysable, and its roots more easily separable from accretionary elements than... any other IE language&quot; (123, 289); see also Beekes, R.S.P., 1990: Vergelijkende Taalwetenschap cited by K Elst 2005. Tussen Sanskrit en Nederlands, Het Spectrum, Utrecht, &quot;The distribution [of the two stems as/s for &quot;to be&quot;] in Sanskrit is the oldest one&quot; (Beekes 1990:37); &quot;PIE had 8 cases, which Sanskrit still has&quot; (Beekes 1990:122); &quot;PIE had no definite article. That is also true for Sanskrit and [[Latin]], and still for [[Russian language|Russian]]. Other languages developed one&quot; (Beekes 1990:125); &quot;[For the declensions] we ought to reconstruct the [[Proto-Indo-Iranian]] first,... But we will do with the [[Sanskrit]] because we know that it has preserved the essential information of the [[Proto-Indo-Iranian]]&quot; (Beekes 1990:148); &quot;While the accentuation systems of the other languages indicate a total rupture, Sanskrit, and to a lesser extent Greek, seem to continue the original IE situation&quot; (Beekes 1990:187); &quot;The root aorist... is still frequent in Indo-Iranian, appears sporadically in Greek and Armenian, and has disappeared elsewhere&quot; (Beekes 1990:279)&lt;/ref&gt;

Kazanas argues that linguistic stability corresponds to geographic stability, claiming that if &quot;the Indo-Aryans were on the move over many thousands of miles (from the [[steppe|Russian steppe]], [[Europe]] and/or [[Anatolia]]) over a very long period of centuries encountering many different other cultures&quot;, their &quot;language should have suffered faster and greater changes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot; &gt;[http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/pdf/rie.pdf A new date for the Rgveda] by N Kazanas published in Philosophy and Chronology, 2000, ed G C Pande &amp; D Krishna, special issue of Journal of Indian Council of Philosophical Research (June, 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|p=144}} points out that this reasoning can be countered by arguing that Vedic retained the Indo-European accent because, as a [[Sacred language|sacerdotal language]], it artificially preserved forms that would otherwise have evolved in a normal spoken language. Vedic Sanskrit is, like other [[sacred language]]s, an [[extinct language]], having evolved into [[Classical Sanskrit]] by the 6th century BC, reaching stability long after Northern India had been settled by Indo-Aryans.

By contrast, [[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]] is a [[living language|living]], [[vernacular]] language that has preserved Indo-European archaisms to the present day, thousands of years longer than Vedic did.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|pp=239–240}} &quot;Lithuanian, for example, preserves archaic Indo-European features to this very day.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Meillet | first = A. | authorlink = Antoine Meillet | title = Introduction à l'étude comparative des langues indo-européennes | edition = 2&lt;sup&gt;ème&lt;/sup&gt; corrigé et augmentée | year = 1908 | publisher = Hachette | location = Paris | language = French | quote =Le lituanien est remarquable par son aspect d'antiquité indo-européenne; il est frappant d'y trouve encore au XVI&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; siècle et jusqu'aujourd'hui des formes qui recouvrent exactement des formes védiques ou homériques et qui reproduisent presque parfaitement des formes indo-européennes supposées &quot;Lithuanian is remarkable for its aspect of Indo-European antiquity; it is striking to still find in Lithuanian in the 16th century and until today forms which are exactly congruent with Vedic or Homeric forms and which reproduce almost perfectly supposed Indo-European forms.&quot; | page = 46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Philology==
The determination of the age in which Vedic literature started and flourished has its consequences for the Indo-Aryan question.  The oldest text, the [[Rigveda]], is full of precise references to places and natural phenomena in what are now Punjab and Haryana, and was unmistakably recorded in that part of India.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}}  The date at which it was composed is a firm ''[[terminus ante quem]]'' for the presence of the Vedic Aryans in India. In the academic mainstream view it was composed in mid to late 2nd millennium BC (Late Harappan)&lt;ref&gt;But Indo-Aryan presence may predate the Rigveda by several centuries even in the immigrationist view; according to [[Asko Parpola]]'s scenario , the Rigvedic Aryans were not the first wave to reach India; his Indo-Aryan &quot;Indian Dasa&quot; were the bearers of the [[Cemetery H]] culture from around 1900 BC; Asko Parpola, 'The formation of the Aryan branch of Indo-European', in Blench and Spriggs (eds), Archaeology and Language III, London and New York (1999).&lt;/ref&gt; and OIT proponents propose a pre-Harappan date.

OIT proponents propose that bulk of Rigveda was composed prior to Indus Valley Civilization by linking archaeological evidence with data from Vedic text and archaeo-astronomical evidence.

===Sarasvati River===
{{Main|Sarasvati river}}

Many hymns in all ten Books of the [[Rigveda]] (except the 4th) extol or mention a divine and very large river named the [[Sarasvati river|Sarasvati]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/2073159.stm BBC] ''India's miracle river ''&lt;/ref&gt; which flows mightily &quot;from the mountains to the [Indian] Ocean”.&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Rigveda]] VII, 95, 2. ''giríbhya aaZ samudraZat''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kazanas 2000:4&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Shrikant G. Talageri|Talageri]] states that &quot;the references to the Sarasvati far outnumber the references to the [[Indus]]&quot; and &quot;The Sarasvati is so important in the whole of the [[Rigveda]] that it is worshipped as one of the Three Great Goddesses&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Talageri, 2000: Ch 4: The Rigvedic Rivers&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The RigVeda&amp;nbsp;— A Historical Analysis&quot;&gt;[http://voiceofdharma.org/books/rig/ The RigVeda - A Historical Analysis] by Shrikant G. Talageri&lt;/ref&gt;

According to palaeoenvironmental scientists the desiccation of Sarasvati came about as a result of the diversion of at least two rivers that fed it, the [[Satluj]] and the [[Yamuna]]. &quot;The chain of tectonic events ... diverted the [[Satluj]] westward (into the [[Indus]]) and the Palaeo Yamuna eastward (into the [[Ganges]]) ... This explains the ‘death’ of such a mighty river (the Sarasvati) ... because its main [[tributaries|feeders]], the Satluj and Palaeo Yamuna were weaned away from it by the Indus and the Gangaa respectively”.&lt;ref&gt;Rao 1991: 77-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Feuerstein et al. 1995: 87-90&lt;/ref&gt; This ended at c 1750, but it started much earlier, perhaps with the upheavals and the large flood of 1900, or more probably 2100.&lt;ref&gt;Elst 1993: 70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allchins 1997: 117&lt;/ref&gt;  P H Francfort, utilizing images from the French satellite SPOT, finds&lt;ref&gt;Francfort 1992&lt;/ref&gt; that the large river Sarasvati is pre-Harappan altogether and started drying up in the middle of the [[4th millennium BC]]; during [[Indus Valley Civilization|Harappan]] times only a complex [[irrigation]]-canal network was being used in the southern region of the [[Indus Valley]]. With this the date should be pushed back to c 3800 BC.

The [[Nadistuti]] hymn (RV 10.75) gives a list of names of rivers where Sarasvati is merely mentioned while Sindhu receives all the praise.
This may well indicate that   [[RV 10]] could be dated to a period after the first drying up of Sarasvati  when the river lost its preeminence.&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot;/&gt; It is agreed that the tenth Book of the [[Rigveda]] is later than the others.&lt;ref&gt;(Kazanas 2000:4, 5)&lt;/ref&gt;

The 414 archeological sites along the bed of Saraswati dwarf the number of sites so far recorded along the entire stretch of the Indus River, which number only about three dozen.  About 80 percent of the sites are datable to the fourth or third millennium BCE, suggesting that the river was in its prime during this period.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bryant|2001|p=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; If this date were used for the composition of the hymns about Sarasvati, then the Indo-Aryans would necessarily have been in India in the [[4th millennium BC]].

===Items not in the Rigveda===
Some items typical of later Sanskrit literature are absent from the Rigveda. This is usually taken as strong evidence that the Rigvedic hymns have a geographical background restricted to the extreme northwest of the Indian subcontinent, corresponding to the route of immigration. OIT proponents have taken the same evidence as indicating an extremely early date for the Rigveda, predating the Harappan civilization.

*The [[Rigveda]] does not mention [[silver]], though it does mention ''ayas'' ([[metal]] or [[copper]]/[[bronze]]) and ''candra'' or ''hiran-ya'' ([[gold]]). Silver is denoted by ''rajatám híran-yam'' literally ‘white gold’ and appears in post-Rigvedic texts. There is a generally accepted demarcation line for the use of [[Silver#History|silver at around 4000 BC]] and this metal is archaeologically attested in the Harappan Civilization&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allchins 1969: 285&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rao 1991: 171&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allchins et. all cited by Kazanas 2000:1&lt;/ref&gt;

*The Rigveda makes no reference to the Harappan culture. The characteristic features of the Harappan culture are [[urban contemporary|urban]] life, large [[building]]s, permanently erected [[fire]] altars and [[brick]]s. There is no word for brick in the Rigveda and ''iswttakaa'' (brick) appears only in post-Rigvedic texts. (Kazanas 2000:13)&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot;/&gt; The Rigvedic altar is a shallow bed dug in the ground and covered with grass (e.g. RV 5.11.2, 7.43.2-3; Parpola 1988: 225). Fixed brick-altars are very common in post-Rigvedic texts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rig-Veda is pre-Harappan - 2006&quot; &gt;[http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/english/documents/RVpH.pdf  Rig-Veda is pre-Harappan] by N Kazanas&lt;/ref&gt;

*The Rigveda mentions no [[rice]] or [[cotton]]. A compound term is used which later referred to rice cakes used for sacrificial purposes, but the word vrīhí, meaning 'rice', does not occur. Rice was found in at least three Harappan sites: [[Rangpur]] ([[2000 BCE]] - [[1500 BCE]]), [[Lothal]] (c [[2000 BCE]]) and [[Mohenjodaro]] (c [[2500 BCE]]) as Piggott,&lt;ref&gt;Piggott 1961: 259&lt;/ref&gt; Grist&lt;ref&gt;Grist 1965&lt;/ref&gt; and others testify.&lt;ref&gt;Rao 1991: 24, 101, 150 etc&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, despite the importance of the rice in ritual in later times, the Rigveda makes no mention of it.  The cultivation of [[cotton]] is well attested in the Harappan civilization and is found at many sites thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Piggott et. all cited by Kazanas 2000:13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Elst 1999: Ch 5.3.10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Update on the Aryan Invasion Debate&quot;&gt;[http://voi.org/books/ait/ Update on the Aryan Invasion Debate] by Koenraad Elst&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Nakshatra]] were developed in 2400 BCE, they are important in a religious context yet the [[Rigveda]] does not mention this, which suggests the [[Rigveda]] is before 2400 BCE.  The youngest book only mentions [[constellation]]s,&lt;ref&gt;RV 10:85:2&lt;/ref&gt; a concept known to all cultures, without specifying them as lunar mansions.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Sergent: Genèse de l’Inde, 1997 p.118 cited by Elst 1999: Ch 5.5) [http://voi.org/books/ait/ Update on the Aryan Invasion Debate] by Koenraad Elst&lt;/ref&gt;

*On the other hand, it has been claimed that the [[Rigveda]] has no term for &quot;[[sword]]&quot;, while [[Bronze Age sword|Bronze swords]] were used aplenty in the [[Bactria]]n culture and in [[Pirak]]. [[Ralph Griffith]] uses “sword” twelve times in his translation, including in the old books 5 and 7, but in most cases a literal translation would be more generic &quot;sharp implement&quot; (e.g. ''{{IAST|vāśī}}''), the transition from &quot;[[dagger]]&quot; to &quot;[[sword]]&quot; in the [[Bronze Age]] being a gradual process.

The fore-mentioned features are found in post Rigvedic texts&amp;nbsp;– the Samhitas, the Brahmanas and fully in the Sutra literature. For instance, brick altars are mentioned in Satapatha Brahmanaṇa 7.1.1.37, or 10.2.3.1 etc. Rice ( ''vrihi'' ) is found in AV 6.140.2; 7.1.20; etc. Cotton karpasa appears first in Gautama’s (1.18) and in Bandhāyana's (14.13.10) Dharmasūtra. The fact of the convergence of the post-Rigvedic texts and the Harappan culture was noted long ago by archaeologists. [[Bridget Allchin|Bridget]] and [[F. Raymond Allchin]] stated unequivocally that these features are of the kind “described in detail in the later Vedic literature” (1982: 203).&lt;ref name=&quot;Rig-Veda is pre-Harappan - 2006&quot; &gt;[http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/english/documents/RVpH.pdf  Rig-Veda is pre-Harappan Pg.6] by N Kazanas&lt;/ref&gt;

Based on these set of statements, OIT proponents argue that the whole of the RV, except for some few passages which may be of later date, must have been composed prior to Indus Valley Civilization.&lt;ref name=&quot;A new date for the Rgveda&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Update on the Aryan Invasion Debate&quot;/&gt;

===Memories of an Urheimat===
The fact that the Vedas&lt;ref&gt;Cardona 2002: 33-35; Cardona, George. The Indo-Aryan languages, RoutledgeCurzon; 2002 ISBN 0-7007-1130-9&lt;/ref&gt; do not mention the Aryans' presence in India as being the result of a migration or mention any possible [[Urheimat]], has been taken as an argument in favour of the OIT. The reasoning is that it is not uncommon for migrational accounts to be found in early mythological and religious texts, a classical example being the [[Book of Exodus]] in the [[Torah]], describing the legendary migration of the Israelites from Egypt to Canaan.

Proponents of the OIT, such as Koenraad Elst, argue that it would have been expectable that migrations, and possibly an Urheimat were mentioned in the Rigveda if the Aryans had only arrived in India some centuries before the composition of the earliest Rigvedic hymns. They argue that other migration stories of other Indo-European people have been documented historically or archaeologically, and that the same would be expectable if the Indo-Aryans had migrated into India.&lt;ref name=&quot;Update on the Aryan Invasion Debate&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Elst 1999: Ch 4.6&lt;/ref&gt;

From the mainstream academic viewpoint, the concern is the degree of historical accuracy that can be expected from the Rigveda, which is a collection of hymns, not an account of tribal history, and those hymns assumed to reach back to within a few centuries of the period of Indo-Aryan arrival in Gandhara make for just a small portion of the text.&lt;ref&gt;e.g. Thomas Oberlies, Die Religion des Rgveda, Wien 1998, p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt;

Regarding migration of Indo-Aryans and imposing language on Harappans, Kazanas notes that &quot;The intruders would have been able to rename the rivers only if they were conquerors with the power to impose this. And, of course, the same is true of their Vedic language: since no people would bother of their own free will to learn a difficult, inflected foreign language, unless they had much to gain by this, and since the Aryan immigrants had adopted the “material culture and lifestyle” of the Harappans&lt;ref&gt;Allchins 1997: 223&lt;/ref&gt; and consequently had little or nothing to offer to the natives, the latter would have adopted the new language only under pressure. Thus here again we discover that the substratum thinking is invasion and conquest.&quot; &quot;But invasion is the substratum of all such theories even if words like ‘migration’ are used. There could not have been an Aryan immigration because (apart from the fact that there is no archaeological evidence for this) the results would have been quite different. Immigrants do not impose their own demands or desires on the natives of the new country: they are grateful for being accepted, for having the use of lands and rivers for farming or pasturing and for any help they receive from the natives; in time it is they who adopt the language (and perhaps the religion) of the natives. You cannot have a migration with the results of an invasion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;`The AIT and scholarship' by Kazanas  July 2001 Page 2,3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Material archaeology==

The opinion of the majority of professional archaeologists interviewed seems to be that there is no archaeological evidence to support external Indo-Aryan origins.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bryant|2001|p=231}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus while the linguistic community stands firm with the [[Kurgan hypothesis]] archaeological community tends to be more agnostic.

According to one archaeologist, J.M. Kenoyer:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Although the overall socioeconomic organization changed, continuities in [[technology]], subsistence practices, settlement organization, and some regional [[symbols]] show that the indigenous population was not displaced by invading hordes of [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indo-Aryan]] speaking people. For many years, the ‘invasions’ or ‘migrations’ of these Indo-Aryan-speaking Vedic/Aryan tribes explained the decline of the Indus civilization and the sudden rise of urbanization in the Ganga-[[Yamuna]] valley. This was based on simplistic models of culture change and an uncritical reading of Vedic texts...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;J. M. Kenoyer: “The Indus Valley Tradition of Pakistan and Western India”, Journal of World Prehistory, 1991/4; cited in Bryant 2001:190&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The examination of 300 skeletons from the Indus Valley Civilization and comparison of those skeletons with modern-day Indians by [[Kenneth A. R. Kennedy|Kenneth Kennedy]] has also been a supporting argument for the OIT. Kennedy claims that the Harappan inhabitants of the Indus Valley Civilization are no different from the inhabitants of India in the following millennia.&lt;ref&gt;(Hemphill, Lukacs and Kennedy 1991, see also Kenneth Kennedy 1995)&lt;/ref&gt; However, this does not rule out one version of the Aryan Migration Hypothesis which suggests that the only &quot;migration&quot; was one of languages as opposed to a complete displacement of the indigenous population.

Haüsler (as cited in {{Harvcolnb|Bryant|2001|p=141}}) also found that archaeological evidence in central Europe showed continuous linear development, with no marked external influences.

{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|p=236}} grants that &quot;there is at least a series of archaeological cultures that can be traced approaching the Indian subcontinent, even if discontinuous, which does not seem to be the case for any hypothetical east-to-west emigration.&quot;

==Genetic anthropology==
{{Main|Genetics and Archaeogenetics of South Asia}}
[[File:Y-Haplogroup R1 distribution.png|thumb|250px|Distribution of R1a (purple) and R1b (red)]]
Unlike the Indo-European migration hypothesis, there is no clear genetic evidence for a prehistoric migration out of India. There is no evidence of widespread genetic displacement in Europe after the Paleolithic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | author=Richards et al. | year=1996 | title=Paleolithic and neolithic lineages in the European mitochondrial gene pool | periodical=American journal of human genetics |volume=59 |issue=1 | pages=185–203}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | author=Semino et al. | year=2000 | last2=Passarino | first2=G | last3=Oefner | first3=PJ | last4=Lin | first4=AA | last5=Arbuzova | first5=S | last6=Beckman | first6=LE | last7=De Benedictis | first7=G | last8=Francalacci | first8=P | last9=Kouvatsi | first9=A | title=The Genetic Legacy of Paleolithic ''Homo sapiens sapiens'' in Extant Europeans: A Y Chromosome Perspective  | periodical=Science |volume=290 |issue=5494 | pages=1155–1159 | doi=10.1126/science.290.5494.1155 | pmid=11073453|bibcode = 2000Sci...290.1155S }}.&lt;/ref&gt; And {{Harvtxt|Hemphill|1998}} finds &quot;no support for any model that calls for the ultimate origins of north Bactrian oasis Oxus Civilization populations to be inhabitants of the Indus Valley.&quot;

The virtual absence of India-specific [[Human mitochondrial DNA haplogroup|mtDNA haplogroups]] outside of India argues against a large scale population movement out of India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Chaubey et al.|2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tracing a possible &quot;out of India&quot; migration has therefore until recently focused upon [[Human Y-chromosome DNA haplogroups|Y-chromosome haplogroups]]. Concerning Y DNA, [[Haplogroup R2 (Y-DNA)|haplogroup R2]] is characterized by [[genetic marker]] M124, and is rarely found outside India, Pakistan, Iran, and southern Central Asia. Outside of southern Eurasia, M124 was found at an unusually high frequency of 0.440 among the [[Kurmanji]] of [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], but at a much lower frequency of only 0.080 among the [[Kurmanji]] of [[Turkmenistan]]. The M124 frequency of 0.158 found among [[Chechen people|Chechens]] may be unrepresentative because it was derived from a [[sample size]] of only 19 Chechens. Outside of these populations and the [[Romani people]], M124 is not found in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Kivisild|2003}}&lt;br&gt;{{Citation | author=Nasidze et al. | year=2005 | periodical=Annals of Human Genetics |volume=69 | pages=401–412 | doi=10.1046/j.1529-8817.2005.00174.x | title=MtDNA and Y-chromosome Variation in Kurdish Groups | pmid=15996169 | last2=Quinque | first2=D | last3=Ozturk | first3=M | last4=Bendukidze | first4=N | last5=Stoneking | first5=M | issue=Pt 4}}.&lt;br&gt;{{Citation | author=Nasidze et al. | year=2003 | periodical=Hum Genet |volume=112 | pages=255–261}}.&lt;br&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Wells et al.|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mass movements of people to or from India that might be associated with the spread of Indo-European languages have tended to revolve around [[Haplogroup R1a1 (Y-DNA)|Y-chromosome haplogroup R1a1]], which is identified with the M17 mutation. On the one hand, this Y lineage is found in higher levels amongst northern Indians and amongst higher castes, and is also found in modern populations in Central Asia and Eastern Europe.&lt;ref name=sw167&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Wells|2002|p=167}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ichg2011.org/cgi-bin/ichg11s?abst=stepanov%20hindustan&amp;sort=ptimes&amp;sbutton=Detail&amp;absno=20168&amp;sid=252250&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the pattern within India is not always so clear, with lower castes and southern populations also sometimes showing high levels, and in fact several studies have proposed that the deepest roots of this lineage may be in or near India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Kivisild et al.|2003}}, Mirabal et al. (2009), Underhill et al. (2009), Sengupta et al. (2005), Sahoo et al. (2006), Sharma et al. (2009), and Thangaraj et al. (2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

The latest research conducted by Watkins et al. (2008) questions the use of uniparental markers such as the [[Y chromosome]] or [[mitochondrial]] DNA, neither of which is immune to the effects of [[natural selection]]; they also argue for the need to analyze [[autosomal]] polymorphisms in conjunction with [[Y-chromosomal]] and [[mitochondrial]] DNA in order to generate a more comprehensive picture of population genetic structure. The authors of the study write: &quot;The historical record documents an influx of Vedic Indo-European-speaking immigrants into northwest India starting at least 3500 years ago. These immigrants spread southward and eastward into an existing agrarian society dominated by Dravidian speakers. With time, a more highly-structured patriarchal caste system developed ... our data are consistent with a model in which nomadic populations from northwest and central Eurasia intercalated over millennia into an already complex, genetically diverse set of subcontinental populations. As these populations grew, mixed, and expanded, a system of social stratification likely developed in situ, spreading to the Indo-Gangetic plain, and then southward over the Deccan plateau.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2621241/?tool=pubmed&lt;/ref&gt;

Reich et al. (2009) indicates that the modern Indian population is a result of admixture between Indo-European (ANI) and Dravidian (ASI) populations. The authors of the study write: &quot;It is tempting to assume that the population ancestral to ANI and CEU spoke 'Proto-Indo-European', which has been reconstructed as ancestral to both Sanskrit and European languages, although we cannot be certain without a date for ANI–ASI mixture.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://genepath.med.harvard.edu/~reich/2009_Nature_Reich_India.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Recent research indicates a massive admixture event between ANI-ASI populations 1200 to 3500 years ago, &quot;overlapping the time when Indo-European languages first began to be spoken in the subcontinent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ichg2011.org/cgi-bin/showdetail.pl?absno=20758&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
*The linguistic center of gravity principle states that a language family's most likely point of origin is in the area of its greatest diversity. Only one branch of Indo-European, Indo-Aryan, is found in India, whereas the [[Italic languages|Italic]], [[Venetic language|Venetic]], [[Illyrian languages|Illyrian]], [[Germanic languages|Germanic]], [[Baltic languages|Baltic]], [[Slavic languages|Slavic]], [[Thracian language|Thracian]], and [[Greek language|Greek]] branches of Indo-European are all found in Central-Eastern Europe. Because it requires a greater number of long migrations, an Indian Urheimat is far less likely than one closer to the center of Indo-European linguistic diversity.&lt;ref name=jpm152/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Sapir|1949|p=455}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dyen (1965), as quoted in {{Harvnb|Bryant|2001|p=142}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the existence of the [[Tocharian languages|Tocharian]] language family in Western China would shift the center of gravity eastward.  Some scholars argue that the various language families in Central and Eastern Europe evolved fairly recently, which implies that there was less diversity in the western side of the Indo-European language family during the 2nd millennium BCE at a time contemporaneous with Vedic Sanskrit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Bryant|2001|p=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*The Indic languages show the influence of the [[Dravidian languages|Dravidian]] and [[Munda languages|Munda]] language families. No other branch of Indo-European does. If the Indo-European homeland had been located in India, then the Indo-European languages should have shown some influence from Dravidian and Munda.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Parpola|2005|p=48}}. &quot;...numerous loanwords and even structural borrowings from Dravidian have been identified in Sanskrit texts composed in northwestern India at the end of the second and first half of the first millennium BCE, before any intensive contact between North and South India. External evidence thus suggests that the Harappans most probably spoke a Dravidian language.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Mallory|1989|p=44}}. &quot;The most obvious explanation of this situation is that the Dravidian languages once occupied nearly all of the Indian subcontinent and it is the intrusion of Indo-Aryans that engulfed them in north India leaving but a few isolated enclaves.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

*To postulate the migration of PIE speakers out of India necessitates an earlier dating of the Rigveda than is normally accepted by Vedic scholars in order to make a deep enough period of migration to allow for the longest migrations to be completed.{{Harv|Mallory|1989}}{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}

==See also==
* [[Indigenous Aryan Theory]]
* [[Aryan Invasion Theory (history and controversies)]]
* [[Indo-Aryan migration]]
* [[Neolithic Europe]]
* [[Proto-Indo-European language]]
* [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]]
* [[Urheimat]]
* [[Indomania]], [[Indophobia]]
* [[In Search of the Cradle of Civilization]]

===Competing hypotheses===
* [[Anatolian hypothesis]]
* [[Armenian hypothesis]]
* [[Kurgan hypothesis]]
* [[Paleolithic Continuity Theory]]

==Notes==
&lt;!-- To add a reference simply enclose the text you want to appear here inside a &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; pair in the correct place in the body of the article.--&gt;
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography and References==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{Citation | last=Alinei | first=Mario |author-link=Mario Alinei | year=2003 | title=Linguistic and interdisciplinary evidence for Indo-European, Uralic and Altaic indigenism in Eurasia | periodical=Quaderni di semantica |volume=XXIV |issue=2}}.
*{{Citation | year=1997 | editor-last=Blench | editor-first=Roger |editor1-link=Roger Blench | editor2-last=Spriggs | editor2-first=Matthew | title=Archaeology and Language | publication-place=London | publisher=Routledge |volume=I: ''Theoretical and Methodological Orientations''}}.
*{{Citation | last =Bryant | first =Edwin | author-link =Edwin Bryant (author) | year =2001 | title =[[The Quest for the Origins of Vedic Culture]]: The Indo-Aryan Migration Debate | publisher =Oxford University Press | isbn =0195137779}}.
*{{Citation | last =Cavalli-Sforza | first =Luigi Luca |author-link=Luigi Luca Cavalli-Sforza | year =2000 | title =Genes, Peoples, and Languages | edition =  | journal =Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America| place =New York | volume =94 | issue =15 | pages =7719 | publisher =North Point Press | isbn = | pmid =9223254 | pmc =33682 | doi =10.1073/pnas.94.15.7719 | bibcode =1997PNAS...94.7719C}}.
*{{Citation | author=Chaubey et al. | author-link=Toomas Kivisild | year=2007 | title=Peopling of South Asia: investigating the caste-tribe continuum in India | periodical=BioEssays |volume=29 |issue=1 | pages=91–100 | doi=10.1002/bies.20525 | pmid=17187379 | last2=Metspalu | first2=M | last3=Kivisild | first3=T | last4=Villems | first4=R}}.
*{{Citation | last=Diakonoff | first=Igor M. | author-link=Igor Diakonov | year=1995 | title=Two Recent Studies of Indo-Iranian Origins | periodical=Journal of the American Oriental Society |volume=115 |issue=3 | pages=473–477 | doi=10.2307/606224 | jstor=606224 | publisher=American Oriental Society | last2=Kuz'mina | first2=E. E. | last3=Ivantchik | first3=Askold I.}}.
*{{Citation| last=Dyen | first=Isidore |author-link=Isidore Dyen |title=A Lexostatistical Classification of the Austronesian Languages |journal=International Journal of American Linguistics (suppl.) |volume=31 |year=1965 |pages=1–64}}
*{{Citation | last =Elst | first =Koenraad | author-link =Koenraad Elst | year =1999 | title =Update on the Aryan Invasion Debate | place =New Delhi | publisher =[[Aditya Prakashan]] | isbn =81-86471-77-4 | url =http://voi.org/books/ait/}}.
*{{Citation | publication-date=1995 | editor-last=Erdosy | editor-first=George | title=The Indo-Aryans of Ancient South Asia: Language, Material Culture and Ethnicity | publication-place=Berlin/New York | publisher=Walter de Gruyter | isbn=3110144476 | year=1995}}.
*{{Citation | last=Handwerk | first=Brian | title=India Acquired Language, Not Genes, From West, Study Says | newspaper=National Geographic | date=January 10, 2006 | url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/01/0110_060110_india_genes_2.html}}.
*{{Citation | last=Hemphill | first=Brian E. | author-link= | last2=Lukacs | first2=John R. | author2-link=John R. Lukacs | last3=Kennedy | first3=K.A.R. | author3-link=Kenneth A. R. Kennedy | publication-date=1991 | contribution=Biological Adaptations and Affinities of the Bronze Age Harappans | editor-last=Meadow | editor-first=Richard H. | title=Harappa Excavations 1986–1990: A Multidisciplinary Approach to Third Millennium Urbanism | publication-place=Madison, WI | publisher=Prehistory Press}}.
*{{Citation | last=Hemphill | first=Brian E. | author-link= | year=1998 | title=Biological Affinities and Adaptations of Bronze Age Bactrians: III. An Initial Craniometric Assessment | periodical=''[[American Journal of Physical Anthropology]]'' |volume=106 | issue=3 | pages=329–348 | doi=10.1002/(SICI)1096-8644(199807)106:3&lt;329::AID-AJPA6&gt;3.0.CO;2-H}}.
*{{Citation| author = Kazanas, Nicholas| title = A new date for the Rgveda | version =| publisher = special issue of Journal of Indian Council of Philosophical Research | date =  June, 2001  | url = http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/pdf/rie.pdf | format = [[PDF]]| accessdate =| postscript = . }}
*{{Citation | last=Kazanas | first=N. | author-link=Nicholas Kazanas | year=2002 | title=Indigenous Indo-Aryans and the ''Rigveda'' | periodical=Journal of Indo-European Studies |volume=30 | pages=275–334 | url = http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/pdf/en/indology/IIR.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = 30 December 2009 }}.
*{{Citation | last=Kazanas | first=N. | author-link=Nicholas Kazanas | year=2003 | title=Final Reply | periodical=Journal of Indo-European Studies |volume=31 | pages=187–240 | url = http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/pdf/en/indology/Final%20Reply.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = 30 December 2009}}.
*{{Citation | author=Kivisild et al. | author-link=Toomas Kivisild | year=2003 | title=The Genetic Heritage of the Earliest Settlers Persists Both in Indian Tribal and Caste Populations | periodical=Am. J. Hum. Genet. |volume=72 | pages=313–332 | url=http://evolutsioon.ut.ee/publications/Kivisild2003b.pdf|format=PDF | doi=10.1086/346068 | pmid=12536373 | last2=Rootsi | first2=S | last3=Metspalu | first3=M | last4=Mastana | first4=S | last5=Kaldma | first5=K | last6=Parik | first6=J | last7=Metspalu | first7=E | last8=Adojaan | first8=M | last9=Tolk | first9=HV | issue=2 | pmc=379225}}.
*{{Citation | last =Kuz'mina | first =Elena Efimovna |author-link=Elena Kuz'mina | year =1994 | title =Откуда пришли индоарии? (Whence came the Indo-Aryans) | place =Moscow | publisher =Российская академия наук ([[Russian Academy of Sciences]])}}.
* {{Citation | last =Kuz'mina | first= Elena Efimovna |author-link=Elena Kuz'mina |year=2007 |publisher=Brill |editor-first=James Patrick |editor-last=Mallory |editor-link=J. P. Mallory |title= The Origin of the Indo-Iranians |series=Leiden Indo-European Etymological Dictionary Series |location=Leiden }}
* [[J. P. Mallory|Mallory, J. P.]] 1998. A European Perspective on Indo-Europeans in Asia. In: The Bronze Age and Early Iron Age Peoples of Eastern and Central Asia. Ed. Mair. Washingion DC: Institute for the Study of Man.
*{{Citation | last=Mallory | first=J. P. | author-link=J. P. Mallory | year=2002 | title=Editor's Note | periodical=Journal of Indo-European Studies |volume=30 | pages=274}}.
*{{Citation|last1=Mirabal|year=2009|first1=Sheyla|last2=Regueiro|first2=M|last3=Cadenas|first3=AM|last4=Cavalli-Sforza|first4=LL|last5=Underhill|first5=PA|last6=Verbenko|first6=DA|last7=Limborska|first7=SA|last8=Herrera|first8=RJ|title=Y-Chromosome distribution within the geo-linguistic landscape of northwestern Russia|journal=European Journal of Human Genetics|pmid=19259129|volume=17|issue=10|pmc=2986641|pages=1260–1273|doi=10.1038/ejhg.2009.6}}
*{{Citation | surname=Parpola | given=Asko | authorlink=Asko Parpola | year=1998 | chapter=Aryan Languages, Archaeological Cultures, and Sinkiang: Where Did Proto-Iranian Come into Being and How Did It Spread? | editor=Mair | title=The Bronze Age and Early Iron Age Peoples of Eastern and Central Asia | publisher=Institute for the Study of Man | place=Washington, D.C.}}
*{{Citation | last=Parpola | first=Asko | author-link=Asko Parpola | year=2005 | contribution=Study of the Indus script | title=Transactions of the 50th International Conference of Eastern Studies | place=Tokyo | publisher=The Tôhô Gakkai | pages=28–66}}.
*{{Citation | author=Sahoo et al. | year=2006 | title=A prehistory of Indian Y chromosomes: Evaluating demic diffusion scenarios | periodical=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences |volume=103 |issue=4 | pages=843–848 | url=http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content/full/103/4/843 | doi=10.1073/pnas.0507714103 | pmid=16415161 | last2=Singh | first2=A | last3=Himabindu | first3=G | last4=Banerjee | first4=J | last5=Sitalaximi | first5=T | last6=Gaikwad | first6=S | last7=Trivedi | first7=R | last8=Endicott | first8=P | last9=Kivisild | first9=T | pmc=1347984 | bibcode=2006PNAS..103..843S}}.
*{{Citation | last=Sapir | first=Edward | author-link=Edward Sapir | year=1949 | publication-date=1985 | editor-last=Mandelbaum | editor-first=David G. | editor-link= | title=Selected Writings in Language, Culture, and Personality | publisher=University of California Press}}.
*{{Citation | last1=Sengupta| year=2005 | first1=S | last2=Zhivotovsky | first2=LA | last3=King | first3=R | last4=Mehdi | first4=SQ | last5=Edmonds | first5=CA | last6=Chow | first6=CE | last7=Lin | first7=AA | last8=Mitra | first8=M | last9=Sil | first9=SK | title=Polarity and Temporality of High-Resolution Y-Chromosome Distributions in India Identify Both Indigenous and Exogenous Expansions and Reveal Minor Genetic Influence of Central Asian Pastoralists | periodical=Am. J. Hum. Genet. | volume=78 | issue=2 | pages=202–21 | pmid=16400607 | pmc=1380230 | doi=10.1086/499411}}.
*{{Citation | last = Sharma et al.| title = The Autochthonous Origin and a Tribal Link of Indian Brahmins: Evaluation Through Molecular Genetic Markers| journal = THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF HUMAN GENETICS 57th Annual Meeting| volume = | issue = | pages = | date = | year = 2007| url = http://www.ashg.org/genetics/ashg/annmeet/2007/call/abstractbook.pdf| doi = }}
*{{Citation | last1 = Sharma | first1 = S | last2 = Rai | first2 = E | last3 = Sharma | first3 = P | last4 = Jena | first4 = M | last5 = Singh | first5 = S | last6 = Darvishi | first6 = K | last7 = Bhat | first7 = AK | last8 = Bhanwer | first8 = AJ | last9 = Tiwari | first9 = PK| title = The Indian origin of paternal haplogroup R1a1(*)substantiates the autochthonous origin of Brahmins and the caste system| journal = J. Hum.Genet.| volume =54| issue =1| pages =47–55| year = 2009| url = http://www.nature.com/jhg/journal/v54/n1/abs/jhg20082a.html| doi =10.1038/jhg.2008.2| pmid =19158816}}
*{{Citation | last =Talageri | first =Shrikant G. | author-link =Shrikant G. Talageri | year =2000 | title =The Rigveda: A Historical Analysis | place =New Delhi | publisher =[[Aditya Prakashan]] | isbn =8177420100 | url =http://www.voiceofdharma.com/books/rig/ | accessdate =May 2007}}.
*{{Citation | last =Thomason | first =Sarah Grey | author-link = | last2 =Kaufman | first2 =Terrence | author2-link = | publication-date =1991 | year =1988 | title =Language Contact, Creolization, and Genetic Linguistics | publisher =University of California Press | isbn =0-520-07893-4}}.
*{{Citation | last=Tikkanen | first=Bertil | year=1999 | contribution=Archaeological-linguistic correlations in the formation of retroflex typologies and correlating areal features in South Asia | editor-last=Blench | editor-first=Roger | editor2-last=Spriggs | editor2-first=Matthew | title=Archaeology and Language | publication-place=London | publisher=Routledge  |volume=IV: ''Language Change and Cultural Transformation'' | pages=138–148}}.
*{{citation|title=The Influence of Natural Barriers in Shaping the Genetic Structure of Maharashtra Populations|url=http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0015283|last1=Thangaraj |last2=Naidu |last3=Crivellaro |last4= Tamang |last5= Upadhyay | year=2010 | journal=PLoS ONE |volume=5 |issue=12|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0015283}}
*{{Citation|last1=Underhill|first1=Peter A|last2=Myres|year=2009|page=479|first2=Natalie M|last3=Rootsi|first3=Siiri|last4=Metspalu|first4=Mait|last5=Zhivotovsky|first5=Lev A|last6=King|issue=4|first6=Roy J|last7=Lin|first7=Alice A|last8=Chow|first8=Cheryl-Emiliane T|last9=Semino|first9=Ornella|title=Separating the post-Glacial coancestry of European and Asian Y chromosomes within haplogroup R1a|volume=18|journal=European Journal of Human Genetics|doi=10.1038/ejhg.2009.194|pmid=19888303|pmc=2987245}}
*{{Citation | last =Villar | first =Francisco | year =2000 | title =Indoeuropeos y no indoeuropeos en la Hispania Prerromana | publisher =Ediciones Universidad de Salamanca | isbn =84-7800-968-X}}.
*{{Citation | author=Wells et al. | author-link=Spencer Wells | publication-date=2001-08-28 | year=2001 | title=The Eurasian Heartland: A continental perspective on Y-chromosome diversity | periodical=Proc Natl Acad Sci USA |volume=98 |issue=18 | pages=10244–10249 | doi=10.1073/pnas.171305098 | pmid=11526236 | last2=Yuldasheva | first2=N | last3=Ruzibakiev | first3=R | last4=Underhill | first4=PA | last5=Evseeva | first5=I | last6=Blue-Smith | first6=J | last7=Jin | first7=L | last8=Su | first8=B | last9=Pitchappan | first9=R | pmc=56946|bibcode = 2001PNAS...9810244W }}.
*{{Citation | last=Wells | first=Spencer | author-link=Spencer Wells | year=2002 | title=The Journey of Man: A Genetic Odyssey | publisher=Princeton University Press}}.
*{{Citation | last=Witzel | first=Michael | author-link=Michael E. J. Witzel | year=1999 | title=Substrate Languages in Old Indo-Aryan (Ṛgvedic, Middle and Late Vedic) | periodical=Electronic Journal of Vedic Studies |volume=5 |issue=1 | url=http://www.ejvs.laurasianacademy.com/ejvs0501/ejvs0501article.pdf|format=PDF}}.
*{{Citation | last=Witzel | first=Michael | author-link=Michael E. J. Witzel | date=2000-02-17 | publication-date= | contribution=The Languages of Harappa | contribution-url=http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/~witzel/IndusLang.pdf | editor-last=Kenoyer | editor-first=J. | editor-link=Jonathan Mark Kenoyer | title=Proceedings of the conference on the Indus civilization | place=Madison | publication-place= | accessdate =2007-07-18}}.
*{{Citation | last=Witzel | first=Michael | author-link=Michael E. J. Witzel | year=2003 | title=Ein Fremdling im Rgveda | periodical=Journal of Indo-European Studies |volume=31 |issue=1–2 | pages=107–185}}.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/english/documents/RVpH.pdf  Rig-Veda is pre-Harappan] by Nicholas Kazanas
*[http://www.omilosmeleton.gr/pdf/rdp.pdf The RV date&amp;nbsp;— a postscript] by Nicholas Kazanas
*[http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/articles/aid/keaitlin1.html Linguistic aspects of the Aryan non-invasion theory] ([[Koenraad Elst]])
*[http://voi.org/books/rig/index.htm  The RigVeda - A Historical Analysis] by Shrikant Talageri
*[http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/rigveda/index.htm The RigVeda Index] Ralph T.H. Griffith, Translator 1896
*[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/ifihhome/articles/bbl001.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+00:21:54 The Homeland of Indo-European Languages and Culture: Some Thoughts] By [[B.B. Lal]]
*[http://www.indiastar.com/ancient.htm Book Review by C. J. S. Wallia]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Out Of India Theory}}
[[Category:Hindutva]]
[[Category:Indo-European]]
[[Category:Indology]]

[[de:Out-of-India-Theorie]]
[[no:Ut fra India teorien]]
[[ru:Теория исхода из Индии]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
