<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6460599" ns="0" title="Ancient technology in Stargate"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|primarysources=April 2009|in-universe=April 2009}}
The [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]] (also known as &quot;Alterans&quot; and &quot;Lanteans&quot;) are a fictional advanced race in the [[Stargate Program|Stargate]] franchise, and are depicted as the precursor to modern-day humans. Their most notable creation in Stargate mythology is the entire [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] network. Ancient science and technology, with a few exceptions, is shown as being superior to that of other races. The Ancients are portrayed as being extremely advanced in the areas of healing, power generation, and biology. They are also credited with designing a number of fictional weapons, primarily for use in the centuries-long war with the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] in the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]]. [[Ori technology in Stargate]] is shown as similar to that of the Ancients, since they are also depicted as ascended beings. In Stargate chronology, all Ancient technology was created prior to their [[Ascension (Stargate)|ascension]], with the exception of the [[Ascension (Stargate SG-1)|Velona]] weapon, assisted by the character [[Orlin]], and the weapon created by the character [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Moros.2FMyrddin.2FMerlin|Merlin]] to destroy ascended beings. However, not all the artifacts credited to the Ancients are depicted as a complete success.

==Power sources==
Ancient technology has varied in power and capability over the passage of many millions of years.  Early Ancient technology has shown various advantages over Later Period Ancient technology for inexplicable reasons.  The multi-million-year old vessel ''Destiny'' possesses an early hyperdrive system that manages FTL travel in normal space with the use of multiple modular drives, giving it vastly superior speed to the later hyperdrive systems that utilized hyperspace windows.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}  ''Destiny'' also possesses the ability to convert plasma discharges from the chromosphere of a sun into energy without damage, giving it the ability to recharge at any point in travel while Late Period Ancient ships were more fragile and required an exhaustible power supply provided by ZPMs.  While certain prototypical properties of Destiny such as shields, weapons, and interface technology improved significantly over time, the reasons for the loss of many superior advantages of Early Period Ancient technology have not been explained.  Ancient beings themselves have also expressed a similar loss of advanced abilities over millions of years; the Stargate device was conceived by an Alteran during a dream on the eve of the exodus from the Ori galaxy, but by the end of the war with the Wraith, Ancient scientists such as Janus required lengthy periods of work to create equally powerful technology such as time-travel.

===Zero Point Module {{anchor|ZPM}}===
[[File:Zeropointmodule.jpg|thumb|upright|Zero Point Module (ZPM)]]
A fictional Ancient power source used to power their cities and outposts. ZPMs supposedly extract vacuum energy from a small artificially-created region of subspace,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Rising&quot; (Stargate Atlantis)&lt;/ref&gt; based on the concept of [[zero-point energy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;zpenergy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Zero Point Energy goes Hollywood! |url=http://www.zpenergy.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=831 |accessdate=2008-03-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ZPMs are depicted as more powerful and efficient than fictional [[Naquadah]] generators or any conventional energy source on present day Earth, and are shown as lasting for thousands of years.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rising&quot; (Stargate Atlantis)&lt;/ref&gt;

The first ZPM is found by [[Jack O'Neill]] in the ''SG-1'' season 7 finale &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot; at an abandoned outpost, and used to power Ancient weaponry left behind on Earth to repel [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]]' attack on Earth. The same ZPM allows [[Stargate Command]] to open a wormhole to [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] in the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; Another is found on Earth in an alternate timeline and allows Earth to send supplies and reinforcements to Atlantis.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; The finding and recapturing of ZPMs is a recurring theme on ''Stargate Atlantis'', being a necessary asset to protect the city from attacks and invasion, to power the city (e.g., for space travel) and to accelerate [[Earth starships in Stargate|Earth ships]] in-between galaxies. However, they also have destructive powers, which has been misused by [[Camulus (Stargate)|Camulus]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Zero Hour (Stargate SG-1)|Zero Hour]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Trust (Stargate)|Trust]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Critical Mass (Stargate Atlantis)|Critical Mass]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and McKay aboard an [[Asuran]] [[Ancient City Ship|City ship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Progeny&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Progeny (Stargate Atlantis)| title=Progeny| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the ''[[Stargate Atlantis|Atlantis]]'' characters and aliens pronounce ZPM as ''[[Zee]]-P-M'' (with an American accent). The team's Canadian scientist, [[Rodney McKay]], on the other hand, pronounces the abbreviation in the standard Canadian fashion, ''[[Zed]]-P-M''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Wilson |first=Mark |url=http://scifi.about.com/od/stargate/a/SGA_hewlett_3.htm |title=Interview: David Hewlett |publisher=scifi.about.com |date=March 2007 |accessdate=2008-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other power sources===
*'''Project Arcturus:''' Experimental project to extract [[vacuum energy]] from the current stargate universe, which could replace Zero Point Modules, based on Doranda. It failed and several Ancients involved died trying to shut it down. The Atlantis Expedition discovers the device, but run into the same problem: the device constantly generates new and exotic particles that would make it impossible to stabilize, which causes the destruction of 5/6 of the solar system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trinity&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Trinity|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Atlantis team later experiments with shunting the exotic particles to another universe. However, the other universe is inhabited, and an alternate McKay travels to Atlantis to stem the damage being done to his universe.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKay and Mrs. Miller&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|McKay and Mrs. Miller|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Ram scoop]] like devices:''' The Ancient starship ''[[Destiny (Stargate)|Destiny]]'' is powered by a series of devices similar to ram scoops on each &quot;fin&quot; at the rear of the ship. The vessel flies through the corona of a star to recharge its reactors. The shields protect the vessel from the intense solar heat while this process occurs.
*'''Submerged Geothermal Station:''' A small facility the Ancients constructed to find an area where volcanic activity was close to the surface. Once found, the Ancients made use of the planet's geothermal energy. An umbilical cord is tethered from the facility to Atlantis to deliver power.
*'''Supervolcano Geothermal Facility''': A large Ancient outpost was discovered on Taranis, a planet in the Pegasus galaxy where the Orion was also stored. This outpost contained an Ancient shield and utilized geothermal energy from a dormant supervolcano. Excessive use of the facility destabilized the volcano, resulting in an eruption which rendered the planet uninhabitable.
*'''O'Neill's jury-rigged device:''' The first time that Colonel Jack O'Neill had the knowledge of the Ancients downloaded into his mind by an Ancient Repository of Knowledge, he used this knowledge to build a complex device that interfaced with the power supply for Earth's Stargate. The device provided the requisite amount of power for the Stargate to create a wormhole to another galaxy by depleting the liquid Naqahdah energy cell of a staff weapon, which allowed O'Neill to travel to an Asgard-controlled location in the Ida galaxy. The device he built to power the Stargate for this purpose worked only once until a second Samantha Carter arrived from a parallel universe, and the two Carters managed to figure it out so that the Alternate-Carter could return to her universe via the Quantum Mirror and contact the Asgard (by travelling to the Asgard's home galaxy via Stargate) to stop the Goa'uld Apophis from conquering Earth, similar to what Daniel Jackson had witnessed when he discovered the Quantum Mirror on an abandoned planet.

==Shielding==
[[Shield (science fiction)|Shields]] were used by the Ancients aboard their ships and outposts. Ancient shields prove to be almost impenetrable, as long as sufficient power is maintained to operate them. In contrast, the shields of other races, such as the Goa'uld and Asgard, are weakened directly by outside forces, like enemy fire and natural phenomena, causing them to fail or diminish in capacity rather quickly in cases of extreme stress. Various types of shields include:
*'''Prison cell shield:''' Ancient prison cells are known to employ shields between their bars to prevent occupants from escaping, as shown within Atlantis as well as their ships. Atlantis' sister ship was shown not to have this capability but this is most likely due to the severe lack of power available.
*'''Aurora-class shields:''' The shield of [[Aurora class warship]]s contours around the ship, like an extra hull, instead of an ordinary bubble.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot;&gt;&quot;[[No Man's Land (Stargate Atlantis)|No Man's Land]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; These shields are incredibly powerful, and have a yellow gold-like color. The ''Orion's'' shields, operating at well-below full power, were able to withstand a [[supervolcano]]'s eruption for 4.1 seconds, while using the eruption to propel it out of its hangar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inferno&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Inferno (Stargate Atlantis)|Inferno]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Atlantis' shield:''' The massive dome-like [[Force field (science fiction)|force field]] protects the city from enemy attacks,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; extreme weather,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Storm&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Storm (Stargate Atlantis)|The Storm]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and water pressure when submerged in the ocean.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; The power required to operate the shield depends on the load it is being subjected to. When interfaced with a [[Puddle Jumper]]'s cloak generator, it acts as an invisibility shield and draws less power than it normally would, though it offers no protection other than invisibility. During normal operation the shield can be sustained by one [[ZPM]]. The shield draws a substantial amount of power when under strain. The shield could only be sustained by a single ZPM for just days when under heavy attack from a [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] fleet,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; but for 10,000 years under the pressure of thousands of feet of water with only three ZPMs used in sequence.
*'''Personal shield:''' A palm-sized shield generator worn on one's person that projects a defensive barrier. It deflects any objects propelled at it, and has inertial dampeners. The shield is activated by the [[ATA gene]], and controlled by the user's mind, though the user must be trained in mind-control to override the conscious desires in the use of the device; for example, the user may believe they do not need the shield, but their subconscious may still believe they require protection, causing the shield to remain active until the danger passes. Once a person activates the device, only that person can use it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot; /&gt; However, on at least one occasion, a personal shield is worn by several users. The shield can prevent the user from eating or drinking while the device is active,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot; /&gt; but experienced users have been known to eat and drink while wearing it. The wearer still requires air to breathe, and thus is not protected from drowning or being buried alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irresponsible&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Irresponsible (Stargate Atlantis)|Irresponsible]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Three personal shields have so far been encountered. One was discovered in [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] and used by [[Rodney McKay]], but its power source is depleted by an energy-absorbing creature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot; /&gt; Another was used by a McKay from a [[Parallel universe (fiction)|Parallel universe]] to cross over to our universe.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKay and Mrs. Miller&quot;&gt;&quot;[[McKay and Mrs. Miller (Stargate Atlantis)|McKay and Mrs. Miller]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The third is used by [[Lucius Lavin]], although its power source was later depleted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irresponsible&quot; /&gt;
*'''Stargate shield:''' Much like the Iris on the Earth Gate, Atlantis' Stargate is protected by a shield that can be activated at a touch of a button to prevent any matter from materializing beyond the [[event horizon]]. Unlike the iris, it is transparent and one can see the suppressed kawoosh and impact of objects prevented from rematerializing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; The Shield has yet to be breached by anything, but a &quot;back-door&quot; is coded into the shield's control system by Dr. McKay, allowing him to deactivate it remotely from an off world location and preventing anyone else (including the inhabitants of Atlantis) from reactivating it.
*'''Puddle Jumper shield:''' The Atlantis [[Puddle Jumper]] cloaking devices can be modified to create a shield instead. The shield drains much more power than the cloak does, however.
*'''''Destiny'''s Shield:''' Stargate Universe's [[List of starships in Stargate#Destiny-class ship|Destiny]] appears to have a far more primitive Ancient shielding technology than Atlantis and other Ancient ships. Whereas Atlantis' shield appears to specialize in containing atmosphere, Destiny's shield is far inferior in this capability. Though Atlantis appears not to be airtight itself (stated several times throughout Atlantis that the shield is necessary for space travel), the shield retains the atmosphere with ease. The shield is battle tested in Season 1 Episode 11 and it is put under severe strain in the short fight with the aliens encountered, but ''Destiny'' is very damaged, with the power lines damaged enough for the ship being capable of storing only 40% of its maximum reserves, the shields also aren't at full power. The shield's obvious purpose is to withstand extreme temperatures when diving into a star's corona to recharge itself, though the recharging itself also powers the shields.  However, with all available power devoted to shields during a battle, they can take a lot: during a battle simulation ''Destiny'' was running, all available power was devoted to the shields and they were said to be able to hold out for 44 minutes against nine alien ships and were only penetrated when six more ships showed up and joined in the firing.

==Transportation==
The Ancients were the first race known to develop interstellar transport technology, being able to make intergalactic trips millions of years before human life was ever seeded in the Milky Way and Pegasus galaxies, and possessed  multiple methods of achieving this from ship mounted engines to devices that could transport people. They also possessed short-ranged transportation for non-interstellar use.

===Starship drives===
=====Intergalactic hyperdrive=====
The Ancients were the first race to build an intergalactic hyperdrive. The Ancients have the most powerful hyperdrives known to exist; [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] (and presumably other city-ships) can travel several million light-years in mere hours when powered by a full complement of ZPMs. By comparison, the Asgard-built intergalactic hyperdrive on an Earth [[List of Earth starships in Stargate#Daedalus class|''Daedalus''-class]] starship takes 18 days to make the same trip, four if similarly powered by a ZPM.

=====Interstellar hyperdrives=====
Unlike their city-ships, most Ancient vessels are powered by the more conventional interstellar hyperdrive, which cannot traverse intergalactic distances in a reasonable time frame but can move across a galaxy with relative ease. The hyperdrives equipped on the Aurora-class could be modified to make an intergalactic trip if necessary, possibly meaning the interstellar hyperdrives of other Ancient vessels could be modified in a similar manner; though they were usually ill-equipped to make such a trip and it is unknown how fast they would be (but likely far slower than an Asgard ship). Like their intergalactic counterparts, Ancient interstellar hyperdrives are far more powerful than those of other races. McKay designed an interstellar hyperdrive for a Puddle Jumper, but it was only reliable for about two trips and drained the Jumper's power quickly. (SG1: ''[[Ark of Truth]]'') (ATL: &quot;[[Rising (Stargate Atlantis)|Rising]]&quot;, &quot;[[Aurora (Stargate Atlantis)|Aurora]]&quot;, &quot;[[Tao of Rodney]]&quot;, &quot;[[Lifeline (Stargate Atlantis)|Lifeline]]&quot;, &quot;[[Enemy at the Gate (Stargate Atlantis)|Enemy at the Gate]]&quot;)

=====FTL drive=====
The Ancient starship ''[[Destiny (Stargate)|Destiny]]'' and its Seed ships use an unidentified form of [[faster-than-light]] propulsion which must remain active for at least 4 hours uninterrupted to prevent damage, this indicates it undergoes considerable strain from entering and exiting FTL. This FTL is described primarily as being distinct from [[hyperspace (science fiction)|hyperspace]], an example of this is that hyperspace is depicted as a tunnel, the ''Destiny'' FTL drive is depicted as if the ship is pushing through something, creating a trailing energy effect along the hull, similar to [[St. Elmo's fire]]. The FTL-drive itself spans the entire breadth of the stern of the vessel. In contrast to a hyperdrive, which opens a window in subspace upon activation, the FTL-drive rapidly accelerates the vessel to faster-than-light speeds. Due to the inertial dampeners, the only visible effects of the drive is a stretched, blurry sensation felt when the drive is accelerating. When active, the ships shields must remain active in order to protect it from objects the ship may encounter in its path and the speed of the ship itself. If the shield were to fail mid-flight, the ship would disintegrate. The drive is apparently extremely resilient (a characteristic of all Ancient technology), having remained in operation well over fifty million years. Following a sabotage attempt by an enemy alien faction, the crew determined that removing one of the drive's modules would actually improve overall drive efficiency, also indicating that the drive can continue to function unhindered without all of its components operational.

=====Wormhole drive=====
An experimental technology installed on Atlantis, capable of traversing vast distances in moments. In &quot;[[Enemy at the Gate (Stargate Atlantis)|Enemy at the Gate]]&quot;, the expedition uses it at the risk of instantly vaporizing the city, allowing Atlantis to reach Earth in time to defend it against an attack by a ZPM-powered Wraith hive ship. The drive essentially functions in a similar manner to a stargate, in that it creates an artificial wormhole that envelopes the entire city, transporting it almost instantaneously to its intended destination. The research into the drive was abandoned by the Ancients due to the enormous power constraints and the highly likely possibility of destroying the city. When the Atlantis Expedition was en route to Earth to defend against a Wraith attack, the stardrive failed on the edge of the Milky Way galaxy. With no remaining options to complete the journey, Dr. Radek Zelenka suggested to Richard Woolsey that he complete Dr. Rodney McKay's calculations that would theoretically safely engage the city in a wormhole &quot;jump&quot;. Woolsey agreed and Atlantis safely transported into orbit around Earth in the midst of the Wraith's attack on Earth.

=====Sublight drive=====
A type of sub-FTL seen only in the episode &quot;[[The Return (Stargate Atlantis)|The Return]]&quot;, under which an Ancient warship with damaged hyperdrive, the Tria, traveled consistently at 99% of the speed of light. They however had a ZPM onboard and patched it into their sub-light engines allowing them to push to 99% the speed of light and maintain it for 10,000 non relative years(about 12 years on the ship). They were attempting to return to Earth to rejoin the Ancients from Atlantis. As a result of traveling at that speed, they had experienced very limited passage of time. They encountered the Daedalus in the intergalactic void while the Earth ship was testing the nearly completed Midway Station.

=====Ancient Stardrive=====
The Ancient Stardrive is a drive unique to Ancient city-ships such as Atlantis. It is apparently a combination of both a sublight drive and a hyperdrive. Spanning the entire underside of the city-ship, it is capable of propelling the immensely heavy vessel away from the planet's surface, into orbit and through hyperspace. Considered one of the quickest drives in existence, Atlantis has traversed the distance from its home in Pegasus to the edge of the Milky Way galaxy in mere hours, a feat which takes the Daedalus approximately 18 days to complete. In additional spaceflight, the drive is also crucial for liftoff and entry to control the city-ship to ensure a smooth take off and landing.

===Ring transporter===
[[Image:SGTeleRings.jpg|thumb|right|Transport rings with a transport in progress]]
Originally developed and used by the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]], but later used by the [[Goa'uld]], the [[Tok'ra]], and the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]]. The rings are roughly half the diameter of a Stargate and function under similar principles. The matter within the first set of rings is swapped with the matter in the second set of rings. A single set of rings can also be used to transfer matter over short distances. All matter inside the rings is dematerialized and transported via matter stream to another set of rings in a different location where it is then rematerialized. The five or eight rings levitate slightly off the ground and stack on top of each other during operation. Each ring transporter platform weighs 12.9 tons, but what components are used in the &quot;platform&quot; is unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Other Guys&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Other Guys|episodelink=The Other Guys (Stargate SG-1)|series=Stargate SG-1|serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After a completed transport, the rings move back into their storage platform and deactivate. The rings themselves do not transport. Some ring platforms are portable and can be moved when inactive. They have sensors that detect other active transport rings in an area. Transport rings are also used to enter and exit spacecraft, with one set of rings inside the craft and another set of rings mounted outside the hull. This is commonly seen with the Goa'uld [[Tel'tak]] cargo ships and [[Al'kesh]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Children of the Gods|episodelink=Children of the Gods (Stargate SG-1)|series=Stargate SG-1|serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some of the Earth ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Memento&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Memento|episodelink=Memento (Stargate SG-1)|series=Stargate SG-1|serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is possible to intercept a matter stream that is in transport by interposing a set of mobile rings between the sending rings and the planned receiving rings. However, such an intercept requires that the ''entire'' matter stream be captured by the intercepting rings; otherwise, the transported people will not fully reintegrate, resulting in death. In the original Stargate film, O'Neil used the rings to decapitate one of Ra's foot soldiers by pinning him under the rings as they were activated, causing only the soldier's head to be transported.

===Stargate===
{{Main|Stargate (device)}}
Also known as ''Astria Porta'' in Ancient, and to the Goa'uld and Jaffa as the &quot;Chappa'ai&quot; (Cha-Pa-Eye).&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot; /&gt; were created and distributed by the Ancients across several galaxies, along with [[Dial-Home Device]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; to control them, forming the Stargate Network.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; A traveller may use any Stargate to travel almost instantaneously to any other Stargate in the system, so long as he knows the &quot;address,&quot; a combination of at least seven symbols (six for the 3D position and one for the point of origin) that must be entered on the DHD (and assuming that the traveller is aware of [[stellar drift]] and can compensate for its effect on gate travel). Gates with a DHD communicate with each other through updates the only gate that has to take stellar drift into consideration is Earths gate since it does not have a DHD. Eight symbols must be used to dial a stargate that is in a different galaxy (the extra symbol referred to in SG-1 as being &quot;like an area code&quot;). The nine-symbol address is a specific combination used to dial the [[Destiny (Stargate)|Destiny]], a massive Ancient vessel that was part of a project to explore the universe, before the Ancients ascended. A Stargate is a one-way portal; it can only be entered from the side it is activated at. Simultaneous access is impossible. The Stargate is often considered to be the Ancients most famous creation, as the Ancients are often called the &quot;Gate Builders&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Fifth Race]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Because the Goa'uld are scavengers, they claimed that they were the builders to make the populations of the planets they enslaved worship them as gods.

===Other===
*'''&quot;Eye of the Gods&quot;:''' A large [[obelisk]] located not far from the Stargate of the Sodan world, It transports people to another location where a similar transporter is located to get back. An energy signature is detected within the column of stones, although it remains unknown how the device functions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babylon&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Babylon (Stargate SG-1)|Babylon]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; A control crystal is required to activate the obelisk. Without the crystal, the obelisk can be transported to, but cannot transport people back.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arthur's Mantle&quot; /&gt; [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Ganos Lal/Morgan le Fay|Morgan le Fay]] uses similar obelisks to transport Merlin and those with him to various planets throughout the Milky Way, which also contains command overrides for the DHD and is able to distinguish between a regular human and an Orici.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Quest (Stargate SG-1)|The Quest]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Atlantis transporters:'''In Stargate Atlantis the cityship does not appear to be equipped with ring transporters but instead it has transporter rooms (initially mistaken for storage cupboards) which would seem to be an upgraded version of the technology as they work in a similar manner. They may also be compatible with ring transporters similar to the way that separate era stargates are compatible.
*'''Beam transporter:''' Outposts built by Ancients after their return from the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Dwarf Galaxy]] possessed transporters that were similar to Asgard transporters. Such devices were used to reveal treasures to SG-1 after passing several tests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

==Weapons==
===Asurans===
{{Main|Asuran}}
The ultimate product of extensive [[Ancients (Stargate)|Ancient]] research into smaller and more effective weapons for use against the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]], the result being microscopic nanites capable of attacking and destroying Wraith cells. They were programmed with an aggression that surpassed even that of the Wraith, and the ability to replicate to far greater numbers to increase their effectiveness. They replicated at such a rate that they took even the Ancients by surprise. As they became more advanced, the molecular machines began interlocking and assembling themselves into more complex constructs, and eventually they reached the point where they exactly emulated the Ancients in appearance. They desperately pleaded with the Ancients to have the aggression removed from their base code, but since the Ancients included a directive in the coding that prevented the Asurans from harming them, they continued the experiment. After they concluded that they would never become the weapon they desired to create, they launched a massive attack on their homeworld in an attempt to destroy them, and then erased all traces of them in their database. Even after this, a few nanites survived and began replicating, bringing about a second-birth of their kind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Progeny&quot; /&gt;  They are finally destroyed by the Tau'ri with the help of the Wraith and the Travellers.  However, it should be noted that a small contingent of replicators under Dr. Weir were not destroyed, but were eventually sent through a stargate into space, so they couldn't do anything more.

===Dakara superweapon===
An extremely powerful device hidden inside a monument on [[Dakara]], which was later turned into a [[Goa'uld]] temple. It was once used by the Ancients to re-create life in the galaxy after a devastating plague.&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Threads|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is capable of destroying all life in the galaxy as well. Anubis intended to use it to repopulate the galaxy according to his own designs. However, [[Jacob Carter]] recognizes that it is also the galaxy's only hope against the [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]]. The weapon uses an energy wave that decomposes matter into its constituent parts. He, (along with [[Selmak]]), [[Samantha Carter]], and Ba'al reprogram the device to emit an energy wave matching that of the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator Disruptor]], and send it through all the Stargates in the galaxy at once, and wipes out the Replicators. In {{sgcite|Threads|SG-1}}, Anubis conquers Dakara and almost completes his plan to wipe the galaxy clean, but is stopped by [[Oma Desala]]. Confronted by how close they came to annihilation, the [[Free Jaffa Nation]] agrees to dismantle the device. However, in {{sgcite|Counterstrike|SG-1}}, the weapon is used again to fight the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]]. The Jaffa High Council uses it to eliminate the crew of an [[Ori mothership]], so they can capture it. Their attack is successful, but the [[Orici]] [[Adria (Stargate)|Adria]] is protected from the weapon by her personal shield, and takes the Ori mothership to Dakara where she fires a weapon that annihilates the Dakara superweapon.

===Drone weapon===
[[Image:rising038.jpg|thumb|A single inactive Drone Weapon being analyzed.]]
An extremely powerful projectile weapon, shaped like a meter-long squid, capable of autonomously targeting and destroying its target, even if it is moving extremely fast. These are the Ancient's main type of weapon. In the Pegasus Galaxy, drones are rare in the aftermath of the loss of the Ancients' war against the Wraith. Only a few dozen remained in [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], which were used up during the siege by the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; A larger supply is found in another city ship, which is later used to replenish Atlantis' armory.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tower&quot; /&gt; They are also found on [[Puddle Jumper]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt; and [[Aurora class battleship]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aurora&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Aurora (Stargate Atlantis)|Aurora]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Asurans]] also use drones. In the [[Milky Way]], thousands of drones have been discovered in Ancient outposts such as the [[Antarctica]] outpost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; Drones are partially intelligent weapons that are capable of seeking, tracking, and engaging targets on their own accord. They are normally controlled by an [[Ancient Control Chair]] that reads the operator's mind and can send thousands of drones swarming to attack an entire fleet at once.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; They appear to be guided by a central control system using various available sensors,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tower&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Tower (Stargate Atlantis)|The Tower]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and can be controlled either by continuous operator control&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Siege (Stargate Atlantis)|The Siege, Part II]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; or in a fire-and-forget manner.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tower&quot; /&gt; Aurora-class ships have a dedicated control chair for the drones, with the second meant to fly the ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Travelers&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=Travelers |episodelink=Travelers (Stargate Atlantis) |series=Stargate Atlantis |serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An active drone is enveloped in a bright yellow glow. Drones fired from a control chair require a [[ZPM]] for normal operation,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; though a [[Naqahdah generator|Mark II Naqahdah generator]] set on a controlled overload can provide the necessary power (but will fail after three uses).&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; Drones require an outside power source, and will shut down in mid-flight if this power source is disabled. A drone was observed causing a relatively small explosion on impact,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tower&quot; /&gt; while a swarm enveloped a [[Kull warrior]] while on its way from Anubis' attacking fleet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; Conversely, two Drone Weapons are enough to completely destroy a Goa'uld [[Ha'tak]] if it hits a critical spot&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good to Be King&quot;&gt;&quot;[[It's Good to Be King (Stargate SG-1)|It's Good to Be King]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and a single drone can seriously damage a [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] cruiser.&lt;ref name=&quot;Condemned&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Condemned (Stargate Atlantis)|Condemned]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Drones have the ability to shield itself from impact with matter to a certain degree, allowing them to literally tunnel through larger enemies such as ships before returning to detonate. Drones have also been observed passing through ships, with unused ones heading back to their launch site,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; and can be used under water.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Return (Stargate Atlantis)|The Return]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a smaller variant called '''mini-drones'''. It is theorized that the drones are used to guard certain areas against people without the ancient gene, as was the case on queen Harmony's planet where only the wearer of a special ancient &quot;key&quot; (pendant) can control the mini-drones from the &quot;test site&quot; where the Ancients developed mini-drone technology, which was perfected in Pegasus while the normal sized drones were invented in the Milky Way.&lt;ref&gt;{{sgcite|Harmony|Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2008/01/30/january-30-2008-and-the-big-news-iscoming-soon-plus-botm-nominees January 30, 2008: And the big news is…coming soon! Plus BOTM nominees. « Josephmallozzi’s Weblog]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Replicator Disruptor===
The most effective weapon against [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]], and the only one completely effective against human-form Replicators, it disrupts communication between cells, rendering each one inert. When fired, any Replicator in its blast radius falls apart into its constituent units. The weapon is created by [[Jack O'Neill]], who had the entire Ancient Database downloaded into his mind at the time, in conjunction with Asgard computers.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;&quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Replicators are able to become immune to the device, requiring the recalibration of the disruptor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gemini&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Gemini (Stargate SG-1)|Gemini]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The actual prop was piston-driven and had a trigger device inside. Because the model shop knew that actor [[Richard Dean Anderson]] would play with it off-screen, they made it extra-robust.&lt;ref&gt;[[Andy Mikita]] in the audio commentary for &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Area 51]] produced a version of the Replicator Disruptor specifically to combat the [[Asuran]]s. (see &quot;[[Tau'ri technology in Stargate#Anti-Replicator Gun (ARG)|Anti-Replicator Gun]]&quot;).

===Sangraal===
Also known as the [[Holy Grail]] or (as in the episode &quot;Camelot&quot;) the Bloodstone, is a weapon designed by [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Moros.2FMyrddin.2FMerlin|Merlin]] to neutralize [[ascension (Stargate)|ascended beings]], including the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]], but cannot target a specific group of ascended but rather wipes all of them out within the weapon's range. The weapon consists of several devices working together, with a red stone as the &quot;key&quot; to make it work.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| title=The Quest| episodelink=The Quest (Stargate SG-1)| series=Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]], the notion of the Grail as a cup or chalice was a late addition to the myth, but some chroniclers originally described the Holy Grail as a stone that fell from the heavens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| title=Camelot| episodelink=Camelot (Stargate SG-1)| series=Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Exactly how it works is unknown, but the [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]] have surmised that it's an energy transfer device, similar to a [[Zero Point Module]], except that the energy is channelled not from sub-space into ordinary space-time, but rather into the dimension occupied by Ascended beings. The effect of this again theorized by the Asgard as two standing waves canceling each other out. The Sangraal is launched through the [[Technology in Stargate#Ori technology|Supergate]] by Dr. Jackson&lt;ref name=&quot;The Shroud&quot; /&gt; and confirmed to have destroyed the Ori.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Dominion (Stargate SG-1)| title=Dominion| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ark of Truth&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Stargate: The Ark of Truth| title=Ark of Truth| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lagrangian Point Defense Satellite===
Enormous satellites floating in deep space, equipped with an energy beam weapon powerful enough to cut a [[Wraith Hive-Ship]] in half. Puddle Jumpers can dock with it. The satellite can be charged by multiple types of power sources, storing power in its [[capacitor]] until it has enough energy to fire. During the war with the Wraith, Atlantis was guarded by a network of satellites placed at [[Lagrangian Point]]s to protect the city. However, they were destroyed one by one, until eventually only one remained, damaged and without power. When the Wraith decide to attack Atlantis again after the Atlantis Expedition had taken up residence there, a team led by [[Rodney McKay]] repairs the satellite to use against the incoming Wraith fleet. The repairs allowed the weapon to destroy one Hive-Ship using secondary power lines, but the systems overloaded after the first shot and it is soon destroyed by a barrage of Wraith weapons fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt;

===Personal Weapons===
*'''Lantean Pistol''' A side arm carried by the crew of the [[Aurora-class battleship|Aurora]] in their virtual reality. This weapon also appears to have been mimicked by the Asurans. It appears to have a stun setting and presumably one to kill too.
*'''Lantean Grenade''' A small oval device that is opened, twisted, then closed to activate. Although the two devices seen in '[[The Defiant One]]' are found on a Wraith corpse, the golden colour, inorganic design and the fact that the grenades seem designed to kill rather than stun lead to a high probability that these are in fact of Lantean origin.

===Other===
*'''Ark of Truth:''' Invented by Amelius, and is built to [[Brainwashing|brainwash]] someone into believing whatever is programmed into it, as long as it is true. The Alterans left the device behind in their home galaxy rather than use it against the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] followers, because it contravened their belief in free will. SG-1 eventually travels to the Ori galaxy to find the device, so as to convince the Ori army that the Ori are not gods. They find the Ark underground on Celestis with the guidance of [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Ganos Lal/Morgan le Fay|Morgan le Fay]]. Although Adria's soldiers capture the device, [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] manages to activate it and convert the Doci, whose telepathic link in turn converts all the Priors in the Ori galaxy. They bring the Ark to the Milky Way and it converts all the Priors there also, causing Adria to lose the power she previously gained from her worshipers, rendering her no more powerful than any other ascended being. The Ark is eventually taken to [[Area 51]] for study.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Stargate: The Ark of Truth| title=Stargate: The Ark of Truth| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Attero_Device&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
*'''Attero device:'''{{Anchor|Attero device|Other 2}} An extremely powerful weapon built by [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Janus|Janus]], which emits subspace interference that destabilizes the formation of Wraith hyperspace windows when activated. As a result, any Wraith ship is instantly destroyed by entering hyperspace. It was abandoned by Janus because it emits radiation which causes energy to quickly buildup within any active Stargate in Pegasus, leading to its destruction in a powerful explosion equivalent to twelve nuclear bombs. The device is reactivated by a renegade Asgard faction unconcerned with the loss of lives, but is eventually shut down by Dr. McKay, then destroyed by a Travellers ship, so it cannot be used again. The control key, however, is taken by the Asgard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=First Contact (Stargate Atlantis)| title=First Contact| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Lost Tribe (Stargate Atlantis)| title=The Lost Tribe| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Explosive tumor machine:''' An extremely powerful bio-weapon created by the Ancients. The device emits radiation which causes the body to gather specific elements in a tumor behind the victim's lung, which eventually explodes. The device is activated by two scientists in Atlantis, one of whom dies. The other is saved by [[Carson Beckett]], though Beckett himself is killed when the excised tumor explodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{sgcite|Sunday|Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Gate overloader:''' A weapon able to target a Stargate and turn its naquadah to a deadly weapon. The weapon would send massive amounts of energy through a Stargate to be stored in the receiving gate, which would keep absorbing energy until it can't hold any more, eventually exploding with devastating power. The resulting blast would be big enough to destroy [[Colorado]], and the ensuing dust cloud would destroy all life on [[Earth]]. It is capable of maintaining an active wormhole between two Stargates indefinitely, until the target gate is destroyed. It is used against the [[Tau'ri]] by [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]], although the SGC is able to dispose of the gate, transporting it to space before it explodes. The weapon itself is destroyed by [[Teal'c]], [[Bra'tac]] and [[Rya'c]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Redemption (Stargate SG-1)|Redemption]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

==Miscellaneous technologies==
===Shrine of Talus===
A device with an unknown purpose, which is powered by a super heavy element giving off an unknown form of ionizing radiation. A parasite that causes &quot;Second Childhood&quot; is affected by the radiation, allowing those suffering from the ailment to become themselves for a day before a quick death from immune system failure or leaving the range of the shrine's radiation.

===ATA Gene===
The Ancient Technology Activation gene (ATA) is a specific [[gene]] present in all Ancients, and some of their human descendants, which acts as a key to much of their technology; if the user does not possess the gene, the technology will not activate. The ATA gene instructs various cells in the body to produce a series of proteins and enzymes that interact with the skin, nervous system, and brain, allowing the gene carriers to operate Ancient technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;rising&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Rising (Stargate Atlantis)| title=Rising| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though rare naturally in most humans,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Tower (Stargate Atlantis)| title=The Tower| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. [[Carson Beckett]] develops a [[retrovirus|retroviral]] [[gene therapy]] (using a deactivated mouse retrovirus) to transfer the Ancient gene expression to humans,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot; /&gt; but the treatment only has a 48% success rate.&lt;ref name=&quot;hot zone&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Hot Zone (Stargate Atlantis)| title=Hot Zone| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; The necessity of the gene in utilizing Ancient technology varies. In some cases, like use of the Control Chair, the gene is required for continued use, while other devices simply need to be initially activated by someone with the gene, after which anyone can use the device. Gene expression is stronger in some carriers, allowing them to use Ancient technology instinctively while others require training and practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;rising&quot; /&gt;  The individual's ability to operate ancient devices are ranked by a system devised as the CIA(Chair Interface Aptitude). It seems people with it naturally occurring seem to have a higher CIA (such as Sheppard and Beckett are higher than McKay).&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemy at the Gate&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Enemy at the Gate (Stargate Atlantis)| title=Enemy at the Gate| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Natural gene carriers from Earth include [[Major General]] [[Jack O'Neill]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; [[Lieutenant Colonel|Lt. Colonel]] [[John Sheppard (Stargate)|John Sheppard]] (he apparently has a very strong form of the gene, and operates Ancient technology almost instinctively), Dr. [[Carson Beckett]],&lt;ref name=&quot;rising&quot; /&gt; [[Sergeant|Sgt.]] [[Tau'ri characters in Stargate Atlantis#Markham|Markham]] (who was killed in action),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Thirty-eight Minutes| title=Thirty-eight Minutes| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. Kusanagi (who was mentioned but never seen), and Joe Spencer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Citizen Joe (Stargate SG-1)| title=Citizen Joe| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gene carriers by therapy include Dr. [[Rodney McKay]] (as the first human trial),&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Hide and Seek (Stargate Atlantis)| title=Hide and Seek| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Colonel|Col.]] [[Tau'ri characters in Stargate Atlantis#Dillon Everett|Dillon Everett]],&lt;ref name=&quot;siege2&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Siege (Stargate Atlantis)| title=The Siege, Part 2| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some of his troops. Gene carriers of unknown source include [[Lieutenant|Lt.]] Miller,&lt;ref&gt;Miller piloted a Jumper in {{cite episode| episodelink=The Siege (Stargate Atlantis)| title=The Siege, Part 1| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. Abrams,&lt;ref&gt;Abrams used a life signs detector in {{cite episode| episodelink=The Defiant One (Stargate Atlantis)| title=The Defiant One| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Major]] [[Lorne (Stargate)|Lorne]].&lt;ref&gt;Lorne piloted a Jumper in {{cite episode| episodelink=Condemned (Stargate Atlantis)| title=Condemned| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; The gene therapy did not work on Dr. [[Radek Zelenka]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hot zone&quot; /&gt; The status of Dr. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] as a carrier is uncertain. He utilized Ancient technology after encountering the Ancient Repository that Merlin used in his laboratory. This technology modified Dr. Jackson's genetic make up, so he could resist the effects of being transformed into an [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] [[Prior (Stargate)|Prior]], as well as allowing him to house Merlin's consciousness. Whether it modified his genetics to include the Ancient gene, or whether he already possessed it, is unknown. However, the Goa'uld [[Goa'uld characters in Stargate#Anubis|Anubis]] was able to use Ancient technology due to him being partly [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascended]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Full Circle (Stargate SG-1)| title=Full Circle| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting that Daniel may also be able to use Ancient technology as he was an ascended being. Whether his ascension or the repository were responsible for his ability to use Ancient technology at the time is unknown, as he has not used any ATA gene-based technology since. Lt. [[Aiden Ford]] asked for the gene therapy during the nanovirus crisis,&lt;ref name=&quot;hot zone&quot; /&gt; but it was never said if he got it after the crisis. After Ford used a Puddle Jumper to leave Atlantis,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Siege, Part 3 (Stargate Atlantis)| title=The Siege, Part 3| series= Stargate Atlantis| serieslink=Stargate Atlantis}}&lt;/ref&gt; series' writer [[Martin Gero]] explained in an online message&lt;ref&gt;[http://forum.gateworld.net/showthread.php?t=14193 Ford and the Jumper - A clarification by Martin Gero]&lt;/ref&gt; that he does not have the gene, because &quot;The Jumpers, while near and inside Atlantis, are pretty much on autopilot when it comes to landing and taking off.&quot;

Series writer and producer [[Joseph Mallozzi]] has stated in his blog that the ATA gene did not factor into any [[Stargate Universe]] story lines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/09/28/september-28-2009-only-four-days-to-the-stargate-universe-premiere-lou-diamond-philips-the-return-of-the-mailbag/]&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Arthur's Mantle&quot;===
A device built by [[Moros (Stargate)|Merlin]] that pushes matter [[Phase (waves)#Phase difference|'out of phase']] with normal reality, making everything within its area of effect invisible and intangible. It also doubles as a computer. The device was used to conceal his research on the [[Sangraal (Stargate)|Sangraal]], a weapon capable of destroying ascended beings. The console was concealed in the [[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon]] cave under [[Glastonbury Tor]], [[England]]. The device was named by Merlin's trusted aides, the [[Knights of the Round Table]]. In order to access the data from its computer, the user must be out of phase, to prevent the ascended Ancients from discovering it. The device itself is accessible from either dimension, allowing a person to enter and exit. Although being out of phase hides the user from both the Ancients and conventional observers, those wearing [[Mythology of Stargate#Jaffa|Sodan]] personal cloaking device, which operate on a similar principle, can observe affected matter, though they cannot interact with it. The device is accidentally accessed by [[Samantha Carter|Colonels Carter]] and [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Mitchell]], who were rendered out of phase by the device. With the eventual help of [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]], they manage to return to normal; however, its power source is permanently depleted in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arthur's Mantle&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Arthur's Mantle (Stargate SG-1)|Arthur's Mantle]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; The device is then exploited as a defensive weapon by Colonel Carter, first on a village under threat by the Ori&lt;ref name=&quot;Line in the Sand&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Line in the Sand (Stargate SG-1)|Line in the Sand]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; then on the entire planet Earth in an alternate reality.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Road Not Taken&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Road Not Taken (Stargate SG-1)|The Road Not Taken]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Communication device with stones===
A dome-shaped device with a blue crystal spire designed to facilitate communications across vast distances. The device works in tandem with palm-sized oval stones. When inserted into one of twelve slots on the base, the stones allow the user's mind to take over the body of whoever last touched the stones on the other end, provided someone with the ATA gene activated them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot; /&gt; The reverse is also true if those on the receiving end make use of a similar device. The device draws its power from subspace (the same way a ZPM does), and works seamlessly even when communicating over billions of light-years apart. The ''Destiny''{{'}}s FTL drive is shown to disrupt the connection when it either deactivates or engages, but the stones reestablish contact within seconds.

In addition to their regular function, two communications stones can form a psychic link between the last two people that used them. SG-1 retrieved one of these stones from the same planet where the [[Miscellaneous technology in Stargate#Quantum Mirror|quantum mirror]] was discovered. The stone was kept in Daniel Jackson's lab and inadvertently activated by [[Jack O'Neill]]. Another stone was purchased at a yard sale by Joe Spencer, a barber from [[Indiana]], who was then able to see O'Neill's memories as he recalled them while writing his mission reports.&lt;ref name=&quot;Citizen Joe&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Citizen Joe]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

One of these devices was discovered under Glastonbury Tor, and it was subsequently used by Dr. Jackson and Vala. It transported their minds to the Ori galaxy into the bodies of a married couple, Harrid and Sallis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot; /&gt; Their minds were sent back by a similar device, but the transfer was cut short by a [[Prior (Stargate)|Prior]]. Col. Mitchell and [[Teal'c]] eventually destroyed it by throwing it into the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate's]] unstable vortex, bringing Daniel and Vala back.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Origin (Stargate SG-1)|Origin]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Several months later, Vala Mal Doran contacted the [[Stargate Command|SGC]] from the Ori Galaxy using the device thanks to the Ori underground resistance, and warned [[SG-1]] about the nearing Ori invasion of the [[Milky Way]]. However, the link was cut by her husband Tomin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crusade&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Crusade (Stargate SG-1)|Crusade]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Another communication device was found in the Pegasus galaxy, switching Dr. Keller's mind with that of a thief. Both Keller and the thief were able to use each other's bodies despite the lack of a second device. Unable to find any shut-down switch, Ronon shoots it to break the link.

In ''[[Stargate Universe]]'', Stargate Command has apparently devised a more compact version of the communication device. This version is a boxed-shaped device with room for five stones in an 'X' formation. The stones are simply placed on the flat panel of the device to activate it. It can be deactivated by removing the power source attached to the base. The team aboard the ''Destiny'' has access to one, as does Stargate Command, allowing for regular communication between the expedition and Earth. Like the original, the transfer works both ways and will only deactivate when deprived of power (which is much easier with this version). Due to the vast distance between Earth and the Destiny the transfer will only work if both devices are active, and deactivating either device will terminate the link. In addition, stones must be placed on both devices for a transfer to occur, as shown when Young had to bring in an additional person to switch with Chloe after they both used the device (Telford had been the only one present on the other end). However, connections across a shorter distance (as in the same or adjacent galaxies) still work with only one device present, as seen when Young switched body with a Blueberry Alien. These Aliens seem to have developed a similar device, which they used to switch bodies with Vanessa James.  This issue was compounded when she did not have her imprint erased from the stone she was inadvertently switched with a member of the alien race who ended up sabotaging Destiny.

The SGU device has been shown to glitch when Destiny jumps to FTL travel, allowing for minds to be inadvertently returned to their host bodies.

The SGU device's link is also terminated upon either linked individual entering an active Stargate, or at least one going to ''Destiny''.

It is also revealed that the death of one person using the stones, also kills the person on the other end. (As and edit, a more current episode shows that the physical body of the person dies while the mental being of the person gets lost and &quot;floats&quot; around.) The mental part was able to be reconnected with by the stone user to fall asleep. The person(s) mind(s) would then download into the stone users and will disappear and be lost if it is not taken out of the body i.e. through a neural link in a control chair. In SGU one of the characters has two other characters minds downloaded into her brain through the stones (who where thought to be dead) and were taken out through the chair on-board.

===Control Chair===
[[Image:Atlantischairroom.jpg|thumb|right|Atlantis' Ancient Control Chair used by Sheppard.]]
A chair-shaped [[Brain-computer interface|neural interface]] which allows the user to remotely control systems on whatever facility the chair is installed in, such as the [[Ancient City Ship]] or smaller Ancient outposts like the one in [[Antarctica]]. The chairs, like most Ancient technology, requires the [[Ancient Technology Activation gene]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Rising (Stargate Atlantis)|Rising]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; They are primarily used to fire and control [[Drone Weapon]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Siege (Stargate Atlantis)|The Siege]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; though they are also shown to be used to pilot spacecraft in addition to more minor systems such as [[holographic projector]]s and power distribution.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot; /&gt; They are normally powered by a [[Zero Point Module]], but can be powered by [[Naqahdah Generator|Mark II Naqahdah reactors]] in a &quot;controlled overload&quot;, which provides just enough energy to activate the chair three times before the reactor burns out.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; Two chairs have been encountered in the [[Milky Way]] – Proclarush Taonas and the [[Antarctica]] outpost on [[Earth]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus Galaxy]], chairs are located in the tower of [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; and its [[List_of_starships_in_Stargate#Cityship|sister cities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tower&quot; /&gt; Ancient ''Aurora''-class starships each have two chairs, one for weapons and the other for piloting. The one for piloting looks different than the ones for drone control.
In ''Stargate Universe'' series, the spaceship ''Destiny'' has a primitive version of the control chair, which also acts as the ship's [[Ancient_technology_in_Stargate#Repository_of_Knowledge|repository of knowledge]].

===DNA Resequencer===
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Dnaresequencer.jpg|thumb|[[Samantha Carter]] under experimentation in the DNA Resequencer.]] --&gt;
:
A genetic manipulation device, which &quot;resequences&quot; to an extreme state of [[transhumanism|human advancement]], granting the subjects what appeared to be [[superhuman]] powers. Nirrti attempted to use the machine to create humans with superpowers, called &quot;hok'taur&quot;, [[Goa'uld]] slang meaning &quot;advanced human&quot;, to take as hosts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Metamorphosis&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]| episodelink=Metamorphosis (Stargate SG-1)| title=Metamorphosis}} | [http://media.dave.tv/sites/stargatesg1/screenplays/s06e16.PDF Screenplay]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rite of Passage&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]| episodelink=Rite of Passage (Stargate SG-1)| title=Rite of Passage}} | [http://media.dave.tv/sites/stargatesg1/screenplays/s05e06.PDF Screenplay]&lt;/ref&gt;

The device works by altering a subject's [[DNA]] and consequently increasing their [[brain]] activity from roughly 10% up to 90% (based on the popular but inaccurate myth that humans only use [[10% myth|10% of their brain]] at any given time).&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt;  Depending on the length of time for which they were subjected to the machine, various characters were shown to have abilities such as [[telekinesis]] and [[telepathy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Metamorphosis&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt; super-human senses and strength,&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt; supernatural health and self healing,&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]| episodelink=Frozen (Stargate SG-1)| title=Frozen}} | [http://media.dave.tv/sites/stargatesg1/screenplays/s06e04.PDF Screenplay]&lt;/ref&gt; perfect memory, and the power to heal by touch.&lt;ref name=&quot;Metamorphosis&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frozen&quot; /&gt; The show's [[Ascension (Stargate)|ascended beings]] possessed similar supernatural abilities of the same order but in far greater magnitudes and proficiencies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maternal Instinct&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Maternal Instinct|episodelink=Maternal Instinct (Stargate SG-1)|series=Stargate SG-1|serieslink=Stargate SG-1}} | [http://media.dave.tv/sites/stargatesg1/screenplays/s03e20.PDF Screenplay]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman 2&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]| episodelink=The Fourth Horseman (Stargate SG-1) #Part 2| title=The Fourth Horseman (Part 2)}} | [http://media.dave.tv/sites/stargatesg1/screenplays/s09e11.PDF Screenplay]&lt;/ref&gt; It was confirmed in Season 9 of ''SG-1'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt; that through extreme evolution, such as that provided by the DNA Resequencer, a being would gradually acquire Ascended powers until genuinely Ascending themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt;

The [[Theatrical property|prop]] consists of three components. Two of the components are physical but the third is [[computer]] generated.  The first component is a pedestal that rests on the floor, elevating the actor in the device and drawing attention to him or her. Above the user was the second component, an orange globe. This was what appeared to be the technological part of the device (at least the first time the device appeared).&lt;ref&gt;[[DVD]] [[television director|director's]] commentary of the episode {{sgcite|Metamorphosis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the editing process, the third component was added: a computer generated energy field which appears to paralyze the user, and a computer-generated representation of DNA surrounding the user.

A device with similar capabilities was found in an initially submerged part of Atlantis,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tao of Rodney&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Tao of Rodney]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; although it differs considerably in appearance. The diposition of the command console on a pedestal and under the blue light emitter of the &quot;resequencing&quot; field suggest it was designed for self-modifications.

===Holographic sentry===
A [[hologram]] was used as a security measure by [[Merlin (Stargate)|Merlin]] in his vault in &quot;Avalon&quot; and at his library in &quot;Camelot&quot;. The hologram was capable of interacting with people and certain other projected objects, particularly holographic [[sword]]s, but [[bullet]]s would pass straight through it when fired at it. The hologram was designed to resemble a medieval [[knight]], to test the worthiness of those who entered. If the program had determined the visitors to be &quot;worthy&quot;, the treasures and hidden technology inside the cave would be revealed. When [[SG-1]] gained access to the cavern, the sentry was eventually defeated by [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Cameron Mitchell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon&quot; /&gt; Another holographic knight guarded Merlin's library on Camelot, where his research on an anti-[[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] weapon, the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Sangraal|Sangraal]], was kept. Instead of battling those who trespass within the library, the hologram, which was known to the locals as the ''Black Knight'', emerge in the village to incite terror and discourage re-admittance. When SG-1 visited Camelot in search for more information on the weapon, the hologram almost killed Col. Mitchell, before [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] was able to destroy the control crystals governing the program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Camelot (Stargate SG-1)|Camelot]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Repository of Knowledge===
The [[wikia:Stargate:Ancients' repository of knowledge|Repository of the Ancients]] is a device that stores all knowledge of the Ancients. The interface is a metallic circle, with a dark window in the middle, and is usually attached to a wall. The console is designed to allow a human to place his/her head into it, whereupon the device grabs them by the temples and downloads the entire database into their mind. The transfer of knowledge from this device can cause serious problems for beings whose physiology is not prepared to take the mental strain. The device was used on two separate occasions by Jack O'Neill, both times threatening his life; during both of these times, he was able to build a powerful generator.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fifth Race&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Fifth Race (Stargate SG-1)| title=The Fifth Race| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was also shown to be able to create a weapon capable of defeating any [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]]&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=New Order (Stargate SG-1)| title=New Order| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and use healing powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Lost City (Stargate SG-1)| title=Lost City| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; A variation appears in &quot;The Quest&quot;. This version is smaller, does not latch on to the user's head, and has additional, hand-sized input devices at its base. It interfaces with a replication device to allow users to build devices from the molecule up. It was used by Merlin to create the first [[Sangraal (Stargate)|Sangraal]]. Merlin downloaded his mind into the device when he could not complete work on the second, allowing Daniel to finish it. It also allowed Daniel to use telekinetic powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Shroud&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Shroud (Stargate SG-1)| title=The Shroud| series= Stargate SG-1| serieslink=Stargate SG-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In ''Stargate Universe'' series, the spaceship ''Destiny'' has a primitive version of the [[Ancient_technology_in_Stargate#Control_Chair|control chair]], which also acts as the ship's repository of knowledge.

===Stasis Chamber===
A device designed to put the occupant into a state of [[suspended animation]]. The device slows the user's bodily functions to a near halt but does not stop them. Thus, over long periods, the person can potentially age to a point where being removed would be fatal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Before I Sleep&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Before I Sleep (Stargate Atlantis)|Before I Sleep]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; One such device was located inside the Antarctic outpost and used by Colonel O'Neill, who put himself in stasis to stop the Ancient knowledge in his brain from killing him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot; /&gt; Another chamber was encountered on Atlantis, where an alternate version of [[Elizabeth Weir (Stargate)|Elizabeth Weir]] had survived for 10,000 years, reawakening every 3,300 years to rotate among Atlantis' three ZPMs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Before I Sleep&quot; /&gt; The clone of [[Carson Beckett]] enters another such pod to prevent death that was caused by cellular deterioration from the cloning process. A third stasis chamber on a planet contained Khalek, a clone Anubis created by using his own pre-Ascended DNA.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Prototype (Stargate SG-1)|Prototype]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Another such device is found containing Merlin himself, who stayed in suspended animation for about 1,000 years (since the time of King Arthur), when SG-1 enlists his help to re-create the Sangraal.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot; /&gt; Similar devices are used in Aurora-class ships, for use on extended voyages. These stasis chambers are egg-shaped and require the user to lie down. The pods can be modified so that the occupants can participate in [[virtual reality]], allowing their minds to remain active during long voyages. The pods interface with the ship's computer, so the crew can work on tasks while asleep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aurora&quot; /&gt;

===Time dilation device===
{{See also|Time Dilation Device}}
A device capable of altering the speed at which time passes in an area around itself. The first Ancient time dilation technology was in the Pegasus galaxy, where the Lanteans had constructed a refuge on a planet known as the Cloister, which had one entrance. The entire 'valley' region was engulfed by the time dilation field that accelerated time within its position in order to allow the inhabitants to learn how to [[Ascension (Stargate)|ascend]]. The field was a potent defensive mechanism as it prevents objects from entering the bubble from orbit, as they would be destroyed from the stresses generated by the field. The device is powered by a ZPM.&lt;ref name=&quot;Epiphany&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Epiphany (Stargate Atlantis)]]&quot; (''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; A second form was later seen in the [[Milky Way]], used by [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Ganos Lal/Morgan le Fay|Morgan le Fay]] as one of her tests for persons searching for the Sangraal. This model had a set field around the location of the mountain, which almost froze objects that entered the field and was the reason why many human villagers were lost on the quest as they had become trapped in the field. However, as part of the test, a set path is present that allowed movement without being compromised.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot; /&gt; And a third was installed by the Asgard into the ''Odyssey'', (along with an Asgard core and many other systems) which Colonel Carter used in [[Unending]] to protect the ''Odyssey'' from the Ori, while she could find a way to isolate the Asgard core from the hyperdrive and shut the core down as it was giving off a signal the Ori could trace through sub-space.

A similar device was discovered a few years earlier. This was much larger, which dialed several planets through the Stargate to form a subspace bubble. The machine was flawed, as it only creates a short-term [[time loop]], which forces the planets that the device dialed to relive the same ten hours again and again. It is powered by the ionized atoms in the atmosphere caused by the geo-magnetic storms on the planet. Two capacitors start to hum and emit static electricity that is channeled to the Stargate. The Ancients originally created it to stop a plague that was wiping them out, although it eventually only forced them to keep doing the same thing over and over. In the end, they were forced to shut down the device.&lt;ref name=&quot;Window of Opportunity&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Window of Opportunity (Stargate SG-1)|Window of Opportunity]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other===
*'''&quot;Ascendometer&quot;:''' An Ancient device used to measure a person's synaptic activity. Designed to work alongside the [[DNA Resequencer (Stargate)|DNA Resequencer]], the scanner analyzes a subject's current physiological status and feeds the information back into the resequencer. It was able to locate the areas of the brain that were used for advanced abilities such as [[telekinesis]], and was apparently used by the Ancients during their pursuit of [[ascension (Stargate)|Ascension]]. One of the scanners was discovered in the lab where [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] created and experimented on Khalek, a clone created by Anubis using his pre-ascension DNA. After the [[Stargate Command|SGC]] brought Khalek back to Earth for study, the scanner was brought with them and used to monitor his development. The device was nicknamed &quot;ascendometer&quot; by [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Colonel Mitchell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot; /&gt; The device was later sent to [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] and used on [[Rodney McKay]] after he accidentally manipulated his own DNA.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tao of Rodney&quot;/&gt;
*'''Clava Thessara Infinitas:''' Ancient for &quot;Key to Infinite Treasure&quot;, a circular tablet that supposedly holds the location of a cache of Ancient weapons. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] believes it to be a hoax. In {{sgcite|Memento Mori|SG-1}}, the [[Goa'uld]] [[Athena (Stargate)|Athena]] abducts [[Vala Mal Doran]] and probes her mind in an attempt to find the treasure. In {{sgcite|Bad Guys|SG-1}}, SG-1 goes to a planet in search of it, only to end up being mistaken for hostage takers in a museum. In {{sgcite|Dominion|SG-1}}, the Clava Thessara Infinitas is used as a pretense in a plan by [[SG-1]] to capture [[Adria (Stargate)|Adria]].
*'''Containment vessel:''' A device that encapsulates its contents in a layer of subspace. One such device is found on [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]] in {{sgcite|Hide and Seek|Atlantis}}. The Ancients had modified the device to attract and trap an energy creature as part of their research into [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascension]].
*'''Heliopolis &quot;Book&quot;''' A device detailing the meaning of human existence, found on PB2-908. Its design is similar to a DHD, but the only button on it is the red hemisphere in the center. Once pressed, an orange beam of light shoots out from the center and produces 3D [[holographic]] displays of elements, said to be a language anyone can understand. It has a shield that can absorb fire from Goa'uld staff weapons, as displayed in the episode.
*'''Inertial dampeners:''' A field of artificial gravity found in ships and personal shields to minimize the effects of [[inertia]]. They are activated first before ships take flight, and can be adjusted.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Storm&quot; /&gt;
*'''Interdimensional visibility device:''' Cylindrical device, though its complete purpose remains unknown, the device is known to have the ability to allow humans to perceive alien creatures that exist in other dimensions. The creatures do interact with our dimension in a limited way, as they appear to be resting on solid objects. Anyone who touches the device receives the extra-sensory perception, and becomes able to detect the creatures. This ability is spread via physical contact. It emits a type of radiation that appears to attract the creatures, and is controlled by reordering the crystals that power the mechanism in various positions. The Ancients constructed the device to study these extra-dimensional creatures. The device was later brought back to Earth by [[SG-1]], after which several SGC personnel began seeing the creatures. The effect was transmitted outside the base, though SG-1 was eventually able to contain the outbreak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sight Unseen&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Sight Unseen (Stargate SG-1)|Sight Unseen]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Kino:''' A spherical data-gathering device about the size of a softball found aboard the ''Destiny'' in ''[[Stargate Universe]]''. It has audio and visual recording abilities, as well as a wide range of other scanning devices. It hovers under its own power. The ''Destiny'' apparently carries a large supply, dispensed from a device resembling a gumball machine. The devices can be controlled by a primary panel near the dispenser or through handheld remotes. It is the Ancient equivalent of a [[Earth technology in Stargate#Mobile Analytic Laboratory Probe (M.A.L.P.)|MALP]], as it can be sent through an active Stargate and controlled remotely to gather data about the planet. [[Eli Wallace]] discovered the Kinos and named them after the Russian [[Kino-Pravda]] [[newsreel]] series.&lt;ref&gt;http://stargate.mgm.com/view/character/171/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; Eli uses the room housing the device as his personal quarters.
*'''Magnetic harmonic resonance:''' A device created by Janus in order to hide a secret laboratory on Atlantis and discovered by [[Rodney McKay]] and [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]]. The device is activated by emitting a series of tones tuned to a specific [[resonance frequency]] which destabilizes the atomic structure of an object. Magnetic fields are used to preserve the shape of the object, and to prevent material making up the object from getting swept along with other objects passing through it. The only known example of this technology has been to create a wall hiding the entrance to Janus's lab.
*'''Personal cloaking device:''' Consists of a triangular crystal worn around the arm,&lt;ref name=&quot;Babylon&quot; /&gt; allowing a user to exist out of phase. They can still see and interact with each other. Apparently, the cloaking device works similar to the Ancient device known as &quot;Arthur's Mantle&quot;, as the cloak's user will be able to interact with someone rendered out of phase by the Mantle, though they would still pass right through them if touched.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arthur's Mantle&quot; /&gt; The devices were mostly used by the [[Mythology of Stargate#Jaffa|Sodan]], though the SGC acquired several after the Sodan were exterminated by the Ori. Schematics for an Ancient cloaking device were found in Janus's secret lab, suggesting he may be the one who designed the device.

==See also==
*[[Ancient starships in Stargate]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

{{Stargate}}

[[Category:Stargate technology]]

[[cs:Antické technologie ve Hvězdné bráně]]
[[ka:ძველები (ვარსკვლავთკარიბჭე)#ტექნოლოგია]]
[[ru:Технологии Древних в Звёздных вратах]]
[[tr:Kadim teknolojisi (Yıldız Geçidi)]]
[[uk:Технології древніх]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
