<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6492448" ns="0" title="Mountain View College (Philippines)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Mountain View College (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox University
|name            = Mountain View College
|native_name     = Colegio ng Tanawing Kabundukan
|image           = 
|motto           = Shine On Till Jesus Comes
|established     = 1953
|type            = Private, Sectarian
|staff           =
|president       = Dr. Daniel D. Dial &lt;br/&gt;([[List of Presidents of Mountain View College (Philippines)|List of Presidents]])
|head_label      =
|head            =
|students        = 2,401
|undergrad       = 
|postgrad        =
|profess         =
|location        = [[Valencia City, Bukidnon]], {{flagicon|Philippines}} [[Philippines]]
|campus          = [[Rural area|Rural]] and [[Suburban]]
|free            =
|colours         = Blue and Yellow {{color box|blue}}{{color box|yellow}}
|nickname        = The School of the Light
|affiliations    = [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]], [[Association of Christian Schools, Colleges, and Universities]]
|footnotes       =
|website         =http://www.mvc.edu.ph
|logo            =
}}

'''Mountain View College''' (or '''MVC''') is a [[private school|private]], [[co-educational]], [[Seventh-day Adventist]] college in [[Valencia City, Bukidnon|Valencia City]], [[Bukidnon]], [[Philippines]] which was established in 1953.
It has a semestral enrollment of more than 2000 students primarily from [[Mindanao]], although there are also quite a number from [[Luzon]] and the [[Visayas]].  International enrollment from [[Cambodia]], [[Canada]], [[China]], [[Germany]], [[Indonesia]], [[Malaysia]], [[Micronesia]], [[Mongolia]], [[Myanmar]], [[South Korea]], the [[United States]], and other countries in [[Africa]] and [[Asia]], comprises about five percent of the total populace.

== History ==
MVC was founded by [[Andrew Nelson|Andrew Nathaniel Nelson]] in response to the growing interest in Christian education within the Philippines.
A 584% increase for a six-year period in the college enrollment of [[Adventist University of the Philippines|Philippine Union College]],
where he was then president, necessitated the search for another site.
Based on a nine-point criteria founded on Adventist principles and prior experience in the founding of two other educational institutions
([[Seattle Junior Academy]] in 1915 and [[Japan Missionary College]] in 1925), Dr. Nelson came upon MVC's present
site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| url = http://www.adventistarchives.org/doc_info.asp?DocID=74648
| last = Nelson
| first = Andrew
| title = Pioneering a new college in the Philippines
| journal = [[The Youth's Instructor]]
| date =  March 17, 1953 |   volume = 101
| issue = 11
| pages = 12–21
| accessdate = 2010-03-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Manticao, Misamis Oriental]] served as MVC's temporary campus from 1949 to 1952, while the search was on for a site that met the criteria.
It was then known as Philippine Union Junior College.
In 1953, MVC moved to its present location and opened its doors to students from the Southern Philippines. The previous campus then became [[Mindanao Mission Academy]]. MVC's first offerings were certificates or associate degrees in business, education, and religion. It held its first graduation exercises in 1957, four years after its official opening.

As of 2009, the college has 132 full time and part-time teaching faculty members and 73 staff members in the industrial and support service departments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| url = http://www.adventistarchives.org/doc_info.asp?DocID=180512
| last = General Conference of Seventh-day Adventists
| title = Institutional Statistics for 2009: Section 1-- Educational Institutions and Primary Schools
| journal = 147th Annual Statistical Report - 2009
| date =  2009
| page = 56
| accessdate = 2011-05-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campuses==

The main campus is located on a {{convert|2500|ft|m|-1|sing=on}} plateau in [[Mount Nebo (Philippines)|Mt. Nebo]], [[Valencia City, Bukidnon|Valencia City]], with an area of 10.24&amp;nbsp;km², which includes farmlands, forests, and ranch lands ideal for industry work. The land has an ample supply of water that allows MVC to have its own [[hydroelectric plant]]s, providing the campus populace with enough electricity along with an abundant water supply for the homes and other college facilities.

An annex campus is located in [[Bagontaas]], [[Valencia City, Bukidnon|Valencia City]], which is occupied by the School of Nursing. It includes a solarium, dormitories, classrooms, offices, and a cafeteria.

==Student life==

The student body of MVC is represented by the Central Student Council which elects its officers every school year.
Each of the seven schools has its own local council which elects its officers every semester.
About 80% of the students are housed in three ladies' dormitories, three men's dormitories, a co-ed dormitory, and a married-student dormitory.
The rest either stay with the faculty or commute from the nearby [[sitios]], [[barangays]], or [[philippine municipality|municipalities]].

===Student organizations===

MVC is home to a number of student organizations. Included here are the current and defunct organizations:

The political organizations include: Central Student Council, School of Agriculture Student Council, School of Arts and Sciences Student Council, School of Business and Accountancy Student Council, School of Computing Student Council, School of Education Student Council, School of Nursing Student Council, and School of Theology Student Council. Inter-school organizations include: ANAK, OP, and PE.

Academic organizations include: Circle of English Majors, Lambda Sigma, Mu Sigma Kappa, Society of Agricultural Majors, Society of Electrical Technologists, Teachers of Tomorrow - Ethyl Young Chapter, Teachers of Tomorrow - Urbano Oliva Chapter, Young Ellen's Club, Young Theologians Club.

The singing groups include the:
*Airwaves
*Advent Philomels
*Alauda Arvensis
*Blazing Mentors
*Cherubs
*Chordal Resonance
*Chordal Streams
*Daybreak
*First Light
*Hilltop Chorale
*MVC Singers
*Pinewoods Chorale
*Singing Ambassadors
*Sons and Daughters
*Sound of Care
*Thrushes Ministrants
*and Vibrant Echoes.
There are also other musical groups, such as: Hilltop Symphonic Band and His Instruments. 

Cultural organizations include:  Adventist Muslim Relations, International Students Association, area specific organizations, such as: Association of DAvao Mission Students (ADAMS); and the alumni organizations of the Adventist academies in Mindanao and the Visayas. Service, outreach, and ministerial organizations include: Hilltop Amateur Radio Team (HART), LIGHT, Master Guides, Ministerial Seminar, Peer Counselors, Regeneration, Rescue 741, Seekers for Truth, Student Association of Literature Evangelists (SALE), and SULADS. Miscellaneous organizations are: EARTH Society, Advent Explorers, and the Reach-out Gymnaires.

===Student media===

Also featured at MVC are a number of student publications, both current and defunct: Dots and Dashes, Non-Linear Points, The Orchid, Outreach, Newsprint, Pencil, The Slashes, The Sentry, BEAMS, Hilltop  Flashes, and The Views. Students also man the campus AM station, DXCR.

== Courses offered ==

*Associate in Office Administration

*Bachelor in Elementary Education
*Bachelor in Secondary Education, majors in Biological Sciences, English, [[Music, Arts, Physical Education, and Health|MAPEH]], Mathematics, Social Studies, [[Technology and Livelihood Education|TLE]], Values Education
*Bachelor of Arts in English Language
*Bachelor of Arts in History
*Bachelor of Arts in Theology
*Bachelor of Science in Accountancy
*Bachelor of Science in Accounting Technology
*Bachelor of Science in Agriculture, majors in Animal Science, Crop Science
*Bachelor of Science in Applied Mathematics
*Bachelor of Science in Biology
*Bachelor of Science in Computer Science
*Bachelor of Science in Information Systems
*Bachelor of Science in Information Technology
*Bachelor of Science in Business Administration, majors in Financial Management, Human Resource Management, Management, Management Accounting
*Bachelor of Science in Nursing
*Bachelor of Science in Office Administration, majors in Computer Education, Office Management

*Technical-Vocational Course: Automotive Servicing (NC 2)

*Basic Education: [[Mountain View College Academy|High School]], Elementary, Kindergarten 2, Kindergarten 1

== See also ==
* [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]]
* [[List of Seventh-day Adventist colleges and universities]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mvc.edu.ph Official website]
* [http://www.mvcollege.org MVC Old Website]
* [http://www.virtualmvc.com MVC Alumni Website]

{{coord|7|58.9|N|125|00.4|E|display=title|region:PH_type:landmark_source:GNS-enwiki}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the Seventh-day Adventist Church]]
[[Category:Adventist universities and colleges in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1953]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
