<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6513114" ns="0" title="World War III in popular culture"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Globalize|date=July 2010}}
'''World War III''' is a common [[War in popular culture|theme]] in [[popular culture]]. Since the 1940s, countless books, films, and television programmes have used the theme of [[nuclear weapon]]s and a [[World War III|third global war]].&lt;ref name=Biggs&gt;Biggs, Lindy and Hansen, James (editors), 2004, ''Readings in Technology and Civilisation'', ISBN 0-7593-3869-8.&lt;/ref&gt; The presence of the [[Soviet Union]] as an international rival armed with nuclear weapons created a persistent fear in the [[United States]]. There was a pervasive dread of a [[nuclear warfare|nuclear]] World War III, and popular culture reveals the fears of the public at the time.&lt;ref name=Worland&gt;Worland, Rick, 2006, ''The Horror Film: An Introduction'', Blackwell Publishing, ISBN 1-4051-3902-1.&lt;/ref&gt; This theme in the arts was also a way of exploring a range of issues far beyond nuclear war.&lt;ref name=Franklin&gt;Franklin, Jerome, 2002, ''Atomic Bomb Cinema: The Apocalyptic Imagination on Film'', Routledge, ISBN 0-415-93660-8.&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Spencer R. Weart]] called nuclear weapons a &quot;symbol for the worst of modernity.&quot;&lt;ref name=Biggs/&gt;

During the Cold War, concepts such as [[mutual assured destruction]] (MAD) led lawmakers and government officials in both the United States and the Soviet Union to avoid entering a nuclear World War III that could have had catastrophic consequences on the entire world.&lt;ref name=Lipschutz&gt;Lipschutz, Ronnie D., 2001, ''Cold War Fantasies: Film, Fiction, and Foreign Policy'', Rowman &amp; Littlefield, ISBN 0-7425-1052-2.&lt;/ref&gt; Various scientists and authors, such as [[Carl Sagan]], predicted massive, possibly life ending destruction of the earth as the result of such a conflict.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}} [[Military strategy|Strategic analysts]] assert that nuclear weapons prevented the United States and the Soviet Union from fighting World War III with [[conventional weapon]]s.&lt;ref name=Angelo&gt;Angelo, Joseph A., 2004, ''Nuclear Technology'', Greenwood Press, ISBN 1-57356-336-6.&lt;/ref&gt;  Nevertheless, the possibility of such a war became the basis for [[speculative fiction]], and its simulation in books, films and video games became a way to explore the issues of a war that has thus far not occurred in reality.&lt;ref name=Lipschutz/&gt; The only places a global nuclear war have ever been fought are in expert scenarios, theoretical models, war games, and the art, film, and literature of the [[History of nuclear weapons|nuclear age]].&lt;ref name=Martin&gt;Martin, Andrew, and Petro, Patrice, 2006, ''Rethinking Global Security: Media, Popular Culture, and the &quot;War on Terror&quot;'' Rutgers University Press, ISBN 0-8135-3830-0.&lt;/ref&gt; The concept of mutually assured destruction was also the focus of numerous movies and films.&lt;ref name=Lipschutz/&gt;

Prescient stories about nuclear war were written before the invention of the atomic bomb. The most notable of these is ''[[The World Set Free]]'', written by [[H. G. Wells]] in 1914. During [[World War II]], several nuclear war stories were published in [[science fiction]] magazines such as [[Analog Science Fiction and Fact|''Astounding'']].&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; In [[Robert A. Heinlein|Robert A. Heinlein's]] story &quot;[[Solution Unsatisfactory]]&quot; the US develops radioactive dust as the ultimate weapon of war and uses it to destroy [[Berlin]] in 1945 and end the war with Germany. The Soviet Union then develops the same weapon independently, and war between it and the US follows.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}} The bombing of [[Hiroshima]] and [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]] in 1945 made stories of a future global nuclear war look less like fiction and more like prophecy.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; When [[William Faulkner]] received the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] in 1949, he spoke about Cold War themes in art. He worried that younger writers were too preoccupied with the question of &quot;When will I be blown up?&quot;&lt;ref name=Halliwell&gt;Halliwell, Martin, 2007, ''American Culture in the 1950s'', Edinburgh University Press, ISBN 0-7486-1885-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

==1940s: Dawn of the atomic age==
[[The atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] ushered in the &quot;atomic age&quot;, and the bleak pictures of the bombed-out cities released shortly after the end of World War II became symbols of the power of the new weapons.

On August 29, 1949, the Soviet Union tested its first atomic bomb, code named &quot;[[Joe 1]]&quot;. Its design imitates the American plutonium bomb that was dropped on Nagasaki, Japan in 1945.

== 1950s: Fears of the new and unknown==
[[Image:AtomicWar0101.jpg|thumb|right|200px|1952 [[comic book]] cover, stories speculating on 1960 events]]
American fears of an impending apocalyptic World War III with the [[Eastern Bloc|communist bloc]] were strengthened by the quick succession of the Soviet Union’s nuclear bomb test, the [[Chinese Civil War|Chinese Communist Revolution]] in 1949, and the beginning of the [[Korean War]] in 1950. [[pundit (expert)|Pundits]] named the era &quot;the age of anxiety&quot;, after [[W. H. Auden]].&lt;ref name=Worland/&gt; In 1951 an entire issue of ''[[Collier's]]'' magazine was devoted to a fictional account of World War III. The issue was entitled &quot;[[Preview of the War We Do Not Want]]&quot;. In the magazine, war begins when the [[Red Army]] invades [[Yugoslavia]] and the United States responds by conducting a three month long bombing campaign of Soviet Union military and industrial targets. The Soviet Union retaliates by bombing [[New York City]], [[Washington, D.C.]], [[Philadelphia]], and [[Detroit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Imaginary War: Civil Defense and American Cold War Culture |last=Oakes |first=Guy |year=1994 |publisher=Oxford University Press
US |location= |isbn=0195090276 |pages=56–57 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Against this background of dread there was an outpouring of cinema with frightening themes, particularly in the science fiction genre. Science fiction had previously not been popular with either critics or movie audiences, but it became a viable [[Hollywood]] genre during the [[Cold War]]. In the 1950s science fiction had two main themes: the invasion of the Earth (symbolising the US) by superior, aggressive, and frequently technologically advanced aliens; and the dread of atomic weapons, which was typically portrayed as a revolt of nature, with irradiated monsters attacking and ravaging entire cities.&lt;ref name=Worland/&gt;

In ''[[The Day the Earth Stood Still (1951 film)|The Day the Earth Stood Still]]'' (1951), a flying saucer lands on the [[National Mall|Mall in Washington DC]], where it is surrounded by troops and tanks. The alien Klaatu delivers an ultimatum that the Earth must learn to live in peace or it will be destroyed. ''[[The War of the Worlds (1953 film)|The War of the Worlds]]'' (1953) has a montage sequence where the countries of Earth join together to fight the Martian invaders. The montage conspicuously omits the Soviet Union, implying that the aliens are a metaphor for communists. The most elaborate science fiction films in the 1950s were ''[[This Island Earth]]'' (1955) and ''[[Forbidden Planet]]'' (1956). In the climax of both films the characters witness the explosion of alien planets, implying Earth's possible fate.&lt;ref name=Worland/&gt; ''[[The World, the Flesh and the Devil (1959 film)|The World, the Flesh and the Devil]]'' (1959) is also in the science fiction genre. In it, a man, a woman, and a bigot (the devil) roam [[New York City]] after a nuclear war. Only those three characters appear in the film. Also released in 1959 was ''[[On the Beach (1959 film)|On the Beach]]'', directed by [[Stanley Kramer]] and starring [[Ava Gardner]], [[Gregory Peck]] and [[Fred Astaire]].  Based on the [[On the Beach (novel)|successful novel]] by [[Nevil Shute]], the film deals with the citizens of [[Australia]] as they await radioactive fallout, a result of a catastrophic [[Nuclear warfare|nuclear war]] in the [[Northern Hemisphere]]. The [[French people|French]] author [[Stefan Wul]]'s 1957 novel ''[[Niourk]]'' provided a portrait of New York after World War III.&lt;ref&gt;Horn, Pierre L., 1991, ''Handbook of French Popular Culture'', Greenwood, ISBN 0-313-26121-0, page 236.&lt;/ref&gt;  The 1959 novel [[Alas, Babylon]] depicted the effects of nuclear war on a small town in Florida; an television adaptation was broadcast in 1960.

''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'', [[George Orwell]]'s bleak 1949 novel about life after a third world war, rose to cultural prominence in the 1950s. In it the world has endured a massive atomic war and is politically divided into three totalitarian superstates, which are intentionally locked into a perpetual military stalemate; this never-ending warfare is used to subjugate their populations.

== 1960s: Expanding popularity ==
In the 1960s, media about the threat of nuclear world war gained wide popularity. According to [[Susan Sontag]], these films struck people’s &quot;imagination of disaster...in the fantasy of living through one’s own death and more the death of cities, the destruction of humanity itself.&quot;&lt;ref name=Quart&gt;Quart, Leonard, and Auster, Albert, 2001, ''American Film and Society'', Praeger/Greenwood, ISBN 0-275-96743-3, p. 76-77.&lt;/ref&gt; A leading member of the 1960s anti-war movement, singer-songwriter [[Bob Dylan]] evoked the topic of WWIII thrice in his seminal ''[[The Freewheelin' Bob Dylan]]'', in &quot;[[Masters of War]]&quot;, &quot;[[Talkin' World War III Blues]]&quot;, and &quot;[[A Hard Rain's a-Gonna Fall]]&quot;.  The 1968 [[Philip K. Dick]] novel ''[[Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?]]'', adapted to film in 1982 as ''[[Blade Runner]]'', features as its setting an Earth having been damaged greatly by the radioactive fallout of a nuclear war termed &quot;World War Terminus.&quot;

In [[1964 in film|1964]] three films about the threat of accidental nuclear war were released, ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'', ''[[Fail-Safe (1964 film)|Fail-Safe]]'', and ''[[Seven Days in May]]''. Their negative portrayal of [[National missile defense|nuclear defence]] prompted the [[United States Air Force]] to sponsor films such as ''[[A Gathering of Eagles]]'' to publicly address the potential dangers of nuclear defense.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; 

''Dr. Strangelove'' is a [[black comedy]] by [[Stanley Kubrick]] about the [[nuclear arms race]] between the US and the Soviet Union and the doctrine of mutually assured destruction.&lt;ref name=Angelo/&gt; Following a bizarre mental breakdown the [[Commanding officer|C.O.]] of a [[Strategic Air Command|SAC]] base orders the [[B-52]] [[Air wing|wing]] operating from his base to attack the [[Soviet Union]]. The title character, Dr. Strangelove, is a parody of a composite of Cold War figures, including [[Wernher von Braun]], [[Henry Kissinger]], and [[Herman Kahn]]. The secret code Operation DROPKICK, mentioned by [[George C. Scott]]'s character, may be an oblique reference to [[Operation Dropshot]].

The 1964 film ''[[Fail-Safe (1964 film)|Fail-Safe]]'' was adapted from a best-selling [[Fail-Safe (novel)|novel]] of the same name by [[Eugene Burdick]] and [[Harvey Wheeler]]. In it, nuclear disaster is caused by a technological breakdown that mistakenly launches American bombers to attack the Soviet Union. In order to prove the mistake and placate the Soviets, thereby saving the world from nuclear war, the US President orders the destruction of New York after a US bomber succeeds in destroying Moscow. The film was made in a semi-documentary style, ending just as the explosion over New York City begins.&lt;ref name=Quart/&gt;

''[[The War Game]]'' ([[1965 in film|1965]]), produced by [[Peter Watkins]], deals with a fictional nuclear attack on Britain. This film won the [[Academy Awards|Oscar]] for Best Documentary, but was withheld from broadcast by the [[BBC]] for two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mnsi.net/~pwatkins/warGame.htm|title=Peter Watkins - The War Game|accessdate=2007-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== 1970s: Fears continue ==
The American public's concerns about nuclear weapons and related technology continued to be present in the 1970s. The most talked about events in the 1970s were the [[Vietnam War]], the [[Watergate scandal]], the [[Iran hostage crisis]], the [[energy crisis]], and  [[stagflation]]. None of these issues easily lent themselves to apocalyptic scenarios.&lt;ref name=Franklin/&gt; In the 1977 [[Robert Aldrich]] film ''[[Twilight's Last Gleaming]]'', a nuclear [[missile silo]] is seized by renegade [[USAF|US Air Force]] officers, who threaten to start World War III if the American government does not reveal secret documents that show that the military needlessly prolonged the Vietnam War.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=History of the American cinema |last=Harpole |first=Charles |year= |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=0520232658 |page=203 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On television, the British science fiction series ''[[Doctor Who]]'' based a 1972 storyline, ''[[Day of the Daleks]]'' on the premise of time travellers from the future attempting to trigger a present-day nuclear war between the superpowers.

== 1980s: Belief in an imminent threat ==
In the early 1980s there was a feeling of alarm in Europe and North America that a nuclear World War III was imminent. In 1982, 250,000 people protested against nuclear weapons in [[Bonn]], then the capital of [[West Germany]].&lt;ref name=Nichols&gt;Nichols, Thomas M., 2002, ''Winning the World: Lessons for America's Future from the Cold War'', Praeger/Greenwood, ISBN 0-275-96663-1.&lt;/ref&gt; On June 12, 1982, more than 750,000 protesters marched from the [[United Nations headquarters|U.N. headquarters building]] to [[Central Park]] in New York to call for a [[Nuclear freeze|Nuclear Freeze]].&lt;ref name=rosenzweig&gt;Rosenzweig, Roy, and Blackmar, Elizabeth, 1992, ''The Park and the People: A History of Central Park'', Cornell University Press, ISBN 0-8014-9751-5.&lt;/ref&gt; The public accepted the technological certainty of nuclear war, but did not have faith in nuclear defence.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; Tensions came to a head with the NATO exercise [[Able Archer 83]], which, combined with other events such as President Reagan's &quot;[[Evil Empire]]&quot; speech and the deployment of the [[Pershing II]] missile in Western Europe, as well as the erroneous Soviet shoot-down of [[Korean Air Lines Flight 007]], had the Soviets frantically convinced that the West was about to launch an all-out war against the USSR. 

These fears were manifested in the popular culture of the time, with images of nuclear war in books, film, music, and television. In the mid 1980s artists and musicians drew parallels with their time and the 1950s as two key moments in the Cold War.&lt;ref name=Halliwell/&gt;

There was a steady stream of popular music with apocalyptic themes. The 1983 hit &quot;[[99 Luftballons]]&quot; by [[Nena]] tells the story of a young woman who accidentally triggers a nuclear holocaust by releasing balloons. The music video for &quot;Sleeping with the Enemy&quot; had images of the [[Red Army]] parading in [[Red Square]], American high school marching bands, and a [[mushroom cloud]]. The 1984 hit &quot;[[Two Tribes]]&quot; by [[Frankie Goes to Hollywood]] had actors resembling [[Konstantin Chernenko]] and [[Ronald Reagan]] fighting each other amidst a group of cheering people. At the end of their fight, the Earth explodes.&lt;ref name=Nichols/&gt; [[Sting (musician)|Sting's]] 1986 song &quot;Russians&quot; highlighted links between [[Nikita Khrushchev|Nikita Khrushchev's]] threats to bury the US and Reagan's promise to protect US citizens.&lt;ref name=Halliwell/&gt; Many [[punk rock|punk]], [[hardcore punk|hardcore]] and [[crossover thrash]] bands of the era, such as [[The Varukers]] and [[Discharge (band)|Discharge]], had lyrics concerning nuclear war, the end of mankind and the destruction of the Earth in much of their early material. Several hit songs seemed to describe attempts to survive nuclear exchange or decry the arms race, such as [[Donald Fagen]]'s [[New Frontier]] and [[Don Henley]]'s [[The End of the Innocence (song)|The End of the Innocence]], respectively. Others portrayed an 'oh, well' attitude toward an imminent WWIII([[Modern English]]'s &quot;Melt With You&quot;), while others conveyed an outright panic over the possibility([[Genesis (band)|Genesis]]'s [[Land of Confusion]]). Still others described the possible aspects and after effects of nuclear war([[Talking Heads]]'s [[Burning Down the House]], but this is only one interpretation of the lyrics), and some seemed to describe life in the Communist Bloc(possibly [[Crowded House]]'s [[Don't Dream It's Over]]), justifying the West taking a stand, though not military action.

Films and television programmes made in the 1980s had different visions of what World War III would be like.&lt;ref name=Halliwell/&gt; ''[[Red Dawn]]'' (1984) portrayed a World War III that begins unexpectedly, with a surprise Soviet and Cuban invasion of the United States. A small band of teenagers fight the Soviet and Cuban occupation using guerrilla tactics.&lt;ref name=Lipschutz/&gt; In the 1983 [[James Bond]] film ''[[Octopussy]]'', James Bond tries to stop World War III from being started by a renegade Soviet general.&lt;ref name=Nichols/&gt; [[WarGames]] (1983) had a teenage gamer accidentally hacking the U.S. nuclear defense network(thinking he'd hacked a computer game company), which reveals a potentially catastrophic flaw in the newly automated system.

In the early 1980s there were a number of films made for television that had World War III as a theme. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC's]] ''[[The Day After]]'' (1983), [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS's]] [[Testament (film)|''Testament'']] (1983), and the [[BBC|BBC's]] ''[[Threads]]'' (1984) depicted nuclear World War III. The three movies show a nuclear war against the Soviet Union, which sends its troops marching across Western Europe. These films inspired many to join the [[Anti-nuclear|anti-nuclear movement]].&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; ''Threads'' is notable for its graphically disturbing and realistic depictions of post-nuclear survival.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}}

''The Day After'' was shown on ABC on November 20, 1983, at a time when Soviet-US relations were at rock bottom, just weeks after the [[NATO]]-led [[Able Archer 83]] exercises, and less than three months after [[Korean Air Lines Flight 007]] was shot down by Soviet [[interceptor aircraft|jet interceptors]]. ABC warned its audience about the graphic nature of the film. ''The Day After'' became a political event in itself and was shown in over forty countries.&lt;ref name=Nichols/&gt; The shocking and disturbing content discouraged advertisers, but had the largest audience for a made-for-TV movie up to that time&lt;ref name=fallout/&gt; (a record which still stands as of 2008){{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} and influenced the [[Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty]] negotiations in 1986.&lt;ref name=fallout&gt;[http://www.lawrence.com/news/2003/nov/19/fallout_from/ Fallout from 'The Day After'], Lawrence.com November 19, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[1982 in television|1982]] NBC miniseries ''[[World War III (miniseries)|World War III]]'', directed by [[David Greene (director)|David Greene]], received little critical attention.&lt;ref name=Franklin/&gt; In the programme, a Soviet Spetznaz (Special Forces) invasion of [[Alaska]] in order to destroy the [[Trans-Alaska Pipeline System|Alaska oil pipeline]] escalates to a full scale war. The miniseries abruptly ends with the President releasing US nuclear forces against the Soviets. This narrative is almost unique because the film ends moments before the world is annihilated with nuclear weapons. Similar stories about the destruction of the world showed the possibility of the world's rebirth following global destruction.&lt;ref name=Franklin/&gt; 

During the 1980s, the [[techno-thriller]] became a literary phenomenon in the United States. These novels about high-tech non-nuclear warfare reasserted the value of conventional weapons by showing how they would be vital in the world's next large scale conflict.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; [[Tom Clancy|Tom Clancy's]] novels proposed the idea of a technical challenge to the Soviet Union, where World War III could be won using only conventional weapons, without resorting to nuclear weapons. Clancy’s detailed explanation of how and why World War III could begin involves oil shortages in the Soviet Union caused by Islamic terrorism within it. ''[[The Hunt for Red October]]'' (1984) hypothesized that the Soviet Union’s technology would soon be better than the Americans'. ''[[Red Storm Rising]]'' was a detailed account of the coming world war.&lt;ref name=Lipschutz/&gt; Soon after the Cold War ended techno-thriller  novels changed from stories about fighting the Soviet Union to narratives about fighting terrorists.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; 

Comics also began to address the issue of World War III with the implications of super-powered beings as metaphors for nuclear weapons. Marvel Comics gathered many of their Russian super-hero and villain characters into a new group, called &quot;The Soviet Super-Soldiers&quot; which answered directly to the Soviet Government. They also addressed the issue of Russian born mutants, in X-Factor Annual #1, with a story that revealed that all Soviet born mutants were forcibly drafted upon discovery, to serve as covert assassins for the Soviet government. 

The most notable Marvel story addressing the issue of World War III was in Uncanny X-Men #150. In it, the villain Magneto once again threatens the world, with the threat of using his newly increased magnetic powers to cause unspeakable destruction across the globe unless all of the governments of the world cede control over the planet to him. Magneto, when confronted by the X-Men, defends his murderous actions (which includes destroying an entire Russian city and sinking a Soviet nuclear submarine) by stating that if he not take over the world then and there, that mutantkind would be destroyed along with mankind in the event of a nuclear war. 

Meanwhile DC began to explore, in the pages of its various black-ops themed comics, similar ideas as they introduced various Soviet backed super-powered beings. These appeared in the pages of Suicide Squad, Firestorm the Nuclear Man, Captain Atom, and Checkmate.

The most notable characters introduced were the armored suit wearing soldiers &quot;The Rocket Reds&quot;, a special platoon of armor wearing Russian soldiers who were introduced in the pages of &quot;The Green Lantern Corps&quot; in Green Lantern #206. 

World War III was also a major theme of the 1987 [[Justice League]], as it went from an apolitical organization to being backed by the United Nations. 

While mainstream DC Comics offered an optimistic look at World War III, other comics were more cynical. &quot;[[Batman: The Dark Knight Returns]]&quot; portrayed World War III erupting over the issue of a small Latin American country, with the Soviet Union effectively &quot;winning&quot; the war overnight by using a specially designed weapon called a &quot;Coldbringer&quot;; the Coldbringer produces a massive electromagnetic pulse designed to shut down all technology and cover the sky with soot and dust, effectively condemning all of America to [[nuclear winter]] but without the mass murdering side-effects of radiation. The mini-series also featured Superman being portrayed as a government agent, working as a one-man army for the US Government. Unlike Watchmen's Dr. Manhattan however, Superman is shown to be conflicted with his job as a government agent and still refuses to take human lives (something Dr. Manhattan had no problems with).

The best selling and acclaimed mini-series turned graphic novel [[Watchmen (comic)|''Watchmen'']] takes place in an alternate 1985 where superheros exist and where Nixon is still President. In the story, [[Dr. Manhattan]], an omnipotent super-hero created in a lab accident in the 1960s, has become America's chief &quot;weapon&quot; and defender in their war against the Soviet Union and his disappearance (manipulated by his fellow super-hero [[Adrian Veidt]]) has caused relations between the Soviet Union and America, already on tense terms, to explode as the Soviets begin exploiting Manhattan's disappearance, causing the United States to stand ready to begin nuclear war with the Soviets. The series itself also takes a nhillistic view of super-heroes &quot;solving&quot; the issue of how to prevent World War III: in the end, the brilliant genius Veidt decides that the only way to save the world is to create a new threat that would be powerful enough to scare humanity into uniting for its own self-preservation. To this end, Veidt has spent over a decade building a genetically engineered monster which he teleports into New York City, killing millions yet succeeding in uniting America and the Soviets together. Though his scheme is discovered by his fellow heroes, they ultimately opt to keep silent, lest the world resume the path to destruction.

[[When the Wind Blows (graphic novel)|''When the Wind Blows'']], a [[graphic novel]] by [[Raymond Briggs]], was published in 1982.  The novel is a bitter [[satire]] on the advice given by the British government about how to survive a nuclear war,&lt;ref name=Ousby&gt;Ousby, Ian, 1996, ''Cambridge Paperback Guide to Literature in English'', ISBN 0-521-43627-3, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; where a working-class couple that do not believe that nuclear war is possible die of [[radiation sickness]] after a nuclear explosion. It reflects Briggs’ participation in the British [[Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament]].&lt;ref name=Silveiy&gt;Silveiy, Anita, 2002, ''The Essential Guide to Children’s Books and Their Creators'', Houghton Mifflin Books, ISBN 0-618-19082-1, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; Briggs is best known as a writer and illustrator of children’s literature, but this novel was written for an older audience&lt;ref name=Ousby/&gt; and is his bleakest work. The novel’s message greatly affected young adult readers. Briggs rewrote the novel for radio, stage,&lt;ref name=Silveiy/&gt; and an [[When the Wind Blows (film)|animated film]] that was released in 1986.&lt;ref name=Beck&gt;Beck, Jerry, 2005, ''The Animated Movie Guide'', Chicago Review Press, ISBN 1-55652-591-5, p. 309.&lt;/ref&gt;

== 1990s: Fears subside==
The Cold War ended without the destructive final global war that had often been envisioned in popular culture,&lt;ref name=Nichols/&gt; and the public's fears of World War III were allayed. On the other hand, the previously classified [[Stanislav Petrov]] incident of 1983 seemed to imply that the risk of accidental nuclear war due to technical malfunction had been greater than previously anticipated. The theme of nuclear armageddon launched by military [[artificial intelligence]] computer systems without human decision was explored in the 1991 blockbuster movie ''[[Terminator 2: Judgment Day]]''.  During the early 90s and the [[Gulf Crisis]], [[Tabloid (newspaper format)|tabloid]] papers and other press discussed whether World War III would be linked to prophecies of [[Nostradamus]] concerning a third great war.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nostradamuspredictionhoax.com/gulf.htm&lt;/ref&gt; 

Movies about nuclear weapons that saved humanity were popular. Films such as such as [[Armageddon (1998 film)|''Armageddon'']] and ''[[Deep Impact (film)|Deep Impact]]'' (1998).&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt; ''[[Blast from the Past (movie)|Blast from the Past]]'' ([[1999 in film|1999]]) is a comedy about a 1960s family caught in the grip of Cold War paranoia. Falsely convinced that World War III has started, they hide in their fallout shelter, only to emerge 35 years later in the post–Cold War world. [[Jonathan Schell]] complained to the ''[[New York Times]]'' that &quot;the post–Cold War generation knows less about nuclear danger than any generation.&quot;&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt;

''[[Yellow Peril (novel)|Yellow Peril]]'' (1991) by [[Wang Lixiong]], is about a civil war in the [[People's Republic of China]] that becomes a nuclear exchange and soon engulfs the world. It was banned by the [[Chinese Communist Party]] but remained popular.{{Citation needed|date=August 2007}}

World War III is referenced in the 1996 film [[Star Trek: First Contact]]. [[William T. Riker]] states that 600 million people were killed and very few world governments are left.

== 2000s: Concern over terrorism ==
After the [[9/11|September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks]], a scenario of World War III beginning as a result of a nuclear or other catastrophic terrorist attack became prominent. Terrorism in the form of nuclear, chemical, or biological attacks now occupy the place in popular culture once held by the vision of a nuclear World War III between world powers.&lt;ref name=Martin/&gt;

[[Paramount Pictures]] released a film adaptation of Tom Clancy's ''[[The Sum of All Fears (film)|The Sum of All Fears]]'' in 2002. The production of the film began before 9/11, and was originally intended as an escapist [[thriller (genre)|thriller]] where [[CIA]] analyst [[Jack Ryan (Tom Clancy)|Jack Ryan]] fights Neo-Nazis who conspire to detonate a nuclear weapon at a football game to start a nuclear war between Russia and the United States. However, the film’s release just seven months after 9/11 made it very topical. [[Phil Alden Robinson]], the film's director, commented that &quot;a year ago, you'd have said, 'great popcorn film,'...Today you say, 'that's about the world I live in.'&quot; There was an aggressive promotional campaign, with movie trailers and television commercials showing the nuclear destruction of a city and a special premiere for politicians in Washington, D.C. 

Recently, World War III has also become the topic of several popular video games, reflecting the trend towards increased public consciousness of the possibility of a future global war.  Games such as ''[[Tom Clancy's EndWar]]'', ''[[Battlefield 3]]'' and ''[[Frontlines: Fuel of War]]'', paint scenarios about a Third World War driven by the need for resources on the part of the various combatants.  ''[[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2]]'' and ''[[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3]]'' are also recent examples; at the end of the latter's launch advertisement, the &quot;W&quot; in &quot;WW3&quot; flips itself to read &quot;MW3.&quot; These games feature a global war between the United States and Russia after the United States is framed for a massacre at a Moscow airport and soon after the Russians expand their war into France, Germany and England. Other games such as ''[[World In Conflict]]'', and ''[[Turning Point: Fall of Liberty]]'' take place in [[alternate history|alternate histories]] where global war is a reality, the former being a war between the [[United States]] and the [[Soviet Union]], and the latter being a war between the [[United States]] and a much stronger [[Nazi Germany]] that won [[World War II]], both games depicting an invasion of America. The ''[[Fallout (series)|Fallout]]'' series portrays the effects of a nuclear holocaust in the future after a war between China and the United States in the late 21st century. [[Ace Combat]] [[Ace Combat: Assault Horizon|Assault Horizon]] portrays the United States and Russia going to war due to a massive superweapon being built. The 2007 bestselling game [[DEFCON (video game)|DEFCON]] places players in charge of preparing to and then fighting a nuclear war with other human or computer-generated players attacking from and defending different sectors of planet Earth; its simple 1980s-style vector graphics are inspired by those seen in the 1983 hit movie [[WarGames]].

In 2000 a made-for-television remake of ''[[Fail Safe (2000 TV)|Fail-Safe]]'' was produced; it continued to be set, however, in the same time period as the original film.

The video game [[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2]], released on November 2009, depicts the start of World War III after [[Russia]] blames the [[United States]] for a massacre at Zakhaev International Airport in [[Moscow]].

== 2010s: Fall of Terrorism, Rise of Conspiracy ==
The pronounced death of Osama bin Laden by the American President Barack Obama at 11:35 p.m., May 1st, 2011, has drastically reduce the danger of [[terrorism]]. However, certain sources claim that Osama is still alive&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gold |first=Matea |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/world/la-fg-bin-laden-conspiracy-20110503,0,3052618.story |title=Osama bin Laden dead: Bin Laden's burial at sea fuels 'death hoax' rumor |work=Los Angeles Times |date= May 2, 2011|accessdate=May 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; after Operation [[Neptune]] [[Spear]] which started on May 1st, 2011.

Many countries across the world, excluding Pakistan and Iran, celebrated over the death of Osama. The [[Abbottabad]], [[Pakistan]] residents claim that Osama's death was a U.S. conspiracy against Pakistan. Iranians believed that Osama may had been working with the U.S. during the entire war of terror. Ismail Kosari, an Iranian MP, said that Osama bin Laden was just a puppet controlled by the [[Zionist]] regime in order to present a violent image of Islam after the [[September 11 attacks]].

Several hoax about Osama's death were found in Twitter and Facebook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/pakistan/8489304/Osama-bin-Laden-killed-conspiracy-theories-proliferate-in-wake-of-raid.html | title=Osama bin Laden killed: conspiracy theories proliferate in wake of raid | date=May 3, 2011 | work=[[The Daily Telegraph]] | accessdate=May 3, 2011 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

World War III and its predicted aftermath continues to be portrayed in popular media around the world such as in recent video games ''[[Metro 2033]]'', ''[[Fallout 3]]'', ''[[Fallout New Vegas]]'', ''[[Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 3]]'', ''[[ARMA 3]]'', and ''[[APOX]]''. 

[[Alien invasion|Alien invasions]] have become a popular topic as a World War III like conflict with the alien invaders portrayed in a similar way to a military invasion, such as seen in the films [[Battle: Los Angeles]], [[Skyline (film)|Skyline]] and the TV series [[Falling Skies]]

== See also ==
*[[Nuclear weapons in popular culture]]
*[[Survivalism in fiction]]
*[[Death of Osama bin Laden]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.wsu.edu/~brians/nuclear/index.htm ''Nuclear Holocausts: Atomic War in Fiction'', By Paul Brians, Professor of English, Washington State University, Pullman, Washington.]

[[Category:Fictional wars]]
[[Category:Topics in popular culture]]
[[Category:Nuclear war and weapons in popular culture]]
[[Category:World War III speculative fiction| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
