<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="652389" ns="0" title="South African Special Forces Brigade"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= South African Special Forces Brigade
|image=[[File:South African Special Forces Brigade.svg|150px]]
|caption=Special Forces Compass Rose insignia
|dates= 1972–present
|country= [[File:Flag of South Africa 1928-1994.svg|23px|border]]{{flagicon|South Africa}} [[South Africa]]
|allegiance= [[South African National Defence Force]]
|branch= Joint Operations Division
|type= [[Special forces]]
|role= [[Reconnaissance]],  [[Sabotage]], [[Underwater demolition]], [[Counter-terrorism]]
|size= 
|command_structure=
|garrison=Speskop, [[Pretoria]], [[Gauteng]]
|garrison_label=
|nickname=Recces
|patron=
|motto=''We fear naught but God''
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
|identification_symbol_3=
|identification_symbol_3_label=
}}

The '''South African Special Forces Brigade''' (popularly known as &quot;Recces&quot;) is the only [[Special Forces]] unit of the [[South African National Defence Force]] (SANDF).

On October 1, 1972, 1 Reconnaissance Commando was created at [[Oudtshoorn]], South Africa. It was relocated a few years later to [[Durban]], South Africa. This was the first South African Special Forces unit. 

The South African special forces played a significant role in the country's 30 year long [[South African Border War|border war]] in [[Namibia]] and [[Angola]].
 
South African Special Forces now consists of Special Forces Headquarters in Pretoria, 4 Special Forces Regiment in Langebaan, 5 Special Forces Regiment - [[Phalaborwa]] and the Special Forces School in Murrayhill.

4 Special Forces Regiment specialise in maritime-related activities, whereas 5 Special Forces regiment specialises more in overland techniques, especially long-range infiltration.

The Brigade is not a part of the [[South African Army]], it is directly under the command of the Joint Operations Division of the SANDF.

== History ==
The first South African Special Forces unit, [[1 Reconnaissance Commando (South Africa)|1 Reconnaissance Commando]], was established in the town of [[Oudtshoorn]], [[Cape Province]] on 1 October 1972. On 1 January 1975, this unit was relocated to [[Durban]], [[KwaZulu-Natal Province|Natal]], where it continued its activities as the airborne specialist unit of the special forces.

Later, two additional Reconnaissance Commandos were formed:
* [[South African 4 Reconnaissance Commando|4 Reconnaissance Commando]], specialising in seaborne operations, was established in the coastal town of [[Langebaan]], [[Cape Province]].
* [[South African 5 Reconnaissance Commando|5 Reconnaissance Commando]] was established at the [[Duku-Duku]] camp in [[Natal Province|Natal]], but was later moved to [[Phalaborwa]] in the [[Transvaal Province|Transvaal]] province.   

On 1 January 1981, a re-organisation of Special Forces took place, as part of which the Reconnaissance Commandos and other special forces were transformed into an independent formation, directly under the command of the (then) [[South African Defence Force]] (instead of the South African Army). As part of the re-organisation, the various Reconnaissance Commandos were also given the status of [[regiment]]s. In the latter part of the same decade, a Special Forces headquarters and a Special Forces stores depot were also added to the Special Forces structure.

Between the years 1981 and 1990, Special Forces was home to unconventional operations such as [[Project Barnacle]], the [[Civil Cooperation Bureau]] and a variety of other operations conducted under the aegis of [[7 Medical Battalion Group]].

In 1991, the structure of the special forces underwent another change, when the special forces headquarters was disbanded and a Directorate Reconnaissance, reporting directly to the Chief of the Army, was established instead.

Another organisational change followed in 1993, when the Directorate Reconnaissance became 45 Parachute Brigade.  As a result of this, all the units were renamed: 1 Reconnaissance Regiment became 452 Parachute Battalion, 4 Reconnaissance Regiment became 453 Parachute Battalion and 5 Reconnaissance Regiment became 451 Parachute Battalion.

As a result of the changes that took place in South Africa after the first fully democratic elections, the special forces organisation was changed to its current structure in 1996. The Special Forces Brigade, as it is presently known, consists of 4 and 5 Special Forces Regiments as well as 1 Maintenance Unit, which provides logistic support. Designation of these forces as being of &quot;brigade&quot;-size, however, is highly misleading.  Total fighting manpower of 4 and 5 Special Forces Regiments combined does not approach even the strength of a regular infantry battalion.

As part of the military transformation process, 1 Special Forces Regiment was disbanded in 1996.

== Operations ==
[[File:SADF-Special Forces-001.jpg|thumb|Member of the South African Special Forces performing a parachute jump]]
The South African &quot;Recces&quot; were deployed to many local hot spots during the late 1970s and early 1980s, particularly [[Angola]].

The main enemy then was a  group known as [[SWAPO]] (South West Africa’s People Organization). It was a [[Guerrilla warfare|guerrilla]] organization fighting for an independent [[Namibia]].

One of the &quot;Recces&quot;' most effective operations came in 1982: [[Operation Mebos]] penetrated deep into Angola and destroyed the SWAPO Headquarters. In [[Operation Askari]], in the winter of 1984, the &quot;Recces&quot; cut off almost all supply lines to and from the SWAPO in Angola. In 1985, a &quot;Recce&quot; team undertook the controversial [[Operation Cabinda]], a failed attempt to sabotage Angolan oil installations run by [[Gulf Oil]].

In early summer of 1985, another &quot;Recce&quot; team under the command of SADF Captain Andre Diedericks crossed into Angola’s [[Cuando Cubango]] province, and with [[UNITA]]'s help, protection and escort was secretly deployed around [[Menongue]] area. The team had at their disposal the [[9K31 Strela-1|9K31 “Strela-1” AA system]] manned and operated by the team members. Team’s mission was to carry out covert combat operations, code names &quot;Catamaran 1,&quot; &quot;Catamaran 2&quot; and “Cerberus” with the goal to disrupt air traffic in Cuando Cubango province by shooting down air transports, combat aircrafts and gunships using the AA system.
On 11 June 1985, roughly 80 km from Menongue, the team shot down Angolan airplane, a light utility aircraft, [[Britten-Norman]] [[Britten-Norman Islander|BN-2 “Islander”]]. The “Islander”, in route from Menongue to Cuito Cuanavale with a crew of 2 and 5 passengers was also carrying 69 million [[kwanza]]s (Angola’s currency), several months of salary for FAPLA’s 16th Brigade’s personnel based in [[Cuito Cuanavale]]. When the “Islander” fell to the ground the money was stolen and the remains of the dead passengers had been pillaged by UNITA soldiers attached to protect the &quot;Recce&quot; team.
On 25 November 1985, the same “Recce” team had also [[1985 &quot;Aeroflot&quot; Antonov An-12 crash|shot down an “Aeroflot” Antonov AN-12]], cargo airplane. The AN-12 transport en-route from Cuito Cuanavale to Luanda carrying 8 crew members and 13 passengers crashed approximately 43 km south-east of Menongue. All people on board (twelve Soviet and nine Angolan nationals) died in the crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Journey Without Boundaries |last=Diedericks |first= Andre|year= 2007|publisher= Just Done Productions|isbn= 9781920169589}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Selection ==
The Ultimate Challenge, as South African Special Forces Selection is often called, is considered one of the harder special forces selection courses in the world&lt;ref&gt;http://www.recce.co.za/home/chairman-s-welcom&lt;/ref&gt;. A soldier must meet very high requirements to even attend Special Forces Selection. In accordance with SANDF regulation, only South African citizens are permitted.

===Pre-selection training===

This includes all aspects of psychological and physical tests. For the psychological tests, soldiers will be given written tests and oral interviews with Special Forces [[Non-commissioned officer|NCOs]]. A soldier must be self-controlled and mature. Soldiers are ejected from the course if there is any suggestion of mental instability. The Physical Test includes 40 continuous [[Press up|push ups]], 67 [[Sit-up (exercise)|sit ups]] in two minutes, fireman lift, three-kilometre run in full gear in thirteen minutes, a rope climb (to show upper body strength ), 40 shuttle runs in 95 seconds and wall scaling. A student must scale a {{convert|10|ft|m|adj=mid|-high}} wall, complete a fifteen-kilometre march in less than 120 minutes and perform 120 shuttle kicks.

===Parachute selection course===

[[44 Parachute Regiment (South Africa)|Basic Parachute School]] is one of the most demanding. All Special Forces candidates who aren't parachute-qualified will have to attend this course.

===Special Forces orientation course===

This is a time when a student will learn what Special Forces are and what they do. He will be told about what to look forward to in training. He is made to train every day to get into shape for the toughest part of Selection yet.

===Special Forces selection===

Selection is an event during which candidates are placed in an extremely mentally and physically demanding set of situations and circumstances, through which they must pass. It is in duration approximately a week.
For the duration of Selection, the candidates do not sleep or eat, and have no rest period at all.
Only an extremely small percentage of persons who begin Selection ever pass it. In some years, no-one has managed to pass Selection, and there are other cases where only 1 or 2 persons out of an entire Selection group pass.

===The cycle===

Once past the Selection process, he will be placed on a training cycle to acquire the skills required. These include: air co-operation, water orientation, obstacle crossing, [[bushcraft]], [[tracking]] and [[Survival skills|survival]], [[demolition]]s and tactics in urban as well as rural areas.

Advanced Airborne Training: a recruit will be taught about military [[free-fall]] such as [[HALO/HAHO|HALO and HAHO]]. They will also learn about helicopter operations – how to [[Abseiling|rappel]] fast down a rope out of [[helicopters]]. [[Extraction (military)|Combat extraction]] is also taught, along with learning how to set up a [[Landing Zone|LZ]].

Land training consists of many things: including [[Sniper|sniping]], demolitions and [[reconnaissance]]. Bushcraft and survival is also taught. [[Climbing]] and [[photography]] are taught to new recruits. Urban and rural combat is perhaps the newest training – developed quite recently, this training provided South Africa with a new [[Counter-terrorism|counter-terrorist]] force. [[Combat medic|Medical]] and [[Military communications|communications]] training is also given to those who wish to become qualified.

Maritime training consists of the use of small boats, underwater demolitions, swimming, [[diving]], beach reconnaissance and [[navigation]]. It is thought to be based on the [[Special Boat Service|SBS]] training.

== Weaponry ==
* [[AK 47]]
* [[AKM]]
* [[RPK]]
* [[R4 assault rifle|R4 and R5 Assault rifle]]
* [[FN FAL]] rifle
* [[Heckler &amp; Koch MP5]] Submachine gun
* [[Vektor SP1]] handgun
* Various sniper rifles including the [[Denel NTW-20]] [[anti-materiel rifle]]
As a special forces unit they also have access to a wide variety of standard and non-standard firearms.

== Operator's Badge ==
All South African Special Forces operators receive the Operator's Badge, which is given only to those members who have completed all the qualifications as an Operator. It consists of an inverted Commando Knife within a laurel wreath, which is meant to symbolise both special forces (the knife) and victory (the wreath).

Standard operator badges are silver, but a gold badge with an embedded diamond is awarded to Operators with more than 10 years of active service.

==See also==
* [[Delta Force]]
* [[SEAL Team Six]]
* [[Special Activities Division]]
* [[Special Air Service]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
*Peter Stiff ''The Silent War'', Galago Publishing Pty Ltd 1999 ISBN 0620243007
*Andre Diedericks ''Journey Without Boundaries'', Just Done Productions Publishing ISBN 9781920169589
*Jack Greeff ''A Greater Share of Honour'', Just Done Productions Publishing ISBN 9781920315061

== External links ==
*[http://www.recce.co.za South African Special Forces League website]
*[http://www.specwarnet.net/world/sasfb.htm Specwarnet.com report]
*[http://www.specialoperations.com/Foreign/South_Africa/SF_Brigade/Default.htm Specialoperations.com report]
*[http://home.blarg.net/~whitet/sarecee.htm Training account]
*[http://rhodesiawassuper.com/information.php?info_id=102 Samples of recces emblems]

[[Category:Brigades of South Africa]]
[[Category:Special forces of South Africa]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1972]]

[[fr:South African Special Forces Brigade]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
