<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="65468" ns="0" title="George Brett"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{otherpersons}}
{{Infobox MLB player
|name=George Brett
|image=George Brett 1990 CROP.jpg
|caption=Brett batting in 1990.
|position=[[Third baseman]] / [[Designated hitter]] / [[First baseman]]
|bats=Left
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|1953|5|15}}
|birth_place=[[Glen Dale, West Virginia]]
|debutdate=August 2
|debutyear=1973
|debutteam=Kansas City Royals
|finaldate=October 3
|finalyear=1993
|finalteam=Kansas City Royals
|stat1label=[[Batting average]]
|stat1value=.305
|stat2label=[[Hit (baseball)|Hits]]
|stat2value=3,154
|stat3label=[[Home run]]s
|stat3value=317
|stat4label=[[Run batted in|Runs batted in]]
|stat4value=1,595
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Kansas City Royals]] ({{By|1973}}–{{By|1993}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* 13× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] selection ([[1976 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1976]], [[1977 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1977]], [[1978 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1978]], [[1979 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1979]], [[1980 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1980]], [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1981]], [[1982 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1982]], [[1983 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1983]], [[1984 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1984]], [[1985 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1985]], [[1986 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1986]], [[1987 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1987]], [[1988 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1988]])
* [[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1985}})
* [[Gold Glove Award]] winner (1985)
* 3× [[Silver Slugger Award]] winner (1980, 1985, 1988)
* 1980 [[AL MVP]]
* 1985 [[ALCS MVP]]
* 1986 [[Lou Gehrig Memorial Award]]
* 1980 [[Hutch Award]]
* [[Kansas City Royals#Retired numbers|Kansas City Royals #5]] retired
|hofdate={{By|1999}}
|hofvote=98.2% (first ballot) 
}}
'''George Howard Brett''' (born May 15, 1953 in [[Glen Dale, West Virginia]]), nicknamed '''&quot;Mullet&quot;''', is a former [[Major League Baseball]] [[third baseman]], [[designated hitter]], and [[first baseman]]. He played his entire 21-year baseball career for the [[Kansas City Royals]]. Brett's 3,154 career hits are the most by any third baseman in major league history, and 15th all-time.  Brett is one of four players in MLB history to accumulate 3,000 hits, 300 home runs, and a career .300 batting average with the others being [[Hank Aaron]], [[Willie Mays]], and [[Stan Musial]].  He was inducted into the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] in 1999 on the first ballot.

==Biography==
===Early life and baseball career===
Brett was the youngest of four sons of a sports-minded family which included [[Ken Brett|Ken]], the second oldest, a major league pitcher who had pitched in the [[1967 World Series]] at age 19. Brothers John (eldest) and Bobby had brief careers in the minor leagues. Although his three older brothers were born in [[Brooklyn, New York|Brooklyn]], George was born in the [[Northern Panhandle of West Virginia|northern panhandle]] of [[West Virginia]]. Jack &amp; Ethel Brett then moved the family to the Midwest and three years later to [[El Segundo, California|El Segundo]], a suburb of [[Los Angeles]], just south of [[Los Angeles International Airport]]. George grew up hoping to follow in the footsteps of his three older brothers. He graduated from [[El Segundo High School]] in 1971 and was drafted by the [[Kansas City Royals]] in the second round (29th overall) of the [[1971 in baseball|1971]] baseball draft. His high school teammate was pitcher [[Scott McGregor (baseball)|Scott McGregor]].
&lt;ref&gt;''[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1124692/1/index.htm Sports Illustrated]'' - &quot;Love and Hate in El Segundo&quot; - Jack Brett &amp; his sons - 1981-08-17&lt;/ref&gt;

Brett began his professional baseball career as a [[shortstop]], but had trouble going to his right defensively and was soon shifted to third base. As a third baseman, his powerful arm remained an asset, and he remained at that spot for more than 15 years. Brett's minor league stops were in [[Billings, Montana]] (1971) for Rookie League, [[San Jose, California]] (1972) for Single-A, and [[Omaha, Nebraska]] in 1973 for Triple-A with the [[Omaha Royals]], batting .291, .274, and .284 respectively. The [[Kansas City Royals|Royals]] promoted him to the major leagues on August 2, 1973, when he played in 13 games and was 5 for 40 (.125).

Brett won the starting third base job in [[1974 in baseball|1974]], but struggled at the plate until he asked for help from [[Charlie Lau]], the Royals' batting coach. Spending the [[1974 in baseball|1974]] All-Star break working together, Lau taught Brett how to protect the entire plate and cover up some holes in his swing that experienced big-league pitchers were exploiting. Armed with this knowledge, Brett developed rapidly as a hitter, and finished the year with a .282 batting average in 113 games.

Brett topped the .300 mark for the first time in [[1975 in baseball|1975]], hitting .308, and then won his first batting title in [[1976 in baseball|1976]] with a .333 average. The four contenders for the batting title that year were Brett and Royals teammate [[Hal McRae]], and [[Minnesota Twins]] teammates [[Rod Carew]] and [[Lyman Bostock]]. In dramatic fashion, Brett went 2 for 4 in the final game of the season against the Twins, beating out his three rivals, all playing in the same game. His lead over second-place McRae was less than .001. Brett won the title when a fly ball dropped in front of Twins left fielder [[Steve Brye]], bounced on the [[Kauffman Stadium|Royals Stadium]] [[AstroTurf]] and over Brye's head to the wall; Brett circled the bases for an inside-the-park home run. McRae, batting just behind Brett in the line up, grounded out and Brett won his first batting title.

===Early career success===
From May 8 through May 16, 1976, Brett had 3 or more hits in 6 consecutive games, a Major League record. That year, the Royals won the first of three straight AL West Division titles, beginning a great rivalry with the [[New York Yankees]] &amp;mdash; whom they faced in the American League Championship Series each of those three years. In the fifth and final game of the [[1976 American League Championship Series|1976 ALCS]], Brett hit a three-run homer in the top of the eighth inning to tie the score at six &amp;mdash; only to see the Yankees' [[Chris Chambliss]] launch a solo shot in the bottom of the ninth to give the Yankees a 7&amp;ndash;6 win. 

A year later, Brett emerged as a power hitter with 22 home runs helping the Royals to another [[American League Championship Series]], [[1977 American League Championship Series|1977]]. In [[1978 in baseball|1978]] Brett batted .294 (the only time between 1976 and 1983 in which he did not bat at least .300) in helping the Royals win a third consecutive [[American League West]] title. However, Kansas City once again lost to the Yankees in the [[1978 American League Championship Series|ALCS]], but not before Brett hit three home runs off [[Catfish Hunter]] in Game Three, becoming the second player to hit three home runs in an LCS game ([[Bob Robertson]] was the first, having done so in Game 2 of the [[1971 National League Championship Series|1971 NLCS]]).

Brett followed that up with a successful [[1979 in baseball|1979]] season, in which he finished third in AL MVP voting. He became the sixth player in league history to have at least 20 doubles, triples and homers all in one season (42-20-23) and led the league in hits, doubles and triples while batting .329, with an [[on-base percentage]] of .376 and a [[slugging percentage]] of .563.

===1980===
All these impressive statistics were just a prelude to [[1980 in baseball|1980]], when Brett won the American League [[MLB Most Valuable Player award|MVP]] and batted .390, a modern record for a [[third baseman]]. Brett's batting average was at or above .400 as late in the season as September 19, and the country closely followed his quest to bat .400 for an entire season, a feat which has not been accomplished since [[Ted Williams]] in [[1941 in baseball|1941]].

Brett's 1980 batting average of .390 is second only to [[Tony Gwynn]]'s [[1994 in baseball|1994]] average of .394 (Gwynn played in 110 games and had 419 at-bats in the strike-shortened season, compared to Brett's 449 at bats in 1980) for the highest single season batting average since 1941. Brett also recorded 118 [[run batted in|RBI]], while appearing in just 117 games; it is the first instance of a player averaging one RBI per game (in more than 100 games) since [[Walt Dropo]] [[1950 Major League Baseball season|thirty seasons prior]]. He led the American League in both [[slugging percentage|slugging]] and [[on-base percentage]].

Brett started out slowly, hitting only .259 in April. In May, he hit .329 to get his season average to .301. In June, the 27 year-old third baseman hit .472 (17-36) to raise his season average to .337, but played his last game for a month on June 10, not returning to the lineup until after the All-Star Break on July 10.

In July, after being off for a month, he played in 21 games and hit .494 (42&amp;ndash;85), raising his season average to .390. Brett started a 30-game [[hitting streak]] on July 18, which lasted until he went 0-3 on August 19 (the following night he went 3-for-3). During these 30 games Brett hit .467 (57-122). His high mark for the season came a week later, when Brett's batting average was at .407 on August 26, after he went 5-for-5 on a Tuesday night in [[Milwaukee Brewers|Milwaukee]]. He batted .430 for the month of August (30 games), and his season average was at .403 with five weeks to go. For the three hot months of June, July, and August 1980, George Brett played in 60 [[American League]] games and hit .459 (111&amp;ndash;242), most of it after a return from a monthlong injury. For these 60 games he had 69 RBIs and 14 home runs. 

Brett missed another 10 days in early September and hit just .290 for the month. His average was at .400 as late as September 19, but he then had a 4 for 27 slump, and the average dipped to .384 on September 27, with a week to play. For the final week, Brett went 10-for-19, which included going 2 for 4 in the final regular season game on October 4. His season average ended up at .390 (175 hits in 449 at-bats = .389755), and he averaged more than one RBI per game. Brett was the first major league player since 1950 to have more than one RBI per game (90 or more RBIs). Brett led the league in both [[on-base percentage]] (.454) and [[slugging percentage]] (.664) on his way to capturing 17 of 28 possible first-place votes in the MVP race.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/awards/awards_1980.shtml#ALmvp. Baseball Awards Voting for 1980 - Baseball-Reference.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Since Al Simmons also batted .390 in 1931 for the Philadelphia Athletics, the only higher averages subsequent to 1931 were by [[Ted Williams]] of the [[Red Sox]] (.406 in 1941) and [[Tony Gwynn]] of the [[San Diego Padres]] (.394 in the strike-shortened 1994 season).

More importantly, the Royals won the American League West, and would face the Eastern champion [[1980 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] in the [[1980 American League Championship Series|ALCS]].

====1980 post-season====
In the 1980 post-season, Brett led the Royals to their first American League pennant, sweeping the [[1980 American League Championship Series|playoffs]] in three games from the rival [[1980 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] who had beaten K.C. in the [[1976 American League Championship Series|1976]], [[1977 American League Championship Series|1977]] and [[1978 American League Championship Series|1978]] playoffs. In Game 3, Brett hit a ball well into the third deck of [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]] off of Yankees closer [[Rich Gossage|Goose Gossage]]. Gossage's previous pitch had been timed at 97&amp;nbsp;mph, leading ABC broadcaster Jim Palmer to say, &quot;I doubt if he threw that ball 97 miles an hour.&quot;  A moment later Palmer was given the actual reading of 98.  &quot;Well, I said it wasn't 97.&quot;  
Brett then hit .375 in the [[1980 World Series]], but the Royals lost in six games to the [[1980 Philadelphia Phillies season|Philadelphia Phillies]]. During the Series, Brett made headlines after leaving Game 2 in the 6th inning due to [[hemorrhoid]] pain. Brett had minor surgery the next day, and in Game 3 returned to hit a home run as the Royals won in 10 innings 4-3. After the game, Brett was famously quoted &quot;...my problems are all behind me.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;behind&quot;&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20090305&amp;content_id=3921596
|publisher=mlb.com
|title=Memories fill Kauffman Stadium
|date=March 5, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1981 he missed two weeks of Spring training to have his hemorrhoids removed.&lt;ref name=&quot;hemorrhoids&quot;&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DC1439F932A35750C0A967948260
|publisher=New York Times
|title=Brett in Hospital for Surgery
|date=March 1, 1981
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Pine Tar Incident===
{{Main|Pine Tar Incident}}
[[Image:George brett pine tar bat rotated.JPG|thumb|300px|right|The [[baseball bat]] used by '''George Brett''' in the Pine Tar Incident on July 24, 1983.]]
On July 24, 1983, the Royals played the [[1983 New York Yankees season|Yankees]] at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]]. In the top of the ninth inning with two out, Brett hit a two-run homer to put the Royals up 5&amp;ndash;4. Upon Brett crossing the plate, Yankees manager [[Billy Martin]] cited to the umpires a [[Rules of baseball|rule]] that stated that any foreign substance on a bat could extend no further than 18&amp;nbsp;inches from the knob. The umpires measured the amount of [[pine tar]], a legal substance used by hitters to improve their grip, on Brett's bat; the pine tar extended about 24&amp;nbsp;inches. The home plate umpire, [[Tim McClelland]], signaled the player out, ending the game as a Yankees win. An angry Brett charged out of the dugout and was immediately ejected. The Royals protested the game, and American League president [[Lee MacPhail]] upheld the protest, reasoning that the bat should have been excluded from future use but the home run should not have been nullified.  Amid much controversy, the game was resumed on August 18 from the point of Brett's home run and ended with a Royals win.

===1985===
In [[1985 in baseball|1985]], Brett had another brilliant season in which he helped propel the Royals to their second American League Championship. He batted .335 with 30 home runs and 112 RBI, finishing in the top 10 of the league in 10 different offensive categories. Defensively, he won his only [[Gold Glove]]. In the final week of the regular season, he went 9-for-20 at the plate with 7 runs, 5 homers, and 9 RBI in six crucial games, five of them victories, as the Royals closed a gap and won the division title at the end. He was MVP of the [[1985 American League Championship Series|1985 playoffs]] against the [[1985 Toronto Blue Jays season|Toronto Blue Jays]], with an incredible Game 3. With KC down in the series two games to none, Brett went 4-for-4, homering in his first two at bats against [[Doyle Alexander]], and doubled to the same spot in right field in his third at bat, leading the Royals comeback. Brett then batted .370 in the [[1985 World Series|World Series]] against the [[1985 St. Louis Cardinals season|St. Louis Cardinals]] including a four-hit performance in Game 7. The Royals again rallied from a 3&amp;ndash;1 deficit to become World Series Champions for the only time in Royals history.

===Later career===
In [[1987 in baseball|1988]], Brett moved across the diamond to [[first baseman|first base]] in an effort to reduce his chances of injury and had another top-notch season with a .306 average, 24 homers and 104 RBI. But after batting just .290 with 16 homers the next year, it looked like his career might be slowing down. He got off to a terrible start in [[1990 in baseball|1990]] and at one point even considered retirement. But his manager, former teammate [[John Wathan]], encouraged him to stick it out. Finally, in July, the slump ended and Brett batted .386 for the rest of the season. In September, he caught [[Rickey Henderson]] for the league lead, and in a battle down to the last day of the season, captured his third batting title with a .329 mark. This feat made Brett the only major league player to win batting titles in three different decades.

Brett played three more seasons for the Royals, mostly as their [[designated hitter]], but occasionally filling in for injured teammates at first base. He passed the 3,000-hit mark in [[1992 in baseball|1992]], though he was picked off by [[Los Angeles Angels|Angel]] first baseman [[Gary Gaetti]] after stepping off the base to start enjoying the moment. Brett retired after the [[1993 in baseball|1993]] season; in his final at-bat, he hit a single up the middle against [[1993 Texas Rangers season|Rangers]] closer [[Tom Henke]] and scored on a home run by now teammate Gaetti.

Brett's #5 was retired by the Royals on April 7, 1997. His number was the second number retired in Royals history, preceded by former Royals manager, the late [[Dick Howser]] (#10), in 1987. It was followed by [[second baseman]] and longtime teammate [[Frank White (baseball)|Frank White]]'s #20 in 1998.

He was voted the [[DHL Hometown Heroes|Hometown Hero]] for the Royals in a two-month fan vote. This was revealed on the night of September 27, 2006 in an hour-long telecast on [[ESPN]]. He was one of the few players to receive more than 400,000 votes.&lt;ref name=&quot;votes&quot;&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://kansascity.royals.mlb.com/NASApp/mlb/news/article.jsp?ymd=20060927&amp;content_id=1686268&amp;vkey=news_kc&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=kc
|publisher=MLB.com
|title=Brett named Royals Hometown Hero
|date=September 27, 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legacy===
[[Image:RoyalsRetired.JPG|right|thumb|Brett's number 5 was retired by the Royals alongside [[Dick Howser]] and [[Frank White (baseball)|Frank White]].]]
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = RoyalsRetired05.PNG
|Name   = George Brett
|Number = 5
|Team   = Kansas City Royals
|Year   = 1994
|}}
His 3,154 career hits (2,044 hits actually as a third baseman, with Wade Boggs at 2,788 at the position according to www.baseball-reference.com) are the second most by any third baseman in major league history, and 15th all-time. Baseball historian [[Bill James]] regards him as the second-best third baseman of all time, trailing only his contemporary, [[Mike Schmidt]]. Brett was elected to the Hall of Fame in [[1999 in baseball|1999]], with what was then the fourth-highest voting percentage in baseball history (98.2%), trailing only [[Tom Seaver]], [[Nolan Ryan]], and [[Ty Cobb]]. In 2007, [[Cal Ripken Jr.]] passed Brett with 98.5% of the vote. His voting percentage was higher than all-time outfielders [[Babe Ruth]], [[Hank Aaron]], [[Willie Mays]], [[Stan Musial]], [[Ted Williams]], and [[Joe DiMaggio]]. That same year, he ranked Number 55 on ''[[The Sporting News]]''' list of the 100 Greatest Baseball Players, and was nominated as a finalist for the [[Major League Baseball]] All-Century Team. Brett is one of four players in MLB history to accumulate 3,000 hits, 300 home runs, and a career .300 batting average (the others are [[Stan Musial]], [[Willie Mays]], and [[Hank Aaron]]). Most indicative of his hitting style, Brett is sixth on the career doubles list, with 665 (trailing [[Tris Speaker]], [[Pete Rose]], [[Stan Musial]], [[Ty Cobb]], and [[Craig Biggio]]). Combining his superior hitting skill with his great defensive ability and team focus (and humility), George Brett is arguably one of the most complete baseball players of all time.

===Post baseball activities===
[[File:George Brett - USS Reagan - Feb 2009.jpg|thumb|Brett in February 2009.]]
Following the end of his baseball career, Brett became a vice president of the Royals and has worked as a part-time coach, as a special instructor in [[spring training]], filling in as the batting coach, and as a minor league instructor dispatched to help prospects develop. He also runs a baseball equipment and foam-hand company, Brett Bros., with Bobby and, until his death, [[Ken Brett]]. He has also lent his name to a restaurant that failed on the [[Country Club Plaza]].

In 1992, Brett married the former Leslie Davenport and they currently reside in the Kansas City suburb of [[Mission Hills, Kansas]]. The couple has three children: Jackson (named after his father), Dylan (named after [[Bob Dylan]]), and Robin (named after fellow Hall of Famer [[Robin Yount]] of the [[Milwaukee Brewers]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/danpatrick/blog/64703/index.html | work=CNN | title=Hall of Famer Brett doesn't trust Clemens, upset by 'roids}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brett has also continued to raise money for ALS (amyotrophic lateral sclerosis), commonly known as Lou Gehrig's Disease. Brett started to raise money for the Keith Worthington Chapter during his playing career in the mid 1980s.

====Team Ownership====
In [[1998 in baseball|1998]], an investor group headed by Brett and his older brother, Bobby, made an unsuccessful bid to purchase the Kansas City Royals. Brett is the principal owner of the [[Tri-City Dust Devils]], the Single-A affiliate of the [[Colorado Rockies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tricity.dustdevils.milb.com/index.jsp?sid=t460 |title=Tri-City Dust Devils: About |accessdate=2008-05-09 |format= |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt; He and his brother Bobby also co-own the [[Rancho Cucamonga Quakes]], a [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] Single-A partner, and lead ownership groups that control the [[Spokane Chiefs]] of the Western Hockey League,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sportsnet.ca/hockey/juniors/2008/05/19/king_brett_chiefs From MLB to CHL - Sportsnet.ca&lt;!-- Bot generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[West Coast League]]'s [[Bellingham Bells]], and the [[High Desert Mavericks]] of the [[California League]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=3990869 George Brett, Brother To Buy Another Team in Minors] ESPN, March 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Major League Baseball Hit Records]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball doubles records]]
*[[List of top 300 Major League Baseball home run hitters]]
*[[List of major league players with 2,000 hits]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 400 doubles]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 100 triples]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 runs]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 RBIs]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career stolen bases]]
*[[3000 hit club]]
*[[20–20–20 club]]
*[[Hitting for the cycle]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball batting champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball doubles champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball triples champions]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Baseballstats |mlb= |espn= |br=b/brettge01 |fangraphs=1001400 |cube=b/george-brett|brm=brett-001geo}}
*Career statistics at [http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=brettge01 Baseball-Almanac.com]
*{{bbhof|brett-george}}

{{s-start-collapsible|header={{s-ach}}}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball Batting Champions|American League Batting Champion]] | before=[[Rod Carew]] &lt;br&gt; [[Fred Lynn]] &lt;br&gt; [[Kirby Puckett]] | years=1976 &lt;br&gt; 1980 &lt;br&gt; 1990| after= [[Rod Carew]] &lt;br&gt; [[Carney Lansford]] &lt;br&gt; [[Julio Franco]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Don Baylor]] | title = [[MLB Most Valuable Player Award|American League Most Valuable Player]] | years = 1980 | after = [[Rollie Fingers]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Kirk Gibson]] | title = [[American League Championship Series|American League Championship Series MVP]] | years = [[1985 in baseball|1985]] | after = [[Marty Barrett (second baseman)|Marty Barrett]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Dale Murphy]] | title = [[Lou Gehrig Memorial Award]] | years = 1986 | after = [[Rick Sutcliffe]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{1985 Kansas City Royals}}
{{AL MVPs}}
{{AL batting title}}
{{ALCS MVP}}
{{Lou Gehrig Memorial Award}}
{{Hutch Award}}
{{AL 3B Gold Glove Award}}
{{AL 1B Silver Slugger Award}}
{{AL 3B Silver Slugger Award}}
{{3000 hit club}}
{{Royals Retired Numbers}}
{{Kansas City Royals}}
{{1999 Baseball HOF}}
{{Baseball Hall of Fame third basemen}}
{{SN Sportsman of the Year}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Brett, George
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = May 15, 1953
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Glen Dale, West Virginia]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Brett, George}}
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Billings Mustangs players]]
[[Category:San Jose Bees players]]
[[Category:Omaha Royals players]]
[[Category:Kansas City Royals players]]
[[Category:Gold Glove Award winners]]
[[Category:American League Most Valuable Player Award winners]]
[[Category:American League All-Stars]]
[[Category:American League batting champions]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball announcers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball controversies]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball designated hitters]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball third basemen]]
[[Category:Baseball players from California]]
[[Category:Baseball players from West Virginia]]
[[Category:People from Marshall County, West Virginia]]
[[Category:People from Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:1953 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[es:George Brett]]
[[fr:George Brett]]
[[ko:조지 브렛]]
[[ja:ジョージ・ブレット]]
[[simple:George Brett (baseball)]]
[[zh:喬治·布列特]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
