<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6574209" ns="0" title="Civil war in Afghanistan (1996–2001)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    =War in Afghanistan 1996-2001 
| partof      =[[Afghan Civil War|War in Afghanistan]]
| image       =[[File:1996afghan (1).png|280px]]
| caption     =Situation in Afghanistan late 1996
| date        =September 27, 1996–October 7, 2001
| place       =[[Afghanistan]]
| coordinates =
| map_type    =
| latitude    =
| longitude   =
| map_size    =
| map_caption =
| map_label   =
| territory   =
| result      = Defeat of Dostum's forces (United Front) in 1998 by the Taliban. Stalemate with varying fronts between the Taliban and Massoud's forces (United Front). Followed by [[War in Afghanistan (2001-present)|Operation Enduring Freedom]] and removal of the Taliban from power by United Front forces and [[ISAF]]. 
| status      =
| combatant1  ={{flagicon|Afghanistan|Taliban}} [[Taliban]] ([[Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan]])&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of al-Qaeda.svg}} [[Al-Qaeda]]&lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Pakistan}} 

----
''Supported by:''
&lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Saudi Arabia}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Arab Emirates}} 
| combatant2  ={{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|United Front]] ([[Islamic State of Afghanistan]])
----
''Supported by:''&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Iran}} [[Iran]]&lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|India}} [[India]]&lt;ref name=&quot;McLeod&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  |last = McLeod
  |first = Duncan
  |title = India and Pakistan: friends, rivals or enemies?
  |publisher = Ashgate Publishing, Ltd., 2008
  |isbn = 0754674371, 9780754674375}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant3  =
| commander1  ={{flagicon|Afghanistan|Taliban}} [[Mohammed Omar]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|Taliban}} [[Obaidullah Akhund]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|Taliban}} [[Mullah Dadullah]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of al-Qaeda.svg}} [[Osama bin Laden]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of al-Qaeda.svg}} [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Pakistani Army.svg}} [[General|Gen.]] [[Pervez Musharraf]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Pakistani Army.svg}}  [[Lieutenant-General|LTG]] [[Mahmud Ahmed]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Pakistani Army.svg}} [[Lieutenant-General|LTG]] [[Hamid Gul]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Pakistani Army.svg}} LTG [[Naseem Rana]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Pakistani Army.svg}} [[Lieutenant-General|LTG]] [[Ziauddin Butt]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of the Pakistani Army.svg}} [[Colonel|COL]] [[Amir Sultan Tarar|Amir Tarrar]]
| commander2  ={{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Burhanuddin Rabbani]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Haji Abdul Qadir]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} Qari Baba&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Bismillah Khan]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Mohammed Fahim]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Hussain Anwari]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} Arif Noorzai&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} Haji M. Mohaqeq&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Rashid Dostum]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Afghanistan|1992}} [[Ismail Khan]]
| commander3  =
| units1      =
| units2      =
| units3      =
| strength1   =
| strength2   =
| strength3   =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| casualties3 =
| notes       =
}}
{{Campaignbox Afghanistan}}

On September 27, 1996, the [[Taliban]] seized the Afghan capital [[Kabul]] and established the [[Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan]]. The [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]] government remained the internationally recognized government of Afghanistan. The Taliban's Emirate received recognition only from [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Pakistan]] and the [[United Arab Emirates]]. The defense minister of the Islamic State of Afghanistan, [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]], in opposition to the Taliban created the [[United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|United Front]] (Northern Alliance). The United Front included all Afghan ethnicities: [[Tajik people|Tajik]]s, [[Uzbeks]], [[Hazara people|Hazara]]s, [[Turkmen people|Turkmens]], some [[Pashtuns]] and others. Massoud fought for a [[republic]] and national consolidation to achieve a lasting peace in Afghanistan. During the conflict, the Taliban received complementary military support by Pakistan and financial support by Saudi Arabia. Pakistan interfered militarily in Afghanistan, deploying battalions and regiments of its [[Frontier Corps]] and [[Pakistan Army|Army]] against the United Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2007|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xpQI6HKV-ZY&amp;feature=related |title = Inside the Taliban| publisher = [[National Geographic]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;History Commons&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2010 |url =http://www.historycommons.org/entity.jsp?entity=ahmed_shah_massoud |title = History Commons| publisher = [[History Commons]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Al Qaeda]] supported the Taliban with regiments of imported fighters from Arab countries and [[Central Asia]]. In the late period of the war of an estimated 45,000 force fighting on the side of the Taliban only 14,000 were Afghan (Taliban).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;

==Main participants==
[[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] (for the United Front and the Islamic State of Afghanistan), [[Mohammed Omar|Mullah Mohammad Omar]] (for the Taliban) and [[Osama Bin Laden]] together with [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]] (for &quot;Al Qaeda&quot; and different Arab interests) were the main leaders of the war residing in Afghanistan. There were other leaders, mainly from Pakistan (like [[Pervez Musharraf]] and later General Mahmud) on the one side and from the United Front (i. e. [[Haji Abdul Qadir]], Rashid Dostum) on the other side, who, however, were not always present in Afghanistan itself. The quality of life of the Afghan population was heavily dependent on the specific leader that was directly controlling the area in which they lived. Sharp contrast could be witnessed regarding life and structures in different areas.

===United Front===
====Ahmad Shah Massoud====
[[File:Massoud 2000.jpg|thumb|300px|left|[[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] conferring with advisers in August 2000 during the battle for [[Taloqan]].]]
Throughout much of its operational history, the United Front was headed by [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]], a [[Kabul University]] engineering student turned military leader who played a leading role in driving the [[Red Army|Soviet army]] out of [[Afghanistan]], earning him the nickname ''Lion of [[Panjshir Province|Panjshir]]''. His followers also call him ''Āmer Sāheb-e Shahīd'' (''Our Beloved Martyred Commander'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; The Wall Street Journal at that time dedicated one of its covers to Massoud calling him &quot;the Afghan who won the Cold War&quot;. Following the withdrawal of [[Soviet war in Afghanistan|Soviet troops from Afghanistan]] and the subsequent collapse of the [[Democratic Republic of Afghanistan|Soviet-backed government]] of [[Mohammad Najibullah]], Massoud became the [[Afghan Ministry of Defense|Defense Minister]] in 1992 under the government of [[Burhanuddin Rabbani]]. Following the rise of the [[Taliban]] in 1996, Massoud returned to the role of an armed opposition leader, serving as the military commander of the [[United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|United Islamic Front]] (Northern Alliance).

Massoud was a deeply religious and spiritual person, who strongly opposed the interpretations of Islam followed by the Taliban or Al Qaeda. A Sunni Muslim he also always carried a book of Sufi-mystic al-Ghazali with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;

The Taliban repeatedly offered Massoud a position of power to make him stop his resistance. Massoud declined for he did not fight for the sake of power. He explained in one interview: 
:''&quot;The Taliban say: &quot;Come and accept the post of prime minister and be with us&quot;, and they would keep the highest office in the country, the presidentship. But for what price?! The difference between us concerns mainly our way of thinking about the very principles of the society and the state. We can not accept their conditions of compromise, or else we would have to give up the principles of modern democracy. We are fundamentally against the system called &quot;the Emirate of Afghanistan&quot;.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.orient.uw.edu.pl/balcerowicz/texts/Ahmad_Shah_Masood_en.htm |title =The Last Interview with Ahmad Shah Massoud | publisher = Piotr Balcerowicz}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Massoud was convinced that only a democratic system could ensure a lasting peace in Afghanistan. He wanted to convince the Taliban to join a [[political process]] leading towards democratic elections in a foreseeable future.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;/&gt; His proposals for peace can be seen [http://www.peace-initiatives.com/frame.htm here: Proposal for Peace, promoted by Commander Massoud].

On September 9, 2001, two days before the [[September 11 attacks]] in the United States, Massoud was assassinated in [[Takhar Province]] of Afghanistan by suspected [[al-Qaeda]] agents. The funeral, although taking place in a rather rural area, was attended by hundreds of thousands of mourning people. [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aq-zqA1DMWs see video].
The following year, he was named &quot;National Hero&quot; by the order of Afghan President [[Hamid Karzai]]. The date of his death, September 9, is observed as a national holiday in Afghanistan, known as &quot;Massoud Day.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lonelyplanet.com/worldguide/afghanistan/events Afghanistan Events], Lonely Planet Travel Guide.&lt;/ref&gt;  The year following his assassination, in 2002, Massoud was nominated for the [[Nobel Peace Prize]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marktheday.com/nationholidaydates/afg_ahmadshahmassoudday.aspx National Holiday Dates], Massoud Day and Nobel Peace Prize Nomination&lt;/ref&gt;

One refugee who cramped his family of 27 into an old jeep to flee from the Taliban to the area of Massoud described Massoud's territory as &quot;the last tolerant corner of Afghanistan&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Journeyman Picture/ABC Australia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=1997 |url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EvYglyjbHkI |title = Massoud's Last Stand| publisher = Journeyman Pictures/ABC Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; About his life in Massoud's area he stated:&quot;I feel freedom here. I like ... you know, nobody bothers me. I do my job. I take care of my family. The way which I like I live in this area.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Journeyman Picture/ABC Australia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=1997 |url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EvYglyjbHkI |title = Massoud's Last Stand| publisher = Journeyman Pictures/ABC Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Massoud had no influence on the lives of people living in the areas of Rashid Dostum (who had joined the United Front to fight the Taliban.)

In the area of Massoud women and girls did not have to wear the Afghan burqa. They were allowed to work and to go to school. In at least two known instances Massoud personally intervened against cases of forced marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;  While it was Massoud's stated conviction that men and women are equal and should enjoy the same rights, he also had to deal with Afghan traditions which he said would need a generation or more to overcome. In his opinion that could only be achieved through education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;

Massoud created democratic institutions which were structured into several committees: political, health, education and economic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; Still, many people came to him personally when they had a dispute or problem and asked him to solve their problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;

Hundreds of thousands of refugees fled the Taliban to the areas of Massoud. In 2001 Massoud and famous photographer and former UN ambassador [[Reza Deghati]] described the bitter situation of the Afghan refugees and asked for humanitarian help. ([http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60 see video])&lt;ref name=&quot;EU Parliament (2)&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60 |title = Massoud in the European Parliament 2001| publisher = EU media}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====[[Abdul Qadir (Afghan leader)|Abdul Qadir]]====
[[File:Massoud and Qadir 2.PNG|thumb|250px|Ahmad Shah Massoud (right) greets Pashtun anti-Taliban leader and later Vice President of Afghanistan [[Haji Abdul Qadir]]]]
Haji Abdul Qadir Arsala (c. 1951 in Jalalabad, Afghanistan-July 6, 2002 in Kabul, Afghanistan) (Arabic: الحاج عبد القادر‎) was a prominent Pashtun anti-Taliban leader in the United Front. He was the brother of [[Abdul Haq (Afghan leader)|Abdul Haq]], a well-known resistance leader against the [[Soviet invasion of Afghanistan]]. Qadir's family was a traditionally powerful one, with ties to former Afghan king [[Zahir Shah]]. Abdul Qadir had a base of power in the east of Afghanistan and was the governor of his home province of [[Nangarhar]] before the Taliban took power. 

Qadir became the [[Vice President]] of Afghanistan in the post-Taliban administration of [[Hamid Karzai]]. On July 6, 2002, Qadir and his son-in-law were killed by gunmen. Another of his sons, Haji Mohammed Zaher, was shot dead in Kabul also in 2002.

===Taliban===

Mullah [[Muhammad Omar]] headed the Taliban forces during the Afghan civil war. Dressed with a coat which he claimed to be the coat of the Islamic prophet Muhammad, Mullah Omar declared himself Amir-ul-Momineen, which means Commander of the Faithful. He has rarely been photographed and hardly speaks to journalists directly. Many see Mullah Omar as a nominal figure trained and controlled by Pakistan's intelligence agency, the ISI.

Followers of the Taliban claim that Mullah Omar was born in the central province of Uruzgan in 1962. Other sources place his birth in Kandahar at around 1959. They also say that he studied in several Islamic schools outside of Afghanistan especially in Quetta, Pakistan. In the 1980s he joined the resistance against the Soviet invasion. It is believed that he lost his eye fighting the Soviets as a deputy Chief Commander in the Harakat-i Islami party of Mohammad Nabi Mohammadi. In 1994 Mullah Omar liberated Kandahar from a cruel dictatorial governor in a first appearance of the Taliban movement.

Mullah Omar has strong links with another popular figure in world politics, Osama Bin Laden, and is married to a daughter of Bin Laden. Despite several US requests to hand over Osama Bin Laden, Mullah Omar refused. His current whereabouts are unknown but he is believed to hide in either Kandahar or Pakistan.

The Physicians for Human Rights (PHR) analyze: &quot;The Taliban is the first faction laying claim to power in Afghanistan that has targeted women for extreme repression and punished them brutally for infractions. To PHR's knowledge, no other regime in the world has methodically and violently forced half of its population into virtual house arrest, prohibiting them on pain of physical punishment ...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=1998 |url = http://physiciansforhumanrights.org/library/documents/reports/talibans-war-on-women.pdf |title = The Taliban's War on Women. A Health and Human Rights Crisis in Afghanistan| publisher = [[Physicians for Human Rights]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After taking control of the capital city of Kabul on September 26, 1996, the Taliban issued edicts forbidding women to work outside the home, attend school, or to leave their homes unless accompanied by a male relative. In public, women had to be covered from head to toe in a burqa, a body-length covering with only a mesh opening to see and breathe through. Women were not permitted to wear white (the color of the Taliban flag) socks or white shoes, or shoes that make noise while they are walking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt;  Also, houses and buildings had to have their windows painted over so women could not be seen inside.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt;  Women were practically banned from public life, denied access to health care, education, and work and they were not allowed to laugh in a manner they could be heard by others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt;

The Taliban, without any real court or hearing, cut people's hands or arms off when accused of theft. Taliban hit-squads from the infamous &quot;Ministry for Promotion of Virtue and Prevention of Vice&quot; watched the streets conducting arbitrary brutal and public beatings of people when they saw what they considered as unislamic behavior.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt;

===Pakistan===
[[File:Pervez Musharraf - World Economic Forum Annual Meeting Davos 2008 number3.jpg|thumb|Former Pakistan [[President of Pakistan|President]] [[Pervez Musharraf]]]]

General [[Pervez Musharraf]], a retired four star general who served as [[Chairman Joint Chiefs of Staff Committee (Pakistan)|Chairman]] of [[Joint Chiefs of Staff Committee, Pakistan|Joint Chiefs of Staff Committee]] from 1998 to 2001 and the [[Chief of Army Staff (Pakistan)|Chief of Army Staff]] of Pakistan Army from 1998 to 2007 played an instrumental role in drafting Pakistan's role in the Afghan civil war. In 2001, he would go on to become Pakistan's military ruler and President as well. General Pervez Musharraf was responsible for sending thousands of Pakistani nationals to fight alongside the Taliban and Bin Laden against [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]].&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;History Commons&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2007 |url =http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB227/index.htm#17 |title =Documents Detail Years of Pakistani Support for Taliban, Extremists | publisher = [[George Washington University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In total there were believed to be 28,000 Pakistani nationals fighting inside Afghanistan against the forces of Massoud.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; 20,000 were regular Pakistani soldiers either from the [[Frontier Corps]], 50th Airborne Division or 12th regular army regiments, and an estimated 8,000 were militants recruited in [[madrassa]]s filling regular Taliban ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; The estimated 25,000 Taliban regular force thus comprised more than 8,000 Pakistani nationals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 1998 document by the [[U.S. State Department]] confirms that &quot;20-40 percent of [regular] Taliban soldiers are Pakistani.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;/&gt; The document further states that the parents of those Pakistani nationals &quot;know nothing regarding their child's military involvement with the Taliban until their bodies are brought back to Pakistan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;/&gt; A further 3,000 fighter of the regular Taliban army were Arab and Central Asian militants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of roughly 45,000 Pakistani, Taliban and Al Qaeda soldiers fighting against the forces of Massoud only 14,000 were Afghan (Taliban).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; 

Lieutenant-General [[Mahmud Ahmed]], the former director-general of Pakistan's [[Inter-Services Intelligence]] (''ISI''), was responsible for the support to the Taliban. Many of ''ISI'' officers, such as [[Lieutenant-General]] [[Hamid Gul]], Lieutenant-General [[Naseem Rana]], Lieutenant-General [[Ziauddin Butt]] and retired [[Colonel]] [[Colonel Imam|Sultan Amir Tarar]], played a major role in the war. The officers provided financial, economic, strategic, and military assistance to the Taliban. Pakistan's Combatant forces were led under the military leadership of General [[Naseem Rana]], as he was the principle military commander of entire Pakistan's combatant forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt; Training of the Taliban was provided by Colonel (retired) Tarar and, financial assistance was managed by General (retired) Hamid Gul..&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt; Major-General Ziauddin Butt served as the intelligence coordinator under General Naseem Rana.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt; In this entire course of the war, all of the leading generals reported to General Naseem Rana who, of course, submitted his evaluation and later brief General Musharraf on the efforts led by him in Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;/&gt; General Musharraf also sent young military and paramilitary soldiers under General Naseem to fight against the Northern Alliance, and none of them were told by General Musharraf or General Naseem Rana on why they are being sent to fight the war, on behalf of Taliban, against the enemy who did not declare the war on Pakistan, The Northern Alliance.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt;  The Pakistani soldiers fought the war with Khaki [[Shalwar Qameez]], rather than wearing official war uniform, as they were ordered by General Naseem Rana. It was done by General Naseem Rana in an attempt to hide the identity of soldiers being Pakistani, and to avoid national pressure from the Navaz Sharif government and the international pressure from the Western world.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt; 

Ahmad Shah Masood secretly sent a courier that contacted [[Navaz Sharif]], [[Prime minister of Pakistan|Prime minister]] at that time. Details of Pakistan Army and ''ISI'''s involvement were provided to Prime minister Sharif. When Sharif tried to intervene, General Musharraf stopped Sharif, and called Taliban as &quot;valuable assets&quot; and &quot;Front-line defenders of Pakistan&quot;, therefore rejected any orders from Sharif to stop the Pakistan support for Taliban. However, in 2008, former [[United States Deputy Secretary of State|U.S. Deputy Secretary of State]] [[John Negroponte]] had defended General Musharraf, and knew the entire history of ''ISI''. John Negroponte clarified that time has been changed and ''ISI'' is making an effort to fight against terrorism. 

Observers interviewed by Human Rights Watch in Afghanistan and Pakistan reported that Pakistan Army Aviation Corps ''4th Army Aggressor Squadron'''s [[surveillance aircraft]] assisted Taliban forces during combat operations in late 2000, and that senior members of Pakistan's intelligence agency and army were involved in planning major Taliban military operations. As the war progressed, Pakistan Army deployed its ''50th Airborne Division'' and the ''Frontier Corps'' to provide logistic support to Taliban campaigns against the Massoud's forces.

====Cooperation on Afghanistan with Saudi Arabia====
Pakistan and Saudi Arabia have created a deep strategic partnership on a variety of issues one of the more important being Afghanistan. After Musharraf's coup in October 1999, the Saudi capital Riyadh was the first foreign capital Pervez Musharraf visited, to signify the importance he gave to PAK-Saudi relations.  President Musharraf honored King Abdullah by conferring upon him Pakistan's highest civil award, Nishan-e-Pakistan, in a colorful investiture ceremony at the presidential palace.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saudiembassy.net/2006News/News/RelDetail.asp?cIndex=5929]&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 Jan 2007, the Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques King Abdullah conferred the King Abdul Aziz Medallion, the Kingdom's top honor, on Pakistani President Gen. Pervez Musharraf during a ceremony at his palace in Riyadh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arabnews.com/?page=1&amp;section=0&amp;article=91233&amp;d=22&amp;m=1&amp;y=2007]&lt;/ref&gt; The first Pakistani leader ever to receive this highest Saudi honor.

===Al-Qaeda===
[[File:Hamid Mir interviewing Osama bin Laden.jpg|thumb|[[Pakistan|Pakistani]] journalist [[Hamid Mir]] with [[Osama bin Laden]] in 1997]]

[[Osama bin Laden]] was a member of the prominent Saudi bin Laden family and the founding leader of [[Al Qaeda]]. After the attacks on September 11, 2001 (in which 3 000 people died on U.S. soil), Osama bin Laden and his organization have been major targets of the United States' [[War on Terror]]. Osama bin Laden was killed in Pakistan on May 2, 2011, shortly after 1 a.m. local time by a United States special forces military unit. 

[[Ayman al-Zawahiri]] was the second and last &quot;[[emir]]&quot; of [[Egyptian Islamic Jihad]]. In 1998 al-Zawahiri formally merged Egyptian Islamic Jihad into bin Laden's organization. He is often described as a &quot;lieutenant&quot; to [[Osama bin Laden]], though bin Laden's chosen biographer has referred to him as the &quot;real brains&quot; of al-Qaeda.&lt;ref name=&quot;CSM1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| first=Scott| last=Baldauf| title = The 'cave man' and Al Qaeda| publisher = Christian Science Monitor| date = 31 October 2001| url =http://www.csmonitor.com/2001/1031/p6s1-wosc.html| accessdate = 2008-04-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ayman al-Zawahiri is believed to be hiding in Pakistan's Federally Administered Tribal Areas by some analysts while other observers believe he might be hiding in major urban areas in Pakistan or elsewhere.

From 1996 to 2001 Osama Bin Laden and Ayman al-Zawahiri became a virtual state within the Taliban state. Bin Laden sent Arab fighters to join the fight against the United Front, especially his so-called [[055 Brigade]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily Times&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2008|url =http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2008\08\31\story_31-8-2008_pg3_4 |title = BOOK REVIEW: The inside track on Afghan wars by Khaled Ahmed| publisher = ''[[Daily Times (Pakistan)|Daily Times]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN&quot;&gt;{{cite web |date=unknown|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Grugy2txSvc&amp;feature=search |title = Brigade 055| publisher = [[CNN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arab militants under Bin Laden were responsible for some of the worst massacres in the war, killing hundreds of civilians in areas controlled by the United Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; A report by the [[United Nations]] quotes eyewitnesses in many villages describing Arab fighters carrying long knives used for slitting throats and skinning people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile fighters of Bin Laden's Brigade 055 were known for committing collective suicide before running risk of being taken prisoners by enemy forces themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steve Coll: Ghost Wars&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Steve Coll| authorlink = Steve Coll| title =Ghost Wars: The Secret History of the CIA, Afghanistan, and Bin Laden, from the Soviet Invasion to September 10, 2001 |edition=February 23, 2004 |pages=720| publisher =Penguin Press HC | isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Strategic Cooperation with the Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan (IMU)====
The [[Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan]] (IMU) is a militant group formed in 1991&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/40209731?seq=7 The Fires of Faith in Central Asia]&lt;/ref&gt; with strong ties to Al Qaeda.
It is estimated that the IMU in the late 1990s was approximately 2000 men strong, and that they contributed around 600 fighters to the Taliban's offensive against Massoud, participating in the siege of [[Taloqan]], where they fought alongside Bin Laden's [[055 Brigade]]. They were operating out of bases in Taliban-controlled areas of northern [[Afghanistan]]. In 2001 the IMU was largely destroyed while fighting alongside the Taliban against the [[United States]]-led coalition forces in Afghanistan. An unknown number of their fighters escaped with remnants of the Taliban to [[Waziristan]] in [[Pakistan]] where they created a follow-up organization. The IMU's longterm leader [[Tahir Yuldashev]] was killed as a result of an August 27, 2009, U.S. predator airstrike in [[South Waziristan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Long War Journal&quot;&gt;{{cite web |date=August 17, 2010|url =http://www.longwarjournal.org/archives/2010/08/islamic_movement_of_2.php |title = Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan names Abu Usman as new leader| publisher = Long War Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Usman succeeded him as the new leader of the IMU.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long War Journal&quot;/&gt; Today there are an estimated 2,500 to 4,000 IMU fighters based in Pakistan's tribal regions and in Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long War Journal&quot;/&gt;

==Background and history==
===Taliban rise to power===
After the fall of the [[communist]] [[Najibullah]]-regime in 1992, the Afghan political parties agreed on a peace and power-sharing agreement (the Peshawar Accords).&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;&gt;{{cite web|date= |url =http://www.hrw.org/en/reports/2005/07/06/blood-stained-hands|title = Blood-Stained Hands, Past Atrocities in Kabul and Afghanistan's Legacy of Impunity | publisher = [[Human Rights Watch]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Peshawar Accords created the [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt; From the first day of its founding until late 1994, the newly-created Islamic State of Afghanistan (ISA) came under attack by [[Gulbuddin Hekmatyar]]'s [[Hezb-i Islami]] militia armed, financed and instructed by neighboring Pakistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neamatollah Nojumi&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last =Neamatollah Nojumi | authorlink = | title =The Rise of the Taliban in Afghanistan: Mass Mobilization, Civil War, and the Future of the Region|edition=2002 1st |pages=| publisher = Palgrave, New York }}&lt;/ref&gt; Afghanistan expert [[Amin Saikal]] concludes in ''Modern Afghanistan: A History of Struggle and Survival'': 
{{blockquote|''&quot;Pakistan was keen to gear up for a breakthrough in [[Central Asia]]. [...] [[Islamabad]] could not possibly expect the new Islamic government leaders [...] to subordinate their own nationalist objectives in order to help Pakistan realize its regional ambitions. [...] Had it not been for the ISI's logistic support and supply of a large number of rockets, Hekmatyar's forces would not have been able to target and destroy half of Kabul.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt;}}
[[File:Abdul Rashid Dostum VOA Jan 22 2002 retouched.jpg|left|thumb|[[Abdul Rashid Dostum]], leader of [[National Islamic Movement of Afghanistan|Junbish-i-Milli Islami Afghanistan]]]]

[[Abdul Rashid Dostum]] and his [[Junbish-i Milli]] militia joined an alliance with Hekmatyar in early 1994. In addition, [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Iran]] - as competitors for regional [[hegemony]] - supported Afghan militias hostile towards each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last =Amin Saikal | authorlink = Amin Saikal| title =Modern Afghanistan: A History of Struggle and Survival|edition=2006 1st |page=352| publisher = I.B. Tauris &amp; Co Ltd., London New York | isbn=1-85043-437-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Human Rights Watch, Iran was assisting the [[Shia]] [[Hazara people|Hazara]] [[Hezb-i Wahdat]] forces of [[Abdul Ali Mazari]], as Iran was attempting to maximize Wahdat's military power and influence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roy Gutman&quot;&gt;GUTMAN, Roy (2008): How We Missed the Story: Osama Bin Laden, the Taliban and the Hijacking of Afghanistan, Endowment of the United States Institute of Peace, 1st ed., Washington D.C.&lt;/ref&gt; Saudi Arabia supported the [[Wahhabite]] [[Abdul Rasul Sayyaf]] and his [[Ittihad-i Islami]] faction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt; Conflict between the two militias soon escalated into a full-scale war. The capital city [[Kabul]] saw extremely violent fighting during that period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neamatollah Nojumi&quot;/&gt; Power was highly decentralized.

Meanwhile, southern Afghanistan was neither under the control of foreign-backed militias nor the government in Kabul, but was ruled by local leaders such as [[Gul Agha Sherzai]] and their militias. In 1994, the [[Taliban]] (a movement originating from [[Jamiat Ulema-e-Islam]]-run religious schools for Afghan refugees in Pakistan) also developed in Afghanistan as a politico-religious force, reportedly in opposition to the [[tyranny]] of the local governor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matinuddin, Kamal 1999 pp.25&quot;&gt;Matinuddin, Kamal, ''The Taliban Phenomenon, Afghanistan 1994–1997'', [[Oxford University Press]], (1999), pp.25–6&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, the Taliban took power in several provinces in southern and central Afghanistan.

In late 1994, most of the militia factions ([[Hezb-i Islami]], [[Junbish-i Milli]] and [[Hezb-i Wahdat]]) which had been fighting in the battle for control of Kabul were defeated militarily in Kabul by forces of the Islamic State's [[Secretary of Defense]] [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]]. Bombardment of the capital came to a halt.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;&gt;Amnesty International. &quot;DOCUMENT - AFGHANISTAN: FURTHER INFORMATION ON FEAR FOR SAFETY AND NEW CONCERN: DELIBERATE AND ARBITRARY KILLINGS: CIVILIANS IN KABUL.&quot; 16 November 1995 Accessed at: http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/ASA11/015/1995/en/6d874caa-eb2a-11dd-92ac-295bdf97101f/asa110151995en.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;International Committee of the Red Cross&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=1995|url=http://www.icrc.org/eng/resources/documents/misc/57jly2.htm |title =Afghanistan: escalation of indiscriminate shelling in Kabul| publisher =International Committee of the Red Cross}}&lt;/ref&gt; Massoud tried to initiate a nationwide [[political process]] with the goal of national [[Democratic consolidation|consolidation]] and [[democratic]] elections, also inviting the [[Taliban]] to join the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Marcela Grad| authorlink = | title = Massoud: An Intimate Portrait of the Legendary Afghan Leader|edition=March 1, 2009 |pages=310  | publisher =  Webster University Press| isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Taliban declined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; They started shelling Kabul in early 1995 but were defeated by forces of the Islamic State government under [[Secretary of Defense]] [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]].&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;/&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zzPcMB9SQz0&amp;feature=search see video] [[Amnesty International]], referring to the Taliban offensive, wrote in a 1995 report:
{{blockquote|''&quot;This is the first time in several months that Kabul civilians have become the targets of rocket attacks and shelling aimed at residential areas in the city.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;/&gt;}}
The Taliban's early victories in 1994 were followed by a series of defeats that resulted in heavy losses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (5)&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=|url=http://www.hrw.org/reports98/afghan/Afrepor0-01.htm#P81_13959|title =II. BACKGROUND | publisher = Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 26, 1996, as the Taliban with military support by Pakistan and financial support by Saudi Arabia prepared for another major offensive, Massoud ordered a full retreat from Kabul.&lt;ref&gt;Coll, ''Ghost Wars'' (New York: Penguin, 2005), 14.&lt;/ref&gt; The Taliban seized Kabul on September 27, 1996, and established the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan. The Islamic State government remained the internationally recognized government of Afghanistan. The Taliban's Islamic Emirate received recognition only from Saudi Arabia, Pakistan and the United Arab Emirates.

===Creation of the United Front===
Ahmad Shah Massoud and Abdul Rashid Dostum, two former archenemies, created the United Front (Northern Alliance) against the Taliban that were preparing offensives against the remaining areas under the control of Massoud and those under the control of Dostum. [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EvYglyjbHkI see video] The United Front included beside the dominantly [[Tajik people|Tajik]] forces of Massoud and the [[Uzbeks|Uzbek]] forces of Dostum, [[Hazara people|Hazara]] factions and Pashtun forces under the leadership of commanders such as [[Abdul Haq (Afghan leader)|Abdul Haq]], [[Haji Abdul Qadir]], Qari Baba or diplomat [[Abdul Rahim Ghafoorzai]]. From the Taliban conquest in 1996 until November 2001 the United Front controlled roughly 30% of Afghanistan's population in provinces such as [[Badakhshan Province|Badakhshan]], [[Kapisa Province|Kapisa]], [[Takhar Province|Takhar]] and parts of [[Parwan Province|Parwan]], [[Kunar Province|Kunar]], [[Nuristan Province|Nuristan]], [[Laghman Province|Laghman]], [[Samangan Province|Samangan]], [[Kunduz Province|Kunduz]], [[Ghōr Province|Ghōr]] and [[Bamyan Province|Bamyan]]. This union did not consist of a &quot;Northern Alliance&quot; thus only the &quot;northern states&quot; of Afghanistan, but included resistance forces from all parts and all major ethnicities of the country.

Massoud did not intend for the United Front to become the ruling government of Afghanistan. His vision was for the United Front to help establish a new government, where the various ethnic groups would share power and live in peace through a democratic form of government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;

===Taliban massacres===
According to a 55-page report by the [[United Nations]], the Taliban, while trying to consolidate control over northern and western Afghanistan, committed systematic massacres against civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2001-10-12/news/0110120312_1_taliban-fighters-massacres-in-recent-years-mullah-mohammed-omar|title=Taliban massacres outlined for UN |accessdate=|author= Newsday|authorlink= |year=2001|month=October |work=|publisher= Chicago Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.papillonsartpalace.com/massacre.htm|title=Confidential UN report details mass killings of civilian villagers |accessdate=October 12, 2001|author= Newsday|authorlink= |year=2001|month= |work=|publisher= newsday.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; UN officials stated that there had been &quot;15 massacres&quot; between 1996 and 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; They also said, that &quot;[t]hese have been highly systematic and they all lead back to the [Taliban] Ministry of Defense or to Mullah Omar himself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; The Taliban especially targeted Shias or Hazaras.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; Many civilians fled to the area of Massoud. The National Geographic concluded: &quot;The only thing standing in the way of future Taliban massacres is Ahmad Shah Massoud.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt;

===Excerpts of the war===
====Panjshir====
The Taliban with the support of the [[Pakistan Army]]'s ''13th Regular Army'' and the ''50th Airborne Division'' launched an aggressive series of military operations against Panjshir and the surrounding areas. The Pakistan Army's'' 4th Army Aggressor Squadron'' provided the reconnaissance intelligence to the ''13th Regular Army'', ''50th Airborne Division'', and the Taliban forces. Meanwhile, [[Al-Qaida]] and [[Arab Brigade]]s launched their own military campaign to support the Taliban hoping to gain control of the [[Panjshir Valley]]. This operation, planned and launched under General Naseem Rana, was well planned, more organized and comprehensibly studied by Pakistan Armed Forces.

Despite the large series of organized attacks operatoins led by the General Rana of Pakistan Army and their Taliban allies, they were not able to subdue the Panjshir. Ahmad Shah Massoud, who had defeated the [[Soviet Union]]'s [[40th Army]] in his [[Panjshir offensives|hometown]] before, successfully defended the Panjshir Valley, and diverted further assaults led by the ''13th Regular Army'' and the ''50th Airborne Division'' of Pakistan.

====Kabul and Kunduz====
The Islamic State's [[Secretary of Defense]] [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]], who still represented the legitimate government as recognized by the international community and the United Nations, in 1997 summoned a conference under his leadership to decide on a future government and prime minister. The Pashtun [[Abdul Rahim Ghafoorzai]], who was not affiliated with any party, was the candidate at that time and without dissenting votes was elected as new prime minister. Ghafoorzai's program was cordially received by wide sections of the population. A first step towards a new popular government was made. Massoud had the Afghan army equipped with newly acquired military uniforms and advanced after a few large offensive to the gates of '''Kabul'''. The alliance pushed forward with [[tank]]s, [[armored personnel carrier]]s, and heavy weapons into the [[Bagram airbase]], which was the first major victory against the Taliban since they lost Kabul.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Afghan government forces recapture key military positions|date=1996-10-19|publisher=''CNN News''|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9610/19/afghanistan/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; After making gains north of the capital, they met heavy resistance by Taliban forces inside Kabul.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Afghanistan's Taliban, opposition both claim gains|date=1997-07-31|publisher=''CNN News'' |url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9707/31/afghanistan/}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time the new prime minister's airplane crashed over Bamiyan. By Ghafoorzai's death, Massoud lost his hope for a stable government in Kabul. Massoud withdrew his troops from the north of Kabul, since he did not intend to march into Kabul without having formed a government before which would be acceptable for all especially for the civilian population since that would have harbored the danger of a repetition of the 1992-1994 period.

Approximately 2,000 Taliban fighters in '''Kunduz''' were surrounded by forces of Massoud. These Taliban forces were able to survive when they allied with one of [[Abdul Rasul Sayyaf]]'s former [[Ittihad-i Islami]] commanders.&lt;ref&gt;Matinuddin, Kamal. &quot;The Taliban Phenomenon: Afghanistan 1994-1997.&quot; Accessed at: http://books.google.com.tr/books?id=BIyVMkjat2MC&amp;pg=PA98&amp;lpg=PA98&amp;dq=battles+of+mazar-e+sharif+1997&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=sQ58cyXFxw&amp;sig=erg4IhED0-XVJwCZvCp6RO-hBnQ&amp;hl=tr&amp;ei=TgQdS4eWBsSEsAaEt_yvCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CBcQ6AEwAzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=battles of mazar-e sharif 1997&amp;f=false , page 102&lt;/ref&gt; Mullah Amir Khan Muttaqi, who was among these men, led an attack on 4 July 1997 against the capital of Takhar, Taloqan, which was under the control of Massoud. Although the attack failed it produced difficulties for the United Front on another front.

====Mazar-i Sharif====
{{Main|Battles of Mazar-i-Sharif 1997-1998}}

In May 1997, angry at Dostum's alleged involvement in the assassination of his brother, [[Abdul Malik Pahlawan]] and other commanders such as Qari Alam Rosekh, General [[Abdul Majid Rouzi]] and Ghafar Pahlawan met with Taliban commanders Mullah [[Abdul Razzaq (Taliban Governor)|Abdul Razzaq]] and Mullah Ghaus in Baghdis. They agreed that Malik would betray Dostum, capture [[Ismail Khan]] and take control of the city of [[Mazar-e Sharif]].&lt;ref&gt;Afghanistan Justice Project. &quot;Casting Shadows: War Crimes and Crimes Against Humanity, 1978-2001.&quot; 2005. Accessed at: http://www.afghanistanjusticeproject.org/ [Accessed on 10 November 2009], page 115&lt;/ref&gt; Malik attacked Dostum's forces in Jawzjan on 22 May 1997, and occupied Dostum's stronghold of Sheberghan. Most of Dostum's commanders defected and joined Malik and even some of his air force pilots joined the battle on Malik's side.&lt;ref&gt;The Taliban Phenomenon, page 98&lt;/ref&gt; Although the exact details of the agreement were not clear, it appears as if the Taliban had failed to take their part. On May 25, the Taliban entered Mazar-e Sharif and began to close schools, offices and impose Sharia law. In the Hazara sections of the city, particularly in the north-east and east areas around Syedabad, local [[Hezb-i Wahdat]] commanders and armed &quot;civilians&quot; began to enlist themselves in resistance.

On 22 May 1997 fighting also broke out between Dostum's forces and the Taliban in [[Andkhoy]] and Khwaja Dokoh. Massoud sent reinforcements.

On May 30, heavy fighting broke out around Syedabad. Taliban fighters were ambushed. At this point, Malik changed allegiances allying his forces with Hezb-i Wahdat, taking thousands of Taliban soldiers as prisoners in [[Maimana]], [[Sheberghan]] and [[Mazar-e Sharif]]. The Taliban prisoners were summarily executed, reportedly under the supervision of Malik's brother General Gul Mohammad Pahlawan.&lt;ref&gt;Afghanistan Justice Project, 116&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates of the total number killed were 3000. Furthermore Junbish commanders such as Ghulam Haidar Jawzjani were also captured and killed, along with Salam Pahlawan and Rais Omar Bey. In the months following the defeat of the Taliban in Mazar-e Sharif, Malik then proceeded to reincorporate troops loyal to [[Ismail Khan]] into the city's administration.

By July 1998 the Taliban had taken control of much of the area north of Herat, including the road linked to Maimana. On 8 August 1998, the Taliban re-entered Mazar-e Sharif.

Some [[Hezb-i Islami]] forces joined the Taliban during that time encircling the front lines of Hezb-i Wahdat at Qalai-Zaini-Takhta Pul.&lt;ref&gt;Afghanistan Justice project, 120&lt;/ref&gt; About 1,500 - 3,000 Wahdat fighters were trapped and killed by the Taliban and Hezb-i Islami. Senior commanders of Wahdat such as [[Muhammad Muhaqiq]] evacuated by helicopter.

[[Junbish-i Milli]] infighting between Dostum's forces and those of Malik furthermore created opportunities for the Taliban. The Taliban were able to surround Mazar-i Sharif from the rear, capturing [[Hairatan]] directly across from [[Termez]] on 20 September.
The Taliban then proceeded to enter the city where they executed approximately 4,000 civilians mostly of Hazara ethnic or Shia religious background. The Taliban, for the next 6 days were reported to have gone door to door looking for male Hazara Shias and then subsequently executing them. Thousands of prisoners were transported by both sides in metal transport truck containers were many suffocated or died of heat stroke. One Taliban hit-squad, Sipah-i Sahaba, captured the Iranian consulate where they shot dead one journalist and 8 Iranian intelligence and diplomatic officers.&lt;ref&gt;Afghanistan Justice Project, 121&lt;/ref&gt;

====Return of Ismail Khan====
In March 1997, Ismail Khan (United Front) returned from Iran. He led approximately 2,000 fighters to fight the Taliban in Badghis and push them to approximately 20 kilometers north of the Mughrab river leading to Qala-i Naw.&lt;ref&gt;The Taliban Phenomenon, 95&lt;/ref&gt; The Taliban's advance was halted but significant gains could not be made by either side.

====Iran-Taliban Crisis====
Among those killed in Mazar-i Sharif [[1998 Iranian diplomats assassination in Afghanistan|were several Iranian diplomats]]. Others were kidnapped by the Taliban, touching off a hostage crisis that nearly escalated to a full scale war, with [[Iran]] amassing 250,000 Iranian soldiers on the Afghan border.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Iranian military exercises draw warning from Afghanistan|date=1998-08-31|publisher=[[CNN]]|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/meast/9808/31/iran.games/}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later admitted that the diplomats were killed by the Taliban, and their bodies were returned to Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Taliban threatens retaliation if Iran strikes|date=1998-09-15|publisher=[[CNN]]|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/meast/9809/15/iran.afghan.tensions.02/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September the Taliban claimed that Iran had violated its [[airspace]]. Later Iran claimed minor clashes had occurred between the Taliban and Iran after the Taliban had allegedly led a [[Raid (military)|raid]] into eastern Iran, though the Taliban denied it led the raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Afghanistan claims Iranian aircraft invaded its airspace|date=1998-10-02|publisher=[[CNN]]|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/meast/9810/02/iran.afghanistan/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Iran reports clash with Afghan militia|date=1998-10-08|publisher=[[CNN]]|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/meast/9810/08/iran.afghan.01/}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually with UN [[mediation]], the tensions cooled.

===Assassination of Massoud===
In early 2001 Massoud addressed the [[European Parliament]] in [[Brussels]] asking the [[international community]] to provide [[humanitarian]] help to the people of Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;European Parliament&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60 |title = Massoud in the European Parliament 2001| publisher = EU media}}&lt;/ref&gt; He stated that the Taliban and [[Al Qaeda]] had introduced &quot;a very wrong perception of [[Islam]]&quot; and that without the support of Pakistan and Bin Laden the Taliban would not be able to sustain their military campaign for up to a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;European Parliament&quot;/&gt; On this visit to Europe he also warned that his intelligence had gathered information about a large-scale attack on U.S. soil being imminent.&lt;ref name=&quot;gwu.edu&quot;&gt;Defense Intelligence Agency (2001) report http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB97/tal32.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Guerre en Afghanistan (octobre 2001).PNG|thumb|Map of the situation in Afghanistan in August 2001 until [[Operation Enduring Freedom]]]]
On September 9, 2001, two Arab [[suicide attack]]ers allegedly belonging to Al Qaeda, posing as journalists, detonated a bomb hidden in a video camera while interviewing [[Ahmed Shah Massoud]]. Commander Massoud died in a helicopter that was taking him to a hospital. In over 26 years he had survived dozens of other assassination attempts by the Soviet KGB and the Afghan communist intelligence service, the Pakistani ISI, [[Gulbuddin Hekmatyar]], the Taliban and Al Qaeda.

===Defeat of the Taliban in Kabul===
{{Main|War in Afghanistan (2001–present)}}
For many days the United Front denied the death of Massoud for fear of desperation among their people. In the end the slogan &quot;Now we are all Massoud&quot; became a unifying battle cry. After the attacks of September 11, 2001, on U.S. soil which killed 3000 people, ground troops of the United Front ousted the Taliban from power in Kabul. In November and December 2001 the United Front gained control of much of the country. This was facilitated by extensive bombing of Taliban forces and military infrastructure by the United States during the U.S.-led attack on Afghanistan.

==See also==
*[[Timeline of the history of Afghanistan]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
;Starving to Death Afghanistan (documentary report March 1996) by Journeyman Pictures/ABC Australia
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zzPcMB9SQz0 Taliban attack Kabul and Massoud]
;Massoud's Last Stand - Afghanistan (documentary report 1997) by Journeyman Pictures/ABC Australia
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EvYglyjbHkI Afghanistan in 1997]
;Inside the Taliban (documentary film 2007) by the National Geographic
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xpQI6HKV-ZY&amp;feature=related Inside the Taliban]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Civil War In Afghanistan (1996–2001)}}
[[Category:20th century in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:21st century in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:1996 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:1997 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:1998 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:1999 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:2000 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:2001 in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:Afghan Civil War|*]]
[[Category:Afghanistan–Pakistan relations]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Taliban]]
[[Category:Warlordism]]

[[es:Guerra Civil Afgana (1992-2001)]]
[[ja:アフガニスタン紛争 (1989年-2001年)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
