<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="663591" ns="0" title="Phil Jackson"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the basketball coach|other people with the same name|Philip Jackson (disambiguation)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox NBA biography
| name         = Phil Jackson
| image        = Phil Jackson 3.jpg
| width        = 200px
| caption      =
| position     = [[Forward (basketball)|Forward]] / [[Center (basketball)|Center]]
| height_ft    = 6
| height_in    = 8
| weight_lb    = 220
| league       = 
| number       = 18, 17
| birth_date   = {{birth date and age|mf=yes|1945|09|17}} 
| birth_place  = [[Deer Lodge, Montana|Deer Lodge]], Montana
| nationality  = American
| high_school  = [[Williston High School (North Dakota)|Williston HS]] ([[Williston, North Dakota|Williston]], North Dakota)
| college      = [[North Dakota Fighting Sioux basketball|North Dakota]] (1964–1967)
| draft_year   = 1967
| draft_round  = 2
| draft_pick   = 17
| draft_team   = [[New York Knicks]]
| career_start = 1967
| career_end   = 1980
| years1 ={{nbay|1967|start}}–{{nbay|1977|end}} | team1 = New York Knicks
| years2 ={{nbay|1978|start}}–{{nbay|1979|end}} | team2 = [[New Jersey Nets]]
| cyears1 ={{nbay|1989|start}}–{{nbay|1997|end}} | cteam1 = [[Chicago Bulls]]
| cyears2 ={{nbay|1999|start}}–{{nbay|2003|end}} | cteam2 = [[Los Angeles Lakers]]
| cyears3 ={{nbay|2005|start}}–{{nbay|2010|end}} | cteam3 = [[Los Angeles Lakers]]
| highlights   = &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
'''As player:'''&lt;br&gt;
*2× [[List of NBA champions|NBA Champion]] ([[1970 NBA Finals|1970]], [[1973 NBA Finals|1973]])
*[[NBA All-Rookie Team|NBA All-Rookie First Team]] ({{nbay|1967|end}})
'''As coach:'''&lt;br&gt;
*11× [[List of NBA champions|NBA Champion]] ([[1991 NBA Finals|1991]]–[[1993 NBA Finals|1993]], [[1996 NBA Finals|1996]]–[[1998 NBA Finals|1998]], [[2000 NBA Finals|2000]]–[[2002 NBA Finals|2002]], [[2009 NBA Finals|2009]]–[[2010 NBA Finals|2010]])
*6× [[Eastern Conference (NBA)#Eastern Conference champions|Eastern Conference Champion]] ({{nbay|1990|end}}–{{nbay|1992|end}}, {{nbay|1995|end}}–{{nbay|1997|end}})
*7× [[Western Conference (NBA)#Western Conference champions|Western Conference Champion]] ({{nbay|1999|end}}–{{nbay|2001|end}}, {{nbay|2003|end}}, {{nbay|2007|end}}–{{nbay|2009|end}})
*[[NBA Coach of the Year Award|NBA Coach of the Year]] ({{nbay|1995|end}})
*4× [[NBA All-Star Game|NBA All-Star Game Coach]] ([[1992 NBA All-Star Game|1992]], [[1996 NBA All-Star Game|1996]], [[2000 NBA All-Star Game|2000]], [[2009 NBA All-Star Game|2009]])
*[[50 Greatest Players in NBA History#Coaches|Top 10 Coaches in NBA History]]
| profile      = action_jackson
| stat1label   = [[Point (basketball)|Points]]
| stat1value   = 5,428 (6.7 ppg)
| stat2label   = [[Rebound (basketball)|Rebounds]]
| stat2value   = 3,454 (4.3 rpg)
| stat3label   = [[Assist (basketball)|Assists]]
| stat3value   = 898 (1.1 apg)
| letter       = j
| bbr          = jacksph01
| HOF_coach    = phil-jackson
}}
'''Philip Douglas''' &quot;'''Phil'''&quot; '''Jackson''' (born September 17, 1945) is a retired American professional basketball coach and player. Jackson is widely considered one of the greatest coaches in the history of the [[National Basketball Association|National Basketball Association (NBA)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;50th&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://bleacherreport.com/articles/198121-auerbach-vs-jackson-who-is-the-best-nba-coach-of-all-time Auerbach vs Jackson]&lt;/ref&gt; His reputation was established as head coach of the [[Chicago Bulls]] from 1989 through 1998; during his tenure, Chicago won six NBA titles. His next team, the [[Los Angeles Lakers]], won five [[NBA]] titles from 2000 to 2010. In total, Jackson has won 11 [[List of NBA championship head coaches|NBA titles as a coach]], surpassing the previous record of nine set by [[Red Auerbach]]. He holds the record for the most championships in NBA history as a player and a head coach, after breaking the tie with [[Bill Russell]] when the [[Los Angeles Lakers]] won the [[2009 NBA Finals]]. Jackson was a player on the 1970 and 1973 NBA champion [[New York Knicks]].

Jackson is known for his use of [[Tex Winter]]'s [[triangle offense]] as well as a [[holistic]] approach to coaching that is influenced by [[Eastern philosophy]], earning him the nickname &quot;[[Zen master|Zen Master]]&quot;. Jackson cites [[Robert Pirsig]]'s book ''[[Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance]]'' as one of the major guiding forces in his life. He also applies Native American spiritual practices as documented in his book ''Sacred Hoops''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/sports/jan-june00/jackson_6-16.html Online NewsHour: Court Zen- June 16, 2000&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He is the author of several candid books about his teams and his basketball strategies. Jackson is also a recipient of the state of [[North Dakota]]'s [[Roughrider Award]]. In 2007 Jackson was inducted into the [[Basketball Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.realgm.com/src_wiretap_archives/45442/20070402/jackson_and_williams_lead_hof_class/|title=RealGM: Wiretap Archives: Jackson And Williams Lead HOF Class}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, as part of celebrations for the [[National Basketball Association]]'s 50th anniversary, Jackson was named one of the 10 greatest coaches in league history.&lt;ref name=&quot;50th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nba.com/history/top_10_coaches.html|title=Top 10 Coaches in NBA History|work=NBA.com|accessdate=August 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early years==
Jackson was born in [[Deer Lodge, Montana|Deer Lodge]], Montana. Both of his parents, Charles and Elisabeth Funk&lt;ref name=Halberstam&gt;{{cite book |last=Halberstam |first=David |authorlink=David Halberstam |title= Playing for Keeps: Michael Jordan and the World He Made |year=1999 |publisher=[[Random House]] |location=New York |isbn=0679415629 |pages=252–53}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson, were [[General Council of the Assemblies of God in the United States of America|Assemblies of God]] ministers. Elisabeth came from a long line of [[Mennonites]] before her conversion to the Assemblies of God. In the churches that they served, his father generally preached on Sunday mornings and his mother on Sunday evenings. Eventually, his father became a ministerial supervisor.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; Phil, his two brothers, and his half-sister grew up in a remote area of Montana in an austere environment, in which no dancing or television was allowed. Jackson did not see his first movie until he was a senior in high school, and went to a dance for the first time in college.&lt;ref name=Halberstam /&gt; Growing up, he assumed he would become a minister.  

Jackson attended high school in [[Williston, North Dakota|Williston]], North Dakota where he played varsity basketball and led the team to two state titles. He also played [[American football|football]], was a [[pitcher]] on the baseball team, and threw the [[discus]] in track and field competitions.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; The high school now has a sports complex named after him. His brother Chuck speculated years later that the three Jackson sons threw themselves passionately into athletics because it was the only time they were allowed to do what other children were doing.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; Jackson attracted the attention of several baseball scouts. Their notes found their way to future NBA coach [[Bill Fitch]], who had previously coached baseball, and had been doing some scouting for the [[Atlanta Braves]]. Fitch took over as head basketball coach at the [[University of North Dakota]] in the spring of 1962, during Jackson's junior year of high school.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt;

Bill Fitch successfully recruited Jackson to [[University of North Dakota|UND]], where he was a member of [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]] fraternity.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt;&lt;ref name=SAE&gt;[http://www.sae.net/index.asp?r=fraternity&amp;sr=facts&amp;ssr=facts Facts and History], Sigma Alpha Epsilon.&lt;/ref&gt;  Jackson did well there, helping the [[North Dakota Fighting Sioux|Fighting Sioux]] to third- and fourth-place finishes in the [[NCAA Men's Division II Basketball Championship|NCAA Division II tournament]] in his sophomore and junior years (1965 and 1966). Both years, they were beaten by [[Southern Illinois Salukis|Southern Illinois]].&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; Jackson's future Knicks teammate [[Walt Frazier]] was the Salukis' biggest star, but the two only faced off in 1965, as Frazier was academically ineligible in 1966.

==NBA playing career==
In [[1967 NBA Draft|1967]], Jackson was drafted in the second round by the [[New York Knicks]]. While he was a good all-around athlete, with unusually long arms, he was limited offensively and&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; compensated with intelligence and hard work on defense.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; Jackson eventually established himself as a fan favorite and one of the NBA's leading substitutes. He was a top reserve on the Knicks team that won the NBA title in [[1972-73 NBA season|1973]]. Jackson missed being part of New York's 1970 championship season due to [[spinal fusion]] surgery; however, he authored a book entitled &quot;Take It All,&quot; a photo diary of the Knicks' 1970 Championship run. 

Soon after the 1973 title, several key starters retired, creating an opening for Jackson in the starting lineup.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt; In the [[1974-75 NBA season]], Jackson and the [[Milwaukee Bucks]]' [[Bob Dandridge]] shared the lead for total [[Personal foul (basketball)|personal fouls]], with 330 each.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/leagues/NBA_1975_stats.html 1974–75 NBA Player Register], basketball-reference.com&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson lived in [[Leonia, New Jersey|Leonia]], New Jersey during this time.&lt;ref&gt;Adamek, Steve; and Iannazzone, Al. [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-53411268.html &quot;Lakers Notebook&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', June 5, 2002. Accessed March 30, 2011. &quot;Phil Jackson's memories of New Jersey are fond and forgetful. He finished his playing career with the Nets when they played their home games at Rutgers, about an hour trip from where he lived in Leonia.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; After going across the [[Hudson River|Hudson]] in [[1978-79 NBA season|1978]] to play two seasons for the [[New Jersey Nets]], he retired from play in [[1979-80 NBA season|1980]].

==Coaching==
In the following years, he mainly coached in lower-level professional leagues, notably the [[Continental Basketball Association]] and [[Puerto Rico]]'s ''[[National Superior Basketball]]'' ([[National Superior Basketball|BSN]]). While in the CBA, he won his first coaching championship, leading the [[Albany Patroons]] to their first CBA title in 1984. In Puerto Rico, he coached the [[Piratas de Quebradillas]] (1984 and 1987) and the Gallitos de Isabela (1984–1986), both teams with great tradition in the league. He regularly sought an NBA job, but was invariably turned down. He had acquired a reputation for being sympathetic to the [[counterculture]] during his playing years, which may have scared off potential NBA employers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halberstam&quot;/&gt;

===Chicago Bulls===
[[File:Phil Jackson Lipofsky.JPG|thumb|right|Jackson won six NBA championships coaching the [[Chicago Bulls]] during the 1990s. [[Michael Jordan]] was among Bulls players he coached that time.]]

Jackson was hired as assistant coach, under [[Doug Collins]], for the Bulls in 1987, and promoted to [[head coach]] in 1989. It was around this time that he met [[Tex Winter]] and became a devotee of Winter's [[triangle offense]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ktka.com/news/2007/feb/22/Former_K_State_basketball/|publisher=KTKA.com|work=ABC News|title=Former K-State basketball star dies at 72|date=February 22, 2007|accessdate=October 2, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.basketball.ca/en/hm/inside.php?sid=87&amp;id=1161&amp;PHPSESSID=1f02554bda44c6de62046f6a3f345ec6|work=Canada Basketball|title=Candidates for the 2007 Class of the FIBA Hall of Fame announced|date=May 25, 2007|accessdate=October 2, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 9 seasons, Jackson coached the Bulls to 6 championships in impressive fashion, twice winning three straight championships over separate three year periods. The &quot;three-peat&quot; was the first since the [[Boston Celtics]] won eight titles in a row from 1959 through 1966.

Jackson and the Bulls made the playoffs every year, and failed to win the title only three times. [[Michael Jordan]]'s first retirement after the 1993 season marked the end of the first &quot;three-peat,&quot; and although Jordan returned just before the [[1995 NBA Playoffs|1995 playoffs]], it was not enough to prevent a playoff exit to the [[Orlando Magic]].

Despite the Bulls' success, tension between Jackson and Bulls general manager [[Jerry Krause]] grew. Some believed that Krause felt under-recognized for building a championship team and believed that Jackson was indebted to him for giving him his first NBA coaching job. In the summer of 1997, Jackson was not invited to the wedding of Krause's stepdaughter, although all of the Bulls' assistant coaches were, as was [[Tim Floyd]], then head coach at [[Iowa State Cyclones men's basketball|Iowa State]], Jackson's eventual successor.&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt;  After contentious negotiations, Jackson was signed for the 1997–98 season only. Krause announced the signing by emphasizing that Jackson would not be rehired even if the Bulls won the 1997–98 title. Jackson then told Krause that he seemed to be rooting for the other side, to which Krause responded, &quot;I don't care if it's 82-and-0 this year, you're fucking gone.&quot;&lt;ref name=Halberstam/&gt;  Krause publicly portrayed Jackson as a two-faced character who had very little regard for his assistant coaches. At the height of the controversy in the spring of 1998, one of Krause's staff went to press row in Chicago's [[United Center]] to explain to a reporter the insidious nature of Jackson's ego.

After the Bulls' final title of the [[Michael Jordan|Jordan]] era in 1998, Jackson left the team vowing never to coach again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The head Bull rides off into the sunset|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/basketball/nba/news/1998/06/22/jackson_update/|work=CNN.com|publisher=Associated Press|accessdate=July 9, 2011|date=June 22, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, after taking a year off, he decided to give it another chance with the [[Los Angeles Lakers]] in 1999.

===Los Angeles Lakers===
{{Ref improve section|date=April 2011}}
[[File:Phil Jackson coaching LAL.jpg|thumb|225px|right|Phil Jackson (right) coaching the Lakers]]
Jackson took over a talented Lakers team and immediately produced results as he did in Chicago. In his first year in L.A., the Lakers went 67–15 during the regular season to top the league. Reaching the conference finals, they dispatched the [[Portland Trail Blazers]] in a tough seven-game series and then won the [[2000 NBA Finals|2000 NBA championship]] by beating the [[Indiana Pacers]].

With the talented superstar duo of [[Kobe Bryant]] and [[Shaquille O'Neal]], the strong supporting cast of [[Glen Rice]], [[Derek Fisher]], [[Rick Fox]], [[Devean George]], [[A. C. Green]], [[Robert Horry]], and [[Brian Shaw]], and the assistance of former Bulls [[Horace Grant]], [[Ron Harper]], and [[John Salley]], Jackson would lead the Lakers to two additional titles in [[2001 NBA Finals|2001]] and [[2002 NBA Finals|2002]], against the [[Philadelphia 76ers]] and [[New Jersey Nets]], adding up to his third [[three-peat]] as head coach. The main serious challenge the Lakers faced was from their conference rival, the [[Sacramento Kings]].

However, injuries, weak bench play, and [[Bryant–O'Neal feud|full-blown public tension]] between Bryant and O'Neal eventually slowed the team down, and they were beaten in the second round of the [[2002-03 NBA season|2003]] NBA Playoffs by the eventual champion [[San Antonio Spurs]].
Afterward, Jackson clashed frequently with Bryant. While remarkably efficient in Jackson's &quot;[[triangle offense]]&quot;, Bryant had a personal distaste for Jackson's brand of basketball and subsequently called it &quot;boring.&quot; In games, Bryant would often disregard the set offense completely to experiment with his own one-on-one moves, incensing the normally calm Jackson. Bryant managed to test Jackson's patience enough that the &quot;Zen Master&quot; even demanded that Bryant be traded, although Laker management rejected the request.

Prior to the [[2003-04 NBA season|2003–04 season]], the Lakers signed NBA star veterans [[Karl Malone]] and [[Gary Payton]], who had been franchise players for the [[Utah Jazz]] and the [[Seattle SuperSonics]], respectively, leading to predictions by some that the team would finish with the best record in NBA history. But from the first day of training camp, the Lakers were beset by distractions. Bryant's [[Kobe Bryant sexual assault case|trial for alleged sexual assault]], continued public sniping between O'Neal and Bryant, and repeated disputes between Jackson and Bryant all affected the team during the season. Despite these distractions, the Lakers beat the defending champion Spurs en route to advancing to the [[2004 NBA Finals]] and were heavy favorites to regain the title. However, they were stunned by the [[Detroit Pistons]], who used their strong defense to dominate the Lakers, winning the title four games to one. This marked the first time in 10 attempts as head coach that Jackson had lost in the [[NBA Finals]].

On June 18, 2004, three days after the loss to the Pistons, the Lakers announced that Jackson would leave his position as Lakers coach. Jackson was seeking to double his salary from $6&amp;nbsp;million to $12&amp;nbsp;million on his expiring contract. He had a contract offer outstanding from the Lakers, but he had not acted on it.&lt;ref name=lazenby2006_p423&gt;[[#lazenby2006|Lazenby 2006]], p.423&lt;/ref&gt; Winter said Jackson announced at the [[NBA All-Star Game|All-Star]] break that he would not want to return to the Lakers if Bryant returned.&lt;ref name=lazenby2006_p423/&gt; Many fans attributed Jackson's departure directly to the wishes of Bryant, as Lakers owner [[Jerry Buss|Dr. Jerry Buss]] reportedly sided with Bryant. Jackson, Bryant and Buss all denied that Bryant had made any explicit demand regarding Jackson. However, O'Neal, upon hearing General Manager [[Mitch Kupchak]]'s announcement of the team's willingness to trade O'Neal and its intention to keep Bryant, indicated that he felt the franchise was indeed pandering to Bryant's wishes with the departure of Jackson. O'Neal's trade to the Miami Heat was the end of the &quot;Trifecta&quot; that had led the Lakers to three championship titles.

That fall, Jackson released ''[[The Last Season: A Team in Search of Its Soul|The Last Season]]'', a book which describes his point of view of the tensions that surrounded the 2003–04 Lakers team. The book was pointedly critical of [[Kobe Bryant]]; at one point, Jackson called him &quot;uncoachable&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-RbLBGZwiR4&amp;feature=related Kobe vs Michael Documentary(Part 2)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Without Jackson and O'Neal the Lakers were forced to become a faster paced team on the court. Though they achieved some success in the first half of the season, injuries to several players including stars Kobe Bryant and Lamar Odom forced the team out of contention, going 34–48 in [[2004-05 NBA season|2004–05]] and missing the playoffs for the first time in 11 years. [[Rudy Tomjanovich]], Jackson's successor as coach, resigned midway through the season after coaching just 41 games, citing health issues not relating to his past bout with bladder cancer, which immediately led to speculation that the Lakers might bring Jackson back.

On June 15, 2005, the Lakers rehired Jackson. Jackson took a Laker squad that was mediocre, aside from Bryant, and led them to a seventh-seed playoff berth. Once again promoting the notion of selfless team play embodied by the [[triangle offense]], the team achieved substantial results, especially in the last month of the season. Jackson also worked seamlessly with Bryant, who had earlier shown his desire to bring back Jackson to the bench. Bryant's regular-season performance won him the league scoring title and made him a finalist in MVP voting. However, the Lakers faced a tough 2006 first-round matchup against the second-seeded [[Phoenix Suns]], who were led by eventual MVP winner [[Steve Nash]]. It was the first time that Jackson's team had failed to reach the second round of the playoffs. The Lakers jumped out to a 3–1 lead following a dramatic last second shot by Bryant in overtime to win game four, but the Suns recovered to win the last three and take the series.

On January 7, 2007, Jackson won his 900th game, currently placing him 9th on the all-time win list for NBA coaches. With this win, Jackson became the fastest to reach 900 career wins, doing so in only 1,264 games and beating Pat Riley's previous record of 900 in 1,278 games.

On December 12, 2007, after announcing he would return to his position as coach just a few days prior, Jackson inked a 2-year contract extension to continue his tenure with the [[Los Angeles Lakers]] through the end of the 2009–2010 season.

During the 2007–08 season, the Lakers were able to obtain [[Pau Gasol]] in a trade with the [[Memphis Grizzlies]]. With another star to pair with Bryant, Jackson coached the Lakers to an appearance in the [[2008 NBA Finals]] against the [[Boston Celtics]]. Boston went on to win the series 4–2, in the process handing Jackson and the Lakers their worst playoff loss ever in Game 6, a 39 point defeat. It was only the 2nd time in 11 appearances that Jackson had lost an NBA Finals.

On December 25, 2008, Jackson became the sixth coach to win 1,000 games, with the Lakers defeating the Celtics in their first matchup since the last year's finals. He was the fastest to win 1,000 games, surpassing [[Pat Riley]], who had taken 11 more games than Jackson.

Jackson again coached the Lakers to the NBA Finals in [[2009 NBA Finals|2009]], defeating the [[Utah Jazz]], [[Houston Rockets]], and [[Denver Nuggets]] in the process. In the Finals, the Lakers defeated the [[Orlando Magic]] 4–1, clinching Jackson's 10th NBA championship as head coach and surpassing the record for most championships won by a head coach previously held by [[Red Auerbach]]. 

On February 3, 2010, Jackson recorded his 534th win as Lakers head coach, surpassing Pat Riley to become the most successful coach in franchise history. The Lakers would go on to a fifth consecutive playoff berth in [[2010 NBA Playoffs|2010]]. They defeated the [[Oklahoma City Thunder]], [[Utah Jazz]], and [[Phoenix Suns]] in the playoffs before defeating the [[Boston Celtics]] in the [[2010 NBA Finals]], earning Jackson his eleventh NBA championship as head coach and his fifth with the Lakers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/nba/recap?gameId=300617013|title=Bryant, Artest rally Lakers to 16th championship |date=June 17, 2010|work=ESPN|accessdate=June 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He tied original Lakers head coach [[John Kundla]]'s record for most championships won by a head coach in franchise history.

On July 1, 2010, Jackson, after giving it tremendous thought and consulting with his doctors over health concerns, announced that he would return to coach the Lakers for the 2010–11 season.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.yahoo.com/nba/news;_ylt=AgEulkIpjiJ1N3Saog.Z3rzYrYZ4?slug=ap-lakers-jackson Phil Jackson returning to coach Lakers next season] Yahoo Sports. July 1, 2010. Accessed July 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 2, 2010, Jackson signed a new contract with the Lakers to return for what he mentioned was &quot;his last stand&quot;, meaning the 2010–11 season would be his last. In January 2011, he reiterated that it would be his final season, explaining that in the past there was the possibility that maybe he would reconsider. &quot;This year, there's no maybe,&quot; said Jackson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=McMenamin |first=Dave |title=Phil Jackson still plans to retire |date=February 28, 2011 |work=ESPNLosAngeles.com |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/los-angeles/nba/news/story?id=6066049 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5wRLD9RTl |archivedate=February 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He reasserted that position after the Lakers were swept out of the playoffs by that season's [[2010–11 Dallas Mavericks season|eventual NBA champions, the Dallas Mavericks]], in the conference semifinals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Howard-Cooper|first=Scott|title=Phil Jackson is Retired … Maybe|url=http://hangtime.blogs.nba.com/2011/05/11/phil-jackson-is-retired-maybe/|publisher=NBA.com|accessdate=May 15, 2011|date=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Awards ==
{{Expand section|date=June 2010}}
In 2002 the [[United States Sports Academy]] awarded Jackson the Amos Alonzo Stagg Coaching Award.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gatorzone.com/story.php?id=12389&amp;html=basketball/men/news/20070717060100.html&amp;sport=baskm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Motivational techniques==
Along with being called the &quot;Zen Master,&quot; Jackson is known as the master of mind games.

In the [[2001 NBA Finals]] against the [[Philadelphia 76ers]], Jackson had [[Tyronn Lue]], a player on the Lakers who was comparable in size and height to Sixers star [[Allen Iverson]], wear a sock on his arm during Lakers practice to simulate Iverson's use of a compression arm sleeve as part of his regular gametime attire. Philadelphia media considered this to be a mind game tactic of Jackson's, but the main idea was to simulate what a game against Iverson is like, right down to the tattoos and cornrows (which Lue also had).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nba.com/finals2001/lue_lakers_010608.html?nav=ArticleList NBA Finals 2001&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Head coaching record==

Jackson has had a winning record every year as a head coach, and currently has the highest winning percentage of any Hall of Fame coach. Along with his NBA-record eleven championships, he is the only coach to win at least ten championships in any of North America's major professional sports.

{{NBA coach statistics legend}}
{{NBA coach statistics start}}
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |[[Chicago Bulls|CHI]]
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1989}}
|82||55||27||.671|| align=&quot;center&quot; |2nd in Central||16||10||6||.625
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[1990 NBA Playoffs|Conf. Finals]]
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1990}}
|82||61||21||.744|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Central||17||15||2||.882
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[1991 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1991}}
|82||67||15||.817|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Central||22||15||7||.682
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[1992 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1992}}
|82||57||25||.695|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Central||19||15||4||.789
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[1993 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1993}}
|82||55||27||.671|| align=&quot;center&quot; |2nd in Central||10||6||4||.600
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[1994 NBA Playoffs|Conf. Semifinals]]
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1994}}
|82||47||35||.573|| align=&quot;center&quot; |3rd in Central||10||5||5||.500
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[1995 NBA Playoffs|Conf. Semifinals]]
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1995}}
|82||72||10||.878|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Central||18||15||3||.833
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[1996 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1996}}
|82||69||13||.841|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Central||19||15||4||.789
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[1997 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |CHI
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1997}}
|82||62||20||.756|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Central||21||15||6||.714
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[1998 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|-
| align=&quot;left&quot; |[[Los Angeles Lakers|LAL]]
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|1999|trunc=y}}
|82||67||15||.817|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||23||15||8||.652
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[2000 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2000}}
|82||56||26||.683|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||16||15||1||.938
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[2001 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2001}}
|82||58||24||.707|| align=&quot;center&quot; |2nd in Pacific||19||15||4||.789
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[2002 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2002}}
|82||50||32||.610|| align=&quot;center&quot; |2nd in Pacific||12||6||6||.500
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[2003 NBA Playoffs|Conf. Semifinals]]
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2003}}
|82||56||26||.683|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||22||13||9||.591
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[2004 NBA Finals|NBA Finals]]
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2005}}
|82||45||37||.549|| align=&quot;center&quot; |3rd in Pacific||7||3||4||.429
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[2006 NBA Playoffs|First Round]]
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2006}}
|82||42||40||.512|| align=&quot;center&quot; |2nd in Pacific||5||1||4||.200
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[2007 NBA Playoffs|First Round]]
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2007}}
|82||57||25||.695|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||21||14||7||.676
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[2008 NBA Finals|NBA Finals]]
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2008}}
|82||65||17||.793|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||23||16||7||.696 
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[2009 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2009}}
|82||57||25||.695|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||23||16||7||.696 
| align=&quot;center&quot; |'''Won [[2010 NBA Finals|NBA Championship]]'''
|- 
| align=&quot;left&quot; |LAL
| align=&quot;left&quot; |{{nbay|2010}}
|82||57||25||.695|| align=&quot;center&quot; |1st in Pacific||10||4||6||.400
| align=&quot;center&quot; |Lost in [[2011 NBA Playoffs|Conf. Semifinals]]
|-class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
| align=&quot;left&quot; |'''Career'''
| ||1640||1155||485||.704|| ||333||229||104||.688
{{s-end}}

==Personal life==
Jackson is divorced with five children and seven grandchildren.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://blogs.forbes.com/jennagoudreau/2011/01/24/la-lakers-jeanie-buss-doesnt-play-by-the-rules-gayle-king-phil-jackson-boy-toy-playboy | work=Forbes | first=Jenna | last=Goudreau}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson has been dating Jeanie Buss, the daughter of Lakers owner [[Jerry Buss]], since 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family&quot;/&gt; He owns homes in [[Playa del Rey, Los Angeles]], and [[Lakeside, Montana]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2011/apr/07/sports/la-sp-phil-jackson-lakers-20110408 Retirement can't come soon enough for Phil Jackson]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books by Phil Jackson==
*{{cite book|title=Take It All!|year=1970|coauthor=George Kalinsky|isbn=10 0020291906}}
*{{cite book|title=Maverick|year=1975|coauthor=[[Charley Rosen]]|isbn=0-87223-439-8}}
*{{cite book|title=Sacred Hoops: Spiritual Lessons of a Hardwood Warrior|year=1995|coauthor=Hugh Delehanty|isbn=0-7868-6206-8}}
*{{cite book|title=More than a Game|year=2001|coauthor=[[Charley Rosen]]|isbn=1-58322-060-7}}
*{{cite book|title=[[The Last Season: A Team in Search of Its Soul]]|year=2004|coauthor=Michael Arkush|isbn=1-59420-035-1}}
*{{cite book|title=The Los Angeles Lakers: 50 Amazing Years in the City of Angels (Foreword by Phil Jackson)|year=2009|foreword=Phil Jackson|isbn=0-98232-420-0}}
*{{cite book|title=Journey to the Ring: Behind the Scenes with the 2010 NBA Champion Lakers|url=http://www.journeytothering.com/|year=2010|isbn=0-9823242-2-7}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Additional reading==

*{{cite book |last=Lazenby |first=Roland |authorlink=Roland Lazenby |title=The Show: The Inside Story of the Spectacular Los Angeles Lakers in the Words of Those Who Lived It |year=2006 |publisher=[[McGraw-Hill Professional]] |location=New York City |isbn=9780071430340 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=HiH8z6EmSIsC&amp;lpg=PA121&amp;vq=balloons&amp;dq=the%20show%20roland%20lazenby&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |ref=lazenby2006 |accessdate=April 18, 2011}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{commons}}
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20101202225337/http://www.nba.com/historical/playerfile/index.html?player=action_jackson Phil Jackson player file] at NBA.com
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20101201035612/http://www.nba.com/coachfile/phil_jackson/ Phil Jackson coach profile] at [[NBA.com]]
*[http://www.insidehoops.com/coach/phil-jackson.shtml Phil Jackson] InsideHoops.com profile
*{{imdb name|0413944}}
*[http://www.hoophall.com/hall-of-famers/tag/phil-jackson National Basketball Hall of Fame]
*[http://www.basketball-reference.com/coaches/jacksph01c.html NBA career stats as a coach] at Basketball-Reference
*[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/j/jacksph01.html NBA career stats as a player] at Basketball-Reference

{{Navboxes |list1=
{{1967 NBA Draft}}
{{New York Knicks 1969-70 NBA champions}}
{{New York Knicks 1972-73 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls 1990-91 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls 1991-92 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls 1992-93 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls 1995-96 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls 1996-97 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls 1997-98 NBA champions}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers 1999-2000 NBA champions}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers 2000-01 NBA champions}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers 2001-02 NBA champions}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers 2008–09 NBA champions}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers 2009–10 NBA champions}}
{{Chicago Bulls}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers head coaches}}
{{Los Angeles Lakers}}
{{2007 Basketball HOF}}
{{Basketball Hall of Fame coaches}}
{{NBA10C}}
{{NBA Coaches of the Year}}
}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Jackson, Phil
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =September 17, 1945
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Deer Lodge, Montana|Deer Lodge]], Montana
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Jackson, Phil}}
[[Category:1945 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Basketball players from Montana]]
[[Category:Basketball players from North Dakota]]
[[Category:BSN coaches]]
[[Category:Chicago Bulls assistant coaches]]
[[Category:Chicago Bulls head coaches]]
[[Category:Continental Basketball Association coaches]]
[[Category:New Jersey Nets broadcasters]]
[[Category:Converts to Buddhism]]
[[Category:Los Angeles Lakers head coaches]]
[[Category:National Basketball Association head coaches]]
[[Category:New Jersey Nets players]]
[[Category:New York Knicks draft picks]]
[[Category:New York Knicks players]]
[[Category:People from Leonia, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People from Powell County, Montana]]
[[Category:People from Williams County, North Dakota]]
[[Category:North Dakota Fighting Sioux men's basketball players]]

[[ar:فل جاكسون]]
[[ca:Phil Jackson]]
[[da:Phil Jackson]]
[[de:Phil Jackson]]
[[es:Phil Jackson]]
[[fa:فیل جکسون]]
[[fr:Phil Jackson]]
[[gl:Phil Jackson]]
[[hr:Phil Jackson]]
[[it:Phil Jackson]]
[[he:פיל ג'קסון]]
[[lv:Fils Džeksons]]
[[lt:Phil Jackson]]
[[nl:Phil Jackson]]
[[ja:フィル・ジャクソン]]
[[pl:Phil Jackson]]
[[pt:Phil Jackson]]
[[ru:Джексон, Фил]]
[[simple:Phil Jackson]]
[[fi:Phil Jackson]]
[[tr:Phil Jackson]]
[[bat-smg:Phil Jackson]]
[[zh:菲尔·杰克逊]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
