<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="66402" ns="0" title="Brown v. Board of Education"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Infobox SCOTUS case
|Litigants=Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka
|ArgueDate=December 9
|ArgueYear=1952
|ReargueDate=December 8
|ReargueYear=1953
|DecideDate=May 17
|DecideYear=1954
|FullName=Oliver Brown et al. v. Board of Education of Topeka et al.
|Citation=74 S. Ct. 686; 98 L. Ed. 873; 1954 U.S. LEXIS 2094; 53 Ohio Op. 326; 38 A.L.R.2d 1180
|USVol=347
|USPage=483
|Prior=Judgment for defendants, 98 F. Supp. 797 ([[United States District Court for the District of Kansas|D. Kan.]] 1951)
|Subsequent=Judgment on relief, 349 U.S. 294 (1955) (''Brown II''); on remand, 139 F. Supp. 468 (D. Kan. 1955); motion to intervene granted, 84 F.R.D. 383 (D. Kan. 1979); judgment for defendants, 671 F. Supp. 1290 (D. Kan. 1987); reversed, 892 F.2d 851 (10th Cir. 1989); vacated, 503 U.S. 978 (1992) (''Brown III''); judgment reinstated, 978 F.2d 585 (10th Cir. 1992); judgment for defendants, 56 F. Supp. 2d 1212 (D. Kan. 1999)
|Holding=Segregation of students in [[Public school (government funded)|public schools]] violates the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]], because separate facilities are inherently unequal. District Court of Kansas reversed.
|SCOTUS=1953-1954
|Majority=Warren
|JoinMajority=''all''
|LawsApplied=[[United States Constitution]], [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Amendment XIV]]
}}
[[File:Educational separation in the US prior to Brown Map.svg|right|thumb|Educational separation in the US prior to Brown]]
'''''Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka''''', 347 U.S. 483 (1954),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://laws.findlaw.com/us/347/483.html |title=Brown v. Board of Education, 347 U.S. 483 (1954) |publisher=FindLaw |accessdate=2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[landmark decision]] of the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] that declared state laws establishing separate [[Public school (government funded)|public schools]] for black and white students unconstitutional.  The decision overturned the  ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' decision of 1896 which allowed state-sponsored segregation.  Handed down on May 17, 1954, the [[Warren Court]]'s unanimous (9–0) decision stated that &quot;separate educational facilities are inherently unequal.&quot; As a result, [[de jure]] [[racial segregation]] was ruled a violation of the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] of the [[United States Constitution]]. This ruling paved the way for [[Racial integration|integration]] and the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)|civil rights movement]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crmvet.org/tim/timhis54.htm#1954bvbe ''Brown v Board of Education'' Decision] ~ Civil Rights Movement Veterans&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
For much of the sixty years preceding the ''Brown'' case, [[race relations]] in the U.S. had been dominated by [[racial segregation in the United States|racial segregation]]. This policy had been endorsed in [[Nadir of American race relations|1896]] by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] case of ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'', which held that as long as the separate facilities for the separate races were equal, segregation did not violate the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] (&quot;no State shall... deny to any person... the equal protection of the laws.&quot;).

The [[plaintiffs]] in ''Brown'' asserted that this system of [[racial segregation in the United States|racial separation]], while masquerading as providing separate but equal treatment of both white and black Americans, instead perpetuated inferior accommodations, services, and treatment for black Americans. Racial segregation in education varied widely from the 17 states that required racial segregation to the 16 that prohibited it. ''Brown'' was influenced by [[UNESCO]]'s 1950 Statement, signed by a wide variety of internationally renowned scholars, titled ''[[The Race Question]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prins&quot;&gt;[http://portal.unesco.org/en/ev.php-URL_ID=30431&amp;URL_DO=DO_TOPIC&amp;URL_SECTION=201.html “Toward a World without Evil: Alfred Métraux as UNESCO Anthropologist (1946–1962)”], by [[Harald E.L. Prins]], UNESCO {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; This declaration denounced previous [[scientific racism|attempts at scientifically justifying racism]] as well as morally condemning [[racism]]. Another work that the Supreme Court cited was [[Gunnar Myrdal]]'s ''[[An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy]]'' (1944). Myrdal had been a signatory of the UNESCO declaration. The research performed by the educational psychologists [[Kenneth and Mamie Clark|Kenneth B. Clark]] and [[Kenneth and Mamie Clark|Mamie Phipps Clark]] also influenced the Court's decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Desegregation to diversity?|url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/sep04/deseg.html|publisher=[[American Psychological Association]]|year=2004|accessdate=2008-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Clarks' &quot;[[Kenneth and Mamie Clark#Doll experiments|doll test]]&quot; studies presented substantial arguments to the Supreme Court about how segregation had an impact on black schoolchildren's mental status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2005/may/03/local/me-clark3 |title=Kenneth Clark, 90; His Studies Influenced Ban on Segregation - Los Angeles Times |publisher=Articles.latimes.com |date=2005-05-03 |accessdate=2010-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Brown v. Board of Education ==
In 1951, a [[class action]] suit was filed against the Board of Education of the City of [[Topeka, Kansas]] in the [[United States District Court for the District of Kansas]]. The plaintiffs were thirteen Topeka parents on behalf of their twenty children.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, ''[http://cjonline.com/stories/050904/04b_localcase.shtml Legacy of Brown: Many people part of local case, Thirteen parents representing 20 children signed up as Topeka plaintiffs]'', The Topeka Capital-Journal (Sunday, May 9, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

The suit called for the school district to reverse its policy of racial segregation. Separate elementary schools were operated by the Topeka Board of Education under an 1879 Kansas law, which permitted (but did not require) districts to maintain separate elementary school facilities for black and white students in twelve communities with populations over 15,000. The plaintiffs had been recruited by the leadership of the Topeka [[NAACP]]. Notable among the Topeka NAACP leaders were the chairman [[McKinley Burnett]]; Charles Scott, one of three serving as legal counsel for the chapter; and Lucinda Todd.

The named plaintiff, [[Oliver Brown (civil rights)|Oliver L. Brown]], was a parent, a welder in the shops of the [[Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway|Santa Fe Railroad]], an assistant pastor at his local church, and an [[African American]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/law/jan-june04/brown_05-12.html Black, White, and Brown], ''PBS NewsHour'' (2004-05-12).&lt;/ref&gt; He was convinced to join the lawsuit by Scott, a childhood friend. Brown's daughter Linda, a third grader, had to walk six blocks to her school bus stop to ride to [[Brown v. Board of Education National Historic Site|Monroe Elementary]], her segregated black school one mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km) away, while Sumner Elementary, a white school, was seven blocks from her house.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/5kwQQveNZ Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka] MSN Encarta, archived on 31 October 2009 from [http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761588641/brown_v_board_of_education_of_topeka.html the original]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjonline.com/indepth/brown/historic-spots-map.shtml |title=Interactive map of locations in Topeka important to the Brown case – Topeka Capital Journal online |publisher=Cjonline.com |date=1992-10-26 |accessdate=2010-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As directed by the NAACP leadership, the parents each attempted to enroll their children in the closest neighborhood school in the fall of 1951. They were each refused enrollment and directed to the segregated schools. Linda Brown Thompson later recalled the experience in a 2004 PBS documentary:

: .&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. well. like I say, we lived in an integrated neighborhood and I had all of these playmates of different nationalities. And so when I found out that day that I might be able to go to their school, I was just thrilled, you know. And I remember walking over to [[Sumner Elementary School|Sumner school]] with my dad that day and going up the steps of the school and the school looked so big to a smaller child. And I remember going inside and my dad spoke with someone and then he went into the inner office with the principal and they left me out .&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. to sit outside with the secretary. And while he was in the inner office, I could hear voices and hear his voice raised, you know, as the conversation went on. And then he immediately came out of the office, took me by the hand and we walked home from the school. I just couldn't understand what was happening because I was so sure that I was going to go to school with Mona and Guinevere, Wanda, and all of my playmates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://brownvboard.org/video/blackwhitebrown/ ''Black/White &amp; Brown''], transcript of program produced by KTWU Channel 11 in Topeka, Kansas. Originally aired May 3, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Kansas case, &quot;Oliver Brown et al. v. The Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas,&quot; was named after Oliver Brown as a legal strategy to have a man at the head of the roster. Also, it was felt by lawyers with the National Chapter of the NAACP, that having Mr. Brown at the head of the roster would be better received by the U.S. Supreme Court Justices because Mr. Brown had an intact, complete family, as opposed to someone who was a single parent head of household{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}. The thirteen plaintiffs were: Oliver Brown, Darlene Brown, Lena Carper, Sadie Emmanuel, Marguerite Emerson, Shirley Fleming, [[Zelma Henderson]], Shirley Hodison, Maude Lawton, Alma Lewis, Iona Richardson, and Lucinda Todd.&lt;ref&gt;Brown Foundation for Educational Equity, Excellence and Research, [http://brownvboard.org/mythsandtruths/ ''Myths Versus Truths''] (revised April 11, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ric Anderson, ''[http://cjonline.com/stories/050904/04b_localcase.shtml Legacy of Brown: Many people part of local case, Thirteen parents representing 20 children signed up as Topeka plaintiffs]'', The Topeka Capital-Journal (Sunday, May 9, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt; The last surviving plaintiff, Zelma Henderson, died in Topeka, on May 20, 2008, at the age of 88.&lt;ref name=nyt&gt;{{cite news |first=Margalit |last=Fox|title=Zelma Henderson, Who Aided Desegregation, Dies at 88  |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/22/us/22henderson.html?bl&amp;ex=1211601600&amp;en=d0a1ed67ee5b8c74&amp;ei=5087%0A|work=[[New York Times]] |publisher= |date=2008-05-22 |accessdate=2008-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://replay.web.archive.org/20080524231336/http://www.twincities.com/national/ci_9333780?nclick_check=1 Last surviving Brown v. Board plaintiff dies at 88] The Associated Press, May 21 2008, archived on May 24 2008 from [http://www.twincities.com/national/ci_9333780?nclick_check=1 the original]&lt;/ref&gt;

The District Court ruled in favor of the Board of Education, citing the U.S. Supreme Court precedent set in ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'', {{ussc|163|537|1896}}, which had upheld a state law requiring &quot;separate but equal&quot; segregated facilities for blacks and whites in railway cars.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.cjonline.com/stories/031604/loc_brown10.shtml School facilities for Negroes here held comparable]'', The Topeka State Journal (August 3, 1951)&lt;/ref&gt; The three-judge District Court panel found that segregation in public education has a detrimental effect upon negro children, but denied relief on the ground that the negro and white schools in Topeka were substantially equal with respect to buildings, transportation, curricular, and educational qualifications of teachers.&lt;ref&gt;''Brown v. Board of Education'', [http://brownvboard.org/research/opinions/brownfsp.htm 98 F. Supp. 797] (August 3, 1951).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Supreme Court review ===
The case of ''Brown v. Board of Education'' as heard before the Supreme Court combined five cases: ''Brown'' itself, ''[[Briggs v. Elliott]]'' (filed in [[South Carolina]]), ''[[Davis v. County School Board of Prince Edward County]]'' (filed in [[Virginia]]), ''[[Gebhart v. Belton]]'' (filed in [[Delaware]]), and ''[[Bolling v. Sharpe]]'' (filed in [[Washington D.C.]]).

All were NAACP-sponsored cases. The ''Davis'' case, the only case of the five originating from a student protest, began when sixteen-year-old [[Barbara Rose Johns]] organized and led a 450-student walkout of [[Robert Russa Moton Museum|Moton High School]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crmvet.org/tim/timhis51.htm#1951ssmh Student Strike at Moton High] ~ Civil Rights Movement Veterans&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Gebhart'' case was the only one where a trial court, confirmed by the [[Delaware Supreme Court]], found that discrimination was unlawful; in all the other cases the plaintiffs had lost as the original courts had found discrimination to be lawful.

The Kansas case was unique among the group in that there was no contention of gross inferiority of the segregated schools' physical plant, curriculum, or staff. The district court found substantial equality as to all such factors. The Delaware case was unique in that the District Court judge in ''Gebhart'' ordered that the black students be admitted to the white high school due to the substantial harm of segregation and the differences that made the schools separate but ''not'' equal. The NAACP's chief counsel, [[Thurgood Marshall]]—who was later appointed to the U.S. Supreme Court in 1967—argued the case before the Supreme Court for the plaintiffs. Assistant attorney general Paul Wilson—later distinguished emeritus professor of law at the [[University of Kansas]]—conducted the state's ambivalent defense in his first appellate trial.

=== Unanimous opinion and key holding ===
In spring 1953 the Court heard the case but was  unable to decide the issue and asked to rehear the case in fall 1953, with special attention to whether the Fourteenth Amendment's Equal Protection Clause prohibited the operation of separate public schools for whites and blacks.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://americanhistory.si.edu/Brown/history/index.html Smithsonian, “Separate is Not Equal: Brown v. Board of Education’’]&lt;/ref&gt;

The case was being reargued at the behest of Associate Justice [[Felix Frankfurter]], who used re-argument as a stalling tactic, to allow the Court to gather a unanimous consensus around a ''Brown'' opinion that would outlaw segregation.  Chief Justice Vinson had been a key  stumbling block.  The justices in support of desegregation spent much effort convincing those who initially dissented to join a unanimous opinion.  Even though the legal effect would be same for a majority versus unanimous decision, it was felt that it was vital to not have a dissent which could be relied upon by opponents of desegregation as a legitimizing counterargument.

Conference notes and draft decisions illustrate the division of opinions before the decision was issued.&lt;ref name=nyorker&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newyorker.com/archive/2004/05/03/040503crbo_books|publisher=[[The New Yorker]]|date=2004-05-03|title=Did Brown Matter?|author=[[Cass R. Sunstein]]|accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Justices [[William O. Douglas|Douglas]], [[Hugo Black|Black]], [[Harold Hitz Burton|Burton]], and [[Sherman Minton|Minton]] were predisposed to overturn Plessy.&lt;ref name=nyorker/&gt; [[Fred M. Vinson]] noted that Congress had not issued desegregation legislation; [[Stanley F. Reed]] discussed incomplete [[cultural assimilation]] and [[states' rights]] and was inclined to the view that segregation worked to the benefit of the African-American community; [[Tom C. Clark]] wrote that &quot;we had led the states on to think segregation is OK and we should let them work it out.&quot;&lt;ref name=nyorker/&gt; [[Felix Frankfurter]] and [[Robert H. Jackson]] disapproved of segregation, but were also opposed to [[judicial activism]] and expressed concerns about the proposed decision's enforceability.&lt;ref name=nyorker/&gt; After Vinson died in September 1953, President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] appointed [[Earl Warren]] as Chief Justice.&lt;ref name=nyorker/&gt; Warren had supported the integration of Mexican-American students in California school systems following ''[[Mendez v. Westminster]].''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The quest for a general theory of leadership|url=http://books.google.com/?id=yoSpyA152NQC&amp;pg=PT183&amp;dq=earl+warren++++menendez&amp;cd=6#v=onepage&amp;q=|author=George R. Goethals, Georgia Jones Sorenson|publisher=[[Edward Elgar Publishing]]|year=2006|page=165|isbn=9781845425418}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While all but one justice personally rejected segregation, the self-restraint faction questioned whether the Constitution gave the Court the power to order its end. The activist faction believed the Fourteenth Amendment did give the necessary authority and were pushing to go ahead. Warren, who held only a recess appointment, held his tongue until the Senate, dominated by southerners, confirmed his appointment.

Warren convened a meeting of the justices, and presented to them the simple argument that the only reason to sustain segregation was an honest belief in the inferiority of Negroes.  Warren further submitted that the Court must overrule ''Plessy'' to maintain its legitimacy as an institution of liberty, and it must do so unanimously to avoid massive Southern resistance.  He began to build a unanimous opinion.

Although most justices were immediately convinced, Warren spent some time after this famous speech convincing everyone to sign onto the opinion.  Justices Robert Jackson and Stanley Reed finally decided to drop their dissent to what was by then an opinion backed by all the others. The final decision was unanimous.  Warren drafted the basic opinion and kept circulating and revising it until he had an opinion endorsed by all the members of the Court.&lt;ref&gt;James T. Patterson, '' Brown v. Board of Education: A Civil Rights Milestone and Its Troubled Legacy'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Holding ===
The key holding of the Court was that, even if segregated black and white schools were of equal quality in facilities and teachers, segregation by itself was harmful to black students and unconstitutional.  They found that a significant psychological and social disadvantage was given to black children from the nature of segregation itself, drawing on research conducted by [[Kenneth and Mamie Clark|Kenneth Clark]] assisted by [[June Shagaloff Alexander|June Shagaloff]]. This aspect was vital because the question was not whether the schools were &quot;equal&quot;, which under ''Plessy'' they nominally should have been, but whether the doctrine of ''separate'' was constitutional.  The justices answered with a strong &quot;no&quot;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Does segregation of children in public schools solely on the basis of race, even though the physical facilities and other &quot;tangible&quot; factors may be equal, deprive the children of the minority group of equal educational opportunities? We believe that it does...

Segregation of white and colored children in public schools has a detrimental effect upon the colored children. The impact is greater when it has the sanction of the law, for the policy of separating the races is usually interpreted as denoting the inferiority of the negro group. A sense of inferiority affects the motivation of a child to learn. Segregation with the sanction of law, therefore, has a tendency to [retard] the educational and mental development of negro children and to deprive them of some of the benefits they would receive in a racial[ly] integrated school system...

We conclude that, in the field of public education, the doctrine of &quot;separate but equal&quot; has no place. Separate educational facilities are inherently unequal. Therefore, we hold that the plaintiffs and others similarly situated for whom the actions have been brought are, by reason of the segregation complained of, deprived of the equal protection of the laws guaranteed by the Fourteenth Amendment. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Local outcomes ===
The Topeka middle schools had been integrated since 1941. Topeka High School was integrated from its inception in 1871 and its sports teams from 1949 on.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjonline.com/indepth/flood/stories/071001_floodclass.shtml |title=Topeka Capital Journal article on integration of THS sports teams |publisher=Cjonline.com |date=2001-07-10 |accessdate=2010-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Kansas law permitting segregated schools allowed them only &quot;below the high school level.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjonline.com/stories/022802/ksb_release.shtml |title=Topeka Capital Journal on line article |publisher=Cjonline.com |date=2002-02-28 |accessdate=2010-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Soon after the district court decision, election outcomes and the political climate in Topeka changed. The Board of Education of Topeka began to end segregation in the Topeka elementary schools in August 1953, integrating two attendance districts. All the Topeka elementary schools were changed to neighborhood attendance centers in January 1956, although existing students were allowed to continue attending their prior assigned schools at their option.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cjonline.com/stories/031604/loc_brown4.shtml ''Racial bar down for teachers here''], Topeka Daily Capital (January 19, 1956)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cjonline.com/stories/031604/loc_brown16.shtml ''First step taken to end segregation''], Topeka Daily Capital (September 9, 1953)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cjonline.com/stories/031604/loc_brown7.shtml ''Little Effect On Topeka'']
Topeka Capital-Journal (May 18, 1954)&lt;/ref&gt; Plaintiff Zelma Henderson, in a 2004 interview, recalled that no demonstrations or tumult accompanied desegregation in Topeka's schools:

: &quot;They accepted it,&quot; she said. &quot;It wasn't too long until they integrated the teachers and principals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Erin Adamson, ''[http://www.cjonline.com/stories/051103/our_brown1.shtml Breaking barriers: Topekans reflect on role in desegregating nation's schools]'', Topeka Capital Journal (May 11, 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Topeka Public Schools administration building is named in honor of McKinley Burnett, NAACP chapter president who organized the case.

[[Brown v. Board of Education National Historic Site|Monroe Elementary]] was designated a U.S. [[National Historic Site (United States)|National Historic Site]] unit of the National Park Service on October 26, 1992.

== Social implications ==
Not everyone accepted the ''Brown v. Board of Education'' decision. In Virginia, Senator [[Harry F. Byrd, Sr.]] organized the [[Massive Resistance]] movement that included the closing of schools rather than desegregating them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crmvet.org/tim/timhis54.htm#1954mr &quot;Massive Resistance&quot; to Integration] ~ Civil Rights Movement Veterans&lt;/ref&gt; See, for example, [[The Southern Manifesto]]. For more implications of the ''Brown'' decision, see [[Desegregation]].

In 1957, [[Arkansas]] Governor [[Orval Faubus]] called out his state's [[Arkansas Army National Guard|National Guard]] to [[Little Rock Nine|block black students' entry]] to [[Little Rock Central High School]]. President [[Dwight Eisenhower]] responded by deploying elements of the [[101st Airborne Division]] from [[Fort Campbell]], Kentucky, to Arkansas and by federalizing Faubus' National Guard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crmvet.org/tim/timhis57.htm#1957lrsd The Little Rock Nine] ~ Civil Rights Movement Veterans&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 1957, [[Florida]]'s response was mixed. Its legislature passed an [[Interposition]] Resolution denouncing the decision and declaring it null and void. But [[Governor of Florida|Florida Governor]] [[LeRoy Collins|Thomas LeRoy Collins]], though joining in the protest against the court decision, refused to sign it arguing that the attempt to overturn the ruling must be done in legal methods.

In 1963, [[Alabama]] Gov. [[George Wallace]] personally blocked the door to [[Foster Auditorium]] at the [[University of Alabama]] to prevent the enrollment of two black students. This became the infamous [[Stand in the Schoolhouse Door]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crmvet.org/tim/timhis63.htm#1963tuscaloosa Standing In the Schoolhouse Door] ~ Civil Rights Movement Veterans&lt;/ref&gt; where Wallace personally backed his &quot;segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever&quot; policy that he had stated in his 1963 inaugural address.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/wallace/sfeature/quotes.html The American Experience; George Wallace: Settin' the Woods on Fire; Wallace Quotes], [[Public Broadcasting Service]], pbs.org, 2000. Retrieved February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; He moved aside only when confronted by [[Henry V. Graham|General Henry Graham]] of the Alabama National Guard, who was ordered by President John F. Kennedy to intervene.

The intellectual roots of ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'', the landmark United States Supreme Court decision upholding the constitutionality of [[Racial segregation in the United States|racial segregation]] in 1896 under the doctrine of &quot;[[separate but equal]]&quot; were, in part, tied to the [[scientific racism]] of the era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=Tm2I6LNZ7-cC&amp;pg=PA55&amp;lpg=PA55&amp;dq=plessy+ferguson+scientific+racism|page=55|title=Race, Law, and Culture: Reflections on Brown v. Board of Education|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=1997|author=Austin Sarat|quote=What lay behind ''Plessy v. Ferguson''? There were, perhaps, some important intellectual roots; this was the era of scientic racism.|isbn=9780195106220}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=fuXX4wQXYlsC&amp;pg=PA184&amp;dq=plessy+case+lofgren+scientific+testimony|title=The Plessy Case|author=Charles A. Lofgren|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=1988|page=184|quote=But he [ [[Henry Billings Brown]] ] at minimum established popular sentiment and practice, along with legal and scientific testimony on race, as a link in his train of reasoning.|isbn=9780195056846}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the popular support for the decision was more likely a result of the racist beliefs held by many whites at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;rlac&quot;&gt;''Race, Law, and Culture: Reflections on Brown v. Board of Education'' By Austin Sarat. Page 55 and 59. 1997. ISBN 0-19-510622-9&lt;/ref&gt;  In deciding ''Brown v. Board of Education'', the Supreme Court rejected the ideas of scientific racists about the need for segregation, especially in schools. The Court buttressed its holding by citing (in [http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=347&amp;invol=483#f11 footnote 11]) social science research about the harms to black children caused by segregated schools.

Both scholarly and popular ideas of [[hereditarianism]] played an important role in the attack and backlash that followed the ''Brown'' decision.&lt;ref name=&quot;rlac&quot; /&gt; The ''[[Mankind Quarterly]]'' was founded in 1960, in part in response to the ''Brown'' decision.&lt;ref&gt;''‘Scientific’ Racism Again?”:1 Reginald Gates, the Mankind Quarterly and the Question of “Race” in Science after the Second World War'' Journal of American Studies (2007), 41: 253–278 Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jackson&quot;&gt;''Science for Segregation: Race, Law, and the Case Against Brown v. Board of Education. By John P. Jackson. ISBN 0-8147-4271-8 Page 148&lt;/ref&gt;

School desegregation has been argued to have contributed to [[white flight]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/0049-089X(87)90001-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legal criticism and praise ==
[[File:Brown V. Board of Education Exhibit.jpg|thumb|right|[[United States courts of appeals|U.S. circuit judges]] [[Robert A. Katzmann]], [[Damon J. Keith]], and [[Sonia Sotomayor]] at a 2004 exhibit on the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]], [[Thurgood Marshall]], and ''Brown v. Board of Education'']]
[[William Rehnquist]] wrote a memo titled &quot;A Random Thought on the Segregation Cases&quot; when he was a law clerk for Justice [[Robert H. Jackson]] in 1952, during early deliberations that led to the ''Brown v. Board of Education'' decision. In his memo, Rehnquist argued: &quot;I realize that it is an unpopular and unhumanitarian position, for which I have been excoriated by 'liberal' colleagues but I think ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' was right and should be reaffirmed.&quot; Rehnquist continued, &quot;To the argument .&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. that a majority may not deprive a minority of its constitutional right, the answer must be made that while this is sound in theory, in the long run it is the majority who will determine what the constitutional rights of the minorities are.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;William Rehnquist, [http://a255.g.akamaitech.net/7/255/2422/26sep20051215/www.gpoaccess.gov/congress/senate/judiciary/sh99-1067/324-325.pdf &quot;A Random Thought on the Segregation Cases&quot;], S. Hrg. 99-1067, Hearings Before the Senate Committee on the Judiciary on the Nomination of Justice William Hubbs Rehnquist to be Chief Justice of the United States (July 29, 30, 31, and August 1, 1986).&lt;/ref&gt; Rehnquist also argued for ''Plessy'' with other law clerks.&lt;ref&gt;
Peter S. Canellos,[http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2005/08/23/memos_may_not_hold_robertss_opinions/ Memos may not hold Roberts's opinions], [[The Boston Globe]], August 23, 2005. Here is what Rehnquist said in 1986 about his conversations with other clerks about ''Plessy'':&lt;blockquote&gt;I thought ''Plessy'' had been wrongly decided at the time, that it was not a good interpretation of the equal protection clause to say that when you segregate people by race, there is no denial of equal protection. But ''Plessy'' had been on the books for 60 years; Congress had never acted, and the same Congress that had promulgated the 14th Amendment had required segregation in the District schools.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. I saw factors on both sides.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. I did not agree then, and I certainly do not agree now, with the statement that ''Plessy against Ferguson'' is right and should be reaffirmed. I had ideas on both sides, and I do not think I ever really finally settled in my own mind on that.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. [A]round the lunch table I am sure I defended it.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. I thought there were good arguments to be made in support of it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;S. Hrg. 99-1067, Hearings Before the Senate Committee on the Judiciary on the Nomination of Justice William Hubbs Rehnquist to be Chief Justice of the United States (July 29, 30, 31, and August 1, 1986).&lt;/ref&gt; However, during his 1971 confirmation hearings, Rehnquist said, &quot;I believe that the memorandum was prepared by me as a statement of Justice Jackson's tentative views for his own use.&quot; Justice Jackson had initially planned to join a dissent in ''Brown''.&lt;ref&gt;Justice [[William O. Douglas]] wrote: “In the original conference there were only four who voted that segregation in the public schools was unconstitutional. Those four were Black, Burton, Minton, and myself.” See Bernard Schwartz, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=Y5cUCl4hSWUC&amp;pg=PA96&amp;ots=5UtEFgR-B5&amp;dq=%22May+17,+1954%22+and+%22memorandum+for+the+file%22&amp;num=100&amp;sig=JrgkG7MAPIwfCPRBYYtwY9XULP4 Decision: How the Supreme Court Decides Cases]'', page 96 (Oxford 1996). Likewise, Justice [[Felix Frankfurter]] wrote: “I have no doubt that if the segregation cases had reached decision last term, there would have been four dissenters—Vinson, Reed, Jackson, and Clark.” Id. Justice Jackson’s longtime legal secretary had a different view, calling Rehnquist’s Senate testimony an attempt to &quot;smear the reputation of a great justice.&quot; See Alan Dershowitz, [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/alan-dershowitz/telling-the-truth-about-c_b_6844.html Telling the Truth About Chief Justice Rehnquist], [[Huffington Post]], September 5, 2005, accessed March 15, 2007.  See also [[Felix Frankfurter]] on the death of Justice Vinson.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, at his 1986 hearings for the slot of Chief Justice, Rehnquist put further distance between himself and the 1952 memo: &quot;The bald statement that Plessy was right and should be reaffirmed, was not an accurate reflection of my own views at the time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Adam Liptak, ''[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/11/weekinreview/11lipt.html?ei=5088&amp;en=5f85796f9c88b565&amp;ex=1284091200&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss&amp;pagewanted=print The Memo That Rehnquist Wrote and Had to Disown]'', NY Times (September 11, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;
In any event, while serving on the Supreme Court, Rehnquist made no effort to reverse or undermine the ''Brown'' decision, and frequently relied upon it as precedent.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://a255.g.akamaitech.net/7/255/2422/26sep20051215/www.gpoaccess.gov/congress/senate/judiciary/sh99-1067/303-305.pdf Cases where Justice Rehnquist has cited ''Brown v. Board of Education'' in support of a proposition], S. Hrg. 99-1067, Hearings Before the Senate Committee on the Judiciary on the Nomination of Justice William Hubbs Rehnquist to be Chief Justice of the United States (July 29, 30, 31, and August 1, 1986).

Also see Jeffery Rosen, [http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/200504/rosen/2 Rehnquist the Great?], [[Atlantic Monthly]] (April 2005): &quot;Rehnquist ultimately embraced the Warren Court's Brown decision, and after he joined the Court he made no attempt to dismantle the civil-rights revolution, as political opponents feared he would&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some aspects of the ''Brown'' decision are still debated. Notably, Supreme Court Justice [[Clarence Thomas]], himself an African American, wrote in ''[[Missouri v. Jenkins]]'' (1995) that at the very least, ''Brown I'' has been misunderstood by the courts.

: Brown I did not say that &quot;racially isolated&quot; schools were inherently inferior; the harm that it identified was tied purely to de jure segregation, not de facto segregation. Indeed, Brown I itself did not need to rely upon any psychological or social-science research in order to announce the simple, yet fundamental truth that the Government cannot discriminate among its citizens on the basis of race.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.

: Segregation was not unconstitutional because it might have caused psychological feelings of inferiority. Public school systems that separated blacks and provided them with superior educational resources making blacks &quot;feel&quot; superior to whites sent to lesser schools—would violate the Fourteenth Amendment, whether or not the white students felt stigmatized, just as do school systems in which the positions of the races are reversed. Psychological injury or benefit is irrelevant&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.

: Given that desegregation has not produced the predicted leaps forward in black educational achievement, there is no reason to think that black students cannot learn as well when surrounded by members of their own race as when they are in an integrated environment. (.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.) Because of their &quot;distinctive histories and traditions,&quot; black schools can function as the center and symbol of black communities, and provide examples of independent black leadership, success, and achievement.&lt;ref&gt;''Missouri v. Jenkins'', [http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=search&amp;court=US&amp;case=/us/515/70.html 515 U.S. 70 (1995)] (Thomas, J., concurring).&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Constitutional [[originalists]], notably [[Raoul Berger]] in his influential 1977 book &quot;Government by Judiciary,&quot; make the case that ''Brown'' cannot be defended by reference to the original understanding of the 14th Amendment. They support this reading of the 14th amendment by noting that the [[Civil Rights Act of 1875]] did not ban segregated schools. Other originalists, including [[Michael W. McConnell]], a federal judge on the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit]], in his article &quot;Originalism and the Desegregation Decisions,&quot; argue that the [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Radical Reconstructionists]] who spearheaded the 14th Amendment were in favor of desegregated southern schools.

The case also has attracted some criticism from more liberal authors, including some who say that Chief Justice Warren's reliance on psychological criteria to find a harm against segregated blacks was unnecessary. For example, [[Drew S. Days]] has written:&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN081479890X&amp;id=gL1YYW3MOyAC&amp;pg=RA1-PA97&amp;lpg=RA1-PA97&amp;ots=XjVzgRg8WQ&amp;dq=%22developed+criteria+for+evaluating+the+%22&amp;sig=CaG_xa3sJXNlR4PVBQt4D9Cjd7Y#PRA1-PA97,M1 What 'Brown v. Board of Education' Should Have Said], [[Jack Balkin]] ed., page 97 (2001, New York University Press)&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;we have developed criteria for evaluating the constitutionality of racial classifications that do not depend upon findings of psychic harm or social science evidence. They are based rather on the principle that 'distinctions between citizens solely because of their ancestry are by their very nature odious to a free people whose institutions are founded upon the doctrine of equality,' ''[[Hirabayashi v. United States]]'', 320 U.S. 81 (1943).&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&quot;

In his book &quot;The Tempting of America&quot; (page 82), [[Robert Bork]] endorsed the ''Brown'' decision as follows:

: By 1954, when Brown came up for decision, it had been apparent for some time that segregation rarely if ever produced equality. Quite aside from any question of psychology, the physical facilities provided for blacks were not as good as those provided for whites. That had been demonstrated in a long series of cases . . . The Court's realistic choice, therefore, was either to abandon the quest for equality by allowing segregation or to forbid segregation in order to achieve equality. There was no third choice. Either choice would violate one aspect of the original understanding, but there was no possibility of avoiding that. Since equality and segregation were mutually inconsistent, though the ratifiers did not understand that, both could not be honored. When that is seen, it is obvious the Court must choose equality and prohibit state-imposed segregation. The purpose that brought the fourteenth amendment into being was equality before the law, and equality, not separation, was written into the law.

In June 1987, [[Philip Elman]], a civil rights attorney who served as an associate in the Solicitor General's office during Harry Truman's term, claimed he and Felix Frankfurter were mostly responsible for the Supreme Court's decision, and stated that the NAACP's arguments did not present strong evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;EL)&quot;&gt;Harvard Law Review, Vol. 100, No. 8 (Jun., 1987), pp. 1938–1948&lt;/ref&gt;  Elman has been criticized for offering a self-aggrandizing history of the case, omitting important facts, and denigrating the work of civil rights attorneys who had laid the groundwork for the decision over many decades.&lt;ref&gt;See, eg, Randall Kennedy. &quot;A Reply to Philip Elman.&quot; Harvard Law Review 100 (1987):1938–1948.&lt;/ref&gt; Public officials in the United States today are nearly unanimous in lauding the ruling. In May 2004, the fiftieth anniversary of the ruling, President [[George W. Bush]] spoke at the opening of the &quot;[[Brown v. Board of Education National Historic Site]]&quot;, calling ''Brown'' &quot;a decision that changed America for the better, and forever.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2004/05/20040517-4.html ''Remarks by the President at Grand Opening of the Brown v Board of Education National Historic Site''], Topeka, Kansas (May 17, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; Most Senators and Representatives issued press releases hailing the ruling.

== Brown II ==
{{see also|Griffin v. County School Board of Prince Edward County}}
In 1955, the Supreme Court considered arguments by the schools requesting relief concerning the task of desegregation. In their decision, which became known as &quot;''Brown II''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[wikisource:Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka (349 U.S. 294)|Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka]]'', {{Ussc|349|294|1955}}&lt;/ref&gt; the court delegated the task of carrying out school desegregation to district courts with orders that desegregation occur &quot;with all deliberate speed,&quot; a phrase traceable to [[Francis Thompson]]'s poem, [[Hound of Heaven|''The Hound of Heaven'']].&lt;ref&gt;Jim Chen, [http://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=778884 ''Poetic Justice''], 29 Cardozo Law Review (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of the earlier decision were displeased with this decision. The language “all deliberate speed” was seen by critics as too ambiguous to ensure reasonable haste for compliance with the court's instruction. Many Southern states and school districts interpreted &quot;Brown II&quot; as legal justification for resisting, delaying, and avoiding significant integration for years—and in some cases for a decade or more—using such tactics as closing down school systems, using state money to finance segregated &quot;private&quot; schools, and &quot;token&quot; integration where a few carefully selected black children were admitted to former white-only schools but the vast majority remained in underfunded, unequal black schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crmvet.org/tim/timhis55.htm#1955ads The &quot;Brown II,&quot; &quot;All Deliberate Speed&quot; Decision] ~ Civil Rights Movement Veterans&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, based on &quot;Brown II,&quot; the U.S. District Court ruled that [[Prince Edward County, Virginia]] did not have to desegregate immediately. When another court case in 1959 ruled that the county's schools finally had to desegregate, the county board of supervisors stopped appropriating money for public schools which remained closed for five years, from 1959 to 1964. White students in the county were given assistance to attend white-only &quot;private academies&quot; that were taught by teachers formerly employed by the public school system, while black students had no education at all unless they moved out of the county.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |last=Smith
  |first=Bob
  |title=They Closed Their Schools
  |publisher=University of North Carolina Press
  |year=1965}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Brown III ==
In 1978, Topeka attorneys Richard Jones, Joseph Johnson and Charles Scott Jr. (son of the original ''Brown'' team member), with assistance from the [[American Civil Liberties Union]], persuaded Linda Brown Smith—who now had her own children in Topeka schools—to be a plaintiff in reopening ''Brown''. They were concerned that the Topeka Public Schools' policy of &quot;open enrollment&quot; had led to and would lead to further segregation. They also believed that with a choice of open enrollment, white parents would shift their children to &quot;preferred&quot; schools that would create both predominantly African American and predominantly European American schools within the district. The district court reopened the ''Brown'' case after a 25-year hiatus, but denied the plaintiffs' request finding the schools &quot;unitary&quot;. In 1989, a three-judge panel of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit|10th Circuit]] on 2–1 vote found that the vestiges of segregation remained with respect to student and staff assignment. In 1993, the Supreme Court denied the appellant School District's request for ''[[certiorari]]'' and returned the case to District Court Judge Richard Rodgers for implementation of the Tenth Circuit's mandate.

After a 1994 plan was approved and a bond issue passed, additional elementary magnet schools were opened and district attendance plans redrawn, which resulted in the Topeka schools meeting court standards of racial balance by 1998. Unified status was eventually granted to Topeka Unified School District #501 on July 27, 1999. One of the new [[magnet schools]] is named after the Scott family attorneys for their role in the ''Brown'' case and civil rights.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www2.topeka.k12.ks.us/scott/history.htm ''Topeka Public Schools Desegregation History: &quot;The Naming of Scott Computer Technology Magnet&quot;'']&lt;/ref&gt;

== Related cases ==
* ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'', 163 U.S. 537 (1896)—separate but equal for schools
* ''[[Lum v. Rice]]'',  275 U.S. 78 (1927)-separate schools for Chinese pupils from white schoolchildren
* ''[[Powell v. Alabama]]'', 287 U.S. 45 (1932)—access to counsel
* ''[[Hernandez v. Texas]]'', 347 U.S. 475 (1954)—the Fourteenth Amendment protects those beyond the racial classes of white or Negro.
* ''[[Smith v. Allwright]]'', 321 U.S. 649 (1944)—non-white voters in primary elections
* ''[[Sipuel v. Board of Regents of Univ. of Okla.]]'', 332 U.S. 631 (1948)—access to taxpayer state funded law schools
* ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]'', 334 U.S. 1 (1948)—restrictive covenants
* ''[[Mendez v. Westminster]]'', 64 F. Supp. 544 (1946)—prohibits segregating Mexican American children in California
* ''[[Sweatt v. Painter]]'', 339 U.S. 629 (1950)—segregated law schools in Texas
* ''[[McLaurin v. Oklahoma State Regents]]'', 339 U.S. 637 (1950)—prohibits segregation in a public institution of higher learning
* ''[[Briggs v. Elliott]]'', 347 U.S. 483 (1952) '''''Brown'' Case #1'''—Summerton, South Carolina.
* ''[[Davis v. County School Board of Prince Edward County]]'', 103 F. Supp. 337 (1952) '''''Brown'' Case #2'''—Prince Edward County, Virginia.
* ''[[Gebhart v. Belton]]'', 33 Del. Ch. 144 (1952) '''''Brown'' Case #3'''—Claymont, Delaware
* ''[[Bolling v. Sharpe]]'', 347 U.S. 497 (1954) '''''Brown'' companion case'''—dealt with the constitutionality of segregation in the [[District of Columbia]], which—as a federal district, not a state—is not subject to the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].
* ''[[NAACP v. Alabama]]'', 357 U.S. 449 (1958)—privacy of NAACP membership lists, and free association of members
* ''[[Cooper v. Aaron]]'', 358 U.S. 1 (1958) – Federal court enforcement of desegregation
* ''[[Boynton v. Virginia]]'', 364 U.S. 454 (1960) — outlawed racial segregation in public transportation
* ''[[Heart of Atlanta Motel v. United States]]'', 379 U.S. 241 (1964)—held constitutional the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], which banned racial discrimination in public places, particularly in public accommodations even in private property.
* ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]'', 388 U.S. 1 (1967) — banned [[anti-miscegenation laws]] (race-based restrictions on marriage).
*''[[Alexander v. Holmes County Board of Education]]'', 396 U.S. 1218 (1969) – changed ''Brown'''s requirement of desegregation &quot;with all deliberate speed&quot; to one of &quot;desegregation now&quot;
* ''[[Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education]]'', 402 U.S. 1 (1971) — established bussing as a solution
* ''[[Guey Heung Lee v. Johnson]]'', 404 U.S 1215 (1971) – &quot;Brown v. Board of Education was not written for blacks alone&quot;, desegregation of Asian schools in opposition to parents of Asian students
* ''[[Milliken v. Bradley]]'', 418 U.S. 717 (1974) — rejected bussing across school district lines.
* ''[[Parents Involved in Community Schools v. Seattle School District No. 1]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=000&amp;invol=05-908 |title=FindLaw &amp;#124; Cases and Codes |publisher=Caselaw.lp.findlaw.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; 551 U.S. 701, 127 S. Ct. 2738 (2007)—rejected using race as the sole determining factor for assigning students to schools.&lt;ref&gt;For analysis of this decision, see also Joel K. Goldstein, [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1387162 &quot;Not Hearing History: A Critique of Chief Justice Roberts's Reinterpretation of ''Brown'',&quot;] 69 Ohio St. L.J. 791 (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[List of United States Supreme Court cases|List of United States Supreme Court Cases]]

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; See [[Case citation]] for an explanation of these numbers.

== Common misconceptions ==
* The most common misconception about ''Brown v. Board of Education'' is that the case is solely about Linda Brown and whether she should or should not be able to attend the school nearest her home. In fact, ''Brown'' was a consolidation of five different cases, from four states, all of which dealt with the same issue. (A similar case from the District of Columbia was handled separately.) Linda Brown was merely the &quot;poster child,&quot; as it were, for some 200 plaintiffs altogether. A dozen attorneys and countless community activists were involved in effort to eliminate &quot;de jure&quot; racial segregation in the public schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://brownvboard.org/summary/ Background Summary] at brownvboard.org. Retrieved 18 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The second most common misconception is that the case talks about the hardship that affected Linda Brown because she was not able to attend her local school, because it was for white children only. In fact, the case discusses the hardships collectively faced by all of the children concerned. It also focuses a lot of attention on the psychological well-being of the children in reference to the segregation of schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lva.lib.va.us/whoweare/exhibits/brown/whatwas.htm What Was Brown v. Board of Education?], an exhibition at the Library of Virginia. Retrieved 27 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* It is sometimes thought that Oliver Brown was the named plaintiff in the consolidated cases because he was alphabetically first in the list. In fact Darlene Brown, another plaintiff, (no relation to Oliver Brown) would have been the named plaintiff if that had actually been the case.
* It is also frequently thought that ''Brown'' was the first legal challenge to racially segregated schools in the United States. In fact, it was the eleventh case to challenge the 1879 Kansas law, and the third case from Topeka.&lt;ref&gt;[http://brownvboard.org/content/court-cases-prelude-brown-1849-1949 Timeline] at brownvboard.org. Retrieved 27 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Timeline of the African American Civil Rights Movement]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
*{{Cite book |first=Richard |last=Kluger |title=Simple Justice: The History of Brown v. Board of Education and Black America's Struggle for Equality |year=1975 |location=New York |publisher=Knopf |isbn=0394472896 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}
*{{Cite document |authorlink=Gunnar Myrdal |first=Gunnar |last=Myrdal |title=[[An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy]] |year=1944 |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |location=New York |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}
*{{Cite book |first=Charles J., Jr. |last=Ogletree |title=All Deliberate Speed: Reflections on the First Half Century of Brown v. Board of Education |location=New York |publisher=W.W. Norton |year=2004  |isbn=0393058972 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}
*{{Cite book |first=James T. |last=Patterson |authorlink=James T. Patterson (historian)|title=Brown v. Board of Education: A Civil Rights Milestone and Its Troubled Legacy |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |year=2001 |isbn=0195156323}}
*{{Cite book |title=I dissent: Great Opposing Opinions in Landmark Supreme Court Cases |last=Tushnet |first=Mark |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2008 |publisher=Beacon Press |location=Boston |isbn=9780807000366 |pages=133–150 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}
* [[UNESCO]], ''[[The Race Question]]'' (1950)

== External links ==
{{wikisource}}
* [http://www.lawnix.com/cases/brown-board-education.html Case Brief for Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka at Lawnix.com]
* [http://curiae.law.yale.edu/search/casedetail?casecitation=347+U.S.+483 Case information and transcripts on The Curiae Project]
* [http://www.nps.gov/brvb/ Brown v. Board of Education National Historic Site] (US Park Service)
* [http://laws.findlaw.com/us/347/483.html Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, 347 U.S. 483 (1954)] (full text with hyperlinks to cited material)
* [http://www.floridamemory.com/FloridaHighlights/collins/ A copy of Florida's 1957 Interposition Resolution in Response to the Brown decision, with Gov. Collin's handwritten rejection of it.] Made available for public use by the State Archives of Florida.
*[http://eisenhower.archives.gov/Research/Finding_Aids/U.html U.S. District Court of Kansas: Records of Browns v. Board of Education, Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library]
*[http://eisenhower.archives.gov/Research/Digital_Documents/Civil_Rights_BrownvsBoE/BrownvsBOEfiles.html Documents relating to Brown vs. Board of Education at the Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library]
* [http://www.clearinghouse.net/detail.php?id=5479 Documents from the district court, including the original complaint and trial transcript, at the Civil Rights Litigation Clearinghouse]
{{African-American Civil Rights Movement|state=uncollapsed}}
{{AAUS}}
{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Brown V. Board Of Education}}
[[Category:1954 in United States case law]]
[[Category:Education in Kansas]]
[[Category:History of education in the United States]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1945–1964)]]
[[Category:Lawsuits]]
[[Category:Legal history of Kansas]]
[[Category:Presidency of Dwight D. Eisenhower]]
[[Category:School segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:United States equal protection case law]]
[[Category:United States school desegregation case law]]
[[Category:United States Supreme Court cases]]
[[Category:1954 in Kansas]]

{{Link FA|de}}
{{Link FA|zh}}

[[cs:Brown v. školní rada Topeky]]
[[de:Brown v. Board of Education]]
[[es:Brown v. Board of Education]]
[[fa:براون در برابر هیئت آموزش]]
[[fr:Brown v. Board of Education]]
[[ko:브라운 대 토피카 교육위원회 재판]]
[[it:Brown c/ Board of Education]]
[[he:פסק דין בראון נגד מועצת החינוך]]
[[nl:Brown vs. Board of Education]]
[[ja:ブラウン対教育委員会裁判]]
[[no:Brown mot skolestyret]]
[[ru:Браун против Совета по образованию]]
[[simple:Brown v. Board of Education]]
[[sr:Браун против Одбора за образовање Топике]]
[[fi:Brown vastaan Topekan koululautakunta]]
[[sv:Brown mot skolstyrelsen]]
[[zh-yue:布朗裁決]]
[[zh:布朗訴托皮卡教育局案]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
