<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="670532" ns="0" title="University of Cape Town"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{hatnote|&quot;UCT&quot; redirects here. UCT may also be a misabbreviation for [[Coordinated Universal Time]].}}
{{Infobox University
|name            = University of Cape Town
|image_name      = University of Cape Town coat of arms.png
|image_size      = 150px
|image_alt       = Coat of arms of the University of Cape Town
|motto           = Spes Bona
|mottoeng        = Good Hope
|established     = 1st October 1829
|type            = [[Public university|Public]]
|endowment       = [[South African rand|R]]2,173.4 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Annual Report for the year ended 31 December 2009 |publisher=University of Cape Town |url=http://www.uct.ac.za/usr/finance/afs/afs2009.pdf |accessdate=17 September 2010 |page=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;small&gt;([[United States dollar|US$]]300 million {{as of|2010|lc=on}})&lt;/small&gt;
|chancellor      = [[Graça Machel]]
|vice_chancellor = Dr [[Max Price]]
|academic_staff   = 1,980
|administrative_staff = 2,520
|students        = 23,500
|undergrad       = 15,800
|postgrad        = 6,700
|city            = [[Cape Town]]
|province        = [[Western Cape]]
|country         = South Africa
|coor            = {{coord|33|57|27|S|18|27|38|E|display=inline,title|region:ZA_type:edu}}
|campus          = 4 [[suburb]]an and 2 [[urban area|urban]] campuses
|former_names    = [[South African College]]
|colours         = [[light blue (color)|Light blue]], [[Dark blue (color)|Dark blue]] and [[White]] {{color box|#ADD8E6}}&amp;nbsp;{{color box|#00285C}}&amp;nbsp;{{color box|#FFFFFF}}
|nickname        = Ikeys
|mascot          = Tiger
|affiliations    = [[Association of African Universities|AAU]], [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]], [[Cape Higher Education Consortium|CHEC]], [[Higher Education South Africa|HESA]], [[International Association of Universities|IAU]], [[Worldwide Universities Network|WUN]]
|website         = [http://www.uct.ac.za/ www.uct.ac.za]
| logo  = [[Image:UCT banner.png|248px|University of Cape Town logo]]
}}
The '''University of Cape Town''' ('''UCT''') is a [[public university|public]] [[research university]] located in [[Cape Town]] in the [[Western Cape]] province of South Africa. UCT was founded in 1829 as the [[South African College]], and is the oldest university in South Africa and the [[List of oldest universities in continuous operation|second oldest extant university in Africa]].

==History==
[[File:University of Cape Town 1930.jpg|thumb|left|250px|University of Cape Town's Groote Schuur campus in 1930]]
The roots of UCT lie in the establishment of the [[South African College]] in 1829 as a school for boys. In 1874 the [[South African College Schools]], teaching up to secondary level, were separated from the College, which prepared students for the examinations of the [[University of the Cape of Good Hope]]. In 1918 the South African College was elevated to full university status with the power to award degrees, and renamed the University of Cape Town.

UCT moved to the [[Groote Schuur]] Estate campus in 1928. During the [[apartheid]] era, roughly 1960-1990, many UCT students consistently opposed apartheid, and the university was a bastion of liberalism. However, the demographics of the university did not begin to change meaningfully until the 1980s and especially the 1990s. 1987 saw frequent clashes between protesting students and police, with reporting of police presence on the campus being censored by the government. On 24 April 1987 the police entered the campus and this marked the first time since 1972 that South Africa's police services had suppressed a demonstration at a white university.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cape Times report&quot;&gt;Cape Times, staff reporter, front page, Saturday, 25 April 1987. &quot;Large parts of the University of Cape Town campus were at times uninhabitable yesterday afternoon and some lectures were disrupted as a result of actions by certain people which may not be reported in terms of state-of-emergency press censorship. South African Breweries suffered a R120 000 loss when a cab of one of their vehicles was burnt on the upper campus in the wake of a students’ protest march over the deaths of six railway workers and the dismissal of 16 000 others. The government’s Interdepartmental Press Liaison Centre, last night refused the Cape Times permission to publish the full facts concerning the day’s events at UCT. They also refused the newspaper permission to publish three photographs taken during the afternoon, including one of the burnt out vehicle. A four hour confrontation between the people who may not be identified and about 150 – 200 students followed a lunch time meeting attended by about 700 students, called to protest at the deaths and firing of SA Railway’s and Harbour’s Workers Union (SARHWU) on Wednesday.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; 

The UCT crest was designed in 1859 by [[Charles Davidson Bell]], Surveyor-General of the Cape Colony at the time. Bell was an accomplished artist who also designed medals and the triangular Cape stamp.

==Campus==
[[Image:UCT Upper Campus landscape view.jpg|left|thumb|A view of UCT]]
The main teaching campus, known as the Upper Campus, is located on the [[Cecil Rhodes|Rhodes]] Estate on the slopes of [[Devil's Peak (Cape Town)|Devil's Peak]]. This campus contains, in a relatively compact site, the faculties of [[Science]], [[Engineering]], [[Commerce]], and [[Humanities]] (except for the arts departments), as well as [[Smuts Hall]] and Fuller Hall [[Dormitory|residences]]. Upper Campus is centered on Jameson Hall, the location for graduation and other ceremonial events, as well as many examinations. The original buildings and layout of Upper Campus were designed by [[JM Solomon]] and built between 1928 and 1930. Since that time, many more buildings have been added as the university has grown. Upper Campus is also home to the main library, The Chancellor Oppenheimer library which holds the majority of the University's 1.3 million volume collection.

Contiguous with Upper Campus, but separated from it by university sports fields and the [[M3 road (Cape Town)|M3 expressway]], are the Middle and Lower Campuses. These campuses, which are spread through the suburbs of [[Rondebosch, Cape Town|Rondebosch]], [[Rosebank, Cape Town|Rosebank]] and [[Mowbray, Cape Town|Mowbray]], contain the [[Law]] faculty, the [[South African College of Music]], most of the student residences, most of the university administrative offices, and various sporting facilities. The state of the art artificial grass [[soccer]] field has been approved by FIFA for training for [[2010 FIFA World Cup|World Cup]] teams.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uct.ac.za/dailynews/?id=7052&lt;/ref&gt; The Upper, Middle and Lower Campuses together are often referred to as the &quot;main campus&quot;.

The Faculty of [[Health Sciences]] is located on the [[Medical School]] campus next to the [[Groote Schuur Hospital]] in [[Observatory, Cape Town|Observatory]]. The [[Michaelis School of Fine Art|Fine Arts]] and [[Drama]] departments are located on the Hiddingh Campus in central [[Cape Town]]. The University's original building, now known as the ''Egyptian Building'', on the Hiddingh campus, was built in the [[Egyptian Revival]] style. The only other campus built in this style was the [[Medical College of Virginia]] in [[Richmond, Virginia]] in the United States. The [http://www.gsb.uct.ac.za UCT Graduate School of Business] is located on the [[Breakwater Lodge]] Campus at the [[Victoria &amp; Alfred Waterfront]].
[[Image:Uct-rag-concert-at-kirstenbosch-gardens-001.jpg|right|thumb|Hiddingh Hall Library on Hiddingh campus in Gardens Cape Town]]

==Organisation==
[[Image:UCT Jammie Plaza.jpg|thumb|Jameson Hall and Jammie Plaza, the focal point of the upper campus]]
The organisation of the University is defined in the Statute of the University of Cape Town, in accordance with the ''[[Higher Education Act, 1997]]''. Before 2002, it was defined by a [[private act|private Act of Parliament]].

The titular head of the University is the [[Chancellor (education)|Chancellor]]; this is a ceremonial position without executive power. The primary role of the Chancellor is to confer degrees on behalf of the University, and to represent the University to the rest of the world. The current Chancellor is Ms [[Graça Machel]], elected for her first 10-year term in September 1999 and re-elected in May 2010.

The executive head of the University is the [[Vice-Chancellor]] (or VC). The VC has the overall responsibility for the policy and administration of the University. The current VC is Dr [[Max Price]], who replaced Professor [[Njabulo Ndebele]] on 1 July 2008. The VC is assisted in his task by a number of [[Deputy Vice-Chancellor]]s (DVCs) who handle specific portfolios. The [[Registrar (academic)|Registrar]] is responsible for the academic administration of the University, as well as legal matters, and is secretary to the University Council and Senate.

[[Image:UCT Kramer Law School.jpg|left|thumb|The Kramer Building, home of the Law Faculty]]
The academic departments of UCT are divided into six faculties: [[Commerce]], [[Engineering]] and the [[Built Environment]], [[Health Sciences]], [[Humanities]], [[Law]], and [[Science]]; each faculty is led by a Dean. The multidisciplinary Center for Higher Education Development rates on a level equal to the faculties. Although the Graduate School of Business is considered to be part of the Faculty of [[Commerce]], it is run independently and has its own Dean and Director.

==Students and staff==
[[Image:UCT Tugwell and Marquard.jpg|thumb|Tugwell and Marquard residence halls]]
{{As of|2009}}, 23,500 students were enrolled, of which 6,700 (28,5%) were [[postgraduate]] students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.uct.ac.za/about/intro/statistics/ |title=Introducing UCT: Statistics |work=About the University |publisher=University of Cape Town |accessdate=8 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ratio between male and female students is almost exactly 50:50. Over 50% of the student body is non-white. International students account for 19% of total student enrollment at 4300, representing over 100 countries. 

UCT employs approximately 4500 staff members of whom 44% are academic staff; the rest are administrative and support staff. In 2007 UCT had 866 permanent academic staff members. Between 85% and 90% of academic staff hold doctoral or masters qualifications.

==Student life==
UCT has 36 different sports clubs, including [[team sport]]s, [[individual sport]]s, [[extreme sport]]s and [[martial arts]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sportsclubs.uct.ac.za/clubs.html |title=Current Sports Clubs at UCT |accessdate=2007-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university's sports teams, and in particular the [[rugby union]] team, are known as the &quot;[[Ikey Tigers]]&quot; or the &quot;Ikeys&quot;. The &quot;Ikey&quot; nickname originated in the 1910s as an [[anti-semitism|anti-semitic]] epithet applied to UCT students by the students of [[Stellenbosch University]], because of the supposed large number of Jewish students at UCT.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Swanson |first=Felicity |editor=Field, Sean, et al. |title=Imagining the City: Memories and Cultures in Cape Town |url=http://www.hsrcpress.ac.za/full_title_info.asp?id=2193 |format=PDF |accessdate=2007-06-08 |year=2007 |publisher=HSRC Press |location=Cape Town |isbn=0-7969-2179-2 |page=210 |chapter=‘Die SACS kom terug’: intervarsity rugby, masculinity and white identity at the University of Cape Town, 1960s-1970s |chapterurl=http://www.hsrcpress.ac.za/download.asp?filename=013%20-%2011_Imagining_the_City~216200731940PM.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stellenbosch is UCT's traditional rugby opponent; an annual &quot;Intervarsity&quot; match is played between  the two universities.

There are more than 80 student societies at UCT; these fall generally into five categories:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.uct.ac.za/students/societies/societies/ |title=Student Affairs: Societies |accessdate=2007-06-08 |publisher=University of Cape Town |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070603191341/http://www.uct.ac.za/students/societies/societies/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Academic societies for those interested in a particular field of study or studying a particular topic: The most prominent of these include the History and Current Affairs Society (HCA), United Nations Association of South Africa (UNASA) and Students for Law and Social Justice (SLSJ).
* Political societies, including branches of the youth wings of national political parties such as the South African Students Congress (SASCO), the Democratic Alliance Students Organisation (DASO), and the African National Congress Youth League.
* Religious societies, some of which are associated with religious denominations or local places of worship.
* National/cultural societies for students from particular countries or particular ethnic backgrounds.
* Special interest societies (such as RainbowUCT, the universities LGBTI society) for those interested in various activities or issues.

In addition to the plethora of student societies, there are several student organisations dedicated to the development of communities surrounding the University in the Cape Metropolitan Area. Some of the biggest include: [[SHAWCO]], Ubunye and RAG.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.uct.ac.za/students/services/community/SHAWCO/ |title=Student Community Service: SHAWCO |accessdate=2010-03-01 |publisher=University of Cape Town}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, several students movements have developed, such as the [[Green Campus Initiative (UCT)|Green Campus Initiative]].

[[Image:Uct-rag-concert-at-kirstenbosch-gardens-032.jpg|left|thumb|Walking on University Avenue north on upper campus]]

==Rankings==
{{see also|Rankings of universities in South Africa|Rankings of business schools in South Africa}}
The University of Cape Town is the highest ranked African university in the [[QS World University Rankings]], the [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]], and the [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]]. It achieved a rank of 156 in the 2011 [[QS World University Rankings]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011?page=3&lt;/ref&gt; and a rank of 103 in the 2011 [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2011-2012/top-400.html |title=Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2011–2012 |accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; making it the only African university in the top 200. Within this same ranking UCT was placed in the top 50 in the categories of life sciences and social sciences.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.topuniversities.com/university/98/university-of-cape-town&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2009/results/101-200&lt;/ref&gt; UCT's [[Master of Business Administration|MBA]] programme was globally ranked at 60 in 2011 by the [[Financial Times]], and was ranked first in the &quot;value for money&quot; category.&lt;ref&gt;http://rankings.ft.com/businessschoolrankings/university-of-cape-town/global-mba-rankings-2011#global-mba-rankings-2011&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to this, The University of Cape Town was placed as the second best business school in Africa and the Middle East in the 2010 [[QS Global 200 Business Schools Report]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.topmba.com/mba-rankings/top-business-schools-report-2010/regions/top-business-schools-in-africa-and-middle-east&lt;/ref&gt;  The University also achieved a rank of 141 - 145 in the Russian based Global Universities Ranking&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globaluniversitiesranking.org/|title=Global Universities Ranking 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Affiliations==
UCT is a member of the [[Worldwide Universities Network]], the [[Association of African Universities]], the [[Association of Commonwealth Universities]], the [[Cape Higher Education Consortium]], [[Higher Education South Africa]], and the [[International Association of Universities]].

==Notable alumni==
[[File:J.M. Coetzee.JPG|right|thumb|150px|[[J. M. Coetzee]], twice awarded the [[Booker Prize]] and awarded the 2003 [[Nobel Prize in Literature]], did his undergraduate studies in Mathematics and got a Master of Arts degree from the University of Cape Town.]]
{{main|List of Notable Alumni of the University of Cape Town }}
Five of the University's graduates have become [[Nobel Prize|Nobel]] Laureates:

*[[Ralph Bunche]], American political scientist and diplomat awarded the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] in 1950 for his role in the [[1949 Armistice Agreements]].
*[[Max Theiler]], virologist awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine]] in 1951 for developing a vaccine against [[yellow fever]].
*Professor [[Allan McLeod Cormack]] ([[Nobel Prize in Medicine|Medicine]], 1979)
*Sir [[Aaron Klug]] ([[Nobel Prize in Chemistry|Chemistry]], 1982)
*Professor Emeritus [[J. M. Coetzee]] ([[Nobel Prize in Literature|Literature]], 2003)

==Notable staff==
*Cosmologist [[George Francis Rayner Ellis|George Ellis]], collaborator with [[Stephen Hawking]] and winner of the 2004 [[Templeton Prize]], Distinguished Professor of Complex Systems in the Department of Mathematics and Applied Mathematics.
*Author [[Andre Brink]], professor in the English Language and Literature Department.
*Author [[Breyten Breytenbach]], visiting professor in the Graduate School of Humanities from January 2000.
*Professor [[David H. M. Brooks]] (1950–1996), author of ''On living in an Unjust Society'' and ''The Unity of the Mind''.
*[[Helen Zille]], former [[Mayor of Cape Town]] and current [[Premier of the Western Cape]], former Director of [[Public Relations]] for the university.

==Notable research==
*Africa Earth Observatory Network [(AEON)] http://www.aeon.uct.ac.za, an Earth Science initiative aiming to promote Earth Stewardship through science, with partners in Germany and France.
*The Department of [[Mathematics]] and [[Applied Mathematics]] is an international centre for research in the fields of [[physical cosmology|cosmology]] and [[topology]].
*The Centre for Rhetoric Studies, the only one of its kind on the African Continent (director: [[Philippe-Joseph Salazar]]).
*The Department of [[Physics]] is home to the UCT-[[CERN]] research centre, which is partially responsible for the software design of the High Level Trigger component of the [[A Large Ion Collider Experiment|ALICE]] experiment at the [[Large Hadron Collider]], as well as other activities related to ALICE.
*The Department of [[Electrical Engineering]] is involved in the development of technology for the [[Karoo Array Telescope]] (KAT). KAT is a precursor to the [[Square Kilometer Array]], a proposed International project to build the world's largest radio telescope by 2020. Research groups in [[Radio frequency|RF]] design and [[digital]] design contribute to the RF front-end and digital back-end of the KAT project.
* The Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine [(IIDMM)] http://www.uct.ac.za/depts/iidmm is engaged in research on candidate tuberculosis vaccines, and is developing candidate HIV vaccines matched to the South African epidemic.
*The MRC/UCT Medical Imaging Research Unit [(MIRU)] http://www.miru.uct.ac.za, inspired by the work of alumnus [[Allan McLeod Cormack]] who won a Nobel Prize for the [[X-ray computed tomography|CAT-scanner]], studies brain and cardiac function and develops diagnostic imaging tools, one of which has led to the spinout of [[CapeRay]].

==See also==
* [[Centre for Curating the Archive]]
* [[List of universities in South Africa]]
* [[Education in South Africa]]
* [[Chancellor of the University of Cape Town]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
*[http://www.info.gov.za/view/DownloadFileAction?id=65297 Statute of the University of Cape Town], Government Notice No. 1199, 20 September 2002.

==External links==
*[http://www.uct.ac.za/ UCT website]
*[http://www.sarua.org/?q=uni_University+of+Cape+Town Southern African University]
*[http://opencontent.uct.ac.za/ UCT OpenContent - Open Educational Resource website]
{{University of Cape Town navbox|state=uncollapsed}}
{{South African universities}}
{{FNB Varsity Cup}}
{{Worldwide Universities Network|Cape Town, University of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cape Town, University of}}
[[Category:University of Cape Town| ]]
[[Category:Universities in the Western Cape]]
[[Category:Education in Cape Town|University of Cape Town]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1829]]
[[Category:Public universities in South Africa]]
[[Category:Association of Commonwealth Universities]]

[[af:Universiteit van Kaapstad]]
[[ar:جامعة كيب تاون]]
[[de:Universität Kapstadt]]
[[fa:دانشگاه کیپ‌تاون]]
[[fr:Université du Cap]]
[[it:Università di Città del Capo]]
[[sw:Chuo Kikuu cha Cape Town]]
[[lv:Keiptaunas universitāte]]
[[nl:Universiteit van Kaapstad]]
[[ja:ケープタウン大学]]
[[no:Universitetet i Cape Town]]
[[pl:Uniwersytet Kapsztadzki]]
[[pt:Universidade da Cidade do Cabo]]
[[ru:Кейптаунский университет]]
[[fi:Kapkaupungin yliopisto]]
[[ve:Yunivesithi ya Cape Town]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
