<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="671747" ns="0" title="Norwegians"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Ethnic group|
|group=Norwegians&lt;br&gt;''Nordmenn''
|image=&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top:1px; margin-bottom:1px;&quot;&gt;[[Image:Norwegians (ethnicgroup)b.png|250px]]
|caption=&lt;small&gt;[[St. Olaf]] {{•}} [[Peder Tordenskjold|P. Tordenskjold]] {{•}} [[Niels Henrik Abel|N. H. Abel]] {{•}} [[Frederik Stang|F. Stang]] &lt;br&gt;[[Henrik Ibsen|H. Ibsen]] {{•}} [[Edvard Grieg|E. Grieg]] {{•}} [[Fridtjof Nansen|F. Nansen]] {{•}} [[Edvard Munch|E. Munch]] &lt;br&gt;[[Roald Amundsen|R. Amundsen]] {{•}} [[Eivind Groven|E. Groven]] {{•}} [[Liv Ullmann|L. Ullmann]] {{•}} [[Ole Gunnar Solskjær|O. G. Solskjær]] &lt;br&gt;[[Princess Märtha Louise of Norway|Pr. Märtha]] {{•}} [[Mette-Marit, Crown Princess of Norway|Pr. Mette-Marit]] {{•}} [[Siv Jensen|S. Jensen]] {{•}} [[Lisa-Mari Moen Jünge|L-M. M. Jünge]] &lt;/small&gt;
|poptime='''12 million'''{{smallsup|a}}{{citation needed|date=September 2011}}&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(0.17% of the world's population)&amp;nbsp;{{smallsup|a}}&lt;/div&gt;
|popplace={{flagcountry|Norway}}{{Ref label|aaa|a}}:4,305,886&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Without immigrant background&quot; : Population 1.1.2010 (4 305 886 [http://www.ssb.no/innvbef_en/tab-2010-04-29-06-en.html])&lt;/ref&gt;
|region1 ={{flagcountry|United States}}
|pop1     = 4,712,232 &lt;ref&gt;The [http://www.euroamericans.net/norwegian.htm# 2000 American census] reports that the United States, in the 2000 census, has 4,477,725 inhabitants of (partial) Norwegian ancestry.&lt;/ref&gt;
|region2  = {{flagcountry|Canada}}{{Ref label|aaa|a}}
|pop2     = 521,390&lt;ref&gt;[http://www12.statcan.ca/english/census06/data/highlights/ethnic/pages/Page.cfm?Lang=E&amp;Geo=PR&amp;Code=01&amp;Data=Count&amp;Table=2&amp;StartRec=1&amp;Sort=3&amp;Display=All&amp;CSDFilter=5000 Shows a list over Canadas different ethnic groups, reports that there is 363,760 persons reporting Norwegian as one ancestry in Canada, of these 44,790 reported only Norwegian].&lt;/ref&gt;
|region3  = {{flagcountry|Brazil}}{{Ref label|aaa|a}}
|pop3     = 465,441&lt;ref&gt;The [http://www.ibge.com.br/norwegian.htm# 2000 Brazilian census] reports that Brazil, in the 2000 census, has 465,44 inhabitants of (partial) Norwegian ancestry.&lt;/ref&gt;
|region4  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}{{Ref label|aaa|a}}{{Ref label|bbb|b}}
|pop4     =13,798&lt;ref name=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Number of Norwegians registered at the Embassy for living in each of these countries.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
''also circa 42,000 [[Orcadians]] and [[Shetlanders]]''
|region5  = {{flagcountry|Sweden}}{{Ref label|aaa|a}}
|pop5     = 48,385&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scb.se/statistik/_publikationer/BE0101_2005A01_BR_BE0106TAB.pdf Swedish Statistics from 2005. Shows the official number of Norwegians in Sweden at page 20.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.migrationinformation.org/datahub/countrydata/data.cfm Sweden: Stock of foreign-born population by country of birth, by year]&lt;/ref&gt;
|region6  ={{flagcountry|Australia}}
|pop6     = 32,850&lt;ref&gt;[http://elecpress.monash.edu.au/pnp/free/pnpv7n4/v7n4_3price.pdf Swedish Statistics from 2005. Shows the official number of Norwegians in Sweden at page 20.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.migrationinformation.org/datahub/countrydata/data.cfm Australian: Stock of foreign-born population by country of birth, by year]&lt;/ref&gt; 
|langs=[[Norwegian language|Norwegian]]&lt;br&gt;
Closely related (mutually intelligible) languages include [[Danish language|Danish]] and [[Swedish language|Swedish]]. Other related languages include [[Faroese language|Faroese]] and [[Icelandic Language|Icelandic]], and to a lesser extent, all [[Germanic languages]].&lt;br&gt;
[[Norwegian American]]s: Historically [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]], but later [[English language|English]] because of [[Americanization (immigration)|Americanization]].
|rels=[[Norse paganism]] (-900)&lt;br&gt;[[Catholic Christianity]] (1000-1500)&lt;br&gt;[[Lutheran Christianity]](1600-)&lt;ref&gt;83% of the population of Norway are members of the Christian Evangelical Lutheran [[Church of Norway]]. Norway is highly secularized, and only about 10% of the population attend religious services more than once a month. The Norwegians in Norway are more secular than the Norwegians in the United States. North Dakota has the lowest percentage of non-religious people of any state, and it also has the most churches [[per capita]] of any state, which is a state were 30.4 % of the population is Norwegian.&lt;/ref&gt;
| related=[[Faroese people|Faroese]], [[Icelanders]], [[Germans]]/[[Austrians]],&lt;ref name=&quot;hpgl.stanford.edu&quot;/&gt; [[Danes]], [[Dutch people|Dutch]], [[Swedes]], [[Shetland]]ers, [[Orcadians]], [[Scottish people|Scots]], [[English people|English]], [[Normans]] &lt;br&gt;Other [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] ethnic groups
| footnotes = 

a. {{note|aaa}} Does not include people of [[Faroese people|Faroese]], [[Icelandic people|Icelandic]], [[Orcadians|Orcadian]] or [[Shetlanders|Shetlandic]] ancestry. Does include persons with partial Norwegian ancestry.
b. {{note|bbb}} Note that there are millions of [[British people|Britons]] of [[Scandinavia]]n ancestry and ethnicity, though mixed with others.
|}}
{{Norwegian-people}}
'''Norwegians''' ({{lang-no|nordmenn}}) constitute both a nation and an [[ethnic group]] native to [[Norway]]. They share a common culture and speak the [[Norwegian language]]. Norwegian people and their [[Norwegian diaspora|descendants]] are found in migrant communities worldwide, notably in [[Norwegian American|United States]], [[Norwegian Canadian|Canada]] and [[Brazil]].

==History==
{{Main|History of Norway|Germanic peoples|History of Scandinavia}}
Towards the end of the 3rd millennium BC, [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European speaking]] [[Battle-Axe culture|Battle-Axe peoples]] migrated to Norway bringing [[Horse|domesticated horses]], [[agriculture]], [[cattle]] and [[wheel|wheel technology]] to the region. 

During the [[Viking age]], [[Harald I of Norway|Harald Fairhair]] [[Unification of Norway|unified]] the [[Norsemen|Norse]] [[petty kingdom]]s  after being victorious at the [[Battle of Hafrsfjord|The Battle of Hafrsfjord]] in the 880s. Two centuries of [[Viking expansion]] tapered off following the decline of [[Norse paganism]] with [[Christianization of Scandinavia|the adoption of Christianity]] in the 11th century. During [[Black Death|The Black Death]], approximately 60% of the population died and in 1397 Norway entered a [[Denmark–Norway|union]] with [[Denmark]]. 

In 1814, following Denmark-Norway's defeat in the [[Napoleonic Wars]], Norway entered a [[Union between Sweden and Norway|union]] with [[Sweden]] and adopted a [[Constitution of Norway|new constitution]]. [[Norwegian romantic nationalism|Rising nationalism]] throughout the 19th century led to a [[Norwegian union dissolution referendum, 1905|1905 referendum]] granting [[Dissolution of the union between Norway and Sweden in 1905|Norway independence]]. Although [[History of Norway#Norway in World War I|Norway remained officially neutral]] in [[World War I]], the country was [[The Neutral Ally|unofficially allied]] with the [[Entente powers]]. In [[World War II]] Norway proclaimed it's neutrality, but was nonetheless [[Occupation of Norway by Nazi Germany|occupied for five years]] by [[Nazi Germany]] (1940–45). In 1949, neutrality was abandoned and Norway became a member of [[NATO]]. [[Energy in Norway|Discovery of oil and gas]] in adjacent waters in the late 1960s boosted [[Economy of Norway|Norway's economic fortunes]] but in referenda held in [[Norwegian European Communities membership referendum, 1972|1972]] and [[Norwegian European Union membership referendum, 1994|1994]], Norway rejected joining the [[EU]]. Key domestic issues include [[Immigration to Norway|integration of a fast growing immigrant population]], maintaining the country's generous social safety net with an [[Ageing of Europe|aging population]], and preserving economic competitiveness.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/no.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geographic distribution==
{{Main|Norwegian diaspora}}
As with many of the people from European countries, Norwegians are spread throughout the world. There are more than 100,000 Norwegian citizens living abroad permanently, mostly in the U.S.A., U.K., and other [[Scandinavian countries]].

Once one forgoes his or her Norwegian citizenship, he or she ceases to be Norwegian. Despite this, some people choose to continue see themselves as having ethnic or cultural ties to Norway; as such, they may include the word &quot;Norwegian&quot; in their description for themselves (for example, in the United States, [[Norwegian-Americans]]).

===Viking Age===
{{Main|Norsemen|Viking Age|Vikings|Viking expansion|Varangians}}
Norwegian Vikings travelled north and west and founded vibrant communities in the [[Faroe Islands]], [[Shetland]], [[Orkney]], [[Iceland]], [[Ireland]], [[Scotland]], and northern [[England]]{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}. They conducted extensive raids in Ireland and founded the cities of [[Cork (city)|Cork]], [[Dublin]], and [[Limerick]]{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}. In 947, a new wave of Norwegian Vikings appeared in England when [[Erik Bloodaxe]] captured [[York]].

Apart from Britain and Ireland, Norwegian Vikings established settlements in largely uninhabited regions{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}. The first known permanent Norwegian settler in Iceland was [[Ingólfur Arnarson]]. In the year 874 he settled in [[Reykjavík]].

After his expulsion from Iceland [[Erik the Red]] discovered Greenland, a name he chose in hope of attracting Icelandic settlers{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}. Viking settlements were established in the sheltered fjords of the southern and western coast{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}. Erik's relative [[Leif Eriksson]] later discovered [[North America]].

===The Netherlands===
During the 17th and 18th centuries, many Norwegians emigrated to the Netherlands, particularly Amsterdam. This emigration is regarded as the second of the waves of emigration from Norway (the first being the trek to the England, Atlantic islands, Normandy, etc. during the Viking age, and the third was to North America, not counting the Gothic emigrations to Continental Europe in the 2nd and 3rd centuries A.D.). Loosely estimated, some 10% of the population may have emigrated, in a period when the entire Norwegian population consisted of some 800,000 people.

The Norwegians left with the Dutch trade ships that when in Norway traded for timber, hides, herring and [[stockfish]] (dried codfish). Young women took employment as maids in Amsterdam. Young men took employment as sailors. Large parts of the Dutch merchant fleet and navy came to consist of Norwegians and Danes. They took Dutch names, so no trace of Norwegian names can be found in the Dutch population of today. One well-known illustration is that of Admiral Kruys. He was hired in Amsterdam by Peter I to develop the Russian navy, but was originally from [[Stavanger]], Norway (Kruys means &quot;cross&quot;, and the Russian maritime flag is today also a blue cross on white background).

The emigration to the Netherlands was so devastating to the homelands that the Danish-Norwegian king issued penalties of death for emigration, but repeatedly had to issue amnesties for those willing to return, announced by posters in the streets of Amsterdam. Increasingly, Dutchmen who search their genealogical roots turn to Norway. Many Norwegians who emigrated to the Netherlands, and often were employed in the Dutch merchant fleet, emigrated further to the many Dutch colonies such as New Amsterdam (New York).

===United States===
{{Main|Norwegian American|Icelandic American}}
[[Image:Norwegians-in-NorthAmerica -.png|thumb|left|A map of [[North America]], with the percentage of [[Canadians|Canada]] and [[United America|Americans]] of Norwegian descent in each Canadian province and territory and U.S. state and Washington, D.C., respectively]]
Many Norwegians emigrated to the U.S.A. between the 1850s and the 1920s. Today, the descendants of these people are known as Norwegian Americans. According to the 2000 U.S. Census, three million Americans consider Norwegian to be their sole or primary ancestry. It is estimated that as many as a further 1.5 million more are of partial Norwegian ancestry.
Travelling to and through Canada and Canadian ports were of choice for Norwegian settlers immigrating to the United States. In 1850, the year after Great Britain repealed its restrictive Navigation Acts in Canada, more and more emigrating Norwegians sailed the shorter route to the Ville de Québec (Quebec City) in Canada, to make their way on to USA cities like Chicago, Milwaukee, and Green Bay by steamer. For example, in the 1850s, 28,640 arrived at Quebec, Canada, en route to the USA, and 8,351 at New York directly.

Norwegian Americans represent 2-3% of the non-Hispanic [[European American|Euro-American]] population in the U.S. They mostly live in both the [[Upper Midwest]] and [[Pacific Northwest]].

===Canada===
{{Main|Norwegian Canadian|Icelandic Canadian}}
[[File:Saskatoon in Winter.jpg|thumb|right|7% of the population in [[Saskatoon]] in [[Canada]] is of Norwegian ancestry.]]
As early as 1814, a party of Norwegians was brought to [[Canada]] to build a winter road from York Factory on Hudson Bay in northern Canada to the infant Red River settlement at the site of present-day [[Winnipeg, Manitoba]], Canada. Norway House is one of the oldest trading posts and Native-Canadian missions in the Canadian West. Willard Ferdinand Wentzel served the North West Company of Canada in the Athabasca and Mackenzie regions and accompanied Sir John Franklin on his overland expedition in 1819–20 to the Canadian Arctic.

Norwegians immigrated to Canada in search of the Canadian Dream. This immigration lasted from the mid-1880s until 1930, although Norwegians were already working in Canada as early as 1814. It can be divided into three periods of roughly fifteen years each. In the first, to about 1900, thousands of Norwegians homesteaded on the Canadian prairies. In the second, from 1900 to 1914, there was a further heavy influx of Norwegians immigrating to Canada from the United States because of poor economic conditions in the USA, and 18,790 from Norway. In the third, from 1919 to 1930, 21,874 people came directly from Norway, with the peak year in 1927, when 5,103 Norwegians arrived, spurred by severe depression at home. They came with limited means, many leaving dole queues.

From 1825 to 1900 some 500,000 Norwegians landed at Ville du Quebec in Canada (and other Canadian ports) for travelling through Canada was the shortest corridor to the USA's central states. In spite of efforts by the Government of Canada to retain these immigrants for Canada, very few remained because of Canada's somewhat restrictive land policies at that time and negative stories being told about Canada from U.S. land agents deterring Norwegians from going to Canada. Not until the 1880s did Norwegians accept Canada as a land of opportunity. This was also true of the many Americans of Norwegian heritage who immigrated to Canada from the USA with &quot;Canada Fever&quot; seeking homesteads and new economic opportunities. By 1921 one-third of all Norwegians in Canada had been born in the USA.

These new Canadians became British subjects in Canada, and part of the British Empire. Canadian citizenship, as a status distinct from that of a British subject, was created on 1 January 1947, with Canada being the first Commonwealth country to create their own citizenship. Prior to that date, Canadians were British subjects and Canada's nationality law closely mirrored that of the United Kingdom. On 1 January 1947, Canadian citizenship was conferred on most British subjects connected with Canada. Unlike in the USA, Canada was part of the British Empire and most Norwegians would have become Canadians and British subjects at the same time.

According to the 2006 Canadian census, 432,515 Canadians reported Norwegian ancestry (Norwegian-Canadians). Norwegians make up 2% of the White Canadian population. However, the actual figure may be higher. It is important to note that because so many Norwegian women married men of other nationalities, and thus by census rules are not counted as having children of this ethnic origin, this tends to reduce the number in the statistics.

===Australia===
{{Main|Norwegian Australian|Norwegian New Zealander}}
[[Image:Lenguas germánicas.PNG|240px|thumb|right|'''West Germanic languages'''
{{legend|#9cff00|Dutch (Low Franconian, West Germanic)}}
{{legend|#38ff00|Low German (West Germanic)}}
{{legend|#00d200|Central German (High German, West Germanic)}}
{{legend|#008000|Upper German (High German, West Germanic)}}
{{legend|#ff8811|English (Anglo-Frisian, West Germanic)}}
{{legend|#ffbb77|Frisian (Anglo-Frisian, West Germanic)}}
'''North Germanic languages'''
{{legend|#0000ff|East Scandinavian}}
{{legend|#00ffff|West Scandinavian}}
{{legend|#ff0000|Line dividing the North and West Germanic languages}}]]
{{main|Norwegian language}}
An organized European [[immigration to Australia]] was initiated in 1788. And most of the early emigrants were deported from the [[United Kingdom|Britain]].

There were people from the [[British Isles]] as completely dominated when emigration to Australia changed character from being deported, to be virtually voluntary. In David Copperfield Charles Dickens allows Mr. Micawber go to Australia as a result of economic problems, and it was a piece on the way representative. From the 1830s used by the British authorities planned export of surplus population, and over the years up to 1897 was 600,000 persons exported in whole or in part at public expense.

But when the [[gold rush]]  began in Australia in 1851 flocked to the volunteers, and it has been said that as many as 5000 Norwegian-born was in the periods. Around 1860 there shall have been around 2500 Norwegians there. A good number of these had previously tried luck that gold miners in [[California]], and many went also return to America. ''Gullgravere'' guess almost by definition, fortune seekers, and thus prepared to move around depending on your luck might smile, and there was little stability there.

===Russia===
{{See|Kola Norwegians}}

In the 19th century a community known as the [[Kola Norwegians]] settled in the environs of the Russian city of [[Murmansk]]. They have suffered persecution under [[Joseph Stalin]] and after 1990 were offered a chance to get back to Norway. There are very few of them left there today.

===Other===
{{see also|Norwegian settlement in Iceland|Scandinavian migration to the United Kingdom|Norwegian Swedes|Norwegian South African|Scandinavian Brazilian}}

==Genetics==
According to recent genetic analysis, both mtDNA and Y chromosome polymorphisms showed a noticeable genetic affinity between the Norwegian population and other ethnic groups in [[Northern Europe|Northern]] and [[Central Europe]], particularly with the Germans. This is due to a history of at least a thousand years of large-scale migration both in and out of Norway.&lt;ref name=&quot;hpgl.stanford.edu&quot;&gt;http://hpgl.stanford.edu/publications/EJHG_2002_v10_521-529.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Norwegian population is typical of the Northern European population with [[Haplogroup I1 (Y-DNA)|Haplogroup I1]] being most common. Norwegians also show the characteristic [[R1a]] genes of the paternal ancestorship at 17.9%&lt;ref name=&quot;ajhg.org&quot;&gt;http://www.ajhg.org/AJHG/abstract/S0002-9297(07)63256-X Estimating Scandinavian and Gaelic Ancestry in the Male Settlers of Iceland - Agnar Helgason et al., 2000, Am. J. Hum. Genet. 67:697–717, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; to 30.8%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosser et al. 2000&quot;&gt;Rosser et al. (2000)&lt;/ref&gt; Such large frequencies of R1a have been found only in East Europe and India.&lt;ref&gt;F. Luca, F. Di Giacomo, T. Benincasa et al., &quot;Y-Chromosomal Variation in the Czech Republic,&quot; American Journal of Physical Anthropology 132:132–139 (2007).&lt;/ref&gt; [[R1b]] gene showing paternal descent is also widespread at 25.9%.&lt;ref name=&quot;ajhg.org&quot;/&gt; to 30.8%&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosser et al. 2000&quot;/&gt;

== Language ==
{{Main|Norwegian language|North Germanic languages|German language|German dialects}}
[[Norwegian language|Norwegian]] is a [[North Germanic language]] with approximately 5 million speakers, of whom most are located in [[Norway]]. There are also some speakers of Norwegian in [[Denmark]], [[Sweden]], [[Germany]], [[United Kingdom|Britain]], [[Spain]], [[Canada]], and the [[United States]], where the largest community of speakers exists, with 55,311 speakers as of 2000; approximately half of the speakers live in [[Minnesota]] (8,060), [[California]] (5,865), [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] (5,460), [[New York]] (4,200), and [[Wisconsin]] (3,520).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mla.org/map_data_results&amp;mode=lang_tops&amp;SRVY_YEAR=2000&amp;lang_id=616 U.S Census 2000]&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2006, in Canada, there are 7,710 [[Norwegian language|Norwegian speakers]], of whom 3,420 reside in [[British Columbia]], 1,360 in [[Alberta]], and 1,145 in [[Ontario]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www12.statcan.ca/census-recensement/2006/dp-pd/tbt/Rp-eng.cfm?TABID=1&amp;LANG=E&amp;APATH=3&amp;DETAIL=0&amp;DIM=0&amp;FL=A&amp;FREE=0&amp;GC=0&amp;GK=0&amp;GRP=1&amp;PID=89186&amp;PRID=0&amp;PTYPE=88971,97154&amp;S=0&amp;SHOWALL=0&amp;SUB=0&amp;Temporal=2006&amp;THEME=70&amp;VID=0&amp;VNAMEE=&amp;VNAMEF= | title=Detailed Mother Tongue (148), Single and Multiple Language Responses (3) and Sex (3) for the Population of Canada, Provinces, Territories, Census Metropolitan Areas and Census Agglomerations, 2006 Census – 20% Sample Data |year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Culture ==
{{Main|Culture of Norway}}
'''Norwegian culture''' is closely linked to the country's [[History of Norway|history]] and [[Geography of Norway|geography]]. The unique [[Norwegian farm culture]], sustained to this day, has resulted not only from scarce resources and a harsh climate but also from [[Ancient Norwegian property laws|ancient property laws]]. In the 18th century, it brought about a strong [[Norwegian romantic nationalism|romantic nationalistic]] movement, which is still visible in the [[Norwegian language]] and [[:Category:Norwegian media|media]]. In the 19th century, Norwegian culture blossomed as efforts continued to achieve an independent identity in the areas of literature, art and music.

=== Cuisine ===
{{main|Cuisine of Norway}}
[[Image:Smalahove01.JPG|250px|thumb|right|[[Smalahove]] is course served in parts of [[Western Norway]].]]
Norway's culinary traditions show the influence of long seafaring and farming traditions with [[salmon]] (fresh and cured), [[herring]] (pickled or marinated), [[trout]], [[cod]]fish and other seafood balanced by cheeses, dairy products and excellent breads (predominantly dark/darker). [[Lefse]] is a common Norwegian potato flatbread, common around Christmas. For renowned Norwegian dishes, see [[lutefisk]], [[smalahove]], [[pinnekjøtt]], [[Krotekaker]] and [[fårikål]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everyculture.com/No-Sa/Norway.html Culture of Norway. Everyculture.com.] Retrieved 27 November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Music ===
{{main|Music of Norway}}
Along with the classical [[Norwegian music|music]] of [[romanticism|romantic]] [[composer]] [[Edvard Grieg]] and the modern music of [[Arne Nordheim]], [[Norwegian black metal]] has become something of an export article in recent years.

Norway's classical performers include [[Leif Ove Andsnes]], one of the world's more famous pianists, and [[Truls Mørk]], an outstanding cellist.

The jazz scene in Norway is also thriving. [[Jan Garbarek]], [[Mari Boine]], [[Arild Andersen]], and [[Bugge Wesseltoft]] are internationally recognised while [[Paal Nilssen-Love]], [[Supersilent]], [[Jaga Jazzist]] and [[Wibutee]] are becoming world-class artists of the younger generation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.studyinnorway.no/sn/Living-in-Norway/Culture Culture from Study in Norway]. Retrieved 2 December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Norway has a strong [[folk music]] tradition which remains popular to this day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.norway.org.uk/culture/music/folk/folk.htm Norwegian Folk Music from Norway, official site in the UK.] Retrieved 25 November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the most prominent folk musicians are [[Hardingfele|Hardanger fiddlers]] [[Andrea Een]], [[Olav Jørgen Hegge]], [[Vidar Lande]] and [[Annbjørg Lien]], violinist [[Susanne Lundeng]], and vocalists [[Agnes Buen Garnås]], [[Kirsten Bråten Berg]] and [[Odd Nordstoga]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.norway.org.uk/culture/contemporaryart/ Contemporary art from Norway the official site.] Retrieved 28 November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Celebrations ===
Norwegians celebrate their national day on May 17, dedicated to the [[Constitution of Norway]]. Many people wear ''[[bunad]]'' (traditional costumes) and most participate in or watch the [[Norwegian Constitution Day]] 
parade that day, consisting mostly of children, through the cities and towns. The [[Norwegian romantic nationalism|national romanticist]] author [[Henrik Wergeland]] was the founder of the 17 May parade. 
Common [[Christianity|Christian]] holidays are also celebrated, the most important being [[Christmas]] (called ''[[Yule|Jul]]'' in Norway after the pagan and early [[Viking]] winter solstice) and [[Easter]] (Påske). In Norway, the [[Santa]] (called [[Nissen]]) comes at [[Christmas Eve]], the 24th of December, with the presents, not the morning after as in many English speaking countries. He usually comes late in the evening, after the Christmas dinner many children consider long, boring and unnecessary. 

''[[Jonsok]]'' ([[John the Baptist|St. John]]'s Passing), or ''[[St. Hans]]'' ([[John the Baptist|St. John]]'s Day), i.e. 24 June, is also a commonly revered holiday. It marks [[midsummer]] and the beginning of summer vacation, and is often celebrated by lighting [[bonfire]]s the evening before. In Northern areas of Norway, this day has 24 hours of light, while southern areas have only 17.5 hours.

===Religion===
[[File:Our.savior.jpg|thumb|right|[[Our Savior's Lutheran Church (Cranfills Gap, Texas)|Our Savior's Lutheran Church]], a [[Lutheran]] church located near [[Cranfills Gap, Texas]] in an [[unincorporated community]] known as Norse, [[Texas]]. The congregation for the church was organized on June 14, 1869 by Norwegian settlers of [[Bosque County, Texas]].]]
{{see also|Religion in Norway|Norwegian American#The Norwegian Lutheran Church in the United States}}

The conversion of Norway to [[Christianity]] from [[Norse paganism]] began in [[1000]] AD. By the middle of the 11th century, Christianity had become well-established in Norway and had become dominant by the middle of the 12th century. The Norwegians were [[Catholics]] until the [[Denmark|Danish]] king [[Christian III of Denmark]] forced them to convert to [[Lutheranism]] and established a state-governed church. The [[church (building)|church]] undertook a program to convert the [[Sámi people|Sámi]] in the 16th and 17th century, with the program being largely successful.

In the 19th century, emigration from Norway for political and religious motives began and Lutheranism spread to the United States. As a result of this,{{citation needed|month=March 2011|Most Nordic people are religiously moderate - I have heard of no oppression of Christians here.|date=March 2011}} many of the Norwegians remaining in Norway were religiously moderate; subsequently, church attendance declined throughout the 20th century, as reflected by 78% of the population stating that religious is unimportant in a Gallup poll&lt;ref&gt;[https://worldview.gallup.com/default.aspx GALLUP WorldView]&lt;/ref&gt; and low weekly church attendance, at 2%,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aftenbladet.no/livssyn/1086156/2_prosent_gaar_i_kirken_paa_en_vanlig_soendag.html [[Stavanger Aftenblad]] - 2 prosent går i kirken på en vanlig søndag]&lt;/ref&gt; particularly when compared to that of [[North Dakota]], the state in which Norwegians constitute approximately 30.4% of the population. Of all U.S. states, North Dakota has the lowest percentage of non-religious people and the largest number of churches per capita. It weekly church attendance is at 43%.&lt;ref name=&quot;religious survey&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris/key_findings.htm | title=American Religious Identification Survey | work=Exhibit 15 | publisher = The Graduate Center, City University of New York | accessdate = 2006-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;church&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.us-moving.com/north-dakota.html | title= North Dakota Movers| work= | publisher = US-Moving.com | accessdate = 2007-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;church&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20060502/news_lz1n2thelist.html San Diego Times, May 2, 2006], from 2006 Gallup survey&lt;/ref&gt;

In Norway the [[Church of Norway]] and state are not separated. When baptised, children are registered in the [[Church of Norway]]'s member register, leading to a large membership, although many people do not remain observant as adults. A majority of both ethnic Norwegians and Sámi are nominally Christian, but not necessarily observant.

==Famous Norwegians==
This list only includes people of some notable Norwegian ancestry.

* [[Dominic Purcell]], Australian actor famous from the popular TV-Series [[Prison Break]].
* [[Eliot Ness]], legendary American Prohibition Agent, notable for being the man who brought down gangster [[Al Capone]].
* [[Geir Haarde]], former prime minister of Iceland.
* [[Iggy Pop]], American musician.
* [[John Ashcroft]], US Attorney General.
* [[Joni Mitchell]], Canadian singer.
* [[Josh Groban]], American singer.
* [[Kjell Laugerud García]], former dictator of Guatemala.
* [[Kristanna Loken]], American actress.
* [[Marilyn Monroe]], legendary American actress, model and singer.
* [[Matt Groening]], creator of world famous TV-cartoon ''[[The Simpsons]]''.
* [[Melyssa Ford]], Canadian supermodel of Norwegian, Russian and Caribbean descent.
* [[Paris Hilton]], American media personality, model, singer, and actress. Heiress of [[Hilton Hotels]].
* [[Tom Waits]], American singer.
* [[Russel Crowe]], a [[New Zealand]] born [[Australia]]n actor.
* [[Walter Mondale]], former US Vice President and Senator.
* [[A-ha]], Norwegian pop group

==Other terms used==
The Norwegians are and have been referred to by other terms as well.
Some of them include:
*'''''Nordmenn''''': A term used by Scandinavians to denote Norwegians. It translates as &quot;Northmen&quot;. (Singular: '''Nordmann''')
*''[[Northmen]]'': Old term used by other European peoples to denote the peoples originating in the northern regions of Europe.
*''[[Norsemen]]'' or Norse: [[Viking Age]] peoples of [[Nordic countries|Nordic]] origin.
*''[[Vikings]]'': Used in the Nordic countries to denote people who went raiding, pillaging or ''slave catching'' during the Viking Age. Used in a similar way by other peoples but can also mean [[Scandinavians]] in general.
*''[[Minnewegian]]'': [[Colloquial]] term for a [[Norwegian Minnesotan]].
*''Norrbagge'': A Swedish derogatory term for Norwegians (first attested use in 1257), based on the root ''bagge'' meaning sheep's testicles.
*''Norski'': Common name for Northern American Norwegians.

==See also==
*[[List of Germanic peoples]]
{{Portal|Norway}}
*[[List of Norwegians]]
*[[Norway]]
*[[Scandinavians]]
*[[Norsemen]]
*[[Scandinavia]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{NorwegianDiaspora}}
{{Norway topics}}

[[Category:Ethnic groups in Europe]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in Norway]]
[[Category:Norwegian people]]

[[af:Noorweërs]]
[[az:Norveçlilər]]
[[be:Нарвежцы]]
[[be-x-old:Нарвэжцы]]
[[bg:Норвежци]]
[[cs:Norové]]
[[da:Nordmænd]]
[[de:Norweger]]
[[et:Norralased]]
[[eo:Norvegoj]]
[[fo:Norðmenn]]
[[fr:Norvégiens]]
[[hr:Norvežani]]
[[id:Bangsa Norwegia]]
[[os:Норвегиаг адæм]]
[[it:Norvegesi]]
[[ka:ნორვეგიელები]]
[[lt:Norvegai]]
[[hu:Norvégok]]
[[mk:Норвежани]]
[[nl:Noren (volk)]]
[[no:Nordmenn]]
[[nn:Nordmenn]]
[[pl:Norwegowie]]
[[pt:Noruegueses]]
[[ru:Норвежцы]]
[[sk:Nóri]]
[[sl:Norvežani]]
[[sh:Norvežani]]
[[fi:Norjalaiset]]
[[sv:Norrmän]]
[[tr:Norveçliler]]
[[uk:Норвежці]]
[[ur:ناروینی]]
[[bat-smg:Nuorvegā]]
[[zh:挪威人]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
