<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="67538" ns="0" title="Australian Defence Force"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Use Australian English|date=October 2011}}
{{Featured article}}
{{Infobox National Military
|country=Australia
|name=Australian Defence Force
|image=[[Image:autriservice.gif|300px|Tri-service Flag]]
|caption=The ADF Tri-Service Flag
|image2=
|caption2=
|founded=1901
|current_form=1976 (ADF established)
|branches=[[Royal Australian Navy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Australian Army]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Royal Australian Air Force]]
|headquarters=Part of the [[Australian Defence Organisation]]
&lt;!-- Leadership --&gt;
|commander-in-chief=[[Governor-General of Australia|Governor-General]] [[Quentin Bryce]], [[Companion of the Order of Australia|AC]] as [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Elizabeth II, Queen of Australia's]] representative
|minister=[[The Hon.]] [[Stephen Smith (Australian politician)|Stephen Smith]]
|minister_title=[[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister for Defence]]
|commander=[[General (Australia)|General]] [[David Hurley]] [[Companion of the Order of Australia|AC]], [[Distinguished Service Cross (Australia)|DSC]]
|commander_title=[[Chief of the Defence Force (Australia)|Chief of the Defence Force]]
|age=16.5 years of age for selection process, 17 years of age is actual serving age (As of 2007)
|manpower_data=2009 est.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA_Aust&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/as.html|title=CIA – The World Fact Book – Australia|last=Central Intelligence Agency|publisher=CIA|accessdate=16 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|manpower_age=16–49
|available=4,999,988
|available_f=4,870,043
|fit=4,341,591
|fit_f=4,179,659
|reaching=144,959
|reaching_f=137,333
|active=59,023
|ranked=68
|reserve=21,850 (Active)&lt;br /&gt; 22,166 (Standby)
|deployed=3,300 (July 2011)&lt;ref name=Globalops_July2011&gt;{{cite web|title=Global Operations|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/op/index.htm|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|amount={{A$|26.5 billion}} (2010–11)&lt;ref name=Thomson_2011_vi /&gt;
|percent_GDP=1.8 percent
&lt;!-- Industrial --&gt;
|domestic_suppliers=
|foreign_suppliers=
|imports=
|exports= Confidential, but thought to be over A$600 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Defence and Security Overview|url=http://www.austrade.gov.au/Defence-and-homeland-security-overview/default.aspx|publisher=Austrade|accessdate=23 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Related articles --&gt;
|history=[[Military history of Australia]]
|ranks=[[Australian Defence Force ranks and insignia]]
}}
The '''Australian Defence Force''' (ADF) is the [[Armed forces|military organisation]] responsible for the defence of [[Australia]]. It consists of the [[Royal Australian Navy]] (RAN), [[Australian Army]], [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) and a number of 'tri-service' units. The ADF has a strength of just under 81,000 full-time personnel and [[Military reserve force|active reservists]], and is supported by the [[Department of Defence (Australia)|Department of Defence]] and several other civilian agencies. 

During the first decades of the 20th century, the [[Government of Australia|Australian Government]] established the armed services as separate organisations. Each service had an independent [[chain of command]]. In 1976, the government made a strategic change and established the ADF to place the services under a single headquarters. Over time, the degree of integration has increased and tri-service headquarters, logistics and training institutions have supplanted many single-service establishments.

The ADF is technologically sophisticated but relatively small. Although the ADF's 59,023 full-time active-duty personnel, 21,850 active [[Military reserve force|reserves]] and 22,166 standby reserves make it the largest military in [[Oceania]], it is still smaller than most Asian militaries. Nonetheless, the ADF is supported by a significant budget by worldwide standards and is able to deploy forces in multiple locations outside Australia.

==Role==
===Legal standing===
The ADF's legal standing draws on the executive government sections of the [[Australian Constitution]]. Section 51(vi) gives the [[Government of Australia|Commonwealth Government]] the power to make laws regarding Australia's defence and defence forces. Section 114 of the Constitution prevents the States from raising armed forces without the permission of the Commonwealth and Section 119 gives the Commonwealth responsibility for defending Australia from invasion and sets out the conditions under which the government can deploy the defence force domestically.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2010_2&quot;&gt;Khosa (2010), p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Section 68 of the Constitution sets out the ADF's command arrangements. The Section states that &quot;the command in chief of the naval and military forces of the Commonwealth is vested in the [[Governor-General of Australia|Governor-General]] as the [[Monarchy in Australia|Queen's]] representative&quot;. In practice, however, the Governor-General does not play an active part in the ADF's command structure, and the elected [[Government of Australia|Australian Government]] controls the ADF. The [[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister for Defence]] and several subordinate ministers [[Civilian control of the military|exercise this control]]. The Minister acts on most matters alone, though the [[National Security Committee of Cabinet (Australia)|National Security Committee of Cabinet (NSC)]] considers important matters. The Minister then advises the Governor-General who acts as advised in the normal form of [[executive government]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2010_2&quot; /&gt;

===Current priorities===

The Australian Government's defence policies are guided by the [[white paper]] ''[[Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030]]'', which was released in 2009. The white paper argued that Australia's strategic environment is likely to become more complex and uncertain due to the changing relationships between nations in the [[Asia-Pacific]] region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_5&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; In response to this, it set out a policy of increasing the ADF's capabilities over the period to 2030. This includes significantly expanding the ADF's maritime capabilities, improving the firepower of Army units and equipping the RAAF with modern and more capable aircraft. The ADF's communication, intelligence and logistics capabilities are also to be improved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_6&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; The current government has committed to producing new defence white papers &quot;at intervals of no greater than five years&quot; so that changes to Australia's strategic environment are taken into account during defence planning.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_5 /&gt; The next white paper is planned to be released in 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson_2011_vii&quot;&gt;Thomson (2011), p. vii&lt;/ref&gt;

''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030'' identifies Australia's strategic objectives and the ADF capabilities which are necessary for these to be met. It states that &quot;Australia's most basic strategic interest remains the defence of Australia against direct armed attack&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Defence_2009_12&quot;&gt;Defence (2009), p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; In order to accomplish this, the ADF needs to be capable of dominating the air and sea approaches to Australia, which includes defending the country's sea lanes and infrastructure.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_5 /&gt; The next most important priority is identified as &quot;the security, stability and cohesion of our immediate neighbourhood, which we share with [[Indonesia]], [[Papua New Guinea]], [[East Timor]], [[New Zealand]] and the South Pacific island states&quot;.&lt;ref name=Defence_2009_12 /&gt; This includes ensuring that the ADF is capable of intervening in these countries to protect Australian citizens, providing humanitarian assistance and, if necessary, stabilising countries at risk of becoming [[failed state]]s.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_6 /&gt; The third most important priority identified in the white paper is contributing to &quot;the stability of the wider 
Asia-Pacific region&quot; and particularly [[Southeast Asia]].&lt;ref name=Defence_2009_12 /&gt; This requires that the ADF be able of assisting countries in the region to respond to threats to their security, including in cooperation with the [[United States]]. Such assistance may include the deployment of large Australian military forces.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_6 /&gt; The fourth priority set out is &quot;preserving an international order that restrains aggression by states against each other, and can effectively manage other risks and threats&quot;.&lt;ref name=Defence_2009_12 /&gt; This requires that the ADF be able to contribute limited forces to operations throughout the world.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_6 /&gt;

==History==
{{Main|Military history of Australia|History of the Royal Australian Navy|History of the Australian Army|History of the Royal Australian Air Force}}

===Formation of the Australian Defence Force===
[[Image:Melbourne Midway small.JPG|thumb|upright|alt=An aerial photo of an aircraft carrier with several aircraft on her flight deck. Another carrier is visible in the background.|The retirement of {{HMAS|Melbourne|R21|6}} without replacement in 1982 marked a shift away from the policy of 'forward defence'.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Australia has maintained military forces since [[Federation of Australia|federation as a nation]] in January 1901. Shortly after Federation, the Australian Government established the [[Australian Army]] and Commonwealth Naval Force by amalgamating the forces each of the states had maintained.&lt;ref&gt;Grey (2008), p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; In 1911, the Government established the [[Royal Australian Navy]], which absorbed the Commonwealth Naval Force.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al. (2008), p. 467&lt;/ref&gt; The Army established the Australian Flying Corps in 1912 although this separated to form the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] in 1921.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al. (2008), pp. 61, 457&lt;/ref&gt; The services were not linked by a single chain of command, as they each reported to their own separate Minister and had separate administrative arrangements. The three services saw action around the world during [[Military history of Australia during World War I|World War I]] and [[Military history of Australia during World War II|World War II]], and took part in conflicts in Asia during the [[Cold War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Australians at war|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/atwar/|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=13 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The importance of [[Joint warfare|'joint' warfare]] was made clear to the Australian Military during World War II when Australian naval, ground and air units frequently served as part of single commands. Following the war, several senior officers lobbied for the appointment of a [[commander in chief]] of the three services. The government rejected this proposal and the three services remained fully independent.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; The absence of a central authority resulted in poor coordination between the services, with each service organising and operating on the basis of a different [[military doctrine]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Horner_p44&quot;&gt;Horner (2001), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;

The need for an integrated command structure received more emphasis as a result of the inefficient arrangements which at times hindered the military's efforts [[Military history of Australia during the Vietnam War|during the Vietnam War]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Horner_p44&quot;/&gt; In 1973, the Secretary of the [[Department of Defence (Australia)|Department of Defence]], [[Arthur Tange]], submitted a report to the [[Government of Australia|Government]] that recommended the unification of the separate departments supporting each service into a single Department of Defence and the creation of the post of Chief of the Defence Force Staff. The government accepted these recommendations and the Australian Defence Force was established on 9&amp;nbsp;February 1976.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Defence of Australia era===
[[Image:Kangaroo 89.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A group of men wearing green military uniforms walking across barren ground.|Australian soldiers lead a column of American troops during Exercise Kangaroo '89, which was held in northern Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Until the 1970s, Australia's military strategy centred on the concept of 'forward defence', in which the role of the Australian military was to cooperate with allied forces to counter threats in Australia's region. In 1969, when the United States began the [[Guam Doctrine]] and the British withdrew '[[east of Suez]]', Australia developed a defence policy emphasising self-reliance of the Australian continent. This was known as the [[Defence of Australia Policy]]. Under this policy, the focus of Australian defence planning was to protect Australia's northern maritime approaches (the sea-air gap) against enemy attack.&lt;ref&gt;Tewes, Rayner and Kavanaugh (2004).&lt;/ref&gt; In line with this goal, the ADF was restructured to increase its ability to strike at enemy forces from Australian bases and to counter raids on continental Australia. The ADF achieved this by increasing the capabilities of the RAN and RAAF and relocating regular Army units to [[northern Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

At this time, the ADF had no military units on operational deployment outside Australia. In 1987, the ADF made its first operational deployment as part of [[Operation Morris Dance]], in which several warships and a rifle company deployed to the waters off [[Fiji]] in response to the [[1987 Fijian coups d'état]]. While broadly successful, this deployment highlighted the need for the ADF to improve its capability to rapidly respond to unforeseen events.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 225–227.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the late 1980s, the Government has increasingly called upon the ADF to contribute forces to peacekeeping missions around the world. While most of these deployments involved only small numbers of specialists, several led to the deployment of hundreds of personnel. Large peacekeeping deployments were made to [[Namibia]] in early 1989, [[Cambodia]] between 1992 and 1993, [[Operation Solace|Somalia]] in 1993, [[Rwanda]] between 1994 and 1995 and [[Bougainville Province|Bougainville]] in 1994 and from 1997 onwards.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 228–255.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Australian contribution to the 1991 Gulf War]] was the first time Australian personnel were deployed to an active war zone since the establishment of the ADF. Although the warships and [[Clearance Diving Team (RAN)|clearance diving team]] deployed to the [[Persian Gulf]] did not see combat, the deployment tested the ADF's capabilities and command structure. Following the war the Navy regularly deployed a [[List of recent Australian warship deployments to the Middle East|frigate to the Persian Gulf or Red Sea]] to enforce the [[Iraq sanctions|trade sanctions imposed on Iraq]].&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 231–237.&lt;/ref&gt;

===East Timor and after===
[[Image:RAAF C-130 Iraq 2008.JPG|thumb|alt=Side view of a propeller-driven plane flying just above the ground|A RAAF [[C-130 Hercules]] in Iraq during 2008. These aircraft support ADF operations in Iraq and Afghanistan.]]
In 1996, [[John Howard]] led the [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal Party's]] election campaign and became Prime Minister. Subsequently, there were significant reforms to the ADF's force structure and role. The new government's defence strategy placed less emphasis on defending Australia from direct attack and greater emphasis on working in cooperation with regional states and [[Foreign relations of Australia|Australia's allies]] to manage potential security threats.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Army (2008), p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 95–96&lt;/ref&gt; From 1997 the Government also implemented a series of changes to the ADF's force structure in an attempt to increase the proportion of combat units to support units and improve the ADF's combat effectiveness.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 93–95&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADF's experiences during the [[International Force for East Timor|deployment to East Timor in 1999]] led to significant changes in Australia's defence policies and to an enhancement of the ADF's ability to conduct operations outside Australia. This successful deployment was the first time a large Australian military force had operated outside of Australia since the Vietnam War and revealed shortcomings in the ADF's ability to mount and sustain such operations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Jenny |last=Sinclair |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Operation Chaos |url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/11/19/1037490107525.html |work=[[The Age]] |date=19 December 2002 |accessdate=2007-07-06 }}. See also Australian National Audit Office (2002). [http://www.anao.gov.au/uploads/documents/2001-02_Audit_Report_38.pdf ''Management of Australian Defence Force Deployments to East Timor'']. ANAO, Canberra.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2000, the Government released a new Defence White Paper, ''Defence 2000 – Our Future Defence Force'' that placed a greater emphasis on preparing the ADF for overseas deployments. The Government committed to improve the ADF's capabilities by improving the readiness and equipment of ADF units, expanding the ADF and increasing [[Real versus nominal value (economics)|real]] Defence expenditure by 3% per year.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2005b), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003 and 2005, the ''Defence Updates'' emphasised this focus on expeditionary operations and led to an expansion and modernisation of the ADF.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2006a), pp. 7–8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2000, the ADF's expanded force structure and deployment capabilities have been put to the test on a number of occasions. Following the [[September 11 attacks|11 September 2001 terrorist attacks]] on the United States, Australia committed a [[special forces]] task group and an [[air-to-air refuelling]] aircraft to operations in [[Afghanistan]], and naval warships to the [[Persian Gulf]] as [[Operation Slipper]].&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al. (2008), pp. 8–9&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003, approximately 2,000 ADF personnel, including a special forces task group, three warships and 14 [[F/A-18 Hornet]] aircraft, took part in the [[Australian contribution to the 2003 invasion of Iraq|invasion of Iraq]].&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al. (2008), p. 248&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in 2003, elements of all three services deployed to the [[Solomon Islands]] as part of the [[Regional Assistance Mission to the Solomon Islands]]. In late 2004, over 1,000 ADF personnel deployed to Indonesia in [[Operation Sumatra Assist]] following the [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake]].&lt;ref&gt;Australian Minister for Defence media release [http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/HillTpl.cfm?CurrentId=4739 ''ADF Head Home from Aceh'']. 24 March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2006, approximately 2,000 ADF personnel deployed to East Timor in [[Operation Astute]] following unrest between elements of the [[Timor Leste Defence Force]].&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al. (2008), p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;

===Current operations===
{{Main|Current Australian Defence Force deployments}}
In July 2011, around 3,300 ADF personnel were deployed on twelve operations in Australian territory and overseas. Approximately 400 of these personnel were taking part in domestic maritime security tasks.&lt;ref name=Globalops_July2011 /&gt; 
[[File:SOTG soldier with rifle April 2010.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A man wearing a green camouflage uniform and a tan camouflage baseball cap looking through a rifle scope. He is resting his rifle on a dirt wall and steep mountains are visible in the background.|A Special Operations Task Group soldier in Afghanistan during 2010]]

The ADF currently has several forces deployed to the Middle East. The ADF's contribution to the [[War on Terrorism|international coalition against terrorism]] in [[Afghanistan]] (designated [[Operation Slipper]]) is the largest ADF deployment, with about 1,550 personnel in the country at any time. Operation Slipper also includes the deployment of one of the RAN's frigates to the Arabian Sea and Gulf of Aden on counter piracy and maritime interdiction duties.&lt;ref name=Commitment_in_Afghanistan&gt;{{cite web|title=Australia's Commitment in Afghanistan|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/op/afghanistan/info/factsheet.htm|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Australian force in Iraq is now limited to 33 soldiers assigned to protect the Australian Embassy in [[Baghdad]] ([[Operation Kruger]]) and two officers attached to the [[United Nations Assistance Mission for Iraq]].&lt;ref name=Globalops_July2011 /&gt; Detachments of two maritime patrol aircraft and three C-130 Hercules transport aircraft support operations in Iraq and Afghanistan; these are based at [[Al Minhad Air Base]] in the [[United Arab Emirates]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nautilus_Al_Minhad_Air_Base&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalcollab.org/Nautilus/australia/bases/mirage|title=Al Minhad Air Base – Global Collaborative|year=2009|work=Australian Bases Abroad|publisher=Nautilus Institute|accessdate=13 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ADF also maintains three small contributions totalling 61 personnel to peacekeeping operations in the Middle East and Africa.&lt;ref name=Globalops_July2011 /&gt; All ADF units in the Middle East come under the overall command of Joint Task Force 633, whose headquarters is located at Al Minhad Air Base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nautilus_Al_Minhad_Air_Base&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/australias-basing-its-87m-secret-on-sensitive-absurdity-20091107-i2vy.html|title=Australia's basing its $87m secret on sensitive absurdity|last=Hyland|first=Tom|date=8 November 2009|work=The Age|accessdate=13 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ADF units are currently deployed on two operations in Australia's immediate neighbourhood. Approximately 404 personnel, most of whom form part of the joint Australia-New Zealand International Security Force, are deployed to [[East Timor]] on peacekeeping duties as part of [[Operation Astute]]. About 80 soldiers are also deployed in the Solomon Islands as the ADF's contribution to the [[Regional Assistance Mission to the Solomon Islands]].&lt;ref name=Globalops_July2011 /&gt;

===Future trends===
[[File:F-35A three-view.PNG|thumb|alt=Colour drawing depicting the top, side and front of a modern jet fighter aircraft. The aircraft is painted grey and has one engine.|The Australian Government intends to buy at least 72 F-35A Lightning II aircraft to re-equip the RAAF's air combat force between 2014 and 2021&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=F-35 Joint Strike Fighter – Australia's Next Generation Air Power|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/dmo/lsp/jsf.cfm|publisher=Defence Material Organisation|accessdate=18 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Australia's changing security environment will lead to new demands being placed on the Australian Defence Force. Although it is not expected that Australia will face any threat of direct attack, [[terrorist]] groups and tensions between nations in [[East Asia]] pose threats to Australian security. The unstable governments in many South Pacific countries may lead to some of these countries becoming [[failed state]]s in the future. States such as [[Fiji]] may require Australian military-led interventions to restore [[civil government]].&lt;ref&gt;Australian Department of Defence (2007a), pp. 13–23.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Demographics of Australia|Australian demographic trends]] will put pressure on the ADF in the future.&lt;ref&gt;Ken Henry (2005) [http://www.ada.asn.au/defender/Summer%2005-06/Australia's%20Defence%20to%202045%20(Henry).pdf 'Australia's Defence to 2045: The Macro-economic Outlook'] in ''Defender'', Spring 2005, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; Excluding other factors, the aging of the Australian population will result in smaller numbers of potential recruits entering the Australian [[labour market]] each year. Some predictions are that population aging will result in slower economic growth and increased government expenditure on pensions and health programs. As a result of these trends, the aging of Australia's population may worsen the ADF's manpower situation and may force the Government to reallocate some of the Defence budget.&lt;ref&gt;Henry (2005), pp. 22–23.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, relatively few young Australians consider joining the military and the ADF has to compete for recruits against private sector firms which are able to offer higher salaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grey&quot;&gt;Grey (2008), p. 280&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADF has developed strategies to respond to Australia's changing strategic environment and population base. These strategies include expanding the ADF and introducing new equipment in order to increase Australia's [[Power in international relations|strategic weight]]. To maintain Australia's qualitative lead over neighbouring states the ADF intends to introduce new technologies and maintain the high quality of Australian military training. The ADF is also seeking to develop and implement improved military tactics based upon the integration of technology and better cooperation between the services.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Department of Defence (2006a). ''[http://www.aph.gov.au/house/committee/jfadt/esstrends/subs/sub7.pdf Submission to the Joint Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Inquiry into the Economic, Social and Strategic Trends in Australia’s Region and the Consequences for Our Defence Requirements]''. Australian Department of Defence. Canberra, pp. 11–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current structure==
[[Image:Russell Offices.JPG|thumb|alt=A group of multi-story office buildings. A lake, mountains and a jet of water are visible in the background.|The ADF headquarters and the main offices of the Department of Defence are located in the [[Russell Offices]] complex in Canberra]]
The Australian Defence Force, [[Department of Defence (Australia)|Department of Defence]] and [[Defence Materiel Organisation]] (DMO) make up the [[Australian Defence Organisation]] (ADO), which is often referred to as 'Defence'.&lt;ref name=Defence_about_us&gt;{{cite web|title=About us|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/ips/aboutus.htm|work=Information Publication Scheme|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[diarchy]] of the [[Chief of the Defence Force (Australia)|Chief of the Defence Force]] (CDF) and the Secretary of the Department of Defence administers the ADO. The ADF is the military component of the ADO and consists of the Royal Australian Navy (RAN), the Australian Army and the Royal Australian Air Force (RAAF).&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 2–3&lt;/ref&gt;

The Department of Defence is staffed by both [[civilian]] and military personnel and includes agencies such as the DMO, [[Defence Intelligence Organisation]] (DIO) and [[Defence Science and Technology Organisation]] (DSTO). The DMO purchases and maintains defence equipment. The DSTO provides science and technology support to the defence forces.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2010), pp. 50–51&lt;/ref&gt;

===Command arrangements===
{{See also|Current senior Australian Defence Organisation personnel}}
The ADF's command arrangements are specified in the ''Defence Act (1903)'' and subordinate legislation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_2&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; This act states that the [[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister of Defence]] &quot;shall have the general control and administration of the Defence Force&quot; and that the CDF, the Secretary of the Department of Defence and the chiefs of the three services must act &quot;in accordance with any directions of the Minister&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Defence Act 1903 - Section 8|url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/cth/consol_act/da190356/s8.html|work=Defence Act 1903|publisher=Australasian Legal Information Institute|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The leaders of the ADO are also responsible to the junior ministers who are appointed  
to manage specific elements of the defence portfolio.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_2 /&gt; [[Stephen Smith (Australian politician)|Stephen Smith]] is the current Minister of Defence, and the other ministers in the portfolio are [[Minister for Defence Materiel (Australia)|Minister for Defence Materiel]] [[Jason Clare]] and [[Warren Snowdon]], who is both the [[Minister for Veterans' Affairs (Australia)|Minister for Veterans' Affairs]] and [[Minister for Defence Science and Personnel (Australia)|Minister for Defence Science and Personnel]]. Senator [[David Feeney]] is the Parliamentary Secretary for Defence.&lt;ref name=Defence_leaders&gt;{{cite web|title=Defence Leaders|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/leaders/index.htm|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The CDF is the most senior appointment in the ADF. The CDF commands the ADF, and is notionally the equal of the Secretary of Defence, the most senior public servant in the Department of Defence.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_2 /&gt; The CDF is the only four-star officer in the ADF and is a [[General]], [[Admiral]] or [[Air Chief Marshal]]. In addition to their command responsibilities, the CDF is also the Minister of Defence's principal military adviser.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_3&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; General [[David Hurley]] is the current CDF, and assumed this position on 4&amp;nbsp;July 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chief of the Defence Force|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/leaders/chief/index.htm|work=Defence Leaders|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hugh White, a prominent academic and former Deputy Secretary in the Department of Defence, has criticised the ADF's current command structure. White argues that the Minister plays too large a role in military decision-making and does not provide the CDF and Secretary of Defence with necessary and sufficient authority to manage the ADO effectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Hugh |last=White |title=The real battle is far from the battlefield |url=http://www.lowyinstitute.org/PublicationGet.asp?i=403 |work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |date=25 May 2006 |accessdate=2007-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the current ADF command structure the day-to-day management of the ADF is distinct from the command of military operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_13&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; The services are administered through the ADO, with the head of each service (the [[Chief of Navy (Australia)|Chief of Navy]], [[Chief of Army (Australia)|Chief of Army]] and [[Chief of Air Force (Australia)|Chief of Air Force]]) and the service headquarters being responsible for raising, training and sustaining combat forces. The Chiefs are also the CDF's principal advisor on matters concerning the responsibilities of their service.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 12–13&lt;/ref&gt;

While the individual members of each service ultimately report to their service's Chief, the Chiefs do not control military operations. Control of ADF operations is exercised through a formal command chain headed by the [[Chief of Joint Operations (Australia)|Chief of Joint Operations]] (CJOPS), who reports directly to the CDF. The CJOPS commands the [[Headquarters Joint Operations Command (Australia)|Headquarters Joint Operations Command]] (HQJOC) as well as temporary joint task forces. These joint task forces comprise units assigned from their service to participate in operations or training exercises.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_14&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

===Joint combat forces===
[[File:HQJOC.JPG|thumb|Part of the HQJOC complex near Bungendore]]
Operational command of the ADF is exercised by HQJOC, which is located at a purpose-built facility near [[Bungendore, New South Wales]]. This is a 'joint' headquarters comprising personnel from the three services and includes a continuously manned Joint Control Centre. HQJOC's main role is to &quot;plan, monitor and control&quot; ADF operations and exercises, and it is organised around groups of plans, operations and support staff. HQJOC also monitors the readiness of the ADF units which are not assigned to operations and contributes to developing Australia's [[military doctrine]].&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_14 /&gt; 

As well as HQJOC, the ADF has a number of permanent joint operational commands responsible to the CJOPS. Joint Operations Command (JOC) includes the two headquarters responsible for patrolling Australia's maritime borders on a day to day basis, [[Northern Command (Australia)|Northern Command]] and [[Border Protection Command (Australia)|Border Protection Command]]. Other JOC units include the Joint Movements Group and the Air and Space Operations Centre. In addition, individual ADF units and Joint Task Groups are assigned to JOC during operations, and HQJOC includes officers responsible for submarine and special operations forces.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2010), pp. 13–15&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Australian Navy===
{{Main|Royal Australian Navy}}
The Royal Australian Navy (RAN) is the [[navy|naval branch]] of the Australian Defence Force. The RAN operates 74 vessels of all sizes, including [[frigate]]s, [[submarine]]s, [[patrol boat]]s and auxiliary ships.&lt;ref name=IISS_2011_224 /&gt; The RAN is one of the most modern navies in the Pacific and is responsible for defending Australian waters and undertaking operations in distant locations.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Australian Navy (2006), p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are two parts to the RAN's structure. One is an operational command, Fleet Command, and the other is a support command, Navy Systems Command.&lt;ref&gt;Sea Power Centre – Australia (2005), pp. 33–36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IISS_2011_224&quot;&gt;International Institute for Strategic Studies (2011), p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; The Navy's assets are administered by four 'forces' which report to the [[Commander Australian Fleet]]. These are the [[Fleet Air Arm (RAN)|Fleet Air Arm]], the Mine Warfare, Clearance Diving, Hydrographic, Meteorological and Patrol Force, [[Royal Australian Navy Submarine Service|Submarine Force]] and Surface Force.&lt;ref name=RAN_forces&gt;{{cite web|title=Forces|url=http://www.navy.gov.au/Forces|work=Organisation|publisher=Royal Australian Navy|accessdate=14 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Australian Army===
{{Main|Australian Army}}
[[Image:Australia Army 2010.png|thumb|right|240px|alt=An organisation chart which uses military unit symbols to depict the Australian Army's structure|The Australian Army's structure in 2010]]
The Australian Army is Australia's military land force. While the Australian Army is principally a [[light infantry]] force, it is currently being 'hardened and networked' and expanded to enable it to conduct higher-intensity operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies_Army2010_3&quot;&gt;Davies (2010), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

The Army is organised into three main elements which report to the Chief of Army; the Headquarters of the [[1st Division (Australia)|1st Division]], [[Special Operations Command (Australia)|Special Operations Command]] and Forces Command. Headquarters 1st Division is responsible for high-level training activities and is capable of being deployed to command large scale ground operations. It does not have any combat units permanently assigned to it, though it commands units during training activities and the Land Combat Readiness Centre reports to the divisional headquarters. Most of the Army's units report to Forces Command, which is responsible for overseeing their readiness and preparing them for operations. Special Operations Command is responsible for preparing the ADF's [[special forces]] units for operational deployments. This organisation came into effect during January 2011; before this time the Army's three regular brigades were permanently assigned to the Headquarters 1st Division.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Army (2008a), pp. 5–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IISS_2011_223&quot;&gt;International Institute for Strategic Studies (2011), p. 223&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australian Army's main combat forces are grouped in brigades. These comprise a mechanised brigade—[[1st Brigade (Australia)|1st Brigade]], a light infantry brigade—[[3rd Brigade (Australia)|3rd Brigade]], a motorised brigade—[[7th Brigade (Australia)|7th Brigade]], six Army Reserve brigades, an aviation brigade ([[16th Brigade (Australia)|16th Brigade]]), a combat support and [[ISTAR]] brigade ([[6th Brigade (Australia)|6th Brigade]]) and a logistics brigade (the [[17th Brigade (Australia)|17th Brigade]]).&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 24–27&lt;/ref&gt; The Army's main tactical formations are [[battlegroup (army)|battlegroups]] formed around the headquarters of a [[battalion]]-sized formation.&lt;ref name=Davies_Army2010_3 /&gt;

Special Operations Command (SOC) commands the ADF's special forces units. It comprises the [[Australian Special Air Service Regiment|Special Air Service Regiment]], two commando regiments, the [[Incident Response Regiment (Australia)|Incident Response Regiment]] and signals, logistics and training units.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; The Army's special forces units have been expanded since 2001 and are well equipped and capable of being deployed by sea, air or land.&lt;ref&gt;Davies (2010), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Australian Air Force===
{{Main|Royal Australian Air Force}}
The Royal Australian Air Force (RAAF) is the [[air force]] branch of the ADF. The RAAF has modern [[Military aircraft|combat]] and [[Cargo aircraft|transport aircraft]] and a network of bases in strategic locations across Australia.

Unlike the other services, the RAAF has only a single operational command, [[RAAF Air Command]], which includes the [[RAAF Training Command|Air Force Training Group]]. RAAF Air Command is the operational arm of the RAAF and also consists of the [[Air Combat Group RAAF|Air Combat Group]], [[Air Lift Group RAAF|Air Lift Group]], [[Surveillance and Response Group RAAF|Surveillance and Response Group]], [[Combat Support Group RAAF|Combat Support Group]] and [[Aerospace Operational Support Group RAAF|Aerospace Operational Support Group]]. Each group consists of a number of [[Wing (air force unit)|wings]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF_structure&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/Structure/|title=Our Structure: Royal Australian Air Force|work=Royal Australian Air Force official website|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=15 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The RAAF has [[List of Royal Australian Air Force aircraft squadrons|eighteen flying squadrons]]; four combat squadrons, two maritime patrol squadrons, five transport squadrons, six training squadrons (including three [[Operational Conversion Unit|operational conversion units]] and a forward air control training squadron) and one [[Airborne Early Warning &amp; Control]] squadron. The Air Force also includes a single independent [[Flight (military unit)|flight]] ([[No. 5 Flight RAAF|No. 5 Flight]]). A large number of ground support units support these flying squadrons, including three expeditionary combat support squadrons, two [[Airfield Defence Guards|airfield defence squadrons]] and communications, radar and medical units.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 28–35&lt;/ref&gt;

==Logistic support==
[[Image:RAAF S76a SAR.jpg|thumb|alt=A helicopter painted red and white at rest on grass. Cars are parked in the background.|[[CHC Helicopter]]s has been contracted to provide the RAAF's search and rescue capability&lt;ref&gt;Australian Minister for Defence Press Release, 26 February 2004. [http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/Hilltpl.cfm?CurrentId=3572 Defence Invests in Pilot Safety]. Accessed 7 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The ADF's [[military logistics|logistics]] are managed by the DMO and the Joint Logistics Command. The DMO was created in 2000 by merging the ADF's Support Command Australia with the Department of Defence's Defence Acquisition Organisation and National Support Division.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 278–279&lt;/ref&gt; The DMO purchases all forms of equipment and services used by the ADF and is also responsible for maintaining this equipment throughout its life of type.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 53&lt;/ref&gt;

The DMO is not responsible for directly supplying deployed ADF units; this is the responsibility of the [[Joint Logistics Command]] and the single service logistic units.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Joint Logistics Command|url=http://www.directory.gov.au/osearch.php?ou%3DJoint%20Logistics%20Command,ou%3DVice%20Chief%20of%20the%20Defence%20Force,ou%3DDepartment%20of%20Defence,o%3DDefence,o%3DPortfolios,o%3DCommonwealth%20of%20Australia,c%3DAU&amp;changebase|work=Government Online Directory|publisher=Department of Finance and Deregulation |accessdate=6 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; These units include the Navy's Systems Command and replenishment ships, the Army's [[17th Brigade (Australia)|17th Combat Service Support Brigade]] and Combat Service Support Battalions, and the  [[Combat Support Group RAAF]].&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 273&lt;/ref&gt;

The increasing role of the [[private sector]] forms an important trend in the ADF's logistics arrangements. During the 1990s many of the ADF's support functions were transferred to the private sector to improve the efficiency with which they were provided. Since these reforms most of the 'garrison' support services at military bases have been provided by [[Private military company|private firms]]. The reforms also led to many of the ADF's logistics units being disbanded or reduced in size.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 265–279&lt;/ref&gt; Since this time private firms have increasingly been contracted to provide critical support to ADF units deployed outside Australia. This support has included transporting equipment and personnel and constructing and supplying bases.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2005d), pp. 30–32.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military intelligence==
[[File:AP-3C Orion 2918573216.jpg|thumb|alt=A grey, four engined aircraft viewed from below while it is in flight|A Royal Australian Air Force AP-3C Orion aircraft. These aircraft are fitted with advanced signals intelligence and electronic signals intelligence equipment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=McLaughlin|first=Andrew|title=Quiet Achievers. RAAF Orions on patrol|journal=Australian Aviation|date=December 2007|issue= 245|pages=pp. 41–42|publisher=Phantom Media|location=Canberra|issn=08130876}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Australian Defence Force's [[Military intelligence|intelligence]] collection and analysis capabilities include each of the services' intelligence systems and units, two joint civilian-military [[List of intelligence gathering disciplines|intelligence gathering]] agencies and two strategic and operational-level [[intelligence analysis]] organisations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Horner_150&quot;&gt;Horner (2001), p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Australian Intelligence Community|url=http://www.igis.gov.au/aic/index.cfm|publisher=Inspector General of Intelligence and Security|accessdate=24 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each of the three services has its own intelligence assets.&lt;ref name=Horner_150 /&gt;  RAN doctrine states that &quot;all maritime units&quot; contribute to the collection of intelligence and many of the RAN's ships are capable of collecting communications and electronic transmissions. The [[Collins class submarine]]s are particularly effective in this role.&lt;ref&gt;Sea Power Centre – Australia (2005), p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; The Army's intelligence units include the 1st Intelligence Battalion, 7th Signals Regiment (Electronic Warfare), three [[Regional Force Surveillance Units]] and the [[Australian Special Air Service Regiment|Special Air Service Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;Australian Department of Defence (2006). [http://www.defence.gov.au/budget/05-06/dar/web_only_section/05_adf.html ''Defence 2005–06 Annual Report – web only section. ADF Units and Establishments'']. Accessed 6 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The RAAF's intelligence assets include the [[Jindalee Operational Radar Network]] and other air defence radars, [[No. 87 Squadron RAAF|No. 87 Squadron]] and the [[Lockheed AP-3C Orion|AP-3 Orion]] aircraft operated by [[No. 92 Wing RAAF|No. 92 Wing]].&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 31–35&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Aerospace Operational Support Group|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/groups/aosg.aspx|work=RAAF website|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=18 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Defence Intelligence Group|Defence Intelligence and Security Group]] within the Department of Defence supports the services and cooperate with the civilian agencies within the [[List of Australian intelligence agencies|Australian Intelligence Community]]. This Group consists of the [[Defence Imagery and Geospatial Organisation]] (DIGO), [[Defence Signals Directorate]] (DSD) and [[Defence Intelligence Organisation]] (DIO). The DIGO is responsible for [[GEOINT|geospatial intelligence]] and producing maps for the ADF, the DSD is Australia's [[signals intelligence]] agency and the DIO is responsible for the analysis of intelligence collected by the other intelligence agencies. The three agencies are headquartered in Canberra, though the DIGO has staff in [[Bendigo, Victoria|Bendigo]] and the DSD maintains several permanent signals collection facilities in other locations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_p123&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 125&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSD includes a Cyber Security Operations Centre (CSOC) which is responsible for protecting Defence and other Australian Government agencies against [[cyberwarfare]] attacks. The CSOC was established in January 2010 and is jointly staffed by the DSD, other sections of the ADO, [[Attorney-General's Department (Australia)|Attorney-General's Department]], [[Australian Security Intelligence Organisation]] and [[Australian Federal Police]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Defence Signals Directorate|title=Cyber Security Operations Centre|url=http://www.dsd.gov.au/_lib/pdf_doc/csoc_brochure.pdf|publisher=Defence Signals Directorate|accessdate=9 October 2010|page=5|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Berkovic |first=Nicola|title=Defence on a cyber war footing|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/nation/defence-on-a-cyber-war-footing/story-e6frg6nf-1225820171172|accessdate=9 October 2010|newspaper=The Australian|date=16 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the United States military, the ADF does not class cyberwarfare as being a separate sphere of warfare.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Welsh|first=Dylan|title=Cyber soldiers|url=http://www.smh.com.au/technology/technology-news/cyber-soldiers-20101008-16c7e.html|accessdate=9 October 2010|newspaper=The Sydney Morning Herald|date=9 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personnel==
[[File:16th Air Defence Regiment soldiers posing with RBS-70 July 2011.jpg|thumb|alt=Photograph of eight people wearing camouflage uniforms posing with a rocket launcher. Several camouflaged trucks are visible in the background.|Personnel from the Army's [[16th Air Defence Regiment, Royal Australian Artillery|16th Air Defence Regiment]] with one of the unit's [[RBS 70]] systems]]
The Australian military has been an [[Volunteer military|all-volunteer force]] since [[Conscription in Australia|the abolition of conscription in 1972]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Conscription|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/encyclopedia/conscription/|work=Encyclopedia|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=23 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both women and men can enlist in the ADF, although there are some restrictions on the positions that women may fill.&lt;ref name=Age&amp;Gender&gt;{{cite web|title=Age &amp; Gender|url=http://www.defencejobs.gov.au/recruitmentCentre/canIJoin/ageAndGender/|work=Defence Jobs|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=23 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In general, only Australian citizens can enlist in the ADF though permanent residents are accepted in &quot;exceptional circumstances&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Citizenship|url=http://www.defencejobs.gov.au/recruitmentCentre/canIJoin/citizenship/|work=Defence Jobs|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=23 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The minimum age for recruits is 17 and the retirement age is 60 for permanent personnel and 65 for reservists.&lt;ref name=Age&amp;Gender /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ADF Members Given More Career Choice|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/minister/NelsonMintpl.cfm?CurrentId=6517|work=Media Release|publisher=The Hon. Dr Brendan Nelson, Minister for Defence|accessdate=23 July 2011|date=2 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

===Personnel numbers===
In the 2010–2011 financial year the ADF had an average strength of 59,023 permanent (full-time) and 21,850 reserve (part-time) personnel.&lt;ref name=DefPBS2011&gt;Department of Defence (2011), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; In addition there were 22,166 inactive members of the Standby Reserve as at June 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Year_Book_Aust_2009-10_people&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=People|url=http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/Lookup/6D4CD661FDBA3226CA25773700169C59?opendocument|work=Year Book Australia, 2009–10|publisher=Australian Bureau of Statistics|accessdate=18 July 2010|author=Australian Bureau of Statistics|location=Canberra|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Army is the largest service, followed by the RAAF and RAN. In that time, the ADO also employed an average of 20,656 civilian [[Australian Public Service]] (APS) staff and 675 contractors.&lt;ref name=DefPBS2011/&gt; Average levels for the 2010–2011 financial year were as follows:&lt;ref name=DefPBS2011/&gt;

{| class=wikitable &lt;!-- border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; --&gt;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#efefef&quot;
|'''Service'''||'''Permanent'''||'''Active Reserve'''||'''Total'''
|-
|Navy||14,215||2,150||'''16,365'''
|-
|Army||30,235||16,900||'''47,135'''
|-
|Air Force||14,573||2,800|||'''17,375'''
|-
|'''Total'''||'''59,023'''||'''21,850'''||'''80,873'''
|}

[[Image:ADF strengths 90-06.JPG|thumb|The average permanent strengths of the services between 1990 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;Compiled from Khosa (2004), pp. 40–41 and [http://www.defence.gov.au/annualreports/ Australian Department of Defence annual reports]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
During the 2009–10 financial year 6,063 people enlisted in the ADF on a permanent basis. This represented 91% of the ADF's recruitment target for that year.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence (2010a), p. 351&lt;/ref&gt; A further 671 people enlisted as part of the gap year scheme (96% of the target) and 2,629 joined the reserves (84% of the target).&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence (2010a), pp. 353–354&lt;/ref&gt; During that financial year 4,000 people left the ADF's permanent force, representing a 7.1% separation rate.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence (2010a), p. 356&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of ADF personnel has changed over the last 20 years. During the 1990s the strength of the ADF was reduced from around 70,000 to 50,000 permanent personnel as a result of budget cuts and the commercialisation of some elements of the military. The ADF began to grow from 2000 after the defence white paper released that year called for an expansion to the military's strength. During the 2003–04 to 2005–06 financial years the strength of the ADF dropped as a result of problems with attracting further recruits. The ADF has consistently grown in all subsequent financial years, however. This growth is attributable to increased spending on recruitment and improved recruitment and retention policies. Nevertheless, some parts of the ADF are suffering from shortages of personnel (such as technicians and trades people) and demand for skilled labour in the broader economy is driving up the wages the ADF needs to pay to retain key personnel.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2009), pp. 35–38&lt;/ref&gt; As of May 2010, 20 employment categories were considered &quot;critical or perilous&quot; due to a shortage of skilled personnel, though this had been reduced from 32 such categories in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Parnell |first=Sean|title=Skill shortage threatens defence|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/skill-shortage-threatens-defence/story-e6frg8yo-1225966030939|accessdate=23 December 2010|newspaper=The Australian|date=6 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of the 2011-12 budget, Defence planned to have a strength of 58,627 full-time personnel supported by 21,397 civilians and contractors in the 2018-19 financial year.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2011), pp. 34–35&lt;/ref&gt; The Strategic Reform Program has included transferring the roles filled by several hundred ADF members to civilian APS staff as a means of reducing costs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Watt|first=David|title=Workforce|url=http://www.aph.gov.au/library/pubs/RP/BudgetReview2010-11/DefenceWorkforce.htm|work=Budget 2010–11: Defence|publisher=Parliament of Australia Parliamentary Library|accessdate=23 July 2011|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reserves===

Each of the branches of the ADF has a reserve component. These forces are the [[Royal Australian Naval Reserve]], [[Australian Army Reserve]] and [[Royal Australian Air Force Reserve]].&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2011), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; The main role of the reserves is to supplement the permanent elements of the ADF during deployments and crises, including [[natural disaster]]s. This can include attaching individual reservists to regular units or deploying units composed entirely of reserve personnel.&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2001), p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; As reservists serve on a part-time basis, they are less costly to the government than permanent members of the ADF. However, the nature of their service can mean that reservists have a lower level of readiness that regular personnel and require additional training before they can be deployed.&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2001), p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; It has historically proven difficult to set a level of training requirements which allows reservists to be rapidly deployable yet does not act as a disincentive to recruitment and continued participation.&lt;ref name=Dennis_46 /&gt; 
[[File:5-6 RVR ANZAC Day 2008.JPG|thumb|left|Members of the Army Reserve [[5th/6th Battalion, Royal Victoria Regiment]] marching on ANZAC day 2006]]

There are two main categories of reserve personnel; those in the active reserve and those in the standby reserve.&lt;ref name=Year_Book_Aust_2009-10_people /&gt; Members of the active reserve have an annual minimum training obligation.&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2001), p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; Army and RAAF reservists may also volunteer for the high readiness reserve; this category of reservists have higher training and active service obligations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Categories of Service&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Categories of Service|url=http://www.defencereserves.com/aspx/categories_of_service.aspx|work=Defence Reserves Support|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=24 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DoD_2009_90&quot;&gt;Department of Defence (2009), p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the standby reserve are not required to undertake training, and would only be called up in response to a national emergency or to fill a specialised position. Most standby reservists are former full-time members of the ADF.&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2001), p. 58&lt;/ref&gt;

While Australian Naval Reserve personnel are assigned to permanent units, most members of the Army Reserve and Air Force Reserve are members of reserve units. Most of the RAAF's reserve units are not capable of being deployed, however, and reserve personnel are generally attached to regular air force units during their periods of active service.&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2001), pp. 36, 61, 65, 76&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, the Army Reserve is organised into permanent units, though it is unlikely that these would be deployed in their entirety.&lt;ref&gt;ANAO (2001), pp. 36, 45&lt;/ref&gt; There have been long-running debates over whether the Army Reserve and its structure remain relevant to modern warfare.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis_46&quot;&gt;Dennis et al (2008), p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; 

The ADF's increased activities since 1999 and shortfalls in recruiting permanent personnel has led to reservists being more frequently called to active service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grey&quot; /&gt; This has included large scale domestic deployments, which have included providing security for major events such as the [[2000 Summer Olympics]] and responding to natural disasters. Large numbers of reserve personnel have also been deployed as part of ADF operations in Australia's region; this has included the deployment of Army Reserve [[Company (military unit)|rifle companies]] to East Timor and the Solomon Islands. Smaller numbers of reservists have taken part in operations in locations distant from Australia.&lt;ref name=DoD_2009_90 /&gt; Notably, companies of the Army Reserve [[1st Commando Regiment (Australia)|1st Commando Regiment]] have regularly been deployed to Afghanistan as part of the Special Operations Task Group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Afghanistan : International Security Assistance Force|journal=Australian &amp; NZ Defender|year=2009|volume=No. 68|issue=Summer 2009|page=p. 28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Training===
Individual training of Australian servicemen and women is generally provided by the services in their own training institutions. Each service has its own training organisation which manages this individual training. Where possible, however, individual training is increasingly being provided through tri-service schools.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt;

Military academies include [[HMAS Creswell|HMAS ''Creswell'']] for the Navy, [[Royal Military College, Duntroon]] for the Army, and the Officer Training School – [[RAAF Base East Sale]] for the Air Force. The [[Australian Defence Force Academy]] is a Tri-Service university for officer cadets of all services wishing to attain a university degree through the Australian Defence Force. Navy recruit training is conducted at [[HMAS Cerberus (naval base)|HMAS ''Cerberus'']], Army recruits are trained at the [[Army Recruit Training Centre]] and Air Force recruits at [[RAAF Base Wagga]].&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 294–301.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women in the ADF===
{{Main|Women in the Australian military}}
[[File:RAAF airwoman performing preflight checks of a C-130.jpg|thumb|alt=A woman wearing a camouflaged military uniform sitting in the cockpit of an aircraft|A female RAAF pilot conducting pre-flight checks of a C-130 Hercules deployed to the Middle East in 2009]]
Women first served in the Australian military during World War II when each service established a separate female branch. The RAAF was the first service to fully integrate women into operational units, doing so in 1977, with the Army and RAN following in 1979 and 1985 respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Horner (2001), pp. 321–324.&lt;/ref&gt; The ADF initially struggled to integrate women, with integration being driven by changing Australian social values and Government legislation rather than a change in attitudes within the male-dominated military.&lt;ref&gt;Joan Beaumont (2001). ''Australian Defence Sources and Statistics''. Oxford University Press, Melbourne, p. 357.&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of positions available to women in the ADF has increased over time. Although servicewomen were initially barred from combat positions, these restrictions began to be lifted in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Parliamentary Library [http://www.aph.gov.au/library/intguide/fad/women_armed.htm Women in the armed forces: the role of women in the Australian Defence Force]. Accessed 16 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010 approximately 92% of employment categories and 84% of positions in the ADF were available to females as well as males. The only positions which women are currently excluded from are those in which there is a high probability of 'direct combat', which includes all [[infantry]] positions and other positions in which there is a high probability of [[hand to hand combat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/fr/RR/Womenindefence/Roles.html|title=Roles of Women in the ADF|year=2009|work=Women in Defence|publisher=Australian Department of Defence|accessdate=12 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, while almost all positions in the Navy and Air Force are open to women, women are excluded from a high proportion of Army positions.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2004), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the expansion in the number of positions available to women and other changes which aim to encourage increased female recruitment and retention, there has been little growth in the proportion of female permanent defence personnel.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2009), p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1989–1990 financial year women made up 11.4% of the ADF personnel. In the 2008–2009 financial year women occupied 13.5% of ADF positions. During the same period the proportion of civilian positions filled by women in the Australian Defence Organisation increased from 30.8% to 42.8%.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2010), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, defence minister Joel Fitzgibbon instructed the ADF to place a greater emphasis on recruiting women and addressing barriers to women being promoted to senior roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Tom |last=Allard |title=Women, your armed forces need you |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/national/women-your-armed-forces-need-you/2008/03/23/1206206927415.html |work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |date=24 March 2008 |accessdate=24 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Plan to put women in combat roles |url=http://www.news.com.au/story/0,23599,23302398-2,00.html |publisher=News.com.au |date=2 March 2008|accessdate=23 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2011 Minister for Defence Stephen Smith announced that the Cabinet had decided to remove all restrictions on women serving in combat positions, and that this change would come into effect within five years. This decision was supported by the CDF and the chiefs of the services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Thompson|first=Jeremy|title=Women cleared to serve in combat|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2011-09-27/women-on-the-frontline/2946258|date=27 September 2011|accessdate=27 September 2011|newspaper=ABC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ethnic composition===

A high percentage of ADF personnel are drawn from the [[Anglo-Celtic]] portion of Australia's population. In 2007 the proportion of ADF personnel born in Australia and the other predominately Anglo-Celtic countries was higher than this population group's share of both the Australian workforce and overall population. As a result, analyst Mark Thomson argues that the ADF is unrepresentative of Australia's society in this regards and that recruiting more personnel from other ethnic backgrounds would improve the ADF's language skills and cultural empathy.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2009), pp. 47–49&lt;/ref&gt; The ADF is developing a new advertising campaign to attract recruits from non Anglo-Celtic backgrounds.&lt;ref name=Year_Book_Aust_2009-10_people /&gt;

The ADO is currently seeking to expand the number of [[Indigenous Australians]] it recruits and improve their retention rate.&lt;ref name=Year_Book_Aust_2009-10_people /&gt; Restrictions on Indigenous Australians' ability to enlist in the military existed until the 1970s, though hundreds of Indigenous men and women had joined the military when restrictions were reduced during the world wars. By 1992 the representation of Indigenous Australians in the ADF was equivalent to their proportion of the Australian population, though they continue to be under-represented among the officer corps. Two of the Army's three Regional Force Surveillance Units ([[NORFORCE]] and the [[Far North Queensland Regiment|51st Battalion, Far North Queensland Regiment]]) are manned mostly by Indigenous Australian reservists.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al. (2008), pp. 3–5&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 Indigenous Australians made up 1.4% of permanent ADF personnel and 1.8% of reservists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2010_81&quot;&gt;Khosa (2010), p. 81&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexuality===
{{See also|Sexual orientation and military service#Australia}}
Like many of its allies, Australia allows gay men and lesbians to serve openly. Openly gay and lesbian personnel were banned from the ADF until November 1992 when the Australian Government decided to remove this prohibition. The heads of the services and most military personnel opposed this change at the time, and it caused considerable public debate.&lt;ref&gt;Grey (2008), p. 275&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dennis_264&quot;&gt;Dennis et al (2008), p. 264&lt;/ref&gt; 

Opponents of lifting the ban on gay and lesbian personnel argued that doing so would greatly harm the ADF's cohesiveness and cause large numbers of resignations. This did not eventuate, however, and the reform caused relatively few problems.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis et al (2008), pp. 264–265&lt;/ref&gt; A 2000 study found that lifting the ban on gay service did not have any negative effects on the ADF's morale, effectiveness or recruitment and retention and may have led to increased productivity and improved working environments.&lt;ref&gt;Belkin and McNichol (2000)&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1&amp;nbsp;January 2009 same-sex couples have had the same access to military retirement pensions and superannuation as opposite-sex couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Defence law changes recognise same-sex couples|url=http://abc.gov.au/news/stories/2008/12/18/2450532.htm?site=news|accessdate=5 September 2010|publisher=ABC News|date=18 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Defence expenditure and procurement==
===Current expenditure===
{{See also|Australian federal budget}}
The Australian Government allocated {{A$|26.5 billion}} to the Australian Defence Organisation in the 2011–2012 financial year. This level of expenditure is equivalent to approximately 1.8% of Australian [[Gross Domestic Product]] and 7.3% of the Government's planned expenditure over the 2011–2012 financial year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson_2011_vi&quot;&gt;Thomson (2011), p. vi&lt;/ref&gt; In broad terms, 31.1% of the 2011–2012 defence budget will be allocated to personnel expenses, 35.4% to operating costs and 26.6% to investment.&lt;ref name=Thomson_2011_vi /&gt;

The 2009 defence white paper included a commitment to increase defence spending by 3% in real terms each year over a 21 year period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomson_2011_viii&quot;&gt;Thomson (2011), p. viii&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the white paper also specified that defence would be required to undertake a package of reforms named the 'Strategic Reform Program' which aimed to save {{A$|20.6 billion}} over ten years through improvements to management practices and other efficiencies.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2011), p. 119&lt;/ref&gt; While the amount of money allocated to defence in the 2011–2012 budget was 4.2% higher in real terms than that provided in the previous financial year, defence was required to hand back {{A$|1.5 billion}} which it had failed to spend in previous years. A further {{A$|1.3 billion}} of previously planned investment expenditure was deferred until after 2014 and the long-range estimated expenditure on defence was reduced by {{A$|3.9 billion}} over the ten years from 2011.&lt;ref name=Thomson_2011_vi /&gt; These reductions are due to delays in many of the capital projects specified in the white paper.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2011), pp. vi–ix&lt;/ref&gt;

In relative terms, Australia's defence expenditure as a proportion of GDP is greater than that of most developed Western nations, but is smaller than the proportion allocated to defence by Australia's larger neighbours. The [[Stockholm International Peace Research Institute]] has estimated that Australia's defence spending in 2010 was the 13th highest of any country in [[purchasing power parity]] terms.&lt;ref&gt;SPRI (2011), Constant (2009) USD table&lt;/ref&gt; As a proportion of GDP Australia's defence spending ranks as 57th of the countries for which data is available.&lt;ref name=&quot;SPRI_GDP_2011&quot;&gt;SPRI (2011), Share of GDP table&lt;/ref&gt;

===Long term procurement projects===

The ''Defence Capability Plan'' (DCP) sets out the ADF's long term capital programs. DCPs have been regularly produced since 2000.&lt;ref name=Thomson_2011_vi /&gt; The current public version DCP, which was released in 2009 and updated in late 2010, contains 140 projects and phases of projects which have a total estimated cost of {{A$|153 billion}} in 2010 dollars. Work on these projects will take place between 2011 and 2020.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence (2010), pp. iii, 1&lt;/ref&gt; The most expensive and complex projects in the DCP are the [[Collins class submarine replacement project‎]], the purchase of at least 72 F-35 Lightning II fighters, upgrades to the RAAF's Wedgetail AEW&amp;C aircraft, the replacement of many of the ADF's wheeled vehicles, the replacement of the Army's ASLAV and M-113s and the development of new [[Planned Australian offshore combatant vessel|offshore combatant vessels]] and frigates to replace most of the RAN's surface combatants.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence (2010), p. 309&lt;/ref&gt;

The increasing cost of defence equipment poses a challenge to the ADF. The [[Australian Strategic Policy Institute]] estimates that the cost of purchasing and operating the equipment in the ''Defence Capability Plan'' may exceed the projected Defence Budget. If additional resources are not made available to correct this funding shortfall the government may be forced to reduce the ADF's size.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2006a).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current equipment==
{{See also|Current Royal Australian Navy ships|Weaponry of the Australian Army|Royal Australian Air Force#Current strength|l3=Current aircraft of the RAAF}}
[[File:US Navy 100624-N-6854D-014 HMAS Newcastle (FFG 06) pulls into Joint Base Pearl Harbor-Hickam, Hawaii, to support RIMPAC 2010.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A grey warship sailing near the shoreline.|''Adelaide'' Class frigate {{HMAS|Newcastle|FFG 06|6}}]]
While the Australian Defence Force seeks to be a high-technology force, much of its equipment is approaching obsolescence and is scheduled to be replaced or upgraded in the near future.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2005b), pp. 9–10&lt;/ref&gt; Australia [[Australia and weapons of mass destruction|does not possess]] [[weapons of mass destruction]] and has ratified the [[Biological Weapons Convention]], [[Chemical Weapons Convention]] and [[Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty]].&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 98–99&lt;/ref&gt; Although most of the ADF's weapons are only used by single service, there is an increasing emphasis on commonality. The three services use the same small arms and the [[Browning Hi-Power|FN Herstal 35]] is the ADF's standard hand gun, the [[F88 Austeyr]] the standard rifle, the [[F89 Minimi]] the standard light support weapon, the [[FN MAG|FN Herstal MAG-58]] the standard light machine gun and the [[M2 Browning machine gun|Browning M2HB]] the standard heavy machine gun.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

The Royal Australian Navy operates a large number of ships and submarines. The Navy's 12 frigates are its most capable surface combatants. The four remaining [[Adelaide class frigate|''Adelaide'' class frigates]] provide the RAN's surface offensive capability, while the eight [[Anzac class frigate|''Anzac'' class frigates]] are general purpose escorts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies&quot;&gt;Davies (2008), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; The RAN's submarine force has six [[Collins class submarine|''Collins'' class submarines]], which currently rank among the most effective conventional submarines in the world.&lt;ref&gt;Frame (2004), pp. 284–285.&lt;/ref&gt; There are currently 14 [[Armidale class patrol boat]]s for border security and fisheries patrol duties in Australia's northern waters. The RAN's amphibious force comprises the Landing Ship Heavy {{HMAS|Tobruk|L 50|6}} and six [[Balikpapan class LCH|''Balikpapan'' class Landing Craft Heavy]]. The Navy's minesweeping force operates six [[Huon class minehunter|''Huon'' class minehunters]], two of which are currently operating as patrol boats, and three auxiliary minesweepers. An auxiliary tanker, a fleet replenishment ship, and six survey vessels support these combatants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies&quot;/&gt; As at December 2010 the Fleet Air Arm's helicopter force comprised 16 [[Sikorsky SH-60 Seahawk|Seahawk]]s for anti-submarine tasks, six [[Westland Sea King|Sea King]] and five [[NHIndustries NH90|MRH 90]] transport helicopters and 13 [[Eurocopter AS350|Squirrel]] and three [[AgustaWestland AW109|AW109]]s for training purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flightglobal_Insight_2010_10&quot;&gt;Flightglobal Insight (2010), p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Australian Bushmaster Afghanistan March 2010 crop.jpg|thumb|alt=A camouflaged military vehicle on top of a hill. The valley behind the vehicle contains several complexes of buildings and flowering trees. A steep mountain range is in the background|An Australian Army Bushmaster PMV in Afghanistan]]
The Australian Army is primarily a [[light infantry]] force equipped with equipment which may be carried by individual soldiers. However, the Army's equipment includes a substantial quantity of armoured vehicles and artillery. Moreover, the Army is introducing additional armoured vehicles into service as part of the 'hardened and networked army' initiative.&lt;ref name = &quot;AA_Hard_Network&quot;&gt;Australian Army [http://www.defence.gov.au/ARMY/HNA/Home.htm The Hardened and Networked Army]. Accessed 17 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The Army's [[Armoured warfare|armoured]], [[Mechanised infantry|mechanised]] and [[Motorised infantry|motorised]] units are currently equipped with 59 [[M1A1 Abrams]] main battle tanks, 774 [[M113 armored personnel carrier|M113]] armoured personnel carriers (including vehicles in store), and 257 [[ASLAV]] armoured reconnaissance vehicles. 838 [[Bushmaster PMV|Bushmaster Protected Mobility Vehicles]] are being introduced into service. The Army's artillery holdings consist of 109 [[L118 Light Gun|L119 Hamel]] 105&amp;nbsp;mm calibre towed guns, 36 155&amp;nbsp;mm towed [[M198 howitzer]]s, an unspecified number of 81&amp;nbsp;mm mortars and 30 [[RBS-70]] surface-to-air missiles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Khosa_2011_36-37&quot;&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 36–37&lt;/ref&gt; As at December 2010 [[Australian Army Aviation]] is equipped with 91 helicopters, including 26 [[Bell OH-58 Kiowa|Kiowa]] reconnaissance helicopters, 16 of a planned 22 [[Eurocopter Tiger]] armed reconnaissance helicopters, 34 [[Sikorsky S-70|S-70A-9 Blackhawk]], six [[Boeing CH-47 Chinook|CH-47 Chinook]] and eight of a planned 41 [[NHIndustries NH90|MRH 90]] transport helicopters and a single [[Eurocopter AS350|Squirrel]].&lt;ref name=Flightglobal_Insight_2010_10 /&gt; The Army also operates several [[Boeing ScanEagle|ScanEagle]] and [[Elbit Skylark|Skylark]] unmanned aerial vehicles. In addition, the Army is equipped with 15 [[LCM-8]] watercraft to support amphibious operations.&lt;ref name=Khosa_2011_36-37 /&gt;

[[Image:F-18 refueling 070628-M-5500G-252.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Three grey jet fighters in formation. The aircraft closest to the camera has a hose attached to it.|[[F/A-18 Hornet]]s refuelling from a [[Boeing 707]] tanker]]
The Royal Australian Air Force operates combat, maritime patrol, transport and training aircraft. As at October 2011 the combat aircraft force comprised 71 [[McDonnell Douglas F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18 Hornets]]  24 [[Boeing F/A-18E/F Super Hornet|F/A-18F Super Hornets]]. The maritime patrol force was equipped with 19 AP-3C Orions and three of a planned six [[Boeing 737 AEW&amp;C|Boeing Wedgetail]] [[Airborne early warning and control]] aircraft had been accepted into service. The air transport force operated 21 [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules|C-130 Hercules]] and five [[Boeing C-17 Globemaster III|C-17 Globemaster III]]s. The RAAF also operates three [[Bombardier Challenger 600|Bombardier Challenger]] and two [[Boeing Business Jet]] [[Boeing 737|737]] aircraft as [[Royal Australian Air Force VIP aircraft|VIP transports]]. One of five [[Airbus]] [[Airbus A330 MRTT|KC-30B Multi-Role Tanker Transports]] being introduced into service. The RAAF also operates 67 [[Pilatus PC-9]] and 33 [[Hawker-Siddeley Hawk|Hawk 127]] training aircraft. Nine [[Beechcraft Super King Air|Beechcraft B300 King Air]] are used for training and transport tasks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flightglobal_Insight_2010_9&quot;&gt;Flightglobal Insight (2010), p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; Twelve of the Super Hornets are being modified during production to allow them to be upgraded to [[EA-18G Growler]] standard at a later date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,25114315-31477,00.html|title=Half of Super Hornets shipment to be made electronic warfare ready|last=AAP|date=27 February 2009|publisher=The Australian|accessdate=2009-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current bases==
[[File:HMAS Ballarat and another Anzac Class frigate June 2011.JPG|thumb|alt=Colour photo of two grey-painted warships moored alongside a wharf. A large crane and several buildings are visible behind the ships.|[[HMAS Ballarat (FFH 155)|HMAS ''Ballarat'']] and another ''Anzac'' class frigate moored at Fleet Base East]]
{{Main|List of Australian military bases}}
The Australian Defence Force maintains 60 major bases and many other facilities across all the [[states and territories of Australia]]. These bases occupy millions of hectares of land, giving the ADO Australia's largest real estate portfolio. In addition, [[Defence Housing Australia]] manages around 17,000 residences which are occupied by members of the ADF.&lt;ref name=Year_Book_Aust_2009-10_people /&gt; While most of the Army's permanent force units are based in [[northern Australia]], the majority of Navy and Air Force units are based near [[Sydney]], [[Brisbane]] and [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]]. Few ADF bases are currently shared by different services. Small Army and RAAF units are also located at [[RMAF Base Butterworth|Royal Malaysian Air Force Base Butterworth]].&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2010), pp. 16–35&lt;/ref&gt;

The administrative headquarters of the ADF and the three services is located in [[Canberra]] alongside the main offices of the Department of Defence and Defence Materiel Organisation and the interim headquarters of Joint Operations Command. JOC and the other operational headquarters will be co-located near [[Bungendore, New South Wales]] as part of the Headquarters Joint Operations Command Project.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Department of Defence, [http://www.defence.gov.au/id/hqjoc/purpose.htm Headquarters Joint Operations Command Project – Project Purpose]. Accessed 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Royal Australian Navy has two main bases; [[Fleet Base East]] in Sydney and [[Fleet Base West]] near Perth. The Navy's operational headquarters, Fleet Headquarters, is located adjacent to Fleet Base East. The majority of the Navy's patrol boats are based at [[HMAS Coonawarra|HMAS ''Coonawarra'']] in [[Darwin, Northern Territory]] with the remaining patrol boats and the hydrographic fleet located at {{HMAS|Cairns|naval base|6}} in [[Cairns]]. The [[Fleet Air Arm (RAN)|Fleet Air Arm]] is based at {{HMAS|Albatross|air station|6}} near [[Nowra, New South Wales]].&lt;ref&gt;Royal Australian Navy (2006), pp. 44–47.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australian Army's regular units are concentrated in a small number of bases, most of which are located in Australia's northern states. The Army's operational headquarters, Land Command, is located at [[Victoria Barracks, Sydney|Victoria Barracks]] in Sydney. Most elements of the Army's three regular brigades are based at [[Robertson Barracks]] near Darwin, [[Lavarack Barracks]] in [[Townsville]], [[Queensland]], and [[Gallipoli Barracks]] in Brisbane. The Deployable Joint Force (Land) Headquarters is also located at Gallipoli Barracks. Other important Army bases include the [[Oakey Army Aviation Centre|Army Aviation Centre]] near [[Oakey, Queensland]], [[Holsworthy Barracks]] near Sydney, [[Woodside Barracks]] near [[Adelaide, South Australia]] and [[Campbell Barracks (Australia)|Campbell Barracks]] in Perth. Dozens of [[Australian Army Reserve|Army Reserve]] depots are located across Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Department of Defence [http://www.defence.gov.au/budget/05-06/dar/downloads/2005-2006_Defence_DAR_21_additional.pdf ''2005–06 Defence Annual Report – Web Section''], p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Royal Australian Air Force maintains a number of air bases, including three which are only occasionally activated. The RAAF's operational headquarters, [[RAAF Air Command|Air Command]], is located at [[RAAF Base Glenbrook]] near Sydney. The Air Force's combat aircraft are based at [[RAAF Base Amberley]] near [[Ipswich, Queensland]], [[RAAF Base Tindal]] near [[Katherine, Northern Territory]] and [[RAAF Base Williamtown]] near [[Newcastle, New South Wales]]. The RAAF's maritime patrol aircraft are based at [[RAAF Base Edinburgh]] near Adelaide and most of its transport aircraft are based at [[RAAF Base Richmond]] in Sydney. RAAF Base Edinburgh is also home to the control centre for the [[Jindalee Operational Radar Network]]. Most of the RAAF's training aircraft are based at [[RAAF Base Pearce]] near Perth with the remaining aircraft located at [[RAAF Base East Sale]] near [[Sale, Victoria]] and RAAF Base Williamtown. The RAAF also maintains a network of bases in northern Australia to support operations to Australia's north. These bases include [[RAAF Base Darwin]] and [[RAAF Base Townsville]] and three [[RAAF Bare Bases|'bare bases']] in [[Queensland]] and [[Western Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2011), pp. 28–35, 48&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF Bases&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=RAAF Bases|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/bases/index.aspx|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force|accessdate=14 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the RAAF's operational bases, only Tindal is located near an area in which the service's aircraft might feasibly see combat. While this protects the majority of the RAAF's assets from air attack, most air bases are poorly defended and aircraft are generally hangered in un-hardened shelters.&lt;ref&gt;Peacock and von Rosenbach (2011), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;

==Domestic responsibilities==
The Australian Defence Force has a number of domestic responsibilities. In most of these tasks the ADF supports the relevant civilian authorities. These responsibilities are typically undertaken by specialised elements of the ADF, though the services' combat elements can be deployed within Australia in response to major emergencies.
[[File:HMAS Albany 2010.jpg|thumb|alt=A grey warship underway. Land is visible in the background.|left|The Navy's [[Armidale class patrol boat|''Armidale'' class patrol boats]] ({{HMAS|Albany|ACPB 86|6}} pictured) are mainly used for border and fisheries patrol tasks&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sea Power Centre Australia|title=Welcome to the Armidale Class|url=http://www.navy.gov.au/Publication:Semaphore_-_Issue_4,_2006|work=Semaphore – Issue 4,&amp;nbsp;February 2006|publisher=Royal Australian Navy|accessdate=17 October 2010|date=February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The ADF makes a significant contribution to Australia's domestic maritime security. ADF ships, aircraft and Regional Force Surveillance Units conduct patrols of northern Australia in conjunction with the [[Australian Customs Service]]. This operation, which is code-named [[Operation Resolute]], is commanded by the [[Border Protection Command (Australia)|Border Protection Command]] which is jointly manned by members of the ADF and Customs. Up to 400 personnel were assigned to Operation Resolute in July 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Operation RESOLUTE|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/opEx/global/opresolute/index.htm|work=Global Operations|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=18 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Protecting Australia's Offshore Maritime Areas|url=http://www.bpc.gov.au/webdata/resources/files/ProtectingAustraliasOffshoreMaritimeAreas.pdf|work=Fact sheet|publisher=Border Protection Command|accessdate=18 July 2010|author=Border Protection Command|location=Canberra|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the ADF does not have a significant nation-building role, it provides assistance to remote [[Indigenous Australian]] communities. Since 1996 the Army has regularly deployed engineer units to assist remote communities. Under this program a single [[Royal Australian Engineers|engineer squadron]] works with one community for several months each year to upgrade the community's infrastructure and provide training.&lt;ref&gt;Minister Assisting the Prime Minister for Indigenous Affairs media release [http://www.atsia.gov.au/media/media06/171106.aspx Army celebrates 10 years of service to Indigenous communities]. 17 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Army Aboriginal Community Assistance Program|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/opEx/exercises/aacap/index.htm|work=Operations and Exercises|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=18 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ADF also took part in the intervention in remote Northern Territory Indigenous communities between June 2007 and October 2008. During this operation ADF personnel provided logistical support to the [[Northern Territory National Emergency Response|Northern Territory Emergency Response Task Force]] and helped conduct child health checks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Operation OUTREACH|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/opEx/global/opoutreach/index.htm|work=Global Operations|publisher=Department of Defence|accessdate=18 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADF shares responsibility for [[counter-terrorism]] with civilian law enforcement agencies. Under the Australian National Counter-Terrorism Plan the [[Law enforcement in Australia|State and Territory police]] and emergency services have the primary responsibility for responding to any terrorist incidents on Australian territory. If a terrorist threat or the consequences of an incident are beyond the capacity of civilian authorities to resolve the ADF may be [[Military Aid to the Civil Power|'called out']] to provide support. In order to meet its counter-terrorism responsibilities the ADF maintains two elite [[Tactical Assault Group (Australia)|Tactical Assault Groups]], the [[Australian Incident Response Regiment|Incident Response Regiment]], and a company-sized high readiness group in each [[Australian Army Reserve|Army Reserve]] brigade and the [[1st Commando Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;The Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet (2004). ''[http://www.dpmc.gov.au/publications/protecting_australia/docs/protecting_australia.pdf Protecting Australia Against Terrorism]''. DPMC, Canberra, pp. 52–53.&lt;/ref&gt; While these forces provide a substantial counter-terrorism capability, the ADF does not regard domestic security as being part of its 'core business'.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Smith and Anthony Bergin (2006). ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=104&amp;pubtype=6 Australian domestic security: The role of Defence]''. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foreign defence relations==
[[File:RAF RAAF USAF C-17s 2007.jpg|thumb|A group of people wearing overalls standing together in front of three grey aircraft are visible in the background.|Australian, British and United States C-17 Globemasters and aircrew in Britain during 2007.]]
{{See also|Foreign relations of Australia}}
The Australian Defence Force cooperates with militaries around the world. Australia's formal military agreements include the [[ANZUS|ANZUS Alliance]] with the United States of America, the Closer Defence Program with New Zealand and the [[Five Power Defence Arrangements]] with [[Malaysia]], [[Singapore]], New Zealand and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2010), p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; Australia is currently developing closer security ties with Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Nazemroaya, Mahdi Darius | title=Global Military Alliance: Encircling Russia and China | publisher=Centre for Research on Globalization |date=10 May 2007 |url=http://www.globalresearch.ca/index.php?context=viewArticle&amp;code=NAZ20070510&amp;articleId=5605}}&lt;/ref&gt; ADF activities under these agreements include participating in joint planning, intelligence sharing, personnel exchanges, equipment standardisation programs and joint exercises.&lt;ref&gt;Australian Department of Defence (2002). ''[http://www.defence.gov.au/publications/f2020.pdf Force 2020].'' Australian Department of Defence, Canberra, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Australia is also a member of the [[UKUSA Community|UKUSA]] signals intelligence gathering agreement.&lt;ref&gt;Beaumont (2001), p. 457.&lt;/ref&gt;

New Zealand, Singapore and the United States maintain military units in Australia. The New Zealand and Singaporean forces are limited to small training units at ADF bases, with the New Zealand contingent comprising nine [[New Zealand Army|Army]] personnel involved in air navigation training.&lt;ref name=&quot;IISS_2010_396&quot;&gt;International Institute for Strategic Studies (2010), p. 396&lt;/ref&gt; Two [[Republic of Singapore Air Force]] pilot training squadrons are based in Australia; 126 Squadron at the [[Oakey Army Aviation Centre]] and 130 Squadron at RAAF Base Pearce.&lt;ref&gt;Scramble.nl [http://www.scramble.nl/sg.htm Republic of Singapore Air Force]. Accessed 7 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Singapore Army]] also uses the [[Shoalwater Bay|Shoalwater Bay Military Training Area]] in Queensland for annual large-scale exercises.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Exchange of notes to bring into force the new Shoalwater Bay Training Area Agreement |publisher=Australian High Commission in Singapore |date=15 February 2006 |url=http://www.singapore.embassy.gov.au/sing/Shoalwater.html |accessdate=2007-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two United States intelligence and communications facilities are located in Australia; the [[Pine Gap]] satellite tracking station near [[Alice Springs]] and [[Naval Communication Station Harold E. Holt]] near [[Exmouth, Western Australia]]. Pine Gap is jointly operated by Australian and United States personnel and Naval Communication Station Harold E. Holt has been an exclusively Australian-operated facility since 1999. In early 2007 the Australian Government approved the construction of a new unmanned US communications installation at the Defence Signals Directorate [[Australian Defence Satellite Communications Station]] facility near [[Geraldton, Western Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Australia-US Joint Communications Facility to be hosted at Geraldton |publisher=Australian Department of Defence |date=15 February 2007 |url=http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/NelsonMintpl.cfm?CurrentId=6375 |accessdate=2007-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Military]] also frequently uses Australian exercise areas and these facilities have been upgraded to support joint Australian-United States training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Craig |last=Skehan |coauthors=Marian Wilkinson and Lindsay Murdoch |title=New bases for US forces in far north Australia |url=http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/07/08/1089000295713.html?from=storylhs |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |date=9 July 2004 |accessdate=2007-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to these facilities, between 200 and 300 US Military personnel are posted to Australia to liaise with the ADF and in November 2011 the Australian and American Governments announced plans to rotate [[United States Marine Corps]] and [[United States Air Force]] units through bases in the Northern Territory for training purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Nicholson|first=Brendan|title=Elite northern unit gives US access in a crisis|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/obama-in-australia/elite-northern-unit-gives-us-access-in-a-crisis/story-fnb0o39u-1226197274548|accessdate=20 November 2011|newspaper=The Australian|date=17 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The ADF provides assistance to militaries in Australia's region through the Defence Cooperation Program. Under this program the ADF provides assistance with training, infrastructure, equipment and logistics and participates in joint exercises with countries in South East Asia and Oceania. The Pacific Patrol Boat Program is the largest Defence Cooperation Program activity and supports 22 [[Pacific class patrol boat]]s operated by twelve South Pacific countries. Other important activities include supporting the development of the [[Timor Leste Defence Force]] and [[Papua New Guinea Defence Force]] and supplying watercraft to the [[Armed Forces of the Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;Khosa (2010), p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; Australia also directly contributes to the defence of Pacific countries by periodically deploying warships and aircraft to patrol their territorial waters; this includes an annual deployment of RAAF AP-3 Orions to the region as part of a multi-national maritime surveillance operation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Orion casts its net in fisheries op|url=http://australianaviation.com.au/2011/11/orion-casts-its-net-in-fisheries-op/|accessdate=5 December 2011|newspaper=Australian Aviation|date=24 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Operation Kurukuru catches illegal ships|url=http://www.solomonstarnews.com/news/national/9020--operation-kurukuru-catches-illegal-ships|accessdate=5 December 2011|newspaper=Solmon Star|date=16 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under an informal agreement Australia is responsible for the defence of [[Nauru]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA_Nauru&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/nr.html|title=CIA – The World Factbook – Nauru|last=Central Intelligence Agency|year=2009|work=The World Factbook|publisher=Central Intelligence Agency|accessdate=17 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Assessment of capabilities==
The ADF's capabilities enable it to carry out a range of tasks. The size of the force that the government can deploy differs according to the likelihood of high-intensity combat and the distance from Australia. In overall terms, Dr. Mark Thomson of the [[Australian Strategic Policy Institute]] assesses the ADF's size and capability as being typical for a [[Western world|Western]] nation with Australia's economic and population base.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2005), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HMAS Collins Kockums photo.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A black submarine travelling on the surface of the sea|''Collins'' class submarine {{HMAS|Collins|SSG 73|6}}]]

The ADF has probably the most capable air and naval capabilities in the [[South-East Asia]] region. However, the small size of the Army and the age of much of the RAN and RAAF's equipment constrains Australia's ability to make large-scale deployments or engage in high-intensity combat.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2003), p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; The ADF's personnel shortages may also limit its ability to quickly conduct new deployments.&lt;ref&gt;Gregor Ferguson 'People and Logistics is the Key'. ''Australian Defence Magazine'', June 2007, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADF is highly capable of defeating direct attacks on Australia by conventional forces, though such attacks are highly improbable at present. The ADF's intelligence gathering capabilities should enable it to detect any attacking force before it reaches Australia. Once detected, the RAN and RAAF would be able to defeat the attacking force while it was still in Australia's maritime approaches. The Army and RAAF are also capable of defeating small raiding forces once they are detected.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2003), p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; The ADF currently maintains sufficient forces to meet its domestic security and counter-terrorism responsibilities.&lt;ref&gt;Smith and Bergin (2006), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The RAN and RAAF are capable of deploying significant numbers of capable ships and aircraft, these forces are large and modern enough to operate independently in a high-threat environment and would typically make up a small part of a larger international coalition force. Due to its relatively small size the Army's capability for high intensity warfare is more limited than that of the other services.
[[File:2RAR 070622-F-1644L-095.jpg|thumb|alt=A group of men wearing camouflaged military uniforms and carrying guns walking through bushland|Light infantrymen from the [[2nd Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment]]]]

As a result of these limitations, the ADF is capable of providing only relatively small, but high-quality, 'niche' forces for high intensity warfare. Such forces include the Navy's submarines, the Army's special forces and the RAAF's Orion aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2003), pp. 13–14. See also Horner (2001), p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the ADF's logistic capabilities are insufficient to independently supply such forces deployed in areas distant from Australia. As a result, the ADF can only contribute forces to high intensity warfare outside of Australia's region when larger coalition partners provide logistical support.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo (2004), p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADF is highly capable of undertaking peacekeeping operations around the world. The Navy's frigates and transport ships, the Army's light infantry battalions and the RAAF's transport aircraft are well-suited to peacekeeping. The ADF has the capability to undertake peacekeeping and low-intensity warfare operations independently in Australia's region and can sustain such deployments for a lengthy period. It is also capable of leading international peacekeeping forces in the Asia-Pacific region and the ADF is capable of defending and invading all of its Pacific neighbours and countries to the north such as the Philippines and Papua New Guinea, although the probability of this is very small with the exception of Fiji.&lt;ref&gt;Thomson (2003), pp. 14–16.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|last=Australian Army|title=The Fundamentals of Land Warfare|publisher=Australian Army|year=2008|location=Canberra|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/ARMY/PUBS/downloads/LWD_1_The_Fundamentals_of_Land_Warfare_Full.pdf}}
* {{Cite web|last=Australian Army|title=Adaptive Army Public Information Paper|url=http://www.army.gov.au/ArmyInternet/docs/Adaptive_Army_Public_Info_Paper.pdf|publisher=Australian Army|accessdate=15 November 2010|date=2008a}}
*{{cite book|last=Australian National Audit Office (ANAO)|title=Australian Defence Force Reserves : Department of Defence|year=2001|publisher=Australian National Audit Office|location=Canberra|isbn=0642442576|url=http://www.anao.gov.au/~/media/Uploads/Documents/2000%2001_audit_report_33.pdf}}
* {{cite book|last=Department of Defence|title=Force 2020|year=2002|publisher=Department of Defence|location=Canberra}}
* Department of Defence (2006). ''[http://www.defence.gov.au/budget/05-06/dar/index.htm Defence Annual Report 2005–06.]'' Australian Department of Defence, Canberra.
* {{cite web|last=Department of Defence|title=Submission to the Joint Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Inquiry into the Economic, Social and Strategic Trends in Australia's Region and the Consequences for Our Defence Requirements|url=http://www.aph.gov.au/house/committee/jfadt/esstrends/subs/sub7.pdf|publisher=Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Foreign Affairs Sub-Committee|accessdate=23 July 2011|year=2006a}} 
* Australian Department of Defence (2007a). ''[http://www.defence.gov.au/ans/2007/default.htm Australia's National Security. A Defence Update 2007]''. Australian Department of Defence, Canberra.
* {{cite book|last=Department of Defence|title=Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030|year=2009|publisher=Department of Defence|isbn=978-0-642-29702-0|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/whitepaper/}}
* {{cite book|last=Department of Defence|title=Defence Capability Plan 2009 : December 2010 Update|year=2010|publisher=Department of Defence|location=Canberra|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/dmo/id/dcp/DCP_DEC10.pdf}}
* {{cite book|last=Department of Defence|title=Defence Annual Report 2009-10 Volume 1 Department of Defence|year=2010a|publisher=Department of Defence|isbn=978-0-642-29733-4|location=Canberra}}
* {{Cite book|title=Portfolio Budget Statements 2011–12: Defence Portfolio|year=2011|publisher=Commonwealth of Australia|isbn=978-0-642-29739-6|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/budget/11-12/pbs/2011-2012_Defence_PBS_Complete.pdf|author=Department of Defence|location=Canberra}}
* Australian National Audit Office (2002). [http://www.anao.gov.au/uploads/documents/2001-02_Audit_Report_38.pdf ''Management of Australian Defence Force Deployments to East Timor'']. ANAO, Canberra. ISBN 0-642-80620-9
* Australian Department of the Prime Minister and Cabinet (2004). ''[http://www.dpmc.gov.au/publications/protecting_australia/docs/protecting_australia.pdf Protecting Australia Against Terrorism]''. DPMC, Canberra.
* Australian Parliamentary Library (2000) [http://www.aph.gov.au/library/intguide/fad/women_armed.htm Women in the armed forces: the role of women in the Australian Defence Force].
* {{Cite book |first=Joan |last= Beaumont |year=2001 |title=Australian Defence Sources and Statistics |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Melbourne |isbn=0-19-554118-9}}
* {{cite web|last=Belkin|first=Aaron |title=The Effects of Including Gay and Lesbian Soldiers in the Australian Defence Forces: Appraising the Evidence|url=http://www.palmcenter.org/publications/dadt/the_effects_of_including_gay_and_lesbian_soldiers_in_the_australian_defence_forces_appraising_the_evidence|publisher=Palm Center|accessdate=24 September 2010|coauthors=McNichol, Jason |year=2000}}
* Davies, Andrew (2008). ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=162&amp;pubtype=9 ADF capability review: Royal Australian Navy]. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra.
* {{Cite web|last=Davies|first=Andres|title=Army capability review 2010|url=http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=257&amp;pubtype=9|work=Policy Analysis|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|accessdate=18 June 2010|year=2010}}
* {{Cite book|last=Dennis|first=Peter|coauthors=et al.|title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History|publisher=Oxford University Press Australia &amp; New Zealand|location=Melbourne|year=2008|edition=Second|isbn=978-0-19-551784-2}}
*{{cite web|last=Flightglobal Insight|title=World Air Forces 2010|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/airspace/media/reports_pdf/world-air-forces-2010-78877.aspx|work=Flight Insight Reports |publisher=Flightglobal Insight|accessdate=18 December 2010|year=2010}}
* {{Cite book |last=Frame |first=Tom |authorlink=Tom Frame (bishop) |title=No Pleasure Cruise. The Story of the Royal Australian Navy |year=2004 |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Sydney |isbn=1-74114-233-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Grey|first=Jeffrey|title=A Military History of Australia|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Port Melbourne|isbn=9780521697910|edition=Third}}
* Henry, Ken (2005) [http://www.ada.asn.au/defender/Summer%2005-06/Australia's%20Defence%20to%202045%20(Henry).pdf 'Australia's Defence to 2045: The Macro-economic Outlook'] in ''Defender'', Spring 2005. Pages 19–24.
* {{Cite book|last=Horner|first=David|title=Making the Australian Defence Force|series=The Australian Centenary History of Defence Volume IV|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Melbourne|year=2001|isbn=0-19-554117-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=International Institute for Strategic Studies|title=The Military Balance 2010|year=2010|publisher=Routledge|location=London}}
* {{Cite book|last=International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS)|title=The Military Balance 2011|year=2011|publisher=Routledge|location=London|issn=14799022}}
* Joint Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade (2000). ''[http://www.aph.gov.au/house/committee/jfadt/army/armyindx.htm From Phantom to Force: Towards a More Efficient and Effective Army]''. The Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia, Canberra. ISBN 0-642-36628-4
* {{Cite book|last=Khosa|first=Raspal|title=Australian Defence Almanac 2004–2005|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|location=Canberra|year=2004|issn=1449-9355|url=http://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/3124080}}
* {{Cite book|last=Khosa|first=Raspal|title=Australian Defence Almanac 2006–2007|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|location=Canberra|year=2006|url=http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=100&amp;pubtype=8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Khosa|first=Raspal|title=Australian Defence Almanac 2010–2011|year=2010|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|issn=14499355|url=http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=263&amp;pubtype=8|location=Canberra}}
* {{Cite book|last=Khosa|first=Raspal|title=Australian Defence Almanac 2011-2012|year=2011|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|issn=|url=http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=303&amp;pubtype=8|location=Canberra}} 
* {{Cite book|last=Palazzo|first=Albert|title=Battles Near and Far. A Century of Overseas Deployment. The 2004 Chief of Army Military History Conference|editor=Dennis, Peter and Grey, Jeffrey|publisher=Army History Unit|location=Canberra|year=2005|chapter=Organising and Dispatching the ADF's Expeditionary Force for the War in Iraq|isbn=0-9757669-0-2|isbn-status=May be invalid – please double check}}
*{{cite book|last=Peacock|first=Lindsay|coauthors=von Rosenbach, Alexander|title=Jane's World Air Forces, Issue Thirty Four|year=2011|publisher=IHS Jane's|location=Coulsdon, UK|issn=17482526}}
* Royal Australian Navy (2006) [http://www.navy.gov.au/Publication:Australia%27s_Navy_Today ''Australia's Navy Today'']
* Sea Power Centre – Australia (2005). ''[http://www.navy.gov.au/Publication:Navy_Contribution_to_Australian_Maritime_Operations The Navy Contribution to Australian Maritime Operations (RAN Doctrine 2 – 2005)].'' Defence Publishing Service, Canberra. ISBN 0-642-29615-4.
* Smith, Andrew; Bergin, Anthony (2006). ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=104&amp;pubtype=6 Australian domestic security: The role of Defence]''. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra.
* Stevens, David (editor) (2001). ''The Royal Australian Navy. A History.'' Oxford University Press, Melbourne. ISBN 0-19-555542-2.
* {{cite web|title=The SIPRI Military Expenditure Database|year=2011|url=http://milexdata.sipri.org/|publisher=Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SPRI)|accessdate=23 July 2011}}
* Tewes, Alex; Rayner, Laura; Kavanaugh, Kelly (2004) ''[http://www.aph.gov.au/library/pubs/rb/2004-05/05rb04.htm Australia's Maritime Strategy in the 21st century]''. Australian Parliamentary Library Research Brief no. 4 2004–05.
* Thomson, Mark (2003) ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=33&amp;pubtype=1 Pay Your Money &amp; Take Your Pick: Defence Spending Choices for Australia]''. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra.
* Thomson, Mark (2005). ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=73&amp;pubtype=3 The Cost of Defence. ASPI Budget Brief 2005–2006]''. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra.
* Thomson, Mark (2005b). ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=78&amp;pubtype=6 Punching above our weight? Australia as a middle power]''. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra
* Thomson, Mark (2005c). [http://www.ada.asn.au/defender/Winter%202005/Easier%20Said%20Than%20Done%20(Defender,%20Winter%202005).pdf 'Easier Said Than Done: At the Six-year Mark in Remaking the ADF'] in ''Defender'', Winter 2005.
* Thomson (2005d). [http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=66&amp;pubtype=5 ''War and Profit: Doing business on the battlefield'']. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra,
* Thomson, Mark (2006). ''[http://www.aspi.org.au/htmlver/25983Your_Defence$06/index.html Your Defence Dollar: The 2006–07 Defence Budget]''. Australian Strategic Policy Institute, Canberra.
* Thomson, Mark (2006a). [http://www.ada.asn.au/defender/Winter%202006/Planning%20on%20Hope%20or%20Pessimism%20(Defender,%20Winter%202006).pdf Defence Budget 2006/07: 'Planning on Hope or Pessimism'] in ''Defender'', Winter 2006.
* {{Cite book|last=Thomson|first=Mark|title=The Cost of Defence: ASPI Defence Budget Brief 2009–2010|year=2009|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|url=http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=215&amp;pubtype=3|location=Canberra}}
* {{cite book|last=Thomson|first=Mark|title=The Cost of Defence: ASPI Defence Budget Brief 2011-2012|year=2011|publisher=Australian Strategic Policy Institute|location=Canberra|url=http://www.aspi.org.au/publications/publication_details.aspx?ContentID=294&amp;pubtype=3}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Military of Australia}}
{{Commons category|Military of Australia}}
* [http://www.defence.gov.au Australian Defence Organisation website]
{{Australian Defence Force}}
{{Australia topics}}

[[Category:Commonwealth Government agencies of Australia]]
[[Category:Military of Australia| ]]

[[ar:القوات الدفاع الملكية الأسترالية]]
[[de:Australian Defence Force]]
[[es:Fuerza de Defensa Australiana]]
[[fr:Australian Defence Force]]
[[it:Australian Defence Force]]
[[he:כוחות ההגנה של אוסטרליה]]
[[hu:Ausztrália hadereje]]
[[ja:オーストラリア国防軍]]
[[no:Australias forsvar]]
[[pt:Forças Armadas da Austrália]]
[[ru:Силы обороны Австралии]]
[[simple:Australian Defence Force]]
[[fi:Australian puolustusvoimat]]
[[sv:Australiens försvarsstyrkor]]
[[tr:Avustralya Ordusu]]
[[uk:Австралійські Сили Оборони]]
[[vi:Lực lượng Quốc phòng Úc]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
