<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="675891" ns="0" title="Adelphi University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other|Adelphi (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox university
|image          = [[Image:Adelphi University Seal.svg|200px|Seal of Adelphi University]]
|name           = Adelphi University
|motto          = ''The Truth Shall Make Us Free''
|established    = June 24, 1896
|type           = [[Private university|Private]]
|endowment      = $86 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf |title=Part One |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president      = [[Robert A. Scott]]
|city           = [[Garden City, New York|Garden City]]
|state          = [[New York]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|coor           = {{Coord|40.7202|-73.6517|type:edu_region:US-NY|display=inline,title}}
|students       = 8,603
|undergrad      = 5,137
|postgrad       = 3,466
|staff          = 956
|campus         = [[Suburban]], {{convert|75|acre|m2}}  (304,000&amp;nbsp;m²)
|sports         = 17 Varsity Teams&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncaa.com/schools/3_Adelphi.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors		= [[Brown (color)|Brown]] and [[Gold (color)|Gold]] {{color box|#591F00}} {{color box|#FDB813}}
|nickname	= Panthers
|mascot		= Panther
|athletics	= [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]]
|affiliations	= 
|website        = [http://www.adelphi.edu/ www.adelphi.edu]
|logo           = [[Image:Adelphi University.svg|200px]]
}}
'''Adelphi University''' is a private, [[nonsectarian]] university located in [[Garden City, New York|Garden City]], in [[Nassau County, New York]], [[United States]]. It is the oldest institution of higher education on [[Long Island]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adelphi.edu/about/history.php |title=About Adelphi: Adelphi University |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date=January 7, 2011 |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the sixth year, Adelphi University has been named a “Best Buy” in higher education by the Fiske Guide to Colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;adelphi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adelphi.edu/prospective/|title=Prospective College Students |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date=2011 |accessdate=October 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university was also named a 2010 Best College in the Northeastern Region by The Princeton Review.&lt;ref name=&quot;adelphi&quot;/&gt; The institution is a national leader in preparing students to become &quot;independent, lifelong learners, and contributors to knowledge and service in an ever-changing world,&quot; and was awarded the prestigious 2010 Carnegie Classification for Community Engagement by the [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://events.adelphi.edu/news/2011/20110208.php|title=Adelphi University Receives 2010 Community Engagement Classification by the Carnegie Foundation |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date=2011 |access date=October 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. News and World Report ranked Adelphi University as #152 among Tier 1 National Universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/adelphi-university-2666 |title=Adelphi University - Best Colleges Directory/National Universities |date=2011 |work=Best Colleges 2012 |publisher=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report|U.S.News &amp; World Report LP]] |location=New York, NY  |accessdate= November 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

==History==
===Adelphi College===
Adelphi University began with the Adelphi Academy, founded in [[Brooklyn]], [[New York]] in 1863. The academy was a private preparatory school located at 412 Adelphi Street, in the [[Fort Greene, Brooklyn|Fort Greene]] neighborhood of Brooklyn, but later moved to the corner of Lafayette Avenue and Clifton Place, in [[Clinton Hill, Brooklyn|Clinton Hill]]. It was formally chartered in 1869 by the Board of Trustees of the City of Brooklyn for establishing &quot;a first class institution for the broadest and most thorough training, and to make its advantages as accessible as possible to the largest numbers of our population.&quot; One of the teachers at the Adelphi Academy was [[Harlan Fiske Stone]], who later served as the [[Chief Justice of the United States]].

In 1893, [[Charles Herbert Levermore|Dr. Charles Herbert Levermore]] was appointed as the head of Adelphi Academy. Seeking to establish a liberal arts college for the City of Brooklyn, Levermore received a charter from the Board of Regents of the State of New York, officially establishing Adelphi College on June 24, 1896. The college received its charter through the efforts of Timothy Woodruff, former Lieutenant Governor of New York and future first president of the Board of Trustees. Adelphi was one of the first coeducational institutions to receive a charter from the State of New York. At the time of its foundation, the college numbered only 57 students and 16 instructors. The Adelphi Academy continued to exist as a separate but nonetheless connected entity to the college. The new college was located in a building behind the Adelphi Academy, on the corner of St. James's Place and Clifton Place, in Brooklyn.

In 1912, Adelphi became a women's college. In 1922, the school raised over one million dollars to expand the overcrowded facilities in Brooklyn. In 1925, Adelphi College severed its ties with the Adelphi Academy, the latter closing in 1930. In 1929, the college moved from its founding location in Brooklyn to the current location of its main campus in [[Garden City, New York]]. The original three buildings of the Garden City campus, Levermore Hall, Blodgett Hall and Woodruff Hall, were designed by [[McKim, Mead and White]]. 

In 1938, the Dance Program was founded by the world famous dancer [[Ruth St. Denis]]. In 1943, the School of Nursing was established in response to the need for nurses due to American involvement in [[World War II]]. First Lady [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] presided over the opening of two federally funded residence halls on campus, in a speech entitled &quot;The Challenge of Nursing for Young Women Today.&quot;

In 1946, after World War II ended, Adelphi reverted back to a coeducational college and started admitting new students on the federal [[Servicemen's Readjustment Act (USA)|GI Bill]]. New sports teams were created following the readmission of men to the school. In 1952, the first program for clinical psychology was established at the school; it was also the forerunner to the Institute for Advanced Psychological Studies.

===Adelphi University===
In 1963, the [[University of the State of New York|New York State Board of Regents]] granted the college university status, and the name was changed to Adelphi University. In 1964, the School of Business was founded. In 1966, the Institute for Advanced Psychological Studies was founded. In 1973, the University established ABLE (Adult Baccalaureate Learning Experience) for the education of adults. Now known as University College, it was one of the earliest programs created for nontraditional students. In 1984, the Institute for Teaching and Educational Studies was founded; it became the School of Education in 1990. In 1993, the Society of Mentors was established, giving students faculty advisors that they could consult on an as-needed basis to assist them in their studies. In 1995, the Honors College was founded.

In January 1963, Adelphi Suffolk College (which had started out in 1955 offering extension courses in [[Suffolk County, New York]]) purchased the former [[W.K. Vanderbilt]] estate in [[Oakdale, New York]].  In 1968 it was spun off to [[Dowling College]] after its chief benefactor, [[Robert W. Dowling|Robert Dowling]].

Adelphi faced a serious scandal in 1996, as the school celebrated its 100th anniversary. University president Peter Diamandopoulos and the Board  of Trustees were accused of neglect of duty, misconduct and failure to carry out the educational purposes of Adelphi. The New York State Board of Regents was called in to investigate; Diamandopoulos, along with all but one of the Board of Trustees, was dismissed from office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lambert |first=Bruce |url=http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/people/d/peter_diamandopoulos/index.html |title=New York Times articles about Peter Diamandopoulos |publisher=Topics.nytimes.com |date= |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The university was in dire financial straits until the current president, Dr. [[Robert A. Scott]], was installed in the position in 2000. Scott saved the school by decreasing tuition, increasing scholarships offered for the students, and launching an advertising campaign to increase enrollment. Since that time, the school has surpassed many of its previous gains, and is said to be undergoing a new renaissance. Adelphi University has been ranked as a &quot;Best Buy&quot; college by the Fiske Guide to Colleges for the last four years for its quality education offered at a comparatively affordable price.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fiskeguide.com/fgc_8a.html Fiske Guide to Colleges – Best Buys: Private]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adelphi University also participates in the [[National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities]]'s (NAICU) [[University and College Accountability Network (U-CAN)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=member center |url=http://www.naicu.edu/member_center/adelphi |title=NAICU – President |publisher=Naicu.edu |date= |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Breast cancer support program==
The university's School of Social Work is home to the Adelphi New York Statewide Breast Cancer Hotline and Support Program, which marks its 30th anniversary in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adelphi.edu/nysbreastcancer/ |title=Adelphi NY Statewide Breast Cancer Hotline and Support Program |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date=December 20, 2010 |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The program began in 1980 as the Woman-to-Woman Hotline, a free and confidential service to help women with breast cancer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adelphi.edu/nysbreastcancer/aboutus.html |title=Adelphi NY Statewide Breast Cancer Hotline and Support Program |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date= |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the second oldest breast cancer hotline in the United States; over 100 trained volunteers offer information and emotional support for women and men suffering from breast cancer. There are professional social workers, bi-lingual Spanish-speaking staff and support staff, along with support groups, educational programs and individual counseling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adelphi.edu/nysbreastcancer/youcando.html |title=Adelphi NY Statewide Breast Cancer Hotline and Support Program |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date= |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Levermore Global Scholars program==
The Levermore Global Scholars program (LGS) is a unique program of distinction at Adelphi University that brings together students interested in global studies and civic engagement  and committed to improving and understanding the world they live in. This innovative program emphasizes global learning, civic engagement, community service  in the local organizations, study and service abroad and scholars’ involvement in designing and leading their own initiatives with a social or global cause. Open to all majors, LGS selects students on the basis of their interest in global learning, study and service abroad, their experience with community work and their leadership potential.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adelphi.edu/levermorescholars/ |title=Levermore Global Scholars Program: Adelphi University |publisher=Adelphi.edu |date=January 10, 2011 |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
===Colleges, schools and degrees===
*College of Arts and Sciences: [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]], [[Bachelor of Science|B.S.]], [[Bachelor of Fine Arts|B.F.A.]], [[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|M.A.]], [[Master of Science|M.S.]], [[Master of Fine Arts|M.F.A.]], [[Doctor of Arts|D.A.]], [[Doctor of Audiology|Au.D.]]
*University College: A.A., A.S., A.A.S., B.A., B.S., Post-baccalaureate Certificate, M.S.
*Gordon F. Derner Institute of Advanced Psychological Studies: [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]], [[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|M.A.]], [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]]
*Ruth S. Ammon School of Education: B.S.Ed., M.A.
*School of Business: B.B.A., M.B.A., M.S./M.B.A. (with School of Nursing).
*School of Nursing: B.S., M.S., M.S./M.B.A. (with School of Business), Ph.D.
*School of Social Work: B.S.W., [[Master of Social Work|M.S.W.]], D.S.W., Ph.D.
*Honors College

===Joint degree programs===
*'''Dentistry:''' [[Tufts University School of Dental Medicine]] (4-4 B.S./[[Doctor of Dental Medicine|D.M.D.]]), [[New York University College of Dentistry]] (3–4 B.S./[[Doctor of Dental Surgery|D.D.S.]])
*'''Engineering:''' [[Columbia University]], [[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]], [[Stevens Institute of Technology]] (3-2 B.A./B.S.)
*'''Environmental Studies:''' [[Columbia University]] (3-2 B.A./B.S. or 4-2 B.A./M.S.)
*'''Law:''' [[New York Law School]] (3-3 B.A. or B.S./[[Juris Doctor|J.D.]])
*'''Optometry:''' [[State University of New York State College of Optometry|SUNY State College of Optometry]] (3–4 B.S./[[Optometry|O.D.]])
*'''Osteopathic Medicine:''' [[Touro College of Osteopathic Medicine]] (3–4 B.S./[[D.O.]])
*'''Physical Therapy:''' [[New York Medical College]] (4-3 B.S./D.P.T.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://academics.adelphi.edu/jointdegree/ |title=Joint Degree/Early Assurance and Early Acceptance Programs &amp;#124; Adelphi University |publisher=Academics.adelphi.edu |date=January 10, 2011 |accessdate=January 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International programs===
{{Div col|4}} 
*Adelphi in Britain
*Adelphi in The Bahamas
*Adelphi in Florence
*Adelphi in Greece
*Adelphi in Mexico
*Adelphi Civitas Global Professional Internship – Warsaw, Poland
*Adelphi in China
*Adelphi in Egypt
*Adelphi in Spain
*Adelphi in Dominican Republic
*Adelphi in Australia
 {{Div col end}}

==School facts==
===College and University Presidents===
====Adelphi College====
*Charles H. Levermore, 1896–1915
*Frank D. Blodgett, 1915–1937
*Paul Dawson Eddy, 1937–1963

====Adelphi University====
{{Div col|3}} 
*Paul Dawson Eddy, 1963–1965
*Arthur Brown, 1965–1967
*Robert Olmsted, 1967–1969
*Charles Vevier, 1969–1971
*Randall McIntyre, 1971–1972
*Timothy Costello, 1972–1985
*Peter Diamandopoulos, 1985–1997
*Igor Webb, 1997
*James A. Norton, 1997–1998
*[[Matthew Goldstein]], 1998–1999
*Steven L. Isenberg, 1999–2000
*[[Robert A. Scott]], 2000–present
 {{Div col end}}

===School seal===
The first school seal was developed with the foundation of the Adelphi Academy in 1869. Essentially, it was the current seal with several differences. First, the legend read &quot;Adelphi Academy&quot; and &quot;Brooklyn, New York&quot;. Second, the letters in the emblem were &quot;AA&quot;. Third, the eventual school motto, &quot;The Truth Shall Make Us Free&quot; did not appear. The motto was introduced in the second seal with the foundation of the college in 1896. At this time, the legend was changed to read &quot;Adelphi College&quot;, the letters &quot;AA&quot; were changed to &quot;AC&quot;, and the new date of foundation was introduced. The third seal removed the year 1869 from the emblem, reflecting the separation of the Academy and the college in 1925. The fourth seal was introduced in 1930 and changed the legend &quot;Brooklyn, New York&quot; to &quot;Garden City, New York&quot;. The fifth and current seal was introduced in 1963, reflecting the school's University status. The legend now reads &quot;Adelphi University&quot; and the letters are &quot;AU&quot;. The inscription ''Vita sine litteris mors est'', meaning &quot;Life without learning is death&quot;, appears on all variations of the school seal.

==Main campus buildings==
===Main halls===
Many of the buildings on the Garden City campus are symmetrical in nature. This is likely because [[Garden city movement|garden cities]] are typically planned symmetrically.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, John Peter. ''The Planning of the Master City.'' John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1916, p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, Woodruff Hall has a second chimney solely to preserve the symmetry of the building. 
*Alice Brown Early Learning Center

{{Div col|3}}
*''Alumnae Hall (School of Nursing)''
*Alumni House
*Center for Sports and Recreation

*''Blodgett Hall''
*Hagedorn Hall of Enterprise (School of Business)
*Harvey Hall (School of Education)
*The Hy Weinberg Center (Institute for Advanced Psychological Studies)
*Klapper Center for Fine Arts

*''Levermore Hall''

*''Performing Arts Center, which now includes the Olmsted Theatre''
*Post Hall

*''The Science Building''
*The Social Work Building
*Swirbul Library

*''The Ruth S. Harley University Center''

*''Woodruff Hall''
{{Div end}}

===Residence halls===
{{Div col|3}}
*Chapman Hall
*Earle Hall
*Eddy Hall
*Linen Hall
*Residence Hall A (formerly known as New Hall)
*Residence Hall B
*Waldo Hall
{{Div end}}

===Recognized Men's Fraternities===
{{Div col|3}}
*[[Kappa Sigma]]
*[[Phi Sigma Kappa]]
*[[Zeta Beta Tau]]
*[[Pi Lambda Phi]]
{{Div end}}

===Recognized Sororities &amp; Women's Fellowships===
{{Div col|3}}
*[[Alpha Kappa Alpha]]
*[[Delta Delta Delta]]
*[[Delta Gamma]]
*[[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]]
*[[Delta Sigma Theta]]
*[[Phi Sigma Sigma]]
*[[Sigma Delta Tau]]
*[[Sigma Lambda Upsilon]]
{{Div end}}

===Recognized co-ed Fraternal organizations===
*[[Delta Sigma Pi]]
*Theta Delta Sigma Society (Multicultural)
*[[Alpha Kappa Psi]]

===Recognized organizations &amp; clubs===
{{Div col|3}}
*[[Hellenic Society]]
*[[Gay–straight alliance|LGBTSSA]]
*[[PAWS Web Radio]]
*[[The Delphian]]
*Student Government Association
*Psychology Club
*Works in Progress
*Accounting Society
*Biology Club
*Anthropology Club
*Chemistry Club
*Criminal Justice Club
*Adelphi Ballroom Club
*Future Teachers Association
*Human Resources Society
*Math and Computer Science Club
*Nation Student Speech-Language-Hearing Association (NSSLHA)
*Spanish Club
*Latin-American Student Organization
*Pre-Law Society
*Oracle

{{Div end}}

== Athletics==
'''Adelphi University Panthers'''

The Adelphi Panthers are the athletic teams of Adelphi University. The Panthers compete at the NCAA Division I level for men's soccer and women's bowling, and NCAA Division II level for all other sports. Adelphi is a member of The Northeast-10 Conference.

The Panthers have won twelve NCAA Division II National Championships in three different sports.  The men's lacrosse team has won 7, as recently as 2001. The Women's Lacrosse team has won 4, and are the current defending Back to Back National Champions (2009, 2010). In 1974 the men's Soccer team were the National Champions. They have also won numerous individual national championships in track and field.

== Baseball==

East Coast Conference Championships 8 (1993* 1994* 1996* 1997* 1999 2007* 2009*) *''Also Tournament Champs''

NCAA Division II College World Series 4 (1993 1996 1997 1999)

The baseball team has participated in the NCAA Division II College World Series four times, as recently as 1999. The team has seen several of their players selected in the MLB first year player draft, including Bobby Lanigan who was selected in the 3rd round (92nd overall) by the Minnesota Twins in 2008 and Kieth Couch who was selected 413th overall by the Boston Red Sox in 2010. The Baseball team is currently led by Head Coach and Former New York Yankee Bullpen coach Dom Scala. Their home games are played at William J. Bonomo Memorial Field, a state of the art artificial turf complex located in the heart of the campus.

==Soccer==
Adelphi has both a men's and women's soccer team. The men's team competes at the Division I level and is a member of the Atlantic Soccer Conference.  The women's team competes at the Division II level and is a member of the Northeast-10 conference.  

The men's team won the 1974 Division II National Championship and have won 3 ASC championships in 2006, 2008, and 2009. In addition, they were also declared tournament champions in 2006 and 2009. The team produced former professional Soccer player and United States national team member Chris Armas. Armas was a USISL All-Star for the Long Island Rough Riders and in 1996 was selected in the first round of the MLS Supplemental Draft by the Los Angeles Galaxy. He also went on to play for Puerto Rico and the United States national team.

The women's soccer team has won 7 ECC championships (1996, 1997, 2001–04, 2007). They also won tournaments in 2004 and 2007.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aupanthers.com/ot/adel-champs.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
*[[Chris Armas]], professional soccer player, [[Chicago Fire S.C.|Chicago Fire]] of [[Major League Soccer]].
*[[Michael Balboni]], Deputy Secretary for Public Safety for the State of New York.
*[[Nick Cummings]], Ph.D. Past president of the [[American Psychological Association]] and founding board chairman of Care Integra, a for-profit company that works with clients to create &quot;integrated healthcare solutions.&quot; Author of ''Eleven Blunders That Have Crippled Psychotherapy in America: A Remedial Unblundering''.
*Robert G. Darling, M.D. Former White House physician during the [[Bill Clinton]] presidency.
*[[Gary Dell'Abate]], &quot;Baba Booey.&quot; Long-time producer of ''[[The Howard Stern Show]]''.
*[[Meredith Eaton-Gilden]], American psychologist and actress.
*[[Paul Ekman]], Ph.D. American psychologist.
*[[John Forslund]], Television play-by-play announcer for the [[Carolina Hurricanes]] of the [[National Hockey League|NHL]].
*[[Karen Fraction]], Broadway dancer and actress.
*[[Charles J. Fuschillo, Jr.]], [[New York State Senator]], 8th District, representing the South Shore of Nassau and Suffolk Counties.
*Stuart Goldfarb, '76, former President and Chief Executive Officer of BMG Music Service, Columbia House, Book of the Month Club, Literary Guild, Doubleday Book Club; former Executive VP, NBC.
*[[Wes Green]], professional lacrosse player, [[Los Angeles Riptide]] of [[Major League Lacrosse]], and [[San Jose Stealth]] of [[National Lacrosse League]].
*Dr. Marjorie J. Hill, Chief Executive Officer, [[Gay Men's Health Crisis]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}
*[[Alice Hoffman]], ''[[The New York Times|New York Times]]'' best-selling author.
*[[Earlene Hill Hooper]], [[New York State Assembly]]woman, 18th District, representing much of [[Nassau County, New York|Nassau County]].
*[[Jonathan Larson]], creator of the Broadway musical ''[[Rent (musical)|Rent]]''.
*[[Michael Lindsay]], actor and voice artist
*[[Gregory W. Meeks]], congressman from New York, 6th District, representing [[Queens]].
*[[Donna Orender]] (née Geils), women's pro basketball league all-star &amp; current WNBA president
*[[Billy Phillips]], former professional soccer player and coach.
*[[Gary Sullivan (soccer)|Gary Sullivan]], professional soccer player, [[Long Island Rough Riders]] of the [[USL First Division]].
*[[Rebecca Tobey]], sculptor
*[[Ed Towns|Edolphus Towns]], congressman from New York, 10th District, representing [[Brooklyn]].
*[[Robert B. Willumstad]], former Chairman and CEO, [[American International Group]].
*[[Mike Windischmann]], soccer, captain of United States World Cup team in 1990.
*[[Theresa Wolfson]] a labor economist and educator, won the John Dewey Award of the [[League for Industrial Democracy]].
*[[Nick Turturro]] Actor; younger brother of [[John Turturro]].

== Notable faculty (past and present) ==
* Anagnostis Agelarakis, American anthropologist whose discoveries of the remains of 4 women in Eleutherna, Crete conferred a distinction in ''[[Archaeology (magazine)|Archaeology]]'''s list of Top 10 discoveries of 2009.
* Robert E. Bradley, President of The Euler Society and chairman of the History of Mathematics Special Interest Group of the [[Mathematical Association of America]].
* [[Rebecca Coleman Curtis]], renowned psychoanalyst.
*[[Al Davis]] (1929-2011), served as former line coach for the Adelphi College football team from 1950 to 1951.
*[[Jerry March]] (1929–97), organic chemist and professor of chemistry; authored March's Advanced Organic Chemistry text
*Paul Mattick Jr., Professor and Chair of Philosophy. Author of &quot;Business as Usual: The Economic Crisis and the Failure of Capitalism&quot;. Son of [[Paul Mattick]] Sr.
* [[Paul Moravec]], 2004 Pulitzer Prize winner in music composition.
* [[Lawrence Raphael]], Professor of Communication Sciences and Disorders
* Alan R. Sadovnik, Professor Emeritus; Board of Governors Distinguished Service Professor, Rutgers University

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.adelphi.edu Official website]
*[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_2666_brief.php US News and World Report's profile of Adelphi]

{{Atlantic Soccer Conference}} 
{{Northeast Ten Conference}}
{{Women's Colleges that are Coeducational}}

[[Category:Adelphi University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in New York]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1896]]
[[Category:McKim, Mead, and White buildings]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges on Long Island]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Nassau County, New York]]

[[fa:دانشگاه آدلفی]]
[[no:Adelphi University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
