<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6778324" ns="0" title="Flooz.com"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| company_logo = 
| company_type = Corporation (closed)
| foundation   = 
| location     = [[New York City]]
| key_people   = 
| industry     = Internet Payments
| products     = Flooz
}}

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Flooz.jpg|thumb|150px|The Flooz.com logo with Whoopi Goldberg, its spokesperson.]] --&gt;
'''Flooz.com''' was a [[Dot-com company|dot-com]] venture, now defunct, based in [[New York City]] that went online in February 1999, promoted by comic actress [[Whoopi Goldberg]] in a series of television advertisements. Started by [[iVillage]] co-founder Robert Levitan, the company attempted to establish a [[currency]] unique to [[Internet]] merchants, somewhat similar in concept to airline [[frequent flier program]]s or grocery store stamp books. The name &quot;flooz&quot; was based upon the Arabic word for money, فلوس, ''fuloos''. Users accumulated flooz credits either as a promotional bonus given away by some internet businesses or purchased directly from flooz.com which then could be redeemed for merchandise at a variety of participating online stores. Adoption of flooz by both merchants and customers proved limited, and it never established itself as a widely recognized medium of exchange, which hindered both its usefulness and appeal. 

In 2001, Flooz.com was notified by the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] that a Russian organized crime syndicate was using Flooz and stolen credit card numbers as part of a [[money-laundering]] scheme, in which stolen credit cards were used to purchase currency and then redeemed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DB1E31F934A1575BC0A9679C8B63 E-Commerce Report; Seller of Online Currency May Have Been Victim of Fraud] New York Times, Aug 27 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Levitan has stated that fraudulent purchases accounted for 19% of consumer credit card transactions by mid-2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestandard.com/news/2008/07/21/where-are-they-now-flooz Where are they now: Flooz] The Industry Standard&lt;/ref&gt;

The company announced its closure on August 26, 2001, perceived as an early indicator of the growing [[dot-com bubble|dot-com bust]]. Upon the company's closing, all unused flooz credits became worthless and nonrefundable. Over its short history, flooz.com reportedly exhausted from $35 to $50 million in venture capital.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnet.com/4520-11136_1-6278387-1.html Top 10 dot-com flops] CNET.com&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Internet currency]]
* [[Bitcoin]]
* [[InternetCash.com]]
* [[Beenz.com]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Internet properties established in 1999]]
[[Category:Dot-com]]
[[Category:Defunct websites]]
[[Category:Electronic currencies]]
[[Category:Defunct online companies]]

{{tech-company-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
