<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6813773" ns="0" title="DYMI"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Radio_station 
 | name = DYMI Shine Radio
 | image =  
 | city = 
 | area = Barangay Simsiman, [[Calinog]], [[Iloilo]]
 | branding = Shine Radio 94.7 DYMI-FM
 | slogan = 
 | airdate = 1998
 | frequency = 94.7 MHz
 | format = [[music]], [[news]], [[Public affairs programming|public affairs]], [[religious broadcasting]]
 | power = 1,000 [[watt]]s
 | erp = 5,000 [[watt]]s
 | class = 
 | callsign_meaning = '''DY'''&lt;br&gt;'''M'''ary&lt;br&gt;'''I'''mmaculate
 | owner = [[Radio Veritas-Global Broadcasting Corporation]] &amp; [[Catholic Media Network]] 
 | website = [http://www.catholicmedianetwork.org Catholic Media Network]
 | staff = [[Dave Johnson]], [[Angela]], [[Alexander Sphere]], [[Gellou]], [[Shem Simon]]
}}

'''Shine Radio''' DYMI-FM 94.7 MHz [[Calinog]] is an [[FM broadcasting|FM]] station owned and operated by [[Radio Veritas-Global Broadcasting Corporation]] in the [[Philippines]].DYMI-FM [[studio]] is located at [[Calinog]], [[Iloilo]]. The main format of the station is music, news, public service and religious format design for all.
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:CMN.jpg]] --&gt;

&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT COPY-PASTE INFORMATION BEYOND THIS AREA! AVOID PLAGIARISM!!!--&gt;
==DYMI 94.7 Calinog History==
Every dream has a beginning ...
DYMI 94.7 began with a song

It all started with a passion for good music and uplifting praise songs, a hobby and a gift for a priest who desired to glorify God with his songs.
Today, Veritas DYMI 94.7 Shine Radio (MI stands for Mary Immaculate), stands high on its permanent location on top of cello-Carreon Heights, Brgy. Libot,  Calinog, Iloilo, because Rev. Fr. Tomas Delicana, then parish priest of Calinog for 15 years, was not contented to keep the song in his heart. He wanted it echoed through the hills of Central Panay.
94.7  Radio Station started as an experimental station in the summer of 1998, broadcasting with a power of only 100 milliwatts on the rooftop of Calinog Parish Church. The station carried the [[Holy Mass]] on air daily, to the delight of the people, especially those who, for physical or whatever reason, cannot attend Mass in Church.
As the station gained momentum and attracted the attention of the listening public, it gradually expanded its focus to include community information, public affairs programs as well as choices of great songs and well-loved selections. The local broadcasts also gathered their own captive audiences in communities reached by the programs. Some groups even formed 94.7 Fans Club which gave inspiration support to the station.
Some other people inspired by his enthusiasm and persistence, joined in building the dream. After about two years, the station enjoyed increased audience support, private placements motivated staff and crew and generous people who sponsored the upgrading of equipment and offered financial support.
It transferred location to a much higher ground at Sunshine Valley, Simsiman Calinog with the help of kind benefactors who donated parcels of land to the station.
In May 2002, DYMI 94.7 obtained a franchise from Radio Veritas and a P.A to install and maintain as a commercial radio station from the National Telecommunications Commission (NTC). It obtained a temporary permit (TP) operate in Feb 2006 and since then DYMI as been operating as a commercial radio station with a frequency of 1,000 watts at 5,000 ERP, standing side-by-side the Statue of Our Lady of Perpetual Help on top of Celo – Carreon Heights, Brgy. Libot, Calinog, Iloilo.

== Radio Veritas Stations == 
*[[Radio Veritas|DZRV 846 kHz-Manila]] 
*DWRV 1233 kHz-Bayombong 
*DZRV 90.1 MHz-Bayombong 
*[[Mother's Touch|DWRV 98.3 MHz-Naga]] 
*DWVR 1267 kHz-San Jose City, Nueva Ecija 
*DYMI 94.7 MHz-Calinog, Iloilo

{{Iloilo City FM}}

{{coord missing|Philippines}}

[[Category:Iloilo City radio stations|DYMI-FM 94.7 Calinog, Iloilo]]
[[Category:Catholic radio stations]]
[[Category:Radio stations established in 1998]]

{{Philippines-radio-station-stub}}
{{Christian-radio-station-stub}}
{{RC-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
