<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="681327" ns="0" title="Microsoft Works"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Software|
| name                   = Microsoft Works
| logo                   =   
| screenshot             = 
| caption                = Microsoft Works Task Launcher Version 9.0
| developer              = [[Microsoft]]
| latest_release_version = 9.0
| latest_release_date    =  
| latest_preview_version = 
| latest_preview_date    = 
| operating_system       = [[Microsoft Windows]]
| genre                  = [[Office suite]]
| license                = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website                = [http://www.microsoft.com/works microsoft.com/works]
| status                 = Discontinued (The product is still available for sale, however it is being phased out in favor of [[Microsoft Office]] Starter and Basic Editions)
}}

'''Microsoft Works'''  is an integrated package software that is produced by [[Microsoft]]. Works is smaller, less expensive, and has fewer features than [[Microsoft Office]] or other major office suites. Its core functionality includes a [[word processor]], a [[spreadsheet]] and a [[database management system]]. Newer versions have a [[calendar]] application and a dictionary while older releases included a [[terminal emulator]]. A 'Works Portfolio' utility offers [[Microsoft Office shared tools#Microsoft Binder|Microsoft Binder]]-like functionality.

==History==
Microsoft Works started life as Mouseworks, an integrated spreadsheet, word processor and database program, designed for the Macintosh by ex-Apple alumnus Don Williams and Rupert Lissner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Vy8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;lpg=PA6&amp;ots=b97LlyN781&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage Microsoft Works for Macintosh Expected]&lt;/ref&gt; Williams was planning to emulate the success of [[Appleworks]], a similar product for Apple II computers. However, Bill Gates and his Head of Acquisitions, [[Alan M. Boyd]], convinced Williams to license the product to Microsoft instead.&lt;ref&gt;'''''Gates'''''. By Stephen Manes, Paul Andrews, Page 328&lt;/ref&gt; Initially it was to be a scaled-down version of Office for the (then) small laptops such as the Radio Shack [[TRS-80 Model 100]] which Microsoft was developing. As laptops grew in power, however, Microsoft Works, as it was to be called, evolved as a popular product in its own right.

Through version 4.5a, Works used a ''monolithic'' program architecture whereby the Works [[Word Processor]] and [[Spreadsheet]]/[[Database]] documents ran in [[window (computing)|window]]s of the same program interface. This resulted in a small memory and disk footprint, which enabled it to run on slower computers with requirements as low as 6 MB of RAM and 12 MB free disk space.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/135878 System requirements for Works for Windows 95].&lt;/ref&gt;

Works 2000 (Version 5.0) switched to a modular architecture which opens each document as a separate instance and uses the print engine from [[Internet Explorer]]. &quot;Works Suite&quot; versions bundled personal productivity and entertainment software such as [[Microsoft Money]], [[Encarta]], [[Microsoft Streets &amp; Trips|Streets &amp; Trips]] and [[Microsoft Digital Image|Digital Image]]. These &quot;Works Suite&quot; versions also bundled a copy of [[Microsoft Word]], although there was never a newer version bundled than Word 2002. A possible reason for this might be that Word 2003 or later does not run on Windows 9x or Windows Me operating systems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/word/HA102127131033.aspx Microsoft Office Word 2003 system requirements]&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2008, &quot;Works Suite&quot; versions have been discontinued, only the standalone Works software is available at retail; while system builders and [[Original_equipment_manufacturer#Computers|OEMs]] can choose between it and Works Suite 2008 (which includes only Works and [[Microsoft Word|Word 2003]]).

==Features==
Microsoft Works has built-in compatibility for the Microsoft Office document formats (&lt;tt&gt;DOC&lt;tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;XLS&lt;/tt&gt;), including, but not limited to, the ability of the Works Word Processor to open [[Microsoft Word]] documents and the ability of the Works Spreadsheet to open [[Microsoft Excel]] workbooks. Newer versions include task panes but do not include significantly updated features. Even in the latest version (Version 9.0), the [[Windows 95]]-era icons and toolbars have not been updated to stay consistent with modern application software. Version 9.0 which offers [[Windows Vista]] compatibility, is available in two editions, an advertisement-free paid version, available in retail and OEM versions and an ad-supported free version (Works SE) which is available only to [[Original Equipment Manufacturers|OEMs]] for preinstalling on new computers. 

While its utility for larger organizations is limited by its use of [[Proprietary software|proprietary]] native .&lt;tt&gt;WKS&lt;/tt&gt; (spreadsheet), .&lt;tt&gt;WDB&lt;/tt&gt; (database) and .&lt;tt&gt;WPS&lt;/tt&gt; (word processor) file formats, the simplicity and ease of integrating database/spreadsheet data into word processor documents (e.g., [[mail merge]]) allow it to remain an option for some small and home-based business owners. Version 4.5a is particularly noted in this respect. The database management system, while a &quot;[[flat file database|flat file]]&quot;, i.e. non-[[Relational Database|relational]], allows the novice user to perform complex transformations through formulas (which use standard algebraic syntax and can be self-referential) and user-defined reports which can be copied as text to the clipboard.

By installing the [[Office 2007|2007 Office System]] Compatibility Pack, the Works Word Processor and Spreadsheet can import and export [[Office Open XML]] document formats, although they are converted rather than being operated upon natively. The Works Calendar can store appointments, integrates with the [[Windows Address Book]], as well as Address Book's successor, Windows Contacts and can remind users of birthdays and anniversaries. It supports importing and exporting [[iCalendar]] (&lt;tt&gt;.ICS&lt;/tt&gt;) files. It does not however support subscribing to iCalendar files or publishing them online via [[WebDAV]]. Up to version 8, using the Works Task Launcher, the calendar and contacts from [[Windows Address Book]] could be synchronized with portable devices. In Works 9.0, the sync capability has been removed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/940004/ Works 9 does not support synchronizing the Works Calendar and the Address Book together with portable devices]&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to its low cost ($40 retail, $10 [[Original Equipment Manufacturer|OEMs]]), companies frequently pre-installed Works on their consumer grade machines.

==Sponsored Edition==
For several years, Microsoft considered having an advertising-supported version of Works. In August 2007, it said that it would start piloting a version called '''Works SE''' (which stands for Sponsored Edition), but the company gave few details on where or how the product would be offered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Works SE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.com/8301-13860_3-9922750-56.html?tag=nefd.top|title=Microsoft quietly offering ad-funded Works|publisher=[[CNET News]]|author=Ina Fried|date=2008-04-18|accessdate=2008-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Microsoft has subsequently started offering Works SE in a limited set of countries (United States, France, Canada, Poland and the United Kingdom) with little marketing to back it up, due to its being primarily a [[pilot project]] as of April 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;Works SE&quot; /&gt; Proof of this is shown in Microsoft Office Starter 2010 that includes advertising.

==File format compatibility==
Microsoft makes file format converter filters for [[Microsoft Word]] for opening and saving to Works Word Processor format.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?displaylang=en&amp;FamilyID=bf41401e-70fa-465d-ae2e-cf44dbf05297 Microsoft Works 6–9 File Converter]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?displaylang=en&amp;FamilyID=b37a2510-6ad0-495a-8262-48305325110b Microsoft Works 4 File Converter]&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft Office Excel can import newer Works Spreadsheets because the newer Works Spreadsheet also uses the Excel format but with a different extension (*.xlr).&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/271074 Works: How to Recover Data from a Corrupted Works Spreadsheet]&lt;/ref&gt; There is an import filter for older Works 2.0 spreadsheet format (*.wks);&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rl-software.com/converter/wks-wdb-to-excel.htm MS Works Spreadsheet (*.wks) and Database (*.wdb) files to Excel 97/2000/XP/2003 Conversion: RL Software]&lt;/ref&gt; however it may be disabled in the registry by newer [[Microsoft Office]] [[Service pack]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.msdn.com/david_leblanc/archive/2008/01/04/office-sp3-and-file-formats.aspx Office SP3 and File formats]&lt;/ref&gt; As far as Works Spreadsheet 3.x/4.x/2000 (*.wks) and Works database (any version of *.wdb) files are concerned, Microsoft does not provide an import filter for Excel or Access. There are third party converters available for converting these filetypes to Excel spreadsheets: For database files (*.wdb) there is also a donateware utility;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.codealchemists.com/worksdatabaseconverter/ Works Database Converter]&lt;/ref&gt; for spreadsheet (*.wks) and database (*.wdb) files a commercial solution is available.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rl-software.com Works Spreadsheet (*.wks) and Database (*.wdb) converter]&lt;/ref&gt;

A general [[C++]] library, abandoned in 2007, which has been experimentally published as ''wps_test'',&lt;ref name=&quot;wps_test&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Ziem
  | first = Andrew
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors = 
  | title = Re: libwps for Microsoft Works .wps  
  | work = 
  | publisher = Usenet; gmane.comp.lib.wpd.devel
  | date = 19 August 2006
  | url =http://article.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lib.wpd.devel/1324
  | doi = 
  | accessdate = 2006-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; works for extracting text from many different Microsoft Works versions' documents with rudimentary formatting. It was later published as &quot;libwps&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://libwps.sourceforge.net/ libwps: a Microsoft Works file word processor format import filter library]&lt;/ref&gt; As of February 2011, no mainstream versions of [[OpenOffice.org]], [[AbiWord]], or [[KWord]] have included it for various reasons. OpenOffice.org has not included it because of restrictions with the Joint Copyright Assignment (JCA),&lt;ref&gt;[http://openoffice.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=8938 Bug 8938 – import/export filters for Microsoft Works (.wdb, .wps and .wks)]&lt;/ref&gt; but OpenOffice.org variants such as [[OxygenOffice]], [[Go-oo]], [[LibreOffice]] and [[NeoOffice]] have included libwps.  Also, libwps provides a command line converter. A commercially-available solution for converting to and from Microsoft Works files on the Macintosh platform is the MacLinkPlus product from [[DataViz]].  Free online conversion services are also available.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zamzar.com/ zamzar.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  Microsoft Works uses [[structured storage]] as a container format for its data. An [[iFilter]] for Works file formats to be indexed and searched is not yet available.

==Version history==
[[Image:Ms-works-2.0-dos.png|thumb|Microsoft Works 2.0 for DOS.]]

===Works for MS-DOS===
*Microsoft Works 1.05
*Microsoft Works 1.12
*Microsoft Works 2.0 and 2.00a
*Microsoft Works 3.0, 3.0a and 3.0b

===Works for Mac OS===
*Microsoft Works 1.0
*Microsoft Works 2.0
*Microsoft Works 3.0
*Microsoft Works 4.0

===Works for Microsoft Windows===
*Microsoft Works 2.0 and 2.0a ([[Windows 3.1x|Windows 3.x]])
*Microsoft Works 3.0, 3.0a and 3.0b (Windows 3.x)
*Microsoft Works 4.0, 4.0a, 4.5 and 4.5a ([[Windows 95]])
*Microsoft Works 2000 (v.5) (Microsoft Works Suite 2000)
*Microsoft Works 6.0 (Microsoft Works Suite 2001 and 2002) - Last version for [[Windows 95]]
*Microsoft Works 7.0 (Microsoft Works Suite 2003 and 2004) - Last version for [[Windows 98]] (Original release)
*Microsoft Works 8.0 (Microsoft Works Suite 2005) - Last version for [[Windows 98#Second Edition|Windows 98 SE]]/[[Windows Me|Me]]/[[Windows 2000|2000]]- Fully compatible with Windows Vista 32-bit
*Microsoft Works 8.5 (Free update for Works 8.0 and Microsoft Works Suite 2006 users)
*Microsoft Works 9.0 (Microsoft Works Plus 2008) - First version fully compatible with all versions of [[Windows Vista]]

==See also==
* [[Comparison of office suites]]
* [[Microsoft Office]]
* [[List of applications with iCalendar support]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*{{Official website|http://www.microsoft.com/products/works/}}
*[http://www.wpsconverter.com/ wps converter]

{{Word processors}}
{{Spreadsheets}}
{{Microsoft}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Works}}
[[Category:Office suites|Microsoft Works]]
[[Category:Mac OS software]]
[[Category:Mac OS X software]]
[[Category:Microsoft software]]
[[Category:1983 software]]

[[ar:مايكروسوفت ووركس]]
[[de:Microsoft Works]]
[[es:Microsoft Works]]
[[fr:Microsoft Works]]
[[hr:Microsoft Works]]
[[id:Microsoft Works]]
[[it:Microsoft Works]]
[[nl:Microsoft Works]]
[[ja:Microsoft Works]]
[[nn:Microsoft Works]]
[[pl:Microsoft Works]]
[[pt:Microsoft Works]]
[[ru:Microsoft Works]]
[[fi:Microsoft Works]]
[[sv:Microsoft Works]]
[[uk:Microsoft Works]]
[[zh:Microsoft Works]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
