<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="682089" ns="0" title="University of Southern Maine"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox University
|name= University of Southern Maine
|image= [[Image:UsmLogo.png|center]]
|motto=
|established= 1878
|type= [[Public university|Public]]
|faculty= 
|president= [[Selma Botman]]
|city= [[Gorham, Maine|Gorham]], [[Lewiston, Maine|Lewiston]], [[Portland, Maine|Portland]]
|state= [[Maine]]
|country= [[United States|USA]]
|coor            = {{coord|43|39|45|N|70|16|34|W |region:US-ME_type:edu |display=inline,title}}
|students= 10,974
|undergrad= 
|campus= [[Suburban]]
|nickname= [[Siberian Husky|Huskies]]
|mascot= 
|website= [http://usm.maine.edu/ usm.maine.edu]
}}

The '''University of Southern Maine''' (USM) is a multi-campus public urban comprehensive university and part of the [[University of Maine System]].  USM's three primary campuses are located in [[Portland, Maine|Portland]], [[Gorham, Maine|Gorham]],  and [[Lewiston, Maine|Lewiston]].  Originally founded as two separate universities (Gorham Normal School, University of Maine at Portland), the two state universities were combined in 1970 to help streamline the public university system in Maine and eventually expanded by adding the Lewiston campus in 1988. The Portland Campus is home to the [[Edmund Muskie]] School of Public Service along with the Bio Sciences Research Institute and the [[University of Maine School of Law]], the [[Osher Lifelong Learning Institutes|Osher Lifelong Learning Institute]] and the Osher Map Library.  The Gorham campus, much more residential, is home to the College of Education and the School of Music.  At Lewiston-Auburn, students experience a small, intimate campus, with a focus on interdisciplinary learning.  Each campus maintains its own &quot;atmosphere&quot;, and professionals from all campuses provide a world-class experience at this regional university.&lt;ref name=mission&gt;
{{cite web
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|title= USM History and Mission
|accessdate= May 11, 2009
|url= http://www.usm.maine.edu/discover/mission.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

As of 2008, USM had 8,133 undergraduate students and 2,320 graduate and law school students, with an average class size of 22 and a student-faculty ratio of 17:1.&lt;ref name=ataglance&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://www.usm.maine.edu/quicklook.pdf
|format= pdf
|title= USM at a glance
|accessdate= 2009-05-18
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

USM is among the “Best Northeastern Colleges,” according to The [[Princeton Review]]’s 2007 listings,&lt;ref name=pr2007&gt;
{{cite book
|title= The Best Northeastern Colleges, 2007 Edition
|publisher= [[Random House]]/[[Princeton Review]]
|date= August 1, 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was also included in its 2007 edition of &quot;America's Best Value Colleges.&quot;&lt;ref name=USMPRPR&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://usm.maine.edu/mcr/news/0607releases/princeton.htm 
|title= Princeton Review Ranks USM Among the Best in the Northeast
|date= September 28, 2006 
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|accessdate= 2009-03-04
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The current president of USM is Dr. Selma Botman, who assumed the role on July&amp;nbsp;1, 2008 after serving as the Chief Academic Officer for the [[CUNY]] system in New York.&lt;ref name=Botman&gt;
{{cite web
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|title= President Botman Kicks Off Presidency and Academic Year on High Note
|date= August 2008
|accessdate= May 11, 2009
|url= https://blogs.usm.maine.edu/publicaffairs/archives/date/2008/08
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former President Dr. Richard Pattenaude became chancellor of the [[University of Maine System]] on July&amp;nbsp;1, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|title= USM President Richard Pattenaude, Soon to be Chancellor of the UMaine System, 'Worked Hard, Did Well, Had Fun.'
|date= May 12, 2007
|accessdate= May 11, 2009
|url= http://www.usm.maine.edu/mcr/news/0607releases/postcomm.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mission statement==
The mission statement of the university was amended by its Faculty Senate in November 2008, providing:
:&quot;The University of Southern Maine, northern New England's outstanding public, regional, comprehensive university, is dedicated to providing students with a high quality, accessible, affordable education. Through its undergraduate, graduate and professional programs, USM faculty members educate future leaders in the liberal arts and sciences, engineering and technology, health and social services, education, business, law and public service. Distinguished for their teaching, research, scholarly publication and creative activity, the faculty are committed to fostering a spirit of critical inquiry and civic participation. USM embraces academic freedom for students, faculty, and staff, and advocates diversity in all aspects of its campus life and academic work. It supports sustainable development, environmental stewardship, and community involvement. As a center for discovery, scholarship and creativity, USM provides resources for the state, the nation, and the world.&quot;&lt;ref name=senateMinutes&gt;University of Southern Maine, Faculty Senate. 2008. ''Minutes of the USM Faculty Senate Meeting, November 7, 2008''. Portland, ME: University of Southern Maine Faculty Senate.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Evolving from [[Gorham Academy]] into an institution of higher education, USM originated in 1878 as Gorham Normal School, later called Gorham State Teachers College and then simply Gorham State College.  In 1970 that institution merged with the University of Maine at Portland (previously Portland Junior College) and became the University of Maine at Portland-Gorham (UMPG).&lt;ref name=USMSpecColl&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://library.usm.maine.edu/specialcollections/timeline.html
|accessdate= 2009-06-14
|title= USM Timeline
|work= Special Collections
|publisher= USM Libraries
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The name was changed to University of Southern Maine in 1978. The Lewiston-Auburn campus was founded in 1988. USM is a major educational engine in the overall growth and development of economic, civic, and cultural life in southern [[Maine]]. USM offers baccalaureate and master's degree programs as well as doctoral programs in Public Policy, and School Psychology.&lt;ref name=mission /&gt;

==Campuses==
===Portland Campus===
[[Image:UsmPortlandAcademBldg.jpg|thumb|right|Luther Bonney, Masterton Hall, and the Science building at USM's Portland Campus]]
The main part of the campus consists entirely of non-residential buildings. Many department offices are located around the perimeter of the campus center in converted multi-story homes as well as in the major buildings. The primary academic areas of the Portland campus are business, nursing, history, political science, economics, sociology, biology, physics, chemistry, math, English, psychology, media studies, modern and classical languages and literatures, American and New England studies.&lt;ref name=AcadProgs&gt;
{{cite web
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|title= Academic Programs
|accessdate= May 11, 2009
|url= http://www.usm.maine.edu/academic/
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gorham Campus===
{{coord|43|40|54|N|70|26|54|W |region:US-ME_type:edu |name=Gorham campus, University of Southern Maine}} 
[[Image:Frederick Robie Hall, Gorham, ME.jpg|thumb|right|Robie Andrews Hall is one of the original Gorham State College buildings. It is now primarily a residence hall with some mixed academic usage on the first floor. Taken from a 1907 postcard.]]
Gorham is home to most of the University's dormitories and competitive athletic facilities. The primary academic areas residing in Gorham are industrial technologies, engineering, art, music, theater, counseling and education, anthropology, geography, environmental sciences, and geosciences.&lt;ref name=AcadProgs /&gt; [[McLellan House]], built in 1773, was acquired by Gorham State College in 1966. It was initially converted into dormitories and later into office space.&lt;ref name=GorhamCampus&gt;[http://library.usm.maine.edu/specialcollections/campusdescriptionGorham.html Campus Descriptions: GORHAM CAMPUS] Library, University of Southern Maine&lt;/ref&gt;
Dorms located on the Gorham campus are listed below: 

*Woodward Hall
*Dickey and Wood Towers: Dickey and Wood Towers were opened in 1970 and formerly inaugurated in 1973. They are named after Edna Dickey, who taught history at the university from 1945-1972 as well as serving as Dean of Women from 1945–69 and Esther Wood, who taught social sciences from 1930-1973.&lt;ref name=GorhamCampus/&gt;
*Upton Hall and Hastings Hall: Upton Hall and the adjacent Hastings Hall are named after Ethelyn Upton and Mary Hastings, both of whom were prominent faculty. Upton Hall, home of the university healthcenter and bookstore, was opened in 1960. Hastings Hall opened in 1968. Together, the complex can house up to 300 students.&lt;ref name=GorhamCampus/&gt;
*Anderson Hall
*Robie Andrews Hall: Robie Hall is named after former Maine Governor [[Frederick Robie]], who served from 1883-1887. It was built in 1897 to replace a female-only dormitory which had burnt down in 1894.&lt;ref name=GorhamCampus/&gt;
*Phillipi Hall: Opened in 2004&lt;ref name=GorhamCampus/&gt;
*New Residence Hall (completed fall of 2007)

===Lewiston-Auburn Campus===
{{coord|44|4|35|N|70|10|20|W |region:US-ME_type:edu |name=Lewiston-Auburn campus, University of Southern Maine}}
[[Image:usm lac front.jpg|thumb|right|USM's Lewiston-Auburn campus, Front entrance. This campus was established in 1988]]
The Lewiston-Auburn campus  of the University of Southern Maine is the newest of the three campuses and has recently built and opened a new wing in order to accommodate its rapid growth.  The college on this campus is known as Lewiston-Auburn College (USM&amp;nbsp;LAC). USM&amp;nbsp;LAC is committed to being a national leader in interdisciplinary education,  serving as a resource for the community, providing an outstanding educational experience for its students through degree programs that are responsive to changing cultural and workplace demands and that are available to a non-traditional and diverse student body.&lt;ref name=USMLACInfo&gt;
{{cite web
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|title= USM Lewiston-Auburn College General Info
|accessdate= May 18, 2009 
|url= http://www.usm.maine.edu/lac/info/
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baccalaureate degree programs available at USM&amp;nbsp;LAC are: Arts and Humanities, Leadership and Organizational Studies, Natural and Applied Sciences, Social and Behavioral Sciences and Occupational Therapy. An extension program in Industrial Technology from USM’s School of Applied Science, Engineering and Technology and extended programs in Nursing (BS &amp; RN to BS) from USM’s College of Nursing and Health Professions  are also offered at the Lewiston-Auburn campus. Master of Arts in Leadership and Master of Occupational Therapy degrees are offered exclusively at Lewiston-Auburn College. Additionally, USM’s College of Education and Human Development extends a master degree in Literacy to USM Lewiston-Auburn.&lt;ref name=USMLACInfo /&gt;

===Distance Learning locations===
The University offers courses off-campus courses via Interactive Television at locations in [[Saco, Maine|Saco]], [[Bath, Maine|Bath]], and [[Sanford, Maine|Sanford]].&lt;ref name=USMOCC&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://www.usm.maine.edu/eap/offcampus/index.htm 
|title= Off-Campus Courses
|publisher= University of Southern Maine
|accessdate= 2009-03-04
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:UsmHuskies.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]] --&gt;
The University of Southern Maine sponsors the 23 sports at the [[NCAA]] [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]] level. The majority of sports compete in the [[Little East Conference]]; wrestling competes as an independent Division III team, men's and women's ice hockey compete in the [[ECAC East]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uscho.com/2009/02/27/this-week-in-the-ecac-east-and-nescac/&lt;/ref&gt;
   
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''Men's intercollegiate athletic teams''' 
* [[Baseball]]
* [[Basketball]]
* [[Cheerleading]]
* [[Cross country running|Cross Country]]
* [[Golf]]
* [[Ice Hockey]]
* [[Lacrosse]]
* [[Soccer]]
* [[Tennis]]
* [[Track &amp; Field]] (indoor)
* [[Track &amp; Field]] (outdoor)
* [[Wrestling]]
{{col-2}}
'''Women's intercollegiate athletic teams''' 
* [[Basketball]]
* [[Cheerleading]]
* [[Cross country running|Cross Country]]
* [[Field Hockey]]
* [[Golf]]
* [[Ice Hockey]]
* [[Lacrosse]]
* [[Soccer]]
* [[Softball]]
* [[Tennis]]
* [[Track &amp; Field]] (indoor)
* [[Track &amp; Field]] (outdoor)
* [[Volleyball]]
{{col-end}}

==Alumni==
* [[Richard A. Bennett]], state legislator
* [[Joseph Brannigan]], state legislator
* [[Michael F. Brennan]], state legislator, earned M.A. at Muskie School of Public Policy
* [[Kate Chappell]], founder of [[Tom's of Maine]] (1983)
* [[Kathleen Chase]], state legislator (1991)
* [[John Currier]], officer in the US Coast Guard
* [[Don Dodge]], developer advocate for Google
* [[Alison Goodwin]], painter
* [[Simon M. Hamlin]], U.S. Congressman
* [[Hannah Holmes]], journalist (1988)
* [[Kevan Jones]], British Member of Parliament
* [[Brian Langley]], state legislator
* [[Lois Lowry]], novelist  (1972)
* [[David A. Marshall]], artist and Portland city councilor
* [[Matthew Quinn Martin]], actor, writer, director and musician
* [[Jean Ginn Marvin]], state legislator, earned M.A. at Muskie School of Public Policy
* [[Walter Mattson]], former president of the ''[[New York Times]]''  (1953)
* [[Chellie Pingree]], U.S. Congresswoman
* [[Luke Robinson (wrestler)|Luke Robinson]], professional wrestler (2008)
* [[Tony Shalhoub]], actor (1977)
* [[Raymond C. Stevens]], research scientist (1986)
* [[Kevin St.Jarre]], writer, earned [[Stonecoast MFA Program in Creative Writing|MFA at Stonecoast Program in Creative Writing]]
* [[Nancy Sullivan (politician)|Nancy Sullivan]], state legislator
* [[Cleon Turner]], state legislator in Massachusetts
* [[John Bruce Wallace]], philosopher and artist

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{kml}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.usm.maine.edu}}

{{University of Maine system}}
{{Little East Conference navbox}}
{{Universities and colleges in Maine}}
{{Portland, Maine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Southern Maine, University Of}}
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1878]]
[[Category:University of Southern Maine|*]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:University of Maine System]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Androscoggin County, Maine]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Cumberland County, Maine]]
[[Category:Education in Portland, Maine]]
[[Category:Education in Lewiston, Maine]]

[[no:University of Southern Maine]]
[[pnb:یونیورسٹی آف ساؤتھرن مینے]]
[[simple:University of Southern Maine]]
[[sh:University of Southern Maine]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
