<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6881707" ns="0" title="East London (bus company)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2010}}
{{Infobox Bus transit
| name            = Stagecoach London (East London)
| logo            = Stagecoach ballbus.png
| logo_size       = 164
| image           = East London 15029.JPG
| image_size      = 
| image_caption   = One of East London's new [[Scania OmniCity]]s.
| company_slogan  = 
| parent          = [[Stagecoach Group]]  
| routes          = 59&lt;br&gt; 55
| founded         = 1988
| headquarters    = West Ham Bus Garage, Stephenson Street E16 4SA 
| locale          = 
| service_area    = [[Greater London]]
| service_type    = [[Bus]]
| hubs            = 
| stations        =
| lounge          = 
| fleet           = 
| ridership       = 
| fuel_type       = 
| operator        = [[Stagecoach London]]
| ceo             = 
| website         = [http://www.stagecoachbus.com/ www.stagecoachbus.com] 
}}
'''East London''' is one of many operators of bus services contracted to [[Transport for London]], mainly in the east of the city. Its legal name is '''East London Bus &amp; Coach Company Ltd''', and it is currently owned largely by [[Stagecoach Group]], as part of [[Stagecoach London]].
{{TOClimit}}

==History==
East London was established in late 1988 and became a registered company on 1 April 1989. It was one of the 12 operating subsidiaries of [[London Buses|London Buses Limited]], and upon the [[Privatisation of London bus services|privatisation]] of LBL in 1994 was acquired, along with [[Selkent]], by the [[Stagecoach Group]]. The company subsequently traded as Stagecoach East London before, in November 2000, Stagecoach's London operations were rebranded simply as Stagecoach London, with buses receiving 'Stagecoach in London' fleetnames. Stagecoach sold these operations in 2006 to Macquarie Bank and the East London fleetname reappeared, as did the Thames sailing barge logo used by the company during LBL days. The business was re-purchased in October 2010 by Stagecoach.

Both the buses involved in the London bombings of [[7 July 2005 London Bombings|7 July 2005]], and the [[21 July 2005 London Bombings|attempted bombings]] two weeks later, belonged to Stagecoach London.

==Garages==
East London has five bus garages.

===Barking (BK)===
This runs London bus routes [[London Buses route 5|5]], [[London Buses route 15|15]] (Early/late journeys only), [[London Buses route 62|62]], [[London Buses route 101|101]], [[London Buses route 145|145]], [[London Buses route 169|169]], [[London Buses route 366|366]], [[London Buses route 387|387]], [[London Buses route 396|396]], Night route [[London Buses route N15|N15]] and school route [[London Buses route 687|687]].

The current peak vehicle requirement is 111.

====History====
Barking garage was opened in 1924 by the [[London General Omnibus Company]] to cater for the increased demand from the new housing estates springing up in [[Becontree]].

Barking is remembered by many enthusiasts as being the last garage to operate [[AEC Regent III RT|RT]]s on 7 April 1979. In 1992, it was intended to close this garage, along with those at North Street and Seven Kings, in favour of a new super-garage at [[Chadwell Heath]]. As it turned out, this super-garage was not built due to the land for it being contaminated, and only Seven Kings closed.&lt;ref name=Titan&gt;Wharmby, Matthew, ''The London Titan'' (Ian Allan Publishing, 2008). ISBN 978-0-7110-3299-6&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, by 1994, Barking found itself with a scheduled requirement for 109 buses, mainly [[Leyland Titan (B15)|Titan]]s and DA-class [[Optare Delta]]s.

From 3 March 2012, Stagecoach have gained the contract for route 275 and will be operated from this garage.

====Bus types in use====
* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 9.9m &amp; 10.5m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 5, 15, 101, N15 and as trainers.
* [[Optare Versa]] 10.4m for route 396.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro200 Dart]] 10.2m for routes 62 and 366.
* [[Dennis Dart SLF]] 10.2m / [[Plaxton Pointer 2]] for route 366.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro400]] 10.2m for routes 62, 145, 169, 387 and 687. To be introduced on routes 101 and 275 from March 2012.

===Bow (BW)===
This garage holds 113 buses, and runs London bus routes [[London Buses route 8|8]], [[London Buses route 15|15]], and 24-hour routes [[London Buses route 205|205]] and [[London Buses route 277|277]] and Night route [[London Buses route N8|N8]].

The current peak vehicle requirement is 100.

====History====
Opened as a tram depot by the north Metropolitan Tramways Company in 1908 on land once occupied by an asylum, it was converted to operate trolley buses in 1939. It was converted to motor bus operation in 1959 including the installation of large overground fuel tanks. Shortly after its conversion, it took up the allocation of the nearby Clay Hall garage when that closed.

The garage has had a long association with the [[Routemaster]], receiving its first examples in the early 1960s, some of which remained right up until August 2004 when the type was withdrawn from route 8. In December 2007, Bow took over the running of Heritage route 15 from the closed Waterden Road garage until this moved to West Ham in June 2009, along with the last Routemaster built, RML2760, which features at special events.

====Bus types in use====

* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 10.5m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 8, 15, 277 and N8.
* [[Scania OmniCity]] 10.6m for route 205.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro400|Alexander Dennis Enviro400H hybrid]] 10.1m to be introduced on route 15 from January 2012.

===Leyton (T)===

This garage runs London bus routes [[London Buses route 48|48]], [[London Buses route 55|55]], [[London Buses route 56|56]], [[London Buses route 69|69]] (night service only on this 24-hour route), [[London Buses route 97|97]], [[London Buses route 215|215]], [[London Buses route 230|230]] and Night route [[London Buses route N55|N55]].


The current peak vehicle requirement is 104.

====History====
Leyton garage was built in 1912 by the [[London General Omnibus Company]] to replace an existing garage acquired from London Metropolitan, and was in an ideal position to benefit from developing areas. During the [[Second World War]] the garage suffered bomb damage but was not rebuilt until a major renovation in 1955.

The garage was the first to receive post-war RT's, 78 of which were allocated by 1947, and a further 30 were added for the trolleybus conversion program in 1959. RT operation at Leyton ended in 1972.

When the [[London Buses|London Buses Limited]] subsidiaries were established, Leyton was taken up by the [[London Forest]] subsidiary. In 1991, plans to close the garage were a contributing factor in strike action by all of the company's staff, which ultimately resulted in the winding-up of London Forest, with Leyton garage passing to East London.&lt;ref name=Titan /&gt;

Leyton was the first garage for another bus type in 1999, when Stagecoach began taking delivery of low-floor Dennis Trident 2 10.5m/Alexander ALX400s. The current operational allocation is entirely low-floor.

====Bus types in use====
* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 9.9m &amp; 10.5m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 55, 69, 97, 230, N55 and as trainer.
* [[Scania OmniCity]] 10.6m for routes 48, 56 and 215.

===Romford (North Street) (NS)===
This garage runs London bus routes [[London Buses route 86|86]], [[London Buses route 103|103]], [[London Buses route 175|175]], [[London Buses route 247|247]], [[London Buses route 294|294]], [[London Buses route 296|296]], [[London Buses route 496|496]], school route [[London Buses route 647|647]] as well as Night route [[London Buses route N86|N86]].

The current peak vehicle requirement is 92.

====History====
Romford garage is also called North Street (hence its NS code) as London Transport already had a 'country bus' garage: Romford (London Road). It was opened in 1953 to take the strain off nearby Hornchurch garage, and also to cope with the new Harold Hill estate. Built in the post-war style of an [[London Underground|Underground]] station, it was initially able to house 115 buses, although only 67 were allocated when opened. The allocation grew to 90 by 1958.

In 1992, along with Barking and Seven Kings (which did subsequently close although due to loss of routes by competitive tender), the garage was earmarked for closure in favour of a new super-garage at Chadwell Heath, which ultimately was never built. By 1994, Romford was allocated 84 buses, mainly Titans. In 2004 the allocation had dropped slightly to 76, although with a good year of tender wins in 2005 the garage is up to full capacity.  The garage was home to East London Coaches private hire operation from 1990 to 2005 when the section moved to the now closed Waterden Road garage.

[[Arriva London]], have successfully gained the contract for route 647 and from 31 March 2012 they will be operating it from their Barking (DX) garage.

====Bus types in use====
* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 9.9m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 175, 247 and 294.
* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 10.5m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 86, 103,647 and N86.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro200 Dart]] 10.2m for route 296.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro400]] 10.2m for route 496.

===West Ham (WH)===
This garage runs London bus routes [[London Buses route 5|5]] (Early/late journeys only), 15 (Early/Late journeys only), [[London Buses route 15 (Heritage)|15 (Heritage)]], [[London Buses route 69|69]], [[London Buses route 104|104]], [[London Buses route 106|106]], [[London Buses route 115|115]], [[London Buses route 147|147]], [[London Buses route 158|158]], [[London Buses route 238|238]], [[London Buses route 241|241]], [[London Buses route 257|257]], [[London Buses route 262|262]], [[London Buses route 323|323]], [[London Buses route 330|330]], [[London Buses route 473|473]], [[London Buses route 488|488]], [[London Buses route 541|541]], [[London Buses route D3|D3]], school route [[London Buses route 678|678]], night bus routes [[London Buses route N15|N15]] and [[London Buses route N550|N550]].

The current peak vehicle requirement is 202.

====History====
The present West Ham garage was opened in February 2008 as the replacement for Stratford garage. Whilst construction work was underway, all major engineering work on its buses was carried out at Rainham. However, the garage became fully operational in November 2009 taking over its own maintenance. The new garage is able to hold over 300 buses. It is the biggest Bus garage in the UK and is the new location for East London Bus Group's head office and training centre.

[[Arriva London]], have successfully gained the contract of route 678 and from 31 March 2012 they will operate it.

====Bus types in use====
* [[AEC Routemaster]] for route 15 Heritage.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro400]] 10.8m as a logistical spare
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro200Dart]] 10.2m for routes 323, 488 and D3.
* [[Dennis Dart SLF]] 10.2m / [[Alexander ALX200]] for route D3.
* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 9.9m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 147, 241, 262, 473, 541 and 678.
* [[Dennis Trident 2]] 10.5m / [[Alexander ALX400]] for routes 5, 15, 69, 104, 115, 158, 238, 257, 330, 678, N15 and N550. To be introduced on routes 147 and 241 from January 2012.
* [[Scania OmniCity]] 10.6m for route 106.
* [[Alexander Dennis Enviro400]] 10.2m to be introduced partially on route 104, partially on route 158 and route 238 from 3 March 2012.

==Former garages==

===Stratford (SD)===
All operations from this garage were transferred to West Ham in February 2008 when the garage closed following a compulsory purchase for Olympic development.

====History====
[[File:East London 18500.JPG|thumb|Spirit of London at a bus event. The name is displayed on the side by the doors.]]
Stratford garage, opened in 1992, was a large yard on an old industrial estate by the River Lea, opposite the Hackney garage which was owned by [[First London]]. It was originally called &quot;Bow Midibus Base&quot; on account of the fact that it housed midibuses which had been previously based at Bow and West Ham. It also operated buses with rooftop flashing beacons for the [[London City Airport]] contract.

One vehicle from this garage was destroyed in the London bombings of 7 July 2005. Thirteen passengers were killed, but the driver of the bus, George Psaradakis, escaped serious injury and was able to return to work a few weeks later. The bus was replaced in October 2005 by the first [[Alexander Dennis Enviro400]] off the production line, which was named &quot;Spirit of London&quot; and it is now at West Ham.

===Waterden Road (Stratford Olympic) (WA)===
This garage closed in December 2007 due to a compulsory purchase order to enable work on the site for the [[2012 Summer Olympics]].

====History====
Waterden Road opened early in 2004 with an allocation for approximately 100 buses, mainly articulated [[Mercedes-Benz Citaro]]s for route 25. By 2005, East London had relocated both its training centre and its private hire fleet to this garage. The private hire fleet was disbanded in 2007.

The garage had been open for less than four years when Olympics work forced its closure, the training centre subsequently moving to West Ham.

===Upton Park (U)===

====History====
Prior to West Ham being built it was the largest garage in the east end of London, Upton Park was opened by the LRCC in 1907 but was requisitioned for the war effort in 1915 and was not returned to use until 1919. In 1931 it was totally revamped and enlarged to create a capacity of just over 200 buses. In 1988 the garage operated the X15 &quot;Beckton Express&quot; using ex-Green Line [[Routemaster]] RMCs. The service was a trial, and even sold newspapers to commuters on board.

On 16 September 2011, routes 104, 115, 238, 262, 330, 473 and N550 was transferred to West Ham (WH) and route 101 was transferred to Barking (BK). &lt;ref&gt;http://www.stagecoachbus.com/Upton%20Park%20Closure.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 September 2011, Upton Park (U) garage was shut down. There was no driver redundancies as a result of the garage closure as they were moved with the routes to other locations. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.stagecoachbus.com/Upton%20Park%20Closure.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 September 2011, [[Blue Triangle]] gained the contract for route 376 and are now operating it from their Rainham (BE) garage. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.londonbusroutes.net/changes.htm#138&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of bus operators of the United Kingdom]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|East London Bus Group}}
*[http://www.elbg.com/ East London Bus Group website]
*[http://londonbusesbyadam.zenfolio.com/ London Bus Routes Zenfolio]

{{StagecoachGroup|state=autocollapse}}
{{Bus companies in Greater London}}
{{London bus operators}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:East London (Bus Company)}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
