<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6908253" ns="0" title="Windows Live Family Safety"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=November 2009}}
{{Infobox software|
| name = Windows Live Family Safety
| logo = [[Image:Windows Live OneCare FSS logo.png|center|64px|Windows Live Family Safety Icon]]
| screenshot = [[Image:Windows Live Family Safety.png|275px]]
| caption = Windows Live Family Safety homepage
| latest_release_version = Wave 4 (Build 15.4.3538.0513)
| latest_release_date = {{Release_date|2011|07|06}}
| latest_preview_version = 
| latest_preview_date    = {{release date|mf=yes|2010|08|17}}
| developer = [[Microsoft]]
| operating_system = [[Microsoft Windows]]
| genre = [[Parental controls|Parental Control]]
| license = 
| website = http://familysafety.live.com/
}}
[[Image:Windows Live Family Safety Filter.png|280px|thumb|right|Windows Live Family Safety Filter]]

'''Windows Live Family Safety''', developed by [[Microsoft]], is free parental monitoring and [[content-control software]] for [[Microsoft Windows]] under the [[Windows Live]] brand. 

== Features ==

* Web Filtering - Family Safety has a [[Windows Filtering Platform]] driver to filter web browsing. This works on all browsers, filters in 18 different languages, and contains the following levels:
** Allow List Only - Only allows websites that a parent has added to the Allow list.
** Child-Friendly Sites - Above plus allows a list of websites designed for children. [http://familysafety.live.com/kids Child-Friendly Websites] has a listing of the more popular kid sites and allows you to search the entire list of kid sites.
** General Interest - Blocks social networking, web mail, web chat, and adults sites.
** Online Communications - Blocks adult sites.
** Warn on adult - Allows all websites but warns when the site contains suspected adult material. This setting was designed for older children who you trust to make good decisions when the web filter incorrectly categorizes a site.

* Activity Reporting - Parents can obtain a list of the websites visited. In addition, computer usages time, programs run, files downloaded, and games run will be reported via [[Windows Parental Controls]].
* Lock [[SafeSearch]] on for [[Google]], [[Bing]], [[Yahoo!]], and other popular search engines.
* Control of [[Windows Parental Control]] settings to set time limits, game restrictions ala [[ESRB]], [[PEGI]], [[CERO]], [[Computer Software Rating Regulation]], [[Game Rating Board]], and [[Unterhaltungssoftware Selbstkontrolle]]. as well as general application restrictions.
* Family Safety allows remote access to its features via the web interface. Windows Live Family Safety 2011 added support for using the web filtering/blocking controls without the child having a [[Windows Live ID]].
* Contact Management - Parents are able to create &quot;allow&quot; lists for [[Windows Live Contacts]] services such as [[Windows Live Messenger]] and [[Hotmail]] to help prevent their children from communicating with unknown contacts and instead only communicate with contacts that parents have approved. Alternatively, parents can just monitor who the child as on their allow list. This was added for [[Windows Live Messenger#Windows Live Messenger 8.5|Windows Live Messenger 8.5]].
* Windows Live Family Safety blocks [[Internet Explorer 8#InPrivate|InPrivate browsing]] in [[Internet Explorer 8]] and [[Internet Explorer 9|9]].
* Image Filtering - Family Safety has a filter which looks for adult content in images. The filter is only run on websites which do not do an adequate job of filtering the images and only on computers with sufficient performance capabilities. When an image is blocked, Family Safety blurs it out.

== History ==
A preview of Windows Live OneCare Family Safety was first offered to 3000 beta testers in March 2006. After over a year and a half of testing, the final version was released on November 6, 2007. On 15 December 2008, Microsoft released an updated version 2009 of the software, and rebranded it as Windows Live Family Safety, removing it from the discontinued [[Windows Live OneCare]] family of products. Web Filtering and Activity Reporting were previously features in Windows Vista Parental Controls. They were removed from the [[Windows 7]] release when they were moved to [[Windows Live]]. On September 30, 2010, Windows Live Family Safety 2011 (Wave 4) was released as part of [[Windows Live Essentials|Windows Live Essentials 2011]].


== System requirements ==
[[Windows Vista]] Service Pack 2 with the Platform Update for Windows Vista, [[Windows 7]] (32-bit or 64-bit editions), Windows Server 2008 R2, or Windows Server 2008 with Service Pack 2 and the Platform Update for Windows Server 2008. It works on [[Internet Explorer]] 6 or later, [[Google_Chrome|Chrome]] 2 or later, [[Firefox]] 2.0 or later, [[Opera_browser|Opera]] 10 or later, and [[Safari (web browser)|Safari]] 3.0 or later.

An older version of Family Safety is available for [[Windows XP]].

== See also ==
*[[Windows Live]]
*[[Windows Live OneCare]]
*[[Microsoft Security Essentials]]
*[[List of content-control software]]

== References ==
*[http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2010/06/microsoft-taking-aim-at-ilife-with-windows-live-wave-4.ars Arstechnica: Family Safety is compared to Mac OS X Parental Controls, and it wins hands down]
*[http://windowsteamblog.com/windows_live/b/windowslive/archive/2010/07/16/what-s-new-with-family-safety.aspx Windows Team Blog: What’s new with Family Safety?]
*[http://windowsteamblog.com/windows/b/windowsexperience/archive/2009/08/20/updated-version-of-windows-live-family-safety-released.aspx Windows Experience Blog: Updated Version of Windows Live Family Safety Released]
*[http://www.wired.com/geekdad/2009/09/7-things-to-like-about-parental-controls-in-windows-7/ Wired: 7 Things to Like about Parental Controls in Windows 7]
*[http://news.softpedia.com/news/Microsoft-Introduces-Windows-Live-OneCare-Family-Safety-Beta-34312.shtml Softpedia: Microsoft Introduces Windows Live Family Safety Beta]

== External links ==
*[http://fss.live.com Windows Live Family Safety]
*[http://windowslive.com/desktop/familysafety Windows Live Family Safety information]

{{Windows Live}}

[[Category:Windows Live|Family Safety]]
[[Category:Content-control software]]

[[ar:الحماية العائلية المباشرة من ويندوز]]
[[es:Windows Live Protección infantil]]
[[mr:विंडोज लाइव्ह फॅमिली सेफ्टी]]
[[nl:Windows Live Family Safety]]
[[pt:Windows Live OneCare Proteção para a Família]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
