<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="6933432" ns="0" title="2006 San Francisco 49ers season"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--Important Note: This page complies with [[Wikipedia:Centralized discussion/Sports results]]--&gt;
{{Infobox NFL season
| team = San Francisco 49ers
| year = 2006
| record = 7-9
| division_place = 3rd [[NFC West]]
| coach = [[Mike Nolan]]
| stadium = [[Monster Park]]
| playoffs = ''did not qualify''
| pro bowlers = 3
| uniform = File:NFCW-1998-2008-Uniform-SF.PNG
}}
The '''[[2006 NFL season|2006]] [[San Francisco 49ers]] season''' began with the team trying to improve on their 4-12 record in [[2005 NFL season|2005]]. Despite having improved from their previous two disastrous seasons and were in the top 10 best offense in the league in 2006 ,they missed the playoffs for the fourth straight year, continuing their playoff drought. The 49ers celebrated their 60th anniversary during the 2006 season, because, although it was their 61st season, the 2006 calendar year marked the 60th anniversary of the franchise's founding in 1946.

==Off season==
Soon after the end of the 2005 season, [[Mike McCarthy (American football)|Mike McCarthy]], the 49ers' offensive coordinator of one year, left for the [[Green Bay Packers]]. On January 17, 2006, the 49ers hired [[Norv Turner]] as McCarthy's replacement. Whereas McCarthy based the majority of his offense on Bill Walsh's West Coast Offense, Turner has been known to use a power running scheme and vertical passing game more often than the West Coast scheme. Turner came to the 49ers after two unsuccessful seasons as the head coach of the 49ers' crossbay rivals, the [[Oakland Raiders]].

The 49ers gained the 6th pick in the [[2006 NFL Draft]] after winning a coin toss with the [[Oakland Raiders]] at the scouting combine in Indianapolis. The 49ers used their first pick on Maryland Tight End [[Vernon Davis]]. They then used their next pick (acquired from the [[Denver Broncos]] via the [[Washington Redskins]]) on North Carolina St. Defensive End [[Manny Lawson]]. The rest of their picks were Wisconsin Wide Receiver [[Brandon Williams (wide receiver)|Brandon Williams]], Penn St. RB [[Michael Robinson (running back)|Michael Robinson]], Tennessee DE [[Parys Haralson]], Central Missouri St. Wide Receiver [[Delanie Walker]], North Carolina St. Safety [[Marcus Hudson]], Louisiana St. DE [[Melvin Oliver]], and Arkansas Safety [[Vickiel Vaughn]].

The 49ers had two major free agent acquisitions in the off season. [[Larry Allen]], a perennial [[Pro Bowl]] left guard from the [[Dallas Cowboys]], and [[Antonio Bryant]], a talented but oft-troubled wide receiver from the [[Cleveland Browns]]. The 49ers also traded [[Kevan Barlow]] to the [[New York Jets]] for what is believed to be a 2007 4th round draft pick.

==2006 schedule==
===Preseason===
[[File:Packers at 49ers 8-16-08 4.JPG|thumb|The 49ers on offense against the Packers on August 16]]

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Week
! Date
! Time
! Opponent
! Result 
! Game site
! TV
! NFL Recap
|-
|-style=&quot;background: #ddffdd;&quot;
| 1
| August 11, 2006
| 7 p.m.
| [[Oakland Raiders]]
|  W 28 - 14
| [[Oakland-Alameda County Coliseum]]
| NFL Network
| align=center colspan=&quot;1&quot; |[http://www.nfl.com/gamecenter/recap?game_id=29791&amp;displayPage=tab_recap&amp;season=2008&amp;week=PRE1 Recap]
|-
|-style=&quot;background: #ddffdd;&quot;
| 2
| August 16, 2008
| 6 p.m.
| [[Green Bay Packers]]
|  W 34 - 6
| [[Candlestick Park]]
| NFL Network
| align=center colspan=&quot;1&quot; |[http://www.nfl.com/gamecenter/recap?game_id=29812&amp;displayPage=tab_recap&amp;season=2008&amp;week=PRE2 Recap]
|-
|-style=&quot;background: #ddffdd;&quot;
| 3
| August 21, 2008
| 5 p.m.
| [[Chicago Bears]]
|  W 37 - 30
| [[Soldier Field]]
| NFL Network
| align=center colspan=&quot;1&quot; |[http://www.nfl.com/gamecenter/recap?game_id=29816&amp;displayPage=tab_recap&amp;season=2008&amp;week=PRE3 Recap]
|-
|-style=&quot;background: #ffdddd;&quot;
| 4
| August 29, 2008
| 7 p.m.
| [[San Diego Chargers]]
|  L 17-20
| [[Candlestick Park]]
| NFL Network
| align=center colspan=&quot;1&quot; |[http://www.nfl.com/gamecenter/recap?game_id=29847&amp;displayPage=tab_recap&amp;season=2008&amp;week=PRE4 Recap]
|}

==Regular season==
===Week 1: at Arizona Cardinals===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=49ers
|R1=7||R2=7||R3=7||R4=6||RT=27
|Home='''Cardinals'''
|H1=21||H2=3||H3=7||H4=3||HT=34
}}
''at [[University of Phoenix Stadium]], [[Glendale, Arizona]]'' 

Sunday,September 10, 2006

The 49ers opened the regular season against the [[Arizona Cardinals]] on September 10. Despite losing 34-27, many positives can be taken out of the game. RB [[Frank Gore]] rushed for 88 yards and caught 6 receptions for over 80 yards with two touchdowns. Rookie tight end [[Vernon Davis]] and second year quarterback [[Alex Smith]] hooked up for a touchdown pass with Smith equaling his touchdown total of the entire 2005 season and passing for an encouraging 288 yards with 23 completions out of 40 attempts. The 49ers had several chances to win it, however, many controversial non-calls were made by the officials, including a blatant pass interference in the end zone, which would have tied the game with just a little over 2 minutes to go. The 49ers would start their 60th season 0-1

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter
'''
SF- [[Vernon Davis]] 31 yard pass from [[Alex Smith]] ([[Joe Nedney]] kick)

AZ- [[Troy Walters]] 2 yard pass from [[Kurt Warner]] ([[Neil Rackers]] kick)

AZ- [[Edgerrin James]] 1 yard rush (Neil Rackers kick)

AZ- [[Anquan Boldin]] 6 yard pass from Kurt Warner (Neil Rackers kick)

'''2nd Quarter
'''

SF- [[Frank Gore]] 4 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

AZ- Neil Rackers 36 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Frank Gore 2 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

AZ- [[Adam Bergen]] 7 yard pass from Kurt Warner (Neil Rackers kick)

'''4th Quarter
'''
SF- Joe Nedney 22 yard field goal

AZ- Neil Rackers 30 yard field goal	

SF- Joe Nedney 44 yard field goal

===Week 2: vs. St. Louis Rams===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=Rams
|R1=0||R2=10||R3=0||R4=3||RT=13
|Home='''49ers'''
|H1=3||H2=0||H3=14||H4=3||HT=20
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]'' 

Sunday, September 17, 2006

The 49ers played their second game of the season against the [[St. Louis Rams]] on September 17 in a Week 2 home-opener. After a loss to the [[Arizona Cardinals]] the previous week, the 49ers redeemed themselves with a win at home. Second year quarterback Alex Smith threw for 233 yards with 11 completions and one touchdown pass to [[Antonio Bryant]]. Bryant had four receptions with 131 yards. Running back Frank Gore ran for a (at the time) career-best 127 yards with a touchdown, despite [[Jonas Jennings]] and [[Larry Allen]] being sidelined with injuries. San Francisco won 20-13 and evened out their record at 1-1

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 32 yard field goal

'''2nd quarter'''

STL- [[Jeff Wilkins]] 49 yard field goal

STL- [[Torry Holt]] 3 yard pass from [[Marc Bulger]] (Jeff Wilkins kick)

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Frank Gore 32 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- [[Antonio Bryant]] 72 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

STL- Jeff Wilkins 40 yard field goal

SF- Joe Nedney 20 yard field goal

=== Week 3: vs. Philadelphia Eagles ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''Eagles'''
|R1=14||R2=10||R3=7||R4=7||RT=38
|Home=49ers
|H1=0||H2=3||H3=7||H4=14||HT=24
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]'' 

Sunday, September 24, 2006

The 49ers stayed at home for a Week 3 contest against the [[Philadelphia Eagles]]. From the get-go, the Niners trailed as QB [[Donovan McNabb]] managed to complete two TD passes to RB [[Brian Westbrook]] (a 4-yard pass) and WR [[L.J. Smith]] (a 1-yard pass) in the first quarter. In the second quarter, San Francisco would get on the board with Kicker [[Joe Nedney]] completing a 48-yard field goal, but Philadelphia would strike hard, as RB [[Brian Westbrook]] ran 71 yards for a touchdown and Kicker [[David Akers]] completed a 21-yard field goal. In the third quarter, both sides managed to get themselves a touchdown. Eagles DT [[Mike Patterson (American football)|Mike Patterson]] returned a 49ers fumble 98 yards for a touchdown, while the Niners' rookie RB [[Michael Robinson (running back)|Michael Robinson]] got a 1-yard TD run. In the fourth quarter, San Francisco tried to come back with Robinson getting another 1-yard TD run.  However, the Eagles got an 8-yard TD run by Westbrook.  The Niners would get one more score, as QB [[Alex Smith]] completed a TE [[Eric Johnson (tight end)|Eric Johnson]], but that would as far as they would get, as the 49ers fell to 1-2 on the year.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

PHI- [[Brian Westbrook]] 4 yard pass from [[Donovan McNabb]] ([[David Akers]] kick)	

PHI- [[L.J. Smith]] 1 yard pass from Donovan McNabb (David Akers kick)

'''2nd quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 48 yard field goal

PHI- Brian Westbrook 71 yard rush (David Akers kick)

PHI- David Akers 21 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

PHI- [[Mike Patterson (American football)|Mike Patterson]] 98 yard fumble return (David Akers kick)

SF- [[Michael Robinson (running back)|Michael Robinson]] 1 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Michael Robinson 1 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

PHI- Brian Westbrook 8 yard rush (David Akers kick)

SF- [[Eric Johnson (tight end)|Eric Johnson]] 15 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

=== Week 4: at Kansas City Chiefs ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=49ers
|R1=0||R2=0||R3=0||R4=0||RT=0
|Home='''Chiefs'''
|H1=10||H2=14||H3=3||H4=14||HT=41
}}
''at [[Arrowhead Stadium]], [[Kansas City, Missouri]]'' 

Sunday, October 1, 2006

After losing at home to the Eagles, the 49ers flew to [[Arrowhead Stadium]] for a Week 4 match-up with the [[Kansas City Chiefs]]. Unfortunately, this match-up was one-sided from beginning to end, with the Chiefs' offense being in top form, the Niners get crushed by KC's defense, and the usual loudness of the stadium (via the Chiefs fans) also probably affected the team's ability to execute. The 49ers tried their best, but in the end, QB [[Damon Huard]] and the Kansas City Chiefs were the better team in the fight. 49ers would drop their record to 1-3

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

KC- [[Dante Hall]] 13 yard pass from [[Damon Huard]] ([[Lawrence Tynes]] kick)

KC- Lawrence Tynes 22 yard field goal

'''2nd Quarter'''

KC- [[Larry Johnson (American football)|Larry Johnson]] 1 yard rush (Lawrence Tynes kick)

KC- [[Eddie Kennison]] 34 yard pass from Damon Huard (Lawrence Tynes kick)

'''3rd Quarter'''

KC- Lawrence Tynes 49 yard field goal

'''4th Quarter'''

KC- Larry Johnson 2 yard rush (Lawrence Tynes kick)

KC- Dante Hall 60 yard punt return (Lawrence Tynes kick)

=== Week 5: vs. Oakland Raiders ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=Raiders
|R1=3||R2=10||R3=0||R4=7||RT=20
|Home='''49ers'''
|H1=7||H2=0||H3=14||H4=13||HT=34
}}
at ''[[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco]], [[California]]''

Sunday, October 8, 2006

Hoping to rebound from their loss in Kansas City, the 49ers went home for Week 5 as they played a Bay Area battle with the [[Oakland Raiders]]. The Niners drew first blood with QB [[Alex Smith]] throwing a 4-yard TD pass to WR [[Arnaz Battle]], yet the Raiders would respond with kicker [[Sebastian Janikowski]] getting a 33-yard field goal for the first quarter. In the second quarter, things started to look grim, as Oakland took the lead with Janikowski kicking a 36-yard field goal, while QB [[Andrew Walter]] threw a 22-yard TD pass to WR [[Randy Moss]]. In the third quarter, the 49ers would rebound, as Smith hooked up with Battle again for a 6-yard TD pass. Later, Alex would throw a 33-yard TD pass to RB [[Maurice Hicks]], giving San Francisco the lead. In the fourth quarter, the 49ers continued to roll, as kicker [[Joe Nedney]] kicked a 19-yard field goal, while rookie DE [[Melvin Oliver]] returned a fumble 12 yards for a touchdown. The Niners would allow one last touchdown from the Raiders, in the form of QB [[Marques Tuiasosopo]] completing an 8-yard pass to TE [[Courtney Anderson]], but Nedney would help the Niners get win #2 with a 39-yard field goal. This beating of their Cross-bay rivals would bring the 49ers to a 2-3 record

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- [[Arnaz Battle]] 4 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

OAK- [[Sebastian Janikowski]] 33 yard field goal

'''2nd Quarter'''

OAK- Sebastian Janikowski 36 yard field goal

OAK- [[Randy Moss]] 22 yard pass from [[Andrew Walter]] (Sebastian Janikowski kick)

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Arnaz Battle 6 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- [[Maurice Hicks]] 33 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 19 yard field goal

SF- [[Melvin Oliver]] 12 yard fumble return (Joe Nedney kick)

OAK- [[Courtney Anderson]] 8 yard pass from [[Marques Tuiasosopo]] (Sebastian Janikowski kick)

SF- Joe Nedney 39 yard field goal

=== Week 6: vs. San Diego Chargers ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''Chargers'''
|R1=14||R2=21||R3=3||R4=10||RT=48
|Home=49ers
|H1=7||H2=12||H3=0||H4=0||HT=19
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]''

Sunday, October 15, 2006 

Nothing RB [[LaDainian Tomlinson]] does on the ground really impresses the [[San Diego Chargers]] at this point. For that, the star running back must take to the air. Tomlinson seemed to be trying to jump out of [[Candlestick Park]] while hurdling the goal line on one of his four touchdown runs—and his elevation was the Chargers' inspiration. Tomlinson set a franchise record while seemingly spending most of the afternoon in the end zone, and QB [[Philip Rivers]] passed for a career-high 334 yards and two more scores in San Diego's 48-19 victory over San Francisco. Tomlinson got his third score 33 seconds before halftime, capping San Diego's 35-point first half and essentially finishing off the 49ers (2-4) with an astonishingly high leap over the goal-line pile. WR [[Bryan Gilmore]] and FB [[Moran Norris]] caught scoring passes as the Chargers gave up more points in the first half alone than they allowed in any of their first four games. But San Diego shut out San Francisco in the second half, with QB [[Alex Smith]] finishing 20 of 31 for 214 yards. San Francisco's offense has been better than expected heading to the club's bye week, but the defense has been just as bad as feared. Two weeks after giving up 41 points to the Chiefs, the 49ers seemed lost from the moment top CB [[Walt Harris (American football)|Walt Harris]] was ruled out with a hamstring injury. This crushing blow put the 49ers record at 2-4.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SD- [[Antonio Gates]] 57 yard pass from [[Philip Rivers]] ([[Nate Kaeding]] kick)

SF- [[Bryan Gilmore]] 15 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

SD- [[LaDainian Tomlinson]] 5 yard rush (Nate Kaeding kick)

'''2nd Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 42 yard field goal

SD- [[Vincent Jackson]] 33 yard pass from Philip Rivers (Nate Kaeding kick)

SD- LaDainian Tomlinson 1 yard rush (Nate Kaeding kick)

SF- [[Moran Norris]] 2 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- Safety

SD- LaDainian Tomlinson 1 yard rush (Nate Kaeding kick)

'''3rd Quarter'''

SD- Nate Kaeding 24 yard field goal

'''4th Quarter'''

SD- Nate Kaeding 44 yard field goal

SD- LaDainian Tomlinson 5 yard rush (Nate Kaeding kick)

=== Week 8: at Chicago Bears ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=49ers
|R1=0||R2=0||R3=0||R4=10||RT=10
|Home='''Bears'''
|H1=24||H2=17||H3=0||H4=0||HT=41
}}
''at [[Soldier Field]], [[Chicago, Illinois]]'' 

Sunday, October 29, 2006

Wearing bright orange uniforms and showing their speed on defense and special teams, the [[Chicago Bears]] overwhelmed the 49ers who were coming off their Bye Week. They jumped to a 24-0 first-quarter lead and 41-0 halftime cushion before coasting to a 41-10 victory. [[Brian Urlacher]]'s one-handed interception was headed to the highlight reel as soon as he tumbled to the ground after somehow batting the ball to himself. Urlacher's stellar play symbolized what kind of afternoon it was for the refreshed and still unbeaten [[Chicago Bears]] -- and how frustrating the day was for the [[San Francisco 49ers]]. San Francisco entered giving up 32 points a game, but the defense wasn't to fault early on because turnovers allowed the Bears to work from short fields. Drives started at the 15, 41 and 13, and they turned all three into touchdowns to take the big opening-quarter lead. The 49ers coughed up the ball a fourth time late in the half when WR [[Antonio Bryant]] caught a pass and fumbled, with CB [[Ricky Manning Jr.]] recovering. San Francisco averted a shutout in the fourth quarter on a 23-yard field goal by K [[Joe Nedney]] and a 16-yard TD pass from Smith to WR [[Antonio Bryant]]. QB [[Alex Smith]] finished 16 of 26 for 146 yards. RB [[Frank Gore]] rushed for 111 yards on 12 carries, thanks to a 53-yard run. The 49ers now stand at 2-5.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

CHI- [[Robbie Gould]] 43 yard field goal
 
CHI- [[Thomas Jones (American football)|Thomas Jones]] 7 yard rush (Robbie Gould kick)

CHI- [[Muhsin Muhammad]] 5 yard pass from [[Rex Grossman]] (Robbie Gould kick)

CHI- [[Cedric Benson]] 1 yard rush (Robbie Gould kick)

'''2nd Quarter'''

CHI- [[Desmond Clark]] 1 yard pass from Rex Grossman (Robbie Gould kick)

CHI- Robbie Gould 36 yard field goal

CHI- [[Desmond Clark]] 27 yard pass from Rex Grossman (Robbie Gould kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 23 yard field goal

SF- Antonio Bryant 16 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

=== Week 9: vs. Minnesota Vikings ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=Vikings
|R1=3||R2=0||R3=0||R4=0||RT=3
|Home='''49ers'''
|H1=0||H2=6||H3=0||H4=3||HT=9
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]'' 

Sunday, November 5, 2006

With just 238 total yards and a host of dropped passes and mistakes, the [[Minnesota Vikings]] showed every negative effect of its injury problems and a short week of preparation after Monday night's loss to New England. But count QB [[Brad Johnson (American football)|Brad Johnson]] among those shocked by the 49ers sudden defensive acumen. San Francisco managed just 133 total yards with its own miserable offense, but got cohesive play from the same unit that gave up 41 points by halftime last week at Chicago. The Niners simplified their game plan and hung on, stopping Minnesota's final drive with 1:04 left. QB [[Alex Smith]] passed for just 105 yards and RB [[Frank Gore]] rushed for only 41 as San Francisco hung on for its eighth straight home victory since 1988 over the Vikings, now 4-4, who'll be shaking their heads all the way back to the Twin Cities after failing to mount any significant offensive attack. QB [[Brad Johnson (American football)|Brad Johnson]] passed for 136 yards but made three turnovers for the Vikings, whose final drive ended when WR [[Troy Williamson]] dropped an on-target pass on third down before S [[Mark Roman]] and CB [[Shawntae Spencer]] prevented WR [[Bethel Johnson]] from catching a desperate pass at the goal line. K [[Joe Nedney]] left [[Monster Park]] Sunday with a game ball after accounting for all of the 49ers scoring efforts. Nedney hit from 25, 30 and 51 yards out. The 51-yarder he had to kick twice after a game clock debacle. The 49ers, now 3-5, had just enough offense to back a shocking performance by their previously pourous defense (which had allowed 150 points in its last four games), led by new starting LB and NFC Defensive Player of the Week [[Brandon Moore (linebacker)|Brandon Moore]], who finished with 14 tackles and 1 sack. With the win, the 49ers advanced to 3-5.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

MIN- [[Ryan Longwell]] 21 yard field goal

'''2nd Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 25 yard field goal

SF- Joe Nedney 30 yard field goal

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 51 yard field goal

=== Week 10: at Detroit Lions ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''49ers'''
|R1=10||R2=3||R3=3||R4=3||RT=19
|Home=Lions
|H1=0||H2=3||H3=7||H4=3||HT=13
}}
''at [[Ford Field]], [[Detroit, Michigan]]'' 

Sunday,November 12, 2006

San Francisco kept Detroit in the game with missed opportunities, then made just enough plays for a rare two-game winning streak and its first road win. RB [[Frank Gore]] set a franchise record with 148 yards rushing in the first half and scored on a 61-yard run before leaving with a concussion. San Francisco led 13-3 at halftime after scoring on three of its first four drives, wishing it had a bigger lead after out gaining Detroit 247-102 yards and recovering a fumble without giving up a turnover. The 49ers had chances to go ahead big in the third quarter because Detroit had two turnovers on its first three plays, but they came away with only a field goal and a 13-point lead. Gore then caught a 7-yard pass, wobbled off the field and didn't return. QB [[Alex Smith]]'s fumble midway through the third quarter set up a score that helped the Lions get back in the game. The 49ers drove down the field to set up K [[Joe Nedney]]'s fourth field goal, a key score because it made Detroit go for a TD instead of kicking a tying field goal late in the game. S [[Keith Lewis]] intercepted QB [[Jon Kitna]]'s pass at the 49ers' 2 with 2½ minutes left and San Francisco now 4-5 picked up the one first down it needed to seal the game, winning consecutive games for the second time since 2003. RB [[Frank Gore]] finished with career-high 159 yards rushing and San Francisco's QB [[Alex Smith]] was 14 of 20 for 136 yards with a fumble. WR [[Arnaz Battle]] caught six passes for 55 yards, and converted a third-and-4 on the final drive to allow the 49ers to run out the clock. The 49ers' defense again came up huge, allowing only 273 total offensive yards and forcing 4 turnovers. LB [[Brandon Moore (linebacker)|Brandon Moore]] was yet again the story, leading the team with 9 tackles, 2 sacks and forcing 2 turnovers. With the win, the 49ers advanced to 4-5.

'''Scoring Summary''' 

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- Frank Gore 61 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- Joe Nedney 28 yard field goal

'''2nd quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 23 yard field goal

DET- [[Jason Hanson]] 25 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 23 yard field goal

DET- [[Daniel Campbell]] 8 yard pass from [[Jon Kitna]](Jason Hanson kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 47 yard field goal

DET- Jason Hanson 33 yard field goal

===Week 11: vs. Seattle Seahawks===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=Seahawks
|R1=0||R2=0||R3=7||R4=7||RT=14
|Home='''49ers'''
|H1=3||H2=17||H3=0||H4=0||HT=20
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]'' 

Sunday, November 19, 2006

In their first match up of the season versus division-leading rival [[Seattle Seahawks]], the 49ers jumped to a 20-0 lead at halftime thanks to the combined efforts of running back Frank Gore and the defense. This was the first game back from injury for Seattle running back [[Shaun Alexander]], and he was held to just 37 rush yards. On the other side of the ball, Frank Gore ran for a career-high 212 yards on his way to topping the 1,000-yard mark for the season. The Seahawks offense turned the ball over five times during the game, including three interceptions thrown by quarterback [[Seneca Wallace]], two of which were picked off by San Francisco [[cornerback]] [[Walt Harris (American football)|Walt Harris]]. Alex Smith, 49ers quarterback, threw one touchdown pass and also rushed for a one-yard touchdown, the first rushing touchdown of his career. The win elevated the 49ers to a .500 record, and put them just one game out of first place in their division, behind the 6-4 Seahawks.

On the final play of the game, a pass to Seattle's fullback Mack Strong, the Seahawks attempted to continue the play which was similar to [[The Play]] which made the Cal-Stanford rivalry famous. However 49ers Rookie Marcus Hudson recovered the lateral attempt and the game was over. In a reference to [[The Play]], radio announcers on [[107.7 The Bone]] declared &quot;The band is NOT on the field&quot;

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 39 yard field goal

'''2nd Quarter'''

SF- Arnaz Battle 9 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick) 

SF- Alex Smith 1 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- Joe Nedney 18 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SEA- [[Deion Branch]] 38 yard pass from [[Seneca Wallace]] ([[Josh Brown (American football)|Josh Brown]] kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

SEA- [[Darrell Jackson]] 41 yard pass from Seneca Wallace (Josh Brown kick)

===Week 12: at St. Louis Rams===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=49ers
|R1=0||R2=7||R3=7||R4=3||RT=17
|Home='''Rams'''
|H1=0||H2=13||H3=0||H4=7||HT=20
}}
''at the [[Edward Jones Dome]], [[St. Louis, Missouri]]'' 

Sunday, November 26, 2006

Riding high from their home upset over the Seahawks, the 49ers flew to the [[Edward Jones Dome]] for an NFC West rematch with their historic rival, the [[St. Louis Rams]].  After a scoreless first quarter, the Niners trailed early.  In the second quarter, the Rams struck first with kicker [[Jeff Wilkins]] getting a 24-yard field goal, while RB [[Steven Jackson]] got a 36-yard TD run.  San Francisco would get on the board with RB [[Frank Gore]] getting a 12-yard TD run, yet Wilkins gave St. Louis a 51-yard field goal as time ran out on the half.  In the third quarter, the 49ers took the lead as QB [[Alex Smith]] completed a 1-yard TD pass to TE [[Eric Johnson (tight end)|Eric Johnson]] for the only score of the period.  In the fourth quarter, kicker [[Joe Nedney]] gave the Niners a six-point lead with a 24-yard field goal.  However, the Rams would get the win with QB [[Marc Bulger]] completing a 5-yard TD pass to WR [[Kevin Curtis]].  With the loss, the 49ers fell to 5-6.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''2nd Quarter'''

STL- Jeff Wilkins 24 yard field goal

STL- [[Steven Jackson]] 36 yard rush (Jeff Wilkins kick)

SF- Frank Gore 12 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

STL- Jeff Wilkins 51 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Eric Johnson 1 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 24 yard field goal

STL- [[Kevin Curtis]] 5 yard pass from Marc Bulger (Jeff Wilkins kick)

===Week 13: at New Orleans Saints===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road=49ers
|R1=3||R2=0||R3=7||R4=0||RT=10
|Home='''Saints'''
|H1=0||H2=14||H3=10||H4=10||HT=34
}}
''at the [[Louisiana Superdome]], [[New Orleans, Louisiana]]''

Sunday, December 3, 2006 

Hoping to rebound from their road loss to the Rams, the 49ers flew to the [[Louisiana Superdome]] for a Week 13 fight with the [[New Orleans Saints]].  In the first quarter, the Niners took an early lead with kicker [[Joe Nedney]] nailing a 29-yard field goal for the only score of the period.  In the second quarter, the 49ers lost their lead with RB [[Reggie Bush]]'s 1-yard and 8-yard TD runs.  In the third quarter, San Francisco came close with QB [[Alex Smith]]'s 48-yard TD pass to WR [[Antonio Bryant]], yet New Orleans gained some distance with kicker [[John Carney (American football)|John Carney]]'s 19-yard field goal and QB [[Drew Brees]]' 5-yard TD pass to Bush.  In the fourth quarter, the Saints wrapped things up with Bush's 10-yard run and Carney's 33-yard field goal.  With their second-straight loss, the 49ers fell to 5-7.

'''Scoring Summary''' 

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 29 yard field goal

'''2nd Quarter'''

NO- [[Reggie Bush]] 1 yard rush ([[John Carney (American football)|John Carney]] kick)

NO- Reggie Bush 8 yard rush (John Carney kick)

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Antonio Bryant 48 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

NO- John Carney 19 yard field goal

NO- Reggie Bush 5 yard pass from [[Drew Brees]] (John Carney kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

NO- Reggie Bush 10 yard rush (John Carney kick)

NO- John Carney 33 yard field goal

=== Week 14: vs. Green Bay Packers ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''Packers'''
|R1=7||R2=10||R3=7||R4=6||RT=30
|Home=49ers
|H1=3||H2=3||H3=7||H4=6||HT=19
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]''

Sunday, December 10, 2006

Trying to end their two-game skid, the 49ers went home for a Week 14 fight with the [[Green Bay Packers]].  In the first quarter, the Niners got an early lead with kicker [[Joe Nedney]] nailing a 24-yard field goal, yet the Packers gained the lead with QB [[Brett Favre]]'s 36-yard TD pass to WR [[Ruvell Martin]].  In the second quarter, San Francisco's troubles grew as Packers kicker [[Dave Rayner]] nailed a 23-yard field goal, while RB [[Ahman Green]] got a 1-yard TD run.  The Niners would respond with Nedney kicking a 36-yard field goal.  In the third quarter, the 49ers had RB [[Frank Gore]] get a 1-yard TD run, yet Green Bay responded with Favre completing a 68-yard TD pass to WR [[Donald Driver]].  In the fourth quarter, the Packers wrapped things up with Rayner kicking a 44-yard and a 21-yard field goal.  The Niners would get a touchdown, as QB [[Alex Smith]] completed a 52-yard TD pass to rookie TE [[Vernon Davis]], yet a botched snap foiled the following PAT.  With their third-straight loss, the 49ers fell to 5-8.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 24 yard field goal

GB- [[Ruvell Martin]] 36 yard pass from [[Brett Favre]] ([[Dave Rayner]] kick)

'''2nd Quarter'''

GB- Dave Rayner 23 yard field goal

GB- [[Ahman Green]] 1 yard rush (Dave Rayner kick)

SF- Joe Nedney 36 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 36 yard field goal

GB- [[Donald Driver]] 68 yard pass from Brett Favre (Dave Rayner kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

GB- Dave Rayner 44 yard field goal

GB- Dave Rayner 21 yard field goal

SF- Vernon Davis 52 yard pass from Alex Smith

=== Week 15: at Seattle Seahawks ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''49ers'''
|R1=0||R2=3||R3=0||R4=21||RT=24
|Home=Seahawks
|H1=7||H2=0||H3=0||H4=7||HT=14
}}
''at [[Qwest Field]], [[Seattle]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]''

Thursday, December 14, 2006 

Trying to end a three-game skid, the 49ers flew to [[Qwest Field]] for an NFC West rematch with the [[Seattle Seahawks]] on Thursday night.  In the first quarter, the Niners started off bumpy as Seahawks RB [[Shaun Alexander]] got a 3-yard TD run for Seattle's early strike and the only score of the period.  In the second quarter, San Francisco would get a field goal before halftime as kicker [[Joe Nedney]] nailed one from 39 yards out.  After a scorless third quarter, the Niners were in full force as QB [[Alex Smith]] completed an 8-yard TD pass to rookie TE [[Vernon Davis]].  Afterwards, Smith would complete a 20-yard TD pass to RB [[Frank Gore]].  Then, the 49ers wrapped the game up with Smith getting a very easy 18-yard QB sneak for a touchdown.  Seattle would get one more score as QB [[Matt Hasselbeck]] completed a 22-yard TD pass to TE [[Jerramy Stevens]].  Fortunately, the Niners would get the win and the season sweep over the Seahawks.  With the win, the 49ers improved to 6-8

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SEA- [[Shaun Alexander]] 3 yard rush (Josh Brown kick)

'''2nd Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 39 yard field goal

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Vernon Davis 8 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- Frank Gore 20 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- Alex Smith 18 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

SEA- [[Jerramy Stevens]] 22 yard pass from [[Matt Hasselbeck]] (Josh Brown kick)

=== Week 16: vs. Arizona Cardinals ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''Cardinals'''
|R1=10||R2=10||R3=0||R4=6||RT=26
|Home=49ers
|H1=3||H2=3||H3=7||H4=7||HT=20
}}
''at [[Monster Park]], [[San Francisco, California]]''

Sunday, December 24, 2006

Following their road win over the Seahawks,and hoping to clinch a playoff spot,the 49ers went home for an NFC West rematch with the [[Arizona Cardinals]].  In the first quarter, the Niners struck first with kicker [[Joe Nedney]] getting a 49-yard field goal, yet the Cardinals took the lead with kicker [[Neil Rackers]] getting a 25-yard field goal, along with RB [[Marcel Shipp]]'s 5-yard TD run.  In the second quarter, things continued to get worse for the 49ers as QB [[Matt Leinart]] completed a 6-yard to WR [[Larry Fitzgerald]], along with Rackers nailing a 39-yard field goal.  The Niners would be able get a field goal before halftime as Nedney kicked from 32 yards out.  In the third quarter, San Francisco started to come back as RB [[Frank Gore]] got a 2-yard TD run for the only score of the period.  In the fourth quarter, Arizona increased its lead as Rackers was awarded a missed 37-yard field goal and was successful in kicking a 32-yard field goal.  Even though Gore managed to get a 1-yard TD run, the Niners fell short of a comeback.  With the loss, the 49ers fell to 6-9, securing them their fourth consecutive losing season.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 49 yard field goal

AZ- Neil Rackers 25 yard field goal

AZ- [[Marcel Shipp]] 5 yard rush (Neil Rackers kick)

'''2nd Quarter'''

AZ- [[Larry Fitzgerald]] 6 yard pass from [[Matt Leinart]] (Neil Rackers kick)

AZ- Neil Rackers 39 yard field goal

SF- Joe Nedney 32 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Frank Gore 2 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

'''4th Quarter'''

AZ- Neil Rackers 37 yard field goal

AZ- Neil Rackers 32 yard field goal

SF- Frank Gore 1 yard rush (Joe Nedney kick)

=== Week 17: at Denver Broncos ===
{{Linescore Amfootball|
|Road='''49ers'''
|R1=0||R2=3||R3=14||R4=6||R5=3||RT=26
|Home=Broncos
|H1=3||H2=10||H3=3||H4=7||H5=0||HT=23
}}
''at [[Invesco Field at Mile High]], [[Denver, Colorado]]'' 

Sunday, December 31, 2006

Trying to end their season on a positive note, the 49ers flew to [[Invesco Field at Mile High]] to take on the playoff hopeful [[Denver Broncos]].  In the first quarter, the Broncos struck first with kicker [[Jason Elam]] getting a 22-yard field goal for the only score of the period.  In the second quarter, Denver continued its dominance with Elam kicking a 21-yard field goal, while CB [[Champ Bailey]] returned an interception 70 yards for a touchdown.  The Niners would get a field goal before halftime as kicker [[Joe Nedney]] got one from 46 yards out.  In the third quarter, San Francisco took the lead as QB [[Alex Smith]] completed a 32-yard TD pass to RB [[Moran Norris]], while CB [[Walt Harris (American football)|Walt Harris]] returned an interception 28 yards for a touchdown.  The Broncos would sneak close with Elam kicking a 22-yard field goal.  In the fourth quarter, Nedney gave the Niners a little cushion with a 29-yard and a 46-yard field goal.  However, Denver managed to tie the game with QB [[Jay Cutler (American football)|Jay Cutler]] completing a 9-yard TD pass to TE [[Tony Scheffler]]. The game would go to overtime, where both sides fought hard and fierce as the period wore on. San Francisco eventually prevailed with two minutes remaining as Nedney helped knock the Broncos out of the playoff picture with a game-winning 36-yard field goal. With the win, the 49ers ended their season at 7-9.

'''Scoring Summary'''

'''1st Quarter'''

DEN- [[Jason Elam]] 22 yard field goal

'''2nd Quarter'''

DEN- Jason Elam 21 yard field goal

DEN- [[Champ Bailey]] 70 yard interception return (Jason Elam kick)

SF- Joe Nedney 46 yard field goal

'''3rd Quarter'''

SF- Moran Norris 32 yard pass from Alex Smith (Joe Nedney kick)

SF- [[Walt Harris (American football)|Walt Harris]] 28 yard interception return (Joe Nedney kick)

DEN- Jason Elam 22 yard field goal

'''4th Quarter'''

SF- Joe Nedney 29 yard field goal

SF- Joe Nedney 46 yard field goal

DEN- [[Tony Scheffler]] 9 yard pass from Jay Cutler (Jason Elam kick)

Overtime

SF- Joe Nedney 36 yard field goal

==Standings==
{{2006 NFC West standings}}

{{San Francisco 49ers}}
{{San Francisco 49ers seasons}}
{{2006 NFL season by team}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2006 San Francisco 49ers Season}}
[[Category:2006 National Football League season by team|San Francisco 49ers]]
[[Category:San Francisco 49ers seasons]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
