<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="695624" ns="0" title="Vulcan salute"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Leonard Nimoy by Gage Skidmore 2.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Leonard Nimoy demonstrating the Vulcan Salute.]]
The '''Vulcan salute''' is a [[hand gesture]] consisting of a raised hand, palm forward with the [[finger]]s parted between the middle and [[ring finger]], and the thumb extended. Often, the famous line, &quot;'''Live long and prosper'''&quot;, is said after it.  The salute was devised and popularised by [[Leonard Nimoy]], who portrayed the half-[[Vulcan (Star Trek)|Vulcan]] character [[Spock|Mr. Spock]] on [[Star Trek: The Original Series|the original ''Star Trek'' television series]] in the late 1960s.

==Overview==
The Vulcan salute first appeared in 1967 on the ''Star Trek'' second season opening episode, &quot;[[Amok Time]]&quot;. The gesture famously has a reputation for being difficult to make without practice or the covert pre-positioning of the fingers, and actors on the original show reportedly had to position their fingers off-screen with the other hand before raising their hand into frame. This reputation may stem from variations in individuals' [[manual dexterity]]. This reputation is parodied somewhat in the motion picture ''[[Star Trek: First Contact]]'' when [[Zefram Cochrane]], upon meeting a Vulcan for the first time in human history, is unable to return the Vulcan salute gesture and instead shakes the Vulcan's hand.

[[File:Kohanim hands blessing photo.jpg|thumb|left|Blessing gesture that was the inspiration for the Vulcan salute]]
In his autobiography ''[[I Am Not Spock]]'', Nimoy wrote that he based it on the [[Priestly Blessing]] performed by [[Judaism|Jewish]] [[Kohen|Kohanim]] with both hands, thumb to thumb in this same position, representing the [[Hebrew alphabet|Hebrew]] letter [[Shin (letter)|Shin]] (ש), which has three upward strokes similar to the position of the thumb and fingers in the salute. The letter Shin here stands for Shaddai, meaning &quot;Almighty (God)&quot;.  Nimoy wrote that when he was a child, his grandfather took him to an [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] synagogue.  There he saw the blessing performed and was very impressed by it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/herocomplex/2009/05/leonard-nimoy-star-trek-fans-can-be-scary.html#more|title=Leonard Nimoy: 'Star Trek' fans can be scary |publisher=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The accompanying spoken blessing, &quot;''Live long and prosper''&quot; (''Dif-tor heh smusma'' in [[Vulcan (Star Trek)#Language|Vulcan language]] as spoken in ''[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture]]'') also appeared for the first time in &quot;[[Amok Time]]&quot;, scripted by [[Theodore Sturgeon]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sfsite.com/gary/stur01.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The less-known reply is &quot;Peace and long life.&quot; This format is similar to common [[Middle East]]ern greetings (''[[As-Salamu Alaykum|Salaam alaykum]]'' in Arabic and ''[[Shalom aleichem]]'' in Hebrew), meaning &quot;peace be upon you&quot;, and its reply, &quot;upon you be peace&quot;. An even more ancient variation can be found with the Ancient Egyptians: the blessing ''[[ankh wedja seneb]]'', usually translated as &quot;may he live, be prosperous, be healthy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The exact translation of the Egyptian hieroglyphics phrase into English is somewhat open to interpretation, however &quot;life&quot;, &quot;prosperity&quot; and &quot;health&quot; are the three symbols used in the formula. The [[Something Awful]] comedy website translates it as &quot;Live long&quot;..[http://www.somethingawful.com/d/comedy-goldmine/heiroglyphs.php?page=2], while the more academic source (Gardiner, Alan (1957). ''Egyptian Grammar''. Griffith Institute, Ashmolean Museum, page 239) gives it as &quot;may he live, be prosperous, be healthy.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[Romeo and Juliet]]'' contains the line, &quot;Live and be prosperous.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Act V. Sc iii. Romeo and Juliet.  Shakespeare, William. [[Folger Shakespeare Library]] Edition. 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Rock-paper-scissors-lizard-Spock]], an extension of [[Rock-paper-scissors]] utilising the gesture.
* [[Professional wrestling|Pro-wrestlers]] [[Big Van Vader]] and [[Nelson Frazier, Jr.|Big Daddy V]] used the Vulcan salute to taunt their opponents and fans.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{memoryalpha|Vulcan salute}}
*[http://www.pinenet.com/~rooster/v-salute.html The Jewish Origin of the Vulcan Salute] – a page by Rabbi Yonassan Gershom, with photos and diagrams of how the Salute forms the Hebrew letter Shin, the use of the Blessing Hands gesture on Jewish gravestones and jewelry, etc.

{{Gestures}}
{{Star Trek}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vulcan Salute}}
[[Category:Star Trek terminology]]
[[Category:Gestures]]
[[Category:Vulcans|Salute]]
[[Category:Greetings]]

[[ca:Salutació vulcaniana]]
[[es:Saludo vulcano]]
[[zh:瓦肯举手礼]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
