<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="700160" ns="0" title="Remaster"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the software term|Software remastering}}
{{Multiple issues|tone=December 2007|refimprove=July 2008}}
'''Remaster''' (and its derivations, frequently found in the phrases '''digitally remastered''' or '''digital remastering''') is a word marketed mostly in the digital audio age, although the remastering process has existed since recording began. Frequently advertised with regard to [[CD]] and [[DVD]] releases, remastering has become a powerful [[buzzword]] in multimedia industries, and it generally implies quality enhancement of sound and/or picture to a previously existing recording. To create a new master, mixing of individual session tapes tracks becomes necessary, where applicable. For example, the [[reissue]] boom that began in the mid-nineties saw remastered versions of the back-catalogues of [[Kiss (band)|Kiss]], [[The Who]], [[The Byrds]] and others, while remastered editions of first-generation DVD releases are similarly bestsellers. Despite its status as an industry buzzword, however, remastering actually refers to a fairly distinct process, one that does not inherently include the notion of a positive or neutral upgrade. 
==Mastering==
{{details|Audio mastering}}
To understand the concept of remastering, it is beneficial to understand that often a pyramid of copies would be made from a single original &quot;master&quot; recording, which might itself be based on previous recordings. For example, sound effects (a door opening, punching sounds, falling down the stairs, a bell ringing, etc.) might have been added from copies of sound effect tapes similar to modern sampling to make a radio play for broadcast. 

A ''master'' is the [[recording]] which experts state will be the definitive copy that is duplicated for the end user usually into other formats i.e. LP records, CDs, DVDs etc.. 

Problematically, several different levels of masters often exist for any one audio release. As an example, examine the way a typical music [[album]] from the 1960s was created. Musicians and vocalists were recorded on multi-track [[Magnetic tape|tape]]. This tape was [[Audio mixing (recorded music)|mix]]ed to create a [[stereo]] or [[monaural|mono]] master. A further master tape would likely be created from this original master recording consisting of [[equalization]] and other adjustments and improvements to the audio to make it sound better on record players for example.

More master recordings would be duplicated from the equalized master for regional copying purposes (for example to send to several pressing plants). Pressing masters for [[vinyl recording]]s would be created. Often these interim recordings were referred to as Mother Tapes. All vinyl records would derive from one of the master recordings.

Thus, ''mastering'' refers to the process of creating a master. This might be as simple as copying a tape for further duplication purposes, or might include the actual equalization and processing steps used to fine-tune material for release. The latter example usually requires the work of mastering engineers.

With the advent of [[digital recording]] in the late 1970s, many mastering ideas changed. Previously, creating new masters meant incurring an [[analog signal|analogue]] generational loss; in other words, copying a tape to a tape meant reducing the [[signal-to-noise ratio]]. This means how much of the original intended &quot;good&quot; information is recorded against faults added to the recording as a result of the technical limitations of the equipment used (noise, e.g. [[tape hiss]], static, etc.). Although [[Audio noise reduction|noise reduction]] techniques exist, they also increase other audio distortions such as [[azimuth shift]], [[Wow (recording)|wow]] and [[Flutter (electronics and communication)|flutter]], [[print-through]] and [[stereo image shift]].

With digital recording, masters could be created and duplicated without incurring the usual generational loss. As [[CDs]] were a [[digital]] format, digital masters created from original analog recordings became a necessity.

==Remastering==
[[File:Remaster.png|thumb|275px|right| The Big Boss - Left Original Footage and Right Re-masted Footage.]]
Remastering is the process of making a new master for an album, movie, or any other creation. It tends to refer to the process of porting a recording from an analogue medium to a digital one, but this is not always the case. 

For example, a [[vinyl record|vinyl]] LP originally pressed from a worn-out pressing master many [[generation loss|tape generations]] removed from the &quot;original&quot; master recording could be remastered and re-pressed from a better-condition tape. ''All'' [[CDs]] created from analogue sources are technically digitally remastered.

The process of creating a digital transfer of an analogue tape remasters the material in the digital domain, even if no [[equalization]], [[Audio level compression|compression]], or other processing is done to the material. Ideally, because of their high resolution, a CD or DVD (or other) release should come from the best source possible, with the most care taken during its transfer.

Additionally, the earliest days of the [[CD]] era found [[digital]] technology in its infancy, which sometimes resulted in poor-sounding digital transfers. The earliest days of the [[DVD]] era were not much different, with early [[DVD]] copies of [[movies]] frequently being produced from worn prints, with low bitrates and muffled audio.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} When the first [[CD]] remasters turned out to be bestsellers, companies soon realized that new editions of back-catalogue items could compete with new releases as a source of revenue. Back-catalogue values skyrocketed, and today it is not unusual to see expanded and remastered editions of fairly modern albums.

Master tapes, or something close to them, can be used to make CD releases. Better processing choices can be used. Better prints can be utilized, with sound elements remixed to [[5.1 surround sound]] and obvious print flaws digitally corrected. The modern era gives publishers almost unlimited ways to touch up, doctor, and &quot;improve&quot; their media, and as each release promises improved sound, video, extras and others, producers hope these upgrades will entice people into making a purchase.

==Criticism==

While digitally remastering films generally improve the visual quality, remastering audio on CDs has many critics. Many remastered CDs from the late 1990s onwards have become casualties of the [[loudness war]], where the average volume of the recording is pushed ever higher at the expense of dynamic range, making the new remastered version sound much louder at regular listening volume than an uncompressed version, making it sound very different from the original one. Some have also criticised the overuse of noise reduction in the remastering process.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stevehoffman.tv/dhinterviews/HoffLesson5.htm&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=Levine2007&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/17777619/the_death_of_high_fidelity |work=Rolling Stone |title=The Death of High Fidelity:In the age of MP3s, sound quality is worse than ever |last=Levine |first=Robert |date=December 26, 2007 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071230101658/http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/17777619/the_death_of_high_fidelity |archivedate=December 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Interview with Steve Wilson in Preston 53 Degrees venue, date 20/4/07.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
* [[Special edition]]

[[Category:Audio engineering]]

[[de:Remastering]]
[[es:Remasterizar]]
[[fr:Remastering]]
[[ja:デジタルリマスター]]
[[no:Mastertape]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
