<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7008868" ns="0" title="Florida State Seminoles football"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox NCAA football school
| TeamName         = Florida State Seminoles football
| CurrentSeason    = 2011 Florida State Seminoles football team
| Image            = Florida State University interlocking FS logo.svg
| ImageSize        = 80px
| Helmet           = Florida St OLD16.gif
| ImageSize2       = 140px
| HeadCoachDisplay = Jimbo Fisher
| HeadCoachLink    = Jimbo Fisher
| HeadCoachYear    = 2nd
| HCWins           = 18
| HCLosses         = 8
| HCTies           = 0
| Stadium          = Bobby Bowden Field at Doak Campbell Stadium
| StadCapacity     = 82,300
| StadSurface      = Grass
| Location         = [[Tallahassee, Florida]]
| ConferenceDisplay= ACC
| ConferenceLink   = Atlantic Coast Conference
| ConfDivision     = Atlantic
| FirstYear        = 1947
| AthlDirectorDisp = Randy Spetman
| AthlDirectorLink = Randy Spetman
| WebsiteName      = Seminoles.com
| WebsiteURL       = http://seminoles.com
| ATWins           = 472
| ATLosses         = 235
| ATTies           = 17
| ATPercentage     =.668
| BowlWins         = 24
| BowlLosses       = 14
| BowlTies         = 2
| NatlTitles       = 2 &lt;small&gt;(1993, 1999)&lt;/small&gt;
| ConfTitles       = 15
| Heismans         = 2
| AllAmericans     = 33
| uniform          = Image:ACC-Uniform-FSU.png
| Color1           = Garnet
| Color1Hex        = 990000
| Color2           = [[Gold (color)|Gold]]
| Color2Hex        = F1C058
| FightSong        = [[FSU Fight Song]]
| MascotDisplay    = [[Chief Osceola and Renegade|Osceola &amp; Renegade]]
| MascotLink       =
| MarchingBand     = [[Marching Chiefs]]
| PagFreeLabel     = Outfitter
| PagFreeValue     = [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]]
| PagFreeLabel     = Rivals
| PagFreeValue     = [[Miami Hurricanes football|Miami Hurricanes]]&lt;br&gt;[[Florida Gators football|Florida Gators]]&lt;br&gt;[[Clemson Tigers football|Clemson Tigers]]
}}
The '''Florida State Seminoles football''' team represents [[Florida State University]] in [[college football]]. The [[Florida State Seminoles]] compete in [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)#Division I-Bowl Subdivision|Division I-FBS]] and are members of the [[ACC Atlantic Division|Atlantic Division]] of the [[Atlantic Coast Conference]] (ACC). Florida State has won two national championships (1993 and 1999) and finished in the top five of the [[AP Poll]] for 14 straight years from 1987 through 2000. The team has produced two [[Heisman Trophy]] winners: [[quarterback]] [[Charlie Ward]] in [[1993 NCAA Division I-A football season|1993]] and [[quarterback]] [[Chris Weinke]] in [[2000 NCAA Division I-A football season|2000]]. The current head coach of the team is [[Jimbo Fisher]].  Longtime Head Coach [[Bobby Bowden]] retired following the Seminoles' win in the [[2010 Gator Bowl]]. The team plays its home games at [[Doak Campbell Stadium]], located on-campus at [[Florida State University]] in [[Tallahassee, Florida]].

==History==
===Florida State College Eleven===
[[File:FSU 1899 FootballTeam n044028.jpg|thumb|left|1899 West Florida Seminary football team at College Hall. College Hall was located at the present site of the Westcott Building on the campus of [[Florida State University]]]]
[[Florida State University]] traces the origins of its modern [[American football]] team to 1947, after the school became [[coeducational]] following more than forty years as a white women's college. However, football had been played at the school prior to its 1905 reorganization as a women's college. The sport was played at the school, which was known as the [[West Florida Seminary]] until 1901 and as [[History of Florida State University|Florida State College]] from 1901–1905, prior to 1902. However the early games were [[intramural]] between students, and not played against outside teams.&lt;ref&gt;Kabat, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1902 Florida State College students, supported by president [[Albert A. Murphree]], organized the school's first official football club to play against other schools and teams. The team was known as the &quot;Florida State College Eleven&quot; and [[W. W. Hughes]], professor of [[Latin]] and the head of men's sports at the school, served as the first coach.&lt;ref&gt;Kabat, pp. 20–24.&lt;/ref&gt; They played their first game against the Bainbridge Giants, a city team from [[Bainbridge, Georgia]], defeating them 5–0. The team then played back-to-back matches against [[Florida Agricultural College]] (which later merged into what is now the [[University of Florida]]) one week apart, winning the first 6–0 and losing the second 0–6. The following season student enthusiasm grew even more, and the Eleven arranged a full schedule of six games. They competed against teams such as the University of Florida in Lake City (as Florida Agricultural College was then called), [[Georgia Tech]], and the [[East Florida Seminary]] (another school that merged into the University of Florida), and finished the season by competing against [[Stetson College]] in [[Jacksonville, Florida|Jacksonville]] for ''[[The Florida Times-Union]]'''s Championship Cup.&lt;ref&gt;Kabat, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; The following year [[Jack Forsythe]] replaced Hughes as coach, and the Eleven won the state championship by defeating Stetson in Tallahassee.&lt;ref&gt;Kabat, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

This would be the Eleven's last season, however, as the [[Florida State Legislature]] passed the Buckman Act, which reorganized the state's colleges, and Florida State College became the Florida Female College (later Florida State College for Women), a school for white women. Four other institutions (including the University of Florida in Lake City and the East Florida Seminary) were merged into the new white men's-only [[University of the State of Florida]] in [[Gainesville, Florida|Gainesville]]. Many of Florida State's male students, including members of the [[Fraternities and sororities|fraternity]] system and the football team transferred to the new university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fsu.edu/about/history.html |title=About Florida State University - History |accessdate=2009-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1906 the new school established its first official football team led by former Florida State College coach Jack Forsythe. Several former FSC players transferred to [[Grant University]] (now the [[University of Tennessee at Chattanooga]]), with five joining Grant's football team. In 1909 several veterans of the FSC Eleven founded a city team named the Tallahassee Athletics, but this folded after one season. Except for this, until 1947 Tallahassee's only organized or collegiate football team were the team from the [[Florida Agricultural and Mechanical College for Negroes]] (now Florida A&amp;M University).&lt;ref&gt;Kabat, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early years===
The end of [[World War II]] brought enormous pressure on the university system in Florida, which saw an influx of veterans applying for college under the [[GI Bill]]. The Florida Legislature responded by renaming the Florida State College for Women the Florida State University and allowing men to attend the university for the first time since 1905. Football then returned to Florida State University, beginning in the 1947 season.  From 1948 through 1959, the Seminole football program achieved much success under coaches [[Don Veller]] and [[Tom Nugent]]. In 1950, Veller led the Seminoles to an 8-0 record, the first unbeaten season ever for any Florida college.  Nugent gave the Noles their first win over an SEC opponent with a 10-0 victory against Tennessee in 1958.

===Bill Peterson era (1960-1970)===
With the arrival of [[Bill Peterson]] in 1960, the Seminoles began their move to national prominence.  Under Peterson's direction, the Seminoles beat the Florida Gators for the first time in 1964 and earned their first major bowl bid.  Peterson also led the Seminoles to their first ever top ten ranking.  During his tenure as head coach, Peterson also gave a young assistant by the name of [[Bobby Bowden]] his first major college coaching opportunity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://seminoles.cstv.com/trads/fsu-trads-hall-new.html |title=Florida State University, Seminoles.Com website for FSU Athletics - FSU Hall of Fame |accessdate=2010-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 1967, Peterson also engineered another first for the Seminole program when he decided to begin the recruitment of [[African American]] football players.  Apparently, he did so without approval from either the school president or its athletic director.  On December 16, 1967, the Seminoles signed Ernest Cook, a fullback from Daytona Beach.  Several months later, the Seminoles would sign running back Calvin Patterson from Dade County.  Ultimately, Cook decided to switch his allegiance to Minnesota where he would become an All-Big Ten running back.  In the fall of 1968, Patterson would become the first African American student to play for the Seminoles as a starter for the Florida State freshmen football team. In the fall of 1970, [[J. T. Thomas (defensive back)|J. T. Thomas]] would become the first black to play in a varsity game for the Seminoles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/1995-01-01/features/9412270197_1_policeman-calvin-patterson-carpenters/2 | title =End Zone; The Tragic Story of Calvin Patterson, FSU's First Black Football Player. |publisher=SunSentinel.com|date=1995-01-01 |accessdate=2010-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/summary_0199-729684_ITM |title=Scholarship honors FSU's first black football player. &amp;#124; Goliath Business News |publisher=Goliath.ecnext.com |date=2004-02-01 |accessdate=2010-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bobby Bowden era (1976-2009)===
Under head coach Bobby Bowden, the Seminole football team became one of the nation's most competitive football teams, greatly expanding the tradition of football at Florida State. The Seminoles played in five national championship games between 1993 and 2001, and claimed the championship twice, in 1993 and 1999. The FSU football team was the most successful team in college football during the 1990s, boasting an 89% winning percentage. FSU also set an NCAA record for most consecutive Top 5 finishes in the AP football poll – receiving placement 14 years in a row, from 1987 to 2000. The Seminoles under Bowden were the first college football team in history to go wire-to-wire (ranked first place from preseason to postseason) since the AP began releasing preseason rankings in 1936. On December 1, 2009 Bowden announced that he would retire from coaching after the Seminoles' upcoming bowl game on New Year's Day 2010 against West Virginia in the Gator Bowl.

===The dynasty (1987–2000)===
The best years of Florida State football came in the late 1980s and throughout the 1990s. The Seminoles had 14 consecutive seasons with 10 or more wins and a top five finish. They had a record of 152–19–1 between these years (11 of their 19 losses were decided by seven points or less). FSU's accomplishments in these 14 seasons included 11 bowl wins, nine ACC championships in nine years, two Heisman Trophy winners, and two national championships.

 {| border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|AP Rank
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Championships
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Bowl
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1987 || 11–1 || 2nd |||| Won Fiesta
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1988 || 11–1 || 3rd |||| Won Sugar
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1989 || 10–2 || 3rd |||| Won Fiesta
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1990 || 10–2 || 4th |||| Won Blockbuster
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1991 || 11–2 || 4th |||| Won Cotton
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1992 || 11–1 || 2nd || ACC champions || Won Orange
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1993 Florida State Seminoles football team|1993]] || 12–1 || 1st || ACC champions, National champions  || Won Orange
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1994 || 10–1–1 || 4th || ACC champions || Won Sugar
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1995 || 10–2 || 4th || ACC co-champions || Won Orange
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1996 || 11–1 || 3rd || ACC champions || Lost Sugar
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1997 || 11–1 || 3rd || ACC champions || Won Sugar
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1998 || 11–2 || 3rd || ACC co-champions || Lost Fiesta
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1999 Florida State Seminoles football team|1999]] || 12–0 || 1st || ACC champions, National champions || Won Sugar
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2000 || 11–2 || 5th || ACC champions || Lost Orange
|}
|}

===Jimbo Fisher era (2010-present)===
On January 5, 2010, Fisher officially became the ninth head football coach in Florida State history. Fisher's ascension helped lead Florida State to a top-10 recruiting class in 2010 and the #1 and #2 recruiting class in the country, according to ESPN and Rivals. In his first season as head coach, Florida State went 10-4 with a 6-2 record in ACC conference play. The Seminoles went to their first ACC Championship Game since 2005, losing to Virginia Tech 44-33, and had their first ten win season since 2003. Fisher's first Florida State team notably beat the Miami Hurricanes 45-17 and the Florida Gators 31-7, en route to capture the Seminoles' first &quot;state championship&quot; since 1999. Florida State would go on to the Chick-Fil-A Bowl, where they would beat Steve Spurrier's South Carolina Gamecocks, 26-17.

==Historical ranking==
In terms of winning percentage, Florida State ranks as the 3rd most successful team in the past 25 years (as of the 2010 season) with a 77% win rate (231-69-2) and 12th over the last half century (1955–2010) with 67%.&lt;ref&gt;http://football.stassen.com/cgi-bin/records/calc-wp.pl?start=1955&amp;end=2010&amp;rpct=100&amp;ss=on&amp;se=on&amp;c1a=on&amp;by=Win+Pct&lt;/ref&gt;

The College Football Research Center lists Florida State as the 10th best college football program in history (ahead of rivals Miami and Florida, at #15 and #18 respectively).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cfrc.com/Archives/Top_Programs_2010.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Seven Florida State squads were listed in Billingsley’s Top 200 Teams of All Time (1869–2010),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cfrc.com/Archives/Top_200_2010.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and after the 2008 season, ESPN ranked Florida State the 9th most prestigious program in history.&lt;ref&gt;http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/news/story?id=3849028&lt;/ref&gt;

The Associated Press poll statistics show Florida State with the 7th most appearances in the final AP Top 5 (with 15).  Since the Coaches Poll first released a final poll in 1950, Florida State has 32 seasons where the team finished ranked in the top 25 in the Coaches Polls.

==Notable moments==
*'''[[2010 NCAA Division I FBS football season|2010]]''' - '''''The Golden Toe''''' -- In the first ever walk-off, game winning kick in school history, Dustin Hopkins booted a 55-yard field goal as time expired to lift the Seminoles to a 16-13 victory over Clemson.  Just a week prior, Hopkins missed a potential game winning field goal with 7 seconds left in a 37-35 loss to North Carolina.

*'''[[2005 NCAA Division I FBS football season|2005]]''' - '''''The Miami Muff''''' -- In 2005, the Florida State Seminoles finally gained some redemption for the past Wide Right heartbreaks. Trailing 10-7, the Hurricanes drove down the field to set up a game-tying field goal with 2:16 left. When the ball was snapped, it was mishandled by holder Brian Monroe and the ball never reached the kicker's foot. This ultimately led to a Florida State victory

*'''[[2003 NCAA Division I FBS football season|2003]]''' - '''''Rix to Sam''''' -- Florida held a 34-31 lead in the fourth quarter when Seminole QB [[Chris Rix]] hit WR [[PK Sam]] for a 52 yard touchdown pass with 50 seconds remaining, giving the Seminoles a 38-34 win. Before the winning score, Rix had completed a 17-yard pass on 4th and 14 deep in Seminole territory to keep the drive alive.

*'''[[2000 NCAA Division I FBS football season|2000]]''' - '''''FSU Wins Second National Championship''''' -- Florida State scored first and took advantage of a blocked punt for a touchdown, giving the Seminoles a 14–0 lead in the first quarter. Virginia Tech, led by QB [[Michael Vick]], answered with a touchdown drive of its own before the end of the quarter, but Florida State scored two quick touchdowns to begin the second quarter. Virginia Tech scored a touchdown before halftime, but halfway through the game, Florida State held a 28–14 lead. In the third quarter, Virginia Tech's offense gave the Hokies a lead with a field goal and two touchdowns. Tech failed to convert two two-point conversions, but held a 29–28 lead at the end of the third quarter. Florida State answered in the fourth quarter, however, taking a 36–29 lead with a touchdown and successful two-point conversion early in the quarter. From this point, the Seminoles did not relinquish the lead, extending it to 46–29 with another touchdown and a field goal. With the win, Florida State clinched the 1999 BCS national championship, the team's second national championship in its history.

*'''[[1996 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1996]]''' - '''''#1 vs #2''''' -- The #1–ranked and undefeated Gators came in to Tallahassee favored against the second-ranked Seminoles. The 'Noles got off to a quick start when [[Peter Boulware]] blocked the Gator's first punt of the game, resulting in a touchdown. Florida's eventual Heisman Trophy winner quarterback [[Danny Wuerffel]] threw three interceptions in the first half, and FSU had a 17–0 lead after one quarter of play. Wuerffel got on track after that, throwing for three touchdowns. The last one (to WR Reidel Anthony) cut the Florida State lead to three points with just over a minute left to play. The ensuing onside kick went out of bounds, however, and the Seminoles held on for the 24–21 upset win.

*'''[[1994 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1994]]''' - '''''The Choke at Doak''''' -- In the greatest fourth-quarter comeback of the series, the Gators led the Seminoles 31–3 after three quarters. However, the Seminoles scored 28 points in the final fifteen minutes to tie the game at 31-31. The Seminoles then won a rematch in the [[Sugar Bowl]] 23–17, referred to as &quot;The Fifth Quarter in the French Quarter.&quot;

*'''[[1994 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1994]]''' - '''''FSU Wins First National Championship''''' -- This 60th edition to the [[Orange Bowl]] featured the Nebraska Cornhuskers, and the Florida State Seminoles. Florida State came into the game 11-1, and ranked first in the nation. Nebraska came into the game undefeated at 11-0, and with a number 2 ranking. Late in 4th quarter, FSU's Heisman trophy winning quarterback [[Charlie Ward]] drove the Seminoles all the way to the Nebraska 3 yard line. The Huskers held and forced [[Scott Bentley]] to kick his fourth field goal of the night, which was good, and FSU led 18-16 with just 21 seconds remaining. Florida State players and coaches went wild on the sidelines, and were penalized for excessive celebration, costing them 15 yards on the ensuing kickoff. As a result, the Huskers were able to get a decent return and began their final possession at their own 43 yard line. As time ran down, [[Tommy Frazier]] hit tight end Trumane Bell for a 29 yard gain to the FSU 28 yard line. The clock ticked down to 0:00, setting off more chaos on the FSU sideline, complete with the compulsory Gatorade bath given to FSU coach [[Bobby Bowden]]. However, referee John Soffey ruled that Bell was down with 1 second left on the clock, and ordered the field cleared, allowing Nebraska placekicker Byron Bennett an opportunity to kick the game winning field goal. But the 45 yard kick sailed wide left, preserving the 18-16 win for the Seminoles.

*'''[[1993 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1993]]''' - '''''Ward to Dunn''''' -- The Seminoles came into The Swamp ranked No. 1 and looking to play for the national championship. Florida had clinched the SEC East championship and were themselves ranked in the top five. Early on it looked to be a Florida State rout, as the Seminoles took a 27–7 lead into the fourth quarter. However, Florida scored two quick touchdowns to make the score 27–21. With six minutes remaining, the Seminoles faced third down at their own 21-yard-line. In what many people consider the greatest play in Florida State history, Heisman Trophy winning quarterback [[Charlie Ward]] hit freshman [[Warrick Dunn]] up the sideline for a 79-yard game-clinching touchdown run and a 33–21 FSU win.

*'''[[1991 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1991]]''' - '''''Big Win at the Big House''''' -- In the their trip ever at Michigan Stadium, Florida State would beat the #3 Michigan Wolverines 51-31 behind quarterback [[Casey Weldon]]'s 268 yards and 2 TDs and [[Amp Lee]]'s 122 yards rushing. One of the most memorable plays in Florida State history occurred in the 1st quarter when cornerback [[Terrell Buckley]] returned an [[Elvis Grbac]] interception for a 40 yard touchdown.

*'''[[1988 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1988]]''' - '''''Puntrooskie''''' -- Florida State had a 4th down and 4 to go at its own 21 yard line with about a minute and a half to go in the 4th quarter at Clemson. They lined up to punt but the ball was snapped to an up back who handed it to [[Leroy Butler]] who ran down the left side of the field all the way to the Clemson 4 yard line. Florida State wound up kicking a field goal to win the game, 24-21.

*'''[[1964 NCAA Division I FBS football season|1964]]''' - '''''FSU's First Win Over UF''''' -- Florida State had never beaten Florida, gaining only a 3-3 tie in six tries, all at Gainesville. Since 1947, when Florida State College for Women became Florida State University, its athletes have endured &quot;girl school&quot; taunts. During the week Florida players wore stickers on their helmets in practice reading &quot;Never, FSU, Never.&quot; The thrust may have added considerable fuel to FSU's already blazing fire. FSU's aggressive defense helped force five Florida fumbles, and the Seminoles claimed four of them. The Tribe intercepted two passes. FSU lost two fumbles and had one pass intercepted. [[Steve Tensi]] connected on 11 of 22 throws for 190 yards. [[Fred Biletnikoff]], a decoy much of the way and well covered by Florida, caught only two, for 78 yards and a TD. The 16-7 win ended six years of FSU frustration against the Gators and left Florida with a 5-3 record. FSU ended its regular season with a 8-1-1 chart, a showing exceeded only by an unbeaten 1950 season which came at a time when the Tribe was playing in a lesser league.

==Stadium==
[[File:Doak Campbell Stadium Inside.jpg|thumb|left|A view of the north end zone]]
The stadium, named after former Florida State President [[Doak S. Campbell]], hosted its first game against the [[Randolph-Macon College]] [[Yellowjacket]]s on October 7, 1950 with the Seminoles winning the game 40&amp;ndash;7. At that time the facility had a [[seating capacity]] of 15,000. Florida State first began play at '''Centennial Field''' during the team's inaugural 1947 season and would continue to play there for the following two years (1948 and 1949). Doak Campbell Stadium, with its original capacity of 15,000 in 1950, was built at a cost of $250,000. In 1954, the stadium grew to a capacity of 19,000. Six thousand more seats were added in 1961. During the [[Bill Peterson]] era (1960–70), the stadium was expanded to 40,500 seats, and it remained at that capacity for the next 14 years.  Since that time, the stadium has expanded to almost 83,000, largely due to the success of the football team under head coach [[Bobby Bowden]] coupled with the ever growing student body. It now is the largest football stadium in the Atlantic Coast Conference (ACC). Aesthetically, a [[brick]] [[facade]] surrounding the stadium matches the architectural design of most of the buildings on the university's campus. In addition to the obvious recreational uses, The University Center surrounds the stadium and houses many of the university's offices. The field was officially named Bobby Bowden field on November 20, 2004 as Florida State hosted intrastate rival Florida.

==Current coaching staff==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; white-space:nowrap;&quot;
|-
! Name !! Position
|-
| [[Jimbo Fisher]] || Head Coach
|-
| [[James Coley]] || Offensive Coordinator/Tight Ends Coach
|-
| [[Mark Stoops]] || Defensive Coordinator/Defensive Backs Coach
|-
| Eddie Gran || Special Teams Coordinator/Running Backs Coach
|-
| [[Dameyune Craig]] || Recruiting Coordinator/Quarterbacks Coach
|-
| [[Lawrence Dawsey]] || Wide Receivers Coach
|-
| D.J. Eliot || Defensive Ends Coach
|-
| Odell Haggins || Defensive Line Coach
|-
| [[Greg Hudson]] || Linebackers Coach
|-
| Rick Trickett || Offensive Line Coach
|}

==Head coaches==
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; &lt;!-- Records through end of 2010 season --&gt;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Tenure
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Coach
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Years
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Pct.
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1947 || [[Ed Williamson]] || 1 || 0-5 || .000
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1948–1952 || [[Don Veller]] || 5 || 31-12-1 || .716
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1953–1958 || [[Tom Nugent]] || 6 || 34-28-1 || .548
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1959 || [[Perry Moss]] || 1 || 4-6 || .400
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1960–1970 || [[Bill Peterson]] || 11 || 62-42-11 || .587
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1971–1973 || [[Larry Jones]] || 3 || 15-19 || .441
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1974–1975 || [[Darrell Mudra]] || 2 || 4-18 || .182
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1976–2009 || [[Bobby Bowden]] || 34 || 304-97-4^ || .758
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2010–present || [[Jimbo Fisher]] || 2 || 18-8 || .692
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| Totals
! style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| 9 coaches
! style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| 65 seasons
! style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| 472-235-17
! style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| .667
|}
|}

^ Bobby Bowden's record does not include 12 wins that were vacated that would otherwise make his record 316-97-4.

==Championships==
===National championships===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Coach
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Selector
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Bowl
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1993 Florida State Seminoles football team|1993]] || [[Bobby Bowden]] || [[AP National Championship Trophy|AP]], [[AFCA National Championship Trophy|Coaches]] || 12–1 || Won [[1994 Orange Bowl|Orange]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1999 Florida State Seminoles football team|1999]] || [[Bobby Bowden]] || [[BCS National Championship Game|BCS]], [[AP National Championship Trophy|AP]], [[AFCA National Championship Trophy|Coaches]] || 12–0 || Won [[2000 Sugar Bowl|Sugar]]
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! colspan=&quot;3;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| Total National Titles
! colspan=&quot;2;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| '''2'''
|}
|}

===Conference championships===
'''Conference Affiliations'''
*1947: [[NCAA Division I-A independent schools|Independent]]
*1948–1950: Dixie Conference
*1951–1991: Independent
*1992–present: [[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC]]

{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Conference
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Overall Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Conference Record
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1948 || Dixie || 7–1 || 4–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1949 || Dixie || 9–1 || 4–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1950 || Dixie || 8–0 || 2–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1992 || ACC || 11–1 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1993 || ACC || 12–1 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1994 || ACC || 10–1–1 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1995&lt;small&gt;†&lt;/small&gt; || ACC || 10–2 || 7–1
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1996 || ACC || 11–1 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1997 || ACC || 11–1 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1998&lt;small&gt;†&lt;/small&gt; || ACC || 11–2 || 7–1
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1999 || ACC || 12–0 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2000 || ACC || 11–2 || 8–0
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2002 || ACC || 9–5 || 7–1
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2003 || ACC || 10–3 || 7–1
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2005 || ACC || 8–5 || 5–3
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| colspan=4; | &lt;small&gt;† Denotes co-champions&lt;/small&gt;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| Total Conference Titles
! colspan=&quot;2;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| '''15'''
|}
|}

===Divisional championships===
Divisional play began in the Atlantic Coast Conference at the start of the 2005 football season following the addition of [[Boston College]].  Coincidentally, in both years, they had the same 5–3 record as Boston College.  In 2005, Florida State won at BC, whereas BC won at Florida State in 2008.

{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Division
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Overall Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Conference Record
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2005 || ACC Atlantic || 8–5 || 5–3
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2008&lt;small&gt;†&lt;/small&gt; || ACC Atlantic || 8–4 || 5–3
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2010 || ACC Atlantic || 9–3 || 6–2
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| colspan=4; | &lt;small&gt;†&lt;/small&gt; Denotes co-champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| Total Division Titles
! colspan=&quot;2;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| '''3'''
|}
|}

===Conference championship games===
Florida State has appeared in the [[ACC Championship Game]] as the winner of the Atlantic Division twice, defeating Virginia Tech of the Coastal Division in the inaugural game in 2005, and losing to Virginia Tech in 2010.

{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Division Championship
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|ACC CG Result
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Opponent
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|PF
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|PA
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2005 || ACC Atlantic || '''W''' || [[Virginia Tech Hokies football|Virginia Tech]] || 27 || 22
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2010 || ACC Atlantic || '''L''' || [[Virginia Tech Hokies football|Virginia Tech]] || 33 || 44
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:center; color:#900; background:#f1c058;&quot;
|| '''Totals'''
|| '''2'''
|| '''1–1'''
||
|| '''60'''
|| '''66'''
|}
|}

==Undefeated seasons==
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Coach
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1950 || 8-0|| [[Don Veller]] 
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1999 || 12-0|| [[Bobby Bowden]] 
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:center; color:#900; background:#f1c058;&quot;
|| '''Totals'''
|| '''2'''
||
|}
|}

==State Championships==
A &quot;State Championship&quot; refers to when the Florida State University Seminoles, the University of Florida Gators, or the University of Miami Hurricanes beat the other two teams from the state of Florida in the same season.
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Coach
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Score Against Miami
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Score Against Florida
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1964 || Bill Peterson || 14-0 || 16-7
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1978 || Bobby Bowden || 31-21 || 38-21
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1979 || Bobby Bowden || 40-23 || 27-16
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1989 || Bobby Bowden || 24-10 || 24-17
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1993 || Bobby Bowden || 28-10 || 33-21
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1996 || Bobby Bowden || 34-16 || 24-21
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1998 || Bobby Bowden || 26-14 || 23-12
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1999 || Bobby Bowden || 31-21 || 30-23
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2010 || Jimbo Fisher || 45-17 || 31-7
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 2011 || Jimbo Fisher || 23-19 || 21-7
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:center; color:#900; background:#f1c058;&quot;
|| '''Totals'''
|| '''10'''
||
||
|} 
|}

==Records and results==
===Year-by-year results===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; class=
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Year
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Coach
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Record
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Championships
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1947 || Ed Williamson || 0–5 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1948 || Don Veller || 7–1 || Dixie Conference Champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1949 || Don Veller || 9–1 || Dixie Conference Champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1950 || Don Veller || 8–0 || Dixie Conference Champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1951 || Don Veller || 6–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1952 || Don Veller || 1–8–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1953 || Tom Nugent || 5–5 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1954 || Tom Nugent || 8–4 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1955 || Tom Nugent || 5–5 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1956 || Tom Nugent || 5–4–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1957 || Tom Nugent || 4–6 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1958 || Tom Nugent || 7–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1959 || Perry Moss || 4–6 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1960 || Bill Peterson || 3–6–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1961 || Bill Peterson || 4–5–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1962 || Bill Peterson || 4–3–3 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1963 || Bill Peterson || 4–5–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1964 || Bill Peterson || 9–1–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1965 || Bill Peterson || 4–5–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1966 || Bill Peterson || 6–5 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1967 || Bill Peterson || 7–2–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1968 || Bill Peterson || 8–3 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1969 || Bill Peterson || 6–3–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1970 || Bill Peterson || 7–4 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1971 Florida State Seminoles football team|1971]] || Larry Jones || 8–4 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1972 || Larry Jones || 7–4 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1973 || Larry Jones || 0–11 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1974 || Darrell Mudra || 1–10 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1975 || Darrell Mudra || 3–8 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1976 || Bobby Bowden || 5–6 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1977 || Bobby Bowden || 10–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1978 || Bobby Bowden || 8–3 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1979 || Bobby Bowden || 11–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1980 || Bobby Bowden || 10–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1981 || Bobby Bowden || 6–5 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1982 || Bobby Bowden || 9–3 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1983 || Bobby Bowden || 8–4 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1984 || Bobby Bowden || 7–3–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1985 Florida State Seminoles football team|1985]] || Bobby Bowden || 9–3 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1986 || Bobby Bowden || 7–4–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1987 || Bobby Bowden || 11–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1988 || Bobby Bowden || 11–1 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1989 || Bobby Bowden || 10–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1990 || Bobby Bowden || 10–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1991 Florida State Seminoles football team|1991]] || Bobby Bowden || 11–2 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1992 Florida State Seminoles football team|1992]] || Bobby Bowden || 11–1 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1993 Florida State Seminoles football team|1993]] || Bobby Bowden || 12–1 || ACC champions; National Champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1994 || Bobby Bowden || 10–1–1 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1995 || Bobby Bowden || 10–2 || ACC co-champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| 1996 || Bobby Bowden || 11–1 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1997 Florida State Seminoles football team|1997]] || Bobby Bowden || 11–1 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1998 Florida State Seminoles football team|1998]] || Bobby Bowden || 11–2 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[1999 Florida State Seminoles football team|1999]] || Bobby Bowden || 12–0 || ACC champions; National Champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2000 Florida State Seminoles football team|2000]] || Bobby Bowden || 11–2 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2001 Florida State Seminoles football team|2001]] || Bobby Bowden || 8–4 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2002 Florida State Seminoles football team|2002]] || Bobby Bowden || 9–5 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2003 Florida State Seminoles football team|2003]] || Bobby Bowden || 10–3 || ACC champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2004 Florida State Seminoles football team|2004]] || Bobby Bowden || 9–3 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2005 Florida State Seminoles football team|2005]] || Bobby Bowden || 8–5 || ACC Atlantic Division champions; Inaugural [[2005 ACC Championship Game|ACC Championship Game]] champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2006 Florida State Seminoles football team|2006]] || Bobby Bowden ||2–6&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2007 Florida State Seminoles football team|2007]] || Bobby Bowden || 0–6&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2008 Florida State Seminoles football team|2008]] || Bobby Bowden || 9–4 || ACC Atlantic Division co-champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2009 Florida State Seminoles football team|2009]] || Bobby Bowden || 7–6 ||
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2010 Florida State Seminoles football team|2010]] || Jimbo Fisher || 10–4 || ACC Atlantic Division champions
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[2011 Florida State Seminoles football team|2011]] || Jimbo Fisher || 8-4 ||
|}
|}
1- Five (5) 2006 season wins vacated due to using ineligible players

2- All Seven (7) 2007 season wins vacated due to using ineligible players

===All-time bowl record===
Florida State has played in 40 bowl games in its history and owns a 24&amp;ndash;14&amp;ndash;2 record in those games. Florida State's two most common opponents in bowl play have been Oklahoma and Nebraska. The Seminoles are 1&amp;ndash;3 against Oklahoma in bowl games and 4&amp;ndash;0 against Nebraska. Florida State's most common bowl destination has been the Orange Bowl (8 trips). Its second most common bowl destinations have been the Sugar Bowl and the Gator Bowl (6 trips each). The Seminoles also hold the longest active Bowl Appearance record at 30 appearances (after the 2011 season) only being surpassed in the all-time record by Nebraska with 35 appearances.
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; class=&quot;collapsible collapsed&quot; !Year-by-Year
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Date
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Bowl
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Win/Loss
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Opponent
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|PF
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|PA
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| January 2, 1950 || [[Cigar Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[Wofford College|Wofford]] || 19 || 6
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| January 1, 1955 || [[Sun Bowl]] || '''L''' || [[UTEP|Texas-El Paso]] || 20 || 47
|- align=center
| December 13, 1958 || [[Bluegrass Bowl]] || '''L''' || [[Oklahoma State Cowboys football|Oklahoma State]] || 6 || 15
|- align=center
| January 2, 1965 || [[Gator Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[Oklahoma Sooners football|Oklahoma]] || 36 || 19
|- align=center
| December 24, 1966 || Sun Bowl || '''L''' || [[University of Wyoming|Wyoming]] || 20 || 28
|- align=center
| December 30, 1967 || Gator Bowl || '''T''' || [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|Penn State]] || 17 || 17
|- align=center
| December 30, 1968 || [[Peach Bowl]] || '''L''' || [[LSU Tigers football|LSU]] || 27 || 31
|- align=center
| December 27, 1971 || [[Fiesta Bowl]] || '''L''' || [[Arizona State Sun Devils football|Arizona State]] || 38 || 45
|- align=center
| December 23, 1977 || [[Capital One Bowl|Tangerine Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[Texas Tech Red Raiders football|Texas Tech]] || 40 || 17
|- align=center
| January 1, 1980 || [[Orange Bowl (game)|Orange Bowl]] || '''L''' || Oklahoma || 7 || 24
|- align=center
| January 1, 1981 || Orange Bowl || '''L''' || Oklahoma || 17 || 18
|- align=center
| December 30, 1982 || Gator Bowl || '''W''' || [[West Virginia Mountaineers|West Virginia]] || 31 || 12
|- align=center
| December 30, 1983 || Peach Bowl || '''W''' || [[North Carolina Tarheels|North Carolina]] || 28 || 3
|- align=center
| December 22, 1984 || [[Citrus Bowl]] || '''T''' || [[Georgia Bulldogs football|Georgia]] || 17 || 17
|- align=center
| December 30, 1985 || Gator Bowl || '''W''' || Oklahoma State || 34 || 23
|- align=center
| December 31, 1986 || [[All-American Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[Indiana Hoosiers|Indiana]] || 27 || 13
|- align=center
| January 1, 1988 || Fiesta Bowl || '''W''' || [[Nebraska Cornhuskers football|Nebraska]] || 31 || 28
|- align=center
| January 2, 1989 || [[Sugar Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[Auburn Tigers football|Auburn]] || 13 || 7
|- align=center
| January 1, 1990 || Fiesta Bowl || '''W''' || Nebraska || 41 || 17
|- align=center
| December 28, 1990 || [[Blockbuster Bowl]] || '''W''' || Penn State || 24 || 17
|- align=center
| January 1, 1992 || [[Cotton Bowl Classic]] || '''W''' || [[Texas A&amp;M Aggies football|Texas A&amp;M]] || 10 || 2
|- align=center
| January 1, 1993 || Orange Bowl || '''W''' || Nebraska || 27 || 14
|- align=center
| January 1, 1994 || Orange Bowl (national title game) || '''W''' || Nebraska || 18 || 16
|- align=center
| January 2, 1995 || Sugar Bowl || '''W''' || [[Florida Gators football|Florida]] || 23 || 17
|- align=center
| January 1, 1996 || Orange Bowl || '''W''' || [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish football|Notre Dame]] || 31 || 26
|- align=center
| January 2, 1997 || Sugar Bowl (national title game)|| '''L''' || Florida || 20 || 52
|- align=center
| January 1, 1998 || Sugar Bowl || '''W''' || [[Ohio State Buckeyes football|Ohio State]] || 31 || 14
|- align=center
| January 4, 1999 || Fiesta Bowl&lt;br&gt;[[BCS National Championship Game]] || '''L''' || [[Tennessee Volunteers football|Tennessee]] || 16 || 23
|- align=center
| January 4, 2000 || Sugar Bowl&lt;br&gt;BCS National Championship Game || '''W''' || [[Virginia Tech Hokies football|Virginia Tech]] || 46 || 29
|- align=center
| January 3, 2001 || Orange Bowl&lt;br&gt;BCS National Championship Game || '''L''' || Oklahoma || 2 || 13
|- align=center
| January 1, 2002 || Gator Bowl || '''W''' || Virginia Tech || 30 || 17
|- align=center
| January 1, 2003 || Sugar Bowl || '''L''' || Georgia || 13 || 26
|- align=center
| January 1, 2004 || Orange Bowl || '''L''' || [[Miami Hurricanes football|Miami]] || 14 || 16
|- align=center
| January 1, 2005 || Gator Bowl || '''W''' || West Virginia || 30 || 18
|- align=center
| January 3, 2006 || Orange Bowl || '''L'''&lt;br&gt;(3 OT) || Penn State || 23 || 26
|- align=center
| December 27, 2006 || [[Emerald Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[UCLA Bruins Football|UCLA]] || 44 || 27&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
|- align=center
| December 31, 2007 || [[Music City Bowl]] || '''L''' || [[Kentucky football#Football|Kentucky]] || 28 || 35
|- align=center
| December 27, 2008 || [[Champs Sports Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[Wisconsin Badgers football|Wisconsin]] || 42 || 13
|- align=center
| January 1, 2010 || Gator Bowl || '''W''' || West Virginia || 33 || 21
|- align=center
| December 31, 2010 || [[Chick-Fil-A Bowl]] || '''W''' || [[South Carolina]] || 26 || 17
|- align=center
| December 29, 2011 || Champs Sports Bowl ||      || Notre Dame   ||     ||
|- class=&quot;unsortable&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900; text-align:center;&quot;
| '''Total''' || '''41 bowl games''' || '''24–14–2''' || || '''955''' || '''793'''
|}
|}
1 - Bowl win vacated due to using ineligible players

==Rivalries==
Florida State's traditional rivals have been the [[Florida Gators football|University of Florida Gators]] and the [[Miami Hurricanes football|University of Miami Hurricanes]].

Since 2002, the [[Florida Cup]] has been awarded to Florida State, Florida, or Miami if one team defeats the other two teams in the same season (it is not necessary for the two losing teams to have played each other). Five Florida Cups have been awarded, with Miami winning three, Florida State winning one, and Florida winning one. Florida State won the Cup in 2010 by beating Miami and Florida, even though Florida did not play Miami that season.

===Florida===
{{Main|Florida – Florida State rivalry}}
{{See also|The Choke at Doak}}
Florida State and Florida have played each other 56 times. The Gators hold a 33&amp;ndash;21&amp;ndash;2 all-time lead against the Seminoles. During the Bobby Bowden Era, FSU barely lost out at 17&amp;ndash;18&amp;ndash;1. Current Florida State head coach [[Jimbo Fisher]] is 2-0 against University of Florida.

===Miami===
{{Main|Miami – Florida State rivalry}}
{{See also|Wide Right I|Wide Right II}}
The Miami-Florida State rivalry dates to 1951, when the [[Miami Hurricanes football|Miami Hurricanes]] defeated the Seminoles 35&amp;ndash;13 in their inaugural meeting. The schools have played uninterrupted since 1966, with Miami holding the all-time advantage, 31&amp;ndash;25.

During the 1980s and 90s, the series emerged as one of the premier rivalries in college football. Between 1983 and 2002, the Hurricanes and Seminoles combined to win 7 national championships (5 for Miami, 2 for Florida State) and play in a whopping 13 national championship games (83, 85, 86, 87, 89, 91, 92, 93, 96, 98, 99, 00, 01). The rivalry has been popular not only because of its profound national championship implications and the competitiveness of the games but also because of the immense NFL-caliber talent typically present on the field when the two teams meet. The famous 1987 matchup featured over 50 future [[NFL]] players on both rosters combined.

The games have been characterized by remarkable team speed, big plays, hard hitting, and missed field goals. In 2004, the intensity of the rivalry was dialed up another notch when Miami joined the [[Atlantic Coast Conference]] and the teams became intra-conference rivals.

The rivalry is a [[Nielsen ratings|television ratings]] bonanza, accounting for the two highest rated college football telecasts in [[ESPN]] history. The 2006 game between Miami and FSU was the second most-viewed college football game, regular season or bowl, in the history of [[ESPN]], averaging 6,330,000 households in viewership (6.9 rating). It trailed only the 1994 game between Miami and FSU, which notched a 7.7 rating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | accessdate=2006-11-29 | url=http://www.theacc.com/sports/m-footbl/spec-rel/090706aag.html | title=FSU-Miami Game Grabs ESPN's Largest Audience | agency=Associated Press | date=2006-09-06 | publisher=TheACC.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Clemson===
{{Main|The Bowden Bowl}}
Florida State has a lesser rivalry with Atlantic Division foe [[Clemson University]] [[Clemson Tigers football|Tigers]].  Florida State leads the all-time series 17–8.  Florida State dominated the contests through most of the 1990s but 1999 marked a milestone as the hire of Bobby Bowden's son Tommy led to the first meeting, in 1999, which was the first time in Division I-A history that a father and a son met as opposing head coaches in a football game.  During the time Tommy coached at Clemson the game was known as the &quot;Bowden Bowl&quot; Bobby won the series in the 9 years it played before Tommy's resignation, winning 5–4 with all four losses within the last five seasons. Tommy's four wins in the series remain the only times the son has ever beaten the father when facing off as head coach in any of America's four major sports.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}.

One sticking point in the rivalry remains that a proud Clemson Tiger program that was strong in the 1980s had won 6 of the past 11 ACC titles from 1981–1991.  1991 would be the last ACC Championship the Tigers would ever win as Florida State entered the ACC in 1992 and proceeded to win the next 9 ACC Championships in a row, and 12 of the next 14 in the series.  The Tigers advanced to the 2009 ACC title game for the first time since its inception in 2005 but a late [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets football|Georgia Tech]] victory lengthened the Tigers' title drought.

==Academic cheating scandal==
In Spring 2007, several FSU athletes including football players were accused of cheating in an online music history class. The NCAA ruled that Florida State was guilty of major violations, announced that it would reduce scholarship limits in 10 sports and force Florida State to vacate all of the victories in 2006 and 2007 in which the implicated athletes participated and placed the university on probation for four years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/07/sports/ncaafootball/07ncaa.html | work=The New York Times | title=N.C.A.A. Penalizes Florida State for Academic Fraud | first=Lynn | last=Zinser | date=March 7, 2009 | accessdate=May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Florida State appealed parts of the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/2009-04-23-fsu-appeal_N.htm | work=USA Today | title=Florida State formally appeals part of NCAA sanctions | date=April 23, 2009 | accessdate=May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 5, 2010 the [[NCAA]] Infractions Appeals Committee denied FSU's appeal and ruled that all penalties, including vacating up to fourteen wins during the 2006–2007 seasons would remain in effect. FSU officials responded that they were surprised and disappointed by the NCAA decision and felt that their own investigation and self-imposed penalties were sufficient. The NCAA Infractions Appeals Committee responded that &quot;the cooperative efforts of the university in the academic cheating scandal involving 61 Florida State athletes failed to outweigh the aggravating factors in the case.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orlandosentinel.com/sports/college/seminoles/os-fsu-ncaa-appeal-bowden-01052010,0,413893.story |title=Florida State loses NCAA appeal; Bowden to lose victories |publisher=Orlandosentinel.com |date= |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The games to be vacated will be determined by certifying in which of the 14 games any of the 25 ineligible players competed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.tbo.com/content/2010/jan/05/051159/fsu-loses-ncaa-appeal-must-vacate-wins/ |title=FSU loses NCAA appeal, must vacate wins |publisher=.tbo.com |date=2010-01-05 |accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
12 wins were eventually vacated in all.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=FSU academic fraud: Case timeline|url=http://www.orlandosentinel.com/sports/orl-fsu-academic-fraud-timeline-091108,0,695768.story|newspaper=Orlando Sentinel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mascot==
{{main|Native American mascot controversy#Florida State Seminoles}}

==Individual national award winners==
===Players===
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*'''[[Heisman Trophy]]'''
:[[Charlie Ward]] - 1993
:[[Chris Weinke]] -2000
*'''[[Maxwell Award]]'''
:[[Charlie Ward]] - 1993
*'''[[Walter Camp Award]]'''
:[[Charlie Ward]] - 1993
*'''[[Davey O'Brien Award]]
:[[Charlie Ward]] - 1993
:[[Chris Weinke]] - 2000
*'''[[Dick Butkus Award]]
:[[Paul McGowan (American football)|Paul McGowan]] - 1987
:[[Marvin Jones (American football)|Marvin Jones]] - 1992
{{col-2}}
*'''[[Johnny Unitas Golden Arm Award]]
:[[Casey Weldon]] - 1991
:[[Charlie Ward]] - 1993
:[[Chris Weinke]] - 2000
*'''[[Jim Thorpe Award]]
:[[Deion Sanders]] - 1988
:[[Terrell Buckley]] - 1991
*'''[[Lombardi Award]]
:[[Marvin Jones (American football)|Marvin Jones]] - 1992
:[[Jamal Reynolds]] - 2000
*'''[[Lou Groza Award]]
:[[Sebastian Janikowski]] - 1998, 1999
:[[Graham Gano]] - 2008
{{col-end}}

===Coaches===
*'''[[The Home Depot Coach of the Year Award]]'''
:[[Bobby Bowden]] - 1994
*'''[[Broyles Award]]'''
:[[Mickey Andrews]] - 1996

==Helmets==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; | Year(s) Used
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; | Description
! scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; | Image
|-
| 1962–1964 || In 1962, plain gold helmets were used only during the first two games, against The Citadel and Kentucky. This design was used through 1964 where it was used for some games. || [[File:Florida St OLD1.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1962 || Beginning with the team's third game in 1962, FSU introduced a triple helmet design scheme. On their helmets the offensive unit wore an arrow logo, the defensive unit a tomahawk, and the multi-purpose players an &quot;indian head&quot;. This scheme was in place until the end of the 1962 season. || [[File:Florida St OLD4.gif|150px|Offensive Helmet]][[File:Florida St OLD3.gif|150px|DefensiveHelmet]][[File:Florida St OLD2.gif|150px|Multi-Purpose Helmet]]
|-
|1964 || While this design was in use for most of the 1964 season, the team used plain gold helmets (like the first helmet shown above) during at least the game against Georgia in 1964.
 || [[File:Florida St OLD5.gif|150px]] 
|-
| 1965 || Used for the 1965 season. || [[File:Florida St OLD6.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1966–1968 || Used for the 1966 through 1968 seasons.  || [[File:Florida St OLD7.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1968 || This design was used only during the inaugural Peach Bowl game in Atlanta on December 30, 1968, a 31–27 loss to LSU. || [[File:Florida St OLD8.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1969 || Used for the last eight games of the 1969 season. || [[File:Florida St OLD9.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1970 || Used for the 1970 season. || [[File:Florida St OLD10.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1971–1974 || Used for for the 1971 through 1974 seasons. || [[File:Florida St OLD11.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1975 || This design was only used during the first two games against Texas Tech and Utah State at the beginning of the 1975 season.|| [[File:Florida St OLD12.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1975 || Used during one game only, a 10–6 loss to Iowa State on September 27, 1975. || [[File:Florida St OLD13.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1975 || Used for the last eight games of the season. || [[File:Florida St OLD14.gif|150px]]
|-
| 1976–present || This helmet has been worn since 1976 and has remained unchanged.  || [[File:Florida St OLD16.gif|150px]]
|-
| 2009 || Black helmets were worn during the November 21, 2009 home game against Maryland in order to &quot;pay tribute to Osceola, the legendary Native American warrior whose leadership of the Seminoles during the Second Seminole War has made him an enduring symbol of the unconquered spirit that Florida State athletes seek to embody&quot;. || [[File:Florida St OLD15.gif|150px]]
|}

==Players of note==
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; class=&quot;collapsible collapsed&quot;
|-
!Current/Former Professional players
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Clifton Abraham]] - [[Defensive back]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Derrick Alexander (defensive end)|Derrick Alexander]] - [[Defensive end]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Mister Alexander]]- [[Linebacker]], [[Houston Texans]]
*[[Brian Allen (linebacker)|Brian Allen]] - [[Linebacker]], [[St. Louis Rams]]
*[[Greg Allen]] - [[Running Back]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Richard Amman]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Terry Anthony]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Joe Avezzano]] - [[Center (American football)|Center]], [[New England Patriots]]
*[[Tom Bailey (American football)|Tom Bailey]] - [[Running Back]], [[Philadelphia Eagles]]
*[[Shannon Baker]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Indianapolis Colts]]
*[[Alex Barron (American football)|Alex Barron]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[New Orleans Saints]]
*[[Ed Beckman]] - [[Tight End]], [[Kansas City Chiefs]]
*[[Edgar Bennett]] - [[Running Back]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Scott Bentley]] - [[Placekicker]], [[Denver Broncos]], [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Louis Berry]] - [[Punter (American football)|Punter]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Fred Biletnikoff]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Anquan Boldin]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Baltimore Ravens]]
*[[Lorenzo Booker]] - [[Running Back]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Michael Boulware]] - [[Safety (American football position)|Safety]], [[Seattle Seahawks]], [[Houston Texans]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Peter Boulware]] - [[Linebacker]]-[[Defensive End]], [[Baltimore Ravens]]
*[[Jeff Braunwart]] - [[Linebacker]] - [[Safety]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Leon Bright]] - [[Kick Returner]], [[New York Giants]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Derrick Brooks]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Everette Brown]] - [[Defensive End]]/[[Linebacker]], [[Carolina Panthers]]
*[[Milford Brown]] - [[Offensive Guard]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Tony Bryant]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Terrell Buckley]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Green Bay Packers]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Brodrick Bunkley]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Devin Bush]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Atlanta Falcons]], [[St. Louis Rams]]
*[[Bobby Butler (American football)|Bobby Butler]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Leroy Butler]] - [[Free Safety]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Marion Butts]] - [[Running Back]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[Bill Capece]] - [[Placekicker]], [[Houston Oilers]]
*[[Bill Cappleman]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Greg Carr (American football)|Greg Carr]] - [[Wide receiver]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[Alphonso Carreker]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Green Bay Packers]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Duane Carrell]] - [[Punter (American football)|Punter]], [[Dallas Cowboys]], [[Los Angeles Rams]]
*[[Dexter Carter]] - [[Running Back]], [[San Francisco 49ers]]
*[[Jerome Carter]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Pat Carter]] - [[Tight End]], [[Detroit Lions]], [[Los Angeles Rams]]
*[[Tony Carter (cornerback)|Tony Carter]] - [[Cornerback (American football)|Cornerback]], [[free agent]]
*[[Walter Carter]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*Marcello Church - [[Linebacker]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Derrick Clark]] - [[Running Back]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Harvey Clayton]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]
*[[Tay Cody]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[Randy Coffield]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Seattle Seahawks]], [[New York Giants]]
*[[Laveranues Coles]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[New York Jets]], [[Washington Redskins]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Andre Cooper]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Bert Cooper]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Vernon Crawford]] - [[Linebacker]], [[New England Patriots]]
*[[Henri Crockett]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Zack Crockett]] - [[Fullback (American football)|Fullback]], [[Indianapolis Colts]], [[Oakland Raiders]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Antonio Cromartie]] - [[Cornerback]], [[New York Jets]]
*[[Jeff Curchin]] - [[Offensive Tackle]] [[Offensive Guard]], [[Chicago Bears]]
*[[Buster Davis (linebacker)|Buster Davis]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Arizona Cardinals]], [[Indianapolis Colts]], [[Houston Texans]]
*[[Chauncey Davis]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Chris Davis (football player)|Chris Davis]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Tennessee Titans]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Lawrence Dawsey]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]], [[New York Giants]]
*[[William &quot;Red&quot; Dawson|Bill Dawson]] - [[Tight End]], [[Boston Patriots]]
*[[Rhett Dawson]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Houston Oilers]]
*[[Howard Dinkins]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Darnell Dockett]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Arizona Cardinals]]
*[[Dedrick Dodge]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Seattle Seahawks]], [[San Francisco 49ers]]
*[[Char-ron Dorsey]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Ron Dugans]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Jamie Dukes]] - [[Center (American football)|Center]]/[[Offensive Guard]], [[Atlanta Falcons]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Warrick Dunn]] - [[Running Back]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Mario Edwards]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[['Omar Ellison]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[Tom Feamster]] - [[Placekicker]], [[History of the Indianapolis Colts|Baltimore Colts]]
*[[Lane Fenner]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[Jackie Flowers]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Victor Floyd]] - [[Running Back]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[William Floyd (American football)|William Floyd]] - [[Fullback (American football)|Fullback]], [[San Francisco 49ers]], [[Carolina Panthers]]
*[[Andre Fluellen]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Detroit Lions]]
*[[Dan Footman]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Cleveland Browns]], [[Indianapolis Colts]]
*[[Todd Fordham]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]
*[[Reggie Freeman]] - [[Linebacker]], [[New Orleans Saints]]
*[[Corey Fuller]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Steve Gabbard]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Michael Ray Garvin]] - [[Wide Receiver]]/[[Cornerback]], [[Arizona Cardinals]]
*[[Graham Gano]] - [[Placekicker]], [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Talman Gardner]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[New Orleans Saints]]
*[[Kent Gaydos]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Derrick Gibson]] - [[Safety (American football position)|Safety]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Chip Glass]] - [[Tight End]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Hector Gray]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Detroit Lions]]
*[[E.G. Green]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Indianapolis Colts]]
*[[Lamont Green]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Letroy Guion]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Grant Guthrie]] - [[Placekicker]], [[Birmingham Americans]], [[Buffalo Bills]]
*[[Odell Haggins]] - [[Nose Tackle]], [[San Francisco 49ers]]
*[[Kim Hammond]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Eric Hayes (American football)|Eric Hayes]] - [[Defensive Tackle]] - [[Nose guard|Nose Guard]], [[Seattle Seahawks]]
*[[Geno Hayes]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Mario Henderson]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Jim Hendley]] - [[Center (American football)|Center]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Dick Hermann]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Jessie Hester]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Ron Hester]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Montrae Holland]] - [[Guard (American football)|Guard]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Chris Hope]] - [[Safety (American football position)|Safety]], [[Tennessee Titans]]
*[[Rodney Hudson]]- [[Center (American football)|Center]]/[[Guard (American football)|Guard]], [[Kansas City Chiefs]]
*[[Gary Huff]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Chicago Bears]]
*[[Deon Humphrey]] - [[Linebacker]], [[San Diego Chargers]], [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]
*[[Charlie Hunt]] - [[Linebacker]], [[San Francisco 49ers]]
*[[Paul Irons]] - [[Tight End]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Alonzo Jackson]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]
*[[Bobby Jackson (cornerback)|Bobby Jackson]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[New York Jets]]
*[[Dexter Jackson (American football)|Dexter Jackson]] - [[Safety (American football position)|Safety]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Sebastian Janikowski]] - [[Placekicker]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Garth Jax]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Michael Jennings (American football)|Michael Jennings]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Brad Johnson (American football)|Brad Johnson]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Minnesota Vikings]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]], [[Washington Redskins]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Greg Johnson (American football)|Greg Johnson]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Philadelphia Eagles]]
*[[Jerry Johnson (American football)|Jerry Johnson]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Lonnie Johnson]] - [[Tight End]], [[Buffalo Bills]]
*[[Reggie Johnson (American football)|Reggie Johnson]] - [[Tight End]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Travis Johnson]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[San Diego Chargers]]
*[[Fred Jones (linebacker)|Fred Jones]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Greg Jones (American football)|Greg Jones]] - [[Fullback (American football)|Fullback]], [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]
*[[Hassan Jones]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Marvin Jones (American football)|Marvin Jones]] - [[Linebacker]], [[New York Jets]]
*[[Walter Jones (American football)|Walter Jones]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[Seattle Seahawks]]
*[[Willie Jones (American football)|Willie Jones]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[Danny Kanell]] - [[Quarterback]], [[New York Giants]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Bill Kimber]] - [[Defensive End]], [[New York Giants]]
*[[Kevin Knox]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Arizona Cardinals]]
*[[Ken Lanier]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Amp Lee]] - [[Running Back]], [[San Francisco 49ers]], [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Keith Lester]] - [[Tight End]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Ron Lewis (wide receiver)|Ron Lewis]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[San Francisco 49ers]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Kevin Long (offensive lineman)|Kevin Long]] - [[Center (American football)|Center]], [[Tennessee Oilers]]
*[[Kim Mack]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Seattle Seahawks]]
*[[Nick Maddox]] - [[Running Back]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Joe Majors]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Houston Oilers]]
*[[Martin Mayhew]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Kez McCorvey]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Detroit Lions]]
*[[Dale McCullers]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Bryant McFadden]] - [[Cornerback]], [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]
*[[Toddrick McIntosh]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Dennis McKinnon]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Chicago Bears]]
*[[Scott McLean]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Ryan McMahon]]- [[Center (American football)|Center]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Eddie McMillan]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Los Angeles Rams]]
*[[Adrian McPherson]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Grand Rapids Rampage]] ([[Arena Football League (1987-2008)|AFL]])
*[[Travis Minor]] - [[Running Back]], [[Miami Dolphins]], [[St. Louis Rams]]
*[[Snoop Minnis|Marvin &quot;Snoop&quot; Minnis]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Kansas City Chiefs]]
*[[Orson Mobley]] - [[Tight End]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Eric Moore (defensive end)|Eric Moore]] - [[Defensive End]], [[New England Patriots]]
*[[Zeke Mowatt]] - [[Tight End]], [[New York Giants]]
*[[Les Murdock]] - [[Placekicker]], [[New York Giants]]
*[[Lee Nelson (American football)|Lee Nelson]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[St. Louis Cardinals]]
*[[Gerald Nichols]] - [[Nose Tackle]], [[New York Jets]]
*[[A.J. Nicholson]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Lee Paige]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Sterling Palmer]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Gary Parris]] - [[Tight End]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Julian Pittman]] - [[Defensive End]], [[New Orleans Saints]]
*[[Scott Player]] - [[Punter (American football)|Punter]], [[Arizona Cardinals]], [[New England Patriots]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Tommy Polley]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Christian Ponder]]- [[Quarterback]]- [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[David Ponder]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Kendyll Pope]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Indianapolis Colts]]
*[[Eric Powell (American football)|Eric Powell]] - [[Defensive End]], [[UFL Orlando]] ([[United Football League (2009)|UFL]])
*[[Willie Reid]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Samari Rolle]] - [[Cornerback]], [[Tennessee Titans]], [[Baltimore Ravens]]
*[[Tony Romeo]] - [[Tight End]], [[Boston Patriots]]
*[[Gerard Ross]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Seattle Seahawks]]
*[[Orpheus Roye]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[P.K. Sam]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Buffalo Bills]]
*[[Garrison Sanborn]] - [[Long snapper]], [[Buffalo Bills]]
*[[Deion Sanders]] - [[Cornerback]], [[Atlanta Falcons]], [[San Francisco 49ers]], [[Dallas Cowboys]], [[Baltimore Ravens]], [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Corey Sawyer]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[Stanley Scott]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Ron Sellers]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Dallas Cowboys]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Clay Shiver]] - [[Center (American football)|Center]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Mike Shumann]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[San Francisco 49ers]]
*[[Corey Simon]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Philadelphia Eagles]], [[Indianapolis Colts]]
*[[Carl Simpson]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Chicago Bears]]
*[[Ernie Sims]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Indianapolis Colts]]
*[[Antone Smith]] - [[Running Back]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Barry Smith (American football)|Barry Smith]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Kendall Smith]]- [[Linebacker]]- [[Arizona Cardinals]]
*[[Larry Smith (defensive tackle)|Larry Smith]] - [[Defensive Tackle]], [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]
*[[Sammie Smith]] - [[Running Back]], [[Miami Dolphins]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Shevin Smith]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Jesse Solomon]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Minnesota Vikings]], [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Greg Spires]] - [[Defensive End]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Rohn Stark]] - [[Punter (American football)|Punter]], [[History of the Indianapolis Colts|Baltimore Colts]]
*[[Walt Sumner|Walter Sumner]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[Steve Tensi]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Nat Terry]] - [[Defensive Back]], [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]
*[[Tra Thomas]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[Philadelphia Eagles]], [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]
*[[Craphonso Thorpe]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Winnipeg Blue Bombers]] ([[Canadian Football League|CFL]])
*[[Lawrence Timmons]] - [[Linebacker]], [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]
*[[Javon Walker]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
*[[B. J. Ward (American football)|B.J. Ward]] - [[Safety (American football position)|Safety]], [[Free Agent]]
*[[Peter Warrick]] - [[Wide Receiver]], [[Bloomington Extreme]] ([[Indoor Football League|IFL]])
*[[Leon Washington]] - [[Running Back]], [[Seattle Seahawks]]
*[[Pat Watkins]] - [[Safety (American football position)|Safety]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Dekoda Watson]]- [[Linebacker]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Chris Weinke]] - [[Quarterback]], [[Carolina Panthers]], [[San Francisco 49ers]]
*[[Markus White]]- [[Linebacker]], [[Washington Redskins]]
*[[Ray Willis]] - [[Offensive Tackle]], [[Miami Dolphins]]
*[[Kamerion Wimbley]] - [[Defensive End]]/[[Linebacker]], [[Oakland Raiders]]
|}

===College Football Hall of Famers===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot;
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Name
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Position
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Years
! style=&quot;background:#900; color:#f1c058;&quot;|Induction
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Ron Sellers]] || Wide Receiver || 1966–68 || 1988
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Fred Biletnikoff]] || Wide Receiver || 1962–64 || 1991
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Darrell Mudra]] || Coach || 1974–75 || 2000
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Bobby Bowden]] || Coach || 1976–2009 || 2006
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Charlie Ward]] || Quarterback || 1989, '91–93 || 2006
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Ron Simmons]] || Nose Guard || 1977–1980 || 2009
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
| [[Deion Sanders]] || Defensive Back || 1985–1988 || 2011
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! colspan=&quot;4;&quot; style=&quot;background:#f1c058; color:#900;&quot;| Total Hall of Famers – 7
|}
|}

===Retired jerseys===
* #2 - [[Deion Sanders]], DB, 1985–88
* #10- [[Derrick Brooks]], LB, 1991–1994
* #16 - [[Chris Weinke]], QB, 1997–2000
* #17 - [[Charlie Ward]], QB, 1989–93
* #25 - [[Fred Biletnikoff]], WR, 1962–64
* #27 - [[Terrell Buckley]], DB, 1989–1991
* #28 - [[Warrick Dunn]], RB, 1993–96
* #34 - [[Ron Sellers]], FL, 1966–68
* #50 - [[Ron Simmons]], NG, 1977–80

===Other famous players===
{{main|List of Florida State University football players}}
*[[Fred Biletnikoff]] - [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]] [[Wide Receiver]]
*[[Lee Corso]] - Retired [[college football]] [[head coach]], [[ESPN]] [[College GameDay (football)|College Gameday]] analyst
*[[Burt Reynolds]] - Actor
*[[Ron Simmons]] - A football legend in his own right when he played at Florida State, Simmons would later go on to fame as a [[professional wrestler]] under his own name and under the name '''Faarooq''' after a short stint with the [[Cleveland Browns]]
*[[T. K. Wetherell]] - former President of [[Florida State University]]
*[[Mack Brown]] - current head coach of the [[Texas Longhorns football|Texas Longorns]] football team.

===Four year Lettermen===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; class=&quot;collapsible collapsed&quot;
|-
!Seminole Football Lettermen List
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nolefan.org/nole-fan.swf&lt;/ref&gt;{{Unreliable source?#template-documentation|date=September 2010}}
*No. 31 - [[Billy Allen]] - Safety - 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984
*No. 26 - [[Greg Allen (American football)|Greg Allen]] - Tailback - 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984
*No. 09 - [[Richie Andrews]] - Kicker - 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990
*No. 08 - [[Terry Anthony]] - Wide Receiver - 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
*No. 66 - [[Parrish Barwick]] - Offensive Lineman - 1982, 1984, 1985, 1986
*No. 06 - [[Louis Berry]] - Punter - 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986
*No. 76 - [[Alphonso Carreker]] - Defensive Tackle - 1980, 1981, 1982, 1983
*No. 13 - [[Dexter Carter]] - Tailback - 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
*No. 59 - [[Keith Carter (American football)|Keith Carter]] - Linebacker - 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
*No. 85 - [[Pat Carter]] - Tight End - 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
*No. 68 - [[Lenny Chavers]] - Nose Guard - 1981, 1983, 1984, 1985
*No. 29 - [[Lawrence Dawsey]] - Wide Receiver - 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990
*No. 28 - [[Dedrick Dodge]] - Free Safety - 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
*No. 05 - [[Chip Ferguson]] - Quarterback - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 27 - [[Victor Floyd]] - Tailback - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 10 - [[Corian Freeman]] - Cornerback &amp; Linebacker - 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990
*No. 76 - [[Steve Gabbard]] - Defensive Tackle - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 03 - [[Herb Gainer]] - Wide Receiver - 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
*No. 21 - [[John Hadley]] - Free Safety &amp; Linebacker - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 53 - [[Odell Haggins]] - Nose Guard - 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
*No. 78 - [[Eric Hayes (American Football)|Eric Hayes]] - Defensive Tackle - 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
*No. 46 - [[Felton Hayes]] - Linebacker - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 99 - [[Bruce Heggie]] - Linebacker - 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986
*No. 04 - [[Jessie Hester]] - Wide Receiver - 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984
*No. 55 - [[Fred Jones (linebacker)|Fred Jones]] - Linebacker - 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986
*No. 88 - [[Hassan Jones]] - Wide Receiver - 1982, 1983, 1984, 1985
*No. 32 - [[Martin Mayhew]] - Cornerback - 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
*No. 40 - [[Greg Newell]] - Free Safety - 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
*No. 83 - [[Dave Roberts (tight end)|Dave Roberts]] - Tight End - 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990
*No. 20 - [[Keith Ross]] - Tailback - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 63 - [[Mark Salva]] - Offensive Lineman - 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
*No. 02 - [[Deion Sanders]] - Cornerback - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 16 - [[Tracy Sanders]] - Cornerback - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 37 - [[Stan Shiver]] - Strong Safety - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 26 - [[Alphonso Williams]] - Strong Safety - 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988
*No. 17 - [[Eric Williams (cornerback)|Eric Williams]] - Cornerback - 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
|}

===Bob Crenshaw Award winners===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; class=&quot;collapsible collapsed&quot;
|-
![[Bob Crenshaw Award]] (Player with the Biggest Heart)
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
Given in the memory of Robert E. (Bob) Crenshaw (Played 1952–55), Florida State Football Captain in 1954 and student leader who was killed in a jet crash in 1958. The plaque's inscription reads: &quot;To the football player with the Biggest Heart.&quot; The recipient is chosen by his teammates as the man who best exemplifies the qualities that made Bob Crenshaw an outstanding football player and person.
*1958 Al Ulmer, Guard
*1959 Ramon Rogers, Center
*1960 Abner Bigbie, Fullback
*1961 Paul Andrews, Fullback
*1962 Jim Sims, Tackle
*1964 Larry Brinkley, Fullback
*1964 Dick Hermann, Linebacker
*1965 Howard Ehler, Defensive Back
*1966 Ed Pope, Guard
*1967 Kim Hammond, Quarterback
*1968 Billy Gunter, Running Back
*1969 Stan Walker, Guard
*1970 Bill Lohse, Linebacker
*1971 Bill Henson, Defensive Tackle
*1972 David Snell, Defensive Back
*1973 Steve Bratton, Defensive End
*1974 Jeff Gardner, Offensive Guard
*1975 Lee Nelson, Defensive Back
*1976 Joe Camps, Defensive Back
*1977 Aaron Carter, Linebacker
*1978 Scott Warren, Defensive End
*1979 Greg Futch, Offensive Tackle
*1980 Monk Bonasorte, Defensive Back
*1981 Barry Voltapetti, Offensive Tackle
*1982 Blair Williams, Quarterback
*1983 [[Ken Roe]], Linebacker
*1984 [[Todd Stroud]], Noseguard
*1985 [[Pete Panton]], Tight End
*1986 [[Greg Newell]], Free Safety
*1987 [[Mark Salva]], Center
*1988 [[Jason Kuipers]], Offensive Guard
*1989 [[Tony Yeomans]], Offensive Guard
*1990 [[Lawrence Dawsey]], Wide Receiver
*1991 [[Dan Footman]], Defensive End
*1992 [[Robbie Baker]], Center
*1993 Jon Nance, Noseguard
*1994 Steve Gilmer, Safety
*1994 Enzo Armella, Noseguard
*1995 Todd Rebol, Linebacker
*1996 Connell Spain, Defensive Tackle
*1997 [[Greg Spires]], Defensive End
*1998 Troy Saunders, Cornerback
*1999 Reggie Durden, Cornerback
*2000 Patrick Newton, Linebacker
*2001 Bradley Jennings, Linebacker
*2002 [[Anquan Boldin]], Wide Receiver
*2003 [[David Castillo]], Center
*2004 [[Bryant McFadden]], Cornerback
*2005 [[Andre Fluellen]], Defensive Tackle
*2006 [[Darius McClure]], Safety
*2007 [[Anthony Houllis]], Rover
*2008 [[Ryan McMahon]], Center
*2009 [[Ryan McMahon]], Center
*2009 Markus White, Defensive End
*2010 [[Andrew Datko]], Offensive Tackle
|}

==Current roster==
{{Florida State Seminoles roster}}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*{{cite journal |last1=  Kabat|first1= Ric A.|last2= |first2= |year=July 1991 |title= Before the Seminoles: Football at Florida State College, 1902-1904|journal= Florida Historical Quarterly|publisher= Florida Historical Society|volume= 70|issue= 1|pages= 20–37|url= http://brokert10.fcla.edu/DLData/CF/FullText/fhq_70_1.txt|doi= }}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* {{Official website|http://www.seminoles.com/sports/m-footbl/fsu-m-footbl-body.html}}

{{Florida State Seminoles football navbox}}
{{Florida State University}}
{{Atlantic Coast Conference football navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Florida State Seminoles Football}}
[[Category:Florida State Seminoles football|*]]
[[Category:Sports clubs established in 1947]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
