<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="70350" ns="0" title="Marie Bashir"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox Governor
| image = Marie-bashir-in-wahroonga-2008 Crop.jpg
| honorific-prefix = &lt;small&gt;[[Her Excellency]] [[Professor]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
| name = Marie Bashir&lt;br /&gt;
| honorific-suffix = &lt;small&gt;[[Companion of the Order of Australia|AC]], [[Commander of the Royal Victorian Order|CVO]]&lt;/small&gt;
| order = 37th
| office = Governor of New South Wales
| term_start = 1 March 2001
| term_end = 
| lieutenant = [[James Spigelman]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Tom Bathurst]]
| monarch = [[Elizabeth II]]
| predecessor = [[Gordon Samuels]]
| successor =
| order2 = 17th [[List of University of Sydney people#Administration|Chancellor of the University of Sydney]]
| term_start2 = 1 June 2007
| term_end2 = 
| predecessor2 = [[Kim Santow]]
| successor2 =
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1930|12|01|df=y}}
| birth_place = [[Narrandera]], [[New South Wales]], [[Australia]]
| death_date =
| death_place =
| spouse = [[Nicholas Shehadie|Sir Nicholas Shehadie]]
| relations =
| children = Michael Shehadie&lt;br/&gt;Susan Shehadie&lt;br/&gt;Alexandra Shehadie
| residence = [[Mosman, New South Wales]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Government House, Sydney]]
| alma_mater = [[University of Sydney]]
| occupation = 
| profession = Medicine and Psychiatry
| religion =
| signature =
| website = 
| footnotes =
}}

'''Marie Roslyn Bashir''' [[Companion of the Order of Australia|AC]], [[Commander of the Royal Victorian Order|CVO]] (born 1 December 1930) is the present [[Governor of New South Wales]] since 2001 and also the [[Chancellor]] of the [[University of Sydney]] since 2007. Born in [[Narrandera]], [[New South Wales]], Bashir graduated from the University of Sydney in 1956 and held various medical positions, with a particular emphasis in psychiatry. In 1993 Bashir was appointed as the Clinical Director of Mental Health Services for the Central Sydney Area, which she held until she was appointed as Governor in March 2001. She was further appointed in June 2007 as Chancellor of the [[University of Sydney]].

==Early life and background==
Marie Roslyn Bashir was born in 1930 in [[Narrandera]], New South Wales, to [[Lebanese people|Lebanese]]-born parents Michael Bashir and Victoria Melick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldpress.org/0601people2.htm|title=Marie Bashir: From Psychiatry to Politics|last=Coleman|first=Sarah|publisher=[[World Press Review]]|accessdate=20 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=book1&gt;{{cite book|last=Clune|first=David|authorlink=|coauthors=Turner, Ken|title=The Governors of New South Wales: 1788-2010|publisher=Federation Press|year=2009|location=Sydney|pages=pg 614|nopp=Y|url=|doi=|id=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her father and her paternal uncle were both medical graduates from the [[American University of Beirut]] while her maternal family had come to Australia in the 19th century.&lt;ref name=book1/&gt; Bashir attended Narrandera Public School and enrolled in 1943 in [[Sydney Girls High School]], where her mother had also attended.&lt;ref name=DistinguishedOldGirls&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.sghs.nsw.edu.au/History/index.html|title= Distinguished Old Girls |accessdate= 25 May 2008|work= The History of Sydney Girls High School|publisher= Sydney Girls High School}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bashir then moved to Sydney to live with her grandmother in order to attend. Upon graduating, Bashir studied at the [[Sydney Conservatorium of Music]], becoming a proficient violinist.&lt;ref name=book2/&gt; 

She completed the degrees of [[Bachelor of Medicine, Bachelor of Surgery|Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery]] (MBBS) in 1956 at the [[University of Sydney]], residing at [[The Women's College, University of Sydney|The Women's College]] from 1950 to 1955. In 1959 she was elected to the College Council, became Honorary Secretary in 1960 and was Chair from 1982 to 1990. She took up life membership of the College Union in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.thewomenscollege.com.au/marie-bashir.php|title= Marie Bashir|accessdate= 8 August 2010|publisher= The Women's College}}&lt;/ref&gt; While at university she met rising rugby player, [[Nicholas Shehadie]], and on 23 February 1957 they were married in [[St Philip's Church, Sydney]] by [[Felix Arnott|Dr Felix Arnott]], then the Warden of [[St Paul's College, University of Sydney]].&lt;ref name=book2&gt;{{cite book|last=Clune|first=David|coauthors=Turner, Ken|title=The Governors of New South Wales: 1788-2010|pages=pg 615|nopp=Y|url=|doi=|id=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Together they had their first child, Michael, in 1959, followed by two daughters, Susan and Alexandra. 

==Medical career==
Upon her graduation in medicine, Bashir took up a posting as a junior resident medical officer at [[St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney|St Vincent's Hospital]] and then to the [[Royal Alexandra Hospital for Children]]. After first living in [[Elizabeth Bay, New South Wales|Elizabeth Bay]], Bashir and Shehadie moved their family to [[Pendle Hill, New South Wales|Pendle Hill]] in Western Sydney, where Bashir worked as a General Practitioner. However, wanting to assist people suffering from mental illnesses, Bashir eventually decided to take up postgraduate studies in Psychiatry. To make this easier, Bashir and her family moved back into central Sydney to [[Mosman, New South Wales|Mosman]] on the North Shore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Clune|first=David|coauthors=Turner, Ken|title=The Governors of New South Wales: 1788-2010|pages=pp 615–616|nopp=Y|url=|doi=|id=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1971 Bashir was named as &quot;[[Australian Mother of the Year Award|Australian Mother of the Year]]&quot;. When Shehadie was made [[List of Mayors and Lord Mayors of Sydney|Lord Mayor of Sydney]], Bashir became the Lady Mayoress of Sydney from 1971 to 1973. When Shehadie was knighted in 1976, Bashir acquired the title 'Lady Shehadie', but seldom uses it, preferring to use her maiden name. After completion of postgraduate studies in psychiatry, she was made a Member of the [[Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists]] in 1971, becoming a Fellow in 1980. From 1972, Bashir was a teacher, lecturer and mentor to medical students at The University of Sydney.&lt;ref name=USyd&gt;{{cite press release| title=Professor Marie Bashir elected University Chancellor| publisher=University of Sydney| date=30 April 2007| url=http://www.usyd.edu.au/news/84.html?newsstoryid=1687| accessdate=21 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972 Bashir was appointed Director of the [[Rivendell Child, Adolescent and Family Unit|Rivendell Child, Adolescent and Family Service]], which provides consultative services for young people with emotional and psychiatric issues. In 1987 she was appointed director of the Community Health Services in the Central Sydney Area, which put emphasis on early childhood services, migrant and Indigenous health as well as the elderly. On 13 June 1988 she was made an [[Officer of the Order of Australia]] (AO) &quot;In recognition of service to medicine, particularly in the field of adolescent mental health&quot;.&lt;ref name=AO&gt;[http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=883752&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true Officer of the Order of Australia], AO, 13 June 1988, itsanhonour.gov.au&lt;br /&gt;'''Citation:''' ''In recognition of service to medicine, particularly in the field of adolescent mental health''.&lt;/ref&gt; 

From 1990 to 1992, she served on the New South Wales Women's Advisory Council. In 1993, she was appointed as Clinical Professor of Psychiatry at the [[University of Sydney]], and in 1994 as the Clinical Director of Mental Health Services for the Central Sydney Area. This was a time of major reform in mental health service delivery, which contributed to substantial change in the provision of public sector mental health services and she served until 2001.&lt;ref name=USyd/&gt; In her university role, Bashir instrumental in developing collaborative teaching programs between colleagues in [[Vietnam]] and [[Thailand]] with Australian psychiatrists, chairing the [[University of New South Wales]] Third World Health Group (1995-2000) and supporting various financial and social support programmes for International students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Clune|first=David|coauthors=Turner, Ken|title=The Governors of New South Wales: 1788-2010|pages=pg 617|nopp=Y|url=|doi=|id=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1995, in a partnership with the [[Aboriginal Medical Service]], [[Redfern, New South Wales|Redfern]], she established the Aboriginal Mental Health Unit, which provides regular clinics and counselling at both the Aboriginal Medical Service in Sydney and mainstream centres. From 1996, Bashir also took up the consultative role of senior psychiatrist to the Aboriginal Medical Service. As well as champoining the health of indigenous Australians, Bashir also continued her focus on youth and juvenile issue, particularly through her terms chairing the NSW Juvenile Justice Advisory Council (1991-1999) and as conultative psychiatrist to Juvenile Justice Facilities (1993-2000).&lt;ref name=USyd/&gt; On 1 January 2001, Bashir was awarded the [[Centenary Medal]].&lt;ref name=CM&gt;[http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=1123499&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true Centenary Medal], 1 January 2001, itsanhonour.gov.au&lt;/ref&gt;

==Governor and Chancellor==
In early 2001, on the recommendation of Premier [[Bob Carr]], [[Elizabeth II|Elizabeth II, Queen of Australia]], appointed Bashir as the [[Governor of New South Wales]], thus becoming the state's first female governor, and the first governor of any Australian state from a Lebanese background. She was sworn in on 1 March 2001 and on 30 March she was appointed as a [[Companion of the Order of Australia]] (AC).&lt;ref name=AC&gt;[http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=885264&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true Companion of the Order of Australia], AC, 30 March 2001, itsanhonour.gov.au&lt;br /&gt;'''Citation:''' ''In recognition of service as Governor of New South Wales''.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon her appointment, &lt;i&gt;Sydney Morning Herald&lt;/i&gt; journalist [[David Marr]] noted: &quot;what could be more valuable behind the scenes in Macquarie St than this woman's unique expertise with troubled adolescents?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;D.Marr, ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 2 March 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Bashir's appointment was welcomed by both sides of politics and commended in a &lt;i&gt;Sydney Morning Herald&lt;/i&gt; editorial as &quot;an inspired choice&quot; as well as noting that Bashir would be &quot;a powerful advocate for the powerless&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Clune|first=David|coauthors=Turner, Ken|title=The Governors of New South Wales: 1788-2010|pages=pg 619|nopp=Y|url=|doi=|id=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In that role, Bashir departed from past practice. For Australian aborigines, Bashir launched an indigenous health initiative to support indigenous medicine and nursing students as well as supporting the progress of reconciliation. Bashir also took up the position of Patron of the Gay and Lesbian Counselling Service, which addresses mental and social issues in the LGBT community. In 2002, Bashir became Patron of the Australia-Vietnam Medical Trust and became intimately involved in collaborative health programs in Vietnam, particularly in rural areas. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Clune|first=David|coauthors=Turner, Ken|title=The Governors of New South Wales: 1788-2010|pages=pg 625|nopp=Y|url=|doi=|id=|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 May 2001, the [[Governor-General of Australia|Governor-General]], [[William Deane|Sir William Deane]], invested Bashir as a Dame of Grace of the [[Most Venerable Order of the Hospital of St John of Jerusalem]] (DStJ).&lt;ref name=DStJ&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gg.gov.au/program.php/view/id/114/|title=Governor-General's Program – 17 May 2001|publisher=[[Governor-General of Australia]]|accessdate=3 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having previously studied violin at the [[Conservatorium of Music, Sydney]], in 2002 Bashir was asked to become the Patron of the Sydney University Graduate Choir. She is also a Patron of [[Opera Australia]] and the [[Sydney Symphony Orchestra]].

In 2003 Bashir received the Mental Health Princess Award, awarded by [[Galyani Vadhana|Princess Galyani Vadhana of Thailand]], for contribution to collaborative mental health programs between Australia and Thailand and in 2004 she was recognised as an [[Australian Living Treasures|Australian Living Treasure]].&lt;ref name=nrhc/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nsw.nationaltrust.org.au/about/treasures.asp|title=Australia's Living National Treasures|publisher=[[National Trust of Australia]]|accessdate=3 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004 she was made an Honorary Member of the [[United Nations Development Fund for Women]] (UNIFEM).&lt;ref name=nrhc&gt;{{cite web|url=http://9thnrhc.ruralhealth.org.au/keynotes/docs/transcript/bashir_KN_transcript.pdf|title=9th National Rural Health Conference|accessdate=21 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2004, Bashir was appointed Commander of the [[National Order of the Cedar]] by His Excellency General [[Emile Lahoud]], President of the Republic of Lebanon.&lt;ref name=nrhc/&gt; On 14 September, Premier Carr announced that he would recommend to the Queen that Bashir's term be extended for another three years. Buckingham Palace confirmed his recommendation on 1 October saying that: &quot;The Queen is content for Her Excellency Professor Marie Bashir AC, to remain in her current position until February 2008 as recommended.&quot;&lt;ref name=Parl1&gt;{{cite web | title=Governor of New South Wales Reappointment| work = Hansard | publisher = NSW Parliament| date=26 October 2004| url=http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/parlment/hansart.nsf/V3Key/LA20041026003| accessdate=22 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 31 March 2006, The Queen appointed her a [[Commander of the Royal Victorian Order]] (CVO).&lt;ref name=CVO&gt;[http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=1129467&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true Commander of the Royal Victorian Order], CVO, 31 March 2006, itsanhonour.gov.au&lt;br /&gt;'''Citation:''' ''Governor of New South Wales''.&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2007 Bashir was elected by the University Senate to take up a four-year appointment as Chancellor of the University of Sydney on 1 June 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.smh.com.au/news/National/Bashir-named-Uni-of-Sydney-chancellor/2007/04/30/1177788063827.html|title= Bashir named Uni of Sydney chancellor|date= 30 April 2007|accessdate= 9 August 2010|work= [[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |publisher=[[Fairfax Media]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was announced on 15 October 2007 that the Queen, on the recommendation of Premier [[Morris Iemma]], had extended Bashir's appointment as Governor for a further four years to February 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title = NSW Governor Bashir to stay on| work = [[ABC News (Australia)|ABC News]]| publisher = [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]| date = 15 October 2007| url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/10/15/2059508.htm?site=news| accessdate= 22 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 November 2009, she was invested as a Chevalier of the [[Légion d'Honneur|Ordre National de la Légion d'Honneur]] by His Excellency [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], President of the French Republic, and presented by His Excellency Mr Michel Filhol, Ambassador of France in Australia.&lt;ref name=LoH&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.ambafrance-au.org/france_australie/spip.php?article3650| title = Official inauguration of the new building of the Sydney Alliance Française| publisher = French Embassy, Australia| accessdate= 21 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the longest serving State Governor, Bashir holds a [[dormant commission]] to act as the [[Administrator (Australia)|Administrator of the Commonwealth]] when the [[Governor-General of Australia]] is absent from Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.ag.gov.au/portal/govgazonline.nsf/85B98B2949AD84ACCA256D580002A424/$file/S205.pdf| title = Royal sign manual - Commission| publisher = [[Commonwealth of Australia]]| work = Gazette S205| date = 17 June 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has held the position of Administrator many times: from 10 July to 17 July 2007, 30 September to 12 October 2007, 20 April to 4 May 2008 in the absence of [[Michael Jeffery]], and from 30 July to 6 August 2008, 5 November to 19 November 2008, 17 March to 2 April 2009, 7 June to 12 June 2010, in the absence of [[Quentin Bryce]]. 

In May–June 2010, the New South Wales Government experienced a series of resignations: [[Karyn Paluzzano]] over expenses abuse, [[David Campbell (Australian politician)|David Campbell]] over a personal scandal, [[Ian Macdonald (New South Wales politician)|Ian Macdonald]] over expenses abuse and [[Graham West]]'s retirement. These were widely seen as highlighting the NSW Government's inability to govern effectively and in response to this there were various calls for Bashir to take action as Governor and dismiss the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url = http://www.theage.com.au/national/nsw-ministers-quit-forcing-new-reshuffle-20100605-xl35.html| title = NSW ministers quit, forcing new reshuffle| date = 5 June 2010| accessdate= 22 August 2010| publisher = Fairfax Media| work = [[The Age]] | location = Melbourne| first = Adam| last = Bennett}}&lt;/ref&gt; She played down these calls in a radio interview on 10 June, saying that:
{{Bquote|&quot;The only way that they [the NSW Government] can disappear, so to speak, is if there's a vote of no confidence... Elections do come round from time to time so it's back in the hands of the people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title = Governor can't sack NSW Government| work = ABC News| publisher = Australian Broadcasting Corporation| date = 10 June 2010| url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2010/06/10/2923555.htm| accessdate= 22 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In late 2010, [[Mosman Municipal Council]] decided to name the new Sports centre in Rawson Park for Bashir in recognition of her service to both New South Wales and the Mosman community. She officially opened the &quot;Marie Bashir Mosman Sports Centre&quot; on 10 December 2010 with the Mayor, Cr. Anne Connon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Sports hub named after Marie Bashir |publisher=The Mosman Daily |date=30 October 2010 |url=http://mosman-daily.whereilive.com.au/news/story/sports-hub-named-after-bashir/ |accessdate=31 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Play begins at sports facility |publisher=The Mosman Daily |date=12 December 2010 |url=http://mosman-daily.whereilive.com.au/news/story/play-begins-at-sports-facility/ |accessdate=31 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 September 2011, Liberal Premier [[Barry O'Farrell]] announced that he had recommended to the Queen that Bashir's term be extended for another two years to 2014, which had been accepted: &quot;Over the past 10 years the Governor's caring nature, her genuine interest in local communities and her extraordinary work rate have endeared her to people everywhere...Because of her diverse background, career and interests, Professor Bashir has given a historic and important post a contemporary relevance and resonance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Governor of New South Wales| work = Hansard | publisher = NSW Parliament| date=14 September 2011| url=http://parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/PARLMENT/hansArt.nsf/V3Key/LA20110914010?open&amp;refNavID=HA8_1| accessdate=23 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Titles, styles and honours==
===Titles===
{{Infobox viceroy styles
| image = [[File:Crest of the Governor of New South Wales.svg|50px]] 
| name = Marie Bashir
| dipstyle = Her Excellency
| offstyle = Your Excellency
| altstyle = Ma'am
}}
* '''1930{{ndash}}1956''': ''Miss'' Marie Bashir
* '''1956{{ndash}}1971''': ''Doctor'' Marie Bashir
* '''1971{{ndash}}1973''': ''Doctor'' Marie Bashir, Lady Mayoress of Sydney
* '''1973{{ndash}}1976''': ''Doctor'' Marie Bashir
* '''1976{{ndash}}1988''': ''Doctor'' Marie Bashir, Lady Shehadie
* '''1988{{ndash}}1993''': ''Doctor'' Marie Bashir AO, Lady Shehadie
* '''1993{{ndash}}2001''': ''Professor'' Marie Bashir AO, Lady Shehadie
* '''2001{{ndash}}2006''': ''Her Excellency Professor'' Marie Bashir AC, Governor of New South Wales
* '''2006{{ndash}}present''': ''Her Excellency Professor'' Marie Bashir AC CVO, Governor of New South Wales
** As Administrator: ''Her Excellency Professor'' Marie Bashir AC CVO, Administrator of the Commonwealth of Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ag.gov.au/portal/govgazonline.nsf/17B9EA974CEC7F50CA25770700146CA0/$file/S%2055.pdf Commonwealth of Australia Gazette S55 dated 16 April 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;
** As Chancellor: ''Her Excellency Professor'' Marie Bashir AC CVO, Chancellor of the University of Sydney

The Governor's style and title in full is: ''Her Excellency Professor Marie Bashir, Companion of the Order of Australia, Commander of the Royal Victorian Order, Governor of the State of New South Wales in the Commonwealth of Australia.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nsw.gov.au/sites/default/files/Government_Gazette_1_April.pdf New South Wales Government Gazette dated 1 April 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Honours===
&lt;center&gt;

[[Image:OrderAustraliaRibbon.png|100x30px]]
[[Image:Royal Victorian Order UK ribbon.png|100x30px]]

[[Image:Order of St John (UK) ribbon.png|100x30px]]
[[Image:Centenary Medal (Australia) ribbon.png|100x30px]]
[[Image:Order of the Cedar - Commander (Lebanon) Ribbon.png|100x30px]]
[[Image:Legion Honneur Chevalier ribbon.svg|100x30px]]

&lt;/center&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|rowspan=2|[[File:OrderAustraliaRibbon.png|80px]] || Companion of the [[Order of Australia]] (AC) || 2001&lt;ref name=AC/&gt;
|-
|Officer of the [[Order of Australia]] (AO) || 1988&lt;ref name=AO/&gt;
|-
|[[Image:Royal Victorian Order UK ribbon.png|80px]] || Commander of the [[Royal Victorian Order]] (CVO) || 2006&lt;ref name=CVO/&gt;
|-
|[[Image:Order of St John (UK) ribbon.png|80px]] || Dame of Grace of the [[Venerable Order of St John|Venerable Order of St John of Jerusalem]] (DStJ) || 2001&lt;ref name=DStJ/&gt; 
|-
|[[Image:Centenary Medal (Australia) ribbon.png|80px]] || [[Centenary Medal]] || 2001&lt;ref name=CM/&gt;
|-
|[[Image:Order of the Cedar - Commander (Lebanon) Ribbon.png|80px]] || Commander of the [[National Order of the Cedar]] || 2004&lt;ref name=nrhc/&gt;
|-
|[[Image:Legion Honneur Chevalier ribbon.svg|80px]] || Chevalier of the [[Legion d'Honneur]] || 2009&lt;ref name=LoH/&gt;
|-
|}

====Appointments====
* {{flagicon|Australia}} In 1980 she was made a [[Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists|Fellow of the Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists]] (FRANZCP).

====Honorary degrees====
* {{flagicon|New South Wales}} On 11 October 2002, she was appointed a [[Doctor of Medicine]] (honoris causa) by the [[University of Sydney]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usyd.edu.au/senate/committees/advisoryBashir.shtml|title=Professor Marie Bashir AC|publisher=[[University of Sydney]]|accessdate=3 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Honorary military appointments====
* {{flagicon|Australia}} '''1 March 2001{{ndash}}''': Honorary and Regimental [[Colonel (United Kingdom)|Colonel]] in the [[Royal New South Wales Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vaseyhousing.com.au/PDFs/12th-Edition-March-2007.pdf|title=Royal New South Wales Regiment memorial|publisher=Vasey Housing Association|accessdate=3 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Image:Ensign of the Royal Australian Air Force.svg|22px]] '''1 March 2001{{ndash}}''': Honorary [[Air Commodore]] of [[No. 22 Squadron RAAF|No. 22 Squadron]] [[Royal Australian Air Force]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defence.gov.au/media/DepartmentalTpl.cfm?CurrentId=2419|title=No.22 (City of Sydney) Squadron, RAAF, Department of Defence|publisher=Australian Government|accessdate=3 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Image:Naval Ensign of Australia.svg|border|22px]] '''9 October 2008{{ndash}}''': Honorary [[Commodore (Royal Navy)|Commodore]], Navy Warfare Training, [[Royal Australian Navy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rfd.org.au/documents/Inv_Syd_09.pdf|title=Vice-Regal Review of the National Reserve Forces Day parade|publisher=Reserve Forces Day Council|accessdate=29 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/web/common.nsf/key/ResourcesSystemTheGovernorofNewSouthWales Parliament of NSW – Professor Marie Bashir]
* [http://www.usyd.edu.au/senate/Bashir.shtml University of Sydney – Chancellor Marie Bashir]
* [http://www.defence.gov.au/media/download/2009/mar/20090313/20090313ran8099747_159.jpg Photo: Bashir with RADM Nigel Coates, Commander Australian Fleet, at 2009 RAN Fleet Review.]
* [http://www.22squadronassociation.org.au/ADSUM%20page.htm Bashir in Mess Dress as Honorary Air Commodore]
* [http://www.defence.gov.au/news/armynews/editions/1162/images/15-unveil.jpg Photo: Bashir as Honorary Colonel]
* [http://www.defence.gov.au/anzacday2008/gallery/20080428c/20080425ran8098978_522_drn.jpg Photo: Bashir with ADCs at ANZAC Day 2008.]

{{s-start}}
{{s-gov}}
{{s-bef |before= [[Gordon Samuels]] }}
{{s-ttl |title= [[Governor of New South Wales]] |years= 2001{{ndash}}present }}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-aca}}
{{s-bef |before= [[Kim Santow]] }}
{{s-ttl |title= [[List of University of Sydney people#Administration|Chancellor of the University of Sydney]] |years= 2007{{ndash}}present }}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-end}}

{{Governors of New South Wales}}
{{Australian governors}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME =Bashir, Marie
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH = 1 December 1930
| PLACE OF BIRTH =[[Narrandera]], New South Wales, Australia
| DATE OF DEATH =
| PLACE OF DEATH =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Bashir, Marie}}
[[Category:1930 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Australian people of Lebanese descent]]
[[Category:University of Sydney alumni]]
[[Category:Australian medical doctors]]
[[Category:Australian academics]]
[[Category:University of Sydney faculty]]
[[Category:Australian psychiatrists]]
[[Category:Governors of New South Wales]]
[[Category:Companions of the Order of Australia]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Centenary Medal]]
[[Category:Dames of Grace of the Order of St John]]
[[Category:Commanders of the Royal Victorian Order]]
[[Category:Chevaliers of the Légion d'honneur]]

[[cs:Marie Bashirová]]
[[fr:Marie Bashir]]
[[pl:Marie Bashir]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
