<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="707151" ns="0" title="Wing Commander (film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Film
| name           = Wing Commander
| image          = Wing commander post.jpg
| caption        = Theatrical release poster
| writer         = [[Chris Roberts (film producer)|Chris Roberts]]&lt;br&gt;Kevin Droney
| starring       = [[Freddie Prinze, Jr.]]&lt;br&gt;[[Saffron Burrows]]&lt;br&gt;[[Matthew Lillard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tchéky Karyo]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jürgen Prochnow]]&lt;br&gt;[[David Warner (actor)|David Warner]]
| director       = Chris Roberts
| producer       = Donna Burkons&lt;br&gt;Joseph Newton Cohen&lt;br&gt;Jean-Martial Lefranc&lt;br&gt;Todd Moyer&lt;br&gt;Tom Reeve&lt;br&gt;Romain Schroeder&lt;br&gt;Neil Young
| distributor    = [[20th Century Fox]]
| cinematography = [[Thierry Arbogast]]
| music          = Kevin Kiner
| editing        = Peter Davies
| released       = '''United States'''&lt;br&gt;March 12, 1999&lt;br&gt;'''United Kingdom'''&lt;br&gt;June 25, 1999&lt;br&gt;'''Australia'''&lt;br&gt;September 16, 1999
| runtime        = 100 min.
| country        = {{USA}}&lt;br&gt;{{LUX}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $30,000,000
| gross          = $11,578,059
| music          = [[David Arnold]]&lt;br&gt;Kevin Kiner
| preceded_by    = 
| followed_by    = 
}}

'''''Wing Commander''''' is a [[science fiction film]] based on the [[Wing Commander (franchise)|same titled]] video game series, released in 1999. It was directed by [[Chris Roberts (film producer)|Chris Roberts]], the creator of the game series, and stars [[Freddie Prinze, Jr.]], [[Matthew Lillard]], [[Saffron Burrows]], [[Tchéky Karyo]], [[Jürgen Prochnow]], [[David Suchet]] and [[David Warner (actor)|David Warner]].  Principal photography occurred in [[Luxembourg]] and post-production was done in [[Austin, Texas]].

==Plot==
Based loosely on the plot of the [[Wing Commander (video game)|game]], the story unfolds in the middle of an interstellar war between the [[Terran Confederation]] and the cat-like alien [[Kilrathi]]. Set in 2654, the movie tells the story of [[Christopher Blair]] and [[Todd Marshall]], young pilots assigned to the carrier [[TCS Tiger's Claw|Tiger Claw]], as they fly their first combat missions. A massive Kilrathi armada is en-route for Earth and the Tiger Claw is assigned to fight a suicidal delaying action in order to allow the rest of the Terran fleet to reach Earth. Tensions exist between Blair and his fellow pilots because he is part &quot;Pilgrim&quot;. Pilgrims are a strain of humanity who have special abilities relating to interstellar navigation; they had previously fought a war against the Confederation.

==Cast==
*[[Freddie Prinze Jr.]] as First Lieutenant Christopher Blair
*[[Saffron Burrows]] as Lieutenant Commander Jeanette &quot;Angel&quot; Devereaux
*[[Matthew Lillard]] as First Lieutenant Todd &quot;Maniac&quot; Marshall
*[[Tchéky Karyo]] as Commodore James &quot;Paladin&quot; Taggart (as Tcheky Karyo)
*[[David Suchet]] as Captain Lawrence Sansky
*[[Jürgen Prochnow]] as Commander Paul Gerald
*[[David Warner (actor)|David Warner]] as  Admiral Geoffrey Tolwyn
*[[Ginny Holder]] as Lieutenant Rosie &quot;Sister Sassy&quot; Forbes
*[[Hugh Quarshie]] as Obutu
*[[Ken Bones]] as Admiral William &quot;Bill&quot; Wilson
*[[John McGlynn (actor)|John McGlynn]] as Commodore Richard Bellegarde
*[[Richard Dillane]] as Lieutenant Ian &quot;Hunter&quot; St. John
*[[Mark Powley]] as Lieutenant Adam &quot;Bishop&quot; Polanski
*[[David Fahm]] as Lieutenant Joseph &quot;Knight&quot; Khumalo
*[[Simon MacCorkindale]] as Flight Boss
*[[Fraser James]] as Helmsman

==Relations to other ''Wing Commander'' works==
The film has been criticized by some fans for altering the visual style of the most recent ''Wing Commander'' games. The most notable shift between the games and the movie is the appearance of the Kilrathi. Although the movie's Kilrathi retain feline facial characteristics, they lose their signature fur entirely. Roberts has since said that this change was a result of his ongoing unhappiness with the appearance of the 'live' Kilrathi, none of which lived up to his internal vision. He had previously re-imagined the Kilrathi between ''Wing Commander III'' and ''[[Wing Commander IV: The Price of Freedom|IV]]'', going so far as to completely redesign the Melek character between the two games.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://guide.solsector.net/images/Wc3melek.jpg Melek in Wing Commander III]'&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'[http://wcnews.com/newershots/full/animatronicmelek1.jpg Melek in ''Wing Commander IV]'&lt;/ref&gt; Roberts, even after production of the film, was left unsatisfied with the results of the film version of the Kilrathi;&lt;ref name=&quot;kilrathi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wcnews.com/news/update/2389|title=Blast From The Past | publisher=WCNews | work=WCNews | author=Christopher Reid | accessdate=2007-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; some interviews imply that the puppets were built before the sets were completed, and were too large to be filmed without hunching over unnaturally.

Several changes in character backgrounds and nationalities were also made, as well as plot and name changes. The 'pilgrim' story is new to the film, although there is some resemblance to the borderworlders of ''[[Wing Commander IV: The Price of Freedom|Wing Commander IV]]''. The carrier's name was changed to ''Tiger Claw'', rather than ''Tiger's Claw''. The visual appearance of the ships also changed radically; the Rapier fighters featured in the film were built from scrapped [[English Electric Lightning]] jet fighter fuselages.

Roberts cast actors that bore little physical resemblance to those who previously held the part. However, this was not the first time characters' appearances got an overhaul. Paladin, for example, has gone from being a thin fair-haired man in ''Wing Commander I'' &amp; ''II''&lt;ref&gt;[http://wcnews.com/newershots/headmuseum/wc1paladin.gif] Paladin in WC1/2&lt;/ref&gt; (voiced by Martin Davies) to being a large dark-haired [[Scotland|Scotsman]] in ''Wing Commander III'' and ''IV''&lt;ref&gt;[http://wcnews.com/newestshots/full/rotkparody2.jpg] Paladin in WC3/4&lt;/ref&gt; (played by [[John Rhys-Davies]]) to being a middle aged French accented Turk in the movie&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wcnews.com/shots/movie/full/stlg5.jpg] Paladin in the film&lt;/ref&gt; (played by Karyo).

''[[Wing Commander Arena]]'', the latest game in the series, makes reference to the movie, including references to the Pilgrim War,&lt;ref name=&quot;Arena1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wcnews.com/news/update/7698|title=But Is It Ours? | publisher=WCNews | work=WCNews | author=Ben Lesnick | accessdate=2007-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; while using ships and settings which first appeared in the main series of games.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arena2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wcnews.com/arena/ships.shtml|title=The Ships of Wing Commander Arena | publisher=WCNews | work=WCNews | author=Ben Lesnick | accessdate=2007-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
''Wing Commander'' was panned by critics. It received a rating of 11% on [[Rotten Tomatoes]] based on 46 reviews, and a 0% rating by the site's Top Critics.&lt;ref name=&quot;rottent&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/wing_commander/|title=Wing Commander (1999) on Rotten Tomatoes | accessdate=2008-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also considered a major box office flop: the total domestic gross of Wing Commander's theatrical run is estimated at $11,578,059, not nearly enough to recoup its $30 million budget.&lt;ref name=&quot;boxoff&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=wingcommander.htm |title=Wing Commander (1999) on Box Office Mojo | accessdate=2008-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chris Roberts never directed another motion picture. He did, however, serve as a producer on ''[[The Punisher (2004 film)|The Punisher]]'', ''[[The Jacket]]'' and ''[[Lord of War]]''.  

In 2009, ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' listed the film on their list of top ten worst video games movies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Top 10 Worst Video Game Movies | url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,1851626_1851846_1851706,00.html | work=[[Time Magazine]] | publisher= | date= 2008-10-20| accessdate=2009-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Novelization==
The novelization of the film by Peter Telep was fairly faithful to the film itself.  However, in the book the plot to discredit Blair is more far-reaching and includes [[David Suchet]]'s character, Captain Jason Sansky. There is also more general information about the Kilrathi and their first attack on a space station. The novel is based on the film's shooting script, which includes most of this information. Significant cuts removed the 'traitor' subplot from the finished film, since it heavily involved the unimpressive Kilrathi puppets. Admiral Bill Wilson was to be the traitor that compromised the Pegasus station (there were a number of scenes between Wilson and Bokoth, the commander of the Kilrathi battle group). In addition, Wilson provoked a knife fight on board the Kilrathi ConCom between Blair and Commander Gerald. Gerald wounded Blair, but everyone came to their senses and Blair used his Pilgrim Cross knife to kill Admiral Wilson (the only surviving element of this in the film is that Blair has a bandage on his hand during the scene where Paladin gave Blair his Pilgrim Cross). Also, Sansky was to commit suicide rather than be captured as a traitor; however, since all of his 'traitor' scenes were removed, the film now implies that Sansky died from head injuries he received during battle.

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{imdb title|id=0131646|title=Wing Commander}}
* {{Amg movie|176656|Wing Commander}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|id=wing_commander|title=Wing Commander}}

{{Wing Commander series}}

[[Category:1999 films]]
[[Category:1990s action films]]
[[Category:1990s science fiction films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American science fiction action films]]
[[Category:British science fiction films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films based on video games]]
[[Category:Films set in the 27th century]]
[[Category:Science fiction war films]]
[[Category:Space adventure films]]
[[Category:20th Century Fox films]]
[[Category:Wing Commander]]

[[de:Wing Commander (Film)]]
[[fr:Wing Commander (film, 1999)]]
[[it:Wing Commander - Attacco alla Terra]]
[[nl:Wing Commander (film)]]
[[ru:Командир эскадрильи (фильм)]]
[[uk:Командир ескадрильї]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
