<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="712915" ns="0" title="Drury, New Zealand"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">
{{Location map
 |New Zealand
 |label=Drury
 |lat_dir=S | lat_deg=37 | lat_min=06
 |lon_dir=E | lon_deg=174 | lon_min=57
 |position=left
 |width= 150
 |float=right
 |caption=
}}

{{Infobox New Zealand suburbs
| name           = Drury
| image          =  
| caption1       =  
| city1          = Auckland Council
| city2          = 
| ward           = Franklin
| established    = 
| area           =
| population     = 3, 582
| popdate        = 2006
| trainstations  =
| ferryterminals =
| airports       =
| hospitals      = 
| north          = [[Rosehill, New Zealand | Rosehill]]
| northeast      = [[Opaheke]]
| east           = Ponga
| southeast      = [[Ararimu]]
| south          = [[Ramarama]]
| southwest      = [[Ramarama]]
| west           = Runciman
| northwest      = [[Hingaia]]
| map            = 
| caption2       = 
}}

Drury is a rural town near [[Auckland]], in northern [[New Zealand]]. Located 36 kilometres to the south of [[Auckland CBD]], under authority of the [[Auckland Council]]. Drury lies at the southern border of the [[Auckland]] metropolitan area, 12 kilometres to the northeast of [[Pukekohe]], close to the Papakura Channel, an arm of the [[Manukau Harbour]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jasons.co.nz/drury|title=Drury Travel Guide |publisher=[[Jasons Travel Media]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==History==

Drury was formerly home to a military base. The population declined when this was closed. During the [[New Zealand land wars]], Drury was the last place on the Great South Road where protection from Maori was provided. Maori used the Drury Hills to watch the Great South Road, and plan attacks from them.{{cn|date=May 2011}}

During the major reformation of local government in 1989, Drury was included in the [[Auckland Region]] and made up the southern edge of the [[Papakura District]], along with a certain extent of the eastern surrounding rural areas, previously known as '''Franklin County'''. Drury was until recently a relatively small semi-rural area nestling at the foot of the low-lying [[Bombay Hills]]. Urban spread of the city has rendered it an extreme southern suburb, close to the junction between [[New Zealand State Highway network|State Highways 1 and 22]], both of which head south towards the [[Waikato]] region.

After a review of the [[Royal Commission on Auckland Governance]], the entire [[Auckland Region]] was amalgamated into a single city authority. As well as the former [[Papakura District]] and [[Franklin District]], all other territorial authorities were be abolished and the entire area was dissolved into a single [[Auckland Council|Auckland city council]]. The town of Drury was included in the ''Franklin'' ward, one of the thirteen administrative structures of the new Auckland city.

==People==

The Drury population is predominantly [[Europe]]an as at 2006, at 75.3 percent. Maori residents make up 11.9 percent of the suburb, and 7.0 percent being of Asian ethnicity. According to the 2006 New Zealand census, (for residents aged 15 years and older) the most common occupational group in Drury is ''Managers'', and the least common group is ''Machinery operators and drivers'', with an unemployment rate of 3.3 percent of the Drury population.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.papakura.govt.nz Papakura District Council]
*[http://www.auckland.govt.nz New Auckland Council]

{{Coord|37|06|S|174|57|E|region:NZ_type:city|display=title}}

[[Category:Populated places in New Zealand]]
[[Category:Suburbs of Auckland]]


{{Auckland-geo-stub}}

[[nl:Drury]]
[[nn:Drury på New Zealand]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
