<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7181074" ns="0" title="List of Ed, Edd n Eddy characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Unreferenced|date=August 2007}}
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that Plank, as well as any other one-shot appearance, does not constitute a character. The same thing applies to parents. If you add these here, they will be deleted. --&gt;
This is a description of the twelve recurring [[fictional character]]s from the [[Cartoon Network]] [[animated television series]] '''''[[Ed, Edd n Eddy]]'''''. The show revolves around three main characters (Ed, Edd, and Eddy), usually referred to as &quot;the Eds&quot;. There is a secondary group of characters (Kevin, Rolf, Nazz, Jimmy, Sarah and Jonny), three neighbor sisters known as &quot;the Kankers&quot;, and an absent character (Eddy's brother).

==The Eds==
=== Eddy===
:''Voiced by: [[Tony Sampson]]''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that middle names, last names, or ages are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Eddy''' is a greedy, ill-tempered con artist and loudmouth, the self-appointed leader of the Eds and one of the main [[protagonist]]s of the series. He goes to great lengths to scam the other kids out of their money, even at the expense of his friends' credibility. His efforts are all in the pursuit of jawbreakers, which he loves as much as he does money. He is very sensitive about his short stature, suggesting that he may have a [[Napoleon complex]]. Eddy detests school, and more than once has tried to escape. His report card labels him a [[megalomania]]c. Eddy loves his retro styled room, complete with a lava lamp, a large round king-sized bed, a disco ball, and a record player. Eddy is mostly seen commanding the two Eds into building the scams while he usually does non-physical work or simply sits around. It is shown that Eddy cannot learn from his mistakes; on several occasions, he taunts and insults Sarah to the point where she loses her temper and attacks him. He is incredibly selfish, caring for only the well-being of himself and acquiring jawbreakers, even choosing them over his friends. Despite his typically cruel treatment of them, it is shown on multiple occasions that he does indeed care about Ed and Edd and consider them his best friends. He is also a tragic character on the inside since his behavior came from the abuse that he endured from his older brother. He keeps his bad character until the end of the movie when he learns from his past and gives up his old ways for true friendship. 

Creator Danny Antonucci has said that all of the Ed's were based on different aspects of his own personality. Regarding Eddy he has said, &quot;There's my Eddy side, brash loudmouthed, constantly wanting attention. Much like the only child that I am. Eddy however is living under the shadow of an older brother so he's desperately trying to carve out his niche in life.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;animationbymistake&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://animationbymistake.fateback.com/abm/dannytalk.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080302131130/http://animationbymistake.fateback.com/abm/dannytalk.html|archivedate=March 2, 2008|title=Animation By Mistake: Chatting with Danny Antonucci|author=Topp, Kit R R|date=October 2002|accessdate=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Edd===
:''Voiced by: [[Samuel Vincent]]''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that guesses and original research about what's under Edd's hat, middle names, ages, and being friends with Kevin are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, please discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Edd''' (commonly referred to as Double D) is a young inventor, neat freak and one of the main [[protagonist]]s of the series. The most intelligent of the trio, he is never seen without his head covered in some manner, almost always by his trademark sock-like black ski hat, hiding a secret unknown to everyone besides Ed and Eddy, which they learned in the episode &quot;Stop Look Ed&quot;, when Eddy tied Edd's hat to a ceiling fan, and when he tried to get to Eddy it came off of him; he quickly covered himself back up, telling them never to tell anyone what they saw. While there have been vast fan-based speculations on what is under the hat, nothing has been officially revealed by the show's creators. He also has a significant [[Diastema (dentistry)|gap in his teeth]], which he sometimes gets things stuck in, to his embarrassment (see &quot;Key to My Ed&quot;). Because of his moral center and good heart, he is typically more socially accepted by the other inhabitants of the cul-de-sac than Ed and Eddy are. His parents put a heavy workload on him, communicating an excess of tasks solely through a multitude of sticky notes. Edd hates being treated terribly by everyone and is easily frustrated. Edd is normally a straight-A student in all of his classes and hates sports (apparently because of an odd, never-discussed &quot;dodgeball&quot; incident). Edd is highly intelligent, [[Ambidexterity|ambidextrous]] (evident in &quot;One+One=Ed&quot;), and able to construct complicated machines from cardboard, signs, and various kinds of junk the Eds come across. His knowledge proves to be useful in many ways, and sets him apart from the other children of the cul-de-sac. Edd is the only Ed not to have another family member appear in the series (Sarah is Ed's sister and Eddy's brother appears in the movie).

Like the other two Eds, Double D's personality was largely based upon show creator Danny Antonucci, who has said &quot;there's my Edd side, neurotic, analytical, must be organised. Also if Eddy &amp; Ed single D weren't around, Edd would be happy with his own company, something that works for me too.&quot; Antonucci has also explained that the habit of Edd's parents to communicate with him through sticky notes was based on a habit of his own parents.&lt;ref name=&quot;animationbymistake&quot;/&gt;

===Ed===
:''Voiced by: [[Matt Hill]]''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that last names, middle names, ages, references to intelligence or the lack of it, references to allergies (one episode rule), and superhuman strength (almost any of the characters can get it) are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, please discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Ed''' is the strong, dimwitted workhorse of the group and one of the main [[protagonist]]s of the series. His skin is yellow, unlike the other characters and he is known to laugh a lot and is happy most of the time. Ed has amazing physical strength which is humorously worked into many of the show's plots. His mind is a subculture grab bag full of comics and monster movies, which he often confuses with reality and also having the habit of shouting random remarks which have almost nothing to do with the current conversations. Ed (to the misfortune of many people) is utterly at the mercy of his tyrannical younger sister, Sarah, for whom he cares deeply, and is an easy target of her manipulations. Much to the dismay of [[mysophobic]] Edd, he has very poor personal hygiene, even to the point of being terrified of soap and liking the smell of sweaty boots. He loves buttered toast, gravy, comics, a cereal called &quot;Chunky Puffs&quot;, pudding skin, and animals, especially chickens.

Creator Danny Antonucci explained Ed's inspiration saying, &quot;Ed is...me, following his own path and slightly dysfunctional, a daydreamer who while people are doing one thing, will be busy thinking of another.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;animationbymistake&quot;/&gt;

==Other children in the Cul-de-Sac==
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that middle names, ages, or references to ethnic background are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;

===Jonny===
:''Voiced by: David Paul Grove''
'''Jonny ''' (referenced in the credits as &quot;Jonny 2x4&quot;) is a loner and considered by his peers to be a nuisance. Jonny is often made fun of for his big head and has a tendency to get his head caught in branches when climbing trees. He talks a lot, and frequently gets on the other kids' nerves. He is rarely seen without his imaginary friend, a 2x4 wooden board with drawn-on eyes and a mouth, aptly named '''Plank'''. Jonny seems innocent and gullible, and often forgives people no matter what they do. He does not seem to mind the antics of the Eds, and is often the most friendly out of all the cul-de-sac kids towards them. He is very protective of Plank, and will burst into acts of bravery or extreme aggression if Plank is stolen or harmed in some way. He does not seem to acknowledge that Plank is just an inanimate, silent, 2x4 piece of wood, and when asked for help with an imaginary friend, he claimed to have no clue what the Eds are talking about. He and Plank both have superhero alter egos (Captain Melonhead and Splinter the Wonderwood, respectively), which they assumed twice throughout the series; first in &quot;Robbin' Ed&quot; to thwart Eddy's &quot;Thingamajig&quot; scam and to fight Eddy's own one-time only alter ego, Professor Scam, and then in &quot;Ed, Edd n Eddy's Big Picture Show&quot; to hunt down and get revenge on the Eds. After &quot;Big Picture Show&quot;, he and Plank become The Gourd and Timber the Dark Shard in order to take revenge on the entire cul-de-sac. However, Plank tells Jonny that there isn't enough time left in the movie.

===Jimmy===
:''Voiced by: Keenan Christenson''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that references to last names, ages, fear of other characters, references to sexual orientation or romantic attachment to any other character are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Jimmy''' is an insecure child, with a propensity to cry. He is most often seen spending his time with Sarah. Jimmy is highly accident-prone, often seen sporting bandages, casts, and braces (particularly headgear), and is considered the weakest kid in the cul-de-sac. Though Jimmy has a cowardly, delicate, and [[effeminate]] personality, he truly wishes to be strong and muscular. He can be crafty when motivated, and had twice made scams that were very successful. Jimmy has shown how deeply attached he is to Sarah when someone tries to take her away from him. For most of the series he wore a retainer to correct his teeth, due to a bowling pin accident during one of Eddy's scams. In one episode, Eddy takes Jimmy under his wing as his protége. Sometimes the Eds are quick to ruin his dreams

===Sarah===
:''Voiced by: [[Janyse Jaud]]''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that references to superhuman strength, last names or ages are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Sarah''' is Ed's bossy, spoiled, fussy, short-tempered and self-absorbed little sister, who acts cute and charming only when it serves her. Sarah has Ed's unending loyalty and obedience, mostly from her threats of snitching on him. She has a short temper and is easily agitated by others, especially her brother and Eddy. She is almost always playing with Jimmy, and when she's not, rushes to his aid the moment Jimmy calls her. Sarah writes about her innermost feelings in her diary, and has a slight love for Edd (albeit usually not enough to spare him from her wrath).

===Kevin===
:''Voiced by: [[Kathleen Barr]]''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that references to superhuman strength, last names, ages, claims that Kevin likes the Eds, references to Kevin and Nazz as a couple, phobia of needles (one episode rule) are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Kevin''' is a stereotypical jock. He is cynical and can be cruel at times. Kevin has a garage full of jawbreakers, thanks to his father who works at a jawbreaker factory. He loves customizing his bike, skateboards, and snowboards. When not riding his trusty bike, he usually hangs out with Rolf and Nazz in the lane. He hates the Eds to the point of paranoia, but his animosity towards them is mostly geared towards Eddy; the two are mortal enemies and often go entirely out of their way to humiliate or physically harm each other at the first opportunity. He tends to call the Eds &quot;dorks&quot; and has a habit of coming up with words merged with &quot;dork&quot; to suit the situation.

===Rolf===
:''Voiced by: [[Peter Kelamis]]''
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that references to superhuman strength, last names, ages or references to Rolf's origins other than what is already said are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Rolf''' is an immigrant from a presumably [[Eastern Europe]]an culture with odd customs (which he displays frequently, and it often involves a wide variety of meat) and has a thick accent to match. He works his parents' small farm within the cul-de-sac, and leads a scouting group called the &quot;Urban Rangers&quot;, which includes Jimmy, Plank, and Jonny. Rolf usually [[Illeism|refers to himself in third person]], as well as being the son of a shepherd, in which he takes pride. His faithful farm animals are three pigs (one named Wilfred), a goat named Victor, at least six chickens (two named Bridget and Gertrude), a cow named Beatrice, and five sheep. He hardly minds the Eds (whom he calls the &quot;Ed boys&quot;) unless they make a fool out of him or offend him in some way, after which he is not afraid to use brute force. He seems to be very muscular, but this is usually only shown when he is angry. Rolf confuses the rest of the kids to no end with his unusual customs and food-making.

===Nazz===
:''Voiced by: [[Tabitha St. Germain]]'' (Season 1), ''[[Jenn Forgie]]'' (Season 3) and ''[[Erin Fitzgerald]]'' (Season 2 &amp; Season 4 - Season 6)
&lt;!-- Consensus has been reached that references to superhuman strength, last names, ages, references to Kevin and Nazz being a couple, a possible liking of Edd, or claiming that Nazz was once obese, are not suitable for this section. If you do want to add those, discuss it on the talk page before adding it here. --&gt;
'''Nazz''' is the stereotypical unattainable love interest. Nazz is usually seen with Kevin. All of the boys except Rolf and Jimmy are infatuated with her. Whenever she approaches, the Eds begin to sweat and lose the ability to speak coherently. She is the head cheerleader at Peach Creek Junior High. She generally does not mind the Eds unless they bother her. She is the only one besides the Kankers to have her last name undeniably revealed (Van Bartonschmeer), which occurred during the movie.

==Other characters==
===Kanker Sisters===
'''Lee''', '''Marie''', and '''May''' are three sisters who serve as the main [[antagonists]] towards the cul-de-sac and its inhabitants. Lee is the leader with curly red hair that covers her eyes, Marie has blue hair, and May is the buck-toothed blonde. They live in the nearby trailer park called Park 'n' Flush. If there is one thing that all of the kids in the cul-de-sac can agree on, it's that they all hate the Kanker Sisters. While all the Kankers like the Eds, it has been shown that May prefers Ed, Marie for Edd, and Lee for Eddy. May is voiced by Erin Fitzgerald (who also voices Nazz in seasons 2 and 4-6), except Season 3, when she was voiced by [[Jenn Forgie]] (who also voices Nazz in season 3), Marie is voiced by Kathleen Barr (who also voices Kevin), and Lee is voiced by Janyse Jaud (who also voices Sarah).

===Eddy's Brother===
[[File:Eddy's Brother.png|thumbnail|right|Eddy and his Brother.]]
:''Voiced by: [[Terry Klassen]]''
Eddy's brother is mentioned frequently throughout the series, mostly by Eddy. Eddy mentions how his brother taught him much about how to scam, and to be a con artist. He was previously an unseen character, but he finally makes an appearance in the movie. Eddy's brother at first seems out to be everything that the other kids imagined, but it turns out that all of the folklore surrounding him was made up by Eddy to impress the other kids, and he is really a bully who picks on Eddy mercilessly and refers to him as &quot;pipsqueek.&quot; He also works at the amusement park, &quot;Mondo a-Go Go&quot;, but his specific job is unknown.

===Wilfred===
Wilfred is a sloppy [[pig]] who belongs to Rolf. He is at times used for transportation or helping with chores. He has developed bad behavioral habits such as eating Rolf's garden hose, destroying vegetable crops from his garden, and running away at times. He once attended Peach Creek Jr. High in Rolf's place so Rolf wouldn't have to take a test. Wilfred also turned on Rolf in the movie after Rolf was abusing him and yelling at him.

===Victor===
Victor is a [[goat]] who is perhaps the most dangerous animal on the Rolf's farm. Like Wilfred, he loves Rolf's vegetables, but is [[omnivore|omnivorous]] as he will eat virtually anything (which is something very unnatural for a goat). Rolf has used Victor as a guard dog, getting him to attack the Eds when their plan to snap a photo of Rolf for a calendar went awry in the episode ''Quick Shot Ed''. It is known that Victor has an utter, as referenced in the episode ''Robbin Ed''.

==See also==
* [[List of Ed, Edd n Eddy episodes|List of ''Ed, Edd n Eddy'' episodes]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Ed, Edd n Eddy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Ed, Edd N Eddy Characters}}
[[Category:Lists of characters in American television animation|Ed, Edd n Eddy]]
[[Category:Lists of characters in Canadian television animation]]
[[Category:Ed, Edd n Eddy|Characters]]

[[it:Personaggi di Ed, Edd &amp; Eddy]]
[[pl:Lista bohaterów serialu animowanego Ed, Edd i Eddy]]
[[tr:Ed, Edd ve Eddy karakter listesi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
