<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="72544" ns="0" title="North Carolina State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{coord|35.785548|-78.67157|type:city_region:US|display=title}}
{{Infobox University
|name = North Carolina State University at Raleigh
|image_name = NC State Seal.svg
|image_size = 175px
|established = March 7, 1887
|type =  [[Land-grant university]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Sea-grant university]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Space-grant university]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Public university|Public]]
|endowment = $503 million&lt;ref&gt;As of July 1, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = NC State University Financial Report | work = 2010 NC State University | publisher = NC State University Controller's Office | url = http://www.fis.ncsu.edu/controller/financial_reports/2010_Financial_Report.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = July 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|chancellor = [[Randy Woodson|William Randolph &quot;Randy&quot; Woodson]]
|faculty = 2,073
|staff=5,341
|Total = 34,376
|undergrad = 23,636
|postgrad = 8,267
|city = [[Raleigh, North Carolina|Raleigh]]
|state = [[North Carolina]]
|country = United States 
|campus = [[Urban area|Urban]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|2110|acre|km2|1|abbr=on}}
|nickname = [[NC State Wolfpack|Wolfpack]]
|colors = Red and white&lt;br/&gt;{{color box|#CC0000}} {{color box|white}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncsu.edu/brand/web/web-guideline/ NCSU Brand – Web Standards]&lt;/ref&gt;
|athletics = [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] FBS&lt;br/&gt;24 varsity sports
|former_names = North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts and North Carolina State College
|website = [http://www.ncsu.edu/ www.ncsu.edu]
|logo = [[Image:NC State brick logo.svg|200px|center]]
|footnotes = &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = NC State University Financial Report | work = 2009 NC State University | publisher = NC State University Controller's Office | url = http://www.fis.ncsu.edu/controller/financial_reports/2009_Financial_Report.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = November 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''North Carolina State University at Raleigh'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The People's University at home and afar | url=http://www.ncsu.edu/about-nc-state/history/index.php | publisher=North Carolina State University | accessdate=September 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; ('''NCSU''') is a [[public university|public]], [[coeducation]]al, extensive [[research]] [[university]] located in [[Raleigh, North Carolina]], United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncga.state.nc.us/enactedlegislation/statutes/html/bysection/chapter_116/gs_116-4.html|title=GS 116-4|publisher=State of North Carolina |accessdate=2008-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commonly known as '''NC State''', the university is part of the [[University of North Carolina]] system and is a [[land-grant university|land]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/about-nc-state/university-administration/index.php|title=University Administration|publisher=NCSU|accessdate=2008-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[sea grant colleges|sea]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seagrant.noaa.gov/colleges/textlinks.html/index.php|title=Sea Grant College text list|publisher=NOAA|accessdate=2008-06-10}}{{dead link|date=December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[space grant colleges|space grant]] institution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/pdf/58251main_Space_Grants.pdf/index.php|title=National Directory of Space Grant Contacts|publisher=NASA|accessdate=2008-06-10}}{{dead link|date=December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university forms one of the corners of the [[Research Triangle]] in addition to [[Duke University]] in [[Durham]] and [[The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]].

The [[North Carolina General Assembly]] founded the North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts, now NC State, on March 7, 1887, as a [[land-grant university|land-grant college]]. Today, NC State has an enrollment of more than 33,000 students, making it the largest university in [[North Carolina]]. While NC State has historical strengths in [[agriculture]], [[life sciences]], [[design]], [[engineering]] and [[textiles]], it offers 115 [[bachelor's degree]]s.  The university is nationally acclaimed for its academic prestige and commitment to student development. The Center for Student Leadership, Ethics, &amp; Public Service is the university's premiere center dedicated to developing cultured students. The graduate school offers more than 100 areas of study leading to 169 [[master's degrees|master's]], 69 [[PhDs|doctoral]] degrees, and a Doctor of Veterinary Medicine.&lt;ref&gt;Data are for 2009. {{Cite web | title = NC State University Financial Report | work = 2009 NC State University | publisher = NC State University Controller's Office | url = http://www.fis.ncsu.edu/controller/financial_reports/2009_Financial_Report.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = November 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{main|History of North Carolina State University}}
The [[North Carolina General Assembly]] founded NC State on March 7, 1887 as a [[land-grant university|land-grant college]] under the name &quot;North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts.&quot; As a land-grant college, NC State would provide a liberal and practical education while focusing on military tactics, agriculture and the mechanical arts without excluding [[classical education movement|classical studies]]. Since its founding, the university has maintained these objectives while building on them.&lt;ref name = &quot;libraries&quot;/&gt; [[Image:NCSU-Freshmen 1889.JPG|thumb|right|First freshman class at North Carolina College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts in 1889.]] After opening in 1889, NC State saw its enrollment fluctuate and its mandate expand. During the [[Great Depression]], the North Carolina government headed by Governor Oliver Max Gardner, administratively combined the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], the [[University of North Carolina at Greensboro|Women's College at Greensboro]], and NC State. This conglomeration became the [[University of North Carolina]] in 1971. After [[World War II]], the university has constantly grown and changed.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}} In the summer of 1956, North Carolina State University enrolled its first African-American undergraduates, Edward Carson and Manuel Crockett.&lt;ref name = &quot;libraries&quot;/&gt; [[Image:Raleigh AM College 1909 View LOC.jpg|left|thumb||Panoramic photo of campus taken around 1909]]

In 1966, single year enrollment reached 10,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;libraries&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://historicalstate.lib.ncsu.edu/histories/historical-sketch-of-north-carolina-state-university|title=Historical Sketch of North Carolina State University|publisher=NC State Libraries|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1970s saw enrollment surpass 19,000 and the addition of the School of Humanities and Social Sciences. NC State celebrated its centennial in 1987 and reorganized its internal structure renaming all its schools to colleges (e.g. School of Engineering to the [[North Carolina State University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]]). Also in this year, it gained {{convert|700|acre|km2|1|abbr=on}} of land that would later become the Centennial Campus. During the next decade and a half and continuing today, NC State has focused on developing its new Centennial Campus. Over $620 million has been invested in facilities and infrastructure at the new campus with {{convert|62|acre|km2|1|abbr=on}} of space being constructed. There are also 61 private and government agency partners located on Centennial Campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://centennial.ncsu.edu/overview/quickFacts.html|title=Quick Facts|publisher=NC State Centennial Campus Partnership Office |accessdate=2008-05-25 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080415182331/http://centennial.ncsu.edu/overview/quickFacts.html |archivedate = April 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, NC State has almost 8,000 employees, over 31,000 students, a $1.01&amp;nbsp;billion annual budget, and a $535&amp;nbsp;million endowment. It is the largest university in the state and one of the anchors of North Carolina's [[Research Triangle]], together with [[Duke University]] and the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]].&lt;ref name=&quot;planninganalysis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/about-nc-state/quick-view/index.php|title=NC State University at a glance|publisher=NC State University Planning and Analysis|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nacubo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Images/All%20Institutions%20Listed%20by%20FY%202007%20Market%20Value%20of%20Endowment%20Assets_2007%20NES.pdf|title=2007 NACUBO Endowment Study|publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers|format=PDF|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campuses==
===Main Campus===
{{main|Main Campus of North Carolina State University}}
[[Image:HolladayHallNCSU.JPG|thumb|left|Holladay Hall, the first building built on NC State's campus in 1889, now houses the Chancellor's Office.]]
NC State's Main Campus has three sub-campuses: North Campus, Central Campus, and South Campus. North Campus is the oldest part of NC State and is home to most academic departments and a few residence halls. Central Campus is primarily composed of residence halls, cafeterias, gymnasiums and student support facilities. Finally, Greek Court, the McKimmon Conference and Training Center, and student park-and-ride areas are found on South Campus. North and Central Campus are separated by the [[North Carolina Railroad]]. Pedestrian [[tunnel]]s allow students to commute between campuses. Central and South Campuses are separated by Western Boulevard, a major downtown artery. University Housing divides Main Campus into West, Central, and East Campus for residence hall purposes. West and Central campuses are divided by Dan Allen Drive, while Central and East are divided by Morill Drive and [[Reynolds Coliseum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/facilities/campus_history/index.htm|title=Campus History|publisher=NC State Facilities Division|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Pulstar2.jpg|thumb|right|175px|NC State's [[Pulstar (nuclear reactor)|PULSTAR]] Reactor is a 1 MW pool-type [[nuclear reactor|nuclear]] [[research reactor]].]]Architecturally, Main Campus is known for its distinctive red [[brick]] buildings. Because of oversupply, odd brick statues dot the landscape, the [[The Brickyard (NC State)|University Plaza]], colloquially named &quot;The Brickyard&quot;, in Central Campus is nicknamed for its paving material, and most sidewalks are also made from brick. The Brickyard and sidewalks also sporadically contain white brick mosaics and other patterns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/nso/traditions/campus/brickyard/brickyard.htm|title=Traditions: Brickyard|publisher=NC State New Student Orientation|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[North Carolina State University Memorial Bell Tower|Memorial Bell Tower]], located in the Northeast corner of North Campus, serves as the signature of NC State and appears in the NC State Official Seal. It was constructed as a monument to alumni killed in [[World War I]]. The granite tower, completed in 1937, is 115&amp;nbsp;feet (35 m) tall. As a tradition, the Bell Tower is lit in red at night immediately following athletic victories and certain academic achievements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://chancellor.ncsu.edu/belltower.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060901090821/chancellor.ncsu.edu/belltower.html|title=Belltower Celebrations|publisher=NC State Office of the Chancellor|archivedate=2006-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Bell Tower, however, does not actually have a bell; The carillon system that can be heard ringing from the bell tower is actually housed in nearby Holladay Hall.

The [[Court of North Carolina]], just West of the Memorial Bell Tower, is surrounded by the 1911 Building; the College of Humanities and Social Sciences in Tompkins, Caldwell, Winston Halls and The College of Education in Poe Hall; Page Hall, home to College of Engineering offices; and Leazar Hall, former location of the Computer Science Teaching Labs. It was once home to 100 trees (one for every [[County (US)|county]] in [[North Carolina]]), but damage caused by [[Hurricane Fran]] in 1996 reduced the number significantly, including the destruction of a particularly old and large tree which was some {{convert|12|ft|m}} in diameter. Some replanting has occurred, but the Court's former appearance is far from being restored.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/facilities/buildings/tower.html|title=Memorial Bell Tower|publisher=NC State Facilities Division|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:NCSU Belltower.png|thumb|160px|left|Completed in 1937, the '''Memorial Bell Tower''' was built to honor thirty-three NC State alumni who died in World War I. It stands {{convert|115|ft|m|abbr=on}} tall.]]
Southwest of the Court of North Carolina is another landmark, the [[North Carolina State University Free Expression Tunnel|Free Expression Tunnel]]. The Tunnel functions as one of three pedestrian tunnels underneath the railroad tracks separating North Campus and Central Campus. This particular tunnel is the site of sanctioned [[graffiti]]; anyone may paint there, and it is often the place for political statements, personal messages, and art.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://media.www.technicianonline.com/media/storage/paper848/news/2006/05/25/News/Free-Expression.Tunnel.Open-2013899.shtml|title=Free Expression Tunnel open|last=Pittner|first=Danielle|date=2006-05-25|publisher=''Technician''|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thefire.org/index.php/article/9967.html|title=Free Expression Tunnel|last=Shibley|first=Robert|date=2008-11-24|publisher=''FIRE''|accessdate=2009-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Centennial===
{{main|Centennial Campus of North Carolina State University}}
NC State's main campus is augmented by the {{convert|1334|acre|km2|1|abbr=on|adj=on}} mixed-use Centennial Campus. Located {{convert|1|mi|km|1|abbr=on|adj=on}} south of the Memorial Bell Tower, this campus houses university, corporate, and government research, in addition to classrooms and non-student residences. The College of Textiles has been based on this campus since 1991.  Beginning in 2002, the College of Engineering began to relocate to Centennial Campus.  Currently, six of the nine College of Engineering departments are housed in three Engineering Buildings in an area known as the Engineering Oval.  The [[Golden LEAF Biomanufacturing Training and Education Center]] (BTEC), part of the College of Engineering, is located adjacent to the Engineering Oval.  The offices of [[Red Hat]], [[ABB Group|ABB]], and the [[National Weather Service]] are also on the Centennial Campus, as well as [[Centennial Campus Magnet Middle School (Raleigh, NC)|Centennial Campus Magnet Middle School]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://centennial.ncsu.edu/overview/ourPurpose.html|title=Centennial Campus Overview.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Centennial Biomedical Campus===
The [[North Carolina State University Centennial Biomedical Campus]] is located {{convert|2.5|mi|km|1|abbr=on}} west of the Memorial Bell Tower. The campus is anchored by [[North Carolina State University College of Veterinary Medicine]]--NC State's professional college and North Carolina's only [[veterinary medicine]] program. The {{convert|180|acre|km2|adj=on}} campus consists of 20 buildings including the {{convert|100000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} CVM Research Building where biomedical investigations in genomic sciences; vaccine development; cancer immuno-therapy; emerging and infectious zoonotic diseases; and diseases of the lung, respiratory track, skin, and digestive system are undertaken. The Center for Comparative Medicine and Translational Research, the Veterinary Teaching Hospital with its clinical research and clinical trials, and the Teaching Animal Unit (TAU), which is a working farm, are also campus elements. The Randall B. Terry, Jr. Companion Animal Veterinary Medical Center will more than double the size of the current hospital when completed in late 2010-early 2011.

[[J. C. Raulston Arboretum]] is an {{convert|8|acre|km2|2|abbr=on|adj=on}} [[arboretum]] and [[botanical garden]] operated by NC State, and located just south of West Campus. It is open daily without charge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/jcraulstonarboretum/|title=JC Raulston Arbortum self description.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sustainability===
In March 2008, NC State launched the University Sustainability Office to address environmental concerns on campus and includes a Director of Sustainability, a Sustainability Outreach Coordinator, a Sustainability Program Coordinator, and a Sustainability Student intern.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCSU Sustainability: History of Campus Sustainability&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = NCSU Sustainability: History of Campus Sustainability
  | publisher =NC State University
  | url =http://www.ncsu.edu/sustainability/history.php
  | accessdate = 2009-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
NC State has established a commitment to reduce its annual energy consumption per square foot by at least 4% over a 10 year period.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCSU Sustainability: Energy &amp; Climate&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = NCSU Sustainability: Energy &amp; Climate
  | publisher =NC State University
  | url =http://www.ncsu.edu/sustainability/energy_climate.php#
  | accessdate = 2009-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the university has surpassed the Executive Order 156 goal of diverting 40 percent of their solid waste stream from the landfill through a variety of campus reuse and recycling programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCSU Sustainability: Energy &amp; Climate&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = NCSU Sustainability: Waste Reduction &amp; Recycling
  | publisher =NC State University
  | url =http://www.ncsu.edu/sustainability/waste_reduction_recycling.php
  | accessdate = 2009-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; NC State incorporates locally grown, organic, and free range foods into dining service meals at several events such as Earth Week’s EarthFest and the annual All Carolinas Meal with foods local to the Carolinas.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCSU Sustainability: Dining&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = NCSU Sustainability: Dining
  | publisher =NC State University
  | url =http://www.ncsu.edu/sustainability/dining.php
  | accessdate = 2009-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Examinations of the campus’ sustainability practices by the Sustainable Endowments Institute resulted in a “C+” grade for NC State on the College Sustainability Report Card 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sustainable Endowments Institute Report Card&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title =College Sustainability Report Card 2009
  | publisher =Sustainable Endowments Institute
  | url =http://www.endowmentinstitute.org/
  | accessdate = 2009-06-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
===Structure===
{{see also|University of North Carolina}}
NC State is one of 16 campuses that constitute the [[University of North Carolina]] system. Each campus has a high degree of independence, but each submits to the policies of the UNC system Board of Governors. The 32 voting members of the Board of Governors are elected by the North Carolina General Assembly for four-year terms. President [[Thomas W. Ross]] heads the system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title = University of North Carolina Board of Governors
 | work =
 | publisher = University of North Carolina System
 | date = 2006-04-06
 | url =http://www.northcarolina.edu/content.php/bog/index.htm
 | doi =
 | accessdate =2007-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title = Erskine Bowles
 | work =
 | publisher = University of North Carolina
 | date =2007-04-01
 | url =http://intranet.northcarolina.edu/docs/pres/erskine/3.1.07_erskine_bowles_bio_narrative.pdf
 | format = PDF
 | doi =
 | accessdate =2007-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Board of Trustees of NC State has thirteen members and sets all policies for the University. The UNC system Board of Governors elects eight of the trustees and the Governor of North Carolina appoints four. The student body president serves on the Board of Trustees as a voting member. The UNC system also elects the Chancellor of NC State, currently Randy Woodson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title = NC State Board of Trustees
 | work =
 | publisher =North Carolina State University
 | date =
 | url =http://chancellor.ncsu.edu/trustees/
 | format =
 | doi =
 | accessdate =2007-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title = Dr. James L. Oblinger Biography
 | work =
 | publisher =North Carolina State University
 | date =2007-01-23
 | url =http://chancellor.ncsu.edu/biography.html
 | doi =
 | accessdate =2007-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Board of Trustees administers NC State's eleven academic [[colleges]]. Each college grants its own degrees with the exception of the First Year College which provides incoming freshmen the opportunity to experience several disciplines before selecting a major. The [[North Carolina State University College of Agriculture and Life Sciences|College of Agriculture and Life Sciences]] is the only college to offer [[associate's degrees]] and the [[North Carolina State University College of Veterinary Medicine|College of Veterinary Medicine]] does not grant undergraduate degrees. Each college is composed of numerous [[Academic department|departments]] that focus on a particular discipline or degree program, for example [[English studies|English]], [[Computer Science]], or [[Accounting]]. There are a total of 66 departments administered by all eleven NC State colleges.

In total, NC State offers nine [[associate's degree]]s in agriculture,&lt;ref name=&quot;ncsu1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://harvest.cals.ncsu.edu/aginstitute/index.cfm?pageID=1123|title=AGI Curriculum|publisher=NCSU|accessdate=January 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bachelor's degree]]s in 102 areas of study, [[master's degree]]s in 108 areas and [[doctorate degree]]s in 60 areas. NC State is known for its programs in [[agriculture]], [[engineering]], [[veterinary medicine]], and [[science]]. The [[textile]] and [[paper engineering]] programs are notable, given the uniqueness of the subject area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = North Carolina State University Institutional Profile
 | publisher= University of North Carolina
 | format = PDF
 | url = http://intranet.northcarolina.edu/docs/assessment/Profiles/2006-07/Inst.Prof._2006NCSU.pdf
 | accessdate = 2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title =NC State Co-Op Employer Information
 | url =http://www2.ncsu.edu/ncsu/co-op_ed/employ.html
 | accessdate =2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | title = GE Foundation Makes $500,000 Grant to North Carolina State University to Help Diverse Students Realize Math Potential.
 | publisher =U.S. Newswire
 | date  = 2004-01-04
 | url =http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-112100264.html
 | accessdate =2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Academic Divisions===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;font-size: smaller; margin-left: 1em;&quot;
|-
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | College
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Enrollment&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(Fall 2009)
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Degrees include&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
! Undergrad
! Graduate&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
| Agriculture and Life Sciences
| 4,908
| 908
|
*Biological Sciences
*Animal Science
*Biochemistry
*Genetics
|-
| Design
| 502
| 257
|
*Art and Design
*Graphic Design
*Architecture
*Landscape Architecture
*Industrial Design
*Design Studies
|-
| Education
| 852
| 1,110
|
*Technology, Engineering, and Design Education (TDE)
*Elementary Education
*Middle Grades Education (Math, Science, Language Arts, Social Studies)
*Business and Marketing Education
*Secondary Education (Math, Science, English, Social Studies)
*Higher Education Admin
*Mathematics Education
*School Admin
|-
| Engineering
| 6,046
| 2,322
|
*Aerospace Engineering
*Biological Engineering
*Biomedical Engineering
*Chemical Engineering
*Civil Engineering
*Computer Engineering
*Computer Science
*Electrical Engineering
*Environmental Engineering
*Industrial Engineering
*Mechanical Engineering
*Nuclear Engineering
*Paper Engineering
*Textile Engineering
|-
| Humanities and Social Sciences
| 4,062
| 886
|
*Criminology
*Sociology 
*Psychology
*Public Administration
*Communication
|-
| Management
| 2,584
| 612
|
*Accounting
*Business Administration
*Economics
|-
| Natural Resources
| 1,203
| 256
|
*Parks, Recreation and Tourism
*Forest Management
*Professional Golf Management
*Sport Management
|-
| Physical and Mathematical Sciences
| 849
| 690
|
*Mathematics
*Physics
*Chemistry
*Statistics
|-
| Textiles
| 938
| 157
|
*Textile and Apparel Management
*Textile Engineering
*Textile Technology
|-
| Veterinary Medicine
| 0
| 403
|
*Biomedical Sciences
*Veterinary Medicine
*Immunology
|-
| First Year College
| 1,417
| 0
| (Non-degree granting)
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; |
#As of Fall 2009; does not include non-degree students; full list available at [http://www2.acs.ncsu.edu/UPA/fastfacts/trendenr.htm].
#This list is not exclusive; full lists are available at [http://www.ncsu.edu/registrar/curricula/index.html].
#Graduate programs are run by the respective colleges, but all graduate degrees &lt;/br&gt;are awarded by the Graduate School.
|}

===Admission===
Considered a ''more selective'' university, NC State accepts more than half of those who apply for undergraduate admissions. For the class of 2012, 59% of about 18,000 applicants who applied for admission to N.C. State were accepted. For the Class of 2013, over 19,000 applications were received and only 55% were accepted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=NC State|publisher = [[CollegeBoard]] | url=http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=614&amp;profileId=1 | accessdate=June 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the largest application pool ever at N.C. State and the highest among the UNC system. This class includes about 160 valedictorians and salutatorians. About 48% were ranked in the top 10% of their class and 83% ranked in the top 20%. The mean GPA for freshman entering fall of 2010 is 4.23.

Transfer admission is also very competitive. According to college board, 3,868 students apply for one of the 1,389 places in the transfer class at NCSU. The mean transfer GPA was a 3.30 fall of 2008. For the fall of 2010 almost 3,900 students applied for about 1,100 spaces.&lt;ref name=&quot;common_data&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title =Colleges and Careers
 | work =
 | publisher =Princeton Review
 | year =2006
 | url =http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/admissions.asp?listing=1022851&amp;LTID=1&amp;intbucketid=
 | format =
 | doi =
 | accessdate =2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =
 | first =
 | authorlink =
 | coauthors =
 | title =Carnegie Classifications
 | work =
 | publisher = The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching
 | year =2002
 | url =http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=15570&amp;start=782
 | format =
 | doi =
 | accessdate =2007-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=North Carolina State University Profile|publisher= University of North Carolina System| url=http://www.northcarolina.edu/content.php/assessment/reports/profiles/current.htm | accessdate=2005-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=NC State Common Data Set|publisher = North Carolina State University | url=http://www2.acs.ncsu.edu/UPA/commondata/ | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

NC State requires undergraduate admission candidates to choose a preferred college of study. After determining that an applicant meets the overall university requirements, the individual college must also agree to accept the student. Because of this process, some colleges have significantly higher admission requirements than others. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = McNichol
 | first = Beth
 | title = The Right Stuff: Getting in at NC State
 | journal = NC State Magazine
 | volume = Summer 2005
 | url = http://www.alumni.ncsu.edu/media/magpdfs/summer05.pdf
 | accessdate =2006-07-20|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Graduate School reviews all [[postgraduate]] education applications. For fall 2005, 7,206 prospective students applied to the Graduate School; 2836 (39.4%) were admitted. Of these, 1,755 (61.9%) enrolled. Total fall 2005 graduate enrollment 6,128.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Annual Report for the Graduate School: 2005–06 | publisher=North Carolina State University|url=http://www.fis.ncsu.edu/grad_publicns/reports/anrp05-06.htm
 | accessdate=September 8, 2006 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Library===
The library system at NC State, ranked 27th out of 113 North American research libraries, includes 3.4 million volumes and 54 thousand journal subscriptions (as of 2005).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=About the Libraries: NCSU Libraries | url=http://www.lib.ncsu.edu/administration/aboutthelibraries.html | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Association of Research Libraries | url=http://www.arl.org/ | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The library system has an annual budget of over $20 million and consists of eight libraries. The largest library, [[D. H. Hill Library]], located on [[North Carolina State University Main Campus|Main Campus]] is over eleven stories tall and covers over 119 thousand square feet (11 thousand square meters).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=D.H. Hill Library | url=http://www.ncsu.edu/facilities/buildings/dhhill.html | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; NC State, as a member of the [[Triangle Research Libraries Network]] (TRLN), has interlibrary loan services with [[Duke University]], the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], and [[North Carolina Central University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=NCSU Libraries Fact Sheet: NCSU Libraries | url=http://www.lib.ncsu.edu/publications/factsheet/factsheet.html | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reputation and rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| GUR                  =
| ARWU_W               =
| ARWU_N               =
| ARWU_SCI             =
| ARWU_ENG             =
| ARWU_SOC             =
| USNWR_NU             = 111
| USNWR_Bus            =
| USNWR_Law            =
| USNWR_Medr           =
| USNWR_Eng            =
| USNWR_Ed             =
| THES_W               =
| Wamo_NU              =
| Forbes               =
}}

[[US News and World Report]] places NC State 111th out of 248 national universities in the US (52nd out of public colleges). The [[Shanghai Jiao Tong University]]'s [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] positions NC State 101st among 500 world universities in terms of scientific research leading towards a [[Nobel Prize]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=NC State Official Data Used in Rankings | url=http://www2.acs.ncsu.edu/UPA/commondata/ | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ed.sjtu.edu.cn/rank/2005/ARWU2005FullList.pdf ARWU2005PubData.xls]&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, it was ranked 96th worldwide in 2009 according to [[Global University Ranking]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globaluniversitiesranking.org/images/banners/top-100(eng).pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

NC State is rated twelfth among the nation's colleges and universities in terms of value, according to Kiplinger's Personal Finance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.kiplinger.com/tools/colleges/pubcollege.php?sortby=INRANK04&amp;orderby=flip&amp;states%5B%5D=ALL&amp;myschool%5B%5D=none&amp;outputby=table|title=Kiplinger's Personal Finance 100 Best Values in Public Colleges}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, NC State was ranked second by Princeton Review&lt;ref name=&quot;NCSURankingPR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/news/press_releases/06_03/056.htm|title=NC State Ranked Second in National 'Best Value' List| accessdate=April 2, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=College on The Princeton Review | url=http://www.princetonreview.com/college | accessdate=November 23, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and fifth by ''U.S. News &amp; World Report'' on their lists of best values among the nation's public colleges and universities. Recently, the university was ranked 6th in the country by The Princeton Review on the list of best value for 2010 at a public university.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/bvnatudoc_brief.php US News Best Value]&lt;/ref&gt; For 2010 the Wall Street Journal surveyed recruiters and ranked NC State number 19 among the top 25 recruiter picks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704554104575435563989873060.html | work=The Wall Street Journal | title=The Top 25 Recruiter Picks | date=2010-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scholarships===
There are several notable scholarships of North Carolina State University which include:
'''The Park Scholarship Program''' – Made possible by generous financial support from the [[Park Foundation]] of Ithaca, New York, The Park Scholarship Program was established in 1996. Among the most prestigious undergraduate merit scholarships, the Park program pays expenses for 4 years of study at NC State, a one time computer stipend, and costs associated with enrichment activities. There are approximately 35 in-state scholarships (valued at $80,000) and 15 out-of-state scholarships (valued at $130,000) awarded each year to incoming freshmen at North Carolina State University. Selection is based upon scholarship, service, leadership, and character.
'''The Centennial Scholarship''' – A scholarship to the College of Textiles. Introduced by the North Carolina Textile Foundation in 1999 as a part of the College of Textiles' Centennial Celebration, Centennial Scholarships carry the greatest value among all scholarships at the College of Textiles. Furthermore, the Centennial Scholarship is among the highest valued scholarships offered at North Carolina State University. This scholarship covers approximately 80 % of expenses to attend NC State, and on-campus housing (or a stipend for an equal amount) and a meal plan (or predetermined allowance), with any remaining funds to be used as a stipend for books and travel expenses (for up to eight semesters). In addition, each Centennial Scholar will have access to a $7,500 enrichment fund that will allow him/her to participate in a variety of leadership, language immersion and international studies programs, attend international textile shows and benefit from other approved textile enrichment opportunities. Selection is based upon demonstrated high academic achievement throughout high school with proven and potential leadership qualities, extracurricular activities and unique life experiences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tx.ncsu.edu/student_services/centennial_scholars.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
'''The Caldwell Fellows Program''' – Created by the NC State Alumni Association to honor the legacy of former Chancellor [[John T. Caldwell]], the Caldwell Fellows Program is a leadership development scholarship program with a strong focus on [[servant leadership]]. To be eligible, an applicant must be a full-time, first-year student at NC State University with a GPA of 3.25 or greater and meet the program's selection criteria. Caldwell Fellows are selected on the basis of strong academic performance, leadership potential, orientation toward community and service, commitment to personal growth and a demonstrated interest in and commitment to maximizing program opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncsu.edu/caldwell/apply/ Selection Criteria ]&lt;/ref&gt; Students that go through the program are challenged by Dr. Caldwell's charge to '''&quot;THINK BIG&quot;''' in all their pursuits.

==Athletics==
{{main|NC State Wolfpack}}
[[Image:Carter-Finley Stadium 1.jpg|200px|thumb|right|[[Carter-Finley Stadium]]]]
[[Image:RBC Center.jpg|200px|thumb|right|[[RBC Center]]]]

The athletic teams of NC State, known as the '''Wolfpack''', compete in 24 intercollegiate varsity sports. NC State is a founding member of the [[Atlantic Coast Conference]] and has won eight national championships: two NCAA championships, two [[AIAW]] championships, and four titles under other sanctioning bodies. Most NC State fans and athletes recognize the [[Carolina-NC State rivalry|rivalry with the North Carolina Tar Heels]] as their biggest, although most UNC fans are apathetic about it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Doyel
  | first = Gregg
  | coauthors =
  | title = A new perspective on Wolfpack-Heels rivalry.
  | work =
  | pages =
  | publisher = The Charlotte Observer
  | date = 25 September 2001
  | url = http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-7851811_ITM
  | accessdate = 2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  NC State was a founding member of the [[Southern Conference]] and is also one of the four teams on [[Tobacco Road]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Fellenzer
  | first = JEFF
  | coauthors =
  | title = TAKING A TRIP DOWN TOBACCO ROAD North Carolina Basketball Isn't a Game, It's a State of Mind.
  | work =
  | pages =
  | publisher = LA Times
  | date = March 21, 1989
  | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/66421603.html?dids=66421603:66421603&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Mar+21%2C+1989&amp;author=JEFF+FELLENZER&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=TAKING+A+TRIP+DOWN+TOBACCO+ROAD+North+Carolina+Basketball+Isn't+a+Game%2C+It's+a+State+of+Mind&amp;pqatl=google
  | accessdate = 2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The primary logo for NC State athletics is a red block 'S' with an inscribed 'N' and 'C'. The block S has been in use since 1890 but has seen many alterations through the years. It became the sole logo for all NC State athletic teams in 2000 and was modernized to its current design in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncsu2&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Timeline of Athletics at NCSU
  | work =
  | pages =
  | publisher =NC State University
  | date =
  | url = http://www.lib.ncsu.edu/universityarchives/historicalstate/athleticstimeline.html
| accessdate = 2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NC State athletic teams are nicknamed the 'Wolfpack' (most women's teams are also called the &quot;Wolfpack,&quot; except for the women's basketball team who go by the &quot;Wolfpack Women&quot;). The name was adopted in 1922 when a disgruntled fan described the behavior of the student body at athletic events as being &quot;like a wolf pack.&quot; Prior to the adoption of the current nickname, NC State athletic teams went by such names as the Aggies, the Techs, and the Red Terrors. Since the 1960s the Wolfpack has been represented at athletic events by its mascots, Mr. and Ms. Wuf. In print, the 'Strutting Wolf' is used and is known by the name 'Tuffy.'&lt;ref name=&quot;ncsu2&quot;/&gt;

===Athletic Facilities===
The stadium property is {{convert|3.4|mi|km|abbr=on}} northwest of the Memorial Bell Tower. Both [[Carter-Finley Stadium]] and the [[RBC Center]] are located there. Aside from the two stadiums, the property is mainly open space used for event parking. The property borders the [[North Carolina State Fair]] to the North and hosts [[Tailgate party|tailgating parties]] before NC State [[American Football|football]] games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rbccenter.com/CommentAndFAQ/faq.asp|title=RBC Center Description.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/facilities/buildings/carter-finley.html|title=Carter-Finley Stadium Description.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
[[Image:NCSU DH HILL Library.png|thumb|180px|left|D.H. Hill Library stands 11 stories tall and is named for NC State's first librarian.]]

Greek Life is a thriving part of NC State's campus life with over 52 social fraternities and sororities among an array of other professional organizations. Many [[residence halls]] host events, though alcohol policies are strictly enforced. One significant party is the &quot;College of Design Halloween Bash&quot; hosted by the College of Design every October. By far the largest party and social events are those associated with sporting events.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

The student center of the University includes an [[African American]] Cultural Center which has an art gallery and a library. There is also a multicultural student affairs office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/aacc/index.php|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070208102854/http://www.ncsu.edu/aacc/index.php|archivedate=2007-02-08|title=African American Cultural Center at NCSU}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Student life at North Carolina State University includes opportunities in a diverse range of activities and organizations. In addition to fraternities and sororities, there are multicultural groups, arts groups, political and social action groups, service and professional groups, religious groups, sports and recreation groups, academic and professional groups, and special interest groups such as the [[Clogging]] Team, THE QUIZ BOWL CLUB,the Film Society, the [[Judo]] Club, the [[equestrianism|Equestrian]] Club, and the Black Finesse Modeling Troupe.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

===Residence life===
Thirty-three percent of all students live on campus in one of twelve residence halls.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}} Most residence halls provide events that acclimate incoming students to the college experience. The residence hall or residence hall area has an elected council to provide for local event programming and an outlet for student concerns. Collectively, representatives from the from each hall make up the Inter-Residence Council which represents the on-campus residence-life community as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/irc |title=Inter-Residence Council.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

University housing facilities are divided into four areas: East Campus, Central Campus, West Campus, and University Apartments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/housing/halls/index.php |title=University Housing Residence Halls.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====East Campus====
East Campus consists of ten residence halls.  They are among the oldest residence halls at the university.  Clark Dining Hall serves most of East Campus.
*Watauga (1903)
*Syme (1916)
*Welch (1920)
*Gold (1920)
*Bagwell (1924)
*Berry (1939)
*Becton (1939)
*North (1974, purchased by the university in 1982)
*Wood (1983)
*Avent Ferry (1973, purchased by the university in 1994)

====Central Campus====
Central Campus consists of seven residence halls.
*Turlington (1940)
*Alexander (1940)
*Tucker (1949)
*Owen (1949)
*Bowen (1968)
*Metcalf (1968)
*Carroll (1968)

====West Campus====
West Campus consists of three residence halls.  They are the three largest halls on campus.  Fountain Dining Hall serves most of West Campus.
*Bragaw (1959)
*Lee (1964)
*Sullivan (1966)

====University apartments====
*E.S. King Village (1959)
*Western Manor (2007)
*Wolf Village (2004)

===Student Government===
Founded in 1921, NC State [[Student Government]] is a student-run organization that serves as the official voice of the student body and attempts to better the student experience at the University. Both a governing body and an advocacy group, Student Government is involved in policy-making, adjudication, programming, advocating, community service, and countless other activities. The organization is a clearinghouse for concerns from students and answers from administrators. The organization also is responsible for distributing a portion of the fees it receives to student organizations in a process known as appropriations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://students.ncsu.edu/home/overview.php |title=Description of the NC State Student Government.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Student Government at NC State is composed of three branches. The Student Senate is a 64-member body that legislative policy and Student Government budgets. The Student Body President heads the executive branch. The president executes policy passed by the senate and is a member of the NC State Board of Trustees. The Student Chief Justice heads the [[judicial branch]] and is the only student body elected member of the branch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://students.ncsu.edu/judicial/index.php |title=NC State's Judicial Branch.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student traditions===
====Service NC State====
Service NC State (SNCS) is sponsored by the Center for Student Leadership, Ethics &amp; Public Service as the definitive service event to welcome new students to NC State's campus, and as a way to impact the community. This event is open to all students, faculty, staff and the Raleigh community. The event role models the university's mission to impact and support its local and global community. 
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/csleps/service/servicenc.htm|title=Service NC State- Center for Student Leadership, Ethics, &amp; Public Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Homecoming Week====
Homecoming week, an event run by the AASAP (Alumni Association Student Ambassador Program), is one of the only homecoming weeks entirely run by students. Usually at the end of October, starts with a Kickoff event and ends with the Pack Howl pep rally and concert. Featured performers have included [[Lonestar]], [[Ludacris]], [[Chris Daughtry]], and most recently [[Cartel (band)|Cartel]], [[Guster]] and [[The Avett Brothers]].

During the week, events such as Wear Red-Get Fed, a parade down [[Hillsborough Street]], and a campus-wide Spirit Competition take place. The week also includes a Leader of the Pack competition honoring NC State's brightest and most passionate female and male student leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.technicianonline.com/media/storage/paper848/news/2007/10/26/News/Homecoming.Events.Finish.In.Full.Swing-3058972.shtml|title=Homecoming events finish in full swing}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Shack-A-Thon====
The Shack-A-Thon, an NCSU tradition since 1991, is NC State's Habitat for Humanity's annual fall fundraiser. Habitat for Humanity at NCSU Campus Chapter partners with many other student organizations to take over the Brickyard by building shacks that the students live, sleep, and study in for an entire week. Each group raises money by collecting from people walking through the brickyard. This money goes toward funding a house through Habitat for Humanity of Wake County.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/stud_orgs/habitat/doShack.php|title=Shack-A-Thon at NCSU}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Krispy Kreme Challenge====
A more recent tradition of NC State is the [[Krispy Kreme Challenge]]. In this race, students meet at the University's Memorial Bell Tower, then run to a [[Krispy Kreme]] shop {{convert|2|mi|km|1|abbr=on}} away. Each student must eat twelve glazed [[doughnuts]], then run back to the Bell Tower within one hour. The Challenge was listed as one of the &quot;102 Things You Gotta Do Before You Graduate&quot; by ''Sports Illustrated''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=2005-09-27|title=102 More Things You Gotta Do Before You Graduate (South)|journal=''SI On Campus''|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proceeds from the race go to the NC Children's Hospital, and the 2011 raised $100,000. &lt;ref&gt;[http://krispykremechallenge.com &quot;Krispy Kreme Challenge&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student media===
''[[Technician (newspaper)|Technician]]'' has been NC State's student-run newspaper since 1920. It employs students throughout the year and reports on campus news, sports, entertainment, and state and national news. ''Technician'' is published Monday through Friday when school is in session with a circulation of about 20,000. The paper is funded by advertisement and a student media fee; it is distributed for free at numerous locations on campus and at area merchants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.technicianonline.com/about/|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080201162826/http://www.technicianonline.com/about/|archivedate=2008-02-01|title=About Us|publisher=''Technician''|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NC State's oldest student publication, the ''Agromeck'' [[yearbook]], celebrated its 100th birthday with the 2002 edition. It acts as a compendium of student life on campus including sporting events, social activities, and day-to-day living. The yearbook serves as a historian of campus and is a reminder of the way things used to be. Each year, nearly 1,000 copies are printed and sold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncsu.edu/agromeck/history.htm|title=''Agromeck'' Yearbook History|publisher=NC State Student Media|accessdate=2008-05-25}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The University has its own student-run radio station, [[WKNC]]. The radio station broadcasts at 25,000 watts and reaches all corners of &quot;the Triangle&quot; (Raleigh, Durham and Chapel Hill). In 2010, WKNC was voted &quot;Best College Radio Station of the Triangle&quot; by readers of the [[Independent Weekly]]. The station hosts several formats run by student [[disc jockey]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wknc.org/about/history.php|title=The history of WKNC|last=Teel|first=Mark|publisher=WKNC 88.1: The Revolution|accessdate=2008-05-25 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080424053325/http://wknc.org/about/history.php |archivedate = April 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alumni==
{{main|List of North Carolina State University people}}
[[Image:Jim Goodnight.jpg|thumb|250px|left|Jim Goodnight, founder of SAS Institute.]]
[[Image:Henry Shelton official portrait.jpg|200px|thumb|right|Henry H. Shelton, Former chairman of the U.S. Armed Forces [[Joint Chiefs of Staff]]]]
[[Image:Philip Rivers 2008.JPG|left|thumb|Philip Rivers, [[Lists of NFL starting quarterbacks|NFL Quarterback]] and [[Pro Bowl|NFL Pro-Bowler]]]]

NC State has 156,297 living alumni with 61% of alumni living in North Carolina.&lt;ref name=&quot;planninganalysis&quot;/&gt;  There are 100 alumni clubs in North Carolina and another 42 states also have active clubs. In addition to alumni, the university employs 2,040 faculty and 5,843 staff. A number of NC State alumni and faculty have made significant contributions in the fields of government, military, science, academia, business, arts, and athletics, among others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = NC State Alumni
  | work =
  | publisher = NC State University
  | date =
  | url = http://www.ncsu.edu/alumni/index.php
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ncsu3&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = NC State Notable Alumni
  | work =
  | publisher = NC State University
  | date =
  | url = http://ncsu.edu/alumni/prominent-alumni/index.php
  | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071018130847/http://ncsu.edu/alumni/prominent-alumni/index.php
  | archivedate = 2007-10-18
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Rajendra Pachauri - WEF 2008 (cropped).jpg|200px|thumb|Rajendra Kumar Pachauri, Nobel Prize winner]]

[[John Edwards]], former U.S. Senator and two time presidential candidate, [[Jim Hunt|James B. Hunt Jr.]], 4-term [[Governor of North Carolina]] and [[Robert Gibbs]], Former [[White House Press Secretary]], are among the most notable alumni with involvement in politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = John Edwards Biography
  | work =
  | publisher = Biography.com
  | date =
  | url = http://www.biography.com/search/article.do?id=11158797
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = James B. Hunt
  | work =
  | publisher = US Department of Education
  | date =
  | url = http://www.ed.gov/about/bdscomm/list/hiedfuture/bios/hunt.pdf
  | format =PDF
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Combining science and politics, [[Rajendra K. Pachauri|Rajendra Kumar Pachauri]] is the elected chief of [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change]], an organization that shared the 2007 [[Nobel Peace Prize]] with [[Al Gore]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Alumnus Shares 2007 Nobel Peace Prize
  | work =
  | publisher = NC State University
  | date =
  | url = http://www.ncsu.edu/featured-stories/intl-connections/oct-2007/nobel-prize/index.php
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several alumni hold or have held top positions at large companies. These include: [[Caterpillar Inc.]] ([[James W. Owens]]), [[Thomasville Furniture Industries]] (Nancy Webster), [[DuPont]] (Ed Woolard), [[SAS Institute]] ([[James Goodnight]]), Citrix Systems (Mark Templeton) and [[MurFam Enterprises]] ([[Wendell Murphy]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;ncsu3&quot;/&gt;  [[Donald Bitzer]], the father of [[Plasma display|Plasma Television]] and [[Emmy Award]] winner currently sits on the faculty of NC State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = ECE Alumni Win Emmy
  | work =
  | publisher = University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
  | date =
  | url = http://www.engr.uiuc.edu/communications/outlook/Text%2042-1-2/dev.emmy.htm
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over 50 NC State alumni have achieved the rank of Brigadier General or higher in the [[Military of the United States|United States Military]].
The first four star officer at NCSU, General [[Maxwell R. Thurman]], a former [[Vice Chief of Staff of the U.S. Army]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Military Ties
  | work =
  | publisher = NC State Alumni Association
  | date =
  | url = http://www.alumni.ncsu.edu/military/officers.php
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hugh Shelton]], now retired, was a former [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] and a four star [[general]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = General Hugh Shelton Elected to Red Hat Board of Directors
  | work =
  | publisher = Red Hat, Inc.
  | date = April 30, 2003
  | url = http://www.redhat.com/about/presscenter/2003/press_shelton.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  General [[Dan McNeill]] currently commands the International Security Assistance Force in [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = General Dan K McNeill
  | work =
  | publisher = North Atlantic Treat Organization
  | date = 27 August 2007
  | url = http://www.nato.int/isaf/structure/bio/comisaf/mcneill.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; General [[William C. Lee]] is often referred to as the &quot;Father of the U.S. [[airborne forces|Airborne]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Aviation: From Sand Dunes to Sonic Booms
  | work =
  | publisher = National Park Service
  | date =
  | url = http://www.nps.gov/history/nr/travel/aviation/lee.htm
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some alumni have become national academic leaders.  [[Albert Carnesale]] was the chancellor of [[UCLA]] from 1997 to 2006 after a 23 year tenure at [[Harvard University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Albert Carnesale
  | work =
  | publisher = UCLA
  | date =
  | url = http://www.pastleaders.ucla.edu/carnesale.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[William C. Friday|Bill Friday]] served as president of the [[University of North Carolina system]] for 30 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =William Friday
  | work =
  | publisher = UNC-TV
  | date =
  | url = http://www.unctv.org/biocon/wfriday/
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[William Brantley Aycock]] served as chancellor of the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]] from 1957 until 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = William Aycock
  | work =
  | publisher = UNC Library
  | date =
  | url = http://www.lib.unc.edu/mss/inv/a/Aycock,William_B.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several NC State students later became professional athletes. [[Bill Cowher]] coached 15 seasons with the [[Pittsburgh Steelers|Steelers]] including the [[Super Bowl XL]] championship team and he currently is a studio analyst for ''[[The NFL Today]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Bill Cowher Profile
  | work =
  | publisher = Scout.com
  | date =
  | url = http://pit.scout.com/a.z?s=68&amp;p=8&amp;c=1&amp;nid=1151563
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Over 130 NC State alumni play or have played in the [[National Football League|NFL]]. Notable former players include [[Torry Holt]], [[Roman Gabriel]], [[Ted Brown]], [[Dick Christy]], [[Haywood Jeffires]], Dr. [[Jerry Punch]], [[Jim Ritcher]], [[Koren Robinson]] and [[Dewayne Washington]].  Notable current players include [[Adrian Wilson (American football)|Adrian Wilson]] of the [[Arizona Cardinals]], [[Jerricho Cotchery]] of the [[New York Jets]], #1 pick [[Mario Williams]] and [[Anthony Hill (American football)|Anthony Hill]] who play for the [[Houston Texans]], [[Tank Tyler]] of the [[Carolina Panthers]], [[Stephen Tulloch]] of the [[Detroit Lions]] and [[Philip Rivers]] who plays for the [[San Diego Chargers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = NFL Players who attended North Carolina State University
  | work =
  | publisher = Database Football
  | date =
  | url = http://www.databasefootball.com/players/bycollege.htm?sch=North+Carolina+State+University
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another 41 alumni have played for the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] including hall of famer [[David Thompson (basketball)|David Thompson]] and players [[Tom Gugliotta]], [[Kenny Carr]], [[Spud Webb]], [[Cedric Simmons]], [[Julius Hodge]], [[J.J. Hickson]], [[Josh Powell]], and [[Thurl Bailey]]. Former players [[Nate McMillan]] and [[Vinny Del Negro]] are current NBA head coaches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = NBA/ABA Players who attended North Carolina State University
  | work =
  | publisher = Basketball Reference
  | date =
  | url = http://www.basketballreference.com/players/bycollege.htm?sch=North+Carolina+State+University
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2008-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Actor and Comedian [[Zach Galifianakis]] also attended NC State University.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zach_Galifanakis&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[University Statisticians of the Southern Experiment Stations]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commons}}
* [http://www.ncsu.edu/ North Carolina State University] (official website)
* [http://www.gopack.com/ GoPack.com] (official athletics website)
* [http://historicalstate.lib.ncsu.edu/ Historical State] (historical timeline, photos, and other resources)
* [http://centennial.ncsu.edu/ Centennial Campus]
* [http://www.btec.ncsu.edu/ Golden LEAF Biomanufacturing Training and Education Center (BTEC)]

{{North Carolina State University}}
{{University of North Carolina}}
{{Atlantic Coast Conference}}

[[Category:North Carolina State University]]
[[Category:Land-grant universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1887]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in the Research Triangle, North Carolina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in North Carolina]]
[[Category:University of North Carolina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Raleigh, North Carolina]]

[[da:North Carolina State University]]
[[de:North Carolina State University]]
[[es:Universidad Estatal de Carolina del Norte]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی کارولینای شمالی]]
[[fr:Université d'État de Caroline du Nord]]
[[nl:North Carolina State University]]
[[ja:ノースカロライナ州立大学]]
[[no:North Carolina State University]]
[[pnb:نارتھ کیرولائنا سٹیٹ یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:North Carolina State University]]
[[pt:Universidade Estadual da Carolina do Norte]]
[[simple:North Carolina State University]]
[[fi:Pohjois-Carolinan osavaltionyliopisto]]
[[zh:北卡罗来纳州立大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
