<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="725686" ns="0" title="Screeching Weasel"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name                = Screeching Weasel
| image               =
| caption             =
| background          = group_or_band
| origin              = [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], United States
| genre               = [[Punk rock]], [[pop punk]], [[hardcore punk]] (early)
| years_active        = 1986–1989&lt;br/&gt;1991–1994&lt;br/&gt;1996–2001&lt;br/&gt;2004&lt;br/&gt;2009–present
| label               = Underdog, Roadkill, [[Lookout! Records|Lookout!]], [[Selfless Records|Selfless]], [[Fat Wreck Chords]], [[Panic Button Records|Panic Button]], [[Asian Man Records|Asian Man]]
| associated_acts     = [[Riverdales]], [[The Queers]], [[Squirtgun]], [[Common Rider]], [[Sludgeworth]], [[The Vindictives]], [[Crimpshrine]], [[Green Day]]
| website             = [http://www.screechingweasel.com/ ScreechingWeasel.com]
| current_members     = [[Ben Weasel]]&lt;br /&gt;Zac Damon&lt;br /&gt;Mike Hunchback&lt;br /&gt;Dave Klein&lt;br /&gt;Pierre Marche
| past_members        = [[Dan Vapid]]&lt;br/&gt;Drew Fredrichsen&lt;br/&gt;Justin Perkins&lt;br/&gt;Adam Cargin&lt;br/&gt;[[John Pierson (musician)|John Jughead]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Vince Vogel|Vinnie Bovine]]&lt;br/&gt;Steve Cheese&lt;br/&gt;Warren Fish&lt;br/&gt;[[Aaron Cometbus]]&lt;br/&gt;Brian Vermin&lt;br/&gt;Douglas Ward&lt;br/&gt;Dave Naked&lt;br/&gt;Scott &quot;Gub&quot; Conway&lt;br/&gt;[[Dan Panic]]&lt;br/&gt;Johhny Personality&lt;br/&gt;[[Mike Dirnt]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mass Giorgini]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Dan Lumley]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Phillip Hill]]&lt;br/&gt;Simon Lamb
}}
'''Screeching Weasel''' is an American [[punk rock]] band originally from [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]]. The band was formed in 1986 by [[Ben Weasel]] and [[John Pierson (musician)|John Jughead]].
Since their formation, Screeching Weasel have broken up and reformed numerous times with numerous line-up changes. Ben Weasel has been the only constant member, though Jughead was present in every incarnation of the band until 2009. Other prominent members include guitarist/bassist [[Dan Vapid]] and drummer [[Dan Panic]], who have each appeared on six of the band's studio albums, and [[Green Day]] bassist [[Mike Dirnt]] who was briefly a member of the band.&lt;ref&gt;{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r252460|label=How To Make Enemies And Irritate People}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Screeching Weasel recorded 12 studio albums, splitting time between a number of famous [[independent record labels]] such as [[Lookout! Records]] and [[Fat Wreck Chords]]. Despite never achieving mainstream success, a number of largely popular acts cite them as influential.

==History==
===Early years (1986-1989)===
In 1986, Ben Foster and John Pierson were inspired to start a band after attending a [[Ramones]] concert.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Huey |first=Steve |url=http://music.yahoo.com/ar-263692-bio--Screeching-Weasel |title=Screeching Weasel Biography on Yahoo! Music |publisher=Music.yahoo.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Foster (who played bass and sang) rechristened himself &quot;Ben Weasel&quot;, while Pierson, a guitarist, dubbed himself &quot;John Jughead&quot;. The duo recruited Steve Dubick as drummer who went by the alias of Steve Cheese to complete the band.

The band originally called themselves All Night Garage Sale but changed their name to Screeching Weasel, a variation of a name a friend had suggested, Screaming Otter, which was a reference to a t-shirt that read, &quot;I'VE GOT A SCREAMING OTTER IN MY PANTS!&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;DeRogatis&quot; /&gt; Shortly after their formation, Weasel decided that it was too difficult to play bass and sing at the same time, so [[Vince Vogel]], whom took the stage name &quot;Vinnie Bovine&quot; joined as the band's bassist. The band recorded their debut album, ''[[Screeching Weasel (album)|Screeching Weasel]]'', in one night for $200 and released it on Chicago label Underdog Records in 1987.

In 1988, Bovine was fired from the band and was replaced with Warren Fischer, better known as Fish, and former member of the band Ozzfish. The band recorded their second studio album, ''[[Boogadaboogadaboogada!]]'', which featured Weasel playing second guitar (he would later state that he only played on about a quarter of the songs) and made a name for themselves by opening a show for [[Operation Ivy (band)|Operation Ivy]] at [[924 Gilman Street]]. Steve Cheese was fired from the band shortly after the recording due to his unwillingness to tour outside of Chicago. He was replaced by [[Aaron Cometbus]] for two shows&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.myspace.com/officialscreechingweasel |title=Screeching Weasel |publisher=Myspace.com |date=2008-09-21 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; whom then was replaced by Brian Vermin. ''Boogadaboogadaboogada!'' was released in late 1988 on Roadkill Records, a label formed by investor David Best and managed by Ben Weasel following an introduction of the two by producer [[Mass Giorgini]].

After what Weasel described as a &quot;disastrous&quot; tour,&lt;ref&gt;[http://weasels.littletype.com/docs.ktm-liner-notes.php Kill The Musicians - Orig. Liner Notes-ScreechingWeasel.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Fish left the group and was replaced by [[Dan Vapid|Dan Schafer]], originally nick-named &quot;Sewercap&quot; and later renamed Danny Vapid. The new band members recorded an extended play entitled ''[[Punkhouse]]'' for Limited Potential Records soon after that. The band ended up recording four more songs in 1989 that were featured on compilations, featuring a second guitarist Doug Ward, whom also joined the band for several live performances. Screeching Weasel disbanded when Vermin and Vapid stated that they wanted to leave the band to concentrate on their side project, [[Sludgeworth]].

===First reformation (1991-1994)===
After the break-up, Weasel and Jughead formed a new band called The Gore Gore Girls, and Ben briefly performed in the original incarnation of [[The Vindictives]]. In 1991, the members of Screeching Weasel reunited for what was intended as a one-off gig to pay off debts the band incurred from the recording of ''[[Boogadaboogadaboogada!]]''. The line-up consisted of Ben, Jughead, Vapid, Vermin, and Ward. After the show, Vapid discussed the idea of reforming Screeching Weasel with Jughead. All of the band's members agreed to reform, with the exceptions of Brian Vermin and Douglas Ward. To replace Vermin, drummer [[Dan Panic]] (Dan Sullivan) was brought in. Before recording their third studio album, ''[[My Brain Hurts]]'' (1991)for [[Lookout! Records]], Weasel decided that he wanted to focus on singing and would no longer be playing guitar in the band. Vapid switched instruments from bass to guitar, and former Gore Gore Girls bassist Dave Naked joined the band. The recording sessions for the album also produced the extended play ''[[Pervo Devo]]''.

After recording ''My Brain Hurts'', Dave Naked was fired from the band and Scott &quot;Gub&quot; Conway, Panic's former bandmate, was brought in as the band's bassist to tour. After the tour, Johnny Personality of The Vindictives became the band's bassist, as Gub was committed to another band. By late 1992, the band had recorded the follow-up to ''My Brain Hurts'', ''[[Wiggle (album)|Wiggle]]'', which also marked their first collaboration with producer [[Mass Giorgini]], whom went on to produce the vast majority of the Screeching Weasel catalog, and also became the bassist of the band from 1998 to 2004. Personality then left the band to focus on The Vindictives. Instead of adding a new member, Weasel moved back to guitar, and Vapid moved back to bass.

The band was then asked to record a cover of an entire Ramones album, ''[[Ramones (Screeching Weasel album)|Ramones]]'' (1992), followed later that year by ''[[Anthem for a New Tomorrow]]''. Shortly after the record's release, Weasel decided that he no longer wanted to perform live, and Vapid left after falling out with the rest of the band. Screeching Weasel enlisted the help of Green Day bassist [[Mike Dirnt]] to record what they intended to be their final studio album. After the release of ''[[How to Make Enemies and Irritate People]]'' (1994), the band broke up for the second time.

===Second reformation (1996-2001)===
Following the second breakup, Weasel, Vapid, and Panic formed the band the [[Riverdales]] and experienced some notoriety touring with Green Day.&lt;ref&gt;Cowie, Douglas. [http://www.sobriquetmagazine.com/encyclopedia/Screeching_Weasel Screeching Weasel.] ''Sobriquet Magazine.''&lt;/ref&gt; By 1996, they rejoined with Jughead and recorded a new Screeching Weasel album ''[[Bark Like a Dog]]'' for [[Fat Mike]]'s [[Fat Wreck Chords]] label. The album peaked at number 34 on the [[Top Heatseekers|''Billboard'' Heatseekers]] chart, making it their highest-charting album.&lt;ref&gt;{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p14192|label=Screeching Weasel &gt; Charts &amp; Awards &gt; Billboard Albums}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, both Vapid and Panic left by mutual decision after the recording, and Weasel and Jughead decided to go on without them, adding bassist Mass Giorgini (whom had served as the band's producer in the past) and drummer [[Dan Lumley]]. Weasel also decided for the second time that he no longer wanted to play guitar, so guitarist Zac Damon was added.

In 1998, the group's new line-up recorded the ''[[Major Label Debut]]'' EP; the first release on [[Panic Button Records]], a label Ben and John had formed that year and quickly followed it with ''[[Television City Dream]]''. Their next release, 1999's ''[[Emo (album)|Emo]]'', featured the same line-up minus Zac Damon, who was unable to record due to school commitments at the time. In 2000 the band brought in [[Phillip Hill]] as a second guitarist and recorded what would be their final album, ''[[Teen Punks in Heat]]''. After the album, Screeching Weasel made their first live appearances since 1993, playing 30 minute matinees at Chicago's [[House of Blues]]. The band broke up for the third—and allegedly final—time on July 6, 2001, due to Jughead's frustration of a lack of touring.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jimdero.com/News2003/May16Blackouts.htm |title=Punk goes acoustic |publisher=Jimdero.com |date=2003-05-16 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hiatus and brief third reformation===
After the third breakup, Jughead started a new band called [[Even in Blackouts]], while Weasel released a solo album titled ''[[Fidatevi]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r592818|label=Fidatevi}}&lt;/ref&gt; and new Riverdales album, ''[[Phase Three]]''.

Both Weasel and Jughead authored books seemingly related to Screeching Weasel. In 2001, [[Ben Weasel]] published ''Like Hell'', the account of a fictional punk band called Pagan Icons and the life of their frontman, Joe Pagan. Jughead released ''Weasels in a Box'', his admittedly fictionalized account of Screeching Weasel's history. Both books were published by Hope And Nonthings, a [[publishing house]] run by Jughead.  Jughead also continued his membership with the [[Neo-Futurists]], a theater group he has written and performed with since 1997, appearing in a show called [[Too Much Light Makes the Baby Go Blind]].

In 2004, Ben reclaimed all of the Screeching Weasel masters from [[Lookout! Records]] in the wake of long-running financial and personal conflicts. The masters were subsequently licensed to and reissued by [[Asian Man Records]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/10547 |title=Asian Man Records to re-release Screeching Weasel catalogue |publisher=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; That same year a line-up consisting of Ben Weasel, Jughead, and multi-year Screeching Weasel veterans Dan Vapid, Mass Giorgini, and Dan Lumley came together to play surprise sets at the Chicago club [[The Fireside Bowl]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.punknews.org/article/8411 Punknews.org | Screeching Weasel Reunion&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Ben Weasel, there was an intention to tour that year, but &quot;the offers just weren't there&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;avclub1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Ryan |first=Kyle |url=http://www.avclub.com/chicago/articles/ben-weasel-why-am-i-not-doing-my-own-band-after-al,33494/ |title=Ben Weasel: &quot;Why am I not doing my own band after all?&quot; &amp;#124; Music &amp;#124; The A.V. Club Chicago |publisher=Avclub.com |date=2009-10-09 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ben released a second solo album, ''[[These Ones Are Bitter]]'', in 2007, and gave his first solo live performance at that years [[Insubordination Fest]] in [[Baltimore]]. During his set, backed up by [[The Guts]], he was joined on stage by Dan Vapid for several Screeching Weasel and Riverdales songs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Beat |first=Jersey |url=http://jerseybeat.blogspot.com/2007/07/insubordination-fest-2007-day-three.html |title=Jersey Beat |publisher=Jerseybeat.blogspot.com |date=2007-07-11 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ben Weasel and Dan Vapid also played two shows in August 2008 at Reggie's Rock Club in Chicago, playing the entirety of [[My Brain Hurts]] as well as other songs by Screeching Weasel, The Riverdales, and from Ben Weasel's solo albums.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/29350 |title=Ben Weasel and Dan Vapid to play &quot;My Brain Hurts&quot; live |publisher=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fourth reformation (2009-present)===
In March 2009, Ben Weasel announced on his blog that he had reformed Screeching Weasel. For the first time, the band featured a lineup without John Jughead, although longtime member Dan Vapid had rejoined. Ben wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;I really want to give you the lowdown on the SW re-formation but there's honestly not a lot to say. Legal issues prevented me from doing my own band on my own terms over the past couple of years but thankfully those problems are all resolved now. The kind of stuff happens sometimes. I won't deny that those problems - which were really just the culmination of many years of a lot of other b.s. - left a foul taste in my mouth about SW. But now that all the headaches are behind me I'm feeling great about it. I'm finally running my own band again and I'm really happy and excited to be back at it. I've got a killer line-up {{sic|hide=y|comprised |of}} myself, Danny Vapid, Simon Lamb (the Ritalins), Justin Perkins (Yesterday's Kids) and Adam Cargin (Blueheels) (he's also the new Riverdales drummer) and we've got a great set list.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by benweasel at 03:42 PM |url=http://benweasel.mu.nu/archives/285007.php |title=Weasel Manor: Screeching Weasel/Riverdales June 19–20 in Austin TX |publisher=Benweasel.mu.nu |date=2009-03-27 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In response to the resurrection of the Screeching Weasel name without his involvement, Jughead released the following statement via his MySpace page:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If it weren’t for the fact that I actually enjoy conversing with the fans of my prior bands, I would never have found out about a new band called Screeching Weasel beginning to tour. “This can’t be the band I was in.” I say to myself. “I would have been preparing.”  My mind would much prefer going to a place of calm contemplation than into a dark cold room filled with anger and the emotions associated with betrayal. So to avoid painful emoting I first took the facts that Ben and I started a band together called Screeching Weasel, we both spent all our days making that band a home for ourselves, and 18 years later we put it to rest. This along with the statement made by both me and Ben on many occasions that the band wouldn’t be Screeching Weasel without either of us, makes me assume that this band playing isn’t Screeching Weasel, because I don’t recall having kicked myself out of the band. So it seems logical that this is not Screeching Weasel. If it were I would have to admit that I longer [sic] have friends named Ben Foster or Dan Schafer. As for people like Ben Weasel, Dan Vapid, or even John Jughead, I have nothing to say, because they never really existed, they were just made up names for a bunch of friends that tried to do something different in order to survive and make a living in this world. And I imagine they are all still trying to make a living somehow, seeing that their band’s prominent “leader” never wanted to tour in order to make it financially viable to continue on.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=blog.view&amp;friendId=40240030&amp;blogId=479816553 |title=A Statement by John Jughead Pierson van John Jughead Pierson (John Jughead Pierson) op Myspace |publisher=Blogs.myspace.com |date=2010-06-16 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/32891 |title=Jughead releases statement on Screeching Weasel reformation |publisher=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Weasel later revealed the split with Jughead was the result of two-year long legal battle over Screeching Weasel's business affairs and, although they were resolved, Weasel said &quot;it was not an amicable split&quot; and that &quot;things had gone way, way past the point of no return in terms of our friendship and any semblance of a working relationship anymore&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jerseybeat.com/benweasel.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2009, Mike Park of [[Asian Man Records]] announced that Weasel had decided to sever his relationship with the label and that [[Recess Records]] would be carrying the Screeching Weasel, [[Riverdales]] and Ben Weasel solo back catalogues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/36003 |title=Asian Man and Ben Weasel part ways |publisher=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 30, 2010, Ben Weasel appeared on ''[[Last Call with Carson Daly]]'' to talk about his personal problems with anxiety disorders and [[agoraphobia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.punknews.org/article/40202&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 15, 2011, the band released its first album in eleven years, ''[[First World Manifesto]]'' on Fat Wreck Chords.  It was produced by [[Mike Kennerty]] of [[The All-American Rejects]].  It was announced that the label will also be releasing the back catalogs of Screeching Weasel, the Riverdales, and Ben Weasel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fatwreck.com/news |title=News: Fat Wreck Chords |publisher=Fatwreck.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 18, 2011, during Screeching Weasel's [[South by Southwest|South by Southwest Festival]] performance at the Scoot Inn in Austin, Texas, Foster punched the face of a female audience member who had thrown a beer and ice cubes at him, and also spit in his face. As a result a woman on the stage, believed to be the club's owner, grabbed him from behind, and Ben mistaking her for an attacking fan turned around and punched her twice in the scuffle. Foster was then restrained by security and left the venue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mxdwn.com/2011/03/19/news/screeching-weasel-frontman-involved-in-altercation-with-two-women-at-sxsw-gig/|title=Screeching Weasel Frontman Involved in Altercation With Two Women at SXSW Gig|publisher=mxdwn.com|date=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 22, Foster apologized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mxdwn.com/2011/03/22/news/ben-weasel-apologizes-for-altercation-with-fan-at-sxsw/ |title=Ben Weasel Apologizes for Altercation with Fan at SXSW |publisher=mxdwn.com|accessdate=2011-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 23, Punknews.org posted a statement from the four other members of Screeching Weasel, Dan Schafer, Adam Cargin, Justin Perkins and Drew Fredrichsen, announcing their resignation from the band. &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The un-calculated act put forth by Ben 'Weasel' Foster leading up to and including the violence that erupted on stage is seen by the band as shameful and embarrassing. The sentiments and actions expressed were completely out of our control and in no way represent the band members' view points or moral compasses. As a result, the band has discussed at length and has come to the conclusion that as a group we will not likely be able to muster the dignity to attempt a live performance as 'Screeching Weasel' in the for-seeable future.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/article/42026 |title=Screeching Weasel members resign |publisher=Punknews.org |date=2010-06-30 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On March 31, Weasel announced the cancellation of &quot;Weasel Fest&quot;, a 3-day event in honor of Screeching Weasel's 25th anniversary that had been scheduled to take place at Reggie's Rock Club in Chicago, after many of the other acts on the bill dropped out in the wake of the SXSW incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.benweasel.com/2011/03/31/reggies-shows-canceled/&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview published in July 2011, [[Fat Mike]], owner of Fat Wreck Chords, stated that he had no interest in releasing another Screeching Weasel record, although the label might still reissue the band's back catalog.&lt;ref&gt;http://exclaim.ca/Interviews/WebExclusive/nofxs_fat_mike/Page/3&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite speculation of a breakup, Screeching Weasel has scheduled a show for October 29 at Reggie's Rock Club in Chicago with [[The Queers]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.punknews.org/article/43591&lt;/ref&gt;  As of yet, the band's line-up, save for Ben Weasel, has not been announced.  A new EP, titled ''The Carnival of Schadenfreude'', is also being prepared for release &lt;Ref&gt;http://www.interpunk.com/item.cfm?Item=197332&amp;&lt;/ref&gt;.

A documentary on the band is in the works&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/#!/weaselmovie&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Musical style and influence==
In addition to the Ramones, Ben Weasel credits bands such as [[Black Flag (band)|Black Flag]], [[D.O.A. (band)|D.O.A.]], [[The Dickies]] and [[Zero Boys]] for laying the groundwork for Screeching Weasel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adita.org/redlinedistribution/interviews/benweasel.shtml |title=Red Line Distribution - Ben Weasel |publisher=Adita.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much like the Ramones, Screeching Weasel's common lyrical themes include [[girls]] and [[mental health]] problems (Weasel suffered from anxiety).&lt;ref name=&quot;DeRogatis&quot; /&gt; While Weasel has been the sole writer of the majority of the band's catalogue, a number of songs credit Vapid, Jughead, or [[The Queers]]' frontman Joe King as co-writers.

Many subsequent punk and pop punk bands who have experienced mainstream success cite Screeching Weasel as an influence. [[Blink-182]] covered the band's song &quot;The Girl Next Door&quot; on their album ''[[Buddha (album)|Buddha]]'', with Blink-182 guitarist [[Tom Delonge]] citing them as one of the biggest influences on his songwriting.&lt;ref name=&quot;DeRogatis&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.jimdero.com/OtherWritings/Other%20Weasel.htm| title = Screeching Halt| accessdate = 2007-02-18| author = DeRogatis, Jim| authorlink = Jim DeRogatis| date = [[2001]]| publisher = [[Spin (magazine)|Spin]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other influenced bands include [[Green Day]] (whose bassist previously played in Screeching Weasel), [[The All-American Rejects]] (whose guitarist Mike Kennerty produced ''First World Manifesto''), fellow Chicago bands [[Rise Against]] and [[Alkaline Trio]], and popular [[ska punk]] band [[Less Than Jake]].&lt;ref name=&quot;avclub1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.thejusticeonline.com/media/storage/paper573/news/2004/09/07/Arts/Rise-Against.Talks.Politics.Punk-711365.shtml |title=Rise Against talks politics, punk - Arts |publisher=Media.www.thejusticeonline.com |date=2011-03-22 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spinner.com/2009/11/30/alkaline-trio-emulate-punk-forefathers-on-new-album/ |title=Alkaline Trio Emulate Punk 'Forefathers' on New Album |publisher=Spinner |date=2009-11-30 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, a number of independent punk bands such as [[The Apers]], [[The Leftovers]], [[The Manges]], and [[The Unlovables]] cite Screeching Weasel as influential.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.punknews.org/review/935 |title=The Apers - The Apers |publisher=Punknews.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.razorcake.org/site/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=23675 |title=Interview with The Leftovers |publisher=Razorcake |date=2010-09-05 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ampmagazine.com/4732/the-manges-bad-juju-full-album-stream/ |title=The Manges – Bad Juju – Full Album Stream |publisher=AMP Magazine |date=2010-10-07 |accessdate=2011-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Members==
* [[Ben Weasel]] - [[Lead vocalist|lead vocals]], [[guitar]] (1986–2001; 2004; 2009–present)
* [[John Pierson (musician)|John Jughead]] - guitar, [[Backing vocalist|backing vocals]] (1986–2001; 2004)
* [[Vince Vogel|Vinnie Bovine]] - [[Bass guitar|bass]] (1986–1988)
* Steve Cheese - [[Drum kit|drums]] (1986–1988)
* [[Aaron Cometbus]] - drums (1988) (two shows)
* Warren Fish - bass (1988–1989)
* Brian Vermin - drums (1988–1990)
* [[Dan Vapid]] - bass, guitar, backing vocals (1989–1994; 1996; 2004; 2009–2011)
* Doug Ward - guitar (1989)
* Dave Naked - bass (1991–1992)
* Scott &quot;Gub&quot; Conway - bass (1992)
* [[Dan Panic]] - drums (1991–1996)
* Johnny Personality - bass (1992)
* [[Mass Giorgini]] - bass (1994; 1996–2001; 2004)
* [[Mike Dirnt]] - bass (1994)
* [[Dan Lumley]] - drums (1996–2001, 2004)
* Zac Damon - guitar (1997–1998; 2011-present)
* [[Phillip Hill]] - guitar (2000–2001)
* Simon Lamb - guitar (2009–2010)
* Justin Perkins - bass (2009–2011)
* Adam Cargin - drums (2009–2011)
* Drew Fredrichsen - guitar (2010–2011)
* Dave Klein - bass (2011-present)
* Pierre Marche - drums (2011-present)
* Mike Hunchback - guitar (2011-present)

==Discography==
'''Studio albums'''
* ''[[Screeching Weasel (album)|Screeching Weasel]]'' (1987)
* ''[[Boogadaboogadaboogada!]]'' (1988)
* ''[[My Brain Hurts]]'' (1991)
* ''[[Ramones (Screeching Weasel album)|Ramones]]'' (1992)
* ''[[Wiggle (album)|Wiggle]]'' (1993)
* ''[[Anthem for a New Tomorrow]]'' (1993)
* ''[[How to Make Enemies and Irritate People]]'' (1994)
* ''[[Bark Like a Dog]]'' (1996)
* ''[[Television City Dream]]'' (1997)
* ''[[Emo (album)|Emo]]'' (1999)
* ''[[Teen Punks in Heat]]'' (2000)
* ''[[First World Manifesto]]'' (2011)

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
{{reflist}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.screechingweasel.com Official Screeching Weasel website]
*{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p14192|label=Screeching Weasel}}
* [http://www.bigwheelmagazine.com/show_preview/screeching-weasel-preview-at-club-nokia-in-los-angeles-ca-on-sunday-september-19-2010 Interview with Danny Vapid]

{{Screeching Weasel}}

[[Category:Musical groups established in 1986]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 1989]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 1991]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 1994]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 1996]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 2001]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2004]]
[[Category:American pop punk musical groups]]
[[Category:Musical groups from Chicago, Illinois]]
[[Category:Fat Wreck Chords artists]]
[[Category:Musical quintets]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2009]]

[[de:Screeching Weasel]]
[[es:Screeching Weasel]]
[[fr:Screeching Weasel]]
[[it:Screeching Weasel]]
[[hu:Screeching Weasel]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
