<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="728326" ns="0" title="Dick Button"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox figure skater
|name= Dick Button
|image=Dick Button at 1980 Winter Olympics.jpg
|caption=Dick Button commentating at the [[1980 Winter Olympics]] in Lake Placid
|fullname= Richard Totten Button
|altname=
|country= [[United States of America|United States]]
|formercountry=
|birth_date= {{Birth date and age|1929|7|18}}
|birth_place= [[Englewood, New Jersey]], [[United States]]
|hometown=
|residence=
|death_date=
|death_place=
|height=
|partner=
|formerpartner=
|coach=
|formercoach= [[Gustave Lussi]]
|choreographer=
|formerchoreographer=
|skating club= [[SC of Boston]] &lt;br&gt; [[Philadelphia SC &amp; HS]]
|retired= 1952
|medaltemplates= &lt;!-- see [[Template:MedalRelatedTemplates]] --&gt;
{{MedalCountry | [[United States of America|United States]]}}
{{MedalSport | Men's [[Figure skating]]}}
{{MedalCompetition | [[List of Olympic medalists in figure skating|Olympic Games]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1952 Winter Olympics|1952 Oslo]]|[[Figure skating at the 1952 Winter Olympics|Men's Singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1948 Winter Olympics|1948 St. Moritz]]|[[Figure skating at the 1948 Winter Olympics|Men's Singles]]}}
{{MedalCompetition|[[World Figure Skating Championships|World Championships]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1952 World Figure Skating Championships|1952 Paris]]|[[1952 World Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1951 World Figure Skating Championships|1951 Milan]]|[[1951 World Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1950 World Figure Skating Championships|1950 London]]|[[1950 World Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1949 World Figure Skating Championships|1949 Paris]]|[[1949 World Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1948 World Figure Skating Championships|1948 Davos]]|[[1948 World Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalSilver|[[1947 World Figure Skating Championships|1947 Stockholm]]|[[1947 World Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalCompetition|[[European Figure Skating Championships|European Championships]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1948 European Figure Skating Championships|1948 Prague]]|[[1948 European Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalCompetition|[[North American Figure Skating Championships|North American Championships]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1951 North American Figure Skating Championships|1951 Calgary]]|[[1951 North American Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1949 North American Figure Skating Championships|1949 Philadelphia]]|[[1949 North American Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1947 North American Figure Skating Championships|1947 Ottawa]]|[[1947 North American Figure Skating Championships|Men's singles]]}}
}}
'''Richard Totten &quot;Dick&quot; Button''' (born July 18, 1929) is an American former [[figure skating|figure skater]] and a well-known long-time skating [[television]] analyst. He is a two-time [[Figure Skating at the Olympic Games|Olympic Champion]] (1948, 1952) and five-time [[World Figure Skating Championships|World Champion]] (1948–1952). He is also the only non-European man to have become [[European Figure Skating Championships|European Champion]].

Button is credited as having been the first skater to successfully land the [[axel jump|double axel]] jump in competition in 1948, as well as the first triple jump of any kind – a triple [[loop jump|loop]] – in 1952. He also invented the flying [[camel spin]], which was originally known as the &quot;Button camel&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt;

==Biography==
===Amateur career===
Dick Button was born and raised in [[Englewood, New Jersey]]. He began skating at a young age. He did not begin training seriously until the age of 12 after his father overheard him being told he would never be a good skater.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Button |first=Dick |title=Dick Button On Skates  |accessdate=2007-09-06  |edition= |series= |date= |year=1955 |month= |publisher=Prentice-Hall  |location=Englewood Cliffs, N.J.  |id=Catalog Card No. 55-12069 | pages =40–41 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, Button's father sent him to New York to take lessons from ice dancing coach [[Joe Carroll]].  He trained over the summer in [[Lake Placid, New York]], eventually switching on Carroll's recommendation to coach [[Gustave Lussi]], who coached Button for the rest of his career.

In his first competition, the 1943 Eastern States Novice Championship, he placed second behind [[Jean-Pierre Brunet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; In 1944, he won the Eastern States Junior title which earned him the opportunity to compete at the National Novice Championships. He won the event. In 1945, his third year of serious skating, he won the Eastern States Senior title and the national Junior title. At this time, he was also skating [[pair skating|pairs]], and competed with [[Barbara Jones]]{{Disambiguation needed|date=June 2011}} in Junior Pairs at the 1946 Eastern States Championships. They performed Button's singles program side by side with minor modifications and won.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; This competition, where Button also competed as a single skater, led into the 1946 [[United States Figure Skating Championships]].

Button won the 1946 U.S. Championships at age 16, winning by a unanimous vote. According to Button, this was the first time anyone had won the men's novice, junior, and senior titles in three consecutive years.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; This win earned Button a spot to the [[1947 World Figure Skating Championships]].

At the 1947 World Championships, Button was second behind rival [[Hans Gerschwiler]] following the [[compulsory figures]] part of the competition, with 34.9 points separating them.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; Button won the [[free skating]] portion, but Gerschwiler had the majority of first places from the judges, three to Button's two.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; Button won the silver medal at his first Worlds. It was the last time he placed lower than first in competition.

At the competition, Button was befriended by [[Ulrich Salchow]]. Salchow, who was disappointed when Button did not win, presented him with the first International Cup Salchow had won in 1901.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; Button later passed on this trophy to [[John Misha Petkevich]] following the [[1972 Winter Olympics|1972 Olympics]] and [[1972 World Figure Skating Championships|World Championships]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Petkevich  |first=John Misha |authorlink=John Misha Petkevich |coauthors= |title=Figure Skating: Championship Techniques  |year=1989 |publisher=Sports Illustrated  |location= |isbn=1568000707  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Button faced Gerschwiler again at the [[1948 European Figure Skating Championships]]. Button led after figures in points, having 749 points to Gerschwiler's 747.8, but Gerschwiler led in placings, with 14 to Button's 15.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; During the free skate, Button performed his Olympic program for the first time. He won, with 11 placings to Gerschwiler's 18.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; Following this year, when North Americans took home the men's and ladies' titles, non-Europeans were no longer allowed to enter into the European Championships. Button is the only American to have won the European Championships.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt;

At the [[1948 Winter Olympics]], Button led Gerschwiler by a 29.6 point lead following the figures portion of the competition, having won four of the five figures.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; Button had been attempting the [[Axel jump|double axel jump]] in practice but had never landed it. In practice on the day before the free skating event, Button landed one in practice for the first time. He decided to put it into his free skate for the next day. Button landed it in competition, becoming the first skater in the world to do so. Button received eight firsts and two seconds, for a total of 10 places. Gerschwiler had 23.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt;  That combined with the figures results gave Button the gold medal.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Benjamin T. &quot;Button Brings It.&quot; Skating Jan. 2009: 32–33.&lt;/ref&gt; He became, and remains, the youngest man to win the Olympic gold in figure skating.&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usoc.org/26_597.htm |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070928005756/http://www.usoc.org/26_597.htm |archivedate = September 28, 2007  |title=United States Olympic Committee – Button, Richard T. (Dick)  |accessdate=2007-09-06 |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Button went on to the [[1948 World Figure Skating Championships|1948 World Championships]], where he faced Gerschwiler for the last time. Button won the event. At the time, the U.S. Championships were held after the World Championships, and Button finished his season by defending his national title.

In February 1948, Button, his coach, and his mother were in [[Prague]] to perform an exhibition. They were stranded there after the [[Communism|Communist]] uprising and had to be extracted by the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt;

In 1949, Button won the [[James E. Sullivan Award|Sullivan Award]] as the outstanding amateur athlete in the United States. He is one of 2 male figure skaters to win this award. Evan Lysacek being the other.&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;

Button had intended to attend [[Yale University]] beginning in the fall of 1947, but deferred a year due to the Olympics.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot;/&gt; Although he had originally been assured that his skating would not be a problem as long as his grades were good, he was later informed that he could not continue competing if he wanted to attend Yale. On advice from people from the [[Skating Club of Boston]], Button applied to, and was accepted at, [[Harvard University]]. Button was a full-time student at Harvard while skating competitively and graduated in 1952.

Button won every competition he entered for the rest of his competitive career. He trained at the [[Skating Club of Boston]] while attending Harvard, commuting to Lake Placid during breaks.

As reigning and defending champion, as well as being the first skater to perform a double axel and a flying camel, Button was under pressure to perform a new jump or spin every season. In 1949, he performed a double loop-double loop combination. In 1950, he performed the double loop-double loop-double loop. In 1951, he performed a [[Axel jump|double axel]]-double loop combination and a [[Axel jump|double axel]]-[[Axel jump|double axel]] sequence.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; For the [[1952 Winter Olympics]], Button and Lussi began working on a triple jump. They settled on training the triple loop. Button landed it for the first time in practice in December 1951 at the Skating Club of Boston, and for the first time in exhibition in [[Vienna]] following the European Championships.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Dick Button gold medal.jpg|thumb|right|Dick Button's 1952 Olympic gold medal]]
At the [[1952 Winter Olympics]], Button had the lead after figures, with 9 first places, over [[Helmut Seibt]]. Button's point total was 1,000.2 to Seibt's 957.7.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; During his free skate, Button successfully landed the triple loop, becoming the first person to complete a triple jump in competition.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; He then went on to defend his titles at the [[1952 World Figure Skating Championships]] and U.S. Championships.

===Professional career===
Button decided to enter [[Harvard Law School]] in the fall of 1952. Because of the time commitments, Button retired from amateur skating that year in order to focus on law school.&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt; Following his retirement, Button signed on to skate with the [[Ice Capades]] during his law school vacations.

After his competitive skating career ended, Button toured with [[Ice Capades]] and [[Holiday on Ice]], and completed a [[Bachelor of Laws]] (LL.B.) degree at [[Harvard Law School]].&lt;ref name=&quot;abc&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abcmedianet.com/shows05/sports/commentators/button.shtml |title=ABC SPORTS COMMENTATOR: Dick Button |accessdate=2007-09-06 |work= |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070404154807/http://www.abcmedianet.com/shows05/sports/commentators/button.shtml |archivedate = April 4, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; After graduation, he was [[Bar association|admitted to the bar]] in [[Washington, D.C.]].&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;  He co-produced &quot;Dick Button's Ice-Travaganza&quot; for the [[1964 New York World's Fair]], starring 1963 World Champion [[Donald McPherson (figure skater)|Donald McPherson]], but the ice show lost money and closed after a few months.
As an actor, Button has performed  in movie roles such as &quot;[[The Young Doctors]]&quot; starring Fredrich March,  to &quot;[[The Bad News Bears Go to Japan]]&quot; starring Tony Curtis. And, in television roles on The Hallmark Hall of Fame's &quot;Hans Brinker]]&quot; co-starring Tab Hunter, as well as  &quot;[[Dancing is a Man's Game]]&quot;  dancing alongside star Gene Kelly and famed New York City Ballet star Edward Villella, and appeared in &quot;[[Mr. Broadway]]&quot; starring Mickey Rooney. Other television appearances include &quot;[[Beverly Hills 90210]]&quot; and Stephen Spielberg's &quot;[[The Animaniacs]]&quot;, &quot;[[Omnibus (U.S. TV series)|Omnibus]]&quot;, &quot;[[Art Linkletter's House Party]]&quot;, numerous appearances on the Hallmark Hall of Fame, &quot;[[Christmas at Rockefeller Center]]&quot; with Robert Goulet and Carol Lawrence; among his other numerous guest star television appearances. On the stage, Button has starred in the touring productions of Irving Berlin's &quot;[[Call Me Madam]]&quot;, Leonard Bernstein's&quot;[[On the Town (musical)|On the Town]]&quot;, The Gershwins' &quot;[[Girl Crazy]]&quot;, Rodgers and Hart's   &quot;[[Pal Joey]]&quot; , &quot;[[The Teahouse of the August Moon (play)|The Teahouse of the August Moon]]&quot;, &quot;[[Tall Story]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Picnic]]&quot;  as well as in the New York City Center revivals of &quot;[[Mister Roberts (play)|Mister Roberts]]&quot; and &quot;[[South Pacific (musical)|South Pacific]]&quot; to name a few. Button also studied acting with the famed Sandy Meisner at his school in New York City.

Button provided commentary for CBS's broadcast of the [[Figure skating at the 1960 Winter Olympics|1960 Winter Olympics]], launching a decades-long career in television broadcast journalism.  Button again did commentary for CBS's broadcast of the [[1961 United States Figure Skating Championships]].  Then, beginning in 1962, he worked as a figure skating analyst for [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC Sports]], which had acquired the rights to the [[United States Figure Skating Championships|U.S. Championships]] as well as the [[1962 World Figure Skating Championships]].  During ABC's coverage of figure skating events in the 1960s, 1970s and 1980s, Button became the sport's best-known analyst, well-known for his frank and often caustic appraisal of skaters' performances. He won an [[Emmy Award]] in 1981 for Outstanding Sports Personality – Analyst.&lt;ref name=&quot;abc&quot; /&gt;  Although other U.S. television networks aired the Winter Olympics from the 1990s onward, Button still appeared on ABC's broadcasts of the [[United States Figure Skating Championships|U.S.]] and [[World Figure Skating Championships]] until ABC removed them from its broadcast schedule in 2008.  Button's reputation and influence in the sport of figure skating therefore long outlasted his own competitive and performing career.

[[Image:Push Dick's Button.jpg|thumb|right|Push Dick's Button logo]]
During the [[Figure skating at the 2006 Winter Olympics|2006 Games]], Button appeared on loan from ABC to once again provide commentary on the Olympics.  Also during the [[2006 Winter Olympics]], [[USA Network]] ran a show called ''[[Olympic Ice]]''. A recurring segment, called &quot;Push Dick's Button,&quot; invited viewers to send in questions which Button answered on the air.  The segment proved very popular so ABC and ESPN put it into various broadcasts, most notably the [[2007 Skate America]], the [[2007 United States Figure Skating Championships]], and the [[2007 World Figure Skating Championships]].

In the fall of 2010 Button was lead Judge on the popular ABC show &quot;[[Skating with the Stars]]&quot; produced by BBC Worldwide, producers of the hit show &quot;[[Dancing with the Stars]]&quot;. In 2009, Button served as a judge on the CBC's ''[[Battle of the Blades]]'' reality show.  He again appeared on NBC to do commentary for [[Figure skating at the 2010 Winter Olympics|2010 Games]].

As founder of Candid Productions, he created a variety of made-for-television sports events, including the &quot;[[World Professional Figure Skating Championships]]&quot;, &quot;[[Challenge of Champions]]&quot;, [[Dorothy Hamill]] specials for HBO, and other non-skating sporting events like ''[[Superstars]].''&quot;[[Super Teams]]&quot;, &quot;[[Junior Superstars]]&quot;, &quot;[[Women's Superstars]]&quot;, and the popular &quot;[[Battle of the Network Stars]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;abc&quot; /&gt;

Button was inducted into the [[World Figure Skating Hall of Fame]] in 1976, the same year it was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldskatingmuseum.org/Museum_HOF_Inductees.htm |title=Official Site World Figure Skating Museum and Hall of Fame: Hall of Fame Members |accessdate=2007-09-06 |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Personal life===
In 1975, Button married figure skating coach [[Slavka Kohout]], but they later divorced.
&lt;ref&gt;[[Scott Hamilton (figure skater)|Scott Hamilton]], ''Landing It''.  ISBN 1-57566-466-6&lt;/ref&gt;  Button has two children, Edward and Emily.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Button suffered a serious head injury on July 5, 1978 when he was one of several men [[assault]]ed in [[Central Park]] by a gang of youths armed with baseball bats.  According to articles on different days in [[the New York Times]], Button was variously reported to have been passing through the park while jogging on his way to an appointment with a cabinetmaker;  when he was attacked .  Three persons were subsequently convicted of [[assault]] for the attacks.  Contemporary news accounts and trial testimony indicated that the assailants were intending to target [[gay]] people, but there was no indication that any of the victims were targeted specifically.  News accounts stated the attackers targeted persons in the [[Central Park]] Ramble area as that was an area where [[gay]] persons congregated, but that the victims were attacked at random, and that because of the random nature of the attacks &quot;. . . the police said there was no reason to believe the victims were homosexual.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[The New York Times]],  July 7, 1978; July 8, 1978; July 9, 1978; July 13, 1978; July 14, 1978; July 28, 1979; October 17, 1979&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 31, 2000, Button was skating at a public rink in New York State when he fell, fracturing his skull and causing a serious brain injury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Richard | last=Sandomir | coauthors= |authorlink= | title=Dick Button Now Back on the Stage He Loves | date=2006-02-15 | publisher= | url =http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/15/sports/olympics/15button.html | work =New York Times | pages = | accessdate = 2010-02-15 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;  He has since recovered, and now is a national spokesman for the Brain Injury Association of America &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biausa.org/spokespersons.htm |title=Brain Injury Awareness Month |accessdate=2010-02-15 |work=Brain Injury Association of America }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as continuing his Award{{fact|date=November 2011}} winning commentary for the broadcasts of The Olympic Games, and various figure skating television shows.

==Firsts==
* First skater to land a [[axel jump|double axel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;
* First skater to land a triple jump (a [[loop jump|triple loop]])&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;
* First male skater to perform the [[camel spin]] and inventor of the flying camel spin (also known as the Button Camel, after him)
* Only American to win the [[European Figure Skating Championships|European title]].&lt;ref name=&quot;onskates&quot; /&gt;
* First American [[World Figure Skating Championships|World Champion]].
* First American to win the Olympic title in figure skating.
* First and only American back-to-back Olympic champion in figure skating.&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;
* First and only male skater to simultaneously hold all the following titles: [[United States Figure Skating Championships|National]], [[North American Figure Skating Championships|North American]], [[European Figure Skating Championships|European]], [[World Figure Skating Championships|Worlds]], and [[Figure skating at the 1948 Winter Olympics|Olympics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;
* Youngest man to win the Olympic title in figure skating (age 18).&lt;ref name=&quot;usoc&quot; /&gt;

==Results==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Event
! 1944
! 1945
! 1946
! 1947
! 1948
! 1949
! 1950
! 1951
! 1952
|-
| [[Winter Olympic Games]] || || || || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st || || || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st
|-
| [[World Figure Skating Championships|World Championships]] || || || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:silver;&quot;| 2nd ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st
|-
| [[European Figure Skating Championships|European Championships]] || || || || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st || || || ||
|-
| [[North American Figure Skating Championships|North American Championships]] || || || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st || ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||
|-
| [[United States Figure Skating Championships|U.S. Championships]] ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st N. ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st J. ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st ||  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:gold;&quot;| 1st
|}

* N = Novice level; J = Junior level

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;
*  {{PDFlink|[http://www.xcelenergycenter.com/uploads/assets/saintpaul2008/news/Past%20U.S.%20Champions.pdf Past U.S. Champions – Senior]|123&amp;nbsp;KB}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.abcmedianet.com/shows05/sports/commentators/button.shtml ABC Sports biography of Dick Button]
*[http://www.usolympicteam.com/26_597.htm Dick Button's U.S. Olympic Team bio]{{Dead link|date=May 2010}}
* [http://www.olympic.org/uk/utilities/multimedia/gallery/results_uk.asp?entid=77&amp;MediaType=vid Olympic.org Video: Dick Button lands the first double axel]
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/02/11/AR2006021101460.html Ranking the Rink]
* {{IMDb name|0125413|Dick Button}}

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{NavigationOlympicChampionsFigureSkatingMen}}
{{NavigationWorldChampionsFigureSkatingMen}}
{{NavigationNorthAmericanChampionsFigureSkatingMen}}
{{NavigationEuropeanChampionsFigureSkatingMen}}
{{NavigationUSChampionsFigureSkatingMen}}
{{Battle of the Blades}}
{{Olympics on CBS}}
{{Sullivan Award winners}}
}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Button, Dick
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Button, Richard
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=United States figure skater and analyst
|DATE OF BIRTH=July 18, 1929
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Englewood, New Jersey]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Button, Dick}}
[[Category:1929 births]]
[[Category:American male single skaters]]
[[Category:Figure skating commentators]]
[[Category:Figure skaters at the 1948 Winter Olympics]]
[[Category:Figure skaters at the 1952 Winter Olympics]]
[[Category:Harvard Law School alumni]]
[[Category:James E. Sullivan Award recipients]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Olympic figure skaters of the United States]]
[[Category:People from Englewood, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Sports Emmy Award winners]]
[[Category:Olympic gold medalists for the United States]]
[[Category:Olympic medalists in figure skating]]

[[de:Richard Button]]
[[es:Dick Button]]
[[fa:دیک باتون]]
[[fr:Dick Button]]
[[ja:ディック・バトン]]
[[no:Richard Button]]
[[pl:Richard Button]]
[[pt:Dick Button]]
[[ru:Баттон, Дик]]
[[fi:Dick Button]]
[[tr:Dick Button]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
