<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7290308" ns="0" title="Big Ben"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=June 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}
{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
[[Image:Clock Tower - Palace of Westminster, London - September 2006-2.jpg|right|thumb|''Big Ben'' is in the Clock Tower]]
'''Big Ben''' is the nickname for the great [[Bell (instrument)|bell]] of the [[clock]] at the north end of the [[Palace of Westminster]] in [[London]],&lt;ref name=wbfbb&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.whitechapelbellfoundry.co.uk/bigben.htm | title = The Story of Big Ben | publisher=Whitechapel Bell Foundry | accessdate =19 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is generally extended to refer to the clock or the [[clock tower]] as well.&lt;ref name=BigBenCOD&gt;{{cite book|last=Fowler|first=H. W.|authorlink=Henry Watson Fowler|others=First edited by H. W. Fowler and F. G. Fowler|title=The Concise Oxford dictionary of current English|edition=Sixth edition|year=1976|page=95|publisher=[[Clarendon Press]]|isbn=0198611218|quote=Big Ben, great bell, clock, and tower, of Houses of Parliament}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the largest four-faced [[Chime (bell instrument)|chiming]] clock and the third-tallest free-standing clock tower in the world.&lt;ref name=CTBUH&gt;[http://www.ctbuh.org/Portals/0/Tallest/CTBUH_TallestClockGovernmentPalace.pdf]{{Dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It celebrated its 150th anniversary on 31 May 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Happy birthday, Big Ben|work=The Times |location=UK ||number=69521|date=1 January 2009|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; during which celebratory events took place.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.bigben.parliament.uk/ixbin/indexplus?record=ART16|title=Join in the anniversary celebrations|publisher=United Kingdom Parliament}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;livingheritage&quot; /&gt; The erecting of the tower was completed on 10 April 1858. The clock tower has become one of the most prominent symbols of both London and England, often in the [[establishing shot]] of films set in the city.

== Tower ==

[[File:Palace of Westminster, London - Feb 2007.jpg|thumb|left|300px|The [[Palace of Westminster]], the Clock Tower and [[Westminster Bridge]]]]

The present Clock Tower was raised as a part of [[Charles Barry]]'s design for a new palace, after the old Palace of Westminster was largely destroyed by fire on the night of 16 October 1834.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/building/palace/big-ben/enquiries/|title=Big Ben—Frequently asked questions|publisher=UK Parliament|accessdate=18 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/building/palace/big-ben/key-dates-/1289-90/|title=Key dates: 1289-1834 |publisher=UK Parliament |accessdate=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new Parliament was built in a Neo-gothic style. Although Barry was the chief architect of the Palace, he turned to [[Augustus Welby Northmore Pugin|Augustus Pugin]] for the design of the Clock Tower, which resembles earlier Pugin designs, including one for [[Scarisbrick Hall]]. The design for the Clock Tower was Pugin's last design before his final descent into madness and death, and Pugin himself wrote, at the time of Barry's last visit to him to collect the drawings: &quot;I never worked so hard in my life for Mr Barry for tomorrow I render all the designs for finishing his bell tower &amp; it is beautiful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rosemary Hill, ''God's Architect: Pugin &amp; the Building of Romantic Britain'' (2007) p. 482&lt;/ref&gt; The tower is designed in Pugin's celebrated [[Gothic Revival architecture|Gothic Revival]] style, and is {{convert|96.3|m|ft}} high (roughly 16 stories).&lt;ref name=Bong&gt;
{{cite news|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/31002198/ |title=Bong! Big Ben rings in its 150th anniversary|agency=Associated Press|date=29 May 2009|accessdate=1 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bottom {{convert|61|m|ft}} of the Clock Tower's structure consists of brickwork with sand coloured [[Anston]] limestone [[cladding (construction)|cladding]]. The remainder of the tower's height is a framed spire of [[cast iron]]. The tower is founded on a {{convert|15|m|ft|adj=on}} square raft, made of {{convert|3|m|ft|adj=on}} thick concrete, at a depth of {{convert|4|m|ft}} below ground level. The four clock dials are {{convert|55|m|ft}} above ground. The interior volume of the tower is 4,650 cubic metres (164,200 cubic feet).

Despite being one of the world's most famous tourist attractions, the interior of the tower is not open to overseas visitors, though United Kingdom residents are able to arrange tours (well in advance) through their Member of Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/visiting/visitingandtours/bigben.cfm |title=Clock Tower tour – UK Parliament |publisher=Parliament.uk |date=21 April 2010 |accessdate=30 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the tower has no lift, so those escorted must climb the 334 limestone stairs to the top.&lt;ref name=Bong/&gt;

Because of changes in ground conditions since construction (notably tunnelling for the [[Jubilee Line]] extension), the tower leans slightly to the north-west, by roughly 220&amp;nbsp;millimetres (8.66&amp;nbsp;in) at the clock dials, giving an inclination of approximately 1/250.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.royalsoced.org.uk/events/reports/2001-2002/rae_02.pdf |title=A tale of two towers: Big Ben and Pisa |format=PDF |accessdate=30 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Staff
  | title = Tunnel Vision
  | work=Post Report Summary
  | publisher=Parliamentary Office of Science and Technology
  | date = January 1997
  | url = http://www.parliament.uk/post/pn090.pdf
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Due to thermal effects it oscillates annually by a few millimetres east and west.

== Clock ==
=== Dials ===

The clock dials are big enough that the Clock Tower was once the largest four-faced clock in the world.
[[File:Clock Tower - Palace of Westminster, London - May 2007.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The dial of the Great Clock of Westminster. The hour hand is 2.7&amp;nbsp;metres (9&amp;nbsp;ft) long and the minute hand is 4.3&amp;nbsp;metres (14&amp;nbsp;ft) long]]

The clock and dials were designed by [[Augustus Pugin]]. The clock dials are set in an iron frame {{convert|7|m|ft}} in diameter, supporting 312 pieces of opal glass, rather like a [[Stained glass|stained-glass]] window. Some of the glass pieces may be removed for inspection of the hands. The surround of the dials is [[Gilding|gilded]]. At the base of each clock dial in gilt letters is the [[Latin]] inscription:

{{cquote|DOMINE SALVAM FAC REGINAM NOSTRAM VICTORIAM PRIMAM|}}

Which means ''O Lord, keep safe our Queen Victoria the First''.

=== Movement ===

[[Image:BigBenAtDusk.jpg|thumb|left|The Clock Tower at dusk, with [[The London Eye]] in the background]]

The clock's [[Movement (clockwork)|movement]] is famous for its reliability. The designers were the lawyer and amateur [[Horology|horologist]] [[Edmund Beckett, 1st Baron Grimthorpe|Edmund Beckett Denison]], and [[George Biddell Airy|George Airy]], the [[Astronomer Royal]]. Construction was entrusted to clockmaker [[Edward John Dent]]; after his death in 1853 his stepson Frederick Dent completed the work, in 1854.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/livingheritage/building/big_ben/building_clock_tower/building_great_clock.cfm|title=Denison, Dent and delays|date=13 November 2009|work=Building the Great Clock|publisher=UK Parliament|accessdate=23 November 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the Tower was not complete until 1859, Denison had time to experiment: Instead of using the [[Escapement#Deadbeat escapement|deadbeat escapement]] and [[remontoire]] as originally designed, Denison invented the double three-legged [[Escapement#Gravity escapement|gravity escapement]]. This [[escapement]] provides the best separation between [[pendulum]] and clock mechanism. The pendulum is installed within an enclosed windproof box sunk beneath the clockroom. It is 3.9m long, weighs 300&amp;nbsp;kg and beats every 2 seconds. The clockwork mechanism in a room below weighs 5 tons.
On top of the pendulum is a small stack of old [[British one penny coin (pre-decimal)|penny coins]]; these are to adjust the time of the clock. Adding a coin has the effect of minutely lifting the position of the pendulum's [[Center of mass|centre of mass]], reducing the effective length of the pendulum rod and hence increasing the rate at which the pendulum swings. Adding or removing a penny will change the clock's speed by 0.4 seconds per day.&lt;ref name=livingheritage&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/livingheritage/building/big_ben/facts_figures/great_clock_facts.cfm|title=Great Clock facts|date=13 November 2009|work=Big Ben|publisher=UK Parliament |accessdate=23 November 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 May 1941, a German bombing raid damaged two of the clock's dials and sections of the tower's stepped roof and destroyed the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]] chamber. Architect [[Sir Giles Gilbert Scott]] designed a new five-floor block. Two floors are occupied by the current chamber which was used for the first time on 26 October 1950. Despite the heavy bombing the clock ran accurately and chimed throughout [[the Blitz]].
{{-}}

The Big Ben clock tower has been tilting as a result of the excavation of tunnels near Westminster.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ingenia.org.uk/ingenia/issues/issue9/mair.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The tower has tilted an additional 0.9 mm each year since 2003,&lt;ref&gt;TIME Magazine Vol. 178, No. 16| 2011&lt;/ref&gt; and the tilt can now be seen by the naked eye.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://newsfeed.time.com/2011/10/10/report-big-ben-could-become-leaning-tower-of-london/ | work=Time | date=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Malfunctions, breakdowns, and other outages===
[[Image:Cleaning Big Ben.jpg|thumb|right|The south clock face being cleaned on 11 August 2007]]
*1916: for two years during [[World War I]], the bells were silenced and the clock face darkened at night to prevent attack by German [[Zeppelin]]s.&lt;ref name=Bong/&gt;
*1 Sept. 1939: although the bells continued to ring, the clock faces were darkened at night through [[World War II]] to prevent guiding [[The Blitz|Blitz]] pilots.&lt;ref name=Bong/&gt;
*New Year's Eve 1962: The clock slowed due to heavy snow and ice on the long hands, causing the pendulum to detach from the clockwork, as it is designed to do in such circumstances, to avoid serious damage elsewhere in the mechanism—the pendulum continuing to swing freely. Thus it chimed in the new year 10 minutes late.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1559986/Big-Ben-silenced-for-maintenance.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | title=Big Ben silenced for maintenance | first1=Carina | last1=Namih | date=11 August 2007 | accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 August 1976: First and only major breakdown. The air brake speed regulator of the chiming mechanism broke after more than 100 years of torsional fatigue causing the fully wound 4 ton weight to spin the winding drum out of the movement, causing a large amount of damage. The Great Clock was shut down for a total of 26 days over nine months – it was reactivated on 9 May 1977; this was its longest break in operation since it was built. During this time [[BBC Radio 4]] had to make do with the [[Greenwich Time Signal|pips]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Big Ben: The Bell, the Clock and the Tower |author=Peter MacDonald |isbn=0750938277}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although there were minor stoppages from 1977 to 2002 when the maintenance of the clock was carried out by the old firm of clockmakers Thwaites &amp; Reed, these were often repaired within the permitted two hour downtime and not recorded as stoppages. Prior to 1970 the maintenance was carried out by the original firm of Dents and since 2002 by Parliamentary staff.
*27 May 2005: the clock stopped at 10:07&amp;nbsp;pm local time, possibly due to hot weather; temperatures in London had reached an unseasonable 31.8&amp;nbsp;°C (90&amp;nbsp;°F). It restarted, but stopped again at 10:20&amp;nbsp;pm local time and remained still for about 90 minutes before restarting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/4589527.stm |work=BBC News  |title= Big Ben chimes stoppage mystery | date=28 May 2005 | accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*29 October 2005: the mechanism was stopped for about 33 hours so the clock and its chimes could be worked on. It was the lengthiest maintenance shutdown in 22 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_pictures/4389002.stm |work=BBC News  |title= In pictures: Big Ben's big turn off | date=29 October 2005 | accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*7:00&amp;nbsp;am 5 June 2006: The clock tower's &quot;Quarter Bells&quot; were taken out of commission for four weeks&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hutton |first=Robert |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000102&amp;sid=ak.qvEQ42YM4&amp;refer=uk |title=Big Ben's Chime Won't Sound the Same to Londoners for a While |publisher=Bloomberg  |date=4 June 2006 |accessdate=30 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a bearing holding one of the quarter bells was damaged from years of wear and needed to be removed for repairs. During this period, BBC Radio 4 broadcast recordings of British [[bird song]] followed by the pips in place of the usual chimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/theeditors/2006/06/bongs_and_birds.html |work=BBC News  |title= The Editors: Bongs and Birds |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*11 August 2007: Start of 6-week stoppage for maintenance. Bearings in the clock's going train and the &quot;great bell&quot; striker were replaced, for the first time since installation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6941611.stm |work=BBC News  |title= Big Ben silenced for repair work | date=11 August 2007 | accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the maintenance works, the clock was not driven by the original mechanism, but by an [[electric motor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bigben.parliament.uk/ixbin/indexplus?record=ART134 |title=Big Ben 1859 – 2009 – Keeping the Great Clock ticking  |publisher=UK Parliament |accessdate=27 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once again, [[BBC Radio 4]] had to make do with the pips during this time.

== Bells==
=== Great Bell ===
[[Image:big-ben-1858.jpg|thumb|left|The second 'Big Ben' (centre) and the Quarter Bells from ''[[News of the World|The Illustrated News of the World]]'' 4 December 1858]]
[[Image:big-ben-modern.jpg|thumb|right|A modern picture of 'Big Ben']]
The main bell, officially known as the ''Great Bell'', is the largest bell in the tower and part of the Great Clock of Westminster. The bell is better known by the nickname ''Big Ben''.&lt;ref name=&quot;greatbell&quot; /&gt;

The original bell was a 16.3-[[tonne]] (16&amp;nbsp;[[long ton|ton]]) hour bell, cast on 6 August 1856 in [[Stockton-on-Tees]] by [[John Warner &amp; Sons]].&lt;ref name=wbfbb/&gt; The bell was named in honour of Sir [[Benjamin Hall, 1st Baron Llanover|Benjamin Hall]], and his name is inscribed on it.&lt;ref name=&quot;times22505&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=22 October 1859|title=Big Ben of Westminster|journal=[[The Times]]|location=London|issue=22505|page=5|quote=It is proposed to call our king of bells 'Big Ben' in honour of Sir Benjamin Hall, the President of the Board of Works, during whose tenure of office it was cast}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, another theory for the origin of the name is that the bell may have been named after a contemporary heavyweight boxer [[Ben Caunt|Benjamin Caunt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/livingheritage/building/big_ben/building_clock_tower/great_bell.cfm|title=The Great Bell – Big Ben|date=13 November 2009|work=The building and its collections|publisher=UK Parliament|accessdate=23 November 2009|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is thought that the bell was originally to be called ''Victoria'' or ''Royal Victoria'' in honour of [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icons.org.uk/theicons/collection/big-ben/features/how-did-big-ben-get-its-name |title=How did Bigger Ben get its Name? – Big Ben – Icons of England |publisher=Icons.org.uk |accessdate=30 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; but that an MP suggested the nickname during a Parliamentary debate; the comment is not recorded in [[Hansard]].

Since the tower was not yet finished, the bell was mounted in [[Palace of Westminster#Grounds|New Palace Yard]]. Cast in 1856, the first bell was transported to the tower on a trolley drawn by sixteen horses, with crowds cheering its progress. Unfortunately, it cracked beyond repair while being tested and a replacement had to be made. The bell was recast at the [[Whitechapel Bell Foundry]] as a 13.76-[[tonne]] (13½&amp;nbsp;[[Long ton|ton]]) bell.&lt;ref&gt;The actual weight quoted by the founders is 13&amp;nbsp; [[Long ton|tons]] 10&amp;nbsp;[[hundredweight|cwts]] 3&amp;nbsp;[[Avoirdupois#British adaptation|qtrs]] 15&amp;nbsp;[[Pound (mass)|lbs]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=wbfbb/&gt; This was pulled {{convert|200|ft|m|abbr=on}} up to the Clock Tower’s belfry, a feat that took 18 hours. It is 2.2&amp;nbsp;metres tall and 2.9&amp;nbsp;metres wide. This new bell first chimed in July 1859. In September it too cracked under the hammer, a mere two months after it officially went into service. According to the foundry's manager, George Mears, Denison had used a hammer more than twice the maximum weight specified.&lt;ref name=wbfbb/&gt; For three years Big Ben was taken out of commission and the hours were struck on the lowest of the quarter bells until it was reinstalled. To make the repair, a square piece of metal was chipped out from the rim around the crack, and the bell given an eighth of a turn so the new hammer struck in a different place.&lt;ref name=wbfbb/&gt; Big Ben has chimed with an odd twang ever since and is still in use today complete with the crack. At the time of its casting, Big Ben was the largest bell in the British Isles until &quot;Great Paul&quot;, a 17&amp;nbsp;tonne (16¾&amp;nbsp;ton) bell currently hung in [[St Paul's Cathedral]], was cast in 1881.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.inloughborough.com/local%20history/Great_Paul.shtml|title=The History of Great Paul|publisher=Bell foundry museum, Leicester|accessdate=19 October 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080406001107/http://www.inloughborough.com/local+history/Great_Paul.shtml |archivedate = 6 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Chimes ===

[[File:BBC World Service Big Ben 1-1-2009.ogg|thumb|left|Click to hear [[BBC World Service]] announce itself, then play [[Westminster Chimes]] and the 12 strikes of Big Ben as broadcast at exactly 00:00:00 GMT on 1 January 2009.]]
Along with the Great Bell, the [[Belfry (architecture)|belfry]] houses four [[quarter bells]] which play the ''[[Westminster Quarters]]'' on the quarter hours. The four quarter bells are G{{music|sharp}}, F{{music|sharp}}, E, and B. They were cast by John Warner &amp; Sons at their Crescent Foundry in 1857 (G{{music|sharp}}, F{{music|sharp}} and B) and 1858 (E). The Foundry was in Jewin Crescent, in what is now known as The Barbican, in the City of London.

The Quarter Bells play a 20-chime sequence, 1–4 at quarter past, 5–12 at half past, 13–20 and 1–4 at quarter to, and 5–20 on the hour (which sounds 25 seconds before the main bell tolls the hour). Because the low bell (B) is struck twice in quick succession, there is not enough time to pull a hammer back, and it is supplied with two wrench hammers on opposite sides of the bell. The tune is that of the [[Cambridge Chimes]], first used for the chimes of [[Church of St Mary the Great, Cambridge|Great St Mary]]'s church, [[Cambridge]], and supposedly a [[Variation (music)|variation]], attributed to [[William Crotch]], on a [[Phrase (music)|phrase]] from [[George Frideric Handel|Handel]]'s ''[[Messiah (Handel)|Messiah]]''. The notional words of the chime, again derived from Great St Mary's and in turn an allusion to [[Psalm]] 37:23–24, are: &quot;All through this hour/Lord be my guide/And by Thy power/No foot shall slide&quot;. They are written on a plaque on the wall of the clock room.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Milmo
  | first = Cahel
  | title = Bong! A change of tune at Westminster
  |work=The Independent |location=UK
  | date = 5 June 2006
  | url = http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/bong-a-change-of-tune-at-westminster-481163.html
  | accessdate =8 April 2008
| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Lockyer
  | first = Herbert
  | title = A devotional commentary on psalms
  | publisher=Kregel Christian Books
  | year = 1993
  | location = Grand Rapids, MI
  | url =
  | id =
  | isbn =0825431468
  | page =  149 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Clear}}

==Nickname==

[[Image:Whitehall Street Traffic.jpg|right|thumb|200px|[[Double-decker bus]]es frame a busy [[Whitehall]] with Big Ben in the background.]]

The origin of the nickname ''Big Ben'' is the subject of some debate. The nickname was applied first to the Great Bell; it may have been named after [[Benjamin Hall, 1st Baron Llanover|Sir Benjamin Hall]], who oversaw the installation of the Great Bell, or after boxing's English Heavyweight Champion [[Benjamin Caunt]].&lt;ref name=wbfbb /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;greatbell&quot;&gt;[http://www.parliament.uk/about/images/exterior/bell.cfm UK Parliament – The Great Bell (Big Ben)]. Retrieved 13 July 2007. {{Wayback | url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/images/exterior/bell.cfm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; | date=20071012035101 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;clocktower&quot;&gt;[http://www.parliament.uk/about/history/big_ben/facts.cfm UK Parliament – The Clock Tower (Big Ben): Facts and figures] Accessed 13 July 2007 {{Dead link|date=May 2010}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;clocktowercloseup&quot;&gt;[http://www.parliament.uk/about/images/exterior/clocktower1.cfm UK Parliament – Clock Tower close-up] Accessed 13 July 2007 {{Dead link|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Now ''Big Ben'' is often used, by extension, to refer to the clock, the tower and the bell collectively, although the nickname is not universally accepted as referring to the clock and tower.&lt;ref name=BigBenCOD/&gt;&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;{{cite web|title=Big Ben|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/64921/Big-Ben|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online|accessdate=27 October 2008|first=Jonathan D.|last=Betts|date=26 November 2008|work=Encyclopædia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Columbia&gt;{{cite web|title=Big Ben|url=http://www.bartleby.com/65/bi/BigBen.html|publisher=Columbia University Press|accessdate=27 October 2008|year=2001–07|work=The Columbia Encyclopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Encarta&gt;{{cite web|title=Big Ben|url=http://uk.encarta.msn.com/dictionary_1861813060/Big_Ben.html|publisher=Microsoft Corporation |accessdate=14 January 2009|year=2009|work=Encarta World English Dictionary [North American Edition]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kwQ5lg9Y|archivedate=31 October 2009|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some authors of works about the tower, clock and bell sidestep the issue by using the words ''Big Ben'' first in the title, then going on to clarify that the subject of the book is the clock and tower as well as the bell.&lt;ref name=Lockhart&gt;{{cite web|title=Big Ben and the Westminster Clock Tower|url=http://isbndb.com/d/book/big_ben_and_the_westminster_clock_tower.html|publisher=isbndb.com|accessdate=27 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=MacDonald&gt;{{cite web|title=Big Ben: The Bell, The Clock And The Tower|url=http://isbndb.com/d/book/big_ben_the_bell_the_clock_and_the_tower.html|publisher=isbndb.com|accessdate=27 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Significance in popular culture ==
The clock has become a symbol of the United Kingdom and London, particularly in the visual media. When a television or film-maker wishes to indicate a generic location in Britain, a popular way to do so is to show an image of the Clock Tower, often with a [[Routemaster|red double-decker bus]] or [[black cab]] in the foreground.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Patterson
  | first = John
  | author-link =
  | last2 =
  | first2 =
  | author2-link =
  | title = City Light
  | newspaper=[[The Guardian]]
  | date = 1 June 2007
  | url = http://arts.guardian.co.uk/filmandmusic/story/0,,2091939,00.html
| location=London}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The sound of the clock chiming has also been used this way in audio media, but as the [[Westminster Quarters]] are heard from other clocks and other devices, the unique nature of this sound has been considerably diluted.

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Big Ben 2009.jpg|thumb|right|The Clock Tower during the 2008/2009 New Years Eve Celebrations. {{deletable image-caption}}]] --&gt;
The Clock Tower is a focus of New Year celebrations in the United Kingdom, with radio and TV stations tuning to its chimes to welcome the start of the year. Similarly, on [[Remembrance Day]], the chimes of Big Ben are broadcast to mark the 11th hour of the 11th day of the 11th month and the start of two minutes' silence.

[[Image:Big Ben London closeup.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Superior part of the clock tower.]]

[[ITN]]'s ''[[ITV News at Ten|News at Ten]]'' opening sequence features an image of the Clock Tower with the sound of Big Ben's chimes punctuating the announcement of the news headlines, and has done so on and off for the last 41 years. The Big Ben chimes (known within ITN as &quot;The Bongs&quot;) continue to be used during the headlines and all [[ITV News]] bulletins use a graphic based on the Westminster clock dial. Big Ben can also be heard striking the hour before some news bulletins on [[BBC Radio 4]] (6 pm and midnight, plus 10&amp;nbsp;pm on Sundays) and the [[BBC World Service]], a practice that began on 31 December 1923. The sound of the chimes are sent in real time from a microphone permanently installed in the tower and connected by line to [[Broadcasting House]].

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Clock Tower - Palace of Westminster - 20090803.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Superior part of the clock tower.]] --&gt;
Londoners who live an appropriate distance from the Clock Tower and Big Ben can, by means of listening to the chimes both live and on the radio or television, hear the bell strike thirteen times on New Year's Eve. This is possible due to what amounts to an offset between live and electronically transmitted chimes since the [[speed of sound]] is a lot slower than the speed of radio waves. Guests are invited to count the chimes aloud as the radio is gradually turned down.

The Clock Tower has appeared in many films, most notably in the 1978 version of ''[[The Thirty Nine Steps (1978 film)|The Thirty Nine Steps]]'', in which the hero [[Richard Hannay]] attempted to halt the clock's progress (to prevent a linked bomb detonating) by hanging from the minute hand of its western dial. In the fourth [[James Bond]] film ''[[Thunderball (film)|Thunderball]]'' a mistaken extra strike of Big Ben on the hour is designated by criminal organisation [[SPECTRE]] to be the signal that the British Government has acceded to its nuclear extortion demands. The gag phrase &quot;Big Ben!  Parliament!&quot; is repeated for comic effect by [[Chevy Chase]] in ''[[National Lampoon's European Vacation]]'' as the depicted family remains stuck on the [[Lambeth Bridge|Lambeth Bridge Roundabout]]. It was also used in the filming of ''[[Shanghai Knights]]'' starring [[Jackie Chan]] and [[Owen Wilson]], and was depicted as being partially destroyed in the ''[[Doctor Who]]'' episode &quot;[[Aliens of London]]&quot;. An animated version of the clock and its inner workings were also used as the setting for the climactic final battle between [[Basil of Baker Street]] and his nemesis Ratigan in the [[Walt Disney]] animated film ''[[The Great Mouse Detective]]'' as well as ''[[Peter Pan]]'' where Peter lands on the clock before they head to Neverland. It is shown being destroyed by a [[UFO]] in the film ''[[Mars Attacks!]]'', by a prehistoric creature in ''[[Gorgo (film)|Gorgo]]'', and by a lightning bolt in the film ''[[The Avengers (1998 film)|The Avengers]]''. It is destroyed on purpose and quite graphically in the movie ''[[V for Vendetta (film)|V for Vendetta]]'' and is flooded in the film ''[[Flood (film)|Flood]]''. In ''[[Reign of Fire (film)|Reign of Fire]]'', it is destroyed by [[dragons]]. The apparent &quot;thirteen chimes&quot; detailed above was also a major plot device in the ''[[Captain Scarlet and the Mysterons]]'' episode, &quot;[[Big Ben Strikes Again]]&quot;.

During the [[United Kingdom general election, 2010|2010 General Election]] the results of the national exit poll were projected onto the face of Big Ben.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=General election results beamed onto Big Ben |url=http://www.parliament.uk/business/news/2010/05/big-ben-projections/|publisher=parliament.uk|accessdate=30 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Accolades ==

A survey of 2,000 people found that the tower was the most popular landmark in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/7337319.stm |work=BBC News  | title=Big Ben 'UK's favourite landmark' | date=9 April 2008 | accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Big Ben was polled as the ''Most Iconic [[London in film|London Film]] Location''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.metro.co.uk/fame/article.html?in_article_id=72142&amp;in_page_id=7
|title=Big Ben most iconic London film location
|publisher=metro.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|London}}
* [[Victoria Tower]]

==References==

{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==

{{Commons|Big Ben}}
* [http://www.bigben.parliament.uk/ Official website]
* {{PDFlink|[http://www.parliament.uk/documents/upload/G11.pdf Palace of Westminster factsheet]|395&amp;nbsp;KB}}
* [http://www.whitechapelbellfoundry.co.uk/bigben.htm Whitechapel Bell Foundry on Big Ben]
* [http://www.flickr.com/photos/uk_parliament/tags/bigben UK parliament's interior photos of Big Ben and the Clock Tower]
* {{PDFlink|[http://www.raeng.org.uk/news/publications/ingenia/issue9/Mair.pdf ''Innovative engineering to control Big Ben's tilt'']|747&amp;nbsp;KB}} – A technical paper from Cambridge University
* [http://www.houghtonlespring.org.uk/articles/big_ben_clapper.htm Big Ben's old clapper] as forged in Houghton-le-Spring, Co Durham

{{Coord|51|30|02.2|N|00|07|28.6|W|type:landmark_scale:3000|display=title}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1859]]
[[Category:Bell towers]]
[[Category:Bells]]
[[Category:Clock towers in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:National government buildings in London]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in London]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in London]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Westminster]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Westminster]]
[[Category:Gothic Revival architecture in London]]
[[Category:Turret clocks]]
[[Category:Palace of Westminster]]

[[ar:بيج بن]]
[[az:Biq Ben]]
[[be:Біг-Бен]]
[[be-x-old:Біг-Бэн]]
[[bcl:Big Ben]]
[[bg:Биг Бен]]
[[bo:པིན་ཆེན་ཆུ་ཚོད།]]
[[bs:Big Ben]]
[[ca:Big Ben]]
[[cs:Big Ben]]
[[cy:Big Ben]]
[[da:Big Ben]]
[[de:Big Ben]]
[[et:Big Ben]]
[[es:Big Ben]]
[[eu:Big Ben]]
[[fa:ساعت بیگ بن]]
[[fr:Big Ben]]
[[ga:Big Ben]]
[[gl:Big Ben]]
[[ko:빅 벤]]
[[hy:Բիգ Բեն]]
[[hi:बिग बेन]]
[[hr:Big Ben]]
[[id:Big Ben]]
[[is:Klukkuturn Westminsterhallar]]
[[it:Big Ben]]
[[he:ביג בן]]
[[jv:Big Ben]]
[[kn:ಬಿಗ್ ಬೆನ್]]
[[la:Big Ben]]
[[lv:Bigbens]]
[[lt:Vestminsterio laikrodžio bokštas]]
[[hu:Big Ben]]
[[mk:Биг Бен]]
[[ml:ബിഗ് ബെൻ]]
[[arz:بيج بين]]
[[ms:Big Ben]]
[[nl:Big Ben]]
[[ja:ビッグ・ベン]]
[[no:Big Ben]]
[[nn:Big Ben]]
[[pnb:بگ بن]]
[[pl:Big Ben]]
[[pt:Big Ben]]
[[ro:Big Ben]]
[[ru:Биг-Бен]]
[[sq:Big Ben]]
[[simple:Big Ben]]
[[sk:Hodinová veža (Westminsterský palác)]]
[[so:Big Ben]]
[[ckb:بیگ بن]]
[[sr:Биг Бен]]
[[fi:Big Ben]]
[[sv:Big Ben]]
[[ta:பிக் பென்]]
[[te:బిగ్ బెన్]]
[[th:บิ๊กเบน]]
[[tr:Big Ben]]
[[uk:Біг-Бен]]
[[ur:بگ بین]]
[[vec:Big Ben]]
[[vi:Big Ben]]
[[zh:大本钟]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
