<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7295983" ns="0" title="Battle of Karameh"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Karameh
| partof      = the [[War of Attrition]]
| image       = [[File:Israeli raid in house during Karama.jpg|250px]]
| caption     = Israeli soldiers deployed during the Battle of Karameh.
| date        = March 21, 1968
| place       = [[Karameh]], {{flagicon|Jordan}} [[Jordan]]
| coordinates =
| territory   =
| result      = Israeli military victory and destruction of the Karameh camp&lt;ref&gt;Zeev Maoz, Defending the Holy Land, A Critical Analysis of Israel’s Security and Foreign Policy, University of Michigan Press, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars page 205&quot;&gt;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars, Random House New York, 1982 @ page 205&lt;/ref&gt;
| status      =
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Israel}} [[Israel]]
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|Jordan}} [[Jordan]]&lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO]] &lt;small&gt;(mostly [[Fatah]])&lt;/small&gt;
| combatant3  =
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Israel}} [[Levi Eshkol]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Uzi Narkis]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Moshe Dayan]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Jordan}} [[Mashhour Haditha]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Jordan}} [[Asad Ghanma]] &lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Yasser Arafat]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Abu Iyad]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Khalil Wazir|Abu Jihad]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Abu Ali Iyad]]
| commander3  =
| strength1   = 1 armored brigade;&lt;br /&gt;1 infantry brigade;&lt;br /&gt;1 paratroop battalion;&lt;br /&gt;1 engineering battalion;&lt;br /&gt;5 artillery battalions
| strength2   = {{flagicon|Palestine}} 900&lt;ref name=&quot;morris368&quot; /&gt;–1000&lt;ref name=&quot;carta-1961&quot; /&gt; guerrillas&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Jordan}} About 15,000 &lt;ref&gt;Fruchter-Ronen,I. (2008). Black September: The 1970-41 Events and their Impact on the Formation of Jordanian National Identity. ''Civil Wars'', v.10 (3), pp. 244-260. Figure on 246.&lt;/ref&gt; (1 infantry division;&lt;br /&gt;1 armored brigade)
| strength3   =
| casualties1 = 28 dead&lt;ref name=&quot;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars page 205&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;69 wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars page 205&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;4 tanks;&lt;br /&gt;2 half-tracks&lt;br /&gt;2 armored cars;&lt;br /&gt;1 aircraft
| casualties2 ='''Jordan'''&lt;br /&gt;84 dead&lt;br /&gt;250 wounded;&lt;br /&gt;4 captured;&lt;br /&gt;30 tanks&lt;br /&gt;2 aircraft
'''PLO'''&lt;br /&gt;100–200 dead; &lt;br /&gt;~100 wounded;&lt;br /&gt;120–150 captured
| casualties3 = 175 buildings destroyed
| notes       =
}}
{{Campaignbox War of Attrition}}
{{Unbalanced|date=April 2011}}
The '''Battle of Karameh''' ({{lang-ar|معركة الكرامة}}) was fought on March 21, 1968 in the town of [[Karameh]], [[Jordan]], between the [[Israel Defense Forces]] (IDF) and combined forces of the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] (PLO) and the [[Jordanian Army]]. It was planned by [[Israel]] as two concurrent raids on PLO camps, one in Karameh and one in the distant village of [[Safi, Jordan|Safi]] — codenamed '''Operation Inferno''' ({{lang-he|מבצע תופת}}) and '''Operation Asuta''' (מבצע אסותא), respectively — but the former turned into a full-scale battle,&lt;ref name=&quot;inferno&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
| last = Ben-Tzedef
| first = Eviatar
| title = Inferno at Karameh
| work = nfc
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 2008-03-24
| url = http://www.nfc.co.il/Archive/003-D-28622-00.html?tag=10-27-34
}} {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; when the Jordanian Army engaged the invaders.

The attacks were in reprisal for a series of raids by the PLO against Israel, mostly by the [[Fatah]] faction, which culminated in an Israeli school bus hitting a mine. Israel assumed that the Jordanian Army would ignore the invasion, but the latter fought alongside the [[Palestinians]] and inflicted heavy losses upon the Israeli forces. The Israelis withdrew at the end of a day's battle, having destroyed most of the Karameh camp and taken hundreds of prisoners.

Both sides declared victory. On a tactical level, the battle did end in Israel's favor&lt;ref name=&quot;Zeev Maoz page 246&quot;&gt;Zeev Maoz, Defending the Holy Land, A Critical Analysis of Israel’s Security and Foreign Policy, University of Michigan Press, 2006 @page 246&lt;/ref&gt; and the purpose of the mission was achieved.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars page 205&quot;&gt;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars, Random House New York, 1982 @ page 205&lt;/ref&gt; However, for the Palestinians it became a mythological victory that established their national claims.&lt;ref name=&quot;neff&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;assessment&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| issn = 0040-718X
| title = The Israeli Assessment
| work = Time
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 1968-12-13
| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,839651,00.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; At first, the battle was seen as unifying the [[Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan|Hashemite Jordan]] with its many Palestinian refugees and residents, as [[King Hussein]] had proclaimed &quot;I think we may reach a position where we are all [[fedayeen]].&quot; After the battle however, the PLO's strength began to grow, and Palestinians spoke openly of taking over Jordan as part of [[Palestine]]. This situation eventually led to [[Black September in Jordan]], in 1970.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot; /&gt;

==Background==
Following the seizure of [[West Bank]] from Jordan in the June 1967 [[Six-Day War]], Israel destroyed the existing [[Fatah]] networks there. Starting in early 1968 however, Fatah guerrillas began raiding Israel from bases on the Jordanian side of the river. Most of these attacks were successfully blocked by the IDF. [[Jordanian Army]] infantry and artillery units gave the Fatah squads covering fire at times, leading to frequent direct skirmishes between the IDF and the Jordanian Army. On February 14–15, Jordanian mortars hit several Israeli settlements in the [[Beit Shean Valley]] and along the [[Jordan Valley (Middle East)|Jordan Valley]]. IDF artillery and the IAF retaliated against Jordanian bases and artillery batteries, as well as the American-financed [[East Ghor Main Canal]].  As a result, thousands of Jordanian farmers fled eastwards, and [[fedayeen]] moved into the valley.  An American-sponsored ceasefire was arranged and King Hussein declared he would prevent these groups from using Jordan as a base for attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris367-368&quot;&gt;Morris (1999), pp. 367–368&lt;/ref&gt; In February, he sent twenty carloads of troops and police to order a Fatah unit to leave Karameh. When it arrived, the column found itself surrounded by men wielding machine guns; their commander said &quot;You have three minutes to decide whether you leave or die&quot;. They withdrew.&lt;ref name=brotherhood/&gt; By March, several hundred civilians lived in the camp, along with about 900 guerrillas, mostly from Fatah, and PLO leader [[Yasser Arafat]], who had his headquarters there.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris368&quot;&gt;Morris (1999), p. 368&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aharon Yariv]], Chief of the [[Military Intelligence Directorate (Israel)|Military Intelligence Directorate]], stated that a raid would damage Fatah's prestige. On the other hand, [[Israeli Foreign Minister]], [[Abba Eban]], and his chief of bureau, Gideon Rafael, being mindful of an adverse American reaction, were afraid it might result in killing innocent civilians and be a political disservice to Israel. Chief of Staff ([[Ramatkal]]) [[Haim Bar-Lev]] promised a &quot;clean action&quot;. [[Israeli Defense Minister]], [[Moshe Dayan]], asked for a &quot;principal approval&quot; for a raid but this was denied by the cabinet. He warned the other ministers that a bus might strike a mine.&lt;ref name=&quot;segev&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| last = Segev
| first = Tom
| title = It started at Karameh
| work = Haaretz
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| url = http://www.haaretz.co.il/hasite/pages/ShArt.jhtml?itemNo=947557
}} {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 18, an Israeli school bus was blown up by a mine near [[Be'er Ora]] in the [[Arabah|Arava]], killing two adults and wounding ten children.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris368&quot; /&gt; It was the 38th Fatah operation in little more than three months.&lt;ref name=telegraph/&gt; That night, the cabinet approved the attack. The U.S. tried to prevent it by forwarding Israel a message from King Hussein. [[Israeli Prime Minister]], [[Levi Eshkol]], called the cabinet in for further counseling, but only the [[National Religious Party]] leader, [[Haim-Moshe Shapira]], vocally opposed it, while [[Israeli Education Minister]], [[Zalman Aran]] opposed it but remained silent.&lt;ref name=&quot;segev&quot; /&gt;

==Prelude==

On March 4, [[Dairat al-Mukhabarat al-Ammah|Jordanian intelligence]]  began to detect Israeli activity near the border, as IDF troops began to concentrate near the [[Allenby Bridge|Allenby]] and [[Damia Bridge]]s. Jordan ordered the 1st Infantry Division to take up positions near those bridges and around Karameh.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack331-332&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), pp. 331–332&lt;/ref&gt; On March 17, Dayan warned that the Arabs were preparing for a &quot;new wave of terror,&quot; which Israel would take steps to contain if King Hussein of Jordan could not. Eshkol repeated that message to the [[Knesset]], and on the same day, Israeli Ambassador Yosef Tekoah filed two complaints with the [[United Nations]] against what he termed the Arabs' &quot;repeated acts of aggression.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;foray&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
| issn = 0040-718X
| title = Foray into Jordan
| work = Time
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 1968-03-29
| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,838079-1,00.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By March 20, Jordan had identified parts of the Israeli 7th Armored Brigade, 60th Armored Brigade, 35th Paratroop Brigade, 80th Infantry Brigade, a combat engineer battalion and five artillery battalions between those bridges. The Jordanians assumed the Israelis were planning an attack with a drive on [[Amman]], and the army took up positions near the bridges, with the 60th Armored Brigade joining the 1st Infantry Division. Jordan also added most of its armored car, antitank and artillery units to the 1st Infantry Division. The total firepower was 105 [[Patton tank]]s and 88 artillery pieces. The infantry divisions were deployed near the bridges, each with a tank company. The artillery was mostly deployed on the higher Jordan Valley ridges overlooking Karameh for topological advantage.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack331-332&quot; /&gt;

The Israeli forces amounted to less than a brigade of armor, an infantry brigade, a paratroop battalion, an engineering battalion and five battalions of artillery. The units were divided into four task forces. The largest of these was to cross the Allenby Bridge and reach Karameh from the south; a second one was to cross the Damiyah Bridge, and reach Karameh from the north, thus completing a pincer move. Meanwhile, paratroopers were to be lifted by helicopters into the town while the fourth force would make a diversionary attack at [[King Abdullah Bridge]] to draw the Jordanian forces from Karameh and to cover the main attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack331-332&quot; /&gt;

Prior to the attack, the [[Israeli Air Force]] (IAF) dropped leaflets telling the Jordanian army that Israel had no intention to hurt them, and that they should not intervene;&lt;ref name=&quot;iaf&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = Operation Inferno
| work = iaf.org.il
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| url = http://www.iaf.org.il/Templates/FlightLog/FlightLog.aspx?lang=HE&amp;lobbyID=40&amp;folderID=48&amp;subfolderID=321&amp;docfolderID=828&amp;docID=6835&amp;docType=EVENT
}} {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; the leaflets went unheeded.  [[Time (magazine)|Time magazine]] reported the fedayeen had been warned in advance by Egyptian intelligence, and most of the 2,000 Arab commandos who used Karamah as a training base had pulled back into the surrounding hills to snipe at the Israelis. Some 200 guerrillas stayed inside to defend the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;foray&quot;/&gt;  Later, Arafat's deputy, [[Abu Iyad]], claimed in his memoirs that he and Arafat had been tipped off about the Israeli attack by Jordanian officers, who learned it from the [[CIA]].&lt;ref name=&quot;morris368-369&quot;&gt;Morris (1999), pp. 368–369&lt;/ref&gt;

==The battle==
[[File:Karame battle.png|thumb|250px|Map showing the Jordanian positions (green) and the Israeli advance (blue)]]
At 5:30&amp;nbsp;AM on March 21, the Israeli forces attacked simultaneously on the three bridges.&lt;ref name=&quot;dupuy352&quot;&gt;Dupuy (2002), p. 352&lt;/ref&gt; Combat engineers built a [[pontoon bridge]] in the north and the troops crossed the river.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack332-333&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), pp. 332–333&lt;/ref&gt; The Israeli spearheads pushed across the Hussein Bridge&lt;!-- Which Bridge is that? it is not on the map --&gt; and were advancing towards Shunat Nimreen. At 6:30&amp;nbsp;AM, Israeli helicopters started landing the bulk of the paratrooper battalion north of Karameh.&lt;ref name=&quot;dupuy353&quot;&gt;Dupuy (2002), p. 353&lt;/ref&gt; An Israeli aircraft was supposed to drop leaflets addressed to Fatah after the paratroopers had surrounded the town. However, due to difficult weather conditions, the helicopters flying the paratroopers arrived twenty minutes too late.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloody&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = Bloody battle at Karameh
| work = Sayeret Zanhanim
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| url = http://www.gal-ed.co.il/zanchanim-palsar/show_item.asp?itemId=55&amp;levelId=59462&amp;itemType=0
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}} {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When the southern task force began their drive north towards Karameh, they encountered a Jordanian infantry brigade supported by armor, artillery and antitank weapons. The Israeli Air Force launched airstrikes, but was only able to inflict minor damage on the dug-in Jordanians. Fighting from their entrenched positions, the Jordanians repelled several Israeli assaults.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack332-333&quot; /&gt; In the south, Jordanian artillery shelling prevented the Israelis from erecting another pontoon bridge on the site of the Abdullah bridge, halting the Israeli advance there.&lt;ref name=&quot;carta-1961&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|encyclopedia= Carta's Atlas of Israel|year=1980|publisher=[[Carta (publisher)|Carta]]|location=[[Jerusalem]], [[Israel]]|editor=Evyatar Nur|author=Wallach, Jeuda|coauthors=Ayalon, Avraham; Yitzhaki, Aryeh|title=Operation Inferno|volume= Volume 2 — The Second Decade 1961–1971|pages=122}} {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gonen's force spread in three directions from Shuna: One or more companies drove north to Karameh, An infantry battalion and a tank battalion moved east to block the Salt road, and another infantry battalion moved south to assist the force trying to break across the Abdullah Bridge. Gonen later claimed that the action on the Abdullah bridge was merely a diversion. Meanwhile, the force that crossed the Damiya Bridge established itself on the east bank. Engineers began constructing a new bridge and the force advanced east to the Musri junction, where it was supposed turned south to Karameh.

The force driving on Karameh via the Allenby bridge broke through and proceeded to the town. They reached Karameh shortly before 7:00.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris369&quot;&gt;Morris(1999), p. 369&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the paratroopers and armor drove north to operate in the Fatah camp.  The paratroopers destroyed most of the camp; many of the Palestinians, including Arafat, fled eastward.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack333&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), p. 333&lt;/ref&gt;  By 8:00 the Israeli forces had taken control of the town, which turned out to be a bigger PLO base than the Israelis originally thought.&lt;ref name=&quot;herzog205&quot;&gt;Herzog (1982), p. 205&lt;/ref&gt; At this point, the Damiya force held Musri, but could not advance south, as the advance was repulsed by the northern brigade of the Jordanian 1st Division. The paratroopers at Karameh were met with resistance by Fatah commandos and Jordanian regulars supported by Jordanian artillery. The paratroopers suffered heavy losses, and were joined by the northern column of the Hussein Bridge force. The combined force was engaged in heavy fighting against the central brigade of the 1st division and a number of Fatah fighters. The rest of the Hussein Bridge force was blocked to the east and south of Shuna by elements of the 1st Division's central and southern brigades and by a tank battalion from Salt.&lt;ref name=&quot;dupuy353&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Karama Battle 4.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Jordanian artillery battery at Karameh, 21 March 1968.]]
A small force of Israeli infantry and armor tried to protect the right flank of the forces invading from the south from attacks by the Jordanian forces deployed near the King Abdullah bridge. The Jordanians attacked with some armor, but the Israelis put up resistance, and the battle turned into a stalemate.

A large force of Israeli infantry and armor went east to block the road from [[Salt, Jordan|Salt]] to the Allenby bridge, and they encountered the Jordanian 60th Armored Brigade which tried to join the defense of Karameh. In the resulting battle, the Jordanians lost eight Patton tanks without destroying any Israeli tanks, and withdrew to the hills, where they dug in and continued to fire down on the Israelis. The Israeli Air Force launched airstrikes against Jordanian armor and artillery positions, but was unable to stop the firing.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack333&quot;/&gt; Within the next two hours, Israeli artillery fire and airstrikes were launched against Jordanian defenses on the Musri-Karameh road, the Salt road, and east of Abdullah Bridge. The Israelis also consolidated their hold on Karameh with of airstrikes and artillery, and began demolishing the camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;dupuy354&quot;&gt;Dupuy (2002), p. 354&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 175 houses were blown up.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris369&quot; /&gt;

Meanwhile, Operation Asuta was mounted against a few smaller guerrilla bases south of the [[Dead Sea]], near Safi, where the school bus had struck the mine. About twenty Jordanian soldiers and policemen and twenty Fatah fighters were killed, and twenty-seven were taken prisoner. The Israelis suffered no casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris369&quot; /&gt;

Frustrated in their hopes of entrapping the entire PLO force, the Israelis quickly pulled out, but had to fight their way back to Israeli territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;foray&quot;/&gt; At 11:00 the Israelis began to withdraw, with [[Sikorsky H-34]] helicopters evacuating the troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;iaf&quot;/&gt; Because orders came down to recover as many vehicles as possible, they only completed their withdrawal by 20:40.&lt;ref name=&quot;carta-1961&quot; /&gt; 

===Casualties===
{{see also|Israeli casualties of war|Palestinian casualties of war}}
Casualties estimates vary:

* '''Israel''': [[Chaim Herzog]] and [[Kenneth Pollack]] estimate 28 dead and 69 wounded;&lt;ref name=&quot;herzog205&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack334&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), p. 334&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shabtai Teveth]] gives 32 killed and 70 wounded out of a force of 1,000 soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Teveth, Shabtai (1969/1970) ''The Cursed Blessing. The story of Israel's occupation of the West Bank.'' Weidenfield &amp; Nicolson. SBN 297 00150 7. Translated from Hebrew by Myra Bank. Page 261.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Benny Morris]] writes that Israel lost 33 dead and 161 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris369&quot; /&gt; Israel also lost four tanks, three half-tracks, two armored cars and a [[113 Squadron (Israel)|113 Squadron]] [[Dassault Ouragan]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack334&quot; /&gt; although the pilot succeeded in parachuting to safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;herzog205&quot; /&gt; A [[Dassault Mirage III|Mirage]] had to crash land.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris369&quot; /&gt;

* '''Jordan''': [[Zeev Maoz]] and [[Benny Morris|Morris]] cite a figure of some 84 Jordanian soldiers killed and another 250 wounded. Four were captured. 30 tanks were destroyed. Maoz notes that two Jordanian aircraft were shot down.&lt;ref&gt;Zeev Maoz, Defending the Holy Land: A Critical Analysis of Israel's Security &amp; Foreign ... University of Michigan Press (2006) 244-246&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''PLO''': Herzog: 200 dead, 150 captured; Morris: 156 dead, 141 captured;&lt;ref name=&quot;morris369&quot; /&gt; Pollack: 100 dead, 100 wounded, 120–150 captured.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack334&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), p. 334&lt;/ref&gt; According to Morris, a further 20 PLO guerillas were killed and 27 captured during the corresponding [[Operation Asuta]]. Teveth states 170 killed and 130 taken prisoner.

===Israeli command structure===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;4&quot;|[[Israel Defense Forces]] — Lieutenant General [[Haim Bar-Lev]]
|-
!colspan=&quot;4&quot;|[[Central Command (Israel)|Central Command]] — Major General ([[Aluf]]) [[Uzi Narkiss]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|[[80th Brigade]] (elements)&lt;ref name=&quot;carta-1961&quot; /&gt;
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Colonel [[Rafael Eitan]]
|Tovia Force (reduced battalion)
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|Uzi Force (reduced battalion)
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;|[[7th Armoured Brigade (Israel)|7th Brigade]]&lt;ref name=&quot;carta-1961&quot; /&gt;
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;|Colonel [[Shmuel Gonen]]
|Rotem Company
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|Plada Company
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|Shimshi Company
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|Eitan Platoon
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;|[[Paratroopers Brigade]] (35th)&lt;ref name=&quot;paratroopers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.paratroops.org.il/siteArticle.asp?aid=56&amp;cid=64|title=Between the Wars — Jordan|accessdate=2008-09-13}} {{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;|Colonel [[Danny Mat]]
|890th Battalion
|Lieutenant Colonel [[Dan Shomron]]
|-
|50th Battalion
|Lieutenant Colonel [[Tubi Shapira]]
|-
|202th Battalion (elements)
|Lieutenant Colonel [[Zvi Bar]]
|-
|Paratroopers Reconnaissance Unit
|Captain [[Matan Vilnai]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;9&quot;|[[Israeli Air Force|Air Force]] (elements)&lt;ref name=&quot;iaf&quot; /&gt;
|rowspan=&quot;9&quot;|Major General (Aluf)&lt;br /&gt;[[Mordechai Hod]]
|[[116 Squadron (Israel)|116 &quot;Flying Wing&quot; Squadron]] (leaflet drop)
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[101 Squadron (Israel)|101 &quot;First Fighter&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[105 Squadron (Israel)|105 &quot;Scorpion&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[110 Squadron (Israel)|110 &quot;Northern Knights&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[113 Squadron (Israel)|113 &quot;Hornet&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[117 Squadron (Israel)|117 &quot;First Jet&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[119 Squadron (Israel)|119 &quot;Bat&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[124 Squadron (Israel)|124 &quot;Rolling Sword&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[114 Squadron (Israel)|114 &quot;Night Leaders/Super Frelon&quot; Squadron]]
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Combat Engineering Corps]] (elements)
|colspan=&quot;3&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|-
|[[Artillery Corps (Israel)|Artillery Corps]] (elements)
|colspan=&quot;3&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|}

==Aftermath==
[[File:Karama aftermath 5.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The destroyed Karameh camp after the battle]]
Israel claimed to have accomplished its objective of destroying the Fatah camp,&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack333&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;herzog205&quot;/&gt; and on a tactical level, the battle did indeed end in Israel's favor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zeev Maoz page 246&quot;/&gt; &quot;The Karama operation exposed the vulnerability of PLO units deployed along the Jordan River and so they moved their concentrations up into the mountains. This imposed additional strains on them and made their operations into the West Bank even more involved and difficult than they had been hithero.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars page 205&quot;/&gt; Politically however, Israel was heavily condemned by the world opinion. [[United States Ambassador to the United Nations|U.S. Ambassador to the UN]], [[Arthur Goldberg]], said &quot;We believe that the military counteractions such as those which have just taken place, on a scale out of proportion to the acts of violence that preceded it, are greatly to be deplored.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;foray&quot;/&gt; US Ambassador to Israel, [[Walworth Barbour]], said that in twenty years time, a historian would write that day down as the beginning of the destruction of Israel. Eban reported the Ambassabor's statement to the cabinet, and [[Menachem Begin]] said such an utterance must not be cited in a cabinet meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;segev&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Karama aftermath 4.jpg|thumb|left|widthpx|Jordanian soldiers on an abandoned Israeli half-track]]
The battle of Karameh did provide Fatah with a propaganda boost.&lt;ref name=&quot;segev&quot;/&gt; [[Gideon Rafael]] later said that &quot;The operation gave an enormous lift to Yasser Arafat's Fatah organization and irrevocably implanted the Palestine problem onto the international agenda, no longer as a humanitarian issue of homeless refugees, but as a claim to Palestinian statehood&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;neff&quot;/&gt; [[Uzi Narkis]], who commanded the operation, resigned as chief of the [[Central Command (Israel)|Central Command]] for a position in the [[Jewish Agency]] shortly after the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;inferno&quot;/&gt;

Jordan claimed to have won the battle and stopped an Israeli drive on Amman.&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack333-334&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), pp. 333–334&lt;/ref&gt; Hussein said on television after the battle, &quot;I think we may reach a position where we are all [[fedayeen]]&quot;, while Arafat said &quot;What we have done is to make the world... realize that the Palestinian is no longer refugee number so and so, but the member of a people who hold the reins of their own destiny and are in a position to determine their own future&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;neff&quot;/&gt; Palestinians and Arabs generally considered the battle a psychological victory over the IDF, which had been seen as 'invincible' until then, and recruitment to guerilla units soared.&lt;ref&gt;A.I.Dawisha, ''Arab Nationalism in the Twentieth Century: From Triumph to Despair,'' Princeton University Press, 2003 p.258&lt;/ref&gt; Fatah reported that 5,000 volunteers applied to join within 48 hours of the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;neff&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
| issue = March 1998
| pages = 87–88
| last = Neff
| first = Donald
| title = Battle of Karameh Establishes Claim of Palestinian Statehood
| work = Washington Report on Middle East Affairs
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| url = http://www.washington-report.org/backissues/0398/9803087.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; By late March, there were nearly 20,000 fedayeen in Jordan.&lt;ref name=&quot;brotherhood&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
| issn = 0040-718X
| title = A Brotherhood of Terror
| work = Time
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 1968-03-29
| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,838080-1,00.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:Jordanian soldier.jpg|thumb|widthpx|A monument in Karameh commemorating the Jordanian fighters.]]Iraq and Syria offered training programs for several thousand guerrillas. The [[Persian Gulf states]], led by [[Kuwait]], raised money for them through a 5% tax on the salaries of their tens of thousands of resident Palestinian workers, and a fund drive in [[Lebanon]] raised $500,000 from [[Beirut]] alone. The Palestinian organizations began to guarantee a lifetime support for the families of all guerrillas killed in action.&lt;ref name=&quot;brotherhood&quot;/&gt; Within a year after the battle, Fatah had branches in about eighty countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurz56&quot;&gt;Kurz (2006), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the battle, Fatah began to engage in communal projects to achieve popular affiliation.&lt;ref name=&quot;kurz55&quot;&gt;Kurz (2006), p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; The battle of Karameh and the subsequent increase in the PLO's strength are considered to have been important catalysts for the 1970 events of [[Black September in Jordan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| title = 1968: Karameh and the Palestinian revolt
| work = Telegraph
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 2002-05-16
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/1400177/1968-Karameh-and-the-Palestinian-revolt.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pollack335&quot;&gt;Pollack (2002), p. 335&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
* {{Cite book
| publisher = Military Book Club
| last = Dupuy
| first = Trevor N.
| title = Elusive Victory: The Arab-Israeli Wars, 1947-1974
| year = 2002
}}
* {{Cite book
| publisher = Vintage
| isbn = 1400079632
| last = Herzog
| first = Chaim
| coauthors = Shlomo Gazit
| title = The Arab-Israeli Wars: War and Peace in the Middle East
| date = 2005-07-12
| page = 560
}}
* {{Cite book
| publisher = Sussex Academic Press
| isbn = 978-1-84519-032-3
| last = Kurz
| first = Anat N.
| title = Fatah and the Politics of Violence: The Institutionalization of a Popular Struggle
| date = 2006-01-30
| page = 228
}}
* {{Cite book
| publisher = Vintage
| isbn = 978-0-679-74475-7
| last = Morris
| first = Benny
| title = Righteous Victims: A History of the Zionist-Arab Conflict, 1881–2001
| date = 2001-08
| page = 800
}}
* {{Cite book
| publisher = Bison Books
| isbn = 978-0-8032-8783-9
| last = Pollack
| first = Kenneth M.
| title = Arabs at War: Military Effectiveness, 1948–1991
| date = 2004-09-01
| page = 717
}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{cite web
| title = S/PV.1406 of 23 March 1968 — The United Nations discussion on the battle
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| url = http://domino.un.org/unispal.nsf/59c118f065c4465b852572a500625fea/e51eb57a95fd2c72052567fb0053748f!OpenDocument
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
* {{Cite news
| title = Jordan celebrates the 31st anniversary of al-Karamah battle
| work = Arabic News
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 1999-03-22
| url = http://www.arabicnews.com/ansub/Daily/Day/990322/1999032227.html
}}
* {{Cite video
| title = The Karameh action, from the documentary &quot;The Pillar of Fire&quot;
| accessdate = 2008-09-03
| date = 2008-03-12
| time = 140&amp;nbsp;seconds
| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R06eBN8WXj4
}} {{he icon}}

{{Israeli–Palestinian conflict}}
{{Arab–Israeli conflict}}

{{coord|31|57|05.76|N|35|34|48.75|E|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Karameh}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1968]]
[[Category:War of Attrition]]
[[Category:Battles involving Jordan]]

[[ar:معركة الكرامة]]
[[de:Schlacht von Karame]]
[[fa:نبرد کرامه]]
[[fr:Bataille de Karameh]]
[[he:פעולת כראמה]]
[[no:Slaget om Karameh]]
[[ru:Сражение при Караме]]
[[fi:Karamehin taistelu]]
[[tr:Karameh Muharebesi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
