<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="730229" ns="0" title="Digital gold currency"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{POV-check|date=May 2009}}

'''Digital gold currency''' (or '''DGC''') is a form of [[electronic money]] based on ounces of [[gold]]. It is a kind of [[representative money]], like a US paper [[gold certificate]] at the time (from 1873 to 1933) that these were exchangeable for gold on demand. The typical [[unit of account]] for such currency is the [[gold gram]] or the [[troy ounce]], although other units such as the [[gold dinar]] are sometimes used.  DGCs are backed by gold through unallocated or allocated gold storage.  

Digital gold currencies are issued by a number of companies, each of which provides a system that enables users to pay each other in units that hold the same value as [[gold bullion]].  These competing providers issue independent [[currency]].

==Features==
=== Universal currency ===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2009}}
Proponents claim that DGC offers a truly global and borderless [[world currency]] system which is independent of [[exchange rate]] variations and political manipulation. Gold, silver, platinum and palladium each have recognized international currency codes under [[ISO 4217]]. 
===Asset protection===
Unlike [[fractional-reserve banking]], DGCs hold 100% of clients' funds in reserve as gold, silver, and/or platinum, which can be exchanged via digital certificates. Proponents of DGC systems say that deposits are protected against [[inflation]], [[devaluation]] and other economic risks inherent in [[fiat currency|fiat currencies]]. These risks include the [[monetary policy]] of countries or territories, which are said by proponents to be harmful to the value of paper currency.

===Bullion investing===
{{Main|Gold as an investment|Silver as an investment}}

All of the other digital gold currency systems can be used to buy, hold, and sell precious metals, but do not promote themselves as an &quot;investment&quot;, as this implies an anticipated return.

=== Exchanging national currency ===
Some providers do not sell DGC directly to clients. For those DGCs, e-currency must be bought and sold via a [[digital currency exchanger]].  

Currency exchangers accept payment in national currencies by a variety of methods, including [[wire transfer|Bank Wire]], Direct Deposit, Cheque, Money Order. Some exchangers also sell and fund pre-paid debit cards to make it easier for their clientele to convert DGC into an easily spendable form of national currency.

DGCs are known as [[private currency]] as they are not issued by [[government]]s.

=== Non-reversible transactions ===
Unlike the [[credit card]] industry, digital gold currency issuers generally do not have services to dispute or reverse charges. So, reversing transactions, even in case of a legitimate error, unauthorized use, or failure of a vendor to supply goods is difficult, if not impossible. This means that using digital gold currency is more akin to a [[cash]] transaction, while [[PayPal]] transfers, for example, could be considered more similar to credit card transactions.

The advantage of this arrangement is that the operating costs of the digital currency system are greatly reduced by not having to resolve payment disputes. Additionally, it allows digital gold currency transactions to clear instantly, making the funds available immediately to the recipient. By contrast, credit cards, checks, ACH and other reversible payment methods generally have a &quot;clearing time&quot; of 72 hours or more.

==Risks==

As with all financial media, there are several types of risk inherent to the use of DGCs: management risk, [[political risk]], [[data security]] and exchange risk.

===Management and political risks===
DGCs, like all financial institutions and public securities, have a layer of risk in the form of the management of the issuing institution.  Controls aimed to limit management risk are called &quot;[[governance]]&quot;.

All other DGC providers operate under self-regulation. DGC providers are not banks and therefore not subject to many [[bank regulation]]s that pertain to fractional reserve lending as they do not engage in lending. However, DGCs do provide a method for transferring currency from one person to another, and therefore may fall under regulations pertaining to money transmitting in various jurisdictions.

The [[Global Digital Currency Association]] (GDCA), which was founded in 2002, is a non-profit association of online currency operators, exchangers, merchants and users.  The GDCA is an example of the DGC industry's attempt at self-regulation. On their website they claim their goal is to &quot;further the interests of the industry as a whole and help with fighting fraud and other illegal activities, arbitrate disputes and act as escrow agent when and where required.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://gdcaonline.com/index.html Global Digital Currency Association Ltd.]&lt;/ref&gt; Of the current DGC providers, [[Pecunix]], [[Liberty Reserve]] and eight others have become members of the association. It costs one gram of gold to file a complaint if you are not a member, and the list of filable complaints is not exhaustive. Their domain name is registered anonymously through [http://domainsbyproxy.com domains by proxy], see [http://www.whois.net/whois_new.cgi?d=gdcaonline&amp;tld=com whois].

====OS-Gold, Standard Reserve and INTGold====
Several companies claiming to be Digital Gold Currencies sprang up and failed between 1999 and 2004, such as OS-Gold,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;OS-Gold&quot;, The Gold Economy Magazine, September 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Standard Reserve&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Why Standard Reserve Failed&quot;, The Gold Economy Magazine, May 2003&lt;/ref&gt; and INTGold.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;INTGold&quot;, The Gold Economy Magazine, September 2003&lt;/ref&gt; All these companies failed because the principals diverted deposits for other purposes instead of holding them in the form of gold. In each of these cases, account holders lost several million dollars worth of gold when the &quot;institution&quot; failed.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

====e-gold and 1mdc====
Following April 27, 2007, the [[United States Department of Justice]] forced [[e-gold]] to liquidate some 10 to 20 million dollars worth of e-gold, and is attempting to bring a case against e-gold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/pr/2007/April/07_crm_301.html|title=Digital Currency Business E-Gold Indicted for Money Laundering and Illegal Money Transmitting|date=April 27, 2007|publisher=US Department of Justice|accessdate=2008-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; e-gold has committed to counter what its founders have declared to be groundless allegations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.e-gold.com/letter3.html|title=e-gold  Founder Denies Criminal Charges|date=April 30, 2007|publisher=e-gold|accessdate=2008-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[1mdc]] was backed by e-gold, so events that affected e-gold also affected 1mdc. Once e-gold Ltd. was instructed by the US government to freeze and liquidate all 1mdc accounts, 1mdc became insolvent by default along with all other e-gold accounts seized in the April 27 action.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

====e-Bullion====
As of August 2008 Jim Fayed of [[e-Bullion]] is in United States Federal custody where he faces felony charges of conducting unlicensed money transactions and the murder of his business partner.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

As of January 2010 e-Bullion is closed for business and the website unavailable.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

As of June 2011 e-Bullion owner James Fayed was found guilty of murder in the State of California, and sentenced to death.

===Data security===
Digital Gold Systems are completely dependent on electronic storage and transmission of account ownership information. Therefore the security of a given digital currency account is dependent upon the security of the Issuer as well as the security of the Account Holder's computer.

While the Digital Gold Issuers employ data security experts to protect their systems, the average account holder's computer is poorly protected against malware (trojans, worms, and viruses) that can be used to intercept information that could be used to access the user's DGC account.  Therefore the most common attacks on digital currency systems are directed against account holder's computer through the use of [[malicious spam]], [[phishing]] and other methods.

Issuers have taken quite different approaches to this problem.  E-gold basically places the entire responsibility on the shoulders of the user, and uses a user-name and password authentication system that is weak and highly vulnerable to interception by malware. (Though it is the most common authentication method used by online banks.)  The &quot;not our problem&quot; approach to user security has negatively contributed to e-gold's public image, as not a few e-gold accounts have been hacked and swept clean by attackers..{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

e-Bullion offers account holders a &quot;Cryptocard&quot; security token that changes the passphrase with each logon, but charges the account holder USD $99.50 for the token. E-bullion does not require customers to use the Cryptocard, so account holders who choose not to get one may suffer from the same security issues as e-gold customers.

[[Pecunix]] devised a unique rotating key system that provides many of the benefits of a security token without requiring the user to buy one. Pecunix also supports the use of [[Pretty Good Privacy|PGP signature]]s to access an account, which is probably the strongest of all authentication methods.

===Exchange risk===
Digital gold currency is a form of [[representative money]] as it directly represents gold metal on deposit or in custody. This depends on the issuer.  Most issuers have the gold on deposit - i.e., the issuer will redeem the digital currency obligation with physical metal.  Just as the exchange rates of national currencies fluctuate against each other, the exchange rates of DGCs fluctuate against national currencies, which is reflected by the price of gold in a particular currency. This creates exchange risk for any account holder, in the same way one would experience exchange risk by holding a bank account in a foreign currency. 

Some DGC holders make use of the digital currency for daily monetary transactions, even though most of their normal income and expenses are denominated in the national currency of their home country.  Fluctuations in the value of gold against their national currency can create some confusion and difficulty for new users as they see the &quot;value&quot; of their DGC account fluctuate in terms of their native currency.

In contrast to exchange risk, caused by gold's fluctuation against national currency, the [[purchasing power]] of gold (and therefore DGCs) is measured by its fluctuation against other commodities, goods and services. Since gold has historically been the refuge of choice in times of inflation or economic hardship, the purchasing power of gold becomes stronger during times of negative sentiment in the markets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/oilRpt/idUSN2238876720080122 | work=Reuters | title=US gold bounces on inflation fears, safe haven bid | first=Frank | last=Tang | date=January 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to this speculative interference, there are times when purchasing power has also declined. For example, in 2007&amp;ndash;2008, gold volatility closely tracked the run-up in oil prices.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;TedBits&quot;, Ty Andros, Trader View, April, 2008, http://news.goldseek.com/GoldSeek/1207289100.php&lt;/ref&gt;

==Providers==
Comparison of operating DGCs ({{As of|2011|2|lc=on}}):
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:92%&quot;
! Digital gold currency
! Date&lt;br&gt;founded
! [[Financial regulation|Financially regulated]]
! [[Global Digital Currency Association|GDCA]]&lt;br&gt;member
! Bullion&lt;br&gt;stored
! Bullion audit&lt;br&gt;trail
! Number&lt;br&gt;of user&lt;br&gt;accounts
! [[Digital currency exchanger|DCE]] transfers accepted
! [[Wire transfer]]s accepted
! Annual storage fee
! Processing fee&lt;br&gt;(when receiving from another user)
|-
| [[e-dinar]]
| 2000
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| 1%
| 1% (with max. 0.015 gold dinar)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.e-dinar.com/html/4_4.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Pecunix]]
| 2002
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| 2,777 oz gold
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| 0%
| 0.15 - 0.50% (with min. 0.0001 - max. 3.0 gold grams)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pecunix.com/money.refined...ind.feestructure&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|-
| iGolder
| 2005
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| x%
| 1% 
|-
|-
| Liberty Reserve
| 2004
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| x%
| 1% 
|-
|-
| gbullion
| 2007
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| x%
| 1% 
|-
|-
| [[GoldMoney]]
| 2001
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| 18tn Au&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goldmoney.com/report-monthly.html Monthly Audit - Allocated Gold - GoldMoney.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| 19.114
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| 0.18%
| 0% 
|-
|-
| [[e-gold]]
| 1999
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| Undisclosed
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{Y}}
| blocked by USG
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| align=&quot;center&quot;| {{N}}
| 1%
| 1% 
|-
|}

==Criticisms==

DGC providers and exchangers have been accused of being a medium for fraudulent [[high-yield investment program]] (HYIP) schemes. In January 2006, ''[[BusinessWeek]]'' reported that [[ShadowCrew]], an online gang, used the [[e-gold]] system in a massive [[identity theft]] and fraud scheme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/06_02/b3966094.htm|title=Gold Rush|date=January 9, 2006|accessdate=2008-01-22|publisher=Business Week}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional banks are also used frequently for such fraud. Allegations that e-gold is a safe medium for crime and fraud are strongly denied by its Chairman and founder, Dr. [[Douglas Jackson (businessman)|Douglas Jackson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.e-gold.com/letter.html|title=Letter from Dr. Douglas Jackson; Chairman, e-gold, Ltd.|date=6 January 2006|accessdate=2008-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Further, it can be argued that such problems lay with the source of the information or monies, rather than the location of storage of such ill-gotten gains.  In other words, it would be difficult to claim the bank as villain when the criminal activity occurred by other parties away from the storage location.

Many DGC providers do not disclose the amount of bullion stored (see table), or do not allow independent external bullion audits, raising concerns that such companies do not maintain a 100% [[reserve ratio]], or that their currency is entirely virtual and not backed by physical gold at all.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

== Cultural references ==
*The novel ''[[Cryptonomicon]]'' by [[Neal Stephenson]] uses the idea of a gold-based digital currency in combination with strong [[cryptography]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Cryptonomicon |last= Stephenson |first=Neal |year=2002 |publisher=Avon Books |location=New York |isbn=0-06-051280-6 |pages=387, 476–477, 500, 659}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The novel ''Alongside Night'' by [[J. Neil Schulman]] features several types of competing DGCs.{{Nonspecific|date=April 2010}}
*The novel ''[[Molon Labe!]]'' by [[Kenneth W. Royce]] features a gold based digital accounting system very similar to DGCs.{{Nonspecific|date=April 2010}}
*The novel ''Minerva'' by [[Robert P. Murphy]] features DGCs prominently.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Minerva | last=Murphy | first=Robert P. | year=2004 | publisher=strike-the-root.com | url=http://www.strike-the-root.com/content/minerva-chapter-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The novel ''The Cryptographer'' by [[Tobias Hill]] is centered around Soft Gold, a DGC.{{Nonspecific|date=April 2010}}

==See also==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;

* [[Digital currency exchanger]]
* [[Digital gold bug]]
* [[e-gold]]
* [[Bitcoin]]
* [[Full-reserve banking]]
* [[Gold as an investment]]
* [[Gold exchange-traded fund]]
* [[Gold standard]]
* [[Silver as an investment]]
* [[Gold to Go]] (Automated banking machine)
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

&lt;!-- Spam or personal referral links will be removed immediately --&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Digital Gold Currency}}
[[Category:Digital gold currencies| ]]

[[fr:Devise en or numérique]]
[[zh:数字黄金货币]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
