<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7317420" ns="0" title="Indian Naval Air Arm"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= Indian Naval Air Arm
|image=
|caption=
|start_date= 1961
|country= [[India]]
|allegiance=
|branch=
|type=
|role=
|size= 5,000 personnel &lt;br&gt; ~240 aircraft 
|command_structure= [[Indian Navy]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|current_commander=
|current_commander_label=
|ceremonial_chief=
|ceremonial_chief_label=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|colonel_of_the_regiment_label=
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label= Crest
|identification_symbol_2= [[Image:IAF-roundel.svg|60px|Roundel]]
|identification_symbol_2_label= [[Roundel]]
|identification_symbol_3= [[Image:IAF-Fin-Flash.svg|60px|The IN Fin Flash]]
|identification_symbol_3_label= Fin flash
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_attack= [[BAE Sea Harrier]]
|aircraft_bomber= [[Tupolev Tu-142]]
|aircraft_[[Airborne Early Warning]]= [[Kamov Ka-31]]
|aircraft_fighter= [[Mikoyan MiG-29K]], [[BAE Sea Harrier]]
|aircraft_interceptor= [[Mikoyan MiG-29K]]
|aircraft_recon= [[Ilyushin Il-38]]
|aircraft_patrol= [[Ilyushin Il-38]] 
|aircraft_trainer= [[HAL HPT-32 Deepak]], [[HAL Kiran]]
|aircraft_transport= [[Dornier Do 228]]
}}

The '''Indian Naval Air Arm''' is part of the [[Indian Navy]] which is tasked to provide an aircraft carrier based strike capability, fleet air defence, maritime reconnaissance, and anti-submarine warfare. To undertake these tasks, the Indian Navy employs an aircraft carrier and a variety of manned and unmanned aircraft and helicopters. The [[INS Viraat]] carries a complement of [[Sea Harrier]] aircraft and Kamov, Sea King, Chetak and Dhruv helicopters. The [[Kamov Ka-27|Kamov Ka-31]] provides [[AEW]] support for the fleet. In the anti-submarine role, the [[Westland Sea King|Sea King]], Ka-28 and the indigenously-built [[HAL Dhruv]] are used. The [[MARCOS (India)|MARCOS]] use Sea King and HAL Dhruv helicopters while conducting operations. Reconnaissance operations are carried out by [[Tupolev Tu-142]]s, [[Ilyushin Il-38]]s, [[Dornier Do 228]]s and also by [[HAL Chetak]] helicopters. The [[Unmanned aerial vehicle|UAV]] arm consists of around 30 UAVs, such as [[IAI Heron|Heron]] and Searcher-IIs, that are operated from ships and shore for better surveillance. The Indian Navy also maintains an aerobatic display team, the [[Sagar Pawan]]. The Sagar Pawan team will be replacing the present [[HAL Kiran|HJT-16 Kiran]] with the [[HAL HJT-36|HJT-36]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://indian-navy.101center.net/ 101 Center]&lt;/ref&gt; The HJT-36 will also be used in training pilots.

== History ==
The first naval air station, [[INS Garuda Kochi|INS ''Garuda'']], was inaugurated in Cochin on 11 May 1953.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=zLdeAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=INS+Garuda&amp;dq=INS+Garuda&amp;ei=c6RBSMHpD4TqiQGW0JmJBQ&amp;pgis=1 ''Military Year-book'' - India 1965]&lt;/ref&gt; This went hand-in-hand with the commissioning of the No.550 Squadron,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Timeline.html ''Bharat-Rakshak.com'' - Indian Navy Timeline - &quot;11 May 1953: First Naval Air Station, INS Garuda, inaugurated at Cochin. No.550 Squadron (consisting of Sealand and Firefly aircraft) commissioned&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; utilizing [[Short Sealand]] aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/wbgoanam01.html ''Naval Aviation Museum, Dabolim, Goa, India'' - http://www.warbirdsofindia.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Fairey Firefly]] aircraft&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/wbgoanam02.html ''Naval Aviation Museum, Dabolim, Goa, India'' - http://www.warbirdsofindia.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

1960 saw the No.300 White Tigers Squadron,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Timeline.html ''Bharat-Rakshak.com'' - Indian Navy Timeline - &quot;1960: No.300 White Tigers Squadron (consisting of Sea Hawk aircraft) commissioned.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; consisting of Sea Hawks&lt;ref name=&quot;warbirdsofindia.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/wbgoanam03.html ''Naval Aviation Museum, Dabolim, Goa, India'' - http://www.warbirdsofindia.com]&lt;/ref&gt; aircraft being commissioned.

In the very next year (1961), [[INS Vikrant|INS ''Vikrant'']] (formerly HMS ''Hercules'') was acquired by the Indian Navy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=zLdeAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=INS+Vikrant&amp;dq=INS+Vikrant&amp;ei=j6tBSJy0GZOcjgGYtqCIBQ&amp;pgis=1 ''Military Year-book'' - India 1965]&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Vikrant'''s initial airwing consisted of British [[Hawker Sea Hawk]] fighter-bombers and a French [[Breguet Alize|Alize]] anti-submarine aircraft. On 18 May 1961, the first jet landed on board, piloted by Lieutenant (later Admiral) R H Tahiliani. That year, the No.310 Cobras Squadron (consisting of Alize aircraft &lt;ref name=&quot;warbirdsofindia.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=PY8CvlKC7kgC&amp;pg=PA159&amp;dq=310+cobras+squadron&amp;ei=G61BSLPKHoa4jgHD1tiIBQ&amp;sig=FuSTnuxVRv1ZP7niCgxDweECKXM ''Aircraft Carriers: The World's Greatest Naval Vessels and Their Aircraft'' By Richard Jones,  Chris Bishop,  Chris Chant,  Christopher Chant]&lt;/ref&gt;) was commissioned. After playing an important role in several major Indian military actions, specifically the liberation of Goa and the India-Pakistan war in 1971, she was decommissioned in January 1997&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=kEj-2a7pmVMC&amp;pg=PA20&amp;dq=INS+Vikrant+decommissioned&amp;ei=-LlBSLC_BojCiQGyws2IBQ&amp;sig=2tc2x_iM2z1dEfXFmxW5MMcHSY0 ''Students' Britannica India'' By Dale Hoiberg,  Indu Ramchandani]&lt;/ref&gt; and turned into a museum ship.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mutiny.wordpress.com/2007/03/02/ins-vikrant-the-naval-museum/ ''INS Vikrant - the naval museum''] Posted by Nita&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Alize1270.jpg|thumb|left|The Alize Anti-Submarine Aircraft used on the Vikrant]]
In 1976, the [[Indian Air Force]] handed over [[Super Constellation]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warbirdsofindia.com/wbgoanam06.html ''Naval Aviation Museum, Dabolim, Goa, India'' - http://www.warbirdsofindia.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  aircraft to the No.312 Albatross Squadron&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Timeline.html ''Bharat-Rakshak.com'' - Indian Navy Timeline - &quot;1976: No.312 Albatross Squadron (consisting of Super Constellation aircraft) commissioned.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Dabolim]], Goa. Being fairly old aircraft at that point, these were withdrawn from active service by 1983. The No.315 Winged Stallions Squadron was commissioned in 1977&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Timeline.html ''Bharat-Rakshak.com'' - Indian Navy Timeline - &quot;01 October 1977: No.315 Winged Stallions Squadron (consisting of IL-38 aircraft) commissioned.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; with the [[Ilyushin Il-38]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/IL-38.html Bharat-Rakshak ''Indian Navy Timelines'']&lt;/ref&gt; aircraft.

===Operation Vijay===

The [[INS Vikrant]] participated in [[Operation Vijay (1961)|Operation Vijay]], the liberation of [[Goa]] from [[Portugal]]. Its role was primarily to deter foreign naval intervention&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sankalpindia.net/drupal/?q=node/2413 Sankalp India Foundation - &quot;What happened during Operation Vijay (1961)?&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; during the 40-hour long military action in December, 1961.

===India Pakistan War 1971===

The [[INS Vikrant]] played a major role in the successful Naval blockade of East Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=PY8CvlKC7kgC&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=Vikrant+1971&amp;ei=ibFTSM_PMY6QtAPb4fm7Cw&amp;sig=-dy2013FLTEJScp0xIjPhdvxN8w Aircraft Carriers: The World's Greatest Naval Vessels and Their Aircraft] By Richard Jones,  Chris Bishop,  Chris Chant,  Christopher Chant&lt;/ref&gt; Stationed off the [[Andaman &amp; Nicobar]] islands along with Indian naval ships, INS Bramhaputra and INS Beas, the Vikrant redeployed towards [[Chittagong]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mj30oQuTBDU&amp;amp;feature=related YouTube documentary]&lt;/ref&gt; at the outbreak of hostilities. The morning of 4 December 1971, the eight Sea Hawk aircraft on the Vikrant launched an air raid on [[Cox's Bazaar]] from 60&amp;nbsp;nm away. That evening, the air group struck Chittagong harbour. Future strikes targeted Khulna and Mongla. A PTI message is supposed to have read, &quot;Chittagong harbour abalze as ships and aircraft of the (Pakistan) Eastern Naval Fleet bombed and rocketed. Not a single vessel can be put to sea from Chittagong&quot;. Air strikes staged from the Vikrant continued till 10 December 1971.

Given naval intelligence that indicated the intent of the [[Pakistan Navy]] to break through the Indian Naval blockade using camouflaged merchant ships, the Vikrant's Sea Hawks struck shipping in the Chittagong and Cox's Bazar harbours, sinking or incapacitating most merchant ships there.

The [[PNS Ghazi]] submarine was deployed to sink the [[INS Vikrant]]. However, she sank off [[Visakhapatnam]] harbor under mysterious circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=ZcejlMRYNAAC&amp;pg=PA179&amp;dq=PNS+Ghazi&amp;ei=LKdDSKG0H4KijgGs1qG-BQ&amp;sig=9YcFuLJttkAY3wIH965XTx6eU1Y Seapower: A Guide for the Twenty-first Century] By Geoffrey Till&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aircraft Carrier ==
[[Image:INS Viraat (R22) Malabar 07.jpg|left|thumb|INS Viraat in the [[Bay of Bengal]]]]
[[INS Viraat]] was originally commissioned in the [[Royal Navy]] as [[HMS Hermes (R12)|HMS Hermes]] on 18 November 1959.&lt;ref name=&quot;bharat-rakshak.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Viraat.html - ''Centaur Class'' - http://www.bharat-rakshak.com]&lt;/ref&gt; While in the Royal Navy, Hermes was the flagship carrier during the [[Falkland Islands]] campaign. The vessel was acquired by the [[Indian Navy]] in April 1986 following an extensive refit at [[HMNB Devonport|Devonport Dockyard]]. Another refit followed between 1999 and 2001, which is expected to extend her useful life till 2010. However, there is some uncertainty around this retirement date.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/india/r-viraat.htm - ''R 22 Viraat Class HMS Centaur Class (UK) Aircraft Carrier'' - GlobalSecurity.org]&lt;/ref&gt; The second refit upgraded propulsion systems, added a package of sensors to sound emergency alerts, and introduced modern communication systems. In addition, long-range surveillance radar, weapon systems, and new hangar with fire curtains was installed. The lift system was revamped to reduce reaction time in the event of an attack and a new flood alarm system was installed.&lt;ref name=&quot;bharat-rakshak.com&quot;/&gt; Another year of down time followed while the ship received the Israeli [[Barak SAM|Barak surface-to-air missile]] system in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;bharat-rakshak.com&quot;/&gt; In a wartime scenario, the INS Viraat can embark up to 18 combat aircraft. INS Viraat is ideally suited for two missions: supporting amphibious operations and conducting ASW operations. Despite its age and range considerations, INS Viraat can quite effectively project naval and air power anywhere in the South Asia region.

== Current Inventory of the Naval Air Arm ==
=== Aircraft ===

* [[Mikoyan]] [[MiG-29K]] 
[[Image:MiG-29K on the MAKS-2009 (01).jpg|thumb|The Mig-29 Ks to be stationed on the [[INS Vikramaditya]]]]
The MiG-29K program was revived by Russia in response to the decision of the Indian Navy to acquire the [[Soviet aircraft carrier Admiral Gorshkov]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fas.org/nuke/guide/russia/airdef/mig-29.htm MIG-29 FULCRUM (MIKOYAN-GUREVICH)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/MiG-29K.html MiG-29K/KUB FULCRUM-D at Bharat-Rakshak]&lt;/ref&gt; As reported by MiG Bureau, the Indian Navy's association with the MiG-29K began in Apr 2002 when a team led by Commander Gupta reached Moscow to evaluate the MiG-29K prototype for possible induction into the Indian Navy. The Team evaluated the aircraft on ground as well as in the air (the flight evaluation was conducted by a Navy Test Pilot Commander Ahuja). Some other aircraft were also evaluated but the MiG-29K was chosen. The first 4 of the 16 aircraft contracted for were inducted into the Indian Navy late 2009. The Indian Navy is likely to buy 29 more of these aircraft. On 20 January 2004, the Indian Navy signed a contract for 12 single-seat MiG-29K and 4 two-seat MiG-29KUB [http://research.scottrade.com/qnr/Public/Markets/Article?dockey=100-217c0885-1  11(9+2)of 16 delevered]. The first MIG-29K for the Indian Navy took flight on 22 January 2007. Though it is ready it is not yet in service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kuku.sawf.org/News/32608.aspx First MiG-29K/KUB aircraft for Indian Navy undergoes flight tests]&lt;/ref&gt; First four of the sixteen aircraft was expected to be delivered by September 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Galleries/AirArm/Vishnu/ Bharat-Rakshak.com]:The Indian Navy's first MiG-29KUB&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thaindian.com/newsportal/uncategorized/russia-to-deliver-first-four-mig-29k-by-september_10050745.html Russia to deliver first four MiG 29K by September]&lt;/ref&gt; but has been delayed until the spring of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.rian.ru/russia/20080929/117273754.html Russia to start MiG fighter deliveries to India in spring 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;  The fighter plane is different from the MiG-29 flown by [[Indian Air Force]]. The aircraft has been made ready for aircraft carrier operation by hardening the undercarriage.  The aircraft also has much better over-the-nose vision to make it easy to land aboard a carrier at high angle of attack.  The Naval version also has additional fuel carrying capacity as also a capacity to carry more weapons since there are a total of nine stations as against only seven with the Air Force version.  The aircraft also has a full glass cockpit with three large size multi-function displays.  Modifications were made for Indian Navy requirement featured Zhuk-ME radar, RD-33MK engine, combat payload up to 5,500&amp;nbsp;kg, 13 hardpoints (inclusive of the multi-lock bomb carriers), additional fuel tanks situated in dorsal spine fairing and wing LERXs, increased total fuel capacity by 50% comparing to first variant of MiG-29 and updated 4-channel digital fly-by-wire flight control system. With special coatings MiG-29K radar reflecting surface is 4-5 times smaller than of basic MiG-29. Cockpit displays consist of wide HUD and 3 (7 on MiG-29KUB) colour LCD MFDs and French Sigma-95 satellite GPS module and [[Topsight E]] helmet-mounted targeting system. Compatible with the full range of weapons carried by the MiG-29M and MiG-29SMT.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rediff.com/news/2007/jan/25navy.htm Navy's MiGs superior to IAF's Sukhois]&lt;/ref&gt; The MIG-29 KUB ( two seat trainer) is similar to the MIG-29K but with reduced operational range. The aircraft will be fielded on the aircraft carrier [[INS Vikramaditya]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/story/21523.html First MiG 29 K for Indian Navy takes off]&lt;/ref&gt; A new squadron has been raised &amp; is being christened &quot;Black Panthers&quot;.  It will get its first batch of four [[MiG-29K]] fighters later this year.  The squadron will (initially IFTU, will be led by Cdr AD Theophilus, an ex-Sea Harrier pilot)&lt;ref&gt;http://livefist.blogspot.com/2009/08/exclusive-mig-29k-squadron-to-be-called.html&lt;/ref&gt;
	
* [[BAE Sea Harrier]]
[[Image:Harrier IN Malabar 07.jpg|thumb|A Sea Harrier takes off from [[INS Viraat]]]]
The BAE Sea Harrier operates from the [[INS Viraat]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WlAiq2Umj1w Indian Navy Sea Harrier Operations video on YouTube]&lt;/ref&gt; The BAE Sea Harrier FRS Mk.51 / T Mk.60 fly with the INAS 300 and INAS 552 squadrons of the Indian Navy. They were first acquired by the Indian Navy in the mid-1980s. After years of undergoing maintenance in the UK, the Indian Navy launched Project Ashok to set up a maintenance facility in Kochi in 1994. A mid-life upgrade in 1999 for these aircraft was cancelled when the decision was made to purchase MiG-29K air defence fighters, to be deployed aboard the [[INS Vikramaditya]] (formerly Admiral Gorshkov). The Sea Harriers are armed with the Matra Magic-II AAM and the Sea Eagle Anti-ship missiles. The aircraft were upgraded with the [[Elta]] [[EL/M-2032]] radar and the [[Rafael Derby]] BVRAAM missiles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Galleries/AirArm/Harrier/ Bharat-Rakshak.com]: The White Tigers of Rewa&lt;/ref&gt; Though the Sea Harriers were expected to remain in service with the Indian Navy till 2012-15, limited upgrades are being performed on these Sea Harriers by [[Hindustan Aeronautics Limited]] (HAL), to extend the life of the aircraft by 15 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2007/11/29/219935/india-to-extend-sea-harrier-by-15-years.html Flight Global]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Tupolev Tu-142]]
The [[Indian Navy]] operates eight Tu-142 aircraft. The aircraft was inducted into service in the year 1988. Upgrading of the aircraft are taking place, which helps to extend the service life of the aircraft by sixteen years. One the upgraded aircraft has been handed over to the Indian Navy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eng.cnews.ru/news/line/indexEn.shtml?2007/10/10/269866 Modernized Tu-142 handed over to Indian Eastern Headquarters]&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft operates from INS Rajali and INS Hansa. Two Tu-142 aircraft are being fitted with the air launched version of the [[Brahmos]]. The aircraft will be the test platform for the Brahmos cruise missiles. The integration and tests of the missile is expected to be completed by 2010.&lt;ref&gt;Forceindia.net&lt;/ref&gt; The eight aircraft will be fitted with the Brahmos cruise missiles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rusnavy.com/news/othernavies/index.php?ELEMENT_ID=10007 Upgraded ASW aircraft Tu-142ME delivered to Indian Navy]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Unmanned aerial vehicle|UAV]]
The [[Indian Navy]] operates at least two squadrons of [[IAI Heron|Heron]] and [[IAI Searcher|Searcher Mk-II]] UAVs, based in [[Kochi]] and [[Porbandar]].&lt;ref name=toi-uav&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/ahmedabad/Eye-in-the-sky-to-guard-Gujarat-coast/articleshow/7308504.cms | work=The Times Of India | title=Eye in the sky to guard Gujarat coast}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zeenews.com/news678714.html Navy to commission UAV squadron at Porbandar]&lt;/ref&gt; There are plans to have at least two more squadrons of UAVs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.domain-b.com/aero/indian_uav.htm Birds of a different feather]&lt;/ref&gt; UAVs are operated from ships to increases the range of surveillance. There are plans to introduce rotary UAVs into the Indian Navy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2006/12/15/stories/2006121504351600.htm Maritime surveillance capability needs to be strengthened: Mehta]&lt;/ref&gt; These UAVs will have higher endurance and load carrying capability resulting in better reconnaissance capabilities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/thehindu/holnus/002200802110325.htm Indian Navy developing new generation UAV]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Helicopters ===
[[Image:Indian Navy dhruv.jpg|thumb|right|Dhruv of the Indian Navy.]]
[[File:SeaKing Mk42B Indian Navy 2005.JPG|thumb|right|A Sea King assigned to the destroyer [[INS Mumbai]].]]
[[HAL Dhruv]] Developed by [[Hindustan Aeronautics Limited]], the Navy received its first Dhruvs on 28 March 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Galleries/AirArm/Dhruv/ Bharat-Rakshak.com]: HAL Dhruv at Aero India '05&lt;/ref&gt; It is expected to receive a total of 120 units to replace the Chetak helicopters in service. The naval variant is fitted with the Super Vision-2000 maritime radar, capable of detecting targets with low radar cross section at a range of 200&amp;nbsp;km. The anti-submarine version of the helicopter is fitted with dunking sonar, torpedoes, depth charges. The helicopter may also be fitted with the missiles for anti-ship roles.

[[Kamov Ka-25|Kamov Ka-25 Hormone]], [[Kamov Ka-28|Kamov Ka-28 Helix-A]], and the [[Kamov Ka-31|Kamov Ka-31 Helix-B]]: The [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Ka-25.html KA-25] was acquired by the Indian Navy in 1980 for [[anti-submarine warfare]], but had severe technological limitations. The [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Ka-28.html KA-28] were acquired in the mid-80s, and were said to be a quantum leap over their predecessors from an ASW standpoint. The [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Ka-31.html KA-31]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Galleries/AirArm/Ka31/ Bharat-Rakshak.com]: Eyes in the Skies&lt;/ref&gt; takes the Kamov capabilities even further by enabling real-time network-centric warfare for the Indian Navy.

[[Westland Sea King]] and the Sikorsky [[SH-3 Sea King]]: Used principally for [[anti-submarine warfare]] (ASW) and search &amp; rescue roles,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Seaking.html Sea King]&lt;/ref&gt; the helicopter fleet operate from INS Garuda (Kochi) as well as INS Kunjali-II (Mumbai) air stations. US sanctions on India in response to India's [[Pokhran-II|nuclear tests]] resulted in a large part of the Sea King fleet being grounded for want of spare parts. Seventeen of the Sea King helicopters will be upgraded. The upgrade will feature day and night capability, capability to work in adverse weather conditions, integration of two anti-ship missiles with a range of fifty kilometres and a new radar.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=3585408&amp;c=ASI&amp;s=AIR India to Upgrade 17 Sea King Copters for $300M]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aérospatiale Alouette III|Aérospatiale SA 316 Alouette III]]: Also known as the [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Chetak.html Chetak], these choppers have seen active service in the Navy as well as the Coast Guard. They are carried on several combatant as well as non-combatant ships. They are also operated from and maintained at the [[INS Kunjali-II]] and [[INS Utkrosh]] [[Naval Air Station]]s in Mumbai and Port Blair respectively.

=== Naval Aircraft Inventory ===
The Navy operates 241 aircraft, including 22 (34 more added) combat jets, 13 tactical bombers, 145 helicopters and 30 UAVs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milaviapress.com/orbat/india/index.php Indian military aviation OrBat]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Standard table|0}}
! style=&quot;text-align: left; background: #aacccc;&quot;|Aircraft
! style=&quot;text-align: left; background: #aacccc;&quot;|Origin
! style=&quot;text-align: left; background: #aacccc;&quot;|Type
! style=&quot;text-align: left; background: #aacccc;&quot;|Versions
! style=&quot;text-align: left; background: #aacccc;&quot;|In service&lt;ref name=&quot;awst_20070115&quot;&gt;&quot;World Military Aircraft Inventory&quot;, Aerospace Source Book 2007, ''[[Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology]]'', 15 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
! style=&quot;text-align: left; background: #aacccc;&quot;|Notes
|----
| [[File:MiG-29K on the MAKS-2009 (02).jpg|150px]]   &lt;br&gt; [[Mikoyan MiG-29K]] || {{RUS}} || Multi role Fighter&lt;hr&gt;Trainer || [[MiG-29K]]&lt;hr&gt;MiG-29KUB ||9&lt;hr&gt;2 || 45 aircraft of the type have been ordered of which 37 are MiG 29K (9 of which have been delivered&lt;ref name=&quot;9 mig29s&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bharatrakshak.com/NEWS/newsrf.php?newsid=14817|title=Indian Navy gets new MiG-29K carrier-borne fighters
|publisher=Economic Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and 8 are the two-seat MiG 29 KUB trainer variant.&lt;ref name=&quot;45_mig29k&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/India-Russia-to-ink-12-bn-deal-for-29-more-MiG-29Ks/articleshow/5460879.cms|title=India, Russia to ink $1.2 bn deal for 29 more MiG-29Ks|publisher=Times of India|author=Rajat Pandit|date=18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;45mig29k_rianovosti&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.rian.ru/russia/20100219/157943434.html|title=Russian MiG-29K jets officially enter service with Indian Navy|publisher=RIA Novosti}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first 12 Russian-made MiG-29K fighters to be deployed on the aircraft carrier INS Vikramaditya, formerly the Admiral Gorshkov.
|-----
| [[File:Harrier land Malabar 2007.jpg|150px]]   &lt;br&gt; [[BAE Sea Harrier]] || {{UK}} || Fighter&lt;hr&gt;Trainer || FRS 51&lt;hr&gt; T 60 ||8&lt;hr&gt;3 ||Cleared to fly again after being grounded due to a harrier crash&lt;ref&gt;http://oheraldo.in/pagedetails.asp?nid=26504&amp;cid=2&lt;/ref&gt;
|-----
| [[File:Tupolev Tu-142 Krivchikov 2007.jpg|150px]] &lt;br&gt; [[Tupolev Tu-142]] Bear || {{RUS}} || Maritime patrol || Tu-142M || 8 ||To be replaced by [[P-8I Neptune]]
|-----
| [[File:Ilyushin Il-38SD Krivchikov 2007.jpg|150px]]  &lt;br&gt; [[Ilyushin Il-38|Ilyushin Il-38 May]] || {{RUS}} || Maritime patrol || Il-38SD || 5 ||  .&lt;ref&gt;http://www.janes.com/extracts/extract/jau/jau_1019.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-----
| [[File:Wiki dornierdo228 lgw1.jpg|150px]]  &lt;br&gt; [[Dornier Do 228]] || {{GER}}&lt;hr&gt;{{IND}} || Utility transport || Do 228-101&lt;hr&gt;Do 228-201 || 1&lt;hr&gt;19 || To be replaced by [[NAL Saras]]
|-----
| [[File:HAL Kiran Aero India-2007.jpg|150px]]  &lt;br&gt; [[HAL HJT-16 Kiran]] || {{IND}} || Trainer ||  || 20&lt;ref&gt;[http://lite.epaper.timesofindia.com/mobile.aspx?article=yes&amp;pageid=1&amp;edlabel=TOIKM&amp;mydateHid=04-03-2010&amp;pubname=&amp;edname=&amp;articleid=Ar00100&amp;format=&amp;publabel=TOI timesofindia]&lt;/ref&gt; || 12 Mk-I and 8 Mk-II.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraphindia.com/1100304/jsp/frontpage/story_12175567.jsp the telegraph]&lt;/ref&gt; 
|-----
| [[File:Indian Navy dhruv.jpg|150px]]  &lt;br&gt; [[HAL Dhruv]] || {{IND}} || Utility helicopter ||  || 8 ||
|-----
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;| [[File:SeaKing Mk42B Indian Navy 2005.JPG|150px]][[Westland Sea King]] ||rowspan=&quot;4&quot;| {{UK}} ||rowspan=&quot;4&quot;| Naval helicopter || Sea King 42 Anti-submarine warfare version|| 5 || 12 built, 2 lost and 5 retired &lt;ref&gt;http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Aviation/Aircraft/112-Westland-Sea-King.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-----
||Sea King 42A Anti-submarine warfare version||2|| 3 built, 1 lost
|-----
||Sea King 42B Anti-ship warfare version||17|| 20 built, 3 lost
|-----
||Sea King 42C Search and rescue, utility transport version||5|| 5 built
|-----
| [[File:SH3H HS15 CVW15 1995.JPEG|150px]] &lt;br&gt;[[Sikorsky SH-3 Sea King]] || {{USA}} || Anti Submarine Warfare Utility helicopter || UH-3H || 6 ||
|-----
| [[File:Indian Navy Chetak.jpg|150px]]   &lt;br&gt; [[Aérospatiale Alouette III|Aérospatiale SA 316 Alouette III]] || {{IND}} || Utility helicopter || SA 316B&lt;hr&gt;SA 319 || 30&lt;hr&gt;25 || built by HAL
|-----
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[File:Ka-25 sfrj.jpg|150px]]  --&gt;&lt;br&gt; [[Kamov Ka-25|Kamov Ka-25 Hormone]] || {{RUS}} || Naval helicopter ||  || 7 ||
|-----
| [[File:Kamov Ka-27PS.JPEG|150px]] &lt;br&gt; [[Kamov Ka-28|Kamov Ka-28 Helix-A]] || {{RUS}} || Anti Submarine Naval helicopter ||  || 13 (incl. of 3 trainers) ||
|-----
| [[File:Ka-31-2007.jpg|150px]] &lt;br&gt; [[Kamov Ka-31|Kamov Ka-31 Helix-B]] || {{RUS}} || AEW ||  || 9 ||
|-----
|-----
|[[File:HAL Deepak.jpg|150px]] &lt;br&gt; [[HAL HPT-32 Deepak]] || {{IND}} || Basic trainer ||  || 8 ||
|-----
| [[File:Heron UAV 2009.jpg|150px]] &lt;br&gt; [[IAI Heron]] || {{ISR}} || UAV ||  || 12 ||
|-----
| [[File:IAI-Searcher2.jpg|150px]] &lt;br&gt; [[IAI Searcher|IAI Searcher MkII]] || {{ISR}} || UAV ||  || 18 ||
{{Close table}}

== Future Aircraft Carriers ==
[[Vikrant class aircraft carrier|''Vikrant'' class aircraft carrier]]:In April 2005, India began construction of a 40,000&amp;nbsp;tonne ''Vikrant'' class aircraft carrier at a cost of {{INRConvert|40|b|1}} and scheduled to operate 30 aircraft, including [[HAL Tejas|Naval LCA]], [[MiG 29|MiG-29K]], and Sea Harrier combat aircraft, as well as [[HAL Dhruv]], [[Kamov Ka-31|Ka-31]], and [[H-3 Sea King|Sea King Mk.42]] helicopters. Four [[turbine]] engines will power the ship. The carrier is being constructed by state-run [[Cochin Shipyard]] Limited.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.chinadaily.com.cn/english/doc/2005-04/12/content_433517.htm India's construction of aircraft carrier.]&lt;/ref&gt; and will be commissioned by 2012-13. The Indian Minister of State for Defence, Pallam Raju, went on record in September 2006 stating that the aircraft carrier is likely to be commissioned by 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newindpress.com/NewsItems.asp?ID=IEA20060913042608 IAC construction]&lt;/ref&gt; There are plans to build more Indigenous aircraft carriers.&lt;ref&gt;*[http://deccanherald.com/deccanherald/nov152006/national2344220061114.asp India to have ‘3-carrier Navy’]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Baku DN-SN-89-06990c.jpg|thumb|left|[[Soviet aircraft carrier Admiral Gorshkov|''Admiral Gorshkov'']] was sold to India for conversion into a STOBAR carrier to be named [[INS Vikramaditya]].]]
[[INS Vikramaditya]]: On 20 January 2004, after years of negotiations, [[Russia]] and [[India]] signed a deal for the sale of the ship, the then-[[Soviet aircraft carrier Admiral Gorshkov|Admiral Gorshkov]]. The ship was free, while India will pay US$800 million for upgrade and refit of the ship, as well as at least an additional $1bn for the aircraft and weapons systems. The Navy looked at equipping the carrier with the [[E-2D]], but decided not to. The deal also includes the purchase of 12 single-seat [[MiG-29K]] 'Fulcrum-D' (Product 9.41) and 4 dual-seat [[MiG-29K|MiG-29KUB]] aircraft (with an option for 14 more aircraft)$1bn, 6 [[Kamov Ka-31]] &quot;Helix&quot; reconnaissance and anti-submarine helicopters, torpedo tubes, missile systems, and artillery units. Facilities and procedures for training pilots and technical staff, delivery of simulators, spare parts, and establishment maintenance on [[Indian Navy]] facilities are also part of the contract.
The announced delivery date for INS Vikramaditya was August 2008, an ambitious schedule, but one that would allow the carrier to enter service in 2009, around the time as light carrier [[INS Viraat]] (formerly HMS Hermes, last of the Centaur class) was scheduled to retire. The new ship will berth at the new Indian Navy facility in [[Karwar]], on India’s west coast. The INS Viraat’s retirement is now set for 2010-2012. The sea trials of [[INS Vikramaditya]] are expected to begin by 2010 and delivery is expected by 2012.

== Aircraft Under Development and Future Aircraft ==
[[Image:Tejas Trainer 62 New Delhi Parade.jpg|thumb|right|[[HAL Tejas]] naval variant will be similar to the Tejas trainer variant.]]
[[Image:HAL Saras.jpg|thumb|right|[[NAL Saras]].]]

*[[HAL Tejas]]:The naval variant of the Tejas will have strengthened landing gear and other necessary modifications for service on an aircraft carrier. Two Naval prototypes will be built, the NP-1 (Naval Prototype-1) which will be a two seat variant and NP-2 (Naval Prototype-2), a single seat variant for carrier operations. The Tejas is expected to be delivered before 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lca-tejas.org/naval%20tejas.html Naval Tejas]&lt;/ref&gt; The first flight of NP-1 is expected to take place by the end of 2008 but the carrier trials was delayed due to the delay in the delivery schedule of [[INS Vikramaditya]]. Hence the trials will have to be carried out at the SBTF (Shore-based Test Facility) under construction at the naval airbase INS Hansa in Goa. Indian Navy plans to operate two squadrons (40 aircraft) of carrier borne Tejas aircraft from the two aircraft carries, INS Vikramaditya and INS Vikrant.&lt;ref&gt;[http://indiatoday.digitaltoday.in/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=4818&amp;issueid=41&amp;Itemid=1 Gorshkov delay stalls carrier trials of naval LCA]&lt;/ref&gt; Indian navy has placed an order for six Naval LCAs. At an approximate cost of {{INRConvert|150|c|1}} per aircraft, that will provide a {{INRConvert|900|c|1}} infusion into the Naval LCA programme.&lt;ref&gt;
http://news.rediff.com/report/2009/sep/21/navy-places-order-for-6-tejas-lca.htm Navy places Rs 900-cr order for 6 Tejas LCA&lt;/ref&gt; The Navy has a requirement of 50-60 Tejas aircraft. The first Naval prototype NP-1, was rolled out in July 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/bangalore/report_indian-navy-fastens-its-seatbelt-for-light-combat-aircraft-tejas_1400112 Indian Navy fastens its seatbelt for Light Combat Aircraft Tejas]&lt;/ref&gt; NP-1 which is undergoing taxi trials is expected to take to the skies in July 2011. Tejas will replace the Sea harriers in service with the Indian Navy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://daily.bhaskar.com/article/BAN-coming-soon-lcas-naval-variant-2094535.html Coming soon, LCA's naval variant]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Boeing P-8 Poseidon|P-8I Neptune]]: New Delhi and Boeing have inked a lucrative, $2.1 billion contract for the delivery of 12 P-8I Neptune sub hunters.The new aircraft will replace a fleet of Russian-manufactured Tupolev-142M planes. P-8I varies from the P-8A. The [[Magnetic anomaly detector]] (MAD) has been kept intact while an aft-mounted radar provides 360 degree aerial radar surveillance capability. The aircraft is being readied for debut flight.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2011/09/21/362335/picture-indias-first-737-based-p-8i-nears-flight-debut.html PICTURE: India's first 737-based P-8I nears flight debut]&lt;/ref&gt; 

*Medium Range Maritime Reconnaissance Aircraft: The Indian Navy issued an RFP for six medium-range maritime reconnaissance (MRMR) aircraft. Possible ontenders include [[ATR 72|ATR-72MP]]/ [[ATR 42|ATR-42MP]], [[EADS CASA C-295|EADS C-295MPA]]/[[CASA CN-235|C-235MPA]], [[Dassault Falcon 900|Dassault's Falcon 900MPA]] and [[Embraer R-99|Embraer P-99A]] platforms.

*[[E-2 Hawkeye|E-2D Advanced Hawkeye]]

*17 [[BAE Hawk|Hawk Trainer]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2008/01/11/stories/2008011160161400.htm  IAF to get 40 more Hawk AJTs]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/news/navy-inks-rs-3000cr-ajt-deal/651334/0 Navy inks Rs 3000-cr AJT deal] deliveries start from 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[HAL HJT-36]]

* 20 [[Anti-submarine warfare|ASW Helicopters]] (to replace Sea King) Extended to 60 helos &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3738/is_200407/ai_n9458633 Indian Navy in the Market For New ASW Helicopters]&lt;/ref&gt;

* 15 [[NAL Saras]] aircraft have been ordered, mostly to replace the Dornier Do-228.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.webindia123.com/news/articles/India/20081220/1133595.html Indian navy places order for Saras aircraft]&lt;/ref&gt; The Navy has a requirement for 25 Saras aircraft and design changes are being conducted on the aircraft for using it in maritime environment. The first Naval Saras will roll out in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2011/09/19/362205/indian-air-force-to-buy-15-saras-twin-turboprops-as-trainers.html Indian air force to buy 15 Saras twin turboprops as trainers]&lt;/ref&gt;

* 40 Unmanned helicopters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ndtv.com/convergence/ndtv/story.aspx?id=NEWEN20080045672 India developing unmanned helicopter]&lt;/ref&gt; This helicopter is under development and will be based on the HAL-built Cheetah helicopters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.domain-b.com/defence/sea/indian_navy/20071205_maritime.html Indian Navy RFPs for maritime patrol aircraft soon, to develop rotary wing UAVs ne]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Rustom]] UAV

* 50 Light Helicopers &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defensenews.com/story.php?i=4748275&amp;c=ASI&amp;s=TOP India Seeks Info on Light Helos From Contractors]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Personnel and Structure ==
The 5000-person&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Administrative.html Bharat-Rakshak.com]:Administrative Structure&lt;/ref&gt; Naval Air Arm is headed by Rear Admiral Vijay Shankar, Assistant Chief of Naval Staff (Air).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Officers.html Bharat-Rakshak.com]: NAVY SENIOR APPOINTMENTS &amp; OFFICERS LIST&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Western Command ===
[[Image:Harrier land Malabar 2007.jpg|thumb|[[Sea Harrier]] landing on aircraft carrier [[INS Viraat|INS ''Viraat'']].]]
[[File:Chetak(070407-N-4953E-002).jpg|thumb|[[HAL Chetak]] from [[INS Rana|INS ''Rana'']].]]
On the other hand, FONA controls training, maintenance and other functions of naval aviation. Aircraft yards at [[Kochi, India|Kochi]], [[Kerala]] and [[Dabolim]], [[Goa]] are responsible for maintaining the fleet's air arm. An exclusive base, INS Shikra for helicopters was commissioned in Mumbai.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2009/01/23/stories/2009012355401300.htm  Navy chief calls for enhanced preparedness]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Eastern Command ===

To protect and preserve India's growing trade with Southeast Asia&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/ENC.html Bharat-Rakshak.com]: Western Command&lt;/ref&gt; and offer a bulwark against Chinese dominance in the Bay of Bengal, a new naval base is being built near [[Visakhapatnam]]. It is expected to be capable of harboring two aircraft carriers, including the new Vikrant-class aircraft carrier that is being planned.

=== Southern Command ===

It has at least one airfield.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/SNC.html Bharat-Rakshak.com]: Southern Command&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Andaman &amp; Nicobar Command ===

A fighter squadron is expected to be based in [[Port Blair]] in the future,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/ANC.html Bharat-Rakshak.com]: Andaman &amp; Nicobar Command&lt;/ref&gt; to bolster the strength of the squadron of [[Mil Mi-8|Mi-8]] helicopters currently operating there.

=== Muscat (Oman) ===
A new airbase will be setup in Muscat, Oman to tackle piracy in the Gulf of Aden.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/2009/02/02/stories/2009020250210600.htm  Naval air base to tackle piracy]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Former aircraft ==
* [[Armstrong Whitworth Sea Hawk]] - maritime strike
* [[Breguet Alize]] - Carrier-based ASW
* [[Hughes 269]] - training helicopter
* [[Lockheed Super Constellation]] - maritime patrol

==See also==

* [[Indian Coast Guard]]
* [[Naval ranks and insignia of India]]
* [[Middle Ground Coastal Battery]]
* [[Project Seabird]]
* [[Indian Ancient Maritime History]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.indian-military.org/home/reports/indian-military-blog/imorg-exclusive-admins-visit-to-vt-21-fighting-redhawks-at-us-naval-air-stationkingsville-tx.html/ Indian Navy Pilot training facility at US NAS Kingsville, Texas, USA]
* [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/NAVY/Air-Arm.html Naval Air Arm]
* [http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_431.shtml Indian Naval Aviation - Part 1 @ ACIG.org]
* [http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_432.shtml Indian Naval Aviation - Part 2 @ ACIG.org]
* [http://www.lca-tejas.org/naval%20tejas.html Naval Tejas, lca-tejas.org]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YeX4-vVWmRM&amp;feature=related Documentary on YouTube on the INS Vikrant]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0r4blywbzl8 Video of IL-38 of IN firing anti-ship missile]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j-84fIZggHA YouTube video by user vishv with some good photographs]
* [http://www.flickr.com/photos/vikramwalia/2127148882/ INS Vikrant docked in Mumbai]
* [http://www.flickr.com/photos/mogun23/2112156393/ Image of Kamov helicopter]

{{Commons category|Aircraft of the Indian Navy}}

{{Ship classes of the Indian Navy}}
{{Military of India}}
{{aviation lists}}

[[Category:Indian Navy]]
[[Category:Naval aviation services]]
[[Category:Aviation in India|Navy]]
[[Category:Indian naval air stations]]

[[fr:Marine indienne]]
[[mr:भारतीय नौदल]]
[[ja:インド海軍]]
[[te:భారత నావికా దళం]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
