<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="73453" ns="0" title="Cinderella"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Infobox Folk tale
|Folk_Tale_Name = Cinderella
|Image_Name     = Cendrillon2.JPG
|Image_Caption  = [[Gustave Doré]]'s illustration for ''Cendrillon''
|Aarne-Thompson Grouping       = 510a
|Mythology      =
|Country        = Worldwide
|Region         =
|Origin_Date    =
|Published_In   = ''The [[Pentamerone]]'' (1634) &lt;br/&gt;''[[Mother Goose Tales]]'' (1697)&lt;br/&gt;''[[Grimm's Fairy Tales]]'' (1812)
|Related        =
}}
&quot;'''Cinderella and The Little Glass Slipper'''&quot; ({{lang-fr|Cendrillon ou La petite Pantoufle de Verre}}, {{lang-de|Aschenputtel}}) is a [[folk tale]] embodying a [[myth]]-element of [[justice|unjust]] oppression/triumphant reward. Thousands of variants are known throughout the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Great Fairy Tale Tradition: From Straparola and Basile to the Brothers Grimm|last=Zipes|first=Jack|authorlink=Jack Zipes|year=2001|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Co|isbn= 978-0393976366|page= 444}}&lt;/ref&gt; The title character&lt;ref&gt;Although both the story's title and the character's name change in different languages, in English-language folklore &quot;Cinderella&quot; is the archetypal name.&lt;/ref&gt; is a young woman living in unfortunate circumstances that are suddenly changed to remarkable fortune. The word &quot;[[wikt:cinderella|cinderella]]&quot; has, by analogy, come to mean one whose attributes are unrecognised, or one who unexpectedly achieves recognition or success after a period of obscurity and neglect. The still-popular story of &quot;Cinderella&quot; continues to influence popular culture internationally, lending plot elements, allusions, and [[trope (literature)|tropes]] to a wide variety of media.

==Early versions==
The Cinderella theme may well have originated in [[classical antiquity]]. The [[Ancient Greek]] historian [[Strabo]] (''[[Geographica]]'' Book 17, 1.33) recorded in the 1st century BC the tale of the [[Greeks in Egypt|Greco-Egyptian]] girl [[Rhodopis]], &quot;rosy-cheeked&quot;, who lived in the [[colonies in antiquity|Greek colony]] of [[Naucratis]] in [[Ancient Egypt]]. It is often considered the oldest known version of the story:

{{quote|They tell the fabulous story that, when she was bathing, an eagle snatched one of her sandals from her maid and carried it to Memphis. While the king was administering justice in the open air, the eagle, when it arrived above his head, flung the sandal into his lap. The king, having been stirred both by the beautiful shape of the sandal and by the strangeness of the occurrence, sent men in all directions into the country in quest of the woman who wore the sandal. When she was found in the city of Naucratis, she was brought up to Memphis and became the wife of the king...&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Strabo/17A3*.html#ref178|title=Strabo's account of Rhodopis|author=Strabo|date=23|work=The Geography|accessdate=25 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aldokkan.com/art/cinderella.htm &quot;The Egyptian Cinderella&quot;], an embellished retelling.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Herodotus]], some five centuries before [[Strabo]], supplied further information about Rhodopis in his ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|Histories]]'', writing that Rhodopis came from [[Thrace]], and was the slave of Iadmon of [[Samos]], and a fellow-slave of [[Aesop]]. She was taken to Egypt in the time of [[Pharaoh]] [[Amasis II|Amasis]], and freed there for a large sum by Charaxus of [[Mytilene]], brother of [[Sappho]], the lyric poet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Fairytale in the ancient world|last= Anderson|first= Graham|year=2000|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415237024|page=27|url=http://books.google.com/id=B2DAAlUrbBIC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=Fairytale+in+the+ancient+world+rhodopis&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=Fairytale%20in%20the%20ancient%20world%20rhodopis|accessdate=25 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Histories|last=Herodotus|authorlink=Herodotus|url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/searchresults?target=en&amp;inContent=true&amp;q=Rhodopis&amp;doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0126|accessdate=25 March 2010}}, book 2, chapters 134 and 135.&lt;/ref&gt;

The story later reappears with [[Claudius Aelianus|Aelian]] (ca. 175–ca. 235),&lt;ref&gt;Aelian, [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/aelian/varhist13.xhtml#b28 &quot;Various History&quot;, 13.33]&lt;/ref&gt; showing that the Cinderella theme remained popular throughout antiquity.

Another version of the story, ''[[Ye Xian]]'', appeared in ''[[Miscellaneous Morsels from Youyang]]'' by [[Tuan Ch'eng-Shih]] around 860. Here, the hardworking and lovely girl befriends a fish, the reincarnation of her mother, who was killed by her stepmother. Ye Xian saves the bones, which are magic, and they help her dress appropriately for a festival. When she loses her slipper after a fast exit, the king finds her slipper and falls in love with her (eventually rescuing her from her cruel stepmother). Another version of the story, which is similar to the Chinese version, exists in the Philippines. The story is known as &quot;Mariang Alimango&quot; (Mary the Crab). In this version, the spirit of her dead mother reincarnates as a crab, hence the title, and serves as her &quot;fairy godmother&quot;.

In the Vietnamese version [[Tam Cam|Tấm Cám]] there is part two of the story in which the protagonist Tấm later turned into antagonist by boiling her stepsister alive and then fool the stepmother to being cannibalism by eating her own daughter's flesh, which she told the stepmother that is just a jar of food.

Several different variants of the story appear in the medieval ''[[One Thousand and One Nights]]'', also known as the ''Arabian Nights'', including &quot;The Second Shaykh's Story&quot;, &quot;The Eldest Lady's Tale&quot; and &quot;Abdallah ibn Fadil and His Brothers&quot;, all dealing with the theme of a younger sibling harassed by two jealous elders. In some of these, the siblings are female, while in others, they are male. One of the tales, &quot;Judar and His Brethren&quot;, departs from the [[happy ending]]s of previous variants and reworks the plot to give it a [[Tragedy|tragic]] ending instead, with the younger brother being poisoned by his elder brothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Arabian Nights Encyclopedia|last=Ulrich Marzolph, Richard van Leeuwen|first=Hassan Wassouf|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]|year=2004|isbn=1576072045|page=4|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aspects of Cinderella may be derived from the story of [[Cordelia of Britain|Cordelia]] in [[Geoffrey of Monmouth]]'s ''[[Historia Regum Britanniae]]''. Cordelia is the youngest and most virtuous of [[Leir of Britain|King Leir]] of [[Britons (historic)|Briton]]'s three daughters, however her virtue is such that it will not allow her to lie in flattering her father when he asks, so that he divides up the kingdom between the elder daughters and leaves Cordelia with nothing.  Cordelia marries her love, Aginippus, King of the [[Franks]], and flees to [[Gaul]] where she and her husband raise an army and depose her wicked sisters who have been misusing their father.  Cordelia is finally crowned Queen of the Britons.  However her reign only lasts five years.  The story is famously retold by [[King Lear|Shakespeare]], but given a tragic ending.

==Cenerentola, Cinderella and Aschenputtel==
[[File:DBP 1965 485 Wohlfahrt Aschenputtel.jpg|right|thumb|Aschenputtel at her mother's grave, with birds]]

In 1634, [[Giambattista Basile]], a Neapolitan soldier and government official, wrote ''Lo cunto de li cunti'' (The Story of Stories), or [[Pentamerone]]. It featured the tale of Cenerentola, which features a wicked step mother and step sisters, magical transformations, a missing slipper, and a hunt by a prince for the owner of the slipper.

==Plot (Cenerentola)==
A widowed prince has a daughter who is the subject of envy and anger towards his new wife, and the girl is ensnared by her governess in killing her stepmother and convincing her father to marry her. The governess succeeds, and then brings forward six daughters of her own, who abuse Zezolla (the Cinderella figure), and sending her into the kitchen to work as a servant. The prince goes into the island of Sardinia, meets a fairy who gives presents to his daughter, and brings back for her, a golden spade, a golden bucket, a silken napkin, and a date seedling. The girl cultivates the tree, and when the King gives a ball, Zezolla appears dressed richly by a fairy living in the date tree. The King falls in-love with her, and on the third night, threads one of her overshoes. The King invites all of the maidens in the land to a feast with a shoe-test, identifies Zezolla after the shoe jumps from his hand to her foot, and eventually marries her.

One of the most popular versions of Cinderella was written by [[Charles Perrault]] in 1697. The popularity of his tale was due to his additions to the story, including the pumpkin, the fairy-godmother and the introduction of glass slippers.&lt;ref&gt;An modern edition of the original French text by Perrault is found in Charles Perrault, ''Contes'', ed. Marc Soriano (Paris: Flammarion, 1989), pp. 274-79.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another well-known version was recorded by the German brothers [[Brothers Grimm|Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm]] in the 19th century. The tale is called ''&quot;Aschenputtel&quot;'' (''&quot;Cinderella&quot;'' in English translations) and the help comes not from a fairy-godmother but the wishing tree that grows on her mother's grave.

==Plot (Aschenputtel)==
A rich gentleman's wife lay dying, and calling her only daughter to her bedside, asked her to remain kind and generous, and God will protect her. She then died and was buried. After a transition of seasons (winter and spring) the widower married another woman, who had two daughters of her own; they were beautiful yet cruel and wicked. The stepsisters destroyed the girl's clothes, sent her into the kitchen to do the worst chores, and renamed her Cinderella. Despite all of this the girl remained good and pious, and would always go to her mother's grave to cry and pray to God to give better circumstances for herself.

One day, the gentleman visits a fair, promising his stepdaughters gifts of luxury. One asks for beautiful dresses, while the other for pearls and diamonds. His own daughter merely asks for the first twig that will hit his hat off on the way. The gentleman goes into his way, and acquires presents for his stepdaughters. While passing a forest he gets a hazel twig, and gives it to his daughter. She plants the twig over her mother's grave, waters it with her tears and over the years, it grows into a glowing hazel tree. Under it the girl would pray for thrice a day, and a white bird would always come to talk and grant her everything she would ask for.

The king decides to give a festival that will last for three whole days and nights, and invites all the beautiful maidens in the land to attend, because the prince is supposed to select from one of them a bride for himself. The two sisters were also invited, but when Cinderella begged them to allow her to go with them into the celebration, the stepmother scoffed her off, because she had no dress nor shoes to wear. When the girl insisted, the woman threw a dish of lentils into the ashes for her to pick up, guaranteeing her permission to attend the festival, and when the girl accomplished the task in less than an hour with the help of two, white doves sent by God from Heaven, the stepmother only redoubled the task and threw down even a greater quantity of lentils. When Cinderella was able to accomplished it in a greater speed, not wanting to spoil her daughters' chances, the stepmother hasted away with them to the ball and left the crying stepdaughter behind.

The girl retreats to the graveyard to ask for help. The white bird drops a silver gown and silk shoes. She goes to the ball, with the precaution of leaving before midnight. The prince dances with her, but she eludes him before midnight strikes. The next evening, the girl appeared in a grander apparel. The prince fell in-love with her and danced her the whole evening, but when midnight came, she left again. The third evening, she appeared dressed with gold. Now the prince was determined to keep her, and had entire stairway smeared with pitch. Cinderella lost her track of time, and when she ran away to leave, one of her golden slippers stuck on that pitch. The prince proclaimed that he would marry the maiden whose foot would fit the golden slipper.

The next morning, the prince went into Cinderella's house and tried the slipper on the eldest stepsister. The sister was advised by her mother to cut off her heel in order to fit the slipper, and while riding with the prince, the two doves from Heaven told the Prince that blood drips from her heel. Appalled at her treachery, he went back again and tried the slipper to the other stepsister. She cut off her toe in order to get in her foot in the slipper, and again the prince was fooled. While he was riding with her on the way to the king's castle, the doves alerted him again about the blood on her foot. He came back to inquire for another girl. The gentleman tells him that they kept a kitchen-maid in the house - yet did not mention that she was his own daughter - and the prince asked him to let her try the slipper. The girl appeared after washing herself, and when she had put on the slipper, the prince recognized her as the stranger he danced at the ball.

In the end during Cinderella's wedding, as she was walking down the aisle with her stepsisters as her bridesmaids, for they had hoped to worm their way into her favor, the doves from Heaven flew down and struck the two stepsister's eyes, one in the left and the other in the right. When the wedding came to an end, and Cinderella and her prince was marching out of the church, the doves flew again, stricking the remaining eyes of the two, evil sisters blind, the punishment they have to endure for the rest of their lives.

==Plot (taken from Perrault)==

[[File:Cinderella - Project Gutenberg etext 19993.jpg|thumb|right|[[Oliver Herford]] illustrated the fairy godmother inspired from the Perrault version]]
(See above for many variations)

Once upon a time, there was a widower who married a proud and haughty woman as his second wife. She had two [[false hero|daughters]], who were equally vain. By his first wife, he'd had a beautiful young daughter, a girl of unparalleled goodness and sweet temper. The Stepmother and her daughters forced the first daughter into servitude, where she was made to work day and night in menial chores. After the girl's chores were done for the day, she would retire to the barren and cold room given to her, and would curl up near the fireplace in an effort to stay warm.  She would often arise covered in cinders, giving rise to the mocking nickname &quot;Cinderella&quot;. Cinderella bears the abuse patiently and dares not tell her father, since his wife controls him entirely.

One day, the [[Prince Charming|Prince]] invites all the young ladies in the land to a [[ball (dance)|ball]], planning to choose a wife from amongst them. The two [[step family|Stepsisters]] gleefully planned their [[ball gown|wardrobes]] for the ball, and taunted Cinderella by telling her maids were not invited to the ball. 

As the sisters depart to the ball, Cinderella cries in despair. Her [[Fairy Godmother]] magically appears and immediately begins to transform Cinderella from house servant to the young lady she was by birth, all in the effort to get Cinderella to the ball. She turns a [[pumpkin]] into a golden carriage, [[mouse|mice]] into [[horse]]s, a [[rat]] into a [[coachman]], and [[lizard]]s into [[footman|footmen]]. She then turns Cinderella's rags into a beautiful jeweled [[ball gown|gown]], complete with a delicate pair of glass [[slipper]]s. The Godmother tells her to enjoy the ball, but warned that she had to return before [[midnight]], when the [[magic (paranormal)|spells]] would be broken.

At the ball, the entire [[noble court|court]] is entranced by Cinderella, most especially the Prince. At this first ball, Cinderella remembers to leave before midnight. Back home, Cinderella graciously thanks her Godmother. She then greets the stepsisters, who had not recognized her earlier and talked of nothing but the beautiful girl at the ball.

Another ball is held the next evening, and Cinderella again attends with her Godmother's help. The Prince has become even more entranced, and Cinderella in turn becomes so enchanted by him she loses track of time and leaves only at the final stroke of midnight, losing one of her glass slippers on the steps of the [[palace]] in her haste. The Prince chases her, but outside the palace, the guards watch only a simple country wench leave. The Prince pockets the slipper and vows to find and marry the girl to whom it belonged. Meanwhile, Cinderella keeps the other slipper, which did not disappear when the spell was broken.

The Prince tries the slipper on all the women in the kingdom. When the Prince arrives at Cinderella's villa, the [[False hero|stepsisters]] try in vain to win over the prince. Cinderella asks if she might try, while the stepsisters taunt her. Naturally, the slipper fits perfectly, and Cinderella produces the other slipper for good measure. The stepsisters beg for [[forgiveness]], and Cinderella forgives them for their [[cruelty|cruelties]].

Cinderella [[marriage|marries]] the Prince, and the stepsisters also marry two [[lord]]s.

The first moral of the story is that [[beauty]] is a treasure, but graciousness is priceless. Without it, nothing is possible; with it, one can do anything.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/perrault06.html Perrault: Cinderella; or, The Little Glass Slipper]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the second moral of the story mitigates the first one and reveals the criticism that Perrault is aiming at:
&quot;Another moral: Without doubt it is a great advantage to have intelligence, courage, good breeding, and common sense. These, and similar talents come only from heaven, and it is good to have them. However, even these may fail to bring you success, without the blessing of a godfather or a godmother.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/perrault06.html Perrault: Cinderella; or, The Little Glass Slipper]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Character Name==
The name Cinderella may have been derived from the circumstances of her work with her step-mothers family. Supposedly her name was &quot;Ella&quot;, but she was in charge of tending the fire, and while doing this, the cinders would often pop out and burn her. Thus she was meanly nicknamed Cinder-Ella.{{fact|date=November 2011}}

==Types==
Folklorists have long studied variants on this tale across cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;fits&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.artic.edu/webspaces/510iftheshoefits/2criteria.html If The Shoe Fits: Folklorists' criteria for #510]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In 1893, [[Marian Roalfe Cox]], commissioned by the [[Folklore Society of Britain]], produced ''Cinderella: Three Hundred and Forty-Five Variants of Cinderella, Catskin and, Cap o'Rushes, Abstracted and Tabulated with a Discussion of Medieval Analogues and Notes.''&lt;ref name=&quot;fits&quot;/&gt;

Further [[morphology (folkloristics)|morphology]] studies have continued on this seminal work.&lt;ref name=&quot;fits&quot;/&gt;

''Cinderella'' is classified as [[Aarne-Thompson]] type 510A, the persecuted heroine. Others of this type include ''[[The Sharp Grey Sheep]]'', ''[[The Golden Slipper]]'', ''[[The Story of Tam and Cam]]'', ''[[Rushen Coatie]]'', ''[[Fair, Brown and Trembling]]'' and ''[[Katie Woodencloak]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Heidi Anne Heiner, &quot;[http://www.surlalunefairytales.com/cinderella/other.html Tales Similar to Cinderella]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adaptations==
[[File:Massenet Cendrillon.jpg|right|thumb|[[Jules Massenet|Massenet]]'s opera Cendrillon]]
[[File:CinderAdelphi.jpg|thumb|right|Pantomime at the Adelphi]]
[[File:Cinderella Christmas exhibit, Minden, LA IMG 2295.JPG|right|thumb|Cinderella [[Christmas]] exhibit in [[Minden, Louisiana|Minden]], [[Louisiana]]]]

The story of &quot;Cinderella&quot; has formed the basis of many notable works:

===Opera===
* ''Cendrillon'' (1749) by [[Jean-Louis Laruette]]
* ''Cendrillon'' (1810) by [[Nicolas Isouard]], libretto by [[Charles-Guillaume Étienne]]
* ''[[La Cenerentola]]'' (1817) by [[Gioachino Rossini]]
* ''Aschenbrödel'' (1878) by [[Ferdinand Langer]]
* ''[[Cendrillon]]'' (1894-5) by [[Jules Massenet]], libretto by [[Henri Caïn]]
* ''Cinderella'' (1901-2) by [[Gustav Holst]]
* ''La Cenerentola'' (1902) by [[Ermanno Wolf-Ferrari]]
* ''[[Cendrillon (Viardot)|Cendrillon]]'' (1904) by [[Pauline García-Viardot]]
* ''Aschenbrödel'' (1905) by [[Leo Blech]], libretto by Richard Batka
* ''[[La Cenicienta]]'' (1966) by [[Jorge Peña Hen]]
* ''Cinderella'', a &quot;pantomime opera&quot; (1979) by [[Peter Maxwell Davies]]
* ''Cendrillon'', children's opera (1994) by [[Vladimir Kojoukharov]]

===Ballet===
* ''[[Cinderella (Fitinhof-Schell)|Cinderella]]'' (1893) by Baron Boris Vietinghoff-Scheel
* ''[[Aschenbrödel]]'' (1901) by [[Johann Strauss II]], adapted and completed by [[Josef Bayer]]
* ''Das Märchen vom Aschenbrödel'' (1941) by [[Frank Martin (composer)|Frank Martin]]
* ''Soluschka'' or ''[[Cinderella (Prokofiev)|Cinderella]]'' (1945) by [[Sergei Prokofiev]]
* ''Cinderella'' (1980) by [[Paul Reade]]
* ''Cinderella'' (2010) by [[David Bintley]]
* ''Cinderella - A Tragic Tale'' (2011) by Terence Kohler for Finnish National Ballet, Music by Lera Auerbach
&lt;!-- * ''Cinderella'', choreographed and directed by Stanton Welch for the [[Australian Ballet]] in 1996. Principal artist Miranda Coney danced the lead role on opening night, with Steven Woodgate as Cinderella's stepsister and Damien Welch as Dandini.
We could list a number of famous choreographies on Prokofiev's ballet, but that probably belongs on the Cinderella (Prokofiev) page --&gt;

===Ice Show===
* ''Cinderella'' (2008) by [[Tim A. Duncan]] and Edward Barnwell

===Verse===
* ''Assepoester'' (1981) by [[Jan Kal]]

===Theater===
====Pantomime====
Cinderella debuted as a [[pantomime]] on stage at the [[Theatre Royal, Drury Lane|Drury Lane Theatre]], [[London]] in 1904 and at the [[Adelphi Theatre]] in London in 1905. [[Phyllis Dare]], aged 14 or 15, starred in the latter. In 1926, Cinderella was caught on [[film]] in the [[London Palladium]], starring [[Lennie Dean]] in the lead role.

In the traditional pantomime version the opening scene is set in a forest with a hunt in sway and it is here that Cinderella first meets Prince Charming and his &quot;right-hand man&quot; Dandini, whose name and character come from [[Gioachino Rossini]] opera (''[[La Cenerentola]]''). Cinderella mistakes Dandini for the Prince and the Prince for Dandini.

Her father, Baron Hardup, is under the thumb of his two stepdaughters, the [[Ugly sisters]], and has a servant named [[Buttons (pantomime)|Buttons]], who is Cinderella's friend. Throughout the pantomime, the Baron is continually harassed by the Broker's Men (often named after current politicians) for outstanding rent. The Fairy Godmother must magically create a coach (from a pumpkin), footmen (from mice), a coach driver (from a frog), and a beautiful dress (from rags) for Cinderella to go to the ball. However, she must return by midnight, as it is then that the spell ceases.

A version debuted in the USA at the El Portal Theatre, NoHo in 2010. It was produced by Lythgoe Family Productions of So You Think You Can Dance fame and MPI Entertainment.

====Musical theatre====
* ''Cinderella: The Musical'' by [[Landon Parks]] (book &amp; lyrics) and [[Ioannis Kourtis]] (music) is an English language musical stage show written in 2009, and based on the opera ''Cendrillon'' by [[Jules Massenett]].
* ''[[Cinderella (musical)|Cinderella]]'' by [[Rodgers and Hammerstein]] was produced for television three times:
** ''Cinderella'' (1957) features [[Julie Andrews]] as Cinderella, [[Jon Cypher]], [[Kaye Ballard]], [[Alice Ghostley]] and [[Edie Adams]] (broadcast in color, but only black-and-white [[kinescope]]s exist today).
** ''Cinderella'' (1965) features [[Lesley Ann Warren]] as Cinderella, [[Stuart Damon]] as the Prince, [[Ginger Rogers]] as the Queen, [[Walter Pidgeon]] as the King, [[Celeste Holm]] as the Fairy Godmother and [[Jo Van Fleet]] as the Stepmother.
** ''Cinderella'' (1997) features [[Brandy Norwood|Brandy]] as Cinderella, [[Paolo Montalbán]], [[Whitney Houston]], [[Whoopi Goldberg]], [[Victor Garber]], [[Bernadette Peters]], and [[Jason Alexander]].
:The Rodgers and Hammerstein version has also been staged live at times. A successful version ran in 1958 at the [[London Coliseum]] with a cast including [[Tommy Steele]], Yana, [[Jimmy Edwards]], [[Kenneth Williams]] and Betty Marsden. This version was augmented with several other [[Rodgers and Hammerstein]]'s songs plus a song written by Tommy Steele, &quot;You and Me&quot; which he sang with [[Jimmy Edwards]].  Bobby Howell was the musical director. A 2005 version featured Paolo Montalbán and an ethnically diverse cast, like the 1997 TV version. Broadway Asia Entertainment produced a staged International Tour starring [[Lea Salonga]] and Australian actor Peter Saide in 2008.
* ''[[Mr. Cinders]]'', a musical which opened at the [[Adelphi Theatre]], London in 1929. Filmed in 1934
* ''[[Into the Woods]]'' by [[Stephen Sondheim]] (1988), in which Cinderella is one of many fairy tale characters who take part in the plot. This is partly based on the Grimm Brothers version of &quot;Cinderella,&quot; including the enchanted birds, mother's grave, three balls, and mutilation and blinding of the stepsisters.
* ''[[The Return of The Glass Slipper]]'' by Mary Donelly
* ''Cinderella'' by Kate Hawley is written in the style of British [[pantomime|pantos]].
* ''[[Cindy (musical)|Cindy]]'', a 1964 [[Off-Broadway]] musical composed by [[Johnny Brandon]]
* ''Золушka'' ''(or'' Zolushka'')'', a 2002 made-for-TV Russian pop musical
* ''Cinderella'' (2007), a pantomime written by [[Stephen Fry]] for the [[Old Vic Theatre]]
* ''Cinderella the Musical'' (2008), features J-Pop group [[Morning Musume]] and the [[Takarazuka Revue]]
* ''Cinderella Sillyious Musical'' (2008/09), a musical comedy produced by [[Ross Petty]] for the [[Elgin Theatre]] Toronto
* ''If the shoe fits'' (2011) Riverside Theater Guild

===Films===
Over the decades, hundreds of films have been made that are either direct adaptations from Cinderella or have plots loosely based on the story. Almost every year at least one, but often several such films are produced and released, resulting in Cinderella becoming a work of literature with one of the largest numbers of film adaptations ascribed to it.
* ''[[Cinderella (1899 film)|Cinderella]]'' (1899), the first ever film version, produced in [[France]] by [[Georges Méliès]].
* ''Cinderella'' (1911), a [[silent film]] starring [[Florence La Badie]]
* ''[[Cinderella (1914 film)|Cinderella]]'' (1914), a silent film starring [[Mary Pickford]]
* ''Aschenputtel'' (1922) [[Silhouette animation|silhouette shadow play]] short by [[Lotte Reiniger]].
* ''Cinderella'', an animated [[Laugh-O-Gram Studio|Laugh-O-Gram]] produced by [[Walt Disney]], first released on December 6, 1922. This film was about 7.5 minutes long.
* ''A Kick for Cinderella'' (1925), a [[Bud Fisher]] animation featuring [[Mutt and Jeff]].
* ''Cinderella'' (1925), a [[Walter Lantz]] animation in the [[Dinky Doodle]] series.
* ''[[Poor Cinderella]]'' (1934), a [[Fleischer Studios]] animated short film starring [[Betty Boop]]
* ''[[Cinderella Meets Fella]]'', (1938), a [[Merrie Melodies]] animated short film featuring Egghead, the character who would eventually evolve into [[Elmer Fudd]], as Prince Charming.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yc8AN1feUkA&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[First Love (1939 film)|First Love]]'' (1939), musical modernization with [[Deanna Durbin]] and [[Robert Stack]]
* ''[[Cinderella (1947 film)|Cinderella]]'' (Зо́лушка) (1947), a [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] musical film by [[Lenfilm]] studios, starring [[Erast Garin]] and [[Faina Ranevskaya]]
* ''[[Cinderella (1950 film)|Cinderella]]'', (1950) a [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] animated feature released on February 15, 1950, now considered one of [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]]'s classics. A [[direct-to-video]] sequel, ''[[Cinderella II: Dreams Come True]]'', was released in 2002. A second direct-to-video sequel ''[[Cinderella III: A Twist in Time]]'' was released in 2007.
* ''[[Aschenputtel]]'' (1955), West German film, dubbed into English and released in the USA in 1966 as ''Cinderella''.
* ''[[The Glass Slipper]]'' (1955), feature film with [[Leslie Caron]] and [[Michael Wilding (actor)|Michael Wilding]]
* ''[[Cinderfella]]'' (1960), notable in that the main character is a man, played by [[Jerry Lewis]]
* ''[[Cinderella (musical)#1965 version|Cinderella]]'' (1965), [[Rodgers and Hammerstein]] musical starring [[Ginger Rogers]], [[Walter Pidgeon]], [[Lesley Ann Warren]], and Stuart Damon. Written by Joseph Schrank. 
* The story also inspired an episode of ''[[The Flintstones]]'' entitled, ''Cinderellastone'', which originally aired on October 22, 1964.  In it, [[Fred Flintstone|Fred]], mad because he was not invited to Mr. Slate's party, dreams he is Cinderella (complete with a Fairy Godmother voiced by [[June Foray]]) and goes to the party.  The next day, he gets a big promotion and finds that he wasn't invited due to a clerical oversight.
* ''[[Popelka (1969)|Popelka]]'' (Cinderella, 1969), a Czech musical film
* ''[[Hey, Cinderella!]]'' (1970), a 60-minute film produced by the [[Jim Henson Company]]. This comedy version features Jim Henson's trademark [[The Muppets|Muppets]] (including a small role by [[Kermit the Frog]]).
* ''[[Sinderella Kül Kedisi]]'' (1971) Turkish film with [[Zeynep Değirmencioğlu]]
* ''[[Tři oříšky pro Popelku|Tři oříšky pro Popelku / Drei Haselnüsse für Aschenbrödel]]'' (Three Nuts for Cinderella; known in the UK as Three Gifts for Cinderella), a Czech-German movie released in 1973
* ''[[The Slipper and the Rose]]'', a 1976 British musical film starring [[Gemma Craven]] and [[Richard Chamberlain (actor)|Richard Chamberlain]].
* ''[[Cinderella (1977 film)|Cinderella]]'', a 1977 American [[erotic]] musical comedy starring [[Rainbeaux Smith|Cheryl &quot;Rainbeaux&quot; Smith]], [[Brett Smiley]] and [[Sy Richardson]], directed by [[Michael Pataki]]
* ''[[Cindy (film)|Cindy]]'' (1978), made for television
* ''[[Cinderella (1979 film)|Zolushka]]'', a 1979 musical Soviet animated film.
* ''[[The Tender Tale of Cinderella Penguin]]'' (1981), an [[Academy Award|Oscar]]-nominated animated short from the [[National Film Board of Canada]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NFB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nfb.ca/film/the_tender_tale_of_cinderella_penguin|title=The Tender Tale of Cinderella Penguin|last=Perlman|first=Janet|year=1981|work=NFB.ca|publisher=National Film Board of Canada|accessdate=2009-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Fresh (song)|Fresh]]'' (1985), a music video for the song by [[Kool &amp; the Gang]] features a Cinderella theme.
* ''[[Working Girl]]'' (1988), starring [[Melanie Griffith]], a reworking of the Cinderella story, set in corporate America.
* ''[[Hello Kitty &amp; Friends: Cinderella|Hello Kitty's Cinderella]]'' (1989), an [[anime]] short film starring [[Hello Kitty]], was released in Japan.
* ''[[Hello Kitty &amp; Friends: Cinderella|Hello Kitty - Cinderella]]'' was released in the U.S. as part of the ''[[Hello Kitty and Friends]]'' anime series.
* ''[[Ashpet: An American Cinderella]]'', a 1990 Southern &quot;[[Appalachia]]&quot; version of the story, adapted from the Brothers Grimm, starring [[Louise Anderson]] and directed by [[Tom Davenport]].
* ''[[If the Shoe Fits (film)|If the Shoe Fits]]'' (1990), modern take on the Cinderella story set in France starring [[Rob Lowe]] and [[Jennifer Grey]]
* ''[[Cinderella (1994 film)|Cinderella]]'' (1994), produced by [[Jetlag Productions]] and distributed by [[GoodTimes Entertainment]], premiered on video.
* ''[[Cinderella Monogatari]]'' (1996) Japanese Anime version of Cinderella. Consisted of 26 episodes.
* ''[[Ever After]]'' (1998), starring [[Drew Barrymore]], a post-feminist take on the Cinderella myth.
* ''[[Cinderella (2000 TV film)|Cinderella]]'' (2000), a British television film production set in mid-20th century and starring [[Kathleen Turner]]
* ''[[Confessions of an Ugly Stepsister]]'' (2002), A look at the classic &quot;Cinderella&quot; story from the perspective of one of her 'ugly' stepsister adapted from [[Gregory Maguire]]'s book of the same name&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0267384/ Confessions of an Ugly Stepsister (2002)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[A Cinderella Story]]'' (2004), a modernization featuring [[Hilary Duff]] and [[Chad Michael Murray]]
* A segment of the 2005 Turkish [[anthology film]] ''[[Istanbul Tales]]'' made up of five stories based on popular fairy tales is based on this tale in which Cinderella is a prostitute
* ''[[Cinderelmo]]'', a Cinderella story featuring ''[[Sesame Street]]'s'' [[Elmo]] and [[Keri Russell]]
* ''[[Happily N'Ever After]]'' (2007)
* ''[[Year of the Fish]]'' (2008)
* ''[[Another Cinderella Story]]'' (2008) starring [[Selena Gomez]] and [[Drew Seeley]]
* ''[[Elle: A Modern Cinderella Tale]]'' (2010) starring [[Sterling Knight]] and [[Ashlee Hewitt]]
* ''[[Grazilda]]'' (2010), a Philippine TV series. It tells the story of Cinderella but its focused on what happened after happily ever after.
* ''[[A Cinderella Story: Once Upon A Song]]'' (2011) starring Lucy Hale. A modern day story about Katie (Cinderella), her music, and her Prince Charming.
* ''[[Cinderella (1950 film)#Sequels and other media|Cinderella]]'' (2013) starring [[Amanda Seyfried]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.collider.com/2010/06/30/amanda-seyfried-cinderella-live-action-disney-aline-brosh-mckenna/ Amanda Seyfried Rumored for Live-Action CINDERELLA]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Books===
* Cox M.-R. Cinderella. Three Hundred and Forty-five Variants of Cinderella, Catskin, and Cap 0’ Rushes, abstracted and tabulated, with a discussion of mediaeval analogues, and notes, by Marian Roalfe Cox. L., 1893.
* Rooth A.B. The Cinderella cycle. Lund: Gleerup, 1951.
* 50 Ways To Retell A Story: Cinderella by Alan Peat, Julie Peat and Christopher Storey: Published by Creative Educational Press Ltd 2010. ISBN 978-0-9544755-5-0.

====Novels====
* ''[[Chinese Cinderella]]'' by [[Adeline Yen Mah]]
* ''[[Politically Correct Bedtime Stories]]'' by [[James Finn Garner|James Garner]]. In this version, Cinderella is dressed in a gown &quot;woven of [[silk]] which was stolen from unsuspecting [[silkworms]]&quot; and has all the men fighting to death over her. This enables the women to take over the government and pass the law that women should only wear comfortable clothes.
* ''[[Bound (novel)|Bound]]'' by [[Donna Jo Napoli]]
* ''[[Confessions of an Ugly Stepsister]]'' by [[Gregory Maguire]]. Maguire's style of writing is to twist fairy tales. In his novel, Cinderella is the spoiled child, whose confinement to the heath is self-imposed after the death of her mother.
* ''[[Ella Enchanted]]'' by [[Gail Carson Levine]] Ella was put under a spell at birth that forces her to obey any order given to her. An unusual twist as it features the ball only in the last few chapters, dealing more with Ella's struggle against the curse and because the prince (Charmont) knows Ella before the ball but does not recognize her as she is in disguise.
* ''[[Cinderellis and the Glass Hill]]'' by [[Gail Carson Levine]]
* ''[[I was a Rat! or The Scarlet Slippers]]'' by [[Philip Pullman]]
* ''[[Bella at Midnight]]'' by [[Diane Stanley]]
* ''[[Just Ella]]'' by [[Margaret Peterson Haddix]]
* ''[[Nine Coaches Waiting]]'' by [[Mary Stewart]]
* ''[[The Glass Slipper]]'' by [[Eleanor Farjeon]]
* ''[[Phoenix and Ashes]]'' by [[Mercedes Lackey]]
* ''[[When Cinderella Falls Down Dead]]'' by [[Joshua Gabe and Grayian Phoenix]]. In this version, Cinderella is reembodied into the 21st Century in the body of a young girl.
* ''[[Witches Abroad]]'' by [[Terry Pratchett]]
* The Midnight Dancers by Regina Doman makes references to the fairy tale. The heroine Rachel is exploited by her stepmother and stepsisters, and routinely sneaks out to dance.
* ''[[Godmother, The Secret Cinderella Story]]'' by [[Carolyn Turgeon]]. Lil is the fairy that was given the task of helping Cinderella get to the ball and the prince, but she is trapped in the body of an aging elderly woman for the huge mistake she made. To redeem her mistake, she tries to get two single New Yorkers together to a ball.
* ''[[Her Feet Chime]]'' by [[Rumki Chowdhury]]. In this Bangladeshi version, Asha's evil aunt and cousin turn her into a servant, renaming her Thamsha, and breaking all family relations with her. Asha's servant friends help her wear a ginger garment and meet her Nawabzada, Bengali Prince, at a palace gathering.
* ''[[Mrs. Beast]]'' by [[Pamela Ditchoff]]
* ''[[Cindy Ella]]'' by [[Robin Palmer]]
* ''[[The Fairy Godmother]]'' by [[Mercedes Lackey]]
* [[Jim C. Hines]] Princess series of book include Danielle Whiteshore (Cinderella) after her marriage to the prince.
* Cinderella's Secret Diary (Book 1: Lost) by Ron Vitale tells the story of what happens to Cinderella after her marriage to the Prince and who the Fairy Godmother truly is.

====Short stories====
* ''[[Catch the Moon]]'' by [[Judith Ortiz Cofer]]
* ''[[Rosie's Dance]]'' by [[Emma Hardesty]]

====Comic books====
* Cinderella appears as [[List of Fables characters#Cinderella|a character]] in [[Bill Willingham]]'s Vertigo series, ''[[Fables (comic)|Fables]]''. Cinderella (or &quot;Cindy&quot;, as her fellow Fables call her) is the third and final of [[List of Fables characters#Prince Charming|Prince Charming]]'s ex-wives and is Fabletown's resident super spy. Her cover is the ownership of her own shoe store, the Glass Slipper, and she maintains a bitter persona in order to throw off the suspicions of the rest of her community. She also appeared in her own spin-off comic, ''[[Cinderella: From Fabletown with Love]]''.
* ''[[Cinderalla]]'' by [[Junko Mizuno]]
* ''[[Ludwig Revolution]]'' by [[Kaori Yuki]]. In this version, Cinderella's feet are too large and the series' protagonist lends her his shoe for the evening, acting as her Fairy Godmother. Also, the Prince doesn't hold the ball to find his wife, but to find the woman with large feet who killed his pet lizard, Isolde.

===Songs===
Some popular songs that make reference to the story of Cinderella include:

* ''Half Past Midnight'' a single by Canadian rock group [[The Staccatos]], that released 1967.
* ''Cinderella Stay Awhile'' a song by [[Michael Jackson]] from his 1975 album ''[[Forever, Michael]]''.
* ''[[Cinderella (Vince Gill song)|Cinderella]]'' by [[Vince Gill]], released 1987.
* ''[[Hey Cinderella]]'' (1993) by [[Suzy Bogguss]].
* ''[[Cinderella Blue]]'' (1994) by Robert Lucas of the band [[Canned Heat]].&lt;ref&gt;http://music.aol.com/song/robert-lucas/cinderella-blue/978736&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Cinderella Undercover]]'' (1998) by [[Oingo Boingo]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amazon.com/Cinderella-Undercover/dp/B001NTNJY6&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Snoopfella'' a song by [[Snoop Dogg]] from his album ''[[No Limit Top Dogg]]'' (1999).
* ''Cinderella'' a song by [[Britney Spears]] from her 2001 album ''[[Britney (album)|Britney]]''.
* ''[[Cinderella (Sweetbox song)|Cinderella]]'', a 2001 single by [[Sweetbox]].
* ''[[Cinderella (Shakaya song)|Cinderella]]'' by [[Shakaya]], released 2002.
* ''[[Cinderella (The Cheetah Girls song)|Cinderella]]'' a 2003 single by [[The Cheetah Girls (recording artists)|The Cheetah Girls]].
* ''The Glass Slipper'' by [[The Dresden Dolls]] from debut live album ''[[A Is for Accident]]'', that first released in 2003 and leaked on the internet in 2009.
* ''Cinderella'' by [[Tata Young]] from her 2004 album ''[[I Believe (Tata Young album)|I Believe]]''.
* ''Cinderella'' song by [[Steven Curtis Chapman]] from ''[[This Moment (album)|This Moment]]'' (2007).
* ''A Cinderella Story'' by [[Mudvayne]]'s fourth album ''[[The New Game]]'' (2008).
* ''[[A Dustland Fairytale]]'' a single by [[The Killers]] from their third album ''[[Day &amp; Age]]'' (2008).
* ''Fairytale'' by [[Sara Bareilles]] from her album live album ''[[Between the Lines: Sara Bareilles Live at the Fillmore]]'' (2008).
* ''[[It's Midnight Cinderella]]'' by [[Garth Brooks]]
* ''Cinderella Man'' by [[Eminem]] from his album ''[[Recovery (Eminem album)|Recovery]]'' (2010)
* ''Romeo and Cinderella'' from ''[[Hatsune Miku: Project DIVA]]'', released in 2010.
* ''Cinderella Romance'' by [[Hatsune Miku]]
* ''Cendrillon'' by [[Hatsune Miku]] and [[KAITO]] (a retelling of &quot;Cinderella&quot; with a dark twist)
* ''[[Cinderella's Curls]]'' by [[Waxing Gibbous]].
* ''Mayonaka no Door'' by [[Liu Yifei]] (first ending of ''[[Demashita! Powerpuff Girls Z]]'')
* ''[[Not Your Cinderella]]'' by [[Catherine Britt]]
* ''[[One Headlight]]'' by [[The Wallflowers]]
* ''[[Stealing Cinderella]] by [[Chuck Wicks]]
* ''[[Dark Fantasy (song)|Dark Fantasy]]'' by [[Kanye West]] featuring [[Nicki Minaj]] from Kanye's fifth album [[My Beautiful Dark Twisted Fantasy]] (2010)
* ''There is Music in You'' by [[Rodgers &amp; Hammerstein]]
* ''Umbrella'' (Remix), originally by [[Rihanna]] &amp; [[Jay-Z]] but remixed by [[Chris Brown (American singer)|Chris Brown]] and retitled &quot;Cinderella&quot;
* ''[[C\C (Cinderella\Complex)]]'' by [[High-King]]
* ''Cinderella 신데렐라'' by Korean pop singer [[Seo In-Young]]
* ''Cendrillon'' (The French name for Cinderella) by French rock group [[Téléphone]]
* ''[[Rindercella]]'' by [[Archie Campbell]]
* ''Cinderella'' by [[Sajjad Ali]]
* ''[[21Ji Made no Cinderella]]'' by [[Berryz Koubou]]
* ''[[Hadashi no Cinderella Boy]]'' by [[NEWS]]
* ''[[Shi no Butou~Romance of the Cendrillon]]'' by [[Malice Mizer]]
* ''[[Cinderfella Dana Dane]]'' by [[Dana Dane]]
* ''[[Cinderela]]'' by the late Portuguese singer [[Carlos Paião]]
* ''[[Hannah Montana Forever#Track listing|Barefoot Cinderella]] by [[Hannah Montana]]
* ''Cinderella'' by [[Damien Burner Blazé Jackson]]
* ''Cinderella'' by [[Steven Curtis Chapman]]

====Cinderella jumprope song====
There is a [[jumprope]] song for children that involves Cinderella&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=The British Library|title=Skipping games - Cinderella, dressed in yellow|url=http://www.bl.uk/learning/langlit/playground/browseadultview.html#cm=Videos&amp;gm=Skipping&amp;id=120554&amp;id2=121109|work=Playtimes|publisher=The British Library|accessdate=5 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Cinderella dressed in yellow, went upstairs to kiss her fellow,
by mistake she kissed a snake, how many doctors will it take?
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 etc.  (Go to 20 then go down to the next line)&lt;br&gt;
Cinderella dressed in blue, went upstairs to tie her shoe,
made a mistake and tied a knot, how many knots will she make?
1, 2, 3, etc.&lt;br&gt;
Cinderella dressed in green, went downtown to buy a ring,
made a mistake and bought a fake, how many days before it breaks?
1, 2, 3, etc.&lt;br&gt;
Cinderella dressed in lace, went upstairs to fix her face,
oh no oh no, she found a blemish, how many powder puffs till she's finished?
1, 2, 3, etc.&lt;br&gt;
Cinderella dressed in silk, went outside to get some milk,
made a mistake and fell in the lake, how many more till she gets a break?
1, 2, 3, etc.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The counting continues as long as the jumper avoids missing a jump.  If they do then the counting starts again.

Variations:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Cinderella dressed in yellow, went downtown to meet her fellow (or &quot;to buy some mustard&quot;).
On the way, her girdle busted.  All the people were disgusted.&lt;br&gt;
(Heard in Jackson Heights, [[Queens]], late 1950s)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Cinderella dressed in yellow, went upstairs to kiss her fellow. how many kisses did she give him?&lt;br&gt;
(Heard in [[Northern Ireland]])&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Cinderella dressed in yell'a, went downstairs to kiss a fell'a. Made a mistake and kissed a snake, how many stitches (or &quot;doctors&quot;) did it take?&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Cinderella dressed in yell'a, went downtown to kiss her fell'a. How many kisses did he get? 1,2,3 etc.

(Heard in Leesburg, Florida, Early 2009)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Cinderella dressed in yell'a, tell me the name of your sweet fella a,b,c,d,e,f,g,h,i,j,k,,l,m,n,o,p,q,r,s,t,u,v,w,x,y,z
(The jumper runs out when the first letter of their crush or boyfriend/girlfriend's name is called and shouts their name at the same time)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Video games===
In 2005, Disney released ''[[Disney's Cinderella: Magical Dreams]]'' for the Nintendo [[Game Boy Advance]].
Cinderella was also featured in Disney's / Square's video game Kingdom Hearts&lt;ref&gt;Anise Hollingshead, &quot;[http://gameboy.gamezone.com/gzreviews/r26918.htm Review of ''Disney's Cinderella: Magical Dreams''],&quot; ''GameZone'' (10/03/2005).&lt;/ref&gt; where she is one of the seven princesses of heart which are needed to open the door to darkness. She, along with her entire world, also are in Kingdom Hearts: Birth by Sleep.

In 2011, ''MoaCube'' released the [[visual novel]] ''[[Cinders (visual novel)|Cinders]]''. A darker adaption of the Cinderella story.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://moacube.com/news/so-whats-cinders-about/|title=Cinders|author = &quot;TeeGee&quot;|publisher= MoaCube|date = 2011-06-27|accessdate=2011-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In other languages===
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
!Language!!Name!!Romanisation
|-
|[[Arabic language|Arabic]] || '''رودوبس''' || ''Rūdūbis''
|-
|[[Bulgarian language|Bulgarian]] || '''Пепеляшка''' || ''Pepelyashka''
|-
|[[Catalan language|Catalan]] 
|colspan=2| '''Ventafocs'''
|-
|[[Chinese language|Chinese]] || '''灰姑娘''' || ''Huīgūniang''
|-
|[[Croatian language|Croatian]] 
|colspan=2| '''Pepeljuga'''
|-
|[[Czech language|Czech]] 
|colspan=2|  '''Popelka'''
|-
|[[Danish language|Danish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Askepot'''
|-
|[[Dutch language|Dutch]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Assepoester'''
|-
|[[English language|English]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cinderella'''
|-
|[[Estonian language|Estonian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Tuhkatriinu'''
|-
|[[Filipino Language|Filipino]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Sinderela'''
|-
|[[Finnish language|Finnish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Tuhkimo'''
|-
|[[French language|French]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cendrillon'''
|-
|[[German language|German]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Aschenputtel'''
|-
|[[Greek language|Greek]] || '''Σταχτοπούτα''' || ''Stachtopoúta''
|-
|[[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] ||  '''סינדרלה'''\'''לכלוכית''' || ''Sinderela''\''Lichluchit''
|-
|[[Hindi language|Hindi]] ||  '''सिंडिरेल्ला''' || ''Sindirēllā''
|-
|[[Hungarian language|Hungarian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Hamupipőke'''&lt;!--Hamupipöke--&gt;
|-
|[[Indonesian language|Indonesian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cinderella'''
|-
|[[Irish language|Irish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cinderella'''
|-
|[[Icelandic language|Icelandic]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Öskubuska'''
|-
|[[Italian language|Italian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cenerentola'''
|-
|[[Japanese language|Japanese]] || '''シンデレラ''' || ''Shinderera''
|-
|[[Korean language|Korean]] || '''신데렐라''' || ''Sinderella''
|-
|[[Latvian language|Latvian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Pelnrušķīte'''
|-
|[[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Pelenė'''
|-
|[[Macedonian language|Macedonian]] || '''Пепелашка''' || ''Pepelashka''
|-
|[[Norwegian language|Norwegian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Askepott'''
|-
|[[Persian Language|Persian]] || '''سیندرلا''' || ''Sinderela''
|-
|[[Polish language|Polish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Kopciuszek'''
|-
|[[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cinderela'''
|-
|[[Romanian language|Romanian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cenuşăreasă'''&lt;!--Cenușăreasa--&gt;
|-
|[[Russian language|Russian]] || '''Золушка''' || ''Zolushka''
|-
|[[Serbian language|Serbian]] || '''Пепeљуга''' || ''Pepeljuga''
|-
|[[Slovak language|Slovak]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Popoluška'''
|-
|[[Slovenian language|Slovenian]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Pepelka'''
|-
|[[Swedish language|Swedish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Askungen'''
|-
|[[Spanish language|Spanish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Cenicienta'''
|-
|[[Thai language|Thai]]  || '''ซินเดอเรลล่า''' || ''Cinderella''
|-
|[[Turkish language|Turkish]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Külkedisi'''
|-
|[[Vietnamese language|Vietnamese]]  
|colspan=2|  '''Công Chúa Lọ Lem'''
|-
|[[Ukrainian language|Ukrainian]] || '''Попелюшка''' || ''Popelyushka''
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Folklore}}
* [[Cinderella effect]]
* [[Cinderella complex]]

{{clear}}
==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{wikisource}}
{{Wikisource1911Enc|Cinderella}}
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext00/pntmn10.txt Cenerentola in Pentamerone by Giambattista Basile (English translation)]
* [http://digitalgallery.nypl.org/nypldigital/dgkeysearchresult.cfm?parent_id=504396&amp;word= Photos and illustrations from early ''Cinderella'' stage versions], including one with [[Ellaline Terriss]] and one with [[Phyllis Dare]]

{{Brothers Grimm}}

[[Category:Fairy tales]]
[[Category:Brothers Grimm]]
[[Category:Works by Charles Perrault]]
[[Category:Fictional princesses]]
[[Category:Fictional orphans]]
[[Category:Characters in fairy tales]]
[[Category:European fairy tales]]

{{Link GA|th}}

[[ar:سندريلا]]
[[zh-min-nan:O͘-cha-bó͘]]
[[bg:Пепеляшка]]
[[br:Luduennig]]
[[ca:La Ventafocs]]
[[cs:Popelka]]
[[da:Askepot]]
[[de:Aschenputtel]]
[[et:Tuhkatriinu]]
[[el:Σταχτοπούτα]]
[[es:Cenicienta]]
[[eu:Errauskine]]
[[fa:سیندرلا]]
[[fr:Cendrillon]]
[[ga:Luaithríona]]
[[gu:સિન્ડ્રેલા]]
[[ko:신데렐라]]
[[hr:Pepeljuga]]
[[id:Cinderella]]
[[it:Cenerentola]]
[[he:סינדרלה]]
[[la:Cinerella]]
[[lt:Pelenė]]
[[hu:Hamupipőke (mese)]]
[[mk:Пепелашка]]
[[ms:Cinderella]]
[[my:စင်ဒရဲလား]]
[[nl:Assepoester]]
[[ja:シンデレラ]]
[[no:Askepott]]
[[pl:Kopciuszek (baśń)]]
[[pt:Cinderela]]
[[ro:Cenușăreasa]]
[[ru:Золушка]]
[[simple:Cinderella]]
[[sl:Pepelka]]
[[sr:Pepeljuga]]
[[sh:Pepeljuga]]
[[fi:Tuhkimo]]
[[sv:Askungen]]
[[kab:Cendrillon]]
[[th:ซินเดอเรลล่า]]
[[tr:Külkedisi]]
[[uk:Попелюшка]]
[[zh:灰姑娘]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
