<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7361306" ns="0" title="You Got the Love"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox single
| Name           = You Got the Love
| Artist         = [[The Source (band)|The Source]] / [[Candi Staton]]
| Released       = 1986
| Format         = Vinyl Single
| Genre          = [[Disco]]
| Label          = [[Streetwave Records|Streetwave]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pFgbtb_qozM The Source - You Got the Love, video]. [[YouTube]].&lt;/ref&gt;
| Writer         = Stephens/Harris/Bellamy
}}
{{Infobox single
| Name           = You Got the Love
| Cover          = The Source (Feat. Candi Staton) - You Got The Love.jpg
| Artist         = [[The Source (musician)|The Source]] / [[Candi Staton]]
| Released       = 21 January 1991 &lt;small&gt;(UK)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br /&gt;1996–1997 (Re-release)&lt;br /&gt;6 February 2006 &lt;small&gt;(UK)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(Re-release)
| Format         = CD single
| Genre          = [[House music|House]]
| Length         = 3:30 (Now Voyager Radio Edit)&lt;br /&gt;6:07 (Now Voyager Mix)
| Label          = [[Positiva Records|Pos/itiva]]
| Writer         = TrueLove/Stevens/Harris
| Producer       = [[The Source (musician)|The Source]]
}}

&quot;'''You Got the Love'''&quot; is a 1986 single by the band [[The Source (band)|The Source]] and [[Candi Staton]]. One of its many remixers also adopted the name [[The Source (musician)|The Source]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.discogs.com/artist/Source%2C+The+(7) You Got the Love by The Source, release]. [[Discogs]].&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, the song was recorded by English [[Soul music|soul]] singer [[Joss Stone]] for her fourth [[studio album]], &quot;''[[Colour Me Free!]]''&quot; released in October 2009. In November 2009, another cover version was released as a single by English [[indie rock]] [[music group|band]], [[Florence &amp; The Machine]].

==Details==
The original version is a soul/disco/gospel track (released in the UK by Streetwave in 1986) written by Anthony B. Stephens, Arnecia Michelle Harris and John Bellamy. It featured an a cappella version utilised by Paul Simpson for a remix of the [[Adeva]] song &quot;Musical Freedom&quot; in 1989. The most well known house mix by DJ Eren was released in 1991 and layered the vocal track over an instrumental version of the [[Frankie Knuckles]]/[[Jamie Principle]] house song &quot;[[Your Love (Frankie Knuckles song)|Your Love]]&quot; itself a stripped down version of the italo-disco track &quot;Feels Good (Carrots and Beets)&quot; by Electra featuring Tara Butler. The original Candi Staton track had been recorded for a [[Direct-to-video|video-only]] 1980s documentary about an obese man who was trying to lose weight. When approached by The Source, Candi said she couldn't remember having recorded a song called &quot;You Got the Love&quot;. It was only later that she realised she had performed the song years earlier for the documentary. The producers of the video had selected the song for her to sing, but as they had no funds to pay her, they donated half of the copyright and publishing to Candi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://arts.guardian.co.uk/filmandmusic/story/0,,1737687,00.html | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=I was so drunk I fell on to the stage | first=Sophie | last=Heawood | date=24 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DJ Eren track was originally released in 1991, and reached number 4 in the [[UK Singles Chart]]. It was remixed and re-issued in 1997 (including the Now Voyager mix), this time reaching number 3, the song's highest position, and then re-issued again in 2006 with new mixes by the [[Shapeshifters (band)|Shapeshifters]] among others, reaching number 7. The 2006 mix also featured more lyrics than the first two versions.

The &quot;Now Voyager mix&quot; (released in 1996 and 1997) of the track was featured in the final moments of the ''[[Sex and the City]]'' [[An American Girl in Paris, Part Deux (SATC episode)|series finale]] in 2004. The track's new mixes and the inclusion of the track in the show is one factor of its 2006 reissue. The ''Original Bootleg Radio Mix'' of the track was also featured in the film ''[[Layer Cake (film)|Layer Cake]]'' in the club where Sidney talks to the film's protagonist as he looks on at Sidney's girlfriend.

In 2007, Manchester Band [[The Longcut]] recorded a version as part of their double A-Side release on Melodic Records

&quot;Florence and the Machine&quot; version was released 16 November 2009, from the acclaimed album &quot;Lungs&quot;, and is considered to be the song that launched their career

The song has a clear Christian message: Staton talks of giving up on God, only to discover that He has &quot;got the love I need to see me through&quot;, and that &quot;the Saviour's love is real&quot;. The theme behind the song is one of uplift and empowerment.

==Music video==
The 1997 video features the &quot;Now Voyager mix&quot; and portrays a black man carrying a cross, and being guided by an angel and tempted by the Devil.

The 2006 version features the &quot;Now Voyager mix&quot; in a black and white video. Set in London, it portrays an [[Angelic]] young man watching out for the poor, lonely and vulnerable in the streets, subways and gardens.

==Single listings==
===1986 version===
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Extended Vocal)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Radio Edit)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Club House)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (House Apella)

===1991 version===
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Eren's Bootleg Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Morning Time Mix)

===1996 UK version (1)===
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Now Voyager Radio Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Now Voyager Mix)

===1996 UK version (2)===
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Now Voyager Radio Edit)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Shapeshifters Radio Edit)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Extended New Voyager Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Shapeshifter Main Vocal Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Truelove, Lys &amp; Gigi Remix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Paradise Soul Mix)
#Enhanced video

===1997 Australian version===
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Now Voyager Radio Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Original Radio Edit)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Truelove, Lys, &amp; Gigi Remix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Shapeshifters Main Vocal Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Shapeshifters Alt. Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Now Voyager Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Original Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Paradise Soul Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Rhythm Masters Classic Vocal Mix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Asle Bjorn Remix)
#&quot;You Got the Love&quot; (Wayne G Circuit Anthem Mix)

==Florence and the Machine version==
{{Infobox single
| Name           = You Got the Love
| Cover          = YGTL.jpg
| Artist         = [[Florence and the Machine|Florence + the Machine]]
| Album          = [[Lungs (album)|Lungs]]
| Released       = 5 January 2009&lt;br/&gt;16 November 2009 &lt;small&gt;(re-release)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.buzzjack.com/forums/index.php?showtopic=100654 |title=New Release Schedule (Physical) : Monday 28 September – BuzzJack Music Forum |publisher=Buzzjack.com |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2011 &lt;small&gt;(United States)&lt;/small&gt;
| Format         = [[Music download|Digital download]], CD single, [[gramophone record|vinyl]] (7 inch)
| Recorded       =
| Genre          = [[Indie pop]], [[Soul music|soul]]
| Length         = 2:48
| Writer         = Anthony B. Stephens
| Label          = [[Universal Island]]
| Producer       = [[Charlie Hugall]]
| Last single    = &quot;[[Drumming Song]]&quot;&lt;br /&gt;(2009)
| This single    = &quot;'''You've Got the Love'''&quot;&lt;br /&gt;(2009)
| Next single    = &quot;[[#You Got the Dirtee Love|You Got the Dirtee Love]]&quot;&lt;br /&gt;(2010)
| Misc           = {{Extra track listing
  | Album          = [[Lungs (album)|Lungs]]
  | Type           = single
  | Tracks         =
# &quot;[[Dog Days Are Over]]&quot;
# &quot;[[Rabbit Heart (Raise It Up)]]&quot;
# &quot;I'm Not Calling You a Liar&quot;
# &quot;Howl&quot;
# &quot;[[Kiss with a Fist]]&quot;
# &quot;Girl with One Eye&quot;
# &quot;[[Drumming Song]]&quot;
# &quot;Between Two Lungs&quot;
# &quot;[[Cosmic Love]]&quot;
# &quot;My Boy Builds Coffins&quot;
# &quot;Hurricane Drunk&quot;
# &quot;Blinding&quot;
# &quot;'''You've Got the Love'''&quot;
}}
}}

&quot;'''You've Got the Love'''&quot; is the fifth single released by the band [[Florence and the Machine]]; the band consists of Florence Welch (the lead singer) and a backing band made of session musicians, from their 2009 Brit award-winning debut album ''[[Lungs (album)|Lungs]]''. It was first released on 1 December 2008 as the [[A-side and B-side|B-side]] of their second single &quot;[[Dog Days Are Over]]&quot;. It was then later released as a digital download only single on 5 January 2009 in the United Kingdom only, after the mass praise it received during the release of &quot;Dog Days Are Over&quot;. It is a cover version of the song &quot;You Got the Love&quot; by [[The Source (musician)|The Source]] featuring [[Candi Staton]] with a slightly changed name. After being released well before ''Lungs'' was finally recorded and released, it was later featured on the album as its bonus track.

The single was given a re-release on physical format on 16 November 2009 in the United Kingdom. For the reissue a music video was shot.

===Background===
The track, which is significantly shorter than the original, was produced by [[Charlie Hugall]], who also produced three other tracks on ''Lungs''. Hugall was also involved in the bass and percussion development of the song. The track features Isabella Summers on piano, Christopher Lloyd Hayden on drums, Tom Moth on harp, Rob Ackroyd on guitar and Florence Welch on vocals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.discogs.com/Florence-The-Machine-Lungs/release/1872408 |title=Florence + The Machine* – Lungs (CD, Album, Enh, Ltd, Dig + CD, Album, Ltd, Dig) at Discogs |publisher=Discogs.com |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Florence Welch describing her inspiration behind covering &quot;one of her favourite songs ever&quot;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;As a kid, going to clubs and raves, this song made me feel love. At Bestival last year we were top of the bill on that stage, so we were thinking of an amazing cover we could do, and I thought of [[Candi Staton]]. Even in rehearsals, playing it was just the most euphoric feeling. Then playing it live and seeing everyone's arms in the air, and the faces – it was the best feeling ever! I was dressed as a genie sea-monster, and I remember looking at my guitarist as we played the first chords, and then there was the reaction and it was like tearing ourselves open and just exploding on the crowd, and then all did it back. It's a feeling you couldn't express. I'm really excited that now in our live shows I'm going to be playing one of my favourite songs ever, loads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.florenceandthemachine.net/news/24-30/florence-on-lungs-part-three/0-6 |title=Official Website &amp;#124; News &amp;#124; Gigs &amp;#124; Music &amp;#124; Blogs – News |publisher=Florence And The Machine |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&quot;You've Got the Love&quot;, a fan favourite of the band has been played at numerous festivals around the United Kingdom during 2008 and 2009. Including the Bestival, [[Glastonbury Festival|Glastonbury]], Way Out West, [[Brighton]], Electric Picnic, [[Leeds]], Smash &amp; Grab and with an acoustic version being performed at a festival in [[Reading, Berkshire|Reading]]. It's also been performed Live In Ibiza on [[BBC Radio 1]] and at the BBC Live Big Weekend.

===Critical response===
Reviewers have also commented on this song during reviews of &quot;Dog Days Are Over&quot;. [[MusicOMH]] commented on the song by saying that &quot;Following with her tradition of some finely chosen cover versions, there's even an excellent rendition of The Source's You Got the Love.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musicomh.com/singles/florence-and-the-machine-2_1108.htm Florence and the Machine MusicOMH Review]. [[MusicOMH]] review.&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Contactmusic.com]] also commented on the song by saying that &quot;The B-side cover of [[The Source (musician)|The Source]] ft. [[Candi Staton]]'s &quot;You Got the Love&quot; is equally strong.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.contactmusic.com/new/home.nsf/singlereview/florence-and-the-machine-dog-days-are-overx09x12x08 Florence and the Machine dog days are over - contactmusic review]. [[Contactmusic.com]].&lt;/ref&gt; Dailymusicguide.com also positively reviewed the single, writing, 
&quot;Florence + The Machine have used the format of the original remix but have certainly breathed new life into this old classic. With Florence Welch's distinctive voice she makes this song her own. The inclusion of a harp only adds to the gentle sway effect produced by the track, bursting gently in without malice at around eighteen seconds in.
The song's lyrics are empowering: Florence's heavenly voice has a vulnerable quality which, as it has with relatively short career so far, grows stronger through You've Got The Love's verse and chorus. It's empowering, liberating and moving all at the same time, not least conveyed by the emotion in Welch's vocals. Rating: 4/5&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymusicguide.com/Reviews/florence-and-the-machine-youve-got-the-love-single-review-26022009-2043.aspx Florence and the Machine &quot;You've Got The Love&quot; - single review]. www.dailymusicguide.com.&lt;/ref&gt; Altsounds.com reviewed the track, writing, &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; is a standard pop number that does something in a non-standard fashion – it isn't afraid of looking at its simplistic melodic hooks and accepting it with a touch of lyrical honesty and contemplative imprint.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hangout.altsounds.com/reviews/107878-florence-and-the-machine-a-lot-of-love-a-lot-of-blood-ep.html |title=Altsounds.com Reviews &amp;#124; Florence and the Machine – A Lot of Love, A Lot of Blood [EP&amp;#93; |publisher=Hangout.altsounds.com |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music video===
Despite originally being released as a single almost nine months earlier, the band announced on 18 September 2009 that a music video would be made for the song and would be shot on 21 September 2009 in London. It features Welch in a white, sparkly leotard dancing on a large [[moon]]-shaped platform suspended over a nightclub, an homage to [[Studio 54]]. The video later shows many people beneath her dancing to the song. The video that will air on United Kingdom television has a different version of the song to the one on the album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.florenceandthemachine.net/news/0-6/appear-in-the-video-for-youve-got-the-love |title=Official Website &amp;#124; News &amp;#124; Gigs &amp;#124; Music &amp;#124; Blogs – News |publisher=Florence And The Machine |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Track listing===
====Original release (digital download)====
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; (produced by [[Charlie Hugall]], mixed by [[Cenzo Townshend]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.soundonsound.com/sos/mar10/articles/it_0310.htm |title=Secrets Of The Mix Engineers: Cenzo Townshend |publisher=Soundonsound.com |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;) – 2:58

====UK Single====
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; – 2:50
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; ([[Tom Middleton]] remix) – 7:54
# &quot;[[Addicted To Love (song)|Addicted To Love]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/B002U086VI/ Florence and the Machine &quot;You've Got The Love&quot;, single]. &quot;[[Amazon.com]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; – 3:20

====Re-release====
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; – 2:50
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; (Jamie xx re-work feat. [[The xx]]) – 5:43
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; ([[Tom Middleton]] remix) – 7:54
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; (Steve Pitron &amp; Max Sanna remix&lt;ref&gt;[http://soundcloud.com/maxsanna/florence-the-machine-you-got-the-love-max-sanna-steve-pitron-club-mix &quot;Listen to the Steve Pitron &amp; Max Sanna Remix on Soundcloud&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;) – 6:21
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; (Live from [[Abbey Road Studios|Abbey Road]]) – 3:45
# &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; ([[Fraser T. Smith|Fraser T Smith]]) remix

===Chart performance===
Upon the original release of &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; it peaked at #158 on the [[UK Singles Chart]]. The song later re-entered the singles chart at #124 and moved up to #68 in the next weeks chart. The following week it fell seven places to #75 before dropping out of the Top 100.

It then re-entered the chart, two weeks later on 22 August 2009 at #59, where it peaked before dropping out the Top 100 again. Its re-entry pattern then continued when it re-entered three weeks later on 12 September 2009 at #88.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chartstats.com/songinfo.php?id=34530 |title=UK Singles &amp; Albums Chart Archive |publisher=Chart Stats |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The song peaked at #16, after the single's actual release in 2009.

It spent a total of eight weeks within in the top 100, longer than both previous singles &quot;[[Kiss with a Fist]]&quot; and &quot;[[Dog Days Are Over]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chartstats.com/artistinfo.php?id=12139 |title=Florence &amp; The Machine |publisher=Chart Stats |date= |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 January 2010, &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; climbed 18 places to a new peak of #13 in the UK singles chart and on 31 December 2009 and its use in the last episode of [[Gavin &amp; Stacey]] on the 1 January 2010. One week later on 10 January 2010, the song peaked at #5 in its 34th week in the UK singles chart, becoming Florence's most successful song and first ever top ten hit. Following her BRIT Performance in February 2010, &quot;You've Got The Love&quot; climbed to #12, just missing out on the Top 10. It has so far spent 30 weeks in the UK Top 40 Singles Chart. Making it definitely her most successful single so far.

On 8 January 2010, &quot;You've Got the Love&quot; climbed up the [[Irish Singles Chart]], reaching a peak of #21, whereas before it had only reached #30. After falling out of the charts, on 26 February 2010, &quot;You've Got The Love&quot; re-entered the Irish Singles Chart, reaching a new current peak of #16.

In January, You've got the Love entered the Australian singles [[ARIA Charts]] at number 50, and remained within the top 50 for a large amount of time. In February and March, it was consistently increasing positions, where it eventually reached a peak of number 30. Due to popular T.V shows like [[Domestic Blitz]] and [[MasterChef Australia]] using it in commercials, the song rapidly climbed to number 17, on the 4th of April, and to its highest peak of number 9 on the 11th of April. It hasn't been released as a physical single, and has relied solely on digital sales, where it has peaked at number 5.

In New Zealand the single began receiving mainstream radio airplay causing it to rise to 50{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} on the airplay chart, however the airplay has since dropped. In Australia the track has reached the top ten, currently peaking at number nine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ariacharts.com.au/pages/charts_display.asp?chart=1U50 Florence And The Machine &quot;You've Got The Love&quot; on ARIA Charts]. [[ARIA Charts]].&lt;/ref&gt; The song was also used in [[MasterChef Australia]] promos.

====Charts====
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
!style=&quot;col&quot;|Chart (2009)
!style=&quot;col&quot;|Peak&lt;br/&gt;position
|-
|[[New Zealand|New Zealand Airplay]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radioscope.net.nz/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2631&amp;Itemid=32 |title=RadioScope100 &amp;#124; 20 December 2009 – RadioScope New Zealand |publisher=Radioscope.net.nz |date=20 December 2009 |accessdate=11 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|50
|-
!style=&quot;col&quot;|Chart (2010)
!style=&quot;col&quot;|Peak&lt;br/&gt;position
|-
{{singlechart|Australia|9|artist=Florence + The Machine|song=You've Got The Love|accessdate=4 November 2010}}
|-
{{singlechart|Belgium (Flanders)|25|artist=Florence + The Machine|song=You've Got The Love|accessdate=4 November 2010}}
|-
{{singlechart|Denmark Airplay|7|artist=Florence + The Machine|song=You've Got The Love|year=2009|week=45}} 
|-
{{singlechart|Billboardeuropeanhot100|20|artist=Florence and the Machine|artistid=1010895|accessdate=4 November 2010}}
|-
{{singlechart|Germany|52|artist=Florence%B1The Machine|song=You've Got The Love|accessdate=4 November 2010}}
|-
{{singlechart|Ireland|16|year=2010|week=08}}
|-
{{singlechart|UKchartstats|5|artist=Florence &amp; The Machine|song=You've Got The Love|songid=34452|accessdate=4 November 2010}}
|-
!style=&quot;col&quot;|Chart (2011)
!style=&quot;col&quot;|Peak&lt;br/&gt;position
|-
{{singlechart|Billboardalternativesongs|34|artist=Florence and the Machine|artistid=1010895|accessdate=11 July 2011}}
|-
|}

====End-of-year charts====
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
!Chart (2009)
!Position
|-
|[[UK Singles Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;UK2009year&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ukchartsplus.co.uk/UKChartsPlusYE2009.pdf |title=Charts Plus Year end 2009 |publisher=Charts Plus |format=PDF |accessdate=2010-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|95
|-
!Chart (2010)
!Position
|-
|[[Australian Singles Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AUSendofyear&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aria.com.au/pages/aria-charts-end-of-year-charts-top-100-singles-2010.htm|title=ARIA Charts – End Of Year Charts – Top 100 Singles 2010|publisher=[[Australian Recording Industry Association]]|accessdate=2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|63
|-
|UK Singles Chart&lt;ref name=uk2010&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ukchartsplus.co.uk/UKChartsPlusYE2010.pdf|title=End Of Year Charts: 2010|publisher=[[UKChartsPlus]]|accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|59
|}

==You Got the Dirtee Love==
{{Infobox single
| Name           = You Got the Dirtee Love
| Cover          = YGTDL.jpg
| Artist         = [[Florence and the Machine|Florence + the Machine]] featuring [[Dizzee Rascal]]
| Album          = [[Lungs (album)|Between Two Lungs]] and [[Tongue n' Cheek|Tongue n' Cheek (Deluxe Edition)]]
| Released       = 17 February 2010 &lt;small&gt;(Digital download)&lt;/small&gt;
| Format         = [[Music download|Digital download]]
| Track_no       = 13
| Recorded       =
| Genre          = [[Grime (music)|Grime]], [[indie pop]], [[Concert|live]]
| Length         = 3:38
| Writer         =
| Label          = [[Island Records|Universal Island]]
| Producer       =
| Misc           =
|Chronology      = [[Florence and the Machine]] singles
|Last single     = &quot;[[#Florence and the Machine version|You've Got the Love]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;(2009)
|This single     = &quot;'''You Got the Dirtee Love'''&quot;&lt;br&gt;(2010)
|Next single     = &quot;[[Dog Days Are Over]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;(Re-release)&lt;br&gt;(2010)
|Misc            =
{{Extra chronology
|Artist          = [[Dizzee Rascal]] singles
|Type            = singles
|Last single     = &quot;[[Dirtee Cash]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;(2009)
|This single     = &quot;'''You Got the Dirtee Love'''&quot;&lt;br&gt;(2010)
|Next single     = &quot;[[Dirtee Disco]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;(2010)
}}
}}

At the [[2010 BRIT Awards]] on 16 February 2010, Florence and the Machine were joined by [[Dizzee Rascal]] an extended version of &quot;You Got the Love&quot; which featured [[Dizzee Rascal]] interweaving his rap [[Dirtee Cash]]; she was awarded a BRIT Award for having made the best British album of the year, ''[[Lungs (album)|Lungs]]'', while he won the Best British Male award.

The single, entitled &quot;You Got the Dirtee Love&quot; was released on 17 February 2010 exclusively to iTunes, one day after the BRITs performance. On 21 February 2010, the single entered the [[UK Singles Chart]] at number 2. As of 10 May 2010, the song has been certified silver and has sold more than 280,000 copies in the [[United Kingdom|UK]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musicweek.com/story.asp?sectioncode=1&amp;storycode=1041079 Florence &amp; The Machine with Dizzee Rascal perform &quot;You Got The Dirtee Love&quot; at the BRITS Awards]. [[Music Week]].&lt;/ref&gt; The single is featured on the ''Dirtee Deluxe Edition'' of Dizzee Rascal's ''[[Tongue n' Cheek]]'' album. The song charted in [[Ireland]] following the album's release. The single is also available on deluxe and bonus editions of Florence + The Machine's album Lungs.

The song was performed at [[Radio 1's Big Weekend]] in North Wales on 22 May 2010, and again at the [[Glastonbury Festival 2010]] on 25 June.
The song was also performed at Capital's Summertime Ball 2010, where Florence appeared as a special guest during Dizzee's set.

===Chart performance===
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
!Chart (2010)
! style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|Peak&lt;br/&gt;Position
|-
{{singlechart|Australia|27|artist=Florence + The Machine &amp; Dizzee Rascal|song=You Got The Dirtee Love (Live At The BRIT Awards 2010)}}
|-
{{singlechart|Ireland|24|artist=Florence + The Machine &amp; Dizzee Rascal|song=You Got The Dirtee Love (Live At The BRIT Awards 2010)|year=2010|week=23}}
|-
|[[European Hot 100 Singles]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.billboard.com/#/charts/european-hot-100?chartDate=2010-03-06 Florence &amp; The Machine &amp; Dizzee Rascal &quot;Youe Got The Love Dirtee Love&quot; on European Hot 100]. [[European Hot 100 Singles]], [[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]].&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|8
|-
{{singlechart|UK|2|artist=Florence / Dizzee Rascal|song=You Got The Dirtee Love|date=2010-02-27}}
|}

====Year-End Charts====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Country (2010)
! Peak position
|-
|UK Singles Chart&lt;ref name=uk2010/&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|54
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
* [http://www.discogs.com/artist/Source%2C+The The Source]
* [http://www.discogs.com/artist/Now+Voyager?noanv=1 Now Voyager]
* [http://www.soundonsound.com/sos/mar10/articles/it_0310.htm Sound on Sound article on the recording and mixing of Florence &amp; The Machine's version]
* [http://www.musicomh.com/downloads/source_0106.htm Video]

{{Florence and the Machine}}
{{Dizzee Rascal}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:You Got The Love}}
[[Category:1986 singles]]
[[Category:1991 singles]]
[[Category:1997 singles]]
[[Category:2006 singles]]
[[Category:2010 singles]]

[[it:You've Got the Love]]
[[mk:You Got the Love]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
