<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="738218" ns="0" title="Masuji Ibuse"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Onesource|date=March 2008}}

{{Japanese name|Ibuse}}
{{nihongo|'''Masuji Ibuse'''|井伏 鱒二|Ibuse Masuji|extra=February 15, 1898—July 10, 1993}} was a [[Japanese people|Japanese]] [[author]].

==Life and work==
Ibuse was born in 1898 to a landowning family in the village of [[Kamo]] which is now part of [[Fukuyama, Hiroshima]]. 

At the age of 19 he started studying at [[Waseda University]] in [[Tokyo]]. He was at first interested in studying poetry and painting but was encouraged to study fiction and ended up specialising in [[French literature]]. 

He was harassed sexually by a gay professor named [[Noburu Katagami]],{{Fact|date=March 2008}} so he had to leave the university before graduation, but began publishing stories in the early 1920s. 

He began to be recognised in the late 20's when his work was favorably mentioned by some of Japan's top critics. He appeared on the literary scene with the publication of ''Salamander'' in 1929, and thereafter continued to write in a style characterized by a unique blend of humour and bitterness. 

He was awarded the [[Naoki Prize]] for ''John Manjirou, the Cast-Away; his Life and Adventure'' and continued to publish works filled with warmth and kindliness, while at the same time showing his keen power of observation. The themes he employed were usually intellectual fantasies that used animal allegories, historical fiction, and  the country life. During [[World War II]] he worked for the government as a propaganda writer.

==Adolescence==
Ibuse failed his entrance exam to Hiroshima middle school but in 1911 he gained admission to Fukuyama Middle School. Fukuyama Middle School was an elite academy and was linked to eminent scholars. Fukuyama's teachers boasted the school's pedigree but Ibuse did not care much for this. Ibuse speaks of this school as following Western ideals, according to ''The First Half of My Life'' he says the school emphasized Dutch learning and French military exercises.

Ibuse was made fun of at this school; he even went as far as to avoid wearing glasses in an effort to not being ridiculed.&lt;ref name=&quot;pools&quot;&gt;Pools of water, pillars of fire: the literature of Ibuse Masuji&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Ibuse enjoyed the Western influences of his education, his grandfather arranged for private tutorial of Chinese literature, however, this training came to a stop when Ibuse's tutor died.&lt;ref&gt;Pools of water, pillars of fire: the literature of Ibuse Masuji. John Whittier Treat&lt;/ref&gt;
At his school, Ibuse had to often deal with rules that forbade students to read fictional literature; this prevented Ibuse from reading popular works during this period. However Ibuse managed to read works from Shimazaki Toson and Mori Ogai. In 1916, Ibuse even wrote a letter to Ogai with the pseudonym Kuchiki Sansuke. Ogai believed Sansuke was a famous scholar and sent a reply to Sansuke expressing his gratitude.
While in middle school, Ibuse's brother Fumio submitted a poem to the Tokyo journal ''Shusai bundan'' using Ibuse's name. Ibuse was reprimanded by the principal of Fukuyama's school but he was also praised by receiving two fan letters. The reprimand Ibuse received influenced him to express an interest in the visual arts.&lt;ref name=&quot;pools&quot;/&gt;

Ibuse studied the arts at Fukuyama Middle School; he enjoyed the classes but did not feel he wanted to commit his life to becoming an artist.
Ibuse graduated from middle school in 1917; he wanted to continue his artist endeavours under the tutorship of established painter Hashimoto Kansetsu but this opportunity was denied by Kansetsu.

In 1917 at nineteen years of age, Ibuse started preparing to enter Waseda University; he was greatly influenced by his brother Fumio and by a friend of his Yamane Masakazu.

Ibuse moved to Tokyo and experienced a sense of inspiration from leaving the country (Fukuyama) and moving to the big city, Ibuse described this experience in ''Thoughts One February Ninth'': &quot;sometimes I feel that half of me wants to return to the country while the other half would like to cling to Tokyo until the very end.&quot;

Tokyo appeared to be surreal for Ibuse, he felt lonely and missed his Fukuyama home. Nevertheless, Ibuse decided to stay in a boardinghouse near Waseda University; he often moved but always staying near Waseda, he visited Fukuyama only occasionally.
In Tokyo, Ibuse befriended eccentric young men and literary hopefuls. During his stay at Waseda University, Ibuse witnessed political unrest and the expressed radicalism of university students. Ibuse did not appeal to the political ideologies of the era. In fact, he was dissatisfied with the consistent strikes and revolts.&lt;ref name=&quot;pools&quot;/&gt;

At Waseda University, Ibuse was greatly influenced by the works of Shakespeare and Basho; he was also an avid reader of French fiction and poetry. Ibuse went as far as to pawn a watch to try to understand the necessities of writers.

In 1918 Ibuse met naturalist writer Iwano Homei. Homei's literature was appealing to Ibuse and would later influence some of Ibuse's literary works.
Ibuse befriended student Aoki Nampachi in Waseda, Aoki was a mentor and a great influence in the writings of Ibuse, Aoki's influence can be found in &quot;The Carp,&quot; where Ibuse ideolizes Aoki's friendship and represents his feelings towards this friendship in a carp.
Ibuse started writing his first essays in 1922, shortly after the death of Aoki. Ibuse often found inspiration in his loneliness and in his encounters with geishas, his first literary works where in the style of prose, he had severed ties with Waseda University and started writing for small magazines.

One of Ibuse's first contributions was for the magazine ''Seiki'', it was originally written for Aoki in 1919 and titled &quot;The Salamander,&quot; in 1923 it was renamed &quot;Confinement.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pools of water, pillars of fire: the literature of Ibuse Masuji. John Whittier Treat.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ibuse was known and appreciated for most of his career, although it wasn't until after the war that he became famous. In 1966 he published his most well known work, ''[[Black Rain (novel)|Black Rain]]'', which won him international acclaim and several awards including the [[Noma Prize]] and the [[Order of Cultural Merit]], the highest honor that can be bestowed upon a Japanese author. The novel draws its material from the [[bombing of Hiroshima]] with the title referring to the nuclear fallout. Ibuse was not present at the time of the bombing, but uses the diaries of survivors to construct his narrative. His earlier story ''Kakitsubata'' (“The Crazy Iris”, first published in 1951) deals with similar themes.

==Selected works==
*''[[Yu Hei]]'' &quot;Confinement&quot; (1923)
*''[[Sanshouo]]'' (1929) &quot;Salamander and Other Stories&quot; (trans. by John Bester)Kodansha International 1981.
*''[[Sazanami Gunki]]'' (1930-38)  &quot;Waves: A War Diary&quot;
*''[[Shigotobeya]]'', (1931)
*''Kawa'' (1931-32) - &quot;The River&quot;
*''[[Zuihitsu]]'', (1933)
*''[[Keirokushu]]'' )(1936) - &quot;Miscellany&quot;
*''[[Jon Manjiro Hyoryuki]]'', (1937) - &quot;John Manjiro, the Cast-Away: His Life and Adventures&quot;
*''[[Shukin Ryoko]]'', (1937)
*''[[Sazanami Gunki]]'', (1938) - &quot;trans. in Waves: Two Short Novels&quot;
*''[[Tajinko Mura]]'', 1939
*''[[Shigureto Jokei]]'', 1941
*''[[Ibuse Masuji Zuihitsu Zenshu]]'', 1941 (3 vols.)
*''[[Hana No Machi]]'', 1942 - &quot;City of Flowers&quot;
*''[[Chushu Meigetsu]]'', 1942
*''[[Aru Shojo No Senji Nikki]]'', 1943 - &quot;A Young Girl's Wartime Diary&quot;
*''[[Gojinka]]'', 1944
*''[[Wabisuke]]'', 1946 - &quot;trans. in Waves: Two Short Novels&quot;
*''[[Magemono]]'', 1946
*''[[Oihagi No Hanashi]]'', 1947
*''[[Ibuse Masuji Senshu]]'', 1948 (9 vols)
*''[[Yohai Taicho]]'', 1950 - &quot;Lieutenant Lookeast and other stories&quot;
*''[[Kawatsuri]]'', 1952
*''[[Honjitsu Kyushin]]'', 1952 - &quot;No Consultations Today&quot;,
*''[[Ibuse Masuji Sakuhinshu]]'', 1953 (5 vols.)
*''[[Hyomin Usaburo]]'', 1954-55
*''[[Nyomin Nanakamado]]'', 1955
*''[[Kanreki No Koi]]'', 1957
*''[[Ekimae Ryokan]]'', 1957
*''[[Nanatsu No Kaidō]]'', 1957
*''[[Chinpindo Shujin]]'', 1959
*''[[Bushu Hachigatajo]]'', 1963
*''[[Mushinjo]]'', 1963
*''[[Ibuse Masuji Zenshu]]'', 1964 (2 vols.)
*''[[Black Rain (novel)|Kuroi Ame]]'', 1966 - ''[[Black Rain (novel)|Black Rain]]'' (trans. by John Bester) - [[Black Rain (Japanese film)|film]] 1989, dir. by Shohei Imamura
*''[[Gendai Bungaku Taikei]]'', 1966
*''[[Hanseiki]]'', 1970 - &quot;The First Half of My Life&quot;
*''[[Shincho Nihonbungaku]]'', 1970
*''[[Tsuribito]]'', 1970
*''[[Ibuse Masuji Zenshu]]'', 1975 ( 14 vols.)
*''[[Choyochu No Koto]]'', 1977-80 - &quot;Under Arms&quot;
*''[[Ogikubo Fudoki]]'', 1981 - &quot;An Ogikybo Almanac&quot;

==External links==
*[http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/ibuse.htm http://www.kirjasto.sci.fi/ibuse.htm]
* http://www.f.waseda.jp/mjewel/jlit/authors_works/modernlit/ibuse_masuji.html
* {{imdb name|id=0406600|name=Masuji Ibuse}}
* [http://www.facm.net/eng/episode2.htm]

==References==

&lt;references /&gt;
*[[Encyclopædia Britannica 2005 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]], article- &quot;Ibuse Masuji&quot;
* {{cite book | last = Treat | first = John Whittier | authorlink = John Whittier Treat | year = 1988 | title = Pools of Water, Pillars of Fire: The Literature of Ibuse Masuji  | publisher = University of Washington Press | isbn = 0295966254 }}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Ibuse, Masuji
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1898
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1993
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ibuse, Masuji}}
[[Category:1898 births]]
[[Category:1993 deaths]]
[[Category:Japanese writers]]
[[Category:Japanese novelists]]
[[Category:Japanese short story writers]]
[[Category:Japanese essayists]]
[[Category:People from Fukuyama (city)]]
[[Category:People associated with the atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]]

[[de:Ibuse Masuji]]
[[es:Masuji Ibuse]]
[[fr:Masuji Ibuse]]
[[it:Masuji Ibuse]]
[[hu:Ibusze Maszudzsi]]
[[ja:井伏鱒二]]
[[pl:Masuji Ibuse]]
[[ro:Masuji Ibuse]]
[[ru:Ибусэ, Масудзи]]
[[zh:井伏鱒二]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
