<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="738922" ns="0" title="KZJO"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Broadcast |
  call_letters             = KZJO|
  city                     = |
  station_logo             = [[File:JoeTV.png|230px]]|
  station_slogan           = |
  station_branding         = ''JOEtv''|
  former_channel_numbers   = '''Analog''':&lt;br&gt;22 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]], 1985-2009)|
  digital                  = 25 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br&gt;[[virtual channel|Virtual]]: 22 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])|
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = [[MyNetworkTV]]|
  network                  = |
  founded                  = |
  airdate                  = June 22, 1985|
  location                 = [[Seattle|Seattle, Washington]]|
  callsign_meaning         = '''''&lt;u&gt;Z&lt;/u&gt;'''''(S)eattle's '''''&lt;u&gt;JO&lt;/u&gt;'''''E TV&lt;br&gt;(The '''''&lt;u&gt;Z&lt;/u&gt;''''' also serves as a callback to the former KTZZ calls)|
  former_callsigns         = KTZZ-TV (1985-1999)&lt;br /&gt;KTWB-TV (1999-2006)&lt;br&gt;KMYQ (2006-2010)|
  owner                    = [[Tribune Company]]|
  licensee                 = Tribune Television Holdings, Inc.|
  sister_stations          = [[KCPQ]]|
  former_affiliations      = independent (1985-1995)&lt;br /&gt;[[The WB Television Network|The WB]] (1995-2006)|
  effective_radiated_power = 1000 kW|
  HAAT                     = 290 m|
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = 69571|
  coordinates              = {{coord|47|36|56.8|N|122|18|30.2|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.joeswall.com/ www.joeswall.com/]|
}}
'''KZJO''', channel 22, is a [[MyNetworkTV]]-affiliated television station in [[Seattle]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]].  Owned by the [[Tribune Company]], KZJO uses '''''JOEtv''''' for its on-air branding.  The station can be viewed on channel 10 on most [[Western Washington]] cable systems, and also operates two UHF translators.
 
KZJO's offices and broadcasting center along with its transmitter are co-located with sister station [[KCPQ]] (channel 13) on the west shore of [[Lake Union]] in the [[Westlake, Seattle, Washington|Westlake]] neighborhood of Seattle. Additionally, they rebroadcast KCPQ on their DT2 [[digital subchannel]] in a reduced form of 720p in order to provide the station to all viewers possible in the main Seattle area, as KCPQ broadcasts from near [[Bremerton, Washington|Bremerton]] and provides weak signal quality to the eastern portion of the market.

==History==
The station began broadcasting as '''KTZZ''' on June 22, 1985. The call letters stood for '''T'''elevision '''22''', the '''Z'''s closely resembling numeral '''2'''s.  At that time there was a hole in the market for cartoons and sitcoms.  While [[KSTW]] (channel 11) was running such programming, KCPQ counter-programmed with more adult fare like dramas, game shows, and movies.  As such, KTZZ signed on with a lineup of classic off-network sitcoms, westerns, cartoons, movies, and dramas. Initially the station was profitable under the ownership of [[Alden Communications]].  Originally, to keep people from changing channels, the station broadcast only its station ID—no commercials—between the [[closing credits]] of one show and the opening credits of the next show.  One Christmas season as snow fell in the [[Puget Sound]] area viewers were treated to a gag in which someone pretending to be a janitor takes control of the station for a few moments to deliver &quot;the news&quot; which was mostly a fake weather forecast which began &quot;The weather outside is frightful.  But inside it's quite delightful.  As long as I've got no place to go, let it snow, let it snow, let it snow.&quot;

A couple years later, the station was sold to [[Dudley Broadcasting]]. By 1988, KCPQ and KSTW had strong lineups, including almost all of the children's programming available. KTZZ was also the home, for several years, of the eclectic Seattle talk show [[The Spud Goodman Show]].  Producing the weekly interview/music/feature show was an ambitious undertaking for a small station, and the program relied heavily on a large staff of volunteers. The programming costs became too high for KTZZ. As a result, KTZZ began airing [[CBS]] shows pre-empted by [[KIRO-TV]] (channel 7), along with paid programming and brokered shows.  It still ran some conventional syndicated product, but they were essentially programs that no other stations wanted.  For a time in 1993, channel 22 aired a 10:00 p.m. newscast produced by KIRO-TV.

Originally, KTZZ agreed to affiliate with the new [[UPN|United Paramount Network]] in 1994. However, the UPN affiliation went to KIRO when that station lost its CBS affiliation to KSTW (which was eventually sold to [[Paramount Pictures]]), and KTZZ agreed to affiliate with [[The WB Television Network|The WB]] instead. KTZZ picked up cartoons, such as ''[[Goof Troop]]'' and ''[[Bonkers]]'' from KSTW in 1995, added more off-network sitcoms and moved away from the brokered format. As it began airing programming from The WB, KTZZ was helped in part by the fact that KCPQ was moving towards news and more first-run syndicated talk, courtroom, and drama shows.

KTZZ was purchased by [[Tribune Broadcasting]] (along with sister station [[WXMI]] in [[Grand Rapids, Michigan]]) from [[Emmis Communications]] in 1998, and changed its call letters to '''KTWB-TV''' ('''T'''he '''W'''arner '''B'''rothers Network) the next year. After Tribune acquired KCPQ in early 1999, KTWB's license was transferred back to Emmis in the short-term until the [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]]'s approval of television [[duopoly (broadcasting)|duopolies]] later that year, though Tribune managed and operated the station during this period via a [[local marketing agreement]]. In 2004, KTWB revised its on-air brand from ''WB 22'' to ''Seattle's WB'' as part of a groupwide branding effort.

On January 24, 2006, the WB and UPN networks announced they would merge into a new network called [[The CW Television Network|The CW]].  CBS-owned KSTW, the then-current UPN station, was chosen as The CW's Seattle-Tacoma affiliate.  KTWB was slated to return to its previous independent status, but on May 15, 2006, Tribune announced that it would affiliate channel 22 (and two other WB stations not included in the CW affiliation deal) with MyNetworkTV.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bizjournals.com/seattle/stories/2006/05/15/daily7.html&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:KMYQ-TV.png|thumb|left|Logo as myQ², used from 2006-2010.]]
On July 14, 2006, channel 22's call letters were officially changed to '''KMYQ''' to reflect its new affiliation, and the station's brand name was changed to ''myQ²'' on August 7, 2006.

With the loss of the WB, KZJO may now carry Fox network programming should KCPQ preempt for a special (such as the [[Jerry Lewis MDA Telethon]]), a breaking news story, or any other emergency.

On March 31, 2008, KMYQ began airing a KCPQ-produced 9:00 p.m. newscast (&quot;Q13 Fox News @ Nine on myQ²&quot;, now called &quot;Q13 Fox News @ Nine on JOEtv&quot;) Monday through Sunday.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/CA6542492.html?industryid=47169&lt;/ref&gt; KMYQ became just the second MyNetworkTV affiliate in the [[Pacific Time Zone]] to have had a 7:00pm–9:00pm early prime schedule (the first was [[KQCA]] in [[Sacramento, California|Sacramento]], which has since moved MyNetworkTV programming back to its normal 8:00-10:00 pm timeslot).

On September 13, 2010, the station moved its MyNetworkTV programming to 11:00 p.m.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tvlistings.zap2it.com/tvlistings/ZCSGrid.do?stnNum=10769&amp;channel=10]&lt;/ref&gt; KMYQ changed its call letters to '''KZJO''' and rebranded as ''JOEtv''. The station airs mostly syndicated programming such as [[The Simpsons]], [[My Name is Earl]] and [[King of the Hill]] in addition to the MyNetworkTV programming.&lt;ref&gt;[http://joeswall.com/]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br clear=all&gt; On September 19, 2011, the station moved MyNetworkTV programming yet again, this time, back an hour, to 12:00 a.m.

==Digital television==
KZJO is currently on UHF channel 25.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! Video
! Aspect&lt;br&gt;Ratio
! Programming
|-
| 22.1 || 720p || rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 16:9 || Main KZJO programming / MyTV 
|-
| 22.2 || rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 480i || Simulcast of [[KCPQ]]
|-
| 22.3 || 4:3 || [[Antenna TV]]
|}

==Translators==
KZJO is rebroadcast on the following translator stations.

Analog Translator
* '''[http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/tvq?call=K25CH K25CH]'''  Channel 25 [[Centralia, Washington|Centralia]]


Digital Translator
* '''[http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/tvq?call=K29ED K29ED]'''  Channel 29 [[Everett, Washington|Everett]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://joeswall.com/ JOEtv]
*{{TVQ|KZJO}}
*{{TV Fool|KZJO}}
*{{BIA|KZJO|TV|TV}}

{{Seattle TV}}
{{MNTV Washington}}
{{Tribune}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kmyq}}
[[Category:Television stations in Seattle, Washington]]
[[Category:Tribune Broadcasting]]
[[Category:MyNetworkTV affiliates]]
[[Category:Antenna TV affiliates]]
[[Category:Channel 22 virtual TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 25 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1985]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
