<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="74217" ns="0" title="Olympic Flame"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:olympic flame.jpg|right|thumbnail|The torch relay of the [[2002 Winter Olympics]] passes through [[Cincinnati, Ohio]]]]
The '''Olympic Flame''' or '''Olympic Torch''' is a [[symbol]] of the [[Olympic Games]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot; &gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/topic-1102259/Olympic-flame Britannica on Olympic Flame]&lt;/ref&gt; Commemorating the theft of fire from the Greek god [[Zeus]] by [[Prometheus]], its origins lie in [[ancient Greece]], where a fire was kept burning throughout the celebration of the [[Ancient Olympic Games|ancient Olympics]]{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}. The fire was reintroduced at the [[1928 Summer Olympics]] in [[Amsterdam]], and it has been part of the modern Olympic Games ever since.  According to legend, the torch's flame has been kept burning ever since the first Olympics.{{dubious|No evidence for this, even as a cite to a myth. Besides, the re-kindling from the sun or via ritual is a big part of the performance.|date=June 2011}}

In contrast to the Olympic flame proper, the [[torch relay]] of modern times which transports the flame from Greece to the various designated sites of the games had no ancient precedent and was introduced by [[Carl Diem]] at the controversial 1936 [[Berlin Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/14/sports/olympics/14torch.html?ex=1207972800&amp;en=732b3844bc19c839&amp;ei=5070 
  | publisher = The New York Times 
  | work = Sports &gt; Olympics 
  | title = Hitler's Berlin Games Helped Make Some Emblems Popular 
  | date=2004-08-14 
  | accessdate=2010-03-27
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage==
The Olympic Torch today is ignited several months before the opening ceremony of the [[Olympic Games]] at the site of the [[ancient Olympics]] in [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]], Greece. Eleven women, representing the [[Vestal Virgins]],&lt;ref group=&quot;notes&quot; &gt;The Roman [[Vesta]] is derived from the Greek goddess [[Hestia]]. Hestia's rituals at the founding of a new settlement also included the transfer of a continuous flame from the founding city.&lt;/ref&gt; perform a ceremony in which the torch is kindled by the light of the Sun, its rays concentrated by a [[parabolic reflector|parabolic mirror]].

The Olympic Torch Relay ends on the day of the opening ceremony in the central stadium of the Games. The final carrier is often kept unannounced until the last moment, and is usually a sports celebrity of the host country. The final bearer of the torch runs towards the cauldron, often placed at the top of a grand staircase, and then uses the torch to start the flame in the stadium.  It is considered a great honor to be asked to light the Olympic Flame. After being lit, the flame continues to burn throughout the Olympics, and is extinguished on the day of the closing ceremony.

==History==
{{Ref improve section|date=March 2009}}
{{See also|List of Olympic torch relays}}

===Ancient Olympics===
For the ancient Greeks, fire had divine connotations—it was thought to have been stolen from the gods by [[Prometheus]]. Therefore, fire was also present at many of the sanctuaries in [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]], [[Greece]]. A fire permanently burned on the altar of [[Hestia]] in [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]], [[Greece]]. During the Olympic Games, which honored [[Zeus]], additional fires were lit at his temple and that of his wife, [[Hera]]. The modern Olympic flame is ignited at the site where the temple of Hera used to stand.

===The modern era===

[[Image:Marathontoren01.jpg|thumb|upright|The Marathon Tower at the [[Olympisch Stadion (Amsterdam)|Olympic Stadium]] in [[Amsterdam]], where the first modern Olympic Flame burnt in [[1928 Summer Olympics|1928]]]]
[[Image:Olympictorche-Berlin.jpg|thumb|left|Olympic flame at Berlin games 1936]]
Flame from the ancient games was reintroduced during the [[1928 Summer Olympics|1928 Games]]. An employee of the Electric Utility of Amsterdam lit the first Olympic flame in the Marathon Tower of the [[Olympisch Stadion (Amsterdam)|Olympic Stadium]] in Amsterdam.

The modern convention of moving the Olympic Flame via a relay system from Greece to the Olympic venue began in 1936. [[Carl Diem]] devised the idea of the torch relay for the [[1936 Summer Olympics]] in Berlin that was organized by the [[Nazi Party|Nazis]] under the guidance of [[Joseph Goebbels]]. [[Krupp]] armaments company produced the torches in wood and metal, inspired by an olive leaf. The Olympic Flame was lit by a concave mirror in Olympia, Greece and transported over 3,187 kilometres by 3,331 runners in twelve days and eleven nights from Greece to Berlin. [[Leni Riefenstahl]] later staged the torch relay for the 1938 film ''[[Olympia (1938 film)|Olympia]]''. The film was part of the Nazi propaganda machine’s attempt to add myth and mystique to [[Adolf Hitler]]’s regime. Hitler saw the link with the ancient Games as the perfect way to illustrate his belief that classical Greece was an [[Aryan race|Aryan]] forerunner of the modern German Reich.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article3699278.ece 
  | title= Who put the Olympic flame out? 
  | publisher=[[timesonline.co.uk]] 
  | date=2008-04-07 
  | accessdate=2008-04-07 
  | location=London 
  | first=Nico  | last=Hines
}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were minor protests in [[Yugoslavia]] and [[Czechoslovakia]] on the way, which were suppressed by the local security forces.

Although most of the time the torch with the Olympic Flame is still carried by runners, it has been transported in many different ways. The fire travelled by boat in 1948 to cross the [[English Channel]] and was carried by rowers in [[Canberra]] as well as by [[dragon boat]] in [[Hong Kong]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  |url=http://www.singtao.com/breakingnews/20080502a131407.asp
  |title=施幸余乘龍舟傳送火炬
  |date=2008-05-02
  |publisher=Singtao
  | language = Chinese
  |accessdate=2008-05-02
}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2008, and it was first transported by [[Fixed-wing aircraft|airplane]] in 1952, when the fire travelled to [[Helsinki]]. In 1956, all carriers in the torch relay to [[Stockholm]], where the equestrian events were held instead of in Melbourne, travelled on horseback.

Remarkable means of transportation were used in 1976, when the flame was transformed to a radio signal. From [[Athens]], this signal was transmitted by [[satellite]] to [[Canada]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Montréal&quot;&gt;{{cite web 
  | url = http://www.olympic.org/uk/passion/museum/permanent/summer/montreal_uk.asp 
  | title = Montréal 
  | publisher = International Olympic Committee 
  | work = The Olympic Museum Lausanne
}}&lt;/ref&gt; where it was received and used to trigger a [[laser]] beam to re-light the flame. This distinctive 1976 torch was manufactured by [[John L. Saksun]]'s The Queensway Machine Products Ltd. In 2000, the torch was carried under water by divers near the [[Great Barrier Reef]]. Other unique means of transportation include a [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]] [[canoe]], a [[camel]], and [[Concorde]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
  | url = http://multimedia.olympic.org/pdf/en_report_1020.pdf 
  | title = Report 
  | year = 2008 
  | format = [[PDF]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[2004 Olympic Torch Relay|2004]], the first global torch relay was undertaken, a journey that lasted 78 days. The Olympic flame covered a distance of more than 78,000&amp;nbsp;km in the hands of some 11,300 [[torchbearer]]s, travelling to Africa and South America for the first time, visiting all previous Olympic cities and finally returning to [[Athens]] for the [[2004 Summer Olympics]].

The climactic transfer of the flame from the torches to the cauldron at the host stadium concludes the relay and marks the symbolic commencement of the Games. Perhaps one of the most spectacular of these ceremonies took place at the [[1992 Summer Olympics|1992 Barcelona Games]], when [[Paralympics|Paralympic]] [[archery|archer]] [[Antonio Rebollo]] ignited the cauldron by shooting a burning arrow over it, which ignited gas rising from the cauldron.&lt;ref name=&quot;1992Report&quot;&gt;[http://www.la84foundation.org/6oic/OfficialReports/1992/1992s4.pdf Official Report of the 1992 Summer Olympics, Vol. 4], p. 70 (confirming arrow lit the gas above the cauldron) and p. 69 (time-lapse photo of lighting; the arrow passed through the upper reaches of the flame).&lt;/ref&gt; [[1994 Winter Olympics|Two years later]], the Olympic fire was brought into the stadium of [[Lillehammer]] by a [[ski jumping|ski jumper]]. In Beijing 2008, [[Li Ning]] 'ran' on air around the Bird's Nest and lit the flame. In Vancouver 2010, four athletes—[[Catriona LeMay Doan]], [[Wayne Gretzky]], [[Steve Nash]] and [[Nancy Greene]]—were given the honor of lighting the flame simultaneously (indoor) before [[Wayne Gretzky]] transferred the flame to an outdoor cauldron at Vancouver's waterfront.

==Lighters ==
[[Image:Paavo Nurmi sytyttää olympiatulen 1952.jpg|thumb|upright|Paavo Nurmi lights the Olympic fire in Helsinki in 1952.]]
[[Image:Olympic flame at opening ceremony.jpg|thumb|The Olympic Flame at the Opening Ceremony, Athens 2004 Games]]
[[File:Li Ling during 2008 Summer Olympics opening ceremony.jpg|thumb|upright|Li Ning, a Chinese gymnast, lit the Olympic Flame during the opening ceremony of the 2008 Summer Olympics after 'flying' around the stadium on wires
 |alt=An Asian man in red and white athletic shirt and shorts, and wearing sneakers, is suspended by wires in the air while holding a lit torch. In the background, a large crowd in a stadium can be seen, as well as two blurred flags.]]
[[File:The Olympic Cauldron in Vancouver.jpg|thumb|The Vancouver olympic flame]]
{{See also|List of people who have lit the Olympic Cauldron}}
Over the years, it has become a tradition to let famous athletes, former athletes and/or athletes with significant achievements and milestones be the last runner in the Olympic torch relay and have the honor of lighting the Olympic Cauldron. The first well-known athlete to light the cauldron in the stadium was ninefold Olympic Champion [[Paavo Nurmi]], who excited the home crowd in Helsinki in 1952.  Other famous last bearers of the torch include [[France|French]] [[football (soccer)|football]] star [[Michel Platini]] (1992), heavyweight [[boxing]] champion [[Muhammad Ali]] (1996), Australian aboriginal runner [[Cathy Freeman]] (2000), and [[Ice Hockey]] player [[Wayne Gretzky]] (2010).

On other occasions, the people who lit the cauldron in the stadium are not famous, but nevertheless symbolize Olympic ideals. [[Japan]]ese runner [[Yoshinori Sakai]] was born in [[Hiroshima]] on August 6, 1945, the day the [[nuclear weapon]] [[Little Boy]] destroyed that city. He symbolized the rebirth of Japan after the [[Second World War]] when he opened the [[1964 Summer Olympics|1964 Tokyo Games]].  At the [[1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Games]] in [[Montreal]], two teenagers &amp;mdash; one from the French-speaking part of the country, one from the English-speaking part &amp;mdash; symbolized the unity of [[Canada]].

==Routes==
The Olympic torch travels routes that symbolise human achievement. In 1976 the flame was transmitted from Greece to the [[New World]] via satellite. Heat sensors in Greece detected the flame, the signal was sent to Ottawa via satellite and there a laser beam lit the torch.&lt;ref&gt;Winn, L.: [http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/olympics/2010/blog/2010/02/17/olympic-design-canadas-torches/ Olympic Design: Torches &amp; Cauldrons]. ''Sports Illustrated'', Feb. 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The torch, but not the flame, was taken into space by astronauts in 1996 and 2000.&lt;ref&gt;The Olympic Museum: ''[http://multimedia.olympic.org/pdf/en_report_655.pdf The Olympic flame and torch relay]''. Lausanne, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Torches ==
The design of the torch used in the relay to the Games changes for each Games. They may be designed to represent a classical ideal, or to represent some local aspect of those particular Games.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC, Torches&quot; &gt;{{Cite news
  |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13424048
  |title=Torch Timeline
  |publisher=[[BBC News online]]
  |year=2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT, Torches&quot; &gt;{{Cite news
  |url=http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2010/02/09/sports/olympics/0209-torches-graphic.html 
  |journal=[[New York Times]]
  |date=9 February 2010
  |title=Passing the Torch: An Evolution of Form
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  |title=Pictures of all Olympic Summergames Torches 
  |url=http://olympic-museum.de/quickview/all_torches.htm
  |publisher=olympic-museum.de
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some, such as Albertville in 1992 and Turin in 2006 have been designed by famous industrial designers. These design-led torches have been less popular than the more classical designs, the Turin torch in particular being criticised for being simply too heavy for the runners.

The torch for the 1948 [[1948 Summer Olympics|London Olympics]] was designed by architect [[Ralph Lavers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;V&amp;A, 1948 torch&quot; &gt;{{cite web 
  |publisher= [[Victoria and Albert Museum]]
  |url= http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/metalwork/metalwork_stories/olympic_torch/index.html
  |title= Olympic Torch, London 1948
  |work=Metalwork
  |accessdate= 2007-11-19
}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were cast in [[Hiduminium]] aluminium alloy&lt;ref name=&quot;Flight, 22 July 1948, 1948 Olympics&quot; &gt;{{cite journal
  |journal=[[Flight (magazine)|Flight]] 
  |title=1948 Olympics
  |section=Here and There
  |url=http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1948/1948%20-%201112.html
  |format=PDF
  |date=22 July 1948
  |pages=90
  |ref=Flight, 22 July 1948, Reynolds
}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a length of 47&amp;nbsp;cm and a weight of 960&amp;nbsp;g. This classical design of a long handle capped by a cylindrical bowl re-appeared in many later torch designs. The torch used for the final entry to the stadium and the lighting of the cauldron was of a different design, also a feature that would re-appear in later years. This torch did not require the long distance duration or weather resistance of the other torches, but did need a spectacular flame for the opening ceremony. At the Melbourne Olympics of 1956, the magnesium / aluminium fuel used for the final torch was certainly spectacular, but also managed to injure its holder.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC, 2000&quot; &gt;{{Cite web
  |url=http://www.abc.net.au/science/slab/torch/default.htm 
  |title=Olympic torch technology
  |publisher=[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]
  |quote=Australian runner, Ron Clarke carried a spectacular, fizzling flame into the Melbourne Olympic Stadium in 1956 only to miss out on the ceremony having his magnesium burns dressed. 
  |year=2000
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Runners were also burned by the solid-fueled torch for the 1968 Mexico Games.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC, Torches&quot; /&gt;

The fuel used for the torch has varied. Early torches used solid or liquid fuels, including olive oil.&lt;ref&gt;[http://entertainment.howstuffworks.com/olympic-torch.htm/printable How Olympic Torches Work]&lt;/ref&gt; For a particularly bright display, pyrotechnic compounds and even burning metals have been used. Since the Munich Games of 1972, most torches have instead used a liquefied gas such as [[propylene]] or a [[propane]]/[[butane]] mixture. These are easily stored, easily controlled and give a brightly luminous flame.

The number of torches made has varied between 6,200 for the 1980 Moscow Games to a mere 22 for Helsinki in 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC, Torches&quot; /&gt;

In transit, the flame sometimes travels by air. A version of the miner's safety lamp is used, kept alight in the air. These lamps are also used during the relay, as a back-up in case the primary torch goes out. This has happened before several Games, but the torch is simply re-lit and carries on.

The torch has twice been carried across water. The 1968 Grenoble Winter Games was carried across the port of [[Marseilles]] by a diver holding it aloft above the water.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC, Torches&quot; /&gt; In 2000 an underwater flare was used by a diver across the [[Great Barrier Reef]] en route to the Sydney Games.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC, 2000&quot; /&gt;

The latest torch is designed by Edward Barber and Jay Osgerby ([[BarberOsgerby]]) for the [[2012_Summer_Olympics|2012 London Games]]. Despite a deeply cynical response to the logo and mascots of the London Games, this torch design appears to have been well accepted in the UK and internationally.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13673497
  |title=Designing an Olympic 'torch for our time' (2012)
  |year=2011
  |publisher=[[BBC News online]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Protests ==
There have been protests against the Olympic flame relay due to its origins with the Nazis. In the 1956 Melbourne Games, local [[veterinary surgeon|veterinary]] student [[Barry Larkin (Olympics)|Barry Larkin]] protested against the relay by tricking onlookers by carrying a fake flame, consisting of a pair of underpants set on fire in a [[plum pudding]] can, attached to a chair leg. He successfully managed to hand over the fake flame to the Mayor of Sydney, [[Pat Hills]] and escape without being noticed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.thebirdman.org/Index/Temp/Temp-OlympicUnderwearRelay-EH.htm
  |title=Olympic Underwear Relay
  |publisher=The Birdman|accessdate=2008-04-06 
  |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080413001401/http://www.thebirdman.org/Index/Temp/Temp-OlympicUnderwearRelay-EH.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; 
  |archivedate = 2011-05-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video
  |people=[[Stephen Fry]]
  |title=QI Presents: Strictly Come Duncing
  |medium=DVD|publisher=Warner Music Entertainment|date=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Turpin|first=Adrian|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4159/is_20040808/ai_n12758702
  |title=Olympics Special: The Lost Olympians (Page 1)
  |publisher=Find Articles, originally ''The Independent on Sunday''
  |date=2004-08-08|accessdate=2008-04-06 
  |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080413034334/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4159/is_20040808/ai_n12758702 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; 
  |archivedate = 2011-05-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 there were various attempts to stop the Olympic Flame as a protest against China's human rights record. In London, a &quot;ring of steel&quot; was formed around the Flame to protect it, but one protester, Ian Harold Brown,  managed to grab hold of the torch while it was being held by television presenter [[Konnie Huq]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  |last=Lews  |first=Paul
  |coauthors=Kelso, Paul
  |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/apr/07/olympicgames2008.china2
  |title=Thousands protest as Olympic flame carried through London
  |publisher=''[[The Guardian]]''
  |date=7 April 2008
  |accessdate=18 May 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cauldron==
{{See also|List of people who have lit the Olympic Cauldron}}
The cauldron and the pedestal are always the subject of unique and often dramatic design.  These also tie in with ''how'' the cauldron is lit during the Opening Ceremony.
*In Los Angeles in 1984, [[Rafer Johnson]] lit a &quot;wick&quot; of sorts at the top of the archway after having climbed a big flight of steps. The flame flared up a pipe, through the Olympic Rings and on up the side of the tower to ignite the cauldron.
*In Barcelona in 1992, [[Antonio Rebollo]], an [[archery|archer]] shot a flaming arrow over the cauldron to light it. Though Rebollo intentionally overshot the cauldron,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/olympics2000/926190.stm
  |title=Ceremonial hall of shame
  |work=BBC Sport
  |date=15 September 2000
  |first=John  |last=Mathews
}}&lt;/ref&gt; his arrow still lit it by igniting the gas rising from the cauldron.&lt;ref name=&quot;1992Report&quot; /&gt;
*In Atlanta in 1996, the cauldron was an artistic [[scroll]] decorated in red and gold. It was lit by boxing legend [[Muhammad Ali]], using a mechanical, self-propelling fuse ball that transported the flame up a wire from the stadium to its final resting place.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|id=5TaITzi64Sw|title=1996 Atlanta Opening Ceremonies - Lighting of the Cauldron}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[1996 Summer Paralympics]], the scroll was lit by [[paraplegic]] [[climbing|climber]] [[Mark Wellman]], hoisting himself up a rope to the cauldron.
*For the [[2000 Summer Olympics]] in Sydney, [[Cathy Freeman]] walked across a circular pool of water and ignited the cauldron through the water, surrounding herself within a ring of fire. The planned spectacular climax to the ceremony was delayed by the technical glitch of a computer switch which malfunctioned, causing the sequence to shut down by giving a false reading. This meant that the Olympic flame was suspended in mid-air for about four minutes, rather than immediately rising up a water-covered ramp to the top of the stadium. When it was discovered what the problem was, the program was overridden and the cauldron continued up the ramp, where it finally rested on a tall silver pedestal.
*For the [[2002 Winter Olympics]] in Salt Lake City, Utah, USA, the cauldron was lit by the members of the winning 1980 US hockey team. After being skated around the centre ice rink there in the stadium, the flame was carried up a staircase to the team members, who then lit a &quot;wick&quot; of sorts at the bottom of the cauldron tower which set off an impressive line of flames that traveled up inside the tower until it reached the cauldron at the top which ignited. This cauldron was the first to use glass and incorporated running water to prevent the glass from heating and to keep it clean.
*For the [[2004 Summer Olympics]] in Athens, the cauldron was in the shape of a giant olive leaf which bowed down to accept the flame from windsurfer [[Nikolaos Kaklamanakis]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsimg.bbc.co.uk/media/images/39952000/jpg/_39952778_athens203x270.jpg 2004 picture], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the [[2006 Winter Olympics]] in Turin, [[Stefania Belmondo]] placed the flame on an arched lighting apparatus, which initiated a series of fireworks before lighting the top of the {{convert|57|m|ft}} high Olympic Cauldron, the highest in the history of the Winter Olympic Games.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|id=bIT21W1MfaU|title=Olympic Opening Ceremony Torino 2006 - Light of Passion}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the [[2008 Summer Olympics]] in Beijing, the cauldron resembled the end of a scroll that lifted out from the stadium rim and spiralled upwards. It was lit by [[Li Ning]] a Chinese gymnast, who was raised to the rim of the stadium by wires. He ran around the rim of the stadium while suspended and as he ran, an unrolling scroll was projected showing film clips of the flame's journey around the world. As he approached the cauldron, he lit an enormous wick, which then transferred the flame to the cauldron. The flame then spiralled up the structure of the cauldron before lighting it at the top.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://www.china.org.cn/olympics/news/2008-08/13/content_16214170.htm 
  | title = Builders reveal secrets of giant Olympic cauldron
  | publisher = 8-13-2008 
  | work = China.org.cn
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the [[2010 Winter Olympics]] at [[Vancouver]], British Columbia, Canada, only three out of four poles came out of the ground. The athletes were to simultaneously light the base of the poles, which would then carry the flame upwards to the cauldron. Because the site of the ceremonies - [[BC Place Stadium|BC Place]] - was a domed stadium, [[Wayne Gretzky]] was sent via the back of a pick-up truck to a secondary site - the [[Vancouver Convention Centre]] which served at the [[International Broadcast Centre]] for these Olympics - to light a larger cauldron of a similar design as Olympic rules state that the flame must be in public view for the entirety of the Olympics.

==See also==
{{Commons|Olympic torch}}
{{Wikinews|Protests surround Olympic torch relay}}
* [[Eternal flame|Eternal Flame]]
* [[Flame of Hope]]
* [[International Olympic Committee]]
* [[Olympic symbols]]
* [[Olympic Oath]]
* [[Queen's Baton Relay]], an analogous relay associated with the [[Commonwealth Games]]
* [[Panamerican Torch]], a torch relay associated with the [[Panamerican Games]]
* [[Asian Games Torch]], a torch relay associated with the [[Asian Games]]
* The Olympic Flame has been used as a symbol and main motif numerous times in different commemorative coins.  A recent sample was the [[Euro gold and silver commemorative coins (Finland)#2002 coinage|50th anniversary of the Helsinki Olympic Games commemorative coin]], minted in 2002, celebrating the 50th anniversary of this event. In the Obverse, the Olympic Flame above the Earth can be seen. Note that [[Finland]] is the only country highlighted on earth, as a representation of the host of these games.

==References==
*Volker Kluge. 1997-2004. ''Olympische Sommerspiele &amp;ndash; Die Chronik''. Five volumes. Sportverlag except Vol. 5 (Südwest-Verlag). ISBN 3-328-00715-6; ISBN 3-328-00740-7; ISBN 3-328-00741-5; ISBN 3-328-00830-6; ISBN 3-517-06732-6.

==Notes==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Olympicflame.ogg|2006-01-10}}
{{Reflist|group=notes}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.olympic.org/uk/games/index_uk.asp Official site of the Olympic Movement] - Images and information on every game since 1896
* [http://multimedia.olympic.org/pdf/en_report_655.pdf IOC brochure on the history of Olympic Flame (1 MB PDF)]
* [http://www.torchrelay.net TorchRelay.net] - Torch Relay coverage. Includes torchbearer profiles, photos, videos, and more.
* [http://www.athensinfoguide.com/olympictorchessummer.htm Athens Info Guide] - A list of past torches
* [http://www.sondrenorheim.com/olympics/ Sondre Norheim - on the three occasions when the Olympic Flame was lit in Morgedal]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7330949.stm BBC article on the history of the torch]
*[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/olympics/ The Nazi Olympics: Berlin 1936 - online exhibition]
*[http://www.ctvolympics.ca/torch/follow-torch/index.html Live feed of current torch relay]
{{Olympic symbols}}

[[Category:Olympic Flame|*]]
[[Category:Athletic culture based on Greek antiquity|Flame]]
[[Category:Ceremonial flames]]
[[Category:Olympics opening ceremonies]]

[[af:Olimpiese vlam]]
[[ar:شعلة أولمبية]]
[[bg:Олимпийски огън]]
[[bs:Olimpijski plamen]]
[[ca:Flama olímpica]]
[[cs:Olympijský oheň]]
[[da:Olympiske ild]]
[[de:Olympischer Fackellauf]]
[[et:Olümpiatuli]]
[[el:Ολυμπιακή Φλόγα]]
[[es:Llama olímpica]]
[[eo:Olimpika flamo]]
[[fa:مشعل المپیک]]
[[fr:Flamme olympique]]
[[ko:올림픽 성화]]
[[hi:ओलम्पिक ज्वाला]]
[[hr:Olimpijski plamen]]
[[id:Api Olimpiade]]
[[it:Fiamma olimpica]]
[[he:הלפיד האולימפי]]
[[ka:ოლიმპიური ცეცხლი]]
[[la:Ignis Olympicus]]
[[lt:Olimpinė liepsna]]
[[hu:Olimpiai láng]]
[[ms:Api Olimpik]]
[[nl:Olympische vlam]]
[[ja:聖火]]
[[no:Den olympiske ild]]
[[pl:Znicz olimpijski]]
[[pt:Chama Olímpica]]
[[ru:Олимпийский огонь]]
[[sa:ओलम्पिक् ज्वाला]]
[[sq:Pishtari olimpik]]
[[simple:Olympic Flame]]
[[sk:Olympijský oheň]]
[[sr:Олимпијски пламен]]
[[sh:Olimpijski plamen]]
[[fi:Olympiatuli]]
[[sv:Den olympiska elden]]
[[tl:Apoy ng Olimpiko]]
[[th:คบเพลิงโอลิมปิก]]
[[uk:Олімпійський вогонь]]
[[zh-yue:奧運聖火]]
[[zh:奥林匹克圣火]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
