<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="742578" ns="0" title="University of Texas–Pan American"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name = {{nowrap|The University of Texas–Pan American}}
|image = [[Image:Utpaseal.jpg|University of Texas - Pan American seal]]
|motto = {{lang-la|Disciplina praesidium civitatis}} (Education, the Guardian of Society)
|established = [[1927]]
|type = [[Public]] [[State university system|state university]]
|president = Dr. Robert S. Nelsen (President-Designate)
|city = [[Edinburg, Texas|Edinburg]]
|state = [[Texas]]
|country = [[United States|USA]]
|students = 17,534 (2008)&lt;ref name=&quot;student-faculty-pop&quot;&gt;[http://www.utsystem.edu/news/CampusDescriptions/UTPA.htm/ Enrollment] ''The University of Texas System''. Accessed 22 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
|faculty = 819 (2008)
|campus = [[urban area|Urban]], 238 acres (0.96 km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)
|nickname = Broncs
|mascot = Bucky the [[Bronc]]
|colors = Green and Orange {{color box|#006600}}{{color box|#FF6600}}&lt;ref name=&quot;colors&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=University of Texas-Pan American|title=Colors|url=http://ur.utpa.edu/publications/styleguide/91cc06314fbe83f2210|work=[http://ur.utpa.edu/publications/styleguide UTPA Styleguide]|accessdate=2011-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;White and green prior to UT System merger.&lt;ref name=&quot;old colors&quot;&gt;[http://www.panam.edu/newhop/ Colors] ''The University of Texas - Pan American Handbook of Operating Procedures''. Accessed 22 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
|website = [http://www.utpa.edu/ www.utpa.edu]
|logo = [[File:UPTA Logo.svg|200px|alt=Four alternating green and orange rectangles arranged as a pinwheel with a white star superimposed in center. To the right of the pinwheel graphic are the letters &quot;UTPA&quot; in large font, and the pinwheel graphic and acronym are underscored with the small-font text &quot;The University of Texas-Pan American&amp;trade;&quot;]]
|footnotes =
}}
'''The University of Texas–Pan American''' ('''UTPA'''), founded as '''Edinberg College''', is a state university located in [[Edinburg, Texas]].  Founded in 1927, it is a component institution of [[The University of Texas System]].  The university serves the [[Rio Grande Valley]] and South&amp;nbsp;Texas with baccalaureate, masters-level, and doctoral degrees. Since the institution's founding, it has grown from 200 students to over 17,000, making UTPA the [[List of largest Texas universities by enrollment|tenth-largest]] university in the state of [[Texas]].  The majority of these students are natives of the Rio Grande Valley. UTPA also operates an Upper Level Studies Center in Rio Grande City, Starr County, Texas.

==History==
* '''Edinburg College.''' Founded in 1927 as a two-year [[junior college]] administered by the [[Edinburg Consolidated Independent School District|Edinburg School District]].
* '''Edinburg Junior College.''' Designated as a [[junior college]] in 1933 and admitted to the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools|Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools of Southern States]].
* '''Pan American College.''' [[Hidalgo County, Texas|Hidalgo County]] permitted to hold referendum for a four-year university in 1951; school became '''Pan American Regional College''' on December 20, 1951. Name changed to Pan American College following January, 1952, appointment of a [[Board of Regents]]. Became 22nd member institution of the Texas System of Colleges and Universities in 1965, as a state [[junior college|senior college]]. Approved to offer graduate programs in 1970, beginning with [[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|Master of Arts]], [[Master of Education]], and [[Master of Science]].
* '''Pan American University.''' Achieved full university status and changed name to PAU. In 20-year period from 1965 to 1984, enrollment grew from 2,000 to nearly 10,000. Established second campus at [[Brownsville, Texas|Brownsville]] in 1973 (now [[University of Texas at Brownsville]]). In December 1988, board members reached merger agreement with the [[University of Texas System]] pending state legislative approval (one of a series of similar mergers among state universities during that time period), granted in September, 1989.
* '''The University of Texas–Pan American.''' Adopted present name subsequent to merger, preserving the nearly 40-year legacy of the Pan American name.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;&gt;{{Handbook of Texas|id=uu/kcunf|name=University of Texas-Pan American|accessed October 13, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
UTPA's main campus is located in the western part of [[Edinburg, TX|Edinburg]], and comprises 289 acres.&lt;ref name=&quot;colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com&quot;&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/edinburg-tx/utpa-3599&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of academic buildings are enclosed by or span a covered walk way that spans the perimeter of the original campus.  In recent years UTPA has added a new wellness center(2007&lt;ref&gt;http://www.utpa.edu/news/index.cfm?newsid=3349&lt;/ref&gt;), and dormitory (Unity Dormitory 2007&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kirksey.com/project/university_of_texas_pan_american_unity_hall&lt;/ref&gt;).  On the northeast corner of campus is the [[Edinburg Stadium|Edinburg Baseball Stadium]], which is also the home of the [[Edinburg Roadrunners]] an independent baseball team.  The stadium was completed in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;http://mysite.verizon.net/charliesballparks/stadiums/edinburg.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Starr County Upper-Level Center===
The Starr Country Upper-Level Center is located in [[Rio Grande City, Texas|Rio Grande City]]. The center opened in 2003&lt;ref&gt;http://www.utpa.edu/news/index.cfm?newsid=2539&lt;/ref&gt; and was rededicated and moved to a new location in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.utpa.edu/news/index.cfm?newsid=4138&lt;/ref&gt;  Most courses offered are in bilingual education.  There are also limited courses in criminal justice, history, English, and anthropology.&lt;ref&gt;http://portal.utpa.edu/utpa_main/daa_home/oug_home/sculc_home&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:Sciandengpath.jpg|right|250px|thumbnail|Pathway leading toward the Science and Engineering buildings.]]
As part of its [[mission statement]], the university offers a wide variety of degrees spanning across 6 colleges.  Currently, there are 56 [[bachelor's degree|bachelor's]] degrees, 45 [[master's degree|master's]] degrees, 2 [[doctorate|doctoral]] degrees, and one cooperative [[Doctor of Pharmacy|doctoral pharmacy]] program with [[The University of Texas at Austin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;areas-of-excellence&quot;&gt;[http://www.panam.edu/president/areasofexcellence.htm Areas of Excellence] ''The University of Texas – Pan American''. Accessed 22 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rankings===
US News and World report rates UTPA as a tier 2 University.&lt;ref name=&quot;colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com&quot;/&gt;  

In [[Forbes]]' 2009 best college rankings that heavily weighted proportion of graduates who obtain a job upon graduation, UTPA ranked 32 among public universities and 218 among all universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/2009/08/06/best-public-colleges-opinions-colleges-09-top.html | work=Forbes | title=America's Best Public Colleges | date=5 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Among public schools in Texas, UTPA ranked only behind the University of Texas and Texas A&amp;M.

In 2009 UTPA ranked behind only Florida International for bachelor degrees awarded to Hispanic students.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hispanicoutlook.com/top100_focus.htm?section=b&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the U.S. government, among schools with an enrollment of at least 5,000 students, UTPA ranked as the 2nd most affordable school in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/galleries/2011/pf/college/1106/gallery.10_most_affordable_colleges/index.html | work=CNN | first=Annalyn | last=Censky | title=10 Most Affordable Colleges}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admissions, enrollment and retention===

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;
!Ethnic enrollment,&lt;br /&gt; 2010&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stateuniversity.com/universities/TX/The_University_of_Texas_Pan_American.html&lt;/ref&gt;
!Male&lt;br /&gt;
!Female&lt;br /&gt;
!Total&lt;br /&gt;
|-
|[[Asian American]]
| 89
| 132
| 221
|-
|[[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic American]]
| 6,148
| 8,985
| 15,133
|-
|[[White American|Caucasian American]]
| 492
| 515
| 1,007
|-
|[[African American]]
| 59
| 56
| 115
|-
|[[Native Americans in the United States|American Indian]]
| 8
| 10
| 18
|-
|Non Resident Alien
| 455
| 475
| 930
|-
|Not stated/Unknown
| 43
| 67
| 110
|-
|Total
| 7,294
| 10,240
| 17,534
|}

Historically UTPA has had open enrollment such that any student able to graduate from an approved public or private high school was granted admission to the University.  This policy was implemented by former president Miguel Nevarez.  After Nevarez retired UTPA moved towards minimum admission standards.  The minimum standards for Fall 2011 admission are a diploma from a recognized high school and a combined Math/Verbal SAT score of 860 or an ACT score of 18.  Additionally the minimum criteria will be met with a SAT score of 810 or ACT score of 17 if the applicant is in the top third of his/her graduating class or an SAT score of 760 or ACT score of 16 will suffice if the applicant is in the top quarter of his/her graduating class.&lt;ref&gt;http://portal.utpa.edu/utpa_main/dess_home/admissions_home_new/freshmen_home&lt;/ref&gt;  Any student who graduates from a recognized Texas high school as a member of the top 10% of his/her graduating class is guaranteed admission.

In 1997 UTPA started the University Scholars Program in an attempt to retain top local high school students.  The program is an objective academic scholarship based on three tiers.  The first tier is high school graduation standing.  The second tier is advanced placement testings.  The third tier is standardized testing scores.  UTPA will guarantee full tuition funding for any student who meets one of many objective minimum requirements in all three tiers.&lt;ref&gt;https://portal.utpa.edu/portal/page/portal/utpa_main/dua_home/development_home_new/images_files/TieredBrochure-5.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

UTPA's first to second year retention rate for full time students is 71%.&lt;ref name=&quot;forbes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2010/94/best-colleges-10_The-University-of-Texas-Pan-American_94595_2.html | work=Forbes | title=#436 The University of Texas-Pan American Page 2 of 2 | date=11 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  UTPA's 4-year graduation rate is 13% and the 6-year graduation rate is 36%.&lt;ref name=&quot;forbes.com&quot;/&gt;  The proportion of students who receive some sort of financial aid is 86%.

==Student life==
===Housing===
All students under the age of 21 who have earned fewer than 30 credit hours are required to reside on campus unless they are married, a parent or have a permanent residence within 60 miles of campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://portal.utpa.edu/utpa_main/dess_home/residence_home/residence_housing&lt;/ref&gt;  UTPA offers 3 residence halls and 1 community of on-campus apartments.  Troxel Hall and Heritage Hall are the oldest residence halls on campus and until 2000 were the only residence options for students.  Heritage Hall is an all female residence hall. At the end of 2009 Troxel Hall closed due to low capacity.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.panamericanonline.com/news-proposal/low-occupancy-to-close-troxel-hall-dormitory-1.1871083&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2000 the Bronc Village Apartments were completed on north campus and offered students 1, 2 and 4 bedroom options.&lt;ref&gt;http://portal.utpa.edu/utpa_main/dess_home/residence_home/residence_housing/housing_bva/bva_info&lt;/ref&gt;  In fall 2006 Unity Hall was opened as the first new residence hall in more than 30 years; it has 204 double rooms and is divided into male and female wings.&lt;ref name=&quot;utpa.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.utpa.edu/news/index.cfm?newsid=3348&lt;/ref&gt;  Heritage Hall, Unity Hall and the Bronc Village apartments combined can hold approximately 800 students&lt;ref name=&quot;utpa.edu&quot;/&gt;

===Student organizations and activities===
===Athletics===
The University of Texas–Pan American competes in NCAA Division I, in the [[Great West Conference]]. It is one of five schools in the University of Texas System that compete in Division I; the others are the UT campuses in Austin, El Paso, San Antonio, and Arlington.

UTPA won the 1963 [[NAIA national men's basketball championship]] under Coach Sam Williams.  [[Lucious Jackson]] a/k/a Luscious &quot;Luke&quot; Jackson was one of the players on that championship team.  Jackson was selected 4th overall during the 1964 NBA draft. He played on the 1964-65 NBA all rookie team and played in the NBA All Star game that same year.  Jackson played his entire career with the [[Philadelphia 76ers]].

The basketball program, during the mid 1970's was coached by [[Abe Lemons]].  Under Lemons, the program had very successful seasons but, lamentably, failed to get invited to any NCAA tournaments.  Coach Lemons was later hired away by the University of Texas at Austin.

Upon Lemons' departure to the [[University of Texas]], [[Bill White (basketball coach)|Bill White]] was named the head basketball coach.  While at Pan American, Coach White led the Broncs to their first post-season tournament play at the Division I level.  During the 1980-81 season, Pan American earned a berth to the [[1981 National Invitation Tournament]].  The Broncs lost to the 1981 NIT champs, the [[University of Tulsa]] Golden Hurricane.

The basketball program was later coached by [[Lon Kruger]], who later went on to coach at [[Kansas State University]], [[University of Florida]], [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign|University of Illinois]] and [[University of Nevada, Las Vegas]].  He also coached the [[Atlanta Hawks]] of the [[NBA]].

UTPA Tennis program won several doubles NAIA championships from 1959 through 1962 under Coach Don Russell, who himself captured several championships while playing and coaching the team.

UTPA baseball squad placed 4th in the 1971 College World Series under Coach [[Al Ogletree]].

It has been announced that the Broncs would be charter members of the previously football-only [[Great West Conference]] when it begins all-sports play in 2008. During the fall of 2008, the UTPA Cross Country team was the first to win the Great West Conference team title.&lt;ref&gt;http://deseretnews.com/article/1,5143,700241969,00.html New Great West Conference&lt;/ref&gt;  UTPA was previously a member of the [[Sun Belt Conference]] from 1991-1998.

==Alumni==

*[[Pablo Almaguer]]: Chair of the State Bar of Texas Board of Directors
*[[Gloria Anzaldua]]: Novelist, Educator, Cultural Theorist
*[[Hispanic_Admirals_in_the_United_States_Navy#Other_Hispanic_Admirals|Jose Luis Betancourt, Jr.]]: Retired Rear Admiral of the [[United States Navy]]
*[[Minerva G. Carcaño]]: Bishop
*[[Mire Chatman]]: Euro Basketball player
*[[Ken Green (basketball, born 1959)|Apple Green]]: Retired NBA player
*[[Rene Guerra]]: Hidalgo County District Attorney
*[[Greg Guy]]: Former NCAA basketball scoring champion
*[[Jim Hickey (baseball)|Jim Hickey]]: MLB Pitching Coach
*[[Juan &quot;Chuy&quot; Hinojosa]]: Texas State Senator
*[[Perry Hill (baseball)|Perry Hill]]: MLB Assistant Coach
*[[Rubén Hinojosa]]: Congressman
*[[Lucious Jackson]]: Olympic Gold Medalist and NBA player
*[[Eddie Lucio]]: Texas State Senator
*[[Otto Moore]]: Retired NBA Player
*[[Valente Rodriguez]]: Actor
*[[Marshall Rogers (basketball)|Marshall Rogers]]: Former NCAA Basketball Scoring Champion
*[[Fred Taylor (basketball player)|Fred Taylor]]: Retired NBA Player
*[[Jim Tyrone]]: Retired MLB Player and Member of UTPA College World Series Team
*[[Wayne Tyrone]]: Retired MLB Player and Member of UTPA College World Series Team
*[[George Williams (catcher)|George Williams]]: Retired MLB Catcher

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Texas|University}}
*[http://www.utpa.edu/ UTPA Main] ''Official page for The University of Texas–Pan American''
*[http://www.utpabroncs.com/ Bronc Athletics] ''Official page for Bronc Athletics''
*[http://www.utpaalumni.com/ UTPA Alumni] ''UTPA Alumni Association''
{{UT system}}
{{Great West Conference}}
{{Public universities in Texas}}

{{Coord|26.306227|N|98.173249|W|source:dewiki_region:US-TX_type:landmark|format=dms|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Texas–Pan American, University Of}}
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Texas]]
[[Category:University of Texas–Pan American| ]]
[[Category:University of Texas System|Pan American]]
[[Category:Edinburg, Texas|University of Texas–Pan American]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1927]]
[[Category:Consortium for North American Higher Education Collaboration]]
[[Category:Education in Hidalgo County, Texas]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Hidalgo County, Texas]]
[[Category:Education in Starr County, Texas]]

[[de:University of Texas-Pan American]]
[[es:Universidad de Texas–Pan American]]
[[fa:دانشگاه تگزاس-پان آمریکن]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
