<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="74326" ns="0" title="Nadia Comăneci"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox gymnast
|name= Nadia Comăneci
|image=Nadia Comaneci 1977.jpg
|fullname= Nadia Elena Comăneci
|nickname=
|country= {{Flagcountry|ROU|1965}}
|formercountry=
|birth_date= {{birth date and age|mf=yes|1961|11|12}}
|birth_place= [[Onești]]
|hometown=
|height=
|discipline= WAG
|level=
|natlteam=
|gym=National Training Center
|collegeteam=
|headcoach=
|assistcoach=
|formercoach= [[Béla Károlyi]]; [[Marta Károlyi]]
|choreographer=Geza Pozar
|music=
|eponymousskills=[[Comăneci salto]] (uneven bars)
|retired= 1981
|show-medals = yes
|medaltemplates= &lt;!-- see [[Template:MedalRelatedTemplates]] --&gt;
{{MedalCompetition|[[Olympic Games]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Montréal]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics – Women's artistic individual all-around|All-Around]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Montréal]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics – Women's uneven bars|Uneven Bars]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Montréal]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics – Women's balance beam|Balance Beam]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics|1980 Moscow]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics – Women's balance beam|Balance Beam]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics|1980 Moscow]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics – Women's floor|Floor]]}}
{{MedalSilver|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Montréal]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics – Women's artistic team all-around|Team]]}}
{{MedalSilver|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics|1980 Moscow]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics – Women's artistic team all-around|Team]]}}
{{MedalSilver|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics|1980 Moscow]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1980 Summer Olympics – Women's artistic individual all-around|All-Around]]}}
{{MedalBronze|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Montréal]]|[[Gymnastics at the 1976 Summer Olympics – Women's floor|Floor]]}}
{{MedalWorldChampionships}}
{{MedalGold|[[1978 World Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1978 Strasbourg]]|Balance Beam}}
{{MedalGold|[[1979 World Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1979 Ft. Worth]]|Team}}
{{MedalSilver|[[1978 World Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1978 Strasbourg]]|Team}}
{{MedalSilver|[[1978 World Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1978 Strasbourg]]|Vault}}
{{MedalEuropeanChampionships}}
{{MedalGold|[[1975 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1975 Skien]]|All-Around}}
{{MedalGold|[[1975 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1975 Skien]]|Uneven Bars}}
{{MedalGold|[[1975 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1975 Skien]]|Balance Beam}}
{{MedalGold|[[1975 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1975 Skien]]|Vault}}
{{MedalGold|[[1977 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1977 Prague]]|All-Around}}
{{MedalGold|[[1977 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1977 Prague]]|Uneven Bars}}
{{MedalGold|[[1979 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1979 Copenhagen]]|All-Around}}
{{MedalGold|[[1979 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1979 Copenhagen]]|Vault}}
{{MedalGold|[[1979 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1979 Copenhagen]]|Floor}}
{{MedalSilver|[[1975 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1975 Skien]]|Floor}}
{{MedalSilver|[[1977 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1977 Prague]]|Vault}}
{{MedalBronze|[[1979 European Women's Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1979 Copenhagen]]|Balance Beam}}
{{MedalCompetition|[[Summer Universiade]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[1981 Summer Universiade|1981 Bucharest]]|Team}}
{{MedalGold | [[1981 Summer Universiade|1981 Bucharest]]|All-Around}}
{{MedalGold | [[1981 Summer Universiade|1981 Bucharest]]|Uneven Bars}}
{{MedalGold | [[1981 Summer Universiade|1981 Bucharest]]|Vault}}
{{MedalGold | [[1981 Summer Universiade|1981 Bucharest]]|Floor}}
}}

'''Nadia Elena Comăneci''' ({{IPA-ro|ˈnadi.a koməˈnet͡ʃʲ}}; born November 12, 1961) is a [[Romania]]n [[gymnastics|gymnast]], winner of three [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] gold medals at the [[1976 Summer Olympics]] in [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], [[Canada]], and the first female gymnast ever to be awarded a [[perfect 10 (gymnastics)|perfect score of 10]] in an Olympic gymnastic event. She is also the winner of two gold medals at the 1980 Summer Olympics. She is one of the best-known gymnasts in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;infoplease&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.infoplease.com/ce6/society/A0822234.html|title=Gymnastics|accessdate=September 6, 2007|publisher=infoplease.com|year=2007|author=The Columbia Electronic Encyclopedia, 6th ed.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boa&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.olympics.org.uk/sporthistory.aspx?gt=S&amp;sp=GA Gymnastics history|title=British Olympic Association|accessdate=September 6, 2007|publisher=British Olympic Association|year=2007|author=British Olympic Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/olympics/gymnastics/story/2008/05/14/f-olympics-womengymnastics-history.html &quot;Munchkin leads European charge of gymnastics&quot;] CBC sports, June 3, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000 Comăneci was named as one of the athletes of the century by the [[Laureus World Sports Awards|Laureus World Sports Academy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/SPORT/04/29/nadiacomaneci/index.html | work=CNN | title=Nadia Comaneci | date=July 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Comăneci was born in Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej (now [[Onești]]), [[Romania]], as the daughter of Gheorghe and Ștefania-Alexandrina.&lt;ref name=youngathlete&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/Articles/Misc-Comăneci_YA.html &quot;Olympic Champion Nadia Comăneci''] ''Young Athlete,'' August 1978&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Her pregnant mother was watching a Russian film in which the heroine's name was [[Nadya]], the [[diminutive]] version of the Russian name ''[[Nadezhda (given name)|Nadezhda]]'' (which means &quot;Hope&quot;). She decided that her daughter would be named Nadia, too. Comăneci also has a younger brother named Adrian.&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early gymnastics career==

Nadia began gymnastics in kindergarten with a local team called &quot;Flacăra&quot;, with coaches Duncan and Munteanu.&lt;ref name=Fischer&gt;[http://www.gymn.ca/gymnasticgreats/wag/comaneci.htm Whatever Happened to Nadia Comăneci?] Barbara Fisher and Jennifer Isbister, 2003, Gymnastics Greats.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg.&lt;/ref&gt; At age 6 she was chosen to attend [[Béla Károlyi]]'s experimental gymnastics school after Karolyi spotted her and a friend turning [[Cartwheel (gymnastics)|cartwheel]]s in a schoolyard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.com/Articles/Misc-Comaneci_YA.html &quot;Olympic Champion Nadia Comăneci''] ''Young Athlete,'' August 1978&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 17–19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=si&gt;[http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1091387/2/index.htm &quot;Nadia Awed Ya''] Frank Deford, ''Sports Illustrated,'' August 2, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;  Nadia was training with the Károlyis by the time she was 7 years old, in 1968. She was one of the first students at the gymnastics school established in Onești by Béla and his wife, Marta.  Unlike many of the other students at the Károlyi school, Comăneci was able to commute from home for many years because she lived in the area.&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 19&lt;/ref&gt;

Nadia placed 13th in her first Romanian National Championships in 1969. A year later, in 1970, she began competing as a member of her hometown team and became the youngest gymnast ever to win the Romanian Nationals.&lt;ref name=youngathlete/&gt; In 1971, she participated in her first international competition, a dual junior meet between Romania and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]], winning her first [[List of gymnastics terms#A|all-around]] title and contributing to the team [[Gold medal|gold]]. For the next few years, she competed as a junior in numerous national contests in Romania and additional dual meets with nearby countries such as [[Hungary]], [[Italy]] and [[Poland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;List of competitive results&quot;&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/bios/women/comaneci.html List of competitive results] Gymn-Forum&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of 11, in 1973, she won the all-around gold, as well as the [[Vault (gymnastics)|vault]] and [[uneven bars]] titles, at the Junior Friendship Tournament (Druzhba), an important meet for junior gymnasts.&lt;ref name=&quot;List of competitive results&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 27–28&lt;/ref&gt;

Nadia first major international success came at the age of 13, when she nearly swept the 1975 European Championships in [[Skien]], [[Norway]], winning the all-around and gold medals on every event but the [[Floor (gymnastics)|floor exercise]], in which she placed second. She continued to enjoy success in other meets in 1975, winning the all-around at the &quot;Champions All&quot; competition and placing first in the all-around, vault, [[Balance beam|beam]], and bars at the Romanian National Championships. In the Pre-Olympic test event in [[Montreal]], Comăneci won the all-around and the balance beam golds, as well as [[Silver medal|silver]]s in the vault, floor, and bars behind accomplished Soviet gymnast [[Nellie Kim]], who would prove to be one of her greatest [[Sports rivalry|rival]]s over the next five years.&lt;ref name=&quot;List of competitive results&quot;/&gt;

In March 1976, Comăneci competed in the inaugural edition of the [[American Cup (Gymnastics)|American Cup]] at [[Madison Square Garden]] in [[New York City|New York]]. She received unprecedented scores of 10.0, which signified a perfect routine without any deductions, on vault in both the preliminary and final rounds of competition and won the all-around.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/Articles/NYT-1976_AmCup2.html &quot;Gymnast Posts Perfect Mark&quot;] Robin Herman, ''[[New York Times]],'' March 28, 1976&lt;/ref&gt; Comăneci also received 10s in other meets in 1976, including the prestigious [[Chunichi Cup]] competition in [[Japan]], where she posted perfect marks on the vault and uneven bars.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/results/CCup/Women/1976.html Scores for 1976 Chunichi Cup] Gymn-Forum&lt;/ref&gt;

The international community took note of Comăneci: she was named the [[United Press International]]'s &quot;Female Athlete of the Year&quot; for 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;UPI Athletes of the Year&quot;&gt;[http://www.hickoksports.com/history/upiaoy.shtml UPI Athletes of the Year]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Montreal Olympics==
At the age of 14, Comăneci became one of the stars of the [[1976 Summer Olympics]] in [[Montreal]]. During the team portion of the competition on July 18, her routine on the uneven bars was scored at a 10.0.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usghof.org/files/bio/n_comaneci/n_comaneci.html|title=Biography: COMANECI, Nadia|publisher=U.S. Gymnastics Hall of Fame|accessdate=17 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first time in modern Olympic gymnastics history that the score had ever been awarded. The scoreboards were not even equipped to display scores of 10.0—so Nadia's perfect marks were reported on the boards as 1.00 instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Still A Perfect 10&quot;&gt;[http://www.olympic.org/upload/news/olympic_review/review_2005628172259_UK.pdf &quot;Still A Perfect 10&quot;] ''Olympic Review,'' Paul Ziert, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Over the course of the Olympics, Comăneci would earn six additional 10s, en route to capturing the all-around, beam, and bars titles and a [[bronze medal]] on the floor exercise. The Romanian team also placed second in the team competition.&lt;ref name= &quot;InterGym&quot;&gt;[http://www.intlgymnast.com/legends/comaneci.html Legends: Nadia Comăneci] ''International Gymnast'' magazine&lt;/ref&gt;

Comăneci was the first Romanian gymnast to win the all-around title at the Olympics. She also holds the record as the youngest Olympic gymnastics all-around champion ever; with the revised age-eligibility requirements in the sport (gymnasts must now turn 16 in the calendar year to compete in the Olympics; in 1976 gymnasts had to be 14 by the first day of the competition&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aafla.org/OlympicInformationCenter/OlympicReview/1980/ore155/ORE155p.pdf &quot;Within the International Federations&quot;] (PDF). ''Olympic Review,'' 1980&lt;/ref&gt;), it is currently not possible to legally break this record.&lt;!--Based on the decisions of the FIG, which has moved the age limits up three times since 1980 and wants to change it to 18, it's very, very unlikely 14 year olds will ever be allowed at the Olympics again, but we'll leave out the &quot;never&quot; for now --&gt;

Comăneci's achievements at the Olympics generated a significant amount of media attention. An instrumental piece from the musical score of the 1971 film ''[[Bless the Beasts and Children (film)|Bless the Beasts and Children]]'', &quot;Cotton's Dream&quot; (which was also used as the title theme music from the American [[soap opera]] ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'') became associated with her after cinematographer/feature reporter [[Robert Riger]] used it against slow-motion montages of Nadia on the television program [[Wide World of Sports (US TV series)|ABC's Wide World Of Sports]]. The song became a top ten single in the fall of 1976, and the composers, [[Barry De Vorzon]] and [[Perry Botkin, Jr.]], renamed it to &quot;[[Nadia's Theme]]&quot; after her.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olympic.org/uk/athletes/profiles/bio_uk.asp?PAR_I_ID=44503 &quot;Nadia Comăneci: The Perfect 10&quot;] International Olympic Committee (IOC) website&lt;/ref&gt; However, Comăneci never actually performed to &quot;Nadia's Theme.&quot; Her floor exercise music was a medley of the songs &quot;[[Yes Sir, That's My Baby]]&quot; and &quot;[[Jump in the Line]]&quot; arranged for piano.&lt;ref name=si /&gt; Nadia Comăneci's achievements are also pictured in the entrance area of the Madison Square Garden in New York City presenting her perfect 10.00 beam-exercise.

She was the 1976 BBC Sports Personality of the Year in the overseas athletes category&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/keyfacts/stories/spoty_overseas.shtml List of winners, BBC Sports Personality of the Year (Overseas)] BBC press office&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Associated Press]]'s 1976 &quot;Female Athlete of the Year&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://encarta.msn.com/media_701500051_761551983_-1_1/Associated_Press_Athletes_of_the_Year.html Associated Press Athletes of the Year] MSN Encarta. [http://www.webcitation.org/5kx7iDzto Archived] 2009-11-01.&lt;/ref&gt; She also retained her title as the UPI Female Athlete of the Year.&lt;ref name=&quot;UPI Athletes of the Year&quot;/&gt; Back home in Romania, Comăneci's success led her to be named a &quot;[[Hero of Socialist Labor]]&quot;; she was the youngest Romanian to receive such recognition during the administration of [[Nicolae Ceauşescu]].&lt;ref name=Fischer/&gt;

== 1977–1980 ==
Comăneci successfully defended her European all-around title in 1977, but when questions about the scoring were raised, Ceauşescu ordered the Romanian gymnasts to return home. The team followed orders and controversially walked out of the competition during the event finals.&lt;ref name=Fischer/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 61–62&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the 1977 Europeans, the Romanian Gymnastics Federation removed Comăneci from her longtime coaches, the Károlyis, and sent her to [[Bucharest]] to train at the 23 August sports complex. The change was not positive for Comăneci. Grappling with both the stress of her parents' divorce and the new training environment, she was extremely unhappy and her gymnastics and overall fitness suffered.&lt;ref name=Fischer/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 64–68&lt;/ref&gt; Heavier and out-of-shape, Comăneci competed in the [[1978 World Artistic Gymnastics Championships|1978 World Championships]]. A fall from the uneven bars resulted in a 4th place finish in the all-around behind [[Elena Mukhina]], Nellie Kim, and [[Natalia Shaposhnikova]], but Comăneci won the beam title.

After the 1978 Worlds, Comăneci was permitted to return to Deva and to the Károlyis.&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 68–72&lt;/ref&gt; In 1979, a newly slim and motivated Comăneci won her third consecutive European all-around title, becoming the first gymnast, male or female, to achieve the feat. At the [[1979 World Championships in Artistic Gymnastics|World Championships]] that December, Comăneci led the field after the compulsory competition but was hospitalized before the optional portion of the team competition for blood poisoning caused by a cut in her wrist from her metal grip buckle. Against doctors' orders, she left the hospital and competed on the beam, where she scored a 9.95. Her performance helped give the Romanians their first team gold medal. After her performance, Comăneci spent several days recovering in All Saints Hospital and underwent a minor surgical procedure for the infected hand, which had developed an [[abscess]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/Articles/Misc-Comaneci-1979.html &quot;Nadia.&quot;] ''The Epistle,'' (All Saints Episcopal Hospital), January 1980&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 87–91&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Little Girls in Pretty Boxes.'' Ryan, Joan. 1995, Doubleday. ISBN 0-385-47790-2&lt;/ref&gt;

Comăneci participated in the [[1980 Summer Olympics]] in Moscow, where she placed second, by a small margin, to [[Yelena Davydova]]. She defended her Olympic title in the balance beam and tied with [[Nellie Kim]] for the gold medal in the floor exercise. The Romanian team finished second overall.

Comăneci retired from competition in 1981. Her official retirement ceremony took place in Bucharest in 1984 and was attended by the [[International Olympic Committee]] Chairman.&lt;ref name=&quot;Still A Perfect 10&quot;/&gt;

==Post retirement==

In 1981, Comăneci participated in a gymnastics exhibition tour in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/Articles/NYT-1981_Comaneci_Tour.html &quot;Miss Comăneci, 19, Makes Fresh Start&quot;]. Ira Berkow, ''New York Times,'' March 6, 1981&lt;/ref&gt; During the tour, her coaches, Béla and Marta Károlyi, along with the Romanian team choreographer Géza Pozsár, defected.&lt;ref&gt;''Little Girls in Pretty Boxes.'' Ryan, Joan. 1995, Doubleday. ISBN 0-385-47790-2 pg. 201&lt;/ref&gt; Upon her return to Romania, Comăneci's actions were strictly monitored. She was granted leave to attend the [[1984 Summer Olympics|1984 Olympics]] in [[Los Angeles]] but was supervised for the entire trip. Aside from that journey, and a few select trips to Moscow and Cuba, Comăneci was forbidden to leave the country for any reason.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Still A Perfect 10&quot;/&gt; &quot;Life...&quot; she wrote in her autobiography, &quot;took on a new bleakness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

In Romania, between 1984 and 1989, Comăneci was a member of the Romanian Gymnastics Federation and helped coach the Romanian junior gymnasts. In November 1989, a few weeks before the [[Romanian Revolution of 1989|revolution]], she defected with a group of other young Romanians. Her overland journey took her through Hungary, Austria, and finally, to the United States.&lt;ref name=Fischer/&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;InterGym&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Letters to a Young Gymnast''. Comăneci, Nadia. 2004, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01276-0 pg. 137–148&lt;/ref&gt; Her initial arrival in the United States generated some negative press, focusing on her penchant for heavy makeup and flashy clothes, and the fact that her constant companion Constantin Panait (a Romanian exile who arranged her escape from Romania and initially exercised considerable control over her as her self-appointed business manager) was a married father of four.&lt;ref name = &quot;Escaping&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Schneider | first = Karen S.  | authorlink = 
  | title = After Escaping Her Romanian Svengali, Nadia Comăneci Tries to Get Her Life Back on the Beam
  | journal = [[People (magazine)|People]] | volume = 34 | issue = 21 | pages = 
  | publisher =  | date = 1990-11-26
  | language =  | url = http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20113727,00.html
  | accessdate = 2011-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the help of her former coach Béla Károlyi and his friend Alexandru Stefu, a Romanian rugby coach, Comăneci was able to make a break with Panait and settle in Montreal.&lt;ref name = &quot;Escaping&quot;/&gt; She successfully distanced herself from the image problems of her initial arrival from Romania. Comăneci spent most of her time touring and promoting lines of gymnastics apparel and aerobic equipment. She also dabbled in modeling, appearing in advertisements for wedding dresses and Jockey underwear.&lt;ref name= &quot;InterGym&quot; /&gt;

While she was living in Montreal, [[Bart Conner]], whom she had met for the first time in 1976 at the American Cup, contacted her and invited her to live in Oklahoma. They became engaged in 1994. Together with Conner, she returned to Romania for the first time since her defection (and since the [[fall of Communism]] and [[Nicolae Ceaușescu|Ceauşescu]]'s death), and the couple were married in Bucharest on April 27, 1996. The ceremony was broadcast live in Romania, and the reception was held in the former presidential palace.&lt;ref name= &quot;InterGym&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-72893201.html &quot;Nadia Tumbles over Wedding&quot;] ''Cincinnati Post,'' April 6, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 29, 2001, Comăneci became a [[naturalized citizen]] of the United States. She has also retained her Romanian passport, making her a [[dual citizen]].&lt;ref name=Fischer/&gt;

In December 2003, Comăneci's book ''[[Art of Mentoring|Letters To A Young Gymnast]]'' was published, a combination of mentoring book and memoir. The book answered questions that she has received in letters from fans. She has also been the subject of several unofficial biographies, television documentaries and a made-for-television film, ''Nadia,'' that was broadcast in the United States shortly before the 1984 Olympics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0087774/ Nadia at the IMDB]&lt;/ref&gt;

Comăneci and Conner welcomed their first child, a son named Dylan Paul Conner, on June 3, 2006 in [[Oklahoma City]], [[Oklahoma]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,198443,00.html &quot;Nadia Comăneci, Bart Conner Welcome Baby Boy&quot;] Associated Press, June 6, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://old.jurnalul.ro/articol.php?id=60535 &quot;Former Gymnasts Nadia Comăneci and Bart Conner Baptized Their First Child, Dylan Paul&quot;] Catalina Iancu, ''Jurnalul National,'' August 28, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent activities==
[[File:Comaneci05.jpg|thumb|Nadia Comăneci (right) with [[Condoleezza Rice]].]]
Comăneci is active in many charities and international organizations. In 1999, she became the first athlete to be invited to speak at the [[United Nations]] to launch the Year 2000 International Year of Volunteers. She is currently the Vice-Chair of the Board Of Directors of the International [[Special Olympics]] and Vice President of the Board of Directors of the [[Muscular Dystrophy Association]].&lt;ref name= &quot;InterGym&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mda.org/Publications/Quest/q74bart_nadia.html &quot;MDA's Perfect 10s&quot;] Muscular Dystrophy Association&lt;/ref&gt; She has also personally funded the construction and operation of the Nadia Comăneci Children's Clinic, a clinic in Bucharest that provides low-cost and free medical and social support to Romanian children.&lt;ref name=&quot;Still A Perfect 10&quot;/&gt;

In 2003, the Romanian government appointed her as an Honorary Consul General of Romania to the United States to deal with bilateral relations between the two nations. She performs this function based out of her [[Norman, Oklahoma]] office.&lt;ref name=&quot;consul&quot;&gt;[http://www.state.gov/s/cpr/rls/fco/fallwinter2/71029.htm ''Diplomatic List'', Office of the Chief of Protocol, U.S. Department of State.] Summer 2006. Accessed January 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the world of gymnastics, Comăneci is the Honorary President of the Romanian Gymnastics Federation, the Honorary President of Romanian Olympic Committee, Ambassador of Sports of Romania and a member of the International Gymnastics Federation Foundation. She and her husband own the Bart Conner Gymnastics Academy, the Perfect 10 Production Company and several sports equipment shops. They are also the editors of ''International Gymnast'' magazine. Additionally, Comăneci and Conner have provided television commentary for many gymnastics meets, most recently the 2005 World Championships in [[Melbourne]]&lt;ref name= &quot;InterGym&quot; /&gt; and the 2008 Olympic Games in Beijing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espnmag/story?id=3540036 |title=The First Family of Gymnastics |accessdate=2008-08-21 |last=Roenigk |first=Alyssa |work=ESPN The Magazine |date=2008-08-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, her 10.0 Montreal uneven bars routine was featured in a commercial for [[Adidas]] which ran during the Athens Olympics.

On August 10, 2007, Nadia was a &quot;mob&quot; participant on the American version of the game show [[1 vs. 100 (US game show)|1 vs 100]], and was not eliminated until the last 20 members of the mob were left. In January 2008, she was one of the contestants in the celebrity edition of [[Donald Trump]]'s television program ''[[The Apprentice (U.S. Season 7)|The Apprentice]].''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eonline.com/news/article/index.jsp?uuid=c22898ed-f3a8-42dc-905d-5eb02aec8103 &quot;Trump's celebrity 'Apprenti' revealed&quot;] Gina Serpe, E! News, November 19, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
Comăneci received the [[Olympic Order]], the highest award given by the [[International Olympic Committee]], in 1984 and 2004. She is the only person to receive this honor twice, and was also the youngest recipient. She has also been inducted into the [[International Gymnastics Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Nadia Comaneci | work = International Gymnastics Hall of Fame | url = http://www.ighof.com/honorees/honorees_nadia.html | accessdate = May 12, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Special skills==
Comăneci was known for her clean technique, innovative and difficult original skills, and her stoic, cool demeanor in competition.&lt;ref name=si /&gt;&lt;ref name=indy&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4159/is_20040411/ai_n12753831 &quot;SPORTS ACTIVE: NO TURNING BACK – Nadia Comăneci's perfect Olympic 10&quot;] George Chesterson, ''The Independent,'' April 11, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=leap&gt;[http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1090964/index.htm &quot;A Great Leap Backward&quot;] Anita Verschoth, ''Sports Illustrated,'' April 12, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,914450-3,00.html &quot;The Games: Up in the Air&quot;] ''Time'', August 2, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;

On the uneven bars, Comăneci performed her own release move, a kip to front salto. The skill is named after her in the women's ''[[Code of Points (artistic gymnastics)|Code of Points]]'' and, as of 2005, was rated as an 'E' element.&lt;ref name=indy /&gt;&lt;ref name=leap /&gt; Also named for her is the 'Comăneci dismount' a half twist to back salto.

On the balance beam, Comăneci was the first gymnast to successfully perform an aerial walkover and an aerial cartwheel-back handspring flight series. She is also credited as being the first gymnast to perform a double-twist dismount.&lt;ref name=si /&gt;&lt;ref name=indy /&gt;&lt;ref name=leap /&gt;

Comăneci's skills on the floor exercise included a double back salto and a double twist.&lt;ref name=leap /&gt;

==Pop culture references==
*''[[Nadia (film)|Nadia]]'' is a 1984 made-for-television [[biopic]] of Nadia Comăneci.


==See also==
*[[List of Eastern Bloc defectors]]
*[[List of multiple Olympic medalists at a single Games]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.bartandnadia.com Official Site of Bart Conner and Nadia Comăneci]
* [http://www.intlgymnast.com International Gymnast Magazine]
* [http://gymnastics.about.com/od/famousgymnasts/p/nadiacomaneci.htm Profile of Nadia Comăneci]
* [http://www.gymn-forum.net/bios/women/comaneci.html List of competitive results at Gymn Forum]
* [http://www.nadiacomaneci.eu/en/index.php The Nadia Comaneci Foundation Website]
{{S-start}}
{{Succession box
|before=[[Irena Szewińska]]|
|title=[[United Press International Athlete of the Year Award#Female winners|United Press International&lt;br /&gt;Athlete of the Year]]|
|after=[[Rosemarie Ackermann]]|
|years=1975, 1976}}
{{Succession box
|before=[[Billie Jean King]]|
|title=[[Flo Hyman Memorial Award]]|
|after=[[Bonnie Blair]]
|years=1998}}
{{S-end}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-ach}}
{{Succession box
|title=[[Associated Press Athlete of the Year|Associated Press Female Athlete of the Year]]
|before={{Flagicon|USA}} [[Chris Evert]]
|after={{Flagicon|USA}} [[Chris Evert]]
|years=1976}}
{{S-end}}

{{Footer olympic champions individual all-round women}}
{{Footer Olympic Champions - Artistic Gymnastics - Women's Balance Beam}}
{{Footer Olympic Champions - Artistic Gymnastics - Women's Floor Exercise}}
{{Footer Olympic Champions - Artistic Gymnastics - Women's Uneven Bars}}
{{NavigationWorldChampionsArtisticGymnasticsWomenTC}}
{{NavigationWorldChampionsArtisticGymnasticsWomenBalanceBeam}}
{{The Apprentice}}
{{The Celebrity Apprentice Season 1}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
|NAME = Comăneci, Nadia
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION =
|DATE OF BIRTH = November 12, 1961
|PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Oneşti]]
|DATE OF DEATH =
|PLACE OF DEATH =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Comaneci, Nadia}}
[[Category:1961 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Gymnasts at the 1976 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Gymnasts at the 1980 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:Olympic gymnasts of Romania]]
[[Category:Olympic gold medalists for Romania]]
[[Category:World champion gymnasts]]
[[Category:Medalists at World Gymnastics Championships]]
[[Category:Romanian gymnastics coaches]]
[[Category:Romanian defectors]]
[[Category:Defectors to the United States]]
[[Category:Romanian female artistic gymnasts]]
[[Category:Originators of elements in artistic gymnastics]]
[[Category:Participants in American reality television series]]
[[Category:The Apprentice (U.S. TV series) contestants]]
[[Category:Romanian exiles]]
[[Category:Naturalized citizens of the United States]]
[[Category:Romanian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:American people of Romanian descent]]
[[Category:People from Oneşti]]
[[Category:Olympic silver medalists for Romania]]
[[Category:Olympic bronze medalists for Romania]]
[[Category:Olympic medalists in gymnastics]]

{{Link FA|ms}}
{{Link FA|pt}}
{{Link GA|ja}}

[[af:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ar:ناديا كومانيتش]]
[[bcl:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[bg:Надя Команечи]]
[[bn:নাদিয়া কোমেনিচি]]
[[ca:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[cs:Nadia Comaneciová]]
[[da:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[de:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[el:Νάντια Κομανέτσι]]
[[es:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[eo:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[fa:نادیا کومانچی]]
[[fr:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[fy:Nadia Comaneci]]
[[gl:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ko:나디아 코마네치]]
[[hr:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[io:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[id:Nadia Comaneci]]
[[it:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[he:נדיה קומנץ']]
[[la:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[lv:Nadja Komaneči]]
[[hu:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ms:Nadia Comaneci]]
[[nl:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ja:ナディア・コマネチ]]
[[nap:Nadia Comaneci]]
[[no:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[pl:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[pt:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ro:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ru:Команечи, Надя]]
[[sq:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[scn:Nadia Comaneci]]
[[simple:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[sl:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[sr:Нађа Команечи]]
[[fi:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[sv:Nadia Comaneci]]
[[tl:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[th:นาเดีย โคมานิชี]]
[[tr:Nadia Comăneci]]
[[ur:نادیہ کومانچی]]
[[zh:纳迪娅·科马内奇]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
