<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7440912" ns="0" title="Smith and Jones (Doctor Who)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Doctor Who episode
|number = 179
|serial_name=Smith and Jones
|show=DW
|type=episode
|image=[[Image:Smith and Jones.jpg|275px]]&lt;!-- FAIR USE of Smith and Jones.jpg: see image description page at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image:Smith and Jones.jpg for rationale --&gt;
|caption=[[Martha Jones]] looks on as the [[Tenth Doctor|Doctor]], posing as John Smith, is scanned and identified as non-human by the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Judoon|Judoon]] in the hospital upon the Moon.
|doctor=[[David Tennant]] ([[Tenth Doctor]])
|companion=[[Freema Agyeman]] ([[Martha Jones]])
|guests=
* [[Anne Reid]] – [[List of Doctor Who villains#Florence Finnegan|Florence Finnegan]]
* [[Roy Marsden]] – Mr Stoker
* [[Adjoa Andoh]] – [[Francine Jones]]
* [[Gugu Mbatha-Raw]] – [[Tish Jones]]
* [[Reggie Yates]] – [[Leo Jones (Doctor Who)|Leo Jones]]
* [[Trevor Laird]] – [[Clive Jones]]
* Kimmi Richards – Annalise
* Ben Righton – Oliver Morgenstern
* [[Vineeta Rishi]] – Julia Swales
* [[Paul Kasey]] – [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Judoon|Judoon]] Leader
* [[Nicholas Briggs]] – Judoon Voices
|writer=[[Russell T Davies]]
|director=[[Charles Palmer (director)|Charles Palmer]]
|script_editor=[[Simon Winstone]]
|producer=[[Phil Collinson]]
|executive_producer=Russell T Davies&lt;br&gt;[[Julie Gardner]]
|production_code=3.1
|length= 45 minutes
|date=31 March 2007
|preceding=&quot;[[The Runaway Bride (Doctor Who)|The Runaway Bride]]&quot;
|following=&quot;[[The Shakespeare Code]]&quot;
|series=[[Doctor Who (series 3)|Series 3]]
|series_link=Series 3 (2007)
}}
&quot;'''Smith and Jones'''&quot; is the first episode of the [[Doctor Who (series 3)|third series]] of the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[science fiction television]] series ''[[Doctor Who]]''. It was first broadcast on [[BBC One]] on 31 March 2007. It sees the debut of [[Freema Agyeman]] as new [[companion (Doctor Who)|companion]] [[Martha Jones]]. Agyeman had previously appeared as Martha's cousin Adeola in &quot;[[Army of Ghosts]]&quot;.

The episode sees [[Tenth Doctor|the Doctor]] ([[David Tennant]]) meeting [[Martha Jones]] ([[Freema Agyeman]]), a medical student at Royal Hope Hospital. The hospital is transported to the [[Moon]], whereupon the Doctor and Martha must contend with a Plasmavore posing as Florence Finnegan ([[Anne Reid]]), as well as the [[Judoon#Judoon|Judoon]] (voiced by [[Nicholas Briggs]]), who are hunting for Finnegan.

The episode was the first to feature Martha's family, her mother [[Francine Jones|Francine]] (played by [[Adjoa Andoh]]), father [[Clive Jones|Clive]] ([[Trevor Laird]]), sister [[Tish Jones|Tish]] ([[Gugu Mbatha-Raw]]), and brother [[Leo Jones (Doctor Who)|Leo]] ([[Reggie Yates]]).

The episode was shot mainly in August 2006, with [[Singleton Hospital]] and the [[University of Glamorgan]] doubling as the fictional Royal Hope Hospital. The Judoon wear prosthetics; for budget reasons only one Judoon is seen to take his helmet off.

According to the [[Broadcasters' Audience Research Board|BARB]] figures this episode was seen by 8.7 million viewers and was the ninth most popular broadcast on British television in that week. It garnered an [[Appreciation Index]] of 88.&lt;ref name=&quot;companion-smith&quot; /&gt;

==Plot==
===Synopsis===
Martha Jones is a particularly astute medical student. On her way into work at a London hospital, she bumps into a strange man ([[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]]) who pauses in front of her and removes his tie, saying, &quot;Like so, see?&quot; When she arrives at work, she again meets the Doctor, who is lying in bed posing as a patient under the name John Smith. He is unaware of seeing Martha earlier in the morning.

[[File:Moon Smith and Jones.jpg|thumb|250px|left|The hospital on the Moon's surface]]
A brutal mercenary police force, the rhinoceros-like [[Judoon]], who have no jurisdiction on Earth, transports the hospital to the Moon using a &quot;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O Scoop&quot; in order to apprehend and execute [[List of Doctor Who villains#Florence Finnegan|Florence Finnegan]], a shapeshifting, bloodsucking [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Plasmavore|Plasmavore]] with the ability to appear as whatever species whose blood she consumes. As soon as the hospital is in position, the cylindrical Judoon ships land and the troopers march into the building (due to their bodily shape and heavy footwear, their motion is referred to throughout the script as &quot;[[yomp]]ing&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;shooting&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/writersroom/insight/downloads/scripts/doctor_who_3_ep_1.pdf|title=&quot;Smith and Jones&quot; Shooting Script|accessdate=3 January 2009|last=Davies|first=Russell T|authorlink=Russell T Davies|format=PDF|pages=19|quote=FX: STOKER's POV, though still distant: yomping across the Moon, a long line of JUDOON.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Judoon begin scanning everyone in the hospital, cataloguing the humans whilst attempting to find the non-human criminal. Finnegan attempts to evade capture by sucking the blood of humans. Her first victim is Mr Stoker, the head doctor, and consequently she registers as a human when the Judoon scan her. But the Doctor is identified as &quot;non-human&quot; and thus is thought to be the fugitive by the Judoon, forcing him and Martha, with whom he teamed up shortly after arriving on the Moon, to flee.

The Doctor and Martha discover Stoker's body drained of blood, confirming the Doctor's suspicion of a Plasmavore in the hospital (and explaining the Doctor's presence there to the audience). The Doctor kisses Martha, thus leaving traces of non-human on her, and goes after Finnegan. The traces cause the Judoon to fully scan her, stalling them. The Doctor finds the Plasmavore in an [[MRI]] room; thinking he's human, Finnegan sucks his blood, causing him to collapse unconscious, apparently dead. Judoon arrive and confirm the non-human is deceased. Martha enters, realises that Finnegan has absorbed non-human blood, grabs a Judoon's scanner and exposes Finnegan as non-human. Confirming Finnegan is the fugitive they seek, the Judoon execute her for the murder of the child princess of Padrivole Regency Nine.

Before being caught, Finnegan had modified the [[MRI]] scanner to make it destroy all life on the Moon and on the half of Earth facing the Moon except herself, thus allowing her to use the Judoon ships to escape. Their job done, the Judoon evacuate. Martha uses [[CPR]] on the Doctor's two hearts and manages to revive him and he turns off the scanner. Oxygen levels are low and the occupants of the hospital are near death but, as they depart, the Judoon return the hospital safely to Earth.

Later, Martha's brother's birthday party breaks down into a nasty family row. Having gone outside, she spies the Doctor and follows him to the [[TARDIS]]. He invites Martha to go on a trip with him as a reward for her help. Martha hesitates until the Doctor says he can travel in time as well, and proves it by travelling back to the previous morning and taking off his tie in front of Martha (later explaining, &quot;Crossing into established events is strictly forbidden &amp;mdash; except for cheap tricks&quot;). After this demonstration, Martha steps into the TARDIS (noting that it's bigger on the inside). The Doctor refers to [[Rose Tyler]] and emphasises that Martha is not replacing her but is only going to get one trip as he prefers to travel alone.

===Continuity===
*Martha asks the Doctor if he has a brother and he replies, &quot;Not any more&quot;. A brother to the Doctor was previously mentioned in the [[Doctor Who spin-offs|spin-off]] [[Virgin New Adventures|New Adventure]] novel ''[[Tears of the Oracle]]'' by [[Justin Richards]], which was edited by [[Simon Winstone]], [[script editor]] for this episode. The brother's name, or at least the name he used, was [[Irving Braxiatel]].
*Though the Doctor recognises the [[Judoon]], this is their first appearance in the Doctor Who universe.
*Morgenstern refers to a &quot;[[Story arcs in Doctor Who#Mr Saxon|Saxon]]&quot; during his radio broadcast, claiming that the events of the episode prove Saxon's theories about alien life correct; in the preceding episode, &quot;[[The Runaway Bride (Doctor Who)|The Runaway Bride]]&quot;, a Mr. Saxon is said to have given the military the order to fire on the Empress's ship.  A &quot;Vote Saxon&quot; poster, identical to one seen in the ''[[Torchwood]]'' episode &quot;[[Captain Jack Harkness]]&quot;, and also in the trailer for the series, can be seen in the alleyway when the Doctor collects Martha. 'Mr Saxon' became the running theme for the third series, which came to its conclusion in the episodes &quot;[[Utopia (Doctor Who)|Utopia]]&quot;, [[The Sound of Drums]]&quot; and &quot;[[Last of the Time Lords]]&quot;.
*The alias &quot;John Smith&quot; was given to the Doctor by [[Jamie McCrimmon]] in the serial ''[[The Wheel in Space]]'' and has been used as an alias by the Doctor on multiple occasions since, most notably during his [[Third Doctor|third incarnation]]. Prior to this episode, his most recent use of the alias was in &quot;[[School Reunion (Doctor Who)|School Reunion]]&quot;.
*At one point, the Doctor wears the same dressing gown he wore in &quot;[[The Christmas Invasion]]&quot;, which originally belonged to [[Jackie Tyler]]'s friend, Howard.
*Martha refers to the spaceship crashing into Big Ben in &quot;[[Aliens of London]]&quot;, the events of &quot;[[The Christmas Invasion]]&quot; or &quot;[[The Runaway Bride (Doctor Who)|The Runaway Bride]]&quot;, and the Battle of Canary Wharf against the Cybermen from &quot;[[Army of Ghosts]]&quot;. She also recalls the loss of her cousin Adeola who &quot;worked at Canary Wharf&quot; and disappeared (a reference to the &quot;Army of Ghosts&quot; character played by the same actress&lt;ref name=&quot;LizoInt&quot;&gt;{{cite interview
 | last = Davies
 | first = Russell T
 | subjectlink = Russell T Davies
 | interviewer = [[Lizo Mzimba]]
 | title = Exclusive Q&amp;A: The brains behind Dr Who
 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/cbbcnews/hi/newsid_5330000/newsid_5339400/5339430.stm
 | format = Q&amp;A
 | program = [[CBBC]] [[Newsround]]
 | date = 2006-09-12
  | accessdate=4 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;).
*The Doctor voices his approval of the hospital shop, a reference to &quot;[[New Earth]]&quot;, when he stated that he likes &quot;little shops&quot;.
*The Doctor grabs Martha's hand and says, &quot;Run!&quot; when the [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Slab|Slabs]] burst through the door. This echoes a similar moment between the [[Ninth Doctor]] and [[Rose Tyler|Rose]] in &quot;[[Rose (Doctor Who)|Rose]]&quot;.
*The Doctor asks for a [[banana]] [[milk shake]]. He previously mentioned the fruit in &quot;[[The Doctor Dances]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Girl in the Fireplace]]&quot;, and in the book ''[[Forever Autumn (Doctor Who)|Forever Autumn]]'', the Doctor also repeatedly asks for a banana split in an ice-cream parlour.
*The Doctor is able to focus [[X-ray|Röntgen radiation]] into his left shoe, showing no real concern to his health. He is, however, susceptible to excessive radiation, the factor that caused the Tenth and [[Third Doctor|Third]] Doctors to [[Regeneration (Doctor Who)|regenerate]] in ''[[The End of Time]]'' and ''[[Planet of the Spiders]]'' respectively.
*The events of this episode are revisited in the 2008 episode &quot;[[Turn Left (Doctor Who)|Turn Left]]&quot;, in which Martha, [[Sarah Jane Smith]], [[Luke Smith (The Sarah Jane Adventures)|Luke Smith]], [[Maria Jackson]] and [[Clyde Langer]] are killed stopping the Plasmavore in a parallel timeline in which the Doctor died during the events of &quot;[[The Runaway Bride (Doctor Who)|The Runaway Bride]]&quot;. In that timeline, Oliver Morgenstern was the only person who survived these events, and only because Martha gave him the last oxygen tank.
*Julia Swales is mentioned as working at the CERN research facility in the ''[[Torchwood]]'' spin-off audio play &quot;[[Lost Souls (Torchwood)|Lost Souls]]&quot;.
*Martha and the Doctor return to the Moon to watch the [[Apollo 11]] landing four times.&lt;ref&gt;Martha's statement to DI Billy Shipton in &quot;[[Blink (Doctor Who)|Blink]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Outside references===
*Martha refers to [[Zovirax]], a cold sore treatment. In the television advertisements for Zovirax a woman goes about her daily routine hiding her cold sores by wearing a motorbike helmet similar to those worn by the [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Slab|Slabs]].
*The Doctor says that he once had a laser spanner which was stolen by Emily Pankhurst, who he refers to as 'a cheeky woman'. [[Emmeline Pankhurst]] was one of the founders of the early 20th century British [[Women's suffrage in the United Kingdom|Suffragette]] movement.
*The Doctor implies that he assisted [[Benjamin Franklin]] during his famous 1752 electricity experiment involving lightning, a kite and a key.
*'Mrs. Finnigan', the Plasmavore, is found drinking Mr. Stoker's blood. Mr. Stoker was intended by Russell T Davies to be a reference to the character Mr Stoker in his 1989 series ''[[Children's Ward]]''. However, the design department saw this as a reference to Bram Stoker, author of ''Dracula'', so the sign 'B. Stoker' was placed on the office door during production.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Production==
This is the first episode not to have a pre-credits sequence since the [[Ninth Doctor]] episode &quot;[[Rose (Doctor Who)|Rose]]&quot; (another series opener, also introducing a new companion). The next series opener, &quot;[[Partners in Crime (Doctor Who)|Partners in Crime]]&quot;, would also have no pre-credits sequence.

===Filming===
Filming took place mainly in August 2006, with additional work done in September, October and November of that year. The hospital was filmed in several places over August - the School of Sciences at the [[University of Glamorgan]]&lt;ref group=&quot;location&quot;&gt;School of Sciences (Hospital): {{Coord|51|35|38|N|3|19|18|W |name=University of Glamorgan, School of Sciences |type:landmark_region:GB-WLS}}&lt;/ref&gt; was used, as well as parts of [[Singleton Hospital]] in [[Swansea]],&lt;ref group=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Singelton Hospital (Hospital): {{Coord|51|36|34|N|3|59|7|W |name=Singleton Hospital |type:landmark_region:GB-WLS}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Usk Valley Business Park.&lt;ref group=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Usk Valley Business Park (Hospital):{{Coord|51|42|33|N|3|0|20|W |name=Usk Valley Business Park |type:landmark_region:GB-WLS}}&lt;/ref&gt; The verandah and the staff kitchen were shot in the Doctor Who production team's studios at Upper Boat, [[Trefforest]].&lt;ref name=&quot;companion-smith&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Upper Boat Studios: {{Coord|51|34|32|N|3|18|2|W |name=Upper Boat Studios |type:landmark_region:GB-WLS}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The alley at the end where the TARDIS was parked was filmed in [[Pontypridd]] in September 2006. The scenes featuring Martha's family were recorded in October 2006, also mainly in [[Pontypridd]].&lt;ref name=&quot;companion-smith&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web
|url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/arts/sites/doctor-who-wales/alllocations/pontypridd-market-street
|title= Walesarts, Market Street, Pontypridd
|publisher = BBC
|author =
|date =
|accessdate = 2010-05-30
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The street scenes with Tish at the start of the episode were filmed on Queen's Street in Cardiff in October.

The overall shape of the hospital was also modified to resemble the more square shape of [[St Thomas' Hospital]].  Early in the episode, a shot of the front of Singleton Hospital is seen where part of the building has been removed and an image of the [[London Eye]] added to make it appear that the hospital is in the location of St. Thomas'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/2340579.stm Article with picture of Singleton Hospital which closely resembles a shot in the opening of the episode]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
The first use of Martha's theme in the music for the episode is sung by [[Melanie Pappenheim]].&lt;ref&gt;according to the ''[[Doctor Who Confidential]]'' episode &quot;Meet Martha Jones&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; She previously featured in &quot;The Doctor's Theme&quot;, &quot;Bad Wolf Theme&quot; and &quot;Doomsday&quot;. The music at the start of the episode, when Martha is talking on the phone to her family, is &quot;[[Sunshine]]&quot; by [[Arrested Development (hip hop group)|Arrested Development]].

===Cast notes===
*[[Freema Agyeman]] previously played Adeola Oshodi in &quot;[[Army of Ghosts]]&quot; (2006).
*[[Adjoa Andoh]] previously appeared as [[Sister Jatt]] in the Tenth Doctor episode &quot;[[New Earth]]&quot; (2006).
*[[Anne Reid]] previously appeared as Nurse Crane in the [[Seventh Doctor]] story ''[[The Curse of Fenric]]'' (1989).
*[[Trevor Laird]] previously appeared as [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Frax|Frax]] in the [[Sixth Doctor]] story ''[[Mindwarp]]'' (1986).
*[[Roy Marsden]] previously appeared in the [[Eighth Doctor]] audio drama ''[[Human Resources (Doctor Who audio)|Human Resources]]''.

==Broadcast and reception==
===Publicity and broadcast===
It was originally planned that the episode would air on 17 March 2007, however, the date was shifted back a week to 24 March, when it was realised that it would have gone up against the final of [[ITV1]] series ''[[Dancing on Ice]]''. The episode was then shifted back another week, to 31 March, because of England's [[UEFA European Football Championship|European Championship]] qualifier against Israel on 24 March.&lt;ref name=&quot;companion-smith&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pixley|first=Andrew|year=2007|month=August|title=Smith and Jones|journal=Doctor Who Magazine Special - Series 3 Companion|publisher=Panini Magazines}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two specially created trailers for the third series were shown on the BBC in the two weeks before broadcast. These trailers featured clips from the series, predominantly with clips of &quot;Smith and Jones&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;companion-trailer&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pixley|first=Andrew|year=2007|month=August|title=Series Three Trailer|journal=Doctor Who Magazine Special - Series 3 Companion|publisher=Panini Magazines}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Smith and Jones&quot; and &quot;[[The Shakespeare Code]]&quot; were previewed to the press on 21 March. This created much hype in the press for the new series in the days leading up to broadcast.&lt;ref name=&quot;companion-smith&quot; /&gt;

===Overseas broadcast===
The first North American broadcast of the episode occurred on 18 June 2007, when the [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]] aired it in Canada. &quot;Smith and Jones&quot; takes place after the 2006 Christmas special &quot;The Runaway Bride&quot;, but the CBC aired them in reverse order, showing &quot;Smith and Jones&quot; immediately prior to &quot;Bride&quot;.

The episode made its US broadcast debut on 6 July 2007, on the [[Sci Fi Channel (United States)|Sci Fi Channel]], directly following &quot;The Runaway Bride&quot;.

==Notes==
;Locations
{{Reflist|2|group=location}}
;Citations
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Empty section|date=October 2011}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote|Tenth Doctor}}
{{TardisIndexFile|Smith and Jones}}
*{{BBCDWnew | year=2007 |id = 301| title = Smith and Jones }}
*{{Doctor Who RG | id= who_tv23 | title=Smith and Jones | quotes=y}}
*{{Brief | id=2007a | title=Smith and Jones | quotes=y}}
*{{IMDB episode|0974728|Smith and Jones}}
*{{Bbc.co.uk|id=/writersroom/insight/downloads/scripts/doctor_who_3_ep_1.pdf|title=''Smith and Jones - Script''}}

;Reviews
*{{DWRG| id=smithjones | title=Smith and Jones | quotes=y}}
*{{OG | id=2007-01 | title=Smith and Jones | quotes=y}}

{{Doctor Who (series 3)}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Smith And Jones (Doctor Who)}}
[[Category:Tenth Doctor episodes|Smith and Jones]]
[[Category:2007 television episodes]]
[[Category:Screenplays by Russell T Davies]]
[[Category:Vampires in film and television]]
[[Category:Moon-related television series]]
[[Category:Doctor Who stories set on Earth]]
[[Category:2007 in British television]]

[[fr:La Loi des Judoons]]
[[ru:Смит и Джонс]]
[[vo:Elan Smith ä Jones]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
