<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="744923" ns="0" title="Tracey E. Bregman"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| image        = &lt;!-- [[Freely licenced]] images only. NO SCREEN CAPTURES. Please do not put a fair-use image here, it will be deleted - see [[WP:NONFREE]] --&gt;
| name         = Tracey E. Bregman
| othername    = Tracey Bregman&lt;br&gt;Tracey E. Bregman-Recht
| birth_date    = {{birth date and age|1963|05|29}}
| birth_place     = [[Munich, Germany]]
| occupation = Actress
| yearsactive = 1978–present 
| othername = Tracy Bregman &lt;br&gt; Tracey Bregman Recht &lt;br&gt; Tracey E. Bregman Recht &lt;br&gt; Tracy E. Bregman Recht 
| spouse =  Ronald Recht (1987-2010)
}}
'''Tracey E. Bregman''' (born May 29, 1963) is an [[Germany|German]]-[[United States|American]] [[soap opera]] [[actress]]. She is best known for the role of [[Lauren Fenmore]] on ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'' (1983–1995, 2000, 2001–present) and ''[[The Bold and the Beautiful]] '' (1992, 1993, 1994, 1995–1999, 2000, 2002, 2004, 2007) and for her role as [[The_Young_and_the_Restless_minor_characters#Sarah_Smythe|Sarah Smythe]] on ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'' (2010).

==Personal life==
She was born in [[Munich, Germany]] to [[United States|American]] musical arranger, record producer and composer [[Buddy Bregman]] and actress Suzanne Lloyd. She lived in Great Britain until the age of 10 when her family relocated to California. She has been acting since she was 11 years old. 

In 2004, Bregman launched her own yoga inspired clothing line &quot;Bountiful Buddha&quot; which sold popularly at friend [[Lisa Rinna]]'s boutique &quot;Belle Gray&quot; in Los Angeles.

Bregman is also an active supporter and honorary board member for Chenoa Manor, an animal sanctuary in Chester County, Pennsylvania.[1]

As implied by her clothing line, Bregman regularly does Yoga, pilates, cardio and hike'. Her favorite novel is ''The Red Tent'' by Anita Diamant. Some of her favorite films are: ''[[Terms of Endearment]]'', ''[[When Harry Met Sally]]'', Broadcast News - she has been quoted as saying that she &quot;likes to laugh and cry in the same movie!&quot; Television shows she has said to enjoy are: ''[[Inside the Actors Studio|The Actors Studio]] on [[Bravo!]]'', ''[[Gilmore Girls]]'', ''[[Sex and the City]]'', ''[[Secret Diary of a Call Girl]]'' and ''[[Modern Family]]''.
Bregman has two sons, Austin and Landon, who is a very talented actor as well. She also has two stepdaughters, Emily and Lindsay, from ex-husband Ron's previous marriage. She currently resides in Malibu, California.

She is good friends with her ''Y&amp;R'' co-stars [[Michelle Stafford]] and [[Christian LeBlanc]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbs.com/daytime/the_young_and_the_restless/interviews/interviews.php?sec=6 Interviews - The Young and the Restless&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Also, Bregman has launched her own jewellery line on [[The Canadian Shopping Channel]], called the Tracey Bregman Collection. It is only available in Canada.

In July, 2011 she appeared on [[HSN]] as a Spokesmodel for the [[Jabot Cosmetics|Jabot]] cosmetics line.

==Career==
Despite her recurring status as [[Lauren Fenmore|Lauren]] on ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'', she continues to be featured prominently in storylines, namely in the 2005-2006 storyline involving the return of her character's arch nemesis, [[Sheila Carter]] ([[Kimberlin Brown]]). Lauren has been married to lawyer Michael Baldwin, portrayed by [[Christian LeBlanc]], since December 9, 2005. Her previous marriages and relationships include detective Paul Williams, rock star Danny Romalatti, Dr. Scott Grainger, Brad Carlton, Ridge Forrester, and Eric Forrester. Lauren has one son, Scotty Grainger Jr., with Dr. Scott Grainger who is now deceased. Although Scotty was born on screen in 1992, when he reappeared in Genoa City in 2006, he was aged to be 24 years of age - a grad student currently working on his masters in Education. The aging of Scotty appeared to be quite unrealistic as the character of Lauren is only about 40 or so, which is likely why he left the canvas of Genoa City shortly after his return. Lauren recently gave birth to a second child, Fenmore Michael Baldwin (aka &quot;Fen&quot;). He too was kidnapped by Sheila in February 2007, but has since been returned to his parents safe and sound.

Lauren Fenmore's parents are Neil Fenmore, played by [[Jim Storm (actor)|Jim Storm]], and Joanna Manning, portrayed by [[Susan Seaforth Hayes]], best known for her role as Julie on ''[[Days of our Lives]]''. She is the [[CEO]] of her late father's international chain of department stores, &quot;Fenmore's&quot; which is largely how she acquired her wealth. For a complete history of her character, please see the character's [[Lauren Fenmore Baldwin|history page]].

In light of her character's newfound romance with [[Christian LeBlanc]]'s character Michael, Bregman's recognition has increased immensely due to the couple's popularity.

Prior to ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'', Bregman also appeared on the soap opera [[Days of our Lives]] between the years of 1978 - 1980, portraying troubled teen [[Donna Temple Craig]].

As of April 2010, Bregman took on the role of Sheila Carter's sister [[Sarah Smythe|Sarah]], who is in fact a double for her character Lauren.

She also appeared along side ''Y&amp;R'' co-star [[Christian LeBlanc]] in the video for ''[[I Keep On Loving You]]'' by [[Reba McEntire]] in 2010.

She was the first actress to be awarded the [[Daytime Emmy Award for Outstanding Younger Actress in a Drama Series]] (then known as the &quot;Outstanding Ingenue in a Drama Series&quot;) when it was introduced in 1985 and has been Nominated four times for the Daytime Emmy including 2006 and 2008 for Outstanding Supporting Actress.

==Selected filmography==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; sortable
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot;
! Show || Character || Duration
|-
| [[The Young and the Restless]] || [[Lauren Fenmore Baldwin]]&lt;br&gt;[[The Young and the Restless minor characters#Sarah Carter|Sarah Smythe]] || 1983–1994, 1995, 2000, 2001–present&lt;br&gt;April 2, 2010- May 4, 2010 
|-
| [[Sex &amp; Mrs. X]] || Katherine || 2000
|-
| [[The Bold and the Beautiful]] || [[Lauren Fenmore Baldwin|Lauren Fenmore]] || 1992, 1993, 1994, 1995–1999, 2002, 2004, 2007
|-
| [[The Love Boat]] || Trish Carruthers  || February 1982
|-
| [[Days of our Lives]] || Donna Temple Craig || 1978–1980
|-
| [[Happy Birthday to Me (film)|Happy Birthday to Me]] || Ann Thomerson || 1981
|}

==References==
{{No footnotes|date=March 2008}}
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{imdb name|id=0106844|name=Tracey E. Bregman}}
* [http://www.soapcentral.com/y&amp;r/theactors/bregman.php Tracey E. Bregman profile from Y&amp;R Online]
*[http://www.tv.com/tracey-e.-bregman/person/10385/summary.html?q=TRacey%20E.%20Bregman&amp;tag=search_results;title;0] at [[Tv.com]]

{{Daytime Emmy Award Outstanding Younger Actress 1985-1989}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Bregman, Tracey E.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =May 29, 1963
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Munich, Germany]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Bregman, Tracey E.}}
[[Category:1963 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Munich]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:American soap opera actors]]
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:Daytime Emmy Award winners]]

[[nl:Tracey E. Bregman]]
[[pl:Tracey E. Bregman]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
