<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="749853" ns="0" title="Fovea centralis"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Anatomy |
Name         = Fovea centralis |
Latin        = fovea centralis  |
GraySubject  = |
GrayPage     = |
Image        = Schematic diagram of the human eye en.svg |
Caption      = Schematic diagram of the [[human eye]], with the fovea at the bottom. It shows a horizontal section through the right eye |
Image2       = |hi!!!
Precursor    = |
System       = |
Artery       = |
Vein         = |
Nerve        = |
Lymph        = |
MeshName     = |
MeshNumber   = |
}}
The '''fovea centralis''', also generally known as the '''fovea''' (the term ''fovea'' comes from the Latin, meaning ''pit'' or ''pitfall''), is a part of the [[human eye|eye]], located in the center of the [[macula]] region of the [[retina]]. 
&lt;ref name=WebvisionRetina&gt;
{{cite web |url=http://webvision.med.utah.edu/sretina.html |title=Simple Anatomy of the Retina |work=Webvision |publisher = University of Utah |accessdate=2011-09-28 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=IOVSnomen&gt; - 
&quot;Relation Between Superficial Capillaries and Foveal Structures in the Human Retina&quot; - 
(with nomenclature of fovea terms), Masayuki Iwasaki and Hajime Inomara, - 
''Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science'' (journal), - 
volume 27, pages 1698-1705, 1986, IOVS.org, webpage: - 
[http://www.iovs.org/cgi/reprint/27/12/1698.pdf IOVS-fovea-capillaries]. - 
&lt;/ref&gt; The fovea is responsible for sharp central [[Visual perception|vision]] (also called [[foveal]] vision), which is necessary in humans for [[reading (activity)|reading]], watching [[television]] or movies, driving, and any activity where visual detail is of primary importance. The fovea is surrounded by the ''parafovea'' belt, and the ''perifovea'' outer region.&lt;ref name=IOVSnomen/&gt; The parafovea is the intermediate belt, where the [[ganglion]] cell layer is composed of more than five rows of cells, as well as the highest density of cones; the perifovea is the outermost region where the ganglion cell layer contains two to four rows of cells, and is where visual acuity is below the optimum. The perifovea contains an even more diminished density of cones, having 12 per 100 micrometres versus 50 per 100 micrometres in the most central fovea. This, in turn, is surrounded by a larger [[peripheral vision|peripheral]] area that delivers highly compressed information of low resolution. Approximately 50% of the nerve fibers in the [[optic nerve]] carry information from the fovea, while the other 50% carry information from the rest of the retina. The parafovea extends to a distance of 1¼ mm from the central fovea, and the perifovea is found 2¾ mm away from the fovea centralis.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;eye, human.&quot;Encyclopædia Britannica. 2008. [[Encyclopædia Britannica 2006 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]]&lt;/ref&gt; 


==Description==
In the human eye the term ''fovea'' (or ''fovea centralis'') denotes the pit in the [[retina]], which allows for maximum acuity of vision.

[[Image:AcuityHumanEye.svg|270px |thumb |left| The diagram shows the relative acuity of the left human eye (horizontal section) in degrees from the fovea.&lt;ref&gt;Hans-Werner Hunziker, (2006) Im Auge des Lesers: foveale und periphere Wahrnehmung - vom Buchstabieren zur Lesefreude  [ The function of the fovea is to catch detailed visual information 3 to 4 times per second at different parts of the [[visual field]]. The brain integrates this information within the framework of the condensed [[peripheral vision]] (extra-foveal information).
the eye of the reader: foveal and peripheral perception - from letter recognition to the joy of reading] Transmedia Stäubli Verlag Zürich 2006 ISBN 978-3-7266-0068-6&lt;/ref&gt; ]]

The human fovea has a diameter of about 1.0&amp;nbsp;mm with a high concentration of [[Cone cell|cone photoreceptor]]s. The center of the fovea is the foveola – about 0.2&amp;nbsp;mm in diameter – where only cone photoreceptors are present and there are virtually no [[rod cell|rods]].&lt;ref name=WebvisionRetina/&gt; The central fovea consists of very compact cones, thinner and more rod-like in appearance than cones elsewhere. Starting at the outskirts of the fovea, however, rods gradually appear, and the absolute density of cone receptors progressively decreases.

In the primate fovea (presumably including human) the ratio of [[ganglion cell]]s to [[Photoreceptor cell|photoreceptor]]s is about 2.5; almost every ganglion cell receives data from a single cone, and each cone feeds onto between 1 and 3 ganglion cells.&lt;ref&gt;Ahmad ''et al.'', 2003. Cell density ratios in a foveal patch in macaque retina. ''Vis. Neurosci.'' 20:189-209.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, the acuity of foveal vision is limited only by the density of the cone mosaic, and the fovea is the area of the eye with the highest sensitivity to fine details.&lt;ref&gt;Smithsonian/The National Academies, ''Light:Student Guide and Source Book.'' [[Carolina Biological Supply Company]], 2002. ISBN 0-89278-892-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

Compared to the rest of the [[retina]], the cones in the foveal pit have a smaller diameter and can, therefore, be more densely packed (in a [[hexagon]]al pattern). The high spatial density of cones accounts for the high visual acuity capability at the fovea. This is enhanced by the local absence of retinal blood vessels from the fovea, which, if present, would interfere with the passage of [[light]] striking the foveal cone mosaic. The absence of inner retinal cells from the foveae of primates is assumed to contribute further to the high acuity function of the fovea.

The fovea centralis is a central pit, near the optic axis. It eliminates the necessity to pass through the inner, non-sensitive neurons and allows direct passage to the receptors. It is employed for accurate vision in the direction where it is pointed. If an object is large and thus covering a large angle, the eyes must constantly shift their gaze to subsequently bring different portions of the image into the fovea (as in reading).

Since the macula does not have a [[blood supply]], the fovea must receive [[oxygen]] from the vessels in the [[choroid]], which is across the [[retinal pigment epithelium]] and [[Bruch's membrane]].  This blood supply alone does not satisfy the metabolic needs of the fovea under conditions of bright light, and the fovea, thus, exists in a state of [[Hypoxia (medical)|hypoxia]] when under bright illumination.

Since cones contain the pigmented [[opsin]]s that allow humans to discriminate color, the fovea is largely responsible for the [[color vision]] in [[humans]], which is superior to that of most other [[mammal]]s{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}.

The fovea comprises less than 1% of retinal size but takes up over 50% of the [[visual cortex]] in the brain.
&lt;ref&gt;
     &quot;The Stimulus and Anatomy of the Visual System&quot; (with fovea description),
     Hanover College, Psychology Department,
     [http://72.14.209.104/search?q=cache:lKxaO6dAKrsJ:psych.hanover.edu/classes/sensation/chapters/Chapter%25203.doc HanoverCollege-Fovea-PDF-as-HTML].
&lt;/ref&gt; The foveal pit is not located exactly on the [[optical axis]], but is displaced about 4 to 8 degrees temporal to it. The fovea sees only the central two degrees of the visual field, which is roughly equivalent to twice the width of your thumbnail at arm's length.&lt;ref&gt;
     Fairchild, Mark. (1998), ''Color Appearance Models''. Reading, Mass.: Addison, Wesley, &amp; Longman, p.7. ISBN 0-201-63464-3
&lt;/ref&gt;

Surrounding the foveal pit is the foveal rim, where the neurons displaced from the pit are located. This is the thickest part of the retina.

Since the fovea does not have rods, it is not sensitive to dim lights. [[Astronomer]]s know this; in order to observe a dim star, they use [[averted vision]], looking out of &quot;the side of their eyes&quot;.

The fovea is covered in a yellow pigment called [[xanthophyll]],&lt;ref name=WebvisionRetina/&gt; with the [[carotenoid]]s [[zeaxanthin]] and [[lutein]] (Balashov and Bernstein, 1998{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}), present in the cone [[axon]]s of the Henle fibre layer.&lt;ref name=WebvisionRetina/&gt;  The pigment area absorbs blue light and is probably an [[evolution]]ary adaptation to the problem of [[chromatic aberration]].

The fovea is also a pit in the surface of the retinas of many types of fish, reptiles, and birds. Among mammals, it is found only in [[simian]] [[primates]]. The retinal fovea takes slightly different forms in different types of animals. For example, in primates, cone photoreceptors line the base of the foveal pit, the cells that elsewhere in the retina form more superficial layers having been displaced away from the foveal region during late [[fetus|fetal]] and early [[postnatal]] life. Other foveae may show only a reduced thickness in the inner cell layers, rather than an almost complete absence.

The only photo-receptors located in the fovea of most humans are three kinds of cone photo receptors. The red, blue, and green allow the eye to see the colours that humans need for survival; however, some organisms are known to possess four independent channels for conveying color information, or possessing four different types of cone cells in the eye, a characteristic called ''tetrachromacy''. Organisms with tetrachromacy are called [[tetrachromats]]. The rods are located on the fovea's periphery. This assists the eye in seeing in the dark.

==See also==

*[[Eye movement (sensory)|Eye movement]]
*[[Eye movement in language reading]]
*[[Eye movement in music reading]]
*[[Gaze-contingency paradigm]]
*[[Macular degeneration]]
*[[Foveated imaging]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Eye}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fovea Centralis}}
[[Category:Eye anatomy]]

[[bn:ফোভিয়া]]
[[ca:Fòvea òptica]]
[[de:Fovea centralis]]
[[es:Fóvea]]
[[eo:Foveo]]
[[fr:Fovéa]]
[[ko:중심와]]
[[it:Fovea]]
[[he:רשתית#מבנה רשתית האדם]]
[[nl:Fovea centralis]]
[[ja:中心窩]]
[[no:Fovea centralis]]
[[pl:Dołek środkowy siatkówki oka]]
[[pt:Fóvea]]
[[ru:Центральная ямка]]
[[sk:Fovea]]
[[sv:Fovea]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
