<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="753577" ns="0" title="Fitchburg State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">:''This article is for the state college in Fitchburg, Massachusetts. For other uses see [[FSC (disambiguation)]]''

{{Infobox university
|name            =Fitchburg State University
|native_name     =
|latin_name      =
|image_name      =Fitchburg State College Seal.jpg
|image_size      =100px
|motto           =Perseverantia
|established     =1894
|type            =[[Public university|Public]]
|endowment       =$7.0 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff           =
|faculty         =171 full-time
|president       =Robert V. Antonucci
|principal       =
|rector          =
|chancellor      =
|vice_chancellor =
|dean            =
|head_label      =
|head            =
|students        = 5,201
|undergrad       = 3,522
|postgrad        = 1,679
|doctoral        =
|city            ={{flagicon|USA}}[[Fitchburg, Massachusetts|Fitchburg]]
|state           =[[Massachusetts|MA]]
|country         =[[United States|USA]]
|coor            ={{Coord|42.588858|-71.789167|display=inline,title}}
|campus          =[[Urban area|Urban]], 31.4 acres (0.13 km²) &lt;small&gt;main campus&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;226.2 acres (0.92km²) &lt;small&gt;total&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/facilities/mainpages/interestingfacts.cfm Facilities - Interesting Facts&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|free_label      =
|free            =
|colors          =[[Green]] {{color box|green}} and [[Gold]] {{color box|gold}}
|colours         =
|mascot          =[[Falcon]]
|nickname        =The Burg
|affiliations    =[[NCAA Division III]], [[New England Football Conference]]
|website         =http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/
|logo            =[[File:Fitchburg State 2 line logo.png|200px]]
|publictransit   =[[Montachusett Regional Transit Authority]], [[Wallace Civic Center]]
}}

'''Fitchburg State University''', also known as '''Fitchburg State''', is a four-year public institution of higher learning with a compact urban campus, located in the city of [[Fitchburg, Massachusetts]].  Fitchburg State University has over 3,500 undergraduate and over 1650 graduate/continuing education students, for a total student body enrollment over 5200. The College offers [[Postgraduate certificate]]s, [[Bachelor's degree]]s, [[Master's degree]]s, and [[Master of Business Administration|MBA]]s in more than 25 academic disciplines. The main campus, the McKay Campus School, and athletic fields comprise 79 acres (320,000 m²) in the city of Fitchburg; the biological study fields comprise 120 acres (490,000 m²) in the neighboring towns of [[Lancaster, Massachusetts|Lancaster]], [[Leominster, Massachusetts|Leominster]], and [[Lunenburg, Massachusetts|Lunenburg]].

==History==
[[Image:State Normal School, Fitchburg, MA.jpg|thumb|The State Normal School in Fitchburg]]Fitchburg State University was founded as the '''State Normal School in Fitchburg''' in 1894 by the [[Massachusetts General Court|state legislature]]. Its first President was John G. Thompson (President 1895–1920). Initially a secondary education school for women (coeducation arrived in 1911), the Normal School was not authorized to grant Bachelor degrees until 1930, after the presidency of William D. Parkinson (1920–1927), and during Dr. Charles M. Herlihy's (1927–1945) tenure. In 1932, that authorization was extended to all academic disciplines in Education. At the same time, the name was changed to '''State Teachers College at Fitchburg'''. Dr. Charles M. Herlihy's died while in office and was followed by Dr. William J. Sanders (1945–1950) and  Ellis F. White (1950–1953).

During Ralph H. Weston's (1953–1963) presidency of the college, the Education program was the primary focus. That changed in 1960, when the school changed its name to '''State College at Fitchburg''' and added degree programs outside of Education. In 1965, the College's name evolved into '''Fitchburg State College'''. James J. Hammond (1963–1975) and Dr. Vincent J. Mara (1975–2003) were the next two presidents of the school and added many buildings to the campus, most notably what are now called the Hammond Building and Mara Village. More recently, a new west wing was added to the Mara compound.

In the past five years, since Robert V. Antonucci (2003–present) became president, the college has focused on enhancing its buildings and grounds as well as its programs. The school has focused on renovations and rehabilitation of underused buildings and areas as opposed to extensive building, even though there has been some. One notable building is the {{convert|3500|sqft|m2|adj=on}} campus police station (2008).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fitchburgpride.com/news/2008/0829/front_page/002.html&lt;/ref&gt; A new science building and renovation of the Condike Science building is in the works with construction slated to begin in 2011.

Continuing Education at Fitchburg State University began in 1915, with the first summer courses offered through the College. Twenty years later, its first graduate programs were established.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/aboutus/history/ Fitchburg State College - History of the College&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2010, the Massachusetts House of Representatives and Senate voted to grant Fitchburg state university status and change its name to '''Fitchburg State University'''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mass.gov/legis/186history/h04864.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The measure was signed into law by Massachusetts Governor Deval Patrick on July 28, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.fsc.edu/fscnews/index.cfm?detail=818&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.salemstate.edu/about/10414.php&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
The college originally housed students in buildings that are now surrounding the alumni quad.

===Campus Buildings===

* The '''Hammond Campus Center''' contains the Amelia V. Gallucci-Cirio Library, the main campus center, the Game Room, the Underground, the Follet Bookstore, and the Hammond Eatery. The third floor houses the student services center which includes the tutor center, math center, writing center, disability services, and counseling services, among others.

The Amelia V. Gallucci-Cirio Library is the main library on campus with over 1 million books, rolls of [[microfiche]], journals, and periodicals, on four floors. It has an extensive collection of children's and young adults books. The Library holds many special collections from notable alumni, faculty, and local residents.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/library/archives/index.cfm Amelia V. Gallucci-Cirio Library: Archives &amp; Special Collections]&lt;/ref&gt; These special collections include works from [[Robert Cormier]], well-known author for young adults, and [[R. A. Salvatore]], a prolific fantasy writer, well-known for his ''[[Forgotten Realms]]'' novels and ''[[The DemonWars Saga]]''. There are works by Richard Kent, former music teacher for whom Kent Recital Hall was named, Ernst Fandreyer's translation of Gauss' proof, works by William Wolkovich-Valkavicius, as well as papers by John Ellis Van Courtland Moon, former professor of history.

* '''Thompson Hall''', built in 1896, was the college's original building. It is now primarily a classroom building. It is home to the Nursing Department and its laboratories, including a 10-bed mock hospital which is fully equipped to be used in case of an emergency on campus. When the Hammond Campus Center was built, a tunnel that ran to the former Palmer House dormitory was made into a thoroughfare between the second level of the new building and the basement of Thompson Hall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/facilities/thompson/thompfloorb.cfm Capital Planning &amp; Maintenance - Thompson Hall - Basement Floor Plan]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Percival Hall.JPG|thumb|left|Percival Hall]]

* '''Edgerly Hall''' was first used as “an eighth-grade model and practice school,” which made it one of the first [[junior high schools]] in America. It is now home to the [[Computer Science]] and [[Mathematics]] departments, plus computer labs and classrooms.

* '''Percival Hall''' is directly across the Quad from Edgerly and is the home of the Behavioral Science department, including [[Psychology]], [[Sociology]], and [[Criminal Justice]]  It also houses Percival Auditorium, which seats 400, and classrooms.

* '''Miller Hall''' sits near Percival Hall and Thompson Hall, and houses offices for the [[English language|English]] and [[History]] departments.

* The '''Anthony Building''' is the student service center on campus, hosting offices for Admissions, Financial Aid, Student Accounts, Graduate and Continuing Education, Registrar, and the OneCard office. 

* The '''Dupont Facilities Building''' houses the schools maintenance department.

* The '''Condike Science Building''' houses science classrooms, laboratories and departmental offices, as well as a 135-seat lecture hall.  

* The '''Conlon Arts Building''' is actually two buildings connected by an enclosed walkway. One building is home to the large [[Communication studies|communications]]/media and [[industrial arts|industrial technology]] departments and home to the school's [[Information Technology]] office. This section of the building includes large video and film production resources, a large photography and graphic arts department, and metal, wood, and theatrical scene shops. The other part contains a 280-seat lecture hall, the offices of the fine arts faculty, as well as art/music studios and classrooms.
[[Image:Fitchburg State College Hammond Building.JPG|thumb|The Hammond Campus Center, with Thompson Hall to the left.]]

===Residence halls===
The campus has six residence halls, three of which have rooms in suites, two are designated as apartment-style living, and one has a normal dormitory layout.&lt;ref&gt;[http://virtualtour.fsc.edu Tour]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/campusliving/ Fitchburg State College - Housing and Residential Services]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Fitchburg State Townhouses.JPG|thumb|left|The Townhouse Apartments]]

Aubuchon Hall, Mara Village, and Russell Towers are the three suite halls. Each suite has a common living room area, four to six rooms, and a bathroom. Aubuchon Hall and Mara Village have &quot;locked off&quot; suites: A key is needed to get into the suites.  Aubuchon is home to the office of Housing and Residential Services, which is located on the first floor. Russell is home to the Student Health Service, which provides students with two nurse practitioners and a physician during the week.  Recently, the Campus Mail Center moved to the bottom floor of the Mara Village Commons Building located within the Mara complex.

There are two apartment-style residence halls on campus: the Townhouse Apartments and the North Street Apartments. Because of their layout, both of these halls are usually reserved for upperclassmen. Each one of the 33 Townhouses is equipped with a combination living room/kitchen area, one-and-a-half baths, and individual bedrooms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/campusliving/housingcost.html Housing and Residential Services - Housing Process - Housing Costs&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The North Street Apartment building was acquired in the summer of 2007 and consists of six apartments. Each apartment has a living room area, bathroom, and kitchen.

Herlihy Hall is the smallest, and oldest, of the college's current residence halls but has the largest rooms. It houses 150 students in a normal dormitory style (one long corridor with rooms off it), and has the luxury of being connected to the dining commons.
[[File:Russell Towers.JPG|thumb|Russell Towers]]

Mara Village was recently expanded and opened for the fall 2009 semester. The $12 million expansion added 125 beds and allows 50% of the undergraduate population to live on campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fsc-alumni.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=234&amp;Itemid=99999999&lt;/ref&gt;

The campus has also adopted Cedar Street Home as a residence hall. Previously, this building from 1900 was a nursing home. The university bought it in 2005 and currently rents the single rooms to girls from sororities.

===Dining facilities===
Holmes Dining Commons, often referred to as &quot;Daka,&quot; is the main dining facility on campus. It spans North Street, the main road through campus, and lets foot traffic easily move from one side of the street. It is run by the [[foodservice]] Chartwells and is [[buffet]] style. In the summer of 2006, it had a $4 million renovation.

===Transportation===
Transportation around Fitchburg State University's campus is usually accomplished through walking. Also, there is a shuttle bus that goes from the [[Wallace Civic Center]], through campus, and then to the [[MBTA Commuter Rail]] stop. The loop takes about 15 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/campuspolice/shuttlebus.html Campus Police - Shuttle Bus Service]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[MBTA Commuter Rail]] stop closest to the college is the [[Fitchburg (MBTA station)|Fitchburg]] stop on the [[Fitchburg Line]]. The line ends at [[North Station]] and is about an hour and a half ride. It is [[wheelchair accessible]] and a short walk from campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mbta.com/schedules_and_maps/rail/lines/?route=FITCHBRG MBTA schedule]&lt;/ref&gt;

A new addition to transportation on and off campus is the collaboration between the school and the [[Montachusett Regional Transit Authority]] (MART). Faculty, staff and students can ride any of the bus routes in Fitchburg or [[Leominster, Massachusetts|Leominster]] free of charge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.fsc.edu/fscnews/index.cfm?detail=488 Fitchburg State College - Public Relations - News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[File:Fitchburg State College Entrance.JPG|thumb|Fitchburg State College Entrance]]
Fitchburg State employs the [[Carnegie rule]].  This translates to the requirement that a student take at least 4 classes per semester to be considered a full-time student.  In most cases, 5 classes per semester are required for a student to complete their major within 4 years.

The most competitive majors at Fitchburg State are [[Nursing]], [[Communication studies|Communications Media]] (including Film and Video Production), [[Education]], [[Business Administration]], and [[Industrial Technology]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/enrollsrv/topten.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; The Industrial Technology department, along with the [[English studies|English]] department, have hosted the [[Kennedy Center American College Theater Festival]] Region 1 festival from 2006 to 2009.

===Majors and Concentrations===
Fitchburg State University offers 56 undergraduate majors and concentrations in the departments of Biology, Business Administration, Communication Studies, Computer Science, Criminal Justice, Early Childhood Education, Earth Science, Economics, Elementary Education, English, Exercise &amp; Sport Science, Geography, History, Human Services, Industrial Technology, Interdisciplinary Studies, Mathematics, Middle School Education, Nursing, Political Science, Psychology, Secondary Education, Sociology, Special Education, Technology Education, and Pre-Professional Programs.

===Rankings and Accreditations===
Fitchburg State University is accredited by the [[New England Association of Schools and Colleges]], the [[Commission on Collegiate Nursing Education]], the International Assembly for Collegiate Business Education, the Council for Standards in Human Service Education, and the National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education.

Individual programs have been accredited by the Massachusetts Department of Education, the National Association of State Directors of Teacher Education and Certification, the Interstate Certification Compact of Educational Personnel, the State Board of Registration in Nursing, the Board of Higher Education, and the Commonwealth Honors Program.&lt;ref&gt;2007 Fitchburg State College Viewbook, page 22&lt;/ref&gt;

[[U.S. News and World Report]] ranked Fitchburg State College as a Universities–Master's (North) school, third tier (highest ranked [[Template:Massachusetts Public Colleges|Massachusetts State College]]) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_2184_brief.php USNews.com: America's Best Colleges 2008: Fitchburg State College: At a glance&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
===College Teams===
[[Image:Fscfalcon.jpg|right|100px]]
University is currently ranked as an [[NCAA Division III]] college. It offers men's [[Baseball]], [[Basketball]], [[Soccer]], [[American football|Football]], and [[ice hockey]]. Women's sports offered are [[Basketball]], [[Soccer]], [[Softball]], [[Field Hockey]], and [[Lacrosse]]. [[Cross country running|Cross Country]] and [[Track &amp; Field]] are offered for both men and women.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fscfalcons.com/landing/index&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intramural Sports===
Fitchburg State University also offers a selection of [[intramural sports]] each semester. These sports are only students on campus versus other students on campus. The chosen sports can differ from year to year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/intramural/ Fitchburg State College - Intramural Sports]&lt;/ref&gt; In the past, they have included, [[Basketball]], [[Dodgeball]], [[Flag Football]], [[Road hockey|Floor Hockey]], [[Kickball]], [[Soccer]] (indoor and outdoor), [[Softball]], [[swimming (sport)|Swimming]], [[Ultimate Frisbee]], and [[Volleyball]].

==Student activities==
===Organizations===
Fitchburg State University recognizes over 60 student clubs and organizations, including the student-run newspaper, The Point,&lt;ref&gt;http://falcon.fsc.edu/thepoint/&lt;/ref&gt; and the student-run radio station, WXPL (91.3 FM).&lt;ref&gt;http://falcon.fsc.edu/~wxpl/&lt;/ref&gt; Currently the [[Dance]] club  is the largest club on campus. Other organizations include the [[Anime]] Club, [[Biology]] Club, [[English studies|English]] Club, Falcon Players ([[Drama]] Club), FSC [[Habitat for Humanity]], FSC EMS ([[Rescue Squad]]),&lt;ref&gt;http://falcon.fsc.edu/rescuesquad/&lt;/ref&gt; GEO Club, [[Math]] Club, [[MASSPIRG]] at FSC, Fitchburg Activities Board (FAB), [[Martial Arts]] Club, Nursing Student Association (NSA), [[Pi Mu Epsilon]] [[Mathematics]] Honor Society, [[Psychology]] Club, [[Student Government Association]] (SGA), Filmmaker's Society, Model United Nations Team, and the Table Top Gaming Club and the Fitchburg State University Business Society.

===Greek life===
FSU is home to two fraternities and three sororities. Approximately 4-5% of undergraduate students are affiliated with fraternities and sororities recognized by the College. The recognized fraternities on campus are [[Sigma Pi]] and [[Sigma Tau Gamma]], while the recognized sororities are [[Phi Sigma Sigma]], [[Sigma Sigma Sigma]], and [[Alpha Sigma Tau]].

==Notable alumni==
* [[Robert Cormier]], author
* [[Paul Coyne]], TV producer/editor
* [[Jonathan Egstad]], special effects creator
* [[Jennifer Flanagan|Jennifer L. Flanagan]], member of the [[Massachusetts House of Representatives|Mass. House of Representatives]]
* [[Joe Gurney]], professional hockey player
* [[Bert Jacobs]], co-founder of [[Life is Good]]
* [[Patrick O'Brien Demsey]], actor
* [[Peter H. Reynolds]], author and illustrator
* [[R. A. Salvatore]], fantasy writer
.

==See also==
* [[Wallace Civic Center]]
* [[Montachusett Regional Transit Authority]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/ FSC Homepage]
* [http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/gce/ Graduate and Continuing Education at Fitchburg State College]
* [http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/publicrel/fsctoday/ Fitchburg State Today newsletter]
* [http://www.virtualtour.fsc.edu FSC Virtual Tour]
* [http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/library/archives/index.cfm Amelia V. Gallucci-Cirio Library: Archives &amp; Special Collections]
* [http://www.fitchburgstate.edu/cultural/ CenterStage at Fitchburg State College]

{{Little East Conference navbox}}
{{New England Football Conference}}
{{Massachusetts Higher Education}}

[[Category:Public universities and colleges in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1894]]
[[Category:Film schools in the United States]]
[[Category:Massachusetts film and television]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Worcester County, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Fitchburg, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Fitchburg State University]]

[[pnb:فچبرگ سٹیٹ یونیورسٹی]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
