<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="75458" ns="0" title="Windows Me"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS version
|name=Windows Me
|family=Microsoft Windows
|logo=Microsoft Windows Millenium Edition Logo.svg
|screenshot=WindowsME.png &lt;!-- Warning: Do ''not'' change the screenshot unless there is BIG change in the UI. When taking screenshot, please resize your window (e.g. 640*480), disable your extensions and use the default theme. --&gt;
|caption=Screenshot of Windows Me
|developer=[[Microsoft]]
|source_model=[[Closed source]]
|license=Microsoft [[End User License Agreement|EULA]]
|kernel_type=[[Monolithic kernel]]
|preceded_by=[[Windows 98]]
|succeeded_by=[[Windows XP]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|title=A+ Certification Study Guide|author=Michael Pastore|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=FdjlYvbxnlsC&amp;pg=PA315&amp;dq=difference+between+windows+me+and+2000&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=kHWoTcenI5D0tgObt6j6DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CF4Q6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=difference%20between%20windows%20me%20and%202000&amp;f=false|year=2003|isbn=978-0072227666|publisher=McGraw-Hill|pages=315|edition=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|release_version=4.9 (Build 3000)
|first_release_date=September 14, 2000
|first_release_url=http://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/press/2000/sept00/availabilitypr.mspx
|release_date={{Start date and age|2000|9|14}}
|release_url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/features/2000/sept00/09-14winme.mspx
|support_status=Unsupported as of 11 July 2006&lt;ref name=supportend&gt;{{cite web|url= http://support.microsoft.com/gp/lifean18|title=Windows 98, Windows 98 SE, and Windows Me Support ends on 11 July 2006|accessdate=2006-06-10|publisher=Microsoft}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=January 2009 &lt;!-- approximate date of template insertion for dating hidden maintenance categories --&gt;
}}

'''Windows Millennium Edition''', or '''Windows Me''' (pronounced as an abbreviation, &quot;M-E&quot;), is a graphical [[operating system]] released on September 14, 2000 by [[Microsoft]],&lt;ref name=presspass&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/press/2000/sept00/availabilitypr.mspx|title=Microsoft Announces Immediate Availability Of Windows Millennium Edition (Windows Me)|date=2000-09-14|work=Microsoft PressPass - Information for Journalists|accessdate= 2008-08-02|publisher=[[Microsoft]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was the last operating system released in the [[Windows 9x]] series. Support for Windows Me ended on July 11, 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;supportend&quot; /&gt;

Windows Me was the successor to [[Windows 98]] and, like Windows 98, was targeted specifically at home PC users.&lt;ref name=presspass/&gt; It included [[Internet Explorer 5.5]], [[Windows Media Player]] 7, and the new [[Windows Movie Maker]] software, which provided basic video editing and was designed to be easy to use for home users. Microsoft also updated the graphical user interface, [[Windows Shell|shell]] features, and [[Windows Explorer]] in Windows Me with some of those first introduced in [[Windows 2000]], which had been released as a business-oriented operating system seven months earlier. Windows Me could be upgraded to [[Internet Explorer 6]] SP1 (but not to SP2 (SV1) or [[Internet Explorer 7]]), [[Outlook Express]] 6 SP1 and Windows Media Player 9 Series. Microsoft [[.NET Framework]] up to and including version 2.0 is supported, however versions 2.0 SP1, 3.x, and greater are not. Office XP was the last version of Microsoft Office to be compatible with Windows Me.

Windows Me is a continuation of the Windows 9x model, but with restricted access to [[real mode]] [[MS-DOS]] in order to speed up system [[Booting|boot]] time.&lt;ref name=&quot;realmode&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://support.microsoft.com/kb/269524|title=Overview of Real Mode Removal from Windows Millennium Edition|publisher=Microsoft}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was one of the most unpopular changes in Windows Me, because applications that needed real mode DOS to run, such as older disk utilities, did not run under Windows Me (although the system could be booted into real mode DOS using a bootable Windows Me floppy disk).

Compared with other releases of Windows, Windows Me had a short shelf-life of just over a year; it was soon replaced by the [[Windows NT]]-based [[Windows XP]], which was launched on October 25, 2001.

==History==
In 1998, Microsoft stated that there would be no version of [[Windows 9x]] after [[Windows 98]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winsupersite.com/reviews/win2k_gold.asp|title=Paul Thurrot's SuperSite for Windows: The Road to Gold: The development of Windows 2000 Review|author=Paul Thurrot|date=15 December 1999|publisher=SuperSite for Windows|accessdate=2007-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1999, however, Microsoft released Windows 98 Second Edition, and then announced a new version of [[Windows 9x]] which was later revealed to be codenamed Millennium. In 2000, this was released as Windows Millennium Edition (Windows Me).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.winsupersite.com/reviews/windowsme_gold.asp|title=Paul Thurrot's SuperSite for Windows: The Road to Gold: The development of Windows Me|author=Paul Thurrot|date=5 July 2000| publisher=SuperSite for Windows|accessdate=2007-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At least 3 betas of Windows Me were available during its development phase. On September 24, 1999, Microsoft announced that Windows Millennium Beta 1 was released.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winsupersite.com/reviews/windowsme_gold.asp |title=Paul Thurrott's SuperSite for Windows: The Road to Gold: The development of Windows Me |publisher=Winsupersite.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Windows Millennium Beta 2 was released on November 24, 1999, and added a couple of new features such as System File Protection and Game Options Control Panel. Several interim builds were released between Beta 1 and 2, and added features such as [[Windows Update|automatic updates]] and personalized menus. Beta 3 was released on April 11, 2000. The general availability date was December 31, 2000. Microsoft ended mainstream support for Windows Millennium Edition on December 31, 2003. Extended support ended on July 11, 2006. Windows 98 Extended support ended the same day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/lifecycle/?p1=6519 |title=Microsoft Support Lifecycle - Windows Millennium Edition |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Windows Me also contained the [[Microsoft Java Virtual Machine]], which caused it and Windows 98 to be pulled from the [[Microsoft Developer Network]] at the end of 2003.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Thurrot - [http://www.windowsitpro.com/Article/ArticleID/41086/41086.html Microsoft to Retire Windows 98, Others]. [[eWeek]], 8 December 2003&lt;/ref&gt; At launch time, Microsoft announced a time-limited promotion&lt;ref name=&quot;MePromoPrice&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/press/2000/jul00/promopricingpr.mspx |title=Microsoft Announces Promotional Pricing For Windows Millennium Edition Upgrade |publisher=Microsoft.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; from September 2000–January 2001 which entitled [[Windows 95]] or [[Windows 98]] users to upgrade to Windows Me for $59.95 instead of the regular retail upgrade price of $109.&lt;ref name=&quot;MePromoPrice&quot;/&gt;

Shortly after Windows Me was released, Microsoft launched a campaign-initiative to promote Windows Me in the U.S., which they dubbed the ''Meet Me Tour''. A national partnered promotional program featured Windows Me, [[Original equipment manufacturer#Computers|OEMs]] and other partners in an interactive multimedia attraction in 25 cities across the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windowsitpro.com/article/articleid/19449/microsoft-to-hit-the-road-with-meet-me-tour.html |title=Microsoft to hit the road with 'Meet Me' tour |publisher=Windowsitpro.com |date=2000-08-29 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==New and updated features==
[[Image:Winme gold 18.png|thumb|right|Windows Me [[Software_release_life_cycle#RTM|RTM CD]]]]

===User interface===
Windows Me featured the [[Windows Explorer#Windows Me and Windows 2000|shell enhancements]] inherited from [[Windows 2000]] such as personalized menus, customizable Windows Explorer toolbars, auto-complete in Windows Explorer address bar and Run box, Windows 2000 advanced file type association features, displaying comments in shortcuts as tooltips, extensible columns in Details view (IColumnProvider interface), icon overlays, integrated search pane in Windows Explorer, sort by name function for menus, ''Places bar'' in common dialogs for ''Open'' and ''Save'', cascading [[Start menu]] [[special folder]]s, some Plus! 95 and Plus! 98 themes, and updated graphics. The notification area in Windows Me and later supports [[HiColor#16-bit highcolor|16-bit high color]] icons. The Multimedia control panel has also been updated from Windows 98. ''Taskbar and Start Menu'' options allow disabling drag and drop and can prevent moving or resizing the taskbar.

===Hardware support improvements===
*'''Faster boot times''': Windows Me features numerous improvements for improving [[Cold boot#Hard reboot|cold boot]] time, pre and post-logon boot times and time required for resuming from hibernation.&lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/archive/fast-boot.mspx |title=Improving &quot;Cold Boot&quot; Time for System Manufacturers |publisher=Microsoft.com |date=2001-12-04 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Processing of real mode configuration files, Config.sys and Autoexec.bat is bypassed at startup and essential real mode drivers are moved to Io.sys. &lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;/&gt; The registry is loaded only once; only portions of the registry required for boot are loaded initially, and registry is split across three files instead of two for efficient loading &lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;/&gt;. Plug and Play device enumeration is more parallelized than Windows 98. &lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;/&gt; Boot time is not affected due to unavailability of a DHCP server or other network components. &lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;/&gt; There are also optimizations to prevent boot slowdown due to [[BIOS]] [[Power-on self-test|POST]] operations. &lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;/&gt;
*'''[[Windows Image Acquisition]]''': Windows Me introduced the Windows Image Acquisition [[Application programming interface|API]] for a standardized method of allowing Windows applications to transparently and more easily communicate with image acquisition devices, such as [[digital camera]]s and [[Image scanner|scanners]]. WIA intended to improve the configuration and the user interface for interacting with scanners and such devices, (which were previously supported by the [[TWAIN]] standard) and simplify writing device drivers for developers. WIA also includes support for USB still image capture device classes such as scanners and cameras through the [[Picture Transfer Protocol]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms630368(VS.85).aspx |title=Windows Image Acquisition (WIA) (Windows) |publisher=Msdn.microsoft.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Improved power management and suspend/resume operations''': The OEM version of Windows Me supports OS-controlled ACPI S4 sleep state &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.activewin.com/interviews/microsoft/7.shtml |title=Interview with Nicolas Coudière, Chief Product Manager: Microsoft Windows Millennium Edition (Me) |publisher=Activewin.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Hibernate (OS feature)|hibernation]]) and other power management features without manufacturer-supplied drivers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/archive/winpowmgmt.mspx#EUE |title=Windows Power Management |publisher=Microsoft.com |date=2001-12-04 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''USB and FireWire support improvements''': Windows Me is the only operating system in the Windows 9x series that includes generic drivers for [[USB mass storage device]]s&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/system/bus/USB/USBFAQ_intro.mspx#E2DAC Microsoft USB FAQ]{{dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and USB printers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/archive/usbprint.mspx#EXB |title=USB Printers - Architecture and Driver Support |publisher=Microsoft.com |date=2005-11-02 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Support for FireWire [[Serial Bus Protocol 2|SBP-2]] scanners and storage devices is also improved. &lt;ref&gt; [http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg454506#E3AAC IEEE1394 and the Windows platform] &lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Windows legacy audio components#Multimedia Extensions (MME)|waveOut]], [[DirectSound]], and [[DirectShow]] APIs support non-[[Pulse Code Modulation|PCM]] formats such as [[AC-3]] or [[Windows Media Audio|WMA]] over [[S/PDIF]]. &lt;ref&gt; [http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463249 Non-PCM Wave Formats and WDM Audio Drivers] &lt;/ref&gt;

===Digital media===
*'''[[Windows Movie Maker]]''': This utility is based on [[DirectShow]] and [[Windows Media]] technologies to provide Microsoft Windows computer systems with basic video capture and edit capabilities. It provides users with the ability to capture, edit, and re-encode media content into the [[Windows Media]] format, a tightly compressed format which requires a minimal amount of storage space on the computer's hard disk, when compared to many other media formats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/expertzone/communities/movie.mspx |title=Microsoft Windows Movie Maker Community |publisher=Microsoft.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Windows Media Player|Windows Media Player 7]]''' offers many new features and capabilities compared to previous versions, including the WindowsMedia.com guide and radio tuner which are an integral part of the player, as well as integrated jukebox and player capabilities, and interactive skins to allow consumers to personalize the look, feel, and operation of the player by changing the user interface.
*'''[[Windows DVD Player]]''': Microsoft has included a redesigned version of their [[DVD player]] in Windows Me. Unlike the Windows 98 version, the new Windows Me version supports software decoding for playback of DVD movies without a dedicated decoder card.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/272985 |title=Description of DVD Player in Windows Millennium Edition |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date=2007-01-29 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Image Preview''': In Windows Me, images can be viewed by using the Image Preview utility. It allows users to rotate an image, print or zoom in/out an image. Image Preview supports images with .&lt;tt&gt;BMP&lt;/tt&gt;, .&lt;tt&gt;DIB&lt;tt&gt;, .&lt;tt&gt;EMF&lt;tt&gt;, .&lt;tt&gt;GIF&lt;tt&gt;, .&lt;tt&gt;JPEG&lt;tt&gt;, .&lt;tt&gt;PNG&lt;tt&gt;, .&lt;tt&gt;TIF&lt;tt&gt; and .&lt;tt&gt;WMF&lt;tt&gt; file formats. The ''My Pictures'' folder also integrates previewing images.
*'''Games''': Windows Me includes version 7.1 of the [[DirectX]] API which introduced [[DirectPlay#DirectPlay Voice|DirectPlay Voice]], and also offers several new games: Internet Backgammon, Internet Checkers, Internet Hearts, Internet Reversi, Internet Spades. It also includes [[Spider Solitaire (Windows)|Spider Solitaire]] from Plus! 98 and [[Full Tilt! Pinball|Pinball]] from Plus! for Windows 95. The final version of DirectX available for Windows Me is DirectX 9.0c, which was released on 7 April 2006.

===Networking technologies===
*'''Net Crawler''': Windows Me introduced a net crawling feature &lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/276322 How to Disable Net Crawl Functionality]&lt;/ref&gt; which automatically searches out and creates shortcuts to network shares and printers in ''My Network Places''. This can be controlled using the ''Automatically search for network folders and printers'' option. Shortcuts that are added by the net crawler but not detected again on the network in a reasonable time period are aged out and deleted.
*'''New [[TCP/IP]] Stack''': Windows Me includes the [[Windows 2000]] networking stack and architecture&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/technet/archive/WinMe/maintain/netcomp.mspx?mfr=true |title=Windows Me Networking features |publisher=Microsoft.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was known to be more reliable, full-featured, stable and offered better performance. Support for networking over [[FireWire]], improved [[Infrared Data Association|infrared]] support, a network diagnostic troubleshooter and a new Home Networking wizard are also included.
*The '''Home Networking Wizard''' is designed to help users to set up a computer that is running Windows Me for use on a small [[home network]]. This includes setting up [[Internet Connection Sharing]] (ICS) on a computer running Windows Me so the computer can share a connection to the Internet with other computers on the home network.
*'''[[Dial-up|Dial-up Networking]]''' component was updated in Windows Me, and provides several enhancements while maintaining the desired features of prior releases of the operating system. The user interface had been reworked to provide all configurable parameters in one convenient location. The user interface now included three new tabs: ''Networking'', ''Security'' and ''Dialing''. To improve dial-up networking, Windows Me includes built-in support for the Connection Manager dial-up client. Using the Connection Manager Administration Kit (an optional networking component in Windows 2000 Server), network administrators can pre-configure and deploy dial-up networking connections, by means of a Connection Manager service profile, to Windows Me–based client machines.
*'''[[Network Driver Interface Specification]] (NDIS)''' NDIS version 5.0 for Windows Me was enhanced to provide programming interface parity with NDIS version 5.0 in Windows 2000. This means that the programming interfaces that the author of a network device driver uses are the same for both of these Windows platforms.
*'''[[Universal Plug and Play]]''': Windows Me introduced support for Universal Plug and Play (UPnP). Universal Plug and Play and NAT traversal APIs can also be installed on [[Windows 98]] by installing the Windows XP Network Setup Wizard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa939488(WinEmbedded.5).aspx |title=Network Setup Wizard Down Level Setup |publisher=Msdn.microsoft.com |date=2006-10-18 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===System utilities===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2010}}

*'''[[System Restore]]''': Windows Me introduced the &quot;System Restore&quot; logging and reversion system, which was meant to simplify troubleshooting and solve problems. It was intended to work as a rollback and recovery feature so that if the installation of an application or a driver adversely affected the system, the user could undo the installation and return the system to a previously working state. It does this by monitoring changes to Windows system files and the [[Windows registry|registry]]. System Restore protects only the operating system files, not documents, and therefore is not a substitute for a backup program.  The System Restore feature sometimes ended up restoring [[malware]] which the user had previously removed, since its method of keeping track of changes is fairly simplistic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://antivirus.about.com/od/windowsbasics/a/systemrestore.htm|title=Disabling System Restore to Remove Viruses|author=Mary Landesman|publisher=About.com|accessdate=2007-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; By disabling System Restore, the malware could be removed, but the user lost all saved restore points.  System Restore also suffered from a bug in the date-stamping functionality that may cause System Restore to date-stamp snapshots that are taken after 8 September 2001 incorrectly. This can prevent System Restore from locating these snapshots and can cause the system restore process to fail. Microsoft released an update to fix this problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/?kbid=290700 |title=Checkpoints that you create after 8 September 2001 do not restore your computer |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date=2007-10-26 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''[[System File Protection]]''': First introduced with [[Windows 2000]] (as [[Windows File Protection]]), and expanding on the capabilities introduced with [[System File Checker]] in Windows 98, [[System File Protection]] aimed to protect system files from modification and corruption silently and automatically. When the file protection is in effect, replacing or deleting a system file causes Windows Me immediately and silently to restore the original copy. The original is taken from a hard drive backup folder (&lt;tt&gt;%WinDir%\Options\Install&lt;/tt&gt;) or from the Windows Me installation CD, if the cached copy of files on the hard disk has been deleted. If no installation CD is in the drive, a dialog box alerts the user about the problem and requests that the CD be inserted. [[System File Protection]] is a different technology from [[System Restore]] and should not be confused with the latter. [[System Restore]] maintains a broad set of changed files including added applications and user configuration data stored repeatedly at specific points in time restored by the user, whereas [[System File Protection]] protects operating system files with no user input.
*'''[[MSConfig|System Configuration Utility]]''' allows users to manually extract and restore individual system files from the Windows Me setup files. It has also been updated with three new tabs called &quot;Static VxDs&quot;, &quot;Environment&quot; and &quot;International&quot;. The ''Static VxDs'' tab allows users to enable or disable static [[VxD|virtual device drivers]] to be loaded at startup, the ''Environment'' tab allows users to enable or disable [[environment variable]]s, and the ''International'' tab allows users to set international language keyboard layout settings that were formerly set via the real mode MS-DOS configuration files. A ''Cleanup'' button on the ''Startup'' tab allows cleaning up invalid or deleted startup entries.
*'''[[System Monitor]]''' has been updated with a Dial-Up Adapter section. Users can now monitor items such as Connection Speeds, Bytes Received or Transmitted / Second.
*'''[[SCANDISK]]''' runs from within Windows upon an improper shutdown before the [[Windows Shell]] loads.
*'''[[Automatic Updates]]''': The Automatic Updates utility automatically downloads and installs critical updates from the [[Windows Update]] Web site with little user interaction. It is set up to check Windows Update once every 24 hours by default. Users can choose to download which update they want, although high-priority updates must be downloaded and installed.
[[Image:WindowsMEbOXcovershot.png|thumb|right|Windows Me operating system box cover shot]]
*'''Compressed Folders''': Windows Me includes support for [[ZIP (file format)|ZIP]] files through a shell extension known as Compressed Folders. Originally introduced in the [[Microsoft Plus!|Plus! 98]] pack for Windows 98, this feature allows users to create, access and extract files from ZIP archives similar to a regular folder in Windows. The user can also restrict access to files with a password.
*A new '''Help and Support''' program has also been added, replacing the [[HTML Help]]-based documentation in Windows 2000 and Windows 98. The Help and Support Center is entirely HTML-based and takes advantage of a technology called Support Automation Framework (SAF), that can show support information from the internet, allows collecting data for troubleshooting via WMI and scripting and for third parties to plug into Windows Help and Support.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/winme/bulk/oem/health/Support_Automation_Framework_56k/MS_Studio_PCHFest_Support_Automation_Framework.ppt Support Automation Framework]{{dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several other support tools also shipped with Windows Me.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=/servicedesks/webcasts/en/wc020101/wct020101.asp&amp;sd=dell |title=Windows Millennium Edition support tools webcast |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Windows Me also includes Internet Explorer 5.5 which supports a new Print Preview feature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winsupersite.com/reviews/millennium_b3.asp |title=Paul Thurrott's SuperSite for Windows: Windows Millennium Edition (Windows Me) Beta 3 Reviewed |publisher=Winsupersite.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also shipped with the [[MSN Messenger|MSN Messenger Service]].

===Accessibility features===
*'''[[On-Screen Keyboard]]''': Originally introduced with Windows 2000, a program called On-screen Keyboard has been added, which makes it possible to input characters using the mouse instead of the keyboard. This feature is useful for computers that use a [[Graphics tablet|tablet]] as the primary pointing device or for [[accessibility]] purposes.
*The ''Mouse'' Control Panel incorporates [[IntelliPoint]] features, namely, ClickLock (selecting or dragging without continuously holding down the mouse button), hiding the pointer while typing and showing it by pressing ''Ctrl''.
*The cursor (system caret) can be set to a thicker width.
*Increased [[Active Accessibility]] support in utilities such as [[Calculator (Windows)|Calculator]] and [[Magnifier (Windows)|Magnifier]]

==Removed features==
===Real mode DOS===
One of the most publicized changes from Windows 98 is that Windows Me does not include [[real mode]] [[MS-DOS]].&lt;ref name=&quot;realmode&quot;/&gt; According to Microsoft, with real mode support removed, Windows Me could potentially have faster reliable boot performance. &lt;ref name=&quot;FastBoot1&quot;/&gt;

The [[Config.sys]] and [[Autoexec.bat]] files are no longer read or executed during startup by IO.SYS. The command shell &lt;code&gt;[[command.com]]&lt;/code&gt; is not executed and &lt;code&gt;[[WIN.COM|win.com]]&lt;/code&gt; is bypassed by direct execution of VMM32.VXD from [[IO.SYS]]. Because of these changes, the system can neither boot into an MS-DOS command prompt nor exit to DOS from Windows. Real mode drivers, such as &lt;code&gt;[[ansi.sys]]&lt;/code&gt; cannot be loaded and older applications that require real mode do not run.

In Windows Me, the Autoexec.bat and Config.sys files are used only to set global [[environment variable]]s. The two files (if present) are scanned for settings relating to the environment variables, and any other commands present are removed into a Windows registry key (see below). The two files thus contain only settings and preferences which configure the &quot;global environment&quot; for the computer during the boot phase or when starting a new MS-DOS Virtual Machine (VM).

To specify or edit other startup values (which, in Windows 98, would be present in the autoexec.bat file) the user must edit the following Windows registry key:
:&lt;code&gt;HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\System\CurrentControlSet\Control\SessionManager\Environment&lt;/code&gt;

For troubleshooting and crash recovery, both the Windows Me CD-ROM and the Windows Me startup disk (a user-creatable floppy disk, known as the Emergency Boot Disk) allowed booting into real mode MS-DOS.

===Other components===
Windows Me was aimed exclusively at home users whereas previous versions of Win9x were expected to be used in an [[Enterprise software|enterprise]] business setting. Several features of its predecessors did not work or were officially unsupported by Microsoft on Windows Me, including Automated Installation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/250104 |title=Automated Installation Support in Windows Me |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date=2007-01-27 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Active Directory]] client services,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/276472 |title=Directory Services Client Is Not Included with Windows Me |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date=2007-01-29 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; System Policy Editor,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/266271/en-us |title=The Policy Editor Tool Is Not Supported in Windows Millennium Edition |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date=2007-01-27 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Microsoft Personal Web Server|Personal Web Server]] and [[Active Server Pages|ASP]] not supported on Windows Me although it was supported on predecessors, Windows 98 and Windows 95.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/297943|title=Getting Started with Active Server Pages|publisher=MicroSoft}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Resource Kit]] publication, targeted towards system administrators, was never published for Windows Me.

Other features removed or never updated to work with Windows Me included [[Microsoft Fax]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/258689 |title=Microsoft Fax not supported on Windows Millennium Edition |publisher=Support.microsoft.com |date=2007-01-27 |accessdate=2010-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[QuickView]] and [[DriveSpace]].

==Relation to other Windows releases==
{{Main|History of Microsoft Windows}}

Windows Me was complemented by [[Windows NT|NT]]-based [[Windows 2000]], which was aimed at professional users. Both operating systems were succeeded by [[Windows XP]] with their features unified. All Windows Me support, including security updates and security related hotfixes, was terminated on July 11, 2006. Support for Windows 98 and Windows 98 SE was also terminated on that date. Microsoft ended support for these products because the company considers them obsolete and running these products can expose users to security risks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://microsoft.com/windows/support/endofsupport.mspx|title=Windows End of support for Windows 98, Windows Me, and Windows XP Service Pack 1|accessdate=2006-10-16|publisher=Microsoft}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many third-party applications written for earlier editions of Microsoft Windows, especially older games, run under Windows Me but not under Windows 2000. This fact has become less relevant with the sharp decline in popularity of Windows Me after the release of Windows XP, which features a [[compatibility mode]] which allows many of these older applications to run.

If an installation CD-ROM from the Windows 2000 family is inserted into the drive of a computer running Windows Me, the user is prompted to upgrade to Windows 2000 because Windows Me has an older version number than Windows 2000. While this is not technically so (Windows Me was released several months after Windows 2000), Windows Me ''is'' in fact derived from the older, monolithic MS-DOS codebase (Windows 4.x) while Windows 2000 is the first of the NT 5.0 family, making the latter an upgrade.

Windows 2000 cannot, however, be upgraded to Windows Me. If an installation CD-ROM from Windows Me is inserted while running Windows 2000, the user will receive an error message that Setup cannot run from within Windows 2000. The user is prompted to shut down Windows 2000, restart the computer using Windows 95 or 98, or start MS-DOS and then run Setup from the MS-DOS command prompt.

Windows XP, which is NT-based, became the successor to Windows Me. It also closed the gap between consumer Windows and Windows NT. In addition, no service packs for Windows Me were released.

Along with Windows 2000 from the [[Windows NT|NT]] family, Windows Me was the last version of Windows that lacked [[Microsoft Product Activation|product activation]].

Windows Me was the last operating system to be based on the Windows 9x ([[Monolithic kernel|monolithic]]) kernel and MS-DOS.

==System requirements==
===Minimum system specifications===
*Processor: Pentium 150&amp;nbsp;MHz
*Hard drive space: 320&amp;nbsp;MB
*RAM: 32&amp;nbsp;MB

===Recommended system specifications===
*Processor: [[Pentium II]] 300&amp;nbsp;MHz
*Hard drive space: 2&amp;nbsp;GB
*RAM: 64&amp;nbsp;MB&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/253695|title=Minimum hardware requirements to install Windows Millennium|accessdate=2006-10-16|publisher=Microsoft}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Physical RAM limit===
The maximum amount of physical RAM in a PC that Windows Me supports is 1.5 GB.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/304943 Physical RAM limit for Windows Me.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikibooks|Basic Computing Using Windows/Appendices/Dual Booting}}
*[http://www.guidebookgallery.org/guis/windows/winme/ GUIdebook - Graphical User Interface gallery]
*[http://www.activewin.com/interviews/microsoft/7.shtml Interview with Nicolas Coudière, Chief Product Manager: Microsoft Windows Millennium Edition]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.microsoft.com/windowsme/ Windows Me home page]: The official Windows Me home page from the internet archives
*[http://www.msfn.org/board/index.php?showforum=91 Windows 9x Member Projects]: The Windows 9x Member Projects

{{History of Windows}}

[[Category:2000 software]]
[[Category:Discontinued versions of Microsoft Windows]]
[[Category:Microsoft Windows]]
[[Category:Windows Me]]
[[Category:DOS issues]]
[[Category:Operating system criticisms]]

[[ar:ويندوز ميلينيوم]]
[[az:Windows Me]]
[[bg:Windows Me]]
[[ca:Windows Me]]
[[cs:Windows Me]]
[[da:Windows Me]]
[[de:Microsoft Windows Millennium Edition]]
[[et:Windows Me]]
[[es:Windows Me]]
[[fr:Windows Me]]
[[gl:Windows Me]]
[[ko:윈도 Me]]
[[hr:Windows Me]]
[[id:Windows Me]]
[[it:Windows Me]]
[[lt:Windows Me]]
[[hu:Windows Me]]
[[mr:विंडोज एमई]]
[[ms:Windows Me]]
[[nl:Windows Me]]
[[ja:Microsoft Windows Millennium Edition]]
[[no:Windows Me]]
[[uz:Windows Me]]
[[pl:Microsoft Windows Me]]
[[pt:Windows ME]]
[[ro:Windows Me]]
[[ru:Windows ME]]
[[si:වින්ඩෝස් Me]]
[[simple:Windows Me]]
[[sk:Windows Me]]
[[sl:Windows Me]]
[[fi:Windows Me]]
[[sv:Windows ME]]
[[tl:Windows Me]]
[[ta:விண்டோஸ் மில்லேனியம்]]
[[th:วินโดวส์มี]]
[[tr:Windows Me]]
[[uk:Windows Me]]
[[vec:Windows Me]]
[[vi:Windows Me]]
[[yi:Windows Me]]
[[zh:Windows Me]]
[[hy:Windows Me]]
[[hy:Windows Me]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
