<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7553208" ns="0" title="Sony Entertainment Television (Latin America)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{update|date=November 2010}}

{{Infobox TV channel
|name         = Sony Entertainment Television
|launch       = September 30, 1995
|logofile     = Canal Sony.svg
|logosize     = 150px
|picture format    = [[480i]] ([[SDTV]]) &lt;br /&gt;[[1080i]] ([[HDTV]])
|broadcast area    =  Latin America |
|sister names =  [[AXN]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sony Spin]]
|owner        =  [[Sony Pictures Entertainment]]|
| sat serv 1 = [[Dish Network Mexico]]
| sat chan 1 = Channel 211 (908 in HD)
| adsl serv 1 = [[UNE EPM Telecomunicaciones]]
| adsl chan 1 = Channel 54
|web      =  [http://www.canalsony.com/ canalsony.com]|
}}

'''Sony Entertainment Television''', commonly shortened to '''Canal Sony''' (''&quot;Sony Channel&quot;'', in both Spanish and Portuguese), is a general entertainment channel co-based in [[Perú]], Chile, Venezuela, Brazil and [[Miami, Florida]], United States. It airs in 26 countries in Latin America,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.canalsony.com/&lt;/ref&gt; and is owned by [[Sony Pictures Entertainment]]. In the region, it is distributed by [[HBO Latin America Group]].

When Sony Entertainment Television Latin America began transmissions in 1995, it was a premium entertainment cable television channel that aired movies and series from Sony Pictures Entertainment. When the premium service failed in the late 1990s, it became a basic cable television channel.

Unlike most national television networks in Latin America, which air all the imported shows dubbed, Sony airs most of its shows [[subtitles|subtitled]] (in Portuguese or Spanish, depending on the country).

Sony Entertainment Television Latin America shows new series or the most recent season series from United States television networks such as ''[[Will &amp; Grace]]'', ''[[American Idol]]'', ''[['Til Death]]'', ''[[30 Rock]]'',  ''[[Queer Eye for the Straight Guy]]'',  ''[[Falcon Beach]]'', ''[[America's Next Top Model]]'', ''[[Scrubs (TV series)|Scrubs]]'', ''[[My Wife and Kids]]'', ''[[Everybody Hates Chris]]'', ''[[Medium (TV series)|Medium]]'', ''[[Ghost Whisperer]]'', ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'',  ''[[Charmed]]'', ''[[Whose Line Is It Anyway?]]'', ''[[Grey's Anatomy]]'', ''[[According to Jim]]'', ''[[Desperate Housewives]]'', ''[[That '70s Show]]'', ''[[Ugly Betty]]'', ''[[Big Day]]'', ''[[Samantha Who?]]'' and reruns or previous seasons of shows such as ''[[Seinfeld]]'', ''[[Mad About You]]'', ''[[Dawson's Creek]]'', ''[[Melrose Place (1992 TV series)|Melrose Place]]'', ''[[Beverly Hills, 90210]]'', ''[[Married with Children]]'', ''[[The Nanny (TV series)|The Nanny]]'', ''[[My Wife and Kids]]'' and ''[[Frasier]]''. Recently it has been broadcasting several hard comedy series, particularly from the UK such as ''[[Balls of Steel (TV series)|Balls of Steel]]'' and ''[[Da Ali G Show]]''.

Sony Entertainment Television biggest production so far is: ''[[Latin American Idol]]''. The first season included 20 countries, with auditions in [[Caracas]], Venezuela, [[Bogotá]], Colombia, Mexico City and finishing in [[Buenos Aires]], Argentina, the host country. The show did not include Brazil, because the country already has [[Ídolos Brazil|their own version]] on [[terrestrial television]]. The winner of the first season was [[Mayre Martinez]] from Venezuela, winning, amongst other prizes, a record deal, a car and a record contract.

On June 12, a redesign of the channel welcomed three new original productions by SET. '''Nada Que Ver''' was the first one, but it aired for a very short period of time, and was replaced with ''[[The IT Crowd]]'' due to unpopularity and criticism. Recently the first season of ''The IT Crowd'' finished and ''Nada Que Ver'', returned to the programation of P.I (Politically Incorrect, also named after the sound of a bleep in Spanish diction).
''FusionA2'' (Fused) is a reality show in which two bands are brought together for two days to prepare and play a song together. And ''[[Ya es 1/2 Día en China]]'' (It's Noon in China) A late night show in the format of [[NBC]]'s  ''[[The Tonight Show]]'' with [[Jay Leno]]. The show is currently hosted by [[Luis Chataing]].

Sony Entertainment Television regularly cooperates with popular brands, like [[Sony Ericsson]], or Sony's competitors, like [[Philips]], to present new products in their mini-show &quot;Los Huevos de Oro&quot; (The Golden Eggs), which is shown during commercial breaks. SET also shows music videos, as occasional time-fillers. Another popular feature the channel has been known for is ''Si Se Lo Perdió'' (in Portuguese, ''Vale o Bis''), which means &quot;In Case You Missed It&quot;, a block that would re-air any new episodes of prime time shows that aired during the week on Sundays, convenient for those that missed the original airings during the week.

''Nada que Ver'' is not aired in Brazil and is not on air currently.

''[[Ugly Betty]]'' will be aired in Mexico, starting April 2008.

Sony started airing movies in Tuesday's prime time. Although the name of the slot refers to Hollywood-produced humor, the movies aired are all romantic comedies, such as Little Black Book, America's Sweethearts, and My Best Friend's Wedding. On ''December 2009'' this space was moved to Saturdays, until it was eventually dropped in 2010, though a movie block will return to the Brazilian feed on Thursdays, starting in April 2011, as '''Cine Sony'''. At the same time this block return to the other regional feeds in Spanish, but on Fridays, as '''EPH: Espacio Producido Hollywood''' (&quot;Hollywood-Produced Space&quot;). 

The channel have aired original shows, such as [[Mexico's Next Top Model]] and [[Brazil's Next Top Model]] (Both based in [[America’s Next Top Model]], which airs on the channel). Other original Latin-American series that premiered on the channel are [[Los Simuladores]] and ''Los Caballeros las prefieren Brutas''. 

In 2011, the Sony Pictures channels in Brazil gained greater independence from the Spanish-language feeds,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anmtv.xpg.com.br/animax-sony-anuncia-regionalizacao-de-seus-canais-no-brasil/ ANMTV - ''Animax: Sony anuncia regionalização de seus canais no Brasil.]&lt;/ref&gt; and as part of that, it was announced that [[CSI: Crime Scene Investigation]] would return to SET in Brazil, while in the rest of the region, that show remains on sister channel [[AXN]]. In October 2011, [[CSI: Miami]] would make such channel switch in Brazil. [[CSI: NY]] remains seen on AXN in the entire region.

==Programs==
{{see|List of programs broadcast by Sony Entertainment Television (Latin America)}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.canalsony.com SET Latin America]

[[Category:Sony Pictures Television]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
