<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7560754" ns="0" title="Gotham (typeface)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox font
| name =
| image = GothamSpec.svg|
| style = [[Sans-serif]]
| classifications = [[sans-serif|Geometric sans-serif]]
| releasedate = 2000
| creator = [[Tobias Frere-Jones]]
| foundry = [[Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones]]
| variations = Gotham Rounded, Gotham Condensed, Gotham Narrow, Gotham X-Narrow
|}}

'''Gotham''' is a family of geometric [[sans-serif]] digital typefaces designed by American type designer [[Tobias Frere-Jones]] in 2000. Gotham's letterforms are inspired by a form of architectural [[signage]] that achieved popularity in the mid-twentieth century, and are especially popular throughout [[New York City]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gotham&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.typography.com/fonts/font_history.php?historyItemID=1&amp;productLineID=100008|title=Gotham:History|publisher=Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones|accessdate=2009-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since creation, Gotham has been highly visible due to its appearance in many notable places, including a large amount of campaign material created for [[Barack Obama presidential campaign, 2008|Barack Obama's 2008 presidential campaign]], as well as the cornerstone of the [[One World Trade Center]], the tower to be built on the site of the former [[World Trade Center]] in New York.

==Creation and style==
The Gotham font was initially commissioned by ''[[GQ]]'' magazine, whose editors wanted to display a sans-serif with a &quot;geometric structure&quot; that would look &quot;masculine, new, and fresh&quot; for their magazine. Although the magazine was initially considering a series of fonts that either looked like techno CD covers or were more traditional like [[Futura (typeface)|Futura]], they agreed that they needed something &quot;that was going to be very fresh and very established to have a sort of credible voice to it,&quot; according to [[Jonathan Hoefler]].&lt;ref name=&quot;helvetica-film&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.helveticafilm.com/newblog/2008/02/19/a-font-we-can-believe-in/|title=A Font You Can Believe In|last=Hustwit|first=Gary|date=2 February 2008|publisher=HelveticaFilm.com|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Frere-Jones' inspiration for the typeface came from time spent walking block-by-block through [[Manhattan]] with a camera to find source material,&lt;ref name=&quot;morning-news&quot;/&gt; and he based the font on the lettering seen in older buildings, especially the sign on the Eighth Avenue facade of the [[Port Authority Bus Terminal]]. &quot;I suppose there's a hidden personal agenda in the design,&quot; Frere-Jones said, &quot;to preserve those old pieces of New York that could be wiped out before they're appreciated. Having grown up here, I was always fond of the 'old' New York and its lettering.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;morning-news&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.themorningnews.org/archives/personalities/is_gotham_the_new_interstate.php|title=Is Gotham the New Interstate?|last=Siegel|first=Dimitri|date=8 August 2002|publisher=[[The Morning News (online magazine)|The Morning News]]|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The lettering that inspired this typeface originated from the style of 1920s era sans-serifs like [[Futura (typeface)|Futura]], where &quot;Type, like architecture, like the organization of society itself, was to be reduced to its bare, efficient essentials, rid of undesirable, local or ethnic elements.&quot; This theme was found frequently in Depression-era type in both North America and Europe, particularly Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;werner&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.aiga.org/content.cfm/freedom-tower-type|title=Freedom Tower Type|last=Werner|first=Paul T.|date=16 July 2004|journal=AIGA Journal of Design|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; This simplification of type is characterized by Frere-Jones as &quot;not the kind of letter a type designer would make. It's the kind of letter an engineer would make. It was born outside the type design in some other world and has a very distinct flavor from that.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;helvetica-film&quot;/&gt;

Reviews of Gotham focus on its identity as something both American and specific to New York City. According to David Dunlap of ''[[The New York Times]]'', Gotham &quot;deliberately evokes the blocky no-nonsense, unselfconscious architectural lettering that dominated the [New York] streetscape from the 1930's through the 1960's.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;times-dunlap&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/08/nyregion/08blocks.html|title=9/11 Cornerstone, Chiseled With a New York Accent|last=Dunlap|first=David|date=8 July 2004|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Andrew Romano of ''[[Newsweek]]'' concurs. &quot;Unlike other sans serif typefaces, it's not German, it's not French, it's not Swiss,&quot; he said. &quot;It's very American.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.newsweek.com/blogs/stumper/archive/2008/02/27/how-obama-s-branding-is-working-on-you.aspx|title=Expertinent: Why the Obama &quot;Brand&quot; Is Working|last=Romano|first=Andrew|date=27 February 2008|publisher=Newsweek|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Frere-Jones, Gotham wouldn't have happened without the ''GQ'' commission. &quot;The humanist and the geometric ... had already been thoroughly staked out and developed by past designers. I didn't think anything new could have been found there, but luckily for me (and the client), I was mistaken.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;morning-news&quot;/&gt;

==On the Freedom Tower==
Gotham was prominently featured in 2004 as the typeface on the cornerstone for the [[One World Trade Center|Freedom Tower]] at the [[World Trade Center]] site, itself owned by the [[Port Authority of New York and New Jersey]], which also owns the bus terminal that inspired the typeface. In a [[Independence Day (United States)|Fourth of July]] speech at its unveiling, then-Governor [[George Pataki]] cited the cornerstone as the &quot;bedrock of our state&quot;. The text is written in all-uppercase letters, which was criticized, as some wanted a mix of upper and lower-case to &quot;give the words a human voice.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;times-dunlap&quot;/&gt;

==In the Obama campaign==
[[File:Change We Can Believe In.svg|frame|right|Gotham as featured in the Obama '08 campaign slogan]]
Original materials for the [[Barack Obama presidential campaign, 2008|Obama campaign]] used the serif [[Perpetua (typeface)|Perpetua]]. Later, however, upon hiring [[John Slabyk]], and Scott Thomas, the campaign made the change to Gotham, and the font was used on numerous signs and posters for the campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doctor&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.ricethresher.org/media/storage/paper1290/news/2008/11/07/Election08/Campaign.Messages.Marked.By.Typography-3530592.shtml|title=Campaign messages marked by typography|last=Doctor|first=Eric|date=7 November 2008|publisher=The Rice Thresher|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[International Herald Tribune]]'' praised the choice for its &quot;potent, if unspoken, combination of contemporary sophistication (a nod to his suits) with nostalgia for America's past and a sense of duty.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BrandObama&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/04/arts/04iht-design7.html|title=Brand Obama, a leader in the image war|last=Rawsthorn|first=Alice|date=6 April 2008|publisher=International Herald Tribune|accessdate=2011-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; John Berry, an author of books on typography, agreed: &quot;It's funny to see it used in a political campaign because on the one hand it's almost too ordinary yet that's the point. It has the sense of trustworthiness because you've seen it everywhere.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LA-times&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2008/mar/30/image/ig-font30|title=The Character Issue|last=Tschorn|first=Adam|date=2 April 2008|publisher=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Graphic designer [[Brian Collins (designer)|Brian Collins]] noted that Gotham was the &quot;linchpin&quot; to Obama's entire campaign imagery.&lt;ref name=&quot;To the Letter Born&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://campaignstops.blogs.nytimes.com/tag/gotham-typeface/|title=To the Letter Born|last=Heller|first=Steven|date=2 April 2008|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Observers of the [[Democratic Party (United States) presidential primaries, 2008|primary]] and general elections compared Obama's design choices favorably to those made by his opponents. In her campaign, [[Hillary Clinton]] used [[New Baskerville]], a serif used by book publishers, law firms, and universities, while [[John McCain]] used [[Optima]], the same font used for the [[Vietnam Veterans Memorial]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BrandObama&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Non-Fontogenic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.typography.com/ask/showBlog.php?blogID=79|title=...and Non-Fontogenic...|date=21 February 2008|publisher=Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also has to be noticed that while the Obama campaign material still used the [[Perpetua (typeface)|Perpetua typeface]], the short-lived [[John Edwards]] campaign was already using Gotham Ultra.&lt;ref name=&quot;A Change We Made&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.typography.com/ask/showBlog.php?blogID=63|title=A Change We Made|date=4 January 2008|publisher=Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Obama won the presidency, Gotham and similar typefaces found their way into various federal government projects, most notably the identity of the [[2010 United States Census]].

==Notable examples==
Gotham has found its way into other commercial media, as well. [[Coca-Cola]], television shows [[Maury (TV series)|''Maury'']] and ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'', the [[Tribeca Film Festival]], the [[Qwest]] advertisements, and the [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] Governor's Office of Customer Service have all used Gotham in logos.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doctor&quot;/&gt; The Georgia state government cited Gotham's &quot;clean, fresh lines&quot; and variations that &quot;offer a variety of options for use in all marketing, advertising and signage applications&quot; as reason for its use.&lt;ref name=&quot;georgia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://team.georgia.gov/OCS/OCS_CommonFiles/OCS_Files/CS_Branding.pdf|title=Governor's Office of Customer Service Brand Standards Manual|publisher=Georgia Governor's Office of Customer Service|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Starbucks]] used the typeface in conjunction with the [[United States presidential election, 2008|2008 Presidential election]] to advertise an offer of free coffee to people who vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whywhywhywhywhy.com/2008/11/starbucks-using-gotham-typeface-to-endorse-obama/|title=Starbucks Using Gotham Typeface to Endorse Obama?|last=Neale|first=McDavitt Van Fleet|date=3 November 2008|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a2J8KJDsqqY|title=If you vote, Starbucks buys your coffee|publisher=YouTube|accessdate=2009-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gotham has also been used by [[Yahoo!|Yahoo's]] website as well as [[The Criterion Collection]]'s.

Gotham has also been used by [[Rite Aid|Rite Aid Pharmacy]], [[Banana Republic]], [[Crest (toothpaste)|Crest]] dental hygiene products, and [[Smirnoff]] Cocktails.

The Malaysian [[Astro (satellite TV)|Astro]] network uses Gotham for most of its text.

Frere-Jones said about the typeface when it was released in 2002: &quot;With Gotham’s origin—and my own stubborn opinions—I think that anywhere in the suburban sprawl would be the worst place for it: advertising for featureless subdivisions, the specials board at the Exit 23 [[Dairy Queen]], bumper stickers that say ‘I [heart] my SUV’ and so on.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;morning-news&quot; /&gt;

* Gotham is the brand font for [[Tom Ford]], [[Yahoo!]], and [[ZipRealty]]. 

* Gotham is the font used in the [[Chicago 2016 Olympic bid|Chicago 2016 Summer Olympic Games Bid]].

* Gotham is used in new logo of TV channels [[Discovery Channel]] and [[HGTV]], and branding for [[QVC]], [[USA Network]] and [[History Channel]]. 

* A modified version of Gotham Ultra is used by [[Cartoon Network]] for its new logo and for presentation.

* The [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] uses Gotham for its on-screen typographic identity, beginning with the graphic refresh of [[ABC News (Australia)|ABC News]] bulletins on [[ABC1]] and the launch of [[ABC News 24]] on 22 July, 2010.

* Gotham is used for the titles to Christopher Nolan's film ''[[Inception]]'', Duncan Jones' ''[[Moon (film)|Moon]]'', David O. Russell's ''[[The Fighter (2010 film)|The Fighter]]'', and Tom Ford's film ''[[A Single Man (film)|A Single Man]]''.

* Gotham has been used for Nickelodeon's presentations on TV.

* Gotham has been used for the John Hampden Grammar School's, High Wycombe, United Kingdom stationery

* Gotham was used for the popular ''I'm With Coco'' posters during [[Conan O'Brien]]'s [[2010 Tonight Show conflict]]. The font was eventually adopted for [[TBS (TV channel)|TBS]]'s ''[[Conan (TV series)|Conan]]'' logo.

* Gotham has been used for [[BBC Sport]] television programmes' on-screen graphics since the [[2010 FIFA World Cup]].  

* Gotham is used in the logos of Austrian national broadcaster [[ORF (broadcaster)|ORF]].

A customized version of Gotham is the font used for the new logo of [[United Continental Holdings]], replacing the previous font of [[Continental Airlines]], called [[Perpetua (typeface)|Monotype Perpetua]] and the corporate font of [[United Airlines]].

==Variations==
Gotham originally was introduced with an italic as well as a range of widths.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gotham&quot; /&gt; In 2007, a Rounded variant was introduced due to a commission from [[Print (magazine)|''Print'']] magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Typographica-Rounded&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://typographica.org/2007/on-typography/gotham-rounded-corners-cut-by-popular-demand/|title=Gotham Rounded: Corners Cut by Popular Demand|date=10 January 2007|publisher=Typographica|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Hoefler and Frere-Jones introduced new Narrow and Extra Narrow versions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.typography.com/ask/showBlog.php?blogID=165|title=THE NEW GOTHAMS: 46 New Fonts from H&amp;FJ|date=20 January 2009|publisher=Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones|accessdate=2009-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 4, 2011, Hoefler and Frere-Jones announced that they had created a new custom version of Gotham with serifs for the use of President Barack Obama's 2012 campaign. In announcing the news they wrote: &quot;Can We Add Serifs to Gotham? For the President of The United States? Yes We Can.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hoefler|first=Jonathan|title=Can We Add Serifs to Gotham?|url=http://www.typography.com/ask/showBlog.php?blogID=261|publisher=H&amp;FJ News|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==Further reading==
*Friedl, Frederich, Nicholas Ott and Bernard Stein. ''Typography: An Encyclopedic Survey of Type Design and Techniques Through History.'' Black Dog &amp; Leventhal: 1998. ISBN 1-57912-023-7.
*Macmillan, Neil. ''An A–Z of Type Designers.'' Yale University Press: 2006. ISBN 0-300-11151-7.

==External links==
*[http://www.typography.com/fonts/font_overview.php?productLineID=100008 Official Gotham page] at [[Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones]]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ow6ajKO0XsM &quot;Jonathan Hoefler and Tobias Frere-Jones on Gotham&quot;] - an [[outtake]] from the film ''[[Helvetica (film)|Helvetica]]'' that discusses the creation of the font.

[[Category:Hoefler &amp; Frere-Jones typefaces]]
[[Category:Geometric sans-serif typefaces]]
[[Category:virtual typefaces]]

[[ru:Готэм (шрифт)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
