<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="757030" ns="0" title="Replicator (Stargate)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues| in-universe=December 2009
 | primarysources=December 2008
 | fiction=December 2009
 | notability=December 2009}}
{{Stargaterace
| image = [[File:Replicator top.jpg|200px]]
| caption = A basic Replicator &quot;bug&quot;.
| name = Replicator
| type = [[Machine|Mechanical race]]
| affiliation = 
| planet = 
| first = &quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot; (2000)
| last = 
}}
In the [[military science fiction]] series ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'', the '''Replicators''' are antagonistic [[self-replicating machine]]s that propagate by ingesting the metals  that make up civilizations and use them to create either blocks that form the bug-like version or smaller cells that compose the human-form &quot;Replicators&quot;.  They were first mentioned indirectly in the season 3 episode {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, and first seen onscreen in {{sgcite|Nemesis}}. The Replicators are primarily the enemies of the [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]] race, but Earth must also contend with them on several occasions. The [[Asuran]]s of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'', essentially human-form &quot;Replicators&quot;, might be related to those in ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''.

==Show history==
The Replicators first appear in the season 3 finale {{sgcite|Nemesis}}, following hints by [[Thor (Stargate)|Thor]] in {{sgcite|Fair Game}} about an enemy worse than the [[Goa'uld]] in their home galaxy of Ida. [[SG-1]] faces off against the Replicators who have infested Thor's mothership, the ''Beliskner'', to prevent them from invading Earth. They destroy the deceleration drive on the ''Beliskner'', causing it to burn up in Earth's atmosphere. In the following episode {{sgcite|Small Victories}}, a single surviving Replicator from the ''Beliskner'' infests a [[Russia]]n [[submarine]] before being neutralized. At the same time, [[Samantha Carter]] helps Thor avert an imminent Replicator invasion of the Asgard homeworld, Halla. In the season 5 premiere {{sgcite|Enemies}}, SG-1 encounters the Replicators after being thrown to another galaxy by a [[supernova]]. The Replicators take over their [[Ha'tak|Goa'uld mothership]] and head for the Milky Way; to prevent them from reaching their destination, SG-1 sabotages the mothership's engines so that it crashes into the planet Delmak upon exiting hyperspace.

The episode {{sgcite|Menace}} reveals that the Replicators were created by the android '''Reese''' (played by [[Danielle Nicolet]]) as &quot;toys&quot; that she programmed to protect her when the others on her world attempted to shut her down. As the Replicators multiplied, they escaped her control and destroyed her civilization before moving on. After being brought back to the [[Stargate Command|SGC]], Reese creates more Replicators out of available materials, which overrun the base and are only stopped after Colonel [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] shoots her. It is possible that shooting her was unnecessary though, as mentioned by Dr. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] after Reese's death in {{sgcite|Menace}}. Reese is handed over to the Asgard, who find within her a base command that allows them to summon all the Replicators. They intend to use the command to trap all the Replicators on Halla inside a time dilation field that would give them years to devise a more permanent solution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Unnatural Selection&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Unnatural Selection|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Unnatural Selection}}, Thor calls upon SG-1 to investigate when the time dilation device fails to activate. They find that the device has been reversed to accelerate the passage of time inside and that the surface of Halla has been completely converted into Replicator blocks. They also encounter the human-form Replicators (''see below''), the new faces of the Replicator threat. SG-1 is able to reactivate the time dilation field by appealing to the humanity of one of the human-forms, Fifth.

In the season 8 premiere {{sgcite|New Order}}, the Asgard have collapsed Halla's sun into a [[black hole]] trying to destroy the Replicators. However, the Replicators escape, led by a now-vengeful Fifth. Their invasion of the new Asgard homeworld Orilla is turned away after O'Neill (who had subsequently had the knowledge of the Ancients downloaded into his mind again) uses the knowledge of the Ancients to create the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator disruptor]]. Fifth also creates a copy of Samantha Carter to serve as his consort and spy. Replicator Carter betrays Fifth, killing him, and takes over control of the Replicators in {{sgcite|Gemini}}, and oversees the full-scale invasion of the Milky Way in {{sgcite|Reckoning}}. She and her brethren are finally defeated using the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Dakara superweapon|Dakara superweapon]]. The Replicators return in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', where one is created by the Asgard computer core on the Earth ship ''Odyssey'' by IOA agent James Marrick. The IOA plans to use the Replicators as a weapon against the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]]; however the Replicator escapes and soon replicates, overrunning the ship. Facing off against the Replicator-controlled Marrick, Mitchell manages to find the kill-switch the IOA built into the Replicators, allowing Carter to deactivate them.

==Technology==
Standard Replicators are composed of [[Modular design|modular]] blocks, comparable to [[microcomputers|individual computers]], that come together to perform tasks. According to Thor, the blocks generate a &quot;reactive modulating monopolar energy field&quot; that allows them to self-assemble into various configurations. Each Replicator block contains two million &quot;isolated keron pathways&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Small Victories|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; All Replicators are interconnected via a subspace network. Replicator blocks can assemble into any form needed;&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|New Order|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the most commonly encountered shape is a small &quot;bug&quot; with four limbs and &quot;wings&quot; on its back. The bug can upgrade itself into a larger &quot;queen&quot; to facilitate replication.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ark of Truth&quot;&gt;''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Large numbers of Replicators can form into [[Starships in Stargate#Replicator starships|starships]], which are first seen in {{sgcite|New Order}}. In {{sgcite|Enemies}}, many Replicator bugs assemble into a larger structure to enhance the hyperdrive of a Goa'uld mothership. In ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', the Replicators form a skeletal structure that implants into Marrick's body, to gain access to his mind. The Replicator structure continues to function even after Marrick's body is destroyed.

The main Replicator directives are to multiply and to assimilate new technologies. Replicators utilize whatever materials are available; in {{sgcite|Small Victories}}, the Replicators created from a Russian submarine are made of [[steel]] and susceptible to [[rust]]ing. Multiple blocks are required for replication,&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;/&gt; and the process requires a large amount of energy.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ark of Truth&quot;/&gt; Replicators are attracted to the most advanced technologies available, thus they ignore the relatively crude technology of the Earth ship ''Prometheus'' in {{sgcite|Unnatural Selection}}. Replicators adapt very quickly to new technologies and they are capable of enhancing technology they encounter beyond its original specifications.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Enemies|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Replicators are impervious to all known handheld [[energy]] weapons, including [[Goa'uld technology in Stargate#Zat'nik'tel|zat'nik'tel]]s and [[Goa'uld technology in Stargate#Staff Weapon|staff weapon]]s. They can be shattered by projectile [[firearm]]s, though given time and relative proximity to each other, the blocks will re-assemble. Replicator bugs produce a [[corrosive]] [[liquid]] (&quot;Replicator spray&quot;) capable of dissolving through any known material but [[concrete]] and [[glass]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Nemesis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the nigh-invulnerable armor of [[Kull Warrior]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Reckoning|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In close quarters, they can produce an electrical discharge to kill their opponents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;/&gt; Replicator bugs are strong for their size; a single one held open the [[hydraulics|hydraulic]] blast doors of the SGC's gate room in {{sgcite|Reckoning}}.

==Human-form Replicators==
In the ''Stargate SG-1'' episode &quot;[[Unnatural Selection (Stargate SG-1)|Unnatural Selection]]&quot;, SG-1 encounters the human-form Replicators on the former Asgard world of Halla, who capture them and probe their minds to learn about Earth and the SGC. The human-form Replicators are [[Claytronics#Programmable_Matter|claytronic]] in nature, derived from the technology of the android Reese's self-repair [[nanite]]s. They are physically indistinguishable from humans and possess immense strength and resilience, lacking the traditional Replicators' vulnerability to firearms. They are capable of interfacing with the mind of a human by extending their hand into the victim's forehead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Unnatural Selection&quot;/&gt; Human-form Replicators can restructure parts of themselves to form implements such as stabbing weapons,&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;/&gt; or disconnect portions from the whole.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gemini&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Gemini|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Neutronium]] is a crucial element in the construction of human-form Replicators.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt; The original human-form Replicators depicted in {{sgcite|Unnatural Selection}} are, in order of their creation:

*'''First''', their leader, played by [[Ian Buchanan]].
*'''Second''', played by [[Kristina Copeland]].
*'''Third''', played by [[Tahmoh Penikett]].
*'''Fourth''', played by [[Rebecca Robbins]].
*'''Fifth''', played by [[Patrick Currie]].
*'''Sixth''', played by [[Shannon Powell]].

At the end of &quot;Unnatural Selection&quot;, all the human-form Replicators are trapped on Halla after SG-1 activates the time-dilation device. The only one of the original six Replicators who appears in subsequent episodes is Fifth, who escapes Halla in &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;.

Another human-form Replicator also appears in &quot;New Order&quot;, '''Eighth'''. He was played by [[James Bamford (actor)|James Bamford]], the stunt-coordinator of ''Stargate Atlantis'', which was shooting its pilot during &quot;New Order&quot;; the producers wanted to make Bamford feel as part of the family.&lt;ref&gt;[[Andy Mikita]] in the audio commentary for &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Eighth is recovered, damaged and inactive, by [[Thor (Stargate)|Thor]], as a means to tap into the Replicator network and determine the location of Fifth. Eighth activates and breaks free aboard Thor's ship, and is disintegrated by [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] using the newly constructed [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator Disruptor]].&lt;ref&gt;Eighth's name is not mentioned in the episode, but appears in the ending credits&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fifth===
[[Image:StargateCharFifth1.jpg|thumb|[[Patrick Currie]] as Fifth]]
Played by [[Patrick Currie]], '''Fifth''' is a human-form Replicator introduced in &quot;[[Unnatural Selection (Stargate SG-1)|Unnatural Selection]]&quot;. He is the fifth human-form to be created on the planet [[Halla (Stargate)|Halla]], and unlike the others he lacks the programming flaws of the android [[Reese (Stargate)|Reese]], on which the human-forms are based. This makes him more &quot;human&quot; than the other Replicators, who consider him &quot;weak&quot; as a result. After SG-1 is captured by the Replicators, Fifth becomes fascinated by them, especially [[Samantha Carter]], and attempts to help them. Carter promises to take Fifth with them if he can give them access to the Asgard [[Technology in Stargate#Asgard technology|time dilation device]] that could trap the other Replicators. Fifth agrees, but [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] believes he represents too great a danger and orders Carter to set the device's timer so that Fifth is left behind. Fifth is confronted by the other Replicators, and discovers SG-1's deception moments before the device activates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Unnatural Selection&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Unnatural Selection (Stargate SG-1)|Unnatural Selection]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Fifth returns in the season 8 episode &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;, in which the Asgard have collapsed Halla's sun to destroy the Replicators once and for all. He is able to modify the time dilation device to escape, and heads for the new Asgard homeworld of Orilla. En route, he captures Samantha Carter and tortures her in revenge for exploiting his trust. He eventually relents when she appeals to his humanity again, and instead places her into an illusory world where he takes the place of [[Pete Shanahan]], her boyfriend, and professes his love for her. The Replicators invade Orilla and Fifth confronts the rest of SG-1, who are armed with a [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator Disruptor]]. Carter tells him that she would rather be dead than be trapped in her current state, and that if he truly loved her he would let her go. Thus, Fifth leaves her behind as he retreats from Orilla. However, at the end of the episode, he creates a Replicator duplicate of Carter to serve as his consort.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot; /&gt;

Fifth appears for the last time in &quot;[[Gemini (Stargate SG-1)|Gemini]]&quot;, conspiring with Replicator Carter to obtain data from the SGC that would immunize them from the Replicator Disruptor. Replicator Carter however never returned his feelings, believing him unfit to command the Replicators. She ultimately betrays him, taking the data for herself while manipulating him into being destroyed by the Disruptor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gemini&quot; /&gt;

===Replicator Carter===
[[Image:RepliCarter.jpg|thumb|[[Amanda Tapping]] as Replicator Carter.]]
[[Amanda Tapping]] played '''Replicator Carter''' (commonly referred to as '''RepliCarter''' by the producers, actors, fans and characters),&lt;ref&gt;[[Martin Wood]] and [[Amanda Tapping]] in the audio commentary for &quot;[[Lifeline (Stargate Atlantis)|Lifeline]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[Replicator (Stargate)#Human-form Replicators|human-form Replicator]] created from information that Fifth had collected while holding the real Sam Carter in prison on board his ship.

She first appeared at the end of &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;, having been created by Fifth with the intention of being an exact and perfect copy intended to resemble the original Samantha &quot;Sam&quot; Carter with every aspect of her personality including the original Carter's character and memory intact. 

But unlike the original who hated him and had even ended up betraying him, Fifth had designed Replicator Carter with the intention of her solely being devoted to him and perhaps even sharing his feelings, something the original Carter would never ever agree to do.

After triumphing in Replicator Carter's creation, Fifth, realizing that she still harbored all the emotions and feelings of the original Carter began training her in the hope that he could force her to become a completely separate entity while also serving as a loyal warrior who would also obey him without question. 

To help achieve this goal and make it a possible reality, Fifth then had Replicator Carter undergo a brutal training regime which usually involved her being subjected to various situations which saw her killing many of the original Carter's friends and colleagues, a process that was repeated over and over again. 

Unfortunately, while Fifth's plans did come to fruition, they worked in the opposite way of what he had originally planned for as the strain of what she was doing eventually and permanently robbed Replicator Carter of any mercy, guilt or regret she might have felt which resulted in her becoming an unforgiving, psychotic, brutal and overall relentless killing machine with nothing but achieving power for herself while also conquering and gaining complete control over the galaxy on her mind. She also grew to hate Fifth for his actions, seeing him as nothing more than a single weakling which also resulted in her becoming a major adversary in the eighth season of the series, threatening the entire Milky Way galaxy. 

Fifth intended her to be a duplicate of the real [[Samantha Carter]], but one who would return his affections.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;&quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Replicator Carter seemingly defected from Fifth to the SGC in &quot;[[Gemini (Stargate SG-1)|Gemini]]&quot;. She claimed that she'd abandoned Fifth because she possessed the real Carter's memories and character. However, she had actually been deceiving both the SGC and Fifth all along: from the former she developed a means to immunize herself from the Replicator Disruptor, and the latter she abandoned to be destroyed, having only pretended to love him. And with Fifth dead, Replicator Carter took over the vacant position, gaining full leadership of the entire Replicator race.

Replicator Carter told her human counterpart that all humans desire power, and that the only difference between them was that she wasn't limited by her own fears.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gemini&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Gemini (Stargate SG-1)|Gemini]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to the original Carter, Replicator Carter was something of a ruthless being who lived only to kill those who stood in her way and to also cause endless destruction. And unlike the original who was bound by duty, loyalty and principle, Replicator Carter had no such restrictions set in her programming and as such regularly let her ambitions run free.

In &quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning]]&quot;, Replicator Carter launched a full-scale invasion of the Milky Way and personally eliminated the last of the [[Goa'uld]] [[System Lord]]s including Yu. She abducted [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] and probed his mind to find the location of the [[Dakara superweapon]], the only thing in the galaxy capable of stopping her and her brethen. She sent her massive Replicator-controlled [[Ha'tak]] fleet to Dakara to destroy the device, where they engaged the forces of [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] and the [[Jaffa Rebellion]]. 

She also sent Replicators to attack Earth, where they overran much of [[Stargate Command]]. However, at a critical moment, Daniel Jackson was able to exploit his connection to the Replicator network and freeze all the Replicators. 

Though Replicator Carter eventually broke their connection and stabbed Daniel through the heart, killing him, a fate that had previously befallen Lord Yu, Daniel's own actions bought enough time for the real Carter and [[Tok'ra#Selmak|Jacob/Selmak]] to finish calibrating the Dakara weapon and activate it. The resulting energy wave broke Replicator Carter and all her brethren into their constituent parts, finally ending the threat of Replicator Carter and her race once and for all although her actions had life-changing consequences for the entire Milky Way galaxy and its people. 

Due to the fact that she had decided to move against the Goa'uld and kill them off in an attempt to gain territory for herself, the power struggle that ensued eventually demolished the majority of the Goa'uld's forces, weakening them. 

And with the Replicators having been destroyed, many unoccupied vessels previously occupied by Goa'uld forces but now abandoned soon fell into the domains of groups such as the Free Jaffa Nation and also the Lucian Alliance.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.gateworld.net/omnipedia/races/links/replicators.shtml &quot;Replicators&quot;] at [[GateWorld]] Omnipedia.
* [http://www.stargate-sg1-solutions.com/wiki/Replicators &quot;Replicators&quot;] at StargateWiki (SG-1 Solutions).
* [http://stargate.wikia.com/wiki/Replicators &quot;Replicators&quot;] at Stargate Wikia.

{{StargateNav}}

[[Category:Stargate races]]
[[Category:Fictional robots]]
[[Category:Fictional characters who can duplicate themselves]]
[[Category:Fictional weapons of mass destruction]]

[[ar:متضاعفين]]
[[bs:Replikatori]]
[[bg:Репликатори]]
[[cs:Replikátoři]]
[[fr:Réplicateurs (Stargate)]]
[[hr:Replikatori (Zvjezdana vrata)]]
[[it:Replicatori (Stargate)]]
[[hu:Replikátor]]
[[pl:Replikatory]]
[[ro:Replicator (Stargate)]]
[[ru:Репликаторы (Звёздные врата)]]
[[sl:Replikatorji]]
[[sh:Replikatori (Stargate)]]
[[sv:Lista över raser i Stargate#Replikatorer]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
