<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="762801" ns="0" title="The Burkiss Way"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Radio Show
| show_name          = The Burkiss Way
| image              = 
| imagesize          = 
| caption            = 
| format             = [[Sketch comedy]]
| audio_format       = [[monaural|mono]]&lt;br /&gt;[[stereophonic sound|stereo]] (from Lesson 28)
| record_location    = BBC [[Paris Studio]], Lower Regent Street, London
| runtime            = 30 minutes
| creator            = 
| writer             = [[Andrew Marshall (writer)|Andrew Marshall]]&lt;br /&gt;[[David Renwick]]
| producer           = [[Simon Brett]] (series 1&amp;ndash;2)&lt;br /&gt;[[John Lloyd (writer)|John Lloyd]] (series 3&amp;ndash;4)&lt;br /&gt;[[David Hatch]] (series 5&amp;ndash;6)
| executive_producer = 
| starring           = [[Denise Coffey]] (series 1)&lt;br /&gt;[[Jo Kendall]] (series 2&amp;ndash;6)&lt;br /&gt;[[Chris Emmett]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Nigel Rees]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fred Harris (presenter)|Fred Harris]]
| narrated           = 
| opentheme          = 
| endtheme           = 
| country            = United Kingdom
| language           = English
| home_station       = [[BBC Radio 4]]
| syndicates         = [[BBC Radio 7]]
| first_aired        = 27 August 1976
| last_aired         = 15 November 1980
| num_series         = 6
| num_episodes       = 47
| other_names        = 
| website            = http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00c8x5n
| podcast            = 
}}
'''''The Burkiss Way''''' was a [[BBC Radio 4]] sketch [[comedy]] series broadcast from August 1976 to November 1980. It was written by [[Andrew Marshall (writer)|Andrew Marshall]] and [[David Renwick]], with additional material in early episodes by [[John Mason (writer)|John Mason]], [[Colin Bostock-Smith]], [[Douglas Adams]], [[John Lloyd (writer)|John Lloyd]] and others. The show starred [[Denise Coffey]] (series 1), [[Jo Kendall]] (series 2 onward), [[Chris Emmett]], [[Nigel Rees]] and [[Fred Harris (presenter)|Fred Harris]]. The series had three producers, announced as &quot;[[Simon Brett]] of [[Stepney]]&quot;, &quot;[[John Lloyd (writer)|John Lloyd]] of [[Europe]]&quot;, and &quot;[[David Hatch|David 'Hatch of the BBC' Hatch]]&quot;.

The series had its roots in two half-hour sketch shows entitled ''Half-Open University'' which Marshall and Renwick had written with Mason for [[BBC Radio 3|Radio 3]] as a parody of [[Open University]] programmes. The first, broadcast on 25 August 1975, spoofed [[science]], the second, on 1 December 1975, [[history]].

In a similar vein, ''The Burkiss Way'' was based on fictional [[correspondence course]]s by &quot;Professor Emil Burkiss&quot; entitled ''The Burkiss way to Dynamic Living'', and each episode or &quot;lesson&quot; had a number and a title based on one of the course's subjects: &quot;Lesson 1: Peel Bananas the Burkiss Way&quot;, &quot;Lesson 2: Pass Examinations the Burkiss Way&quot;, and so on. Although the numbers and titles were maintained throughout the run, a rapid change of style early in the second series saw the radio correspondence course become a hook rather than a narrative device, and it was mentioned only in passing. From here on the programme continued in a more obvious sketch format, though it was to use increasingly [[Monty Python|Pythonesque]] devices including surreal, [[Stream of consciousness|stream-of-consciousness]] linking, back-referencing and aggregation. Like the Pythons before them, the writers lampooned and tinkered with the medium on which the show was broadcast. Radio 4's continuity style was spoofed. Many later episodes had false endings, sometimes disguised as genuine continuity announcements. The opening and [[closing credits]] might be anywhere within the show. One show ran backwards from the closing to the opening credits, while another was allegedly dropped, broken and glued together with a tube of BBC coffee, resulting in a disjointed running order with many sketches beginning and ending in mid-sentence.

The show's humour was based on [[surrealism]] and literary and media [[parody|parodies]], sprinkled with puns. 

In the first series Chris Emmett made several appearances as a dirty old man; in episode 2, his character became [[Prime Minister]] thanks to the ''Burkiss Way''. From series 2 this voice became &quot;Eric Pode of [[Croydon]]&quot;, one of the show's few recurring characters and the only one not a parody of a real person. He is a man with unsavoury habits, inspired by ''[[Round the Horne]]'s'' [[Kenneth Williams|&quot;J. Peasemold Gruntfuttock&quot;]]. Each week he is interviewed by Fred Harris's character, who calls  him Mister Croydon, is disgusted by his habits and puns, and always remarks, &quot;isn't he a panic&quot;. This was one of the show's two catchphrases, the other being &quot;there will now be a short intermission&quot;. There was usually a series of linked sketches through each episode, the intermission sketches providing a break.

The fact that Douglas Adams had written for the show did not prevent his becoming a target for satire. He was parodied as Mister Different Adams whose catchphrase is &quot;I see comedy as a kind of...&quot; Adams's ''[[The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy]]'' was also a target; the 1979 Christmas show (''Eric Pode of Croydon's Easter Special'') closes with [[Peter Jones (actor)|Peter Jones]] as his [[HHGTTG]] character, ''The Book'', attempting to vilify [[BBC Radio 4]] for broadcasting ''The Burkiss Way'', but in typical fashion he is cut off in mid-sentence.

As time went on the show became increasingly surreal, and in several sketches the writers seemed to see how many strange ideas they could cram into a sketch. For example, one later episode contains a sketch about an [[amoeba (genus)|amoeba]] employed by the Department of Civil Service Staff Recruitment and Fisheries as a token [[Desmond Dekker|Desmond Dekker and the Aces]] but who keeps [[asexual reproduction|reproducing asexually]] by [[mitosis]] while singing a [[Lee Dorsey]] song.

''The Burkiss Way'' ran to 47 episodes in six series, but the episode and series numbering are derailed by &quot;Lesson 31&quot; and &quot;Lesson 32&quot;, which are a single episode masquerading as two half-episodes, the first of which ends series 3 and the second of which begins series 4. There are two &quot;Lesson 39&quot;s, both entitled &quot;Repeat Yourself the Burkiss Way&quot;, which have identical beginnings. The consequence is that &quot;Lesson 33&quot; through the first &quot;Lesson 39&quot; have lesson numbers that are one greater than the cumulative number; from the second &quot;Lesson 39&quot; onward the correct numbering is restored.

A sketch in Lesson 28 featuring unsubtle references to [[News anchor|newscaster]] [[Reginald Bosanquet]]'s [[alcoholism]] was cut following the first broadcast and was never reinstated. 

The last episode was cut short by 6 minutes on its first repeat transmission, on the instructions of the controller of BBC Radio 4. The missing material lampooned the grovelling approach of Radio 4 to the Queen Mother's 80th birthday celebrations. Repeats on BBC7 are still censored, although a restored version was broadcast in ''Celebrate The Burkiss Way'' on BBC7 on Saturday, 4 April 2009, (repeated most recently on BBC Radio4 Extra on December 3rd 2011).

The show gained a cult following and has several [[rerun]]s on [[BBC 7]]. Listeners complained about some omissions, which may indicate that episodes have been lost or [[Wiping (magnetic tape)|wiped]] &amp;ndash; notably Lesson 6 &amp;ndash; and some episodes have been broadcast in mono, suggesting the original stereo masters were wiped. Off-air recordings of the entire run survive in collectors' hands. (Lesson 6 is unique in being only 15 minutes).

A book, ''Bestseller! The Life and Death of Eric Pode of Croydon'', was published by Allen &amp; Unwin in 1981, loosely based on sketches from the series.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall A and Renwick D (1981), ''Bestseller: The Life and Death of Eric Pode of Croydon'', Allen &amp; Unwin, London, ISBN 0-04-827036-9&lt;/ref&gt;

A BBC Radio Collection in 1994 contained excerpts rather than complete episodes .

{{Listen|filename=Eric Von Contrick.ogg
|title=Burkiss Way, &quot;Eric Von Contrick&quot; sketch excerpt |description=An excerpt from Douglas Adams's Burkiss Way sketch, &quot;Eric Von Contrick&quot; excerpt}}

==Episode list==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Series!!Lesson!!Title!!scope=&quot;col&quot; width=&quot;140&quot;|First broadcast
|-
|rowspan=&quot;6&quot;|1||1||Peel Bananas the Burkiss Way||27 August 1976
|-
|2||Pass Examinations the Burkiss Way||3 September 1976
|-
|3||Escape from Prison the Burkiss Way&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;also known as &quot;[[The Burke Special|The Burkiss Special]] with [[James Burke (science historian)|James Burkiss]]&quot;&lt;/small&gt;||10 September 1976
|-
|4||Solve Murders the Burkiss Way||17 September 1976
|-
|5||Keep Unfit the Burkiss Way||24 September 1976
|-
|6||Win Awards the Burkiss Way||1 October 1976
|-
|rowspan=&quot;13&quot;|2||7||[[How to Win Friends and Influence People|Influence Friends and Win People]] the Burkiss Way||15 December 1976
|-
|8||Plan Christmas Schedules the Burkiss Way||22 December 1976
|-
|9||Gain Spiritual Fulfilment the Burkiss Way||29 December 1976
|-
|10||Govern Britain the Burkiss Way||5 January 1977
|-
|11||[[Journey to the Unknown|Journey into the Unknown]] the Burkiss Way||12 January 1977
|-
|12||Make Short Comedy Programmes the Burkiss Way||19 January 1977
|-
|13||Commemorate [[Silver Jubilee of Elizabeth II|Jubilee]]s the Burkiss Way||26 January 1977
|-
|14||Do You Know What the Burkiss Way||2 February 1977
|-
|15||[[:wiktionary:skive|Skive]] From School the Burkiss Way||9 February 1977
|-
|16||Get Off With [[Life imprisonment|Life]] the Burkiss Way||16 February 1977
|-
|17||[[This Is Your Life (UK TV series)|This Is Your Life]] the Burkiss Way||23 February 1977
|-
|18||Become a Rock Star the Burkiss Way||2 March 1977
|-
|19||Replace the Burkiss Way||9 March 1977
|-
|rowspan=&quot;12&quot;|3||20||Discover Gravity the Burkiss Way||15 November 1977
|-
|21||Get Cut Off the Bur...||22 November 1977
|-
|22||Succeed in Business the Burkiss Way||29 November 1977
|-
|23||Son of the Burkiss Way||6 December 1977
|-
|24||One Hour to the Burkiss Way||13 December 1977
|-
|25||Not to be Opened Until Christmas the Burkiss Way||20 December 1977
|-
|26||First Prize the Burkiss Way||27 December 1977
|-
|27||[[Around the World in Eighty Days|Around the World]] the Burkiss Way||3 January 1978
|-
|28||Ignore These Programme Titles the Burkiss Way||10 January 1978
|-
|29||Complain About the Burkiss Way||17 January 1978
|-
|30||Not the Burkiss Way||24 January 1978
|-
|31||[[Bruce Forsyth|Bruce]]'s Choice||rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|31 January 1978
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|4||32||Start New Series the Burkiss Way
|-
|33||The Last Burkiss Way||7 February 1978
|-
|34||The Next to Last Burkiss Way||14 February 1978
|-
|rowspan=&quot;7&quot;|5||35||Remember the Burkiss Way||2 April 1979
|-
|36||Rise from the Grave the Burkiss Way||9 April 1979
|-
|37||Is Britain Going the Burkiss Way? (part 1)||16 April 1979
|-
|38||Is Britain Going the Burkiss Way? (part 2)||23 April 1979
|-
|39||Repeat Yourself the Burkiss Way||30 April 1979
|-
|39||Repeat Yourself the Burkiss Way||7 May 1979 &lt;!--a different lesson with the same number and title--&gt;
|-
|40||Avoid Like the Plague the Burkiss Way||14 May 1979
|-
|Special||41||Eric Pode of Croydon's Easter Special||26 December 1979
|-
|rowspan=&quot;6&quot;|6||42||[[The Man from U.N.C.L.E.|The Man From]] the Burkiss Way||11 October 1980
|-
|43||Sack the Burkiss Way||18 October 1980
|-
|44||Love [[Big Brother (Nineteen Eighty-Four)|Big Brother]] the Burkiss Way||25 October 1980
|-
|45||Write extremely long titles with lots and lots of words in, like this, so that the ''[[Radio Times]]'' will have to allot more space than the measly half a centimetre of billing space we usually get and at least it'll look a bit more prominent on the page, although still nowhere near the 50 column inches they give to ''[[The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy (radio series)|The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy]]'' the Burkiss Way&lt;ref&gt;Wells, Paul, [http://www.radiolistings.co.uk/programmes/b/bu/burkiss_way__the.html &quot;The Burkiss Way&quot;], ''Radiolistings'', accessed 1 April 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;also known as &quot;Write Extremely Long Titles the Burkiss Way&quot;&lt;/small&gt;||1 November 1980
|-
|46||Settle Out Of Court the Burkiss Way||8 November 1980
|-
|47||Wave Goodbye to [[CBE]]s the Burkiss Way||15 November 1980
|-
|}

Lessons 31 and 32 were 15-minute episodes transmitted one immediately after the other.

The two lessons numbered 39 were different, but started exactly the same way. 

Sources:
&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Mike, [http://www.transdiffusion.org/radio/comedy/burkiss-compleat &quot;The Compleat Burkiss Way&quot;], ''Transdiffusion Broadcasting System'', accessed 30 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, Steven, [http://www.britishcomedy.org.uk/comedy/burkiss2.htm &quot;The Guide to the Burkiss Way&quot;], ''The British Comedy &amp; Drama Website'', accessed 30 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Lavalie, John, [http://epguides.com/BurkissWay/ &quot;The Burkiss Way (a Titles &amp; Air Date Guide)&quot;], ''epguides.com'', accessed 30 March 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[End of Part One]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Hitchhiker's}}
*[http://www.transdiffusion.org/rmc/comedy/burkiss.asp Radiomusications &amp;mdash; The Burkiss Way]
*[http://www.britishcomedy.org.uk/comedy/burkiss.htm How to write a web site the Burkiss Way]
{{David Jason}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Burkiss Way}}
[[Category:BBC radio comedy programmes]]
[[Category:Lost BBC episodes]]
[[Category:Radio sketch shows]]
[[Category:BBC Radio 4 programmes]]
[[Category:1976 radio programme debuts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
