<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="762849" ns="0" title="Stargate"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about||the film|Stargate (film)|the device itself|Stargate (device)|other uses}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2011}}
{{Infobox media franchise
|title=''Stargate''
|image caption=An activated [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]], the central object of the fictional Stargate universe, here depicted in the ''[[Stargate SG-1|SG-1]]'' television series.
|image=sg1stargatefront.jpg
|imagesize=260
|origin=''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' (film)
|creator=[[Roland Emmerich]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dean Devlin]]
|films=''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' &lt;br&gt;''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' &lt;br&gt;''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' '' 
&lt;!-- &quot;Stargate: Children of the Gods - Final Cut&quot; is not a separate movie, it's a Stargate SG-1 pilot episode director's cut edition on DVD like &quot;Stargate: director's cut&quot; edition , this section is only for original movies and shows, not for their future editions. DO NOT ADD &quot;Stargate: Children of the Gods - Final Cut&quot; IN THIS SECTION!--&gt;
|tv=''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' &lt;br&gt;''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' &lt;br&gt;''[[Stargate Universe]]''
|atv=''[[Stargate Infinity]]''
|games=
|vgs= ''[[Stargate: Resistance]]''
|books=[[Stargate literature|Literature]]
|comics=[[List of Stargate comics|Comics]]
|soundtracks=
|music=
}}
'''''Stargate''''' is a [[Adventure science fiction|adventure]] [[military science fiction]] [[Media franchise|franchise]], initially conceived by [[Roland Emmerich]] and [[Dean Devlin]]. The first film in the franchise was simply titled ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]''. It was originally released on October 28, 1994, by [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]] and [[Carolco]], and became a hit, grossing nearly $200&amp;nbsp;million (USD) worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=stargate.htm |title=Stargate (1994) |publisher=''''Box Office Mojo'' | accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/1994/0SGTE.php|title=Movie Stargate - Box Office Data, News, Cast Information - The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services, LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three years later, [[Brad Wright]] and [[Jonathan Glassner]] created a television series titled ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' as a sequel for the film.

In addition to film and television, the ''Stargate'' franchise has expanded into other media, including [[List of Stargate literature|books]], video games, and [[List of Stargate comics|comic books]]. These supplements to the film and television series have resulted in significant development of the show's fictional universe and mythology. In 2008, the films ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' and ''[[Stargate: Continuum|Continuum]]'' were released [[direct-to-DVD]], which in total grossed over $21&amp;nbsp;million in the United States. In 2002 the franchise's first animated series, ''[[Stargate Infinity]]'', began airing, which holds no canonicity in the franchise despite its ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''-inspired plot. In 2004, the TV series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' was released as a spin off from ''Stargate SG-1'' and a third series, ''[[Stargate Universe]]'', premiered on October 2, 2009. ''Stargate Universe'' was cancelled during its second season, leaving it on a cliffhanger. Then on April 17, 2011, Stargate producer Brad Wright announced that any plans for the continuation of the franchise had been cancelled indefinitely, ending 17 years of Stargate television production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Colvin&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |first=Chad | last=Colvin |title=SGU continuation, other movies dead — for now |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2011/04/wright-sgu-continuation-other-movies-dead-for-now/ |format= |agency=|work=GateWorld |date=April 17, 2011|accessdate=April 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Premise==
''Stargate'' productions center on the premise of a &quot;[[Stargate (device)|Stargate]]&quot;, a ring-shaped device that creates a [[wormhole]] enabling personal transportation to complementary devices located cosmic distances away. Under the control of the United States government, the Stargate discovered on Earth is kept a secret from the public. This allows for storylines to present [[suspension of disbelief|no contradiction]] between depicted events and [[reality]], an effect compounded by setting ''Stargate'' in the [[present day]] and depicting Earth accurately, with any unrealistic technology originating solely from alien civilizations. These extraterrestrial civilizations are typically more [[Industrialisation|pre-industrial]] than [[science|scientifically advanced]] and are almost always human. Together, this allows for stories predominated by human interaction in Earth-like environments, an unusual feature for a science fiction franchise focused on exploration of other worlds.

In the story, this is explained as being the result of alien interference in Earth's distant past—the concept influenced by the theories of [[Erich von Däniken]]. Many ancient [[mythology|mythologies]] are shown to be the result of aliens who had visited Earth posing as [[polytheism|gods]] by using their technology to give the impression of deific power. While some of these aliens had benign intentions, a race later known in ''Stargate SG-1'' as the &quot;[[Goa'uld]]&quot; used Stargates to move slaves from [[Ancient Egypt]] to other habitable planets, simultaneously being responsible for the Egyptian religion and culture. Following a successful rebellion, the Goa'uld fled Earth, and the Stargate was buried and forgotten until modern times, when the United States acquired it following an archaeological dig. With the rediscovery of the function of the Stargate, the galaxy becomes a source of knowledge as well as threats, and the attention of the Goa'uld is drawn once more to Earth.

==Franchise releases==
Due to multiple developers working separately and independently on the franchise over the years, the various ''Stargate'' productions are not entirely consistent with each other; and while no set of works forms an official [[canon (fiction)|canon]],&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworldbradwright&quot;&gt;{{Cite interview|subject=Brad Wright |interviewer= Darren Sumner |program=''GateWorld'' |title=Brad Wright Interview |city=''Chicago'' | language=| accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; the largest [[fanbase|following]] exists for the three live-action series.&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworldomnipedia&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=|url=http://www.gateworld.net/omnipedia/faq.shtml#5 |work=GateWorld |title=GateWorld Omnipedia | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through the work of various authors and developers, at least six separate story cycles can be discerned, some of which are continuations of the other ones (either endorsed or unendorsed by their predecessor).

===Media releases===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=99% border=&quot;1&quot;
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Film
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Release date
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Box office revenue
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Director
|-
! align=&quot;center&quot; | United States
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Foreign
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Total
|-
| ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|author=
|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/1994/0SGTE.php
|title=Stargate (1994)
|work=The Numbers
| language=
| accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| October 28, 1994
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $71,565,669
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $125,000,000
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $196,565,669
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Roland Emmerich]]
|-
| ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]''&lt;ref name=thenumberstaot&gt;{{Cite web
| url = http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2008/0SGAT.php
| title = Stargate - The Ark of Truth
| accessdate = May 5, 2008
| work=The Numbers
| publisher=Nash Information Services
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| March 11, 2008
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $13,166,110
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $20,354,000
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $33,520,110
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Robert C. Cooper]]
|-
| ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]''&lt;ref name=thenumbers&gt;{{Cite web
| url = http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2008/0SGCT.php
| title = Stargate - Continuum
| accessdate = May 5, 2009
| work=The Numbers
| publisher=Nash Information Services
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| July 29, 2008
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $8,055,900
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $17,872,384
| align=&quot;center&quot;| $25,728,284
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Martin Wood]]
|-
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Series
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Creator(s)
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Original Run
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Episodes
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Seasons
|-
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Debut
! align=&quot;center&quot; | End
|-
| ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;allmoviesg1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|author=Hal Erickson
|url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-sg-1-tv-series-159885
|title=Stargate SG-1 [TV Series]
|work=Allmovie
|accessdate=May 5, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Brad Wright|Wright]], [[Jonathan Glassner|Glassner]]
| align=&quot;center&quot;| July 27, 1997
| align=&quot;center&quot;| March 13, 2007
| align=&quot;center&quot;| 214
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[List of Stargate SG-1 episodes|10]]
|-
| ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;allmovieatlantis&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|author=Hal Erickson
|url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-atlantis-tv-series-312306
|title=Stargate Atlantis [TV Series]
|work=Allmovie
|accessdate=May 5, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Brad Wright|Wright]], [[Robert C. Cooper|Cooper]]
| align=&quot;center&quot;| July 16, 2004
| align=&quot;center&quot;| January 9, 2009
| align=&quot;center&quot;| 100
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[List of Stargate Atlantis episodes|5]]
|-
| ''[[Stargate Universe]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;allmovieuniverse&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|author=Cammila Albertson
|url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-universe-tv-series-478052
|title=Stargate Universe [TV Series]
|work=Allmovie
|accessdate=May 5, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Brad Wright|Wright]], [[Robert C. Cooper|Cooper]]
| align=&quot;center&quot;| October 2, 2009
| align=&quot;center&quot;| May 9, 2011
| align=&quot;center&quot;| 40
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[List of Stargate Universe episodes|2]]
|-
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Animated Series
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Creator(s)
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Original Run
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Episodes
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Seasons
|-
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Debut
! align=&quot;center&quot; | End
|-
| ''[[Stargate Infinity]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;allmovieinfinity&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|author=Hal Erickson
|url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-infinity-animated-tv-series-272518
|title=Stargate SG-1 [Animated TV Series]
|work=Allmovie
|accessdate=May 5, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot;| Lewald, Maliani
| align=&quot;center&quot;| September 14, 2002
| align=&quot;center&quot;| March 24, 2003
| align=&quot;center&quot;| 26
| align=&quot;center&quot;| [[List of Stargate Infinity episodes|1]]
|}

===Game releases===
{{main|Stargate games}}
*''[[Stargate: Resistance]]'' is an online, third-person shooter. It was released February 10, 2010. It has since been canceled due to contracts with MGM. It is still downloadable however.
*''[[Stargate Worlds]]'' was a Stargate-universe [[Massively multiplayer online role-playing game]] in development prior to its cancellation. The writers and producers of Stargate viewed Stargate Worlds as running side by side with the show in complete canon.
* ''[[Stargate SG-1: The Alliance]]'' was a computer game based on the Stargate universe, which was due to be released in late 2005, but was canceled.
* A [[Stargate TCG|Stargate Trading Card]] game was released in May 2007. It is available in both Online and Print forms. Designed by Sony Online Entertainment—who also run the Online version of the game—and published by Comic Images.
* A [[Stargate SG-1 (roleplaying game)|Stargate Role-Playing Game]] ([[Role-playing game|RPG]]) was produced by [[Alderac Entertainment Group|Alderac Entertainment]]. It was considered canon by both the publishers, and the staff of MGM.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alderac.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=6471 Posts by the Adelrac Entertainment staff on their boards]&lt;/ref&gt; However, when [[Sony]] bought [[MGM]], they lost the license to produce Stargate RPG products and the RPG license is currently unassigned.
* Two video games based on the film were released by [[Acclaim Entertainment]]: a 1995 [[Stargate (1995 video game)|eponymous]] side-scrolling platformer for the [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System]] (SNES) and [[Sega Genesis]], and a [[Tetris]]-like [[puzzle game]] for the [[Sega Game Gear]] and [[Nintendo Game Boy]].
*There are three simulator-style [[amusement park]] rides named ''[[Stargate SG-3000]]'' located at [[Six Flags Kentucky Kingdom]], [[Six Flags Great America]], and [[Six Flags Marine World]].
* A [[Stargate (pinball)|Stargate pinball game]] has been produced by [[Gottlieb]].
* Text and turn-based games were also created with the theme of the original universe of Stargate, although slightly different from &quot;reality&quot;, all made by Kingdom Games Ltd. Many versions of the same stargate universe have been created and still work in parallel. Among those are [http://gatewars.com/ Stargate Wars], [http://quantumgate.gatewars.com/index.php?r=sgw Quantum Gate], and [http://battlecorp.gatewars.com/index.php?r=origins BattleCorp]. On the forums related to the stargate games developed by Kingdom Games Ltd. a text-based [[roleplaying]] story was created, called the Enmity Saga. This story takes place in the starting universe of Stargate:SG1, mainly on unvisited planets.
*''[[Stargate: Asgard Heroes]]'' is an online browser mmorpg created by Evolution Vault. The initial release received some [http://osg1.com/2009/12/asgard-heroes-review/ poor reviews] which helped the development of the game and a better user interface.

==''Stargate'' franchise timeline==
{{Stargate timeline}}

==Theatrical films==
===''Stargate''===
{{main|Stargate (film)}}

In 1994, the [[military science fiction]] feature film ''Stargate'' was released; directed by [[Roland Emmerich]] and co-written by [[Dean Devlin]]. The film lays the foundation for all the Stargate productions that come after it, by explaining the notion, function, and history of the Stargate.

The theatrical version of the film begins with the unearthing of the Stargate in [[Giza]] in 1928. As of [[Present Day]] (i.e. 1994), the failing [[egyptologist]] [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] ([[James Spader]]) helps to make the Stargate work again by deciphering the [[hieroglyphs]] on the [[cover stone]]s of the Stargate, now housed at a military base in Creek Mountain, Colorado. A team led by Colonel [[Jack O'Neill|Jack O'Neil]] ([[Kurt Russell]]) is ordered to step through the Stargate and identify potential military threats on the other side. Jackson accompanies them to aid in translations to allow them to return home later. At their arrival, the team discovers a [[slave]] civilization serving an alien who is [[Ra (Stargate)|posing as the Egyptian god Ra]] ([[Jaye Davidson]]). He and his minion-gods have taken human form, commanding the slaves with brute force. With the help of the locals, O'Neil's team is eventually able to instigate a [[slave rebellion]], overwhelming Ra's forces. Ra escapes in his mothership, but O'Neil is able to [[Teleportation|teleport]] and detonate a nuclear warhead on-board Ra's ship in orbit. With Ra dead, the civilization can live in peace; O'Neil and his team return home through the Stargate, but Daniel Jackson stays on the planet with a young local woman named [[Sha'uri]].

===Other releases and future development {{anchor|Future productions}} ===
After Bill McCay had written a [[Stargate film novels|series of five novels]] continuing the story the original creators had envisioned, and despite the success of the ''Stargate'' television series, Dean Devlin stated in 2006 that &quot;he has struck a production deal with MGM and is developing the long-delayed sequel feature films that will pick up the story from the 1994 original&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;newstargatefilmfromorg&quot;/&gt; According to Devlin, two movie sequels would have picked up the story from the 1994 original, but not the mythology of the ''SG-1'' and ''Atlantis'' series, with the original stars Kurt Russell and James Spader. Devlin regretted giving MGM control over the franchise.&lt;ref name=&quot;newstargatefilmfromorg&quot;/&gt; The first movie already tapped into Egyptian mythology; the second one would have moved into other mythologies; and the third would tie all the mythologies together.&lt;ref name=&quot;ignrusselspader&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=|url=http://www.comingsoon.net/news/movienews.php?id=15537 |title=Devlin Announces Plans For Stargate Sequels |work=ComingSoon.net | language=| accessdate=April 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Stargate Atlantis'' producer Brad Wright said in 2002 that &quot;Devlin can wish to do a sequel to Stargate all he wants. MGM owns the rights, and I doubt very much that they'll ask him to do it. He knows better.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworldinterview&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=|url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/brad_wright.shtml |title=Interview: Brad Wright |work=GateWorld | language=| accessdate=April 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Plans for producing two sequels of the original film were announced by the original film's creator [[Dean Devlin]] at the 2006 [[San Diego Comic-Con]]. He has said he is currently in talks with MGM to produce four films and he would like two of them to be the final two films in his envisioned Stargate trilogy. In an interview with [[Sci Fi Wire]], Devlin says that should the sequels be made, he hopes to enlist [[Kurt Russell]] and [[James Spader]] in the two sequels. Both Russell and Spader have expressed interest, Devlin revealed. &quot;They've always said they wanted to do it. The irony is actually because it was 12 years ago that we made Stargate, [and] part two was actually supposed to take place about 12 years later. We were just going to kind of age them up as actors. So it actually works out really nicely.&quot; These sequels would bypass the 12 years of mythology created by ''SG-1'' and ''Atlantis'' if they are produced.&lt;ref name=&quot;newstargatefilmfromorg&quot;/&gt;

Dean Devlin has spoken out again on July 4, 2011 stating that he hasn't given up on the idea of sequels to his 1994 feature film.  He talked about the idea again in a new interview with Collider.  Devlin actually wrote it as a trilogy of movies, but was never able to do parts two and three.  His hope is, now that the series is starting to wind down, that perhaps it will be time to actually get to do parts two and three.

Devlin has said &quot;I think it'll change a little bit from our original idea since so many years have passed,&quot; he said. &quot;We wanted to explore the idea of how the Stargates were built originally, and where else in the universe they exist, and why they exist — and where else they exist on Earth. We had really planned out, as a trilogy of films, to allow this mythology to grow bigger and bigger.&quot;  &quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworldinterview2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=|url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2011/07/devlin-still-talking-stargate-movie-sequels/ |title=Interview: Darren |work=GateWorld | language=| accessdate=July 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stargate was directed by Roland Emmerich, and starred Kurt Russell as Colonel Jack O'Neil and James Spader as Dr. Daniel Jackson.  Devlin said he would absolutely want to use the same actors.  The movie was shot with a modest budget of $55 million, and released in October of 1994.

In the meantime, Lionsgate remains the major rights holder to the original film; this was due to the fact that its predecessor, Live Entertainment, owned home video rights to the [[Carolco Pictures]] library and had also owned international distribution rights, although Carolco itself was on the brink of bankruptcy when they produced this film.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

==Television==
===''SG-1''===
{{main|Stargate SG-1}}
[[File:Sg1-poster.jpg|thumb|upright|The original starring cast of ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''.]]
In 1997, [[Jonathan Glassner]] and [[Brad Wright]] co-developed ''Stargate SG-1'', a television series intended to continue the story laid down by the original film. Although new actors were cast, several roles from the film were reprised, including the main characters Daniel Jackson and Jack O'Neill (which was re-spelled to include an extra &quot;L&quot;). The [[Stargate Command]] setting was transferred from a fictional military facility located in Creek Mountain, to the [[Cheyenne Mountain]] military complex. Other variations and differences between the original film and ''SG-1'' mostly concern the location of the planet [[Abydos (Stargate)|Abydos]], the alien [[Ra (Stargate)|Ra]], the race of Ra's underlings ([[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]]), and Stargate travel.&lt;ref name=nytimes &gt;{{Cite web |author=Will Joyner |title=Through a Gate to the Far Side of the Universe: A TV Series |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D7163AF935A15754C0A961958260 |work=The New York Times |date=July 26, 1997 |accessdate=October 15, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A765597 |title=Stargate SG-1 – TV Shows |publisher=BBC | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The series debuted on [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] on July 27, 1997, and moved to the [[Syfy|Sci-Fi Channel]] after its fifth season.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/art-main.html?2001-08/14/12.30.sfc|title=Announcement from SciFi Channel|work=SciFi Wire | accessdate=May 5, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It starred [[Richard Dean Anderson]] (as [[Jack O'Neill|O'Neill]]) and [[Michael Shanks]] (as [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Jackson]]), alongside [[Amanda Tapping]], [[Christopher Judge]] and [[Don S. Davis]] playing the new characters [[Samantha Carter]], [[Teal'c]] and [[George Hammond (Stargate)|George Hammond]]. The cast remained fairly regular for most of ''SG-1'''s run, but experienced some changes. [[Michael Shanks]] left the show at the end of Season 5 and was replaced by [[Corin Nemec]] as [[Jonas Quinn]]. Shanks returned at the beginning of Season 7 and Nemec was written out. At the end of Season 7 [[Don S. Davis|Davis]] left the show and Anderson filled the gap he left in the story. Season 9 saw the departure of [[Richard Dean Anderson|Anderson]], but added new regulars [[Beau Bridges]] and [[Ben Browder]]. After a debut episode in Season 8, followed by appearances in eight episodes of Season 9, [[Claudia Black]]'s popular reception earned her a position in the regular cast in Season 10.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thescifiworld.net/interviews/claudia_black_01.htm|title=Interview – Vala joins ''SG-1'' regulars|work=SciFi World | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[MGM]] put an average of $1,400,000 into each episode of the show, and regards it as one of its most important franchises.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stargate 200&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/CA6332083.html|title=''Stargate 200'': 10 years of ''Stargate'' success|work=MultiChannel | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate'' was taken off air in 2007; however, two movies entitled ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' and ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' were made to tie up loose ends.

===''Atlantis''===
{{main|Stargate Atlantis}}
[[File:Sga poster 1.JPG|thumb|upright|The original starring cast of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''.]]
The ''Stargate Atlantis'' series follows the adventures of the &quot;Atlantis expedition&quot;, a combination of military forces and civilian scientists that travel to the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus galaxy]] in search of the Lost City of [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], left behind by the most powerful race known to ever have lived, referred to as the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]], also known as Lanteans and Alterrans. The finding of the city had been a plot arc for most of ''SG-1'''s Season 7, and the Ancients themselves had been a long-running facet of the ''SG-1'' setting. Arriving at the City, the expedition discover that the Pegasus galaxy is dominated by a terrible enemy known as the &quot;[[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]]&quot;, against whom they must defend themselves, despite being vastly outnumbered.

''Stargate Atlantis'' was a spin-off television series from ''Stargate SG-1''.  A new feature film was originally intended to transition the two series after the sixth season of ''SG-1''.  Later, ''SG-1'' was renewed for a seventh season, and the feature film was then planned to transition that season.  Finally, when ''SG-1'' was renewed for an eighth season, the intended film instead became the two-part [[season finale]] episode &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot;, and the setting of ''Stargate Atlantis'' was moved to the [[Pegasus Galaxy (Stargate)|Pegasus galaxy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | author=Sharon Gosling | title = Stargate Atlantis: The Official Companion Season 1 | origdate = | year = 2005 | origmonth = July | publisher=Titan Books | location = London | isbn = 1-84576-116-2 | pages = 10–14 | chapter = Watergate }}&lt;/ref&gt; This allowed the two shows to exist side-by-side within the same [[fictional universe]], and later the two shows even become interconnected. ''Atlantis'' was developed by most of the same people and in the same studios as ''SG-1''.

''Atlantis'' debuted on the Sci-Fi Channel on July 16, 2004, starring [[Joe Flanigan]] and [[Torri Higginson]] in the lead roles, with [[Rainbow Francks|Rainbow Sun Francks]], [[David Hewlett]], and [[Rachel Luttrell]] alongside. Hewlett and Higginson's characters had previously appeared in ''SG-1'' (though Higginson inherited the role from actress [[Jessica Steen]]). In ''Atlantis''' second season, [[Paul McGillion]] and [[Jason Momoa]] (replacing Francks) were added as regulars. At the end of the third season, Higginson and McGillion were removed as regulars, both serving recurring roles in the 4th season. Season 4 brought in Amanda Tapping, reprising her role as Samantha Carter from SG-1, and [[Jewel Staite]] in a recurring role. Tapping left the show for season five to concentrate on ''[[Sanctuary (web series)|Sanctuary]]'', and was replaced by [[Robert Picardo]], who reprised his role as [[Richard Woolsey]] from both ''SG-1'' and ''Atlantis''. However, in late summer 2008 it was announced that SciFi would not renew ''Atlantis''. The final episode aired on January 9, 2009.

===''Universe''===
[[File:SGUcast.jpg|thumb|The main cast of ''Universe''. The series has a much larger main cast than previous ''Stargate'' shows.]]
{{main|Stargate Universe}}
''[[Stargate Universe]]'' is the third live-action ''Stargate'' series, and premiered on October 2, 2009. The series was pitched to the [[Syfy|Sci Fi Channel]] in the fall of 2007, just before the writer's strike—which put a hold on the project. &quot;The pitch was received very well,&quot; according to Stargate Atlantis co-creator Brad Wright. Sci Fi Channel ordered ''Universe'' after announcing the cancellation of ''Stargate Atlantis''. Syfy announced on December 16, 2010 that they would not pick the show up for a third season. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.deadline.com/2010/12/syfy-cancels-stargate-universe|title=Syfy Cancels &quot;Stargate Universe&quot;|accessdate=December 16, 2010 |date=December 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The final episode aired May 9, 2011.

After the events of [[Stargate Atlantis]] research into the Stargates 9th and final chevron&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworld.net&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://gateworld.net/news/2008/08/istargate_universei_has_a_go.shtml | title=Stargate Universe Has A Go! | author=Darren Sumner | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; lead to an expedition being stranded across the universe on board an Ancient ship called &quot;Destiny&quot; which has been traveling through the universe unmanned for millions of years and is presently several billion light years from Earth. With no apparent way home, the show follows the crew as they struggle to survive on board Destiny. The show was intended to have a darker tone than its predecessors as well as delve more into the humanity of the characters and their relationships with each other while also remaining true to the Stargate mythology and continuity.

===''The Ark of Truth &amp; Continuum''===
{{main|Stargate: The Ark of Truth|Stargate: Continuum}}
''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' is a direct-to-DVD movie written and directed by [[Robert C. Cooper]]. The film is the conclusion of ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] arc, and picks up after the SG-1 series finale, but takes place before the fourth season of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''. ''The Ark of Truth'' was released as a [[Region 1]] DVD release on March 11, 2008. [[Sky One]] has broadcast the film on March 24, 2008, to be followed by the [[Region 2]] DVD release on April 28, 2008, with the [[Region 4]] DVD release on April 9, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/02/sky_one_to_air_iark_of_truthi_in.shtml |title=Sky One to air Ark of Truth in March |work=GateWorld |date=February 29, 2008 |date=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' is a direct-to-DVD movie written by [[Brad Wright]] and directed by [[Martin Wood]]. Some scenes for this movie were already shot at the end of March 2007, but the original start date was set for May 22 at Vancouver's Bridge Studios. The production budget was $7&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2007/08/tapping_discusses_isg-1i_movies.shtml |title=Tapping discusses SG-1 movies |date=August 9, 2007|work=GateWorld |accessdate=August 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movie was released on DVD and Blu-ray Disc on July 29, 2008. The Region 4 DVD was released on August 6, 2008 with the Region 2 DVD released on August 18, 2008;&lt;ref name=gw_nov2107&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2007/11/wright_icontinuumi_is_classic_is.shtml |title=Wright: Continuum is classic Stargate |publisher=GateWorld |date=November 21, 2007 |accessdate=November 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; followed by possible TV broadcasts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.playbackmag.com/articles/magazine/20070402/stargate.html |title=Stargate goes nuclear |date=April 2, 2007|work=Playback Magazine |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film is a time-travel adventure and is the second sequel to ''Stargate SG-1'', after ''Stargate: The Ark of Truth''.

===''Future feature film projects''===
Executive producer [[Brad Wright]] has revealed that &quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot;, ''Stargate SG-1'''s pilot episode, is being re-cut into a ''Stargate SG-1'' direct-to-DVD movie with brand new visual effects and scenes not previously included in the television version.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=Darren Sumner |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/04/special_edition_of_isg-1i_pilot_.shtml |title=Special edition of SG-1 pilot episode in the works |date= |work=GateWorld |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2009, MGM confirmed a third ''SG-1'' new film that Brad Wright had first announced in May 2008.&lt;ref name=gw_need_rda/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |first=Darren|last=Sumner |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2009/04/anderson-confirms-sgu-appearances/ |title=Anderson confirms SGU appearances |work=GateWorld |date=April 6, 2009 |accessdate=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wright will co-write the film with former ''Stargate Atlantis'' executive producer [[Carl Binder]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |first=Joseph|last=Mallozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2008/10/09/october-9-2008-actor-tyler-mcclendon-answers-your-questions/ |title=October 9, 2008: Actor Tyler McClendon Answers Your Questions |work=WordPress |date=October 9, 2008|accessdate=March 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Martin Wood will serve as director.&lt;ref name=jm_090102/&gt; According to Wright, the film would center on the Jack O'Neill character and will reunite as many of the ''SG-1'' cast as possible, depending on the cost of the film and actor availability.&lt;ref name=gw_need_rda&gt;{{Cite web |author=David Read |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/05/wright_stargate_movies_need_onei.shtml |title=Wright: Stargate movies need O'Neill |work=GateWorld |date=May 12, 2008 |accessdate=March 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michael Shanks (Daniel Jackson) has confirmed his and Richard Dean Anderson's participation.&lt;ref name=scifi_surprise&gt;{{Cite web |author=Ian Spelling |url=http://scifiwire.com/2009/01/michael-shanks-has-a-surprise-about-stargate-universe.php |title=Michael Shanks has a surprise about Stargate Universe |work=SciFi.com |date=January 26, 2009 |accessdate=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amanda Tapping confirmed her appearance in the third SG-1 film and the first ''Atlantis'' movie.&lt;ref name=cinemablend&gt;{{Cite web |author=Kelly West |url= http://www.cinemablend.com/television/Amanda-Tapping-Talks-About-Sanctuary-12460.html |title=Amanda Tapping Talks About Sanctuary |publisher=cinemablend.com |date=April 28, 2009 |accessdate=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Wright, the character of [[Vala Mal Doran]] will not appear in the film.&lt;ref name=jm_090102&gt;{{Cite web |author=Joseph Malozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/01/02/january-2-2009-brad-wright-answers-your-questions/ |title=Brad Wright Answers Your Questions |work=WordPress |date=January 2, 2009|accessdate=January 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The working title for the film, ''[[Stargate: Revolution]]'' was revealed by Joseph Mallozzi in his blog.&lt;ref name=jm_091111&gt;{{Cite web |author=Joseph Malozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/11/11/november-11-2009-tech-troubles-x-2-get-your-questions-in-for-adam-troy-castro-mailbag/ |title=Tech Troubles x 2! Get your questions in for Adam-Troy Castro! Mailbag! |work=WordPress |date=November 11, 2009|accessdate=November 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Sci-Fi and [[Joseph Mallozzi]], a ''Stargate Atlantis'' two hour [[direct-to-DVD]] movie has been given the go ahead after the series was cancelled at the end of its fifth season. More movies are expected to follow in the Atlantis series if the first movie is successful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/134413-_Stargate_Atlantis_Run_Ends_On_Season_5.php |title=‘Stargate Atlantis’ Run Ends On Season 5 |author=Kent Gibbons|work=MultiChannel News |date=|accessdate=May 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rumored working title for the film is ''[[Stargate Extinction]]''. By May 2009 the script for the film was finished.&lt;ref name=&quot;projecttwillight&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |first=Darren | last=Sumner |title=Mallozzi on Stargate Atlantis movie |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/08/mallozzi_on_istargate_atlantisi_.shtml |agency=|work=GateWorld |date=August 24, 2008|accessdate=May 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 17, 2011, Stargate writer and executive producer Brad Wright announced that the SGU movie is not going to happen, he also confirmed that the proposed Stargate SG-1 and Atlantis movies have been permanently shelved, along with another movie idea he had been trying to get a greenlight on, which would have combined and involved cast members of all three series, - at least for now.&lt;ref name=&quot;Colvin&quot;/&gt;

==''Infinity''==
[[File:StargateInfinity 2008-DVD-cover.jpg|thumb|upright|The Complete Series cover art]]
{{main|Stargate Infinity}}
''[[Stargate Infinity]]'' is an American [[Cartoon|animated]] science fiction television series created by Eric Lewald and Michael Maliani as a spin off from its [[sister show]], ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''. The [[story arc]] in ''Infinity'' is set 30 years into the future and follows [[Gus Bonner]] and his team. Bonner's team was created after he was framed for a crime he did not commit. He escaped from [[Stargate Command]] (SGC) after the hostile alien race Tlak'kahn attacked the SGC to find the chrysalis. Together with his team he escapes through the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] with the chrysalis. From that point forward they go from planet to planet until they find the evidence to clear their names while learning about the unique cultures in the [[galaxy]], so that they can one day return back to [[Earth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cjar.com/cj_shows_stargate.php|title=Stargate Infinity|work=[[Cookie Jar Group|Cookie Jar Entertainment]]|accessdate=June 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The story arc was never resolved because of low viewership ratings, the show was cancelled in 2003.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}

''Stargate Infinity'' premiered in September 2002 as part of [[4Kids Entertainment]]’s [[4Kids TV|FOX BOX]] Saturday morning line-up on [[Fox Broadcasting Company|FOX]] and went off the air in June 2003. Due to its lack of popularity the show is almost completely unrecognized. The series was cancelled before any of its [[story arc]]s could be resolved. The show was of [[low budget]], which was constantly noted by the media.&lt;ref name=regiontwo/&gt;&lt;ref name=shoutfactory/&gt; [[DIC Entertainment]] released a 4-episode DVD on October 7, 2003 in Region 1. [[MGM Home Entertainment]] released a five disc season [[box set]] on August 13, 2007 in region 2.&lt;ref name=regiontwo&gt;{{Cite web | publisher=Total Sci Fi Online |accessdate=June 7, 2009 |author=|url=http://totalscifionline.com/reviews/820-stargate-infinity-box-set |title=Stargate Infinity Box Set | date=August 20, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shout! Factory]], a company known for releasing cult animated series, acquired the rights to the show and released the entire series to DVD on May 13, 2008 in Region 1.&lt;ref name=shoutfactory&gt;{{Cite web |author=|url=http://www.scifimoviepage.com/dvd/stargate_infinity-dvd.html |title=Stargate Infinity: The Complete Series |work=Sci Fi Movie Page |date= |accessdate=June 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2009, there is yet to come a release of ''Stargate Infinity'' package in Region 4, namely Oceania and Latin America.&lt;ref name=regionfour&gt;{{Cite web |author=|url=http://www.ezydvd.com.au/item.zml/800114 |title=Stargate: Infinity - The Complete Series |work=EzyDVD |date= |accessdate=June 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The writers and producers of ''Stargate SG-1'', ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' and ''[[Stargate Universe]]'' and the main [[canon (fiction)|canon]] of the ''Stargate'' franchise were not involved with ''Infinity'', and neither MGM, the production teams nor the fans of ''Stargate'' consider ''Infinity'' to be an official part of the ''Stargate'' universe. According to ''Stargate SG-1'' co-creator [[Brad Wright]], the animated series should not be considered official ''Stargate'' [[canon (fiction)|canon]]. Commenting on it, he stated, &quot;I don't have a problem with it. I'm just not involved.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wright&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| author=Sumner, Darren | url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/brad_wright.shtml|title=Brad Wright (Interview) | year=2001 |work=GateWorld | accessdate=June 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
{{main|Stargate Fandom|List of awards and nominations received by Stargate SG-1|List of awards and nominations received by Stargate Atlantis|List of awards and nominations received by Stargate Universe}}

''Stargate'' took in $16.7&amp;nbsp;million on its opening weekend,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://boxofficemojo.com/alltime/weekends/month/?mo=10&amp;p=.htm| title=Top Opening Weekends By Month | date= | publisher=boxofficemojo.com | accessdate=April 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and received mixed reactions from critics; while it was panned by the likes of [[Roger Ebert]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author=Roger Ebert | url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19941028/REVIEWS/410280308/1023 | title=Stargate |work=Sun Times | accessdate=April 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; several positive reviews counterbalanced this leading to a score of 46% on [[Rotten Tomatoes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author=| url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/?name_order=asc | title=Stargate |work=Rotten Tomatoes | accessdate=April 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the film was originally intended as the first of a trilogy of films,&lt;ref name=&quot;newstargatefilmfromorg&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=Patrick Lee |url=http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/index.php?category=0&amp;id=37194 |title=Devlin Develops New ''Stargates'' |work=Sci-Fi.com | language=| accessdate=April 3, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Emmerich and Devlin ultimately moved on to produce ''[[Independence Day (film)|Independence Day]]'', and it was not until 2006 that Devlin showed renewed interest in developing sequels.&lt;ref name=&quot;ignrusselspader&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=Stax |url=http://movies.ign.com/articles/720/720070p1.html |title=Comic-Con 2006: Devlin on Stargate Sequels |work=IGN | language=| accessdate=April 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the intervening time, copyright-holder [[MGM]] succeeded the film with the television series ''Stargate SG-1'' without the input of Emmerich and Devlin.
[[File:Stargate SG-1 SG team Dragon Con 2008 cropped.jpg|thumb|Fans (called &quot;Gaters&quot;) posing as SG teams at Dragon Con in 2008]]
''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' has won the [[Saturn Award]] for ''Best Syndicated Television Series'' on numerous occasions, and its cast has won similar awards for acting.&lt;ref name=saturn&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.saturnawards.org/past.html |title=Saturn Awards – Past Award Winners |publisher=Saturn Awards |accessdate=March 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently it has received acclaim for its [[visual effect]]s, which increased in quality and realism as the show gained a larger budget.&lt;ref name=&quot;vfx&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/05/istargatei_grew_cutting_edge_vfx.shtml|title=Stargate grows cutting edge VFX industry|work=GateWorld | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 21, 2006, the [[Sci Fi Channel (United States)|Sci Fi Channel]] announced that it would not be renewing ''Stargate SG-1'' for an eleventh season after a series of poor performances in the [[Nielsen ratings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/index.php?category=2&amp;id=37607 |title=SG-1 Ends Run; Atlantis Back| work=scifi.com | date=August 22, 2006 |accessdate=May 5, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many fans were enraged at the news, even creating websites in reaction to exhibit their commitment to the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/08/fans_rally_savestargatesg1.com.shtml |title=Fans Rally: SaveStargateSG1 | work=GateWorld | date=|accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spokesmen for the production have said all options for the continuation of ''SG-1'' are being considered, including complete digital broadcasting.&lt;ref name=&quot;sg1 future&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/CA6366152.html|title=MGM Insists ''Stargate'' Won't Shut|work=MultiChannel News | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Executive producer [[Robert C. Cooper]] told the fansite [[GateWorld]] exclusively that he was working to continue ''SG-1''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/08/cooper_isg-1i_will_go_on.shtml|title=Cooper: ''SG-1'' will go on|work=GateWorld | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, no network or company has ordered new episodes of ''SG-1'', so the show is on hold until a new buyer can be found. However, SciFi has attempted to block other networks from taking up the show, citing its original exclusive contract with MGM.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/08/mgm_considers_isg-1is_future.shtml|title=MGM Considers ''Stargate SG-1'' Future|work=GateWorld | accessdate=May 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;'' [[Stargate Atlantis]]'' has won several awards for its actors, visual effects and directors, including a [[WorldFest-Houston International Film Festival|WorldFest]] Platinum Award for [[David Winning]]'s direction of an early Season 1 episode.&lt;ref name=&quot;dwinning&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.davidwinning.com/awards.html |title=Groundstar Entertainment Presents David Winning - Filmmaker - Director |publisher=Groundstar |accessdate=April 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Atlantis'' proved to be equally as successful as ''SG-1'', with Nielsen ratings and viewership. The ''Stargate'' franchise in 2009 won a Constellation Award in the category of Outstanding Canadian Contribution to Science Fiction Film or Television in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://constellations.tcon.ca/|title=The Constellation Awards |publisher=Constellation Awards |accessdate=September 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The average viewership to ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Atlantis'' was around 10&amp;nbsp;million a week worldwide. According to ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Atlantis'' co-creator [[Brad Wright]], the show is very popular in Great Britain, Germany, France and Australia, but with a steadily declining viewership in [[homeland]] Canada. It was estimated that around 30&amp;nbsp;million ''Stargate'' DVDs were sold worldwide in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |author=Andrews, Mark |url=http://www2.canada.com/vancouversun/news/business/story.html?id=8cadeca7-c0a8-403f-b6d6-7c1f728a9aa7&amp;k=25558&amp;p=2 |title=Stargate's success is out of this world |work=The Vancouver Sun |accessdate=April 8, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DVD release of ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' in the US earned MGM/Fox US $1.59&amp;nbsp;million in rentals in the first week after the release, and another US $1.38&amp;nbsp;million in rentals in the second week. In its third week it earned US $1.19&amp;nbsp;million in rentals totaling US $4.16&amp;nbsp;million . The DVD has also earned US $9.0&amp;nbsp;million in sales.&lt;ref name=thenumberstaot/&gt; ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' would go on to gross over $8&amp;nbsp;million United States dollars in the United States.&lt;ref name=thenumbers/&gt; The film sparked mostly positive reviews with movie critics.&lt;ref name=&quot;skye&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://tv.sky.com/preview-stargate-continuum |title=Preview: Stargate Continuum |work=Sky Entertainment |accessdate=April 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scfico&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| author=Nix | url=http://www.scificool.com/stargate-continuum-2008-movie-review/ |title=Stargate: Continuum (2008) Movie Review |work=Sci Fi Cool |accessdate=April 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| author=Nix | url=http://bluray.ign.com/articles/895/895143p1.html |title=Stargate: Continuum Blu-ray Review |work=IGN |accessdate=April 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A third ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' movie was planned to follow ''Continuum'' but the third movie was put on hold with any other future Stargate movies; the film will center around the character of [[Jack O'Neill]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2009/04/third-sg-1-movie-has-a-go/ |title=Third SG1 movie has a go |publisher=GateWorld |date=|accessdate=April 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Literature==
{{main|Stargate literature|List of Stargate comics|List of Stargate audiobooks}}
There are three series of novels based on the Stargate franchise, one based on the original ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' film and two based in the ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' and ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' television shows. A series of books written by [[Bill McCay]] were published from 1995 to 1999 that were unofficial sequels to the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=|url=http://www.fantasticfiction.co.uk/m/bill-mccay/ |title=Bill McCay |date= |work=Fantasy Fiction |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; These were produced by consulting the original notes made by [[Dean Devlin]] and [[Roland Emmerich]], in an attempt to envision where the film &quot;would have gone&quot;. Neither party has commented on whether McCay's interpretation was correct. Despite the fact that he attempted to remain close to the original vision, the subsequent television series ''Stargate SG-1'' (which began under an entirely independent development) developed the story along different lines, making no attempt to reconcile the plot lines of the books. This marked the first major branching of the franchise.

Later, from 1999 to 2001, [[New American Library|ROC]] published four novels based in ''Stargate SG-1'' written by [[Ashley McConnell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=|url=http://www.fantasticfiction.co.uk/m/ashley-mcconnell/stargate-sg1.htm |title=SG-1 by Ashley McConnell |date= |work=Fantasy Fiction |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, UK-based [[Fandemonium (publisher)|Fandemonium Press]] started a new series of licensed tie-in novels based on ''Stargate SG-1''. Due to the conflict with ROC's license, these books were available in Australia, Canada, New Zealand, South Africa and the UK, but not in the US. Fandemonium books became available in the US in 2006. The official ''Stargate Magazine'', produced by Titan Publishing, began publishing short stories written by Fandemonium authors in their 8th issue. The stories alternate between both ''SG-1'' and ''Atlantis''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=|url=http://titanmagazines.com/app?service=external/Product&amp;sp=l12 |title=Stargate Magazine |date= |work=Titan Magazines |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A series of [[comic book]]s, based on ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Stargate Atlantis'', began to be published by [[Avatar Press]] in 2003. Five have been published to date, with stories by James Anthony and artwork by Jorge Correa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=|url=http://www.avatarpress.com/stargate/ |title=Stargate |date= |work=Avatar Press |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2008 it was announced that [[Big Finish Productions]] would release officially-licensed [[audiobooks]] featuring members of the cast reading new stories. The first two stories, available on CD and digital download, are ''[[Gift of the Gods]]'' read by [[Michael Shanks]] and ''[[A Necessary Evil (Stargate audio)|A Necessary Evil]]'' read by [[Torri Higginson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=|url=http://www.bigfinish.com/Stargate-SG-1-and-Atlantis |title=Stargate SG-1 and Atlantis |date= |work=Big Finish Production |accessdate=July 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|3}}

==External links==
&lt;!--WARNING; PLEASE READ BEFORE EDITING; do not link the MGM Stargate Video site, as it will be deleted should someone add it again.--&gt;
* [http://www.scifi.com/stargate/ SyFy Channel ''Stargate'' Website]
* [http://www.mgm.com/title_title.do?title_star=STARGATE MGM ''Stargate'' Film]
* [http://stargate.mgm.com Official Stargate site] at [[MGM|mgm.com]]
* [http://www.bigfinish.com/Stargate-SG-1-and-Atlantis/ ''Stargate Talking Books'' Official Site]
* [http://www.stargateworlds.com/ Stargate Worlds Homepage]
* [http://stargate.wikia.com/wiki/Stargate_Wiki Stargate Wikia]
* [http://collider.com/ ''Official Collider Site'' - For the latest movie news, movie reviews, movie trailers, movie interviews, TV news, video interviews, images, posters, and movie clips ...]

{{Stargate}}

[[Category:Stargate| ]]
[[Category:Ancient Egypt in fiction|Stargate]]
[[Category:Films about language and translation]]
[[Category:Science fiction films]]
[[Category:Wormholes in fiction]]
[[Category:Media franchises]]
[[Category:Television franchises]]

[[ar:ستارغيت]]
[[bg:Старгейт]]
[[ca:Stargate]]
[[es:Stargate]]
[[eo:Stargate]]
[[fr:Stargate]]
[[ga:Stargate]]
[[ko:스타게이트]]
[[it:Stargate (franchise)]]
[[he:סטארגייט]]
[[ka:ვარსკვლავთკარიბჭე]]
[[la:Stargate]]
[[lv:Zvaigžņu Vārti]]
[[lt:Žvaigždžių vartai]]
[[nl:Stargate (franchise)]]
[[ja:スターゲイト]]
[[no:Stargate (science fiction)]]
[[pl:Gwiezdne wrota]]
[[pt:Stargate]]
[[ro:Stargate]]
[[ru:Звёздные врата]]
[[sl:Zvezdna vrata]]
[[sr:Звездана капија]]
[[sh:Stargate]]
[[sv:Stargate]]
[[tr:Yıldız Geçidi]]
[[uk:Зоряна Брама]]
[[zh:星际之门]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
