<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="764618" ns="0" title="Jim Plunkett"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about||the Irish writer|James Plunkett|the AFL player|Jim Plunkett (Australian footballer)}}
{{refimprove|date=November 2009}}
{{Infobox NFL player
|image=
|caption = 
|position=[[Quarterback]]
|number=16
|birth_date={{birth date and age|1947|12|5}}
|birth_place=[[San Jose, California]]
|highschool=[[William C. Overfelt High School|William C. Overfelt]], [[James Lick High School|James Lick]]
|heightft=6
|heightin=3
|weight=220
|debutyear=1971
|debutteam=New England Patriots
|finalyear=1986
|finalteam=Los Angeles Raiders
|draftyear=1971
|draftround=1
|draftpick=1
|college=[[Stanford University|Stanford]]
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[New England Patriots]] ([[1971 NFL season|1971]]-[[1975 NFL season|1975]])
* [[San Francisco 49ers]] ([[1976 NFL season|1976]]-[[1977 NFL season|1977]])
* [[Oakland Raiders|Oakland/L.A. Raiders]] ([[1978 NFL season|1978]]-[[1986 NFL season|1986]])
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Super Bowl XV]] MVP
* 1971 [[UPI AFL-AFC Rookie of the Year]]
* 1980 [[NFL Comeback Player of the Year]]
* 2&amp;times; [[Super Bowl]] champion ([[Super Bowl XV|XV]], [[Super Bowl XVIII|XVIII]])
|stat1label=[[Touchdown|TD]]-[[Interception (football)|INT]]
|stat1value=164-198
|stat2label=Yards
|stat2value=25,882
|stat3label=[[Passer rating|QB Rating]]
|stat3value=67.5
|nfl=PLU604056
|CollegeHOF=60027
}}
'''James William &quot;Jim&quot; Plunkett''' (born December 5, 1947) is a former [[American football]] [[quarterback]] who played college football for [[Stanford University]], where he won the [[Heisman Trophy]], and professionally for three [[National Football League]] teams: the [[New England Patriots]], [[San Francisco 49ers]] and [[Oakland Raiders|Oakland/Los Angeles Raiders]].  He led the Raiders to two [[Super Bowl]] victories ([[Super Bowl XV|XV]] and [[Super Bowl XVIII|XVIII]]). He is the only eligible quarterback to start (and win) two Super Bowls without being inducted into the [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]] in [[Canton, Ohio]].

==Biography==
Smith was born to [[Mexican American]] parents with an Irish-German great-grandfather on his paternal side. Plunkett's father was a news vendor afflicted with progressive blindness, who had to support his blind wife along with their three children.&lt;ref name=&quot;hero&quot;&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,877161-2,00.html Saturday's Hero]&lt;/ref&gt; In an effort to aid the family's financial situation, Plunkett worked a series of odd jobs while growing up, including serving as a gas station attendant, grocery store clerk and as a laborer on construction sites. In an acknowledgement of his Mexican roots, Plunkett chose the fictional character of [[Zorro]] as his hero{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}.

Jim went to [[William C. Overfelt High School]] in the 9th and 10th grades and then transferred and graduated from [[James Lick High School]] both of which are located in [[San Jose, California|East San Jose, California]]. Plunkett showed his talent for tossing the football by winning a throwing contest at the age of 14 with a heave of over 60 yards.  Once he arrived at the school, he played quarterback and defensive end for the football team, with his athletic ability also helping him compete in [[basketball]], [[baseball]], [[Track and field athletics|track]] and [[wrestling]].  He is on their hall of fame wall in the James Lick gymnasium.

===College===
Upon entering [[Stanford University]], Smith endured a rough freshman campaign after being weakened by a thyroid operation.  His performance originally caused head coach [[John Ralston (coach)|John Ralston]] to switch him to defensive end, but Plunkett was adamant in remaining at quarterback, throwing 500 to 1,000 passes every day to polish his arm. He earned the opportunity to start in 1968, and in his first game, completed ten of thirteen passes for 277 yards and four touchdowns, and never relinquished his hold on the starting spot.  Plunkett's arrival ushered in an era of wide-open passing, pro-style offenses in the [[Pacific-10 Conference|Pac-8]], a trend that has continued to the present.

His successful junior campaign saw him set league records for touchdown passes (20), passing yards (2,673) and total offense (2,786). This display of offensive firepower led [[Washington State University|Washington State]] coach Jim Sweeney to call Plunkett &quot;The best college football player I've ever seen.&quot; After his junior year, Plunkett became eligible to enter the [[NFL draft]], which would have given him a chance to earn a large roster bonus for himself and his mother. He passed up the chance at a paycheck, however, so that he could set a good example to the [[chicano]] youth he had tutored.  In his senior year,1970, he led Stanford to their first [[Rose Bowl game|Rose Bowl]] appearance since 1952, a game that ended with a 27-17 Stanford victory over the favored [[Ohio State Buckeyes]].

With eighteen passing and three rushing touchdowns added to his 2,715 passing yards on the year (which broke his own conference record), Plunkett was awarded the 1970 [[Heisman Trophy]], the award given annually to the top college football player in the country. Though he had set so many records on the season, 1970 had been the &quot;Year of the Quarterback,&quot; and Plunkett beat out [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame's]] [[Joe Theismann]] and [[Archie Manning]] of [[Ole Miss]] to win the award. He was the first [[Hispanics in the United States|Latino]] to win the Heisman Trophy. Aside from the Heisman, he captured the [[Maxwell Award]] for the nation's best quarterback and was named player of the year by [[United Press International]], ''[[The Sporting News]]'', and [[SPORT magazine|''SPORT'' magazine]]. In addition, the American College Football Coaches Association designated him as their Offensive Player of the Year.  He became the second mulitiple recipient of the [[W.J. Voit Memorial Trophy]], awarded each year to the outstanding football player on the Pacific Coast.  Plunkett received the Voit Trophy in both 1969 and 1970.

===NFL Career===

[[UCLA]] coach [[Tommy Prothro]] had called Plunkett the &quot;best pro quarterback prospect I've ever seen&quot;, echoing Sweeney's words from the year prior. His excellent arm strength and precision made him attractive to pro teams that relied much more heavily on the passing game than most college teams of the late 1960s. In 1971, he was drafted with the first overall pick in the NFL draft by the [[New England Patriots]] (the team was still known as the Boston Patriots at the time of the draft; the name change to New England did not become official until March 21 of that year). Plunkett owns the distinction of being the only player of Hispanic heritage to be drafted with the first overall pick in the NFL draft. The Patriots finished the season at 6-8, fourth place in the [[AFC East]]. Plunkett's first game was a 20-6 victory over the [[Oakland Raiders]], the Patriots' first regular-season contest at [[Foxboro Stadium|Schaefer Stadium]]. New England also influenced the AFC East championship race, as Plunkett's 88-yard fourth-quarter touchdown pass to former Stanford teammate [[Randy Vataha]] on the final day of the season dropped the [[History of the Indianapolis Colts|Baltimore Colts]] to a 10-4-0 record and into second place in the division behind the 10-3-1 [[Miami Dolphins]]. Two weeks before the Patriots defeated the Colts, Plunkett engineered a 34-13 victory over the Dolphins.

Plunkett's touchdowns dropped and his interceptions rose in the following seasons, however, and he struggled with injuries and a shaky offensive line for the rest of his tenure in New England. By 1975, the Patriots drafted [[Steve Grogan]], who would become a fixture with the club for 16 seasons, and under the leadership of coach [[Chuck Fairbanks]], New England's offense became more run-oriented, led by [[Sam Cunningham]].

Prior to the [[1976 NFL Draft]], Plunkett was traded to the [[San Francisco 49ers]] in exchange for QB Tom Owen, two first round picks in 1976, and a first and second round pick in [[1977 NFL Draft|1977]]. He led the team to a 6-1 start before faltering to an 8-6 record.  After a 5-9 season in 1977, the 49ers released him during the 1978 preseason.

Plunkett then joined the [[Oakland Raiders]] in 1978, serving in a reserve capacity over the next two years, throwing no passes in 1978 and just 15 passes in 1979. However, five weeks into the [[1980 NFL season]], his career took a major turn when starting QB [[Dan Pastorini]] fractured his leg in a game against the [[Kansas City Chiefs]]. The 33-year-old Plunkett came off the bench to relieve Pastorini, throwing five interceptions in a 31-17 loss. The Raiders, however, believing that [[Marc Wilson (American football)|Marc Wilson]] did not have the experience they wanted, called on Plunkett to start for the remainder of the year. In his first game as a starter, he completed eleven of fourteen passes with a touchdown and no interceptions. Plunkett guided Oakland to nine victories in eleven games and a playoff berth as a [[Wild card (sports)|wild card]]. Plunkett led the Raiders to four playoff victories, including the first-ever victory by a wild card team in the [[Super Bowl]], defeating the [[Philadelphia Eagles]] 27–10 in [[Super Bowl XV]]. Throwing for 261 yards and three touchdowns, Plunkett was named the game's [[Most Valuable Player|MVP]]; subsequently, Plunkett has the distinction of being the first [[minority group|minority]] to quarterback a team to a Super Bowl victory and the only Hispanic to be named Super Bowl MVP. In addition to this, he became the second of four players to win the Heisman Trophy and Super Bowl MVP, [[Roger Staubach]] before him, and [[Marcus Allen]] and [[Desmond Howard]] after him.

After returning to the backup role in 1983, Plunkett again assumed starting duties, this time after an injury to Wilson. The Los Angeles Raiders advanced to [[Super Bowl XVIII]], where they defeated the [[Washington Redskins]], 38-9. Plunkett completed 16 of 25 passes for 172 yards and a touchdown in the game.

Plunkett spent most of his last three seasons either injured or as a backup. He retired after the 1986 season, and is currently the fourth-leading passer in Raiders history. He currently holds the [[Oakland Raiders]] record, as well as tied for the league record, for the longest career pass. The [[99-yard pass play]] occurred during an October 2nd, 1983 game against the [[Washington Redskins]].

Currently, Plunkett does a post-game radio show of Raiders games, and is a co-host of several Raiders TV shows. A feature film based on his life is in the works.

==See also==
*[[Bay Area Sports Hall of Fame]]

==References==
*Jim Plunkett Story: The Saga of a Man Who Came Back by Dave Newhouse
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.nfl.com/players/jimplunkett/profile?id=PLU604056 Profile] at NFL.com
* {{cfbhof|id=60027|name=Jim Plunkett}}
* {{Heisman|id=j-plunkett70|name=Jim Plunkett}}
* {{pro-football-reference|id=P/PlunJi00|name=Jim Plunkett}}

{{navboxes
|list=
{{s-start}}
{{s-ach}}
{{succession box | title=[[National Football League|NFL]] [[Super Bowl MVP]]s | before=[[Terry Bradshaw]] | years=[[Super Bowl XV]], 1981 | after=[[Joe Montana]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of NFL first overall draft choices|First Overall Pick in NFL Draft]] | before=[[Terry Bradshaw]] | years=1971 | after=[[Walt Patulski]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[NFL Comeback Player of the Year Award]]| before=[[Larry Csonka]]| years=1980| after=[[Ken Anderson (quarterback)|Ken Anderson]]}}
{{s-sports}}
{{succession box | title=Stanford Starting Quarterbacks | before=[[Chuck Williams (football)|Chuck Williams]]| years=1968-1970| after=[[Don Bunce]]}}
{{succession box | title=New England Patriots Starting Quarterbacks | before=[[Joe Kapp]]| years=1971-1975| after=[[Steve Grogan]]}}
{{succession box | title=San Francisco 49ers Starting Quarterbacks | before=[[Steve Spurrier]]| years=1976-1977| after=[[Steve DeBerg]]}}
{{succession box | title=Oakland/Los Angeles Raiders Starting Quarterbacks | before=[[Dan Pastorini]]| years=1980-1983| after=[[Marc Wilson (American football)|Marc Wilson]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{Heisman Winners}}
{{Maxwell Award Winners}}
{{Walter Camp Award}}{{Chic Harley Award}}{{Sporting News College Football Player of the Year}}{{UPI College Football Player of the Year}}{{Walter Camp Alumni of the Year}}
{{NFL NumberOne Draft Picks}}
{{1971 NFL Draft}}
{{PatriotsFirstPick}}
{{Super Bowl XV}}
{{Super Bowl XVIII}}
{{Super Bowl MVPs}}
{{NFL Comeback Players of the Year}}
{{PatriotsQuarterback}}
{{49ersQuarterbacks}}
{{RaidersQuarterbacks}}
{{StanfordQuarterbacks}}
}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Plunkett, Jim
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =December 5, 1947
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[San Jose, California]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Plunkett, Jim}}
[[Category:1947 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Heisman Trophy winners]]
[[Category:Los Angeles Raiders players]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:American sportspeople of Mexican descent]]
[[Category:National Football League first overall draft picks]]
[[Category:American football quarterbacks]]
[[Category:New England Patriots players]]
[[Category:Oakland Raiders players]]
[[Category:Sportspeople from San Jose, California]]
[[Category:San Francisco 49ers players]]
[[Category:Stanford Cardinal football players]]
[[Category:Super Bowl MVPs]]

[[de:Jim Plunkett]]
[[pt:Jim Plunkett]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
