<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7674023" ns="0" title="Employee monitoring software"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=September 2009}}

'''Employee monitoring software''' is a means of [[employee monitoring]], and allows company administrators to monitor and supervise all their employee computers from a central location. It is normally [[deploy]]ed over a business network and allows for easy centralized log viewing via one central networked PC.
== Related techniques ==
;Keystroke monitoring: Log all keystrokes along with the window name they are typed. See also [[Keystroke logging]], [[Hardware keylogger]]
;[[Email]]s sent and received logging
;Events timeline logging: Log all events employees performed and view them in an organized listing.
;Website activity: Log all websites visited by the popular browsers. See also [[Web analytics]], [[Web log analysis software]]
;Application usage: Monitor and log all applications ran.
;Documents opened: Record documents and files opened and viewed.
;Attentiveness monitoring: Display a popup on the employee's workstation with a set amount to time to click it.

== Optional functions ==
* [[Remote Desktop]] Viewing - Grab [[screenshot]]s of the remote computer's desktop.
* Remote System Information Viewing - View a listing of various system information for the remote PC.
* Remote Internet Connections Viewing - View a list of the current Internet connections on the remote machine.
* Remote Recent Document History Viewing
* Remote Message Display
* Remote System Lockdown Control

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== See also ==
*[[Malware]]
*[[Spyware]]
*[[Spy software]]
*[[Trojan horse (computing)|Trojan horse]]
*[[Computer surveillance]]
*[[Job satisfaction]]

==External links==
*[http://www.brett-tech.com/Company/ReadArticle.aspx?LinkId=5Jan07 Should You Monitor Your Employees' Web Use?]
*[http://www.jobsite.co.uk/career/advice/big_brother.html Is Big Brother watching you?]


{{DEFAULTSORT:Employee Monitoring Software}}
[[Category:Business software]]
[[Category:Computer security software]]


{{Business-software-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
