<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7679254" ns="0" title="Protection of Person and Property Act 1881"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=June 2008}}
[[Image:William Ewart Gladstone by Rupert Potter.jpg|thumb|right|The 1881 Act was introduced by [[William Ewart Gladstone]].]]
The '''Protection of Person and Property Act 1881''' was  one of more than 100 Coercion Acts [[List of Acts of the Parliament of the United Kingdom, 1801–1819|passed by the Parliament]] of [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland]] between 1801 and 1922, in an attempt to establish law and order in [[Ireland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hks.harvard.edu/var/ezp_site/storage/fckeditor/file/pdfs/centers-programs/centers/taubman/working_papers/donohue_00_civillib.pdf|format=PDF|title=Civil Liberties, Terrorism, and Liberal Democracy: Lessons from the United Kingdom|accessdate=2008-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1881 Act was passed by [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|parliament]] &lt;ref&gt;&quot;United Kingdom.&quot;Encyclopædia Britannica. 2008. [[Encyclopædia Britannica 2006 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]] 	10 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and introduced by [[William Ewart Gladstone|Gladstone]]. It allowed for persons to be [[imprisoned]] without trial.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/gladstone_and_ireland.htm ::Gladstone and Ireland::&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 October 1881, the Act was used to arrest  [[Charles Stewart Parnell|Charles Parnell]] &lt;ref name=Times1&gt;[[The Times]], Arrest Of Mr. Parnell, 14 October 1881&lt;/ref&gt; after his newspaper, the ''United Ireland'', had attacked the Land Act:&lt;ref name=&quot;Hickey&quot;&gt;&quot;Hickey&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

:''An Act for the better Protection of Person and Property in Ireland''

:''Copy warrant to arrest

''Whereas by an order of the [[Lord Lieutenant of Ireland|Lord-Lieutenant]]... by virtue of the Act... and of every power and authority in this behalf... the county of the city of Dublin should become a prescribed district and Charles Stewart Parnell ...suspected... guilty, as [[Principal (criminal law)|principal]], of... inciting other[s] to intimidate divers persons to abstain from...namely to pay rents lawfully due...Command... to arrest said Charles Stewart Parnell...and lodge him in [[Kilmainham]]...during the continuance of the said Act unless sooner discharged or tried by our direction.&lt;ref name=Times1/&gt;

== Coercion Act 1881==
[[File:William Edward Forster by Henry Tanworth Wells.jpg|thumb|upright|William Edward Forster by Henry Tanworth Wells.&lt;ref&gt;National Portrait Gallery, London, accessed September 2009&lt;/ref&gt;]]
On [[William Ewart Gladstone|Gladstone]]'s return to office in 1880, [[William Edward Forster]] was made [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]]. He carried the [[Compensation for Disturbance Bill]] through the Commons, only to see it thrown out in the Lords. On 24 January 1881, he introduced a new Coercion Bill in the House of Commons, to deal with the growth of the [[Irish National Land League]].  Despite a 41-hour long [[fillibuster]] in the House by the [[Irish Parliamentary Party]], the bill passed, among its provisions being one enabling the British government in Ireland to arrest without trial persons &quot;reasonably suspected&quot; of crime and conspiracy.

==Coercion legislation in Ireland==
Over 100 such acts were passed, some of the more notable of which were &quot;An Act for the more effectual Suppression of Local Disturbances and Dangerous Associations in Ireland&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;1833, 3 Will. IV, c. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The Protection of Life and Property in Certain Parts of Ireland Act&quot;,&lt;ref&gt; 1871, 34 &amp; 35 Vict., c. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;Protection of Person and Property Act 1881&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;44 &amp; 45 Vict., c. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

An Irish Coercion Bill was proposed by [[Robert Peel|Sir Robert Peel]] to calm the increasing difficult situation in [[Ireland]] as a result of the [[Great Famine (Ireland)|Great Famine]] 1844–47. The Bill was blocked and this led, in part, to Peel's retirement as Prime Minister. Later attempts to introduce Irish coercion acts were blocked by the filibustering of [[Joseph Biggar]].

As a response to the [[Plan of Campaign]] of the mid 1880s the new [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]]  [[Arthur Balfour]] secured a tough Perpetual Crimes Act (1887) (or Coercion Act) aimed at the prevention of [[boycott]]ing, [[intimidation]], [[unlawful assembly]] and the organisation of conspiracies against the payment of agreed rents. The Act resulted in the imprisonment of hundreds of people including over twenty MPs.

The so-called ''Crimes Act'' (or &quot;Coercion&quot; Act) was condemned by the [[Catholic Church hierarchy|Catholic hierarchy]] since it was to become a permanent part of the law and did not have to be renewed annually by parliament, but the [[Papacy]] issued the bull [http://www.newadvent.org/library/docs_le13sn.htm &quot;Saepe Nos&quot;] in [[1888]] which was uncritical of the Acts. Trial by jury was abolished.

An influential analysis of the pros and cons of the Act was published in [[1888]] by W. H. Hurlbert, a Catholic Irish-American author.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/14510 Hurlbert W., &quot;Ireland under Coercion&quot; vol. 1 online] [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/14511 vol.2 online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many hundreds were imprisoned at times under the Acts, including many prominent politicians and agrarian agitators,{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} [[Joseph Biggar]], [[Alexander Blane]], [[Michael Davitt]], [[John Dillon]], [[James Gilhooly]], [[Patrick Guiney]], [[Matthew Harris (politician)|Matthew Harris]], [[John Patrick Hayden|John Hayden]], [[J. E. Kenny]], [[Andrew Kettle]], [[Denis Kilbride]], [[Pat O'Brien (Irish politician)|Pat O'Brien]], [[William O'Brien]], [[James Joseph O'Kelly|James O'Kelly]], [[Charles Stewart Parnell]], [[Douglas Pyne]], [[Willie Redmond]], [[Timothy Daniel Sullivan|Timothy Sullivan]].

==References==
{{reflist|1}}

{{UK legislation}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

[[Category:Land reform in Ireland]]
[[Category:Acts of the Parliament of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:History of Ireland 1801–1923]]
[[Category:United Kingdom Acts of Parliament 1881]]

[[fr:Irish Coercion Acts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
