<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7699834" ns="0" title="Opera Mobile"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox web browser
| name                   = Opera Mobile
| logo                   = [[File:Opera Mobile logo.png|150px]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Screenshot of Opera Mobile 11 for Android.png|240px|]]
| caption                = Opera Mobile 11 for Android
| developer              = [[Opera Software]]
| frequently updated     = yes
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date    =
| platform               = [[Android (operating system)|Android]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://my.opera.com/operamobile/blog/opera-mobile-11-for-android-and-symbian
  |title=Opera Mobile 11 for Android and Symbian
  |publisher=[[Opera Software]]
  |accessdate=2011-03-22
  |quote = Supported platforms:	S60, Android
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Maemo]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11 labs&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://my.opera.com/operamobile/blog/opera-mobile-11-labs-release-for-maemo-meego-and-windows
  |title=Opera Mobile 11 labs release for Maemo, MeeGo and Windows
  |publisher=[[Opera Software]]
  |accessdate=2011-03-22
  |quote = Supported platforms:	Maemo (labs), Meego (labs), Windows (labs)
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[MeeGo]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11 labs&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[S60 (software platform)|S60]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Windows Mobile]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 10&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Windows]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11&quot;/&gt;
| engine                 = [[Presto layout engine|Presto]]
| status                 = Active
| genre                  = [[Mobile browser]]
| license                = [[Freeware]]
| website                = {{URL|www.opera.com/mobile}}
}}
'''Opera Mobile''' is a [[web browser]] for [[smartphones]] and [[personal digital assistants|PDA's]] developed by the [[Opera Software]] company. The first version was released in 2000 for the [[Psion Series 7]] and [[Psion Netbook|netBook]]. Today, it is available for a variety of devices that run on [[Android (operating system)|Android]], [[S60 platform|S60]], [[Windows Mobile]], [[Maemo|Maemo (labs)]], and [[MeeGo|MeeGo (labs)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.opera.com/mobile/specs/
  |title=Opera Mini &amp; Opera Mobile Technical Specifications
  |publisher=[[Opera Software]]
  |accessdate=2007-10-18
  |quote = Supported platforms:	S60, Windows Mobile, Android, Maemo (labs edition*)
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opera Mobile 10 was released to [[Mobile network operator|operators]] and [[OEM]]s on December 10, 2009, as a direct-to-distributor version and was made available on the Opera website on March 16, 2010. It is available on Android, BREW, Windows Mobile, and Symbian/S60 smartphones, and it is in development for [[Maemo]] devices.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 10&quot;&gt;[http://www.opera.com/press/releases/2009/12/10/ One user interface (UI) on any mobile phone]. Opera.com (2009-12-10). Retrieved on 2011-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;We’re back! Opera Mobile 10 on Maemo&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://labs.opera.com/news/2010/05/11/
  |title=We’re back! Opera Mobile 10 on Maemo
  |publisher=Opera Software
  |accessdate=2010-05-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The first devices to run a mobile edition of Opera were the [[Psion Series 5]], [[Psion Series 5mx]], [[Psion Series 7]], and then [[Psion netBook]]. They ran Opera Mobile 3.6, released in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
| url=http://www.opera.com/pressreleases/en/2000/03/20000331.dml
| title=mCommerce Now a Reality on Psion Platform
| publisher=Opera Software
| date=2000-04-03
| accessdate=2007-12-04
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://jp.opera.com/products/mobile/brochures/OperaMobileTimeline.pdf
| title=Opera Mobile Timeline
| publisher=Opera Software
| year=2006
| accessdate=2007-12-04
| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070205231904/http://jp.opera.com/products/mobile/brochures/OperaMobileTimeline.pdf |archivedate = February 5, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opera Mobile was ported to the [[Windows Mobile]] operating system in 2003.&lt;ref name=&quot;Timeline&quot;/&gt;

* Version 6.0 was the initial release.
* On June 25, 2003, the first update came in the form of version 6.01, which was a minor update, mainly correcting bugs.
* Version 6.10, released on October 27, 2003, introduced several user interface and usability improvements, considerably optimized performance, and slightly improved page rendering. It was also the first version to support [[proxy server]]s, [[Wireless Application Protocol|WAP]] pages, and the first one to be released in localized versions for 9 different languages.
* On July 13, 2005, almost two years after the previous iteration, version 8.0 was launched. This version was the first to require [[Symbian OS]] 7 (previous ones could function in Symbian 6.1). This version introduced the Opera Mobile Accelerator, a technology that used an Opera-run external server to slim-down the pages' content to reduce the traffic to the phones. This was also the first version to support [[dynamic HTML]], and greatly improved compatibility with several web standards.
* On November 14, 2005, version 8.5 was introduced. This version introduced password management and form auto-filling functionality, added some more languages for localized versions, and made some improvements to stability and reduced-screen rendering quality.
* On April 5, 2006, version 8.6 was released and was also the first version to support Symbian OS 9. New to this version is the ability to support multiple browsing windows, support for [[Scalable Vector Graphics]], introduction of [[URL]] autocompletion as well several changes in the customization aspect. It was also the first version of Opera Mobile that allowed for the possibility to configure it as the device's default browser, allowing for it to be launched whenever a web page was requested to be opened.
* Version 8.65 was released on August 29, 2006, which was mostly a welcome makeover and optimization to the then considered mature 8.60.
* Opera Mobile 9.0 was announced in February 2007 with a planned feature list, &quot;coming soon&quot; banners in the official Opera Mobile website, and official announcements in Opera's Community Forum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.softpedia.com/news/Opera-Mobile-9-Unveiled-46893.shtml Opera Mobile 9 Unveiled - The new version includes Widgets and Intelligent Zoom - Softpedia]. News.softpedia.com. Retrieved on 2011-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt; With no reason given, version 9.0 was cancelled, all references to it swept from Opera's site and 8.65 went back to being the latest version, being given a very slight refresh in the form of a new build that offered a handful of hardly-noticeable features, some of them platform-dependent.
* On February 5, 2008, Opera Mobile 9.5 was announced&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opera.com/pressreleases/en/2008/02/05/ Opera unleashes innovative technology in latest mobile Web browser — Opera Mobile 9.5]. Opera.com (2008-02-05). Retrieved on 2011-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt; and has been given several estimated release timeframes, each of which has been silently ignored with a new one being set after it. An initial beta version of Opera Mobile 9.5 was released on July 17, 2008, although the only platform supported by this version was Windows Mobile.
* A second beta release of Opera Mobile 9.50 was made on October 20, 2008, including support for Opera Widgets, and adding Symbian UIQ3 as a further platform. With this release, the newest version of Opera Mobile for Symbian S60 remains 8.65.
* On March 26, 2009, Opera announced that there won't be any final version of Opera mobile 9.5. Instead they would flip over to developing 9.7 because of changes in the [[Presto layout engine]].
* On June 8, 2009, Opera Mobile 9.7 beta was made available for download. It introduced the new rendering engine Presto 2.2 and Opera Turbo. Other features planned for 9.7 are an improved Widget manager, Google Gears, and OpenGL ES support.
* On November 2, 2009, Opera Mobile 10 beta for Symbian S60 was made available for download, sporting a revamped user interface and performance enhancements.
* On December 10, 2009, Opera Mobile 10 was released to operators and OEMs. It includes Opera's new, cross-platform UI framework that unifies the look and feel of the browser across all platforms running Opera Mobile or [[Opera Mini]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 10&quot;/&gt;
* On February 12, 2010, Opera Mobile 10 beta 3 was publicly released for Windows Mobile and Symbian devices.  It includes support for Flash Lite 3.1 as well as better recognition for third party input solutions in Windows Mobile.  It also adds support for Windows Mobile Standard (non-touchscreen) handsets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 10&quot;/&gt;
* On March 16, 2010, Opera Software released the final versions of Opera Mobile 10.
[[File:Nokia5800 Opera Mobile 10 1 Beta.JPG|thumb|290px|left|The [[Nokia 5800 XpressMusic]], running Opera Mobile 10.1 Beta]]
* On May 11, 2010, Opera labs released a preview build of Opera Mobile 10 for [[Maemo]]. The preview build has the same features available in Opera Mobile 10 for other platforms but uses Opera's new JavaScript engine (codenamed [[Carakan (script engine)|Carakan]]), as well as the new vector graphics library (codenamed Vega).&lt;ref name=&quot;We’re back! Opera Mobile 10 on Maemo&quot;/&gt;
* On October 15, 2010, Opera Software released Opera Mobile 10.1 Beta for Android to the Android Market, the first public build for Android.
* On March 22, 2011, Opera Software released Opera Mobile 11 for Android,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11&quot; /&gt; Symbian S60,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11&quot; /&gt; Maemo,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11 labs&quot; /&gt; MeeGo,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11 labs&quot; /&gt; and [[Windows]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mobile 11 labs&quot; /&gt;

== Features ==
&lt;!-- [[File:Mini 5 Commercial.ogv|thumb|350px|Opera Mobile 10 and Opera Mini 5 Commercial]] --&gt;
Opera Mobile uses the [[Presto layout engine]] and supports many web standards, as well as [[Ajax (programming)|Ajax]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opera.com/business/solutions/mobile/features/ Opera Solutions: Opera Mobile]. Opera.com. Retrieved on 2011-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt; As of version 9.7, it can use Opera Turbo that compresses web pages via [[Opera Software]]'s &quot;Turbo&quot; servers, thus reducing download size. Because web pages are compressed, page loading times are improved, and bandwidth consumption is reduced by up to 80%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opera.com/press/releases/2009/02/12/ Opera unveils turbo-charged browsing at Mobile World Congress 2009]. Opera.com (2009-02-12). Retrieved on 2011-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The browser can dynamically reformat [[web page]]s for small screen, using Opera's Small Screen Rendering (SSR) technology and [[word wrap|text-wrapping]].

Opera Mobile 10 includes a &quot;[[Features of the Opera web browser#Speed Dial|Speed Dial]]&quot; feature, which allows the user to add links shown as thumbnail images in a page displayed when a new tab is opened. Once set up, this feature allows the user to more easily navigate to the selected web pages, and [[Tab (GUI)|visual tabs]], that allow the browsing multiple Web sites at one time. It also includes a [[password manager]] and [[Pop-up ad|pop-up handler]], and it supports [[copy and paste]], [[autocomplete|address auto-complete]], [[page zooming|zooming]], history, and [[bookmark (web)|bookmarks]].

The browser can be used by either using finger-touch or stylus on a touchscreen or with a keypad and can be displayed in portrait and landscape mode.

== Awards ==
* Smartphone and PocketPC Magazine &quot;Best mobile browser for both Windows-based Pocket PC and Smartphones&quot; 2007&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
| url=http://www.intomobile.com/2007/11/28/opera-mobile-named-best-windows-mobile-browser.html
| title=Opera Mobile named 'Best Windows Mobile Browser'
| last=Park
| first=Will
| publisher=IntoMobile
| date=2007-11-28
| accessdate=2007-11-29
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mobile Gala &quot;Best program for mobile phones&quot; 2004&lt;ref name=&quot;Awards&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.opera.com/products/mobile/reviews/
| title=Reviews and Awards
| publisher=[[Opera Software]]
| accessdate=2007-10-13
| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071010125931/http://www.opera.com/products/mobile/reviews/ |archivedate = October 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mobile Gala &quot;Best program for handheld computers&quot; 2004&lt;ref name=&quot;Awards&quot;/&gt;
* Tietokone magazine &quot;Best Software Product of the Year&quot; 2003&lt;ref name=&quot;Awards&quot;/&gt;

== Devices ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2011}}
[[File:HTCOpera.png|thumb|250px|right|The HTC build, running on an [[HTC Touch Pro]].]]
Opera Mobile comes pre-installed on some devices, and often, a special build is made for the particular device. Some devices that feature Opera Mobile pre-installed are:

* [[Nokia N90]]
* [[Sony Ericsson P1]]
* [[Sony Ericsson XPERIA X1]]
* [[HTC Touch Viva]]
* [[HTC Touch Diamond]]
* [[HTC Touch Diamond2]]
* [[HTC Touch Pro]]
* [[HTC Touch Pro 2]]
* [[HTC Touch HD]]
* [[HTC HD2]]
* [[Meizu M8]]
* [[Creative Zii]]
* [[Samsung i900 Omnia]]
* [[Samsung i8000|Samsung i8000 Omnia II]]
* [[Motorola ROKR E6]]

&lt;!--  if any of this is still relevant please move to a more suitable section.

== Future development ==
The Opera Software company [http://www.opera.com/pressreleases/en/2007/02/12/ announced] that Opera Mobile 9 would support widgets and offer a more intelligent zoom feature. Opera Mobile 9's internal builds passed the [[Acid2]] test.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://operawatch.com/news/2007/04/opera-for-windows-mobile-passes-acid2-test-on-pace-to-become-first-wm-browser-to-pass-test.html
| title=Opera for Windows Mobile passes Acid2 test; on pace to become first WM browser to pass test
| last=Goldman
| first=Daniel
| date=2007-04-23
| accessdate=2007-12-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://my.opera.com/spz/blog/show.dml/268384
| title=Opera for Symbian passes Acid2
| date=2007-05-24
| accessdate=2007-12-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://www.intomobile.com/2006/05/25/opera-mobile-passes-the-acid2-test.html
| title=Opera Mobile passes the Acid2 test
| last=Belic
| first=Dusan
| date=2006-05-25
| accessdate=2007-12-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opera Mobile 9 was being ported from the desktop edition of Opera.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://labs.opera.com/
| title=The ACID2 smile on mobile phones
| last=Ford
| first=Thomas
| date=2006-05-29
| accessdate=2007-12-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was expected to be released in the first half of 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://www.mobilewhack.com/opera-mobile-9-2008-coming-soon/
| title=Opera Mobile 9 2008 Coming Soon
| publisher=MobileWhack
| accessdate=2007-12-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://operawatch.com/news/2007/12/here-comes-opera-mobile-9.html
| title=Here comes Opera Mobile 9
| publisher=[[Opera Software]]
| date=2007-12-10
| accessdate=2007-12-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 5, 2008, Opera announced&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://www.opera.com/pressreleases/en/2008/02/05/
| title=Opera unleashes innovative technology in latest mobile Web browser
| date=2008-02-05
| accessdate=2008-04-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt; that it would now instead be working on towards releasing Opera Mobile 9.5, in order to unify its Opera Mobile and desktop browser product around the same release version and underlying rendering engine.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://operawatch.com/news/2008/02/what-happened-to-opera-mobile-90.html
| title=Where did Opera Mobile 9.0 go?
| date=2008-02-07
| accessdate=2008-04-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A pre-alpha internal build of Opera Mobile 9.5 was leaked onto the Internet, for the Windows Mobile platform. There are now multiple different versions of Opera Mobile leaked on the Internet, with varying rendering speeds and even different way of zooming. Some versions now even support Flash Lite 3.1 for full YouTube and Flash webpage support.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
| url=http://my.opera.com/operamobile/blog/2008/02/15/a-note-about-the-leaked-build
| title=A note about the leaked build
| date=2008-02-15
| accessdate=2008-04-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opera has since released the official beta: [http://www.opera.com/products/mobile/ Opera Mobile site] --&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Opera Mini]]
* [[Opera (web browser)]]
* [[Mobile browser]]
* [[Firefox for mobile]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.opera.com/mobile/ Opera Mobile (official site)]
* [http://www.opera.com/mobile/specs/ Opera Mini vs Mobile comparison table]

{{OperaBrowser}}
{{Web browsers}}

[[Category:Opera Software|Mobile]]
[[Category:Mobile browsers]]
[[Category:Pocket PC software]]
[[Category:Symbian software]]
[[Category:Android software]]
[[Category:Windows software]]

[[ar:أوبرا موبايل]]
[[de:Opera#Opera Mobile]]
[[es:Opera Mobile]]
[[fa:اپرا موبایل]]
[[fr:Opera Mobile]]
[[ko:오페라 모바일]]
[[hi:ऑपेरा मोबाइल]]
[[it:Opera (browser)#Opera Mobile]]
[[nl:Opera Mobile]]
[[ja:Opera Mobile]]
[[uz:Opera Mobile]]
[[pl:Opera Mobile]]
[[pt:Opera Mobile]]
[[ro:Opera (navigator web)#Opera Mobile pentru dispozitive mobile]]
[[ru:Opera Mobile]]
[[fi:Opera Mobile]]
[[zh:Opera Mobile]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
