<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="770690" ns="0" title="Twenty20"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{For|the Malayalam film|Twenty:20}}
[[File:England vs Sri Lanka.jpg|thumb|400px|A view of the Twenty20 match between [[England cricket team|England]] and [[Sri Lanka cricket team|Sri Lanka]] at the [[Rose Bowl, Hampshire|Rose Bowl]] on 15 June 2006]]
'''Twenty20''' is a form of [[cricket]], originally introduced in England for professional inter-county competition by the [[England and Wales Cricket Board]] (ECB), in 2003. A Twenty20 game involves two teams, each has a single [[innings]], batting for a maximum of 20 [[over (cricket)|overs]]. Twenty20 cricket is also known as '''T20 cricket'''. It has been played at club and junior levels for years, usually in evenings when daylight was a problem.   

A Twenty20 game is completed in about two and half hours, with each inning lasting around 75 minutes, thus bringing the game closer to the timespan of other popular team sports. It was introduced to create a lively form of the game which would be attractive to spectators at the ground and viewers on television and as such it has been very successful. The ECB did not intend that Twenty20 would replace other forms of cricket and these have continued alongside it.

Since its inception the game has spread around the cricket world. On most international tours there is at least one Twenty20 match and all [[Test cricket|Test]]-playing nations have a domestic cup competition. The inaugural [[ICC World Twenty20]] was played in South Africa in 2007 with [[India cricket team|India]] winning by five runs against [[Pakistan cricket team|Pakistan]] in the final.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/twenty20wc/content/current/story/312320.html|title=India hold their nerve to win thriller|publisher=Cricinfo.com|date=24 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan won the [[2009 ICC World Twenty20]], defeating Sri Lanka by eight wickets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wt202009/content/current/story/410042.html|title=Afridi fifty seals title for Pakistan|publisher=Cricinfo.com|date=21 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; England won the [[2010 ICC World Twenty20]] defeating Australia in the final by 7 wickets.

==History==
===Origins===
[[File:Andrew Strauss twenty20.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[England cricket team|England]] batsman [[Andrew Strauss]] batting for [[Middlesex County Cricket Club|Middlesex]] against [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]]]]
The idea of a shortened format of the game at a professional level was discussed by the [[England and Wales Cricket Board]] (ECB) in 1998 and 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;t20hist&quot;&gt;[http://www.cricinus.com/2007/09/twenty20cricket-history.html History of Twenty20 cricket] All Out For Nothing. Retrieved 9 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

When the [[Benson &amp; Hedges Cup]] ended in 2002, the [[England and Wales Cricket Board|ECB]] needed another one day competition to fill its place. The cricketing authorities were looking to boost the game's popularity with the younger generation in response to dwindling crowds and reduced sponsorship. It was intended to deliver fast paced, exciting cricket accessible to thousands of fans who were put off by the longer versions of the game. Stuart Robertson, the marketing manager of the ECB, proposed a 20 over per innings game to county chairmen in 2001 and they voted 11–7 in favour of adopting the new format.&lt;ref&gt;Newman, Paul; [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/cricket/article-1025831/Meet-man-invented-Twenty20-cricket--man-missing-millions.html Meet the man who invented Twenty20 cricket – the man missing out on millions]; [[Daily Mail]]; 11 June 2008. Retrieved 6 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  A media group was invited to develop a name for the new game and Twenty20 was the chosen title. Twenty20 cricket is also known as T20 cricket. A mathematician from [[Perth, Western Australia]], Dr George Christos, also claims to have proposed a similar format to the ICC and ECB in 1997. However, the ICC has dismissed his involvement in developing the final concept.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thewest.com.au/default.aspx?MenuID=4&amp;ContentID=116230 Perth man seeks credit for Twenty20]; [[The West Australian]]; 6 January 2009. Retrieved 6 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Twenty20 cricket was formally introduced in 2003 when the [[England and Wales Cricket Board|ECB]] launched the [[Twenty20 Cup]] and was marketed with the slogan &quot;I don’t like cricket, I love it&quot;, taken from the [[10cc]] song &quot;[[Dreadlock Holiday]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;t20hist&quot;/&gt;

===Twenty20 Cup===
The first official Twenty20 matches were played on 13 June 2003 between the English counties in the [[Twenty20 Cup]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cricinfo.com/link_to_database/ARCHIVE/2003/ENG_LOCAL/TWENTY-20/SCORECARDS/13JUN2003/ Matches played 13 June 2003] Cricinfo. Retrieved 9 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The first season of Twenty20 in England was a relative success, with the [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey Lions]] defeating the [[Warwickshire County Cricket Club|Warwickshire Bears]] by 9 wickets in the final to claim the [[Twenty20 Cup]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cricinfo.com/link_to_database/ARCHIVE/2003/ENG_LOCAL/TWENTY-20/SCORECARDS/KNOCK-OUTS/SURREY_WARWICKS_TWENTY-20-FINAL_19JUL2003.html Twenty20 Cup, 2003, Final – Surrey v Warwickshire] Cricinfo. Retrieved 9 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 July 2004 [[Middlesex County Cricket Club|Middlesex]] vs. [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]] (the first Twenty20 game to be held at [[Lord's Cricket Ground|Lord's]]) attracted a crowd of 26,500, the largest attendance for any [[county cricket]] game other than a one-day final since 1953.

===Twenty20 Worldwide===
Pakistan Cricket Board initiated The Twenty-20 Cup in 2004 as a professional league for Twenty20 cricket competition in Pakistan,sponsored by Faysal Bank. Overall 13 teams from different part of the country participated in the competition and Faisalabad Wolves team won the final. On 10 January 2005 Australia's first Twenty20 game was played at the [[WACA Ground]] between the [[Western Warriors]] and the [[Victorian Bushrangers]]. It drew a sellout crowd of 20,700.&lt;ref name=&quot;indiatwenty20.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiatwenty20.com/twenty20-history.htm|title=Twenty20: Past, Present and Future|publisher=India Twenty20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting 11 July 2006 19 West Indies regional teams competed in what was named the [[Stanford 20/20]] tournament. The event has been financially backed by billionaire [[Allen Stanford]], who gave at least US$28,000,000 funding money. West Indies legends also backed the programme, and several &quot;looked after&quot; the teams during their stay in and around the purpose built ground in Antigua. It was intended that the tournament would be an annual event. [[Guyanese cricket team|Guyana]] won the inaugural event, defeating [[Trinidad and Tobago cricket team|Trinidad and Tobago]] by 5 wickets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/stanford/content/story/256391.html|title=Guyana crowned Stanford 20/20 champions|publisher=Cricinfo.com|date=14 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The top prize for the winning team was US$1,000,000, but other prizes were given throughout the tournament, such as play of the match (US$10,000) and man of the match (US$25,000).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jamaicaobserver.com/sports/html/20060208T230000-0500_98302_OBS_DATES_FOR_STANFORD_TWENTY___ANNOUNCED.asp|title=Dates for Stanford Twenty20 announced|publisher=The Jamaica Observer|date=9 February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 November 2008 the Superstars West Indies team (101-0/12.5 overs) beat England (99/all out) by 10 wickets. England slumped to 33–4 and then 65–8 after 15 overs before Samit Patel's 22 took them to 99 in 19.5 overs, still easily their lowest Twenty20 total. Chris Gayle scored an impressive 65 runs not out.

On 5 January 2007 [[Queensland Bulls]] played the [[New South Wales Blues]] at [[Brisbane Cricket Ground|The Gabba]], [[Brisbane]]. A crowd of 11,000 was expected based on pre-match ticket sales. However, an unexpected 16,000 turned up on the day to buy tickets, causing disruption and confusion for surprised Gabba staff as they were forced to throw open gates and grant many fans free entry. Attendance reached 27,653.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thetwenty20cup.co.uk/db/aus/article.asp?NewsID=1093|title=Gabba fans let in for free|publisher=Cricket20.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For 1 February 2008's Twenty20 match between Australia and India, 84,041&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ausvind/content/story/334462.html|title=India crash to nine-wicket defeat|publisher=Cricinfo.com|date=1 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; people attended the match at the [[Melbourne Cricket Ground]] involving the Twenty20 World Champions against the ODI World Champions.
Twenty20 attracted many of fans to the game through the [[Indian Premier League]].The first [[Indian Premier League]] which was staged in India in [[2008 Indian Premier League|2008]] changed the face of the game. The league involved over hundreds of players contracted and over billion dollars investment. It was won by [[Rajasthan Royals]] with the [[Chennai Super Kings]] finishing as runners-up. The second edition was staged in [[2009 Indian Premier League|South Africa]] which was won by [[Deccan Chargers]] beating the [[Royal Challengers]] in the final. The third edition was played in [[2010 Indian Premier League|India]] despite the many challenges and controversies occurred. The league was won by the [[Chennai Super Kings]] with [[Mumbai Indians]] finishing as the runners-up.in the fourth edition chennai super kings defended their title by thrashing the royal challengers from bengaluru in their hometown

===Twenty20 Internationals===
On 17 February 2005 [[Australian cricket team|Australia]] defeated [[New Zealand cricket team|New Zealand]] in the first men's full international Twenty20 match, played at [[Eden Park]] in [[Auckland]]. The game was played in a light-hearted manner – both sides turned out in kit similar to that worn in the 1980s, the New Zealand team's a direct copy of that worn by the [[Beige Brigade]]. Some of the players also sported moustaches/beards and hair styles popular in the 1980s taking part in a competition amongst themselves for ''best retro look'', at the request of the Beige Brigade. Australia won the game comprehensively, and as the result became obvious towards the end of the NZ innings, the players and umpires took things less seriously – [[Glenn McGrath]] jokingly replayed the [[Trevor Chappell]] [[1981 underarm bowling incident|underarm]] incident from a 1981 ODI between the two sides, and [[Billy Bowden]] showed him a mock [[Penalty_card#Red_card|red card]] (red cards are not normally used in cricket) in response.

The first Twenty20 international in England was played between [[English cricket team|England]] and [[Australian cricket team|Australia]] at the [[Rose Bowl, Southampton|Rose Bowl]] in Hampshire on 13 June 2005, which England won by a record margin of 100 runs.

On 9 January 2006 [[Australian cricket team|Australia]] and [[South African cricket team|South Africa]] met in the first international Twenty20 game in Australia. In a first, each player's [[List of nicknames used in cricket|nickname]] appeared on the back of his uniform, rather than his surname. The international match drew a crowd of 38,894 people at [[Brisbane Cricket Ground|The Gabba]]. Australia convincingly won the match with [[man of the match]] [[Damien Martyn]] scoring 96 runs.

On 16 February 2006 [[New Zealand cricket team|New Zealand]] defeated [[West Indian cricket team|West Indies]] in a tie-breaking [[bowl-out]] 3–0; 126 runs were scored apiece in the game proper. The game was the last international match played by [[Chris Cairns]] – NZC handed out life-size cardboard masks of his face to patrons as they entered the ground.

===Criticism===

Although the format has proven successful, it has been argued that since Twenty20 encourages far-from-technical cricket, youngsters wanting to pick up the game will be misguided into believing that cricket is all about trying to hit 6s and 4s no matter how you do it.&lt;ref name=&quot;indiatwenty20.com&quot;/&gt;

=== Impact on the game ===
[[File:Twenty20 cricket start.JPG|thumb|right|300px| Twenty20 matches can have some exciting displays such as when Batsmen run out to the pitch]]Twenty20 cricket is claimed to have resulted in a more athletic and &quot;explosive&quot; form of cricket. Indian [[physical fitness|fitness]] coach [[Ramji Srinivasan]] declared in an [[interview]] with the Indian fitness website ''Takath.com'', that Twenty20 had &quot;raised the bar&quot; in terms of fitness levels for all players, demanding higher levels of strength, [[speed]], [[agility]] and [[reaction time]] from all players irrespective of role in the team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.takath.com/articles/20090619|title=An interview with Ramji Srinivasan|publisher=Takath.com|date=19 June 2009}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Not everyone accords with this view, however, citing for instance the fact that a retired player like [[Shane Warne]] has been successful in such tournaments as the [[Indian Premier League|IPL]]. [[Ramesh Powar]] is another good example of an &quot;unfit&quot; player who has flourished in the IPL.

Shane Warne has never been known for physical fitness. However, other successful retired players such as [[Adam Gilchrist]] and [[Matthew Hayden]] have. In fact, Hayden credited retirement from International cricket with aiding his performance in general and fitness in particular in the IPL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.canberratimes.com.au/news/local/sport/cricket/hayden-heroics-shining-light-of-ipl/1511995.aspx|title=Hayden heroics shining light of IPL|publisher=Canberra Times|date=13 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, speaking at the annual [[Cowdrey Lecture]] at [[Lord's]], former Australian wicketkeeper Adam Gilchrist pushed for Twenty20 to be made an Olympic sport.  &quot;It would,&quot; he said, &quot;be difficult to see a better, quicker or cheaper way of spreading the
game throughout the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in [[Lawrence Booth|Booth, Lawrence]]. &quot;[[Myth]]s; And [[stereotype]]s.&quot; ''The Spin'', 30 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Match format and rules==
===Format===
Twenty20 match format is similar to [[limited overs cricket]] in that it involves two teams, each with a single [[innings]], the key difference being each team bats for a maximum of 20 [[over (cricket)|overs]]. In terms of visual format, the batting team members do not arrive from and depart to traditional dressing rooms, but come and go from a &quot;bench&quot; (typically a row of chairs) visible in the playing arena, analogous to association football's &quot;[[Technical area]]&quot; or a baseball &quot;[[Dugout (baseball)|dugout]]&quot;.

[[File:Twenty20 game.jpg|thumb|right|300px|[[Middlesex County Cricket Club|Middlesex]] playing against [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]] at [[Lord's Cricket Ground|Lord's]], in front of a 28,000-strong crowd]]

===General rules===
The [[Laws of cricket]] apply to Twenty20, with some exceptions:

* Each bowler may bowl a maximum of only one-fifth of the total overs per innings. For a full, uninterrupted match, this is 4 overs.

*Should a bowler deliver a [[no ball]] by overstepping the [[Popping_crease#Popping_crease|popping crease]], it costs 1 run and his next delivery is designated a &quot;free-hit&quot;. In this circumstance the batsman can only be dismissed through a [[run out]], [[Hit the ball twice|hitting the ball twice]], [[obstructing the field]] or [[Handled the ball|handling the ball]].

* The following [[Fielding (cricket)|fielding]] restrictions apply:
** No more than five fielders can be on the [[leg side]] at any time.
** During the first six overs, a maximum of two fielders can be outside the [[Fielding (cricket)#Restrictions on field placement|30-yard circle]] (This is sometimes referred to as the [[Powerplay (cricket)|powerplay]]).
** After the first six overs, a maximum of five fielders can be outside the fielding circle.

* If the fielding team do not start to bowl their 20th over within 75 minutes, the batting side are credited an extra six runs for every whole over bowled after the 75 minute mark; the umpire may add more time to this if he believes the batting team are wasting time.

===Tie deciders===
{{Main|Super Over}}
Currently, if the match ends with the scores tied and there must be a winner, the tie is broken with a one over per side &quot;Eliminator&quot;&lt;ref name=Cricinfo_Twenty20_Eliminator_27Jun2008&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/358299.html
| title=One-over eliminator could replace bowl-out  
| date = 27 June 2008
| accessdate =26 December 2008
| publisher=cricinfo.com [[cricinfo.com]]}}
&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;[[Super Over]]&quot;:&lt;ref name=ABC_Twenty20_NZvWI_26Dec2008_SuperOver&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/12/26/2455345.htm
| title=Windies edge NZ in Twenty20 thriller  
| date = 26 December 2008
| accessdate =26 December 2008
| publisher=www.abc.net.au [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cricinfo_Twenty20_NZvWI_26Dec2008_SuperOver&gt;
{{cite web
| url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/nzvwi2008_09/content/current/story/384254.html
| title=Benn stars in thrilling tie  
| date = 26 December 2008
| accessdate =26 December 2008
| publisher=cricinfo.com [[cricinfo.com]]}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 
Each team nominates three batsmen and one bowler to play a one-over per side &quot;mini-match&quot;, sometimes referred to as a &quot;One1&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cricinfo_Twenty20_NZvWI_26Dec2008_VettoriopposesSuperover_HTMLline422&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/nzvwi2008_09/content/story/384312.html|title=Vettori opposes Super Over|date=26 December 2008|publisher=www.cricinfo.com [[cricinfo.com]]|accessdate=5 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cricinfo_Twenty20_13Jan2009_TheEliminator&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/magazine/content/current/story/386201.html|title=One1|last=The Explainer|date=13 January 2009|publisher=www.cricinfo.com [[cricinfo.com]]|accessdate=5 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In turn, each side bats one over bowled by the one nominated opposition bowler, with their innings over if they lose two wickets before the over is completed. The side with the higher score from their Super Over wins.

Tied Twenty20 matches were previously decided by a &quot;[[Bowl-out]]&quot;.

==International==
{{Main|Twenty20 International}}
[[Twenty20 International]]s have been played since 2005. To date, 17 nations have played the format, including all [[Test cricket#Test cricket playing teams|test playing nations]].  

&lt;!--The order and dates in the following list of nations are left unexplained--&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Nation
! Twenty20 International debut
|- 
| [[Australia national cricket team|Australia]]
| 17 February 2005
|-
| [[New Zealand national cricket team|New Zealand]]
| 17 February 2005
|-
| [[England cricket team|England]]
| 13 June 2005
|-
| [[South Africa national cricket team|South Africa]]
| 21 October 2005
|-
| [[West Indies cricket team|West Indies]]
| 16 February 2006
|-
| [[Sri Lanka national cricket team|Sri Lanka]]
| 15 June 2006
|-
| [[Pakistan national cricket team|Pakistan]]
| 28 August 2006
|-
| [[Bangladesh national cricket team|Bangladesh]]
| 28 November 2006
|-
| [[Zimbabwe national cricket team|Zimbabwe]]
| 28 November 2006
|-
| [[India national cricket team|India]]
| 1 December 2006
|-
| [[Kenya national cricket team|Kenya]]
| 1 September 2007
|-
| [[Scotland national cricket team|Scotland]]
| 12 September 2007
|-
| [[Netherlands national cricket team|Netherlands]]
| 2 August 2008
|-
| [[Ireland cricket team|Ireland]]
| 2 August 2008
|-
| [[Canada national cricket team|Canada]]
| 2 August 2008
|-
| [[Bermuda national cricket team|Bermuda]]
| 3 August 2008
|-
| [[Afghanistan national cricket team|Afghanistan]]
| 2 February 2010
|}

===ICC World Twenty20 tournament===
{{Main|ICC World Twenty20}}
Every two years an [[ICC World Twenty20]] tournament is to take place, except in the event of a [[ICC Cricket World Cup]] being scheduled in the same year, in which case it will be held the year before. The first tournament was in [[2007 ICC World Twenty20|2007 in South Africa]] where [[India cricket team|India]] defeated [[Pakistan cricket team|Pakistan]] in the final. The [[2009 ICC World Twenty20|second tournament]] was won by [[Pakistan cricket team|Pakistan]] who beat [[Sri Lanka cricket team|Sri Lanka]] by 8 wickets in England on 21 June 2009. The [[2010 ICC World Twenty20]] tournament was held in West Indies in May 2010, where [[England cricket team|England]] defeated [[Australia cricket team|Australia]] by 7 wickets.

===T20 International Rankings===
On 29 November 2011, the ICC released the international rankings.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Country !! Matches !! Points !! Rating
|-
| England || 11 || 1435 || 130
|-
| New Zealand || 9 || 1056 || 117
|-
| Sri Lanka || 9 || 1056 || 117
|-
| South Africa || 8 || 900 || 113
|-
| Pakistan || 14 || 1496 || 107
|-
| Australia || 12 || 1223 || 102
|-
| India || 7 || 688 || 98
|-
| West Indies || 8 || 711 || 89
|-
| Afghanistan || 3 || 224 || 75
|-
| Zimbabwe || 7 || 376 || 54
|}

==Domestic==
[[File:IPL T20 Chennai vs Kolkata.JPG|thumb|right|250 px|An [[Indian Premier League]] match commencing at the [[Chepauk Stadium]] between [[Chennai Super Kings]] and [[Kolkata Knight Riders]]]]
{{Main|List of domestic Twenty20 cricket competitions}}

This is a list of the main Twenty20 domestic competitions in each cricketing country.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=#bdb560b 
!Country 
!Domestic Competitions 
|-
|[[Cricket in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]] || [[Afghanistan Provincial Twenty20 Tournament]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Australia|Australia]] || [[Big Bash League]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Bangladesh|Bangladesh]] || [[Bangladesh NCL (National Cricket League) Twenty20|NCL T20]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Canada|Canada]] || [[Scotiabank National T20 Championship]]
|-
|[[Cricket in England|England]] || [[Friends Life t20]]
|-
|[[Cricket in India|India]] || [[Indian Premier League|DLF Indian Premier League]], [[Indian Cricket League]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Kenya|Kenya]] || [[East Africa Trophy]] 
|-
|[[Cricket in New Zealand|New Zealand]] || [[State Twenty20|HRV Cup]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Pakistan|Pakistan]] || [[Pakistan Super League]] and [[Twenty-20 Cup|Faysal Bank Twenty20 Cup]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Scotland|Scotland]] || [[Murgitroyd Twenty20]]
|-
|[[Cricket in South Africa|South Africa]] || [[Standard Bank Pro 20 Series]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Sri Lanka|Sri Lanka]] || [[Sri Lankan Premier League]]
|-
|[[Cricket in United States|U.S.A.]] || [[American Premier League]] and [[NYPD Cricket League]]
|-
|[[Cricket in the West Indies|West Indies]] || [[Caribbean Twenty20]]
|-
|[[Cricket in Zimbabwe|Zimbabwe]] || [[Metropolitan Bank Twenty20]]
|}

==Champions Twenty20 League==
{{Main|Twenty20 Champions League}}
The [[Champions League Twenty20]] often called CLT20 is a twenty20-based cricket [[tournament]] featuring teams from India, South Africa, England, Australia, Sri Lanka, New Zealand, Pakistan and the [[West Indies]]. The [[tournament]] however does not feature equal number of teams from each country. The [[Winners]] and the runners-up of the domestic leagues from Pakistan, India, South Africa, England and Australia and the champions of the other 4 countries are also featured in the [[tournament]].

===2008 Season===

{{Main|2008 Champions League Twenty20}}

The first edition was supposed to have featured in India with 8 teams.Though there were rumours that only teams from India, South Africa, Australia and England would be allowed to take part, [[Sialkot Stallions]] of Pakistan was also allowed entry. The [[tournament]] was however postponed and later cancelled due to the [[2008 Mumbai attacks]].

===2009 Season===
{{Main|2009 Champions League Twenty20}}
After the cancellation of the inaugural edition, the tournament witnessed some changes to enhance fan support. The league was to feature 2 teams from India, South Africa, Australia and England and 1 each from [[West Indies]], New Zealand, Sri Lanka and Pakistan. The format of the game was also changed in contrast to the [[Twenty20 World Cup]]. However [[Sialkot Stallions]] from Pakistan were denied entry due to the political tensions between India and Pakistan. [[Delhi Daredevils]] the league topper of the [[Indian Premier League|IPL]] were chosen to substitute them. The [[NSW Blues]] beat the [[Trinidad &amp; Tobago]] to win the trophy.

===2010 season===
{{Main|2010 Champions League Twenty20}}

The 2010 Champions League Twenty20 was held in the month of September in South Africa. There were only 10 teams instead of 12 as the top 2 English counties could not participate. The 10 teams were placed in two groups. [[Chennai Super Kings]] beat the [[Chevrolet Warriors]] of South Africa in the final.

===2011 season===
The [[2011 Champions League Twenty20]] was held in the month of September and hosted in India and won by Mumbai Indians.

==Records==
These statistics are correct as of 30 August 2011 and include all [[First-class cricket|first-class]]-equivalent level Twenty20 matches.

'''Most Twenty20 runs'''
{|class=wikitable
|-
! Player!!Matches!!Runs!!HS!!Career span
|-
|{{flagicon|Australia}} [[David Hussey]] || 157 || 3,905 || 100* || 2004–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|Australia}} [[Brad Hodge]] || 127 || 3,690 || 106 || 2003–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|Australia}} [[David Warner (cricketer)|David Warner]] || 112 || 3,233 || 135* || 2007–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|NZL}} [[Brendon McCullum]] || 112 || 3,073 || 158* || 2005–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|England}} [[Owais Shah]] ||  119 || 2,953 || 80 || 2003–2011
|}
(*) = [[not out]]

'''Most Twenty20 wickets'''
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=#bdb76b
! Player!!Matches!!Wickets!!BBI!!Career span
|-
|{{flagicon|Australia}}{{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Dirk Nannes]] || 122 || 154 || 5/40 || 2007–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|South Africa}} [[Alfonso Thomas]] || 113 || 136 || 4/27 || 2004–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|South Africa}} [[Albie Morkel]] || 157 || 131 || 4/30 || 2004–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|Pakistan}} [[Yasir Arafat (cricketer)|Yasir Arafat]] || 103 || 122 || 4/17 || 2006–2011
|-
|{{flagicon|Pakistan}} [[Shahid Afridi]] || 94 || 120 || 5/20 || 2004–2011
|}

===Other records===
* Highest individual score – [[Brendon McCullum]] 158*(74) [[Kolkata Knight Riders]] vs [[Royal Challengers Bangalore]] ([[2008 Indian Premier League]])
* Highest team total – by {{Cr|Sri Lanka}} '''260/6 (20 overs)''' vs {{Cr|Kenya}} '''88/10 (19.3 overs)''' ([[2007 ICC World Twenty20#SL world record|2007 ICC World Twenty20]])
* Most sixes in an innings – {{flagicon|England}} [[Graham Napier]] ([[Essex Eagles|Essex]]) '''16''' ([[2008 Twenty20 Cup]])
* Most sixes in career – {{flagicon|Australia}} [[David Hussey]] '''167'''  
* Fastest hundred – {{flagicon|India}} [[Yusuf Pathan]] ([[Rajasthan Royals]]) ''37 balls''' (2010 Indian Premier League)
* Fastest fifty – {{flagicon|India}} [[Yuvraj Singh]] '''12 balls''' (20Twenty Cup 2007)
* Most hundreds – {{flagicon|New Zealand}} [[Brendon McCullum]], {{flagicon|Jamaica}} [[Chris Gayle]], {{flagicon|Australia}} [[Ian Harvey]], {{flagicon|Australia}} [[Adam Gilchrist]], {{flagicon|Australia}} [[David Warner (cricketer)|David Warner]]  '''3'''
* Best innings bowling figures (International) – {{flagicon|Sri Lanka}} [[Ajantha Mendis]] (Sri Lanka) '''6/16''' (vs Australia, Aug 2011)
* Best innings bowling figures (Domestic) – {{flagicon|Malaysia}} [[Arul Suppiah]] ([[Somerset County Cricket Club|Somerset]]) '''6/5''' '''in 22 balls'''  ([[2011 Friends Life t20]])
* Most runs in one over – {{flagicon|Jamaica}} [[Chris Gayle]] '''37, 6 balls 4 sixes 3 fours + 1 no ball''' ([[2011 Indian Premier League]]) against Kochi Tuskers Kerala's [[Prasanth Parameswaran]]
* Longest six – {{flagicon|Australia}} [[Adam Gilchrist]] '''124 Metres''' (2011 Indian Premier League) against RCB

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Twenty20}}
*[http://stats.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/records/index.html?class=6 Cricinfo – Twenty20 records]

{{Forms of cricket}}
{{Twenty20 leagues}}
{{Team Sport}}

[[Category:Twenty20 cricket|*]]

[[de:Twenty20]]
[[fr:Twenty20]]
[[gu:ટ્વેન્ટી20]]
[[ko:트웬티 20]]
[[hi:ट्वेन्टी ट्वेन्टी]]
[[it:Twenty20]]
[[kn:ಟ್ವೆಂಟಿ೨೦]]
[[ml:ട്വന്റി 20 ക്രിക്കറ്റ്‌]]
[[mr:२०-२० सामने]]
[[nl:Twenty20]]
[[ja:トゥエンティ20]]
[[pl:Twenty20]]
[[pt:Twenty20]]
[[simple:Twenty20]]
[[ta:இருபது20]]
[[te:ట్వంటీ 20]]
[[uk:Двадцять20]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
