<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708702" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in On Her Majesty&#039;s Secret Service"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=February 2008}}
This is a list of henchmen in the novel and film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.

==Irma Bunt==
{{James Bond Character|
||bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Irma Bunt
|portrayed=[[Ilse Steppat]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]
}}

'''Irma Bunt''' is the main henchwoman in the [[James Bond]] novel and film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''. She is portrayed by German actress [[Ilse Steppat]]. The role was Steppat's only [[English language|English]] speaking part.

A stocky, red haired middle aged woman, Irma Bunt resides at the mountain-top clinic of [[Piz Gloria]] with [[Ernst Stavro Blofeld]]. Bunt is first introduced at a train station taking Bond up to the clinic by sleigh and helicopter while he is disguised as [[Sir Hilary Bray]]. She ostensibly looks after the girls who are suffering allergies – and secretly being brainwashed into &quot;angels of death&quot; &amp;mdash; and has dinner with them and &quot;Sir Hilary&quot;. A red-haired disciplinarian in the mold of [[Rosa Klebb]], Bunt is determined to keep any fraternizing between &quot;Sir Hilary&quot; and the girls kept to a minimum. In the film Bond himself subtly insults her by telling her that her name comes from a nautical word for the baggy, swollen part of a sail, though in the novel Bond starts tricking her into thinking she's a duchess.

When Bond escapes from Piz Gloria after his cover as Sir Hilary Bray is blown, Bunt helps some of the men pursue him in the village at the bottom of the mountain with a [[Mercedes-Benz W111]]. She fails in this and is almost killed when she is caught in an explosion at a [[stock car]] rally which Tracy had led her into in an attempt to shake her off. Bunt and the other three occupants of the car managed to escape it just before the explosion, but one of them was caught in the blast while crawling away - though the camera did not have enough focus for the viewer to see who it was, nor was the identity of the person mentioned later.

She is not seen again until right at the end of the film after 007's wedding (a scene deleted from the film had Bunt trailing Bond and Tracy when they are purchasing a wedding ring from a jewellery store). Bunt shows up, alive and well, in a car driven by Blofeld. As they pass the newlyweds, Bunt leans out of the window and fires at Bond with an [[M16 rifle|M16]]. Bond is unharmed, but Tracy is killed.

Unusually for a Bond film villain, Bunt escaped punishment and retribution from 007: she was neither seen nor mentioned in the following film, ''[[Diamonds Are Forever (film)|Diamonds Are Forever]]'' (actress Ilse Steppat had died just after ''On Her Majesty's Secret Service'' reached cinemas), where Bond avenges Tracy's death by relentlessly tracking down and killing Blofeld. Other villains, such as [[Jaws (James Bond)|Jaws]], survive because they switched allegiances. In the book ''[[You Only Live Twice (novel)|You Only Live Twice]]'', Bond incapacitates her before the final show-down with Blofeld and it is later stated that she was subsequently killed in the destruction of the castle in which they were living. She is the main villain in [[Raymond Benson]]'s 1997 short story [[James Bond uncollected short stories#&quot;Blast from the Past&quot;|&quot;Blast from the Past&quot;]], an unofficial sequel to ''[[You Only Live Twice (novel)|You Only Live Twice]]''.

==Grunther==
{{James Bond Character|
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Grunther
|portrayed=[[Yuri Borienko]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Grunther''' is a henchman in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.  He is portrayed by [[Yuri Borienko]]. 

Grunther is a henchman to Ernst Stavro Blofeld. He appears from Piz Gloria onwards. In the film, he is first seen with Irma Bunt. Later, he is seen denying [[Shaun Campbell]] access to the Piz Gloria base and later holds him prisoner. He leads the first group on the downhill ski to catch the escaping Bond. He crashes into a tree and ends up with Blofeld's second group. His final appearance is during the Battle of Piz Gloria, in which he fights with [[Tracy Bond]] and is killed when she impales him on a wall of spikes.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Braun==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Braun
|portrayed=[[George Lane Cooper]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Braun''' is a henchman in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.  He is portrayed by [[George Lane Cooper]]. 

Braun's is a SPECTRE henchman with large [[sideburns]]. He is one of two [[SPECTRE]] henchmen who accompany Irma Bunt in her pursuit of Bond through a small town in the [[Alps]]. He and Felsen fight with Bond in a shed and are defeated by him, but Bunt recalls them to her car and they chase Bond and Tracy through a racecourse. Braun sits on the left side front seat of the car, next to the driver, and manges to get a few potshots off at Bond's car before he is forced to abandon his car before it blows up.

Braun is not to be confused with another henchman called Braun, who featured in the later Bond film ''[[Licence to Kill]]''.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Felsen==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Felsen
|portrayed=[[Les Crawford]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Felsen''' is a henchman in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.  He is portrayed by [[Les Crawford]]. 

Felsen is a thin [[SPECTRE]] henchman who accompanies Irma Bunt and Braun in their pursuit of Bond. He and Braun are knocked out by Bond, but are woken up by Bunt in order to chase Bond and Tracy in their car. Felsen sat in the back seat with Bunt and tried to shoot at Bond's car on the highway, but his car veered off the road before he could fire. He abandoned the car before it blew up at the racetrack.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==SPECTRE Driver==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=SPECTRE Driver
|portrayed=[[Reg Harding]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''SPECTRE Driver''' is a henchman in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.  He is portrayed by [[Reg Harding]]. 

This man drives Bunt, Felsen, and Braun after Bond during his second escape from Piz Gloria Allergy Clinic. He strafes a [[phone booth]] in the Alpine town Bond flees to, allowing Braun and Felsen to fill it with bullets. Beyond that, he does little more than get ordered around by Bunt. He abandons the car when it blows up at the racetrack.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Gumbold==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Gumbold
|portrayed=[[James Bree]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Active
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Gumbold''' is a Swiss lawyer with offices in Berne in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.  He is portrayed by [[James Bree]]. 

Gumbold is a [[Swiss]] [[Lawyer|attorney]] who is in the employ of [[SPECTRE]]. His role is to help [[Blofeld]] be recognized as Balthazar, [[Count]] de Bleuchamp. His role in the film is minimal, although Bond finds documents from the [[College of Arms]] in his office that help lead him to Blofeld.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==SPECTRE Skier==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=SPECTRE Skier
|portrayed=[[George Leech]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''SPECTRE Skier''' is a henchman in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''.  He is portrayed by [[George Leech]]. 

There are several SPECTRE skiers, with this man being the only one with a significant part. He comes after Bond during his escape from Piz Gloria, after hearing the scream of another skier whom Bond threw over a cliff. Bond knocks out this skier, intent on stealing his skis to replace the ones he lost dealing with the first skier. This skier wakes up and attacks Bond, so Bond strangles him into submission with his own skis and then tosses him off a nearby cliff.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Blofeld's Angels of Death==
The '''Angels of Death''' are several beautiful women from all over the world (though in the novel, only ten from the UK) being brainwashed by [[Blofeld]] under the guise of allergy treatment. Their mission is to help Blofeld contaminate and ultimately sterilize the world's food supply. Blofeld claimed he will rescind this threat if all his past crimes are pardoned and he is recognized as the current Count de Bleauchamp. In the novel, Ruby's last name is &quot;Windsor&quot;, and a subplot emerges with Bond (as Hilary Bray) promising to track her heritage.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;
! Name || Actress || Allergy ||   || Name || Actress || Allergy
|- 
| [[Ruby Bartlett]] (English)|| [[Angela Scoular]] || Chicken ||   || Nancy (Hungarian?)|| [[Catherine Schell|Catherina von Schell]] || Potatoes
|- 
|American Girl || Dani Sheridan || Pork || 
|| Helen (Scandinavian) || [[Julie Ege]] || Fish
|-
| Australian Girl || [[Anouska Hempel]]|| Beef || || Indian Girl || Zara || Lentils
|-
|  Chinese Girl || Mona Chong ||Rice || || Irish Girl || [[Jenny Hanley]] || Corn (Maize) 
|- 
| English Girl || [[Joanna Lumley]] || || || Israeli Girl || Helena Ronee || Shellfish
|- 
| German Girl || Ingrit Black || Citrus|| || Jamaican Girl || Sylvana Henriques || Bananas
|}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]
[[Category:SPECTRE members]]
[[Category:On Her Majesty's Secret Service|Henchmen]]

[[fr:Irma Bunt]]
[[nl:Irma Bunt]]
[[pt:Irma Bunt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
