<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708798" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in The Man with the Golden Gun"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">A list of henchmen from the [[1974 in film|1974]] [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Man with the Golden Gun (film)|The Man with the Golden Gun]]'' from the [[List of James Bond henchmen]].  None of these henchmen appears in the novel.

==Andrea Anders==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Andrea Anders
|portrayed=[[Maud Adams]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Francisco Scaramanga]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
{{main|Andrea Anders (James_Bond)|l1=Andrea Anders}}
Ms. Andrea Anders is the mistress of [[Francisco Scaramanga]]. She is portrayed by [[Maud Adams]], the only woman to play two separate Bond girls.

She is responsible for retrieving the custom made gold bullets from munitions manufacturer Lazar and delivering them to Scaramanga. She also provides services to Scaramanga as a lover only before he makes a kill, claiming like bullfighters it improves the eyesight. It is later revealed that it was Ms. Anders who sent the gold bullet to London as well as the note with Scaramanga's fingerprint on it with the hopes of Bond liberating her from Scaramanga's world. Scaramanga disposes of Ms. Anders with the use of his golden gun and gold bullet after learning of her affairs with Bond.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Nick Nack==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Nick Nack
|image=[[Image:NickNack2.jpg]]
|portrayed=[[Hervé Villechaize]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Francisco Scaramanga]]
|status=Captured-final fate unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
{{otheruses2|Nick Nack}}
'''Nick Nack''', played by [[France|French]] actor [[Hervé Villechaize]], is an all-round personal assistant to [[Francisco Scaramanga]], acting as butler, housekeeper, and chef, as well as a [[henchman]] to Scaramanga's criminal activities. Although Nick Nack is very loyal to Scaramanga, he sometimes hires assassins to try and kill him so that he may inherit his estate.  Scaramanga tolerates it as a means to practise his skills.  

After his master's defeat and death, and the loss of his inheritance when Scaramanga's base explodes, Nick Nack tries to kill Bond and Goodnight on the [[Junk (ship)|junk]] and after a short fight, an annoyed Bond stuffs him in a suitcase and locked him in a wooden cage where he awaits MI6 custody.

A distinctive feature of Nick Nack was his height, standing only 1.18 metres (3'11&quot;) tall.

Nick Nack appears in the 1990s animated spin-off, [[James Bond Jr]] as a member of the SCUM organisation and partner-in-crime of fellow henchman [[Jaws (James Bond)|Jaws]].

Nick Nack was an inspiration for [[Doctor Evil]]'s [[Mini-Me]] in the [[Austin Powers (film series)|Austin Powers]] films, which parodied the James Bond series.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

There's a mode in [[GoldenEye 007 (2010 video game)]] called &quot;Nick Nack Mode&quot;. In this mode, you can't go up ladders.

==Kra==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Kra
|portrayed=[[Sonny Caldinez]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Francisco Scaramanga]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
'''Kra''', portrayed by [[Sonny Caldinez]], is a mechanic in charge of maintenance and security at Scaramanga's estate. He appears to be a sleazy guy and is fixated by the body of Mary Goodnight, making her feel physically uncomfortable in her bikini. He is killed during James Bond's raid when he is pushed into a vat of liquid helium by [[Mary Goodnight]], the reason behind the estate's explosion.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Hai Fat==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=[[File:007HaiFat.jpg]]
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Hai Fat
|portrayed=[[Richard Loo]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|age=Unknown
|affiliation= Self-employed, &lt;br&gt; [[Francisco Scaramanga]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Hai Fat''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Man with the Golden Gun (film)|The Man with the Golden Gun]]''. He is a multi-millionaire [[Thailand|Thai]] businessman and is portrayed by the late [[Richard Loo]].

Hai Fat, the owner of Hai Fat Industries, hires [[Francisco Scaramanga]] (the film's central villain) to assassinate the inventor of the &quot;Solex&quot; (a revolutionary solar energy device) and steal the Solex. British agents are also trying to trace the Solex; Hai Fat's name is mentioned and Bond suggests to [[M (James Bond)|M]] that they should meet. Bond then goes to Hai Fat’s property and breaks in, &quot;disguising&quot; himself as [[Scaramanga]] (whom he believes Hai Fat has never met) by applying a fake third nipple, an abnormality of Scaramanga's. Hai Fat tells Bond to leave, but then sees the third nipple on Bond’s chest and tells Bond to join him for dinner that night. Bond believes that Hai Fat thinks he is Scaramanga, but Hai Fat is later seen speaking with the real Scaramanga, telling him that he doesn’t plan for Bond to get in his way.  When Bond goes to dinner, he is knocked out. Scaramanga's henchman [[Nick Nack]] is about to kill him, but Hai Fat stops him, telling him that Bond must go to &quot;school&quot; (which turns out to be a kung fu training school, where he intends that Bond should be killed). Hai Fat is next seen in his office talking to Scaramanga.  Hai Fat tells Scaramanga that he should have never employed him.  Scaramanga silently assembles his Golden Gun, and after Hai Fat takes the Solex out of his safe, Scaramanga shoots him dead. As the new chairman, Scaramanga first order is to have Hai Fat placed in Hai Fat's own tomb.

Hai-Fat almost isn't a henchman, as he is the one that employed Scaramanga as an understudy to his operations and assassin. Chula also is under the employ of Hai Fat as well as Nick Nack to some extent.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Chula==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Chula
|portrayed=[[Chan Yiu Lam]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|age=Unknown
|affiliation=[[List of James Bond henchmen in The Man With The Golden Gun#Hai Fat|Hai Fat]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Chula''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Man with the Golden Gun (film)|The Man with the Golden Gun]]'' portrayed by [[Chan Yiu Lam]]. An intimidating black belt in [[karate]] with a steely stare, he is considered the finest fighter in Hai Fat's school. After Bond kicks out the initial fighter, Chula is cheered on by the school to fight Bond. However before he is able to do much damage Bond is able to escape through the thin wall out onto the road outside where he is met by [[Lieutenant Hip]]. Later Chula and several of the others at the karate school chase Bond down the river but to no avail.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Lazar==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Lazar
|portrayed=[[Marne Maitland]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Self-employment|Self Employed]]/[[Francisco Scaramanga]]
|status=Actve
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
Lazar is an independent munitions manufacturer who resides in [[Macau]]. He is portrayed by the late [[Marne Maitland]]. 
Lazar manufactures the 23 carat signature gold bullets used by Scaramanga and other so called &quot;quality crafted&quot; munitions for other assassins. Bond visits him and asks Lazar that he already made bullets for Francisco Scaramanga. He threatened to shoot him in the groin if he doesn't give Bond information. He later has an order of golden bullets and tells Bond that he has to go to the casino. He is later seen in the casino putting the box of golden bullets in a basket and is never seen again later in the film.
{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|Man With the Golden Gun]]
[[Category:The Man with the Golden Gun (film)|Henchmen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
