<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708870" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in A View to a Kill"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=October 2011}}
A list of henchmen from the [[1985 in film|1985]] [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'' from the [[List of James Bond henchmen]].

==May Day==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[May Day (character)]] --&gt;
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=May Day
|portrayed=[[Grace Jones]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Max Zorin]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

[[Grace Jones|'''May Day''']] is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'', played by actress and singer [[Grace Jones]].

The character makes a return in the multiplayer portion of the [[Nintendo 64]] games, ''[[GoldenEye 007 (1997 video game)|GoldenEye 007]]'' and ''[[The World Is Not Enough (video game)|The World Is Not Enough]]'' and the multiplatform game, ''[[Nightfire]]''.

===Biography===
May Day is the henchwoman and lover of chief villain [[Max Zorin]]. She is portrayed as the head of an all-female group of guards for Zorin. She also has [[superhuman strength]], through her heavy use of [[anabolic steroid]]s. In one scene, she lifts a KGB guard over her head with no apparent effort.

Early in the film, she kills Bond's French contact [[List of James Bond allies in A View to a Kill#Achille Aubergine|Achille Aubergine]] in the restaurant at the top of the [[Eiffel Tower]] using a poisoned stage prop. Bond then goes on a chase to try to track her down. As she parachutes from the tower Bond then tries to follow by hijacking a passing taxi, but she eventually gets away with Zorin in a speedboat in the [[Seine]].

May Day and Bond next meet at Zorin's horse stud farm during his annual thoroughbred sale. She tells Zorin that she recognises Bond (who is using the name James St John Smythe as a cover) from somewhere, but it is not until several hours later that she realises that he was the man at the Eiffel Tower who had chased her.

The two share an intimate evening (where May Day does everything she can to top Bond during sex), but shortly afterwards (after Zorin has uncovered Bond's true identity with the use of a camera on his computer), she strangles Bond's MI6 companion [[Sir Godfrey Tibbett]] while he is taking a [[Rolls-Royce (car)|Rolls-Royce]] through a car wash, and then collaborates with Zorin to try to drown Bond in the car.  

Later in the film, she is onboard Zorin's airship, escorts a Taiwanese tycoon who refuses to take part in Project Main Strike, down to a flight of stairs, and presses a button that collapses the stairs, sending the tycoon falling to his death into the [[San Francisco]] Bay.  At Zorin's oil pumping station, she catches [[KGB]] agent Klotkoff attempting to plant a [[limpet mine]] on the station, resulting in [[Klotoff (007)|Klotkoff]] [[(Bogdan Kominowski)]] being thrown into the intake pipe rotors, chopping him to pieces. Two days later, May Day is with Zorin when he catches Bond and Stacey Sutton in the city hall, confiscates Bond's [[Walther PPK]], and helps Zorin set the building ablaze, though Bond and Stacey manage to escape.  

She is one of a select few henchmen to switch sides during a Bond film; others include [[Pussy Galore]] in ''Goldfinger'' and [[Jaws (James Bond)#Jaws|Jaws]] in ''[[Moonraker (film)|Moonraker]]'', [[Tiffany Case]] in ''[[Diamonds Are Forever (film)|Diamonds Are Forever]]'', Dr. Ladislav Kutze in ''[[Thunderball (film)|Thunderball]]'' and possibly [[Magda (James Bond)|Magda]] from ''[[Octopussy]]''. The switch comes after Zorin floods a mine near [[Silicon Valley]] which he is using in his scheme to destroy the region, thereby cornering the market in microchips. Bond and companion [[Stacey Sutton]] try to escape the mine, with May Day, Pan Ho, and Jenny Flex in pursuit; Sutton gets away, but Bond and May Day fall into the floodwaters.

Once the waters start to subside, the two wind up together again, and see the lifeless bodies of Jenny Flex and others of May Day's colleagues. May is immediately furious at Zorin, since he sees May Day and her partners as completely expendable, and is more than willing to help Bond foil Zorin's plan. The pair then go to a fault where Zorin has set a bomb whose detonation would cause a massive earthquake that would lead to the flooding of Silicon Valley. 

May Day uses her massive upper-body strength to lower Bond to the bomb, lift Bond and the bomb back to the surface, and put the bomb on a handcar to send it out of the mine on an existing railroad line. However, the brakes on the car malfunction and unexpectedly deactivate. May Day realizes that the bomb can only be removed from the mine if she stays on the car and holds the brakes open. Bond tries to get her to jump and save herself, but she tells Bond about the brake problem. Her last words to Bond are ''&quot;Get Zorin for me!&quot;''

As Zorin and his remaining henchmen are sitting in an airship over [[San Francisco Bay]], looking at the culmination of their plan, they suddenly see May Day exiting the mine with the bomb. Zorin exclaims ''&quot;May Day!&quot;'', and the camera then changes to focus on her giving Zorin a defiant stare. The bomb then explodes, instantly killing her, but heroically foiling Zorin's plan. Zorin himself was killed shortly afterwards in a fight with Bond on the [[Golden Gate Bridge]].

==Scarpine==
{{James Bond Character|Scarpine
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Scarpine
|portrayed=[[Patrick Bauchau]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Max Zorin]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Scarpine''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'', played by actor [[Patrick Bauchau]].

===Biography===
Scarpine is introduced to us after Bond clears through his security check with [[Pan Ho]]. He politely introduces himself to Bond and gives him all the necessary information about what events will be taking place at the horse sale and even takes him to the showing. He then sends Bond on his way to the guest quarters to be met by [[Jenny Flex]].

Scarpine is later seen at the party, when Bond uses his polarizing sunglasses to see inside Zorin's office to spy on his meeting with Stacey. He asks how he's enjoying the party and  'St. John Smythe' retorts with a name correction and speaks of how he'll have a good turnout for the sale. As Bond walks away, he sneers at him.  Later Zorin instructs Scarpine to have security ''&quot;Keep a good eye on him[007]&quot;''

As General Gogol comes to confront Zorin at the château and insult him. May Day strongarms the guard and Jenny Flex, Pan Ho, and Scarpine also come out pointing their guns at the KGB General who threatens Zorin that ''&quot;no one ever leaves the KGB&quot;''.

In San Francisco at the City Hall scene where Zorin kills W.G. Howe, Scarpine kills the receptionist (offscreen) and takes control of the ground floor. As Zorin sends Bond and Stacey in the elevator, Scarpine is ready at the controls to stop it in its descent. Zorin then uses Pan Ho's [[Molotov cocktails]] to set the lift alight. Scarpine meets up with his partners in crime and drives away in the car.

Later in the mine, we see Scarpine with Zorin for the majority of the time, though he is handed the dynamite by Jenny Flex, something that would later lead to her own demise. Scarpine then, without anyone else noticing, arms the dynamite and hides it in a mine cart filled with explosives.  He is overseeing the miners' work by consulting with the mine foreman about the seepage issues, but then after the mine is flooded, he assists Zorin in the slaughter of all the innocent mine workers with an [[Uzi]]. Jenny Flex and Pan Ho are killed from the rushing water, while May Day makes peace with Bond. They work feverishly to move the bomb before it explodes, and May Day sacrifices herself, asking Bond to avenge her.

During the conclusion of the film, Scarpine takes flight in the blimp with Zorin and tries kill Bond, who is hanging onto a mooring rope, by ramming him into the [[Golden Gate Bridge]]. However, after the blimp crashes Scarpine is knocked out by [[Stacey Sutton]] with a fire extinguisher and is helpless for most of the fight. Zorin grabs a fire ax and chases Bond onto the bridge where he falls to his death after a brief struggle. Scarpine regains consciousness as Dr. Carl Mortner lights a stick of dynamite and fumbles it, and they are both killed in the explosion which also destroys the blimp.{{-}}

==Jenny Flex==
{{James Bond Character| Jenny Flex
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Jenny Flex
|portrayed=[[Alison Doody]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Max Zorin]]&lt;br&gt;[[May Day]]
|status=[[Deceased]]
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Jenny Flex''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'', played by Irish actress [[Alison Doody]].  She was the youngest [[Bond Girl]] to ever appear.

===Biography===
Jenny Flex is one of two henchwomen to [[May Day (James Bond)|May Day]], the other being Pan Ho. She is first seen in the film walking down the stairs to greet Bond (under the guise of James St. John Smythe) at [[Max Zorin]]'s château. After stating her name to Bond, he reacts in the same way he did to [[Plenty O'Toole]] in ''[[Diamonds Are Forever (film)|Diamonds Are Forever]]'': &quot;''Of course you are''&quot;.  She then escorts Bond and his chauffeur Sir Godfrey Tibbett up to Bond's quarters. Flex is next seen at the reception party at the chateau conversing with Pan Ho and other guests.

Later in the film, when Tibbett is going to get his car washed at the local BP garage so he can telephone [[M (James Bond)|M]] about 007's discoveries, Flex and Pan Ho provide a distraction by pretending to have engine trouble while Tibbett gets the car washed so May Day can murder him. She next is seen while Bond is being disposed of in the [[Rolls-Royce (car)|Rolls-Royce]].

When General Gogol and his men confront Zorin, his henchmen, including Flex, May Day, Scarpine, and Pan Ho outgun them, forcing them to leave. In San Francisco City Hall, when Zorin has murdered W.G. Howe, Flex appears in the doorway with petrol canisters and begins to douse the carpeting so the building can be set aflame. After this, we see her walking out of the office with the canisters and then in the car looking at the destruction she's caused.

In the Main Strike mine sequence, Flex is seen patrolling the grounds and hands Scarpine the tool which leads to her demise: the dynamite (disguised as a coffee thermos) to flood the fault.  After that, she assists in positioning the detonator Zorin intends to use to create a double earthquake, which would be utilized to annihilate [[Silicon Valley]].  Then after Bond and Stacey Sutton are discovered, she chases them with May Day and Pan Ho. After being directed another way by May Day with Pan Ho, Zorin decides to flood the fault before the personnel are evacuated, despite Bob Conley's protests. While the carnage ensues, the film cuts to Jenny and Pan Ho, who are about to be washed away by the oncoming floodwaters.  Their attempts to outrun the waters prove futile, and they both drown. Jenny's dead body is later seen floating in the mine as May Day and Bond are escaping, much to the grief of May Day.

Like many characters in the Bond Universe the name Jenny Flex is a pun - in this case [[Genuflection|genuflect]].

==Pan Ho==
{{James Bond Character|Pan Ho
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Pan Ho
|portrayed=[[Papillon Soo Soo]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Max Zorin]], [[May Day]]
|status=[[Deceased]]
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Pan Ho''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'', played by actress [[Papillon Soo Soo]].

===Biography===
Pan Ho along with Jenny Flex and May Day make up Zorin's deadly trio and main henchwomen. Pan Ho is first seen checking security for the visitors arriving in the château. She halts James Bond's (posing as a wealthy man named James St.John Smythe) Rolls-Royce and takes his invitation to read his name in a very thick Chinese accent.

Pan Ho is later seen at the party, chatting alongside Jenny Flex with the other guests. When Tibbett is getting the car washed and is about to telephone M, he is tailed by Jenny Flex and Pan Ho, providing a distraction so that May Day may strangle and murder him. While Bond is being knocked unconscious in the Rolls-Royce, she is also present.

When Gogol comes to confront Zorin at the château and they insult Zorin. May Day strongarms the guard, Jenny Flex, Pan Ho, and Scarpine also come out pointing their guns at the KGB general who threaten Zorin about ''&quot;No one ever leaving the KGB&quot;''.

In San Francisco at the City Hall scene where Zorin kills W.G. Howe, Pan Ho can be seen in the background making [[Molotov cocktails]] to burn the building down and especially Bond and geologist Stacey Sutton in the elevator. Shortly after, she hands the explosive to Zorin to drop on the elevator, rushes out with one of the gasoline canisters, and can be seen looking at the destruction she's caused in the getaway car.

In the mine, we see Pan Ho patrolling the grounds holding a clipboard, with Zorin when the bomb is being armed, and when he's trying to break into the mine shack. When Stacey and Bond are detected, she, May Day, and Jenny Flex chase after them and May Day separates the group. Zorin then decides to flood the fault much to Bob Conley's protest, and the film, after the destruction ensues, cuts to Pan Ho and Jenny as they confront the oncoming floodwaters with a shriek. We see Pan Ho holding onto the ground for dear life, but she is swept away and drowns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/bond-villains/papillon-soo-soo |title=James Bond multimedia &amp;#124; Papillon Soo Soo (Pan Ho) |publisher=Jamesbondmm.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* It's interesting to note that in the script Pan Ho gets all of Scarpine's lines up to ''&quot;No, no, those are the servant's quarters&quot;''. She also, instead of Scarpine, when Bond is being knocked out and put into the Rolls-Royce, is the one who pats down Bond and knocks him out cold with the gun. In the script, she had a much bigger part than just her one liner.

==Hans Glaub/Carl Mortner==
{{James Bond Character|Hans Glaub/Carl Mortner
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Hans Glaub/Carl Mortner
|portrayed=[[Willoughby Gray]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Max Zorin]], in WWII [[Nazi Germany]] ([[Adolf Hitler]])
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Dr. Hans Glaub''', alias '''Dr. Carl Mortner''', is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[A View to a Kill]]'', played by [[Willoughby Gray]].

===Biography===
Dr. Hans Glaub was a [[Nazi Germany|Nazi]] [[German people|German]] [[physician]] who conducted [[Nazi human experimentation|medical experiments]] on [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration camp]] inmates during [[World War II]]. One particular experiment would play a major role in the plot of the film—he had [[pregnancy|pregnant]] women injected with massive quantities of [[anabolic steroid|steroids]] in an attempt to create &quot;super-children&quot;. The large majority of the pregnancies ended in [[miscarriage]]. A few babies were born and grew to be exceptionally intelligent; unfortunately for the survivors, the experiments had a severe side effect—[[psychosis]]. One of the babies born from the experiments was the film's villain, Max Zorin.

After the war, the victorious [[Allies of World War II|Western Allies]] sought to try Glaub as a [[war crimes|war criminal]], but he was spirited away by the [[Soviet Union]], where he continued his experiments with steroids; the Soviets ordered him to be [[doping (sport)|doping]] their athletes. Sometime during this period, he took the Mortner alias (in the German release version, Mortner's former identity was that of a Polish communist named Jan Kopersky). Sometime in the [[1960]]s he had escaped the USSR, which Bond points out was the same exact time Zorin appeared in the West. While not directly mentioned in the film, it is strongly implied that Glaub/Mortner raised the young Zorin, explaining why Mortner is practically the only person Zorin somewhat cares for. He also worked with the adult Zorin, developing a doping program for Zorin's [[thoroughbred]] [[horse racing|race horses]].

He meets his end shortly after Bond and Zorin have their final fight on the [[Golden Gate Bridge]]. He awakens after having been knocked unconscious by [[Stacey Sutton]] (who had been snatched minutes earlier by Zorin, who wanted to gain revenge on Bond for the death of Mayday) in Zorin's airship immediately before the fight. When Mortner sees Zorin fall to his death from the bridge, he reacts violently. First, he pulls out a pistol and fires at Bond and Sutton. Once his pistol runs out of ammunition, he goes into a cabinet, pulls out a small bundle of [[dynamite]], lights the fuse, and prepares to throw the dynamite at Bond. Bond quickly reacts, grabbing the axe that Zorin had used in their fight and cutting the mooring rope, which Bond had previously tied to the bridge superstructure. 

The shock of the unmooring causes Mortner to lose his balance, forcing him to let go of the dynamite, which rattles around the cabin. The shock also awakens Scarpine; the two struggle to grab the dynamite and throw it out. A now suicidal Mortner grabs the dynamite, but by that time it is too late; the dynamite immediately explodes, killing them and destroying the airship while Bond and Stacey make their escape.
[http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/bond-villains/willoughby-gray]
{{-}}

==Bob Conley==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=[[Bob Conley]]
[http://web.njit.edu/~conley/ConleyPic.JPG]
|portrayed=[[Manning Redwood]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Self-Employed &lt;br&gt; [[Max Zorin]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Villain]]
}}

'''Bob Conley''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film, ''A View To A Kill'', portrayed by Manning Redwood.

Conley is first seen at Max Zorin's party as Dr. Carl Mortner introduces him to Bond. He is introduced as a Texas businessman involved with oil, which makes Bond suspicious, as since a numerous number of people were involved with oil as well.  Before working with Zorin, Conley worked in a [[South African]] gold mine, but hastily escaped when a cave-in caused the 20 deaths of his fellow workers, leading to his departure from South Africa.  Later in the film, Conley can be seen in the meeting room located in the interior Zorin's airship

He is seen again with Zorin, as a pawn in his plan to dominate Silicon Valley, pumping sea water in the oil. He tells Zorin that the pump should flow at least the minimum amount. Zorin tells him to maximize it, which he hesitates to do.

Conley is with Zorin inside the cave when Project: Main Strike is about to occur while Zorin is arming the detonator. His men then lower Conley standing on the crane positioning the detonator into the pit filled with literally tons of explosives.  Conley then places it in the correct spot, and then yells for his men to raise him back up. When 007 and geologist Stacey Sutton are detected, Zorin commands Conley to &quot;''close up the entrance; nobody gets out.''&quot;   Soon Zorin realizes that Conley's men can't be trusted anymore. He intends to kill all of them, and is prepared to sacrifice May Day's life. Conley argues against this, reminding him of how loyal his workers are to him, but is hit in the back by Zorin's henchman [[#Scarpine|Scarpine]] and throws him off a ledge. The workers rush to aid the presumably dying Conley whilst Zorin floods the fault and begins to shoot at his workers with a machine gun. The workers are forced to leave Conley for dead when Zorin opens fire. 
{{-}}

==W.G. Howe==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=W.G. Howe
|portrayed=[[Daniel Benzali]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Self-Employed &lt;br&gt; [[Max Zorin]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''W.G. Howe''' is portrayed by [[Daniel Benzali]].

Howe is [[Stacey Sutton]]'s employer and Director of Oil and Mines for the state of [[California]]. He is on the payroll of [[Max Zorin]], who uses him to fudge records and cover up Zorin's illegal mine work.

When Stacey finds him out, Howe fires her, but soon, having outlived his usefulness, Zorin decides to kill him. Having already cornered Bond and Stacey near Howe's office in [[San Francisco City Hall]], Zorin shoots Howe dead and decides to blame it on Bond before starting a fire which he is confident will kill Bond and Stacey in the lift. However, they manage to escape and climb down the ladder of a fire engine, and by the time they reach the ground, emergency services have found Howe's corpse and the police are blaming Bond. However, before they can arrest him, he and Stacey escape in a fire engine and finally manage to outrun the police. [http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/bond-villains/daniel-benzali]

{{-}}

==Venz==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Venz
|portrayed=[[Dolph Lundgren]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[KGB]]
|status=Active
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
One of General Gogol's KGB henchmen. [[Dolph Lundgren]] got his first movie role as Venz through [[Grace Jones]] (May Day), whom which he was dating and living with at the time. That same year, he went to star as [[Ivan Drago]], [[Rocky Balboa]]'s Russian opponent in the film [[Rocky IV]].

{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|View]]
[[Category:James Bond characters]]

[[Category:A View to a Kill|Henchmen]]

[[pt:May Day]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
