<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708854" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in For Your Eyes Only"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2008}}
A list of henchmen from the [[1981 in film|1981]] [[James Bond]] film and short story ''[[For Your Eyes Only (film)|For Your Eyes Only]]'' from the [[List of James Bond henchmen]].

==Emile Locque==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Emile Locque
|portrayed=[[Michael Gothard]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]]&lt;!--The character is Aristotle in the original short story, but the movie consistently refers to him as &quot;Aris&quot;.--&gt;
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Emile Leopold Locque''' is a [[fictional character]] and [[List of James Bond villains|henchman]] working for [[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[For Your Eyes Only (film)|For Your Eyes Only]]''. He is played by [[Michael Gothard]]. He is not heard to speak during the film, although he is not [[Muteness|mute]]: at one point, he is seen speaking into a car phone (although his voice is never heard), and he screams in terror in his final scene.

===Biography===
Locque is a brutal killer who was originally involved with drug syndicates in [[Marseille]] and [[Hong Kong]], eventually becoming an enforcer in the [[Brussels]] underworld. He was arrested and sent to prison in [[Namur (city)|Namur]], [[Belgium]]; however, he broke out after strangling his [[psychiatrist]]. Locque is known to leave a dove pin on his victims after killing them, although that appears to have been part of his attempt to frame [[Milos Columbo]], who is known as &quot;The Dove.&quot; Distinguishing characteristics on Locque also include [[octagon]]al glasses, which are identified in a comical scene where Q attempts different types of eyewear on a computer composite sketch after mistakingly making Locque's nose like Pinocchio's. 

Locque is first seen at the home of [[#Hector Gonzales|Hector Gonzales]], where he pays Gonzales on behalf of Kristatos for killing [[Judy Havelock|Melina Havelock]]'s parents. The Havelocks were on a special assignment to find a sunken ship that holds ATAC, a machine used by the [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] to communicate and co-ordinate the [[Royal Navy]]'s fleet of [[UGM-27 Polaris|Polaris]] [[submarines]]. He kills a male guest in the swimming pool at Gonzales's mansion - the first of the killings he commits in the film.

After Melina assassinates Gonzales, Locque takes the cash back. Bond later follows Locque to the [[Alps]] where he is attacked while skiing by both Locque and another hitman. Later, Locque returns and kills Luigi Ferrara, Bond's Italian contact, and leaves his signature dove pin for Bond to find in the his parked [[Lotus Esprit]] where Ferrara had been sitting while Bond was visiting [[Bibi Dahl]]. Locque killed Ferrara by slitting his throat with a knife. 

Columbo told him this after he had Bond captured just as Locque was preparing to shoot him on a beach where he had already run over and killed Countess Lisl von Schraff, having presumably been alerted to them by Apostis, who had driven Bond and Lisl to her house in his car and overheard the conversation between them about Kristatos. Bond had managed to avoid being killed by Locque by kicking a gun from his hand, while Locque's armed accomplice was gunned down by one of the four men who captured Bond on Columbo's orders.

After meeting Columbo, Bond learns from him that Kristatos is working for the [[KGB]] and attempting to find the missing ATAC on their behalf. He also informs him that Locque is working for Kristatos, and not for Columbo as Kristatos had earlier told him.

On a mission to prove that it is Kristatos, Columbo involves Bond in a raid of one of Kristatos's opium warehouses in [[Albania]] where Locque is found inside. During the ensuing battle between Kristatos's and Columbo's men, Locque guns down several of the latter's thugs. He then sets up a booby trap by attaching a detonator to one of the large sea mines in the warehouse itself in an attempt to kill Bond and Columbo, which fails but annihilates all the raw opium stored inside.  After attempting to escape, Locque becomes trapped in his [[Mercedes-Benz W116|Mercedes-Benz 450 SEL]] teetering on the edge of a cliff after Bond fired a shot through the windscreen and wounded Locque's arm. Bond subsequently tosses Locque his trademark dove pin that he left on Ferrara and then kicks the car over the edge, killing Locque in the fall to the rocks below. His body is seen falling from the car when it lands on the rocks. Bond comments that he had no head for heights to his allies.

==Hector Gonzales==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Hector Gonzales
|portrayed=[[Stefan Kalipha]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Herr von Hammerstein (short story)&lt;br/&gt;[[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]] (film)
|status=Deceased
|role= [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Hector Gonzales''' is a character from the [[Ian Fleming]] short story &quot;[[For Your Eyes Only (short story)|For Your Eyes Only]]&quot; and the homonymous film, where he is portrayed by Stefan Kalipha. In both he is a [[Cuba]]n [[hitman]] with no particular style or modus operandi.

===Short story biography===
In the short story, Gonzales is hired by Herr von Hammerstein, a [[Nazi]] [[war crime|war criminal]], to kill a [[Jamaica]]n couple, the Havelocks, so von Hammerstein could get their property. James Bond is then sent by [[M (James Bond)|M]], who was a friend of the Havelocks, to track down von Hammerstein. In [[Vermont]], von Hammerstein is killed by [[Judy Havelock]], the dead couple's daughter. In the shootout that follows, Bond kills von Hammerstein's henchmen, including Gonzales, and escapes with Judy.

===Film biography===
In the film, Gonzales is hired by [[#Emile Locque|Emile Locque]] to assassinate oceanographer Timothy Havelock and his wife Iona, as they were working secretly for the British to recover [[NATO]]'s ATAC system from the wreck of the St. Georges. Having brought the couple's daughter, [[Judy Havelock|Melina]] by a seaplane to the Havelock's yacht, Gonzales makes a second run over the boat and uses his plane's hidden machine guns on the Havelocks' boat. Only Melina survives, and she describes him to the Greek police, giving MI6 their only lead to begin investigations. Bond is sent to Gonzales' poolside estate in [[Madrid]] to interrogate him, where he sees him at a party being paid a large sum of money by Locque. Bond gets captured and ordered to be killed by Gonzales. However, a vengeful Melina, hidden in the bushes, shoots Gonzales with a crossbow, killing him as he dives into the swimming pool, and enabling Bond to escape.

==Erich Kriegler==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Erich Kriegler
|portrayed=[[John Wyman]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[KGB]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[Bond villain]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Erich Kriegler''', portrayed by British actor [[John Wyman]], is an [[East Germany|East German]] [[biathlon|biathlete]] and [[KGB]] thug, who is hired by [[Aristotle Kristatos]] to kill Bond and deliver the ATAC submarine tracking device from the sunken British ship to the Russians. He is also the object of [[Bibi Dahl]]'s  passion. Posing as a seemingly innocent sportsman&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/bond-villains/john-wyman |title=James Bond multimedia &amp;#124; John Wyman (Eric Kriegler) |publisher=Jamesbondmm.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; he tries to catch Bond in [[Cortina]] twice, first by pursuing him in a ski chase through the Italian alps (firing shots at him before unsuccessfully trying to hit him by throwing the gun), then (joined by two other men) by attacking him dressing as a [[ice hockey]] player where Bond has just said farewell to [[Bibi Dahl]]. He is next seen days later aboard Kristatos' yacht and helps capture 007 and Melina Havelock. Later in the St. Cyrill monastery, he meets his death by being shoved out of the window in a fight with Bond using a spiked [[candelabra]], falling all the way to the bottom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/bond-villains/john-wyman |title=James Bond multimedia &amp;#124; John Wyman (Eric Kriegler) |publisher=Jamesbondmm.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kriegler is the fifth in a line of tall, blond, Germanic henchmen to fight 007, which include Red Grant from ''[[From Russia With Love (film)|From Russia With Love]]'', [[Vargas (James Bond)|Vargas]] from ''[[Thunderball (film)|Thunderball]]'', Hans from ''[[You Only Live Twice (film)|You Only Live Twice]]'', [[List of James Bond henchmen in Diamonds are Forever|Peter Franks]] in ''[[Diamonds Are Forever (film)|Diamonds Are Forever]]'', Necros from ''[[The Living Daylights (film)|The Living Daylights]]'' and Stamper from ''[[Tomorrow Never Dies (film)|Tomorrow Never Dies]]''

==Apostis==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Apostis
|portrayed=[[Jack Klaff]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]]
|status=Deceased
|role= [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Apostis''' is a [[fictional character]] and [[List of James Bond villains|henchman]] working for [[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[For Your Eyes Only (film)|For Your Eyes Only]]''. He is a [[Greeks|Greek]] character  played by [[Jack Klaff]]. He serves as Kristatos' chauffeur when he drives 007 and Milos Columbo's mistress Countess Lisl von Schlaf to her home.  He apparently informs Emile Locque of their location, resulting in Lisl's death. He is later ordered by his boss to take the ATAC to St. Cyril's after aiding in the capture James Bond and Melina Havelock. There, he tries to thwart Bond's rock-climbing by knocking out his piton hooks from above, but just as he is working the last hook loose, Bond throws a [[piton]] into his chest and he falls to his death.

==Claus==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Claus
|portrayed=[[Charles Dance]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]]
|status=Deceased
|role= [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Claus''' is a [[fictional character]] and [[List of James Bond villains|henchman]] working for [[Aristotle Kristatos|Aris Kristatos]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[For Your Eyes Only (film)|For Your Eyes Only]]''. He is played by [[Charles Dance]], in his early appearance. Claus is Locque's assistant, always seen at his side. Like his employer, he is a professional [[hitman]]. He is killed by a [[harpoon]] fired by one of Columbo's men on the beach in Greece where Locque has just killed Lisl von Schlaff, just as he and Locque preparing to shoot Bond.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|For Your Eyes Only]]
[[Category:For Your Eyes Only (film)|Henchmen]]

[[pt:Emile Locque]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
