<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708987" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in Casino Royale"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{notability|notability|date=January 2009}}
{{unreferenced|date=February 2008}}
{{plot|date=January 2009}}

:''This list does not include henchmen from the [[Casino Royale (1967 film)|1967 film of the same name]].''
A list of [[henchmen]] from the original [[1953]] [[Casino Royale (novel)|novel]] and [[2006 in film|2006]] [[James Bond]] film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'' from the [[List of James Bond henchmen]].

==Steven Obanno==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed:  [[image:006CSR Mads Mikkelsen 013-1-.jpg|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 29 April 2009}}]] --&gt;
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Steven Obanno
|portrayed=[[Isaach De Bankolé]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Lord's Resistance Army]], &lt;br&gt; 
[[Quantum (James Bond)|Quantum]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Villain]]
}}
'''Steven Obanno''' is a [[List of James Bond villains|villain]] in the 2006 [[James Bond]] film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]''. He is portrayed by [[Isaach De Bankolé]].

Obanno is a high ranking member of the [[Lord's Resistance Army]]. He also has ties to Quantum represented by the mysterious [[White (James Bond)|Mr. White]]. Obanno banks a considerable sum ($101,206,000) with another of White's associates, [[Le Chiffre]]. 

Le Chiffre ends up losing Obanno's money when one of his [[Short (finance)|stock shorting]] schemes fails due to Bond's intervention. Without notifying Obanno or Mr. White, Le Chiffre arranges a high-stakes poker tournament at Casino Royale in [[Montenegro]] to recoup the loss.   

When Obanno learns of the loss of his money, he and his bodyguard travel to Montenegro, break into Le Chiffre's hotel suite and ambush him and his mistress Valenka; threatening to cut off one of her arms. Le Chiffre, however, is not moved by the threat and implores Obanno to give him one day to win the tournament and recoup the loss. Obanno grants this and leaves the suite. In the hall, Obanno and his bodyguard notice Bond and Vesper lurking in the vicinity. When the bodyguard sees the hearing device in Bond's ear, he moves to attack Bond, who throws him over a stairwell to his death. Obanno then attacks Bond with a machete concealed inside his jacket. He and Bond then engage a brutal fight in the stairwell. As the fight ends at the bottom of the stairwell, Bond gains the upper hand and throttles Obanno to death. Mathis then disposes of their bodies by putting them in the car trunk belonging to Leo, one of Le Chiffre's henchmen, framing him for their murders.

{{-}}

==Alex Dimitrios==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed:  [[image:Dimitrios-1-.jpg|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 29 April 2009}}]]  --&gt;
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Alex Dimitrios
|portrayed=[[Simon Abkarian]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Le Chiffre]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
|relatives= '''Wife:''' [[Solange Dimitrios]] (Deceased)
}}

'''Alex Dimitrios''' is a fictional villain in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]''. He is portrayed by Armenian-French actor [[Simon Abkarian]].

Dimitrios is a [[government contractor]] who has worked in [[Iraq]], [[Afghanistan]], [[Chechnya]], [[Rwanda]], [[Nicaragua]], and [[El Salvador]]. He is also a dealer in arms and information with ties to various [[death squads]] and right-wing paramilitary groups around the world. He is a known associate of [[terrorist]] financier [[Le Chiffre]], who uses him to do the dirty work in many of his stock shorting schemes. He is married to [[Solange Dimitrios|Solange]]. In the film he's tasked with hiring someone to blow up a new [[superjumbo]] airliner that is to be unveiled at Miami International Airport.

Dimitrios and Solange are in the Bahamas when they encounter Bond. He and Bond play a game of poker, which results in Bond winning an [[Aston Martin DB5]]. Later that night when 007 seduces Solange, Dimitrios calls to tell her that he is on his way to Miami. Bond tails Dimitrios to Miami where he is to meet with Carlos at a [[Body Worlds]] exhibit. While he is there, Dimitrios leaves his baggage that contains the [[Miami International Airport]] Security uniform for Carlos to pick up. He is killed when Bond quietly stabs him and leaves his body at the exhibit after a struggle with the latter's [[stilleto]]. According to his file in ''Quantum Of Solace'' video game, he was born in [[Lebanon]].

{{-}}

==Valenka==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed:  [[image:Vane.jpg|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 29 April 2009}}]] --&gt;
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Valenka
|portrayed=[[Ivana Miličević]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Le Chiffre]] 
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]
}}

'''Valenka''', played by [[Ivana Miličević]], is a [[Bond girl]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'', though she does not interact romantically with Bond.

Valenka is the alluring companion of [[Le Chiffre]], following him wherever he goes, and is also romantically involved with him (though in the novel, it is stated that Le Chiffre is a heavy womanizer though he plans on settling down and having a family). She is first seen swimming in the sea next to Le Chiffre's luxurious yacht in a blue swimsuit while they are in the Bahamas. She encounters Bond during the poker tournament in Montenegro, and poisons his drink on Le Chiffre's orders. Along with Le Chiffre, she is attacked by [[Steven Obanno]] and his henchman in their hotel room. Obanno threatens to cut off her arm with a [[machete]] - notably, Le Chiffre does not protest her impending dismemberment, causing Obanno to tell Valenka that she should get a better boyfriend. Obanno does not cut off her arm, however, and she stays with Le Chiffre. She is killed by Mr. White along with Le Chiffre and the rest of his associates.
{{-}}

==Kratt==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Kratt
|portrayed=[[Clemens Schick]]
|StandIn=[[Clemens Schick]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Le Chiffre]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
'''Kratt''' is a henchman to the villain [[Le Chiffre]] in the 2006 film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]''.

Kratt is Le Chiffre's shaven-headed right-hand man–bodyguard and is never far from his side. He first appears in Uganda when Le Chiffre meets [[Steven Obanno]]. After bomb-maker Mollaka was killed by James Bond, Kratt informs Le Chiffre of this setback on board his [[Sunseeker]] yacht in the [[Bahamas]]. When terrorist middleman Alex Dimitrios comes to meet with Le Chiffre at the yacht, Kratt frisks Dimitrios for weapons and the henchman then leads Dimitrios on board. Kratt is also present at the subsequent meeting between the two. Later in Montenegro, after Bond crashes his Aston Martin, Kratt uses a [[butterfly knife]] to dig a minuscule tracking device implanted in 007's forearm. When Le Chiffre and his entourage take a captured Bond and treasury agent [[Vesper Lynd]] aboard a barge, Kratt once again uses his knife, this time to cut the seat off a cane-bottomed chair, then strips Bond of his clothing and ties him to the chair. He is killed along with Le Chiffre by Mr. White when found torturing Bond and Vesper.{{-}}

==Leo==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Leo
|portrayed=[[Emmanuel Avena]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Le Chiffre]]
|status=Arrested
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Leo''' is a henchman to the villain [[Le Chiffre]] in the 2006 film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]''.

Leo is one of Le Chiffre's henchmen who first appears alongside Kratt at the Casino Royale in Montenegro. He is arrested by the local police after Bond's ally Mathis places the bodies of [[Steven Obanno]] and his bodyguard in the trunk of his car, framing Leo for their murders.
{{-}}


==Mollaka==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed:  [[image:BOND -- SEBASTION FOUCAN AS MOLLAKA-254x163-1-.jpg|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 29 April 2009}}]] --&gt;
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Mollaka
|portrayed=[[Sébastien Foucan]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Le Chiffre]] &lt;br&gt;
[[Alex Dimitrios]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Mollaka''', played by [[Sébastien Foucan]], is a freelance bomb maker hired by Alex Dimitrios on behalf of [[Le Chiffre]].

Mollaka is encountered in Madagascar where he is being shadowed by [[MI6]] agents James Bond and his co-agent Carter at a [[mongoose]]/[[cobra]] fight at an abandoned hotel. Due to a foolish mistake made by Carter, who, by constantly touching his earpiece to communicate with Bond, blows his cover, Mollaka catches on and leads Bond on a high speed footchase through the jungle and through a construction site. At first, Mollaka takes cover behind a pile of pipes with his pistol drawn, believing he has given 007 the slip. He is mistaken; Bond had hijacked a bulldozer and uses it to plow through other obstacles in his way. Mollaka fires at him but Bond is protected by the bulldozer's bulletproof windshield. The bomb maker then races up the girders forming the skeleton of a building with ease. Bond follows by running up the arm of a crane just as authorities arrive at the scene. A construction worker swings at Mollaka with a welding torch before the latter kicks the worker off the beam on which he is standing. Mollaka climbs up a ladder to the top after shooting two police officers and then jumps onto a load of pipes being suspended high above the ground by a towering crane. Following this stunt, Mollaka, who is still being tailed by Bond climbs up the crane cable to the top of the crane. After Bond catches up to his quarry's position, Mollaka shoots at 007 again only to discover that the pistol is out of ammunition. In anger, he throws the gun at Bond, who catches it and returns the favor, nearly throwing Mollaka off the crane. The two have a brief fistfight before Mollaka leaps onto another crane and then jumping onto the roof below him. Bond follows him the same way through another building under construction where, at one point, the terrorist jumps down an elevator shaft, vaults off of the wall, and lands into the floor below. Bond pursues Mollaka to the Nambutu Embassy, where he was an employee. Bond follows him into the embassy where he incapacitates Mollaka and attempts to take him into custody and hold Mollaka hostage when cornered by the embassy guards after being shot at in a firefight. Bond momentarily lets Mollaka go, but then suddenly draws a concealed pistol from his waist and shoots Mollaka in the chest, killing him.  Bond then immediately shoots a gas tank, causing an explosion that disorients the embassy guard and gives Bond the opportunity to escape. Bond manages to steal Mollaka's backpack that contains a [[time bomb]] and cellphone which eventually leads him to [[Alex Dimitrios]] in the Bahamas. When Bond &quot;murdered&quot; Mollaka, the exact scene when he was shot was captured on a security camera directly behind Bond, and the photo became front-page news coverage in [[England]]. This event forces Le Chiffre to hire another terrorist bomber, Carlos. 

He is a very physically fit and agile man who utilizes [[free running]] techniques whilst being chased. In reality, the actor who portrayed him was the cofounder of modern free running.

{{-}}

==Carlos==

{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Carlos
|portrayed=[[Claudio Santamaria]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Le Chiffre]] &lt;br&gt;
[[Alex Dimitrios]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Carlos''' is a freelance terrorist hired by [[Alex Dimitrios]] on behalf of [[Le Chiffre]] to destroy the new superjumbo airliner prototype at Miami International Airport. He is Mollaka's replacement. 

Carlos is first seen by Bond as he leaves the [[Body Worlds]] exhibit in Miami. Bond tails him to [[Miami International Airport]] where he loses track of Carlos after they clear the security checkpoint. Carlos changes into a uniform worn by the [[Miami-Dade Police Department]] and sneaks into the secure area where he sets off the airport's [[fire sprinkler]]s causing a mass panic and evacuation at the airport. Under the cover of the chaos, he drives onto the tarmac and kills an airport tanker driver by breaking his neck.  

He secures a small but powerful keyring bomb on the truck's undercarriage and arms it on his cell phone, which is the remote control for the bomb before he drives away with it. Bond makes it on to the tarmac and gives chase before leaping onto the back of the tanker. In an attempt to shake Bond off, Carlos side-sweeps a tow tug, but 007 leaps off before it strikes. Carlos then reverses while attempting to shoot Bond with the pistol he obtained from the airport armory, and then makes a sharp turn back into forward driving. Carlos drives the tanker into various airport vehicles, like a luggage flatbed train and an articulated bus, attracting the attention of the police and security personnel. Bond makes it into the cab and a brutal fight ensues with Carlos leaping from the tanker (after the terrorist strapped the safety belt through the steering wheel in order to keep the tanker at a speedy rate) as it crashes towards the superjumbo airliner. At the last second Bond takes control of the tanker and brings it to a stop inches near the airliner. Bond is mistaken for the terrorist and is violently subdued by the police. He sees Carlos off in the distance about to detonate the bomb on his cell phone. Unknown to Carlos, Bond had removed the bomb from the tanker and clipped it to Carlos' belt, and Carlos dies from the resulting explosion.

==Gettler==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed:  [[image:Gettler-1-.jpg|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 29 April 2009}}]]  --&gt;
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Gettler
|portrayed=[[Richard Sammel]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SMERSH (James Bond)|SMERSH]] (novel)&lt;br&gt;[[Quantum (James Bond)|Quantum]] (film)
|status= Active (novel) &lt;br&gt; Deceased (film)
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Gettler''' is an assassin working for [[Quantum (James Bond)|Quantum]] (in the film) and [[SMERSH (James Bond)|SMERSH]] (in the novel). He wears a Panama hat in both the film and novel. Also, he wears an eyepatch in the novel, while in the film he wears glasses with a darkened left lens. He is supposedly a Swiss watch salesman.

===Novel bio===
'''Adolph Gettler''' is a [[SMERSH (James Bond)|SMERSH]] operative sent to hunt down Bond and Vesper after [[Le Chiffre]] is killed by SMERSH itself. He fails when Vesper commits suicide. 

===Film bio===
Gettler is first seen by Vesper in Venice as she and Bond go down the [[Grand Canal (Venice)|Grand Canal]] in their yacht. After Bond uncovers Vesper's betrayal, he runs across the city trying to locate her and finds her about to hand off the funds from the poker game with [[Le Chiffre]] to Gettler. Gettler takes Vesper hostage with a dagger and Bond chases them into a building under renovation, all the while having to outrun gunfire from Gettler's men. When Gettler's bodyguard, The Tall Man, attempts to shoot Bond, the agent causes the building to sink into the Grand Canal, thus starting an all-out brawl between Gettler's thugs and Bond whilst avoiding the steadily rising water level. During this fight Gettler's main weapon is a [[Jericho 941]]. As the briefcase full of money drifts off the edge of a floorboard, Gettler tries to grab it before it falls into the water below. He loses the case, but it is later retrieved by [[Mr. White (James Bond)|Mr. White]]. During the brawl Gettler aids in the fight against Bond although he primarily stays out of range. Bond fights his way through several thugs, and finally kills Gettler by shooting his left eye (the one covered with a darkened lens) with the same [[nailgun]] that Gettler attempted to kill Bond with moments before. Gettler's corpse is then left sitting on the ground as the building sinks into the canal.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Dryden==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Dryden
|portrayed=[[Malcolm Sinclair]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[MI6]]/unknown
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Villain]]
}}
'''Dryden''' is a [[List of James Bond villains|villain]] from the [[2006 in film|2006]] ''[[James Bond]] film [[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]''. Although technically not a henchman, he is not a main villain either.  

===Film biography===
Dryden is seen in the pre-title sequence. In [[Prague]], he drives up to his office. He is about to sit down when [[James Bond (character)|James Bond]] interrupts him. Bond says [[M (James Bond)|M]] knows he is selling MI6 secrets. Dryden replies that if M was so sure, she would have sent a double-0 (00) agent. Bond, who is not yet 007, tells Dryden he has already killed one (Fisher) and needs another. Dryden attempts to shoot Bond, but finds that Bond has removed the ammunition. Bond then kills Dryden.

In the moment when Bond shoots him, a photo of Dryden together with his wife and daughter is shown for a split second, which he takes with him to his death.

===Novel biography===
Although never mentioned by name in the books, [[Ian Fleming]] mentions how Bond obtained his 00 license. One of the men he kills was a [[Japanese people|Japanese]] [[cipher]] expert on the 36th floor of the [[GE Building|RCA Building]] in New York (although this attack was carried out with a sniper rifle from an adjoining building). The other man he kills was a [[double agent]] in [[Stockholm]], which was probably the inspiration for Dryden, even though he was, in the book, killed with a knife. It also says &quot;and.. well he just didn't die so quickly.&quot;

{{-}}

==Fisher==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Fisher
|portrayed=[[Daud Shah (actor)|Daud Shah]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Dryden
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
'''Fisher''' is a henchman or contact to Dryden in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'' (his name is never actually uttered on screen). His exact relationship with Dryden is not established on screen. He is notable as the first man to be killed by James Bond, and the first of two kills required in order for Bond to qualify for 00-status. Bond's killing of Fisher is shown in a flashback just prior to Bond's killing of Dryden. Bond and Fisher engage in hand-to-hand combat in a men's washroom (the exact location of which is not indicated.

Fisher heads to the cricket game hoping to catch Bond there. After a while he notices Bond casually standing in the stand, Fisher then remembers he forgot the gun he got from Dryden and makes a quick rush up to the changing-rooms where he hid it and ran into the bathroom and screams 'OUT' and as the man is walking out, Bond rushes in and knocks the gun out of Fisher's hand, starting a fight, Both combatants have guns, but the majority of the fight involves Bond and Fisher throwing each other through toilets and cubicle walls. 

Eventually, Bond gets the upper hand by throwing Fisher against the wall and knocking him to the ground, he drags Fisher to the sink and appears to drown Fisher in a sink. However, as Bond turns to retrieve his gun, Fisher, who feigned his death, grabs his own gun. Bond turns and fires, and this is shown on screen as a modified version of the [[James Bond gun barrel sequence|traditional gun barrel sequence]] and leads into the opening credits.

{{-}}

== Tall Man==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name= Tall Man
|portrayed=[[Leos Stransky]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Gettler]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

Tall Man is Gettler's main bodyguard/Henchman during the Venice climax and the only other villain credited from that sequence. He is played by Actor/Stuntman Leos Stransky.

Tall Man first appears alongside Gettler when they are to retrieve the money from Vesper. Gettler is shown handing the silver case containing the money to Tall Man who is standing behind him. When Bond is discovered Tall Man flees with Gettler taking Vesper as their hostage and escaping into a building under renovation. Tall Man takes position on the upper floor waiting for Bond to come through the doors but is thrown off balance when Bond shoots out the air bags holding up the building's foundations. Bond fights his way through the other assassins before confronting Tall Man. The two are seen crashing through a wall whereafter Bond stuns him with a blow to the face and uses him for a human shield as Gettler opens fire, shooting Tall Man in the shoulder. He is finally killed when the elevator shaft in the center breaks free and crushes him to death.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Obanno's Lieutenant==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name= Obanno's Lieutenant
|portrayed=Michael Offei
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Steven Obanno]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Obanno's Lieutenant''' is a henchman to Steven Obanno, although he never has any speaking role.

Obanno's Lieutenant appears in Uganda. Whilst Obanno talks to the sinister Mr. White, Obanno's Lieutenant keeps his eye on the doorway, his job apparently being to keep a lookout for Le Chiffre and Kratt who are expected. Later when Le Chiffre and Kratt arrive he opens up several suitcases of money, and then later helps put the funds in the back of Le Chiffre's convoy.

Obanno's Lieutenant later appears in the Casino Royale where he ambushes Le Chiffre and his girlfriend Valenka in their hotel room. Whilst holding Valenka, Obanno's Lieutenant forces her to hold out her arm, after Obanno demands a keepsake for the betrayal, but saying that Le Chiffre needs his hand to play cards. After Obanno grants Le Chiffre some more time to get the money, Obanno and his Lieutenant leave. Whilst he and Obanno are exiting through the hallway they see James Bond and Vesper Lynd standing in a doorway kissing. However, Obanno's Lieutenant spots the earpiece in Bond's ear and hears Valenka's gasping. He draws a gun and shoots at Bond, although missing him by inches. As he chases Bond into the stairwell, Bond grabs his arm and throws him over the stairs to his death. His body is later seen in Le Chiffre's henchman Leo's car trunk so as to frame the latter for murder, leading to his arrest.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

{{James Bond characters}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of James Bond Henchmen In Casino Royale}}
[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|Casino Royale]]
[[Category:Casino Royale (2006 film)|Henchmen]]

[[pt:Valenka]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
