<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708581" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in Dr. No"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=February 2008}}
A list of henchman from the [[1962 in film|1962]] [[James Bond]] [[Dr. No (novel)|novel]] and [[Dr. No (film)|film]] ''Dr. No'' from the [[List of James Bond henchmen]].

==Miss Taro==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Miss Taro
|portrayed=[[Zena Marshall]]
|gender=Female
|affiliation=[[Dr. Julius No]], [[List of James Bond allies in Dr. No#Pleydell-Smith|Pleydell-Smith]] (formerly)
|status=Arrested
|role=[[Bond girl]]/[[List of James Bond henchmen|Henchwoman]]
}}

'''Miss Taro''' ([[Zena Marshall]]) is the leading villainess from ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]'', the series' debut film. She is a [[Bond girl]] and a [[List of James Bond henchmen|Henchwoman]]. She is a secretary in the Government House, in [[Kingston, Jamaica]], to Colonial Secretary, Pleydell-Smith. She also is a henchwoman and spy to [[Doctor Julius No]]; only Bond discovers this.

Bond first meets Miss Taro, a [[Chinese Jamaican]], at Government House. When she grasps that Bond and Pleydell-Smith are talking about Dr. No, she spies through the keyhole of his office door. Bond then persuades her to a rendezvous at her house outside of Kingston; he does not know she is a Spectre agent. Enroute to her house, Bond eludes Spectre pursuers and arrives at her house; surprising her.

Miss Taro then sleeps with Bond, making time for [[Professor Dent]] to go there and kill him. She is the first Bond Girl  agent 007 seduces while on mission; the previous liaison was [[Sylvia Trench]], who is unrelated to the mission. Bond then telephones for a &quot;taxi&quot; to collect them for dinner out. She boards the taxi, then understands it is a police trap she walked into, not a taxi; she is arrested, Bond remains in her house, awaiting Professor Dent's attempt to kill him.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==The Three Blind Mice==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=The Three Blind Mice
|portrayed=[[Eric Coverly]], &lt;br /&gt;[[Charles Edghill]] and &lt;br /&gt;[[Henry Lopez]]
|gender=All [[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Dr. Julius No|Dr. No]]
|status=All Deceased; killed in car crash
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
The '''Three Blind Mice''' are three professional assassins who work for [[Dr. Julius No]], typically getting close to their targets by posing as blind beggars. They shoot British Secret Service representative [[John Strangways]] with suppressor equipped pistols and later murder his secretary, Mary Prescott. Their killings bring [[James Bond (character)|James Bond]] to Jamaica to investigate. The Three Blind Mice attempt to eliminate Bond as he exits a taxi outside of his hotel but their attempt fails. Later on they pursue Bond's [[Sunbeam Alpine]] with their [[LaSalle (automobile)|LaSalle]] through the mountains, with the help of their Hearse Driver, while he is on his way to see [[List of James Bond henchmen in Dr. No#Miss Taro|Miss Taro]]. During the chase an adroit maneuver by Bond leads them to veer off a mountainside and die when their car explodes into flames below.
 
The Three Blind Mice are not mentioned in the film's opening or end credits. The name &quot;Three Blind Mice&quot;, comes from the song that plays in the background when they are first introduced at the beginning of the film.[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FgNZJio4zkI] [[The James Bond Encyclopedia]] recently released the names of all three actors of the Three Blind Mice as well as their Hearse Driver:
* Eric Coverly (1st Beggar)
* Charles Edghill (2nd Beggar)
* Henry Lopez (3rd Beggar)
* Adrian Robinson (Hearse Driver)
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Dr. No's photographer==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Dr No’s photographer
|portrayed=[[Marguerite LeWars]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]}}

'''Dr. No's photographer''' (named '''Freelance''' by [[James Bond]]) is an unnamed female [[photographer]] (Though in the novel, her name is '''Anabelle Chung''') working for [[Doctor Julius No]] of [[SPECTRE]] in the 1962 [[James Bond]] film ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]''.

The photographer, an attractive dark-haired woman of [[Chinese Jamaican]] descent, first appears in the film at [[Kingston, Jamaica|Kingston]] airport where she attempts to take a photograph of [[James Bond]] as he arrives in [[Jamaica]]. Bond half-consciously shields his face with his hat and gets into the car of [[Mr. Jones (James Bond)|Mr. Jones]], also of [[SPECTRE]].

She later reappears in the film, again sent by Dr. No to take another photograph of Bond as he is discussing plans with [[Felix Leiter]] and [[List of James Bond allies in Dr. No#Quarrel|Quarrel]] at a [[Jamaica]]n [[Calypso music|calypso]] [[restaurant]]. This time she is spotted by Bond who orders Quarrel to seize her. Bond asks her who she is working for and she replies that she was working for the [[The Daily Gleaner (Jamaica)|Daily Gleaner]], a local newspaper in [[Kingston, Jamaica|Kingston]]. When Bond asks the head waiter to check it out, she is forced to change her story and confess that she was a freelance [[photographer]]. She then attempts to physically harm Quarrel by cutting his face with a broken flashbulb from her camera. Quarrel seems unaffected and threatens to break her arm. Bond then destroys her film and she is set free, never to be seen again, after stating that the men will be sorry for their actions; she may have been killed for failing the mission but it was never mentioned.

[[Marguerite LeWars]], who portrayed the photographer, was the reigning Miss Jamaica at the time of shooting in 1962.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Mr. Jones==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name= Mr. Jones
|portrayed=[[Reginald Carter]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[SPECTRE]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Villain]]}}

'''Mr. Jones''' is a fictional character from the first [[James Bond]] film, ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]'', released in [[1962]]. He is the first Bond villain to officially encounter Bond in the entire [[film]] franchise.

In the film, [[James Bond]], played by [[Sean Connery]], travels to [[Jamaica]] to investigate interference with [[United States|American]] [[space]] [[rocket]]s which appears to be originating in the area. As Bond leaves [[Norman Manley International Airport|Kingston Airport]], Mr. Jones, dressed in a beige uniform and cap, coolly greets him and insists that he is a [[chauffeur]] from Government House who had been sent to meet him. Bond phones Government House (under the pretext of checking his reservation), but learns that no car has been sent, thus identifying Jones as an imposter. Bond's suspicions increase when he observes the photographer (see above &quot;Dr. No's Photographer&quot;) speak with Jones as he finds out no car was sent in the phone call.

Bond is then driven by Jones along a coastal road in a black 1957 Chevrolet Bel Air convertible. He begins to drive quickly when they are being tailed (by [[Felix Leiter]] of the [[CIA]]). Bond orders Jones to take a road on the right, losing the pursuers, where the car comes to a stop, with Bond holding the imposter at [[gun]]-point. Bond asks Jones for whom he is working, and Jones tries to reach for a pistol in the glove compartment. Despite resistance, Bond is quick to overcome him and again demands an answer. Mr. Jones begs for a [[cigarette]], which, unknown to Bond, has a [[cyanide]] pill as a filter. He breaks this pill from the [[cigarette]] with his teeth and dies within seconds, cursing Bond with his final words: &quot;To hell with you.&quot;

It is found later in the film that Jones was in fact an agent of the crime syndicate [[SPECTRE]] and was working for [[Doctor Julius No]], who had ordered that [[James Bond|Bond]] be followed and killed.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Professor R. J. Dent==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Professor R. J. Dent
|portrayed=[[Anthony Dawson]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Dr. Julius No|Dr. No]]
|status=Deceased; shot by bond
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Professor R. J. Dent''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]'', portrayed by [[Anthony Dawson]], who would later portray [[Ernst Stavro Blofeld]], head of SPECTRE, in ''[[From Russia with Love (film)|From Russia with Love]]'' and ''[[Thunderball (film)|Thunderball]]''.

Dent is a Geologist with a private practice in Kingston; he also secretly works for [[Doctor Julius No]]. He is first seen playing cards with [[List of James Bond allies in Dr. No#John Strangways|John Strangways]] and other officials. When investigating Strangways' death, Bond initially suspects Dent, when he finds the rocks Dent is studying are [[radioactive]].

Bond then questions Dent about the rocks in his office after encountering his young secretary played by [[Bettina Le Beau]]. Dent reports his fears about Bond to Dr. No, who orders him to eliminate Bond with a deadly [[Tarantula]]. Dent puts it into Bond's bed, but he kills it. When Bond meets with [[List of James Bond henchmen in Dr. No#Miss Taro|Miss Taro]], Dent sneaks up to the house, but not before Miss Taro speaks about the plot.

Bond waits for Dent, putting pillows under his covers as a decoy. Dent empties his gun into the bed, leaving him defenseless when Bond, having quipped &quot;That's a Smith and Wesson and you've had your six,&quot; executes him with a shot to the chest and a follow-up bullet from his .32 [[Walther PPK]] pistol in the back.

This scene was controversial because it showed the hero of the film killing a man in cold blood, and even though Ian Fleming had conceived the character as one who is authorized to commit such actions, in none of his novels is Bond shown acting in this manner. According to ''James Bond: The Legacy'', the filmmakers needed a scene to illustrate the &quot;licensed to kill&quot; concept and in fact had originally filmed the scene to show Bond firing several more bullets into Dent, but ultimately removed all but the first shot (some televised broadcasts such as those by the American [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] network delete the second bullet to the back). It is sometimes stated that an alternate version was shot with Dent firing first and Bond returning fire, but this is a myth.

Interestingly the pistol used by Dent is a semi-automatic, necessarily as it is fitted with a [[suppressor]]. Generally [[Smith &amp; Wesson#Semi-automatic_pistols|Smith and Wesson semi-automatics]] of the period would have a magazine of at least eight rounds, with another in the chamber. There are [[Smith &amp; Wesson Model 39|Smith &amp; Wesson Model 52]] pistols designed for target shooting with a five round magazine, with one in the chamber making six. However, the gun that Dent used was actually an [[M1911A1]], made by [[Colt's Manufacturing Company|Colt]] not a Smith and Wesson.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Crab Key Guards==
The Crab Key guards are fictional characters from the film Dr No, who work for Dr No by guarding Crab Key. They are first seen when Professor Dent is on his way to meet Dr No. When Bond, Quarrel and Honey are on Crab Key their radar picks up the signal of Bond's boat and the guards come up in their boat. One guard with a loudspeaker announces to the hiding Bond, Quarrel and Honey to give themselves up. They stay hidden and the guards later come back with sniffer dogs to find them, but are all thrown off the scent from them hiding. One of them is searching for them until Bond stabs him in the back and leaves his body to float in the water. They are also seen when Bond and Honey are having dinner with Dr No. One of them took away Honey Ryder to be locked into a water filling room. Next one guard is holding Bond while the other beats Bond and puts him into a cell. Bond later knocks one of them out in the room that Honey was in so she and Bond can escape Dr No's lair. The last we see of them is that they are seen fleeing along with the rest of No's crew out of Dr No's lair as it goes up in flames.
{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|Dr. No]]
[[Category:SPECTRE members]]
[[Category:Dr. No (film)|Henchmen in Dr. No]]

[[pt:Miss Taro]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
