<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708918" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in GoldenEye"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Citations missing|date=November 2008}}
{{Original research|date=November 2008}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of James Bond henchmen in ''GoldenEye''}}
This is a list of [[List of James Bond henchmen|henchmen]] from the [[James Bond]] 1995 film ''[[GoldenEye]]''. 

==Xenia Onatopp==
{{main|Xenia Onatopp}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Xenia Onatopp
|portrayed=[[Famke Janssen]], [[Kate Magowan]] (2010 video game)
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=Soviet Military / Janus
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]
}}
'''Xenia Sergeevna Onatopp''' ({{lang-ru|Ксения Сергеевна Онатопп}}) is a [[List of James Bond villains|supporting villain]] in the James Bond film ''[[GoldenEye]]'', played by actress [[Famke Janssen]].

===Biography===

Xenia, born in the former [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] republic of [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], was a fighter [[Aviator|pilot]] in the [[Red Air Force]]. After the collapse of the [[USSR]], she joined the crime syndicate Janus, led by renegade [[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]] agent [[Alec Trevelyan]]. Early in the movie, Bond gets into a car chase with her, meets her at a [[casino]], and places her under [[surveillance]].

She is a classic representation of a &quot;[[femme fatale]]&quot;, and can derive [[lust murder|sexual satisfaction from killing]]. In one scene, she lures [[Canada|Canadian]] admiral Chuck Farrell ([[Billy J. Mitchell]]) onto a yacht moored off [[Monte Carlo]] and while engaging in violent sex, crushes him to death between her thighs, achieving orgasm as he expires. During this, a fellow operative steals his ID, granting them access to the Tiger.

Xenia then hijacks the prototype [[Eurocopter Tiger]] by killing the two pilots.  Later, she and turncoat Russian General [[Arkady Grigorovich Ourumov|Arkady Ourumov]] use the hijacked Tiger in an attack on the Severnaya satellite control center in central [[Siberia]], where they steal the controller for the GoldenEye [[electromagnetic pulse]] (EMP) satellite weapon. During the attack, she fires an [[AKS-74U]] carbine around the control room, murdering all the military personnel and technicians present, again getting [[Sexual arousal|sexually aroused]] in the process.

She then appears as Bond's link to the Janus group. In a meeting arranged by Bond's dealings with Valentin Zukovsky, a Russian arms dealer, Xenia arrives to meet Bond as he swims lengths in the Turkish Baths of his hotel - The St Petersburg Grand. Initially sneaking around the pool, Bond discovers her presence and hurls her into the steam room. Exchanging lines and revealing their attraction for one another, Xenia attempts to seduce Bond, forcefully kissing him and coercing the agent to set down his weapon, before biting his lip, causing him to hurl her at the wall. Following a period of violent sexual foreplay where Xenia crushes Bond between her thighs, Bond finally draws his weapon on her and demands to be taken to Janus.

In her final encounter with Bond, she ambushes him and Simonova and begins torturing him between her legs. However, Bond is able to connect the rope she rappelled down to her safety harness, grabs her [[AK-74]] rifle, and shoots down the helicopter with her rifle.  The result pulls Onatopp off Bond and sends her flying in the crotch of a tree, with her safety harness crushing her to death. As Bond quips, &quot;She always did enjoy a good squeeze&quot;

===Other appearances===
Onatopp has appeared in a number of [[James Bond games|James Bond video games]] as a playable [[multiplayer]] character. Her first appearance was in the 1997 video game adaptation of ''GoldenEye'', ''[[GoldenEye 007 (1997 video game)|GoldenEye 007]]'' for the [[Nintendo 64]]. She is with Trevelyan on the train stage of the game. If the player quickly shoots her after eliminating Ourumov, she will yell to Trevelyan that she is wounded and to wait up for her. This buys the player more time to escape from the train. She later reappears in the jungle stage. Similar to the film, she is killed in the jungles of Cuba after battling with Bond, although Bond is unable to make her die by way of the tree trunks, and she never engages in her trademark physical attacks, using firearms instead. Killing Xenia is the only way for the player to [[dual-wield]] two different guns in the game without a complex series of button presses; Xenia uses an RC-[[FN P90|P90]] and a [[Milkor MGL|grenade launcher]] at the same time.

In the James Bond game ''[[Nightfire]]'', Xenia also appears as a multiplayer character. She can be unlocked by a cheat on the cheats menu and the code is JANUS, the organization she worked for in the movie. 

She later appeared in the spinoff Bond game, ''[[GoldenEye: Rogue Agent]]'' where she worked for [[Dr. Julius No]] and was [[GoldenEye (character)|GoldenEye]]'s alluring opponent, and appears to be commander of an army of Dr. No's that has taken over Hoover Dam. She is killed in ''Rogue Agent'' after being thrown off of the [[Hoover Dam]], while fighting Goldeneye. In the game she was voiced by actress [[Jenya Lano]].

She appears in the [[GoldenEye 007 (2010 video game)|''GoldenEye'' remake]] as a former Russian general who served under Oroumov during the Russian invasion of [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]. Her plot is significantly changed for the remake. She now appears in the new Nightclub level(where Bond first meets her), and asassinates Valentin Zurkofsky after he gives vital information about Janus to Bond. She also betrays and asassinates General Ouromov in the train level in which she now appears. During her final confrontation with Bond, she is lowered down to him from a helicopter and proceeds to engage in hand-to-hand combat with him; she is defeated when Bond launches a missile at her helicopter while she is strangling him, the helicopter crashing into a nearby gorge and dragging Xenia down with it. This death is based more on the original film than the first video game was. Xenia is voiced by and modeled after [[Kate Magowan]].

After her portrayal by Famke Janssen, Xenia was voted the 5th most memorable [[Bond Girl]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,1557446_6,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Boris Grishenko==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[GoldenEye 007 (1997 video game)]] --&gt;
{{Unreferenced|date=March 2008}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Boris Ivanovich Grishenko
|portrayed=[[Alan Cumming]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|status= deceased
|affiliation=Russian Defence Space Division / Janus
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Boris Ivanovich Grishenko''' (Russian: Борис Иванович Грищенко) is a fictional genius in the James Bond film ''GoldenEye'' played by [[Scotland|Scottish]] actor [[Alan Cumming]].

He is a brilliantly talented [[computer programmer]] and [[hacker (computer security)|hacker]] who has hacked the [[United States Department of Justice]]. He is boldly confident and a colorfully witty non-conformist who describes Americans as &quot;''Slug heads!''&quot;, often shouting his catchphrase, ''&quot;I am invincible!&quot;'' whenever he succeeds, which makes him a comic relief character.  All in all, he is disliked by many of his lifeless colleagues, who see him as an overwrought prankster, especially about his habits of using slang about breasts and/or buttocks as passwords.  Boris frequently [[pen spinning|spins a pen]] with his hand while working, and is often seen typing with one hand.

Boris works at the [[Severnaya (James Bond)|Severnaya]] observatory in [[Siberia]] which watches over the two weapons [[satellite]]s, Petya and Mischa.  Boris flees the facility, flying off with [[Arkady Grigorovich Ourumov|General Arkady Ouromov]] and Xenia Onatopp moments before its destruction, having allied himself with [[Alec Trevelyan]] to shift ownership of the GoldenEye satellite.  His main purpose with Janus is to operate the GoldenEye satellite in exchange for a share of the profits.  Boris helps his comrades [[kidnap]] [[Natalya Simonova]], the only other survivor of the attack on Severnaya. 

While attempting to crack the access codes for the GoldenEye, he obtains a [[grenade]] disguised as a pen from Bond's wide arsenal of gadgets.  After Boris unknowingly activates it, Bond knocks the pen out of Boris' hand, leading to an explosion that destroys much of the control center, giving Bond and Natalya a perfect opportunity to escape.  After emerging from the destruction of the satellite control room, Boris shouts his catchphrase  before vats of [[liquid nitrogen]] explode, freezing and, killing him. He appears in the videogame chronologically earlier than the incident at Severnaya.

===Boris in GoldenEye 007 video game===
Boris appears twice in ''GoldenEye 007'', a video game for the Nintendo 64 based on the film. The first time the player meets him is in the Severnaya observatory, where he is simply known as &quot;Programmer&quot;. The player coerces him into disabling the security on a [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]]. This event does not occur in the film, as Bond never goes to the observatory in Severnaya in the movie.

The next time the player sees him is in the satellite control center. When they meet, Boris fumbles with a Walther PPK (called PP7 in game for copyright reasons), then begs for his life claiming ''&quot;Trevelyan made me do it!&quot;'' Killing Boris will result in a mission failure, as Natalya claims to have seen Bond kill Boris on a security camera and refuses to help Bond any more.

Boris is also playable as a [[multiplayer]] character.

{{See also2|[[Love and Death#Cast|Boris Grushenko]]}}

==General Ourumov==
{{Unreferenced|date=March 2008}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name= Arkady Grigorovich Ourumov
|portrayed=[[Gottfried John]], [[Laurentiu Possa]] (2010 video game)
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Soviet Army / Russian Ground Forces / Janus
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

General '''Arkady Grigorovich Ourumov''' (Russian: Аркадий Григорович Урумов) is a supporting villain and henchman in the James Bond film ''GoldenEye'', played by [[Germans|German]] actor [[Gottfried John]]. General Ourumov is mostly based on the secondary Bond villain [[General Orlov]] from a previous Bond film ''[[Octopussy]]''. At first the audience is led to believe Ourumov is the main antagonist of the film.  However it is later on revealed that Alec Trevelyan 006 is the real villain.

===Biography===
{{Inappropriate tone|date=March 2008}}

Joining the Soviet Army at 18, Ourumov always had a zeal for power, and would constantly use any means necessary to get his way to the top. 27 years later, Ourumov, who had grown tired of having little power, was finally promoted to colonel and was given the important job of being in charge of a Soviet Russian Chemical Weapons Factory. During his early days in his new position he meets a young and bitter Alec Trevelyan, who tells Ourumov of his past, his hatred for MI6 and his future intentions, but makes sure to leave out a few vital details about himself. Alec offers Ourumov a part in his plan for which he will be paid well and receive his status as the next &quot;Iron Man Of Russia&quot;;, Ourumov graciously accepts. The two pledge not to see each other again until Alec and James Bond are to go on a mission to destroy Ourumov's base. However, Ourumov and Alec have different plans. Alec deliberately gets himself caught by Ourumov and his men, and Bond witnesses as Ourumov shoots Alec in the head. Ourumov attempts to catch Bond and almost succeeds, but Bond just manages to escape.

The shooting was staged, however. Unknown to Bond, Trevelyan is still alive, albeit deeply scarred on the right side of his face (courtesy of Bond, whose explosives he had detonated earlier). He becomes an international terrorist under the name &quot;Janus&quot; (The two-faced Roman god). Ourumov, supposed to be executed for the destruction of the chemical weapons base, frames one of his soldiers for the incident and is instead promoted to the rank of General, and is placed in charge of the Severnaya Space Facility in Siberia. Ourumov also has the job of employing another member for The Janus Crime Syndicate - he hires [[Xenia Onatopp]], an ex-Soviet fighter pilot, with whom he is familiar. For the next nine years The Janus Crime Syndicate will terrorize Russia without getting caught and with all their identities remaining secret, and Ourumov gains more power, which starts to trouble the Russian Government.

A year before the main plot of ''Goldeneye'' takes place, Ourumov completes the establishment of their syndicate's greatest weapon: &quot;GoldenEye&quot;. Two Goldeneye satellite dishes were built:  one in Siberia, and one hidden in Cuba.  Anyone who becomes suspicious of Ourumov is killed by Xenia. The Syndicate's first act is to steal the Tiger Helicopter. Ourumov and Xenia personally take care of the operation under the strict order of Janus not to fail. They successfully manage to steal it before Bond can stop them, and arrive in Siberia hours later, where the Second Act of their operation will take place. Ourumov made sure to hire the most intelligent computer programmer to take care of the Goldeneye weapon: Boris Grishenko. Ourumov and Xenia enter the satellite base, where the corrupt general orders one of his men to give him the Goldeneye and authorization codes they need to test-fire Goldeneye. Upon receiving these, Xenia suddenly shoots everyone in the base, and together they arm the Goldeneye to fire on Severnaya to eliminate the evidence. The two leave, pleased with their success, not knowing that one person is still alive - Natalya Simonova.

Ourumov and [[Xenia Onatopp|Xenia]] take Boris with them and escape moments before the Goldeneye weapon detonates, and their witness Natalya narrowly escapes. Afterwards, Ourumov heads back to Russia to report to Defense Minister Mishkin. Ourumov soon learns that Natalya Simonova is alive and he leaves immediately, frustrated with Xenia's failure to kill &quot;everyone&quot;. He assigns Boris and Xenia to find her, which doesn't take them long. Ourumov takes Natalya to Alec's hideout, where he ties her up in the Tiger helicopter to await her death. Bond also ends up tied up in the helicopter, after learning Alec is alive and that he is a traitor. Bond and Natalya escape moments before the Tiger helicopter explodes, but are soon caught by Russian troops and taken to a large government building where they are locked in a prison cell.

Later, upon hearing that Mishkin has Bond and Natalya in custody, Ourumov arrives and storms into the cell where Mishkin is interrogating the pair. Ourumov argues with Mishkin, trying to convince him that Bond is the traitor.  Mishkin yells for a guard to arrest Ourumov, but the general turns and shoots both the guard and Mishkin with Bond's gun. After improvising a cover story, Ourumov then calls for the guards to kill Bond and Natalya, but is grabbed by Bond, beaten, and thrown into a wall, knocking him flat. Ourumov leads his soldiers throughout the base, searching for Bond and Natalya. His men capture Natalya, leaving Bond to escape on his own. Ourumov takes one of his men and Natalya and they escape out into the streets by car, but soon Bond bursts through a wall behind them in a tank. He leaves behind a path of destruction as he chases Ourumov through the streets of St Petersburg. Ourumov escapes and arrives at Alec's personal train. Ourumov boards the train with Natalya, and explains to Trevelyan what has happened and that Bond has escaped.  Later, their journey is halted by Bond, who uses the hijacked tank to stop the train. Bond boards the damaged train and holds Trevelyan and Onatopp at gun point. Ourumov is called in and he holds Natalya with a gun to her head.  Bond reveals to Ourumov that Alec is a Lienz Cossack, leaving Ourumov shocked. Alec smooths things over by telling him how rich and powerful he will soon be. Bond demands that Natalya be released. Alec nods for Ourumov to shoot Natalya, but his intention is for Ourumov to distract Bond while he escapes, throwing the [[Russia]]n [[General]] into a [[sacrificial lamb]], at which, Ourumov is too slow and ends up being shot by Bond's AKS-74U, thereby putting an end to the life of the &quot;Iron Man Of Russia&quot;.

===Ourumov in ''GoldenEye 007'' video games===
In ''[[GoldenEye 007 (1997 video game)|GoldenEye 007]]'', a video game for Nintendo 64 based on the movie, Ourumov appears in only three of the game's missions, initially when the then-Colonel apparently murders 006, another in which Bond infiltrates a Russian facility in [[Kyrgyzstan]] to investigate an unscheduled test firing of a missile, believed to be a cover for the launch of a GoldenEye satellite (this location, however, is never shown or mentioned in the film), and lastly in a mission aboard Janus' armoured train, where the General is holding [[Natalya Simonova]] at gunpoint. As in the movie, Bond shoots the General while in the train, thus saving Natalya's life. Ourumov is a playable character in the [[multiplayer]] mode.

Ouromov also appears in the ''Goldeneye 007'' 2010 remake. In this version of the Goldeneye story, Ouromov is a renegade from the beginning, having previously commanded Xenia during the Russian invasion of Georgia but now selling weapons on the black market. Rather than being Trevelyans's loyal henchman he is the leader of Janus. During the confrontation on the train, Xenia betrays and shoots Ouromov (making Trevelyan the new Janus) rather than Bond killing the general himself. It is possible that Xenia killed  Ouromov after plotting with Trevelyan to take over Janus. Ourumov is voiced by and modeled after Laurentiu Possa.

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;
{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|GoldenEye]]
[[Category:GoldenEye|Henchmen]]

[[pt:General Ourumov]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
