<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708972" ns="0" title="List of henchmen in Die Another Day"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This is a '''list of [[henchman|henchmen]]''' from the 2002 [[James Bond]] film '''''[[Die Another Day]]'''''.

==Zao==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= [[Image:Zao by Rick Yune.jpg|200px]]
|caption=Yune as the extreme looking Zao which required over three hours in make-up.
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Zao
|portrayed=[[Rick Yune]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[North Korea]] &lt;br&gt; [[Gustav Graves|Colonel Tan-Sun Moon]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
'''Zao''' is a [[North Korea]]n secret-agent played by [[Rick Yune]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT Review&quot;&gt;
{{cite news |first=A.O. |last=Scott  |title= Die Another Day (2002)|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/mem/movies/review.html?_r=1&amp;res=9C07E6D81439F931A15752C1A9649C8B63&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=Miranda%20Frost&amp;st=cse&amp;oref=login |publisher= The New York Times |date=2002-11-22 |accessdate=2008-09-09  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Yune described his character as one of the most &quot;extreme&quot; looking Bond villains.&lt;ref name=&quot;Counting Down&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.countingdown.com/features/?feature_id=265168 |title=Interview: Rick Yune |accessdate=2008-09-09 |author=Larry Carroll|date=2002-11-21  |publisher=Counting Down }}1&lt;/ref&gt; Yune's makeup, which included the implantation of real diamonds, required three hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Counting Down&quot;/&gt;

=== Biography ===
He was originally a [[North Korea]]n operative under the command of [[Gustav Graves|Colonel Tan-Sun Moon]] as the Colonel [[arms dealing|illegally dealt in arms]] in the [[Korean Demilitarized Zone|Demilitarized Zone]] of [[North Korea]]. Bond, posing as a [[diamond]] smuggler called Van Bierk infiltrated Moon's base as part of an [[MI6]] operation, hoping to exchange diamonds for arms and expose Moon. The case of diamonds was rigged with explosives and blew up, embedding several stones in Zao's face. Moon was supposedly killed in the assault. Zao went rogue, attempting to blow up a summit between the Chinese and the South Koreans. He killed three Chinese agents, but was later found and arrested by the [[United Nations|UN]] forces. Bond was held captive by [[General Moon|Moon's father]].

14 months later, MI6 received intelligence that Bond may have cracked under the torture and revealed vital information, so a trade was arranged - Zao for Bond. Following Moon, Zao traveled to [[Cuba]], planning to receive [[gene therapy]] to alter his appearance. However, Bond found the lab and halted the procedure before it was completed: Zao was left in a &quot;blank human &quot; state, an hairless [[albino]] with silvery eyes and  with the diamonds still embedded under his skin. Zao fought Bond to a draw and escaped again. During his escape, [[List of James Bond allies in Die Another Day#Jinx|Giacinta &quot;Jinx&quot; Johnson]] attempted to shoot Zao, but failed.

Zao caught up with Moon, who, through a course of gene therapy, was now Sir [[Gustav Graves]], in [[Iceland]]. Bond, however, had figured out Graves' true identity. Ordered to kill Bond, Zao got in his modified [[Jaguar XKR]], activated [[thermal imaging]] and chased Bond and his [[Aston Martin Vanquish]] across the ice plains using a number of deadly weapon emplacements installed in the Jaguar, such as a [[Gatling gun]] that rose from the rear section of the car. The chase led back to the melting ice palace, where Bond used the Aston Martin V12 Vanquish's adaptive camouflage to fool Zao into driving into the melted ice while the latter attempted to ram the Vanquish with the Jaguar's front retractable battering ram. Bond shot down a [[chandelier]] which landed on Zao as he tread the freezing water, impaling him. The chandelier was, fittingly, made from diamonds.

===Trivia===
Despite the character being a North Korean, Zao is not a Korean name, and therefore cannot be written in [[Korean language|Korean]] since the language has no &quot;z&quot; sound (although it is possible to transcribe it as ''Jao''). However, the word itself coincidentally means ''evil'' in [[serbo-croatian]].

==Miranda Frost==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|image= 
|name= Miranda Frost
|portrayed= [[Rosamund Pike]]
|gender= [[Female]]
|affiliation= [[Gustav Graves]]/[[MI6]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Miranda Frost''' is a spy and [[Bond girl]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Die Another Day]]''. She is played by [[Rosamund Pike]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT Review&quot;/&gt; Frost is a double agent working for [[MI6]]; however, her allegiance lies with [[Gustav Graves]], the main villain of the film.

=== Biography ===
Miranda Frost is a [[Harvard]]-educated, gold medal-winning [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] fencer (trained by [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]]'s character, [[List of James Bond allies in Die Another Day#Verity|Verity]]) posing as Graves' publicist and [[fencing]] partner. She won [[Fencing at the 2000 Summer Olympics|gold]] at the [[2000 Sydney Olympics]] by default, after Graves organized the real gold medalist's death by [[steroids]] overdose. She is sent by [[M (James Bond)|M]] to work alongside Bond, but does not approve of Bond's methods. When Bond is caught by [[Mr. Kil]] and his minions, Frost helps Bond keep incognito by kissing him. They later go to Bond's room and have [[sexual intercourse|sex]]. James awakens and goes after Graves. Frost pleads for him not to go, but he insists.  Unbeknownst to 007, Miranda secretly emptied the magazine of Bond's [[Walther P99]]. Later when she pulls a gun on Graves, it is revealed that she was the one who betrayed Bond in North Korea, which led to 14 months of torture for him, as well as framing him for revealing the identity of the head American agent which led to his execution at the hands of the North Korean Army. At this point she reveals that she is still a traitor, and turns the gun on Bond. Bond escapes with the ring that Q gave him - which shatters the glass floor that he is currently on - and Frost and Bond fall into the jungle environment part of the Ice Palace. Frost and [[List of James Bond allies in Die Another Day#Jinx|Giacinta &quot;Jinx&quot; Johnson]] have a climactic fight aboard the descending plane. Frost narrowly slices Jinx in the stomach, but Jinx grabs a dagger-impaled copy of ''[[The Art of War]]'' and stabs Miranda in the heart, killing her.

* According to actress Rosamund Pike, in her DVD commentary for ''Die Another Day'', Frost was originally going to be named [[Gala Brand]], after the [[Bond girl]] in the novel ''[[Moonraker (novel)|Moonraker]]''.

==Vladimir Popov==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Vladimir Popov
|portrayed=[[Michael Gorevoy]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Gustav Graves]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
'''Vladimir Popov''' (played by [[Michael Gorevoy]]) is a scientist who works for [[Gustav Graves]].

=== Role ===
Vladimir Popov works as [[Gustav Graves]]' personal scientist. He makes his first appearance in the film when timing Graves, who is attempting to beat his best time across the ice in an ice dragster.

Popov reveals his role as a sort of mad scientist when he invents for Graves a remote control for the Icarus satellite which doubles as a heat-beam weapon. Popov is mainly seen throughout the rest of the film following Graves, but doing nothing of major importance. He annoys Graves when he reveals that Bond has beaten his speed record while escaping from Icarus.

The mad scientist's demise occurs when James Bond inadvertently shoots a hole in one of the windows of Graves' airborne jet, causing the cabin to depressurize; Popov is sucked out of the plane along with the other North Korean generals to their deaths.

== Dr. Alvarez ==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Dr. Alvarez
|portrayed=[[Simon Andreu]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Gustav Graves]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
'''Dr. Alvarez''' (played by [[Simon Andreu]]) is a Surgeon affiliated to [[Gustav Graves]].

=== Role ===
Dr. Alvarez is a surgeon in the gene therapy clinic on Isla Los Organos. Using the DNA of people such as orphans, vagrants, etc., he is able to create new physical appearances for his patients, whom, it is implied, are mostly dictators. Jinx poses as a potential patient in order to search for Zao's files, and upon the doctor telling her &quot;I like to think of myself as an artist,&quot; she kills him, quipping that &quot;most artists are not truly appreciated until after they're dead.&quot;

==Mr. Kil==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Mr. Kil
|portrayed=[[Lawrence Makoare]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Gustav Graves]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Villain]]}}

'''Mr. Kil''' is a henchman of the main villain, [[Gustav Graves]]. In the film he was portrayed by [[New Zealand]] [[actor]] [[Lawrence Makoare]]. Kil is first introduced alongside his partner Pertant when Bond arrives in [[Iceland]]: &quot;I am Mr Kil&quot;. Bond quips back: &quot;Well, there's a name to die for.&quot; He [[tortures]] [[List of James Bond allies in Die Another Day#Jinx|Giacinta &quot;Jinx&quot; Johnson]] and straps down her hands and feet.  He is later killed by Jinx with a [[laser]] which impales him through the back of the head and out of the top of his mouth while fighting with Bond. After his demise, Bond and Jinx use the laser to cut Kil's hand off and use its pattern to gain access to Graves's personal quarters.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{James Bond characters}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Die}}
[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen]]
[[Category:Fictional secret agents and spies]]
[[Category:Die Another Day|Henchmen]]

[[pt:Zao (James Bond)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
