<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7708823" ns="0" title="List of James Bond henchmen in The Spy Who Loved Me"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">A list of [[List of James Bond henchmen|henchmen]] from the [[1977 in film|1977]] [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]''.

==Jaws==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Jaws  
|portrayed=[[Richard Kiel]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|age=Mid 30s|
|affiliation= [[Karl Stromberg]] (''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]])''&lt;br&gt;[[Hugo Drax]] (''[[Moonraker (film)|Moonraker]]'')
|status=Active
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]] (later in [[Moonraker (film)|Moonraker]] [[List of James Bond allies|Ally]])
}}

Jaws gets his nickname from his trademark [[steel]] teeth. These are capable of biting through a wide variety of materials, and Jaws prefers to kill his victims by biting through their [[Jugular vein]]. The character was played in both ''The Spy Who Loved Me'' and the following film ''[[Moonraker (film)|Moonraker]]'' by actor [[Richard Kiel]]. 

Jaws, and his sidekick Sandor, were based on the villains Sol &quot;Horror&quot; Horowitz and &quot;Sluggsy&quot; Morant from [[Ian Fleming]]'s novel [[The Spy Who Loved Me (novel)|The Spy Who Loved Me]].

===Appearances===
====Films====
Jaws first appeared in the 1977 film ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]'' as a [[henchman]] to the [[Bond Villains|villain]], [[Karl Stromberg]]. He would later appear in the sequel ''[[Moonraker (film)|Moonraker]]'' as a henchman to the villain [[Hugo Drax]]. In his second appearance Jaws changed from a ruthless and unstoppable killing machine to more of a comedy figure. He eventually turns against Drax and helps Bond to defeat him. In Moonraker he gains a girlfriend, Dolly, who like Jaws almost never speaks.

In addition to having steel teeth, Jaws was also gigantic and extremely strong, which forced Bond to be especially inventive while fighting him. In combat during ''The Spy Who Loved Me'', Bond found himself caught in an unbreakable death grip by Jaws, who was about to fatally bite him; Bond only escaped by using a broken electric lamp to send an electric shock through the assassin's teeth to stun him.

Jaws also has an uncanny ability to survive any misfortune seemingly unscathed and come back to challenge Bond again. In ''The Spy Who Loved Me'', Jaws survives an Egyptian structure's collapse on top of him, being hit by a van, being thrown from a rapidly-moving train, sitting in the passenger seat of a car which veers off a cliff in [[Sardinia]] and explodes (landing in a hut below, to the owner's dismay), a battle underwater with a shark, and the destruction of Stromberg's lair.  In ''Moonraker'', he survives falling several thousand feet after accidentally disabling his own parachute (he falls through a circus tent and lands in the trapeze net), a crash through a building inside a runaway cable car, and going over [[Iguazu Falls]]. After each of these incidents, he always picks himself up, dusts off his jacket, straightens his tie and nonchalantly walks away. After the destruction of [[Hugo Drax|Drax's]] space station, a throw-away line near the end is made that the American shuttle rescued him and his girlfriend.

He also appeared in a minor cameo in ''[[Inspector Gadget (film)|Inspector Gadget]]'' during the end credits where Sykes, [[Dr. Claw|Sandford Scolex]]'s assistant, is giving a speech to a henchmen support group. Other notable James Bond villains can also be seen during this scene.

Jaws only speaks once, in ''Moonraker'', when he makes a toast to his girlfriend, &quot;Well, here's to us&quot;.

===Elsewhere in popular culture===

*Jaws was spoofed in the [[1977 in film|1977]] [[Mel Brooks]] film, ''[[High Anxiety]]'', which featured a psychopathic killer named &quot;Braces&quot;, who wore large metal braces on his teeth for a reason that was never explained.
*In a 2008 comic strip featuring ''[[Dick Tracy]]'', a henchman, &quot;Braces&quot;, who wears dental braces, is electrocuted after wiring from his own robot is caught in his dental hardware.
*Jaws also makes a cameo in the animated series ''[[Jackie Chan Adventures]]'' (episode ''Tough Luck''), where he auditions as a prospective henchman for Finn and gets his steel teeth (which are revealed to be [[dentures]]) stuck in a board he bites into.
*Jaws appeared in the 1990s animated spin-off ''[[James Bond Jr.]]'' as a member of the SCUM organization and partner-in-crime of fellow henchman [[List of James Bond henchmen in The Man with the Golden Gun#Nick Nack|Nick Nack]]. In the show, Jaws underwent some change in his apearance; he was more muscular, and his chin was also metal. Also, Jaws spoke regularly.
*In the final credits sequence of the [[Inspector Gadget (film)|''Inspector Gadget'' movie]], Dr. Claw's assistant is shown attending a &quot;Henchman's Anonymous&quot; meeting. Richard Kiel, who is billed in the credits as &quot;Famous Big Guy with Metal Teeth&quot;, is in attendance along with [[List of James Bond henchmen in Goldfinger#Oddjob|Oddjob]] (who is credited as &quot;Famous Villain with Deadly Hat&quot;).
*[[Get Smart (film)|''Get Smart'']], which is both a [[parody]] and an [[homage]] to the James Bond [[James Bond (film series)|film series]], has a character named [[The Great Khali|Dalip]], who looks like Jaws and does his Moonraker stunt of falling from the sky without a parachute and surviving. He also turns towards the good side in the end.
*''[[Mythbusters]]'' tested the plausibility of Jaws biting through the steel cable car wire. The model based on the dentures used in the movie had little impact on the steel cable, even with a hydraulic press at ten times human bite strength. Jamie Hyneman then took huge metal pincers and went as &quot;Claws&quot;, who, as the announcer said, was &quot;Meaner than Oddjob, more ferocious than Jaws, taller than Nick Nack, and creepier than [[List of James Bond henchmen in Live and Let Die#Tee Hee Johnson|Tee Hee]].&quot; With the metal pincers, he gets through the cord easily. Also, in the storyboard reenactment of the sequence from ''[[Moonraker (film)|Moonraker]]'', Jaws appears with a [[Emilio Largo|Largo]]-style eye patch, and a moustache, neither of which was seen in the actual films in which the character appeared.
*The character &quot;Braces&quot; in the video game ''[[TimeSplitters 2]] is based on Jaws.

====Games====
Jaws' principal [[James Bond games|videogame]] appearances are in the 1997 [[Nintendo 64]] game ''[[GoldenEye 007 (1997 video game)|GoldenEye 007]]'' in a bonus mission in which he is a henchman to the deceased Hugo Drax whom Bond needs to defeat, and a playable character in the multi-player mode, and the multi-platform 2004 game ''[[James Bond 007: Everything or Nothing|Everything or Nothing]]'' as a henchman to Nikolai Diavolo (voiced by [[Willem Dafoe]]).  Both games use Richard Kiel's likeness and voice (grunts and sound effects).  His likeness can also be found as the character Chuck Ferdon in the 2006 game ''Rugby'' by Electronic Arts.

Jaws is a playable multiplayer character in the 2010 video game ''[[GoldenEye 007 (2010 video game)|GoldenEye 007]]'' for the [[Nintendo Wii]] and the 2011 re-release ''GoldenEye 007: Reloaded'' for the [[PlayStation 3]] and [[Xbox 360]].

In the  game ''Everything Or Nothing'', Jaws is electrocuted and is inside a train that is knocked over the side of a bridge. Later he drives a tanker intending to destroy the New Orleans levees, but Bond destroys his tanker. In another instance during a fight on a large lift in which Jaws is equipped with a flamethrower, Bond shoots the flamethrower backpack which ignites Jaws. Bond then climbs into the [[cockpit]] of a plane and ejects his seat as the lift plummets to the ground. When Bond later lands on the remains at the bottom, Jaws is nowhere to be found and he is not seen or mentioned again in the game, which suggests that he has escaped the base and death once again.

In a multiplayer arena in the same game, Jaws wanders around looking for players to hurt. He can't be hurt himself, and any players that try to hurt him will be killed almost immediately by him.

Jaws is an unlockable multiplayer character in the game ''[[Nightfire]]''. He is the tallest character in the game, and his punches can kill almost instantly. The character model's teeth are visible at close range.

Jaws appears briefly in the Sega Mega Drive/Genesis game ''James Bond The Duel''. He wanders briefly around a section toward the end of the first stage and defeats the player with one touch.

Jaws also appears in the Game Boy game ''James Bond 007'' as a boss. Bond must lead him to magnetized pads that will temporarily hold him in place, allowing time for Bond to attack him.

===Films compared with novelisations===
Most of the background information on Jaws comes from [[Christopher Wood (writer)|Christopher Wood]]'s [[novelisation]] of the film ''The Spy Who Loved Me''; published as ''James Bond, The Spy Who Loved Me'' to differentiate from [[Ian Fleming]]'s novel.  In Wood's version, Jaws's real name is Zbigniew Krycsiwiki and he was born in [[Kraków]], [[Poland]].  After a failed attempt at becoming a basketball player (despite his astonishing height) Krycsiwiki was arrested by the secret police for having taken part in the (fictitious) &quot;1972 bread riots&quot;.  Whilst he was imprisoned the police &quot;beat him with hollow steel clubs encased in thick leather&quot; until they thought he was dead, leaving his jaw broken beyond repair.  Krycsiwiki later escaped and stowed aboard one of Stromberg's vessels.  Eventually he was caught, but instead of turning him in, Stromberg hired a prestigious doctor to create an artificial jaw.  After 14 operations Krycsiwiki's jaw was restored using steel components that created two rows of terrifying razor-sharp teeth, although Jaws was left [[speech disorder|mute]].

Since none of the above is actually mentioned in either movie, this is not necessarily considered [[canon (fiction)|canonical]], and Wood contradicts his own continuity when one compares his scripts and his novelisations.  In the novelisation of ''The Spy Who Loved Me'' Wood specifically states that Jaws is a mute. However, though Jaws remains mute in Wood's ''[[James Bond and Moonraker]]'' novelisation, he actually ''does'' speak at the end of the film.  

In the book, Jaws remains attached to the magnet that Bond dips into the tank, as opposed to the film where Bond releases Jaws from the magnet into the water:
:''Now both hands were tearing at the magnet, and Jaws twisted furiously like a fish on the hook. As Bond watched in fascinated horror, a relentless triangle streaked up behind the stricken giant. A huge gray force launched itself through the wild water, and two rows of white teeth closed around the threshing flesh.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Wood, Christopher | year = 1977 | title = James Bond, The Spy Who Loved Me | publisher = Glidrose Publications | isbn = 0-446-84544-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The initial script concluded with Jaws being killed by the shark, but after a rough test screening (where [[Lewis Gilbert]]'s grandson was present), Jaws was so well liked that the scene was changed to have him survive.

===Production===
The character was inspired by Fleming's description of a hoodlum named Horror in his novel ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (novel)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]''. When Horror speaks, he reveals steel-capped teeth. Jaws' teeth were designed by Katharina Kubrick Hobbs using a [[Gear|cog]]-like design since she felt pointy teeth would injure the actor. Still, the dentures were uncomfortable and Richard Kiel could only wear them for about 35 seconds.&lt;ref&gt;''Inside The Spy Who Loved Me''. ''The Spy Who Loved Me'' Ultimate Edition DVD, Disk 2&lt;/ref&gt; When Jaws was to bite through an object a normal human can't bite through - for example, [[cable car]] wire - the film makers used licorice.

===References===
{{reflist}}

==Sandor==
{{Refimprove|date=March 2008}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Sandor
|portrayed=[[Milton Reid]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Sandor''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]'', played by actor and wrestler [[Milton Reid]]. Sandor, a stereotypical-looking thug (burly and bald-headed), attempts to kill Bond in Egypt under the orders of Stromberg; he finds Bond before Jaws does and ambushes him iafter he was lured there by Felicca, a Stromberg agent, but misses his shot and kills her instead of Bond. Bond then pursues him over the rooftops and after a brief fistfight Sandor starts to fall over the edge of the building. Sandor grabs Bond by his tie at the last second to try to hold on. Bond demands information; right after Sandor divulges what he knows, Bond lets him fall to his death. 

Last Words:&lt;br /&gt;
Bond: &quot;Where's Fekkesh?&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
Sandor: &quot;Pyramids!&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
[Bond lets Sandor fall to his death]&lt;br /&gt;
Bond: &quot;What a helpful chap.&quot;

&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Log Cabin Girl==
{{Refimprove|date=March 2008}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Log Cabin Girl
|portrayed=[[Sue Vanner]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[KGB]]
|status= Active
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]
}}

'''Log Cabin Girl''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]'', played by actress [[Sue Vanner]]. She appears in the intro to the film making love with Bond overnight in the cozy log cabin high in the Austrian mountains. However after he leaves, it appears she is an enemy ([[KGB]] agent) and contacts her cohorts to pursue Bond as he leaves on skis. [http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/bond-girls/sue-vanner]
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Felicca==
{{Refimprove|date=March 2008}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Felicca
|portrayed=[[Olga Bisera]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[Bond girl]] / [[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]
}}

'''Felicca''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]'', played by actress [[Olga Bisera]]. When Bond arrived in Cairo, Egypt to contact Aziz Fekkesh in regard to the microfilm of the submarine tracking system developed by Stromberg, he instead found Felicca, who coyly said that Frekkesh would be &quot;a little late&quot;. As Felicca distracts Bond by kissing him passionately, Sandor, hiding from a behind an overlooking window, attempted to shoot Bond. Felicca meets her demise when Sandor misses his mark and the bullet strikes her instead of Bond in a manner reminiscent of ''[[Thunderball (film)|Thunderball]]''. 

&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Naomi==
{{Refimprove|date=March 2008}}
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Naomi
|portrayed=[[Caroline Munro]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Karl Stromberg]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchwoman]]
}}

'''Naomi''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]'', played by actress [[Caroline Munro]].

===Biography===

Naomi is [[Karl Stromberg]]'s personal helicopter pilot/assistant. She is first seen in the film escorting Dr. Bechman and Professor Markovitz in to see Stromberg and then exits. She is then not seen again until much later in the film.

When we next see Naomi, she is escorting Bond and Amasova, who are posing as a [[marine biology|marine biologist]] and his wife, on a boat to Stromberg's ocean lair ''Atlantis'' to meet Stromberg. Bond flirts with Naomi, annoying Amasova. While Bond has his meeting with Stromberg, Naomi entertains Amasova, showing her around ''Atlantis''.

After Bond and Amasova leave their meeting with Stromberg, he orders [[Jaws (James Bond)|Jaws]] to let the couple get ashore and then kill them. 

Indeed while driving along [[Sardinia]]'s coastal roads, several attempts are made to kill Bond and Amasova. There is a failed attempt by a motorcycle assassin, who careers off a cliff after his exploding sidecar triggers an explosion of feathers from a passing lorry which obscures his view. Jaws and his henchmen then appear in a [[Ford Cortina]] and three of them fire gunshots at Bond's car, only for Bond to reply with a substance which obsecures their windscreen and causes it to veer off the road and crash into the roof of a barn. A helicopter then appears , chasing the car. As the helicopter comes from behind the cliff, it tries to gun down Bond's [[Lotus Esprit]]. It then flies alongside the car, and Bond is shocked to see Naomi piloting it. Bond nods at her, and Naomi responds with a sultry wink and opens fire again.

Naomi chases Bond all over the highways of Sardinia until he comes to a pier which he immediately drives off into the water. Naomi hovers overhead, believing she has won. Unbeknown to her, however, the Lotus is a submersible, and it had disappeared into the water and out of her sight. Bond then arms a surface-to-air missile and blows Naomi out of the sky. She was the first woman to ever be undeniably killed by James Bond.

==Sergei Barzov==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Sergei Barzov
|portrayed=[[Michael Billington (actor)|Michael Billington]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[KGB]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Sergei Barzov''' is portrayed by [[Michael Billington (actor)|Michael Billington]].

A sniper and assassin for the [[KGB]], Borzov, at a signal from the girl in the cabin, leads a group of men skiing down the slopes to catch up with James. When he gets close, James aims and fires a ski-pole into his chest, killing him.

Later, it is discovered that Barzov is [[Anya Amasova]]'s boyfriend, and that she has sworn to avenge his death by killing James.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Aziz Fekkesh==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Aziz Fekkesh
|portrayed=[[Nadim Sawalha]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Self-employed&lt;br&gt;Indirectly, [[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Aziz Fekkesh''' is portrayed by [[Nadim Sawalha]].

Fekkesh is an [[Egypt]]ian businessman and part of the ring smuggling the submarine tracking device's plans that [[Karl Stromberg]] commissioned. Bond, hoping to intercept the plans, is ambushed by Sandor at Fekkesh's apartment. Getting the information out of Sandor that Fekkesh is at a show at the [[Pyramids of Giza]], Bond follows him there, but Fekkesh is killed by Jaws, though not before Fekkesh passes the device's plans (on [[microfilm]]) on to the next link in the chain, Max Kalba.

Searching for information, Bond opts to follow Fekkesh's trail and meet with Kalba at his [[nightclub]]. 
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Max Kalba==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Max Kalba
|portrayed=[[Vernon Dobtcheff]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Self-employed&lt;br&gt;Indirectly, [[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

'''Max Kalba''' is portrayed by [[Vernon Dobtcheff]].

Kalba is a [[nightclub]] owner in [[Egypt]] and another link in the chain smuggling the submarine tracking device's plans on microfilm. After he receives the device from Aziz Fekkesh and Fekkesh is killed, Bond takes Fekkesh's place to meet with Kalba.

During the meeting, Kalba is distracted by a phone call, and when he goes to take it, he is met by Jaws, who crushes Kalba's [[Vertebrate trachea|trachea]] with his metal teeth and steals the microfilm from him.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Motorcyclist==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Motorcyclist
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}

The motorcyclist is a henchman of Karl Stromberg. When Bond and Anya were driving in the Lotus Esprit in Sardinia, he suddenly started chasing them with his motorbike. When Bond and Anya got stuck behind a truck, he launched his jet-powered sidecar (as guided missile role) at the Lotus, but then James overtook the truck and the sidecar hit the truck what contained pillow feathers, what then exploded and created a cloud of feathers and the motorcyclist drives off the cliff, covered in feathers. James then remarks: &quot;All those feathers and he still can't fly&quot;.

==Dr. Bechmann==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Dr. Bechmann
|portrayed=[[Cyril Shaps]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Self-employed&lt;br&gt;Indirectly, [[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
Dr. Bechmann is portrayed by [[Cyril Shaps]].

Bechmann is a renowned scientist who is working for Karl Stromberg. He designs the submarine-tracking device along with his colleague, Professor Markovitz. When the device is complete, Stromberg decides that instead of paying them they have outlived their usefulness and has their helicopter blown up.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Professor Markovitz==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Professor Markovitz
|portrayed=[[Milo Sperber]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=Self-employed&lt;br&gt;Indirectly, [[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
Professor Markovitz is portrayed by [[Milo Sperber]].

Markovitz is a renowned scientist who is working for Karl Stromberg. He designs the submarine-tracking device along with his colleague, Dr. Bechmann. When the device is complete, Stromberg decides that they have outlived their usefulness and has their helicopter blown up. A secretary who smuggled the plans for the device on microfilm is also killed by being dropped into a shark tank.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Liparus Captain==
{{James Bond Character|
|bgcolor=#000
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Liparus Captain
|portrayed=[[Sydney Tafler]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Karl Stromberg]]
|status= Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond villains|Henchman]]
}}
The Liparus Captain is played by [[Sydney Tafler]].

The Liparus Captain is the captain of Karl Stromberg's [[flagship]], the ''Liparus''. He is not seen until late in the film, carrying out various duties and operations in the ship's control centre. The captain ultimately answers to Stromberg. When the American, British and Russian submarine crews escape, the captain of the ''Liparus'' is able to warn Stromberg and give the order to seal off the control centre. Although he confidently tells Stromberg no other mishaps will occur, the Liparus Captain is killed when Bond detonates a bomb placed against the wall of the centre. As the crews storm the control centre, the captain tells Bond he is too late to derail Stromberg’s plan and that the SLBMs will begin ignition in four minutes.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

{{James Bond characters}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jaws}}
[[Category:Lists of James Bond henchmen|Spy Who Loved Me, The]]
[[Category:Fictional assassins]]
[[Category:The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|Henchmen]]

[[fr:Requin (James Bond)]]
[[it:Squalo (James Bond)]]
[[nl:Jaws (James Bond)]]
[[sv:Hajen (James Bond)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
