<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7709601" ns="0" title="All Saints (group)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|name = All Saints
|image =  
|caption =
|background = group_or_band
|origin = [[London]], [[Greater London]]
|instrument = [[Vocals]]
|genre = [[Hip hop music|Hip hop]], [[dance-pop]], [[Contemporary R&amp;B|R&amp;B]], [[Urban contemporary|urban]]
|years_active = 1993–2001&lt;br&gt;2006–2009
|label =[[ZTT Records]] &lt;small&gt;(1993–1995)&lt;/small&gt; [[London Records|London]] &lt;small&gt;(1996–2001)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br /&gt;[[Parlophone]] &lt;small&gt;(2006–2007)&lt;/small&gt;
|past_members = [[Shaznay Lewis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Melanie Blatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Nicole Appleton]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Natalie Appleton]]
}}

'''All Saints''' were a [[United Kingdom|British]]/[[Canada|Canadian]] [[girl group]]. Founded in 1993 as '''All Saints 1.9.7.5''', the group consisted of founding members [[Melanie Blatt]] and [[Shaznay Lewis]], and sisters [[Nicole Appleton]] and [[Natalie Appleton]]. They became one of the most successful British pop groups of the 1990s, with nine top ten singles (including five number-ones), two platinum albums, two gold albums and record sales in excess of ten million worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1106842.stm |title=10 Million Worldwide |publisher=BBC News |date=2001-01-09 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All Saints were formed as a trio in 1993 with Blatt, Lewis and Simone Rainford, who released two singles before Rainford's departure in 1995. Natalie and Nicole Appleton joined the group for the production of their debut album, ''[[All Saints (album)|All Saints]]'' (1997), which produced three UK number-one singles, including the [[BRIT Award]]-winning &quot;[[Never Ever (All Saints song)|Never Ever]]&quot;. Their second album, ''[[Saints &amp; Sinners (All Saints album)|Saints &amp; Sinners]]'' (2000), was also a success and yielded two number-one hits, although the group broke up in 2001. They later reformed for a third album, ''[[Studio 1]]'' (2006), but it sold poorly. All Saints were confirmed to have split up for a second time in 2009, and Melanie Blatt has said that the group will never reform.

==Formation==
Both [[Melanie Blatt]] and [[Shaznay Lewis]] started their career by singing backing vocals at [[Sarm West Studios]], the ZTT recording studios near All Saints Road, London. In 1993, Blatt, Lewis and the original third member [[Simone Rainford]], were signed to [[ZTT Records]], and music manager Ron Tom decided the trio should become a group.

All Saints 1.9.7.5 were launched as a trio in the vein of girl group [[Eternal (band)|Eternal]]. In 1994, All Saints 1.9.7.5. performed for their first time at the ''Touch'' Magazine stage at the [[Notting Hill]] Carnival.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.montrealmirror.com/ARCHIVES/1998/031998/cover.html Montreal Mirror] Accessed 31 December 2005&lt;/ref&gt; They released two singles together, but they were not successful. Additionally, Rainford and Blatt had conflicting visions of the band's musical direction which caused tensions in the band.

By 1994, the complicated recording sessions had produced the group's first single, &quot;[[Silver Shadow (song)|Silver Shadow]]&quot;, and the three girls performed throughout the UK. In mid 1995, Rainford left the band and ZTT Records dropped the remaining duo from their label. Regardless, Blatt and Lewis set out to find a replacement for Rainford. Conducting many auditions, Blatt's father met [[Nicole Appleton]] whom she knew from her days at the [[Sylvia Young Theatre School]]. Appleton's sister Natalie subsequently became a fourth member of the group.

== Subsequent career ==
=== 1997–1998: ''All Saints'' ===
{{Main|All Saints (All Saints album)}}
After forming a new group in May 1996, the four singers met with [[Karl Gordon|Karl &quot;K-Gee&quot; Gordon]], a former band member of [[Outlaw Posse]], who recorded a demo for &quot;[[I Know Where It's At]]&quot;. The band began looking for a new record deal, but most record labels wanted to model them after the [[Spice Girls]], who had become an international sensation by that time. The demo made its way to [[London Records]], where [[John Benson Brooks|John Benson]] finalised the recording deal in November 1996.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canoe.ca/JamMusicPopEncycloPagesA/all_saints.html Jam Music] Accessed 31 December 2005 {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; All Saints recorded their debut album, ''[[All Saints (All Saints album)|All Saints]]'', with producers such as [[Cameron McVey]], [[Magnus Fiennes]], Karl &quot;K-Gee&quot; Gordon, [[John Benson]], [[Johnny Douglas]], and [[Nellee Hooper]].

In mid 1997, the single &quot;I Know Where It's At&quot; broke the group into the mainstream, reaching number four on the [[UK Singles Chart]]. Their second single, &quot;[[Never Ever (All Saints song)|Never Ever]]&quot;, was issued in November 1997 and launched them worldwide, peaking at number one in the UK and Australia. The single sold 1.2 million copies in the UK alone (receiving a double platinum certification from the [[British Phonographic Industry]]) and won the group two [[BRIT Awards]] in 1998: Best British Single and Best British Video. The album ''All Saints'' was released in November 1997, reached number two on the [[UK Album Chart]], and was BPI-certified five times platinum in the UK for sales of 1.5 million. The third single from the album was the double A-side &quot;[[Under the Bridge / Lady Marmalade]]&quot;, which became their second UK number-one single in May 1998, earning a gold certification for 400,000 copies sold. The same month, the album was re-released with a slightly different track listing. &quot;[[Bootie Call]]&quot;, the fourth single, also went to number one, and the silver-certified &quot;[[War of Nerves]]&quot; (the fifth and final release) peaked at number seven, selling 200,000 copies.

The album achieved success in countries such as Australia ([[Australian Recording Industry Association|double platinum]], selling 140,000 copies), Canada ([[CRIA|triple platinum]], 300,000 copies), and the United States, where ''All Saints'' was certified platinum by the [[RIAA]] for sales of one million and produced two top forty singles on the [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]]: &quot;I Know Where It's At&quot; and &quot;Never Ever&quot;. In November 1998, All Saints received the [[MTV Europe Music Award]] for Best Breakthrough Artist and performed at the ceremony, although Blatt was absent due to her pregnancy.

=== 1999–2001: ''Saints &amp; Sinners'' and film debut ===
{{Main|Saints &amp; Sinners (All Saints album)}}

All Saints returned in February 2000 with the single &quot;[[Pure Shores]]&quot;, written by [[Shaznay Lewis]] and [[William Orbit]] for the soundtrack of the film ''[[The Beach (film)|The Beach]]'' (starring [[Leonardo DiCaprio]]). &quot;Pure Shores&quot; was their fourth number-one single in the UK and the second best-selling single of 2000, with 600,000 copies sold; it also became their first and only number-one single in Ireland and was a substantial hit across Europe and Australia. The song won an [[Ivor Novello Award]] for Most Performed Work.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1444030/craig-david-wins-ivor-novellos.jhtml&lt;/ref&gt; All Saints performed the song at the 2000 [[MTV Europe Music Awards]].
 
Also in 2000, the Appleton sisters and Blatt made their film debut with ''[[Honest (film)|Honest]]'', which was directed by former [[Eurythmics]] member [[David A. Stewart|Dave Stewart]]. ''Honest'' is a black comedy set in [[Swinging London]] in the late 1960s, in which the singers playing three street-wise, saucy sisters who head &quot;up West&quot; to pursue a life of crime. The film became most notable for the topless scenes by the [[Appleton (music duo)|Appleton sisters]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Top 10 Worst Vanity Projects&quot; [http://www.theshiznit.co.uk/feature/top-10-worst-vanity-projects.php]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Their performances were widely panned; one critic remarked, &quot;It is the worst kind of rubbish, the kind that makes you angry you have wasted 105 minutes of your life watching it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0192126/news?year=2000]&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2000, All Saints released the single &quot;[[Black Coffee (All Saints song)|Black Coffee]]&quot;, which became their fifth and final number-one single in the UK, selling 200,000 copies. This preceded their second studio album, ''[[Saints &amp; Sinners (All Saints album)|Saints &amp; Sinners]]'', which debuted at number one on the UK Albums Chart, eventually reaching double platinum certification in the UK for sales of 600,000 copies. The second and final single was &quot;[[All Hooked Up]]&quot; in January 2001, which peaked at number seven.

=== 2001: Break-up and ''All Hits'' ===
{{Main|All Hits}}
In February 2001, All Saints announced that they were to take a break so that they &quot;could clear the air between themselves&quot;. Melanie Blatt said later that year that it was uncertain if they would reform, citing their difficulties with the financial and business aspects of the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/1496270.stm | work=BBC News | title=All Saints 'split over money' | date=2001-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shaznay Lewis later explained that the catalyst for the break-up was a disagreement over who would wear a certain jacket for a photoshoot: &quot;I would never in a million years have put money on the group ending over a jacket incident. But when that incident happened, it fired up so strong, it had to be over. And the way I was then, the state we'd got into then, there was no way she was getting that stupid jacket.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2004/oct/10/popandrock1 | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Polly | last=Vernon | title=Patience of a saint | date=2004-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2001, [[London Records]] released a [[greatest hits]] compilation entitled ''[[All Hits]]''. It contains the group's hit singles and Blatt's first solo single, &quot;[[TwentyFourSeven (song)|TwentyFourSeven]]&quot;, a collaboration with [[Artful Dodger]]. The album peaked at number eighteen on the UK Albums Chart and was later certified gold, selling 100,000 copies. In 2008, a slightly altered edition of the album was given away for free as part of a promotion with ''[[The Mail on Sunday]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mailonsunday.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1048112/Free-CD-inside-weekends-Mail-On-Sunday--All-Saints-All-Hits.html Free CD in this week's ''Mail on Sunday'': All Saints] from [[Daily Mail]] website.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2006–2007: Reunion and ''Studio 1'' ===
{{Main|Studio 1 (album)}}

On 24 January 2006, it was announced that the band had reformed and signed a record deal with [[Parlophone]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.contactmusic.com/new/xmlfeed.nsf/mndwebpages/all%20saints%20confirm%20reunion_24_01_2006 |title=All Saints confirm reunion |publisher=Contact music |date= |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; They subsequently began work on their third studio album, ''[[Studio 1 (album)|Studio 1]]''. The first single, &quot;[[Rock Steady (All Saints song)|Rock Steady]]&quot; (released in November 2006), reached number three on the UK Singles Chart. ''Studio 1'' entered the albums chart at number forty, falling significantly short of the success of &quot;Rock Steady&quot; and the group's previous releases; it has since sold 60,000 copies according to the BPI, being certified silver.

A second single, &quot;[[Chick Fit]]&quot;, followed in February 2007, but promotional appearances and a physical release were cancelled and it failed to reach the top 200. It was subsequently reported that All Saints and Parlophone had parted ways and the group canceled their planned UK tour.

=== 2008–2009: Later activities ===
In January 2008, Nicole Appleton and Melanie Blatt served as &quot;hijackers&quot; on [[E4 (channel)|E4]]'s ''[[Big Brother: Celebrity Hijack]]'', during which Blatt said that they had a record deal with an undisclosed company in a conversation with housemate [[Nathan Fagan-Gayle]].

In February 2008, in a press release for the [[Wideboys]]' single with Shaznay Lewis (&quot;Daddy O&quot;) posted on the official website of [[All Around the World (record label)|All Around the World]], it was stated that All Saints were recording in the studio and would be back with new material before the end of 2008. Because no record label was mentioned in the update, fans assumed that the group's new label was All Around the World.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/bizarre/article1006752.ece |title=Saints set for new comeback |publisher=Thesun.co.uk |date=2008-04-07 |accessdate=2009-08-13 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2008, All Around the World discredited claims that All Saints had been signed with them with a post at their official website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aatw.com/?page=16 |title=All Saints&amp;nbsp;— a bit of clarification |publisher=Aatw.com |date= |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2009, Melanie Blatt told the ''[[London Lite]]'': &quot;All Saints are never getting back together again. I never want to sing again. I recently did the Brits with Nic and we just went round chatting to people and then got drunk. That's my goal&amp;mdash;to get paid for chatting to people and getting drunk!&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/showbiz/article-23737001-melanie-blatt-all-saints-will-never-get-back-together.do&lt;/ref&gt;

A second compilation album, ''[[Pure Shores: The Very Best of All Saints]]'', was released in September 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B0041EPTKC&lt;/ref&gt; This two-disc collection features the group's hit singles alongside a selection of album tracks and B-sides.

== Solo careers ==
'''[[Melanie Blatt]]''' was the first member to record after the group disbanded. In September 2001, she collaborated with [[Artful Dodger (UK band)|Artful Dodger]] on the track &quot;[[TwentyFourSeven (song)|TwentyFourSeven]]&quot;, which peaked at number six in the UK. In February 2002, Blatt replaced [[Kelis]]'s vocals on the UK release of the track &quot;I'm Leavin'&quot; by [[Outsidaz]] and [[Rah Digga]]; the single reached number forty-two. Her third single, &quot;[[Do Me Wrong]]&quot;, was released in August 2003 through [[London Records]] and peaked at number eighteen. Blatt was dropped by the label due to low sales, and the album she was working on at the time never materialised.

In April 2005, Blatt returned to the music industry with a new single, &quot;[[See Me]]&quot;, which was included on the ''[[Robots (film)|Robots]]'' film soundtrack and peaked at number seventy-eight in the UK. The single was released through Swollen Ankle Ltd, with whom Blatt began working on an album. During mid 2005, she played small venues in the UK and performed material from the album, which was shelved when All Saints reunited in early 2006.

After All Saints' split, '''[[Natalie Appleton|Natalie]]''' and '''[[Nicole Appleton]]''' wrote and recorded their own album, formed the duo [[Appleton (music duo)|Appleton]] and signed a contract with [[Polydor Records]]. In September 2002, the Appleton sisters launched their first single, &quot;[[Fantasy (Appleton)|Fantasy]]&quot;, which reached number two in the UK. Their autobiography, ''Together'', was published the following month. Their second single, &quot;[[Everything's Eventual (album)|Don't Worry]]&quot;, was released in March 2003 and reached number five in the UK before the release of their first album, ''[[Everything's Eventual (album)|Everything's Eventual]]'', the same month. The album peaked at number nine; its final single was &quot;[[Everything's Eventual (album)|Everything Eventually]]&quot;, which was released in July 2003 and peaked at number thirty-eight. Appleton and Polydor subsequently parted ways.

'''[[Shaznay Lewis]]''' released her first solo single, &quot;[[Never Felt Like This Before]]&quot;, in July 2004; it reached number eight in the UK. Her album ''[[Open (Shaznay Lewis album)|Open]]'' followed two weeks later via London Records and peaked at number twenty-two, although the second single, &quot;[[You (Shaznay Lewis song)|You]]&quot;, charted only at number fifty-six. In November 2004, Lewis was one of the artists involved in the [[Band Aid 20]] re-recording of &quot;[[Do They Know It's Christmas?]]&quot;. In early 2008, Lewis collaborated with [[Wideboys]] on the UK top forty hit &quot;Daddy O&quot;.

==Discography==
{{Main|All Saints discography}}
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
;Albums
*1997: ''[[All Saints (All Saints album)|All Saints]]''
*2000: ''[[Saints &amp; Sinners (All Saints album)|Saints &amp; Sinners]]''
*2006: ''[[Studio 1 (album)|Studio 1]]''

;Compilations
*1998: ''[[The Remix Album (All Saints album)|The Remix Album]]''
*2001: ''[[All Hits]]''
*2010: ''[[Pure Shores: The Very Best of All Saints]]''
{{col-3}}

;Singles
*1995: &quot;[[Silver Shadow (song)|Silver Shadow]]&quot;
*1995: &quot;[[Let's Get Started|If You Wanna Party (I Found Lovin)]]&quot; 
*1995: &quot;[[Let's Get Started]]&quot; (Japan release only)
*1997: &quot;[[I Know Where It's At]]&quot;
*1997: &quot;[[Never Ever (All Saints song)|Never Ever]]&quot;
*1998: &quot;[[Under the Bridge / Lady Marmalade|Under the Bridge&quot;/&quot;Lady Marmalade]]&quot;
*1998: &quot;[[Bootie Call]]&quot;
*1998: &quot;[[War of Nerves]]&quot;
*2000: &quot;[[Pure Shores]]&quot;
*2000: &quot;[[Black Coffee (All Saints song)|Black Coffee]]&quot;
*2001: &quot;[[All Hooked Up]]&quot;
*2006: &quot;[[Rock Steady (All Saints song)|Rock Steady]]&quot;
*2007: &quot;[[Chick Fit]]&quot;
{{S-end}}

==Awards and nominations==
{{awards table}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;7&quot;| 1998
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| &quot;Never Ever&quot; || [[BRIT Awards|BRIT Award for Best British Single]] || {{won}}
|-
| BRIT Award for Best British Video || {{won}}
|-
| All Saints || BRIT Award for Best British Breakthrough Act || {{nom}}
|-
| &quot;Never Ever&quot; || [[MTV Europe Music Award]] for Best Song || {{nom}}
|-
| ''All Saints'' || MTV Europe Music Award for Best Album || {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| All Saints
| MTV Europe Music Award for Best Group || {{nom}}
|-
| MTV Europe Music Award for Best New Act || {{won}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| 1999
| [[Under the Bridge / Lady Marmalade|&quot;Under the Bridge&quot; / &quot;Lady Marmalade&quot;]]  || BRIT Award for Best British Video || {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| All Saints
| BRIT Award for Best British Dance Act || {{nom}}
|-
| 2000 || MTV Europe Music Award for Best Pop || {{won}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;5&quot;| 2001
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| &quot;Pure Shores&quot; || BRIT Award for Best British Single || {{nom}}
|-
| BRIT Award for Best British Video || {{nom}}
|-
| All Saints || BRIT Award for Best British Group || {{nom}}
|-
| &quot;Pure Shores&quot; || [[Ivor Novello Award]] for Most Performed Work || {{won}}
|-
| All Saints || [[NME Awards|NME Award]] for Best Pop Act || {{nom}}
|-
{{end}}

==See also==
{{Wikipedia-Books|All Saints}}
* [[List of best-selling girl groups]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|All Saints (musical group)|All Saints (group)}}
&lt;!-- Do ''not'' add links to forums or non-English language sites per Wikipedia guidelines--&gt;
* {{myspace|allsaints|All Saints}}
*{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p182958|label=All Saints}}
* [http://www.allsaintsband.com All Saints Fundamental Fansite]

{{All Saints}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:All Saints}}
[[Category:All Saints (group)| ]]
[[Category:Brit Award winners]]
[[Category:British dance music groups]]
[[Category:British rhythm and blues musical groups]]
[[Category:British girl groups]]
[[Category:Musical groups from London]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1993]]
[[Category:Musical groups reestablished in 2006]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 2009]]

[[ar:أول سينتس]]
[[bg:Ол Сейнтс]]
[[cy:All Saints]]
[[da:All Saints]]
[[de:All Saints]]
[[es:All Saints]]
[[fr:All Saints]]
[[it:All Saints (gruppo musicale)]]
[[he:אול סיינטס]]
[[ka:All Saints]]
[[nl:All Saints (band)]]
[[ja:オール・セインツ (グループ)]]
[[pl:All Saints]]
[[pt:All Saints]]
[[ru:All Saints]]
[[simple:All Saints (group)]]
[[sk:All Saints]]
[[fi:All Saints (yhtye)]]
[[sv:All Saints]]
[[th:ออลเซนต์ส (กลุ่มดนตรี)]]
[[tr:All Saints]]
[[vi:All Saints]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
