<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7737454" ns="0" title="List of James Bond allies in The Living Daylights"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=February 2008}}
This is a list of [[James Bond]] [[List of James Bond allies|allies]] in the film ''[[The Living Daylights]]''.

==Recurring allies==
*[[M (James Bond)|M]] - [[Robert Brown (British actor)|Robert Brown]]
*[[Q (James Bond)|Q]] - [[Desmond Llewelyn]]
*[[Miss Moneypenny]] - [[Caroline Bliss]]
*[[Felix Leiter]] - [[John Terry (actor)|John Terry]]
*[[General Gogol]] - [[Walter Gotell]]
*[[Fredrick Gray]] - [[Geoffrey Keen]]

==Saunders==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Saunders
|portrayed=[[Thomas Wheatley]]
|gender=Male
|affiliation=[[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Saunders''' is a fictional [[James Bond]] character in the film ''[[The Living Daylights]]''.  He is portrayed by [[Thomas Wheatley]].

===Film biography===
He first appears as Bond's companion as they attempt to arrange for [[General Georgi Koskov]], whom they believe to be a high-profile [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] defector, to escape to the West. When Bond refuses to kill the cellist [[Kara Milovy]], whom Koskov was setting up as his &quot;assassin&quot;, Saunders threatens to charge him with insubordination.

Later, after Koskov arranges for his escape and Bond realizes that Koskov's defection was actually faked, he has Saunders gather information on Milovy's patron [[Brad Whitaker]], who turned out to be Koskov's accomplice, and produce a bogus [[United Kingdom|British]] passport to enable her to travel with him.

After Bond and Saunders meet in a café in [[Vienna]] and Bond gets the intelligence and the passport, Saunders is killed when Whitaker's henchman [[Necros (James Bond)|Necros]] detonates a bomb set in the mechanism of a sliding glass door, sending it smashing into Saunders. As Bond reaches his body, a balloon floats down, reading the words Smiert Spionem (Death To Spies).
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==General Leonid Pushkin==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Leonid Pushkin|portrayed=[[John Rhys-Davies]]
|gender=Male
|affiliation=[[KGB]]
|status= Active
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}

'''General Leonid Pushkin''' is the head of the [[KGB]] in the [[film]] ''[[The Living Daylights]]''. He is played by Welsh actor [[John Rhys-Davies]]. Although he is originally thought by [[James Bond]] and the rest of the [[MI6]] to be the enemy, a KGB leader turned psychotic, Bond, still suspicious of [[Koskov]], stages Pushkin's death in the view of the Russian [[List of James Bond henchmen in The Living Daylights#Necros|Necros]] to investigate Koskov's defection. The real enemies, Koskov and Whitaker, believe Pushkin to be dead and feel free to pursue their goals in [[Afghanistan]]. Pushkin later shows up at Whitaker's villa in [[Tangier]] and orders a shocked Koskov executed. Pushkin turns out to be an invaluable ally.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

=== Trivia ===
* Originally Pushkin's role was really that of Gogol, but due to health status of [[Walter Gotell]] was decided to create the character of Pushkin.

* Pushkin was in the early draft of [[Goldeneye]] and would have played a critical role in the film pursuing Bond throughout Russia.

==Kamran Shah==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Kamran Shah
|portrayed=[[Art Malik]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Afghanistan|Afghan]] ''[[Mujahideen]]''
|status=Active
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Kamran Shah''' was a fictional character from the [[James Bond]] film, ''[[The Living Daylights]]''. He was played by [[Art Malik]].

An [[Oxford University|Oxford]]-educated deputy commander of the [[Mujahideen]]'s Eastern District in [[Afghanistan]], Shah is fighting the Soviet occupation. Bond encounters him in a prison on a Soviet airbase, and helps him escape. In return, Shah accompanies Bond and [[Kara Milovy]] back to his base.

Bond discovers that Shah is assisting a drug deal with [[General Georgi Koskov]], without realising that the drugs he is selling will be used to buy arms to fight his own people. Shah follows Bond to the airbase where he and his men help Bond destroy the drug haul, and the airbase. At the end of the film, Shah and his men appear in Europe in order to attend a classical concert given by Kara.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Rosika Miklos==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Rosika Miklos
|portrayed=[[Julie T. Wallace]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=
|status=Active/Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Rosika Miklos''' is a fictional character from the [[James Bond]] film, ''[[The Living Daylights]]''. She was played by 6 foot 2&amp;nbsp;inch (188&amp;nbsp;cm) tall actress [[Julie T. Wallace]].

Miklos is an infiltrated agent for MI6 in [[Bratislava]], working at the Russian oil pipeline into [[Austria]]. When Bond smuggles [[General Georgi Koskov|General Koskov]] through the pipe in a cleaning scouring plug, Miklos distracts the supervisor of the pipe by putting his head between her breasts. As soon as the triggered alarms go off, Miklos rejects the supervisor, exclaiming indignantly, &quot;What kind of girl do you think I am!&quot;.

&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Rubavitch==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Rubavitch
|portrayed=[[Virginia Hey]]
|gender=Female
|affiliation=[[List of James Bond allies in The Living Daylights#General Leonid Pushkin|General Leonid Pushkin]]
|status=Active
|role=[[Bond girl]]/[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Rubavitch''' is a fictional character from the [[James Bond]] film, ''[[The Living Daylights]]''. She was played by [[Virginia Hey]]. She is General Pushkin's girlfriend.
When 007 broke into Pushkin's hotel room she was waiting for Pushkin. Pushkin called for his guard but Bond ripped her robe off, exposing her breasts to the guard to distract him.
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;
{{James Bond characters}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of James Bond Allies In The Living Daylights}}
[[Category:Lists of James Bond allies|Living Daylights, The]]
[[Category:The Living Daylights|Allies]]

[[es:Anexo:Aliados de James Bond En The Living Daylights]]
[[pt:General Pushkin]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
