<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="773700" ns="0" title="St. Thomas Aquinas College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|other schools named after St. Thomas Aquinas|Institutions named after Thomas Aquinas}}
{{Infobox university
|name = St. Thomas Aquinas 
|image = [[File:Stac torch.png]]
|motto =
|established = 1952
|type = [[Private university|Private]]
|calendar = Semester
|president = Dr. [[Margaret Fitzpatrick]]
|students = 2,400
|city = {{flagicon|USA}} [[Sparkill, New York|Sparkill]]
|state = [[New York|NY]]
|country = [[United States|USA]]
|campus = [[Suburban area|Suburban]]
|athletics =14 Varsity Teams&lt;br&gt;[[East Coast Conference]]&lt;br&gt;[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]]
|colors = [[Maroon (color)|Maroon]] {{color box|maroon}} [[Gold]] {{color box|gold}}
|free_label = Newspaper
|free = Thoma
|mascot = [[St. Thomas Aquinas College#St. Thomas Aquinas College Spartans|Spartans]]
|website= [http://www.stac.edu/ www.stac.edu]
|logo =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[Image:St-Thomas-Aquinas-College.jpg|248px|St. Thomas Aquinas College Logo]] --&gt;}}

[[Image:9.4.07StThomasAquinasCollegebyLuigiNovi.JPG|right|thumb|The campus of St. Thomas Aquinas College, showing Costello Hall in the background.]]

'''St. Thomas Aquinas College''' is a private four-year [[liberal arts college]] in [[Rockland County, New York]] that occupies a forty-eight acre campus. Located at 125 [[New York State Route 340|Route 340]] in [[Sparkill, New York]], the college is named after the [[Middle Ages|medieval]] [[philosopher]] and [[theology|theologian]] [[Thomas Aquinas]].  It was founded by the [[Dominican Sisters]] of Sparkill, New York. 

==Majors Offered==
'''Bachelor of Arts:'''
Art,
Art Therapy,
Communications Arts,
English,
English 7-12 certification,
History,
Philosophy/Religious Studies,
Romance Languages,
Spanish,
Spanish 7-12 certification

'''Bachelor of Science:'''
Accounting,
Biology,
Biology 7-12 certification,
Business Administration,
Computer Science,
Criminal Justice,
Finance,
Forensic Science,
Graphic Design,
Liberal Arts and Sciences,
Marketing,
Mathematics,
Mathematics 7-12 certification,
Medical Technology,
Natural Sciences (Biology, Chemistry, Physics),
Natural Sciences (Biology, Chemistry, Physics) 7-12 certification,
Psychology,
Recreation &amp; Leisure (Leisure Management, Sports Management, Therapeutic Recreation),
Social Sciences,
Social Sciences 7-12 certification,

'''Bachelor of Science in Education:'''
Childhood Education (Grades 1-6),
Childhood Education and Special Education (Grades 1-6)

'''Pre-Professional Studies'''
Pre-Dental&lt;br&gt;
Pre-Law&lt;br&gt;
Pre-Medical&lt;br&gt;
Pre-Pharmacy

'''Dual Degrees:'''
Biology/Biomedical Engineering&lt;br&gt;
Chiropractic&lt;br&gt;
Engineering&lt;br&gt;
Physical Therapy&lt;br&gt;
Podiatry

'''Master in Business Administration'''
Finance&lt;br&gt;
General Studies (also available in an online format)&lt;br&gt;
Marketing

'''Master Science in Teaching'''
Available for students who's undergraduate degree is not in teaching.&lt;br&gt;
Childhood Education Grades 1-6 (39 credits)&lt;br&gt;
Childhood and Special Education Grades 1-6 (45 credits)&lt;br&gt;
Adolescent Education Grades 7-12

'''Master Science Education'''
Educational Leadership (leading to School Building Leader certification&lt;br&gt;
Special Education (Grades 1-6)&lt;br&gt;
Special Education (Grades 7-12)&lt;br&gt;
Literacy Education (Birth- Grade 6)&lt;br&gt;
Literacy Education (Grades 5-12)&lt;br&gt;
Post Masters Professional Certificate in Literacy&lt;br&gt;
Post Masters Professional Certificate in Special Education

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:stac spartans.jpg]] --&gt;

==Special programs==
'''Honors Program'''

The Honors Program at St. Thomas Aquinas College is designed for students of superior academic ability with a decided commitment to humane values. The Program reflects the declared mission of the College as an institution committed to both the search for truth through the enlightenment that comes from knowledge and to human freedom that is an outgrowth of seeking the truth.

The objectives of the Honors Program at St. Thomas Aquinas College, which was implemented in 1987, are student centered and may be expressed as follows:

to experience the inter-relatedness of knowledge from various disciplines;

to deepen a passion for knowledge that goes beyond the more formal aspects of education;

to experience that the search for truth is timeless and never ending;

to realize the necessity of discipline in scholarly pursuits;

to appreciate more fully the broad array of gifts of all persons.

Students who are selected for admission to the Honors Program will have their academic schedules modified to include special courses taught by versatile professors dedicated to the humane objectives of the Program. Over the several semesters of their attendance at St. Thomas Aquinas College these students will be invited to enroll in a series of Honors courses, beginning with special sections of freshman English and followed by advanced courses on particular topics in a variety of disciplines. Some of these courses will be interdisciplinary in nature and may be team-taught. The Honors Program encompasses the four years of undergraduate study during which students are expected to complete a minimum of six Honors courses.

Applicants to the Honors Program are strongly encouraged to apply early. Completed applications are considered on a rolling basis, and admission to the Honors Program is highly competitive.

Application to the Honors Program is open to new freshmen entering college as full time students in the Fall semester who meet the following criteria:

High school average of 90 or above in major subjects at the time of application, and

Combined SAT scores of at least 1200 with no section less than 550 or ACT composite score of 27.

Evidence of a rigorous course of study in high school (usually includes honors and/or AP courses).

Evidence of substantial involvement in extra-curricular activities.

'''Pathways'''

Pathways, formerly known as &quot;The STAC Exchange,&quot; is a program serving selected college students with learning disabilities and/or attention deficit disorders at St. Thomas Aquinas College. The program emphasizes individualized support and personal attention in a comfortable atmosphere conducive to education.

The STAC Exchange was established at St. Thomas Aquinas College in 1982 to meet the growing need for specialized services at the college level for bright students with learning disabilities. In an effort to serve this population, STAC researched, developed, and implemented a pilot program for select high school graduates with the potential to earn a college degree. The STAC Exchange has adapted to the increasing diversity of college students with learning disabilities and attention deficit disorders, with an emphasis on individualized services. In September 2004, the program's name was changed to &quot;Pathways,&quot; a name that better reflects its mission.

Pathways focuses on the development of effective learning strategies by critically evaluating and educating each student about his or her specific needs and abilities. The aim is to break the pattern of dependency often created in students with learning deficits, to foster a spirit of independent and active learning, to teach students to maximize strengths in order to compensate for weaknesses, and to inspire confidence in the student's own abilities.

Pathways students represent almost every major the College offers, often attaining academic honors as they work toward their degree. After graduation, some Pathways alumni have pursued graduate study at such institutions as Fordham University, New York University, Iona College, and John Jay College; some have remained at STAC to pursue master's degrees in Education or Business. Pathways graduates are employed in a wide variety of positions, including special education teacher, high school teacher, college instructor, recreation therapist, school psychologist, police officer, radio broadcaster, national park ranger, mortgage broker, and small business owner.

==Athletics==
The St. Thomas Aquinas College Spartans field 16 varsity [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] [[East Coast Conference]] athletic teams. These include Track and Field, Cross Country, Baseball, Basketball, Lacrosse, Soccer, Softball, Golf, and Tennis.

==Notable alumni==
*[[Barbara Corcoran]], self-made real estate millionaire who sold her company The Corcoran Group for $70 million in 2001.
*[[Gordon M. Johnson]], Representative of the [[New Jersey Legislative Districts, 2001 redistricting#District 37|37th legislative district]] in the [[New Jersey General Assembly]].&lt;ref name=NJLEG&gt;[http://www.njleg.state.nj.us/members/Johnson.asp Assemblyman Johnson's Legislative Website], [[New Jersey Legislature]]. Accessed July 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Frank Messina]], poet and author.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.harlemlive.org/community/events/poetry_night/Hweek.html Poetry Night At Jimmy's Cafe], Harlem Live. Accessed October 7, 2007. &quot;He is an Italian American, from New Jersey who attended Northern Valley Regional High School and St. Thomas Aquinas College.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Gordon Chiesa]], an assistant coach for the [[Memphis Grizzlies]] of the NBA.
*[[Dominick Goose]], Creator of Goose Video Productions, video slideshowing
*[[Major Marvin L. Hill]], Command Sergeant Major of US Central Command.
*[[Kevin P. Duignan]], Vice President for Institutional Advancement at St. Thomas Aquinas College.
*[[Steve Maney]], Popular Morning Radio Host KRQ Tucson, KDND Sacramento, WHBQ Memphis
*[[Craig Zucker]], Maryland State Delegate for the 14th legislative district
*[[Jeremy Brown]], Deputy Editor, ''WWE Magazine''

==Pop culture==
The campus was also used as a filming location for the 2003 [[Katie Holmes]] film [[Pieces of April]]. Big Al's brother went there.  External shots of Marion Hall, an educational building that also houses the school's main business office and several professors offices, is used as the grandmother's nursing home.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.stac.edu/ St. Thomas Aquinas College's Official Site]

{{New York Collegiate Athletic Conference}}
{{Dominican College and Universities}}

{{coord missing|New York}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Saint Thomas Aquinas College}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in New York]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Dominican universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Dominican College| (New York)]]
[[Category:St. Thomas Aquinas College alumni| ]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1952]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Rockland County, New York]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
