<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="77887" ns="0" title="Ion Television"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--Note: Do not change the name article to ION Television as that violates WP:TRADEMARK--&gt;
{{Infobox broadcasting network
|network_name = Ion Television|
|network_logo = [[File:Ion Television logo.svg|150px]] |
|slogan = ''&quot;Positively Entertaining&quot;''|
|country = [[United States]]|
|network_type = [[Terrestrial television|Broadcast]] [[television network]], [[Direct-broadcast satellite|satellite]] television network|
|available = National (but not available in all markets)|
|owner = [[ION Media Networks]]|
|key_people = R. Brandon Burgess|
|launch_date = August 31, 1998 (as '''PAX TV''')&lt;br&gt;July 1, 2005 (as '''''i''''': '''Independent Television''')&lt;br&gt;January 29, 2007 (as '''Ion Television''')|
|founder = [[Bud Paxson|Lowell 'Bud' Paxson]]|
|Picture format = [[480i]] (SD)&lt;br&gt;[[720p]] (HD)|
|past_names = Pax (1998–2005)&lt;br&gt;i (2005–2007)|
|website = http://www.iontelevision.com|
}}
'''Ion Television''' (stylized &quot;ion TELEVISION&quot;) is a [[United States]] [[broadcast television|broadcast]] [[television network]].  Owned by [[ION Media Networks]], the networked commenced broadcasting on August 31, 1998 as '''PAX TV''', a named it used until July 1, 2005, when it became '''''i'': Independent Television'''; the network was rechristened Ion on January 29, 2007.  {{As of|2010}}, the network was reportedly viewable in 99 million homes in the U.S. through its group of 60 stations, as well as cable and satellite distribution. Its stations reach all of the top 20 U.S. markets and 37 of the top 50 markets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionmedianetworks.com/]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===PAX===
[[File:PAX logo.svg|thumb|100px|right|The logo for PAX TV, used from its August 31, 1998 launch until July 1, 2005.  A monochrome version was used at times on-air; an initial version featured a dove above the &quot;X.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northpine.com/broadcast/captures/ia/kfpx.html Source: Northpine.com (screen shot image)]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The network was originally named Pax Net, then renamed PAX TV before its launch in 1998 by [[Bud Paxson|Lowell &quot;Bud&quot; Paxson]], co-founder of the [[Home Shopping Network]] and chairman of Paxson Communications. The network also aired religious programming at night from [[The Worship Network]] during the late night hours and contemporary Christian television network Praise TV Friday and Saturday nights from midnight–3 a.m. ET/PT.

Most of PAX's initial affiliates were Paxson Communications-owned affiliate stations of the Infomail TV Network or [[InTV]], a broadcast network launched in 1995 by Lowell &quot;Bud&quot; Paxson, that relied solely on infomercial programming.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-16217997.html Paxson's IN TV: move over UPN, WN (Lowell Paxson predicts that his Infomall TV Network will out perform United Paramount Network and WB Network)], ''[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]]'' (via HighBeam Research), January 23, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; The network launched on August 31, 1998&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4458284.html Pax TV to offer family programming], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'' (via HighBeam Research), August 16, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; with PAX's initial schedule being much larger in scope than it would be in later years. It consisted of general entertainment programs from noon-midnight ET/PT weekdays and of paid programming from midnight-1 a.m. ET/PT, 5 a.m.–noon ET/PT, and all afternoon on Saturdays and Sundays.

Initial programming on the network consisted of new shows, such as ''[[It's a Miracle (TV series)|It's a Miracle]]'', the [[game show]] ''[[The Reel to Reel Picture Show]]'', and [[talk show]]s ''[[Woman's Day]]'' and ''Great Day America'', along with reruns of older programming, including ''[[Highway to Heaven]]'', ''[[Here's Lucy]]'', ''[[The Hogan Family]]'', ''[[Dave's World]]'', and ''[[Touched by an Angel]]''. New episodes and older reruns of ''[[Candid Camera]]'' were also shown. The network also created some original dramas such as ''[[Sue Thomas: F.B.Eye]]'', ''[[Doc (TV series)|Doc]]'', ''[[Mysterious Ways (TV series)|Mysterious Ways]]'', ''[[Hope Island (TV Series)|Hope Island]]'', and ''[[Twice in a Lifetime (TV series)|Twice in a Lifetime]]''.

PAX aired many game shows, Examples include first-run revivals of established cable games such as ''[[Supermarket Sweep]]'' and ''[[Shop 'til You Drop]]'', Plus some original games including ''[[On the Cover (game show)|On the Cover]]'',  ''[[Balderdash (game show)|Balderdash]]'' and [[Born Lucky]]. Later, the network would carry re-runs of ''[[Family Feud]]'' and (Thanks to their partial ownership by NBC) ''[[The Weakest Link]]''.

===From PAX to ''i''===
[[Image:i independent television logo.jpg|75px|left|thumb|''i'' logo, used from July 1, 2005 to January 29, 2007]]On June 28, 2005, Paxson announced it would rebrand PAX as ''i'', in order to reflect a new strategy of &quot;providing an independent broadcast platform for producers and syndicators who desire to reach a national audience.&quot; After the transition was complete, PAX TV would continue to air programming under its PAX brand on one of its digital channels over the air and in select cable homes (''see [[#National/secondary programming|below]]''). Some media observers jocularly postulated that ''i'' was code for &quot;[[infomercial]]&quot;.

With this rebranding also came the following changes to the programming lineup:
* ''i'' dropped overnight programming from [[The Worship Network]], which had been airing late nights on the network since its launch in August 1998. The time period is now leased to infomercials. Worship programming moved to a digital subchannel on local ''i'' affiliates.
* In many markets starting in the Fall of 2002, some PAX stations had aired editions of local newscasts from local [[NBC]] affiliate stations. This was discontinued from some ''i'' station lineups on June 30, 2005.
* Also dropped was &quot;Tomorrow's Weather Tonight&quot;, a five-minute segment featuring current weather and forecasts from [[WeatherVision]] which had aired on the channel since 2000.

[[Image:IONTelevision.svg|100px|thumb|right|Ion Television logo used from January 29, 2007 to September 8, 2008.  This logo still serves as the corporate insignia for [[ION Media Networks]], while a green-tinted version serves as the logo for [[ION Life]].]]On January 29, 2007, the network changed its name again, to the current '''ION Television'''. The programming was, for the most part, unchanged at that time; the network continued to feature programming from its content deals, such as ''[[Who's the Boss?]]'', ''[[Mama's Family]]'', ''[[Growing Pains]]'', and ''[[The Wonder Years]]''. However, in 2008, the network re-tooled its focus, emphasizing the 18–49 demographic and airing various, newer programming attracting a younger audience, such as ''[[Boston Legal]]'', ''[[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]]'' and ''[[Criminal Minds]]''.

==Programming==
{{Main|List of programs broadcast by Ion Television}}
Ion Television operates on a 90-hour network programming schedule, which it adopted in March 2011. It provides 90 hours of afternoon and [[prime time]] general entertainment programming to affiliated stations Monday-Fridays from 3 p.m.-3 a.m. ET/PT, and Saturdays and Sundays from 1 p.m.-3 a.m. ET/PT, along with a children's programming block known as [[qubo]] airing for one hour each on Wednesday–Fridays from 8-9 a.m. ET/PT. All other times are filled with religious programming or infomercials. The network will in the future resume original programming. However the current method of using syndicated programming is very similar to the international model of broadcasting used in Europe, Canada, Latin America, Asia and Australia, but not the United States. This model mixes imported and syndicated shows with original programming.

On May 1, 2008, Ion Television released its new programming plan for the 2008–2009 season at the [[New York Public Library]] in [[New York City]]. In addition to the &quot;new&quot; programming as described, Ion announced a new logo and slogan for the network, ''Positively Entertaining.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businesswire.com/portal/site/google/?ndmViewId=news_view&amp;newsId=20080501006048&amp;newsLang=en ION Television Presents &quot;Positively Entertaining&quot; Program Lineup at 2008 Sales Presentation], ''Business Wire'', May 1, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Recent programming deals===
In 2006, Ion Media Networks reached several programming deals. Two were with major programming suppliers announced within a week of each other. Another would bring original programming to the Ion network, among other things.

On June 27, 2006, Ion announced a comprehensive programming deal with [[Warner Bros. Television Distribution]], giving them broadcast rights to movies and programming owned by Warner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionmedia.tv/press/press.cfm?id=11 Press&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; On July 5, 2006, Ion announced a similar deal with [[Sony Pictures Television]], giving them broadcast rights to movies and programming owned by Sony.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionmedia.tv/press/press.cfm?id=12 Press&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Starting in September, programs and feature-length movies from both libraries were phased into the primetime schedule. The schedule was heavy on programs from the deals such as ''[[Who's the Boss?]]'', ''[[Designing Women]]'', ''[[Mama's Family]]'', ''[[Growing Pains]]'', ''[[Green Acres]]'', and ''[[The Wonder Years]]''. However, all shows were phased out when the network entered its current direction. Ion also struck a deal with [[NBC Universal]] for library content, which gave it access to shows such as ''[[Alfred Hitchcock Presents]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionmedia.tv/press/press.cfm?id=19 Press&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In January 2008, Ion and [[Comcast]] reached an agreement to continue to carry Ion, as well as add [[Qubo]] and [[ION Life]] to Comcast's channel lineups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.multichannel.com/article/CA6522639.html ION Media Plugs In New Comcast Accord], ''Multichannel News'', January 14, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2008 Ion Television reached a multiyear agreement with [[Warner Bros. Television Distribution]], which gave the network access to the studio's more recent movies. ''[[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]]'' joined in September 2008, and ''[[Criminal Minds]]'' and ''[[Ghost Whisperer]]'' were added to the Ion Television lineup in 2009. ''Ghost Whisperer'' began airing on Ion on June 1, 2009 on Mondays.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sitcomsonline.com/blog/2009/05/sitcomsonlinecom-2009-10-upfront_14.html Sitcomsonline.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2009, the network announced that it had acquired broadcast rights to air the award-winning [[Canada|Canadian]] cable drama series ''[[Durham County (TV series)|Durham County]]'' in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionmedia.tv/press/press.cfm?id=137 ION Television Acquires the Award-Winning Original TV Series ''Durham County''], January 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The show aired only briefly.

Most Ion programs now come from either [[20th Century Fox Television]] or [[CBS Television Distribution]]. Ion Television has announced deals with various studios to acquire nearly 40 major feature films and television series from [[Paramount Pictures]], [[20th Century Fox]] and [[Warner Bros.]].&lt;ref name=deals&gt;[http://www.sitcomsonline.com/blog/2010/02/ion-adds-mash-to-weekdays-ion-announces.html ION Adds &quot;M*A*S*H&quot; to Weekdays; ION Announces New Deals with Studios], ''Sitcoms Online'', February 16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 21, 2011, it was announced that Ion Television would air the remaining 11 episodes from season four of ''[[Flashpoint (TV series)|Flashpoint]]'', after CBS airs the first 8 episodes of season four.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.deadline.com/2011/01/canadian-drama-flashpoint-in-u-s-syndi-deal-will-air-originals-on-cbs-and-ion/&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2011, Ion Television acquired six films from [[Starz Media]] and will begin air them as part of its Big Movie Weekend starting in November.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.multichannel.com/article/470986-Ion_Television_Inks_Starz_Media_Deal_For_Six_Theatricals.php&lt;/ref&gt; Ion also acquired syndication rights of top-rated cable progams ''[[Psych]]'' and ''[[Monk (tv series)|Monk]]'', from [[NBCUniversal]]. Also added is ''[[House MD]]'', also from [[NBCUniversal]], which will begin airing twice a week. The programs will begin to air in Fall of 2012. 

On August 24, 2011, Ion Television and [[PMC (company)|Penske Media Corporation]], announced the launch of Entertainment News Television (ENTV), an original multi-platform breaking news service, which will consist of content mainly from the resources of the Hollywood Life and [[Deadline.com]] entertainment news sites.

In September 2011, Ion Television acquired the syndication rights to ''[[Leverage (TV series)|Leverage]]'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.tvweek.com/blogs/tvbizwire/2011/09/tnt-series-gets-syndication-de.php&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[George Lopez (TV series)|George Lopez]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.deadline.com/2011/09/ion-acquires-comedy-george-lopez/&lt;/ref&gt; ''George Lopez'' began airing on September 29, while ''Leverage'' will debut in 2012.

===Other programming===
====Children's programming====
The network, as PAX TV, aired a five-hour children's programming block called ''PAX Kids'' on Saturday and Sunday mornings, which featured mostly religious children's programming and archive programming from [[DIC Entertainment]] such as the ''[[Super Mario Bros.]]'' [[List of Mario television series|animated series]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117469438.html?categoryid=18&amp;cs=1&amp;query=|title=Paxson, DIC in kidstuff deal for Pax Net|date=April 3, 1998|work=Variety|accessdate=2009-08-15 | first=Richard | last=Katz}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lineup lasted only a year and a half, presumably due to low ratings. (The last animated show to be cancelled was ''[[Archie's Weird Mysteries]]''). What was unusual about the lineup is that although it was a weekend-only lineup like ABC, CBS and NBC, it was spread over two days, Saturday and Sunday.

In May 2006, the network announced plans to launch a new children's block on Saturday mornings starting in September 2006 as part of the Qubo endeavor (''see [[#Qubo|below]]''), teaming ION Media Networks with NBC Universal, [[Scholastic Press]], [[Corus Entertainment]]'s [[Nelvana]]  unit, [[Classic Media]] and its [[Big Idea Productions]] unit. Qubo includes blocks airing on Ion Television, [[NBC]] and [[Telemundo]] (NBC Universal's Spanish-language network) along with a 24/7 digital broadcast kids channel, Qubo Channel, video-on-demand services and a branded website. ION Television, along with [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]], are the only broadcast networks that broadcast children's programming on weekday afternoons.

The [[Qubo]] lineup on Ion Television features the same programming as the NBC Qubo lineup. On Friday, September 15, 2006 ''i'' started airing the Qubo programs ''[[VeggieTales]]'', ''[[Dragon (TV series)|Dragon]]'', ''[[3-2-1 Penguins!]]'', ''[[Babar (TV series)|Babar]]'', ''[[Jane and the Dragon]]'', and ''[[Jacob Two-Two]]''.

====Sports====
Previous network sports event telecasts included [[Conference USA]] [[college football]] games (produced by [[CBS College Sports Network|College Sports Television]]), the [[Women's United Soccer Association]], [[Real Pro Wrestling]] (which more resembles the amateur form than the theatrically based ring sport), the [[Champions Tour]] of golf, [[Paralympic Games]], and ''[[BodogFight (TV series)|BodogFight]]''.

Ion Television aired [[NFL Films]]' weekly highlight program, the ''[[NFL Films Game of the Week]]'', Saturdays at 6 PM ET beginning September 15, 2007, with the [[New York Giants|Giants]]-[[Dallas Cowboys|Cowboys]] game from September 9. The series ran from September 9 through December 29, but was not renewed for 2008.

Ion Television was supposed to begin coverage of the [[American Indoor Football Association]] beginning in March 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aifaprofootball.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=142&amp;Itemid=1 This Week In The AIFA Previews Season Kickoff]. AIFA press release. 4 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the game's producers did not provide a live broadcast and the deal was canceled.

On December 28, 2010, Ion Television signed a deal with the [[Ultimate Fighting Championship]] to air the preliminary fights to their January 1 pay per view [[UFC 125]].&lt;ref&gt;http://mmajunkie.com/news/21864/ion-television-lands-ufc-125-prelims-dana-white-promises-three-fights.mma&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 22, 2011, it was announced that the preliminary fights of [[UFC 127]] would air on February 24, 2011, on Ion Television.

In November 2011, it was announced that the four preliminary bouts of [[UFC 140]] would air on December 10th, 2011 on ion Television.

===Ion Plus===
Separate national feeds have been made available to Dish Network, DirecTV, [[Time Warner Cable]], [[Comcast]], [[Charter Communications|Charter]], and non-O&amp;O stations, featuring programming from [[ION Life]] in place of paid programming that airs on the main network.

Prior to the launch of Ion Life, the Ion Plus feeds carried reruns of cancelled PAX original programs (''[[Miracle Pets]]'', ''[[Beat the Clock]]''), as well as [[public domain]] movies and [[situation comedy|sitcom]] episodes (''[[I Married Joan]]'', ''[[The Beverly Hillbillies]]'').

The feeds used the PAX name and [[Digital on-screen graphic|bug]] after PAX had changed its name to ''i'', until about September 2005.

===Ion HD===
In early 2009, Ion Media Networks had planned to launch ION Television HD by February 16.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.multichannel.com/article/162874-Ion_To_Launch_HD_Simulcast_On_Feb_16.php? Multichannel News January 28, 2009 Ion To Launch HD Simulcast On Feb 16 - Initial Rollout Phase Will Reach 20 DMAs, 46 Million Households]&lt;/ref&gt; However, on February 19 they released a statement saying that to avoid confusion with the current [[Digital television|DTV]] transition, they will postpone [[HDTV]] plans until March 16.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.engadgethd.com/2009/02/19/ion-scared-off-by-the-dtv-transition-postpones-debut-another-mo/ Engadget HD February 19, 2009 ION scared off by the DTV transition, postpones debut another month]&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, stations began to switch in late February from [[480i]] to [[720p]], with most programming [[pillarbox]]ed by [[navy blue|very dark blue]] bars instead of black ones.

Not all of ION's owned-and-operated stations currently operate the HD feed.

==Multiplexing==
Ion affiliates have made notable use of &quot;[[multiplexing]]&quot;, or splitting a digital TV channel into separate digital sub-channels. On these sub-channels, the stations/network broadcasts three (formerly four) digital channels.

===Qubo on Ion Television===
{{Main|Qubo}}
On May 8, 2006, Ion Media Networks, NBC Universal, [[Corus Entertainment|Corus Entertainment's]] [[Nelvana]] unit, [[Scholastic Books]], [[Classic Media]] and its [[Big Idea Productions]] unit announced plans to launch Qubo, a new children's entertainment endeavor spread across all medium platforms, including [[video-on-demand]] on [[digital cable]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ionmedia4&quot;&gt;[http://www.ionmedia.tv/press/press.cfm?id=4 Press&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The new project features new and library programming from the partners, each one producing a new series a year.

The primary goal for Qubo is to &quot;champion literacy and values in the children's television category&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ionmedia4&quot;/&gt; Qubo made its debut on NBC and [[Telemundo]] on September 9, 2006, with NBC's Qubo block repeating on Ion Television on Fridays at 3:00 pm.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionmedia.tv/press/press.cfm?id=14 Press&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A 24-hour digital television network began January 8, 2007;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.qubo.com/qubo247.asp How To Get qubo Channel&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; programming on the Qubo channel features a daily repeating 4-hour block of shows, all featuring programming exclusive to the new channel. As a consequence to this, the ''i'' secondary feed was replaced on ''i'' O&amp;Os with a repeating promo loop in late September 2006.

===Ion Life===
{{Main|ION Life}}
The network launched on February 19, 2007 as [[ION Life]].

===The Worship Network===
{{Main|The Worship Network}}

The Worship Network was originally founded in 1992 to &quot;create an atmosphere in the home to inspire and encourage a quiet time to worship God.&quot; When PAX launched in 1998, The Worship Network provided overnight programming. In 2005, PAX and The Worship Network struck a deal in which the network would be carried on a digital subchannel of PAX 24 hours a day.

Until January 31, 2010 the Worship Network was carried on digital subchannels of Ion [[O&amp;O]]s and in some cases, was used as an alternative to the main Ion network feed. It is also seen around the world through its 250 broadcast affiliates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worship.net/history.html Worship.net]&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 31, 2010 Ion dropped the Worship Network from their stations' lineups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worship.net/article/january-2010-newsletter Worship.net]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Subchannel ordering====
Though each channel map may vary by market, usually the ION affiliate is carried on channel -1, with Qubo on -2 and ION Life on -3.

==Differences between Ion and other broadcast networks==
Ion Television, unlike other broadcast networks, does not necessarily allow its owned and operated stations to air [[Broadcast syndication|syndicated programming]] during the daytime and late night hours. In the United States, syndicated programming accounts for a majority of local network affiliate and independent stations revenue.

Network programming (on stations that have a network affiliation) and infomercials make up the rest. Since paid programming makes up most of Ion's schedule, the benefit is that it provides the main source of revenue. However, this is also a drawback since Ion relies more on infomercials rather than sitcoms and dramas; sponsors of [[television series]] often have qualms about their message being lost on stations whose primary content is infomercials and other paid programming. During the 2005–2006 season, Ion (as ''i'') launched only one new series, ''[[Palmetto Pointe]]'', a teen drama series which only lasted six episodes, and in 2006–2007, the network went entirely to a lineup of reruns (except for Health Report and Ion Life specials). However, beginning in July 2007, this changed, as ION inked a deal with [[RHI Entertainment]], who is producing new series for Ion.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

As a result, there are a small number of stations (such as [[WKFK-LP]]) that have taken dual affiliation with both Ion and another smaller network, usually either [[America One]] or [[MyNetworkTV]].

The fact that Ion airs more infomercials than they do series programming is the main reason why some satellite operators dropped Ion affiliates from their channel lineups.&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVE&quot;&gt;[http://www.directv.com/see/landing/pax.html DirecTV.com: PAX]&lt;/ref&gt;

In some markets, [[DirecTV]] carries a &quot;place holder&quot; simulcast of the national modified feed (for example, [[Los Angeles]] area viewers watch Ion on both channels 30, [[KPXN-TV|KPXN]], and 305).

==Network troubles==
In 2003, the predecessor Pax network scaled back its operations. It was originally offering five or six new series each season. That year the number of new series airing on Pax dwindled to just two: ''[[Sue Thomas: F.B.Eye]]'', which was pulled in 2005, and ''[[Doc (TV series)|Doc]]'', which were pulled in 2004 because Pax's international backer, [[CTV Television Network|CTV]], pulled out of producing the shows. The organization seemingly recovered a year later when seven TV series made it to Pax's 2004-05 schedule.

In the Spring of 2005, it was reported that PAX intended to break its contract with [[NBC Universal]], which eliminated most of their entertainment programming, and rely on [[infomercial]]s, talk shows, and other paid programming to help increase cash flow. However, the network issued a press release on May 25, 2005, in which Paxson Communications chairman [[Bud Paxson|Lowell &quot;Bud&quot; Paxson]] was quoted{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} as saying:

{{cquote|There have been several reports in the press that the Company is dropping or reducing entertainment programming. Those reports are totally incorrect. The Company will continue to offer the same or an increased amount of entertainment programming than it has in the past.}}

In November 2005, NBC Universal was granted a transferrable option to purchase a controlling stake in Paxson Communications.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} If this option is exercised, NBC would acquire approximately 63 ''i'' affiliates. As part of the agreement, Lowell Paxson left the network (and its parent company).

According to a statement on its website,&lt;ref name=&quot;DAVE&quot;/&gt; [[DirecTV]] planned to terminate its agreement with the ''i'' network in February 2006 and would drop ''i'' as well as its local channels from the DBS service. DirecTV cited that &quot;most of [''i'' Network's] programming consists of infomercials and other promotional shows&quot;, despite an earlier promise by network executives that the network &quot;would consist of general, family-oriented entertainment&quot;. To appease DirecTV officials, the network decided to junk some infomercials and shopping shows and replace them with old public domain programming and cancelled PAX originals (''see [[#Ion Plus|below]]''). The channels were expected to be removed from the service by February 28, 2006. However, in May 2006, it was announced that DirecTV and Ion Media had come to a new carriage agreement.

In early 2006, it was announced that the ''i'' affiliates in [[Memphis, Tennessee]] ([[WPXX-TV]]), [[Rapid City, South Dakota]] ([[KKRA-LP]]) and [[Greenville, North Carolina]] ([[WEPX-TV]], as well as [[WPXU-TV]] in [[Jacksonville, North Carolina]]) would add programming from [[MyNetworkTV]] in September 2006, thus causing programming airing on ''i'' to be unavailable on these stations while MNTV is broadcasting. This blow came after losing some affiliates in New Mexico, New York, and Illinois completely (although the New York station, [[WWBI-LP]] in [[Plattsburgh (city), New York|Plattsburgh]], subsequently rejoined ''i'' after a sale that resulted in the affiliation change fell through). In April 2006, it was reported ''i'' owed more than US $250,000,000 to creditors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/CA6327128.html?display=John+Higgins&amp;referral=SUPP Burgess' Burden - 4/24/2006 - Broadcasting &amp; Cable&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Standard &amp; Poor's reported a much higher debt in March 2008, owing $867,000,000 to creditors and having a bond rating of CCC+/Outlook Negative.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/money/companies/2008-03-21-sp-weakest-links-list_N.htm Standard &amp; Poor's 'Weakest Links' list]. [[USA Today]]. 22 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, ''i'' struck several major content deals (''see details [[#Recent programming deals|above]]'') in hopes of assuring its long-term future.

Days after the network changed to Ion, a small California-based entertainment group named Positive Ions, Inc. sued ION Media Networks, claiming that the network stole the &quot;Ion&quot; branding.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadcastnewsroom.com/articles/viewarticle.jsp?id=100984 Positive Ions Continues Fight with ION Media Networks over ION(R) - BroadcastNewsroom&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Positive Ions has registered trademarks on the word &quot;Ion&quot; and has used the mark commercially since 1999. On May 14, 2007, Positive Ions filed for an injunction that, if granted, would require ION Media Networks to change its name once again.

In April 2009, it was announced that Ion was one again facing balance sheet problems. The company disclosed that it was in discussions with lenders on &quot;a comprehensive recapitalization&quot; of its balance sheet. That translates to an effort to restructure its considerable debt, which stands at $2.7 billion as of April 2009, according to ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]''.

On May 19, 2009, [[ION Media Networks]] filed for [[chapter 11 bankruptcy]] protection, putting the Ion network under bankruptcy for the second time, saying it had reached an agreement with holders of 60% of its first lien secured debt that would extinguish all of its $2.7 billion in legacy debt and preferred stock and recapitalize the company with a $150 million new funding commitment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.multichannel.com/article/233139-Ion_Files_For_Bankruptcy_Protection.php Ion Files for Bankruptcy Protection], ''MultiChannel News'', May 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 15, 2009, RHI entered into a settlement agreement to resolve a dispute with ION Media which, if approved by the Bankruptcy Court, will result in the termination of the programming agreement between RHI and ION.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxbusiness.com/story/markets/industries/media/rhi-entertainment-announces-results-second-quarter-ended-june RHI Entertainment Announces Results for the Second Quarter Ended June 30, 2009], ''FOXBusiness.com'', August 5, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

In late September 2009, a year after Ion purchased WPXX and WEPX/WPXU from Flinn Broadcasting, those stations returned to carrying Ion full-time as they used the out of MyNetworkTV cancelling all existing affiliation agreements in the wake of that network converting to a [[programming service]]. [[WITN-TV|WITN]] took over MyNetworkTV affiliation via a digital subchannel in Greenville/Washington/New Bern NC, with Memphis CW affiliate [[WLMT]] picking up only ''[[WWE SmackDown]]'' in place of WPXX.

===Major market absences===
Ion has no over-the-air stations in several major markets, most notably [[Baltimore, Maryland]]; [[San Diego, California]]; [[Charlotte, North Carolina]]; [[Cincinnati, Ohio]]; and [[St. Louis, Missouri]]. In [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]], a deal by Paxson to buy [[WPCB-TV]] and trade it for secondary PBS station WQEX was rejected by the [[Federal Communications Commission]] in a [[WINP-TV#Controversy|huge controversy]] in the late 1990s; it would not be until 2010 that Paxson's successor, ION, would successfully buy WQEX, which was since converted to a commercial license as [[WINP-TV]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/459634-Ion_to_Buy_WQEX.php Broadcasting &amp; Cable: &quot;Ion to Buy WQEX: &quot;Positively entertaining&quot; network grabs Pittsburgh outlet&quot;, November 8, 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt; St. Louis at one time received the network by way of a low-power repeater of [[WPXS]], a station in [[Mount Vernon, Illinois]]). In Charlotte, [[WAXN-TV]] carried some Pax programming from 1998 to 2000, but was never formally affiliated with the network. [[Buffalo, New York]] and [[Rochester, New York]], normally treated as separate markets, share Ion affiliate [[WPXJ-TV]], which is centrally located between the two cities and is licensed to [[Batavia, New York|Batavia]].

In addition, in several other markets, Ion's predecessor was sold to another television station group to affiliate with a different network or a Spanish service, and through either a lack of channel space or interest in the network. Ion has not reappeared in those markets. They include:
* [[Champaign, Illinois|Champaign]]-[[Springfield, Illinois]]: WPXU (now [[The CW Television Network|CW]] affiliate [[WBUI]])
* [[Green Bay, Wisconsin]]: WPXG (now CW affiliate [[WCWF]])
* [[Albuquerque, New Mexico]]: KAPX (now [[TeleFutura]] affiliate [[KTFQ-DT|KTFQ]])
* [[Fresno, California|Fresno]]-[[Visalia, California]]: KPXF (now TeleFutura affiliate [[KTFF-DT|KTFF]])
* [[Little Rock, Arkansas]]: KYPX (now independent station [[KMYA-DT|KMYA]])
* [[Reno, Nevada]]: [[KREN-TV|KREN]] (now CW affiliate)
* [[Baton Rouge, Louisiana]]: [[WLFT-CA]] (now independent religious)
* [[Charlottesville, Virginia]]: WADA-LP (now [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] affiliate [[WAHU-CA]])
* [[Lafayette, Louisiana]]: [[KDCG-LP]] (now [[Retro Television Network|RTN]] affiliate)
* [[Shreveport, Louisiana]]: [[KPXJ]] (now CW affiliate)
* [[Montgomery, Alabama]]: [[WBMM]] (first to [[Daystar Television Network]], now a CW affiliate)
* [[Sioux Falls, South Dakota]]: [[KAUN-LP]] (now [[Retro Television Network|RTN]] affiliate)
* [[Madison, Wisconsin]]: [[W43BR]] (now [[America One]] affiliate)

In several markets, the station's [[city of license]] is considered outside the main portion of a market's metropolitan area, like [[Minneapolis – Saint Paul]], where that area's affiliate station ([[KPXM-TV|KPXM]]) transmits from [[St. Cloud, Minnesota|St. Cloud]], 60 miles northwest; [[Detroit]], where affiliate [[WPXD-TV|WPXD]] is licensed to [[Ann Arbor, Michigan]], 40 miles west; [[Hartford, Connecticut|Hartford]], where affiliate [[WHPX-TV|WHPX]] is licensed to [[New London, Connecticut|New London]] 40 miles southeast; and [[Milwaukee]], where affiliate [[WPXE-TV|WPXE]] is licensed to [[Kenosha, Wisconsin|Kenosha]], with its analog transmitter south of Milwaukee in [[Racine County, Wisconsin|Racine County]] (although its digital transmitter is located at the traditional Milwaukee tower farm on the north side of the city). In [[Cleveland]], Ion airs on the former ABC affiliate in [[Akron, Ohio|Akron]] ([[WVPX-TV]]), which had formerly targeted an audience in Akron and [[Canton, Ohio|Canton]].

==Network slogans==
* ''Pax TV: A Friend of the Family'' (1998–1999)
* ''Pax TV: Share It With Someone You Love'' (1999–2000)
* ''Pax TV: Share The Wonder'' (2000–2001)
* ''Pax TV: Feel Good TV'' (2001–2002)
* ''I want my Pax TV'' (2002–2003; after the dispute with [[DirecTV]])
* ''Pax TV: Feel The Spirit'' (2003–2004)
* ''Pax TV: Oh what a night!'' (2004–2005)
* ''i: Independent Television'' (2005–2006)
* ''What's Your ION?'' (2006–2007) -- a play on the name, ion, which is pronounced like the words &quot;eye&quot; and &quot;on&quot;, and a play on the phrase &quot;What's your eye on?&quot;
* ''ION: Your Home for Popular TV Favorites'' (2007–2008)
* ''ION Television: Positively Entertaining'' (2008–present) -- a play on the name, [[ion]], which is an atom or molecule with a positive or negative electrical charge.

==See also==
* [[List of Ion Television affiliates]]
* [[List of programs broadcast by Ion Television]]
* [[List of stations owned and operated by ION Media Networks]]
* [[List of United States cable and satellite television networks]]
* [[List of United States over-the-air television networks]]
* [[Lists of corporate assets]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.iontelevision.com}}
* [http://www.qubo.com/ Qubo.com]
* [http://www.ionlife.tv/ IONlife.tv]
* [http://www.worship.net/ Worship.net]

{{Broadcast Television}}
{{Sports television in the United States}}
{{ION}}

[[Category:American television networks]]
[[Category:Ion Television]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1998]]
[[Category:English-language television stations in the United States]]

[[es:ION Television]]
[[id:Ion Television]]
[[pt:ION Television]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
