<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7827116" ns="0" title="Williams FW19"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Racing car |
  Car_name         = Williams FW19 |
  Image            =  |
  Category         = [[Formula One]] |
  Constructor      = [[WilliamsF1|Williams]] |
  Designer         = {{flagicon|UK}} [[Patrick Head]] (Technical Director)&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|UK}} [[Adrian Newey]] (Chief Designer) |
  Predecessor = [[Williams FW18|FW18]] |
  Successor = [[Williams FW20|FW20]] |
  Team             = [[WilliamsF1|Rothmans Williams Renault]] |
  Drivers          = 3. [[Jacques Villeneuve]]&lt;br&gt;4. [[Heinz-Harald Frentzen]] |
  Chassis          = [[carbon fiber|Carbon-fibre]] and honeycomb composite structure |
  Front suspension = [[WilliamsF1|Williams]] inboard torsion bar, double wishbone, operated by pushboard bellcrank |
  Rear suspension  = [[WilliamsF1|Williams]] inboard coil-spring/double wishbone, operated by pushboard bellcrank |
  Engine name      = [[Renault F1|Renault]] RS9, RS9A and RS9B |
  Capacity         = |
  Configuration    = [[V10 engine|V10]] (71°) |
  Turbo/NA         = [[naturally aspirated]] |
  Engine position  = |
  Gearbox name     = [[WilliamsF1|Williams]]/[[Komatsu Limited|Komatsu]] |
  Gears            = 6-speed|
  Type             = transverse semi-automatic |
  Differential     = |
  Fuel             = [[Elf Aquitaine|Elf]] |
  Tyres            = [[Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company|Goodyear]] |
  Debut            = [[1997 Australian Grand Prix]] |
  Races            = 17 |
  Wins             = 8 |
  Cons_champ       = 1 ({{f1|1997}}) |
  Drivers_champ    = 1 ({{f1|1997}}) |
  Poles            = 11 |
  Fastest_laps     = 9 |
}}
The '''Williams FW19''' was the car with which the [[WilliamsF1|Williams]] [[Formula One]] team used to compete in the [[1997 Formula One season]].  It was driven by [[Jacques Villeneuve]], who was in his second year with the team, and [[Heinz-Harald Frentzen]], who moved from [[Sauber]] to replace the dropped {{F1|1996}} champion, [[Damon Hill]]. Williams also employed test drivers [[Jean-Christophe Boullion]] and [[Juan Pablo Montoya]].

The car was a logical development of the extremely successful [[Williams FW18|FW18]], which had comfortably won both titles in {{F1|1996}}.  It was also the last Williams chassis to receive input from designer [[Adrian Newey]], who left the team to join [[McLaren (racing)|McLaren]] during the season, and the last to run a works [[Renault F1|Renault]] engine before the French marque's temporary withdrawal. It also benefited from design input from [[Patrick Head]]. However, {{F1|1997}} was more difficult for Williams, as they faced a tough, season-long challenge from [[Michael Schumacher]] and [[Scuderia Ferrari|Ferrari]].  After a controversial collision between Villeneuve and Schumacher in the [[1997 European Grand Prix|season finale]], the Canadian took the Drivers' Championship, with the team claiming the Constructors' Championship at the [[1997 Japanese Grand Prix|previous race]].  Frentzen, by contrast, had a disappointing year and could win only one race to Villeneuve's seven. However, he did finish second in the drivers' championship due to the disqualification of Michael Schumacher.

The team eventually scored 123 points to win the Constructors' Championship.

The car, as previously mentioned, was the last Williams to use the highly successful [[naturally aspirated]] Renault RS9 [[V10 engine]] along with the in-house Williams gearbox. The car used [[Elf Aquitaine|Elf]] fuel, [[Castrol]] oil, [[Penske Corporation|Penske]] shock absorbers and [[Automotive Products|AP Racing]] carbon [[disc brake]]s.

==1997 Season==

The car had the tough challenge of picking up the baton from [[1996 Formula One season|1996's]] [[Williams FW18|FW18]], which had walked away with both titles in the hands of [[Damon Hill]], now departed for [[Arrows]], and the retained Jacques Villeneuve.

The season began in the way 1996 left off for Williams, with Villeneuve taking pole and Frentzen joining him on the front row for the opening race in [[1997 Australian Grand Prix|Australia]]. Villeneuve was in trouble right from the start, however, and a bad start pulled him back into the field and he was taken out by [[Johnny Herbert]] in the [[Sauber]]. This left Frentzen in the lead, but he was jumped by [[David Coulthard]]'s [[McLaren]] in the second pitstops. He was still on for second place, however, but his brakes failed three laps from the end and it was a no score for Williams.

Villeneuve took pole again in [[1997 Brazilian Grand Prix|Brazil]], with Frentzen down in a disappointing 8th. Villeneuve held the lead for the entire race apart from three laps during the second round of pitstops and held on to take his and Williams' first win of the season. Frentzen, however, had a far more exciting race, dropping to 13th at the start, being passed by Hill, [[Ralf Schumacher]] in the [[Jordan Grand Prix|Jordan]], [[Rubens Barrichello]]'s [[Stewart Grand Prix|Stewart]], Coulthard and Herbert. He repassed Barrichello and Herbert in the early laps, but remained in 11th after the first stops. The second stops were better for him, and he passed Ralf Schumacher, Hill and Coulthard, emerging in 8th. He was passed late on by [[Giancarlo Fisichella]] in the Jordan and demoted to 9th, so once again scored no points. This result left Villeneuve equal top of the championship with Coulthard and Williams equal second with [[Benetton Formula|Benetton]] and behind McLaren.

An early [[safety car]] was triggered in [[1997 Argentine Grand Prix|Argentina]] due to the collision between Coulthard and [[Scuderia Ferrari|Ferrari's]] [[Michael Schumacher]]. This was good for the Williams team, who had started 1-2, with Villeneuve on pole for the third consecutive time. It didn't last very long for Frentzen, though, as his clutch broke after only five laps, meaning he had still scored no points for the season. Villeneuve was able to hold onto the lead for the vast majority of the race, with only five laps during the pitstops led by the Ferrari of [[Eddie Irvine]]. The Canadian's second win of the season left him and the team clear at the top of the championship table, despite Frentzen being yet to score.

The [[Grove, Oxfordshire|Grove]] based team locked out the front row yet again in [[1997 San Marino Grand Prix|San Marino]], and Villeneuve retained his 100% pole position record for 1997. Frentzen was jumped by Michael Schumacher at the start, and the Williams cars ran 1st and 3rd until the first round of pitstops, when Villeneuve was already suffering from gearbox problems. Frentzen jumped  his compatriot Schumacher and took the lead while Villeneuve dropped to 3rd with his problems. He finally retired on lap 41. Frentzen was under pressure from Schumacher to the very end, but held on to take his first ever F1 victory. Villeneuve held on to his championship lead, as did the team, and Frentzen moved up to equal third - he, [[Gerhard Berger]] of Benetton, [[Mika Häkkinen]] of McLaren, Irvine and Coulthard all had 10 points.

Frentzen took his first career pole at the [[1997 Monaco Grand Prix|Monaco Grand Prix]], but Villeneuve was back in third with Michael Schumacher splitting them. The Ferrari man jumped Frentzen at the very wet start and the Jordans of Fisichella and Ralf Schumacher also got through. Villeneuve had an awful start and was down to 9th, behind Coulthard, Herbert, Barrichello and [[Olivier Panis]]'s [[Prost Grand Prix|Prost]] as well. Frentzen had a spin and Villeneuve had technical problems, and they were soon running 16th and 17th. As the rain continued to fall, they picked up places due to the accidents of Herbert and [[Jarno Trulli]] in the [[Minardi]], Berger having to stop for a new front wing and actually passing [[Shinji Nakano]]'s Prost on the racetrack. This left them in 11th and 12th with Frentzen still leading his teammate, but on lap 17 Villeneuve pulled into the pits with a problem, later identified as accident damage after a brush with the barrier, and retired. Frentzen picked up a place on the same lap due to [[Jean Alesi]] spinning his Benetton out of the race. The German passed [[Ukyo Katayama]] in the other Minardi a lap later, and was in 9th. He was still in 9th on lap 40 when he ran wide at the seafront chicane and bounced across the kerbs, damaging his right front suspension. He the hit the wall on the other side of the track, which caused almost identical damage to the left front suspension. He was out of the race, and the Williams Monaco challenge was over. Michael Schumacher's victory left him top of the championship by four points from Villeneuve. Frentzen had been demoted to fourth due to Eddie Irvine's 3rd place, and Williams had been bumped down to 2nd by the Ferrari performance.

The Williams cars were back on the front row in [[1997 Spanish Grand Prix|Spain]], with Villeneuve on pole again. Villeneuve held position at the start despite intense pressure from Coulthard and Michael Schumacher. Frentzen, however, dropped down to 6th as the McLaren and the Ferrari swept passed him along with Alesi and Häkkinen. Frentzen had run as high as third, but by the time the second pitstops were over he was down to 8th - Herbert and Panis had got passed him as well. At the end Villeneuve was able to hold onto the lead only because Olivier Panis, an unlikely challenger, was caught in the traffic of Eddie Irvine and [[Jos Verstappen]]'s [[Tyrrell Racing|Tyrrell]]. Frentzen was not much help to the Canadian, only moving up to 8th with a last lap move on Fisichella. This result allowed Villeneuve to move back to the lead of the championship, but meanwhile Frentzen was slipping, from 4th to 6th as Panis and Coulthard overtook him.

{{-}}

==Complete Formula One results==
([[:Template:F1 driver results legend 2|key]]) (results in '''bold''' indicate pole position; results in ''italics'' indicate fastest lap) 
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; font-size:95%&quot;
! Year
! Team
! Engine
! Tyres
! Drivers
! 1
! 2
! 3
! 4
! 5
! 6
! 7
! 8
! 9
! 10
! 11
! 12
! 13
! 14
! 15
! 16
! 17
! Points
! WCC
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| {{F1|1997}}
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| [[WilliamsF1|Williams]]
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| [[Renault F1|Renault]] [[V10 engine|V10]]
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| {{Goodyear}}
||
|| [[1997 Australian Grand Prix|AUS]]
|| [[1997 Brazilian Grand Prix|BRA]]
|| [[1997 Argentine Grand Prix|ARG]]
|| [[1997 San Marino Grand Prix|SMR]]
|| [[1997 Monaco Grand Prix|MON]]
|| [[1997 Spanish Grand Prix|ESP]]
|| [[1997 Canadian Grand Prix|CAN]]
|| [[1997 French Grand Prix|FRA]]
|| [[1997 British Grand Prix|GBR]]
|| [[1997 German Grand Prix|GER]]
|| [[1997 Hungarian Grand Prix|HUN]]
|| [[1997 Belgian Grand Prix|BEL]]
|| [[1997 Italian Grand Prix|ITA]]
|| [[1997 Austrian Grand Prix|AUT]]
|| [[1997 Luxembourg Grand Prix|LUX]]
|| [[1997 Japanese Grand Prix|JPN]] 
|| [[1997 European Grand Prix|EUR]]
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|'''123'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|'''1st'''
|-
| [[Jacques Villeneuve]]
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| '''Ret'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| '''''1'''''
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| '''1'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| '''Ret'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| Ret
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| '''1'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| Ret
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFFFDF&quot;| 4
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| '''1'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| Ret
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| 1
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFFFDF&quot;| '''''5'''''
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFFFDF&quot;| 5
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| '''''1'''''
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| 1
|bgcolor=&quot;#000000&quot; style=&quot;color:white&quot;| '''DSQ'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFDF9F&quot;| '''3'''
|-
| [[Heinz-Harald Frentzen]]
|bgcolor=&quot;#CFCFFF&quot;| ''8''
|bgcolor=&quot;#CFCFFF&quot;| 9
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| Ret
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFBF&quot;| ''1''
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| '''Ret'''
|bgcolor=&quot;#CFCFFF&quot;| 8
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFFFDF&quot;| 4
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFDFDF&quot;| 2
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| Ret
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| Ret
|bgcolor=&quot;#EFCFFF&quot;| ''Ret''
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFDF9F&quot;| 3
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFDF9F&quot;| 3
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFDF9F&quot;| 3
|bgcolor=&quot;#FFDF9F&quot;| ''3''
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFDFDF&quot;| ''2''
|bgcolor=&quot;#DFFFDF&quot;| ''6''
|}

==References==
*''[[AUTOCOURSE]] 1997-98'', [[Alan Henry|Henry, Alan]] (ed.), Hazleton Publishing Ltd. (1997) ISBN 1-874557-47-0

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach|aw}}
{{succession box | before = [[Williams FW18]] | title = [[Autosport]]&lt;br /&gt;Racing Car Of The Year | after = [[McLaren MP4/13]]| years = 1997}}
{{s-end}}

{{Williams}}
{{F1 cars 1997}}

[[Category:Williams Formula One cars]]
[[Category:1997 Formula One season cars]]

[[es:Williams FW19]]
[[fr:Williams FW19]]
[[it:Williams FW19]]
[[ja:ウィリアムズ・FW19]]
[[pl:Williams FW19]]
[[pt:Williams FW19]]
[[ru:Williams FW19]]
[[sl:Williams FW19]]
[[fi:Williams FW19]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
