<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Characters of Final Fantasy Tactics Advance" to="Final Fantasy Tactics Advance" tofragment="Characters" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="430549" ns="0" title="Final Fantasy Tactics Advance"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox VG
| title = Final Fantasy Tactics Advance
| image = [[File:FinalFantasyTacticsAdvanceGBACoverArtUS.jpg|North American box art]]
| developer = [[Square Enix#Production teams|Square Product Development Division 4]]&lt;ref name=&quot;developer&quot; /&gt;
| publisher = {{vgrelease|JP=[[Square (company)|Square]]|NA=[[Nintendo]]|EU=Nintendo}}
| director = Yuichi Murasawa
| producer = [[Yasumi Matsuno]]
| artist = [[Ryoma Itō]]&lt;br/&gt;Hideo Minaba&lt;br/&gt;[[Hiroshi Minagawa]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Akihiko Yoshida]]
| writer = Kyoko Kitahara&lt;br/&gt;Jun Akiyama
| composer = [[Hitoshi Sakimoto]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Nobuo Uematsu]]
| engine = 
| released = {{vgrelease|JP=February 14, 2003|NA=September 8, 2003|PAL=October 24, 2003}}
| genre = [[Tactical role-playing game]]
| modes = [[Single-player]], [[Multiplayer game|multiplayer]]
| ratings = {{vgratings|ESRB=Everyone|PEGI=3+|USK=6+|OFLCA=G8+}}
| platforms = [[Game Boy Advance]]
| media = 128 [[megabit]] [[cartridge (electronics)|cartridge]]
| requirements =
| input =
| series = ''[[Final Fantasy]]''
}}
{{nihongo|'''''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'''''|ファイナルファンタジータクティクスアドバンス}} is a [[tactical role-playing game]] developed and published by [[Square Co.|Square]] (now [[Square Enix]]) for the [[Nintendo]] [[Game Boy Advance]]. A spin-off of the popular ''[[Final Fantasy]]'' series, the game shares several traits with 1997's ''[[Final Fantasy Tactics]]'', although it is not a direct sequel. The player assembles a clan of characters, and controls their actions over grid-like battlefields. Players are mostly free to decide the classes, abilities, and statistics of their characters.

The game's story centers on four children; Marche, Mewt, Ritz, and Doned, who live in a small town named St. Ivalice. The children are transported to a realm of the same name as their town, &quot;[[Ivalice]]&quot;, after discovering an ancient magical book. The story then focuses on the exploits of Marche as he attempts to return to the real world while facing opposition from those around him.

''Tactics Advance'' is one of the initial products from the cooperation of Square and [[Nintendo]] made for the [[Game Boy Advance]] console; it was developed by the team brought over from the game company [[Quest Corporation]]. Following its release, ''Tactics Advance''-themed merchandise was introduced. The game was positively received. It has a sequel, ''[[Final Fantasy Tactics A2: Grimoire of the Rift]]'' for the [[Nintendo DS]].

==Gameplay==
[[Image:FinalFantasyTacticsAdvanceGBAScreenshot.png|left|thumb|A screenshot of an early battle in ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance''.]]
In ''Tactics Advance'', [[turn-based tactics|turn-based tactical]] battles take place on a three-dimensional isometric field. The player takes the role of Marche, a clan leader; he must organize the clan's members and advance their status through missions that are offered in pubs.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Harris, Craig|url=http://gameboy.ign.com/articles/436/436979p1.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|date=2003-09-05|work=IGN.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The player competes against the computer's team in turn-based play, although unlike ''Final Fantasy Tactics'' characters execute their actions instantly.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Kasavin, Greg|url=http://www.gamespot.com/gba/strategy/finalfantasytacticsadvance/review.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|date=2003-09-08|work=GameSpot.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Missions are tasks undertaken by a clan. There are four types of missions: regular, encounter, dispatch, and area. In regular missions, Marche's entire party ventures to a particular location to do battle. Many of these missions are used to advance the story.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rpgf&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Bogdanowicz, Robert|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/reviews/finalfantasytacticsa/index2.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|date=2003-10-02|work=RPGFan.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In encounter missions, Marche's group battles a rival mercenary clan by purchasing a mission or meeting them on the map. In dispatch missions, which do not involve battle, Marche temporarily sends away one member from his party. Area missions are usually a dispatch mission where Marche's clan can liberate certain regions to obtain bonuses and discounts at shops.

Some missions, typically dispatch missions, require a special item to be in possession in order to accept the mission. Others require a dispatch character to have a specific job class. In regards to items, this may mean another mission must be done to get an item that would allow you to perform the later mission.

The world map is initially empty except for the starting location; it is customized as the player wins location &quot;tokens&quot; after certain missions. These tokens represent different terrains and settlements, such as plains, mountains, deserts, forests, and towns, that can be placed in slots on the world map. Items are rewarded to the player depending on the placement of the tokens.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot;/&gt; Ivalice also introduces areas called jagds, lawless slums that Judges avoid. Jagd is a German word which means ''the hunt''. Jagds are the only places in the game in which a character can die; everywhere else, they are protected from death by the Judges and are simply knocked out.

''Tactics Advance'' also offers multiplayer capability for two players. Players may cooperate or compete using a link-cable peripheral, and also trade items and party members. Additional missions and items are also offered when players link.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign&quot;/&gt;

===Job system===
{{seealso|Final Fantasy character classes}}
There are 34 &quot;jobs&quot; in ''Tactics Advance'' that govern a character's stats, equipment, and abilities. Most items that can be equipped have various abilities assigned to them, each available for use by characters of a certain job while the item is equipped. When a battle is completed, characters will receive Ability Points (AP) distributed over their currently equipped weapons or items (such as armor). Once a target amount of AP has been accumulated for a given ability, the character will master that ability, allowing the character to use them at any time, regardless of items equipped and job chosen. Mastery of abilities in different jobs will eventually allow the character access to more jobs. For example, if a human unit wishes to change jobs to Paladin, it needs to master at least two &quot;action&quot; abilities from the &quot;soldier&quot; job.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideJobs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://guides.ign.com/guides/480116/page_3.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Guide|pages=3|last=Dunham|first=Alexis|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Units have a primary job which determines the stat boosts they receive when they [[experience point#Level-based progression|level up]] and the attributes associated with that class. A unit may also have a secondary job set of abilities, where it can use any abilities of the selected job, but with the stat profile of the primary job. For example, an Assassin with a Sniper secondary job could use abilities from both jobs, but has the stat profile and appearance of an Assassin, its primary job. This may deny the use of some abilities depending on their equipped weapon. In the previous example, any abilities that require the possession of a great bow, will not be allowed for use if the character has a Katana equipped.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideJobs&quot;/&gt;

''Tactics Advance'' also introduces five playable races: Humans, the small rodentlike [[Moogle]]s, the strong lizard-like Bangaa, the agile rabbit-like Viera, and the magically-skilled Nu Mou. Certain jobs are only available to certain races. Along with the abilities obtained with experience, each race has a guardian beast called a &quot;Totema&quot; to represent whom and which can be summoned to whose aid when a member of that race has 10 Judge Points, that is after your clan has defeated that Totema as part of the main story line.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideRaces&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://guides.ign.com/guides/480116/page_2.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Guide|pages=2|last=Dunham|first=Alexis|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Laws===
One feature of ''Tactics Advance'' is the Laws system. Laws are set by Judges, invincible [[arbitration|arbiter]]s present at each battle, with some exceptions.  Laws may forbid the use of certain weapons, items, elemental spells, or status changes. Breaking a law results in punishment by Carding, the receipt of a [[misconduct (football)|red or yellow card]]. Imprisonment happens if a character infringes a law twice or knocks out another unit with a forbidden ability or weapon. However, Jagds have no Judges or laws; units knocked out in the Jagds will die and permanently leave the clan if they are not revived by the end of the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideWalkthrough&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://guides.ign.com/guides/480116/page_6.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Guide|pages=6–10|last=Dunham|first=Alexis|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To offset the difficulty of having things forbidden for use, there are certain things that are recommended by the Judges, and therefore grant Judge Points if used. Judge Points (JP) are used to carry out [[Combo (video gaming)|combo]]s with nearby allies or to summon a Totema. JP are also received upon knocking out an opponent. Later in the game, the player gains the ability to use law cards, which can add laws, and anti-law cards, which can nullify laws that are already in effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideWalkthrough&quot;/&gt;

==Plot==
===Characters===
The story of ''Tactics Advance'' revolves around three primary characters: Marche Radiuju, the main character who battles the dream worlds of his friends; Ritz Malheur, a stubborn girl who speaks her mind and changes sides in her struggle for self-acceptance; and Mewt Randell, a boy whose mother died that discovers a magical entity that changes the world into the world of Ivalice. There are also secondary characters, such as Doned Radiuju, Marche's little brother who does not desire to return to the real world, since he is sick in the real world and healthy in the dream one; and Cid Randell, Mewt's father who becomes the Judgemaster of Ivalice.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideRaces&quot;/&gt;

Within Ivalice, there are other characters that help advance the plot. Some characters befriended Marche, such as the moogles Montblanc and Nono; Ezel Berbier, a Nu Mou troublemaker and self-proclaimed genius; and Shara, a Viera archer who befriends Ritz. There are other characters who antagonize Marche, including Babus Swain, a Nu Mou Royal mage in Mewt's service; Llednar Twem, a mysterious enforcer who replaces the Judges when they become independent of the Palace; and Queen Remedi, who is the ruler of Ivalice and was in the Gran Grimoire itself in a form modeled after Mewt's deceased mother.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNGuideRaces&quot;/&gt;

===Story===
{{seealso|Ivalice}}
Ivalice is a world created by four ordinary children: Marche Radiuju, a new student and resident of St. Ivalice and its school; Mewt Randell, a shy boy still attached to the memory of his late mother; Ritz Malheur, a loud and outspoken classmate of Marche and Mewt; and Doned Radiuju, Marche's younger, handicapped brother and a big fan of fantasy novels and video games.  Mewt comes across a dusty old tome in a local used bookstore and eagerly wishes to show it to his friends. Unaware that the book is the legendary Gran Grimoire, Mewt brings the book over to Marche's house along with Ritz. The old book is written in a language none of them have ever seen before, and a single inscription reads: &quot;Alta oron, Sondus kameela&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;'''Marche''': I can't read these letters at all! Maybe they're some kind of magic spell! / [...] / '''Mewt''': .....Alta oron. Sondus kameela...It sure sounds like magic! {{cite video game|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|developer=[[Square (company)|Square]]|publisher=Square Co. |date=2003-09-08|platform=Game Boy Advance}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next morning, Marche wakes up in the world of Ivalice. The fantasy Ivalice is supposedly a reincarnation of Mewt's memories from a ''Final Fantasy'' game.&lt;ref&gt;'''Marche''': Well, it's just...I've seen a bangaa, but in a computer game, not real
life! / '''Moogle''': Kupo? / '''Marche''': It's called &quot;Final Fantasy.&quot; It's not real. Not really. It's like a pretend world, with heroes and monsters... / '''Moogle''': So you're saying here is just like your pretend world? / '''Marche''': Yeah, come to think of it, it's just like in the game! {{cite video game|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|developer=[[Square (company)|Square]]|publisher=Square Co.|date=2003-09-08|platform=Game Boy Advance}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marche is separated from the others, and immediately begins a quest to return home.  Even after realizing how much better his life is in the new Ivalice, he believes that none of it is real and is even more determined to return to his home.&lt;ref&gt;'''Marche''': What? You mean you'd rather stay here? / '''Ritz''': Yeah. I like this world. Don't you, Marche? / '''Marche''': Well, I... / '''Ritz''': If you want to turn everything back to normal... Go ahead. But don't expect me to help you. {{cite video game|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance |developer=[[Square (company)|Square]] |publisher=Square Co. |date=2003-09-08 |platform=Game Boy Advance }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The other children, and Mewt's father Cid, slowly realize through Marche's efforts that the world has been shaped according to their wishes. Mewt is no longer being teased, is reunited with his deceased mother, and is now the Prince of Ivalice; Ritz no longer has her white [[albinism|albinic]] hair, instead having the silky red hair which she always wanted; Doned can now walk and is no longer sickly; Marche is suddenly athletic and powerful; Cid is the highest-ranking official in the nation; and all of them now live in ''[[Final Fantasy]]'', the video game the children all love.&lt;ref&gt;'''Marche''': Mewt? Prince Mewt? &quot;My world&quot;? This world must be a reflection of Mewt's desires! His mom's still alive, everyone does what he says..... I'm living in Mewt's dream! So if I change the world back to the way it was... I'm destroying his dream world! No wonder he doesn't want me here... {{cite video game|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance |developer=[[Square (company)|Square]] |publisher=Square Co. |date=2003-09-08 |platform=Game Boy Advance }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually Marche succeeds in his quest to return Ivalice to normal.  He achieves this by destroying the crystals, or world threads, of Ivalice and defeating the Li-Grim.&lt;ref&gt;'''Marche''': I came to destroy that crystal... or World-Thread or whatever you call it. And I'm not leaving until I do! {{cite video game|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|developer=[[Square (company)|Square]]|publisher=Square Co. |date=2003-09-08|platform=Game Boy Advance }}&lt;/ref&gt;  He teaches the other children in the process that they cannot live in fantasy but must learn to live with their misfortunes in reality.  The other children are wiser from the experience, as the ending reveals them all to have become happy with themselves.

In addition to the main plot, there are two side plots: the Redwing Arc and the Judge Arc. The Redwing Arc centers around the Redwings clan, a foreign crime ring, their subordinate clan Borzoi, and their smuggled foreign monsters. The other is the Judge Arc, unlockable after beating the main three hundred missions. This serves as an alternative ending where Marche stays in Ivalice, overthrows corrupt judges, and becomes next in line for Cid's judge sword.&lt;ref&gt;'''Marche''': It's over. / '''Cid''': Thank you, Marche. You went above and beyond the call of duty. '''Marche''': Not at all! I was glad I was able to help. / '''Cid''': You know... / '''Marche''': What?  / '''Cid''': I would give you my judge sword. {{cite video game|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|developer=[[Square (company)|Square]]|publisher=Square Co.|date=2003-09-08|platform=Game Boy Advance}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
Rumors of the game's development began when Square announced its publishing agreement with Nintendo, and it was later confirmed by the producer Matsuno. The development team of ''Tactics Advance'', Square's Product Development Division 4, was constructed from employees of [[Quest Corporation]], and work began in February 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;developer&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.square-enix.com/jp/company/j/news/2003/download/0302-200311180000-01.pdf |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060506042003/http://www.square-enix.com/jp/company/j/news/2003/download/0302-200311180000-01.pdf |archivedate=2006-05-06 |title=「ファイナルファンタジータクティクス アドバンス」世界市場で出荷150万本突破！ |date=2003-11-18 |language=[[Japanese language|Japanese]] |publisher=[[Square Enix Co., Ltd.]] |accessdate=2011-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Harris, Craig|url=http://gameboy.ign.com/articles/356/356282p1.html|title=Famitsu Confirms Final Fantasy Tactics GBA|date=2002-03-27|work=IGN.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; This comes after Quest announced the handover of its software development team to Square, of which the former is famed for its [[Tactics Ogre: Let Us Cling Together|Tactics Ogre]] series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Gamespot staff|url=http://www.gamespot.com/gba/strategy/finalfantasytacticsadvance/news.html?sid=2871391|title=Square acquires Quest's software development division|date=2002-06-19|work=GameSpot.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially thought of as a port of ''Final Fantasy Tactics'', ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' is developed with an entirely new storyline and setting, and received significant changes to make it more user-friendly for the GBA handheld console; e.g. a quick-save function.

''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' uses the gameplay of ''Final Fantasy Tactics'', but introduced certain changes such as a customizable map for the world of Ivalice. While built for the Game Boy Advance, ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'''s graphics are vibrantly colored and extensively detailed, and though environments and characters are wholly sprite-based, facial expressions are easily identifiable and many motion frames have been given to create a smooth animation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Torres, Ricardo|url=http://www.gamespot.com/gba/strategy/finalfantasytacticsadvance/news.html?sid=2881079|title=TGS 2002: Hands-onFinal Fantasy Tactics Advance|date=2002-09-20|work=GameSpot.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Harris, Craig|url=http://gameboy.ign.com/articles/435/435441p1.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|date=2003-08-26|work=IGN.com |accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The game also introduced an option to switch between three display modes. Two of the modes are optimized for gameplay on Game Boy Advance and the new Game Boy Advance SP respectively, and there's also a TV mode for better color display while playing this game into a television screen by using a Game Boy Player which, must be attached to a Game Cube for this to work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Winkler, Chris|url = http://www.rpgfan.com/news/2003/1052.html|title=New Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Details Announced|date=2003-01-19|work=RPGFan.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Japan, ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'''s story was expanded and broadcast in Japanese radio stations. The radio drama entitled ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' Radio Edition was broadcast in four radio stations within Japan from early January 2003 to late March 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Winkler, Chris|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/news/2002/2280.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Goes Radio|date=2003-12-20|work=RPGFan.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==
{{main|Music of the Final Fantasy Tactics series}}
The music in ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' was primarily composed by [[Hitoshi Sakimoto]], with additional music contributed by Kaori Ohkoshi and Ayako Saso; [[Nobuo Uematsu]] provided the main theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamespot.com/gba/strategy/finalfantasytacticsadvance/tech_info.html?tag=tabs;summary|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Tech Info|publisher=[[GameSpot]]|accessdate=2009-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Original Soundtrack'' album was released by [[DigiCube]] on February 19, 2003. It spans 74 tracks and covers a duration of 2:05:27. The first disk includes every song from the game, as it sounds through the [[Game Boy Advance]] hardware. The second disk contains fully orchestrated versions of 32 of the same 42 tracks.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFOST&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Vardaro, Richard|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance OST|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ffta-ost/index.html|publisher=RPGFan|accessdate=2008-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[New age music|new age]] [[arrangement]] album entitled ''White: Melodies of Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'', a selection of musical tracks from the game arranged by Yo Yamazaki, Akira Sasaki, and Satoshi Henmi, was released by [[SME Visual Works]] on February 26, 2003. ''White'' spans 11 tracks and covers a duration of 46:10.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFWHITE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Gann, Patrick|title=White: Melodies of Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ffta-white/index.html|publisher=RPGFan|accessdate=2008-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the game, the classical-themed soundtrack is compressed into [[MIDI]] file format. Simple sound effects are used during battles, and there are no voices or speech within the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;rpgf&quot;/&gt;

==Reception==
{{VG Reviews
|GR = 87.64%&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gamerankings.com/gba/560436-final-fantasy-tactics-advance/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|MC = 87 of 100&lt;ref&gt;http://www.metacritic.com/game/game-boy-advance/final-fantasy-tactics-advance&lt;/ref&gt;
|EGM = 9 of 10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Bettenhausen, Shane; Hsu, Dan; Mielke, James|year=2003|month=October|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|journal=Electronic Gaming Monthly|issue=171|page=166|issn=1058-918X}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Edge = 7 of 10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Edge Staff|year=2003|month=December|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|journal=Edge Magazine|issue=130|page=105|issn=1350-1593}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Fam = 33 of 40&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rpgamer.com/news/japan/aw020503.html|title=RPGamer &amp;gt; Japandemonium - Second Season|publisher=Rpgamer.com|date=|accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|GSpot = 8.2 of 10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamespot.com/gba/strategy/finalfantasytacticsadvance/index.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance for Game Boy Advance - Final Fantasy Tactics Advance GBA - Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Game Boy Advance Game|publisher=Nintendo|date=DS|accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|IGN = 9.0 of 10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gameboy.ign.com/articles/436/436979p1.html|title=IGN: Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|publisher=Gameboy.ign.com|author=Craig Harris|date=|accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|rev1 = RPGFan
|rev1Score = 8.1 of 10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/reviews/finalfantasytacticsa/index2.html|title=RPGFan Reviews - Final Fantasy Tactics Advance|publisher=RPGFan|date=|accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|rev2 = ''[[GameNOW]]''
|rev2Score = 10 of 10&lt;ref name=gamenow&gt;{{cite web | archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20040504110923/www.gamenowmag.com/article2/0,2053,1489836,00.asp | url=http://www.gamenowmag.com/article2/0,2053,1489836,00.asp | archivedate=May 4, 2004 | title=It don't get much more real. | last=Lopez | first=Miguel | date=October 1, 2003 | work=[[GameNOW]] | accessdate=April 12, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|NWR = 7.5 of 10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamerankings.com/gba/560436-final-fantasy-tactics-advance/index.html|title=Game Rankings - External Link|publisher=Gamerankings.com|date=|accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Xplay = 4 of 5&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.g4tv.com/xplay/reviews/554/Final_Fantasy_Tactics_Advance.html|title=G4 - X-Play - Reviews|publisher=G4tv.com|date=|accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|compilation = no
}}

''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' sold over 440,000 copies during its year of release in Japan, with nearly 225,000 units being sold in its first week alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2003 Top 100 Best Selling Japanese Console Games|url=http://the-magicbox.com/Chart-BestSell2003b.shtml|work=The-MagicBox.com|accessdate=2008-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Wollenschlaeger, Alex|date=February 20, 2003|title=Japandemonium - Off the Hook|url=http://www.rpgamer.com/news/japan/aw022003.html|work=RPGamer.com|accessdate=2008-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; By August 6, 2004, more than 1 million units of the game were sold in North America and Europe together.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=August 6, 2004| title=Annual Report 2004|url=http://www.square-enix.com/eng/pdf/ar/20040806_01.pdf#page10|work=Square-Enix.com|accessdate=2008-12-20}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The game was well received among the gaming community, widely regarded to feature an outstanding combination of music, graphics, gameplay, and storyline. ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' won Best Handheld Game at the [[Interactive Achievement Awards|7th Annual Interactive Achievement Awards]] in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AIAS Annual Awards|url=http://www.interactive.org/awards/2004_7th_awards.asp|work=Academy of Interactive Arts &amp; Sciences|accessdate=2008-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also rated as outstanding by [[IGN]] (9.0 out of 10) and given 5 out of 5 by [[GameSpy]]. In 2007, ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' was named 14th best Game Boy Advance game of all time in IGN's feature reflecting on the Game Boy Advance's long lifespan.&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Craig Harris|date=2007-03-16|url=http://gameboy.ign.com/articles/772/772284p3.html|title=Top 25 Game Boy Advance Games of All Time|publisher=IGN.com|accessdate=2007-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also rated the 67th best game made on a Nintendo System in ''[[Nintendo Power]]'''s Top 200 Games list.&lt;ref name=&quot;NP Top 200&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|year=February 2006|title=NP Top 200|periodical=Nintendo Power|volume=200|pages=58–66|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reviewers were pleased with graphics and visuals of ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance''; GameSpot adding that the battles are &quot;clear and colorful&quot;, and character jobs are easily identified, though gameplay becomes slow when too many character sprites are in one screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot;/&gt; The gameplay is also lauded for retaining the elements of ''Tactics Ogre'' yet offers freedom to players to develop characters as they wish.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot; /&gt; ''[[GameNOW]]'' said that the game &quot;lives up to its legacy—and then some&quot;, and called it &quot;easily one of the best GBA games around&quot;.&lt;ref name=gamenow /&gt; Criticism was thrown to the game's menu, which was cluttered with complicated options in organizing the clan members, and did not detail out statistics for characters and equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;rpgf&quot;/&gt; Some reviewers thought there are too many character jobs since some jobs overlap one another and certain abilities are redundant.&lt;ref name=&quot;nwr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Metts, Jonathan|url=http://www.nintendoworldreport.com/reviewArt.cfm?artid=4138&amp;CFID=30555671&amp;CFTOKEN=7047d980c0012122-F60FF80E-C09F-3E62-05010BE4A523E195|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Review|date=2003-10-13|work=Nintendoworldreport.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
In 2007, a sequel to ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' was released for the [[Nintendo DS]] as part of the [[Ivalice Alliance]] series, ''[[Final Fantasy Tactics A2: Grimoire of the Rift]]''. While the story focuses on different characters than ''Advance'', several characters from the game appear in cameo roles, such as Montblanc and Mewt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://guides.ign.com/guides/869381/page_6.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics A2: Grimoire of the Rift Guide|last=Habib|first=Jon|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Montblanc also appears in ''Final Fantasy XII'' as the leader of Clan Centurio.

To commemorate the release of ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' in Japan, several pieces of merchandise were introduced exclusive for the region. This came in the form of web money cards, posters, character card collections and a set of twenty pin badges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Winkler, Chris|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/news/2002/2050.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Merchandise|date=2003-10-13|work=RPGFan.com |accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/pics/ffta/products.html|title=RPGFan Pictures - Final Fantasy Tactics Advance - Products|publisher=RPGFan|accessdate=2009-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Winkler, Chris|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/news/2003/1080.html|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Pin Badges Announced|date=2003-01-27|work=RPGFan.com|accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Square and Nintendo also announced a limited-edition ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance''-themed Game Boy Advance SP package to commemorate the game and the console's launching in February 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Yap, Eric|url=http://www.gamespot.com/gba/strategy/finalfantasytacticsadvance/news.html?sid=2908736|title=Limited-edition Game Boy Advance SP, Final Fantasy Tactics|date=2003-01-14|work=GameSpot.com |accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Japanese-exclusive adaptation of the game's story in [[radio drama]] form was also released. It was aired in January and February 2003. The series was released by [[DigiCube]] on CD in four separate parts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| year=2006|author = Squareenixmusic.com staff| url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/albums/f/fftaradio1.html| archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071223134901/http://www.squareenixmusic.com/albums/f/fftaradio1.html| archivedate=2007-12-23|title=Final Fantasy Tactics Advance Radio Edition - Complete Version: Vol. 1|accessdate=2007-10-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some plot details were changed, such as when a few moments after Mewt reads the inscription on the magical book, it transforms the world right in front of their faces.

==See also==
{{Wikipedia-Books|Final Fantasy  Tactics series}}
{{-}}
==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://na.square-enix.com/games/FFT-A/ Official site for North America]
*''[http://www.metacritic.com/games/platforms/gba/finalfantasytacticsadvance/ Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]'' at [[Metacritic]]
*[http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Final_Fantasy_Tactics_Advance ''Final Fantasy Tactics Advance'' at the FF Wikia]

{{Ivalice}}
{{Final Fantasy series}}

[[Category:2003 video games]]
[[Category:Final Fantasy games]]
[[Category:Final Fantasy Tactics]]
[[Category:Game Boy Advance games]]
[[Category:Game Boy Advance-only games]]
[[Category:Interactive Achievement Award winners]]
[[Category:Tactical role-playing video games]]
[[Category:Video games with isometric graphics]]
[[Category:Parallel universes (video games)]]

{{good article}}

[[es:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[fr:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[ko:파이널 판타지 택틱스 어드밴스]]
[[id:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[it:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[ja:ファイナルファンタジータクティクスアドバンス]]
[[no:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[pl:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[pt:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[ru:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[simple:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]
[[th:ไฟนอลแฟนตาซี แทกติกส์ แอดวานซ์]]
[[uk:Final Fantasy Tactics Advance]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
