<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="787650" ns="0" title="Sim racing"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Racing simulator|professional simulators|Driving simulator}}
{{Refimprove|date=September 2007}}
{{Original research|date=September 2007}}
{{VG Simulation}}
'''Sim''' ('''simulated''') '''racing''' is the collective term for [[computer software]] (i.e. a [[vehicle simulation game]]) that attempts to simulate accurately [[auto racing]] (a [[racing video game]]), complete with real-world variables such as fuel usage, damage, tire wear and grip, and suspension settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Game Design|author= Bob Bates|pages=59|isbn=978-1592004935|publisher=Course Technology PTR|edition=2|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; To be competitive in sim racing, a driver must understand all aspects of [[car handling]] that make real-world racing so difficult,&lt;ref name=&quot;lfs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=More about the (online) racing simulator|url=http://www.lfs.net/?page=moreabout|publisher=lfs.net|accessdate=2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as [[threshold braking]], how to maintain control of a car as the tires lose traction, and how properly to enter and exit a turn without sacrificing speed. It is this level of difficulty that distinguishes sim racing from &quot;arcade&quot; driving games where real-world variables are taken out of the equation and the principal objective is to create a sense of speed as opposed to a sense of realism.&lt;ref name=&quot;lfs&quot;/&gt;

In general, sim racing applications such as, ''[[Grand Prix Legends]]'', ''[[iRacing]]'', ''Virtual Grand Prix 3'', ''[[GT Legends]]'', ''[[rFactor]]'', ''[[F1 Challenge '99-'02]]'', ''[[GTR2]]'', ''[[Live for Speed]]'', ''[[netKar Pro]]'', and ''[[X Motor Racing]]'' are less popular than [[arcade game|arcade-style games]] such as ''[[Need for Speed]]'' series, mainly because much more skill and practice is required to master them. However, sims such as ''[[NASCAR Racing 2003 Season]]'', and ''[[Richard Burns Rally]]'' have achieved world wide fame. Also, because of the demands on the computer system, race sims require faster computers to run effectively, as well as a somewhat costly steering wheel and pedals for the throttle and brakes. Most arcade driving games can be played with a simple joystick controller or even a mouse and keyboard.

With the development of online racing capability, the ability to drive against human opponents as opposed to [[Game AI|computer AI]] is the closest many will come to driving real cars on a real track. Even those who race in real-world competition use simulations for practice or for entertainment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Video Game Review|url=http://www.racerchicks.com/motor/Review_NASCAR4.html|publisher=racerchicks.com|accessdate=2008-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Continued development of the [[physics engine]] software that forms the basis of these sims, as well as improved hardware (providing tactile feedback), the software gets ever closer to reality.

==History==
===Early years===
[[Racing video game]]s had been attempting to provide driving simulation experiences since ''[[Pole Position (video game)|Pole Position]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[[IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Society|IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Council]] &amp; [[IEEE Electron Devices Society]] (October 1-3, 2000), [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=TpVVAAAAMAAJ ''2000 IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference proceedings''], p. 65, [[Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers]], ISBN 0780359712&lt;/ref&gt; a 1982 [[arcade game]] developed by [[Namco]], which the game's publisher [[Atari]] publicized for its &quot;unbelievable driving realism&quot; in providing a [[Formula 1]] experience behind a [[racing wheel]] at the time. It featured other [[artificial intelligence|AI]] cars to race against, crashes caused by [[Collision detection|collisions]] with other vehicles and roadside signs, and introduced a qualifying lap concept where the player needs to complete a [[time trial]] before they can compete in [[Grand Prix motor racing|Grand Prix]] races.&lt;ref&gt;{{KLOV game|id=9063|name=Pole Position}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also pioneered the [[Third person (video games)|third-person]] rear-view perspective used in most racing games since then, with the track's vanishing point swaying side to side as the player approaches corners, accurately simulating forward movement into the distance.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Perron &amp; Mark J. P. Wolf (2008), ''Video game theory reader two'', p. 157, [[Taylor &amp; Francis]], ISBN 041596282X&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Pole Position II]]'' was released in 1983 and featured several improvements like giving the player the choice of different race courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{KLOV game|id=9064|name=Pole Position II}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[TX-1]]'', developed by [[Tatsumi (company)|Tatsumi]] in 1983,&lt;ref&gt;[http://flyers.arcade-museum.com/?page=thumbs&amp;db=videodb&amp;id=5911 TX-1], The Arcade Flyer Archive, [[Killer List of Videogames]]&lt;/ref&gt; was licensed to Namco,&lt;ref name=TX-1/&gt; who in turn licensed it to Atari in America,&lt;ref name=TX-1/&gt; thus the game is considered a successor to ''Pole Position II''.&lt;ref name=TX-1/&gt; ''TX-1'', however, placed a greater emphasis on realism, with details such as forcing players to brake or downshift the gear during corners to avoid the risk of losing control, and let go of the accelerator when going into a skid in order to regain control of the steering. It also used [[Haptic technology|force feedback]] technology, which caused the steering wheel to vibrate, and the game also featured a unique three-screen arcade display for a more [[2.5D|three-dimensional]] perspective of the track. It also introduced [[nonlinear gameplay]] by allowing players to choose which path to drive through after each checkpoint, eventually leading to one of eight possible [[Multiple endings|final destinations]].&lt;ref name=TX-1&gt;{{KLOV game|id=10004|name=TX-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; An early attempt at creating a home driving simulator was [[Takara Tomy|Tomy]]'s 1983 game ''Turnin' Turbo Dashboard'', the first home video game to feature a steering wheel controller.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcpro.co.uk/features/361591/the-top-ten-retro-gaming-secrets/2 The top ten retro gaming secrets: Steering wheel controllers are older than you think], [[CNET.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, Sega's ''[[Hang-On]]'', a popular [[Grand Prix motorcycle racing|Grand Prix]] style rear-view motorbike racer,&lt;ref name=Hang-On&gt;{{KLOV game|id=8068|name=Hang On}}&lt;/ref&gt; was considered the first full-body-experience video game,&lt;ref name=&quot;gamecentercx&quot;&gt;[[Retro Game Master|GameCenter CX]] - 2nd Season, Episode 13&lt;/ref&gt; and was regarded as the first motorbike simulator for its realism at the time, in both the handling of the player's motorbike and the AI of the computer-controlled motorcyclists.&lt;ref name=Hang-On/&gt; It used [[Haptic technology|force feedback]] technology and was also one of the first [[arcade game]]s to use [[History of video game consoles (fourth generation)|16-bit graphics]] and Sega's &quot;Super Scaler&quot; technology that allowed [[2.5D|pseudo-3D]] [[Sprite (computer graphics)#Move to 3D|sprite-scaling]] at high [[frame rate]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.retro.ign.com/articles/974/974695p3.html IGN Presents the History of SEGA: World War], [[IGN]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The following year, [[Konami]] released ''[[WEC Le Mans]]'', an early car driving simulator based on the [[24 Hours of Le Mans]]. It attempted to realistically simulate car driving, with the car jumping up and down, turning back and forth, and spinning up to 180 degres, with an emphasis on acceleration, breaking, and gear shifting, along with the need for counter-steering to avoid spin-outs. It also featured a day-night cycle, accurately simulated courses approved by the [[Automobile Club de l'Ouest]], and force feedback to simulate road vibration in the form of a vibrating steering wheel that reacts to the driver's acceleration and off-road bumps.&lt;ref&gt;{{KLOV game|10383|WEC Le Mans 24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first racing game with simulation pretensions on a home system is believed to have been ''[[REVS (computer game)|REVS]]'', released in [[1986]]. ''REVS'' was a [[Formula Three|Formula 3]] sim that delivered a semi-realistic driving experience by [[Geoff Crammond]] that ran on the 8-bit [[Commodore 64]] and [[BBC Micro|BBC]]. ''REVS'' had a big fan base in England, but not so much in the United States.&lt;ref name=GSpot-Papyrus/&gt; This was then superseded by the widely popular ''[[Hard Drivin']]'' which was an arcade and home computing staple released in 1989, and one of the most widely played simulators up to that point.

Sim racing is generally acknowledged to have really taken off in [[1990]] with the introduction of [[Papyrus Design Group]]'s ''[[Indianapolis 500: The Simulation]]'', designed by David Kaemmer and Omar Khudari on 16-bit hardware. The game is often generally regarded as the personal computer's first true auto racing simulation. Unlike most other racing games at the time, ''Indianapolis 500'' attempted to simulate realistic [[Game physics|physics]] and [[telemetry]], such as its portrayal of the relationship between the four contact patches and the pavement, as well as the loss of grip when making a high-speed turn, forcing the player to adopt a proper racing line and believable throttle-to-brake interaction. It also featured a garage facility to allow players to enact modifications to their vehicle, including adjustments to the tires, shocks and wings.&lt;ref name=GSpot-Papyrus&gt;{{cite web|title=The History of Papyrus Racing - Page 2|url=http://www.gamespot.com/features/6103365/p-2.html|publisher=''[[Gamespot]]''|accessdate=2008-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; With ''Indy 500'', players could race the full {{convert|500|mi|km}}, where even a blowout after {{convert|450|mi|km}} would take the player out of the competition. The simulation sold over 200,000 copies.

The next major milestone was the 1992 release of ''[[Formula One Grand Prix (Geoff Crammond)|Formula One Grand Prix]]'' (AKA ''World Circuit'' in some markets) by [[MicroProse]], also developed by Geoff Crammond. This moved the genre along significantly. Multiplayer was made possible by allowing different drivers to take turns, and racers could also hook up their machines for racing via a [[null modem]] cable. This only allowed two drivers to race. Leagues emerged where drivers would submit records of their single player races to compare with other drivers. This is the first sim in which drafting/slip streaming was possible.

Papyrus followed up Indy 500 with ''[[IndyCar Racing]]'' in [[1993]] and F1GP was surpassed in all areas.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} Papyrus later released more tracks and a final expansion included the Indy 500 track plus a paintkit. Now drivers could easily customize their cars. ''IndyCar Racing'' sold around 300,000 copies.

The first variant of Papyrus' ''NASCAR'' series was launched in [[1994]]. In [[SVGA]] (640x480) it pushed the PCs of the time to the limit. Suddenly a resolution of 320x200 seemed a poor option and ''NASCAR'' was the race sim of choice for anyone with a capable PC, particularly in North America. It was the first sim where cars no longer looked like boxes.  It keyed in on sophisticated physics modeling.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} ''NASCAR 1'' sold over one million units.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} Moreover, the first real online racing started with ''NASCAR 1'' using the &quot;Hawaii&quot; dial-in servers and it was not uncommon for these early sim racers to have $300 to $1500 phone bills. Online racing had seen its first true realization, and to many, this was the dawn of &quot;real&quot; sim racing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/5.02/ffdrivesim_pr.html Hard Drive] [[Wired.com]] Retrieved 2011-01-13&lt;/ref&gt;

[[1995]] saw the release of ''[[IndyCar Racing II]]'', updating the first version with the new NASCAR graphics engine. A year later, [[MicroProse]] released the successor to F1GP, ''[[Grand Prix 2 (game)|Grand Prix 2]]'', to much anticipation. ''GP2'' became successful not just because of its detailed and thorough simulation of the [[1994]] Formula 1 season, but also because it was customizable; this was achievable by way of the online community. Players could change everything about the game: drivers, teams, graphics, physics, car shapes, and eventually even the racetracks. Offline leagues reached their peak with ''GP2'' in [[1998]].{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

In [[1996]], ''NASCAR 2'' was released, further improving the original, and the number of sim racers exploded. The [[Total Entertainment Network|TEN]] multiplayer hosting service was introduced and went live in November of 1997 with the backing of NASCAR and the online sim racing community grew.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}} 

1997 saw the release of [[Polyphony Digital]]'s ''[[Gran Turismo (video game)|Gran Turismo]]'', which was in production for five years since 1992,&lt;ref&gt;http://venturebeat.com/2010/01/14/gran-turismos-creator-takes-a-fifth-stab-at-a-perfect-racing-game/&lt;/ref&gt; and is considered by some to be the most influential console racing game of all time.&lt;ref name=GameSpot/&gt; As the most realistic driving simulation seen on a console up until that time, it offered meticulous tuning options and introduced an [[Nonlinear gameplay|open-ended]] [[Be-a-pro mode|career mode]] where players had to undertake [[driving test]]s to acquire [[Driver's license|driving licenses]], earn their way into races, and choose their own career path.&lt;ref name=GameSpot&gt;[http://www.gamespot.com/features/6148640/index.html The Greatest Games of All Time: ''Gran Turismo''], [[GameSpot]]&lt;/ref&gt; Later games introduced [[endurance racing (motorsport)|endurance racing]] events, such as the [[1000 km Suzuka]], [[24 Hours of Le Mans]] and [[24 Hours Nürburgring]].&lt;ref&gt;Gran Turismo 4 event list, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Gran Turismo (series)|''Gran Turismo'' series]] has since become the best-selling [[Racing video game|racing game]] franchise to date, having sold over 61.41 million units worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gtplanet.net/5-5-million-copies-of-gt5-sold-series-tops-60-million/ |title=http://www.gtplanet.net/5-5-million-copies-of-gt5-sold-series-tops-60-million/ |accessdate=2010-12-10 |date=2010-12-10 |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Graphic accelerators era===
Graphics accelerator cards brought a new level of realism to the graphics and physics of sim racing games. These new [[graphics processing unit]]s provided [[texture mapping]], [[antialiasing]], [[Particle system|particle effects]] (i.e. fog, rain and snow), and the capability to perform polygonal calculations faster, while taking the load off of the main processor. ''[[F1 Racing Simulation]]'' by [[Ubisoft]], was among the first to utilize the new technology in [[1997]]. 

After years of development, Microprose released ''[[Grand Prix 3]]'', which used a more modern graphics engine and featured the same customizable structure of ''GP2''. ''GP3'' was ultimately seen as a bit of a disappointment though, lacking proper network-multiplayer-support and using only an evolution of the GP2 graphic-engine. Still, its similarity allowed easy track conversions back and forth.

Another milestone in sim racing came in 1998 with the release of ''[[Grand Prix Legends]]'' (GPL) from Papyrus, based on the [[1967]] F1 season. It was hailed as outstanding in all areas, but especially the physics and online multiplayer capability. For many, their first real experience with online racing was GPL, or the later variants of ''NASCAR'' that used the ''GPL'' engine. The release of a third-party add-on for GPL—VROC (Virtual Racers Online Connection) -- allowed racers to join together online and race in leagues.

Despite its age, ''GPL'' has remained a top class sim even in 2008 thanks to a strong community, who collectively have updated the graphics to utilize the current CPU and graphics capabilities and have created loads of add-on tracks of a high quality. Modding teams have managed to create new physics sets, and a [[1965]] [[1966]] and [[1969]] variants are now available with many improvements over the original. 

Since ''GPL'', [[Image Space Incorporated]] has produced ''[[Sports Car GT]]'' in 1999 and the ''F1'' series starting in 2000, all published by [[Electronic Arts]]. Unlike the Papyrus sims, the physics are easily modified, and a large community has developed dedicated to modifying the ISI sims. One such modding team, [[Simbin]], have created their own company and have released several games, including ''[[GTR - FIA GT Racing Game]]'', ''[[GT Legends]]'', ''[[GTR - FIA GT Racing Game 2|GTR 2]]'', ''[[RACE - The Official WTCC Game]]'', ''[[RACE 07 - The Official WTCC Game|RACE 07]], ''[[STCC - The Game]]'', ''[[GTR Evolution]]'' and ''[[Race On]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Simbin Game titles|url=http://www.simbin.se/main/games.htm| publisher=simbin.se|accessdate=2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wired magazine wrote an in-depth article about racing sims called Hard Drive in their February 1997 issue.[http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/5.02/ffdrivesim_pr.html]

===Current developments===	 
[[Image:X_Motor_Racing_Menu.jpg|thumb|right|200px|''[[X Motor Racing]]'' (2010)]]	 
 
David Kaemmer, co-founder of the now-defunct Papyrus,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The History of Papyrus Racing - Page 1|url=http://www.gamespot.com/features/6103365/index.html|publisher=''[[Gamespot]]''|accessdate=2008-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; has released ''[[iRacing]]'', a new multiplayer-oriented simulation run on a subscription model. Rally fans have a hardcore racing simulator with ''[[Richard Burns Rally]]''. Eero Piitulainen, lead physics programmer for Richard Burns Rally, is currently developing a new multi-class online racing simulator called ''[[Driver's Republic]]''.	 
		 
A small, 3-man team is developing ''[[Live for Speed]]'', which has just announced the third, and final phase of a 3-phase development cycle. Phase 2 brought in many updates, including the first real cars (The [[BMW Sauber]] F1 car being included in those), however for Phase 3 the first real-world circuit has been announced - The [[Rockingham Motor Speedway]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Live For Speed - Rockingham coming to LFS|url=http://www.lfs.net/?page=rockingham|accessdate=2009-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The circuit will be laser-scanned for absolute accuracy. Also coming soon is another real-world car - the new [[VW Scirocco]]; for which several physics changes have had to be made to ensure a fully accurate simulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Live For Speed - New Tyre Physics|url=http://www.lfs.net/|accessdate=2009-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;	 
		 
In August, 2005, ISI released ''[[rFactor]]'', a highly modifiable sim based on their gMotor2 physics engine. Notable for its initial download-only distribution model, ''rFactor'' originally released with fictional cars and tracks. ISI's encouragement of the enthusiast mod community has led to an unprecedented number of add-ons, including 800-horsepower-stock cars. Subsequent releases of rFactor featured Formula One cars and recreations of real track layouts under fictitious names.	 
		 
Paolo Cattani has developed ''[[Virtual Grand Prix 3]]'' (published by A&amp;M), notable for its quasi-finite elements tyre model and its clever Artificial Intelligene. [[AutoSimSport Magazine]] awarded ''VGP3'' as &quot;the 3rd best simulator of the year&quot; in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;autosimsport.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AutoSimSport Media LLC - The Home of AutoSimSport Magazine|url=http://autosimsport.net|publisher=autosimsport.net/|accessdate=2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; 	 
		 
[[Kunos Simulazioni]] has released ''[[netKar Pro]]'', a new version of ''netKar'' which attempts to bring together highly accurate physics and sound modeling as well as [[DirectX]] 9 graphics. Development tools for modifying ''NKP'' have been announced.	 
		 
[[The Sim Factory]] has announced a partnership with the [[Automobile Racing Club of America|ARCA Racing series]] and Image Space Incorporated to create a realistic and sanctioned online racing simulation. The simulation is currently being developed using input from real drivers, real crew chiefs, real data, and engineers specializing in all the areas needed to recreate a simulated stock car racing environment.	 
		 
More recently, Eugene Cojocar of Exotypos released [[X Motor Racing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Interview with Eugene Cojocar for AutoSimSport |publisher=''AutoSimSport.net''|url = http://www.autosimsport.net/issues/aUtosimsport_v3i02.zip | accessdate = 2007-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;, and Reiza Studios released Game Stock Car ([[Game Stock Car|GSC]]). &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Game Stock Car – Now Available!|publisher=''virtualr.net''|url=http://www.virtualr.net/game-stock-car-now-available | accessdate = 2011-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Venues ===

It was around the turn of the millennium that the technology was reaching a maturity that enticed pioneers to establish dedicated race venues. Sim Racing Ltd in the UK developed the concept of dedicated race venues for drivers and sim drivers alike. Their first offering came in the form of a range of drivers challenge activities. Sim Racing Ltd are now growing their range of offerings across the UK and beyond. Hyperstim are also opening a number of race centres around the world. Recently a new centre has started in Holland. This centre contains 20 dedicated simulators connected via local area network, using rFactor and ''GTR'' as main software simulators.  Recently venues have opened in the US when in August, 2011 [[Simraceway]] opened a 30,000 square-foot performance driving facility in Sonoma, Calif. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=SimRaceway Opens Real-World Driving School|url=http://pc.gamespy.com/pc/simraceway/1191998p1.html|publisher=Gamespy.com|accessdate=2011-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; helping to make simulation racing more mainstream and increasing the potential for many more people to enjoy motor sports as a participant activity.

The oldest and longest running simulator racing website is The Pits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Pits - 10 years:1995-2005|url=http://www.thepits.us/about.html|publisher=thepits.us|accessdate=2008-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Started in 1995 when an entrepreneur editor from the UK wanted a place to host his modification for the ''Indycar Racing II'' sim, it has continued to serve the community with a multitude of firsts in the simulator racing world, as well as downloads and helpful information.  Some of the firsts include the first complete mod (or modification) for racing simulation software, The Pits Touring Car Championship, released in 1997. 

One of the latest trends in sim racing is towards broadcasting the events. There are a growing number of leagues that are now running flag to flag coverage of their events.  And like other forms of motorsports the fans can outnumber the drivers by many. There are several places for fans to go to find out more about simulator racing.  Since January 2005, [[AutoSimSport Magazine]] has provided industry leading content for sim racers.&lt;ref name=&quot;autosimsport.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=AutoSimSport Media LLC - The Home of AutoSimSport Magazine|url=http://autosimsport.net|publisher=autosimsport.net/|accessdate=2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Beginning its 4th year of publication, AutoSimSport Magazine continues to provide quality media for sim racers the world over to keep current with the latest advancements in simulators, hardware, and where the sim racing industry is headed.  Since 2010, &quot;Crash Cast FM&quot; is a new simracing radioshow/podcast.

=== Online Communities ===
In recent years as international interest has grown, so has the online community and underground racing circuit.  These communities act as a focal point for users around the world to engage with one another co-ordinate racing schedules, exchange modded cars, tracks, discuss hardware configurations and facilitate other communications.  

== See also ==
*[[Racing game]]
*[[Vehicle simulation game]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{VideoGameGenre}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sim Racing}}
[[Category:Racing simulators| ]]
[[Category:Video game genres]]

[[de:Rennsimulation]]
[[fr:Sim racing]]
[[ja:レースシミュレーション]]
[[ru:Автосимулятор]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
