<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7881958" ns="0" title="List of James Bond allies in Octopussy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This is a list of [[James Bond]] [[List of James Bond allies|allies]] in the film ''[[Octopussy]]''.

==Recurring Allies==
*[[M (James Bond)|M]] - [[Robert Brown (British actor)|Robert Brown]]
*[[Q (James Bond)|Q]] - [[Desmond Llewelyn]]
*[[Miss Moneypenny]] - [[Lois Maxwell]]
*[[General Gogol]] - [[Walter Gotell]]
*[[Fredrick Gray]] - [[Geoffrey Keen]]

==Vijay==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Vijay
|portrayed=[[Vijay Amritraj]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]]
|status=Deceased
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Vijay''' is a fictional character from the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Octopussy]]''. He was played by the Indian tennis player [[Vijay Amritraj]].

A talented and good-natured man, Vijay is a field operative in India, who assists Bond in making contact with [[Kamal Khan]], as well as keeping him informed of Khan's activities. As a member of the same tennis club as Khan, he is able to watch him closely. When asked by Bond if he'd learnt anything since attending the club, Vijay replies, &quot;Well, my backhand has improved.&quot;

Bond visits the Floating Palace to see Octopussy, and Vijay keeps watch from the shore. He is killed when a group of hired thugs come across him on their way to attack Bond on the island. Q finds him still alive off-screen, but dies shortly after saying &quot;It was Kamal's men.&quot;
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

== Sadruddin ==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Sadruddin
|portrayed=[[Albert Moses]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|affiliation=[[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]]
|status=Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Sadruddin''' is a fictional character from the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Octopussy]]''. He was played by Albert Moses.

Is the section chief in [[New Delhi]] and hence senior to Vijay. Impersonation of a small taxi driver and provides information to Bond. It is seen when Bond shares his money earned later as Kamal Khan and heals the wounds of Bond when Kamal Palace escapes and gives the information of Octopussy.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

== Bianca ==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Bianca
|portrayed=[[Tina Hudson]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[Secret Intelligence Service|MI6]]
|status=Alive
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}
'''Bianca''' is a fictional character from the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Octopussy]]''. She was played by [[Tina Hudson]].

=== Film Biography ===
Is a beautiful MI6 agent who accompanies Bond to destroy a secret air base in Cuba. When the mission goes awry, Bianca distracts the security guards at Bond and then neutralizes the promise to see her in Miami and at the same moment Bond pilots his [[Homebuilt aircraft|homebuilt]] [[Bede BD-5|Bede BD-5J]].
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Penelope Smallbone==
{{James Bond Character|
|image= 
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Miss Penelope Smallbone
|portrayed=[[Michaela Clavell]]
|gender=[[Female]]
|affiliation=[[MI6]]
|status=Unknown
|role=Bond ally
}}

Miss '''Penelope Smallbone''' is [[Miss Moneypenny]]'s assistant in the [[James Bond]] film [[Octopussy]].  She is portrayed by [[Michaela Clavell]].  The character was originally planned to replace [[Lois Maxwell]]'s Moneypenny; however the idea was scrapped.{{fact|date=January 2011}}

===Film Biography===
There is not much known about Miss Smallbone, she briefly appears in Octopussy and is never seen again.  When Bond enters, he looks at Smallbone and thinks she is Moneypenny claiming that she was looking better every day. After Bond talks to Moneypenny, he gives Smallbone his flowers and leaves.  Both Smallbone and Moneypenny sigh after Bond leaves.

==Jim Fanning==
{{James Bond Character|
|image=  
|bgcolor=#039
|fgcolor=#fff
|name=Jim Fanning
|portrayed=[[Douglas Wilmer]]
|gender=[[Male]]
|age=Unknown
|affiliation=[[MI6]]
|status=Active/Unknown
|role=[[List of James Bond allies|Ally]]
}}

'''Jim Fanning''' is a [[fictional character]] that appears in the [[James Bond]] film ''[[Octopussy]]''.  He is an [[art]] expert and is portrayed by [[Douglas Wilmer]].

===Biography===
Jim Fanning is an Art Expert whose knowledge revolves art history and jewelry. He often works with [[MI6]] and is appointed to attend an art auction where the fake of a priceless [[Fabergé Egg]] is being auctioned - unfortunately for him he is accompanying [[007]].

===Film Biography===
Jim Fanning is first seen in [[M (James Bond)|M’s]] office with [[Sir Fredrick Gray]].  They talk to Bond about a Fabergé Egg.  Bond knows all the things about the egg, except that is a fake, something that Fanning found out.  Fanning then discusses the real egg and thinks the seller was a Russian.  He then asks Bond will go to the auction to spot the seller.  We next see him with Bond at the auction.  He tells Bond a few things about what the price of the egg should go for.  They find out the buyer of the egg, who is [[Kamal Khan]] alongside [[Magda (James Bond)|Magda]].  Fanning tells him that Khan is normally a seller but this time he is buying.  Bond then realises that Khan will go to any price to get the egg.  To Fanning’s surprise, Bond bids for the egg, which a distressed Fanning to ask
*Fanning: Have you gone mad?
*Bond: Let’s see how badly he wants it.
Fanning is then horrified that Bond has bid again.  When Khan bids over the top (after Bond has switched the real with the fake egg), he doesn’t bid again and Fanning is slightly relieved.

It is unknown what happens to Jim Fanning after that.

Fanning seems to be based on an art critic and government consultant named &quot;Fanshawe&quot; who plays a similar role in the Ian Fleming short story &quot;The Property of a Lady,&quot; which provides the Fabergé and Sotheby's background for the movie.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;
{{James Bond characters}}

[[Category:Lists of James Bond allies|Octopussy]]
[[Category:Octopussy|Allies]]

[[pt:Vijay]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
