<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="791271" ns="0" title="New York Institute of Technology"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name = New York Institute of Technology
|image = [[Image:A2 Seal.jpg|205x205 px|NYIT Seal]]
|motto =
|established = 1955
|type = [[Private School|Private]]
|president = [http://www.nyit.edu/president/biography Dr. Edward Guiliano]
|city = [[Manhattan]]
|state = [[New York|NY]]
|country = [[United States|USA]]
|undergrad = 7,718
|postgrad = 5,162
|faculty = 273 full-time, 832 adjunct (Spring 2010 semester, domestic)
|campus = [[Suburban]] [[urban area|Urban]]
|free_label = NCAA
|free = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], 1 team &lt;br /&gt;[[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]], 9 teams
|mascot = [[NYIT Bears|Bear]]
|colors = Blue and Yellow {{color box|#1569C7}}&amp;nbsp;{{color box|#FBB917}}
|Web site = [http://www.nyit.edu/ www.nyit.edu]
|logo    = &lt;CENTER&gt;[[Image:Nyit logo.gif|NYIT Logo]]&lt;/CENTER&gt;}}

'''New York Institute of Technology''' (also known as '''NYIT''') is a private, non-sectarian, co-educational research university in [[New York City]]. NYIT has five schools and two colleges, all with a strong emphasis on technology and applied scientific research. The university has two New York campuses, one in Old Westbury [[Long Island]] and one near Columbus Circle in [[Manhattan]], as well as several global campuses and programs (e.g. [[Bahrain]], [[Canada]], [[China]], [[Jordan]], [[United Arab Emirates]]). NYIT offers a total of 90 undergraduate degree, graduate degree programs, and medical degree programs to 15,000 students in academic areas such as architecture and design; arts and sciences; education; engineering and computing sciences; health professions; management; and osteopathic medicine.
	
Its [[Carnegie Classification]] is Masters-Granting (Doctorate-Granting through New York College of Osteopathic Medicine of the New York Institute of Technology) &quot;Research University,&quot; very high research activity&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=194091&amp;start_page=institution.php&amp;clq=%7B%22ipug2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ipgrad2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22enrprofile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ugprfile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22sizeset2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22basic2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22eng2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22search_string%22%3A%22new+york+institute+of+technology%22%2C%22first_letter%22%3A%22%22%2C%22level%22%3A%22%22%2C%22control%22%3A%22%22%2C%22accred%22%3A%22%22%2C%22state%22%3A%22%22%2C%22region%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urbanicity%22%3A%22%22%2C%22womens%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hbcu%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hsi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22tribal%22%3A%22%22%2C%22msi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22landgrant%22%3A%22%22%2C%22coplac%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urban%22%3A%22%22%7D|title=Carnegie Classification|publisher=Carnegie Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, NYIT received a grant from the [[U.S. Department of Energy]] to study the relationship between electric vehicles and renewable energy charging stations. NYIT has also partnered with the [[U.N.]] to promote the International Water Conference in 2008 and the International Energy Conference in 2009. In addition to sustainable technology, NYIT faculty and students are also involved in other areas of research, including cardiovascular health, epilepsy, blindness, staph infection, and cyber security. 

==History==
{{Main|NYIT History}}
In 1910, NYIT’s predecessor, New York Technical Institute, was licensed by the New York State Board of Regents. In 1955, NYIT opened under a provisional charter granted by the New York State Board of Regents to NYIT; its first campus opened at 500 Pacific Street in Brooklyn, in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/2006/winter/features/feature_1.php ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The founders of NYIT, and in particular, [[Alexander Schure]], [[Ph.D.]],&lt;ref name=sunsentinel&gt;{{cite news|first=Scott|last=Travis |title=NSU's former chancellor, Alexander Schure, dies|url=http://www.sun-sentinel.com/news/broward/fl-schure-obit-20091123,0,1622342.story|work=[[South Florida Sun-Sentinel]]|publisher=|date=2009-11-23 |accessdate=2009-11-28|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5lcmDlJjU |archivedate=2009-11-28|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; started NYIT with the mission of offering career-oriented professional education, providing all qualified students access to opportunity, and supporting applications-oriented research that benefits the larger world. Schure later served as NYIT's first president.&lt;ref name=sunsentinel/&gt;
[[File:Alex schure.jpg|thumb|NYIT's first president, Alexander Schure, Ph.D., Ed.D.]]

NYIT sought to meet critical national demands, particularly the need for scientists, engineers, and high-level technicians in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyit.edu&quot;&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/2006/winter/features/the50s.php ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the higher education community at the time, a debate arose around the concern that humanities studies would be overshadowed by too much emphasis on science and engineering. NYIT's goal was to create a balance between science/engineering and a liberal arts education, and ever since, it has been focusing on this model to prepare students for current and future careers. NYIT's mission resonated among industry and learners. By the 1958–1959 academic year, the university had more than 300 students, and the time had come to expand its physical operations.

In April 1958, the college purchased the [[Pythian Temple (New York City)|Pythian Temple]] at 135–145 W. 70th St. in Manhattan for its main center. The building, adjacent to the planned [[Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts]], was an ornate 12-story structure with a columned entranceway. Built in 1929 at a cost of $2 million, it included among its features a huge 1,200-seat auditorium.

In 1958, NYIT sponsored the first National Technology Awards, created by Frederick Pittera, an organizer of international fairs and a member of the NYIT Board of Trustees, to help raise funds for the NYIT science and technology laboratories. The awards, held  at the [[Waldorf-Astoria]] Hotel, were attended by several hundred guests, with entertainment provided by the U.S. [[Air Force Band]]. Senator [[Lyndon Johnson]] was the keynote speaker. His speech was broadcast nationally by the [[ABC Radio Network]]. Among the honorees were Dr. [[Werner von Braun]] and Major General [[Bernard Schriever]], Commanding General of the Ballistic Air Command. Photos, press clippings, and audio tapes of the event are on view at the Lyndon Johnson Library at Austin, Texas.

[[File:Nyit computers.jpg|thumb|left|NYIT pioneered computers in the classrooms, it was the first to introduce “teaching machines” in the 1950s]]
NYIT’s faculty designed curricula to incorporate modern technologies with teaching and [[applied academics]]. In 1959, NYIT introduced “teaching machines” for student instruction in physics, electronics, and mathematics.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyit.edu&quot;/&gt; NYIT also pioneered the use of [[mainframes]] as a teaching tool, having received its first, donated by the CIT Financial Corporation, in 1965.

The curricula was successful enough that NYIT received two grants totaling approximately $3 million from the federal government – one to develop a system of individualized learning through the use of computers; the other to develop a computer-based course in general physics for midshipmen at the [[United States Naval Academy]] in Annapolis, Md.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/2006/winter/features/the60s.php ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NYIT was also a pioneer in 3-D computer animation. Before [[Pixar]] and [[Lucasfilm]], there was NYIT’s Computer Graphics Lab (CGL).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fundinguniverse.com/company-histories/Pixar-Animation-Studios-Company-History.html Pixar Animation Studios – Company History]. Fundinguniverse.com. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1974, NYIT’s [[Computer Graphics Lab]] (CGL) was established and attracted the likes of: [[Pixar Animation Studios]] President [[Edwin Catmull]] and co-founder Alvy Ray Smith; [[Walt Disney Feature Animation]] Chief Scientist Lance Joseph Williams; [[Dreamworks]] animator Hank Grebe; and [[Netscape]] and [[Silicon Graphics]] founder Jim Clark.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/2006/winter/features/the70s.php ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1995, NYIT’s School of Engineering took first place in the U.S. Department of Energy’s Clean Air Road Rally. The student engineering team spent three years designing and building the high-performance hybrid electric car that beat out 43 other vehicles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/2006/winter/features/the90s.php ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, NYIT opened its first international program in China.

In 2002, NYIT installed the fastest broadband network on the East Coast.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/2006/winter/features/the2000s.php ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, NYIT opened its Bahrain campus to students seeking an American-style education in the Middle East.

In 2005, NYIT participated in its first Solar Decathlon, an international competition sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy. NYIT was one of nineteen colleges internationally and the only school in the New York metropolitan area. The team, composed of students and faculty, captured fifth place honors.

In 2007, NYIT co-hosted the International Energy Conference and Exhibition in Daegu, South Korea. In that year, the university also received $500,000 in federal funding to develop a &quot;green print&quot; initiative to research alternative fuel technology and determine its carbon footprint.

In 2008, NYIT installed a state-of-the-art 3-D motion capture lab for its Fine Arts program in Old Westbury. The system allows the university to use Hollywood technology to teach the next generation of computer animators. Later that year, NYIT was awarded a $130,000 research contract by United Space Alliance to help NASA scientists design the crew module of the Orion spacecraft using 3-D motion capture technology. NYIT's College of Osteopathic Medicine also uses 3-D motion capture technology to help doctors better identify mobility and stability problems in patients with Parkinson's disease.

NYIT sponsored the first annual International Water Conference in July 2008 at the United Nations in New York City. The event brought together representatives from non-governmental organizations, international corporations, and universities  to discuss the need to safeguard the planet's water resources. The following year, NYIT sponsored its second U.N. event, the International Energy Conference (Aug. 31-Sept. 1, 2009) to welcome energy secretaries, policy makers, and executives from multinational companies to examine opportunities and innovations in the field of sustainable technology.

Today, NYIT is recognized as one of the top science and engineering schools&lt;ref name=&quot;colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com&quot;&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/old-westbury-ny/nyit-4804/@@Index_SB.html NYIT | New York Institute of Technology | Best College | US News]. Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt; and now offers a total of 90 [[undergraduate degree]], [[graduate degree]] programs, and [[medical education|medical degree]] programs to 15,000 students in academic areas such as architecture and design; arts and sciences; education; engineering and computing sciences; health professions; management; and osteopathic medicine; with more than half pursuing advanced degrees. Campuses are located in New York (Manhattan and Old Westbury, Long Island), Bahrain (Manama/Adliya), Canada (Vancouver), China (Nanjing), Jordan (Amman), and the United Arab Emirates (Abu Dhabi). NYIT's other global graduate degree programs are located in China at Jiangxi University of Finance and Economics (JUFE) and Tongji University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/academics/academic_programs/ academic_programs | academics | NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

NYIT's future is characterized as a continuation and maturation of it original mission, as defined by its 25-year plan introduced in 2005 called NYIT: 2030.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/images/uploads/about/NYIT2030-SettingDirectionsMeetingChallenges.pdf – 2010-03-03]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Schools and Colleges==
NYIT comprises the following academic schools:
*[http://nyit.edu/architecture School of Architecture and Design]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/education School of Education]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/engineering School of Engineering and Computing Sciences]
*[http://nyit.edu/health_professions School of Health Professions]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/management School of Management]
*[http://nyit.edu/arts_and_sciences College of Art and Sciences]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/nycom College of Osteopathic Medicine] ([[New York College of Osteopathic Medicine]])

==Campuses==
=== Old Westbury===
[[File:NYIT Old Westbury Academic Quad.JPG|thumb|Right|Academic Quad, Old Westbury]]
[[File:NYIT Wisser Memorial Library.JPG|thumb|Right|The George and Gertrude Wisser Memorial Library, also at the Old Westbury campus]]
New York Institute of Technology's [[Old Westbury]], [[New York|N.Y.]] campus is located on the former estate of [[Cornelius Vanderbilt Whitney]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsday.com/about/ny-iholi021105story,0,1099033.htmlstory?coll=4thrail-bottom-promo ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Opened in 1963, this campus is not only the largest in the area, but also in student population. It houses the sports complex, administrative offices, as well as [http://nyit.edu/deseversky/ de Seversky Center] (named for [[Alexander de Seversky]]), a well-known party and event venue on Long Island. The Old Westbury campus is mainly a commuter campus, although some residential students live on the nearby [[State University of New York at Old Westbury]] campus. Old Westbury is also home to the '''[[New York College of Osteopathic Medicine]]''' ('''NYCOM''') which is NYIT's medical school and the only osteopathic medical school on Long Island.
*[http://www.nyit.edu/images/uploads/about/Map-Old-Westbury.pdf Map of NYIT Old Westbury Campus]
*[http://www.wikimapia.org/#y=40811146&amp;x=-73603871&amp;z=16&amp;l=0&amp;m=h Aerial view of NYIT Old Westbury Campus]

===Manhattan===
The [[Manhattan]] campus is located between 60th and 62nd streets on Broadway, adjacent to [[Columbus Circle]] and near [[Central Park]]. While it offers a full range of classes in all of NYIT's major schools, the majority of students enroll in programs that concentrate in media, communications, computer science, and engineering. &lt;br /&gt;
The campus comprises five buildings:
* The Main Campus Building, 1855 Broadway
* The New Technology Building, 16 W. 61st St.
* 26 W. 61st St.
* The Student Activities Building, 1849 Broadway
* The Auditorium on Broadway, 1871 Broadway
[[File:P2270001.jpg|thumb|left|Broadway Center, Manhattan]]
NYIT Manhattan campus is home to a number of student clubs and organizations such as the Allied Health Life Science Organization, Bear Hug Club, Student Nurses Association, Dance Club, American Medical Student Association, Student Programming Association, Society of Hosteurs, and American Institute for Architecture Students.

Residential students have two dorm options for the Manhattan campus: Riverside Terrace on the Upper West Side,which offers single and double rooms supervised by full-time staff;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/campus_manhattan/residence_halls/riverside/ riverside | residence_halls | campus_manhattan | NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Clark Residence in Brooklyn, offering double rooms supervised by full-time staff,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/campus_manhattan/residence_halls/clark/ clark | residence_halls | campus_manhattan | NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt; which NYIT shares with other schools, mainly [[Pace University]] and [[New York University]] (NYU).
*[http://www.nyit.edu/images/uploads/about/MN_map.pdf Map of NYIT Manhattan Campus (PDF)]
*[http://www.wikimapia.org/#y=40769866&amp;x=-73982717&amp;z=19&amp;l=0&amp;m=h Aerial view of NYIT Manhattan campus]

===Global Campuses===
NYIT's long-term strategic plan includes a goal for NYIT to be a global university by the year 2030.  Within this global university, students will be able to move among campuses with complete internal transferability of credits and graduate with the same NYIT degree from any campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/nyit_worldwide/canada/ NYIT-Worldwide | NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition to its New York locations, NYIT has campuses in the following countries:
* [[Bahrain]] ([[Manama]])
* [[Canada]] ([[Vancouver]])
* [[China]] ([[Nanjing]])
* [[Jordan]] ([[Amman]])
* [[United Arab Emirates]] ([[Abu Dhabi]])

==Interdisciplinary Graduate Centers and Research==
===Graduate Centers===
[[File:NYCOM.jpg|thumb|New York College of Osteopathic Medicine]]
NYIT's interdisciplinary centers of excellence feature interdisciplinary research, graduate degree programs, and &quot;best-in-class&quot; work in a small number of highly-targeted niches. These centers bring together departments, faculty, and students for ambitious collaborations and exchanges of ideas.

The Center for Global Health is one of NYIT's pioneering centers of excellence, and opened its doors in 2007.

The Center for Metropolitan Sustainability is focused on creating a pathway to our urban future. Combining aspects of architecture, engineering, and management, we look to educate students and the general population about the right choices for sustainability.

The Center for Gerontology and Geriatrics collaborates with the academic community, government, civic, professional and business groups, and funders, in its mission to help prepare for an aging society on the regional, state, national, and global levels.

===Research===
In 2008, NYIT received a grant from the U.S. Department of Energy to study the relationship between electric vehicles and renewable energy charging stations.  For a total cost of $250,000, NYIT was able to install two solar carports (one at its Old Westbury campus and one at its Central Islip campus), convert two Toyota Prius to plug-ins with extra battery capacity, and install data collection technology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/news/2009/Oct./article_150/ NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;  Each carport spans 4 parking spots, provides level 1 charging (110 volt) at each parking spot, and supports a 10&amp;nbsp;kW solar array.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HxJWCIFFbOk LI News Tonight: Solar Carport]. YouTube. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;  Congressman Steve Israel who helped to secure the federal grant spoke at the ribbon cutting ceremony for the Central Islip carport.  He said:

{{Cquote|I'm proud to have worked with NYIT to make this innovative project happen. This is a great example of how alternative energy technologies can help us all go 'off the grid.' I look forward to the day when we're all using solar panels to charge our cars and light our homes.}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/news/2009/July/article_145/ NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

NYIT's research on electric vehicles, solar energy, and their resulting environmental and grid impacts continues in partnership with the Long Island Power Authority and the Electric Power Research Institute.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lipower.org/newscenter/pr/2009/100209-hybrid.html LIPA Press Release: LIPA and NYIT Partner to Research Solar Carports that Charge Electric, Hybrid Cars]. Lipower.org (2009-10-02). Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt; The study currently has NYIT Students participate in car-share program where they are able to drive the plug-in Priuses between their homes and the school campus.  The school plans to expand participation to faculty members as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsday.com/columnists/jennifer-smith/nyit-studying-electric-cars-future-on-li-1.1568538 NYIT studying electric cars' future on LI]. Newsday.com (2009-11-05). Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to sustainable technology, NYIT faculty and students are also involved in other areas of research, including cardiovascular health, epilepsy, blindness, staph infection, and cyber security.

==Rankings==

''2011 US News Best Colleges'' ranked NYIT as a top university in the north among regional schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com&quot;/&gt;

''2010 Chronicle of Higher Education'' ranked NYIT as one of the best colleges in the nation to work for, identified as outstanding in the category of compensation and benefits.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/section/The-Academic-Workplace/156 Great Colleges to Work For – The Chronicle of Higher Education]. Chronicle.com. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

''2009 Architect Magazine'' ranked NYIT one of the top four Building Technology Schools in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uillinois.edu/clips/January-05-2010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Insertwww.uillinois.edu/clips/January-05-2010.pdf footnote text here&lt;/ref&gt;

''2009 Campus Safety'' survey ranked NYIT as the safest college in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecampusslate.com/news-features/nyit-named-safest-college-in-america-by-dailybeast-com-1.943234 &quot; + artTitle.replace(&quot;-&quot;,&quot;&quot;) + &quot; – &quot; + &quot;The Campus Slate&quot; + &quot; – &quot; + &quot;News &amp; Features&quot; + &quot;]. Thecampusslate.com. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

''US News Best Colleges'' ranks NYIT as one of the Best Undergraduate Engineering Programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/new-york-institute-of-technology-194091/overall-rankings]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accreditation==
===Overall Accreditation and Charter===
* Commission on Higher Education of the Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools (all campuses)
* New York Institute of Technology is chartered by the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York

===Academic Program Accreditations===
* Accreditation Council for Occupational Therapy Education of the American Occupational Therapy Association
* Accreditation Review Commission on Education for the Physician Assistant Inc.
* American Osteopathic Association's Commission on Osteopathic College Accreditation
* Commission on Accreditation in Physical Therapy Education (CAPTE)
* Council for Interior Design Accreditation
* Engineering Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology Inc. (ABET)
* National Architectural Accrediting Board (NAAB)
* National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education
* Technology Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology Inc. (ABET)
* The International Assembly for Collegiate Business Education (IACBE) for business programs

===Campus-Specific Accreditations, Licensures, and Approvals===
NYIT-Bahrain: Accredited by the Ministry of Higher Education and Scientific Research in Bahrain and received certification by the International Organization for Standardization (ISO), making it the first private university in Bahrain to be awarded this distinction. The ISO recognizes administrative, financial, and management quality that reflects positively on the standards of education provided to its students.

==Student Media==
===LI News Tonight===
LI News Tonight is a nightly television newscast produced on the Old Westbury campus as both a community service to Nassau and Suffolk counties and an internship opportunity where you can learn all about careers in television news. For more than 25 years, college interns have covered breaking news and feature events alongside reporters and photographers from professional news stations, with their work appearing that evening on a nightly TV newscast aired on a Long Island cable station.

===Campus Newspapers===
On the Old Westbury campus, NYIT students produce '''the Campus Slate''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://admin2.collegepublisher.com/se/the-campus-slate &quot; + artTitle.replace(&quot;-&quot;,&quot;&quot;) + &quot; – &quot; + &quot;The Campus Slate&quot; + &quot;]. Admin2.collegepublisher.com. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt; the student-run newspaper founded in 1966. On the Manhattan campus, students produce the '''NYIT Chronicle''', a student-run newspaper founded in 2005.

===NYIT Magazine===
NYIT Magazine is the official magazine of New York Institute of Technology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine Magazine | NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt; The award-winning magazine features articles on topics relevant to alumni and the community, and includes news of events, research, sports coverage, and profiles as professor and alumni accomplishments. The magazine is published three times a year.

===WNYT===
Radio station [[WNYT (internet radio)|WNYT]] was formed shortly after NYIT opened its Old Westbury campus in the mid-1960s, operating from studios located in Education Hall. The student-run station has alternately broadcast on campus via carrier current and closed circuit connections, and during the 1970s and early 1980s, it served as the audio for Cablevision’s on-screen program guide. Today, WNYT is heard online, with Internet-based programming via RealAudio.

==Athletics==
===Old Westbury===
{{Main|NYIT Bears}}
[[Image:NYITBears.png|thumb|Right|NYIT Athletics Logo]]
With the exception of its baseball team, which plays in [[NCAA Division I]] independently until 2009 and will join the [[Great West Conference]] in 2010,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyit.edu/athletics/baseball Baseball | Baseball | NYIT]. Nyit.edu. Retrieved on 2011-04-03.&lt;/ref&gt;  NYIT's athletic programs compete in [[NCAA Division II]], and are members of the [[East Coast Conference]] ([http://www.eastcoastconference.org/ ECC]). The teams are called the Bears, and the school colors are blue and gold. NYIT offers Men's Lacrosse, Men's and women's basketball, Softball, Men and Women's Cross Country Track, women's volleyball, and Men and Women's soccer. NYIT has had much athletic success. The men's basketball team reached the NCAA Division II Championship game in 1980. The Lacrosse team has won four national championships, in 1997, 2003, 2005 and 2008. The volleyball team reached the NCAA tournament every year from 2001–2006, and in 2005, the men's soccer team reached the 2005 NCAA Division II elite eight. As of 2006 there is a developing cheerleading program.
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:NYITchampionship.jpg|thumb|left|Men's Lacrosse celebrates the 2005 National Championship]] --&gt;

===Manhattan Recreational Sports===
Students on the Manhattan campus have the opportunity to participate in various recreational sports team. The Manhattan campus offers recreational sports teams in men's basketball, men's and women's soccer, co-ed volleyball, co-ed softball, and co-ed dodgeball. The recreational sports teams play in various leagues and in various gyms across New York City. The men's basketball team has been the most successful, winning YMCA Vanderbilt league championships in 2005 and 2006.

==Greek life==
=== Fraternities===

*[[Tau Sigma Chi]]
*[[Alpha Chi Rho]]
*[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]
*[[Iota Nu Delta]]
*[[Zeta Beta Tau]]
*[[Delta Sigma Phi]]

===Sororities===
*[[Eta Chi Gamma]]
*[[Zeta Phi Beta]]
*[[Alpha Sigma Tau]]

===Coed===
[http://www.digammaomegaxi.org DiGamma Omega Xi Inc.]

==Notable alumni==
* [[John Antioco]], CEO, [[Blockbuster Video]]
*[[Candice Night]], Lead singer, [[Blackmore's Night]]
* David Hickey, president and CEO, [[Lumeta Corporation]]
* [[Richard J. Daly]], CEO, [[Broadridge Financial Solutions]]
* [[William Bauman]], vice president, [[Computer Associates]]
* [[Daisy Exposito-Ulla]], former CEO, The Bravo Group [[Young &amp; Rubicam]]
* [[Jim Geoghan]], co-creator and TV producer, [[The Suite Life of Zack &amp; Cody]]
* [[Curtis Brunson]], vice president, [[L-3 Communications]]
* [[Jerry Romano]], chairman, [[New York Emmy Awards]]
* [[Kenneth B. Jones]], president and CEO, [[Performance Consulting, NY]]
* [[Thomas S. Ricci]], vice president, [[Thomas Properties Group]]
* [[Craig D. Button]], US Air Force pilot noted for his mysterious flight and crash
* [[Harriet Schapiro Mauro]], talent producer for TV shows and live events, involved with [[Who Do You Think You Are? (U.S. TV series)|Who Do You Think You Are?]]
* [[Patti Ann Browne]], TV News Anchor, [[Fox News]]
* [[Allison Baver]], Olympic Speed Skating Medalist (Bronze, 2010)
* [[Greg Panos]], futurist, [[virtual reality]] expert, [[virtual actor/human simulation]] evangelist
* [[Humayun Chaudhry]], physician and CEO, [[Federation of State Medical Boards]]
* [[Vincent Connare]], font designer
* [[Don Cooper]], head pitching coach, [[Chicago White Sox]]
* [[Brian Kenny (sportscaster)|Brian Kenny]], ESPN SportsCenter Anchor
* [[Karl Von Batten]], founder of [[America Educates]]
* [[Richard Jadick]], naval surgeon credited for saving the lives of 30 marines and sailors during the [[Operation Phantom Fury|Second Battle of Fallujah]], earning him the [[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/11787394/site/newsweek/ ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Brian McLaughlin, New York state assemblyman
* [[Jill Nicolini]], traffic reporter for &quot;The PIX Morning News&quot; in New York
* [[Adam Pascal]], actor, singer, and producer (most notable as Roger Davis in the Broadway musical [[Rent (musical)|Rent]])
* Joseph Saladino, New York state assemblyman
* [[Steve Salvatore]], medical correspondent for [[WPIX]] in New York
* Anthony Seminerio, New York state assemblyman
* [[Queen Sylvia of Buganda]]
* [[Allen Watson]], former Major League Baseball pitcher (member of the [[2000 World Series]] Champion [[New York Yankees]])
* [[Won, Hereditary Prince Imperial of Korea]], contested Head of the [[Korean Imperial Household]]
* [[Rik Cordero]], music video, commercial, and film director
* Anders Cohen, chief of neurosurgery and spine surgery at Brooklyn Hospital Center
* Sue Chin, chief architect and vice president for planning and design at the Wildlife Conservation Society's Exhibition and Graphic Arts Department
* Thomas Vecchione, design director for Gensler
* Arkar Latt, operations manager of Turner International, which oversaw the construction of the [[Burj Khalifa|Burj Dubai]]
* Peter Ruggiero, design partner at Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill
* Ted Moudis, founder and senior principal of Ted Moudis Associates
* Phil Bottega, deputy head of facilities at Societe Generale
* Gary S. Lynch, managing director and Global Leader of Supply Chain Risk Management Practice at Marsh (NYC)
* Chris Amenita, senior vice president of ASCAP's Enterprises Group
* Bob Frank, former president of E1 Music (formerly Koch Records)
* Eric Cole, chief scientist and senior fellow at Lockheed Martin Corporation
* Art Klein, executive producer of Bottle Shock
* Michael Klein, president and CEO of Xoft Inc.
* Anthony Gioeli, former president and CEO of Atrua Technologies
* Bill Zerella, chief financial officer of Force10 Networks
* Jenni &quot;J-woww&quot; Farley Cast member of the [[Jersey Shore (TV series)]]

==Presidents==
*[[Alexander Schure]], Ph.D. – 1955–1982
*Matthew Schure, Ph.D. – 1982–2000
*Edward Guiliano, Ph.D. – 2000–

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nyit.edu New York Institute of Technology Web site]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/nycome New York College of Osteopathic Medicine (NYCOM)]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/athletics/ NYIT Athletics]
*[http://www.nyit.edu/magazine/ NYIT Magazine]
*[http://www.wnytradio.com WNYT Radio]
*{{IMDb company|id=0061366|company= New York Institute of Technology}}
*[http://www.the-sheet.com/ the-sheet.com- Architectural Web Base]
{{NYIT}}
{{New York Collegiate Athletic Conference}}
{{NYC Colleges}}
{{New York City}}

{{coord|40.769719|N|73.98247|W|source:dewiki_region:US-NY_type:landmark|format=dms|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:New York Institute Of Technology}}
[[Category:Universities and colleges in New York]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1955]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges on Long Island]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Schools in Nassau County, New York]]
[[Category:New York Institute of Technology]]

[[de:New York Institute of Technology]]
[[fr:New York Institute of Technology]]
[[ja:ニューヨーク工科大学]]
[[no:New York Institute of Technology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
