<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7916560" ns="0" title="Rhona Goskirk"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|name= Rhona Goskirk
|image=[[File:RhonaGoskirk.png|200px]]
|introducer=[[Steve November|Steve Frost]] (2001, 2002)&lt;br /&gt;[[Gavin Blyth]] (2010)
|portrayer=[[Zoe Henry]]
|years=2001, 2002, 2010—
|classification=[[List of Emmerdale characters#Present characters|Present; regular]]
|spinoffs={{nowrap|''Paddy and Marlon:,&lt;br /&gt;The Big Night In (2011) ''}}
|home= Dale View
|occupation=[[Veterinary Surgeon]]
|romances= [[Marlon Dingle]] (2001, 2002, 2010,2011) &lt;br&gt; [[Paddy Kirk]] (2010—)
|sons= [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)#Leo|Leo Goskirk]]
|first=17 September 2001
|last=
}}

'''Rhona Goskirk''' is a [[fictional character]] who is a veterinary surgeon, from the British [[ITV1]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'', played by [[Zoe Henry]]. She made her first on-screen appearance on 17 September 2001. The character was introduced by series producer [[Steve Frost]] and appeared initially in 2001 and 2002, when the character then left. She returned to ''Emmerdale'' as a full time character in March 2010, reintroduced by series producer Gavin Blyth.

==Creation==
The character was first introduced to ''Emmerdale'' in September 2001, by series producer [[Steve Frost]] played by [[Zoe Henry]]. The character was initially introduced as a locum, leaving a month later. However the character was not introduced as a regular until 2002, when Rhona was reintroduced in June of that year where she stayed in the village until December 2002. In reality, Rhona left the village after [[Marlon Dingle|Marlon's]] love interest, [[Tricia Dingle|Tricia]] returned to the village and she was no longer needed at the vets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.emmerdale.org/emmerdale/profiles/Rhona.htm|title=Emmerdale's Rhona Goskirk|publisher=Emmerdale Org|author=Emmerdale Org|date=15 September 2003|accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rhona was reintroduced by series producer Gavin Blyth in 2010 as a locum once again, with Zoe Henry reprising the role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/scoop/a203037/zoe-henry-returns-to-emmerdale.html|title=Zoe Henry returns to 'Emmerdale'|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|author=Green, Kris|date=13 February 2010|accessdate=2010-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Storylines==
===2001–02===
Rhona first appeared in the village in September 2001 as a locum, helping [[Paddy Kirk|Paddy]] and covering for [[Zoe Tate|Zoe]], whilst she was away on holiday. She and [[Marlon Dingle|Marlon]]  fell for each other and they began dating as his ex-girlfriend, Tricia, had left him and the village. However, Tricia returned and Rhona left not long after, before Zoe returned.

In June 2002, Rhona returned to cover for Zoe when she needed time off due to her mental illness and Paddy needed another vet. She and Marlon soon resumed their relationship and began spending time together again, realising they had more in common than they first thought, including [[Laurel and Hardy]] films and design. When Tricia found out that Rhona had returned, she was very upset but Rhona left again in December 2002.

===2010—===
Rhona returned in March, again as a locum. This time, she covered for [[Paddy Kirk|Paddy]], after he was beaten up by surrogate son [[Aaron Livesy|Aaron]]. Rhona served as the locum for a few weeks whilst Paddy recovered but soon clashed with receptionist, [[Pearl Ladderbanks|Pearl]], due to Pearl's protecting Paddy. 

She began staying at The Grange B&amp;B. It was later revealed that between 2002-2010, Rhona married but divorced, realising that he was not the right person for her. Rhona left after fulfilling her contract but returned when Paddy needed time off to look after Aaron, following his suicide attempt. She planned to stay in the village in a more permanent position, moving in with [[Andy Sugden]] and [[Ryan Lamb]] but didn't stay long, due to her romance with [[Marlon Dingle]]. She moved in with him, [[Bob Hope]] and [[Lizzie Lakely]] but moved out again after ending things with Marlon as she realised she had fallen in love with Paddy. She confided in [[Laurel Thomas]] that her relationship with Paddy had become difficult and was seriously considering leaving the village so Laurel told Paddy to sort things out with her before she left.

Rhona found out that she is pregnant with Marlon's baby which has Down's sydrome. She considers having a termination but changes her mind after a conversation with [[Hazel Rhodes]] opens her eyes. 

On 1st February, she attends her scan with Paddy and Marlon. When she goes in, the [[sonographer]] is an old school friend of hers, [[Stephanie Ray]], and it is revealed that Rhona was very rebellious when she was at school. She tries to set Marlon and Stephanie up on a date but he hated her.

Marlon decided that they should try pregnancy yoga and whilst there, she decided to go to the next class alone, because Marlon had been very irritating. She goes to the foetal heart scan in March and is told everything is fine but she worries herself again. She and the boys visit a Downs Syndrome support group where she feels more comfortable talking to people in her situation. 

In April, she and Paddy decide that it would be best to tell Aaron about the baby's condition and are touched by his reaction.
She experiences [[Braxton Hicks]] Contractions twice before she goes into labour in the Woolpack on 30th May 2011 after being knocked over during a scuffle between Aaron Livesy and Adam Barton. On 31st May she gives birth to a boy who is named Leo.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Emmerdale}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Goskirk, Rhona}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional veterinarians]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2001]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
