<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7920195" ns="0" title="List of students at South Park Elementary"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">Several '''student''' characters attend the fictional school '''South Park Elementary''' in the animated television show ''[[South Park]]''. The school is one of the most prominent settings on the show, the [[narrative]] of which revolves mostly around the students. 

[[File:SPClass.jpg|right|thumb|500px|The class from ''[[South Park]]''. Depicted in this image are, from left to right, [[#Timmy|Timmy]], [[#Others|Red]], [[Butters Stotch|Butters]], [[#Bradley|Bradley]] (front), [[#Tweek Tweak|Tweek]] (back), [[#Clyde Donovan|Clyde]], [[Eric Cartman|Cartman]], [[#Others|Kevin]] (front), [[#Token Black|Token]] (back), Annie, [[Kyle Broflovski|Kyle]], [[#Bebe Stevens|Bebe]] (front), [[#Pip Pirrup|Pip]] (back), [[Kenny McCormick|Kenny]], [[Stan Marsh|Stan]], [[#Francis|Francis]] (front), [[#Craig Tucker|Craig]] (back) and [[#Wendy Testaburger|Wendy]]. Not pictured: [[#Jimmy Valmer|Jimmy]]]].

==Overview== 

While a few characters from varying grades have been depicted in recurring minor roles, the students in the [[fourth grade]]—including central characters [[Stan Marsh]], [[Kyle Broflovski]], [[Kenny McCormick]], [[Eric Cartman]], and [[Butters Stotch]]—receive the primary focus of the series. The fourth grade class is taught throughout most of the series by [[Herbert Garrison|Mr. Garrison]], with a hiatus between seasons 4 and 6 when he is replaced by [[Ms. Choksondik]]. These students also attended class under Mr. Garrison during their previous time as third graders during ''South Park''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; first three-and-a-half seasons.

In tradition with the show's [[Cutout animation|animation style]], all characters listed below are composed of simple geometrical shapes and bright colors.&lt;ref name=&quot;method&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = Matt Cheplic | title = 'As Crappy As Possible': The Method Behind the Madness of South Park | publisher = [[Penton Media]] | date = 1998-05-01 | url = http://digitalcontentproducer.com/mag/video_crappy_possible_method/ | accessdate = 2009-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;avr&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = Abbie Bernstein| title = South Park – Volume 2 | publisher = AVRev.com| date = 1998-10-27| url = http://www.avrev.com/dvd-movie-disc-reviews/tv-shows/south-park-volume-2.html| accessdate = 2008-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ever since the show's second episode, &quot;[[Weight Gain 4000]]&quot; ([[South Park (season 1)|season one]], 1997), all characters on ''South Park'' have been animated with computer software, though they are portrayed to give the impression that the show still utilizes the method of animating [[construction paper]] composition cutouts through the use of [[stop motion]], which was the technique used in creating the show's first episode, &quot;[[Cartman Gets an Anal Probe]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;method&quot;/&gt;

In addition to the main characters, other students below will sometimes give a brief monologue as a means of expressing the lessons they have attained during the course of an episode. Most of the characters are foul-mouthed as a means for series creators [[Trey Parker]] and [[Matt Stone]] to display how they claim young children really talk when they are alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;avr&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;abc4&quot;&gt;{{cite web| author=Jake Trapper and Dan Morris| title=Secrets of 'South Park'| publisher=[[ABC News]]| date=2006-09-22| url=http://abcnews.go.com/Nightline/Entertainment/Story?id=2479197&amp;page=4| accessdate=2009-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the male students are amused by bodily functions and [[toilet humor]],&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = Jeffrey Ressner and James Collins| title = Gross And Grosser | work = [[Time (magazine)|Time]] | date = 1998-03-23 | url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,988028,00.html | accessdate = 2009-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and their favorite television personalities are [[Terrance and Phillip]], a [[Canada|Canadian]] duo whose comedy routines on their [[Show-within-a-show|show-within-the-show]] revolve substantially around fart jokes. In response to the focus on elements of satire in ''South Park'', Parker has said that the main goal of the show is to portray the students as &quot;kids just being kids&quot; as a means of accurately showcasing &quot;what it's like to be in [elementary school] in America&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rocky&quot;&gt;{{cite news| author = Saunders| title = At 10, 'South Park' still bites| work = [[Rocky Mountain News]]| date = 2006-07-17| url = http://www.rockymountainnews.com/drmn/spotlight_columnists/article/0,2777,DRMN_23962_4848796,00.html| accessdate = 2009-05-03}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Main class ==
===Bebe Stevens===
'''Bebe Stevens''' is [[Wendy Testaburger]]'s best friend and has often been seen keeping company with fellow female classmates throughout the duration of the series. She has frizzy blonde hair and wears a red coat. Bebe first prominently appears in the [[South Park (season 1)|season 1]] episode &quot;[[Weight Gain 4000]]&quot;, where she narrates a play for [[Kathie Lee Gifford]]'s visit to South Park and the play was directed by [[Mr Garrison]]. In the [[South Park (season 2)|season 2]] episode &quot;[[Clubhouses (South Park)|Clubhouses]]&quot;, she develops a crush on [[Kyle Broflovski]] and uses a game of [[Truth or Dare]] as an excuse to kiss him. She plays a major role in the episode &quot;[[Bebe's Boobs Destroy Society]]&quot;, when the boys' attraction to her increases due to her newly developing breasts. When the attention became unwanted, she professes her wish to have others appreciate her for her aspirations and intelligence instead. She later plays a large role in the [[South Park (season 11)|season 11]] episode &quot;[[The List (South Park)|The List]]&quot;, where she abuses her powers within the &quot;list committee&quot; to change the list so that [[#Clyde Donovan|Clyde]] is the cutest boy, so that she can date him for free shoes. She is arrested after a brawl with Wendy and accidentally shooting Kenny. Bebe is voiced by ''South Park'' supervising producer [[Jennifer Howell]] and [[Mary Kay Bergman]] in &quot;[[Weight Gain 4000]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;

===Butters Stotch===
{{Main|Butters Stotch}}
'''Leopold &quot;Butters&quot; Stotch''' is cheerful, naïve, optimistic, and more passive than the show's other child characters, and can become increasingly anxious, especially when faced with the likelihood of punishment by his parents. He is often treated poorly by other characters and put in painful or humiliating situations. As a result of his increasing popularity with the show's staff and fans, Butters was given a more prominent role beginning with the show's [[South Park (season 5)|fifth season]] (2001). He is voiced by Matt Stone.&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;

===Clyde Donovan===
'''Clyde Donovan''' (originally '''Clyde Goodman''' and briefly '''Clyde Harris''') maintains a friendship with the show's main characters and is among the most often-seen of the boys' extended group, playing small roles in several episodes. He is also known for his constant crying at &quot;the drop of the hat&quot;. He made his first prominent appearance in the [[South Park (season 3)|season 3 (1999)]] episode &quot;[[Tweek vs. Craig]]&quot; where he told everyone that both Tweek and Craig wussed out and went home instead of fighting each other. In the [[South Park (season 4)|season 4 (2000)]] episode &quot;[[Cartman's Silly Hate Crime 2000]]&quot; as &quot;the second fattest kid&quot; in class besides Cartman, and is chosen to replace him in the sled race.  The [[South Park (season 11)|season 11 (2007)]] episode &quot;[[Lice Capades]]&quot; focuses heavily on Clyde and a group of [[Anthropomorphism|anthropomorphic]] [[lice]], who are portrayed as living in a civilized society on Clyde's head. Clyde was so embarrassed when a girl at the doctors office asked what he was going in for he said he had [[AIDS]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.statehornet.com/media/storage/paper1146/news/2007/03/23/Features/Head-Lice.Outbreak.On.south.Park-2789745.shtml|title=Head lice outbreak on 'South Park'|date=2007-03-27|publisher=media.www.statehornet.com|accessdate=2009-05-16|last=Van Meter|first=Brandon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clyde is also featured prominently in the episode &quot;[[The List (South Park)|The List]]&quot;, where the girls vote him the cutest boy in class (although this list is later revealed to be false).  Clyde also has a major appearance in the three part story arc [[Coon 2: Hindsight]], [[Mysterion Rises]] and [[Coon vs. Coon and Friends]] appearing as his alter-ego Mosquito. His [[nasal voice]] is provided by Trey Parker.&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;
It is revealed in the episode [[Crack Baby Athletic Association]] that Clyde is part Dutch.  In the episode [[Mystery of the Urinal Deuce]], it is revealed that Clyde had a colostomy at the age of 5.

===Craig Tucker===
'''Craig Tucker''', commonly characterized by his blue [[chullo]] hat and [[nasal]], monotone voice, is one of the more prominent members of the children's classroom. Cartman once claimed that Craig was the &quot;biggest troublemaker in [their] class&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tweek&quot;/&gt; and parents of his classmates have cited him as a &quot;bad influence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pandemic&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=[[Pandemic (South Park)|Pandemic]] |url= |series= [[South Park]] |credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]] (writer) |station= [[Comedy Central]]|airdate=2009-10-22 |season=12 |number=177 |minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In a [[running gag]] during the show's earlier seasons, [[establishing shot]]s of [[Mr. Mackey]]'s office would feature Craig waiting outside.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=1695 |title=FAQ Archives: Who is that kid who always sit in front of Mr. Mackeys office who flips people off? | accessdate=2009-05-13 |date=2001-06-27 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; Craig has a habit of giving people [[finger (gesture)|the finger]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/81|title=Craig|accessdate=2008-10-13 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; a trait the show's official website attributes to his learning the behavior from his family, all of whom frequently use the gesture as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tweek&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=[[Tweek vs. Craig]] |url= |series= [[South Park]] |credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]], [[Matt Stone|Stone, Matt]] and [[Pam Brady|Brady, Pam]] (writers) |station= [[Comedy Central]]|airdate=1999-06-23 |season=3 |number=36 |minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=4737|title=FAQ – South Park Studios|publisher=www.southparkstudios.com|accessdate=2009-05-16|last=|first=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This trait was last seen in the [[South Park (season 6)|Season 6 (2002)]] episode &quot;[[Fun with Veal]]&quot;.

Craig dislikes the [[List of characters in South Park#Main characters|four main characters]] and rivals them in several episodes. Craig is a [[Pragmatism|pragmatist]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=O'Neal |first=Sean |title=South Park: Season 13: Episode 5: &quot;Fishsticks&quot; |work=[[The A.V. Club]] |date=2009-04-08 |url=http://www.avclub.com/articles/fishsticks,26396/ |accessdate=2009-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has no wish of being involved in any extraordinary adventures the other main characters on the show customarily experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;411maniaPandemic2&quot;/&gt; In the [[South Park (season 12)|season 12]] (2008) episodes &quot;[[Pandemic (South Park)|Pandemic]]&quot; and &quot;[[Pandemic 2 - The Startling]]&quot;, Craig repeatedly castigates the main characters' propensity to have a pursued activity or idea disproportionately backfire. Despite his hatred for adventure, he plays a crucial role in these two episodes, saving the world from guinea animals, but is shown even after doing so unintentionally to care little.&lt;ref name=&quot;411maniaPandemic2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.411mania.com/movies/dvd_reviews/89107/South-Park-10.29.08:-Pandemic-2---The-Startling.htm |title=South Park 10.29.08: Pandemic 2 – The Startling |accessdate=2008-10-29 |author=Perry, DC |date=2008-11-02 |work=411mania.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNPandemic&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=IGN: Pandemic Review |url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/922/922947p1.html |author=Fickett, Travis |publisher=IGN |date=2008-10-23 |accessdate=2008-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Craig is one of the most often-used of the boys' extended group, often providing lines in group scenes with the other children. He is voiced by series co-creator Matt Stone.

===Eric Cartman===
{{Main|Eric Cartman}} 

One of the show's four main characters and one of the most popular and iconic characters, '''Eric Cartman''' is obese, obnoxious, racist, and considerably sociopathic.  Most other students are alienated by Cartman's insensitive, often [[misogynistic]], and [[bigot]]ed behavior, though they are occasionally influenced by his obtrusive, manipulative, and propagandist antics. While Cartman has few if any attachments towards people, he exhibits a softhearted fondness for cats as seen in the episode &quot;[[Major Boobage]]&quot;. He is voiced by Trey Parker.&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;

=== Jimmy Valmer ===
'''Jimmy Valmer''' (formerly '''Jimmy Swanson''' and sometimes spelled '''Vulmer'''), voiced by Trey Parker, is physically handicapped, requiring crutches in order to walk. Hampered by his withering legs, Jimmy prefers to be called &quot;handi-capable&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Anderson | first = Brian C. | title = We're Not Losing the Culture Wars Anymore | url = http://www.city-journal.org/html/13_4_were_not_losing.html | date = Autumn 2003 | accessdate = 2008-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/98 |title=Jimmy |accessdate=2008-11-02 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jimmy is able to speak coherently, though his speech is largely affected by his [[stuttering]] and his tendency to end some of his sentences with &quot;...very much&quot;. He aspires to be a stand-up comedian, and is often featured performing his routines. His catchphrase during his routines is &quot;Wow, what a great audience!&quot;

Jimmy first appears in the [[South Park (season 5)|season five]] (2001) episode &quot;[[Cripple Fight]]&quot;, in which he moves to South Park from a neighboring town and antagonizes [[#Timmy|Timmy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;/&gt; Parker and Stone initially intended for this to be Jimmy's only appearance, but decided to include the character in subsequent episodes.&lt;ref name=&quot;cripplefightcomm&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Trey Parker, Matt Stone|date=2003|title=&quot;South Park&quot; – The Complete Fifth Season |medium=DVD|publisher=Comedy Central}} Mini-commentary for episode &quot;Cripple Fight&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Now portrayed as a South Park resident, student, and good friend of Timmy, Jimmy has been a recurring character ever since. Jimmy's parents had made fun of handicapped children in high school, and believe that Jimmy's disability is a punishment from God. The [[South Park (season 8)|season eight]] (2004) episode &quot;[[Up the Down Steroid]]&quot; ends with Jimmy addressing the issue of [[anabolic steroid]] use in athletic competitions, declaring it as &quot;cheating&quot; while suggesting that professional athletes who use steroids voluntarily reject the accolades and records attributed to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://media.www.dailypennsylvanian.com/media/storage/paper882/news/2004/07/22/Sports/David.Kuhn.Steroids.Sour.Fun.Of.Olympics-2151098.shtml| title=Steroids sour fun of Olympics| date=2004-07-22| publisher=media.www.dailypennsylvanian.com| accessdate=2009-05-16| last=Kuhn| first=David}}&lt;/ref&gt; Melanie McFarland of the ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' describes Jimmy and Timmy's capabilities and portrayal in the show as Parker and Stone declaring their opposition to political correctness as social restriction.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcfarland&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.seattlepi.com/tv/287052_southpark02.html| title=Oh my God, 'South Park' killed a decade!| date=2006-09-30| publisher=www.seattlepi.com| accessdate=2009-05-16| last=McFarland| first=Melanie}}&lt;/ref&gt; When praising the show for both its depiction of Jimmy and Timmy and its coverage of disability-related issues, ''[[The Seattle Times]]'' columnist Jeff Shannon, a [[Quadriplegia|quadriplegic]], describes Jimmy and Timmy as &quot;goodwill ambassadors&quot;.&lt;ref name=shannon&gt;{{cite web| url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/entertainment/2002648630_timmy28.html| title=The Seattle Times: Arts &amp; Entertainment: Timmy of &quot;South Park&quot; challenges viewers' attitudes about people with disabilities| date=2005-11-28 | publisher=seattletimes.nwsource.com| accessdate=2009-05-16| last=Shannon| first=Jeff}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kenny McCormick===
{{Main|Kenny McCormick}}

'''Kenny McCormick''' comes from one of the poorest families in town, and almost always wear a parka so that the hood covers most of his face and muffles his speech. He often shows a precocious interest in and knowledge of sex, unlike his friends, often providing Stan, Kyle and Cartman with a graphic (albeit muffled) definition of such confusing sexual terminology as &quot;dildo&quot; and &quot;fingerbang&quot;. As a [[running gag]], he dies in most episodes of the first five seasons before returning in the next. This gag has become occasional following Kenny's absence through season 6, and is explained in the [[South Park (season 14)|season 14]] (2010) episode &quot;[[Coon vs. Coon and Friends]]&quot; as resulting from his parents dabbling in the [[Cult of Cthulhu]] around the time of his conception. He is voiced by Matt Stone.&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;

===Kyle Broflovski===
{{Main|Kyle Broflovski}}
'''Kyle Broflovski''' is one of the main four characters in the show and stars and co-stars in many episodes.  Kyle is distinctive as one of the few [[Jewish]] children on the show, and because of this, he often feels like an outsider amongst his friends and classmates. Kyle is also the child who clashes the most often with Cartman.  Kyle is both voiced by and based on Matt Stone.&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;

===Pip Pirrup===
'''Phillip &quot;Pip&quot; Pirrup''', voiced by [[Matt Stone]],&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt; was featured mostly during the first few seasons of the series. He was later relegated to being a background character after his role in the show was replaced by [[Butters Stotch|Butters]]. Pip is originally from [[England]], and shares his name with the main protagonist of the [[Charles Dickens]] novel ''[[Great Expectations]]''. Wearing a bow tie and [[flat cap]], he was often teased by his fellow classmates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/info.php?character_id=70|title=Pip|accessdate=2008-11-02 |work=South Park Studios}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; While largely passive, the only thing that would drive him to anger is when fellow students mistake him for being [[French people|French]]. The show's official website has noted that this is in reference to the animosity shared between some natives of Britain and France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=38210|title=FAQ – South Park Studios|publisher=www.southparkstudios.com|accessdate=2009-05-16|last=|first=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar gag is seen in ''[[South Park: Bigger, Longer, and Uncut]]'', in which The Mole, a young French boy, is called &quot;British&quot; by Cartman. Pip is the central figure of an [[Pip (South Park)|eponymous episode]] during the show's [[South Park (season 4)|fourth season]]. The episode, which does not feature any of the show's other characters, was a comedic retelling of ''[[Great Expectations]]'', with Pip assuming the role of his character's namesake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Pip |url=http://tv.nytimes.com/episode/70374/South-Park/overview |work=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=2009-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/19/arts/television-radio-a-study-guide-for-south-park.html?pagewanted=2| title=A Study Guide for 'South Park'| date=2000-11-19 | publisher=www.nytimes.com| accessdate=2009-05-16| last=Zeidner| first=Lisa}}&lt;/ref&gt; After this titular episode, Pip became a background character with only two further speaking appearances—as a candidate for the new fourth boy in &quot;[[Professor Chaos]]&quot; and then being absent for eight years until another brief appearance in &quot;[[201 (South Park)|201]]&quot; to beg the [[Mecha-Streisand]] to spare South Park, but it responds by stepping on him, killing him.

===Stan Marsh===
{{Main|Stan Marsh}}
'''Stan Marsh''' is the most level-headed and convivial of the four boys. Stan is generally kind, honest, smart, well-meaning, assertive, and often shares with his best friend [[#Kyle Broflovski|Kyle]] a leadership role as the main [[protagonist]] of the show. Stan is portrayed as the [[everyman]] among the show's four central characters. Stan is both voiced by and based on Trey Parker.&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;/&gt;

=== Timmy Burch ===
'''Timmy Burch''' is a mentally  and physically handicapped boy who uses a motorized wheelchair. Voiced by [[Trey Parker]],&lt;ref name=&quot;voices2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=|title=FAQ Archives: Who does the voices for the characters on South Park?|accessdate=2011-01-16 |date=2002-04-23 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; he is based on an elementary school acquaintance of ''South Park'' art director [[Adrien Beard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/behind/interviews.php?interview=27|title=An interview with Adrien Beard|work=South Park Studios}} Accessed on Feb. 16, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Timmy's exact condition has never been specified in the show, though ''South Park''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; official website describes it as &quot;a strange combination of [[palsy]] and [[Tourette syndrome|Tourette's]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;condition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=5250|title=FAQ}}South Park Studios. Accessed on Nov. 14, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Timmy's vocabulary is mostly limited to the enthusiastic shouting of his own name which could be [[aphasia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;shannon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pe&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author =Todd Vanderwerff| title = South Park: The Best of the Bleeping Best| work = [[The Press-Enterprise]]| date = 2007-08-13| url = http://www.pe.com/lifestyles/stories/PE_Fea_Local_D_southparkten813.5e596d.html| accessdate = 2009-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;timmy!&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=837 |title=FAQ Archives: Has Timmy ever said anything but &quot;Timmy&quot; or &quot;Gobbles.&quot;|accessdate=2008-11-03 |date=2001-05-21 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Timmy first appears as a minor character in the [[South Park (season 4)|season four]] (2000) episode &quot;[[The Tooth Fairy Tats 2000]]&quot;. Parker and Stone had to push hard for the inclusion of the character, as [[Comedy Central]] was originally reluctant to allow the show to feature a character with a cognitive disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = 40 Questions| publisher = southparkstudios.com | date = 4 October 2001 | url = http://treyparker.info/archives_spstudios.htm| accessdate = 2009-01-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;toothfairycomm&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Trey Parker, Matt Stone|date=2002|title=&quot;South Park&quot; – The Complete Fourth Season |medium=DVD|publisher=Comedy Central}} Mini-commentary for episode &quot;The Tooth Fairy Tats 2000&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The duo asserted their intention of portraying other children as treating him as an equal,&lt;ref name=&quot;toothfairycomm&quot;/&gt; while stressing the importance of both including a mentally retarded character who is &quot;happy to be [himself]&quot;, and representing him &quot;as part of the gang and not as the subject of cruel schoolyard humor&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.tvguide.com/news/south-park-adds-41763.aspx| title=South Park Adds Disabled Character| date=2000-04-06| publisher=tvguide.com| accessdate=2009-05-16| last=Brown| first=Rich}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two weeks after his debut, Timmy was a central figure in the episode &quot;[[Timmy 2000]]&quot;, where doctors and school faculty erroneously attribute his behavior to [[Attention Deficit Disorder|ADD]] in the show's condemnation of the rampant diagnosis of the disorder.&lt;ref name=shannon/&gt; 

Timmy quickly became a fan favorite, and was once voted &quot;The Greatest Disabled TV Character&quot; in a poll conducted by a [[BBC]]-sponsored [[webzine]] named ''Ouch!'', where he was more popular among disabled voters than among non-disabled voters.&lt;ref name=&quot;shannon&quot;/&gt; [[IGN]] ranked Timmy second in a list of the &quot;Top 10 ''South Park'' Peripheral Characters&quot;, stating that &quot;''South Park'''s most controversial character may be one of the funniest and most enduring&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN3&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/770/770593p3.html |title=Top 10 South Park Peripheral Characters |accessdate= 2008-11-24 |last=Iverson |first=Dan |coauthors=Zoromski, Brian |date=2007-03-06 |work=[[IGN]] |publisher=[[IGN Entertainment]] |page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parker noted that soon after Timmy debuted, fans he encountered began mimicking the character's exclamation of &quot;Timmy!&quot; as opposed to their earlier habits of impersonating Cartman and repeating the show's other popular catchphrases.&lt;ref name=&quot;toothfairycomm&quot;/&gt; When the handicapped [[#Jimmy Vulmer|Jimmy]] was introduced in the [[South Park (season 5)|season five]] (2001) episode &quot;[[Cripple Fight]]&quot;, Timmy becomes jealous of Jimmy's newfound popularity with the main characters, and the two later got into a violent brawl in a parking lot. The two make amends, and are depicted as good friends in subsequent episodes.

Melanie McFarland of the ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' describes Jimmy and Timmy's capabilities and portrayal in the show as Parker and Stone declaring their opposition to political correctness as social restriction.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcfarland&quot;/&gt; When praising the show for both its depiction of Jimmy and Timmy and its coverage of disability-related issues, ''[[The Seattle Times]]'' columnist Jeff Shannon, a [[Quadriplegia|quadriplegic]], describes Jimmy and Timmy as &quot;goodwill ambassadors&quot;, while commenting that &quot;Timmy appears, at first glance, to uphold the condescending disability stereotypes that are gradually fading from mainstream entertainment. But like everything else in 'South Park,' he's actually challenging preconceptions, toppling taboos and weaving his singularity into the fabric of the show&quot;.&lt;ref name=shannon/&gt;

=== Token Black ===
{{Redirect|Token Black|the general use of a [[black people|black]] token character|Tokenism}}
'''Token Black''' (previously '''Williams''') is the only [[black people|black]] child in ''South Park''.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;/&gt; His name is a reference to [[tokenism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Asadullah, Ali | title = Contemporary Cartoon Conjures Racist Past | publisher = IslamOnline.net| date = 2001-11-15| url = http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?c=Article_C&amp;cid=1158658390218&amp;pagename=Zone-English-ArtCulture%2FACELayout| accessdate = 2008-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tokenism&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = McWhorter, John H. | title = RACE; Black Isn't a Personality Type (abstract) | work = [[Los Angeles Times]] | date = 2002-05-12| url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/119226020.html?dids=119226020:119226020&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=May+12%2C+2002&amp;author=JOHN+H.+McWHORTER&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;desc=RACE%3B+Black+Isn't+a+Personality+Type&amp;pqatl=google | accessdate = 2008-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name has been interpreted as an example of the anti-[[political correctness]] attitude of ''South Park''&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson&quot;/&gt; and as an implication that the tokenism phenomenon is outmoded enough to be a laughing matter.&lt;ref name=&quot;tokenism&quot;/&gt; Despite the role that his name implies, Token will sometimes play a significant part in an episode, and has been a recurring character since his first major role in the [[South Park (season 4)|season four]] (2000) episode &quot;[[Cartman's Silly Hate Crime 2000]]&quot;. His next came in the [[South Park (season 5)|season five]] (2001) episode &quot;[[Here Comes the Neighborhood]]&quot;, where he is picked on for being rich. He invites several other wealthy families to move to South Park (who all happen to be black), leading the townspeople to refer to them as &quot;richers&quot;. 

Episodes in which he plays a major role often address ethnicity-related topics. In &quot;[[Cartman's Silly Hate Crime 2000]]&quot;, he declares [[Hate crime laws in the United States|hate crime legislation]] to be &quot;a savage hypocrisy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dummocrats.com/archives/000097.html |title=Dummocrats: Listen Up: John McCain is a Republican (you fools) |date=2004-05-12 |publisher=www.dummocrats.com |accessdate=2009-05-16 |last=
|first=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[South Park (season 11)|season 11]] (2007) episode &quot;[[With Apologies to Jesse Jackson]]&quot;, Stan is perplexed by Token's rebuffs of his attempts to make amends with Token after [[Randy and Sharon Marsh|Stan's father]] reluctantly exclaimed &quot;niggers&quot; when attempting to solve a puzzle as a contestant during a live taping of ''[[Wheel of Fortune (U.S. game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]''. When Stan has an epiphany, he tells Token &quot;I've been trying to say that I understand how you feel, but I'll never understand. I'll never really get how it feels for a black person to [hear] somebody use the N-word&quot;, to which Token accepts Stan's apology by saying &quot;Now you get it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;boston&quot;&gt;{{cite news| author = Vanessa E. Jones | title = No offense, but ...| publisher = The Boston Globe | date = 2008-01-29| url = http://www.boston.com/lifestyle/articles/2008/01/29/no_offense_but_/ | accessdate = 2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Parker and Stone had originally taken turns providing their voices for the few lines Token had as a minor character.&lt;ref name=&quot;neighborhoodcomm&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Trey Parker, Matt Stone|date=2003|title=&quot;South Park&quot; – The Complete Fifth Season |medium=DVD|publisher=Comedy Central}} Mini-commentary for episode &quot;Here Comes The Neighborhood&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Token is now voiced by ''South Park'' art director and co-producer [[Adrien Beard]].&lt;ref name=&quot;voices&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=450 |title=FAQ Archives: Who does the voices of Clyde and Token? And who does most of the female voices on the show?|accessdate=2008-10-12 |date=2001-04-30 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; When trying to find a new voice actor for Token during production of &quot;Cartman's Silly Hate Crime 2000&quot;, Parker said he recruited Beard &quot;because he was the only black guy we had in our building at the time&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;hatecrimecomm&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Trey Parker, Matt Stone|date=2003|title=&quot;South Park&quot; – The Complete Fifth Season |medium=DVD|publisher=Comedy Central}} Mini-commentary for episode &quot;Cartman's Silly Hate Crime 2000&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Tweek Tweak ===
'''Tweek Tweak''' is a boy characterized by his [[hyperactivity]], [[paranoia]] and [[anxiety]],&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/770/770593p1.html |title=Top 10 South Park Peripheral Characters |accessdate= 2008-11-21 |last=Iverson |first=Dan |coauthors=Zoromski, Brian |date=2007-03-06 |work=[[IGN]] |publisher=IGN Entertainment |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to his mass consumption of [[coffee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudiohttp://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special:UserLogout&amp;returnto=List_of_students_at_South_Park_Elementary&amp;returntoquery=action%3Dedit%26section%3D16s.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=9552 |title=FAQ Archives: Is &quot;Tweek&quot; his first name or his last name?|accessdate=2008-11-14 |date=2002-08-22 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; His strained voice is provided by Stone,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=28|title=FAQ Archives: Who does the voice of Tweek? Because just hearing his voice kind of makes me wonder how it effects the throat.|accessdate=2008-11-24 |date=2001-04-18 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he tends to scream, &quot;Oh, Jesus, dude!&quot;, &quot;GAH!&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN1&quot;/&gt; and &quot;Too much pressure!&quot;. His name is taken from a slang term referring to recreational users of [[methamphetamine]], as well as hyperactive or dysfunctional people in general.{{citation needed|date=April 2010}}

While [[List of South Park families#The Tweeks|Tweek's parents]]—who run a coffee shop—attribute his hyperactivity to [[ADHD predominantly inattentive]], it is actually a result of the two frequently giving Tweek coffee to &quot;calm him down.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;condition&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=6124 |title=FAQ Archives: What's Wrong with Tweek?|accessdate=2008-11-14 |date=2002-01-29 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has the effect of increasing his [[caffeine]] levels and worsening his mental state.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN1&quot;/&gt; As a result, Tweek is constantly shaking or twitching and is always depicted with spiky, disheveled blond hair and an incorrectly buttoned shirt. 

Tweek is introduced in the [[South Park (season 2)|season two]] (1998) episode &quot;[[Gnomes (South Park episode)|Gnomes]]&quot;, and is as prominent as one of the four main characters throughout the middle portion of the [[South Park (season 6)|sixth season]] (2002). The character Kenny is [[Kenny's deaths|absent during the majority of the season]], which allowed the show's creators and writing staff an opportunity to provide larger roles for both Tweek and Butters,&lt;ref name=&quot;page2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = Page 2 Staff| title = Matt Stone| publisher = [[ESPN]] | date = 2002-03-13| url = http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/print?id=1350858&amp;type=page2Story | accessdate = 2009-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  both of whom were growing more popular with both the viewers and staff of the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;kennydiescomm&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Trey Parker, Matt Stone|date=2003|title=&quot;South Park&quot; – The Complete Fifth Season |format=Mini-commentary for episode &quot;Kenny Dies&quot;|medium=DVD|publisher=Comedy Central}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny ultimately returns in the season finale &quot;[[Red Sleigh Down]]&quot;, and though Butters has continued as a significant presence, Tweek has remained in the background since.

===Wendy Testaburger===
'''Wendy Testaburger''' is the show's most prominent female student, and the show's main source of perspective in that regard. Her best friend is [[#Bebe Stevens|Bebe Stevens]], and her boyfriend is [[#Stan Marsh|Stan]], though their relationship as such has received less focus in the show's later seasons. Wendy has previously been voiced by [[Karri Turner]] (in the unaired pilot), [[Mary Kay Bergman]], [[Mona Marshall]], [[Eliza Schneider]], and is currently voiced by [[April Stewart]]. Wendy's character is reportedly based on Liane Adamo, a former fiancée of series co-creator [[Trey Parker]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.spscriptorium.com/SPBios/TheKids.htm |title=The Children  |accessdate=2008-10-10 |work=[http://www.spscriptorium.com/ South Park Scriptorium]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fellow co-creator [[Matt Stone]] has also cited the name of Wendy Westiberg, the wife of an old friend from his childhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people=Trey Parker, Matt Stone|date=2003|title=South Park: The Complete First Season: &quot;Weight Gain 4000&quot;|format=Audio commentary |medium=CD|publisher=Comedy Central}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wears a pink beret and a purple coat. She has long black hair with uneven bangs. Wendy made her first appearance unnamed, but clearly recognizable, in &quot;[[The Spirit of Christmas (short film)|The Spirit of Christmas]]&quot;. 

Like her boyfriend Stan, Wendy is mature for her age, critical of popular trends, moral and intellectual. She rallies for liberal causes in several episodes, such as [[Breast Cancer]] and the suffering of [[Bottlenose Dolphins]], often arguing with [[Eric Cartman]] who calls her a &quot;bitch&quot; or &quot;ho&quot; in response. Although the two generally only argue, he pushes her to the limit in the [[South Park (season 12)|Season 12 (2008)]] episode &quot;[[Breast Cancer Show Ever]]&quot; where in the two engage in a fight on the playground. Despite these differences, in the episode [[Chef Goes Nanners]], Wendy and Cartman work together to change South Park's flag. During this time, the two have what Bebe calls [[sexual tension]]. Towards the end of the episode, Wendy kisses Cartman, to which Stan replies by staring at the two with mouth agape.

Wendy is known to be protective of her relationship with Stan. In the [[South Park (season 1)|Season 1 (1997)]] episode &quot;[[Tom's Rhinoplasty]]&quot; when Stan, along with the other boys, falls in love with an attractive substitute teacher, with Wendy accusing her of stealing Stan from her, eventually formulating a complex plan to get her thrown into the [[Sun]]. She also sometimes displays jealousy – in the [[South Park (season 6)|Season 6 (2002)]] episode &quot;[[Bebe's Boobs Destroy Society]]&quot;, her best friend, Bebe Stevens, receives more attention than she does because of Bebe's developing breasts. Wendy then gets breast implants, but the boys end up ridiculing her after only just realizing the control Bebe's breasts had on them. This behavior is somewhat contradicted by episodes such as &quot;[[Stupid Spoiled Whore Video Playset]]&quot; and &quot;[[Dances with Smurfs]]&quot; where she is more concerned with principles than trends and attention

Since she got back with Stan, Wendy's role briefly expanded – she and Stan partner up in &quot;[[Super Fun Time]]&quot;, she beats Cartman up in &quot;Breast Cancer Show Ever&quot; and a plotline in the episode &quot;[[Elementary School Musical (South Park)|Elementary School Musical]]&quot; shows Stan suspecting that Wendy may leave him for a popular kid called Bridon. Their relationship appears to have gotten somewhat stronger since their previous one, as the two are much more affectionate towards one another. On the other hand, Stan seems to have gotten more used to her and her affections, having not thrown up on her outside of &quot;[[The List (South Park)|The List]]&quot; episode, since the movie (and outside of that, the second season). In fact, Wendy was able to kiss Stan on the cheek (in the episode [[Elementary School Musical (South Park)|Elementary School Musical]]) without his normal reaction of vomiting.

Wendy was voted student council president, something first noted in &quot;[[Bebe's Boobs Destroy Society]]&quot; and re-addressed seven seasons later in &quot;[[Dances with Smurfs]]&quot;, when Cartman becomes the morning announcer and starts spreading defaming comments about her—most notably her supposed [[genocide]] of the [[Smurfs]]. In response to the allegations, Wendy becomes a guest on Cartman's morning show and manipulates his own story of the Smurf holocaust before announcing her resignation and electing him as the new school council president, effectively relieving him of his morning announcement job. Throughout the episode, Stan solidly defends her. 

Wendy is very prominent in the show's earlier seasons, usually quarreling with [[Eric Cartman]] or reinforcing her relationship with [[Stan Marsh]]. She speaks in several episodes (especially in the first season) and is often chosen to help the boys out over her classmates. Over the course of the fifth season, Wendy's role diminished greatly and she increasingly becomes just &quot;one of the girls&quot;, and she has only one minor role in Season Six. This culminates in her breakup with Stan for Token Black in &quot;[[Raisins (South Park)|Raisins]]&quot; after which she makes only scattered prominent appearances until the end of the eleventh season, where she gets back together with Stan, and her role in the show has been much more prominent. Her original role as the voice of reason and an enemy of Cartman has been primarily taken by [[Kyle Broflovski]].

In response to the question 'Will Stan and Wendy ever kiss?&quot; during a South Park Studios interview, Trey Parker said that Stan and Wendy kissed a multitude of times, and jokingly that, during an episode he couldn't recall, they also had sex, but &quot;you didn't see it.&quot; Parker then added &quot;If you're dumb enough to look you deserve to lose that much of your life&quot;.

=== Others ===
Several other students appear as recurring background characters, while also having minor roles in various episodes, including:

* {{Anchor|Bill Allen|Fosse McDonald|Bill Allen and Fosse McDonald}}'''Bill Allen and Fosse McDonald''' are two bullies who occasionally antagonize the [[List of characters in South Park#Main characters|main characters]]. They constantly give off obnoxious giggles in deep voices, and refer to everything as &quot;gay&quot;. Their demeanor is similar to that of ''[[Beavis and Butthead]]''. In the episode &quot;[[An Elephant Makes Love to a Pig]]&quot;, they act as the sidekicks of '''Terrance Mephesto''',who is the son of mad scientist [[List of South Park residents#Dr. Alphonse Mephesto and Kevin|Alphonse Mephesto]]. They also play a small but crucial role in the [[South Park (season 7)|season 7]] episode [[Lil Crime Stoppers]], by kidnapping a girl's [[doll]], thus allowing the boys to become real detectives. Though none of them appear in class any longer, they are still frequent background characters.
* {{Anchor|Damien Thorn}}'''Damien Thorn''' (voiced by Matt Stone) is the eponymous character of a [[Damien (South Park)|first season episode]]. Inspired by [[Damien Thorn]] from the 1976 horror film ''[[The Omen]]'', Damien is [[Satan (South Park)|Satan]]'s son, who briefly attended South Park Elementary before moving from South Park. He later makes cameo appearances in &quot;[[Professor Chaos]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Death Camp of Tolerance]]&quot;, &quot;[[Dances With Smurfs]]&quot;, &quot;[[Funnybot]]&quot; and the movie &quot;South Park: Bigger, Longer, &amp; Uncut&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.southparkstudios.com/guide/characters/sally-darson Sally Darson – Character Guide]. South Park Studios. Retrieved on 2011-11-14.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Anchor|Dog Poo Petuski|DogPoo}}'''Dog Poo Petuski''' (or '''DogPoo'''&lt;ref name=&quot;DogPoo&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/42|title=DogPoo|accessdate=2008-11-17 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt;) (voiced by Trey Parker) is characterized by his lack of [[hygiene|personal hygiene]], and resembles [[Pig-Pen]] from ''[[Peanuts]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;DogPoo&quot;/&gt; Dog Poo is almost exclusively used as a background character, his only speaking roles coming in the episodes &quot;[[Professor Chaos]]&quot; and &quot;[[It's a Jersey Thing]]&quot;. He still occasionally appears in the hallway.
* {{Anchor|Jason}}'''Jason''' (voiced by Trey Parker and Matt Stone) is visually modeled after [[Jason McHugh]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/136|title=Jason|accessdate=2008-11-18 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=19092 |title=FAQ Archives: I've noticed the &quot;Jason&quot;-character actually looks a bit like Jason McHugh, is this intentional?|accessdate=2008-11-18 |date=2004-12-10 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; an actor who starred in the movies ''[[Cannibal! The Musical]]'' and ''[[Orgazmo]]'', both written by ''South Park'' creators [[Trey Parker]] and [[Matt Stone]].  Jason has brown hair and wears a purple coat with a dark gray collar and a pair of blue jeans. He only appeared in class in &quot;[[South Park is Gay!]]&quot;
* {{Anchor|Leroy Jenkins}}'''Leroy Jenkins''' first appears in the episode &quot;[[Mystery of the Urinal Deuce]]&quot; where he shows his pet frog to the class during show and tell. After that he is only seen in the background like most of the minor students. He is seen wearing a blue shirt and glasses and has freckles and brown hair.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/2010/oct FAQ]. South Park Studios. Retrieved on 2011-11-14.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Anchor|Kevin Stoley}}'''Kevin Stoley''' (voiced by Matt Stone) is characterized by his preference to bring along his ''[[Star Wars]]''-related toys, much to the annoyance of other characters who are participating in role-playing games not associated with ''Star Wars''. In [[Conjoined Fetus Lady]], it is revealed that Kevin is of Chinese ancestry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fatbeard&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=[[Fatbeard]] |url= |series= [[South Park]] |credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]] (writer) |station= [[Comedy Central]]|airdate=2009-04-22 |season=13 |number=188 |minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=O'Neal |first=Sean |title=South Park: Season 13: Episode 7: &quot;Fatbeard&quot; |work=[[The A.V. Club]] |date=2009-05-01 |url=http://www.avclub.com/articles/fatbeard,27043/ |accessdate=2009-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;[[Fatbeard]]&quot;, he plays a bigger role where he becomes part of Cartman's pirate crew. Kevin has black hair and wears a light blue shirt.
* {{Anchor|Bradley}}'''Bradley Biggle''' (voiced by Matt Stone) is a background character who speaks occasionally, making his first appearance in &quot;[[Rainforest Shmainforest]]&quot;. In the &quot;[[Coon 2: Hindsight|Coon and Friends]]&quot; story arc as Mintberry Crunch, he fights alongside Coon and Friends, but is relatively minor until the third episode, when he is revealed to be the younger brother of [[#Goth kids|Henrietta]], and has the super power of mint and berries with a &quot;tasty yet satisfying crunch&quot;, which he uses to defeat [[Cthulhu]]. In this same episode, his true name is revealed to be Gok-zarah, and he is from the planet Kokajun.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Coon vs. Coon and Friends]]|url=|series=[[South Park]]|credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]] (writer)|station=[[Comedy Central]]|airdate=2010-11-10|season=14|number=208|minutes=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Anchor|Red|Bertha|Rebecca}}'''Red''' (also known as '''Bertha'''&lt;ref name=&quot;erectionday&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=[[Erection Day]] |url= |series= [[South Park]] |credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]] (writer) |station= [[Comedy Central]]|airdate=2005-04-20 |season=9 |number=132 |minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and '''Rebecca'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode |title=[[The List (South Park)|The List]] |url= |series= [[South Park]] |credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]] (writer) |station= [[Comedy Central]]|airdate=2007-11-14 |season=11 |number=167 |minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;) (voiced by Eliza Schneider and April Stewart) is a girl who, as her name suggests, has dark red hair. She is frequently featured as Bebe and Wendy's friend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/114|title=Red|accessdate=2008-11-21 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ESM&quot;&gt;{{cite episode |title=[[Elementary School Musical (South Park)|Elementary School Musical]] |url= |series= [[South Park]] |credits=[[Trey Parker|Parker, Trey]] (writer) |station= [[Comedy Central]]|airdate=2008-11-12 |season=12 |number=180 |minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Anchor|Annie Faulk}}'''Annie Faulk''' (voiced by Mary Kay Bergman, Eliza Schneider and April Stewart) is a background character who speaks occasionally. Despite never having a significant role, she has appeared in every classroom scene since the first episode of the series.
* {{Anchor|Francis}}'''Francis''' is a background character who speaks occasionally. He has a light brown sweatshirt with Snacky Smores logo on it, brown hair with lock down bangs on his forehead and pair of dark blue jeans.
* {{Anchor|Lola}}'''Lola''' is a background female character voiced by April Stewart. She wears a dark green sweatshirt and has long brown hair in which one strand is near her left eye, while wearing a plastic headband. She is paired up with [[#Token Black|Token]] for [[Mr Garrison|Mrs. Garrison's]] assignment in &quot;[[Follow That Egg]]&quot;, the only episode where her name is mentioned.
* {{Anchor|Gordon Stoltski}}'''Gordon Stoltski''' reads the announcements at South Park elementary until he is killed in a double-homicide/suicide perpetrated by a distraught cuckold in &quot;[[Dances with Smurfs]]&quot;, who mistakes the child for a 40 year old truck driver from Chicago.
* {{Anchor|Jessie}}'''Jessie''' is a cute friendly girl who first appeared in &quot;[[Stupid Spoiled Whore Video Playset]]&quot;. She wears a pink sweatshirt with flower logo on it, pair of blue jeans and has long blonde hair in which one strand is near her left eye, while wearing a plastic headband. She has a friend named Kal.
* {{Anchor|Kal}}'''Kal''' is a brown-haired girl. She has a pink bow on her hair. Her first appearance is &quot;Stupid Spoiled Whore Video Playset&quot;.

== Students from other grades ==
=== Ike Broflovski ===
{{Main|List of South Park families#Ike Broflovski}}
'''Ike Moisha Broflovski''' is [[Kyle Broflovski|Kyle]]'s younger adopted brother, and the only [[Canada|Canadian]]-born student at the school. He is a gifted three-year-old, and received advanced placement in the school's kindergarten class. Ike is voiced by the children of the people who work at the South Park Studios.

=== Dougie ===
'''Dougie''' is a red-haired, freckled, second-grade boy with glasses, who first appeared in&quot;[[Two Guys Naked in a Hot Tub]]&quot;. His most prominent appearances come when he assumes the role of '''General Disarray''', sidekick to [[Butters Stotch|Butters]]'s alter-ego Professor Chaos. He wants to be a TV news reporter when he grows up.&lt;ref&gt;[[Two Guys Naked in a Hot Tub]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;[[Simpsons Already Did It]]&quot;, he displays a thorough knowledge of the TV show ''[[The Simpsons]]'', pointing that all of Professor Chaos' schemes resemble plots of that show. He was also the one to let Butters know that freezing oneself in the snow was actually not a good idea when Butters helped Cartman to do so in the episode&quot;[[Go God Go]]&quot;.

=== Goth kids ===
'''The Goth kids''' are a group of stereotypical [[Goth subculture|goths]], usually composed of four members: A tall, curly-haired boy who walks with a cane, a small child who appears to be a kindergartner, an overweight girl named Henrietta Biggle, and a boy with black hair with dyed red streaks who constantly flicks his long fringe out of the way when it gets in his eyes. In season 14, they were finally added to the title sequence of the show after making several appearances since season 7. In [[South Park (season 7)|season seven]] (2003) episode &quot;[[Raisins (South Park)|Raisins]]&quot;, [[Stan Marsh|Stan]] briefly becomes the fifth member of their group, his nickname being &quot;Raven&quot;. They frequently stereotype everyone else and display [[double standards]] in their talks about conformity;&lt;ref name=&quot;erectionday&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goths&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Goths |url= http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/131|accessdate=2008-11-23 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, they are also often portrayed in a sympathetic light.&lt;ref name=&quot;AVCUngroundable&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Josh |last=Modell |title=The Ungroundable |url=http://www.avclub.com/articles/the-ungroundable,13374/ |work=[[The A.V. Club]] |date=2008-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNUngroundable&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=IGN: The Ungroundable Review |url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/932/932385p1.html |last=Fickett |first = Travis |publisher=[[News Corporation]] | work = [[IGN]] |date=2008-11-20 |accessdate=2008-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Goth kids are easily provoked,&lt;ref name=&quot;AVCUngroundable&quot;/&gt; and are very protective of their image. They find it annoying to be confused with [[emo]] kids, but even more frustrating to be compared to the Hot Topic &quot;vampire&quot; kids.&lt;ref name=&quot;AVCUngroundable&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNUngroundable&quot; /&gt;  The Goth kids were seen taking part in a talent show in season 9 performing a song about never taking part in a talent show.  The eldest Goth boy was in Stan's dance crew in &quot;[[You Got F'd in the A]]&quot;.  The Goth kids are never seen attending classes; they are normally seen listening to [[Gothic rock|goth music]], drinking coffee, and smoking.&lt;ref name=&quot;AVCUngroundable&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/faq/archives.php?id=16431 |title=FAQ Archives: Why arent the goth kids in the class w/ the rest of the kids when they show them all at their desk?|accessdate=2008-11-23 |date=2004-05-06 |work=South Park Studios}}&lt;/ref&gt; They appear as followers of [[Cthulhu]] in &quot;[[Mysterion Rises]]&quot;, though they have become disillusioned in the [[Coon vs. Coon and Friends|following episode]] because [[Cthulhu]] hasn't lived up to their expectations.

=== Sixth-graders ===
The '''Sixth-graders''' are a group of older students who tend to bully the fourth-graders. They are usually seen riding their [[bicycles]]. They were originally depicted as fifth graders, but moved to sixth grade in the fourth season. Their leader is a boy with a distinctive haircut who is always depicted wearing a shirt with a logo of his own face. He regularly refers to the fourth-graders disparagingly as &quot;Fourthies&quot;. Episodes concerning the sixth-graders' interactions with the main characters have become less frequent in later seasons.

== In other media ==
Wendy and Pip were multi-player characters in the video game ''[[South Park (video game)|South Park]]''. The preceding two characters, along with Tweek, Bebe, and Damien were playable in [[South Park Rally]]. All aforementioned characters with the exception of Damien, along with Craig, Clyde, Token, Jimmy, Timmy, and Red are unlockable characters along with [[Butters Stotch]] and [[Professor Chaos]] (only available as an exclusive Downloadable Content code) in [[South Park Let's Go Tower Defense Play!]].

Songs performed by characters from South Park have appeared in the ''[[Rock Band]]'' series. &quot;[[Timmy and the Lords of the Underworld]]&quot;, featuring Timmy, features as a bonus song in the [[Rock Band (video game)|first game]], while Cartman's interpretation of [[Lady Gaga]]'s &quot;[[Poker Face (Lady Gaga song)|Poker Face]]&quot; was released as downloadable content for the series on March 16, 2010.

==See also==
*[[List of South Park families]]
*[[List of supporting characters on South Park]]
*[[List of staff at South Park Elementary]]
*[[List of minor characters on South Park]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.southparkstudios.com/fans/characters/?page=1&amp;type=kid South Park Studios – Characters] Overview of child characters at the show's official website

{{South Park}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Students At South Park Elementary}}
[[Category:Lists of characters in South Park|Students]]
[[Category:Lists of fictional children|South Park]]
[[Category:Child characters in television|South Park]]
[[Category:Fictional characters from Colorado]]

[[da:Elever på South Park Elementary]]
[[fr:Élèves de l'école primaire de South Park]]
[[hu:South Park-i tanulók és iskolai alkalmazottak]]
[[pl:Lista uczniów Szkoły Podstawowej w South Park]]
[[ro:Craig Tucker]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
