<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7934167" ns="0" title="Vaharai Bombing"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox civilian attack
| title      = Vaharai bombing
| image      = 
| caption    = 
| location   = [[Kathiraveli]], [[Batticaloa|Batticaloa district]], [[Sri Lanka]]
| coordinates = 
| target     = [[Sri Lankan Tamil]] refugees
| date       = November 7, 2006
| time       = 
| timezone   = +6 GMT
| type       = Artillery fire
| fatalities = 45
| injuries   = 100
| perps      = [[Sri Lankan Army]]
| susperps   = 
| weapons    = 
}}

The '''Vaharai bombing''' is a disputed event in the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]. It occurred on November 7, 2006 when, according to survivors of the incident interviewed by [[Reuters]], the [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]] fired artillery at [[Sri Lanka]]n military personnel from near a school where [[minority group|minority]] [[Sri Lankan Tamil]] [[refugees]] displaced by the current phase of the [[Sri Lankan civil war]] had taken shelter.&lt;ref name=REU1&gt;{{cite news|url=http://in.news.yahoo.com/061110/137/69950.html| date= 2006-11-10|title=Sri Lanka says sinks rebel boats, Tamil MP killed |publisher=Reuters| accessdate =2006-11-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061110143904/http://in.news.yahoo.com/061110/137/69950.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Sri Lankan Army]] returned fire and around 45&lt;ref name=BBC2&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6128094.stm| date= 2006-11-08|title=Lanka army 'kills 45 civilians' |publisher=BBC World Service| accessdate = 2006-11-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; civilians were killed. Over 100 were injured and admitted to the local hospitals. However, people who were interviewed by [[Human Rights Watch]] claimed that the [[LTTE]] did not even fire artillery. Further, the rebel LTTE denies firing artillery from close to the school. The incident occurred at around 11.35 a.m close to Kathiraveli, a coastal village in Vaharai [[peninsula]] of the [[Batticaloa]] district in eastern [[Sri Lanka]].

==The incident==
[[Image:LocationSriLanka.png|left|thumb|Location of [[w:Sri Lanka|Sri Lanka]]]]
The LTTE claimed the shelling killed 43 displaced Tamil civilians who had been taking shelter after the recent flare up of the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]. However the [[SLMM]] counted 23 bodies.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC2&quot;/&gt; About 300 were wounded, 127 of them seriously. Many were killed when two shells hit school buildings housing a large number civilians.&lt;ref name = &quot;DNA World&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.dnaindia.com/report.asp?NewsID=1063199
| title = Lanka gov’t ‘regrets’ killing 65 civilians
| accessdate = 2006-11-14
| date = November 9, 2006
| publisher = DNA World
| quote = Keheliya Rambukwella said ‘the Norwegian-led [[Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission]] had reported seeing 23 bodies after the rockets had been fired into two school buildings housing a large number of displaced Tamil civilians’
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Shelling also damaged the ‘Sonobo Infants Home’ seriously injuring nearly 12 infants.&lt;ref name = &quot;Asian&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.asiantribune.com/index.php?q=node/3097
| title = Sri Lanka military reported to have killed 65 civilians
| accessdate = 2006-11-14
| date = November 9, 2006
| publisher = Asiantribune.com
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Sri Lankan Conflict}}
The town [http://www.mapygon.com/sri-lanka/eastern/kathiraveli/ Kathiraveli] in the Vaharai region is mainly populated by minority [[Sri Lankan Tamils]] and indigenous [[Vedda]] people. It was under the de facto control of the [[LTTE]] rebels.

The Sri Lankan government responded saying that the refugees housed within the school were being used as [[human shields]] by the [[LTTE]]. The Nordic ceasefire monitors, the [[Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission]], said they did not see any LTTE military installations nearby.&lt;ref name=BBC1&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6131566.stm| date= 2006-11-09|title=Anger over Lanka civilian deaths |publisher=BBC World Service| accessdate = 2006-11-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However the government's account was supported by survivors of the incident who had fled the area and subsequently taken shelter in government controlled territory. [[Reuters]] reported one survivor saying, &quot;First I heard big guns fired (by the LTTE) from the camp area. I jumped into a bunker. Then the army returned fire and I heard big explosions in the camp.&quot;&lt;ref name=REU1&gt;{{cite news|url=http://in.today.reuters.com/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=topNews&amp;storyID=2006-11-10T143450Z_01_NOOTR_RTRJONC_0_India-275732-3.xml&amp;archived=False| date= 2006-11-10|title=Sri Lanka says sinks rebel boats, Tamil MP killed |publisher=Reuters| accessdate =2006-11-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, [[Human Rights Watch]] conducted interviews with 12 witnesses to the attack. All witnesses said that there were no LTTE fighters located in or adjacent to the [[Internally displaced person|IDP]] camp at the time of the attack or directly before. They also reported that the nearest LTTE military base was the Sinnakangai camp on the coast about two kilometers away. None of the interviewees had seen or heard outgoing shelling earlier that day. Another women who lived near the [[Internally displaced person|IDP]] camp claimed “Before the shelling I heard nothing. It was sudden, we didn’t expect it”. Another man whose children were wounded in the shelling said that there was no LTTE present near the camp and he did not hear any shelling from the LTTE.&lt;ref name=HRW1&gt;{{cite news|url=http://hrw.org/reports/2007/srilanka0807/4.htm#_Toc173322248| date= |title=Attack at the Kathiravelli School |publisher=[[Human Rights Watch]]| accessdate = 2007-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reactions ==
* [[Image:Flag of Sri Lanka.svg|20px]] [[Politics of Sri Lanka|Sri Lankan Government]] - Government defence spokesman Keheliya Rambukwella said the military had targeted two Tamil Tiger artillery positions but admitted a civilian centre was also hit. &quot;While we regret this whole episode, we also must say that national security is uppermost in our minds. Actions by the defence authorities were inevitable. The Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) had been firing mortar and artillery at government positions, as well as civilian settlements, in the region for over a week.&quot; Media Minister Anura Yapa said &quot;The LTTE is using humans as shields to cover their operations.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;DNA World&quot;/&gt; Another defense ministry statement read: &quot;The Tigers had been planning this situation since the beginning of this month by detaining the innocent civilians in those areas by force to be used as a human shield when the time arises.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Asian&quot;/&gt; Tamil legislators from the dominant Tamil speaking party in the Sri Lankan parliament, [[Tamil National Alliance]] demonstrated in front of the [[United Nations]] local offices of [[UNICEF]]&lt;ref name=AFP&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://uk.news.yahoo.com/09112006/323/photo/sri-lankan-tamil-mps-colombo-protest-against-artillery-attack.html
| date = 2006-11-09
| title = Sri Lankan Tamil MPs in Colombo protest against the artillery attack
| publisher = AFP
| accessdate = 2006-11-09
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and handed over a petition to the UN offices demanding intervention to protect refugees in the island's troubled areas. &quot;We urge your good selves to take immediate action regarding this matter and take steps to safeguard the internally displaced Tamil speaking people and other civilians&quot; the legislators told the [[UN High Commissioner for Refugees]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.lankanewspapers.com/news/2006/11/9255.html
| title = Sri Lanka regrets killing of civilians
| accessdate = 2006-11-14
| date = November 9, 2006
| publisher = lankanewspapers.com
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently a Tamil National Alliance parliamentarian, [[Nadarajah Raviraj]] who had demonstrated in front of the UN offices was shot and killed in Colombo.&lt;ref name=REU1&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://in.today.reuters.com/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=topNews&amp;storyID=2006-11-10T143450Z_01_NOOTR_RTRJONC_0_India-275732-3.xml&amp;archived=False
| date = 2006-11-10
| title = Sri Lanka says sinks rebel boats, Tamil MP killed 
| publisher = [[Reuters]]
| accessdate =2006-11-11
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ap2&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/11/10/asia/AS_GEN_Sri_Lanka_Attack.php
| date = 2006-11-09|title=Tamil member of Parliament killed in Sri Lankan capital 
| publisher = Associated Press 
| accessdate = 2006-11-09
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Tamil Tigers]] - There was widespread anger amongst the Tamil community in Sri Lanka . The Tamil Tigers said in a statement on their website. &quot;Is it possible that the Sri Lankan military’s intention was to teach the Tamils the lesson that they, the military, can kill refugees in such numbers, and no one can stop them?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/09/world/asia/09lanka.html?fta=y
| title = Artillery Fire Kills 23 Civilians and Wounds 135 in Sri Lanka
| accessdate = 2006-11-14
| date = November 9, 2006
| publisher = [[New York Times]]
| first=Shimali
| last=Senanayake
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* The Chief Minister of the [[India]]n state of [[Tamil Nadu]], M. Karunanidhi, deplored the incident and pondered &quot;how long it could tolerate the Sri Lankan Army's atrocities against Tamils there.&quot;&lt;ref name=PTI1&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.hindu.com/thehindu/holnus/004200611092032.htm
| date= 2006-11-09
| title = Karunanidhi deplores shelling by Lankan forces |publisher=Press Trust of India 
| accessdate = 2006-11-09
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061128100601/http://www.hindu.com/thehindu/holnus/004200611092032.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Image:Flag of the United Nations.svg|20px]] [[United Nations]]  - The United Nations strongly condemned the attack and considered it an &quot;indiscriminate use of force&quot; on civilians.&lt;ref name=UN1&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWB.NSF/db900SID/EGUA-6VDNCG?OpenDocument| date= 2006-11-09|title=Sri Lanka: United Nations condemns indiscriminate use of force |publisher=United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs| accessdate = 2006-11-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  
* [[Amnesty International]] - The international human rights group urged the government of Sri Lanka to investigate the attack on the civilians as matter of urgency. Amnesty International's Asia Pacific Director Purna Sen said in a press release, “It is appalling that the military should attack a camp for displaced people -- these are civilians who have already been forced from their homes because of the conflict…. Killing and injuring civilians can never be justified. The government must investigate this terrible attack as a matter of urgency. It must ensure that those responsible are brought to justice to signal to the rest of the military that attacking civilians will not be tolerated”&lt;ref name=amnesty1&gt;{{cite news|url=http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGASA370322006| date= 2006-11-08|title=Sri Lanka: Attack on displaced civilians must be investigated |publisher=Amnesty International Press Release | accessdate = 2006-11-09 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061113231708/http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGASA370322006 |archivedate = 2006-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Image:US-DeptOfState-Seal.jpg|20px]] The [[United States Department of State|US State Department]] strongly condemned the incident and exhorted the &quot;Sri Lankan Government to adopt corrective measures to prevent civilian casualties that also take into account instances where civilians may be used as &quot;human shields&quot; in the future.&quot; and expected &quot;an immediate, independent investigation into the November 8 incidents and bring the responsible parties to justice.&quot;&lt;ref name=uss&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2006/75770.htm| date= 2006-11-09|title=Military Attack in Eastern Sri Lanka|publisher=US State Department Press Release | accessdate = 2006-11-09 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061110001305/http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2006/75770.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Image:Emblem of the ICRC.svg|20px]] [[International Committee of the Red Cross]] - A spokesman said they evacuated 74 wounded from a hospital in the rebel-held area to a government-controlled area.&lt;ref name = &quot;DNA World&quot;/&gt;
* The [[Humanitarian Law Project]] in a letter to UN High Commissioner, severely condemned the actions of the Sri Lankan army and considered the artillery attack on the Vaharai refugee camp a &quot;[[war crime]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=hlc&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tamilcanadian.com/tc_images/world/na/Letter_to_HRHC_10_November_2006_Address.pdf?u=sitemade| date= 2006-11-09|title=Letter to [[United Nations]] High Commissioner |publisher=Humanitarian Law Project Letter | accessdate = 2006-11-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accusations of blocked humanitarian aid==
The [[LTTE]] political head for the [[Trincomalee]] district claimed &quot;The Government has already blocked the relief assistance to the internally displaced persons in Vaharai area. They were provided dry rations under the United Nation’s [[World Food Program]] and that was too stopped for three weeks.&quot; In addition, the LTTE accused the Sri Lankan government of preventing ambulances carrying the injured to pass military checkpoints for nearly 3 hours.&lt;ref name=Tamilnet2&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tamilnet.com/art.html?catid=13&amp;artid=20209| date= 2006-11-09|title=SLA denied transport to Vaharai injured for 3 hours- Elilan |publisher=Tamilnet| accessdate = 2006-11-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of massacres in Sri Lanka]]
* [[List of attacks attributed to Sri Lankan government forces]]
* [[List of attacks attributed to the LTTE]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200611/s1784269.htm/ Sri Lankan military shelling kills 65 civilians rebels; abc.net.au; November 9, 2006]
* [http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200611/s1785100.htm/ Sri Lanka voices regret over civilian deaths; abc.net.au; November 9, 2006]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6128094.stm/ Lanka army 'kills 45 civilians'; BBC World Service; November 8, 2006]
* [http://transcurrents.com/tamiliana/archives/217 Massacre of innocent civilians at Kathiraweli – Trancurrents]
*[http://commentisfree.guardian.co.uk/alex_stein/2006/11/post_660.html Double Standards at the United Nations (UN)]
* [http://vaharaidisplaced.blogspot.com/ Vaharai Displaced: A Pictorial from Humanity Ashore]
*[http://www.flickr.com/photos/arjunan/page2/ Vaharai bombing: A Pictorial by Arjunan]

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vaharai}}
[[Category:2006 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan Tamil history]]
[[Category:Civilian massacres in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 2006]]
[[Category:Sri Lanka Army]]

[[ta:வாகரை குண்டுத்தாக்குதல்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
