<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="794030" ns="0" title="William Howard Taft IV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{seealso|Taft family}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name               = William Howard Taft IV
|image              = William Howard Taft IV, Deptuty Secretary of Defense, official portrait.JPEG
|imagesize          = 
|caption            = Taft, c. 1981
|office             = 
|term_start         = 
|term_end           = 
|predecessor        = 
|successor          = 
|birth_date         = {{birth date and age|1945|09|13|mf=y}}
|birth_place        = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|death_date         = 
|death_place        = 
|nationality        = [[United States of America]]
|party              = 
|alma_mater         = [[Yale University]]
|occupation         = Lawyer
}}
'''William Howard Taft IV''' (born on September 13, 1945) is an [[Lawyer|attorney]] who has served in the United States government under several [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] administrations. He is the son of [[William Howard Taft III]] and the great-grandson of U.S. President [[William Howard Taft]]. 

==Education, family==
Taft was born in [[Washington, D.C.]] and attended [[St. Paul's School (Concord, New Hampshire)|St. Paul's School]], graduating with classmate [[John Kerry]] in 1962. He earned his bachelor of arts degree in English from [[Yale University]] in 1966 and his law degree from [[Harvard Law School]] in 1969. 

He and his late wife, Julia Vadala Taft, had three children—Maria Consetta Taft, Julia Harris Taft, and William Howard Taft V.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/03/18/AR2008031803341.html Julia Taft Obituary]&lt;/ref&gt; He resides in Lorton, Va.

==Government service and legal career==
After researching the FTC as one of &quot;[[The Nader Report on the Federal Trade Commission|Nader's Raiders]]&quot;, Taft served briefly as attorney adviser to the chairman of the [[Federal Trade Commission]] in 1970.

From 1970 to 1973, he was the principal assistant to [[Caspar W. Weinberger]], who was deputy director, then director, of the [[Office of Management and Budget]] in the [[Executive Office of the President]] under President [[Richard Nixon]]. Taft assisted him in the management of the budgetary process, policy review, and program oversight for the entire federal government. 

Taft married [[Julia V. Taft|Julia Vadala]] in 1974.

Taft served from 1973 to 1976 as the [[executive assistant]] to the [[United States Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare]]. In April 1976 Taft was appointed by President [[Gerald Ford]] to serve as [[general counsel]] of the [[United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare|Department of Health, Education, and Welfare]]. In that post, as the chief lawyer for the department and the principal administrator of the Office of the General Counsel, he supervised over 350 lawyers in Washington and 10 regional offices. 

During the [[Jimmy Carter|Carter administration]], he was an attorney with the Washington, D.C. [[law firm]] of [[Leva, Hawes, Symington, Martin and Oppenheimer]].

In February [[1981]], as one of his first appointments, President [[Ronald Reagan]] appointed Taft as [[General Counsel of the Department of Defense]]. Taft was then appointed [[Deputy Secretary of Defense]] and served from January 1984 to April 1989. He served as acting [[Secretary of Defense]] from January to March 1989 after [[George H. W. Bush]] became president. Bush's initial nominee, [[John Tower]], was not confirmed by the [[United States Senate]] after much contentious debate and testimony.  The eventual appointee confirmed in March was [[Dick Cheney|Richard B. Cheney]] (later [[Vice President of the United States]], 2001-2009).  Although he was only acting Secretary of Defense, and never confirmed as the permanent Secretary, he became the third member of his family to hold a position as civilian head of a military department, following his great-great-grandfather [[Alphonso Taft]] (under President [[Ulysses S. Grant]]) and his great-grandfather [[William Howard Taft]] (under President [[Theodore Roosevelt]]).

Taft served as [[United States Permanent Representative to NATO|U.S. Permanent Representative to NATO]], which has the rank of ambassador, from 1989 to 1992, during the [[Gulf War]].

During the [[Bill Clinton|Clinton administration]], Taft entered private practice with the [[Washington, D.C.]], law firm of [[Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver &amp; Jacobson]].

===Service in George W. Bush administration===
After the election of [[2000]], [[George W. Bush]] appointed Taft to serve as [[Legal Adviser of the Department of State|chief legal advisor]] to the [[United States Department of State]] under Secretary of State [[Colin Powell]], with whom he was reportedly friends. This appointment was technically a significantly lower appointment than he had held in other administrations, but it permitted him to work with his wife, [[Julia Taft]], a top State Department official in charge of [[refugees]] who also served during the Clinton administration.

In 2004, Taft's name surfaced as a dissenter concerning the policy of interrogation techniques for military detainees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A759-2004Jun23.html Lawyer for State Dept. Disputed Detainee Memo ]&lt;/ref&gt; In a January 11, 2002, memo, Taft opposed [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] lawyers to argue that the president could not &quot;suspend&quot; U.S. obligations to respect the [[Geneva Conventions]] and that a legal argument to do so was &quot;legally flawed and procedurally impossible.&quot; This was also the position of Secretary of State Colin L. Powell, who attempted to persuade Bush to reconsider. [[Alberto R. Gonzales]], the White House counsel, subsequently advised Bush in a memo that Taft and Powell were wrong and the Justice Department's analysis was &quot;definitive.&quot; Gonzales claimed terrorist attacks &quot;require a new approach in our actions toward captured terrorists,&quot; and argued that if suspected terrorists had never respected the Geneva Conventions' human rights protections, the U.S. didn't need to do so.

==Leaving government service==

After the re-election of President Bush, resignation of Colin Powell and appointment of [[Condoleezza Rice]] as secretary of state, Taft resigned to return to private practice, again at Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver &amp; Jacobson.  Currently he is a visiting professor in at Stanford Law School, having succeeded [[Allen Weiner]] as the Warren Christopher Professor of the Practice of International Law and Diplomacy in 2007.&lt;ref name=SLS&gt;[http://www.law.stanford.edu/news/pr/57/William%20Taft%20IV%20to%20Join%20Stanford%20Law%20School%20as%20the%20Warren%20Christopher%20Professor%20of%20the%20Practice%20of%20International%20Law%20and%20Diplomacy/ &quot;William Taft IV to Join Stanford Law School as the Warren Christopher Professor of the Practice of International Law and Diplomacy&quot;] [[Stanford Law School]], April 4, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2009 he was named chair of the board of trustees for [[Freedom House]], an independent watchdog organization that supports the expansion of freedom around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=70&amp;release=753 &quot;Freedom House Welcomes William H. Taft IV as New Chairman&quot;]; retrieved January 15, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 12, 2006, Taft co-signed (along with 28 other retired military or defense department officials) a letter to the chairman and ranking member of the Senate Armed Services committee in which he stated his belief that the Bush Administration's attempt to redefine Common Article 3 of the Geneva Convention &quot;poses a grave threat&quot; to U.S. service members.

Taft is said to be one of the sources who told journalists [[David Corn]] and [[Michael Isikoff]] that former Deputy Secretary of State [[Richard Armitage (politician)|Richard Armitage]] was the source syndicated columnist [[Robert Novak]] had when he made public the fact that [[Valerie Plame|Valerie Wilson]] worked for the CIA. In a review of Corn's and Isikoff's book, ''Hubris: The Inside Story of Spin, Scandal, and the Selling of the Iraq War'', Novak wrote: &quot;I don't know precisely how Isikoff flushed out Armitage [as Novak's original source], but ''Hubris'' clearly points to two sources: Washington lobbyist [[Kenneth Duberstein]], Armitage's political adviser, and William Taft IV, who was the State Department legal adviser when Armitage was deputy secretary.&quot;&lt;ref name=rnovak&gt;[http://www.weeklystandard.com/Utilities/printer_preview.asp?idArticle=12785&amp;R=EE501DF13 Novak, Robert, &quot;Who Said What When: The rise and fall of the Valerie Plame 'scandal']&quot;, [[The Weekly Standard]], October 16, 2006, book review of ''Hubris: The Inside Story of Spin, Scandal, and the Selling of the Iraq War'', by Michael Isikoff and David Corn, accessed October 8, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ffhsj.com/index.cfm?pageID=42&amp;itemID=620 Bio at Fried, Frank, Harris, Schriver &amp; Jacobson LLP]
*[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ho/po/com/12312.htm United States Department of State: US Ambassadors to NATO]

{{start box}}
{{s-legal}}
{{succession box
| title=[[Legal Adviser of the Department of State]]
| before=David Andrews
| after=[[John B. Bellinger III]]
| years=2001 &amp;ndash; 2005}}
{{s-off}}
{{succession box
| title=[[United States Deputy Secretary of Defense]]
| before=[[W. Paul Thayer]]
| after=[[Donald J. Atwood Jr.|Donald J. Atwood, Jr.]]
| years=1984–1989
}}
{{s-dip}}
{{succession box
| title=[[United States Permanent Representative to NATO|U.S. Ambassador to NATO]]
| before=[[Alton G. Keel, Jr.]]
| after=[[Reginald Bartholomew]]
| years=1989–1992
}}
{{end box}}
{{USNATOambassadors}}
{{USDepSecDef}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Taft, William Howard IV
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =September 13, 1945
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Washington, D.C.]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Taft, William Howard IV}}
[[Category:1945 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:St. Paul's School (Concord, New Hampshire) alumni]]
[[Category:Lawyers who have represented the United States government]]
[[Category:Taft family]]
[[Category:United States Deputy Secretaries of Defense]]
[[Category:Ambassadors of the United States]]
[[Category:Permanent Representatives of the United States to NATO]]
[[Category:Washington, D.C. lawyers]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:Yale University alumni]]
[[Category:Harvard Law School alumni]]
[[Category:Plame affair figures]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
