<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7948994" ns="0" title="Zahra Amir Ebrahimi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
|name            = Zahra Amir Ebrahimi
|image             =
|image_size        = 220
|birth_date            = {{birth year and age|1981}}
|origin          = [[Iran]]
|occupation      = [[actress]], [[photographer]]
| background=non_performing_personnel
}}
'''Zahra Amir Ebrahimi''' ({{lang-fa| زهرا اميرابراهيمی}}) (born 1981) is an [[Iran]]ian professional photographer, television actress and short movies director.&lt;ref name = &quot;DailyMail&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=Outrage in Iran as actress does a &quot;Paris&quot; and her sex video ends up on the net |url= http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=415903&amp;in_page_id=1770 |publisher= Daily Mail | first= Richard |last=Creasy |date= November 11, 2006 |accessdate= 2006-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

She studied teather in Tehran, and started her professional life with making short movies. She made her first movie when she was only eighteen. She became very popular shortly after her first work in Iranian public TV. She was well known in Iran for her role in the popular [[Iran]]ian [[soap opera]] ''[[Narges]]'', as a [[pious]] young woman.

Ebrahimi is also a professional photographer, whose work focuses on social topics and issues.  She now lives outside of her country because of several problems she faced in Iran after a scandel she became the center of.

== Scandal ==
{{Main|Iranian sex tape scandal}}
In 2006, Ebrahimi became the centre of an Iranian sex tape scandal when a videotape of a woman, claimed to be Ebrahimi, having sex with a man was leaked to the internet and released on CD. She subsequently became the subject of an official investigation handled by [[Tehran]]'s chief prosecutor, [[Saeed Mortazavi]].  The unnamed man on the tape, who is suspected of releasing it, reportedly fled to [[Armenia]] but was subsequently returned to Iran and charged with breach of public morality laws.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title= Iranian actor in sex video scandal says ex-fiance faked footage |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/iran/story/0,,1954553,00.html |publisher= The Guardian | first= Robert |last=Talt |date= November 22, 2006 |accessdate= 2006-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview with the Guardian, Ebrahimi denied being the woman in the film and dismissed it as a fake made by a vengeful former fiancé who used studio techniques to form a montage of incriminating images designed to destroy her career.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian&quot; /&gt;

Rumours of an attempted suicide were also denied by Ebrahimi with a public message: ''&quot;I just want to tell my country's people that I am alive. I am thinking about the strength of Iranian women and will defend the respect of the girls and women of my nation.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title= Sex footage leaves actress fighting to save honour |url= http://news.scotsman.com/movies.cfm?id=1663762006 |publisher= The Scotsman | first= Michael |last=Theodoulou |date= November 10, 2006 |accessdate= 2006-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Amir Ebrahimi, Zahra
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1981
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Amir Ebrahimi, Zahra}}
[[Category:1981 births]]
[[Category:Iranian television actors]]
[[Category:Living people]]


{{Iran-actor-stub}}

[[da:Zahra Amir Ebrahimi]]
[[de:Sahra Amir Ebrahimi]]
[[fa:زهرا امیرابراهیمی]]
[[fr:Zahra Amir Ebrahimi]]
[[jv:Zahra Amir Ebrahimi]]
[[hu:Zahra Amir Ebráhimi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
