<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7955348" ns="0" title="Université de Montréal"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|UdeM}}
{{Coord|45|30|17|N|73|36|46|W|display=title|type:edu}}
{{Infobox university
|name = ''Université de Montréal''
|image_name = UdeM CoA.png
|image_size = 213px
|motto            = ''Fide splendet et scientia'' ([[Latin]])
|mottoeng         = It shines by faith and knowledge
|established = 1878 as Université Laval à Montréal  
|type = [[Public university|Public]]
|endowment = [[Canadian dollar|$]] 133.938 million&lt;ref name=&quot;annual&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.direction.umontreal.ca/recteur/documents/rapport-annuel/rap_an2009en.pdf|title=Financial Report|work=2009 Annual Report|publisher=Universite de Montreal|accessdate=11 August 2011|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|rector = [[Guy Breton]]
|city =[[Montreal]]
|state = [[Quebec|QC]]
|country = [[Canada]]
|coords = {{Coord|45|30|11|N|73|36|54|W|}}
|campus = [[Urban area|Urban]], [[park]], {{convert|60|ha|acre|abbr=on}} 
|faculty = 6,607&lt;ref name=stats&gt;[http://www.umontreal.ca/infogen/en_bref/stats/index.html Université de Montréal official statistics] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff = 4,379&lt;ref name=stats /&gt;
|undergrad = 41,055&lt;ref name=stats /&gt;
|postgrad = 14,485&lt;ref name=stats /&gt;
|colors = |colors= [[Royal blue]], [[White]] and [[Black]] {{color box|#4169E1}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}} {{color box|#000000}}
|mascot = Carabin
|athletics     = 15 varsity teams&lt;br/&gt;'''[[Montreal Carabins|Carabins]]'''
|affiliations   = [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[International Association of Universities|IAU]], [[Agence universitaire de la Francophonie|AUF]], [[L'Association des universités de la francophonie canadienne|AUFC]], [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]], [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport|CIS]], [[Quebec Student Sports Federation|QSSF]], [[International Forum of Public Universities|IFPU]], [[U15 (universities)|U15]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]], [[Canadian University Press|CUP]].
|website = [http://www.umontreal.ca/ www.umontreal.ca]
|logo = [[Image:Universite de Montreal logo.svg|center|230px]]
}}

The '''Université de Montréal'''&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.direction.umontreal.ca/recteur/documents/rapport-annuel/rap_an2007en.pdf 2007 Annual Report] {{en}}. Université de Montréal Accessed October 20, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; ('''UdeM''') is a [[Public_university#Canada|public]] [[francophone]] research university in [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], [[Canada]]. It comprises thirteen faculties, more than sixty departments and two&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umontreal.ca/english/overview/overview.html General overview of Université de Montréal]&lt;/ref&gt; affiliated schools: the [[École Polytechnique de Montréal|École Polytechnique]] (School of Engineering) and [[HEC Montréal]] (School of Business). It offers more than 650 undergraduate programmes and graduate programmes, including 71 doctoral programmes.

The university has [[Quebec]]'s largest sponsored research income and the fourth largest in [[Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.researchinfosource.com/2010-top50-sup.pdf - Canada’s Top 50 Research Universities 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; allocating close to [[Canadian dollar|$]]447.2 million to research conducted in more than 150 research centres as of 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.direction.umontreal.ca/recteur/documents/rapport-annuel/rap_an2007en.pdf 2007 Annual Report] {{en}}, &quot;Research Income by University&quot;, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; It is also part of the [[U15 (universities)|U15]] universities. More than 55,000 students are enrolled in undergraduate and graduate programs, making it the second largest university in Canada in terms of student enrollment.&lt;ref name=stats /&gt;

==History==
===Early years===

As an institution, the university was first founded when the [[Université Laval]] in [[Quebec City]] founded a new branch in Montréal in 1878, which became known as the Université de Laval à Montréal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title='Fitzhenry and Whiteside Book of Canadian Facts and Dates'  |last=Pound |first=Richard W. |publisher=Fitzhenry and Whiteside |year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; This initially went against the wishes of Montréal's [[prelate]], who advocated an independent university in his city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1878-a.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Certain parts of the institution's educational facilities, such as those of the [[Séminaire de Québec]], had already been established in Montréal as early as 1876.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0008242 The Canadian Encyclopedia - University]&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Holy See|Vatican]] granted the university some administrative autonomy in 1889, thus allowing it to choose its own professors and license its own diplomas. However it was not until May 8, 1919 that a papal charter from [[Pope Benedict XV]] granted full autonomy to the university.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=U1ARTU0003530 The Canadian Encyclopedia - Université de Montréal]&lt;/ref&gt;
It thus became an independent Catholic university and adopted Université de Montréal as its name.&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1878-f.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; Laval composed by Wilfrid Beaudry was dedicated to the students at Laval University and the Université de Montréal. The music for piano was published in Québec by J. Beaudry, circa 1906.&lt;ref&gt;Laval http://amicus.collectionscanada.gc.ca/ourl/c.php?id=16182129&amp;l=eng&amp;s=amicus&lt;/ref&gt;

At the time of its creation, less than a hundred students were admitted to the university's three faculties, which at that time were located in [[Vieux-Montréal|Old Montreal]]. These were the faculty of theology (located at the [[Grand séminaire de Montréal]]), the faculty of law (hosted by the [[Society of Saint-Sulpice]]) and the faculty of medicine (at the [[Château Ramezay]]).&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.umontreal.ca/english/overview/brief_history.html Université de Montréal - English - Brief History]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umontreal.ca/infogen/en_bref/historique.html Université de Montréal - Information générale&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Graduate school|Graduate training]] based on German-inspired American models of specialized course work and completion of a research thesis was introduced and adopted.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;
Most of Québec's [[secondary education]] establishments employed classic course methods of varying quality. This forced the university to open a [[University-preparatory school|preparatory school]] in 1887 to harmonize the education level of its students. Named the &quot;Faculty of Arts&quot;, this school would remain in use until 1972 and was the predecessor of Québec's current [[CEGEP]] system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1878-a.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Founding by provincial charter===

Although a branch of [[Laval University]] was planned as Montreal's first French-language university, it was not until February 14, 1920, that the first provincial charter founding the university was passed.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;
The second provincial charter was passed in 1950.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; 
The policy of university education initiated in the 1960s (following the [[Quiet Revolution]]) was a response to popular pressure and the belief that higher education was a key to social justice and economic productivity for individuals as well as society.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;
The third provincial charter, which was passed in 1967, defined the Université de Montréal as a public institution, dedicated to higher learning and research, in the administration of which students and teachers would have the right to participate.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

===Campus relocation===
[[Image:Pavillon saintdenis.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Former campus on Rue Saint-Denis.]]
[[Image:Université de Montréal.JPG|thumb|right|250px|A view of the present Roger Gaudry building, built in 1943 and designed by [[Ernest Cormier]], on Mont-Royal.]]
From 1876 to 1895, most university classes took place in the [[Grand séminaire de Montréal]]. From 1895 to 1942, it was housed in a building at the intersection of [[Rue Saint-Denis|Saint-Denis]] and [[Rue Sainte-Catherine|Sainte-Catherine]] streets in Montreal's eastern downtown [[Quartier Latin, Montreal|Quartier Latin]].

Unlike English language universities in Montréal, such as [[McGill University]], the university suffered a lack of funding for two major reasons: the relative poverty of the [[French Canadian]] population and the complications ensuing from its remote management from [[Quebec City]]. The downtown campus was hit by three different fires between 1919 and 1921, further complicating the university's already precarious finances and forcing it to spend much of its resources on repairing its own infrastructure.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1919-a.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1930, enough funds had been accumulated to start the construction of a new campus on the north west slope of [[Mount Royal]], adopting new plans designed by [[Ernest Cormier]]. However, the [[Great Depression|financial crisis of the 1930s]] virtually suspended all ongoing construction.&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1919-d.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Many speculated that the university would have to sell off its unfinished building projects in order to ensure its own survival. Not before 1939 did the [[Politics of Québec|provincial government]] directly intervene by injecting public funds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1919-f.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Campus construction subsequently resumed and the mountain campus was officially inaugurated on June 3, 1943.&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1943-a.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The university's former downtown facilities would later serve Montreal's second francophone university, the [[Université du Québec à Montréal]] (UQAM).

===Nuclear research===

{{Main|Montréal Laboratory}}

In 1943, the university assisted the [[Western Allies]] by providing laboratory accommodations on its campus. Scientists there worked to develop a nuclear reactor, notably by conducting various [[heavy water]] experiments. The research was part of the larger [[Manhattan Project]], which aimed to develop the first [[atomic bomb]]. Scientists here managed to produce the first [[atomic battery]] to work outside of the [[United States]]. One of the participating [[Quebec|Québécois]] scientists, Pierre Demers, also discovered a series of radioactive elements issued from [[Neptunium]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1943-a.html#b Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Growth and expansion===

[[Image:Exterior of Ecole Polytechnique de Montreal.jpg|200px|thumb|right|École Polytechnique as it stands today.]]

Two distinct schools eventually became affiliated to the university. The first was the [[École Polytechnique de Montréal|École Polytechnique]], a school of engineering, which was founded in 1873 and became affiliated in 1887. The second was the [[HEC Montréal|École des Hautes Études Commerciales]], or HEC, which was founded in 1907 and became part of the university in 1915.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;
The first francophone school of architecture in Canada opened in 1907 at the École Polytechnique.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0009565 The Canadian Encyclopedia - Architectural Education]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Between 1920 and 1925, seven new faculties were added to the initial three: Philosophy, Literature, Sciences, Veterinary medicine, Dental surgery, Pharmacy and Social sciences.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;
Notably, the Faculty of Social sciences was founded in 1920 by [[Édouard Montpetit]], the first [[Laïcité|laic]] to lead a faculty.&lt;ref&gt;[http://125.umontreal.ca/histoire/1919-b.html Université de Montréal - Fêtes du 125&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; - 125 ans d'histoire (1878-2003)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]  {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; He thereafter fulfilled the role of secretary-general until 1950.

In 1965, the appointment of the university's first secular rector, [[Roger Gaudry]], paved the way for modernization. The university established the first adult education degree program offered by a [[French Canadian]] university in 1968.

An important event that marked the university's history was the [[École Polytechnique massacre]]. On December 6, 1989, a gunman armed with an automatic rifle entered the École Polytechnique building, killing 14 people, all of whom were women, before taking his own life.

Since 2002, the university has embarked on its largest construction projects since the late 1960s, with five new modern buildings planned for advanced research in pharmacology, engineering, aerospace, cancer studies and biotechnology.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;

==Campus==
[[Image:Université de Montréal map2.png|thumb|left|200px|Mont-Royal campus.]]
[[File:Universite-de-Montreal-tower.jpg|thumb|Pavillon Roger-Gaudry.]]
The university's main campus is located on the northern slope of [[Mont-Royal]] in the [[Outremont (borough)|Outremont]] and [[Côte-des-Neiges]] boroughs. Its landmark [[Pavilion (structure)|Pavilion]] [[Roger Gaudry|Roger-Gaudry]] , which was designed by the noted architect [[Ernest Cormier]], can be seen from around the campus and is known for its imposing tower. It is built mainly in the [[Art Deco]] style, with some elements of [[International style (architecture)|International style]].

The campus is served by the [[Côte-des-Neiges (Montreal Metro)|Côte-des-Neiges]], [[Université-de-Montréal (Montreal Metro)|Université-de-Montreal]], and [[Édouard-Montpetit (Montreal Metro)|Édouard-Montpetit]] [[Montreal Metro|metro]] stations.

Apart from its main Mont-Royal campus, the university also maintains four regional facilities in [[Lanaudière]], [[Laval, Québec|Laval]], [[Longueuil]], [[Québec City|Québec]] and [[Mauricie]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campusregionaux.umontreal.ca/ Université de Montréal - Bureau de l'enseignement régional] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campus in Laval, just north of Montréal, was opened in 2006. It is Laval's first university campus, and is located in the area near the [[Montmorency (Montreal Metro)|Montmorency]] metro station. In October 2009, the university announced an expansion to its Laval satellite campus with the commissioning of its six-storey Cité du Savoir complex.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cité du Savoir&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cyberpresse.ca/actualites/quebec-canada/education/200910/14/01-911374-nouveau-campus-de-ludm-a-laval.php|title=Nouveau campus de l'UdM à Laval|last=Croteau|first=Martin|date=October 14, 2009|work=La Presse|language=French|accessdate=2009-10-16|location=Montreal}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to solve the problem of lack of space on its main campus, the university is also planning to open a new campus in [[Outremont (borough)|Outremont]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.siteoutremont.umontreal.ca/ Université de Montréal - Outremont facility project page] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal]] (CHUM) and the [[Centre hospitalier universitaire Sainte-Justine]] are the two teaching hospital networks of the Université de Montréal's Faculty of Medicine, although the latter is also affiliated with other medical institutions such as the Institut universitaire de gériatrie de Montréal, Montreal Heart Institute, Hôpital Sacré-Coeur and Hôpital Maisonneuve-Rosemont.

===Student life===

There are various student groups, clubs and associations on the university's campus, the largest of them being the [[FAÉCUM]], a federation of [[students' union]]s.

The campus offers various student-run newspapers, the largest being ''Quartier Libre'', a member of the [[Canadian University Press]] (CUP). The campus also has its own student-run radio station, [[CISM-FM]].

The Université de Montréal officially recognized one fraternity on the campus: [[Sigma Thêta Pi]] .&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sae.umontreal.ca/groupes.htm Université de Montréal Student Group]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
===Faculties===
[[Image:Faculté de Musique UdeM.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Université de Montréal's Faculty of Music]]
*Faculty of Landscape Architecture, Design and Urban Planning. The Faculty of Architecture offers a program in architecture accredited by the Canadian Architectural Certification Board at both the bachelor level (B.Arch.) and the master's level (M.Arch.). &lt;ref&gt; http://www.raic.org/architecture_architects/becoming_an_architect/education_e.htm Architecture Canada &lt;/ref&gt; 
*Faculty of Arts and Sciences
*[[Université de Montréal Faculty of Law|Faculty of Law]]
*Faculty of Continuing Education
*Faculty of Graduate Studies
*[[Université de Montréal Faculty of Medicine|Faculty of Medicine]]
*Faculty of Dentistry
*[[Université de Montréal Faculty of Veterinary Medicine|Faculty of Veterinary Medicine]]
*Faculty of Music
*Faculty of Pharmacy
*Faculty of Education
*Faculty of Nursing
*Faculty of Theology and Religious Studies
*Department of Kinesiology
*School of Optometry

===Affiliated schools===
*[[HEC Montréal]] (School of Management)
*[[École Polytechnique de Montréal|École Polytechnique]] (School of Engineering)

===Research centres===
Several research-dedicated organizations can also be found on the university's campus, such as the [[Centre for International Studies]] and the Centre de Recherches Mathématiques.

===Rankings===
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2009}}
{{Canadian university rankings
| UniName = Université de Montréal
| QS_W = 137
| ARWU_CAN = 5-6
| MAC_med = 12
| MAC_comp = 
| MAC_undergrad =
| ARWU_W = 102-150
| ARWU_SCI =
| ARWU_ENG =
| ARWU_LIFE =
| ARWU_MED =
| ARWU_SOC = 76-100
| THES_W = 104
| THES_HEAL = 47
}}

====National====
The Université de Montréal was ranked 13th (among 15 universities) in Canada in the category &quot;Medical Doctoral&quot; in the [[Maclean's]] 18th Annual Ranking issue, which ranks Canadian universities only.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} The Medical Doctoral category ranks universities that have a broad range of Ph.D. programs and research, as well as medical schools. Furthermore, since Maclean's began ranking Canadian law schools in 2007, it has placed Universite de Montréal's law school first overall [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]] school for the second year in a row.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} Meanwhile, the ''Gourman Ranking of Canadian Universities'' ranked Universite de Montréal 12th (over 60 universities in Canada) in its 1998 report on undergraduate programs.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

====International====
International rankings have been comparatively generous to Université de Montréal. However, in 2011 [[QS World University Rankings]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011?page=2&lt;/ref&gt; ranked the university 137th in the world (and sixth in Canada), dropping back 29 places from its position of 107th in the [[THE-QS World University Rankings]].&lt;ref&gt;[[QS Top Universities]], &quot;[http://www.topuniversities.com/world-university-rankings-1#columns=school|country|rank2009|rank2008|score2009|classification2009|arts_rank2009|engineering_rank2009|life_rank2009|natural_rank2009|social_rank2009@@@&amp;grid_url=/sites/all/modules/university_rankings/rankings.json.php?search_name=minnesota&amp;search_country=Country&amp;search_rank=|grid_page=1|grid_rowNum=25|grid_sortname=rank2009|grid_sortorder=asc]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The same research ranked Université de Montréal 81st in the world for arts and humanities, 83rd for [[life sciences]], 86 for [[social sciences]], 117 for engineering and technology, and 128 for [[natural sciences]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Times Higher Education]], &quot;[http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/hybrid.asp?typeCode=438 QS World University Rankings: Top 200 World Universities]&quot;. 01-10-2009. (Retrieved 13-11-2009)&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] 2011, Université de Montréal ranked 5th to 6th in Canada and 102nd to 150st in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_CAN&quot; /&gt; The [[Global University Ranking]] 2009 placed Université de Montréal 72-73rd in the world and 3rd in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globaluniversitiesranking.org/images/banners/top-100(eng).pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Newsweek]] Top 100 Global Universities ranking does not include Universite de Montréal as one of the top 100 universities in the world.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} In 2009, [[Forbes]] ranked Université de Montréal's business school, [[HEC Montréal]], 10th in the world among non-U.S. universities for its one-year [[MBA]] program. Université de Montréal ranked 1st in Canada in the one-year MBA program category.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

==Athletics==
The university is represented in [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]] by the [[Montreal Carabins|Carabins]]. The Carabins, whose origins date back to 1922,&lt;ref name=carabins1&gt;[http://www.carabins.umontreal.ca/pages/APropos/historique.aspx?lang=FR-CA Université de Montréal - Carabins - Historique] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; currently rank among the top 10 university teams in Canada. The organization has over 350 student athletes organized in 17 different teams and 10 disciplines: badminton, [[Canadian football|football]], golf, swimming, alpine skiing, [[Association football|soccer]], tennis, hockey, cheerleading and volleyball. Following the establishment of a Club of Governors in June 2002, the Carabins are now partly financed through private funds. Initially led by [[Formula One]] [[List of Formula One Grands Prix|Grand Prix]] president Normand Legault, the Club is composed of various business personalities and is currently headed by [[Rona (company)|Rona]] CEO Robert Dutton.

On January 31, 2008, the Carabins announced the creation of its first female hockey team, which after training and preparation should officially start competing by fall 2009.&lt;ref name=carabins1 /&gt;

==Faculty and alumni==
{{Main|List of Université de Montréal people}}

===Noted faculty===

* [[Stéphane Dion]], former professor of political science, leader of the [[Liberal Party of Canada]] (2006–2008).
* [[Hubert Lacroix]], associate professor with Faculty of Law
* [[James R. Taylor]], professor emeritus at the department of communication.
* [[Michel Seymour]], professor of philosophy.
* [[Dale C. Thomson]], [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|DFC]], professor and departmental director. Also professor and Vice-Principal of [[McGill University]] and a professor of international relations and Director of the Center of Canadian Studies at [[Johns Hopkins University|Johns Hopkins University's]] [[Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies|School of Advanced International Studies]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] and the [[author]] of several important historical works.
* [[Jean-Daniel Lafond]], former professor and former [[Viceregal consort of Canada]].
* [[Igor Melchuk]], former professor of linguistics and translation.
* [[Jocelyn Faubert]], Director of the Visual Perception and psychophysics laboratory at the School of Optometry.

===Noted alumni===

An Order of Merit is appointed to particularly successful alumni on annual basis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.diplomes.umontreal.ca/association/evenements.aspx?id=4 Université de Montréal - Gala de l'Ordre du Mérite] {{fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Modjtaba Sadria]], Philosopher, Honorary Professor of Centre for Ethics in Medicine and Society in Monash University, Australia
*[[Ishfaq Ahmad]], nuclear physicist and pioneer of Pakistani nuclear program
*[[Stéphanie Allard-Gomez]], diplomat
*[[Carlos Alvarado-Larroucau]], francophone author, poetry, novel, essay.
*[[Louise Arbour]], Supreme Court of Canada Justice (1999&amp;ndash;2004), UN High Commissioner for Human Rights (2004&amp;ndash;2008)
*[[Denys Arcand]], filmmaker
*[[Michel Bastarache]], Supreme Court of Canada Justice (1997&amp;ndash;2008)
*[[Josephat T. Benoit]], nine-term Mayor of [[Manchester, New Hampshire]]
*[[Jean-Jacques Bertrand]], Premier of Québec (1968&amp;ndash;1970)
*[[André Boisclair]], leader of the Parti Québécois (2005&amp;ndash;2007)
*[[Robert Bourassa]], Premier of Québec (1970&amp;ndash;1976, 1985&amp;ndash;1994)
*[[Louis R. Chênevert]], [[Chief Executive Officer|CEO]] of [[United Technologies Corporation]]
*[[Marie Deschamps]], Supreme Court of Canada Justice (2002&amp;ndash;present)
*[[Maurice Duplessis]], Premier of Québec (1936&amp;ndash;1939, 1944&amp;ndash;1959)
*[[Dédé Fortin]], singer
*[[Armand Frappier]], physician and microbiologist
*[[Lomer Gouin]], Premier of Québec (1905&amp;ndash;1920)
*[[Roger Guillemin]], Nobel Prize Laureate (Medicine, 1977)
*[[Michaëlle Jean]], journalist, Governor General of Canada
*[[Daniel Johnson, Jr.]], Premier of Québec (1994)
*[[Daniel Johnson, Sr.]], Premier of Québec (1966&amp;ndash;1968)
*[[Pierre-Marc Johnson]], Premier of Québec (1985)
*[[Antonio Lamer]], Supreme Court of Canada Chief Justice (1990&amp;ndash;2000)
*[[Blanche Lamontagne-Beauregard]], first published female poet in Québec
*[[Bernard Landry]], Premier of Québec (2001&amp;ndash;2003)
*[[Georges-Émile Lapalme]], leader of the Québec Liberal Party (1950&amp;ndash;1958)
*[[Elsie Lefebvre]], PM for the Laurier-Dorion county
*[[Isabelle Mercier]], professional poker player
*[[Anne Montminy]], competitive diver, lawyer
*[[Jacques Parizeau]], Premier of Québec (1994&amp;ndash;1996)
*[[Pierre-Karl Péladeau]], CEO of Québecor
*[[Hubert Reeves]], astrophysicist
*[[Paul Sauvé]], Premier of Québec (1959&amp;ndash;1960)
*[[Lucille Teasdale-Corti]], surgeon and international humanitarian aid worker (1929&amp;ndash;1996)
*[[Pierre Trudeau|Pierre Eliott Trudeau]], Prime Minister of Canada (1968&amp;ndash;1979, 1980&amp;ndash;1984)

==See also==
{{Portal box|Montreal|University}}
*[[Canal Savoir]]
*[[Education in Montréal]]
*[[Fédération des associations étudiantes du campus de l'Université de Montréal]]
*[[List of Québec universities]]
*[[List of universities with accredited dietetic programs]]
*[[Higher education in Québec]]
*[[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]]
*[[Canadian government scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian university scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian industrial research and development organizations]]
*[[Centre for International Studies]]
*[[Poly-World]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Bizier, Hélène-Andrée. 1993. ''L'Université de Montréal: la quête du savoir''. Montréal: Libre expression. 311 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 2891115228 [http://openlibrary.org/b/OL14721366M]

==External links==
*[http://www.umontreal.ca Université de Montréal]
*[http://www.imtl.org/search.php?name=Universit%E9+de+Montr%E9al&amp;vsearch=1 Pictures and information on Université de Montréal buildings]

{{Montreal}}
{{Qc_Uni}}
{{G13}}
{{International Forum of Public Universities}}
{{Canadian law schools}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Montreal, Universite De}}
[[Category:Art Deco buildings in Canada]]
[[Category:Université de Montréal|*]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1878]]
[[Category:Universities in Quebec]]
[[Category:Medical education in Canada]]
[[Category:Association of Commonwealth Universities]]
[[Category:Ernest Cormier buildings]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Montreal]]

[[cs:Université de Montréal]]
[[de:Universität Montreal]]
[[es:Universidad de Montreal]]
[[fa:دانشگاه مونترآل]]
[[fr:Université de Montréal]]
[[ko:몬트리올 대학교]]
[[it:Università di Montréal]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת מונטריאול]]
[[la:Universitas Montis Regii]]
[[lt:Monrealio universitetas]]
[[nl:Universiteit van Montréal]]
[[ja:モントリオール大学]]
[[no:Université de Montréal]]
[[pl:Uniwersytet Montrealu]]
[[pt:Universidade de Montreal]]
[[ru:Монреальский университет]]
[[uk:Монреальський університет]]
[[zh:蒙特利尔大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
