<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7974318" ns="0" title="UCLA Taser incident"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''UCLA Taser incident''' occurred on November 14, 2006, when Mostafa Tabatabainejad, a fourth-year [[University of California, Los Angeles|UCLA]] student, was [[Taser#Drive Stun|stunned]] multiple times with a [[Taser]] by [[University of California Police Department|campus police]], for allegedly refusing to be escorted out of the College Library Instructional Computing Commons (CLICC) lab at [[Powell Library]]. The police had been called after Tabatabainejad had refused to provide his BruinCard (student [[Identity document|ID]]) to a UCLA Community Service Officer during a routine check. Part of the incident was recorded on video by a [[camera phone]].

Tabatabainejad, an [[Iranian-American]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://cbs2.com/local/local_story_319101652.html &quot;Campus Police Use Stun Gun On UCLA Student&quot;], [[CBS]]2 Los Angeles, November 15, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; who adheres to the [[Bahá'í Faith]],&lt;ref name=&quot;cb2-groups-call&quot;&gt;[http://cbs2.com/topstories/local_story_321104536.html &quot;Groups Call For Answers In UCLA Stun Gun Incident&quot;], the [[Associated Press]] at [[CBS]]2 Los Angeles, November 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-suit-Taser&quot;&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=39026 &quot;Student to file suit in Taser incident&quot;] by Sara Taylor, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; said through his lawyers that he refused to identify himself because he believed himself a victim of [[racial profiling]] and that the tasing was an instance of [[police brutality]].

Tabatabainejad filed a federal lawsuit alleging that the officers used excessive force and that they violated the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|Americans with Disabilities Act]]. The case was settled on May 15, 2009, with UCLA agreeing to pay $220,000 to Tabatabainejad. 

==Incident==
At approximately 11:30 p.m. on November 14, 2006, Community Service Officers were conducting routine checks of students' BruinCard IDs in [[Powell Library]]. [[University of California Police Department|UCPD]] Assistant Chief of Police Jeff Young said the checks are a standard procedure in the 24-hour library after 11:00 p.m., when use of the library is restricted to staff, faculty and students.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;&gt;[http://www.dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=38960 &quot;Community responds to Taser use in Powell&quot;] by Sara Taylor, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Tabatabainejad refused to produce university identification, he was asked to leave the premises.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-file-suit&quot;&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=39009 &quot;Student to file suit against UCPD&quot;] by Sara Taylor, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; When Tabatabainejad failed to leave, UCPD officers were called to the scene,&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;/&gt; arriving approximately 10 minutes later.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-report&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- p.14 (18 in file) --&gt; Following a confrontation, the officers used the Taser in its [[Taser#Drive_Stun|&quot;Drive Stun&quot;]] capacity.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;/&gt; In this mode, the Taser causes pain without incapacitating the target.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aele.org/taser-lvmpd.pdf &quot;Use of the Taser&quot;] from the Las Vegas Metropolitan Police Department.&lt;/ref&gt;

Tabatabainejad was released from custody after being given a citation for obstruction/delay of a peace officer in the performance of duty.  According to a press release issued by the UCPD, he was also issued a court date.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucpd-memo&quot;&gt;[http://www.ucpd.ucla.edu/ucpd/zippdf/2006/Taser%2011-15-06.pdf &quot;Re: Powell Library Incident&quot;], memo released by the UCLA Police Department.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Officers===
Terrence Duren, a former [[United States Marine Corps|Marine]] and 18-year veteran of the [[University of California Police Department#UCPD, Los Angeles|UCLA Police Department]], tasered Tabatabainejad multiple times. The 2001 UCLA Officer of the Year,&lt;ref name=&quot;Duren Named 2001 Officer of Year&quot;&gt;[http://www.ucpd.ucla.edu/ucpd/officer_of_the_year_2001.html Officer of the Year 2001], [[University of California Police Department#UCPD, Los Angeles|UCPD]], [[UCLA]], 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Duren has been the subject of other use-of-force complaints and previously recommended for dismissal.&lt;ref name=lat1&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2006/nov/21/local/me-taser21 &quot;Officer in Taser case identified&quot;] by Charles Proctor and Richard Winton, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', November 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In an October 2003 incident, Duren shot and wounded a homeless man in a University building, a case that went to trial. In May 1990, Duren was accused of using his nightstick to choke Kent S. Scott, who was idling in front of a fraternity late on a Saturday night. Scott sued and the university moved to have Duren removed from the force, but later gave him 90 days’ suspension.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat1&quot;/&gt; Duren has stated all of the past allegations against him regarding police misconduct and use of excessive force were investigated by the UCPD and proven false.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-officer-named&quot;&gt;[http://www.dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=39047 &quot;Officer named in Taser incident&quot;] by Sara Taylor, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;  (The homeless man was convicted of assaulting an officer.&lt;ref name=lat1 /&gt;) Prior to joining the UCPD in the late 1980s, Duren was fired from the [[Long Beach Police Department (California)|Long Beach Police Department]] due to &quot;poor report-writing skills and geographical knowledge&quot;.&lt;ref name=lat1/&gt; Following the Tasering incident, Duren remained on active duty.

Also on the scene were Officers Alexis Bicomong, Kevin Kilgore, and Andrew Ikeda.  *

===Video and eyewitness accounts===
Part of the event is recorded in a [[#External links|six-minute cell phone video recorded by another student]].  The video has been widely disseminated online, and an edited version is available on the ''[[Daily Bruin]]'' site. Tabatabainejad is first heard (though not seen) repeatedly shouting &quot;Don't touch me!&quot; to the officers. Over the course of the video, he is stunned multiple times, while officers repeatedly order him to stand up and stop fighting, and threaten to administer further stuns. Tabatabainejad repeatedly states that he is not fighting and that he will leave the premises.  He shouts that he has a medical condition,&lt;ref name=&quot;db_breaking_news&quot;&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/2006/nov/15/breaking-news-student-shot-wit/ &quot;Student shot with Taser by UCPD officers&quot;] by Lisa Connolly, Derek Lipkin and Saba Riazati, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 15, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and shouts &quot;Here's your [[USA PATRIOT Act|PATRIOT Act]]! Here's your fucking abuse of power!&quot;  Witnesses say that when it was clear none of the other students were going to help him, Tabatabainejad said &quot;Am I the only [[martyr]]?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;chicago trib&quot;&gt;[http://www.chicagotribune.com/technology/la-me-taser18nov18,1,7745969.story?ctrack=1&amp;cset=true &quot;UCLA orders outside probe of Taser arrest&quot;] by R. Winton, ''[[The Chicago Tribune]]'', November 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; According to one witness, &quot;[Tabatabainejad was] no possible danger to any of the police.  [He was] getting shocked and Tasered as he was handcuffed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;/&gt; Bystanders can be heard demanding the officers' names and badge numbers, and shouting for them to stop using the Taser on Tabatabainejad.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;/&gt;

At one point, the officers told the crowd to stand back and threatened to tase anyone who approached too closely.&lt;ref name=&quot;db_breaking_news&quot;/&gt; A female student said that the officers threatened to tase her when she asked an officer for his name and badge number.&lt;ref name=&quot;db_breaking_news&quot;/&gt; According to an [[American Civil Liberties Union|ACLU]] attorney, such a threat of force in response to a badge number request constitutes illegal assault.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;/&gt; At 6:36 in the video, an officer tells a male student, &quot;Get back over there or you’re going to get tased, too.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-community-responds&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-report&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- p.40 (44 in file) --&gt; The student, wearing a white t-shirt in the video, can be seen &quot;using intense body language&quot; and &quot;talking heatedly and with raised [voice]&quot;&lt;!-- voices --&gt; prior to being confronted.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-report&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- p.39 (43 in file) --&gt; The officer first tells the student to &quot;back up&quot; before threatening tasing.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-report&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- p.40 (44 in file) --&gt;

A press release issued by the UCPD claims that the officers &quot;asked Tabatabainejad to leave the premises multiple times&quot;, and that Tabatabainejad refused to leave.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucpd-memo&quot;/&gt;
Witnesses dispute this account, saying that Tabatabainejad had begun to walk toward the door with his backpack when an officer approached him and grabbed his arm, whereupon Tabatabainejad told the officer several times to let go.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes-a-third&quot;&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-cellcamera16nov16,0,4794591.story?page=1&amp;coll=la-home-headlines &quot;A third incident, a new video&quot;] by Amanda Covarrubias and Stuart Silverstein, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', November 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Tabatabainejad has said through his lawyers that he was stunned five times,&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-file-suit&quot;/&gt; which is the count reported in the media immediately after the incident.&lt;ref name=lat1/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-usac-opposes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacbee.com/101/story/79337.html &quot;UCLA sets Taser probe&quot;] by Laura Mecoy, ''[[The Sacramento Bee]]'', November 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dailycal.org/sharticle.php?id=22375 &quot;Students Protest Taser Incident&quot;] by Sarah Kamshoshy, ''[[The Daily Californian]]'', ''November 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The reported count was reduced to three after the release of the independent report.&lt;ref name=&quot;db-independent-report-full&quot;/&gt;

The independent report clarifies:
{{Quote|It is our understanding that Tabatabainejad remembers being tased on at least four or five occasions. Officer 2 [Durden] notes at the conclusion of his initial report that &quot;it’s possible that I may have tased Tabatabainejad a 4th time, but I am unsure at which time this may have occurred.&quot;&lt;!-- 162 Officer 2 Supplemental Report, 2. --&gt; Various media accounts following the incident reported the common assumption from several students that Tabatabainejad &quot;was hit with a Taser five times when he did not leave.&quot;&lt;!-- 163 Sara Taylor, &quot;Student to file suit in Taser incident,&quot; ''The Daily Bruin'', 20 November 2006. --&gt; Accordingly, we cannot rule out the possibility that Tabatabainejad was tased more than the three discrete times that we have identified and confirmed. Still, we note that the internal recording system in the X26 Taser is considered by most law enforcement personnel to be reliable, and we have no reason to believe that its record of three Taser firings is inaccurate.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-report&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- p.38, 42 in file --&gt;}}

==Official response==
According to the UCPD press release from soon after the incident, &quot;Tabatabainejad went limp and refused to exit as the officers attempted to escort him out.&quot; The release also states that Tabatabainejad &quot;encouraged library patrons to join his resistance.&quot; At this point, the officers &quot;deemed it necessary to use the Taser in a 'Drive Stun' capacity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucpd-memo&quot;/&gt;

In a statement released November 15, 2006, the day after the incident, Acting Chancellor Norman Abrams said:
{{Quote|Investigators are reviewing the incident and the officers' actions. The investigation and review will be thorough, vigorous and fair.

The safety of our campus community is of paramount importance to me. Routinely checking student identification after 11 p.m. at the campus library, which is open 24 hours, is a policy posted in the library that was enacted for the protection of our students. Compliance is critical for the safety and well-being of everyone.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.ucla.edu/page.asp?RelNum=7513 &quot;Statement from UCLA Acting Chancellor Norman Abrams About Incident at Powell Library&quot;], November 15, 2006. Accessed August 4, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On November 17, 2006, a press conference was held by Abrams and UCPD Chief Karl Ross, during which it was announced that the UCPD was planning to conduct an independent investigation into the incident led by Merrick Bobb, president of the [[Police Assessment Resource Center]].&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucla-bulletin&quot;&gt;[http://www.ucla.edu/bulletin/powell-incident.html &quot;Powell Incident Investigation&quot;] ''[[UCLA]]'', November 17, 2006. Accessed August 4, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 18, 2006, Iran's Foreign Ministry spokesman Mohammad-Ali Hosseini condemned the incident, and urged punishment for those responsible.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irna.ir/en/news/view/menu-236/0611189589150523.htm &quot;Spokesman condemns beating of Iranian student by US police&quot;], [[Islamic Republic News Agency]], November 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 1, 2007, the results of the internal and independent investigations were released, nine months after the incident. The independent investigation found a number of policy violations, but the internal investigation found none. According to Abrams's statement, the difference in conclusions &quot;is not unusual in the legal system. Reasonable people may disagree regarding the inferences to be drawn from the same set of facts, and the facts may differ if some witnesses testify in one investigation and not in the other.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.ucla.edu/page.asp?RelNum=8131 &quot;Statement Regarding Report of Independent Investigation of Taser Incident at UCLA&quot;], UCLA Office of Media Relations, August 1, 2007. Accessed August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The internal investigation is confidential, but the full independent report is available for review.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-report&quot;&gt;''[http://www.newsroom.ucla.edu/taserreport/ A Bad Night at Powell Library: The Events of November 14, 2006]'' by Merrick Bobb, Matthew Barge and Camelia Naguib, [http://www.parc.info/ Police Assessment Resource Center], August 2007. Accessed September 3, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 10, 2007, the UCLA Police Department released its new policy governing Taser use. The policy was developed from recommendations made in the independent report and with input from experts on Tasers and police use-of-force policy. School administrators and student leaders were asked to review and comment on the policy before it was finalized.&lt;ref name=&quot;db_new_policy&quot;&gt;[http://www.dailybruin.com/news/2007/dec/10/new-taser-policy-released/ &quot;New Taser policy released&quot;] by Anthony Pesce, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', December 10, 2007. Accessed January 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Community response==
[[Image:Taser rally.jpg|thumb|right|Student news conference on taser incident, November 17, 2006.]]

On November 17, 2006, 400 protesters,&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-ucla-community&quot;/&gt; including UCLA faculty and staff, parents, community members, and UCLA students, gathered at [[Kerckhoff Hall]] to protest the incident.  This was followed by a march to the UCPD police station, where protesters were met by officers in riot gear.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-file-suit&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-taser18nov18,0,4080498.story?coll=la-home-headlines &quot;UCLA orders outside probe of Taser arrest&quot;] by Richard Winton, Rong-Gong Lin II and Charles Proctor, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', November 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The protest was organized by more than fifty student organizations to demand an independent investigation into the incident, and to demand the inclusion of students in the investigation.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-ucla-community&quot;&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=39010 &quot;UCLA community gathers to protest Taser incident, campus violence&quot;] by Julia Erlandson and Anthony Pesce, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Combiz Abdolrahimi, chairman of the National Iranian-American Council at UCLA, said that the chancellor should &quot;appoint students who will be able to make sure the investigation is transparent&quot;. He also called for a temporary suspension of the officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-ucla-community&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Taser rally 2.jpg|thumb|left|Students protest taser incident, November 17, 2006.]]

On the same day as the protest, Abrams announced an independent investigation in addition to the internal investigation.&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucla-bulletin&quot;/&gt;

On November 18, 2006, the [[University of California Students Association]] passed a &quot;Police Brutality Resolution&quot; regarding recent incidents at [[University of California, Santa Cruz|UC Santa Cruz]] and UCLA.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucsa-resolution&quot;&gt;[http://www.ucsa.org/board/resolutions/PoliceBrutalityResolution_Final.pdf &quot;UCSA Police Brutality Resolution&quot;], by Foaad Khosmood, Doug Jorgesen, and Tina Park, November 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; A ''Daily Bruin'' editorial criticized the UCLA portion of the resolution, describing it as &quot;full of inaccuracies&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-edit-ucsa&quot;&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=39144 &quot;Editorial: UCSA Taser resolution inaccurate, uninformed&quot;], ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 29, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 21, 2006, the UCLA Undergraduate Students Association Council passed a resolution &quot;opposing inappropriate force against students by university police&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-usac-opposes&quot;&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/2006/nov/22/usac-opposes-inappropriate-for/ &quot;USAC opposes 'inappropriate force'&quot;] by Kimberly Young and Jennifer Han, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', November 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lawsuit==
Tabatabainejad's former lawyer, Stephen Yagman, announced on November 17, 2006 that he planned to file a lawsuit against university police alleging &quot;brutal excessive force&quot; and false arrest.&lt;ref name=&quot;bruin-file-suit&quot;/&gt; According to Yagman, Tabatabainejad was asked to show his university identification card and did not do so because he believed he was being singled out for racial profiling. Yagman, who characterized the incident as an example of police brutality, claimed Tabatabainejad was the only person who was asked to show ID. A November 22, 2006 article in the ''Los Angeles Times'' reported that Yagman had said on November 21 that he was no longer representing Tabatabainejad.

On January 17, 2007, Tabatabainejad filed a federal lawsuit alleging the campus officers used excessive force, and that they violated the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]]. He was seeking unspecified damages.&lt;ref name=lat-taser-lawsuit-filed&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-011707taser,0,6813210.story?coll=la-home-headlines &quot;UCLA student sues over tasering&quot;] by Andrew Blankstein, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', January 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the lawsuit, Tabatabainejad has [[bipolar disorder]] and informed the officers of his condition, but was treated in a way that constitutes discrimination under the ADA.&lt;ref name=db-taser-lawsuit-filed&gt;[http://dailybruin.com/news/2007/jan/18/student-files-lawsuit-over-tas/ &quot;Student files lawsuit over Taser use&quot;] by Sara Taylor, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', January 18, 2007. Accessed June 3, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; His attorney, Paul Hoffman, said that a February 2008 court date had been set.&lt;ref name=db-independent-report-full&gt;[http://www.dailybruin.com/news/2007/aug/06/report_examines_use_force/ &quot;Report examines use of force&quot;] by Anthony Pesce, ''[[Daily Bruin]]'', August 6, 2007. Accessed August 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; On May 15, 2009, UCLA announced that the university would pay $220,000&lt;ref&gt;[http://dailybruin.ucla.edu/stories/2009/may/18/taser-plaintiff-awarded-220000/ &quot;Taser plaintiff awarded $220,000&quot;], The Daily Bruin, May 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; to settle the civil rights lawsuit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.ucla.edu/portal/ucla/ucla-and-former-student-settle-92329.aspx &quot;UCLA and former student settle Taser case&quot;], UCLA Newsroom, May 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==UCPD policy on Taser use==
The UCLA PD policy in effect at the time of the incident calls the Taser a &quot;less lethal device&quot; and says that &quot;although not absolutely prohibited, officers should give additional consideration to the unique circumstances involved prior to applying the Taser to ...&lt;!-- excerpts 1 item from a list --&gt; Individuals who are handcuffed or otherwise restrained&quot; (4C). According to the policy, the &quot;Drive Stun&quot; capacity is appropriate &quot;to eliminate physical resistance from an arrestee in accomplishing an arrest or physical search&quot; (6A) as well as &quot;pain compliance against passive resistors&quot; (6B).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucpd.ucla.edu/ucpd/zippdf/2006/Taser_Policies.pdf General Order 05-01], UCPD policy on Taser use, amended September 27, 2005.  Accessed March 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the ten UC campus police departments, six have equipped officers with Tasers, but only UCLA had a flexible policy authorizing Tasers to be used as a pain-compliance tool against suspects who are passively resisting.&lt;ref name=lat-taser-use-limited&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-taser22nov22,1,6782386.story?coll=la-headlines-california&amp;ctrack=1&amp;cset=true &quot;Taser use limited at most UC campuses&quot;] by Rong-Gong Lin II, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', November 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The UCLA PD released its new Taser policy on December 10, 2007. According to UCPD Chief Karl Ross, the new policy is considerably longer, includes specific definitions of appropriate and inappropriate use, and explicitly prohibits use against a &quot;passive resister&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;db_new_policy&quot;/&gt;&lt;!-- prefer to directly cite new policy if found --&gt;

==See also==
*[[Taser controversy]]
*[[Taser safety issues]]
*[[Taser International]] - Taser Manufacturer
*[[Braidwood Inquiry]] - Official Canadian inquiry into Tasers and similar devices
*[[University of Florida Taser incident]]
*[[Robert Dziekański Taser incident]]
*[[Iman Morales Taser incident]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://dailybruin.com/news/articles.asp?id=39014 ''Daily Bruin'' TV: Students march at UCLA to protest actions taken by police against student]
*[http://www.linder.com/archives/category/ucla-taser-cops/ KNX Newsradio audio of the Nov. 17th Abrams press conference and an eyewitness account of the taser incident.]
&lt;!---

Video below is not subject to normal Wikipedia copyright restrictions on linking to YouTube -- please see talk page before removing. (Kane5187, 10:49, 19 November 2006).

--&gt;
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5g7zlJx9u2E YouTube video of the incident caught on a cameraphone]
* [http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGAMR511392004 Excessive and lethal force? Amnesty International's concerns about deaths and ill-treatment involving police use of tasers]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ucla Taser Incident}}
[[Category:University of California, Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Electroshock weapon controversies]]
[[Category:Taser]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
