<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="798120" ns="0" title="University of Evansville"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|image=
|motto= Civic Mission…Sacred Trust
|name=University of Evansville&lt;/font&gt;
|established=1854 ([[University of Evansville#History|details]])
|type=[[private university|private]] [[coeducational]]
|endowment=$59.6 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|faculty65646
|president=[[Thomas A. Kazee]]
|city=[[Evansville, Indiana|Evansville]]
|state=[[Indiana]]
|country=[[United States|USA]]
|students=3,050
|undergrad=2,900
|postgrad=150
|campus=[[Urban area|Urban]]; 100&amp;nbsp;acres (0.32&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)
|free_label=Athletics Conference
|free = [[Missouri Valley Conference]]
|athletics=14 [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] teams,&lt;br /&gt;called [[Evansville Purple Aces|Purple Aces]]
|colors=[[Purple]] and [[White]]
|mascot=Ace Purple
|affiliations=[[United Methodist Church]]
|website=[http://www.evansville.edu/ www.evansville.edu]
}}

The '''University of Evansville''' ('''UE''') is a small, private [[university]] with approximately 3,050 students located in [[Evansville, Indiana]]. Founded in 1854 as Moores Hill College, it is located near the interchange of the [[Lloyd Expressway]] and [[U.S. Route 41]]. It is affiliated with the [[United Methodist Church]]. The University features [[liberal arts]] and [[science]]s degrees, most with strong cooperative learning opportunities both on and off campus.

UE operates a satellite [[campus]], [[Harlaxton Manor|Harlaxton College]], in [[Grantham]], [[England]]. UE athletic teams participate in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] athletics as a member of the [[Missouri Valley Conference]]. The teams are known as the Purple Aces. The University of Evansville is nationally renowned for its Theatre and Physical Therapy departments. The University is known as a leader in the area of [[New Formalism]] poetry{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}} as the home of [[The Formalist]] and its successor journal, [[Measure (journal)|Measure]]. The University of Evansville Press also publishes exclusively books and anthologies on formal poetry, including an annual winner of its [[Richard Wilbur]] Award.

== Academics ==
On April 9, 2010 the Board of Trustees selected Thomas A. Kazee, former Executive Vice President and Provost at Furman University, as the University of Evansville's 23rd president. Former president Stephen G. Jennings began retiring in May 2010.
Kazee assumed Presidential duties on June 1, 2010. In August 2010, ''[[Forbes]]'' magazine listed the University of Evansville at No. 296 on their 610&amp;nbsp;&quot;Best Colleges&quot; list. This list was compiled from 6,600 colleges and universities worldwide, with the note that there was very little distinction between the highest rated institution to the last as the criteria for inclusion was extremely high and those institutions cited all share excellent status as institutions of Higher Learning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =Martin| first =John| title =Forbes lists UE among best schools| publisher =[[Evansville Courier &amp; Press]]| date =2010-08-15| url =http://www.courierpress.com/news/2010/aug/15/no-headline---15a03ue-brf/| accessdate =2010-08-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; That same month, ''[[US News &amp; World Report]]'' recognized the University of Evansville as one of the 10&amp;nbsp;best regional universities in the Midwest in its annual ranking of &quot;America's Best Colleges&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =Brubeck| first =Sarah| title =UE ranks with 'America's Best Colleges'| publisher =''Evansville Courier &amp; Press''| date =2010-08-16| url =http://www.courierpress.com/news/2010/aug/16/ue-ranks-with-americas-best/| accessdate =2010-08-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Colleges and schools ===
[[File:UE1.JPG|thumbnail|left|250px|Front Oval in the Spring of 2005.]]

The University of Evansville is academically organized into three colleges and two schools:
* '''College of Arts &amp; Sciences''' contains these departments: Archaeology and Art History, Art, Biology, Chemistry, Communication, English, Foreign Languages, History and Geography, Law, Politics, and Society, Mathematics, Music, Philosophy and Religion, Physics, Psychology, and Theatre
* '''College of Education &amp; Health Sciences'''
** contains the '''School of Education'''
** contains these departments: Exercise and Sports Studies, Nursing and Health Sciences, and Physical Therapy
* '''College of Engineering &amp; Computer Science''' contains the Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department and the Mechanical and Civil Engineering Department
* '''The Schroeder Family School of Business Administration''' contains the Department of Accounting and Business Administration

=== Harlaxton College ===
In addition to studying in the city of Evansville, the University's students can choose to study abroad in [[England]] at [[Harlaxton Manor|Harlaxton College]], &quot;The British Campus of the University of Evansville&quot;.  The College was formed and controlled by Stanford University prior to its passing to The University of Evansville. The college is located about 90&amp;nbsp;miles north of London in [[Lincolnshire]], a few miles away from the town of [[Grantham|Grantham, England]] (home of Sir Isaac Newton and Margaret Thatcher). The study abroad program at the University of Evansville has consistently been rated as one of the best study abroad programs in the nation, ranked #1 in Europe and #7 globally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Top 25- Study Abroad| url=http://www.ueharlax.ac.uk/about_us/college/Top25StudyAbroad.cfm | accessdate=2008-07-29|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080201223009/http%3A//www.ueharlax.ac.uk/about_us/college/Top25StudyAbroad.cfm |archivedate = February 1, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Accreditations ===
{{abbreviations|section|date=February 2011}}
The electrical and mechanical engineering programs have been continuously accredited by [[ABET]] Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology since 1970, and the civil engineering and computer engineering programs since 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=ABET Accredited Programs | url=http://www.abet.org/accredited_programs.shtml | accessdate=2007-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The School of Business Administration is accredited by the [[AACSB]] Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business International and provides a variety of professional programs in accounting, economics, finance, global business, management or marketing.
The Exercise Science major is endorsed by the [[American College of Sports Medicine]] (ACSM) and the [[National Strength and Conditioning Association]] (NSCA).

== History ==
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot;
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; | '''History at a glance'''
|-
| style=&quot;width:150px;&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| Moores Hill Male and Female Collegiate Institute
| '''Established'''
| 1854
|-
| '''Opened'''
| 1856
|-
| '''Location'''
| [[Moores Hill, Indiana|Moores Hill]], [[Indiana|IN]] [[USA]]
|-
| style=&quot;width:150px;&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Moores Hill College
| '''Renamed'''
| 1887&lt;ref name=history&gt;{{cite web| title=The History of the University of Evansville | publisher=University of Evansville | url=http://www.evansville.edu/150/history.asp?version=1 | accessdate=2007-03-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070313081658/http://www.evansville.edu/150/history.asp?version=1  |archivedate = 2007-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Closed'''
| 1917&lt;ref name=history /&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;width:150px;&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Evansville College
| '''Reopened'''
| 1919
|-
| '''Location'''
| [[Evansville, Indiana|Evansville]], [[Indiana|IN]] [[USA]]
|-
| style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;| University of Evansville
| '''Renamed'''
| 1967
|}

The University of Evansville began in 1854 when Moores Hill Male and Female Collegiate Institute was founded by John Moore in the small town of Moores Hill in southeastern Indiana. The first college building at Moores Hill, Moore Hall, was completed on December 1, 1856, although the opening day of classes for the new college were held in the unfinished building on [[September 9]]th. The institution struggled financially during its time in Moores Hill, and a fire destroyed Moore Hall in 1915. The institution continued to operate in a second building, Carnegie Hall, until the move to Evansville.  The former campus in Moores Hill continued operation as an elementary and high school.  Carnegie Hall is now maintained as a museum.

On March 21, 1917, George S. Clifford made a presentation at a special session of the Indiana Conference of the [[Methodist Church]]. He suggested moving the college to [[Evansville, Indiana]]. Clifford produced a map that indicated a lack of colleges in the Evansville area - there were none within 50&amp;nbsp;miles of the city within Indiana. After deliberation, the school was relocated to Evansville in 1919 and renamed Evansville College. It operated in temporary quarters in downtown Evansville until Administration Hall (now Olmsted Hall) was completed in 1922. This is the only building remaining on campus from before World War II.

In the period from World War II to 1960, Evansville College grew significantly. Enrollment grew from about 400 during the [[Great Depression]] to 1,500 in 1946. Also following the war, the Science and Engineering Building and Alumni Memorial Union were commissioned. The Clifford Memorial Library was completed in 1957. Five residence halls were built between 1958 and 1967, along with a fitness center, dining hall, and an art building. In 1967, due to the institution's growth and organizational changes, the name was changed to the University of Evansville with the approval of the Indiana State General Assembly. Also in 1967, a new theater building, Hyde Hall, housing Shanklin Theater was finished.

In 2010 The University of Evansville completed early its Endowment Campaign to raise $80 million after having raised an additional $60 million five years previous to the new campaign.

== Athletics ==
{{main|Evansville Purple Aces}}
The University of Evansville athletic teams have the nickname the Purple Aces (originally the &quot;Pioneers&quot;).  Both men's and women's varsity sports play at the [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] level and compete in the [[Missouri Valley Conference]], except for the men's swimming and diving teams which compete in the [[Mid-American Conference]]

== Campus ==
The university is known for its grassy open spaces and tree cover.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} The university landscape is well maintained{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}, and many students take advantage of the spacious lawns and large shade trees.

The campus is bounded on the north by the [[Lloyd Expressway]], the south by Lincoln Avenue, west by Rotherwood Avenue, and on the east by Weinbach Avenue. Walnut Street bisects the campus. Sesquicentennial Oval, the ceremonial entrance to campus, opens off of Lincoln Avenue. The oval was named in 2004 in commemoration of the university's 150th anniversary. The Schroeder Family School of Business, McCurdy Alumni Memorial Union, Hyde Hall, Olmsted Administration Hall, Clifford Memorial Library, and Koch (pronounced Cook) Center for Science and Engineering surround Sesquicentennial Oval. Most of the buildings follow an old limestone motif, and renovations generally emulate the rest of the building.

== Accomplishments ==

In the 2008-2009 Academic school year, the University of Evansville captured a title in the Concrete Canoe over perennial winners, the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]]. The winning canoe, named Sauske, will compete at the national convention in Alabama. The American Society of Civil Engineers at UE also claimed top honors at the same conference competition. The ASCE chapter at UE has been increasing their placing in their region since 2004, steadily increasing in the ranks despite hard competition from renowned engineering schools like Purdue and UW–Madison.

== Greek life ==
Sororities
* [[Alpha Omicron Pi]] 1951
* [[Alpha Phi]] 1974-1983 (closed)
* [[Chi Omega]] 1951
* Delta Omega Zeta (local)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Delta Omega Zeta Website | url=[http://www.geocities.com/deltaomegazeta/ http://www.geocities.com/deltaomegazeta/]{{dead link|date=October 2011|bot=AnomieBOT}} | accessdate=2007-03-20}}{{dead link|date=October 2010|bot=AnomieBOT}} {{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Phi Mu]] 1952
* [[Zeta Tau Alpha]] 1964

Fraternities

* [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]] 1955
* [[Lambda Chi Alpha]] 1956
* [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]] 1957
* [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]] 1957
* [[Phi Kappa Tau]] 1968
* [[Phi Gamma Delta]] 1997

== Notable alumni ==
=== Entertainment ===
* [[David Emge]], actor ''[[Dawn of the Dead]]''
* [[Crista Flanagan]], actress, comedian ''[[MADtv|MadTV]]''
* [[Kelli Giddish]], actress ''[[All My Children]]''
* [[Ron Glass]], actor ''[[Firefly (TV series)|Firefly]]'', ''[[Barney Miller]]''
* [[Deirdre Lovejoy]], actress ''[[The Wire]]''
* [[Rami Malek]], actor ''[[The Pacific (miniseries)|The Pacific]]'', ''[[Night at the Museum]]'', ''[[Night at the Museum: Battle of the Smithsonian]]'', and ''[[The War at Home (TV series)|The War at Home]]''
* [[Jack McBrayer]], actor ''[[30 Rock]]''
* [[Jim Michaels]], producer of ''[[Supernatural]]'', ''[[Everybody Hates Chris]]'', and ''[[Lois &amp; Clark: The New Adventures of Superman]]''
* [[Carrie Preston]], actress
* [[The Watson Twins]], Musicians
* Karl Kenzler, actor ''[[Mary Poppins (musical)|Marry Poppins]]''
* Kimberly D'Armond, actor ''[[Sorry, Right Number]]''
* [[Matt Williams (producer)|Matt Williams]], producer and writer of ''[[The Cosby Show]]'', ''[[Home Improvement (TV series)|Home Improvement]]'', and ''[[Roseanne (TV series)|Roseanne]]''
* [[David McFadzean]]  producer and writer of ''Home Improvement'' and ''Roseanne''
* [[Rutina Wesley]], actress ''[[True Blood]]''

===Politics===
*[[Lloyd Winnecke]], 34th Mayor of [[Evansville, Indiana|Evansville]]
*Marsha Abell, Vanderburgh County Commissioner

=== Business ===
* [[Khalid Abdullah Almolhem|Khalid Almolhem]], Director General of [[Saudi Arabian Airlines]]
* [[Wayne Davidson]], former CEO of [[Bristol-Myers Squibb]]
* Adam Johnson, CEO of [[Hydraulic Wind Power, LLC]]

=== Sports ===
* [[Marty Amsler]], former National Football League defensive end&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.evansville.edu/donors/honorroll2008-2009/honorRollAlumni.cfm |title=Honor Roll of Donors |publisher=University of Evansville |location=1800 Lincoln Avenue, Evansville, Indiana 47722 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5sxwKWjvK |archivedate=September 23, 2010 |accessdate=September 23, 2010 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Andy Benes]], former [[MLB]] player
* [[Don Buse]], [[NBA]] All-Star
* [[Jamey Carroll]], [[MLB]] player
* [[Sal Fasano]], [[MLB]] All Star
* [[Jamie Davison]], infielder for [[Rockford Thunder]] [[National Pro Fastpitch|NPF]] pro softball team
* [[Scott Haffner]], Former NBA player who was drafted in the 2nd round of the 1989 NBA draft
* [[Mark Murray (baseball)|Mark Murray]], professional baseball player
* [[Troy Perkins]], [[DC United]] [[Major League Soccer|MLS]] Goal Keeper
* [[Jerry Sloan]], [[NBA]] player and Hall of Fame head coach
* [[Cory Elenio]], [[Columbus Crew]] [[Major League Soccer|MLS]] Midfielder
* [[Alec Dufty]], [[NY Red Bulls]] [[Major League Soccer|MLS]] Goal Keeper
* [[David Weir (Scottish footballer)|David Weir]], soccer player for [[Everton F.C.]], [[Rangers F.C.]], [[Heart of Midlothian F.C.|Hearts]] and [[Scotland]]
* [[Joe Fiorentino]] Martial Arts Champion, 2008 #1 Ranked Director Division Grappler in the Nation, Inducted into United States Martial Arts Hall of Fame, Awarded President's Volunteer Service Award from President Obama, 2010 Illinois State Bar Association Law Enforcement Award.

=== Sciences and Engineering ===
* [[Richard Harbert Smith]], professor and researcher of [[aeronautical engineering]] at [[MIT]] (1929/45).

=== Other ===
* [[John B. Conaway]], Lieutenant General and former Chief of [[National Guard Bureau]]
* [[Marilyn Durham]], novelist
* [[Lisel Mueller]], poet who won the [[Pulitzer Prize for Poetry]] in 1997
* [[David J. Lawson]], a [[Bishop]] of the [[United Methodist Church]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Bibliography ==

* Klinger, George; &quot;We Face the Future Unafraid&quot; (Evansville, Ind; University of Evansville Press, 2003).  ISBN 978-0-930982-56-0

== External links ==
* [http://www.evansville.edu/ Official website]
* [http://gopurpleaces.com Official athletics website]
* [http://www.evansville.edu/aboutue/campusmap.asp Campus map]
* [http://www.ueharlax.ac.uk/ Harlaxton College British campus]

{{Evansville, Indiana}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Metropolitan Evansville}}
{{Indiana Colleges and Universities}}
{{Missouri Valley Conference}}
{{Mid-American Conference}}
{{MethodistColleges}}
{{MUPEC}}

{{coord|37.971631|-87.531552|type:landmark_region:US|format=dms|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Evansville, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Evansville|*]]
[[Category:Education in Evansville, Indiana]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the United Methodist Church]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indiana]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1854]]
[[Category:National Register of Historic Places in Evansville, Indiana]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Evansville, Indiana]]

[[es:Universidad de Evansville]]
[[mr:युनिव्हर्सिटी ऑफ एव्हान्सव्हिल]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
