<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8024324" ns="0" title="List of Saw characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Saw'' characters}}
[[File:Saw-cast.jpg|thumb|Actors who have portrayed central characters of the series.  Top, left to right: Tobin Bell, Shawnee Smith, Cary Elwes. Bottom, left to right: Costas Mandylor, Danny Glover, Betsy Russell.|250px]]
The [[Saw (franchise)|''Saw'' series]] of [[horror films]] features a large cast of characters created primarily by Australian director [[James Wan]] and screenwriter [[Leigh Whannell]]. The series focuses on the character of [[Jigsaw (Saw)|John Kramer]] ([[Tobin Bell]]), the &quot;Jigsaw Killer&quot;, who seeks out those he considers to be wasting their lives and subjects them to torturous and lethal traps, referred to as &quot;tests&quot; and &quot;games&quot;, in an attempt to make them appreciate living.  The series comprises seven films: ''[[Saw (film)|Saw]]'' (2004), ''[[Saw II]]'' (2005), ''[[Saw III]]'' (2006), ''[[Saw IV]]'' (2007), ''[[Saw V]]'' (2008), ''[[Saw VI]]'' (2009), and ''[[Saw 3D]]'' (2010).

{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

==''Saw'' short==
===Billy{{anchor|Billy the Puppet}}===
{{main|Billy (Saw)}}
*Voiced by [[Tobin Bell]]
*Appears in: ''[[Saw (2003 film)|Saw]]'' (short), ''[[Saw: Rebirth]]'', ''[[Saw (film)|Saw]]'', ''[[Saw II]]'', ''[[Saw III]]'', ''[[Saw IV]]'', ''[[Saw V]]'', ''[[Saw VI]]'', ''[[Saw 3D]]'', ''[[Saw (video game)|Saw: The Video Game]]'', ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]''

'''Billy''' is a [[Ventriloquism#Ventriloquist's dummy|ventriloquist puppet]] created by [[#John Kramer (Jigsaw Killer)|John Kramer]] to communicate with his victims. Billy usually appears on a TV screen when talking to victims, but sometimes appears in person. Billy gives the victims their instructions to get free from their traps before the 60 seconds or minutes expires. Billy has also appeared in every adaption of ''Saw'', becoming an icon of the series. Billy was created for John and Jill Tuck's unborn son Gideon.

===David===
*Portrayed by [[Leigh Whannell]]
*Appears in: ''Saw'' short

David is Jigsaw's victim in the ''Saw'' short film. This character played the part of Amanda in the short film, which is an early version of the Jaw Splitter scene. He is portrayed by Leigh Whannell, who portrayed Adam in the first official film.

==''Saw''==
===Adam Stanheight===
{{anchor|Adam|Adam Faulkner|Adam Stanheight}}
*Portrayed by [[Leigh Whannell]]
*Appears in: ''Saw'', ''Saw III''

Adam is a photographer employed by Detective Tapp to follow the man he suspected of being the Jigsaw Killer, Lawrence Gordon. Adam is kidnapped and placed into a game alongside Gordon, with them being given conflicting goals to accomplish by a certain time. After failing to complete their tests by the deadline they were confronted by Zep Hindle. Adam beat Zep to death with a toilet tank cover while Gordon crawled away to get help. The real Jigsaw shows himself and tells Adam that the key to his restraint is in the bathtub, which is drained when Adam accidentally kicked the plug out. Adam grabs Zep's pistol and tries to shoot Jigsaw but is electrocuted by his hidden remote control before he can get a shot off. Jigsaw then turns off the lights and shuts the bathroom door, leaving Adam to die. Flashbacks in ''Saw III'' show his abduction by Jigsaw's apprentice, Amanda, and her subsequent suffocation of him with a plastic bag as an act of mercy. His decomposing corpse is shown in ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'' and ''Saw 3D''. His voice is heard near the end of ''Saw II'' after Amanda and [[List of Saw characters#Daniel Matthews|Daniel Matthews]] enter the bathroom, and he is seen in several archive flashbacks throughout ''Saw 3D''. According to the official ''Saw'' website, in a still image used in one of the flash scenes, Adam's last name is &quot;Faulkner&quot;. However, it is revealed in ''Saw V'' that Adam's last name is Stanheight, as indicated by a document observed by Agent Strahm.

===Alison and Diana Gordon===
{{anchor|Alison|Diana}}
*Portrayed by [[Monica Potter]] and [[Makenzie Vega]]
*Appears in: ''Saw''

Alison and Diana are the wife and young daughter of Lawrence Gordon.  During the events of ''Saw'', Alison and Diana were held [[hostage]] by Zep Hindle as part of Lawrence's test.  When Lawrence failed his test, Zep is meant to kill both Alison and her daughter but interference by Detective Tapp allows Lawrence's family to escape safely.

===Allison Kerry===
{{anchor|Allison|Allison Kerry}}
*Portrayed by [[Dina Meyer]]
*Appears in: ''Saw'', ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V''

Allison Kerry is one of the first detectives working on the [[Jigsaw (Saw)|Jigsaw Killer]] case. She is first seen in ''Saw'', working with David Tapp and Steven Sing. In ''Saw II'' she works with Eric Matthews and Daniel Rigg, and helps aid Matthews during his test in order to try and save his [[#Daniel Matthews|son]], where she urges him to follow Jigsaw's rules. In ''Saw III'', after Matthews is kidnapped and presumed dead following the events of ''II'', Kerry becomes wracked with guilt for his loss. She and [[Mark Hoffman|Detective Hoffman]] are assigned a case where Kerry points out that a trap does not follow Jigsaw's [[modus operandi]], because the trap did not give the victim a chance to escape, and thus does not believe Jigsaw is responsible for it. She is later captured and placed in her own trap (&quot;Angel Trap&quot;). Even though she follows the rules and tries to secure her freedom, the trap was designed and rigged by Amanda Young to not release her and the trap tore her [[ribcage]] from her body. Her corpse is later discovered by Rigg and the FBI. It is shown in ''Saw IV'' that she is also an FBI contact passing information to Agents [[#Peter Strahm|Peter Strahm]] and [[#Lindsey Perez|Lindsey Perez]]. It is shown in ''Saw IV'' on the files Rigg goes through, that Kerry's first name is Allison. In ''Saw V'', a memorial service is held to honor Kerry, Tapp, Sing, Matthews, and Rigg, all of whom had died in the course of the film series.

===Amanda Young===
{{anchor|Amanda}}
{{main|Amanda Young}}
[[File:Shawneegfdl.PNG|thumb|150px|Smith portrayed Amanda Young, Jigsaw's apprentice]]
*Portrayed by [[Shawnee Smith]] (film) and [[Jen Taylor]] (game)
*Appears in: ''Saw: Rebirth'', ''Saw'', ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D'', ''Saw: The Video Game''

Amanda is one of Jigsaw's earliest targets who managed to survive her 'game'. Believing she had changed from her [[self harm|self-harming]] ways, Jigsaw recruits her as his apprentice. Intended to carry on his legacy, she becomes disillusioned with Jigsaw's [[philosophy]] and begins to design inescapable traps intended to kill the victim even if they passed their test. She is ultimately killed by [[#Jeff Denlon|Jeff Denlon]] after he witnessed her shooting his wife, [[#Lynn Denlon|Lynn Denlon]]. She appears through archive footage in ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'' and ''Saw 3D'', and in newly-filmed flashbacks in ''Saw VI''.

===Carla Song===
{{anchor|Carla}}
*Portrayed by [[Alexandra Bokyun Chun]] (film)
*Appears in: ''[[Saw (film)|Saw]]'', ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]''

Carla is a doctor at a free clinic who has a minor role in ''Saw'' where she has an affair with [[#Lawrence Gordon|Dr. Lawrence Gordon]].  She has a larger role in the events of the video game ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood'' where she comes to Jigsaw's attention because she is stealing vital pharmaceuticals and selling them for profit on the street to drug addicts. She is found by Michael Tapp with her arms secured to the ceiling of an elevator shaft and her legs secured to the roof of an elevator. Michael is tasked with completing a test in order to release her safely, with failure resulting in the elevator lowering, tearing Carla in half. It is revealed that she is part of a criminal conspiracy alongside Henry, Joseph, and Sarah to sell drugs, Carla being responsible for procuring more specialist items from her clinic. Though she and Michael work together, she is soon isolated with Henry Jacobs, who slashes her to death with a pair of scissors.

===David Tapp===
{{anchor|Detective Tapp}}
{{main|David Tapp}}
*Portrayed by [[Danny Glover]] (film) and Earl Alexander (game)
*Appears in: ''Saw'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw: The Video Game''

David Tapp is a detective who is assigned to investigate early Jigsaw crimes. Evidence leads him to suspect Dr. Lawrence Gordon of being Jigsaw and leads him to a possible hideout for Jigsaw. Tapp and his partner Sing finds the real Jigsaw and attempts to arrest him but are stopped when the killer activates a nearby trap, threatening the life of the man trapped within it. Sing rushes to help the victim while Tapp attempts to arrest Jigsaw but Jigsaw retaliates by slicing open Tapp's throat. As they pursue Jigsaw, Sing is killed in a booby-trap for which Tapp blames himself. 

Still convinced that Gordon is Jigsaw, Tapp investigates him privately, inadvertently coming into conflict with Zep Hindle who is holding Gordon's family hostage. Tapp gave chase and fought with Zep but is shot and left for dead. In ''[[Saw (video game)|Saw: The Video Game]]'', it is shown that Tapp is nursed back to health by Jigsaw and placed in a series of traps in an asylum, forced to overcome tests and other victims sent to kill him. In the game's &quot;Freedom&quot; ending, Tapp manages to escape the asylum but commits suicide sometime afterwards by shooting himself in the head in his apartment because he could not overcome his obsession with Jigsaw. In ''[[Saw V]]'', Tapp is given a police memorial. In the ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood'' video game, his son Michael is also tested.  The game details how Michael, a reporter, abused their strained relationship during David's investigation to steal information on the Jigsaw case and write an expose that tarnishes Tapp's reputation, leading to him being dismissed from the force.

===Donnie Greco===
{{anchor|Donnie Greco|Donnie|Dead Cellmate}}
*Portrayed by [[Oren Koules]]
*Appears in: ''Saw'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV''

Donnie Greco&lt;ref&gt;The name Donnie Greco appears in a document observed by Agent Strahm, speculated to be the man Amanda Young had to kill to survive her test.  This is confirmed in ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood'' via a case file&lt;/ref&gt; first appears in Amanda's Reverse Bear Trap scene in ''Saw''. He is heavily tranquilized (injected with an [[opioid overdose]]) and unable to move or feel anything, as part of Amanda's test. The key to the lock on the reverse bear trap had been placed in his stomach, and to get to it, Amanda has to cut into him. She is told that he is dead, but he begins to stir slightly as she knelt over him with the knife; nevertheless, she still disembowels him to get the key. Donnie is seen again in ''Saw III'' in a flashback showing Jigsaw preparing the trap by painting a question-mark on Donnie's stomach. He appears in a flashback in ''Saw IV'' exiting Jill's health clinic with Paul Leahy. The original script of ''Saw'' reveals Donnie is Amanda's drug dealer.{{cn|date=September 2011} Oren Koules, who portrayed Greco, is one of the producers of the franchise.

===Jeff Ridenhour===
{{anchor|Jeff Ridenhour}}
*Portrayed by [[Ned Bellamy]] (film) and Dex Manley (game)
*Appears in: ''Saw'', ''Saw: The Video Game''

Jeff&lt;ref&gt;His last name is stated to be Thomas in the first ''Saw'' video game. However, it is shown in ''Saw V'' that his family name is Ridenhour, as indicated by a document observed by Agent Strahm, and in several case files found in ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''. Because of this, Jeff's surname is not completely clear.&lt;/ref&gt; first appears in ''Saw'' as a victim of one of Jigsaw's experimental traps. He is bound to a chair with two drills facing his neck. Jigsaw activates the drills, advancing them toward Jeff's neck, and tells Det. Steven Sing that the key to free him is on a ring with dozens of others. Without enough time to check all the keys, Sing shoots the bits off the drills to stop them. In an early draft for ''Saw IV'', he made an appearance as a hidden man being forced into performing kidnappings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saw IV Rough Draft&quot;&gt;http://www.megaupload.com/?d=L0XMTV1G First Draft&lt;/ref&gt;

He later appears in ''Saw: The Video Game''. Jeff is shown to have become suicidal from Detective Tapp repeatedly questioning him about Jigsaw. Detective Tapp saves him and he runs away. During the events of ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood'', it is revealed that two days after Jeff escaped from Whitehurst asylum, he commits suicide.

===John Kramer (Jigsaw Killer) {{anchor|Jigsaw|Jigsaw Killer|John Kramer}}===
{{main|Jigsaw (Saw)}}
[[File:Bell, Tobin (2007).jpg|thumb|150px|Bell has portrayed John Kramer (&quot;Jigsaw&quot;) in the films]]
*Portrayed by [[Tobin Bell]] (film/game) and George Williams (animated comic)
*Appears in: ''Saw: Rebirth'', ''Saw'', ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D'', ''Saw: The Video Game'', ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

John Kramer is a successful engineer, married to Jill Tuck and expecting a son, Gideon. Following the [[miscarriage]] of his son caused by Amanda Young and [[#Cecil|Cecil]], John became distraught and later learned he had an aggressive inoperable [[brain tumor]]. He attempted suicide but ultimately survived finding a new appreciation for life, realizing how much of his own he had wasted. Using his wealth and skill, John set about testing others' will to live by placing them in deadly traps, hoping to make them too appreciate their lives. Those who failed would have a jigsaw-shaped piece cut from their flesh. This missing piece is used to coin his nickname, &quot;Jigsaw&quot; or &quot;The Jigsaw Killer&quot;. John, on his death bed, is killed by [[#Jeff Denlon|Jeff Denlon]] in ''Saw III''.

===Lawrence Gordon===
{{anchor|Dr. Gordon}}
[[File:CaryElwesApr10.jpg|thumb|150px|Cary Elwes portrayed Dr. Lawrence Gordon in the first film, and appears in the [[Saw 3D|seventh film]]]]
{{main|Lawrence Gordon (character)}}
*Portrayed by [[Cary Elwes]] (film) and [[Stan Kirsch]] (animated comic).
*Appears in: ''Saw: Rebirth'', ''Saw'', ''Saw 3D''

Dr. Lawrence Gordon is the man responsible for diagnosing John Kramer's cancer and is initially a suspect in the Jigsaw case. As Jigsaw, John targeted Gordon for engaging in an affair with his medical student, Carla Song, despite having a loving family. Gordon is placed in a trap alongside Adam Stanheight and tasked with killing him before the time limit ran out or his wife and daughter would be executed. He fails to do this, but instead severs his own foot to free himself from his shackles, attempting to crawl to freedom and promising to bring help back for Adam.  After crawling from the bathroom, he uses a hot steam pipe to [[Cauterization|cauterize]] his wound and prevent fatal blood loss.  Jigsaw finds him unconscious shortly after and begins helping him recover from his injury, later fitting him with a prosthetic foot.  

Jigsaw manages to recruit Gordon's aid afterwards, employing his talents in many of his traps such as sewing the key behind [[#Michael Marks|Michael]]'s eye (''Saw II''), suggesting [[#Lynn Denlon|Lynn Denlon]] as a test subject (''Saw III''), stitching [[#Trevor|Trevor]]'s eyes shut (''Saw IV'') and writing a cryptic note that Hoffman found on his desk (''Saw V'').  Following Jigsaw's death, Gordon is left a package that is delivered by his wife Jill, that contains instructions to watch over Jill on his behalf.  After Hoffman kills Jill and attempts to flee, he is ambushed by three people in Pig masks, their leader revealed as Gordon.  Hoffman is taken to the bathroom trap originally used on Gordon and shacked.  When Hoffman tries to reach a hacksaw to free himself, Gordon purposely throws it out of reach before leaving Hoffman in the bathroom to die.

In ''Saw V'' it is revealed that Hoffman set up Gordon as a Jigsaw suspect by placing Gordon's penlight at a Jigsaw crime scene.

===Mark Wilson===
{{anchor|Mark|Mark Wilson}}
*Portrayed by Paul Gutrecht
*Appears in: ''Saw: Rebirth'', ''Saw''

Mark,&lt;ref name=FullDisclosure&gt;''Full Disclosure Report: Piecing Together Jigsaw''&lt;/ref&gt; a 30-year-old software analyst,&lt;ref name=FullDisclosure/&gt; is one of Jigsaw's earliest victims, targeted because he feigned illness and injury to excuse himself from his responsibilities when he is in fact perfectly healthy. Mark is stripped naked and informed that he had a slow-acting poison in his body, and the antidote is locked away in a safe in the room. Mark has to overcome the broken-glass covered floor and use a candle to read the safe combination written on the wall, wary of the fact his flesh is smeared with [[napalm]]. Mark eventually fumbles with the candle and the substance ignites, burning him alive; his charred corpse is found later by police. According to the list in ''Saw V'', Mark is the second victim of Jigsaw's traps.  A case file from Detective Tapp reveals that he is using his &quot;illness&quot; for medical insurance fraud, and that he used Umbrella Insurance, the same group of people tested in ''Saw VI''.{{clarify|date=September 2011}}

===Paul Leahy===
{{anchor|Paul|Paul Leahy}}
*Portrayed by Mike Butters
*Appears in: ''Saw: Rebirth'', ''Saw'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V''

Paul is one of Jigsaw's earliest victims, chosen because he attempted suicide by cutting his wrists despite having a 'good' life with a wife and kids. Paul is placed in a large cage lined with a maze of [[razor wire]] and is given 2 hours to crawl his way to freedom, the irony of this being that if Paul wants to live he would have to cut himself but if he really wants to die, all he has to do is wait. Paul dies of injuries from the razor wire before reaching the exit. Paul is later seen in ''Saw IV'' leaving Jill's drug clinic. In ''Saw V'', Paul is shown being kidnapped by Jigsaw and Hoffman for his test in ''Saw''.

===Steven Sing===
{{anchor|Detective Sing|Steven Sing}}
*Portrayed by [[Ken Leung]]
*Appears in: ''Saw'', ''Saw V''

Steven Sing is a detective who is called to the crime scene investigation of one of Jigsaw's victims. He and his partner, David Tapp, are assigned to the case. Tapp found a clue in one of the tapes left over from the crime scene, leading Sing and Tapp right to Jigsaw's hideout. There, they find a [[#Jeff Ridenhour|Jeff Ridenhour]] in a trap with drills aimed at his neck. Jigsaw arrives and activates the device when the officers exposed themselves, forcing the detectives to choose between arresting him or saving Jeff. Sing shot the drills and deactivates them before pursuing Jigsaw through the warehouse after Jigsaw slashes Tapp's throat with a hidden wrist-blade. While in pursuit, Sing accidentally activates a tripwire which triggeres four shotguns hidden above to fire and kill him. Sing's death triggeres Tapp's obsession with Jigsaw. In ''Saw V'', Sing is given a police memorial.

It is shown in the [[Saw: The Video Game|video game]] that Sing has a wife named [[#Melissa Sing|Melissa]] and a son named Franklin. Melissa encounters Tapp during the game and blames him for the death of her husband. In one of Tapp's case files found in ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]'', Detective Tapp establishes a great deal of respect and admiration for his partner's work ethic, though he also notes that &quot;he tends to drink more than most. Doesn't seem to affect his judgement though.&quot;
{{-}}

===Zep Hindle===
{{anchor|Zepp Hindle|Zep|Zepp}}
*Portrayed by [[Michael Emerson]] (film) and Jeff Shuter (animated comic).
*Appears in: ''Saw: Rebirth'', ''Saw''

Zep is an [[orderly]] who worked in the hospital where John Kramer, the Jigsaw Killer, is treated for his cancer. He forms a bond with John while he is being treated, but is considered to have &quot;issues of his own&quot; by him. John seems to see a lot of his own actions in Zep's goals, reminding him of himself before he is diagnosed with cancer.&lt;ref name=SawRebirth&gt;[[Saw: Rebirth]]&lt;/ref&gt; Zep is later forced to watch Adam Stanheight and Dr. Gordon play out their game that takes place in a bathroom. If Lawrence fails to kill Adam by 6:00, then Zep will be forced to kill Lawrence's wife and child, whom he has been holding hostage, in order to save himself from the slow-acting nerve agent in his bloodstream. He will then have to kill Lawrence himself and retrieve an antidote from Jigsaw. Lawrence fails, but his wife and daughter manage to escape from Zep's grip before he can kill them, as Zep is attacked by David Tapp, a former detective who is watching the Gordons' home from across the street. Zep is forced to flee down to the sewers that leads to the bathroom to kill Lawrence, but Tapp follows him; the two fought, and Zep shot Tapp in the chest and leaves him to die.  In the bathroom, where Lawrence has already shot Adam, Zep prepares to kill Lawrence. Before he could do so, though, Adam knocks him down and beats him to death with a toilet tank lid.

Throughout the film, Zep is presented as a [[Red herring (plot device)|red herring]], with the audience being encouraged to believe that he is Jigsaw, rather than a victim of one of Jigsaw's games. The truth is revealed only after Adam searches the body, looking for a key to free himself, and finds a microcassette recorder that contains Jigsaw's instructions to Zep. On the commentary for ''Saw'', Leigh Whannell and James Wan stated that Zep enjoyed the sense of power he is given over others which he did not have before. Zep's decomposed corpse is later shown in ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'' and ''Saw 3D''.

==''Saw II''==
===Addison Corday===
{{anchor|Addison|Addison Corday}}
*Portrayed by [[Emmanuelle Vaugier]]
*Appears in: ''[[Saw II]]'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V''

Addison is a prostitute and a victim in the Nerve Gas House in ''Saw II''. Like the other adult victims in the house, she was arrested by Eric Matthews. Though she attempts to work with the other prisoners to survive, upon learning that another victim, Daniel, is Eric Matthews' son, she begins working alone to find the antidote for the gas that is slowly killing everyone. When she reaches into a hanging glass box to retrieve an antidote syringe, her arms become caught in folding razor blades and she begins bleeding heavily while trying to pull free. Xavier later finds her, but after reading the number on the back of her neck, he leaves her to bleed to death. In ''Saw IV'' she is shown prior to John Kramer becoming Jigsaw, offering him 'company' in her role as a prostitute.

It is revealed in the commentary for the second film that there is a key already in the lock at the back of the trap Addison died in, and all she had to do in order to live is to turn it and grab the antidote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |people=David Hackl (production designer) |date=2005 |title=The Traps of Saw II: The Hand Trap |medium=DVD |publisher=Lionsgate Home Entertainment |accessdate={{nowrap|August 25, 2011}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is also revealed her trap is intended for Gus, who died earlier on, which is why she is shown ripping up his envelope and tossing his tape aside.{{cn|date=September 2011}} Addison's trap is supposed to be a &quot;waffle iron,&quot; which she would have to push her face into, a concept that was partially resurrected in Saw IV with the Knife Chair Trap.{{cn|date=September 2011}} According to the ''Saw II'' website, Addison is written to be 29 years old.&lt;ref name=OfficialSawII&gt;{{cite web|url=http://saw2.com/censored/site.html|Official ''Saw II'' website|publisher=[[Lions Gate Entertainment|Lionsgate]]|accessdate={{nowrap|September 22, 2011}}|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20051215113922/http://saw2.com/censored/site.html|archivedate{{nowrap|October 7, 2007}}|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

===Daniel Matthews===
{{anchor|Daniel Matthews|Daniel}}
*Portrayed by [[Erik Knudsen]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II''

Daniel appears in ''Saw II'', as the son of Eric Matthews. After a falling out with his father, Daniel goes missing but is reveals to have been captured and placed in another of Jigsaw's games alongside several convicts, all arrested by Daniel's father. As the game progresses, Daniel's lineage is discovered and he is abandoned by many of the other victims. With time running low, Daniel and Amanda begins to work together to get away from Xavier, an enraged victim who is hunting them. Xavier eventually finds them but Daniel manages to slice open Xavier's neck with a saw, killing him and saving Amanda and himself. After these events it is revealed that Amanda, Jigsaw's new apprentice, had taken the unconscious Daniel to Jigsaw's lair and they had locked him in a safe as an incentive for Eric Matthews in his own test. He appears in a flashback (with the use of a [[body double]]) in ''Saw V'', and is seen in archive footage in the endings of ''Saw III'' and ''Saw 3D''.

===Daniel Rigg===
{{anchor|Daniel Rigg|Rigg}}
*Portrayed by [[Lyriq Bent]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V''

Daniel Rigg is a [[S.W.A.T.]] officer who first appears in ''Saw II'', assisting detectives Eric Matthews and Allison Kerry in arresting Jigsaw, but ultimately failing to capture the felon after Eric helped Jigsaw escape. He holds the rank of Sergeant for this film, but is promoted to Lieutenant and put in command of the S.W.A.T. team before the events of ''Saw III''. Appearing only briefly in ''Saw III'', Rigg is eventually put into a series of tests as the protagonist in ''Saw IV'', in which he has to rethink many of the Jigsaw Killer's ideals. He suffers a gunshot wound to the stomach in his final test; and it is revealed that he died of blood loss in ''Saw V'' and is also given a memorial, along with Detectives Eric Matthews, Allison Kerry, David Tapp, and Steven Sing. On the Photographs of the five dead officers, Rigg's picture shows his first name as Daniel.

Lyriq Bent has remarked that: &quot;I didn't know what to expect of his character in the fourth movie. Lieutenant Rigg has really come into himself. In ''Saw II'', he is really the strong, silent type that really didn't know what is going on around him. You had a sense that there is something going on with him internally, and I think that sparked a lot of curiosity in the audience. They wanted to know, 'Who is this guy, and what's he all about?' In ''Saw IV'', you get to find out who he is, and what he's all about, and how he feels about the situation that he's in, and how he feels about the type of work that he's in and people and all that. And I think he's a character that people are gonna like, because they can relate to him on so many different levels. He's a real person. In ''Saw IV'', you get to go on a journey with him, and it's pretty much an emotional journey. At the end, I only hope that the audience will be as exhausted and worn out as he is, because he becomes this broken man.&quot;{{cn|date=September 2011}} 

===Eric Matthews===
{{main|Eric Matthews (Saw)}}
*Portrayed by [[Donnie Wahlberg]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V''

Eric Matthews is a detective who led a SWAT team to Jigsaw's latest lair in ''Saw II''. Before he could be arrested, Jigsaw reveals he has possession of Eric's [[#Daniel Matthews|son]] and that he will have to play in Jigsaw's game to see him again. It is revealed that Eric is chosen because he had planted evidence to secure convictions against people for crimes they had not committed. Eric, concerned about his son, refuses to follow Jigsaw's rules and in doing so he ended up brutalizing the weakened cancer patient and later becomes trapped and shackled in the same bathroom in which Adam dies in. However, he shatters his own foot to allow him to squeeze free of the shackle and pursue Amanda, his captor and one of the victims of his evidence-planting. He brutally beats Amanda before she gained the upper-hand and leaves him for dead. Jigsaw later finds Matthews, had his foot repaired and held him captive until he could be used in a trap designed for Daniel Rigg. After Rigg fails his test, Matthews is killed when his head is crushed between two large blocks of ice. He is later given a police memorial in ''Saw V'' and appears via archive footage from the previous films.

===Gus Colyard===
{{anchor|Gus|Gus Colyard}}
*Portrayed by [[Tony Nappo]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II'', ''Saw IV''

Gus is a businessman who appears in ''Saw II'' as a prisoner in the Nerve Gas House alongside several other victims. Waking up in the house, Gus quickly becomes paranoid of the other victims and tries to help Xavier escape the room they are trapped in. As Gus peers through a peephole in the door to the room, Xavier inadvertently triggers a trap, firing a bullet through Gus' head, killing him. Like the other victims, Gus is in the house because he was framed for crimes by Eric Matthews. His trap is supposed to be the Razor Box trap, with his tape saying how &quot;he is always reaching into the cookie jar for money.&quot; According to the ''Saw II'' website, Gus is written to be 38.&lt;ref name=&quot;OfficialSawII&quot;/&gt; It is shown in ''Saw V'' that his family name is Colyard, as indicated by a document observed by Agent Strahm.
{{-}}

===Jonas Singer===
*Portrayed by [[Glenn Plummer]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II''

Jonas appears in ''Saw II'' as a prisoner in the Nerve Gas House. Like other victims of the house, Jonas had been framed and jailed by Eric Matthews, and it is implied that he had been part of a gang. Though Jonas handles the traps of the house calmly and logically, he remains skeptical of his survival and is ultimately killed by Xavier after they get into a fight. According to the ''Saw II'' website, Jonas is written to be 41 years old.&lt;ref name=OfficialSawII/&gt; It is shown in ''Saw V'' that his family name is Singer, as indicated by a document observed by Agent Strahm.

===Laura Hunter===
*Portrayed by [[Beverley Mitchell]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II''

Laura appears in ''Saw II'' as a prisoner of the Nerve Gas House alongside seven other victims, all but one of whom were framed for crimes by Eric Matthews. Through a flashback, it is revealed that Obi Tate had kidnapped her for Jigsaw. As the game progresses, Laura becomes physically weaker and soon after discovering that another victim, Daniel Matthews, is the son of the man who framed her, she succumbs to the effects of the Nerve Gas, suffering a [[Non-epileptic seizure|seizure]] and dying in Amanda's arms. Laura also appears briefly in ''Saw V'' lying unconscious when Jigsaw and Hoffman are setting up the house trap. According to the ''Saw II'' website, Laura is written to be 24 years old.&lt;ref name=OfficialSawII/&gt; It is shown in ''Saw V'' that her family name is Hunter, as indicated by a document observed by Agent Strahm.
{{-}}

===Michael Marks===
*Portrayed by Noam Jenkins
*Appears in: ''Saw II'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw 3D''.

Michael, a police informant working for Eric Matthews, appears in the opening scene of ''Saw II'', with the two halves of a spike-filled helmet locked around his neck. A videotape from Jigsaw and a set of X-ray slides reveals that the key had been surgically implanted behind his right eye, and a scalpel had been left in the room so he could extract it. Jigsaw believed that Michael had wasted his life by simply watching others' activity; in order to survive, he has to give up that ability. He can not bring himself to cut out his eye and is killed when the helmet's timer runs out and is slammed shut on his head.

Michael is seen again later in a flashback in ''Saw IV'', in the waiting room of Jill's clinic. It is shown in ''Saw V'' that his family name is Marks, as indicated by a document observed by Agent Strahm. He makes an appearance in ''Saw 3D'', where it is revealed that [[#Lawrence Gordon|Dr. Gordon]] sewed the key behind his eye.

===Obi Tate {{anchor|Obi}}===
*Portrayed by Tim Burd (film) and Marc Carr (game)
*Appears in: ''Saw II'', ''Saw III'', ''Saw: The Video Game''

Obi Tate&lt;ref&gt;In Saw V, Obi's last name is shown to be Tate, via a file Agent Strahm observes, and it appears after Addison Corday's.&lt;/ref&gt; appears in ''Saw II'', a victim in the Nerve Gas House alongside several other victims. He remains isolated from the rest of the group until they face a trap addressed to Obi himself with a message revealing that Obi had aided Jigsaw in kidnapping the other victims in the house. Two antidote syringes were placed inside a cold furnace; he could use one for himself and give the other away. When he crawls in and tries to retrieve the syringes, he triggers a mechanism that seals and ignites the furnace, burning him to death. A clue given on Obi's tape indicates that he could save himself by turning a valve within the furnace, highlighted by an image of the Devil.  However he fails to reach through the flames to activate it and it is not made clear whether he is aware of the clue's meaning.

Obi has brief cameo appearances in ''Saw III'' in a flashback. In ''Saw V'' he is shown unconscious being dragged into the nerve gas house by Mark Hoffman, and briefly appears in archive footage in ''Saw 3D''. Obi appears in ''Saw: The Video Game'' where he is rescued from another furnace by David Tapp. In the game it is revealed that Obi desires to be tested by Jigsaw repeatedly, thinking of it as a 'gift'. According to the ''Saw II'' commentary, Obi is accused of being an arsonist.{{clarify|date=September 2011}}

===Xavier Chavez===
*Portrayed by [[Franky G]]
*Appears in: ''Saw II'', ''Saw III''

Xavier Chavez&lt;ref&gt;His family name is given as 'Chavez' in a document observed by Agent Strahm in Saw V&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[Psychopathy|sociopathic]] [[drug dealer]] who appears in ''Saw II''. Imprisoned in the Nerve Gas House, Xavier is forced to hunt for an antidote to the gas that is slowly killing him, risking others to avoid harming himself in the various traps. Like most of the other victims of the house, Xavier had been framed by Detective Eric Matthews to secure a conviction. Remembering the instructions given at the start of the game, Xavier realizes that the victims have numbers written on the back of their necks which, when combined, will open a safe containing a dose of the antidote. Xavier begins hunting down the other victims to collect their numbers before realizing that one of the victims, Daniel, is the son of Eric Matthews. He corners Daniel and Amanda in the bathroom (from ''Saw'') but Daniel lashes out, fatally slashing Xavier's throat with a hacksaw. His corpse appears briefly at the start of ''Saw III'', and he is seen unconscious with the other victims in a scene from ''Saw V'', in which Jigsaw and Hoffman are setting up the house trap. Xavier appears in archive footage in the endings of ''Saw III'' and ''Saw 3D'', and his decomposed corpse is briefly seen again in ''Saw 3D''. According to the ''Saw II'' website, Xavier is written to be 40 years old.&lt;ref name=OfficialSawII/&gt;

==''Saw III''==
===Corbett Denlon===
*Portrayed by Niamh Wilson
*Appears in: ''[[Saw III]]'', ''[[Saw V]]'', ''[[Saw VI]]'' (flashback)

Corbett is the neglected daughter of Lynn and Jeff Denlon in ''[[Saw III]]''. She is kidnapped and hidden away in Jigsaw's lair, given a limited air supply. Her father learns of her kidnapping in the warehouse upon killing Jigsaw, revealing that he would have to play another game to get Corbett back. However that game never materialized since he is shot dead by Agent Strahm in ''Saw IV''. During ''Saw IV'', Hoffman is seen holding one of Corbett's stuffed animals in a scene in which he talks with Perez. Corbett has a brief appearance in ''Saw V'' where she is seen with the stuffed animal being taken out of the warehouse and given to a police officer by Hoffman. After the credits roll on the Director's Cut of ''Saw VI'' Amanda is seen talking to Corbett through the door of the room she's captive in, urging her not to trust Hoffman when he saves her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bloody-disgusting.com/news/18805 | title=A New Ending to 'Saw VI' on Director's Cut DVD?! | work=Bloody Disgusting | publisher=The Collective | date=January 22, 2010 | accessdate=January 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dylan Denlon===
*Portrayed by Stefan Georgiou
*Appears in: ''Saw III''

Dylan Denlon is Jeff Denlon's son. He is run over by a drunk driver named Timothy Young. Since Timothy did not get the punishment he deserved, Jeff becomes unstable and angry, which is why he is tested in ''Saw III''.

===Danica Scott===
*Portrayed by Debra McCabe
*Appears in: ''Saw III''

Danica Scott is the only witness to the death of Jeff Denlon's son, Dylan. Instead of staying to testify, Danica fled the scene, and is later kidnapped as part of Jeff's tests. She is stripped [[nude]] and suspended by her wrists in a freezer room. The key that would free her is hanging behind a set of frozen pipes. Once Jeff enters, water begins spraying on Danica, and she is able to convince Jeff to help her. He manages to get the key, tearing part of his cheek off in the process when it froze onto the pipes. However, he is unable to open the lock, which is already covered with ice, before Danica's body is frozen solid. According to the final draft of the ''Saw III'' script, Danica is written to be in her 30's.&lt;ref name=DanicaAge&gt;[http://i94.photobucket.com/albums/l118/Jack-Of-Hearts-8/SawIIIScriptDanicasReveal.jpg ''Saw III'' script, Danica's age]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

===Halden===
*Portrayed by [[Barry Flatman]]
*Appears in: ''[[Saw III]]''

Halden is a judge who presided over the case of Timothy Young, a drunk driver who killed Jeff's son, Dylan. Halden is captured and positioned as part of Jeff's test of forgiveness to see if Jeff could overcome his anger at Halden for only giving Timothy a six-month sentence for his crime. He is placed at the bottom of a large vat, with a chain across his throat, and rotted pig carcasses are dropped into a nearby set of saws so that the liquefied material will pour down on him. The key to free him is in an incinerator filled with Dylan's belongings; Jeff eventually burns the items, finds the key, and saves Halden from drowning just in time. Later, while confronting Timothy, Jeff accidentally triggers a shotgun that discharges into Halden's face, killing him.

According to the final draft of the ''Saw III'' script, Halden is written to be in his 50s.&lt;ref name=HaldenAge&gt;[http://i94.photobucket.com/albums/l118/Jack-Of-Hearts-8/SawIIIScriptHaldensReveal.jpg ''Saw III'' script, Halden's age]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

===Jeff Denlon=== &lt;!--&quot;Reinhart&quot; is Jeff's surname according to the back of the Saw 3 DVD cover. --&gt;
*Portrayed by [[Angus Macfadyen]]
*Appears in: ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV''

Jeff is one of Jigsaw's victims in ''Saw III'' due to his obsession with vengeance against those that were involved in the death of his son Dylan and the trial of the killer. Jeff is kidnapped and is subjected to a series of encounters with those he held accountable for the incident, faced with the choice of helping them to live or allowing them to die in their individual traps. Jeff's final test is a confrontation with Jigsaw himself to prove he has learned how to forgive. Jeff claims to forgive Jigsaw before cutting open his throat. In killing Jigsaw, Jeff inadvertently kills his wife Lynn by triggering her trap. Jigsaw's final message is for Jeff to undergo another test to save his [[#Corbett Denlon|daughter]], but he is killed by Agent Strahm  seconds later (shown in ''Saw IV''). Jeff appears in archive footage in ''Saw V'' and ''Saw VI'', and is mentioned by Dr. Gordon in ''Saw 3D'' as he is discussing his wife Lynn with Jigsaw.

Jeff's surname is &quot;Denlon&quot; in the film, but is &quot;Reinhart&quot; on the back of the ''Saw III'' DVD cover.

When asked whether he liked his character even though he hesitated in saving people, Angus Macfadyen said, &quot;Yeah, well, I think it's kind of set up in the film that even though you think he could save them, even when he tries to, it's set-up so it all seems a little too late. That is something we were discussing is how long do you wait and pause? Because if you've done that in one room, you know you can't do that in the next because otherwise it's going to be too late for that person. So we were having lots of debates. And also because each scene, you can't play them all the same. You've got to build in each one. So did I like him? I don't think he liked himself very much.&quot;&lt;ref name=IGNAngus&gt;[http://movies.ign.com/articles/742/742130p2.html IGN interview with Angus Macfadyen]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jill Tuck {{anchor|Jill Tuck-Kramer|Jill Kramer}}===
{{main|Jill Tuck}}
*Portrayed by [[Betsy Russell]]
*Appears in: ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D''

Jill Tuck is John Kramer's ex-wife who divorced him after he becomes increasingly distant and cold following the miscarriage of their son, Gideon, accidentally caused by Cecil Adams, with Amanda being with Cecil at the time. She is initially suspected of aiding the Jigsaw Killer or in fact being the killer. After John's death, Jill visits his lawyer to hear his final will, during which she is bequeathed a box containing his last intended games and victims including one that Jill needed to test herself. Submitting to his final wishes, Jill placed Mark Hoffman in a seemingly unwinnable game intending to kill him.

However, Jill witnessed as Hoffman managed to escape his trap and she fled to the police for protection.  Demanding immunity, Jill offers to provide the evidence necessary to implicate him in the Jigsaw murders.  While in protective custody, Hoffman is able to infiltrate the police station and kill her with the reverse bear-trap used on Amanda.

===Lynn Denlon===
*Portrayed by [[Bahar Soomekh]]
*Appears in: ''[[Saw III]]''

Lynn is an [[emergency room|ER]] doctor who is kidnapped in ''Saw III'' by Amanda and tasked with keeping John Kramer/Jigsaw alive until the completion of his latest game. Lynn is placed in a collar rigged with shotgun shells, which is designed to detonate if she moves too far from Jigsaw or if his heart monitor flatlines. She performs extensive [[brain surgery]] and care to ensure he stays alive until her husband Jeff completed his three tests. Lynn is supposed to be released when Jeff finished, but ultimately Jigsaw's apprentice Amanda Young refuses, believing that she had not learned anything from her experience and jealous of the attention Jigsaw had shown her. Lynn is injured by a gunshot from Amanda before being revealed as Jeff Denlon's estranged wife. Jeff then kills Amanda and Jigsaw, unknowingly activating his wife's trap, blowing her head to pieces. She appears in archive footage in ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI'' and ''Saw 3D''. In ''Saw 3D'', it is revealed that it is Lawrence Gordon who suggests her as a suitable doctor to operate on Jigsaw, showing him a photo of her.

When asked about why she believed her character is being tested, Bahar Soomekh said, &quot;I think this is what's so interesting and that's what I would ask is in Jigsaw's mind he's justified in everything that he does, right? These are people, whether they are drug dealers or they've done something wrong. But that's how psychotic and wrong he actually is. Because he justifies it. What did Lynn do? That's what's so disturbing because he's not justified at all in doing what he does. In his mind, he thinks he's helping these people. How does he help Lynn? He doesn't help Lynn at all. But I think, in his mind, because my character's depressed ... so she's been dead inside. She's totally dead inside and this is Jigsaw's way of waking her up and saying, 'What the hell are you doing?' And she does. You see the metamorphosis in her.&quot;&lt;ref name=IGNBahar&gt;[http://movies.ign.com/articles/742/742130p1.html IGN interview with Bahar Soomekh]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mark Hoffman {{anchor|Detective Hoffman}}===
{{main|Mark Hoffman}}
*Portrayed by [[Costas Mandylor]]
*Appears in: ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D''
 
Mark Hoffman is a detective who used his knowledge of the Jigsaw crimes to murder the man who killed his sister while placing the blame on Jigsaw. In ''Saw IV'' he becomes a participant in Daniel Rigg's test before revealing himself as one of Jigsaw's apprentices by freeing himself from his trap. Hoffman holds the legacy to the Jigsaw killings and continues to operate 'games' set out by Jigsaw before his death. Despite framing Peter Strahm for his crimes, Hoffman is discovered to be the last Jigsaw killer, forcing him to kill everyone who knows. After Jill Tuck attempts to kill him with an unwinnable trap, Hoffman sets up a game for [[List of Saw characters#Bobby Dagen|Bobby Dagen]] to serve as a distraction for the police so that he can infiltrate the police station where Jill is being held. After killing Jill and preparing to leave town, Hoffman is abducted by Dr. Gordon and left to die in the bathroom from the first film.

According to producers [[Oren Koules]] and [[Mark Burg]], Hoffman is named after late Saw producer [[Gregg Hoffman]], who died shortly after the announcement of ''Saw III''.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

===Timothy Young===
*Portrayed by Mpho Koaho
*Appears in: ''[[Saw III]]'', ''[[Saw VI]]''(flashback)

Timothy Young is a medical student who, while [[driving drunk]], hit and kills Jeff Denlon's son, Dylan. Timothy only receives 6 months in prison due to a lack of witnesses at the trial. He appears in ''Saw III'', kidnapped and placed in a cross-shaped device named &quot;The Rack,&quot; one of the traps that Jigsaw describes as his personal favorite. The Rack begins to individually rotate Timothy's limbs beyond their capable motion, rending his flesh and breaking his bones. Jeff is tasked with obtaining the key to free Timothy and despite their past relationship Jeff obtains the key. However, Jeff is too late and the device twists Timothy's head, fatally breaking his neck. Timothy appears in a flashback in ''Saw VI'', and also is credited with the name of Tim.

According to Jigsaw, Timothy is 27 when he died.&lt;ref name=TimAge&gt;[http://i94.photobucket.com/albums/l118/Jack-Of-Hearts-8/SawIIIScriptTimsTape.jpg ''Saw III'' script, Tim's age]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Troy===
*Portrayed by [[J. Larose]]
*Appears in: ''Saw III'', ''Saw IV''

Troy is one of [[#Amanda Young|Amanda's]] first victims, chosen because of his long prison record for unnamed crimes despite having a privileged upbringing. Troy is tasked with tearing out eleven chains bound through his flesh and bones before a nearby bomb detonates, but he is unable to remove the final chain through his [[human mandible|mandible]] in time. It is later revealed that Troy's only exit from the trap had been welded shut, leaving him no way to survive even if he removed all the chains. Troy is later seen in a flashback in ''Saw IV'', in the waiting room of Jill's clinic.

==''Saw IV''==
===Dr. Heffner===
*Portrayed by James Van Patten
*Appears in: ''Saw IV'', ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D''

Dr. Heffner is the [[medical examiner]] that performs the [[autopsy]] of John, in the beginning of ''Saw IV''. He appears briefly in ''Saw VI'', where he tells Agent Perez, Erickson and Hoffman that he performed all of Jigsaw's victims autopsy and also confirms to them that Seth Baxter's trap had not been done by Jigsaw. He noted that a different knife was used in his trap/murder to cut the &quot;jigsaw puzzle piece&quot; from his flesh. In ''Saw 3D'', Dr. Heffner is killed by Hoffman, who had hid inside a body bag in the morgue in order to sneak into the police headquarters to exact his revenge on Jill Tuck.

===Art Blank===
*Portrayed by [[Justin Louis]]
*Appears in: ''[[Saw IV]]''

Art is a lawyer involved in a housing development project with John Kramer and Jill Tuck before the events that would turn John into Jigsaw. Art is targeted by Jigsaw for successfully defending guilty people in his role as lawyer, including [[#Brenda|Brenda]] (a pimp), [[#Ivan Landsness|Ivan]] (a rapist) and [[#Rex|Rex]] (an abusive husband). Art first appeared in a trap that pits him against another victim, Trevor. Art's mouth is sewn shut, while Trevor's eyes are sewn shut.  Art manages to kill Trevor, tearing his mouth open, and later has a hand in setting up the tests for [[#Daniel Rigg|Daniel Rigg]]. He is eventually tasked with keeping [[Eric Matthews (Saw)|Eric Matthews]] and [[Mark Hoffman]] alive until the 90-minute time period for Rigg's tests runs out, after which he would be able to free himself and both captives. However, Rigg crashes through the door with one second to spare, causing Eric's death, then shoots and kills Art after mistaking the tape recorder in his hand for a gun. He is seen in archive footage in ''Saw V'', and is seen in a photograph with John outside Gideon Meat Packing in the police station's evidence room in ''Saw 3D''.

===Brenda===
*Portrayed by Sarain Boylan
*Appears in: ''Saw IV''

Brenda is a female pimp who appears in ''Saw IV'' as a victim in Daniel Rigg's game. Brenda is placed in a machine designed to tear her scalp from her head and Rigg is instructed to simply walk away from her as she is not worth saving. After he dials in a lock combination written on the gears and releases her, she attacks him with a knife that had been hidden in the room. Rigg subdues her by throwing her into a mirror; by the time the police arrives at the scene, she is dead. She had been instructed by Jigsaw that the only way to prevent Rigg from sending her to prison for her crimes is to kill him. Art Blank had acted as her lawyer in previous criminal trials and got her acquitted.

===Cecil Adams===
*Portrayed by Billy Otis
*Appears in: ''Saw IV'', ''Saw VI''

Cecil&lt;ref&gt;Cecil's last name, &quot;Adams&quot;, is shown in ''Saw IV'', on a file that Jigsaw had obtained.  This surname is again referenced in ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''.  However in ''Saw V'', the name Cecil Fletcher appears.  Because of this, Cecil's surname is not completely clear&lt;/ref&gt; appeared in ''Saw IV'', playing a large role in the transformation of John Kramer into Jigsaw. As Jill Tuck is closing down her drug clinic for the night, he begs her to let him back in; once inside, he robs the facility and shoves a door open into her stomach, inadvertently causing her to have a [[miscarriage]]. John later abducts Cecil and places him in the first Jigsaw trap: a chair with razor blades digging into his wrists, from which he can only escape by pushing his face through a rack of knives to hit the release switch. The chair collapses in the process and Cecil charges at John, who steps aside so that Cecil could fall into a pile of razor wire which kills him. In ''Saw VI'', it is shown that Cecil robs Jill's clinic at [[Amanda Young]]'s request.

===Fisk===
*Portrayed by Mike Realba
*Appears in: ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V''

Fisk is a detective who first appears in ''Saw IV'' working with agents Peter Strahm and Lindsey Perez. In ''Saw IV'', he discovers Lieutenant Daniel Rigg's fingerprints at the scene of Allison Kerry's death on a bullet casing lodged between her body and the trap. In ''Saw V'', he is  present at Gideon Meat Packing when the FBI rescues Mark Hoffman and Corbett Denlon. Fisk is also seen in flashbacks with Hoffman at the scene of Seth Baxter's death and is later told by Hoffman to keep him in the loop about the Jigsaw killings.

===Ivan Landsness===
*Portrayed by [[Marty Adams]]
*Appears in: ''Saw IV''

Ivan appears in ''Saw IV'' as the clerk of the Alexander Motel. Suspected of multiple, vicious rapes but freed repeatedly due to the efforts of his lawyer, Art Blank, Ivan is part of Daniel Rigg's second test. Following instructions, Rigg confronts and abducts Ivan, threatening him with a gun while forcing him into an adjoining motel room. There, they are both confronted with photographic evidence of Ivan's crimes, including a video recording of him raping a young girl. Enraged, Rigg instructed Ivan to place himself into the trap laid out across the bed, clamps his head in a vise, and supplies him with the tools to escape: two push-buttons that will each drive a blade into one of his eyes. Ivan only blinds one eye before the 60-second timer ran out, and the trap rips his limbs from his body as a result.

===Lindsey Perez===
*Portrayed by [[Athena Karkanis]]
*Appears in: ''Saw IV'', ''Saw VI''

Introduced in ''Saw IV'', Lindsey Perez is an FBI agent assigned to the Jigsaw case along with her partner, Peter Strahm. With information provided by Allison Kerry before her murder stating that two officers might be in danger, she and Strahm performed a thorough investigation concerning the disappearances of Daniel Rigg and Mark Hoffman. As they follow the trail of Rigg's tests, it becomes apparent at one of the locations they come across that they themselves were being targeted by Jigsaw, as Kerry had warned. At the last building that Rigg had been at, Perez barely escapes death when Strahm pulled her out of the firing path of a harpoon (which in turn hit a crime scene photographer). Minutes later, they entered a room where they are confronted with a Billy doll and a tape meant for her. As she leaned forward to hear what the voice is saying, the Billy doll's face explodes, severely injuring her face and neck with shrapnel. In ''Saw V'', it is implied that she dies from her injuries; her last words to Strahm were &quot;Detective Hoffman,&quot; leading to Strahm's initial suspicion regarding Hoffman.

She is revealed to be alive in ''Saw VI'', though prominently scarred, and back on the Jigsaw investigation. Dismissive of Strahm being Jigsaw's accomplice, she and Dan Erickson investigates abnormalities in evidence found that implicates Strahm and a distorted tape made by Hoffman in creating his own trap. As soon as the tape is unscrambled, Hoffman quickly attacks, slashing Erickson's throat, using a technician as a human shield against Perez's gunshots, and fatally stabbing Perez. When Hoffman demands who else is aware of his secret, she simply tells him &quot;everyone&quot; before dying. Her body, and everything else in the audio lab, is set on fire to destroy evidence.

===Morgan and Rex {{anchor|Rex}}===
*Portrayed by Janet Land and Ron Lea
*Appears in: ''Saw IV''

Morgan and Rex are a married couple.  Rigg suspected Rex of abusing his wife and their daughter Jane but is unable to arrest him as Morgan and Jane refused to testify against him.  In frustration, Rigg punches Rex, prompting his lawyer Art to threaten him with a lawsuit.  Hoffman intercedes, claiming Rigg was acting in self-defense and the matter was dropped.  Rex and Morgan are later put into a Jigsaw test as part of Rigg's game.  The pair are locked back to back in a harness, their bodies impaled with several long spikes.  A tape left for Morgan informes her that she could free herself by removing the spikes but would kill Rex in the act; the spikes pierced major blood vessels on Rex's body.  When Rigg found the pair, Rex was dead and Morgan was unconscious, having removed all but one spike.  He gave her the key to the harness and told her she would have to save herself, then set off a fire alarm to alert the authorities to her presence.  When found by Strahm and Perez, Morgan said that Rigg had saved her.  The Director's Cut of the film shows Rigg removing the final spike himself.

===Peter Strahm===
[[File:Saw PeterStrahm.jpg|thumb|FBI Agent Peter Strahm]]
*Portrayed by [[Scott Patterson (actor)|Scott Patterson]]
*Appears in: ''Saw IV'', ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI''

Peter Strahm is an FBI Agent assigned to the Jigsaw case. Strahm is the first to theorize that Jigsaw may have have more than one apprentice and following the murder of Allison Kerry he becomes obsessed with stopping the killings. Pursuing Daniel Rigg as he engages in his own game, Strahm eventually finds Jigsaw and Amanda's corpses and kills Jeff Denlon in self defense. Strahm continues his pursuit of the final apprentice but is captured and placed in a game set to kill him but manages to escape. Suspicious of Hoffman, Strahm continues his investigation but is crushed to death in a trap when he again fails to follow the rules. Hoffman subsequently frames Strahm as the last apprentice, placing his mobile phone at a Jigsaw crime scene and using his recovered, severed-hand to place fingerprints on Jigsaw victims and traps. Though his partner Perez and boss Erickson both discover his innocence, they are murdered by Hoffman before they can act on the information and Hoffman once again plants his fingerprints at the scene, leaving Strahm as the suspected final Jigsaw apprentice. He is seen in archive footage throughout ''Saw VI'', and his corpse is seen at the beginning of the film.

===Tracy Rigg===
*Portrayed by Ingrid Hart
*Appears in: ''Saw IV''

Tracy Rigg is the wife of Officer Daniel Rigg, who is often alone at home because Rigg spends such a rigorous amount of time at his occupation. In her last appearance, she reminds Rigg that he cannot save everyone when he refuses to assist her and her mother.

===Trevor===
*Portrayed by Kevin Rushton
*Appears in: ''Saw IV'', ''[[Saw 3D]]''

Trevor appears in ''Saw IV'' as a victim placed in a trap with Art Blank. He awakes with his eyes sewn shut. He unknowingly has a key stuck to the back of his neck that would have freed both himself and Art, whose lips are sewn shut. Trevor attacks Art thinking he was a threat, but Art kills Trevor, retrieved the key and saves himself from the device they are chained to. ''Saw 3D'' reveals that it was Lawrence Gordon who sewed his eyes shut, and presumably Art's mouth.

==''Saw V''==
===Angelina Acomb===
*Portrayed by Sarah Flower
*Appears in: ''[[Saw V]]''

Angelina is the younger sister of Detective Mark Hoffman, who is murdered by her boyfriend Seth Baxter. Seth is later murdered by Hoffman after he is released from prison after merely five years on a technicality. When Hoffman is confronted by Jigsaw after the killing, he states that he loves his sister, and is infuriated when her killer is released from prison.

===Ashley Kazon===
*Portrayed by Laura Gordon
*Appears in: ''Saw V''

Ashley is killed in the Neck Tie Trap made by the apprentice of Jigsaw. The game consists of five people called &quot;The Fatal Five&quot;, their first test is to retrieve a key from across the room to unlock their collars. If they cannot retrieve the keys in 60 seconds the collars will pull them into a V blade that will decapitate them. Ashley is not able to pull herself hard enough to take the key so at the end she realizes that she cannot survive. She begins to scream in desperation until the clock runs out. She is an ex-fire inspector who was fired for covering up the arson behind a fire that kills 8 people; the main driving force behind ''Saw V''.

===Brit Stevenson===
*Portrayed by [[Julie Benz]]
*Appears in: ''Saw V''

Brit is the victim of Jigsaw's game in ''Saw V''. The vice president of a real estate company, Brit is placed in a series of four traps along with four other people. The five victims believes that one person will have to die in each room in order for the others to move ahead; Brit fatally stabs one of them herself in the third room. In the final room, though, she realizes that the group could have worked together so that everyone would survive to the end. She and Mallick, the only other person to reach this point, determines that the members of the group were connected through a building fire, which she had orchestrated, killing eight people. Brit and Mallick are forced to injure themselves severely in order to obtain enough blood to open the exit door. As she crawls from the room, Dan Erickson finds her and calls for medical assistance.

===Charles Salomon===
*Portrayed by [[Carlo Rota]]
*Appears in: ''Saw V''

Charles, a reporter, is a victim in the main game of ''Saw V'' alongside four other people. He is shown to be intelligent and to possess knowledge about the other victims and their mutual involvement in an arson scam. He attacks Mallick in two tests to obtain a key and ensure his survival but is attacked by Luba with a metal bar, left to die as the other three victims moves to safety from the explosive devices in the room. Charles realizes, too late, that the victims were supposed to work together and that they can all survive the traps with teamwork. The explosives detonates and kills Charles. Charles had been writing a report about the arson of the building Mallick burned down, but inevitably buried the story to serve whatever cynical needs of his own. 

===Dan Erickson===
*Portrayed by [[Mark Rolston]]
*Appears in: ''Saw V'', ''Saw VI''

Dan Erickson &lt;ref&gt;Erickson's first name &quot;Dan&quot; was shown during the end credits of ''Saw V.'' [http://www.lionsgatepublicity.com/epk/saw5/docs/pro_notes.doc SAW V Cast]&lt;/ref&gt; is an FBI agent in charge of the Jigsaw case. He relieves Peter Strahm of duty following his narrow escape from a Jigsaw trap and grew increasingly wary of him as Strahm became obsessed with Jigsaw. After he is informed by Hoffman that Strahm believes there to be another Jigsaw accomplice, Erickson places a trace on Strahm's mobile phone to find him. Going to the phones location, Erickson finds a Jigsaw facility and a heavily injured Brit and Mallick, victims of a current game, before calling for paramedics. In ''Saw VI'', Erickson returns alongside Lindsey Perez, having helped her fake her death for her own safety, to investigate Strahm's apparent link to Jigsaw. As they investigate, Erickson and Perez display suspicion of Hoffman, believing evidence implicating Strahm had been planted. Once the distortion is removed from the Jigsaw-style tape found at the Seth Baxter trap, Hoffman is revealed as the true accomplice. He lashes out violently, severing Erickson's jugular vein and stabbing Perez repeatedly. Erickson is shown to still be alive as Hoffman poured gasoline on his body to set him on fire and destroy the evidence.

===Luba Gibbs===
*Portrayed by [[Meagan Good]]
*Appears in: ''Saw V''

Luba, a city planner, was a victim in the main game of ''Saw V'', alongside four other people. Surviving the first trap, Luba assaults Charles after he attacks Mallick, leaving Charles to die when explosive devices in the room detonates. Luba made it to the third game but she is stabbed in the neck by Brit who did not trust her and her corpse is used as an electrical conductor to activate the door to the final trap. Luba is revealed to have played a role in an arson scam that killed eight people, an event that links all the victims of the game. She had accepted bribes from a sports team owned by her father, Richard Gibbs, to allow a stadium to be built on the site of the building Mallick burned down.

===Scott Mallick===
*Portrayed by [[Greg Bryk]]
*Appears in: ''Saw V'', ''[[Saw 3D]]''

Mallick, an arsonist and heroin addict, is one of five victims in the most prominent game in ''Saw V''. Suspicious of the other victims, Mallick manages to make it through most of the traps that are seemingly designed to kill off one of the victims per phase. He is saved by Luba in one test at the expense of Charles' life but she turns on him in another trap. Mallick is rescued by Brit who murders Luba and the pair used Luba's corpse to complete that phase of the game. In the final test, Mallick began to understand his connection to the other victims that is through an incident, orchestrated by Brit, in which he burned down a supposedly abandoned building, killing eight people and leaving him guilt-ridden. Mallick and Brit, realizing that the victims had been meant to work together to reach the final game, are forced to bi-sect their arms in a saw to provide enough blood to the device and end the game in time. With the game over, Mallick passes out from blood loss as Brit crawls out of the room. In ''Saw 3D'', Mallick appears in [[#Bobby Dagen|Bobby Dagen]]'s support group, wearing a cast on his injured arm.

===Pamela Jenkins===
*Portrayed by Samantha Lemole
*Appears in: ''Saw V'', ''Saw: The Video Game'', ''Saw VI''

Pamela is a reporter following the Jigsaw killings who first appears in ''Saw V'', attending a press conference being held by Mark Hoffman. In ''Saw VI'' she begins pursuing Jill Tuck for information about Jigsaw, presenting her with a letter found at an earlier Jigsaw crime-scene, later revealed to be that given by Hoffman to Amanda. She is kidnapped and placed in a cell opposite of Tara and Brent's with a message telling her that she is there as punishment for sensationalizing his story and twisting his message for her own gain, and is be forced to &quot;experience the meaning of sacrifice&quot; and &quot;see the consequence for those who unjustly hurt others&quot;.  At the end of [[#William Easton|William Easton]]'s game, he is confronted by Pamela, who is revealed to be his sister, and the family of a [[#Harrold Abbott|man]] whose medical insurance had been denied by William, in part leading to his death. The man's [[#Brent|son]] activates a device which kills William as Pamela watches. Pamela also appears in ''[[Saw (video game)|Saw: The Video Game]]'', providing information to another journalist, [[#Oswald McGullicuty|Oswald McGullicuty]], who plans to write a book and not credit Pamela. Knowing this, Pamela steals all his notes, preventing him from writing the book, in order to write a book of her own. Despite her relationship to William Easton, the game and films show her last name as Jenkins.

===Seth Baxter===
*Portrayed by Joris Jarsky
*Appears in: ''Saw V''

Seth Baxter is the boyfriend and murderer of Hoffman's younger sister. After serving five years of a life sentence in prison, he is released on a technicality. Hoffman, enraged by the death of his only family member, kidnaps Seth and puts him in a trap that mimics Jigsaw's methods but is rigged to be inescapable. In order to avoid being killed by a swinging pendulum blade, he is told, he must put his hands into two presses and push the starter buttons to crush them. Even though he does so, the pendulum still descends and slices him in half as Hoffman watches through a peephole. Seth appears in flashbacks in Saw VI, where the FBI, investigating Peter Strahm's connection to Jigsaw, discover that the trap had not, in fact, been done by Jigsaw, as Hoffman used a knife with serrated edge to carve the jigsaw piece into Baxter's body instead of the surgical quality blade used by John, a detail pointed out by Dr. Hefner, who is the mortician for every dead Jigsaw victim.

==''Saw VI''==
===Addy and Allen===
*Portrayed by Janelle Hutchison and Shawn Ahmed.
*Appears in: ''[[Saw VI]]'', ''[[Saw 3D]]'' (Addy)

Addy and Allen, William Easton's secretary and file clerk, are victims forced to take part in his second game at the abandoned Rowan Zoological Institute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zoo&quot;&gt;The zoo's name is mentioned at the beginning of ''Saw 3D'' on a TV while Hoffman is stitching up his face (at the 10:55 mark).&lt;/ref&gt; They are standing on retractable ledges with [[barbed wire]] nooses around their necks and with their hands tied so they can not free themselves, while William holds the ends of two chains connected to the ledges. In order to move on, he has to drop one chain and let that person die. He is presented with information that Addy is a diabetic and in poor health but had a family, while Allen is in good health but had no loved ones to leave behind. The chains are gradually reeled in, making it harder for William to keep holding them both; he finally chooses to save Addy, while the wire noose cut Allen's throat and strangles him to death when his ledge retracts.

In ''Saw 3D'', Addy is part of Bobby Dagen's self-help group meeting.

===Brent and Tara Abbott {{anchor|Brent|Tara}}===
*Portrayed by [[Devon Bostick]] and [[Shauna MacDonald]]
*Appears in: ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D'' (Tara)

Brent and Tara are the teenage son and widow of a man named Harold Abbott whose health insurance policy is revoked by William Easton on a technicality, contributing to his death. They are captured and placed in one of two cages at the abandoned Rowan Zoological Institute&lt;ref name=&quot;Zoo&quot;/&gt; at the end of William's series of tests, with [[#Pamela Jenkins|Pamela Jenkins]] in the other. Once William reaches the end, Tara and Brent are given the choice of sparing his life or ending it. Despite expressing anger for her husband's death, Tara listens to the pleas for mercy from both William and Pamela, but cannot bring herself to kill William. However, Brent can not forgive him and triggers the device himself, causing a group of needles to swing down into William's back and inject him with [[hydrofluoric acid]]. Pamela, Tara, and Brent watches in horror as he is dissolved from the inside out.

Tara appears in ''[[Saw 3D]]'' at Bobby Dagen's self-help group meeting.  Devon Bostick was offered to return as Brent, but turned it down due to scheduling conflicts with ''Hidden 3D''.&lt;ref name=&quot;demonDevon&quot;&gt;{{cite podcast|url=http://www.demonfm.co.uk/?q=node/1449|title=Demon FM Meets....Devon Bostick (at '''11:15 11:55''')|website=Demon FM |host=[[Devon Bostick]], David Murphy and Matt Horn |date=September 30, 2010 | accessdate=October 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Carousel Room Victims{{anchor|Aaron|Dave|Emily|Gena|Josh|Shelby}}===
*Portrayed by: [[James Gilbert (actor)|James Gilbert]] (Aaron), [[Darius McCrary]] (Dave), Larissa Gomes (Emily), [[Melanie Scrofano]] (Gena), Shawn Mathieson (Josh), [[Karen Cliche]] (Shelby)
*Appears in: ''Saw VI'', ''[[Saw 3D]]'' (Emily)

Aaron, Dave, Emily, Gena, Josh, and Shelby (collectively referred to as &quot;The Dog Pit&quot; by their boss, William Easton) are six of William's junior associates, who did the investigative work as a teamed unit to weed out health insurance applications and claims that can be denied. They are placed at the abandoned Rowan Zoological Institute&lt;ref name=&quot;Zoo&quot;/&gt; into the last of William's four tests, chained to a [[carousel]] and facing a shotgun mounted on a mechanical winch. Just as their work resulted in  of all applications being denied or prematurely terminated, William can choose only  of the group of sixtwo of them can be saved by pushing buttons that will drive spikes into his hand, while the other four will die. If he does nothing, all six will be killed. Each argues and accuses one another of trying to win William's favor as he struggles with his decisions. Ultimately he chooses to save Emily, a mother of two, and Shelby, whose parents are sick and needed her to take care of them. Aaron, Gena, Dave, and Josh are left to die in that order. The carousel stops on Aaron first, making him the first to die. Gena dies second and is the third person the carousel stops on; she insists that she is pregnant while everyone opposes her and calls her a liar. Dave dies third as the fourth round of the carousel stops on him; he tries to bribe William for his life. Josh becomes outraged and angry at William for choosing Shelby instead of him, criticizing him and shouting for William to look him in the eye as he become the last to die on the carousel.

In ''Saw 3D'' Emily is part of Bobby Dagen's survivor group meeting.

===Debbie===
*Portrayed by [[Caroline Cave]]
*Appears in: ''Saw VI''

Debbie is the attorney for Umbrella Health and William Easton.  She is kidnapped and placed in William's third test at the abandoned Rowan Zoological Institute&lt;ref name=&quot;Zoo&quot;/&gt;, with a device strapped to her chest which will launch a spear through her head unless she reaches the end of a steel-cage maze in 90 seconds. William has to help her, diverting jets of scalding steam away from her path and onto himself, severely burning him. After reaching the end of the maze, she discovers that to escape the device she will need a key sewn into William's flesh. She attacks him with a nearby circular saw but is unable to retrieve the key before her time runs out; the device activates and kills her.

===Eddie===
*Portrayed by Marty Moreau
*Appears in: ''Saw VI''

Eddie is a [[predatory lending]] banker, who takes part in a test in ''Saw VI'', along with his co-worker [[List of Saw characters#Simone|Simone]], in which they are placed in adjoining cells. He wears a head harness with screws poised at the temples, and has a knife and a meat cleaver on hand. A balance scale is placed between his and Simone's cell; the one who can cut off more weight in body parts and put them on the scale in 60 seconds will live, while the other will be killed by the screws boring into his or her skull. Eddie, being overweight, slices several chunks of flesh from his stomach, but Simone severs her left arm and tips the scale in her favor, leading to Eddie's death.

===Hank===
*Portrayed by [[Gerry Mendicino]]
*Appears in: ''Saw VI''

Hank is a janitor for Umbrella Health, working for William Easton. He is kidnapped and placed in the first of William's four tests, suspended in a vice-like trap which will crush either his or William's chest, leaving only one survivor. Jigsaw informs them that every breath they take will cause the vice to tighten and that Hank is a smoker, despite a history of health problems. Though William encourages Hank to hold his breath he is unable to do so, breathing heavily until the vice crushes and kills him, freeing William.

===Harold Abbott===
*Portrayed by [[George Newbern]]
*Appears in: ''Saw VI''

Harold is the husband of Tara and father of Brent. Flashbacks throughout ''Saw VI'' reveal that his health insurance policy was revoked by William Easton due to a discrepancy found on his application, and he would later die from heart disease. Tara and Brent, his widow and son, are placed in a game that puts William's life at stake. Brent kills him by activating a trap which injects [[hydrofluoric acid]] into his body, as an act of revenge for William's role in Harold's death.

===Simone===
*Portrayed by [[Tanedra Howard]]
*Appears in: ''Saw VI'', ''Saw 3D''

Simone is a [[predatory lending]] banker, who takes part in a test along with her co-worker [[List of Saw characters#Eddie|Eddie]] in ''Saw VI''. They are placed in adjoining cells. Since they have figuratively extracted their &quot;pound of flesh&quot; from loan recipients who they knew could never pay them back, they will literally have to do the same in order to survive. She wears a head harness with screws poised at the temples, and has a knife and a meat cleaver on hand. A balance scale is placed between her and Eddie's cell; whichever captive cuts off the most weight in body parts and throws them onto the scale in sixty seconds will live, while the other will be killed by the screws boring into his or her skull. Eddie, being overweight, slices several chunks of flesh from his stomach, but Simone who is slender, realizes she has no other choice but to sever her arm, which quickly tips the scale in her favor. Simone survives and is later questioned by Hoffman and the FBI in her hospital room. She violently retaliates toward Hoffman when he asks her if she learned from her experience.

Simone appears in ''Saw 3D'' at Bobby Dagen's survivor group meeting. She berates [[List of Saw characters#Sydney|Sydney]], saying that it should not have taken a trap to leave her boyfriend, and states that her test had taught her nothing and the damage from her survival has only amplified her bitterness towards life, especially since her appearance in the previous film.

===William Easton===
*Portrayed by [[Peter Outerbridge]]
*Appears in: ''Saw VI''

William Easton is an insurance executive at Umbrella Health who is a target of Jigsaw's tests. His company was responsible for John Kramer's medical coverage which denied him funding for experimental treatment of his cancer and he had helped fund Jill Tuck's rehab clinic. William's tests takes place at the abandoned Rowan Zoological Institute&lt;ref name=&quot;Zoo&quot;/&gt; and involves him making similar decisions about who will live and die from his work life before a timer runs out or else he will be dismembered by explosives strapped to his limbs. Completing his tests, he discovers himself in a fifth test, which is not meant for him but for the surviving family of a man whose coverage had been canceled by William. Though he and his captured sister, Pamela Jenkins, were able to appeal to the wife's humanity and spare William, her son activates the device which impaled William on a bed of needles which pumped [[hydrofluoric acid]] into his body, dissolving his body in half and killing him.

==''Saw 3D''==
===Brad, Dina, and Ryan===
{{anchor|Brad|Dina|Ryan}}
*Portrayed by [[Sebastian Pigott]] (Brad), Anne Lee Greene (Dina), Jon Cor (Ryan)
*Appears in: ''[[Saw 3D]]''

These three victims are placed in a storefront window at a public shopping center. Brad and Ryan are chained by the wrists to opposite ends of a worktable, while Dina is suspended above its center. A movable carriage with three razor wheels - one facing each man, a third aimed at Dina - is attached to the table. Appearing on the scene, Billy the puppet states that Dina has manipulated both men's affections for her in order to coerce them into stealing things for her. Since she had claimed to love each man, they will have the chance to fight for her love and their survival. In order to free her, one will have to push the carriage to the other's end within 60 seconds, killing him; alternatively, they can spare each other and Dina will die once the timer runs out. After a brief fight in which Brad is slightly wounded, Ryan offers a truce and they chose to save themselves, leaving Dina to be cut in half by the center wheel.  

Jon Cor's character was originally written to die, but was changed during filming.&lt;ref name=&quot;DemonJon&quot;&gt;{{cite podcast|url=http://www.demonfm.co.uk/?q=node/1513|title=Demon FM Meets...Jon Cor (Saw 3D)|work=[[DemonFM]]|date=October 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bobby Dagen===
{{anchor|Bobby}}
*Portrayed by [[Sean Patrick Flanery]]
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Bobby Dagen is the author of a self-help book based on his accounts of surviving a Jigsaw trap. In reality, though, he has made the entire story up in order to find quick fame and success. He is abducted and put into a series of tests at the abandoned Clear Dawn Psychiatric Hospital, along with his wife Joyce and three of his key staff members. Three of his tests each lead to the death of one staffer; in the next, he must pull out two of his teeth in order to obtain the combination to the door leading to Joyce. For the final test, he must undergo the ordeal that he claimed to have endured in his book: drive two meathooks through his pectoral muscles, then haul himself up on the attached chains to connect two extension cords and shut off the electrified wire around Joyce's platform. As he is about to plug in the cords, the hooks tear out of his flesh and he drops to the floor, and he watches helplessly as a large metal capsule slams shut around Joyce and she is incinerated within it.

===Cale===
*Portrayed by [[Dean Armstrong]]
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Cale is Bobby Dagen's best friend and co-conspirator in his lies as a Jigsaw survivor. He is deemed as &quot;hearing no evil&quot;, after choosing to help Bobby carry off his scheme to become famous by fabricating the account of surviving a trap. Blindfolded and hooked to a noose on the end of a [[winch]] at the abandoned Clear Dawn Psychiatric Hospital, Cale stands at one end of a hallway whose floor has fallen away to leave only the support beams and a few loose planks. Bobby is at the other end, and the key to free Cale hangs from the ceiling between them. In 60 seconds, Bobby must guide Cale across the hallway, get the key, and pass it to him in order to prevent him from being hanged. Bobby throws the key to Cale, who just misses catching it and dies when the winch lifts him off his feet.

===Dan, Evan, Jake, and Kara===
{{anchor|Dan|Evan|Jake|Kara}}
*Portrayed by Dru Viergever (Dan), [[Chester Bennington]] (Evan), Benjamin Clost (Jake), [[Gabby West]] (Kara)

These four victims, all members of a skinhead gang, are placed in a trap set inside a junkyard's garage. Evan is in the driver's seat of a car whose rear end is up on jacks, with his back, arms, and legs glued down. His girlfriend Kara is tied down to the floor with barbed wire, her head directly beneath one rear wheel; Dan stands strapped to a pole behind the car, with chains running from the bumper to his wrists and jaw; Jake is chained to the closed garage door, directly in front of the car. To save them and himself, Evan must tear himself loose from the seat and pull a lever protruding from the engine compartment within 30 seconds as the engine revs. He fails to do so, and the car is dropped off its jacks, crushing Kara's head. As it speeds forward Dan's arms and jaw are ripped off, Jake is hit and killed, and the car crashes into a pile of wrecks outside, causing Evan to go flying through the windshield.

===Matt Gibson===
{{anchor|Matt}}
*Portrayed by [[Chad Donella]]
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Matt Gibson is an internal affairs detective who takes an interest in the Jigsaw case when Jill Tuck asks to speak to him personally. She offers to turn over evidence of Hoffman's crimes in exchange for police protection and immunity from prosecution. When Gibson was a uniformed officer, his life was saved by Hoffman, who killed an unarmed homeless man menacing Gibson. The incident led Gibson to mistrust Hoffman from that moment on, and he and his partner Rogers lead the efforts to find him. Clues left by Hoffman lead Gibson to the observation area for Hoffman's tests of Bobby Dagen, where he is killed by a remote-controlled automatic weapon placed in the room.

===Joyce Dagen===
{{anchor|Joyce}}
*Portrayed by [[Gina Holden]]
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Joyce is [[#Bobby Dagen|Bobby Dagen]]'s wife. She did not know her husband had lied about not being in a Jigsaw trap. She is placed in Bobby's test at the abandoned Clear Dawn Psychiatric Hospital, when she wakes up with a collar connected to her neck which gradually draws her closer to the floor. As Joyce watches Bobby fail his tests, he makes it to her in time to save her. He must re-enact the test he claimed to have survived; however, he fails to complete it, resulting in Joyce being enclosed in a [[Brazen Bull]] and burned to death.

===Nina===
*Portrayed by Naomi Snieckus
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Nina is Bobby Dagen's publicist, who is deemed as &quot;speaking no evil&quot; by being his greatest link to the media but never revealing the truth of Bobby being a fraud. She is also being held at the abandoned Clear Dawn Psychiatric Hospital; locked in a straitjacket and surrounded by four spikes aimed at her neck, Nina has a fishhook and line down her throat, with a key at the end that will release her. Bobby has 60 seconds to pull the hook up from her stomach. Attached to the mechanism is a decibel meter that propels the spikes closer to Nina whenever the room's sound level rises above a whisper. The timer starts and Bobby repeatedly stops to quiet Nina's screams before he finally pulls the key free, but he is too late and the trap kills her.

===Rogers===
*Portrayed by: Laurence Anthony
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Rogers is an [[Internal affairs (law enforcement)|Internal Affairs]] officer who helps Gibson investigate Hoffman. Once Gibson figures out Hoffman's location, he puts Rogers in charge of guarding Jill Tuck, who has been moved to a holding cell in the police station for her protection. After Hoffman sneaks back into the station, he kills every officer standing between him and Jill, with Rogers being the last to die.

===Palmer===
*Portrayed by: [[Kim Schraner]]
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Palmer is an [[Internal affairs (law enforcement)|Internal Affairs]] officer who works with Gibson. She traces Hoffman's location via the messages he sends to Gibson, but is killed by Hoffman while he is searching for Jill Tuck.

===Sidney===
{{anchor|Sydney|Sidney}}
*Portrayed by: [[Olunike Adeliyi|Wendy Olunike Adeliyi]]
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Sidney is a Jigsaw survivor who appears at Bobby Dagen's support group.  She reveals that she had been placed into a trap with her abusive boyfriend, Alex, suspended above a series of upturned lawnmowers.  Alex tried to knock her to her death but fell, killing himself in the process and saving her.  She remarks during the group that the trap &quot;set her free&quot; of his abuse.

===Suzanne===
*Portrayed by Rebecca Marshall
*Appears in: ''Saw 3D''

Suzanne is Bobby Dagen's lawyer, who is deemed as &quot;seeing no evil&quot; by ignoring her duty as a lawyer and turning a blind eye to Bobby's fraud. Her test occurs at the abandoned Clear Dawn Psychiatric Hospital; she is placed horizontally inside a steel frame that begins to rotate her toward a standing position, where three spikes are placed to pierce her eyes and mouth. To save her, Bobby must lift a pair of weighted handles at shoulder height and hold them for at least 30 seconds to stop Suzanne's rig from approaching the spikes. However, as he does this, two rods pierce his sides. Bobby begins the task and drops the contraption before holding it as Suzanne is inches from death. With only two seconds left, Bobby painfully drops it and Suzanne is killed.

==''Saw: The Video Game''==
===Jennings Foster===
*Portrayed by Troy Lund
*Appears in: ''[[Saw (video game)|Saw: The Video Game]]'', ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]''

Jennings is the head of a CSI team who cooperates with David Tapp's department to solve murder cases. Unbeknownst to others, Jennings committed a hit-and-run years ago that led him to frame an innocent citizen to avoid conviction himself. For this, Jigsaw places Jennings as a victim for Tapp to save in a pendulum trap similar to the one  featured in ''Saw V''. Tapp saves him, but Jennings blames Tapp for being there and runs away. He also makes a brief appearance in ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]'', where he is seen assisting the investigation into Tapp's death and photographing the crime scene at David Tapp's apartment. In one of the case files, he seems to be very grateful towards Tapp for saving his life.

===Melissa Sing===
*Portrayed by Kahn Doan
*Appears in: ''Saw: The Video Game''''

Melissa is the widow of [[#Steven Sing|Detective Steven Sing]], who is killed after falling victim to one of Jigsaw's traps in ''[[Saw (film)|Saw]]''. Upon Steven's death, Melissa becomes a neglectful parent to her son, Franklin and blames [[David Tapp|Tapp]] for ruining her family. For this, she is placed in Whitehurst Asylum during ''Saw: The Video Game'' in an iron-maiden trap for Tapp to save her from. Tapp saves her, but she left him quickly. During the finale of the game, if the player chooses the ''Truth'' door, Melissa is revealed to have been held against her will following her trap and was forced to help Jigsaw, keeping Tapp's game going until 6:00, or her son would die. Attempting to evade Tapp, she is accidentally killed by a shotgun trap. However, in the ''Freedom'' ending, she is saved along with the other victims in the asylum and set free, never having her incidental ties to Jigsaw revealed.

A file written by Tapp in ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]'' confirmed that Melissa survives the events of the previous game.

===Oswald McGullicuty===
*Portrayed by [[David Scully (actor)|David Scully]]
*Appears in: ''Saw: The Video Game''

Oswald is the newspaper writer who coined the nickname &quot;The Jigsaw Killer&quot;. One of his articles is seen in ''[[Saw (film)|Saw]]''. In the game, Oswald is placed in Whitehurst Asylum due to Jigsaw believing Oswald is perverting his message and also for blaming Tapp of being the real Jigsaw Killer. It is revealed in case files that Oswald was originally writing a novel about Jigsaw, but his notes were stolen by [[#Pamela Easton|Pamela Jenkins]] in an effort to thwart him and write a book of her own. Tapp finds Oswald in a folding table trap, which he releases him from, only to be killed by metal slabs immediately after.

===Pighead===&lt;!--[[Pighead]] redirected here--&gt;
*Appears in: ''Saw: The Video Game''

Pighead is a masked person who works for Jigsaw. He appears in ''Saw: The Video Game'' and watches over [[#David Tapp|Detective Tapp]]'s game. He is shown to be hostile and is witnessed by Detective Tapp killing several test subjects around Whitehurst Asylum. Pighead seems to taunt Detective Tapp throughout the game, and sometimes attempts to come after him. Later on near the end of the game, Detective Tapp is required to fight Pighead, who wants to kill Tapp and sabotage his game in order to surpass Jigsaw. Tapp manages to kill Pighead and get hold of a key to the library where his final choice is awaiting. Jigsaw labels Tapp a &quot;murderer&quot; for killing his servant. Pighead wears a red boxer robe and the infamous pig mask concealing his identity.  He is referenced in one of David Tapp's audio tapes in ''Saw II: Flesh and Blood'', with Tapp feeling guilt having killed him, not knowing if the person in the costume had a family or is another victim forced to obey Jigsaw.

==''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''==
===Campbell Iman===
*Appears in: ''[[Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood]]''

Campbell is a playable character in ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''. He is targeted by Jigsaw because of his addiction to drugs and his estrangement from his son, who is also a drug-addict. His last name is mentioned in a case file which also revealed that he has lymphoma. Jigsaw places him in a &quot;Venus Fly Trap&quot; device which he escapes by cutting out a key buried near his own eye. After traversing several traps, Campbell is informed that there is another subject, Michael Tapp, in the game and that only one may live. Campbell is given the choice of sacrificing himself for a stranger, who has a potentially long life ahead of him, or saving himself, knowing he has only a short time to live because of his cancer. This choice decides the fate of Michael Tapp at the end of the game.

If Campbell sacrifices himself, he gets crushed by spiked moving walls. If Campbell chooses to save himself, Michael dies and Campbell meets Jigsaw who informs him that his son is safe, having passed his own test prior to the events of the game, and all he has to do is leave through the exit. Campbell instead attempts to attack Jigsaw only to be killed by a concealed, falling scythe.

===Henry Jacobs===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Henry is the Chief of Police in David Tapp's precinct. He is involved in the Jigsaw cases and is the chief officer involved in the investigation into Detective Tapp's death. Henry is involved in a conspiracy alongside Joseph, Carla, and Sarah to steal seized drugs and sell them on the streets, bringing him to Jigsaw's attention. When Michael finds him, Henry is strapped to a chair with a revolver placed in his mouth that will fire unless Michael can pass a test. Though he appears helpful upon his release, he begins stalking Michael throughout the game in order to kill him and prevent his corruption from being revealed. After Joseph escapes, Henry finds and allies himself with Joseph in order to find Michael and any others who could reveal their secrets, leading him to murder Carla Song. Henry later runs into Pighead II, who stabs him repeatedly in the chest.

===Joseph Poltzer===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Joseph is a corrupt vice cop who abused his position to steal drugs seized from criminals and sell them in a cartel, alongside Henry, Carla, and Sarah. As a member of the group, he is kidnapped by Jigsaw and placed in a vice trap designed to crush all of his limbs and his skull unless Michael can save him. Michael's father had accidentally uncovered their drug cartel while investigating Jigsaw, so he teamed-up with the Henry Jacobs to hunt and kill Michael, Carla, and Sarah to tie up any loose ends that could reveal their criminal actions. He later executes Sarah as she is about to reveal the true identity of Pighead II. He and Michael get embroiled in a fight which results in them breaking through a wall and plummeting into an alley below. They struggle over Joseph's gun, but Michael eventually triumphs and fatally shoots Joseph in the head.

===Michael Tapp===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Michael Tapp is Detective [[David Tapp]]'s estranged son and the main, playable-character in ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''. He is a reporter, investigating his father's recent death when he is captured by Pighead II and forced to undergo a series of lethal traps set up by Jigsaw.  As he progress he saves several people, freeing Henry, Sarah, Joseph, Carla and Solomon while surviving other victims loose in the game; criminals previously arrested by his father after revenge on his son. Though initially friendly, Henry, and later Joseph, begins stalking Michael in order to kill him and prevent his corruption and role in a drug cartel being revealed should Michael escape. Henry is killed by Pighead II before he can kill him however and Michael is able to kill Joseph himself. During the game, Michael is revealed to have abused his strained relationship with his father to steal documents pertaining to the Jigsaw case, including David's botched sting that resulted in [[#Steven Sing|Detective Steven Sing's]] death. Using this information for personal gain and revenge against his father for feelings of abandonment, Michael wrote an expos which destroyed his father's career, unwittingly aiding the drug cartel run by Henry and Joseph, and partially contributing to his father's eventual suicide.

In the finale, it is revealed that Campbell and Michael's tests had occurred concurrently, with Michael's fate left in Campbell's hands. Campbell is given the choice at the end of his own test to sacrifice himself for Michael, a stranger, or save himself at Michael's expense. If Campbell chooses himself, Michael is trapped and crushed to death by a spiked moving ceiling. If Campbell sacrifices himself, Michael survives.  Jigsaw reveals that Michael's real test is to see if he had the ability to punish the corrupt (Henry and Joseph) and so he is given a choice between two doors; one leads Michael to freedom and the chance to use the evidence found by his father to print the story of Jigsaw and the drug cartel. The other door reveals a Pighead costume and an offer to help people see the truth inside themselves, implying Michael can become Jigsaw's apprentice. The choice made is not revealed to the player.

===Pighead II {{anchor|Pighead 2|Pig Head II|Pig Head 2}}===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Pighead II is a character in the second video game, a replacement for the [[#Pig Head|Pighead]] who died during the events of the first game. Little is known about the character except that he is garbed in similar attire to the original Pighead and that he is involved in placing some individuals into their respective traps, including Carla. Throughout the game, he can be seen kidnapping Michael and killing other victims. He later corners and kills Henry Jacobs. Before her death, Sarah Blalok indicated that Michael Tapp knew the man behind the pig mask and that he is a friend of his father's. However, she is killed before she reveals his identity. Although Pighead appears to work for Jigsaw, he commits acts of murder against his philosophy. Pighead II is never hostile towards Michael.

===Sarah Blalok===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Sarah is a drug addict, [[prostitute]], and an informant for David Tapp. David gives her a second chance by helping her escape from her previous life. Following his death, however, she begins to fall back into her previous lifestyle. She blames Michael Tapp for betraying his father and contributing to his suicide. Michael finds her trapped in a sealed tank slowly filling with water and is forced to solve a puzzle to free her before she drowns. Though initially hostile towards Michael, she later becomes more friendly, explaining that his father loved Michael even after his betrayal. She is revealed to have been part of a criminal conspiracy alongside Carla, Henry, and Joseph; her role being to sell drugs on the streets.  While searching for Jigsaw, David Tapp discovers their drug cartel and Sarah is used to mislead him, even though she is aware that Tapp is not concerned about the drug cartel because of his obsession with Jigsaw. Through her own admission, it is revealed that she had feelings for David. She is found by Joseph Poltzer as she is about to disclose the identity of Pighead II. Joseph sneaks up on Sarah and shoots her in the head.

===Solomon Bates===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Solomon is an accountant involved in a housing development project with John Kramer and Art Blank before the events that would turn John into Jigsaw. He is later responsible for using his accountancy role to hide the illegal money made by the drug cartel consisting of Henry, Joseph, Carla and Sarah, thus bringing him to Jigsaw's attention. When Michael finds him, Solomon is found chained to a suspended cart set on a track filled with slowly-rising flames that will burn him alive unless Michael pushes him out of harm's way. Upon his release, he reveals the truth about the members of the drug cartel and that Michael's father accidentally stumbled on their operations during his search for Jigsaw. He is last seen being cornered by Pighead II and thrown into a pit of syringes. Pighead II then seals the door before Michael can enter.

===Zeke===
*Appears in: ''Saw II: Flesh &amp; Blood''

Zeke is a Jigsaw victim whose original trap mangles his hands beyond repair, stripping away much of the flesh. He is in fact a [[pedophile]] who molested little girls, and is saved from his trap by Michael but passes out from blood loss. Between this event and the events of the game, he has his damaged forearms replaced with large blades and becomes psychotic, chasing and attempting to kill Michael at any opportunity. Michael manages to lure him in between two spiked wall devices in front of a door way that snap shut and crush him.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==

{{Saw}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Saw Characters}}
[[Category:Lists of film characters|Saw]]
[[Category:Saw characters|*]]

[[ar::  ]]
[[da:Fiktive personer i Saw]]
[[es:Anexo:Personajes de Saw]]
[[fr:Personnages de la srie Saw]]
[[ru:   ]]
[[sv:Lista ver karaktrer i Saw]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
