<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="803950" ns="0" title="Cell (microprocessor)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Power Architecture}}

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Cell Broadband Engine Processor.jpg|300px|right|thumb|Layout of the IBM Cell die]] --&gt;
'''Cell''' is a [[microprocessor]] architecture jointly developed by [[Sony]], [[Sony Computer Entertainment]], [[Toshiba]], and [[IBM]], an alliance known as &quot;STI&quot;. The architectural design and first implementation were carried out at the STI Design Center in [[Austin, Texas]] over a four-year period beginning March 2001 on a budget reported by Sony as approaching [[US$]]400 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ps3.qj.net/Cell-Designer-talks-about-PS3-and-IBM-Cell-Processors/pg/49/aid/14805|title=Cell Designer talks about PS3 and IBM Cell Processors|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cell is shorthand for '''Cell Broadband Engine Architecture''', commonly abbreviated ''CBEA'' in full or ''Cell BE'' in part. Cell combines a general-purpose [[Power Architecture]] [[Multi-core (computing)|core]] of modest performance with streamlined [[coprocessor|coprocessing]] elements&lt;ref name=&quot;ibmrpaper&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.research.ibm.com/people/m/mikeg/papers/2006_ieeemicro.pdf|title=Synergistic Processing in Cell&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s Multicore Architecture|publisher=IEEE|accessdate=2007-03-22|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; which greatly accelerate [[multimedia]] and [[vector processing]] applications, as well as many other forms of dedicated computation.&lt;ref name=&quot;ibmrpaper&quot;/&gt;

The first major commercial application of Cell was in Sony's [[PlayStation 3]] [[Video game console|game console]]. [[Mercury Computer Systems]] has a dual Cell server, a dual Cell [[Blade server|blade]] configuration, a rugged computer, and a PCI Express accelerator board available in different stages of production. Toshiba had announced plans to incorporate Cell in [[High-definition television|high definition]] television sets, but have seemed to abandon the idea. Exotic features such as the [[XDR DRAM|XDR]] memory subsystem and coherent [[#Element Interconnect Bus (EIB)|Element Interconnect Bus]] (EIB) interconnect&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hotchips.org/archives/hc17/2_Mon/HC17.S1/HC17.S1T2.pdf|title=Cell Broadband Engine Interconnect and Memory Interface|publisher=IBM|accessdate=2007-03-22|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; appear to position Cell for future applications in the [[supercomputing]] space to exploit the Cell processor's prowess in [[floating point]] kernels. 

The Cell architecture includes a [[memory coherence]] architecture that emphasizes efficiency/watt, prioritizes [[Bandwidth (computing)|bandwidth]] over [[Latency (engineering)|latency]], and favors peak computational [[throughput]] over simplicity of [[Code (computer programming)|program code]]. For these reasons, Cell is widely regarded as a challenging environment for [[Software engineering|software development]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.com.com/Octopiler+seeks+to+arm+Cell+programmers/2100-1007_3-6042132.html|title=Octopiler seeks to arm Cell programmers|first=Stephen|last=Shankland|publisher=CNET|date=2006-02-22|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; IBM provides a comprehensive [[Linux]]-based Cell development platform to assist developers in confronting these challenges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://lwn.net/Articles/159564/|title=Cell Broadband Engine Software Development Kit Version 1.0|publisher=LWN|date=2005-11-10|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Software adoption remains a key issue in whether Cell ultimately delivers on its performance potential. Despite those challenges, research has indicated that Cell excels at several types of scientific computation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lbl.gov/Science-Articles/Archive/sabl/2006/Jul/CellProcessorPotential.pdf|title=The Potential of the Cell Processor for Scientific Computing|coauthors=Samuel Williams, John Shalf, Leonid Oliker, Shoaib Kamil, Parry Husbands, Katherine Yelick|publisher=Computational Research Division, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory|accessdate=2010-12-24|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear:left&quot;&gt;{{Cell microprocessor segments}}

==History==

[[Image:Peter Hofstee.jpg|right|thumbnail|[[Peter Hofstee]], one of the chief architects of the Cell microprocessor]]

In mid-2000, [[Sony Computer Entertainment]], [[Toshiba Corporation]], and [[IBM]] formed an alliance known as &quot;STI&quot; to design and manufacture the processor.&lt;ref&gt;Krewell, Kevin (14 February 2005). &quot;Cell Moves Into the Limelight&quot;. ''[[Microprocessor Report]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The STI Design Center opened in March 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;kahle&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Introduction to the Cell multiprocessor | publisher=IBM Journal of Research and Development |
url=http://researchweb.watson.ibm.com/journal/rd/494/kahle.html|date=2005-08-07|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Cell was designed over a period of four years, using enhanced versions of the design tools for the [[POWER4]] processor. Over 400 engineers from the three companies worked together in Austin, with critical support from eleven of IBM's design centers.&lt;ref name=&quot;kahle&quot;/&gt;

During this period, IBM filed many [[patents]] pertaining to the Cell architecture, manufacturing process, and software environment. An early patent version of the Broadband Engine was shown to be a chip package comprising four &quot;Processing Elements&quot;, which was the patent's description for what is now known as the ''Power Processing Element''. Each Processing Element contained 8 ''APUs'', which are now referred to as SPEs on the current Broadband Engine chip. Said chip package was widely regarded to run at a clock speed of 4&amp;nbsp;GHz and with 32 APUs providing 32&amp;nbsp;[[FLOPS|GFLOPS]] each, the Broadband Engine was shown to have 1 teraflop of raw computing power. This design was fabricated using a [[90 nm|90&amp;nbsp;nm]] [[Silicon on insulator|SOI]] process.&lt;ref name=&quot;xbit-65&quot;/&gt;

In March 2007 IBM announced that the [[65 nm|65&amp;nbsp;nm]] version of Cell BE is in production at its plant in [[East Fishkill, New York]].&lt;ref name=&quot;xbit-65&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=IBM Produces Cell Processor Using New Fabrication Technology. | url=http://www.xbitlabs.com/news/cpu/display/20070312121941.html | publisher=X-bit labs | accessdate=March 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.psu.com/node/7409|title=65nm CELL processor production started|publisher=PlayStation Universe|date=2007-01-30|accessdate=2007-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2008, IBM announced that it will begin to fabricate Cell processors with the [[45 nm|45&amp;nbsp;nm]] process.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20080207-ibm-shrinks-cell-to-45nm-cheaper-ps3s-will-follow.html IBM shrinks Cell to 45nm. Cheaper PS3s will follow&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2008, IBM introduced the high-performance double-precision floating-point version of the Cell processor, the [[PowerXCell 8i]],&lt;ref name = &quot;PowerXCell 8i&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=IBM Offers Higher Performance Computing Outside the Lab | url=http://www.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/24180.wss | publisher=IBM | accessdate=May 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; at the 65&amp;nbsp;nm feature size.

In May 2008, an [[Opteron]]- and PowerXCell 8i-based supercomputer, the [[IBM Roadrunner]] system, became the world's first system to achieve one petaFLOPS, and was the fastest computer in the world until third quarter 2009. The world's three most energy efficient supercomputers, as represented by the [[Green500]] list, are similarly based on the PowerXCell 8i.

The 45&amp;nbsp;nm Cell processor was introduced in concert with Sony's [[PlayStation 3#Slim_model|PlayStation 3 Slim]] in August 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArsTechnicaInterview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2009/08/sony-answers-our-questions-about-the-new-playstation-3.ars |title=Sony answears our questions about the new PlayStation 3 |date=August 18, 2009 |accessdate=August 19, 2009 |publisher=[[Ars Technica]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2009, an IBM representative said that it has discontinued the development of a Cell processor with 32 SPUs&lt;ref name=&quot;HPCwire&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hpcwire.com/features/Will-Roadrunner-Be-the-Cells-Last-Hurrah-66707892.html |title=Will Roadrunner Be the Cell's Last Hurrah? |date=October 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HeiseOnline&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/SC09-IBM-laesst-Cell-Prozessor-auslaufen-864497.html |title=SC09: IBM lässt Cell-Prozessor auslaufen |date=November 20, 2009 |accessdate=November 21, 2009 |publisher=[[HeiseOnline]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but they have not halted development of other future products in the Cell family.&lt;ref name=&quot;DriverHeaven&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.driverheaven.net/news.php?newsid=344 |title=IBM have not stopped Cell processor development |date=2009-11-23 |accessdate=2009-11-24|publisher=[http://www.driverheaven.net/ DriverHeaven.net]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Commercialization===
{{update|date=November 2010}}
On May 17, 2005, Sony Computer Entertainment confirmed some specifications of the Cell processor that would be shipping in the then-forthcoming [[PlayStation 3]] console.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=David|last=Becker|url=http://news.com.com/PlayStation+3+chip+has+split+personality/2100-1043_3-5566340.html?tag=nl|title=PlayStation 3 chip has split personality|work=[[CNET]]|date=2005-02-07|accessdate=2007-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;e3witpro&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.windowsitpro.com/Articles/ArticleID/46431/46431.html?Ad=1|title=Sony Ups the Ante with PlayStation 3|first=Paul|last=Thurrott|publisher=WindowsITPro|date=2005-05-17|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;e3ign&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://gear.ign.com/articles/615/615521p1.html|title=E3 2005: Cell Processor Technology Demos|first=Chris|last=Roper|publisher=IGN|date=2005-05-17|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; This Cell configuration has one Power processing element (PPE) on the core, with eight physical [[#Synergistic Processing Elements (SPE)|SPEs]] in silicon.&lt;ref name=&quot;e3ign&quot;/&gt; In the PlayStation 3, one SPE is locked-out during the test process, a practice which helps to improve manufacturing yields, and another one is reserved for the OS, leaving 6 free SPEs to be used by games' code.&lt;ref name=&quot;GameDevelMag&quot;/&gt; The target clock-frequency at introduction is 3.2&amp;nbsp;[[GHz]].&lt;ref name=&quot;e3witpro&quot;/&gt; The introductory design is fabricated using a 90-[[nanometer]] [[Silicon on insulator|SOI]] process, with initial volume production slated for IBM's facility in [[East Fishkill, New York]].&lt;ref name=&quot;xbit-65&quot;/&gt;

Note that the relationship between [[multi-core (computing)|cores]] and [[thread (computer science)|threads]] is a common source of confusion. The PPE core is [[simultaneous multithreading|dual threaded]] and manifests in software as two independent threads of execution while each active SPE manifests as a single thread. In the PlayStation 3 configuration as described by Sony, the Cell processor provides nine independent threads of execution.

On June 28, 2005, IBM and [[Mercury Computer Systems]] announced a partnership agreement to build Cell-based computer systems for [[embedded system|embedded]] applications such as [[medical imaging]], [[industrial inspection]], [[aerospace]] and [[defense (military)|defense]], [[reflection seismology|seismic processing]], and [[telecommunications]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mcs&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.supercomputingonline.com/article.php?sid=13477|title=Mercury Wins IBM PartnerWorld Beacon Award|publisher=Supercomputing Online|date=2007-04-12|accessdate=2007-05-18 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070928223222/http://www.supercomputingonline.com/article.php?sid=13477 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mercury has since then released [[Blade server|blades]], conventional [[19-inch rack|rack servers]] and [[PCI Express]] accelerator boards with Cell processors.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcs&quot;/&gt;

In the fall of 2006, IBM released the QS20 [[blade (computing)|blade module]] using double Cell BE processors for tremendous performance in certain applications, reaching a peak of 410 [[FLOPS|gigaFLOPS]] per module. The [[QS22]] based on the PowerXCell 8i processor is used for the [[IBM Roadrunner]] supercomputer. Mercury and IBM uses the fully utilized Cell processor with 8 active SPEs. On April 8, 2008, Fixstars Corporation released a [[PCI Express]] accelerator board based on the PowerXCell 8i processor.&lt;ref name=&quot;gigaaccel180&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Fixstars Releases Accelerator Board Featuring the PowerXCell 8i | publisher=Fixstars Corporation | url=http://www.fixstars.com/en/company/press/20080403.html|date=2008-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sony's high performance media computing server [[zego|ZEGO]] uses a 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz Cell/B.E processor.

==Overview==
[[Image:Cell-Processor.jpg|200px|right|thumb|A Cell Processor]]

The '''Cell Broadband Engine'''—or ''Cell'' as it is more commonly known—is a microprocessor designed to bridge the gap between conventional desktop processors (such as the [[Athlon 64]], and [[Core 2]] families) and more specialized high-performance processors, such as the [[NVIDIA]] and [[ATI]] graphics-processors ([[Graphics processing unit|GPU]]s). The longer name indicates its intended use, namely as a component in current and future [[digital distribution]] systems; as such it may be utilized in high-definition displays and recording equipment, as well as computer entertainment systems for the [[high-definition television|HDTV]] era. Additionally the processor may be suited to [[digital imaging]] systems (medical, scientific, ''etc.'') as well as [[physical simulation]] (''e.g.'', scientific and [[structural engineering]] modeling).

In a simple analysis, the Cell processor can be split into four components: external input and output structures, the main processor called the ''Power Processing Element'' (PPE) (a two-way [[Simultaneous multithreading|simultaneous multithreaded]] [[Power Architecture#Specifications|Power ISA v.2.03]] compliant core), eight fully functional co-processors called the ''Synergistic Processing Elements'', or SPEs, and a specialized high-bandwidth [[circular data bus]] connecting the PPE, input/output elements and the SPEs, called the ''Element Interconnect Bus'' or EIB.

To achieve the high performance needed for mathematically intensive tasks, such as decoding/encoding [[MPEG]] streams, generating or transforming three-dimensional data, or undertaking [[Fourier analysis]] of data, the Cell processor marries the SPEs and the PPE via EIB to give access, via fully [[Direct memory access#Cache coherency problem|cache coherent]] [[Direct memory access|DMA (direct memory access)]], to both main memory and to other external data storage. To make the best of EIB, and to overlap computation and data transfer, each of the nine processing elements (PPE and SPEs) is equipped with a [[Direct memory access#DMA engine|DMA engine]].   Since the SPE's load/store instructions can only access its own local memory, each SPE entirely depends on DMAs to transfer data to and from the main memory and other SPEs' local memories. A DMA operation can transfer either a single block area of size up to 16KB, or a list of 2 to 2048 such blocks. One of the major design decisions in the architecture of Cell is the use of DMAs as a central means of intra-chip data transfer, with a view to enabling maximal asynchrony and concurrency in data processing inside a chip.&lt;ref name=&quot;geschwindpaper&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Chip multiprocessing and the cell broadband engine | first=Michael |last=Gschwind | publisher= ACM |
url=http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1128023 | year= 2006 | accessdate= 29 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The PPE, which is capable of running a conventional operating system, has control over the SPEs and can start, stop, interrupt, and schedule processes running on the SPEs. To this end the PPE has additional instructions relating to control of the SPEs. Unlike SPEs, the PPE can read and write the main memory and the local memories of SPEs through the standard load/store instructions.  Despite having [[Turing complete]] architectures, the SPEs are not fully autonomous and require the PPE to prime them before they can do any useful work. Though most of the &quot;horsepower&quot; of the system comes from the synergistic processing elements, the use of [[DMA]] as a method of data transfer and the limited local memory footprint of each SPE pose a major challenge to software developers who wish to make the most of this horsepower, demanding careful hand-tuning of programs to extract maximal performance from this CPU.

The PPE and bus architecture includes various modes of operation giving different levels of [[memory protection]], allowing areas of memory to be protected from access by specific processes running on the SPEs or the PPE.

Both the PPE and SPE are [[RISC]] architectures with a fixed-width 32-bit instruction format. The PPE contains a 64-bit [[general purpose register]] set (GPR), a 64-bit floating point register set (FPR), and a 128-bit [[Altivec]] register set. The SPE contains 128-bit registers only. These can be used for scalar data types ranging from 8-bits to 128-bits in size or for [[SIMD]] computations on a variety of integer and floating point formats. System memory addresses for both the PPE and SPE are expressed as 64-bit values for a theoretic address range of 2&lt;sup&gt;64&lt;/sup&gt; bytes (16 exabytes or 16,777,216 terabytes). In practice, not all of these bits are implemented in hardware. Local store addresses internal to the SPU processor are expressed as a 32-bit word. In documentation relating to Cell a word is always taken to mean 32 bits, a doubleword means 64 bits, and a quadword means 128 bits.
&lt;!-- Far from perfect but trending toward accuracy. Could not find either the virtual address range limit or the physical address range limit. Note that a &quot;system address&quot; on the SPU is an address passed to the SPU DMA controller; the LS has only 2^14 addressable locations (257K/16B) ~~~~ --&gt;

===PowerXCell 8i===
In 2008, IBM announced a revised variant of the Cell called the '''[[PowerXCell 8i]]''', which is available in QS22 [[BladeCenter|Blade Servers]] from IBM. The PowerXCell is manufactured on a [[65 nm]] process, and adds support for up to 32 GB of slotted DDR2 memory, as well as dramatically improving double-precision floating-point performance on the SPEs from a peak of about 12.8 [[GFLOPS]] to 102.4 GFLOPS total for eight SPEs, which, coincidently, is the same peak performance as the [[NEC SX-9]] vector processor released around the same time. The [[IBM Roadrunner]] supercomputer, the world's fastest 2008-2009, consists of 12,240 PowerXCell 8i processors, along with 6,562 [[AMD Opteron]] processors.&lt;ref name=&quot;beyond3dpowerxcell&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= IBM announces PowerXCell 8i, QS22 blade server | publisher= Beyond3D | url= http://www.beyond3d.com/content/news/640 |month= May | year= 2008 | accessdate= 10 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The PowerXCell 8i powered super computers also dominated the all top 6 &quot;greenest&quot; systems in the Green500 list, with highest MFLOPS/Watt ratio supercomputers in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Green 500 list, Nov 2009 &quot;&gt;{{cite web |title= The Green500 List - November 2009| url= http://www.green500.org/lists/2009/11/top/list.php}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beside the QS22 and supercomputers, the PowerXCell processor is also available as an accelerator on a PCI Express card and is used as the core processor in the [[QPACE]] project.

==Architecture==
While the Cell chip can have a number of different configurations, the basic configuration is a [[multi-core (computing)|multi-core]] chip composed of one &quot;Power Processor Element&quot; (&quot;PPE&quot;) (sometimes called &quot;Processing Element&quot;, or &quot;PE&quot;), and multiple &quot;Synergistic Processing Elements&quot; (&quot;SPE&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;cellbriefing&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Cell Microprocessor Briefing | publisher=IBM, Sony Computer Entertainment Inc., Toshiba Corp. | url=http://pc.watch.impress.co.jp/docs/2005/0208/kaigai153.htm |date= 7 February 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The PPE and SPEs are linked together by an internal high speed bus dubbed &quot;Element Interconnect Bus&quot; (&quot;EIB&quot;). Due to the nature of its applications, Cell is optimized towards [[single precision]] [[floating point]] computation. The SPEs are capable of performing [[double precision]] calculations, albeit with an order of magnitude performance penalty.  New chips expected mid-2008 are rumored to boost SPE double precision performance as high as 5x over pre-2008 designs. In the meantime, there are ways to circumvent this in software using iterative refinement, which means values are calculated in double precision only when necessary. [[Jack Dongarra]] and his team [http://www.netlib.org/lapack/lawnspdf/lawn175.pdf demonstrated] a 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz Cell with 8 SPEs delivering a performance equal to 100 GFLOPS on an average double precision [[Linpack]] 4096x4096 matrix.

===Power Processor Element (PPE)===
The ''PPE'' is the [[Power Architecture]] based, two-way [[Simultaneous multithreading|multithreaded]] core acting as the controller for the eight SPEs, which handle most of the computational workload. The PPE will work with conventional operating systems due to its similarity to other 64-bit PowerPC processors, while the SPEs are designed for vectorized floating point code execution. The PPE contains a 64 [[KiB]] level 1 [[cache]] (32 KiB instruction and a 32 KiB data) and a 512 KiB Level 2 cache. The size of a cache line is 128 bytes. Additionally, IBM has included an [[AltiVec]] unit&lt;ref name=&quot;seminar&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Power Efficient Processor Design and the Cell Processor | publisher=IBM | url=http://www.cerc.utexas.edu/vlsi-seminar/spring05/slides/2005.02.16.hph.pdf |date= 16 February 2005|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is fully pipelined for [[single precision]] floating point.  (Altivec does not support [[double precision]] floating-point vectors.)  Each PPE can complete two double precision operations per clock cycle using a scalar-fused multiply-add instruction, which translates to 6.4 [[GFLOPS]] at 3.2 GHz; or eight single precision operations per clock cycle with a vector fused-multiply-add instruction, which translates to 25.6 [[GFLOPS]] at 3.2 GHz.&lt;ref name=&quot;pacellperf&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Cell Broadband Engine Architecture and its first implementation | publisher=IBM developerWorks | url= http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/library/pa-cellperf/|date= November 29, 2005 | accessdate= 6 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- use of KiB is intentional, please do not modify --&gt;

==== Xenon in Xbox 360 ====
The PPE was designed specifically for the Cell processor but during development, [[Microsoft]] approached IBM wanting a high performance processor core for its [[Xbox 360]]. IBM complied and made the tri-core [[Xenon (processor)|Xenon processor]], based on a slightly modified version of the PPE.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gamasutra.com/view/feature/3904/processing_the_truth_an_interview_.php Processing The Truth: An Interview With David Shippy]&quot;, Leigh Alexander, ''Gamasutra'', January 16, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123069467545545011.html Playing the Fool]&quot;, Jonathan V. Last, ''Wall Street Journal'', December 30, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Synergistic Processing Elements (SPE) ===
&lt;!-- do not rename section without changing forward reference above --&gt;
Each SPE is composed of a &quot;Synergistic Processing Unit&quot;, SPU, and a &quot;Memory Flow Controller&quot;, MFC ([[Direct memory access|DMA]], [[Memory management unit|MMU]], and bus interface).&lt;ref name=&quot;ibmresearch&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=IBM Research - Cell | work=IBM | url=http://www.research.ibm.com/cell/ | accessdate=11 June 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; An SPE is a [[RISC]] processor with [[128-bit]] [[SIMD]] organization&lt;ref name=&quot;seminar&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;synergistic&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Synergistic Processing in Cell's Multicore Architecture | publisher= IEEE Micro | url= http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/cache/papers/cs2/624/http:zSzzSzwww.research.ibm.comzSzpeoplezSzmzSzmikegzSzpaperszSz2006_ieeemicro.pdf/gschwind06synergistic.pdf |month= March | year= 2006 | accessdate= 1 November 2006|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;spearch&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= A novel SIMD architecture for the Cell heterogeneous chip-multiprocessor | publisher=Hot Chips 17 | url= http://www.hotchips.org/archives/hc17/2_Mon/HC17.S1/HC17.S1T1.pdf |date= August 15, 2005 | accessdate= 1 January 2006|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; for single and double precision instructions. With the current generation of the Cell, each SPE contains a 256&amp;nbsp;[[KiB]] [[1T-SRAM|embedded SRAM]] for instruction and data, called &quot;Local Storage&quot; (not to be mistaken for &quot;Local Memory&quot; in Sony's documents that refer to the VRAM) which is visible to the PPE and can be addressed directly by software. Each SPE can support up to 4 [[GiB]] of local store memory. The local store does not operate like a conventional CPU [[cache]] since it is neither transparent to software nor does it contain hardware structures that predict which data to load. The SPEs contain a 128-bit, 128-entry [[register file]] and measures 14.5&amp;nbsp;mm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; on a 90&amp;nbsp;nm process. An SPE can operate on sixteen 8-bit integers, eight 16-bit integers, four 32-bit integers, or four single-precision floating-point numbers in a single clock cycle, as well as a memory operation. Note that the SPU cannot directly access system memory; the 64-bit virtual memory addresses formed by the SPU must be passed from the SPU to the SPE memory flow controller (MFC) to set up a DMA operation within the system address space.
&lt;!-- Far from perfect but trending toward accuracy. Could not find either the virtual address range limit or the physical address range limit. Note that a &quot;system address&quot; on the SPU is an address passed to the SPU DMA controller; the LS has only 2^14 addressable locations (256K/16B) ~~~~ --&gt;

In one typical usage scenario, the system will load the SPEs with small programs (similar to [[thread (computer science)|threads]]), chaining the SPEs together to handle each step in a complex operation. For instance, a [[set-top box]] might load programs for reading a DVD, video and audio decoding, and display, and the data would be passed off from SPE to SPE until finally ending up on the TV. Another possibility is to partition the input data set and have several SPEs performing the same kind of operation in parallel. At 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz, each SPE gives a theoretical 25.6 [[GFLOPS]] of single precision performance.

Compared to a modern [[personal computer]], the relatively high overall floating point performance of a Cell processor seemingly dwarfs the abilities of the SIMD unit in desktop CPUs like the [[Pentium 4]] and the [[Athlon 64]]. However, comparing only floating point abilities of a system is a one-dimensional and application-specific metric. Unlike a Cell processor, such desktop CPUs are more suited to the general purpose software usually run on personal computers. In addition to executing multiple instructions per clock, processors from Intel and AMD feature [[branch predictor]]s. The Cell is designed to compensate for this with compiler assistance, in which prepare-to-branch instructions are created. For double-precision floating point operations, as sometimes used in personal computers and often used in scientific computing, Cell performance drops by an order of magnitude, but still reaches 20.8 GFLOPS (1.8 GFLOPS per SPE, 6.4 GFLOPS per PPE). The PowerXCell 8i variant, which was specifically designed for double-precision, reaches 102.4 GFLOPS in double-precision calculations.&lt;ref name=&quot;ppcnuxpowerxcell&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title= Cell successor with turbo mode - PowerXCell 8i | publisher= PPCNux | url= http://www.ppcnux.com/?q=node/7144 |month= November | year= 2007 | accessdate= 10 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent tests by IBM show that the SPEs can reach 98% of their theoretical peak performance using optimized parallel Matrix Multiplication.&lt;ref name=&quot;pacellperf&quot;/&gt;

[[Toshiba]] has developed a [[co-processor]] powered by four SPEs, but no PPE, called the [[SpursEngine]] designed to accelerate 3D and movie effects in consumer electronics.

===Element Interconnect Bus (EIB)===
The EIB is a communication bus internal to the Cell processor which connects the various on-chip system elements: the PPE processor, the memory controller (MIC), the eight SPE coprocessors, and two off-chip I/O interfaces, for a total of 12 participants in the PS3 (the number of SPU can vary in industrial applications). The EIB also includes an arbitration unit which functions as a set of traffic lights. In some documents IBM refers to EIB bus participants as 'units'.

The EIB is presently implemented as a circular ring consisting of four 16B-wide unidirectional channels which counter-rotate in pairs. When traffic patterns permit, each channel can convey up to three transactions concurrently. As the EIB runs at half the system clock rate the effective channel rate is 16 bytes every two system clocks. At maximum [[concurrency]], with three active transactions on each of the four rings, the peak ''instantaneous'' EIB bandwidth is 96B per clock (12 concurrent transactions * 16 bytes wide / 2 system clocks per transfer). While this figure is often quoted in IBM literature it is unrealistic to simply scale this number by processor clock speed. The arbitration unit imposes additional constraints which are discussed in the '''Bandwidth Assessment''' section below.

IBM Senior Engineer [[David Krolak]], EIB lead designer, explains the concurrency model:

:''A ring can start a new op every three cycles. Each transfer always takes eight beats. That was one of the simplifications we made, it's optimized for streaming a lot of data. If you do small ops, it does not work quite as well. If you think of eight-car trains running around this track, as long as the trains aren't running into each other, they can coexist on the track.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolak&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/library/pa-expert9/|title=Meet the experts: David Krolak on the Cell Broadband Engine EIB bus|publisher=IBM|date=2005-12-06|accessdate=2007-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each participant on the EIB has one 16B read port and one 16B write port. The limit for a single participant is to read and write at a rate of 16B per EIB clock (for simplicity often regarded 8B per system clock). Note that each SPU processor contains a dedicated [[Direct memory access|DMA]] management queue capable of scheduling long sequences of transactions to various endpoints without interfering with the SPU's ongoing computations; these DMA queues can be managed locally or remotely as well, providing additional flexibility in the control model.

Data flows on an EIB channel stepwise around the ring. Since there are twelve participants, the total number of steps around the channel back to the point of origin is twelve. Six steps is the longest distance between any pair of participants. An EIB channel is not permitted to convey data requiring more than six steps; such data must take the shorter route around the circle in the other direction. The number of steps involved in sending the packet has very little impact on transfer latency: the clock speed driving the steps is very fast relative to other considerations. However, longer communication distances '''''are''''' detrimental to the overall performance of the EIB as they reduce available concurrency. &lt;!-- thinking about the Krolak interview, I have no justification for using the term hops, they could be opening the circuit end to end for the transaction; still, it seems more likely that it functions in hops and I do not feel like rewriting this passage right now; changed to steps and stepwise after seeing a comment by HappyVR using this term instead ~~~~ --&gt;

Despite IBM's original desire to implement the EIB as a more powerful cross-bar, the circular configuration they adopted to spare resources rarely represents a limiting factor on the performance of the Cell chip as a whole. In the worst case, the programmer must take extra care to schedule communication patterns where the EIB is able to function at high concurrency levels.

David Krolak explains:
:''Well, in the beginning, early in the development process, several people were pushing for a crossbar switch, and the way the bus is designed, you could actually pull out the EIB and put in a crossbar switch if you were willing to devote more silicon space on the chip to wiring. We had to find a balance between connectivity and area, and there just was not enough room to put a full crossbar switch in. So we came up with this ring structure which we think is very interesting. It fits within the area constraints and still has very impressive bandwidth.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Krolak&quot;/&gt;

====Bandwidth assessment====
For the sake of quoting performance numbers, we will assume a Cell processor running at 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz, the clock speed most often cited.

At this clock frequency each channel flows at a rate of 25.6&amp;nbsp;GB/s. Viewing the EIB in isolation from the system elements it connects, achieving twelve concurrent transactions at this flow rate works out to an abstract EIB bandwidth of 307.2&amp;nbsp;GB/s. Based on this view many IBM publications depict available EIB bandwidth as &quot;greater than 300&amp;nbsp;GB/s&quot;. This number reflects the peak ''instantaneous'' EIB bandwidth scaled by processor frequency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hpc.pnl.gov/people/fabrizio/papers/ieeemicro-cell.pdf|title=Cell Multiprocessor Communication Network: Built for Speed|publisher=IEEE|accessdate=2007-03-22|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, other technical restrictions are involved in the arbitration mechanism for packets accepted onto the bus. The IBM Systems Performance group explains:

:''Each unit on the EIB can simultaneously send and receive 16B of data every bus cycle. The maximum data bandwidth of the entire EIB is limited by the maximum rate at which addresses are snooped across all units in the system, which is one per bus cycle. Since each snooped address request can potentially transfer up to 128B, the theoretical peak data bandwidth on the EIB at 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz is 128Bx1.6&amp;nbsp;GHz = 204.8&amp;nbsp;GB/s.''&lt;ref name=&quot;pacellperf&quot;/&gt;

This quote apparently represents the full extent of IBM's public disclosure of this mechanism and its impact. The EIB arbitration unit, the snooping mechanism, and interrupt generation on segment or page translation faults are not well described in the documentation set as yet made public by IBM.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}

In practice effective EIB bandwidth can also be limited by the ring participants involved. While each of the nine processing cores can sustain 25.6&amp;nbsp;GB/s read and write concurrently, the memory interface controller (MIC) is tied to a pair of XDR memory channels permitting a maximum flow of 25.6&amp;nbsp;GB/s for reads and writes '''combined''' and the two IO controllers are documented as supporting a peak combined input speed of 25.6&amp;nbsp;GB/s and a peak combined output speed of 35&amp;nbsp;GB/s.

To add further to the confusion, some older publications cite EIB bandwidth assuming a 4&amp;nbsp;GHz system clock. This reference frame results in an instantaneous EIB bandwidth figure of 384&amp;nbsp;GB/s and an arbitration-limited bandwidth figure of 256&amp;nbsp;GB/s.

All things considered the theoretic 204.8&amp;nbsp;GB/s number most often cited is the best one to bear in mind. The ''IBM Systems Performance'' group has demonstrated SPU-centric data flows achieving 197&amp;nbsp;GB/s on a Cell processor running at 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz so this number is a fair reflection on practice as well.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/library/pa-cellperf/&lt;/ref&gt;

====Optical interconnect====
Sony is currently working on the development of an optical interconnection technology for use in the device-to-device or internal interface of various types of cell-based digital consumer electronics and game systems.

=== Memory and I/O Controllers ===

Cell contains a dual channel [[Rambus]] XIO macro which interfaces to Rambus [[XDR DRAM|XDR memory]]. The memory interface controller (MIC) is separate from the XIO macro and is designed by IBM. The XIO-XDR link runs at 3.2&amp;nbsp;Gbit/s per pin. Two 32-bit channels can provide a theoretical maximum of 25.6&amp;nbsp;GB/s.

The I/O interface, also a Rambus design, is known as [[FlexIO]]. The FlexIO interface is organized into 12 lanes, each lane being a unidirectional 8-bit wide point-to-point path. Five 8-bit wide point-to-point paths are inbound lanes to Cell, while the remaining seven are outbound. This provides a theoretical peak bandwidth of 62.4&amp;nbsp;GB/s (36.4&amp;nbsp;GB/s outbound, 26&amp;nbsp;GB/s inbound) at 2.6&amp;nbsp;GHz. The FlexIO interface can be clocked independently, typ. at 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz. 4 inbound + 4 outbound lanes are supporting memory coherency.

==Possible applications==
{{main|Cell microprocessor implementations}}

===Video processing card===
Some companies, such as [[Leadtek]], have released [[PCI-E]] cards based upon the Cell to allow for &quot;faster than real time&quot; transcoding of [[H.264]], [[MPEG-2]] and [[MPEG-4]] video.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Leadtek PxVC1100 MPEG-2/H.264 Transcoding Card  | url=http://www.legitreviews.com/article/1134/1/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Blade server===
On 29 August 2007, IBM announced the [[BladeCenter]] QS21. Generating a measured 1.05 giga–floating point operations per second (gigaFLOPS) per watt, with peak performance of approximately 460 GFLOPS it is one of the most power efficient computing platforms to date. A single BladeCenter chassis can achieve 6.4 tera–floating point operations per second (teraFLOPS) and over 25.8 teraFLOPS in a standard 42U rack.

[http://www.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/22258.wss IBM Press Release]

On 13 May 2008, IBM announced the [[BladeCenter]] QS22. The QS22 introduces the PowerXCell 8i processor with five times the double-precision floating point performance of the QS21, and the capacity for up to 32 GB of DDR2 memory on-blade.

[http://www.ibm.com/press/us/en/pressrelease/24180.wss IBM Press Release]

===PCI Express Board===

Several companies provide PCI-e boards utilising the IBM PowerXCell 8i. The performance is reported as 179.2 GFlops (SP), 89.6 GFlops (DP) at 2.8&amp;nbsp;GHz.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fixstars.com/en/company/press/20080403.html| title=Fixstars Press Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.linuxdevices.com/news/NS6832279023.html|title=Cell-based coprocessor card runs Linux}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Console video games===
[[Sony]]'s [[PlayStation 3]] [[video game console]] contains the first production application of the Cell processor, clocked at 3.2&amp;nbsp;[[GHz]] and containing seven out of eight operational SPEs, to allow Sony to increase the [[Fabrication (semiconductor)#Device test|yield]] on the processor manufacture. Only six of the seven SPEs are accessible to developers as one is reserved by the OS.&lt;ref name=&quot;GameDevelMag&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Optimizing Cell Core | author=Martin Linklater | work=Game Developer Magazine, April 2007 | pages=15–18  | quote=To increase fabrication yields, Sony ships PlayStation 3 Cell processors with only seven working SPEs. And from those seven, one SPE will be used by the operating system for various tasks, This leaves six SPEs and 1 PPE for game programmers to use.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home cinema===
Toshiba has produced [[High-definition television|HDTVs]] using Cell. They have already presented a system to decode 48 [[Standard-definition television|standard definition]] [[MPEG-2]] streams simultaneously on a [[1080i|1920×1080]] screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;techon&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Toshiba Demonstrates Cell Microprocessor Simultaneously Decoding 48 MPEG-2 Streams | publisher=Tech-On! | url=http://techon.nikkeibp.co.jp/english/NEWS_EN/20050425/104149/?ST=english |date= April 25, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IEEE_Spectrum&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title= Winner: Multimedia Monster | publisher = IEEE Spectrum | url=http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/jan06/2609| date = 1 January 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can enable a viewer to choose a channel based on dozens of thumbnail videos displayed simultaneously on the screen.

===Supercomputing===
IBM's latest supercomputer, [[IBM Roadrunner]], is a hybrid of General Purpose CISC Opteron as well as Cell processors. This system assumed the #1 spot on the June 2008 Top 500 list  as the first supercomputer to run at [[FLOPS|petaFLOPS]] speeds, having gained a sustained 1.026 petaFLOPS speed using the standard [[Linpack]] benchmark. IBM Roadrunner uses the PowerXCell 8i version of the Cell processor, manufactured using 65&amp;nbsp;nm technology and enhanced SPUs that can handle double precision calculations in the 128-bit registers, reaching double precision 102 GFLOPs per chip.&lt;ref name=&quot;roadrunner&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Beyond a Single Cell | url=http://www.cs.utk.edu/~dongarra/cell2006/cell-slides/04-Ken-Koch.pdf | publisher=Los Alamos National Laboratory | accessdate=October 25, 2006|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cellscientific&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=The Potential of the Cell Processor for Scientific Computing | url=http://repositories.cdlib.org/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4262&amp;context=lbnl | publisher= ACM Computing Frontiers |accessdate=October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cluster computing===
Clusters of [[PlayStation 3]] consoles are an attractive alternative to high-end systems based on Cell blades. Innovative Computing Laboratory, a group led by [[Jack Dongarra]], in the Computer Science Department at the University of Tennessee, investigated such an application in depth.&lt;ref name=&quot;scop3&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=SCOP3: A Rough Guide to Scientific Computing On the PlayStation 3 | url=http://www.netlib.org/netlib/utk/people/JackDongarra/PAPERS/scop3.pdf | publisher=Computer Science Department, University of Tennessee | accessdate=May 8, 2007|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Terrasoft Solutions is selling 8-node and 32-node PS3 clusters with [[Yellow Dog Linux]] pre-installed, an implementation of Dongarra's research.

As first reported by Wired Magazine on October 17, 2007,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Astrophysicist Replaces Supercomputer with Eight PlayStation 3s|url=http://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/news/2007/10/ps3_supercomputer/ |publisher=Wired Magazine |accessdate=2007-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; an interesting application of using PlayStation 3 in a cluster configuration was implemented by Astrophysicist Dr. [[Gaurav Khanna]], from the Physics department of [[University of Massachusetts Dartmouth]], who replaced time used on supercomputers with a cluster of eight PlayStation 3s.  Subsequently, the next generation of this machine, now called the ''[[PlayStation 3]] Gravity Grid'', uses a network of 16 machines, and exploits the Cell processor for the intended application which is binary [[black hole]] coalescence using [[perturbation theory]]. In particular, the cluster performs astrophysical simulations of large [[supermassive black holes]] capturing smaller compact objects and has generated numerical data that has been published multiple times in the relevant scientific research literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://gravity.phy.umassd.edu/ps3.html | title= PS3 Gravity Grid | publisher = Gaurav Khanna, Associate Professor, College of Engineering, University of Massachusetts Dartmouth | accessdate =}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Cell processor version used by the PlayStation 3 has a main CPU and 6 floating-point vector processors, giving the Gravity Grid machine a net of 16 general-purpose processors and 96 vector processors.  The machine has a one-time cost of over $9,000 to build and is adequate for black-hole simulations which would otherwise cost $6,000 per run on a conventional supercomputer.  The black hole calculations are not memory-intensive and are highly localizable, and so are well-suited to this architecture. Khanna claims that the cluster's performance exceeds that of a 100+ Intel Xeon core based traditional Linux cluster on his simulations. The PS3 Gravity Grid gathered significant media attention through 2007,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9043942/PS3_cluster_creates_homemade_cheaper_supercomputer | title= PS3 cluster creates homemade, cheaper supercomputer }}&lt;/ref&gt; 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/science-news/3325757/Why-scientists-love-games-consoles.html | title= Why scientists love games consoles | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Roger | last=Highfield | date=2008-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/12/22/AR2008122201980.html | title= Nothing Escapes the Pull of a PlayStation 3, Not Even a Black Hole | work=The Washington Post | first=Matt | last=Peckham | date=2008-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; 2009 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.space.com/businesstechnology/090128-playstation3-blackholes.html | title= Playstation 3 Consoles Tackle Black Hole Vibrations}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=100969805 | title= Playstation 3: A Discount Supercomputer?}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://spectrum.ieee.org/computing/hardware/the-supercomputer-goes-personal | title= The Supercomputer Goes Personal}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-11168150 | title= The PlayStation powered super-computer | work=BBC News | date=2010-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://blogs.forbes.com/johnfarrell/2010/11/12/black-holes-and-quantum-loops-more-than-just-a-game/ | title= Black Holes and Quantum Loops: More Than Just a Game | work=Forbes | first=John | last=Farrell}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The computational Biochemistry and Biophysics lab at the [[Universitat Pompeu Fabra]], in [[Barcelona]], deployed in 2007 a [[BOINC]] system called [[GPUGRID.net | PS3GRID]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=PS3GRID.net | url=http://www.ps3grid.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; for collaborative computing based on the CellMD software, the first one designed specifically for the Cell processor.

The United States [[Air Force Research Laboratory]] has announced plans to deploy a PlayStation 3 cluster of 1760 units, nicknamed the &quot;Condor Cluster&quot;, for analyzing [[high-resolution]] [[satellite imagery]]. The Air Force claims the Condor Cluster would be the 33rd largest supercomputer in the world in terms of capacity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Defense Department discusses new Sony PlayStation supercomputer | url=http://blog.cleveland.com/metro/2010/11/defense_department_discusses_n.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Distributed computing===
With the help of the computing power of over half a million PlayStation 3 consoles, the distributed computing project [[Folding@Home]] has been recognized by [[Guinness World Records]] as the most powerful distributed network in the world. The first record was achieved on September 16, 2007, as the project surpassed one [[FLOPS|petaFLOPS]], which had never been reached before by a distributed computing network. Additionally, the collective efforts enabled PS3 alone to reach the petaFLOPS mark on September 23, 2007. In comparison, the world's second most powerful supercomputer at the time, IBM's [[BlueGene/L]], performed at around 478.2 teraFLOPS. This means Folding@Home's computing power is approximately twice BlueGene/L's (although the CPU interconnect in BlueGene/L is more than one million times faster than the mean network speed in Folding@Home.). As of May 7th 2011, Folding@home runs at about 9.3 x86 petaFLOPS, with 1.6 petaFLOPS generated by 26,000 active PS3s alone. In late 2008, A cluster of 200 PlayStation 3 consoles was used to generate a rogue [[Transport Layer Security|SSL]] certificate, effectively cracking its encryption.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.engadget.com/2008/12/30/hackers-playstation-3-make-ssl-much-less-secure/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mainframes===
IBM announced April 25, 2007 that it will begin integrating its Cell Broadband Engine Architecture microprocessors into the company's line of [[IBM System z|mainframes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1895,2122352,00.asp?kc=EWEWKEMLP042807BOE1|title=IBM Mainframes Go 3-D|publisher=[[eWeek]]|date=2007-04-26|accessdate=2007-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Password cracking===
The architecture of the processor makes it better suited to hardware-assisted cryptographic [[brute force attack]] applications than conventional processors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/7118997.stm|title=PlayStation speeds password probe |date=2007-11-30|accessdate=2011-01-17|publisher=[[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Software engineering==
{{Main|Cell software development}}

Due to the flexible nature of the Cell, there are several possibilities for the utilization of its resources, not limited to just different computing paradigms:&lt;ref name=&quot;scei&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=CELL: A New Platform for Digital Entertainment | publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment Inc. | url=http://www.research.scea.com/research/html/CellGDC05/ |date= March 9, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Job queue===
The PPE maintains a job queue, schedules jobs in SPEs, and monitors progress. Each SPE runs a &quot;mini kernel&quot; whose role is to fetch a job, execute it, and synchronize with the PPE.

===Self-multitasking of SPEs===
The kernel and scheduling is distributed across the SPEs. Tasks are synchronized using [[Mutual exclusion|mutexes]] or [[Semaphore (programming)|semaphores]] as in a conventional [[operating system]]. Ready-to-run tasks wait in a queue for an SPE to execute them. The SPEs use shared memory for all tasks in this configuration.

===Stream processing===
Each SPE runs a distinct program. Data comes from an input stream, and is sent to SPEs. When an SPE has terminated the processing, the output data is sent to an output stream.

This provides a flexible and powerful architecture for [[stream processing]], and allows explicit scheduling for each SPE separately. Other processors are also able to perform streaming tasks, but are limited by the kernel loaded.

===Open source software development===
An open source software-based strategy was adopted to accelerate the development of a Cell BE ecosystem and to provide an environment to develop Cell applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.research.ibm.com/people/m/mikeg/papers/2007_ieeecomputer.pdf|title=An Open Source Environment for Cell Broadband Engine System Software|date=June 2007|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2005, patches enabling Cell support in the Linux kernel were submitted for inclusion by IBM developers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Arnd|last=Bergmann|url=http://lkml.org/lkml/2005/6/21/390|title=ppc64: Introduce Cell/BPA platform, v3|date=2005-06-21|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arnd Bergmann (one of the developers of the aforementioned patches) also described the Linux-based Cell architecture at [[LinuxTag]] 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;linuxtag&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=The Cell Processor Programming Model | work=LinuxTag 2005 |
url=http://www.linuxtag.org/typo3site/freecongress-details.html?talkid=156 | accessdate=11 June 2005 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20051118073736/http://www.linuxtag.org/typo3site/freecongress-details.html?talkid=156 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 18 November 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both PPE and SPEs are programmable in C/C++ using a common API provided by libraries.

[[Fixstars Solutions]] provides [[Yellow Dog Linux]] for IBM, and Mercury Cell-based systems, as well as for the PlayStation 3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://us.fixstars.com/news/2006/2006-10-17.shtml|title= Terra Soft to Provide Linux for PLAYSTATION3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Terra Soft strategically partnered with Mercury to provide a Linux Board Support Package for Cell, and support and development of software applications on various other Cell platforms, including the IBM BladeCenter JS21 and Cell QS20, and Mercury Cell-based solutions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.terrasoftsolutions.com/products/mercury/intro.shtml Terra Soft - Linux for Cell, PlayStation PS3, QS20, QS21, QS22, IBM System p, Mercury Cell, and Apple PowerPC&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Terra Soft also maintains the Y-HPC (High Performance Computing) Cluster Construction and Management Suite and Y-Bio gene sequencing tools. Y-Bio is built upon the RPM Linux standard for package management, and offers tools which help bioinformatics researchers conduct their work with greater efficiency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= Y-Bio | url=http://www.terrasoftsolutions.com/products/y-bio/programs.shtml|date=2007-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; IBM has developed a pseudo-filesystem for Linux coined &quot;Spufs&quot; that simplifies access to and use of the SPE resources. IBM is currently maintaining a Linux [[kernel (computer science)|kernel]] and [[GDB]] ports, while Sony maintains the [[GNU toolchain]] ([[GNU Compiler Collection|GCC]], [[GNU Binutils|binutils]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Arnd Bergmann on Cell | publisher=IBM developerWorks | url=http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/library/pa-expert4/|date=2005-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2005, IBM released a &quot;Cell Broadband Engine (CBE) Software Development Kit Version 1.0&quot;, consisting of a simulator and assorted tools, to its web site. Development versions of the latest kernel and tools for [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora Core]] 4 are maintained at the [[Barcelona Supercomputing Center]] website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bsc.es/projects/deepcomputing/linuxoncell/|title=Linux on Cell BE-based Systems|publisher=Barcelona Supercomputing Center|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2007, Mercury Computer Systems released a Software Development Kit for PLAYSTATION(R)3 for High-Performance Computing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Mercury Computer Systems Releases Software Development Kit for PLAYSTATION(R)3 for High-Performance Computing | publisher=PRNewswire-FirstCall | url=http://www.mc.com/mediacenter/pressrelease.aspx?id=10454|date=2007-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2007, Fixstars Corporation released the new &quot;CVCell&quot; module aiming to accelerate several important [[OpenCV]] APIs for Cell. In a series of software calculation tests, they recorded execution times on a 3.2&amp;nbsp;GHz Cell processor that were between 6x and 27x faster compared with the same software on a 2.4&amp;nbsp;GHz Intel Core 2 Duo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=&quot;CVCell&quot; - Module developed by Fixstars that accelerates OpenCV Library for the Cell/B.E. processor | publisher=Fixstars Corporation | url=http://www.fixstars.com/en/company/press/20071128.html|date=2007-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the release of kernel version 2.6.16 on March 20, 2006, the Linux kernel officially supports the Cell processor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.com.com/2100-7344_3-6052314.html|title=Linux gets built-in Cell processor support|first=Stephen|last=Shankland|publisher=CNET|date=2006-03-21|accessdate=2007-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Sony Toshiba IBM Center of Competence for the Cell Processor|STI Center of Competence for the Cell Processor]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/cell/ Cell Broadband Engine resource center]
*[http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/cell/docs_documentation.html Standards and documentation]
*[http://cell.scei.co.jp/ Sony Computer Entertainment Incorporated's Cell resource page]
*[http://www.cmpware.com/Docs/ProductBrief_3.0_CellBE.pdf Cmpware Configurable Multiprocessor Development Kit for Cell BE]
*[http://www.realworldtech.com/page.cfm?ArticleID=RWT021005084318 ISSCC 2005: The CELL Microprocessor, a comprehensive overview of the CELL microarchitecture]
*[http://members.forbes.com/forbes/2006/0130/076.html Holy Chip!]
*[http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/power/library/pa-tacklecell5/index.html The little broadband engine that could]
*[http://arstechnica.com/articles/paedia/cpu/cell-1.ars Introducing the IBM/Sony/Toshiba Cell Processor — Part I: the SIMD processing units]
*[http://arstechnica.com/articles/paedia/cpu/cell-2.ars Introducing the IBM/Sony/Toshiba Cell Processor -- Part II: The Cell Architecture]
*[http://www.gamezero.com/team-0/articles/interviews/dr_h_peter_hofstee/ The Soul of Cell:  An interview with Dr. H. Peter Hofstee]

{{IBM}}
{{Toshiba}}
{{PlayStation 3}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Cell (Microprocessor)}}
[[Category:PowerPC microprocessors]]
[[Category:IBM microprocessors]]
[[Category:Cell BE architecture]]

[[bs:Cell mikroprocesor]]
[[ca:Cell]]
[[de:Cell (Prozessor)]]
[[es:Cell]]
[[eo:Cell]]
[[fr:Cell (processeur)]]
[[ko:셀 (마이크로프로세서)]]
[[it:Cell (processore)]]
[[nl:Cell (processor)]]
[[ja:Cell Broadband Engine]]
[[no:Cell]]
[[pl:Cell (procesor)]]
[[pt:Cell (microprocessador)]]
[[ro:Cell (procesor)]]
[[ru:Cell]]
[[sk:Cell (mikroprocesor)]]
[[fi:Cell (suoritin)]]
[[sv:Cell (processor)]]
[[zh:Cell]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
