<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8050128" ns="0" title="BBC Two &#039;1991-2001&#039; idents"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Dablink|This article is about the set of idents used on [[BBC Two]] between 1991 and 2001. For more of the channel's identity before and after this timescale, see the channel's section within the [[History of BBC television idents]].}}
{{refimprove|date=September 2009}}
[[File:BBC Two Paint ident.jpg|thumb|right|''Paint'', the first and last of this series to be broadcast.]] 

'''''BBC Two '1991-2001' idents''''' were broadcast from 16 February 1991 until 19 November 2001 on [[BBC Two]]. The idents were created by branding agency [[Lambie-Nairn]], who also created the [[Channel 4]] logo still used to this day. The idents consist of a [[sans-serif]] '2', enlarged in the middle on-screen, accompanied by the colour veridian and synthesized bell music.&lt;ref name=&quot;www2.tv-ark.org.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.tv-ark.org.uk/bbctwo/1991_idents.html |title=BBC Two &amp;#124; 1991 Idents |publisher=TVARK |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally created to restore the public's perception of BBC2, they have become one of the most popular television idents in history, with [[fan mail]] received and its [[cult status]]. {{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}

The ident package was retained following the corporate rebrand of the [[BBC]] in [[Logo of the BBC#1997|1997]] with a new logo and new idents commissioned.

==Conception==
The newly recruited [[BBC Two|BBC2]] controller, [[Alan Yentob]], noticed that the then logo for the channel, which featured 'TWO' in red, green and blue within a white background and the 'O' being white, was affecting the reputation of BBC2. Surveys commissioned realised that most viewers thought the new look &quot;dull&quot; and &quot;worthy&quot;. He then decided to commission a worthy successor capable of displaying the personality of the channel, revealing his thoughts in the ''How did they do it?'' episode - about the idents.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.tv-ark.org.uk/bbctwo/1991_idents.html |title=BBC Two &amp;#124; 1991 Idents |publisher=TVARK |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box |width=75em | bgcolor=#c6dbf7 |align=center |quote=&quot;I realized there was a problem almost as soon as I took over the channel [BBC2]. It was obvious that the logo [TWO] made absolutely no impact. In fact, it was something anyone could have told you. It was singularly unmemorable, and told you nothing about the personality of the channel. So we decided to commission a corporate design company to do some research.&quot;|salign=right |source=Alan Yentob&lt;ref name=&quot;HDTDT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=tvlivevideo |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GbpITaGT4-8 |title=BBC2 1991-2001 Idents / How Do They Do That? |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The idents were designed by branding expert [[Martin Lambie-Nairn]], and first aired on the same day as the [[BBC One|BBC1]] virtual [[globe]] [[ident]], also designed by Lambie-Nairn as part of a corporate rebrand of both channels. 

{{quote box |width=75em | bgcolor=#c6dbf7 |align=center |quote=&quot;We took this '2', actually, and you think to yourself &quot;Well, there's nothing special about this&quot;. But there is something special about this, actually. It's a very distinctive '2'. It's very sharp bits on it and it's rather nice and fat. The reason we wanted that particular '2' is because we wanted to do things with it. So, you need lots of '2', lots of body on the '2' in order to achieve that.&quot;|salign=right |source=Martin Lambie-Nairn&lt;ref name=&quot;HDTDT&quot;/&gt;}}

==Idents==
The idents featured a [[sans-serif]] '2' in a variety of different forms and environments accompanied by an element of the colour viridian and accompanied by a static [[Logo of the BBC#1986|corporate logo]] DOG below the '2'. Another DOG often used with the look was a small '888' legend in the top right of the screen. This meant that subtitles were available to accompany the programme on [[Ceefax]] page 888. Following the 1997 rebrand, the BBC logo was changed, with the word TWO added after the logo at the bottom of the screen. The '888' legend was also phased out, to be replaced with 'Subtitles' following the uptake in digital television and the increased use of the new [[BBC Red Button|BBC Text service]]. The new idents commissioned after 1997 also placed less emphasis on the use of Viridian and the bell music. Later on, as the [[Internet]] also began to increasingly grow, the URL of BBC's website (www.bbc.co.uk) was included in idents on-screen in middle of June 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lambie-nairn.com/page.asp?partid=143 |title=Our Work Archive |publisher=Lambie-Nairn.com |accessdate=2007-09-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070928165047/http://www.lambie-nairn.com/page.asp?partid=143 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Regular===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; &quot;
! style=&quot;width:50%; background:#1f777b;&quot;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white&quot;&gt;Title&lt;/span&gt;
! style=&quot;width:50%; background:#1f777b;&quot;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white&quot;&gt;Air dates&lt;/span&gt;
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Paint'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|

&lt;div align=&quot;justified&quot;&gt;''Paint'' featured a white polystyrene '2' on a black &amp; white background, splashed by a blob of [[viridian]] paint which hurtles in horizontally from the right side of the screen. In this ident's soundtrack, the paint is heralded by a steady cymbal crash as it comes into view, reaching a peak upon contact with the '2', followed a two-note resonant sound, symbolic of the dripping paint. This illusion was created by moving the '2' and the camera onto its side by 90 degrees anti-clockwise, to make it appear as though the paint was falling sideways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=alwardemshire |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vzLkk5pyr3w&amp;feature=related |title=How did they did the BBC2 1991-2001 Idents 1 |publisher=Youtube.com |date=1991-04-20 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first showing of this ident as well as the first showing of the whole run, coincidentally or not, did not feature the [[Digital On-screen Graphic|DOG]] as it would later show the 1987 and later on the 1997 corporate logo, subtitles indicator (originally 888 then later on &quot;Subtitles&quot;) etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;  It was both the first and last in this series of idents to be broadcast.

Edited in October 1997.&lt;/div&gt;
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Water'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|

&lt;div align=&quot;justified&quot;&gt;This ident featured an [[Aqua (color)|aqua]]-coloured '2' on a background of the same colour, half submerged in a pool of [[water]] at a 45 degree angle.
Using a similar method to ''Paint'', the '2' and camera are both at 45 degrees, giving the impression of the water flowing diagonally when the shot of the '2' is upright. Wind instruments and reverberated ethnic percussion featured in the audio, enhancing the atmosphere. One of the four original idents to be shown throughout the run of the whole series.&lt;/div&gt;

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Blade'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
One of the four idents to last the entire run, ''Blade'' featured a sharp, metal '2' falling into a [[viridian]]-coloured block and impaling it on its edge, standing and wobbling. Audio is a short, sharp cymbal crash with slow attack, subtly changing tone and fading out as the '2' has pierced the block.

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Neon'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
Also known as ''Sign'', it had a '2' on a black background with seven viridian [[neon]] lights attached to it, flashing in random sequences. The soundtrack matched the timing of the lights as they flashed on and off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=alwardemshire |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vzLkk5pyr3w&amp;feature=related |title=How did they did the BBC2 1991-2001 Idents 2 |publisher=Youtube.com |date=1991-04-20 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was one of the four original idents to be shown throughout the entire run.

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Copper Cut-Out'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 31 December 1999&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
As the title suggests, it featured a [[copper]] cut-out of a '2' off of which sparks flew, as the figure glowed at its edges. This was punctuated with a loud, distinctive metallic clang sound in the audio, which overlaid a gentle, major chord pad.

Edited in October 1997 but was withdrawn at the end of 1999 along with ''Silk'', ''Firecracker'', ''Diary'' and ''Steam''.
|-
| center; width: 300px;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Glass'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - December 1993 (Northern Ireland and North West in 3 October 1997)&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
Featured a [[glass]]-cut '2', which reflected light&amp;nbsp;— with some noticeable viridian colour&amp;nbsp;— in various directions. Soundtrack consists of a resonant bell-like chime, between lighter bells paired with breathy sounds, giving a relaxing feel. It was one of the first to be taken out of service, along with ''Paper Cut-Out'' but was played by accident once in the North West in about 1996/1997. However, this ident continued in Northern Ireland until the 1997 revamp.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Silk'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 31 December 1999&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
This ident included a swathe of [[viridian]] [[silk]] literally drifting over the top of a '2' shape, as if they were [[ocean]] waves. Haunting wails and loud bell tolls to form a dramatic soundtrack, conjuring up imagery of the '2' as a sinking ship. The jingle used in ''Neon'' is also heard in the audio. This was known to be a nightmare-inducing ident back in the day, especially with children.

Edited in October 1997 but was dropped from the line-up at the end of 1999 along with four other idents.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Paper Cut-Out'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - December 1993&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
''Paper Cut-Out'' featured a completely grey, [[paper]]-like foreground, with a '2'-shaped cut-out in the middle. The background behind it featured a colourful blue sky, with white clouds. The audio track is very minimal, with faint drums and a high-pitched, tweeting melody, heavy on repetition. Along with ''Glass'' it was withdrawn in 1993.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Black &amp; White Copper Cut-Out'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 3 October 1997&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
This ident was the black-&amp;-white equivalent of the original ''Copper Cut Out'' with viridian sparks flying off the '2'. Withdrawn from the line-up in 1997, when the BBC corporate logo was revamped.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Shadow'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 3 October 1997&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
A simple ident, showing the cast shadow of a slowly rotating '2' on a viridian wall. The soundtrack shares some note similarities with ''Paint'' and ''Glass'', albeit is not as minimal, with hints of percussion and greater variety and prominence in the chords. Withdrawn from the line-up in 1997, when the BBC corporate logo was revamped.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Water Reflection'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 3 October 1997&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
A subtle variation on ''Water'', the light was altered in such a way that it cast a reflection of the water line onto the top half of the '2'. It also had the same audio as ''Water''. This was also withdrawn before the 1997 corporate logo revamp along with four other idents.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Garden'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;16 February 1991 - 1 March 1991, January 1994 - October 1997, June 2001 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
''Garden'' depicted a circular patch of grass in the middle, from which sprouted several white flowers that formed the shape of the '2'. Introduced as a one-off ident in 1991 for a series of gardening programmes, it was launched as a regular ident two years later, albeit with different music. The soundtrack originally had the remix of ''Water'' but had its own soundtrack with the music being quite similar to that of ''Car'', small sound of bells to begin with and gets louder when the '2' rises from the patch. It was withdrawn from the line-up before the 1997 corporate logo revamp, however it was brought back again for the 2001 [[Chelsea Flower Show]] (albeit with the then current &quot;BBC TWO&quot; legend) and remained in use until the end, making it the only ident to have been reinstated.

Edited in June 2001.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Powder'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;26 October 1992 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
This featured a birds-eye view of the '2' falling onto a bed of white [[Powder (substance)|powder]], revealing a layer of viridian powder beneath it, left streaked around the '2' as the stray particles clear away. Red and blue lights were cast onto the figure as it fell. The audio track has a sharp, cymbal-like effect as the '2' is falling, and this culminates in a deep cymbal crash as the '2' hits the surface, along with a sustained bass note. The soundtrack continues in the aftermath of the crash, with a faint, deep texture accompanying the bass, although this would have been rarely heard, due to the track usually being faded down for continuity by this point.

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Optics'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;26 October 1992 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
''Optics'' included many [[optical fiber]]s of mainly viridian and green colour, swaying from side to side, initially with great momentum but slowly and eventually settling into the shape of the '2' symbol. The slow-tempo audio was atmospheric, carried by warm melodic sounds and a deep bass note, with a high choir pad towards the end. Along with ''Powder'', this was one of the first new idents to be added to the roster, and allegedly replacing ''Glass'' and ''Paper Cut Out'', it was to be the joint-second longest running ident and would last for the rest of the series until the 2001 rebrand. An ident produced with [[computer-generated imagery|CGI]], ''Optics'' was also the last ident to be played out with the slanted BBC logo.

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Car'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;1 November 1993 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
One of a new series of idents introduced in 1993. It featured a viridian '2' with an aerial moving about on wheels in a yellow studio, in the same manner as a remote-controlled car. The car noise varies in pitch as it whizzes around at varying speeds. It's possible that this inspired the [http://www2.tv-ark.org.uk/bbc2national/bbc2national2001.html 2001-2007 series of idents].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.tv-ark.org.uk/bbctwo/2001_idents.html |title=BBC Two &amp;#124; 2001 Idents |publisher=TVARK |date= |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Dog'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;1 November 1993 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
Also known as &quot;Fluffy Dog&quot;. This ident included a fluffy green '2' whirring, yapping and doing back flips in the manner of a [[toy]] mechanical [[dog]]. The bassline of the audio track is the same as that heard in ''Copper Cut Out''. There was also a short variant where the '2' turned into a scared piece of cotton, but it was only seen during a Monster Night promo from 1998.

Edited in October 1997.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''TV'''''&lt;/div&gt;
|style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;1 November 1993 - 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
A House Included with a TV They Changes the Channel and Revals the '2' in the TV

Edited on November 2001
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Crystal Ball'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;1 November 1993 - December 1995&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
A rarely seen ident that was introduced as one of the 1993 idents, ''Crystal Ball'' was inexplicably dropped after just 26 months. It featured a [[crystal ball]] rolling across a blue, purple and green background, revealing a distorted image of a '2' as it passed over the middle of the screen. One possible explanation for its removal so quickly after launch was the similarity between it and the [[History of BBC television idents|BBC One 'Virtual Globe' ident]]. It's also rumoured that the ident was pulled due to the decreased visibility of the '2', which was only in view for a split second. A sparse minor chord composition overlaid subtle howling effects, lending a mystical feel. This was the very first ident to be taken out of use.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Firecracker'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;1 November 1993 - 31 December 1999&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
Also known as &quot;Exploding Fireworks&quot; or simply &quot;Fireworks&quot;. This featured a [[viridian]] '2' on a rusty-looking brown desk, with live [[firecracker]]s attached to it. The [[firecracker]]s go off, launching the '2' towards the camera, before it is pulled back into place by an attached cable&amp;nbsp;— which can be clearly seen after the final explosion. The final [[firecracker]] actually fails to go off. The featured soundtrack starts with a rich, deep orchestral texture as the fuse burns down, then as each firecracker goes off, it is paired with a simultaneous crash and musical note&amp;nbsp;— while both during the explosion and in the aftermath, windchimes play a waltz through the piece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=alwardemshire |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vzLkk5pyr3w&amp;feature=related |title=How did they did the BBC2 1991-2001 Idents 3 |publisher=Youtube.com |date=1991-04-20 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The notes played during the explosions are vaguely similar to what became BBC Two's [[signature tune]] from 2001–2007.

Edited in October 1997 but was withdrawn at the end of 1999 along with 4 other idents.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Diary'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;February 1995 - 31 December 1999&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
This ident featured a white '2' on a black background, with [[paper]] layers peeling off and drifting away. This was originally meant to have several layers quickly peel off, but instead looped the same four layers in different directions due to tangling wirework.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=alwardemshire |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vzLkk5pyr3w&amp;feature=related |title=How did they did the BBC2 1991-2001 Idents 4 |publisher=Youtube.com |date=1991-04-20 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The music consists of a gentle E-minor chord-scale piece, led by a harp on single plucked notes, plus very faint, high-pitched strings. This ident along with ''Steam'' were the last regular idents to be added to the line-up before the 1997 revamp.

Edited in October 1997 but was withdrawn at the end of 1999 along with 4 other idents.
|-
| center;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;'''''Steam'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;February 1995 - 31 December 1999&lt;/div&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fff; style=;&quot;width:50;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid #1f777b; vertical-align:top;&quot;|
This featured a viridian-coloured, metallic '2' of extremely hot temperature, as a ring of syringes dispensed water droplets which fell onto and around the figure. Any drops landing on the boiling '2' instantly evaporated into steam, and upon impact were accompanied by a tinkling sound on the audio track. The soundtrack beared a strong resemblance to that of ''Optic'' only with a D# chord progression, with four synth-lead notes in order to create an atmospheric feel. This ident along with ''Diary'' were the last regular idents to be added to the line-up before the 1997 revamp.

Edited in October 1997 but was withdrawn at the end of 1999 along with 4 other idents.

Like ''Firecracker'', the four notes played at the beginning of the ident are vaguely similar to what became BBC Two's [[signature tune]] from 2001–2007.
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Aerial'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;4 October 1997 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
''Aerial'' featured a viridian '2' with [[antenna (radio)|aerials]] attached to it in a red studio, appearing in random places between flashes of static, before finally appearing in the centre of the screen. The soundtrack is slightly similar to ''Car'' (which aired in 1993 from the previous era), featuring notably prolific use of synthesized bell sounds. This was the first ident to be shown with the then-new &quot;BBC TWO&quot; legend. This was one of the new idents to be added to the line-up after the 1997 revamp along with  ''Duck'', ''Paint Pot'', ''Zapper'' and ''Gorilla''.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Duck'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;4 October 1997 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
This ident depicted a soapy setting, from which a yellow '2' resembling a [[rubber duck]] emerged, giving a little squeak. Later showings of ''Duck'' has the 'BBC TWO' [[DOG]]'s colour changed to black in order to be visible on the lighter background.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Paint Pot'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;4 October 1997 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
In a parody of the original ''Paint'' ident, a silver [[paint pot]] is bombarded by lots of little [[viridian]] '2's, once again falling sideways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jimwoodward1212 |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fiPoJUooPPE |title=BBC 2 Paint-Pot Ident |publisher=YouTube |date=1999-04-16 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The music is similar to ''Paint'', with some slight changes to the score. Usually, apology screens were made on this ident.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Zapper'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;4 October 1997 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
This featured a [[fly zapper]] in the shape of a '2' upon a wall. A fly is attracted to it, but the zapper breaks on contact and the fly buzzes away, leaving a smoke trail behind it. Behind the sound effects of the zapper is essentially the same audio as ''Sign''.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Gorilla'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;4 October 1997 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
There were two variations on this ident. A [[gorilla]] stands up a yellow '2' in one ident and knocks it over in the other. Originally a special ident for a wildlife programme, it became a regular symbol.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Swan'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;January 1998 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
Introduced at the start of 1998, it featured three white '2's swimming past a clearly bemused [[swan]], which shakes its head shortly after. The soundtrack was of mid-slow tempo, no percussion, with harp and a rich, dreamy background texture.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Dalek'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;13 November 1999 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
Originally a special ident for ''[[Doctor Who]] Night'', its popularity meant it went on to join the roster of regular idents. It featured black &amp; white [[Dalek]]s in the shape of '2's moving between a grey corridor. The audio intro draws inspiration from the style of the series' famous theme tune lead. A variant on this ident, named ''Exterminate'', has the sequence opening with the Dalek '2' shouting the familiar phrase.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Excalibur'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;1 January 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
One of six new idents to be introduced at early 2000, ''Excalibur'' featured a blue '2' rising from a pool of water sideways, à la ''Paint''. As the '2' emerges, stray droplets of water fall off the '2' and back into the water, causing (vertical) ripples, with each drop that hits the water being accompanied by a finger cymbal-esque note on the soundtrack. This ident did not feature the viridian. It was the last in this series of idents to be broadcast on BBC Two Scotland.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Catalyst'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;1 January 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
In this ident, liquid droplets fly in from the top right corner of the screen and cause flames to flare up around the '2' on contact. This is heralded with the sound of dramatic, blaring horns. The flames die down after about 18 seconds, revealing the 2 to be completely undamaged, before the cycle starts again. The music was later updated with the same audio as ''Sign'' along with flaring sounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jimwoodward1212 |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EtyTYG9fXwA&amp;feature=related |title=BBC 2 Catalyst Ident |publisher=YouTube |date=2008-11-09 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Wave Day'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;1 January 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
Originally called ''Wave'', this featured a '2' within a sheet of blue liquid that splashes around it throughout. The soundtrack opens with a three-note melodic synth chime that features occasionally thereafter, and the sound of filling water serves to enhance the visuals.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Predator'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;1 January 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
''Predator'' begins centered on a '2'-shaped [[butterfly]] sitting within a [[jungle]] environment. The camera then zooms out, and the '2' is gobbled up by a larger '2' in the form of a [[Venus Flytrap]]. The audio starts off quiet and gentle, but then builds to a [[crescendo]] as the butterfly '2' gets swallowed, before returning to quietude. This ident was later revived (albeit with the then-current look) in mid-2006 (renamed ''Venus Fly Trap''), and remained in occasional use until the entire set was revamped in 2007. This along with the Christmas 2000 ident (used for the [[2006 Winter Olympics]] between 10–26 February) were the only idents to be revived in the 2001-2007 set.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Kebab'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;1 January 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
Kebab has a '2' made of meat on a kebab spinning. It has a new Eastern soundtrack. There were 3 variations where the kebab was in different stages of cooking.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Woodpecker'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;1 January 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
This ident depicted five metal poles, of varying distance, against an orange background. Viridian '2's edge their way down the poles in the same manner as a mechanical [[woodpecker]]. The soundtrack features a fitting whistled four-note jingle, vaguely similar to what became BBC Two's [[signature tune]] from 2001–2007, amongst the drilling of the woodpecker '2's.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|-
| center;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;'''''Wave Night'''''&lt;/div&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align: left; &quot;|&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;2 September 2000 – 19 November 2001&lt;/div&gt;
|- 0&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
Introduced in the last half of the year, it was a retake on the original ''Wave (Day)'' ident. It now featured a darker background and liquid pool, with a bright cyan '2'. The side(s) at which the liquid rose were also reversed, for example starting up the left side instead of the right. The soundtrack was the same as the original ''Wave Day''. This was the final ident to be added to the regular [[roster]] before the entire set was revamped in 2001.
|- border-color: #1F777B; style=&quot;background:#1f777b; color:white; width:50px;&quot;
|colspan = &quot;4&quot;|
|}

===Special Idents===
Since 1974, [[BBC Two]] has aired special idents for use at national celebrations such as [[Christmas]]. The Christmas idents were changed annually throughout this period (except for 2001 where the channel would have rebranded prior to Christmas of that year), and were seen as a Christmas tradition for BBC's [[BBC One|1]] and [[BBC Two|2]] to produce a new Christmas package on an annual basis (This tradition was broken in 2003 when [[BBC One]] reused the previous years ident, and in recent times when the same ident was used alongside BBC Two for 4 Christmases consecutively). In contrast, Halloween and [[St. Valentine's Day]] idents were only produced between 1991 and 1997.

*Christmas 1991 - A wrapped up 2 set against a cloudy night sky with stars and the moon interacting and looking.
*Christmas 1992 - A red 2 appears as fairy lights on a Christmas tree.
*Christmas 1993 - A metallic coloured 2 is hoisted up atop a Christmas tree by hobbit like creatures.
*Christmas 1994 - A large yellow 2 in a dome against a [[tundra]] landscape.
*Christmas 1995 - [[Wallace and Gromit]] accompany a 2 covered in fairy lights while sat at Christmas dinner.
*Christmas 1996 - A wizard walks on clouds in the sky, before spinning and turning into a 2 made of stars.
*Christmas 1997 - A white 2 in a snowglobe with the faces of BBC Two's Christmas lineup appearing as reflections in the snowglobe.
*Christmas 1998 - A green fairy moves back to reveal the 2 atop a Christmas tree with surreal white and green colours.
*Christmas 1999 - A similar theme to last year, and the first ident to feature the ''bbc.co.uk'' URL. The 2, complete with wings, knocks the fairy off the tree before taking her place.
*Christmas 2000 - Two small white 2's skate on top of, and fall off, a huge ice-covered 2. This ident was reused in 2006.

As well as the Holiday idents, many other special idents were produced, mainly to introduce themed nights of programming on the channel, or specific programmes.

*Puzzle - Used for a night about the origins of puzzles
*Made In Japan - Japanese Culture
*English - Little England programmes
*Billboard - Art programmes on Commissions and Collaborations
*Wet &amp; Windy - The Weather
*One World
*War &amp; Peace - War themed night
*A Night Of Love - Love programmes for Valentine's Day
*Birth Night
*Crime &amp; Punishment - Justice System
*One Day In The Sixties
*BBC Two 30th Anniversary
*Centenary - Centenary of Film
*Mars Weekend
*Red Dwarf night - 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jimwoodward1212 |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EtyTYG9fXwA&amp;feature=related |title=Red Dwarf BBC2 idents montage |publisher=Youtube.com |date=2008-11-09 |accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Evolution weekend
*Monster night
*It's Scary Out There - Horror films
*Seventies
*[[The Simpsons|Simpsons]] Night
*I love the 80s - Adapted from a sting
*Star Trek night

==Stings==
During the run of the idents, there were also quick, usually humorous short [[animation]]s shown before the trailers known as 'Stings'. Such examples included a 2-shaped pancake landing in a frying pan, a '2' performing stunts on a bicycle, or a set of spinning plates in the form of the '2'. These were sometimes themed to suit a particular event, such as sport coverage. Examples include a set of snooker balls racked in the '2' shape (of which&amp;nbsp;— like some others&amp;nbsp;— there was more than one variant of the scene). Animations were also often created annually to match the theme of that year's Christmas symbol; for example, a set of short animations featuring [[Wallace and Gromit]] were used during the 1995 Christmas period along with a similarly themed ident.

Today, these 'sting' animations are not remembered as prominently as most of the idents. They were usually only a few seconds long and, particularly from 1997, the '2' would become a character rather than a symbol, an idea that was carried on for the [[BBC Two]] yellow idents from 2001.

Below is an incomplete, short summary of some of the stings.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Name
!Description
|-
| Jelly
| A [[Gelatin|gelatin (jelly)]] '2' jumps over the floor in a room. The room and the 2 are both dark yellow. First aired 1993.
|-
| Cliffhanger
| A '2' hanging on the top of a wooden object, possibly about to fall off. Introduced in 1993.
|-
| Crash
| A '2' crashes into the screen and gets dizzy. First aired 1995.
|-
| Door
| A '2' in a dark room, with a door being closed, leaving the '2' in darkness. There were two versions in this ident. Introduced around 1994.
|-
| Polaroid
| A [[Instant camera|polaroid camera]], printing off a [[photograph]] with a '2' on. The colour of the 2, and the angle of the camera, were changed from time to time. Introduced in 1991.
|-
| Ten Pin
| A [[Bowling|bowling game]], showing a '2' as the only pin not knocked down. A ball is rolled to try and knock the 2 over, but the 2 jumps into the air, making the ball fall down. First aired 1995.
|-
| Hangover
| A glass of water (or some other type of transparent liquid), with two '2'-shaped [[Alka-Seltzer]] tablets being dropped into the water and dissolving. Introduced around 1994.
|-
| Spaghetti
| A bowl of '2'-shaped [[spaghetti]] pieces in a tomato sauce. First aired 1991.
|-
| Plunge
| A '2' jumps from a high diving board into a pool of water. First aired 1995.
|-
| Slinky
| A Slinky-shaped '2' rolls down some stairs. First aired 1993.
|-
| Cuckoo Hooligan
| A naughty [[cuckoo]] '2' leaps out of a [[clock]], and tries to hit the [[camera]]. First aired 1993.
|-
| Pump
| An inflatable '2' pumps on a patio. First aired 1995.
|-
| Velcro
| Also known as 'Sticky Pad'. A '2' made out of [[Velcro]] in a vidarin room tries to get out. First aired 1997.
|-
| Harley Bike
| A bicycle '2' does a trick, and then rides home. First aired 1993.
|-
| Newton's Cradle
| A '2' ball is seen in a Newton's Cradle type of toy. First aired 1994.
|-
| Pounce
| A '2' that looks like a cow or a cat practices pouncing. First aired 1994.
|-
| Ducks
| A '2' is crowed by hundreds of rubber ducks. First aired 1997.
|-
|Hair Curlers
|A hair drying machine opens to reveal '2' shaped hair curlers in the woman's hair First aired 1991.
|-
|Sub
|One of three animated shorts featuring the duck '2', who also starred in his own ident. The '2' pops up from underneath the bubbles, and like a submarine periscope, looks around in different directions, before sinking below surface again. First aired 1997.
|-
|Jaws
|The third in this family of shorts. This one features the duck '2' swimming through the bubble bath squeaking the theme from Jaws. First aired 1997.
|-
|Web
|The spider makes its web, and the web turns into a '2'. First aired 1995.
|-
|Whacky
|A saw makes a circle around the '2', causing the '2' to fall. First aired 1993.
|-
|Fridge
|The '2' becomes fat in a freezer and falls. First aired 1998.
|}

==Further references==
*The 1991-1997 version of ''Powder'' was aired in the titles of the [[3rd National Television Awards]] on 8 October 1997 on ITV1. This was the final broadcast of this version, and it had ceased to exist on BBC Two some days before. It was only a second long clip of the ident.
*An [[Internet meme]] based on making mock-versions of the BBC Two '1991-2001' idents has appeared. Some various mock idents include ''Blade II'', ''Spin'', ''Transylvania'', ''Starfield'', and ''Water Splash''.
*The [[B.F.T.]] titles from [[Children's BBC]] in 1991 featured a small recreation of the ''Blade'' ident in the opening titles.
*'Glass' appeared as part of a spoof BBC Two programme menu sequence in 1994 comedy series [[The Day Today]], which aired shortly after the ident had been removed from regular network use.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{portal|BBC}}
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/bbctwo/noise/?id=idents BBC Two page on idents]
**[http://downloads.bbc.co.uk/bbctwo/pdf/ident_poster.pdf Idents wall poster] (750KB)
*[http://idents.tv/blog/?p=456 idents.tv] the new BBC Two idents
*[http://www2.tv-ark.org.uk/bbctwo/1991_idents.html BBC2 1991-1997 idents at TV Ark]
*[http://www2.tv-ark.org.uk/bbctwo/1997_idents.html BBC Two 1997-2001 idents at TV Ark]

{{s-start}}
{{succession box |
  before=[[BBC Two 'TWO' ident|TWO]] |
  title=[[BBC television idents]] |
  years=16 February 1991&amp;ndash;19 November 2001|
  after=[[BBC Two 'Personality' idents|Personality 2s]] |
}}
{{s-end}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{BBC}}
{{BBC Television}}
{{BBC Ident}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bbc Two 1991-2001 Idents}}
[[Category:BBC television|Idents]]
[[Category:Television presentation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
