<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8124711" ns="0" title="List of Black Lagoon characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=May 2007}}
The following is a list of characters from the Japanese [[manga]] and [[anime]] ''[[Black Lagoon]]''.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

== The Lagoon Company ==
[[Image:Lagoon Company.jpg|300px|thumb|The entire Lagoon Company. From left to right: Benny, Rock, Revy and Dutch.]]

===Rock===
;{{anime voices|[[Daisuke Namikawa]]|[[Brad Swaile]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Rokuro Okajima'''|岡島緑郎|Okajima Rokurō}}, also known as {{nihongo|'''Rock'''|ロック|Rokku}}, is the [[protagonist]] of the series. He was a Japanese [[salaryman]] for Asahi Industries in [[Tokyo]] until he was taken hostage by the crew of the ''Black Lagoon''. He joined the Lagoon Company after his department chief, Kageyama, abandoned him (he was declared dead) in an attempt to cover up the [[smuggling]] operation in which Rock had been an unwitting participant. Rock is a humble and mild-mannered person despite being on the business end of guns from friend and foe alike, and often seems surprised at the barbarity of the [[Southeast Asian]] crime world. He still wears his tie, short-sleeved dress shirt, and dress pants because, although now a pirate, he still retains his business persona. He prefers to use words over weapons when interacting with others. Rock, after joining the Lagoon company, has wondered if he is experiencing [[Stockholm syndrome]].

Within the Lagoon Company, Rock is usually responsible for account management, diplomacy, negotiation, interpretation, and the occasional errand.  Having once worked in the resource investigation department of Asahi Industries, Rock is also skilled in [[geology]]. He is also a skilled linguist, being effectively bilingual in Japanese (his [[native language]]) and English as well as being familiar with other languages, including [[Spanish language|Spanish]], [[Romanian language|Romanian]] and [[Russian language|Russian]]. He also has a surprisingly high tolerance for alcohol, owing to the heavy-drinking lifestyle of a ladder-climbing salaryman. Rock's earnest personality has earned him the interest of several figures in Roanapur, including Balalaika, Mr. Chang, Rowan &quot;Jackpot&quot; Pigeon, Yolanda, Eda (who develops a crush on him), and young Garcia Lovelace, whom he trusts to the greatest degree. In many ways, Rock is the heart of the Lagoon Company, serving as a balance for his more jaded teammates and as a bright spot in the world of darkness that is Roanapur. Dutch has stated that he believes Lagoon Company is complete with Rock not holding a gun, saying his bullets are the kind to ricochet back at them.

Rock is one of the &quot;luckiest&quot; characters in the series as he managed to survive every single thing he experienced from being taken hostage to being shot at. Thus far, he has survived the wrath of Revy, Balalaika, Roberta, and Sawyer.  He is personally appointed by Mr. Chang to help Garcia Lovelace, much to Lagoon Company's disapproval. Rock eventually begins to enjoy his life as a pirate and becomes even more comfortable with corruption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 9|year=2010|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=El Baile de la muerte, Part 24|page=|isbn=1-4215-3629-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in a conversation with Fabiola, he demonstrates a darker, sadistically ruthless side of his personality clearly influenced by Revy and the Roanapur environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 9|year=2010|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=El Baile de la muerte, Part 30|page=|isbn=1-4215-3629-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; His proposal plan to Fabiola for dealing with Roberta angered her since it is a high risk gamble with other people's lives on the line, but Rock was unfazed by it. After getting shot by an angered Fabiola in the extra missing pages of chapter 76 with a blank round resulting in broken ribs, he feels very upset and told Benny in chapter 77 that he learned his lesson the hard way and shall not meddle in other people's business anymore as the results don't always turn out well. Benny even points out that there are things about him that scare almost everyone in Roanapur, with Fabiola telling Rock that he is now being viewed as a citizen of Roanapur and perhaps the biggest number 1 bastard in Roanapur. Rock asked Benny if he has changed, with Benny not knowing the answer to that. In &quot;The Wired Red Wild Card&quot; arc, he is last seen driving a car with Revy.

While Rock has a family in Tokyo, he does not seem to have much connection to them due to their somewhat apathetic attitude towards him. It was later revealed that he did not pass his college entrance exams on his first try, leading his family to lower their expectations of him. It is known that he has a father, a mother, and an older brother who was academically capable and thus attained a job in the Japanese government.  He was born in the 49th year of the [[Showa period]], according to the manga version, which corresponds to 1975-1976.

===Revy===
;{{anime voices|[[Megumi Toyoguchi]]|[[Maryke Hendrikse]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Revy'''|レヴィ|Revi}}, sometimes referred by her full name {{nihongo|'''Rebecca'''|レヴェッカ|Revekka|romanized ''Revecca'' in the Japanese media}}, is the female [[protagonist]] of the series. She does most of the fighting for the Lagoon Company. Very little is revealed about her past.  Revy is a [[Chinese-American]] born and raised in [[Chinatown, Manhattan]], near Mott Street, spending most of her youth as a thief and murderer. Flashbacks throughout the series reveal that she may have honed her skills with firearms by shooting at cans, and that her first murder may have involved shooting a guy who asks her for wine/money everyday that she resolves on stealing just to give the demand if she can't, she gets battered. She got arrested upon failed thievery and is beaten and raped by a police officer. This triggered Becky, Revy's real name to kill her caretaker by using a gun while using a pillow as a [[Suppressor|silencer]]. Revy is very competitive, strong, stubborn, impatient, and extremely ill-tempered. Unlike Rock, she is undiplomatic, believing in the use of brute force and coercion to get her way. In contrast to this, she is revealed to be highly ticklish. She is also a heavy smoker and drinker. Of all the characters in the series, Revy is recognized as the most foul-mouthed.

She is a merciless and sadistic killer without a conscience who will kill anyone at the slightest provocation, even unarmed civilians. She has a changing but volatile attitude towards Rock, the newest and most polite crew member of the ''Black Lagoon''; though she respects him later in the series, she is mostly hostile towards him, having nearly murdered him on two occasions and threatening him with death on several others. However, she does have a tendency to save Rock from critical situations, and later on she admits to considering Rock as family to Balalaika. It is likely that she is attracted to Rock, based on her reactions to Eda's teasing, which appear to be jealousy. Her attraction is further suggested in the last scenes of Season 2 when Eda asked her if she had gotten anywhere with Rock, instead of denying it with a short comment as usual she said she rather not say causing Eda to laugh at her hopelessness when it comes to men.  

Revy is also very protective of Rock. An example can be found in her anger and resolve to kill Chaka after he beats Rock. She has also lied or gone against her &quot;nature&quot; in order to save him; such as when he was kidnapped by Takenaka and she lied about him having the documents they required when she actually had them the whole time, or when she stood up to Balalaika when she held Rock at gunpoint after he opposed her plan to destroy the Washimine group. She also went to Japan as his bodyguard (when Rock acted as Balalaika's translator), but as pointed out by Benny the only real reason she went was to look after him because she was worried about him.  

According to [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] agents on [[Basilan (island)|Basilan Island]], Revy is still notorious in the [[New York City Police Department|NYPD]], particularly at the fictional 27th Precinct.

Revy is one of the deadliest fighters in the series, whose skill with firearms and ability to dodge bullets is almost superhuman and unparalleled. There are only a few other characters, such as Roberta and Ginji, that can hold their ground against her in combat. In episode 11 of the first season Revy concedes to Mr. Chang that she does not possess his level of skill but hopes to attain it eventually. Her weapons of choice are a [[Akimbo (firearms)|pair]] of modified [[Beretta 92]]FS's; which are made out of stainless steel and had their barrels extended from 4.9&quot; to 5.9&quot; each (the 5.9&quot; is the combat MOD barrel) and also adapted for [[suppressor|silencers]]. They are engraved with the words &quot;9mm Sword Cutlass&quot; on both sides, the [[Jolly Roger]] of the pirate [[Calico Jack]] (which is also inlaid into the ivory grips), and a manufacture inscription in [[Thai alphabet|Thai]]. Due to her [[Cross-dominance|ambidextrous]] marksmanship skills, she is nicknamed &quot;Two Hand&quot; by the denizens of Roanapur, which is based on Douglas E. Winter's novel '''Run'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 1|year=2008|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=Editor's Note: Revy &quot;Two Hand&quot;|page=206|isbn=978-1-4215-1382-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Revy is also proficient in the use of other weapons, such as high powered rifles and the [[M79 grenade launcher]]. 

Constantly living on the edge of life, Revy has developed a rather bleak, almost [[nihilism|nihilistic]] outlook on life, relying only on her own power, skills, and money. She does believe in god but not emotions. However, she seems to respect and trust her companions.

===Dutch===
;{{anime voices|[[Tsutomu Isobe]]|[[Dean Redman]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Dutch'''|ダッチ|Dacchi}} is the African-American leader of the Lagoon Company and captain of the ex-[[U.S. Navy]] [[PT boat]] ''Black Lagoon''. He is a former [[United States Marine Corps|Marine]] who fought in the [[Vietnam War]]. Shortly before the war ended (presumably in 1973), Dutch went [[AWOL]], escaping to Thailand to work as a mercenary. He tends to stay away from the fighting associated with Lagoon Company's activities. Instead, he gives orders and negotiates contracts with clients, usually Balalaika of Hotel Moscow. However, Dutch is very capable in combat, skillfully wielding a [[Remington 870]] Marine Magnum shotgun and a [[Smith &amp; Wesson Model 29|Smith &amp; Wesson 629]] revolver. Dutch is a calm, easygoing character, and most of the time, is quite friendly. His body is heavily muscled, and he is always seen wearing a pair of sunglasses, typically dressed in camouflage pants and wearing a [[flak jacket]]. He appears to be in his 30s, but is most likely in his 40s, given his apparent military service in Vietnam given the setting of ''Black Lagoon'' in the 1990s.  In the &quot;Baile de los Muertos&quot; saga in the manga, it is suggested that Dutch lied about his Vietnam service and could just simply be a mercenary with no past. But a U.S solder said to Rock, in the previous chapter, to beware of Dutch, because a man like Dutch never lie without a serious reason. He could have a simply mercenery life or a mysterious one.

===Benny===
;{{anime voices|[[Hiroaki Hirata]]|[[Brian Drummond]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Benny'''|ベニー|Benī}} is a college dropout from a [[Florida]] university where he studied until getting into trouble with the [[FBI]] and the mafia, and would have ended up dead if Revy had not saved him. He works as the Lagoon Company's mechanic, computer specialist, and researcher.  He also functions as the Lagoon's driver, and appears to be the owner of the [[Dodge Coronet#1968-70|1969 Dodge Coronet R/T]] (later replaced with a [[Pontiac GTO#First generation|1965 Pontiac GTO]]) that Lagoon Company travels around Roanapur in. He is Jewish, or at least of [[Jewish]] descent as he puts it, and is often called &quot;Benny-Boy&quot; by Dutch. Benny joined the Lagoon Company two years before Rock, after Revy rescued him.  Benny has an easygoing and non-violent personality. He readily admits to Rock that the two of them are not gunfighters in any way, shape, or form. Unlike Rock, however, Benny is willing to turn a blind eye to Revy and Dutch's more violent methods.  Benny also tends to be possessive of his computers, and will not let anyone else touch them.  In the second season, he met Greenback Jane, and, after impressing her with his computer abilities, began an online relationship with her.  Jane returns to Roanapur following the teams completion of the Lovelace Incident and Benny meets up with her. Possibly based on [[Jake Adelstein]].

==Hotel Moscow==
[[File:Hotel Moscow.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Boris and Balalaika.]]
Hotel Moscow is a branch of the [[Russian mafia]] based on Thai soil. The Bougainvillea Trade Company serves as a front for their activities. It is composed of the men who served under Balalaika in the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan]], who are dedicated to her.

===Balalaika (Vladilena)===
;{{anime voices|[[Mami Koyama]]|[[Patricia Drake]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Balalaika'''|バラライカ|Bararaika}} is the boss of Hotel Moscow. Her real name is Vladilena, a reduction from [[Vladimir Lenin|'''Vlad'''imir '''I'''lich '''Len'''in]]. She was brought up by her grandfather, the military head of the USSR. Before joining the mafia, Balalika was a captain in the [[Soviet Army]] and a ''[[Russian Airborne Troops|Vozdushno-Desantnye Vojska]]'' paratrooper who served in the Soviet war in Afghanistan. A fine marksman and sniper, she was nicknamed &quot;[[balalaika]]&quot;, one of Soviet Army's slang terms for the [[Dragunov sniper rifle]]. Due to Balalaika's leadership during the hellish fighting in Afghanistan, her men look up to her as their superior and will do just about anything upon her orders. As a combat officer, she is a skilled strategist and well-rounded fighter, capable of taking care of herself despite the fact that all of her troopers, including Boris, often worry about her. Although she has shown herself to be rather cynical on occasion, she is also a pragmatic and professional businesswoman. She frequently employs Dutch and the Lagoon Company, apparently because they share a mutual respect.

Balalaika can be easily identified by the burn marks which scar most of the right side of her face, neck, and chest which she suffered in Afghanistan, earning her the nickname &quot;Fry-Face&quot; by those who dislike her. She has long blonde hair, and usually wears a [[greatcoat|military greatcoat]], thrown over a low-cut business suit. She smokes [[cigar]]s, in contrast with the other characters who smoke [[cigarette]]s. Based on her service in Afghanistan and the missed opportunity to participate in the [[1984 Summer Olympics]] in Los Angeles, she is between 31–35 years old. She is one of the few people to earn Revy's respect. In turn, Balalaika also seems to hold Rock in high regard, sometimes relying on his knowledge and business skills.

In critical operations, Balalaika calls upon a personal cadre of ex-Soviet airborne troops and [[Spetsnaz GRU|Spetsnaz]] commandos who are Afghanistan veterans. Known as the ''Desantniki'',&lt;ref&gt;In the manga and English dub, they were called Vysotoniki.&lt;/ref&gt; they act as Hotel Moscow's special ops team. When conducting foreign operations from Thai soil, she uses the Russian cargo ship ''Maria Zeleska'' as a legal cover from the police and various law enforcement agencies. In spite of the fact that Balalaika is on the [[Interpol]] list, she uses her real name in Japan, being covered by [[diplomatic immunity]].

===Boris===
;{{anime voices|[[Taiten Kusunoki]]|[[Mark Acheson]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Boris'''|ボリス|Borisu}} is Balalaika's second-in-command. He can be easily identified by the large scar running from the right side of his forehead to his left cheek. He is a calm, broad-built man with a deep Russian accent. Like Balalaika, he also saw service in Afghanistan. She still refers to him as &quot;Sergeant&quot; rather than by his name, suggesting that he was her former [[platoon sergeant]]. He is very loyal and protective of Balalaika and often worries for her safety when she decides to fight in the field. In an Omake, he used to be a weak girlish looking boy before joining the army (this is unconfirmed however, as the Omakes are non-canon.)

==The Chinese [[Hong Kong]] Triad==
They are led by Chang, who is a proficient gun fighter in his own right. Chang is more patient than Balalaika in terms of getting into battle. Under his services are Shenhua, who is his top assassin; Sawyer, who does disposal jobs for him frequently despite not being a member of the organization, and Leigharch, who is their getaway driver until recent events prevented him from acting in this capacity.

===Mr. Chang===
;{{anime voices|[[Toshiyuki Morikawa]]|[[Trevor Devall]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Bai Ji-Shin Chang'''|張維新|Chan Waisan}} is the boss of a Thailand branch of the [[Sun Yee On]] [[Triad society|Triad]]. Like Revy, he is adept with dual-wielding pistols ([[Beretta 76]] and [[AMT Hardballer]]) in a fashion similar to that of [[gun fu]], the former of which are inscribed with a Chinese symbol, meaning &quot;Heavenly King&quot;, on the grips. Chang is far more proficient in this dual-wielding gunfighting style than Revy, who, in episode 11, freely admits that she is &quot;not on his level yet&quot;. It is implied that it is he who taught her this style of combat, though that is yet to be clarified.{{citation needed|date=May 2007}} It may be this prowess in combat that makes Chang the only male whom Revy respectfully refers to as &quot;Sir&quot;. 

He has a deep respect for Balalaika (who annoys him by referring to him as &quot;Babe&quot;), though their beliefs are known to collide. Their relationship is almost playful in a business sort of way, which began after they survived a shootout with each other. They both have the ability to join forces, but choose not to because it would make their respective lives boring. He also comments that Rock's actions will determine the fate of not only Garcia and Roberta, but of Roanapur itself, and is rather amused at Rock's &quot;unique&quot; way of handling things. Unlike most criminal bosses in the town, he advocates cooperation and joint ventures to keep the [[status quo]] in Roanapur. He has a conversation with Eda (which might mean that she is one of his US Government contacts) concerning &quot;Grey Fox&quot;, the unit responsible for the death of the head of the Lovelace Family, and gets irritated when Eda taunts him when suggesting that he was not to do anything &quot;foolish&quot; as it will mean the destruction of Roanapur at the hands of the United States.

Chang seems easily amused, and unusually-easygoing and lighthearted, especially given his position. This might be attributed to the fact that he was once a member of law enforcement, which he reveals after being called 'an inhuman scumbag' by Rock and laughing out loud in response, and he might very well be seeing his current position as an ironic twist of fate.

His past as law enforcer may explain his combat expertise. Chang manages to survive a shootout with Balalaika, escape from ambush of superior number of Islamic front jihadists, and disarm Fabiola easily. His expertise is often overshadowed by his easygoing character, in comparison with the ill-tempered Revy and near-psychotic Roberta.

Mr. Chang is based on characters commonly played by [[Chow Yun-fat]] in films by [[John Woo]], such as John Lee in ''[[Replacement Killers]]'' and especially [[Mark Gor]] in ''[[A Better Tomorrow]]'', as both Chang and Gor are members of the Hong Kong Triads, wield dual pistols and don similar attire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 3|year=2008|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=Editor's Note: The Triads|page=193|isbn=978-1-4215-1892-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{-}}

===Shenhua===
;{{anime voices|[[Yoko Sasaki]]|[[Saffron Henderson]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Shenhua'''|シェンホア|Shenhoa}} is a [[Taiwan]]ese [[assassination|assassin]] in the employ of Mr. Chang. She prefers to use various edged weapons in close combat, in particular a pair of [[Thai E-nep Knives]] linked together with a length of leather rope at the handles, thus using them as modified [[rope dart]]s. She is also skilled in the use of throwing knives. Shenhua is a professional rival of Revy (who refers to her as &quot;Chinglish&quot; in the anime and &quot;Yes Lady&quot; in the manga; in return Shenhua calls Revy &quot;[[Twinkie]]&quot; in the anime (yellow on the outside (Chinese) and white on the inside), whom she has worked with and against at times. While Chang and the Triad are her primary employers, she also has been shown to do freelance work as well. Her personal religion is [[Taoism]]. However, she tells Eda in episode 18 that she is an [[Atheist]], but this was due to a mistranslation in the English dubbed anime. One of her most notable traits is her broken speech pattern, which is always moving between [[Chinese language|Chinese]] and [[English language|English]]. She is last seen being helped to walk by Lotton (who says that he will take her to a doctor, despite her having suffered what she believes to be a fatal wound) after being shot by Eda while hunting for Greenback Jane. In the El Baile de la Muerte arc, she is revealed to have survived the battle when Revy is shown calling her on the phone. She agrees to take up Revy's offer to help Garcia fight off the Colombian Cartel who is trying to kill Roberta.
She showed her first glimpse of fear when in close range combat with Roberta when she managed to catch one of Shenhua's kukri in her teeth and shattered the blade to pieces.

It is unknown if Shenhua has any unarmed hand-to-hand skills, although it seems likely. In the anime, she fights only with blades, and never engages anyone in true hand-to-hand combat.  The only other person who does this is Sawyer the Cleaner, who frequently works with her in &quot;disposal&quot; jobs.
{{-}}

===Leigharch===
;{{anime voices|Akimasa Ohmori|[[Trevor Devall]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Leigharch'''|レガーチ|Regāchi}} is an Irish driver who worked with Shenhua during the incident involving the Islamic Liberation Front. A compulsive user of [[marijuana]], he has a distressingly frequent tendency to hallucinate at inopportune times, such as in the middle of a car chase. Most of his hallucinations are actually references to Western pop culture, such as [[Playmate]]s, ''[[Star Trek]]'' characters like [[Jean-Luc Picard]] and [[Klingon]]s, or sixties rock music such as [[Jimi Hendrix]]. Leigharch is said by Shenhua during the Greenback Jane incident to have suffered a massive overdose (he &quot;couldn't get back from Mars&quot;), inducing psychological damage severe enough to commit him to full-time medical attention. Despite his drug addition and hallucinations, he was still considered a skilled driver before his overdose.
{{-}}

==The Colombian Cartel==
The cartel noted in this section is separate from the Manisalera Cartel which was originally responsible for Garcia Lovelace's kidnapping and was subsequently wiped out by Roberta and Balalaika and seems to have since taken over their territory. Along with the Italian Mafia, they are the most brash of the criminal organizations, much to the disgust of Balalaika and Chang.  Just them barely appearing often results in needless fighting and bloodshed.  They are led by Abrego, who is somewhat of a coward and usually travels with his men.  Lately, they have been made a fool of in the criminal underworld because of the Lovelace Family and their two killer maids.  While the Italians do it for profit, the Cartels do it as a sense of pride, which usually gets them into unwanted trouble.  It is revealed that they had a hand in the assassination of Diego Lovelace. 

===Abrego===
;{{anime voices|[[Hisao Egawa]]|[[Eli Gabay]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Abrego'''|アブレーゴ|Aburēgo}} is a Colombian drug cartel boss operating in Roanapur. Whilst very arrogant, he has a tendency to be cowardly. He was presumed dead after the South American maid Roberta detonated a bomb in the bar he was in, although his appearance in later episodes is evidence that he somehow survived. After the explosion and the loss of many of his gunmen, Abrego's influence in Roanapur seems to have fallen, judging from the attitude he takes from Balalaika, Chang and Verrocchio.  He is once again made a fool of, this time by Fabiola.  

Ever since the incident with Roberta, the Cartel had tried numerous times to figure out where she was hiding; fortunately for Roberta, through her connection with the Lovelace family, Roberta was protected daily by local police and military forces.  Thus, the Cartel couldn't even touch her without causing an incident.  Currently, he sends for many FARC Soldiers to assist the cartel in finding Roberta; however, much of the FARC has been suspicious of the cartel's action and even threatened to betray them.
{{-}}

===Gustavo===
{{nihongo|'''Gustavo'''|グスターボ|Gusutābo}} is one of Abrego's main henchmen.  At first, he is seen doing simple tasks for Abrego, such as disposal jobs, early in the series.  Recently, he's been assigned to track down Roberta after hearing rumors of her returning to the city by other groups, including the police, Triad, and Hotel Moscow.  He, along with some men, search for Roberta throughout the city and meets up with Revy and Rock.  He then explains the situation within the Cartel regarding Roberta.  He then crosses paths with Fabiola, who is requesting the aid of Lagoon Company.  Fabiola is threatened by him and his men, as Revy then instigates a fight between them, resulting in a comical argument between him and Bao over the use of the telephone, much to Revy's amusement.  In desperation, he tries to call Abrego, who is out with a girl according to his subordinates.  He calls all of them in to warn them of another maid who is as fierce as Roberta.  Finally, he orders the total destruction of the Yellow Flag, much to Bao's anger as the Yellow Flag is demolished again.  He is left behind by his men after Fabiola scares them off.  Because of his failure, Abrego has ordered him to be killed on sight.  He is later seen at Abrego's side during a meeting with the other gangs.

== Other Roanapur gangsters ==
===Verrocchio===
;{{anime voices|[[Banjo Ginga]]|[[Scott McNeil]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Verrocchio'''|ヴェロッキオ|Verokkio}} is the boss of a branch of the [[Sicilian Mafia|Italian mafia]] based in Thailand. He once attempted to use the child assassins, Hänsel and Gretel, to kill the rival gang leaders, including Balalaika and Mr. Chang, in an attempt to seize complete leadership of Roanapur's criminal underworld. Verrocchio was killed when Hänsel and Gretel turned against him on a murderous whim.
{{-}}

===Ronny the Jaws===
'''Ronny the Jaws''' is Verrocchio's replacement as the Italian Mafia's boss after his death at the hands of the twins. He wears braces; hence his name. His real name was unknown until Chapter 79; Balalaika calls him by the derogatory slang &quot;Dago&quot; prior to this. He seems to have a cooler head than Verrocchio but is still plenty arrogant and foolish;  Balalaika and Chang seem to dislike him and his immature way of handling serious business.  He doesn't hold much respect for Abrego either and treats him rudely despite being the newest amongst members of those holding the most power in Roanapur. Revy says his group is almost as vicious as Hotel Moscow and he appears to have an alliance with the [[Albanian Mafia]].

===Chen===
;{{anime voices|Suetsu Tokaichi|[[Louis Chirillo]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Chen'''|陳|Chin}} was a Chinese crime boss who made several serious attempts to replace Balalaika as one of the major powers of Roanapur. Balalaika found out about his plans to kill the Lagoon Company and personally murdered him, which consisted of tying him to a chair and then blowing up his apartment using plastic explosives and gasoline.
{{-}}

===Luak===
;{{anime voices|[[Naoya Uchida]]|[[Alistair Abell]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Luak'''|ルアク|Ruaku}} is the captain of a pirate gang that operated in the rivers and seas of Thailand.  He was contracted by Chen to kill off the Lagoon Company when Dutch wouldn't accept Chen over Balalaika.  Luak's gang ambushed the Black Lagoon, but the entire gang was wiped out by Revy and Dutch. Revy is seen to fire a round from an [[M79 grenade launcher]] into his boat at the end of the fight destroying it, so he is presumed dead. 
{{-}}

==The Church of Violence/The Rip-Off Church==
Using their front as a Christian (specifically [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]]) church, their main business is illegal imports, mainly firearms.  However, they are known to import other items, including drugs, which seems to offend Balalaika as it is bad for their business. So far they have consistently outsmarted Hotel Moscow in terms of imports. They have a fairly good working relationship with Chang, who grants them the exclusive ability to sell weapons within his territory. Dutch refers them as &quot;The Rip-Off Church&quot; due to the group charging heavily on goods, especially those needed for missions. So far, it seems Rock is able to arrange proper business deals with the Church.  The Church is always money-hungry and are known to do double-dealings, much to the disgust of Revy.

===Eda===
;{{anime voices|[[Jun Karasawa]]|[[Lisa Ann Beley]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Eda'''|エダ}} is a woman posing as a nun in the rip-off Church, with ties to the underground, since the convent is mainly a smuggling organization. She is friends with Revy, but this does not prevent them from confronting each other, as they share the same hotheaded personality.  She has taken a liking to Rock during the &quot;Second Barrage&quot; episodes, and makes fun of Revy by threatening to take Rock for herself. She often calls Rock &quot;Romeo.&quot;

Eda has blond hair, blue eyes, and wears angular pink sunglasses even with her nun's [[Religious habit|habit]], and is often seen either chewing gum or smoking.  She is in her mid-30s.  Before she came to work for the Church, she claimed to be from [[Langley, Virginia]]. Langley, Virginia, is a [[metonymy|metonym]] for the CIA as its headquarters is located there. Later on, it is revealed that Eda is an operative for the [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] and is being hosted by the Church of Violence in return for monetary payments. She is given an assignment by the CIA to track down Grey Fox, the same foe Roberta is hunting as they are a threat to her CIA division. She provides Mr. Chang with much of the intelligence about Grey Fox, but warns him about his actions. Presumably, Eda herself is accompanying Roberta to chase the Grey Fox.

Eda's preferred firearm is a [[Glock 17L]] (as seen in manga chapter 41), which she wields proficiently, despite Revy's claims that she is a &quot;second-rate gunman&quot;.

She apparently was loosely modeled after the character Thana from ''[[Ms. 45]]''.

===Yolanda===
;{{anime voices|Akiko Takeguchi|[[Shirley Millner]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Yolanda'''|ヨランダ|Yoranda}} is the leader of The Rip-Off Church. She appears to be quite old and wears an [[eyepatch]] over her right eye. Despite her age and gentle appearance, she leads her organization with an iron fist. As the head of her organization, Yolanda usually never fights, leaving this job to gunmen like Eda and Rico. However, she does carry a customized [[Gold plating|golden]] [[Desert Eagle]] and uses it without hesitation in due course, such as in chapter 38 of the manga. It should be noted that she can fire the Desert Eagle one-handed and with deadly accuracy, seemingly unaffected by the gun's infamous weight and heavy recoil. Her looks could be based on [[Mother Angelica]], a real-life [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] nun who, at one time, wore an eyepatch over her left eye. Yolanda is usually stern with Eda drinking alcohol in the church and seems to love tea. After an intelligent conversation with Rock, who convinces her to make a deal with Lagoon Company, she is impressed by his abilities and credits Dutch for finding someone as rare as him. She refers to Revy as &quot;Rebecca&quot; and tells her that she might learn a thing or two from Rock. She has connections with all the criminal organization in terms of intelligence, and though not officially part of the CIA, she serves as Eda's informant and confidant.  She gives Eda fair warning that her opponent is no rookie and that she should be careful.

===Rico===
;{{anime voices|[[Tetsuya Kakihara]]|[[Simon Hill (actor)|Simon Hill]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Rico'''|リカルド|Rikarudo}} (Ricardo) is an apprentice priest in the Rip-Off Church. Like Eda and Yolanda, he is a highly skilled gunman whose choice of weapon is a [[M60 machine gun]]. He refers to Eda as &quot;Big sis&quot; (''&quot;Ane-san&quot;'' in Japanese) instead of &quot;Sister&quot;, much to her chagrin.

== Citizens of Roanapur ==
===Bao===
;{{anime voices|[[Shirō Saitō]]|[[Alec Willows]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Bao'''|バオ|Bao}} is the bartender and owner of the Yellow Flag bar. He is an ex-[[Army of the Republic of Vietnam|ARVN]] soldier who fought in the [[Vietnam War]]. He often feels harassed by Lagoon Company, especially Revy, for messing up his bar whenever they get into a fight with another party and reminds Revy to pay for the damage she has caused, which she always avoids doing.  Balalaika seems to cover the repairs after Roberta destroyed it, which implies that the bar may be owned by Hotel Moscow.  Seen as a great hang-out by most of the residents as it give many &quot;jobs&quot; to locals.  After being rebuilt, he calls the Lagoon Company to tell them that Roberta is back in town.  When Revy and Rock arrive along with Gustavo, they all meet up with Fabiola.  After some words, Revy instigates a fight between Gustavo and Fabiola leading once again to the destruction of his bar. Bao claims that his bar has been destroyed more than 15 times, most of it done by Revy.
{{-}}

===Flora===
Madame Flora is the morbidly obese [[madam]] of the &quot;Sloppy Swing&quot;, a brothel located on the top floor of Bao's bar. She took a liking to Rock and offered to &quot;service him herself&quot; (were she a bit younger).

===Rowan &quot;Jackpot&quot; Pigeon===
;{{anime voices|[[Masaki Aizawa]]|[[Adrian Holmes]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Rowan &quot;Jackpot&quot; Pigeon'''|ローワン|Rōwan}} is the owner and manager of the GoofFest [[strip club]] on Rachiada Street in Roanapur. Of African descent, he has employed Revy as an [[Sadism and masochism|S/M]] dancer once in the past, possibly putting her as a [[dominatrix]]. He has stated, however, that she &quot;could give it and take it&quot;, implying that Revy could also have been the submissive. This is changed in the anime, with Rowan conistently asking Revy to join is BDSM show when she comes to his place, but with her expressing disgust at the idea. He is also a movie dealer who carries both legal and illegal genres (such as all forms of [[pornography]] and [[snuff films]]).   He is extremely frightened of Hotel Moscow, especially of Balalaika.
{{-}}

===Chief Watsup===
;{{anime voices|[[Masaaki Tsukada]]|[[Dale Wilson]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Chief Watsup'''|ワトサップ|Watosappu}} is the chief of the corrupt Roanapur police.  He receives a regular stipend from Roanapur's criminal cartels, as well as the Lagoon Company, to stay away from their [[police corruption|illegal activities]].  It is implied throughout the series that Revy tends to cause a lot of trouble in public and he usually has to bail her out much to his chagrin.  He gets used to Revy's trouble making and he and Revy became sort of friends.  For the most part, Watsup upholds this deal as long as his benefactors do not cause public incidents. He has dealt with Balalaika on more than one occasion, although she detests him.
{{-}}

==Bounty hunters and mercenaries==
===The Captain===
;{{anime voices|[[Masahiko Tanaka]]|[[Paul Dobson (actor)|Paul Dobson]]}}
'''The Captain''' is the rank of an unknown mercenary in the employ of the Extra Order Company, a fictional [[private military company]] similar to modern day [[Blackwater Worldwide]] and the now defunct [[Executive Outcomes]], where the initials EO come from. An experienced ex-soldier who saw action in the [[First Liberian Civil War|Liberian civil war in the early 1990s]], Captain had no qualms with killing anyone he was asked to kill. He was also something of a challenge-seeker, since he wanted to prolong his fight with the Lagoon Company, whom he saw as worthy opponents. This proved to be his undoing however, since Rock realized this and came up with a strategy to exploit Captain's attitude. While attacking the ''Black Lagoon'' head-on in a [[Mil Mi-24]], the boat launched itself off a sunken ship and fired two torpedoes that brought down the Captain's helicopter, one hitting him in the face before detonating.  
{{-}}

===Sawyer the Cleaner===
;{{anime voices|[[Asami Yaguchi]]|[[Venus Terzo]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Frederica Sawyer'''|ソーヤー|Sōyā}}, also known as '''Sawyer the Cleaner''', is a young girl, appearing to be in her late teens-early twenties, who specializes in body disposal, but also does occasional bounty hunter work. She is the person that the [[Triad society|Triads]] (and probably others) turn to execute people in the most brutal ways possible, usually to serve as examples for their clientele and enemies. Her legitimate business front is, fittingly, a meat packing business named &quot;U.G. Pork&quot;. 

Sawyer works in a white-tiled room, which is covered in blood from her various executions, and uses a [[chainsaw]] as her tool of trade. When on the job, she is dressed like a surgeon, but otherwise she wears [[Gothic fashion|gothic]] clothing. Few people seem to recognize her when she is not wearing her surgeon's robes. Because her throat had been cut open at some point, she speaks with an [[mechanical larynx|Ultravoice]]. She also seems to have various emotional issues, as she will drop into fetal position if she loses her Ultravoice.

Like Shenhua, Sawyer is an assassin who eschews the use of firearms in combat. Instead, she utilizes a thick-bladed chainsaw over half-her-height long, the same one she uses on her victims. The size and build of the weapon allows her to deflect rapid gun-fire with horrifying ease, although this can still push her back.   

Much like Roberta, Sawyer is presented as an &quot;unstoppable&quot; attacker, much in the manner of [[Leatherface]] from ''[[The Texas Chainsaw Massacre (franchise)|The Texas Chainsaw Massacre]]'', where she will cut through any obstacle in her path while stalking her prey, and the fact she enjoys her work immensely makes her even more dangerous. Her name may also be a homage to the Sawyer family of that film series and when she realized she had lost her Ultravoice in episode 18 she briefly reenacts Leatherface's &quot;chainsaw dance&quot; of rage. Strangely, she is one of the few bounty hunters to survive the manhunt on Jane, and is later seen doing some &quot;cleanup&quot; work on a Roanapur side street in the morning. She worked with Shenhua and Lotton in helping Garcia fight off the Colombian Cartel, who were trying to kill Roberta. She also seems to have replaced her hand held Ultravoice with a wraparound version of the device that can be worn around her neck. Just like Shenhua, she first showed her fear of Roberta after their first encounter when Roberta managed to stop and break the chain of Sawyer's chainsaw with her guns.  

She does not only do disposal jobs, but also cleaning jobs for hotel rooms. When she forgets her Ultravoice, she requests someone to translate for her and draws descriptions on a window or on a person's back to &quot;speak&quot;. Given the chance to explain, she's extremely graphic about the details of her profession to the point those around her tell her to stop being descriptive. Despite the gruesome nature of her job, Sawyer seems to have a rather happy, yet morbid demeanor at times. In chapter 78 when she explained to Rock that he touched a mattress that had absorbed the bodily fluids of the corpses that died 14 days prior in the hotel room he, Benny, Jane and Feng Yifei were staying in, Sawyer has a blissful expression while everyone else vomits at this information.
{{-}}

===Claude &quot;Torch&quot; Weaver===
;{{anime voices|[[Youichi Nishijima]]|[[Jason Simpson]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Claude &quot;Torch&quot; Weaver'''|クロード・“トーチ”・ウィーバー|Kurōdo &quot;Tōchi&quot; Wībā}} is a heavyset, middle-aged man with blonde hair and glasses and always sports a grin with a look of a stereotypical [[everyman]]. As his nickname would suggest, he is a [[pyromaniac]] who uses a [[lighter]] shaped-and-sized [[flamethrower]] as his weapon of choice, although for heavy-duty jobs, he will also use a full-sized flamethrower. In spite of his profession and the fact he burnt his own wife to death (which he claims took five minutes), Claude claims to be religious (which religion is unknown) and is [[teetotal]]. He is one of the few characters in the series that does not use foul language, preferring to speak with euphemisms (such as &quot;darn&quot; or &quot;shucks&quot;) instead. He is blown up by Revy while hunting for Greenback Jane.
{{-}}

===Lotton the Wizard===
;{{anime voices|[[Tomokazu Sugita]]|[[Samuel Vincent]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Lotton the Wizard'''|ロットン・“ザ・ウィザード”|Rotton &quot;Za Wizādo&quot;}} is a mysterious-looking man and one of the bounty hunters hired to capture &quot;Greenback&quot; Jane. He has silver hair, wears a black trenchcoat and shaded glasses, and speaks in a light voice. His weapon of choice is one or more [[Mauser C96]](s) with an extended magazine, although it's unknown whether this is an actual Mauser or a foreign version of the gun. He does not drink alcohol (he claims he's allergic to it). He gets shot by Revy when he tries to make a fancy entrance. It is implied that he is not a mighty fighter, but a poser. However, he did survive a fall from atop a warehouse building after getting shot due to his Kevlar vest, so the full extent of his abilities is still in question. He worked with Sawyer and Shenhua in helping Garcia fight off the Colombian Cartel, who were trying to kill Roberta.

He is also one of the few bounty hunters to survive the manhunt for Jane. After the battle takes off in the sea, he gets up and aids a gravely wounded Shenhua and Sawyer. Due to the uncommon act of kind-heartedness, Shenhua comments that he is not the type to kill and would be better as a host in a [[bordello]], but Lotton claims that he is too clumsy for that. He is seen playing video games with Sawyer at Shenhua's residence in chapter 57 of the manga.  Revy refers him as being more of a gigolo than a gunman; in addition, Revy forgets that she shot Lotton during the Greenback Jane incident (she shot him on reflex) causing Shenhua and Sawyer to mock her intelligence.

His style of dress and mannerisms are very similar to both [[Captain (Hellsing)|The Captain]] and [[Heinkel Wolfe and Yumie Takagi|Heinkel Wolfe]] of the popular vampire anime and manga series [[Hellsing]]. He would also seem to be something of a parody of the &quot;brooding [[bishounen]]&quot; archetype in anime.

===Shane Caxton===
{{nihongo|'''Major Shane Caxton'''|キャクストン|Kyakusuton}} is an American black-ops operator who is currently in Roanapur, awaiting deployment into Indochina. Like Dutch, Caxton is a Vietnam War veteran who still holds on to his moral code of conduct. Caxton's team, called &quot;[[Intelligence Support Activity|Gray Fox]]&quot;, under orders from a division of the [[National Security Agency|NSA]], orchestrated the assassination of Garcia Lovelace's father. As a result of his action, he has made an enemy of the formidable Roberta, which their confrontation involves the entire city of Roanapur, including the Triad, Hotel Moscow, and the Church of Violence. Despite this, Mr. Chang is trying to get Caxton and his men out of Roanapur to prevent Roberta from killing them, as their deaths will trigger a war between the Roanapur gangsters and the United States government.  When he meets up with Lagoon Company, he automatically recognizes Dutch and mentions something to Dutch that seemed to shock him.

It is revealed he is a highly-esteemed operator by his fellow colleagues especially Gray Fox's second in command for his decency, integrity and honorable conduct. He is the ideal symbol of America in the story.  In a flashback, he executed one of his subordinates, Larkin, in retaliation for murdering innocent women and children out of pleasure during the Vietnam War, implying he does not tolerate that kind of conduct.  He also protects Garcia Lovelace as he and his team are escaping from Hotel Moscow. By the end of the arc, he is finally slain, not by Roberta, but Garcia himself in order to end Roberta's rampage. However, it is later revealed Caxton faked his own death and Garcia's gun was filled with blanks.

===Bren the Black Death===

Bren the Black Death runs a murder for hire business. According to Revy, he has an office in Roanapur but rarely does jobs there because of overlaping contracts. Roberta hires him to gather a team to attack Grey Fox to drive them out into the open. He sends in a group of hired guns knowing very well that they will be slaughtered by the trained soldiers. He then kills the one survivor himself.

===Filano===
Filano is a young boy who works for Bren the Black Death. He is seen observing the battle between the Grey Foxes and Roberta. He says he prefers to kill with an ordinary object or with nothing at all. He is particularly fond of pushing people downstairs or in front of trains. He considers guns to be the lowest form of killing. He does however like to play first person shooters. He also likes anime.

==U-1324 Crew and Passengers==
===Lieutenant Commander Wentzel Ahbe===
;{{anime voices|[[Shigeru Ushiyama]]|[[Brian Drummond]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Captain (or Lieutenant Commander) Wentzel Ahbe'''|アーベ|Ābe}} was the decorated skipper of the [[Type IX U-boat#Type IXC|Type IXC]] [[U-boat]] U-1324 and a survivor of the [[Battle of the Atlantic (1939-1945)|Battle of the Atlantic]].  His last order in the closing months of [[World War II]] in Europe was to take the U-1324 and its veteran crew along with two passengers from the [[Kriegsmarine]] naval base at [[Kiel]] to ostensibly return Lt. Col. Matsuda to [[Jakarta|Batavia]].  He succeeded in getting safely to the [[Indian Ocean]], but ran into trouble with [[US Navy]] destroyers near the [[Nicobar Islands]] on March 25, 1945, which succeed in fatally crippling the U-1324 with [[depth charge]]s, leaving it stranded on the seafloor.  With only two hours of air left, he relieved his crew of their military duties and allowed them to face death however they chose.  Ahbe was a patriot, but he despised the Nazi cause, expressing his bitterness to the SS Lieutenant Colonel that the Nazis had brought Germany to ruin and satisfaction that U-1324’s sinking had meaning if his children would never see the Nazi flag again, leading the latter to shoot him.  In their last act of loyalty to their captain, his crew avenged him.  Ahbe left behind a wife and two children.  

His [[Knight's Cross#Knight's Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords (mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern)|Knight’s Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]] is sought after by Revy after she and Rock recover ''The Twelve Knights Led by Brunhilda'' for its value on the open market.  Ahbe is also shown to have received the [[Iron Cross#Iron Cross|Iron Cross 1st Class]] among his other decorations.

He is apparently modeled after [[Jürgen Prochnow]]'s character from ''[[Das Boot]]''. Additionally, the U-1324 bears the famed laughing sawfish emblem of the {{GS|U-96|1940|2}}.
{{-}}

===Lieutenant Colonel Matsuda===
;{{anime voices|Hitoshi Bifu|[[Hiro Kanagawa]]}}
'''Lieutenant Colonel Matsuda''' was an [[Imperial Japanese Army]] officer posted to Germany to study aeronautics, where he remained until the early part of 1945.  Returning him to Japanese-held [[Jakarta|Batavia]] is the apparent final mission of the U-1324.  He formed a fast friendship with Captain Ahbe and was sociable with the crew, engaging them in games of [[shogi]] during the voyage from Kiel to Batavia.  When the U-1324 was fatally depth charged and runs aground on the seabed near the Nicobar Islands, he committed [[seppuku]] (ritual [[suicide]]) using his [[katana]]. He does not appear in the manga.

Matsuda is based on the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] lieutenant commander Genzo Shoji, who was posted to Germany to study aeronautics as well, and tried to return to Japan as a passenger of U-234. However, when Germany surrendered in the midst of the voyage, the captain of U-234 decided to surrender to the U.S. Navy. Consequently, Shoji committed seppuku—suicide—to avoid capture. This episode was turned into the movie ''Das Letzte U-Boot'' in Germany in 1990. 
{{-}}

===SS Lieutenant Colonel Spielberger===
;{{anime voices|Takata Kuroda|[[Michael Dobson (actor)|Michael Dobson]]}}
'''SS Lieutenant Colonel''' ([[Obersturmbannführer]]) {{nihongo|'''Spielberger'''|シュピールベルガー|Shupīruberugā}} was the U-1324’s second passenger.  A member of the [[Sicherheitsdienst|SD]], he was charged with the care of the painting ''The Twelve Knights Led by Brunhilda'', which is part of a Nazi plot to prepare for the Nazis' eventual return to power following their defeat in World War II.  

He boarded the U-1324 the night before it sailed.  Unlike Lt. Col. Matsuda, he was not as sociable, tending to keep to himself belowdecks, even when the U-boat was safely cruising on the surface in daytime.  Like Captain Ahbe he also had a family, a wife and child in [[Stuttgart]], but unlike the former, was more focused on the failure of his mission rather than on them in his final hours.  Ahbe's anti-Nazi comments infuriated him, leading him to fatally shoot the captain.  About to then shoot himself, he decided to take down as many of the U-1324’s crewmembers as possible in his final moments when they avenged their captain's murder.
{{-}}

==Neo Nazis (Aryan Socialist Union)==
The Aryan Socialist Union is a [[paramilitary]] group of aspiring stereotypical [[Neo Nazis]] styling themselves along the lines of the Nazi [[Sturmabteilung]]. Though it's not explicitly stated, it is implied they are based in the [[United States]] (in the manga they were apparently all [[German-Americans]], due to the way they spoke such as &quot;Fraulein&quot; or &quot;Jawohl&quot;). They have a large arsenal of weapons such as [[MAC-10]] machine pistols, [[MG3]] machine guns, [[AK47]] assault rifles, [[Luger P08 pistol|Luger]] and double action trigger-outfitted Colt 45 pistols (in the manga, they carried multiple kinds of handguns) and even [[BGM-71 TOW|TOW]] [[anti-tank missile|Anti-Tank Missiles]]. 

However, they do not realize that they have been lied to and are being set up by Sir Alfred, the head of the Neo Nazi movement, who believes they are a waste. There are more than 30 of them aboard their recovery ship, along with seemingly innocent hostages used to pilot the ship. It is unknown how many, if any, survived the conflict with the Lagoon Company.

===Ratchman===
;{{anime voices|[[Ryuji Nakagi]]|[[Richard Newman]]}}
[[Oberster SA-Führer|Überführer]] {{nihongo|'''Ratchman'''|ラッチマン|Racchiman}} is a short, fat man who leads the Aryan Socialist Union.  He and his men are sent to retrieve a painting that was supposedly painted by [[Hitler]] and will reunite the Nazis and return them back to their former glory.  He hopes that, by obtaining the painting, he will have proven himself and his men loyal enough to be accepted into the Neo Nazi underworld. Though he shows loyalty on the surface, he is a coward at heart. Ratchman's lack of foresight and proper planning enables the Lagoon Company to sneak onto the ASU's recovery ship and launch a surprise attack while his men are drunk from celebrating after they recover the painting. He is murdered by Revy and Dutch. It is mentioned in the manga that his group is a minority party in American politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 2|year=2008|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=Das Wieder Erstehen Des Adlers Part 3|page=63|isbn=978-1-4215-1891-6200}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===[[Gruppenführer]]===
;{{anime voices|[[Ken Narita]]|[[Brian Dobson]]}}
The {{nihongo|'''Gruppenführer'''|クルッペンフェラー|Kuruppen Ferā}} is the commander of the Aryan Socialist Union's Suicide Corps, the recovery team who was sent to retrieve ''The Twelve Knights Led by Brunhilda'' from the U-1324.  He is the only man, other than Ratchman, to get emotionally worked up over the latter's bombastic pronouncement of his mission.  Feller leads his men down to the U-1324 using a special diving pod to connect with the U-boat's hatch.  Getting caught up in a firefight with Revy, he is the only member of his team to set foot in the U-1324 to make it out alive, recovering the painting in the process. Proving himself as a Nazi seems to matter to him more greatly than the lives of his comrades, as shown by his willingness to abandon his men once he had gained control of the painting, and his caviler attitude afterward.

When Revy and Dutch assault the Aryan Socialist Union aboard their recovery ship, he attempts to arm himself with a [[MG42]] to fight back, but is shot in the back by Revy in the ship's [[Magazine (artillery)#Naval magazines|magazine]]. In the manga, he is last seen fighting Revy inside the submarine; his fate afterwards is unknown.

===Fritz Stanford===
;{{anime voices|[[Youichi Nishijima]]|[[Mark Gibbon]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Fritz Stanford'''|ブリッツ・スタンフォード|Burittsu Sutanfōdo}} is the Captain ([[Sturmhauptführer]]/[[Scharführer]]) of the Nazi boat that is sent to obtain the [[World War II]]  painting in the sunken [[U-boat]]. He is a physically huge man, and is filled with blind faith and overconfidence. Despite this, he is the only member of the group to question whether the painting was worth the sacrifice of so many of the organization's resources. In the end, it is this overconfidence that gets him killed when he brags about his weapon and threatens Revy (as she slowly reloads her weapon), who shoots him in the chest and then point blank in the head, mostly just to shut him up. He wields a large [[Gold plating|gold]] [[Luger P08 pistol|Luger]] chambered for the [[.454 Casull]] cartridge.

===Sir Alfred===
;{{anime voices|[[Fumio Matsuoka]]|French Tickner}}
Little is known about {{nihongo|'''Alfred'''|アルフレード|Arufurēdo}}, except he seems to be the head of the Neo Nazi underworld. He is an elderly man, most likely in his 80s, since he was in the [[SS]] during the war, and it is implied that he is a combat veteran. Sir Alfred sets up a test of loyalty and ability for Ratchman and his Aryan Socialist Union, in which he purposely sends them to face-off with the Lagoon Company. Even though he sets them up, he already knows that Ratchman will most likely be defeated. Ratchman and the Lagoon Company are unaware that they are being set up. Sir Alfred feels that Ratchman and his men are idiots and a disgrace to call themselves Nazis, seeing their easy defeat by a group of &quot;racially inferior&quot; members as proof of their incompetence in his view. He even thanks Dutch and Revy for killing them off for him, and even harbours an amount of respect for Dutch, despite being a black man. Dutch later finds out that the Spanishman who hired him was in fact The Boss setting him up. In the manga it is mentioned that he played a part in operation [[ODESSA]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 2|year=2008|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=Das Wieder Erstehen Des Adlers Part 3|page=64|isbn=978-1-4215-1891-6200}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Protectors of the Islamic Front==
The &quot;Protectors of the Islamic Front&quot; (known as &quot;Islamic Front of National Salvation&quot; in the manga&lt;ref name=&quot;Page 98&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 3|year=2008|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=Goat, Jihad, Rock'N Roll Part 1|page=98|isbn=978-1-4215-1892-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ) is a [[Mujahideen|Jihadist]] group based in South East Asia. They seem to be a fairly large organization, judging from the sizable group of fighters they send to attack the Lagoon office, and the number of men in the Philippine Jungle encampment located in Mindanao. They also appear to be a rather skilled terrorist group, carrying out a successful bombing of the U.S. [[Embassy]] in [[Zaire]] (see also [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]), and the planning of a terrorist attack in the [[United States]] with the implicit goal of assassinating the [[President of the United States|President]] by using biological weapons on the New York Subway in Manhattan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hiroe|first=Rei|title=Black Lagoon, Volume 3|year=2008|publisher=[[Viz Media]]|chapter=Goat, Jihad, Rock'N Roll Part 1|page=99|isbn=978-1-4215-1892-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among their main allies is the [[Abu Sayyaf]] Group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Page 98&quot;/&gt;

Documents detailing the plan of this &quot;Presidential Attack&quot; fall into the hands of Chang, who plans to give them to the [[CIA]] in exchange for money, with the Lagoon Company acting as the couriers. Subsequently, the group desperately attempts to recapture the documents, as the attack would be foiled should the documents reach their destination. The Islamic Front's members appear to be more well versed in military style tactics than the Lagoon Company's other opponents (such as the Aryan Socialist Union or Luak's gang), but prove to be little match for Revy, Chang, and Shenhua, and many of them are killed in their efforts to retrieve the Documents. 

The anime depicts the Islamic fighters wearing balaclavas while the manga depicts them wearing shemaghs.

===Masahiro Takenaka===
;{{anime voices|Katsuhiko Sasaki|[[Fred Henderson]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Masahiro Takenaka'''|竹中正洋|Takenaka Masahiro}} is a soft spoken co-leader of the terrorist group &quot;Protectors of the Islamic Front&quot; and a patient, sociable person who rarely loses his cool. Despite being involved with an [[Islamic terrorist]] group, he himself is an atheist. Born in the [[Adachi, Tokyo|Adachi ward in Tokyo]], Masahiro was once an enthusiastic activist for human rights before joining the [[Japanese Red Army]] during the [[Cold War]]. Later, he was forced to evade arrest by hiding overseas after most of its members were arrested. Takenaka is based on the [[Japanese Red Army]] member [[Kozo Okamoto]].
{{-}}

===Ibraha===
;{{anime voices|[[Ken Yamaguchi]]|[[MacKenzie Gray]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Ibraha'''|イブラハ|Iburaha}} is a co-leader of the &quot;Protectors of the Islamic Front&quot;, leading one of its main cells in the [[Philippines]], and is resolute in his hatred of [[Israel]], as his son was killed by Israeli soldiers in [[Beirut]], [[Lebanon]] in 1987, after which he  dedicated his life to fighting the West. Compared to Takenaka, he is the exact opposite in personality, while Takenaka is calm, reasonable and clever; Ibraha is paranoid, unreasonable and always want to fight without thinking. While chasing Revy, Rock, and Shenhua towards a [[Basilan]] military base, he is shot and killed by Takenaka for refusing to pull their forces back for a retreat, as allowing them to continue would have gotten them all killed.
{{-}}

==The Washimine Group==
The Washimine group were a [[Yakuza]] formerly run by {{nihongo|Ryuzo Washimine|鷲峰龍三|Washimine Ryūzō}}.  Balalaika came to Japan to work out a deal with the Washimine group to expand their influence in Japan in exchange for helping them weaken a rival Yakuza group, the Kousa Council.  However, when Hotel Moscow's methods went too far, Tsugio Bando, the current head of the Washimine group, tried to stop them and was killed by Balalaika, who decided she would instead destroy both groups and take over their operations.  Following his death, Ryuzo's daughter was put in charge.  In the end, the entire Washimine group, and family, were wiped out along with the Kousa Council.

===Yukio Washimine===
;{{anime voices|[[Houko Kuwashima]]|[[Lalainia Lindbjerg]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Yukio Washimine'''|鷲峰雪緒|Washimine Yukio}} is a high school senior and the only daughter of Ryuzo Washimine, who was the former ''kumicho'' (boss) of the [[yakuza]] organization &quot;Washimine-gumi&quot; (Washimine Group). As the only surviving direct relation of the former boss of the Washimine Group, only Yukio had a viable claim to the leadership of the Group. She reluctantly takes up the leadership when &quot;Hotel Moscow&quot; steps up their efforts to claim a part of the Japanese criminal underworld. She falls, seemingly inevitably, into the world of the yakuza and fantasizes about running away with Ginji to Roanapur to stake a claim in that world of crime. In her spare time, Yukio enjoyed reading a wide variety of books, particularly those concerning philosophy (she is once seen reading a book written by [[Martin Heidegger]]). She commits suicide with Ginji's sword after Ginji is killed by Revy. Thoughtful, intelligent and talented, the misfortune of being the only heir to the Washimine group proved too much for Yukio to live by. 
{{-}}

===Ginji Matsuzaki===
;{{anime voices|[[Kiyoyuki Yanada]]|[[Michael Adamthwaite]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Ginji Matsuzaki'''|松崎銀次|Matsuzaki Ginji}} is the acting ''wakagashira'' (underboss) of Washimine Group, and is Yukio's most loyal and humble personal body guard, and possibly love interest. He works as a street stall vendor, but was formerly an assassin nicknamed &quot;''Hitokiri Ginji''&quot; (Manslayer Ginji) due to his use of a [[katana]] in combat.  His skills in its use are exceptional, manifesting themselves in such feats as cleaving bullets in two in midflight.  Coupled with his ability to evade gunfire from multiple foes, Ginji almost completely eschews the use of firearms.

Ginji had protected Yukio for a long time and hoped that she would live out her life normally despite her family's criminal background. He seems to regret his past as a murderer, but is willing to take up arms again for those he cares for. He is killed by Revy in a prearranged duel after he and Yukio realize they can't defeat Balalaika and the rest of Hotel Moscow.

So far, Ginji is the only one whom Revy admits had the perfect chance to kill her. After shattering Revy's cutlass and forcing her to fall back, Ginji proceeds to stab Revy in spot; if he was not distracted by Yukio, Revy would have had no way to defend herself.

It is interesting to note that although Revy calls Ginji &quot;Jumbo&quot; because of his height, the name &quot;Jumbo&quot; may also refer to Takeshi Takeda (AKA &quot;Jumbo&quot;) from the [[Yotsuba&amp;!]] manga series with whom he shares an uncanny resembalance.

===Tsugio Bando===
;{{anime voices|[[Tomomichi Nishimura]]|[[John Novak]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Tsugio Bando'''|坂東次男|Tsugio Bandō}} is the ''wakagashira'' (underboss) of the Washimine Group. Since the position of boss of the Washimine Group is left vacant by the death of the former boss Ryuzo Washimine, Yukio's father, Tsugio is the actual boss of the Washimine Group. Tsugio is very loyal to the memory of Ryuzo, who had protected him after he just arrived in Tokyo from Osaka. Due to his hate of the Kousa Council's ill-treatment of the Washimine Group, he allied with Hotel Moscow for a short time in order for his group to rise and make a name for itself. However, his plans and Hotel Moscow's completely differed in approach as Balalaika was more brutal in her methods. He is killed in a desperate attempt to assassinate Balalaika and protect the Washimine Group, Balalaika easily dodging his attempt to stab her and then breaking his neck.

===Yoshida===
;{{anime voices|[[Kenta Miyake]]|[[Trevor Devall]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Yoshida'''|吉田|Yoshida}} is one of the enforcers working for the Washimine Group. He was very loyal to Tsugio Bando and refers to him as an older brother. Yoshida is usually seen as a bodyguard for Tsugio, and later Yukio when she inherits the leadership of the Washimine Group. During Yukio's inheritance of the Washimine Group's head position, it was Yoshida who rallied support for the young lady. He is killed by Chaka during Yukio's kidnapping.
{{-}}

===Chaka===
;{{anime voices|[[Wataru Takagi]]|[[Jonathan Holmes]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Chaka'''|チャカ|Chaka}} is one of the enforcers working for the Washimine Group who fancies himself as a &quot;Wild West&quot; gunman and is fluent in English. Arrogant, cruel, and sadistic, Chaka is often seen as an idiot by his peers. His earlier appearance showed that Revy's reputation as a gunman in Roanapur is such that even the yakuza in Japan have heard of her. Shortly after Yukio becomes the boss of the Group, Chaka makes his bid to take over the leadership by kidnapping her with the help of a street gang. He was determined to fight Revy in a quickdraw showdown, but she refused and lured him into fighting a duel with Ginji instead, who defeated and finished him off by letting him drown in a pool with both his hands severed. His character and appearance is likely based on Kakihara from [[Ichi the killer]], as both of them are longing for a strong opponent equal to them and are sadistically violent. Possibly based on a presumably-existing [[Kudo-kai]] member hanging around [[Harajuku]].

==The Lovelace Family==
The Lovelace are one of the 13 prominent [[South America]]n families.  However, the family has come under hard times from not only their peers due to their political beliefs, but also from the Colombian Cartel, which has been harassing employees of the family in order to take control of their land.  However, because of Diego Lovelace's military and political connections, the family is constantly protected from threats.  In addition, the family includes Roberta (aka Rosarita Cisneros), a former FARC terrorist who is wanted by both the Cartel and various law enforcement agencies.  Because of her close relationship with the family, she is accepted as one of their own, serving as maid and, if necessary, bodyguard.  Another maid, who is combat ready like Roberta, is Fabiola Igesias.

===Diego Jose San Fernando Lovelace===
{{nihongo|'''Diego Jose San Fernando Lovelace'''|ディエゴ・フェルナンド・ラブレス|Diego Ferunando Raburesu}} was the former head of the Lovelace family, eleventh in succession. While it is one of the thirteen noble families of South America, the Lovelace family fell upon hard times, with only the meager income from their plantations maintaining their lifestyle.  He took in Rosarita Cisneros, when she was escaping from the Colombian Cartel as a favor to his old friend, Roberta's father.  He took her in and treated her as family.  Recently, he was assassinated during a speech due to the fact his political beliefs were seen as a threat by many.  This event makes Roberta take up the &quot;Bloodhound&quot; persona once more.

===Garcia Lovelace===
;{{anime voices|[[Kazue Ikura]]|[[Cathy Weseluck]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Garcia Fernando Lovelace'''|ガルシア・フェルナンド・ラブレス|Garushia Ferunando Raburesu}} is the only son of Diego Jose San Fernando Lovelace, aged about 12 to 13 at his first appearance. He was heir to the Lovelace family line, and as such, is its current head, the twelfth in succession after his father was assassinated. He was kidnapped for a short while by a Colombian cartel and was transported by the Lagoon Company as &quot;goods&quot;. He and Roberta left Roanapur shortly afterwards, with some help from Hotel Moscow. He has apparently returned to Roanapur searching for Roberta with a new maid named Fabiola, waiting in a local hotel called the &quot;Sunken Palace Hotel&quot; and seemed to have matured greatly in terms of emotional strength, as commented by Rock, since his last appearance.  He treats both Roberta and Fabiola as if they were his extended family and in return, both care for him equally.  He requests help from Lagoon Company with additional help from Chang, Shenhua, Sawyer, and Lotton.  However, the only person he truly trusts in Roanapur is Rock.  To stop Roberta, Garcia comes up with the most drastic plan to stop her rampage, fake Caxton's death with his own hands, thus taking away Roberta's &quot;Path of Justice&quot;; this causes an angry Roberta to hallucinate once more causing her to shoot him; this enabled Garcia to snap Roberta out of it mainly because the promise Roberta made to Garcia of not harming him, a vow she broke. In the aftermath, Chang told Rock that the Lovelace family will still have a hard road ahead of them in future.
{{-}}

===Roberta===
;{{anime voices|[[Michie Tomizawa]]|[[Tabitha St. Germain]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Roberta'''|ロベルタ|Roberuta}} is a maid who worked for four years at the Lovelace household in [[Venezuela]]. Although her domestic skills such as cleaning and cooking were poor, she developed a close friendship with the young son of the Lovelace family, Garcia. Roberta was once known as {{nihongo|'''Rosalita Cisneros'''|ローザリタ・シスネロス|Rōzarita Shisunerosu}}, a former [[Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia|FARC]] guerrilla trained as an assassin in [[Cuba]] and an internationally wanted criminal.  Balalaika refers her as a &quot;hardcore terrorist&quot; to the point that Hotel Moscow had to deploy all their commandos as well as Balalaika getting involved in the situation personally should things get out of hand.  Revy refers to her as &quot;Fucking Four Eyes&quot; or &quot;That Fucking Glasses Bitch&quot;.  She earned the moniker &quot;Bloodhound of Florencia&quot; for her relentless drive to achieve her objectives. Her tormented past and the smell of blood, gunpowder and muck like that of a sewer rat emanating from her was something Revy understood full well.

In combat, Roberta is a truly fearsome opponent, having trained in a wide variety of martial, stealth, and weapon skills. Among the weapons she has used were a .50 caliber [[sniper rifle]], [[combat knife]], [[SPAS-12]] shotgun disguised as an umbrella(reinforced with Kevlar), [[machine gun]], and semi-automatic [[grenade launcher]] hidden in a suitcase, spiked [[brass knuckles]], [[trench spike]], and twin IMBEL Model 911 pistols (see Colt [[M1911 pistol]]s). Her strength, speed, endurance, and instincts were honed to almost [[superhuman]] levels, so much so that Rock at one point refers to her sardonically as &quot;a killer robot from the future&quot; (a reference to [[James Cameron]]'s ''[[Terminator (series)|Terminator]]'' movies).

While Roberta is one of the most powerful warrior-women in ''Black Lagoon'', she is also humane. She is unwaveringly devoted to her master and his son, Garcia, whom she loves deeply as if he were her own child. Roberta and Revy fight each other, but only to beat themselves up. Rock interferes, but Roberta and Revy tell him to stay out of it. In the manga and anime, the fight ends in a draw right after they punch each other out simultaneously, (though Garcia claims she won because she remained conscious). Her kindness can easily change as seen in a humorous omake in Volume 1 of the manga when Garcia slapped her butt in a playful manner, which prompted her to pinch his arm and lift him up off the ground by the skin of his arm as punishment. There are a few hints that she may be religious,  unlike many of the other main characters in ''Black Lagoon'', specifically [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] judging from the large [[crucifix]] she wears around her neck. It should also be noted that she very rarely uses profanity.

She admitted that she did murder children, women, or anyone in name of revolution during her [[FARC]] years. Disillusioned by the fact that she was merely a tool for the drug cartels in cahoots with [[FARC]], she opted out and joined the Lovelace clan as a maid through her father who is a friend of Lovelace. Despite being asked by Garcia not to pick up gunfighting anymore, later events in the manga, which depicts her watching helplessly as a bomb was set killing many including Diego Lovelace.  Garcia's question of why was his father was a victim makes her go into battle again, seeking revenge. Roberta also shows signs of a growing madness; she is shown taking mouthfuls of anti-psychotics, and experiencing haunting hallucinations in the form of her past victims.  She once again stalks the city of Roanapur in search of the one responsible for assassinating her master. Unfortunately, it turns out to be the US Special Forces, who's intentions were to assassinate a general and had to sacrifice Diego Lovelace to complete their mission.  Roberta's quest for vengeance has put many of the residents including Hotel Moscow, the Triad, and the Colombian Cartel on high alert as it could mean the end for all of them if their new enemy is the United States.  Most of the residents blame the Lagoon Company for attracting her back to Roanapur  despite the fact the group was in the dark about the situation and brushed it off as if it were an [[Elvis]] sighting.  Further into her quest, she begins to lose sight of her goal, almost returning to her former persona to the point she begins to lose her sanity and has trouble identifying friend and foe, thus almost harming Garcia and Fabiola in the process.  The Columbia Cartel even comments that she is no longer the hound they once knew, but a stray wolf searching for purpose.  Her oath as the &quot;Bloodhound of Florencia&quot; is &quot;In the name of Santa Maria, a hammer blow of righteousness to all injustice.&quot;

In Chapter 73, Roberta is last seen with an American woman, presumably Eda. The woman is able to disarm Roberta easily and pass her through the security, so whether she is Eda or not, she is definitely an American security agent.  She finally catches up with Grey Fox and annihilates the entire squad minus Caxton, who is thought to be slain by Garcia (however, it later reveals he faked his own death); in order to stop her madness.  In anger, she shoots Garcia, severely wounding him (though implied its not a mortal wound), she catches Garcia in her arms just realizing  what she has done. In the extra missing pages of chapter 76, she and Garcia kissed and they made up with each other and returns to the Lovelace home. However, in the fifth episode of the OVA, Roberta is severely injured and is confined to a wheelchair as she later regains the ability to walk slowly (she has lost her left arm, her right eye, and visible as she is being wheeled out is a prosthetic foot and ankle, implying her lower right leg has been amputated as well).

In issue #50 of ''[[Anime Insider]]'' magazine, director [[Sunao Katabuchi]] comments that the animation staff referred Roberta as an &quot;Evil [[Mary Poppins]]&quot;. He goes on to add that creator [[Rei Hiroe]] long thought of Roberta as a kind of &quot;Death Poppins&quot;.

===Fabiola Iglesias===
;{{anime voice|[[Satsuki Yukino]]|}}
{{nihongo|'''Fabiola Iglesias'''|ファビオラ・イグレシアス|Fabiora Igureshiasu}} is a young maid in the employ of the Lovelace family. She is one of the maids who work as Roberta's subordinates, and the only other combat-trained person among the maids apart from Roberta herself. In combat, she prefers to use two [[MAG-7]]s that were given to her by Roberta. She also carries a pump action [[China Lake NATIC]] (Mistakenly referred to as an [[EX 41 grenade launcher]] in the Manga).  She also has heel blades concealed in her shoes (a possible reference to the [[James Bond]] film ''[[From Russia with Love (film)|From Russia with Love]]'', in which the antagonist [[Rosa Klebb]] famously attempts to use poison-laced blades concealed in her shoes to kill the main protagonist).  

Fabiola first appears in the same bar, The Yellow Flag, that Roberta met the Lagoon crew in, panicking everybody with her resemblance to Roberta. However, unlike Roberta, her suitcase is revealed to be filled with lollipops and a lunchbox with [[Scooby Doo]] and [[Ranger Smith]] on it. She is currently helping Garcia search for Roberta. She is something of a comic relief when compared with Roberta (whom she calls &quot;head housemaid&quot; with the utmost respect), as she is little, carries her grenade launcher concealed in her outfit, and is often prominent in humorous situations; such as her height, being picked up like a bratty little kid, to being made fun of her breast size. 

Dutch describes her as a &quot;short version of the Killer Maid&quot;, after she destroys Bao's bar.  She states that she comes from the poorest slums of [[Caracas]], where she lived with her ten siblings until she was employed by the Lovelace Family. As noticed by Rock, she does not brawl, being a proficient practitioner of [[capoeira]].  According to her, she and Roberta are the only two maids in the Lovelace house who are proficient in firearms, with Roberta being the better of the two.  She also mentions that there are three other maids in the Lovelace house: Karina, Masica and Davia (though it's unknown at this time if they're combat proficient as well).  This makes Revy question her &quot;Just what is the Lovelace plantation like? Full of bad-ass motherfuckers who could storm the Iranian embassy by themselves?&quot;. Fabiola was disgusted at Revy for being heartless and merciless against her foes, with Revy lecturing her that love and friendship do not apply in Roanapur. She and Garcia are reunited with Roberta; but the happiness is short lived when she and Roberta witness Garcia shooting Caxton with a Colt 45 filled with blanks and in retaliation Roberta shoots Garcia.  She and Roberta then tend to a wounded Garcia. On their way back, they encountered Rock and Fabiola gets upset and disgusted with him and shot him with a blank round which injured Rock's ribs for &quot;gambling with people's lives&quot;. She told Rock they will not meet again and that he shall &quot;continue to dance with the walking dead in Roanapur.&quot;

Just like Roberta, Fabiola is very protective of Garcia.  She is more brash than her mentor, but not as much as Revy.  She tries to attack Chang after seeing him with Garcia, but he easily disarms her without trying.  She loves to play in the pool when she's relaxing, but is embarrassed to ask Garcia for a break, despite the fact he is aware of her activities.

==Other characters==
===Kageyama===
;{{anime voices|[[Jōji Nakata]]|[[Ross Douglas]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Kageyama'''|景山|Kageyama}} is one of the department chiefs of Asahi Industries, based in Tokyo. He was entrusted by its board of directors to ensure that their illegal activities were not exposed. Kageyama betrayed Rock by appointing Captain to kill him and the Lagoon Company, thus encouraging Rock to stay on with the Company. Although Kageyama is married and has three children (one teenage son, one teenage daughter, and one pre-teen daughter), he seems to place more emphasis on his job than on his family.

===Hänsel and Gretel===
{{anime voices|[[Omi Minami]]|[[Ashleigh Ball]]}} (Hänsel)&lt;br/&gt;
{{anime voices|[[Tomoko Kaneda]]|[[Jocelyne Loewen]]}} (Gretel)

'''Hänsel and Gretel''' are two unnamed Romanian twin orphans. They were abandoned in a state-run [[orphanage]] due to their parents' inability to afford keeping them. As a result of  being repeatedly forced to participate in [[Pedophilia|paedophilic]] [[snuff film]]s in which they are either raped or forced to murder other children, and being repeatedly forced to watch the people running the orphanage beat one of the children to death in front of them, the twins eventually became deranged, sadistic killers just to survive. The horrid engrossment with their torturing and murdering for pleasure is shown during the first part of Season 2 when the twins first arrive to Roanupor as they purposely wound one of Balalaika's men during a gunfight, bring him back to their temporary stay with Verrocchio's headquarters, and proceed to probe his body with sharp objects as a medical experiment, and then drain his body of blood and organs for them to bathe in; afterwards they kill Verrocchio and his men out of indulgence, even though they were supposed to help them escape the city. Unknown to most people, &quot;Hänsel&quot; and &quot;Gretel&quot; are actually two personalities alternately adopted by the two children, both of whom suffer from [[Dissociative Identity Disorder]], meaning they swap being &quot;Hänsel&quot; and &quot;Gretel&quot; with each other from time to time (it is likely that these were their screen names in the films). There are slight implications that they could be [[incest]]uous, possibly due to the abuse they suffered in the state-run orphanage. It is never made clear of what gender the twins are: in one scene, &quot;Gretel&quot; (formerly &quot;Hänsel&quot; before swapping) shows 'her' genitalia to Rock in what she presumably came to believe was a show of gratitude, causing him to flee in disgust and anger for her and Hänsel to have been betrayed since birth and to have been deprived of their humanity and a better chance at life than to become monstrosities, having known nothing but 'blood and darkness' their whole lives.

Both of them are white haired and dressed in dark [[gothic fashion|gothic clothing]], such as &quot;Gretel&quot; is dressed in a [[Gothic Lolita]] outfit.

In combat, &quot;Hänsel&quot; wields a sharp, wicked-looking [[battle axe]] while &quot;Gretel&quot; uses a [[M1918 Browning Automatic Rifle]] that appears to be taller than 'she' is. Both also carry additional sidearms. While they were mentally deranged, Hänsel and Gretel were also cunning, having used two other children as decoys to distract the bounty hunters and using money to distract Eda. They were also not above using their innocent appearance to deceive their enemies.

As revenge for killing Balalaika's men, Hänsel is shot from a distance by one of her snipers and left to bleed to death, as he's left crying, in one of Roanapur's parks as Balalaika used herself as bait much to Boris' displeasure, while Gretel manages to escape and eventually boards the ''Black Lagoon'' of her own volition. Due to Rock's kindness she takes a genuine liking to him. However, just as Gretel disembarks she is gunned down by the get away man Dutch contacted, who was bribed by Hotel Moscow. Though initially shocked by her sudden death, Rock is glad that now she and her brother could rest in peace.

The characters' names are taken from the German fairy tale, ''[[Hänsel and Gretel]]''. Many of the series' characters compare them to a similar pair of disturbed, sadistic twins from the American film ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]''. In the manga, the song sung by Gretel to Rock on the Black Lagoon is called &quot;Midnight, the Stars, and You&quot;, the song used in the ending credits to ''The Shining''. In the anime, she sings &quot;The World of Midnight&quot;, made for the anime and sung by Minako Obata.
Despite only being in three episodes they have a considerably large fanbase.

===Greenback Jane===
;{{anime voices|[[Miki Nagasawa]]|[[Kelly Sheridan]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Janet Bhai'''|ジャネット・バーイー|Janetto Bāī}}, also known as {{nihongo|'''Greenback Jane'''|ジェーン|Jēn}}, is a professional money [[counterfeit]]er and ''[[Hacker (computer security)|hacker]]'' from [[India]]. She served as the leader for her project team, which was spread around the world but was connected thanks to the internet, and is quite knowledgeable on the details of the [[dollar bill]]. Coincidentally, she falls in love with Benny after he displays his hacking skills. Janet currently seems to be having an [[internet romance]] with Benny. One of the running gags of her story arc is her clumsiness and poor luck, which usually result in her being subject to a [[pantyshot]].  After the Lovelace incident, Janet returns to Roanapur searching out Benny and the team. She, with help of her counterfeiting group, hacks a server of the &quot;Rainbach AG&quot; Corporation and makes a scapegoat of a [[People's Liberation Army|PLA spy]]. Jane is apparently a [[nymphomaniac]], though Benny calls it &quot;a bit broad-minded as far as sex goes&quot;. Revy replies that &quot;if that's &quot;a bit&quot;, then Death Valley is a sand pit in a park&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Chapter 81, Page 5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russell===
;{{anime voices|[[Masaki Terasoma]]|[[Brian Dobson]]}}
{{nihongo|'''&quot;Groovy Guy&quot; Russell'''|“グルーヴィ・ガイ”・ラッセル|&quot;Gurūvi Gai&quot; Rasseru}} is a middle-aged [[United States|American]] man who works for the Florida crime syndicate that's tracking Jane. He is quite distinguishable, since he dresses like a [[cowboy]]: he has the trademark [[cowboy hat|hat]], [[cowboy boots|boots]] with spurs, a [[revolver]] at the hip, [[bandolier]] belt, tan shirt and jeans. He is not taken serious by the other bounty hunters because he is an outsider. Even Shenhua says, &quot;Cowboy, this no Florida&quot;, meaning that he is in over his head.  However, his skills are shown to be more than everyone thought, when he is the last bounty hunter left in the hunt for Jane and he duels Eda onboard the Lagoon. It is then later revealed that he and Eda have met previously in the United States, but Eda says they have never met. Shortly before killing him, she confesses to him to be from the CIA.

===Vasili Laptev===
;{{anime voices|Toshihiko Kojima|[[Ted Cole]]}}
{{nihongo|'''Vasili Laptev'''|ヴァシリ・ラプチェフ|Vashiri Rapuchefu}} is the boss of a branch of the Russian mafia based in Tokyo. A former [[KGB]] officer, Laptev had many difficulties operating in Japan due to his status as a ''[[gaijin]]'' (foreigner). Considered distasteful and incompetent by Balalaika, he appeared to lose his standing with his peers back in Russia and this was reflected in his arrogant personality, since he did not speak Japanese despite being based in Japan. Laptev's detachment is slaughtered single-handedly by Ginji when the fallout between Hotel Moscow and the Washimine-gumi begins.

===Masami Kousa===
;{{anime voices|Masahiro Tanaka|[[Andrew Kavadas]]}}
Head of Kousa Council. In past both Washimine and Kousa Yakuza's were allies as Yukio's father and Masami's &quot;brother&quot; were blood brothers. When they both died and Masami took over, any relationship the two groups had were gone and the Kousa's mistreated the Washime group badly to the point that Masami wouldn't recognize Yukio as the heir to the Washimine group and wanted someone in his group to take over. His mistreatment led the Washime group to call Hotel Moscow to weaken them. In the end of Fujiyama Gangsters arc, Masami was about to form an alliance with Hotel Moscow when Balalaika, after talking with Rock, decided to kill him and his lieutenants cited she wouldn't want to work with a group with such poor merchandise.

===Maki===
;{{anime voices|[[Shiho Kawaragi]]|[[Ashleigh Ball]]}}
'''Maki''' is a female high school junior and goes to the same high school as her friend, Yukio Washimine. Maki seems to be a symbolic representative of the typical Japanese high school girl who is interested in skin-care, has a part-time job, reads [[light novel]]s, and has poor school grades.

===Feng Yifei/Li Xinlin===
Li Xinlin is a Chinese hacker in the People's Liberation Army. She is assigned to infiltrate Greenback Jane's group under the alias Feng Yifei. However, Jane and the other hacker are aware of this and use her to tap into in the PLA's computers. When this is discovered, Li's superiors believed she was a traitor and put a contract on her life to Roanapur-based mercenaries.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{-}}{{Black Lagoon}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Black Lagoon Characters}}
[[Category:Black Lagoon]]
[[Category:Lists of anime and manga characters|Black Lagoon]]

[[fr:Personnages de Black Lagoon]]
[[no:Liste over mindre rollefigurer i Black Lagoon]]
[[ru:Список персонажей аниме и манги «Пираты „Чёрной лагуны“»]]
[[sq:Lista e personazheve të Black Lagoon]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
