<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="81553" ns="0" title="Teotihuacan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{About|the archaeological site|the town and municipality|Teotihuacán de Arista}}
{{Coord|19|41|33|N|98|50|37.68|W|type:landmark_scale:20000|display=title}}
{{Infobox World Heritage Site
| WHS         = Pre-Hispanic City of Teotihuacan
| Image       = [[Image:View from Pyramide de la luna.jpg|300px]]
| imagecaption= View of the Avenue of the Dead and the [[Pyramid of the Sun]], from the [[Pyramid of the Moon]]
| State Party = [[Mexico]]
| Type        = Cultural
| Criteria    = I, II, III, IV, VI
| ID          = 414
| Region      = [[List of World Heritage Sites in the Americas|North America]]
| Year        = 1987
| Session     = 11th
| Link        = http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/414
}}
[[Image:Piramide de la Luna 072006.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The view from the [[Pyramid of the Sun]]]]

'''Teotihuacan''' &amp;ndash; also written '''''Teotihuacán''''', with a [[Spanish orthography|Spanish orthographic accent]] on the last syllable &amp;ndash; is an enormous [[archaeology|archaeological]] site in the [[Valley of Mexico|Basin of Mexico]], just 30 miles northeast of Mexico City, containing some of the largest [[Mesoamerican pyramid|pyramidal structures]] built in the [[pre-Columbian]] [[Americas]]. Apart from the pyramidal structures, Teotihuacan is also known for its large residential complexes, the Avenue of the Dead, and numerous colorful, well-preserved [[mural]]s. Additionally, Teotihuacan produced a thin orange pottery style that spread through Mesoamerica.&lt;ref&gt;Ancient Mexico and Central America&lt;/ref&gt;

The city is thought to have been established around 100 BCE and continued to be built until about 250 CE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Teotihuacan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Teotihuacan|url=http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/teot/hd_teot.htm|work=Heilbrunn Timeline of Art History|publisher=Department of Arts of Africa, Oceania, and the Americas, The Metropolitan Museum of Art   Source: Teotihuacan {{!}} Thematic Essay | Heilbrunn Timeline of Art History | The Metropolitan Museum of Art}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city may have lasted until sometime between the 7th and 8th centuries CE. At its zenith, perhaps in the first half of the [[1st millennium]] CE, Teotihuacan was the largest city in  the pre-Columbian Americas.  At this time it may have had more than 200,000 inhabitants, placing it among the largest cities of the world in this period.  Teotihuacan was even home to multi-floor apartment compounds built to accommodate this large population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Teotihuacan&quot;/&gt; The civilization and cultural complex associated with the site is also referred to as Teotihuacan or Teotihuacano.  

Although it is a subject of debate whether Teotihuacan was the center of a state empire, its influence throughout [[Mesoamerica]] is well documented; evidence of Teotihuacano presence can be seen at numerous sites in [[Veracruz]] and the [[Geography of Mesoamerica#Maya Region|Maya region]]. The Aztecs may have been influenced by this city. The ethnicity of the inhabitants of Teotihuacan is also a subject of debate.  Possible candidates are the [[Nahua peoples|Nahua]], [[Otomi people|Otomi]] or [[Totonac]] ethnic groups.  Scholars have also suggested that Teotihuacan was a multiethnic state.

The city and the archaeological site are located in what is now the [[San Juan Teotihuacán]] [[Municipalities of Mexico|municipality]] in the [[Mexico (state)|State of México]], Mexico, approximately {{convert|40|km|mi}} [http://maps.google.com/?ie=UTF8&amp;ll=19.692173,-98.844337&amp;spn=0.032648,0.071926&amp;t=h&amp;z=15 northeast] of [[Mexico City]].  The site covers a total surface area of 83 km² and was designated a [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage Site]] in 1987.  It is the most visited archaeological site in Mexico.

==Name==

The name ''Teōtīhuacān'' was given by the [[Classical Nahuatl language|Nahuatl]]-speaking [[Aztec]] centuries after the fall of the city.  The term has been [[Gloss (transliteration)|glossed]] as &quot;birthplace of the gods&quot;, reflecting [[Nahua peoples|Nahua]] creation myths that were said to occur in Teotihuacan. Nahuatl scholar [[Thelma D. Sullivan]] interprets the name as &quot;place of those who have the road of the gods.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Millon (1993, p.34)&lt;/ref&gt; 
The name is pronounced {{IPA-nah|te.oːtiːˈwakaːn}} in [[Nahuatl]], with the accent on the syllable ''wa''.  By normal Nahuatl orthographic conventions, a written accent would not appear in that position.  Both this pronunciation and Spanish {{IPA-es|te.otiwaˈkan}} are used, and both spellings appear in this article. [[Image:SunPyramid.jpg|right|thumb|400px|Sun Pyramid and the Teotihuacán Diorama at the Teotihuacán Museum.]] 

The original name of the city is unknown, but it appears in [[Maya script|hieroglyphic texts]] from the Maya region as ''puh'', or &quot;Place of Reeds&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mathews and Schele (1997, p.39)&lt;/ref&gt; This suggests that the Maya of the [[Mesoamerican chronology#Classic Era|Classic]] period understood Teotihuacan as a Place of Reeds similar to other [[Mesoamerican chronology#Postclassic Era|Postclassic]] Central Mexican settlements that took the name ''[[Tollan]]'', such as [[Tula, Hidalgo|Tula-Hidalgo]] and [[Cholula (Mesoamerican site)|Cholula]].  

This naming convention led to much confusion in the early 20th century, as scholars debated whether Teotihuacan or Tula-Hidalgo was the Tollan described by 16th–century chronicles.  It now seems clear that ''Tollan'' may be understood as a generic Nahua term applied to any large settlement.  In the Mesoamerican concept of urbanism, ''Tollan'' and other language equivalents serve as a [[metaphor]], linking the bundles of reeds and rushes that formed part of the [[Lake|lacustrine]] environment of the [[Valley of Mexico]] and the large gathering of people in a city.&lt;ref&gt;Miller and Taube (1993, p.170)&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[Image:Classic sites 1.svg|thumb|right|255px|Teotihuacan and other important Classic Era settlements]]

===Origins and foundation===
The early history of Teotihuacan is quite mysterious, and the origin of its founders is debated. For many years, archaeologists believed it was built by the [[Toltec]]. This belief was based on colonial period texts, such as the [[Florentine Codex]], which attributed the site to the Toltecs.  However, the Nahuatl word &quot;Toltec&quot; generally means &quot;craftsman of the highest level&quot; and may not always refer to the Toltec civilization centered at [[Tula, Hidalgo]].  Since Toltec civilization flourished centuries after Teotihuacan, the people could not have been the city's founders. 

In the Late Formative period, a number of urban centers arose in central Mexico. The most prominent of these appears to have been [[Cuicuilco]], on the southern shore of [[Lake Texcoco]].  Scholars have speculated that the eruption of the [[Xitle]] volcano may have prompted a mass emigration out of the central valley and into the Teotihuacan valley. These settlers may have founded and/or accelerated the growth of Teotihuacan. 

Other scholars have put forth the [[Totonac]] people as the founders of Teotihuacan.  There is evidence that at least some of the people living in Teotihuacan came from areas influenced by the Teotihuacano civilization, including the [[Zapotec civilization|Zapotec]], [[Mixtec]] and [[Maya civilization|Maya]] peoples.  The culture and architecture of Teotihuacan was influenced by the [[Olmec]] people, who are considered to be the &quot;mother civilization&quot; of Mesoamerica.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} 

The earliest buildings at Teotihuacan date to about 200 BCE.  The largest pyramid, the [[Pyramid of the Sun]], was completed by 100 CE.&lt;ref&gt;Millon (1993, p.24)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Zenith===
The city reached its peak in 450 CE, when it was the center of a powerful culture whose influence extended through much of the Mesoamerican region. At its peak, the city covered over 30&amp;nbsp;km² (over 11½ square miles), and probably housed a population of over 150,000 people, possibly as many as 250,000.&lt;ref&gt;Malmström (1978, p.105) gives an estimate of 50,000 to 200,000 inhabitants.  Coe ''et al.'' (1986) says it &quot;might lie between 125,000 and 250,000.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Various districts in the city housed people from across the Teotihuacano region of influence, which spread south as far as [[Guatemala]].  Notably absent from the city are fortifications and military structures. 


[[Image:MW-Teotihuacan8.jpg|thumb|left|Platform along the Avenue of the Dead showing the ''[[talud-tablero]]'' architectural style]]
[[File:Facade of the Temple of the Feathered Serpent (Teotihuacán).jpg|thumb|Restored partion of Teotihucan architecture showing the typical Mesoamerican use of red paint complemented on gold and jade decoration upon marble and granite.]]

The nature of political and cultural interactions between Teotihuacan and the centers of the Maya region (as well as elsewhere in Mesoamerica) has been a long-standing and significant area for debate.  Substantial exchange and interaction occurred over the centuries from the Terminal Preclassic to the Mid-Classic period.  &quot;Teotihuacan-inspired ideologies&quot; and motifs persisted at Maya centers into the Late Classic, long after Teotihuacan itself had declined.&lt;ref&gt;Braswell (2003, p.7)&lt;/ref&gt;  However, scholars debate the extent and degree of Teotihuacano influence.  Some believe that it had direct and militaristic dominance; others that adoption of &quot;foreign&quot; traits was part of a selective, conscious and bi-directional [[cultural diffusion]].  New discoveries have suggested that Teotihuacan was not much different in its interactions with other centers from the later empires, such as the Toltec and Aztec.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/ngm/0610/feature5/index.html|title=Mexico's Pyramid of Death|work=[[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]]|year=2006|accessdate=2008-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2004/12/041203084345.htm|title=Sacrificial Burial Deepens Mystery At Teotihuacan, But Confirms The City's Militarism|publisher=[[ScienceDaily]]|year=2004|accessdate=2008-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that Teotihuacan had a major influence on the Preclassic and Classic Maya, most likely by conquering several Maya centers and regions, including Tikal and the region of Peten, and influencing Maya culture. 

Architectural styles prominent at Teotihuacan are found widely dispersed at a number of distant Mesoamerican sites, which some researchers have interpreted as evidence for Teotihuacan's far-reaching interactions and political or militaristic dominance.&lt;ref&gt;See for example Cheek (1977, ''passim.''), who argues that much of Teotihuacan's influence stems from direct militaristic conquest.&lt;/ref&gt;  A style particularly associated with Teotihuacan is known as ''[[talud-tablero]]'', in which an inwards-sloping external side of a structure (''talud'') is surmounted by a rectangular panel (''tablero'').  Variants of the generic style are found in a number of Maya region sites, including [[Tikal]], [[Kaminaljuyu]], [[Copan]], [[Becan]], and [[Oxkintok]], and particularly in the [[Petén Basin]] and the central Guatemalan highlands.&lt;ref&gt;See Laporte (2003, p.205); Varela Torrecilla and Braswell (2003, p.261).&lt;/ref&gt;  The ''talud-tablero'' style pre-dates its earliest appearance at Teotihuacan in the Early Classic period; it appears to have originated in the [[Tlaxcala-Puebla]] region during the Preclassic.&lt;ref&gt;Braswell (2003, p.11)&lt;/ref&gt;  Analyses have traced the development into local variants of the ''talud-tablero'' style at sites such as Tikal, where its use precedes the 5th-century appearance of iconographic motifs shared with Teotihuacan.  The ''talud-tablero'' style disseminated through Mesoamerica generally from the end of the Preclassic period, and not specifically, or only, via Teotihuacano influence.  It is unclear how or from where the style spread into the Maya region.&lt;ref&gt;Braswell (2003, p.11); for the analysis at Tikal, see Laporte (2003, pp.200&amp;ndash;205)&lt;/ref&gt;

The city was a center of industry, home to many potters, jewelers and craftsmen. Teotihuacan is known for producing a great number of [[obsidian]] artifacts.  No ancient Teotihuacano non-[[ideogram|ideographic]] texts are known to exist (or known to have existed).  Inscriptions from Maya cities show that Teotihuacan nobility traveled to, and perhaps conquered, local rulers as far away as [[Honduras]].  [[Maya script|Maya inscriptions]] note an individual nicknamed by scholars as &quot;[[Spearthrower Owl]]&quot;, apparently ruler of Teotihuacan, who reigned for over 60 years and installed his relatives as rulers of [[Tikal]] and [[Uaxactun]] in [[Guatemala]].  

[[Image:Teotihuacan mask Branly 70-1999-12-1.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Stone mask discovered at Teotihuacan, 3rd to 7th century CE.]]

Scholars have based interpretations about the culture at Teotihuacan on archaeology, the murals that adorn the site (and others, like the [[Wagner Murals]], found in private collections), and hieroglyphic inscriptions made by the [[Maya civilization|Maya]] describing their encounters with Teotihuacano conquerors.  The creation of murals, perhaps tens of thousands of murals, reached its height between 450 and 650 CE.  The painters' artistry was unrivaled in Mesoamerica.  It has been compared with those of painters in [[Renaissance]] [[Florence, Italy]].&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Collapse===
Scholars had thought that invaders attacked the city in the 7th or 8th century, sacking and burning it. More recent evidence, however, seems to indicate that the burning was limited to the structures and dwellings associated primarily with the [[elite]] class.  Some  think this suggests that the burning was from an internal uprising.  They say the invasion theory is flawed because early archaeological work on the city was focused exclusively on the palaces and temples, places used by the elites.  Because all of these sites showed burning, archaeologists concluded that the whole city was burned. Instead, it is now known that the destruction was centered on major civic structures along the Avenue of the Dead.  Some statues seem to have been destroyed in a methodical way, with their fragments dispersed. 

Evidence for population decline beginning around the 6th century lends some support to the internal unrest hypothesis.  The decline of Teotihuacan has been correlated to lengthy [[droughts]] related to the [[climate changes of 535-536]] CE.  This theory of ecological decline is supported by archaeological remains that show a rise in the percentage of juvenile skeletons with evidence of [[malnutrition]] during the 6th century.  This finding does not conflict with either of the above theories, since both increased warfare and internal unrest can also be effects of a general period of drought and famine.&lt;ref&gt;Kaufman (2001, p.4)&lt;/ref&gt;  Other nearby centers such as [[Cholula (Mesoamerican site)|Cholula]], [[Xochicalco]], and [[Cacaxtla]] competed to fill the power void left by Teotihuacan's decline.  They may have aligned themselves against Teotihuacan to reduce its influence and power.  The art and architecture at these sites emulates Teotihuacan forms, but also demonstrates an eclectic mix of motifs and iconography from other parts of Mesoamerica, particularly the Maya region.

==Teotihuacan culture==
===Ethnicity===
Archaeological evidence suggests that Teotihuacan was a multi-ethnic city, with distinct quarters occupied by [[Otomi people|Otomi]], [[Zapotec civilization|Zapotec]], [[Mixtec]], [[Maya civilization|Maya]] and [[Nahua peoples]].  The [[Totonac]]s have always maintained that they were the ones who built it.  The Aztecs repeated that story, but it has not been corroborated by archaeological findings. [[Image:QuetzalTeotihuacan.JPG|right|thumb|300px|A detail found on the Quetzalcóatl Pyramid on the Ciudadela, now displayed at the Teotihuacán Museum.]]   

In 2001, [[Terrence Kaufman]] presented linguistic evidence suggesting that an important ethnic group in Teotihuacan was of [[Totonacan languages|Totonacan]] and/or [[Mixe–Zoquean languages|Mixe–Zoquean]] linguistic affiliation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.albany.edu/anthro/maldp/Nawa.pdf Terrence Kaufman, &quot;Nawa linguistic prehistory&quot;], SUNY Albany&lt;/ref&gt;  He uses this to explain general influences from Totonacan and Mixe–Zoquean languages in many other [[Mesoamerican languages]], whose people did not have any known history of contact with either of the above-mentioned groups. Other scholars maintain that the largest population group must have been of Otomi ethnicity, because the Otomi language is known to have been spoken in the area around Teotihuacan both before and after the classic period and not during the midddle period.&lt;ref&gt;* {{cite journal |author={{aut|Wright Carr, David Charles}} |year=2005 |title=El papel de los otomies en las culturas del altiplano central 5000 a.C - 1650 d.C|journal=[[Arqueología mexicana]] |volume=XIII |issue=73 |pages=19}} {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religion===
The religion of Teotihuacan was similar to that of other Mesoamerican cultures. Many of the same gods were worshiped, including the [[Feathered Serpent]] (the Aztecs' ''[[Quetzalcoatl]]'') and Rain God (the Aztecs' ''[[Tlaloc]]''.)&lt;ref&gt;Coe (1994), p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; The dominant civic architecture is the pyramid.  Politics were based on the state religion; religious leaders were the political leaders.&lt;ref&gt;Sugiyama: 111&lt;/ref&gt;

Teotihuacanos practiced [[human sacrifice]]: human bodies and animal sacrifices have been found during excavations of the pyramids at Teotihuacan.    Scholars believe that the people offered human sacrifices as part of a dedication when buildings were expanded or constructed.  The victims were probably enemy warriors captured in battle and brought to the city for ritual sacrifice to ensure the city could prosper.&lt;ref&gt;Coe (1994), p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt;  Some men were decapitated, some had their hearts removed, others were killed by being hit several times over the head, and some were  buried alive.  Animals that were considered sacred and represented mythical powers and military were also buried alive, imprisoned in cages: cougars, a wolf, eagles, a falcon, an owl, and even venomous snakes.&lt;ref&gt;Sugiyama: 109, 111&lt;/ref&gt;

===Residency=== 
Teotihuacan was a mix of residential and work areas.  Elite homes were usually compounds which housed multiple elite families (one home was found that was capable of housing 60-100 families). Elite residences were typically made of plaster, each wall in every section elaborately decorated with murals. These compounds or apartment complexes were typically found within the city center.
Different sections of the city housed particular ethnic groups and immigrants. These areas are called barrios, meaning neighborhoods. Typically, these sections of the city were speaking multiple languages.

==Archaeological site==
Knowledge of the huge [[ruins]] of Teotihuacan was never completely lost. After the fall of the city, various squatters lived on the site. During Aztec times, the city was a place of pilgrimage and identified with the myth of Tollan, the place where the sun was created. Teotihuacan astonished the Spanish ''[[conquistador]]es'' during the post-conquest era.  Today Teotihuacan is one of the most noted archaeological attractions in Mexico.

===Excavations and investigations===
In the late 17th century [[Carlos de Sigüenza y Góngora]] (1645–1700) did some excavations around the Pyramid of the Sun.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.milenio.com/node/501242 Tunnel under Pyramid of the Feathered Serpent under exploration in 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
Minor archaeological excavations were conducted in the 19th century.  In 1905 archaeologist [[Leopoldo Batres]] ([[:es:Leopoldo Batres|es:Leopoldo Batres]]) led a major project of excavation and restoration.  The Pyramid of the Sun was restored to celebrate the centennial of [[Mexican War of Independence]] in 1910. Excavations at the ''Ciudadela'' were carried out in the 1920s, supervised by [[Manuel Gamio]].  Other sections of the site were excavated in the 1940s and 50s.  The first site-wide project of restoration and excavation was carried out by [[INAH]] from 1960–65 and supervised by [[Jorge R. Acosta|Jorge Acosta]].  This undertaking had the goals of clearing the Avenue of the Dead, consolidating the structures facing it, and excavating the Palace of ''[[Quetzalpapalotl]]''.

During the installation of a &quot;sound and light&quot; show in 1971, workers discovered the entrance to a tunnel and cave system underneath the Pyramid of the Sun.&lt;ref&gt;Heyden (1975, p.131)&lt;/ref&gt;  Although scholars long thought it to be a natural cave, more recent examinations have established the tunnel was entirely manmade.&lt;ref&gt;Šprajc (2000, p.410)&lt;/ref&gt;  The interior of Pyramid of the Sun has never been fully excavated.  

In 1980-1982, another major program of excavation and restoration was carried out at the Pyramid of the Feathered Serpent and the Avenue of the Dead complex.  Most recently{{when|date=May 2011}}, a series of excavations at the Pyramid of the Moon have greatly expanded evidence of cultural practices.

[[File:Teotihuacancityplan.png|thumb|300px|left|The layout of the city]]

===Site layout===
The city's broad central [[Avenue (landscape)|avenue]], called &quot;Avenue of the Dead&quot; (a translation from its Nahuatl name ''Miccoatli''), is flanked by impressive ceremonial architecture, including the immense [[Pyramid of the Sun]] (second largest in the [[New World]] after the [[Great Pyramid of Cholula]]) and the [[Pyramid of the Moon]].  Along the Avenue of the Dead are many smaller talud-tablero platforms.  The Aztecs believed they were tombs, inspiring the name of the avenue.  Now scholars have established these were ceremonial platforms that were topped with temples.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

Further down the Avenue of the Dead is the area known as the Citadel, containing the ruined [[Temple of the Feathered Serpent]].  This area was a large plaza surrounded by temples that formed the religious and political center of the city.  The name &quot;Citadel&quot; was given to it by the Spanish, who believed it was a fort.  Most of the common people lived in large apartment buildings spread across the city.  Many of the buildings contained workshops where artisans produced pottery and other goods.

The geographical layout of Teotihuacan is a good example of the [[Mesoamerican architecture|Mesoamerican tradition of planning cities]], settlements and buildings as a representation of the view of the Universe.  Its urban grid is aligned to precisely 15.5º east of North.  One theory says this is due to the fact that the sun rose at that same angle during the same summer day each year.  Settlers used the alignment to calibrate their sense of time or as a marker for planting crops or performing certain rituals.  Another theory is that there are numerous ancient sites in Mesoamerica that seem to be oriented with the tallest mountain in their given area.  This appears to be the case at Teotihuacan, although the mountain to which it is oriented is not visible from within the Teotihuacan complex due to a closer mountain ridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;TeotihuacanHistory&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ourworldwonders.com/Teotihuacan/History.htm|title=Teotihuacan History}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Pecked-cross circles throughout the city and in the surrounding regions indicate how the people managed to maintain the urban grid over long distances.  It also enabled them to orient the Pyramids to the distant mountain that was out of sight.

The Ciudadela was completed during the Miccaotli phase and the Pyramid of the Sun underwent a complex series of additions and renovations. The Great Compound was constructed across the Avenue of the Dead, west of Ciudadela. This was probably the city’s marketplace. The existence of a large market in an urban center of this size is strong evidence of state organization. Teotihuacan was by now simply too large and too complex to have been politically viable as a chiefdom.

The Ciudadela is a great enclosed compound capable of holding 100,000 people. About 700,000 cubic meters (yards) of material was used to construct its buildings. Its central feature is the Temple of Quetzalcoatl, which was flanked by elite apartments. The entire compound was designed to overwhelm visitors.

== Threat from development ==
The archaeological park of Teotihuacan is under threat from development pressures.  In 2004, the governor of [[Mexico state]], [[Arturo Montiel]], gave permission for [[Wal-Mart]] to build a large store in the third archaeological zone of the park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Ross, John|date=February 27 - March 1, 2009|title=The World's Most Remarkable Buildings Under Threat|work=[[Counterpunch.org]] Weekend Edition|url=http://www.counterpunch.org/ross02272009.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[Counterpunch.org]], &quot;[P]riceless artifacts uncovered during store construction were reportedly trucked off to a local dump and workers fired when they revealed the carnage to the press.&quot;{{citequote}}
{{wide image|CiudadelaTeotihuacan.jpg|900px|The Ciudadela, on the opposite side from the Pyramid of the Moon}}

More recently{{when|date=May 2011}}, Teotihuacan has become the center of controversy over Resplandor Teotihuacano,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.resplandorteotihuacano.com/&lt;/ref&gt; a proposed massive light and sound spectacular, which, according to [[Statesman.com]] &quot;includes large metallic structures, 2,500 lights and three kilometers of cables.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Schwartz, Jeremy|date=January 8, 2009|title=Light and sound show threatens to damage Teotihuacan pyramids|work=[[Statesman.com]]|url=http://www.statesman.com/blogs/content/sharedgen/blogs/austin/mexico/entries/2009/01/08/light_and_sound_show_threatens.html?cxntfid=blogs_uncovering_mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{wide image|Teotihuacan-360degree-Panorama.jpg|900px|360° View of the Avenue of the Dead, the [[Pyramid of the Sun]] and the [[Pyramid of the Moon]]}}
{{wide image|AvenueoftheDeadTeotihuacan.jpg|900px|Panoramic view from the summit of the [[Pyramid of the Sun]], with the [[Pyramid of the Moon]] on the far right}}

==See also==
* [[Spring equinox in Teotihuacán]]
* [[Balberta]], a Teotihuacan trading partner on the Pacific Coast of Guatemala
* [[Cerro de la Estrella]], a large Teotihuacano-styled pyramid in what is now part of Mexico City
* [[List of archaeoastronomical sites by country]]
* [[List of megalithic sites]]
* [[List of Mesoamerican pyramids]]
* [[Montana (Mesoamerican site)]], a Teotihuacan colony on the Pacific Coast of Guatemala

==Gallery==
&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=3&gt; 
Image:Teonate.JPG|Front view of the [[Pyramid of the Sun]]
Image:Piramide del Sol 072006.JPG|Another view of the Pyramid of the Sun
Image:Pyramid of the sun teotihuacan with crowd.jpg|Left side view of the Pyramid of the Sun
Image:Teotihuacan.jpg
Image:TeotihuacanModel.JPG|Model of the Teotihuacan site located at [[National Museum of Anthropology]] in Mexico City.
Image:Jaguar Mural, Teotihuacan.jpg|Jaguar painting
Image:Teotihuacan_mask_Louvre_MH_78-1-187.jpg|Marble mask, 3rd - 7th century
Image:Teotimask2.jpg|Serpentine mask, 3rd-6th century
Image:teotihuacanmask.jpg|Turquoise mask pendent, 3rd-6th
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==References==
===Notes===
{{reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin|indent=yes}}&lt;!--If indent param. is used,   Pls use a colon (:) instead of asterisk (*) for bullet markers in the references list --&gt;
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Berrin, Kathleen}} |coauthors=and {{aut|Esther Pasztory}} |year=1993 |title=Teotihuacan: Art from the City of the Gods |location=New York |publisher=Thames and Hudson|isbn=0-500-23653-4 |oclc=28423003}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Braswell, Geoffrey E.}} |year=2003 |chapter=Introduction: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |title=The Maya and Teotihuacan: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |editor=Geoffrey E. Braswell (Ed.) |location=Austin |publisher=University of Texas Press |pages=1&amp;ndash;44|isbn=0-292-70587-5 |oclc=49936017}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Brown, Dale M.}} (ed.) |year=1992 |title=Aztecs: Reign of Blood and Splendor |series=Lost Civilizations series|location=Alexandria, VA |publisher=Time-Life Books |isbn=0-809-49854-5 |oclc=24848419}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Cheek, Charles D.}} |year=1977 |chapter=Excavations at the Palangana and the Acropolis, Kaminaljuyu |title=Teotihuacan and Kaminaljuyu: a Study in Prehistoric Culture Contact |editor=William T. Sanders and Joseph W. Michels (Eds.) |location=University Park |publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press |pages=1&amp;ndash;204|isbn=0271005297 |oclc=3327234}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Coe, Michael D.}} |authorlink=Michael D. Coe |coauthors=and {{aut|Rex Koontz}} |year=1994 |origyear=1962 |title=Mexico: From the Olmecs to the Aztecs |location=New York |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |isbn=0-500-27722-2 |oclc=50131575}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Coe, Michael D.}} |authorlink=Michael D. Coe |coauthors={{aut|Dean Snow}} and {{aut|Elizabeth Benson}} |year=1986 |title=Atlas of Ancient America |publisher=Facts on File |location=New York |isbn=0-816-01199-0}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Cowgill, George L.}} |authorlink=George Cowgill |year=1992 |chapter=Teotihuacan Glyphs and Imagery in the Light of Some Early Colonial Texts |title=Art, Ideology, and the City of Teotihuacan: A Symposium at Dumbarton Oaks, 8th and 9th October 1988 |editor=[[Janet Catherine Berlo]] (ed.) |location=Washington, DC |publisher=[[Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection]] |pages=231–246 |isbn=0-88402-205-6 |oclc=25547129}}
: {{cite journal |author={{aut|Cowgill, George}} |authorlink=George Cowgill |year=1997 |date= |title=State and Society at Teotihuacan, Mexico |journal=[[Annual Review of Anthropology]] |url= |format=[[PDF]] online reproduction |volume=26 |issue=1 |pages=129–161|location=Palo Alto, CA |publisher=Annual Reviews Inc |doi=10.1146/annurev.anthro.26.1.129 |oclc=202300854}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Davies, Nigel}} |year=1982 |title=The Ancient Kingdoms of Mexico|publisher=Penguin Books|location=England|isbn=0-14-013587-1}}
: {{cite journal |author={{aut|Heyden, Doris}} |authorlink=Doris Heyden|title=An Interpretation of the Cave underneath the Pyramid of the Sun in Teotihuacan, Mexico|journal=[[American Antiquity]]|year=1975|coauthors=|volume=40|issue=2 |location=Menasha, WI|publisher=[[Society for American Archaeology]] |doi= 10.2307/279609 |oclc=1479302|pages=131–147|id= |format=|jstor=279609 }}
: {{cite web |author={{aut|Kaufman, Terrence}} |authorlink=Terrence Kaufman |year=2001 |title=Nawa linguistic prehistory |url=http://www.albany.edu/anthro/maldp/papers.htm |publisher=Mesoamerican Language Documentation Project}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Laporte, Juan Pedro}} |year=2003 |chapter=Architectural Aspects of Interaction Between Tikal and Teotihuacan during the Early Classic Period |title=The Maya and Teotihuacan: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |editor=Geoffrey E. Braswell (Ed.) |location=Austin |publisher=University of Texas Press |pages=199&amp;ndash;216|isbn=0-292-70587-5 |oclc=49936017}}
: {{cite journal |author={{aut|Malmström, Vincent H.}} |year=1978 |title=Architecture, Astronomy, and Calendrics in Pre-Columbian Mesoamerica |journal=Journal for the History of Astronomy |volume=9 |pages=105–116 |url=http://www.dartmouth.edu/~izapa/M-15.pdf |format=[[PDF]] Reprinted |accessdate=2007-01-17}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Miller, Mary}} |authorlink=Mary Miller |coauthors=and {{aut|[[Karl Taube]]}} |year=1993 |title=The Gods and Symbols of Ancient Mexico and the Maya: An Illustrated Dictionary of Mesoamerican Religion |publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson |location=London |isbn=0-500-05068-6 |oclc=27667317}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Millon, René}} |year=1993 |chapter=The Place Where Time Began: An Archaeologist's Interpretation of What Happened in Teotihuacan History |title=Teotihuacan: Art from the City of the Gods |editor=Berrin, Kathleen and Esther Pasztory (Eds.) |location=New York |publisher=Thames and Hudson|pages=16&amp;ndash;43|isbn=0-500-23653-4 |oclc=28423003}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Schele, Linda}} |authorlink=Linda Schele |coauthors=and {{aut|[[Peter Mathews (archaeologist)|Peter Mathews]]}} |year=1998 |title=The Code of Kings: The Language of Seven Sacred Maya Temples and Tombs |publisher=[[Charles Scribner's Sons|Scribner]] |location=New York  |pages= |isbn=0-684-80106-X |oclc=37819972}}
:Séjourné, Laurette
:{{cite book |author={{aut|Sugiyama, Saburo}}|year=2003 |title=Governance and Polity at Classic Teotihuacan; in Julia Ann Hendon, Rosemary A. Joyce, &quot;Mesoamerican archaeology&quot; | publisher=Wiley-Blackwell}}
:Séjourné, Laurette,''Un Palacio en la ciudad de los dioses, Teotihuacán'', Mexico, Instituto nacional de antropología e historia, 1959.
:Séjourné, Laurette,''El Universo de Quetzalcóatl'', Fondo de Cultura Económica, 1962.
:Séjourné, Laurette, ''Arqueología de Teotihuacán, la cerámica'', Fondo de Cultura Económica, 1966. 
:Séjourné, Laurette,''Teotihuacan, métropole de l'Amérique'', Paris, F. Maspero, 1969.
: {{cite journal |author={{aut|Šprajc, Ivan}} |year=2000|title=Astronomical Alignments at Teotihuacan, Mexico|journal=[[Latin American Antiquity]]|volume=11|issue=4 |location=Washington, DC |publisher=[[Society for American Archaeology]] |doi= 10.2307/972004 |pages=403&amp;ndash;415|id= |format= |last2=Sprajc |first2=Ivan|jstor=972004 }}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Taube, Karl A.}} |authorlink=Karl Taube |year=2000 |title=The Writing System of Ancient Teotihuacan |url=http://www.mesoweb.com/bearc/caa/01.html |format=[[PDF]] |series=Ancient America series #1|location=Barnardsville, NC |publisher=Center for Ancient American Studies |oclc=44992821}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Varela Torrecilla, Carmen}} |coauthors=and {{aut|Geoffrey E. Braswell}} |year=2003 |chapter=Teotihuacan and Oxkintok: New Perspectives from Yucatán |title=The Maya and Teotihuacan: Reinterpreting Early Classic Interaction |editor=Geoffrey E. Braswell (Ed.) |location=Austin |publisher=University of Texas Press |pages=249&amp;ndash;272|isbn=0-292-70587-5 |oclc=49936017}}
: {{cite book |author={{aut|Weaver, Muriel Porter}} | year = 1993 | title = The Aztecs, Maya, and Their Predecessors: Archaeology of Mesoamerica | edition = 3rd | publisher = Academic Press | location = San Diego | isbn =0-012-63999-0}}
: {{cite journal |author={{aut|Webmoor, Timothy}} |year=2007 |title=Reconfiguring the Archaeological Sensibility: Mediating Heritage at Teotihuacan, Mexico |url=http://humanitieslab.stanford.edu/Teotihuacan/180 |format=online digital publication, in ''Symmetrical Archaeology'' [2005–, collaboratory directors T. Webmoor and C. Witmore]  |version=PhD thesis |publisher=Stanford Humanities Lab/Metamedia, [[Stanford University]] |accessdate=2008-06-02}}
{{refend}}&lt;!-- END biblio format style --&gt;

==External links==
{{Commons category|Teotihuacán}}
* [http://astro.temple.edu/~dcm/teo.htm Teotihuacan Research Guide], academic resources and links, maintained by [[Temple University]]
* [http://jqjacobs.net/mesoamerica/teotihuacan.html Teotihuacan Photo Gallery], by James Q. Jacobs
* [http://studentweb.tulane.edu/~dhixson/teo/teo.html Mesoamerican Photo Archives: Teotihuacan], by David Hixson
* [http://www.paraisovirtual.com/Teotihuacan/Teotihuacan-360-Panorama.html 360° Panoramic View of the Avenue of the Dead, the Pyramid of the Sun and the Pyramid of the Moon ], by Roland Kuczora
*[http://www.teotihuacan.com.mx Teotihuacan Mexico, culture, history and tourism]

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Navboxes
|title=Articles and topics related to Teotihuacan
|state=collapsed
|list1=
{{World Heritage Sites in México}}
{{Pre-Columbian}}
{{Empires}}
}}

[[Category:Teotihuacan|*]]
[[Category:Ancient peoples]]
[[Category:Mesoamerican sites]]
[[Category:History museums in Mexico]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Mexico]]
[[Category:Mexico City metropolitan area]]
[[Category:Archaeoastronomy]]
[[Category:Ancient cities]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Mexico]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in the State of Mexico]]

{{Link FA|de}}

[[ar:تيوتيهواكان]]
[[be:Тэатыўакан]]
[[bg:Теотиуакан]]
[[bs:Teotihuacan]]
[[ca:Teotihuacan]]
[[cs:Teotihuacán]]
[[cy:Teotihuacán]]
[[da:Teotihuacán]]
[[de:Teotihuacán]]
[[el:Τεοτιουακάν]]
[[es:Teotihuacan]]
[[eo:Teotiŭakano]]
[[eu:Teotihuacan]]
[[fa:تئوتیهواکان]]
[[fr:Teotihuacan]]
[[ko:테오티우아칸]]
[[hr:Teotihuacán]]
[[id:Teotihuacan]]
[[it:Teotihuacan]]
[[he:טאוטיווקאן]]
[[ka:ტეოტიუაკანი]]
[[lt:Teotihuakanas]]
[[hu:Teotihuacan]]
[[ms:Teotihuacan]]
[[nah:Teōtīhuacān]]
[[nl:Teotihuacán (historische stad)]]
[[ja:テオティワカン]]
[[no:Teotihuacán]]
[[pl:Teotihuacán]]
[[pt:Teotihuacan]]
[[ro:Teotihuacán]]
[[qu:Teotiwakan]]
[[ru:Теотиуакан]]
[[simple:Teotihuacán]]
[[sr:Теотивакан]]
[[sh:Teotihuacan]]
[[fi:Teotihuacán]]
[[sv:Teotihuacán]]
[[tr:Teotihuacan]]
[[uk:Теотіуакан]]
[[vi:Teotihuacan]]
[[zh:特奧蒂瓦坎]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
