<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="815803" ns="0" title="Ghost (game)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the word game|the board game|Ghosts (board game)}}
{{refimprove|talk=y|date=January 2008}}
'''Ghost''' is a spoken [[word game]] in which players take turns adding letters to a growing word fragment, trying not to be the one to complete a valid word. Each fragment must be the beginning of an actual word, and usually some minimum is set on the length of a word that counts, such as three or four letters. The player who completes a word loses the round and earns a &quot;letter&quot; (as in the basketball game [[Variations of basketball|horse]]), with players being eliminated when they have been given all five letters of the word &quot;ghost&quot;.

Ghost can be played by two or more players of any age and requires no equipment, although it can be played with pencil and paper instead of being spoken aloud.

==Game play==
A player is chosen at random to start the game, and begins by naming any letter of the alphabet. Players then take turns to add letters to this fragment, with the aim being to avoid completing an actual word. The player whose turn it is may - instead of adding a letter - challenge the previous player to prove that the current fragment is actually the beginning of a word. If the challenged player can name such a word, the challenger loses the round; otherwise the challenged player loses the round. If a player bluffs, or completes a word without other players noticing, then play continues. When a round ends, play generally passes to the left.

If any score is kept at all, the traditional method uses the letters of the word &quot;Ghost&quot; in the same fashion as the basketball game horse, with each loss giving the player the next letter of the word, and a player being eliminated when they have all five letters.

In some versions of the game, players that obtain all the letters of &quot;ghost&quot; continue to participate by trying to distract other players and turn them into ghosts. If a player does not have all the letters of the word &quot;ghost&quot; and he or she talks to an existing ghost, they immediately become a ghost. This rule serves to accelerate games of Ghost with many players. This is also a rule in the games of Llama and Llano.

==Winning strategy==
Since the game tree of Ghost can be derived from the list of combinations of letters that are considered to be words, the game (as played by two players) can be easily &quot;[[solved game|solved]]&quot; to find a winning strategy for one player.

Alan Frank, a member of the [[National Puzzlers' League]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=NPL Directory|journal=The Enigma|publisher=[[National Puzzlers' League]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; constructed a sample winning strategy in 1987, based on the [[Tournament Word List|Official Scrabble Players Dictionary]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ghostbusters&quot;, [[Word Ways: The Journal of Recreational Linguistics|Word Ways]],'' 1987, page 206&lt;/ref&gt; [[Randall Munroe]] posted a sample winning strategy in 2007 on the news page of his [[webcomic]], [[xkcd]].  He based his solution on the [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] dictionary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blag.xkcd.com/2007/12/31/ghost/ Randall's Solution]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
'''Superghost''' (also known as [[Lexicant]] or Llano) is played by choosing either the beginning or end of the growing word fragment and adding a letter there. For example, given the fragment ERA, a player might offer '''B'''ERA or ERA'''D'''.  This version was played by [[James Thurber]] and his circle of friends.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newyorker.com/archive/1951/09/29/1951_09_29_027_TNY_CARDS_000231926 |title=&quot;Do 'You Want To Make Something Out of it?, Or, If you Put An &quot;O&quot; On &quot;Understo&quot;, You'll Ruin My &quot;Thunderstorm&quot; |accessdate=2007-07-10 |author=James Thurber |authorlink=James Thurber |coauthors= |date=29 September 1959|month=9 |format= |work= |publisher=The New Yorker |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Superduperghost''' is played by deciding whether to reverse the letters of the word fragment before adding a letter to the fragment's beginning or end.   For example, given the fragment ERA, a player might offer '''B'''ERA, ERA'''D''', '''N'''ARE, or ARE'''N'''. This variant was first broadly adopted at the 1978 World Science Fiction Convention in Phoenix, Arizona (IguanaCon) and is credited to Cary Hammer and [[Mark Malamud]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

'''Xghost''' (sometimes also known as Superduperghost or Llama) is played by adding a letter anywhere in the growing word fragment, including between letters.  For example, given the fragment ERA, a player might offer  '''B'''ERA, ERA'''D''', E'''B'''RA, or ER'''M'''A.  This version was invented by [[Daniel Asimov]]  around 1970. Originally and still often known as '''Superduperghost''', it was played by his circle of mathematics grad student friends at [[U.C. Berkeley]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

'''Spook''' is played by adding letters to a &quot;pool&quot; in which no fixed order is assumed. In this game, one's objective is to avoid completing a letter pool which can be ordered to form a word.  For example, given  the pool {A,B,F,L,S,U}, a player would be unwise to add H, which would form the word BASHFUL. However, he or she might add B, and cite the word FLASHBULB if challenged.

These variants usually require much more effort and time to play than the conventional game, and as such are lesser-known and less popular.

[[Cheddar Gorge (game)|'''Cheddar Gorge''']] is played by adding a ''word'' to the end of a growing ''sentence'' fragment, and avoiding the completion of a sentence.  This variant was popularized on the BBC Radio show ''[[I'm Sorry I Haven't a Clue]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/comedy/clue.shtml BBC Website for ''I'm Sorry I Haven't a Clue''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
The game of ''Ghost'' was played in an episode of [[Ghostwriter (TV series)|Ghostwriter]] in the &quot;Who is Max Mouse?&quot; story arc.

==See also==
*[[Unhalfbricking#Title_and_cover|Unhalfbricking]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ghost (Game)}}
[[Category:Word games]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
