<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="819227" ns="0" title="Utah Valley University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox University
|  width          = 100px
|  name           = Utah Valley University
|  image          = [[Image:UVU Seal.png|200px]]
|  motto          = &quot;Engage&quot;
|  established    = 1941
|  type           = [[Public university|Public]]
|  president      = [[Matthew S. Holland]]
|  city           = [[Orem]]
|  state          = [[Utah]]
|  country        = [[United States|USA]]
|  coor           = {{coord|40|16|40|N|111|42|50|W|type:landmark|display=inline,title}} 
|  undergrad      = 32,670
|  postgrad       = 
|  postgrad_label = 
|  faculty        = 
|  campus         = [[Suburban]]
|  colors         = [[Green]] &amp; [[Gold]] (Yellow), with [[White]] trim
|  mascot         = [[Utah Valley Wolverines|Wolverines]]
|  website        = [http://www.uvu.edu/ www.uvu.edu]
|  logo           = [[Image:UVU-Institutional-Mark.png|80px|UVU wordmark]]
}}

'''Utah Valley University''' or '''UVU''', is a publicly funded university in located in [[Orem, Utah]]. With a current enrollment of 32,670 students as of 2011&lt;ref&gt;http://sirepub.lehi-ut.gov/cache/2/aihdbn45pfmaxrjjltnhme45/20530407192011121553990.PDF&lt;/ref&gt;, Utah Valley University is now the largest public university in the State of Utah. UVU is a teaching institution which provides opportunity, promotes student success, and meets regional educational needs. The university currently offers approximately 58 bachelor degrees, 66 associate degrees, 21 certificate/diploma programs, and 3 high-demand master degrees in education, business and nursing. In the most recent fall 2010 semester the school had 32,670 students attending.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uvu.edu/iri/uvglance/At%20a%20glance%202009%20update01Apr10.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The university’s Wasatch Campus in [[Heber, Utah|Heber City, Utah]], also offers bachelor degrees in business management and secondary education, as well as associate degrees in accounting, behavioral science, business management, elementary education and general education.

Utah Valley University is a teaching institution that prepares students through a combination of academic and hands-on learning, a process dubbed &quot;engaged learning&quot; at UVU. The institution was awarded the Community Engagement Classification by the Carnegie Foundation in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2008 Carnegie Classification|publisher=Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/news/sub.asp?key=51&amp;subkey=2821}}{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Previously called '''Utah Valley State College''' (UVSC), the school attained [[university]] status in July 2008, changing to Utah Valley University. [[Matthew S. Holland]], appointed as the first president of UVU, officially began his duties on June 1, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://media.www.uvureview.com/media/storage/paper982/news/2009/06/22/News/University.Key.Passed.To.Pres.Holland-3748808.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:UVSCcampus.jpg|300px|left|A view of Utah Valley University's campus.]] --&gt;UVU was founded in the fall of 1941, when the Utah State Vocational Office consolidated federal work program classes into one campus in [[Provo, Utah|Provo]]. At this time, the school was known as the Central Utah Vocational School.
Growth brought numerous changes to UVU over the following decades, and the school was renamed several times to reflect its changing role. In 1963, the name was changed from Central Utah Vocational School&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uvu.edu/visitors/about/history.html&lt;/ref&gt; to Utah Trade Technical Institute. In 1967, the school became Utah Technical College at Provo, and was given the authority to confer associate degrees for the first time. In 1977, the institution began moving to its present location beside the [[Interstate 15|I-15]] in Orem. In 1987, it became Utah Valley Community College.

It wasn't until 1993 that the school was named Utah Valley State College and began awarding four-year degrees. The Utah legislature approved renaming it as a university in February 2007 (effective July 1, 2008), allowing it to begin offering master's degrees, although the school continues to place particular emphasis on its two- and four-year degree programs.

On July 1, 2008, the institution was awarded university status and changed its name to Utah Valley University to reflect the shift.

UVU is Utah's largest public university, and the largest employer in Orem&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mountainland.org/Economic_Development/Business/Employers.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; with over 1,400 full-time faculty and staff, and over 3,200 part-time faculty and staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;http://www.uvu.edu/iri/factbooks/factbook0910.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

When it was a community college, the school had approximately 8,000 students enrolled, growing by approximately 3,000 students a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | title=UVU looking for funds to replace overloaded science building | url=http://heraldextra.com/news/local/central/orem/article_846a476e-58d5-5db9-bb23-8754e14098e2.html | publisher=The Daily Herald | year=2010 | accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heraldextra.com/news/local/education/college/article_5ffb95fb-b0d8-5cd2-b643-1b6e419e5600.html UVU enrollment up 8 percent, funding still a concern&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Currently there are 32,670 students enrolled for Fall semester 2010 at UVU.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deseretnews.com/article/700077882/UVUs-record-growth-tests-funding-ability.html?pg=1 UVU's record growth tests funding ability | Deseret News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
=== Accreditation and admissions===
UVU was accredited by the Commission on Colleges of the [[Northwest Association of Secondary and Higher Schools|Northwest Association of Schools]] in 1969, and had its accreditation renewed in 1984, 1995, and 2005. Vocational accreditation was granted in 1976, and renewed in 1990 and 1995 by the Utah State Office of Vocational Education. In December 2006, the UVU School of Business received accreditation from the [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business|AACSB]].

UVU is an [[Open admissions|open enrollment]] university and despite the University's size and growth it looks as though administration will keep enrollment open for the time being.{{Or|reason=Please provide a source|date=November 2011}}

About 88% of UVU students come from Utah but an increasing number of students are coming from different countries and states. In 2009, UVU students represented all 50 states and 67 countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

===Faculty===
Notable faculty include [[Scott Carrier]], an author and radio producer whose stories have been featured on &quot;[[This American Life]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisamericanlife.org/Radio_Episode.aspx?sched=866 Archive | This American Life&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Marty Val Hill, a [[National Speakers Association|NSA]] national outstanding professor of the year,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Professor Honored|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4188/is_20060810/ai_n16656782/|accessdate=6 September 2011|newspaper=Deseret News|date=08/10/06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Craig Huish, a [[American Hotel &amp; Lodging Educational Institute|AHLEI]] national Lamp of Knowledge award winner as an Outstanding U.S. Educator&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=UVU Professor Honored As Outstanding US Educator|url=http://orem.fox13now.com/news/news/uvu-professor-honored-outstanding-us-educator/57575|accessdate=2 October 2011|newspaper=Fox 13 News|date=6 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;, and Jay DeSart, a geocacher, who created an election forecast model cited by ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' in predicting Barack Obama’s presidential win.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Putcha, ed|first=Chandra S.|title=Methods of Forecasting American Election Outcomes: Studies in Strategies for Prediction, chapter title: A Tale of Two Models: The DeSart and Holbrook State-Level Forecast Model in 2008|year=2010|publisher=Edwin Mellen Press|location=Lewiston, NY|isbn=0773438270|pages=163|url=http://www.uvu.edu/profpages/profiles/show/user_id/1181}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pyrah|first=Joe|title=UVU Professor Says Obama Will Win Big|url=http://www.heraldextra.com/news/local/article_3b98f317-4708-54e2-9ad7-8c6a41fa3483.html|accessdate=2 October 2011|newspaper=Daily Herald|date=13 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rankings and awards==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| Forbes               = 346
| USNWR_NU             = &lt;!-- NR --&gt;
| Wamo_NU              = &lt;!-- NR --&gt;
}}
UVU has chosen not to participate in ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' college and university rankings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/orem-ut/utah-valley-4027 Utah Valley University - Best College - Education - US News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2001, UVU student teams have placed first or second overall in the national [[SkillsUSA]] competition. Each year, students from UVU place well in national [[FBLA-PBL|Phi Beta Lambda]] and [[Delta Epsilon Chi]] business competitions.  At the 2008 national [[FBLA-PBL|Phi Beta Lambda]] conference in Atlanta, Georgia, UVU students were awarded twelve top-ten finishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=National Leadership Conference Results|publisher=FBLA-PBL, Inc.|url=http://utah-fbla-pbl.org/pbl/about/news/2008-National-Leadership-Conference-Results/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
UVU's main campus is located in Orem with satellite campuses in [[Heber City]], [[Spanish Fork, Utah|Spanish Fork]], North Orem, [[Provo Municipal Airport|Provo airport]], and [[Lehi, Utah|Lehi]]. UVU's main campus encompasses {{convert|228|acre|km2}} and includes 48 buildings. Each building has been built using the same style of unfinished concrete with all ten of the major buildings on campus connected by {{convert|30|ft|m|adj=mid|-wide}} concourses. UVU has beautiful grounds including two reflecting ponds on the west side of campus, a stream running through the east part of campus, and a multi-dimensional fountain in the middle of campus.

UVU is home to the Utah Community Credit Union Center,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heraldextra.com/news/local/article_15adf972-b454-11df-9c00-001cc4c002e0.html/ Utah Community Credit Union buys naming rights for UVU events center&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  formerly the [[David O. McKay Events Center]] which was built in 1996 with a capacity to seat 8,500 people. The events center is governed by a board consisting of representatives from UVU, Utah County and Orem City. It not only holds campus activities and sporting events but also community events such as major concerts, trade shows and expos, high school sports tournaments, family shows, graduations, and banquets. It is not only the headquarters of the UVU athletics department but also the NBA’s Development League [[Utah Flash]]. It is also home to UVU’s renowned culinary arts program, including Greg’s Restaurant. On average, the Events Center hosts 150-170 events per year. As many as 360,000 people patronize the Events Center on an annual basis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uvu.edu/blogs/newsroom/2010/01/19/mckay-name-moves-to-uvu-education-building/ UVU Press Releases » Blog Archive » McKay Name Moves to UVU Education Building&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The new library or UVU's Digital Learning Center is often referred to as the &quot;jewel&quot; of campus being the newest addition to campus.

===Digital Learning Center===
{{Unreferenced|date=November 2011}}
In September 2006, the school began construction of a new Digital Learning Center to replace the {{convert|35000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} Losee Resource Center (library). The &quot;DLC&quot; is {{convert|180000|sqft|m2}} and is located northeast of the Liberal Arts building. It opened on July 1, 2008. UVU President [[William A. Sederburg]] hired Cooper, Roberts, Simonsen and Associates and Layton Construction as the design/build team for the new Digital Learning Center, with acclaimed New York architect Jacob Alspector as lead architect. “We chose the design we’re going with because it was an exceptional design that still kept a lot of the same features of our current campus. So it looks like it’s supposed to be there yet it stands out,” said Jim Michaelis, associate vice president of Facilities Planning. The $48 million project includes networked computers, computer labs, a computer reference area (Information Commons), media center, 31 study rooms, and wireless internet throughout the building.

The library is the “greenest” state-owned building in Utah, and won two 2008 awards from Intermountain Construction magazine for its energy efficiency.

==Organization==
The university is part of the [[Utah System of Higher Education]].  The primary colleges and schools at the university are:

* College of Humanities &amp; Social Sciences
* College of Science and Health
* College of Technology and Computing
* School of Public Services
* School of the Arts
* School of Education
* University College
* Woodbury School of Business
 
Other academic support programs include Distance Education, Extended Studies, Summer, concurrent, Community and Continuing Education, and Honors. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.uvu.edu/collegesandschools/&lt;/ref&gt;


==Performing arts==
=== Dance===
UVU is home to one of the largest public collegiate ballroom dance programs in the United States. Over the last several years, the Ballroom Dance Company has grown into a premiere performance troupe. The company has over 130 members divided into four teams; one touring team, one reserve and two back up teams. The backup teams provide the students with the training and performance skills necessary to meet the demands of the touring team. The UVU Ballroom Dance Company has received numerous awards, honors, and accolades as they have performed and competed throughout the United States and abroad including recently winning the first ever College Dance Championship on ABC's TV series [[Dancing With The Stars]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://uvu.edu/blogs/newsroom/2010/05/26/uvu-ballroom-team-wins-dancing-with-the-stars-college-championship/ UVU Press Releases » Blog Archive » UVU ballroom team wins Dancing with the Stars College Championship&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The team is currently directed by Scott Asbell with Tara Boyd as the head choreographer.

==Athletics==
{{main|Utah Valley Wolverines}}
The school mascot is the [[Wolverine]], and the colors are green and gold.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wolverinegreen.com/genrel/logos.html Utah Valley Official Athletic Site - Athletics News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The school competes in most major sports at various levels. The school's NCAA sports are men's and women's [[basketball]], men's and women's [[track and field]], men's and women's [[Cross country running|cross country]], [[baseball]], [[Collegiate wrestling|wrestling]], [[softball]], women's [[soccer]], and women's [[volleyball]]. The school also fields several club teams including men's [[ice hockey]] (which competes in the [[ACHA]]), men's [[soccer]], men's [[volleyball]], men's [[lacrosse]], and men's and women's [[Rugby union|rugby]].

The Wolverines play their home basketball games in the 8,500-seat Utah Community Credit Union Center. The men's basketball team finished the 2008-09 season with a 17-11 record,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wolverinegreen.com/sports/m-baskbl/recaps/030509aaa.html Seniors Go Out with Big Win - UTAH VALLEY OFFICIAL ATHLETIC SITE&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; which capped off its 26th winning season in a row. The UCCU Center is also home to the [[Utah Flash]] of the [[NBA D-League]] and the [[Utah Valley Thunder]] of the [[American Indoor Football Association]].

The baseball team plays at Brent Brown Ballpark, a 2,500-seat facility (3,000 additional fans can sit on a grass berm that wraps around third base and left field, bringing total capacity to 5,500) that opened on March 25, 2005. Brent Brown Ballpark is also the home of the [[Orem Owlz]], a minor-league affiliate of [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim]], that competes in the [[Pioneer Baseball League]].

The school's club hockey team, which competes in [[ACHA]] Division 2, plays its home games at the [[Peaks Ice Arena]], a 2002 Winter Olympics hockey venue.

The athletic program is in [[NCAA|NCAA Division I]].  After numerous years of playing as an independent team, the Wolverines are now affiliated with the [[Great West Conference]], which began its inaugural all-sports season in 2008-09.&lt;ref&gt;[http://deseretnews.com/article/1,5143,700241969,00.html New Great West Conference]&lt;/ref&gt;

The UVU student section is called the Mighty Athletic Wolverine League, or ''MAWL'', a name created by student and executive vice president Justin Davies.

==Media==
The school has an independent, student-run weekly newspaper called the [[UVU Review]]. The newspaper began publishing under the name on June 30, 2008, the day before the university transition became official.&lt;ref&gt;http://media.www.uvureview.com/media/storage/paper982/news/2008/04/14/News/Fond-Farewell.To.The.College.Times-3323554.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; UVU Review's Editor-in-Chief was [[Jack Waters]] for the 2008-09 year, followed by [[Jennie Nicholls-Smith]] in 2009-10. The 2010-2011 staff is headed by David Self Newlin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uvureview.com/aboutus/]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fire Academy==
The school is one of few Utah universities which provides free training to Utah fire agencies. In August 2009, the university unveiled a {{convert|53|ft|m|adj=mid|-long}} [[Mobile Command Center]], acquired by [[federal grants]]. The Utah Valley University Fire Academy Mobile Command Training Center cost an estimated $200,000 to $300,000 and provides both students and firefighters with realistic fire training.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heraldextra.com/news/local/central/orem/article_5111ceff-8b3a-5fd5-bc77-4ca4270ed677.html UVU fire academy unveils new mobile training center&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alumni==
{{Alumni|date=October 2011}}
*[[A. J. Cook (actress)|A.J. Cook]] - Actress [[Criminal Minds]]
*[[Ricky Allman]] - Internationally renowned painter
*[[Mitch Jones]] - [[Major League Baseball]] player for the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]]
*[[Kam Mickolio]] - [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher for the [[Arizona Diamondbacks]]
*[[Ronnie Price]] - basketball player for the [[Utah Jazz]] of the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]]
*[[Michael McDonald (basketball)|Michael McDonald]] - former basketball player for the [[New Orleans Hornets]] of the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]]
*[[Travis Hansen]]- former basketball player for the [[Atlanta Hawks]] of the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]]
*[[Gregg Hale (musician)|Gregg Hale]] - former guitarist for the band [[Spiritualized]]
*Christina Lowe, [[Miss Utah]] 2010, A Miss America Semifinalist&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uvu.edu/blogs/newsroom/2011/01/19/uvu-alumna-christina-lowe-miss-utah-a-miss-america-semifinalist/]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Noelle Pikus Pace]] - World Cup gold medalist in [[Skeleton (sport)|Skeleton]] (tobogganing)
*[[Matthew S. Petersen]] - Chairman of the [[Federal Election Commission]], and former [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] chief counsel to the [[United States Senate Committee on Rules and Administration]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fec.gov/members/petersen/petersen_bio.shtml Biographical Information of FEC Commissioner Matthew S. Petersen&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Chelsie Hightower]] - Professional dancer on hit TV series ''[[Dancing with the Stars]]'' and ''[[So You Think You Can Dance (US)|So You Think You Can Dance]]''
*[[Wesley Silcox]] - World champion bull rider
*[[Chris Scanlon]] - CEO of PMA Media Group

==References==
{{Reflist}}
&quot;UVSC celebrates first 'unofficial' university grads&quot;; Salt Lake Tribute,http://www.sltrib.com/ci_5767536

==External links==
*[http://wolverinegreen.cstv.com/ Official athletics website]
*[http://www.unitedbasketballconference.com/ United Basketball Conference]
*[http://www.utahsbr.edu/prospective_students/institutions/uvsc.htm Utah System of Higher Education]
*[http://www.uvureview.com/ UVU Review (student newspaper) website]
*[http://www.uvu.edu/iri/ UVU Institutional Research and Information]

{{Utahcolleges}}
{{Great West Conference}}

[[Category:Utah Valley University| ]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Mormon studies]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Utah]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1941]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Utah County, Utah]]

[[de:Utah Valley University]]
[[no:Utah Valley State College]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
