<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8212792" ns="0" title="Zune Software"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
|name    = Zune Software
|logo    = 
|screenshot = [[Image:Zune-collection.png|300px]]
|caption  = Zune Software 4.8 on [[Windows 7]]
|developer = [[Microsoft]]
|operating_system =[[Windows XP|Windows XP SP3]]&lt;br&gt;[[Windows Vista|Windows Vista SP2]]&lt;br&gt;[[Windows 7]]
|released =
|frequently updated= Yes&lt;!-- Release version update? Don't edit this page, just click on the version number! --&gt;
|genre   = [[media player (application software)|Media player]]
|license  = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
|website  = [http://www.zune.net/en-us/products/software Zune.net]
}}

The Zune software functions as management software for [[Windows Phone 7]], [[Zune#Zune devices|Zune devices]], and [[Microsoft Kin]], a full media player application with a library, an interface to the Zune Marketplace, and as a media streaming server.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.zune.net/en-us/support/usersguide/sharing/mediasharingfaq.htm |title=Media Sharing FAQ |accessdate=November 21, 2008 |work=|publisher=Microsoft |date= |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080822183517/http://www.zune.net/en-us/support/usersguide/sharing/mediasharingfaq.htm |archivedate = August 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''Zune Software''' is used to sync with all devices with Zune functionality. Zune devices work exclusively with the Zune software and Marketplace. The Zune software applies many design principles of Microsoft's [[Metro (design language)|Metro design language]].

==Content==

As a media player, the Zune software supports the following formats:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! multimedia !! supported formats
|-
| Audio || [[MP3]], [[Advanced Audio Coding|AAC]] (Low complexity), .mp4, .m4b, .mov, [[Windows Media Audio|WMA]] (standard, pro, and lossless)
|-
| Video || [[MPEG4]] (in .mp4, .m4v and .mov containers), [[H.264]] (in .mp4, .m4v and .mov containers), [[WMV]], [[ASF]], [[Audio Video Interleave|AVI]] (in .avi container)
|-
| Images || [[JPEG]]
|}

The Zune software organizes the media in its library and allows users to add to the library by [[ripping]] from CDs, syncing with a Zune device, and downloading from the Zune Marketplace. The Zune software also allows one to organize song [[metadata]]. It can automatically download album art and metadata tag data for content in the library.

On the PC, the Zune software [[Streaming media|streams]] files to other PCs, the [[Xbox 360]], and other compatible devices. The Zune software also connects with the Zune social and keeps track of files swapped with other users.

The Zune software runs only on 32-bit [[Windows XP]] or 32-bit/64-bit [[Windows Vista]]/[[Windows 7]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zune.net/en-US/support/usersguide/gettingstarted/pcreqs.htm Zune Software: System Requirements]&lt;/ref&gt; Windows XP Professional x64 Edition is not supported.

'''Zune Marketplace''' is an online store that offers music, podcasts, TV shows, movies, music videos, and mobile applications. Content can be viewed or purchased on Windows PCs with the [[Zune]] software installed, Zune devices, the [[Xbox 360]], [[Windows Phone 7]] phones, or the [[Microsoft Kin]] phones.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.zune.net/en-us/products/learningcenter/zunemarketplace&lt;/ref&gt;

===History===
{{main|Zune Software version history}}

The 1.0 versions of the Zune software were a modified version of [[Windows Media Player]] 11{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}} while versions since 2.0 are built independently with additional [[DirectShow]] decoders for [[Advanced Audio Coding|AAC]], [[MPEG-4]] and [[H.264]]. The current version of the software is 4.8.2345.0, released on August 22, 2011.  Several versions of the software have been released.

==Zune Marketplace==
====Music====
Initially offering 2 million songs, the Zune Marketplace has grown to offer 14 million songs,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TfKsS113nAY&lt;/ref&gt; all of which are now available in MP3 format at up to 320kbps and are [[Digital rights management|DRM]]-free. Music on Zune Marketplace is offered by the [[World music market|big four music groups]] ([[EMI]], [[Warner Music Group]], [[Sony BMG]] and [[Universal Music Group]]), as well as smaller music labels.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

The home page of the Zune Marketplace shows featured music as selected by Microsoft, and the most popular music. Users can search, or filter by genres including rock, pop, dance, urban, and others.

Prior to Zune Marketplace’s music becoming DRM-free, songs were protected by a different DRM system than songs protected by Microsoft’s now-abandoned [[PlaysForSure]] initiative DRM, with the result that songs purchased from a PlaysForSure store cannot be played on any Zune-compatible device.

====Videos====

Zune Marketplace offers television shows from the following companies: [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]], [[Anime]], [[Bravo (US TV channel)|Bravo]], [[Cartoon Network]], [[CBS]], [[Discovery Communications]], [[E!]], [[Fox]], [[G4 (TV channel)|G4]], [[GamerTV]], [[History Channel]], [[Marvel Entertainment, Inc.|Marvel]], [[MLB]], [[NBC]], [[Paley Center]], [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]], [[Spike (TV channel)|Spike]], [[Starz (TV network)|Starz]], [[SyFy]], [[Total Nonstop Action Wrestling|TNA]], [[USA Network]], and [[Viacom]] .

Movies from [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]], [[Universal Studios|Universal]], [[Warner Brothers]], [[20th Century Fox]] and other studios are offered for purchase or time-limited rental. Some movies are available in HD. Selected content purchased via Zune Marketplace on the Xbox 360 additionally offers 5.1 surround sound.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=More films, faster with Zune |url=http://www.xbox.com/en-GB/news-features/news/More-films-faster-with-Zune.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Music videos are also offered for purchase.

====Applications====
{{see also|Zune Games|Windows Phone Marketplace}}

Zune Marketplace includes an applications section where apps and games can be downloaded for the Zune HD. The store initially launched with 9 apps, all of which were developed by Microsoft and released for free. The selection has since expanded. Apps currently available include several games, [[Facebook]], [[Twitter]], and [[Windows Live Messenger]].

The Zune PC software also allows users to browse, purchase, and install Windows Phone 7 apps from Windows Phone Marketplace.

===International availability===

Zune Marketplace was originally only available in the United States. In October 2010, certain Zune Marketplace content became available in additional countries in North America, Europe, Asia, and Australasia. The following table shows content availability by country:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/press/2010/sep10/09-20ZuneIntlPR.mspx?rss_fdn=Press%20Releases|title=Zune to Expand Multiscreen Entertainment Services Into International Markets|publisher=Microsoft News Center}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Content !! Countries
|-
| Music || United States, United Kingdom, France, Italy, Spain, Germany, Canada, Australia
|-
| Zune Music Pass|| United States, United Kingdom, France, Italy, Spain, Canada, Australia
|-
| Podcasts || United States
|-
| TV || United States, Canada
|-
| Movie Rental|| United States, United Kingdom, France, Italy, Spain, Germany, Austria, Japan,  Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Mexico
|-
| Movie Purchase|| United States, United Kingdom, France, Germany, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Japan
|-
| Applications || United States, United Kingdom, France, Italy, Spain, Germany, Japan, South Korea, Canada,   Hong Kong, Australia, New Zealand, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Czech Republic, Denmark, Finland, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Mexico, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Russia, Singapore, South Africa, Sweden, Switzerland, Taiwan
|}

It has been discovered that there are a number of workarounds for accessing the Zune Pass and other Zune Marketplace capabilities outside of the countries where it has been launched.

===Platforms===

The Zune software for Windows PCs offers the entire selection of music, podcasts, videos, and apps. The Xbox 360 offers movie and music video downloads, as well as Zune Pass streaming. Zune devices, Windows Phone 7 devices and the Microsoft Kin phones permit the download and streaming of music; Windows Phone 7 devices additionally allow the download of applications. None of these devices allow the download of video.

===Pricing===

Purchases are made in the Microsoft Points currency, which can also be used to purchase content from Xbox Live and Games for Windows Live marketplaces. The exchange rate is one United States dollar to 80 Microsoft points. Most music tracks are priced at 79 points or 99 points. This works out to US$0.9875 or US$1.24 per song.

===Zune Music Pass===

Zune Music Pass is a music subscription service, which allows subscribers to download an unlimited number of songs for as long as their subscription is active. The songs can be played on up to 3 Windows PCs and on up to 3 other Zune-compatible devices, but cannot be burned to an audio CD. Songs downloaded using Zune Pass are provided in WMA format at 192kbps and are restricted by DRM. Zune Music Pass subscribers in the United States and other select countries can also download 10 songs per month to keep even after their subscription ends. This is offered in the form of a 10-song credit that does not rollover.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.engadget.com/2006/09/14/Zune-marketplace-to-keep-your-Zune-player-happy/|title=Zune Marketplace To Keep Your Zune Player Happy|date=2006-09-14|publisher=Engadget|first=Cyrus|last=Farivar}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.zune.net/en-US/products/zunepass/default.htm&lt;/ref&gt; On October 3rd, 2011, the Zune Music Pass price was lowered to $9.99/month, removing the 10 song credit and making it available in Canada. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.engadget.com/2011/09/29/microsoft-announces-new-10-zune-music-pass-expands-service-to/&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Comparison of online music stores]]
*[[Zune]]
*[[Windows Phone 7]]
*[[Xbox 360]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.zune.net}}

{{Windows Mobile}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Zune Software}}
[[Category:Digital audio]]
[[Category:Jukebox-style media players]]
[[Category:Streaming music services]]
[[Category:Microsoft software]]
[[Category:Online music database clients]]
[[Category:Podcasting software]]
[[Category:Tag editors]]
[[Category:Windows CD ripping software]]
[[Category:Windows CD/DVD writing software]]
[[Category:Windows media players]]
[[Category:Zune]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
