<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8224272" ns="0" title="Violent Is the Word for Curly"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Film |
  | name           = Violent Is the Word for Curly |
  | image          = ViolentCurlyTITLE.jpg|
  | caption        = |
  | director       = [[Charley Chase]]|
  | writers        = [[Al Giebler]]&lt;br&gt;[[Elwood Ullman]]|
  | starring       = [[Moe Howard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Larry Fine]]&lt;br&gt;[[Curly Howard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bud Jamison]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gladys Gale]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dick Curtis]]&lt;br&gt;[[Marjorie Deanne]]&lt;br&gt;[[Pat Gleason (actor)|Pat Gleason]]&lt;br&gt;[[Al Thompson]] |
  | cinematography = [[Lucien Ballard]]|
  | editing        = [[Art Seid]]|
  | producer       = Charley Chase&lt;br&gt;[[Hugh McCollum]] |
  | distributor    = [[Columbia Pictures]] |
  | released       = July 2, 1938 ([[United States|U.S.]]) |
  | runtime        = 17' 37&quot; |
  | country        = {{FilmUS}}
  | language       = [[English language|English]]
  | preceded_by = ''[[Healthy, Wealthy and Dumb]]'' |
  | followed_by = ''[[Three Missing Links]]''
}}

'''''Violent Is the Word for Curly''''' is the 32nd [[short subject]] starring American [[slapstick]] comedy team the [[Three Stooges]]. The trio made a total of 190 shorts for [[Columbia Pictures]] between [[1934 in film|1934]] and [[1959 in film|1959]].

==Plot==
{{Plot|date=September 2010}}
Administrators at a Mildew College, an all-girl school, are begging the school's largest benefactor, Mrs. Catsby ([[Gladys Gale]]), to provide an athletic fund for the school. She does not approve of girls playing sports, and informs the administrators that the money will be used for the salaries of the three new European professors that are arriving that day.  Meanwhile, the Stooges have just started a new job as servicemen at a service station, with a strong held belief of &quot;super soyvice!&quot;   When they get a customer (three older German men driven by a [[chauffeur]]), they proceed to provide their own inept brand of service, angering the men. The mayhem ends when Curly accidentally puts [[gasoline]] in the [[radiator]] and Moe checks it with a match. The resulting explosion prompts the Stooges to flee in a nearby [[ice cream]] truck that they had coincidentally thrown the German men's suitcases into. Curly climbs in the back while Moe and Larry are in the front.
[[Image:ViolentCROP.jpg|thumb|300px|left|Curly is seconds away from getting slugged by Moe in a colorized screen shot from ''Violent Is the Word for Curly''.]]

The Stooges finally stop when they run out of gas. Moe and Larry realize that Curly is still in the back of the truck and is now frozen solid. They thaw him out by tying him to a tree branch over an open fire (Moe: &quot;Twenty minutes to a pound...heh heh heh, we'll be here a month!&quot;) This works fine until Curly wakes up on fire and jumps into a nearby lake. When Moe and Larry try to help him out, he pulls them in with him. Now soaked, the boys decide to see if there are any dry clothes in the suitcases they had thrown into the truck.

The suitcases, it turns out, belong to the three new professors for Mildew College, and as the boys, now decked in their gowns and mortarboards, try to hitch a ride, Mrs. Catsby spots then and picks them up, bringing them to the school.  During the introductions of the &quot;new professors,&quot; a student gets wise with a nonplussed Larry, and in order to test their &quot;mental coordination&quot;, Moe begins a rendition of &quot;[[Swinging the Alphabet]]&quot;, which starts off fine and eventually transcends into a jazzy, off-time performance.


Later, during the buffet lunch, the three professors show up, blowing the Stooges' cover and vowing to return to &quot;[[Hamburg]] on the [[Sikorsky S-42|Clipper]]!&quot; When Mrs. Catsby angrily confronts the Stooges, they tell her that the college needs athletics, not the foreign professors. They offer to demonstrate and the class follows. Meanwhile, the professors mix an explosive into a basketball.  The boys demonstrate football plays using the basketball, and force Mrs. Catsby to join in. After being tackled &quot;on her own five yard line,&quot; she agrees to provide an athletic fund if the boys would get the professors back. As the boys are about to agree, Curly throws an errant basket, going over the fence and exploding in front of the professors, who are blown back into the Stooges clutches. The boys vow to clean them up and give a little &quot;super soyvice.&quot;

==Curly gets cooked==
During one scene, Curly is tied to a revolving spit that is placed over an open fire. He is then &quot;roasted&quot; in order to thaw him out after having slept in an ice cream truck. Future Stooge director [[Edward Bernds]] was present during the filming and noticed that Curly's weight was causing a problem. &quot;Curly was so heavy Moe and Larry couldn't turn the crank,&quot; Bernds said. &quot;The straps holding him slipped and he was hanging directly over the fire. Before they could get him off, he was pretty well seared. Curly was hollering his head off, and I don't blame him. Being roasted alive belongs to the [[Inquisition]], not making two-reel comedies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Forrester, Jeff (2002). ''Three Stooges: The Triumphs and Tragedies of the Most Popular Comedy Team of All Time'', p. 80. Donaldson Books, ISBN 0971580103&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
*The title ''Violent Is the Word for Curly'' is a parody of the film ''[[Valiant Is the Word for Carrie]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Solomon, Jon. (2002) ''The Complete Three Stooges: The Official Filmography and Three Stooges Companion'', p. 133; Comedy III Productions, Inc., ISBN 0971186804&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[Film colorization|colorized]] version of this film was released in 2004. It was part of the DVD collection entitled &quot;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0002A2WG8/ Stooged &amp; Confoosed].&quot;
* Despite the fact that Mildew College is an all-girls school, a male student can be seen sitting in the classroom during &quot;Swinging the Alphabet&quot;.
* During Curly's solo section on &quot;Swinging...&quot; (&quot;K, A, Kay!, K, E, Key!...&quot;), he noticeably sings his parts faster than the music or the other singers.

==See also==
&quot;[[Swinging the Alphabet]]&quot;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{ThreeStooges}}

[[Category:1938 films]]
[[Category:The Three Stooges films]]
[[Category:Black-and-white films]]
[[Category:1930s comedy films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Charley Chase]]

[[pt:Violent Is the Word for Curly]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
