<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8245411" ns="0" title="Thao with the Get Down Stay Down"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=March 2011}}

{{Infobox musical artist
|name            = Thao with The Get Down Stay Down
| image             = Thao nguyen 042.jpg
| caption        = Thao with the Get Down Stay Down live in Tucson, Arizona, November 18, 2009
|landscape        = Yes
|background      = group_or_band 
|origin          = [[Falls Church]], [[Virginia]], [[United States]]
|genre           = [[Folk rock]], [[Alternative rock]]
|years_active    = 2003–Present
|label           = Trust Me Corporation&lt;br /&gt;[[Kill Rock Stars]]
|website             = [http://www.thaomusic.com/ Official Site]
|current_members = Thao Nguyen, Adam Thompson, Lisa Schonberg
|Former_members   = Frank Stewart, Willis Thompson
}}
'''Thao with The Get Down Stay Down''' is a [[San Francisco, California]]-based (formerly [[Falls Church, Virginia]]) [[alternative rock|alternative]] [[folk rock]] music group.  It consists of Thao Nguyen ([[Singing|vocals]], [[guitar]]), Adam Thompson ([[bass guitar]]), and Lisa Schonberg ([[Drum kit|drums]]). Frank Stewart (lead guitar, [[record producer|production]]) and Willis Thompson ([[Drum kit|drums]]) are former members of the band.

==History==
Thao began playing guitar at age 12. She began performing and recording as an indie-folk duo with a high school friend, Brenna Clerkin. Raised in [[Falls Church, Virginia]] with her single mother, she often practiced her songs while working at her mother's [[laundromat]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/04/16/AR2009041601538.html/ Thao Nguyen Rejects 9-to-5 life for Music Career - washingtonpost.com]. Retrieved 2010-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt; She often cites [[Lilith Fair]] as an inspiration for her desire to become a singer/songwriter.  After recording an [[Extended play|EP]] that differed from her initial style, she began performing as a soloist with her acoustic guitar.

Nguyen met drummer Willis Thompson while studying for her degrees in Sociology and Women’s Studies at [[The College of William and Mary]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.kexp.org/blog/2009/09/30/song-of-the-day-thao-with-the-get-down-stay-down-know-better-learn-faster/ Song of the Day: September 30, 2009 - kexp.org] Retrieved 2011-01-25.&lt;/ref&gt;  Willis Thompson was a member of Camp Tigerclaw, Acousticore, and Murphy's Kids. He is also a contributing member to the band The Light Footwork. Thao Nguyen and Willis Thompson met Adam Thompson (no relation) during a show at the Harrison Street Coffee Shop in [[Richmond, Virginia]]. At the time, Adam Thompson was performing as a solo jazz-influenced act under the moniker The OK Bird.  Frank Stewart, member of the bands Durian and Verbal, would produce the first full-length album ''Like the Linen'' in 2005 and join the band as a lead guitarist.  Although only Willis and Nguyen initially performed live on tour, the four members began touring as a group during the [[Kill Rock Stars]]' Sound the Hare Heard tour during the summer of 2006.  The name of the band was originally suggested by a former bassist of the band.  Nguyen would expand the initial suggestion of &quot;The Get Down&quot; to &quot;The Get Down Stay Down.&quot; Thao Nguyen still occasionally performs as a soloist, including a European tour with [[Laura Veirs]] and the Tortured Souls in August 2006.

==Current==

[[Image:Thao nguyen williamsburg.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Thao (on tour with [[Mirah]]) performing at the [[Williamsburg,_Brooklyn#Music_scene|Music Hall of Williamsburg]]]]The band is managed by [[Slim Moon]], former president of the [[Kill Rock Stars]] label.
After sending &quot;Like the Linen&quot; to Laura Veirs, Thao was able to get connected to [[Tucker Martine]], Veirs' drummer and producer for [[The Decemberists]] and [[Sufjan Stevens]]. In August 2006, the group began recording with Martine in Seattle and released the album &quot;We Brave Bee Stings And All&quot; in January 2008. Thao Nguyen has since moved to [[San Francisco]], [[California]]. The band toured in 2008 with [[Xiu Xiu]], and separately with [[Rilo Kiley]] before heading out on their first headlining tour that summer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=94282059 Thao Nguyen: Tiny Desk Concert: NPR]. Retrieved 2010-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Thao appeared solo on the nationwide [[Hotel Cafe Tour]]. She collaborated with another Kill Rock Stars band, the [[Portland Cello Project]], on their first album, &quot;The Thao and Justin Power Sessions,&quot; released on June 9, 2009. Thao and the Get Down Stay Down released their second full-length album &quot;Know Better Learn Faster&quot; on October 13, 2009. Thao was joined by [[Andrew Bird]] on the title track &quot;Know Better Learn Faster.&quot; The band toured the US with the Portland Cello Project and David Shultz and the Skyline in late 2009, and spent time touring the US and Europe in Winter/Spring 2010.

In early 2010, Thao performed with [[Mirah]] at the Noise Pop festival in San Francisco. The two later announced a 2010 North American tour, billed under the name Thao and Mirah With The Most of All.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pitchfork.com/news/38602-mirah-and-thao-to-tour-together/ Mirah and Thao to Tour Together]&lt;/ref&gt; The two shared the stage to perform a collaborative set made up of each artist's respective songs. Thao provided backup vocals, guitar, [[banjo]], and [[bongo drum]] percussion on Mirah's songs.

In May 2010, a video for the song &quot;Body&quot;, directed by [[Dianna Agron]], debuted on the website of humanitarian organization [[Oxfam America]].  The video features a prelude of Thao and Dianna talking about their friendship, the making of the video, and their work on behalf of Oxfam.

The band's track &quot;When We Swam&quot; is the opening theme for Australian prime-time TV series ''[[Offspring (TV series)|Offspring]]'' (which premiered in Australia in August 2010).

The band also composed and performed the soundtrack for the 2011 film, ''American Teacher''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=American Teacher Soundtrack|url=http://differentfurstudios.com/blog/?p=4948|publisher=Different Fur Studios|accessdate=6 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
===Albums===
* ''Like the Linen'' (2005)
* ''Daytrotter Sessions'' (2006)
* ''[[We Brave Bee Stings and All]]'' (2008)
* ''[[Know Better Learn Faster]]'' (2009)

===Singles===
* &quot;Bag of Hammers&quot; from ''[[We Brave Bee Stings and All]]''
* &quot;Know Better Learn Faster&quot; from ''[[Know Better Learn Faster]]''
* &quot;Tallymarks&quot;

===Compilation contributions===
* &quot;Feet Asleep&quot; – ''[[The Sound the Hare Heard]]'' (2006, [[Kill Rock Stars]] compilation disc)
* &quot;Young Man&quot; – ''Kill Rock Stars Winter Holiday Album'' (2006, [[Kill Rock Stars]] compilation, digital release only)

===Collaborations===
* ''Thao/The Thermals Record Store Day Split 7&quot;'' (2009) EP split with the Thermals, released for Record Store Day – April 18, 2009
* ''The Thao and Justin Power Sessions'' (2009) with the Portland Cello Project
* ''[[Thao + Mirah]]'' (2011) LP with [[Mirah]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.thaomusic.com/ Official Website]
*[http://radio.utdallas.edu/blog/?p=148/ Interview with RadioUTD]
*[http://www.myspace.com/thaomusic MySpace profile]
*[http://www.daytrotter.com/daytrotterSessions/189/free-songs-thao-nguyen The Day Trotter Sessions with Free Songs]
*[http://www.bandega.com/band/view/thao-nguyen#interview 2009 Thao Nguyen Interview at Bandega.com]
*[http://blogs.oxfamamerica.org/index.php/2009/10/15/thao-nguyen-why-climate-change-matters-right-now/ Thao blogging for Oxfam America about climate change]
*[http://www.ontaponline.com/view_article.php?article_id=10078 OnTap Review]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xmHIuzElbZc Kill Rock Stars Podcast With Bag of Hammers Video]
*[http://www.rcrdlbl.com/2008/04/18/download_thao_the_get_down_stay_down/ SEEN: Download Thao &amp; the Get Down, Stay Down]
*[http://www.metacritic.com/music/artists/thaowiththegetdownstaydown/knowbetterlearnfaster Know Better Learn Faster reviews at Metacritic.com]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Thao With The Get Down Stay Down}}
[[Category:Musical groups established in 2003]]
[[Category:American folk rock groups]]
[[Category:Indie pop groups from Virginia]]
[[Category:Indie pop groups from San Francisco]]

[[fr:Thao with the Get Down Stay Down]]
[[sv:Thao with the Get Down Stay Down]]
[[zh:Thao with the Get Down Stay Down]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
