<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="827965" ns="0" title="Systrace"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Software
| name                   = Systrace
| logo                   = 
| screenshot             = 
| caption                = 
| collapsible            = 
| author                 = [[Niels Provos]]
| developer              = 
| released               = 
| latest release version = 1.6g
| latest release date    = {{release date|2009|3|15}}
| latest preview version = 
| latest preview date    = 
| frequently updated     = 
| programming language   = 
| operating system       = [[Unix-like]]
| platform               = 
| size                   = 
| language               = 
| status                 = 
| genre                  = [[Computer security]]
| license                = BSD-like
| website                = http://www.systrace.org/
}}
[[Image:Systrace-Screenshot-trojan.png|right|thumb|200px|Systrace displaying an unauthorized syscall using &lt;tt&gt;xsystrace&lt;/tt&gt;.]] '''Systrace''' is a [[computer security]] utility which limits an [[computer application|application's]] access to the system by enforcing access policies for [[system call]]s. This can mitigate the effects of [[buffer overflow]]s and other security vulnerabilities. It was developed by [[Niels Provos]] and runs on various [[Unix-like]] [[operating system]]s.

Systrace is particularly useful when running untrusted or binary-only applications and provides facilities for [[privilege elevation]] on a system call basis, helping to eliminate the need for potentially dangerous [[setuid]] programs. It also includes interactive and automatic policy generation features, to assist in the creation of a base policy for an application.

{{As of|2004}}, systrace is integrated into [[OpenBSD]].  It is also available for [[Linux]] and [[Mac OS X]], although the OS X port is currently unmaintained. It was removed from [[NetBSD]] at the end of 2007 due to several unfixed implementation issues. As of version 1.6f Systrace supports 64-bit Linux. 

==Features==
Systrace supports the following features:
* '''Confines untrusted binary applications''': An application is allowed to make only those system calls specified as permitted in the policy.  If the application attempts to execute a system call that is not explicitly permitted an alarm gets raised.
* '''Interactive policy generation with graphical user interface''': Policies can be generate interactively via a graphical frontend to Systrace.  The frontend shows system calls and their parameters not currently covered by policy and allows the user to refine the policy until it works as expected.
* '''Supports different emulations''': GNU/Linux, BSDI, etc..
* '''Non-interactive policy enforcement''': Once a policy has been trained, automatic policy enforcement can be used to deny all system calls not covered by the current policy.  All violations are logged to Syslog.  This mode is useful when protecting system services like a web server.
* '''Remote monitoring and intrusion detection''': Systrace supports multiple frontends by using a frontend that makes use of the network, very advanced features are possible.
* '''Privilege elevation''': Using Systrace's privilege elevation mode, it's possible to get rid of [[setuid]] binaries.  A special policy statement allows selected system calls to run with higher privileges, for example, creating a [[raw socket]].

==Vulnerability history==  	 
Systrace is still under development, and has had some vulnerabilities in the past, including:
* [http://www.watson.org/~robert/2007woot/ Exploiting Concurrency Vulnerabilities in System Call Wrappers] Paper by [[Robert Watson (computer scientist)]] from the First USENIX Workshop On Offensive Technologies (WOOT07) analyzing system call wrapper races across several wrapper platforms including systrace
* [http://www.systrace.org/index.php?/archives/13-Local-Privilege-Escalation.html Google Security discovers local privilege escalation in Systrace] 
* [http://www.systrace.org/index.php?/archives/4-Local-Root-Exploit-on-NetBSD.html Local root exploit on NetBSD]
* [http://undeadly.org/cgi?action=article&amp;sid=20070809201304  Vulnerabilities in systrace]

==See also==
*[[AppArmor]]
*[[SELinux]]
*[[Mandatory access control]]

==External links==
*[http://www.citi.umich.edu/u/provos/systrace/ Systrace Download Page]
*[http://www.systrace.org/ Systrace webpage]

{{unix-stub}}

[[Category:Unix security-related software]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
