<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="83019" ns="0" title="Motherfucker"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-protect|small=yes}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{wiktionarypar|Motherfucker}}
'''Motherfucker''' (sometimes abbreviated as '''mofo''', '''mf''', or '''mf'er''') is a [[vulgarism]] which, in its most literal sense, refers to one who participates in [[sexual intercourse]] with a [[mother]], either [[MILF (slang)|someone else's mother]], or [[incest|his own]].

== Variants ==
Like many widely used offensive terms, ''motherfucker'' has a large list of [[Minced Oath|minced oaths]]. ''Motherhumper'', ''motherfugger'', ''mother f'er'', ''mothersucker'', ''motherlover'', ''mofo'', ''motherflower'', ''motherkisser'' and many more are sometimes used in polite company or to avoid censorship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jrank&quot;&gt;[http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/articles/pages/749/Motherfucker.html Motherfucker]&lt;/ref&gt; The participle ''motherfucking'' is often used as an emphatic, in the same way as the less strong ''fucking''. The verb ''to motherfuck'' also exists, although it is less common. Conversely, when paired with an adjective, it can become a term denoting such things as originality and [[masculinity]], as in the related phrase &quot;bad ass mother fucker&quot;.
{{wiktionarypar|BAMF}}

Usually the word 'motherfucker' is used in place of a noun in a sentence, such as:
''That [[Trigonometry|trig]] problem was a real motherfucker.''

Almost always, the word does not actually imply that someone has had sex with his own or another person's mother. Instead it is understood as a swear word, related to the usage of parent word &quot;[[fuck]].&quot;

The word is also commonly used as an expletive. For example if a person is told an incredible tale or description of an event they may respond with &quot;Motherfucker&quot; said slowly.

== Popular culture ==
The word appears in [[George Carlin]]'s ''[[Seven dirty words|Seven Words You Can't Say on Television]]''. In one HBO special, he comments that at one point, someone asked him to remove it, since, as a derivative of the word &quot;fuck,&quot; it constituted a duplication.&lt;ref name=&quot;carlin&quot;&gt;{{cite video| people = [[George Carlin|Carlin, George]]| title = On Location: George Carlin at Phoenix| medium = DVD| publisher = HBO Home Video| location =|date=1978 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He later added it back, claiming that the bit's rhythm doesn't work without it.&lt;ref name=&quot;carlin&quot;/&gt;

[[Kurt Vonnegut]]'s classic novel ''[[Slaughterhouse-Five]]'' has, since its original publication, been challenged in libraries and schools on the grounds that the word is used occasionally by the soldiers in the story.  Vonnegut later joked in a speech, published in the collection ''[[Fates Worse Than Death]]'', that &quot;Ever since that word was published, way back in 1969, children have been attempting to have intercourse with their mothers. When it will stop no one knows.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;vonnegut&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Vonnegut|first=Kurt|title=Fates Worse Than Death|year=1992|publisher=Berkeley Books|location=New York|isbn=0425134067|pages=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The word has become something of a catchphrase for [[Samuel L. Jackson]], who frequently utters the word in his movies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jensen|first=Jeff|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/report/0,6115,1219727_1_0_,00.html|title=Kicking Asp|publisher=''[[Entertainment Weekly]]''|date=August 4, 2006|accessdate=June 21, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Literature ==
* ''The Compleat Motherfucker: A History of the Mother of All Dirty Words'' by [[Jim Dawson]] (Feral House, 2009; ISBN 781932 595413) is a history of the word in black culture and in American literature, film, comedy and music.
{{Wiktionary|motherfucker}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Pejorative terms for people]]
[[Category:Profanity]]

[[da:Motherfucker]]
[[ko:Fuck#마더 퍽커]]
[[ms:Pukimak]]
[[ja:マザーファッカー]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
