<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8328026" ns="0" title="Classmate PC"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox computer
|Photo =
|Developer = [[Original Equipment Manufacturer|OEM]]
|Type = [[Subnotebook]]/[[Netbook]]
|Connectivity = 10/100M Ethernet WLAN 802.11b/g with antenna, Mesh [[802.11s]] support
|Media = 1 GB (Linux only), 2 GB [[flash memory]], 4 GB Flash, 30 GB HDD
|OS = [[Windows XP Professional]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mandriva Linux#Mandriva Linux Discovery|Mandriva Linux 2010]]&lt;br&gt; Metasys Classmate 2.0&lt;br&gt;for the Classmate PC
|Input = [[Computer keyboard|Keyboard]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Touchpad]]
|Camera = yes
|Power = 4/6-cell [[Li-ion battery]]
|CPU = [[Intel Atom]] Mobile Processor N270
|Memory = DDR-II 256M (Linux only) or 512/1024 SO-DIMM
|Display = 7” or 8.9” 800x480 Color LCD&lt;br&gt;800 x 480
|Dimensions = 245 mm x 196mm x 44 mm
|Weight = 1.3 kg [2.9 pounds]
}}

The '''Classmate PC''', formerly known as '''Eduwise''', is [[Intel]]'s entry into the market for low-cost [[personal computer]]s for children in the developing world. It is in some respects similar to the [[One Laptop Per Child]] (OLPC) [[trade association]]'s [[Children's Machine]] (XO), which has a similar target market. Although made for profit, the production of the Classmate PC is considered an [[Information and Communication Technologies for Development]] project. The device falls into the newly defined category of [[netbook]]s.

==Intel World Ahead Program==
Intel’s World Ahead Program was established May 2006. The program designed a platform for low cost laptops that third party manufacturers could use to produce low cost machines under their own respective brands.

The Classmate PC is a reference design by Intel. Intel does not build the subnotebooks, but does produce the chips that power them. The reference design is then used by [[original equipment manufacturers|original equipment manufacturers (OEMs)]] worldwide to build their own branded Classmate PC.

==Technology==
Lenovo and Intel launched a new Classmate PC&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=DeCarlo|first=Matthew|title=Lenovo launches Classmate+ academic notebook|url=http://www.techspot.com/news/42768-lenovo-launches-classmate-academic-notebook.html|accessdate=21 October 2011|newspaper=Tech Spot|date=10 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2011.

Intel has had various partners with its iterations of the Classmate PC. Recently, the company has signed up Lenovo as a partner for the latest model, the Classmate+ PC. Reviews of the machine say that it's faster and more tamper proof&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dawson|first=Christopher|title=Classmate PC: Faster, stronger, more|url=http://www.zdnet.com/news/intel-unveils-tablet-classmate-pc-design/261656?tag=btxcsim|publisher=ZD Net|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; .

The Lenovo carry handle is firmly in place at the back of the Classmate+ PC and it's powered by one of Intel's Atom processors, in this case a single core 1.6GHz Atom N455 which is paired with Intel's NM10 chipset.

It will also come with up to 2GB of RAM, a standard netbook style 10.1-inch LCD screen, an option of either an 8 or 16GB SSD or a 160 or 250GB hard drive. Other features include 802.11b/g/n Wi-Fi, 10/100Mbit Ethernet, a 1.3Megapixel webcam, three USB 2.0 ports, a memory card reader, a D-sub connector and a pair of audio jacks.

Lenovo will supply three different battery packs for the Classmate+ PC, a standard 3-cell unit which is said to deliver 3-3.5h battery life depending on whether it's configured with a hard drive or SSD, a 4400mAh 6-cell pack good for between 7-7.5h and finally a 5200mAh high density 6-cell battery pack good for up to 8.5-9h of usage. The Classmate+ PC will only be available to qualified education and government customers through Lenovo or its channel partners.&lt;ref&gt;http://vr-zone.com/articles/lenovo-and-intel-launch-the-classmate-pc/11554.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classmate PC (Clamshell, First Generation)==
The reference [[computer hardware|hardware]] specifications as of September 28, 2006 are:
*Customized mini chassis 245 x 196 x 44
*CPU: Intel [[Celeron M]] mobile processor (915GMS + ICH6-M)
*CPU [[clock speed]] 900&amp;nbsp;MHz (with 32&amp;nbsp;KB L1 cache, no L2 cache, and 400&amp;nbsp;MHz FSB)
[[Image:Intel Classmate PC.jpg||262px|right|Intel Classmate PC]]
* 800 x 480 7&quot;-inch diagonal [[LCD]], [[Low voltage differential signaling|LVDS]] Interface, LED B/L
*256MB of [[DDR2]] [[RAM]]
*1 GB/2 GB [[flash memory]] (connected via USB)
*10/100M [[Ethernet physical layer|Ethernet]]
*Realtek WLAN [[802.11b/g]] with antenna (connected via USB)
*Intel GMS915 [[integrated graphics]] chip (8 MB shared memory)
*Built in [[microphone]]
*Built in [[stereo]] speakers
*Stereo 2 channel audio, jacks for external stereo speakers and microphones, Line-out, and Mic-in
*Integrated [[Computer keyboard|keyboard]] with [[hot key]]s
*Cycle [[touch pad]] with left and right buttons
*Customized Note Taker with wireless pen
*TPM1.2 ([[Trusted Platform Module]] from [[Infineon Technologies]] or [[Nuvoton]]) used for the theft control feature.
*Power source:
**4-cell [[Li-ion battery]] with adapter – approximately 3.5 hours usage
**6-cell [[Li-ion battery]] option – approximately 5 hours usage&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intel.com/intel/worldahead/pdf/cmpcbrochure.pdf Product Info]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a consumer model called MiLeap X, build by HCL Infosystems, India.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hclinfosystems.in/news110.htm MiLeap X press release, February 21, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second Generation (Convertible)==
The successor of the original Classmate design was announced in April 2008&lt;ref&gt;http://www.linuxdevices.com/news/NS5036131897.html&lt;/ref&gt; and reviewed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.laptopmag.com/review/laptops/2gopc.aspx |title=LAPTOP Magazine - Product reviews, tech news, buying guides, and more |publisher=Laptopmag.com |date=2008-04-02 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later on, different photos of the successor leaked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deviceguru.com/2008/08/20/intel-previews-next-gen-classmate-pc/ |title=Intel previews next-gen Classmate PC |publisher=DeviceGuru |date=2008-08-20 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Photos of Classmate PC 3 as a [[tablet computer|tablet PC]] are available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.laptopmag.com/intel-powered-convertible-classsmate-pc-the-touch-netbook-to-emulate |title=Intel-Powered Convertible Classmate PC: The Touch Netbook to Emulate |publisher=Blog.laptopmag.com |date=2008-12-15 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second generation Classmate was unveiled on 3 April 2008 at Intel's Developer Forum. Significant upgrades include:

*Available 30GB PATA hard drive (in addition to 1, 2, and 4 GB SSD).
*Built-in webcam
*Available 9&quot; LCD (the 7&quot; LCD is still available)
*Up to 512MB RAM
*[[IEEE 802.11s|802.11s]] (mesh networking, currently only usable on Linux-based Classmates)
*Available 6-cell battery for up to 6.5 hours usage
*Touchscreen — pen and on-screen soft keyboard
*Tablet mode — simple user-interface shell; quick launcher for tablet mode
*Enhanced software — easier network connection and collaboration simple computer management, and localized, education-friendly content

==Third Generation (Convertible)==
[[File:3rd Generation Intel Classmate at computex 09.jpg|thumb|Third generation of the Classmate PC]]

On [[Computex]] 2009, Intel presented the 3rd generation of the Classmate PC. It comes with a camera and an accelerometer.

==Intel-Powered Convertible Classmate PC==
The Intel-Powered Convertible Classmate PC had its official release at [[CES]] in January 2009 and was aimed at students, teachers, and parents. The Convertible Classmate can be converted from a traditional laptop to a tablet PC to allow children to write and draw more naturally. This model was designed by [[TEAMS Design]] [[Shanghai]] and won several design awards such as the Appliance Design EID Award&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2011 Excellence in Design Awards|url=http://www.appliancedesign.com/HTML/EID/59b1367daf848010VgnVCM100000f932a8c0|work=EID Awards|publisher=Appliance Design|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;, 2008 Spark Award and &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Spark Award 2008|url=http://www.sparkawards.com/Galleries/09_Entries.htm?appid=1948|publisher=Spark Awards|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[International Forum Design|IF]] 2008 China Award&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=iF design award china 2008|url=http://www.ifdesign.de/beitragsdetails_e.html?offset=19&amp;sprache=1&amp;award_id=161&amp;beitrag_id=42577|publisher=International Design Forum Hanover|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;. The initial model includes the following:
*Dual mode: tablet mode and traditional laptop mode.
*When open like a traditional laptop, the screen swivels 180 degrees for easier sharing.
*1.6&amp;nbsp;GHz Intel Atom processor
*1 GB RAM (2 GB max)
*60GB Hard Disk Drive (PATA 1.8&quot;, ZIF socket)
*8.9&amp;nbsp;inch touch screen &amp; advanced palm-resting technology.
*Allows for writing or drawing directly on the screen.
*Built-in camera rotates 180° to enable students to interact in a new way
*Portability: Carrying handle, lightweight and compact size.
*Water-resistant keyboard
*Education-specific features and touch-optimized software
*SD Card Reader; documentation says that you can boot the system off an SD card, or a standard USB thumbdrive
*Comes with either Windows XP installed (standard) or Windows XP Professional (an extra $186 on the 2go)

===Software===
Intel announced that its device would run either [[Linux]] or [[Windows XP|Windows XP Professional]]. Intel is not using [[Windows XP Embedded]] as initially planned. Intel has been actively working with various international and local Linux distributions in various countries.

Intel has worked with [[Mandriva]] to customize their Linux distribution for Classmate PC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS4146178789.html |title=Low-cost student laptops to run Mandriva Linux |publisher=Desktoplinux.com |date=2007-03-29 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Mandriva on Classmate PC: A Linux Education for Everyone |url=http://www.olpcnews.com/software/operating_system/mandriva_classmate_linux.html |title=Mandriva on Classmate PC: A Linux Education for Everyone |publisher=OLPC News |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently, the Intel powered classmate PC has been shown to run the following Linux distributions:

*[[Mandriva Linux]](International &amp; Pan-European Linux operating system mandriva.com)
*[[Metasys]] (International Syst in Brazil)

===Latin America===
In [[Latin America]], contingent upon the receipt of sufficient international fund monies, the [[Mexico|Mexican]] and [[Brazil]]ian governments are evaluating whether to buy Intel's or the OLPC's laptop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.digitaltrends.com/article11875.html |title=Intel to Compete with OLPC in Brazil – Computing News – Digital Trends |publisher=News.digitaltrends.com |date=2006-12-07 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless of the hardware chosen, the Brazilian government announced that it would use the Linux operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Paul |first=Ryan |url=http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20061206-8371.html |title=Intel and OLPC compete for edu-laptop market in Brazil |publisher=Arstechnica.com |date=2006-12-06 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been confirmed that Intel will be shipping the Laptops with [[Mandriva Linux]], Discovery 2007 edition&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.linuxelectrons.com/news/mobile/intels-classmate-mobile-pc-ships-south-america |title=Intel's 'Classmate' Mobile PC Ships to South America |publisher=LinuxElectrons |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the ''Classmate 2.0'' [[Linux distribution]] by the Brazilian company [[Metasys]].

Recently, Venezuelan government ordered 1 million Classmates from Portugal,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2008/09/27/europe/EU-Portugal-Venezuela.php |title=Search - Global Edition - The New York Times |publisher=International Herald Tribune |date=2009-03-29 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theinquirer.net/gb/inquirer/news/2008/09/30/venezuela-portugal-sign |title=Chávez chavs get linux classmates |publisher=The Inquirer |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; one of several bilateral deals that Portuguese officials valued at more than US$3 billion.

Oscar Clarke, President of Intel of Brasil, delivered thirty production units to the Brazilian Ministry of Education (MEC), for evaluation by ''SERPRO'' (Federal Data Processing Service of Brazil).{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}

It is currently available in [[Argentina]] made by 10 diferent brands of manufactures with OS like Linux and Windows also in Paraguay through HITECER S.A - TROVATO CISA GROUP. About the end of 2009, Argentina's government planned to give all the public high school students one of these netbooks. 740 million U$S will be used to give all public schools routers and infrastructure to reduce the digital gap around the country.

===Africa===
In [[Africa]], Intel has also started shipping to [[Libya]] as part of its deal of supplying 150,000 units.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tech.monstersandcritics.com/news/article_1370177.php/Intel_supplies_Libya_with_150000_Classmates |title=Intel supplies Libya with 150,000 Classmates |publisher=Tech.monstersandcritics.com |date=2007-10-31 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Seychelles, Classmate PC were supplied to primary schools as part of Sheikh Khalifa ICT project Seychelles 2010.

===Asia===
In [[Asia]], it has been available in [[Indonesia]] since early March 2008, through two local brands: [[AXIOO International|Axioo]] and [[Zyrex]]. The Zyrex brand, called Anoa, is a rebranded Classmate PC equipped with the Intel ULV 900&amp;nbsp;MHz (400&amp;nbsp;MHz FSB) processor, 512 MB RAM, 2 GB SSD, WiFi, LAN, 7&amp;nbsp;inch screen, 2 USB ports, card reader. The Classmate PC is available in Linux or Windows XP operating system, with the XP version incurring extra cost to cover the licensing.

The Classmate PC is currently available in [[India]] as [[Connoiseur Electronics Pvt.Ltd.]], Smartbook &amp; Classmate PC series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.connoiseur.com/Classmate_Touch_Screen_PC-list.aspx |title=Classmate Touch Screen PC |publisher=Connoiseur.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; This comes with Windows or Ubuntu Linux OS pre-installed.

In late 2007, a deal was made with the [[Vietnam]]ese government to supply local schools with a special Classmate PC for discounted price. As this version is loaded with Hacao Linux, the government was able to avoid operating system licensing fees.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.linuxdevices.com/news/NS4217198426.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe and USA===
The second generation of the device will be available in [[Europe]] and [[USA]], in the hope that more sales will drive down the price.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itpro.co.uk/applications/news/180492/cheap-intel-laptops-coming-to-europe.html |title=Applications: News: Cheap Intel laptops coming to Europe |publisher=ITPro |date=2008-03-20 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Current generation are available from [[CTL]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctlcorp.com |title=CTL Computers, Monitors and More – CTL Corp |publisher=Ctlcorp.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[USA]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classmatepc.com/where-to-buy/NorthAmerica/]&lt;/ref&gt; under CTL's [[2goPC]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.2gopc.com |title=Computer Technology Link |publisher=2Go PC |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; brand as the 2go Classmate PC E10IS,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctlcorp.com/v4/p-872-2go-classmate-pc-e10is-101-netbook-laptop.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt; the 2go Classmate PC E11&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctlcorp.com/v4/p-1059-2go-classmate-pc-e11-101-ruggedized-netbook.aspx |title=2go Classmate PC E11 |publisher=Ctlcorp.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the 2go Convertible Classmate PC NL2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctlcorp.com/v4/p-923-2go-convertible-classmate-pc-nl2-10-hi-res3g-capable-netbook.aspx |title=2go NL2 Hi-Res/3G |publisher=Ctlcorp.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Classmate PC is available from [[CMS Computers]] in the [[United Kingdom]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcretailmag.com/news/29876/Sub-200-PC-steals-show Sub £200 PC steals show], PCRetail, May 16, 2008. Retrieved August 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and most other [[EU|European nations.]]

On May 20, 2008, Italian company [[Olidata]] announced the release of a modded version of the Classmate PC named Jumpc. This version was first on sale in [[Italy]], but by the end of the year it was also available in many [[EU|European]] countries.

On July 31, 2008, Intel, JP Sá Couto (the producer of the ''Tsunami'' Portuguese computers) and the [[Portuguese Government]] headed by Prime Minister [[José Sócrates]] announced the production of the &quot;Magalhães&quot; (a tribute to Portuguese navigator [[Ferdinand Magellan|Magellan]]), a Intel Classmate-based computer that will be produced in [[Portugal]] (by JP Sá Couto) and distributed to Portuguese children in primary education for 50€ (free or at 20€ for students on social aid), as well as being exported to other countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ultimahora.publico.clix.pt/noticia.aspx?id=1337132 Publico: Primeiro computador portátil português pode ser exportado para três continentes] During the presentation the Portuguese government presented the computer as a Portuguese product, when the computer was already on the market in other countries since 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Intel Classmate PC (the 7&quot; version) is available in [[Greece]], and sold as the [[InfoQuest]] &quot;Quest Classmate&quot;, with a blue-coloured exterior. Its specifications include 2 GB storage, Windows XP Professional, no hard drive, no camera, and SD card support. It is sold by various retailers, including [[MediaMarkt]].

Serbian leading IT company &quot;COMTRADE&quot; from April 2009 will introduce &quot;ComTrade CoolBook&quot; netbook (Classmate PC), they already donated 30 netbook's to one Belgrade elementary school.

===Canada===
The Intel Classmate series in Canada is available through [[MDG Computers]] under the following brand names:

– The Intel Clamshell second generation is called the '''MDG Mini 8.9&quot; Rugged Netbook PC''' [http://www.mdg.ca/mini]&lt;br/&gt;
– The Intel Convertible third generation is called the '''MDG Flip 8.9&quot; Touchscreen Netbook PC''' [http://www.mdg.ca/flip]

They are currently being sold through sears.ca, theshoppingchannel.com, and zellers.

In Q4 of 2009 will be introducing the 10.1&quot; versions of both netbooks at retail.

==Comparisons with OLPC project==
The Classmate PC represents Intel's competitive response to the [[OLPC]] XO, whose unusually low prices and use of [[AMD]] chips threatened to steal market share from Intel and other major manufacturers. Although Intel initially criticized the XO laptops for their lack of functionality—Intel's Chairman of the Board, [[Craig Barrett (businessman)|Craig Barrett]], himself claimed consumers wanted the full functionality of a PC—the Classmate PCs are currently being heavily marketed against the XO worldwide. Intel has already secured deals to sell hundreds of thousands of Classmate PCs to [[Libya]], [[Nigeria]] and [[Pakistan]], the same developing countries the [[OLPC]] project had been targeting.&lt;ref&gt;Kraemer et al.: &quot;One Laptop Per Child: Vision vs. Reality&quot;, ''Communications of the ACM'', June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The goals of the Classmate PC project and the OLPC project have some differences. According to Intel: the Classmate PC aims to provide technology that fits into the larger, primarily Windows-based computing environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://download.intel.com/intel/worldahead/pdf/classmatepc_productbrief.pdf?iid=worldahead+ed_cmpc_pdf |title=Product Brief of the Classmate PC |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to the OLPC, the XO breaks from the desktop metaphor to provide a UI ([[Sugar (desktop environment)|Sugar]]) that they feel is more suited to the educational needs of children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.laptop.org/laptop/software/index.shtml |title=One Laptop per Child (OLPC), Software: XO Vision |publisher=Laptop.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the OLPC uses hardware and software highly customized for the educational environment, Intel has argued that the developing world wants to have generic [[Personal computer|PCs]]. In December 2005, Intel publicly dismissed the XO as a 'gadget'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20051212065117/http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/SP263515.htm Reuters AlertNet – World's poorest don't want &quot;$100 laptop&quot; -Intel]&lt;/ref&gt;

Intel joined the OLPC project in July 2007 and was widely expected to work on a version of the project's laptop that used an Intel chip, only to pull out of the project in January 2008. Intel spokesman Chuck Mulloy said it had pulled out because the OLPC organization had asked it to stop backing rival low-cost laptops,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/7171201.stm|work=BBC News|title=One laptop project loses partner|date=January 4, 2008|accessdate= April 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/05/technology/05laptop.html|work=The New York Times|title=Intel Quits Effort to Get Computers to Children|first= John|last=Markoff|date=January 5, 2008|accessdate=April 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; while OLPC's founder [[Nicholas Negroponte]] has accused Intel of underhand sales tactics and trying to block contracts to buy his machines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/7178241.stm|work=BBC News|title=Intel 'undermined' laptop project|date=January 9, 2008|accessdate=April 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Technical comparison===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!
!Classmate PC
!OLPC XO-1&lt;ref&gt;[http://classmatepc.com/productinfo/index.htm#specs&lt;!-- Tech Specs --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
!OLPC XO-1.5&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wiki.laptop.org/images/f/f0/CL1B_Hdwe_Design_Spec.pdf |title=XO-1.5 CL1B Hardware Design specifications |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!Processor
|Intel Atom N270 1.6&amp;nbsp;GHz Processor
Intel Celeron M 900&amp;nbsp;MHz Processor
|AMD Geode LX700@0.8 W + 5536
|Via C7-M (1&amp;nbsp;GHz) ULV CPU
Via VX855 northbridge / southbridge companion chip for peripheral I/O
1 GiByte DDR2 SDRAM system memory, running at 400&amp;nbsp;MHz
Embedded controller for system monitoring
ISA Compatibility: Support for both the MMX and SSE x86 instruction-set extensions
|-
!Display
|8.9&quot; 1024 × 600 color LCD
7&quot; 800 × 480 color LCD&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trustedreviews.com/notebooks/review/2006/09/28/Intel-Classmate-PC-EXCLUSIVE/p1 |title=Intel Classmate PC – EXCLUSIVE – TrustedReviews |publisher=Trustedreviews.com |date=2006-09-28 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
8.9&quot; 1024 x 600 Touch Screen
|[[OLPC XO-1#Display|Low-power]], sunlight readable, user replaceable LED backlight, low cost manufacturing process.
800×600 (color mode), 1200×900 (black and white mode) 7.5-inch LCD&lt;ref&gt;[[XO-1 (laptop)#Hardware|Wikipedia: OLPC XO-1: Hardware]]&lt;/ref&gt;
|7.5in (19&amp;nbsp;cm) color/monochrome dual mode TFT LCD, 1200x900 (200dpi)
Viewing area: 152.4&amp;nbsp;mm x 114.3&amp;nbsp;mm; 6 in x 4.5 in
Sunlight readable
Dedicated display controller (with separate 2-MByte SGRAM frame buffer) supports use of display when CPU is
powered down
Solid state (LED) backlight
|-
!Memory
|1 GB / 512MB DDR-II 256M (Linux only) or 512M SO-DIMM Tech Specs&lt;ref&gt;[http://classmatepc.com/productinfo/index.htm#specs ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|256 MiB dynamic RAM&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://laptop.org/laptop/hardware/specs.shtml |title=One Laptop per Child (OLPC): Laptop Hardware &gt; Specs |publisher=Laptop.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|1 MByte of serial Flash memory provided separately for firmware
Expandable through a single externally accessible SD/MMC memory card socket.
|-
!Operating Systems
|1.[[Pixart|Rxart]] (Argentina only) &lt;br&gt;2.[[Mandriva Linux#Mandriva Linux Discovery|Mandriva Linux Discovery 2007]]&lt;br&gt;3. [[Metasys|Metasys Classmate 2.0]]&lt;br&gt;4. [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu Education Edition for the ClassmatePC]]&lt;br&gt;5. [[Windows XP Professional]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://classmatepc.com/productinfo/index.htm#software Classmate PC : System Configuration : Software]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|1. Customized, low resource version of [[FOSS|open-source]] [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] with the [[Sugar (GUI)|Sugar GUI]] and [[mesh networking]]&lt;br&gt; 3. Customized, low resource version of [[FOSS|open-source]] [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu Linux]] with bundled [[FOSS|open-source]] education applications&lt;br&gt;4. Customized, low resource version of [[Proprietary software|proprietary]] Microsoft Windows XP without mesh networking for $10/laptop&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.technologyreview.com/Infotech/20788/page1/ |title=OLPC Laptop gets Windows, Technology Review, Friday, May 16, 2008 |publisher=Technologyreview.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Fedora 11 base with Sugar 0.84 and Gnome 2.26 [http://wiki.laptop.org/go/Release_notes/10.1.0 Release notes]
|-
! Storage
|16GB / 8 GB / 4 GB Flash (1.8&quot; HDD), 1 GB (Linux only), 2 GB, 4 GB Flash, 30GB HDD&lt;ref name=&quot;classmatepc.com&quot;&gt;http://classmatepc.com/pdf/CMPC_Product_Brief_Sec_Gen_Eng_HiRes.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|1024 MiB SLC NAND flash, high-speed [[flash controller]]
|4 GBytes of NAND Flash memory on motherboard
|-
![[Environmental impact assessment|Environmental Impact]]
|
|[[RoHS]] compliant, 2W power consumption, [[Lifepo4|LiFePO4]] batteries, designed for easy field maintenance to extend the laptop's lifespan&lt;ref name=&quot;XO-1 Hardware Specs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.laptop.org/en/laptop/hardware/specs.shtml|title=OLPC XO-1 Hardware Specifications| accessdate=2008-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|
|-
![[Rugged computer|Ruggedization]]
|Water-resistant keyboard, drop-proof construction, and sturdy, easy-to-clean plastic chassis&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mpccorp.com/products/notebooks/txtbook.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|2&amp;nbsp;mm case walls (instead of typical 1.3&amp;nbsp;mm), ports covered when closed. Dust, water resistant.&lt;ref name=&quot;XO-1 Hardware Specs&quot;/&gt;
|
|-
!Weight
|1.25&amp;nbsp;kg–1.49&amp;nbsp;kg&lt;ref&gt;[http://classmatepc.com/productinfo/index.htm#specs ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|1.45&amp;nbsp;kg- 1.58&amp;nbsp;kg&lt;ref name=&quot;laptop.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://laptop.org/laptop/hardware/specs.shtml |title=One Laptop per Child (OLPC): Laptop Hardware &gt; Specs |publisher=Laptop.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|1.5&amp;nbsp;kg  Size: 245mm (9.65&quot;) _ 230mm (9&quot;) _ 30.5mm (1.2&quot;)
|-
![[Security]]
|Hardware-based theft deterrent.&lt;ref name=&quot;classmatepc.com&quot;/&gt;
|[[Bitfrost]]
|
|-
!Audio
|Stereo 2 channel audio, built-in speakers and microphone, jack for external output and microphone input&lt;ref name=&quot;classmatepc.com&quot;/&gt;
|AC97-compatible audio audio subsystem; internal stereo speakers and amplifier; internal monophonic microphone; jacks for external headphones and microphone; Analog Devices AD1888 and Analog Devices SSM2211 for audio amplification&lt;ref name=&quot;laptop.org&quot;/&gt; Microphone socket can also act as a data logger input
|Audio based on the AC97 codec, with jacks for external stereo speakers and microphones, Line-out, and Mic-in
|-
!Camera
|1.3 MP (rotated), One-click deployment and locking camera option, integrated 30frame/s @ 640x480,&lt;ref name=&quot;classmatepc.com&quot;/&gt;
|Integrated camera at 640×480 resolution at 30FPS&lt;ref name=&quot;laptop.org&quot;/&gt;
|Integrated color video camera
640 x 480 resolution
Full frame rate (30fps)
|-
!Connectivity
|10/100M Ethernet WLAN 802.11b/g/n WLAN with antenna, fMesh support (Linux only),&lt;ref name=&quot;classmatepc.com&quot;/&gt; Security: WPA, WPA-PSK, WPA2, WPA2-PSK
|Integrated 802.11b/g (2.4&amp;nbsp;GHz) interface; Mesh 802.11s networking supported&lt;ref name=&quot;laptop.org&quot;/&gt;
|Wireless networking using an “Extended Range” 802.11b/g and 802.11s (mesh) Marvell 8388 wireless chip, chosen due to its ability to autonomously forward packets in the mesh even if the CPU is powered off. When connected in a mesh, it is run at a low bitrate (2 Mbit/s) to minimize power consumption. Despite the wireless chip's minimalism, it supports WPA.[25] An ARM processor is included.
|}

==Media appearance==
*[[BBC World]] broadcast a program about the [[OLPC]] and the Classmate PC on 10 January 2008.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*[http://download.intel.com/intel/worldahead/pdf/classmatepc_productbrief.pdf?iid=worldahead+ed_cmpc_pdf Intel reference hardware specifications sheet]
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Classmate PC}}
*[http://www.classmatepc.com Intel Classmate PC – Official Portal]
*[http://kidcomputers.com/catalog/Laptops Kid Computers Classmate PC Model]
*[http://www.pixartargentina.com.ar Argentinian Linux of education government – Official Portal]
*[http://blog.mandriva.com/2007/10/31/an-open-letter-to-steve-ballmer/ An open letter to Steve Ballmer] by François Bancilhon ([[Mandriva]]), October 31, 2007.
*[http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/07_28/b4042045.htm?chan=rss_topStories_ssi_5  Business week: OLPC and Classmate PC trying to bury the hatchet] – Jul 2, 2007
*[http://enterprise.linux.com/article.pl?sid=07/05/23/1827201&amp;from=rss Five days with the Classmate PC and Mandriva] – May 24, 2007
*[http://www.engadget.com/2007/03/02/brazils-first-intel-classmate-pc-given-to-o-presidente/#comments Engadget: Brazil's first Intel Classmate PC given to President of Brazil] – March, 03 2007
*[http://www.engadget.com/2006/09/28/intel-announces-specs-production-dates-for-classmate-pc/ Engadget: Classmate PC specs] – September 28, 2006
*[http://www.trustedreviews.com/article.aspx?art=3485 Trusted Reviews: Exclusive Look at the Eduwise] – September 28, 2006
*[http://www.laptopical.com/eduwise.html Laptopical's Overview of the Eduwise Notebook] – May 5, 2006
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20060713190608/http://wcitvideo.com/?p=15 – video of the Intel Eduwise prototype] – June 3, 2006
*[http://education.zdnet.com/?p=1602 Additional images, specifications, and video], ZDNet Education
*[http://www.radiomundial.com.ve:8000/yvke/files/20080913_chavez_computadoras_portugalavi_132.flv President Chavez from Venezuela promotes the Classmate], Radio YVKE Mundial
*http://www.comtradegroup.com/ComTradeGroup/Media/News.aspx?articleId=153 Serbian company COMTRADE, and its web page devoted to promote ClassMate netbook. 2009

{{Netbooks}}
{{Linux mini computers}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Classmate Pc}}
[[Category:Appropriate technology]]
[[Category:Information technology and development]]
[[Category:Subnotebooks]]
[[Category:Linux-based devices]]
[[Category:Intel Corporation]]

[[de:Classmate PC]]
[[es:Classmate PC]]
[[fr:Classmate PC]]
[[id:Classmate PC]]
[[it:Classmate PC]]
[[nl:Classmate PC]]
[[ja:クラスメイトPC]]
[[pl:Classmate PC]]
[[pt:Classmate PC]]
[[ru:Classmate PC]]
[[sv:Classmate PC]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
