<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="833671" ns="0" title="Lincoln University (Pennsylvania)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=July 2009}}
{{Missing information|Leadership, governing board, relationship with faculty, student governance, faculty governance, constituent schools, endowment, fundraising|date=October 2010}}
{{Infobox university
 |name              = Lincoln University originally Ashmun Institute
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Lincoln University logo.png
 |image_size        = 250px
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = ''&quot;If the Son shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed.&quot;''
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = {{Start date and age |1854|04|29}}
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Commonwealth System of Higher Education|State-related]], [[Historically black colleges and universities|Historically black]]
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = $23 Million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lincoln.edu/academicaffairs/reports06-07/botreport021207.html|title=Faculty Update of Board of Trustees Meeting 2/11/2007|last=DeBoy|first=James L.|date=2/12/2007|publisher=LINCOLN UNIVERSITY}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = [[Ivory V. Nelson]]
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 2,649
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Chester County, Pennsylvania|Chester County]]
 |state             = [[Pennsylvania]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = &lt;br&gt;[[United States]]
 |coor              = {{Coord|39|48|30|N|75|55|40|W|type:edu_region:US-PA|display=title,inline}}
 |campus            = [[Rural]] {{convert|422|acre|km2|1}}
 |former_names      = Ashmun Institute
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = [[Orange (color)|Orange]] and [[Blue (color)|Blue]]&lt;br&gt;{{color box|#FF7F00}} {{color box|#003366}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = Lions
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = 
 |affiliations      = 
 |website           = [http://www.lincoln.edu/ www.lincoln.edu]
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = 
}}

'''Lincoln University''' ('''LU''') is the United States' first degree-granting [[Historically black colleges and universities|historically black university]].  It is located near the town of [[Oxford, Pennsylvania|Oxford]] in southern [[Chester County, Pennsylvania|Chester County]], [[Pennsylvania]]. The university also hosts a Center for Graduate Studies in the [[City of Philadelphia]].  Lincoln University provides undergraduate and graduate coursework to approximately 2,500 students.  As former president Dr. [[Horace Mann Bond]] noted in his book ''Education for Freedom: A History of Lincoln University, Pennsylvania'', with the college's founding in 1854, &quot;This was the first institution founded anywhere in the world to provide a higher education in the arts and sciences for youth of African descent.&quot;  

Lincoln University has an impressive list of notable alumni which includes: U.S. Supreme Court Justice, [[Thurgood Marshall]]; Harlem Renaissance poet, [[Langston Hughes]]; musical legend, [[Cab Calloway]]; the first President of Nigeria, [[Nnamdi Azikiwe]]; the first President of Ghana, [[Kwame Nkrumah]]; song artist and activist, [[Gil Scott-Heron]]; Tony Award winning actor, [[Roscoe Lee Browne]]; and architect of the debate team portrayed in the film, ''The Great Debaters'', [[Melvin B. Tolson]]. 

Today, Lincoln University provides a liberal arts and science-based undergraduate core curriculum and select graduate programs to prepare students of every [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]] and nationality.  

The ''Lincoln University Urban Center'' (''LUUC'') is an extension campus in the [[University City, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|University City]] section of Philadelphia, where [[Drexel University]] and [[University of Pennsylvania]] are also located. This campus offers Graduate level programs and continuing education.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.lincoln.edu/luuc/index.html Lincoln University Urban Center]&lt;/ref&gt;  After the renovation that was started in Fall of 2007 is completed, the Urban Center will be known as ''Lincoln University Plaza''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=Inland Real Estate Auctions sells Jos. A. Cacciatore &amp; Co.-owned timber loft development property in UIC neighborhood for $6.25 million|publisher=Heather Pilewski|date=January 11, 2007|url=http://www.inlandgroup.com/news/press_intermediate.asp?index=469|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080526100749/www.inlandgroup.com/news/press_release.asp|archivedate=May 26, 2008}}  Press release about funding of Lincoln University Plaza renovations&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In 1854 Rev. [[John Miller Dickey]], a [[Presbyterian]] minister, and his wife, Sarah Emlen Cresson, a [[Quaker]], founded Ashmun Institute, later named Lincoln University.  They named it after  [[Jehudi Ashmun]], a religious leader and social reformer.  They founded the school for the education of African Americans, who had few opportunities for higher education.  
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; |'''Presidents'''
|-
|[[John Miller Dickey]] {{Ref label|Dickey|A|none}} 
|1854–1856 
|-
|John Pym Carter
|1856-1861
|-
|John Wynne Martin
|1861-1865 
|-
|Isaac Norton Rendall
|1865-1906 
|-
|John Ballard Rendall
|1906-1924 
|-
|Walter Livingston Wright*
|1924-1926
|-
|William Hallock Johnson
|1926-1936
|-
|Walter Livingston Wright
|1936-1945 
|-
|[[Horace Mann Bond]] {{Ref label|Bond|B|none}}
|1945-1957 
|-
|Armstead Otey Grubb*
|1957-1960
|-
|Donald Charles Yelton*
|1960-1961
|-
|[[Marvin Wachman]]
|1961-1969
|-
|Bernard Warren Harleston*
|1970-1970
|-
|Herman Russell Branson
|1970-1985
|-
|Donald Leopold Mullett*
|1985-1987
|-
|[[Niara Sudarkasa]]
|1987-1998
|-
|James Donaldson*
|1998-1999
|-
|[[Ivory V. Nelson]]
|1999-Present
|-
!*Acting president
|}
John Miller Dickey was the first president of the college. He encouraged some of his first students: James Ralston Amos (1826-1864), his brother Thomas Henry Amos (1825-1869), and Armistead Hutchinson Miller (1829/30-1865), to support the establishment of [[Liberia]] as a colony for African Americans.  Each of the men became ordained ministers. 

In 1866, Ashmun Institute was renamed Lincoln University after the assassination of [[President]] [[Abraham Lincoln]].

The college attracted highly talented students from numerous states, especially during the long decades of legal [[Racial segregation|segregation]] in [[Southern United States|the South]].  As may be seen on the list of notable alumni (link below), many went on to achievements in careers in academia, public service, the arts and many other fields. 

In 1945 Dr. [[Horace Mann Bond]], an alumnus of Lincoln, was selected as the first African-American president of the university.  During his 12-year tenure, he continued to do social science research, and helped support the important civil rights case of ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'', decided in 1954 by the [[US Supreme Court]].  He established an important relationship with the collector [[Albert C. Barnes]], who ensured Lincoln University had a role in the management of his art collection, the [[Barnes Foundation]].

In 1972 Lincoln University formally associated with the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania as a [[Commonwealth System of Higher Education|state-related]] institution.   

From 1854 to 1954, Lincoln University graduates accounted for 20 percent of Black physicians and over 10 percent of Black lawyers in the United States.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}
==Academics==
According to ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'', Lincoln University ranks number 27th out of 81 in the 2009 magazine’s first ranking of undergraduate education at HBCUs. It is ranked as a Tier One school on the list.  Lincoln University shares its #27 ranking with [[Oakwood University]] and the [[University of Maryland Eastern Shore]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/t1_hbcu_brief.php?s_cid=related-links:TOP|title=College Rankings|publisher=''[[U.S. News and World Report]]''|accessdate=2008-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lincoln University's &quot;International and Study Abroad Program&quot; had student participation in Service Learning Projects in the countries of Ecuador, Argentina, Spain, Ireland, Costa Rica, Japan, France, Cambodia, Zambia, Liberia, Ghana, Kenya, Russia, Australia, Thailand, the Czech Republic, Mexico, and South Africa.

The new Lincoln-Barnes Visual Arts program is a collaboration between Lincoln University and the Barnes Foundation.  It established a Visual Arts program that leads to a Bachelor's of Fine Arts.

Lincoln University offers 37 undergraduate majors, 22 undergraduate minors, and 5 Pre-Professional (Dentistry, Engineering, Law, Medicine, and Veterinary Science) programs.

===Schools===
[[Image:Lincoln University.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Student Union at Lincoln University]]
;School of Humanities
*English and Mass Communications
*Foreign Languages &amp; Literatures
*Philosophy and Religion
*Visual and Performing Arts
*Horace Mann Bond Honors Program

;School of Natural Sciences &amp; Mathematics
*Biology
*Chemistry
*Environmental Science
*Lincoln's Excellent Academic Program in Science (LEAPS) through the [[National Science Foundation]]
*Mathematics &amp; Computer Science
*Physics

;School of Social Sciences &amp; Behavioral Studies
*Business &amp; Information Technology
*Criminal Justice
*Education
*HPER (Health, Physical Education, Recreation)
*History &amp; Political Science
*Psychology
*Sociology &amp; Anthropology

;School of Graduate Studies
*Master of Human Services (MHS)
*Master of Education (M.Ed)
*Master of Reading (MSR)
*Master of Science in Administration (MSA)

==Campus==
Lincoln University main campus is {{convert|422|acre|km2}} with 56 buildings totaling over one million gross square feet. There are fifteen residence halls that accommodate over 1,600 students. The dormitories range from small dorms such as Alumni Hall, built in 1870; and Amos Hall, built in 1902, to the new coed 400-bed apartment-style living (ASL) suites built in 2005.  A $40.5 million, four-story, {{convert|150000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Science and General Classroom High Technology Building completed in December 2008.  A $26.1 million {{convert|60000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} International Cultural Center construction began on April 10, 2008, that is also now completed.

One of the most visible landmarks on campus is the Alumni Memorial Arch, located at the entrance to the university.  The arch was dedicated by President [[Warren G. Harding]] in 1921 to the Lincoln men who served in World War I.  The Mary Dod Brown Memorial Chapel is the center for campus religious activities.  This Gothic structure was built in 1890 and contains a 300-seat main auditorium and a 200-seat fellowship hall.

Vail Memorial Hall, built in 1899 and expanded in 1954, served as the library until 1972.  The facility houses executive administrative offices including the President, Vice Presidents, and other staff.

The [[Langston Hughes]] Memorial Library (LHML), named after the famous alumnus, houses more than 176,000 volumes, and subscribes to more than 600 current periodicals annually.  A substantial number of the library’s periodicals are on microfilm and can be accessed electronically through the school’s website.  LHML is equipped with the JSTOR database for online academic proprietary research tools.  JSTOR includes archives of over one thousand leading academic journals across multiple disciplines, as well as selected monographs.  A separate section of the library contains special African-American collections.  This includes the personal papers and artifacts of renowned poet Langston Hughes (class of 1929).

The completely renovated Student Union Building contains the bookstore, café, two new television studios and a radio studio, postal services, and multipurpose rooms.  The [[Thurgood Marshall]] Living Learning Center, along with the Student Union Building, are the centers for campus social and meeting activities.  Marshall graduated in the class of 1930, directed the [[NAACP]]'s [[Legal Defense Fund]] in groundbreaking cases, and became the first African American appointed as justice to [[US Supreme Court]]. 

Manuel Rivero Hall is the athletic and recreation center at Lincoln University.  The main gymnasium seats 2,500 for athletic and convocation activities.  A separate full size auxiliary gymnasium, Olympic-size swimming pool, training room facilities, wrestling room, and eight lane bowling alley are contained in this facility. 

Lincoln University Plaza, a six-story building in the [[University City, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|University City]] section of Philadelphia, houses the Graduate Center.

==Student activities==
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3px&quot; style=&quot;width: 24em; float: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; text-align:left;&quot;
!Alma Mater
|-
|Dear Lincoln, Dear Lincoln
To Thee We'll e're be true!
The golden hours we've spent beneath
The dear old Orange and Blue

Will live fore'er in memory,
As guiding stars through life;
For thee our Alma Mater dear,
We'll rise in our might.

For we love every inch of thy sacred soil
Every tree on thy campus green;
And for thee with our might
We will ever toil
That thou mightest be supreme.

We'll raise thy standard to the sky,
Midst glory and honor fly;
And constant and true,
We will live for thee anew,
Our Dear Old Orange and Blue
Hail! Hail! Lincoln!
|-
!A. Dennee Bibb, '11
|}

;Honor Societies
* [[Alpha Chi]] - National Honor Scholarship Society
* [[Alpha Kappa Delta]] National Sociology Honor Society
* [[Alpha Mu Gamma]] National Foreign Language Honor Society
* [[Beta Beta Beta]] National Biological Science Honor Society
* Beta Kappa Chi Honorary Scientific Society
* Chi Alpha Epsilon National Honor Society (Act/T.I.M.E)
* Dobro Slovo - The National Slavic Honor Society
* Iota Eta Tau Honor Society
* [[Omicron Delta Epsilon]] International Honorary Society in Economics
* Phi Iota Sigma Foreign Language Honor Society
* Phi Kappa Epsilon Honor Society
* [[Pi Sigma Alpha]] National Political Science Honor Society
* [[Psi Chi]] National Psychology Honor Society
* [[Sigma Tau Delta]] English Honor Society
* [[Sigma Beta Delta]] Business Honors Society
* [[Kappa Delta Pi]] - Tau Zeta Chapter International Honor Society in Education

;Academic Organizations
* Accounting Club 
* Arabic Club
* Biology Club
* Business and Economics Club
* Chemistry Club
* Chinese Club
* Education Club
* French Club
* Japanese Club
* Music Majors Club
* [[Melvin B. Tolson]] Society (English)
* [[Thurgood Marshall]] Law Society
* National Society of Black Engineers
* National Association of Black Accountants
* Organization for Political Awareness
* Psychology Club
* [[Society of Physics Students]]
* Russian Club
* Society for Math and Computer Science
* Sociology Club
* Spanish Club

;Student Organization and Clubs
* Boys 2 Men Mentoring Program
* Class Clubs (4) 
* Deuce Drill Team
* Forensic Society
* Fun 4 Life
* Gay Straight Alliance (GSA)
* International Club
* Lincoln People For (LP4)
* Lincoln University Concert Choir
* The Lincoln University Dance Troupe
* Lincoln University Gospel Choir
* Lincoln University Jazz Ensemble
* The Lincoln University Orange Crush Marching Band 
* Lincoln University Volunteer Center
* [[NAACP]]
* National Coalition of 100 Black Women
* National Council for Negro Women
* People Standing United (PSU)
* Sisters That Are Respected Seriously (S.T.A.R.S.)
* Students Against A.I.D.S.
* Student Leader Network
* We Are One
* Ziana Fashion Club

;Student Publications, Radio, and Television
* Newspaper - The Lincolnian
* Yearbook - The Lion
* Campus Radio Station - WWLU
* Campus Television Station - LUC-TV

;[[National Pan-Hellenic Council]] Organizations
* [[Alpha Phi Alpha]] - Nu Chapter, 1912
* [[Omega Psi Phi]] -  Beta Chapter, 1914
* [[Kappa Alpha Psi]] - Epsilon Chapter, 1915
* [[Phi Beta Sigma]] -  Mu Chapter, 1922
* [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] -  Epsilon Nu Chapter, 1969 
* [[Delta Sigma Theta]] - Zeta Omega Chapter, 1969
* [[Zeta Phi Beta]] -  Delta Delta Chapter, 1970
* [[Sigma Gamma Rho]] -  Xi Theta Chapter, 1995
* [[Iota Phi Theta]] -  Epsilon Epsilon Chapter, 2000

;Social Fellowships and Service Organizations
* Groove Phi Groove - Lion Chapter
* [[Swing Phi Swing Social Fellowship Incorporated]]

===Athletics===
Lincoln University participates in the NCAA as a Division II institution. Lincoln has won 17 NCAA Division III Track &amp; Field championships since 1985. Lincoln competes as a Division II member of the [[Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association]] and, the [[Eastern College Athletic Conference]]. 

The Lincoln Lions compete in intercollegiate athletics in the following sports: Baseball, Soccer (Men &amp; Women), Basketball (Men &amp; Women), Volleyball, Indoor Track (Men &amp; Women), Tennis (Men &amp; Women), Outdoor Track (Men &amp; Women), Cross-Country (Men &amp; Women), Bowling, Softball, and Football.

The success of the Track and Field program led to the creation of the co-ed athletic fellowship of Track Phi Track at Lincoln in 1981. Some of the requirements include being an All-American and/or striving to become an All-American, meeting and exceeding academic requirements in your major, and participation in Lincoln's Track &amp; Field program for four years.

On {{Start date|2006|04|11}}, Lincoln's Board of Trustees voted to revive the football program, and establish Marching &amp; Pep Bands. The University has petitioned for membership in the [[Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association|CIAA]], of which Lincoln was a founding member.  Lincoln will be moving from the NCAA's Division III to Division II. A club football team is scheduled for the 2008 followed with a full Division II schedule in 2009.  Fielding its first football team in 48 years on August 30, 2008, Lincoln defeated [[George Mason University]], 34-7.  Lincoln lost its final nine games of 2008, but improved to 3-7 in 2009.

The men's basketball team achieved a 46-12 record from 2004- 2006 seasons. The 2005-2006 season witnessed Lincoln's first national basketball ranking, led by &quot;All American&quot;, D3 Hoops &amp; Basketball News &quot;National Player of the Year&quot; Kyle Myricks.  ESPN dubbed him D3's &quot;Most Exciting Player&quot;. The Lions made the sweet sixteen for the first time in school history.

On {{Start date|2006|12|02}}, Lincoln's basketball team set 5 Division III records in a 201-78 victory over [[Ohio State University, Marion Campus|Ohio State Marion]]. Records included points scored in a half, and points scored in a game, as well as the NCAA record for margin of victory.&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/09/sports/ncaabasketball/09lincoln.html?r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin|title=University on the Defensive for Scoring 201 Points|accessdate=2006-12-12|last=Caldwell|first=Dave|date=2006-12-09|publisher=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lincoln University and the Barnes Foundation==
As president of Lincoln University (1945-1957), Dr. [[Horace Mann Bond]] formed a friendship with [[Albert C. Barnes|Albert Barnes]], philanthropist and art collector who established the [[Barnes Foundation]].  Barnes took a special interest in the institution and built a relationship with its students.  In his will Barnes gave Lincoln University the privilege of naming four of the five directors originally defined as the number for the governing board of the [[Barnes Foundation]]. The number of directors has since increased in efforts to correct the collection's protracted financial difficulties. This has diluted Lincoln's influence over the valuable collection, now valued at over two billion dollars.

Philanthropist and art collector Albert C. Barnes had an interest in helping underserved youth and populations.  Barnes intended his collection be used primarily as a teaching resource.  He limited the number of people who could view it, and for years even the kinds of people, with a preference for students and working class.  Visitors still must make appointments in advance to see the collection, and only a limited number are allowed in the galleries at one time.  

In the mid-20th century, local government restricted traffic to the current campus, located in a residential neighborhood.  Barnes' constraints, local factors, and management issues pushed the Foundation near bankruptcy by the 1990s. Supporters began to explore plans to move the collection to a more public location and maintain it to museum standards.  To raise money for needed renovations to the main building to protect the collection, the Foundation sent some of the most famous Impressionist and Modern paintings on tour.  

In 2002, the Barnes Foundation contested Albert C. Barnes' [[Will (law)|will]], arguing that the Merion location of the collection and small number of Board members limited the Foundation's ability to sustain itself financially.  [[Governor of Pennsylvania|Pennsylvania Governor]] [[Edward Rendell]] brokered a settlement in 2005 between the Barnes Foundation and Lincoln University.

==Notable alumni==
[[Image:LangstonHughe_25.jpg|thumb|right|90px|[[Langston Hughes]]]]
{{Main|List of Lincoln University (Pennsylvania) alumni}}
Lincoln University has the distinction of having seven alumni who founded the following colleges and universities in the United States and abroad:  [[South Carolina State University]], Livingstone University, [[Albany State University]], [[Texas Southern University]], Ibibio State College (Nigeria) and the Kwame Nkruma University of Science and Technology (Ghana).{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

Lincoln University has two alumni being honored with commemorative first-class U.S. Stamps by the United States Postal Service: [[Thurgood Marshall]] (BA 1930) and [[Langston Hughes]] (BA 1929).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Black Heritage Stamp Series|url=http://faq.usps.com/eCustomer/iq/usps/request.do?session={9b447760-e017-11e0-dd69-000000000000}&amp;event=5&amp;view%28%29=c{1df45710-57e2-11dc-51b6-000000000000}&amp;objectId=&amp;eksObjectId=&amp;objectType=Case&amp;isJumpEnabled=false&amp;isContentJumpEnabled=false&amp;vendorKey=&amp;objTitle=&amp;versionId=7162&amp;searchProperties=type:natural&amp;naturalAdvance=false&amp;allStr=&amp;phraseStr=&amp;anyStr=&amp;noneStr=&amp;keywordStr=&amp;tTitle=Stamp%20Collecting&amp;topicFromSub=About%20USPS&amp;topicsORSubUrl=&amp;report%280000%29=p{004a9920-6972-11dd-e6c4-000000000000}&amp;bcobjectId={ceff8d00-6974-11dd-e6c4-000000000000}&amp;search=&amp;topicAndSubtopic=Receiving%20Mail$ALL|publisher=The United States Postal Service|accessdate=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable staff==
*[[Irv Mondschein]], track, basketball, and football coach

==Additional reading==
* Horace Mann Bond, ''Education For Freedom'', Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1976 
* Fred Jerome, ''The Einstein File'', ISBN 0-312-28856-5
* {{cite web|url=http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/news/breaking_news/11705771.htm|work=Philadelphia Inquirer|title=The Deal of the Art|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100716185911/http://registration.philly.com/reg/login.do?url=http://www.philly.com/mld/philly/news/breaking_news/11705771.htm|archivedate=May 25, 2005}}{{registration required}}

==Notes==
:'''A.'''{{note_label|Dickey|A|none}}Founder and President of the Board of Trustees Ashmun Institute and Lincoln University
:'''B.'''{{note_label|Bond|A|none}}First Alumni President

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons cat|Lincoln University (Pennsylvania)}}
* [http://www.lincoln.edu/ www.lincoln.edu] - Official web site
* [http://www.lulions.com/ www.lulions.com] Athletics web site
* [http://www.foxnews.com/search-results/m/27531789/too-fat-to-graduate.htm Lincoln University controversy][[Fox News]]

{{Public universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Philadelphia}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund}}

[[Category:Lincoln University (Pennsylvania)| ]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Commonwealth System of Higher Education]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1854]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Chester County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Abraham Lincoln]]

[[es:Universidad Lincoln]]
[[no:Lincoln University (Pennsylvania)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
