<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="83530" ns="0" title="Kristallnacht"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = Kristallnacht
  |Image_Name     = 1938 Interior of Berlin synagogue after Kristallnacht.jpg
  |Imagesize      = 270px
  |Image_Alt      = Photograph of the smashed interior of the Berlin synagogue
  |Image_Caption  = The interior of the [[Fasanenstrasse Synagogue]] in Berlin after ''Kristallnacht''
  |Thumb_Time     =
  |AKA            = Night of Broken Glass
  |Participants   = [[Sturmabteilung|SA stormtroop(er)s]]&lt;/br&gt;German civilians
  |Location       = Nazi Germany and Austria
  |Date           = 9&amp;ndash;10 November 1938
  |Result         =
  |URL            =
}}
'''Kristallnacht''', also referred to as the '''Night of Broken Glass''', and also '''''Reichskristallnacht''''', '''''Pogromnacht''''', and '''''Novemberpogrome''''', was a [[pogrom]] or series of attacks against Jews throughout [[Nazi Germany]] and parts of Austria on 9&amp;ndash;10 November 1938.&lt;ref name=Gilbert42&gt;&quot;ers, leaving the streets covered in pieces of smashed windows&amp;mdash;the origin of the name &quot;Night of Broken Glass.&quot;  Ninety-one Jews were killed, and 30,000 Jewish men&amp;mdash;a quarter of all Jewish men in Germany&amp;mdash;were taken to [[Internment#Concentration camps|concentration camps]], where they were tortured for months, with over 1,000 'German Mobs' Vengeance on Jews,&quot; ''The Daily Telegraph'', 11 November 1938, cited in [[Martin Gilbert|Gilbert, Martin]]. ''Kristallnacht: Prelude to Destruction''. Harper Collins, 2006, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

Jewish homes were ransacked, as were shops, towns and villages, as [[Sturmabteilung|SA stormtroopers]] and civilians destroyed buildings with sledgehammers.&lt;ref name=Gilbert13/&gt; Around 1,668 [[synagogue]]s were ransacked, and 267 set on fire. In Vienna alone 95 synagogues or houses of prayer were destroyed.&lt;ref name=Gilbert30&gt;Gilbert, pp. 30–33.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Martin Gilbert]] writes that no event in the history of German Jews between 1933 and 1945 was so widely reported as it was happening, and the accounts from the foreign journalists working in Germany sent shock waves around the world.&lt;ref name=Gilbert13&gt;Gilbert, pp. 13–14.&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Times'' wrote at the time: &quot;No foreign propagandist bent upon blackening Germany before the world could outdo the tale of burnings and beatings, of blackguardly assaults on defenceless and innocent people, which disgraced that country yesterday.&quot;&lt;ref name=Gilbert41&gt;&quot;A Black Day for Germany,&quot; ''The Times'', 11 November 1938, cited in Gilbert, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

The trigger of the attacks was the assassination of German diplomat [[Ernst vom Rath]] by [[Herschel Grynszpan]], a German-born Polish Jew in Paris, France. ''Kristallnacht'' was followed by further economic and political persecution of Jews, and is viewed by historians as part of Nazi Germany's broader [[racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial policy]], and the beginning of the [[Final Solution]] and the [[Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutchinson 1998&quot;&gt;{{cite book|coauthors=Multiple authors|title=The Hutchinson Encyclopedia 1998 edition|publisher=Helicon Publishing|location=England|year=1998|edition=18 (1998)|series=Hutchinson Encyclopedias|volume=1998|pages=1199|chapter=Kristallnacht|isbn=1-85833-951-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology==
The incident was originally referred to as ''die Kristallnacht'' (literally &quot;crystal night&quot;), alluding to the enormous number of shop windows broken that night. The prefix Reichs- (imperial) was later added (''Reichskristallnacht'') as a sardonic comment on the Nazis' propensity to add this prefix to various terms and titles like ''[[Reichsführer]]''-SS or ''[[Reichsmarschall]]''.

==Background==
{{see|History of the Jews in Austria|History of the Jews in Germany|Nuremberg Laws}}

===Early Nazi persecutions===
In the [[1920s]], most German Jews were fully integrated into German society as German citizens. They served in the German army and navy and contributed to every field of German science, business and culture. {{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} Conditions for the Jews began to change after the appointment of [[Adolf Hitler]] as [[Chancellor of Germany]], who was the leader of the [[Nazi]] group, on 30 January 1933, and the [[Enabling Act of 1933|assumption of power]] by Hitler after the [[Reichstag fire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nazi Germany - dictatorship|url=http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/Nazi_Germany_dictatorship.htm|author=Trueman, Chris|accessdate= 2008-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hitler's Enabling Act|url=http://www.historyplace.com/worldwar2/timeline/enabling.htm|accessdate=2008-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; From its inception, Hitler's regime moved quickly to introduce [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|anti-Jewish policies]]. The 500,000 Jews in Germany, who accounted for only 0.76% of the overall population, were singled out by the [[Nazi propaganda]] machine as an enemy within who were responsible for [[Dolchstoßlegende|Germany's defeat]] in the [[World War I|First World War]] and for her subsequent economic difficulties, such as the [[Inflation in the Weimar Republic|1920s hyperinflation]] and [[Great Depression in Central Europe|Great Depression]].&lt;ref name=Gilbert23&gt;Gilbert, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1933, the German government enacted a series of [[Anti-Jewish legislation in prewar Nazi Germany|anti-Jewish laws]] restricting the rights of German Jews to earn a living, to enjoy full citizenship and to educate themselves, including the ''[[Law for the Restoration of the Professional Civil Service]]'', which forbade Jews to work in the civil service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Refugee Scholars:Conversations with Tess Simpson|last=Cooper|first=R.M.|location=Leeds|year=1992|pages=31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The subsequent 1935 [[Nuremberg Laws]] stripped German Jews of their citizenship and forbade Jews to marry non-Jewish Germans.

The result of these laws was the exclusion of Jews from German social and political life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Holocaust|url=http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005143|accessdate=2008-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many sought asylum abroad; thousands did manage to leave, but as [[Chaim Weizmann]] wrote in 1936, &quot;The world seemed to be divided into two parts — those places where the Jews could not live and those where they could not enter.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Manchester Guardian'', 23 May 1936, cited in A.J. Sherman, ''Island Refuge, Britain and the Refugees from the Third Reich, 1933–1939'', (London, Elek Books Ltd, 1973), p.112, also in [http://christianactionforisrael.org/antiholo/evian/evian.html The Evian Conference — Hitler's Green Light for Genocide] by Annette Shaw&lt;/ref&gt;  To provide help [[Évian Conference|an international conference]] was held on 6 July 1938 to address the issue of Jewish and [[Romani people|Gypsy]] immigration to other countries.  By the time the conference was held, more than 250,000 Jews had fled Germany and [[Austria]], which had been [[Anschluss|annexed by Germany]] in March 1938. However, more than 300,000 German and Austrian Jews were still seeking shelter from oppression. As the number of Jews and Gypsies wanting to leave grew, the restrictions against them also grew, with many countries tightening their rules for admission.

By 1938, Germany &quot;had entered a new radical phase in [[antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] activity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Eric. ''The Nazi Terror – Gestapo, Jews and Ordinary Germans''. United States: Basic Books, 1999, pg 117.&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians believe that the Nazi government had been contemplating a planned outbreak of violence against the Jews and were waiting for an appropriate provocation; there is evidence of this planning dating to 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Friedländer, Saul. ''Nazi Germany and The Jews'' – Volume 1: ''The Years of Persecution 1933-1939'', London: Phoenix, 1997, pg 270&lt;/ref&gt; The German historian [[Hans Mommsen]] in a 1997 interview claimed that a major motive for the pogrom was the desire of the ''Gauleiters'' of the NSDAP to seize Jewish property and businesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Mommsen
  | first = Hans
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors =
  | title = Interview with Hans Mommsen
  | work =
  | publisher = Yad Vashem
  |month=December 12 | year=1997| url = http://www1.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%203850.pdf 
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mommsen was quoted as saying: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The need for money by the party organization stemmed from the fact that [[Franz Xaver Schwarz]], the party treasurer, kept the local and regional organizations of the party short of money. In the fall of 1938, the increased pressure on Jewish property nourished the party's ambition, especially since Hjalmar Schacht had been ousted as ''Reich'' minister for economics.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This, however, was only one aspect of the origin of the November 1938 pogrom. The Polish government threatened to extradite all Jews who were Polish citizens, but would stay in Germany, thus creating a burden of responsibility on the German side. The immediate reaction by the Gestapo as to push the Polish Jews — 16,000 persons — over the borderline, but this measure failed due to the stubbornness of the Polish customs officers. The loss of prestige as a result of this abortive operation called for some sort of compensation. Thus, the overreaction to Hershel Grynszpan's attempt against the diplomat Ernst vom Rath came into being and led to the November pogrom.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The background of the pogrom was signified by a sharp cleavage of interests between the different agencies of party and state. While the Nazi party was interested in improving its financial strength on the regional and local level by taking over Jewish property, Hermann Goering, in charge of the Four-Year Plan, hoped to acquire access to foreign currency in order to pay for the import of urgently-needed raw material. Heydrich and Himmler were interested in fostering Jewish emigration&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Mommsen
  | first = Hans
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors =
  | title = Interview with Hans Mommsen
  | work =
  | publisher = Yad Vashem
  |month=December 12 | year=1997| url = http://www1.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%203850.pdf 
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The [[Zionist]] leadership in the [[Mandate Palestine|British Mandate of Palestine]] wrote in February 1938 that according to &quot;a very reliable private source – one which can be traced back to the highest echelons of the SS leadership&quot; there was &quot;an intention to carry out a genuine and dramatic [[pogrom]] in Germany on a large scale in the near future.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Goerg Landauer to Martin Rosenbluth, 8 February 1938, cited in Friedländer, loc.cit.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact the report of the Woodhead Commission on the partition of the British Mandate of Palestine into a Jewish and an Arab State was presented to the British parliament and published on November 9th, the very day of the Kristallnacht.&lt;ref&gt;R.John, S. Hadawi: &quot;The Palestine Diary&quot;, New York 1970, Vol.1 p.285&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expulsion of Polish Jews in Germany===

In August 1938 the German authorities announced that residence permits for foreigners were being cancelled and would have to be renewed. This included German-born Jews of foreign origin. [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] stated that it would not accept [[History of the Jews in Poland|Jews of Polish origin]] after the end of October. In the so-called “Polenaktion”, more than 12,000 Polish-born Jews, among them philosopher and theologian Rabbi [[Abraham Joshua Heschel]] and future literary critic [[Marcel Reich-Ranicki]], were expelled from Germany on 28 October 1938, on Hitler's orders. They were ordered to leave their homes in a single night, and were only allowed one suitcase per person to store their belongings. As the Jews were taken away, their remaining possessions were seized as booty by both the [[Gestapo|Nazi authorities]] and by their neighbors.

The deportees were taken from their homes to railway stations and were put on trains to the Polish border. The Polish border guards sent them back over the river into Germany. This stalemate continued for days in the pouring rain, with the Jews marching without food or shelter between the borders. Four thousand were granted entry into [[Poland]] but the remaining 8,000 were forced to stay at the border. They waited there in harsh conditions to be allowed to enter Poland. A British newspaper told its readers that hundreds &quot;are reported to be lying about, penniless and deserted, in little villages along the frontier near where they had been driven out by the Gestapo and left.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Expelled Jews' Dark Outlook |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article3531693.ece |work=Newspaper article |publisher=The Times |date=1938-11-01 |accessdate=2008-03-12 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conditions in the [[refugee camps]] &quot;were so bad that some actually tried to escape back into Germany and were shot,&quot; recalled a British woman who was sent to help those who had been expelled.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Recollections of Rosalind Herzfled,&quot; Jewish Chronicle, 28 September 1979, page 80; cited in Gilbert, Martin, The Holocaust—The Jewish Tragedy, London: William Collins Sons &amp; Co. Ltd, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vom Rath shooting===
[[File:Herschel Grynszpan nov 7 1938.jpg|thumb|150px|Herschel Grynszpan]]
Among those expelled was the family of Zindel and Rivka Grynszpan, Polish Jews who had emigrated to Germany in 1911 and settled in Hanover. At the trial of [[Adolf Eichmann]] in 1961, Zindel Grynszpan recounted the events of their deportation from Hanover on the night of 27 October 1938: “Then they took us in police trucks, in prisoners’ lorries, about 20 men in each truck, and they took us to the railway station. The streets were full of people shouting: ’Juden raus! Auf nach Palästina!’ ” (&quot;Jews out, out to Palestine!&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Hannah Arendt, ''Eichmann in Jerusalem'', p.228.&lt;/ref&gt;

Their seventeen-year-old son [[Herschel Grynszpan|Herschel]] was living in Paris with an uncle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hutchinson 1998&quot;/&gt; His sister, Berta, sent him a postcard from the Polish border describing the family's expulsion: &quot;No one told us what was up, but we realised this was going to be the end… We haven't a penny. Could you send us something?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GSA&quot;&gt;German State Archives, [[Potsdam]], quoted in Rita Thalmann and Emmanuel Feinermann, ''Crystal night, 9–10 November 1938'', pages 33, 42&lt;/ref&gt; He received the postcard on November 3. On the morning of Monday, November 7, he purchased a revolver and a box of bullets, then went to the German embassy and asked to see an embassy official.  After he was taken to the office of [[Ernst vom Rath]], Herschel shot him three times in the abdomen. Ironically, Vom Rath himself was a professional diplomat with the Foreign Office who expressed known anti-Nazi sympathies, largely based on the Nazi's treatment of the Jews, and was himself under Gestapo investigation for being politically unreliable.&lt;ref&gt;William L. Shirer, ''The Rise And Fall Of The Third Reich'', page 430&lt;/ref&gt;  Grynszpan made no attempt to escape the French police and freely confessed to the shooting. In his pocket, he carried a postcard to his parents with the message &quot;May God forgive me… I must protest so that the whole world hears my protest, and that I will do.&quot;

On 8 November Germany announced the first punitive measures in response to the shooting. Jewish newspapers and magazines were to cease publication immediately. This cut off Jews from their leadership, whose task was to advise and guide them, particularly about emigration. It was a measure, one British newspaper explained, &quot;intended to disrupt the Jewish community and rob it of the last frail ties which hold it together.&quot;  At the time three German Jewish newspapers had a national circulation, and there were four cultural papers, several sports papers, and several dozen community bulletins, of which the one in Berlin had a circulation of 40,000.&lt;ref name=Gilbert23/&gt; The government announced that Jewish children could no longer attend German state elementary schools.  All Jewish cultural activities were also suspended indefinitely. Their rights as citizens had been stripped.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Nazis Planning Revenge on Jews&quot;, ''News Chronicle'', 9 November 1938&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Kristallnacht''==
===Death of Vom Rath===
[[File:Kristallnacht rh telegram pg1.png|thumb|Telegram sent by Reinhard Heydrich, November 9, 1938]]
Vom Rath died of his wounds on 9 November. Word of his death reached Hitler that evening while he was at a dinner commemorating the 1923 [[Beer Hall Putsch]] with several key members of the Nazi party. After intense discussions, Hitler left the assembly abruptly without giving his usual address. Propaganda Minister [[Joseph Goebbels]] delivered the speech instead, in which he commented that &quot;the Führer has decided that… demonstrations should not be prepared or organized by the party, but insofar as they erupt spontaneously, they are not to be hampered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Friedländer, op.cit., pg 268.&lt;/ref&gt; Chief party judge [[Walter Buch]] later stated that the message was clear; with these words Goebbels had commanded the party leaders to organize a pogrom.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Buch to Goring, 13.2.1939, Michaelis and Schraepler, Ursachen, vol.12, p.582 as cited in Friedländer, pg 271.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some leading party officials disagreed with Goebbels’s actions, fearing the diplomatic crisis it would provoke. [[Heinrich Himmler]] wrote &quot;I suppose that it is Goebbels’s megalomania…and stupidity which are responsible for starting this operation now, in a particularly difficult diplomatic situation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Graml, Anti-Semitism, p.13 cited in Friedländer, op.cit., pg 272&lt;/ref&gt; The Israeli historian [[Saul Friedländer]] believes that Goebbels had personal reasons for wanting to bring about ''Kristallnacht''. Goebbels had recently suffered humiliation for the ineffectiveness of his propaganda campaign during the [[Sudetenland#Sudeten Crisis|Sudeten crisis]], and was in some disgrace over an affair with the [[Czechs|Czech]] actress [[Lída Baarová]]. Goebbels thus needed a chance to prove himself in the eyes of Hitler.

At 1:20am on 10 November 1938, [[Reinhard Heydrich]] sent an urgent secret telegram to the [[Sicherheitspolizei|state police]] and the [[Sturmabteilung]] (SA) containing instructions regarding the riots. This included guidelines for the protection of foreigners and non-Jewish businesses and property. Police were instructed not to interfere with the riots unless the guidelines were violated. Police were also instructed to seize Jewish archives from synagogues and community offices, and to arrest and detain &quot;healthy male Jews, who are not too old,&quot; for eventual transfer to [[concentration camp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://motlc.wiesenthal.com/site/pp.asp?c=gvKVLcMVIuG&amp;b=394829 Heydrich's secret instructions regarding the riots in November 1938] ([[Simon Wiesenthal Center]])&lt;/ref&gt;

===Riots===
[[Image:Kristallnacht example of physical damage.jpg|225px|left|thumb|''Kristallnacht'', example of physical damage]]
The timing of the riots varied from unit to unit. The [[Gauleiter]]s started at about 10:30pm, only two hours after news of Vom Rath’s death reached Germany. They were followed by the SA at 11pm, and the SS at around 1:20am.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} Most were wearing civilian clothes and were armed with sledgehammers and axes, and soon went to work on the destruction of Jewish property. The orders given to these men were very specific, however: no measures endangering non-Jewish German life or property were to be taken (synagogues too close to non-Jewish property were smashed rather than burned); Jewish businesses or dwellings could be destroyed but not looted; foreigners (even Jewish foreigners) were not to be the subjects of violence; and synagogue archives were to be transferred to the [[Sicherheitsdienst]] (SD). The men were also ordered to arrest as many Jews as the local jails would hold, the preferred targets being healthy young men.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The SA shattered the storefronts of about 7500 Jewish stores and businesses, hence the appellation ''Kristallnacht'' (Crystal Night).&lt;ref&gt;GermanNotes, http://www.germannotes.com/hist_ww2_kristallnacht.shtml, retrieved 11/26/2007&lt;/ref&gt; Jewish homes were ransacked all throughout Germany. Although violence against Jews had not been explicitly condoned by the authorities, there were cases of Jews being beaten or assaulted.

This [[pogrom]] damaged, and in many cases destroyed, about 200 [[synagogue]]s (constituting nearly all Germany had), many Jewish cemeteries, more than 7,000 Jewish shops, and 29 department stores. Some Jews were beaten to death while others were forced to watch. More than 30,000 Jewish men were arrested and taken to [[concentration camp]]s; primarily [[Dachau concentration camp|Dachau]], [[Buchenwald concentration camp|Buchenwald]], and [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/kristallnacht/kristallnacht_photo2.html The deportation of Regensburg Jews to Dachau concentration camp] ([[Yad Vashem]] Photo Archives 57659)&lt;/ref&gt; The treatment of prisoners in the camps was brutal, but most were released during the following three months on condition that they leave Germany.

The number of German Jews killed is uncertain. The number killed in the two-day riot is most often cited as 91. In addition, it is thought that there were hundreds of suicides. Counting deaths in the concentration camps, around 2,000-2,500 deaths were directly or indirectly attributable to the ''Kristallnacht'' pogrom. A few non-Jewish Germans, mistaken for Jews, were also killed {{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}.

The synagogues, some centuries old, were also victims of considerable violence and vandalism, with the tactics the Stormtroops practiced on these and other sacred sites described as “approaching the ghoulish” by the United States Consul in Leipzig. Tombstones were uprooted and graves violated. Fires were lit, and prayer books, scrolls, artwork and philosophy texts were thrown upon them, and precious buildings were either burned or smashed until unrecognisable. Eric Lucas recalls the destruction of the synagogue that a tiny Jewish community had constructed in a small village only twelve years earlier:

{{quotation|It did not take long before the first heavy grey stones came tumbling down, and the children of the village amused themselves as they flung stones into the many coloured windows. When the first rays of a cold and pale November sun penetrated the heavy dark clouds, the little synagogue was but a heap of stone, broken glass and smashed-up woodwork.' &lt;ref&gt;Lucas, Eric. “The sovereigns”, Kibbutz Kfar Blum (Palestine) 1945, pg 171 cited in Gilbert, op.cit., p 67.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

After this, the Jewish community was fined 1 billion reichsmarks. In addition, it cost 4 million marks to repair the windows.&lt;ref&gt;[[Raul Hilberg]]. ''The destruction of the European Jews'', Third Edition,  (Yale Univ. Press, 2003, c1961), Ch.3.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- The monetary amount of glass smashed by German mobs was calculated to be worth approximately 24 million marks. SOURCE? --&gt;

Events in only recently annexed Austria were no less horrendous. Of the entire ''Kristallnacht'' only the pogrom in Vienna was completed. Most of Vienna's 94 synagogues and prayer-houses were partially or totally destroyed. People were subjected to all manner of humiliations, including being forced to scrub the pavements whilst being tormented by their fellow Austrians, some of whom had been their friends and neighbours.

Official figures released after the event by Reinhard Heydrich stated that 191 Synagogues were destroyed, with 76 completely demolished; 100,000 Jews were arrested; three foreigners were arrested; 174 people were arrested for looting Jewish shops; and 815 Jewish businesses were destroyed.

The ''Daily Telegraph'' correspondent, [[Hugh Greene|Hugh Carleton Greene]], wrote of events in Berlin:

{{quotation|Mob law ruled in Berlin throughout the afternoon and evening and hordes of hooligans indulged in an orgy of destruction. I have seen several anti-Jewish outbreaks in Germany during the last five years, but never anything as nauseating as this. Racial hatred and hysteria seemed to have taken complete hold of otherwise decent people. I saw fashionably dressed women clapping their hands and screaming with glee, while respectable middle-class mothers held up their babies to see the &quot;fun&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Carleton Greene, Hugh. ''Daily Telegraph'', November 11, 1938 cited in [http://mars.vnet.wnec.edu/~grempel/courses/berlin/lectures/17TheRoadtoWar.html &quot;The Road to World War II&quot;], Western New England College.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:1938 Jews arrested during Kristallnacht line up for roll call at Buchenwald.jpg|thumb|left|225px|Jews arrested during ''Kristallnacht'' line up for roll call at Buchenwald, 1938]]

===Concentration camps===
The violence was officially called to a stop by Goebbels on 11 November, but violence continued against the Jews in the concentration camps despite orders requesting “special treatment” to ensure that this did not happen. On 23 November the ''News Chronicle'' of [[London]] published an article on an incident which took place at the concentration camp of [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]]. Sixty-two Jews suffered punishment so severe that the police, “unable to bear their cries, turned their backs”. They were beaten until they fell and, when they fell, they were further beaten. At the end of it, “twelve of the sixty-two were dead, their skulls smashed. The others were all unconscious. The eyes of some had been knocked out, their faces flattened and shapeless”. The 30,000 Jewish men who had been imprisoned during ''Kristallnacht'' were released over the next three months but, by then, over 2,000 had died.

===Aftermath===
[[File:Destroyed Ohel Yaaqov Synagogue.jpeg|thumb|275px|A ruined synagogue in Munich after ''Kristallnacht'']]
[[Hermann Göring]] met with other members of the Nazi leadership on 12 November to plan the next steps after the riot, setting the stage for formal government action. In the transcript of the meeting, Göring said,
&lt;blockquote&gt;'I have received a letter written on the [[Führer]]'s orders requesting that the Jewish question be now, once and for all, coordinated and solved one way or another… I should not want to leave any doubt, gentlemen, as to the aim of today's meeting. We have not come together merely to talk again, but to make decisions, and I implore competent agencies to take all measures for the elimination of the Jew from the German economy, and to submit them to me.' &lt;ref&gt;Conot, Robert. ''Justice at Nuremberg'' New York, NY: Harper and Row, 1983, pp. 164-172.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The persecution and economic damage done to German Jews continued after the pogrom, even as their places of business were ransacked. They were forced to pay &quot;Judenvermögensabgabe&quot;, a collective fine of one billion marks for the murder of vom Rath (equal to roughly $US 5.5 billion in today’s currency), which was levied by the compulsory acquisition of 20% of all Jewish property by the state. Six million Reichsmarks of insurance payments for property damage due to the Jewish community were to be paid to the government instead as &quot;damages to the German Nation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chgs.umn.edu/Histories__Narratives__Documen/Documents_from_the_Holocaust/Post-Kristallnacht_Document/post-kristallnacht_document.html  JudenVermoegersabgabe] (The Center for Holocaust and Genocide Studies)&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of emigrating Jews surged as those who were able, left the country. In the ten months following ''Kristallnacht'', more than 115,000 Jews emigrated from the Reich.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/kristallnacht/frame.htm Jewish emigration from Germany] (USHMM)&lt;/ref&gt; The majority went to other European countries, the US and Palestine, and at least 14,000 made it to [[Shanghai ghetto|Shanghai]], [[China]]. As part of government policy, the Nazis seized houses, shops, and other property the émigrés left behind.

Many of the destroyed remains of Jewish property plundered during Kristallnacht were dumped at a site near [[Brandenburg]], north of Berlin. In October 2008, this dumpsite was discovered by Yaron Svoray, an investigative journalist. The site, the size of four [[American football]] fields, contains an extensive array of personal and ceremonial items looted during the riots against Jewish property and places of worship on the night of 9 November 1938. It is believed the goods were brought by rail to the outskirts of the village and dumped on designated land. Among the items found were glass bottles engraved with the Star of David, [[mezuzot]], painted window sills, and the armrests of chairs found in synagogues, in addition to an ornamental swastika.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/oct/22/secondworldwar-germany | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Kristallnacht remnants unearthed near Berlin | first=Kate | last=Connolly | date=October 22, 2008 | accessdate=May 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Responses to ''Kristallnacht''==
[[File:19381011 NYT frontpage Kristallnacht.png|thumb|left|The front page of ''[[The New York Times]]'' of November 11, 1938 refers to the attacks occurring &quot;under the direction of Stormtroopers and Nazi party members,&quot; but also said that [[Josef Goebbels|Goebbels]] called a stop to it.]]

===From the Germans===
The reaction of non-Jewish Germans to ''Kristallnacht'' was varied. The British historian [[Martin Gilbert]] believes that “many non-Jews resented the round up”,&lt;ref&gt;Gilbert, op. cit., pg 70&lt;/ref&gt; his opinion being supported by German witness Dr. Arthur Flehinger who recalls seeing “people crying while watching from behind their curtains”.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Arthur Flehinger, “Flames of Fury”, Jewish Chronicle, 9 November 1979, page 27 cited in Gilbert, loc. cit.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Bishop Martin Sasse, a leading [[Protestantism|Protestant]] churchman, published a compendium of [[Martin Luther]]'s writings shortly after the ''Kristallnacht''; Sasse &quot;applauded the burning of the synagogues&quot; and the coincidence of the day, writing in the introduction, &quot;On 10 November 1938, on Luther's birthday, the synagogues are burning in Germany.&quot; The German people, he urged, ought to heed these words &quot;of the greatest anti-Semite of his time, the warner of his people against the Jews.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bernd Nellessen, &quot;Die schweigende Kirche: Katholiken und Judenverfolgung,&quot; in Büttner (ed), &lt;cite&gt;Die Deutschen und die Judenverfolgung im Dritten Reich&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 265, cited in Daniel Goldhagen, &lt;cite&gt;Hitler's Willing Executioners&lt;/cite&gt; (Vintage, 1997).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Diarmaid MacCulloch]] argued that Luther's 1543 pamphlet ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies]]'' was a &quot;blueprint&quot; for the ''Kristallnacht''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Diarmaid MacCulloch]], ''[[Reformation: Europe's House Divided, 1490-1700]]''. New York: Penguin Books Ltd, 2004, pp. 666-667.&lt;/ref&gt;

In an article released for publication on the evening of 11 November, Goebbels ascribed the events of ''Kristallnacht'' to the &quot;healthy instincts&quot; of the German people. He went on to explain: &quot;The German people are anti-Semitic. It has no desire to have its rights restricted or to be provoked in the future by parasites of the Jewish race.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Daily Telegraph'', 12 November 1938. Cited in Gilbert, Martin. ''Kristallnacht: Prelude to Destruction.'' Harper Collins, 2006, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;

Eyewitness accounts show the general response.  Reports of the destruction are the main focus of the article.
&lt;blockquote&gt;They ripped up the belongings, the books, knocked over furniture, shouted obscenities,&lt;ref name=&quot;kold&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.kold.com/Global/story.asp?S=8269951&amp;nav=14RT
|authorlink=Esther Harris, Gerhard Weinberg
|title=Kristallnacht Remembered
|publisher=www.kold.com
|accessdate=2008-05-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The scholarly response in that article is very much the same:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Houses of worship burned down, vandalized, in every community in the country where people either participate or watch,&lt;ref name=&quot;kold&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
There are reports of &quot;destroying...family heirlooms&quot; and many other acts of vandalism.&lt;ref name=&quot;kold&quot;/&gt;

===From the global community===
[[File:Plaque on the New Synagogue.JPG|thumb|150px|After 1945 some synagogues were restored. This one in Berlin features a plaque, reading &quot;Never forget,&quot; a common expression around Berlin]]
The ''Kristallnacht'' pogrom sparked international outrage. It discredited pro-Nazi movements in [[Europe]] and [[North America]], leading to eventual decline of their support. Many newspapers condemned ''Kristallnacht'', with some comparing it to the murderous pogroms incited by Imperial [[Russia]] in the 1880s. The [[United States]] recalled its ambassador (but did not break off diplomatic relations) while other governments severed diplomatic relations with Germany in protest. The [[United Kingdom|British]] government approved the [[Kindertransport]] program for refugee children.

As such, ''Kristallnacht'' also marked a turning point in relations between Nazi Germany and the rest of the world. The brutality of the pogrom, and the Nazi government's deliberate policy of encouraging the violence once it had begun, laid bare the repressive nature and widespread anti-Semitism entrenched in Germany, and turned world opinion sharply against the Nazi regime, with some politicians even calling for war. The only private protest against the Germans following Kristallnacht was held on December 6, 1938. [[William Cooper (Aboriginal Australian)|William Cooper]], an Aboriginal Australian, led a delegation of the Australian Aboriginal League on a march through Melbourne to the German Consulate to deliver a petition which condemned the “cruel persecution of the Jewish people by the Nazi government of Germany.” German officials refused to take the document.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/news.aspx/138896&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Kristallnacht'' as a turning point==
''Kristallnacht'' changed the nature of persecution from economic, political, and social to the physical with beatings, incarceration, and murder; the event is often referred to as the beginning of [[the Holocaust]]. In the words of historian Max Rein in 1988, &quot;Kristallnacht came…and everything was changed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Krefeld&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Krefeld|first=Stadt|others=Cited in Johnson, Eric|title=Ehemalige Krefelder Juden berichten uber ihre Erlebnisse in der sogenannten Reichskristallnacht|publisher=Basic Books|location=Krefeld Stadt Archiv|year=1988|series=Krefelder Juden in Amerika|volume=3|pages=117}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Buchenwald Disabled Jews 13132 crop.jpg|left|thumb|250px|Five handicapped Jewish prisoners who arrived in [[Buchenwald]] after ''Kristallnacht''.]]
While November 1938 predated overt articulation of &quot;the [[Final Solution]],&quot; it nonetheless foreshadowed the [[genocide]] to come.  Around the time of ''Kristallnacht'', the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] newspaper &quot;[[Das Schwarze Korps]]&quot; called for a &quot;destruction by swords and flames.&quot; At a conference on the day after the pogrom, [[Hermann Göring]] said: &quot;The Jewish problem will reach its solution if, in any time soon, we will be drawn into war beyond our border—then it is obvious that we will have to manage a final account with the Jews.&quot;&lt;ref name=Gilbert23/&gt;

Specifically, the Nazis managed to achieve in ''Kristallnacht'' all the theoretical targets they set for themselves: confiscation of Jewish belongings to provide finances for the [[military]] buildup to war, separation and [[solitude|isolation]] of the Jews, and most importantly, the move from the [[antisemitism|antisemitic]] policy of [[discrimination]] to one of physical damage, which began that night and continued until the end of [[World War II]].

The event nonetheless showed the public attitude was not solidly behind the [[perpetrator]]s. Many Germans at the time found the [[pogrom]]s troubling, as they equated them with the days of the SA street rule and lawlessness. The British Embassy at [[Berlin]] and British [[Consular]] offices throughout Germany received many protests and expressions of disquiet from members of the German public about the anti-Jewish actions of the time.

== Modern response ==
Many decades later, association with the ''Kristallnacht'' anniversary was cited as the main reason against choosing 9 November (&quot;[[Berlin Wall#The Fall|Schicksalstag]]&quot;), the day the [[Berlin Wall]] came down in 1989, as the new German national [[Public holiday|holiday]]; a different day was chosen (3 October 1990, [[German reunification]]).

[[Avant-garde]] guitarist [[Gary Lucas]]'s 1988 composition &quot;Verklärte Kristallnacht&quot;, which juxtaposes the [[Israel]]i national anthem, &quot;[[Hatikvah]]&quot;, with phrases from &quot;[[Deutschland Über Alles]]&quot; amid wild electronic shrieks and noise, is intended to be a sonic representation of the horrors of Kristallnacht.  It was premiered at the 1988 [[Berlin]] [[Jazz]] Festival and received rave reviews.  (The title is a reference to [[Arnold Schoenberg]]'s 1899 work &quot;[[Verklärte Nacht]]&quot; that presaged his pioneering work on [[atonality|atonal music]]; Schoenberg was an [[Austria]]n Jew exiled by the Nazis).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.berkshireweb.com/rogovoy/interviews/feat010420.html|title=Gary Lucas: Action guitarist by Seth Rogovoy|publisher=www.berkshireweb.com|accessdate=2008-05-20|quote=A knowing reference to Arnold Schoenberg's &quot;Verklarte Nacht,&quot; the piece ironically juxtaposed the Israeli national anthem, &quot;Hatikvah,&quot; with phrases from &quot;Deutschland Uber Alles,&quot; amid wild electronic shrieks and noise. The next day the papers ran a picture of Lucas with the triumphant headline, &quot;It is Lucas!&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The German [[power metal]] band [[Masterplan (band)|Masterplan]]'s debut album, ''[[Masterplan (Masterplan album)|Masterplan]]'' (2003), features an anti-Nazism song entitled &quot;Crystal Night&quot; as the fourth track. The German band [[BAP (German band)|BAP]] published a song titled ''Kristallnaach'' in their [[Cologne]] dialect, dealing with the emotions of the ''Kristallnacht''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bap.de/musik_songtexte.php |title=BAP Songtexte (German) |accessdate=2008-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
*[[Évian Conference]]
*[[Israel's Department Store]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{refbegin|2}}
;Books in English
*{{cite book
  |author=Browning, Christopher R.
  |title=Collected memories: Holocaust history and postwar testimony
  |publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]]
  |location=Madison
  |year=2003
  |isbn=0-299-18984-8
  |series=George L. Mosse Series in Modern European Cultural and Intellectual History}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Mayer, Kurt
  |title=My Personal Brush with History
  |publisher=[[Kurt Mayer, Confluence Books]]
  |location=Tacoma
  |year=2009
  |isbn=978-0-578-03911-4}}
*{{cite book
  | author=Friedlander, Saul
  | title=Nazi Germany and the Jews : Volume 1: The Years of Persecution 1933-1939
  | publisher=Perennial
  |location=New York, NY
  |year=1998
  |isbn=0-06-092878-6}}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Gilbert, Martin
  | title=The Holocaust: the Jewish tragedy
  | year=1986
  | publisher=Collins
  | location=London
  | isbn=0-00-216305-5}}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Johnson, Eric J.
  | title=Nazi terror: the Gestapo, Jews, and ordinary Germans
  | year=1999
  | publisher=[[Basic Books]]
  | location=New York
  | isbn=0-465-04906-0}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Mosse, George L.
  |title=Toward the Final Solution: A History of European Racism
  |publisher=Howard Fertig
  |location=New York
  |year=1978
  |isbn=0-86527-941-1}}
**{{cite book
|author=Mosse, George L.
|title=Confronting history: a memoir
|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press
|location=Madison
|year=2000
|isbn=0-299-16580-9}}
**{{cite book
|author=Mosse, George L.
|title=Nazi culture: intellectual, cultural and social life in the Third Reich
|publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]]
|location=Madison
|year=2003
|isbn=0-299-19304-7}}
**{{cite book
|author=Mosse, George L.
|title=The Crisis of German Ideology : Intellectual Origins of the Third Reich
|publisher=Howard Fertig
|location=New York
|year=1999
|isbn=0-86527-426-6}}
*{{cite book
|author=Schwab, Gerald
|title=The day the Holocaust began: the odyssey of Herschel Grynszpan
|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group|Praeger]]
|location=New York
|year=1990
|isbn=0-275-93576-0}}
*{{cite book
|author=Shirer, William L.
|title=[[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]]
|publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]
|location=New York
|year=1990
|isbn=0-671-72868-7
|authorlink=William L. Shirer}}
*{{cite book
|author=Yahil, Leni
|title=The Holocaust: the fate of European Jewry, 1932-1945
|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]
|location=Oxford [Oxfordshire]
|year=1990
|isbn=0-19-504523-8}}
*{{cite book
|author=Dawidowicz, Lucy
|title=The War Against the Jews: 1933-1945
|publisher=Bantam
|location=UK
|year=1991 (Re-issue)
|isbn=978-0553345322}}

;Books in German
*[[Hans-Dieter Arntz]] &quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot;. Der Novemberpogrom 1938 auf dem Lande - Gerichtsakten und Zeugenaussagen am Beispiel der Eifel und Voreifel, Helios-Verlag, Aachen 2008, ISBN  978-3-938208-69-4
*{{Cite book
  | author=Doscher, Hans-Jurgen
  | title=Reichskristallnacht: Die Novemberpogrome 1938
  | year= 1988
  | publisher=Ullstein
  | language=German
  | isbn=978-3-550-07495-0 }}
*{{Cite book
  | author=Kaul, Friedrich Karl
  | coauthor=Herschel Feibel Grynszpan
  | title=Der Fall des Herschel Grynszpan
  | year=1965
  | publisher=Akademie-Verl
  | location=Berlin
  | language=German}} ''ISBN Unknown. ASIN B0014NJ88M. Available at [http://hgs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/1/2/217.pdf Oxford Journals] (PDF)''
*{{cite book
  |author=Korb, Alexander
  |title=Reaktionen der deutschen Bevölkerung auf die Novemberpogrome im Spiegel amtlicher Berichte
  |publisher=[[VDM Publishing|VDM Verlag]]
  |location=Saarbrücken
  |language=German
  |year=2007
  |ISBN=978-3-8364-4823-9}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Lauber, Heinz
  |title=Judenpogrom: &quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot; November 1938 in Grossdeutschland : Daten, Fakten, Dokumente, Quellentexte, Thesen und Bewertungen (Aktuelles Taschenbuch)
  |publisher=Bleicher
  |language=German
  |year=1981
  |isbn=3-88350-005-4}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Pätzold, Kurt &amp; Runge, Irene
  |title=Kristallnacht: Zum Pogrom 1938 (Geschichte)
  |publisher=Pahl-Rugenstein
  |location=Köln
  |year=1988
  |language=German
  |isbn=3-7609-1233-8}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Pehle, Walter H.
  |title=Der Judenpogrom 1938: Von der &quot;Reichskristallnacht&quot; zum Völkermord
  |publisher=Fischer Taschenbuch Verlag
  |location=Frankfurt am Main
  |year=1988
  |isbn=3-596-24386-6
  |language=German}}
*{{cite book
  |author=Schultheis, Herbert
  |title=Die Reichskristallnacht in Deutschland nach Augenzeugenberichten (Bad Neustadter Beiträge zur Geschichte und Heimatkunde Frankens)
  |publisher=Rotter Druck und Verlag
  |location=Bad Neustadt a. d. Saale
  |year=1985
  |isbn=3-9800482-3-3
  |language=German}}

;Online resources
{{Commons category|Kristallnacht}}
*Hitler 'led henchmen' in Kristallnacht riots, Daily Telegraph, Oct. 21, 2008 [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/3235356/Hitler-led-henchmen-in-Kristallnacht-riots.html]
*Hitler gave the order, Haaretz, Oct. 31, 2008 [http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1032989.html]
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht
  | work = Holocaust studies
  | author = Rabbi Eliahu Ellis &amp; Rabbi Shmuel Silinsky
  | publisher = Aish.com
  | url = http://www.aish.com/holocaust/overview/Kristallnacht.asp
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite news
  | title = Germany commemorates Nazi era 'Kristallnacht'
  | publisher = CNN.com
  | url = http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/europe/9811/09/germany.kristallnacht/
  | date = 1998-11-09
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080225014507/http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/europe/9811/09/germany.kristallnacht/ |archivedate = February 25, 2008}}
*{{cite web
  | title = What Was Kristallnacht?
  | work = THHP Short Essays
  | publisher = The Holocaust History Project
  | url = http://www.holocaust-history.org/short-essays/kristallnacht.shtml
  | date = 2003-11-28
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht &quot;Night of Crystal&quot;  -  &quot;Night of Broken Glass&quot;
  | work = Holocaust Prelude
  | publisher = Holocaust Education &amp; Archive Research Team
  | url = http://www.holocaustresearchproject.net/holoprelude/kristallnacht.html
  | date = 2006-2007
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht
  | work = From Aryanization to Cultural Loss: The Destruction of the Jewish Fashion Industry in Germany and Austria
  | author = Frieda Miller, Vancouver Holocaust Education Center
  | publisher = Center for Holocaust &amp; Genocide Studies, University of Minnesota
  | url = http://www.chgs.umn.edu/educational/brokenThreads/kristallnacht.html
  | date = 2008-02-25
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Sitting at Nuremberg, Germany 29th July to 8th August 1946
  | work = The Trial of German Major War Criminals Volume 20
  | publisher = The Nizkor Project
  | url = http://www.nizkor.org/hweb/imt/tgmwc/tgmwc-20/tgmwc-20-194-03.shtml
  | year = 2006
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers - Kristallnacht
  | work = Teaching Eleanor Roosevelt; [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] National Historic Site, Hyde Park, New York
  | author = Allida Black, June Hopkins, et al.
  | publisher = US National Park Service archive (nps.gov)
  | url = http://www.nps.gov/archive/elro/glossary/kristallnacht.htm
  | year = 2003
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht: A Nationwide Pogrom, November 9–10, 1938
  | work = Holocaust Encyclopedia
  | publisher = US Holocaust Memorial Museum
  | url = http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/index.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005201
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht: The November 1938 Pogroms
  | work = Online exhibitions, special topics
  | publisher = US Holocaust Memorial Museum
  | url = http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/kristallnacht_02/
  | accessdate = 2008-05-20}}
*{{cite web
  | title = Kristallnacht
  | work = Yad Vashem’s Photo Archives
  | author = Yad Vashem
  | publisher = The Holocaust Martyrs' and Heroes' Remembrance Authority
  | url = http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/kristallnacht/kristallnacht_home_photo.html
  | year = 2004
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{refbegin}}
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/exhibitions/kristallnacht/index.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki It Came From Within... 71 Years Since Kristallnacht] - Online exhibition from Yad Vashem, including survivor testimonies, archival footage, photos, and stories
* [http://www1.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20080424 ''Voices on Antisemitism'' Interview with Susan Warsinger] from the [http://www.ushmm.org/ United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]
* [http://www.ashkenazhouse.org ''Synagogues Memorial institute'' in Jerusalem]
{{refend}}
{{The Holocaust (end)}}
{{Nazism}}
{{World War II}}
{{good article}}

[[Category:Kristallnacht| ]]
[[Category:1938 in Germany]]
[[Category:German words and phrases]]
[[Category:Holocaust anti-Jewish pogroms]]
[[Category:Holocaust antisemitic attacks and incidents]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Germany]]
[[Category:Vandalized works of art]]
[[Category:1938 in Austria]]

{{Link FA|de}}
{{Link FA|fr}}

[[ar:ليلة البلور]]
[[an:Kristallnacht]]
[[bg:Кристална нощ]]
[[bs:Kristalna noć]]
[[br:Nozvezh ar strink]]
[[ca:Nit dels vidres trencats]]
[[ceb:Kristallnacht]]
[[cs:Křišťálová noc]]
[[da:Krystalnatten]]
[[de:Novemberpogrome 1938]]
[[et:Kristallöö]]
[[el:Νύχτα των Κρυστάλλων]]
[[es:Noche de los cristales rotos]]
[[eo:Kristala nokto]]
[[eu:Kristal hautsien gaua]]
[[fa:شب شیشه‌های شکسته]]
[[fr:Nuit de Cristal]]
[[fy:Kristallnacht]]
[[ga:Kristallnacht]]
[[gl:A noite dos cristais rotos]]
[[ko:수정의 밤 사건]]
[[hr:Kristalna noć]]
[[id:Kristallnacht]]
[[is:Kristalsnótt]]
[[it:Notte dei cristalli]]
[[he:ליל הבדולח]]
[[la:Nox crystallorum]]
[[lv:Kristāla nakts]]
[[lt:Krištolinė naktis]]
[[hu:Kristályéjszaka]]
[[mk:Кристална ноќ]]
[[arz:ليلة الكريستال]]
[[nl:Kristallnacht]]
[[ja:水晶の夜]]
[[no:Krystallnatten]]
[[nn:Krystallnatta]]
[[pl:Noc kryształowa]]
[[pt:Noite dos cristais]]
[[ro:Noaptea de cristal]]
[[ru:Хрустальная ночь]]
[[stq:Riekskristallnoacht]]
[[simple:Kristallnacht]]
[[sk:Krištáľová noc]]
[[sl:Kristalna noč]]
[[sr:Кристална ноћ]]
[[sh:Kristalna noć]]
[[fi:Kristalliyö]]
[[sv:Kristallnatten]]
[[ta:கிரிஸ்டல்நாக்ட்]]
[[tr:Kristal Gece]]
[[uk:Кришталева ніч]]
[[yi:קריסטאל נאכט]]
[[zh:水晶之夜]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
