<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8356443" ns="0" title="The Black Mirror"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the computer game|other uses|Black mirror}}
{{Infobox VG
|title = The Black Mirror
|image = [[Image:The Black Mirror.jpg|250px|The Black Mirror.]]
|caption = 
|developer = [[Future Games (company)|Future Games]]
|publisher = {{vgrelease|NA=[[The Adventure Company]]}}{{vgrelease|Czech Republic|CZE|[[Future Games (company)|Future Games]]}}{{vgrelease|United Kingdom|UK|[[GMX Media]]}} 
|distributor = 
|designer = 
|series = 
|engine = AGDS (Advanced Graphic Development System)
|version = 
|released = {{vgrelease|Czech Republic|CZE| February 2003}}{{vgrelease|NA=17 October 2003}}{{vgrelease|EU= 6 April 2004}}{{vgrelease|United Kingdom|UK|28 May 2004}}
|genre = [[adventure game|Adventure]]; [[horror fiction|horror]]
|modes = [[Single player]]
|ratings = [[Entertainment Software Rating Board|ESRB]]: Mature (17+)&lt;br /&gt;[[PEGI]]: 12+
|platforms = [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]
|media = [[CD-ROM|CD]] (2) / [[DVD]] (1)
|requirements =     Windows 98/ME/2000/XP&lt;br /&gt; Pentium III 400 MHz (or equivalent)&lt;br /&gt;64 MB RAM&lt;br /&gt;8 MB DirectX 7.1 compatible video card
|input = [[Computer keyboard|Keyboard]], [[Computer mouse|Mouse]]
}}

'''''The Black Mirror''''' is a third-person [[point-and-click]] [[horror fiction|horror]] [[adventure game]] developed in [[2003]] by [[Future Games (company)|Future Games]], a [[Czech Republic|Czech]] company. Its original name is ''Posel Smrti'' (Death's Messenger). The game features 150 locations and 5 hours of spoken dialogoue. A sequel, ''[[Black Mirror II]]'', was released in 2009.

== Plot ==
Black Mirror is the name of the ancestral [[Manor house|manor]] of the Gordon family located in [[England]]. Samuel Gordon is forced to return there after 12 years absence following the death of his grandfather, William Gordon. Despite occurring under mysterious circumstances, William's death is considered a suicide by everyone except for Samuel. Plagued by sudden nightmares and excruciating headaches, Samuel is determined to find the true causes of his grandfather's death. The exact cause of the death was the fall out of a window. Soon, strange  and unexpected deaths occur. Samuel's investigation reveals that his grandfather has interests in the &quot;world of darkness&quot;. The quests of the game lead to &quot;Dark Mirror&quot;, a [[Portal (fiction)|portal]] to an unknown world. This portal teleports him to the top of the Gordon's castle from where he falls as his grandfather and dies. Elements of black magic are obvious at the final chapter. The &quot;Dark Mirror&quot; is depicted as a book on a [[pentagram]]. Samuel must use five keys on each of the five corners. He also sheds his skin with a knife, in order to open the portal, pouring some blood on the book. 

The game is divided into 6 chapters:

*Chapter I: Return of the Future
*Chapter II: Back to the Light
*Chapter III: Hidden Legacy
*Chapter IV: Forgotten Bound
*Chapter V: Confession of the Truth
*Chapter VI: Look Through the Mirror

== Reception ==

The game's reception has been mixed. While most critics praised its dark atmosphere - created mostly by meticulously drawn backgrounds, music, ambiance and realistic animation and sound effects - the quality of the English voice-overs was unsatisfying to many. Other points of criticism include the game's rigid linear structure, [[pixel hunting]] elements and, most especially, the game's ending.

[[Image:Black Mirror manor.jpg|thumb|320px|left|''The Black Mirror manor]]{{-}}

== Sequels ==

German-based Cranberry Production developed a sequel, ''[[Black Mirror II]]'', in 2009. It takes place in the 1990s, twelve years after the original game. Solitary Darren meets the cute Angelina while he is working at the local photo shop of Biddeford, a small town in New England. Angelina also catches the eye of Darren's despotic, unpopular boss. To add to the mystery, there seems to be a third person interested in Angelina — Darren sees someone chasing her. He decides to investigate these incidents, and his research soon lead him to several locations, such as the small English village of Willow Creek that players will know from the first game.

A second and final sequel by Cranberry Production, ''[[Black Mirror III]]'', was released in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mobygames.com/game/windows/black-mirror-iii/release-info&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gamespot.com/pc/adventure/blackmirroriii/similar.html?mode=versions&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.future-games.cz/www/poselsmrti/hlavni-Eng.html}}
* {{moby game|id=/black-mirror}}
* [http://www.metacritic.com/games/platforms/pc/blackmirror ''The Black Mirror''] at [[Metacritic]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Black Mirror, The}}
[[Category:2003 video games]]
[[Category:Adventure games]]
[[Category:Horror video games]]
[[Category:Point-and-click adventure games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in the Czech Republic]]
[[Category:Video games set in the 1980s]]
[[Category:Video games set in England]]

[[bg:The Black Mirror]]
[[de:Black Mirror]]
[[fa:آینه سیاه]]
[[fr:The Black Mirror]]
[[it:The Black Mirror]]
[[pl:The Black Mirror]]
[[ru:The Black Mirror]]
[[uk:The Black Mirror]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
