<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8398417" ns="0" title="Disney Channel India"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">''For the Disney Channel in other countries, see [[Disney Channel (international)]]. For the original Disney Channel, see [[Disney Channel]].
{{infobox TV channel
|name=Disney Channel India
|logosize= 220px
|logofile= Disney Channel wordmark.svg|
|logocaption= 
|launch= 17 December, 2004
|share as of=February 2007
|owner=[[The Walt Disney Company India Pvt. Ltd.|The Walt Disney Company India]]
|country=India
|headquarters=[[Mumbai]], [[Maharashtra]]
|broadcast area=[[South Asia]]
|sister names=[[Disney XD (India)]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hungama TV]]
|sister blocks names=[[Disney Junior India]]
|slogans=Where magic comes alive
|web=[http://www.disney.in/DisneyChannel Official Website]
|sat serv 1=[[Tata Sky]]|
| sat chan 1=Channel 605|
|sat serv 2=Dish TV|
| sat chan 2=Channel 523|
|sat serv 3=[[BIG TV|BIGTV]]|
| sat chan 3=Channel 603|
|sat serv 4=[[Airtel Digital TV]]|
| sat chan 4=Channel 360|
| cable serv 1 =[[Hathway]]|
| cable chan 1 =Channel 411/64/305
| cable serv 2=Available on most cable systems|
| cable chan 2=Check Local Listings for channels|
}}


'''Disney Channel India''' is an Indian television channel specializing in television programming for children through original series and movies as well as third party programming. It aired in [[India]] in 2004 and is marketed to children and families entertainment. The channel is available on basic cable and satellite television, and is a division of [[Disney India]]. The network is based in [[Mumbai, Maharashtra]], [[India]].&lt;ref name=&quot;disney.in&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.disney.in/corporate/ |title=The Walt Disney Company |publisher=Disney.in |date= |accessdate=2010-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;Disney Channel India Is the 1st Cartoon channel to cross  200+ GRPs in 5 years.

==History and Availability==
Disney Channel began broadcasting in India in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.disney.in/corporate/milestones.htm |title=The Walt Disney Company |publisher=Disney.in |date= |accessdate=2010-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Channel is very popular to Children between 5–17 years of age.&lt;ref name=&quot;disney.in&quot;/&gt; The network is based in [[Mumbai]], [[Maharashtra]] and is available on local cable. It is also available on [[Tata Sky]] on channel 605, [[Dish TV]] on channel 523, [[Big TV|BigTV]] on channel 603, and [[Airtel Digital TV]] on channel 360.  On digital cable services, it is available on DEN Digital on channel 407 and on [[Hathway]] Cable on Channel 410.

Currently Disney Channel India has two subsidiary stations Disney XD India and Hungama TV. It also has a block 'Disney Junior', a re-branded form of Playhouse Disney.

==Disney Junior India==
{{seealso|Disney Junior India}}

==November/December Fiesta==

Disney Channel India has announced a variety of shows this Nov-Dec. They include:

* New episodes of Handy Manny in the Disney Junior Block (Mon-Thu 12pm)
* New Season of Art Attack India (Sundays 9:30am)
* New Season (Season 3!) of Phineas and Ferb (Starts 24th October, 4pm)

Moreover, '''new season of Best Of Luck Nikki''' and a new show, '''a  Poem is....''' to start soon!

==Programming==
{{Main|List of programs broadcast by Disney Channel India}}
{{Main|Disney Channel India Original Series}}
{{Main|List of Disney Channel India series}} ['''The last list (page) is completely un-updated''']

==List of Programs being demanded by viewers==
* [[JONAS L.A.]]
*[[Shake it up]]
* [[So Random]]
* [[Take Two with Phineas and Ferb]]
*[[Jessie]]
*[[Wizards Of Waverly Place]]

==Disney Channel Old Blocks==

===Summer Belongs To You===

It is the summer block that started on Disney Channel India in April 2011. It featured all through April, May and June 2011. It had introduced many new shows, new episodes of Disney shows, new seasons, tons of contests and also viewers' favorite Disney movies.
* [[Best of Luck Nikki]]
* [[Art Attack]]
* [[Phineas and Ferb (season 2)|Phineas and Ferb Season 2]]
* [[Doraemon]] New Episodes
* [[Fish Hooks]]
* [[Mai Ka Laal|Mai ka Laal]]
&lt;ref name=&quot;business-standard.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.business-standard.com/india/news/disney-channels-summer-belongs-to-you/431070/ |title=Summer Belongs To You |publisher=Dishtracking.com/blog |date= |accessdate=2011-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disney Channel's Superstar Summer===
This summer block started in mid April 2010 as a major block consisted of multiple sub-blocks. It featured many shows that were on-going in those days. This block included  [[Hannah Montana (season 3)|Hannah Montana Season 3]] and [[Wizards of Waverly Place#Season 2: 2008-2009|Wizards of Waverly Place Season 2]], [[Karishma Ka Karishma]], Majooba Ka Ajooba, [[The Magic Make-Up Box]] and [[Shararat (sitcom)|Shararat]]. Along with these, it also included the Indian premiere of a lot of shows which includes [[Kya Mast Hai Life]] Season 2, [[Ishaan]],ishaan 2, Pink Lemonade Series 2, [[Sonny With A Chance#Season 2: 2010|Sonny With A Chance Season 2]], [[Phineas and Ferb (season 3)|Phineas and Ferb Season 2]] and [[The Suite Life on Deck#Season 2: 2009-10|The Suite Life on Deck Season 2]].

====Superstar Mornings====
This block started in the month of April along with the premiere of Disney Channel's Superstar Summer block, from 10 AM showing programs like [[Karishma Ka Karishma]], Majooba Ka Ajooba, [[The Magic Make-Up Box]], [[Shararat (sitcom)]] and [[Kya Mast Hai Life]] all summer long.

====Big Bada Boom====
Hosted by Zain, Tara, Murtuza, Bumpy and Nakshatra this block featured new episodes of [[Phineas and Ferb]], [[Hannah Montana]], [[Wizards of Waverly Place]], [[Kya Mast Hai Life]] and [[Ishaan]]. Also it showcased [[Karishma Ka Karishma]] and [[Shararat (sitcom)]].

This block ended in the mid of June, 2010, but the show Big Bada Boom continued.

====Disney Triple Treat Movie====
The Disney Triple Treat Movie is a block used to to air on weekends and began in April, 2007. This movie block featured the airing of three movies on each weekend on Disney Channel India. This block ended in June, 2007.

====Phineas and Ferb-ruary====
Disney channel's this block started to air on February 1, 2010 replacing the re-run airing of [[Jonas L.A.]]. It featured the new episodes of the Disney Channel's original series [[Phineas and Ferb]]. As the name suggests itself, this block ended by the end of February, 2010.This block was also held in 2009 &amp; 2011

'''Note:''' This block also aired on Disney XD UK, in February 2011

====Dhan-Te-Nan====
Dhan-Te-Nan is the block that was held in the festive season thats is October and November in 2009.The block showed many shows and movies including the premiers of [[High School Musical 3: Senior Year]], [[Sky High (2005 film)|Sky High]], [[The Elephant Princess]], [[Patito Feo]] and [[Hannah Montana]].

====12 Days of Christmas====
This block also showed new episodes and movies for 12 days in December 2009.The shows and movies included [[JONAS]], [[The Incredibles]] etc.

'''Note:''' This block also aired on Disney Channel UK, in 2007, 2008 &amp; 2009

====The Great Comedy Challenge====
This block was the first block of 2010. It included a comedy challenge between many Disney Channel Original Shows like [[Kya Mast Hai Life]] season 1, [[Hannah Montana]] season 3, [[Vicky &amp; Vetaal]] , [[JONAS L.A.]], [[Wizards of Waverly Place]], [[That's So Raven]].

====The Fully Funny First Day====
This was the first day of 2010 as the name suggests.On the First day of 2010 thing like [[High School Musical 3: Senior Year]], [[Kya Mast Hai Life]] Bloopers, [[Wizards on Deck with Hannah Montana]] were shown.

====Oye Summer Summer Oye!====
This was the biggest ever block organised by disney channel in 2009.It included many shows and movies like [[Hannah Montana]] 3, [[Wizards of Waverly Place]] 2, [[Sonny with a Chance]], [[The Suite Life on Deck]], [[Shararat (sitcom)]], [[Shaka Laka Boom Boom]], [[Son Pari]], [[Karishma Ka Karishma]] etc; many new episodes were also shown.
NOTE-The Title track of this block as well as the name was inspired from the movie OYE LUCKY LUCKY OYE. The block sub-included many blocks such as ''Oye Summer Mornings/Movies/Weekends Oye!''. Oye Summer fridays featured the new episodes of Disney Channel's original series, [[Wizards of Waverly Place]].

====Kya mast hai Disney Channel====
This block was shown in July–August 2009. The name was taken from The NEW DCOM [[Kya Mast Hai Life]] which became very popular thats why the song was also filmed on the ''Kya Mast Hai Life'' cast. The block feauted new episodes of shows like [[Hannah Montana]], [[Kya Mast Hai Life]], [[Wizards of Waverly Place]], [[Sonny with a Chance]].

====New Year's Celebrations 2009====
This block was shown in the last 5 days of year 2009 and was hosted by the main cast of ''Kya Mast Hai Life''.

====Special Hello====
This was not basically a block but was shown in the year 2009-2010. In This block the cast of famous shows Greeted Indians for special occasions in Hindi. The cast of [[Sonny With a Chance]] greeted India on Diwali and the cast Of [[The Suite Life On Deck]] greeted India on New Year 2010.

====Wiz-Tember====
This block was shown in September 2009 in reference to the USA's Disney Channel Block WIZ-TOBER.This block showed magical shows such as [[Wizards of Waverly Place season 3/4]], [[The Elephant Princess]], [[Shararat (sitcom)|Shararat]].

====Club H.S.M====
This block was shown in october 2009 before ''Dhan-Te-Nan'' as the name suggests,it referred to the premiere of [[High School Musical 3: Senior Year]] after many special previews and interviews.

==Hannah Montana Forever in India==
Disney Channel India showed Hannah Montana Forever on 30 October And the Season Finale Episode of Hannah Montana aired on 7 November 2010 at 5 PM. It is same day of Finale in the USA. With the last episode &quot;I will always remember you&quot; the season was told to be ended by the channel on 7 November, although some episodes were yet to be announced.
But on May 13th, 14th, 20th &amp; 21st, 2011, the remaining few episodes were telecasted and the series finally ended also in India. Althogh, still the episode &quot;Can you see the real me&quot; is yet to be telecasted.

==Recent Contests==
===My School Rocks===
Disney Channel channel has also organized a &quot;My School Rocks&quot; contest in which teams from participating schools perform a Hindi version of &quot;Get'cha Head in the Game&quot; from [[High School Musical]].  The winning school, St. Xavier's of [[Mumbai]], participated in a music video directed by [[Saroj Khan]]. This contest has been closed now.
The contest was again held for [[High School Musical 2]] and [[Camp Rock]]

===Disney Princess===
It started from 2006 and ended in by the end of the same year.
It started a [[Disney Princess]] competition held in [[Mumbai]] by [[Dia Mirza]]. The winner of the competition was a [[Sikh]] girl named '''Kashish Gorawari'''.

==See also==
* [[Buena Vista International India]]
* [[Disney XD (India)]]
* [[History of Disney in India]]
* [[The Walt Disney Company India Pvt. Ltd.]]
* [[Toon Disney India]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.disney.in/DisneyChannel/ Disney Channel India: Official Website]

{{Disney Channel}}

[[Category:Disney Channel]]
[[Category:Children's television channels in India]]
[[Category:Television stations in Mumbai]]
[[Category:Disney India]]

[[es:Disney Channel (India)]]
[[fr:Disney Channel India]]
[[te:డిస్నీ ఛానల్ ఇండియా]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
