<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8432288" ns="0" title="Human rights in Bahrain"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Politics of Bahrain}}

'''Bahrain's''' record on [[human rights]] has been described by [[Human Rights Watch]] as &quot;dismal&quot;, and having &quot;deteriorated sharply in the latter half of 2010&quot;.&lt;ref name=HRW2011&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/world-report-2011/world-report-2011-bahrain] World Report 2011:Bahrain, Human Rights Watch.&lt;/ref&gt;

The government of Bahrain has been accused of marginalizing the majority [[Shia]] [[Muslim]] population, torturing and mistreating political prisoners to extract confessions, blocked websites and blogs associated with the legal opposition, and harassment of  human rights defenders.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bahrainrights.org/en&lt;/ref&gt; The crackdown on protesters during the 2011 Arab Spring has brought further human rights complaints,&lt;ref&gt;[http://jurist.org/paperchase/2011/04/human-rights-organizations-criticize-rampant-abuses-in-bahrain.php Human rights organizations criticize rampant abuses in Bahrain], jurist.org 8 April 2011&lt;/ref&gt; including the destruction of dozens of long-standing Shiite mosques.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0620/Bahrain-stages-trials-of-opponents-despite-new-US-criticism Bahrain stages trials of opponents, despite new US criticism]| By Roy Gutman, McClatchy Newspapers| June 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

On 29 June 2011, King Hamad established the [[Royal Independent Investigation Commission]] to examine the episodes of civil disobedience and alleged human rights offences committed in the aftermath of the February 2011 protests.&lt;ref&gt;''Bahrain News Agency'', [http://bna.bh/portal/en/news/462963 &quot; HM King Hamad Sets up Royal Independent Investigation commission &quot;], ''Bahrain News Agency'', 29 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==History and background==
{{Main|History of Bahrain}}

==Torture==
{{Main|Torture in Bahrain}}

Despite repeated government claims of improvement over the course of several years,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/CAT.C.CR.34.BHR.En?Opendocument Conclusions and recommendations of the Committee against Torture : Bahrain., Committee Against Torture], United Nations Commission for Human Rights, June 21, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arabicnews.com/ansub/Daily/Day/050929/2005092919.html Bahrain ended issue of systematic torture], Arabic News.com, September 29, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; there is evidence that torture is a regular part of the legal process in Bahrain.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2010/03/31/bahrains-torture-problem&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to a 2011 report by [[Human Rights Watch]], between 2007 and 2009, the government regularly practiced torture and ill-treatment in interrogating security suspects.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;  Although government spokesmen have issued denials, there is no evidence of criminal investigations and the government has not imposed disciplinary measures on the alleged perpetrators.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;

In 2011 Human Rights Watch found evidence protections for migrant workers have improved.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;

==Oppression of Shia==
Discrimination against Shia Muslims in Bahrain is severe and systematic enough for a number of sources ([[Time magazine]],&lt;ref name=Baker&gt;Aryn Baker [http://globalspin.blogs.time.com/2011/03/14/saudi-troops-enter-bahrain-to-quell-protests-it-wont-work-for-long/] &quot;Why A Saudi Intervention into Bahrain Won't End the Protests&quot;&lt; March 14, 2011, Time Magazine.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vali Nasr]], Yitzhak Nakash, Counterpunch,&lt;ref name=Lamb&gt;Franklin Lamb [http://www.counterpunch.org/lamb04152011.html] &quot; The Obama Doctrine: AWOL in Bahrain,&quot; April 15–17, 2011, [[CounterPunch]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]],&lt;ref name=BCHRI&gt;[http://www.bahrainrights.org/en/node/3132 &quot;A Smearing Campaign against the Shiite Bahraini Citizens with the Participation of the Bahraini Crown Prince and the Ambassador of Bahrain in Washington&quot;], [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], viewed Mar 31, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; etc.) to have used the term “apartheid” in describing it.

===Origins===
Over 70% of the population of Bahrain are [[Shia]] [[Muslims]].   The ruling [[Al Khalifa family]], who are [[Sunni]] Muslim, arrived in Bahrain from [[Kuwait]] at the end of the eighteenth century.&lt;ref name=Nakash/&gt;&lt;ref name=Amirisefat&gt;Mahdi Amirisefat [http://edition.presstv.ir/detail/85729.htm] 'Bahraini rulers importing extremism', Feb. 15, 2009, Press TV.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Yitzhak Nakash,&lt;ref&gt;professor of Islamic and Middle Eastern Studies at [[Brandeis University]]&lt;/ref&gt; the invasion and conquest led by the [[Al Khalifa family]] in 1783 started an illegitimate occupation, establishing a system of &quot;political apartheid based on racial, sectarian, and tribal discrimination.&quot;&lt;ref name=Nakash&gt;Yitzhak Nakash ''Reaching for Power: The Shi'a in the Modern Arab World,'' (Princeton University Press, 2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Vali Nasr]], senior fellow at the [[Council on Foreign Relations]]&lt;ref&gt;and author of &quot;The Shia Revival: How Conflicts Within Islam Will Shape the Future&quot;,&lt;/ref&gt; the Sunni élite treats Shi'ites as an underclass, limiting them primarily to manual labor and denying them a fair share of state resources. &quot;For Shi'ites, Sunni rule has been like living under apartheid.&quot;&lt;ref name=Ghosh&gt;Bobby Gosh, [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1592849-2,00.html] &quot;Behind the Sunni-Shi'ite Divide,&quot; Feb., 22, 2007, Time Magazine.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operation===

According to [[Time (magazine)|Time Magazine]],  Bahrain is practicing {{quotation|a form of sectarian apartheid by not allowing Shiites to hold key government posts or serve in the police or military. In fact, the security forces are staffed by Sunnis from Syria, Pakistan, and Baluchistan who also get fast-tracked to Bahraini citizenship, much to the displeasure of the indigenous Shiite population.&lt;ref&gt;Raymond Barrett [25] &quot;Bahrain emerging as flashpoint in Middle East unrest,&quot; Feb. 15, 2011, [[Christian Science Monitor]].&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to the [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], while the Shiites exceeds 70% of the population, &quot;they occupy less than 18%  of total top jobs in government establishments. In several government ministries and corporations no Shiite is appointed in leading jobs.&quot;&lt;ref name=BCHR&gt;[[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]] [http://www.bahrainrights.org/node/384] &quot;Sectarian discrimination in the kingdom of Bahrain: The Unwritten Law,&quot; A paper Presented to: WANGO ANNUAL CONFERENCE 2003
(Toward an Ethical and Caring Global Community)September 25–28, 2003 Bangkok, Thailand.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Rajab&gt;Nabeel Rajab [http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=86562&amp;sectionid=3510303] &quot;Press TV:Nabeel Rajab:Discrimination and sectarian oppression in Bahrain, a systematic reality&quot;, 23 Feb 2009, Press TV.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Jobs in the police and armed forced are reserved for Sunni.&lt;ref name=BCHR/&gt;&lt;ref name=Rajab/&gt; Sunni Muslims from favored tribes are admitted to Bahrain as citizens to fill these jobs.&lt;ref name=BCHR/&gt;&lt;ref name=Breeze&gt;Bethany Breeze [http://www.uiargonaut.com/sections/opinion/stories/2011/april/4111/a_silent_apartheid.html]  &quot;A silent apartheid in Bahrain,&quot; April 1, 2011, University of Idaho Argonaut.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Arabia Through the Looking Glass]],'' [[Jonathan Raban]]
Picador, 1987, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shiites and &quot;some Sunnis of Persian origins&quot;, are banned from residing in the city of [[Riffa]], where only the Sunni Muslims are permitted to live.&lt;ref name=BCHR/&gt;

According to [[Human Rights Watch]], Bahrain's personal status law (Law 19/2009), adopted in 2009 and marriage, divorce, custody, and inheritance cases, applies only to Sunnis although women's groups believe that it should treat all citizens equally.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;

There are also concerns of the Bahraini government's systematic efforts to diminish the Shia majority by promotion of immigration of Sunni Muslims and granting them citizenship.&lt;ref name=BCHR/&gt;&lt;ref name=PTV&gt;[http://www.vob.org/en/index.php?show=news&amp;action=article&amp;id=390] &quot;Bahraini Despot Wages Demographic War&quot;, Feb. 17, 2009, Voice of Bahrain.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Dr. [[Saeeid Shahabi]], a London-based journalist,&lt;ref&gt;commentator and political analyst and member of the [[Bahrain Freedom Movement]]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;there is the problem of political naturalization. The ruling family -- similar to the Apartheid regime in South Africa, where you had a minority ruling a majority -- wants to change the demographic situation of the country.&quot;&lt;ref name=Amirisefat/&gt;

====Race and sectarian discrimination====

{{See also|Bandargate scandal}}

Elections and the reconstitution of parliament have been accompanied by a strengthening of previously banned Islamist political societies, and policies advocated by them are now on the public agenda. Al Wefaq, Bahrain’s main Shia Islamist opposition party, has for several years tried to introduce racial segregation, calling for the removal of third world immigrants from predominately Bahraini areas. In 2004, the head of Manama City Council, Al Wefaq’s Murthader Bader, called for the introduction of racial segregation&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=87912&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=27131&amp;date=7/29/2004 Clashes spark call to relocate expats] Gulf Daily News, July 29, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; in the city with the removal of South Asian nationals to other parts of the country. Racial segregation it was argued would best address tensions between locals and third world expatriates that saw [[race riots]] against immigrants in March 2004. In 2006, the call was reiterated by Al Wefaq councillor Sadiq Rahma who said Asians 'make the neighbourhood dirty'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=133367&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=28309&amp;date=1-23-2006 'No go' rule for bachelor labourers] Gulf Daily News, January 23, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The move has been criticised by Bahraini human rights groups as a 'a violation of basic human rights'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=133973&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=28316&amp;date=1-30-2006 Segregation of Asians slammed] Gulf Daily News, January 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; After 2006’s elections, the party’s Abdullah Al A’ali used his parliamentary platform to call for legislation to restrict expatriate labour away from Bahraini families, saying &quot;Labourers who now live in neighbourhoods with Bahraini families should be given a grace period to relocate before they face legal action.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulfnews.com/region/Bahrain/10110820.html Deputy calls for labour housing regulations], Gulf News, 13 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a flurry of race hate messages sent to naturalized Bahrainis from third world countries after opposition political leaders alleged that immigration was tantamount to ‘cultural genocide’. In November 2006, [[Al Ayam (Bahrain)|Al Ayam]] published a collection of threats sent to naturalized citizens warning that they would have to ‘choose between the suitcase and the coffin’, promising ‘Death and fire are your destiny’ and another warned that the author hated all naturalized Bahrainis, &quot;You are detested. You have taken from us, the sons of Bahrain, our homes, jobs and education opportunities. You will face the same destiny as the Egyptians in Iraq [after the end of the Iraq-Iran war]. It will be nails, hammers and a coffin. Your destiny is near.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulfnews.com/region/Bahrain/10080616.html Naturalised Bahrainis face death threats], Gulf News, 11 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism of the Baharaini apartheid system===
Among the journalists, authors and human rights activists who have criticized Bahrain's system as apartheid are [[Mansoor Al-Jamri]], former editor of the Bahraini newspaper [[Alwasat (Bahraini newspaper)|Alwasat]],&lt;ref&gt;Mansoor Al-Jamri says of the political system in Bahrain, &quot;It's apartheid... They've made a decision that half the population is not wanted, and they want to instill fear in this population and dehumanize them.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fleishman&gt;Jeffrey Fleishman [http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/world/la-fg-bahrain-shiites-20110502,0,4278361.story] &quot;After crushed protests, Bahrain is accused of deepened oppression of Shiites&quot;, May 12, 2011, Los Angeles Times.&lt;/ref&gt; 
the [[Bahrain Freedom Movement|Voice of Bahrian]],&lt;ref&gt;UNHCR resolution (Ref: E/CN.4/Sub.2/1997/L.8)  &quot;Questions of the violation of human rights and fundamental freedoms, including policies of racial discrimination and segregation and of apartheid, in all countries,&quot; is a &quot;resolution condemning the government of Bahrain.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=VOCI&gt;[http://www.vob.org/en/index.php?show=news&amp;action=article&amp;id=36] &quot;UN Human Right Sub-Commission Passes a Historic Resolution on Bahrain on 21 August 1997.&quot; Aug. 21, 1997, Voice of Bahrain.&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Saeed Shahabi]] of the [[Bahrain Freedom Movement]],&lt;ref&gt;Saeed Shahabihas called for an end to the &quot;sectarian apartheid&quot; system in Bahrain.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SShahabi&gt;Saeed Sharabi [http://www.presstv.ir/detail/175372.html] &quot;'People to continue protests in Bahrain'&quot;, April 18, 2001, Press TV.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.presstv.ir/detail/176883.html] &quot;'US, Saudis behind Bahraini apartheid'; A sectarian apartheid against the majority Shia population is taking place in Bahrain by the ruling al-Khalifa family whose support comes from Saudi Arabia and by proxy from the United States&quot;, April 26, 2011  PressTV.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Madani&gt;Amir Madini [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/amir-madani/bahrain-arab-spring_b_854191.html] &quot;Arabian Spring: The Hidden Tragedy of Bahrain&quot;, April 27, 2011, Huffington Post.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Iranian [[Press TV]],&lt;ref name=Rajab&gt;Nabeel Rajab [http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=86562&amp;sectionid=3510303] &quot;Press TV:Nabeel Rajab:Discrimination and sectarian oppression in Bahrain, a systematic reality&quot;, 23 Feb 2009, Press TV.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Press TV describes the systematic descrimination against the &quot;indigenous people&quot; of  a policy of &quot;sectarian discrimination, segregation and apartheid.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.presstv.ir/detail/173223.html] &quot;'Human tragedy unfolding in Bahrain&quot;, April 5, 2011, Press TV.&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[New York Times]] columnist Nicholas Kristof,&lt;ref&gt;“the language of the ruling party sounds a lot to me like the language of white South Africans — or even like the language of white southerners in Jim Crow America... There’s a fear of the rabble, a distrust of full democracy, a sense of entitlement.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kristof&gt;Nicholas Kristof, &quot;Is This Apartheid in Bahrain?&quot; New York Times, Feb. 22, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Euronews, &quot;Bahrain: A Country Divided&quot;, Feb. 21, 2011, Euronews.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://special.registerguard.com/turin/2011/mar/18/deep-division-in-bahrain-raises-echoes-of-apartheid/] &quot;Deep division in Bahrain raises echoes of apartheid,&quot; [[The Register-Guard]],March 18, 2011,&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Bahrain: Assault on girls' school in Hamad by security forces, April 23, 201, ''The Muslim News''.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Irshad Manji,&lt;ref&gt;Irshad Manji says &quot;Sunni Muslim minorities control the Shia majorities&quot;, Irshad Manji, ''The trouble with Islam: a wake-up call for honesty and change'', Random House Digital, 2003, p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Shibil Siddiqi,&lt;ref&gt;says &quot;Bahrain is virtually an apartheid state.&quot; Shibil Siddiqi From the Centre for the Study of Global Power and Politics at Trent University, &quot;Democracy and the Middle East,&quot; March 21, 2011, Espress Tribune of the International Herald Tribune.&lt;/ref&gt; Ameen Izzadeen, &lt;ref&gt;&quot;after the dismantling of the apartheid regime in South Africa, Bahrain remained the only country where a minority dictated terms to a majority. More than 70 percent of the Bahrainis are Shiite Muslims, but they have little or no say in the government.&quot; Ameen Izzadeen [24] &quot;Bahrain: the butchery of democracy dream,&quot; March 18, 32011, Daily Mirror&lt;/ref&gt;  Ben Cohen,&lt;ref&gt;Ben Cohen, says &quot;Bahrain is a society where inequality is ethnically rooted, and then buttressed by the denial of civic and political freedoms.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ben Cohen, [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/ben-s-cohen/bahrain-the-missing-a-wor_b_824309.html] &quot;Bahrain: The Missing 'A' Word,&quot; Huffington Post, Feb. 17, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Professor Staci Strobl, &lt;ref&gt;Writing in the ''International Journal of Comparative and Applied Criminal Justice'' , Professor Staci Strobl of the [[John Jay College of Criminal Justice]]  describes the demonstrators as  &quot;protesting an apartheid system that denies them opportunities equal to those of their Sunni
neighbors.&quot;, &quot;From colonial policing to community policing in Bahrain: The historical persistence of sectarianism&quot;, Staci Strobl, ''International Journal of Comparative and Applied Criminal Justice'', 2157-6475, Volume 35, Issue 1, February 2011, Pages 19 – 37.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ali Akbar Salehi]], the Foreign Minister of Iran.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ali Akbar Salehi]], has formally expressed his government's concern over the  “apartheid-like” discrimination practiced against the Shiite majority by the government of Bahrain in a letter addressed to United Nations Secretary-General [[Ban Ki-moon]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Varner&gt;ill Varner, [http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-04-26/bahrain-tells-un-about-hezbollah-s-efforts-to-topple-monarchy.html] &quot;Bahrain Tells UN About Hezbollah’s Efforts to Topple Monarchy&quot;, April 26, 2011, Bloomberg.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Queenann&gt;Gavriel Queenann      [http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-04-26/bahrain-tells-un-about-hezbollah-s-efforts-to-topple-monarchy.html]   &quot;Bahrain Accuses Hizbullah of Provoking Its Domestic Unrest&quot;, April 27, 2011, Israel National News.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996 the UK newspaper [[The Guardian]] stated that, &quot;if Bahrain is to preserve its reputation as a financial and service center in the Gulf, then the government must begin to forge a new national consensus and end the apartheid against the Shi'ites&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Crackdown on Shi'ites hurts Bahrain trade&quot; June 20, 1996, [[The Guardian]], as cited in Joe Stork, Routine abuse, routine denial : civil rights and the political crisis in Bahrain, ISBN 1564322181, New York, Human Rights Watch, 1997, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997 [[Joe Stork]] of [[Human Rights Watch]], reported that the apartheid practiced against the Shia by the government appeared to be &quot;worsening.&quot;&lt;ref name=Stork&gt;Joe Stork, ''Routine abuse, routine denial : civil rights and the political crisis in Bahrain'', ISBN 1564322181, New York, Human Rights Watch, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

===Calls for a boycott===

In 2010 the  Al-Wafa Islamic Movement, Haq Movement and [[Bahrain Freedom Movement]] called for a boycott of the October 23 election to the Bahraini Council of Representatives on the grounds that participation would be &quot;tantamount to accepting the unjust sectarian apartheid system.&quot;&lt;ref name=VOCI&gt;[http://www.vob.org/en/index.php?show=news&amp;action=article&amp;id=36] &quot;UN Human Right Sub-Commission Passes a Historic Resolution on Bahrain on 21 August 1997.&quot; Aug. 21, 1997, Voice of Bahrain.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2011 uprising===

{{Main|2011 Bahraini uprising}}

In February 2011, the tensions between the Sunni ruling minority and the Shi'a majority spilled over into street protests which was violently suppressed by police forces, resulting in multiple civilian deaths.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/19/world/middleeast/19bahrain.html?_r=1|title=Security Forces in Bahrain Open Fire on Protesters|date=2011-02-18|publisher=The New York Times Company|accessdate=22 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  McClatchy Newspapers/csmonitor.com reported that as of mid-May 2011, &lt;blockquote&gt;Authorities have held secret trials where protesters have been sentenced to death, arrested prominent mainstream opposition politicians, jailed nurses and doctors who treated injured protesters, seized the health care system that had been run primarily by Shiites, fired 1,000 Shiite professionals and canceled their pensions, detained students and teachers who took part in the protests, beat and arrested journalists, and forced the closure of the only opposition newspaper.&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

An estimated 1000 Bahrainis have been detained since the uprising and Bahraini and international human rights groups have documented hundreds of cases of torture and abuse of Shia detainees.&lt;ref name=csm.murphy/&gt; According to csmonitor.org, the government has gone beyond the crushing of political dissent to what &quot;appears&quot; to be an attempt to &quot;psychologically humiliating the island’s Shiite majority into silent submission.&quot;&lt;ref name=csm.murphy&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0607/Bahrain-campaign-to-humiliate-Shiites-goes-beyond-politics?cmpid=ema:nws:World%20Daily%2006082011&amp;cmpid=ema:nws:NzI5NjYzNTI3NwS2 Bahrain campaign to humiliate Shiites goes beyond politics], By Caryle Murphy / csmonitor.com / June 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Royal Independent Investigation Commission]] was established on 29 June 2011 by King [[Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa]] to assess the incidents that occurred in the Kingdom during the period of unrest in February and March 2011 and the consequences of these events.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bna.bh/portal/en/news/462963 &quot;HM King Hamad Sets up Royal Independent Investigation Commission&quot;], Bahrain News Agency, 29 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The Commission is expected to report its findings by 30 October 2011.

==Civil and political rights==

Parliamentary and municipal elections take place every four years, since the restoration of elections in 2002, when women were also given the vote for the first time as part of reforms by [[King Hamad]]. Bahrain has a [[bicameral]] legislature with the lower chamber of parliament, the ([[Council of Representatives of Bahrain]]), elected by universal suffrage, and the upper chamber, the ([[Shura Council (Bahrain)|Shura Council]]), appointed directly by the [[King of Bahrain|King]]. Those represented in the Shura Council include members of Bahrain's Christian and Jewish communities.

The [[Prime Minister of Bahrain|Prime Minister]] and government ministers are not elected. They are appointed directly by the King, but ministers can be removed by parliamentary no-confidence votes. The current Prime Minister, [[Khalifah ibn Sulman Al Khalifah]], is the King's paternal uncle and has been in office since 1970. Twelve of the twenty-three cabinet ministers appointed in November 2006 are members of the [[Al Khalifa]] royal family.

Bahrain has a complex civil society, which pre-date the reforms introduced by King Hamad, and has its roots in the emergence of the labour movement and the development of an educated middle class in the 1930s. According to a 2006 study on civil society in Bahrain by the [[European University Institute]], ''Voices in Parliament, Debates in Majalis, Banners on the Street: Avenues of Political Participation in Bahrain'':

{{quote| Generally, civil society has thriven, at least numerically. Bahrain’s NGOs are fragmented – many NGOs are really a spin-off of a political organisation and/or can draw only a narrow ethnic-sectarian segment to their activities. Generally the more elitist the NGO, the less narrowly defined its constituency in sectarian terms: Sectarianism does not play a role in many of the ‘arty’ clubs.

Contrary to views commonly held on Gulf states’ societies, Bahrain’s society offers a complex matrix of interlinking social institutions, understood in a broader anthropological sense. These can in varying degrees be mobilised for political ends.

Catering to the urban elites of both sects, the first clubs were opened in Manama earlier than in the rest of the Gulf region. Namely, the Uruba Club to which most prominent liberals are a member was founded in the early 1930s.

Other venues for political and social interactions are obviously the headquarters of political societies. Several of these also have regular weekly or monthly lecture days. Many headquarters of NGOs and trade unions are located very close to each other, since the king had donated a block of apartments for that purpose in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;iue.it&quot;/&gt;}}

For the average politically active Bahraini, there are usually a number of outlets according to the [[European University Institute]]:

{{quote| A typical male Bahraini with political interests has multiple affiliations: he is a member of a political society, has joined two or three NGOS in the first reform euphoria (related to human rights, women, environment), has been (since he entered his professional life) a member of a professional association. If Shiite, he attends ma’atim at least for holidays, and is involved in some charity, religious or through a local fund. It’s quite likely he is a regular to a majlis, the likelihood even increasing in case he is Sunni with tribal affiliations.&lt;ref name=&quot;iue.it&quot;/&gt;}}

The government’s moves to join international treaties protecting human rights have often been opposed by parliament. The initial attempt to get parliamentary ratification of the Optional Protocol to the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] was blocked in February 2006 on the grounds that leading MPs said contradicted Islamic laws. Al Menbar Bloc president Dr Salah Abdulrahman complained that the covenant would allow citizens to change religions without any restrictions, noting &quot;This means that Muslims could convert to another religion, something against the Islamic law, since those who do so should be beheaded,&quot; he said. &quot;Under the convention, women have the right to marry without their father's consent, while in Islam they should do so if she was a virgin&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=136119&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=28339&amp;date=2-22-2006 MPs refuse to ratify rights law] [[Gulf Daily News]] February 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

It was not until June 2006 that a second attempt was made to ratify the country’s accession to the Covenant, meaning that Bahrain did not formally accede to the treaty until September 20, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohchr.org/english/countries/ratification/4.htm Signatories of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights] [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Civil society has been prominent in supporting specific legislation promoting human rights through parliament. One recent campaign is the call for Bahrain’s government to ratify the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court. It is being led by the Bahrain-branch of the [http://www.iccnow.org/ Coalition for the International Criminal Court] and wants the government to transfer the draft bill on ratification to parliament at the earliest. The Bahraini Coalition for the ICC is headed by Nasser Burdestani (who is also the head of the Bahrain-branch of [[Amnesty International]]), who commented:

{{quote| &quot;The fact that we in Bahrain do not suffer from such grave crimes that are within the court's jurisdiction should facilitate the process of ratification without any reservations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_articles.asp?Article=166591&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29293&amp;date=1/7/2007 Bahrain urged to ratify Rome Statute] [[Gulf Daily News]], January 7, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Citing the role that Bahrain plays in the region and the domino effect, the Coalition for the International Criminal Court Co-ordinator for the Middle East and North Africa, Amal Basha, said Bahrain's ratification could have a significant impact among the neighbouring Persian Gulf countries: &quot;We believe that Bahrain could serve as a real catalyst by ratifying as soon as possible,&quot; she said. &quot;It would provide a serious boost to the growing world movement to ensure accountability for the worst violations of international human rights and humanitarian law.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/Story.asp?Article=166591&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29293 Bahrain urged to ratify Rome Statute] [[Gulf Daily News]], January 7, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Freedom of speech==

The government claims that the press is free.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/Story.asp?Article=177085&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=30019 Bahrain Press one of freest], Gulf Daily News, April 8, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.gulfnews.com/articles/07/03/29/10114491.html Bahrain's media under scrutiny], Gulf News, March 29, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the Penal Code of 1976, still active today, has been widely criticized by local and international human rights bodies for granting the regime widespread powers to suppress dissent. [[Human Rights Watch]] noted in 2004 that the Penal Code gives the government &quot;wide latitude to suppress public criticism&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/09/29/bahrai9413.htm Bahrain: Activist Jailed After Criticizing Prime Minister], [[Human Rights Watch]], 29 September 2004&lt;/ref&gt; and that it &quot;has provisions that contradict international human rights standards&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2006/06/08/bahrai13531.htm Bahrain: King Should Reject Law on Public Gatherings], [[Human Rights Watch]], 8 June 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amnesty International]] in 2004 stated the Code can be used &quot;as a justification to restrict freedom of expression. The organization reiterates its call for the Code to be reviewed as soon a possible to ensure compliance with international human rights standards.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGMDE110052004?open&amp;of=ENG-BHR&quot;&gt;Bahrain: Amnesty International welcomes the release of Abdul Hadi al-Khawaja], [[Amnesty International]], 22 November 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Human Right Watch 2011  country report and the international press, freedom of the press both in print and on web sites is severely with websites blocked, journalists allegedly tortured and editors fired.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fleishman&gt;Jeffrey Fleishman [http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/world/la-fg-bahrain-shiites-20110502,0,4278361.story] &quot;After crushed protests, Bahrain is accused of deepened oppression of Shiites&quot;, May 12, 2011, Los Angeles Times.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bna.bh/portal/en/news/451565?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+BNA_EN+%28BahrainNewsAgency_EN%29&amp;utm_content=Twitter]. [[Bahrain News Agency]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Internet===
[[Image:Batelco.blocked.png|thumb|A Bahraini website blocked]]
Internet censorship in Bahrain is classified as pervasive in the political and social areas, as substantial in Internet tools, and as selective in conflict/security by the [[OpenNet Initiative]] in August 2009.&lt;ref name=ONICountryProfiles&gt;[http://opennet.net/research/profiles &quot;ONI Country Profiles&quot;], Research section at the OpenNet Initiative web site, a collaborative partnership of the Citizen Lab at the Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto; the Berkman Center for Internet &amp; Society at Harvard University; and the SecDev Group, Ottawa&lt;/ref&gt; Bahrain is on [[Reporters Without Borders]]' countries under surveillance by RWB in 2011.&lt;ref name=RWBEnemies&gt;[http://march12.rsf.org/i/Internet_Enemies.pdf ''Internet Enemies''], Reporters Without Borders, Paris, March 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

On  5 January 2009 the Ministry of Culture and Information issued an order (Resolution No 1 of 2009)&lt;ref&gt;Resolution No 1 of 2009, Ministry of Culture and Information,  published in Official Gazette, Issue No.2877, dated 8 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt; pursuant to the Telecommunications Law and Press and Publications Law of Bahrain that regulates the blocking and unblocking of websites. This resolution requires all ISPs - among other things - to procure and install a website blocking software solution chosen by the Ministry. The Telecommunications Regulatory Authority (&quot;TRA&quot;) assisted the Ministry of Culture and Information in the execution of the said Resolution by coordinating the procurement of the unified website blocking software solution. This software solution is operated solely by the Ministry of Information and Culture and neither the TRA nor ISPs have any control over sites that are blocked or unblocked.

==Freedom of Association==

According to the Human Right Watch 2011 country report, freedom of association is severely curtailed by an association law, &quot;which prohibits organizations from involvement in political activities.&quot;&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;  The [[Bahrain Human Rights Society]], the Bahrain [[Migrant Workers' Protection Society (Bahrain)|Migrant Workers' Protection Society]], [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]] and [[Bahrain Youth Human Rights Society]] have been closed or ordered to close.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;

==Bandar Gate==
{{main|Bandargate scandal}} 
The Bandargate scandal refers to an alleged political conspiracy by the certain government officials in Bahrain to foment sectarian strife and marginalize the majority Shia community in the country. The conspiracy was allegedly lead and financed by Sheikh Ahmed bin Ateyatalla Al Khalifa, Minister of Cabinet Affairs and head of the Civil Informatics Organization and member of the Al Khalifa royal family. The allegations were revealed in September 2006, in a 240-page document produced by the Gulf Centre for Democratic Development, and authored by Dr Salah Al Bandar, an adviser to the Cabinet Affairs Ministry. Following the distribution of the report, Bahraini police forcibly deported Dr Al Bandar to the United Kingdom, where he holds citizenship.
According to Dr al-Bandar, the Minister paid five main operatives a total of more than $2.7 million to run:
*a secret intelligence cell spying on Shi’as
*‘GONGOs’ – government operated bogus NGOs like the ‘Bahraini Jurists Society’ and the ‘Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society’
*internet forums and websites that foment sectarian hatred
*subsidisation of ‘new converts’ from Shia Islamic sect to the Sunni sect
payments for election rigging.

==Freedom of religion==
{{Main|Freedom of religion in Bahrain}}

The Constitution states that Islam is the official religion and that Shari'a (Islamic law) is a principal source for legislation. Article 22 of the Constitution provides for freedom of conscience, the inviolability of worship, and the freedom to perform religious rites and hold religious parades and meetings, in accordance with the customs observed in the country; however, the Government placed some limitations on the exercise of this right. The Government continued to exert a level of control and to monitor both Sunni and Shi'a Muslims, and there continued to be government discrimination against Shi'a Muslims in certain fields. Members of other religious groups who practice their faith privately do so without interference from the Government. There were occasional reports of incidents between the Government and elements of the Shi'a majority population, who were often critical of the Sunni-controlled Government's rule. Problems continued to exist, stemming primarily from the Government's perceived unequal treatment of Shi'a in the country.

===Destruction of religious facilities===
In the wake of the 2011 [[Arab Spring]] uprising and crackdown against Shia protest in Bahrain, &quot;dozens&quot; of Shia mosques have been leveled by the government according to a report in McClatchy newspapers. According to Shiite leaders interviewed by the reporter, work crews have often arrived &quot;in the dead of night, accompanied by police and military escorts&quot;, to demolish the mosques, and in many cases, have hauled away the buildings' rubble before townspeople awake so as to leave no trace.  Sheikh Khalid bin Ali bin Abdulla al Khalifa, the minister of justice and Islamic affairs for Bahrain, defended the demolitions stating: &quot;These are not mosques. These are illegal buildings.&quot; However the McClatchy reporter found that photos taken of several mosques before their destruction by the government &quot;showed they were well maintained, decades-old structures.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman&quot;&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0511/Bahrain-s-Sunni-rulers-target-Shiite-mosques?cmpid=ema:nws:Daily%20Auto%2005112011&amp;cmpid=ema:nws:NzI5NjYzNTI3NwS2 Bahrain's Sunni rulers target Shiite mosques], By Roy Gutman, McClatchy Newspapers, May 11, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media and publication===

Bahrain has [[List of newspapers in Bahrain|eight daily newspapers]] representing a broad section of opinion. In 2002, ''[[Alwasat (Bahraini newspaper)|Al Wasat]]'' was set up by [[Mansoor Al-Jamri]], the son of Bahrain's spiritual [[Shi'a]] leader, Sheikh [[Abdul-Amir Al-Jamri]] and the spokesman of the [[Bahrain Freedom Movement]]. The paper is as broadly sympathetic to the Shia Islamist opposition, particularly [[Ali Salman]]. [[Akhbar Al Khaleej]] has traditionally been close to Bahrain's Left and Arab nationalist strands, featuring controversial columnists such as Sameera Rajab. [[Al Ayam (Bahrain)|Al Ayam]] is seen as solidly pro-government, with its proprietor an advisor to the King.

The Press Law 47 of 2002 has been strongly criticised as restrictive as it specifies criminal charges against those who criticise the head of state or Islam, or &quot;threaten national security&quot;.  However, discussion in the newspapers is often robust with journalists frequently criticising government ministers: for instance  one newspaper recently criticised the Minister of Housing, Fahmi Al Jowder, for lavishing &quot;ludicrous praise&quot; on the King.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.gulfnews.com/articles/06/03/01/10022312.html Minister criticised for lavishing 'undue praise', Gulf News, January 3, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2006, the Criminal Court issued a ban on the publication of any news, information or commentary on the series of allegations in the [[Bandargate scandal]], which has continued to date.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bahrainrights.org/ref06100500 Bahraini Higher Criminal Court: Banning Publication of News or Information Related to the “Bandar-Gate” Scandal], [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], 5 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In the following weeks, the Ministry of Information ordered Bahraini [[Internet service provider|ISP]]s to block several websites that violated the ban, include the websites of [[National Democratic Action]] (liberal opposition political society), the [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]] and the [[Arab Network for Human Rights Information]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bahrainrights.org/ref06110200 Ahead of elections: Bahrain govt threatens website owners with prosecution], [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], 2 November 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The block order was accompanied by press statements from the Ministry threatening the website owners with legal action.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=160332&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29225&amp;date=10-31-2006 Banned 'blogs' face legal action], [[Gulf Daily News]], 31 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Many political websites and [[blog]]s are blocked by the government,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=19487 Authorities block access to influential blog covering Bandargate scandal], [[Reporters Without Borders]], 30 October 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bahrainrights.org/ref06103001 Onslaught on freedom of expression in Bahrain continues], [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], October 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; and as of November 2005 the government requires all Bahraini websites are required to register with the Ministry of Information.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=13380 Reporters Without Borders denounces press freedom threat in website registration], [[Reporters Without Borders]], 26 April 2005&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2006, Bahraini government authorities blocked internet access to [[Google Earth]] and [[Google Video]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/d14d3576-7bfa-11db-b1c6-0000779e2340.html Google Earth spurs Bahraini equality drive], [[Financial Times]], November 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bahrainrights.org/ref08080600 Bahraini Authorities Block Access to Google Earth and Google Video], [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], August 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Receantly they have blocked the popular site anonymous.com&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anonymous.com.bh/ anonymous.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

Liberal intellectuals in the press have faced concerted campaigns against them by Islamists. In 2005, hundreds of Shia Islamists protested outside the Al Ayam's offices after it published a cartoon on Iran's [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]]'s election victory; while a Sunni Islamist campaign against the paper's editor, Isa Al Shaygi, was condemned at a conference of the  [[International Federation of Journalists]]: “The vicious and unprovoked attack on a respected and distinguished colleague is an example of the intolerant and undemocratic character of extremist politics that is increasingly being used against the free press.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifj.org/default.asp?Index=3910&amp;Language=EN Journalists’ Leaders Condemn Attack on Independent Newspaper and Editor in Bahrain][[International Federation of Journalists]], May 15, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

All broadcast media is owned and managed by the government. In 2005, three website administrators were arrested by security forces.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freemedia.at/cms/ipi/freedom_detail.html?country=/KW0001/KW0004/KW0089/ World Press Freedom Review 2005: Bahrain], [[International Press Institute]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public gatherings===

New political freedoms mean that public political activity and demonstrations are a common occurrence: according to the Ministry of Interior’s figures there were 498 street demonstrations in 2006, up from 259 the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulfnews.com/region/Bahrain/10113736.html Bahraini rallyists 'often do not know' purpose of protests], March 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2005, [[Human Rights Watch]] said:

{{quote|Bahrain has been a poster child for political reform in the Middle East, but police attacks like this one are a worrisome trend. [...] Bahrain is growing more repressive in response to peaceful political activism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2005/07/22/bahrai11401.htm Bahrain: Investigate Police Beatings], [[Human Rights Watch]], July 22, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Despite this prediction, the [[European University Institute]],  in its study of civil society in Bahrain in 2006, ''Voices in Parliament, Debates in Majalis, Banners on the Street: Avenues of Political Participation in Bahrain'', found that:

{{quote| Demonstrations of all sorts occur on a regular bases – less than common in the region. The laws regulating rallies and demonstrations predate the reforms; a bill for a new one has not yet been passed by parliament. As is the case with press freedom, a general liberal practise without the necessary legal foundation can be assessed. Normally neither the government nor the security forces interfere with demonstrations – unless feeling threatened. This lack of legal certainty is obviously wanted: ‘You have to see what we practice, not what is written in laws. Our practise is very liberal. One also has to see in which part of the world we’re living’ says the then head of the central informatics organisation and now minister of the royal court, Sheikh Mohammed bin Atiyatallah Al Khalifa.&lt;ref name=&quot;iue.it&quot;/&gt;}}

Bahrain is the only country in the Middle East to have sacked a senior government minister as a direct result of a human rights issue. In 2004, when the security forces fired rubber bullets at a demonstration led by Shia religious leaders, [[King Hamad]] immediately fired the country’s longstanding Interior Minister (and member of the royal family) Sheikh Mohammed bin Khalifa Al Khalifa.&lt;ref name=&quot;iue.it&quot;&gt;[http://www.iue.it/RSCAS/WP-Texts/06_27.pdf Voices in Parliament, Debates in Majalis, Banners on the Street: Avenues of Political Participation in Bahrain], Katja Niethammar, Robert Schuman Centre for Advanced Studies, European University Institute, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

While public demonstrations about various issues regularly take place, they have sometimes resulted in clashes between the police and youths. Fifteen Bahraini [[Shia]] activists were arrested between May 16 and 20 May 2007 following clashes the police. Thirteen remain in custody, (as of June 2007) according to the Bahrain [[Youth Society for Human Rights]]. In response to the problem presented by violent protestors, the Serbia-based human rights group, the Centre for Applied Non-Violent Action and Strategies, has been invited to Bahrain to teach demonstrators how to demonstrate peacefully. Under the scheme begun in 2007, peace camps will be set up in various trouble spots where specialists will advise on using protest strategies that do not involve violence. It is expected that a thousand youths will go through the training scheme.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/story.asp?Article=188959&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=30130 Peace camp a hit in villages] Gulf Daily News, July 28, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

The Interior Ministry had to resist pressure in May 2007 from business leaders to ‘crack down’ on the rioters, as well as deal with concerns that local residents would take matters into their own hands and deal with the rioters themselves. Concerns about vigilantism resulted in a call by Central Municipal Council vice-chairman Abbas Mahfoodh for closer cooperation between politicians and the Interior Ministry to stamp out rioting, after residents of the town of Tubli confronted and chased away three masked men who allegedly planned to commit acts of sabotage using Molotov cocktail firebombs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=182166&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=30055&amp;date=5/14/2007 Action against rioting urged], Gulf Daily News, May 14, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In a report issued in 2006, the &quot;[[Arab Network for Human Rights Information]]&quot; (a member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]) documented two cases of human rights activists being harassed by government authorities, through physical and sexual assaults, and fabricated cases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrinfo.net/en/reports/re2006/ Sexual assaults and fabrication of cases against journalists and activists: &quot;Tunisia, Egypt, and Bahrain&quot;], [[Arab Network for Human Rights Information]], 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic and social rights==
{{Empty section|date=May 2008}}

==Women's rights and gender==

{{See also|Gay rights in Bahrain|Women's political rights in Bahrain}}

King Hamad’s moves to promote women’s rights have been described by Amnesty International as representing a “New Dawn for Bahraini Women”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.amnesty.org/web/wire.nsf/March2002/Bahrain New Dawn for Bahraini Women] The Wire, Amnesty International, March 2002&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, women voted for the first time in national elections and were given equal political rights.

However, these top-down reforms have proven contentious, with calls for reform opposed by conservatives and the [[Al Khalifa|royal family]]. In 2002 the decision by [[King Hamad]] to grant women the right to vote and equal political rights with men was opposed by a majority of Bahraini women, with 60% of women&lt;ref&gt;[http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=5888 In the Gulf, women are not women’s best friends], [[Daily Star (Beirut)|Daily Star]], June 20, 2005 (republished by Yale Global)&lt;/ref&gt; surveyed saying they disagreed with the move. Salafists have publicly restated their opposition to women's participation in parliament, and none of the Islamist parties that dominate parliament has ever fielded a female candidate. One woman won a seat in parliament in 2006, although her victory in the sparsely populated constituency in the south of the country was seen by some as engineered by the government which wanted to see a woman represented in Council of Deputies.

A bill prompted by women's rights activists in 2005 to introduce a unified personal status law to protect women's rights in marriage, divorce and other family matters was opposed in a series of large-scale demonstrations organised by an alliance of salafists and Shia Islamists including [[Al Wefaq]] and [[Asalah]]. The demonstrations (and the implicit threat of escalation by those who organised them) forced the government to withdraw the law and was seen as a major defeat for women's rights activists.

In response to sweeping poll victories by Islamists in [[Bahraini parliamentary election, 2006|2006's election]], [[Amnesty International| Amnesty International Bahrain]]'s head of campaigns, Fawzia Rabea, described the threat to women's rights as 'very serious' and called on women to do everything in their power to fight laws proposed by the new parliament that could limit their freedom. After newly elected [[Al Wefaq]] MP, Sayed Abdulla Al A'ali, called for legislation to restrict women's employment rights by banning women from &quot;male-orientated jobs&quot;, Ms Rabea said, &quot;With this type of thinking I am sure we are facing a very big challenge with parliament. I am worried about this, it is very serious.&quot; Bahrain Women's Union president, Mariam Al Ruwaie, expressed surprised at the MP's suggestions, &quot;This does not agree with His Majesty the King's reforms, which give women and men the same rights for education and work. In Bahrain's society women make up 26 per cent of the labour force, there are more girls in schools and universities than men and their results are better...I am worried because the parliament has not started and he [Mr Al A'ali] has said something like this. It is a bad start.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=163123&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29255&amp;date=11-30-2006 Women fight to keep freedom], [[Gulf Daily News]], November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ghada Jamsheer]], the most prominent women's rights activist in Bahrain&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/europe/html/060522/jamsheer.html Ghada Jamsheer], [[Time magazine]], May 14, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulf-daily-news.com/Story.asp?Article=143558&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29056 Activist on Forbes list], [[Gulf Daily News]], 15th May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; has called the government's reforms &quot;artificial and marginal&quot;. In a statement in December 2006 she said:

{{quote|The government is using the family law issue as a bargaining tool with opposition Islamic groups. This is evident through the fact that the authorities raise this issue when ever they want to distract attention from other controversial political issues. While no serious steps are taken to help approve this law, although the government and its puppet National Assembly had no trouble in the last four years when it came to approving restrictive laws related to basic freedoms.

All of this is why no one in Bahrain believes in Government clichés and government institution like the [[Supreme Council for Women|High Council for Women]]. The government used women’s rights as a decorative tool on the international level. While the High Council for Women was used to hinder non-governmental women societies and to block the registration of the Women Union for many years. Even when the union was recently registered, it was restricted by the law on societies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chanad.weblogs.us/?p=516 Women in Bahrain and the Struggle Against Artificial Reforms], Ghada Jamsheer, 18 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Women in the 2011 crackdown===
According to reports in [[NPR]] Bahraini human rights groups say &quot;hundreds of women have been detained&quot; in recent weeks prior to 30 May 2011, &quot;the first time in the wave of protests sweeping the Arab world that large groups of women have been targeted&quot;, according to analysts in the region.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/2011/05/31/136818563/women-the-latest-target-of-bahrains-crackdown Women The Latest Target Of Bahrain's Crackdown] by Kelly McEvers, May 31, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Labor==

According to the [[International Confederation of Free Trade Unions]] annual report of 2006 unions are allowed to play an &quot;effective role&quot; with workers having the right to unionise. According to the ICTFU's annual report:

{{quote|The Workers' Trade Union Law of September 2002 introduced the right to belong to trade unions in Bahrain. It established the General Federation of Bahrain Trade Unions (GFBTU) but not full freedom of association, as all trade unions have to belong to the GFBTU. Workers in the private and public sector may join trade unions, including non-citizens, who make up the majority of Bahrain's workforce.

Only one trade union may be formed at each establishment, but no prior authorisation is required to form a union. The only requirement is that the union's constitution must be communicated to the Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs, together with the names of the founding members.

An amended trade union law that would allow government employees to form trade unions but would remove some workers rights' protection was submitted to Parliament in October 2004. However it had still not been approved by the end of 2005.

Trade unions are not subject to administrative dissolution. They may not engage in political activities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icftu.org/displaydocument.asp?Index=991223920&amp;Language=EN Bahrain, Annual Survey of Violations of Trade Union Rights Worldwide Report], [[International Confederation of Free Trade Unions]], 7 June 2006&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The ICFTU's main concern in its 2006 report was that a new labour law would be far more restrictive of worker's rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icftu.org/displaydocument.asp?Index=991223810&amp;Language=EN Brutal Suppression of Workers’ Rights Detailed in Worldwide Report], [[International Confederation of Free Trade Unions]], 7 June 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The ICFTU commented:

{{quote|A new law, soon to be passed, looks set to restrict unions' freedom to carry out a legal strike. There was much concern about the lack of proper protection foreseen for foreign workers who make up 60 per cent of the workforce. The head of Gulf Air's union was sacked shortly after his election.&lt;ref name=&quot;icftu.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.icftu.org/displaydocument.asp?Index=991223920&amp;Language=EN Annual Survey of Violations of Trade Union Rights, 2006], [[International Confederation of Free Trade Unions]], June 2006&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A visiting delegate from the [[International Labour Organization]] at a seminar in Bahrain on trade unionism, held under the patronage of the Labour Ministry, described some of Bahrain's labour laws as out of line with international standards. According to the ILO international labour standards department deputy director, Karen Curtis, the current rules governing where strikes can be held in Bahrain were too restrictive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=165149&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29276&amp;date=12-21-2006 Union law 'out of global step'], [[Gulf Daily News]], 21 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the government’s labour reforms, Bahrain’s Crown Prince, [[Sheikh Salman bin Hamad Al Khalifa]], was invited as guest of honour to the [[International Labour Organisation| International Labour Organisation’s]] 96th session,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=184935&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=30083&amp;date=6-11-2007 ILO honour for Crown Prince], Gulf Daily News, June 11, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; where he used the opportunity of addressing the conference to announce that the first regional dialogue on workers' issues would be held in Bahrain. &quot;This will offer countries that recruit manpower and those that provide it an opportunity to engage in an open and honest discussion on the impact of globalisation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=185001&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=30084&amp;date=6/12/2007 Voice for workers, Gulf Daily News], July 12, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The ILO Director General Juan Somavia has described the Crown Prince as an innovator with a modern vision of commitment to change and a belief in dialogue. Somavia has noted that Bahrain had been one of the pioneers of Decent Work Country Programmes, beginning with a pilot programme in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ilo.org/global/About_the_ILO/Media_and_public_information/Press_releases/lang--en/WCMS_082998 Crown Prince of Bahrain calls for increased social dialogue, fair globalization, announces regional labour summit], International Labour Organisation, June 11, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Migrant workers===

According to Human Rights Watch, in as of 2011 there were more than 460,000 guest workers in Bahrain, many of whom experience prolonged periods of withheld wages, passport confiscation, unsafe housing, excessive work hours and physical abuse.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt; Government protective measures are &quot;largely ineffective.&quot;&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=171212&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=29344&amp;date=2-27-2007 Wage row workers in protest march], Gulf Daily News, February 27, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2009 Bahrain adopted Decision 79/2009 permitting guest workers, except for domestics, more freedom to change jobs.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt; According to Human Rights Watch, as of 2011 many workers were unaware of this right.&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;

In 2007, government passed legislation to ban construction and other outdoor work between noon and 4pm during the summer – the hottest times of the day. The vast majority of those involved in this type of work being expatriate labourers from the Indian sub-continent. The move was backed by a “massive” labour inspection campaign by the Ministry of Labour to ensure that companies obeyed the decision. The ban was criticized by construction companies saying that the government’s decision would delay their projects, but according to the Ministry of Labour, migrant workers' protection representatives and human rights activities have welcomed the move.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.gulfnews.com/articles/07/07/17/10139834.html Campaign to ensure implementation of break rule in Bahrain launched], Gulf News, July 17, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

An ICFTU Annual Report 2006 found that &quot;Foreign workers harshly treated&quot;:

{{quote|There are a large number of foreign workers and, while in theory they are allowed to join unions and run for union office, they mainly prefer to stay out of union activities as they have no protection against dismissal. According to the proposed legislation, if expatriate workers overstay their work permits, they suffer heavy fines, are imprisoned for unspecified lengths of time and then deported. The government admitted that the new law would not give domestic servants any employment rights, but contained measures that would protect them against abuse from employers.&lt;ref name=&quot;icftu.org&quot;/&gt;}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=188951&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=30130&amp;date=7/28/2007 New union for construction workers], Gulf Daily News, July 28, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite these reforms, Bahrain remains a Tier 3 country on the US State Department Trafficking in Persons report, the worst tier which means that these countries made little or no efforts to improve the situation.

==Human rights NGOs==

There are several generic human rights NGOs in Bahrain, and other NGOs working in related fields such as women's rights, child rights and migrant labour. The two most prominent organisations have been the [[Bahrain Human Rights Society]] and the [[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]], which have frequently been highly critical of one another, the Center accusing the Society of having been unduly close to government. Other NGOs active around 2008-10 included the [[Bahrain Youth Human Rights Society]], the Women’s Petition Committee, the Committee for Martyrs and Victims of Torture, the Human Rights Office of the [[Haq Movement|Haq Movement for Liberty and Democracy]], the Committee for Citizenship-less and the Coordinating Committee for the Defence of Political Detainees. 

As of 2011, several human rights NGOs, including at least the first three named above, had been closed or ordered to close, as was the Bahrain [[Migrant Workers' Protection Society (Bahrain)|Migrant Workers' Protection Society]].&lt;ref name=HRW2011/&gt;

==National human rights institution==

In 2008, during the [[Universal Periodic Review]] of its human rights record at the [[United Nations Human Rights Council|UN Human Rights Council]], the Government announced plans to create a [[national human rights institutions|national human rights institution]] for Bahrain. The [[Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights]] and the Foreign Ministry jointly organised a workshop in Manama, bringing in NHRI experts from [[Jordan]], [[Morocco]] and [[Northern Ireland]] to meet a wide range of Bahraini civil society. The NHRI was duly established by the King on 11 November 2009 through Royal Order No. 46/2009. 

On 25 April 2010 Royal Order No. 16/2010 appointed 17 men and five women as the first members of the NHRI, including prominent human rights activists Salman al-Sayyid ‘Ali Kamal al-Din, the former deputy secretary-general of the independent Bahrain Human Rights Society, as president.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/MDE11/002/2010/en/67984e26-8c76-4152-9dac-626c4a6356da/mde110022010en.html Amnesty International press statement, 30 April 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; While the appointments were initially welcomed by [[Amnesty International]], other NGOs including the Bahrain Center for Human Rights questioned the credibility and independence of the new institution.  The Center alleged that several of the 22 nominees held government appointments or were linked to bodies accused by the Society of operating as government fronts or [[GONGO]]s, such as the [[Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society]], the Jurists Society and the Association of Public Freedoms and Human Rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bahrainrights.org/en/node/3086 Bahrain Centre for Human Rights press release, 2 May 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 September 2010 Salman Kamal al-Din resigned as president, in protest at the institution's failure to criticise the arrests of pro-democracy activists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/world-report-2011/world-report-2011-bahrain Human Rights Watch World Report 2011: Bahrain]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Human rights}}
*[[Bahrain Center for Human Rights]]
*[[Bahrain Human Rights Society]]
*[[Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society]]
*[[List of Bahrain-related topics#Human rights in Bahrain]]
*[[Al Bandar report]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.hrw.org/en/middle-eastn-africa/bahrain Human Rights Watch: Bahrain]
*[http://www.amnestyusa.org/all-countries/bahrain/page.do?id=1011111 Amnesty International: Bahrain]
*[http://bahrainrights.org Bahrain Center for Human Rights]
*[http://www.bhrws.org Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society]
*[http://www.redress.org/country_bahrain.html Redress Trust: Bahrain]
*[http://ifex.org/en/content/view/full/220/ International Freedom of Expression Exchange: Bahrain]
*[http://www.ndi.org/worldwide/mena/bahrain/bahrain.asp National Democratic Institute: Bahrain]
*[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2005/61686.htm Country Reports on Human Rights Practices - 2005], US Department of State
*[http://www.icftu.org/list.asp?Type=ALL&amp;Order=Date&amp;Language=EN&amp;STEXT=bahrain International Confederation of Free Trade Unions: Bahrain]
*[http://www.arabhumanrights.org/en/countries/index.asp?cid=2 Arab Human Rights Index: Bahrain]

*{{PDFlink|[http://www.apfw.org/data/annualconference/2004/english/papers/Bahrain04MahaEn.pdf Freeing the Arab Media from State Control: The state of the Press in Bahrain]|116&amp;nbsp;KB}}, Arab Press Freedom Watch Third Annual Conference, May 2004
*[http://gcclub.org/lectures058.html Bahrain: Five years of lost opportunities],  Proceeding of a  seminar held under the auspices of [[Eric Lubbock, 4th Baron Avebury|Lord Avebury]], the Vice-Chairman of the Parliamentary Human Rights Group in the [[House of Lords]], 15 December 2005
*[http://www.un.org/webcast/unhrc/archive.asp?go=080407 Review of Bahrain] by the [[United Nations Human Rights Council]]'s [[United Nations Human Rights Council#Universal Periodic Review|Universal Periodic Review]], April 7, 2008

{{Human rights in the Middle East}}
{{Asia topic|Human rights in}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Human Rights In Bahrain}}
[[Category:Human rights in Bahrain| ]]

[[ar:حقوق الإنسان في البحرين]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
