<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="84656" ns="0" title="Winsor McCay"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name   = Winsor McCay
| image     = Winsor McCay.jpg
| caption   =
| image_size  =
| birth_date  =September 26, 1869
| birth_place =
| death_date  = July 26, 1934
| death_place =
| cause_death =
| occupation  = Animator, cartoonist
| spouse      =
| parents     = Robert McKay and Janet Murray McKay
| children    =
| signature   =
}}

'''Winsor McCay''' (September 26, 1869 – July 26, 1934) was an American [[cartoonist]] and [[animator]].

A prolific artist, McCay's pioneering early animated films far outshone the work of his contemporaries, and set a standard followed by [[Walt Disney]] and others in later decades. His two best-known creations are the newspaper comic strip ''[[Little Nemo|Little Nemo in Slumberland]]'', which ran from 1905–1914 and 1924–1927, and the animated cartoon ''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'', which he created in 1914.

His comic strip work has influenced generations of artists, including creators such as [[William Joyce (writer)|William Joyce]], [[André LeBlanc (artist)|André LeBlanc]], [[Jean Giraud|Moebius]], [[Maurice Sendak]], [[Chris Ware]] and [[Bill Watterson]].

==Early life==
[[Image:Petit Sammy éternue.jpg|thumb|274px|Little Sammy Sneeze]]
McCay was the son of Robert McKay (later changed to McCay) and Janet Murray McKay; Robert at various times worked as a [[teamster]], a grocer, and a real estate agent. Winsor's exact place and year of birth are uncertain &amp;mdash; he claimed to have been born in [[Spring Lake, Michigan]] in 1871, but his gravestone says 1869, and census reports state that he was born in [[Canada]] in 1867. He was originally named '''Zenas Winsor McKay''', in honor of his father's employer, Zenas G. Winsor. He later dropped the name Zenas.

In 1886, McCay's parents sent him to [[Cleary University|Cleary's Business College]] in [[Ypsilanti, Michigan]] to learn to be a businessman. While in Ypsilanti, he also received his only formal art training, from John Goodison of Michigan State Normal College (now known as [[Eastern Michigan University]]). Goodison taught him the strict application of the fundamentals of [[perspective (graphical)|perspective]], which he put to significant use later in his career. Goodison, formerly a [[stained glass|glass stainer]], also influenced McCay's bold use of color.

==Career==
In 1889, McCay moved to [[Chicago]], intending to study at the [[School of the Art Institute of Chicago|Art Institute of Chicago]], but due to lack of money had to find employment instead. He worked for the National Printing and Engraving Company, producing woodcuts for circus and theatrical posters. Two years later, he moved to [[Cincinnati, Ohio]] and went to work as an artist for Kohl and Middleton's Vine Street [[Dime museum|Dime Museum]]. While in Cincinnati he married Maude Leonore Dufour. McCay began doing vaudeville [[chalk talk]]s in 1906.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filmreference.com/Writers-and-Production-Artists-Lo-Me/McCay-Winsor.html Film reference: Winsor McCay]&lt;/ref&gt; In his ''The Seven Ages of Man'' vaudeville act, he drew two faces and progressively aged them.&lt;ref name=chalk&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=H3USAr6i1e0C&amp;pg=PA3&amp;lpg=PA3&amp;dq=vaudeville+%22chalk+talks%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=phFiS5z0UB&amp;sig=n7ZqUXzoMB0TEKYkURaaR-Wdevo&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=bePVSrGlJJTClAf95JidCQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CAwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=vaudeville%20%22chalk%20talks%22&amp;f=false Stabile, Carol A. and Mark Harrison. ''Prime Time Animation: Television Animation and American Culture''. Routledge, 2003.]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Little Nemo Elephant 1.jpg|thumb|Little Nemo in Slumberland]]
McCay's first major comic strip series was ''[[Tales of the Jungle Imps by Felix Fiddle]]''. Forty-three installments were published from January to November 1903, in the ''[[Cincinnati Enquirer]]''. The strip was based on poems by [[George Randolph Chester]], then a reporter and editor at the ''Enquirer''.  The stories concerned jungle creatures and the ways that they adapted to a hostile world, with individual titles such as ''How the Elephant Got His Trunk'' and ''How the Ostrich Got So Tall''.

His strips ''[[Little Nemo]]'' and ''[[Dreams of a Rarebit Fiend]]'' were both set in the dreams of their characters and featured fantasy art that attempted to capture the look and feel of dreams. McCay's cartoons were never overwhelmingly popular, but always had a strong following because of his expressive graphic style.  Newspaper pages were physically much larger in that time and McCay usually had a half a page to work with.  For [[fantasy art]] in comics, his only rival was [[Lyonel Feininger]], who went on to have a career in the fine arts after his comics days were over.

McCay also created a number of animated short films, in which every single frame of each cartoon (with each film requiring thousands of frames) was hand-drawn by McCay and occasionally his assistants. McCay went on [[vaudeville]] tours with his films. He presented lectures and did drawings; then he interacted with his animated films, performing such tricks as holding his hand out to &quot;pet&quot; his animated creations.
[[Image:Gertie the Dinosaur.ogv|thumb|thumbtime=6:58|left|Gertie the Dinosaur]]
The star of McCay's groundbreaking animated film ''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'' is classified by film and animation historians as the first cartoon character created especially for film to display a unique, realistic personality. In the film, Gertie causes trouble and cries when she is scolded, and finally she gives McCay himself a ride on her back as he steps into the movie picture.

In addition to a series of cartoons based on his popular &quot;rarebit&quot; gags, McCay also created ''[[The Sinking of the Lusitania]]'', a depiction of the attack on the maritime ship. The cartoon contained a message that was meant to inspire America into joining [[World War I]].

==Death and legacy==
McCay died in 1934 and was buried at the [[Cemetery of the Evergreens]] in [[Brooklyn]].

[[Woody Gelman]] discovered many of the original Little Nemo strips at a cartoon studio where [[Bob McCay]], Winsor's son, had worked in 1966.&lt;ref name=Jamieson2010&gt;Mint Condition: How Baseball Cards Became an American Obsession, p.126, Dave Jamieson, 2010, Atlantic Monthly Press, imprint of Grove/Atlantic Inc., New York, NY, ISBN 978-0-8021-1939-1&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the original drawings that Gelman recovered were displayed at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] under the direction of curator [[A. Hyatt Mayor]]. In 1973, Gelman would publish a collection of Little Nemo strips in Italy.&lt;ref name=Jamieson2010 /&gt;

==Comic strips==
*''[[Tales of the Jungle Imps by Felix Fiddle]]'' (1903)
*''[[Little Sammy Sneeze]]'' (1904 to 1906)
*''[[Dream of the Rarebit Fiend]]'' (1904–13)
*''[[The Story of Hungry Henrietta]]'' (1905)
*''[[A Pilgrim's Progress]]'' (1905 to 1910)
*''[[Little Nemo in Slumberland]]'' (1905 to 1914, 1924-1927) (1911-1914 under the title ''[[In the Land of Wonderful Dreams]]'') 
*''[[Poor Jake]]'' (1909 to 1911)

==Filmography==
[[File:Actors Benefit for Crippled Children, Winsor McCay sketching 1908.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Actors Benefit for Crippled Children, Winsor McCay [[sketch]]ing, 1908]]
*''[[Little Nemo]]'' (1911) also titled ''Winsor McCay, the Famous Cartoonist of the N.Y. Herald and His Moving Comics''
*''[[How a Mosquito Operates]]'' (1912) also titled ''The Story Of A Mosquito''
*''[[Gertie the Dinosaur]]'' (1914)
*''[[The Sinking of the Lusitania]]'' (1918)
*''[[Dreams of the Rarebit Fiend]]: Bug Vaudeville'' (1921)
*''Dreams of the Rarebit Fiend: The Pet'' (1921)
*''Dreams of the Rarebit Fiend: The Flying House'' (1921)
*''[[The Centaurs]]'' (1921)
*''Gertie on Tour'' (1921)
*''Flip's Circus'' (1921)
*''The Barnyard Performance'' (1922-27?) also called '' Performing Animals'' and The Midsummer's Nightmare

==Books and collections==
[[Image:LibertyBond-WinsorMcCay.jpg|thumb|Winsor McCay's [[World War I]] poster urging Americans to buy [[Liberty Bond]]s]]
*''Dreams of a Rarebit Fiend'' Dover, ISBN 0-486-21347-1
*''Little Nemo in the Palace of Ice and Further Adventures'' Dover, ISBN 0-486-23234-4
*''The Complete Little Nemo in Slumberland, Vol. I: 1905-1907'' Fantagraphics ISBN 0-930193-63-6 
*''The Complete Little Nemo in Slumberland, Vol. II: 1907-1908'' Fantagraphics ISBN 0-930193-64-4 
*''The Complete Little Nemo in Slumberland, Vol. III: 1908-1910'' Fantagraphics ISBN 1-56097-025-1
*''The Complete Little Nemo in Slumberland, Vol. IV: 1910-1911'' Fantagraphics ISBN 1-56097-045-6
*''The Complete Little Nemo in Slumberland, Vol. V: In the Land of Wonderful Dreams, Part 1: 1911-12'' Fantagraphics ISBN 0-924359-35-8 
*''The Complete Little Nemo in Slumberland, Vol. VI: In the Land of Wonderful Dreams, Part 2: 1913-14'' Fantagraphics ISBN 1-56097-130-4
*''Little Nemo 1905-1914'' Taschen, ISBN 3-8228-6300-9 
*''The Best of Little Nemo in Slumberland'' Stewart, Tabori, &amp; Chang, ISBN 1-55670-647-2
*''Little Nemo in Slumberland: So Many Splendid Sundays'' Sunday Press ISBN 0-9768885-0-5
*''Little Nemo in Slumberland: Many More Splendid Sundays'' Sunday Press ISBN 0-9768885-5-6
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 1'' Checker, ISBN 0-9741664-0-5 (“Tales of the Rarebit Fiend” and “Little Sammy Sneeze”)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 2'' Checker, ISBN 0-9741664-7-2 (More “Tales of the Rarebit Fiend” and “Little Sammy Sneeze,” “Centaurs,” “Hungry Henrietta,” and editorial illustrations.)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 3'' Checker, ISBN 0-9741664-9-9 (More “Tales of the Rarebit Fiend” (1907), “Little Sammy Sneeze,” “A Pilgrim’s Progress,” (1907) and editorial illustrations from New York period.)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 4'' Checker, ISBN 0-9753808-1-8 (more Dream of the Rarebit Fiend (early 1908), A Pilgrim’s Progress (early 1908), various Little Sammy Sneezes, and New York American editorial cartoons.)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 5'' Checker, ISBN 0-9753808-2-6 (Dream of the Rarebit Fiend (late 1908), A Pilgrim’s Progress (late 1908), Phoolish Phillip (all), Hungry Henrietta (all), and New York American editorial cartoons.)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 6'' Checker, ISBN 1-933160-05-5 (“Mr Goodenough”, Dream of the Rarebit Fiend (late 1908), A Pilgrim’s Progress (late 1908), and New York American editorial cartoons.)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 7'' Checker, ISBN 1-933160-05-5 (illustrations from New York editorial period, and collection of comic strips.)
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 8'' Checker, ISBN 1-933160-06-3 
*''Winsor McCay: Early Works, Vol. 9'' Checker, ISBN 978-1-933160-07-8
*''Daydreams and Nightmares'' Fantagraphics, ISBN 1-56097-569-5
*''Little Sammy Sneeze'' Sunday Press ISBN 0-97688-854-8

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* {{cite book|title=Winsor McCay: His Life and Art|author=John Canemaker|year=2005|publisher=Harry N. Abrams, Inc|isbn=0-8109-5941-0}}
* {{cite journal|title=Cartoon Library Acquires McCay Collection|journal=University Libraries New Notes|author=Ohio State University|date=1 June 2006|url=http://www.lib.ohio-state.edu/sites/staff/Newsnotes/nn060601.pdf|format=PDF}}
* {{cite book|title=Of Mice and Magic: A History of American Animated Cartoons; Revised and Updated|author=Leonard Maltin|year=1987|publisher=Plume Books|isbn=0-452-25993-2}}
* {{cite news|title=The Cartoonist Group: Background About Winsor McCay;|url=http://www.cartoonistgroup.com/properties/daydream/about.php/}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.sllib.org/Pages/Special%20Pages/McCay/McCay.htm Spring Lake District Library &quot;The Talented Winsor McCay&quot;]
* [http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/fales/mccay.html The Fales Library of NYU's guide to the David C. Bohnett Collection of Winsor McCay Drawings] 
*[http://www.springlakemccay.blogspot.com/ Meeting McCay]
*{{imdb name|0565560|Winsor McCay}} on [[Internet Movie Database]]
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.coconino-world.com/sites_auteurs/winsor/ Little Nemo in Slumberland Anniversary Special]
*[http://www.centaur.org/mccay/ Winsor McCay's ''The Centaurs''.]
*[http://www.comicstriplibrary.org/ Comic Strip Library has a complete collection of out-of-copyright Little Nemo pages]

{{Little Nemo}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Maccay, Winsor
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1934
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Maccay, Winsor}}
[[Category:1934 deaths]]
[[Category:American animators]]
[[Category:Artists from Cincinnati, Ohio]]
[[Category:Burials at the Cemetery of the Evergreens]]
[[Category:Cleary University alumni]]
[[Category:Comic strip cartoonists]]
[[Category:Eastern Michigan University alumni]]
[[Category:People from Chicago, Illinois]]
[[Category:People from Ypsilanti, Michigan]]
[[Category:Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category:Will Eisner Award Hall of Fame inductees]]

[[bs:Winsor McCay]]
[[ca:Winsor McCay]]
[[de:Winsor McCay]]
[[et:Winsor McCay]]
[[es:Winsor McCay]]
[[fr:Winsor McCay]]
[[hr:Winsor McCay]]
[[it:Winsor McCay]]
[[nl:Winsor McCay]]
[[ja:ウィンザー・マッケイ]]
[[no:Winsor McCay]]
[[pt:Winsor McCay]]
[[ro:Winsor McCay]]
[[ru:Маккей, Уинзор]]
[[sr:Винзор Макеј]]
[[fi:Winsor McCay]]
[[sv:Winsor McCay]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
