<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="84899" ns="0" title="Lititz, Pennsylvania"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{citation style|date=June 2011}}
{{Geobox
| Settlement
&lt;!-- *** Name section *** --&gt;
| name                        = Borough of Lititz
| native_name                 = 
| other_name                  = 
| other_name1                 = 
| category                    = 
&lt;!-- *** Image *** --&gt;
| image                       = LititzStreetScene.jpg
| image_size                  = 250px
| image_caption               = Typical street scene along Main Street in Lititz
&lt;!-- *** Symbols *** --&gt;
| flag                        = 
| flag_size                   =    
| symbol                      = 
| symbol_size                 = 
&lt;!-- *** Etymology &amp; nickname &amp; motto *** --&gt;
| etymology_type              = Named for
| etymology                   = A [[Bohemia]]n [[Litice (castle)|Castle]]
| nickname                    =
| motto                       = The Heart of Lancaster County
&lt;!-- *** Country etc. *** --&gt;
| country                     = United States
| state                       = Pennsylvania
| region                      = [[Lancaster County, Pennsylvania|Lancaster]]
| region_type                 = County
| district                    = 
&lt;!-- *** Geography *** --&gt;
| area_imperial               = 2.3
| area_land_imperial          = 2.3
| area_water_imperial         = 0.0
| area_water_percentage       = auto
| area_percentage_round       = 2
| area_round                  = 1
| location                    =
| lat_d                       = 40
| lat_m                       = 09
| lat_s                       = 17
| lat_NS                      = N
| long_d                      = 76
| long_m                      = 18
| long_s                      = 12
| long_EW                     = W
| elevation_imperial          = 381
| elevation_round             = 1
&lt;!-- *** Population *** --&gt;
| population_as_of            = 2000
| population                  = 9029
| population_density_imperial = 3884.0
| population_density_round    = 1
&lt;!-- *** Government *** --&gt;
| established_type            = Settled
| established                 = 1710
| established1_type           = Founded
| established1                = 1756
| mayor                       = Ronald G. Oettel, Jr. ([[Republican Party (United States)|R]])
| leader1_type                = Manager
| leader1                     = Sue Ann Barry
&lt;!-- *** Various codes *** --&gt;
| timezone                    = [[North American Eastern Time Zone|EST]]
| utc_offset                  = -5
| timezone_DST                = [[Eastern Daylight Time|EDT]]
| utc_offset_DST              = -4
| postal_code                 = 17543
| postal_code_type            = ZIP code
| area_code                   = [[Area code 717|717]] 
| area_code_type              =  
| code2_type                  =
| code2                       =
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free_type                   =  
| free                        =
| free1_type                  =  
| free1                       = 
&lt;!-- *** Map section *** --&gt;
| map                         = Lititz, Lancaster County Highlighted.png
| map_caption                 = Location of Lititz in Lancaster County
| map1                        = Pennsylvania Locator Map.PNG
| map1_caption                = Location of Lititz in Pennsylvania
| map1_locator                = Pennsylvania  
| map2                        = Map of USA PA.svg
| map2_caption                = Location of Pennsylvania in the United States
&lt;!-- *** Website *** --&gt;
| website                     = http://www.lititzpa.com 
}}
 
'''Lititz''' {{IPAc-en|icon|l|ɨ|ˈ|t|ɪ|t|s}}{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} is a borough in [[Lancaster County, Pennsylvania|Lancaster County]], [[Pennsylvania]], 6 miles (approximately 10&amp;nbsp;km) north of the city of [[Lancaster, Pennsylvania|Lancaster]].

==History==
Lititz was founded by members of the [[Moravian Church]] in [[1756]], and was named after a castle (mentioned form of name is [[German language|German]]; [[Czech language|Czech]] name of this castle is ''[[Litice Castle|Litice]]'') in [[Bohemia]] near the village  of [[Kunvald]] where the ancient Bohemian Brethren's Church had been founded in 1457. The roots of the Moravian Brethren's Church date back to the ancient Bohemian Brethren's Church. 

For a century, only Moravians were permitted to live in Lititz. Until the middle of the 19th century, only members of the congregation could own houses; others were required to lease. The lease-system was abolished in 1855, just five years before the beginning of the Civil War. More information can be found in the book ''A Brief History of Lititz Pennsylvania'' by Mary Augusta Huevener, published in 1947.

During a part of the [[American Revolutionary War|American Revolution]], the Brethren's House, built in [[1759]], was used as a hospital. A number of soldiers died and were buried here. Lititz is also home to Linden Hall School, the oldest all-girls boarding school in the United States. Located adjacent to the Moravian Church on {{convert|47|acre|m2}} of land, Linden Hall School was founded by the Moravians in 1746, a decade before the borough was incorporated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Linden Hall|url=http://www.lindenhall.org/content_09.aspx?cat=History|work=Linden Hall History|accessdate=18 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In modern days, Lititz is now recognized for having the longest continuous-running celebration of [[Independence Day (United States)|Independence Day]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}, which has been a town tradition since 1813. This celebration hosts a large volume of tourists and former Lititz residents who return for the Queen of Candles pageant and the yearly fireworks gala supporting Lititz Springs Park.  The park itself is decorated each year, rather extravagantly, with wooden beams and trestles placed from side to side of the stone-walled stream and stretching nearly the entire length of the park. The trestles are fitted sockets for white candles to be placed and lit during the celebration. The first candle has traditionally been lit by the years Queen of Candles pageant winner. Musical performances each year ensue, and in the past years have often included Flamin' Dick and the Hot Rods. The park also hosts festivities for children and a plethora of food similar to what may be found at a fair. The 4th of July parade is sponsored by Lititz Lions. Another large event in the summer is the annual art show sponsored by the Village Art Association of Lititz, along with the craft show sponsored by the Lititz Rotary Club, which extends from the Lititz Springs Park out into Broad Street (PA-501) and Main Street (PA-772).

During 2006 a year long celebration was held commemorating the 250th anniversary of the naming of the town.  Some of the major events included a service and commemoration ceremony in Lititz Springs Park on Sunday June 11, the official naming ceremony on Monday June 12, a fountain show in the park called &quot;Symphonic Springs&quot; during August 20–26th, and a New Year's celebration.

Lititz is often named in lists of &quot;delightfully-named towns&quot; in [[Pennsylvania Dutchland]], along with [[Intercourse, Pennsylvania|Intercourse]], [[Blue Ball, Pennsylvania|Blue Ball]], [[Mount Joy]], [[Bareville]], [[Bird-in-Hand]] and [[Paradise, Pennsylvania|Paradise]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ward65&quot;&gt;Ward's quarterly (1965) p.109 quote: {{quotation|...in such delightfully-named towns in Pennsylvania Dutchland as his native Mount Joy, and neighboring Lititz, Blue Ball, Bareville, Intercourse, Bird in Hand, and Paradise.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Anderson79&quot;&gt;Anderson (1979) p.214 quote: {{quotation|&quot;...but anyone who names their towns Mount Joy, Intercourse, and Blue Ball can't be all bad. Obviously they have more on their minds than just religion.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Museums06&quot;&gt;Museums Association (2006) p.61 quote: {{quotation|Which brings us to Intercourse. You can imagine my delight when I found out that the Amish call the town of Intercourse, Pennsylvania, their home. There seems to be a lot of explanations from locals trying to pass off the name as a bastardisation of 'Enter Course' and so on, but seeing as there are other local towns called Blue Ball, Bird In Hand, and Mount Joy, I suspect that the person responsible had a very juvenile sense of humour. The town sits in upstate Pennsylvania and is a tourist trap for anyone even remotely curious about the Amish way of life.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rand  McNally and Company (1978) p.52&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mencken (1963) p.653 quote: {{quotation|In the years since then many of these names have been changed to more elegant ones,&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and others have vanished with the ghost towns they adorned, but not a few still hang on. Indeed, there are plenty of lovely specimens to match them in the East, in regions that were also frontier in their days, ''e.g.'', the famous cluster in Lancaster county, Pennsylvania: Bird in Hand, Bareville, Blue Ball, Mt. Joy, Intercourse and Paradise.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
Lititz is located at {{Coord|40|9|17|N|76|18|12|W|city}}{{GR|1}}.

Pennsylvania Routes [[Pennsylvania Route 772|772]] (Orange and Main Streets) and [[Pennsylvania Route 501|501]] (Broad Street) run through the town.

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the borough has a total area of {{convert|2.3|sqmi|km2}}, all land.

==Law and government==
*Mayor: Ronald G. Oettel, Jr. (R)
*Borough Manager: Sue Ann Barry
*Borough Council
**Karen Weibel, President
**Todd Fulginiti
**Shane Weaver
**Doug Bomberger
**Ruth McKennon
**James Wynkoop
Lititz, along with Elizabeth and Warwick townships and part of Penn Township, is located in the [[Warwick School District]].
*Schools
**Warwick High School
**Warwick Middle School
**Lititz Elementary School (at former site of K-12 Lititz High School; serves the central and northern part of Lititz borough and western Warwick township out to Penn township and its border with Manheim Central School District)
**John Beck Elementary School (founded independently of the district and incorporated; serves the northern part of Warwick township and Elizabeth township)
**John R. Bonfield Elementary School (serves the eastern part of the school district, including the outskirts of Lititz borough and Warwick township)
**Kissel Hill Elementary School (serves the southern part of Lititz borough and Warwick township south to the Manheim Township line)

==Demographics==
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 9,029 people, 3,732 households, and 2,407 families residing in the borough. The [[population density]] was {{convert|3884.0|/sqmi|/km2|abbr=on}}. There were 3,827 housing units at an average density of  1,646.2 per square mile (636.9/km²). The racial makeup of the borough was 97.23% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 0.44% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.09% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.87% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.03% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 0.50% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 0.83% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 1.52% of the population.

There were 3,732 households out of which 29.1% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 52.9% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 8.5% had a female householder with no husband present, and 35.5% were non-families. 31.0% of all households were made up of individuals and 15.8% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.32 and the average family size was 2.91.

In the borough the population was spread out with 23.0% under the age of 18, 6.1% from 18 to 24, 28.8% from 25 to 44, 20.9% from 45 to 64, and 21.2% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 40 years. For every 100 females there were 86.4 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 82.2 males.

The median income for a household in the borough was $40,417, and the median income for a family was $52,028. Males had a median income of $36,126 versus $25,997 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the borough was $20,601. About 2.6% of families and 4.1% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 3.9% of those under age 18 and 8.7% of those age 65 or over.

==Recent controversies==
===Water pollution===
Lititz has been criticized for its alleged poor ground water quality. The water in Lititz Springs Park tested at 19.1 for [[Nitrates]] on August 8, 2007 in a test paid for by the ''[[Lancaster Intelligencer Journal]]''.&lt;ref name=lol333323&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/local/4/208692 Lititz Springs Park water found high in nitrates]&lt;/ref&gt; Lititz' water quality was also criticized in February 2008 after [[Listerine]] was discharged into the aquifer by the nearby [[Johnson &amp; Johnson]] chemical plant,&lt;ref name=lol3333&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/local/4/216517 Listerine tainted Lititz water]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lol23443&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/local/4/215134 'Minty' Lititz water studied  – Johnson &amp; Johnson plant eyed by DEP]&lt;/ref&gt; and residents complained about a &quot;minty&quot; taste. Johnson and Johnson initially denied any responsibility, but the problem was later identified as the result of a leaky pipe on the company's property. In 2008, the ''Intelligencer Journal'' reported that the nonprofit group League of Humane Voters created a website &quot;dedicated to the cause of monitoring issues surrounding the Lititz watershed.&quot;&lt;ref name=lol23&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/local/4/225771 Web site focuses on Lititz water: League of Humane Voters adopts cause]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lititzwater&gt;[http://lititzwater.org Lititzwater.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

Lititz Borough has a multi-million dollar water treatment plant that removes pollutants so that the water distributed to residents meets all Federal and State regulations.&lt;ref name=record&gt;[http://lititzrecord.com/pages/news/local/4/220707 Kline confirms Lititz water is safe to drink]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Borden family murders===
Lititz received national press coverage on 13 November 2005, after David G. Ludwig shot and killed Michael and Cathryn Borden. Ludwig fled the scene with their daughter, Kara Beth, and an [[Amber Alert]] was issued for her. 

Ludwig was arrested with Kara in Indiana, extradited to Lancaster County, and held on several charges including criminal homicide. He pleaded guilty to two counts of first degree murder, reckless endangerment, statutory sexual assault and firearms violations. Ludwig received two consecutive life sentences without the possibility of parole plus 9.5 to 19 years for the weapons charges. Ludwig lived within the borough of Lititz. The Bordens lived outside the borough in [[Warwick Township, Lancaster County, Pennsylvania|Warwick Township]].

Kara Borden did not return to Lititz following the shooting.

===Racist incident===
The town received national press coverage on 11 October 2007, after three white 16-year-old students allegedly yelled racial slurs and threw paper wads at minority students outside the 1,600-student Warwick High School. School officials vowed to discipline the three students with suspension or expulsion, tighten security, and ban Confederate flags on school property, and six of the students were charged with [[disorderly conduct]].&lt;ref name=racism1&gt;[http://local.lancasteronline.com/4/210712 Six at Warwick charged in wake of racial unrest in district]&lt;/ref&gt;

The superintendent said the incident was revealed only after a teacher overheard other students discussing it and alerted administrators.&lt;ref name=racism&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20071011/ap_on_re_us/high_school_racism_2;_ylt=Arp73lIb6wAejJnYeKv2vetsaMYA Racist incident roils Pa. high school]&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to &quot;[try] to rebound from a string of racially motivated incidents,&quot; the community will commemorate the 2009 [[Martin Luther King Jr. Day]] holiday with a call to unity. The community's churches, including the Lititz [[Moravian Church]], will make &quot;a clear statement against racism.&quot; The Moravian Church's associate pastor, Mark Breland, who is the first [[African American]] to hold that position in the church, will deliver the message. Most of Lititz's congregations don't have African Americans, and community leaders felt that &quot;part of learning to celebrate our diversity begins with hearing about the experience of diversity.&quot;&lt;ref name=lol343&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/local/4/232656 MLK Day service aims to help Lititz heal]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Warwick School District mascot===
The high school's current mascot depicts the profile of a [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]] warrior. Since 1999, some Lititz residents, teachers, and students have criticized the mascot both as a racist stereotype&lt;ref name=lol2343&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/lavoz/4/225648 Is Warwick's Indian logo racist?] – A group of Warwick students have won a partial victory in their quest to banish from the district the logo of an American Indian, which they say is racist.&lt;/ref&gt; and for misrepresenting a Native American religious symbol.&lt;ref name=ab&gt;Knowles, Laura. [http://athleticbusiness.com/articles/lexisnexis.aspx?lnarticleid=1177054666&amp;lntopicid=136030023 Warwick Controversy Over Mascot Renewed.] Intelligencer Journal, April 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign to eliminate the mascot resurfaced during the 2009–2010 school year, as the district renovated the high school's football field; current plans call for a spear design in the center of the field. In 2010, the district removed the warrior logo from the high school's sign, replacing it with a black-and-red seal featuring the letter ''W''.&lt;ref name=lol1243&gt;[http://articles.lancasteronline.com/local/4/257864 Long-debated Warwick logo slowly disappearing] – The mascot has been a source of dispute for years. District sports teams still use the image.&lt;/ref&gt; The warrior image has been used less frequently since 1999;&lt;ref name=ab /&gt; since then, residents have suggested to the school board that the mascot be changed to something representative of Lititz, such as &quot;Wilbur Buds,&quot;&lt;ref name=ab /&gt; a well-known product of the local [[Wilbur Chocolate Company]].

In 2010, the Warwick School Board passed a resolution that from now on, the Native American Head &amp; Spear logos will be used for athletics and the black-and-red seal featuring the letter 'W' will be used for academics. 

In January 2011, a member of a group in support of the Warrior logo/name presented a donation to the school board from a bumper sticker sale that was conducted the previous fall.

==Sister city==
A [[Sister City]] relationship between Lititz and [[Kunvald]] ([[Czech Republic]]) was established on June 11, 2006, during the celebration of the 250th anniversary naming of Lititz. The ceremony took place in Lititz Springs Park.

==Sites of interest==
===Public Services===
*[[Warwick High School (Lititz, Pennsylvania)|Warwick High School]] is located in Lititz, Pennsylvania and operates in the [[Warwick School District]]
*The Lititz Public Library is a member of the [[Library System of Lancaster County]].

===Museums and Historic Sites===
*Gravesite of [[John Sutter|John A. Sutter]]
*Heritage Map Museum
*Johannes Mueller House
*Kready's Country Store Museum
*Pa Quilt &amp; Textile Museum
*[[Sturgis Pretzel House|Julius Sturgis Pretzel Bakery]]
*[[Wilbur Chocolate Company|Wilbur Chocolate Factory]] &amp; Candy Americana Museum
*The [[John Beck's Boys Academy]]

==Notable people==
*[[John Fass]] (1890–1973); book designer, printer, photographer
*[[Bob Longenecker]] (1909–2002); Hollywood talent agent
*[[John Sutter|Johann Augustus Sutter]] (1803–1880); pioneer of California
*[[Louise Adeline Weitzel]] (1862–1934); poet

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:General sutter grave.jpg|General Sutter Grave in [[Lititz]] Moravian Cemetery
Image:Military Hospital Lititz 1778.jpg|Military Hospital Plaque in Lititz‎ ‎ 
Image:Mayor of Lititz Hon. Russell L. Pettyjohn.JPG|Former Mayor of Lititz Hon. Russell L. Pettyjohn
Image:Zinzendorf`s Waistcoat..jpg|Zinzendorf`s Waistcoat at Lititz Moravian Archive and Museum
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Lititz Watch Technicum]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*[[William Charles Anderson|Anderson, William Charles]] (1979) [http://books.google.com/books?id=_lrblWJOI4UC ''Home sweet home has wheels: or, Please don't tailgate the real estate'']
*Henry Louis Mencken, Raven Ioor McDavid (1963) [http://books.google.com/books?id=qsFZAAAAMAAJ ''The American language: an inquiry into the development of English in the United States, Volume 1'']
*[[Museums Association]] (2006) [http://books.google.com/books?id=3v0SAQAAMAAJ ''The Museums journal, Volume 106, Issues 1–6''], Indexes to papers read before the Museums Association, 1890–1909. Compiled by Charles Madeley.
*[[Rand McNally]] and Company (1978) [http://books.google.com/books?id=G6gIAQAAMAAJ ''Vacation &amp; travel guide'']
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=vNEWAQAAMAAJ ''Ward's quarterly, Volume 1''], 1965

==Further reading==
* ''Moravian Historical Society Transactions'', volume ii, (Bethlehem, Pa.)
* Mombert, ''An Authentic History of Lancaster County, Pa.'', (Lancaster, 1869)

==External links==
* [http://www.lititzpa.com Borough of Lititz]

{{Lancaster County, Pennsylvania}}

[[Category:Populated places established in 1756]]
[[Category:History of the America (North) Province of the Moravian Church]]
[[Category:Boroughs in Lancaster County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Place names of Czech origin in the United States]]

[[cs:Lititz]]
[[pdc:Lititz, Pennsilfaani]]
[[es:Lititz]]
[[ht:Lititz, Pennsilvani]]
[[nl:Lititz]]
[[pt:Lititz]]
[[vo:Lititz]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
