<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="85482" ns="0" title="Scientology and the Internet"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox civil conflict
 | conflict = Scientology-Internet conflict
 | date = July 1994 – ongoing
 | partof =
 | image = [[Image:Scientology versus the Internet.png|300px]]
 | caption = Clockwise from above: 1) [[Project Chanology|Protest]] by an Internet group calling itself '[[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]]' against the practices and tax status of the Church of Scientology, 2) Screenshot of error message when attempting to load www.scientology.org on January 25, 2008, 3) Monument-style sign in front of the Founding Church of Scientology in Washington DC.
 | place = Internet, courts of law, worldwide protests
 | status = ongoing
 | methods = [[litigation]], [[spam (electronic)|spam]], [[street protest]]s, [[prank call]]s, [[black fax]]es, [[denial of service]] attacks
 | side1 = 
[[alt.religion.scientology]]
[[File:Anonymous Flag.svg|22px]] [[Project Chanology]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Operation Clambake]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[File:Wise Beard Man.jpg|22px]] [[Mark Bunker|XenuTV]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Image:Wikileaks logo.svg|20px]] [[Wikileaks]]
 | side2 = [[File:Scientology Symbol Logo.png|22px]][[Church of Scientology]]
 | leadfigures1 =
[[Andreas Heldal-Lund]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[File:Wise Beard Man.jpg|22px]] [[Mark Bunker]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Image:Wikileaks logo.svg|20px]] [[Julian Assange]] 
 | leadfigures2 =
[[David Miscavige]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Tom Cruise]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Tommy Davis (Scientology)|Tommy Davis]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Moxon &amp; Kobrin]]
 | howmany1 = unknown
 | howmany2 = ~500,000 members&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adherents.com/Religions_By_Adherents.html |title=Major Religions of the World Ranked by Number of Adherents |publisher=Adherents.com |accessdate=2010-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

[[Image:Anonymous Scientology 4a by David Shankbone.JPG|thumb|A member of the Internet group [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]] which has held protests in many countries against the CoS every month since January, 2008.]]

&quot;'''Scientology versus the Internet'''&quot; refers to a number of disputes relating to the [[Church of Scientology]]'s efforts to suppress material critical of [[Scientology]] on the [[Internet]] through the use of lawsuits and legal threats.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/01/25/ddos_scientology_controversy/ Critics split over DDoS attacks on Scientology] [[The Register]], 25 Januari 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://ibls.com/cs/blogs/internet_law/archive/2008/01/30/hackers-disable-scientology-website-declare-war.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadiancontent.net/commtr/internet-group-launches-war-scientology-following-youtube-video_874.html Internet group launches War on Scientology, following YouTube video] Canadian Content, 23 Januari 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In late 1994, the Church of Scientology began using various legal tactics to stop distribution of unpublished documents written by [[L. Ron Hubbard]]. The Church of Scientology is often accused of [[barratry]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/How_the_Scientology_Organization_uses_and_exploits_the_United_States%27_legal_system_for_its_own_ends
|last=Berry
|first=Graham E.
|title=How the Scientology Organization uses and exploits the United States' legal system for its own ends
|quote=The Pattinson vs. Scientology case had to be dismissed when Scientology engaged in barratry...
|accessdate=January 7, 2011
|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,972865-9,00.html
|title=The Thriving Cult of Greed and Power
|last=Behar
|first=Richard
|newspaper=Time
|date=May 6, 1991
|accessdate=January 7, 2011
|quote=Hubbard warned his followers in writing to 'beware of attorneys who tell you not to sue... the purpose of the suit is to harass and discourage rather than to win.'
|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
|url=http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-06-24/news/Scientologys-Crushing-Defeat/full
|title=Scientology's Crushing Defeat
|last=Ortega
|first=Tony
|newspaper=The Village Voice
|date=June 24, 2008
|accessdate=January 7, 2011
|quote=The federal court threw out the lawsuit (dubbed Wollersheim 2), calling it frivolous and 'bordering on malicious.'
|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; through the filing of [[SLAPP]] suits. The official church response is that its litigious nature is solely to protect its [[copyright]]ed works and the [[trade secret|unpublished status]] of certain documents.

Various critics of the Church of Scientology argue that the church is a [[confidence trick|scam]] and that these secretive writings are proof, or that the documents contain evidence that the [[Medical claims in Scientology doctrine|Church of Scientology's medical practices]] are [[law|illegal]] and [[fraudulent]].&lt;ref&gt;See for instance Jacobsen, Jeff. [http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~dst/NOTs/medical/jacobsen-medical.txt &quot;Medical claims within Scientology's secret teachings&quot;], 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Connor, Mike. [http://groups.google.com/group/alt.religion.scientology/msg/63a67a019d7e0cb4 &quot;How Scientology claims to cure physical illness&quot;], 2003&lt;/ref&gt; Scientology has been convicted of fraud in the courts of several nations, although not those of the United States. Critics have said that the Church of Scientology is [[Copyright misuse|abusing copyright law]] by launching lawsuits against outspoken critics of the organization.&lt;ref&gt;For instance, see Hausherr, Tilman. [http://www.xenu.net/archive/events/9805henson-case/nots34_anal.html &quot;NOTS34: criminality successfully protected by copyright law&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== alt.religion.scientology ==
The [[newsgroup]] ''[[alt.religion.scientology]]'' was created in 1991 by [[Scott Goehring]], partly as a joke, partly for the purpose of informing the public about Scientology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net.Wars&quot;/&gt; Debate over the pros and cons of Scientology waxed and waned on the newsgroup through the first three years of its existence, and [[Flaming (Internet)|flame wars]] were common, as they were on most other newsgroups.

The online battle is generally seen to have begun with the arrival of Dennis Erlich to ''alt.religion.scientology'' in late July, 1994. A former high-ranking official in the organization who had been personally affiliated with L. Ron Hubbard, Erlich's presence on the newsgroup caused a number of regular participants there to sit up and take notice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net.Wars&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--p.4--&gt;&lt;!--p.6--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alt.scientology.war&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/3.12/alt.scientology.war.html
|title = alt.scientology.war
|accessdate = 2007-07-19
|last = Grossman
|first = Wendy M.
|authorlink = Wendy M. Grossman
|year = 2005
|month = December
|format = 3.12
|publisher = [[Wired magazine]]
|pages = 3
|quote = His critical posts, with quotations from the church literature, turned alt.religion.scientology from debating club to battlefield.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Xenu revelation==
On December 24, 1994, the first of a large number of anonymous messages was posted to [[alt.religion.scientology]], containing the text of the [[Scientology beliefs and practices#Confidential materials and reincarnation|&quot;secret&quot; writings of Scientology]] known as the ''[[Operating Thetan|OT Levels]]'' (OT stands for &quot;Operating Thetan&quot;). Included among these postings was [[Xenu|OT III]] (''Operating Thetan Level Three''), which gave L. Ron Hubbard's description of the &quot;[[Xenu]] story&quot;.  Although the Xenu story was published in the Robert Kaufman book ''[[Inside Scientology: How I Joined Scientology and Became Superhuman]]'' in 1972, the ''[[Philadelphia Inquirer]]'' in 1977, and several times in the 1980s in the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'';&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.google.com/group/alt.religion.scientology/msg/d24819df480c74bb?hl=en&amp;dmode=source The Un-Funny Truth about ARS] alt.religion.scientology, 3 September 2010&lt;/ref&gt; this action brought on the actions of lawyers representing Scientology, who contacted various newsgroup participants and posted warnings demanding that the unauthorized distribution of the OT writings cease. The lawyers described the documents as &quot;copyrighted, [[trademark]]ed, unpublished trade secrets&quot;, and the distribution of the materials as a violation of [[copyright law]] and [[trademark law]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Alan | last = Prendergast | title = Hunting rabbits, serving spam: The net under siege | url = http://www.westword.com/1995-10-04/news/hunting-rabbits-serving-spam-the-net-under-siege/full | work = [[Westword|Denver Westword]] | publisher = [[Village Voice Media]] | date = 1995-10-04 | accessdate = 2008-03-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The first postings of the ''OT'' documents were done through an [[anonymous remailer]], and the identity of the person who made them available on the newsgroup was never discovered.  However, Dennis Erlich posted replies to these messages on the newsgroup, and his replies contained the entire text of the original messages (including the disputed materials).  Scientology's lawyers therefore approached him, declaring that Erlich had re-published the copyrighted works in his newsgroup messages.  Erlich's reply to this was to deny their requests to remove his postings from the newsgroup.

== Attempt to remove ''alt.religion.scientology'' ==
On January 11, 1995, Scientology lawyer [[Helena Kobrin]] attempted to shut down the [[Usenet]] [[newsgroup|discussion group]] ''alt.religion.scientology'' by sending a control message instructing Usenet servers to delete the group on the grounds that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;(1) It was started with a forged message; (2) not discussed on [[alt.config]]; (3) it has the name &quot;scientology&quot; in its title which is a trademark and is misleading, as a.r.s. is mainly used for flamers to attack the Scientology religion; (4) it has been and continues to be heavily abused with copyright and trade secret violations and serves no purpose other than condoning these illegal practices.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net.Wars&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Grossman | first = Wendy | title = [[Net.Wars]] | url = http://www.nyupress.org/netwars/ | accessdate = 2006-06-11 | publisher = New York University Press | location = New York | isbn = 0-8147-3103-1 | pages = 77–78 | chapter = Copyright Terrorists | chapterurl = http://www.nyupress.org/netwars/textonly/pages/chapter06/ch06_.html | year = 1997 | month = October}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.xs4all.nl/~kspaink/cos/rnewman/usenet/rmgroup&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In practice, this [[rmgroup message]] had little effect,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xs4all.nl/~kspaink/cos/rnewman/usenet/rmgroup.html]&lt;/ref&gt; since most Usenet servers are configured to disregard such messages when applied to groups that receive substantial traffic, and [[newgroup message]]s were quickly issued for those servers that did not do so. However, the issuance of the message led to a great deal of public criticism of Scientology by [[free-speech]] advocates.

==Raids and lawsuits==

Shortly after the initial legal announcements and ''rmgroup'' attempt, representatives of Scientology followed through with a series of [[lawsuit]]s against various participants on the newsgroup, including Dennis Erlich in [[Religious Technology Center v. Netcom]]. The first raid took place on February 13, 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.thecia.net/users/rnewman/scientology/erlich/home.html The Church of Scientology vs. Dennis Erlich, Tom Klemesrud &amp; Netcom&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Accompanied by Scientology lawyers, federal marshals made several raids on the homes of individuals who were accused of posting Scientology's copyrighted materials to the newsgroup. Raids took place against [[Arnaldo Lerma]] ([[Virginia]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;gospeloftheweb&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Nick | last = Ryan | title = The gospel of the web | url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2000/mar/23/religion.internet | work = Technology | publisher = [[The Guardian]] | date = 2000-03-23 | accessdate = 2007-10-12 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lawrence A. Wollersheim|Lawrence Wollersheim]] and Robert Penny of [[Fight Against Coercive Tactics Network|FACTNet]] ([[Colorado]]), and Dennis Erlich ([[California]]). Internationally, raids took place against [[Karin Spaink]] (The Netherlands) and [[Zenon Panoussis]] (Sweden). In addition to filing lawsuits against individuals, Scientology also sued [[The Washington Post]] for reprinting one paragraph of the OT writings in a newspaper article, as well as several [[Internet service provider]]s, including [[Netcom (USA)|Netcom]], [[Tom Klemesrud]], and [[XS4ALL]]. It also regularly demanded the deletion of material from the [[Deja News]] archive.

Participants in ''alt.religion.scientology'' began using quotes from OT III in particular to publicize the online battle over the secret documents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.xenu.net/archive/leaflet/ | title = The XENU Leaflet | publisher = Operation Clambake | format = download in various formats | author = [[Roland Rashleigh-Berry]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The story of [[Xenu]] was subsequently quoted in many publications, including news reports on [[CNN]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.cnn.com/US/9508/scientology/ | title = Church of Scientology protects secrets on the Internet |date=August 26, 1995 | publisher = [[CNN]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[60 Minutes]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lesley Stahl]]. ''[[60 Minutes]]'', (December 28, 1997) &quot;The Cult Awareness Network&quot;. [[CBS News]].&lt;/ref&gt; It became the most famous reference to the OT levels, to the point where many Internet users who were not intimately familiar with Scientology had heard the story of Xenu, and immediately associated the name with Scientology. The initial strikes against Scientology's critics settled down into a series of legal battles that raged through the courts. The [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]] provided legal assistance to defendant [[Tom Klemesrud]] and his attorney Richard Horning helped find Dennis Erlich Pro Bono defense.  Daily reports of the latest happenings were posted to ''alt.religion.scientology.''  The newsgroup's popularity exploded. As the months and years wore on and the lawsuits continued without end, however, a number of participants in the newsgroup grew silent and moved on.

In the wake of the Scientology actions, the [[Penet remailer]], which had been the most popular [[anonymous remailer]] in the world until the Scientology &quot;war&quot; took place, was shut down.  [[Johan Helsingius]], operator of the remailer, stated that the legal protections afforded him in his country (Finland) were too thin to protect the anonymity of his users and he decided to close down the remailer as a result.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xs4all.nl/~kspaink/cos/rnewman/anon/penet.html The Church of Scientology vs. anon.penet.fi]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=stalking&gt;{{cite web | first = Alan | last = Prendergast | title = Stalking the Net | url = http://www.westword.com/1995-10-04/news/stalking-the-net/full | work = [[Westword|Denver Westword News]] | publisher = [[Village Voice Media]] | date = 1995-10-04 | accessdate = 2008-01-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Sabine | last = Helmers | title = A Brief History of anon.penet.fi | url = http://www.december.com/cmc/mag/1997/sep/helmers.html | work =  | publisher = CMC Magazine | date = 1997-09-01 | accessdate = 2008-01-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Scientology's online campaign ==
After failing to remove the newsgroup, Scientologists adopted a strategy of newsgroup spam and intimidation.&lt;ref name=&quot;flames&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Colman | last = Jones | title = Freedom Flames Out on the 'Net - Who launched the largest-ever sabotage of the Internet?| url = http://www.nowtoronto.com/issues/15/44/News/feature.html | publisher = [[NOW (magazine)|NOW Magazine]] | date = 1996-07-04 | accessdate = 2006-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scientologists hired third parties to regularly flood the newsgroup with pro-scientology messages, vague anti-scientology messages, irrelevant comments, and accusations that other posters are secret Scientologists intent on tracking and punishing posters. This makes the newsgroup virtually unreadable via online readers such as [http://groups.google.com/group/alt.religion.scientology/ Google Groups], although more specialized newsreading software that can filter out all messages by specific &quot;high noise&quot; posters make the newsgroup more usable.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

While legal battles were being fought in the courts, an equally intense and aggressive campaign was waged online. The newsgroup ''alt.religion.scientology'' found itself at the center of an electronic maelstrom of information and disinformation, as the newsgroup itself was attacked both literally and figuratively. Tens of thousands of junk messages were [[spamming|spammed]] onto the newsgroup, rendering it nearly unreadable at times when the message &quot;floods&quot; were at their peaks.&lt;ref name=&quot;flames&quot;/&gt; Over one million [[sporgery]] articles were injected into the newsgroup by Scientology management and staff; former Scientology staff member [[Tory Christman]] has spoken at length about her involvement in these attacks. Lawyers representing Scientology made public appeals to Internet service providers to remove the newsgroup completely from their news servers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document | url=http://www.discord.org/~lippard/skeptic/03.3.jl-jj-scientology.html | title=Scientology v. the Internet: Free Speech &amp; Copyright Infringement on the Information Super-Highway | work=[[Skeptic (U.S. magazine)|''Skeptic'']] | publisher=[[The Skeptics Society]] | volume=3 | issue=3 | year=1995 | pages=35–41 | author=Lippard, Jim | authorlink=Jim Lippard | author2=Jacobsen, Jeff | accessdate=August 9, 2009 | postscript=. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, anonymous participants in the newsgroup kept up a steady stream of [[flame wars]] and off-topic arguments. Participants on the newsgroup accused Scientology of orchestrating these electronic attacks, though the organization consistently denied any wrongdoing.

In the early days of the [[World Wide Web]], Scientology attempted a similar strategy to make finding websites critical of the organization more difficult. Scientology employed Web designers to write thousands of Web pages for their site, thus flooding early [[search engine]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Web of their own&quot;/&gt;  This problem was solved by the innovation of clustering responses from the same [[Web server]], showing no more than the top two results from any one site (e.g. [[Google]]).

Since the inception of the Internet, Scientology has made a policy of using copyright infringement laws to prosecute various Scientology critics posting exposing information on the Web. The Church uses legal pressure combined with [[blackmail]] and [[character assassination]] to attempt to win many court cases in which it involves itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;erlichfree&quot;&gt;Freedom Magazine, Vol 27, Issue 4: [http://web.archive.org/web/19990116234531/http://www.theta.com/goodman/crime.htm ''A Crime By Any Other Name'']. See &quot;Dennis Erlich: Copyright Terrorist&quot;. (Archived January 16th, 1999.)&lt;/ref&gt;  On the other side of the battle, many Web-page developers have linked the words &quot;Dianetics&quot; and &quot;Scientology&quot; to [[Operation Clambake]]. This resulted in the anti-Scientology site having the highest Google index on the term for a while, which in turn resulted in Scientology persuading Google to remove links to the site&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Matt Loney | coauthors = Evan Hansen | title = Google pulls anti-Scientology links | url = http://news.com.com/2100-1023-865936.html | publisher = [[CNet]] | date = 2002-03-21 | accessdate = 2006-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; until international outcry led to the links being restored. This might be considered an early example of a [[Google bomb]], and has led to questions about the power and obligations of Internet search providers.

In the 1990s Scientology was distributing a special software package for its members to protect them from &quot;unapproved&quot; material about the church. The software is designed to completely block out the newsgroup ''[[alt.religion.scientology]]'', various anti-Scientology web sites, and all references to various critics of Scientology. This software package was derided by critics, who accused the organization of censorship and called the program &quot;[[Scieno Sitter]]&quot;, after the [[content-control software]] net-filter program Cyber Sitter. Since no updates have been reported since 1998 (and the original filter program only worked with [[Windows 95]]) the package is unlikely to be in use with recent operating systems and browsers due to [[software rot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Web of their own&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Janelle |last=Brown |url=http://archive.salon.com/21st/feature/1998/07/15feature.html |title=A Web of their own |work=Salon |publisher=Salon.com |date=1998-07-15 |accessdate=2006-06-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2006, Scientology lawyers sent cease-and-desist letters to [[Max Goldberg]], founder of the website [[YTMND]], asking him to take down all sites that either talked about or mocked Scientology, which had recently become a fad on the site following [[Trapped in the Closet (South Park episode)|a popular ''South Park'' episode]]. Goldberg responded by saying that the &quot;claims are completely groundless and I'm not removing anything,&quot; adding to the members of the site, &quot;it should only be a matter of time before we're sued out of existence.&quot; In response, YTMNDers created yet more sites about Scientology, and these were highlighted on the main page. They also campaigned to [[Google bomb]] &quot;The Unfunny Truth About Scientology&quot; site. No legal action was taken against YTMND or Goldberg.

In August 2007, [[MSNBC]] quoted [[Associated Press]] in an article on the [[Wikipedia Scanner]], that computers owned by the Church of Scientology have been removing criticism in the Scientology entry on Wikipedia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20284811/ New online tool traces Wikipedia edits: PCs in Scientology officialdom removed criticism in church's entry], ''[[MSNBC]]'', [[Associated Press]], [[Brian Bergstein]], August 15, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  A [[Fox News]] article also reported that Church of Scientology computers had been used to delete references of the relationship between Scientology and the [[Cult Awareness Network]], in the article on the Cult Awareness Network on Wikipedia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,293389,00.html Wal-Mart, CIA, ExxonMobil Changed Wikipedia Entries], August 16, 2007, [[Fox News]], Rhys Blakely, Fox News Network, LLC.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2009, the Wikipedia Arbitration Committee decided to restrict access to its site from Church of Scientology IP addresses, to prevent self-serving edits by Scientologists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huff&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/05/29/wikipedia-bans-scientolog_n_208967.html|last=Shea|first=Danny|title=Wikipedia Bans Scientology From Site|date=2009-05-29|work=The Huffington Post|accessdate=2009-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Metz&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2009/05/29/wikipedia_bans_scientology/|title=Wikipedia bans Church of Scientology|last=Metz|first=Cade|date=2009-05-29|work=The Register|accessdate=2009-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; A &quot;host of anti-Scientologist editors&quot; were topic-banned as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huff&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Metz&quot; /&gt; The committee concluded that both sides had &quot;gamed policy&quot; and resorted to &quot;battlefield tactics&quot;, with articles on living persons being the &quot;worst casualties&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Huff&quot; /&gt;

==Project Chanology==
{{Wikinews|Wikinews international report: &quot;Anonymous&quot; holds anti-Scientology protests worldwide}}
{{Main|Project Chanology}}

In early 2008, another protest against the Church of Scientology was organised by the Internet-based [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]], which originally consisted of users of the English speaking [[imageboard]] [[4chan]] and forums such as Somethingawful.com, and several [[Internet Relay Chat]] channels, among other Internet-based communities claiming affiliation with Anonymous.

On January 14, 2008, a video produced by the [[Church of Scientology]] featuring an interview with [[Tom Cruise]] was leaked to the Internet and uploaded to [[YouTube]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CookMar17&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=John Cook | title=Scientology - Cult Friction | url=http://radaronline.com/from-the-magazine/2008/03/scientology_anonymous_protests_tom_cruise_01.php | work=[http://radaronline.com/ Radar Online] | publisher=[[Radar (magazine)|Radar Magazine]] | date=March 17, 2008 | accessdate=2008-03-18 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080323063402/http://www.radaronline.com/from-the-magazine/2008/03/scientology_anonymous_protests_tom_cruise_01.php &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WarneJan24&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Warne | first =Dan | title =Anonymous threatens to &quot;dismantle&quot; Church of Scientology via internet | work =[[APC Magazine]] | publisher =[[National Nine News]] | date =January 24, 2008 | url =http://www.apcmag.com/7905/anonymous_threatens_to_dismantle_church_of_scientology_via_internet | accessdate =2008-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KNBCJan24&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=KNBC Staff  | title =Hacker Group Declares War On Scientology: Group Upset Over Church's Handling Of Tom Cruise Video  | work =[[KNBC]] | publisher =  | date =January 24, 2008  | url =http://www.knbc.com/news/15132759/detail.html  | accessdate = 2008-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Church of Scientology issued a copyright violation claim against YouTube requesting the removal of the video.&lt;ref name=&quot;vamosi anonymous hackers&quot;&gt;{{cite news   | last =Vamosi  | first =Robert  | coauthors =  | title =Anonymous hackers take on the Church of Scientology  | work =[[CNET News]]  | pages =  | language =  | publisher =CNET Networks, Inc.   | date =January 24, 2008  | url =http://www.news.com/8301-10789_3-9857666-57.html  | accessdate = 2008-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In response to this, Anonymous formulated [[Project Chanology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;George-Cosh&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =George-Cosh | first =David | coauthors = | title =Online group declares war on Scientology | work =[[National Post]] | pages = | language = | publisher =[[CanWest Global Communications|Canwest Publishing Inc.]] | date =January 25, 2008  | url =http://www.nationalpost.com/news/canada/story.html?id=261308  | accessdate = 2008-01-25 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080128145858/http://www.nationalpost.com/news/canada/story.html?id=261308 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;singel&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Singel | first =Ryan | coauthors = | title =War Breaks Out Between Hackers and Scientology &amp;ndash; There Can Be Only One | work =[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] | pages = | language = | publisher =[[Condé Nast Publications|CondéNet, Inc.]] | date =January 23, 2008 | url =http://blog.wired.com/27bstroke6/2008/01/anonymous-attac.html | accessdate = 2008-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;feran&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Feran | first =Tom | coauthors = | title =Where to find the Tom Cruise Scientology videos online, if they're still posted | work =[[The Plain Dealer]] | pages = | language = | publisher =[[Advance Publications|Newhouse Newspapers]] | date =January 24, 2008 | url =http://www.cleveland.com/entertainment/plaindealer/index.ssf?/base/entertainment-0/120116724530070.xml&amp;coll=2  | accessdate = 2008-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;chanenterprises&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Chan Enterprises  | first =  | coauthors =  | title =Internet Group Declares &quot;War on Scientology&quot;: Anonymous are fighting the Church of Scientology and the Religious Technology Center | work =Press Release  | pages =  | language =  | publisher =PRLog.Org  | date =January 21, 2008  | url =http://www.prlog.org/10046797-internet-group-anonymous-declares-war-on-scientology.pdf |format=PDF| accessdate =2008-01-25  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Calling the action by the Church of Scientology a form of [[Internet censorship]], members of Project Chanology organized a series of [[denial-of-service attack]]s against Scientology websites, [[prank calls]], and [[black fax]]es to Scientology centers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Matthew A. Schroettnig, Stefanie Herrington, Lauren E. Trent |title=Anonymous Versus Scientology: Cyber Criminals or Vigilante Justice?  |date=2008-02-06 |url=http://www.thelegality.com/archives/22 | work =The Legality |accessdate = 2008-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Message to Scientology.ogv|thumb|left|&quot;Message to Scientology&quot;, January 21, 2008]]
On January 21, 2008, Anonymous announced its goals and intentions via a video posted to YouTube entitled &quot;Message to Scientology&quot;, and a [[press release]] declaring a &quot;War on Scientology&quot; against both the Church of Scientology and the [[Religious Technology Center]].&lt;ref name=&quot;chanenterprises&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Thomas  | first =Nicki  | coauthors =  | title =Scientology and the internet: Internet hackers attack the church  | work =[[Edmonton Sun]]  | pages =  | language =  | publisher =Sun Media  | date =January 25, 2008  | url =http://www.edmontonsun.com/News/Edmonton/2008/01/25/4794425.html  | accessdate = 2008-01-25 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dodd&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Dodd | first =Gareth (Editor) | coauthors =Agencies | title =Anonymous hackers vow to &quot;dismantle&quot; Scientology | work =[[Xinhua News Agency]] | pages = | language = | publisher =  | date =January 25, 2008  | url =http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2008-01/25/content_7495986.htm  | accessdate = 2008-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In the press release, the group states that the attacks against the Church of Scientology will continue in order to protect the right to [[freedom of speech]], and end what they believe to be the financial exploitation of church members.&lt;ref name=&quot;brandon&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Brandon| first =Mikhail | coauthors =| title =Scientology in the Crosshairs| work =[[The Emory Wheel]] | pages = | language = | publisher =[[Emory University]] | date =January 28, 2008 | url =http://www.emorywheel.com/detail.php?n=24945 | accessdate =2008-01-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
A new video &quot;Call to Action&quot; appeared on YouTube on January 28, 2008, calling for protests outside Church of Scientology centers on February 10, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;feran the group anonymous&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Feran | first =Tom | coauthors = | title =The group Anonymous calls for protests outside Scientology centers - New on the Net | work =[[The Plain Dealer]] | pages = | language = | publisher =[[Advance Publications|Newhouse Newspapers]] | date =January 31, 2008 | url =http://www.cleveland.com/entertainment/plaindealer/index.ssf?/base/entertainment-0/1201771820310820.xml&amp;coll=2 | accessdate = 2008-02-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vamosi anonymous names&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Vamosi  | first =Robert  | coauthors =  | title =Anonymous names February 10 as its day of action against Scientology  | work =[[CNET News]]  | pages =  | language =  | publisher =CNET Networks, Inc.  | date =January 28, 2008  | url =http://www.news.com/8301-10789_3-9859513-57.html  | accessdate = 2008-01-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 2, 2008, 150 people gathered outside of a Church of Scientology center in [[Orlando, Florida]] to protest the organization's practices.&lt;ref name=&quot;braiker&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Braiker  | first =Brian   | coauthors =  | title =The Passion of ‘Anonymous’: A shadowy, loose-knit consortium of activists and hackers called 'Anonymous' is just the latest thorn in Scientology's side  | work =[[Newsweek]]  | pages =Technology: Newsweek Web Exclusive  | language =  | publisher =Newsweek, Inc.  | date =February 8, 2008  | url =http://www.newsweek.com/id/109410  | accessdate =2008-02-09  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;barkham&quot;&gt;{{cite news   | last = Barkham  | first = Patrick   | coauthors =   | title = Hackers declare war on Scientologists amid claims of heavy-handed Cruise control  | work = [[The Guardian]]  | pages =   | language =   | publisher = Guardian News and Media Limited  | date = February 4, 2008  | url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2008/feb/04/news  | accessdate = 2008-02-03 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wkmg&quot;&gt;{{cite news   | last =Staff  | first =  | coauthors =  | title =Group Lines Road To Protest Church Of Scientology  | work =[[WKMG-TV]]  | pages =  | language =  | publisher =Internet Broadcasting Systems and Local6.com  | date =February 3, 2008  | url =http://www.local6.com/news/15205679/detail.html  | accessdate =2008-02-03  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;eckinger&quot;&gt;{{cite news   | last =Eckinger  | first =Helen  | coauthors =Gabrielle Finley, Katherine Norris  | title =Anti-Scientology group has protest rally  | work =[[Orlando Sentinel]]  | pages =  | language =  | publisher =  | date = February 3, 2008  | url =http://www.orlandosentinel.com/news/local/orange/orl-cfbriefs03_508feb03,0,1439702.story  | accessdate = 2008-02-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Small protests were also held in [[Santa Barbara, California]],&lt;ref name=&quot;standifer&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last = Standifer  | first = Tom  | title = Masked Demonstrators Protest Against Church of Scientology  | work = [[Daily Nexus]]  | pages = Issue 69, Volume 88  | publisher = [[University of California, Santa Barbara]]  | date = February 4, 2008  | url = http://www.dailynexus.com/article.php?a=15686  | accessdate = 2008-02-04 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Manchester|Manchester, England]].&lt;ref name=&quot;barkham&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | last = Eber  | first = Hailey  | title = Anti-Scientologists Warm Up for February 10 | work = [[Radar (magazine)|Radar Online]]  | publisher = Radar Magazine  | date = February 4, 2008  | url = http://www.radaronline.com/exclusives/2008/02/antiscientologists-warming-up-for-february-10.php  | accessdate = 2008-02-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
On February 10, 2008, about 7,000 people [[Template:Project Chanology protests, February 10, 2008‎|protested in more than 93 cities worldwide]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MoncadaFeb12&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Carlos Moncada |title=Organizers Tout Scientology Protest, Plan Another |url=http://suncoastpinellas.tbo.com/content/2008/feb/12/organizers-tout-scientology-protest-plan-another/ |work= |publisher=[[The Tampa Tribune|TBO.com]] |date=2008-02-12 |accessdate=2008-02-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RamadgeFeb14&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | author=Andrew Ramadge | title=Scientology protest surge crashes websites | url=http://www.news.com.au/technology/story/0,25642,23212002-5014239,00.html | work=[[News.com.au]] | publisher=[[News Limited]] | date=2008-02-14 | accessdate=2008-02-14 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RamadgeMar17&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Andrew Ramadge | title=Second round of Anonymous v Scientology | url=http://www.news.com.au/technology/story/0,25642,23389091-5014239,00.html | work=[[News.com.au]] | publisher=[[News Limited]] | date=2008-03-17 | accessdate=2008-03-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Many protesters wore masks based on the character [[V (comics)|V]] from ''[[V for Vendetta]]'' (who in turn was influenced by [[Guy Fawkes]]), or otherwise disguised their identities, in part to protect themselves from reprisals from the Church of Scientology.&lt;ref name=&quot;StateNews&quot;&gt;{{cite news   | last =Harrison   | first =James (''[[The State News]]'') | coauthors =  | title =Scientology protestors take action around world  | pages =  | language =  | date =February 12, 2008  | url =http://www.statenews.com/index.php/blog/entertainment/2008/02/internet_group_ | accessdate = 2008-02-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ForresterFeb11&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2008/02/11/dozens_of_masked_protesters_blast_scientology_church/|title=Dozens of masked protesters blast Scientology church|first=John|last=Forrester|date=2008-02-11|accessdate=2008-02-15|publisher=''[[The Boston Globe]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Anonymous held a [[Template:Project Chanology protests, March 15, 2008‎|second wave of protests]] on March 15, 2008 in cities all over the world, including New York, Chicago, Los Angeles, London, Paris, Vancouver, Toronto, Berlin, and Dublin. Anonymous held its third protest against Scientology on April 12, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;shaundavies&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Davies | first =Shaun  | title =Scientology strikes back in information war | work =[[National Nine News]] | publisher =ninemsn | date =March 20, 2008 | url =http://news.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=409940  | accessdate = 2008-03-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RamadgeMar20&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Andrew Ramadge | title=Scientology site gets a facelift after protests | url=http://www.news.com.au/technology/story/0,25642,23407107-5014239,00.html | work=[[News.com.au]] | publisher=[[News Limited]] | date=2008-03-20 | accessdate=2008-03-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Named &quot;Operation Reconnect&quot;, it aimed to increase awareness of the Church of Scientology's [[Disconnection|disconnection policy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CookMar17&quot; /&gt;  A fourth protest occurred on May 10, 2008 and a fifth (Operation Sea Arrrgh) occurred on June 14, 2008.

==Wikileaks==
In March 2008, [[Wikileaks]] published a 612-page Scientology manual on the eight different [[Operating Thetan]] levels, considered secret by the Church of Scientology.&lt;ref name=Fox&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,368315,00.html | work=Fox News | title=Watchdog Web Site Draws Legal Threats from Scientologists, Mormons | date=2008-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three weeks later, Wikileaks received a warning from the Church of Scientology that the manual was copyrighted and that its publication infringed intellectual-property rights.&lt;ref name=Fox /&gt; Wikileaks refused to remove the material, and its operator released a statement saying that Scientology was a &quot;[[cult]]&quot; that &quot;aids and abets a general climate of Western media self-censorship.&quot;&lt;ref name=Fox /&gt; A Church of Scientology International spokeswoman, writing to FOXNews.com, said: &quot;I can only assume that religious bigotry and prejudice is driving their activity, as there is no altruistic value in posting our copyrighted scriptures, despite Wikileaks' statements to the contrary. Posting entire books and hundreds of pages of published works is not 'Sunshine Policy' but wholesale copyright infringement.&quot;&lt;ref name=Fox /&gt; [[Julian Assange]] replied: &quot;We thought it was a small issue, and our normal fare is government corruption and military secrets, so it seemed that this nutty religious organization was pretty inconsequential in terms of what we normally do. But after receiving these legal threats from them ... it was time for us to make a stand.&quot;&lt;ref name=Fox /&gt;

==Notable legal actions==
{{See also|Scientology and the legal system}}
A few of the court cases were decided in favor of Scientology, while most of the cases were settled out of court.  Many cases have been criticized as examples of malicious litigation and its members and lawyers have been indicted and fined for such actions.  Noteworthy incidents in the later years of the online war included:

*Scientology's lawsuit against ex-member [[Arnaldo Lerma]], his provider Digital Gateway, and ''The Washington Post.'' Lerma posted the [[Fishman Affidavit]] that contained 61 pages including the story of [[Xenu]], a story simultaneously denied and claimed as a trade secret by the Church of Scientology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net.Wars&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--p.9--&gt;

*Zenon Panoussis, a resident of Sweden, was also sued for posting Scientology's copyrighted materials to the Internet. In his defense, he used a provision of the [[Constitution of Sweden]] that guarantees access to public documents. Panoussis turned over a copy of the NOTs documents to the office of the Swedish Parliament and, by law, copies of all documents (with few exceptions) received by authorities are available for anyone from the public to see, at any time he or she wishes. This, known as the Principle of Public Access (''Offentlighetsprincipen''), is considered a basic civil right in Sweden. The case, however, was decided against Panoussis. The results of his case sparked a legal firestorm in Sweden that debated the necessity of re-writing part of the Constitution.&lt;ref name=&quot;ShortTake&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://news.com.com/Short+Take+Scientologists+win+Net+court+case/2110-1023_3-215586.html |title = Short Take: Scientologists win Net court case |accessdate = 2007-08-10 |last = Macavinta |first = Courtney|date = 1998-09-15|work = [[CNET]]|publisher =}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ScientologistSettle&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://news.com.com/Scientologists+settle+legal+battle/2100-1023_3-223683.html?tag=item |title = Scientologists settle legal battle |accessdate = 2007-08-10 |last = Macavinta |first = Courtney|date = 1999-03-30|work = [[CNET]]|publisher =}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 1995 Scientology caused a raid on the servers of Dutch Internet provider [[XS4ALL]] and sued it and [[Karin Spaink]] for copyright violations arising from published excerpts from confidential materials. There followed a summary judgment in 1995, full proceedings in 1999, an appeal in 2003&lt;ref name=&quot;spainking&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://news.com.com/2100-1028_3-5072581.html |title = Scientology loss keeps hyperlinks legal |accessdate = 2007-08-10 |last = Hines |first = Matt |date = 2003-09-08 |work = [[CNET]] |publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LosesRegister&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.theregister.co.uk/2003/09/08/scientologists_loses_copyright_case/ |title = Scientologists loses copyright case |accessdate = 2007-08-10 |last = Libbenga |first = Jan |date = 2003-09-08 |publisher = [[The Register]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; which has been upheld by the Supreme Court of Netherlands in December 2005, all in favor of the provider and Karin Spaink.&lt;ref name=&quot;xs4allpr&quot;&gt;[http://www.religionnewsblog.com/13054/final-victory-xs4all-and-karin-spaink-win-scientology-battle Final Victory! XS4ALL and Karin Spaink Win Scientology Battle], Press Release, December 16, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

*Dennis Erlich and Scientology settled their lawsuits. Erlich withdrew from the online battle entirely, and all mention of him was removed from Church of Scientology material.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net.Wars&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--p.1,4,6-9--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;erlichfree&quot;/&gt;

*Activist [[Keith Henson]] was sued for posting a portion of Scientology's writings to the Internet. Henson defended himself in court without a lawyer, while at the same time he carried out protests and pickets against Scientology. The court found that Henson had committed copyright infringement, and the damage award against Henson was immense: $75,000, an amount which Scientology said was the largest damages ever awarded against an individual for copyright infringement. Henson's case became increasingly more complex and ongoing, with a misdemeanor conviction of interfering with religion in [[Riverside County, California]]. In his Internet writings, Henson said that he was forced to flee the United States and seek [[political asylum|asylum]] in Canada due to ongoing threats against him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Net.Wars&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.mercurynews.com/ci_6320693 |title = Scientology critic seeks pardon |accessdate = 2007-08-11|last = Zapler|first = Mike |date = 2007-07-07|work = [[San Jose Mercury News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--p.10--&gt;

*Scientology is one of the first organizations to make use of the [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]] (DMCA). In June 1999, Scientology used the controversial law to force [[AT&amp;T Worldnet]] to reveal the identity of a person who had been posting anonymously to ''alt.religion.scientology'' with the pseudonym of &quot;Safe&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;UnSafe&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url = http://news.com.com/2100-1023-226676.html |title = Scientology subpoenas Worldnet |accessdate = 2007-08-10|last = Goodin|first = Dan |date = 1999-06-03|work = [[CNET]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In March 2001, legal threats from Scientology lawyers forced [[Slashdot]] to remove text from one of its discussion boards, after an excerpt from [[Xenu|OT III]] was posted there. Slashdot noted this as the first time a comment had to be removed from its system due to copyright concerns, and retaliated by posting a list of links to anti-Scientology websites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://slashdot.org/yro/01/03/16/1256226.shtml |title = Scientologists Force Comment Off Slashdot |accessdate = 2007-09-05|date = 2001-03-16|work = [[Slashdot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*The organization also used the DMCA to force the [[Google]] search engine to erase its entries on the controversial anti-Scientology Web site ''[[Operation Clambake]]'' in March 2002, though the entry was reinstated after Google received a large number of complaints from Internet users. The publicity stemming from this incident led Google to begin submitting DMCA takedown notices it received to the [[Chilling Effects (group)|Chilling Effects]] archive, which archives legal threats of all sorts made against Internet users and Internet sites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/5997 Google Begins Making DMCA Takedowns Public&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Silence&quot;/&gt;

*In September 2002, lawyers for Scientology contacted [[Internet Archive]] (archive.org), the administrators of the [[Internet Archive#Wayback_Machine|Wayback Machine]] and asserted copyright claims on certain materials archived as historical contents of the [[Operation Clambake]] site. In response, the Wayback Machine administration removed the archive of the ''entire'' Clambake site, initially posting a false claim that the site's author had requested its removal. This claim has been removed but (as of January 2011) the site still returns a &quot;Blocked Site Error&quot; from the Wayback archive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Silence&quot;&gt;{{cite web | first = Lisa M.| last = Bowman| title = Net archive silences Scientology critic| url = http://www.news.com/2100-1023-959236.html| publisher = [[CNET]] | date = 2002-09-24| accessdate = 2007-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Internet|Scientology}}
*[[Andreas Heldal-Lund]]
*[[Chilling Effects (group)|Chilling Effects]]
*[[List of trademarks owned by the Church of Scientology and its affiliates]]
*[[Project Chanology]]
*[[Scieno Sitter]]
*[[Scientology and the legal system]]
*[[Scientology controversies]]
*[[Sporgery]]
*[[Streisand effect]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* [http://www.discord.org/~lippard/skeptic/03.3.jl-jj-scientology.html Scientology v. the Internet: Free Speech &amp; Copyright Infringement on the Information Super-Highway], ''Skeptic'' vol. 3, no. 3, 1995, pp.&amp;nbsp;35–41, [[Jim Lippard]] and Jeff Jacobsen.
* {{cite web | first = Wendy M. | last = Grossman | title = alt.scientology.war | url = http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/3.12/alt.scientology.war.html | work = Wired 3.12 | publisher = [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] | date = 1995-12-01 | accessdate = 2008-10-14 }}
* {{cite web | first = Jennifer | last = Bjorhus | title = Scientology Critics Claim Harassment For Using Internet | url = http://archives.seattletimes.nwsource.com/cgi-bin/texis.cgi/web/vortex/display?slug=2138183&amp;date=19950826 | work = [[Seattle Times]] | date = 1995-08-26 | accessdate = 2008-10-14 }}
{{Refend}}
*

==External links==
{{wikinewshas|news on this topic|
*[[n:Church of Scientology website being attacked by hackers|Church of Scientology website being attacked by hackers]]
*[[n:Tom Cruise Scientology promotional video leaked to the Internet|Tom Cruise Scientology promotional video leaked to the Internet]]
*[[n:Interview with Glen Stollery of ScienTOMogy.info|Interview with Glen Stollery of ScienTOMogy.info]]
*[[n:Tom Cruise parody site defiant in face of Scientology threats, demands its day in court|Tom Cruise parody site defiant in face of Scientology threats, demands its day in court]]
*[[n:Church of Scientology does not see humor in website dedicated to Tom Cruise|Church of Scientology does not see humor in website dedicated to Tom Cruise]]
}}
{{wikisource|Religious Technology Center vs. Netcom}}
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b6KM27TUsvM BBC video: ''Scientology v The Internet'' May 15, 1995]
*[http://www.eff.org/legal/cases/Scientology_cases/ EFF Electronic Frontier Foundation &quot;Legal Cases - Church of Scientology&quot; Archive]
*[http://machinist.salon.com/blog/2008/01/16/scientology/index.html Scientology Video]
*[http://www.whyweprotest.net/ Anonymous site stating why they protest]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20060829155933/religiousmovements.lib.virginia.edu/nrms/scientology_briefing.html Briefing prepared by the Church about the Church of Scientology and the internet]
* [http://home.snafu.de/tilman/mystory/dennis_final_judgement.txt RTC v. Dennis Erlich Stipulated Final Judgement and Permanent Injunction]

{{Scientology and the Internet}}
{{Anonymous and the Internet}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scientology Versus The Internet}}
[[Category:Computer law]]
[[Category:Scientology and the legal system]]
[[Category:Digital Millennium Copyright Act takedown incidents]]
[[Category:Scientology versus the Internet|*]]

[[de:Scientology gegen das Internet]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
