<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8551" ns="0" title="David"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the biblical king|other uses| David (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect10|Daud|Dawood|King David}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox monarch
| name = King David
| title = [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|King of Israel]]
| image= David SM Maggiore.jpg
| caption = Statue of David by [[Nicolas Cordier]], in the basilica of [[Santa Maria Maggiore]], [[Rome]]
| reign = over Judah c. 1010–1003 BC; over Judah and Israel c. 1003–970 BC
| coronation
| predecessor = [[Saul]] (Judah), [[Ish-bosheth]] (Israel)
| successor = [[Solomon]]
| suc-type =
| heir =
| consort = [[Michal]], [[Ahinoam]], [[Abigail]], [[Maachah]], [[Haggith]], [[Abital]], [[Eglah]], [[Bathsheba]] and [[Abishag]]
| royal house = [[Davidic line|House of David]] (new house)
| royal anthem =
| father = [[Jesse]]
| mother = not named in the Bible; identified by the [[Talmud]] as [[Nitzevet]], daughter of Adael.
| birth_date = c. 1040 BC
| birth_place = [[Bethlehem]]
| death_date = c. 970 BC
| death_place = [[Jerusalem]]
| buried =}}

'''David''' ({{Hebrew Name|דָּוִד, דָּוִיד|David|Dāwîḏ}}; &lt;small&gt;[[ISO 259-3]]&lt;/small&gt; ''Dawid''; [[Strong's Concordance|Strong's]] ''Daveed''; beloved; {{lang-ar|داوود}} or {{lang|ar|داود}}&amp;lrm;{{ref|A|[note A]}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|Dāwūd}}'') was the second king of the united [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|Kingdom of Israel]] according to the [[Hebrew Bible]] and, according to the [[Gospels]] of [[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]] and [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]], an ancestor of [[Jesus Christ]] through both [[Saint Joseph]] and [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]]. He is depicted as a righteous king, although not without fault, as well as an acclaimed warrior, musician and poet, traditionally credited for composing many of the psalms contained in the Book of [[Psalms]].

[[Edwin Thiele]] dates his life to c. 1040–970 BC, his reign over [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]] c. 1010–1003 BC, and his reign over the united Kingdom of Israel c. 1003–970 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Edwin Thiele, ''The Mysterious Numbers of the Hebrew Kings'', (1st ed.; New York: Macmillan, 1951; 2d ed.; Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1965; 3rd ed.; Grand Rapids: Zondervan/Kregel, 1983). ISBN 082543825X, 9780825438257&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Books of Samuel]], 1 Kings, and 1 Chronicles are the only source of information on his life and reign; the [[Tel Dan stele]] may record the existence in the mid-9th century of a Judean royal dynasty called the &quot;House of David&quot;, although this is disputed. David's life is very important to [[Jewish]], [[Christian]] and [[Islamic]] culture. In Judaism, David, or David HaMelekh, is the [[King of Israel]], and the Jewish people. A direct descendant of David will be the [[Messiah]]. In Islam, he is known as ''Dawud'', considered to be a prophet and the king of a nation.

==Biblical narrative==
[[File:Samuel e david.jpg|200px|left|thumb|[[Samuel (Bible)|Samuel]] anoints David, [[Dura Europos]], [[Syria]], Date: 3rd c. AD]]

===David, chosen by God===
God withdraws his favour from [[Saul]], king of Israel: ''It repenteth me that I have set up Saul to be king, for he is turned back from following me, and has not performed my commandments.'' The prophet [[Samuel (Bible)|Samuel]] seeks a new king from the sons of [[Jesse]] of [[Bethlehem]]. Seven of Jesse's sons are led before Samuel, but Samuel says, &quot;Yahweh has not chosen these.&quot; He then asks, &quot;Are these all the sons you have?&quot; and Jesse answers, &quot;There is still the youngest but he is tending the sheep.&quot; So David is brought to Samuel, and &quot;Yahweh said (to Samuel), 'Rise and anoint him; he is the one.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?book_id=9&amp;chapter=16&amp;version=31]&lt;/ref&gt;

===David at the court of Saul===
God sends an evil spirit to torment [[Saul]],''1 Samuel 16:14'', and his attendants suggest he send for David, a young warrior famed for his bravery and for his skill with the harp. Saul does so and makes David one of his armor-bearers and &quot;whenever the spirit from God came upon Saul, David would take his harp and play. Then relief would come to Saul; he would feel better, and the evil spirit would leave him.&quot;

===David and Goliath===
[[Image:David-goliath28.jpg|thumb|upright|David hoists the severed head of [[Goliath]] by [[Gustave Doré]]]]

The [[Israelites]], under King [[Saul]], face the [[Philistines]] in the [[Valley of Elah]]. The boy David is bringing food to his older brothers who are with Saul. He hears the Philistine giant [[Goliath]] challenging the Israelites to send their own champion to decide the outcome in single combat. David tells Saul he is prepared to face Goliath and Saul allows him to make the attempt. He is victorious, striking Goliath in the forehead with a stone from his [[Sling (weapon)|sling]].  Goliath falls, and David kills him with his own sword and beheads him; the Philistines flee in terror. Saul sends to know the name of the young champion, and David tells him that he is the son of Jesse.&lt;ref&gt;[[1 Samuel]] 17:1-58.&lt;/ref&gt;

===David and Jonathan===
{{Main|David and Jonathan}}
Saul makes David a commander over his armies and offers him his daughter [[Michal]] in marriage for bringing more than 200 foreskins of the Philistines to him. David is successful in many battles, and his popularity awakes Saul's fears — &quot;What more can he have but the kingdom?&quot; By various stratagems the jealous king seeks his death, but the plots only endear David the more to the people, and especially to Saul's son [[Jonathan (1 Samuel)|Jonathan]], who [[David and Jonathan|loves David]] (1 Samuel 18:1, 2 Samuel 1:25-26).&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|1|Samuel|18:1, 2|Samuel|1:25-26 |NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''See'' [[David and Jonathan]]. There is debate amongst some scholars on whether this relationship might have been platonic, romantic or sexual. The Hebrew word 'ahav, meaning &quot;love,&quot; has a very broad range of meanings, including simply the opposite of &quot;hate&quot; (The New Brown-Driver-Briggs-Gesenius Hebrew and English Lexicon [1978], p. 12), which can be shown by loyalty, as in 1 Samuel 18:16, &quot;All Israel and Judah loved David, because he led them in their campaigns.&quot; Boswell, John. ''Same-sex Unions in Premodern Europe''. New York: Vintage, 1994; Martti Nissinen, ''Homoeroticism in the Biblical World'', Minneapolis, 1998; ''When Heroes Love:. The Ambiguity of Eros in the Stories of Gilgamesh and David'' (New York &amp; Chichester, Columbia University Press, 2005); ''Homosexuality and Liminality in the Gilgamesh and Samuel'' (Amsterdam, Hakkert, 2007); Gagnon, ''The Bible and Homosexual Practice. Texts and Hermeneutics'' (Nashville, Abingdon Press, 2001); Markus Zehnder, &quot;Observations on the Relationship Between David and Jonathan and the Debate on Homosexuality&quot;, ''Westminster Theological Journal 69'' (2007) Nevertheless, the Biblical narrative depicts their relationship favourably.&lt;/ref&gt; Warned by Jonathan, David flees into the wilderness, where he gathers a band of followers and becomes the champion of the oppressed while evading the pursuit of Saul. He accepts the town of [[Ziklag]] as a chief from the Philistine king [[Achish]] of [[Gath (city)|Gath]], but continues secretly to champion the Israelites. Achish marches against Saul, but David is excused from the war on the accusation of the Philistine nobles that his loyalty to their cause cannot be trusted.

===David becomes king===
[[Image:Gilboa 123PAN.jpg|thumb|left|500px|Panorama of the [[Harod Valley]] below, part of the [[Jezreel Valley|Jezreel]]- see [[Mount Gilboa]]]]
Jonathan and Saul are killed in battle with the Philistines at [[Mount Gilboa]]. David mourns their deaths, especially that of Jonathan, his friend. He goes up to [[Hebron]], where he is [[Anointing|anointed]] king over [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]]. In the north, Saul's son [[Ish-Bosheth]] becomes king of the tribes of Israel. War ensues between Ish-Bosheth and David, until Ish-Bosheth is murdered. The assassins bring the head of Ish-Bosheth to David hoping for reward, but David executes them for their crime against the Lord's anointed. Yet with the death of the son of Saul, the elders of Israel come to Hebron and David, who is 30 years old, is anointed King over Israel and Judah.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{Bibleverse|2|Samuel|5|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jerusalem and the Davidic Covenant===
David conquers the [[Jebusite]] fortress of [[Jerusalem]], and makes it his capital, and &quot;[[King Hiram I|Hiram]] king of [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]] sent messengers to David, and cedar trees, also carpenters and masons who built David a house.&quot;  David brings the [[Ark of the Covenant]] to Jerusalem, intending to build a temple, but God, speaking to the prophet [[Nathan (Prophet)|Nathan]], forbids it, saying the temple must wait for a future generation. God makes a covenant with David, promising that he will establish the house of David eternally: &quot;Your throne shall be established forever.&quot;

With God's help, David is victorious over his people's enemies. The Philistines are subdued, the [[Moabites]] to the east pay tribute, along with [[Hadadezer]] of [[Zobah]], from whom David takes gold shields and bronze vessels.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Samuel%208:7&amp;version=NASB BibleGateway.com] 2 Samuel 8:7&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bathsheba and Uriah the Hittite===
David commits adultery with [[Bathsheba]], the wife of [[Uriah the Hittite]].&lt;ref&gt;Stassen, Glen Harold &amp; Gushee, David P. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=LlMVrmA-b-4C&amp;lpg=PA200&amp;dq=david%20committed%20adultery&amp;pg=PA200#v=onepage&amp;q=david%20committed%20adultery&amp;f=false Kingdom ethics: following Jesus in contemporary context]'', InterVarsity Press, 2003. p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; Bathsheba becomes pregnant. David sends for Uriah, who is with the Israelite army at the siege of [[Rabbah]], so that he may lie with his wife and conceal the identity of the child's father. Uriah refuses to do so while his companions are in the field of battle and David sends him back to [[Joab]], the commander, with a message instructing him to abandon Uriah on the battlefield, &quot;that he may be struck down, and die.&quot; David marries Bathsheba and she bears his child, &quot;but the thing that David had done displeased the Lord.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2sam%2011;&amp;version=47; 2 Samuel 11]&lt;/ref&gt; The prophet [[Nathan (prophet)|Nathan]] confronts David, saying: &quot;Why have you despised the word of God, to do what is evil in his sight? You have smitten Uriah the Hittite with the sword, and have taken his wife to be your wife.&quot; Nathan presents three punishments from God for this sin. First, that the &quot;sword shall never depart from your house&quot; (2 Samuel 12:10)  second, that &quot;Before your very eyes I will take your wives and give them to one who is close to you, and he will sleep with your wives in broad daylight. 12 You did it in secret, but I will do this thing in broad daylight before all Israel., (2 Samuel 12:12) and finally, that &quot;the son born to you will die.&quot;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|12:14|KJV|}}
David [[repents]], yet God &quot;struck the [David's] child ... and it became sick ... [And] on the seventh day the child died.&quot; David leaves his lamentations, dresses himself, goes to the House of the Lord and worships, and then returns home to eat. His servants ask why he wept when the baby was alive, but ends his mourning when the child dies. David replies: &quot;While the child was still alive, I fasted and wept. I thought, 'Who knows? The {{LORD}} may be gracious to me and let the child live.' But now that he is dead, why should I fast? Can I bring him back again? I will go to him, but he will not return to me.&quot;{{bibleverse|2|Samuel|12:22-23|KJV|}}

===David's son Absalom rebels===
David's son [[Absalom]] rebels against his father, and they come to battle in the [[Wood of Ephraim]]. Absalom is caught by his hair in the branches of an oak and David’s general Joab kills him as he hangs there.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Samuel%2018:14-15&amp;version=ESV 2Samuel 18:14-15]&lt;/ref&gt; When the news of the victory is brought to David, he does not rejoice, but is instead shaken with grief: &quot;O my son Absalom, my son, my son Absalom! Would I had died instead of you, O Absalom, my son, my son!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|2|Samuel|18:33|9}}, King James Version&lt;/ref&gt;

===The old age of David===
When David has become old and bedridden, [[Adonijah]], his eldest surviving son and natural heir, declares himself king. Bathsheba, David's favorite wife, and [[Nathan (prophet)|Nathan the prophet]], fearing that they will be killed by Adonijah, go to David and procure his agreement that [[Solomon]], Bathsheba's son, should sit on the throne. And so the plans of Adonijah collapse, and Solomon becomes king.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/1kings/1kings1.htm 1 Kings 1]&lt;/ref&gt; It is to Solomon that David gives his final instructions, including his promise that the line of Solomon and David will inherit the throne of Judah forever, and his request that Solomon kill his oldest enemies on his behalf.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/1kings/1kings2.htm 1 Kings 2]&lt;/ref&gt;
David dies and is buried in the [[City of David]], having ruled forty years over Israel, seven in Hebron and thirty-three in Jerusalem.

==David the Musician==

{{see also| History of music in the Biblical period}}

[[File:David Playing the Harp 1670 Jan de Bray.jpg|thumb|&quot;David Playing the Harp&quot;  by [[Jan de Bray]], 1670 ]]
In various biblical passages, David is referred to as “the favorite of the songs of Israel,”&lt;ref&gt;2 Samuel 23:1&lt;/ref&gt; the one who soothed Saul with music,&lt;ref&gt;1 Samuel 16:17-23&lt;/ref&gt; and the founder of Temple singing.&lt;ref&gt;2 Chronicles 23:18&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nehemiah 12:24,36, 45-46&lt;/ref&gt;  A Psalms scroll from the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]] (11QPs&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;) attributes 3600 [[tehilim]] (songs of praise) plus other compositions to David.&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to Psalms (pp. 1280, 1281), ''The Jewish Study Bible, Tanakh Translation.'' Berlin, Adele; Brettler, Marc Zvi; Fishbane, Michael, eds. Jewish Publication Society, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0195297512&lt;/ref&gt; Seventy-three of the 150 Psalms in the Bible are attributed to David.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;David&quot; and &quot;Psalms, Book of,&quot; ''New Bible Dictionary'', second edition,1982. Douglas, J.D. (organizing editor), Wheaton, Illinois: Tyndale Press. ISBN 0842346678&lt;/ref&gt; The supreme kingship of [[YHWH|Yahweh]] is the most pervasive theological concept in the book of Psalms,&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to Psalms (p. 1013), ''NIV Study Bible'',1995. Barker, Kenneth, Burdick, Donald; Stek John; Wessel, Walter; Youngblood, Ronald, eds. Zondervan. Grand Rapids, MI, USA ISBN 0310927099&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Psalms, Book of,&quot; ''New Bible Dictionary'', second edition,1982. Douglas, J.D. (organizing editor), Wheaton, Illinois: Tyndale Press. ISBN 0842346678&lt;/ref&gt; and many psalms attributed to David are directed to Yahweh by name,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Psalms, Book of&quot;, ''New Bible Dictionary'', second edition,1982. Douglas, J.D. (organizing editor), Wheaton, Illinois: Tyndale Press. ISBN 0842346678&lt;/ref&gt; whether in praise or petition, suggesting a relationship.&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to Psalms (p. 1284), ''The Jewish Study Bible, Tanakh Translation'', 2004. Berlin, Adele; Brettler, Marc Zvi; Fishbane, Michael, eds. Jewish Publication Society, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0195297512&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[Midrash Tehillim]], King David was prompted to the Psalms by the [[Ruach HaKodesh|Holy Spirit]] that rested upon him.&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Psalms 24 [http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/tmm/tmm17.htm read online]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to ascribing authorship to David, several Psalms are identified with specific events in David’s life.&lt;ref&gt;Psalms 3, 7, 18, 34, 51, 52, 54, 56, 57, 59, 60, 63 and 142, Commentary on II Samuel 22, The Anchor Bible, Vol. 9. ''II Samuel''. P. Kyle McCarter, Jr., 1984. New York: Doubleday. ISBN 0385068085&lt;/ref&gt; [http://mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt2634.htm Psalm 34] is attributed to David on the occasion of his escape from the Abimelech (king) Achish by pretending to be insane.&lt;ref&gt;Psalm 34, ''Interlinear NIV Hebrew-English Old Testament.'' Kohlenberger, J.R, 1987. Grand Rapids, Michigan:Zondervan Publishing House  ISBN 031040200X&lt;/ref&gt; According to the narrative in 1 Samuel 21, instead of killing the man who had exacted so many casualties from him, Abimelech allows David to depart, exclaiming, “Am I so short of madmen that you have to bring this fellow here to carry on like this in front of me? Must this man come into my house?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;1 Samuel 21:15 (NIV)&lt;/ref&gt; Psalm 34 is one of seven [[acrostic]] Psalms in the original Hebrew; most English translations do not retain the acrostic form.&lt;ref&gt;Explanatory Notes on Psalm 34, ‘’Treasury of David’’ (1885), [[Charles H. Spurgeon]], Hendrickson Publishers, 1988. ISBN 0917006259  [http://www.spurgeon.org/treasury/ps034.htm read online]&lt;/ref&gt; The first part of Psalm 34 is directed toward Yahweh in complete and humble gratitude (David does not even mention his own royal status); the second part confidently directs others to Yahweh.&lt;ref&gt;Commentary on Psalm 34,  ''The Jewish Study Bible, Tanakh Translation.'' Berlin, Adele; Brettler, Marc Zvi; Fishbane, Michael, eds. Jewish Publication Society, New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0195297512&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quotation | This poor man cried, and the L&lt;SMALL&gt;ORD&lt;/SMALL&gt; heard him, and saved him out of all his troubles. The angel of the {{LORD}} encamps around those who fear him, and delivers them … Come, O children, listen to me; I will teach you the fear of the {{LORD}}. | Psalm 34:6-7,11 (ESV)}}

In contrast, Psalm 18 is not related to a specific incident but rather to God’s faithful deliverance from “all of his enemies and from the hand of Saul.”&lt;ref&gt;Commentary on II Samuel 22, The Anchor Bible, Vol. 9: ''II Samuel''. P. Kyle McCarter, Jr., 1984. New York: Doubleday. ISBN 0385068085&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Commentary on Psalm 18: The Anchor Bible, Vol. 16. ''Psalms ''I. Mitchell Dahood, 1995. New York:Doubleday. ISBN 0385522509&lt;/ref&gt; The text of this Psalm was thought to date to the 10th century BC even before the discovery of the Dead Sea Scrolls&lt;ref&gt;Feinberg, Charles Lee, Th.D., Ph.D., 1947. The Date of the Psalms.  ''Bibliotheca Sacra'' 104: 426-40 Dallas Theological Seminary Department of Semitics and Old Testament, p. 429 [http://faculty.gordon.edu/hu/bi/Ted_Hildebrandt/OTeSources/19-Psalms/Text/Articles/Feinberg_DatePsalms_BS.pdf read online]&lt;/ref&gt; and is very similar to that of 2 Samuel 22.&lt;ref&gt;2 Samuel 22 and Psalm 18, ''Interlinear NIV Hebrew-English Old Testament.'' Kohlenberger, J.R, 1987. Grand Rapids, Michigan:Zondervan Publishing House  ISBN 031040200X&lt;/ref&gt; In this Psalm, David recalls being in deadly situations: “The cords of death entangled me, the torrents of destruction overwhelmed me.”&lt;ref&gt;Psalm 18:4 (NIV)&lt;/ref&gt;  He cries out to God for help, and God rescues David. {{quotation | I love you, O [[YHWH|LORD]], my strength. The LORD is my rock, my fortress and my deliverer; my God is my rock, in whom I take refuge. He is my shield and the horn of my salvation, my stronghold. I call to the LORD, who is worthy of praise, and I am saved from my enemies. | Psalm 18:1-3 (NIV)}}

The Scottish theologian [[Samuel Rutherford]] (1600–1661) notes that crying out to God is mentioned in many Psalms attributed to David.&lt;ref&gt;For example,  “At noon, will I pray, and cry aloud” Ps 55:17. “In my distress I cried to the {{LORD}}” Ps 18:6. “Unto thee have I cried, O {{LORD}}” Ps 88:13. “Out of the depths have I cried” Ps 130:1. “Unto thee will I cry, O {{LORD}} my rock” Ps 28:1.&lt;/ref&gt; He comments, “Fervour is a heavenly ingredient in prayer. An arrow drawn with full strength hath a speedier issue.” &lt;ref&gt;quoted in Explanatory Notes on Psalm 34, ‘’Treasury of David’’ (1885), [[Charles H. Spurgeon]], Hendrickson Publishers, 1988. ISBN 0917006259  [http://www.spurgeon.org/treasury/ps034.htm read online]&lt;/ref&gt; The Midrash Tehillim teaches from Psalm 4 “that the mere mechanical application to the Throne of Mercy is not efficacious is plainly seen from the words of King David, who says God is nigh to all that call upon Him, and … he adds the important words, 'to those who call upon Him ''in truth''.'”&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Psalms 4, emphasis is in the source. [http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/tmm/tmm17.htm read online]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Psalm 40, David’s cries to God were heartfelt though not necessarily impatient; the poignant combination of a cry for help with a confident expression of faith echo today in the song [[40 (song)|“40”]] by the rock group [[U2]] and that encapsulates David’s experience with his God: {{quotation | I waited patiently for the {{LORD}}; he turned to me and heard my cry. He lifted me out of the slimy pit, out of the mud and mire; he set my feet on a rock and gave me a firm place to stand. He put a new song in my mouth, a hymn of praise to our God.  Many will see and fear and put their trust in the {{LORD}}. | Psalm 40:1-3 (NIV)}}

==Religions and David==
===David in Judaism===
[[Image:Jerusalem Tomb of David BW 1.JPG|thumb|left|upright|The traditional tomb of David in Jerusalem, actually a Crusader tomb.&lt;ref&gt;J. Murphy-O'Connor, ''Oxford Archaeological Guides: The Holy Land'', 105-06.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Infobox saint
|name=King David the Prophet
|birth_date=c. 1040 B.C.E.
|death_date=c. 970 B.C.E.
|feast_day=
|venerated_in=[[Judaism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Christianity]]&lt;br&gt;[[Islam]]
|image=5201-king-david-in-prayer-pieter-de-grebber.jpg
|imagesize=250px
|caption=''King David in Prayer'', by [[Pieter de Grebber]] (c. 1640)
|birth_place=[[Bethlehem]]
|death_place=[[Jerusalem]]
|titles=Holy Monarch, Prophet, Reformer, Spiritual Poet &amp; Musician, Vicegerent of God, Psalm-Receiver 
|beatified_date=
|beatified_place=
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=
|attributes=[[Psalms]], [[Harp]], Head of [[Goliath]]
|patronage=
|suppressed_date=
|issues=
|prayer=
|prayer_attrib=
}}
David is an important figure in Judaism. Historically, David's reign represented the formation of a coherent [[United Monarchy|Jewish kingdom]] centered in [[Jerusalem]]. David is an important figure within the context of [[Jewish messianism]]. In the [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]], it is written that a human descendant of David will occupy the throne of a restored kingdom and usher in a [[messianic age]].

David is also viewed as a tragic figure; his acquisition of Bathsheba, and the loss of his son are viewed as his central tragedies.

Many legends have grown around the figure of David. According to one Rabbinic tradition, David was raised as the son of his father Jesse and spent his early years herding his father's sheep in the wilderness while his brothers were in school. Only at his anointing by Samuel - when the oil from Samuel's flask turned to diamonds and pearls - was his true identity as Jesse's son revealed. David's adultery with Bathsheba was only an opportunity to demonstrate the power of repentance, and some [[Talmud|Talmudic authors]] stated that it was not adultery at all, quoting a Jewish practice of divorce on the eve of battle. Furthermore, according to David's apologists, the death of Uriah was not to be considered murder, on the basis that Uriah had committed a capital offence by refusing to obey a direct command from the King.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=82&amp;letter=D#260 Jewish Encyclopedia, &quot;David&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[midrashim]], [[Adam]] gave up 70 years of his life for the life of David.&lt;ref&gt;Zohar Bereishis 91b&lt;/ref&gt; Also, according to the [[Talmud Yerushalmi]], David was born and died on the Jewish holiday of [[Shavuot]] (Feast of Weeks). His piety was said to be so great that his prayers could bring down things from Heaven.

===David in Christianity===
[[Image:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn 030.jpg|thumb|left|David and [[King Saul]], by [[Rembrandt]]. David plays the lyre (depicted here as a [[harp]]) to the king &quot;tormented by an evil spirit&quot;]]
Originally an earthly king ruling by divine appointment (&quot;the anointed one&quot;, as the title [[Messiah]] had it), the &quot;son of David&quot; became in the last two pre-Christian centuries the apocalyptic and heavenly one who would deliver Israel and usher in a new kingdom. This was the background to the concept of Messiahship in early Christianity, which interpreted the career of Jesus &quot;by means of the titles and functions assigned to David in the mysticism of the Zion cult, in which he served as priest-king and in which he was the mediator between God and man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/152497/David &quot;David&quot;] article from ''Encyclopedia Britannica Online''&lt;/ref&gt; The early Church believed that &quot;the life of David [foreshadowed] the life of Christ; [[Bethlehem]] is the birthplace of both; the shepherd life of David points out Christ, [[The Good Shepherd (Christianity)|the Good Shepherd]]; the five stones chosen to slay Goliath are [[Typology (theology)|typical]] of the [[Holy Wounds|five wounds]]; the betrayal by his trusted counsellor, [[Ahitophel|Achitophel]], and the passage over the [[Kidron Valley|Cedron]] remind us of Christ's [[Passion (Christianity)|Sacred Passion]]. Many of the Davidic Psalms, as we learn from the New Testament, are clearly [[Typology (theology)|typical]] of the future [[Messiah]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John Corbett (1911) [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04642b.htm King David] ''[[The Catholic Encyclopedia]]'' (New York: Robert Appleton Company)&lt;/ref&gt;
In the [[Middle Ages]], &quot;[[Charlemagne]] thought of himself, and was viewed by his court scholars, as a 'new David'. [This was] not in itself a new idea, but [one whose] content and significance were greatly enlarged by him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=DhpKxQT8n74C&amp;pg=PA101&amp;lpg=PA101&amp;dq=charlemagne+described+as+a+new+david&amp;source=web&amp;ots=vjwf-CjzXi&amp;sig=52MXxWcu1a_gSiOTNycuSe8XTWc Oxford Illustrated History of Christianity],&lt;/ref&gt; The linking of David to earthly kingship was reflected in later Medieval cathedral windows all over Europe through the device of the [[Tree of Jesse]], its branches demonstrating how divine kingship descended from Jesse, through his son David, to Jesus.

[[Latin liturgical rites|Western Rite]] churches (Roman Catholic, Lutheran) celebrate his feast day on 29 December, Eastern-rite on 19 December.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saintpatrickdc.org/ss/1229.shtml Saint of the Day] for December 29 at St. Patrick Catholic Church, Washington, D.C.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] and [[Eastern Catholic Church]] celebrate the [[feast day]] of the &quot;Holy Righteous Prophet and King David&quot; on the Sunday of the Holy Forefathers (two Sundays before the [[Great Feast]] of the [[Christmas|Nativity of the Lord]]), when he is commemorated together with other [[genealogy of Jesus|ancestors of Jesus]]. He is also commemorated on the Sunday after the Nativity, together with [[Saint Joseph|Joseph]] and [[James, the Brother of the Lord]].

===David in Islam===
''Main article [[Islamic view of David]]''&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Christianity and Islam]] --&gt;

David ([[Arabic]] داود, ''Dāwūd'') is a highly important figure in [[Islam]] as one of the major [[prophet]]s sent by [[God]] to guide the nation of [[Israel]]. David is mentioned several times in the [[Qur'an]], often with his son [[Solomon]]. In the [[Qur'an]]: David kills Goliath (II: 251) and God grants him kingship and wisdom and enforces it (XXXVIII: 20). David is made God's &quot;[[vicegerent]] on earth&quot; (XXXVIII: 26) and God further gives David sound judgment (XXI: 78; XXXVII: 21-24, 26) as well as the [[Psalms]], which are regarded as books of divine wisdom (IV: 163; XVII, 55). The birds and mountains unite with David in ushering praise to God (XXI: 79; XXXIV: 10; XXXVIII: 18), while God instructs David in the art of fashioning chain-mail out of iron (XXXIV: 10; XXI: 80). Together with Solomon, David gives judgment in a case of damage to the fields (XXI: 78) and David judges in the matter between two disputants in his prayer chamber (XXXVIII: 21-23). Since there is no mention in the [[Qur'an]] of the wrong David did to [[Uriah the Hittite|Uriah]] nor is there any reference to [[Bathsheba]], [[Muslim]]s reject this narrative.&lt;ref&gt;A-Z of Prophets in Islam and Judaism, Wheeler, ''David''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Muslim]] [[tradition]] and the ''[[hadith]]'' stress David's zeal in daily [[prayer]]&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Islam'', ''Dawud''&lt;/ref&gt; as well as in [[fasting]]. [[Qur'an]] commentators, historians and compilers of the numerous ''[[Stories of the Prophets]]'' elaborate upon David's concise Qur'anic narratives and specifically mention David's gift in singing his [[Psalms]] as well as his musical and vocal talents. His voice is described as having had a captivating power, weaving its influence not only over man but over all beasts and nature, who would unite with him to praise [[God]].&lt;ref&gt;''Stories of the Prophets'', Ibn Kathir, ''Story of David''&lt;/ref&gt;

===David in Baha'i Faith===
David is described as a minor prophet who came in the shadow of the [[dispensation]] of Moses to develop and consolidate the process he set in motion.&lt;ref name=&quot;manifestation&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | first = Juan | last = Cole | title = The Concept of Manifestation in the Bahá'í Writings| year = 1982 | journal = Bahá'í Studies | volume = monograph 9  | pages = 1–38 | url = http://bahai-library.com/cole_concept_manifestation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===David in Mormonism ===
The [[Doctrine and Covenants]] of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] cites David as one directed by God to practice [[polygamy]], but who sinned in committing adultery with Bathsheba and having Uriah killed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scriptures.lds.org/en/dc/132/1,38-39#1 Doctrine and Covenants 132:1, 38-39] (see highlighted portions).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historicity of David==
''See [[The Bible and history]] and [[dating the Bible]] for a more complete description of the general issues surrounding the Bible as a historical source.''

===Archaeological evidence===
[[Image:Tel dan inscription.png|thumb|The [[Tel Dan Stele]]]]

====Tel Dan Stele and Mesha Stele====
A fragment of an Aramaean victory stele discovered in 1993 at [[Tel Dan Stele|Tel Dan]] and dated c.850-835 BC contains a phrase {{Hebrew|ביתדוד}} (bytdwd). Because ancient Aramaic script does not contain [[nikkud|vowels]], different readings are possible. Scholars agree that the first part should be read {{Hebrew|בֵּית}} (beyt), meaning &quot;house&quot;. However, the second part can be read as 1) {{Hebrew|דּוֹד}} (dod), which means &quot;uncle&quot; or &quot;beloved&quot; or as 2) {{Hebrew|דָּוִד}} (David). The phrase therefore can mean either &quot;House of the beloved&quot;, &quot;House of the uncle&quot; or &quot;House of David&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;*[http://books.google.com/books?id=eprY1Qd0veAC&amp;pg=PA110&amp;lpg=PA110&amp;dq=there+are+currently+three+extant+fragments+of+the+Tel+Dan+stele&amp;f=false Mykytiuk, Lawrence J. (2004). &quot;Identifying Biblical Persons in Northwest Semitic Inscriptions of 1200-539 B.C.E.&quot; Atlanta, Ga.: Society of Biblical Literature. See pp.&amp;nbsp;110-132 and 265-277.] &quot;If the reading of {{Hebrew|בֵּיתדָּוִד}} [House of David] on the Tel Dan stele is correct, (...) then we have solid evidence that a 9th-century BC Aramean king considered the founder of the Judean dynasty to be a ruler named {{Hebrew|דָּוִד}} [David]. P. 132 states that &quot;Although interpreters are free to favor possibilities . . . other than &quot;the house of David,&quot; these other meanings remain largely theoretical, rather than demonstrable.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Since the stele recounts the victory of an Aramean king over &quot;the king of Israel&quot;, &lt;ref&gt;[[Tel Dan Stele]]&lt;/ref&gt; the translation of &quot;{{Hebrew|ביתדוד}}&quot; as &quot;the House of David&quot; is not illogical.&lt;ref&gt;Biran, Avraham and Naveh, J. &quot;An Aramaic Stele Fragment From Tel Dan.&quot; Israel Exploration Journal 43 (1993).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heardworld.com/higgaion/?m=200509&amp;paged=2 Picking Abraham and Choosing David], Christopher Heard, Associate Professor of Religion at [[Pepperdine University]]. See also Israeli journalist Daniel Gavron's ''[http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/MFAArchive/2000_2009/2003/9/King%20David%20and%20Jerusalem-%20Myth%20and%20Reality King David and Jerusalem - Myth and Reality]'' for a useful overview.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Mesha Stele]] from [[Moab]], dating from approximately the same period, may also contain the name David, in two places: in line 12, where the interpretation is uncertain, and &lt;big&gt;בת[ד]וד&lt;/big&gt; in line 31, where one destroyed letter must be supplied (here it is bracketed in the middle).&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=CS9DKZgzfDIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=identifying+biblical+persons&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=MTiBTandJ9DTgAeMv6GFCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAA#v=snippet&amp;q=%22appendix%20e%20is%20the%20biblical%20king%20david%20named%20in%20the%20mesha%20inscription%22&amp;f=false Mykytiuk, Lawrence J. (2004). &quot;Identifying Biblical Persons in Northwest Semitic Inscriptions of 1200-539 B.C.E.&quot; (Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature), pp. 265-279.]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenneth Kitchen]] has proposed that an inscription of c. 945 BC by the Egyptian Pharaoh [[Shoshenq I]] mentions &quot;the highlands of David.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;K. A. Kitchen, &quot;A Possible Mention of David in the Late Tenth Century BC, and Deity *Dod as Dead as the Dodo?&quot; ''[[Journal for the Study of the Old Testament]]'' 76 (1997): 29–44, especially 39–41.&lt;/ref&gt; Although a reference to King David in this geographical name is not certain, some scholars suggest it is reasonable.&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence J. Mykytiuk, &quot;Corrections and Updates to 'Identifying Biblical Persons in Northwest Semitic Inscriptions of 1200—539 B.C.E.,'&quot; ''Maarav'' 16/1 (2009), pp. 119-121, which observes that this geographical name was inscribed within 45 years or less after the biblical time of King David's death and sees a parallel to another geographic name, &quot;the [[city of David]],&quot; in 2 Sam 5:7,9; 6:10, etc.; 1 Kgs 2:10, etc.; Isa 22:9; 1 Chr 11:5,7, etc.&lt;/ref&gt;

====City of David and Judah, ca. 1000 BC onward====
{{Main|City of David}}
[[File:KDP IMG 4885.JPG|thumb|right|250px|Part of the [[Large Stone Structure]] thought by some archaeologists to be the remains of King David's Palace.]]
The Bronze and Iron Age remains of the [[City of David]], the original urban core of Jerusalem identified with the reigns of David and Solomon, were investigated extensively in the 1970s and 1980s under the direction of Yigal Shiloh of the [[Hebrew University]], but failed to discover significant evidence of occupation during the 10th century BC,&lt;ref&gt;See [[David Ussishkin]], &quot;Solomon's Jerusalem: The Text and the Facts on the Ground,&quot; in: A.G. Vaughn and A.E. Killebrew (eds.), ''Jerusalem in Bible and Archaeology: The First Temple Period'', (Society of Biblical Literature, Symposium Series, No. 18), Atlanta, 2003, pp. 103-115. See also Cahill, J., &quot;David's Jerusalem, Fiction or Reality? The Archaeological Evidence Proves It,&quot; and Steiner, M., &quot;David's Jerusalem, Fiction or Reality? It's Not There: Archaeology Proves a Negative,&quot; both in ''Biblical Archaeology Review'' 24 (July/August 1998). (These two scholars argue opposite sides of the case for a Jerusalem in keeping with the biblical portrayal).&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, [[Eilat Mazar]] found a [[Large Stone Structure]] which she claimed was David's Palace, but the archaeology is contaminated and impossible to date accurately.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=The once and future city |first=Rena |last=Rossner   |url=http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1137605923369&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull  |newspaper=The Jerusalem Post |date=January 26, 2006|accessdate=November 15, 2009 |quote=In August 2005, corroborating her conclusions with biblical verses, Mazar announced that she had found King David's palace.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See [[Eilat Mazar]], &quot;Did I find David's Temple?&quot; in Biblical Archeology Review, Jan/Feb 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Finkelstein and Silberman feel the archaeological evidence from surface surveys indicates that Judah at the time of David was a small tribal kingdom, although both do accept that David and Solomon were likely historical figures in Judah about the 10th century BC. They describe the earliest tales of David as a &quot;classical bandit tale&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Finkelstein, Israel; Neil Asher Silberman''David and Solomon: In Search of the Bible's Sacred Kings and the Roots of the Western Tradition'' Simon &amp; Schuster Ltd (16 October 2006) ISBN 978-0743243629 p32&lt;/ref&gt;

===The biblical account===
The biblical account about David comes from the [[book of Samuel]] and the [[book of Chronicles]] (both of which are divided into two books in Jewish and Christian traditions). (Although almost half of the Psalms are headed &quot;A Psalm of David&quot;, the headings are later additions, and no psalm can be attributed to David with certainty).&lt;ref name=&quot;McKenzie_on_David&quot;&gt;[http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/McKensie_020301.shtml Steven McKenzie, Associate Professor Rhodes College, Memphis, Tennessee].&lt;/ref&gt; Chronicles merely retells Samuel from a different theological vantage point, and contains little if any information not available there, and the biblical evidence for David is therefore dependent almost exclusively on the material contained in the chapters from 1 Samuel 16 to 1 Kings 2.
[[Image:David-icon.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Russian icon|Russian]] [[icon]] of St. David, the Prophet and King, 18th century ([[Iconostasis]] of [[Kizhi]] [[monastery]], [[Karelia]], [[Russia]]).]]

Since [[Martin Noth]] put forward his analysis of the [[Deuteronomistic History]], biblical scholars have accepted that these two books form part of a continuous history of Israel, compiled no earlier than the late 7th century BC, but incorporating earlier works and fragments. Samuel's account of David &quot;seems to have undergone two separate acts of editorial slanting.&quot; The original writers show a strong bias against Saul, and in favour of David and Solomon. Many years later, some scholars believe the Deuteronomists edited the material in a manner that conveyed their religious message, inserting reports and anecdotes that strengthened their monotheistic doctrine. Some of the materials in Samuel I and II — notably the boundary, allotment and administrative lists — are believed to be very early, since they correspond closely to what we know of the territorial conditions of the late Davidic-early Solomonic period.&lt;ref&gt;Norman K. Gottwald, ''Tribes of Yahweh: A Sociology of the Religion of Liberated Israel, 1250-1050 BCE,'' Continuum 1999 pp.156-157, p.162.&lt;/ref&gt;

Beyond this, the full range of possible interpretations is available. The late [[John Bright (biblical scholar)|John Bright]], whose ''History of Israel'', which went through four editions from 1959 to 2000, takes Samuel at face value, but [[Donald B. Redford]] thinks all reconstructions from Biblical sources for the [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|United Monarchy]] period are examples of 'academic wishful thinking',&lt;ref&gt;Donald B. Redford, ''Egypt, Canaan, and Israel in Ancient Times,'' Princeton University Press, 1992 pp.301-307, p.301.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Thomas L. Thompson]] measures Samuel against the archaeological evidence and concludes that &quot;an independent history of Judea during the Iron I [i.e., the period of David] and Iron II periods has little room for historicizing readings of the stories of I-II Samuel and I Kings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/copenhagen.htm &quot;A View from Copenhagen&quot;, Thomas L. Thompson, Professor of Old Testament, Copenhagen University].&lt;/ref&gt; Some interesting studies of David have been written: [[Baruch Halpern]] has pictured David as a lifelong vassal of [[Achish]], the Philistine king of Gath;&lt;ref&gt;Baruch Halpern, &quot;David's Secret Demons&quot;, 2001.[http://www.bookreviews.org/pdf/1551_3721.pdf Review of Baruch Halpern's &quot;David's Secret Demons&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Israel Finkelstein]] and [[Neil Asher Silberman]] have identified as the oldest and most reliable section of Samuel those chapters which describe David as the charismatic leader of a band of outlaws who captures Jerusalem and makes it his capital.&lt;ref&gt;Finkelstein and Silberman, &quot;David and Solomon&quot;, 2006. See review [http://www.archaeology.org/0601/reviews/kings.html &quot;Archaeology&quot; magazine].&lt;/ref&gt; Steven McKenzie, Associate Professor of the Hebrew Bible at [[Rhodes College]] and author of ''King David: A Biography'', states the belief that David actually came from a wealthy family, was &quot;ambitious and ruthless&quot; and a tyrant who murdered his opponents, including his own sons.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKenzie_on_David&quot; /&gt;

==David's succession==
[[Image:France Chartres JesseTree c1145 a.JPG|thumb|upright|The oldest complete [[Tree of Jesse]] window is in [[Chartres Cathedral]], 1145.]]

===Genealogy===
According to {{bibleref|Genesis|46:12|KJV}} and {{Bibleverse||Ruth|4:18-22|HE}}, David is the eleventh&lt;ref name=&quot;david11&quot;&gt;Note, 'eleventh' - counting Judah as first - like the example in the book of Jude where Enoch is said to be the 'seventh from Adam', which makes Adam first. {{bibleref|Jude|1:14|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; generation from [[Judah (Bible)|Judah]], the fourth son of the patriarch [[Jacob]] (Israel). The genealogical line runs as follows: (1) [[Judah (Bible)|Judah]] → (2) [[Pharez]] → (3) [[Hezron]] → (4) [[Ram (Biblical figure)|Ram]] → (5) [[Amminadab]] → (6) [[Nahshon]] → (7) [[Salmon (Biblical figure)|Salmon]] → (8) [[Boaz]] (the husband of [[Ruth (biblical figure)|Ruth]]) → (9) [[Obed (Biblical figure)|Obed]] → (10) [[Jesse]] → (11) David.&lt;ref name=&quot;david11&quot; /&gt;

===David's family===
David was born in [[Bethlehem]], in the territory of the [[Tribe of Judah]]. His father was named [[Jesse]]. His mother is not named in the Bible, but the [[Talmud]] identifies her as [[Nitzevet]] daughter of Adael.&lt;ref&gt;Talmud Tractate Bava Batra 91a&lt;/ref&gt;  David had seven brothers and was the youngest of them all. He had eight wives: [[Michal]], the second daughter of [[King Saul]]; [[Ahinoam]] the Jezreelite; [[Abigail]] the Carmelite, previously wife of [[Nabal]];&lt;ref&gt;|1|Samuel|25&lt;/ref&gt; [[Maachah]], daughter of [[Talmai]], king of [[Geshur]]; [[Haggith]]; [[Abital]]; [[Eglah]]; and [[Bathsheba]], previously the wife of [[Uriah the Hittite]].

The [[Book of Chronicles]] lists David's sons by various wives and [[concubine]]s. In Hebron he had six sons {{Bibleverse|1|Chronicles|3:1-3|NIV}}: [[Amnon]], by Ahinoam; [[Daniel (son of David)|Daniel]], by Abigail; [[Absalom]], by Maachah; [[Adonijah]], by Haggith; [[Shephatiah]], by Abital; and [[Ithream]], by Eglah. By Bathsheba, his sons were: Shammua; [[Shobab]]; [[Nathan (son of David)|Nathan]]; and [[Solomon]]. His sons born in Jerusalem by other wives included: [[Ibhar]]; Elishua; [[Eliphelet]]; Nogah; Nepheg; [[Japhia]]; [[Elishama]]; and [[Eliada]]. {{Bibleverse|2|Samuel|5:14-16|NIV}} According to {{Bibleverse|2|Chronicles|11:18|NIV}}, [[Jerimoth]], who is not mentioned in any of the genealogies, is mentioned as another of David's sons. According to {{Bibleverse|2|Samuel|9:11|NIV}}, David adopted Jonathan's son [[Mephibosheth]] as his own.

David also had at least one daughter, [[Tamar (2 Samuel)|Tamar]] by Maachah, who was raped by Amnon, her half-brother. Her rape leads to Amnon's death. {{Bibleverse|2|Samuel|13:1-29|NIV}} Absalom, Amnon's half-brother and Tamar's full-brother, waits two years, then avenges his sister by sending his servants to kill Amnon at a feast to which he had invited all the king's sons. {{Bibleverse|2|Samuel|13|NIV}}

===Descendants of David===
{{Refimprove|date=October 2010}}
The following are some of the more notable persons who have claimed descent from the Biblical David, or had it claimed on their behalf:
* [[Jesus]] of Nazareth (Jesus Christ)
* [[Maimonides]] (Rabbi Moshe ben Maimon of Spain/haRaMbaM apx. 1135-1204)
* [[Judah Loew]], Yehuda Loew ben Bezalel (c. 1525, Prague; 22 August 1609 Prague), also known as &quot;The Maharal of Prague&quot;.
* The [[Abravanel]] family
* The [[Baal Shem Tov]], and through him every Hassidic Rebbe descended from him
* [[Rabbi Menachem Mendel Schneerson]], whose family is descended from Judah Loew.

==Legend and legacy==
In European Christian culture of the [[Middle Ages]], David was created a member of the [[Nine Worthies]], a group of heroes encapsulating all the ideal qualities of [[chivalry]]. His life was thus proposed as a valuable subject for study by those aspiring to chivalric status. This aspect of David in the Nine Worthies was popularised firstly through literature, and was thereafter adopted as a frequent subject for painters and sculptors.

==Representation in art and literature==
===Art===
Famous sculptures of David include (in chronological order) those by:
* [[Donatello]] (''c.'' 1430 - 1440), [[David (Donatello)|''David'' (Donatello)]]
* [[Andrea del Verrocchio]] (1476), [[David (Verrocchio)|''David'' (Verrocchio)]]
* [[Michelangelo]] (1504), [[David (Michelangelo)|''David'' (Michelangelo)]]
* [[Gian Lorenzo Bernini]] (1624), [[David (Bernini)|''David'' (Bernini)]]
* [[Antonin Mercié]] (1873)

===Literature===
* [[John Dryden|Dryden]]'s long poem [[Absalom and Achitophel]] is an allegory that uses the story of the rebellion of [[Absalom]] against King David as the basis for his satire of the contemporary political situation, including events such as the [[Monmouth Rebellion]] (1685), the [[Popish Plot]] (1678) and the [[Exclusion Crisis]].
* [[Elmer Davis]]'s novel ''Giant Killer'' (1928, The John Day company) retells and embellishes the Biblical story of David, casting David as primarily a poet who managed always to find others to do the &quot;dirty work&quot; of heroism and kingship. In the novel, [[Elhanan son of Jair|Elhanan]] in fact killed Goliath but David claimed the credit; and [[Joab]], David's cousin and general, took it upon himself to make many of the difficult decisions of war and statecraft when David vacillated or wrote poetry instead.
* [[Gladys Schmitt]] wrote a novel titled &quot;David the King&quot; (1946, Doubleday Books) which proceeds as a richly embellished biography of David's entire life. The book took a risk, especially for its time, in portraying David's relationship with Jonathan as overtly [[homoerotic]], but was ultimately panned by critics as a bland rendition of the title character.
* In [[Thomas Burnett Swann]]'s Biblical fantasy novel ''How are the Mighty Fallen'' (1974, DAW), David and Jonathan are explicitly stated to be lovers. Moreover, Jonathan is a member of a winged semi-human race (possibly [[nephilim]]), one of several such races co-existing with humanity but often persecuted by it.
* [[Joseph Heller]] wrote a novel based on David, ''[[God Knows (novel)|God Knows]]'' (1984, Simon &amp; Schuster). Told from the perspective of an aging David, the humanity — rather than the heroism — of various biblical characters is emphasized. The portrayal of David as a man of flaws such as greed, lust, selfishness, and his alienation from God, the falling apart of his family is a distinctly 20th century interpretation of the events told in the Bible.
* [[Juan Bosch]], Dominican political leader and writer, wrote &quot;David: Biography of a King&quot; (1966, Hawthorn, NY) a realistic approach to David's life and political career.
* [[Allan Massie]] wrote &quot;King David&quot; (1996, Sceptre), a novel about David's career which portrays the king's relationship to Jonathan and others as openly [[Homosexuality|homosexual]].
* [[Madeleine L'Engle]]'s novel ''Certain Women'' (1993, HarperOne) explores family, the Christian faith, and the nature of God through the story of King David's family and an analogous modern family's saga.
* [[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]] used the story of David and Bathsheba as the main structure for the [[Sherlock Holmes]] story ''[[The Adventure of the Crooked Man]]''. The betrayal of the Crooked Man is paralleled with David's betrayal of Uriah the Hittite, carried out in order to win Bathsheba.
* [[Stefan Heym]]'s &quot;The King David Report&quot; (1998, Northwestern University Press) is a fiction depicting the writings of the Bible historian Ethan, upon King Solomon's orders, of a true and authoritative report on the life of David, Son of Jesse.
* [[Malachi Martin]]'s 1980 factional novel ''King of Kings: A Novel of the Life of David'' relates the life of David, Adonai's champion in his battle with the Philistine deity Dagon.
* [[William Faulkner]]'s &quot;[[Absalom, Absalom!]]&quot;(1936) refers to the story of Absalom, David's son; his rebellion against his father and his death at the hands of David's general, Joab.  In addition it parallels Absalom's vengeance for the rape of his sister Tamar by his half-brother, Amnon.

===Film===
* [[Gregory Peck]] played King David in the 1951 film ''[[David and Bathsheba]]'', directed by [[Henry King (director)|Henry King]]. [[Susan Hayward]] played Bathsheba and [[Raymond Massey]] played the prophet Nathan.
* [[Jeft Chandler]] played David in the 1960 film ''[[A Story of David]]''
* [[Finlay Currie]] played an aged King David in the 1959 film ''[[Solomon and Sheba]]'', directed by [[King Vidor]]. [[Yul Brynner]] played Solomon and [[Gina Lollobrigida]] played the Queen of Sheba.
* [[Richard Gere]] portrayed King David in the 1985 film ''[[King David (film)|King David]]'' directed by [[Bruce Beresford]].

===Music===
* [[Josquin des Prez]]'s Planxit autem David is a polyphonic setting of 2 Samuel Chapter I verses 17-27, David's lamentation for the dead Saul and Jonathan. His Absalon fili mi is a polyphonic lamentation from David's perspective on the death of his son.
* [[George Frideric Handel]]'s oratorio ''[[Saul (Handel)|Saul]]'' features David as one of its main characters 
* [[Arthur Honegger]]'s oratorio ''[[Le roi David (Honegger)|Le Roi David]]'' ('King David'), with a libretto by Rene Morax, was composed in 1921 and instantly became a staple of the choral repertoire; it is still widely performed.
* [[Leonard Cohen]]'s song &quot;[[Hallelujah (Leonard Cohen song)|Hallelujah]]&quot; has references to David (&quot;there was a secret chord that David played and it pleased the Lord&quot;, &quot;The baffled king composing Hallelujah&quot;) and [[Bathsheba]] (&quot;you saw her bathing on the roof&quot;) in its opening verses.
* &quot;Mad About You&quot;, a song on [[Sting (musician)|Sting's]] 1991 album ''[[The Soul Cages]]'', explores David's obsession with Bathsheba from David's perspective.
* [[Doolittle (album)|Dead]] by the [[Pixies]] is a retelling of David's adultery and repentance.
* [[Herbert Howells]] (1892–1983) composed an artsong for voice and piano called &quot;[[List of compositions by Herbert Howells|King David]]&quot;.
* [[Eric Whitacre]] composed a choral piece, &quot;When David Heard,&quot; chronicling the death of Absalom and David's grief over losing his son.
* [[mewithoutYou]] has a song from their album [[It's All Crazy! It's All False! It's All a Dream! It's Alright]], entitled &quot;The Angel of Death Came to David's Room,&quot; which tells the story of David struggle with the Angel of Death when his (David's) time of death has arrived. It is based on folk tradition of King David and some Hebrew Bible.
*[[Pierce Pettis]] wrote and recorded a song on his album &quot;Making Light of It&quot; called &quot;Absalom, Absalom,&quot; expressing David's feelings of grief over and responsibility for his son's death.
*[[Spoken (band)]] released a track on their album [[Echoes of the Spirit Still Dwell]] called &quot;David&quot; that is based on 2 Samuel 6:14.

===Musical theater===
* [[King David (musical)|King David]], a modern oratorio, with a book and lyrics by [[Tim Rice]] and music by [[Alan Menken]].

===Television===
* [[Nathaniel Parker]] portrayed King David in the 1997 TV film ''David'', with [[Leonard Nimoy]] as Samuel and [[Jonathan Pryce]] as Saul.
* In 2009, NBC introduced the series ''[[Kings (U.S. TV series)|Kings]]'', which was explicitly designed as a modern retelling of the David story.
* In the PBS television series [[Wishbone (TV series)|Wishbone]] the episode &quot;[[List of Wishbone episodes|Little Big Dog]]&quot; recounts the story of David, his favor with Saul, and his triumphant battle over Goliath.
* The season two episode of [[Xena: Warrior Princess]] &quot;[[List of Xena: Warrior Princess episodes|Giant Killer]]&quot; features David and his killing of Goliath.

===Trivia===
For a considerable period, starting in the 15th century and continuing until the 19th, French [[playing card]] manufacturers assigned to each of the court cards names taken from history or mythology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.snopes.com/history/world/cardking.asp &quot;The Four King Truth&quot;] at the [[Urban Legends Reference Pages]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.madore.org/~david/misc/cards.html &quot;Courts on playing cards&quot;], by David Madore, with illustrations of the Anglo-American and French court cards&lt;/ref&gt; In this context, the [[King of Spades]] was often known as &quot;David&quot;.

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints}}
* [[David and Jonathan]]
* [[Large Stone Structure|King David's Palace site]]
* [[King David's Tomb]]
* [[Midrash Shmuel (aggadah)]]
* [[Passover songs]]
* [[Tel Arad]]

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
* {{note|A|A}} &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:120%&quot;&gt;{{script/Arabic|داود}}&lt;/span&gt; is the traditional [[Koranic Arabic|Koran]]ic spelling without [[Arabic diacritics|vocalization]].&amp;nbsp; In [[Modern Standard Arabic]], it is normally written &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:120%&quot;&gt;{{lang|ar|داوود}}&lt;/span&gt;.
{{refend}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* Kirsch, Jonathan (2000) ''King David: the real life of the man who ruled Israel''. Ballantine. ISBN 0-345-43275-4.
* See also the entry &quot;David&quot; in ''[http://www.biblestudytools.com/Dictionaries/EastonsBibleDictionary/ Easton's Bible Dictionary]''.
* Dever, William G. (2001) ''What did the Bible writers know and when did they know it?'' William B. Eerdmans Publ. Co., Cambridge UK.

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Alexander|editor1-first=David|editor2-last=Alexander|editor2-first=Pat|title=Eerdmans' handbook to the Bible|year=1983|publisher=Eerdmans|location=Grand Rapids, Mich.|isbn=0802834868|edition=[New, rev.].}}
*{{cite book|last=Bright|first=John|title=A history of Israel|year=1981|publisher=Westminster Press|location=Philadelphia|isbn=0664213812|edition=3rd}}
*{{cite book|last=Bruce|first=F. F.|title=Israel and the Nations|year=1963|publisher=Eerdmans|location=Grand Rapids, MI}}
*{{cite book|last=Harrison|first=R.K.|title=An Introduction to the Old Testament|year=1969|publisher=Eerdmans|location=Grand Rapids, MI}}
*{{cite book|last=Kidner|first=Derek|title=The Psalms|year=1973|publisher=Inter-Varsity Press|location=Downers Grove, IL|isbn=0877848688}}
*{{cite book|last=Noll|first=K. L.|title=The faces of David|year=1997|publisher=Sheffield Acad. Press|location=Sheffield|isbn=1850756597}}
*{{cite book|last=Thompson|first=J.A.|title=Handbook of life in Bible times|year=1986|publisher=Inter-Varsity Press|location=Leicester, England|isbn=0877849498}}

* For a more complete summary of all the episodes in the Saul/David story in Samuel (but excluding Chronicles), see [http://people.brandeis.edu/~buchsbau/MSGPAPERS/sumsam.pdf synopsis]

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://www.complete-bible-genealogy.com/names/david_593.htm Complete Bible Genealogy] David's family tree
* [http://bib-arch.org/ Double Identity: Orpheus as David. Orpheus as Christ?] Biblical Archaeology Review

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[Davidic line|House of David]]|||||[[Tribe of Judah]]|name=David of the United Kingdom of Israel &amp; Judah}}
{{S-reg|}}
{{S-new|reason=Rebellion from [[United Monarchy|Israel]] under [[Ish-bosheth]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Kingdom of Judah|King of Judah]]|years=1010 BC–1003 BC}}
{{S-aft|rows=2|after=[[Solomon]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Saul]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|King of the United &lt;br/&gt; Israel and Judah]]|years=1003 BC–970 BC}}
{{end}}

{{IsraeliteKings}}
{{Adam to David}}
{{Prophets in the Qur'an|no}}
{{Solomon}}

[[Category:David| ]]
[[Category:Hebrew Bible people]]
[[Category:Kings of ancient Israel]]
[[Category:Kings of ancient Judah]]
[[Category:10th-century BC biblical rulers]]
[[Category:11th-century BC biblical rulers]]
[[Category:Biblical murderers]]
[[Category:Burials in Jerusalem]]
[[Category:History of Jerusalem]]
[[Category:Old Testament saints]]
[[Category:People celebrated in the Lutheran liturgical calendar]]
[[Category:People from Bethlehem]]
[[Category:Shepherds]]
[[Category:Books of Samuel]]

{{Link GA|no}}

[[ace:Daud]]
[[ar:داود]]
[[az:Davud peyğəmbər]]
[[bn:দাউদ]]
[[be:Давыд, цар ізраільска-іудзейскі]]
[[br:David (roue Israel)]]
[[bg:Давид]]
[[ca:David]]
[[cs:David (biblická postava)]]
[[cy:Dafydd (brenin)]]
[[da:Kong David]]
[[pdc:Daafit]]
[[de:David (Israel)]]
[[el:Δαβίδ]]
[[es:David]]
[[eo:Davido]]
[[eu:David]]
[[fa:داوود]]
[[fr:David (Bible)]]
[[fur:Davide]]
[[ga:Dáiví]]
[[gl:David]]
[[hak:Thai-ví-vòng]]
[[ko:다윗]]
[[hi:दाउद]]
[[hr:Kralj David]]
[[id:Daud]]
[[it:Davide]]
[[he:דוד]]
[[ka:დავითი]]
[[sw:Daudi (Biblia)]]
[[ku:Dawid]]
[[lbe:Давуд идавс]]
[[la:David (rex)]]
[[lv:Karalis Dāvids]]
[[lt:Dovydas]]
[[hu:Dávid zsidó király]]
[[mk:Давид]]
[[ml:ദാവീദ്]]
[[nl:Koning David]]
[[ja:ダビデ]]
[[no:David av Israel]]
[[nn:David I av Israel]]
[[pl:Dawid (król Izraela)]]
[[pt:David]]
[[ro:David (Iuda)]]
[[ru:Давид]]
[[sco:David]]
[[sq:Mbreti David]]
[[simple:David]]
[[sk:Dávid (biblická postava)]]
[[so:Nabi Daa'uud C.S.]]
[[ckb:داوود]]
[[sr:Давид (краљ)]]
[[fi:Daavid]]
[[sv:Kung David]]
[[tl:David]]
[[ta:தாவீது அரசர்]]
[[th:เดวิด]]
[[tr:Davud]]
[[uk:Давид]]
[[vi:David]]
[[wo:Daawuda]]
[[yi:דוד המלך]]
[[zh:大衛]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
