<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="858993" ns="0" title="Dependency hell"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=September 2009}}
'''Dependency hell''' is a colloquial term for the frustration of some software users who have installed [[Software package (installation)|software packages]] which have [[dependency (computer science)|dependencies]] on specific [[Software versioning|version]]s of other software packages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dependency Hell&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| title = Urban Dictionary: Dependency Hell
| url = http://dependecy-hell.urbanup.com/680093
| publisher = www.urbandictionary.com
| date = 2004-05-24
| accessdate = 2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was mainly attributable to old [[Linux]] [[package manager]]s. Current package managers have largely solved this problem by automatically resolving and downloading dependencies.

== Overview ==
Often, rather than &quot;[[reinventing the wheel]]&quot;, software is designed to take advantage of other [[software component]]s that are already available, or have already been designed and implemented for use elsewhere. This could be compared to how people building a house might buy [[Commercial off-the-shelf|off-the-shelf]] components, such as bricks, windows, and doors, rather than producing ''everything'' themselves.

Even for a builder, it can be a problem if a building is designed for a certain door type, and only doors with different [[specifications]] are available. However, in the software world, where components evolve rapidly and depend significantly on one another, this problem becomes more pronounced.&lt;ref name=&quot;jamesdonald&quot;/&gt;

The issue of dependency hell may be regarded as an [[anti-pattern]], where the fault lies less with the suppliers of the products than with the framework into which they have to fit.

===Platform-specific===
On specific [[computing platform]]s, &quot;dependency hell&quot; often goes by a local specific name, generally the name of components.

* [[DLL hell]] - A form of dependency hell occurring on [[Microsoft Windows]].
* [[Extension conflict]] - A form of dependency hell occurring on older versions of [[Mac OS]]{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}.
* [[JAR hell]] - A form of dependency hell occurring in the [[Java Runtime Environment]].
* RPM hell - A form of dependency hell occurring in the [[Red Hat]] distribution of [[Linux]] and other distributions that use [[RPM Package Manager|RPM]] as a package manager.&lt;ref name=&quot;linuxcompa&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = Is Linux Annoying?
| last = Weinstein
| first = Paul
| url = http://linuxdevcenter.com/pub/a/linux/2003/09/11/linux_annoyances.html
| publisher = linuxdevcenter.com
| date = 2003-09-11
| accessdate = 2010-04-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Problems ==
Dependency hell takes several forms:

; many dependencies
: An application depends on many [[Library (computing)|libraries]], requiring lengthy downloads, large amounts of disk space, and not being very portable (all libraries must be ported for the application to be ported). It can also be difficult to locate all the dependencies, which can be fixed by having a repository (see below). This is partly inevitable; an application built on a given [[platform (computing)|platform]] (such as [[Java Platform|Java]]) requires that platform to be installed, but further applications do not require it. This is a particular problem if an application uses a small part of a big library (which can be solved by [[refactoring]]), or a simple application relies on many libraries.

; long chains of dependencies
: &lt;tt&gt;app&lt;/tt&gt; depends on &lt;tt&gt;liba&lt;/tt&gt;, which depends on &lt;tt&gt;libb&lt;/tt&gt;, ..., which depends on &lt;tt&gt;libz&lt;/tt&gt;. This is distinct from &quot;many dependencies&quot; if the dependencies must be resolved manually (e.g., on attempting to install &lt;tt&gt;app&lt;/tt&gt;, you are prompted to install &lt;tt&gt;liba&lt;/tt&gt; first. On attempting to install &lt;tt&gt;liba&lt;/tt&gt;, you are ''then'' prompted to install &lt;tt&gt;libb&lt;/tt&gt;.). Sometimes, however, during this long chain of dependencies conflicts arise, where two different versions of the same package are required&lt;ref name=&quot;Dependency-Carousel&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| title = It's Good Work When You Can Find It; The Dependency Carousel
| last = Stevens
| first = Al
| journal = J-DDJ
| volume =  26
| issue =  5
| pages =  121–124
| coden = DDJOEB
| issn = 1044-789X
| url = http://www.drdobbs.com/blog/archives/2008/12/its_good_work_w.html
| publisher = www.drdobbs.com/blog
| date = 2001-05-01
| accessdate = 2010-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see '''conflicting dependencies''' below). These long chains of dependencies can be solved by having a package manager that resolves all dependencies automatically. Other than being a hassle (to resolve all the dependencies manually), manual resolution can mask dependency cycles or conflicts.

; conflicting dependencies
: If &lt;tt&gt;app1&lt;/tt&gt; depends on &lt;tt&gt;libfoo 1.2&lt;/tt&gt;, and &lt;tt&gt;app2&lt;/tt&gt; depends on &lt;tt&gt;libfoo 1.3&lt;/tt&gt;, and different versions of &lt;tt&gt;libfoo&lt;/tt&gt; cannot be simultaneously installed, then &lt;tt&gt;app1&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;app2&lt;/tt&gt; cannot simultaneously be used (or installed, if the installer checks dependencies). When possible, this is solved by allowing simultaneous installations of the different dependencies. Alternatively, the existing dependency, along with all software that depends on it, must be uninstalled in order to install the new dependency. A problem on Linux systems with installing packages from a different distributor (which is not recommended or even supposed to work) is that the resulting long chain of dependencies may lead to a conflicting version of [[GNU C Library|glibc]], the single most important library. If this happens, the user will be prompted to uninstall thousands of packages.

; circular dependencies
: If &lt;tt&gt;appX, version 1&lt;/tt&gt; depends on &lt;tt&gt;app2&lt;/tt&gt;, which depends on &lt;tt&gt;app3&lt;/tt&gt;, which depends on &lt;tt&gt;app4&lt;/tt&gt;, which depends on the original &lt;tt&gt;appX, version 0&lt;/tt&gt;, then, in systems such as RPM or dpkg, the user must install all packages simultaneously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haiku-os.org/documents/dev/dependency_hell Dependency hell]&lt;/ref&gt; - hence on Linux circular dependencies are often the result of a user misunderstanding the packaging system.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}} On other platforms, however, the packaging system may not be able to resolve the circular dependency.

== Solutions ==

; Version Numbering
: The most obvious (and very common) solution to this problem is to have a standardised numbering system, wherein software uses a specific number for each version (aka ''[[Software versioning|major version]]''), and also a subnumber for each revision (aka ''[[minor version]]''), e.g.: '''10'''.1, or 5.'''7'''. The major version only changes when programs that used that version will no longer be compatible.  The minor version might change with even a simple revision that does not prevent other software from working with it. In cases like this, software packages can then simply request a component that has a particular major version, and ''any'' minor version (greater than or equal to a particular minor version). As such, they will continue to work, and dependencies will be resolved successfully, even if the minor version changes.

; Smart Package Management
: Some [[package manager]]s can perform smart upgrades, in which interdependent software components are upgraded at the same time, thereby resolving the major number incompatibility issue too.

: Many current [[Linux]] distributions have also implemented [[Digital library|repository]]-based package management systems to try to solve the dependency problem. These systems are a layer on top of the [[RPM Package Manager|RPM]], [[dpkg]], or other packaging systems that are designed to automatically resolve dependencies by searching in predefined software repositories. Typically these software repositories are [[file transfer protocol|FTP]] sites or websites, [[File directory|directories]] on the local computer or shared across a [[computer network|network]] or, much less commonly, directories on removable media such as CDs or DVDs. This eliminates dependency hell for software packaged in those repositories, which are typically maintained by the Linux distribution provider and [[mirror site|mirrored]] worldwide. Although these repositories are often huge it is not possible to have every piece of software in them, so dependency hell can still occur. In all cases, dependency hell is still faced by the repository maintainers. Examples of these systems include [[Advanced Packaging Tool|Apt]], [[Yellow Dog Updater Modified|Yum]], [[Urpmi]], [[ZYpp]], [[Portage (software)|Portage]], [[Pacman (package manager)|Pacman]] and others.

; Installer Options
: Because different pieces of software have different dependencies, it is possible to get into a [[Virtuous circle and vicious circle|vicious circle]] of dependency [[requirement]]s, or (possibly worse) an ever-expanding [[Tree structure|tree]] of requirements, as each new package demands several more be installed.  Systems such as Debian's [[Advanced Packaging Tool|APT]] can resolve this by presenting the user with a range of solutions, and allowing the user to accept or reject the solutions, as desired.

: The Haskell Compiler GHC is an example of a circular dependency. To compile it, you need GHC. It can be solved by downloading a binary version of GHC, and compiling the new version of GHC with this binary version. This is not uncommon; many large base-level projects such as gcc require self-compilation, but this is not a problem as all operating systems ship with binaries of these.

; [[Portable Applications]]
: An application that is coded to have all of its necessary components included, or is designed to keep all necessary files within its own directory, will not create a dependency problem.  Where possible, this is normally the preferred method{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}&lt;!-- This has serious security implications -- its the easy way ouy, and is thus in some sense preferred, but considered very bad practice from a update standpoint... --&gt;.

; Easy Adaptability in Programming
: If application software is designed in such a way that its programmers are able to easily adapt the interface layer that deals with the OS, window manager or desktop environment to new or changing standards, then the programmers would only have to monitor notifications from the environment creators or component library designers and quickly adjust their software with updates for their users, all with minimal effort and a lack of costly and time-consuming redesign.  This method would encourage programmers to pressure those upon whom they depend to maintain a reasonable notification process that is not onerous to anyone involved.

; [[Software appliances]]
: Another approach to avoiding dependency issues is to deploy applications as a [[software appliance]]. A software appliance encapsulates dependencies in a pre-integrated self-contained unit such that users no longer have to worry about resolving software dependencies. Instead the burden is shifted to developers of the software appliance.

; [[Portable applications]]
: An application (or version of an existing conventional application) that is completely self-contained and requires nothing to be already installed. These are often able to run independently of the system to which they are connected.

== Examples ==

One modern example of dependency hell on Microsoft Windows and Mac OS X is the [[Gecko Runtime Engine]], or GRE, used by [[Mozilla]] projects. Each product released from the Mozilla foundation includes its own version of the complete Gecko Runtime Engine, due to the volatile nature of the programming interfaces used. Thus, if a user installs [[Mozilla Thunderbird|Thunderbird]], [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]], and [[Mozilla Calendar#Sunbird|Sunbird]], there will be three copies of GRE on the machine. These may or may not be compatible, depending on when the GRE [[source tree]] was [[fork (software development)|forked]]. Some external projects like [[Epiphany (web browser)|Epiphany]] depend on specific versions of the [[Mozilla Suite]] to use GRE, and break if a different version is installed; while others such as [[Nvu]] bring their own copy of GRE. The duplication of the GRE is actually a work-around to the core problem of dependency hell.

By [[Static library|statically linking]] Gecko, the Mozilla developers avoid potential dependency hell for their binary packages, at the cost of increased disk and memory usage.
Hard disk&lt;!-- disk /=/ harddisc --&gt; space comes quite cheap these days, therefore increased disk usage in itself is less of a problem than it once was, but the amount of extra non-shareable memory used is still considerable. (Also note that limitations on backing store size are returning with the use of [[solid-state drive]]s for portable computers.) Tools that are statically linked, such as [[Bash (Unix shell)|bash]] or [[make (software)|make]], will never complain about a missing shared object when the [[C standard library|C library]] (glibc) is upgraded.
Both approaches have advantages and disadvantages.

Further, many modern Linux distributions avoid this particular dependency problem by compiling Firefox, Thunderbird, etc. as merely a front-end to the [[XULRunner]] package,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://developer.mozilla.org/en/XULRunner |publisher=mozilla foundation| title=XULRunner homepage}}&lt;/ref&gt; thereby necessitating only one copy of the runtime being installed.  Another solution that stops dependency hell is made possible because a distribution's software repository can keep all of the user's software in sync, unlike on Windows and the Mac OS.

== See also ==
* [[Coupling (computer science)|Coupling]] - Forms of dependency among software artifacts
* [[Configuration management]] - Techniques and tools for managing software versions
* [[Software appliance]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2|refs=&lt;ref name=&quot;jamesdonald&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
| last = Donald
| first = James
| title = Improved Portability  of Shared Libraries
| publisher = Princeton University
| date = 2003-01-25
| url = http://www.princeton.edu/~jdonald/research/shared_libraries/cs518_report.pdf
| accessdate = 2010-04-09}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.dependencywalker.com/ Dependency walker]
* [http://macdependency.googlecode.com/ MacDependency]
* [http://www.scons.org/doc/0.97/HTML/scons-user/x933.html Implicit dependency]
* [http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?ContextIndependence  Context independence]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dependency Hell}}
[[Category:Anti-patterns]]
[[Category:Package management systems]]
[[Category:Revision control systems]]
[[Category:Computer errors]]

[[hr:Dependencijski pakao]]
[[pl:Piekło zależności]]
[[pt:Inferno de dependências]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
