<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Characters in Resident Evil 4" to="List of Resident Evil characters" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="1449500" ns="0" title="List of Resident Evil characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Non-free|list|date=July 2011}}
{{Refimprove|list|date=December 2010}}
{{copy edit|list|date=November 2010}} &lt;!-- various grammar, remove when done --&gt;

This is a list of player and recurring characters that have appeared in the ''[[Resident Evil]]'' [[media franchise]], including both video games and films. &lt;!-- in alphabetical order in their sections --&gt;

== Main characters ==
=== Albert Wesker ===
{{Main|Albert Wesker}}

=== Chris Redfield ===
{{Main|Chris Redfield}}

=== Claire Redfield ===
{{Main|Claire Redfield}}

=== Jill Valentine ===
{{Main|Jill Valentine}}

=== Leon S. Kennedy ===
{{Main|Leon S. Kennedy}}

=== Rebecca Chambers ===
{{main|Rebecca Chambers (character)}}

==Other major characters==
=== Special Tactics And Rescue Service ===
The STARS is a special force in the Raccoon Police Department, introduced in the original ''Resident Evil'' and disbanded before the events of the sequel. Its key members included Albert Wesker, Barry Burton, Brad Vickers, Chris Redfield, Enrico Marini, Forest Speyer, Joseph Frost, Kenneth J. Sullivan, Rebecca Chambers and Richard Aiken.&lt;ref name=stars /&gt;

Besides Chris Redfield, Jill Valentine, Rebecca Chambers and Albert Wesker, three more STARS members are the series' major characters:

==== Barry Burton ====
{{Nihongo|Barry Burton|バリー・バートン|Barī Bāton}} is a middle-aged [[SWAT]]-veteran&lt;ref name=stars /&gt; member of STARS Alpha Team in charge of weapons' supply and maintaince. In the original ''Resident Evil'' game, he is a supporting character in Jill's story, appearing in Chris' story only during the opening cut scene. During the course of the game, it is revealed that he is blackmailed by Albert Wesker to do his bidding, threatening that Umbrella will harm his family if he refuses to carry out a task. He returns in ''[[Resident Evil 3]]'', helping Jill and Carlos escape from Raccoon City before its destruction. Barry also appears in the uncanonical game ''[[Resident Evil Gaiden]]'' as one of its two player characters and is one of the playable characters added in the ''[[Resident Evil 5]]'' downloadable content in the Mercenaries Reunion mode. Barry is voiced by [[Barry Gjerde]] in the first game, by Ed Smaron in its remake, and by [[Jamieson Price]] in ''RE5''. He is also set to appear in the fifth live-action film, ''[[Resident Evil: Retribution]]'', played by [[Kevin Durand]].

==== Brad Vickers ====
{{Nihongo|Brad Vickers|ブラッド・ヴィッカーズ|Buraddo Vikkāzu}} is STARS' helicopter pilot and Alpha team's computer and information expert, nicknamed &quot;Chickenheart&quot;.&lt;ref name=stars&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071026022921/http://www.gamespot.com/gamespot/features/video/res_evil/p19.html STARS Members - GameSpot.com]&lt;/ref&gt; He leaves his teammates stranded in the forest during the opening of the first ''Resident Evil'' after panicking, but returns at the end of the game to save the survivors (Jill, Chris, Barry, and Rebecca). In ''Resident Evil 3'', despite trying to avoid any further involvement in the events surrounding Umbrella, Brad is targeted by the Nemesis, and eventually killed. He can be seen as a zombie in front of the police department in ''[[Resident Evil 2]]'' if the player meets certain goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resident Evil Archives |last=Capcom Staff |authorlink=Capcom |year=2005 |publisher=[[BradyGames]]/[[Capcom]] |isbn=0744006554 |page=136}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brad is voiced by Adam Paul in the first game's remake and by [[Johnny Yong Bosch]] in ''[[Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles]]''.

====Richard Aiken====
{{Nihongo|Richard Aiken|リチャード・エイケン}} is the STARS' radio communications specialist&lt;ref name=stars /&gt; and one of the Bravo Team members involved in the Spencer Mansion Incident. In the original ''Resident Evil'' game, he is found on the east wing of the Mansion's second floor, severely wounded and poisoned by a giant snake. After a brief detour to collect antivenom, Richard dies, either after imparting information and a radio (if the player returns quickly), or prior to their return. In the remake version, whilst playing as Jill, Richard (voiced by [[Joe Whyte]]) will accompany the player into the fight with Yawn, sacrificing himself to push her away from a lethal attack, and being ingested by the snake. Whilst playing as Chris, Richard will be killed during the encounter with the shark-based Neptune monster. In the novel ''The Umbrella Conspiracy'', Richard is found by Chris and Rebecca already dead from the poison. In ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles'', Richard is a companion of Rebecca and is voiced by [[Yuri Lowenthal]]. He is one of the playable characters in the multiplayer mode of ''[[Resident Evil: Deadly Silence]]''.

===Umbrella Corporation===
[[File:Umbrella Corporation logo.svg|thumb|The Umbrella Corporation [[logo]]]]

The Umbrella Corporation is a fictional [[bioengineering]] [[pharmaceutical company]] in the ''Resident Evil'' universe, that serves as one of main antagonists in the series. It is portrayed in the games as a major [[international]] player in a number of markets including [[pharmaceuticals]], medical hardware, [[defense industry|defense]], and [[computers]] along with more [[clandestine operations]] utilizing [[genetic engineering]] and accused viral weaponry. The company is also presented as having a more public face, producing [[cosmetics]], [[consumer products]] and foods. One of Umbrella's subsidiaries is UBCS (Umbrella Biohazard Countermeasure Service), a [[private military contractor]] with a highly trained security force capable of rescue and reconnaissance paramilitary operations. (The corporation also uses its top-secret special forces group to secure and protect its assets and high profile employees.) Umbrella established multiple secret research facilities to develop various bio-weapons. The most prominent research facility is located in the Arklay Mountains, just outside of Raccoon City, and scientists in this facility were able to develop the “T-virus”, a powerful mutagen that could dramatically alter living and recently-died organisms. The virus leaks and contaminates most of the Arklay Facility and its surrounding area, setting the stage for the original ''Resident Evil'' game.

==== Alexia Ashford ====
{{Nihongo|Alexia Ashford|アレクシア・アシュフォード}} is the primary antagonist of ''[[Resident Evil Code: Veronica]]''. Along with her twin brother, Alfred, she is the product of an experiment by her father, the Umbrella's chief senior researcher Alexander (the son of the corporation's deceased co-founder Edward Ashford; he was later himself turned by Alexia into an undead monster called Nosferatu), in which the genetic material of ancestor Veronica Ashford was inserted into an embryo and implanted in a surrogate mother in an attempt to reproduce Veronica's legendary intelligence and beauty. Having successfully inherited these traits, Alexia sought to become an unstoppable world dictator by injecting herself with the T-Veronica Virus and freezing herself for several years in order to retain her own personality and allow her body to control the virus, rather than vice-versa. She awakes during the events of ''Code Veronica'', but is destroyed at the hands of Chris Redfield before she can enact her takeover.

In 2009, [[IGN]] called her the series' &quot;most fearsome villain&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.stars.ign.com/articles/957/957628p6.html Resident Evil: The Many Looks of the Infected (6)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Carlos Oliviera ====
{{Nihongo|Carlos Oliviera|カルロス・オリヴェイラ|Karurosu Orivera}} is a Native American,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071026022925/http://www.gamespot.com/gamespot/features/video/res_evil/p20.html The Umbrella Personnel - GameSpot.com]&lt;/ref&gt; originally a member of a South American anti-government guerrilla group. After government forces wiped out his former organization, Carlos was scouted out by the Umbrella Corporation to join the Umbrella's UBCS. He joined the force and was assigned to Delta Platoon, Company A, along with Nicholai Ginovaef and Mikhail Victor. Despite his violent background, he is warm-hearted and known for joking around.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=DaMa |url=http://www.rehorror.net/thirdeye06/reuc_files.php |title=Resident Evil Horror /&amp;nbsp;– Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles |publisher=Rehorror.net |date= |accessdate=2010-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Resident Evil 3'', Carlos assists Jill Valentine throughout the game as the two of them attempt to escape Raccoon City. At one point Jill becomes infected by the T-virus after a battle with the Nemesis. At this point Carlos becomes playable so that the player can prepare a vaccine for Jill. Ultimately he is successful in escaping the city along with Jill. He reprises his role in ''The Umbrella Chronicles''. The events of ''Resident Evil 3'' are revisited in ''The Umbrella Chronicles'' scenario &quot;Raccoon's Destruction&quot;, in which Carlos is a playable character alongside Jill Valentine. Carlos is voiced by [[Vincent Corazza]] in ''Resident Evil 3'' and by [[Kim Strauss]] in ''The Umbrella Chronicles'' and personified by [[Oded Fehr]] in the films ''[[Resident Evil: Apocalypse]]'', ''[[Resident Evil: Extinction]]'' and ''[[Resident Evil: Retribution]]''. In the live action films, his name is spelled ''Olivera''.

==== Hunk ====
{{Nihongo|Hunk|ハンク|Hanku}} is a member of the Umbrella Security Service Unit in ''Resident Evil 2'',&lt;ref name=&quot;profile&quot;/&gt; also known as &quot;Mr. Death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 3: Nemesis]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=1999-09-22 |platform=[[PlayStation]] |isolang= |quote=Epilogue: &quot;&quot;Once again, only you survived, Mr. Death,&quot; the chopper pilot speaks with a cold bitterness.”Always, only you, survive, Mr. Death,&quot; the pilot continues. But Hunk does not respond to the pilot. He doesn't care. “The Death cannot die...,&quot; the survivor thinks to himself with a warm smile.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hunk appears in a secret minigame entitled &quot;4th Survivor&quot;. This short scenario entails Hunk's journey to escape Raccoon City, beginning with his awakening in the sewers and eventually leading to his extraction from the city. He is the only member of his unit to survive the attack of the mutated William Birkin that takes place shortly after his team-mates have secured samples of the G-virus for Umbrella.&lt;ref name=&quot;profile&quot;&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles]] |developer=[[Capcom]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2007-11-13 |platform=Wii |version= |level= Fourth Survivor |isolang= |quote='HUNK Profile (Archive): &quot;He has carried out a large number of successful operations, many of which he was the only one to return alive from, earning HUNK the nickname &quot;Grim Reaper.&quot; He is a member of Umbrella Special Forces and was the operative that single-handedly retrieved the G-virus despite the rest of his unit being wiped out by the G creature that used to be William Birkin.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; He reappears in ''The Umbrella Chronicles'', in a remake of the &quot;4th Survivor&quot; scenario where the player must reach the [[helipad]] for extraction from Raccoon City, and during the &quot;Memories of a Lost City&quot; scenario in ''[[Resident Evil: The Darkside Chronicles]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Waples, &quot;Hunk&quot; and &quot;HUNK Profile,&quot; ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles Prima Official Game Guide'' (Roseville: Prima Games, 2007), 21, 128.&lt;/ref&gt; Hunk is playable in the &quot;Mercenaries&quot; minigame in ''[[Resident Evil 4]]'', but has no relation to the story.

==== James Marcus ====
{{Nihongo|James Marcus|ジェームス・マーカス|Jēmusu Mākasu}} is the primary antagonist in ''[[Resident Evil Zero]]''. Years before the events of the first ''Resident Evil'', Marcus, along with Ozwell E. Spencer, was one of the founders of the Umbrella Corporation. In his personal journal, Marcus notes that he played an integral role in developing the T-Virus through extensive research with [[leeches]]; however, Spencer betrays Marcus by sending his subordinates, Albert Wesker and William Birkin, to murder Marcus and steal his research.&lt;ref name=&quot;James Marcus 2002&quot;/&gt; Approximately a decade later, Marcus rises from the dead with the aid of his leeches;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;James Marcus: &quot;However, something wondrous happened, it took the T-Virus inside of my queen years to procreate my new life.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil Zero'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), November 11, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; He exacts his vengeance upon Spencer by contaminating the Spencer Mansion, one of the Umbrella Corporation's secret research facilities, with the T-virus, which trigger the events of the first ''Resident Evil'' game.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Marcus plays a larger role in the prequel, ''Resident Evil Zero'', which details the accounts of his resurrection, vendetta, and ultimate downfall at the hands of Billy Coen and Rebecca Chambers. He also appears in ''The Umbrella Chronicles''.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Waples, &quot;James Marcus Profile,&quot; ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles Prima Official Game Guide'' (Roseville: Prima Games, 2007), 126.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mikhail Victor ====
{{Nihongo|Mikhail Victor|ミハイル・ヴィクトール|Mihairu Vikutōru}} (voiced by Ben Campbell) is the leader of the UBCS Delta platoon that both Nicholai and Carlos are part of. According to his backstory, Mikhail is from [[Saint Petersburg]], Russia. He originally served the [[Soviet Army]] before joining a guerilla force until he was eventually arrested by the Russian forces and convicted of acts of terrorism. He was then coerced into leading the UBCS in exchange for his men's freedom.&lt;ref name=rearchives&gt;''Resident Evil Archives'', 2005, Capcom&lt;/ref&gt; In the game, he first appears already wounded inside a cable car. Ultimately, he chose to sacrifice his own life to save Jill and Carlos. He dies when he is blown apart by his own grenade in a failed attempt to destroy the Nemesis. In an early draft of the story, Mikhail was originally scripted to be Nicholai's older brother (hence, his original name was Mikhail Ginovaef).&lt;ref name=rearchives/&gt; He is the only one of the main UBCS operatives not to appear in the film ''Resident Evil: Apocalypse'', being replaced by an original character named Yuri Loginova.

==== Nicholai Ginovaef ====
{{Nihongo|Nicholai Ginovaef|ニコライ・ジノビエフ|Nikorai Jinobiefu}} (voiced by Roger Honeywell) is a member of the UBCS Delta platoon, Company B. According to his back story, Nicholai is from [[Moscow]] and served in the Russian [[Spetsnaz]] before joining the UBCS. He also has an unspoken rivalry with Hunk from ''Resident Evil 2''. Nicholai meets Jill as one of the few surviving operatives from the Delta platoon, along with Carlos and Mikhail. He disappears after an event in the first half of the game and is presumed dead until another encounter with him. Nicholai is in fact one of the Supervisors, UBCS operatives assigned to watch and gather combat data as their comrades fight against Umbrella's bio-weapons. Nicholai's fate varies depending on which route the player takes. In one scene, he is slaughtered by the Nemesis and his corpse is left hanging in an air duct. Another possible outcome shows Nicholai stealing Jill's intended escape helicopter. At this point, the player has the option of attempting to negotiate with him, in which he escapes from the city successfully, or choose to fight back against Nicholai, destroying his chopper along with him. The English localization of ''[[Resident Evil Survivor]]'' features a document supposedly authored by Nicholai after the events of ''Nemesis''. The file is different in the original Japanese version and the Chinese localization of the PC port. The third entry of the document (the portion dated after the events of ''Nemesis'') was actually authored by the &quot;Umbrella B.O.W. Development Staff&quot;, rather than Nicholai.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://projectumbrella.net/articles/Report-Destruction-Raccoon-City |title=Report On The Destruction Of Raccoon City |publisher=Project Umbrella |date=1998-10-06 |accessdate=2010-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nicholai also appears in ''[[Resident Evil Outbreak]]'' in the final scenario &quot;Decisions, Decisions&quot; which depicts the character conducting another mission occurring during the same time period as the second half of ''Resident Evil 3''. He is mentioned in ''The Umbrella Chronicles'', where he is referred to by the codename &quot;Silver Fox&quot;. The character was adapted for the film ''Resident Evil: Apocalypse'' (in which he was played by [[Zack Ward]]), although the film features a more heroic depiction of Nicholai, which differs from the game's original antagonistic portrayal. The film's official novelization renamed him Nicholai Sokolov.

==== Ozwell E. Spencer ====
{{Nihongo|Ozwell E. Spencer|オズウェル・E・スペンサー|Ozuweru E Supensā}} is one of ''Resident Evil's'' most important and mysterious side characters. In the series, he is the owner and co-founder of the Umbrella Corporation, a [[pharmaceutical drug]] company that secretly manufactures bio-organic weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ash&quot;&gt;Alexander Ashford: &quot;My father, Edward, discovered the mother virus in cooperation with Lord Spencer, who was also a nobleman. They studied it for the purpose of military use.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil Code: Veronica'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), December 3, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ash&quot;/&gt; His colleagues, James Marcus and Edward Ashford, join his company, but show more interest in studying the newly discovered Progenitor virus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ash&quot;/&gt; Eventually, Edward Ashford dies, and Spencer seizes control of the company and its research by sending his subordinates, Albert Wesker and William Birkin, to assassinate Marcus.&lt;ref name=&quot;James Marcus 2002&quot;&gt;James Marcus: &quot;Ten years ago, Spencer had me assassinated.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil Zero'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), November 11, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Ashford: &quot;If nothing is done, Umbrella will be taken over by Spencer.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil Code: Veronica'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), December 3, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Spencer conducts some of his company’s research in the Arklay Research Facility, in the Arklay Mountains. He hires George Trevor, a famed architect to construct a mansion to conceal the facility.&lt;ref&gt;George Trevor: &quot;There are only two people that know the secret of this mansion, Sir Spencer and myself. If they kill me, Sir Spencer will be the only person that knows the secret.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil Remake'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), April 30, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; Spencer's plans progress smoothly, until Marcus returns from the dead,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; and begins to seek revenge with the help of his test subjects. Marcus destroys one of Spencer’s luxury trains, and causes a viral outbreak in the Arklay Research Facility.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;James Marcus: &quot;It was I who scattered the T-Virus in the mansion, needless to say I contaminated the train too.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil Zero'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), November 11, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; The outbreak spreads throughout the region, sparking the events of ''Resident Evil Zero'' and the original ''Resident Evil''. The virus subsequently spreads to Raccoon City during the events of ''Resident Evil 2'' and ''Resident Evil 3: Nemesis'', prompting the U.S. government to contain the outbreak by ordering the destruction of the city.&lt;ref&gt;Leon Kennedy: &quot;Not taking any chances, the President of the United States ordered a contingency plan&amp;nbsp;— to sterilize Raccoon City.&quot; Capcom, Resident Evil 4, Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), January 11, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; After the city's destruction, Spencer attempts to disguise the incident as a government conspiracy by hiring top lawyers and false witnesses. His actions prolong the legal proceedings, and allow the Umbrella Corporation to stay afloat for five more years. Ultimately, Wesker betrays Spencer by handing over secret documents to the U.S. government, and &lt;ref&gt;Albert Wesker: &quot;My dear Spencer. How the mighty have fallen. Your Umbrella has folded and now you are a fugitive in the same world you once sought to control. We shall meet again before the conclusion of this drama. Then you will learn of the history I will write for this world.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles'', Capcom, Nintendo Wii, (in English), November 30, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; seals Spencer's doom by personally testifying against him in court. Umbrella's business license is summarily suspended, and the U.S. government works swiftly to dismantle the remains of the organization.&lt;ref&gt;Leon Kennedy: &quot;With the whole affair gone public, the United States government issued an indefinite suspension of business decree to Umbrella. Soon its stock prices crashed and for all intents and purposes Umbrella was finished.&quot; Capcom, ''Resident Evil 4'', Capcom, Nintendo GameCube, (in English), January 11, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; After Umbrella's public fall from grace, Spencer retreats to his mansion in Europe. He is eventually located by Chris Redfield and Jill Valentine prior to the events of ''Resident Evil 5'', but is swiftly killed by Albert Wesker before the two can reach him.

==== Sergei Vladimir ====
{{Nihongo|Sergei Vladimir|セルゲイ・ウラジミール|Serugei Urajimīru}} is a Russian employee of Umbrella, its most loyal enforcer and the main antagonist of ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles''. Following the fall of the Soviet Union, he approached the Umbrella Corporation and quickly became one of the company's top officers. He became personally acquainted with Umbrella founder Ozwell E. Spencer, who began to rely on Sergei as a loyal and effective enforcer. Sergei subsequently formed and led Umbrella's UBCS,&lt;ref&gt;Famitsu Magazine, Week 2 September 2007 Issue&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Umbrella's internal espionage organization, Monitor. Agents that answered directly to Sergei include the likes of Nicholai Ginovaef. Sergei undertakes the Umbrella Corporation's most important tasks through the ''Resident Evil'' series, including stealing the Red Queen from the Arklay Research Facility, extracting Ozwell Spencer from Raccoon City before its destruction, and securing important research information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=DaMa |url=http://www.rehorror.net/thirdeye06/reuc_characters.php |title=Resident Evil Horror /&amp;nbsp;– Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles |publisher=Rehorror.net |date= |accessdate=2010-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sergei is killed by Albert Wesker while attempting to prevent him from stealing a database containing the Umbrella Corporations most important documents and research data.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Waples, &quot;Sergei Vladimir Profile,&quot; ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles Prima Official Game Guide'' (Roseville: Prima Games, 2007), 127.&lt;/ref&gt; Sergei was voiced by [[Patrick Seitz]].

==== William Birkin ====
{{Nihongo|William Birkin|ウィリアム・バーキン|Wiriamu Bākin}} makes his debut as the main antagonist of ''Resident Evil 2''. After completing his G-virus project, he is mortally wounded by agents of the Umbrella Special Forces and his work is stolen. Left for dead, he injects himself with the G-virus, thus turning himself into a monster, he then kills his attackers, causing a T-virus vial to be leaked into the city's drainage system, resulting in the zombie outbreak in the game. During the course of the game, he encounters the main characters: Leon S. Kennedy and Claire Redfield, as he undergoes gradual mutation and begins losing any semblance of his original human form. He is eventually defeated by Leon and Claire, with the help of his daughter Sherry. Birkin is mentioned in ''Wesker's Report'' as the scientist who helped Wesker fake his death and is retroactively mentioned in the GameCube remake of the first ''Resident Evil''. He also makes an appearance in ''Resident Evil Zero'', where he assists Wesker from behind the scenes, and also appears in a cutscene in ''The Umbrella Chronicles'' along with Albert Wesker.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Waples, &quot;William Birkin's Profile,&quot; ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles Prima Official Game Guide'' (Roseville: Prima Games, 2007), 127.&lt;/ref&gt; In the first ''Resident Evil'' film, Birkin makes an uncredited [[cameo appearance]] as the head of the Nemesis project and is portrayed by actor [[Jason Isaacs]], who was also the film's narrator. According to a [[Audio commentary|commentary]] by [[Paul W.S. Anderson]], Isaacs was planned to reprise this role in the sequel ''Resident Evil: Apocalypse'', but left the project for undisclosed reasons; an original character named Dr. Sam Isaacs (played by [[Iain Glen]]) was created to fulfill Birkin's role in the sequel.

=== Other characters === 
==== Ada Wong ====
{{Main|Ada Wong}}

==== Ashley Graham ====
{{Nihongo|Ashley Graham|アシュリー・グラハム|Ashurī Gurahamu}} is the new U.S. President's daughter in ''Resident Evil 4''.&lt;ref&gt;Dan Birlew, &quot;ashley graham&quot;, ''Resident Evil 4: Bradygames Signature Series Guide'' (Indianapolis: Pearson Education, 2006), 6.&lt;/ref&gt; A college student living in [[Massachusetts]], Ashley is abducted by a mysterious cult while attempting to return home.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graham&quot;/&gt; She is taken to an undisclosed part of [[Europe]] and held captive in a village inhabited by humans infected by mind-controlling parasites. The cult's leader, Osmund Saddler, plans to infect her with Las Plagas, to carry out the cult's secret agenda.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mission&quot;&gt;{{cite video game|title=Resident Evil 4 |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Our Mission (File): &quot;We must influence the minds of the people who advise the President. After this is done, the rest of the departments will quickly fall under our sway..&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is rescued by Kennedy, and works alongside him to thwart the cult's plans and escape. In addition to being able to receive commands and perform simple tasks, Ashley briefly becomes a playable character for a portion of the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot; /&gt; Her character was voiced by [[Carolyn Lawrence]],&lt;ref name=&quot;credits&quot; /&gt; who described her character as &quot;vulnerable, because Leon has to come to her rescue all the time.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cary&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=Chris | last=Carle | coauthors= | title=Babe Interview: Carolyn Lawrence | date=2005-08-02 | publisher=IGN | url =http://stars.ign.com/articles/663/663669p1.html | work = | pages =2–3 | accessdate = 2008-06-04 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[GameDaily]] listed Ashley Graham as part of its &quot;Babe of the Week: Hottest Blondes&quot; feature, adding that they would give her the &quot;pain in the neck&quot; award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=January 16, 2009 | By: Robert Workman | More |url=http://www.gamedaily.com/articles/galleries/babe-of-the-week-hottest-blondes/?page=6 |title=Gallery and Images |publisher=GameDaily |date=2009-01-16 |accessdate=2010-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, [[Cracked (magazine)|Cracked]] listed her as one of the 15 most annoying video game characters, commenting that developers need to realize that no one likes to defend the weak and defenseless in video games,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Swaim |first=Michael |url=http://www.cracked.com/article_15902_15-most-annoying-video-game-characters-from-otherwise-great-games.html |title=The 15 Most Annoying Video Game Characters (From Otherwise Great Games) |publisher=Cracked.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; while [[GamesRadar]] used her as an example of the &quot;pure-hearted love interest&quot;, stating that this kind of character lacks personality,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/the-top-7-lazy-character-clichs/a-2008072111311385086/p-2 |title=The Top 7... Lazy Character Clichés |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2010-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also listed her as one of the top seven most irritating video game characters, stating that while she is not completely useless, she is not very resourceful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/the-top-7-irritating-female-characters/a-20080728104413532023 |title=The Top 7... Irritating female characters |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2010-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Billy Coen ====
{{Nihongo|Billy Coen|ビリー・コーエン|Birī Kōen}} is first mentioned in a police report filed by Rebecca Chambers in the [[Nintendo 64]] version of ''Resident Evil 2'', foreshadowing the events of the then-unreleased prequel.&lt;ref&gt;IGN Staff (2000-09-07). [http://cube.ign.com/articles/084/084568p1.html N64: 0&amp;nbsp;– Cube: RE0]. [[IGN]]. Retrieved on 2009-01-02&lt;/ref&gt; A former Second Lieutenant in the [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marine Corps]], Billy is sentenced to death by a military court for killing 23 civilians but manages to escape on route to his execution. He seeks refuge in the Ecliptic Express, a stranded train, where he meets Rebecca Chambers. The two form an alliance in order to survive, using their talents to discover the Umbrella Corporation’s secrets.&lt;ref name=&quot;re0&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=Matt | last=Salee | coauthors= | title=Guides: Resident Evil Zero (GCN) | year=2002 | publisher=IGN | url =http://guides.ign.com/guides/15353/index.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-05-23 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both characters are monitored by James Marcus, who sends various creatures to subdue them. After revealing the details of his demise, Marcus mutates into the Queen Leech.&lt;ref name=&quot;re0&quot; /&gt; In the final battle sequence, Billy and Rebecca destroy the Queen Leech by exploiting its vulnerability to sunlight. Rebecca allows Billy to escape, telling the authorities that he subsequently perished in the Arklay Mountains after their encounter. Billy also appears in '' The Umbrella Chronicles''.&lt;ref name=&quot;re0&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last =Giancarlo | first =Varanini | author-link = | title =Evil to the Core | newspaper = [[Nintendo Power]] | pages = 33–38 | date = 2007-05-22 | url = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Jack Krauser ====
[[File:Jack-krauser-57542.jpg|thumb|Krauser in ''[[Resident Evil 4]]'']]

{{Nihongo|Jack Krauser|ジャック・クラウザー|Jakku Kurauzā}} is a mercenary hired to do Saddler's bidding.&lt;ref&gt;Dan Birlew, &quot;jack krauser&quot;, ''Resident Evil 4: Bradygames Signature Series Guide'' (Indianapolis: Pearson Education, 2006), 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally a U.S. government operative, Krauser was friends with Leon Kennedy, before apparently perishing in a helicopter crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Jack Krauser: &quot;I died in a crash, two years ago. Is that what they told you?&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Krauser is responsible for kidnapping Ashley, claiming he committed the act to gain Saddler's trust. He has little interest in Saddler's agenda, and only seeks to recover a sample of Las Plagas for Albert Wesker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Leon Kennedy: &quot;What do you want?&quot; Jack Krauser: &quot;Hmph. The sample Saddler developed, that's all.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Jack Krauser: &quot;Just so we understand each other clearly, I don't trust you. Nor does Wesker. If you try to do anything clever, I will kill you.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Leon Kennedy: &quot;You got her involved just for that?!&quot; Jack Krauser: &quot;All for Umbrella's sake.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to being a skilled knife fighter and archer, Krauser possesses superhuman speed, stamina, strength, and gained the ability to transform his left arm into a giant mutated claw.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot; /&gt; He confronts Kennedy twice in the game. After apparently dying during a fight with Kennedy, Krauser appears as a boss in the &quot;Assignment: Ada&quot; scenario, and is killed once and for all by Ada in the &quot;Separate Ways&quot; scenario.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sepway&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=ign.com | last=&quot;Nix&quot; | coauthors= | title=Resident Evil 4: Separate Ways | date=2005-09-26 | publisher=IGN | url =http://ps2.ign.com/articles/653/653900p1.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Krauser is playable in Mercenaries mode. He uses his bow in combat and can also utilize his mutated arm as a melée weapon. ''The Darkside Chronicles'' provides backstory for Krauser as he is partnered with Leon to arrest a drug lord in South America. During their journey they discover the village has suffered an outbreak of the T-virus,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Kevin | last=Glifford | coauthors= |authorlink= | title=Leon and Krauser Reunite in RE: Darkside Chronicles | date=2009-09-09 | publisher=[[1UP.com]] | url =http://www.1up.com/do/newsStory?cId=3175960 | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2009-09-10 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; discover Manuela Hidalgo, who has been infected with the T-Veronica virus, and learn of Wesker and Umbrella's conspiracy. Before defeating the mutated drug lord, Krauser's arm is severely injured, infecting him with T-Veronica, and he is forced to leave the military. Having learned about Wesker, and wanting a new job, he becomes interested in what kind of power he can attain with Wesker's help. Krauser's character was voiced by [[Jim Ward (voice actor)|Jim Ward]].&lt;ref name=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Game Credits for Resident Evil 4 | year=2005 | publisher=[[Moby Games]] | url =http://www.mobygames.com/game/gamecube/resident-evil-4/credits | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-07-10 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Lisa Trevor ====
{{Nihongo|Lisa Trevor|リサ・トレヴァー|Risa Torevā}} is a character and enemy in the remake of ''Resident Evil'' and ''The Umbrella Chronicles''.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Waples, &quot;The Infected: Lisa Trevor,&quot; ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles Prima's Official Game Guide'' (Roseville: Random House, Inc., 2007), 27.&lt;/ref&gt; She is the daughter of George Trevor, a famed architect who designed the Arklay Research Facility. After George discovers that the mansion is actually hosting a secret underground laboratory, Spencer kidnaps him and his family. While his henchmen kill off George, his wife and daughter are used as test subjects for the Umbrella Corporation's viral experiments. Lisa spent nearly 30 years in captivity, undergoing several horrific experiments that rob her of her humanity. She develops uncanny abilities that make her stronger, and in essence, immortal. Lisa also proves to be the key in the development of Birkin's G-virus, as she becomes the first living specimens to successfully adapt and absorb it. Lisa loses her mind during this period, and becomes obsessed with finding her mother, who was killed years before. Wesker, then one of Umbrella's top research scientists, orders his personnel to dispose of Lisa; however, she survives her execution, and wanders the mansion's grounds in hopes of finding her mother. Finally she was able to find the skull of her mother. Nearly a decade later, Lisa encounters various STARS members, before finding Wesker in the mansion. Wesker escapes the mansion's self-destruction, where Lisa is killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Schedeen |first=Jesse |url=http://uk.stars.ign.com/articles/961/961553p1.html |title=Best Resident Evil Bosses&amp;nbsp;— Stars Feature at IGN |publisher=Uk.stars.ign.com |date=2009-03-11 |accessdate=2010-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Luis Sera ====
{{Nihongo|Luis Sera|ルイス・セラ|Ruisu Sera}} is a Spanish investigator, who is attempting to assist Kennedy and Wong in their efforts against Los Illuminados.&lt;ref&gt;Dan Birlew, &quot;luis sera&quot;, ''Resident Evil 4: Bradygames Signature Series Guide'' (Indianapolis: Pearson Education, 2006), 7.&lt;/ref&gt; He is extremely familiar with the village where the game is set and formerly worked with Osmund Saddler to research and develop the cult's mind-controlling parasites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Sera and the Third Party (File): &quot;The whereabouts of Sera are still unknown. Most likely he's using an old secret passage taught to him by his grandfather, who used to hunt in this region long ago. I'm pretty certain that he's hiding our property somewhere in the forest.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; After realizing Saddler intends to use the parasites for malicious purposes, he begins to attempt to sabotage the cult's mission. Sera meets Kennedy after both men are captured by villagers.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot; /&gt; He introduces himself as a former policeman from [[Madrid, Spain|Madrid]], who became dissatisfied with his job.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Luis Sera: &quot;I used to be a cop in Madrid. Now I'm just a good-for-nothing guy, who happens to be quite the ladies' man. Policía... you put your life on the line, no one really appreciates you enough for it. Being a hero isn't what it's cracked up to be anymore...&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is later revealed in the game that Sera was one of the top researchers in finding Las Plagas. He considered the outbreak to be his fault and started trying his utmost to eliminate this. Sera continues to assist Kennedy, but is ultimately killed by Saddler before he can present him with a sample of Las Plagas.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Capture Luis Sera (File): &quot;It appears he took some vaccines when he stole our &quot;sample&quot;. The vaccines we can do without, but we must retrieve the &quot;sample&quot; for it is our life blood.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; His character was voiced by [[Rino Romano]].

==== Osmund Saddler ====
{{Nihongo|Osmund Saddler|オズムンド・サドラー|Ozumundo Sadorā}} (voiced by [[Michael Gough (voice actor)|Michael Gough]]) is the primary antagonist in ''Resident Evil 4''.&lt;ref&gt;Dan Birlew, &quot;osmund saddler&quot;, ''Resident Evil 4: Bradygames Signature Series Guide'' (Indianapolis: Pearson Education, 2006), 11.&lt;/ref&gt; He is the leader of Los Illuminados, the cult responsible for Ashley Graham's kidnapping.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graham&quot;&gt;{{cite video game|title=[[Resident Evil 4]] |developer=[[Capcom|Capcom Production Studio 4]] |publisher=Capcom |date=2005-10-25 |platform=[[PlayStation 2]] |quote=Leon Kennedy: &quot;It was right before I was to take on my duties of protecting the President's daughter when she was abducted. That's the ultimate reason I'm in this lonely and rural part of Europe.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Saddler plans on infecting Graham with a sample of Las Plagas, in hope that she will return home and infect higher ranking members of the U.S. government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mission&quot;/&gt; Saddler then wishes to control them and seize control of the country, and then the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mission&quot;/&gt; He uses samples of Las Plagas to infect and control villagers and even a local [[castellan]] Ramon Salazar (ラモン・サラザール) to perform his bidding. However, his plans are foiled by the combined efforts of Kennedy, Wong and Luis Sera. Kennedy, with the assistance of Wong, kills Saddler near the game's conclusion, and destroys his research and production complex.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamespot&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=Matthew | last=Rorie | coauthors= | title=Resident Evil 4&amp;nbsp;– Gamespot Game Guide | year=2004 | publisher=[[Gamespot]] | url =http://www.gamespot.com/features/6116796/index.html?tag=gameguide;title;1 | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-05-14 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Sherry Birkin ====
Sherry Birkin is the daughter of William and Annette Birkin. She appears in ''Resident Evil 2'', and runs through the Raccoon City after the outbreak. Sherry manages to find Leon and Claire, who protect her while trying to escape the city. Sherry is a player character in some part of the game, but she is completely unarmed and can only avoid the monsters. Her father has been transformed into a monstrous creature by the G-virus and infects his daughter, but Claire gives her an anti-virus, which prevents her from mutating. Sherry assists Leon and Claire in boarding a secret underground train, and successfully escapes Raccoon City before it is destroyed. Sherry also appears in ''Resident Evil: The Darkside Chronicles'' in chapters that recapitulate the events of the ''Resident Evil 2''.

==== Sheva Alomar ====
{{main|Sheva Alomar}}

==== Steve Burnside ====
{{Nihongo|Steve Burnside|スティーブ・バーンサイド|Sutību Bānsaido}} (voiced by Bill Houston, [[Sam Riegel]] in ''The Darkside Chronicles'') is [[Claire Redfield]]'s partner in the game ''[[Resident Evil Code: Veronica]]''. Steve was imprisoned in the Rockfort Island's facility alongside his father, a former Umbrella employee. He escapes from his cell during the viral outbreak. At first, Steve is hesitant to trust Claire and only cooperates with her reluctantly, but later becomes more open and attached to her after he is forced to kill his own father, who has become a zombie during the outbreak. Steve and Claire eventually end up in Umbrella's Antarctic Facility, where he is captured by Alexia and used as a test subject for the T-Veronica virus. Claire meets a chained Steve, who mutates into a monster and attacks Claire; in this form, he is nearly invulnerable to damage, and wields a giant, ceremonial axe. While running from Steve, Claire is attacked by one of Alexia's tentacles. Steve, seeing this, regains control of his mind and cuts the tentacle apart, freeing Claire. In retaliation, Alexia strikes him with one of the tentacles, inflicting a mortal wound. His failing body finally rejects the mutation, and he changes back. He dies in Claire's arms, just after professing his love to her. He was later taken by Albert Wesker due to the T-Veronica virus in his body, and also hinted that he might come back to life. In ''The Darkside Chronicles'' it is revealed that Wesker contacted the drug baron Javier Hidalgo and took a sample of T-Veronica from Steve's corpse in order to sell the virus for Hidalgo's ailing daughter, Manuela. 

== Characters created for the film series ==
=== Alice ===
{{Main|Alice (Resident Evil)}}
[[Alice (Resident Evil)|Alice]] or &quot;Project Alice&quot; (played by [[Milla Jovovich]]) is the main protagonist of the ''Resident Evil'' film series. Originally an agent of the Umbrella Corporation tasked with guarding the entrance to the Hive in Raccoon City, she turned against them after the T-virus was let loose by the greed of her partner. Upon her return from the Hive, she was injected with the virus, and as the only known human being she bonded successfully with it. The virus enhanced her physical and mental capabilities - strength, speed, agility, and for a time [[Telekinesis|telekinetic]] abilities - to superhuman levels. As a result, she has become both the ultimate enemy of Umbrella and the means of salvation to the world.

=== K-Mart ===
K-Mart (played by [[Spencer Locke]]) is a young woman in Claire Redfield's convoy. In ''Resident Evil: Extinction'', K-Mart explains that she changed her name after Claire and the others had found her in a [[Kmart]] store. She states she did not like her name and decided to change it because all those she knew from before the outbreak were dead. In the novel, her name is revealed, by Carlos and confirmed by K-Mart, to be Dahlia. During the events of the film, K-Mart is shown riding in the vehicle with Claire, whom Locke says she has a big sister relationship with. K-Mart is also close with Carlos Olivera (in the novelization and in the film's deleted scene, it is stated she has a crush on him) and Mikey as she is clearly distraught at both of their deaths. K-Mart bonds with Alice as well, giving her a bracelet and in the beginning of the film, explaining her name. Locke describes this as more of a mother-daughter relationship and that K-Mart &quot;definitely look[s] up to Alice in this movie a lot.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Resident Evil: Extinction&amp;nbsp;– Spencer Locke Interview| publisher= horror.com| url= http://www.horror.com/php/article-1711-1.html | accessdate= 2007-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; K-Mart survives through most of the film by hiding in the vehicles, although she does kill a few zombies. In a zombie attack, she is nearly killed by L.J. who has turned into a zombie himself, but is saved by Carlos. At the end, she is one of the few who survive long enough to depart in a helicopter piloted by Claire on the way to Alaska. In ''[[Resident Evil: Afterlife]]'', K-Mart has been captured by the Umbrella Corporation as part of its ''Arcadia'' trap where she has been captured to be experimented upon. She is rescued by Alice, Claire and Chris Redfield, but is at first too out of it to do anything. After recovering, she aids Alice in battle, knocking out Bennett and tossing Alice her shotgun, allowing Alice to (temporarily) defeat Wesker with a shot to the head. K-Mart later stands on deck with the other survivors and watches as the Umbrella Corporation choppers appear.

=== Red Queen and White Queen ===
[[Image:Red Queen.jpg|thumb|The Red Queen in ''[[Resident Evil (film)|Resident Evil]]'']]
[[File:White Queen (Resident Evil film).jpg|thumb|The White Queen in ''[[Resident Evil: Extinction]]'']]

The Red Queen (played by [[Michaela Dicker]]) and White Queen (played by [[Madeline Carroll]]) are characters of the ''Resident Evil'' film series. They are both state-of-the-art [[holographic]] representations of [[artificial intelligence]] [[supercomputer]]s serving to protect different facilities of the Umbrella Corporation. Both AI names are referencing major characters from the novel ''[[Through the Looking-Glass]]'', with the decidedly more deadly Hive AI representing the antagonistic Red Queen,&lt;ref&gt;Rikke Schubart, ''Super bitches and action babes: the female hero in popular cinema, 1970-2006'' (McFarland &amp; Co., 2007), 340.&lt;/ref&gt; and the more helpful AI that appears in ''Resident Evil: Extinction'' representing the protagonistic White Queen. 

The Red Queen was created by the director Paul W. S. Anderson as an [[homage]] to ''[[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001: A Space Odyssey]]'''s [[HAL 9000]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Red Queen&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title= Resident Evil| publisher= [[Rotten Tomatoes]]| url=http://au.rottentomatoes.com/m/resident_evil/about.php| accessdate= 2007-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Red Queen's name itself is a reference to the [[Red Queen's Hypothesis|Red Queen principle]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Principal&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title= &quot;I could kiss you, you bitch.&quot; Michaela Breana Anderson is awesome she is keen to her! :D Race, gender and sexuality in Resident Evil and Resident Evil 2: Apocalypse| publisher= Ejumpcut.org| url= http://www.ejumpcut.org/currentissue/HarperResEvil/index.html| accessdate= 2008-01-01|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071210105143/http://www.ejumpcut.org/currentissue/HarperResEvil/index.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; while her holographic [[Avatar (computing)|avatar]] was modeled after Angela Ashford, daughter of Dr. Charles Ashford, the head programmer. She was designed to monitor the underground Hive laboratory complex, her system also expanding through the Spencer Mansion. In the film, the Red Queen activated her primary and secondary defenses when she detected a sudden leak of the T-virus, responding by sealing the Hive entrances and locking in all of the Umbrella researchers, then eradicating them, and releasing a gas in the mansion above that leaves Alice unconscious and without memory. When a U.B.C.S. commando team sent by Umbrella arrives at the Hive to investigate, the Red Queen detects their approach and her defense systems go online once again, killing most of the team members. Alice and the survivors disable her main [[circuit breaker]]s in order to prevent her from [[Booting|rebooting]]. After being threatened by the team, the Red Queen is forced to show the team a way out of the Hive. The Red Queen isn't heard from again until later in the film, when the only remaining survivors are trapped in a locked laboratory and she demands the infected Rain to be killed. The Red Queen is then permanently disabled by Kaplan when she refuses to open the door and let them out; the lines that the Red Queen spoke when Kaplan tried to disable her were played in &quot;Kill Yourself&quot;, a rap song made by rapper [[Timbaland]]. The Red Queen had not appeared in the ''Resident Evil'' video games previously, but in 2007 she appeared in ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles'' voiced by [[Tara Platt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title= Role Credits| publisher= taraplatt.com| url=  http://www.taraplatt.com/wst_page3.html | title = Voice-Over Resume|accessdate= 2007-12-02 |archiveurl =http://web.archive.org/web/20070717042606/http://www.taraplatt.com/wst_page3.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her character appears as a [[database|database computer]] which provides information relating to the Arklay Incident and T-virus development. In the game's chapter &quot;The Umbrella's End&quot;, the T-A.L.O.S. (Tyrant Armored Lethal Organic System) was monitored and controlled by the Red Queen, which &quot;is the code name for the AI defense system developed by Umbrella&quot;, with an unrestricted access to the entire Umbrella network. It is self-aware and can take these measures based on its own judgment. At the end of the game, Wesker manages to procure all the data the Red Queen possessed for himself, and has it permanently erase itself and deactivate.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Waples, &quot;Red Queen Notes,&quot; ''Resident Evil: The Umbrella Chronicles Prima Official Game Guide''(Roseville: Prima Games, 2007), 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Resident Evil: Extinction'', Alice encounters another holographic AI computer called the White Queen. The White Queen is also modeled after a young girl, but it is never mentioned if the appearance is based on another character. The White Queen is a later version of the Red Queen that holds a counterpart position for the Umbrella facility in [[Las Vegas, Nevada]]. Unlike The Red Queen, The White Queen has further advanced holographic technology and has a more convincing appearance of a child in comparison to the semi-translucent Red Queen hologram. The White Queen helps Alice, saying that, like the original Red Queen, her purpose is to protect human life. She however defends the actions of the Red Queen, citing that the Red Queen had done what was necessary at the time. The White Queen reveals to Alice the cure for the T-virus and offers to help her create it, but Alice must first kill Dr. Isaacs. The White Queen was originally planned to appear in ''Resident Evil'', however, she was cut from the final screenplay.&lt;ref name=&quot;White Queen&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title= White Queen Emitted| publisher= ''Horror Lair''| url=http://www.horrorlair.com/scripts/resevil.html| accessdate= 2007-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the screenplay, her character was brought online by Umbrella to shut down the Red Queen after residents of the Hive were [[Bromochlorodifluoromethane|gassed]] to death.

== Notable creatures ==
=== Nemesis ===
{{Main|Nemesis (Resident Evil)}}

=== Tyrants ===
{{main|Tyrant (Resident Evil)}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{Cite book |title=Resident Evil Archives |author=Capcom Staff |authorlink=Capcom |year=2005 |publisher=[[BradyGames]]/[[Capcom]] |isbn=0744006554}}
* {{Cite book |title=バイオハザード アーカイブス|language=Japanese|author=Capcom Staff|isbn=4-906582-31-1|year=2005|month=March}}

== External links ==
* [[Wikia:residentevil:Category:Characters|Characters]] on the [[Wikia:residentevil:Resident Evil Wiki|Resident Evil Wiki]]
* [[Wikia:residentevil:Category:Creatures|Creatures]] on the [[Wikia:residentevil:Resident Evil Wiki|Resident Evil Wiki]]

{{Resident Evil series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Resident Evil Characters}}
[[Category:Lists of Capcom characters|Resident Evil]]
[[Category:Resident Evil characters| ]]

[[es:Anexo:Personajes de Resident Evil (saga)]]
[[fa:فهرست شخصیت‌های رزیدنت ایول]]
[[fr:Liste des personnages de Resident Evil]]
[[ja:バイオハザードシリーズの登場人物]]
[[pt:Anexo:Lista de personagens de Resident Evil]]
[[ru:Список персонажей серии Resident Evil]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
