<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="864458" ns="0" title="General Zod"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox comics character &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
| character_name = General Zod
| image = GeneralZod.png
| converted = y
| caption = General Zod as seen in ''Action Comics'' #845 (January 2007)&lt;br&gt;Art by [[Adam Kubert]]
| publisher = [[DC Comics]]
| debut = ''[[Adventure Comics]]'' #283&lt;br&gt;(April 1961)
| creators = [[Robert Bernstein (comics)|Robert Bernstein]]&lt;br&gt;[[George Papp]]
| full_name = Dru-Zod
| homeworld = [[Krypton (comics)|Krypton]]
| partners = [[Non (DC Comics)|Non]], [[Ursa (comics)|Ursa]], [[Faora]], [[Quex-Ul]], Nam-Ek, Aethyr-Ka
| alliances = Kryptonian Military Guild
| powers = [[Superhuman strength|Superstrength]], [[Speedster (fiction)|Superspeed]], Superhearing, Superbreath, [[Heat Vision]], [[Flight]], [[Invulnerability]], [[X-Ray Vision]], Skilled Warrior &amp; Military Tactition
| subcat = DC Comics
| villain = y
| sortkey = Zod, General
}}
'''General Zod''' (full name '''Dru-Zod''') is a [[fictional character]] who appears in [[comic book]]s published by [[DC Comics]], a supervillain who is one of [[Superman]]'s more-prominent enemies. The character first appeared in ''[[Adventure Comics]]'' #283 (April 1961), and was created by [[Robert Bernstein (comics)|Robert Bernstein]] and [[George Papp]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dc-ency&quot;&gt;{{Cite book | last = Wallace | first = Dan | author-link = | contribution = General Zod | editor-last = Dougall | editor-first = Alastair | title = The DC Comics Encyclopedia | page = 136 | publisher = [[Dorling Kindersley]] | place = New York | year = 2008 | isbn = 0-7566-4119-5 | oclc = 213309017}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the motion pictures ''[[Superman (film)|Superman: The Movie]]'' (1978) and ''[[Superman II]]'' (1980), Zod is portrayed by British actor [[Terence Stamp]]; the character is the principal villain in the latter film. British film magazine ''[[Total Film]]'' ranked Stamp's version of Zod as #32 on their &quot;Top 50 Greatest Villains Of All Time&quot; list in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://snarkerati.com/movie-news/the-top-50-greatest-heroes-villains-of-all-time-total-film-compiled-list/ |title=The Top 50 Greatest Heroes &amp; Villains Of All Time - ‘Total Film’ Compiled List |publisher=Snarkerati.com |date=2007-11-24 |accessdate=2010-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Pop-culture website [[IGN.com]] also ranked the General as #30 on their list of the &quot;Top 100 Comic Book Villains&quot;, asserting that &quot;Stamp ''is'' Zod&quot; (emphasis in original).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://comics.ign.com/top-100-villains/30.html |title=General Zod is number 30 - IGN |publisher=Comics.ign.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=={{anchor|Fictional character biography}}Character biography==
===Silver Age===
Dru-Zod is a [[megalomaniac]]al [[Kryptonian]], in charge of the military forces on Krypton. He knew [[Jor-El]], Superman's father, when Jor-El was an aspiring scientist. When the space program was abolished after the destruction of the inhabited moon Wegthor (engineered by renegade scientist [[Jax-Ur]]), he attempted to take over Krypton. Zod created an army of robotic duplicates of himself, all bearing a resemblance to [[Bizarro]]. He was sentenced to exile in the [[Phantom Zone]] for 40 years for his crimes. Zod was eventually released by [[Superboy]] when his term of imprisonment was up. However, he attempted to conquer Earth with his superpowers acquired under the yellow sun. Zod was sent back into the Phantom Zone, from which he occasionally escapes to target [[Superman]].

===Modern Age===
====Pocket Universe Zod====
This Zod came from a Krypton in a pocket universe created by the [[Time Trapper]]. He (along with companions [[Quex-Ul]] and [[Faora]]) devastated the Earth of that universe following the death of its Superboy, despite the best efforts of a [[Supergirl (Matrix)|Supergirl]] created by this world's heroic [[Lex Luthor]]. Eventually, the survivors of this world managed to contact the Superman of the main universe to help them, and he was able to take away the powers of the three super-criminals with gold kryptonite (since he was not from that universe, the kryptonite of that reality would have no effect on him). However, as the three vowed to some day regain their powers and return to Superman's world to kill him, Superman was forced to execute them with [[Kryptonite]]&lt;ref&gt;''Superman'' vol. 2 (October 1988)&lt;/ref&gt;; and it was this action which caused him to question his powers and how to deal with evildoers.&lt;ref name=&quot;dc-ency&quot;/&gt; This version of Zod is based closely on the [[Crisis on Infinite Earths|Pre-Crisis]] version; the significant difference is he killed everyone on the pocket Earth, rather than conquering them (there is no Superboy/Superman to stop him).

====&quot;Return to Krypton&quot; Zod====
[[Image:GeneralZodRtK.jpg|thumb|right|165px|&quot;Return to Krypton&quot; Zod from ''Adventures of Superman'' #589 (April 2001)|alt=General Zod in military-style uniform]]
This incarnation of General Zod was introduced in the 2001 storyline &quot;Return to Krypton&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Adventures of Superman'' #589 (April 2001)&lt;/ref&gt; He was the head of the Kryptonian military in an alternate reality created by [[Brainiac 13]]. Like the pre-crisis version, Zod held the Kryptonian equivalent of [[fascist]] beliefs. He sent aliens to the bottled city of [[Kandor]] and planned a military coup. Zod was defeated by Superman and the Jor-El of that Krypton.&lt;ref&gt;''Action Comics'' #776 (April 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russian Zod===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Bizarro]] --&gt;
[[Image:Generalzodrussian21.png|thumb|left|165px|Russian General Zod|alt=General Zod full-length, with long red cape]]
This General Zod is a [[Russians|Russian]] who was affected before his birth by [[Kryptonite]] [[radiation]], since he was the son of two [[cosmonaut]]s whose ship was too close to Kal-El's rocketship. This Zod is unnaturally weak under a yellow sun, but superpowered under a red sun (the opposite of Superman). After his parents died from radiation, he grew up in a [[KGB]] laboratory under the name &quot;Zed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dc-ency&quot;/&gt;

Apparently spoken to by the spirit of the Pocket Universe Zod, Russian Zod created a suit of red armor which filtered the sunlight, and declared himself ruler of the fictional former [[Soviet]] state of [[Pokolistan]]. After several inconclusive encounters with Superman, he revealed his long-range plan to turn the sun red and take Superman's place. This was temporarily successful until [[Lex Luthor]] rescued Superman, gave him a blast of yellow solar radiation to regain his powers, and worked to restore the sun. Superman returned to battle Zod, but refused to kill him. When the sun turned yellow again the now-vulnerable Zod struck Superman with all his power at super-speed, but was killed due to Superman's invulnerability.&lt;ref name=&quot;dc-ency&quot;/&gt;

This Zod is most similar to the Zod who appears in Season 9 of Smallville (see below), since both are initially powerless under a yellow sun but have Kryptonian powers under a red sun. Both Zods plot to turn Earth's sun into a red sun in order to permanently gain these powers.

===Phantom Zod===
Introduced in the twelve-issue ''[[Superman: For Tomorrow|For Tomorrow]]'' (''Superman'' #204-#215) storyline, written by [[Brian Azzarello]] and penciled by [[Jim Lee]], this Zod lives alone in an alternate Phantom Zone and resents Superman for tampering with it. By his own account he comes from the same Krypton as Superman and was exiled to the Phantom Zone by Superman's father, Jor-El. This Zod wears large, spiked black armor and when unmasked, is a bald, white-bearded old man. This incarnation also uses a variation of &quot;Kneel before Zod&quot;. He appeared in Metropia, a version of the Phantom Zone created by Superman to resemble a living world (including apparently-living beings). Since Superman created the world of Metropia with similarities to Krypton, it has been revealed{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} that this (again) is not the real Zod. However, whether or not this was the real Zod of the pre-[[Infinite Crisis]] DC universe he has been superseded by the present storyline (which features a new Zod, freed from the Phantom Zone).

===Krypton Zod===
General Zod appeared as a primary antagonist in the ''[[Superman: Last Son]]'' storyline (written by [[Geoff Johns]] and [[Richard Donner]] [director of ''[[Superman (film)|Superman: The Movie]]'' and most of ''[[Superman II: The Richard Donner Cut|Superman II]]''). In a similar story to that of ''Superman II'', Zod, [[Ursa (comics)|Ursa]], and [[Non (DC Comics)|Non]] escape from the Phantom Zone and come to Earth to try to turn it into a &quot;New Krypton&quot;. This incarnation is the first Post-Crisis Zod who came from Superman's Krypton, and not from an alternate reality.

The backstory for the three Kryptonians was revealed in ''Action Comics Annual'' #10. Non had once been a brilliant scientist, on a par with Jor-El. Both were researching the event which would ultimately destroy Krypton. Zod entered their lab with troops (at this point, Zod was still working for Krypton's Council). Both Jor-El and Non were arrested by Zod, warned by the High Council to halt their research and released. Jor-El set to work creating the rocket that would send his son Kal-El to Earth, while Non began to spread the word of the planet's impending doom. Non's message convinced both Zod and Ursa that Krypton was soon to be destroyed. Non then disappeared from public life, only to return with a mutilated brain. The council had transformed him into a mindless brute, and this act inspired Zod and Ursa to rebel against the Kryptonian government. Without any sense of right and wrong, Non now fought alongside Zod and Ursa. Zod attempted to recruit Jor-El to their cause; however, Jor-El saw that the plans were fueled by greed, lust for power and violence.

This rebellion was short-lived and the rebels were again arrested and sentenced to be executed. Not wishing to resort to execution, Jor-El appealed on their behalf to exile them instead. The council accepted this, on the condition that Jor-El would be the jailer. Zod, Ursa and Non were imprisoned, and embittered against Jor-El for years to come.

The story also features the debut of [[Chris Kent (comics)|Christopher Kent]], a young Kryptonian boy discovered and briefly raised by Superman and Lois Lane. It is revealed that Christopher (whose birth name is Lor-Zod) is the son of Zod and Ursa, born in the Phantom Zone and used as a conduit for their escape. The birth was possible in the otherwise-timeless Phantom Zone because of an ancient accident. An entire Kryptonian prison was transported to the Zone; inside it, time passes.

After ambushing Superman, Zod trapped him in the Zone. At the same time about 25 other Kryptonian criminals also escape the Zone and defeat a number of Earth's heroes, beginning their quest to conquer the planet (starting with Metropolis). Superman escapes the Zone with the aid of [[Mon-El]], and ultimately defeats Zod with the unlikely aid of [[Lex Luthor]], [[Metallo]], [[Parasite (comics)|Parasite]] and [[Bizarro]]. Out of nearly 30 Kryptonians Metallo, Parasite, and Lex Luthor manage to kill five or six of them with Kryptonite and red solar radiation. Zod and his compatriots are sent back into the Phantom Zone; unfortunately, so is Chris Kent. At the end of the &quot;[[Superman: New Krypton|New Krypton]]&quot; arc, it is revealed that [[Alura]] has brought Zod, Ursa, and Non back from the Phantom Zone (making Zod the army's new leader).

====World of New Krypton====

When [[Superman]] decides to see what life is like on New Krypton, he is drafted into the Military Guild under General Zod. Zod and Superman maintain a mistrustful professional relationship. Despite their past, neither seems prepared to behave with marked aggression toward the other.  When Zod orders that Superman and his people kill a Kryptonian criminal, Superman circumvents the order. He feels that killing the criminal would be not only unnecessary, but wrong.  The criminal is arrested, without further fatalities. 

Zod accuses Superman of treason, of which he is found guilty. Before being executed, Superman gives a heartfelt speech about morality.  Much to the everyone's surprise, Zod is apparently moved by the speech.  He requests that the Religious Guild give Superman absolution, overturn the &quot;guilty&quot; verdict.  As a result, Superman is cleared of all charges. When asked why he did not go through with the execution of the son of someone he hated Zod explains that, despite everything that had happened before, he realized that his military would be stronger and better for having Superman in it.  As a result it appears that there is a level of mutual respect (if not peace) between Zod and Superman. 

Later, during a Kryptonian ceremony, Zod is shot by the Kryptonian Ral-Dar (who is working with [[Sam Lane]]). In issue seven of this story arc, he names [[Superman|Kal-El]] temporary General until he has fully recovered. By issue 11 he has recovered, but returns to his duties at the worst possible moment. Kal-El, Adam Strange, and Tyr-Van are about to be killed, after having their powers removed because they were with Tam-Or. Tam-Or is a principal suspect of killing a member of the council; even Superman is unable to halt the execution. Zod stops the execution and (with Kal-El) investigates members of a group of traitors to Krypton. They discover the last member and, after getting him to confess to his crimes, arrest him. As Kal-El and Zod are talking about how Kal-El has changed New Krypton by helping the Labor Guild get on the Council, Brainiac attacks.

====Last Stand of New Krypton====
With New Krypton under attack by Brainiac Zod begins his plan to defeat him after his greatest defeat by the Coluan, when he bottled Kandor from Old Krypton.

====War of the Supermen====
After the final moments of ''Last Stand of New Krypton'' (when the planet was destroyed by a missile fired by General [[Sam Lane]]), Zod declares war on Earth. After a fierce conflict, Zod is pushed back into the Phantom Zone by his son.&lt;ref&gt;''Superman: War of the Supermen'' #4&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other versions==
*General Zod does not appear in the ''[[Superman: The Animated Series|Superman]]'' or ''[[Justice League (TV series)|Justice League]]'' animated series, but appears in the spinoff comics of that universe; in ''[[Superman Adventures]]'' #21, he is an [[Argo City#In other media|Argosian]]. This General Zod also appears in ''[[Justice League Adventures|Justice League Unlimited]]'' #34.
*The General Zod of [[Earth-15]] is this world's Superman. This version is later killed by [[Superman Prime]], who was angry because Zod was not a &quot;maniac&quot;.
*The Zod of ''[[JSA: The Liberty Files]]'' was not a general of any kind. He was recast as a sociopathic 11 year-old, who created a deadly synthetic virus on Krypton for no reason other than fun. Zod was banished to the Phantom Zone because of his actions (the  first child ever sent to the Zone) until American scientists breached the Zone and discovered him. Taken in by the government and named &quot;Clark Kent&quot;, Zod would fool most of his adult superiors by playing the role of a scared child until he grew up and became the adult &quot;Super-Man&quot;.

==Powers and abilities==
{{Main|Powers and abilities of Superman}}
Like all Kryptonians under a yellow sun, General Zod possesses vast strength, speed, and endurance; super hearing; x-ray vision; telescopic, microscopic, and heat vision; super-breath and freeze-breath; invulnerability; healing and flight. In addition, Zod possesses a detailed knowledge of military tactics, giving him an advantage over Superman's somewhat amateurish combat prowess. Zod was trained in fighting arts before receiving his abilities, while Superman is prone to battling his foes with the aide of his own. Despite his tactical superiority in a confrontation with Superman, Zod's main weakness is shown to be his arrogance. Not only does he underestimate Superman's other allies, but he also lacks the ability to acknowledge his mistakes. When Zod originally escaped the Phantom Zone in the post-Crisis continuity, he proclaimed that he could have saved Krypton if his plan to kill the Council had succeeded; Superman's rational argument was that nobody on Krypton would have followed him and his inability to explain exactly ''what'' he would have done to avert Krypton's destruction.

==In other media==
===Film===
====''Superman'' and ''Superman II''====
[[Image:GeneralZodForPresident20084.jpg|thumb|General Zod ([[Terence Stamp]], center), [[Ursa (comics)|Ursa]] ([[Sarah Douglas]]), and [[Non (DC Comics)|Non]] ([[Jack O'Halloran]]) in ''[[Superman II]]''|alt=General Zod, Non (both bearded) and Ursa in the film ''Superman II'']]
General Zod appears in ''[[Superman (film)|Superman: The Movie]]'', ''[[Superman II]]'' and ''[[Superman II: The Richard Donner Cut]]'', portrayed by actor [[Terence Stamp]] as a pathologically arrogant and pompous aristocrat, almost bored with his incredible powers and disappointed with the ease of overtaking Earth. In 2009, issue #7 of the 15-story ''[[Superman: World of New Krypton]]'' copied this with the phrase &quot;Kneel Before Kal-El&quot; on the cover. Terence Stamp's portrayal has led to Zod becoming one of Superman's best-known villains, and fans have come to view his portrayal as the definitive version of the character.{{fact|date=September 2011}} Director [[Richard Lester]] inspired much of Zod (and company)'s destruction of downtown [[Metropolis (comics)|Metropolis]]. One scene involved his heat vision being reflected by Superman. Standing in front of a tanning-salon billboard, he comedically imprinted his silhouette over the bikini-clad figure; the rest of the poster charred. The film portrayal of General Zod is rated #58 on ''[[Wizard (magazine)|Wizard]]'' magazine's &quot;100 Greatest Villains of All Time&quot; list.&lt;ref&gt;''Wizard'' #177; [[Jason Mewes]] also uses the phrase in the 1996 movie ''[[Mallrats]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Terence Stamp is the voice for [[Jor-El]] in the TV series ''Smallville'', and his figure/shape and scream also appear also as Zod in the show (see below).

====''The Man of Steel''====
[[Michael Shannon (actor)|Michael Shannon]] was cast as Zod in the [[Zack Snyder]] film, ''[[Man of Steel (film)|Man of Steel]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first=Gregg | last=Kilday | title=Michael Shannon Set to Play Villain General Zod in 'Superman: Man of Steel' | work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]] | date=April 10, 2011 | url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/heat-vision/michael-shannon-set-play-villain-176799 | accessdate=2011-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===
====''Smallville''====
[[Image:CamBlueZod.jpg|thumb|right|165px|[[Callum Blue]] as Zod in ''[[Smallville]]''|alt=Zod in the TV program ''Smallville'', wearing a black athletic shirt, camouflage pants and dog-tags]]
General Zod appears as a recurring villain in ''[[Smallville]]'', although off-screen at first. References to Zod began with [[Smallville (season 5)|season five]]'s [[season premiere]] &quot;Arrival&quot;, which featured two Kryptonian disciples of Zod (who arrived on Earth in the [[meteor shower]] of the season-four finale) searching for [[Clark Kent (Smallville)|Clark Kent]] ([[Tom Welling]]). The season concludes with the Kryptonian artificial intelligence known as [[Brainiac (comics)|Brainiac]] ([[James Marsters]]), having granted [[Lex Luthor (Smallville)|Lex Luthor]] ([[Michael Rosenbaum]]) Kryptonian superpowers, is able to make him host for Zod's consciousness. The season-six première opens with Zod (Rosenbaum) set to rule over a devastated Metropolis. However, Clark is able to evict Zod's consciousness and send it back to the Phantom Zone. Zod's disembodied spirit resembles [[Terence Stamp]]. In [[Smallville (season 8)|season eight's]] &quot;Bloodline&quot;, Zod's wife [[Faora]] escapes the Phantom Zone and inhabits the body of [[Lois Lane (Smallville)|Lois Lane]] ([[Erica Durance]]). She reveals that she and Zod genetically engineered a son&amp;mdash;[[Davis Bloome]] ([[Sam Witwer]]), ''Smallville''{{'}}s version of [[Doomsday (comics)|Doomsday]]&amp;mdash;after they discovered they could not have children. Zod and Faora sent Doomsday to Earth to destroy the planet and the infant Clark. Faora also remarks that Davis (Witwer) strongly resembles Zod. In the season-eight finale &quot;Doomsday,&quot; Zod's symbol is burnt into the grass by the Orb in the possession of [[Tess Mercer]] ([[Cassidy Freeman]]); a man stands on the burning lawn (a brief, uncredited portrayal by Witwer).

[[Smallville (season 9)|Season Nine]] introduces the return of General Zod as his younger self: Major Zod (British actor [[Callum Blue]]) as a main character. It is revealed that before Krypton exploded, Zod duplicated his DNA when he was still a [[Kandor]]ian Major, before committing the atrocities for which he is known. Kelly Sounders observes, &quot;over the course of the season, the venomous side of Zod rises because he experiences a few key betrayals with our beloved characters.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvguidemagazine.com/smallville/smallvilles-zod-complex-1766.html] {{Dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Season nine begins with Tess as Zod's prisoner in the Luthor mansion; he and many other weakened Kandorians live there.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title=Savior | series=Smallville | credits=Brian Peterson, Kelly Souders (writers). Kevin Fair (director) | network=The CW | airdate=September 25, 2009 | season=9 | episode=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;Metallo&quot;, Zod and his soldiers use LuthorCorp equipment to create the supervillain [[Metallo]] ([[Brian Austin Green]]) using Kryptonian scientific knowledge.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title=Metallo | series=Smallville | credits=Don Whitehead, Holly Henderson (writers). Mairzee Almas (director) | network=The CW | airdate=October 2, 2009 | season=9 | episode=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zod discovers that he is a clone in &quot;Kandor&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title=Kandor | series=Smallville | credits=Al Septien, Turi Meyer (writers). Jeannot Szwarc (director) | network=The CW | airdate=November 6, 2009 | season=9 | episode=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lois, having seen the future, attempts to prevent General Zod and the Kandorians (who have regained their abilities) from ruling Earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title=Pandora | series=Smallville | credits=Drew Landis, Julia Swift (writers). Morgan Beggs (director) | network=The CW | airdate=November 20, 2009 | season=9 | episode=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the episode &quot;Disciple&quot;, he introduces himself to an injured Lois Lane.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title=Disciple | series=Smallville | credits=Jordan Hawley (writer). Mairzee Almas (director) | network=The CW | airdate=January 29, 2010 | season=9 | episode=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clark uses his blood to revive a dying Zod in &quot;Conspiracy&quot;, which has the side effect of awakening Zod's abilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title=Conspiracy | series=Smallville | credits=Al Septien, Turi Meyer (writers). Turi Meyer (director) | network=The CW | airdate=February 26, 2010 | season=9 | episode=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zod masquerades as Clark in &quot;The Blur&quot; until Lois discovers the duplicity. Although Clark is able to convince Zod's followers to leave him when they learn he killed a pregnant Faora, Zod and Clark battle; they are both powerless due to the effects of Blue Kryptonite. The episode ends with Clark in free-fall and Zod ascending, since he is taken out of Earth by the Kryptonian book of Rao. Zod makes a final appearance in the [[Smallville (season 10)|season ten]] (2011) episode &quot;Dominion&quot;. The other Kandorians had chosen to punish Zod by sending him to the Phantom Zone, where he was reunited with the disembodied spirit of General Zod. The united Zod's hatred of Clark is further intensified. As Clark departs from the Zone he destroys the exit, trapping Zod within.

====Other versions====
* In the ''[[Super Friends (1980)|Super Friends]]'' episode &quot;The Evil From Krypton&quot; (1981), a Phantom Zone villain named Zy-Kree resembles the  film version of Zod.
* General Zod appears in the 1988 animated series ''[[Superman (TV series)|Superman]]'' episode &quot;The Hunter&quot; voiced by [[René Auberjonois (actor)|René Auberjonois]]. Zod is imprisoned in the Phantom Zone with [[Ursa (comics)|Ursa]] and [[Faora]] (two Kryptonian women), whereas most portrayals of the conspiracy show the Zod trio composed of two men and one woman.
* Although Zod himself does not appear in ''[[Lois &amp; Clark: The New Adventures of Superman]]'', a similar character loosely based on Zod, Lord Nor (played by [[Simon Templeman]]) battles with Superman in a story arc from the end of the third season to the beginning of the fourth to determine the fate of a group of surviving Kryptonians on New Krypton and the inhabitants of [[Smallville (comics)|Smallville]]. He was killed at the end of the arc by exposure to [[Kryptonite]] gas.
* Zod does not appear in the [[DC animated universe]], but a character appearing on ''[[Superman: The Animated Series]]'' named [[Jax-Ur]], although named after a character in the comics, resembles Zod. With his companion [[Mala (Kryptonian)|Mala]] (who resembles Faora), they try to take over the world as Zod did. The characters were restructured versions of established characters. General Zod appeared in the comic book based on the series, stating that he was native to the planet Argo (the home-world of Supergirl); unlike Jax-Ur, he overthrew the Argoan government and created a junta which subjugated the people of Argo. While creating a navy with which to invade Krypton he was foiled by his own colonels (who believed Zod had become too power-mad) and banished to the Phantom Zone. The colonels then reinstated the Argoan republic, serving as its leaders until the people could assume power once again. Zod's name was used in Argoan folk legend to inspire fear in the children of Argo, saying he would come for children who did not obey their parents.
* Though neither Zod nor Jax-Ur appear in ''[[Justice League (TV series)|Justice League]]'' or ''[[Justice League Unlimited]]'', the ''Justice League Unlimited'' episode &quot;[[For the Man Who Has Everything]]&quot; contains a depiction Superman's dream world where his Kryptonian wife, Loana, mentions another Kryptonian named &quot;Little Zod&quot;.
* The Silver Age version of Zod makes a cameo appearance in the ''[[Legion of Super Heroes (TV series)|Legion of Super Heroes]]'' episode, &quot;Phantoms&quot;. He is one of the many Phantom Zone prisoners attacking the [[Legion of Super-Heroes|Legion]]. The villain Drax is speculated{{Or|date=June 2010}} to be Zod's son, since Drax stated that he was born in the Phantom Zone.
* General Zod appears in the ''[[Robot Chicken]]'' episode, &quot;The Munnery&quot;, voiced by [[Seth Green]]. Zod commands, &quot;Kneel before Zod!&quot; He kneels, and two women beside him kneel as well. [[Exercise and music|Exercise music]] begins, and Zod lies down. &quot;Lay down on your back before Zod! Now! Using your lower abdominals, raise your legs and hold on a five count before Zod! One before Zod! Two before Zod! Three before Zod!&quot; As he continues leading the exercises the camera pulls back, revealing a banner reading, &quot;Bod By Zod&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|ngbqB879_bc|Bod by Zod}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Video games===
* General Zod is mentioned in ''[[World of Warcraft]]'' with a weapon named &quot;Zod's Repeating Longbow&quot;, which bears the phrase &quot;Kneel before him&quot;.
* The 1988 ''Superman'' [[Nintendo|NES]] game has the Zod trio as the final bosses whom Superman must defeat in order to win the game. The fight takes place at the fictional Statue of Freedom in Metropolis, based on the [[Statue of Liberty]].
* General Zod appears in the ''[[DC Universe Online]]'' video game, voiced by [[Alexander Brandon]].

===Novels===
In the novel ''The Last Days of Krypton'' (by [[Kevin J. Anderson]], ISBN 006134074X), General Zod (also known as Commissioner Dru-Zod) is the son of Cor-Zod (former head of the Kryptonian Council).

===Web series===
* Parodies of the character have been seen in some episodes of the web series ''[[Galacticast]]'', played by actor [[Rudy Jahchan]].
* In 2010, Doug Walker of ''[[That Guy with the Glasses]]'' produced a Christmas series in which he plays General Zod analyzing some of the traditions and symbols of Christmas (including snowmen, Christmas trees, and Santa Claus). In February 2011, Walker  appeared as Zod, announcing his candidacy for [[President of the United States]].

===Music===
* The American rock band [[Electric Six]] includes the &quot;Kneel before Zod&quot; line in its song &quot;[[I Shall Exterminate Everything Around Me That Restricts Me from Being the Master|Rip It]]&quot;.
* [[Ireland|Irish]] [[thrash metal]] band [[Gama Bomb]]'s ''[[Citizen Brain]]'' album features a song entitled &quot;In the Court of General Zod&quot;.
* The band How I Became the Bomb wrote a song, &quot;Kneel Before Zod&quot;.
* Kneel To Zod is a metal band in southern Maryland.
* Rapper [[Tech N9ne]], in the song &quot;Sinister Tech&quot;, says &quot;I'll make you kneel before Zod&quot;.
* Rapper [[RZA]] includes the line &quot;Kneel to Zod&quot; in his song, &quot;Gone&quot;.

==See also==
*[[List of Superman enemies]]
*[[Kryptonian]]
*[[Krypton (comics)]]
*[[Last Son (comic)|Last Son]]
*[[Terence Stamp]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{gcdb|type=character|search=General+Zod|title=General Zod}}
*{{comicbookdb|type=character|id=4089|title=General Zod}}
*[http://www.dccomics.com/dcu/heroes_and_villains/?hv=origin_stories/general_zod&amp;p=1 DCComics.com - Origin of General Zod]
* {{DCdatabase|Zod}}
* {{imdb character|0000225}}
* [http://www.generalzod.net GeneralZod.net] - a humor website featuring General Zod
* [http://alankistler.squarespace.com/journal/2009/4/2/kistlers-history-of-general-zod.html Alan Kistler's Profile On: ZOD!] - Comic book historian Alan Kistler does an in-depth article reviewing the long history of Zod from 1961 all the way to 2005, going into detail on the various incarnations and changes in the character. Includes several artwork scans of the different versions of Zod and a discussion of the show ''Smallville''.

{{Superman}}
{{1978–1987 Superman film series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Zod, General}}
[[Category:Comics characters introduced in 1961]]
[[Category:Fictional majors]]
[[Category:DC Comics characters with accelerated healing]]
[[Category:DC Comics characters with superhuman strength]]
[[Category:DC Comics characters who can move at superhuman speeds]]
[[Category:Extraterrestrial supervillains]]
[[Category:Fictional dictators]]
[[Category:Fictional generals]]
[[Category:Fictional mass murderers]]
[[Category:Film characters]]
[[Category:Kryptonians]]
[[Category:Smallville characters]]
[[Category:Fictional admirals]]
[[Category:Fictional clones]]

[[es:General Zod]]
[[fr:Général Zod]]
[[it:Generale Zod]]
[[he:גנרל זוד]]
[[nl:General Zod]]
[[no:Zod]]
[[pt:General Zod]]
[[ru:Генерал Зод]]
[[fi:Kenraali Zod]]
[[tl:General Zod]]
[[tr:Zod]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
