<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8649414" ns="0" title="The Woolpack"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Woolpack.jpg|thumb|The Woolpack|150px]]
''This article is about the soap opera. Click the link for the [[Cumulus cloud]] formation synonym.''

'''''The Woolpack''''' is a [[fictional]] [[public house]] on the popular [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]''. Its sign is a [[wool bale]], a popular symbol in sheep-rearing country. It has played host to many of the soap's storylines and is the focus of the programme. It is the second oldest TV soap pub, opening its doors in October 1972 and being preceded by The Rovers Return Inn which opened in December 1960 and succeeded by The Queen Victoria which opened in February 1985. The Woolpack is the only soap pub to have changed locations as part of a story-line. In 1976, the original Woolpack was found to be suffering from subsidence. Another building was bought by landlords [[Amos Brearly]] and [[Henry Wilks]] and made its debut as The Woolpack later the same year. This was to cover ''Emmerdale Farm'''s move from Arncliffe to Esholt for location filming.

The first Woolpack was the Falcon Inn in [[Arncliffe, North Yorkshire|Arncliffe]]. When the outdoor scenes were moved to [[Esholt]] in 1976 the Commercial Inn was chosen as the new Woolpack. The present Woolpack is on the purpose-built Emmerdale village set on the [[Harewood House|Harewood estate]] which is based on Esholt.

The [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#Plane crash storyline 1993|1993 plane crash]] saw the Woolpack wine bar demolished trapping many people inside and paralysing [[Chris Tate]] from the waist down.  It was also involved in [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#The Storm 2003|the storm of 2003]] where the roof was struck by lightning which caused the chimney to fall through the roof causing a window to collapse and fall on [[Tricia Dingle]], which eventually resulted in her death. 

===The Malt Shovel===
For many years the Woolpack had a rival pub in the village called ''The Malt Shovel'' which was supposedly slightly downmarket compared to the Woolpack. Episodes in which the Malt Shovel have been mentioned include [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#Plane crash storyline 1993|The Plane Crash]] and [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#The Storm 2003|The Storm]] ones. It is presumed that the Malt Shovel is no longer currently trading.

===Current employees===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Job Role !! Characters
|-
| Owners || [[Diane Sugden]], [[Chas Dingle]]
|-
| Bar staff|| [[Bob Hope (Emmerdale)|Bob Hope]], [[Moira Barton]], [[Alicia Gallagher]]
|-
| Chef || [[Marlon Dingle]]
|-
| Cleaner and General Assistant || [[Rachel Breckle]]
|-
| Relief Cleaner and General Assistant || [[Victoria Sugden]]
|}

==Key events==
*1973: [[Amos Brearly]] and [[Henry Wilks]] become Landlords of the Woolpack.
*1976: The Woolpack is found to be suffering from subsidence. New premises are found in the village.
*1978: Landlord [[Amos Brearly]] and [[Henry Wilks]] are held at gunpoint by armed robbers who steal the takings.
*1980: [[Seth Armstrong]], who first appeared in 1978, switches from the Malt Shovel to the Woolpack, becoming a regular bar-propper and a thorn in Amos's side.
*1983: Amos takes up golf. 
*1989: Amos tries to enlist newcomer [[Frank Tate (Emmerdale)|Frank Tate]] to appear in the annual village show. 
*1991: Amos retires, ending an 18 year partnership, Henry later dies, [[Alan Turner (Emmerdale)|Alan Turner]] becomes Landlord.
*1993: The wine bar is demolished by the plane crash, paralysing [[Chris Tate]].
*1998: The pub is burnt down after [[Tricia Stokes]] accidentally sets it on fire with sparklers.
*1999: [[Diane Blackstock|Diane]] and [[Bernice Blackstock]] become landladies.
*2000: Bernice marries [[Ashley Thomas|Ashley]] on Christmas Day.
*2002: After her failed marriage to Ashley, Bernice Thomas sells her half to [[Louise Appleton]] and leaves Emmerdale.
*2004: The Woolpack roof falls through after it is struck by lightning, crushing Tricia Dingle who later dies in hospital. Diane marries [[Jack Sugden|Jack]].
*2006: Louise sells her half to Diane's sister [[Val Pollard|Valerie Lambert]].
*2008: Val marries [[Eric Pollard|Eric]].
*2009: Val sells her share of the pub to Diane, making Diane the sole Landlady.
*2010: Diane sells the pub to Nicola King and her husband [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy]]
*2010: Jimmy and Nicola return the pub to Diane
*2011: Diane sells 50% of the pub to Chastity Dingle

==See also==
*[[Major Emmerdale storylines]]

{{Emmerdale}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Woolpack, The}}
[[Category:Emmerdale]]
[[Category:Fictional bars and inns]]
[[Category:1972 introductions]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
