<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="867306" ns="0" title="Stonyhurst College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox school
| name = Stonyhurst College
| latin_name =  ''Collegium Saxysilvanum''
| image = [[Image:Stonyhurst College Lancashire.jpg|285px|Looking from the golf course towards the oldest part of the school]]
| motto = ''Quant Je Puis''&lt;br/&gt;&quot;All that I can&quot;
| established = 1593 ([[Spanish Netherlands]]); 1794 (England)
| type = [[Independent school]],&lt;br&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] ([[Jesuit]])
| head_name = Headmaster
| head = Mr A. R. Johnson
| school_colours = Green {{color box|Green}} White {{color box|White}}
| city = [[Aighton, Bailey and Chaigley]]
| state = &lt;br&gt;[[Lancashire]]
| country = England
| free_label = Preparatory school
| free_text = [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall]]
| free_label1 = Patron saint
| free_text1 = [[Aloysius Gonzaga]]
| free_label2 = Sister schools
| free_text2 = Saint Peter's Kubatana, [[Zimbabwe]]; Faith School, [[Liverpool]] and, formerly, [[Beaumont College]], [[Old Windsor]]
| free_label3 = Annual fees (2010)
| free_text3 = £27,030 (full boarding), £22,818 (weekly boarding), £15,453 (day) 
| free_text4 = 279 boys, 164 girls. Sixth Form: 143 boys, 80 girls. Boarders: day pupils, 2:1&lt;ref name=isc/&gt;
| free_label5 = Pass rates (2010)
| free_text5 = [[GCSE]] A*-C: 93%, A*/A: 47%;&lt;ref name=Stony_1/&gt; [[A-Level]]: 100%, (A*/A grades: 42%); average UCAS points per student: 356&lt;ref name=Stony_1/&gt;
| website = [http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/ www.stonyhurst.ac.uk]}}

'''Stonyhurst College''' is a [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] [[independent school]], adhering to the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] tradition.&lt;ref name=ISBI/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jesuit_org/&gt; It is located on the [[Stonyhurst|Stonyhurst Estate]] near the village of [[Hurst Green, Lancashire|Hurst Green]] in the [[Ribble Valley]] area of [[Lancashire]], England, and occupies a [[Grade I listed]] building.&lt;ref name=Stony_3/&gt; The school has been fully co-educational since 1999. 

The college was founded in 1593&lt;ref Name=Brit/&gt; by [[Robert Persons|Father Robert Persons SJ]] at [[Saint-Omer|St Omer]],&lt;ref name=cathrob/&gt; at a time when [[penal laws]] prohibited Catholic education in England. After moving to [[Bruges]] in 1762 and [[Liège (city)|Liège]] in 1773, the college moved to England and located at Stonyhurst Hall in 1794.&lt;ref Name=Brit/&gt;&lt;ref name=cathrob/&gt; Today it provides boarding and day education to approximately 450 boys and girls aged 13–18.&lt;ref name=IndSch_1/&gt; On an adjacent site, its [[Preparatory school (UK)|preparatory school]], [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall|St Mary's Hall]], provides education for boys and girls aged 3–13.&lt;ref name=Stony_welcome/&gt;

Under the motto ''Quant Je Puis'', &quot;All that I can&quot;, the school combines an academic curriculum with extra-curricular pursuits.&lt;ref name=IndSch_Stony_2/&gt; Roman Catholicism plays a central role in college life, with emphasis on both prayer and service, according to the Jesuit philosophy of creating &quot;Men and Women for Others&quot;.&lt;ref name=spiritual_1/&gt;

The school's alumni include three [[Saint#Roman Catholicism|Saints]],&lt;ref name=TEM_188/&gt; twelve [[Beatification|''Beati'']],&lt;ref name=TEM_188/&gt; seven archbishops,&lt;ref name=TEM_188/&gt; seven [[Victoria Cross]] winners,&lt;ref name=kirby/&gt; a [[Eduardo López de Romaña|Peruvian president]] and prime minister, a [[Frederick Weld|New Zealand Prime Minister]], a signatory of the [[Charles Carroll of Carrollton|American Declaration of Independence]] and a number of writers, sportsmen, and politicians.&lt;ref name=Stony_4/&gt;

{{Stonyhurst College}}

==History==
{{Main|History of Stonyhurst College}}

===Stonyhurst Hall===
[[Image:Stonyhurst college.jpg|thumb|left|The front of Stonyhurst College]]
{{See also|Stonyhurst}}

The earliest deed concerning the &quot;Stanihurst&quot; is held in the college's Arundell Library; it dates from approximately 1200. In 1372, a license was granted to John de Bayley for an oratory on the site.&lt;ref name=Stony_7/&gt; His descendants, the Shireburn family, completed the oldest portion of the extant buildings.&lt;ref name=Stony_6/&gt; Richard Shireburn began building the hall, which was enlarged by his grandson Nicholas who also constructed the ponds, avenue and gardens.&lt;ref name=handbook36/&gt; Following his death, the estate passed to his wife and then to their sole heir, Mary, the Duchess of Norfolk. In 1754, it was inherited by her cousin [[Lulworth Castle|Thomas Weld]] of [[Lulworth]].&lt;ref name=Stony_8/&gt; A former pupil of the school from its years in Liège, he donated the buildings, with {{convert|30|acre|m2}} of land, in 1794 to the [[Society of Jesus]].&lt;ref name=Hewitson/&gt;

===The college===
{{See also|Colleges of St Omer, Bruges and Liège}}
[[Image:Robert Persons.gif|thumb|right|[[Robert Persons|Fr Robert Persons SJ]]]]

The story of the school starts at [[Saint-Omer|St Omer]] in what was then the [[Spanish Netherlands]] in 1593, where a college, under the Royal Patronage of [[Philip II of Spain]], was founded by [[Robert Parsons (Jesuit)|Fr Robert Persons SJ]] for English boys unable to receive a [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] education in [[Elizabethan era|Elizabethan England]].&lt;ref name=cathrob/&gt; As such it was one of a number of expatriate English schools operating on the European mainland.&lt;ref name=cathrob/&gt; In 1762, the Jesuits were forced to flee and re-established their school at [[Bruges]].&lt;ref name=Hewitson/&gt; The school was moved in 1773 to [[Liège (city)|Liège]], where it operated for two decades before moving to [[Stonyhurst]] on 29 August 1794.  Schooling resumed on Wednesday 22 October of the same year.&lt;ref name=Stony_9/&gt;

The college flourished during the 19th century: the Society of Jesus was re-established in [[United Kingdom|Britain]] at Stonyhurst in 1803,&lt;ref name=handbook36/&gt; and over the century, student numbers rose from the original twelve migrants from Liège.&lt;ref name=Stony_10/&gt; By the turn of the following century, it had become England's largest Catholic college.&lt;ref name=New_Advent_1/&gt; Stonyhurst Hall underwent extensive alterations and additions to accommodate these numbers; the Old South Front was constructed in 1810, only to be demolished and replaced with much grander buildings in the 1880s.&lt;ref name=TEM_195/&gt; A seminary was constructed on the [[Stonyhurst|estate]], and an observatory and meteorological station erected in the gardens.&lt;ref name=handbook36/&gt; The 20th century saw the gradual hiring of a mostly lay staff, as the number of Jesuits declined.&lt;ref name=TEM_164/&gt; The seminary at St Mary's Hall was closed, and the school discontinued its education of university-aged philosophers. With the closure of [[Beaumont College]] in 1967, Stonyhurst became the sole Jesuit public school in England.

Since the [[Second World War]], the buildings have been refurbished or developed. Additions include new science buildings in the 1950s and 1960s, a new boarding wing in the 1960s, a new swimming pool in the 1980s and Weld House in 2010. The school became fully co-educational in 1999.&lt;ref name=TEM_178/&gt;

==Hodder Place, St Mary's Hall &amp; Hodder House==
{{Main|Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall}}
[[Image:St Mary's Hall Stonyhurst.jpg|thumb|left|Saint Mary's Hall]]
The original preparatory school to Stonyhurst, [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall#Hodder Place|Hodder Place]], came into the hands of the Jesuits as part of the estate donated by alumnus Thomas Weld.&lt;ref name=legacies/&gt; Originally used as a [[novitiate]], it became a preparatory school to the college in 1807.&lt;ref name=handbook36/&gt;

[[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall|St Mary's Hall]], on an adjoining site to Stonyhurst, was built as a Jesuit Seminary in 1828 (extended in the 1850s) and functioned until 1926, when the seminarians moved to [[Heythrop College|Heythrop Hall]].&lt;ref name=Hewitson/&gt; The poet [[Gerard Manley Hopkins]], and John Tolkien, son of [[J. R. R. Tolkien]], trained as priests there.&lt;ref name=TEM_140/&gt;&lt;ref name=BBC_Tolkien/&gt; During [[World War II]], the [[English College]] left [[Benito Mussolini]]'s Italy and occupied the hall. After their return to [[Rome]], St Mary's Hall opened as a middle school in 1946.&lt;ref name=Stonyhurst_College_1963_p.38/&gt; At the same time, Hodder Place continued to educate those aged eight to eleven, until its closure and conversion into flats in 1970. Hodder Place pupils moved up to St Mary's Hall to form Hodder Playroom.&lt;ref name=TEM_194/&gt; As successor to Hodder Place, St Mary's Hall has a claim to be the oldest surviving preparatory school in Britain.&lt;ref name=Saint_Marys_Hall/&gt;

In 2004, the old gymnasium at St Mary's Hall was converted into new nursery and infant facilities named [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall#Hodder Place|Hodder House]], for those aged three to seven.&lt;ref name=TEM_181/&gt;

==Religious life==
[[Image:Lady Statue Stonyhurst.jpg|thumb|The Lady Statue at the top of the Avenue, erected in 1882]]

{{Main|Religious life at Stonyhurst College}}

The college is [[Roman Catholicism|Catholic]] and has had a significant place in English Catholic history for many centuries (including controversial events such as the [[Popish Plot]] and [[Gunpowder Plot]] conspiracies).&lt;ref name=TEM41-54/&gt; It was founded initially to educate English Catholics on the continent in the hope that, through them, Catholicism might be restored in England.&lt;ref name=TEM41-54/&gt; Finally, the school settled in England in 1794 and  the [[Society of Jesus]] was officially re-established in Britain in 1803.&lt;ref name=handbook36/&gt; Stonyhurst remained the headquarters of the English Province until the middle of the century; by 1851, a third of the Province's Jesuits were based there.&lt;ref name=TEM_140/&gt;

Until the 1920s, Jesuit priests were trained on site in what is today the preparatory school. There was a drop in vocations after [[World War I]] and the seminary was closed. The number of Jesuits teaching at Stonyhurst fell to a third of the staff within a decade.&lt;ref name=TEM_152/&gt; Since then, the Jesuit presence has been in decline, but the school continues to place Catholicism and Jesuit philosophy at its core under the guidance of a Jesuit-led chaplaincy team and the involvement of the Jesuits in its governance.&lt;ref name=spiritual_1/&gt;

===Jesuit ethos===
[[Image:St Peter's Church, Stonyhurst.jpg|thumb|left|Interior of St Peter's Church]]

The Jesuit educational ethos consists chiefly of seven strands:&lt;ref name=Jesuit_2/&gt;
*Finding God in All Things;
*Caring for the individual;
*Showing love in deeds;
*Building Christian community;
*Engaging with the wider world;
*Encouraging excellence; and
*Co-operating in Jesuit mission.

Under these guiding principles, the college strives for the formation of well-rounded individuals, influenced by [[Ignatius of Loyola|Ignatian]] reasoning and spirituality, and concern for humankind: the development of &quot;Men and Women for Others&quot;.&lt;ref name=spiritual_2/&gt;

[[Image:College Chapel windows.jpg|thumb|right|Boys' Chapel windows.]]

===Chapels===
The school has one main church, St Peter's, and five chapels: the Boys' Chapel, the Chapel of the Angels, the Sodality Chapel, the [[Aloysius Gonzaga|St Aloysius]] Chapel and the [[Ignatius of Loyola|St Ignatius]] Chapel.&lt;ref name=Hewitson_2/&gt;  The last two are both within the towers of St Peter's Church, and are not normally used by pupils.

The Sodality Chapel is the home of the remains of the 3rd century Roman convert [[Gordianus and Epimachus|St Gordianus]].&lt;ref name=Stony_11/&gt; The Jesuits brought his remains from the [[College of St Omer]] and held them beneath the altar since 1859. His bones were temporarily removed in 2006 whilst the chapel underwent restoration, but they have since been returned.&lt;ref name=Stony_12/&gt; The chapel is again used by the re-established [[Sodality]].

Adjacent to the Old Infirmary is the Rosary Garden, a place for spiritual contemplation, at the centre of which is a stone statue of Mary.&lt;ref name=Stony_13/&gt;

St Peter's Church underwent extensive repair and refurbishment in 2010-11. Most of the Victorian stencilling was not restored, although the whitewash was removed from the stencilling above the altar.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cassidyashton.co.uk/portfolio/65/St-Peter-s-Church-Stonyhurst.htm] Refurbishment of St Peters. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Traditions===
It is a long-standing practice that pupils write '''[[Ad Maiorem Dei Gloriam|A.M.D.G.]]''' in the top left hand corner of any piece of work they do. It stands for the Latin phrase ''Ad Majorem Dei Gloriam'' which means ''For the Greater Glory of God''. At the end of a piece of work they write '''L.D.S.''' in the centre of the page. It stands for ''Laus Deo Semper'' which means ''Praise to God Always''. These are both traditional Jesuit mottoes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090804232637/http://geocities.com/TheTropics/7177/amdg.htm AMDG] Information on the Jesuit motto AMDG. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

A distinguishing feature of Stonyhurst is the singing of the ''[[Pater Noster]]'', the &quot;Lord's Prayer&quot; in [[Latin]]. It is sung at mass, and has been adopted as an anthem by the school's sports teams.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1204.shtml Pater Noster] Pater Noster mentioned in the Stonyhurst Association President's speech, May 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Charitable status==
{{See also|Charities of Stonyhurst College}}

[[Image:Stonyhurst tea house.jpg|thumb|left|Public gardens and [[Religious_life_at_Stonyhurst_College#Religious_Publications|''Typographia Collegii'']]]]
As a registered charity,&lt;ref name=legacies/&gt; Stonyhurst is obliged to provide benefits to the wider community under the terms of the [[Charities Act 2006]]. As such, the College is home to the local Catholic parish church, which receives worshippers from [[Hurst Green, Lancashire|Hurst Green]] on a daily basis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salforddiocese.org.uk/parishes/masstimes.html#STONYHURST Salford Diocese] Information on St Peter's Church 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Its sports facilities, including the swimming pool and all-weather pitch are available for public use; the latter will be used for competitors training for the [[London 2012|London 2012 Olympic Games]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1104.shtml London 2012] Stonyhurst: article on London 2012, 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Much of the estate has public access; in particular the gardens and tea house are visited during the summer months, whilst the college plays host to tours, antiques fairs, food festivals, music concerts, conferences and weddings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/otp.shtml Public Access] Stonyhurst: article on public access 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The school has a relationship with a number of [[state schools]], arranging shared activities with their pupils, in particular those serving [[special needs]] children.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_998.shtml Faith Primary School] Stonyhurst: article on Faith Primary School 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the school makes available a number of places to pupils offered on scholarship, bursaries or free of charge; almost a third of current pupils receive financial support for their places.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/cat_index_41.shtml Bursaries] Stonyhurst: information on bursaries 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Motto==
The French motto, '''''Quant Je Puis''''' — '''As Much as I Can''', is central to the ethos of the school, which focusses upon the all-round development of the individual.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_4.shtml As Much as I Can] Stonyhurst: letter from the headmaster 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; It is inherited from the Shireburn family who once owned the original mansion on the site; the family emblem is emblazoned, in stone, with the motto, above the fireplace in the Top Refectory.&lt;ref name=hewit&gt;A. Hewitson, ''Stonyhurst College, Present and Past: Its History, Discipline, Treasures and Curiosities'', (Preston: the Chronicle office, Fishergate. 1888, second edition) pp.25-6&lt;/ref&gt; At the far end of the same room, once the dining room of the Shireburns, the motto can be seen again, carved into the minstrel's gallery: ''Quant Je Puis. Hugo Sherburn armig. me fieri fecit. Anno Domini 1523. Et sicut fuit sic fiat.''&lt;ref name=hewit/&gt;

==Academic==
[[Image:Stonyhurst College crest.JPG|thumb|right|The school crest]]
Academic standards are high: 93% of [[GCSE]] students attain A*-C grades; there is a 100% pass rate at [[A-Level]]; and 100% of [[A-Level]] leavers take up places at universities (10% to [[Oxbridge]]) or on [[gap year]] schemes.&lt;ref name=ISBI/&gt; The school's most recent inspection rated much of the education and pastoral provision as 'outstanding'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/uploads/std2904_report_stonyhurst_final_04_2010.pdf] Stonyhurst Inspection Report. Retrieved 26 August 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Ten GCSEs are usually taken by each pupil, consisting of five compulsory subjects (Religious Studies, [[Mathematics]], [[English Language]] and [[English Literature|Literature]], and a modern language ([[French language|French]], [[German language|German]] or [[Spanish language|Spanish]]) plus Information Technology and Personal, Social Education, with five other options from humanities, sciences, or arts subjects.&lt;ref name=academic/&gt; In Poetry (lower sixth), four or five AS-Levels are taken from a choice of 25 subjects, with a weekly Theology class. One of these may be dropped and the remainder, or all, taken on to A-Level. Six A* - C grades are the requirement for Sixth Form entry.&lt;ref name=academic&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_163.shtml Academic] Stonyhurst: information on academic life 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Each academic department has dedicated teaching rooms around the school, in addition to the general classrooms and playroom study places.

Education during the college's early history was based on [[Ignatius of Loyola|St Ignatius']] ''[[Ratio Studiorum]]'', with emphasis upon theology, classics and science, all of which still feature prominently in the curriculum.&lt;ref name=TEM_25-39/&gt; The educational practice, observed at the [[College of St Omer]], of dividing a class into Romans and Carthaginians continued long after the migration to Stonyhurst but is not employed today; each pupil would be pitched against an opponent with the task of picking up on the other's mistakes in an attempt to score points.&lt;ref name=TEM_195/&gt;

Until Roman Catholics were admitted to [[Oxbridge]] in 1894, Stonyhurst was also home to a number of &quot;philosopher gentlemen&quot; studying BA courses under the London Matriculation Examination system. Their numbers began to fall after 1894 and the department was closed in 1916.&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.151&lt;/ref&gt;

==Libraries and collections==
{{Main|Libraries and collections of Stonyhurst College}}

===Libraries===
[[Image:More Library 1965-2003.jpg|thumb|left|The More Library in 2003, prior to refurbishment.]]

Stonyhurst College has four main libraries: the Arundell, the Bay, the Square and the More (dedicated to [[Saint Thomas More]]).&lt;ref name=libraries&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/cat_index_50.shtml Libraries] Stonyhurst: information on libraries &amp; collections 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The More Library is the main library for students whilst the 'House Libraries' (the Arundell, the Bay, and the Square) contain many artefacts from the [[Society of Jesus]] and English Catholicism.&lt;ref name=libraries/&gt; The Arundell Library, presented in 1837 by Everard, 11th [[Arundell of Wardour|Baron Arundell of Wardour]], is the most significant; it is not only a country-house library from [[Wardour Castle]] but also has a notable collection of 250 Incunabula, medieval manuscripts and volumes of [[Jacobitism|Jacobite]] interest, signal among which is [[Mary I of England|Mary Tudor]]'s Book of Hours, which it is believed was been given by [[Mary, Queen of Scots]], to her chaplain on the scaffold.&lt;ref name=handbook66-7&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) pp.66-7&lt;/ref&gt; The M.S. ''Le Livre de Seyntz Medicines'' was written in 1354 by [[Henry of Grosmont, 1st Duke of Lancaster|Henry, Duke of Lancaster]].&lt;ref name=handbook66-7/&gt; To these were added the archives of the English Province of the [[Society of Jesus]], which include 16th century manuscript verses by [[Robert Southwell (jesuit)|St Robert Southwell SJ]], the letters of [[Edmund Campion|St Edmund Campion SJ]] (1540–81) and holographs of the 19th century poet [[Gerard Manley Hopkins]].&lt;ref name=handbook66-7/&gt; The Arundell Library held the 7th century [[Stonyhurst Gospel]] of St John, before it was loaned to the [[British Library]], as well as a first folio of Shakespeare.&lt;ref name=handbook66-7/&gt; The Stonyhurst copy of the ''Chronicles of [[Jean Froissart]]'', captured at the [[Battle of Agincourt]] in 1415 are currently on loan to the [[Royal Armouries]] in [[Leeds]], where they are the centre-piece of a new exhibition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saintmaryshall.com/article_327.shtml Chronicles of Jean Froissart] SMH news article on the Chronicles of Jean Froissart 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Collections===
[[Image:Do Room Stonyhurst.jpg|thumb|right|The Do Room, displaying items from the collections.]]

Among those collections kept away from public view are the numerous blood-soaked garments from Jesuits martyred in [[Japan]], the skull of [[Cardinal Morton]], the ropes used to quarter [[Saint Edmund Campion|St Edmund Campion SJ]], the hairs of [[Francis Xavier|St Francis Xavier SJ]], an enormous solid silver jewel-encrusted [[monstrance]], the Wintour vestments, a cope made for [[Henry VII of England|Henry VII]], and a thorn said to be from the [[crown of thorns]] placed upon Jesus' head at the [[crucifixion]].&lt;ref name=Hewitson137&gt;A. Hewitson, ''Stonyhurst College, Present and Past: Its History, Discipline, Treasures and Curiosities'', (Preston: the Chronicle office, Fishergate. 1888, second edition) pp.137-140&lt;/ref&gt;

The school has a number of fine paintings, including a portrait of Tsar [[Nicholas I of Russia]] and another of the Jesuit [[Henry Garnet]]. In the Stuart Parlour are portraits of a number of Jacobites including [[James Francis Edward Stuart]], and his sons [[Charles Edward Stuart]] and [[Henry Benedict Stuart]]. There are also several original engravings by [[Rembrandt]] and [[Dürer]], such as the 'Greater Passion' and the 'Car of Maximillian'.&lt;ref name=Hewitson137/&gt;

==Observatory==
[[Image:Stonyhurst observatory.jpg|thumb|left|The rear of the Observatory]]

{{Main|Stonyhurst Observatory}}
{{See also|Stonyhurst disks|Met office weather stations}}

The school has a functioning observatory which was built in 1866.&lt;ref name=Brit/&gt; An older observatory, built in 1838, is now the [[Religious_life_at_Stonyhurst_College#Religious_Publications|''Typographia Collegii'']], but was once one of seven important stations in the country when the [[Meteorological Office]] came under the auspices of the [[Royal Society]].&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 pp.145-7&lt;/ref&gt; The records of temperature taken there start from 1846 and are the oldest continuous daily records in the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00dm7d5 BBC Two - Earth: The Climate Wars, Fightback, Dr Iain Stewart.] Retrieved 20 September 2008&lt;/ref&gt; During the nineteenth century, the observatory was maintained by the astronomer priests, Fr Weld, [[Stephen Joseph Perry|Fr Perry]] and Fr Sidgreaves whose research included astronomy, geomagnetrometry and seismology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fr. Walter Sidgreaves 1837-1919&quot;&gt;[http://www.mikeoates.org/astro-history/sidgreaves.htm Fr. Walter Sidgreaves (1837-1919).] Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Astrophysicist [[Pietro Angelo Secchi]], director of the [[Vatican Observatory]], also taught astronomy at the College during the period.&lt;ref Name=Brit&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9069820/Stonyhurst-College Stonyhurst College] in ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' 2008. Retrieved 9 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sir Edward Sabine]] chose the observatory as one of his main stations when conducting a magnetic survey of Britain in 1858. Five years later Fr Sidgreaves began the first series of monthly geometric observations, which continued until May 1919.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mikeoates.org/astro-history/sidgreaves.htm Fr Walter Sidgreaves (1837-1919).] Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; During the course of the twentieth century, the observatory fell out of use and its telescope, parts of which dated to the 1860s, was sold  after the Second World War. When its private owner came to sell it, the College was able to buy it back and restore it to its original home.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ourworld.compuserve.com/homepages/david_ratledge/tm11.htm Telescope] Article on Stonyhurst's telescope 2002. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The observatory is today used for astronomical purposes again, whilst also functioning as one of four weather stations used by the [[Met Office]] to provide central England temperature data (CET).&lt;ref&gt;[http://badc.nerc.ac.uk/data/cet/ Met Office] Retrieved 21 Oct 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arts==
===Music, Drama and Art===
Music plays a prominent role in school life. All those entering the school in Lower Grammar (year nine) are obliged to learn to play an orchestral instrument.&lt;ref name=music&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_15.shtml Music] Stonyhurst: information on music at the school 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; There are two choirs: the Chapel Choir, which sings regularly at mass, and the ''Schola Cantorum'', composed of teachers and pupils, which sings at concerts and public events such as the May celebration in the college amphitheatre.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1124.shtml May Celebration] Stonyhurst: article on May celebrations, May 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Pupils participate in the school orchestra and various bands, whilst the staff band is a notable feature of the Poetry Banquet and Rhetoric Ball.&lt;ref name=music/&gt;

Drama is equally important, with plays staged throughout the school year, the main performance being at [[School life at Stonyhurst College#Notable events in the school year|Great Academies]], whilst some students take Theatre Studies as an additional [[GCE Advanced Level|AS Level]] subject.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_14.shtml Drama] Stonyhurst: information on drama at the school 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The college has a traditional theatre, the Academy Room, and a high-tech theatre built at [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall|St Mary's Hall]] as part of the Centenaries Appeal in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.173&lt;/ref&gt; The latter plays host to the annual [[Ribble Valley]] International Piano Week.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tictec.co.uk/promoters/ribble-valley-international-piano-week/40 RVIPW] Ribble Valley International Piano Week 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; A number of former pupils have gone on to achieve success upon the stage, including [[Academy Award|OSCAR]]-winning actor and director [[Charles Laughton]] and [[BAFTA]]-winning director and producer [[Peter Glenville]].&lt;ref name=TEM188&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 pp.188-192&lt;/ref&gt;

Art is an important part of the curriculum, and is compulsory for those in Lower Grammar (year nine).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_16.shtml Stonyhurst: art.] Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; There is a dedicated art studio in addition to a separate design and technology centre. Student artwork is displayed on the walls of the Lower Gallery, including a portrait of the [[Queen Elizabeth II|Queen]] painted by Isobel Bidwell during the [[Golden Jubilee#For Queen Elizabeth II|Golden Jubilee]] year; upon receipt of a copy, the Queen's [[lady-in-waiting]] said that &quot;The Queen was delighted to see the painting and know that it is on display in the school&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.thisislancashire.co.uk/2003/2/10/567916.html Lancashire Telegraph] News article on Queen's portrait 2003. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Literary associations===
Stonyhurst has a number of literary associations: its setting has provided inspiration for poets and authors who include former classics teacher [[Gerard Manley Hopkins]], whose poems feature details of the local countryside, and former pupil [[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]] whose &quot;Baskerville Hall&quot; was modelled on Stonyhurst Hall, and who named [[Sherlock Holmes|Sherlock Holmes']] nemesis, Moriarty, after a fellow pupil.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_947.shtml Conan Doyle] Stonyhurst: article on Conan Doyle 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=clitheroe&gt;[http://www.oldclitheroe.co.uk/page172.htm Old Clitheroe] Article on Tolkien &amp; Conan Doyle 2001. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; [[J. R. R. Tolkien]] wrote part of ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]'' in a classroom on the Upper Gallery during his stay at the college where his son taught Classics; his &quot;[[Middle-earth]]&quot; is said to resemble the local area, whilst there are specific resonances in names such as &quot;Shire Lane&quot;, (the name of a road in Hurst Green) and the &quot;River Shirebourn&quot; (the Shireburns built Stonyhurst).&lt;ref name=clitheroe/&gt; [[Poet Laureate]] [[Alfred Austin]], and the poet [[Oliver St John Gogarty]] (&quot;Stately plump Buck Mulligan&quot; in James Joyce's Ulysses) were educated at the school, (as were the sons of [[Oscar Wilde]] and [[Evelyn Waugh]]).&lt;ref name=TEM188/&gt; [[George Archer-Shee]], at the centre of [[Terence Rattigan]]'s play ''[[The Winslow Boy]]'', is an alumnus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.thisislancashire.co.uk/1999/11/24/749773.html This is Lancashire]. Retrieved 7 February 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

The school runs its own publication company, St Omer's Press, which publishes religious literature, and first began when the college was located at [[Saint-Omer|St Omer]] in [[Flanders]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stomerspress.co.uk/ St Omers Press] St Omer's Press website 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Charles_Laughton.jpg|[[Charles Laughton]] photographed by [[Carl Van Vechten]]
Image:GerardManleyHopkins.jpg|[[Gerard Manley Hopkins]]
Image:Conan_doyle.jpg|[[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]]
Image:Tolkien_1916.jpg|[[J. R. R. Tolkien]] in 1916
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Sport==
Pupils are required to participate in games on a regular basis. The school plays [[rugby union]] and other sporting activities are on offer, and since turning fully co-educational, [[hockey]] and [[rounders]] have widened the sports programme.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_20.shtml Sport] Stonyhurst: article on sport 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stonyhurst College Rugby Union Football Club (SCRUFC)===
Rugby has played a big part in the life of the school, despite only supplanting football as the school's primary sport in 1921.&lt;ref name=Hewitson/&gt; All boys are encouraged to play when they enter Lower Grammar but are not required to play throughout their time at the school. Stonyhurst has a successful rugby season, with games well supported by pupils, staff and parents. Sporting rivalry is particularly prominent against [[Ampleforth College]], [[Mount St Mary's College]] and [[Sedbergh School]]. The Stonyhurst Sevens take place annually, attracting large crowds and numerous teams from all over the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.theboltonnews.co.uk/2003/3/12/562120.html Bolton News] News article, 12 March 2003. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The school has produced fifteen international rugby players (England (5), Ireland (6), Scotland (1) Italy (1), the USA (1) and the Bahamas (1) ), as well as players for the Barbarians and the British and Irish Lions.&lt;ref name=TEM188/&gt; Most recently they include Iain Balshaw and [[Kyran Bracken]], who both played for England when they won the [[2003 Rugby World Cup]], whilst another member of that team, [[Will Greenwood]], went to [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall]], where his mother taught [[mathematics|maths]] until 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saintmaryshall.com/article_286.shtml Susan Greenwood] SMH: article on Mrs Greenwood, June 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Current pupils of the school have won places to represent Spain, the Irish Exiles and the Welsh Exiles (under 19s).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1056.shtml Rugby] Stonyhurst: article on school rugby players 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; A number of old boys have also played at varsity level and have won [[blue (university sport)|blues]] for Oxford or Cambridge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_447.shtml Stonyhurst: Cantab Blue.] Stonyhurst: article on Cambridge Blue 2005. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ourfc.org/news/index.asp?ID=541&amp;Status=Display OURFC] Pierre Lafayeedney O.S. mentioned in OURFC article 11 March 2006. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Stonyhurst has had well known coaches, including former England coaches [[Ben Sanders]], [[Dick Greenwood]] and [[Brian Ashton (rugby player)|Brian Ashton]] who coached the first XV.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rugby&quot;/&gt;

Many pupils have represented Stonyhurst in the England Schools U16 and U18 Rugby teams.  These include Daniel Mckenzie and Andy Fuller who both received an U18 England cap in 2000.

[[Image:Stonyhurst Ambulacrum.jpg|thumb|The Ambulacrum, used for sport, the CCF, and indoor marquee, one of the first structures of its kind in Britain, built in 1851.]]

===Stonyhurst Football===
Stonyhurst Football, inherited from the [[College of St Omer]] (along with Stonyhurst Cricket), was played between the handball walls on the Playground.&lt;ref name=Hewitson/&gt; The game was discontinued with the advent of [[Association Football]] but was re-established in 1988 when a &quot;Grand Match&quot; was played at Great Academies; traditionally a &quot;Grand Match&quot; was played on [[Shrove Tuesday]] and was the primary Stonyhurst Football match of the season.&lt;ref name=TEM116&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.116&lt;/ref&gt; The teams were England vs France (although during the [[Crimean War]] England vs Russia was played and more recently England vs Ireland was played in the 1980s).&lt;ref name=TEM116/&gt; The last game took place in 1995. [http://www.flickr.com/photos/nico/3325111/ See: photographs of Stonyhurst Football]

===Sporting facilities===
*all-weather astro-turf sports pitch
*9 hole golf course
*shooting range
*2 ponds used for canoeing and fishing
*25m swimming pool
*2 squash courts
*9 tennis courts
*4 cricket pitches
*8 rugby pitches
*2 football pitches
*weight-training gymnasium
*2 indoor sports halls (one at [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall|SMH]])
*large estate used for cross-country, orienteering, clay-pigeon shooting and rambling

===Rhetoric vs. Hodder cricket and rounders===
Towards the end of the Summer Term each year, Rhetoric boys issue a challenge, written in Latin, to the boys in preparatory at [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall]], inviting them to compete in a cricket match. Preparatory respond in turn, also in Latin. The Rhetoricians take part wearing fancy dress, and are traditionally 'defeated' by preparatory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saintmaryshall.com/article_173.shtml Rhetoric vs Hodder cricket] SMH news article on Rhetoric vs Hodder cricket May 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003, the tradition was adopted by the girls who issued a Latin challenge to preparatory girls inviting them to compete at rounders.

==Military==
[[Image:Stonyhurst war memorial.jpg|thumb|left|The war memorial, by [[Gilbert Ledward]] ]]

===Officer Training Corps (OTC)===
The Stonyhurst [[Officer Training Corps]] assembled for the first time on Tuesday 16 October 1900, in the Ambulacrum, overseen by The First Volunteer Battalion, the [[East Lancashire Regiment]] who gave instruction in drill and musketry.&lt;ref name=otc&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_463.shtml OTC &amp; CCF] Stonyhurst: information on the OTC &amp; CCF 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The original uniform was scarlet with a white piping and slouch hat, which was changed to khaki before the [[First World War]].&lt;ref name=otc/&gt; The Corps was granted the honour of representation at the Coronation of 1910 and sent members to the Royal Review at Windsor in 1911.&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.123&lt;/ref&gt; It also appeared on parade annually for the spectacle of the [[Corpus Christi (feast)|Corpus Christi]] celebrations until the practice became obsolete after [[Vatican II]].&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.139&lt;/ref&gt;

===Combined Cadet Corps (CCF)===
After the [[Second World War]], school OTCs were succeeded by the [[Combined Cadet Force]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mod.uk/defenceinternet/aboutdefence/whatwedo/reserveforcesandcadets/drfc/historyofthecombinedcadetforce.htm Ministry of Defence] MOD article on CCF History 2005. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Stonyhurst's is run from the College Armoury adjoining the Ambulacrum and Shooting Range, led by a team of officers under a Major assigned to the school.&lt;ref name=otc/&gt; It meets weekly on a Thursday afternoon and comprises the following platoons named after Stonyhurst's seven [[Victoria Cross]] winners:&lt;ref name=otc/&gt;

====Junior company====
*Costello Platoon [[Edmond William Costello|(Lieutenant Edmund William COSTELLO V.C., Matakand, India 1897)]]
*Coury Platoon [[Gabriel George Coury|(Second Lieutenant George Gabriel COURY V.C., Guillemont, Somme 1916)]]
*Liddell Platoon [[John Aidan Liddell|(Captain John Aiden LIDDELL V.C, Ostend, Belgium 1915)]]
*Kenna Platoon [[Paul Aloysius Kenna|(Captain Paul Aloysius KENNA V.C., Khartoum, Sudan 1898)]]

====Senior company====
*Dease Platoon [[Maurice James Dease|(Lieutenant Maurice James DEASE V.C., Mons, Belgium 1914)]]
*Jackman Platoon [[James Joseph Bernard Jackman|(Captain James Joseph Bernard JACKMAN V.C., Ed Duda,Tobruk,1941)]]
*Andrews Platoon [[Harold Marcus Ervine-Andrews|(Captain Harold Marcus ERVINE-ANDREWS V.C., Dunkirk 1940)]]
*Support Platoon

Those in Grammar Playroom (year ten) are automatically enrolled in the CCF and are given the option of continuing at the end of the year, following a summer camp which takes place at a local barracks.&lt;ref name=otc/&gt; Training involves a range of activities such as drill (marching and related manoeuvres), shooting, learning how to assemble and clean weapons, tactical planning and team work.&lt;ref name=otc/&gt; The school supplies pupils with uniform, the orderliness of which is rigorously enforced and inspected each week. Each platoon is led by a [[Junior Under Officer]], his [[sergeant]] and [[corporal]]s who are sixth form students.&lt;ref name=otc/&gt;

===Military careers===
{{See also|List of Stonyhurst alumni/ae}}

In recent years, a number of pupils have distinguished themselves as members of the CCF{{Clarify|date=July 2010}} and gone on to receive places at the [[Royal Military Academy Sandhurst]].&lt;ref name=times&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/court_and_social/article3728952.ece Sandhurst], Times online article mentioning O.S., 12 April 2008. Retrieved 10 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=times2&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/court_and_social/the_hitch/article402793.ece The Sovereign's Parade, RMAS] Times online article mentioning O.S., 15 December 2004. Retrieved 10 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gordon&gt;[http://www.gordonpoole.com/?artistID=1261 Speaker] at GordonPoole, retrieved 10 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; This follows a long tradition of service from Stonyhurst pupils: many [[List of Stonyhurst alumni/ae|''Old Stonyhurst (O.S.)'']]  were killed in the two World Wars and are commemorated on the war memorial at the end of the Upper Gallery.&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 pp.150-1&lt;/ref&gt; The Stonyhurst War Records were published in their honour. A memorial at the top of the main staircase records the names of the six [[List of Stonyhurst alumni/ae|O.S.]] killed in the [[Boer War]].

== School organisation ==
{{Main|School life at Stonyhurst College}}

===Playroom system===
[[Image:LGPlayroom.jpg|thumb|Lower Grammar Playroom in 2006]]
Unlike most English public schools, Stonyhurst is organised horizontally by year groups (known as playrooms) rather than vertically by houses, although the girls are also split into junior and senior houses.&lt;ref name=playrooms&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_815.shtml Playrooms] Stonyhurst: information on playrooms 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Each playroom has an assigned playroom master, with each cohort moving through the playrooms, having a sequence of playroom masters (rather than a single housemaster).&lt;ref name=playrooms/&gt;

Currently, the College has the following playrooms, following the Roman order of learning:

* Lower Grammar Playroom ('LG' 13-14)
* Grammar Playroom (14-15)
* Syntax Playroom (15-16, GCSE Year)
* Poetry Playroom (16-17)
* Rhetoric Playroom (17-18)

During the school's history the following playrooms or years have also existed:

* Philosophy ('Phils')
* Upper Syntax
* Humanities
* Upper Grammar
* Middle Grammar

===Lines===
In addition to the horizontal division of the school into playrooms, there is also a vertical grouping which cuts through the year groups, the &quot;lines&quot;, and is used mostly for competitive purposes in sport and music.&lt;ref&gt;TT.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.156&lt;/ref&gt; The Lines and colours are as follows:
* '''Campion''' (Red) (named after [[Edmund Campion|St Edmund Campion]])
* '''St Omers''' (Yellow, though Brown for sporting attire) (named after [[Saint-Omer|St Omer]], the town the school was founded in)
* '''Shireburn''' (Green) (named after the Shireburn family which built Stonyhurst)
* '''Weld''' (Blue) (named after Thomas Weld who donated Stonyhurst to the Jesuits)

==Notable events in the school year==
[[Image:Top Refectory.jpg|thumb|left|Top Refectory, today used for social functions]]
{{Main|School life at Stonyhurst College}}

The '''''Ascensio Scholarum''''', inherited from the [[College of St Omer]], in its present form, is the opening address of the headmaster at the beginning of the year to the entire school gathered in the Academy Room.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_940.shtml Beginning of year] Stonyhurst: article mentioning modern ''ascensio'' 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Previously, it was a formal transition for pupils from one playroom to the next at the beginning of the year, which involved a pupil from each year announcing to the playroom of the year below them that the next playroom had been vacated by the senior pupils.&lt;ref name=handbook24&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.24&lt;/ref&gt; The students and their belongings would then move up to their next playroom.&lt;ref name=handbook24/&gt; This is how it acquired the name, &quot;the ascension of the school&quot;.

'''Great Academies''' takes place annually at the end of the first half of the Summer Term. Although different in its present form, it is a continuation of a tradition begun at St Omers, with the first taking place at Stonyhurst on 6 August 1795.&lt;ref name=Hewitson/&gt; Today, it is an occasion when the school is on display - there are exhibitions, musical performances, the school play, sporting events, as well as prize-giving and the headmaster's speech, culminating with the Rhetoric Ball and Rhetoric Mass the following morning.&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.174&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stonyhurst Association==
{{See also|Charities of Stonyhurst College}}
[[Image:Stonyhurst gardens2006.jpg|thumb|right|The South Front viewed from the gardens]]
After less formal arrangements had been made for many years, the Association was formed in 1879.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stonyhurst College 1963 p.38&quot;/&gt;  Its primary objective is to foster a strong spirit of union amongst past pupils and friends of Stonyhurst, which has been achieved in a variety of ways reflecting the spirit of succeeding generations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guidestar.org.uk/gs_summary.aspx?CCReg=292122&amp;strquery=stonyhurst Guidestar] Stonyhurst Associoation entry on Guidestar 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, there has been a strong charitable emphasis, embedded with similar developments at the College.&lt;ref name=association&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_27.shtml Stonyhurst Association] Stonyhurst: information on the Association 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; This was formalised in 1985, when the Association was granted charitable status by the [[Charity Commission]].  It also supports a number of charities connected to the school including [[Eagle Aid]].&lt;ref name=association/&gt;

===Alumni===
{{Main|List of Stonyhurst alumni/ae}}
Stonyhurst has educated prominent individuals in every area, from statesmen to sportsmen, and actors to archbishops.&lt;ref name=TEM188/&gt; Seven alumni have been awarded the Victoria Cross, the highest award for gallantry; paintings of them adorn the walls of the Top Refectory in the school.&lt;ref name=kirby/&gt;

Notable alumni include:

*[[Charles Carroll of Carrollton]], signatory of the U.S. [[Declaration of Independence]]
*[[Sir Arthur Conan Doyle]], author of [[Sherlock Holmes]]
*[[Thomas Garnet|St Thomas Garnet SJ]], canonized saint and protomartyr of St Omers, one of the [[Forty Martyrs of England and Wales]]
*[[Joseph Mary Plunkett]], Irish signatory of the [[Irish Proclamation of Independence]] who played a leading part in the [[Easter Rising]], for which he was executed
*[[Frederick Weld|Sir Frederick Weld]], Prime Minister of New Zealand
*[[Eduardo López de Romaña|Eduardo Lopez de Romaña]], President of Peru

Alumni currently in the public eye include:
*[[Joe Ansbro]], Scottish Rugby International
*[[Crispian Hollis]], [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Portsmouth|Bishop of Portsmouth]]
*[[Mark Thompson]], [[Director General of the BBC]]
*[[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]], satirist, BAFTA winner
*[[Tom Morris (director)|Tom Morris]], theatre director, producer and writer, and Tony Award winner
*[[Matt Greenhalgh]], screenwriter, BAFTA winner
*[[Tim Hetherington]], photographer, Oscar nominee

==Notable masters==
*[[Brian Ashton (rugby player)|Brian Ashton]], history master and England rugby coach.&lt;ref Name=Rugby/&gt;
*[[Dick Greenwood]], Assistant Bursar and England Rugby coach.&lt;ref Name=Rugby&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1000.shtml Rugby Coaches] Stonyhurst: article on rugby coaches 2007. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Christopher Hollis]], assistant master, history master (1925–1935), author, politician and president of the [[Oxford Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://economia.unipv.it/harrod/edition/editionstuff/rfh.4b0.htm] Biography on Hollis. Retrieved 7 February 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Gerard Manley Hopkins]], classics master and poet.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gerardmanleyhopkins.org/Lectures_2007/hopkins_priest.html+gerard+manley+hopkins+stonyhurst&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=10&amp;client=safari Gerard Manley Hopkins.org. Retrieved 7 February 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Stephen Joseph Perry]], astronomy master.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fr. Walter Sidgreaves 1837-1919&quot;/&gt;
*[[Pietro Angelo Secchi]], astronomy master, astrophysicist, and director of the [[Vatican Observatory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;/&gt;
*[[George Tyrrell]], philosophy master and Roman Catholic modernist.&lt;ref Name=Brit/&gt;

===Headmasters===
Since the College's foundation in [[Flanders]] in 1593, there have been seventy-eight headmasters, (variably known as presidents, rectors, superiors and directors).&lt;ref&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.193&lt;/ref&gt; Until the appointment of Giles Mercer in 1985, the headmaster had always been a member of the Society of Jesus. There have been three lay headmasters.&lt;ref name=&quot;rectors&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.swan.ac.uk/history/research/spencer_project/historical/rectors.html
|author=Maurice Whitehead
|title=Rectors, presidents and headmasters of the English Jesuit college of St Omers, Bruges, Liège and Stonyhurst since 1593
|date=16 January 2006
|accessdate=2006-03-11
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20041221180953/http://www.swan.ac.uk/history/research/spencer_project/historical/rectors.html |archivedate = December 21, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{col-begin}} style=&quot;font-size:100%;&quot;
{{col-2}}

:'''''St Omers, Bruges, Liège (1593-1794)'''''

:''See: [[College of St. Omer#Rectors and Superiors|Heads of St Omers, Bruges, Liège]]''

:'''''Stonyhurst (1794-present)'''''

:''Presidents''

:[[Marmaduke Stone]] SJ (1794-1808)
:Nicholas Sewall SJ (1808-1813)
:John Weld SJ (1813-1816)
:Nicholas Sewall SJ (1816-1817)

:''Rector and Headmaster''

:[[Charles Plowden]] SJ (1817-1819)
:Joseph Tristram SJ (1819-1827)
:Richard Norris SJ (1827-1832)
:Richard Parker SJ (1832-1836)
:John Brownbill SJ (1836-1839)
:Francis Daniel SJ (1839-1841)
:Andrew Barrow SJ (1841-1845)
:Richard Norris SJ (1845-1846)
:Henry Walmesley SJ (1846-1847)
:Richard Sumner SJ (1847-1848)
:Francis Clough SJ (1848-1861)
:Joseph Johnson SJ (1861-1868)
:Charles Henry SJ (1868-1869)
:Edward Purbick SJ (1869-1879)

{{col-2}}

:William Eyre SJ (1879-1885)
:Reginald Colley SJ (1885-1891)
:Herman Walmesley SJ (1891-1898)&lt;ref name=TEM_140/&gt;
:Joseph Browne SJ (1898-1906)
:Pedro Gordon SJ (1906-1907)
:William Bodkin SJ (1907-1916)
:Edward O'Connor SJ (1916-1924)
:Walter Weld SJ (1924-1929)
:Richard Worsley SJ (1929-1932)
:Edward O'Connor SJ (1932-1938)
:Leo Belton SJ (1938-1945)
:Bernard Swindells SJ (1945-1952)
:Francis Vavasour SJ (1952-1958)
:Desmond Boyle SJ (1958-1961)

:''Headmasters''

:[[Frederick Turner SJ|Frederick J. Turner]] SJ (1961-1963)
:George Earle SJ (1963-1971)
:Michael Bossy SJ (1971-1985)
:Giles Mercer (1985-1996)
:Adrian Aylward (1996-2006)
:Andrew Johnson (2006 - present)

:'''''Headmasters of Hodder Place &amp; St Mary's Hall (1807-present)'''''

:''See: [[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall#Headmasters|Headmasters of Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall]]''

{{col-2}}
{{col-end}}

----

[[Image:Stonyhurst College.jpg|725px|thumb|centre|The West Front]]

==See also==
{{Commons category|Stonyhurst College}}
{{Portal box|England|Schools}}
{{col-begin}} style=&quot;font-size:100%;&quot;
{{col-2}}

*[[College of St Omer]]
*[[Stonyhurst|Stonyhurst Estate]]
*[[History of Stonyhurst College]]
*[[Religious life at Stonyhurst College]]
*[[Libraries and collections of Stonyhurst College]]
*[[School life at Stonyhurst College]]
*[[Stonyhurst Saint Mary's Hall]]
*[[Hodder Place]]
*[[List of Stonyhurst Alumni/ae]]
*[[Stonyhurst Gospel]]
*[[Charities of Stonyhurst College]]
*[[Stonyhurst Observatory]]
*[[Stonyhurst disks]]

{{col-2}}

*[[List of Victoria Crosses by School]]
*[[Beaumont College]]
*[[Catholic Church]]
*[[Society of Jesus]]
*[[St Ignatius of Loyola|St Ignatius, founder of the Jesuits]]
*[[Aloysius Gonzaga|St Aloysius Gonzaga, patron saint]]
*[[Gordianus and Epimachus|St Gordianus, interred in the school]]
*[[English Heritage]]
*[[Hurst Green, Lancashire|Hurst Green]]
*[[Forest of Bowland]]

{{col-2}}
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Tolkien&quot;&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/lancashire/lifestyle/2003/12/12/tolkien.shtml BBC Lancashire] BBC article on Stonyhurst &amp; Tolkien connections 2003. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=cathrob&gt;[http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Catholic_Encyclopedia_%281913%29/Robert_Persons?oldid=404094 Robert Parsons],'' Catholic Encyclopaedia'' (1913). Retrieved 9 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook36&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.36&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hewitson&quot;&gt;A. Hewitson, ''Stonyhurst College, Present and Past: Its History, Discipline, Treasures and Curiosities'', (Preston: the Chronicle office, Fishergate. 1888, second edition)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Hewitson 2&quot;&gt;A. Hewitson, ''Stonyhurst College, Present and Past: Its History, Discipline, Treasures and Curiosities'', (Preston: the Chronicle office, Fishergate. 1888, second edition) pp.19-182&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;IndSch 1&quot;&gt;[http://www.indschools.co.uk/cgi-bin/woda/is97new.pl/Show?_id=stonyhurstcollegebb79pz UK Independent Schools Directory] Stonyhurst entry 2008. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;IndSch Stony 2&quot;&gt;[http://www.independentschools.com/england/stonyhurst-college_488.html#full Independent Schools] Stonyhurst entry on Independent Schools 2008. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ISBI&quot;&gt;[http://www.isbi.com/isbi-viewschool/1585-Stonyhurst_College-1.html ISBI Schools] Stonyhurst entry on ISBI 2008. Retrieved 18 February 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;isc&quot;&gt;[http://www.isc.co.uk/school_StonyhurstCollege_Clitheroe.htm ISC] ISC website. Retrieved 26 August 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jesuit org&quot;&gt;[http://www.jesuit.org.uk/schools/stonyhurst_smh.htm UK Jesuits] Stonyhurst entry on UK Jesuit schools 2008. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Jesuit 2&quot;&gt;[http://www.jesuit.org.uk/schools/vision.htm UK Jesuits] Jesuit school Vision Statement 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kirby&quot;&gt;H.L. Kirby &amp; R.R. Walsh, ''The Seven VCs of Stonyhurst College'', (T.H.C.L. Books, Blackburn 1987) ISBN 0-948494-04-2&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;legacies&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_180.shtml Legacies] Stonyhurst: information on legacies 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;New Advent 1&quot;&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14309b.htm Catholic Encyclopaedia] Stonyhurst entry in the Catholic Encyclopaedia (1912). Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Saint Marys Hall&quot;&gt;[http://www.saintmaryshall.com/article_169.shtml Hodder Celebrations] SMH news article on Hodder anniversary 2006. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;spiritual 1&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_25.shtml Spiritual] Stonyhurst: spiritual information 2008. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;spiritual 2&quot;&gt;In particular, students are encouraged to take part in daily prayer, retreats, meditations, celebration of the sacraments, pilgrimages and to be actively involved in [[Charities of Stonyhurst College|charity work]].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 1&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1648.shtml Exam Results] Stonyhurst: Exam results, retrieved 36 August 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 3&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/contact.shtml Visits &amp; Contacts] Stonyhurst: visitor information 2008. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 4&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_31.shtml History] Stonyhurst: school history 2008. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 6&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.46&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 7&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) pp.11-12&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 8&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.18&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 9&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.22&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 10&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.20&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 11&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_384.shtml St Gordianus] Stonyhurst: information on St Gordianus 2006. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 12&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_775.shtml Sodality Chapel] Stonyhurst: article on the rededication of the Sodality Chapel 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony 13&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/article_1195.shtml Rosary Garden] Stonyhurst: article on the opening of the Rosary Garden, May 2008. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stonyhurst College 1963 p.38&quot;&gt;The Authorities of Stonyhurst College, ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire. Third edition 1963) p.38&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Stony welcome&quot;&gt;[http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk/welcome.shtml Welcome] Stonyhurst: welcome page. Retrieved 17 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 25-39&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 pp.25-39&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM41-54&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 pp.41-54&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 140&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.140&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 152&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.152&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 164&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.164&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 178&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.178&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 181&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.181&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 188&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.188&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 194&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.194&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;TEM 195&quot;&gt;T.E. Muir, ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire. Second edition, 2006) ISBN 0-9553592-0-1 p.195&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
* Chadwick, Hubert, S.J. (1962), ''St Omers to Stonyhurst'', (Burns &amp; Oats), No ISBN
* Walsh, R.R. (1989), ''Stonyhurst War Record 1935-45'' (T.H.C.L. Blackburn), ISBN 0-948494-08-5
* Muir, T.E. (2006) ''Stonyhurst'', (St Omers Press, Gloucestershire) second edition, ISBN 0-9553592-0-1
* Kirby, Henry L. and Walsh, R. Raymond (1987), ''The Seven V.C.s of Stonyhurst College'', (T.H.C.L. Blackburn), ISBN 0-948494-04-2
* The Authorities of Stonyhurst College (1963), ''A Stonyhurst Handbook for Visitors and Others'', (Stonyhurst, Lancashire), third edition, No ISBN
* Hewitson, A. (1878), ''Stonyhurst College, Present and Past: Its History, Discipline, Treasures and Curiosities'', (Preston: The Chronicle office), second edition, No ISBN

==External links==
* [http://www.stonyhurst.ac.uk Stonyhurst College website]
* [http://www.saintmaryshall.com/ Stonyhurst St Mary's Hall website]
* [http://www.stjohnsbeaumont.org.uk/ St John's Beaumont website]
* [http://www.osforums.org.uk OSForums unofficial bulletin board for alumni]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14309b.htm Stonyhurst's entry in the 1912 Catholic Encyclopaedia]
* [http://www.stomerspress.co.uk/index.htm St Omers Press]
* [http://www.ribblevalley.gov.uk/site/scripts/documents_info.php?documentID=564 Stonyhurst in the film [[Three Men and a Little Lady]]]
* [http://www.meteogroup.co.uk/uk/home/weather/world_weather/city_weather/city/99060/stonyhurst.html?cityID=99060 Stonyhurst Weather Station Meteogroup entry]
* [http://badc.nerc.ac.uk/cgi-bin/midas_stations/station_details.cgi.py?id=1119&amp;db=midas_stations Stonyhurst Weather Station Met Office entry]

{{Coord|53.8471|N|2.4713|W|type:landmark|display=title}}
{{LancashireSchools}}

{{Good article}}

[[Category:Stonyhurst College|*]]
[[Category:Old Stonyhursts]]
[[Category:Educational charities]]
[[Category:Boarding schools in Lancashire]]
[[Category:Catholic boarding schools]]
[[Category:Jesuit universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic secondary schools in England]]
[[Category:Independent schools in Lancashire]]
[[Category:Member schools of the Headmasters' and Headmistresses' Conference]]
[[Category:Schools with Combined Cadet Forces]]
[[Category:Co-educational boarding schools]]
[[Category:1593 establishments in England]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1593]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Lancashire]]
[[Category:Grade I listed educational buildings]]
[[Category:Schools in Clitheroe]]
[[Category:Schools in Ribble Valley]]
[[Category:Forest of Bowland]]
[[Category:Member schools of the Independent Association of Preparatory Schools]]

[[es:Stonyhurst College]]
[[fr:Stonyhurst College]]
[[it:Stonyhurst College]]
[[no:Stonyhurst College]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
