<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="867860" ns="0" title="Netbook"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Psion device|Psion netBook}}
{{pp-move-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Update|date=September 2011}}

[[File:HP 2133 Mini-Note PC (front view compare with pencil).jpg|thumb|300px|HP 2133 Mini-Note PC netbook&lt;br&gt;(front view, compared to a pencil)]]
[[File:HP Mini 1000.jpg|thumb|A Hewlett-Packard Mini 1000 netbook computer, a type of [[laptop|notebook computer]]]]

'''Netbooks'''  are a category of small, lightweight, [[Legacy-free PC|legacy-free]], and inexpensive [[laptop|laptop computer]]s.

At their inception in late 2007 &lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.computerworld.com/what_was_the_first_netbook ''ComputerWorld'', &quot;What was the first netbook?&quot; May 11, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; as smaller notebooks optimized for low weight and low cost&lt;ref name=&quot;btwsj&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Cheap PCs Weigh on Microsoft |work=Business Technologies |publisher=[[The Wall Street Journal]] |date=December 8, 2008 |url=http://blogs.wsj.com/biztech/2008/12/08/cheap-pcs-weigh-on-microsoft/}}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;mdash; netbooks omitted certain features (e.g., the [[optical drive]]), featured smaller screens and keyboards, and offered reduced computing power when compared to a full-sized laptop. Over the course of their evolution, netbooks have ranged in size from below 5&quot; screen diagonal&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elitezoom.com/umid-netbook-only-48-display.html UMID Netbook Only 4.8″].&lt;/ref&gt; to 12&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mobilewhack.com/asus-set-to-release-101-inch-netbook-in-japan/ Asus Set to Release 10.1 Inch Netbook in Japan].&lt;/ref&gt; A typical weight is {{nowrap|1 kg}} ({{nowrap|2&amp;ndash;3 pounds}}). Often significantly less expensive than other [[laptop]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;pricegrabber&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Netbook Trends and Solid-State Technology Forecast |publisher=pricegrabber.com |pages=7 |format=[[PDF]] |url=https://mr.pricegrabber.com/Netbook_Trends_and_SolidState_Technology_January_2009_CBR.pdf |accessdate=2009-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; by mid-2009, some wireless data carriers began to offer netbooks to users &quot;free of charge&quot;, with an extended service contract purchase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Light and Cheap, Netbooks Are Poised to Reshape PC Industry |publisher=[[The New York Times]] |date=April 1, 2009 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/02/technology/02netbooks.html |quote=&quot;AT&amp;T announced on Tuesday that customers in Atlanta could get a type of compact PC called a netbook for just 50 US$ if they signed up for an Internet service plan...&quot; &amp;mdash; “The era of a perfect Internet computer for 99 US$ is coming this year,” said Jen-Hsun Huang, chief executive of Nvidia, a maker of PC graphics chips that is trying to adapt to the new technological order. |first1=Ashlee |last1=Vance |first2=Matt |last2=Richtel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the short period since their appearance, netbooks have grown in size and features, now converging with new smaller, lighter notebooks and [[subnotebook]]s. By August 2009, when comparing a Dell netbook to a Dell notebook, CNET called netbooks &quot;nothing more than smaller, cheaper notebooks,&quot; noting, &quot;the specs are so similar that the average shopper would likely be confused as to why one is better than the other,&quot; and &quot;the only conclusion is that there really is no distinction between the devices.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnnogg&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Ogg |first=Erica |title=Time to drop the Netbook label |publisher=[[Cable News Network|CNN]] |date=August 20, 2009 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/TECH/ptech/08/20/cnet.drop.netbook.label/index.html |accessdate=2010-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Initially offered with compact versions of [[Linux]] or [[Windows XP]], netbooks now typically use [[Windows 7 Starter]] which Microsoft sells at a lower price but restricts to lower spec hardware.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

== History == 
[[File:ASUS Eee White Alt.jpg|thumb|An [[ASUS Eee PC]] 700, the first mass-produced netbook, used a 7 inch screen.]]
The origins of the netbook can be traced to the [[Network Computer]] (NC) concept of the mid-1990s. In March 1997, Apple Computer introduced the [[eMate 300]] as a subcompact laptop that was a cross between the [[Apple Newton]] [[PDA]] and a conventional laptop computer.  A year later the eMate was discontinued, along with all other Newton devices, with the advent of Apple's 'four boxes' product strategy that included the [[iMac]] and [[iBook]].  More recently, [[Psion]]'s now-discontinued [[Psion netBook|netBook]] line, the [[OLPC XO-1]] (initially called US$100 laptop) and the [[Palm Foleo]] were all small, portable, network-enabled computers.&lt;ref name=&quot;PCMag1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Bajarin |first=Tim |authorlink=Tim Bajarin |title=Jeff Hawkins and the World's First Netbook |publisher=PCMagazine.com |date=November 21, 2008
|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2335072,00.asp}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PCMag2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.technewsworld.com/story/31758.html?wlc=1235434538 Psion's NetBook Pro Abandons EPOC in Favor of Windows CE].&lt;/ref&gt; The generic use of the term &quot;netbook&quot;, however, began in 2007 when [[Asus]] unveiled the [[ASUS Eee PC]]. Originally designed for emerging markets, the {{convert|23|x|17|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} device weighed about {{convert|0.9|kg|lb|0|abbr=on}} and featured a {{convert|7|in|cm|abbr=on}} display, a keyboard approximately 85% the size of a normal keyboard, a [[solid-state drive]] and a custom version of [[Linux]] with a simplified [[GUI|user interface]] geared towards netbook use.&lt;ref name=&quot;PCMag2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Bajarin |first=Tim |title=Netbooks vs. Notebooks |publisher = PCMagazine.com |date=September 12, 2008 |url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2330274,00.asp}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the Eee PC, [[Everex]] launched its Linux-based [[CloudBook]]; [[Windows XP]] and [[Windows Vista]] models were also introduced and [[Micro-Star International|MSI]] released the [[MSI Wind Netbook|Wind]] - others soon followed suit.

The [[OLPC]] project, known for its innovation in producing a durable, cost- and power-efficient netbook for developing countries, is regarded as one of the major factors that led top computer hardware manufacturers to begin creating low-cost netbooks for the consumer market.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pcplus.techradar.com/node/3257 OLPC: The History Of One Laptop Per Child], techradar.com&lt;/ref&gt; When the first [[ASUS Eee PC]] sold over 300,000 units in four months, companies such as [[Dell]] and [[Acer Inc.|Acer]] took note and began producing their own inexpensive netbooks. And while the [[OLPC XO-1]] targets a different audience than do the other manufacturers' netbooks, it appears that [[OLPC]] is now facing competition. Developing countries now have a large choice of vendors, from which they can choose which low-cost netbook they prefer.&lt;ref&gt;Kraemer et al.: &quot;One Laptop Per Child: Vision vs. Reality&quot;, ''Communications of the ACM'', June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Netbook popularity in 2008 (PriceGrabber).png|thumb|250px|Netbook market popularity within laptops in second half of 2008 based on the number of product clicks in the Laptop Subcategory per month by [[PriceGrabber]]&lt;ref name=&quot;pricegrabber&quot; /&gt;]]
By late 2008, netbooks had begun to take [[market share]] away from [[Laptop|notebooks]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hardware.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=08/10/04/1827200 |title=&quot;Netbooks&quot; Move Up In Notebook Rankings |accessdate=2008-10-23 |author=Ian Lamont |date=2008-10-04 |work=Slashdot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to earlier, largely failed attempts to establish mini computers as a new class of mainstream personal computing devices built around comparatively expensive platforms requiring proprietary software applications or imposing severe usability limitations, the recent success of netbooks can also be attributed to the fact that PC technology has now matured enough to allow truly cost optimized implementations with enough performance to suit the needs of a majority of PC users. This is illustrated by the fact that typical system performance of a netbook is on the level of a mainstream PC in 2001, at around one quarter of the cost. While this performance level suffices for most of the user needs, it caused an increased interest in resource-efficient applications such as Google's Chrome, and forced Microsoft to extend availability of Windows XP in order to secure market share. It is estimated that almost thirty times more netbooks were sold in 2008 (11.4 million, 70% of which were in Europe)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umpcportal.com/2008/11/70-of-netbook-sales-are-in-europe 70% of Netbook sales are in Europe].&lt;/ref&gt; than in 2007 (400,000).&lt;ref name=&quot;ee2009-01-10&quot;&gt;[http://www.eetimes.com/news/latest/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=212701251 Analysis: Did Intel underestimate netbook success?]&lt;/ref&gt; For 2009, sales are expected to jump to 35 million, rising to an estimated 139 million in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite press release |title=35 Million Netbook Shipments Expected in 2009: An Era Begins |publisher=[[ABI Research]] |date=2009-01-26 |url= http://www.abiresearch.com/press/1355-35+Million+Netbook+Shipments+Expected+in+2009:+An+Era+Begins |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; This trend is reinforced by the rise of [[web-based application]]s as well as [[Cellular network|mobile networking]] and, according to [[Wired Magazine]], netbooks are evolving into &quot;super-portable laptops for professionals&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.wired.com/gadgets/2009/01/cheap-netbooks.html Puny, Trendy Netbooks Are Growing Up to Suit Business Users]&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Financial crisis of 2007–2010|ongoing recession]] is also helping with the growing sales of netbooks.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.liliputing.com/tag/economy&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Australia]], the [[New South Wales]] [[Department of Education and Training (New South Wales)|Department of Education and Training]], in partnership with [[Lenovo]], are providing Year 9 (high school) students in government high schools with free Lenovo S10e netbooks in 2009 and Lenovo Mini 10 netbooks in 2010 preloaded with software including [[Microsoft Office]] and [[Adobe Systems]]' Creative Suite 4. This is provided under Prime Minister [[Kevin Rudd]]'s Digital Education Revolution, or DER. The netbooks run [[Windows 7]] Enterprise. They have unique tracking devices built-in that the police can use to track the device if it is lost or stolen. The NSW DET retains ownership of these netbooks until the student graduates from Year 12, when the student can keep it. The Government of Trinidad and Tobago-Prime Minister Kamla Persad Bisseser - are also providing free HP laptops to form 1 Students (11 year olds) with the same police trackable software as above.

[[Greece]] is providing all 13 year old students (middle school, or ''[[Gymnasium (school)#Countries with gymnasium schools|gymnasium]]'', freshmen) and their teachers with free netbooks in 2009&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalaid.gr/defaulteng.asp]&lt;/ref&gt; through the &quot;Digital Classroom Initiative&quot;. Students are given one unique coupon each, with which they redeem the netbook of their choice, up to a €450 price ceiling, in participating shops throughout the country. These netbooks come bundled with localised versions of either [[Windows XP]] (or higher) or [[open source]] (e.g. [[Linux]]) operating systems, wired and wireless networking functionality, antivirus protection, preactivated parental controls, and an educational software package.

[[Microsoft]] and [[Intel]] have tried to &quot;cement&quot; netbooks in the low end of the market to protect mainstream notebook PC sales, because they get lower margins on low-cost models. The companies have limited the specifications of netbooks, but despite this [[original equipment manufacturer]]s have announced higher-end netbooks models as of March 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Lai |first=Eric |title=Intel, Microsoft look away as beefed-up netbooks blur lines with notebook PCs |publisher=[[ComputerWorld]] |date=2009-03-30 |url=http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9130757 |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ending in 2008 the report was that the typical netbook featured a {{convert|1.4|kg|lb|0|abbr=on}} weight, a {{convert|9|in|cm|0|abbr=on}} screen, wireless Internet connectivity, [[Linux]] or [[Windows XP]], an [[Intel Atom]] processor, and a cost of less than $400 US.&lt;ref name=&quot;fortune&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Fortt |first=Jon |title=Tech's hope in 2009 - or curse? |publisher=Fortune Magazine |date=December 24, 2008 |url=http://money.cnn.com/2008/12/24/technology/fortt_netbooks.fortune/index.htm |date=2008-12-24 |accessdate=2010-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; A mid-2009 newspaper article&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/businesstechnology/2009579304_ptmacc01.html |work=The Seattle Times |title=Netbooks' price, size make them a worthy Apple rival |first=Glenn |last=Fleishman |date=August 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; said that a typical netbook is {{convert|1.2|kg|lb|1|abbr=on}}, $300 US, and has a {{convert|10|in|cm|abbr=on}} screen,
{{nowrap|1 GB}} of [[random-access memory]], a {{nowrap|160 GB}} [[hard disk drive]], and a wireless transceiver for both home and a mobile network. Buyers drove the netbook market towards larger screens, which grew from {{convert|7|in|cm|abbr=on}} in the original [[Asus Eee PC]] 700 to {{convert|12|in|cm|1|abbr=on}} models in the summer of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asus.com/product.aspx?P_ID=LUiLXJyf53i17Dmh Eee PC 1008HA&lt;/ref&gt;

== Trademarks ==
[[File:OLPC XO next to a Psion Netbook 2.jpg|thumb|[[Psion netBook]]]]
In 1996 [[Psion]] started applying for trademarks for a line of ''netBook'' products that was later released in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prnewswire.co.uk/cgi/release?id=16302 Psion netbook news release].&lt;/ref&gt; International trademarks were issued (including {{US trademark|75215401}} and {{Community trademark|000428250}}) but the models failed to gain popularity&lt;ref name=&quot;arstechnica.com&quot;&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/news/2009/02/save-the-netbooks-fighting-a-trademark-on-extinct-hardware.ars Save the Netbooks: fighting a trademark on extinct hardware]&lt;/ref&gt; and are now discontinued (except for providing accessories, maintenance and support to existing users).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psionteklogix.com/Public.aspx?s=us&amp;p=EOLProducts Psion Teklogix Discontinued Products].&lt;/ref&gt; Similar marks were recently rejected by the [[USPTO]] citing a &quot;likelihood of confusion&quot; under section 2(d).&lt;ref&gt;{{US trademark|77527311}} for 'G NETBOOK' rejected 31 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{US trademark|77580272}} for [[Micro-Star International|MSI]]'s 'WIND NETBOOK'&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{US trademark|77590174}} for [[Coby Electronics Corporation|Coby Electronics]]' 'COBY NETBOOK' rejected 13 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite expert analysis that the mark is &quot;probably [[genericized trademark|generic]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;patenthands&quot;&gt;[http://patenthands.com/ph-blog/how-to-lose-a-trademark-netbook-is-probably-generic/ How To Lose A Trademark: “Netbook” Is Probably Generic] [[Patent Hands]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Psion Teklogix]] issued cease and desist letters on 23 December 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jkontherun.com/2008/12/23/netbook-enthusiast-web-sites-getting-c-d-using-term-netbook/ Netbook enthusiast web sites getting C &amp; D using term “netbook”]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.prnewswire.co.uk/cgi/release?id=16302&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/blog/2008/dec/24/psion-netbook-threats Psion threatens netbook sites over trademarks]&lt;/ref&gt; This was heavily criticised,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crunchgear.com/2008/12/24/netbook-trademarked-already-were-all-doomed/ ‘Netbook’ trademarked already, we’re all doomed].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.wired.com/gadgets/2008/12/using-the-word.html Using the Word 'Netbook' Could Get You Sued].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itwire.com/content/view/22488/53/ Cease and Desist: the netbook war of words].&lt;/ref&gt; prompting the formation of the &quot;Save the Netbooks&quot; [[grassroots]] campaign which worked to reverse the [[Google AdWords]] ban, cancel the trademark and encourage continued generic use of the term.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstechnica.com&quot;/&gt; While preparing a &quot;Petition for Cancellation&quot; of {{US trademark|75215401}} they revealed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcpro.co.uk/news/247933/dell-accuses-psion-of-fraud-over-netbook-claims.html Dell accuses Psion of &quot;fraud&quot; over netbook claims].&lt;/ref&gt; that [[Dell]] had submitted one day before&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/news/2009/02/dell-fights-back-against-psion-netbook-trademark-rampage.ars Dell fights back against Psion netBook trademark rampage].&lt;/ref&gt; on the basis of abandonment, [[genericized trademark|genericness]] and fraud.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crn.com/mobile/214502133 Dell Goes 'Nuclear' Over Netbook Trademark].&lt;/ref&gt; They later revealed [[Psion]]'s counter-suit against [[Intel]], filed on 27 February 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.savethenetbooks.com/2009/03/newsflash-intel-counter-sued-by-psion.html Newsflash: Intel counter-sued by Psion in &quot;netbook&quot; trademark lawsuit; jury trial demanded] [[Save the Netbooks]].&lt;/ref&gt;

It was also revealed around the same time that [[Intel]] had also sued [[Psion Teklogix]] (US &amp; Canada) and [[Psion]] (UK) in the Federal Court on similar grounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.courthousenews.com/2009/02/16/Intel_Wants_Netbook_Trademark_Canceled.htm Intel Wants 'Netbook' Trademark Canceled].&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to seeking cancellation of the trademark, Intel sought an order enjoining Psion from asserting any trademark rights in the term &quot;netbook&quot;, a declarative judgment regarding their use of the term, attorneys' fees, costs and disbursements and &quot;such other and further relief as the Court deems just and proper&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.courthousenews.com/2009/02/16/IntelvPsion.pdf Complaint for Injunctive Relief, Declaratory Judgment &amp; Cancellation of Federal Trademark].&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 2, 2009, Psion announced that the suit had been settled out of court. Psion's statement said that the company was withdrawing all of its trademark registrations for the term &quot;Netbook&quot; and that Psion agreed to &quot;waive all its rights against third parties in respect of past, current or future use&quot; of the term.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-1001_3-10253210-92.html Psion, Intel settle 'Netbook' trademark dispute].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hardware ==
&lt;!-- This section needs some work - it's quite incoherent now but hopefully breaking it into sections will help --&gt;
&lt;!-- As per discussion topic 18, breaking it into subsections will not help incoherence. Editing will.
And subsections make empty parents harder to edit, as the entire article must be edited.--&gt;
[[File:MSI Wind MB1.jpg|thumb|An [[MSI Wind netbook]] [[motherboard]] featuring the [[Intel Atom]] processor]]
Netbooks typically have less powerful hardware than larger laptop computers. Some netbooks do not even have a conventional [[hard disk drive|hard drive]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13554_3-10063963-33.html What is a Netbook computer?]&lt;/ref&gt; Such netbooks use [[Solid-state drive|solid-state]] storage devices instead, as these require less power, are faster, lighter, and generally more shock-resistant, but with much less storage capacity (such as 32, 64, or 128 GB compared to the 100 GB to 2 TB mechanical hard drives typical of many notebooks/laptop computers).

All netbooks on the market today support [[Wi-Fi]] [[wireless networking]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://netbookcave.com/difference-between-a-netbook-and-a-laptop Difference between a Netbook and a Laptop]&lt;/ref&gt; and many can be used on [[mobile network|mobile telephone networks]] with data capability (for example, [[3G]]).  Mobile data plans are supplied under contract in the same way as mobile telephones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.wired.com/gadgets/2008/12/next-time-you-s.html |title=The Next Netbook Trend: Cellphone-Like Contract Deals |publisher=[[Wired (magazine)]]|first=Priya|last=Ganapati|date=2008-12-15 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some also include [[Ethernet over twisted pair|ethernet]] and/or [[modem]] ports, for [[broadband]] or [[dial-up Internet access]], respectively.

=== Processor architectures ===
====x86====
Most netbooks, such as those from [[Asus]], [[Benq|BenQ]], [[Dell]], [[Toshiba]], [[Acer Inc.|Acer]] use the [[Intel Atom]] notebook processor (typically the N270 1.6&amp;nbsp;GHz but also available is the N280 at 1.66&amp;nbsp;GHz, replaced by the N450 series with graphics and memory controller integrated on the chip in early 2010 and running at 1.66&amp;nbsp;GHz), but the x86-compatible [[VIA Technologies]] [[VIA C7|C7]] processor is also powering netbooks from many different manufacturers like [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13924_3-9914927-64.html |title=Why HP chose Via chip over Intel for Mini-Note |first=Brooke |last=Crothers |publisher=[[CNET News]] |date=2009-04-09 |accessdate=2009-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Samsung]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.electronista.com/articles/09/04/03/samsung.nc20.now.available/ |title=Samsung's VIA-powered NC20 netbook now available |publisher=Electronista |date=2009-04-03 |accessdate=2009-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; VIA has also designed the [[VIA Nano|Nano]], a new [[x86-64]]-compatible architecture targeting lower priced, mobile applications like netbooks. Currently, one netbook uses the [[VIA Nano|Nano]]; the Samsung [[NC20]]. Some very low cost netbooks use a [[System-on-a-chip]] [[Vortex86]] processor meant for [[embedded systems]], just to be &quot;Windows compatible&quot;, but with very low performance. In 2011, [[AMD]] launched [[AMD Fusion|Fusion]] netbook processors which are included in [[Asus Eee PC]] 1015T and many others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=mehboob |title=AMD plans to launch Netbooks Processors next year |work=Processor Discussions  |publisher=smartbooktalk.com |date=2010-03-12 |url= http://www.smartbooktalk.com/processor-discussions-f36/amd-plans-to-launch-netbooks-processors-next-year-t174.html |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Patrizio |first=Andy |title=AMD to Introduce Netbook Chip in 2011 |work=Hardware Central |publisher=[[internet.com]] |date=2010-03-10 |url=http://www.hardwarecentral.com/news/article.php/3869796 |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Comparison=====
By definition netbooks accommodate processors with little processing power. For comparison a common dual-core [[Core 2 Duo]] T5600 at 1.83&amp;nbsp;GHz with 2 MB [[L2 cache]] used in low-end laptops has a PassMark score of about 1000 points. The following table shows benchmarks for most common netbook CPUs:&lt;ref&gt;http://cpubenchmark.net/cpu_list.php&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Manufacturer !! Name !! Core Count !! Frequency&lt;br/&gt;([[GHz]]) !! [[L2 cache]]&lt;br/&gt;([[Kilobyte|KB]]) !! [[Thermal Design Power|TDP]]&lt;br/&gt;([[Watt|W]]) !! Reference !! Average&lt;br /&gt;PassMark score
|-
| [[Intel]] || [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors#&quot;Diamondville&quot; (45 nm)|Atom N270]] || 1 || 1.6 || 512 || 2.5 || [http://processorfinder.intel.com/details.aspx?sSpec=SLB73] || 310
|-
| [[Intel]] || [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors#&quot;Pineview&quot; (45 nm)|Atom N450]] || 1 || 1.66 || 512 || 5.5 || [http://ark.intel.com/Product.aspx?id=42503] || 320
|-
| [[Intel]] || [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors#&quot;Pineview&quot; (45 nm)|Atom N550]] || 2 || 1.5 || 1024 || 8.5 || [http://ark.intel.com/Product.aspx?id=50154] || 563
|-
| [[AMD]] || [[List of AMD Athlon 64 microprocessors#&quot;Huron&quot; (65 nm, 15W TDP)|Athlon Neo MV-40]] || 1 || 1.6 || 512 || 15 || [http://products.amd.com/en-ca/NotebookCPUDetail.aspx?id=513&amp;f1=&amp;f2=&amp;f3=&amp;f4=&amp;f5=&amp;f6=&amp;f7=&amp;f8=&amp;f9=] || 391
|-
|-
| [[AMD]] || [[AMD_Fusion#Processing_power|AMD Fusion C-50]] || 2 || 1 || 1024 || 9 || [http://products.amd.com/en-us/NotebookAPUDetail.aspx?id=4&amp;f1=&amp;f2=&amp;f3=&amp;f4=&amp;f5=&amp;f6=&amp;] || 452
|-
|}

====ARM====
[[ARM Holdings]] designs and licenses microprocessor technology with relatively low power requirements and low cost which would constitute an ideal basis for netbooks. In particular, the recent [[ARM Cortex-A9 MPCore]] series of processor cores have been touted by ARM as an alternative platform to x86 for netbooks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Hruska |first=Joel |title=ARM Launches New Cortex-A5 As A Bulkward Against Future Atom processors |publisher=[[HotHardware]] |date=2009-10-23 |url= http://hothardware.com/News/ARM%2DLaunches%2DNew%2DCortexA5%2DAs%2DA%2DBulkward%2DAgainst%2DFuture%2DAtom%2Dprocessors |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=McAllister |first=Neil |title=ARM vs. Atom: The battle for the next digital frontier |publisher=[[InfoWorld]] |date=2009-10-28 |url=http://www.infoworld.com/d/hardware/arm-vs-atom-battle-next-digital-frontier-762 |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; These systems, when available, will be branded as [[smartbook]]s.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} [[Freescale]], a manufacturer of ARM chips, has projected that, by 2012, half of all netbooks will run on ARM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Tofel |first=Kevin C. |title=Freescale Says ARM Will Power Half the Netbook Market |publisher=[[jkOnTheRun]] |date=2009-02-18 |url=http://jkontherun.com/2009/02/18/freescale-says-arm-will-power-half-the-netbook-market/    |accessdate=2009-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2009, [[Nvidia]] announced a dozen [[mobile Internet device]]s running ARM based [[Tegra]] [[System-on-a-chip|SoC's]], some of which will be netbooks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite press release |title=NVIDIA Tegra-Based Devices Revolutionize the 'MID' Market |publisher=[[nVidia]] |date=2009-06-02 |url= http://news.prnewswire.com/ViewContent.aspx?ACCT=109&amp;STORY=/www/story/06-02-2009/0005036371&amp;EDATE= |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smartbooks will deliver features including always on, all-day [[battery life]], [[3G]] connectivity and [[GPS]] (all typically found in smartphones) in a [[laptop]]-style body with a screen size of 5 to 10&amp;nbsp;inches and a [[QWERTY]] keyboard. These systems do not run traditional [[x86]] versions of [[Microsoft Windows]], rather custom [[Linux]] [[operating system]]s (such as Google's [[Android (operating system)|Android]] or [[Chrome OS]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;eetimes&quot;&gt;http://www.eetimes.eu/design/217700855&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj55&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Clark |first=Don |title='Smartbooks' Latest to Join Crowded Computer Market |publisher=The Wall Street Journal |date=December 29, 2009 |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704234304574626541267909328.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other barriers for the adoption of ARM are slowly being removed, for example Adobe is finally working on an implementation of the full version of [[Adobe Flash Player#Supported platforms|Flash player]] for ARM.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/pressreleases/200811/111708ARMAdobeFlash.html Flash 10 for ARM]&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2011, Microsoft announced that the next releases of Windows and Internet Explorer would be able to run on ARM processors. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jan/05/microsoft-windows-8-arm-processors | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Charles | last=Arthur | title='Windows 8' will run on ARM chips - but third-party apps will need rewrite | date=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====MIPS====
Some netbooks use [[MIPS architecture]]-compatible processors. These include the [[Skytone Alpha 400]],&lt;ref name=&quot;engadget_20081222&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Rubin |first=Ross |title=Switched On: Alpha 400 pays a high price for low cost |publisher=[[Engadget]] |date=2008-12-22 |url=http://www.engadget.com/2008/12/22/switched-on-alpha-400-pays-a-high-price-for-low-cost/ |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; based on an [[Ingenic]] [[system on chip]], and the EMTEC [[Gdium]] netbook, which uses the 64-bit [[Loongson]] processor capable of 400 [[million instructions per second]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=h3rman |title=The Loongson-2 MIPS Lemote Yeeloong Netbook |publisher=[[OSNews]] |date=2009-05-21 |url=http://www.osnews.com/story/21530/The_Loongson-2_MIPS_Lemote_Yeeloong_Netbook |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; While these systems are relatively inexpensive, the processing power of current MIPS implementations usually compares unfavorably with those of x86-implementations as found in current netbooks.&lt;ref name=&quot;engadget_20081222&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--How unfavorably does the processing power compare?--&gt;&lt;!--Unclear, but the Engadget piece does suggest it--&gt; After the ARM version, Adobe is planning to release a version of the Adobe Flash Player (version 10.1) for the MIPS platform.&lt;ref name=&quot;MIPS&quot;&gt;{{Cite press release |title=MIPS Technologies Collaborates with Adobe to Optimize Flash Player 10.1 for MIPS® Architecture |publisher=[[MIPS Technologies]] |date=2010-01-05 |url=http://www.mips.com/news-events/newsroom/newsindex/index.dot?id=10021 |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operating systems==
===Windows===
[[File:Samsung N145 Plus.jpg|thumb|right|A Samsung N145 Plus netbook running Windows 7.]]
As of January 2009, over 90% (96% claimed by Microsoft as of February 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=McDougall |first=Paul |title=Microsoft: 96% Of Netbooks Run Windows |publisher=[[InformationWeek]] |date=2009-04-06 |url= http://www.informationweek.com/news/windows/operatingsystems/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=216402927 |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;) of netbooks in the United States are estimated to ship with [[Windows XP]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pcw-linux&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Gralla |first=Preston |title=Think Linux Rules on Netbooks? Think Again |publisher=[[PC World (magazine)|PC World]] |date=2009-03-03 |url= http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/160567/think_linux_rules_on_netbooks_think_again.html |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; which Microsoft was later estimated to sell ranging from US$15 to US$35 per netbook.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.zdnet.com/2100-9595_22-272793.html Microsoft shares hit 11-year low]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB124018108488732939.html | work=The Wall Street Journal | title=Microsoft Gambles on Windows 7 'Starter' | date=April 20, 2009 | first1=Nick | last1=Wingfield | first2=Don | last2=Clark}}&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft has extended the availability of Windows XP for ultra-low cost personal computers from June 2008 until June 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/features/2008/apr08/04-03xpeos.mspx Microsoft Announces Extended Availability of Windows XP Home for ULCPCs], April 3, 2008 Press release&lt;/ref&gt; However, the discounted license costs only applies to reduced size and functionality netbooks, which effectively enables the production of low-cost PCs while preserving the higher margins of mainstream desktops and &quot;value&quot; laptops&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itworld.com/Comp/2218/microsoft-windows-on-lowcost-pcs-080512/ Microsoft to limit capabilities of cheap laptops], IT World May 12, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; as well as avoiding increased use of [[Linux]] installations on netbooks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.computerworlduk.com/technology/hardware/laptops/news/index.cfm?newsid=9006 Microsoft U-turn to stop Linux dominating ultra low cost PC]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Microsoft]] also has &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Mackey |first=Kurt |title=Ars@PDC: Steven Sinofsky on Windows 7 and netbooks |publisher=[[Ars Technica]] |date=2008-10-28 |url= http://arstechnica.com/journals/microsoft.ars/2008/10/28/arspdc-steven-sinofsky-on-windows-7-and-netbooks  |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Windows 7 Starter]] for this class of devices.  As of the first quarter of 2009 many netbook models previously announced with Windows XP for the US market were in fact being released with Windows 7 Starter instead, at the same price point previously announced for the Windows XP editions. However, unlike on regular desktops or notebooks that were sold with Vista but included a coupon for 7, users could not get a coupon for 7 Starter if they bought a netbook.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/article/158861/windows_7_to_ship_in_six_different_versions.html Windows 7 to Ship In Six Different Versions]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://crave.cnet.co.uk/laptops/0,39029450,49300490,00.htm Confirmed: Windows 7 'netbook edition']&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Windows CE]] has also been used in netbook applications, due to its reduced feature design, that keeps with the design philosophy of netbooks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.windowsfordevices.com/news/NS6976598029.html Windows CE takes on Linux in low-end netbooks]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some netbooks have also been sold with Windows Vista (mostly prior to the release of Windows 7).

Many netbooks are by default unable to activate Windows in an enterprise environment using a Microsoft [[Volume license key|Key Management Service]] (KMS) as they lack [[System Locked Preinstallation]] (SLP) capability in their BIOS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=You receive an error message when you try to activate Windows Vista on a computer that was obtained from an OEM |publisher=[[Microsoft]] |date=2009-03-20 |url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/942962 |accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The missing feature artificially segments enterprise customers from the lower end Netbook market; some hardware vendors offer an optional SLP-compliant BIOS to enterprise customers at additional cost.

===Linux===
{{Main|Comparison of netbook-oriented Linux distributions}}
{{As of|2009|11}}, customised [[Linux]] distributions are estimated to ship on 32% of netbooks worldwide (0.5% claimed Microsoft),&lt;ref name=&quot;computerworld-linux&quot;&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9140343/Linux_s_share_of_netbooks_surging_not_sagging_says_analyst |title=Linux's share of netbooks surging, not sagging, says analyst |first=Eric |last=Lai |work=Computerworld |date=November 4, 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; making it the second most popular operating system after Windows. As Linux systems normally install software from an Internet [[software repository]], they do not need an optical drive to install software.

{{As of|2010|08}}, major netbook manufacturers no longer install or support Linux in the United States. The reason for this change of stance is unclear, although it coincides with the availability of Windows 7 Starter and a strong marketing push for the adoption of this OS in the netbook market. However, companies targeting niche markets, such as System76 and ZaReason, continue to pre-install Linux on the devices they sell.

Netbooks have sparked the development of several Linux variants or completely new distributions, which are optimized for small screen use and the limited processing power of the Atom or ARM processors which typically power netbooks. Examples include [[Ubuntu Netbook Edition]], [[EasyPeasy]], [[Joli OS]] and [[MeeGo]]. Both Joli OS and MeeGo purport to be &quot;social oriented&quot; or social networking operating systems rather than traditional &quot;office work production&quot; operating systems.

====Android====
Google's [[Android (operating system)|Android]] software platform, designed for mobile telephone handsets, has been demonstrated on an ASUS Eee PC and its Linux operating system contains policies for [[mobile internet device]]s including the original Asus Eee PC 701.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://venturebeat.com/2009/01/01/android-netbooks-on-their-way-likely-by-2010/ |title=Android netbooks on their way, likely by 2010 |work=SocialBeat |date=January 1, 2009 |first=Matthäus |last=Krzykowski |lastauthoramp=yes |first2=Daniel |last2=Hartmann }}.&lt;/ref&gt; ASUS has allocated engineers to develop an Android-based netbook.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=a4E9sAyqigOU |title=Google Android May Run Asus Netbook, Rival Microsoft (Update1) |work=Bloomberg |date=February 20, 2009 |first=Tim |last=Culpan }}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Freescale]] have also announced plans for a low-cost [[ARM architecture|ARM]]-based netbook design, running Android.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://blogs.zdnet.com/gadgetreviews/?p=1563 |title=Freescale to use Android, ARM for US$ 100 Netbook |work=ZDNet |first=Andrew |last=Nusca |date=February 18, 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2009 a contractor of Dell announced it is porting [[Adobe Flash Lite]] to Android for Dell netbooks.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.fiercewireless.com/press-releases/bsquare-port-adobe-flash-lite-new-google-android-netbook-del?utm_medium=nl&amp;utm_source=internal |title=Bsquare to Port Adobe Flash Lite on New Google Android Netbook for Del |work=FierceWireless |date=May 6, 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Acer Inc.|Acer]] announced Android netbooks to be available in Q3/2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/marketsNews/idUSTP18980620090602 |title=Acer to sell Android netbook PCs in Q3 |work=Reuters |date=June 2, 2009 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2009, a new project, Android-x86,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.android-x86.org/ Android-x86 project]&lt;/ref&gt; was created to provide an open source solution for Android on the x86 platform, especially for netbooks.

Since the initial work on Android, Google announced a netbook specific operating system, Chrome OS, and future operating system development may be forked into Android for smartphones and similar handhelds, and Chrome OS for traditional keyboard driven machines like netbooks.

====Chrome OS====
[[Google]]'s new [[Google Chrome OS|Chrome OS]] is loaded on some netbooks. These are known as [[Chromebook]]s.

====MeeGo====
[[MeeGo]] is a Linux-based open source operating system project. It was first announced at Mobile World Congress in February 2010 by Intel and [[Nokia]] in a joint press conference, with the stated aim being to merge the efforts of Intel's [[Moblin]] and Nokia's [[Maemo]] former projects into one new common project. It is programmed in C++ and comes from [[Linux]] OS Family. It was initially released on 26 May 2010. The latest stable release available is 1.2 released on 19 May 2011. Official website http://www.meego.com/

===Other===
Netbooks have been demonstrated running other operating systems including [[FreeBSD]], [[NetBSD]], [[OpenBSD]],  and [[Darwin (operating system)|Darwin]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

The [[Cloud (operating system)|Cloud]] operating system attempts to capitalize on the minimalist aspect of netbooks.  The user interface is limited to a browser application only.

[[Mac OS X]] has been demonstrated running on various netbooks as a result of the [[OSx86]] project,&lt;ref&gt;[http://gadgets.boingboing.net/2008/12/17/osx-netbook-compatib.html Mac OS X Netbook Compatibility Chart (Updated)]&lt;/ref&gt; although this is in violation of the operating system's [[End User License Agreement]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.wired.com/gadgets/2008/09/it-lives-gadget.html It Lives! Gadget Lab's Netbook Running OS X Leopard]&lt;/ref&gt; Apple has complained to sites hosting information on how to install OS X onto non-Apple hardware (including [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] and [[YouTube]]) who have reacted and removed content in response.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.wired.com/gadgets/2008/12/gadget-lab-vide.html Gadget Lab Video: Running OS X on a Netbook]&lt;/ref&gt; One article nicknamed a netbook running OS X a &quot;[[Hackintosh]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.last100.com/2009/01/05/netbook-goodbye-xp-hello-osx/ Last100, &quot;Hackintosh Netbook: Goodbye XP, hello OSX,&quot; Jan. 5, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Usage==
A June 2009 [[NPD Group|NPD]] study found that 60% of netbook buyers never take their netbooks out of the house.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.npd.com/press/releases/press_090622b.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Another NPD study indicated that by September 2009 netbooks accounted for 20% of all portable computer shipments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Schonfeld |first=Erick |title=Report: Netbooks Now A Fifth Of All Portable Computer Shipments |publisher=[[TechCrunch]] |date=2009-08-31 |url= http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/08/31/report-netbooks-now-a-fifth-of-all-portable-computer-shipments/ |accessdate=2011-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Special &quot;children's&quot; editions of netbooks have been released under Disney branding; their low cost (less at risk), lack of DVD player (less to break) and smaller keyboards (closer to children's hand sizes) are viewed as significant advantages for that target market. The principal objection to netbooks in this context is the lack of good video performance for streaming online video in current netbooks and a lack of speed with even simple games. Adults browsing for text content are less dependent on video content than small children who cannot read.

In addition to education, netbooks have become the tool of choice for the business road warrior. Because of the portability and perfect size between smartphones and laptops, business travelers are increasingly choosing netbooks. According to Jim Rapoza, Chief Technology Analyst at eWEEK, at least 15% of the crowd at DEMO 09, a show that displays emerging technologies, were using netbooks over laptops, and that number, he says, may well have been higher.&lt;ref name=&quot;Computers &amp; Applied Sciences Complete&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Rapoza|first=Jim|title=Netbooks Are Here To Stay|url=http://web.ebscohost.com.library.sunyorange.edu/ehost/detail?vid=6&amp;hid=14&amp;sid=761cdb6e-4325-4102-b30a-a13bc28b5802%40sessionmgr4&amp;bdata=JnNpdGU9ZWhvc3QtbGl2ZQ%3d%3d#db=iih&amp;AN=37334481|work=eWEEK|publisher=Ziff Davis Enterprise|accessdate=5/5/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Netbooks in education==
Netbooks are a growing trend in education for several reasons. The need to prepare children for 21st century lifestyles, combined with hundreds of new educational tools that can be found online, and a growing emphasis on student centered learning are three of the biggest contributing factors to the rising use of Netbook technology in schools.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} Dell was one of the first to mass produce a ruggedised netbook for the education sector, by having a rubber outlay, touchscreen and network activity light to show the teacher the netbook is online.

Netbooks offer several distinct advantages in educational settings. First, their compact size and weight make for an easy fit in student work areas. Similarly, the small size make Netbooks easier to transport than heavier, larger sized traditional laptops. In addition, prices ranging from $200–$600 dollars mean the affordability of Netbooks can be a relief to school budget makers. Despite the small size and price, Netbooks are fully capable of accomplishing most school-related tasks, including word processing, presentations, access to the Internet, multimedia playback, and photo management.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Descy |first=D. |year=2009 |title=Netbook: Small but Powerful Friends |journal=Tech Trends |volume=53 |issue=2 |pages=9–10 |doi=10.1007/s11528-009-0256-z |accessdate=May 5, 2010 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Smartbook==
{{Main|Smartbook}}
A smartbook is a concept of a mobile device that falls between [[smartphone]]s and netbooks, delivering features typically found in smartphones (always on, all-day [[battery life]], [[3G]] connectivity, [[GPS]])&lt;ref name=&quot;eetimes&quot;/&gt; in a slightly larger device with a full keyboard. Smartbooks will tend to be designed to work with online applications.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2009/jul/29/smartbooks-netbooks | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=The smartbook has been waiting 28 years to be the next best thing | first=Jack | last=Schofield | date=2009-07-29 | accessdate=2010-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smartbooks are likely to be sold initially through [[mobile network operators]], as mobile phones are today, with a wireless data plan.&lt;ref name=citation3&gt;Ganapat, Priya (2008-12-15). “[http://blog.wired.com/gadgets/2008/12/next-time-you-s.html The Next Netbook Trend: Cellphone-Like Contract Deals]” – [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] News.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Netbook Size.JPG|An Asus Eee PC 1005HA size comparison with a 15.4 inch laptop
File:ECS G10IL.jpg|[[Elitegroup Computer Systems|ECS]] [[ECS G10IL|G10IL]] [[Microsoft Windows XP|XP]] Netbook with a built-in GSM ([[High-Speed Downlink Packet Access|HSDPA]]) module (europe use)
File:ASUS Eee PC 900 0010.JPG|[[ASUS Eee PC|ASUS Eee PC 900]]

File:Guang Hua Digital Plaza Launch Acer Aspire One.jpg|[[Acer Aspire One]]
File:Dell-inspiron-mini-9.png|[[Dell Inspiron Mini 9]]
File:Zelybron Micro Nina 1.jpg|[[Zelybron Micro Nina]]
File:S10 wiki.JPG|[[Lenovo IdeaPad S10]]
File:Samsung NC20 - Lid Open - Side View.jpg|[[Samsung NC20]]
File:XO-Beta1-mikemcgregor-2.jpg|[[OLPC XO-1]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: File:Litl.jpg|[[Litl]] --&gt;
File:Intel Classmate PC.jpg|[[Classmate PC]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
* [[Apple iPad]]
* [[Comparison of netbooks]]
* [[Nettop]], a desktop equivalent of the netbook
* [[Mobile broadband]]
* [[Mobile modem]]
* [[Tethering]]

{{col-break}}

* [[Mobile phone]]
* [[Pay As You Go (phone)]]
* [[SIM card]]
* [[PDA]]
* [[Mobile internet device]] (MID)
* [[Subnotebook]]
* [[Tablet computer|Tablet personal computer]]
* [[Ultra-mobile PC]] (UMPC)
* [[Smartbook]]

{{col-end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
&lt;!--========================({{No More Links}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =======================({{No More Links}})=============================--&gt;
{{Commons category|Netbooks}}
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://news.cnet.com/Year-in-review-The-rise-of-the-Netbook/2009-1042_3-6248307.html &quot;The rise of the Netbook&quot;] article at [[Cnet.com|Cnet]]
*[http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/news/2009/02/state-of-the-netbook-1.ars &quot;The State of the Netbook&quot;] article at [[Arstechnica.com|Ars Technica]]
*[http://www.wired.com/gadgets/wireless/magazine/17-03/mf_netbooks?currentPage=all &quot;The Netbook Effect: How Cheap Little Laptops Hit the Big Time&quot;] article at [[Wired.com]]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/02/technology/02netbooks.html?pagewanted=1&amp;em &quot;Light and Cheap, Netbooks Are Poised to Reshape PC Industry&quot;] article at [[New York Times]]
&lt;!--
*[http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/09_22/b4133043584164.htm &quot;Netbook Sales Keep Quanta Competitive&quot;] article at [[BusinessWeek]]
*[http://www.economist.com/displayStory.cfm?story_id=13832588 Netbooks: Small but disruptive | The Economist] 
*[http://www.economist.com/displayStory.cfm?story_id=12673233 Rational consumer: Small is beautiful | The Economist] 
*[http://taiwanreview.nat.gov.tw/ct.asp?xItem=44916&amp;CtNode=119 Taiwan Review/High-tech Success Made Simple]
*[http://english.cw.com.tw/article.do?action=show&amp;id=10865 Acer Founder Stan Shih:The Netbook Is the Big Chance for Brand Taiwan]
*[http://english.cw.com.tw/article.do?action=show&amp;id=10673&amp;offset=0 World hardware: Small wonder/THE ECONOMIST INTELLIGENCE UNIT]
*[http://comparisonz.com/compare/100291_netbook-vs-notebook.aspx Comparison of Netbook and Notebook from comparisonz.com]
*[http://brainstormtech.blogs.fortune.cnn.com/2009/11/20/the-man-behind-the-netbook-craze/ The man behind the netbook craze/Fortune Brainstorm Tech]
--&gt;
{{Netbooks}}
{{Computer sizes}}
{{Cloud computing}}

[[Category:Netbooks|*]]
[[Category:Appropriate technology]]
[[Category:Cloud clients]]
[[Category:Information appliances]]

[[ar:نت بوك]]
[[bg:Нетбук]]
[[ca:Ultraportàtil]]
[[cs:Netbook]]
[[da:Netbook]]
[[de:Netbook]]
[[et:Minisülearvuti]]
[[el:Netbook]]
[[es:Netbook]]
[[eu:Netbook]]
[[fa:نت‌بوک]]
[[fr:Netbook]]
[[ko:넷북]]
[[hi:नेटबुक]]
[[id:Netbook]]
[[it:Netbook]]
[[he:נטבוק]]
[[ka:ნეტბუკი]]
[[lo:ເນັຕບຸກ]]
[[hu:Netbook]]
[[ml:നെറ്റ്ബുക്ക്]]
[[mzn:نوت بوک]]
[[nl:Netbook]]
[[ja:ネットブック]]
[[no:NettPC]]
[[pl:Netbook]]
[[pt:Netbook]]
[[ro:Netbook]]
[[ru:Нетбук]]
[[simple:Netbook]]
[[sk:Netbook]]
[[sh:Netbook]]
[[fi:Minikannettava]]
[[sv:Netbook]]
[[ta:நெட்புக்]]
[[th:เน็ตบุ๊ก]]
[[tr:Netbook]]
[[uk:Нетбук]]
[[vi:Netbook]]
[[zh:上网本]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
