<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Fanboy" to="Fan (person)" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="152640" ns="0" title="Fan (person)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Fanboy}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Salman Khan Fans.jpg|280px|thumb|[[Salman Khan]] greets fans at the ''[[Occasion of EID]]'' in [[Delhi, India]].]] --&gt;
A '''Fan''', sometimes also called '''aficionado''' or '''supporter''', is a person with a liking and enthusiasm for something, such as a band or a sports team. Fans of a particular thing or person constitute its [[fanbase]] or [[fandom]]. They may show their [[enthusiasm]] by being a member of a [[fan club]], holding [[fan convention]]s, creating [[fanzine]]s, writing [[fan mail]], or by promoting the object of their interest and attention.

==Etymology==
Paul Dickson, in his ''Dickson Baseball Dictionary'', cites [[William Henry Nugent]]'s work that claims it comes from ''fancy'', a 19th century term from England that referred mainly to followers of [[boxing]]. According to that unsupported explanation, it was originally shortened to ''fance'' then just to the homonym ''fans''. However, Merriam-Webster, the Oxford dictionary and other recognized sources define it as a shortened version of the word ''fanatic'', and the word did first become popular in reference to an enthusiastic follower of a [[baseball]] team. (''[[Fanatic]]'' itself, introduced into English around 1550, means &quot;marked by excessive enthusiasm and often intense uncritical devotion&quot;. It comes from the Modern [[Latin (language)|Latin]] ''fanaticus'', meaning &quot;insanely but divinely inspired&quot;. The word originally pertained to a [[temple]] or sacred place [Latin ''fanum'', poetic English ''fane'']. The modern sense of &quot;extremely zealous&quot; dates from around 1647; the use of ''fanatic'' as a noun dates from 1650.) However, the term &quot;fancy&quot; for an intense liking of something, while being of a different etymology, coincidentally carries a less intense but somewhat similar connotation to &quot;fanatic&quot;. The word emerged as an [[Americanism]] around 1889.

''Supporter'' is a synonym to &quot;fan&quot; which predates the latter term and as such is still commonly used in [[British English]], especially to denote fans of [[sport]]s teams. However, the term &quot;fan&quot; has become popular throughout the [[English language|English]]-speaking world, including the [[United Kingdom]]. The term ''supporter'' is also used in a [[political]] sense in the [[United States]], to a fan of a [[politician]], a [[political party]], and a controversial issue.

==Characteristics==
Fans usually have a strong enough interest that some changes in their [[lifestyle (sociology)|lifestyles]] are made to accommodate devotion to the focal object. As well, fans have a desire for external involvement – they are motivated to demonstrate their involvement with the area of interest through certain behaviors (attending [[Fan convention|conventions]], posting online, etc.). Fans often have a &quot;wish to acquire&quot; material objects related to the area of interest, such as a baseball hit by a famous slugger or a used [[guitar pick]] from their musical hero. As well, some fans have a desire for [[social interaction]] with other fans. This again may take many forms, from casual conversation, e-mail, chat rooms, and electronic mailing lists to regular face-to-face meetings such as fan club meetings and organized conventions.

There are several groups of fans that can be differentiated by the intensity level of their level of involvement or interest in the hobby (level of [[fanaticism]])&lt;ref name=TB&gt;{{cite journal | last = Thorne | first = Scott | coauthors = Bruner, Gordon C. | year = 2006 | title = An exploratory investigation of the characteristics of consumer fanaticism | journal = Qualitative Market Research: an International Journal | volume = 9 | issue = 1 | pages = 51–72 | doi = 10.1108/13522750610640558 | url = http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/ViewContentServlet?Filename=Published/EmeraldFullTextArticle/Articles/2160090104.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; The likelihood for a subject of interest to be elevated to the level of fandom appears to be dictated by its complexity. Complexity allows further involvement of fans for a longer period of time because of the time needed to work the subject of interest 'out.' It also contributes to a greater sense of belonging because of the mental effort invested in the subject.

==Types==
===Celebrities===
These fans will often hold a crush on a major film or TV star, [[singer]], athlete or [[celebrity]] (see [[teen idol]]). This can range from a simple crush to the [[deluded]] belief that they have a &quot;connection&quot; with the star (or even that they &quot;are&quot; the star). In extreme cases, this can lead to [[Celebrity Worship Syndrome]] or [[stalking]] behavior or even [[violent]] attacks or becoming a [[hater]] against the celebrity that they once loved.

This is somewhat related to the concept of [[parasocial interaction]] where audiences develop one-sided relationships with media characters and celebrities.

===Musicals===
Popular [[musical theatre|musicals]] have their own particular sets of fans. ''[[Rent (musical)|Rent]]'' has boasted a sizable number of 'Rentheads' since its Broadway debut{{cn|date=November 2011}}, and likewise those devoted to ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (1986 musical)|The Phantom of the Opera]]'' dub themselves 'Phans.'

===Politics===
Even though they are not collectively called &quot;fans&quot;, more often the term ''supporter'' is used for people who often approve of what certain politicians do, or to a political party. Even though there is far less devotion to politicians, due to the controversial nature of politics, it is not uncommon to find heavy devotion to a politician. For example, former [[President of the United States|U.S. President]] [[Ronald Reagan]] has an unofficial devoted &quot;fan club&quot; on the Internet.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fanpop.com/spots/ronald-reagan&lt;/ref&gt; Often heavy enthusiasm or praise for politicians are from a [[personality cult]], which are usually found in [[dictatorships]]. However, a large fan base for a politician does not in any way make them a dictator; this is determined by an entirely different set of standards.

===Sports===
[[Image:A Cricket fan at the Chepauk stadium, Chennai.jpg|thumb|Sudhir Kumar Chaudhary is a diehard fan of [[cricket]]er [[Sachin Tendulkar]] and the [[Indian cricket team]], who travels to all Indian home games with his body painted as the [[Indian flag]]]]
A sports fan can be an enthusiast for a particular athlete, team, sport, or all of organized sports as a whole. Sports fans often attend sporting events or watch them on television, and follow news through newspapers and internet websites.
The mentality of the sports fan is often such that they will experience a game, or event while living vicariously through players or teams whom the fan favors{{OR|date=July 2011}}. This behavior manifests itself in a number of different ways, depending on the venue. At a stadium or arena, sports fans will voice their pleasure with a particular incident, player, or team by [[cheering]], which consists of clapping, fist-pumping, or shouting positive exclamations toward the field of play and ultimately, the favorable object. Likewise, displeasure toward a particular incident, player, or team may be met by fans with booing, shouting of expletives, and sometimes throwing of objects onto the field. This violent type of fan reaction is often called [[hooliganism]].

[[File:Shea Crowded.jpg|thumb|left|Shea Stadium filled with fans prior to the start of a [[New York Mets]] game in 2008. The stadium had the best attendance in the [[National League]] that year, garnering over 53,000 fans per game on average.]]
Lighter, more harmless objects are also occasionally thrown onto certain fields of play as a form of celebration of a favorable sports feat. This is most common when a member of the home team scores a [[hat trick]] in hockey. Other, more mild forms of displeasure shown by sports fans at sporting events involve simple groans of disappointment, and silence. These actions often denote that the favored home team is being outperformed by, or has lost to the much less-favored road team.

In North America, extremely enthusiastic fans are often called ''[[Rabies|rabid]] fans''. These fans often congregate hours before kickoff in what is known as a [[tailgation]]. The [[Pittsburgh Steelers]] is often cited as an example of a team with a ''rabid fanbase'' because of [[Steeler Nation|their large fanbase]] internationally as well as unusually large [[local news]] coverage in [[Pittsburgh]] in recent years being dedicated to the team even during the [[National Football League|NFL]] [[Season (sports)#Off-season|offseason]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[http://vids.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=vids.individual&amp;videoid=4328974 MySpaceTV Videos: Steeler Nation by INDY STEELERS - Indyburgh(SCM 35)]&lt;/ref&gt;

At [[Bar (establishment)|sports bars]], sports fans will gather together, often while consuming food and alcoholic beverages, with the purpose of following a particular sporting event on television as a group. Sports bars often advertise in hopes of drawing fans of a particular player or team to watch together to increase bonds between fans and prevent fights. This can create the sense of unity in a sports bar as all cheers and boos will appear to be synchronized due to similar feelings and reactions by nearly all fans at the fortunes and misfortunes of the favored team or athlete. Due to the level of devotion and intensity of feeling towards the favored team or athlete by sports bar patrons, as well as partially due to the alcohol being served, behavior that would be seen as unruly or fanatical outside of a sports bar is generally more common inside of one. The intensity of cheering and jeering at a sports bar by sports fans can often range from equal to stronger than that of fans actually at the sporting event for particularly significant games and matches.

[[Image:Wm-oly-de-cr.jpg|thumb|Fans in the [[2006 FIFA World Cup]] in [[Munich]], [[Germany]].]]
At home, sports fans may have few fellow fans but also more freedom. This is sometimes where the most intense cheering or jeering will take place. In the fan's own home, unbridled and lengthy screaming, crying, acts of destruction to household objects, and other manifestations of joy or anguish, are perhaps seen as most acceptable in comparison to the sports bar or sporting venue simply because such acts taken to such an extreme can be seen as disruptive to a large number of fellow fans even if they share the same sentiment if it is of less intensity. The greatest variables of the reaction of a sports fan in their own home are the intensity of the fan's desire to see their team win or perform well, and the presence of another: often a wife, children, or friends who may be significantly less ardent sports fans or not sports fans at all, which may significantly temper the fan's reaction to a highly positive or negative moment due to the fear of causing a scene or scaring those close to the fan, or alienating themselves from said others. Often sports fans will invite other fans of relatively similar rooting intensity over to their house to experience a sporting event together so that all involved can voice pleasure or displeasure to their heart's content and increase [[male bonding|shared bonds]] in the process.

===Professional wrestling===
Fans of professional wrestling can be divided into two groups and eras; marks and smarks. Derived from the same term used to describe the prey of [[conmen]], a [[Mark (professional wrestling)|mark]] is a professional wrestling fan who believes that everything associated with pro wrestling is real, rather than recognizing the existence of [[kayfabe]] (that is, it is a work). A mark can also refer to a devoted fan, either of a particular wrestler, wrestling company, or the sport itself. A mark is also someone who believes everything about a certain wrestling organization is good. This type of mark tends to overlook bad decisions that the organization makes (or to cast said decisions in a positive light) and overreact to the good ones.
A [[smark]] (&quot;smart mark&quot;) is a wrestling fan who understands that the outcome of a professional wrestling match is pre-determined, is privy to the behind-the-scenes operations, and enjoys following the on-screen product as well as the off-screen, backstage affairs. &quot;Smark&quot; is abbreviated professional wrestling slang for &quot;smart mark&quot;. Many smarks are part of the &quot;IWC&quot; (the Internet Wrestling Community), a general term for wrestling fans who use the Internet as their means of fan-to-fan communication. Smarks define themselves by embracing the &quot;workrate&quot;, or talent level, of wrestlers. They typically overlook those whom they see as wielding too much power backstage and support underdogs who they feel have been overlooked by management.

==(Science) fiction, gaming and technology==
===Science fiction fandom===
{{details|Science fiction fandom}}
Since the 1920s, an increasingly elaborate sub-culture of organized [[science fiction fandom]] has arisen, initially among correspondents to the [[letter column]]s of [[science fiction magazine]]s. This non-centralized movement has given birth to [[science fiction fanzines]] (and [[amateur press associations]]), [[science fiction conventions]], the [[Hugo Awards]] (and various imitators/derivatives), [[filk music]], &quot;fan funds&quot; such as the [[Trans Atlantic Fan Fund]], and a variety of other institutions, jargon and customs. It has nurtured writers and artists such as [[Ray Bradbury]], [[Roger Ebert]], [[Lenny Kaye]], [[Michael Moorcock]] and [[Trina Robbins]]; and has generated such spin-offs as [[comic book fandom]], [[media fandom]], the [[Society for Creative Anachronism]], [[game|gaming]] fandom, and [[furry fandom]], sometimes collectively referred to as &quot;fringe fandoms&quot;.

===Fanboy/fangirl===
'''Fanboy''' is a term used to describe a male who is highly devoted and biased in opinion towards a single subject or [[hobby]] within a given field.
Fanboy-ism is often prevalent in a field of products, brands or universe of characters where very few competitors (or enemies in fiction, such as comics) exist. An example is the market for [[Central processing unit|CPUs]] for [[personal computer|PCs]], where [[Advanced Micro Devices|AMD]] and [[Intel Corporation|Intel]] together hold a market share of 99.6% (as of Q1 2009).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.idc.com/getdoc.jsp;jsessionid=VPB2QJXOD4G20CQJAFDCFEYKBEAVAIWD?containerId=prUS21836309&lt;/ref&gt; In this market, users of [[home computer]]s realistically only have a choice between two brands, and hence, a fight over which is better easily ensues. In this field, an &quot;Intel fanboy&quot; prefers CPUs made by Intel, and might aggressively defend their supposed superiority compared to the other brand(s), be skeptical or in denial about negative reviews of the product, and exert a high level of [[brand loyalty]]. The same brand war ensues when comparing video card brands [[Nvidia]] and [[ATI Technologies|ATI]], which together dominate the video card market.

The term originated in [[comic book]] circles, to describe someone who was socially insecure and used comics as a shield from interaction, hence the disparaging connotations.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} Fanboys are often experts on minor details regarding their hobbies, such as [[continuity (fiction)|continuity]] in [[fictional universes]], and they take these details extremely seriously. The term has also been applied to criticize perceived fan [[elitism]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}. The term itself is often used in a derogatory manner by less serious fans of the same material. Nevertheless, self-labeling usages of the term have been noted; in the songs of the [[filk music|fannish]] [[parody]] [[musician]] [[Luke Ski]], many characters proudly consider themselves ''fanboys''.

The term is usually used by and applied to people in their teens or 20s; an age group which is typically found pursuing [[geek]]y hobbies obsessively. Within this group, common objects of deference for fanboys are [[TV show]]s, [[film|movies]], [[anime]], [[automobile|cars]], [[video game console]]s, [[video game]]s, [[music]], [[operating system]]s, [[train]]s, [[home computer]]s (in earlier decades), [[MMORPG]]s, [[Internet service provider|ISPs]], [[software]] and [[computer hardware]] companies.

The term '''fangirl''' can be used to describe a female member of a [[fandom]] community (counterpart to the masculine &quot;fanboy&quot;). Fangirls may be more devoted to emotional and romantic aspects of their [[fandom]], especially [[shipping (fandom)|(relation-)shipping]]. However, it is commonly used in a [[derogatory]] sense to describe a girl's obsession with something, most commonly a male [[teen idol]] or an aspect of [[Japanese pop culture]].
Fangirl behavior can vary in intensity. On one end of the scale are those that, while harboring a crush on a particular actor or character, are perfectly capable of understanding that the fulfilment of the crush is never going to happen. On the other end are the girls who are said to be obsessive in their claims on a fictional character, even fighting with other fangirls over who 'owns' the character in question. Fangirl behavior can fall anywhere in this spectrum, but the closer someone is believed to be towards the obsessive end, the more derogatory the use of the term 'fangirl' to describe them is perceived to be.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} Fangirls of all persuasions are believed to be the largest contributors to [[fanfiction]] websites, sometimes disregarding the canon storyline of their fandom or altering it to fit either their own favored romantic pairings; or themselves into the continuity (termed [[self-insertion]]s or [[Mary Sue]]s).{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}
A popular culture gag is that celebrities would use their fans as an army to take over the world.

===Big Name Fan===
{{details|Big Name Fan}}
A [[Big Name Fan]] is a fan who has achieved notoriety and respect within a fandom for their contributions of various sorts, such as heading of a major fan club. Some big name fans have made such a longstanding contribution to the support of a team or celebrity that they are able to meet the object of their affection and interest. Big Name Fans in some fandoms or fan scenes may have fans of their own and be asked for autographs.

===Otaku===
{{details|Otaku}}
In Japan, where the term ''otaku'' originates, it is applied to fans of almost any topic, including anime/manga, the military, trains, etc. The term in Japan is derogatory (at least to those outside the otaku subculture), but with such works as the popular [[Densha Otoko]], this may be changing. In English, the term [[Otaku]] has been adopted almost exclusively to describe fans of anime, manga and related materials. It also lacks the derogatory overtones it has in Japan.

===Trekkies===
[[Trekkies]] are fans focused on the ''[[Star Trek]]'' [[science fiction]] franchise. Arising out of [[science fiction fandom]] they, to some extent, have served as a template for other organized fandoms in the [[science fiction television]] and [[science fiction film|film]] genres.

It should be noted that some &quot;Trekkies&quot; prefer to be referred to as &quot;Trekkers&quot; as they feel the term &quot;Trekkies&quot; was used in the past as a derogatory name for them and they hope to avoid the traditional stigma sometimes associated with being known as a &quot;Trekkie&quot;.

Many &quot;old school&quot; fans of the ''Star Trek'' universe defiantly, and proudly, refer to themselves, and other ''Star Trek'' fans, as &quot;Trekkies&quot; rather than the kinder, gentler &quot;Trekkers&quot; name used by many of the newer generations of ''Star Trek'' fans.

===Gaming fans===
Gaming fans ([[gamers]]) are fans focused on gaming, usually [[role-playing game]]s, [[board game]]s, [[miniature wargame]]s, [[collectible card game]]s or [[computer game]]s.

==Fan psychology==
===Sports===
The drivers that make people fans, and in particular sports fans, have been studied by psychologists, such as Dan Wann at [[Murray State University]]. They attribute people becoming fans to the following factors:&lt;ref name=Conrad&gt;{{cite book|title=The Business of Sports: A Primer for Journalists|author=Mark Conrad|chapter=What Makes Sports a Unique Business?|pages=xxx–xxxi|year=2006|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0805850449|nopp=true}}&lt;/ref&gt; One element is entertainment, because sports spectatorship is a form of leisure. Sports is also a form of escapism, and being a fan gives one an excuse to yell at something, an activity that may be constrained in other areas of one's life. Fan activities give participants a combination of euphoria and stress (about the potential for their team to lose) for which they coin the name &quot;eustress&quot;. Fans experience euphoria during moments when play is going well for their team, and stress when play is going against their team. This tension between the two emotions generates an unusual sense of pleasure or heightened sensations.

Aesthetics are another draw for some fans, who appreciate the precision or skill of play, or of the coordinated movement of the players during a pre-planned &quot;play&quot;. Family bonding is a reason for some fan activities. Some families go to sports games every month as a family outing to watch a sports event and form a [[human bonding|psychological bond]] with one another as a family. Going to sports events can create a borrowed sense of self-esteem if fans identify with their teams to the extent that they consider themselves to be successful when their teams have been successful (e.g., as seen in the phrase &quot;we have won&quot;).

===Loyalty===
{{Main|Fan loyalty}}
'''Fan loyalty''' is the loyalty felt and expressed by a fan towards the object of his/her fanaticism. Allegiances can be strong or weak. The loyalties of sports fans have been studied by psychologists

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
* [[Behavioral addiction|Addiction]]
* [[Bandwagon effect]]
* [[Beatle Bob]]
* [[Big Name Fan]]
* [[Celebrity Worship Syndrome]]
* [[Chacha Cricket]]
* [[Charisma]]
* [[Cult of personality]]
* [[Fan art]]
* [[Fan club]]
* [[Fan fiction]]
* [[Fan labor]]
* [[Fan loyalty]]
* [[Fan service]]
* [[Fandom]]
* [[Fansite]]
* [[Fanspeak]]
* [[Fanzine]]
* [[Groupie]]
* [[Obsession (disambiguation)|Obsession]]
* [[Roadgeek]]
* [[Trainspotter]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
* {{cite book|author=Daniel L. Wann, Merrill J. Melnick, Gordon W. Russell, and Dale G. Pease|title=SportFans: The Psychology and Social Impact of Spectators|year=2001|location=London|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0415924634}}
* Tucker, Bob. ''The Neo-Fan's Guide To Science Fiction Fandom''. 8th Edition, 1996. KaCSFFS Press. No ISBN listed.

==External links==
* [http://m-w.com/dictionary/fan Merriam-Webster: fan]
* [http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/fan_2?view=uk Oxford Dictionary: fan]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fan (Person)}}
[[Category:Fandom| ]]

[[Peminat]]

[[zh-min-nan:Siáu-iú]]
[[cs:Fanoušek]]
[[da:Fan]]
[[de:Fan]]
[[es:Fan]]
[[eo:Fervora subtenanto]]
[[fr:Supporteur]]
[[gl:Fan]]
[[ko:팬]]
[[it:Fan]]
[[he:אוהד (ספורט)]]
[[kk:Жанкүйер]]
[[lb:Fan]]
[[ms:Peminat]]
[[nl:Fan]]
[[ja:ファン]]
[[no:Supporter]]
[[pl:Fan]]
[[pt:Fã]]
[[ru:Фанат]]
[[simple:Fanatic]]
[[sk:Fanúšik]]
[[fi:Fani]]
[[sv:Supporter]]
[[th:แฟน]]
[[uk:Фанат]]
[[zh-yue:擁躉]]
[[zh:爱好者]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
