<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="874815" ns="0" title="Kurumin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|date=February 2011}}
{{Unreferenced|date=March 2008}}
{{Infobox OS |
  name = Kurumin |
  screenshot = [[Image:kurumin-7.0r3.png|250px]] |
  caption = Kurumin 7.0r3 |
  developer = [[Carlos Morimoto]] |
  family = [[Unix-like]] |
  source_model = [[Open source]] |
  working_state = Discontinued |
  latest_release_version = NG 8.06 |
  latest_release_date = June 2008 |
  kernel_type = [[Monolithic kernel]] |
  license = Various |
  website = [http://www.guiadohardware.net/kurumin/ www.guiadohardware.net/kurumin/] [http://www.kurumin-ng.com.br/ www.kurumin-ng.com.br] |
}}

'''Kurumin''' Linux was a [[Live CD]] [[operating system]] based on [[Debian]]. Its main features are the advanced hardware auto-detection (inherited from Knoppix) and a [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] user interface, and its main goal is ease of use. As of release 7.0, the size of the [[disk image]] is approximately 603 MB.

Version NG 8.06, based on Ubuntu 8.04, was released June 24, 2008, and was discontinued on January 29, 2009.

== Features ==

The distribution boasts an open-source control center (a series of shell scripts and Kommander based panels) named ''ClicaAki'' (roughly: &quot;ClickHere&quot;), which features a series of &quot;magic icons&quot; that install software not included in the live CD (including games and proprietary video drivers) and configure a wide range of networking options. It also provides access to the [[Synaptic Package Manager|Synaptic]] [[package manager]].

The name comes from the [[Tupian languages|Tupi]] word ''&quot;kurumi&quot;'', which means [[boy]]. The usage of the letter K, instead of the usual [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] spelling (''&quot;curumi&quot;'' or ''&quot;curumim&quot;''), brings it in line with [[KDE]] (Kurumin's default [[desktop environment]]), as well as with Knoppix.

The Kurumin control panel ( AKA ClicaAki ), has shortcuts to scripts that perform tasks like downloading and installing free games, with apps divided into categories and a short description of how they work and their differences. This control panel also has scripts for downloading and automatically configuring 3d video cards ( ATI and Nvidia ), a difficult task for novice users. Another feature of the distro is that it has support for many &quot;winmodems&quot;, including some that have no official packages of drivers in the Debian repository, and also with scripts that automate the tasks of compiling and configuring the module. With this features, Kurumin spread the Gnu/Linux operating system in Brazil in a level never seen before. In the late of 2007 Morimoto said that the project would be halted or have its scope reduced. In November 2008 the project was officially discontinued.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
*[[Poseidon Linux]], a distribution based on Kurumin

==External links==
* [http://www.guiadohardware.net/kurumin/ Kurumin official site (in Portuguese)]
* {{DistroWatch|kurumin|NAME=Kurumin}}
* [http://luciano.kurumin.com.br/ Oca do Kurumin (Fansite)]
* [http://lwn.net/Articles/72881/ LWN: Linux in Brazil]

{{linux-distro}}

[[Category:Knoppix]]
[[Category:Portuguese-language Linux distributions]]
[[Category:Discontinued Linux distributions]]

[[es:Kurumin Linux]]
[[fr:Kurumin]]
[[it:Kurumin Linux]]
[[pl:Kurumin]]
[[pt:Kurumin]]
[[ro:Kurumin]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
