<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="87678" ns="0" title="The Waltons"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name            = The Waltons
| image                = [[File:The Waltons Title Screen.png|220px]]
| caption              = Title screen from Season 1 (early episodes, without [[Lorimar]] notice)
| genre                = [[Drama|Family Drama]]
| creator              = [[Earl Hamner, Jr.]]
| starring             = [[Richard Thomas (actor)|Richard Thomas]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ralph Waite]]&lt;br&gt;[[Michael Learned]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ellen Corby]]&lt;br&gt;[[Will Geer]]&lt;br&gt;[[Judy Norton Taylor|Judy Norton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jon Walmsley]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mary Elizabeth McDonough]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eric Scott (actor)|Eric Scott]]&lt;br&gt;[[David W. Harper]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kami Cotler]] 
| narrated             = Earl Hamner, Jr.
| country              = United States
| language             = [[English language|English]]
| num_seasons          = 9
| num_episodes         = 221 + 7 TV movies
| list_episodes        = List of The Waltons episodes
| producer             = Robert L. Jacks&lt;br&gt;Andy White&lt;br&gt;Rod Peterson&lt;br&gt;Claylene Jones
| exec producer        = [[Lee Rich]]&lt;br&gt;[[Earl Hamner Jr.]]&lt;br&gt;[[Rod Peterson]] 
| camera               = [[Single-camera setup|Single-camera]]
| runtime              = 45&amp;ndash;48 minutes
| company              = [[Lorimar Productions]]&lt;br&gt;Amandas Productions
| distributor          = [[Warner Bros. Television]] Distribution
| network              = [[CBS]]
| first_aired          = {{Start date|1972|09|14}}
| last_aired           = {{End date|1981|06|04}}
| status               = Ended
| website              = 
}}

'''''The Waltons''''' is an American television series created by [[Earl Hamner, Jr.]], based on his book ''Spencer's Mountain'', and a 1963 [[Spencer's Mountain|film of the same name]]. The show centered on a family growing up in a rural [[Virginia]] community during the [[Great Depression]] and [[World War II]]. The series pilot was a television movie entitled ''The Homecoming: A Christmas Story'', broadcast on December 19, 1971.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0067209/1971&lt;/ref&gt; The show originally aired  on [[CBS]] beginning in the fall of 1972 for nine seasons. After the series left the air in 1981, three television movie sequels were broadcast in 1982, with three more following in the 1990s.''The Waltons'' was produced by [[Lorimar Productions]] and distributed by [[Warner Bros. Television|Warner Bros. Domestic Television Distribution]] in syndication.

==Plot==
{{Main|List of The Waltons episodes}}
===Setting===
The show takes place in Walton's Mountain, a [[fictional town]] at the foot of a mountain in fictitious Jefferson County, [[Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;In fact, there is a [[Jefferson County, West Virginia]], but not in Virginia.&lt;/ref&gt; The time is during [[the Great Depression]] and [[World War II]], during the presidency of [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]]. John Walton Jr. -- known to nearly everyone as John-Boy -- is seventeen years old,&lt;ref&gt;''The Foundling'', Season one, episode 1&lt;/ref&gt; and his parents have been married for eighteen years.&lt;ref&gt;''The Sinner'', Season one, episode 7&lt;/ref&gt; 

The series' timeframe takes the viewer from 1933 to 1946. The year 1933 is suggested by a brief shot of an [[automobile]] registration, and it is divulged in episode 18 that the date is in the spring of 1933.&lt;ref&gt;''The Courtship'', Season one, episode 18&lt;/ref&gt; The series finale, &quot;The Revel&quot;, evolves around a party and the invitation date is given as June 4, 1946. A span of 13 years is therefore covered in nine seasons. There are some chronological errors, which ostensibly do not hinder the storyline. 

The last episode of season one, ''An Easter Story'', is set in February through April, 1934. The year 1934 takes two seasons to cover, while some successive years are covered in months.&lt;ref&gt;A significant [[anachronism]] occurs in the first season. In the first episode, the Waltons listen to [[Edgar Bergen|Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy's]] radio program (in tribute to Bergen, who played Grandpa in the pilot film). However, Bergen's radio show did not begin airing until 1937.&lt;/ref&gt; 

After the series run, six feature-length sequels were made, set from 1947 through 1969, airing between 1982 and 1997.

&quot;A Walton Thanksgiving Reunion&quot; takes place in 1963, 30 years after &quot;The Homecoming&quot;, even though the actors are only 22 years older.  The Walton family characters would have been in their 30s-40s by then, as well as John and Olivia being in their 60s.  John Walton makes a reference to Grandpa having been dead &quot;15 years,&quot; although by the original series timeline it would have been closer to 25 years. Esther Walton and the Baldwin sisters would have been in their late 90s-100 by the last three reunion movies.

The last sequel, 1997's ''A Walton Easter'' was set in 1969, and contains a serious anachronism that contradicts the setting of the series. John and Olivia celebrate their 40th wedding anniversary, which would have advanced their marriage to 1929, and John-Boy's birth to 1930. Yet in the series, younger Erin graduated high school in 1937 and was born in 1919 (&quot;The Career Girl&quot;, 1977).  This would make Erin eleven years older than John Boy. Earl Hamner Sr., the basis for the John Walton character, died in 1969, the year &quot;A Walton's Easter&quot; takes place.

===Story===
[[File:Waltons 1972.JPG|thumb|180px|left|John, John-Boy, and Olivia Walton.]]
John and Olivia Walton, along with John's parents Zebulon &quot;Zeb&quot; and Esther Walton, raise their seven children during the [[Great Depression in the United States|Great Depression]] and [[World War II]]. The family's story is narrated at the opening and closing of each episode by the middle-aged John-Boy (Earl Hamner Jr.), the oldest son who becomes a journalist and novelist. John manages to eke out a living by operating a [[lumber mill]] with the help of his father, and his sons as they grow older. The family income is augmented by some small-scale farming, and John occasionally hunts to put meat on the table. Relatives and strangers occasionally pass by, to whom the family shares its hospitality as they are able. The small community named after their property is also home to folk of various income levels, ranging from the well-to-do Baldwin sisters, two elderly [[spinster]]s who distill [[moonshine]] that they call &quot;Papa's recipe&quot;; Ike Godsey, postmaster and owner of the general store  with his wife Corabeth (a Walton cousin); a [[African-American|black]] couple, Verdie and Harley Foster; Maude, a sassy octogenarian artist who paints on wood; and Yancy Tucker, a good-hearted handyman with big plans but little motivation. Jefferson County sheriff Ep Bridges keeps law and order in Walton's Mountain. The entire family (except for John) attend a Baptist church, of which Olivia and Grandma Esther are the most regular attenders.

In the signature scene that closes almost every episode, the family house is enveloped in darkness, save for one, two or three lights in the upstairs bedroom windows. Through [[voice-over]]s, two or more characters make some brief comments related to that episode's events, and then bid each other goodnight.

After completing high school, John-Boy attends fictional Boatwright University in the fictional nearby town of Westham. He later goes to [[New York City]] to work as a journalist. [[Richard Thomas (actor)|Richard Thomas]], the original actor to play John-Boy, left the series in 1976 to seek other roles; his farewell episode aired March 17, 1977. He would make some guest appearances before the role was recast with actor [[Robert Wightman]].
[[File:The Waltons 1976.JPG|thumb|170px|Grandma and John-Boy.]]
During the latter half of the 1976-77 season, Grandma Esther Walton suffers a stroke (reflecting actress [[Ellen Corby]]'s own stroke and absence from the program), returning home shortly before the death of her husband, Grandpa Zeb Walton (reflecting actor [[Will Geer]]'s death during the 1978 summer hiatus), and underscores her diminished capacity to move and speak.

During the last five years of the series, Mary Ellen and Ben marry and begin having families of their own. Erin, Jason and John Boy are married in later television movie sequels.

[[World War II]] deeply affects the family. All four of the Walton boys enlist in the military. Mary Ellen's physician husband, Curtis &quot;Curt&quot; Willard, is sent to [[Pearl Harbor]] and is reported to have perished in the [[attack on Pearl Harbor|Japanese attack]] on December 7, 1941. Years later, Mary Ellen hears of sightings of her &quot;late&quot; husband, investigates and finds him alive (played by another actor), but brooding over his war wounds and living under an assumed name. She later remarries.

John-Boy's ([[Robert Wightman]]) military plane is shot down, while Olivia becomes a volunteer at the [[Veteran's Administration|VA hospital]] and is seen less and less (reflecting actress [[Michael Learned]]'s reduced involvement), eventually developing [[tuberculosis]] and entering an Arizona sanitarium.  Olivia's cousin, Rose Burton ([[Peggy Rea]]), moves into the Walton house to watch over the brood. Two years later, John, Sr., moves to Arizona to be near Olivia, marking the departure of [[Ralph Waite]] from the cast.  Grandma appeared in only a handful of episodes during the final season (she was usually said to be visiting relatives in nearby Buckingham County), as an increasingly frail Ellen Corby was forced to drop to [[recurring]] status.  In 1981, the writers anticipated season 10 without the paternal John Sr. and created a ''de facto'' dad by wedding Cousin Rose to her salesman beau Stanley Perkins (played by [[William Schallert]]). Nonetheless, with five of the original actors gone, the series was not renewed for another season.

==Characters==
&lt;!----- ATTENTION: Please DO NOT add to this section without group discussion first. This section is meant to be brief. I you have relevant info to add to the charaters PLEASE do it on the List of Waltons characters Wiki, not here. Thank you!--------&gt;
{{Main|List of The Waltons characters}}
[[File:The Waltons 1974.JPG|thumb|170px|Grandpa and Grandma Walton.]]
The following is a '''brief''' summary of the central recurring characters. See the '''main article''' for a more complete list.
* John &quot;John-Boy&quot; Walton, Jr. ([[Richard Thomas (actor)|Richard Thomas]], pilot, series seasons 1–5, guest season 6, three movie sequels; [[Robert Wightman]], seasons 8-9 and one movie sequel), the oldest of seven children, aged 17 in season one.
* John Walton, Sr. (pilot, [[Andrew Duggan]]; [[Ralph Waite]] series and movie sequels), the family patriarch
* Olivia Walton (pilot, [[Patricia Neal]]; [[Michael Learned]] series seasons 1-7, guest season 8, and movie sequels), John's wife.
* Zebulon Tyler &quot;Zeb/Grandpa&quot; Walton, (pilot, [[Edgar Bergen]]; [[Will Geer]] seasons 1-6, not replaced after Geer's death), John's father
* Esther &quot;Grandma&quot; Walton ([[Ellen Corby]], appears regularly season 1 until Corby's stroke midway through season 5; returns last episode of season 6 and remains through the end of season 7; then appears only occasionally in seasons 8 and 9 (and subsequently five of the six sequels), John's mother
* Jason Walton ([[Jon Walmsley]]), John-Boy's younger brother, aged 15 in season 1; musically talented
* Mary Ellen Walton ([[Judy Norton Taylor]]), the oldest Walton daughter, about two years younger than Jason. She becomes a nurse, and is the first Walton child to marry and have children.
* Erin Esther Walton ([[Mary Elizabeth McDonough]]), second Walton daughter. In the first few seasons it is unclear whether she or Ben is older, but she is established as the fourth to graduate from high school in season 5. Works as a telephone operator, and attends business (secretarial) school.
* Benjamin &quot;Ben&quot; Walton ([[Eric Scott (actor)|Eric Scott]]), third Walton son; has an entrepreneurial spirit.
* James Robert &quot;Jim-Bob&quot; Walton ([[David W. Harper]]), youngest Walton son; mechanically inclined, his ambition is to become a pilot.
* Elizabeth Walton ([[Kami Cotler]]), youngest of the seven children
* Rose Burton ([[Peggy Rea]]), seasons 8-9; Olivia's matronly cousin who fills in as matriarch during Olivia's absence.

==Production==
===Inspiration===
Earl Hamner's rural childhood growing up in the [[unincorporated community]] of [[Schuyler, Virginia]], provided the basis for the setting and many of the storylines of ''The Waltons''. His family and the community provided many life experiences which aided in the characters, values, area, and human-interest stories of his books, movies, and television series. Hamner provided the voice-over of the older John-Boy, usually heard at the end of each episode.

John-Boy Walton's fictional [[alma mater]], Boatwright University, is patterned after Richmond College, which became part of the [[University of Richmond]] on Boatwright Drive, near [[Westham Station]] in [[The West End (Richmond, Virginia)|The West End of Richmond, Virginia]], about 70 miles east of Schuyler.

===Filming===
The town of Walton's Mountain was built in the rear area of the Warner Brothers Studios, but the mountain itself was part of the range opposite Warner studios in Burbank, California. The Walton's house facade was built on the ''[[Here Come the Brides]]'' set on the Columbia Ranch studio, now one of the Warner Brothers studios. The Waltons' house is still used as scenery at Warner Brothers. For example, it served as the Dragonfly Inn on ''[[Gilmore Girls]]''.

==Broadcast and release==
===Ratings===
*1972–1973: #20&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classictvhits.com/tvratings/1972.htm ClassicTVHits.com: TV Ratings &gt; 1972–1973]&lt;/ref&gt;
*1973–1974: #2&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classictvhits.com/tvratings/1973.htm ClassicTVHits.com: TV Ratings &gt; 1973–1974]&lt;/ref&gt;
*1974–1975: #8&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classictvhits.com/tvratings/1974.htm ClassicTVHits.com: TV Ratings &gt; 1974–1975]&lt;/ref&gt;
*1975–1976: #14&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classictvhits.com/tvratings/1975.htm ClassicTVHits.com: TV Ratings &gt; 1975–1976]&lt;/ref&gt;
*1976–1977: #15&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classictvhits.com/tvratings/1976.htm ClassicTVHits.com: TV Ratings &gt; 1976–1977]&lt;/ref&gt;
*1977–1978: #21&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classictvhits.com/tvratings/1977.htm ClassicTVHits.com: TV Ratings &gt; 1977–1978]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== DVD releases ===
[[Warner Home Video]] has released all nine seasons and six TV movies of ''The Waltons'' on DVD in Region 1.  Seasons 1-4 have been released in Region 2. The pilot movie, ''The Homecoming - A Christmas Story'', was released by [[Paramount Home Entertainment]]. [[Lorimar]] produced the series, CBS produced the pilot film, which is why Paramount, under [[CBS Home Entertainment]], handles home video rights for ''The Homecoming''. 
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|DVD Name 
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Ep #
|-
! Region 1
! Region 2 (UK)
|-
| ''The Homecoming - A Christmas Story''
| align=&quot;center&quot;|1
| September 23, 2003
| N/A
|-
| The Complete 1st Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|25
| May 11, 2004
| November 1, 2004
|-
| The Complete 2nd Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|25
| April 26, 2005
| July 3, 2006
|-
| The Complete 3rd Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|25
| April 25, 2006
| September 11, 2006
|-
| The Complete 4th Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|25
| January 23, 2007
| March 5, 2007
|-
| The Complete 5th Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|25
| May 8, 2007
| N/A
|-
| The Complete 6th Season 
| align=&quot;center&quot;|25
| January 8, 2008
| N/A
|-
| The Complete 7th Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|23
| April 29, 2008
| N/A
|-
| The Complete 8th Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|23
| January 6, 2009
| N/A
|-
| The Complete 9th Season
| align=&quot;center&quot;|22
| April 28, 2009
| N/A
|-
| TV Movie Collection (not including the original movie)
| align=&quot;center&quot;|6
| January 26, 2010
| N/A
|}

===Current status===
''The Waltons'' airs in the U.S. on [[The Inspiration Network|INSP - Inspiration]] each weekday at 1pm, 8pm, and 9pm Eastern time. The show can also be seen on the [[Hallmark Channel]] weekdays at 3pm, 4pm, and 5pm Eastern time. [[Gospel Music Channel]] (gmc) runs two episodes of ''The Waltons'' weekdays at 12 noon and 1pm Eastern and three episodes weeknights at 6pm, 7pm and 8pm Eastern. INSP also frequently on holiday weekends will air Waltons marathons or specials including cast reunions. In Canada, ''The Waltons'' airs on [[VisionTV]] weekdays at 5:00 pm ET,6:00 pm AT. The show is on the True Entertainment Channel in the UK, Sky Digital channel 188 and Freesat channel 142, Monday to Friday at 12:00 pm and 5.00pm.

==Reception and impact==
===Emmy Awards===
''The Waltons'' won the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Drama Series]] in 1973. Also in 1973 Richard Thomas won the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Lead Actor - Drama Series|Emmy]] for Lead Actor in a Drama Series. Michael Learned won the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Lead Actress - Drama Series|Emmy]] for Lead Actress in a Drama Series three times (1973, 1974, and 1976). Ellen Corby was also a three-time winner in the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actress - Drama Series|Supporting Actress]] category, winning in 1973, 1975, and 1976.  Will Geer was awarded the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actor - Drama Series|Supporting Actor Emmy]] in 1975. Veteran actress [[Beulah Bondi]] won an Emmy in 1977 for Lead Actress in a Single Performance for her guest appearance as Martha Corrine Walton in the episode ''The Pony Cart'' (Episode #111). She first appeared in The Waltons episode ''The Conflict'' (Episode #51) as the widow of Zeb Walton's brother.

The series also earned a [[Peabody Award]] for its first season.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.peabody.uga.edu/winners/details.php?id=738&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cultural references===
[[Image:WMCS.jpg|right|thumb|200px|The Walton's Mountain Country Store in Nelson County, Virginia]]
*During a speech in January 1992, then-president George H. W. Bush mentioned that he wanted to &quot;make American families a lot more like the Waltons and a lot less like ''[[The Simpsons]]''&quot;. Later, in the [[cold opening]] to an episode, [[Bart Simpson]] responded to the comment, quipping, &quot;We're just like The Waltons. We're praying for an end to the Depression, too&quot;.
*A country store in Nelson County, VA is called the ''Walton's Mountain Country Store''.
*In [[Gilmore Girls]], season 1 episode 6, Lorelai tells Rory about her birth in detail and Rory says 'I wonder if the Waltons ever did this'.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*''Ike Godsey of Walton's Mountain,'' by Joe Conley. Albany, BearManor Media 2010. ISBN 978-1-59393-508-5.

==External links==
* {{imdb title|id=0068149|title=The Waltons}}
* {{tv.com|1279|The Waltons}}
* [http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/W/htmlW/waltonsthe/waltonsthe.htm Encyclopedia of Television]
* [http://www.waltonmuseum.org/ Walton's Mountain Museum official website]
* [http://www.the-waltons.com/ The Waltons website]
* [http://www.grandpawalton.20megsfree.com/ A Walk with Grandpa Walton and the Walton family]
* [http://users.galesburg.net/~atkins/waltons.html The Walton's Mountain Community Center]
* [http://www.rockfish-river.com Rockfish-river.com - German /english Waltons-fanpage with travel reports, reports about Walton reunions and many photos and videos]
* [http://www.waltonsmountaincountrystore.com Waltons Mountain]
* [http://the-waltons-home-page.com/ The Waltons Unofficial Home Page]
* [http://www.videosforfamily.com/thewaltons.htm &quot;A Tribute To The Waltons&quot; - Cast Interviews]
* [http://www.hallmarkchannel.com/thewaltons The Waltons on Hallmark Channel]

{{EmmyAward DramaSeries 1951-1975}}
{{GoldenGlobeTVDrama 1969-1989}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Waltons, The}}
[[Category:1972 television series debuts]]
[[Category:1981 television series endings]]
[[Category:1970s American television series]]
[[Category:1980s American television series]]
[[Category:American drama television series]]
[[Category:Best Drama Series Golden Globe winners]]
[[Category:CBS network shows]]
[[Category:Emmy Award winning programs]]
[[Category:English-language television series]]
[[Category:Fictional families]]
[[Category:Fictional characters from Virginia]]
[[Category:Peabody Award winning television programs]]
[[Category:Television programs based on novels]]
[[Category:Television series by Warner Bros. Television]]
[[Category:Television shows set in Virginia]]
[[Category:Television series set in the 1930s]]
[[Category:Television series set in the 1940s]]

[[de:Die Waltons]]
[[es:The Waltons]]
[[fr:La Famille des collines]]
[[it:Una famiglia americana]]
[[nl:The Waltons]]
[[pl:The Waltons]]
[[pt:The Waltons]]
[[sh:The Waltons]]
[[fi:Waltonin perhe]]
[[sv:Familjen Walton]]
[[tr:The Waltons]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
