<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="DCAE Cosford" to="RAF Cosford" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="12453827" ns="0" title="RAF Cosford"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox airport 
| name         = RAF Cosford
| nativename   = 
| nativename-a = 
| nativename-r = 
| image        = RAF Cosford.png
| image-width  = 125
| caption      = Station crest
| IATA         = 
| ICAO         = EGWC
| type         = Military
| owner        = 
| operator     = [[Royal Air Force]]
| city-served  = 
| location     = [[Albrighton, Bridgnorth|Albrighton]]
| elevation-f  = 272
| elevation-m  = 83
| coordinates  = {{Coord|52|38|24|N|002|18|20|W|type:airport|name=RAF Cosford}}
| latd = 52 | latm = 38 | lats = 42 | latNS = N
| longd= 002 | longm= 15 | longs= 20 | longEW= W
| coordinates_type       = airport
| coordinates_region     = GB
| pushpin_map            = United Kingdom Shropshire
| pushpin_label          = EGWC
| pushpin_map_caption    = Location in Shropshire
| website      = [http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafcosford/ raf.mod.uk/rafcosford]
| metric-rwy   = Yes
| r1-number    = 06/24
| r1-length-f  = 3,890
| r1-length-m  = 1,186
| r1-surface   = [[Asphalt]]
| r2-number = 
| r2-length-f = 3,900
| r2-length-m = 1,180
| r2-surface = [[Grass]]
| stat-year    = 
| stat1-header = 
| stat1-data   = 
| stat2-header = 
| stat2-data   = 
| footnotes    = 
}}

'''RAF Cosford''' (formerly '''DCAE Cosford''')&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/dcaecosford/aboutus/thenamerafcosford.cfm RAF Cosford]&lt;/ref&gt; {{Airport codes||EGWC}} is a [[Royal Air Force]] station in [[Cosford, Shropshire|Cosford]], [[Shropshire]], just to the northwest of [[Wolverhampton]] and next to [[Albrighton, Bridgnorth|Albrighton]].

==Use of the station==
===History===
RAF Cosford opened in 1938 as a joint aircraft maintenance, storage and technical training unit. It has remained mainly a training unit to this day. The ''Fulton Mess'' barrack block was constructed just before WW2 as the largest single building barrack block in the UK. It is now used for technical training.

A substantial [[Princess Mary's Royal Air Force Nursing Service|PMRAFNS]] hospital was established at RAF Cosford, the most westerly such RAF hospital in the UK. Constructed of wooden spurred hutting the hospital closed on 31 December 1977 and was demolished in 1980. For the three summers between 1978 and 1980 the empty hospital formed the venue for annual training camps for the [[Royal Observer Corps]], with wards and theatres converted into barrack accommodation and training rooms.

The extensive sports facilities at Cosford, based around a banked indoor running track, became well known nationally through televised annual indoor championships that featured top athletes from all over the world.

===Cosford today===
[[File:24 Approach.jpg|thumb|Runway 24 at RAF Cosford, as seen during final approach.]]
Schools currently stationed there include: [[No. 1 School of Technical Training]], [[Number 1 Radio School|No 1 Radio School]], the Defence School of Photography and the RAF School of Physical Training. Flying units include the [[Birmingham University Air Squadron|University of Birmingham Air Squadron]], No 8 [[Air Experience Flight]] and No 633 [[Volunteer Gliding Squadron]]. The Wales and West regional headquarters and West Mercian Wing headquarters of the [[Air Training Corps]] are based there, along with 2497 (Cosford) Squadron of the ATC.

Cosford became part of the [[Defence College of Aeronautical Engineering]] (DCAE), which was formed on 1 April 2004. Other units located at Cosford include elements of the [[Defence College of Communications and Information Systems]] (DCCIS), the Defence School of Photography (DSOP) and the RAF School of Physical Training.

In early 2009 there was a strong chance that the DCAE would relocate to [[RAF St Athan]] and therefore a decision was given to rename the base RAF Cosford.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafcosford/aboutus/dcaecosfordpresent.cfm RAF Cosford History]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operational units===
*Defence College of Aeronautical Engineering Cosford
**HQ DCAE
**Aerosystems Training Wing
**Military Training Wing
*Lodger Units
**No 1 Radio School (Part of the Defence College of Communication and Information Systems (DCCIS).
**Defence School of Photography (Part of the Defence Intelligence and Security Centre (DISC)).
**RAF School of Physical Training.
**HQ Wales and Western Region Air Training Corps.
**Headquarters West Mercia West Wing Air Training Corps.
**The RAF Museum Cosford.
**University of Birmingham Air Squadron
**No 8 Air Experience Flight,
**No 633 Volunteer Gliding Squadron
**2497 Squadron (Air Training Corps)

===Aerospace museum===
There is also the Aerospace Museum at the site, which is a branch of the [[Royal Air Force Museum Cosford|Royal Air Force Museum]]. Amongst the large collection of military aircraft is a unique collection of research and development aircraft, including one of two existing examples of the [[BAC TSR-2|TSR2]], a multi-role combat aircraft, controversially scrapped by the [[Harold Wilson|Wilson]] Government and still a point of discussion within the RAF. There are also collections of missiles and airliners. 

The Cold War Exhibition opened on 7 February 2007 by former prime minister Baroness [[Margaret Thatcher]] and [[Anne, Princess Royal|HRH Princess Anne]]. Exhibits include the only collection of three V bombers ([[Vickers Valiant|Valiant]], [[Handley Page Victor|Victor]] and [[Avro Vulcan|Vulcan]]) in the same place in the world.

===Future plans===
Following the UK Government's 2001 [[Defence Training Review]] (DTR), the [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] proposed handing over armed forces skills training to a private sector bidder for a 25-year term, and it was announced on 17 January 2007 that the [[Metrix UK|Metrix]] consortium had been awarded Preferred Bidder status for Package 1 of this programme. As a consequence, it is anticipated that all technical training will move from Cosford to Metrix's main campus to be built on the [[RAF St Athan]] site over a 5-year period from 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnn.gov.uk/Content/Detail.asp?ReleaseID=257220&amp;NewsAreaID=2 Government News Network - Wednesday 17 January 2007 13:22]&lt;/ref&gt; This in turn has been deferred with no anticipated move from Cosford to St Athan for DCAE and No1 RS staff and trainees before 2014-15 at the earliest. For those other training schools, headquarters and units at present at Cosford, decisions have yet to be made about their future location.[http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafcosford/aboutus/dcaecosfordpresent.cfm]

On 31 January 2008, the Government announced that when 1 Signal Brigade and [[102nd Logistics Brigade (United Kingdom)|102 Logistics Brigade]] withdraw from [[Germany]] they will move to Cosford. It was also noted that Metrix propose to establish a Learning Centre and Design facility at the Cosford site.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafcosford/}}
*[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/cosford/ RAF Museum Cosford]
*[http://www.633vgs.org.uk/ Official 633 Gliding School site]
*{{WAD|EGWC}}
*[http://www.nationalcoldwarexhibition.org.uk/ National Cold War Exhibition site ]
*[http://www.cosfordflyingclub.org/ Cosford Flying Club Home Page]

[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1938]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force stations in Shropshire|Cosford]]
[[Category:Volunteer Gliding Squadron|633 VGS]]
[[Category:Airports in England|Cosford]]

[[ar:كلية كوسفورد لهندسة الطيران]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
