<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8824877" ns="0" title="Timeline of events in Hamilton, Ontario"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{See also|History of Hamilton, Ontario|List of Royal visits to Hamilton, Ontario}}

Below is a timeline of events in [[Hamilton, Ontario]] [[Canada]].

[[Image:Joseph Brant 2.jpg|thumb|right|[[Joseph Brant]], 1786]]

==Before 1800==
* According to all records from local historians, this district was inhabited by the [[Neutral Indians]] who called it '''ATTIWANDARONIA.''' &lt;ref name=SAGA&gt;{{cite book|title=Saga of a City|first=Milton |last=Watson|publisher=The Hamilton Spectator|year=1938}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1616- Like most of the Americas south of the tree line, the original inhabitants of the Hamilton area were [[First Nations|Indians]]. The first European to visit what is now Hamilton was probably [[Étienne Brûlé]] in 1616. Lasalle also visited the area, a fact commemorated at a park in nearby Burlington.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1-p143&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Hamilton Biography (Vol I, 1791–1875)|first=Thomas Melville |last=Bailey|publisher=W.L. Griffin Ltd|page=143|year=1981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1650- The [[Iroquois]] Indians fought the [[Neutral Nation|Neutrals]] in a great battle on the foot of present day ''Emerald Street''. This area was the end of an old Indian trail that led to the Dundas Valley. The Iroquois landed from [[canoes]] and won the battle because they had obtained [[guns]] from the [[Dutch (ethnic group)|Dutch]], and the Neutrals refused to trade with the whites. So many Neutrals were slain that the mound where they were buried could still be seen after 250 years (1900).&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1780- About the year that both [[Robert Land]] and [[Richard Beasley]] arrived.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1784- About 10,000 [[United Empire Loyalists]] are settled in what is now southern Ontario, chiefly in [[Niagara-on-the-Lake, Ontario|Niagara]], around the [[Bay of Quinte]], and along the [[St. Lawrence River]] between [[Lake Ontario]] and [[Montreal]]. They are soon followed by many more Americans, some of them not so much ardent loyalists but attracted nonetheless by the availability of cheap, arable land. At the same time large numbers of Iroquois loyal to Britain arrive from the United States and are settled on reserves west of Lake Ontario. Kingston and Hamilton became important settlements as a result of the influx of Loyalists.&lt;ref name=LOYALISTS&gt;{{cite web| title =United Empire Loyalists' Association of Canada| url=http://www.uelac.org/
| accessdate = 2007-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1788- (1788–1793) The townships at the [[Head-of-the-Lake]] were surveyed and named. The area was first known as The Head-of-the-Lake for its location at the western end of Lake Ontario.&lt;ref name=headlake&gt;{{cite web| title =Chronology of the Regional Municipality of Hamilton-Ontario| url=http://epe.lac-bac.gc.ca/100/200/301/ic/can_digital_collections/cultural_landmarks/twps.html| accessdate = 2007-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1790- Richard Beasley occupied ''Burlington Heights'' (now the site of ''Dundurn'' and ''Harvey Parks'') in 1790 &amp; was granted land by the Crown in 1799. A local entrepreneur, Beasley's business ventures included fur trading, land acquisition and establishment of a grist mill in [[Ancaster, Ontario|Ancaster]]. He was a member of the legislative assembly of [[Upper Canada]] from 1791 to 1804 and was appointed colonel of the 2nd regiment of the York militia in 1809. Financial difficulties forced Beasley to sell lands at Burlington Heights, but it was purchased in 1832 by [[Allan MacNab|Sir Allan Napier MacNab]] who built [[Dundurn Castle]] on foundations of Beasley's brick home.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Hamilton Biography (Vol I, 1791–1875)|first=Thomas Melville |last=Bailey|publisher=W.L. Griffin Ltd|year=1981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1791- Barton township established originally in Lincoln township. Eventually becomes part of Wentworth County in 1816.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1791- a total of 31 families are recorded  as having settled at the ''Head-of-the-Lake'' (present day Hamilton).&lt;ref name=FOOTSTEPS&gt;{{cite book|title=Footsteps In Time: Exploring Hamilton's heritage neighbourhoods|first=Bill |last=Manson |publisher=North Shore Publishing Inc|year=2003|isbn= 1-896899-22-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1791- Like [[British North America]] itself, the Six Nations confederacy was torn apart by the [[American Revolution]]. Indians loyal to the Crown, under their leader Captain [[Joseph Brant]], were settled in several nearby areas of what became Upper Canada in 1791 and ultimately Ontario in 1867.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1792- Administratively, the whole area was part of the Nassau District, which was renamed the Home District in 1792. Additionally, parts of the area were separately incorporated into the West Riding of [[York County, Ontario|York County]] and First Riding of [[Lincoln County, Ontario|Lincoln County]]. In 1798, most of the future Hamilton became part of Niagara District while remaining in Lincoln County.&lt;ref name=barton2&gt;{{cite web| title =A History of the city of Hamilton| url=http://epe.lac-bac.gc.ca/100/200/301/ic/can_digital_collections/cultural_landmarks/hamhist.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1795- First Lodge of [[Free Masons]], Barton Lodge. (November 20)&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

==1800–1829==
* 1801– Concession 2 lot 14, Barton Township was part of the original [[Crown Grant]] to [[John Askin]] on July 10, 1801. He sold to [[Nathaniel Hughson]] senior who sold to [[James Durand]] around 1806.&lt;ref name=barton&gt;{{cite web| title =Gore Park, Barton Township| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Gore+Park.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1801– First log court house.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1801– First documented murder case in Hamilton. Victim's name was ''Bartholomew London''.&lt;ref name=murder&gt;{{cite web| title =First documented murder in Hamilton: 1801| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Murder+1801-1899.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1803– [[John Ryckman]], born in Barton township, described the area in 1803 as he remembered it: &quot;The city in 1803 was all forest. The shores of the bay were difficult to reach or see because they were hidden by a thick, almost impenetrable mass of trees and undergrowth...Bears ate pigs, so settlers warred on bears. Wolves gobbled sheep and geese, so they hunted and trapped wolves. They also held organized raids on rattlesnakes on the mountainside. There was plenty of game. Many a time have I seen a deer jump the fence into my back yard, and there were millions of pigeons which we clubbed as they flew low.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;barton2&quot;/&gt;

* 1809– Talk of creating a townsite at what is now the intersection of [[John Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|John]] and [[Main Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Main Streets]] arose as early as 1809, but the war delayed the scheme until 1816 when [[George Hamilton (politician)|George Hamilton]] and Nathaniel Hughson successfully promoted Hamilton as the judicial centre for the counties of Halton and Wentworth (the Gore District).&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1812– The town of Hamilton was conceived by George Hamilton when he purchased the Durand farm shortly after the [[War of 1812]].&lt;ref name=HAMBIO1/&gt;

* 1813–  Two American schooners, the [[Hamilton (schooner)|Hamilton]] and the [[Scourge (Schooner)|Scourge]], capsized in Lake Ontario in 1813.&lt;ref name=hamsco&gt;{{cite web| title =Hamilton-Scourge web site| url=http://www.hamilton-scourge.city.hamilton.on.ca/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1813– June 5–6 – British win [[Battle of Stoney Creek]].&lt;ref name=stoneycreek&gt;{{cite web| title =Battlefield House Museum Battle of Stoney Creek 1813| url=http://www.battlefieldhouse.ca/billy_battle.asp| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1813– Eleven men hanged for treason right across the street from where Dundurn Castle eventually gets built.&lt;ref name=firstelect&gt;{{cite web| title = Chronology of Cities, Towns and Townships of Hamilton| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Townships.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-10}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1813– Hamilton laid out as a village.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1814– Wm. Sheldon opened the first store at the corner of [[King Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|King Street]] and John Street.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1815– A chopping mill is the first industry in Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;ref name=HISINDI&gt;{{cite web| title = History of Industry in Hamilton, Ontario| url=http://epe.lac-bac.gc.ca/100/205/301/ic/cdc/industrial/intro.htm| accessdate = 2009-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1815– George Hamilton, a settler and local politician, established a town site in the northern portion Barton Township after the war in 1815. He kept several east-west roads which were originally Indian trails, but the north-south streets were on a regular grid pattern. Streets were designated &quot;East&quot; or &quot;West&quot; if they crossed [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street]] or Highway 6. Streets were designated &quot;North&quot; or &quot;South&quot; if they crossed King Street or Highway 8.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1816– Barton township population is 668.&lt;ref name=bartont&gt;{{cite web| title =Barton township population: 1816| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Barton+Census+1816.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1816– Hamilton becomes a village.&lt;ref name=headlake /&gt;

* 1817– Barton township population is 800.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1817– First common school on land now occupied by city. It was on King Street, east of [[Wellington Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Wellington Street]].&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1821– First Hamilton School opened. A private school with John Law as master.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1824– First [[Methodist]] church, Now First United.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1827– Growth was aided in 1827 by a channel cut to link [[Burlington Bay]] directly with Lake Ontario, thus improving its marine transportation.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1829– First newspaper, ''Gore Balance'', published by Bartimus Ferguson.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

==1830–1839==
* 1830– Last man to stand in [[pillory]].&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1832– First bound book, ''Samuel Thomson's New Guide to Health'' published by Smith and Hackstaff.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1832– [[Cholera]] swept the city.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1833– George Hamilton’s settlement was incorporated as a police village in 1833. On January 8, 1833 the Legislature passed a further act &quot;To define the limits of the Town of Hamilton, in the District of Gore, and to establish a police station and public market therein.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1833– When the Town of Hamilton was incorporated in 1833, one of the first orders of business, after a closely fought election where 3 out of the 4 candidates had no opposition, was to find a suitable place for the town board to meet.  For the first few years they made do with meeting in local taverns such as Thomas Wilson's inn on the corner of John and [[Jackson Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Jackson Streets]].&lt;ref name=cityhall&gt;{{cite web| title =City Hall town meetings at local Taverns- 1833| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/City+Hall.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1833– The Garland, a local newspaper, publishes a synopsis, Hamilton contained &quot;about one hundred and twenty dwelling houses and upwards of one thousand inhabitants&quot; and then went on to list 4 public buildings, 7 taverns, 16 stores, 2 watchmakers, 2 saddlers, 4 merchant tailors, 4 cabinet makers, 4 boot and shoe makers, 2 bakers, 4 newspapers, 1 druggist, 1 tin and sheet iron manufactory, 1 hatter and 3 millineries. (February 16, 1833)&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1834– Beach Canal opens and population now at 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1835– [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street]] was the ''Lake Road'' and in 1835, James Street was extended south, but was interrupted by a [[bog]] at [[Hunter Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Hunter Street]] which eventually (1844) was drained out and graded.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOOTSTEPS&quot;/&gt;

* 1835– Sir Allan MacNab completed Dundurn Castle, his stately home, in 1835.&lt;ref name=macnab&gt;{{cite book| last = Bailey| first = Melville| title = The History of Dundurn Castle and Sir Allan MacNab | date = 1987 (reprint)| pages = 1–38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1835– Hamilton's first Bank was the Gore Bank of Hamilton. Chartered in 1835 and opened on Monday May 2, 1836.&lt;ref name=Bank&gt;{{cite web| title = Fast Facts from Hamilton's Past| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Fast+Facts.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-08 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060905060213/http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Fast+Facts.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1835– One of Hamilton's early newspapers is published by [[George Perkins Boothesby Bull]]; ''The Hamilton Gazette, and General Advertiser''. Newspaper lasts until 1856.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1836– George Hamilton, the city's founder, died on February 20, 1836. His body was buried at the family burial plot on the family's own farm. It is now part of ''Mountain Side Park''. The monument (tombstone) at the Hamilton cemetery wasn't put there until 1894. (George Hamilton's body was not buried at the Hamilton cemetery).&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1836– Hamilton's growth continues. City's boundaries now include The Bay to the north, The mountain ([[Niagara Escarpment]]) to the south, [[Queen Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Queen Street]] to the west and Wellington Street to the east.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1836– Hamilton Waterworks Company incorporated.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1837– Sir Allan MacNab, A boy soldier in the War of 1812, he led Gore militia to crush insurgents in the [[Rebellion of 1837]] for which he was knighted the following year.&lt;ref name=&quot;macnab&quot;/&gt;

* 1838– Sir Allan MacNab, is knighted.&lt;ref name=&quot;macnab&quot;/&gt;

* 1838– St. Mary's Roman Catholic Church  on ''Park Street'' is completed.&lt;ref name=STMARYS&gt;{{cite book|title=Hamilton: An Illustrated History|first=John C. |last=Weaver |publisher=James Lorimer &amp; Company Publishers|year=1982|isbn= 0-88862-593-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1840–1849==
* 1842– First municipal council. The first elections are held and 26 people are chosen to represent the townships of Gore.&lt;ref name=&quot;firstelect&quot;/&gt;

* 1843– First city owned fire engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1846– Hamilton received its city charter in June-9, 1846 by an act of Parliament, 9 Victoria Chapter 73. 3 newspapers, 2 lending libraries, 3 bookstores, 5 common schools, all rented; 2 boys' schools, 3 ladies' seminaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=HENLEY&gt;{{cite book |last= Henley |first= Brian |title= 1846 Hamilton: From a frontier town to the Ambitious City |publisher= North Shore Publishing |year=1995 |isbn= 0-9698460-7-X cloth}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1846– The first telegraph wire in Canada is strung between Hamilton and Toronto on December 1846.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = History of Industry in Hamilton, Ontario| url = http://collections.ic.gc.ca/industrial/intro.htm|archivedate = 2006-02-06|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060206234910/collections.ic.gc.ca/industrial/intro.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1846– ''The Hamilton Spectator'' newspaper is born. (still going strong today).&lt;ref name=CANTIM&gt;{{cite web| title = United Province of Canada Timeline Canadian Encyclopedia| url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCETimelineBrowse&amp;Params=A3PER22SRT1| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1847– [[Colin Campbell Ferrie]] becomes Hamilton's first Mayor.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1847– [[Hugh Cossart Baker, Sr.]] establishes the first life insurance company in Canada (21 August 1847); the [[Canada Life Assurance Company]], with Baker as its president, manager and actuary. (Father of Hamilton telephone pioneer; [[Hugh Cossart Baker, Jr.]])&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1848– King and [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Streets]] [[macadamized]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1849– 92 deaths recorded from [[cholera]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1849– Sir [[William Osler]], &quot;Father of Modern Medicine&quot; (born: July 12, 1849). Raised largely in [[Dundas, Ontario]].&lt;ref name=WOSLER&gt;{{cite web| title =Dictionary of Canadian Biography: Sir William Osler| url=http://www.biographi.ca/009004-119.01-e.php?&amp;id_nbr=7631| accessdate = 2007-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1850–1859==
* 1850– First lighting of streets by gas.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1851– First land bought by the Board of Education.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1852– First orphanage asylum. Population now at 10,300.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1853– First union-journeymen [[carpenters]] formed union and went on strike. First street numbers on buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1854– the newly renamed [[Great Western Railway (Ontario)]] became Hamilton’s first functioning railway in 1854. Completion of this railway and the Niagara Suspension Bridge transforms Hamilton into a major centre and part of the American immigration route from [[New York]] or [[Boston]] to [[Chicago]] or [[Milwaukee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1854– September 11, [[Allan Napier MacNab|Sir Allan Napier MacNab]] becomes the [[List of Joint Premiers of the Province of Canada|Premier]] of Canada West, the only Prime Minister of Canada that Hamilton has ever produced. (The Joint Premiers of the Province of Canada, who were the heads of government of the Province of Canada from the 1841 unification of Upper Canada and Lower Canada until Confederation in 1867. Each administration was led by two men, one from Canada West (now [[Ontario]]) and one from Canada East (now [[Quebec]]). Officially, one of them at any given time had the title of Premier while the other had the title of deputy.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1854– Cholera epidemic- more than 600 deaths.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1855– Hamilton's core boasted a sewer system, graded streets and planked sidewalks. Stumps, boulders, and rocks were finally removed from the streets, animals were banned from wandering freely on the new thoroughfares.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOOTSTEPS&quot;/&gt;

* 1855– [[Grand Lodge of Canada]] is formed in Hamilton, Ontario (10 November 1855). The National Office of the Supreme Council 33° of the Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite of Freemasonry of Canada whose Grand Orient is in Hamilton, Ontario, is located adjacent to this historic Scottish Rite building.

* 1856– First use of [[chloroform]] in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1856– [[Daniel C. Gunn]] engine shop on Wellington Street North, Hamilton, Ontario, produces first Canadian-built locomotives.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1857– 57 passengers were killed when a train derailed near the [[Desjardins Canal]].&lt;ref name=DESJARDINS&gt;{{cite web| title = Desjardins Canal Disaster| url=https://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Desjardins+Canal+Disaster.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1857– When the Great Western railroad made the present opening for the Desjardins Canal, the bones of a [[mammoth]] were found.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1858– ''The Hamilton Times'' newspaper begins publishing 9 January 1858. The newspaper lasts until 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1858– Last man imprisoned here for debt.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1859– Mayor elected by the people. [[Henry McKinstry]] first elected mayor.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1859– Last public execution.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

==1860–1869==
* 1860– First tap water in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1860– The ''Crystal Palace'' opened up at ''Victoria Park'' 20 September 1860. It was home to the area's largest fall fair for many years. The local ''Hamilton Herald'' newspaper was quoted as saying on 22 September 1890, &quot;The Carnival of Venice, The Paris Exposition or the World's Fair in Chicago will be nowhere tomorrow when the great Central Fair is opened at the Crystal Palace Groundsw in this city.&quot; The structure was demolished in 1891.&lt;ref name=HAMTIMES&gt;{{cite book|title=Hamilton our Lives and Times|first=Brian |last=Henley |publisher=The Hamilton Spectator|year=1993|isbn= 0-9697255-0-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1860– First railway sleeping car built in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1862– The city had invested in the Great Western Railway (Ontario) but the government of Canada favoured the rival [[Grand Trunk Railway]]. Also the end of the [[Recession|Depression]] (1857–1862) and population dips downwards in Hamilton and the city could not meet the interest on its bonds, many of which were held by British investors. To save the city from its creditors temporarily, [[Henry Beasley]] removes the assessment rolls, thus preventing a levy of special tax. Foundries and machine shops associated with the Great Western Railway failed and several established wholesalers closed their accounts. Daniel C. Gunn's locomotive works went bankrupt, but the manufacturers of farm implements and stoves-the mainstays of iron foundries- were able to weather the crisis. Those owned by [[Dennis Moore (Canadian manufacturer)|Dennis Moore]] and the Copp brothers endured, but their employees suffered wage cuts and layoffs. Canadian patent laws and the underemployed workers skilled in machinist trades lured an important new industrial enterprise from the U.S.A.- the manufacture of sewing machines by [[Richard Wanzer]]. From this development there evolved the ready-made clothing industry, which [[William Eli Sanford]] introduced locally. From judicial village to commercial town to railway centre, Hamilton moves to an ever stronger dependency on industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1864– First Board of Trade- Hon. [[Isaac Buchanan]], President. 27 churches and 77 taverns in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1867– Confederation of Canada.

* 1868– Hottest day ever recorded in Hamilton as the thermometer hits 41.4 °C &lt;ref name=VANHAM&gt;{{cite book|title=Vanished Hamilton Calender|first=Margaret |last=Houghton |publisher=North Shore Publishing|year=2006|isbn= 1-896899-39-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1869– On Wednesday, November 3, 1869, in a room above George Lee's Fruit Store, the Hamilton Football Club was formed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Football Canada timeline&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.footballcanada.com/history_timeline.asp|title=Canadian Football Timelines (1860 – present)|accessdate=2006-12-23|publisher=[[Football Canada]] |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070228064050/http://www.footballcanada.com/history_timeline.asp &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hamilton Football Clubs have captured the [[Grey Cup]] in every decade of the 20th century, a feat matched in pro sport by only one other franchise, the [[Montreal Canadiens]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Football Canada timeline&quot; /&gt;

==1870–1879==
* 1870–1870s decade; Confederation era Hamilton boosters lose a commercial and financial edge to Toronto and consciously shift to the economic strategy of attracting industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1870– Daily [[temperature]] published.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1872– The [[Nine Hour Movement]] is born, Hamilton unionists urge government to limit working hours to nine per day.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1872 – the [[Bank of Hamilton]] was established. It lasted until 1924. The Bank of Hamilton merged with The Commerce (later to become the [[Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce]], or CIBC) on January 2, 1924. It was one of the last surviving banks in Canada that was not headquartered in [[Toronto]] or Montreal.&lt;ref name=BANKHAM&gt;{{cite web| title = Mergers and Amalgamations, The Canadian Bank of Commerce| url=http://www.cibc.com/ca/inside-cibc/history/mergers-amalgamations/bank-of-commerce.html CIBC| accessdate = 2007-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1873– The Hamilton Football Club played its first game against the recently-formed [[Toronto Argonauts]], which the Argonauts won. It was in that game that the Hamilton players first wore their colours of yellow and black. Hamilton won the rematch the following Saturday, and it was in the reporting of that game that they were first referred to as the Tigers.

* 1874– The [[Hamilton Street Railway]] (HSR) began offering horse-drawn public transportation.&lt;ref name=HSRhistory&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/~wyatt/alltime/hamilton-on.html |title=Hamilton Street Railway History|accessdate=2007-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=HSRhistory2&gt;{{cite web|url= http://hamiltontransithistory.host-ed.net/index.html|title= Hamilton Transit History|accessdate=2007-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1876– First time all the [[Irish people|Irish]] got together in Hamilton to celebrate March 17- St. Patrick's day.&lt;ref name=Irish&gt;{{cite web| title =St. Patrick's Day in Hamilton: 1876| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/St.+Patricks+Day.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1877– June 20, 1877– First commercial telephone service (Fire Department) in Canada began in Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt; Hugh Cossart Baker, Jr. learned of [[Alexander Graham Bell]]'s invention in 1877 at the Philadelphia International Exposition and from there decided to test the communication tool in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=HAM100&gt;{{cite book|title=The Hamiltonians, 100 Fascinating Lives |first=Margaret |last=Houghton |publisher=James Lorimer &amp; Company Ltd., Publishers Toronto|page=6|year=2003|isbn= 1-55028-804-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1877– Robert Smiley, the founding publisher of [[The Spectator]], sold the newspaper to [[William Southam]] in 1877 as the first link in the Southam newspaper chain.&lt;ref name=memproj&gt;{{cite press release| title =The Hamilton Memory Project| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator- Souvenir Edition|page=MP38| date = June 10, 2006| accessdate = 2006-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1877– Hamilton population at 32,641.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1878– The first telephone exchange in the British Empire was opened in Hamilton. (Hugh Cossart Baker, Jr.)&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAM100&quot;/&gt;

* 1879– May 15- Hamilton is the site of the first commercial long distance telephone line in the British Empire. (Hugh Cossart Baker, Jr.), Hamilton to [[Dundas, Ontario|Dundas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAM100&quot;/&gt;

==1880–1889==
* 1880– [[McMaster University]] opens up in Toronto (''Bloor Street'' campus). Eventually moves to Hamilton in 1930.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1880– Apr 29- Hugh Cossart Baker, Jr. of Hamilton, Ontario received charter to build a national telephone company. It was called ''The Hamilton Telephone Company'' and this was the charter that enabled the creation of the [[Bell Telephone]] Company in Canada. Hugh Cossart Baker, Jr. became the manager of the Ontario division until he retired in 1909.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAM100&quot;/&gt;

* 1880– Trained [[nursing]] introduced in city hospital.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1881– [[Thomas Willson]], Hamilton inventor, designed and patented the first electric [[arc lamps]] in 1881.&lt;ref name=WILLSON&gt;{{cite web| title =Biography of Thomas Willson| url=http://www.biographi.ca/EN/ShowBio.asp?BioId=41897| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1881– First public [[telephones]] installed.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1882– Ernest D’Israeli Smith, ([[E.D. Smith]]) after being frustrated by paying to have his fruit transported from the Stoney Creek area, had founded a company in 1882 to market directly to wholesalers and eliminate the middleman. E.D. Smith &amp; Sons Ltd. continues operating today, and has since the early 20th century has sold manufactured preserves and jams. Its namesake founder served as the Conservative MP for Wentworth around the turn of the 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1883– Asphalt sidewalks on main streets.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1886– [[Florence Lawrence]], &quot;Hollywood's first movie star&quot; is born January 2, 1886 in Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;ref name=florence&gt;{{cite book| last = Brown| first = Kelly R.,| title =Florence Lawrence, the Biograph Girl: America's First Movie Star | year = 1991| isbn = 0-7864-0627-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1888– Group of English businessmen visiting the city nicknamed it the &quot;Birmingham of Canada.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1889– Wentworth Historical Society is founded. (8 January 1889)&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1889– [[James McMillan (politician)|James McMillan]], (born and raised in Hamilton, Ontario) becomes U.S. Senator from the state of Michigan in 1889.&lt;ref name=jamesm&gt;{{cite book|title=Gray Eminence in a Gilded Age: The Forgotten Career of Senator James McMillan of Michigan|first=Geoffrey G. |last=Drutchas|pages=78–113|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1889– [[Robert B. Harris]] (along with his brother John M. Harris) establish the Hamilton Herald newspaper in 1889. Begins publishing on August 1 becoming Hamilton's first one-cent newspaper. Hamilton is now a 3-newspaper town: ''The Hamilton Spectator'', ''The Hamilton Times'' and ''The Hamilton Herald''. Newspaper lasts until 1936.&lt;ref name=HAMBIO2&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Hamilton Biography (Vol II, 1876–1924)|first=Thomas Melville |last=Bailey|publisher=W.L. Griffin Ltd|year=1991}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1890–1899==
[[Image:Thb locomotive 22.jpg|thumb|right|TH&amp;B locomotive No. 22 with crew, circa 1900–1910.]]
[[Image:1899Winton.jpg|thumb|1899 Winton]]
[[Image:The Tigers of Hamilton football team.jpg|thumb|The [[Hamilton Tiger-Cats|Hamilton Tigers]] circa 1906]]
* 1890– First organized Hockey Game held in Hamilton; Bank of Hamilton VS Knox, Morgan. (this is the earliest reference to an organized hockey game being played in Hamilton.){{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

* 1890– Hamilton's first Public Library opens up on Main Street West. Officially opened up by Lord and Lady Aberdeen on September 16, 1890.&lt;ref name=Library&gt;{{cite web| title = Hamilton's Central Library History|url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/AboutTheLibrary/hplhistory.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-10}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1890– First Bowling alley in the City opens at back of the ''J.W. MacDonald Tobacco shop'', (66 [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street North]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1892– June 29, 1892 is the date the first electric [[streetcar]] was operated in Hamilton. The first 2 Electric routes were King Street East and [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street North]]. Street cars continued running on Hamilton streets until 6 April 1951.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1892–  The [[Toronto, Hamilton and Buffalo Railway]] began operations.&lt;ref name=THBHIST&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thbrailway.ca/|title=Toronto, Hamilton and Buffalo Railway Historical Society|accessdate=2007-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1892– The Hamilton Street Railway (HSR) converted to electrically powered vehicles in 1892.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1892– James Street [[Incline railway]] opens up June-11th (1892–1932).&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1893– Hamilton's first large department store opens up; The Right House ([[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street]]). Hamilton's first large department store.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1893– The Sir [[John A. Macdonald]] Statue arrives in Hamilton from London, England on 30 October 1893. Official dedication of the statue took place 1 November 1893. Located at the intersection of King and [[Hughson Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Hughson Streets]]. Prime Minister Sir [[John Sparrow David Thompson|John Thompson]] in attendance.&lt;ref name=statue&gt;{{cite web| title = Sir John A. Macdonald statue, 1893| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Sir+John+A.+Macdonald+Statue.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1893– Hamilton Electric Light Co. Electrify the street railway.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1894– ''Harvey Park'' was named after ''Colonel John Harvey'', a British Officer during the War of 1812. The name was accepted by Hamilton City Council 11 June 1894. (situated just West of ''Dundurn Park'').&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMTIMES&quot;/&gt;

* 1894– Hamilton Herald newspaper and cigar store owner Billy Carroll established the Around the Bay Road Race. Although it is not a proper [[marathon]], it is the longest continuously held long distance foot race in North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;

* 1895– Wentworth Incline railway begins operation on August, 1895. (1895–1936)&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1895– The [[TH&amp;B]] Railway came into Hamilton in 1895. A railway tunnel was then constructed from ''Queen'' to ''Park Street'' to cut down on the noise, pollution and disruption for the wealthy families who lived South of Jackson Street in the ''Durand'' neighbourhood.&lt;ref name=LOCKES&gt;{{cite book|title=Up and Down Locke Street South|first=Ann &amp; Bill |last=Manson |publisher=North Shore Publishing|year=1999|isbn= 1-896899-08-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1896– Sir [[John Morison Gibson]] forms The ''Dominion Power and Transmission Company'', that brought hydroelectric power, for the first time, to Hamilton, from their plant, at DeCrew Falls.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2-p143&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Hamilton Biography (Vol II, 1876–1924)|first=Thomas Melville |last=Bailey|publisher=W.L. Griffin Ltd|page=143|year=1991}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1896– Hamilton Radial Electric Railway extended across Beach Strip. (7 September 1896).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1896– Hamilton [[firefighters]] unionized.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1897– [[John M. Lyle]], Hamilton architect in the late 19th century and early 20th century, designs [[New York Public Library]] in 1897. (Later went on to design the [[Royal Alexandra Theatre]], in Toronto (1907) and [[Union Station (Toronto)]] 1914–1921).&lt;ref name=Lyle&gt;{{cite web| title = Canadian Encyclopedia Biography of John M. Lyle| url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0004816| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1897– [[Adelaide Hoodless]], was a Canadian educational reformer who founded the international women’s organization known as the Women’s Institutes in 1897.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1897– [[Westinghouse Electric (1886)|Westinghouse]] established in Hamilton. first Westinghouse operation outside of the U.S.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1898– The &quot;Five Johns&quot;, (John Cameron, [[John Dickenson (Canadian politician)]], John Morison Gibson, John Moodie, Sr. and John Sutherland), form ''The Cataract Power Co. Ltd.'' introducing electric power to Hamilton in 1898. On August 25, 1898, power was sent twenty seven miles from ''DeCew Falls'', [[St. Catharines]], using water from the old [[Welland Canal]]. New industries, such as the forerunners of the Steel Co. of Canada ([[Stelco]]) and Canadian Westinghouse, were attracted here by the cheaper, more efficient power. One time this Company controlled hydro power from [[Brantford, Ontario|Brantford]] to St. Catharines, including the Hamilton Street Railway and the area's radial lines. Back then the city's nickname was &quot;''The Electric City.''&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1898– The first automobile driven in Canada was by textile manufacturer [[John Moodie]] in 1898; A one-cylinder [[Winton (automobile)|Winton]] he imported from [[Cleveland]]. John Moodie was also one of the founders of Canada's automobile club, the [[Hamilton Automobile Club]], which was founded in 1903 when there were 18 cars in town. By 1920, there were 6,000 and Hamilton's ratio of one car for every 15 people was higher than that of New York, Chicago, Boston or Toronto.&lt;ref name=memproj /&gt;

* 1899– [[Thomas Bain]] in 1899 becomes the [[Speaker of the Canadian House of Commons]] in Ottawa.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1899– Dundurn becomes a city park and the [[Victorian Order of Nurses]] begin work in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

==1900–1909==
[[Image:John Morison Gibson.jpg|thumb|right|Sir [[John Morison Gibson]] in 1908]]
[[Image:Robert Stanley Weir 1899.png|thumb|right|[[Robert Stanley Weir]]]]
* 1902– [[International Harvester]] is the second major United States industry to locate in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1902– Canadian [[Otis Elevator Company]] is formed (August 22)&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1903– ''Hamilton Automobile Club'' (was the first in Canada) founded by John Moodie.&lt;ref name=memproj /&gt;

* 1903– ''Canadian Canners Limited'' formed. (Originally known as ''Canadian Canners Consolidated Companies Limited'')&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1904– [[George Klein (inventor)|George Klein]], (born: August 15, 1904) – often called &quot;The most productive inventor in Canada in the 20th century.&quot;&lt;ref name=Klein&gt;{{cite web| title = Canadian Encyclopedia Biography of George Klein| url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0004345| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1906– Hamilton east elected Ontario's first independent labour candidate, [[Allan Studholme]], who held the seat until his death in 1919.

* 1906– Local boy [[William Sherring]] won an [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] gold medal at [[Athens]] for the marathon.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1906– &quot;One big reason&quot; for almost 75% increase in the population of Hamilton between 1901 and 1912, boasted Sir John Morison Gibson of ''Dominion Power and Transmission Company'', was &quot;Cheap Electric Power Furnished By Us.&quot; This simplistic explanation for the development of Hamilton in the early 20th century leaves much unexamined, but one conclusion cannot be disputed. In the perception of the Hamilton public, a view certainly fostered by Gibson and his fellow hydroelectric promoters, Hamilton was no longer regarded the Birmingham or the Pittsburgh of Canada Hamilton was now, as the title of a 1906 promotional booklet on the city proudly proclaimed, '''&quot;The Electric City.&quot;'''&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1906– Hamilton Street Railway strike of 1906. Violent strike turns ugly and one of the few times in Hamilton's history that the Riot Act is read and enforced.&lt;ref name=hsrstrike&gt;{{cite web| title = Hamilton Street Railway strike of 1906| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Commerce+and+Industry.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060908121255/http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Commerce+and+Industry.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1908– Sir John Morison Gibson (1842–1929) becomes the Lieutenant-Governor of Ontario (1908–1914). from Hamilton.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1908– [[Robert Stanley Weir]], best remembered as the author of the English lyrics to ''[[O Canada]].'' His verses were first published in 1908, he spoke of them as representing ''a humble effort to do a great thing: to supply Canadians with a National Song; not to usurp others more or less in vogue, but to take place with them in the minstrelsy of our country.'' The song became widely used as a national anthem, was approved as such by Canada's parliament in 1967, and was with minor changes to the lyrics, formally legislated as such in 1980.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1908– [[Robert Kerr (athlete)|Robert Kerr]], Irish-Canadian sprinter. He won the gold medal in the 200 metres and the bronze medal in the 100 metres at the 1908 Summer Olympics.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1909– On 24 May 1909 a [[Coney Island]]-type amusement Park was opened in Hamilton. It was known as ''Maple Leaf Park'' and was bounded by [[Barton Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Barton Street]] (north), [[Ottawa Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Ottawa Street]] (east), [[Cannon Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Cannon Street]] (south), ''Rosslyn Avenue'' (west). It failed to attract enough visitors to keep the gates open and only lasted a year. Investors of the Park sold the land to local real estate speculators for $25,000 interested in the property because the land itself was a valuable commodity in the booming East Hamilton market.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMTIMES&quot;/&gt;

==1910–1919==
* 1910– Steel Company of Canada (Stelco) is formed.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1910– [[Andrew Ross (businessman)|Andrew Ross]], local Hamilton businessman builds the [[Barton Street Arena]]; future home of NHL [[Hamilton Tigers (ice hockey)|Hamilton Tigers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1910– The Royal Hotel (later renamed the Royal Connaught Hotel) is constructed on King Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1911– Hamilton hosted its first Aviation Meet at Aviation Park, hastily created on the Arthur O'Heir Survey, adjacent to the Tuckett Farm and Burlington Bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1912– [[Dofasco]], (''Dominion Steel Casting Company'') established. In 1917 named ''Dominion Foundries and Steel'', the company then merges with ''Hamilton Steel Wheel Company''.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;
* 1912– National Steel Car is established.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1912– Hamilton is second only to Montreal in shipping. (4.5 miles of dockage)&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1912– First ever Grey Cup victory by a football team from Hamilton (4th ever Grey Cup). The [[Hamilton Alerts]] defeat the Toronto Argonauts 11-to-4. Game was played in Hamilton at the [[A.A.A. Grounds]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

* 1912– [[Jack Kent Cooke]], born in Hamilton in 1912– was a Canadian-American entrepreneur who became one of the most widely-known executives in North American professional sports. He owned the [[Washington Redskins]] ([[NFL]]), the [[Los Angeles Lakers]] ([[NBA]]), and the [[Los Angeles Kings]] ([[NHL]]), and built The Forum in [[Inglewood, California]].&lt;ref name=cooke&gt;{{cite web| title = Jack Kent Cooke: A Career Biography| url=http://www.jackkentcookefoundation.org/jkcf_web/content.aspx?page=6536536| accessdate = 2007-01-10}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Andrew Carnegie, three-quarter length portrait, seated, facing slightly left, 1913.jpg|thumb|[[Andrew Carnegie]], 1913.]]

* 1912– Dr. Alfred Pain of Hamilton drowns after the [[RMS Titanic|Titanic]] hits an iceberg. (14 April 1912).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1913– After receiving a grant from [[Andrew Carnegie]] of New York the city of Hamilton builds a brand new Library on the south side of Main Street West, across the street from the old Library. It is officially opened by the Lieutenant Governor [and Hamiltonian], Sir John Morison Gibson on May 5, 1913.&lt;ref name=&quot;Library&quot;/&gt;

* 1913– Increased population and prosperity prompted a building boom. As a publicity stunt and raffle, workers and contractors built a house in a day in 1913 which was later featured in a [[Ripley’s Believe It or Not]] cartoon.&lt;ref name=memproj /&gt;

* 1913– the [[Procter &amp; Gamble]] Manufacturing Company (based in Cincinnati) purchased land in Hamilton. This event marks  beginning of company's operations outside the U.S.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1914– Sir [[John Strathearn Hendrie]] (1857–1923) becomes the Lieutenant-Governor of Ontario (1914–1919). from Hamilton.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1914– Construction starts on [[Procter &amp; Gamble]] Hamilton plant, which cost $1 million and consisted of seven buildings: the Crisco building, the boiler house, the gas plant, the soap building, the hardening plant, the kettle and glycerin house, and the machine shop.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1914– Hamilton is connected to Toronto by the first concrete highway built in Canada, Highway  2&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj&quot;/&gt;

* 1915– Procter &amp; Gamble officially opens Hamilton plant, employing 75 workers who made six different products.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1915– ''Herkimer Apartments'', on the corner of [[Bay Street (Hamilton)|Bay Street South]] and ''Herkimer Street'', was the first Hamilton apartment installed with an elevator, which ran from the basement to the fifth floor. Opened in July 1915.&lt;ref name=HERKIMER&gt;{{cite news | last = McGuinness| first = Eric| title = Hamilton Essentials: &quot;When walk-ups were the norm&quot;| publisher = The Hamilton Spectator| date = 2007-03-19| accessdate = 2007-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1916– The [[Royal Connaught Hotel]] opened. (Construction of it started in 1914).&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1917– Gage Park opens up.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1919– Hoover Suction Sweeper Company builds a plant in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1919– Firestone Tire and Rubber Company of Canada is established.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1919– Bay Street, derives its name from its proximity to ''Hamilton Harbour'', which was once ''Burlington Bay''. In 1919, a Federal Order-In-Council changed the name of ''Burlington Bay'' to ''Hamilton Harbour''.&lt;ref name=HAMNAMES&gt;{{cite book|title=Hamilton Street Names: An Illustrated Guide|first=Margaret |last=Houghton|publisher=James Lorimer &amp; Co. Ltd.|year=2002|isbn= 1-55028-773-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1919– Civic Stadium built.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

==1920–1929==
* 1920– Hamilton gets an NHL team called the Hamilton Tigers, but then the team folds after a player's strike in 1925. Players get bought up by [[New York City]] bootleggers and the team there is named the [[New York Americans]] and become the very first pro sports team to play out of the newly built [[Madison Square Garden]] in downtown [[Manhattan]].&lt;ref name=Tigers&gt;{{cite book| last = Wesley| first = Sam, David| title = Hamilton's Hockey Tigers| publisher = James Lorimer &amp; Company Ltd.| year = 2005| isbn = 1550288873}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1921– Pantages Theatre opens up on King Street, (between [[Catharine Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Catharine Street]] and ''Mary Street''), with a seating capacity of 3,500 made it the largest theatre in Canada at the time. Renamed ''The Palace Theatre'' in 1930. It closed down in 1972.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMTIMES&quot;/&gt;

* 1921– The city's population grows to 114,000 making it Canada's 5th largest city.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO2&quot;/&gt;

* 1922– [[CKOC]] radio station starts up. Today it is the oldest radio station in English Canada; second oldest overall. On the air since May 1, 1922&lt;ref name=CKOC&gt;{{cite web| title = CKOC Radio Official web site| url=http://www.oldies1150.com/
| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1922– Prior to the 1922–23 season, the NHL would hold its Governors meeting at the Royal Connaught Hotel on King Street, where the visiting NHL teams who came to town to play against the Hamilton Tigers stayed as well.&lt;ref name=TIGERS&gt;{{cite book|title=Hamilton's Hockey Tigers |first=Sam &amp; David |last=Wesley |publisher=James Lorimer &amp; Company Ltd.|year=2005|isbn= 1550288873}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1922– Beech-Nut Packing Company (makers of the [[Life Savers]] candy), establishes Canadian operations in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1923– On 29 March 1923, real estate agents and politicians announce the winning name, (Name the neighbourhood contest), at the ''Royal Connaught Hotel'' in downtown Hamilton. 6,170 people were gathered for the official announcement. Rev. Canon Percival Lawson Spencer won $200.00 for his submission of the &quot;Westdale&quot; name. Other names that were seriously considered for the neighbourhood include, ''Westhome'', ''Vimy Ridge'', ''Bridgeton'', ''Woodlands Park'', ''Surrey Park'' and ''Bridgeview''.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMTIMES&quot;/&gt;

* 1923– Westinghouse in Hamilton was the first company in Canada to manufacture radios (1923) and electric air cleaners (1944).&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1923– [[Babe Dye]] becomes NHL scoring champion, repeats feat in 1925.&lt;ref name=CHATLAS&gt;{{cite book|title=The Canadian Hockey Atlas|first=Stephen|last=Cole|publisher=Doubleday Canada|year=2006|isbn=978-0-385-66093-8 (0-385-66093-6)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1923– Scottish Rite Cathedral built.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1924– The second Lister Block building erected. (The first one built in 1886 was destroyed by fire in 1923).&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1925– First traffic lights in Canada go into operation at ''the Delta.'' (11 June 1925).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1925– Hamilton Tigers finish first overall in the NHL but players refuse to participate in playoffs. At end of season team folds and players move to New York and join the NHL's newest hockey club; the New York Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tigers&quot;/&gt;

* 1926– First Motor bus on Hamilton streets, 26 August (1926 – present).&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;

* 1927– [[CHML]] began operations in 1927 as a response to censorship of political discussions by Hamilton's first radio station, CKOC. The original owners were Maple Leaf Radio Company, and the &quot;HML&quot; in the callsign stood for &quot;Hamilton Maple Leaf&quot;.&lt;ref name=memproj /&gt;

* 1927 Jack V. Elliot established the ''Elliot Airport'' on the old Ghent homestead, running from the Radial Line to the Bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1927– First airmail flight to Hamilton. (24 August 1927).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1928– Eileen Vollick, Aviator, Fascinated by aviation from childhood this daring young woman enrolled in the Jack V. Elliot Aviation School in Hamilton, Ontario. On March 31, 1928 she passed the federal aviation test and become the first Canadian woman to earn a private pilot's certificate.&lt;ref name=EVOLLIK&gt;{{cite web| title =Famous Canadian Women, Aviation: Eileen Vollick| url=http://famouscanadianwomen.com/on%20the%20job/aviators.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1929– On May 24, 1929 , a great ceremony was attended by numerous citizens of Hamilton . The unveiling of the United Empire Loyalists statue, which was a generous gift to the city by Mr. Stanley Mills, brought great cheers from the crowd gathered outside the Wentworth County Court House.&lt;ref name=loyalists&gt;{{cite web| title = United Empire Loyalists Statue- 1929| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/United+Empire+Loyalist+Statue.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-08 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070428124543/http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/United+Empire+Loyalist+Statue.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1929– Built for $1,000,000, Hamilton's first skyscraper; The Pigott Building: 18-floors, {{convert|210|ft|m}}. Originally an office building, the Pigott Building is now used for condominiums.&lt;ref name=pigott&gt;{{cite web| title = The Pigott Building- 1929| url=http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/bu/?id=pigottbuilding-hamilton-canada| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1930–1939==
[[Image:Entrance CCTK Hamilton.jpg|thumb|right|[[Christ the King Cathedral (Hamilton)|Christ the King Cathedral]]]]
[[Image:Syl Apps.jpg|thumb|right|[[Syl Apps]]]]
* 1930– The first [[British Empire Games]] – now the [[Commonwealth Games]] – were held in Hamilton in 1930 as a result of the efforts of [[Melville Marks Robinson]].&lt;ref name=memproj2&gt;{{cite press release| title = Tigertown Triumphs| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator-Memory Project (Souvenir Edition) page MP56| date =2006-06-10| accessdate = 2006-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1930– McMaster University moves to Hamilton, Ontario from Toronto.&lt;ref name=HAMBIO3&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Hamilton Biography (Vol III, 1925–1939)|first=Thomas Melville |last=Bailey|publisher=W.L. Griffin Ltd|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1930– [[Besha Starkman]] ([[Rocco Perri]]'s wife) murdered on 13 August 1930.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO3&quot;/&gt;

* 1931– Built in 1931, [[Westdale Secondary School]] was immediately deemed the largest composite school in the [[British Empire]], having cost $1.3 million to build and consisting of 4.7 hectares of building, grounds and athletic fields.&lt;ref name=WESTDALE&gt;{{cite press release| title = Celebrity High: Westdale Secondary Alumni| publisher = The Hamilton Spectator| date = 2006-05-19| url = http://www.hamiltonspectator.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=hamilton/Layout/Article_Type1&amp;c=Article&amp;cid=1147989017565&amp;call_pageid=1020420665036&amp;col=1014656511815| accessdate = 2007-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1931– Canada's first birth control clinic was in Hamilton in 1931, as the advocates of birth control, led by Mary (Chambers) Hawkins, the American wife of a prominent city executive, and aided by some of Hamilton society's leading women, it aimed to meet the needs of people whose health and family lives suffered tremendously during the [[Great Depression]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO3&quot;/&gt;

* 1931– Trains no longer block traffic as [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street]] underpass is completed. (3 December 1931).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1932– [[Red Horner]], pro hockey player, helps the [[Toronto Maple Leafs]] win their first [[Stanley Cup]] in 1932.&lt;ref name=&quot;CHATLAS&quot;/&gt;

* 1932– [[Ray Lewis (runner)|Ray Lewis]], captures Bronze medal at 1932 Summer Olympics in L.A. (Track &amp; Field), becoming the very first Canadian-born Black Olympic medalist.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1932– [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James Street]] Incline railway closes and permanently abandoned on May 14, 1932. (1892–1932)&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1933– [[Filtration]] plant opened.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1933– Christ the King Cathedral, a [[Roman Catholic]] church, was consecrated on December 19, 1933.&lt;ref name=christking&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.christthekingcathedral.org/history.htm|title= Christ the King Cathedral History|accessdate=2007-01-10 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070205212034/http://www.christthekingcathedral.org/history.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1933– [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]] allows the city of Hamilton to use the name, [[Royal Botanical Gardens (Ontario)|Royal Botanical Gardens]]. (19 May 1933).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1934– Hamilton is the birthplace of [[Canadian Tire]]. Two brothers John W. Billes and Alfred J. Biles in 1934 open up first associate store in Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;ref name=memproj /&gt;

* 1936– [[Wentworth Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Wentworth]] Incline railway stops operating on August 15, 1936. (1895–1936)&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt; The first day, the public was allowed free access up and down the line. By the time the ''Wentworth Street'' Incline made its last trip on 16 August 1936, it was estimated that nearly 20,000,000 trips had been made up and down the line.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMTIMES&quot;/&gt;

* 1937– [[Syl Apps]], legendary Toronto Maple Leafs captain who led the Leafs to three Stanley Cups and McMaster University alumnus, wins the Calder trophy in 1937 as the top rookie in the [[National Hockey League]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CHATLAS&quot;/&gt;

==1940–1949==
* 1940– The June 1940 issue of ''Canadian Transportation'', in an article titled 'The Transit Service in Hamilton', stated that 72-passenger [[street cars]] of all-steel construction, and fitted for one-man operation, as well as 33 [[buses]] were in operation when it was written. The article went on to say that the Hamilton Street Railway had 27.97 route miles of electric [[railway]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1940– [[Harry Crerar]] was a Canadian general and became the country's &quot;leading field commander&quot; in [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=HCrerar&gt;{{cite book|title=The Generals : the Canadian Army's Senior Commanders in the Second World War |first=J.L.|last=Granatstein|year=Toronto 1993|isbn=0-7737-5728-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1940– John C. Munro Hamilton International Airport; The airport was originally built in 1940 as the Mount Hope Airport, a [[Royal Canadian Air Force]] base. After the war, the airport gradually shifted towards civil use, The military ceased using it as a base in 1964.&lt;ref name=airport2&gt;{{cite web| title = Airport Information: Facts| publisher= John C. Munro Hamilton International Airport| url= http://www.flyhi.ca/airport-information/facts/ | accessdate = 2010-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1941– The [[Royal Botanical Gardens (Ontario)|Royal Botanical Gardens]] was established as an independent entity in 1941 by an act of the provincial government, but the project's origins are traceable to the late 1920s when the City of Hamilton began acquiring land for the beautification of the city’s northwest entrance.&lt;ref name=rbg&gt;{{cite web| title = Royal Botanical Gardens Official web site| url=http://www.rbg.ca/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1943– [[Jackie Callura]], was a Canadian featherweight boxer and became the world featherweight champion by defeating Jackie Wilson in 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1944– Civic bathing beach was closed by the Department of Health.&lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;

* 1944– On 23 April 1944, Rocco Perri was seen for the last time in Hamilton, Ontario. Although his body has never been found, there is speculation that he was murdered, possibly by being put in a barrel filled with cement and dumped into the Burlington Bay. As one [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police]] officer concluded in a 1954 interview, &quot;We won't find his body until the Bay dries up.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO3-p143&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Hamilton Biography (Vol III, 1925–1939)|first=Thomas Melville |last=Bailey|publisher=W.L. Griffin Ltd|page=143|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1944– An earthquake damaged St. Paul's Church spire. (5 September 1944).&lt;ref name=&quot;VANHAM&quot;/&gt;

* 1944– ''Sam Lawrence Park'' can be found on the western end of [[Concession Street (Hamilton, Ontario)]]. Prior to 1944, this property was the Webb Quarry. In February 1944, The City of Hamilton was given {{convert|3|acre|m2}} of land for park use by [[Thomas Hambly Ross]], MP (Hamilton East), and his wife Olive. The park was originally named Ross Park, then renamed Patton Park in 1946, in honour of captain [[John MacMillan Stevenson Patton]], a Hamiltonian who risked his life during World War II by detonating an unexploded bomb. For this exploit he received the first [[George Cross]] for valour. In 1960, the park was renamed to honour [[Sam Lawrence]]. During 1990 to 1994, Sam Lawrence Park underwent a major upgrading that included repairing the stone walls, installing new walkways, site lighting, site furniture, and the redevelopment of the major rock gardens.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAM100&quot;/&gt;

* 1945– [[Win Mortimer]], a comic book and comic strip artist best known as one of the major illustrators of the DC Comics superhero [[Superman]], joined DC Comics.&lt;ref name=mortimer&gt;{{cite web| title =Comiclopedia: Win Mortimer| url=http://www.lambiek.net/artists/m/mortimer_win.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1946– (July 15), After a meeting at the Playhouse Theatre, [[Local 1005]] members marched to the plant gates to start the famous strike of 1946. The fight was over union recognition, a 40-hour work week and wages. With the help of Hamilton's community this struggle changed Canadian labour history. It forced employers to accept [[collective bargaining]] and helped start a mass trade-union movement in Canada.&lt;ref name=memproj58&gt;{{cite press release| title =The Hamilton Memory Project; Local 1005 History| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator- Souvenir Edition page MP58| date = June 10, 2006| accessdate = 2007-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1946– [[Evelyn Dick]] was arrested for murder after local children in Hamilton, Ontario found the torso of her missing estranged husband. The head and limbs had been sawn from his body and evidence that they had been burned in the furnace of her home later surfaced. She was convicted of the murder in 1946 and sentenced to hang. However, lawyer [[John Josiah Robinette|J.J. Robinette]]  appealed her case and won an eventual acquittal. However, in the meantime, the decayed remains of Evelyn's baby boy were found encased in cement under the floorboards of her home. She was convicted of the murder in 1947 and sentenced to 11 years in prison. Evelyn was released from prison in 1958 and quickly disappeared from public view.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj&quot;/&gt;

* 1946– &quot;The Skyway,&quot; Canada's first drive-in theater opens. (July 10, [[Stoney Creek, Ontario]])&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1946– [[John Weir Foote|John Foote]], military chaplain and Ontario cabinet minister, was a  Canadian recipient of the [[Victoria Cross]] in 1946.

* 1946– [[Joe Krol]], Canadian football quarterback (1932–53), won the [[Lou Marsh Trophy]] as Canada's top athlete in 1946.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1946– Hamilton's population was 178,686.&lt;ref name=SAGA/&gt;

* 1948– (August 18), surrounded by more than 400 employees and a battery of reporters, the first vehicle, a blue Champion four-door sedan, rolled off the [[Studebaker]] assembly line.&lt;ref name=memproj45&gt;{{cite press release| title =The Hamilton Memory Project; STUDEBAKER| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator- Souvenir Edition page MP45| date = June 10, 2006| accessdate = 2007-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1948– Canadian Westinghouse designed and built the first Canadian television set.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1948– Susan Shoe Industries Limited was founded.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1949– Hamilton hosted the [[Tim Hortons Brier|Brier]] for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

==1950–1959==
* 1950– [[Ellen Fairclough]] becomes the first female member of the [[Canadian Cabinet]]. Elected to the [[Canadian House of Commons]] in a 1950 by-election after being defeated in the 1949 federal election.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj&quot;/&gt;

* 1950– It was decided that the two Clubs '''Tigers''' and '''Wildcats''' should amalgamate and form one representative team for Hamilton. The present name, '''TIGER-CATS''', and what is known as the modern era of football started in 1950.&lt;ref name=ticats&gt;{{cite web| last = Canuck| first = Johnny| title = Hamilton Tiger Cats Fan Site- HISTORY| url=http://www.johnnycanuck.com/paw/history.htm| accessdate = 2006-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1951– The end of the streetcar era in Hamilton came in the early hours of April 6, 1951 when the Belt Line route was abandoned, car 519 making the last revenue run. Even though it no longer operated on railway tracks, the name Hamilton Street Railway continued to be used, and is still used today.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1951– March 28, 1951– Ballerina [[Karen Kain]] born in Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;ref name=Kain&gt;{{cite web| title = Canadian Encyclopedia Biography: Karen Kain| url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0004210| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1953– [[Hamilton Tiger-Cats]] capture their first Grey Cup in Grey Cup #41; (#8 Grey Cup for a football team from Hamilton). The Tiger-Cats defeated the [[Winnipeg Blue Bombers]] 12-to-6 at [[Varsity Stadium]] in Toronto.&lt;ref name=&quot;ticats&quot;/&gt;

* 1954– [[CHCH]] began broadcasting in 1954 as a [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]] affiliate from a transmitter located at 481 First Road West in Stoney Creek. At the time, all private stations were required to be CBC affiliates.&lt;ref name=chtv&gt;{{cite web| title = CH TV Hamilton History| url=http://www.canada.com/chtv/hamilton/info/history.html| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1954– &quot;[[Golden Horseshoe]]&quot; phrase first used by Westinghouse President, [[Herbert H. Rogge]], in a speech to the Hamilton Chamber of Commerce. (January 12, 1954)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1954– [[Hurricane]] Hazel hits Hamilton. (October 15–16)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1955– [[John Callaghan]], was a Canadian cardiologist who &quot;pioneered open-heart surgery.&quot; He performed Canada’s first successful open heart surgery in 1955.

* 1955– The [[Centre Mall]] was Canada's first mall, built in 1955. One of the first shopping malls in North America, original plans for an enclosed mall were abandoned.

* 1955– Hurricane Connie hits Hamilton. (August 13)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1956– Hamilton is the birthplace of the [[Pioneer Petroleum|Pioneer gas station]]. November 29, 1956, on [[Upper James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|Upper James Street]]. Today over 140 locations across Ontario (8% market share in Ontario) making it one of Canada's largest independent gasoline retailers.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj&quot;/&gt;

* 1956– First computerised election in Hamilton's history takes place.&lt;ref name=COMPUELECT&gt;{{cite web| title = Municipal Election: 1956| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Municipal+Election+1956.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1957– Hamilton is twinned with [[Flint, Michigan]], and its amateur athletes compete in the Canusa Games, held alternatively there and here since 1957. Through the CANUSA games which date back to 1958, Flint and Hamilton hold the distinction of having the oldest continuous sister-city relationship between a U.S. and Canadian city.&lt;ref name=Flint&gt;{{cite web| title = Hamilton Sister Cities: Flint Michigan| url=http://www.mundialization.ca/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1958– New courthouse opened on Main East at John, on the site of old 1879 building.&lt;ref name=ELLENFAIR2&gt;{{cite web| last = Johnston| first = Bill| title = Lament for a Downtown|  date = 2006-06-10|publisher = The Hamilton Spectator|url=http://www.hamiltonspectator.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=hamilton/Render&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1021025161885| accessdate = 2007-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1958– The [[Burlington Bay James N. Allan Skyway]], originally called the Burlington Bay Skyway and referred to locally as simply the Skyway Bridge, is located in Hamilton and Burlington. The Skyway, as it locally known, is part of the Queen Elizabeth Way freeway linking Fort Erie with Toronto in Ontario. The first bridge was completed in 1958.&lt;ref name=skyway&gt;{{cite web| title = History of the James N. Allan Skyway Bridge| url=http://members.aol.com/Hwys/OntHwys/OntHwysQEWHist2.html| accessdate = 2007-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1958– [[Angelo Mosca]], joins the [[Canadian Football League]] in 1958 to play for the Hamilton Tiger-Cats.&lt;ref name=&quot;ticats&quot;/&gt;

* 1958– [[Ronnie Hawkins]] came to Canada in 1958. His first gig was at the Golden Rail in Hamilton where he became an overnight success. It was a result of Hawkins success in Hamilton that he decided to move to Canada permanently. His career spans over five decades and 25 records. His hits include, “Forty Days”, “Mary Lou”, and “[[Hey Bo Diddley]]”.&lt;ref name=MEMPROJ43&gt;{{cite press release| title =The Hamilton Memory Project;| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator- Souvenir Edition page MP43| date = June 10, 2006| accessdate = 2007-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1958– [[Conway Twitty]], singer-songwriter and his band were in town nearly 50 years ago and were playing the [[Flamingo Lounge]] where [[Hamilton Place]] is located today. Legend has it that the drummer, Jack Nance, wrote 'It's Only Make Believe' between sets, although another story puts them at the nearby Fischer Hotel. The song was recorded in 1958 and became the first of nine Top 40 hits for Twitty, selling eight million copies.&lt;ref name=MEMPROJ44&gt;{{cite press release| title =The Hamilton Memory Project;| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator Newspaper- Souvenir Edition page MP44| date = June 10, 2006| accessdate = 2007-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1960–1969==
* 1960– Barton Township annexed by the City of Hamilton and the township ceased to exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1960– [[CHCH Television Tower]] is a 357.5 metre-high guyed TV mast in Hamilton, Ontario, Canada which is the primary transmitter for television station CHCH-TV. When it was built in 1960, the CHCH Television Tower became the tallest structure in Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;chtv&quot;/&gt;

* 1960– The Farmers' Market moved under cover on the ground floor of the Eaton's parking garage built on the market grounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1960– New City Hall opened on Main Street West.&lt;ref name=CITYHALL&gt;{{cite web| title = Modern Hamilton Architecture: City Hall| url=http://pages.interlog.com/~urbanism/moham.html| accessdate = 2007-02-09 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070208175209/http://pages.interlog.com/~urbanism/moham.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1960– Police dogs used for the first time in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=policedogs&gt;{{cite web| title = 1960: Police dogs used in Hamilton for the first time| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Police+dogs.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070427102403/http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Police+dogs.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1961– Old city hall, with its 38-metre clock tower, demolished to allow expansion of Eaton's department store. The clock and bell went into the tower of the 1990 Eaton Centre.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot; /&gt;

* 1961– CHCH disaffiliated from the CBC and becomes an independent TV station.&lt;ref name=&quot;chtv&quot;/&gt;

* 1962– [[John Munro (Canadian politician)|John Munro]], elected to the Canadian House of Commons in the 1962 election, and served continuously as a [[Member of Parliament]] (MP) for Hamilton, Ontario. Munro was appointed to Cabinet by Prime Minister [[Pierre Trudeau]], and served variously as Minister of Amateur Sport, Minister of Health and Welfare and Minister of Labour from 1968 to 1978 when he was forced to resign from over the &quot;Skyshops&quot; scandal.&lt;ref name=&quot;airport2&quot;/&gt;

* 1962– The [[Hamilton Red Wings]] in 1962 capture the [[Memorial Cup]] which featured 1972 [[Summit Series]] hero [[Paul Henderson]]. Hamilton defeated the [[Edmonton Oil Kings]].&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1963– Department of National Defence no longer needs the Hamilton airport. Department of Transportation assumes ownership and operation. The airport was originally built in 1940 as the Mount Hope Airport, a Royal Canadian Air Force base. After the war, the airport gradually shifted towards civil use, The military ceased using it as a base in 1964.

* 1964– Imperial Tobacco Company's Hamilton operations are moved to [[Guelph]], [[Ontario]].&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1964– Hamilton is the birthplace of the [[Tim Hortons]] chain (1964).  The original store (&quot;Store #1&quot;) still operates on Ottawa Street.&lt;ref name=Hortons&gt;{{cite web| title = Tim Hortons Official History| url=http://www.timhortons.com/en/pdfs/en_media_kit.pdf| accessdate = 2007-01-10|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070105141015/http://www.timhortons.com/en/pdfs/en_media_kit.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1966– Terminal Towers including a new eight-storey Holiday Inn opened on the site of the old transit terminal between King and Main at Catharine Street. It is now called ''Effort Square'' and the hotel is a ''Ramada Plaza Hotel''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1966– [[Mohawk College]] starts granting diplomas in 1966, and has since grown into one of the largest provincially funded colleges in the province of Ontario.&lt;ref name=Mohawk&gt;{{cite web| title = Mohawk College of Applied Arts and Technology| url=http://www.timhortons.com/en/pdfs/en_media_kit.pdf| accessdate = 2007-01-10|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070105141015/http://www.timhortons.com/en/pdfs/en_media_kit.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1966– Studebaker Hamilton shuts down as its last car factory. (March 5)&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1967– Hamiltonian [[Paul Szep]], becomes the editorial [[cartoonist]] for the [[Boston Globe]] in 1967. (1967–2001).&lt;ref name=SZEP&gt;{{cite web| title = Canadian Parliamentary Review: Paul Szep| url=http://www.parl.gc.ca/Infoparl/english/issue.htm?param=133&amp;art=854| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1968– [[Lincoln Alexander]], became Canada's first black Member of Parliament when he was elected to the Canadian House of Commons in 1968 as a member of the Progressive Conservative Party of Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj&quot;/&gt;

* 1968– [[Thomas McQuesten]], his historic downtown family home was willed to the City of Hamilton after the death of the last of his five unmarried siblings in 1968. After its restoration was complete in 1971, ''Whitehern'' has been open as a civic [[museum]] and has occasionally served as a period film location.&lt;ref name=WHITEHERN&gt;{{cite web| title =Whitehern Museum Archives: An Online History of the McQuesten Family| url=http://www.whitehern.ca/| accessdate = 2007-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1970–1979==
[[Image:CanadianFootballHallofFame.JPG|right|thumb|The [[Canadian Football Hall of Fame]]]]
[[Image:LandmarkPlaceHamilton.JPG|right|thumb|[[Landmark Place]]]]
[[Image:FirstPlaceHamilton.JPG|thumb|[[First Place Hamilton (building)|First Place Hamilton]]]]
* 1970s- Notable actors from Hamilton are ''[[Second City Television]]'' alumni [[Eugene Levy]], [[Martin Short]] and [[Dave Thomas (actor)|Dave Thomas]]. All three Hamltonians attended McMaster University along with [[John Candy]] in the 1970s.&lt;ref name=Mac&gt;{{cite web| title = McMaster University Alumni| url=http://www.mcmaster.ca/ua/alumni/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1971– ''The Capitol Theatre'' on King East closed.&lt;ref name=CAPITOL&gt;{{cite web|last = Irish| first = Chad| title = Cinema Treasures: The Capitol Theatre (Hamilton ON)| url=http://cinematreasures.org/theater/1874/| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1971– ''IBM Building'' office tower opened on Main West by the old library. Today (2007) known as the [[BDC Building]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1971– ''[[The Hilarious House of Frightenstein]]'' was a Canadian children's television series which was also produced by CHCH in 1971. It was syndicated to television stations across Canada and the United States, and occasionally still appears today in some TV markets. A quirky sketch comedy series, the show's cast included [[Billy Van]], [[Fishka Rais]], [[Guy Big]], [[Mitch Markowitz]], [[Vincent Price]] and [[Julius Sumner Miller]]. Van, in fact, played the vast majority of the characters. 130 episodes of the series were made, in one single nine-month span of time starting in 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;chtv&quot;/&gt;

* 1972– Hamilton's largest theatre, ''the Palace'', was demolished.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1972– The [[Canadian Football Hall of Fame]] officially opened as a museum to dedicate football in Canada, (November 28, 1972) in Hamilton.

* 1972– Phase 1 of Jackson Square completed, including [[Stelco Tower]] and Bank of Montreal Pavilion. The old Bank of Montreal building at Main and [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James]] was used as the city reference library until 1980 and had been vacant or a nightclub site on and off for many years.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1973– ''The Birks Building'' at King and ''James'', demolished to make room for a modernist law office, was once described by Oscar Wilde as &quot;the most beautiful building in all of North America.&quot; &lt;ref name=cflhall&gt;{{cite web| title = Birk's Building demolished-1973.| url=http://www.raisethehammer.org/article/060/| accessdate = 2007-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1973– Stelco Tower is built in downtown Hamilton, 25-floors/ 103-metres. At the time of completion was the tallest building in Hamilton but that title only lasted for a year until [[Landmark Place]] (Century 21 building) was complete in 1974.&lt;ref name=stelcotower&gt;{{cite web| title = Stelco Tower: 1973| url=http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/bu/?id=stelcotower-hamilton-canada| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1973– The last day Tolls were charged on the Burlington Bay James N. Allan Skyway Bridge. (December 28)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1973– ''Hamilton Place'' auditorium opened.&lt;ref name=HAMPLACE&gt;{{cite web| title = Encyclopædia Britannica Online: Hamilton Place: 1973| url=http://www.britannica.com/ebc/article-9039025| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1973– [[Wentworth County]] changes into the Regional Municipality of [[Hamilton-Wentworth]]. (Bill 155)&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1974– Hamilton's tallest building; Landmark Place, (formerly known as the Century 21 building) is completed. 43 stories/ 127.0 metres in height. Also the tallest residential building in Canada outside of Toronto as of January 10, 2007.&lt;ref name=Landmark&gt;{{cite web| title = Landmark Place/ Century 21 Building: 1974| url=http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/bu/?id=landmarkplace-hamilton-canada
| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1974– (January 1), The Regional Municipality of Hamilton-Wentworth came into being.&lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 1974– CHCH TV 11 was first in the world with the television premiere of [[The Godfather]].&lt;ref name=&quot;chtv&quot;/&gt;

* 1976– the [[Hamilton Fincups]] captured the Memorial Cup trophy. The Hamilton team featured future NHL stars [[Willie Huber]], [[Al Jensen]], [[Dale McCourt]], [[Al Secord]] and [[Ric Seiling]]. Hamilton defeated the [[New Westminster Bruins]] in the Finals.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1976– Hamilton's Mayor; Victor Kennedy Copps suffers a severe heart attack during the Around the Bay Road Race and leaves public office.&lt;ref name=VCOPPS&gt;{{cite web| title = Victor Copps Biography| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/1963-1976.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1976– ''First Place'' seniors high rise at ''King'' and Wellington opened on the site of First United Church, which burned in 1969.&lt;ref name=HAMCONV&gt;{{cite web| title = Skyscraperpage.com: Hamilton, Ontario| url=http://www.skyscraperpage.com/cities/?cityID=307| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1976– Widening of [[York Boulevard (Hamilton, Ontario)|York Boulevard]], which involved expropriating hundreds of homes and businesses, was completed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1976– ''The Spectator'', which had been downtown since its founding in 1846, moved out of its King East building to 44 Frid St.&lt;ref name=HAMSPEC2&gt;{{cite web|last = McNeil| first = Mark| title = The last one standing: Hamilton Spectator celebrates 160 years| url=http://www.hamiltonspectator.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=hamilton/Layout/Article_PrintFriendly&amp;c=Article&amp;cid=1152913814085| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1977– Second phase of Jackson Square completed with a six-storey office tower, but not the department store intended to be its major attraction.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1977– The [[Art Gallery of Hamilton]] opened beside the board of education.&lt;ref name=ARTGALL&gt;{{cite web|last = Manson| first = Bill| title = Gallery of distinction.| url=http://www.hamiltonspectator.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=hamilton/Layout/Article_Type1&amp;c=Article&amp;cid=1116022219911&amp;call_pageid=1014656484795| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1977– New police headquarters opened down the street from the old one on [[King William Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|King William]] at ''Mary''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1978– [[Harold Ballard]] buys the Hamilton Tiger-Cats from [[Michael DeGroote]] for $1.2 million in January 1978.&lt;ref name=&quot;ticats&quot;/&gt;

* 1978– [[Teenage Head (band)]], on May 1978, they released their first single &quot;Picture My Face&quot; on [[Epic Records]], and quickly became part of the scene exploding in Toronto.&lt;ref name=teenagehead&gt;{{cite web| title = Teenage Head Official web site| url=http://www.teenagehead.net/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1978– August 7: Hamilton held a round of the Formula Atlantic Championship. The insurance company demanded that the metal containers that formed part of the portable barrier system be filled with sand. In the haste to get this done in time, sand was dumped all over the road. The resulting delay led to the whole event being run in just half a day. Following 30 minutes of practice, a shortened qualifying session was held for 48 minutes, although there was basically only one line due to the sand still lying on the circuit. Finally, at 8pm the race itself was started. The race was originally scheduled for 70 laps. There was a safety car period after an early three car incident. The race was eventually red flagged after 39 laps due to darkness. 1982 Formula One World Champion [[Keke Rosberg]] won the race. In 1983, the Park Street section of track between York and King was removed to build [[Copps Coliseum]]. The paddock area on the track was located where Hamilton Place currently stands.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ellis.v12racing.net/racingcircuits/racingcircuits/]&lt;/ref&gt;

==1980–1989==
[[Image:HamiltonPublicLibrary.JPG|thumb|right|Hamilton's Central Library was opened in 1980 by [[Prince Philip]].]]
[[Image:CoppsColiseumYorkBoulevard.JPG|right|thumb|Copps Coliseum, at York Boulevard, looking East]]
[[Image:SamLawrenceParkHamiltonF.JPG|right|thumb|Sam Lawrence Park, Concession Street landmark]]

* 1980– The Hamilton Central Library and Farmers Market opened.
* 1981– The ''Hamilton Convention Centre'' and the government office tower above it opened. The tower was named the [[Ellen Fairclough Building]] in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMCONV&quot;/&gt;

* 1982– [[Bob Morrow]] wins the first of six mayoral elections, defeating incumbent [[Jack MacDonald (Hamilton politician)|John Alexander McDonald]]. Bob Morrow serves as Mayor of Hamilton from 1983-to-2000 and becomes longest serving mayor in Hamilton's history.&lt;ref name=mayors&gt;{{cite web| title = List of Hamilton Mayors| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/LibraryServices/Localhistory/Mayors.htm| accessdate = 2007-01-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1983– The ''Standard Life Centre'' opened at the west end of Jackson Square.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1983– Renovations began at Gore Park, including cutting down all the mature trees and constructing an amphitheatre. What came to be known as the Gore Park Fiasco was stopped by citizen protests, redesigned and completed in November 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1985– [[Daniel Lanois]], a solo artist in his own right and producer for [[U2]], opens up Grant Avenue Studios in Hamilton, Ontario.&lt;ref name=Lanois&gt;{{cite web| title = Grant Avenue Studios/ Daniel Lanois| url=http://www.grantavestudio.com| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1985– [[Sheraton Hamilton]], connected to ''Jackson Square'', opened, boosting downtown's hotel space.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1985– Copps Coliseum, sports and entertainment arena with a capacity of up to 19,000 (depending on event type and configuration) opens its doors for business. It is named after the former Hamilton mayor, [[Victor K. Copps]].&lt;ref name=COPPSCOL&gt;{{cite web| title = OHL Arena Guide: Copps Coliseum (1985)| url=http://www.ohlarenaguide.com/steelhawk.htm| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1985, November- Hamilton Street Railway uses first Natural Gas Vehicle (N.G.V.) busses in North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HSRhistory2&quot;/&gt;

* 1986– [[World Junior Ice Hockey Championship]] Games in 1986 at Copps Coliseum which saw the Soviets capture gold against Team Canada with a top scoring line that consisted of [[Sergei Fedorov]], [[Alexander Mogilny]] and [[Pavel Bure]].&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1986– The popular downtown restaurant The Chicken Roost closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1987– #99 [[Wayne Gretzky]] and #66 [[Mario Lemieux]] combine forces to capture the [[Canada Cup (ice hockey)|Canada Cup]] at Copps Coliseum as Team Canada defeat the Russians. Canada wins series 2 games to one. All three games end in 6-to-5 scores.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1987– The first of two reflective glass buildings of the CIBC tower ([[Commerce Place I]]) opened at King and James opposite Gore Park. The other ([[Commerce Place II]]) opened in 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMCONV&quot;/&gt;

* 1989– The original name of the first bridge was the Burlington Bay Skyway. After it was twinned, the proposed names of &quot;James N. Allan Skyway&quot; (in honour of the Ontario minister who championed the 1958 bridge) and &quot;James N. Allan Burlington Bay Skyway&quot; were rejected. The official name since 1989 has been &quot;Burlington Bay James N. Allan Skyway&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;skyway&quot;/&gt;

* 1989– The ''Robinson's'' store on [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James South]] between ''Main'' and ''King'' closed and was demolished shortly afterward.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1989– The ''Unified Family Court'' opened in the old central library on Main Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1989– ''The Tivoli Theatre'' on [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James North]] closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1989– ''The Century Theatre'' on ''Mary Street'' closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1989– Fire destroyed two 1840s buildings at the northeast corner of ''King'' and John.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

==1990–1999==
{{Historical populations
| 1791 | 41
| 1816 | 668
| 1833 | 1000
| 1841 | 3000
| 1846 | 6832
| 1850 | 10248
| 1861 | 19096
| 1871 | 26716
| 1877 | 32641
| 1880 | 35009
| 1890 | 44643
| 1900 | 51561
| 1910 | 70221
| 1913 | 88918
| 1914 | 100808
| 1920 | 108143
| 1929 | 134566
| 1939 | 155276
| 1945 | 175364
| 1950 | 192125
| 1960 | 258576
| 1970 | 296826
| 1980 | 306640
| 1990 | 307160
| 2002&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt; | 490268
| 2006 | 504559
|source = &lt;ref name=&quot;SAGA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAMBIO1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bartont&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt;2002=Post-Amalgamation.&lt;/small&gt;
}}

* 1990– April 1990 CKOC (radio station) moved to Hamilton's mountain and took up residence at 883 Upper Wentworth Street, near [[Lime Ridge Mall (Hamilton, Ontario)|Lime Ridge Mall]]. This was the first time any local station had settled away from the lower city.&lt;ref name=CKOC&gt;{{cite web| title = OLDIES 1150 CKOC (Official Web Site)| url=http://www.oldies1150.com/node/509803| accessdate = 2008-08-20}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1990–1990 was the Year Hamilton came closest to landing an NHL franchise when 14,000 Hamilton hockey fans made Non-refundable downpayments for season's tickets in less than 24-hours but was blocked by Seymour Knox III (then owner of the [[Buffalo Sabres]]) and the Toronto Maple Leafs organizations.&lt;ref name=expansion&gt;{{cite news| last = Joyce| first = Gary| title = The Puck Stopped Where?| publisher = Hamilton This Month (magazine) Pg:40–47| date = 1991-04-13| accessdate = 2006-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1990– During 1990 to 1994, ''Sam Lawrence Park'' underwent a major upgrading that included repairing the stone walls, installing new walkways, site lighting, site furniture, and the redevelopment of the major rock gardens.&lt;ref name=&quot;HAM100&quot;/&gt;

* 1990, [[Eric Lindros]] and the [[Oshawa Generals]] defeat the [[Kitchener Rangers]] at Copps Coliseum to capture the Memorial Cup of Hockey.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1990– The ''Hamilton Eaton Centre'' created a major new commercial development beside Jackson Square.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1990– ''F. W. Woolworth'' closed on King East.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1991– In 1991, CKDS adopted the CJXY (Y95.3) callsign and a classic rock format.

* 1991– ''The du Maurier Centre'' on King William, home to ''Theatre Aquarius'', opened.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1991– Stelco moved its head office from Toronto back to Hamilton and the Stelco Tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1991– [[Mark Messier]] leads Team Canada to victory over [[Brett Hull]] and Team U.S.A. to capture the Canada Cup at Copps Coliseum.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1991– Hamilton hosts the Brier for the second time.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 1992– The assets of Amstel Brewery Canada Limited are acquired by a company later called Lakeport Brewing Corporation. The [[Lakeport Brewing Company]] is the biggest discount brewer in Canada (March). Lakeport Brewing Company is Canada's No.1 co-packer of beer, non-alcohol and spirit-based products. The company is also said to be North America's most modernized beverage alcohol production facility.&lt;ref name=HISINDI/&gt;

* 1993– Jean Chrétien became prime minister following the federal election, and names [[Sheila Copps]] as [[Deputy Prime Minister]] and [[Minister of the Environment]].

* 1994– [[Transport Canada]] announces it will divest itself of local and regional airports. The region of Hamilton issues a request for proposals from private firms to run the airport.&lt;ref name=&quot;airport2&quot;/&gt;

* 1994– March 18, &quot;Remembering John&quot; a special memorial service for John Candy arranged by [[The Second City]] is broadcast live on CHCH TV and transmitted via satellite to eight stations across Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;chtv&quot;/&gt;

* 1994– The last Canadian ''Kresge's'' store, in Hamilton, closed at northeast corner of ''King'' and Hughson.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1995–  View Magazine (Hamilton's Weekly) is born and is still going strong.

* 1995– Hurricane Opal hits Hamilton. (October 5–6)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bank&quot;/&gt;

* 1995– Hamilton hosts The [[Juno Awards of 1995]] for the first time, representing Canadian music industry achievements of the previous year, at a ceremony in the Copps Coliseum. [[Mary Walsh (actress)|Mary Walsh]], [[Rick Mercer]] and other regulars of the television series [[This Hour Has 22 Minutes]] were the hosts for the ceremonies which were broadcast on [[CBC Television]].&lt;ref name=Juno&gt;{{cite web| title = Juno Awards: Official web site| url=http://www.junoawards.ca/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1995– ''The Lister Block's'' last tenants were forced to move out, leaving the building vacant.&lt;ref name=LISTER&gt;{{cite web| title = flickr.com photos: Lister Block| url=http://www.flickr.com/photos/74836052@N00/160071550| accessdate = 2007-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1996– Hamilton International Airport Limited (HIAL) is the fully owned subsidiary of TradePort International Corporation. HIAL begins to manage the [[Hamilton/John C. Munro International Airport|John C. Munro Hamilton International Airport]]. TradePort, winner of the bid to take over the airport, assumes responsibility to manage, finance and operate it under a 40-year lease.&lt;ref name=&quot;airport2&quot;/&gt;

* 1996– The conversion of the ''Pigott'' and ''Sun Life buildings'' on [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James South]] at ''Main'' into 110 upscale condominium units was completed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1996– A replica of the original ''Gore Park fountain'' was installed in the park. The original had been replaced in 1960.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1996– The refurbished ''TH&amp;B Station'' became the [[Hamilton GO Transit station]], as well as the city's bus terminal.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1996– ''[[Oh What a Feeling: A Vital Collection of Canadian Music]]'' was a 4-CD box set released in 1996 to celebrate the 25th anniversary of the [[Juno Awards]]. All of the sets feature popular Canadian songs from the 1960s onward. The sets were titled for the song &quot;Oh What A Feeling&quot; by Hamilton Ontario rock band [[Crowbar (Canadian band)|Crowbar]]. From 1969 to 1970, most of the members of the group had been a backup band for Ronnie Hawkins. However, he fired them, saying &quot;You guys are so crazy that you could **** up a crowbar in three seconds!&quot; They recorded their first album in 1970 as [[King Biscuit Boy]] and Crowbar. King Biscuit Boy left the band later in 1970, but continued to appear as a guest performer.

* 1996– Hamilton hosts the [[Juno Awards of 1996]], representing Canadian music industry achievements of the previous year, at a ceremony in the Copps Coliseum. [[Anne Murray]] was the host for the ceremonies, which were broadcast on CBC Television. Prominent nominees were [[Alanis Morissette]] and [[Shania Twain]]. Canadian Music Hall of Fame Inductees: [[David Clayton-Thomas]], [[Denny Doherty]], [[John Kay (musician)|John Kay]], [[Domenic Troiano]], [[Zal Yanovsky]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Juno&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Albert Einstein Head.jpg|thumb|right|[[Albert Einstein]]]]
* 1997– Hamilton hosts the [[Juno Awards of 1997]], representing Canadian music industry achievements of the previous year, at a ceremony in the Copps Coliseum. [[Jann Arden]] was host for the major ceremonies which were broadcast on CBC Television. Major winners were [[Celine Dion]] and [[The Tragically Hip]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Juno&quot;/&gt;

* 1997– The ''Bank of Montreal'' moved out of ''Jackson Square'', where it had been a major first tenant, and into its own building at ''Main'' and Bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

* 1997– [[Lincoln M. Alexander Parkway]] is complete. (called ''The Linc'' by locals) is a municipal [[freeway]] in the city. Named after Lincoln Alexander, the former [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada|Progressive Conservative]] MP and [[Lieutenant Governor]] of Ontario, though he never held a driver's license of his own. It opened on October 15, 1997 and at the present its western terminus is at [[Highway 403 (Ontario)|Highway 403]].  The expressway runs along the south of Hamilton and ends at Mud Street.

* 1999– In 1999, CHML and [[CJXY]] were acquired by [[Corus Entertainment]]. The following year, CJXY swapped frequencies with Corus' CING, taking over CING's former 107.9 frequency; at the same time it changed its moniker to Y108.&lt;ref name=chml&gt;{{cite web| title = CHML Radio: Official web site| url=http://www.900chml.com/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=y108&gt;{{cite web| title = Y108 Radio: Official web site| url=http://www.y108.ca/home/index.cfm| accessdate = 2007-01-10 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061205040703/http://y108.ca/home/index.cfm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 1999– McMaster University is home to a piece of [[Albert Einstein]]'s brain. An autopsy was performed on Einstein by Dr. Thomas Stoltz Harvey, who removed and preserved his brain. Harvey found nothing unusual with his brain, but in 1999 further analysis by a team at McMaster University revealed that his parietal operculum region was missing and, to compensate, his inferior parietal lobe was 15% wider than normal. The inferior parietal region is responsible for mathematical thought, visuospatial cognition, and imagery of movement. Einstein's brain also contained 73% more glial cells than the average brain.

* 1999– Hamilton hosts the [[Juno Awards of 1999]] honouring Canadian music industry achievements, broadcast by CBC Television and hosted by [[Mike Bullard (television)|Mike Bullard]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Juno&quot;/&gt;

* 1999– Eaton's closed as the department store chain collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;ELLENFAIR2&quot;/&gt;

==2000 – present==
[[Image:LIUNAStationHamilton.JPG|thumb|LIUNA Station Hamilton]]
[[Image:Toronto Argonauts vs. Hamilton Tiger-Cats at Rogers Centre, October 27 2005.jpg|thumb|Hamilton Tiger-Cats vs. Toronto Argonauts, October 27, 2005 at [[Rogers Centre]]]]
[[Image:IMG 4916.JPG|thumb|Stinson, 100-storey Connaught Towers presentation, Hamilton Chamber of Commerce, (Monday June 2nd, 2008)]]
* 2000– LIUNA reopened the [[James Street (Hamilton, Ontario)|James North]] CN rail station as a banquet hall.

* 2001– The new city of Hamilton is formed. The Regional Municipality of Hamilton-Wentworth and its six local municipalities; Ancaster, Dundas, [[Flamborough, Ontario|Flamborough]], [[Glanbrook, Ontario|Glanbrook]], '''Hamilton''' and Stoney Creek amalgamate. (January 1) &lt;ref name=&quot;headlake&quot;/&gt;

* 2001– The [[Juno Awards of 2001]] were held in Hamilton, Ontario, hosted by Rick Mercer at Copps Coliseum and broadcast on CBC Television. Performers during the telecast included: [[Deborah Cox]], [[Nelly Furtado]], [[The Guess Who]], [[Jacksoul]], [[Michie Mee]], [[The Moffatts]] and [[Treble Charger]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Juno&quot;/&gt;

* 2002– [[Pat Quinn (ice hockey)|Pat Quinn]], At the 2002 Olympic Winter Games coached Team Canada to their first Olympic Gold Medal in ice hockey at the Olympic Games since 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;CHATLAS&quot;/&gt;

* 2003– [[Hamilton Bulldogs]] of the [[American Hockey League|AHL]] lose in the [[Calder Cup]] Finals to the [[Houston Aeros]].

* 2003– On August 30, 2003, the 60th anniversary of her commissioning into the Royal Canadian Navy, [[HMCS Haida]] (Canada's most famous warship and the last remaining Tribal Class in the world) was moved to the city of Hamilton, Ontario by [[Parks Canada]] where she has become a focal point of a revitalized waterfront.&lt;ref name=HMCS&gt;{{cite web| title = Parks Canada HMCS Haida website| url=http://www.pc.gc.ca/lhn-nhs/on/haida/index_e.asp| accessdate = 2007-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2003– Michael DeGroote, makes a $105 million [[CAD]] donation was given to McMaster's medical program. It is the largest single cash gift in Canadian history and will be used to upgrade the current medical school, called the Michael G. DeGroote School of Medicine.&lt;ref name=degroote&gt;{{cite web| title = Degroote-Largest Cash Gift in Canadian University History| publisher= McMaster University| url=http://www.fhs.mcmaster.ca/pubrel/degroote.htm | accessdate = 2007-01-01 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061210134221/http://fhs.mcmaster.ca/pubrel/degroote.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2003– The Hamilton Golf &amp; Country Club hosted the 2003 Canadian Open golf championship in which [[Bob Tway]] won.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 2003– Hamilton successfully hosted the [[World Cycling Championships]] in 2003. It was only the second time the World Cycling Championships was staged outside of Europe, first time ever in Canada. [[Igor Astarloa]] of [[Spain]] was the winner.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 2004– [[Dave Andreychuk]], captains the [[Tampa Bay Lightning]] of the NHL to the 2004 Stanley Cup.&lt;ref name=&quot;CHATLAS&quot;/&gt;

* 2006– Hamilton hosts the Canadian Open Golf Championship again in 2006 [[Jim Furyk]] won the title.&lt;ref name=&quot;memproj2&quot;/&gt;

* 2006– As of October 5, 2006 speculation has it that [[Jim Balsillie]] of [[Research in Motion]] who offered to buy the [[Pittsburgh Penguins]] for $175-million would move the team to Hamilton where it would play out of the Copps Coliseum Arena.&lt;ref name=Balsillie&gt;{{cite news| last = Waldie| first = Bill| title = RIM boss to buy NHL's Penguins| publisher = The Globe &amp; Mail| date = 2006-10-05| url = http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20061004.wbalsillie04/BNStory/GlobeSportsHockey/home| accessdate = 2006-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2006– On December 15, 2006, Balsillie withdrew his bid to buy the Pittsburgh Penguins. He made the decision after receiving notice from NHL commissioner [[Gary Bettman]] that the league would restrict Balsillie's control over the team. The move was geared at preventing Balsillie from moving the team.&lt;ref name=Balsillie2&gt;{{cite news| last = Anderson| first = Shelly| title = Balsillie ends bid to buy Penguins| publisher = The Post-Gazette| date = 2006-12-15| url =http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/06349/746509-100.stm| accessdate = 2007-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2006– The Hamilton Port Authority handles over 12 million tons of cargo and is visited by over 700 vessels each year. This ranks Hamilton as the busiest of all Canadian Great Lakes ports.&lt;ref name=Port&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hamiltonport.ca/corporate/about.aspx
|title=Hamilton Port Authority: About / History of the Port
|accessdate=2006-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– Hamilton hosts the 2007 [[Tim Hortons Brier]] (March 3–11).&lt;ref name=Brier&gt;{{cite web| title = Hamilton hosting Brier in 2007| url=http://www.curling.ca/fan_central/brier/2007/index.asp|publisher= (www.curling.ca)| accessdate = 2006-12-30 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061225150746/http://www.curling.ca/fan_central/brier/2007/index.asp &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– [[Ronald V. Joyce Stadium]] at McMaster University opens up. Used for football, soccer and rugby.&lt;ref name=MacStad&gt;{{cite web| title = McMaster University: Official web site| url=http://www.mcmaster.ca/| accessdate = 2007-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– [[David Braley Athletic Centre]] at McMaster University opens up.&lt;ref name=&quot;MacStad&quot;/&gt;

* 2007– [[Cayuga International Speedway]], a 5/8-mile oval auto racing track reopens in 2007 after major renovations.&lt;ref name=Cayuga&gt;{{cite web| title = Cayuga International Speedway major renovations| url=http://www.hamiltonscores.com/autoracing/news/?article=061508168|publisher= Hamilton Scores!| accessdate = 2007-01-10 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070211164727/http://www.hamiltonscores.com/autoracing/news/?article=061508168 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– Henderson General Hospital on Concession Street (April 2007) major renovations and expansion started and once complete the hospital will be renamed the ''Juravinski Hospital and Cancer Centre'', (after ''Charles Juravinski'' and his wife Margaret), after they both made a $43-million contribution to health care in Hamilton.&lt;ref name=HENDERSON&gt;{{cite press release| title = StreetBeat: &quot;Mr. Generosity&quot;| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator| date =2007-04-20| accessdate = 2007-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– Hamilton Bulldogs win the Calder Cup, defeating the [[Hershey Bears]] 2–1 before sellout crowd at Copps Coliseum.&lt;ref name=YEARREVIEW&gt;{{cite press release| title = Year In Review, page: A6| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator| date =2007-12-29| accessdate = 2007-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– Hamiltonian [[Brian Melo]] wins the [[Canadian Idol (Season 5)|fifth season]] of [[Canadian Idol]].&lt;ref name=BMeloB&gt;{{cite web| title = Yahoo Canada News: &quot;Hamilton rocker Brian Melo crowned the new Canadian Idol&quot;| url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/cpress/20070912/ca_pr_on_en/tv_canadian_idol_6| accessdate = 2008-03-14}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– [[Red Hill Valley Parkway]] (popularly called the ''Red Hill Creek Expressway'') a municipal expressway running through the city, connecting the Lincoln M. Alexander Parkway to the [[Queen Elizabeth Way]] near [[Hamilton Harbour]]. A four-lane freeway completed in 2007. The parkway was originally scheduled to be opened to vehicular traffic on November 16 but the date was pushed back a day and officially opened November 17.&lt;ref name=REDHILL&gt;{{cite web| title = Red Hill Valley Project| url=http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/CityandGovernment/ProjectsInitiatives/RedHill/|publisher= (www.myhamilton.ca)| accessdate = 2007-04-25 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070208095034/http://www.myhamilton.ca/myhamilton/CityandGovernment/ProjectsInitiatives/RedHill/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– Jim Balsillie of Waterloo, Ontario based Research In Motion, offers to manage and run HECFI, (Hamilton Entertainment and Convention Facilities), which includes Copps Coliseum, Hamilton Place and Convention Centre. Also, offers to upgrade and renovate the Copps Coliseum Arena to make it a 2007 NHL-ready Arena. Price tag for renovations/ upgrades, $100-million (minimum). Name of Jim Balsillie's company that will run and manage all 3-Hamilton landmarks is &quot;Golden Horseshoe Sports &amp; Entertainment.&quot;

* 2007– September 19, CBC organized a meeting in Hamilton at the Convention Centre to discuss the idea of bringing a new radio station to the City citing that 'Hamilton was the largest, and most underrepresented city in the country in terms of media coverage.' &lt;ref name=CBCHAM&gt;{{cite web| title = Hamilton at the top of CBC's list| url=http://www.raisethehammer.org/blog.asp?id=762|publisher= (www.raisethehammer.org)| accessdate = 2007-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– [[Centre Mall (Hamilton)|Centre Mall]] owners announce plans for a 23-building super centre on the property on Barton Street East. Cost is estimated to be around $100-million and will take up {{convert|700000|sqft|m2}} of retail space. This will end up being the largest redevelopment project in the history of Hamilton's east-end.&lt;ref name=CENTMALL&gt;{{cite press release| title = Centre Mall owners plan 23-building super centre.| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator| date =2007-09-27| accessdate = 2007-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2007– It is announced on October 4, that the Mountain Plaza Mall at [[Fennell Avenue (Hamilton, Ontario)|Fennell Avenue]] and Upper James Street is to be rebuilt in a $50-million project. Announcement made on October 4 by Flavio Volpe, spokesperson for Smart Centres Ltd., Vaughan-based company that bought the Mall on November 2006.&lt;ref name=MTNPLZMALL&gt;{{cite press release| title = Mountain Plaza Mall slated for $50-million transformation.| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator; Steve Arnold| date =2007-10-04| accessdate = 2007-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2008– On Friday, February 29, 2008, Hamilton, Ontario Wikipedia page became the &quot;FEATURED ARTICLE.&quot;&lt;ref name=RICKCORDEIRO&gt;{{cite press release| title = A leap in exposure for Hamilton. Thanks mostly to Rick Cordeiro, our city graces the front page of Wikipedia today.| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator; Paul Wilson| date =2008-02-29| accessdate = 2008-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2008– May 2, 2008, Hamilton's most powerful voices in business, the arts, government, social services, health and education called for &quot;breathtaking&quot; change and a reinvention of Hamilton's image at the City's first ever economic summit.&lt;ref name=ECOSUMMIT&gt;{{cite press release| title = Economic think tank 'slam dunk' – Creativity critical to future growth, says urban guru Florida.| publisher =The Hamilton Spectator; Meredith MacLeod| date =2008-05-02| accessdate = 2008-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2008– June 2, 2008, [[Real Estate]] developer [[Harry Stinson]] makes a public presentation of his proposed 100-storey Connaught Towers at the Hamilton Chamber of Commerce building. It would have made it the tallest building in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;De Lazzer , Rachel. &quot;Condo king buys Royal Connaught for $9.5m.&quot; Hamilton Spectator. 29 February 2008: A1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Every city needs an icon.&quot;- Harry Stinson, Hamilton Spectator. 24 May 2008: WR7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=STINSON&gt;{{cite web| title = The Connaught Towers (Official Web Site)| url=http://www.theconnaught.ca| accessdate = 2008-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three months later, on Thursday September 4, Harry Stinson closes up the Connaught Towers sales office in downtown Hamilton and the project is officially cancelled.

* 2008– Hamilton hosts the [[Vanier Cup]]. (Championship trophy of Canadian Interuniversity Sport men's football.)

* 2009– [[Charles, Prince of Wales|Prince Charles, Prince of Wales]] and [[Camilla, Duchess of Cornwall]] visit [[Dundurn Castle]] and [[HMCS Haida (G63)|HMCS ''Haida'']].&lt;ref name=Dundurn&gt;{{cite web| title = Royals charm crowd with walkabout| url=http://thespec.com/article/667107| accessdate = 2009-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2009– [[Toronto]]/ Hamilton wins 2015 [[Pan American Games]] bid.&lt;ref name=PANAM&gt;{{cite web| title = Toronto, Hamilton win Pan Am Games bid.| url=http://thespec.com/article/667961| accessdate = 2009-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 2010– June 23, 2010, A 5.0 magnitude [[2010 Central Canada earthquake|earthquake]] hit Ontario (including Hamilton)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://ca.reuters.com/article/topNews/idCATRE65M4OD20100623 | work=Reuters | title=Quake near Ottawa, rattles Canada and U.S | date=2010-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Hamilton Ontario is the largest city in Canada without a CBC affiliate – and the largest with just one daily newspaper; The [[Hamilton Spectator]].

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Hamilton}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Timeline Of Events In Hamilton, Ontario}}
[[Category:History of Hamilton, Ontario]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
