<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="88493" ns="0" title="Howard Zinn"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Person
|name           = Howard Zinn
|image          = Howard Zinn at lectern cropped.jpg
|caption        = Zinn lecturing in [[Monona Terrace]], [[Wisconsin]]: May 2, 2009
|birth_date     = {{birth date|mf=yes|1922|08|24}}
|birth_place    = [[Brooklyn, New York]], U.S.
|death_date     ={{dda|2010|01|27|1922|08|24}}&lt;ref name=&quot;bost-death&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/breaking_news/2010/01/howard_zinn_his.html |title=Howard Zinn, historian who challenged status quo, dies at 87|last=Feeney|first=Mark |date=27 January 2010 |publisher=Boston.com |accessdate=2010-01-27 |location=USA}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|death_place    = [[Santa Monica, California]], U.S.
|occupation     = [[Historian]]
|main interests = [[History]], [[Civil Rights]], [[anti-war|war and peace]]
|spouse         = Roslyn Zinn (died 2008)&lt;ref name=&quot;bost-death&quot; /&gt;
|alma_mater     = [[New York University]] &lt;small&gt;([[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Columbia University]] &lt;small&gt;([[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|M.A.]])&lt;/small&gt; &lt;small&gt;([[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]])&lt;/small&gt;
}}

'''Howard Zinn''' (August 24, 1922 – January 27, 2010) was an American [[historian]], academic,  author, playwright, and [[social activist]]. Before and during his tenure as a [[political science]] professor at [[Boston University]] from 1964-88 he wrote more than 20 books, which included his best-selling and influential ''[[A People's History of the United States]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/us/29zinn.html? Howard Zinn, Historian, Is Dead at 87], January 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote extensively about the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)|Civil Rights]] and [[Peace movement|anti-war]] movements, as well as of the [[labor history of the United States]]. His memoir, ''You Can't Be Neutral on a Moving Train'', was also the title of a 2004 documentary about Zinn's life and work.&lt;ref name=&quot;HP&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/01/27/howard-zinn-dead-author-o_n_439350.html Howard Zinn Dead, Author Of 'People's History Of The United States' Died At 87] by Hillel Italie, ''[[The Huffington Post]]'', January 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life and career==
===Early life===
Zinn was born to a [[Jew]]ish immigrant family in [[Brooklyn]]. His father, Eddie Zinn, born in [[Austria-Hungary]], emigrated to the U.S. with his brother Samuel before the outbreak of World War I. Howard's mother Jenny Zinn immigrated from the Eastern [[Siberia]]n city of [[Irkutsk]].

Both parents were factory workers with limited education when they met and married, and there were no books or magazines in the series of apartments where they raised their children. Zinn's parents introduced him to literature by sending 10 cents plus a coupon to the ''[[New York Post]]'' for each of the 20 volumes of [[Charles Dickens]]' collected works.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zmag.org/zmag/articles/barzinn.htm Howard Zinn – One Step Ahead of the Landlord].&lt;/ref&gt; He also studied creative writing at [[Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York)|Thomas Jefferson High School]] in a special program established by poet Elias Lieberman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.educationupdate.com/archives/2004/apr04/issue/col_howardzinn.html Appel, Jacob M. Chronicling Lives From Spelman College to B.U. ''Education Update'', April 2004].&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War II===
Eager to fight [[fascism]], Zinn joined the [[Army Air Force]] during World War II and was assigned as a [[bombardier (air force)|bombardier]] in the [[490th Bombardment Group]],&lt;ref&gt;''The Politics of History'' 2nd ed. by Howard Zinn (University of Illinois Press, 1990) pp. 258–274) ISBN 0-252-01673-4.&lt;/ref&gt; bombing targets in [[Berlin]], [[Czechoslovakia]], and [[Hungary]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/v/Ehc3V1g5pm0&amp;rel=1&amp;border=0 |title=Film clip of Zinn |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[anti-war]] stance Zinn developed later was informed, in part, by his experiences. A U.S. bombardier in April 1945, Zinn dropped [[napalm]] bombs on [[Royan#Destruction_of_Royan|Royan]], a seaside resort in southwestern France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Zinn |first=Howard |title=Declarations of Independence |year=1990 |publisher=HarperPerennial |location=New York, NY |isbn=0060921080}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

On a post-doctoral research mission nine years later, Zinn visited the resort near [[Bordeaux]] where he interviewed residents, reviewed municipal documents, and read wartime newspaper clippings at the local library. In 1966, Zinn returned to Royan after which he gave his fullest account of that research in his book, ''The Politics of History''. On the ground, Zinn learned that the aerial bombing attacks in which he participated had killed more than 1000 French civilians as well as some German soldiers hiding near Royan to await the war's end, events that are described &quot;in all accounts&quot; he found as ''&quot;une tragique erreur&quot;'' that leveled a small but ancient city and &quot;its population that was, at least officially, friend, not foe.&quot; In ''The Politics of History'', Zinn described how the bombing was ordered—three weeks before the war in Europe ended—by military officials who were, in part, motivated more by the desire for their own career advancement than in legitimate military objectives. He quotes the official history of the U.S. Army Air Forces' brief reference to the [[Eighth Air Force]] attack on Royan and also, in the same chapter, to the bombing of [[Plzeň|Pilsen]] in what was then [[Czechoslovakia]]. The official history stated that the famous [[Škoda Works|Skoda]] works in Pilsen &quot;received 500 well-placed tons,&quot; and that &quot;Because of a warning sent out ahead of time the workers were able to escape, except for five persons.&quot;

Zinn wrote, &quot;I recalled flying on that mission, too, as deputy lead bombardier, and that we did not aim specifically at the 'skoda works' (which I would have noted, because it was the one target in Czechoslovakia I had read about) but dropped our bombs, without much precision, on the city of Pilsen. Two Czech citizens who lived in Pilsen at the time told me, recently, that several hundred people were killed in that raid (that is, Czechs)—not five.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Politics of History'' p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt;

Zinn said his experience as a wartime bombardier, combined with his research into the reasons for, and effects of the bombing of Royan and Pilsen, sensitized him to the ethical dilemmas faced by [[GI (military)|G.I.s]] during wartime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://progressive.org/mag_zinn0106 |title=Interview with Zinn |publisher=Progressive.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zinn questioned the justifications for military operations that inflicted massive civilian casualties during the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] bombing of cities such as [[Dresden]], Royan, [[Tokyo]], and [[Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] in World War II, [[Hanoi]] during the [[War in Vietnam]], and [[Baghdad]] during the war in [[Iraq]] and the civilian casualties during bombings in [[Afghanistan]] during the current and nearly decade old war there. In his pamphlet, ''Hiroshima: Breaking the Silence''&lt;ref&gt;[http://polymer.bu.edu/~amaral/Personal/zinn.html Zinn ''Hiroshima: Breaking the Silence'' by Howard Zinn].&lt;/ref&gt; written in 1995, he laid out the case against targeting civilians with aerial bombing.

Six years later, he wrote: &quot;Recall that in the midst of the [[Gulf War]], the U.S. military bombed an [[Amiriyah shelter massacre|air raid shelter]], killing 400 to 500 men, women, and children who were huddled to escape bombs. The claim was that it was a military target, housing a communications center, but reporters going through the ruins immediately afterward said there was no sign of anything like that. I suggest that the history of bombing—and no one has bombed more than this nation—is a history of endless [[atrocities]], all calmly explained by deceptive and deadly language like 'accident', 'military target', and 'collateral damage{{'&quot;}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/view/2010/01/28-7 &quot;A Just Cause, Not a Just War&quot; ''The Progressive'' December, 2001.]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Education===
After World War II, Zinn attended [[New York University]] on the [[GI Bill]], graduating with a B.A. in 1951 and [[Columbia University]], where he earned an M.A. (1952) and a Ph.D. in history with a minor in political science (1958). His masters' thesis examined the [[Ludlow massacre|Colorado coal strikes of 1914]].&lt;ref name=&quot;educationupdate2004&quot;&gt;Appel, JM. [http://www.educationupdate.com/archives/2004/apr04/issue/col_howardzinn.html Howard Zinn: Chronicling Lives from Spelman College to Boston U.], April 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; His [[doctoral dissertation]] ''LaGuardia in Congress'' was a study of [[Fiorello LaGuardia]]'s congressional career, and it depicted LaGuardia representing &quot;the conscience of the twenties&quot; as LaGuardia fought for public power, the right to strike, and the redistribution of wealth by taxation.&lt;ref name=&quot;educationupdate2004&quot;/&gt; &quot;His specific legislative program,&quot; Zinn wrote, &quot;was an astonishingly accurate preview of the [[New Deal]].&quot; It was published by the [[Cornell University]] Press for the [[American Historical Association]]. ''La Guardia in Congress'' was nominated for the [[American Historical Association]]'s [[Beveridge Award|Beveridge Prize]] as the best English-language book on American history.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/us/29zinn.html January 29, 2010 &quot;Howard Zinn, Historian, Is Dead at 87&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

While at Columbia, his professors included [[Harry Carman]], [[Henry Steele Commager]], and [[David Herbert Donald|David Donald]].&lt;ref name=&quot;educationupdate2004&quot;/&gt; But it was Columbia historian [[Richard Hofstadter]]'s ''[[The American Political Tradition]]'' that made the most lasting impression. Zinn regularly included it in his lists of recommended readings, and after [[Barack Obama]] was elected [[President of the United States]], Zinn wrote, &quot;If Richard Hofstadter were adding to his book ''The American Political Tradition'', in which he found both 'conservative' and 'liberal' presidents, both Democrats and Republicans, maintaining for dear life the two critical characteristics of the American system, nationalism and capitalism, Obama would fit the pattern.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://socialistworker.org/2008/11/05/what-next-for-the-struggle &quot;What next for struggle in the Obama era?&quot; ''The Socialist Worker'' November 5, 2008, Issue 684].&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1960–61, Zinn was a [[post-doctoral]] Fellow in [[East Asian Studies]] at [[Harvard University]].

===Academic career===
{{Quote box 
| quote = &quot;We were not born critical of existing society. There was a moment in our lives (or a month, or a year) when certain facts appeared before us, startled us, and then caused us to question beliefs that were strongly fixed in our consciousness-embedded there by years of family prejudices, orthodox schooling, imbibing of newspapers, radio, and television. This would seem to lead to a simple conclusion: that we all have an enormous responsibility to bring to the attention of others information they do not have, which has the potential of causing them to rethink long-held ideas.&quot;
| source = — Howard Zinn, 2005 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/views05/0210-28.htm Changing Minds, One at a Time] by Howard Zinn, Published in the March 2005 issue of ''The Progressive''.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | width = 35%
 | align = right 
}}

Zinn was Professor of [[History]] at [[Spelman College]] in Atlanta, Georgia from 1956 to 1963, and Visiting Professor at both the [[University of Paris]] and [[University of Bologna]].

In 1964, Zinn accepted a position at [[Boston University]], after writing two books and participation in the Civil Rights movement in the South.  His classes in [[civil liberties]] were among the most popular at the university with as many as 400 students subscribing each semester to the non-required class. A Professor of [[Political Science]], he taught at BU for 24 years and retired in 1988 at age 64. 

&quot;He had a deep sense of fairness and justice for the underdog. But he always kept his sense of humor. He was a happy warrior,&quot; said Caryl Rivers, [[journalism]] professor at Boston University. Rivers and Zinn were among a group of faculty members who in 1979 defended the right of the school's clerical workers to strike and were threatened with dismissal after refusing to cross a picket line.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE60R5D020100128 Activist, historian Howard Zinn dies at 87] by Ros Krasny at [[Reuters]] January 28, 2010. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Zinn came to believe that the point of view expressed in traditional history books was often limited. He wrote a history textbook, ''[[A People's History of the United States]]'', to provide other perspectives on American history. The textbook depicts the struggles of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] against European and U.S. conquest and expansion, slaves against [[slavery]], unionists and other workers against capitalists, women against [[patriarchy]], and African-Americans for [[civil rights]]. The book was a finalist for the [[National Book Award]] in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalbook.org/nba_winners_finalist_50_07.pdf The National Book Awards Winners &amp; Finalists]. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the years since the first edition of ''A People's History'' was published in 1980, it has been used as an alternative to standard textbooks in many high school and college history courses, and it is one of the most widely known examples of [[critical pedagogy]]. The ''[[New York Times Book Review]]'' stated in 2006 that the book &quot;routinely sells more than 100,000 copies a year&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/30/books/review/30donadio.html &quot;Backlist to the Future&quot;] by Rachel Donadio, July 30, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, Zinn published ''[[Voices of A People's History of the United States]]'' with [[Anthony Arnove]]. ''Voices'' is a sourcebook of speeches, articles, essays, poetry and song lyrics by the people themselves whose stories are told in ''A People's History.'' 

In 2008, the [http://zinnedproject.org Zinn Education Project] was launched to support educators using ''A People's History of the United States'' as a source for middle and high school history. The Project was started when a former student of Zinn, who wanted to bring Zinn's lessons to students around the country, provided the financial backing to allow two other organizations to coordinate the Project. The Project hosts a website that has over 85 free downloadable lesson plans to complement ''A People's History of the United States''.

''[[The People Speak (film)|The People Speak]]'', released in 2010, is a documentary movie inspired by the lives of ordinary people who fought back against oppressive conditions over the course of the history of the United States. The film includes performances by Zinn, [[Matt Damon]], [[Morgan Freeman]], [[Bob Dylan]], [[Bruce Springsteen]], [[Eddie Vedder]], [[Viggo Mortensen]], [[Josh Brolin]], [[Danny Glover]], [[Marisa Tomei]], [[Don Cheadle]], and [[Sandra Oh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bu.edu/today/2009/11/03/people-s-history-moves-small-screen |title= People's history moves small screen |publisher=Bu.edu |date=2009-11-04 |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://howardzinn.org/default/index.php?option=content&amp;task=view&amp;id=103&amp;Itemid=55 |title=Howardzinn.org |publisher=howardzinn.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.com/content/people-speak |title=History channel |publisher=History.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil Rights movement===
From 1956 through 1963, Zinn chaired the department of history and social sciences at [[Spelman College]]. He participated in the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)|Civil Rights movement]] and lobbied with historian August Meier&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oah.org/pubs/nl/2003may/meier.html |title=Biography of August Meier |publisher=Oah.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;to end the practice of the [[Southern Historical Association]] of holding meetings at [[Racial segregation|segregated]] hotels&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Organization of American Historians]]. Obituary of August Meier, May 2003 by John Bracey [[University of Massachusetts]], [[Amherst, Massachusetts|Amherst]], [http://www.oah.org/pubs/nl/2003may/meier.html OAH.org].&lt;/ref&gt;

While at Spelman, Zinn served as an adviser to the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]] (SNCC) and in 1964, [[Beacon Press]] published his book ''SNCC: The New Abolitionists''. Zinn collaborated with historian [[Staughton Lynd]] mentoring student activists, among them [[Alice Walker]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/ae/books/articles/2010/01/31/alice_walker_says_goodbye_to_her_friend_howard_zinn/ [[Alice Walker]] remembers Howard Zinn. January 31, 2010 in the Boston Globe].&lt;/ref&gt; who would later write ''[[The Color Purple]]'', and [[Marian Wright Edelman]], founder and president of the [[Children's Defense Fund|Children’s Defense Fund]]. Edelman identified Zinn as a major influence in her life and, in that same journal article, tells of his accompanying students to a sit-in at the segregated white section of the [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] state legislature.&lt;ref&gt;Edelman, Marian Wright. &quot;Spelman College: A Safe Haven for A Young Black Woman.&quot; ''The Journal of Blacks in Higher Education'', no. 27 (2000): 118–123.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Zinn was a tenured professor, he was dismissed in June 1963, after siding with students in the struggle against segregation. As Zinn described&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenation.com/doc/19600806/zinn/print &quot;Finishing School for Pickets&quot; By Howard Zinn in ''The Nation'' August 6, 1960].&lt;/ref&gt; in ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]],'' though Spelman administrators prided themselves for turning out refined &quot;young ladies,&quot; its students were likely to be found on the picket line, or in jail for participating in the greater effort to break down segregation in public places in Atlanta. Zinn's years at Spelman are recounted in his autobiography ''You Can't Be Neutral on a Moving Train: A Personal History of Our Times.'' His seven years at Spelman College, Zinn said, &quot;are probably the most interesting, exciting, most educational years for me. I learned more from my students than my students learned from me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://globetrotter.berkeley.edu/people/Zinn/zinn-con2.html |title=Interview with Zinn |publisher=Globetrotter.berkeley.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While living in Georgia, Zinn wrote that he observed 30 violations of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]] amendments to the [[United States Constitution]] in [[Albany, Georgia]], including the rights to [[freedom of speech]], [[freedom of assembly]] and [[equal protection]] under the law. In an article on the civil rights movement in Albany, Zinn described the people who participated in the [[Freedom Rides]] to end segregation, and the reluctance of President [[John F. Kennedy]] to enforce the law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zmag.org/zmag/articles/oldzinn.htm Zmag.org] {{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zinn has also pointed out that the [[United States Department of Justice|Justice Department]] under [[Robert F. Kennedy]] and the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]], headed by [[J. Edgar Hoover]], did little or nothing to stop the segregationists from brutalizing civil rights workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mediafilter.org/mff/fbi.html |title=Media Filter article on Zinn |publisher=Mediafilter.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Zinn wrote about the struggle for civil rights, both as participant and historian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reportingcivilrights.org/authors/biblio.jsp?authorId=85 |title=Reporting Civil Rights, Part one: American Journalism 1941–1963 |publisher=The Library of America |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; His second book, ''The Southern Mystique''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.identitytheory.com/people/birnbaum10.html |title=Intervew with Zinn |publisher=Identitytheory.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; was published in 1964, the same year as his ''SNCC: The New Abolitionists'' in which he describes how the sit-ins against segregation were initiated by students and, in that sense, were independent of the efforts of the older, more established civil rights organizations.

In 2005, forty-one years after his firing, Zinn returned to Spelman where he was given an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and gave the commencement address&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.exodusnews.com/education/education051.htm |title=Exodus News article on Zinn |publisher=Atlanta Inquirer (Georgia) via Exodusnews.com |date=2005-05-11 |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Victoria |last= Brittain |title=Howard Zinn's Lesson To Us All |newspaper= [[The Guardian]] |date= 28 January 2010 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2010/jan/28/howard-zinn-america}}&lt;/ref&gt; where he said in part, during his speech titled, &quot;Against Discouragement,&quot; that &quot;The lesson of that history is that you must not despair, that if you are right, and you persist, things will change. The government may try to deceive the people, and the newspapers and television may do the same, but the truth has a way of coming out. The truth has a power greater than a hundred lies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tomdispatch.com/post/2728/graduation_day_with_howard_zinn |title=Tomgram: Graduation Day with Howard Zinn |publisher=Tomdispatch.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}} full text of &quot;Against Discouragement.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-war efforts===
Zinn wrote one of the earliest books calling for the U.S. withdrawal from its war in [[Vietnam]]. ''Vietnam: The Logic of Withdrawal'' was published by Beacon Press in 1967 based on his articles in ''[[Commonwealth]]'', ''[[The Nation]],'' and ''[[Ramparts (magazine)|Ramparts]].'' 

In [[Noam Chomsky]]'s view, ''The Logic of Withdrawal'' was Zinn's most important book. &quot;He was the first person to say—loudly, publicly, very persuasively—that this simply has to stop; we should get out, period, no conditions; we have no right to be there; it's an act of aggression; pull out. It was so surprising at the time that there wasn't even a review of the book. In fact, he asked me if I would review it in ''[[Ramparts (magazine)|Ramparts]]'' just so that people would know about the book.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.democracynow.org/2010/1/28/howard_zinn_1922_2010_a_tribute Howard Zinn (1922–2010): A Tribute to the Legendary Historian with Noam Chomsky, Alice Walker, Naomi Klein and Anthony Arnove].&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1969, radical historians tried unsuccessfully to persuade the [[American Historical Association]] to pass an anti-Vietnam War resolution. &quot;A debacle unfolded as [[Harvard University|Harvard]] historian (and AHA president in 1968) [[John K. Fairbank|John Fairbank]] literally wrestled the microphone from Zinn's hands.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historians.org/Perspectives/issues/2010/1002/1002tim1.cfm &quot;Forty Years On: Looking Back at the 1969 Annual Meeting&quot;] by Carl Mirra [http://www.adelphi.edu/faculty/profiles/profile.php?PID=0430 February 2010 issue of ''Perspectives on History'' published by the American Historical Association].&lt;/ref&gt; Correspondence by Fairbank, Zinn and other historians, published by the AHA in 1970, is online in what Fairbank called &quot;our briefly-famous Struggle for the Mike&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/1970/7006/7006tim1.cfm From the June 1970 AHA Newsletter &quot;Professional Comment and Controversy: An Open Letter to Howard Zinn&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; 

In later years, Zinn was an adviser to the Disarm Education Fund.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.disarm.org/who-we-are/disarm-staff Disarm National Advisory Board]. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Vietnam====
Zinn's diplomatic visit to Hanoi with Rev. [[Daniel Berrigan]], during the Tet Offensive in January 1968, resulted in the return of three American airmen, the first American ''POWs'' released by the North Vietnamese since the U.S. bombing of that nation had begun. The event was widely reported in the news media and discussed in a variety of books including ''Who Spoke Up? American Protest Against the War in Vietnam 1963–1975'' by Nancy Zaroulis and Gerald Sullivan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Who Spoke Up? American Protest Against the War in Vietnam 1963–1975 |publisher=Horizon Book Promotions |year= 1989 |ISBN=0-385-17547-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zinn and the Berrigan brothers, Dan and [[Philip Berrigan|Philip]], remained friends and allies over the years.

Also in January 1968, he signed the “Writers and Editors War Tax Protest” pledge, vowing to refuse tax payments in protest against the war.&lt;ref&gt;“Writers and Editors War Tax Protest” January 30, 1968 ''New York Post''&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Daniel Ellsberg]], a former [[RAND]] consultant who had secretly copied ''[[The Pentagon Papers]]'', which described the internal planning and policy decisions of the United States government during the Vietnam War, gave a copy of them to Howard and Roslyn Zinn.&lt;ref&gt;Ellsberg autobiography, Zinn autobiography.&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[Noam Chomsky]], Zinn edited and annotated the copy of ''The Pentagon Papers'' that Ellsberg entrusted to him. Zinn's longtime publisher, Beacon Press, published what has come to be known as the Senator [[Mike Gravel]] edition of ''The Pentagon Papers,'' four volumes plus a fifth volume with analysis by Chomsky and Zinn.

At Ellsberg's criminal trial for theft, conspiracy, and espionage in connection with the publication of the ''Pentagon Papers'' by ''The [[New York Times]]'', defense attorneys called Zinn as an expert witness to explain to the jury the history of U.S. involvement in Vietnam from World War II to 1963. Zinn discussed that history for several hours, later reflecting on his time before the jury. &quot;I explained there was nothing in the papers of military significance that could be used to harm the defense of the United States, that the information in them was simply embarrassing to our government because what was revealed, in the government's own interoffice memos, was how it had lied to the American public. The secrets disclosed in the Pentagon Papers might embarrass politicians, might hurt the profits of corporations wanting tin, rubber, oil, in far-off places. But this was not the same as hurting the nation, the people,&quot; Zinn wrote in his autobiography. Most of the jurors later said that they voted for acquittal. [p.&amp;nbsp;161] However, the federal judge dismissed the case on the ground that it had been tainted by the [[Richard M. Nixon|Nixon]] administration's [[Daniel Ellsberg#Fielding break-in|burglary of the office of Ellsberg's psychiatrist]].

Zinn's testimony as to the motivation for government secrecy was confirmed in 1989 by [[Erwin Griswold]], who as U.S. solicitor general during the Nixon administration, prosecuted ''The New York Times'' in the Pentagon Papers case in 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/opinion/la-op-blanton21may21,0,1992884.story |title=The lie behind the secrets |author=Blanton, Tom |date=2006-05-21 |publisher=Los Angeles Times |accessdate=2008-01-21}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Griswold persuaded three Supreme Court justices to vote to stop ''The New York Times'' from continuing to publish the Pentagon Papers, an order known as &quot;prior restraint&quot; that has been held to be illegal under the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]]. The papers were simultaneously published in ''[[The Washington Post]]'', effectively nulling the effect of the prior restraint order. In 1989, Griswold admitted that there was no national security damage resulting from the publication of the papers.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt; In a column in the ''Washington Post'', Griswold wrote: &quot;It quickly becomes apparent to any person who has considerable experience with classified material that there is massive over classification and that the principal concern of the classifiers is not with national security, but with governmental embarrassment of one sort or another.&quot;

Zinn supported the G.I. antiwar movement during the U.S. war in Vietnam. In the 2001 film ''[[Unfinished Symphony]]'', Zinn provides a historical context for the 1971 antiwar march by [[Vietnam Veterans against the War]]. The marchers traveled from [[Lexington, Massachusetts|Lexington]], [[Massachusetts]], to [[Battle of Bunker Hill|Bunker Hill]], &quot;which retraced [[Paul Revere]]'s ride of 1775 and ended in the massive arrest of 410 veterans and civilians by the Lexington police.&quot; The film depicts &quot;scenes from the 1971 Winter Soldier hearings,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Winter Soldier Investigation |year=1971}}&lt;/ref&gt; during which former G.I.s testified, with little to no actual evidence, about &quot;atrocities&quot; they either participated in or said they had  witnessed committed by U.S. forces in Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chss.montclair.edu/english/furr/unfinished.pdf Cineaste] pp. 91, 96. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iraq====
[[File:Howard Zinn.jpg|220px|thumb|right|Howard Zinn speaking at [[Marlboro College]] February 2004]]

Zinn opposed the invasion and occupation of Iraq and wrote several books about it. He asserted that the U.S. would end its war with an occupation of Iraq when resistance within the military increased in the same way resistance within the military contributed to ending the U.S. war in Vietnam. He compared the demand by a growing number of contemporary U.S. military families to end the war in Iraq to parallel demands &quot;in the Confederacy in the Civil War, when the wives of soldiers rioted because their husbands were dying and the plantation owners were profiting from the sale of cotton, refusing to grow grains for civilians to eat.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tomdispatch.com/index.mhtml?emx=x&amp;pid=20715 Interview with Zinn].&lt;/ref&gt; Zinn argued that &quot;There is no flag large enough to cover the shame of killing innocent people for a purpose which is unattainable&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thirdworldtraveler.com/Zinn/Tripoli_ZR.html |title=Terrorism Over Tripoli from ''Zinn Reader'', Seven Stories Press (1993) excerpted online |publisher=Thirdworldtraveler.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jean-Christophe Agnew, Professor of History and American Studies at [[Yale University]], told the ''[[Yale Daily News]]'' in May 2007 that Zinn’s historical work is &quot;highly influential and widely used&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yaledailynews.com/articles/view/21049 |title=Zinn calls for activism |publisher=Yale Daily News |date=2007-05-03 |accessdate=2010-01-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071016182602/http://yaledailynews.com/articles/view/21049 |archivedate = October 16, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; He observed that it is not unusual for prominent professors such as Zinn to weigh in on current events, citing a resolution opposing the war in Iraq that was recently ratified by the [[American Historical Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.historians.org/news/166/iraq-war-resolution-is-ratified-by-aha-members |title=American Historical Association Blog: Iraq War Resolution is Ratified by AHA Members |publisher=Blog.historians.org |date=2007-03-12 |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Agnew added: &quot;In these moments of crisis, when the country is split—so historians are split&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Yu |first=Lea |url=http://www.commondreams.org/archive/2007/05/04/963/ |title=Historian Howard Zinn Calls for Activism – CommonDreams.org |publisher=CommonDreams.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Socialism===
Zinn described himself as &quot;Something of an [[Anarchism|anarchist]], something of a [[Socialism|socialist]]. Maybe a [[Democratic socialism|democratic socialist]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://flag.blackened.net/ias/13zinn.htm &quot;War is the Health of the State: An Interview with Howard Zinn&quot;], By Paul Glavin &amp; Chuck Morse, ''Perspectives on Anarchist Theory'', Vol. 7, No. 1, Spring 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; He suggested looking at socialism in its full historical context as a popular, positive idea that got a bad name from its association with Soviet Communism. In [[Madison, Wisconsin]] in 2009, Zinn said:
{{Quote|Let's talk about socialism. I think it's very important to bring back the idea of socialism into the national discussion to where it was at the turn of the [last] century before the Soviet Union gave it a bad name. Socialism had a good name in this country. Socialism had [[Eugene Debs]]. It had [[Clarence Darrow]]. It had [[Mary Harris Jones|Mother Jones]]. It had [[Emma Goldman]]. It had several million people reading socialist newspapers around the country. Socialism basically said, hey, let's have a kinder, gentler society. Let's share things. Let's have an economic system that produces things not because they're profitable for some corporation, but produces things that people need. People should not be retreating from the word socialism because you have to go beyond capitalism.&lt;ref name = &quot;ZirinHP&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/dave-zirin/howard-zinn-the-historian_b_439757.html Howard Zinn: The Historian Who Made History] by [[Dave Zirin]], ''[[The Huffington Post]]'', January 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===FBI files===
Due to a [[Freedom of Information Act (United States)|Freedom of Information Act]] (FOIA) request, on July 30, 2010, the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI) released a file with 423 pages of information on Howard Zinn’s life and activities. During the height of [[McCarthyism]] in 1949, the FBI first opened a domestic security investigation on Zinn (FBI File # 100-360217), based on Zinn’s activities in what the agency considered to be communist [[front groups]] and informant reports that Zinn was an active member of the [[Communist Party of the United States]] (CPUSA).&lt;ref name = &quot;Progress&quot;&gt;[http://progressive.org/node/146176/14010 The FBI’s File on Howard Zinn] by Matthew Rothschild, ''[[The Progressive]]'', July 31, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Zinn denied ever being a member and said that he had participated in the activities of various organizations which might be considered Communist fronts but that his participation was motivated by his belief that in this country people had the right to believe, think, and act according to their own ideals.&lt;ref name = &quot;Progress&quot; /&gt;

Later in the 1960s, as a result of Zinn’s campaigning against the [[Vietnam War]] and his influence on [[Martin Luther King]], the FBI designated Zinn a high security risk to the country, a category that allowed them to summarily arrest him if a [[state of emergency]] were to be declared.&lt;ref name = &quot;Progress&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://foia.fbi.gov/foiaindex/zinn_howard.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The FBI memos also show that they were concerned with Zinn’s repeated criticism of the FBI for failing to protect blacks against white mob violence. Zinn's daughter said she was not surprised by the files; &quot;He always knew they had a file on him&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Progress&quot; /&gt;

==Death==
Zinn was swimming in a hotel pool when he died of an apparent [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/us/29zinn.html &quot;Howard Zinn, Historian, Is Dead at 87&quot; ''The New York Times'' January 29, 2010].&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Santa Monica, California]] on 27 January, 2010. He had been scheduled to speak at the [[Santa Monica Museum of Art]] for an event titled &quot;A Collection of Ideas... [[the People Speak]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-howard-zinn28-2010jan28,0,5610858.story Howard Zinn dies at 87; author of best-selling ''People's History of the United States'': Activist collapsed in Santa Monica, where he was scheduled to deliver a lecture.] by Robert J. Lopez, January 28, 2010. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

In one of his last interviews&lt;ref&gt;[http://bigthink.com/howardzinn/ Howard Zinn video in nine parts].&lt;/ref&gt;
he said he'd like to be remembered &quot;for introducing a different way of thinking about the world, about war, about human rights, about equality,&quot; and &quot;for getting more people to realize that the power which rests so far in the hands of people with wealth and guns, that the power ultimately rests in people themselves and that they can use it. At certain points in history, they have used it. Black people in the South used it. People in the women's movement used it. People in the anti-war movement used it. People in other countries who have overthrown tyrannies have used it.&quot;

He said he wanted to be known as &quot;somebody who gave people a feeling of hope and power that they didn't have before&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/video/2010/01/29-2 Howard Zinn: How I Want to Be Remembered].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable recognition==
*2008  Howard Zinn was selected as a special senior advisor to [[Miguel d'Escoto Brockmann]], the [[President of the United Nations General Assembly]] 63rd session.
	
* Established while he was alive by school teachers, the [http://www.zinnedproject.org/ Zinn Education Project] is Howard Zinn's legacy to middle- and high school teachers and their students. The nonprofit organization offers classroom teachers free and low-cost teaching activities based on ''A People's History'' and like-minded history texts.

==Awards==
{{Quote box
| quote = &quot;I can't think of anyone who had such a powerful and benign influence. His historical work changed the way millions of people saw the past. The happy thing about Howard was that in the last years he could gain satisfaction that his contributions were so impressive and recognized.&quot;
| source = — [[Noam Chomsky]] &lt;ref name=&quot;HP&quot;/&gt;
 | width = 38%
 | align = right 
}}

For his leadership in the Peace Movement, Zinn received the Peace Abbey Courage of Conscience Award in 1996. He received the [[Thomas Merton Award]] and, in 1998, the [[Eugene V. Debs]] Award.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080505034745/http://www.eugenevdebs.com/pages/foundation.html Eugene V Debs Foundation Member Awards]. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, he won the [[Lannan Literary Award]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lannan.org/lf/bios/detail/howard-zinn/ |title=Lannan Foundation – Howard Zinn |publisher=Lannan.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; for nonfiction and the following year won the [[Upton Sinclair]] Award, which honors social activism. In 2003, Zinn was awarded the ''Prix des Amis du [[Monde diplomatique]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amis.monde-diplomatique.fr/article.php3?id_article=252 |title=Prix des Amis du Monde diplomatique 2003 – Les Amis du Monde diplomatique |publisher=Amis.monde-diplomatique.fr |date= |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; for the French version of his seminal work, ''Une histoire populaire des Etats-Unis.''

On October 5, 2006, Zinn received the Haven's Center Award for Lifetime Contribution to Critical Scholarship in [[Madison, Wisconsin|Madison]], [[Wisconsin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.news.wisc.edu/12985.html |title=Zinn to receive Havens Center award (October 4, 2006) |publisher=News.wisc.edu |date=2006-10-04 |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References in popular culture==
* Rap artist [[Murs (rapper)|Murs]], in his song 'Think You Know Me', references Zinn by saying, &quot;In the feds I prayed and I read, anything to keep the system up out of my head. I read Zinn, Young, Bukowski. You really don't know a damn thing about me.&quot;
* An interview with Zinn is featured in the documentary film [[Sacco and Vanzetti (film)|''Sacco and Vanzetti'']] (2007).
* The [[Brother Ali]] song &quot;Lookin' At Me Sideways&quot; from the album [[The Undisputed Truth (Brother Ali album)|The Undisputed Truth]] claims &quot;I am Howard Stern meets Howard Zinn.&quot;
* The [[Pearl Jam]] song &quot;Down&quot; from the album ''[[Lost Dogs (album)|Lost Dogs]]'' was inspired by the band's friendship with Zinn.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} In the March 13, 2010 episode of ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'', lead singer [[Eddie Vedder]]'s guitar sports a sticker reading &quot;ZINN&quot;. A tribute to Howard Zinn's wife, Roslyn, was prominently featured in the tour program for Eddie Vedder's solo tour of 2008.
* Actors [[Matt Damon]] and [[Ben Affleck]], who grew up near Zinn and were family friends, gave ''A People's History'' a plug in their Academy Award-winning screenplay for ''[[Good Will Hunting]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;HP&quot; /&gt;
* [[Marge Simpson]] is seen reading ''A People's History'' in ''[[The Simpsons]]'' episode 1911 &quot;That 90's Show&quot;, which flashes back to when Marge was in college.
* In the [[HBO]] drama series, ''[[The Sopranos]]'', [[Tony Soprano]]'s son [[A.J. Soprano|A.J.]] becomes very interested in &quot;A Peoples History&quot; as it is assigned as a text book at his school.
* Musician [[Bruce Springsteen]]'s bleak album ''[[Nebraska (album)|Nebraska]]'' was inspired in part by ''A People's History''.&lt;ref name=&quot;HP&quot; /&gt;
* ''A People's History'' was the basis for the 2007 documentary, ''Profit Motive and the Whispering Wind''.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HP&quot; /&gt;
* In 2002 punkrock record label [[Alternative Tentacles]], released ''Apocalypse Always!'', a compilation CD featuring many punk rock bands as well as a spoken word track by Howard Zinn.
* The [[NOFX]] song &quot;Franco Un-American&quot; references Howard Zinn.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.plyrics.com/lyrics/nofx/francounamerican.html NOFX lyrics]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the [[System Of A Down]] song &quot;Deer Dance&quot;, about police brutality against peaceful protest, Zinn is paraphrased in the line &quot;We can't afford to be neutral on a moving train&quot; and in their song &quot;A.D.D&quot; from their album &quot;Steal This Album!&quot;: &quot;There is no flag large enough, to hide the shame of a man in cuffs.&quot;
* [[Viggo Mortensen]] and [[Buckethead]] used snippets of one of Zinn's speeches in the song &quot;What Kind of Nation&quot; from their album ''[[Intelligence Failure]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tdrsmusic.com/viggo.htm |title=Viggo Mortensen |author= |publisher=TDRS Music |date=2007-11-23 |accessdate=2010-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.percevalpress.com/intel_failure.html |title=Intelligence Failure |author= |publisher=Perceval Press |year=2007 |accessdate=2010-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.discogs.com/BucketheadViggo-Mortensen-Intelligence-Failure/release/2023349 |title=Buckethead &amp; Viggo - Intelligence Failure |author= |publisher=Discogs |year=2010 |accessdate=2010-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The 2010 Spanish film ''También la lluvia'' (''Even the Rain''), depicting the struggle of the indigenous people of [[Bolivia]] against the privatization of their water supply, is dedicated to his memory.

==Bibliography==
===Author===
* ''LaGuardia in Congress'' (1959) ISBN 0-8371-6434-6, ISBN 0-393-00488-0.
* ''The Southern Mystique'' (1962) ISBN 0-89608-680-1.
* ''SNCC: The New Abolitionists'' (1964) ISBN 0-89608-679-8.
* ''New Deal Thought'' (editor) (1965) ISBN 0-87220-685-8.
* ''Vietnam: The Logic of Withdrawal'' (1967) ISBN 0-89608-681-X.
* ''Disobedience and Democracy: Nine Fallacies on Law and Order'' (1968, re-issued 2002) ISBN 0-89608-675-5.
* ''The Politics of History'' (1970) (2nd edition 1990) ISBN 0-252-06122-5.
* ''The Pentagon Papers'' Senator Gravel Edition. Vol. Five. Critical Essays. Boston. Beacon Press, 1972. 341p. plus 72p. of Index to Vol. I–IV of the Papers, Noam Chomsky, Howard Zinn, editors.
* ''Postwar America: 1945–1971'' (1973) ISBN 0-89608-678-X.
* ''Justice in Everyday Life: The Way It Really Works'' (Editor) (1974) ISBN 0-89608-677-1.
* ''Justice? Eyewitness Accounts'' (1977) ISBN 0-8070-4479-2.
* ''[[A People's History of the United States]]: 1492 – Present'' (1980), revised (1995)(1998)(1999)(2003)(2004)(2005)(2010) ISBN 0-06-052837-0.
* ''Playbook'' by Maxine Klein, [[Lydia Sargent]] and Howard Zinn (1986) ISBN 0-89608-309-8.
* ''Declarations of Independence: Cross-Examining American Ideology'' (1991) ISBN 0-06-092108-0.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=z6p4AAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Declarations+of+Independence:+Cross-Examining+American+Ideology&amp;dq=Declarations+of+Independence:+Cross-Examining+American+Ideology&amp;ots=P3B6og-JYy&amp;sig=_4bK-NUMGayBvnNSQemVqoZyxwY&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=R-5mS5_2BJTWNrqsuP4G&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCcQ6AEwAA Declarations of independence: cross-examining American ideology] By Howard Zinn.&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''A People's History of the United States: The Civil War to the Present'' Kathy Emery and Ellen Reeves, Howard Zinn (2003 teaching edition) ISBN 1-56584-725-3.
* ''Failure to Quit: Reflections of an Optimistic Historian'' (1993) ISBN 0-89608-676-3.
* ''You Can't Be Neutral on a Moving Train: A Personal History of Our Times'' (1994) ISBN 0-8070-7127-7
* ''A People's History of the United States: The Wall Charts'' by Howard Zinn and George Kirschner (1995) ISBN 1-56584-171-9.
* ''Hiroshima: Breaking the Silence'' [http://polymer.bu.edu/~amaral/Personal/zinn.html (pamphlet, 1995)] ISBN 1-884519-14-8.
* ''The Zinn Reader: Writings on Disobedience and Democracy'' (1997) ISBN 1-888363-54-1; 2nd edition (2009) ISBN 978-1-58322-870-8.
* ''The Cold War &amp; the University: Toward an Intellectual History of the Postwar Years'' ([[Noam Chomsky]] (Editor) Authors: [[Ira Katznelson]], [[R. C. Lewontin]], [[David Montgomery (historian)|David Montgomery]], [[Laura Nader]], Richard Ohmann,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.upne.com/0-8195-6589-X.html |title=Politics of Knowledge: Richard Ohmann |publisher=UPNE |date=2010-01-21 |accessdate=2010-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ray Siever, [[Immanuel Wallerstein]], Howard Zinn (1997) ISBN 1-56584-005-4.
* ''[[Marx in Soho|Marx in Soho: A Play on History]]'' (1999) ISBN 0-89608-593-7.
* ''The Future of History: Interviews With David Barsamian'' (1999) ISBN 1-56751-157-0.
* ''Howard Zinn on War'' (2000) ISBN 1-58322-049-6.
* ''Howard Zinn on History'' (2000) ISBN 1-58322-048-8.
* ''La Otra Historia De Los Estados Unidos'' (2000) ISBN 1-58322-054-2.
* ''Three Strikes: Miners, Musicians, Salesgirls, and the Fighting Spirit of Labor's Last Century'' (Dana Frank, Robin Kelley, and Howard Zinn) (2002) ISBN 0-8070-5013-X.
* ''Terrorism and War'' (2002) ISBN 1-58322-493-9 (interviews, Anthony Arnove (Ed.))
* ''The Power of Nonviolence: Writings by Advocates of Peace'' Editor (2002) ISBN 0-8070-1407-9.
* ''Emma: A Play in Two Acts About Emma Goldman, American Anarchist'' (2002) ISBN 0-89608-664-X.
* ''Artists in Times of War'' (2003) ISBN 1-58322-602-8.
* ''The Twentieth Century: A People's History'' (2003) ISBN 0-06-053034-0.
* ''A People's History of the United States: Teaching Edition Abridged'' (2003 updated) ISBN 1-56584-826-8.
* ''Passionate Declarations: Essays on War and Justice'' (2003) ISBN 0-06-055767-2.
* ''Howard Zinn On Democratic Education'' [[Donaldo Macedo]], Editor (2004) ISBN 1-59451-054-7.
* ''The People Speak: American Voices, Some Famous, Some Little Known'' (2004) ISBN 0-06-057826-2.
* ''Voices of a People’s History of the United States'' (with [[Anthony Arnove]], 2004) ISBN 1-58322-647-8; 2nd edition (2009) ISBN 978-1-58322-916-3.
* ''A People's History of the Civil War: Struggles for the Meaning of Freedom'' by David Williams, Howard Zinn (Series Editor) (2005) ISBN 1-59558-018-2.
* ''A Power Governments Cannot Suppress'' (2006) ISBN 978-0-87286-475-7.
* ''Original Zinn: Conversations on History and Politics'' (2006) Howard Zinn and David Barsamian.
* ''[[A People's History of American Empire]]'' (2008) by Howard Zinn, Mike Konopacki and [[Paul Buhle]]. ISBN 978-0-8050-8744-4.
* ''A Young People's History of the United States'', adapted from the original text by Rebecca Stefoff; illustrated and updated through 2006, with new introduction and afterword by Howard Zinn; two volumes, [[Seven Stories Press]], New York, 2007.
** ''Vol. 1: Columbus to the Spanish-American War''. ISBN 978-1-58322-759-6.
** ''Vol. 2: Class Struggle to the War on Terror''. ISBN 978-1-58322-760-2.
** One-volume edition (2009) ISBN 978-1-58322-869-2.
* ''The Bomb'' ([[City Lights Bookstore|City Lights Publishers]], 2010) ISBN 978-0-87286-509-9
* ''The Historic Unfulfilled Promise'' (City Lights Publishers, 2012) ISBN 978-0-87286-555-6

===Contributor===
* ''Admirable Radical: Staughton Lynd and Cold War Dissent, 1945–1970 (2010), Kent State University Press by Carl Mirra ISBN 978-1-60635-051-5
* ''A Gigantic Mistake'' by [[Mickey Z]], (2004) ISBN 1-930997-97-3.
* ''A People's History of the Supreme Court'' by [[Peter H. Irons]] (2000) ISBN 0-14-029201-2.
* ''A Political Dynasty In North Idaho, 1933–1967'' by Randall Doyle (2004) ISBN 0-7618-2843-5.
* ''American Political Prisoners: Prosecutions Under the Espionage and Sedition Acts'' by [[Stephen M. Kohn]] (1994) ISBN 0-275-94415-8.
* ''American Power and the New Mandarins'' by [[Noam Chomsky]] (2002) ISBN 1-56584-775-X.
* ''Broken Promises Of America: At Home And Abroad, Past And Present: An Encyclopedia For Our Times'' by ([[Douglas F. Dowd]] (2004) ISBN 1-56751-313-1.
* ''Deserter From Death: Dispatches From Western Europe 1950-2000'' by [[Daniel Singer (journalist)|Daniel Singer]] (2005) ISBN 1-56025-642-7.
* ''Ecocide of Native America: Environmental Destruction of Indian Lands and Peoples'' by Donald Grinde, Bruce Johansen (1994) ISBN 0-940666-52-9.
* ''Eugene V. Debs Reader: Socialism and the Class Struggle'' by William A. Pelz (2000) ISBN 0-9704669-0-0.
* ''From a Native Son: Selected Essays in Indigenism, 1985–1995'' by [[Ward Churchill]] (1996) ISBN 0-89608-553-8.
* ''Green Parrots: A War Surgeon's Diary'' by [[Gino Strada]], (2005) ISBN 88-8158-420-4.
* ''Hijacking Catastrophe: 9/11, Fear And The Selling Of American Empire'' by [[Sut Jhally]] editor, Jeremy Earp editor, (2004) ISBN 1-56656-581-2.
* ''If You're Not a Terrorist…Then Stop Asking Questions!'' by [[Micah Ian Wright]], (2004) ISBN 1-58322-626-5.
* ''Iraq: The Logic of Withdrawal'' by [[Anthony Arnove]], (2006) ISBN 978-1-59558-079-5.
* ''Impeach the President: The Case Against Bush and Cheney'' Dennis Loo (Editor), Peter Phillips (Editor) Seven Stories Press: 2006) ISBN 1-58322-743-1.
* ''Life of an Anarchist: The Alexander Berkman Reader'' by [[Alexander Berkman]] Gene Fellner, editor, (2004) ISBN 1-58322-662-1.
* ''Long Shadows: Veterans' Paths to Peace'' by David Giffey editor, (2006) ISBN 1-89185-964-9.
* ''Masters of War: Latin America and United States Aggression from the Cuban Revolution Through the Clinton Years'' by Clara Nieto, Chris Brandt (trans) (2003) ISBN 1-58322-545-5.
* ''Peace Signs: The Anti-War Movement Illustrated'' by [[James Mann (writer)|James Mann]], editor (2004) ISBN 3-283-00487-0.
* ''Prayer for the Morning Headlines: On the Sanctity of Life and Death'' by [[Daniel Berrigan]] (poetry) and Adrianna Amari (photography), (2007) ISBN 978-1-934074-16-9.
* ''Silencing Political Dissent: How Post-9-11 Anti-terrorism Measures Threaten Our Civil Liberties'' by Nancy Chang, [[Center for Constitutional Rights]] (2002) ISBN 1-58322-494-7.
* ''Soldiers In Revolt: GI Resistance During The Vietnam War'' by [[David Cortright]], (2005) ISBN 1-931859-27-2.
* ''Sold to the Highest Bidder: The Presidency from Dwight D. Eisenhower to George W. Bush'' by Daniel M. Friedenberg (2002) ISBN 1-57392-923-9.
* ''The Autobiography of Abbie Hoffman'' Intro by [[Norman Mailer]], Afterword by HZ (2000) ISBN 1-56858-197-1.
* ''The Case for Socialism'' by Alan Maass, (2004) ISBN 1-931859-09-4.
* ''The Forging of the American Empire: From the Revolution to Vietnam, a History of U.S. Imperialism'' by [[Sidney Lens]] (2003) ISBN 0-7453-2101-1.
* ''The Higher Law: Thoreau on Civil Disobedience and Reform'' by [[Henry David Thoreau]], Wendell Glick, editor, (2004) ISBN 0-691-11876-0.
* ''The Iron Heel'' by [[Jack London]], (1971) ISBN 0-14-303971-7.
* ''The Sixties Experience: Hard Lessons about Modern America'' by [[Edward P. Morgan]], (1992) ISBN 1-56639-014-1.
* ''You Back the Attack, We'll Bomb Who We Want'' by [[Micah Ian Wright]], (2003) ISBN 1-58322-584-6.
* ''A People's History of the American Revolution'' by [[Ray Raphael]], (2002) ISBN 0-06-000440-1 ''Howard Zinn Foreword for New Press People's History Series''.

===Recordings===
* ''A People's History of the United States'' (1999)
* ''Artists in the Time of War'' (2002)
* ''Heroes &amp; Martyrs: Emma Goldman, Sacco &amp; Vanzetti, and the Revolutionary Struggle'' (2000)
* ''Stories Hollywood Never Tells'' (2000)
* ''You Can't Blow Up A Social Relationship'', CD including Zinn lectures and performances by rock band Resident genius (Thick Records, 2005)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akpress.org/2005/items/youcantblowupzinnresidentgenius &quot;You Can't Blow Up A Social Relationship&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theatre===
* ''[[Emma (play)|Emma]]'' (1976)
* ''[[Daughter of Venus]]'' (1985)
* ''[[Marx in Soho]]'' (1999)

==Biographies==
* Deb Ellis and Denis Mueller, ''Howard Zinn: You Can't Be Neutral on a Moving Train'' (film 2004)&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060507103518/http://firstrunfeatures.com/product418.html FRF's Judith Mizrachy interviews Deb Ellis and Denis Mueller, directors of the film Howard Zinn: You can't be neutral on a moving train]. Retrieved 2010-03-09.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Davis D. Joyce, ''Howard Zinn: A Radical American Vision'' ([[Prometheus Books]], 2003), ISBN 1-59102-131-6
* Gagliano Giuseppe, ''L'intellettuale in rivolta.L'antagonismo politico attraverso le riflessioni di Zinn,Buber,Comsky'' ([[Editrice Uniservice]], 2010), ISBN 9788861786523

==See also==
*[[A People's History of American Empire]]
*[[A People's History of the United States]]
{{Portal bar|Anarchism|Biography|Boston|Liberalism|Social and political philosophy|Socialism|United States|University}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://howardzinn.org HowardZinn.org]
*[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0957016/ Howard Zinn] at [[The Internet Movie Database]]
*{{ZSpace|howardzinn}}
*[http://www.progressive.org/zinn Column archive] at ''[[The Progressive]]''
*{{C-SPAN|howardzinn}}
*{{worldcat id|lccn-n79-59761}}
*{{NYTtopic|people/z/howard_zinn}}
* [http://foia.fbi.gov/foiaindex/zinn_howard.htm Howard Zinn's files] at the [[FBI]]
*[http://vault.fbi.gov/Howard%20Zinn FBI file on Howard Zinn]
* [http://anarchismtoday.org/News/topic=14.html Articles] and [http://anarchismtoday.org/DF_Multimedia/categoryby=19.html videos] featuring Howard Zinn at [http://AnarchismToday.org AnarchismToday.org].
* [http://zinnedproject.org Zinn Education Project]

;Interviews
* [http://www.educationupdate.com/archives/2004/apr04/issue/col_howardzinn.html 2004 Interview With Howard Zinn].
* [http://www.guernicamag.com/interviews/10/a_peoples_history_of_howard_zi/ Interview with ''Guernica: a magazine of arts and politics''].
* [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1524095 ''The Tavis Smiley Show'': &quot;Howard Zinn and the Omissions of U.S. History&quot;], November 27, 2003, National Public Radio.
* [http://www.legalleft.org/?page_id=137 Howard Zinn speaks on &quot;Confronting Empire&quot; at [[Harvard Law School]] in March 2008]
* [http://www.revolutionbythebook.akpress.org/an-interview-with-howard-zinn-on-anarchism-rebels-against-tyranny/ An Interview with Howard Zinn on Anarchism: Rebels Against Tyranny] by [[AK Press]]
* [http://www.negations.net/war-is-the-health-of-the-state-an-interview-with-howard-zinn/ &quot;War is the Health of the State: An Interview with Howard Zinn&quot;], By Paul Glavin &amp; Chuck Morse, ''Perspectives on Anarchist Theory'', Vol. 7, No. 1, Spring 2003

;Obituaries
* [http://www.beaconbroadside.com/broadside/2010/01/helene-atwan-the-loss-of-howard-zinn.html#more Helene Atwan, director of Beacon Press on &quot;The Loss of Howard Zinn&quot; January 29, 2010].
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/29/us/29zinn.html Howard Zinn, Historian, is Dead at 87], By Michael Powell, [[New York Times]], January 28, 2010
* [http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2010/01/27/us/AP-US-Obit-Zinn.html Associated Press obituary January 27, 2010]
* [http://www.oxonianreview.org/wp/howard-zinn-death-of-an-historian/ Obituary] in the ''[[Oxonian Review]]''

;Videos
* [http://bigthink.com/ideas/1228 The Legacy of Howard Zinn ] – video by [http://bigthink.com/ Big Think]
* [http://www.democracynow.org/blog/2010/1/8/howard_zinn_three_holy_wars Howard Zinn on why there are no just wars: &quot;Holy Wars&quot;] – video by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Arn3lF5XSUg&amp;feature=player_embedded ''Empire or Humanity?: What the Classroom Didn't Teach Me about the American Empire'']; by Howard Zinn; Narrated by Viggo Mortensen
* [http://www.zinnedproject.org/why#video Howard Zinn’s talk to teachers at the 2008 National Conference for the Social Studies (NCSS)] hosted by the Zinn Education Project
* [http://fora.tv/2007/01/28/A_Power_Governments_Cannot_Suppress Zinn Speaking About his Book ~ ''A Power Governments Cannot Suppress''] - one hour speech by [[C-SPAN]]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DbaizDSg1YU Howard Zinn on Marxism, Anarchism, and the Paris Commune] interviewed by Sasha Lilley, November 5, 2009
* [http://www.democracynow.org/2010/1/28/howard_zinn_1922_2010_a_tribute Howard Zinn (1922-2010): A Tribute to the Legendary Historian with Noam Chomsky, Alice Walker, Naomi Klein and Anthony Arnove]
* [[American Feud: A History of Conservatives and Liberals]] documentary featuring interviews with Howard Zinn and others
* [http://therealnews.com/t2/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=33&amp;Itemid=74&amp;jumival=359 Zinn on Class in America] - Interview series on [[The Real News]] (TRNN) (6 videos) - April 2009
* [http://www.mediaed.org/wp/howard-zinn Interview with Howard Zinn] [[Media Education Foundation]] (MEF) - July, 2005

{{Persondata
|NAME=Zinn, Howard
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Author and historian
|DATE OF BIRTH=August 24, 1922
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Brooklyn]], [[New York]], [[United States]]
|DATE OF DEATH=January 27, 2010
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Santa Monica]], [[California]], [[United States]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Zinn, Howard}}
[[Category:1922 births]]
[[Category:2010 deaths]]
[[Category:Deaths from myocardial infarction]]
[[Category:African Americans' rights activists]]
[[Category:American anarchists]]
[[Category:American anti–Vietnam War activists]]
[[Category:American anti-war activists]]
[[Category:American dissidents]]
[[Category:American historians]]
[[Category:American media critics]]
[[Category:American feminists]]
[[Category:American political scientists]]
[[Category:American political writers]]
[[Category:American social commentators]]
[[Category:American socialists]]
[[Category:American memoirists]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:American dramatists and playwrights]]
[[Category:American tax resisters]]
[[Category:Columbia University alumni]]
[[Category:Drug policy reform activists]]
[[Category:G7 Welcoming Committee Records artists]]
[[Category:Jewish American historians]]
[[Category:Harvard University staff]]
[[Category:Historians of anarchism]]
[[Category:Historians of the United States]]
[[Category:Male feminists]]
[[Category:New York University alumni]]
[[Category:People from Middlesex County, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:People from Brooklyn]]
[[Category:United States Army Air Forces officers]]
[[Category:Writers from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Writers from New York City]]
[[Category:Jewish American dramatists and playwrights]]

{{Link GA|eo}}
[[ar:هوارد زين]]
[[bn:হাওয়ার্ড জিন]]
[[ca:Howard Zinn]]
[[cs:Howard Zinn]]
[[cy:Howard Zinn]]
[[da:Howard Zinn]]
[[de:Howard Zinn]]
[[et:Howard Zinn]]
[[es:Howard Zinn]]
[[eo:Howard Zinn]]
[[eu:Howard Zinn]]
[[fa:هوارد زین]]
[[fr:Howard Zinn]]
[[ko:하워드 진]]
[[it:Howard Zinn]]
[[he:הווארד זין]]
[[la:Howardus Zinn]]
[[lb:Howard Zinn]]
[[mk:Хауард Зин]]
[[ml:ഹൊവാർഡ് സിൻ]]
[[nl:Howard Zinn]]
[[ja:ハワード・ジン]]
[[no:Howard Zinn]]
[[nn:Howard Zinn]]
[[pl:Howard Zinn]]
[[pt:Howard Zinn]]
[[ru:Зинн, Говард]]
[[simple:Howard Zinn]]
[[fi:Howard Zinn]]
[[sv:Howard Zinn]]
[[tl:Howard Zinn]]
[[tr:Howard Zinn]]
[[zh:霍华德·津恩]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
