<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8859863" ns="0" title="Multi-touch"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Example farm|date=December 2009}}
[[Image:Multitouch screen.svg|thumb|250px|Multi-touch screen]]
In [[computing]], '''multi-touch''' refers to a touch sensing surface's ([[trackpad]] or [[touchscreen]]) ability to recognize the presence of two or more points of contact with the surface. This plural-point awareness is often used to implement advanced functionality such as [[pinch to zoom]] or activating predefined programs.

In an effort of disambiguation or marketing classification some companies further breakdown the various definitions of multi-touch.  An example of this is [[3M]] defining multi-touch as a touch-screen's ability to register three or more distinct positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = What is Multitouch | url = http://solutions.3m.com/wps/portal/3M/en_US/TouchTopics/Home/Terminology/WhatIsMultitouch/ | accessdate = 30 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

==History==
The use of [[touchscreen]] technology to control electronic devices pre-dates multi-touch technology and the personal computer. Early synthesizer and electronic instrument builders like [[Hugh Le Caine]] and [[Bob Moog]] experimented with using touch-sensitive capacitance sensors to control the sounds made by their instruments.&lt;ref name =buxtonoverview&gt;Buxton, Bill. [http://www.billbuxton.com/multitouchOverview.html &quot;Multitouch Overview&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[IBM]] began building the first touch screens in the late 1960s, and, in 1972, [[Control Data]] released the [[PLATO (computer system)|PLATO]] IV computer, a terminal used for educational purposes that employed single-touch points in a 16x16 array as its user interface.

[[file:CERN-Stumpe Capacitance Touchscreen.jpg|thumb|The prototypes&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 |publisher=CERN Courrier
 |date=31 March 2010
 |title=The first capacitative touch screens at CERN
 |url=http://cerncourier.com/cws/article/cern/42092
 |accessdate=2010-05-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the x-y mutual capacitance multi-touch screens (left) developed at [[CERN]]]]

One of the early implementations of mutual capacitance touchscreen technology was developed at [[CERN]] in 1977&lt;ref name=stumpe77&gt;{{citation
 |publisher=CERN
 |author=Bent STUMPE
 |date=16 March 1977
 |title=A new principle for x-y touch system
 |url=http://cdsweb.cern.ch/record/1266588/files/StumpeMar77.pdf
 |accessdate=2010-05-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation
 |publisher=CERN
 |author=Bent STUMPE
 |date=6 February 1978
 |title=Experiments to find a manufacturing process for an x-y touch screen
 |url=http://cdsweb.cern.ch/record/1266589/files/StumpeFeb78.pdf
 |accessdate=2010-05-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; based on their capacitance touch screens developed in 1972 by Danish electronics engineer [[Bent Stumpe]]. This technology was used to develop a new type of [[human machine interface]] (HMI) for the control room of the [[Super Proton Synchrotron]] particle accelerator.

In a handwritten note dated 11 March 1972, Stumpe presented his proposed solution&amp;nbsp;– a capacitative touch screen with a fixed number of programmable buttons presented on a display. The screen was to consist of a set of capacitors etched into a film of copper on a sheet of glass, each capacitor being constructed so that a nearby flat conductor, such as the surface of a finger, would increase the capacity by a significant amount. The capacitors were to consist of fine lines etched in copper on a sheet of glass&amp;nbsp;– fine enough (80 μm) and sufficiently far apart (80 μm) to be invisible (CERN Courier April 1974 p117). In the final device, a simple lacquer coating prevented the fingers from actually touching the capacitors.

Multi-touch technology began in 1982, when the [[University of Toronto]]'s Input Research Group developed the first human-input multi-touch system. The system used a frosted-glass panel with a camera placed behind the glass. When a finger or several fingers pressed on the glass, the camera would detect the action as one or more black spots on an otherwise white background, allowing it to be registered as an input. Since the size of a dot was dependent on pressure (how hard the person was pressing on the glass), the system was somewhat pressure-sensitive as well.&lt;ref name=buxtonoverview /&gt;

In 1983, [[Bell Labs]] at [[Murray Hill, New Jersey|Murray Hill]] published a comprehensive discussion of touch-screen based interfaces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Nakatani
 | first = L. H., John A Rohrlich
 | title = Soft Machines: A Philosophy of User-Computer Interface Design
 | journal = Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI’83)
 | pages = 12–15
 | year = 1983
 | url = http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/800045.801573
 | accessdate = 2009-01-28
 | doi = 10.1145/800045.801573
 | last2 = Rohrlich
 | first2 = John A. }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1984, Bell Labs engineered a touch screen that could change images with more than one hand. In 1985, the University of Toronto group including [[Bill Buxton]] developed a multi-touch tablet that used capacitance rather than bulky camera-based optical sensing systems.&lt;ref name=buxtonoverview/&gt;

A breakthrough occurred in 1991, when [[Pierre Wellner]] published a paper on his multi-touch “Digital Desk”, which supported multi-finger and pinching motions.&lt;ref&gt;Wellner, Pierre. 1991. The Digital Desk. [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S8lCetZ_57g YouTube video]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wellner:Pierre.html Pierre Wellner's papers] via DBLP&lt;/ref&gt;

Various companies expanded upon these inventions in the beginning of the twenty-first century. The company [[Fingerworks]] developed various multi-touch technologies between 1999 and 2005, including Touchstream keyboards and the iGesture Pad. Several studies of this technology were published in the early 2000s by [[Alan Hedge]], professor of human factors and ergonomics at [[Cornell University]].&lt;ref&gt;Westerman, W., Elias J.G. and A.Hedge (2001) Multi-touch: a new tactile 2-d gesture interface for human-computer interaction Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 45th Annual Meeting, Vol. 1, 632-636.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shanis, J. and Hedge, A. (2003) Comparison of mouse, touchpad and multitouch input technologies. Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 47th Annual Meeting, Oct. 13-17, Denver, CO, 746-750.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thom-Santelli, J. and Hedge, A. (2005) Effects of a multitouch keyboard on wrist posture, typing performance and comfort. Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society 49th Annual Meeting, Orlando, Sept. 26-30, HFES, Santa Monica, 646-650.&lt;/ref&gt; Apple acquired Fingerworks and its multi-touch technology in 2005. Mainstream exposure to multi-touch technology occurred in 2007 when the [[iPhone]] gained popularity, with Apple stating they 'invented multi touch' as part of the iPhone announcement,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |url=http://www.businessinsider.com/and-boy-have-we-patented-it-2010-3 |title=&quot;And Boy Have We Patented It&quot; |date=2006 |people=Steve Jobs |quote=And we have invented a new technology called Multi-touch |accessdate=2010-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; however both the function and the term predate the announcement or patent requests, except for such area of application as capacitive mobile screens, which did not exist before Fingerworks/Apple's technology (Apple filed patents for in 2005-2007 and was awarded with in 2009-2010). Publication and demonstration using the term Multi-touch by [[Jefferson Y. Han]] in 2005 predates these,&lt;ref&gt;Han, J. Y. 2005, but even before than by Fingerworks. Low-Cost Multi-Touch Sensing through Frustrated Total Internal Reflection. In Proceedings of the 18th Annual ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology [http://cs.nyu.edu/~jhan/ftirsense/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt; but Apple did give multi-touch wider exposure through its association with their new product and were the first to introduce multi-touch on a mobile device.&lt;ref&gt;Neumayr, Tom, and Kerris, Natalie, 2007 [http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2007/09/05touch.html &quot;Apple Unveils iPod touch ''Revolutionary Multi-touch Interface &amp; Built-in Wi-Fi Wireless Networking''&quot;] accessdate=21 November 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
Microsoft's table-top touch platform [[Microsoft Surface]], which started development in 2001, interacts with both the users touch and their electronic devices.
Similarly, in 2001, Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL) began development of a multi-touch, multi-user system called [[DiamondTouch]], also based on capacitance but able to differentiate between multiple simultaneous users (or rather, the chairs in which each user is seated or the floorpad the user is standing on); the Diamondtouch became a commercial product in 2008.

Small-scale touch devices are rapidly becoming commonplace, with the number of touch screen telephones expected to increase from 200,000 shipped in 2006 to 21 million in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;Wong, May. 2008. Touch-screen phones poised for growth [http://www.usatoday.com/tech/products/2007-06-21-1895245927_x.htm http://www.usatoday.com/tech/products/2007-06-21-1895245927_x.htm] . Retrieved April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
Recently, Displax unveiled a new approach to multitouch that also detects airflow movement. According to Daniel Wigdor, a user experience architect for Microsoft who focuses on multitouch and gestural computing, “If Displax can do this for larger displays, it will really be one of the first companies to do what we call massive multitouch (...) If you look at existing commercial technology for large touch displays, they use infrared camera that can sense only two to four points of contact. Displax takes us to the next step.&lt;ref name=&quot;www.wired.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2010/02/thin-film-touchscreen/ |title=Displax multitouch technology|publisher=Wired|accessdate=2010-02-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

==Brands and manufacturers==
[[File:Apple iPad Event03.jpg|right|220px|thumb|A virtual keyboard on an [[iPad]]]]
[[Apple Inc.|Apple]] has manufactured numerous products using multi-touch technology; most prominently including its [[iPhone]] smartphone and [[iPad]] tablet. Additionally, Apple also holds several [[patent]]s related to the implementation of multi-touch in user interfaces&lt;ref name=pcmag-applepatent&gt;{{cite web|last=Heater|first=Brian|title=Key Apple Multi-Touch Patent Tech Approved|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2339661,00.asp#fbid=lGomcx1lHVv|work=PCmag.com|accessdate=27 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple additionally attempted to register &quot;Multi-touch&quot; as a [[trademark]] in the United States{{emdash}}however its request was denied by the [[United States Patent and Trademark Office]] because it considered the term [[Genericized trademark|generic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Golson|first=Jordan|title=Apple Denied Trademark for Multi-Touch|url=http://www.macrumors.com/2011/09/26/apple-denied-trademark-for-multi-touch/|publisher=MacRumors|accessdate=27 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Multi-touch sensing and processing occurs via an [[ASIC]] sensor that is attached to the touch surface.  Usually, separate companies make the ASIC and screen that combine into a touch screen; conversely, a trackpad's surface and ASIC are usually manufactured by the same company. There have been large companies in recent years that have expanded into the growing multi-touch industry, with systems designed for everything from the casual user to multinational organizations.

It is now common for laptop manufacturers include multi-touch [[trackpad]]s on their laptops, and [[tablet computer]]s respond to touch input rather than traditional stylus input and it is supported by many recent [[operating system]]s.

A few companies are focusing on large-scale surface computing rather than personal electronics, either large multi-touch tables or wall surfaces. These systems are generally used by government organizations, museums, and companies as a means of information or exhibit display.

==Implementations==
Multi-touch has been implemented in several different ways, depending on the size and type of interface. The most popular form are mobile devices, [[Tablet computer|tablets]], touchtables and walls. Both touchtables and touch walls project an image through acrylic or glass, and then back-light the image with LEDs.

'''Types'''
*[[Multitouch Capacitive Technology]]
**[[Capacitive sensing|Surface Capacitive Technology]]
**[[Touchscreen#Projected_capacitance|Projected Capacitive Touch]] (PST)
**[[In-cell: Capacitive]]
*[[Touch Resistive Technology]]
**[[Resistive touchscreen|Analog Resistive]]
**[[Digital Resistive]] or [[In-Cell: Resistive]]
*[[Multitouch Optical technologies]]
**[[Optical Imaging]] or [[Infrared technology]]
**Rear Diffused Illumination (DI)
**[[Infrared Grid Technology]] (opto-matrix) or [[Digital Waveguide Touch]] (DWT)™ or [[Infrared Optical Waveguide]]
**[[Frustrated Total Internal Reflection]] (FTIR) or [[Diffused Surface Illumination]] (DSI) / [[Dispersive Signal Touch]] (DST)
**[[Kinect]]
**[[In-Cell: Optical]]
*[[Touch Wave Technologies]]
**[[Surface acoustic wave|Surface Acoustic Wave]] (SAW)
**[[Bending Wave Touch]] (BWT)
*[[Force-Based Sensing]] or [[Near Field Imaging]] (NFI)

The optical touch technology functions when a finger or an object touches the surface, causing the light to scatter, the reflection is caught with sensors or cameras that send the data to software which dictates response to the touch, depending on the type of reflection measured. Touch surfaces can also be made pressure-sensitive by the addition of a pressure-sensitive coating that flexes differently depending on how firmly it is pressed, altering the reflection.&lt;ref&gt;Scientific American. 2008. [http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=how-it-works-touch-surfaces-explained &quot;How It Works: Multitouch Surfaces Explained&quot;] . Retrieved January 9, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Handheld technologies use a panel that carries an electrical charge. When a finger touches the screen, the touch disrupts the panel's electrical field. The disruption is registered and sent to the software, which then initiates a response to the gesture.&lt;ref&gt;Brandon, John. 2009. [http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9138644/How_the_iPhone_works &quot;How the iPhone Works]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the past few years, several companies have released products that use multi-touch. In an attempt to make the expensive technology more accessible, hobbyists have also published methods of constructing [[DIY]] touchscreens.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;http://www.humanworkshop.com/index.php?modus=e_zine&amp;sub=articles&amp;item=99 &quot;DIY Multi-touch screen&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Interactive-Globus.jpg|thumb|Multitouch GLOBE (domed monitor) with &quot;Multitouch Earth&quot; application]]

==Popular culture references==
Popular culture has also portrayed potential uses of multi-touch technology in the future, including several installments of the [[Star Trek]] franchise.

The television series ''[[CSI: Miami]]'' introduced both surface and wall multi-touch displays in its sixth season. Another television series, ''[[NCIS: Los Angeles]]'' make use of multitouch surfaces and wall panels as an initiative to go digital. Another form of a multi-touch computer was seen in the film ''[[The Island (2005 film)|The Island]]'', where the professor, played by [[Sean Bean]], has a multi-touch desktop to organize files, based on an early version of Microsoft Surface{{Ref|http://www.istartedsomething.com/20070611/microsoft-surface-the-island/}}. Multitouch technology can also be seen in the [[James Bond (film series)|James Bond]] film ''[[Quantum of Solace]]'', where MI6 uses a touch interface to browse information about the criminal Dominic Greene.&lt;ref&gt;2009. [http://garry.posterous.com/quantum-of-solaces-multitouch-ui-video-wall-g &quot; Quantum of Solace Multitouch UI&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Mypods and Boomsticks|an episode]] of the television series ''[[The Simpsons]]'', when [[Lisa Simpson]] travels to the underwater headquarters of [[Apple Inc.|Mapple]] to visit [[Steve Jobs|Steve Mobs]], the erstwhile pretender to the throne of Mapple is shown to be performing multiple multi-touch hand gestures on a large touch wall.

A device similar to the [[Microsoft Surface|Surface]] was seen in the 1982 film ''[[Tron (film)|Tron]]''. It took up an executive's entire desk and was used to communicate with the [[Master Control Program|Master Control computer]].

The interface used to control the alien ship in the movie ''[[District 9]]'' features such similar technology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YZoa1jHSpBw &quot;District 9 - Ship UI &quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Microsoft's Surface was also used in the film ''[[The Day the Earth Stood Still (2008 film)|The Day the Earth Stood Still]]''.

In the film ''[[Minority Report (film)|Minority Report]]'', Tom Cruise uses a set of gloves that resemble a multi-touch interface to browse through information.&lt;ref&gt;http://gizmodo.com/229464/minority-report-touch-interface-for-real&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of multi-touch computers and monitors]]
* [[Gesture recognition]]
* [[Human-Computer Interaction]]
* [[Pen computing]]
* [[Multi-touch gestures]]
* [[Natural User Interface]]
* [[Sketch recognition]]
* [[Surface Computing]]
* [[Tenori-on]]
* [[Touchpad]]
* [[Touch user interface]]
* [[Sensomusic_Usine]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mNfSHm3qDGM Video Demo Of FTIR using Touchscape Components]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_ZVkx31ScZA Video showing the construction of a simple optical touchscreen (&quot;TTable&quot;)]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yktleaoFYtI here is OmniGlobe Spherical Interactive (Multi touch) Display System]
* [http://www.billbuxton.com/multitouchOverview.html Multi-Touch Systems that I Have Known and Loved] – An overview by researcher Bill Buxton of Microsoft Research, formerly at University of Toronto and Xerox PARC.
*[http://users.erols.com/rwservices/pens/penhist.html The Unknown History of Pen Computing] contains a history of pen computing, including touch and gesture technology, from approximately 1917 to 1992.
*[http://rwservices.no-ip.info:81/biblio.html Annotated bibliography of references to pen computing]
* [http://gkos.com/ Multi-touch Chordic Keyboard for iPhone and Android]
* [http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=yrQR2vhd3P4 Multi-touch in Windows 7]
* [http://cs.nyu.edu/~jhan/ftirtouch/ Multi-Touch Interaction Research @ NYU]
*[http://www.cs.uit.no/~daniels/multi-touch/index.html Camera-based multi-touch for wall-sized displays]
*[http://cnmat.berkeley.edu/system/files/attachments/p41-wessel.pdf David Wessel Multitouch]
*[http://www.vimeo.com/6866296 The Virtual Autopsy Table]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IHKpzUI23dU&amp;feature=related Video of Humanaquarium at makers faire using touchscape components]
*[http://multi-touchscreen.com/ Jeff Han's Multi Touch Screen's chronology archive] Debut from 7 Mar 2006 to present
* [http://www.grayr.ru/ MultiTouch Forever Group (MTFG)] by SnickerDudle

{{DEFAULTSORT:Multi-Touch}}
[[Category:Touch user interfaces]]
[[Category:Multi-touch| ]]
[[Category:User interface techniques]]

[[ar:لمس متعدد]]
[[ca:Multi-touch]]
[[cs:Vícedotykové ovládání]]
[[da:Multi-touch]]
[[de:Multi-Touch-Screen]]
[[es:Multitáctil]]
[[fa:چندلمسی]]
[[fr:Multi-touch]]
[[ko:멀티터치]]
[[is:Fjölsnertiskjár]]
[[it:Multi-touch]]
[[nl:Multi-touchscherm]]
[[no:Multitouch]]
[[pl:Multi-Touch]]
[[pt:Ecrã multitáctil]]
[[ro:Multi-touch]]
[[ru:Мультитач]]
[[sk:Viacdotykové ovládanie]]
[[sv:Multi-touch]]
[[ta:பல்முனைத் தொடு இடைமுகம்]]
[[tr:Multi-touch]]
[[uk:Multitouch]]
[[zh:多點觸控]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
