<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="886313" ns="0" title="Underground press"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=October 2010}}
[[File:Oz-33-cover.jpg|thumb|''[[Oz (magazine)|Oz]]'' magazine, number 33]]
The '''underground press''' were the independently published and distributed '''underground papers''' associated with the [[counterculture]] of the late 1960s and early 1970s in the [[United States]], [[Canada]], [[United Kingdom]], and other western nations.

The term &quot;underground press&quot; is also used to refer to illegal publications under oppressive regimes, for example, the ''[[samizdat]]'' and ''[[Polish underground press|bibuła]]'' in the [[Soviet Union]] and [[Poland]] respectively.

==Origins==
This movement borrowed the name from previous &quot;underground presses&quot; such as the [[Dutch underground press]] during the [[Nazism|Nazi]] occupations of the 1940s. The [[French resistance]] published a large and active underground press that printed over 2 million newspapers a month; the leading titles were ''[[Combat (newspaper)|Combat]]'', ''[[Libération-Sud|Libération]]'', ''[[Défense de la France]]'', and ''[[Franc-Tireur (movement)|Le Franc-Tireur]].'' Each paper was the organ of a separate resistance network, and funds were provided from Allied headquarters in London and distributed to the different papers by resistance leader [[Jean Moulin]].&lt;ref&gt;''The French Resistance'' by Raymond Aubrac (Paris: Hazan, 1997), p. 18-32.&lt;/ref&gt; Allied [[prisoners of war]] (POWs) published an underground newspaper called ''Pow wow''. In [[Eastern Europe]], also since approximately the 1940, underground publications were known by the name ''[[samizdat]]''. Those predecessors were truly &quot;underground,&quot; meaning they were illegal, thus published and distributed covertly. While the countercultural &quot;underground&quot; papers frequently battled with governmental authorities, for the most part they were distributed openly through a network of street vendors, newsstands and [[head shop]]s, and thus reached a wide audience.

The underground press in the 1960s and 1970s existed in most countries with high GDP per capita and [[freedom of the press]]; similar publications existed in some developing countries and as part of the ''samizdat'' movement in the [[communist state]]s, notably [[Czechoslovakia]]. Published as weeklies, monthlies, or &quot;occasionals&quot;, and usually associated with [[left-wing politics]], they evolved on the one hand into today's [[alternative weekly|alternative weeklies]] and on the other into [[zine]]s.

==In the United Kingdom==
In [[London]], [[Barry Miles]], [[John Hopkins (political activist)|John Hopkins]] and others produced ''[[International Times]]'' which, following legal threats from ''The Times'' newspaper was renamed ''IT''.

[[Richard Neville (writer)|Richard Neville]] arrived in London from Australia where he had edited ''Oz'' (1963 to 1969). He launched a British version (1967 to 1973), which was [[ISO 216|A4]] (as opposed to ''IT''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s broadsheet format). Very quickly, the relaunched ''Oz'' shed its more austere satire magazine image and became a mouthpiece of the Underground. It was the most colourful and visually adventurous of the alternative press (sometimes to the point of near-illegibility), with designers like Martin Sharp. Other publications followed, such as ''[[Friends (Radical Magazine)|Friends]]'' (later ''Frendz''), based in the [[Ladbroke Grove]] area of [[London]], ''[[Ink (underground paper)|Ink]]'', which was more overtly political, and ''[[Gandalf's Garden]]'' which espoused the mystic path. 

Neville published an account of the [[counterculture]] called ''Playpower'', in which he described most of the world's underground publications. He also listed many of the regular key topics from those publications including Vietnam, Black Power, Politics, Police Brutality, Hippies &amp; Lifestyle Revolution, Drugs, Popular Music, New Society, Cinema, Theatre, Graphics, Cartoons etc.

The underground press offered a platform to the socially impotent and mirrored the changing way of life in the [[UK underground]].

Police harassment of the British underground in general became commonplace, to the point that in 1967 the police seemed to focus in particular on the apparent source of agitation: the underground press. The police campaign may have had an effect contrary to that which was presumably intended. If anything, according to one or two who were there at the time, it actually made the underground press stronger. &quot;It focused attention, stiffened resolve, and tended to confirm that what we were doing was considered dangerous to the establishment&quot;, remembered [[Mick Farren]]. [http://www.thanatosoft.freeserve.co.uk/undergroundfiles/interview.htm] From April 1967, and for some while later, the police raided the offices of ''International Times'' to try, it was alleged, to force the paper out of business. In order to raise money for ''IT'' a benefit event was put together, &quot;The 14 Hour Technicolor Dream&quot; [[Alexandra Palace]] on 29 April, 1967. 

On one occasion - in the wake of yet another raid on ''IT'' - London's alternative press, somewhat astonishingly, succeeded in pulling off what was billed as a 'reprisal attack' on the police. The paper ''Black Dwarf'' published a detailed floor-by-floor 'Guide to [[Scotland Yard]],' complete with diagrams, descriptions of locks on particular doors, and snippets of overheard conversation. The anonymous author, or 'blue dwarf,' as he styled himself,' claimed to have perused archive files, and even to have sampled one or two brands of scotch in the Commissioner's office. The London ''[[Evening Standard]]'' headlined the incident as &quot;Raid on the Yard&quot;. A day or two later ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' announced that the prank had resulted in all security passes to the police headquarters having to be withdrawn and then re-issued.

By the end of the decade, community artists and bands such as [[Pink Floyd]], (before they &quot;went commercial&quot;), the [[The Deviants (band)|The Deviants]], [[Pink Fairies]], [[Hawkwind]], [[Michael Moorcock]] and [[Steve Peregrin Took]] would arise in a symbiotic co-operation with the underground press. The underground press publicised these bands and this made it possible for them to tour and get record deals. The band members travelled around spreading the ethos and the demand for the newspapers and magazines grew and flourished for a while. 

The flaunting of sexuality within the underground press provoked prosecution. ''IT'' was taken to court for publishing small ads for [[homosexuality|homosexuals]]; despite the 1967 [[Sexual Offences Act 1967|legalisation]] of homosexuality between consenting adults in private importuning remained subject to prosecution. The ''Oz'' &quot;School Kids&quot; issue, brought charges against the three ''Oz'' editors who were convicted and given jail sentences. This was the first time the [[Obscene Publications Act 1959]] was combined with a moral conspiracy charge. The convictions were, however, overturned on appeal.

===Local papers===
Apart from publications such as ''IT'' and ''Oz'', both of which had a national circulation, the 1960s and ‘70s saw the emergence of a whole range of local alternative newspapers, which were usually published monthly. These were largely made possible by the introduction in the 1950s of [[Photolithography|offset litho printing]], which was much cheaper than traditional typesetting and use of the rotary letterpress.  Such local papers included ''Aberdeen Peoples Press'', ''Alarm'' (Swansea), ''Andersonstown News'' (Belfast), ''[[Brighton Voice]]'', ''Bristol Voice'', ''Feedback'' (Norwich), ''Hackney People’s Press'', ''Islington Gutter Press'', ''Leeds Other Paper'', ''Response'' (Earl’s Court, London), ''Sheffield Free Press'', and the ''West Highland Free Press''. A 1980 review identified some 70 such publications around the United Kingdom but estimated that the true number could well have run into hundreds.&lt;ref&gt;Crispin Aubrey, Charles Landry, Dave Morley,  Here is the other news: challenges to the local commercial press, p.13  Minority Press Group, 1980&lt;/ref&gt; Such papers were usually published anonymously, for fear of the UK's draconian libel laws. They followed a broad [[Anarchism|anarchist]], [[Libertarianism|libertarian]], left-wing of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], socialist approach but the philosophy of a paper was usually flexible as those responsible for its production came and went. Most papers were run on [[collective]] principles.

===List of UK underground papers===
* ''[[Peace News]]''
* ''[[International Times]]'' (also ''IT'')
* ''[[Oz (magazine)|Oz]]''
* ''[[Gandalf's Garden]]''
* ''[[Heatwave (magazine)|Heatwave]]''
* ''[[The Black Dwarf (newspaper)|Black Dwarf]]''
* ''[[Idiot International]]''
* ''[[Friends (Radical Magazine)|Friends]]'' (later ''Frendz'')
* ''[[Gay News]]''
* ''[[Spare Rib]]''
* ''[[The Fanatic]]''
* ''[[The Leveller]]''
* ''[[Ink (underground paper)|Ink]]''
* '' Running Man''
* ''[[Brighton Voice]]''
* ''[[The Caterpillar - A Visionary Ghetto Tabloid]]''

==In North America==

In the United States, the term ''underground'' did not mean ''illegal'' as it would in other countries. The [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] and various court decisions (e.g. ''[[Near v. Minnesota]]'') give very broad rights to anyone to publish a newspaper or other publication, and severely restrict the government in any effort to close down or censor a private publication. In fact, when censorship attempts are made by government agencies, they are either done in clandestine fashion (to keep it from being known the action is being taken by a government agency) or are usually ordered stopped by the courts when judicial action is taken in response to them. A publication must, in general, be committing a crime (for example, reporters burglarizing someone's office to obtain information about a news item); violating the law in publishing a particular article or issue (printing obscene material, copyright infringement, libel, breaking a non-disclosure agreement); directly threatening national security; or causing or potentially causing an imminent [[emergency]] (the &quot;[[clear and present danger]]&quot; standard) to be ordered stopped or otherwise suppressed, and then usually only the particular offending article or articles in question will be banned, while the newspaper itself is allowed to continue operating and can continue publishing other articles.

In the U.S. the term ''underground newspaper'' generally refers to an independent (and typically smaller) newspaper focusing on unpopular themes or counterculture issues. Typically, these tend to be politically to the left or far left. More narrowly, in the US the term &quot;underground newspaper&quot; most often refers to publications of the period 1965-1973, when a sort of boom or craze for local tabloid underground newspapers swept the country in the wake of court decisions making prosecution for obscenity far more difficult. These publications became the voice of the rising [[New Left]] and the hippie/psychedelic/rock and roll counterculture of the 1960s in America, and a focal point of opposition to the Vietnam War and the draft. In the period 1969-1970 a number of these papers grew more militant and began to openly discuss armed revolution against the state, printing manuals for bombing and urging readers to buy guns; but this trend of the previously pacifistic underground press toward violent confrontation soon fell silent after the brief, farcical rise and fall of the [[Weatherman Underground]] and the tragic shootings at [[Kent State shootings|Kent State]]. A number of papers passed out of existence at this time; among the survivors a new trend toward middle-class values and working within the system emerged, and the underground press began to evolve into the more moderate, life-style oriented &quot;alternative press.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Peck, Abe. ''Uncovering the Sixties'' (New York: Pantheon Books, 1985).&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973 the landmark Supreme Court decision in ''[[Miller v. California]]'' which re-enabled local obscenity prosecutions after a long hiatus sounded the death knell for much of the remaining underground press (including [[underground comix]]), largely by making the local [[head shop]]s which stocked underground papers and comix in communities around the country more vulnerable to prosecution.

The North American countercultural press of the 1960s drew inspiration from predecessors that had begun in the 1950s, such as the ''[[Village Voice]]'' and [[Paul Krassner|Paul Krassner's]] satirical paper ''[[The Realist]].'' Arguably, the first underground newspaper of the 1960s was the ''[[Los Angeles Free Press]]'', founded in 1964 and first published under that name in 1965. In mid-1966, the cooperative [[Underground Press Syndicate]] (UPS) was formed at the instigation of Walter Bowart, the publisher of another early paper, the ''[[East Village Other]]''. The UPS allowed member papers to freely reprint content from any of the other member papers. One of the most notorious underground newspapers to join UPS and rallied activists, poets, and artists by giving them uncensored voice was the ''[[NOLA Express]]'' in New Orleans. Started by Robert Head and Darlene Fife as part of political protests and extending the &quot;mimeo revolution&quot; by protest and freedom-of-speech poets during the 1960s, ''NOLA Express'' was also a member of COSMEP (Committee of Small Magazine Editors and Publishers. These two affiliations with organizations that were often at cross purposes made ''NOLA Express'' one of the most radical and controversial publications of the counterculture movement.&lt;ref&gt;Fife, Darlene. ''Portraits from Memory: New Orleans in the Sixties.'' New Orleans: Surregional Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Part of the controversy about ''NOLA Express'' included graphic photographs and illustrations of which many even in today's society would be banned as pornographic. 

[[Charles Bukowski]]'s syndicated column, ''Notes of a Dirty Old Man,'' ran in ''NOLA Express'', and Franciso McBride's illustration for the story &quot;The Fuck Machine&quot; was considered sexist, pornographic, and created an uproar. All of this controversy helped to increase the readership and bring attention to the political causes that editors Fife and Head supported.&lt;ref&gt;Illustration. Fife, Darlene. ''Portraits from Memory: New Orleans in the Sixties.'' New Orleans: Surregional Press, 2000, pg. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other prominent underground papers included the ''[[San Francisco Oracle]],'' ''[[San Francisco Express Times]]'', the ''[[Berkeley Barb]]'' and ''[[Berkeley Tribe]]''; ''[[Open City (newspaper)|Open City]]'', ([[Los Angeles]]), ''[[Fifth Estate]]'' ([[Detroit]]), ''[[Other Scenes]]'' (dispatched from various locations around the world by [[John Wilcock]]); ''[[Helix (newspaper)|The Helix]]'' ([[Seattle]]); ''[[Avatar (newspaper)|Avatar]]'' ([[Boston]]); ''The [[Chicago Seed]]''; ''[[The Great Speckled Bird (newspaper)|The Great Speckled Bird]]'' ([[Atlanta]]); ''[[The Rag]]'' ([[Austin, Texas]]); ''[[Rat Subterranean News|Rat]]'' ([[New York City]]); and in [[Canada]], ''[[The Georgia Straight]]'' ([[Vancouver]], BC). By 1969, virtually every sizable city or college town in North America boasted at least one underground newspaper. During the peak years of the underground press phenomenon there were generally about 100 papers currently publishing at any given time. 

''[[The Rag]]'', founded in Austin, Texas, in 1966 by [[Thorne Dreyer]] and Carol Neiman, was especially influential and, according to historian John McMillian, was a model for many papers that followed.&lt;ref&gt;McMillian, John. ''The Underground Press in America'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; It was the sixth member of UPS and the first underground paper in the South and, according to Abe Peck, it was the &quot;first undergrounder to represent the participatory democracy, community organizing and synthesis of politics and culture that the New Left of the midsixties was trying to develop.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Peck, Abe. ''Uncovering the Sixties'' (New York: Pantheon Books, 1985).&lt;/ref&gt;

During this period was also a widespread high school underground press movement circulating unauthorized student-published mimeographed sheets at hundreds of high schools around the US. Most of these papers put out only a few issues, running off a few hundred copies of each and circulating them only at one local school, although there was one system-wide antiwar high school underground paper produced in New York in 1969 with a 10,000 copy press run. For a time in 1968-1969 the high school underground press had its own press services, FRED (run by [[C. Clark Kissinger|Clark Kissinger]] of SDS, with its base in Chicago schools) and HIPS (High School Independent Press Service, produced by students working out of [[Liberation News Service]] headquarters and aimed primarily but not exclusively at New York City schools). These services typically produced a weekly packet of articles and features mailed to subscribing papers around the country; HIPS reported 60 subscribing papers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hippy.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=331 &quot;Revolt in the High Schools&quot;] by Diane Divovky, ''Saturday Review'', Feb. 15, 1969, p. 83-84 et seq. Retrieved Jan. 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1968 a survey of 400 high schools in Southern California found that 52% reported student underground press activity in their school.&lt;ref&gt;Glessing, Robert. ''The Underground Press in America'' (Indiana University Press, 1970).&lt;/ref&gt;

The GI underground press in America produced a few hundred titles during the Vietnam War, some produced by antiwar GI coffeehouses, and many of them small, crudely produced, low-circulation mimeographed &quot;zines&quot; written by a draftee editor opposed to the war and circulated locally off-base. Three or four GI underground papers had large-scale, national distribution of more than 20,000 copies including thousands of copies mailed to GIs overseas. These papers were produced with the support of civilian anti-war activists, and had to be disguised to be sent through the mail into Vietnam, where soldiers distributing or even possessing them might be subject to harassment, disciplinary action or arrest. The idea of smuggling a full size printing press into South Vietnam was mooted but determined to be too dangerous to attempt. As an alternative, a few GIs based in South Vietnam were issued small kits to enable them to produce little [[hektograph]]-type zines.

The boom in the underground press was made practical by the availability of cheap offset printing, which made it possible to print a few thousand copies of a small tabloid paper for a couple of hundred dollars, which a sympathetic printer might extend on credit. Paper was cheap, and many printing firms around the country had over-expanded during the 1950s and had excess capacity on their offset web presses, which could be negotiated for at bargain rates.&lt;ref&gt;Glessing, Robert. ''The Underground Press in America'' (Indiana University Press, 1970), p.44. Glessing pins the blame specifically on the Miehle-Goss-Dexter firm, which waged a successful sales campaign in the late 1950s to sell its expensive new high-capacity web-fed offset presses (a full installation cost $100,000) on credit to small newspapers and printing firms across the country which couldn't quite afford them.&lt;/ref&gt;  Most papers operated on a shoestring budget, pasting up camera-ready copy on layout sheets on the editor's kitchen table, with labor performed by unpaid, non-union volunteers. Typesetting costs, which at the time were wiping out many established big city papers, were avoided by typing up copy on a rented or borrowed IBM Selectric typewriter to be pasted up by hand. As one observer commented with only slight hyperbole, students were financing the publication of these papers out of their lunch money.

The underground press phenomenon proved short-lived. By 1973, many underground papers had folded, at which point the Underground Press Syndicate acknowledged the passing of the undergrounds and renamed itself the Alternative Press Syndicate. That organization soon collapsed, to be supplanted by the [[Association of Alternative Newsweeklies]].

During the 1960s and 1970s, there were also a number of [[Alternative press (U.S. political left)|left political periodicals]] with some of the same concerns of the underground press. Some of these periodicals joined the Underground Press Syndicate to gain services such as microfilming, advertising, and the free exchange of articles and newspapers. Examples include ''[[The Black Panther (newspaper)|The Black Panther]]'' (the paper of the [[Black Panther Party]], [[Oakland, California]]), and the ''[[Guardian (US)|Guardian]]'', New York City; both of which had national distribution. The U.S. [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI) conducted surveillance and disruption activities on the underground press in the United States, including a campaign to destroy the [[News agency (alternative)|alternative agency]] [[Liberation News Service]]. As part of its [[COINTELPRO]] designed to discredit and infiltrate radical New Left groups, the FBI also launched phony underground newspapers such as the ''Armageddon News'' at [[Indiana University Bloomington]], ''The Longhorn Tale'' at the [[University of Texas at Austin]], and the ''Rational Observer'' at [[American University]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] The FBI also ran the Pacific International News Service in San Francisco, the Chicago Midwest News, and the New York Press Service. Many of these organizations consisted of little more than a post office box and a letterhead, designed to enable the FBI to receive exchange copies of underground press publications and send undercover observers to underground press gatherings.

''[[The Georgia Straight]]'' outlived the underground movement, evolving into an [[alternative weekly]] still published today; ''Fifth Estate'' survives as an [[anarchism|anarchist]] magazine. Most others died with the era. Given the nature of alternative journalism as a subculture, some staff members from underground newspapers became staff on the newer alternative weeklies, even though there was seldom institutional continuity with management or ownership. An example is the transition in Denver from the underground ''[[Chinook (newspaper)|Chinook]]'', to ''[[Chinook (newspaper)|Straight Creek Journal]]'', to ''[[Westword]]'' [http://www.westword.com], an alternative weekly still in publication. Some underground and alternative reporters, cartoonists, and artists moved on to work in corporate media or in academia.

[[Ray Mungo]], in his classic account of the American underground press, ''Famous Long Ago'', gave a cynical account of the origins of the typical underground newspaper: &quot;Lots of radicals will give you a very precise line about why their little newspaper was started and what needs it fulfills and most of that stuff is bull. You see, the point is they've got nothing to do and the prospect of holding a straight job is so dreary that they join 'the movement' and start hitting up people for money to live, on the premise that they're involved in critical social change blah blah blah.&quot; 

===List of U.S. underground papers===
* ''[[Amazing Grace (newspaper)|Amazing Grace]]'', [[Tallahassee, Florida]]
* ''[[Ann Arbor Argus]]'', [[Ann Arbor, Michigan]], [[1969]]-[[1971]]
* &quot;[[Ann Arbor Sun]]&quot;, [[Ann Arbor, Michigan]], [[1971]]-[[1976]]
* ''[[North Carolina Anvil|The Anvil]]'', [[Durham, North Carolina]], [[1967]]-[[1983]]
* ''[[Astral Projection (newspaper)|Astral Projection]]'', [[Albuquerque, NM]]
* ''[[Avatar (newspaper)|Avatar]]'', [[Boston, Massachusetts]], [[1967]]-[[1968]]
* ''[[Baltimore Free Press]]'', [[Baltimore, Maryland]]
* ''[[Berkeley Barb]]'', [[Berkeley, California]], [[1965]]-[[1980]]
* ''[[Berkeley Tribe]]'', [[Berkeley, California]], [[1969]]-[[1972]] (splintered from the ''Barb'')
* ''[[The Big Us]]'', [[Cleveland, Ohio]], [[1968]]-[[1970]] (changed name to ''Burning River News'')
* ''[[The Black Panther (newspaper)|The Black Panther]]'', [[Oakland, California]]
* ''[[Borrowed Times]]'', [[Missoula, Montana]]
* ''[[Boston Free Press]]'', [[Boston, MA]]
* ''[[Bugle (newspaper)|Bugle-American]]'', [[Milwaukee, Wisconsin]], [[1970]]-[[1978]]
* ''[[Butterfield Express]]'', [[Tucson, Arizona]]
* ''[[Chicago Seed (newspaper)|Chicago Seed]]'', [[Chicago, Illinois]], [[1967]]-[[1973]]
* ''[[Chinook (newspaper)|Chinook]]'', [[Denver, Colorado]], [[1969]]-[[1972]]
* ''[[Columbus Free Press]]'', [[Columbus, Ohio]], [[1969]]-[[ongoing]]
* ''[[Connections (newspaper)|Connections]]'', [[Madison, Wisconsin]]
* ''[[Daily Flash]]'', [[St. Louis, Missouri]] (changed name to ''Xanadu'')
* ''[[Daily Planet (newspaper)|Daily Planet]]'', [[Miami, Florida]]
* ''[[Dallas Notes]]'', [[Dallas, Texas]], [[1967]]-[[1970]] (originally ''Notes from the Underground'')
* ''[[Distant Drummer]]'', [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], [[1967]]-[[1979]] (changed name to ''The Drummer'')
* ''[[Dock of the Bay (newspaper)|Dock of the Bay]]'', [[San Francisco, California]]
* ''[[East Village Other]]'', [[New York, New York]], [[1965]]-[[1972]]
* ''[[Eugene Augur]]'', [[Eugene, Oregon]], [[1969]]-[[1974]]
* ''[[Extra (newspaper)|Extra]]'', [[Providence, Rhode Island]]
* ''[[Fifth Estate (periodical)|Fifth Estate]]'', [[Detroit, Michigan]], [[1965]]-[[ongoing]]
* ''[[Fountain of Light (newspaper)|Fountain of Light]]'', [[Taos, NM]], [[1968]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Free Press of Louisville]]'', [[Louisville, Kentucky]]
* ''[[From Out of Sherwood Forest]]'', [[Newport Beach, California]]
* ''[[Gulf Coast Fish Cheer (newspaper)|Fish Cheer]]'', [[Pensacola, Florida]]
* ''[[The Great Speckled Bird (newspaper)|The Great Speckled Bird]]'', [[Atlanta, Georgia]], [[1968]]-[[1976]]
* ''[[San Francisco Express Times|Good Times]]'', [[San Francisco, California]], [[1969]]-[[1972]] (formerly ''San Francisco Express-Times)
* ''[[Grinding Stone (newspaper)|Grinding Stone]]'', [[Terre Haute, Indiana]]
* ''[[Harry (newspaper)|Harry]]'', [[Baltimore, Maryland]], [[1969]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Helix (newspaper)|Helix]]'', [[Seattle, Washington]], [[1967]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Hundred Flowers (newspaper)|Hundred Flowers]]'', [[Minneapolis, Minnesota]], [[1970]]-[[1972]]
* ''[[Illustrated Paper]]'', [[Mendocino, California]], [[1966]]-[[1967]]
* ''[[Independent Eye]]'', [[Cincinnati, Ohio]]
* ''[[Indianapolis Free Press]]'', [[Indianapolis, Indiana]]
* ''[[The Inquisition (underground newspaper)|The Inquisition]]'', [[Charlotte, North Carolina]]
* ''[[Kaleidoscope (newspaper)|Kaleidoscope]]'', [[Milwaukee, Wisconsin]], [[1967]]-[[1971]]
* ''[[Kudzu (newspaper)|Kudzu]]'', [[Jackson, Mississippi]], [[1968]]-[[1972]]
* [[Liberation News Service]], [[New York, New York]] (original headquarters)
* ''[[The Last Times]]'', [[San Francisco, California]], [[1967]] (Charles Plymell)
* ''[[Los Angeles Free Press]]'', [[Los Angeles, California]], [[1964]]-[[1978]] (new series 2005–ongoing)
* ''[[Los Angeles Staff]]'', [[Los Angeles, California]] (splintered from the ''Free Press'')
* ''[[Love (newspaper)|Love]]'', [[Reno, Nevada]]
* ''[[Madison Kaleidoscope]]'', [[Madison, Wisconsin]]
* ''[[Middle Earth (newspaper)|Middle Earth]]'', [[Iowa City, IA]], [[1967]]-[[1968]]
* ''[[The Monocle]]'', [[Tampa, Florida]]
* ''[[Mother of Voices]]'', [[Amherst, Massachusetts]]
* ''[[Mountain Free Press]]'', [[Denver, Colorado]], [[1968]]-[[1969]]
* ''[[New Age (underground newspaper)|New Age]]'', [[Athens, Ohio]]
* ''[[New York Ace]]'', [[New York, NY]], [[1971]]-[[1972]]
* ''[[NOLA Express]]'', [[New Orleans, Louisiana]]
* ''[[Northwest Passage (newspaper)|Northwest Passage]]'', [[Bellingham, WA]], [[1969]]-[[1986]]
* ''[[Old Mole]]'', [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], [[1968]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Omaha Kaleidoscope]]'', [[Omaha, Nebraska]]
* ''[[Open City (newspaper)|Open City]]'', [[Los Angeles, California]], [[1967]]-[[1969]]
* ''[[Oracle of Southern California]]'', [[Los Angeles, California]]
* ''[[The Organ (newspaper)|The Organ]]'', [[San Francisco, California]], [[1970]]-[[1971]]
* ''[[Other Scenes]]'' (dispatched from various locations around the world)
* ''[[The Paper (newspaper)|The Paper]]'', [[East Lansing, Michigan]]
* ''[[Peninsula Observer]]'', [[Palo Alto, California]], [[1967]]-[[1969]] (formerly ''Midpeninsula Observer)
* ''[[Philadelphia Free Press]]'', [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], [[1968]]-[[1972]]
* ''[[Pittsburgh Fair Witness]]'', [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]], [[1970]]-[[1973]] (formerly ''Grok'')
* ''[[Queen City Express]]'', [[Cincinnati, Ohio]]
* ''[[Quicksilver Times]]'', [[Washington, DC]], [[1969]]-[[1972]]
* ''[[The Rag]]'', [[Austin, Texas]], [[1966]]-[[1977]]
* ''[[Rat Subterranean News]]'', [[New York, New York]], [[1968]]-[[1970]] (later ''Women's LibeRATion'')
* ''[[Razzberry Radicle]]'', [[Dayton, Ohio]]
* ''[[The Realist]]''
* ''[[Rebirth (newspaper)|Rebirth]]'', [[Phoenix, Arizona]], [[1969]]
* ''[[Richmond Chronicle (underground newspaper)|Richmond Chronicle]]'', [[Richmond, Virginia]]
* ''[[Rising Up Angry]]'', [[Chicago, Illinois]], [[1969]]-[[1975]]
* ''[[Root (newspaper)|Root]], [[Memphis, Tennessee]]
* ''[[Sabot (newspaper)|Sabot]]'', [[Seattle, Washington]], [[1970]]-[[1971]]
* ''[[The San Diego Door|San Diego Door]]'', [[San Diego, California]], [[1966]]-[[1970]] (formerly ''Good Morning, Teaspoon'')
* ''[[San Diego Free Press]]'', [[San Diego, California]] [[1968]]-[[1970]] (changed name to ''Street Journal'')
* ''[[San Francisco Oracle]]'', [[San Francisco, California]], [[1966]]-[[1968]]
* ''[[San Francisco Express Times]]'', [[San Francisco, California]], [[1968]]-[[1969]] (changed name to ''Good Times'')
* ''[[San Jose Maverick]]'', [[San Jose, California]], [[1969]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Second City (newspaper)|Second City]]'', [[Chicago, Illinois]]
* ''[[Space City (newspaper)|Space City]]'', [[Houston, Texas]], [[1969]]-[[1972]] (originally ''Space City News'')
* ''[[Spectator (underground newspaper)|The Spectator]]'', [[Bloomington, Indiana]]
* ''[[Spokane Natural]]'', [[Spokane, Washington]], [[1967]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Tuesday's Child (newspaper)|Tuesday's Child]]'', [[Los Angeles, California]], [[1969]]-[[1970]]
* [[Underground Press Syndicate]] (UPS)
* ''[[The Ungarbled Word]]'', [[New Orleans, Louisiana]]
* ''[[View from the Bottom]]'', [[New Haven, Connecticut]], [[1969]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Vortex (newspaper)|Vortex]]'', [[Lawrence, Kansas]], [[1969]]-[[1970]]
* ''[[Washington Free Press]]'', [[Washington, DC]]
* ''[[Willamette Bridge]]'', [[Portland, Oregon]], [[1968]]-[[1971]]
* ''[[Women's LibeRATion (newspaper)|Women's LibeRATion]]'', [[New York City]]
* ''[[Yarrowstalks]]'', [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], [[1967]]

===List of US military GI underground press===

* ''[[The Ally (newspaper)|The Ally]]'', [[New York City, New York]]
* ''[[The Bond (newspaper)|The Bond]]'', [[Berkeley, California]]
* ''[[F.T.A. (newspaper)|F.T.A.]]'', [[Fort Knox, Kentucky]]
* ''[[Jeff Sharlet (Vietnam antiwar activist)|Vietnam GI]]'', [[Chicago, Illinois]], [[1968]]-[[1969]] 

===List of Canadian underground papers===
* ''[[Canada Goose (newspaper)|Canada Goose]]'', [[Edmonton, Alberta]]
* ''[[The Chevron]]'',  [[University of Waterloo]], [[Ontario, Canada]]
* ''[[The Georgia Straight]]'', [[Vancouver, Canada]]
* ''[[Harbinger (Toronto newspaper)|Harbinger]]'', [[Toronto, Ontario]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sources.com&quot;&gt;http://www.sources.com/ssr/Docs/SSR22-1-BritPress.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Logos (Montréal newspaper)|Logos]]'', [[Montréal, Québec]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sources.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/bandes-dessinees/027002-8500-f.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Loving Couch Press]]'', [[Winnipeg, Manitoba]]
* ''[[Octopus (newspaper)|Octopus]]'', [[Ottawa, Ontario]] (aka ''Canadian Free Press'', ''Ottawa's Free Press'')
* ''[[Pop-See-Cul]]'', [[Montréal, Quebec]]

==In Australia==
The most prominent underground publication in Australia was a satirical magazine called ''[[Oz (magazine)|Oz]]'' (1963 to 1969), which owed an obvious debt to the UK magazine ''[[Private Eye]]''. The original Australian edition appeared in 1963 and it continued sporadically until 1969. The Australian editions published after 1966 were edited by [[Richard Walsh]], following the departure for the UK of his original co-editors [[Richard Neville (writer)|Richard Neville]] and [[Martin Sharp]], who founded the British edition (&quot;London Oz&quot;) in 1967.

===List of Australian underground papers===
* ''[[The Digger (Australian magazine)|The Digger]]'' (1972-75)
* ''[[The Living Daylights (Australian magazine)|The Living Daylights]]'' (early 1970s)
* [[New Dawn (magazine)]]
* [[Nexus (magazine)]]

===List of Italian underground papers===
* [[:it:Fuori!|Fuori!]] ([[:it:Torino|Turin]]) 
* [[:it:Re Nudo|Re Nudo]]  ([[:it:Milano|Milan]])
* [[:it:Tampax (rivista ed editrice)|Tampax]]  ([[:it:Torino|Turin]])

==See also==
* [[Alternative press (U.S. political left)]]
* [[Alternative press (U.S. political right)]]
* [[Alternative media]]
* [[:it:Marcello Baraghini|Marcello Baraghini (italian alternative editor)]]
* [[List of underground newspapers]] (by country and state)
* [[News agency (alternative)]]
* [[UK Underground]]
* [[French resistance]]
* [[Jeff Sharlet (Vietnam antiwar activist)]]
* [[:it:Giulio Tedeschi|Giulio Tedeschi (Italian underground activist)]]
* [[:it:Andrea Valcarenghi|Andrea Valcarenghi (Co-editor italian Re Nudo)]]

==References==
* [http://www.thanatosoft.freeserve.co.uk/undergroundfiles/interview.htm Funtopia] Retrieved Aug. 8, 2004
* [http://www.azenphonypress.com/books/voices1_tcontent.html ''Voices from the Underground (Vol. 1): Insider Histories of the Vietnam Era Underground Press'']
* [http://www.azenphonypress.com/books/voices2.html ''Voices from the Underground (Vol. 2): A Directory of Resources and Sources on the Vietnam Era Underground Press'']
* Abe Peck. ''Uncovering the Sixties:The Life and Times of the Underground Press'' (New York: Citadel) 1991.
* [http://www.nuevoanden.com/rag/newmedia.html Dreyer, Thorne and Victoria Smith (1969), &quot;The Movement and the New Media,&quot; Liberation News Service.]
* [http://www.sirnosir.com/archives_and_resources/library/articles/duck_power_05.html &quot;The Underground GI Press: Pens Against the Pentagon&quot;] 

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Leamer, Lawrence. ''The Paper Revolutionaries''. New York, NY: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1972.
* Lewes, James. ''Protest and Survive: Underground GI Newspapers during the Vietnam War''. Westport: Praeger Publishers, 2003. ISBN 0-275-97861-3.
* Mungo, Raymond. ''Famous Long Ago: My Life and Hard Times With the Liberation News Service''. Boston: Beacon Press, 1970. 
* Peck, Abe. ''Uncovering the Sixties''. New York, NY: Pantheon Books, 1985.
* Wachsberger, Ken, editor. ''Voices From the Underground''. Tempe, AZ: Mica Press, 1993.

==External links==
* [http://www.international-times.org.uk International Times]
* [http://www.nexusmagazine.com Nexus Magazine (Australia)]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20060901051727/www.oztrading.net/ Archive of ozit.org], scans of OZ Magazine (archived site) 
* [http://www.lib.uconn.edu/online/research/speclib/ASC/exhibits/voices/ &quot;Voices from the Underground,&quot; an exhibition of the North American underground press of the 1960s; includes a substantial gallery of color images.]
* [http://www.nuevoanden.com/rag/ A digitally scanned archive of the first twelve issues (1966-67) of ''The Rag,'' from Austin, Texas]
* [http://www.trussel.com/lyman/avatar/avatar.htm Examples of the Boston underground newspaper ''Avatar''] (While ''The Avatar'' shared its design approach and many social concerns with other underground papers of the time, in one important respect it was completely atypical: it served as a platform for self-proclaimed &quot;world saviour&quot; [[Mel Lyman]], leader of a communal cult.)
* A number of libraries have extensive [[microfilm]] collections of underground newspapers. For example, the [[University of Oregon]] library has a collection that consists of mostly, but not exclusively [[North America]]n) underground papers.[http://libweb.uoregon.edu/govdocs/micro/uginv.htm]
* [http://pers-www.wlv.ac.uk/~fa1871/ozit.html Counter Cultures: Cultural Politics and the Underground Press]
* [http://www.merkki.com/powwow.htm Pow wow in the 1940s]
* [http://www.sirnosir.com The website for the film ''Sir! No Sir!''] has an extensive collection of primary source materials from the GI underground press
* [http://www.scarletdukes.com/st/tmhou_press3.html A collection of covers of Space City News (Space City!)] by underground artist [[Bill Narum]].
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/organgrinder/2009/jul/17/international-times-underground-newspaper Dugald Baird, ''How International Times sparked a publishing revolution,'' The Guardian, 17 July 2009]
* [http://desertvalleystar.com/pdf/TheTruthIssue3.pdf ''The Truth''] a specimen high school underground paper from 1969

[[Category:Alternative press]]
[[Category:Underground culture]]
[[Category:Alternative media]]
[[Category:Underground press]]

[[de:Alternativzeitschrift]]
[[fr:Presse underground des années 1960 et 1970]]
[[no:Undergrunnspresse]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
