<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="887498" ns="0" title="One News (New Zealand)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox television
| show_name = One News
| image = [[File:onenewslarge.png]]
| camera = [[Multicamera setup|Multi-camera]]
| picture_format = 16:9 [[720p]] (HDTV)&lt;br/&gt;16:9 [[576i]] (SDTV) 
| format = [[News program]]me
| runtime = ''[[One News (New Zealand)#One News|6pm]]:'' 60 minutes (includes advertisement are about 15-20 mins) &lt;br&gt;''[[One News (New Zealand)#NZI Business|NZI Business]]/ [[One News (New Zealand)#Breakfast|Breakfast]]:'' 5 min updates every 30 minutes from 6.00am to 8.30am&lt;br&gt;''[[Good Morning (New Zealand show)|Good Morning]]:'' 5 min updates at 10am and 11am&lt;br&gt;''[[One News at Midday|Midday]]:'' 30 minutes (includes advertisements) &lt;br&gt;''[[One News at 4:30|4:30]]:'' 25 minutes (including adverts)&lt;br&gt;''[[One News Tonight|Tonight]]:'' 30 minutes (including adverts)
| presenter = [[Simon Dallow]] and [[Wendy Petrie]] (6pm weeknights)&lt;br&gt;[[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]] and [[Bernadine Oliver-Kerby]] (6pm weekends)&lt;br&gt;[[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]] or [[Rawdon Christie]] ''([[One News (New Zealand)#Breakfast|Breakfast]]'', ''[[Good Morning (New Zealand show)|Good Morning]]'' &amp; ''[[One News (New Zealand)#One News|Midday]])''&lt;br&gt; [[Pippa Wetzell]] ''([[One News (New Zealand)#One News|4:30]])''&lt;br&gt;[[Greg Boyed]] ''([[One News (New Zealand)#One News|Tonight]])''
| country = [[New Zealand]]
| first_aired = 3 November 1969
| last_aired = present
| website = http://www.tvnz.co.nz/news | www.tvnz.co.nz/news
}}

'''One News''' is the news division of New Zealand television network [[TVNZ]]. The service is [[live television|broadcast live]] from TVNZ Centre in [[Auckland, New Zealand|Auckland]]. The flagship news bulletin is the nightly 6pm news hour, but ''One News'' also has midday, afternoon and late night news bulletins, as well as [[current affairs (news format)|current affairs]] shows such as Breakfast and Close Up.

The 6pm programme is New Zealand's most-watched news programme. As of July 2008, it has a market share of 44% (651,400+ each night).&lt;ref&gt;[http://tvnz.co.nz/view/page/816457/1984361 &quot;Nine months of growth for One News&quot;]. ''TVNZ''. August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The current editor of One News is Paul Patrick, and the head of TVNZ News and Current Affairs is Anthony Flannery.

''One News'' was judged ''Best News'' in the [[Qantas Media Awards]] in September 2008, 2009, 2010 and 2011.

==History==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Judy richard1.jpg|thumbnail|Judy Bailey and Richard Long in the early days]] --&gt;
&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[image:Entertainment-tvnz-holmes.jpg|thumbnail|Paul Holmes hosts ''Holmes'']] --&gt;

Television news in New Zealand started in 1960 with the introduction of television. These bulletins were broadcast from the main centres ([[Auckland]], [[Wellington]], [[Christchurch]] and [[Dunedin]]) operating completely independently of each other due to technical constraints. The [[Wahine disaster|Wahine Disaster]] in April 1968 highlighted the need for a nationwide new network, as footage from [[Wellington]] could not be easily shown in other centres around the country within a short space of time.

The first network news broadcast was live, airing on 3 November 1969 at 7:35pm to the whole country, read by [[Dougal Stevenson]]. This bulletin was possible due to microwave links being established between the four main centres; the programme was called [[NZBC]] Network News. Initially, it was read by [[Philip Sherry]], [[Dougal Stevenson]] or [[Bill Toft]] on a rotating roster.

Prior to the building of the [[Warkworth, New Zealand|Warkworth]] Station in 1971, international programmes could not be received live – the footage had to be flown into New Zealand and was often days old. [[Angela D'Audney]] was the first female newsreader in New Zealand, from 1973. The Network News featured many other newsreaders until the NZBC was dissolved in 1975. The programme was then renamed simply ''News''. Several regional news programmes were broadcast alongside the ''Network News'' to different regions of the country during this time. As the popularity of these bulletins decreased in the late 1980s, the main ''Network News'' bulletin was revamped in 1987. It was renamed ''Network News'' with [[Judy Bailey]] and [[Neil Billington]] presenting the show from the beginning. [[Richard Long (broadcaster)|Richard Long]] and Tony Ciprian alternately presented and produced sports news. Later that year Long took over from Billington as 'Network News' news co-anchor, the beginning of a partnership that would continue for much of the next fifteen years.Ciprian moved to the new commercial channel TV3, the station's first sports news producer. He was with 3 News for almost 20 years. 

Until 1990, four regional news programmes were broadcast – one in each of the four main regions: ''Top Half'' ([[Auckland]] and the upper [[North Island]]), ''Today Tonight'' ([[Wellington]] and the lower North Island and originally the upper South Island), ''The Mainland Touch'' ([[Christchurch]], [[Canterbury (New Zealand)|Canterbury]] and later the upper [[South Island]]) and ''The South Tonight'' ([[Otago]] and [[Southland Region|Southland]]). These programmes ran for 20 minutes during the main news programme at 6.30pm, between the sports and weather news, but were later moved to before the main broadcast to make way for the current affairs programme, ''Holmes'', which was first broadcast on 11 April 1989. It carried the famous tagline ''&quot;Those were our people today, that's Holmes tonight&quot;''. ''Holmes'' screened at 6.30pm weekdays, so the ''Network News'' was moved back to its current time of 6:00pm.

1989 saw the introduction of the first ''One News'' foreign correspondents – [[Liam Jeory]] in London and [[Susan Wood (New Zealand)|Susan Wood]] in Sydney.

In 1989, ''Network News'' was relaunched as ''One Network News'', due to competition from new broadcasting station [[TV3 (New Zealand)|TV3]]'s news programme ''[[3 News|3 National News]]''. In 1995, the main 6pm bulletin was extended from 30 to 60 minutes, coinciding with the unveiling of a new studio set. On 11 August 1997, the early morning ''Telstra Business'' and ''Breakfast'' shows were first aired; Telstra Business was hosted by [[Michael Wilson]]; [[Breakfast]] hosted by [[Susan Wood (television presenter)|Susan Wood]] and [[Mike Hosking]].

The end of 1997 saw the replacement of weekend news presenters [[Angela D'Audney]] and [[Tom Bradley (broadcaster)|Tom Bradley]] with husband and wife [[Simon Dallow]] and [[Alison Mau]]. Bradley resigned, but D'Audney stayed as a backup presenter for other bulletins until her death in February 2002, from a brain tumour.

In 1998, TVNZ signed [[3 News]] anchor [[John Hawkesby]] to replace Richard Long from the start of 1999. But when Haweskby began presenting ''One Network News'' at 6pm alongside Judy Bailey, there was a public outcry over the separation of Bailey and Long, that lead to Long reinstated as co-anchor at 6pm three weeks later. Hawkesby later took [[TVNZ]] to court, a dispute that he subsequently won.

The show was renamed again on 31 December 1999, this time to the current name of ''One News''.

2003 saw a major shake up of TVNZ's news and current affairs programming with entering head [[Bill Ralston]] making sweeping changes to the formats of many programmes. A new state-of-the-art studio came into use for ''One News'' programmes, but many presenters were culled. The changes saw the end of Long and Bailey's 15-year partnership; from January 2004, the main 6pm bulletin reverted to a single-headed broadcast with Judy Bailey as anchor. [[Jim Hickey (broadcaster)|Jim Hickey]], TVNZ's most popular weather presenter, and sports presenter [[April Bruce]] (née Ieremia) also left in 2003. Jim returned to ''One News'' in 2007.

The current affairs programme, ''[[Close Up]]'' was launched in November 2004, when [[Paul Holmes (broadcaster)|Paul Holmes]], host of the ''Holmes'' programme, resigned following failed contract negotiations. ''Close Up'' followed the same format as ''Holmes'', but was hosted by [[Susan Wood (New Zealand)|Susan Wood]] until her sudden resignation in 2006. [[Mark Sainsbury (New Zealand)|Mark Sainsbury]] became the main host following her resignation.

In October 2005, TVNZ announced that it would not be renewing long-standing flagship broadcaster [[Judy Bailey]]'s contract; some observers believe this was a direct reaction to the programme's market share decline in [[Auckland]] to ''[[3 News]]''. An emotional Bailey signed off for the final time at the end of the 6pm ''One News'' bulletin on 23 December 2005. She was TVNZ's longest serving newsreader and had been reporting and presenting with both NZBC and TVNZ for 34 years. When the 6pm edition of ''One News'' returned after the Christmas break of 2005–2006, it reverted back to double-headed presentation with [[Wendy Petrie]] and [[Simon Dallow]] taking over from Bailey.

The weekend 6pm bulletin remained single-headed until September 2008, when popular presenter Peter Williams joined Bernadine Oliver-Kirby as co-anchor.

[[Paul Holmes (broadcaster)|Paul Holmes]] returned to TVNZ as the host on the new political programme ''Q+A'' in 2009.

TVNZ celebrated One News' 40th birthday on 3 November 2009 with some archival footage available on their website.

A Saturday edition of Breakfast will be broadcast from 3 September, hosted by [[Rawdon Christie]] and [[Toni Street]].

==Programmes==

===One News===
* Daily at 6pm
* Weekdays every half hour 6am-8:30am, 10am, 11am, Midday, 4:30pm, 6pm and 10:30pm

[[File:One News satellite ute, Mt Allan fire, NZ 2010.jpg|thumb|right|One News telecommunications [[Coupé utility|ute]], at the 2010 Mt Allan forest fire]]
The main ''One News'' bulletin screens nightly at 6pm and is fronted by [[Simon Dallow]] and [[Wendy Petrie]] on weekdays, and [[Bernadine Oliver-Kerby]], and [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]] at weekends. Sport is presented by [[Jenny-May Coffin]], [[Toni Street]] or [[Andrew Saville]] and weather from [[Karen Olsen]], [[Renee Wright]] or [[Jim Hickey (weather presenter)|Jim Hickey]]. The 6pm bulletin starts off at  with the weather presenter explaining the current weather situation, standing in front of a map of New Zealand showing the country's satellite imagery that day. The bulletin leads with general news items for the first part of the show, with a weather update at about 6:25pm (showing maximum temperatures in towns and cities around the country and live Weather Camera shots in the six main centres). Business and [[One Sport|sports]] items screen next, then the main weather bulletin is aired at about 6:55. There is often one oddspot item before the broadcast ends at 7pm.

On weekdays, ''One News'' screens bulletins right throughout the day. This includes ''One News Breakfast'', hosted by [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]] on Monday-Wednesday and [[Rawdon Christie]] on Thursday and Friday. These are 5–10 minute news and weather updates that screen on the half hour during NZI Business and TV One's Breakfast show (news 6–8.30am, weather 6.35–8.35am). Weather reports during ''Breakfast'' are presented by [[Tamati Coffey]].

At 10am and 11am, during ''[[Good Morning (New Zealand show)|Good Morning]]'', five-minute news and weather updates screen and are hosted by the same presenter for ''Breakfast'' news that day. ''One News'' also produces three half-hour bulletins, which screen at Midday, 4:30pm and 10:30pm. The midday bulletin, ''One News at Midday'' is also hosted by the same presenter for ''Breakfast'' news. ''One News at 4:30'' is presented and produced by [[Rawdon Christie]], and the late night broadcast, ''One News Tonight'' is presented by [[Greg Boyed]]; it usually screens around 10:30pm.

===TVNZ News===

* Daily updates on the hour 6am-11pm
* Daily one hour bulletin at 8pm

One News also resources news bulletins for TVNZ's advertising-free channel, [[TVNZ 7]]. These bulletins are called ''TVNZ News Now'', and are screened live on the hour every hour between 8am-11pm weekdays, and 6am-11pm weekends. The bulletins are five minutes long, and update the latest in news, sport and weather. The 8pm bulletin, ''TVNZ News at 8'' is one hour long, and is presented by [[Greg Boyed]]. This bulletin generally recaps the main stories from the One News 6pm bulletin, but since [[TVNZ 7]] is advertisement free, this enables more time for extended interviews on the day's top stories, and extra international stories are also aired.

The presenters on TVNZ 7 do both presenting and producing during their shifts. TVNZ News Now presenters include: Jenny-May Coffin, Renee Wright, Sharon Fergusson and Glen Larmer. The weekend editions of ''TVNZ News at 8'' are hosted by Miriama Kamo.

===Breakfast===
* Weekdays 6:30am-9am.
* Saturdays 7am-9am.
* Presented by [[Corin Dann]] and [[Petra Bagust]] on weekdays and [[Rawdon Christie]] and [[Toni Street]] on Saturdays.

''Breakfast'' is a two-and-a-half hour long magazine style news and current affairs programme, which looks at the days headlines and events happening around New Zealand. News, sport and weather are updated every half hour, with business news being updated at around 6:40am, 7:10am and 8:10am.

News segments are presented by [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]] Mondays-Wednesdays, and [[Rawdon Christie]] Thursdays-Fridays. [[Tamati Coffey]] is the weather presenter and roving reporter.

''Saturday Breakfast'' screened for the first time on 3 September 2011, hosted by [[Rawdon Christie]] and [[Toni Street]]. It is broadcast from 7am until 9am. It follows a similar format to the weekday edition, except there is no dedicated news/sport presenter - both hosts share presenting of news and sport updates.

''For more details on this topic, see [[Breakfast (New Zealand Television Programme)|Breakfast]]''.

===AMP Business===
* Weekdays at 6.00am
* Presented by [[Nadine Chalmers-Ross]]
{{details|NZI Business}}
''AMP Business'' (formerly ''NZI Business'', ''Breakfast Business'' and ''ASB Business'') is a half-hour business news programme, with insights into issues affecting the business sector. In September 2006, what was then ''NZI Business'' began [[podcast]]ing segments of its programme.

===Close Up===
* Weekdays at 7pm
* Presented by [[Mark Sainsbury (New Zealand)|Mark Sainsbury]]
* Reporters include: Hannah Ockelford, Robyn Janes, Michael Holland, Matt Chisholm, Daniel Faitaua, Jendy Harper, Corrine Ambler, Sofia Wenbourn, Gill Higgins and Donna-Marie Lever
{{details|Close Up}}
''Close Up'' is a half-hour current affairs programme, which features mostly current event or local [[human interest]] stories.

===Sunday===
* Sundays at 7.30pm
* Presented by [[Miriama Kamo]]
{{details|Sunday (TVNZ programme)}}
''Sunday'' is an hour-long current affairs programme, featuring local and international stories.
* Sunday reporters also include: Janet McIntyre, [[Ian Sinclair (broadcaster)|Ian Sinclair]], and John Hudson.

===Te Karere===
* Weekdays at 4.00pm
* Presented by [[Scotty Morrison(TVNZ)|Scotty Morrison]]
{{details|Te Karere}}
''Te Karere'' is a half-hour news programme broadcast entirely in [[Māori language|Māori]]. The weather is also broadcast in Māori. Te Karere attracts between 50,000 – 80,000 viewers a day for this bulletin broadcast without English subtitles.

===Q+A===
* Sundays at 9.00am
* Presented by [[Guyon Espiner]] and [[Paul Holmes (broadcaster)|Paul Holmes]]. [[Therese Aresenau]] is a panelist that is on the show most weeks.
''Q+A'' is an hour-long political show containing an interview with a politician that has been in the news during the previous week and a panel debate on a political hot topic. It is the replacement for ''Agenda'', which stopped screening in late 2008. ''Q+A'' has been screening since Sunday 22 March 2009.
{{details|Q+A|Q+A}}
''Q+A'' won ''Best News/Current Affairs Programme'' in the 2009 [[Qantas Media Awards]].

=== 20/20===
TVNZ News department also produces 20/20
Hosted by Sonja Wilson:
*Reporters: Pete Cronshaw, Sonja Wilson and Beth Roche

==One News Special==
One News Specials are often aired during international, one-off and breaking news events. Often for international breaking news stories, One News airs a video feed from other news organisations. One News aired Specials for the following events:
* on [[September 4]], [[2010]] and on [[February 22]], [[2011]] (in response to the [[Christchurch earthquakes]]).
* on and following [[19 November]] 2010, (in response to the explosion at the [[Pike River Mine]]).
* on [[11 March]], [[2011]] (in response to the [[2011 Japan earthquake]]).

* Annual Government Budget announcements.

* Annual special reports such as ''The Year in Review'' (which airs on the first Sunday of the year and looks at the previous year).

==Previous presenters==
===One News at Midday===
* 1996–1997: [[Susan Wood (New Zealand)|Susan Wood]]
* 1997–2000: [[Liz Gunn]]
* 2000–2003: [[Linda Clark (broadcaster)|Linda Clark]]
* 2003–2008: [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]]
* 2008–2010: [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]]/[[Alison Mau]]
* 2011-present: [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]]/[[Rawdon Christie]]

===One News: First at 4:30===
* 2007–2009: [[Neil Waka]]
* 2009–present: [[Rawdon Christie]]

===One News at 6===
====Weekdays====
* 1970s-mid 1980s: [[Bill Toft]], [[Tom Bradley (broadcaster)|Tom Bradley]], [[Philip Sherry]], [[Jenny Goodwin]], [[Angela D'Audney]] or [[Dougal Stevenson]]
* 1987 [[Neil Billington]] and [[Judy Bailey]]
* 1987–1999, 1999–2003: [[Richard Long (broadcaster)|Richard Long]] and [[Judy Bailey]]
* 1999: [[John Hawkesby]] and [[Judy Bailey]]
* 2004–2005: [[Judy Bailey]]
* 2006–present: [[Simon Dallow]] and [[Wendy Petrie]]

====Weekends====
* early 1990s–1997: [[Tom Bradley (broadcaster)|Tom Bradley]] and [[Angela D'Audney]]
* 1997–1999, 1999–2003: [[Simon Dallow]] and [[Alison Mau]]
* 1999: [[Richard Long (broadcaster)|Richard Long]] and [[Liz Gunn]]
* 2003-2004: [[Simon Dallow]]
* 2004–2008: [[Bernadine Oliver-Kerby]]
* 2008–present: [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]] and [[Bernadine Oliver-Kerby]]

===One News Tonight===
* 1995–1997: [[Simon Dallow]] and [[Alison Mau]]
* 1998–2001: [[Linda Clark (broadcaster)|Linda Clark]]
* 2001–2002: [[Liz Gunn]]
* 2003: [[Simon Dallow]]
* 2003–2004: [[Eric Young (broadcaster)|Eric Young]] and [[Kate Hawkesby]]
* 2005–2006: [[Kate Hawkesby]]
* 2007–present: [[Greg Boyed]]

===TVNZ News at 8===
====Weekdays====
* 2008–2009: [[Greg Boyed]] and [[Geraldine Knox]]
* 2009–present: [[Greg Boyed]]

====Weekends====
* 2008–2009: [[Miriama Kamo]] and [[Sonia Voigt]] (née Madigan)
* 2009–present: [[Miriama Kamo]]

==Backup presenters==

''Note: The name in '''bold''' is the normal presenter, the name(s) following are the backup presenters.''

* ''NZI Business'' and ''Midday'' Business segment
** '''Nadine Chalmers-Ross:''' [[Lisa Davies]]
* ''Breakfast'' (programme):
** '''Petra Bagust:''' [[Alison Mau]] or [[Wendy Petrie]]
** '''Corin Dann:''' [[Greg Boyed]], [[Peter Williams (broadcaster)|Peter Williams]], [[Tim Wilson]], [[Jack Tame]], [[Simon Dallow]], [[Mark Sainsbury (New Zealand)|Mark Sainsbury]] or [[Alison Mau]]
* ''Breakfast'' (news) and ''Midday''
** '''Peter Williams / Rawdon Christie:''' [[Rawdon Christie]], Jenny-May Coffin, [[Bernadine Oliver Kerby]], [[Brooke Dobson]]
* ''Te Karere'':
** '''Scott Morrison:''' [[Tini Molyneux]]
* ''4:30'':
** '''Rawdon Christie:''' [[Greg Boyed]], [[Simon Dallow]], [[Peter Willams]], [[Neil Waka]], Melissa Stokes, [[Bernadine Oliver-Kerby]], [[Jenny-May Coffin]], [[Miriama Kamo]], Renee Wright, [[Wendy Petrie]] or Brooke Dobson
* ''6pm Weekdays'':
** '''Simon Dallow:''' [[Peter Willams]], [[Rawdon Christie]] or [[Greg Boyed]]
** '''Wendy Petrie:''' [[Bernadine Oliver-Kirby]], [[Alison Mau]] or [[Miriama Kamo]]
* ''6pm Weekends'':
** '''Peter Williams:''' [[Rawdon Christie]] or [[Greg Boyed]]
** '''Bernadine Oliver-Kirby:''' [[Miriama Kamo]], [[Alison Mau]] or [[Lisa Davies]]
* ''6pm Sport'':
** '''Andrew Saville / Jenny-May Coffin:''' [[Toni Street]]
* ''6pm Weather'':
** '''Jim Hickey / Karen Olsen:''' [[Renee Wright]] or [[Tamati Coffey]]
* ''Close Up'':
** '''Mark Sainsbury:''' [[Mike Hosking]], [[Greg Boyed]]
* ''TVNZ News At 8 (weekdays)'':
** '''Greg Boyed''': [[Rawdon Christie]], [[Nadine Chalmers-Ross]], [[Tim Wilson]] or [[Miriama Kamo]]
* ''TVNZ News At 8 (weekends)'':
** '''Miriama Kamo''': [[Lisa Davies]] or [[Neil Waka]]
* ''Tonight'':
** '''Greg Boyed''': [[Miriama Kamo]], [[Neil Waka]] or [[Rawdon Christie]]
* ''Q+A'':
** '''Paul Holmes''': [[Guyon Espiner]]

==Reporters==
Source: TVNZ&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=One News Team | publisher=[[TVNZ]] |accessdate=2008-07-17 | url=http://tvnz.co.nz/content/tvone_one_news_people_group/news_four_column_skin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Auckland===
'''General reporters'''
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
Mark Crysell&lt;br&gt;
Garth Bray&lt;br&gt;
Melissa Stokes&lt;br&gt;
Nicole Bremner&lt;br&gt;
Krissy Moreau&lt;br&gt;
Jack Tame&lt;br&gt;
Amy Kelley&lt;br&gt;
Kim Vinnell
{{col-end}}

{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''Breakfast reporter'''&lt;br&gt;
Alison Pugh&lt;br&gt;
Lucas de Jong &lt;br&gt;
{{col-end}}

===Wellington===
'''General reporters'''
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
Heather du Plessis-Allan&lt;br&gt;
Matty McLean &lt;br&gt;
Abby Scott &lt;br&gt;
Renee Graham&lt;br&gt;
Arrun Soma &lt;br&gt;
Simon Bradwell&lt;br&gt;
{{col-end}}

{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''Sports reporter'''&lt;br&gt;
Stephen Stuart
{{col-2}}
'''Breakfast reporter'''&lt;br&gt;
Lucas de Jong
{{col-end}}
'''Late reporter'''&lt;br&gt;
Rebecca Edwards
{{col-end}}

===Christchurch===
'''General reporters'''
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
Tom McRae&lt;br&gt;
Ana Olykan &lt;br&gt;
Vicki Wilkinson-Baker
{{col-2}}
Joy Reid&lt;br&gt;
{{col-end}}

{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''Sports reporter'''&lt;br&gt;
Blair Norton
{{col-2}}
'''Breakfast reporter'''&lt;br&gt;
Charlotte Bellis
{{col-end}}

===Dunedin===
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
John McDermott
{{col-2}}
Megan Martin
{{col-end}}

===Other bureaux===
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''Queenstown'''&lt;br&gt;
Tsehai Tiffin (freelance)
{{col-2}}
'''Palmerston North/Central North Island'''&lt;br&gt;
John Newton
{{col-end}}

===International===
{{col-start}}
{{col-3}}
'''London correspondent'''&lt;br&gt;
Paul Hobbs
{{col-3}}
'''New York correspondent'''&lt;br&gt;
Tim Wilson
{{col-3}}
'''Pacific correspondent&lt;br&gt;
Barbara Dreaver
{{col-end}}

===Gallery (political)===
{{col-start}}
{{col-3}}
'''Editor'''&lt;br&gt;
[[Guyon Espiner]]
{{col-3}}
'''Reporters'''&lt;br&gt;
Jessica Mutch
{{col-3}}
&lt;br&gt;
Michael Parkin
{{col-end}}

===Sports reporters (Auckland-based)===
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
Toni Street&lt;br&gt;
Antony Stevens&lt;br&gt;
Martin Tasker&lt;br&gt;
{{col-2}}
Craig Stanaway&lt;br&gt;
Stephen Stuart&lt;br&gt;
Andrew Morrison&lt;br&gt;
{{col-end}}

===Specialist===
{{col-start}}
Lorelei Mason (health reporter, [[Christchurch]])&lt;br&gt;
Joanna Hunkin (entertainment reporter/producer, Auckland)
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://corporate.tvnz.co.nz/ Television New Zealand corporate website]
* [http://tvnz.co.nz/view/news_index_skin/news_index_group/ One News website]
* [http://corporate.tvnz.co.nz/tvnz_detail/0,2406,111544-247-252,00.html History of New Zealand television]

{{New Zealand television news}}

[[Category:New Zealand news television series]]
[[Category:TV One (New Zealand) programmes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
