<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="8891285" ns="0" title="Agua Fria High School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{coord|33|26|20.52|N|112|20|39.34|W|display=title}}
{{Infobox School
|image=
|name=Agua Fria Union High School
|type=[[Public school (government funded)|Public]]
|location= 530 E. Riley Drive&lt;br&gt;[[Avondale, Arizona|Avondale, AZ]]
|information=(623) 932-7301
|established=1928 (Litchfield Park)&lt;br&gt;1956 (as Agua Fria)
|grades=9-12
|enrollment=1,654 students (1 Oct. 2010)
|principal=Matthew Bentz
|mascot=Owl
|colors= {{colorbox|Red}} {{colorbox|Grey}} Red and grey
|district=Agua Fria Union High School District
|website=[http://www.aguafria.org/education/school/school.php?sectionid=2 Official Site]
[http://www.classreport.org/usa/az/avondale/afhs/1986/ Alumni By Class]}}
'''Agua Fria High School''' is located in [[Avondale, Arizona]]. It is a part of the [[Agua Fria Union High School District]] and was its only school for 43 years.

It was founded in 1928 as '''Litchfield Park High School'''. In 1956, the school was moved to Avondale and gained its present name. In the 1982-83 school year, it was honored as a [[Blue Ribbon Schools Program|Blue Ribbon school]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ed.gov/programs/nclbbrs/list-1982.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Fine arts==
Agua Fria offers college preparatory coursework, along with career and technical education. Agua Fria also offers a respected music program; the Night Owl Jazz band regularly performs at jazz festivals throughout the Phoenix Area, and has qualified for the Arizona State Jazz Festival in both 2006 and 2007. Also in 2006, the Agua Fria Band of Owls was the first to receive a rating of &quot;superior with distinctions&quot; in the district.

==Athletics==
Agua Fria has had a track and field program worth recognition as well. Under the direction of coach Ted Campbell, as well as Brian Bogen, the Owls morphed into perennial winners. Between 1997 and 2007, the boys track team had a duel meet record of 112 wins and 13 losses, came home with countless invitational trophies, took first place in its region five years in a row (from 2004 to 2008), and won state titles back to back in 2006 and 2007.   

Agua Fria basketball has been prominent in tournaments and championships. From 2007 to 2009, the varsity team made it to the 4A-I state finals, but fell short of winning the championship to [[Millennium High School (Goodyear, Arizona)|Millennium High School]] (division rivals) and [[Sunnyslope High School]].

==Solar panels==
In the late spring of 2011, covered parking with solar panel installations will be added to Agua Fria and Millennium high schools; the district had already added solar panels to the roofs at [[Desert Edge High School]] and [[Verrado High School]] in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.azcentral.com/community/swvalley/articles/2011/01/16/20110116agua-fria-solar-panels.html&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that some 40 percent of the entire district's energy needs will come from solar panels at its high schools upon completion.

==Notable alumni==
*[[Everson Griffen]], [[defensive end]] for the NFL [[Minnesota Vikings]]
*[[Randall McDaniel]], [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]] offensive guard (an athletic training building is named for him on campus; his number has also been retired)
*[[Shawn Gilbert]], Major League Baseball player 1997-2000

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Coalition of Essential Schools]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1956]]
[[Category:Schools in Maricopa County, Arizona]]
[[Category:Public high schools in Arizona]]

[[Category:Blue Ribbon schools in Arizona]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
