<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="898503" ns="0" title="Steam (software)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Steampowered|the steam engine|Steam engine}}
{{Infobox software
|name                    = Steam 
|logo                    = [[File:Steam logo.svg|200px]]
|screenshot              = [[File:SteamcontentMay2010Storehighlight.jpg|250px|center]]
|caption                 = The home page of the Steam Client for Windows
|developer               = [[Valve Corporation]]
|released                = {{Start date|2003|09|12}}&lt;ref name=&quot;originalrelease&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/183/|title=Steam Client Released|publisher=Valve Corporation|date=September 12, 2003|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|frequently updated      = yes
|programming language    = [[C++]]
|platform                = [[Microsoft Windows]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mac OS X]]&lt;ref name=&quot;osx_announce&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/3569/|title=Valve to Deliver Steam &amp; Source on the Mac|date=8 March 2010|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=8 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[PlayStation 3]] ([[#PlayStation 3|partially]])&lt;ref name=&quot;eurogamer11-ps3&quot; /&gt;
|size                    = 41.5 megabytes (Windows)&lt;br /&gt;153.5 megabytes (Mac)
|language                = [[#Localization|21 languages]]
|status                  = Active
|genre                   = [[Content delivery]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Digital rights management]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Social network service|Social networking]]
|license                 = [http://store.steampowered.com/subscriber_agreement/ Steam Subscriber Agreement] ([[Proprietary software]])
|website                 = [http://store.steampowered.com/ store.steampowered.com]
}}

'''Steam''' is a [[online distribution|digital distribution]], [[digital rights management]], [[multiplayer]] and communications platform developed by [[Valve Corporation]]. It is used to distribute games and related media online, from small [[independent video game development|independent]] developers to larger software houses. Steam also has [[#Steam Community|community features]], automated game updates, in-game voice and chat functionality.

{{As of|2011|October}}, there are over 1,400 games available through Steam,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Steam Search|url=http://store.steampowered.com/|publisher=[[Valve Corporation]]|accessdate=12 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 35 million active user accounts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=35 Million Active Gamers on Steam Mark|url=http://gamingbolt.com/35-million-active-gamers-on-steam-valve-hints-at-an-improved-source-engine|publisher=Gaming Bolt|accessdate=18th September 2011|date=18 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Valve never releases sales figures, [[Stardock]], the previous owner of competing platform [[Impulse (content delivery)|Impulse]], estimated that, as of 2009, Steam had a 70% share of the digital distribution market for video games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamasutra.com/php-bin/news_index.php?story=26158 |title=Stardock Reveals Impulse, Steam Market Share Estimates |last=Graft|first=Kris|publisher=[[Gamasutra]] |accessdate=November 21, 2009|date=November 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many major [[video game publisher|publishers]] have large catalogues available on Steam, including [[Bethesda Softworks]], [[Activision]], [[Rockstar Games]], [[Square Enix]], [[2K Games]], [[Telltale Games]] and [[Electronic Arts]].

==Client functionality==
===Software delivery and maintenance===
Steam's primary service is to allow its users to [[digital distribution|download games and other software]] that they have in their virtual software library to their local computers. Steam-integrated games are stored as single non-compressed archive files with the extension &lt;code&gt;.gcf&lt;/code&gt; (an [[initialism]] for '''G'''ame '''C'''ache '''F'''ile&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url         = http://supportwiki.steampowered.com/wiki/Game_cache_file_(GCF)
| title       = Game cache file (GCF)
| accessdate  = 20 January 2010
}}{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;). Steam allocates space on the user's hard disk for &lt;code&gt;.gcf&lt;/code&gt; files before downloading in order to reduce fragmentation which may occur when downloading large files and performing disk access. Game Cache Files help to make games more portable, stop users from accidentally overwriting important files, allow for easy modification of resources, and allows for validation of content for errors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url         = http://www.wunderboy.org/docs/gcfformat.php
| title       = Steam GCF File Format
| publisher   = [http://www.wunderboy.org/index.php Wunderboy.org]
| accessdate  = 20 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; For games that do not integrate, a 'No Cache File' system is provided. Here, a &lt;code&gt;.ncf&lt;/code&gt; index file points to a directory of loose files somewhere else on the system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url         = http://developer.valvesoftware.com/wiki/Ncf
| title       = The Valve Developer Community&amp;nbsp;– NCF
| accessdate  = 20 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Users can enable Steam to automatically patch software packages as they are updated by their publishers, or alternatively allow users to manually initiate this patching process. The client allows users to backup game data files to other media, and remove game content files to free space on their machines.

Steam provides minimal [[digital rights management]] (DRM) for software titles, by providing &quot;Custom Executable Generation&quot; for executable files that are unique for each user, but allow that user to install the software on multiple computing devices via Steam or through software backups without limitations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.wired.com/gamelife/2009/03/steam-update-ma/ | title = Steam Update ‘Makes DRM Obsolete’ | first = Eric | last = Caolili | date = 2011-09-08 | accessdate  =2011-09-08 | work = [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, the user is required to have started Steam while connected to the Internet for authentication prior to playing a game, or have previously set up Steam in an &quot;offline&quot; mode while connected online, storing their credentials locally to play without an Internet connection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url  =http://www.pcworld.com/article/190116/steam_pc_gaming_client_gets_surprise_facelift.html |title = Steam PC Gaming Client Gets Surprise Facelift | first = Matt | last = Peckham | date = 2011-09-08 | accessdate = 2011-09-08 | work = [[PC World]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Steam's DRM is available through Steamworks to software developers, but the service allows developers and publishers to include other forms of DRM on top of Steam.

In September 2008, Valve added support for Steam Cloud, a [[cloud computing]] file share that can automatically store game saves and related custom files to Valve's services; users can then access this data from any other machine running the Steam client.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/52906|title=Valve Announces Steam Cloud; Online Network to Store Saved Games Indefinitely|last=Breckon|first=Nick|date=May 29, 2008|accessdate=September 3, 2008|publisher=[[Shacknews]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/55705|title=Steam Cloud Launching With Left 4 Dead; Custom Settings To Be Automatically Backed Up, Applied|last=Faylor|first=Chris|date=September 3, 2008|accessdate=September 3, 2008|publisher=[[Shacknews]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Games must use the appropriate features of Steamworks for this feature to work. Users are able to disable this feature as well on a per-game and per-account basis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://store.steampowered.com/news/4012/ | title = Steam client update released | date = 2010-07-01 | publisher = [[Valve Corporation]] | accessdate = 2010-07-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

To protect against hijacking of accounts, Valve added Steam Guard functionality to the Steam client in March 2011. Steam Guard takes advantage of the identity protection provided with Intel's second generation [[Intel Core|Core]] processors and compatible motherboard hardware to allow the user to lock their account to a specific computer. Once locked, activity by that account on other computers must first be approved of by the user on the locked computer.  Support APIs for Steam Guard are available to third-party developers through Steamworks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/33347/Valve_Unveils_Steam_Guard_For_Account_Security.php | title = Valve Unveils Steam Guard For Account Security | first = Eric | last = Caoili | date  =2011-03-03 | accessdate = 2011-03-03 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; An alternative option available to users interested in using Steam Guard is [[two-factor authentication]] through the use of a one-time verification code sent to a verified email address associated with the Steam account. Many of Steam Guard's features will work the same with the only real difference being the method of authentication.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://store.steampowered.com/news/5123 | title = Steam Guard Now Available to All | date = 2011-03-16 | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | publisher = [[Valve]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Storefront===
Steam includes a digital storefront called the Steam Store, through which users can purchase [[computer games]] [[digital distribution|digitally]]. Once purchased, software is permanently attached to the user's Steam account (however &quot;gifting&quot; of games to other accounts is possible). Content is delivered using a proprietary file transfer [[protocol (computing)|protocol]] from an international network of servers.&lt;ref name=&quot;contentserver-stats&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/stats/content|title=Content Server Stats|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=November 15, 2008}} (click &quot;View individual server statistics&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; Steam sells its products in [[United States dollar|US dollars]], [[Euro]]s, [[pound sterling|pounds sterling]], and [[Roubles]] based on the user's location.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/2110/|title=Steam News&amp;nbsp;– European Local Currency Available|date=2008-12-17|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; From December 2010, the client also supports the [[Webmoney]] payment system, available for many European, Middle East, and Asian countries.&lt;ref name='News - WebMoney Now Available on Steam'&gt;[http://store.steampowered.com/news/4806/ News - WebMoney Now Available on Steam&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The Steam storefront validates a user's region, and certain titles may be restricted to specific regions due to release dates, game classification, or publisher agreements.

Certain games sold through retail channels can be redeemed as titles for user's library within Steam by entering a product code within the software.&lt;ref name=&quot;steamworks-retail&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Steamworks - Retail Support|url=http://www.steampowered.com/steamworks/retailsupport.php|publisher=Valve|accessdate=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For games that incorporate Steamworks, users can purchase redemption codes from other vendors, and redeem these in the Steam client to add the title to their library. Steam offers a framework for selling and distributing [[downloadable content]] (DLC) for games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/2355/|title=Steam offers gamers in-game downloadable content|date=2009-03-16|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|List of Steam titles#Modifications|l1=Steam Modifications}}
Players can add non-Steam games to their library, allowing the game to be easily accessed from the Steam client, and provides support, where possible, for the Steam Overlay features.
The Steam interface allows for user-defined shortcuts to be added. In this way [[mod (computer gaming)|third-party mods]], and games not purchased through the Steam Store, can use Steam features. Valve sponsors and distributes some mods for free,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://storefront.steampowered.com/Steam/Marketing/message/1843/|title=Steam mod hosting announcement|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=2008-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and mods that use [[#Steamworks|Steamworks]] can also use VAC, Friends, the server browser, and any Steam features supported by their parent game.

During mid-2011, Valve began to offer [[free-to-play]] games, such as ''[[Global Agenda]]'', ''[[Spiral Knights]]'' and ''[[Champions Online]]''; this was tied in with their move to make ''Team Fortress 2'' a free-to-play title.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.wired.com/gamelife/2011/06/free-steam-games/ | title = Valve Introduces Free-to-Play Games to Steam | first = Mark | last = Brown | date = 2011-06-15 | accessdate = 2011-09-07 | work = [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Valve included support via Steamworks for [[microtransaction]]s through Steam's purchasing channels for in-game items in these titles, in a similar manner to the existing in-game store for ''Team Fortress 2''.  A subsequent addition later that year added the ability to trade both in-game items and &quot;unopened&quot; game gifts between users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/37056/Valves_Steam_Trading_Leaves_Beta_Adds_Portal_2_Support.php | title = 	Valve's Steam Trading Leaves Beta, Adds Portal 2 Support  | first = Frank | last = Cifaldi | date = 2011-09-06 | accessdate = 2011-09-07 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Steam Community and Matchmaking===
The Steam client, as part of a [[social network service]], allows users to identify friends and join groups through the Steam Community feature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url         = http://www.joystiq.com/2007/09/13/steam-community-officially-launched/
| title       = Steam Community officially launched
| first       = Ross
| last        = Miller
| date        = 13 September 2007
| publisher   = Joystiq
| accessdate  = 18 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Users can use both text chat and [[Peer-to-Peer]] [[Voice over IP|VoIP]] with other users, identify what their friends and other group members are playing, and, for Steamworks-based games that support it, join and invite friends in multiplayer games. Users can also participate in forums hosted by Valve regarding Steam games. In January 2010, Valve reported that 10&amp;nbsp;million of the 25&amp;nbsp;million active Steam accounts had signed up to Steam Community.&lt;ref name=&quot;steamgrowth_2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/3390/|title=Steam Realizes Extraordinary Growth in 2009|date=2010-01-29|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=29 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each user has a unique page that shows what groups and friends they have, their game library including achievements earned, game wishlists, and other social features; users have the option to keep this information private if desired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://developer.valvesoftware.com/wiki/Steam_rating|title=Steam rating|work=Valve Developer Community|accessdate=November 3, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Steam client has been made into an [[OpenID]] provider, allowing third-party websites to utilize a Steam user's identity without requiring the user to expose their Steam credentials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Steam Web APIs|url=http://www.teamfortress.com/post.php?id=4014|work=''[[Team Fortress 2]]'' blog|accessdate=2 July 2010|author=TF2 Team|date=1 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Steam Web API Documentation|url=http://steamcommunity.com/dev|work=Steam Community|publisher=[[Valve Corporation]]|accessdate=2 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steam, through Steamworks, provides a means of server browsing for multiplayer games that utilizes the Steam Community features, allowing users to create lobbies with friends or members of common groups. Steamworks also provides [[Valve Anti-Cheat]] (VAC), Valve's proprietary [[anti-cheat]] system, for game servers to automatically detect and report users who are using [[Cheating in online games|cheats]] in online multiplayer games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url         = https://support.steampowered.com/kb_article.php?ref=7849-RADZ-6869
| title       = Steam Support&amp;nbsp;– Valve Anti-Cheat System (VAC)
| author      = [[Valve Corporation]]
| accessdate  = 18 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steam collects and reports anonymous metrics of its usage, stability, and performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;valveprivacypolicy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.valvesoftware.com/privacy.htm|title=Valve Privacy Policy|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=2007-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the exception of Valve's hardware survey,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/hwsurvey/ hardware survey|title=Valve Hardware Survey |publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=2010-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; most collection occurs without notifying the user or offering an opt-out. Some of these metrics are available publicly, such as what games are being played or statistics on player progress in certain games.&lt;ref name=&quot;ep1stats&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://steamgames.com/status/ep1/|title=Half-Life 2: Episode One Stats|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=2007-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Valve has also used information from these statistics to justify implementing new features in Steam, such as the addition of a [[defragmentation]] option for game caches.&lt;ref name=&quot;defrag-news&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.steampowered.com/Steam/Marketing/message/639/|title=Wednesday May 31, 2006 - Steam client update released|publisher=Valve Corporation|date=31 May 2006|accessdate=2006-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Valve announced on July 15, 2010 that in conjunction with collecting hardware information in Steam's opt-in hardware surveys, they would begin collecting a list of the user's installed software as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=New Software Survey|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/4086/|publisher=[[Valve Corporation]]|accessdate=3 June 2011|date=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Steam Overlay===
For most games launched from Steam, Steam provides an overlay atop the game that can be accessed by a specific keypress. From the Overlay, the user can access their Steam Community lists and participate in chats, manage selected Steam settings, and access a built-in [[web browser]] without having to exit the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.tomshardware.com/news/steam-valve-ie-beta-webkit,9736.html | title = Valve's Steam Ditches Internet Explorer for WebKit | first = Marcus| last = Yam | date  =2010-02-24 | accessdate = 2011-08-03 | publisher = Tom's Hardware }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Overlay also allows for players to take [[screenshot]]s of the games in process, automatically storing these and letting the player to review, delete, or share them during their play session or after completion.

===Steamworks===
Steamworks is a freely available [[application programming interface]] (API) that provided development and publishing tools to game developers, allowing them to take advantage of the Steam client's features.&lt;ref name=&quot;steamworks_demo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.steampowered.com/steamworks/FAQ.php|title=Steamworks FAQ|publisher=[[Valve Corporation]]|accessdate=March 14, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ue3_steamworks&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ue3_steamworks&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://epicgames.com/press_releases/steamworks.html|title=Steamworks  Integration Now Available to Unreal Engine 3 Licensees|publisher=[[Epic Games]]|date=March 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;api overview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://partner.steamgames.com/documentation/api|title=Steamworks API Overview|work=Steamworks partner site|publisher=Valve Corporation|date=May 1, 2008|accessdate=August 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, Steamworks provides means of games to integrate with the Steam client, including networking and player authentication tools for both server and peer-to-peer multiplayer games, matchmaking services, support for Steam community friends and groups, Steam statistics and achievements, integrated voice communications, and Steam Cloud support; the API also provides for anti-cheating devices and digital copy management.&lt;ref name=&quot;api overview&quot;/&gt; Steamworks can be combined with a standard Steam distribution agreement, the latter of which gives it advertising space in the Steam store but also provides Valve with a share of revenue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/app/12900/|title=Audiosurf purchase page|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=February 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Supported platforms ==
Steam was originally released only for [[Microsoft Windows]]-enabled computers, but has since expanded to at least two other platforms.

===Mac OS X===
On March 8, 2010, Valve announced that Steam was in development for [[Mac OS X]].&lt;ref name=&quot;steam mac&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/62687 | title = Steam Coming to Mac in April, Portal 2 This Fall | publisher = [[Shacknews]] | first = Chris | last = Faylor | date =2010-03-08 | accessdate = 2010-03-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The announcement was preceded by a change in the Steam beta client to support the cross-platform [[WebKit]] web browser rendering engine instead of the [[Trident (layout engine)|Trident engine]] from [[Internet Explorer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/uiupdate/|title=A Brand New Steam|date=February 23, 2010|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=February 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/62488|title=Valve Launches Public Beta For New Steam UI|last=Leahy|first=Brian|date=February 23, 2010|publisher=Shacknews|accessdate=February 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/news/3753/|title=New Steam Client Officially Released!|date=2010-04-26|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=26 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to this announcement, it teased the release through several images [[email]]ed to Mac community and gaming web sites featuring Valve game characters with [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] logos or featured in parodies of old [[Macintosh]] advertisements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.desktopreview.com/default.asp?newsID=970&amp;News=Apple+Mac+OS+X+Gaming+Valve+Steam+Portal+2|title=Valve All But Confirms Steam and Portal 2 Coming to Mac OS X|last=Nelson|first=J.R.|date=2010-03-07|publisher=Desktop Preview|accessdate=8 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macrumors.com/2010/03/03/valve-teases-upcoming-half-life-release-for-mac/|title=Valve teases upcoming Half life release for Mac|last=Slivka|first=Eric|date=2010-03-03|publisher=Mac Rumors|accessdate=8 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one case, Valve developed a full video homage to the ''[[1984 (commercial)|1984]]'' Apple Macintosh commercial to announce the availability of ''Half-Life 2'' and its episodes to the service, with some concept images for the video previously used to tease the Mac Steam client.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/63976 | title = Half-Life 2 Hits Mac Steam Tomorrow; Teased via Epic Homage Trailer | publisher = [[Shacknews]] | first= Brian | last = Leahy | date = 2010-05-25 | accessdate = 2010-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Steam mac 1984 homage.jpg|right|thumb|500px|Prior to Steam's Mac OS X release, Valve released teaser ads that paid homage to famous Apple advertisements, such as the ''[[1984 (commercial)|1984]]'' commercial.]]
Originally planned for release in April 2010, Steam for Mac OS X was launched worldwide on May 12, 2010, following a successful beta period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamepron.com/news/2010/04/29/steam-for-mac-on-may-12/|title=Steam for Mac on May 12|last=Citizen|first=Jessica|date=2010-04-30|publisher=GamePron|accessdate=2010-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the Steam client, several features were made available to developers to take advantage of a cross-platform Source engine and platform and network capabilities using Steamworks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/28317/Valve_Dates_Steam_Mac_For_May_12_Updates_Steam_PC.php | title = Valve Dates Steam Mac For May 12, Updates Steam PC | first = Chris | last = Remo | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] | date = 2010-04-29 | accessdate= 2010-05-19} }}&lt;/ref&gt; Through ''SteamPlay'', the Mac OS X client allows players who have already purchased compatible products in the Windows version to re-download the Mac versions at no cost, allowing them to continue to play the game on the other platform; however some third party titles may require the user to purchase again to gain the cross-platform functionality.&lt;ref name=&quot;shacknews mac release&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/63793 | title = Steam's Cross-Platform PC/Mac Game Availability Explained: Some Must Be Bought Again | first = Chris | last = Faylor | date = 2010-05-13 | accessdate = 2010-05-13 | publisher = [[Shacknews]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Steam Cloud is cross-platform compatible. Multiplayer games can also be cross-compatible, allowing Windows and Mac players to play with each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;steam mac&quot;/&gt;

Upon launch, over 50 games, most supporting the ''SteamPlay'' feature, were available for the client. As part of the launch, Valve offered both PC and Mac users to download ''[[Portal (video game)|Portal]]'' for free during the first two weeks of launch.&lt;ref&gt;[http://store.steampowered.com/freeportal/ Welcome to Steam&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnet.com.au/steam-released-for-mac-portal-free-until-may-24-linux-soon-339303101.htm|title=Steam released for Mac, Portal free until May 24, Linux soon?}}&lt;/ref&gt; For some weeks after the Mac client launch, Valve expanded the catalog of offerings for the service on a weekly basis, with each week highlighting a new feature of the service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/100633-Steam-for-Mac-Sets-Portal-Free-UPDATED | title = Steam for Mac Sets Portal Free - UPDATED | first = Andy | last = Chalk | publisher = [[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]] | date = 2010-05-12 | accessdate = 2010-05-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Valve has released the native Mac OS X, [[OpenGL]] versions of ''[[Left 4 Dead]]'', ''[[Left 4 Dead 2]]'', ''[[Team Fortress 2]]'', ''[[Counter-Strike: Source]]'', ''[[Portal (video game)|Portal]]'', and [[Half-Life (series)|''Half-Life 2'']] and its episodes following Steam's release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2010/05/valves-not-so-subtle-hints.ars | title = Steam for Mac: the beta is limited, but the future is bright | first = Ben | last = Kuchera | date = 2010-05-04 | accessdate = 2010-05-19 | publisher = [[Ars Techinca]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Portal 2]]'', released in 2011, was the first Valve title simultaneously released on both the Windows and Mac versions of Steam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/28529/Steam_Launched_For_Mac_Portal_Offered_For_Free.php | title = Steam Launched For Mac, Portal Offered For Free | first = Eric | last= Carolli | date = 2010-05-12 | accessdate = 2010-05-19 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===PlayStation 3===
At [[Electronic Entertainment Expo 2010|E3 2010]], Newell announced that Steamworks would arrive on the [[PlayStation 3]] with ''[[Portal 2]]''. It will provide automatic updates, community support, downloadable content and other unannounced features.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamespot E3 Portal 2&quot;&gt;[http://e3.gamespot.com/story/6265808/portal-2-steamworks-ps3-bound-in-2011 E3 2010: Portal 2, Steamworks PS3-bound in 2011 - News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Portal 2]]''{{'}}s [[PlayStation 3]] release saw Steamworks make its debut on [[Video game console|consoles]]. Several features were offered including cross-platform play and [[instant messaging]], Steam Cloud for saved games, and the ability for PS3 owners to download Portal 2 from Steam (Windows or Mac) at no extra cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;eurogamer11-ps3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2011-01-18-portal-2-ps3-steam-cross-platform-play|title=Portal 2 PS3, Steam cross-platform play|publisher=[[Eurogamer]]|date=January 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Valve's ''[[Counter-Strike: Global Offensive]]'' will also support Steamworks and cross-platform features on the PlayStation 3, including using keyboard and mouse controls as an alternative to the gamepad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/36809/PS3_CounterStrike_GO_Gets_Added_Control_Options_CrossPlatform_Play.php | title = PS3 Counter-Strike: GO Gets Added Control Options, Cross-Platform Play  | first = Kyle | last = Orland | date = 2011-08-26 | accessdate = 2011-08-26 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Valve said they &quot;hope to expand upon this foundation with more Steam features and functionality in DLC and future content releases&quot;.

===Other platforms===
Based on Valve's website &quot;There are no plans to create a native [[Linux]] Steam Client at this time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://support.steampowered.com/kb_article.php?ref=1313-QIPD-5381 Platforms supported by Steam - Browse Steam Glossary - Knowledge Base - Steam Support&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Following the announcement of Steam for [[Mac OS X]], Linux benchmark and news website ''[[Phoronix]]'' found Linux-related references in a beta release of the Mac Steam client. This was followed later by the discovery of files for an incomplete Linux client available for download on Valve's own web servers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.downloadsquad.com/2010/04/22/steam-new-mac-client-hints-at-linux-support/ | title = Steam's new Mac client hints at Linux support | accessdate = 2010-06-07 | last = Mathews | first = Lee | date = 2010-04-22 | work = [[Download Squad]] | publisher = [[Weblogs, Inc.]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slashgear.com/steam-for-linux-next-on-cards-after-os-x-0484157/ Steam for Linux next on cards after OS X?] SlashGear, May 4, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; On May 12, 2010, ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' claimed that Valve had confirmed that a Linux client was planned to be released &quot;in the coming months&quot;, but gave no other details.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/apple/7715209/Steam-for-Mac-goes-live.html Steam for Mac goes live] Telegraph.co.uk, May 12, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; This claim was then repeated on other websites as hearsay evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.linuxinsider.com/story/70007.html | title = Who Will Show Up to Linux's Steam-Powered Playground? | accessdate = 2010-08-13 | date = 2010-05-17 | work = Linux Insider | author = Katherine Noyes}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Valve has since denied working on a Linux version of Steam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.engadget.com/2010/08/23/valve-denies-having-a-linux-version-of-steam-in-the-works/ | title = Valve denies having a Linux version of Steam in the works | accessdate = 2010-09-28 | date = 2010-08-23 | work = Engadget | author = Paul Miller}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Steam is compatible with newest [[Wine (software)|Wine]] layer, and most games operate correctly, although some run slow and require external libraries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://developer.valvesoftware.com/wiki/Steam_under_Linux |title=Steam under Linux - Valve Developer Community |publisher=Developer.valvesoftware.com |date=2011-04-22 |accessdate=2011-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.steamgamesonlinux.com/ |title=Linux + Wine + Steam |publisher=Steam Games on Linux |date= |accessdate=2011-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Xbox 360 currently has no support for Steamworks, but Newell has indicated that they would like to bring the service to the console through the game ''[[Counter-Strike: Global Offensive]]'', which would allow them to provide the same feature set that they can for the PlayStation 3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2011-08-25-valves-gabe-newell-interview | title = Valve's Gabe Newell - Interview | first = Wesley | last = Yin-Poole | date = 2011-08-25 | accessdate = 2011-09-12 | publisher = [[Eurogamer]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Market share and impact ==
Sales figures for Steam have not been released by Valve. However, [[Stardock]], the previous owner of competing platform [[Impulse (content delivery)|Impulse]], estimated that, as of 2009, Steam had a 70% share of the digital distribution market for video games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamasutra.com/php-bin/news_index.php?story=26158 |title=Stardock Reveals Impulse, Steam Market Share Estimates |last=Graft|first=Kris|publisher=[[Gamasutra]] |accessdate=November 21, 2009|date=November 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 2011, ''[[Forbes]]'' reported that Steam sales constituted 50 to 70% of the $4 billion market for downloaded PC games and that Steam offered game producers [[gross margin]]s of 70% of purchase price, compared with 30% at retail.&lt;ref name=forbes-gnprofile&gt;{{cite web|last=Chiang|first=Oliver|title=The Master of Online Mayhem|url=http://www.forbes.com/forbes/2011/0228/technology-gabe-newell-videogames-valve-online-mayhem.html|publisher=[[Forbes]]|accessdate=14 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Recettear: An Item Shop's Tale]]'' sold more than 140,000 units, which its localization distributor, Carpe Fulgur, attribute in part to Steam and its sales.&lt;ref name=&quot;rps postmortem&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.rockpapershotgun.com/2011/01/17/post-mortem-recettear/ | title = Post Mortem: Recettear | first = Alec | last = Meer | date = 2011-01-17 | accessdate = 2011-01-17 | publisher = [[Rock, Paper, Shotgun]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Magicka]]'' sold 30,000 copies on its day of release in January 2011,&lt;ref name=magicka-day1&gt;{{cite web|title=Magicka Charms its Way to the Top of Steam|url=http://www.magickagame.com/news/2011/1/magicka-charms-its-way-to-the-top-of-steam|publisher=[[Paradox Interactive]]|accessdate=26 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and went on to sell 200,000 in 17 days.&lt;ref name=magicka-200k&gt;{{cite web|title=Interview: Magicka's producer talks about reaching the 200,000 sales mark and more|url=http://news.bigdownload.com/2011/02/11/interview-magickas-producer-talks-about-reaching-the-200-000-s/|publisher=[[BigDownload.com]]|accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Garry's Mod]]'' sold 312,541 in its first two years&lt;ref name=gmod-sales&gt;{{cite web|last=Newman|first=Garry|title=GMod10 is 2 years old today!|url=http://www.garry.tv/?p=694|accessdate=29 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and reached 1,000,000 after five years&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Newman|first=Garry|title=Over 1,000,000 sold!|url=http://www.garrysmod.com/2011/07/26/over-1000000-sold/|accessdate=29 August 2011|date=July 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with yearly sales growth of 33%.&lt;ref name=gmod-growth&gt;{{cite web|last=Newman|first=Garry|title=Garry’s Mod Yearly Sales|url=http://www.garry.tv/?p=2212|accessdate=9 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

In November 2011, it was revealed by the developer of [[The Witcher 2: Assassins of Kings]] that Steam was responsible for 80% of the online sales of the game&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamepro.com/article/news/224884/steam-sells-4-times-more-witcher-2-copies-than-all-competitors-combined/|title=Steam Sells 4 Times More Witcher 2 Copies Than All Competitors Combined|accessdate=2011-11-13|publisher=[[GamePro]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.gamepro.com/article/news/224884/steam-sells-4-times-more-witcher-2-copies-than-all-competitors-combined/&amp;date=2011-11-30+19:07:46|archivedate=2011-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==History==
===Beginnings===
&lt;div class=&quot;floatright&quot;&gt;
&lt;timeline&gt;
ImageSize = width:250 height:450
PlotArea = left:50 bottom:10 top:10 right:0

DateFormat = yyyy
Period = from:2002 till:2012
TimeAxis = orientation:vertical order:reverse
ScaleMajor = unit:year increment:1 start:2002
ScaleMinor = unit:year increment:1 start:2002

Colors =
 id:blue value:rgb(0,0,0)
 id:red value:rgb(0.9,0.05,0.05)

Define $dx = 25

Define $up = shift:($dx,1)
Define $dw = shift:($dx,-8)

PlotData=
 bar:Games anchor:till color:red width:15 textcolor:blue align:left fontsize:S mark:(line,white) shift:($dx,-4)
 from:2002 till:2012
 at:2002 shift:($dx,-20) text:&quot;Revealed to public&quot;
 at:2002 shift:($dx,-35) text:&quot;Beta period begins&quot;
 at:2003 shift:($dx,-40) text:&quot;Official release&quot;
 at:2004 shift:($dx,-40) text:&quot;[[Half-Life 2]] release&quot;
 at:2005 shift:($dx,-40) text:&quot;First publisher partnership&quot;
 at:2006
 at:2007 shift:($dx,-35) text:&quot;Steam Community launched&quot;
 at:2008 shift:($dx,-15) text:&quot;Steamworks released&quot;
 at:2008 shift:($dx,-40) text:&quot;Matchmaking released&quot;
 at:2009 shift:($dx,-15) text:&quot;Steam Cloud released&quot;
 at:2010 shift:($dx,-15) text:&quot;UI Update released&quot;
 at:2010 shift:($dx,-30) text:&quot;[[Mac OS X]] client released&quot;
 at:2010 shift:($dx,-45) text:&quot;Translation Server opened&quot;
 at:2011 shift:($dx,-15) text:&quot;[[PS3]] [[Steamworks]] integration&quot;
 at:2011 shift:($dx,-30) text:&quot;[[Portal 2]] cross-platform play&quot;
&lt;/timeline&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Prior to Steam, Valve had problems releasing updates for their online games, such as ''[[Counter-Strike]]'', wherein a patch would result in the disconnection of the larger part of the online user base for several days. They decided to make a platform which would update games automatically, and implement better [[anti-piracy]] and [[anti-cheat]] measures. Valve originally approached several companies—including [[Microsoft]], [[Yahoo!]], and [[RealNetworks]]—to build a client with these features, but all turned them down.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lee|first=James|title=The Last of the Independents?|url=http://www.gamesindustry.biz/articles/the-last-of-the-independents-|publisher=GamesIndustry.biz|accessdate=2010-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steam's development began at an uncertain date prior to 2002. Working titles included &quot;Grid&quot; and &quot;Gazelle&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gameguru.in/pc/2007/24/steam-registers-13-million-active-accounts/|title=Steam Registers 13 million Active Accounts|accessdate=2007-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was revealed to the public on 22 March 2002 at the [[Game Developers Conference]], and was presented purely as a distribution network.&lt;ref name=&quot;steam-announced&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gamespot.com/news/2857298.html|title=GDC 2002: Valve unveils Steam|publisher=[[GameSpot|GameSpot.com]]|date=22 March 2002|accessdate=7 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; To demonstrate the ease of integrating Steam to a game, [[Relic Entertainment]] had created a special version of ''[[Impossible Creatures]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Walker|first=Trey|title=GDC: Steam pushes software over Net|url=http://www.zdnet.com/news/gdc-steam-pushes-software-over-net/121632|publisher=ZDNet|accessdate=2010-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game was ultimately not released on Steam, however.

Valve partnered with a number of companies including [[AT&amp;T]], [[Acer Inc.|Acer]] and [[GameSpy]] Industries. The first [[Mod (computer gaming)|mod]] on the system was ''[[Day of Defeat]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;salon2002&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=James |first=Wagner |url=http://dir.salon.com/story/tech/feature/2002/04/16/modding/index.html |title=Triumph of the mod&amp;nbsp;– Salon.com |publisher=Dir.salon.com |date=2002-04-16 |accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;herring1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.redherring.com/Home/6517 |title=A small games startup is gunning for big publishers |publisher=Redherring.com |date=2002-05-05 |accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[#Mods|Mods]].)

The Steam client was first made available for download in 2002 during the beta period for ''[[Counter-Strike]]'' 1.6. At that time, its primary function was streamlining the patch process common in online [[computer game]]s. Installation and use of Steam was mandatory for ''Counter-Strike'' 1.6 beta testers, but Steam remained an optional component. 80,000–300,000 gamers tested the system when it was in its beta period.&lt;ref name=&quot;salon2002&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadbandreports.com/shownews/32475 |title=Steam Powered&amp;nbsp;– Broadband distribution system to go live&amp;nbsp;– dslreports.com |publisher=Broadbandreports.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The system and web site choked under the strain of thousands of users simultaneously attempting to play the latest version of Counter-Strike.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbr1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadbandreports.com/shownews/32981 |title=Losing Steam&amp;nbsp;– Broadband distribution's rocky road&amp;nbsp;– dslreports.com |publisher=Broadbandreports.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the [[World Opponent Network]] was shut down and replaced by Steam. The online features of games which required World Opponent Network ceased to work unless they were converted to Steam.

Around this time, Valve began negotiating contracts with several publishers and independent developers to release their products on Steam. ''[[Rag Doll Kung Fu]]'' and ''[[Darwinia (computer game)|Darwinia]]'' are two examples, and Canadian publisher [[Strategy First]] announced in December 2005 that it would be partnering with Valve for digital distribution of current and future titles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | publisher = [[Strategy First]] | date = 2005-12-08 | title = Strategy First to Deliver Multiple Titles On-Line via Steam | url = http://www.strategyfirst.com/press/DisplayArticle.asp?sLanguageCode=EN&amp;iArticleID=3250 | accessdate = 2010-07-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, [[Gabe Newell]], the head of Valve, said he was offering mod teams a game engine license and distribution over Steam for $995.&lt;ref name=&quot;salon2002&quot; /&gt;

===Profitability===
[[File:Todd Hollenshead - 1072682961 - pamnesiac.jpg|thumb|[[Todd Hollenshead]], CEO of [[id Software]], at [[QuakeCon]] 2007 presenting the release of all id Software games on Steam]]

In 2005, the first third-party games began to appear on Steam. Valve also announced that Steam was starting to be profitable, if only due to some highly successful Valve games. Although digital distribution was still no match to retail in terms of sales volume, profit margins for Valve and developers were far bigger on Steam than at retail.&lt;ref name=&quot;hr-2005&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/search/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000955338|title=Digital distribution: Keep the money and run?|publisher=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=13 June 2005|accessdate=31 January 2010|quote=Valve won't talk about how many units it's sold through Steam, but Lombardi describes the venture as being &quot;extremely successful. Even though the lion's share of our sales is still at retail, the digital units are wildly more profitable for us.&quot;|archiveurl=http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/37380|archivedate=14 June 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, big developer-publishers such as [[id Software]], [[Eidos Interactive]] and [[Capcom]] started to distribute their games on Steam. In May 2007, 13&amp;nbsp;million accounts had been created on Steam, and 150 games were for sale on the platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url         = http://store.steampowered.com/news/1050/
| title       = Steam Surpasses 13 Million Accounts
| publisher   = [[Valve Corporation]]
| accessdate  = 31 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2007, the release of ''[[The Orange Box]]'', and the distribution of high-profile games such as ''[[BioShock]]'', ''[[Call of Duty 4: Modern Warfare]]'', and ''[[S.T.A.L.K.E.R.: Shadow of Chernobyl]]'', helped increase Steam's popularity.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

===Steam Translation Server===
In March 2010 Valve launched the [https://translation.steampowered.com/ Steam Translation Server], which is a service that allows Steam users to help in the translation of Steam and a selected library of Steam games.  The service was undergoing a closed beta until October 2010. Since then, every Steam user has the ability to apply as a translator.

===November 2011 hack===
On November 6, 2011, Steam temporarily closed the community forums, citing potential [[hack (computer security)|hacking threats]] to the service. Subsequently, on November 10, Valve reported that the hack included a compromise of one of their customer databases, potentially allowing the perpetrators to access customer information including encrypted password and credit card details. At that time, Valve was not aware if the intruders actually accessed this information or discovered the encryption method, but warned users to be alert for fraudulent activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;arssteamhack&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2011/11/valve-confirms-steam-hack-credit-cards-personal-info-may-be-stolen.ars | title=Valve confirms Steam hack: credit cards, personal info may be stolen | first=Casey | last=Johnson | date=11-10-2011 | accessdate=11-10-2011 | publisher = [[Ars Technica]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;registerhack&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/11/09/steam_forum_hack/| title=Steam games forum down amid hack fears| last=Leyden | first=John | accessdate=11-10-2011 | date=11-09-2011 | publisher = [[The Register]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Regional restrictions and pricing===
[[File:Steam regional limitation.PNG|thumb|Some games purchased in one region become unplayable if user moves to another.]]
Steam allows developers and publishers to change prices and restrict game availability depending on the user's location. This can cause some games to cost more than retail prices, despite digital distribution removing the costs of manufacturing, packaging, design, and logistics.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnetsteamed&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnet.com.au/broadband/0,239036008,339288255,00.htm|title=Getting Steamed: digital distribution for games isn't there yet|last=Craig|first=Simms|date=April 18, 2008|accessdate=April 25, 2008|publisher=[[CNET]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lovemoney.com/news/ways-to-save/how-your-pc-can-entertain-you-for-less-4028.aspx |title=How your PC can entertain you for less |publisher=Lovemoney.com |date=2009-10-14 |accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;steamworks_pubservs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://steamgames.com/steamworks/publishingservices.php|title=Steamworks publishing services|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=November 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Valve also restricts game registration and playability to the buyer's country of residence. One example of this regional restriction can be seen where Valve uses Steam's authentication to prevent boxed versions of their games sold in Russia and Thailand, which are priced significantly lower than elsewhere, from being used outside those territories.&lt;ref name=&quot;thai_restrictions_07&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/49656|title=Valve Responds to Steam Territory Deactivations (Updated)|last=Breckon|first=Nick|date=October 29, 2007|accessdate=November 26, 2007|publisher=ShackNews}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steam offers products in four [[currencies]]: [[US Dollar]], [[Euro]], [[Pound Sterling]] and [[Russian Ruble]]. The currency is selected automatically based on the user's location, and cannot be changed. Steam has been heavily criticized by European users for pricing games much higher in [[Eurozone]] countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.techpowerup.com/79349/Valve_Inflicts_European_Gamers_with_$1_=_%E2%82%AC1_Equation.html|title=Valve Inflicts European Gamers with $1 = €1 Equation|date=December 19, 2008|accessdate=December 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Authentication===
It is necessary to authenticate every Steam game online, whether purchased via Steam itself or installed via a retail disc, the first time it is played.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Reimer |first=Jeremy |url=http://arstechnica.com/old/content/2005/09/5351.ars |title=Microsoft previews online software purchasing with the Digital Locker |publisher=Ars Technica |date=2005-09-26 |accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the initial authentication, an offline mode allows games to be run without being connected to your Steam account.

According to the Steam Subscriber Agreement, Steam's availability is not guaranteed and Valve is under no legal obligation to release an update disabling the authentication system in the event that Steam becomes permanently unavailable.&lt;ref name=&quot;ssa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://store.steampowered.com/subscriber_agreement/|title=Steam Subscriber Agreement|publisher=Valve Corporation|accessdate=January 31, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, [[Gabe Newell]], CEO of Valve, said in a post on the Steam User Forums that &quot;Unless there was some situation I don't understand, we would presumably disable authentication before any event that would preclude the authentication servers from being available.&quot; He added, &quot;We've tested disabling authentication, and it works.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forums.steampowered.com/forums/showpost.php?p=10642189&amp;postcount=28|title=What will happen if Steam go bust?|last=Newell|first=Gabe|accessdate=21 November 2009|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100605062932/http://forums.steampowered.com/forums/showpost.php?p=10642189&amp;postcount=28|archivedate=2010-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Distribution policies===
In July 2011, several Electronic Arts games were removed from Steam. EA has stated that this is because of disputes over Valve's policies regarding how Downloadable Content can be distributed to Steam users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Plunkett|first=Luke|title=EA &quot;Hopes to Work out an Agreement&quot; With Steam Over Disappearing Games|url=http://kotaku.com/5825464/ea-hopes-to-work-out-an-agreement-with-steam-over-disappearing-games|accessdate=11 August 2011|date=2011-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a blogpost [[Minecraft]] developer [[Markus Persson]] also cited similar content-related policies as a reason of the game not being available through Steam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Notch |url=http://notch.tumblr.com/post/9550850116/why-no-steam-notch |title=Why no Steam, Notch? : The Word of Notch |publisher=Notch.tumblr.com |date=2011-08-29 |accessdate=2011-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Steam games]]
*[[Games for Windows - Live]]
*[[Origin (digital distribution platform)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Steam (content delivery)|Steam}}
* [http://store.steampowered.com/ Steam website] - Official website
* [http://steampowered.com/steamworks Steamworks] - Steamworks information
* [http://steamcommunity.com/ The Steam Community] - Web access to Steam's social network
* [http://developer.valvesoftware.com/wiki/Category:Steam Valve Developer Community/Steam] - Steam category on the official VDC Wiki

{{Valve technology}}
{{Digital Distribution Platforms}}
{{URI scheme}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Steam (Content Delivery)}}
[[Category:2003 introductions]]
[[Category:Cloud computing]]
[[Category:Digital rights management]]
[[Category:Electronic commerce]]
[[Category:Mac OS X software]]
[[Category:Multiplayer gaming service]]
[[Category:Online retailers]]
[[Category:Software based on Webkit]]
[[Category:Valve Corporation]]
[[Category:Windows software]]

{{Link FA|de}}
{{Link FA|ru}}
[[ar:ستيم (برنامج)]]
[[bg:Steam]]
[[ca:Steam]]
[[cs:Steam]]
[[da:Steam]]
[[de:Steam]]
[[es:Steam]]
[[fr:Steam]]
[[ko:스팀 (플랫폼)]]
[[ia:Steam]]
[[it:Steam (informatica)]]
[[he:Steam]]
[[hu:Steam]]
[[nl:Steam (softwareplatform)]]
[[ja:Steam]]
[[no:Valve Corporation#Steam]]
[[pl:Steam]]
[[pt:Steam]]
[[ru:Steam]]
[[sk:Steam (program)]]
[[sl:Steam]]
[[fi:Steam]]
[[sv:Steam (datorspelsteknik)]]
[[tr:Steam (yazılım)]]
[[uk:Steam]]
[[zh:Steam]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
