<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9004976" ns="0" title="History of the Encyclopædia Britannica"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:History of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}
The ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'' has been published continuously since 1768, appearing in 15 official editions. Several editions have been amended with multi-volume &quot;supplements&quot; (3rd–6th) or undergone drastic re-organizations (15th). In recent years, digital versions of the ''Britannica'' have been developed, both online and on [[optical media]]. Since the early 1930s, the ''Britannica'' has developed several &quot;spin-off&quot; products to leverage its reputation as a reliable reference work and educational tool.

== Historical context ==
{{See also|Encyclopedia|List of encyclopedias}}

Encyclopedias of various types had been published since antiquity, beginning with the collected works of [[Aristotle]] and the ''Natural History'' of [[Pliny the Elder]], the latter having 2493 articles in 37 books. Encyclopedias were published in Europe and China throughout the [[Middle Ages]], such as the delightful ''Satyricon'' of [[Martianus Minneus Felix Capella]] (early 5th century), the ''Speculum majus'' (''The Great Mirror'') of [[Vincent of Beauvais]] (1250), and ''Encyclopedia septem tomis distincta'' (''A Seven-Part Encyclopedia'') by [[Johann Heinrich Alsted]] (1630). Most early encyclopedias did not include biographies of living people and were written in Latin, although some encyclopedias were translated into English, such as ''De proprietatibus rerum (On the properties of things)'' (1240) by [[Bartholomeus Anglicus]]. However, English-composed encyclopedias appeared in the 18th century, beginning with ''Lexicon technicum, or A Universal English Dictionary of Arts and Sciences'' by [[John Harris (writer)|John Harris]] (two volumes, published 1704 and 1710, respectively), which contained articles by such contributors as [[Isaac Newton]]. [[Ephraim Chambers]] wrote a very popular two-volume ''[[Cyclopaedia, or Universal Dictionary of Arts and Sciences|Cyclopedia]]'' in 1728, which went through multiple editions and awakened publishers to the enormous profit potential of encyclopedias. Although not all encyclopedias succeeded commercially, their elements sometimes inspired future encyclopedias; for example, the failed two-volume ''A Universal History of Arts and Sciences'' of [[Dennis de Coetlogon]] (published 1745) grouped its topics into long self-contained treatises, an organization that likely inspired the &quot;new plan&quot; of the ''Britannica''. The first encyclopedia to include biographies of living people was the 64-volume ''[[Grosses Universal-Lexicon]]'' (published 1732–1759) of [[Johann Heinrich Zedler]], who argued that death alone should not render people notable.

==Earliest editions (1st–6th, 1768–1824)==
===[[Encyclopædia Britannica First Edition|1st edition]]===
[[Image:Britannica 1st ed.jpg|thumb|Title page from the first edition]]
[[Image:Britannica 1st ed. page.jpg|thumb|right|A page from the first edition. The flow of short entries is interrupted here by one of the major treatises.]]

The ''Britannica'' was the idea of [[Colin Macfarquhar]], a bookseller and printer, and [[Andrew Bell (engraver)|Andrew Bell]], an engraver, both of [[Edinburgh]]. They conceived of the ''Britannica'' as a conservative reaction to the French ''[[Encyclopédie]]'' of [[Denis Diderot]] (published 1751–1766), which was widely viewed as heretical. Ironically, the ''Encyclopédie'' had begun as a French translation of the popular English encyclopedia, ''[[Cyclopaedia, or Universal Dictionary of Arts and Sciences|Cyclopaedia]]'' published by [[Ephraim Chambers]] in 1728. Although later editions of Chambers' ''Cyclopaedia'' were still popular, and despite the commercial failure of other English encyclopedias, Macfarquhar and Bell were inspired by the intellectual ferment of the [[Scottish Enlightenment]] and thought the time ripe for a new encyclopedia &quot;compiled upon a new plan&quot;.

Needing an editor, the two chose a 28-year-old scholar named [[William Smellie (encyclopedist)|William Smellie]] who was offered 200 [[pound sterling|pounds sterling]] to produce the encyclopedia in 100 parts (called &quot;numbers&quot; and equivalent to thick pamphlets), which were later bound into three volumes. The first number appeared on December 6, 1768 in Edinburgh, priced [[British sixpence coin|sixpence]] or 8 [[pence]] on finer paper. The ''Britannica'' was published under the [[pseudonym]] &quot;A Society of Gentlemen in Scotland&quot;, possibly referring to the many gentlemen who had bought subscriptions.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; By releasing the numbers in weekly installments, the ''Britannica'' was completed in 1771, having 2,391 pages. The numbers were bound in three equally sized volumes covering Aa–Bzo, Caaba–Lythrum, and Macao–Zyglophyllum; an estimated 3,000 sets were eventually sold, priced at 12&amp;nbsp;pounds sterling apiece.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica History&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://corporate.britannica.com/company_info.html
| title = History of Encyclopædia Britannica and Britannica Online
| accessdate = October 17, 2006
| publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Encyclopædia Britannica First Edition|The 1st edition]] also featured 160 beautiful copperplate illustrations engraved by Bell. Some illustrations were shocking to some readers, such as the three pages depicting female pelvises and fetuses in the [[midwife]]ry article; King [[George III of the United Kingdom|George III]] commanded that these pages be ripped from every copy.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

The key idea that set the ''Britannica'' apart was to group related topics together into longer essays, that were then organized alphabetically. Previous English encyclopedias had generally listed related terms separately in their alphabetical order, rather like a modern technical dictionary, an approach that the ''Britannica's''' management derided as &quot;dismembering the sciences&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;online encyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/EMS_EUD/ENCYCLOPAEDIA.html
| title = Online Encyclopedia
| accessdate = September 27, 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although anticipated by [[Dennis de Coetlogon]], the idea for this &quot;new plan&quot; is generally ascribed to [[Colin Macfarquhar]], although [[William Smellie (encyclopedist)|Smellie]] claimed it as his own invention.

Smellie wrote most of the first edition, borrowing liberally from the authors of his era, including [[Voltaire]], [[Benjamin Franklin]], [[Alexander Pope]] and [[Samuel Johnson]]. He later said:&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

{{quote|I wrote most of it, my lad, and snipped out from books enough material for the printer. With pastepot and scissors I composed it!|[[William Smellie (encyclopedist)|William Smellie]]|at a meeting of the Crochallan Fencibles}}

The vivid prose and easy navigation of the first edition led to strong demand for a second. Although this edition has been faulted for its imperfect scholarship, Smellie argued that the ''Britannica'' should be given the benefit of the doubt:

{{quote|With regard to errors in general, whether falling under the denomination of mental, typographical or accidental, we are conscious of being able to point out a greater number than any critic whatever. Men who are acquainted with the innumerable difficulties of attending the execution of a work of such an extensive nature will make proper allowances. To these we appeal, and shall rest satisfied with the judgment they pronounce.|[[William Smellie (encyclopedist)|William Smellie]]|in the Preface to the 1st edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

Smellie strove to make ''Britannica'' as usable as possible, saying that &quot;utility ought to be the principal intention of every publication. Wherever this intention does not plainly appear, neither the books nor their authors have the smallest claim to the approbation of mankind&quot;. On the occasion of the [[Bicentennial of the Encyclopædia Britannica|200th anniversary of the 1st edition]], [[Encyclopædia Britannica Inc.]] published a facsimile of the 1st edition, even including &quot;age spots&quot; on the paper. This has been periodically reprinted and is still part of Britannica's product line.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Encyclopædia Britannica, 1st edition reprint | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica Inc. | year = 2004 | isbn = 0852290667}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--NOTE: Please DO NOT link directly to Amazon, Britannica's On-Line store, or other commercial book sellers. This is what Wikipedia's ISBN feature is designed for. --&gt;

===[[Encyclopædia Britannica Second Edition|2nd edition]]===
After the success of the first edition, a more ambitious [[Encyclopædia Britannica Second Edition|second edition]] was begun in 1776, with the addition of history and biography articles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trivia Library 1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.trivia-library.com/b/history-of-the-encyclopedia-britannica-part-1.htm
| title = History of the Encyclopædia Britannica Part 1
| accessdate = October 19, 2006
| publisher = Trivia-Library.com
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smellie declined to be editor, principally because he objected to the addition of biography. Macfarquhar took over the role himself, aided by pharmacist [[James Tytler]], M.A.,&lt;ref&gt; The degree of M.A. is found after his name in the 11th edition of Britannica in the article Encyclopedia, vol. 9., p. 378 &lt;/ref&gt; who was known as an able writer and willing to work for a very low wage.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Wells | first = James M. | year = 1968 | title = The Circle of Knowledge: Encyclopaedias Past and Present | publisher = The Newberry Library | location = Chicago | id = Library of Congress catalog number 68-21708}}&lt;/ref&gt; Macfarquhar and Bell rescued Tytler from Holyrood Palace, a debtors' prison, and employed him for seven years at 17 shillings per week. Tytler wrote many science and history articles and almost all of the minor articles; by [[Robert Burns]]' estimate, Tytler wrote over three-quarters of the second edition.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Kogan | first = Herman | year = 1958 | title = The Great EB: The Story of the Encyclopædia Britannica | publisher = The University of Chicago Press | location = Chicago | id = Library of Congress catalog number 58-8379}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compared to the 1st edition, the second had five times as many long articles (150), including &quot;Scotland&quot; (84 pages), &quot;Optics&quot; (132 pages), and &quot;Medicine&quot; (309 pages), which had their own indices. The second edition was published in 181 numbers from 21 June 1777 to 18 September 1784; these numbers were bound into ten volumes dated 1778–1783, having 8,595 pages and 340 plates again engraved by [[Andrew Bell (engraver)|Andrew Bell]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica History&quot;/&gt; A [[pagination]] error caused page 8000 to follow page 7099. All the maps of this edition are found in a single 195-page article, &quot;[[Geography]]&quot;.

The second edition improved greatly upon the 1st, but is still notable for the large amount of archaic information it contains. For example, &quot;Chemistry&quot; goes into great detail on an obsolete system of what would now be called alchemy, in which earth, air, water and fire are named elements containing various amounts of [[phlogiston]]. Tytler also describes the architecture of [[Noah's Ark]] in detail (illustrated with a copperplate engraving) and, following [[James Ussher|Bishop Ussher]], includes a remarkably precise [[geochronology|chronology for the Earth]], beginning with its creation on 23 October 4004 B.C. and noting that the [[Deluge (mythology)|Great Flood]] of 2348 B.C. lasted for exactly 777 days. The 2nd edition also reports a cure for [[tuberculosis]]:

{{quote|He chose a spot of ground on which no plants had been sown, and there he made a hole large and deep enough to admit the patient up to the chin. The interstices of the pit were then carefully filled up with the fresh mould, so that the earth might everywhere come in contact with the patient's body. In this situation the patient suffered to remain till he began to shiver or felt himself uneasy...The patient was then taken out, and, after being wrapped in a linen cloth, was placed upon a mattress, and two hours afterwards his whole body was rubbed with the ointment composed of the leaves of the ''[[solanum nigrum]]'' and hog's lard.|[[James Tytler]]|in the 2nd edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

and a somewhat melancholy article on &quot;[[Love]]&quot; that persisted in the ''Britannica'' for nearly a century (until its 9th edition):

{{quote|As the force of love prevails, sighs grow deeper; a tremor affects the heart and pulse; the countenance is alternately pale and red; the voice is suppressed in the sauces; the eyes grow dim; cold sweats break out; sleep absents itself, at least until the morning; the secretions become disturbed; and a loss of appetite, a hectic fever, melancholy, or perhaps madness, if not death, constitutes the sad catastrophe.|[[James Tytler]]|in the 2nd–8th editions of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

Like the first edition, the second was sold in sections by subscription at the printing shop of [[Colin MacFarquhar]]. When finished in 1784, complete sets were sold at Charles Elliot's book shop in Edinburgh for 10 pounds, unbound. Over 1,500 copies of the second edition were sold this way by Elliot in less than one year,&lt;ref&gt;''The Great EB, the story of Encyclopedia Britannica'', Herman Kogan, p. 21 &lt;/ref&gt; making the second edition enough of a financial success that a more ambitious third edition was begun a few years later.

The long period of time during which this edition was written makes the later volumes more updated than the earlier ones. Volume 10, published in 1783 after the [[Revolutionary War]] was over, gives in the entry for Virginia: &quot;Virginia, late one of the British colonies, now one of the United States of North America...&quot;&lt;ref&gt; http://www.hyzercreek.com/britannica.htm&lt;/ref&gt; but the entry in Volume 2 for Boston, published in 1778, states, &quot;Boston, the capital of New England in North America, ....The following is a description of this capital before the commencement of the present American war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt; Encyclopedia Britannica, second edition. Edinburgh. &lt;/ref&gt;

The causes of the [[American Revolution|Revolution]] are outlined concisely by Tytler in the article &quot;Colonies&quot; thus:

{{quote|Because several of the colonies had claimed the soul and exclusive right of imposing taxes upon themselves, the statute 6 Geo. III. c. 12 expressly declares, that all his Majesty's colonies in America, have been, are, and of right ought to be, subordinate to and dependent upon the imperial crown and parliament of Great Britain; who have full power and authority to make laws and statutes of sufficient validity to bind the colonies and people of America, subjects to the crown of Great Britain in all cases whatsoever. And the attempting to enforce this by other acts of Parliament, penalties, and at last by military power, gave rise, as is well known, to the present revolt of our colonies.}}

At the end of volume 10 is a 200-page addendum (page 8996 to 9195) entitled &quot;Appendix containing articles omitted and others further explained or improved, together with corrections of errors and of wrong references.&quot;

===3rd edition===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Encyclopædia Britannica]] --&gt;
The [[Encyclopædia Britannica Third Edition|third edition]] was published from 1788 to 1797 in 300 weekly numbers (1 shilling apiece); these numbers were collected and bound in 30 parts (10 shilling, sixpence each) and finally in 18 volumes with 14,579 pages and 542 plates. [[Colin Macfarquhar|Macfarquhar]] again edited this edition up to &quot;Mysteries&quot; but died in 1793 (aged 48) of &quot;mental exhaustion&quot;; his work was taken over by [[George Gleig]], later Bishop Gleig of Brechin (consecrated 30 October 1808). [[Andrew Bell (engraver)|Andrew Bell]], Macfarquhar's partner, bought the rights to the ''Britannica'' from his heirs.

Nearly doubling the scope of the 2nd edition, Macfarquhar's encyclopedic vision was finally realized. Recruited by Gleig, several illustrious authorities contributed to this edition, such as Dr. [[Thomas Thomson (chemist)|Thomas Thomson]], who introduced the first usage of chemical symbols in the 1801 supplement (see below), and [[John Robison (physicist)|John Robison]], Secretary of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, who wrote several well-regarded articles on [[natural philosophy]]. The third edition established the foundation of the ''Britannica'' as an important and definitive reference work for much of the next century. This edition was also enormously profitable, yielding 42,000&amp;nbsp;pounds sterling profit on the sale of roughly 10,000 copies. The 3rd edition began the tradition (continued to this day) of dedicating the ''Britannica'' to the reigning British monarch, then [[George III of the United Kingdom|King George III]]; calling him &quot;the Father of Your People, and enlightened Patron of Arts, Sciences and Literature&quot;, Gleig wished

{{quote|...that, by the Wisdom of Your Councils, and the Vigour of Your Fleets and Armies, Your MAJESTY may be enabled soon to restore Peace to Europe; that You may again have leisure to extend Your Royal Care to the Improvement of Arts, and the Advancement of Knowledge; that You May Reign long over a Free, Happy and a Loyal People...|[[George Gleig]]|in the Dedication of the 3rd edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

The [[Encyclopædia Britannica Third Edition|3rd edition]] is also famous for its bold article on &quot;Motion&quot;, which erroneously rejects [[Isaac Newton]]'s theory of [[gravitation]]. Instead, Dr. Gleig, or more likely, [[James Tytler]], wrote that gravity is caused by the [[Fire (classical element)|classical element of fire]]. He seems to have been swayed by [[William Jones (ecclesiastic)|William Jones]]' ''Essay on the First Principles of Natural Philosophy'' (1762), which in turn was based on [[John Hutchinson (writer)|John Hutchinson's]] [[Master of Arts (Oxford, Cambridge and Dublin)|MA thesis]], ''Moses' Principia'', which was written in 1724 but rejected by [[Oxford University]]. Nevertheless, Gleig was sanguine about the errors of the 3rd edition, echoing [[William Smellie (encyclopedist)|William Smellie]]'s sentiment in the 1st edition quoted above:

{{quote|For perfection seems to be incompatible with the nature of works constructed on such a plan, and embracing such a variety of subjects.|[[George Gleig]]|in the 3rd edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

The first &quot;American&quot; encyclopedia, ''[[Dobson's Encyclopædia]]'', was based almost entirely on the 3rd edition of the ''Britannica'' and published at nearly the same time (1788–1798), together with an analogous supplement (1803), by the Scottish-born printer, [[Thomas Dobson (printer)|Thomas Dobson]]. The first United States [[copyright]] law was passed on 30 May 1790 &amp;mdash; although anticipated by Section 8 of Article I of the [[United States Constitution]] (ratified 4 March 1789) &amp;mdash; but did not protect foreign publications such as the ''Britannica''. Piracy of the ''Britannica'' in America remained a problem through the 9th edition (1889). Pirated copies were also sold in Dublin by James Moore under the title, ''Moore's Dublin Edition, Encyclopædia Britannica''; this was an exact reproduction of the ''Britannica''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s 3rd edition.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; By contrast, Dobson's work had various corrections and amendments for American readers.

In 1797, [[Fath Ali Shah]] was given a complete set of the ''Britannica'''s 3rd edition, which he read completely; after this feat, he extended his royal title to include &quot;Most Formidable Lord and Master of the Encyclopædia Britannica.&quot;

===[[Encyclopædia Britannica Third Edition|Supplement to the 3rd edition]]===
A two-volume supplement to the 3rd edition was published in 1801, having 1,624 pages and 50 copperplates by D. Lizars. This supplement was published by a wine-merchant, [[Thomas Bonar]], the son-in-law of the ''Britannica's'' owner [[Andrew Bell (engraver)|Andrew Bell]]; unfortunately, the two men quarreled and they never spoke for the last ten years of Bell's life (1799–1809).

The ''Britannica'' explicitly positioned itself as a conservative publication in reaction to the radical French ''[[Encyclopédie]]'' of [[Diderot]] published between 1751-66.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB_encyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | title = Encyclopedias and Dictionaries | encyclopedia = Encyclopædia Britannica, 15th ed. | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica Inc. | year = 2007 | volume = 18 | pages = 257&amp;ndash;286}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the royal dedication penned on 10 December 1800, Dr. Gleig elaborated on the editorial purpose of the ''Britannica''

{{quote|The French Encyclopédie had been accused, and justly accused, of having disseminated far and wide the seeds of anarchy and atheism. If the Encyclopædia Britannica shall in any degree counteract the tendency of that pestiferous work, even these two volumes will not be wholly unworthy of your Majesty's attention.&lt;ref name=&quot;online encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;|[[George Gleig]]|in the Dedication of the Supplement to the 3rd edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

===4th edition===
The 4th edition was begun in 1800 and completed in 1810, comprising 20 volumes with 16,033 pages and 531 plates engraved by [[Andrew Bell (engraver)|Andrew Bell]]. The editor was Dr. [[James Millar (scientist)|James Millar]], a physician, who was good at scientific topics but criticized for being &quot;slow &amp; dilatory &amp; not well qualified&quot;. The mathematical articles of Prof. Wallace were widely praised in the 4th edition but, overall, the 4th edition was a minor revision of the 3rd, updated in its historical and biographical articles.

The copyright of the material in the supplement to the 3rd edition was owned by [[Thomas Bonar]], who asked 20,000&amp;nbsp;pounds sterling for it. The supplemental material was licensed for the fourth edition for 100&amp;nbsp;pounds, but this copyright issue remained a problem through the 5th edition.

Bonar was friendly to the article authors, however, and conceived the plan of paying them as well as the article reviewers, and of allowing them to retain copyright for separate publication of their work.

===5th edition===
After [[Andrew Bell (engraver)|Andrew Bell]] died in 1809, his heirs botched the fifth edition; the dilatory and unqualified Dr. Millar was again the editor. Completed in 1817, the fifth edition sold for 36&amp;nbsp;pounds sterling (''2011: £{{formatnum:{{Inflation|UK|36|1817|2011|r=-2}}}}'') and consisted of 20 volumes with 16,017 pages and 582 plates. The fifth edition was a relatively minor revision of the fourth, which in turn was a relatively minor revision of the 3rd edition and its supplement.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; Afterwards, Bell's trustees sold the rights to the ''Britannica'' for 14,000&amp;nbsp;pounds to [[Archibald Constable]], an apprentice bookseller, who had been involved in its publication from 1788. To secure the copyrights for the 3rd edition supplement, Constable gave Bonar a one-third stake in the ''Britannica''; after Bonar's death in 1814, Constable bought his rights to the ''Britannica'' for 4,500&amp;nbsp;pounds sterling.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

===Supplement to the 5th edition===
After securing sole-ownership rights in December 1816, Constable began work on a supplement to the 5th edition, even before the 5th edition had been released (1817). The supplement was completed in April 1824, consisting of 6 volumes with 4933 pages, 125 plates, 9 maps, 3 &quot;dissertations&quot; and 160 biographies, mainly of people who had died within the preceding 30 years. This edition was the first to have an Index listing the 669 articles.

This supplement had remarkably illustrious contributors. Constable was friends with Sir [[Walter Scott]], who contributed the &quot;Chivalry&quot; article. To edit the supplement, Constable hired [[Macvey Napier]], who recruited other eminent contributors such as Sir [[Humphry Davy]], [[Jean-Baptiste Biot]], [[John Stuart Mill]], [[William Hazlitt]], [[David Ricardo]], and [[Thomas Malthus]]. [[Thomas Young (scientist)|Thomas Young's]] article on [[Egypt]] included the translation of the [[Egyptian hieroglyphs|hieroglyphics]] on the [[Rosetta Stone]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.grubstreetbooks.ca/essays/britannica.html
| title = Encyclopædia Britannica: The Final Edition
| accessdate = October 21, 2006
| last = Wolfe
| first = Morris
| year = 1974
| publisher = Globe and Mail
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===6th edition===
Constable also produced the 6th edition, which was completed in May 1823. It was published in 40 half-volume parts, priced 16 shillings in boards (32 pounds for the set). The editor was [[Charles Maclaren]]. Unfortunately, Constable went bankrupt on 19 January 1826 and the rights to the ''Britannica'' were sold on auction; they were eventually bought on 16 July 1828 for 6150 [[pound sterling|pounds sterling]] by a partnership of four men: Adam Black (a publisher), Alexander Wight (a banker), Abram Thomson (a bookbinder) and Thomas Allen, the proprietor of the ''[[Caledonian Mercury]]''. Not long after, Black bought out his partners and ownership of the ''Britannica'' passed to the Edinburgh publishing firm of [[A &amp; C Black]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Trivia Library 1&quot;/&gt;

==A. and C. Black editions (7th–9th, 1827–1901)==
===7th edition===
[[Image:Rosetta Stone.jpg|150px|thumb|left|Early 19th-century editions of ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' included seminal works such as [[Thomas Young (scientist)|Thomas Young's]] article on [[Egypt]], which included the translation of the [[Egyptian hieroglyphs|hieroglyphics]] on the [[Rosetta Stone]].]]

The 7th edition was begun in 1827 and published from March 1830-January 1842. It was edited by [[Macvey Napier]], who was assisted by [[James Browne (writer)|James Browne]], LLD. It consisted of 21 volumes with 17,101 pages and 506 plates, with an Index of 187 pages. This was the first edition to include a general index for all articles, a practice that was maintained until 1974.

Many illustrious contributors were recruited to this edition, including Sir [[David Brewster]], [[Thomas de Quincey]], [[Antonio Panizzi]] and [[Robert Stephenson]]. [[James Wilson]] did all of [[zoology]], Dr. Hampden did all of Greek philosophy, and [[William Hosking]] contributed an excellent article on [[architecture]]. Mathematical diagrams were made from woodcuts.

The 7th edition went on sale for £24 per set. However, Adam Black had invested over £108,766 in its production: £5,354 for advertising, £8,755 for editing, £13,887 for 167 contributors, £13,159 for plates, £29,279 for paper, and £19,813 for the printing.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; In the end, roughly 5,000 sets were sold but Black considered himself well-rewarded in intellectual prestige.

===8th edition===
The 8th edition was published from 1853–1860 in 21 volumes, with 17,957 pages and 402 plates and a 239-page Index (published separately in 1861). Since [[Macvey Napier]] died in 1847, Adam Black selected for its editor Dr. [[Thomas Stewart Traill]], a professor of medical jurisprudence at Edinburgh University. When Dr. Traill fell ill, he was assisted by a young Scottish philosopher, John Downes. Black was able to hold costs to roughly £75,655. This edition began the tradition of a contributors' banquet to celebrate the edition's completion (5 June 1861).&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

Many long articles were carried over from the 7th edition, but new articles by illustrious contributors were added. In all, there were 344 contributors, including [[Lord Macaulay]], [[Charles Kingsley]], [[Robert Chambers (journalist)|Robert Chambers]], the Rev. [[Charles Merivale]], Dr. [[Joseph Dalton Hooker]], Baron [[Robert Bunsen]], Sir [[John Herschel]], Professors [[Richard Owen]], [[John Stuart Blackie]] and [[William Thomson, 1st Baron Kelvin|William Thomson]] (Lord Kelvin). This edition also featured the first American contributor to the ''Britannica'', [[Edward Everett]], who wrote a 40,000-word hagiographic biography of [[George Washington]]&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

{{quote|In being a living proof that pure patriotism is not a delusion, or virtue an empty name, no one of the sons of man has equalled George Washington.|[[Edward Everett]]|in the 8th edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

===9th edition, The Scholar's Edition===
The landmark ninth edition, often called 'the Scholar's Edition',&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica History&quot;/&gt; was published from January 1875 to 1889 in 24 volumes with one index volume. Up to 1880, the editor was [[Thomas Spencer Baynes]] &amp;mdash; the first English-born editor after a series of Scots &amp;mdash; and [[W. Robertson Smith]] afterwards. An intellectual prodigy who mastered advanced scientific and mathematical topics, Smith was a professor of theology at the Free Church College in Edinburgh, and was the first contributor to the ''Britannica'' who addressed the historical interpretation of the [[Bible]], a topic then already familiar on the Continent of Europe. Dr. Smith contributed several articles to the 9th edition, but lost his teaching position on 24 May 1881, due to the controversy his (ir)religious articles aroused; he was immediately hired to be joint editor-in-chief with Baynes.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

The 9th and 11th editions are often lauded as high points for scholarship; the 9th included yet another series of illustrious contributors such as [[Thomas Henry Huxley]], [[John Strutt, 3rd Baron Rayleigh|Lord Rayleigh]], [[Algernon Charles Swinburne]] and [[William Michael Rossetti]]. [[Robert Louis Stevenson]], then 25, contributed an article about [[Robert Burns]] that, being unenthusiastic, was never printed.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; There were roughly 1100 contributors altogether, a handful of which were women; this edition was also the first to include a significant article about women (&quot;Women, Law Relating to&quot;).

The 9th edition was a critical success, and roughly 8,500 sets were sold in Britain. [[A &amp; C Black]] authorized two American firms, [[Charles Scribner's Sons]] and [[Little, Brown and Company]], to distribute the ''Britannica'' in the United States, and roughly 45,000 sets were sold.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; However, ''several hundred thousand'' pirated copies were also sold in the U.S., which still did not have copyright laws protecting foreign publications.&lt;ref name=&quot;kister_1994&quot; /&gt; Famous pirates of that era include the [[Philadelphia]]n Joseph M. Stoddart, who employed a spy in the ''Britannica's'' own printshop, Neill and Company, in Edinburgh. The spy would steal the proofreader's copies and send them by fastest mail to the United States, allowing Stoddart to publish his version simultaneously with the ''Britannica'' and at nearly half the price ($5 versus $9 per volume). His right to do so was upheld in an infamous decision by Justice Arthur Butler who argued

{{quote|To reproduce a foreign publication is not wrong. There may be differences of opinion about the morality of republishing a work here that is copyrighted abroad; but the public policy of this country, as respects the subject, is in favor of such replication...It is supposed to have an influence upon the advance of learning and intelligence.|Justice Arthur Butler|in his 1879 decision upholding Joseph Stoddart's right to republish the 9th edition of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''}}

Another successful pirate was Henry G. Allen, who developed a photographic reproduction method for the ''Britannica'' and charged only half as much as Stoddart ($2.50 per volume). Other alleged pirates of the 9th edition included [[John Wanamaker]] and the Reverend [[Isaac Kaufmann Funk]] of the [[Funk and Wagnalls]] encyclopedia. Richard S. Pearle &amp; Co. of Chicago printed some sets in 1891, with 24 volumes plus an index Vol. 25, and in 1893 added 3  &quot;American&quot; volumes 25-27 with the index as Vol. 28. Some copies of this version say they were printed by Werner, also of Chicago, and in 1907 Werner printed the commonly found &quot;New Werner Edition.&quot; In 1890, James Clarke published the ''Americanized Encyclopædia Britannica, Revised and Amended''.
However, in 1896, Scribner's obtained court orders to shut down the pirate operations, whose printing plates were melted down as part of the enforcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;kister_1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Kister | first = KF | authorlink = Kenneth Kister | year = 1994 | title = Kister's Best Encyclopedias: A Comparative Guide to General and Specialized Encyclopedias | edition = 2nd | publisher = Oryx Press | location = Phoenix, Arizona | isbn = 0-89774-744-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1903, [[Saalfield Publishing]] published the ''Americanized'' [[Encyclopædia Britannica]] in 8 volumes with a 4 volume supplement (when the British edition had 24 volumes).  The [[Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.|Encyclopædia Britannica Company]] had acquired all the rights to the encyclopedia in America. In addition, [[D. Appleton &amp; Company]] claimed that the 4 volume supplement used material from ''[[Appletons' Cyclopædia of American Biography]]''.

To avoid  further litigation, the suit against Saalfield Publishing was settled in court &quot;by a stipulation in which the defendants agree not to print or sell any further copies of the offending work, to destroy all printed sheets, to destroy or melt the portions of the plates from which the infringing matter in the Supplement as it appears in the ''Americanized [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'' has been printed, and to pay D. Appleton &amp; Co. the sum of $2000 damages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Publishers' Weekly No. 1688, June 4, 1904&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Horace Everett Hooper]] was an American business man, and a close associate of James Clarke, one of the leading American pirates. Hooper recognized the potential profit in the ''Britannica'' and, again in 1896, learned that both the ''Britannica'' and ''[[The Times (London)|The Times]]'' of London were in financial straits. Hooper formed a partnership with Clarke, his brother George Clarke, and [[Walter Montgomery Jackson]] to sell the ''Britannica'' under the sponsorship of ''The Times'', meaning that ''The Times'' would advertise the sale and lend its respectable name. Hooper and his energetic advertising manager, Henry Haxton, introduced many innovative [[sales]] methods: full-page advertisements in ''The Times'', testimonials from celebrities, buying on installment plans, and a long series of so called 'final offers'. Although the crass marketing was criticized as inappropriate to the ''Britannica's'' history and scholarship, the unprecedented profits delighted the manager of ''The Times'', [[Charles Frederic Moberly Bell]],&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; who assessed Hooper as &quot;a ranker who loved to be accepted as a gentleman. Treat him as a gentleman and one had no trouble with him; treat him as an essentially dishonest ranker and one got all the trouble there was to get.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Kitchen | first = F. Harcourt | year = 1925 | title = Moberley Bell and his Times: An Unofficial Narrative | publisher = Philip Allan and Co | location = London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American partnership sold over 20,000 copies of the ''Britannica'' in the United States (four runs of 5000), after which Hooper and Jackson bought out the two Clarke brothers in early 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; [[A &amp; C Black]] had moved to London in 1895 and, on 9 May 1901, sold all the rights to the ''Britannica'' to Hooper and Jackson, then living in London.

The sale of the ''Britannica'' to Americans has left a lingering resentment among some British citizens, especially when it is perceived that parochial American concerns are emphasized.&lt;ref name=&quot;kister_1994&quot; /&gt; For example, one modern British critic has written&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Mosley | first = Charles | title = No title | journal = Manchester Guardian Weekly | date = 10 July 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The full horror of what an American editorial [[monopoly]] entails is seldom appreciated. The American editors who write short in-house (&quot;[[Micropædia]]&quot;) articles are ignorant and [[parochialism|parochial]]...The ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' is a publication so contemptuous of Britain, the land of its birth, that it cannot be bothered to ascertain correct usage when speaking of [[River Thames|the Thames]], a publication so [[insularity|insular]] as to give an entry to [[Alan Whicker]] but none to [[Peter Carington, 6th Baron Carrington|Lords Carrington]] or [[William Whitelaw, 1st Viscount Whitelaw|Whitelaw]]. It amounts to more than impertinence.|Charles Mosley|in the ''Manchester Guardian Weekly'' (10 July 1988)}}

==First American editions (10th–14th, 1901–1973)==
===10th edition (supplement to the 9th)===
[[Image:Map of Africa from Encyclopaedia Britannica 1890.jpg|200px|thumb|right|Map of Africa from the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 1890]]

Again under the sponsorship of ''[[The Times (London)|The Times]]'' of London, the new owners quickly produced an 11-volume supplement to the 9th edition; the editors were [[Hugh Chisholm]], Sir [[Donald Mackenzie Wallace]], [[Arthur T. Hadley]] and [[Franklin Henry Hooper]], the brother of the owner Horace Hooper. Taken together, the 35 volumes were dubbed the &quot;10th edition&quot;. The re-issue of the 9th edition under the moniker &quot;10th edition&quot; caused some outrage, since many articles of the 9th edition were over 25 years old, and beginning to show their age. This led to the popular joke: &quot;''The Times'' is behind the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' and the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' is behind the times.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas_1992&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Thomas | first = Gillian | authorlink = Gillian Thomas | year = 1992 | title = A Position to Command Respect: Women and the Eleventh Britannica | publisher = Scarecrow Press | isbn = 0-8108-2567-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1903 advertising campaign for the 10th edition was an onslaught of [[direct marketing]]: hand-written letters, telegrams, limited-time offers, etc. The following quote, written in 1926, captures the mood&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Courtney | first = Janet E. | year = 1926 | title = Recollected in Tranquillity | publisher = Heinemann | page = 225|location=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Who that is old enough does not remember the &quot;campaign&quot; of 1903, the insidious payment by instalments, the sets dumped at your door, bookcase and all, on receipt of a guinea, the scholarships, the competition questions, the reply-paid telegrams pursuing you to the innermost sanctuary of your home (&quot;From my bath I curse you&quot;, one man wired back!), the &quot;Going, going, gone&quot; tactics &amp;mdash; &quot;Only five days left and one of them the shortest!&quot; so irrelevant, but so arresting!|Janet E. Courtney, long-time employee of the ''Britannica'', from her book, ''Recollected in Tranquillity''}}

An excellent collection of prospectuses received by a single person (C. L. Parker) in that year has been preserved by the [[Bodleian Library]] (catalogued under #39899.c.1). The advertising was clearly targeted at middle and lower-middle class people seeking to improve themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas_1992&quot; /&gt; The advertising campaign was remarkably successful; over 70,000 sets were sold, bringing in over £600,000&amp;nbsp;pounds profit.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; When one British expert expressed surprise to [[Horace Everett Hooper|Hooper]] that so many people would want an outdated encyclopedia, he replied, &quot;They didn't; I ''made'' them want it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

===11th edition===
{{Main|Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition}}
[[File:11Britannica.JPG|200px|thumb|left|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 11th edition]]
The renowned 11th edition of ''Encyclopædia Britannica'' was begun in 1903, and published in 1910–1911 in 28 volumes, with a one-volume Index. Edited by [[Hugh Chisholm]] in London and by [[Franklin Hooper]] in [[New York City|New York]], the 11th edition was the first to be published substantially at one time, instead of volume by volume. Its illustrious contributors are legion, including [[Robert Baden-Powell, 1st Baron Baden-Powell|Baden-Powell]] writing on [[kite|kite-flying]]; [[Arthur Eddington]] on astronomy; [[Edmund Gosse]] on [[literature]] and [[Donald Tovey]] on music. Sometimes called the 1911 ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', this edition is still highly regarded for its lucid explanations of scholarly subjects. Being in the [[public domain]], the complete text is freely available online.&lt;ref&gt;There are many places the encyclopedia can be accessed online, such as [http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/ encyclopedia.jrank.org], [http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Main_Page 1911encyclopedia.org] and [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/13600 The gutenberg project]&lt;/ref&gt; The 11th edition retained the high scholarship and eminent contributors that marked the 9th edition, but tempered that scholarship with shorter, simpler articles that were more intelligible to lay-readers. Thus, the 9th and 11th editions had 17,000 and 40,000 articles, respectively, although they were roughly equivalent in size. This shift accommodated the American business strategy of popularizing the ''Britannica'' for a mass market, while still retaining its quality as a reference work. The high literary and scholarly level of the 11th edition is largely due to the zeal of its owner, [[Horace Everett Hooper]], who held scholarship in high regard and spared no expense to make the 11th edition as excellent as possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

After a heated legal dispute and all-too-public corporate wrangling over ownership of the ''Britannica'' (1908–1909), Hooper bought out [[Walter Montgomery Jackson|Walter Jackson]], becoming the sole owner of the ''Britannica''. The public furor caused ''[[The Times (London)|The Times]]'' to cancel its sponsorship contract with Hooper, feeling that the interests of the newspaper were not being served.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; After failing to win over [[Oxford University]], Hooper managed to secure [[Cambridge University]] as a new sponsor; thus, the 11th edition was published initially by [[Cambridge University Press]], and scholars from Cambridge University were allowed to review the text and veto any overly aggressive advertising.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; Perhaps because of this, the ''Britannica'' encountered financial difficulties, whereupon it was licensed to [[Sears Roebuck]] and Co. of [[Chicago]], who issued a physically smaller but complete version. The owner of Sears, philanthropist [[Julius Rosenwald]], was friends with Horace Hooper and enthusiastic about the ''Britannica's'' promise; he single-handedly saved the ''Britannica'' from [[bankruptcy]] several times over the next fifteen years. Although Sears' smaller set was successful in 1915–1916, sales dropped significantly when the United States entered World War I.

The 11th edition employed 35 named female contributors, out of 1500 total (2.3%). Although this was not much of an increase over the 10th edition (which named 37 female contributors out of 1800 total), it was heralded publicly as a major advance in recognizing the contributions of women in learned circles.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas_1992&quot; /&gt; However, the 11th edition did employ hundreds of women to write unsigned articles; some women, such as Irish medical expert Harriet Hennessy, even rose to be (uncredited) department editors.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomas_1992&quot; /&gt;

[[Image:EncycBrit1913.jpg|thumb|left|250px|1913 [[advertisement]] for the [[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition|11th edition of ''Encyclopædia Britannica'']], with the slogan &quot;When in doubt&amp;mdash;&quot;look it up&quot; in the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''&quot;]]

===12th and 13th editions (competing supplements to the 11th)===
The poor sales of the war years brought the ''Britannica'' to the brink of [[bankruptcy]].  Luckily, the [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] of [[Sears Roebuck]], [[philanthropist]] [[Julius Rosenwald]], was devoted to the mission of the ''Britannica'' and bought its rights on 24 February 1920 from his friend [[Horace Everett Hooper]] for $1.25 million dollars. The ''Britannica's'' headquarters were moved to [[Chicago]], where they have remained ever since. In 1922, a 3-volume supplement to the 11th edition was released that summarized the developments just before, during and after World War I; these three volumes, taken together with the 11th edition, became known as the 12th edition. Horace Hooper died in 1922, a few weeks after the publication of the 12th edition.&lt;ref name=&quot;wells_1968&quot; /&gt; This edition was a commercial failure, losing Sears roughly $1.75 million dollars, after which Sears gave it back to Hooper's widow, Harriett Meeker Cox, and her brother, William J. Cox, who ran the company from 1923-1928.

The passage of a few years led to a better perspective on that era. In 1926, the ''Britannica'' released three ''new'' volumes covering the history of 1910-1926, which were intended to supplant those of the 12th edition. Again taken together with the 11th edition, the new volumes became known as the 13th edition, which maintained the ''Britannica's'' tradition of illustrious contributors: [[Harry Houdini]], [[Albert Einstein]], [[Marie Curie]], [[Sigmund Freud]], [[Henry Ford]], [[Leon Trotsky]], [[Ferdinand Foch]], [[Gustav Stresemann]], [[Thomas G. Masaryk]] and [[Elihu Root]].

In 1928, Rosenwald bought back the rights to the ''Britannica'', leaving Cox as publisher. Cox argued forcefully for a new 14th edition, pointing out that the 11th edition (the bulk of the 12 and 13th editions) was badly out of date. Cox also tried to involve the [[University of Chicago]] in producing the ''Britannica'', even including a $1 million advance from Rosenwald as a temptation; however, the trustees of the University turned down his proposal, a choice they almost repeated a generation later under [[William Benton (senator)|William Benton]].

===14th edition===
By 1926, the 11th edition was beginning to show its age, and work on a new edition was begun. The editors were [[J. L. Garvin]] in London and [[Franklin Henry Hooper]] in [[New York City|New York]]. The 14th edition took three years to complete, at the then exorbitant cost of $2.5 million dollars, all of it invested by [[Julius Rosenwald]] of [[Sears, Roebuck and Company]]. It was very different from the 11th edition, having fewer volumes and simpler articles, continuing the business strategy of popularizing the ''Britannica'' for the American mass market at the expense of its scholarship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trivia Library 1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kister_1994&quot; /&gt; The 14th edition also drew criticism for deleting information unflattering to the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=McCabe | first=Joseph | authorlink=Joseph McCabe | title=Lies and Fallacies of the Encyclopædia Britannica: How Powerful and Shameless Clerical Forces Castrated a Famous Work... | url=http://www.infidels.org/library/historical/joseph_mccabe/lies_of_britannica.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the 14th also included many illustrious contributors, including eighteen [[Nobel Prize|Nobel laureates]] in science, such as [[Robert Millikan]], [[Albert Abraham Michelson]] and [[Arthur Compton]]. More coverage was given to popular entertainment,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | date = 23 September 1929 | title = Patriarch Revised | journal = [[Time (magazine)|TIME]] | url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,732859-1,00.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Gene Tunney]] writing on [[boxing]], [[Lillian Gish]] on [[acting]] and [[Irene Castle]] on [[ballroom dancing]]. [[George Bernard Shaw]] contributed a well-regarded article on [[socialism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; In all, there were roughly 3500 named contributors, of which roughly half were American.&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt; The 14th edition was again criticized for [[sexism]]; for example, less than 6% of its 13,000 biographies were of [[woman|women]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kogan_1958&quot; /&gt;

The 14th edition was published in September 1929, and had 23 volumes with a one-volume Index that also contained a complete atlas. Unfortunately, the [[Great Depression]] struck scarcely a month after the release of the 14th edition, and sales plummeted. Despite the unfailing support of the [[Sears Roebuck]] company, the ''Britannica'' almost went bankrupt over the next few years. Rosenwald died in 1932, and General [[Robert E. Wood]] took over; Cox was removed as publisher and the Secretary-Treasurer of Sears, [[Elkan Harrison Powell]] was installed as the new President of the ''Britannica''.

===Policy of continuous revision===
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2010}}
[[Elkan Harrison Powell|E. H. Powell]] identified and fixed a key vulnerability of ''Britannica'', namely, that its sales (and, hence, the company's income) fluctuated strongly over the life-cycle of an edition. After the release of a new edition, sales would generally begin strong, and decline gradually for 10–20 years as the edition began to show its age; finally, sales would drop off precipitously with the announcement that work had begun on a new edition, since few people would buy an obsolete encyclopedia that would soon be updated. These strong fluctuations in sales led to economic hardship for the ''Britannica''.

To address this problem, Powell suggested in 1933 the policy of continuous revision, with the goal of keeping the ''Britannica'' &quot;always timely and always salable&quot;. The basic idea was to maintain a continuous editorial staff that would constantly revise the articles on a fixed schedule. Earlier encyclopedias did not maintain a continuous editorial staff, but rather assembled one just prior to beginning a new edition. Rather than releasing supplemental editions or volumes, new printings would be made every year with only enough copies made to cover the sales for that year. An analysis of the ''Britannica's'' articles suggested that roughly 75% required only occasional revising, whereas 25% required revision every 1–3 years. The articles were therefore divided into 30 classifications and a schedule for their revision worked out, such that every article would be checked at least twice a decade.

Powell also conceived the ''Britannica's'' &quot;Book of the Year&quot;, in which a single volume would be released every year covering the developments of the previous year, particularly in rapidly changing fields such as science, technology, culture and politics. The &quot;Book of the Year&quot; continues to be published even today. Powell also introduced the Library Research Service (1936), in which owners of the ''Britannica'' could write to have their personal questions researched and answered by the editorial staff.

Under Powell's leadership, the ''Britannica'' began to capitalize on its reputation by aggressively developing &quot;spin-offs&quot;, such as the 12-volume ''Britannica Junior'' for children (published 1934, and revised to 15 volumes in 1947), the historical timeline ''The March of Man'' (published 1935, and edited by Albert Bushwell Hart, Isaac J. Cox and Lawrence H. Dawson), the ''Encyclopædia Britannica World Atlas'' (published 1942, and prepared by G. Donald Hudson) and ''Ten Eventful Years'', a summary of the national and international events surrounding World War II (1937–1946).

===Transfer of ownership to William Benton===
[[Sears Roebuck]] published the ''Britannica'' until 1943. In 1941, Sears offered the rights to the ''Britannica'' as a gift to the [[University of Chicago]]. The story of this offer was recounted at the [[Bicentennial of the Encyclopædia Britannica|bicentennial banquet]] of the ''Encyclopædia Britannica''&lt;ref name=&quot;EB_bicentennial&quot;&gt;{{cite book | year = 1968 | title = Banquet at Guildhall in the City of London, Tuesday 15 October 1968: Celebrating the 200th Anniversary of the Encyclopædia Britannica and the 25th Anniversary of the Honorable William Benton as its Chairman and Publisher | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica International, Ltd. | location = United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|It was after lunch on the afternoon of December 9, 1941 that General [[Robert E. Wood]], Chairman of [[Sears, Roebuck and Company|Sears, Roebuck]] and [[William Benton (senator)|William Benton]], then vice-president of the [[University of Chicago]], were discussing the attack on [[Pearl Harbor]] which had occurred two days earlier. At the end of this conversation, as coffee was served, Bill changed the subject and said to Wood, &quot;General, don't you think it is rather unsuitable for a mail-order house to own the ''Encyclopædia Britannica'', and isn't it even more unsuitable in wartime?&quot;

&quot;Yes&quot;, replied General Wood, &quot;Sears, Roebuck should never have acquired it in the first place.&quot;

&quot;Does it make any money?&quot; Bill asked. Wood replied that sales would earn his company some $300,000 before taxes that year. Bill replied, &quot;Well, General, you know that universities do not have any money. They cannot buy businesses. Why don't you make a gift of the ''Britannica'' to the University of Chicago?&quot;

General Wood did not reply immediately but walked to his car. As he got into the car, he turned to Bill Benton and said, &quot;All right, Bill, I will give you the ''Britannica''.&quot;}}

The [[University of Chicago]] declined the offer, viewing the mission of the university as not entirely consistent with a large commercial publishing house; however it continues even today to be involved in its production, offering editorial advice and allowing its name to be associated with the ''Britannica''. Thus, in 1943, the wealthy and powerful [[William Benton (senator)|William Benton]], a former U.S. senator and advertising executive, obtained exclusive control of the ''Britannica'', which he published until his death in 1973. His widow Helen Hemingway Benton continued to publish the ''Britannica'' until her own death in 1974. After their deaths, the [[Benton Foundation]] continued to manage the ''Britannica'' until it was sold to [[Jacqui Safra]] in 1996.

==The current 15th edition==
===First version (1974–1984)===
Despite the policy of continuous revision, the 14th edition of the ''Britannica'' gradually became outdated, much as its predecessors, the 9th and 11th editions. Beginning in the early 1960s, the failings of the 14th edition began to be collated and published by [[physicist]] [[Harvey Einbinder]], culminating in his highly critical 390-page book, ''The Myth of Britannica'' (1964). Goaded into action, the ''Britannica'' began to work on a new edition, the current 15th.

The 15th edition was produced over ten years at a cost of $32 million dollars and released in 1974 in 30 volumes. The so-called ''New Encyclopædia Britannica'' (or ''Britannica 3'') had a unique three-part organization: a single ''Propædia'' (''Primer for Education'') volume, which aimed to provide an outline of all known, indeed knowable, information; a 10-volume ''Micropædia'' (''Small Education'') of 102,214 short articles (strictly less than 750 words); and a 19-volume ''Macropædia'' (''Large Education'') of 4,207 longer, scholarly articles with references, similar to those of the 9th and 11th editions.&lt;ref name=&quot;chauncy_1975&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Harris | year = 1975 | title = The New Encyclopædia Britannica | journal = Geographical Review | pages = 141&amp;ndash;145 | doi = 10.2307/213852 | volume = 65|first =Chauncy D. | issue = 1 | publisher = Geographical Review, Vol. 65, No. 1 | jstor = 213852}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Micropædia'' and ''Macropædia'' articles are listed in alphabetical order; the 4,287 contributors to the ''Macropædia'' articles are identified scrupulously, but the ''Micropædia'' articles are generally anonymous and unreferenced.

This 15th edition had no general index, which had been a feature of the ''Britannica'' since its 7th edition; even in the 2nd edition, individual long articles had their own indices. The idea of [[Mortimer J. Adler]] was that the ''Propædia'' and the ''Micropædia'' could serve the role of an index. More generally, Dr. Adler felt that the ''Britannica'' should not merely serve as a reference work, but also aspire to be a categorization of ''omne scibile'' (everything knowable), to fulfill [[Francis Bacon]]'s grand conception of [[epistemology]]. Thus, the ''Propædia'' was intended to be the road-map of all knowledge, within which every fact, technique, and theory could be organized.

The lack of an index and the unusual organization into ''two'' sets of alphabetically organized articles provoked much criticism.&lt;ref name=&quot;kister_1994&quot; /&gt; In a typical contemporary assessment, &quot;It is called the ''Micropædia'', for 'little knowledge,' and little knowledge is what it provides. It has proved to be grotesquely insufficient as an index, radically constricting the utility of the ''Macropædia.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Wolff | first = G | month = November | year = 1976 | title = Britannica 3, Failures of | journal = The Atlantic | pages = 107&amp;ndash;110}}&lt;/ref&gt; or, more laconically, &quot;This arrangement has nothing to recommend it except commercial novelty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last = McCracken | first = S | month = February | year = 1976 | title = The Scandal of 'Britannica 3' | journal = Commentary | pages = 63&amp;ndash;68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most readers could not predict whether a given subject would be found in ''Micropædia'' or the ''Macropædia''; the criteria by which the articles were sorted were not obvious even to scholars,&lt;ref name=&quot;chauncy_1975&quot; /&gt; despite Dr. Adler's claims that the sorting followed naturally from the ''Propædia's'' outline of all knowledge.

===Second version (1985–present)===
In 1985, the ''Britannica'' responded to reader requests by restoring the index as a two-volume set. The number of topics indexed by the ''Britannica'' has fluctuated from 500,000 (1985, the same as in 1954) to 400,000 (1989,1991) to 700,000 in the current 2007 print version. Presumably, this recent increase reflects the introduction of efficient electronic indexing, since the size of the encyclopedia has remained nearly constant at approximately 40 million words from 1954 to the present and far less than 40% of the encyclopedia has changed from 1985 to 2007.

Under the editorship of [[Philip W. Goetz]], the 1985 version of the 15th edition introduced other major changes. The 4,207 articles of the first version ''Macropædia'' were combined into 674 longer articles; for example, the individual articles for each of the 50 [[U.S. state]]s were merged into what became a 310-page article &quot;[[United States of America]]&quot;. The ''[[Macropædia]]'' was also restricted somewhat from 19 volumes to the present 17 volumes. At the same time, the number of ''[[Micropædia]]'' volumes was increased from 10 to the present 12 volumes, although the number of articles was reduced from 102,214 to roughly 65,000. The strict 750-word limit was softened to allow articles of medium length, such as [[Internet]], which almost fills one page. Finally, the ''[[Propædia]]'''s Outline of Knowledge was simplified for easier use.

===Development of electronic versions===
[[File:Encyclopaedia Britannica Ultimate Reference Suite.png|thumb|[[Encyclopædia Britannica Ultimate Reference Suite]], available on DVD]]
In the 1980s [[Microsoft]] approached Britannica Inc. to collaborate on a [[CD-ROM]] encyclopedia, but the offer was declined. Senior managers at Britannica were confident in their control of the market and that their healthy profits would continue. At this time complete sets of the encyclopedia were priced between [[USD|$]]1,500 and $2,200, and the product was considered part of a luxury brand with an impeccable reputation handed down from generation to generation. The management did not believe that a CD-ROM could adequately compete or supplement their business.  Microsoft responded by using content from ''[[Funk &amp; Wagnalls Standard Encyclopedia]]'' to create what is now known as ''[[Encarta]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.ifets.info/download_pdf.php?j_id=11&amp;a_id=258
|title= To wire or not to wire? Encyclopædia Britannica versus Microsoft Encarta
|accessdate= November 21, 2006
|last= Alevizou
|first= Panagiota
|format= PDF
|work= Graduate Centre for Culture and Communication, Department of Media Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1990 the ''Britannica's'' sales reached an all-time high of $650 million, but ''Encarta'', released in 1993, soon became a software staple with almost every computer purchase and the ''Britannica's'' market share plummeted. Britannica Inc. countered by offering a CD-ROM version of their product,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-5519440_ITM|title= CD-ROM Technology Poses Challenge for Encyclopedia Industry|accessdate= November 21, 2006|last= Ridder|first= Knight|date= 1994-06-26|work= San Jose Mercury News}}&lt;/ref&gt; although it could not generate the print version's $500–600 in sales commissions. Britannica Inc. decided to charge $995 for just the CD-ROM, while bundling a free disc with the print version, hoping that including the CD-ROM would persuade buyers to stay with the brand.

In 1994 an online version was launched,&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica History&quot;/&gt; with subscriptions for sale for $2,000. By 1996 the price of the CD-ROM had dropped to $200, and sales had dropped to $325 million — about half of their 1990 levels. Only 55,000 hard copy versions were sold in 1994, compared with 117,000 in 1990, and sales later fell to 20,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/40033.stm
| title = Encyclopædia Britannica changes to survive
| accessdate = October 21, 2006
| last = Day
| first = Peter
| date = 2006-12-17
| publisher = BBC News
| quote = Sales plummeted from 100,000 a year to just 20,000.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Facing financial pressure, Britannica Inc. was bought in 1996 by Swiss financier [[Jacob Safra]] for $135 million, a fraction of its book value. Safra introduced severe price-cutting measures to try to compete with ''Encarta'', even offering the entire reference free of charge for a time (around 18 months, from October 1999 to March 2001) on the [[Internet]].

Currently, Britannica co-operates with [[Taiwan]] companies (遠流/智慧藏學習科技公司) to provide a [[Traditional Chinese]]-English bilingual version encyclopedia on internet according to the 2002 edition. It is the first bilingual product of Britannica.

Former editor-in-chief [[Robert McHenry]] believes that Britannica failed to exploit its early advantages in the market for electronic encyclopedias. Britannica had, for example, published the second [[multimedia]] encyclopedia titled [[Compton's Encyclopedia|''Compton's MultiMedia Encyclopedia'']] as early as 1989 (the first one being the ''[[Academic American Encyclopedia]]'' published by [[Grolier Multimedia Encyclopedia|Grolier]]), but did not launch ''Britannica CD'' until 1994, a year after Microsoft launched their ''Encarta'' encyclopedia. McHenry believes these failures were due to a reluctance among senior management to fully embrace the new technology, caused largely by the overriding influence of the sales staff and management. The sales personnel earned commissions from door-to-door selling of the print encyclopedias, which McHenry believes led to decisions about the distribution and pricing of the electronic products being driven by the desires of the sales personnel rather than market conditions and customer expectations.&lt;ref name=&quot;EBonline&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=The Building of Britannica Online | work=howtoknow.com | url=http://www.howtoknow.com/BOL1.html | accessdate = December 30, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DE1E31F935A35757C0A963958260 New York Times article describing the Britannica's financial woes in 1995]
* [http://news.earthweb.com/ec-news/article.php/785031 Retrenching from web in 2001, return to book form]

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of The Encyclopaedia Britannica}}
[[Category:Encyclopædia Britannica]]
[[Category:Cultural history of Scotland]]
[[Category:Scottish Enlightenment]]
[[Category:History of Chicago, Illinois]]

[[he:היסטוריה של האנציקלופדיה בריטניקה]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
