<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9139951" ns="0" title="List of Digimon Frontier characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Merge from |Takuya Kanbara|Koji Minamoto|Zoe Orimoto|J. P. Shibayama|Tommy Himi|Koichi Kimura|Grumblemon|Ranamon|Arbormon|Mercurymon|Celestial Digimon|Ancient Warriors (Digimon)|date=June 2011}} 
{{multiple issues|fansite=July 2010|in-universe=July 2010|lead too short=July 2010|one source=July 2010|plot=July 2010}}
This is a list of characters from the [[Digimon]] [[anime]] series [[Digimon Frontier]].

==Humans==
===Main characters===
* [[Takuya Kanbara]]
* [[Koji Minamoto]]
* [[Tomoki Himi]]
* [[Izumi Orimoto]]
* [[Junpei Shibayama]]
* [[Koichi Kimura]]

===Family===
* '''Yuriko''' &amp; '''Hiroaki Kanbara''': Takuya's mother and father. Voiced in the dub by [[Mari Devon]] and [[Paul St. Peter]].
* '''Shinya Kanbara''': Takuya's brother. He and Takuya often fought each other, like most siblings. Voiced in the dub by [[Philece Sampler]].
* '''Kousei Minamoto''': Kouichi and Koji's father. He took custody of Koji when he divorced Tomoko and told Koji that she was dead. He later remarried Satomi. Voiced in the dub by [[Paul St. Peter]].
* '''Satomi Minamoto''': Koji's stepmother. She was depressed when she thought that Kouji did not love her because he thought about his biological mother. Voiced in the dub by [[Brianne Siddall]].
* '''Tomoko Kimura''': Koji &amp; Kouichi's biological mother. She took custody of Koichi when she divorced Kousei. Though she suffered from sickness, she continued to work because she knew she had to support Kouichi. Voiced in the dub by [[Philece Sampler]].
* '''Yutaka Himi''': Tomoki's older brother. He did not want Tommy to become spoiled, so he kept telling Tommy not to keep asking their parents for everything. This created a distance in their relationship. In the Japanese version, Tommy simply referred to him as 'brother'. The American dub gave him the first name of Yutaka. While Tommy didn't understand what he was telling him at the time, when Asuramon tried to use him, Tommy got it. After Tommy killed Asuramon, he silently thanked Yutaka for trying to tell him something he now got. Voiced in the dub by [[Joshua Seth]].

===Other children===
These are all the other children that were brought by the Trailmon but not chosen to receive a spirit. Ophanimon sent them a message asking them to go home but they chose not to. Ophanimon sent Angemon to protect them, but they thought of Angemon as their Digimon and ignored what he told them. At some point in time, they came to the Beanstalk Village, where the Mamemon gave them the last of their peas. The group planted the peas where a giant bean stalk used to be, and it grew into another beanstalk. After Angemon was killed by the Royal Knights they decided to go back to the real world, but the Royal Knights captured them and took them back to the Beanstalk Village and demanded to know where the code was. After Takuya and the crew saved them, they boarded a Trailmon and went back to the real world. (These kids are rumored to be the holders of the other four spirits)

* '''Katsuharu''': He bullied Tomoki in the past and forced him onto the Trailmon that brought him to the Digital World. He seemed to be the group's unofficial leader.  He thought Tommy was weak but after Tommy saved Teppei, he realized Tommy was stronger than he'd ever been.  He made peace with Tommy and asked to be friends which Tommy accepted.  Later, when he returned to the Real World, he had Tommy shove him onto the train so they'd be even.  At the end of the series he can be seen as one of Tommy's friends that he's hanging out with after leaving the Digital World. Voiced in the dub by [[Kentarou Itou]].
* '''Teppei''': He also bullied Tomoki in the past. He told Tomoki to go back because he thought he was too weak to stay. When he saw Tomoki spirit evolve, he took back what he said.
* '''Chiaki''': She felt she could become stronger if she stayed in the Digital World.
* '''Teruo''': He felt that his old life was boring and that he was free when in the Digital World.

==Digimon==
===Bokomon and Neemon===
Bokomon and Neemon are two rookie Digimon who accompanied the DigiDestined in their adventure. Bokomon is Mutant Digimon, and a scholar. His name comes from the Japanese word, bokoboko, which means the sound of hitting something hollow. He is white and has a horned head and pointed ears. His trademark is the pink ''haramaki'' (body warmer) that he wears around his stomach. It is in this haramaki that he stores his Book of Knowledge from which he learns about the Ten Legendary Warriors. Neemon is a Beast Digimon; he resembles a rather skinny yellow rabbit creature with long pointed ears. He has stubby arms and wears overlarge red pants. Bokomon and Neemon first appeared in episode one of ''Digimon Frontier'' when Cerberumon was attacking Flame Terminal to find a &quot;spirit&quot;. After Takuya became Agunimon and defeated Cerberumon, Bokomon accompanied the five DigiDestined on their adventure.
:''Bokomon is voiced in the dub by [[Brian Beacock]] while Neemon was voiced in the dub by [[Michael Sorich]]''.

===[[Celestial Digimon]]===
The three ruling angel Digimon of the Digital World before Lucemon poisoned Cherubimon's mind and caused the conflict that brought the DigiDestined to the DigiWorld. Though all three eventually were defeated and their Fractal Codes taken, the Celestial Digimon meet again in their reborn rookie forms and begin their friendship anew.

===Lucemon===
[[Image:Lucemon.jpg|thumb|left|]]
* Voiced by [[Mona Marshall]] (US), [[Kumiko Nishihara]] (Japanese, Rookie form), and [[Ryusei Nakao]] (Japanese, Falldown Mode)

The main antagonist of the series, {{nihongo|Lucemon|ルーチェモン|Rūchemon}} is a child-like [[angel]] Digimon who believed others could not think for themselves, and that the world would be a better place if he had absolute power and made all the decisions. Lucemon appeared during the war between Human-type and Beast-type Digimon that occurred in the ancient past of the [[Digimon Frontier]] timeline. Lucemon was able to stop the war, and created the rules for a peaceful society where he had been the ultimate sovereign. However, he was corrupted by his own power and became oppressive towards all other Digimon. His power made him unbeatable until the [[Ancient Warriors|first Legendary Warriors]] appeared and stopped him by sealing him inside the [[Dark Area]]. The governing of the [[Digital World]] was handed over to the three [[Celestial Digimon]] - [[Ophanimon]], [[Seraphimon]] and [[Cherubimon]]. Lucemon was able to corrupt [[Cherubimon]], and had him and, later, the Royal Knights collect the data that would be needed to revive him. They were successful, and Lucemon was revived, allowing him to break free. Later, he becomes {{nihongo|[[Seven Great Demon Lords#Lucemon Chaos Mode|Lucemon Chaos Mode]]|ルーチェモンフォールダウンモード|Rūchemon Fōrudaun Mōdo|Lucemon Falldown Mode}} after consuming the data of the Royal Knights and easily defeated both [[EmperorGreymon]] and [[MagnaGarurumon]] while destroying the 3 moons of the Digital World. He then began to open a portal to the Human World while overpowering the Legendary Warriors until [[Koichi Kimura|Koichi]] sacrificed himself and gave his ''Spirits of Darkness'' to his brother Koji. This resulted in the birth of [[Susanoomon]] who defeated Lucemon. However, Susanoomon was only able to scan part of Lucemon's data - only the good data was scanned, and the evil data reformed itself into a dark Digi-Egg which hatched into  [[dragon|draconic]] {{nihongo|[[Seven Great Demon Lords#Lucemon Shadowlord Mode|Lucemon Shadowlord Mode]]|ルーチェモンサタンモード|Ruchemon Satan Modo|Lucemon Satan Mode}} and flies towards the real world with the Digidestined after him as Susanoomon. During the fight, they learn the Lucemon they're fighting is only a mindless beast carrying the actual Lucemon in his Larva Mode. Once Lucemon's Shadow Lord Mode is rendered completely mindless, it is destroyed by Susanoomon with Lucemon Larva attempting to kill Susanoomon as the Spirits expelled the children and took his attack which seemed to do no damage. Susanoomon de-digivolved into the Spirits of all of the Legendary Warriors, appearing in their Human Warrior forms and using his sword to deliver the deathblow to Lucemon.
{{-}}

===[[Royal Knights]]===
Formerly warriors of justice, the two Royal Knights Dynasmon and Crusadermon served Lucemon so that he would grant them access to the human world, which they wished to rule over.

===Pandamon===
A panda Digimon that resides in Toy Town. He assisted Takuya and Koji into getting into the castle when WaruMonzaemon kidnapped Tommy. After the ShadowToyAgumon was defeated, Pandamon arranges for a ToyAgumon to give the boys a ride back to the others.
:''Voiced in the dub by [[Michael Sorich]] impersonating [[Adam West]]''.

===Sorcerymon===
* Voiced by [[Dave Wittenberg]] (US) &amp; [[Kazunari Kojima]] (Japan).

A servant of [[Seraphimon]], Sorcerymon is a Majin-type Digimon with power over ice. He served Seraphimon as both advisor and caretaker of his castle since the Celestial Digimon set up their order in the Digital World. The [[DigiDestined]] meet Sorcerymon and he led them to where Seraphimon was imprisoned, awakening him with the power of the D-Tectors. After Seraphimon fell to [[Mercurymon]], Sorcerymon led the DigiDestined to a [[Trailmon]] and sacrificed his life to prevent [[Grumblemon]], [[Arbormon]] and [[Ranamon]] from following. His ghost later returned to protect the DigiDestined and [[Takuya Kanbara|EmperorGreymon]] from [[Dynasmon]]'s attack when the [[Royal Knights]] invaded the Forest Kingdom looking for the key to Forest Kingdom's Fractal Code. After the protection from Dynasmon's attack, Sorcerymon's ghost disappeared.

===IceDevimon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=IceDevimon
 |katakana=アイスデビモン
 |japname=
 |image= 
 |level=Champion
 |attribute=Virus
 |family=Nightmare Soldiers
 |type=Fallen Angel
 }}
* ''Voiced by [[Norio Wakamoto]] (Japan) and [[Dave Wittenberg]] impersonating [[Christopher Walken]] (US)

Much like in Digimon Tamers, an IceDevimon was a serial killer in the Digital World,but an extra in the main plot, infamous for destroying villages ([[Gekomon]] and [[Deramon]] were seen running from him) to absorb the Fractal Code of the Digimon ([[Vegiemon]] and [[Gesomon]] were seen as two of his victims) who resided there. It took an entire army to capture him (the only Digimon seen were [[ExVeemon]], [[Aquilamon]], [[Kabuterimon]] and [[Starmon]]; everyone else was offscreen) and seal him under [[Cherubimon]]'s Castle as not even Cherubimon himself could destroy this psycho because of the all the data he absorbed.

During Cherubimon's evil reign, IceDevimon fed on the failed candidates for the Spirits of Darkness. Once the castle was destroyed, IceDevimon was freed to resume his love for killing things, starting with the [[DigiDestined]] out of curiosity of how human data 'tasted'. He froze Takuya and Koji's D-Tectors so that he can have them first and cause some difficulties to the others. He was finally defeated by [[Koichi Kimura#JagerLowemon|JagerLowemon]] and purified by [[Kouichi Kimura#Lowemon|Lowemon]] after [[Zephyrmon]], [[Korikakumon]], and [[J. P. Shibayama|MetalKabuterimon]] combined their attacks to crack him.

{{-}}

===Angemon and Nefertimon===
* Angemon: [[Hikaru Midorikawa]] (Japan). [[Dave Mallow]] (English)
* Nefertimon:  [[Ai Nagano]] (Japan), [[Bridget Hoffman]] (English)

Servants of [[Ophanimon]], Nefertimon served as caretaker of her mistress's Castle of Light while Angemon was charged with the task of protecting Katsuharu, Teppei, Chiaki and Teruo when they wanted to remain in the Digital World after the selection of the Digi-Destined. It was at Steel Town that Angemon meets the Digi-Destined, joining them in protecting his friends from Saggitarimon and his [[Centarumon]] buddies. But the [[Royal Knights]] arrived and Angemon was killed off by [[Dynasmon]], who took his Fractal Code. Later, the DigiDestined arrived to Ophanimon's case, only to find out after a day's search that Nefertimon held the Fractal Code key for the remaining land of the Digital World in her body and her death would ensure the castle's though. The Digi-Destined hesitation resulted with Nefertimon scanned by Dynasmon during the Digi-Destined's attempt to defend the castle from them.

==Movie Digimon==
===Bearmon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=Bearmon
 |description=Can be seen in the deleted scene of ''[[Spriggan]]''
 |katakana=ベアモン
 |japname=
 |image= 
 |level=Rookie
 |attribute=Vaccine
 |family=Nature Spirits
 |type=Beast
 }}
* Voiced by [[Akemi Okamura]] (Japan) &amp; [[Wendee Lee]] (US).
Bearmon (Who is sometimes miss-named &quot;kumamon&quot; like in &quot;Digimon world 2003&quot; for PSX) is one of the Beast-type Digimon who live on the Wandering Island, where his race constantly warred with the Human-type Digimon also living there. His elder brother, [[Grizzlymon]], is the general of the Beast army. However, Bearmon hates the fighting, because he is secretly best friends with [[Kotemon]], one of the Human Digimon.

[[Kouji Minamoto|Koji]] and [[Zoe Orimoto|Zoe]] wound up in the Beast village, where Bearmon took care of them, telling them about the conflict. When they were reunited, the kids began to take sides themselves, each having seen the war from one side’s point of view. Bearmon and Kotemon revealed their friendship to the kids and, as a ‘reward’ for not fighting amongst each other, took them to a cave they had found bearing the symbol of [[Ornismon]], the protective spirit of the island. They were found by [[Grizzlymon]] and [[Dinohyumon]], who started to fight each other, only to be stopped by [[KendoGarurumon]] and [[Takuya Kanbara|Agunimon]] then they forced Bearmon and Kotemon to separate.

When the war reached a crisis point and a massive battle began, Bearmon and Kotemon helped [[Bokomon]], [[Neemon]] and [[Tomoki Himi|Tommy]] to reassemble the shattered hieroglyphics in Ornismon’s chamber, only to discover that the ancient Digimon was not a protector at all but an evil force – one which was then unleashed by [[Murmuxmon]], who had fostered the conflict on the island to gather the necessary amount of Fractal Code to revive Ornismon. Kotemon begged for [[AncientGreymon]] and [[AncientGarurumon]] to save them, only to be destroyed by a blast from Ornismon. Bearmon screamed his name and two Ancient Warriors were reborn, using their power to defeat Ornismon once and for all. In the wake of the [[DigiDestined]]’s departure, Bearmon was reunited with the reborn Kotemon and they made a mural of the DigiDestined on the cave wall.

{{-}}

===Kotemon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=Kotemon
 |katakana=コテモン
 |japname=Kotemon
 |image= 
 |level=Rookie
 |attribute=Data
 |family=Nature Spirits, Dragon's Roar
 |type=Reptile Digimon
 }}
Kotemon was among the Human Digimon whose older brother was Dinohyumon. He was friends with Bearmon but their older brothers refused to let them hang out. During the part where Murmukusmon (who had been disguised as Darcmon and Hippogriffomon) had released Ornismon, Kotemon sacrificed his life to bring AncientGreymon and AncientGarurumon back to destroy Ornismon. His Digi-Egg is kept by Bearmon and it is shown in the credits that he was eventually restored. 
:''Voiced in the dub by [[Debi Mae West]]''.

===Murmuxmon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=Murmuxmon
 |katakana=
 |japname=
 |image= 
 |level=Mega
 |attribute=Virus
 |family=Nightmare Soldiers
 |type=Demon Lord
 }}
Able to assume the form of any Digimon he chooses, Murmuxmon was an evil Digimon who was banished on the Floating Island. It was there, he learned about [[Onismon]] and started the war between the Beast Digimon (As [[HippoGryphomon]]) and the Human Digimon (As [[D'Arcmon]]) for the purpose of extracting enough data to revive the ancient monster and use it to conquer the Digital World and have his revenge. He was ultimately destroyed by [[Agunimon]].

====d'Arcmon====
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=d'Arcmon
 |katakana=ダルクモン
 |japname=
 |image= 
 |level=Champion
 |attribute=Vaccine
 |family=Wind Guardians
 |type=Angel
 }}
* Voiced by [[Tara Platt]] (US) and [[Takako Uehara]] (Japan).
[[List of Champion Digimon (Part 1)#d'Arcmon|d'Arcmon]] was the leader of the Human-type Digimon (made up of [[Kotemon]], [[Dinohyumon]], some [[Yasyamon]], [[Pucchiemon]], [[Nohemon]], and [[FlameWizardmon]]) on the Wandering Island. She preached a message of peace, decrying the violent actions of the war but as things escalated he urged her followers to fight in the name of peace, although she was nowhere to be seen in the ensuing battle. The reasons behind her contradictory actions soon became clear when the [[DigiDestined]] followed her and discovered that she and the leader of the Beast-types, [[HippoGryphomon]], were the same being and with her deception revealed to both sides, d'Arcmon revealed her true identity to be the villainous [[Murmuxmon]]. This digimon is named after the famous French liberateress, [[Joan of Arc]].
{{-}}

====HippoGryphomon====
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=HippoGryphomon
 |katakana=
 |japname=
 |image= 
 |level=Ultimate
 |attribute=Data
 |family=Nature Spirits&lt;br&gt;Wind Guardians
 |type=Mythical Animal
 }}
* Voiced by [[Wally Wingert]] (English) and [[Hikaru Midorikawa]] (Japan).
[[List of Ultimate Digimon (Part 2)#HippoGryphomon|HippoGryphomon]] was the leader of the Beast-type Digimon (made up of [[Bearmon]], [[Grizzlymon]], [[Oryxmon]], [[Rabbitmon]], [[Boarmon]], [[Bullmon]], [[Prairiemon]], and [[Moosemon]]) on the Wandering Island. He preached a message of peace with emotion. The reasons behind his contradictory actions soon became clear when the [[DigiDestined]] discovered that he and the leader of the Human-types, [[d'Arcmon]], were the same being, and, with her/his deception revealed to both sides, HippoGryphomon turned into d'Arcmon then revealed her/his true identify to be the villainous [[Murmuxmon]].
{{-}}

===Dinohyumon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=Dinohyumon
 |katakana=ディノヒューモン
 |japname=Dinohumon
 |image= 
 |level=Champion
 |attribute=Data
 |family=Nature Spirits, Dragon's Roar
 |type=Dragon Man
 }}
* Voiced by [[Doug Erholtz]] (US) &amp; [[Yuji Ueda]] (Japan)
'''[[List of Champion Digimon (Part 1)#Dinohyumon|Dinohyumon]]''' was the second-in-command of the Human-type Digimon on the Wandering Island and rival of [[Grizzlymon]]. He was first encountered by the [[DigiDestined]] as he routed a Beast-type Digimon attack on the Human-type settlement in vain. Later, when attempting to drive [[Bearmon]], a friend of his younger brother Kotemon, away, he got into a big fight with Grizzlymon. [[Takuya Kanbara|Agunimon]] stopped Dinohyumon, who tried to recruit him in preparation for the impending climactic battle. Takuya agreed, as part of the DigiDestined's plan to stop the fight.

When [[Zoe Orimoto|Zoe]] and [[J. P. Shibayama|J.P.]] revealed the connection between the two faction's leaders, Dinohyumon challenged their claim but Takuya countered by asking him where [[d'Arcmon]] was, forcing [[HippoGryphomon]] to transform into d'Arcmon before Dinohyumon's eyes and revive [[Ornismon]]. Spurred on by Kotemon’s sacrifice, Dinohyumon and Grizzlymon joined forces and had their armies weaken Ornismon, allowing [[AncientGreymon]] and [[AncientGarurumon]] to destroy the demon bird once and for all. With the Wandering Island back on the Digital World, Dinohyumon gave his thanks to the DigiDestined and apologized for his actions.

{{-}}

===Grizzlymon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=Grizzlymon
 |katakana=グリズモン
 |japname=Grizzmon
 |image= 
 |level=Champion
 |attribute=Vaccine
 |family=Nature Spirits
 |type=Beast
 }}
* Voiced by [[Peter Spellos]] (US) &amp; [[Kenta Miyake]] (Japan)
[[List of Champion Digimon (Part 2)#Grizzlymon|Grizzlymon]] was the second-in-command of the Beast Digimon on the Wandering Island and got his orders from [[HippoGryphomon]]. When fighting with [[Dinohyumon]] to separate his little brother, [[Bearmon]], from Dinohyumon's brother, [[Kotemon]], [[Takuya Kanbara|Takuya]] and [[Kouji Minamoto|Koji]] intervened as [[Agunimon]] and [[Kouji Minamoto#KendoGarurumon|KendoGarurumon]]. Grizzlymon requested that Koji fight for the Beasts. When [[J. P. Shibayama|J.P.]] and [[Zoe Orimoto|Zoe]] tried to convince Grizzlymon and Dinohyumon that HippoGryphomon and [[d'Arcmon]] were the same being, Grizzlymon ignored them until HippoGryphomon appeared and it turned out that both were the forms for [[Murmuxmon]], who needed the energy from the  [[Ornismon]].  and the Beast Digimon and Dinohyumon and the Human Digimon combined their powers and were able to weaken Ornismon enough for [[AncientGreymon]] and [[AncientGarurumon]] to destroy him. After that, Grizzlymon and Dinohyumon apologized and thanked the Legendary Warriors for restoring peace between the Human Digimon and the Beast Digimon.
{{-}}

===Onismon===
{{Digimon Infobox
 |name=Onismon
 |katakana=
 |japname=Ornismon
 |image= 
 |from=[[Garudamon]]&lt;ref&gt;http://tnis.hp.infoseek.co.jp/web-digimon/st-932.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;
 |level=Mega
 |attribute=Virus
 |family=Nature Spirits&lt;br&gt;Nightmare Soldiers
 |type=Ancient Bird
 }}
Onismon is an ancient Digimon who was sealed away by [[AncientGreymon]] and [[AncientGarurumon]] in ancient times when he terrorized the [[Digital World]]. When the villainous [[Murmuxmon]] heard of him, he planned on reviving him to get revenge on the ones who banished him to the Wandering Island. To do so, Murmuxmon unleashed a war between the human form and beast form Digimon on the island to get many Digi-eggs which would help him revive Onismon. Although the [[DigiDestined]] found out what he planned, it was too late and Murmuxmon was able to revive Onismon. The two then went on a killing spree on the wandering island but the DigiDestined as well as the tanks of both factions were able to cause some damage to the powerful Digimon. [[Bearmon]]'s prayers finally allowed AncientGreymon and AncientGarurumon to appear and they destroyed Onismon, this time for good.

{{-}}

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Digimon}}

[[Category:Lists of Digimon characters|Frontier]]

[[it:Personaggi di Digimon Frontier]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
