<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="919555" ns="0" title="Parody advertisement"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">A '''parody advertisement''' is a fictional [[advertisement]] for a non-existent product, either done within another advertisement for an actual product, or done simply as [[parody]] of advertisements—used either as a way of ridiculing or drawing negative attention towards a real advertisement or such an advertisement's subject, or as a [[comedic device]], such as in a [[comedy skit]] or [[sketch]].

==Overview==
A parody advertisement should not be confused with a fictional brand name used in a program to avoid giving free advertising to an actual product, or to the use of a fictional brand name in an actual advertisement used for comparison, which is sometimes done as opposed to comparing the product to an actual competitor (in some countries, ([[Germany]] or [[Norway]] for example) it is illegal to make disparaging comments about a competitor's product in an advertisement, even if the statements are proven to be true.&lt;ref&gt;Germany's &quot;Act against Unfair Competition&quot; or &quot;Gesetz gegen den unlauteren Wettbewerb&quot; (UWG) of 3 July 2004, § 6 generally forbids the use of [[comparative advertising]].  Technically it is not &quot;illegal&quot; in that almost all actions under the law are based on private lawsuits, e.g. typically the company whose product is being mentioned sues, rather than the government prosecuting.&lt;/ref&gt;)

A parody advertisement can be one in which the advertisement appears to ''actually be a real ad for'' the false product, but then the advertisement is somehow exposed to be a parody and if it is an actual advertisement the actual brand becomes clear.  If it is simply a parody it may or may not indicate that it is one.

==Notable examples==
===Film===
*'''''[[Tropic Thunder]]''''': In addition to ''[[Tropic Thunder]]'''s (in)famous fake movie trailers, the film has a parody ad for the fake products 'Booty Sweat' [[energy drink]] and 'Bust-A-Nut' [[candy bar]].  As part of the film's marketing 'Booty Sweat' has been made into a real life energy drink.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tropicthunder.com/bootysweat/feature.php Booty Sweat Energy Drink]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.energyfiend.com/2008/06/booty-sweat-energy-drink Booty Sweat Energy Drink]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.examiner .com/x-281-Caffeine-Examiner~y2008m8d22-Tropic-Thunder-energy-drink-turns-real--and-doesnt-really-taste-like-Booty-Sweat [[Tropic Thunder]] energy drink turns real - and doesnt really taste like Booty Sweat]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''''[[Bamboozled]]''''': [[Spike Lee]]'s satire has fake ads for 'Da Bomb' [[malt liquor]] and a racistly-named parody of [[Tommy Hilfiger Corporation|Tommy Hilfiger]].  In addition to the appearance in ''[[Bamboozled]]'', 'Da Bomb' makes appearances in two other Spike Lee films, ''[[Clockers (film)|Clockers]]'', and ''[[Inside Man]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0454848/trivia Trivia for Inside Man]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''''[[Grindhouse (film)|Grindhouse]]''''': The film ''[[Grindhouse (film)|Grindhouse]]'', which is essentially the movies ''[[Planet Terror]]'' and ''[[Death Proof]]'' combined, has [[trailer (film)|trailers]] for a number of fictional films.  These include ''[[Machete (film)|Machete]]'', in which the FBI hires a mercenary rather than risk their own agents on a potential suicide mission; ''Werewolf Women of the SS'' about a group of women who run a nazi death camp; ''Don't'', an exploitive horror film; ''Thanksgiving'', a slasher film in the genre of the ''[[Halloween (1978 film)|Halloween]]'' series; and ''Hobo With a Shotgun'' about a vigilante killer similar to the premise of the film ''[[Death Wish (film)|Death Wish]]''.  The trailer for ''Machete'' was so well received it has been decided that the movie will actually be made.
*'''''[[RoboCop]]''''': Parody advertisements are seen throughout the [[RoboCop (franchise)|RoboCop franchise]] for products such as the &quot;6000 SUX&quot;, a parody of the low fuel economy of many American-made cars at that time,&lt;ref&gt;[http://robocop.wikia.com/wiki/6000_SUX 6000 SUX at the RoboCop Wiki]&lt;/ref&gt; the game &quot;NUKEM&quot;, a parody of [[Battleship (game)|Battleship]], and &quot;Magnavolt&quot;, a car security system designed to electrocute and kill would-be carjackers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/therush/article/robocop---a-few-words-from-the-future/18 RoboCop - A Few Words From the Future]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''''[[UHF (film)|UHF]]''''': The [[Weird Al Yankovic]] film ''[[UHF (film)|UHF]]'' has a few fake ads within the film, such as &quot;[[Spatula City]]&quot;, a store that sells nothing but spatulas,&lt;ref&gt;[http://weirdal.wikia.com/wiki/Spatula_City Spatula City at The Weird Al Wiki]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as promos for fake TV shows and movies like &quot;[[Conan the Librarian]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://conan.wikia.com/wiki/Parodies Parodies at the Conan Wiki]&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;[[Gandhi II]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://weirdal.wikia.com/wiki/Gandhi_II Gandhi II at the Weird Al Wiki]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television===
*The American [[sketch comedy]] series '''''[[Saturday Night Live]]''''' produces fictional commercials on a regular basis, usually shown after the guest host's monologue as an &quot;[[Saturday Night Live commercial|introductory commercial]]&quot;, prior to the beginning the main show.  Many of these ads, while they parody actual TV commercials are simple ''[[Parody|comedic parodies]]'' of the style of the real advertisement rather than its product.
*Likewise, many subsequent sketch comedy programs have utilized parody advertisements, including ''[[MAD TV]]'', ''[[In Living Color]]'' and ''[[The Idiot Box (MTV)|The Idiot Box]]''.
*'''''[[Short Circuitz]]''''', an [[MTV]] sketch comedy show starring [[Nick Cannon]], often featured parodies of popular advertisements. Its accompanying website, [http://shortcircuitz.mtv.com ShortCircuitz.mtv.com], allows users to upload their own parody advertisements to compete for a cash prize and a spot on the show.

====Fictional advertisements for real products====
*In the 1990s, the most famous series of parody advertisements were those for the [[Energizer]] battery. A parody itself of a [[Duracell]] battery commercial, in its initial commercial episode first shown in October 1989, a toy pink rabbit, is being filmed in a commercial.  The toy, powered by the battery, escapes the studio and begins a rampage, pounding a drum and rolling through other commercials being made, including those for coffee, wine, a fictional upcoming TV series, long distance service, breakfast cereal, and sinus medication.  A total of 120 fictional commercials and 3 real ones (for [[Twinkies]], [[Purina Cat Chow]], and [[Duracell]]) in both [[English language|English]] and [[Spanish language|Spanish]] involving the [[Energizer Bunny]] were made.
*In an ironic twist, in 1991, [[Energizer Holdings|Eveready Battery Company]] sued the [[Adolph Coors Company]] over an ad for [[Coors Brewing Company|Coors]] beer it was producing, which showed actor [[Leslie Nielsen]] in a full-size rabbit suit pounding a drum, which was parodying Eveready's [[Energizer Bunny]] commercials, which themselves are parodies of [[Duracell]] advertisements and television program previews.  Eveready claimed Coors' ad constituted copyright and trademark infringement.  The court ruled that Coors' ad was a valid parody of Eveready's, considering that Mr. Nielsen &quot;is not a toy, and does not run on batteries.&quot; ''[[Eveready Battery Co. v. Adolph Coors Co.]]'', [[Case citation|765 F. Supp. 440]] (N.D. Ill. 1991).
*The [[GEICO]] insurance company ran a [[GEICO advertising campaigns|series of television commercials]] in which a victim in a disadvantaged situation hears their fate from the [[antagonist]], that they have good news, only the good news is for the antagonist (The antagonist will usually say as the punchline, &quot;I just saved a bunch of money on my car insurance by switching to GEICO&quot;).  Some examples involved a fictional congressional hearing where the witness (the victim) is being informed he is subject to criminal penalties while the chairman of the committee (the antagonist) has saved money on his car insurance, a home repair show reminiscent of [[Bob Vila]] showing a victim couple with a home badly in need of repair, a fictional news report on a volcanic eruption, and a fictional hair restoration commercial. Another example parodied advertisements for [[reality TV]] shows, by showing a couple getting married, and getting disgruntled at living in a tiny house (the punchline: a voiceover saying &quot;The drama may be real, but it won't save you any money on car insurance&quot;, followed by the wife asking her spouse in their tiny [[hot tub]] &quot;Why haven't you called GEICO?&quot;).
*The [[Coca-Cola]] company's lemon-lime soft drink [[Sprite (soft drink)|Sprite]] ran a series of ads for other fictional drink products, which had actual or fictional celebrities endorsing the other product, with the implication that the fictional product was inadequate for quenching one's thirst.
*The gimmick of characters from a commercial invading other spoof ads was first used by the [[United Kingdom|British]] Lager brewers [[Carling Black Label]]. The advert featured a wild west outlaw being roped by a [[Posse comitatus (common law)|posse]] and dragging them off their horses and into adverts for a love compilation Album and Washing up powder.
*&quot;Poser Mobile&quot; ran an advertising campaign for [[T-Mobile]]'s pay-as-you-go cell phone plan featuring a racially diverse group of [[Hip hop music|hip-hop]] [[poseur|poser]]s.  The group of five ambush the cell phone customer and explain that he has to pay hidden charges and fees. One customer in a commercial calls them &quot;clowns&quot;. It is somewhat of a [[parody]] on [[Boost Mobile]]'s &quot;Where You At?&quot; advertising campaign which features prominent [[Hip hop music|hip-hop]] artists such as [[Ludacris]], [[Kanye West]], and [[The Game (rapper)|The Game]].
*''[[MasterCard]]''’s “priceless” commercials have often been parodied [http://humor.beecy.net/videos/priceless/]. The general theme shows a normal setting where several expenses are listed, but at the end one absurd priceless expense constitutes a punch line.

===Magazines and print===
====Mad Magazine====
''[[Mad Magazine]]'' was notorious for regularly running obviously fictional ads for nonexistent products. However, many of these nonexistent products were clearly intended to be parodies of specific well-known brands of real-world products; frequently, the fictional advertisement in ''Mad'' parodied a specific genuine ad campaign for a recognizable brand-name product. For example, in the 1960s (when cigarettes could still be advertised on television), Kent Cigarettes ran a commercial featuring a series of line drawings illustrating the lyrics of a catchy jingle titled &quot;The Taste of Kent&quot;. ''Mad'' promptly ran a fake print ad, using drawings which parodied the style of the line art, illustrating verses about lung cancer and emphysema to a lyric that parodied Kent's jingle, now titled &quot;The Taste of Death&quot;.

According to [[Frank Jacobs]]'s biography ''[[The Mad World of William M. Gaines]]'', Mad's parodies of real advertisements generated so much attention that Mad publisher [[William Gaines]] received requests from the promotional departments of many real products, asking Mad to run parodies of their advertisements. Gaines's standard reply to such requests: &quot;Come up with a really stupid ad campaign, and we'll be happy to make fun of it.&quot;

====Hustler====
The most serious incident involving a fictional advertisement in a magazine caused a lawsuit which reached all the way to the U.S. Supreme Court, when [[Hustler Magazine]] ran a parody of a liquor ad which would ask people about their &quot;first time.&quot;  In the actual ad, what we are led to believe is that the person is being asked about their first sexual experience, when it turns out the question is about their first time they used the sponsor's product, a liqueur.

In the parody advertisement in ''Hustler'', the Reverend [[Jerry Falwell]] is supposedly quoted describing the first time he had sexual intercourse with his mother in an outhouse while intoxicated.  Falwell sued Hustler Magazine and its publisher [[Larry Flynt]] for invasion of privacy, libel and emotional distress.  The jury found for the magazine on the issue of libel (the fictional advertisement clearly indicated it was a parody), but awarded Mr. Falwell $350,000 in damages for the emotional distress and invasion of privacy claims.  The Supreme Court ruled that, since the advertisement was so obviously a parody that no reasonable person could have believed it, Falwell was not libelled and thus is not entitled to damages for emotional distress, and he was not entitled to damages for invasion of privacy because he is a well-known public figure.  ''[[Hustler Magazine v. Falwell|Hustler Magazine, Inc. et al. v. Jerry Falwell]]'', [[Case citation|485 U.S. 46, (1988)]].

====Other examples====
*The Adbusters Media Foundation's magazine ''Adbusters'' features [http://adbusters.org/spoofads/index.php advertisement parodies] that are intended as sharp commentary on the social implications of either the product or the advertising campaign involved (also known as &quot;[[Culture Jamming]]&quot;). One example is a parody of the &quot;[[Joe Camel]]&quot; advertising campaign for [[Camel Cigarettes]], with a pseudo Joe Camel in a hospital bed, his head bald and an [[intravenous drip]] bottle leading into his arm, with the legend &quot;Joe Chemo&quot; on the faux ad, implying that the many years of smoking cigarettes has left &quot;Joe&quot; with cancer and requiring [[chemotherapy]] treatment. [http://adbusters.org/spoofads/tobacco/jc2/]
*The [[Wrigley's]] company created fictional print ads for [[Juicy Fruit]], such as boy bands, an upcoming fictional movie poster, and a phony handheld game system.
*[[Games Magazine]], a monthly publication featuring game- and puzzle-related material, through the 1980s carried a fake ad feature noted (without page number) in each issue's contents with the tagline''&quot;Which of the pitches is full of hitches?&quot;''  One featured item was an abacus simulator running on PCs made by the nonexistent Nat Soh Software Co. of Hong Kong.  The challenge to readers was to scrutinize all of the ads to spot the fake.

===Miscellaneous===
*Superhero-themed rock band [[The Aquabats]] are notorious for styling their live shows after [[Saturday morning cartoon]]s, including engaging in scripted onstage battles with costumed monsters. Typically, when these villains crash the stage, the concert will &quot;cut to commercial&quot; and a video screen behind the band will project a pre-recorded advertisement for an obviously fake Aquabats-brand product, before returning to the show. Such products have included &quot;The Aquabats Totally Slammin' Pudding Dispenser Belt&quot;, &quot;The Aquabats Therapeutic Rub-O-Rama&quot; [[ointment]] and official Aquabats t-shirts (which the commercial claims enables its wearer to eat nails and cut down trees with their bare knuckles).

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=35em}}

{{Appropriation in the Arts}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Parody Advertisement}}
[[Category:Parodies|Advertisement]]
[[Category:Advertising by type]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
