<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9204734" ns="0" title="Jonny Foster"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1=File:Jonny Foster.png
|name=Jonny Foster
|creator=[[Kathleen Beedles]]
|introducer=Kathleen Beedles &lt;small&gt;(2007)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Anita Turner]] &lt;small&gt;(2009)&lt;/small&gt;
|portrayer=[[Richard Grieve]]
|occupation=[[Farrier]] 
|born=1974
|home=[[Australia]]
|classification=[[List of past Emmerdale characters#Last appeared in 2009|Former; regular]]
|mother=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2007)#Patricia Foster|Patricia Foster]]
|husband=[[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul Lambert]] (2008—)
|years=2007–08, 2009
|first=25 February 2007
|last=27 January 2009
}}

'''Jonathan &quot;Jonny&quot; Foster''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'' played by [[Richard Grieve]]. He appeared from 2007 to 2008 and in 2009. Openly [[Homosexual orientation|gay]], in 2008 Jonny enters into a [[civil partnership]] with [[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul Lambert]], the first of any primetime soap opera.

==Character creation and development==
It was announced on 29 March 2008 that Jonny was being written out of the programme,&lt;ref name=&quot;DS3&quot;/&gt; and it was reported that Grieve had been axed by series producer [[Anita Turner]], in addition to the axing of characters [[Grayson Sinclair]] and [[Perdita Hyde-Sinclair]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DS2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a93043/emmerdale-boss-slammed-for-sacking-toddler.html|title='Emmerdale' boss slammed for sacking toddler|first=Beth|last=Hilton|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|date=4 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before this there was already reports of low morale,&lt;ref name=&quot;DS3&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a92574/emmerdale-stars-unhappy-with-new-chief.html|title='Emmerdale' stars 'unhappy' with new chief|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|date=29 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the axing apparently caused friction on set.&lt;ref name=&quot;DS2&quot;/&gt; At the time Grieve said that while he had &quot;thoroughly enjoyed the role&quot; he thought &quot;the time is right to move on.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DS3&quot;/&gt; 

In December 2008, it was announced that Jonny would be returning to ''Emmerdale'' to play a part in the departure of Paul.&lt;ref name=&quot;DS1&quot;/&gt; The actor said that he &quot;couldn't resist this opportunity&quot; to return to the programme.&lt;ref name=&quot;DS1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a137792/jonny-foster-to-make-emmerdale-return.html|title=Jonny Foster to make 'Emmerdale' return|first=Kris|last=Green|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|date=8 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Character history==
Jonny first appears in February 2007 when he strikes up a friendly working relationship with [[bisexual]] [[Grayson Sinclair]]. Grayson's wife, [[Perdita Hyde-Sinclair|Perdy]], soon starts to think they are having affair. She then sets up a business dinner and invites her gay friend Paul Lambert, hoping they get together. This works, and the eventually go on a date. After six months together, Jonny moves into Victoria Cottage with Paul, Paul's father [[Rodney Blackstock]] and [[Emily Kirk]]. He confides in Paul that as a teenager he suffered from an eating disorder as a result of loneliness and unhappiness. During his time in Emmerdale, Jonny sets up an aerobics dance class and a fitness club.

When Grayson and Perdy have difficulties in their relationship – caused by his mother [[Rosemary King|Rosemary]] – she is sectioned, and Paul spends more time with Grayson as he acts a go between the two. Paul develops feelings for Grayson, and Jonny asks Paul to marry him. Paul accepts, but during their engagement he has a one-night stand with Grayson. When Grayson tells Paul it meant nothing to him, Paul feels guilty and tells Jonny. He manages to persuade Jonny not to leave Emmerdale and on 3 March 2008 they have their [[Civil partnership in the United Kingdom|civil partnership]] at Hotten Registry Office. Later that day they have a ceremony at Home Farm, as neither can tell their parents they have already legally married.

After Grayson and Perdy separate, [[Katie Sugden]] gives birth to their child, who she had agreed to surrogate when they were still together. Katie had told Grayson that they would bring up the child together, without Perdy, but changes her mind when she finds out about Grayson’s relationship with Paul. Katie had not told Perdy of her plans to give the child to her, so when Katie goes into labour Perdy tells Grayson. Perdy soon runs off with the baby, but Jonny refuses to believe that Paul had not tipped Grayson off. He later does believe Paul, but he later sees Paul and Grayson hug. Although, Paul said nothing had happened and he had not reciprocated the hug, Jonny said he could no longer trust Paul and leaves the village on 31 July 2008. He later texts asking for a [[divorce]].

In January 2009, Jonny requests they close their joint bank account. Paul's friends, [[Lily Butterfield]] and [[Leyla Harding]], seeing how upset he is decides to try and reconcile him and Jonny. This causes Jonny's mother, [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2007)#Patricia Foster|Patricia]], to visit the village. After initial confusion, Paul convinces Patricia that he still loves Jonny, who has moved to [[Australia]]. He plans to travel to Australia to try and build his relationship with Jonny, but his mother [[Val Pollard]] lies and tells him that Rodney has a heart condition in attempt to ensure he does not leave the village. Lily, however, gets in touch with Jonny and arranges a meeting between him and Paul. While they both still love each other, Paul tells Jonny he cannot leave Emmerdale because of his father's condition. However, on the day Jonny is due to fly out, Paul finds out his mother was lying about his father's condition, and Paul rushes to meet Jonny to fly to Australia with him.

==Reception==
On 3 March 2008, Paul and Jonny made British television history by becoming the first couple on a primetime soap opera to enter a civil partnership since the [[Civil Partnership Act 2004]] came into force on 5 December 2005. Although radio soap ''[[The Archers]]'' and daytime soap ''[[Doctors (2000 TV series)|Doctors]]'' had previously featured civil partnerships, ''Emmerdale'' was the first primetime soap opera to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailyrecord.co.uk/entertainment/entertainment-catch-all/2008/02/28/i-m-proud-we-ll-have-the-first-primetime-gay-soap-wedding-86908-20334052/|title=I'm Proud We'll Have The First Primetime Gay Soap Wedding|first=Rick|last=Fulton|publisher=[[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]]|date=28 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Matthew Bose]], who plays Paul, said he was &quot;proud&quot; ''Emmerdale'' was the first, and commented that soaps &quot;have a great responsibility to show things as they change and be cutting edge&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;/&gt;
Sarah Ellis hip

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{EDBlackstock}}
{{EDLambert}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Foster, Jonny}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional gay males]]
[[Category:Fictional Australian people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
