<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="92121" ns="0" title="Interstate 91"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup-link rot|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox road
|country=USA
|type=I
|route=91
|map=Interstate 91 map.png
|length_mi=290.37
|length_round=2
|length_ref=&lt;ref name=fhwa&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fhwa.dot.gov/reports/routefinder/table1.htm|title=FHWA Route Log and Finder List: Table 1|date=2002-10-31|accessdate=2007-03-28|author=Federal Highway Administration}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|direction_a=South
|direction_b=North
|terminus_a={{jct|state=CT|I|95}} in [[New Haven, Connecticut|New Haven, CT]]
|terminus_b={{jct|state=QC|A|55}} at the [[United States-Canada border|Canadian Border]] at [[Derby Line, VT]]
|established=
|junction=&lt;!-- Major junctions only; Only 5-8 most major intersections and cities belong here; please read [[WP:USRD/STDS]] for more info --&gt;{{jct|state=CT|I|84}} in [[Hartford, Connecticut|Hartford, CT]]&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=MA|I|90|MATP}} near [[Springfield, Massachusetts|Springfield, MA]]&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=VT|I|89}} in [[White River Junction, Vermont|White River Junction, VT]]&lt;br&gt;{{jct|state=VT|I|93}} near [[St. Johnsbury, Vermont|St. Johnsbury, VT]]
}}
'''Interstate 91''' (abbreviated '''I-91''') is an [[Interstate Highway]] in the [[New England]] region of the [[United States]].  It provides the primary north&amp;ndash;south thoroughfare in the western part of New England. The interstate's southern end is in [[New Haven, Connecticut]]&lt;ref&gt;{{google maps |url=http://maps.google.com/maps?q=New+Haven,+CT&amp;ll=41.302765,-72.914028&amp;spn=0.014517,0.022505&amp;hl=en |accessdate=June 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; at [[Interstate 95 in Connecticut|Interstate 95]]; its northern end is at [[Derby Line, Vermont]], a village in the town of [[Derby, Vermont|Derby]], at the [[Canada–United States border|Canadian]] border, where it continues as [[Quebec Autoroute 55|Autoroute 55]]. I-91 is the longest of three Interstate highways whose entire route is located within the New England states, and is also the only primary (two-digit) Interstate highway in New England to intersect all five of the others that run through the region.  The largest cities along its route are [[Springfield, Massachusetts]], [[Hartford, Connecticut]], and [[New Haven, Connecticut]], in order from north to south.

Interstate 91 is {{convert|290|mi|km}} long and runs nearly straight north and south: {{convert|58|mi|km}} in [[Connecticut]]; {{convert|55|mi|km}} in [[Massachusetts]]; and {{convert|177|mi|km}} in [[Vermont]]. (The net displacement is 259 miles (417&amp;nbsp;km), and the net direction is 9.0 degrees clockwise from north or south, i.e., [[northeast by north]] or [[southwest by south]].) I-91 parallels [[U.S. Route 5]] for all of its length, and many of the exits along I-91 provide direct or indirect access to the older route.

Much of the route of Interstate 91 follows the [[Connecticut River]], running from [[Hartford, Connecticut]] northward to [[St. Johnsbury, Vermont]].

==Route description==
{{lengths table}}
|-
|[[Interstate 91 in Connecticut|CT]]
|57.6
|92.7
|-
|[[Massachusetts|MA]]
|54.9
|88.4
|-
|[[Vermont|VT]]
|177
|285
|-
|Total
|290
|467
|}

===Connecticut===
{{main|Interstate 91 in Connecticut}}
[[Image:I91 Connecticut.jpg|right|thumb|250px|I-91 has an [[HOV Lane]] between [[Hartford, Connecticut|Hartford]] and [[Windsor, Connecticut|Windsor]]]]
Interstate 91 is the major north&amp;ndash;south transportation corridor for the center of the state. It is the main route between the larger cities of [[New Haven]], [[Hartford]], and [[Springfield, Massachusetts]]. As such, it is almost always heavily trafficked (especially during rush hour), and maintains at least three lanes in each direction through Connecticut except for a short portion in Hartford at the interchange with [[Interstate 84 (Connecticut)|Interstate 84]]. The three cities also serve as Connecticut's control points along its length of the Interstate. Overhead signs in each direction consistently feature one or two of the cities.

The highway begins just east of downtown New Haven at the intersection with the [[Connecticut Turnpike]] [[Interstate 95 in Connecticut|Interstate 95]] and [[Connecticut Route 34]]. At the bottom of the ramp for Exit 5, [[U.S. Route 5]] has its southern terminus and the first of its many interchanges with the freeway. Leaving New Haven, I-91 follows a northeastward trek through New Haven's suburbs of [[North Haven, Connecticut|North Haven]] and [[Wallingford, Connecticut|Wallingford]] before entering the city of [[Meriden, Connecticut|Meriden]]. In Meriden, about halfway between Hartford and New Haven, I-91 sees an interchange with its first spur route, [[Interstate 691]]. I-691 provides a westward link to [[Interstate 84 (Connecticut)|Interstate 84]] and the city of [[Waterbury, Connecticut|Waterbury]]. Leaving Meriden, I-91 travels briefly through Middletown before passing through Cromwell, Rocky Hill, and Wethersfield, eventually entering the Hartford city limits. Just south of Hartford, the highway begins to directly parallel the [[Connecticut River]]. In Hartford, I-91 interchanges with [[Interstate 84 (Connecticut)|I-84]] before leaving the city limits. I-91 will maintain an urban character throughout its distance to Springfield. Halfway between the two cities, Exit 40 provides direct access (via [[Connecticut Route 20]]) to the [[Bradley International Airport]]. I-91 runs through [[Windsor, Connecticut|Windsor]], [[Windsor Locks, Connecticut|Windsor Locks]], [[East Windsor, Connecticut|East Windsor]] and [[Enfield, Connecticut|Enfield]] (with several exits in each town) before crossing into [[Massachusetts]] at milepost 58.

I-91's final exit in Connecticut is Exit 49, which offers northbound travelers access to [[Longmeadow, Massachusetts]], after which I-91 enters Massachusetts.

===Massachusetts===

Interstate 91 travels {{convert|55|mi}} through the [[Pioneer Valley]] of western Massachusetts paralleling the [[Connecticut River]]. I-91 serves as the major transportation corridor through three Massachusetts counties, linking the cities of [[Springfield, Massachusetts|Springfield]], [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], and [[Greenfield, Massachusetts|Greenfield]]. The three cities serve as the control cities listed on guide and mileage signs, along with [[Brattleboro, Vermont]] beginning with the first northbound conventional mileage sign ({{convert|63|mi}}) in Longmeadow. 

In Springfield, I-91 intersects with [[Interstate 291]] at Exit 6, a {{convert|5.44|mi}} spur going eastbound connecting with the [[Massachusetts Turnpike]], for travelers going either east to [[Boston]] or west to [[Albany, New York]].

North of Springfield, I-91 briefly enters Chicopee itself where there is an interchange with the spur of [[Interstate 391]] before turning westward to cross the Connecticut River into [[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]]. I-391 provides direct access to [[Holyoke, Massachusetts|Holyoke]] center, while I-91 continues on the western side of the river.

Just after the river crossing, Exit 14 is a major interchange with the [[Massachusetts Turnpike]] (I-90) before entering the city of Holyoke where Exit 15 is located. Just after Exit 16 [[U.S. 202]], I-91 goes from three lanes to two lanes in each direction to the Vermont state line. 

After a short exit-less stretch, I-91 enters [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], passing the [[Northampton Airport]] and an [[oxbow lake]]. The towns of [[Hadley, Massachusetts|Hadley]] and [[Amherst, Massachusetts|Amherst]], home to the main campus of the [[University of Massachusetts]], are accessible from I-91 exits in Northampton via [[Massachusetts Route 9|Route 9]].

Continuing north, I-91 enters [[Hatfield, Massachusetts|Hatfield]], and where it begins its straightest section&amp;nbsp;— nearly {{convert|6|mi|km}} without a bend in the road. Several exits provide access to [[U.S. Route 5]] and [[Massachusetts Route 10]] in [[Hatfield, Massachusetts|Hatfield]] and [[Whately, Massachusetts|Whately]] before entering [[Deerfield, Massachusetts|Deerfield]].

I-91 has two exits in [[Greenfield, Massachusetts|Greenfield]]. At Exit 26, there is a rest area/visitor information center for [[Franklin County, Massachusetts|Franklin County]]. Exit 28 in [[Bernardston, Massachusetts|Bernardston]] is the last exit in Massachusetts. Beyond exit 28, I-91 continues for about {{convert|5|mi}} more before crossing into Vermont.

The {{convert|55|mi}} stretch of I-91 in Massachusetts is the only section to feature motorist-aid call boxes. The call boxes are still important, as a good part of I-91 in Massachusetts is rural, unlike many other freeways in the state. Massachusetts is the only state traversed by Interstate 91 where another numbered highway is co-signed onto the Interstate (in this case, U.S. 5, for a {{convert|.5|mi}} spur near the Springfield-Longmeadow town line and MA 2, for approximately {{convert|3|mi|km}} in Greenfield).

===Vermont===
[[Image:I-91-Vermont.JPG|right|thumb|250px|I-91 looking northbound, at Exit 1, Brattleboro]]
Interstate 91 runs along the eastern border of [[Vermont]] and serves as a major transportation corridor for both Vermont and western [[New Hampshire]]. Many exits along Vermont's length of I-91 feature New Hampshire towns on the guide signs (for example, Exit 3, which lists Brattleboro and [[Keene, NH]], as the points of access). Interstate 91 is {{convert|177|mi|km}} long in Vermont and has two lanes in each direction the entire way from the Massachusetts state line at [[Guilford, Vermont|Guilford]] to [[Derby Line, Vermont|Derby Line]], nearly two-thirds of the Interstate's total length, with 29 interchanges. The highway's rural character and long distances between exits in Vermont are in stark contrast to that of its length in Connecticut and the greater [[Springfield, Massachusetts|Springfield]] area in Massachusetts, where exits are more frequent and the road carries four lanes of traffic in each direction at some points. The major control &quot;cities&quot; in Vermont are [[Brattleboro, Vermont|Brattleboro]], [[White River Junction, Vermont|White River Junction]], [[St. Johnsbury, Vermont|St. Johnsbury]], and [[Newport (city), Vermont|Newport]]. When re-entering I-91 North at Exit 28 in [[Derby, Vermont]] the control sign is for Canada.  Of these, only Newport is a city, although the others are fairly sizable towns. The road generally parallels its predecessor, US 5.

I-91 enters Vermont in the town of [[Guilford, Vermont|Guilford]]. Just before Exit 1 in Brattleboro is the Vermont Welcome Center &amp; Rest Area, which has a staffed Tourist Information Center. 

The first 3 exits are all located in the town of Brattleboro. Rt 5 North from Exit 1 provides access to a number of stores and a small industrial area before reaching the south end of the town's center, where a bridge crosses the Connecticut River to [[Hinsdale, New Hampshire]].  Exit 2/Route 9 provides access to the western village of the town (West Brattleboro), then continues west to [[Marlboro, Vermont|Marlboro]] and [[Bennington, Vermont|Bennington]].
[[Image:i91 rockingham vt 20081220.jpg|right|thumb|Northbound I-91 just north of exit 6, Rockingham, VT, looking north]]
Exit 3 is considered to be one of the busiest exits along I-91 in Vermont.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Brattleboro's main retail strip is located here. Following [[Vermont Route 9]] eastward, one can reach [[Keene, New Hampshire]] in {{convert|15|mi|km}}.

After Exit 3, I-91 heads north to pass through the towns of [[Dummerston, Vermont|Dummerston]], [[Putney, Vermont|Putney]], [[Westminster, Vermont|Westminster]], [[Rockingham, Vermont|Rockingham]], [[Springfield, Vermont|Springfield]], [[Weathersfield, Vermont|Weathersfield]], [[Windsor, Vermont|Windsor]], [[Hartland, Vermont|Hartland]], and [[Hartford, Vermont|Hartford]], home of the village of [[White River Junction, Vermont|White River Junction]]. White River Junction, listed as a control city on mileage signs as far south as [[Greenfield, Massachusetts]], is where I-91 and [[I-89]] meet and provide access to many points in Vermont and New Hampshire.

North of the interchange with I-89, I-91 continues towards [[St. Johnsbury, Vermont|St. Johnsbury]] and passes through the towns of [[Norwich, Vermont|Norwich]], [[Thetford, Vermont|Thetford]], [[Fairlee, Vermont|Fairlee]], [[Bradford, Vermont|Bradford]], [[Newbury (town), Vermont|Newbury]] (with access to the village of [[Wells River, Vermont|Wells River]]), and [[Barnet, Vermont|Barnet]], before coming to its next major intersection. Towns in New Hampshire on the other side of the river can also be easily accessed in this stretch. At Exit 19 is the northern terminus of [[Interstate 93]], a major interstate highway in New England, which provides a direct route south through the [[White Mountains (New Hampshire)|White Mountains]] and to almost all major cities in New Hampshire. Just after Exit 19, there are three exits for [[St. Johnsbury, Vermont|St. Johnsbury]], including a major intersection with [[U.S. Route 2]]. Along westbound U.S. 2, the capital of Vermont, [[Montpelier, Vermont|Montpelier]], is eventually reached from I-91, although [[I-89]] provides Montpelier with immediate Interstate access.
[[Image:I-91 in Wheelock VT.jpg|right|thumb|Southbound I-91 in [[Wheelock, Vermont]]]]

Interstate 91 continues northward, now following the [[Passumpsic River]] valley. It passes through Vermont's [[Northeast Kingdom]] region and the town of [[Lyndon, Vermont|Lyndon]]. Two exits in Lyndon serve the village of [[Lyndonville, Vermont|Lyndonville]] and [[Lyndon State College]]. After Exit 24, I-91 departs Route 5, which it had been closely paralleling since the Massachusetts border. I-91 follows the valley of Miller Run,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Van Diver, Bradford B. |title = Roadside Geology | publisher = [[Mountain Press Publishing Company]] | year = 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Miller run feeds southeast into the Passumpsic River&lt;/ref&gt; and there are no convenient services until Barton at exit 25.

The interstate proceeds through [[Sheffield, Vermont|Sheffield]]. Here it reaches the highest point on the road, just north of mile marker 150 on Sheffield Heights, {{convert|1856|ft|m}}.

After leaving the Heights, it enters [[Orleans County, Vermont|Orleans County]] and follows the [[Barton River]] valley north through [[Barton, Vermont|Barton]], [[Orleans, Vermont|Orleans]] and [[Derby, Vermont|Derby]]. Exit 29 is the final U.S. exit on I-91 just after mile marker 177 at [[Derby Line, Vermont|Derby Line]]. Beyond the exit ramp, northbound motorists enter [[Canada|Canadian]] customs at [[Stanstead, Quebec]] and continue into Canada on [[Quebec Autoroute 55|Autoroute 55]] through the [[Eastern Townships]]. To reverse direction without crossing the border, motorists must use Exit 29 to re-enter I-91 southbound. Caswell Avenue, if followed westward for a mile, intersects with [[U.S. Route 5]] at its northern terminus.

As with Connecticut and Massachusetts, U.S. 5 closely parallels Interstate 91 for their entire lengths in Vermont. Indeed, most of the large exit signs on I-91 list U.S. 5 as one of the roads (if not the only road) that can be accessed from the exit, as seen in the exit list below. While paralleling I-91 in Vermont, U.S. 5 is never co-signed onto the freeway, but remains its own two-lane road.

Traffic (and the population of each successive town) tend to diminish as the road proceeds northwards. Average daily traffic count for 2002 were&amp;nbsp;— Brattleboro (25,600), White River Junction (28,900), St. Johnsbury (10,800), and Derby Line (2,500).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interstate-guide.com/i-091.html Interstate I-91] retrieved June 2, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

A limited-access highway replacement for U.S. Route 5 was planned at the federal level starting in 1944.  A 1953 Massachusetts plan was funded by the [[Federal Aid Highway Act of 1956]], along with spur [[Interstate 291 (Massachusetts)|Interstate 291]] (but not [[Interstate 391]]).  From [[Bernardston, Massachusetts|Bernardston]] to [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], I-91 follows an abandoned right-of-way of the [[New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad]].  To support plans for [[urban renewal]] along the &quot;low value&quot; waterfront, the highway crossed the Connecticut River to parallel active NYNHH railroad tracks on the Springfield side of the river, bypassing [[West Springfield|West Springfield, Massachusetts]] and [[Agawam|Agawam, Massachusetts]].  Later, this path was perceived as cutting off the city from the river, restricting further commercial development.  By 1960, a few miles in Massachusetts were completed, starting from the Connecticut and Vermont borders. Massachusetts construction was completed from 1964 to 1970.&lt;ref name=&quot;bostonroads&quot;&gt;http://www.bostonroads.com/roads/I-91_MA/&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s there were plans to extend I-91 across the [[Long Island Sound]] from [[New Haven, Connecticut]] to [[Long Island]] in [[New York]]. The extension would continue south to the southern shore of the island perhaps along the route of the current [[County Route 46 (Suffolk County, New York)|William Floyd Parkway]]{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} in central [[Suffolk County, New York|Suffolk County]]. It would also provide easier access to [[New York City]] via the [[Interstate 495 (New York)|Long Island Expressway]], as well as to [[The Hamptons]] via Sunrise Highway ([[New York State Route 27]]).

Vermont completed its last sections of the turnpike in 1978.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.historicvermont.org/sites/html/history.html&lt;/ref&gt;

After the [[September 11 attacks]] there has been a seldom-manned temporary border patrol checkpoint near [[White River Junction, VT]] that is about {{convert|100|mi|km}} from the [[US-Canada border]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acluvt.org/issues/border_patrol_stops.php The American Civil Liberties Union of Vermont [ACLU VT&amp;#93;&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in the 1990s, several rest areas were downgraded in Vermont, increasing distances between facilities.  In 2008, Vermont closed the Springfield-Rockingham rest areas because of suspected use by drug abusers.  In 2009, the northbound rest area in Hartford was closed, creating a {{convert|90|mi|0|sing=on}} gap in on-highway facilities.  At the present time, there exist 2 intermediate rest areas with facilities in each direction, in addition to a welcome center at each end of the state.  Several parking areas remain open.&lt;ref name=&quot;rh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rutlandherald.com/article/20081210/THISJUSTIN/812100294|title=Drugs, sex force rest stop closure|work=Associated Press|accessdate=2009-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, the Massachusetts Highway Department completed a rebuild of on and off ramps in Springfield, to reduce accidents caused by weaving near the tightly spaced exits.&lt;ref name=&quot;bostonroads&quot; /&gt;

==Future enhancements==
A major rebuild of the interchange with Route 9 in Northampton is in the planning phases, as of 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mhd.state.ma.us/default.asp?pgid=content/i91/i91&amp;sid=about&lt;/ref&gt;

===Impact on Springfield's planned riverfront development===
In 2008, Springfield's urban planners contracted [[UMass Amherst]]'s School of Urban Design to research I-91's effects on Springfield, after receiving complaints from Springfielders about I-91 inhibiting residents' access to Springfield's riverfront, and access to the [[Basketball Hall of Fame]]. By 2011, Amherst had produced several dozen critiques denoting that I-91's current route, height, and development beneath and around the highway are inhibiting the development of the city's greatest potential economic and recreational resources, the [[Connecticut River]], the riverfront, and the Basketball Hall of Fame - and also limiting the interaction between these entities and the [[Metro Center, Springfield, Massachusetts|Metro Center]]. &lt;ref name=&quot;scholarworks.umass&quot;&gt;http://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1004&amp;context=larp_grad_research&amp;sei-redir=1#search=&quot;umass+interstate+91+north+end&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;scholarworks.umass_a&quot;&gt;http://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1000&amp;context=larp_honors&amp;sei-redir=1#search=&quot;umass+interstate+91+north+end&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

During its construction in the 1960s, Interstate 91 sliced through three Springfield neighborhoods: the [[North End, Springfield, Massachusetts|North End]], [[Metro Center, Springfield, Massachusetts|Metro Center]], and the [[South End, Springfield, Massachusetts|South End]]. Widely regarded as positive progress at the time, by 2011, Springfield's portion of I-91 was perceived as disrupting the urban fabric of each riverfront neighborhood, while effectively amputating everything east of the highway - the majority of the city - from the [[Connecticut River]], the [[Connecticut River Walk Park]], and the Basketball Hall of Fame. Unfortunately, Interstate 91 was erected without tunnels, footbridges, and other paths leading to the riverfront, and thus continues to pose logistical problems for people getting to the riverfront, which in turn poses problems for businesses that would like to set-up along Springfield's riverfront. The placement of I-91 has left Springfield's riverfront virtually undeveloped aside from the sliver of land surrounding the [[Basketball Hall of Fame]], an international tourist destination, which under different circumstances, might have more commercial and residential development. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.masslive.com/opinion/index.ssf/2010/02/editorial_tapping_potential_of.html&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2011, academic and civic studies are still underway. Preliminary findings indicate that I-91's placement negatively impacts tourism in Springfield's [[Metro Center, Springfield, Massachusetts|Metro Center]] -- the site of many of Springfield's historic, cultural, and entertainment venues. Springfield's most popular tourist attraction, the riverfront [[Basketball Hall of Fame]] is separated from [[Metro Center, Springfield, Massachusetts|Metro Center]] by a {{convert|20|ft}} stone wall, buttressing an elevated portion of the 6-lane Interstate 91, and greatly discouraging travel between the two areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;scholarworks.umass&quot; /&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;scholarworks.umass_a&quot; /&gt; 

====History====
Initially, in the 1950s and early 1960s, Interstate 91 was planned to be routed through [[West Springfield, Massachusetts]], down the avenue now known as Riverdale Road - with numerous bridges to be built to accommodate traffic into the City of Springfield. Indeed, Riverdale Road is the original four-lane highway built to accommodate the traffic of Interstate 91. (I-91 has since widened to six lanes.) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.kurumi.com/roads/ct/i91.html&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1960s, after Springfield learned that its longtime rival, (and current business partner in the [[Knowledge Corridor]] initiative,) the City of Hartford would use its riverfront to host Interstate 91, Springfield civic leaders petitioned for the I-91 highway to be moved to the east side of the river to cut through the city, rather than employ a series of bridges, as was originally planned. At that time of initial construction, the Connecticut River was polluted, and to many, it seemed as though its best days were long behind it. Construction plans were hastily drawn up, executed, and thus construction began on the I-91 highway. On its completion, although its daily usage far surpassed predictions, I-91 never catalyzed significant growth in Springfield, as was the original hope. 

Academic suggestions have been made that involve the demolition of the current highway, and moving it to a less obtrusive site in the city; the demolition of the highway and following the original path suggested, (Riverdale Road;) and least obtrusively, but still requiring a great deal of work, a plan to construct numerous walkways beneath the elevated highway to better integrate the neighborhoods with the waterfront despite the highway's presence. &lt;ref name=&quot;scholarworks.umass&quot; /&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;scholarworks.umass_a&quot; /&gt; 

In 2010, the [[Urban Land Institute]] made recommendations for how Springfield might reconnect with its riverfront, suggesting the most cost effective but also the most developmentally limiting strategy, (constructing pathways beneath I-91). No decision has been reached regarding those recommendations. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.springfieldcityhall.com/planning/riverfront-proj.0.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exit list==
===Connecticut===
:''See [[Interstate 91 in Connecticut#Exit list]].''
===Massachusetts===
{|class=wikitable
!County
!Town
!Exit #
!Mile&lt;ref&gt;Massachusetts Executive Office of Transportation. 2007. &quot;Interchange Exit Listings (I-91).&quot; Downloaded from:http://www.eot.state.ma.us/default.asp?pgid=planning/disc/interchanges&amp;sid=dtable August 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

!Destinations
!Notes
|-
|rowspan=19|[[Hampden County, Massachusetts|Hampden]]
|[[Longmeadow, Massachusetts|Longmeadow]]
|
|0.0
!colspan=2|CT-MA state line&lt;br&gt;
|-
|rowspan=11|[[Springfield, Massachusetts|Springfield]]
|rowspan=1|1
|rowspan=1|3.58
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]] South&amp;nbsp;– [[Forest Park, Massachusetts|Forest Park]], [[Longmeadow, Massachusetts|Longmeadow]]
|Southbound exit only&lt;br&gt;US 5 joins northbound and leaves southbound
|-
|2
|3.82
|[[Image:MA Route 83.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 83|Route 83]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Forest Park, Massachusetts|Forest Park]], [[East Longmeadow, Massachusetts|East Longmeadow]]
|northbound exit only
|-
|rowspan=1|3
|rowspan=1|4.14
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]] North To [[Image:MA Route 57.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 57|Route 57]], Columbus Avenue (NB)&amp;nbsp;– [[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]] (NB), [[Agawam, Massachusetts|Agawam]] (SB)
|US 5 leaves northbound and joins southbound
|-
|4
|4.64
|[[Image:MA Route 83.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 83|Route 83]], Main Street&amp;nbsp;– [[East Longmeadow, Massachusetts|East Longmeadow]]
|southbound only
|-
|5
|5.25
|Broad Street
|northbound only&lt;br&gt;Formerly northbound Exit 4
|-
|6
|5.65
|Springfield Center (NB)&lt;br&gt;Union Street (SB)
|Old Exit 5 merged with Exit 6
|-
|7
|5.9
|Hall of Fame Avenue&amp;nbsp;– Springfield Center
|southbound only
|-
|8
|6.29
|[[Image:I-291.svg|25px]][[Image:US 20.svg|20px]] [[Interstate 291 (Massachusetts)|I-291]]/[[U.S. Route 20 in Massachusetts|US 20]] East to [[Image:I-90.svg|20px]] [[Interstate 90|I-90]] ([[Massachusetts Turnpike|Mass Pike]]) East
|-
|9
|6.68
|[[Image:US 20.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 20A.svg|25px]] [[U.S. Route 20 in Massachusetts|US 20]] West, [[Massachusetts Route 20A|Route 20A]] East&amp;nbsp;– [[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]], [[Westfield, Massachusetts|Westfield]]
|northbound only
|-
|10
|7.40
|Main Street&amp;nbsp;– [[Chicopee, Massachusetts|Chicopee]], [[North Springfield, Massachusetts|North Springfield]]
|northbound only
|-
|11
|7.51
|[[Image:US 20.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 20|US 20]] West, Birnie Avenue&amp;nbsp;– [[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]]
|southbound only
|-
|[[Chicopee, Massachusetts|Chicopee]]
|12
|8.29
|[[Image:I-391.svg|25px]] [[Interstate 391|I-391]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Chicopee, Massachusetts|Chicopee]], [[Holyoke, Massachusetts|Holyoke]] (NB)
|
|-
|align=center colspan=5|[[Connecticut River]] crossing
|-
|rowspan=2|[[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]]
|13
|9.18
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]] (Riverdale Street)&amp;nbsp;– [[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]]
|split into 13A and 13B
|-
|14
|11.55
|[[Image:I-90.svg|20px]][[Massachusetts Turnpike|Mass Pike]] ([[Interstate 90|I-90]]) &amp;nbsp;– [[Boston]], [[Albany, New York|Albany]]
|-
|rowspan=3|[[Holyoke, Massachusetts|Holyoke]]
|15
|12.40
|Lower Westfield Road&amp;nbsp;– [[Ingleside, Massachusetts|Ingleside]]
|-
|16
|14.22
|[[Image:US 202.svg|25px]] [[U.S. Route 202|US 202]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Holyoke, Massachusetts|Holyoke]], [[South Hadley, Massachusetts|South Hadley]], [[Westfield, Massachusetts|Westfield]] (SB)
|-
|17
|15.19
|[[Image:MA Route 141.svg|25px]] [[Massachusetts Route 141|Route 141]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Holyoke, Massachusetts|Holyoke]], [[Easthampton, Massachusetts|Easthampton]]
|split into 17A and 17B northbound
|-
|rowspan=5|[[Hampshire County, Massachusetts|Hampshire]]
|rowspan=4|[[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]]
|18
|22.81
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], [[Easthampton, Massachusetts|Easthampton]] (SB)
|-
|19
|24.76
|[[Image:MA Route 9.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 9|Route 9]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], [[Amherst, Massachusetts|Amherst]]
|northbound only
|-
|20
|25.91
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 9.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 10.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]], [[Massachusetts Route 9|Route 9]], [[Massachusetts Route 10|Route 10]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], [[Hadley, Massachusetts|Hadley]]
|southbound only
|-
|21
|27.27
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 10.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]]/[[Massachusetts Route 10|Route 10]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Hatfield, Massachusetts|Hatfield]], [[Whately, Massachusetts|Whately]] (NB)
|-
|[[Hatfield, Massachusetts|Hatfield]]
|22
|29.93
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 10.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]]/[[Massachusetts Route 10|Route 10]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Whately, Massachusetts|Whately]], [[North Hatfield, Massachusetts|North Hatfield]]
|northbound only
|-
|rowspan=7|[[Franklin County, Massachusetts|Franklin]]
|rowspan=2|[[Whately, Massachusetts|Whately]]
|23
|32.27
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 10.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]]/[[Massachusetts Route 10|Route 10]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Whately, Massachusetts|Whately]], [[North Hatfield, Massachusetts|North Hatfield]]
|southbound only
|-
|24
|34.71
|[[Image:US 5.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 10.svg|20px]] [[U.S. Route 5|US 5]]/[[Massachusetts Route 10|Route 10]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Deerfield, Massachusetts|Deerfield]], [[Whately, Massachusetts|Whately]] (SB)
|-
|[[Deerfield, Massachusetts|Deerfield]]
|25
|35.87
|[[Image:MA Route 116.svg|25px]] [[Massachusetts Route 116|Route 116]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Deerfield, Massachusetts|Deerfield]], [[Conway, Massachusetts|Conway]]
|southbound only
|-
|rowspan=2|[[Greenfield, Massachusetts|Greenfield]]
|rowspan=1|26
|rowspan=1|43.01
|[[Image:MA Route 2.svg|20px]][[Image:MA Route 2A.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 2|Route 2]] West, [[Massachusetts Route 2A|Route 2A]] East&amp;nbsp;– [[Greenfield, Massachusetts|Greenfield]], [[North Adams, Massachusetts|North Adams]]
|-
|rowspan=1|27
|rowspan=1|45.75
|[[Image:MA Route 2.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 2|Route 2]] East&amp;nbsp;– [[Boston]]
|-
|rowspan=2|[[Bernardston, Massachusetts|Bernardston]]
|28
|50.36
|[[Image:MA Route 10.svg|20px]] [[Massachusetts Route 10|Route 10]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Bernardston, Massachusetts|Bernardston]], [[Northfield, Massachusetts|Northfield]]
|split into 28A and 28B northbound
|-
|
|54.90&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mass.gov/mgis/eotroads.htm MassGIS EOT-OTP Roads data layer]&lt;/ref&gt;
!colspan=2|MA-VT state line
|}

===Vermont===
{|class=wikitable
!County
!Location
!Mile
![[Exit number|#]]
!Destinations
!Notes
|-
|rowspan=7|[[Windham County, Vermont|Windham]]
|[[Guilford, Vermont|Guilford]]
|0.0
|
!colspan=2|MA-VT stateline
|-
|rowspan=3|[[Brattleboro, Vermont|Brattleboro]]
|7.5
|1
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|city1=Brattleboro}}
|-
|8.7
|2
|{{Jct|state=VT|VT|9|dir1=West|city1=Brattleboro|city2=Bennington}}
|-
|11.6
|3
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|9|dir2=East|city1=Brattleboro|location2=[[Keene, New Hampshire|Keene, N.H.]]}}
|-
|[[Dummerston, Vermont|Dummerston]]
|18.2
|4
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|city1=Putney}}
|-
|[[Westminster, Vermont|Westminster]]
|28.6
|5
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|to2=To|VT|121|city1=Westminster|city2=Bellows Falls|location3=[[Walpole, New Hampshire|Walpole, N.H.]]}}
|{{Jct|state=NH|to1=To|NH|123}}
|-
|[[Rockingham, Vermont|Rockingham]]
|35.2
|6
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|103|city1=Rockingham|location2=[[Rutland (town), Vermont|Rutland]]|city3=Bellows Falls}}
|-
|rowspan=7|[[Windsor County, Vermont|Windsor]]
|[[Springfield, Vermont|Springfield]]
|41.7
|7
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|11|VT|106|city1=Springfield}}
|-
|[[Weathersfield, Vermont|Weathersfield]]
|51.4
|8
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|12|VT|131|city1=Ascutney|city2=Windsor}}
|-
|[[Hartland, Vermont|Hartland]]
|60.4
|9
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|12|city1=Windsor|city2=Hartland}}
|-
|rowspan=3|[[Hartford, Vermont|Hartford]]
|69.8
|10
|{{Jct|state=VT|I|89|location1=[[Barre (city), Vermont|Barre]]|city2=Montpelier|location3=[[Lebanon, New Hampshire|Lebanon, N.H.]]}}
|split into 10S and 10N
|-
|70.2
|11
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|city1=White River Junction}}
|-
|72.0
|12
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|city1=Wilder|city2=White River Junction}}
|-
|[[Norwich, Vermont|Norwich]]
|74.8
|13
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|10A|city1=Norwich|location2=[[Hanover, New Hampshire|Hanover, N.H.]]}}
|-
|rowspan=4|[[Orange County, Vermont|Orange]]
|[[Thetford, Vermont|Thetford]]
|84.2
|14
|{{Jct|state=VT|VT|113|to2=To|US|5|city1=Thetford}}
|-
|[[Fairlee, Vermont|Fairlee]]
|91.5
|15
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|city1=Fairlee}}
|-
|[[Bradford, Vermont|Bradford]]
|97.6
|16
|{{Jct|state=VT|VT|25|to2=To|US|5|city1=Bradford|location2=[[Barre (city), Vermont|Barre]]}}
|-
|[[Newbury (town), Vermont|Newbury]]
|110.3
|17
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|302|to2=To|US|5|city1=Wells River|location2=[[Woodsville, New Hampshire|Woodsville, N.H.]]}}
|-
|rowspan=7|[[Caledonia County, Vermont|Caledonia]]
|[[Barnet, Vermont|Barnet]]
|120.4
|18
|{{Jct|state=VT|to1=To|US|5|city1=Barnet|city2=Peacham}}
|-
|[[Waterford, Vermont|Waterford]]
|128.2
|19
|{{Jct|state=VT|I|93|dir1=South|location1=[[Littleton, New Hampshire|Littleton, N.H.]]}}
|-
|rowspan=3|[[St. Johnsbury, Vermont|St. Johnsbury]]
|128.9
|20
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|to2=To|US|2|dir2=East|city1=St. Johnsbury|city2=Barnet}}
|-
|130.6
|21
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|2|to2=To|VT|15|city1=St. Johnsbury|city2=Montpelier}}
|-
|132.6
|22
|{{Jct|state=VT|to1=To|US|5|city1=St. Johnsbury}}
|-
|rowspan=2|[[Lyndon, Vermont|Lyndon]]
|137.1
|23
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|to2=To|VT|114|city1=Lyndonville|city2=Burke}}
|-
|139.9
|24
|{{Jct|state=VT|VT|122|to2=To|VT|114|city1=Wheelock|city2=Sheffield|city3=Burke|city4=Lyndonville}}
|-
|rowspan=6|[[Orleans County, Vermont|Orleans]]
|rowspan=2|[[Barton, Vermont|Barton]]
|156.0
|25
|{{Jct|state=VT|VT|16|city1=Barton|city2=Hardwick}}
|-
|161.4
|26
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|58|city1=Orleans|city2=Irasburg}}
|-
|rowspan=4|[[Derby, Vermont|Derby]]
|170.1
|27
|{{Jct|state=VT|VT|191|to2=To|US|5|VT|105|location1=[[Newport (city), Vermont|Newport]]}}
|-
|172.4
|28
|{{Jct|state=VT|US|5|VT|105|location1=[[Newport (city), Vermont|Newport]]|city2=Derby}}
|-
|177.4
|29
|{{Jct|state=VT|to1=To|US|5|city1=Derby Line}}
|
|-
|177.43&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aot.state.vt.us/Planning/Documents/TrafResearch/Publications/2004RouteLogAADTs.pdf VTrans Traffic Log]&lt;/ref&gt;
|
!colspan=2|Continues into Quebec as [[Image:Quebec Autoroute 55.svg|20px]] ''[[Autoroute 55 (Quebec)|Autoroute 55]]''
|}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Commons-inline}}
* [http://www.bostonroads.com/roads/I-91_MA/ I-91 historical overview] from bostonroads.com

{{start srbox}}
{{ct browse|previous_type=Route|previous_route=89|route=[[list of Connecticut numbered highways|CT]]|next_type=Route|next_route=94}}
{{ma browse|previous_type=Interstate|previous_route=90|route=[[list of Massachusetts numbered highways|MA]]|next_type=Interstate|next_route=93}}
{{vt browse|previous_type=Interstate|previous_route=89|route=[[List of Routes in Vermont|VT]]|next_type=Interstate|next_route=93}}
{{s-end}}
{{interstates}}
{{3di|91}}
{{Navbox
|name       = Connecticut Interstate Highways
|title      = [[Interstate Highway System|Interstate Highways]] in [[Connecticut]]
|titleclass = 
|titlestyle = vertical-align:middle;
|liststyle  = 

|group1     = Current
|list1         = '''[[Interstate 84 in Connecticut|84]]'''{{*}} [[Interstate 384|384]] {{*}} '''[[Interstate 91|91]]''' {{*}} [[Interstate 291 (Connecticut)|291]] {{*}} [[Interstate 691|691]] {{*}} '''[[Interstate 95 in Connecticut|95]]''' {{*}} [[Interstate 395 (Connecticut-Massachusetts)|395]]
|below      = 
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:91}}
[[Category:Interstate 91]]
[[Category:Interstate Highway System]]
[[Category:Interstate Highways in Connecticut]]
[[Category:Interstate Highways in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Interstate Highways in Vermont]]
[[Category:Transportation in Hartford, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Transportation in New Haven, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Transportation in Orleans County, Vermont]]

[[de:Interstate 91]]
[[eu:Interstate 91]]
[[fa:بزرگراه میان‌ایالتی ۹۱]]
[[fr:Interstate 91]]
[[nl:Interstate 91]]
[[no:Interstate 91]]
[[ru:I-91]]
[[simple:Interstate 91]]
[[zh:91號州際公路]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
