<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="924369" ns="0" title="BTR-152"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Weapon
|name= BTR-152
|image=[[File:BTR 152 Yerevan.JPG|300px]]
|caption=BTR-152 in [[Yerevan]], [[Armenia]].
|origin={{USSR}}
|type=[[Armored personnel carrier]]
|is_vehicle=yes
|service=24 March 1950 - present
|used_by=See [[BTR-152#Operators|Operators]]
|wars=See [[BTR-152#Service history|Service History]]
|designer= B. M. Fitterman
|design_date=November 1946 - 1949&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;&gt;[http://www.softland.com.pl/aerojac/aaa/btr152/btr152.html softland]&lt;/ref&gt;
|manufacturer=Automotive Factory No. 2 Zavod imeni Stalina (until 1956)&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt; &lt;/br&gt; Automotive Factory No. 2 Zavod imeni Likhacheva (from 1956 to 1962)&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;
|production_date=1950 - 1962
|number=around 15,000
|variants=See [[BTR-152#Variants|Variants]]
|crew=2 (+18 passengers)&lt;ref name=&quot;BTR-152&quot;&gt;[http://www.israeli-weapons.com/weapons/vehicles/armored_personnel_carriers/btr-152/BTR-152.html BTR-152&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|length=6.55 m &lt;/br&gt; 6.83 m for BTR-152V
|width=2.32 m
|height=2.04 m (without the mg)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;  &lt;/br&gt; 2.36 m (with the mg)&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt; &lt;/br&gt; 2.41 m (BTR-152V with the mg)&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;
|weight=9.91 tonnes&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;&gt;[http://www.inetres.com/gp/military/cv/inf/BTR-152.html &quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|armour=welded steel&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt; &lt;/br&gt; 15 mm front&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt; &lt;/br&gt; 9 mm sides and rear&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt; &lt;/br&gt; 10 mm roof&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt; &lt;/br&gt; 4 mm bottom&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;
|primary_armament=7.62mm [[SGMB]] light machine gun (1,250 rounds) (12.7 mm [[DShK|DShK 1938/46]] heavy machine gun (500 rounds) can be used instead)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
|secondary_armament=2x7.62mm SGMB light machine guns (1,250-1,750 rounds) on side pintel mounts (optional)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
|engine=ZIS-123 6 cylinder in-line water-cooled petrol (for variants based on ZiS-151) &lt;/br&gt; ZiL-137K 6 cylinder in-line petrol (for variants based on ZiL-157)&lt;ref name=&quot;AMW - Agencja Mienia Wojskowego&quot;&gt;[http://www.amw.com.pl/rsm_product_info.php?cRsmPath=&amp;rsm_products_id=60 AMW - Agencja Mienia Wojskowego&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|engine_power=110 hp (82 kW) at 3,000 rpm. (for variants based on ZiS-151) &lt;/br&gt; 107 hp (80 kW) (for variants based on ZiL-157)&lt;ref name=&quot;AMW - Agencja Mienia Wojskowego&quot;/&gt;
|suspension=wheeled 6×6 &lt;br&gt; front - 2 leaf springs and hydraulic shock absorbers. &lt;br&gt; rear - equalising type with 2 leaf springs and torsion bars.
|clearance=300 mm
|speed=75 km/h&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 2&quot;&gt;[http://www.pancerni.abajt.pl/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=41&amp;limit=1&amp;limitstart=1 &quot;Pancerni 2&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/br&gt; 65 km/h for BTR-152V&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;
|fuel_capacity=300 l (79 gal)
|pw_ratio=11.1 hp/tonne (8.3 kW/tonne) &lt;/br&gt; 10.8 hp/tonne (8.1 kW/tonne) for BTR-152V&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;
|vehicle_range=650 km (404 miles)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
}}

The '''BTR-152''' (also known as BTR-140) was a non-amphibious [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] wheeled [[armored personnel carrier]] (BTR stands for ''Bronetransporter'' (БТР, Бронетранспортер, literally &quot;armoured transporter&quot;) [http://www.milparade.com/Soderzhaniye.pdf †]) that entered Soviet service in 1950. By the early 1970s it had been replaced in the infantry vehicle role by the [[BTR-60]]. However, it remained in service in the [[Soviet Army]] and the [[Russian Ground Forces|Russian Army]] until 1993 in a variety of other roles. It was also exported to many [[Third World]] countries where some still remain in service.

==History==
Tanks are an essential element of armed maneuver warfare. Yet, even this high-value, powerful weapon remains vulnerable to [[infantry]] [[anti-tank]] [[tactic]]s especially in urban or confined environments. Hence, infantry accompany tanks to assist in suppressing possible anti-tank action.

During the [[Second World War]], the [[Soviet]] tacticians incorporated joint infantry and tank attacks against German forces, both serving in roles to protect the other. Performance was less than desirable as infantry lacked the armored protection and rapid mobility of the tank, and thus unarmoured troops were vulnerable to enemy fire. This led to employment of armoured infantry carriage vehicles known as [[Armoured Personnel Carrier|APC]]s which overcame these shortcomings.([[#References|Perrett 1987:65]])

After the war, Soviet military analysed the high infantry casualty rate of combined infantry-tank attacks and concluded the lack of APCs were a major cause. This vulnerability in maneuver warfare was given high priority to remedy. The Soviet military industrial complex had its own designs, Lend-Lease vehicles such as the [[M3 Half-track]] and newly acquired German [[SdKfz 251]] to serve as reference. ([[#References|Perrett 1987:65]])

The BTR-152 was one of the first [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] armoured infantry vehicle after the Second World War. It was developed from November 1946 at [[Zavod Imeni Likhacheva|ZiS]] plant by a team (it included K. M. Androsow, A. P. Pietrenko, W. F. Rodionow and P. P. Czerniajew)&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt; led by B. M. Fitterman. The first two prototypes were completed in May 1947 and were followed by three experimental series. The vehicle was adopted by the [[Soviet Army]] on 24 March 1950. The vehicle was based on the existing [[ZiS-151]] truck chassis. Despite an improved engine, the addition of 5 tons of [[vehicle armour|armour]] resulted in the vehicle having insufficient mobility.

Several upgraded versions were designed by W. F. Rodionow and N. I. Orłow&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt; which later entered production. These rectified many problems such as the open roof and the mobility issue. A central tire pressure regulation system was added to allow tire pressure to be adjusted to optimize traction in varying terrain.

Production of the BTR-152 was stopped in 1962. Approximately 15,000 examples were built.

==Description==
[[File:BTR-152-latrun-4.jpg|thumb|left|BTR-152 APC in Yad la-Shiryon Museum, Israel. 2005. Spare tire mounted on the rear of the vehicle is visible.]]
The BTR-152, based on a truck chassis, has the engine located in the front, the crew behind the engine, and an open-topped troop compartment in the rear. The vehicle has all-welded steel construction with sloped armour. The windscreen is protected by twin armoured shutters with integral vision blocks. Driver and commander enter and exit the vehicle via the doors on each side of the crew compartment. The upper part of the doors can be opened without opening the entire door, allowing both crew members a side view. Additionally  both driver and commander can view the battlefield using periscopes mounted over the doors. The vehicle's armour varies from 15&amp;nbsp;mm thick on the front to 9&amp;nbsp;mm thick on the sides, to just 4&amp;nbsp;mm thick on the floor. This provides modest protection from [[small arms]] fire and small shell fragments, but does nothing against larger artillery fragments or heavy machinegun fire. The BTR-152's tires are not protected by armour and are particularly vulnerable to puncture from gunfire of all kinds. The vehicle is sometimes fitted with a winch that has a maximum capacity of 5 tonnes, and is fitted with a 70 m cable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;

The BTR-152 can tow heavy guns, transport 1.9 tonnes of cargo, or a half platoon of infantry. In the APC role, infantrymen can fire their individual weapons from the relative protection of the vehicle, and can exit through the rear doors or by jumping over the sides.&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;

The troop compartment is open-topped, although later versions were enclosed. It can be covered with a tarpaulin to protect the transported cargo or troops from rain and snow; however, it makes it unable for troops to disembark over the sides of the vehicle or mount any of the 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm [[SGMB]] light machine guns. The transported troops sit on two wooden benches. Twin doors at the rear of the hull provide access to the compartment. There are three firing ports on each side of the hull, and a further two in the rear. The driver and gunner are the only ones that have overhead protection. The BTR-152K is the only APC variant to have an armoured roof over the troop compartment and an NBC protection system. All other BTR-152 variants lack NBC protection.
[[File:BTR-152-latrun-1.jpg|thumb|left|BTR-152 in Yad la-Shiryon Museum, Israel, 2005.]]
The BTR-152 APC is armed with a single pintle-mounted 7.62mm SGMB light machinegun which was a typical armament for APCs of its time. It can also mount a 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm DShK 1938/46 heavy machinegun. The machinegun can traverse 45 degrees and elevate between -6 and +24 degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;

Because the original BTR-152 APC used components from the [[ZiS-151]], it shared that truck's maintenance problems and poor cross-country mobility. Later variants using [[ZiL-157]] components featured more power and larger, single tires which reduced the vehicle's shortcomings but did not entirely eliminate them. Serviceability and reliability remained low.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt; The lack of an amphibious capability was also a significant weakness.

Armoured shutters controlled by the driver protect the radiator from hostile fire. Closing the shutters can result in sudden overheating of the engine during combat and can force the driver to reduce speed to avoid damaging the engine. The vehicle therefore becomes a slow, unmaneuverable target on the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;

==Service history==
The vehicle entered active service with the [[Soviet Army]] on 24 March 1950 and was first publicly shown during a parade in Moscow in 1951. It was phased out as an APC between the late 1960s and early 1970s and was replaced by the BTR-60. It remained in service with the Soviet Army and later post-soviet [[Russian Ground Forces|Russian Army]] until 1993 in a variety of roles, including command vehicles, mobile radio stations and ambulances. It was also exported to many [[Third World]] countries where some still remain in service.

BTR-152 first saw combat use during [[Hungarian Revolution of 1956]]. They were later used during the [[Six Day War]] in [[1967]]. Dozens of Egyptian and Syrian BTR-152 APCs were captured by the Israeli Army. They were also used in combat during the [[Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia]] in [[1968]] by the Soviet Army and other Warsaw Pact armies. They also were used in a number of local conflicts like the ones in [[Africa]].

==Variants==
[[File:Czerniaków BTR-152W.JPG|right|thumb|BTR-152V in Muzeum Wojska Polskiego, Warszawa-Czerniaków.]]

===former Soviet Union===
[[File:Two Soviet-built BTR-152V2.JPEG|thumb|right|Two Soviet BTR-152V2''s''.]]

*'''BTR-152''' (1950) - Basic APC based on ZIL-151 truck, many of which would later be covered and converted for other uses, such as ambulances, radio stations, and engineer vehicles. The basic BTR-152 has no winch, has an open top, and has no tire pressure control lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
**'''BTR-152A''' (1951) - BTR-152 converted into a SPAAG armed with a double (ZPTU-2) or quadruple (ZPTU-4) [[KPVT]] 14.5&amp;nbsp;mm antiaircraft heavy machine guns (2400 rounds) in a turret manually operated by a single soldier. The entire crew of the vehicle consisted of 10 soldiers in variant equipped with ZPTU-2 and 5 soldiers in variant equipped with ZPTU-4. The turret is placed inside the troop compartment and can be manually operated by a single soldier. It can make a full turn and its guns can elevate between -5 and +80 degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;&gt;[http://www.pancerni.abajt.pl/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=41&amp;limit=1&amp;limitstart=0 &quot;Pancerni 1&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Legion&quot;&gt;[http://legion.wplus.net/guide/army/ta/btr152.shtml &quot;Legion&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
**'''BTR-152''' converted into a minelayer equipped with racks for anti-tank mines.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
**'''BTR-152B''' (1952) - Artillery command version with a front-mounted winch and external tires pressure regulation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
**'''BTR-152C''' - Communication variant based on BTR-152.&lt;ref name=&quot;Legion&quot;/&gt;
**'''BTR-152V''' (1955) - Variant based on [[ZIL-157]] truck with external tires pressure regulation system, a front-mounted winch and night vision devices for the driver.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;
***'''BTR-152D''' (1955) - Armament as BTR-152A, but based on BTR-152V.
***'''BTR-152I''' - BTR-152V version for artillery command vehicle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
***'''BTR-152S''' - Command and communication post vehicle for infantry commanders. It has a significantly higher full cover roof and additional radios and antennas.&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
***'''BTR-152V1''' (1957) - Received night vision equipment, winch, open top and improved external tires pressure regulation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
****'''BTR-152K''' (1959) - Received armored roof with three big hatches on top of it of which two were opening to the right over the troop compartment, internal tires pressure regulation system and filtering/ventilating system. The weight of the vehicle has increased, the crew went down from 2+18 to 2+13.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Legion&quot;/&gt;
*****'''BTR-152K''' converted into an armoured ambulance.
****'''BTR-152E''' - Armament as BTR-152A, but based on BTR-152V1.
****'''BTR-152U''' - Command vehicle based on BTR-152V1 equipped with external tires pressure regulation system. This command vehicle has a significantly higher full cover roof and additional radios and antennas. It has equipment for staff operations. This vehicle normally tows a trailer carrying additional equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
*****'''BTR-152U''' equipped with internal tires pressure regulation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
******'''BTR-152U''' with fully armoured roof and internal tires pressure regulation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
***'''BTR-152V2''' - BTR-152V version without winch. It has the internal tires pressure regulation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
****'''BTR-152D''' based on BTR-152V2.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
****'''BTR-152B1''' (1958) - Artillery command version with a front-mounted winch, internal tires pressure regulation system and ТВН-2 night vision device for the driver.&lt;ref&gt;[http://legion.wplus.net/guide/army/ta/btr152.shtml BTR-152 armored personnel carrier&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
***'''BTR-152V3''' - BTR-152V with winch on the front, open top, infrared driving lights, and internal tires pressure regulation system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;
***'''BTR-E152V''' (1957) - Experimental version; the second pair of the wheels was moved toward the center of the vehicle in order to improve the off-road performance.

===People's Republic of China===
*'''Type 56''' - Chinese copy.

[[File:BTR-152-TCM-20-hatzerim-2.jpg|right|thumb|BTR-152 TCM-20 at Muzeyon Heyl ha-Avir, Hatzerim, Israel, 2006.]]

===Egypt===
*'''BTR-152''' converted by Egyptians into a SPAAG armed with Czechoslovak KLAD (Egyptian designation is M58) quadruple [[DShK|DShK 1938/46]] 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm anti-aircraft heavy machine guns mounted in the troop compartment. It was withdrawn from service in middle of the 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pancerni 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;

===former East Germany===
[[File:BTR-152-ARV-latrun-3.jpg|right|thumb|BTR-152 converted into an ARV by Lebanese Militia next to a [[BTR-60]] APC in Yad la-Shiryon Museum, Israel, 2005.]]

*'''SPW-152''' - East German version of BTR-152.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;&gt;[http://www.jedsite.info/afv-bravo/bravo-btr/btr-152_series/btr152-series.html JED The Military Equipment Directory]&lt;/ref&gt;
**'''SPW-152''' converted into an armoured ambulance.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
**'''SPW-152U''' - East German command version of BTR-152.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;

===Israel===
*'''BTR-152''' captured from Syrians or Egyptians and modified to fulfil the Israeli Army needs.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
*'''BTR-152 TCM-20''' - Israeli air defense vehicle based on ex-Syrian or ex-Egyptian BTR-152. It is armed with twin 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon in a [[TCM-20]] powered mount.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;

===Lebanon===
*'''BTR-152''' modified by Lebanese Militias. It was fitted with ZU-23-2 anti-aircraft gun placed inside the troop compartment. It was used in fire support and anti-aircraft roles.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
*'''BTR-152''' modified by the [[South Lebanese Army]]. It was fitted with a crane inside a cut down troop compartment. One surviving example is at Yad la-Shiryon Museum in Israel.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;

===Poland===
*'''BTR-152''' converted to serve as a mobile command post. It has additional radios.&lt;ref name=&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;/&gt;
*'''BTR-152''' converted into an engineering vehicle.&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;
*'''BTR-152''' converted into an armoured artillery tractor.&lt;ref name=&quot;softland&quot;/&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:BTR-152 operators.PNG|thumb|400px|BTR-152 operators]]
*{{AFG}}
*{{ALB}}
*{{ALG}}
*{{ANG}}
*{{CAM}}
*{{CUB}}
*{{CYP}}
*{{EGY}} - 300 BTR-152''s''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armyrecognition.com/egypt/egyptian_army_egypt_land_forces_military_army_modern_equipment_vehicle_pictures_description.html Egyptian army] armyrecognition.com&lt;/ref&gt; 675 BTR-152''s'' originally bought. Also Egypt operated 120 BTR-152 converted into SPAAGs (See [[BTR-152#Variants#Egypt|Egypt section]] for details) but withdrawn them from service in the middle of the [[1980s]].
*{{GNQ}}
*{{EST}} - 5&lt;ref name=&quot;Armia&quot;&gt;Armia magazine issue 8/09&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{ETH}}
*{{GEO}}
*{{GIN}}
*{{GNB}}
*{{HUN}}
*{{IDN}}
*{{IND}}
*{{IRN}}
*{{ISR}} - Captured a number of those vehicles during the Six Day War from Egypt and Syria. It was used by Israeli Army mostly in the role of weapon carriers like BTR-152 TCM-20. A small number saw service with Israeli Police.&lt;ref name=&quot;BTR-152&quot;/&gt;
*{{LAO}}
*{{MLI}}
*{{MNG}}
*{{MOZ}}
*{{NIC}}
*{{PRK}}
*{{PRC}} (as Type 56)
*{{COG}}
*{{POL}} - Used by the army but replaced by SKOT APC. In 1982 the Milicja Obywatelska has received 6 BTR-152V1 APCs with special equipment from East Germany's Volkspolizei.&lt;ref name=&quot;softland Transportery opancerzone Milicji Obywatelskiej&quot;&gt;[http://www.softland.com.pl/aerojac/aaa/stan_wojenny/sprzet_mo.html Transportery opancerzone Milicji Obywatelskiej]&lt;/ref&gt; One of the vehicles is still kept in storage by the police forces.
*{{flag|Somaliland}}
*{{SEY}}
*{{SRI}}
*{{SUD}}
*{{SYR}}
*{{TAN}}
*{{UGA}}
*{{VIE}}
*{{YEM}} - 250
*{{ZIM}}

===Former Operators===
*[[al-Murabitun]] - ex-[[PLO]] vehicles on service in the 1980s
*{{BUL}} - Withdrawn from service in the 1990s
*{{DDR}} - Passed on to the unified German state.
*{{IRQ}} - All destroyed or scrapped.
*{{flagicon|North Vietnam}} [[North Vietnam]] - Passed on to the successor state.
*{{ROM}} - Withdrawn from service in the 1990s.
*{{RUS}} - Withdrawn from service in the 1990s
*[[Lebanese Forces]] - Supplied by [[Syria]] and [[Israel]] or captured from the [[PLO]].
* [[South Lebanon Army]] - Supplied by [[Israel]].
*[[Tigers Militia (Lebanon)]] - Supplied by [[Syria]] in the late 1970s
*{{USSR}} - Passed on to successor states.
*{{GER}} - Taken from GDR's army, all scrapped or sold to other countries.
*{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Palestinian Liberation Organization]] - Supplied by [[Syria]]. Passed on to the Lebanese [[al-Murabitun]] militia.
*{{YUG}} - 40, withdrawn in 1970s.

==Notes==
&lt;br&gt;
{{reflist}}

==References==
* ''Soviet/Russian Armor and Artillery Design Practices 1945 to Present'', Andrew Hull, David Markov Steven Zaloga, ISBN 1-892848-01-5
* ''Jane's Armour and Artillery 2005-2006''
* Perrett, Bryan (1987). ''Soviet Armour Since 1945.'' London: Blandford Press. ISBN 0-7137-1735-1.

==External links==
{{commons|BTR-152}}
* [http://btr152.com BTR-152 foto and forum]
* [http://www.fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/land/row/btr-152.htm FAS.org]
* [http://www.fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/land/row/btr-152.htm FAS.org]
* [http://www.armyrecognition.com/Russe/vehicules_a_roues/BTR-152/BTR-152_Russe_description.htm Photo gallery at armyrecognition.com]
* [http://www.slujba.ru/index.php?redir=572 Description and photo gallery at Slujba.ru] (Russian language)
* [http://armoured.vif2.ru/btr152.htm Description and photo gallery at armoured.vif2.ru] (Russian language)

{{Modern IFV and APC}}
{{PostWWIISovietAFVS|APC}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Btr-152}}
[[Category:Command vehicles]]
[[Category:Armoured personnel carriers of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Armoured personnel carriers of the Cold War]]
[[Category:Cold War Soviet armoured fighting vehicles]]

[[ar:بي تي أر-152]]
[[az:BTR-152]]
[[cs:BTR-152]]
[[de:BTR-152]]
[[es:BTR-152]]
[[fr:BTR-152]]
[[it:BTR-152]]
[[he:BTR-152]]
[[ka:БТР-152]]
[[ja:BTR-152]]
[[no:BTR-152]]
[[pl:BTR-152]]
[[ro:BTR-152]]
[[ru:БТР-152]]
[[fi:BTR-152]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
