<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="929736" ns="0" title="Southern Utah University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=September 2009}}
{{Infobox university|
  width          = 100px |
  name           = Southern Utah University |
  image          = [[Image:SUU Academic Logo.png|200px]] |
  motto          = Learning Lives Forever |
  established    = 1897 |
  type           = [[Public university|Public]] |
  president      = Dr. [[Michael T. Benson]] |
  city           = [[Cedar City]] |
  state          = [[Utah]] |
  country        = [[United States|USA]] |
  undergrad      = 7,236 (spring 2011) |
  postgrad       = 788 (spring 2011) |
  postgrad_label = graduate |
  faculty        = 223 |
  campus         = 129 acres (0.52&amp;nbsp;km²) |
  colors         = [[Red]] &amp; [[White]] ([[Black]] Accent){{color box|#FF0000}}{{color box|#FFFFFF}}{{color box|#000000}} |
  free_label     = Mascot |
  free           = [[Thunderbird (mythology)|Thunderbirds]] |
  website        = [http://www.suu.edu/ www.suu.edu]
}}

'''Southern Utah University''', or SUU, is located in [[Cedar City, Utah]]. It was founded in 1897 as an extension of the [[Agricultural College of Utah]], by the citizens of Cedar City.

During its history, the school has been known as:
* Branch Normal School (1897&amp;ndash;1913)
* Branch Agricultural College (1913&amp;ndash;1953)
* College of Southern Utah (1953&amp;ndash;1969)
* Southern Utah State College (1969&amp;ndash;1990)
* Southern Utah University (1991&amp;ndash;present)

Southern Utah University hosts the Tony Award-winning [[Utah Shakespearean Festival]] as well as the [[Utah Summer Games]] which is held in the [[Eccles Coliseum]].

==Academics==
The university's enrollment is 8,024 students as of Spring semester 2011&lt;ref&gt;http://www.suu.edu/general/ir/fact10/enrollment-headcountbyclass.pdf &lt;/ref&gt; , with approximately 223 faculty members teaching in four colleges and three schools:

*College of Education &amp; Human Development
*College of Humanities &amp; Social Sciences
*College of Performing &amp; Visual Arts
*College of Science &amp; Engineering
**School of Computing &amp; Technology (part of the College of Science &amp; Engineering)
*School of Business
*School of Continuing &amp; Professional Studies

==Recognition==
*Consumer's Digest: Top Ten Best Value in America (2004, 2007 and 2009) &lt;ref&gt;[http://suu.edu/ad/pr/toptenvalue.html SUU - Marketing &amp; PR: An Official Top Ten Best Value in America&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suu.edu/ad/pr/news/archives/viewarticle.aspx?id=431 SUU - News: 6/22/2007 - SUU Again Ranked in Consumers Digest Top Ten&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*National Research Center for College &amp; University Admissions: Ninth best admissions website in nation &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suu.edu/ad/pr/news/archives/viewarticle.aspx?id=349 SUU - News: 10/16/2006 - SUU Has Top-Ten Website in Nation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Princeton Review: America’s Best Value Colleges (2007, 2008, 2009) &lt;ref&gt;[http://suu.edu/ad/pr/07princeton.html SUU - Marketing &amp; PR: Princeton Review 2007&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*U.S. News and World Report: America’s Best Colleges &lt;ref&gt;[http://suu.edu/ad/pr/07usnews.html SUU - Marketing &amp; PR: U.S. News and World Report Ranking 2007&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Princeton Review: Best in the West (2004, 2005, 2008, 2009, 2011) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suu.edu/ad/pr/news/archives/viewarticle.aspx?id=248 SUU - News: 11/3/2005 - The Princeton Review Names SUU One of the Best, Again!&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suu.edu/ad/pr/news/archives/viewarticle.aspx?id=539 SUU - News: 7/30/2008 - SUU Ranked as “Best in the West” by The Princeton Review]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Students==
Southern Utah University currently draws students from 45 states, 25 foreign countries, and all of Utah's 29 counties. Of the total enrollment, 58 percent are women and 42 percent are men, a 1.4 to 1 ratio. 11% are of other than caucasian background. About 70 percent of all students live on campus or near the campus. The student-faculty ratio is 22 to 1. The university awards Associate Degrees, Bachelor's Degrees, and Master's Degrees.

==Student Involvement &amp; Activities==
Students have many opportunities to get involved in a number of activities and organizations while attending Southern Utah University. Ranging from the typical collegiate involvement of Student Government and Clubs &amp; Organizations to the uniquiness of the Entertainment Bureau, Leavitt Center, and Outdoor Rec Center.

===Southern Utah University Student Association===
The Southern Utah University [[Student Association]](SUUSA) is governed by the four Executive Council members (Student Body President, Academic Vice President, Clubs &amp; Student Leadership Vice President, and Activities Vice President) which each have their own branch under them. These positions are voted into office each March, along with one representative per college to the Student Senate, by the general student body. Event Directors, members of the President's Cabinet, and Club Directors are appointed by the Executive Council through an application and interview process. They are then investigated and ratified by the Academic Senate. All SUUSA student leaders' term of office lasts for one year.

===Michael O. Leavitt Center for Politics and Public Service===
The Michael O. Leavitt Center for Politics and Public Service (typically referred to as simply the 'Leavitt Center')the name sake of the center is after famous alum [[Michael O. Leavitt]] (Former Utah Governor and [[George W. Bush Cabinet]] member). Student leaders in the Leavitt Center engage the student body through voter registration drives, public policy awareness, and public service. The mission of the center is to provide a foundation for student to prepare themselves in a life of public service, regardless of profession and career. Students can receive funding from the Leavitt Center to spend a semester participating in a Washington, DC internship. Internships include positions in the offices of either of Utah senators, [[Orrin Hatch]] and [[Bob Bennett (politician)|Bob Bennett]], in Nevada Senator [[Harry Reid]]'s office (Reid graduated from SUU in 1959), with the [[Smithsonian Institution]], and with local sports teams.

===SUU Presidential Ambassadors===
The Presidential Ambassadors at SUU are the students many see on the front lines of recruiting High School seniors, transfer students, and others. Ambassadors give tours of the campus to prospective students, host overnight weekends for prospective students, and provide service to the campus community. The typical Ambassador generally is in their Freshmen and Sophomore years, have served in leadership capacities while in High School, and love to talk. Ambassadors can be found in many organizations around campus as they typically get involved.

===Service &amp; Learning Center===
Many students that get involved in the Service &amp; Learning Center do so with in the many student-run organizations operated under the philosophy of the [[service learning]] concept. Between 50-100 students per academic year spend their Spring and/or Winter Breaks in Mexico or other locations in the U.S. (recently Colorado, Washington state, and New Orleans) providing service to orphanages, schools, and even [[Habitat for Humanity]]. Other programs include [[Sub for Santa]], [[Make A Difference Day]], After School Program, and Adopt a Grandparent program. On location in the center is the HOPE Pantry where students can unanimously donate or receive food as needed, the pantry is typically filled through the center's popular Bread and Soup Nite held in the Sharwan Smith Center's Ballroom on the first Monday of each month. Students can also participate in the Service-Learning Scholar and AmeriCorps programs through the center. In the fall semester of 2011 the Service and Learning Center officially changed its name to the Community Engagement Center.

===POWER 91===
[http://www.power91radio.com/ POWER 91] is a student operated radio station in [[Cedar City, Utah]] with the call letters KSUU 91.1. Many of the student [[DJs]] change from semester to semester, with some being employed by the station. One of the most popular student ran shows is [http://www.power91radio.com/weblogs/morning-brew/ The Morning Brew], which airs Monday through Friday from 8-10am. POWER 91 is also home to SUU Athletics. [[American football|Football]] and [[Basketball]] home and road games and [[Women's Basketball]] and [[Gymnastic]] meets are aired on the station.

===SUTV===
SUTV is a cable TV channel operated by Southern Utah University's Department of Communication. It is operated on an [[Distance learning|Educational-access television]] channel of the Bresnan Communications [[Cable TV]] system in Cedar City, Utah. It is affiliated with the [[Classic Arts Showcase]]. Most of the local programs are produced by students enrolled in Communication classes at SUU. Currently airing are programs such as SUTV News, a weekly broadcast of newsworthy local and campus events, and The T-Bird Zone, a showcase of Thunderbird athletics featuring interviews with coaches and players, as well as highlights of games and sports news.

===Greek Life===
There are five recognized Greek service organizations on campus. Three fraternities, [[Chi Phi]], [[Sigma Nu]] and [[Sigma Chi]] as well as two sororities, [[Alpha Phi]] and local Delta Psi Omega.

===Other Notable Student Organizations===
*The University Journal
*SUTV
*The POWER 91 Club
*T-Bird Rugby Club
*Alpha Sigma Pi, The National Society of Leadership &amp; Success
*[[Lambda Pi Eta]]
*The Hip Hop Club
*Miss Southern Utah University Organization (Suspended Indefinitely)
*Multicultural Center
*Black Student Alliance (BSA)
*Queer Straight Alliance (QSA)
*Native American Student Association
*Polynesian Club
*The Buttercream Gang
*Students for eGrace International
*FEMS (Feminist Education and Motivation Society)
*T-Bird Team Karate/ RUFF club
*Philosophy Club
*International Club of Pancakes (ICOP)
*Rodeo Team and Club
*Volley Ten Sock Pong ball Club

==Notable Student Traditions==
===The Howl===
The largest event held by the Student Activities Board. The event usually occurs on a Friday within a week of Halloween. Entertainment varies from year to year, but has generally included Bands, Hypnotists, Mentalists, Comics, etc. Additionally a Halloween costume contest is held with prizes. The main focus of the night is the dance held in the Student Rotunda.

===True T-Bird===
To become a true T-Bird students must kiss their true love near the Old Sorrel statue (located north of the Centrum) at midnight on the night of a Full Moon. The event is also held the night before the Homecoming Football game and is hosted by the SUU Student Alumni Association and POWER 91.

===Miss SUU Pageant===
The Miss SUU Pageant is a pageant that has been held every February since the early 1950s. The winner of the pageant is crowned as the Homecoming Queen and representative of SUU at the [[Miss Utah|Miss Utah pageant]]. The top three win gift baskets and scholarship money. Past winner [[Jill Stevens]] went on to win the [[Miss Davis County]] and [[Miss Utah]] pageants to represent the state at the [[Miss America pageant]]. The organization has been currently suspended by school administrators because of a lack of funding from budget cuts. The Student Activities Board is planning on resuming the pageant in the 2010-11 school year.

==Campus==
[[Image:Southern Utah University 1.jpg|left|thumb|250px|Braithwaite Liberal Arts Center and Old Main]]
The university's first building, built in 1898, remains part of campus, and is affectionately known as ''Old Main''. The university also boasts the legend of ''[http://www.suu.edu/campmap/statues/founders.html Old' Sorrel]'', a [[horse]] who is said to have assisted the citizens in building the school in record-high snow. A statue of the horse is located in front of the Centrum special events center, on the west side of campus. Consistent with its heritage of educating educators, one in three graduates have an education degree.

==Athletics==
{{see also |Southern Utah Thunderbirds football}}
The university's sports teams are known as the Thunderbirds. The colors are red, white and black. Teams compete in The NCAA Football Championship Subdivision (FCS, formerly known as division I-AA) in football ([[Great West Football Conference]]) and in [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] in other sports ([[The Summit League]] and [[Western Athletic Conference]]) SUU also competes in The National Intercollegiate Rodeo Association, in the Rocky Mountain Region. The school will become a full member of the [[Big Sky Conference]] in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bigskyconf.com/news/2010/11/1/GEN_1101105326.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

The Thunderbirds compete in the following sports:
*[[American football|Football]]
*[[Gymnastics]]
*[[Baseball]]
*[[Basketball]]
*[[Cross country running|Cross Country]]
*[[Golf]]
*[[Soccer]]
*[[Softball]]
*[[Tennis]]
*[[Track and Field]]
*[[Volleyball]]
*[[Rodeo]]

==Southern Utah University Alumni Association==
===SUU Alumni Chapters &amp; Networks===
===Chapters===
Iron County, UT, Northeast, Northwest, Salt Lake City, UT, Southern Arizona, Southern California, Southern Nevada, Utah County, UT, Washington County, Washington, D.C.&lt;ref&gt;[http://suu.edu/alumni/networkreps.html SUU Alumni Representatives&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Networks===
Boston, MA, Central Utah, Chicago, IL, Davis County, UT, Florida, Fresno, CA, Juab County, UT, Lincoln County, NV, Logan, UT, Michigan, North Carolina, Nebraska/Iowa, San Francisco, CA, Texas, Weber County, UT.&lt;ref&gt;[http://suu.edu/alumni/networkreps.html SUU Alumni Representatives&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Notable Alumni===
*[[Michael O. Leavitt]], the 14th [[Governor of Utah]] and former [[United States Secretary of Health and Human Services|Secretary of Health and Human Services]] in the [[George W. Bush administration|George W. Bush presidential administration]].
*[[Harry Reid]], [[Senate Majority Leader]], [[110th Congress]]
*[[Jill Stevens]], Miss SUU 2006, Miss [[Davis County, Utah|Davis County]] 2007, [[Miss Utah]] 2007, [[Miss America 2008]] &quot;People's Choice&quot; semifinalist.
*[[Nick Miller (American football)|Nick Miller]], NFL wide receiver for the [[Oakland Raiders]], SUU wide receiver from 2007-2008. 2008 Great West Special Teams Player of the Year.
*[[DeWayne Lewis]], NFL Cornerback, Lewis was a 2 Time Conference Athlete of the Year.
*[[Lonnie Mayne]], Professional wrestler in the 60's and 70's.  NWA United States Heavyweight Champion.
*[[Ricardo Dominguez (professor)|Ricardo Dominguez]], professor and cyber activist
* [[Parley Parker Christensen]], Utah and California politician, Esperantist
* Neil Hjorth

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.suu.edu Official website]
*[http://www.suutbirds.com Official SUU athletics website]
*[http://www.leavittcollection.org Official website for the Michael O. Leavitt Online Archive]

===Academic Programs===
*[http://www.suu.edu/ed/ College of Education]
*[http://www.suu.edu/hss/ College of Humanities &amp; Social Sciences]
*[http://www.suu.edu/pva/ College of Performing &amp; Visual Arts]
*[http://www.suu.edu/cose/ College of Science &amp; Engineering and School of Computing &amp; Technology]
*[http://www.suu.edu/business/ School of Business]
*[http://www.suu.edu/scps/ School of Continuing &amp; Professional Studies]

===Student Activities &amp; Involvement===
*[http://www.suu.edu/suusa SUUSA] Southern Utah University Student Association Government
*[http://www.suu.edu/leavittcenter/ Leavitt Center] Michael O. Leavitt Center for Politics and Public Service
*[http://www.suu.edu/ss/admission/pa/ Presidential Ambassadors] SUU Presidential Ambassadors
*[http://www.suu.edu/ss/service/ Service &amp; Learning Center] SUU Service and Learning Center
*[http://www.suu.edu/suusa/clubs/ Clubs &amp; Organizations] SUU Clubs and Organizations
*[http://www.suu.edu/ss/outdoors/ SUU Outdoors] SUU Outdoor Recreation Center

===Student Resources===
*[http://www.suunews.com suunews.com] Online Student News Journal
*[http://www.suu.edu/suusa SUUSA] SUU Student Association
*[http://www.bard.org Utah Shakespearean Festival official website]
*[http://www.utahsummergames.com Utah Summer Games official website]
{{Clear}}

===Athletic Conferences===
{{The Summit League}}
{{Great West Conference}}
{{Big Sky Conference}}
{{Utahcolleges}}
{{Utahsports}}

{{Coord|37.675448|N|113.071632|W|source:dewiki_region:US-UT_type:landmark|format=dms|display=title}}

[[Category:Southern Utah University| ]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Iron County, Utah]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Iron County, Utah]]
[[Category:Education in Iron County, Utah]]

[[de:Southern Utah University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه جنوبی یوتا]]
[[no:Southern Utah University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
