<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9304667" ns="0" title="Walter Breuning"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{infobox person
|name        = Walter Breuning
|image       = Walter Breuning April 8, 2010.jpg
|image_size  = 250px	
|caption     = Breuning in April 2010 at age 113
|birth_date  = {{birth date|1896|9|21}}
|birth_place = {{nowrap|[[Melrose, Minnesota]], U.S.}}
|death_date  = {{death date|2011|4|14}}&lt;br/&gt;(aged {{age in years and days|1896|9|21|2011|4|14}})
|death_place = {{nowrap|[[Great Falls, Montana]], U.S.}}
|nationality = [[American nationality law|American]] 
|religion    = [[Methodist]]
|ethnicity   =
|spouse      = Agnes C. Breuning (née Twokey)&lt;br&gt;(m. 1922&amp;ndash;57, her death)&lt;br/&gt;Margaret Breuning (née Vanest) &lt;br&gt;(b. 02/1904&amp;ndash; d. 01/1975, aged 70)&lt;br&gt; (m. 1958&amp;ndash;01/1975, her death)
|occupation  = Retired [[Rail transport|railroader]]
|parents     = John Breuning&lt;br&gt;(1864-1915)&lt;br&gt;Cora Mae (née Morehouse)&lt;br&gt;(1870-1917)
|title       = World's oldest living man from July 18, 2009, to April 14, 2011 and the third oldest recognized living person from January 31, 2011, to April 14, 2011.
|education   =
|alma mater  =
}}
'''Walter Breuning''' {{nowrap|(September 21,}} 1896{{ndash}} {{nowrap|April 14,}} 2011) was an [[United States|American]] [[supercentenarian]]. He was the last known surviving man who was born in 1896. Breuning is the oldest undisputed American-born man on record. He was the last verified American man born in the 19th Century. At the time of his death, Breuning was the third oldest undisputed man ever, and one of the [[List of the oldest people|50 undisputed oldest people ever]]. He remains one of only six verified and undisputed men to have reached age 114.

==Biography==
[[Image:wb 7thgrade.jpg|thumb|left|Walter Breuning in seventh grade, second from left, top row with blue &quot;x&quot;, October 1907]]
Walter Breuning was born in [[Melrose, Minnesota]]. He was the son of John Breuning and Cora Morehouse Breuning, and had two brothers and two sisters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite census | title = Twelfth Census of the United States | year = 1900 | location = Melrose, Stearns, Minnesota | roll = T623 792 | page = 16A | line = 33 | accessdate = July 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1901 when he was 5, his family moved to [[De Smet, South Dakota]], where he went to school for nine years until his family broke up in 1910. Breuning referred to this time as &quot;the dark ages&quot;, as his family lived without electricity, water, or plumbing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yahoo.com |title=World's oldest man marks 114th birthday in US |publisher=Yahoo.com |date=1970-01-01 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apart from his parents who died at 50 and 46, longevity runs in Breuning's family. His paternal and maternal grandparents lived into their 90s and his siblings lived to ages 78, 85, 91 and 100. His only surviving family are 1 niece and 3 nephews all now in their 80s, plus great nieces and nephews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/article/20110425/NEWS01/110425016 |title=Breuning's brood fondly recalls world's oldest man &amp;#124; Great Falls Tribune |publisher=greatfallstribune.com |date=2011-04-25 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1910 aged 14, Breuning dropped out of school and began scraping bakery pans for $2.50 weekly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Great Falls Tribune&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/breuning2/main.html |title=Great Falls Tribune tribute site |publisher=Greatfallstribune.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; He joined the [[Great Northern Railway (U.S.)|Great Northern Railway]] in 1913, working for it for more than fifty years. During his early years, Breuning commented that he would have to hide from owner [[James J. Hill]], as Hill did not want any railroad employees under the age of 18 (Breuning was first hired at age 17).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bnsf.com/employees/communications/bnsf_today/2009/01/2009-01-08-b.html |title=Railroad Retiree is Nation's Oldest Living Man, BNSF News, January 8, 2009 |publisher=Bnsf.com |date=2009-01-08 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breuning worked for the Great Northern Railway until age 66, and was also a manager/secretary for the local [[Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine|Shriner's]] club until age 99.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/breuning2/page17.html ]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During [[World War I]], he signed up for military service, but was never called up. When [[World War II]] broke out, he was too old to serve. He moved to Montana in 1918, where he continued working as a clerk for the Great Northern Railway. There, he met Agnes Twokey, a telegraph operator from [[Butte, Montana|Butte]]. He was married to her from 1922 until her death in 1957. They had no children and Breuning was believed to have never married again, as he stated that &quot;Second marriages never work; even first marriages don't work today.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-9UPU2ThSDs&amp;feature=related|title=Oldest Man's 113th Birthday|publisher=CBS|date=September 21, 2009|accessdate=April 13, 2010|last=Hartman|first=Steve}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, after his death, a marriage certificate was located, revealing that he married Margaret Vanest on October 5, 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;greatfallstribune.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/article/20110424/NEWS01/104240301 |title=Breuning's untold chapters: Oldest man had second wife |publisher=Greatfallstribune.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Margaret died on January 15, 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;greatfallstribune.com&quot;/&gt;

Breuning was a [[Freemason]], and a member of Great Falls Lodge No. 118, Great Falls, Montana, for over 85 years. He held the 33rd Degree of the Scottish Rite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.freemason.org/newsEvents/article.htm;jsessionid=E33DC5A2E976FAE64887599773D65283.node2?id=10076 | title = World’s Oldest Man is a Brother | publisher = Masons of California | accessdate = 2011-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.yaarabshrine.net/node/375 | title = Oldest Man In North America is also Oldest Shriner | publisher = YAARAB Shrine of Atlanta  | location = Atlanta, Georgia | accessdate = 2011-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In later years==
Breuning lived at the Rainbow Retirement and Assisted Living Center in [[Great Falls, Montana]] for 32 years, moving in when it was 'The Rainbow Hotel' in 1979 when he was 83. The Rainbow Hotel turned into Rainbow Assisted Living Center in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;boston.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/odd/articles/2008/09/24/man_112_says_secret_to_long_life_is_being_active Man, 112, says secret to long life is being active]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=breuning&gt;{{cite web|title=125 Montana Newsmakers: Walter Breuning|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/125newsmakers5/breuning.html|work=Great Falls Tribune|author=Tribune Staff|accessdate=August 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Each year starting with his 100th, The Rainbow held a Birthday Party for Breuning. As he became older and especially after gaining the title of Oldest Living Man in July 2009 the world media flocked to these occasions, if only to hear Breuning's annual birthday speech.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/breuning2/page3.html |title=videos |publisher=Greatfallstribune.com |date=2006-11-30 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Breuning was a lifelong cigar smoker, but says in an interview at age 110 that he quit in 1999 when he was 103, saying they had become too expensive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=rloznak |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l_DHLvmKt7A&amp;feature=related |title=Walter Breuning at 110-years-old |publisher=YouTube |date=2009-09-28 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, at the age of 108 he briefly started smoking again, encouraged by gifts of cigars from as far away as London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.redorbit.com/news/general/89117/108yearold_man_starts_smoking_again/index.html |title=108-Year-Old Man Starts Smoking Again - General News |publisher=redOrbit |date=2004-09-27 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Breuning retained a sharp memory. For example, he could remember his grandfather talking about his experiences in the [[American Civil War]] when he was three years old, and remembered the day President [[William McKinley]] was shot as the day &quot;I got my first haircut&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CBS |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-9UPU2ThSDs |title=CBS-interview |publisher=Youtube.com |date=2009-09-21 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On his 112th birthday, Breuning said the secret to long life is being active: &quot;If you keep your mind busy and keep your body busy, you're going to be around a long time.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;boston.com&quot; /&gt; 

Breuning dressed in a suit and tie every day. On April 24, 2009, at the age of 112, Breuning was interviewed on CBS by Steve Hartman for ''Assignment America''. When asked by Hartman if he would do a second CBS interview in four years, Breuning said, &quot;Well hell you sure can!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ksl.com/?nid=148&amp;sid=12334015&amp;autostart=y |title=Utah psychiatrist researching what makes supercentenarians tick |publisher=ksl.com |date=2010-09-07 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public events==

On his 110th birthday, in September 2006, Breuning was declared the oldest living retired railroader in the United States. The Governor of [[Montana]], [[Brian Schweitzer]], and the city mayor attended his celebration.

On February 16, 2009, Breuning made an appearance on the ''[[News Hour with Jim Lehrer]]'', giving his views about the current state of the economy and the newly elected president. Breuning said that the first president he ever voted for was [[Woodrow Wilson]], and that the most memorable news item he ever heard about in his life was the [[stock market crash of 1929]]. He also described life during the [[Great Depression]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/perl/media.cgir?t=w&amp;f=virage/newshour/pbsnh021609_350k.asf&amp;s=3116867&amp;e=3388138&amp;extn=.asx |title=The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer, 16 February 2009 |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 24, 2009, Breuning was the focus of a segment done by Steve Hartman's &quot;Assignment America&quot; on the [[CBS Evening News]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2009/04/24/assignment_america/main4967452.shtml |title=America's Oldest Man Keeps Rolling |publisher=Cbsnews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on September 21, 2009, he was the focus of another such segment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2009/09/21/assignment_america/main5328148.shtml?tag=cbsnewsLeadStoriesAreaMain;cbsnewsLeadStoriesPrimary |title=Revisiting the Most Senior of Sr. Citizens |publisher=Cbsnews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his 113th birthday celebrations, Breuning said: &quot;Remember that life's length is not measured by its hours and days, but by that which we have done therein. A useless life is short if it lasts a century. There are greater and better things in us all, if we would find them out. There will always be in this world - wrongs. No wrong is really successful. The day will come when light and truth and the just and the good shall be victorious and wrong as evil will be no more forever.&quot;

The [[BNSF Railway]] named the west end of its new Broadview Subdivision, where it meets the ex-Great Northern Laurel Subdivision near [[Broadview, Montana]], Walter Junction after Breuning. He was present at the dedication of the new line, which serves the Signal Peak Mine, on September 2, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;Andy Cummings, ''[[Trains (magazine)]]'', For BNSF a new coal shipper, December 2009, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 25, 2010, Breuning was honored by Montana Ambassadors for shining a spotlight on the state of [[Montana]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greatfallstribune.com/article/20100225/NEWS01/2250311=.asx ]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Health history and habits ==
In 1960, age 64, Breuning was diagnosed with [[colon cancer]]. It was successfully treated and did not return. Breuning did not have any other health issues until he broke his hip at the age of 108. He spent eight days in the hospital and was totally healed in 21 days.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yaarabshrine.net/node/375 |title=Oldest Man In North America is also Oldest Shriner |publisher=YAARAB Shrine |date=2009-01-15 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2007 at the age of 111, Breuning was fitted with hearing aids. The week before his 113th birthday in September 2009, Breuning fell and bruised his scalp, but was otherwise unhurt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.life.com/image/91007672 |title=Walter Breuning - World's Oldest Man Celebrates His 113th Birthday - Photo |publisher=LIFE |date=2009-09-21 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breuning was in excellent health, walking unaided and refusing to use the elevator to reach his second floor apartment until he broke his hip.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/communities/census2000/20010708/755168.html |title=Montana's centenarians hard to find - Census 2000 - Communities |publisher=GreatFallsTribune.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breuning began to slow down physically in his last year, requiring first a walker and then a motor scooter to get around although his mental state was undiminished to the end. 

Breuning attributed much of his longevity to his diet. Shortly after his wife died, Breuning started eating out at restaurants. Eventually, he stopped eating out, but continued eating two meals a day. He ate a big breakfast and a hearty lunch but skipped an evening meal, snacking on fruit instead. Breuning drank lots of water through the day plus a cup and a half of coffee with breakfast and one cup with lunch. He got up every day at 6:15 a.m. and had breakfast at 7:30 a.m. He then took a stroll around The Rainbow for exercise and could then be found sitting in the lobby chatting with fellow residents and his many visitors. Breuning would retire to his room in mid-afternoon to listen to radio and when his vision allowed him, read the newspaper and his many letters received from people from all over the world.  
  
Overall, Breuning was in good health almost all of his life. His weight was around the same for the last 50 years of his life, {{convert|125|-|130|lb|kg}}. Because Breuning was {{convert|5|ft|8|in|m}}, his [[body mass index]] was around 19.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mensjournal.com/survival-skills-worlds-oldest-man |title=Survival Skills: World’s Oldest Man &amp;#124; Men’s Journal |publisher=Mensjournal.com |date=2011-04-14 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=George |first=Sydne |url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2009-09-24-oldest-man-diet_N.htm |title=Two-meal diet aids in oldest man's longevity |publisher=Usatoday.Com |date=2009-09-24 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; For years Breuning took a baby [[aspirin]] everyday, but he eventually gave that up stating that he didn't need it, from there on he took no medication.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prx.org/pieces/54443/transcripts/131167 |title=Transcripts » Show |publisher=PRX |date= |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breuning believed another key to his longevity was keeping his mind and body active, not retiring until the age of 99. He performed daily [[calisthenics]] almost to the end. He could not read well because his eyesight was badly impaired by cataracts, but he kept himself occupied mentally by listening to the radio.

On March 31, 2011, Breuning was hospitalized for an unspecified illness, thought to be pneumonia. The Governor of Montana, [[Brian Schweitzer]], visited the state's oldest resident in the hospital on April 6 and 8, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/article/20110409/NEWS01/104090310 |title=Governor praises his hospitalized friend, Walter Breuning &amp;#124; Great Falls Tribune |publisher=greatfallstribune.com |date=2011-04-08 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greatfallstribune.com/article/20110415/NEWS01/104150333&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
In an interview with the Associated Press in autumn 2010, Breuning stated that he had no fear or rejection of change – especially death. &quot;We're all going to die. Some people are scared of dying. Never be afraid to die. Because you're born to die,&quot; he said.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenfieldreporter.com/view/story/b7fbd86a47864232bdfd35e8ef9b2299/US--Obit-Worlds-Oldest-Man/ Walter Breuning, world's oldest man, dies in Montana at age 114]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Breuning died peacefully in his sleep of natural causes in a Great Falls hospital at 3:30 p.m. local time on April 14, 2011.&lt;ref name=breuning2&gt;{{cite web|title=Rest in Peace, Walter Breuning, World's Oldest Living Man|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/breuning2/main.html|work=Great Falls Tribune|author=Tribune Staff||date=April 15, 2011|accessdate=August 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had been hospitalized since the beginning of the month with an undisclosed illness. At the time of his death, he was the 3rd oldest living person in the world, and the oldest male.

Before he died, Breuning shared a prayer with his pastor. He said &quot;Talked to him this morning. Reminded him of our agreement.&quot; His pastor asked what the agreement was. He said, &quot;If I'm not going to get better, I'm supposed to go now.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greatfallstribune.com/article/20110415/NEWS01/104150324/0/breuning/World-s-oldest-man-brightened-others-lives-end?odyssey=mod_sectionstories |title=World's oldest man brightened others' lives to the end &amp;#124; Great Falls Tribune |publisher=greatfallstribune.com |date=2011-04-15 |accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Longevity records==
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2011}}
*On September 23, 2006, Breuning, aged 110 years, 2 days, was added to the [[Gerontology Research Group]] list for Guinness World Records.
*On December 27, 2008, [[George Francis (supercentenarian)|George Francis]] died; Breuning, aged 112 years, 97 days, became the oldest living verified man in the United States.
*On July 18, 2009, [[Henry Allingham]] died; Breuning, aged 112 years, 300 days, became the oldest living verified man in the world.
*On November 19, 2009, Chiyo Shiraishi died and Breuning entered the list of the 10 oldest living people in the world.
*On June 23, 2010, Breuning, aged 113 years, 275 days, became one of the 10 verified [[oldest men ever]].
*On September 11, 2010, Breuning, aged 113 years, 355 days, surpassed [[Fred Hale]] to become the oldest undisputed American-born male ever.
*On September 21, 2010, Breuning became the 5th undisputed recorded man in history to reach the age of 114.
*On September 30, 2010, Breuning, aged 114 years, 9 days, became the oldest person ever to be born in the state of [[Minnesota]].
*On January 31, 2011, [[Eunice Sanborn]] died; Breuning, aged 114 years, 132 days, became the 2nd [[oldest living person]] in the world.
*On March 23, 2011, Breuning, aged 114 years, 183 days, became one of the [[List of the verified oldest people|50 verified oldest people ever]].
*On March 30, 2011, Breuning, aged 114 years, 190 days, surpassed [[Yukichi Chuganji]] to become the 3rd oldest undisputed man ever.
*On April 14, 2011, Breuning died, aged 114 years, 205 days, as the 43rd verified oldest person and the 3rd oldest undisputed man ever.
*On May 18, 2011, [[Maria Gomes Valentim]] of Brazil is verified and recognised as the oldest living person, and Walter Breuning was now recognised as the 3rd oldest person since the death of [[Eunice Sanborn]] on January 31, 2011, and dying as the 44th verified oldest person ever.

==See also==
*[[List of supercentenarians from the United States]]
*[[List of the verified oldest men]]
*[[List of the verified oldest people]]
*[[List of oldest people by nation]]
*[[Oldest people]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Walter Breuning}}
*[http://vimeo.com/5839161 Walter Breuning, 33° Scottish Rite Freemason, speaks about the oldest fraternity in the world]
*[http://grg.org/Adams/E.HTM Validated Living Supercentenarians]
*[http://www.recordholders.org/en/list/oldest.html The Oldest Human Beings]
*[http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/breuning2/main.html Great Falls Tribune's Breuning home page, with interactive timeline, photos, video, articles, links]
*[http://www.krtv.com/pages/feature-walter-breuning/ Walter Breuning interviewed on KRTV and on CBS]
*[http://www.greatfallstribune.com/multimedia/Breuning/index.html Video of Walter reflecting on being one of the oldest male U.S. citizens]
*[http://www.greatfallstribune.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070921/NEWS01/70921021 Great Falls' Walter Breuning, one of world's oldest men, turns 111]
*[http://www.boston.com/news/odd/articles/2008/09/24/man_112_says_secret_to_long_life_is_being_active  Report on Walter's 112th Birthday]
*[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/social_issues/jan-june09/walter_02-16.html ''News Hour with Jim Lehrer'' interview with Walter Breuning]

{{S-start}}
{{S-ach|rec}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Henry Allingham]] | title = [[Oldest people|Oldest recognized living man]] | years = July 18, 2009{{ndash}} April 14, 2011 | after = [[Jiroemon Kimura]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{Oldest Men}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Breuning, Walter
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = World's oldest man
| DATE OF BIRTH     = September 21, 1896
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Melrose, Minnesota]],  United States
| DATE OF DEATH     = April 14, 2011
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Great Falls, Montana
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Breuning, Walter}}
[[Category:1896 births]]
[[Category:2011 deaths]]
[[Category:Colorectal cancer survivors]]
[[Category:American Methodists]]
[[Category:People from Great Falls, Montana]]
[[Category:People from Kingsbury County, South Dakota]]
[[Category:People from Melrose, Minnesota]]
[[Category:Verified American supercentenarians]]

[[bcl:Walter Breuning]]
[[da:Walter Breuning]]
[[et:Walter Breuning]]
[[es:Walter Breuning]]
[[fr:Walter Breuning]]
[[it:Walter Breuning]]
[[la:Gualterius Breuning]]
[[ml:വാൾട്ടർ ബ്രൂണിങ്]]
[[nl:Walter Breuning]]
[[ja:ウォルター・ブラウニング]]
[[pl:Walter Breuning]]
[[ru:Брюнинг, Уолтер]]
[[fi:Walter Breuning]]
[[sv:Walter Breuning]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
