<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9339666" ns="0" title="Wau bulan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:WauBulan.jpg|thumb|200px|A typical wau bulan]]
'''Wau bulan''' is an intricately designed Malaysian moon-kite (normally with floral motifs) that is traditionally flown by men in the [[Malaysia]]n state of [[Kelantan]].  It is one of Malaysia's national symbols, some others being the [[kris]] and [[hibiscus]].  The reverse side of the fifty-cent coin of Malaysia (1989 series) features an intricately-decorated wau bulan with a hummer on top&lt;ref name=&quot;Kites in History, in Teaching and in Therapy&quot;&gt;[[Jose Fadul|Fadul, J.]] (2009). Kites in History, in Teaching, and in Therapy. Lulu Press. ISBN 9780557037711&lt;/ref&gt;. The logo of [[Malaysia Airlines]] (MAS) is also based on this kite.

There are many types of wau in Malaysia, each with its own specialty. Wau kucing (cat kite) and wau merak (peacock kite) are some of the variants.

== Characteristics ==
Wau bulan got its name from the crescent moon-like shape of its lower section (bulan means &quot;moon&quot; in [[Bahasa Malaysia]]). Given the right colour, wau bulan apparently resembles a rising crescent moon when flown.&lt;ref&gt;[http://helmycasanova.pasblog.com/TLG-b1/Kerja-Khusus-Sejarah-PMR-2008-b1-p2.htm Kerja Khusus Sejarah PMR 2008 - Wau]&lt;/ref&gt;

The size of wau bulan is bigger than any other Malaysian traditional kite. The typical size is 2.5 meters in width and 3.5 meters in length.&lt;ref&gt;[http://myschoolnet.ppk.kpm.my/pakatan/montage/kite/types_wau2.htm Types of Wau], myschoolnet.&lt;/ref&gt;. This makes the decorations painted on the kite's body to be visible when it is flown high in the air. To make it more distinctive, wau bulan is normally decorated with large, strong-coloured patterns.

== Gallery ==
{{Gallery|width=180|lines=5
|File:Wau-maker_cutting_details_into_a_wau.JPG| A wau-maker in his workshop. Design details in his wau are made by cutting various layers of coloured paper. The cutting is done spontaneously.
|File:Wau_design_close-up.JPG‎| Close-up of a design on a wau.
|File:Finished_wau_and_wau_frame.JPG| A wau-maker's workshop. Foreground: Wau frames. Background: A completed wau. Further background: The wau-maker.
|File:Other_types_of_wau.JPG‎| Example of other types of wau (based on the shape of a wau).
}}
{{Gallery|width=200|lines=2
|title=Wau as a national symbol
|File:waubulaninMalaysiancoin.JPG|The wau bulan featured on the 50 sen [[Malaysian ringgit#Second series (1989)|Malaysian coin]]
}}

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Malaysia-stub}}
{{kite-stub}}
[[Category:Malay culture]]
[[Category:Kites]]
[[Category:National symbols of Malaysia]]

[[ms:Wau bulan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
