<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9376574" ns="0" title="STV (TV network)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the Scottish television network||STV (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox television channel
| name              = STV
| logofile          = STV logo.svg
| logosize          = 175px
| logocaption       = 
| logoalt           = 
| logo2             =
| established       = 
| airdate           = 
| launch            = 30 May 2006
| closed date       = 
| picture format    = [[576i]] ([[SDTV]])&lt;br&gt;[[1080i]] ([[High-definition television|HDTV]])
| share             = '''ITV Network:'''&lt;br&gt;16.0%&lt;br&gt;0.7% (+1)&lt;br&gt;1.0% (HD)&lt;br&gt;
| share as of       = October 2011
| share source      = [http://www.barb.co.uk/report/monthlyViewing?_s=4 BARB]
| network           = [[ITV]]
| owner             = [[STV Group (Scotland)|STV Group plc]]
| parent            = 
| key people        =
| slogan            = &quot;From Scotland to the World&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;Must See TV&quot;,&lt;br&gt;&quot;Altogether Scotland&quot;
| motto             =
| country           = [[Scotland]]
| language          = [[English language|English]]
| broadcast area    = Scotland&lt;br&gt;(Central and Northern)
| affiliates        = 
| headquarters      = [[Pacific Quay]], [[Glasgow]]
| former names      = [[Grampian Television]]&lt;br&gt;(Northern Scotland);&lt;br&gt;[[Scottish Television]]&lt;br&gt;(Central Scotland)
| replaced names    = 
| replaced by names = 
| sister names      = 
| timeshift names   = STV +1
| web               = {{url|stv.tv}}
| terr serv 1       = [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]]
| terr chan 1       = Channel 3&lt;br&gt;Channel 33 (+1)&lt;br&gt;Channel 51 (HD)
| sat serv 1        = [[Freesat]]
| sat chan 1        = Channel 103
| sat serv 2        = [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]]
| sat chan 2        = Channel 103&lt;br&gt;(No Tayside opt)
| sat serv 3        = [[Astra 2D]]
| sat chan 3        = 10906V 22000 5/6&lt;br&gt;10906V 22000 5/6 (+1)&lt;br&gt;10936V 22000 5/6 (HD)
| cable serv 1      = [[Virgin Media]]
| cable chan 1      = Channel 103&lt;br&gt;Channel 114 (+1)&lt;br /&gt;Channel 113 (HD)
| cable serv 2      = [[Smallworld Cable]]
| cable chan 2      = Channel 103&lt;br&gt;Channel 126 (+1)
| iptv serv 1       = [[TalkTalk TV]]
| iptv chan 1       = Channel 3
| online serv 1     = [[STV Player]]
| online chan 1     = [http://www.stv.tv/player Catch up]
| online serv 2     = [[Zattoo]]
| online chan 2     = [http://zattoo.com/view#stv Watch live]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(STV West region)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
'''STV''' is the brand used by both [[ITV]] licensees in Northern and Central Scotland, formerly known as [[Grampian Television]] (now legally '''STV North''') and [[Scottish Television]] (now legally '''STV Central''') respectively. The brand was adopted on Tuesday 30 May 2006 replacing both franchises' identities. Its positioning, identity and brand guidelines were developed by Elmwood Design's Edinburgh office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = Scottish TV and Grampian TV re-branded by Elmwood
  | publisher = Elmwood
  | date = 24 May 2006
  | url = http://www.elmwood.co.uk/news.asp?id=193
  | accessdate = 5 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The STV branding was previously used by Scottish Television from around 1970 to August 1985. Both licensees are owned by [[STV Group (Scotland)|STV Group plc]].

==Programming==
The two licences still produce regional programmes, although the only difference between them is the respective news programmes and overnight output: ''[[STV News at Six]]'' and ''STV News'' broadcast separate bulletins to Northern Scotland (including an opt-out for the Tayside area), Glasgow &amp; West Central Scotland, and Edinburgh &amp; East Central Scotland. There is no STV South as Southern Scotland is part of the [[Border Television]] region (Border being owned by [[ITV plc]]) and programmes are presented there under the [[ITV1]] [[Border Television|Border]] brand.

Emphasising the fact that STV is essentially one channel across the two regions, there is now a single managing director (Bobby Hain - former managing director of [[Scottish Television]]), a single director of programmes (David Brook - former strategy director of [[Channel 4]]) and a single head of news (Gordon MacMillan - former head of news of Scottish TV).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = Gordon takes control of Scotland ...
  | publisher = Sunday Herald
  | date =
  | url = http://www.sundayherald.com/business/businessnews/display.var.1267644.0.gordon_takes_control_of_scotland.php&amp;cid=0&amp;ei=4Mv8RYbEIqikogLyjL2WDA
  | accessdate = 3 October 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071225220858/http://www.sundayherald.com/business/businessnews/display.var.1267644.0.gordon_takes_control_of_scotland.php&amp;cid=0&amp;ei=4Mv8RYbEIqikogLyjL2WDA |archivedate = 25 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Terms in the renewed licences for both STV Central and STV North also mean that regional non-news programmes are shared (and identically scheduled) across both licences.

Although the stations are only required to produce 1.5 hours a week of regional non-news programmes (a single arrangement covering both North and Central regions), the chief executive of [[STV Group (Scotland)|STV Group plc]], Rob Woodward, told MPs at a Westminster briefing in October 2008 that the station would aim to increase its regional output from 2009 onwards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stvplc.tv/content/mediaassets/doc/SPEECH%20.pdf Westminster speech by Rob Woodward], stvplc.tv, 16 October 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Alongside daily regional news coverage, regular STV programming includes the nightly current affairs programme ''[[Scotland Tonight]]'' and rugby highlights programme ''[[STV Rugby]]''. The company also produces many [[Scottish Gaelic language|Gaelic]] programmes, some of which are now produced for the [[Scots Gaelic]]-language channel, [[BBC Alba (TV channel)|BBC Alba]], alongside archive material including ''[[Speaking our Language]]'' and ''[[Machair (TV series)|Machair]]''. On a network scale, one of STV's most famous exports is the long-running crime drama ''[[Taggart]]'', set in [[Glasgow]].

The network's range of programmes was dramatically expanded during the 1990s under director [[Alistair Moffat]]. Previous TV programming includes the serial dramas ''[[Take the High Road]]'', ''[[Garnock Way]]'' &amp; ''High Living'', gameshows ''Now You See It'' and ''[[Wheel of Fortune (UK game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]'', crime series ''Crimedesk'' with [[Bill Knox]], long-running documentary series ''Weir's Way'', lifestyle show ''Room at the Top'', and ''[[Glen Michael]]'s Cartoon Cavalcade'', which lasted 26 years. Another of the station's best-known programmes, ''[[Scotsport]]'', ran continuously for 51 years until May 2008 and remains one of the world's longest-running television sports programmes.

=={{anchor|Withdrawal of networked output}}Withdrawal of networked output==
In July 2009, STV announced that it was withdrawing some networked programmes such as ''[[The Bill]]'', ''[[Doc Martin]]'', ''[[Midsomer Murders]]'', ''[[Poirot]]'', ''[[Lewis (TV series)|Lewis]]'' and a number of other high profile ITV network dramas from its schedules, instead preferring to concentrate on programming made within Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2009/sep/11/stv-defends-dropping-itv-dramas | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=STV defends dropping ITV dramas | first=Chris | last=Tryhorn | date=11 September 2009 | accessdate=23 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The practice of dropping networked shows had been in operation for other programmes since November 2008 when STV announced it would opt-out of programmes they claimed were not performing well in their broadcast region, including ''[[Sharpe's Peril]]'', ''[[Al Murray's Happy Hour]]'', ''[[Moving Wallpaper]]'', ''[[Benidorm (TV series)|Benidorm]]'' and ''[[The Alan Titchmarsh Show]]''. ITV's coverage of the [[FA Cup]] was also dropped.

ITV claimed that STV were in breach of their network agreements by making this decision and are subsequently suing STV for £38 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/scotland/article6845196.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=ITV to take STV to court over 38m programme bill | first=Charlene | last=Sweeney | date=23 September 2009 | accessdate=23 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/glasgow_and_west/8269151.stm | work=BBC News | title=ITV launches £38m STV legal claim | date=22 September 2009 | accessdate=23 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Latterly, STV counter claimed by launching its own legal action against ITV plc,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/8364200.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; Scotland &amp;#124; STV sues ITV in new legal action |publisher=BBC News |date=2009-11-17 |accessdate=2011-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; claiming the company was owed money and unhappy about promotional advertising of ITV services. The then executive chairman of ITV plc, [[Michael Grade]] claimed ITV was the &quot;victim&quot; in the ongoing dispute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/glasgow_and_west/8401923.stm |title=Michael Grade says ITV is the victim in battle with STV |publisher=BBC News |date=2009-12-08 |accessdate=2011-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amid many protests, the company's chief executive Rob Woodward admitted in December 2009 that STV had made a 'major mistake' by dropping some of the networked dramas and replacing them in some cases with imported output, repeats and films. The company pledged to continue with its plan to produce more regional programming and opt out of networked output with further plans announced in August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/politics/scotland/7921232/STV-viewers-to-miss-out-on-new-ITV-dramas.html STV viewers to miss out on new ITV dramas], telegraph.co.uk, 1 August 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 April 2011, ITV and STV settled its legal dispute, with ITV receiving £18 million from STV.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/04/27/itv-stv-idUSLDE73Q09M20110427 |title=STV agrees 18 million stg legal settlement with ITV |publisher=Reuters |date=2011-04-27 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The £18 million consists of a £7.2 million cash payment payable in 2011 and £10.8 million either in programme rights at the end of the year or cash, as adjusted, depending on further discussions with ITV. The programming rights payment is capped at a maximum of £15 million. In addition, STV will receive £2.4 million of credit for programme opt outs in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.londonstockexchange.com/exchange/news/dow-jones/news-detail.html?newsId=20110427SN001396 |title=DJ STV Group PLC Settlement of Legal Actions with ITV |publisher=London Stock Exchange |date=2011-04-27 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; STV said it believed it was in the best interests of shareholders to end the long period of uncertainty. The parties have agreed the basis of a more collaborative relationship for the future.

===Ofcom investigation===
In March 2010, the Telegraph reported that [[Ofcom]] would launch an investigation over claims that STV allowed the Scottish Government to influence its schedules and replace networked series with Scottish based programmes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Johnson&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/politics/scotland/7360960/Ofcom-probes-Alex-Salmond-cash-for-programmes-row.html|title=Ofcom probes Alex Salmond 'cash-for-programmes' row|last=Johnson|first=Simon|date=3 March 2010|publisher=Telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=3 March 2010 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; An Ofcom report released four months later cleared STV of allowing political interference within feature series, but 18 short social action programmes were found to have been influenced too closely by sponsorship from Government agencies and initiatives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://stakeholders.ofcom.org.uk/binaries/enforcement/broadcast-bulletins/STV_sponsors.pdf OFCOM broadcast bulletin - STV sponsorship report], 26 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Studios==
===STV Central===
The STV studios in Glasgow were originally located in the former Theatre Royal in the [[Cowcaddens]] area of the city. The first programme broadcast by STV from the Theatre Royal studios was ''This is Scotland'' on 31 August 1957. In 1974, the company sold the Theatre Royal to Scottish Opera for conversion back to a full theatre and national opera house&lt;ref&gt;''The Theatre Royal : Entertaining a Nation'' by Graeme Smith ISBN 978-0-9559420-0-6&lt;/ref&gt; and moved into custom-built studios next door. The association with [[Cowcaddens]] ended in July 2006 when the station moved to new, smaller studios in [[Pacific Quay]], alongside the [[Glasgow Science Centre]].

In Edinburgh, STV converted the Gateway Theatre in Leith Walk into colour studios during the mid-late 1960s - a facility which proved especially useful in 1969 when a fire gutted studio A at the Theatre Royal, killing two firemen. The Edinburgh studios later became a permanent production centre for ''[[Take the High Road]]'' before being closed in the early 1990s to save costs. STV's Edinburgh base now consists of smaller studio and office facilities for local news and advertising operations.

===STV North===
STV North's [[Aberdeen]] headquarters moved to new smaller studios in the city's [[Tullos|West Tullos area]] in June 2003, vacating a converted tram depot that had been used since Grampian Television's launch in September 1961. Expansions to the Queens Cross complex were made in 1983 and 1987 - the former as part of a £5 million investment into the company's technical facilities.

Around the time of the station's launch, Grampian also established premises in Dundee, later moving to Albany House in 1980 and Harbour Chambers in 1998. In April 2008, a new Dundee studio for local news and advertising operations was opened in the Seabraes area of the city.

Grampian opened a base for local Highlands &amp; Islands newsgathering in [[Inverness]] in 1983, situated in Huntly Street, which remains open today. A studio complex in [[Stornoway]] was opened in 1993 to accommodate the expansion of the station's Scots Gaelic programming production. The studios closed in 2000 following the axing of the Gaelic news service, ''[[Telefios]]''.

Grampian also established secondary studios in Edinburgh during the late 1960s from where some of the station's light entertainment programming was produced. The studios were closed in 1969.

==STV HD==
[[Image:STV HD logo.svg|thumb|right|250px|STV HD logo]]
It was announced on 21 April 2010 that STV intend to launch an HD channel on digital TV, before the [[2010 World Cup]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stvplc.tv/content/mediaassets/doc/STV%20AGM%20IMS_21%20April%202010_FINAL.pdf|title=STV Group plc Chairman’s AGM Statement and IMS|publisher=STV Group plc|date=2010-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The channel follows the launch of [[ITV1 HD]] which became available on 2 April 2010. However, ITV1 HD is not available to Scottish viewers (except Southern Scotland who are served by [[ITV Tyne Tees &amp; Border]]). The station launched on 6 June 2010, initially broadcasting on [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]] channel 51, from the [[Black Hill transmitting station|Black Hill]], Keelylang Hill and [[Bressay transmitting station|Bressay]] transmitters and now broadcasts from all post-digital switchover transmitters in its coverage area. STV HD is also available on cable, on Virgin Media channel 113.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stv.tv/stvhd|title=HD television is coming to STV|publisher=STV|accessdate=2010-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; To begin with, STV HD is a single service across all of STV’s transmission areas. It carries the programmes as seen in West Central Scotland, including news and commercials, with no regional variations. STV says it is currently working with [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]], [[Freesat]] and ITV Network with a view to making STV HD available via satellite as soon as possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmediascotland.com/press_news/25810/stv-launches-hd-service-on-freeview-and-virgin-media|title=STV Launches HD Service on Freeview and Virgin Media|publisher=allmediascotland|date=2010-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The channel was added to the Freeview EPG on 1 June 2010, the Virgin Media EPG on 4 June and satellite tests began on 25 May.

==STV+1==
On 4 January 2011, [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]] announced details for the launch of ITV1+1, together with the possibility that both STV and [[UTV]] will launch their own [[Timeshift channel|timeshift]] services, STV+1 and UTV+1 in Scotland and Northern Ireland respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freeview.co.uk/Resolutions/About-Channels/Channel-changes/ITV1-1-to-launch-on-11-January-2011|title=ITV1 + 1 to launch on 11 January 2011|publisher=Freeview|accessdate=11 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; STV later confirmed that it would launch STV+1 at 8pm on 11 January 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;STV+1 launch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://entertainment.stv.tv/tv/219521-stv-launches-1-channel/|title=STV launches +1 channel|publisher=STV|date=11 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The channel is available to Freeview viewers on channel 33 and [[Virgin Media]] cable customers on channel 114. The channel is not officially available on the [[Freesat]] and [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]] satellite services but may be manually tuned in. There are two regional variations of STV+1; one for north and one for central Scotland.&lt;ref name=&quot;STV+1 launch&quot; /&gt; 

The north receives the Aberdeen based news and advertisements and the [[Central Belt]] service carries Edinburgh-based news and advertisements allowing viewers in the East who cannot watch STV's 6pm &amp; 10:30pm news programmes for the micro-region to watch the bulletins an hour later.

==Regions and Frequencies==
===Regions===
STV serves central and northern Scotland. Within STV, Scotland is split into two regions and four sub-regions. Networked and regional programming is the same in both regions, apart from regional news and advertising. Within both regions, there are further opt-outs providing sub-regional news and commercials.

STV North (formerly [[Grampian Television]]) is based in Aberdeen and serves Northern Scotland. The main news programme serving the area is the North edition of ''[[STV News at Six]]'', alongside short regional bulletins (''STV News'') and a weekly news programme for the deaf (''STV News Review''). The main 6pm programme on weeknights includes local opt-outs from [[Dundee]] (serving [[Tayside]] &amp; North East [[Fife]]) and Aberdeen (serving the [[Grampian|North East]], [[Scottish Highlands|Highlands]] &amp; Islands) on week nights. The two sub-regions also receive separate commercials. 

STV Central (formerly [[Scottish Television]]) is based at the STV Group headquarters in Glasgow and serves Central Scotland. 
Two editions of ''[[STV News at Six]]'' are produced and broadcast each weeknight from Glasgow (for the city &amp; the west of the central belt) and Edinburgh (for the capital city, South [[Fife]] and the [[Lothians]]). The two sub-regions also receive separate late night news bulletins and local commercials. Lunchtime and weekend news bulletins are broadcast from Glasgow across the Central region.

Altogether, the regions and sub-regions serve a [[population]] of 3,849,000.
*STV North (pop: 981,000):
**STV Aberdeen (pop: 724,000) - [[Aberdeen City]], [[Aberdeenshire]], [[Eilean Siar]], [[Highland (council area)|Highland (''except Lochaber'')]], [[Moray]], [[Orkney]] and [[Shetland]]
**STV Dundee (pop: 267,000) - [[Angus]], [[Dundee City]], [[Fife|(North) Fife]], [[Perth and Kinross]]

*STV Central (pop: 2,826,000):
**STV Edinburgh (pop: 572,000) - [[Clackmannanshire]], [[East Lothian]], [[Edinburgh]], [[Fife|(South) Fife]], [[Midlothian]] and [[West Lothian]]
**STV Glasgow (pop: 2,295,000) - [[Argyll and Bute]], [[Highland (council area)|Highland (''Lochaber only'')]], [[East Ayrshire]], [[East Dunbartonshire]], [[East Renfrewshire]], [[Falkirk (council area)|Falkirk]], [[Glasgow]], [[Inverclyde]], [[North Ayrshire]], [[North Lanarkshire]], [[Renfrewshire]], [[Stirling (council area)|Stirling]], [[South Lanarkshire]], [[South Ayrshire]], [[West Dunbartonshire]].

*The areas of [[Dumfries and Galloway]] and the [[Scottish Borders|Borders]] are currently served by [[ITV Tyne Tees &amp; Border]].

===Frequencies===
STV is broadcast on the following main transmitters (and their dependent relays):

====STV Central====
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''West'''
*[[Black Hill transmitting station|Black Hill]]: Channel 43
*Darvel: Channel 23
*Rosneath: Channel 61
*Torosay: Channel 25
{{col-2}}
'''East'''
*[[Craigkelly transmitting station|Craigkelly]]: Channel 24
{{col-end}}

====STV North====
{{col-start}}
{{col-2}}
'''North East, Highlands &amp; Islands'''
*[[Durris transmitting station|Durris]]: Channel 25 (digital)
*Knockmore: Channel 23
*Rosemarkie: Channel 49
*[[Rumster Forest transmitting station|Rumster Forest]]: Channel 24
*Eitshal: Channel 23
*Keelylang Hill: Channel 43
*[[Bressay transmitting station|Bressay]]: Channel 25
{{col-2}}
'''Tayside &amp; North East Fife'''
*[[Angus transmitting station|Angus]]: Channel 53 (digital)
{{col-end}}

==Retaining identity==
STV, together with its counterpart [[UTV]] in [[Northern Ireland]], has resisted adopting the generic [[ITV1]] branding that is now commonplace throughout the [[ITV plc]] regions in the southern Scottish borders, [[England and Wales]] and the [[Channel Islands]], although it has now adopted a single Scottish identity for both its franchises. The only mentioning of the ITV1 brand on Channel 3 in the STV regions occurs during [[ITV Breakfast]] (''[[Daybreak (ITV)|Daybreak]]'' and ''[[Lorraine (TV programme)|Lorraine]]''), which operates as a separate station, and during some networked programmes themselves.

== Online presence ==

STV's official website, [[stv.tv]], consists of news, sport, entertainment, weather, competitions and programming information. The website also features a video catch-up service, [[STV Player]], offering a chance to see networked and regional programming aired on the station for 30 days after their original broadcast. Exclusive online programming in the form of regular video blogs are also produced for the website. In September 2010 [[TV Genius]]'s [[content discovery platform]] was chosen by STV to incorporate an online [[recommender system]] for its STV site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=22:17 |url=http://www.digitalspy.com/forums/showthread.php?t=1351524 |title=TV Genius to Power Content Discovery for STV |publisher=Digitalspy.com |date=2010-09-13 |accessdate=2011-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cuesupplychain.com/news/story.php?news_id=594 |title=STV opts for TV Genius |publisher=Cuesupplychain.com |date=2010-09-10 |accessdate=2011-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Scottish Broadcasting Commission]]
*[[S2 (TV)|S2]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.stv.tv stv.tv] - Official Website
*{{Twitter|STVPress|STV Press}}

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{STV Group plc}}
{{ITV}}
{{Television in Scotland}}
{{Media in the United Kingdom|television}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stv}}
[[Category:2006 in Scotland]]
[[Category:Media in Glasgow]]
[[Category:Orphan initialisms]]
[[Category:Scottish brands]]
[[Category:Scottish media]]
[[Category:STV Group plc]]
[[Category:STV Productions| 1]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 2006]]
[[Category:Television channels in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Television in Scotland]]

[[cy:STV]]
[[fr:STV (chaîne de télévision)]]
[[gd:STV]]
[[nl:STV (Schotse televisiezender)]]
[[sco:STV]]
[[simple:STV]]
[[uk:Ес.Ті.Ві.]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
