<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9387082" ns="0" title="Trúc Bạch Lake"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox lake
 | lake_name = Trúc Bạch Lake
 | image_lake = Truc Bach Lake.jpg
 | caption_lake = 
 | image_bathymetry = 
 | caption_bathymetry = 
 | location = [[Hanoi]]
 | coords = {{coord|21|2|44|N|105|50|17|E|type:waterbody_region:VN|display=inline,title}}
 | type = [[oxbow lake|oxbow]]
 | basin_countries = Vietnam
 | length = ca {{convert|400|m|ft|abbr=on}}
 | width = ca {{convert|300|m|ft|abbr=on}}
 | area = ca {{convert|9|ha|acre|abbr=on}}
 | depth = 
 | max-depth = 
 | volume = 
 | residence_time = 
 | shore = 
 | elevation = ca {{convert|15|m|ft|abbr=on}}
 | islands = a {{convert|20|m|ft|abbr=on}} in the northwest
}}
[[Image:Truc bach lake mccain memorial hanoi 2007 01.jpg|thumb|Monument where McCain was shot-down on Truc Bach Lake]]
'''Trúc Bạch Lake''' ([[Vietnamese language|Vietnamese]]: {{linktext |Hồ| Trúc| Bạch}}) is one of the many lakes in the city of [[Hanoi]], the [[Capital (political)|capital]] of [[Vietnam]]. It is known outside Vietnam as the site where the US politician [[John McCain]] landed as a navy pilot during the [[Vietnam War]] after being shot down. 

Trúc Bạch Lake is located northwest of Hanoi's Old Quarter, immediately adjacent to the eastern shore of the city's largest lake, the [[West Lake, Hanoi|West Lake]] (Hồ Tây), [[oxbow lake|a former branch]] of the [[Red River (Vietnam)|Red River]] whose west bank is nearby. Trúc Bạch Lake was separated from the West Lake by the construction of a narrow [[Dike (construction)|dike]] (Cổ Ngư, &quot;reinforcement&quot;) in the 17th century to allow raising fish. The inhabitants of the Truc Yen Village, located on the south shore of the newly formed lake, were in the business of making bamboo blinds and hence cultivated a small variety of bamboo&lt;ref name=thingsasian&gt;[http://www.thingsasian.com/stories-photos/2746 Story on thingsasian.com]&lt;/ref&gt;. In 1957 and 1958, major Thanh Niên Road was built between the lakes. In 1730s, the [[Trịnh Lords|Trịnh Lord]] [[Trịnh Giang]] had Trúc Lâm [[Palace]] constructed on the lake shore. The building first served as a pleasure palace but was later converted into a prison for royal [[concubines]] found guilty of crime. The [[silk]] they produced, known as &quot;Bamboo Village Silk&quot; became famous for its beauty.
 
The lake front is open only along Thanh Niên Road, the other sides are occupied by houses and residential streets. The lake is among the most seriously polluted in Hanoi. Nearby historical sites include: Quán Thánh Temple to the southwest of the lake,  Châu Long Pagoda to the east, An Trì Temple (dedicated to the worship of a hero from the war against the Chinese [[Yuan Dynasty]]) on Phó Đức Chính Street, and Cẩu Nhi temple on a small hill near the northern corner of the lake.

On October 26, 1967, during the [[Vietnam War]], [[John McCain]], then a US Navy pilot, was [[Early life and military career of John McCain#Prisoner of war|shot down by an anti-aircraft missile]] on a mission against a Hanoi power plant and parachuted wounded into Trúc Bạch Lake, nearly drowning. He was dragged out of water and mauled by a mob. A monument celebrating the downing of &quot;Tchn Sney Ma Can&quot; was erected at the western shore on Than Niên Road; McCain saw it on his first journey to Vietnam in 1985.

==References and external links==
{{reflist}}
* [http://www.thudo.hanoi.gov.vn/eco/jsp/longArticle.jsp?articleID=90&amp;language=2 Article on the lake's history] at Hanoi municipal website
* [http://www.ruaf.org/files/econf2_backgroundpaper_tran_duc_vien.doc The role of aquaculture in pollution-remediation in Tay Lake and Truc Bach Lake of Ha Noi], University of Vietnam ([[Microsoft Word]] document)

{{Hanoi Tourism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Truc Bach Lake}}
[[Category:Lakes of Hanoi]]

[[es:Lago Trúc Bạch]]
[[vi:Hồ Trúc Bạch]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
