<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9424037" ns="0" title="Mark Kellogg (reporter)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Person
|name        = Mark Kellogg
|image       = Markkellogg.jpg
|caption     = Date and photographer unknown.
|birth_date  = {{Birth date|1831|3|31}}
|birth_name  = Marcus Henry Kellogg
|birth_place = [[Brighton, Ontario]], Canada
|death_date  = {{Death date and age|1876|6|25|1831|3|31}}
|death_place = Near the [[Little Bighorn River]] in the eastern [[Montana Territory]]
|occupation  = Newspaper reporter
|nationality = American
}}

'''Mark Kellogg''' (March 31, 1831 – June 25, 1876) was a [[newspaper]] [[reporter]] killed at the [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]]. Kellogg rode with [[George Armstrong Custer]] during the battle and was evidently one of the first men killed by the [[Sioux]] and [[Cheyenne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYHerald&quot;&gt;[http://www.astonisher.com/archives/museum/mark_kellogg_big_horn.html &quot;Mark Kellogg's Prequil to the Battle: A reporter's account of riding with Custer into the Battle of the Little Bighorn,&quot;] ''The New York Herald'', July 11, 1876. Access Feb 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; His dispatches were the only press coverage of Custer and his men in the days leading up to the battle. As a newspaper [[Stringer (journalism)|stringer]] whose reports were picked up around the country, Kellogg is considered the first [[Associated Press]] [[correspondent]] to die in the line of duty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Associated Press history archives&quot;&gt;[http://www.ap.org/pages/about/history/history_first.html Associated Press history archives], accessed Feb. 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life==
Born '''Marcus Henry Kellogg''' on March 31, 1831, in [[Brighton, Ontario]], [[Canada]], Kellogg was the third of ten children. Kellogg's family moved a number of times in his youth before they eventually settled in [[La Crosse, Wisconsin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CusterCompanion&quot;&gt;''The Custer Companion: A Comprehensive Guide to the Life of George Armstrong Custer and the Plains'' by Thom Hatch, Stackpole Books, 2002, pages 203-204.&lt;/ref&gt; While there Kellogg learned to operate a [[telegraph]] and went to work for both the Northwestern Telegraph Company and the Atlantic and Pacific Telegraph Company.

He married Martha J. Robinson in 1861 and they had two daughters. During the years of the [[American Civil War]], Kellogg became the assistant editor for the ''La Cross Democrat'' newspaper. He also unsuccessfully ran for the office of city clerk in 1867 and played shortstop on one of the town's [[baseball]] teams.&lt;ref&gt;''I Go With Custer: The Life &amp; Death of Reporter Mark Kellogg'' by Mark Kellogg, AST Press, 1996, page 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1867 Kellogg's wife died.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oakgrovecemetery.com/about/walkingtour.asp The Mark Kellogg Historical Plaque], Oak Grove Cemetery, La Crosse, Wisconsin, walking tour of Oak Grove Cemetery, accessed Nov. 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Leaving his daughters to be raised by an aunt,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/wlhba/articleView.asp?pg=1&amp;id=2036&amp;key=kellogg&amp;cy= 'La Crosse scribe victim of Custer's Last Charge'], Milwaukee Sentinel, August 21, 1921, The Wisconsin State Historical Society&lt;/ref&gt; Kellogg began drifting around the upper Midwest, working as a reporter and editorial assistant in places such as [[Council Bluffs, Iowa]], and [[Brainerd, Minnesota]]. While living in Brainerd he ran for election to the [[Minnesota Legislature]], but was defeated.  He also worked as a string correspondent for the ''[[St. Paul Pioneer Press|St. Paul Dispatch]]'', with his articles often published under the [[pen name]] of &quot;Frontier.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''I Go With Custer: The Life &amp; Death of Reporter Mark Kellogg'' by Mark Kellogg, AST Press, 1996, page 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1870s, he moved to [[Bismarck, North Dakota]], where in 1873 he helped editor Clement A. Lounsberry found the ''[[Bismarck Tribune]]''. Even though Kellogg was only an editorial assistant for the paper, he substituted for Lounsberry as editor of the Tribune's second, third and fourth issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/calounsberry.htm Clement A. Lounsberry Colonel], United States Army, Arlington National Cemetery website, accessed Feb. 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle of the Little Bighorn==
{{further|[[Battle of the Little Bighorn]]}}
When Lounsberry learned that a military column (including the [[7th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|7th U.S. Cavalry Regiment]] commanded by Lt. Col. [[George Armstrong Custer]]) would soon leave [[Fort Abraham Lincoln]] for the [[Montana Territory]], he agreed to accompany Custer and provide news coverage. However, at the last minute Lounsberry's wife fell ill, so the editor asked Kellogg to take his place.&lt;ref name=&quot;CusterCompanion&quot;/&gt; Lounsberry expected Kellogg would cover nothing more than a sensational military victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;With Custer 1996&quot;&gt;''I Go With Custer: The Life &amp; Death of Reporter Mark Kellogg'' by Mark Kellogg, AST Press, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kellogg sent three dispatches back to Lounsberry, the last one four days before the battle when they were near the mouth of the Rosebud River. His last dispatch read, &quot;By the time this reaches you we would have met and fought the red devils, with what result remains to be seen. I go with Custer and will be at the death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/issues/1998/may/ap.php &quot;The AP Looks Back: 150 Years of Capturing the Moment&quot;] by Marlane A. Liddell, ''Smithsonian Magazine'', May 1998; [http://www.johnconnollybooks.com/journalism_photos.html &quot;150th Anniversary of the AP&quot;] by John Connolly, ''The Irish Times'', September 1998, accessed Feb 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Kellogg wasn't predicting his own death or Custer's defeat;&lt;ref name=&quot;With Custer 1996&quot;/&gt; instead, &quot;at the death&quot; is a phrase borrowed from fox hunting meaning &quot;present at the kill&quot; (''viz''., of the pursued).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/in+at+the+death | title = Entry for ''death'', sense 15 | year = 2009 | work = Dictionary.com Unabridged Based on the Random House Dictionary | publisher = [[Reference.com|dictionary.com]] | accessdate = 2010-01-12 | quote = ''Fox Hunting''. present at the kill.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four days after that dispatch, the [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]] was fought, resulting in the deaths of Custer and the 208 soldiers, scouts, and civilians riding with him, including Kellogg.

==Aftermath==
Colonel [[John Gibbon]], whose men arrived at the battle on the second day and also helped bury the dead, said he found Kellogg's body in a ravine where a number of men from Company E died.&lt;ref name=&quot;CusterCompanion&quot;/&gt; Kellogg's body was [[Scalping|scalped]] and missing an ear; he was identified by the boots he wore.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wyomingtalesandtrails.com/custer4a.html Little Bighorn: Custer and the Battle of the Little Bighorn], From Wyoming Tales and Trails, The Aftermath, Tom Custer, Rain-in-the-Face, accessed Nov. 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Clement Lounsberry learned of the defeat of Custer's force and Kellogg's death, he &quot;worked tirelessly throughout the night&quot; to produce a special edition of ''The Bismarck Tribune''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/calounsberry.htm Clement A. Lounsberry Colonel, United States Army, Arlington National Cemetery website, accessed Feb. 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Published on July 6, 1876, the article was the battle's first full account. Lounsberry also [[telegraph]]ed the news, including Kellogg's correspondence, to a number of eastern newspapers, including ''The New York Herald.'' Two letters written by Kellogg were published posthumously by the Herald on July 11, 1876.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYHerald&quot;/&gt;

As a newspaper [[Stringer (journalism)|stringer]] whose reports were picked up around the country, Kellogg is considered the first [[Associated Press]] correspondent to die in the line of duty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Associated Press history archives&quot;/&gt;

Some of Kellogg's diary and notes survived the battle and these, along with his news accounts, are one of the primary historical sources for information on the days preceding the battle. His notes are now in the possession of the North Dakota State Historical Society.&lt;ref name=&quot;CusterCompanion&quot;/&gt; His satchel, pencil, and eyeglasses are on display in the [[Newseum]] in Washington, DC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.slate.com/id/2183936/ | title=Down With the Newseum! We don't need a gilded home for 6,214 journalism artifacts. | publisher=[[Slate.com]] | date=Feb. 7, 2008 | accessdate=June 25, 2011 | author=Shafer, Jack}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Battle of the Little Bighorn]]
*[[George Armstrong Custer]]
*[[Sitting Bull]]
*[[Crazy Horse]]
*[[Indian Wars]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}
&lt;!--READ ME!! PLEASE DO NOT JUST ADD NEW NOTES AT THE BOTTOM. Use&lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref in the text. --&gt;

==Further reading==
* &quot;Notes on the Little Big Horn Expedition Under General Custer, 1876,&quot; by Mark Kellogg,  ''Contributions to the Historical Society of Montana'', v. 9 (1923).
* ''I Go With Custer: The Life &amp; Death of Reporter Mark Kellogg'' by Sandy Barnard, AST Press, (1996). Includes a reprinting of Kellogg's diary.
* &quot;Custer's 'Mysterious Mr. Kellogg' and the Diary of Mark Kellogg&quot; by John C. Hixon, North Dakota History 17, no.3 (1950).
* &quot;Colonel Custer's Copperhead: The Mysterious Mark Kellogg&quot; by Lewis O. Saum, ''Montana: The Magazine of Western History'' Autumn, 1978: Volume 28, No. 4, published by the Montana Historical Society.
* &quot;Mark Kellogg Telegraphed for Custer’s Rescue&quot; by Oliver Knight (1960). Reprinted from ''North Dakota Historical Society Quarterly'', Vol. 27, No. 2, Spring 1960.
* &quot;The 'Custer Campaign Diary' of Mark Kellogg&quot; by [[Elmo Scott Watson]], ''The Westerners Brand Book 1945-46'', Chicago, (1947).

{{good article}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Kellogg, Mark
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Kellogg, Marcus Henry 
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=American [[newspaper]] [[reporter]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=March 31, 1831
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Brighton, Ontario]], Canada
|DATE OF DEATH=June 25, 1876
|PLACE OF DEATH=Near the [[Little Bighorn River]] in the eastern [[Montana Territory]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kellogg, Mark}}
[[Category:Associated Press]]
[[Category:American reporters and correspondents]]
[[Category:Journalists killed while covering military conflicts]]
[[Category:American people of the Indian Wars]]
[[Category:People from Bismarck, North Dakota]]
[[Category:People from Northumberland County, Ontario]]
[[Category:People from La Crosse, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:1831 births]]
[[Category:1876 deaths]]
[[Category:Associated Press reporters]]
[[Category:Journalists killed in the United States]]

[[fr:Mark Kellogg]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
