<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9425783" ns="0" title="Polish migration to the United Kingdom"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox Ethnic group
|group   = Polish British
|image   = [[File:Blank300.png|285px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Joseph Conrad.PNG|92px]][[Image:Henryk Zygalski.jpg|97px]][[Image:Stanislaw Maczek 2.jpg|95px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Image:Wladyslaw Anders.jpg|98px]][[File:Josef Rotblat ID badge.png|92px]]
|caption = &lt;small&gt;Notable Polish Britons:&lt;br /&gt;[[Joseph Conrad]], [[Henryk Zygalski]], [[Stanisław Maczek]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Władysław Anders]], Sir [[Josef Rotblat]]&lt;/small&gt;
|poptime = 60,711 Polish-born (2001 Census)&lt;br&gt;515,000 Polish-born (2010 ONS estimate)&lt;br&gt;
|popplace = [[United Kingdom|Throughout the United Kingdom]]
|langs    = [[English language|English]], [[Polish language|Polish]], [[Yiddish]] (mostly in the past)
|rels     = [[Roman Catholic]], [[Orthodox Church|Orthodox]], [[Judaism]]}}

'''Polish migration to the United Kingdom''' describes the temporary or permanent [[human migration|migration]] of [[Poles]] to the [[United Kingdom]] (UK). Most Polish migrants to the UK emigrated after two major events, the [[Polish Resettlement Act 1947]] and the [[2004 enlargement of the European Union]]. Today, a large number of Polish-born people live in the UK, and there is a wider population of British Poles including the descendents of previous immigrants.

==History and settlement==
===Early history===
According to the Medieval chroniclers [[Thietmar of Merseburg]] and [[Adam of Bremen]], King [[Canute the Great]] - who ruled both Denmark and England - was the son of a Polish princess, a daughter of [[Mieszko I of Poland]] and sister of [[Boleslaw I of Poland]]. An inscription in &quot;Liber vitae of the New Minster and Hyde Abbey Winchester&quot; mentions King Canute as having  a sister named &quot;Santslaue&quot; (&quot;Santslaue soror CNVTI regis nostri&quot;), which without doubt is a [[Slavic languages|Slavic]] name, and J. Steenstrup suggests this was a rendering of ''Świętosława''. References in medieval chronicles to the involvement of Polish troops in invasions of England are likely related to Canute's Polish ancestry, constituting the earliest evidence of Poles arriving in the country.

In the 16th century, when most grain imports to the British Isles were derived from Poland, Polish travellers came as merchants and diplomats, usually on the [[Eastland Company]] trade route from Gdansk to London. Poles are mentioned in [[Shakespeare's]] [[Hamlet]], which [[Israel Gollancz]] says is an influence of [[The Counsellor]] by [[Wawrzyniec Grzymała Goślicki]]. As early as 1608 there were enough Poles in England for the [[Virginia Company]] to hire a group of them to sail to America to help salvage the [[Jamestown, Virginia|Jamestown Colony]], where they formed an early [[trade union]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.polamcon.org/jamestown/roles-and-accomp.htm&lt;/ref&gt; In the 17th century, Irish Catholics serving in the Swedish Army defected to Poland.&lt;ref&gt;http://home.earthlink.net/~rggsibiba/html/sib/sib2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

After the [[Battle of Vienna]] a central London pub was called the 'King of Poland' and soon after the road it was situated in, was named 'Poland Street' - which exists to this day. In the 18th century some Polish [[Protestants]] settled around Poland Street as religious refugees from the [[counter reformation]] in Poland.

In the 19th century, due to the collapse of the [[November Uprising]] of 1831 against the [[Russian Empire]], many Polish insurgents came to the UK in search of political sanctuary.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_London&quot;&gt;[[BBC London]], [http://72.14.205.104/search?q=cache:bRYqgpo00jgJ:www.bbc.co.uk/london/content/articles/2005/05/26/polish_london_feature.shtml+November+Uprising+of+1831+BBC+London&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=1 Polish London]. accessdate 2008-01-02.&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[First World War]] Poles settled in large numbers in [[London]]{{ndash}} many from the London Polish Prisoner-of-War camps in [[Alexandra Palace]] and [[Feltham]].

===Second World War period===
The Poles made an [[Polish contribution to World War II|important contribution]] to the Allied war effort, which directly led to the formation of the Polish British community as it exists today. The majority of Poles came to the United Kingdom as political émigrés after the German and Soviet [[Occupation of Poland (1939–1945)|occupation of Poland]]. In 1940, with the fall of France, the exiled Polish President, Prime Minister and government transferred to London, along with a first wave of at least 20,000 soldiers and airmen.

Poles formed the fourth-largest armed force after the Soviets, the Americans and the combined troops of British Empire. Poles were the largest group of [[non-British personnel in the RAF during the Battle of Britain]], and the [[303 Polish Squadron]] was the highest-scoring RAF unit in [[Battle of Britain]]. [[Special Operations Executive]] had a large section of covert, elite Polish troops and close cooperation with the [[Armia Krajowa|Polish resistance]]. The Polish Army under British high command were instrumental at the [[Battle of Monte Cassino]], the [[Battle of the Falaise Gap]], the [[Battle of Arnhem]], the [[Siege of Tobruk]] and the liberation of many European cities including [[Bologna]] and [[Breda]].

Perhaps most importantly, the Poles cracked an early version of the Enigma code, which &quot;laid the foundations for British success in cracking German codes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8158782.stm | work=BBC News | title=How Poles cracked Nazi Enigma secret | date=20 July 2009 | accessdate=22 May 2010 | first=Laurence | last=Peter}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former [[Bletchley Park]] cryptologist [[Gordon Welchman]] said: '[[Ultra]] would never have got off the ground if we had not learned from the Poles, in the nick of time, the details both of the German military... [[Enigma machine]], and of the operating procedures that were in use.'&lt;ref&gt;[[Gordon Welchman]], ''The Hut Six Story'', p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt; After the war, [[Winston Churchill|Churchill]] told [[George VI of the United Kingdom|King George VI]]: 'It was thanks to Ultra that we won the war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cited in a 2003 [[Imperial War Museum]] exhibit on &quot;Secret War.'&lt;/ref&gt;

By July 1945 228,000 troops of the [[Polish Armed Forces in the West]] were serving under the high command of the British Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_London&quot; /&gt; Many of these men and women were originally from the [[Kresy]] region of eastern Poland including cities such as [[Lwow]] and [[Wilno]]. They had been deported from Kresy to the [[Russia]]n [[Gulags]] when [[Hitler]] and [[Stalin]] occupied Poland in 1939 in accordance with the [[Nazi-Soviet Pact]]. When two years later [[Winston Churchill|Churchill]] and [[Stalin]] formed an alliance against Hitler, the Kresy Poles were released from the Gulags in Siberia, formed the [[Anders Army]] and marched to Persia to create the [[II Corps (Poland)]] under British high command.

These Polish troops were vital to the [[Allied]] defeat of the Germans in North Africa and Italy, and hoped to return to Kresy in an independent and democratic Poland at the end of the War. But at [[Yalta]], Roosevelt and Churchill agreed that Stalin should keep the Soviet gains [[Hitler]] agreed to in the [[Nazi-Soviet Pact]], including [[Kresy]], and carry out [[Polish population transfers (1944–1946)]]. Consequently, Roosevelt and Churchill had agreed that tens of thousands of veteran Polish troops under British command should lose their [[Kresy]] homes to the Soviet Union, with the implication that relatives including wives and children would be at the mercy of the [[NKVD]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pbs.org/behindcloseddoors/about/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; In reaction, thirty officers and men from the [[II Corps (Poland)]] committed suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;pp.374-383 Olson and Cloud 2003&quot;&gt;pp.374-383 Olson and Cloud 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

Churchill explained his actions in a three-day [[Parliament]]ary debate starting 27 February 1945, which ended in a [[vote of confidence]]. Many MPs openly criticised Churchill over [[Yalta]] and voiced strong loyalty to the UK's Polish allies.&lt;ref name=&quot;pp.374-383 Olson and Cloud 2003&quot;/&gt; Some reporters felt Churchill wasn't confident Poland would be the independent and democratic country Polish troops could return to, because the prime minister also said: 'His Majesty's Government will never forget the debt they owe to the Polish troops... I earnestly hope it will be possible for them to have citizenship and freedom of the British empire, if they so desire.'&lt;ref&gt;http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=BTsNAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=_mkDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4479,4501733&lt;/ref&gt;

During the debate, 25 MPs risked their careers to draft an amendment protesting against the UK's tacit acceptance of Poland's domination by the Soviet Union. These members included: [[Arthur Greenwood]]; [[Sir Archibald Southby, 1st Baronet]]; [[Sir Alec Douglas-Home]]; Commander [[Sir Archibald Southby, 1st Baronet]]; [[James Heathcote-Drummond-Willoughby, 3rd Earl of Ancaster]] and [[Victor Raikes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pp.374-383 Olson and Cloud 2003&quot;/&gt; After the failure of the amendment, [[Henry Strauss, 1st Baron Conesford]], the [[Member of Parliament]] for [[Norwich]], resigned his seat in protest at the British treatment of Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;pp.374-383 Olson and Cloud 2003&quot;/&gt;

===Polish Resettlement Act 1947===

When the Second World War ended, a [[Communist]] government was installed in Poland. Most Poles [[Western betrayal|felt betrayed]] by their wartime allies, and refused to return to Poland, because of the [[Soviet repressions of Polish citizens (1939–1946)]], Soviet conduct around the 1944 [[Warsaw Uprising]], the [[Trial of the Sixteen]] and other executions of pro-democracy Poles, particularly the [[Cursed soldiers|former members]] of the [[Armia Krajowa|Home Army]]. The result was the [[Polish Resettlement Act 1947]], the UK's first mass immigration law.

Large numbers, after occupying resettlement camps of the [[Polish Resettlement Corps]], later settled in London, many recruited as European Volunteer Workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kay|first=Diana|coauthors=Miles, Robert|year=1998|title=Refugees or migrant workers? The case of the European Volunteer Workers in Britain (1946–1951)|journal=Journal of Refugee Studies|volume=1|issue=3-4|pages=214–236|url=http://jrs.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/1/3-4/214|doi=10.1093/jrs/1.3-4.214}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others settled in the British Empire, forming large [[Polish Canadian]] and [[Polish Australian]] communities.

In the 1951 Census of the UK, the Polish-born population of the UK numbered some 162,339, up from 44,642 in 1931.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Holmes|first=Colin|title=John Bull's Island: Immigration and British Society 1871-1971|publisher=Macmillan|location=Basingstoke|year=1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Burrell|first=Kathy|year=2002|title=Migrant memories, migrant lives: Polish national identity in Leicester since 1945|journal=Transactions of the Leicestershire Archaeological and Historical Society|issue=76|pages=59–77|url=http://www.le.ac.uk/lahs/downloads/2002/burrell2002-3.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The relaxation of travel restrictions to and from Poland saw a steady increase in Polish migration to the United Kingdom in the 1950s. [[Brixton]], [[Earls Court]] and [[Lewisham]] were a few of the London areas where they settled. As these communities grew, it was felt by the Polish Catholic hierarchy and the [[England|English]] and [[Scotland|Scottish]] hierarchies that Polish priests should settle and minister specifically to the spiritual needs of the Polish people. The first such parish was Brockley-Lewisham in 1951 and today there are 10 Polish parishes in London, in places such as [[Balham, London|Balham]] and [[Ealing]]. Thriving parishes also exist in many other UK towns and cities.

The longer established communities that ensued after the church established itself were mainly set up by former members of the [[Polish Resettlement Corps]] (PRC) in the late 1940s and early 1950s. Around the hub of a Polish church would be Polish clubs, Cultural Centres as well as a variety of adult and youth organisations such as the Ex-Combatants (SPK), the Polish Youth Group (KSMP) and the Polish Scouting Movement ([[ZHP]] pgk). The original aims of these organisations was to ensure a continuation of Polish language, culture and heritage for the children of the ex PRC members. Many of these groups are still active and steps are being taken to attract newer Polish migrants.

The [[Polish Government in Exile|Polish Government in London]] was not dissolved until 1991, when a freely elected president took office in [[Warsaw]]. The Polish people fought hard to combat communism, and for their right to liberty. Previously a base to fight against the communist regime in Poland, London came to be seen as an important centre to foster business and political relations.

===21st century economic migration===
[[File:Polish-born people in employment in the UK 2003-2010 - chart 2369a at statistics gov uk.gif|thumb|right|Polish-born people in employment in the UK 2003-2010&lt;ref name=&quot;2010 estimates&quot;/&gt;]]
Many of the Polish British community formed after the Second World War had friends and relatives in Poland. Partly because of this bond, there was a steady flow of immigration from Poland to the UK, which then accelerated after the [[fall of communism]] in 1989. Throughout the 1990s, Poles used the freer travel restrictions to move to the UK and work in the [[grey economy]].

At the expansion of the [[European Union|EU]] on 1 May 2004, the UK granted free movement to workers from the new member states.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tescocorporate.com/page.aspx?pointerid=71B7D39196C34FDD98973A56FE14661A Tesco caters for an estimated 1.1 million Poles visiting the UK or living and working there]&lt;/ref&gt;

There are restrictions on benefits that Polish immigrants can claim, which are covered by the [[Worker Registration Scheme]].&lt;ref&gt;Home Office, Border &amp; Immigration Agency, [http://www.workingintheuk.gov.uk/working_in_the_uk/en/homepage/schemes_and_programmes/worker_registration.html The Worker Registration Scheme] Accessed 2007-12-27.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the other European Union member states exercised their right for temporary immigration control (which must end by 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://europa.eu/scadplus/leg/en/cha/c10524.htm Freedom of movement for workers after enlargement] Europa&lt;/ref&gt;) over entrants from these accession states,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4497309.stm Barriers still exist in larger EU], BBC News, 1 May 2005&lt;/ref&gt; although some are now removing these restrictions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3513889.stm EU free movement of labour map], BBC News, 4 January 2007, accessed 26 August 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Delikateski.jpg|thumb|A Polish delicatessen in [[Stroud]], [[Gloucestershire]], opened in 2006]]
The Home Office publishes quarterly statistics on the number of applications to the Worker Registration Scheme. Figures published in August 2007 indicate that 656,395 people were accepted on to the scheme between 1 May 2004 and 30 June 2007, of whom 430,395 were Polish nationals. However, this figure is only indicative as the scheme is an opt-in system without incentive: it costs Poles time and money and isn't enforced. Poles are able to ignore the scheme and work in the UK provided they have a Polish passport or Polish identity card and a National Insurance Number Card, which has led to estimates of Polish nationals in the UK being much higher.&lt;ref&gt;Home Office, Department for Work and Pensions, HM Revenue &amp; Customs and Communities and Local Government, [http://www.ind.homeoffice.gov.uk/6353/aboutus/accessionmonitoringmay04jun1.pdf Accession Monitoring Report: A8 Countries, May 2004-June 2007], 21 August 2007, accessed 26 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Polish magazine ''[[Polityka]]'' has launched a 'Stay With Us' scheme offering young academics a £5,000 bonus to encourage them to stay at home.

Rapid economic growth at home, falling unemployment and the rising strength of the [[złoty]] have, by the autumn of 2007, reduced the economic incentive for Poles to migrate to the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;timesonline.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article3378858.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=Building a future in a land where life is affordable | first=Kamil | last=Tchorek | date=16 February 2008 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Labour shortages in Poland's cities and in sectors such as construction, IT and financial services have also played a part in stemming the flow of Poles to the UK.&lt;ref name=IPPR&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ippr.org/members/download.asp?f=%2Fecomm%2Ffiles%2Ffloodgates%5For%5Fturnstiles%2Epdf|title=Floodgates or turnstiles? Post-EU enlargement migration to (and from) the UK|last=Pollard|first=Naomi|coauthors=Latorre, Maria; Sriskandarajah, Dhananjayan|month=April | year=2008|publisher=Institute for Public Policy Research|pages=21|accessdate=2008-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the August 2007 Accession Monitoring Report, fewer Poles migrated in the first half of 2007 than in the same period in 2006. Launched on 20 October 2007, a campaign by the [[British Polish Chamber of Commerce]], 'Wracaj do Polski' ('Come Back to Poland') encourages Poles living and working in the UK to return home.

There was a [[baby boom]] during [[Martial Law in Poland]] in the early 1980s. Consequently there has been over-supply of new workers on the Polish job market in the 2000s. Unemployment rose and emigration has been a solution for many young Poles. Now that Poland's demographic bulge is ageing, the rate of new entrants to the job market, and therefore emigration, is slowing. Some commentators say the Polish baby-boomers are returning to Poland as they reach child-rearing age themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;timesonline.co.uk&quot;/&gt;
wo

==Demographics==
===Population size===
The [[2001 UK Census]] recorded 60,711 Polish-born people resident in the UK.&lt;ref name=OECD&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/18/23/34792376.xls|title=Country-of-birth database|publisher=[[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]]|accessdate=2009-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; 60,680 of these were resident in [[Great Britain]] (the UK minus [[Northern Ireland]]), compared to 73,951 in 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;Born abroad&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/uk/05/born_abroad/countries/html/poland.stm|title=Born abroad: Poland|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=2009-10-04 | date=7 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the migration that has followed Poland's accession to the EU, the Polish-born population in the whole of the UK is estimated to have risen to 515,000 in the year to March 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;2010 estimates&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.statistics.gov.uk/cci/nugget.asp?id=2369| title=Polish people in the UK: Half a million Polish-born residents| publisher=[[Office for National Statistics]] | date=25 November 2010| accessdate=30 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unofficial estimates have put the number of Poles living in the UK higher, at up to one million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/1565532/Polands-politicians-fly-to-UK-ahead-of-election.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | title=Poland's politicians fly to UK ahead of election | date=8 October 2007 | accessdate=22 May 2010 | first=Harry | last=de Quetteville}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/culture/tvandradioblog/2007/sep/03/radiomovestopolishposition | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Radio moves to Polish position | first=Julita | last=Kaczmarek | date=3 September 2007 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2007/jul/11/news.poland | work=The Guardian | location=London | title='Swiat Wedlung Clarksona, poprosz (World According to Clarkson, please) | first=Rebecca | last=Smithers | date=11 July 2007 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Population distribution===
{{See also|Lists of UK locations with large Polish populations}}
The main hub of the London Polish community is [[Hammersmith]] in west [[London]], as well as [[Ealing]], [[Balham, London|Balham]], [[London Borough of Enfield|Enfield]] and [[London Borough of Haringey|Haringey]]. The activities revolve around the Polish Social and Cultural Centre ([[POSK]]) in King Street. Polish newspapers and food shops are increasingly apparent following Poland's entry into the [[European Union]] in May 2004. Many towns and cities in the UK have long established and relatively large Polish communities, most notably [[London]], [[Liverpool]], [[Birmingham]], [[Bradford]], [[Huddersfield]], [[Leeds]], [[Manchester]], [[Nottingham]] and [[Wakefield]]. Other communities exist in locations such as Leicester, Slough, Reading and Melton Mowbray.

Poles have also settled in [[Hereford]], [[Sheffield]], [[Bolton]], [[Bury, Greater Manchester|Bury]], [[Northampton]], [[Peterborough]] and [[Chorley]] in [[Lancashire]]. There is a long established Polish community in [[Bristol]] and there are also concentrations in [[Derby]], South Yorkshire, [[South Wales]], [[North Wales]] mainly in [[Wrexham]], [[Rugby, Warwickshire|Rugby]], [[Banbury]], [[Luton]], Evesham and [[Swindon]]. Scotland has seen a significant influx of Polish immigrants with estimates of Poles currently living in Scotland ranging from 40,000 according to [[General Register Office for Scotland]] up to 50,000 as per Polish Council,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.scotsman.com/topics.cfm?tid=1508&amp;id=935812007 Polish immigrants swell Scotland's new baby boom]&lt;/ref&gt; with around 5,000 in the [[Scottish Highlands|Highlands]] region. This has led to the creation of a bilingual [[English language|English]]-[[Polish language|Polish]] newspaper.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/highlands_and_islands/6385713.stm Bilingual paper for north Poles]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Carlisle, Cumbria|Carlisle]] in [[Cumbria]], which is twinned with the Polish city of [[Słupsk]], has a Polish population of over 1,600.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carlisle.gov.uk/carlislecc/main.asp?page=2256 Polish immigrants in Carlisle]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Blackpool]] has about 5,000 immigrants living in and around the resort on the [[The Fylde|Fylde coast]]. The local newspaper is one of a handful of British newspapers to have its own online edition in Polish called [http://www.blackpoolgazette.co.uk/CustomPages/CustomPage.aspx?sectionid=11828 ''Witryna Polska'' ].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackpoolgazette.co.uk/ViewArticle.aspx?SectionID=62&amp;articleid=1874795 Polish Gazette in the TV spotlight]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the recent migrations, many towns and cities in the UK now have a growing number of Polish inhabitants. Polish workers are employed in agriculture and light industry in the countrysides of low-population density regions such as [[East Anglia]] and [[East Midlands]].

Official figures on the number of Polish people in [[Northern Ireland]] are difficult to obtain. The total number of Polish nationals who applied for a [[National Insurance Number]] is 12,020 as of 2005, but the actual number of residents is likely to be much higher.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arts.ulster.ac.uk/aich/nbsymposia/documents/trumpup_game.pdf University Of Ulster Project on Polish Minority]&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Police Service of Northern Ireland]] (PSNI) recruitment drive in November 2006 attracted applications from 968 Poles, with language exams being held both in Northern Ireland and [[Warsaw]], but as of 2008 none have entered the PSNI's ranks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/6251117.stm Almost 1,000 Poles apply to PSNI]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/6767227.stm BBC News - No Poles make it into PSNI ranks]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social issues==
===Ethnic tensions===
{{see also|Anti-Polish sentiment in the United Kingdom}}

Polish people living in the UK reported 42 racially motivated violent attacks against them in 2007, compared with 28 in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/7435935.stm | work=BBC News | title=BBC denies MP's anti-Polish claim | date=4 June 2008 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2008 Polish [[Lipka Tatar]] James Lipka, a [[Muslim]], won Mr J Lipka v Response Handling Ltd S/123726/06 F603/30. He was awarded £22,000, including aggravated damages, for racial discrimination suffered while working at the Response Handling call centre based at Ibrox Stadium in Glasgow.  Mr Lipka had been subjected to racist abuse after raising concerns about discrimination against Irish and Asian callers by agents working on projects for the Rangers Football Club and the Student Loans Company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.scotsman.com/scotland/Muslim-in--call-centre.4143689.jp | location=Edinburgh | work=The Scotsman | first=Craig | last=Brown | title=Muslim in call centre abuse wins Â£20,000 | date=3 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://islamineurope.blogspot.com/2008/06/glasgow-22000-for-osama-abuse.html&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 26, 2008, ''[[The Times]]'' published a comment piece by Jewish restaurant reviewer [[Giles Coren]] containing [[anti-Polish sentiment]] including [[stereotypes]] of Polish [[anti-Semitism]]. Coren used the [[racial slur]] '[[Polack]]' to describe Polish immigrants in the UK, arguing that &quot;if England is not the land of milk and honey it appeared to them three or four years ago, then, frankly, they can clear off out of it&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/columnists/giles_coren/article4399669.ece|title=Two waves of immigration, Poles apart|last=Coren|first=Giles|work=[[The Times]]|date=26 July 2008|accessdate=26 September 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The article has been [[Giles Coren#Polish controversy|subject to major criticism]].

The [[far right]] [[British National Party]] (BNP) have used anti-Polish sentiment,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/politics/article1690422.ece BNP advances on Middle England to exploit ‘fear’ of Polish migrants] Andrew Norfolk, The Times, April 23, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and campaigned for a ban on all Polish migrant workers in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1158970/BNP-shot-uses-POLISH-Spitfire-anti-immigration-campaign.html BNP shot down after it uses a POLISH Spitfire to front its anti-immigration campaign] Daily Mail, 4th March 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
In one highly publicised incident, the party used a poster that showed a nostalgic picture of a Second World War Spitfire fighter plane under the slogan &quot;Battle for Britain&quot;, during the party's 2009 European Elections campaign, in which they argued against Polish immigration in Britain. However, apparently unknowingly, the photograph they used was accidentally that of a Spitfire belonging to the 303 Squadron of the Polish Air Force. John Hemming, MP for Yardley, Birmingham, ridiculed the party for accidentally using an image of &quot;Polish heroism&quot; in their campaign: &quot;They have a policy to send Polish people back to Poland – yet they are fronting their latest campaign using this plane.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/politics/4935429/BNP-uses-Polish-Spitfire-in-anti-immigration-poster.html BNP uses Polish Spitfire in anti-immigration poster] 04 Mar 2009, ''The Telegraph''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable individuals==
The following individuals are notable Poles who have lived in the United Kingdom, or British people of Polish ancestry.
=== Businessmen === 
* [[Jack Cohen (Tesco)|Sir Jack Cohen]], the founder of [[Tesco]], was the son of Polish immigrants.&lt;ref name=odnb&gt;[http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/30949 Sir John Edward Cohen at Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Artists and Fashion===
* [[Henryk Gotlib]], painter&lt;ref name=&quot;Untold London&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.untoldlondon.org.uk/news/ART44191.html|title=Poles in London history|last=Lachowicz|first=Marysia|date=21 February 2007|publisher=Untold London|accessdate=15 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Literature and media===
* [[Joseph Conrad]], novelist&lt;ref name=&quot;Untold London&quot;/&gt;

===Musicians and performers===
* [[Mel Giedroyc]], actress and comedienne, one half of '[[Mel and Sue]]' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.express.co.uk/posts/view/184227/Mel-Giedroyc-Dad-s-tragic-childhood-has-made-me-a-better-person&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Daniela Denby-Ashe]], actress
* [[Cher Lloyd]], singer

===Politicians===
*[[Daniel Kawczynski]], [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] MP for [[Shrewsbury and Atcham]], whose family fled Poland in 1940&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/law-and-order/4309742/Daniel-Kawczynski-The-tallest-MP-in-in-Parliament.html|title=Daniel Kawczynski: The tallest MP in in Parliament|work=The Daily Telegraph|date=22 January 2009|accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mark Lazarowicz]], [[Labour Co-operative|Labour and Co-operative]] MP for [[Edinburgh North and Leith]], whose father was Polish&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.marklazarowicz.org.uk/report-from-parliament-north-edinburgh-news-june-2009|title=Report from Parliament (North Edinburgh News, June 2009)|publisher=Mark Lazarowicz|date=June 2009|accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Denis MacShane]], former [[Minister for Europe]], whose father was Polish&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1460740/MacShanes-passion-for-Europe-driven-by-memories-of-war.html|title=MacShane's passion for Europe driven by memories of war|first=Toby|last=Helm|work=The Daily Telegraph|date=1 May 2004|accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[David Miliband]], former [[Foreign Secretary]], whose mother was born in Poland&lt;ref name=Miliband&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/family/7730052/The-miraculous-escape-of-Marion-Miliband.html|title=The miraculous escape of Marion Miliband|first1=Robert|last1=Mendick|first2=Matthew|last2=Day|work=The Daily Telegraph|date=16 May 2010|accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ed Miliband]], leader of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], whose mother was born in Poland&lt;ref name=Miliband/&gt;
* [[Edward Bernard Raczyński]], aristocrat, diplomat, writer, politician and President of Poland in exile (between 1979 and 1986)&lt;ref name=&quot;Untold London&quot;/&gt;
* [[Szmul Zygielbojm]] was a Jewish-Polish socialist politician, [[General Jewish Labour Bund in Lithuania, Poland and Russia|Bund]] leader, and member of the National Council of the Polish Government in Exile. He committed suicide to protest the indifference of the [[Allies in World War II|Allied]] governments in the face of the Holocaust.&lt;ref name=&quot;Untold London&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anglo-Polish Radio ORLA.fm]]
* [[Polish diaspora]]
* [[Dziennik Polski]]
* [[Goniec Polski]]
* [[Polish Radio London]]
* [[Londyńczycy]]
* [[BBC Polish Section]]
* [[Polish government-in-exile|Polish Government in London]]
* [[Western betrayal]]
* [[Federation of Poles in Great Britain]]
* [[World War II Behind Closed Doors: Stalin, the Nazis and the West]]
* [[History of the Jews in Poland]]
* [[Rescue of Jews by Poles during the Holocaust]]
* [[British Jews]]
* [[Oxford University Polish Society]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''A Remarkable School in Exile 1941-1951'', Veritas Foundation Publication, ISBN 0 9545100 0 3
* S.Barnes, ''A Long Way From Home'', Staffordshire University 2003
*Kathy Burrell, ''Polish Migration to the UK in the 'New' European Union'', Ashgate 2009, ISBN 978-0-7546-7387-3
*Dr Diana M Henderson(Editor), ''The Lion and The Eagle'', Cualann Press ISBN 0-9535036-4-X.
*Robert Gretzyngier ''Poles in Defence of Britain'', Grub 2001, ISBN 1-902304-54-3
*Michael Hope, ''The Abandoned Legion'', Veritas Foundation Publication ISBN 1-904639-09-7.
*Michael Hope, ''Polish deportees in the Soviet Union'', Veritas Foundation Publication, ISBN 0-948202-76-9
*W. Jedrzejewicz, ''Poland in the British Parliament 1939-1945'', White Eagle Printing
*G. Kay &amp; R.Negus, ''Polish Exile Mail in Great Britain 1939-1949'', J.Barefoot, ISBN 0 906845 52 1
*Ignacy Matuszewski, ''Did Britain Guarantee Poland's frontiers?'', Polish Bookshop
*Ignacy Matuszewski, ''Great Britain's Obligations Towards Poland'', National Committee of Americans, 1945
*Robert Ostrycharz,''Polish War Graves in Scotland A Testament to the Past'', ISBN 1-872286-48-8.
*Prazmowska, Anita, ''Britain and Poland 1939-1943'', Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0-521-48385-9
* Tim Smith &amp; Michelle Winslow, ''Keeping the Faith The Polish Community in Britain'', Bradford Heritage, ISBN 0-907734-57-X
*Peter Stachura(Editor), ''The Poles in Britain 1940-2000'', Frank Cass ISBN 0-7146-8444-9.
*Keith Sword, ''Identity in Flux'', School of Slavonic and East European Studies 1996, ISBN 0-903425-60-2
*R. Umiastowski, ''Poland, Russia and Great Britain 1941-1945'', Hollis &amp; Carter 1946
*Ian Valentine, ''Station 43 Audley End House and SOE's Polish section'', Sutton  2004, ISBN 0-7509-4255-X
*Various, ''Intelligence co-operation between Poland and Great Britain during World War II'', Vallentine Mitchell 2005, ISBN 0-85303-656-X
*Jonathan Walker, ''Poland Alone'', History Press 2008, ISBN978-1-86227-474-7
*Zubrzycki, Jerzy ''Soldiers and Peasants'', School of Slavonic and East European Studies/Orbis Books 1988, ISBN 0 901149 32 2

'''Memoirs and fiction'''

*Michał Giedroyc, ''Crater's Edge: A Family's Epic Journey Through Wartime Russia'', Bene Factum Publishing Ltd (1 May 2010)
*Matthew Kelly, ''Finding Poland'', Jonathan Cape Ltd (4 Mar 2010)
*Michael Moran, ''A Country in the Moon: Travels in Search of the Heart of Poland'', Granta Books; Reprint edition (2 Mar 2009)
*Joanna Czechowska, ''The Black Madonna of Derby'', Silkmill Press 2008
*Andrew Tarnowski, ''The Last Mazurka: A Tale of War, Passion and Loss'', Aurum Press Ltd (9 May 2006)
*Kasimir Czerniak, Gabi Czerniak, William Czerniak-Jones, ''The Wisdom of Uncle Kasimir'', Bloomsbuy 2006
*Annette Kobak, ''Joe's War - My Father Decoded: A Daughter's Search for Her Father's War'', 2004
*Dr John Geller, ''Through Darkness To Dawn'', Veritas (1 Jan 1989)
*[[Denis Hills]], ''Return to Poland'', The Bodley Head Ltd; First Edition edition (28 Jan 1988)
*[[Slavomir Rawicz]], ''The Long Walk: The True Story of a Trek to Freedom'', Robinson Publishing (26 April 2007)

==External links==
* [http://www.emito.net Emito.net - UK's Polish Community Online]
* [http://www.orla.fm Anglo-Polish Radio ORLA.fm]
* [http://www.magazyn.goniec.com/ Polish Weekly Magazine in the UK]
* [http://www.goniec.com/ Portal for the Polish Minority in the UK]
* [http://www.dziennikpolski.co.uk/ The oldest Polish Newspaper in the UK - Polish Daily/Soldier's Daily]
* [http://www.london.polemb.net/index.php?document=18/ Polish Embassy in the UK, London]
* [http://www.leeds-manchester.pl/ Leeds-Manchester.pl - Portal for the Polish Community in Nothern England]
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2010/jan/17/eastern-european-uk-migrants Young, self-reliant, educated: portrait of UK's eastern European migrants ''The Guardian'']
* [http://www.opsi.gov.uk/RevisedStatutes/Acts/ukpga/1947/cukpga_19470019_en_1 Polish Resettlement Act, as revised]
* [http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/familyhistory/guide/migrantancestors/polish.htm The National Archives: Polish Resettlement]
* [http://www.zpwb.org.uk/ Federation of Poles in Great Britain]
* [http://www.posk.org/index_e.html POSK] Polish Social and Cultural Association
* [http://www.museumoflondon.org.uk/English/Collections/Onlineresources/RWWC/themes/1275/1197 Reassessing what we collect website – Polish London] History of Polish London with objects and images
* [http://www.wracajdopolski.pl Return to Poland - employers' website]
* [http://www.redclydeside.com/scotpolesintro.htm Polish Residents in Scotland, 1861-2001]

{{EuropeansinUK}}
{{Polish diaspora}}

[[Category:British people of Polish descent| ]]
[[Category:Poland–United Kingdom relations]]
[[Category:Polish minorities|British]]
[[Category:Polish communities|British]]
[[Category:Immigration to the United Kingdom by country of origin]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
