<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9428897" ns="0" title="Ubuntu Studio"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- If you update this article, please remember to update other Ubuntu derivatives, which include, but are not limited to: Ubuntu, Kubuntu, Edubuntu, Xubuntu, Gobuntu. --&gt;
{{Infobox OS
|name         = Ubuntu Studio
|logo         = [[File:Ubuntustudio v3 logo-alt.svg|200px|Logo]]
|screenshot   = [[File:UbuntuStudio910.png|300px]]
|caption      = Ubuntu Studio 10.04
|developer    = [[Canonical Ltd.]]&amp;nbsp;/ [[Ubuntu Foundation]] 
|family       = Variant of [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]]
|source_model = [[Open source]]
|latest_release_version = 11.10 (Oneiric Ocelot)
|latest_release_date    = {{release date|2011|04|29}}
|latest_test_version    = 
|latest_test_date       = 
|marketing_target    = Multimedia enthusiasts
|language            = [[English language|English]], [[French language|French]], [[Spanish language|Spanish]], [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]
|kernel_type         = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]] [[Linux kernel]]
|ui                  = [[GNOME]]
|license             = Mainly the [[GNU GPL]] / various others
|working_state       = Current
|supported_platforms = [[IA-32]], [[x86-64]]
|updatemodel     = 
|package_manager = [[Advanced Packaging Tool]] (APT)
|website         = [http://ubuntustudio.org/ ubuntustudio.org]
}}
[[File:Ubuntu studio login screen.png|thumb|The login screen of Ubuntu Studio 8.04]]

'''Ubuntu Studio''' is an officially recognized derivative&lt;ref name=&quot;Ubuntu Derivatives&quot;&gt;[http://www.ubuntu.com/products/whatisubuntu/derivatives Ubuntu Derivatives], Canonical Ltd., Retrieved on 24 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] [[Linux distribution]], which is explicitly geared to general [[multimedia]] production. The original version, based on Ubuntu 7.04, was released on May 10, 2007.

== Features ==
===Real-time kernel===
The real-time [[kernel (computing)|kernel]], first included with Ubuntu Studio 8.04, was modified for intensive audio, video or graphics work. The 8.10 release lacks this real-time kernel. It has been reimplemented in the 9.04 release and stabilized with the release of 9.10. 10.04, in contrast, does not include the real-time kernel by default. As of version 10.10, the real-time kernel is no longer available in the repositories.

Typically, computers used as audio workstations rely on hardware monitoring which may provide low latency, but does not allow the live signal to be manipulated beyond available hardware effects.  To manipulate a live signal, software processing of the signal is necessary, which most audio work stations can only achieve with latencies greater than several tens of milliseconds.  Thus, a notable advantage of the Linux real-time kernel is being able to achieve software processing with latencies well below the human perception threshold of 5 to 10ms.

The scheduler allows applications to request immediate [[CPU]] time, which can drastically reduce audio [[Latency (audio)|latency]]&lt;ref name=&quot;trumm&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | last=Trumm
 | first=Aaron
 | title=The Linux-Based Recording Studio
 | journal=Linux Journal
 | volume=2004
 | issue=121
 | year=2004
 | url=http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=982972.982977
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;. 
In 9.10, the &quot;Ubuntu Studio Controls&quot; provided under System&gt;Administration permit the user to &quot;Enable Nice,&quot; allowing the use of wireless networking and proprietary graphics cards drivers while maintaining low audio latency free of XRUNs (audio drop-outs) in JACK.  A more negative value entered for &quot;Nice&quot; reserves more CPU time for real-time audio processes.

===Appearance and sound theme===
Ubuntu Studio also includes custom artwork and a blue-on-black theme, as opposed to Ubuntu's default purple and orange.  As with the main distribution of Ubuntu, if an [[GPU|accelerated graphics card]] and appropriate driver are used, the advanced desktop effects can be enabled.  More advanced Compiz effects are available in the Synaptic Package Manager (i.e., Ubuntu repositories).  In Karmic 9.10, a fresh sound theme replaces the default Ubuntu theme, with a reverberating melody at startup, and an occasional knock or ping from a button or prompt.

===Access to Ubuntu repositories===
An important advantage of Ubuntu Studio over most other Linux distributions employing the real-time kernel is access to the same repositories available to the main Ubuntu distributions through the Update Manager, Synaptic Package Manager, as well as through the Add/Remove Applications prompt.  This allows for much more frequent operating system updates, and access to a much wider range of software. 

== Installation==
There is currently no [[Live Distro|live]] version available of Ubuntu Studio, and no graphical installer. In addition, the disk image is about 1.8 GB, too large to fit on a standard [[CD]], and as a result the recommended installation medium for Ubuntu Studio is a [[DVD]] or [[USB flash drive]]. Ubuntu Studio can also be installed on a pre-existing Ubuntu installation by installing the &quot;ubuntustudio-desktop&quot; package from [[Advanced Packaging Tool]].

In 9.10, the package &quot;ubuntustudio-audio,&quot; shown during installation (and also available in the Synaptic Package Manager), cannot be installed without a working Internet connection.

A readily available internet connection is required after installation to maintain system components.

== Software included ==
[[File:UbuntuStudio9.10_Multitasking.png|thumb|alt=Ubuntu Studio 9.10 screen shot|Screen shot of Ubuntu Studio 9.10 running JACK Audio Connection Kit - Qt GUI Interface 0.3.4, Ardour 2.8.2, Patchage 0.2.3, Hydrogen 0.9.3 and Blender.]]

===Audio===
* [[a2jmidid]] – a2jmidid is a daemon for exposing legacy ALSA sequencer applications in JACK MIDI system.
* [[Ardour (audio processor)|Ardour]] – a hard disk recorder and digital audio workstation application (Works with JACK).
* [[Audacious (software)|Audacious]] – a lightweight audio player.
* [[Audacity]] – a digital audio editor application.
* BEAST – music composition and modular synthesis application.
* [[Creox]] – A real-time guitar effects program (works with JACK).
* [[FluidSynth]] – Software Wavetable Synthesizer (Works with JACK). 
* [[Hydrogen (software)|Hydrogen]] – an advanced drum machine (Works with JACK).
* [[JACK Audio Connection Kit]] – a sound server daemon that provides low latency connections between applications for both audio and MIDI data.
* [[Jack Rack]] – Virtual rackmount of [[LADSPA]] DSP effects plugins (Works with JACK).  
* [[JAMin]] – the JACK Audio Connection Kit Audio Mastering interface (Works with JACK).
* [[LilyPond]] – a program for engraving sheet music
* [[Mixxx]] – a digital [[DJ]]-style mixing program
* [[MusE]] – a MIDI/Audio sequencer using [[JACK Audio Connection Kit|JACK]] and [[Advanced Linux Sound Architecture|ALSA]]
* [[MuseScore]] – a music scorewriter for Linux, Microsoft Windows and Mac
* [[Patchage]] – GUI access to patch MIDI and Audio software together for JACK. 
* [[Pure Data]] – a programming environment for multimedia (Works with Jack).
* [[Rosegarden]] – a digital audio workstation program (works with JACK). (Not included in latest release – it must be installed)
* [[Tapiir]] – a  software  multitap  delay  with realtime audio I/O. (works with JACK).
* [[Timemachine]] – Records the last 30 seconds of sound to the hard drive, so a 'one off' sound can be captured (Works with JACK).
* [[TiMidity++]] – a software synthesizer that is able to convert from MIDI to various formats.
* [[Xwax]] – a vinyl record emulator.
* [[ZynAddSubFX]] – a complex yet easy to use subtractive, additive, FM synthesizer with DSP effects, and exceptional software synthesizer  (Works with JACK).

===Video===
* [[PiTiVi]] – a video editing program (not included in latest release)
* [[Kino (software)|Kino]] – a non-linear digital video editor
* Stopmotion – a stop-motion animation movie creator
* [[VLC media player]] – a media player
* [[Xjadeo]] – a simple video player that gets sync from JACK transport

===Graphics===
* Agave – a color scheme generator
* [[Blender (software)|Blender]] – a 3D animation program
* [[Enblend]] – an image compositing program
* [[FontForge]] – a typeface (font) editor program
* [[GIMP]] – a raster graphics editor
* [[Hugin_(software) | Hugin]] – photo stitching and HDR merging program
* [[Inkscape]] – a vector graphics editor
* [[Scribus]] – a desktop publishing application
* [[Synfig]] – a 2D vector graphics and timeline-based animation program

==See also==
* [[64 Studio]] – a multimedia production-oriented distribution based on [[Debian]]
* [[Planet CCRMA]] – a set of [[Red Hat]] packages of multimedia production software
* [[Dyne:bolic]] – a multimedia creation oriented Live CD
* [[Puredyne]] – a multimedia oriented Live CD

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Ubuntu Studio}}
* [http://ubuntustudio.org/ Ubuntu Studio homepage]
* [https://help.ubuntu.com/community/UbuntuStudio/Applications Ubuntu Studio applications]
* [https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UbuntuStudio Ubuntu Wiki]
* [http://www.boingboing.net/2007/01/21/ubuntu-studio-linux.html Boing Boing - ''Ubuntu studio - Linux for multimedia creation''] (2007-01-21)
* {{DistroWatch|ubuntustudio|NAME=Ubuntu Studio}} listing of distributions and applications with links
* [http://linuxmusicians.com Linux Musicians community]

{{Ubuntu}}
{{Linux distributions}}
{{FOSS}}

[[Category:Ubuntu (operating system) derivatives]]
[[Category:Linux media creation distributions]]

[[ar:أوبونتو ستوديو]]
[[ast:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[bn:উবুন্টু স্টুডিও]]
[[ca:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[cs:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[da:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[de:Ubuntu#Ubuntu Studio]]
[[es:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[fr:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[ko:우분투 스튜디오]]
[[it:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[hu:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[nl:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[ja:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[no:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[nn:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[pl:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[pt:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[ro:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[ru:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[simple:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[sk:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[fi:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[sv:Ubuntu studio]]
[[tr:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[uk:Ubuntu Studio]]
[[zh:Ubuntu Studio]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
