<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9437281" ns="0" title="Parable of the assassin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Parable of the Assassin''' (also known as the ''Parable of the Killer''),  is a [[parable]] attributed to [[Jesus]].  However, it appears in none of the [[Canonical gospels]] of the [[New Testament]] but only in the non-canonical [[Gospel of Thomas]]. According to the [[Gospel of Thomas]] 98 Jesus said:
:''&quot;The kingdom of the father is like a certain man who wanted to kill a powerful man. In his own house he drew his sword and stuck it into the wall in order to find out whether his hand could carry through. Then he slew the powerful man.&quot;'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.gnosis.org/naghamm/gthlamb.html G. Thomas 98&lt;/ref&gt;

==Authenticity==
The scholars of the [[Jesus Seminar]] gave the parable of the assassin a &quot;pink&quot; rating, indicating 
that it is in their opinion probably, but not certainly, an authentic saying of Jesus.  They were influenced by parallels with the parables of the warring king &lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Luke|14:28-30||}}&lt;/ref&gt; and of the tower builder&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Luke|14:31-32}}&lt;/ref&gt; found in the [[Gospel of Luke]] (see [[Counting the cost]]), and by the &quot;scandalous nature of the image.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Robert Walter Funk and Roy W. Hoover, ''The Five Gospels: What Did Jesus Really Say? the Search for the Authentic Words of Jesus'', HarperCollins, 1997, pp. 524-5&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[Robert Funk]], &quot;[a]ttributing a parable to Jesus not attested in the canonical gospels and known only for a few years was an act of courage that demanded careful deliberation&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 525&quot;&gt;Robert Walter Funk and Roy W. Hoover, ''The Five Gospels: What Did Jesus Really Say? the Search for the Authentic Words of Jesus'', HarperCollins, 1997, [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN006063040X&amp;id=SRI-c0Pf3soC&amp;pg=RA1-PA525&amp;lpg=RA1-PA525&amp;ots=vP-Bse1Hs8&amp;dq=%22parable+of+the+assassin%22&amp;sig=NiYQB6gaCpUu-I-0f2ErfFbcaDE#PRA1-PA525,M1 p. 525]&lt;/ref&gt;.  This decision by the Seminar has been criticized for inconsistency, since the parallel parable of the warring king in Luke was ''not'' given a pink rating.&lt;ref&gt;[[Craig A. Evans]], Bruce D. Chilton, ''Authenticating the Words of Jesus'', Brill Academic Publishers, 2002, [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0391041630&amp;id=Y96yVkPLeioC&amp;pg=RA2-PA411&amp;lpg=RA2-PA411&amp;ots=H4i_fUkshX&amp;dq=%22parable+of+the+assassin%22&amp;sig=-TM9AM60786w4cZIOnSdEbQSWUw#PRA2-PA411,M1 p. 411]&lt;/ref&gt;  The authenticity of this parable has been attacked on the grounds that Jesus would not use a parable that glorifies [[murder]], and because of its use of the phrase &quot;the kingdom of the father&quot; which is not found in the canonical gospels.

==Meaning==
Like the Lucan parables of the warring king and the tower, this parable seems to concern &quot;estimating the cost of an act or the capability to perform it successfully.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=December 2009|reason = dead link: http://www.bibletexts.com/texts/parables.htm#assassin }} In Mark 7:21–23, Jesus explains the idea of evil being rehearsed before taking place. &quot;For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders, thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, lasciviousness, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, foolishness: all these evil things come from within, and defile the man.&quot;{{Or|date=November 2007}} According to some of the fellows of the Jesus Seminar, &quot;the story line of the parable originally had to do with Davidic reversal, as in David and Goliath: the little guy bests the big guy by taking the precautions a prudent person would take before encountering the village bully&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;p. 525&quot;/&gt; A similar message can been found in the [[parable of the strong man]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Parables of Jesus}}

[[Category:Parables of Jesus|Assassin, Parable of the]]

[[it:Parabola dell'assassino]]
[[sr:Прича о убици моћника]]
[[sh:Priča o ubici moćnika]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
