<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9438075" ns="0" title="Scott Grainger, Sr."><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=May 2008}}
{{Primarysources|date=January 2009}}
{{Notability|date=January 2009}}
{{Infobox soap character
| name           = Scott Grainger Sr.
| series         = The Young and the Restless
| portrayer      = [[Peter Barton (actor)|Peter Barton]]
| first          = May 1988 &lt;small&gt;(on ''[[The Young and the Restless|Y&amp;R]]'')&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;November 1993 &lt;small&gt;(on ''[[The Bold and the Beautiful|B&amp;B]]'')&lt;/small&gt;
| last           = November 1993&lt;br&gt; &lt;small&gt;(on ''[[The Young and the Restless|Y&amp;R]]'')&lt;/small&gt; and (on ''[[The Bold and the Beautiful|B&amp;B]]'')&lt;/small&gt;
| cause          = Died from a terminal illness
| creator        = [[William J. Bell]]
| image1         = 
| caption1       = 
| nickname       =  
| gender         = Male
| born           = 
| death          = November 1993
| age            = 
| occupation     = Medical Doctor
| title          = Dr.
| residence      = 
| parents        = James Grainger &lt;small&gt;(father)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Unnamed woman &lt;small&gt;(mother)&lt;/small&gt;
| siblings       = [[Christine Blair]] &lt;small&gt;(paternal half-sister)&lt;/small&gt;
| spouse         = [[Lauren Fenmore]] &lt;small&gt;(divorced; 1989–1990, remarried at his death; 1992–1993)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Sheila Carter]] &lt;small&gt;(annulled; 1990–1993)&lt;/small&gt;
| romances       = [[Christine Blair]] &lt;br&gt; [[Nina Webster]]
| children       = [[Scott Grainger, Jr.|Scott Grainger Jr.]] &lt;small&gt;(son, with [[Lauren Fenmore Baldwin]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt; Dylan Fenmore &lt;small&gt;(thought-to-be son, with [[Lauren Fenmore Baldwin]]; deceased)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt; Unnamed child &lt;small&gt;(son, with [[Sheila Carter]], deceased)&lt;/small&gt;
| grandchildren  =  
| grandparents   = 
| aunts/uncles   = 
| cousins        = 
| nieces/nephews = 
| color         = gray
| color text    = black
}}
'''Dr. Scott Grainger Sr.''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[United States|American]] [[soap opera]] ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'', portrayed by actor [[Peter Barton (actor)|Peter Barton]] from 1988 to 1993. The character crossed over to ''[[The Bold and the Beautiful]]'' briefly in 1993.

==Character==
Scott entered the picture as he was doctor working on Jessica Blair, who had AIDS. In 1989, [[Christine Blair]] ([[Lauralee Bell]]) fell in love with her mother's [[physician|doctor]], Scott Grainger, and they became engaged. The engagement was brought to an end when Christine discovered that Scott was her half-brother, as the result of an affair between Christine's mother, Jessica (Rebecca Street), and Scott's father, Jim ([[John Phillip Law]]). While Christine was disappointed, she was thrilled to be able to meet her real father, Jim.

Scott began dating [[Lauren Fenmore Baldwin|Lauren Fenmore]] ([[Tracey E. Bregman|Tracey Bregman]]). Christine was raped by Derek Stuart ([[Ken Olandt]]) and pressed charges against him. Infuriated by the prospect of a long prison sentence, Derek cornered Christine with a gun, but as he pulled the trigger, Scott arrived and jumped in front of Christine, taking the bullet for her. Scott's near death experience prompted him to propose to Lauren. They married in 1990, despite Lauren's feelings for ex-husband [[Paul Williams (The Young and the Restless)|Paul Williams]] ([[Doug Davidson]]).

Lauren suffered a [[miscarriage]]. Scott was bothered, as he was unaware that Lauren was even pregnant. He turned to nurse [[Sheila Carter]] ([[Kimberlin Brown]]) for comfort. Scott and Lauren decided to give their marriage another try, but both Lauren and Sheila then announced that they were pregnant with Scott's child. Sheila's baby was [[stillbirth|stillborn]]. Desperate to have Scott's child, she stole Lauren's newborn son and named him [[Scott Grainger, Jr.|Scott &quot;Scotty&quot; Grainger, Jr.]], replacing him with a [[black market]] baby, who Lauren named Dylan.

Scott left Lauren and married Sheila. Sheila's mother, Molly (Marilyn Alex), discovered the truth about the &quot;baby switch&quot; and decided to tell Lauren. However, on her way to Lauren's office, Molly suffered a debilitating [[stroke]], which left her [[mute (disorder)|mute]]. Lauren began to visit Molly in hospital, so Sheila formed an elaborate scheme to make it look like her mother had committed [[suicide]]. She then had Molly committed to a [[psychiatric hospital]]. Lauren's &quot;son&quot;, Dylan, soon died of [[meningitis]].

Worried that Molly would tell Lauren the truth, Sheila kidnapped both her mother and Lauren and held them hostage at a [[farmhouse]] out of town. Intending to kill them both, Sheila confessed to switching the babies. She then set fire to the farmhouse, with Lauren and Molly barely escaping. Sheila was pronounced dead and Lauren returned to Scott and Scotty. 

Shortly after, Scott was diagnosed with a terminal illness, which he kept secret from Lauren.  When Lauren discovered Sheila to be alive and well in Los Angeles, she persuaded Scott to vacation with her on Catalina Island, so she could humiliate Sheila in front of her new husband [[Eric Forrester]] ([[John McCook]]).  Lauren was later amazed to learn that Scott already knew that Sheila was alive, as she had visited him in the hospital shortly before.  Lauren persuaded him to talk to Eric about Sheila, but an ill Scott died before he could say anything.  His dying wish was for Lauren to move on with her life and to give Sheila a second chance.

{{The Young and the Restless}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Grainger, Scott}}
[[Category:The Young and the Restless characters]]
[[Category:Fictional doctors]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
