<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="946469" ns="0" title="Marian University (Indiana)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About||the Fond du Lac, Wisconsin, school of the same name|Marian University (Wisconsin)}}
{{advert|date=November 2010}}

{{Infobox university
|name=Marian University (formerly Marian College)
|motto=''Sedes Sapientiae''&lt;br/&gt;Seat of Wisdom
|type=[[private university|private]] [[coeducational]] [[liberal arts]]
|endowment=$7.8 million{{ref_label|endowment|1|1}}
|established=1851 ([[#History|details]])
|city=[[Indianapolis, Indiana|Indianapolis]]
|state=[[Indiana|IN]]
|country=[[USA]]
|faculty=81 full time, 63 part-time
|president=Daniel J. Elsener
|students=2440
|campus=urban
|free_label=Athletics
|free=17 [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]] teams and 1 [[NCCA]] team,&lt;br&gt;called Knights
|colors=[[Blue]] and [[Gold]]
|affiliations=&lt;br/&gt;[[Sisters of St. Francis Oldenburg]]
|website=[http://www.marian.edu www.marian.edu]
}}
'''Marian University''' is a Roman Catholic university in Indianapolis Indiana.

==About==
Marian University, sponsored by the Sisters of St. Francis in Oldenburg, Indiana, traces its roots to their founding in 1851. The Oldenburg Franciscans established schools and a teacher-training school to ensure that their members were good teachers. 

Marian University is located about four miles northwest of [[downtown Indianapolis]]. Marian University has more than 2,200 full- and part-time students from the United States and 12 other countries with a student-faculty ratio of 15.5:1.

==History==
'''1851 – Teacher Training'''

Formed in 1851 in the liberal arts tradition as a teacher training school by the Sisters of St. Francis, Oldenburg to serve the educational needs of the German-Catholic residents of southern Indiana. Under the direction of Father Francis Joseph Rudolph and Mother Theresa Hackelmeier, teachers were trained at Oldenburg for more than a decade before Indiana adopted its first tax-supported normal school.

'''1936 – The Beginning'''

Originally known as St. Francis Normal, the school became a four-year, state-approved institution which merged with Immaculate Conception Junior College to form Marian College. In November 1936, the Sisters of St. Francis purchased the former James Allison estate, “Riverdale,” located in Indianapolis, as a site for Marian College.

'''1937 – Marian College Is Born'''

In 1937, the college moved to Indianapolis under the direction of Mother M. Clarissa Dillhoff, after securing a state charter and purchasing the Riverdale estate in 1936. Allison Mansion became the new location of Marian College. The building housed the library, administrative offices, classrooms, and sleeping quarters for the Sisters. Classes began September 15, 1937.

'''1948 – Expansion, Co-Education, and Accreditation'''

Success brought a need for expansion and, in 1948 the college began an expansion program that included the addition of Clare Hall, the Gymnasium, and Marian Hall. In 1954, as the new Marian Hall was completed, the school became the first co-educational Catholic college in Indiana. Two years later, the North Central Association accredited Marian College.

'''1970 – Growth Continued'''

In 1970, a new {{convert|58000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} library was completed.  It was designed by [[Woollen, Molzan and Partners]].

'''1976 – Accreditation For Teachers and Nurses'''

The National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education formally accepted all teacher education programs of the college in
1976. The Indiana State Board of Nursing approved the associate level nursing curriculum in 1977 and the baccalaureate program in
1987. The National League of Nursing has accredited both programs—the associate in 1986 and the baccalaureate in 1992.

'''2000 – Marian’s Adult Programs'''

Marian's Adult Programs (MAP) offers bachelor and associate degrees in business.

'''2001'''

On November 2, 2001, Daniel J. Elsener was inaugurated as Marian College's eighth president.

'''2009 – Marian College Becomes Marian University'''

On July 1, 2009, Marian College became Marian University. Over the past several years, the college grew and progressed through expansions of the academic curriculum; enhancing the faith dimension on campus the addition of a football team and marching band; and adding and renovating buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marian.edu/Pages/news.aspx?newsid=416}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

'''2010 – Marian University Announces College of Osteopathic Medicine'''

On January 15, 2010, Marian University announced plans to begin a college of osteopathic medicine; the first in Indiana due to the generosity of an anonymous donor’s $30 million pledge.

'''2011'''

On August 1, 2011 Greg Ballard, Mayor of the City of Indianapolis declared it &quot;President Daniel J. Elsener Day&quot; in the city. The proclamation came on the 10-year anniversary of President Elsener's service to Marian University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marian.edu/NewsDocuments/Daniel%20Elsener%20Marian%20University%2010th%20Anniversary%20Day%202011.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 23, 2011 the new school of osteopathic medicine is officially during the groundbreaking ceremony being named after the anonymous donor, AIT Labs CEO Michael A. Evans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marian.edu/Pages/news.aspx?NewsID=560}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
{{peacock|section|date=February 2011}}
Marian University is dedicated to teaching and learning in the Franciscan and liberal arts traditions. Specifically, in the Franciscan school of thought and spirit, education is based on the values of dignity of the individual, peace and justice, reconciliation, and responsible stewardship. Marian University, educates all students in the liberal arts tradition, emphasizing an education of the mind, body, and spirit as well as through multi-department general education requirements.

'''Accounting Program'''

Marian University’s accounting program has a statewide reputation of excellence{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} with a 100 percent employment rate after graduation{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}, due in large part to the internship/co-op programs. These programs are designed to enrich and supplement academic study with the application of professional work experience. The programs are part-time and full-time paid positions for which students can earn up to 24 semester hours of academic credit. The programs can be completed within the four-year academic schedule, rather than the usual five or more years required by some colleges and universities. Upon graduation, many Marian University students are offered permanent, full-time professional positions with their internship employers, or as a result of their experiences.

'''Green Chemistry'''

Marian University launched its green chemistry program in 2003 when Dr. Carl Lecher joined the faculty. The program interlinks undergraduate student research with the first comprehensive, green organic chemistry laboratory curriculum in the state.

'''Speech Team'''

Marian University is one of a small number of Catholic universities with an active speech team. The team’s faith-based approach to forensics emphasizes self-expression, community-building, and horizon-broadening as paths to spiritual maturity across a diversity of religious traditions.

The team travels to nearly 12 tournaments each year, plus a week-long trip to the National Forensic Association’s Individual Events Tournament in April. At tournaments, students compete in a variety of events such as impromptu speaking, persuasive speaking, and dramatic interpretation. On February 20, 2010, the team claimed first place over-all at the state tournament.

'''Teacher Training'''

Marian University offers more ways to earn a teaching license than any other institution in the state{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} via [http://www.marian.edu/Education/Programs/Transition/Pages/TeachforAmerica.aspx Teach for America], [http://www.marian.edu/Education/Programs/Transition/Pages/ITF.aspx Indianapolis Teaching Fellows], traditional education program, [http://www.marian.edu/Education/Programs/MAT/Pages/default.aspx Master’s Bridge to Teaching], Master of Arts in Teaching program, and the [http://www.marian.edu/Education/Programs/AlternativeLicensure/Pages/ACTION.aspx ACTION program]. Marian University is one of the few universities to offer [http://www.nativitymiguelschools.org/ Nativity Miguel Network] teacher training and the [http://www.marian.edu/Pages/news.aspx?NewsID=475 Leadership Academy for Principals].

More than 2,200 full- and part-time students from the United States and 12 other countries with a student-faculty ratio of 15.5:1.

Marian University is organized into five schools with 36 majors and 37 minors:
* [http://www.marian.edu/Business/Pages/default.aspx Clark W. Byrum School of Business]
* [http://www.marian.edu/education/Pages/default.aspx School of Education]
* [http://www.marian.edu/LiberalArts/Pages/default.aspx School of Liberal Arts]
* [http://www.marian.edu/MathandScience/Pages/default.aspx School of Mathematics and Sciences]
* [http://www.marian.edu/Nursing/Pages/default.aspx School of Nursing]

The university also offers accelerated degree programs in business for adults through Marian’s Adult Programs (MAP).

==Student life==
The Student Government of Marian University (SGMU) is actively involved with campus events such as homecoming and the fall festival. Intramural sports are popular, especially basketball, flag football, and ultimate frisbee. The campus recently renovated its dining hall and built a new music building. The performing arts are growing on campus with student plays and other theatrical performances, [[Marian University Marching Band|marching band]], and a speech team which won the state championship and placed 10th in Division I at the national forensics championship in 2010. From 2004 until 2011, Marian University was home to the Booth Tarkington Civic Theatre, a semi-professional community theatre located on campus.

There are nearly [http://www.marian.edu/CampusLife/Pages/StudentActivities.aspx 30 student run clubs and organizations] at Marian University, including [http://collegementors.org/ College Mentors for Kids], [[Pax Christi]] (peace and justice), [[Society for Human Resource Management|Society of Human Resource Management]] (business), Marian University Student Nurses’ Association (MUSNA) (nursing), [[Kappa Delta Pi]], and the Green Life club (general).

Marian University has the highest percentage (21.6) of minority students on campus of any college or university in Indiana, with the exception of Martin University, which is historically a black institution.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}

The university also has attached to it, though not on the campus property,  a college seminary for Catholic seminarians, operated by the Archdiocese of Indianapolis. Approximately 20-30 young men, who are also Marian students, live at the seminary and receive formation there.

==Athletics==
Marian University is nationally known{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} for its cycling team, which practices and competes at the Major Taylor Velodrome. The cycling team is a member of the National Collegiate Cycling Association, NCCA.

Marian University’s cycling team has won 13 national track championships in Division I and is widely regarded as one of the most prestigious programs in the nation. In the 2009-10 seasons, Marian University won both USA Cycling’s Collegiate Track National Championships in 2009 and USA Cycling’s Collegiate Road Championship title in 2010. The cycling team has won a total of 14 national championship titles after winning the 2010 Track National Championships.

Marian University has 16 other NAIA teams for men and women, including a golf and softball team that finished their 2010 seasons as 12th and 14th in the nation in Division II respectively. Marian University is also home to the Mid-Central College Conference champion women’s soccer team. Marian University also recently added a football team in 2008, as well as competitive cheerleading. Men’s and women’s bowling will start in fall of 2010. The school began a football program in 2007 under head coach [[Ted Karras Jr.]]  The football program competes in the Mideast League of the [[Mid-States Football Association]].

* 23 All-Conference selections
* 309 All MCC First Team Honors
* 162 Daktronics NAIA Scholar Athletes
* 25 NAIA All Americans
* 5 NAIA Champions of Character Award recipients
* 6 NAIA Region VIII Player of the Year
* 1 NAIA Region VIII Player of the Year
* 37 MCC championships
* 25 MCC Coach of the Year Honors
* 14 MCC Players of the Year
* 14 USA Cycling Collegiate National Championships

'''Mascot'''

The Marian University mascot is Knightro, the Knight. A medieval knight’s education consisted of activities to educate the mind, body, and spirit.

==See also==
*[[The Indiana College Mathematics Competition]]
*[[Indianapolis Art Center]] provides educational programming for MU

==References==
{{Reflist}}
#{{note_label|endowment||1}}{{note_label|||endowment}} {{cite web | title=America's Best Colleges 2006 | publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report | accessdate=2006-02-03| url=http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_1821_brief.php}}

==External links==
*[http://www.marian.edu/ Official website]
*[http://athletics.marian.edu Official athletics website]
*[http://www.marian.edu/map/forms/campus_map.pdf Campus map]

{{Mid-Central College Conference}}
{{Mid-States Football Association navbox}}
{{Association of Franciscan Colleges and Universities}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Indianapolis}}
{{Indiana Colleges and Universities}}

{{Coord missing|Indiana}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1851]]
[[Category:Franciscan universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indianapolis, Indiana]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1936]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
