<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="947583" ns="0" title="Hogwarts staff"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}
[[File:HogwartsTeachers.jpg|thumb|300 px|Four Hogwarts staff members in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]''. From left to right: [[Miriam Margolyes]] as Pomona Sprout, [[Gemma Jones]] as Poppy Pomfrey, [[Jim Broadbent]] as Horace Slughorn, and [[David_Bradley_(actor)|David Bradley]] as Argus Filch.]]
The following fictional characters are staff members and denizens of [[Hogwarts]] in the ''[[Harry Potter]]'' books written by [[J. K. Rowling]].

==The staff and their positions==
{|Class=wikitable
!style=&quot;width:12em;&quot;|Character
!style=&quot;width:12em;&quot;|Subject/Position
!Background
|-
| Bathsheda Babbling
| [[Hogwarts#Ancient Runes|Ancient Runes]]
| The Ancient Runes teacher during the entire series. The character is never mentioned in the books nor appears in the films, but Rowling has named her on her official site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hp-lexicon.org/about/sources/jkr.com/jkr-com-trans-jottings1.html J.K.Rowling – Official Site &quot;More idle jottings (Page 1)&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Cuthbert Binns
| [[Hogwarts#History of Magic|History of Magic]]
| The History of Magic teacher during the entire series. Binns has the distinction of being the only teacher at Hogwarts who is a [[Ghosts (Harry Potter)|ghost]]. It is said that one day he took a nap in a chair in the teachers’ lounge/staff room and died in his sleep; later, he simply got up to go to teach his next class and &quot;left his body behind&quot;. His lessons are said to be notoriously boring and it is mentioned that the most exciting thing that ever happens in his class is his &quot;entering through the blackboard&quot;. As a ghost he seems unaware of his change from living to dead. In the second book it is he who describes the legend of the [[Chamber of Secrets]] when asked by the students, but in the film version it is McGonagall, as Binns does not appear in any of the films. In the attraction, Harry Potter and the Forbidden Journey at Universal Studios Florida, Professor Binns was mentioned during the walk through but was never seen.   
|-
| Charity Burbage
| [[Hogwarts#Muggle Studies|Muggle Studies]]
| The Muggle Studies teacher from Harry's first to sixth years, but first appears in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''. Because her teachings about Muggles gave an overall favourable impression of them, going so far as to write an editorial praising Muggles in the ''[[Daily Prophet]]'', she runs afoul of the Death Eaters, whose philosophy asserts the supremacy of pure-bloods. She becomes a prisoner of [[Lord Voldemort]], who tortures, kills, and feeds her to [[Nagini (Harry Potter)|Nagini]]. In the film adaptation of ''Deathly Hallows'', Charity is portrayed by [[Carolyn Pickles]].
|-
| [[Alecto and Amycus Carrow]]
| [[Hogwarts#Muggle Studies|Muggle Studies]] / [[Defence Against the Dark Arts|Dark Arts]]
| The Carrows are sibling [[Death Eater]]s, posted as Deputy Headmaster and Deputy Headmistress to Hogwarts to keep control over the school, maintain a reign of fear and to take charge of punishment under Snape's regime as Headmaster in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''. Alecto Carrow taught Muggle Studies, however it should be noted that instead of encouraging increased relations with muggles, they were taught ideologies that muggles were no better than animals. Amycus Carrow taught Defence Against the Dark Arts, however it is noted that there was no defence involved because they had changed the name to Dark Arts, so Amycus frequently taught them the [[Unforgivable Curses]] and openly encouraged students to practice these on their classmates and called the post &quot;Dark Arts&quot;.
|-
| [[Albus Dumbledore]]
| Headmaster
| The Headmaster of Hogwarts since a few decades before Harry's birth until Harry's sixth year at Hogwarts when Dumbledore is killed by [[Severus Snape]]. Dumbledore served previously as Transfiguration teacher during [[Tom Riddle]]'s time at Hogwarts and as Head of Gryffindor House and Deputy Headmaster.  He is played by Richard Harris in Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone and in Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets. Dumbledore is played in subsequent Harry Potter films by Michael Gambon. Dumbledore locates his old friend and colleague Horace Slughorn and uses Harry to encourage him to return to Hogwarts to teach Potions. In Half Blood Prince, Dumbledore is murdered by Snape and is buried on the Grounds of Hogwarts. Students, teachers, Ministry of Magic officials, centaurs including Firenze, merpeople, Hogwarts' Ghosts, members of the Order of the Phoenix and many more attended his funeral. 
|-
| [[#Argus Filch|Argus Filch]]
| Caretaker
| The caretaker of Hogwarts during the entire series. He is a Squib.
|-
| [[Magical creatures in Harry Potter#Firenze|Firenze]]
| [[Hogwarts#Divination|Divination]]
| One of two Divination teachers starting from ''Order of the Phoenix''. A [[Magical creatures in Harry Potter#Centaurs|centaur]], he previously lived with his herd in the [[Hogwarts#Forbidden Forest|Forbidden Forest]]. In the ''Order of the Phoenix'', after Sybill Trelawney is fired by Dolores Umbridge, he is hired by Dumbledore to teach Divination in her stead. The other centaurs found this dishonourable and sacked him from the herd. By ''Half-Blood Prince'', Trelawney was reinstated as Divination teacher, but due to Firenze's situation with his herd, Dumbledore had them teach Divination concurrently.
|-
| [[#Filius Flitwick|Filius Flitwick]]
| [[Hogwarts#Charms|Charms]]
| The Charms teacher and Head of Ravenclaw House during the entire series; he is also shown to be the director of the school's choir in the film adaptation of [[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban|Prisoner of Azkaban]] and [[Harry Potter and the Order of Phoenix|Order of Phoenix]]..
|-
| Wilhelmina Grubbly-Plank
| [[Hogwarts#Care of Magical Creatures|Care of Magical Creatures]]
| A substitute Care of Magical Creatures teacher. She first appears in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'', taking lessons when Hagrid is unable to teach, and substitutes again in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'' when Hagrid is away on a mission for the Order of the Phoenix. The character was played by [[Apple Brook]] in the film ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix (film)|Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]''.
|-
| [[Rubeus Hagrid]]
| [[Hogwarts#Care of Magical Creatures|Care of Magical Creatures]]
| The Half-giant [[gamekeeper]], Keeper of Keys and Grounds, and, from Harry's third year at Hogwarts, the Care of Magical Creatures professor.
|-
| Rolanda Hooch
| [[Hogwarts#Flying|Flying]]
| The Quidditch referee during the entire series, and flying instructor for first year students. She is described as having short, spiky, grey hair, with piercing yellow hawk-like eyes, usually hidden behind goggles. Her expertise is called on along with Professor Flitwick's to test Harry's Firebolt broom for dark magic. [[Zoë Wanamaker]] portrays Madam Hooch in the [[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone (film)|''Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone'' film]].
|-
| Silvanus Kettleburn
| [[Hogwarts#Care of Magical Creatures|Care of Magical Creatures]]
| The Care of Magical Creatures teacher since [[Armando Dippet]] (Dumbledore's predecessor) was headmaster. He eventually retires to &quot;spend time with his remaining limbs&quot;, and his place is eventually taken by Hagrid in ''Prisoner of Azkaban''.
|-
| [[#Gilderoy Lockhart|Gilderoy Lockhart]]
| [[Defence Against the Dark Arts]]
| The Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher in ''[[Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets]]'' (Harry's second year at Hogwarts).
|-
| [[Remus Lupin]]
| [[Defence Against the Dark Arts]]
| The Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher in ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]'' (Harry's third year at Hogwarts).
|-
| [[#Minerva McGonagall|Minerva McGonagall]]
| [[Hogwarts#Transfiguration|Transfiguration]] / Headmistress / Head of Gryffindor House and Deputy Headmistress 
| The Transfiguration teacher and Head of Gryffindor House during the entire series. Deputy Headmistress during the first six novels. Temporary Headmistress of Hogwarts when Dumbledore was sacked in ''Chamber of Secrets''. Temporary Headmistress after Dumbledore's death in ''Half-Blood Prince''. Permanent Headmistress after the Battle of Hogwarts until sometime before the epilogue. McGonagall was to take Dumbledore's place as Headmaster but Minister Pius Thicknesse appointed Severus Snape to Headmaster of the Hogwarts School and after Snape died, McGonagall was appointed to permanent Headmistress of the School. 
|-
| [[Alastor Moody]]
| [[Defence Against the Dark Arts]]
| The Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'' (Harry's fourth year at Hogwarts). It transpires at the end of the book that Moody had been impersonated by [[Barty Crouch, Jr]]. It has therefore been Crouch that has been teaching at Hogwarts for that year; however it is told that the opinions and techniques are similar between individuals.
|-
| Irma Pince
| Librarian
| The librarian of Hogwarts during the entire series. She is compared to an &quot;underfed vulture&quot;, and is very possessive and protective with the library books. The character was portrayed by [[Sally Mortemore]] in the film adaptation of the second book.
|-
| [[#Poppy Pomfrey|Poppy Pomfrey]]
| Matron
| The Matron and nurse in charge of the hospital wing during the entire series.
|-
| [[#Quirinus Quirrell|Quirinus Quirrell]]
| [[Defence Against the Dark Arts]]
| The Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher in ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'' (Harry's first year at Hogwarts).
|-
| Aurora Sinistra
| [[Hogwarts#Astronomy|Astronomy]]
| The Astronomy teacher during the entire series. Sinistra assists Professor Flitwick in moving a petrified [[Justin Finch-Fletchley]] to the hospital wing in ''Chamber of Secrets''. She attends the Yule Ball in Harry's fourth year with the fake Mad-Eye Moody.
|-
| [[#Horace Slughorn|Horace Slughorn]]
| [[Hogwarts#Potions|Potions Master and Head of Slytherin House]]
| The Potions master during ''Half-Blood Prince'' and ''Deathly Hallows''. Head of Slytherin House in ''Deathly Hallows''. Slughorn had served as Potions master and Head of Slytherin during various decades prior to Harry's birth, at least since Tom Riddle's time at Hogwarts and left the position in the 1997 - 1998 school year after the Battle of Hogwarts.
|-
| [[Severus Snape]]
| [[Hogwarts#Potions|Potions Master]] / [[Defence Against the Dark Arts]] / Headmaster and Head of Slytherin House. 
| The Potions master from Harry's first to fifth years. Head of Slytherin House from Harry's first to sixth years. The Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher in ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'' (Harry's sixth year at Hogwarts). When at Dumbledore's request, Snape kills him at the end of ''Half-Blood Prince'', he flees his post at Hogwarts but returns in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'' as Headmaster having been appointed by the Minister for Magic, Pius Thicknesse (who was controlled by Voldemort) until he is killed by Voldemort in the final chapters of ''Deathly Hallows''.
|-
| [[#Pomona Sprout|Pomona Sprout]]
| [[Hogwarts#Herbology|Herbology]]
| The Herbology teacher and Head of Hufflepuff House during the entire series. Her position is eventually taken by [[Neville Longbottom]] who, by the time of the epilogue, is said to be the Herbology teacher.
|-
| [[#Sybill Trelawney|Sybill Trelawney]]
| [[Hogwarts#Divination|Divination]]
| The Divination teacher from 1980 (Harry's birth year) until ''Order of the Phoenix'', when she is fired by Umbridge. Trelawney returns to the work in ''Half-Blood Prince'' and ''Deathly Hallows'', sharing the position with Firenze.
|-
| [[Dolores Umbridge]]
| [[Defence Against the Dark Arts]] / Hogwarts High Inquisitor/Headmistress
| The Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'' (Harry's fifth year at Hogwarts). She was appointed by the Ministry of Magic to address the rumours concerning Voldemort's return that extended from there the previous summer. Umbridge extracted control, becoming Hogwarts' first and only High Inquisitor, and even appointing herself Headmistress, despite not being able to enter Dumbledore's office.
|-
| Septima Vector
| [[Hogwarts#Arithmancy|Arithmancy]]
| The Arithmancy teacher during the entire series, known to give her students large amounts of homework. She is almost knocked over by a distraught [[Rubeus Hagrid]] in ''the Order of the Phoenix''.
|}

==Notable teachers and staff members==
The following are notable teachers and staff members that do not have their own articles or that are not listed in other articles.

===Argus Filch===
'''Argus Filch''' is the caretaker of Hogwarts. While he is not an evil character, he is ill-tempered, which makes him very unpopular with the student body, and occasionally with other staff. His knowledge of the secrets and short-cuts of the castle is almost unparalleled, except perhaps by the [[Weasley twins]], and other users of the [[Marauder's Map]]. He tends to favour almost sadistically harsh punishments, leading to his alliance with [[Dolores Umbridge]]. He has an obsessive dislike of mud, animate toys, and all other things that might interfere with his creation of an immaculately clean and orderly Hogwarts.

Filch is revealed to be a [[Blood purity (Harry Potter)#Squibs|Squib]] in ''[[Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets]]'' when [[Harry Potter (character)|Harry Potter]] accidentally discovers that he is trying to teach himself basic magic from a ''Kwikspell'' correspondence course. Nonetheless, Filch is at least able to use wizardry devices that have their own innate magic, such as the [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Secrecy Sensor|Secrecy Sensor]] used in ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]''. It is hinted that his dislike of students may stem from his disappointment and jealousy at not being able to do magic. In ''the Half Blood Prince'', [[Harry Potter (character)|Harry Potter]] and [[Hermione Granger]] suspect that he is in a relationship with Irma Pince, the librarian at [[Hogwarts]]. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', the final book, when the school starts preparing itself for the Battle of Hogwarts, Filch is seen grumbling that students are out of bed. He is later seen overseeing the evacuation of younger students.

Filch has a cat named '''Mrs. Norris''' to whom he has a particular and possessive attachment. She acts as a hallway monitor or spy for Filch. If she observes students engaging in suspicious activity or out of bed after curfew, she finds Filch and he arrives in seconds. She has been known to follow [[Hagrid]] everywhere he goes in the school, apparently under Filch's orders. According to [[J.K. Rowling]], there is nothing particularly magical about Mrs. Norris, other than her being &quot;just an intelligent (and unpleasant) cat.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/rumours_view.cfm?id=40 JKRowling.com – Rumors section: ''Mrs. Norris is an unregistered Animagus'']&lt;/ref&gt; It's the ambition of many Hogwarts students to &quot;give her a good kick&quot;. In the ''Chamber of Secrets'' incident, Mrs. Norris is temporarily petrified by the [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Basilisk|Basilisk]], which causes Filch extreme distress.

[[David Bradley (actor)|David Bradley]] portrays Filch in the [[Harry Potter (film series)|film series]]. Mrs. Norris was played by a [[Maine Coon]] cat named Peebles.

===Filius Flitwick===
'''Filius Flitwick''' is the [[Hogwarts#Charms|Charms]] Master at Hogwarts and the head of [[Ravenclaw]], and is described as being very short. In ''Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone'' he uses his magical skills to help decorate the Great Hall for Christmas. He is also one of the teachers who casts spells to guard the [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Philosopher's Stone|Philosopher's Stone]] by putting charms on a hundred keys so they can fly, making it difficult to find the key to the door leading to the next chamber.

During Harry's second year, Flitwick helps Professor Sinistra carry a [[Petrifaction in mythology and fiction|petrified]] [[Justin Finch-Fletchley]] to the hospital wing. He teaches the front doors to recognise a picture of [[Sirius Black]] after his second break-in in ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]''. He helps patrol the perimeter of the maze for the third task of the [[Triwizard Tournament]] held in Harry's fourth year. He eventually removes most of the swamp that is created within the school by [[Fred and George Weasley]] in ''Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix'', though he previously leaves the swamp untouched to annoy Professor Umbridge. He does however, choose to leave a small patch of it behind, because he thinks it is &quot;a good bit of magic&quot; and a tribute to the Weasley twins. Near the end of ''Half-Blood Prince'', Flitwick is sent by Professor McGonagall to ask Snape to come to the aid of the [[Order of the Phoenix (organisation)|Order of the Phoenix]] against the intruding [[Death Eaters]]. He either collapses or is stupefied by Snape after requesting his help at the battle. 

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', Flitwick insists that [[Horcrux|Rowena Ravenclaw's Diadem]] is lost, and he is described by Harry (along with Dumbledore) as having been a &quot;model student&quot; who supposedly never entered the [[Room of Requirement|Room of Hidden Things]], and so it never occurred to him that the diadem could be hidden there. Before the Battle of Hogwarts, Flitwick helps to put protective charms around the castle to hinder [[Lord Voldemort]] and his oncoming Death Eaters, and later fights the intruders in the battle, battling [[Death Eater#Yaxley|Yaxley]] and later defeating [[Antonin Dolohov]].

In the film adaptations, Flitwick is portrayed by [[Warwick Davis]]. Rowling said: &quot;I must admit, I was taken aback when I saw the film Flitwick, who looks very much like a goblin/elf (I’ve never actually asked the film-makers precisely what he is), because the Flitwick in my imagination simply looks like a very small old man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/faq_view.cfm?id=95 JKRowling.com – F.A.Q. section: ''Is Flitwick a short human or is he some other type of being?'']&lt;/ref&gt; However, Rowling mentions on her official website that Flitwick is human, with &quot;a dash of goblin ancestry.&quot; His on-screen appearance changes noticeably in ''Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban'', in which he takes on a more human and less elf-like look, with slicked-down dark hair and moustache. According to Davis, the moustachioed character was originally not supposed to be Flitwick; Flitwick was absent from the script for ''Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban'', but &quot;the producer&quot; (presumably [[David Heyman]]) added the new character (as the conductor of the school choir and orchestra, credited as &quot;Choir Master&quot;) so that Davis could still appear in the film. ''Goblet of Fire'' director [[Mike Newell (director)|Mike Newell]] preferred the new look, &quot;and from that moment, the character became known as 'Flitwick'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2009/10/11/warwick-davis-on-new-look-flitwick-for-the-harry-potter-films&lt;/ref&gt;

Flitwick was born on 17 October,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jkrowling.com&lt;/ref&gt; but the year of his birth is never mentioned in the books or films.

===Gilderoy Lockhart===
'''Gilderoy Lockhart''' is a narcissistic wizarding celebrity who has written many books on his fabulous adventures encountering dark creatures. In ''Chamber of Secrets'', Lockhart is appointed as Hogwarts' new [[Hogwarts#Defence Against the Dark Arts|Defence Against the Dark Arts]] instructor. He is unpopular amongst most of the staff, particularly Professor Snape; however, he is greatly admired by many others, particularly witches, such as [[Hermione Granger]] and [[Molly Weasley|Mrs Weasley]], who find him attractive. Harry dislikes Lockhart for a number of reasons: his arrogance, his belief that Harry flew to Hogwarts in a [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Arthur Weasley's car|car]] to seek further attention, his penchant for handing out signed photos of himself, and the trouble he has with simple magic such as healing Harry's broken arm—he accidentally removes all of Harry's arm bones instead. Lockhart is exposed as a [[charlatan]] and a coward when he attempts to avoid entering the [[Chamber of Secrets]] by revealing to Harry and [[Ron Weasley]] that he never performed the amazing feats documented in his books, instead stealing other wizards' experiences and [[Spells in Harry Potter#Obliviate (Memory Charm)|erasing their memories]]. His attempt to use a Memory Charm on Harry and Ron backfires due to his use of Ron's broken wand, and he suffers the permanent near-total amnesia as a result.

In ''Order of the Phoenix'', Harry comes across Lockhart in [[Places in Harry Potter#St. Mungo's|St Mungo's]] while visiting [[Arthur Weasley|Mr. Weasley]] at Christmas. Lockhart is slowly regaining his memory and is childishly proud of being able to write in &quot;joined-up letters&quot;. He still enjoys signing autographs and still receives fan mail, although he has no idea why. Lockhart never fully recovers, despite all efforts to cure him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://the-leaky-cauldron.org/2007/7/30/j-k-rowling-web-chat-transcript J.K. Rowling Web Chat Transcript – The Leaky Cauldron&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Rowling has said Lockhart is the only character she has ever based on a real-life person. Lockhart was inspired by an unrevealed acquaintance who was &quot;even more objectionable than his fictional counterpart&quot; and &quot;used to tell whopping great fibs about his past life, all of them designed to demonstrate what a wonderful, brave and brilliant person he was.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/extrastuff_view.cfm?id=9 JKRowling.com – Extra Stuff section: ''Gilderoy Lockhart'']&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kenneth Branagh]] portrayed Lockhart in the [[Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets (film)|film version]] of ''the Chamber of Secrets''.

[[IGN]] put Gilderoy Lockheart as their 21st top ''Harry Potter'' character.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN Top&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/100/1002569p1.html|title=Top 25 Harry Potter Characters|author=Brian Linder, Phil Pirrello, Eric Goldman, Matt Fowler|date=14 July 2009|work=[[IGN]]|accessdate=3 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; IGN's Joe Utichi also put Gilderoy Lockheart as his 9th top ''Harry Potter'' character, calling him &quot;hilariously corrupt&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joe Top&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/113/1132181p2.html |title=The Top 10 Harry Potter Characters |author=Joe Utichi |date=3 November 2010 |work=[[IGN]] |accessdate=3 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Minerva McGonagall===
[[File:McGonagall.jpg|thumb|225 px|[[Maggie Smith]] was author [[J. K. Rowling]]'s personal choice for the role of McGonagall in the film series.]]
'''Minerva McGonagall''' is [[Head teacher|Deputy Headmistress]], head of [[Gryffindor]] House, [[Hogwarts#Transfiguration|Transfiguration]] professor, and later Headmistress at Hogwarts, where she began teaching in December 1956. She is first introduced in the opening chapter of ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'', when she meets Dumbledore at [[Number 4 Privet Drive]], [[Little Whinging]], Surrey (the home of Harry Potter's aunt and uncle). McGonagall is described as a tall, rather severe-looking woman, with black hair typically drawn into a tight bun. She wears emerald green robes, a pointed hat, and always has a very prim expression. She is, according to Rowling, a sprightly 70-year-old.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accio-quote.org/articles/2000/1000-scholastic-chat.htm Scholastic Chat]. accio-quote.org.&lt;/ref&gt; McGonagall wears square spectacles that match the markings around the eyes of her [[Animagus]] form of a silver [[tabby cat]]; she has the distinction of being the first Animagus introduced in the series and being one of the few registered Animagi of the century, though she was rarely seen using the ability. Harry's immediate impression of her is of someone who is not to be crossed. She has a fondness for tartan, and her handkerchief, dressing gown, and dress robes are patterned with it. Rowling has said McGonagall's birthday is 4 October.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2007/10/3/happy-birthday-minerva-mcgonagall|title=Happy Birthday, Minerva McGonagall!|date=3 October 2007|accessdate=4 October 2007|publisher=[[The Leaky Cauldron (web site)|The Leaky Cauldron]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first book, after seeing Harry fly masterfully his very first time on a broom, she recommends him to fill the position of [[Quidditch#Players|Seeker]], even though first years are normally prohibited from playing Quidditch, and sends Harry a broom. Furthermore, although a rigorous disciplinarian, she often assists Harry indirectly with activities that are not strictly within the rules of Hogwarts; for example, she allows Harry and his friends to use the Transfiguration classroom to practice for tasks in the [[Triwizard Tournament]]. She promises Harry she would do everything in her power to help him to achieve his goal of becoming an [[auror]], and she keeps her promise.&lt;ref name=october-2007-wotm&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/wotm.cfm|title=Wizard of the Month for October|date=20 October 2007|accessdate=20 October 2007|publisher=JK Rowling}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite her stern front, McGonagall is shown to have good intentions at heart and has been known to display a range of emotions, which can often be a shock to her colleagues and students.

It is revealed in ''Order of the Phoenix'' that McGonagall is a member of the [[Order of the Phoenix (organisation)|Order of the Phoenix]]. She and [[Dolores Umbridge]] seem to have a mutual dislike for each other, as Umbridge continuously usurps more and more power from the staff and from Dumbledore and McGonagall in particular. When McGonagall attempts to stop Umbridge and her fellow Ministry cronies from unjustly taking Hagrid away by force, she is hit by four [[List of spells in Harry Potter#Stupefy (Stunning Spell, Stupefying Charm, Stunner)|stunning spells]] without warning, before she can draw her wand. The unconscious septuagenarian is rushed to [[St Mungo's Hospital for Magical Maladies and Injuries|St Mungo's]], where she recovers for awhile. McGonagall returns to the school towards the end of the book, though she temporarily uses a walking stick to support herself. After the death of Dumbledore at the hands of Snape in ''Half-Blood Prince'', she becomes the acting Headmistress of Hogwarts. 

However, in the series finale, she does not become headmistress at the start of term as expected; Snape is appointed by new Minister for Magic [[Pius Thicknesse]], who is actually under the [[Imperius Curse]] and acting for Voldemort. Despite the many changes, she is retained as head of Gryffindor House. Before the Battle of Hogwarts, she goes to the Ravenclaw tower and finds Alecto Carrow stunned and her brother Amycus searching for Harry. When Amycus suggests hurting the students to compensate for his sister's state, McGonagall immediately intervenes. In response, Amycus spits in her face. Harry, who is present and hidden under his invisibility cloak, reveals himself and uses the [[Cruciatus Curse]] on Amycus. Harry then informs McGonagall that Voldemort is on his way and after tying up both the Carrows and placing them in a net, she sends three [[Patronus Charm|Patronuses]] – which manifest in her Animagus form – to warn the other three Heads of House.&lt;ref&gt;{{HP7ref}}, chapter 30&lt;/ref&gt; When on her way to meet the Heads of House, she meets Snape, who questions her about Potter's whereabouts. Not knowing Snape is actually still following Dumbledore's orders and has important information for Harry, she attacks him, engaging in a fierce duel. With help from Professors [[Professor Sprout|Sprout]] and [[Professor Flitwick|Flitwick]], she succeeds in driving Snape away. McGonagall then takes charge of the school again and proceeds to secure it against Voldemort to ensure Harry can fulfil his mission from Dumbledore. She also organises the evacuation of the school's under-age students to ensure their safety. She then leads the remaining students, the staff of Hogwarts, and members of the Order of the Phoenix in the fight against Voldemort. She is seen during the battle with a large gash on her cheek and commanding a herd of charmed desks to charge at Death Eaters. When Harry has been apparently killed, she screams, causing [[Bellatrix Lestrange]] to laugh. Finally, McGonagall ends up duelling Voldemort alongside [[Kingsley Shacklebolt]] and [[Horace Slughorn]]. As is confirmed in ''[[The Tales of Beedle the Bard]]'', McGonagall becomes Headmistress of Hogwarts after the Battle of Hogwarts and Snape's death; however, in an interview Rowling said McGonagall would be retired by the time of the ''Deathly Hallows'' epilogue (19 years after the main events of ''Deathly Hallows''), as she is &quot;getting on in years.&quot;

A backstory of McGonagall, starting from her parents' meeting to the beginning of her tenure as a teacher at Hogwarts, was released as a part of [[Pottermore]].  Born to a magical mother and Muggle father, she grew up in the [[Scottish Highlands]] and went on to become a star pupil at Hogwarts.  After experiencing heartbreak the summer after her graduation, she went on to work at the Ministry of Magic.  With two years of menial work there, she left to pursue a teaching career at Hogwarts and went on to form a lasting friendship with Albus Dumbledore.  She later married her former boss from her time at the Ministry, Elphinstone Urquart - only to be widowed three years later due to a Venomous Tenatcula accident.  It was revealed by Rowling that very few knew of Minerva's suffering, save for perhaps Dumbledore with whom she had confessed her heartbreak.

McGonagall is played by [[Dame Maggie Smith]] in the film adaptations. Smith has described her role as &quot;[[Jean Brodie|Miss Jean Brodie]] in a wizard's hat&quot;, Given that her role becomes progressively smaller as the series goes on, she notes that ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone (film)|Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'' is her favourite thus far.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/theatre/article-23387486-details/I'm%20very%20scared%20of%20being%20back%20on%20stage/article.do &quot;I'm very scared of being back on stage&quot;] This is London. 2 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Smith appeared in all the films of the series except for ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'', which does not take place in Hogwarts. Rowling has stated that she always pictured Smith portraying McGonagall, and claimed the actress to be at the top of her list.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accio-quote.org/articles/2001/1111-telegraph-alderson.html They really do look as I'd imagined they would inside my head.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Rowling named the character after the poet [[William Topaz McGonagall]], whose name she liked. Her first name, Minerva, comes from the Roman goddess of wisdom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accio-quote.org/articles/1999/1099-connectiontransc2.htm#p3 JKR: I'm big on names – I like names, generally. You have to be really careful giving me your name if it's an unusual one, because you will turn up in book six. Erm – I – I collect – some of them are invented. ... Lydon: Minerva McGonagall?  JKR: yeah, McGonagall, old erm – very, very, very bad Scottish poet, McGonagall is – I just loved the name.]&lt;/ref&gt;

IGN listed McGonagall as their seventeenth top ''Harry Potter'' character.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN Top&quot;/&gt;

===Poppy Pomfrey===
'''Madam Poppy Pomfrey''' is a magical [[Healer (fantasy)|Healer]] who is the matron-in-charge of the Hogwarts hospital wing. She is known to be very strict regarding the rules of her infirmary. Ron goes to Madam Pomfrey after being bitten by a dragon named Norbert in ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]''. After Harry defeats [[Professor Quirrell]] in the dungeons, he spends three days unconscious in the hospital wing. In ''Chamber of Secrets'', Madam Pomfrey regrows the bones in Harry's broken arm after [[Gilderoy Lockhart]] accidentally removes them following Gryffindor's Quidditch win over [[Slytherin]]. Hermione ends up in the hospital wing for a month after a mishap with the Polyjuice Potion that leaves her half-feline, then is again hospitalised after she is petrified along with several other students. In ''Prisoner of Azkaban'', Madam Pomfrey speaks approvingly of Remus Lupin's use of chocolate to relieve the effects of a [[dementor]]'s presence on students, commenting that Hogwarts has &quot;finally got a Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher who knows his remedies&quot;. She also tended to Harry after the Quidditch match against Hufflepuff, due to dementors around the pitch. After Umbridge's guards stun McGonagall in ''Order of the Phoenix'', Madam Pomfrey says she would resign in protest were she not afraid of what would become of the students without her presence. She also tends to Hermione, Ginny, Ron, Harry, Neville, and Luna after the battle in the Department of Mysteries. Umbridge is also a recipient of her healing skills after her scuffle with the Centaurs. In ''Half-Blood Prince'', she takes care of Ron after he is poisoned and tends to Harry after his skull is cracked by a Bludger in a Quidditch match. She attempts to heal Bill of his scars from Greyback's attack, without much success, and bursts into tears when she hears of Dumbledore's death. In ''Deathly Hallows'', she and [[Argus Filch]] oversee student evacuations from Hogwarts before the Battle of Hogwarts. She is later seen tending to the injured fighters.

[[Gemma Jones]] appeared as Madam Pomfrey in the film adaptations of ''Chamber of Secrets'', ''Half Blood Prince'', and ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2|Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]''.

===Quirinus Quirrell===
'''Quirinus Quirrell''' is the [[Hogwarts#Defence Against the Dark Arts|Defence Against the Dark Arts]] teacher at [[Hogwarts]] during [[Harry Potter]]'s first year. Prior to his employment at [[Hogwarts]], he is said by [[Rubeus Hagrid]] to have had a &quot;brilliant mind&quot;, and was a fine teacher while studying from books; some time before Harry's arrival at [[Hogwarts]], &quot;he took a year off to get some first-hand experience&quot;. Rowling stated in a live web chat on 30 July 2007 that Quirrell had worked at Hogwarts as [[Muggle]] Studies teacher for a certain length of time, before taking the cursed Defence Against the Dark Arts position in the same year that Harry joined.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloomsbury&quot;&gt;[http://www.bloomsbury.com/harrypotter/content.asp?sec=3&amp;sec2=1 J. K. Rowling Webchat Transcript] from the ''&quot;Harry Potter&quot;'' website at ''&quot;[[Bloomsbury Publishing|Bloomsbury]]&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; Upon his return, he appears perpetually nervous and has developed a stutter and nervous tics. Quirrell's attire includes a new purple [[turban]] which he claims to have received as a reward from an African prince for getting rid of a troublesome zombie.

Harry first meets Quirrell at the [[Places in Harry Potter#The Leaky Cauldron|Leaky Cauldron]], while being escorted by Hagrid to [[Diagon Alley]] to shop for school supplies. Quirrell is next seen at Hogwarts conversing with Snape at the start-of-term banquet, and then regularly while teaching Defence Against the Dark Arts lessons. During the school's Halloween banquet, Quirrell appears in the Great Hall to warn staff and students of a troll in the dungeons and then he faints. While playing Quidditch, Harry is almost thrown off his broom by some sort of curse and he, Ron, and Hermione believe it is Snape who is responsible. They begin to suspect that Snape is trying to steal the [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Philosopher's Stone|Philosopher's Stone]] hidden in a secret chamber in Hogwarts; however, when Harry finally arrives in the chamber, he discovers that it is not Snape, but Quirrell, who is the real villain. Quirrell then reveals that he was the one who let in the troll and attempted to throw Harry off his broom while Snape muttered a counter curse. During the climax of the story, as Harry and Quirrell try to recover the stone from the [[Mirror of Erised]], Voldemort reveals himself on the back of Quirrell's head, formerly concealed by the turban, and speaks directly to Harry, threatening to kill him if he does not assist Voldemort in recovering it. After Harry refuses, Voldemort orders Quirrell to attack Harry, who holds off Quirrell long enough for aid to arrive, at which point Voldemort flees, in his non-physical form. Voldemort's departure, as well as the agony suffered by him because of his contact with Harry, who continues to be protected by the love of his mother and the spell that was cast by her sacrificing her life to save Harry, causes Quirrell to die.

It is later revealed in the chapter ''The Prince's Tale'' from ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'' {{HP7}} that Snape was actually keeping an eye on Quirrell under Dumbledore's orders.

British actor [[Ian Hart]] portrayed Quirrell in the first film.

===Horace Slughorn===
'''Horace E. F. Slughorn''' is the long-serving Potions teacher and Head of Slytherin House since at least the 1940s, until his retirement after the 1980–81 school year. Following his retirement and the resurgence of Voldemort, Slughorn goes into hiding, concealing all knowledge of his whereabouts from both sides in the growing conflict in the wizarding world. However, after moving Snape to [[Hogwarts#Defence Against the Dark Arts|Defence Against the Dark Arts]], Dumbledore locates Slughorn and uses Harry as incentive to convince him to return to teaching Potions. Slughorn is described as preferring to be a &quot;back-seat driver&quot;, obtaining things he desires by using his contacts, particularly students whom he has invited into the &quot;Slug Club&quot;, a group of students favoured by Slughorn, based either on their connections to important people or on his belief that they have traits that will make them important and famous when they leave school such as Gwenog Jones who is the captain of the quidditch team; the Holyhead Harpies, the benefit from this is that he acquires free season tickets whenever he wants them. He is one of the first Slytherin characters to defy the house's [[stereotype]]: while he is self-serving and not above bending rules, he lacks the near-amorality and underhandedness that had, until that point, been a hallmark of the house. He does not resent blood status in general, and admits a pleasurable surprise when he comes upon a talented Muggle-born, such as Hermione or, years before, [[Lily Evans]]. Also, Slughorn notably displays not pride, but shame at having helped a young [[Lord Voldemort|Tom Marvolo Riddle]] perform some of his most noted and impressive feats of magic, as Riddle had questioned Slughorn about [[Horcrux]]es. However, students he deems unimportant he ignores, as though they were not there.

In ''Half-Blood Prince'', Harry is invited to the first meeting of the Slug Club held on the [[Hogwarts Express]]. Slughorn sets less-stringent entry criteria for Advanced Potions than his predecessor, lowering the required grade from a perfect O (Outstanding) to the above-average E (Exceeds Expectations). This last-minute change enables Harry and Ron to take Potions at NEWT level. However, since Harry had not expected to be allowed to join the course, he has none of the necessary materials, and Slughorn lends him an old textbook until Harry can procure his own. Later, Harry does buy a new copy of Advanced Potion-Making from Flourish and Blotts, but switches the covers and gives back the new book. During his first class, Slughorn offers a small amount of [[Felix Felicis]] to the student who brews the best cauldron of the Draught of Living Death. Harry wins with the help of handwritten notes in the borrowed textbook, which had once belonged to Snape. Harry later uses the Felix Felicis to retrieve a memory from Slughorn that details the conversation between the professor and Riddle about Horcruxes as well as the possibility of creating more than one Horcrux.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', Slughorn briefly appears with other teachers assembling to fight Death Eaters. As Snape is now Headmaster, Slughorn has assumed the post of Head of Slytherin. Though he is initially hesitant to join in the ''Battle of Hogwarts'' and is assumed to have evacuated with his house, he returns to the fray later on. It is revealed that he has not fled, but has recruited a large number of reinforcements to fight for Hogwarts. He then summons up the courage to duel Voldemort, alongside McGonagall and [[Kingsley Shacklebolt]].

Slughorn is played by [[Jim Broadbent]] in the film adaptations of ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince (film)|Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'' and ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]''.

IGN called Slughorn their 20th top ''Harry Potter'' character.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN Top&quot;/&gt;

===Pomona Sprout===
'''Pomona Sprout''' is Professor of [[Hogwarts#Herbology|Herbology]] and the Head of [[Hufflepuff]] House. Her birthday is on 15 May.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} She is described as a dumpy little witch with flyaway grey hair who wears a patched, frayed hat and shabby robes, often covered in dirt due to the time she spends tending plants in the Hogwarts greenhouses. Sprout is introduced in ''Philosopher's Stone'', but she plays no active role until ''Chamber of Secrets'', in which she teaches her second year students to work with Mandrake plants. She is responsible for raising the Mandrakes to full maturity, at which point their juice is used to revive the [[petrification|petrified]] victims of the [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Basilisk|basilisk]].

Sprout subsequently appears in ''Goblet of Fire'' in which, as the Hufflepuff Head of House, she comforts [[Ministry of Magic#Others|Amos Diggory]] and his wife after the death of their son, Hufflepuff student [[Cedric Diggory]], whom she knew well. In ''Order of the Phoenix'', Sprout is a non-vocal supporter of Harry's story about Voldemort's resurrection. Like many teachers at Hogwarts, she detests Umbridge's presence and does her best to disobey her. After the raid of Hogwarts in ''Half-Blood Prince'', Sprout is a staunch advocate of keeping Hogwarts open. She also supports the suggestion that Dumbledore should be laid to rest at Hogwarts. Sprout attends Dumbledore's funeral, where she appears cleaner than she has ever been seen before.

In ''Deathly Hallows'', she chases Snape away from Hogwarts with Professors McGonagall and Flitwick. Informed that Voldemort and his Death Eaters are coming to besiege Hogwarts, she uses her knowledge of magical plants by improvising offensive [[botany]], and, with the help of several students, throws Mandrakes and Venomous Tentaculas off the castle walls at the approaching Death Eaters. The epilogue of ''Deathly Hallows'' reveals that [[Neville Longbottom]] has become the new Herbology teacher at Hogwarts. The circumstances of Sprout's departure from the job are not revealed.

Sprout was portrayed by [[Miriam Margolyes]] in the film adaptation of ''Chamber of Secrets'' and ''Deathly Hallows – Part 2''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Miriam Margolyes: I love actors |url=http://www.thisissouthwales.co.uk/showbiz/Miriam-Margolyes-love-actors/article-353431-detail/article.html |work=[[South Wales Evening Post|Evening Post]] |location=South Wales |date=25 September 2008 |accessdate=24 January 2009 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sybill Trelawney===
&lt;!--WE USE THE BRITISH VERSION ON WIKIPEDIA; PLEASE DON'T CHANGE HER NAME TO THE AMERICAN &quot;SIBYLL&quot;. THANK YOU.--&gt;
'''Sybill Patricia Trelawney''' is the professor of [[Hogwarts#Divination|Divination]]. She is the great-great-granddaughter of the celebrated [[clairvoyant|seer]] Cassandra Trelawney, and, in fact, has inherited some of her ancestor's talent. Trelawney is described as a slight woman resembling an insect, draped in a large [[sequin|spangled]] shawl and many gaudy bangles and rings. She speaks in a misty voice and wears thick glasses, which cause her eyes to appear greatly magnified. Her odd classroom in the North Tower of Hogwarts is a cross between &quot;someone's attic and an old-fashioned tea shop&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Rowling, J.K. (1999). ''Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban'', p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; it can only be reached by climbing to the top of the stairs and then up a ladder through a trapdoor set in the ceiling. This dim, heavily scented, and &quot;stiflingly&quot; warm room often affects students' [[wakefulness]].

Trelawney first appears in the third book of the series, when Harry, Ron, and Hermione start divination lessons. The friends generally believe Trelawney is a fraud. However, Gryffindor students [[Parvati Patil]] and [[Dumbledore's Army#Lavender Brown|Lavender Brown]] are very fond of and impressed by her. According to McGonagall, her credibility as a seer is undermined by her habit of erroneously predicting, each year, the death of one of her students. However, from time to time she does make predictions within the books, which come true. Her more profound predictions seem only to happen when she is in a [[trance]] and unaware of what she is saying, with no memory of it afterward.

Prior to the events of the ''Harry Potter'' books, Trelawney falls into a prophetic trance while in an interview with Dumbledore at the [[Places in Harry Potter#The Hog's Head|Hog's Head]], making a prophecy about the birth of a wizard &quot;with the power to vanquish&quot; Voldemort. This prophecy was partly overheard by Snape, who relayed what he heard to Voldemort. This led Voldemort to attack the Potter family, believing that Harry was the child named. In ''Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban'', Trelawney prophesies to Harry about the events of the book's climax. In ''Order of the Phoenix'', Trelawney is first put on probation by Umbridge, and later fired. However, Trelawney continues to reside in Hogwarts castle due to an order by Dumbledore, who believes that she would be in danger outside of Hogwarts due to the prophecy she made during her interview. Dumbledore later reveals that the prophecy is why he keeps her employed as a Divination teacher. Trelawney returns to teaching in ''Half-Blood Prince'', but has to share classes with [[Firenze (Harry Potter)|Firenze]], as he was cast out by his fellow [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Centaurs|centaurs]] when he agreed to replace Trelawney after she was fired. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', she is seen aiding in the Battle of Hogwarts by magically accelerating her crystal balls at Death Eaters. She uses one of these crystal balls to defend an injured Lavender against the attack of werewolf [[Fenrir Greyback]]. In the film adaptation, ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]'', she is seen covering someone's body, with the aid of [[Padma Patil]].

In the British editions of the books, her name is consistently spelled as &quot;Sybill&quot;. In the American editions, from her first appearance in ''Prisoner of Azkaban'' through ''Order of the Phoenix'', her name is spelled as &quot;Sibyll&quot;. However, in the American edition of ''Half-Blood Prince'', it is re-spelled as &quot;Sybill&quot;, matching the UK edition.&lt;ref&gt;Her namesakes, the prophetesses of mythological Greece, were named the &quot;Sibyls&quot; ('Σίβυλλα'')&lt;/ref&gt;

Trelawney is portrayed by [[Emma Thompson]] in the ''Prisoner of Azkaban'', ''Order of the Phoenix'', and ''Deathly Hallows Part 2''.

IGN listed Trelawney as their 23rd top ''Harry Potter'' character and called her &quot;fascinating and fun&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN Top&quot;/&gt;

==Hogwarts ghosts==
Hogwarts is home to at least twenty [[Ghosts (Harry Potter)|ghosts]],{{HP1}} but when people in the novels speak of the ghosts at Hogwarts they are usually referring to one of the four resident ghosts of the Hogwarts houses: Sir Nicholas de Mimsy-Porpington (or, as the students refer to him, Nearly Headless Nick), the almost-decapitated wizard of the Court who resides in [[Gryffindor]] tower; the Bloody Baron, who resides in the [[Slytherin]] dungeon; the jovial Fat Friar, who resides with the [[Hufflepuff]]s; and the Grey Lady, who &quot;lives&quot; with the [[Ravenclaw]]s. These ghosts seem to act as something like advisers and aides to the students; Nick is frequently seen helping Harry during moments of uncertainty or crisis. Another ghost mentioned frequently is [[List of Harry Potter supporting characters#Moaning Myrtle|Moaning Myrtle]].

===The Bloody Baron===
'''The Bloody Baron''' is the Slytherin House ghost. He is the only person besides Dumbledore and Fred and George Weasley who can exert any control over the [[poltergeist]] [[Peeves]]; Peeves is terrified of him for some unknown reason, referring to him as &quot;Your Bloodiness&quot; and &quot;Mr. Baron.&quot;

The Baron's nickname comes from the fact that he is covered with blood, which appears silvery on his ghostly form. When Nearly Headless Nick is asked in the first book why the Baron is so bloody, Nick delicately comments that &quot;&lt;nowiki&gt;[he has]&lt;/nowiki&gt; never asked&quot;. However, this is explained in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', when Helena Ravenclaw tells Harry that the Baron had been in love with her when the two were alive, and when she ran off with her mother's diadem, Rowena Ravenclaw sent the Baron after her, knowing he would not stop until Helena was found. When Helena refused to return with him, however, the Baron killed her in a fit of rage, and then, in remorse, killed himself with the same weapon. He has thus haunted Hogwarts ever since, wearing his ghostly chains as a form of penance.

[[Terence Bayler]] portrayed the Baron in the first film. In contrast to his book counterpart, the Baron is quite mirthful in the film, playfully swiping through the Sorting feast with his sword, much to the amusement of those within his house.

===The Fat Friar===
'''The Fat Friar''' is the Hufflepuff House ghost. He is a jolly man and very forgiving. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'' when the first years are waiting for Professor McGonagall to return and the ghosts pass overhead, the Fat Friar is pleading on behalf of Peeves the Poltergeist to allow him to come to the welcome feast despite his past wrongdoings. Similarly, when Peeves wants to join the welcome feast in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'', the Fat Friar was willing to give him a chance.

[[Simon Fisher-Becker]] appeared as the Fat Friar in the film adaptation of ''Philosopher's Stone''.

===The Grey Lady===
'''The Grey Lady''' is the Ravenclaw House ghost. According to a letter written by Rowling to [[Nina Young]], the actress who played the Grey Lady in the first film, she is &quot;a highly intellectual young lady .... She never found true love as she never found a man up to her standards&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hp-lexicon.org/wizards/ghosts.html Ghosts] [[Harry Potter Lexicon]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'' it is revealed that the Grey Lady is '''Helena Ravenclaw''', daughter of [[#Rowena Ravenclaw|Rowena Ravenclaw]], making her the only house ghost known to be related to one of the Hogwarts founders. She informs Harry that she stole the [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Rowena Ravenclaw's Diadem|Diadem of Ravenclaw]] from her mother, in an attempt to become smarter than her, and then went into hiding in Albania. It was a dying Rowena Ravenclaw's wish to see her daughter again and so she sent for the Bloody Baron to look for her, knowing that he would not rest until he brought her back, partly because he was in love with her. However, she refused to come with him and, in a moment of blind rage, he killed her with a single stab wound to the chest. Overcome with remorse, the Bloody Baron killed himself using the same weapon in turn and wears chains as penitence, &quot;as he should&quot;, the Grey Lady says. The [[Diadem (personal wear)|diadem]] remained in the hollow of a tree in an [[Albania]]n forest until [[Tom Riddle]] managed to charm the story out of her ghost, the Grey Lady. Riddle, who had been seeking out historically significant objects to make into [[Horcruxes]], later retrieved the diadem from Albania and hid it in the [[Room of Requirement]] at Hogwarts while visiting the castle years later.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]'', she was played by [[Kelly Macdonald]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=John|last=Lopez|url=http://www.vanityfair.com/online/oscars/2010/12/boardwalk-empires-kelly-macdonald-on-scorsese-the-coens-and-her-future-on-the-show.html|title=''Boardwalk Empire's'' Kelly Macdonald on Scorsese, the Coens, and Her Future in the Show|publisher=Vanity Fair|date=10 December 2010|accessdate=16 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nearly Headless Nick===
'''Sir Nicholas de Mimsy-Porpington''', often referred to as '''Nearly Headless Nick''', '''Nick''', or '''Sir Nicholas''', is the Gryffindor House ghost who in life was sentenced to death by beheading after a teeth-straightening spell went awry on Lady Grieve.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jkrowling.com/en/ J.K.Rowling Official Site – Harry Potter and more&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately, the executioner's axe was blunt and after 45 hacks Nick's head was still only partially severed. Harry becomes friends with Nick when he attends his &quot;deathday&quot; party (the 500th anniversary of the event) in a Hogwarts dungeon. Nick's death date (31 October 1492) has the distinction of having served as the basis for the entire chronology of the ''Harry Potter'' stories, until the timeline was confirmed by the headstone of [[James Potter (character)|James]] and [[Lily Potter]] in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''. His greatest wish is to become a member of the Headless Hunt, as mentioned in the second book. However, he is excluded due to the fact that he is not actually headless and would not be able to fully participate in the activities.

In ''the Chamber of Secrets'', Nick is a victim of the [[Basilisk (Harry Potter)|Basilisk]] that [[Ginny Weasley]] unleashes under the influence of [[Tom Riddle]]. The stare of the Basilisk is lethal to anyone who looks it directly in the eye. While the living students all have some barrier between them and the Basilisk (and are therefore petrified rather than killed), Nick does look at the Basilisk's eyes directly. However, since he is already dead, he too is only petrified. The character appears again in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'' when Harry has been looking for comfort upon the death of [[Sirius Black]], hoping he can see him later as a ghost. Nick explains that only witches and wizards who fear death and refuse to go on can become ghosts, dashing Harry's hope of communicating with Sirius. He appears briefly in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', when Harry asks him to bring him to the [[#The Grey Lady|Grey Lady]].

The character is portrayed in the film series by [[John Cleese]].

==Hogwarts founders==
Hogwarts was founded a millennium ago by &quot;four of the greatest witches and wizards of the age&quot;:{{HP2}} Godric Gryffindor, Helga Hufflepuff, Rowena Ravenclaw, and Salazar Slytherin. The founders served as Hogwarts' first teachers, and each of the Hogwarts houses is named after one of the founders.

===Godric Gryffindor===
'''Godric Gryffindor''' hailed from a [[Moorland|moor]] that is now known as [[Places in Harry Potter#Godric's Hollow|Godric's Hollow]], a small [[West Country]] village.{{HP7}} Gryffindor is said to have praised courage, determination, and strength of heart above all other qualities. He also was the most in favour of allowing [[Muggle-born]]s into the school. He was initially a close friend of Salazar Slytherin, but over time their friendship deteriorated. &quot;One of the four famous Founders of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, Godric Gryffindor was the most accomplished dueller of his time, an enlightened fighter against Muggle-discrimination and the first owner of the celebrated Sorting Hat.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/wotm.cfm Section: Wizard of the Month Godric Gryffindor] JKRowling.com Retrieved 30 June 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

His known relics are a goblin-made sword adorned with rubies (the Goblins claim that Godric stole it from them, but Goblin notions of ownership are different from human views of ownership) and the [[Sorting Hat]]. The two items share a particular bond: whenever a &quot;true Gryffindor&quot; needs it, the Sword will allow itself to be pulled out of the hat. Godric's sword is goblin wrought silver, so it never needs cleaning and only takes in what strengthens it—when Harry kills a basilisk with it in the Chamber of Secrets it absorbed basilisk venom, making it suitable as a tool for destroying Voldemort's [[Horcruxes]]: Dumbledore uses it to destroy Gaunt's ring, [[Ron Weasley]] uses it to smash Slytherin's locket, and [[Neville Longbottom]] uses it to kill [[Nagini (Harry Potter)|Nagini]].

===Helga Hufflepuff===
'''Helga Hufflepuff''' came from a broad valley. The Sorting Hat describes her as &quot;good Hufflepuff&quot; or &quot;sweet Hufflepuff&quot;. She favoured loyalty, honesty, and dedication. In ''Goblet of Fire'', she is said to have considered &quot;hard workers most worthy of admission&quot;. Elsewhere, she is described as taking &quot;all the rest&quot; of the students after selection by her colleagues. She was a good friend of Rowena Ravenclaw; their friendship is used to emphasise the failed friendship between Godric Gryffindor and Salazar Slytherin.

&quot;One of the four celebrated Founders of Hogwarts, Hufflepuff was particularly famous for her dexterity at food-related Charms. Many recipes traditionally served at Hogwarts feasts originated with Hufflepuff.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mugglesguide.com/modules/news/article.php?storyid=108 New Wizard of the Month May 2007] ''mugglesguide.com.''&lt;/ref&gt; Her wizard card, penned by Rowling, describes her as having &quot;brought people from different walks of life together to help build Hogwarts&quot;, and being &quot;loved for her charming ways&quot;. According to an interview between Rowling and staff from [[The Leaky Cauldron (website)|The Leaky Cauldron]], Hufflepuff introduced [[House-elf|house-elves]] to Hogwarts, where she offered them refuge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2007/10/22/pottercast-122-it-s-saturday-night PotterCast 122] &quot;the-leaky-cauldron.org.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Both the famous wizard card and the illustration on Rowling's website depict her as a plump woman with red hair. Coincidentally, those two traits are commonly used to describe [[Molly Weasley]].

One relic of Hufflepuff, a small golden cup, emblazoned with her symbol of a badger, is passed down to her distant descendant, [[Minor Harry Potter characters#Hepzibah Smith|Hepzibah Smith]]. This cup is stolen by Tom Riddle and made into a Horcrux.

===Rowena Ravenclaw===
''' Rowena Ravenclaw'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mugglesguide.com/modules/news/article.php?storyid=157 New Wizard of the Month August 2007] ''mugglesguide.com.''&lt;/ref&gt; was a witch noted for her cleverness and creativity, and was described by [[Xenophilius Lovegood]] as beautiful. The Sorting Hat introduces her as &quot;Fair Ravenclaw, from [[glen]]&quot;, suggesting she was from Scotland. Ravenclaw devised the ever-changing floor plans and moving staircases in the Hogwarts castle,{{Citation Needed|date=September 2011}} and coined the proverb &quot;Wit beyond measure is man's greatest treasure.&quot; Ravenclaw is described by the Sorting Hat as having selected students according to intelligence and wisdom. &quot;One of the four famous Founders of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, Rowena Ravenclaw was the most brilliant witch of her time, though legend has it that a broken heart—cause unknown—contributed to her early demise.&quot; It is revealed in the ''Deathly Hallows'' that the broken heart contributing to her untimely death was most likely the loss of her daughter, [[Helena Ravenclaw]], who is, in fact, the Ravenclaw House Ghost (nicknamed The Grey Lady), and the loss of her diadem, the very relic to which Ravenclaw's astounding wisdom was attributed.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', Harry learns that an artefact of Ravenclaw's became a [[Horcrux]]: her lost diadem, which granted enhanced wisdom to its wearer. Her daughter, Helena Ravenclaw, had once run away with it to surpass her mother in terms of intelligence and wisdom and hid it in [[Albania]], its whereabouts remaining unknown ever since. She, however, revealed its location to a young [[Tom Riddle]], who proceeded to retrieve it and turn it into a Horcrux. In the original uncursed form, it is said to be able to imbue its wearer with great wisdom. Late in her life, Rowena, suffering from a terminal illness, sent for the [[#The Bloody Baron|Bloody Baron]] to find her daughter so she could see her one last time before she died. However, Helena refused to go with the Baron, and he killed her in a paroxysm of rage. Immediately overcome with guilt, he then took his own life.

===Salazar Slytherin===
'''Salazar Slytherin''' is described as power hungry by the Sorting Hat, and was known as &quot;shrewd Slytherin from [[fen]]&quot;. One of the four celebrated Founders of Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, Salazar Slytherin was one of the first recorded [[Magic (Harry Potter)#Parselmouth|Parselmouths]], an accomplished Legilimens, and a notorious champion of pureblood supremacy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mugglesguide.com/modules/news/article.php?storyid=138 New Wizard of the Month June 2007] ''mugglesguide.com''.&lt;/ref&gt; Slytherin is the only founder whose physical appearance is ever described in any detail; his statue in the [[Chamber of Secrets]] depicts a man &quot;ancient and monkey-like, with a long thin beard that fell almost to the bottom of his sweeping robes.&quot; According to Dumbledore, the qualities that Slytherin prized in his handpicked students included his own rare ability to speak Parseltongue,&lt;ref&gt;''Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets'' – Chapter 18 – Page 333&lt;/ref&gt; resourcefulness, and determination. He also selected his students according to cunning, ambition, and [[Blood purity (Harry Potter)|blood purity]]. Slytherin's first name is a reference to Portuguese dictator Dr. [[António de Oliveira Salazar]].

Slytherin's background is first discussed by [[Professor Binns]] in ''[[Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets]]'' (by Professor McGonagall in the film version): he describes the founding of the school and the schism which developed between Slytherin and the other founders, and he mentions that the castle was founded far from [[Muggles]] because, at that time, common people feared magic and persecuted suspected wizards and witches. Slytherin wanted magical learning restricted to all-magical families, as he believed Muggle-born students to be untrustworthy and he disliked teaching such students. According to ancient legend, Slytherin was responsible for the construction of the Chamber of Secrets. This chamber contained a magically created [[Basilisk (Harry Potter)|Basilisk]], susceptible to control by his Parselmouth descendants and left there to purge the school of all Muggle-borns. This occurred shortly before infighting among the four founders broke out and resulted in Slytherin's departure.

Slytherin owned a locket that became an heirloom for his last known line of descendants, [[The House of Gaunt|the Gaunts]]; later it is turned into a [[Horcrux]] by Lord Voldemort, his last descendent, who shares his ancestor's obsession with pertaining blood purity in the wizard world, and lets that obsession consume him to make him the legendary outlaw and villain feared by all.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Harry Potter|Fictional characters}}
{{Wikipedia-Books|Harry Potter}}
{{hpw|Professor}}
*[http://www.hp-lexicon.org/hogwarts/hogwarts_teachers.html The Harry Potter Lexicon's page on the Hogwarts Staff]

{{Harry Potter}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hogwarts Staff}}
[[Category:Harry Potter characters]]
[[Category:Fictional school personnel]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1997]]
[[bs:Manje važni profesori u Hogwartsu]]
[[ca:Personal de Hogwarts]]
[[cs:Bradavičtí zaměstnanci]]
[[da:Hogwarts' stab]]
[[de:Figuren der Harry-Potter-Romane#Lehrer und Schulbedienstete auf Hogwarts]]
[[hr:Manje važni profesori u Hogwartsu]]
[[he:הארי פוטר - דמויות משנה#אנשי הוגוורטס]]
[[ka:ჰოგვორტსის პერსონალი]]
[[lt:Hogvartso personalas]]
[[hu:Roxforti tanárok]]
[[mk:Персоналот на Хогвортс]]
[[ms:Staf Hogwarts]]
[[ja:マダム・フーチ]]
[[no:Ansatte ved Galtvort høyere skole for hekseri og trolldom]]
[[pl:Pracownicy Hogwartu]]
[[pt:Professores secundários de Hogwarts]]
[[ru:Штат Хогвартса]]
[[fi:Tylypahkan henkilökunta]]
[[sv:Hogwarts#Personal]]
[[th:อาจารย์และบุคลากรในฮอกวอตส์]]
[[tr:Hogwarts Kadrosu]]
[[vi:Nhân viên Hogwarts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
