<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9477787" ns="0" title="Hector Williams"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox character
| colour      = {{Infobox television/colour|The Unit}}
| name        = Hector Lucian Williams
| series      = The Unit
| image       = [[File:HectorWilliams.jpg|250px]]
| caption     = SFC Hector Williams
| first       = First Responders
| last        = Five Brothers
| cause       = 
| portrayer   = [[Demore Barnes]]
| nickname    = 
| alias       = Hammerhead
| title       = Sergeant First Class
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = U.S. Army Special Forces
| family      = 
| spouse      = 
| children    = 
| religion    = 
| nationality = 
}}&lt;!-- Born: November 16, 1976; Died: November 6, 2007 --&gt;

[[Sergeant First Class]] '''Hector Lucian Williams''' ([[United States Army]], callsign: ''Hammerhead'') was a fictional character on the [[CBS]] [[Television program|television series]] ''[[The Unit]]''.  He was portrayed by [[Canada|Canadian]] actor [[Demore Barnes]].

Hector was a Unit [[Operator (military)|operator]] assigned to Alpha Team of the 1st Special Actions Group (official cover as the &quot;[[303rd Logistical Studies Group]]&quot;).  He was an experienced [[marksman]], and frequently served as a [[sharpshooter]] for the team. According to his uniform, he was both [[Special Forces]] and [[Army Ranger|Ranger]] qualified. Williams was likely the most diverse member of Alpha Team. He served as one of the team's [[medic]]s, indicating that he was probably a Special Forces Medical Sergeant (18D) prior to joining the Unit. He was also cross trained in breaching demolitions. He, along with Charles Grey, also served as an instructor in close quarters battle for a SWAT unit, and designed the deliberate assault plan for the Braydon School Takedown in the &quot;In Loco Parentis&quot; episode. He was fluent in Arabic and Spanish, as well as Papuan Tok Pisin, and could speak German, Portuguese and a Pashto/Urdu dialect. Hector's cover was that of a &quot;logistics clerk&quot;.

In Season 1, Hector was engaged to the daughter of a retired [[paratrooper]] who looked upon Hector with disdain due to his career in &quot;logistics&quot;. The paratrooper was familiar with Colonel Tom Ryan, and asked for Hector to be transferred to the [[82nd Airborne Division]]. Ryan let the father know subtly that Hector was not in logistics but actually a [[Counterterrorism|counter-terrorist]]. The father's attitude toward Hector changed, which Hector's fiancée noticed. He came clean to her that he was in counter-terrorism, and she, not seeing job security out of the [[United States Army|Army]] in his future, ended the relationship.

In Season 3, Hector met a woman named Annie at a local bar. She was a waitress and former US Army medic who happened to know Tiffany. They went on a date and then shortly thereafter (with some encouragement from the other Unit women) met up at a local motel in a nearby town. While there, Hector discovered Tiffy and Colonel Ryan having an affair.

During the Season 3 episode &quot;Five Brothers&quot;, Hector was killed when he was hit in the neck with a bullet fired by a sniper as the team made its escape from [[Hezbollah]] during the rescue mission in [[Beirut]]; the sniper's bullet ricocheted from a bone in Hector's neck into his chest whilst caring for injured team-mate [[Charles Grey (The Unit)|Charles Grey]]. The irony of this is that during the episode, and also during the episode's promotional spots, the team member Charles, Hector's roommate, is speculated as being killed, but survives the ordeal due to Williams' medical efforts.

The cover for his death was that he was transporting [[document]]s across an [[airfield]] in [[Turkey]] when [[unexploded ordnance]] blew up, rolling his [[jeep]] and killing him instantly. This scenario is called &quot;Play 16&quot;.

==Awards and decorations==

At the time of his death, Hector's patches, tabs, badges, awards and decorations were as follows:

===Patches, tabs and badges===
*[[U.S. Army Special Forces Command]]
*[[24th Infantry Division (United States)|24th Infantry Division]]
*[[Special Forces Tab]]
*[[Ranger Tab]]
*[[18th Infantry Regiment (United States)|18th Infantry Regiment]]
*[[Combat Infantryman Badge]]
*[[Air Assault Badge]]
*[[Master Parachutist Badge]]
*[[Military Free Fall Parachutist Badge]]
*[[Weapons Qualification Badge|Expert Weapons Qualification Badge]]
* Four [[service stripe]]s (indicating between 12 and 14 years of service){{ref|hector birth|*}}

===Awards and decorations===
Per order of precedence:
*[[File:Silver Star ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Silver Star]]
*[[File:Bronze Star ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Bronze Star]]
*[[File:Purple Heart BAR.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Purple Heart]]
*[[File:Army Commendation Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Army Commendation Medal]]
*[[File:Army Achievement Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Army Achievement Medal]]
*[[File:Army Good Conduct ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Army Good Conduct Medal]] (with silver clasp with two [[Good Conduct Loop|loops]], indicting seven awards)
*[[File:National Defense Service Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[National Defense Service Medal]] (with one bronze [[service star]])
*[[File:Southwest Asia Service ribbon.svg |60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Southwest Asia Service Medal]] (with two bronze service stars){{ref|hector birth|*}}
*[[File:Global War on Terrorism Expeditionary ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Global War on Terrorism Expeditionary Medal]]
*[[File:Global War on Terrorism Service ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Global War on Terrorism Service Medal]]
*[[File:Army Overseas Service Ribbon.svg|60px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Overseas Service Ribbon]] (with [[Award numerals|award numeral]] &quot;4&quot;, indicating four tours)

==Notes==
{{ref begin}}
{{note|hector birth|*}}Hector's grave stone lists him as having been born February 12, 1981,&lt;ref name=&quot;hero&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=List of The Unit episodes| title=Hero| series=The Unit| serieslink=The Unit}}&lt;/ref&gt; yet his dress uniform shows him as having been awarded the Southwest Asia Medal and four service stripes. Since the Southwest Asia medal was not awarded after 1995, Hector would have had to have served two tours in Southwest Asia by age 14. Furthermore his uniform indicates he had between 12 and 14 years of service at his time of death. Making his enlistment age 12 or 14. Conversely his birth date was previously given in &quot;Play 16&quot; as November 16, 1976, so it is possible that the previous decorations and birth date have been stricken from the record, or that this 1976 birthdate is the correct date.
{{ref end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
&lt;!--
* [http://www.imdb.com/character/ch  ] at [[IMDB]]
* [http://www.tv.com/person//summary.html ] at [[TV.com]]
--&gt;

{{The Unit Navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Williams, Hector}}
[[Category:The Unit characters]]
[[Category:Fictional Delta Force personnel]]
[[Category:Fictional Green Berets]]
[[Category:Fictional United States Army Rangers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
