<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9499225" ns="0" title="Areca Backup"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name = Areca Backup
| developer = Olivier PETRUCCI&lt;br/&gt;Internationalization: Stephane BRUNEL
| latest_release_version = 7.1.2 BETA {{Release date and age|2009|05|28}}
| latest_release_version = 7.2.3 {{Release date and age|2011|08|20}}
| operating_system = All operating systems, provided that a Java Runtime Environment has been installed (version 1.4.2 or later); packaged for Linux, Windows 2000/XP
| genre = [[Utility software|Utility]]
| license = [[GNU General Public License|GPL]] v2.0
| website = {{nowrap| [http://www.areca-backup.org http://www.areca-backup.org]}}
|}}

'''Areca Backup''' is a personal file [[backup software]] developed in [[Java (programming language)|Java]]. It is released under the [[GNU General Public License]] (GPL) 2.

== Features ==
Areca Backup includes a backup engine, as well as a [[graphical user interface]] and a [[command-line interface]]. A big drawback of Areca Backup is that you have to keep the zipped backups on your hard drive. You cannot remove them after you save them to backup media, because if you do, the next time you try to perform a backup Areca Backup will backup all the files again, instead of just changed and new files.

The application includes the following features:
* [[ZIP (file format)|ZIP]]/ZIP64 compression
* [[Advanced Encryption Standard|AES]] 128 &amp; [[Advanced Encryption Standard|AES]] 256 encryption
* Backup filters (by extension, subdirectory, regular expression, size, date, status, usage)
* [[Incremental backup]], [[Incremental_backup#Differential|differential]] and full backup support
* [[Delta encoding|Delta]] backup (only the modified parts of the files will be stored, not the whole files)
* Archives merges
* As of date recovery
* [[Database_management_system#Transaction_mechanism|Transaction mechanism]] (with commit/rollback management) for all critical processes (such as backups or merges) to guarantee backups' integrity
* Unix file permissions backup/recovery
* E-Mail reports
* Backup simulation
* [[FTP]] and [[FTPS]] support ([[Transport Layer Security|SSL]]/[[Transport Layer Security|TLS]] in both implicit and explicit modes)
* [[SSH_file_transfer_protocol|SFTP]] support

Areca also provides all tools needed to handle your archives:
* Backup
* Archive recovery (with or without deleted files); entire archives or single files can be easily recovered
* Archive merge: contiguous incremental archives can be merged into a single archive to save storage space
* Archive deletion
* History explorer: different versions of a given file can be browsed and restored
* Archive explorer: files can be searched among your archives

'''Storage modes'''
Areca can handle multiple storage modes:
* Standard: It is the default mode, which is recommended for most users: If you choose this storage mode, a new archive will be created for each backup. All new or modified files since the last backup will be stored in this archive.
* [[Delta encoding|Delta]]: This mode is recommended for advanced users only: If you choose this storage mode, a new archive will be created for each backup. All modified *parts* of files since the last backup will be stored in this archive. This mode is particularly useful if you are handling large files.
* Image: If you choose this storage mode, a unique archive will be created and updated at each backup.

'''Backup types'''
Areca can handle the following types of backups:
* Full Backup: When a full backup is performed, ALL files are stored in your archive (whether they have been modified or not).
* [[Incremental backup]]: When an incremental backup is performed, only the files which have been modified since the last backup are stored in your archive.
* [[Incremental_backup#Differential|Differential backup]]: When a differential backup is performed, only the files which have been modified since the last FULL backup are stored in your archive.

Areca uses the file's size and last modification time to detect modified files. If one of these attributes is modified (whatever its value is), the file is flagged as modified. This allows a fast detection of modified files.

Areca is downloadable pre-packaged for [[Linux]] and [[Windows 2000]]/[[Windows XP]] and [[Windows Vista]]. But it also runs on any other [[operating system]], provided that a [[Java Runtime Environment]] has been installed (version 1.4.2 or later). It has been translated to: Chinese (Simplified), Chinese (Traditional), Czech, Danish, Dutch, English, French, German, Hungarian, Italian, Japanese, Russian, Spanish, Swedish.

==External links==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [http://www.areca-backup.org/ Areca Backup official website]
* [http://www.linuxlinks.com/article/20090106114914738/ArecaBackup.html LinuxLinks.com]
* [http://www.howtoforge.com/creating-backups-with-areca-on-fedora9 HowToForge: detailed instructions with lots of printscreens for Areca on [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] 9], [http://www.howtoforge.com/creating-backups-with-areca-on-fedora9-p2 page 2], [http://www.howtoforge.com/creating-backups-with-areca-on-fedora9-p3 page 3]
* [http://logichaos.com/joomla/guides/34/66-areca-free-backup-recovery-program.html  Videotutorial]
* [http://www.linux-community.de/Internal/Artikel/Print-Artikel/EasyLinux/2009/04/Auf-der-sicheren-Seite Article about Areca Backup on Linux-Community.de (in German)]

[[Category:Free backup software]]
[[Category:Free software programmed in Java]]

[[de:Areca Backup]]
[[es:Areca Backup]]
[[fr:Areca Backup]]
[[ru:Areca Backup]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
