<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9507357" ns="0" title="WokFi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:WokFi-sample2.jpg|thumb|right|Mid-sized WokFi antenna sample]]
'''WokFi''' (a [[portmanteau]] derived from blending [[Wok]] + [[Wi-Fi]]) is a term now commonly used to indicate a style of Wi-Fi antenna made out of simple low-cost Asian cookware [[Scoop (utensil)|scoop]]s, or similar easy-to-find household metallic reflective items.

==Description==
WokFi antennas can be fabricated out of commonly available scoop-shaped utensils (which need not be perfectly [[Parabolic antenna|parabolic]]) in conjunction with a [[Universal Serial Bus|USB]] Wi-Fi [[dongle]]. This approach is considered simpler and cheaper than classical home-built antenna projects (such as the popular [[cantenna]]), but is a very effective method to boost the Wi-Fi connection quality, audit [[Wireless access point|access point]] coverage, and even quickly establish [[Wireless LAN|WLAN]] viability – perhaps if a more professional setup is eventually intended.

==Advantages==
A significant advantage is that regular cheap USB passive extension cables can be used for five-meter (and sometimes greater) runs, with no concerns over proprietary fittings or microwave [[Signal (electrical engineering)|signal]] losses (such as when costly  [[coaxial cable]] is used), since the USB communication operates in the 'slower' digital domain with standardised connectors. Chaining active USB repeaters and passive cables, it is possible to extend the connection even more (tens of metres), which is especially useful with Wi-Fi's microwave frequencies when [[Line-of-sight propagation|line-of-sight]] (LOS) obstacles (such as vegetation and walls) need to be cleared. If using mesh reflectors, usually with a grid under 5&amp;nbsp;mm, the antenna will be lighter and less wind-prone than larger dishes.

==Performance==
WokFi gains are typically 12–15 [[Decibel|dB]], with range boosts, thus 4–6 times over a bare USB adapter. Ranges (LoS) are typically 3–5&amp;nbsp;km,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=&quot;WokFi&quot; Down South|url=http://www.peteredge.orcon.net.nz/wokfidownsouthedit.html |publisher=peteredge.orcon.net.nz |accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; although an aligned pair of similar [[Point-to-point (telecommunications)|point-to-point]] transceiver setups may approach 10&amp;nbsp;km over a clear path. In addition, certain improved WokFi antennas, and antennae made using surplus 2-foot- to 3-foot-diameter round or oval satellite TV dishes, allow even far greater range, up to 20&amp;nbsp;km.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=$10 wok keeps TV station on air |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/1/story.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10425224 |publisher=nzherald.co.nz |accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Interference from nearby 2.4&amp;nbsp;GHz signals (perhaps from cordless phones, AV links, leaky microwave ovens, other APs or Bluetooth) can also be nulled out—a useful feature in this increasingly crowded spectrum portion. Additionally, the performance of abundant low-powered Wi-Fi &quot;dongles&quot;, typically selling for approximately US$15–20, but of only 30–40 [[Watt|mW]] transmitter power and modest receiver sensitivity, can be easily boosted with little more than cheap cookware or pot lids. The &quot;sweet spot&quot; on such ad hoc reflectors can readily be found by bringing the Sun's rays to a focal point, by taping a little ~ 1&quot; mirror bit on the surface of the dish, to see where the sun's rays focus.

==See also==
* [[Cantenna]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.usbwifi.orcon.net.nz/  USB adaptors &amp; DIY antenna = &quot;Poor Man's WiFi&quot; ?] — Kiwi Stan Swan's site, where the whole '''WokFi''' thing sparked
* [http://urbanwireless.info/antennas/dish-with-usb-feed Urban Wireless - Dish with USB Feed] — Parabolic Dish with USB Feed
* [http://www.instructables.com/id/E2YSD0JZ80EQZJIFKI/?relatedLink  WokFi Instructables #1] — based around the web site above.
* [http://www.instructables.com/id/EC0S9C3F0HPZCGN/ WokFi Instructables #2 ] — Step by step instructions on making a WokFi.
* [http://www.nzherald.co.nz/section/1/story.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10425224 $10 wok keeps TV station on air] — A Wokfi which spans 20&amp;nbsp;km
* [http://www.josepino.com/other_projects/index.php?howto_wifi_lid_antenna.jpc Quickee WokFi] — pictorial outline of a quickly made  ≈13dB gain WokFi
* [http://munones.hostzi.com/2010/08/antena-wifi-casera-wokfi/ how to wokfi] — Instrucciones en español con fotografias.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wokfi}}
[[Category:Radio frequency antenna types]]
[[Category:Wireless networking]]
[[Category:Wi-Fi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
