<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9581838" ns="0" title="Skyline Pigeon"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=February 2007}}
{{Infobox Song &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Songs --&gt; |
| Name        = Skyline Pigeon
| Type        = [[Song]] 
| Artist      = [[Elton John]]
| Album       = [[Empty Sky]]
| Cover       = 
| track_no    = 8
| Released    = June 3, 1969 &lt;small&gt;(UK)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;January 13, 1975 &lt;small&gt;(USA)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;March 21, 1980 &lt;small&gt;(USA)&lt;/small&gt;
| Recorded    = DJM Studios, [[1969 in music|1969]]&lt;br&gt;Strawberry Studios, France, June 1972
| Genre       = [[Pop music|Pop]], [[Folk music|folk]]
| Length      = 3:37 (1969), 3:53 (1972)
| Label       = [[DJM Records]]&lt;br/&gt;[[MCA Records]] (US/Canada-1975)
| Writer      = Elton John, [[Bernie Taupin]]
| Producer   = Steve Brown (1969), &lt;br /&gt;Gus Dudgeon (1972)
| prev           = &quot;[[The Scaffold (song)|The Scaffold]]&quot;
| prev_no        = 7
| next           = &quot;[[Gulliver/Hay-Chewed/Reprise]]&quot;
| next_no        = 9
}}
&quot;'''Skyline Pigeon'''&quot; is a song by [[Elton John]] with lyrics by [[Bernie Taupin]]. It is the eighth track off his first album, ''[[Empty Sky]]''. John performed the song at the funeral of [[AIDS]] victim and friend [[Ryan White]] in 1990 on a grand piano although he played Roland Piano on tour and in the studio at the time. It was originally released in August 1968 as a single on the Pye label by Guy Darrell and simultaneously by Roger James Cooke on Columbia Records. It was also recorded by Deep Feeling, a short lived band formed by [[Jim Capaldi]] and Luther Grosvenor, in 1970.

==Musical structure==
The original recording from the &quot;Empty Sky&quot; album features Elton John on [[harpsichord]] and [[Organ (music)|organ]]. It's the only song on the album to feature only John without other musicians. He wrote the song in the style of a [[hymn]]. 

==Performances==
It was played on the radio as early as 1968. It was the most popular song during the very early period of John's musical career, however it was not released as a single. It was performed live in various eras and venues throughout John's career, mainly in Britain, and frequently during his solo shows and pairings with percussionist Ray Cooper. John has always said he regards &quot;Skyline Pigeon&quot; as one of the first &quot;great&quot; songs that he and Bernie wrote.

Apart from its earlier appearances on record, a live, solo piano version recorded at London's Royal Festival Hall during the summer of 1974 was also included as the opening number on the &quot;Here&quot; side of the &quot;Here and There&quot; album in 1976, a place it retained in the 1995 2-CD expanded version remixed by the album's original producer Gus Dudgeon. It was also released on Volume 1 of two EltonJohn.com limited edition CDs recorded live in Madison Square Garden, as part of a series of solo performances John gave in October 1999. The song received a brief revival during a UK tour in 2009.

The song was a tremendous hit in [[Brazil]]. A live performance from January 17, 2009, was broadcast on TV along with the rest of an entire concert John performed in [[Sao Paulo]], Brazil. Again in Brazil in 2011, he played the song during a concert at [[Rock in Rio]] in front of 150.000 people in [[Rio de Janeiro]], on [[23 September]].

==1972 version==
In 1972, John re-recorded the song with his band (Dee Murray, Nigel Olsson and Davey Johnstone) during the sessions for &quot;Don't Shoot Me, I'm Only The Piano Player.&quot; The new recording featured piano instead of harpsichord, and strings and oboe arranged by Paul Buckmaster. Originally issued as the B-side of the hit-single &quot;[[Daniel (song)|Daniel]]&quot;, it first appeared on CD in 1988 as part of the DJM issue of the &quot;Lady Samantha&quot; compilation album, then just a few years later in the U.S. and abroad on the 1992 Mercury release ''[[Rare Masters]]'', and finally as a bonus track on the 1995 reissue of ''[[Don't Shoot Me I'm Only the Piano Player]].''

==Personnel==
Original version:
*Elton John - [[harpsichord]], [[organ (music)|organ]], vocals

1972 version:
*Elton John: piano, vocals
*[[Davey Johnstone]]: [[acoustic guitar]]
*[[Dee Murray]]: [[Bass guitar|bass]]
*[[Nigel Olsson]]: [[Drum kit|drums]]
*[[Paul Buckmaster]]: orchestral arrangements

[[Category:1969 songs]]
[[Category:1972 songs]]
[[Category:Ballads]]
[[Category:Pop ballads]]
[[Category:Elton John songs]]
[[Category:Songs with lyrics by Bernie Taupin]]
[[Category:Songs with music by Elton John]]
[[Category:Soft rock songs]]

[[it:Skyline Pigeon]]
[[pt:Skyline Pigeon]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
