<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="958847" ns="0" title="CFCF-DT"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Broadcast |
  call_letters             = CFCF-DT|
  city                     = [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]]|
  station_logo             = [[Image:CTV logo.svg|200px]]|
  station_slogan           = |
  station_branding         = CTV Montreal|
  analog                   = |
  digital                   = 12 ([[very high frequency|VHF]])&lt;br&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 12.1 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])|
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = [[CTV Television Network|CTV]]|
  network                  = |
  airdate                  = January 20, 1961|
  location                 = |
  callsign_meaning         = '''C'''anada's&lt;br&gt;'''F'''irst&lt;br&gt;'''C'''anada's&lt;br&gt;'''F'''inest &lt;br&gt;(taken from former sister radio station '''[[CINW|CFCF-AM]]''', now defunct)|
  former_callsigns         = |
  former_channel_numbers   = '''Analog''':&lt;br&gt;12 (VHF, 1961-2011)|
  owner                    = [[Bell Media]]|
  licensee                 = |
  sister_stations          = [[CKGM]]|
  former_affiliations      = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (January–October 1961)|
  effective_radiated_power = 10.6 [[watt|kW]]|
  HAAT                     = 299.6 m|
  coordinates              = {{coord|45|30|19|N|73|35|29|W|type:landmark}}|
  homepage                 = [http://montreal.ctv.ca/ CTV Montreal]|
}}

'''CFCF-DT''' (now identified on air as '''CTV Montreal''', previously identified as '''CFCF-12''') is a [[CTV Television Network|CTV]]-[[owned and operated station]] located in [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], [[Canada]]. Until August 30, 2011, CFCF broadcasted an analogue signal on channel 12 at a maximum [[Effective radiated power|ERP]] of 325&amp;nbsp;kW.

==History==
===Canadian Marconi Company (1961–1972)===
CFCF-TV was founded by the [[Canadian Marconi Company]] owner of CFCF radio (AM 600, later [[CINW]] on AM 940 before its closure in 2010; and FM 106.5, now [[CKBE-FM]] at 92.5) after several failed attempts to gain a licence, beginning in 1938, and then each year after [[World War II]]. In 1960, it finally gained a licence, and began broadcasting on January 20, [[1961 in television|1961]] at 5.45pm.   It was the second privately-owned English-language station in Quebec; [[CKMI-TV]] in [[Quebec City]] had signed on four years earlier.
[[File:CFCF 1990s.svg|left|120px|thumb|Former CFCF logo used until it was bought out by CTV.]]
The station was originally located above the Avon Theatre.  The first night on-air was fraught with problems.  A power failure interrupted the opening ceremony, and later on, police raided the downstairs ballroom, with sirens blazing and a number of arrests made.  The station's newscast, ''Pulse News,'' faced a few problems because of the noise from the ballroom.  CFCF-AM-FM-TV moved into their own facilities at 405 [[Ogilvy Avenue]] in Montreal's [[Park Extension]] neighborhood on May 19.

Channel 12 joined CTV as a charter affiliate on October 1. However, its relationship with CTV was somewhat acrimonious over the years, in part because it felt CTV's flagship station, [[CFTO-TV]] in [[Toronto]], had too much influence over the network.  This rivalry even dated to preferred alliances with American networks, with CFCF-TV preferring [[NBC]] (due to CFCF-AM's long-time co-affiliation with NBC Radio) and CFTO-TV preferring [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] (as ABC was an original junior partner owner of CFTO-TV, and John Bassett, Baton's owner, had trained with ABC's Detroit and New York affiliates). Both stations had some ties with [[CBS]], notwithstanding CBS' relationship with CBC/Radio-Canada for news.

===Multiple Access (1972–1979)===
In 1972, because of new foreign ownership guidelines implemented by the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]] (CRTC), CFCF-TV (owned by [[General Electric Canada]] through Canadian Marconi/The General Electric Company (UK), Ltd.) and its sister stations CFCF-AM, CFQR-FM and CFCX-SW were sold to computer and telecommunications company [[Multiple Access Ltd.]], owned by the [[Bronfman family]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CFCFArchivesLibraryArchivesCanada&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | author = Library and Archives Canada
  | title = Description of archived material: CFCF (Montreal) fonds
  | date = 2005-08-07
  | url = http://mikan3.archives.ca/pam/public_mikan/index.php?fuseaction=genitem.displayItem&amp;lang=fre&amp;rec_nbr=190543&amp;rec_nbr_list=106964,97903,190543,190316,189452&amp;print_version=yes
  | accessdate = 2007-12-02 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Multiple Access bought the stations after the CRTC refused to approve purchase offers by Baton Broadcasting (after other CTV partners rejected this sale, and Baton's not wanting to purchase the radio operations only—and due historical rivalries between Baton and CFCF), and by [[CHUM Limited]] (because of indecision over which radio stations would be sold to meet radio ownership limits in Montreal). Multiple Access also was co-owner of [[CITY-TV]] in Toronto (with CHUM) during this time. (Both Baton and CHUM-CITY became CTVglobemedia, which was later in turn became [[Bell Media]], the current owner of CFCF).

===CFCF Inc. (1979-1990s)===
In 1979, Multiple Access sold the stations and its production company, Champlain Productions, to CFCF Inc., headed by [[Jean Pouliot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CFCFArchivesLibraryArchivesCanada&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CCF-CINW-AM&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = DuImage
  | first = Bill
  | title = Radio Station History: CINW(CFCF)-AM, Montreal, Corus Entertainment Inc
  | publisher = Canadian Communications Foundation
  | date = 2007-10
  | url = http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/radio/histories.php?id=492&amp;historyID=243
  | accessdate = 2007-12-02 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CCF-JeanPouliot&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Chouinard
  | first = Yvon
  | title = Biographies: Pouliot, Jean Adelard (1923–2004)
  | publisher = Canadian Communications Foundation
  | date = 2004-08
  | url = http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/personalities/personalities.php?id=336
  | accessdate = 2007-12-02 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;  Later on, the station began broadcasting a 24/7 schedule full of classic TV shows and movies on late nights, because of the popularity of [[VHS]] and [[Betamax]] [[Video cassette recorder|VCRs]] by that time.  As of today, the station now airs mostly infomercials on late nights.

This came after a deal by Baton (this time a willing partner) to purchase Multiple Access Montreal operations fell through. CHUM successfully purchased Multiple Access' Toronto operations (its share of CITY-TV).

CFCF Inc., expanded to include the assets of [[CF Cable|CF Cable TV]], acquired by Pouliot in 1982,&lt;ref name=&quot;CNW-JeanPouliot&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | author = Canadian Newswire
  | title = Canada loses one of its broadcasting pioneers
  | publisher = Channel Canada
  | date = 2004-08
  | url = http://www.channelcanada.com/Article528.html
  | accessdate = 2007-12-02 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
went public in 1985.&lt;ref name=&quot;CCF-JeanPouliot&quot;/&gt;

In 1986, CFCF gained a sister station: [[CFJP-TV]], the flagship station of Pouliot's new French language network, Television Quatre-Saisons (TQS, now [[V (TV network)|V]]). CFCF's profits were used to fund the ailing TQS. Two years later, the radio stations were sold to [[Mount-Royal Broadcasting]], and moved out of the CFCF building a year later.

===CanWest Global and Videotron (1990s)===
Financial relief came to the company in the 1990s, thanks to [[CanWest Global]]. CanWest Global invested money into the station, in exchange for applying to the CRTC to operate a Global repeater station in Montreal. However, CanWest Global changed its mind, citing tax problems.  It did, however, allow CFCF to carry some Global programs; it was already airing some programming from [[Citytv]]. This would not be the end of Global's influence at the station.

In 1997, [[TVA (TV network)|TVA]] sold an interest in CKMI to Canwest. The two companies announced plans to turn CKMI into a Global station, along with a CKMI repeater in Montreal and a large studio complex in Montreal. Pouliot was scared by the prospect of new competition and decided to sell his assets to Vidéotron.  However, Vidéotron also owned TVA, which retained a half-interest in CKMI. This would have resulted in one company having a significant stake in all of the private stations in Montreal—CFCF, CKMI, CFJP and TVA flagship [[CFTM-TV]].

As a result, Vidéotron sold CFCF to [[Western International Communications]] (WIC), who also owned [[CHAN-TV|CHAN]] and [[CHEK-TV|CHEK]] in [[British Columbia]], [[CHCH-TV|CHCH]] in [[Ontario]] and several stations in [[Alberta]]. Over the next few years, CFCF would limit its carriage of CTV programming to little more than its contractually-required 40 hours per week, relying on WIC's library of programming to fill out the schedule, due in large part to the historical tensions between WIC and Baton Broadcasting, the new owners of the CTV network. Meanwhile, TQS was sold to [[Quebecor]], and later to [[Cogeco]] and [[Bell Globemedia]] (which later became CTVglobemedia and now known as Bell Media).

===CTV (2001-present)===
[[Image:CFCF-TV.jpg|thumb|left|CFCF-TV's former logo (2002–2005). As of October 2005 logos with the stations' callsigns are no longer used on CTV stations; instead they all use the main CTV logo.]]

CanWest bought WIC's television assets in 2000. However, the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]] (CRTC) would not allow CFCF to be [[twinstick]]ed with CKMI because Montreal's Anglophone population was too small (though it allowed CanWest to keep [[CJNT-TV]], a multicultural station WIC had bought a year earlier). The station was placed under trusteeship, and had to be sold in short order. In 2001, amid all these wranglings over ownership, Bell Globemedia, owner of CTV, bought the station. With the opening of the Fall 2001 television season, CFCF officially adopted the CTV schedule and all non-CTV shows were dropped. The station also adopted a new golden call letter logo similar to all other CTV owned stations, as well as similar promo and newscast graphics. After 40 years of being master of its own house to a large degree, CFCF lost much of that independence and maneuverability through the CTV/Bell Globemedia deal.

With the exception of local newscasts, which all CTV stations have, CFCF's program schedule is identical to every other CTV station. On October 3, 2005, the unique &quot;CFCF&quot; name used for the station ID and its local news, CFCF News (formerly known as Pulse News until the Bell Globemedia purchase), was abolished and simply renamed &quot;CTV&quot; and &quot;CTV News&quot;. So strong was the &quot;Pulse&quot; brand-name that even years after it was eliminated, many viewers still refer to the newscast as &quot;Pulse&quot;. This renaming to &quot;CTV News&quot; was done at all affiliates across the country&amp;nbsp;— to provide a common brand for the entire network. In 2003, CTV Montreal moved to 1205 Papineau Avenue in the eastern part of [[Downtown Montreal|downtown]], and the master control operations were moved to [[9 Channel Nine Court]], the home of CTV flagship CFTO-TV in Toronto. The area has now become Montreal's (and French Canada's) main media district; [[CBC Television|CBC]], [[Global Television Network|Global]], [[Réseau des sports|RDS]], [[V (TV network)|V]] and [[TVA (TV network)|TVA]] are all within several blocks.  

By 2005, Bell Globemedia was considered to be a non-core asset by parent company BCE (Bell Canada Enterprises) and was sold to a group of investors, which includes the Thomson family. The Bell Globemedia group (made up of the entire CTV Network, as well as the ''Globe and Mail'' newspaper and a variety of other channels and media assets) was renamed &quot;CTVGlobemedia&quot; in late-2006. In April 2011 BCE bought full ownership of CTVGlobemedia and changed the name to &quot;Bell Media&quot;.

The new media giant also acquired [[CHUM Limited]]'s holdings in 2006, including the [[A (TV system)|A-Channel]] stations, MuchMusic and a variety of other specialty channels. But the CHUM deal has also raised serious questions about the high degree of media concentration in Canada. This new conglomerate now owns more than one TV station in several Canadian markets&amp;nbsp;— increasing the worry about job losses and cutbacks.

CFCF has always been the number one, top-rated television station for Anglophone Quebecers. As well, a significant number of bilingual Francophones also watch CFCF&amp;nbsp;— for both programming and news&amp;nbsp;— although [[CFTM-TV|CFTM]] ([[TVA (TV network)|TVA]]), [[CFJP-TV|CFJP]] ([[V]]) and [[CBFT]] ([[Télévision de Radio-Canada|Radio-Canada]]) are the obvious market leaders for Quebec's French community.

CFCF's schedule is now identical to flagship CTV station [[CFTO-TV]] in Toronto, with the only minor difference being ''[[Dr. Phil (TV series)|Dr. Phil]]'' and ''[[The Dr. Oz Show]]'' switching their respective time slots. ''The Dr. Oz Show'' airs weekdays at 3:00 p.m (5:00 p.m on CFTO) and ''Dr. Phil'' airs on weekdays at 5:00 p.m (3:00 p.m on CFTO).

Until March 10, 2009, CFCF aired a local 6AM morning newscast, ''First News'', pre-empting the first half hour of ''[[Canada AM]]''; anchored by Herb Luft, it was cancelled in favor of an early start for ''Canada AM'', which will now be seen in its entirety starting at 6AM. Morning news briefs have also been cancelled. Luft will continue his role as reporter for the station. These cancellations are a part of continuing cutbacks made by CTV due to the [[Late 2000s recession|economic crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://montreal.ctv.ca/servlet/an/local/CTVNews/20090310/mtl_cancels_090310/20090310/?hub=MontrealHome CFCF-TV: &quot;CTV Montreal Cancels First News&quot;, 3/10/2009.]&lt;/ref&gt; Another cut was ''Telethon of Stars'' (1977–2009) that aired during the first weekend of December, consecutively, for 32 years. As of December 2010, Telethon of Stars can only be seen through the Internet (via an 8-hour [[webcast]]), with no television equivalent aired.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.fagstein.com/2010/12/01/no-telethon-on-cfcf/ End of Telethon of stars&lt;/ref&gt; 

On August 5, 2009, CTV camera operator, 44-year-old [[Hugh Haugland]] was killed after a helicopter crash near [[Mont-Laurier, Quebec|Mont-Laurier]] about 240 kilometres from Montreal, Haugland was shooting footage of the destruction left behind by a [[Tornadoes of 2009#August 4|tornado]] that touched down in the area on August 4, 2009. The other person killed in the crash was Roger Belanger, a veteran pilot and local businessman who was in his 60s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20090805/helicopter_crash_090805/20090805?hub=TopStories CTV camera operator killed in helicopter crash 8/5/2009.] CTV.ca&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://montreal.ctv.ca/servlet/an/local/CTVNews/20090805/mtl_haugland_090805/20090805/?hub=MontrealHome CFCF-TV: &quot;Condolences for the Haugland and Belanger families&quot; 8/5/2009.] CTVMontreal.ca&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newswire.ca/en/releases/archive/August2009/05/c2881.html Statement on the Death of CTV Cameraman Hugh Haugland] CTVglobemedia press release via [[Canada NewsWire]], August 5, 2009,&lt;/ref&gt;

Most recently, the station began airing promos for Bell Media's secondary television network, [[CTV Two]], despite the fact that CTV Two stations are only available on satellite, with no Quebec locations.

==Availability==
On cable, CFCF is seen on [[Vidéotron]] channel 11 in the Montreal area (channel 7 in SD and channel 607 in HD on digital cable), [[Charter Communications|Charter]] [[Plattsburgh, New York|Plattsburgh]] channel 13 and [[Comcast]] [[Burlington, Vermont|Burlington]] channel 21; it is also seen on [[Bell TV]] via channels 205 (SD) and 1031 (HD), [[Shaw Direct]] via channel 312, and on Bell Fibe via channels 205 (SD) and 1205 (HD). Most cable distributors in Quebec also carry CFCF, as it is the only CTV station in the province. Despite having only one transmitter, its signal reaches all the way to the [[Laurentides]] and [[Lanaudière]] regions, and also decently covers the [[Champlain Valley]] region in [[Vermont]] and [[New York]].

Before 1997, when [[CHCH-DT|CHCH]] and [[CITY-DT|CITY]] launched rebroadcast transmitters in the [[Ottawa]] region, local cable companies there carried CFCF as well. Because CHCH and CFCF were sharing some programs, CFCF was removed from these systems, except for [[Rogers Cable]].

==Programming==
The station now airs all of the standard CTV schedule. In the past, some children's programming was pre-empted, because of provincial regulations on advertising; the station now carries CTV's few remaining children's programs with [[public service announcement]]s during ad breaks. As well, CFCF did not carry either ''[[Wheel of Fortune (U.S. game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]'' or ''[[Jeopardy!]]'' when these were part of the standard CTV schedule; both were picked up by [[CBC Television|CBC]] nationally in fall 2008.

As with most Canadian stations, the prime-time schedule is usually synchronized with the original [[United States|American]] airings of the same programs because Plattsburgh/Burlington's [[WPTZ]], [[WVNY]], [[WFFF-TV]] and [[WCAX]] are all available on cable in Montreal. CFCF's ratings do generally top all of those stations, as well as the regional [[CBMT|CBC Montreal]] station.

==News operation==
[[Image:Dodge Grand Caravan (CTV Montreal).JPG|A fifth-generation [[Dodge Grand Caravan]] from CTV News.|thumb|right]]
CFCF's newscasts, ''CTV News'' (formerly ''CFCF News'', formerly ''Pulse News''), are headed up by the main weekday Noon and 6 p.m. anchors [[Mutsumi Takahashi]] &amp; [[Todd van der Heyden]], News at 11:30 with Catherine Sherriffs, and Weekend News at 6 p.m. Tarah Schwartz &amp; Paul Karwatsky and Weekend News 11:30 p.m. with Paul Karwatsky. CTV Montreal produces 19 newscasts each week. CFCF also houses CTV's National Montreal News Bureau.

One of its most famous anchors, [[Bill Haugland]], is now retired; his last show aired on November 30, 2006. Bill worked at CFCF for more than 40 years. He covered major stories in the 1960s and 1970s before becoming the lead anchor at CFCF in the late-1970s. Bill was an institution and in a special &quot;Farewell to Bill&quot; show broadcast on his final day, he was heralded by colleagues, viewers and former prime ministers alike. Another veteran newscaster, Brian Britt, who replaced Bill Haugland in 2006 when he retired, retired in July of 2008, and was then fully replaced by [[Todd van der Heyden]]. Britt's last broadcast was on July 24, 2008. On May 11, 2011, it was announced that long time late night news anchor [[Debra Arbec]] left the station to become the main anchor at [[CBC Montreal]]. Various other anchors filled in the void for the remainder of May and then June 2011. CTV reporter/former CJAD &amp; CJFM news announcer Catherine Sherriffs became Arbec's permenant replacement on July 4, 2011.

===News/station presentation===
====Newscast titles====
*''Pulse News'' (1961–2001)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fnW2Cc7JF0Y CFCF Pulse Newsbreak 1995]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''CFCF News'' (2001–2005)
*''[[CTV News]]'' (2005–present)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QJeek9ucsiM CTV Montreal News (Opening/Recap/Closing) - September 17th, 2010 ]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Station slogans====
*&quot;Montreal's Watching CTV&quot; (2005–2008)
{{inc-video}}

===News team===
'''Anchors'''
*Paul Karwatsky - weekends at 6 and 11:30 p.m.; also reporter and weekday fill-in anchor
*Catherine Sherriffs - weeknights at 11:30 p.m.; also reporter and fill-in anchor
*Tarah Schwartz - weekends at 6 p.m.; also reporter and weekday fill-in anchor
*[[Mutsumi Takahashi]] - weekdays at noon and weeknights at 6 p.m.
*[[Todd van der Heyden]] - weekdays at noon and weeknights at 6 p.m.

'''Weather team'''
*Lori Graham - lead weather specialist; weekdays at noon, and weeknights at 6 and 11:30 p.m.
*Lise McAuley - weather specialist; weekends at 6 and 11:30 p.m., also weekday fill-in
*Randy Renaud - weather specialist; fill-in (also an announcer at [[CHOM]])

'''Sports team'''
*Randy Tieman - lead sports anchor/reporter
*Brian Wilde - sports anchor/reporter
*André Corbeil - sports anchor/reporter
*Paul Graif - sports anchor/reporter
*Ted Bird - columnist

'''Reporters'''
*Annie DeMelt - general assignment reporter (currently on maternity leave until 2012)
*Derek Conlon - general assignment reporter
*Stephane Giroux - legislative affairs reporter
*Nadine Ishack - &quot;Sunday Bite&quot; feature reporter
*Maya Johnson - general assignment reporter
*Tania Krywiak - general assignment reporter
*Anne Lewis - general assignment reporter (currently on extended medical leave)
*Rob Lurie - general assignment reporter
*Christine Long - entertainment reporter &quot;What's On&quot;
*Mose Persico - feature reporter &quot;Mose at the Movies&quot;; host &quot;Reel to Real&quot; &amp; &quot;Entertainment Wrap&quot; featurettes
*Camille Ross - general assignment reporter
*Aphrodite Salas - general assignment reporter
*Cindy Sherwin - general assignment reporter; also fill-in anchor
*Caroline van Vlaardingen - investigative/consumer reporter &quot;On Your Side&quot;; also fill-in anchor

== Digital television and high definition==
The station began providing a High-Definition feed to Videotron and Bell Fibe on December 1, 2009 and in September 2010 respectively. It signed-on over the air on temporary pre-transition channel 51 on January 28, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RrpItyPxQfM Digital on air] YouTube, January 28, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 31, 2011, the deadline for the [[Digital television in Canada|analogue television shutdown and digital conversion]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Analog to Digital&quot;&gt;http://digitaltv.gc.ca/eng/1282825334983/1282825604404&lt;/ref&gt; CFCF shut down its analog signal and temporary digital transmitter just after its late night newscast and began its final full power digital transmission on channel 12.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://ctvmontreal.ca/ CTV Montreal]
*[http://www.broadcasting-history.ca/listings_and_histories/television/histories.php?id=105&amp;historyID=78 Canadian Communications Foundation - CFCF-TV History]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20091027055556/http://geocities.com/tvhatton/mtl-local/cfcf  CFCF at TV Hat]
*{{RecnetCanada|CFCF-TV}}
*{{TV Fool|CFCF}}

{{MTL TV}}
{{CTV Stations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cfcf}}
[[Category:CTV Television Network stations|FCF]]
[[Category:Television stations in Montreal|FCF]]
[[Category:Channel 12 TV stations in Canada]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1961]]
[[Category:Quebec Anglophone media]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball over-the-air television broadcasters]]

[[fr:CFCF-DT]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
