<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="960532" ns="0" title="Share-alike"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Cc-sa.svg|thumb|The [[Creative Commons]] icon for Share-Alike, a variant of the [[copyleft]] symbol]]
'''Share-Alike''' is a descriptive term used in the [[Creative Commons]] project for [[copyright]] [[licenses]] which include certain [[copyleft]] provisions. The Share-Alike license comes in two varieties, '''CC-BY-SA''' and '''CC-BY-NC-SA'''.

==Share-alike license types==

As all Creative Commons licenses, share-alike licenses require [[attribution (copyright)|attribution]]. Share-alike means that all derivatives of a work to be licensed under the same (or a compatible) license as the original. Thus, if a person were to use parts of a BY-SA movie to create a new short film, that new short film would also need to be licensed as BY-SA. According to Creative Commons, the advantage of this license is that future users are not able to add new restrictions to a derivative of your work; their derivatives must be licensed the same way.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://wiki.creativecommons.org/Share_Alike |title=Share Alike |accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Share-Alike license is similar to the [[GNU Project]]'s [[GNU General Public License|General Public License]] (GPL) and [[GNU Free Documentation License|Free Documentation License]] (GFDL).

There are two varieties of Share-Alike licenses. The first, CC-BY-SA, allows commercial use. The second, CC-BY-NC-SA, which requires [[non-commercial]] use, only is Share-Alike but is not [[free content]] (and not copyleft, according to some critics).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://robmyers.org/weblog/2008/02/noncommercial-sharealike-is-not-copyleft.html |title=NonCommercial Sharealike is not Copyleft}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==CC-BY-SA and Free Culture Works==

Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike licenses are based on the principles of the [[Free Software movement]]. As applied to content, these principles require a license to grant the following essential freedoms to ALL users of licensed works:

:* the freedom to use the work and enjoy the benefits of using it
:* the freedom to study the work and to apply knowledge acquired from it
:* the freedom to make and redistribute copies, in whole or in part, of the information or expression
:* the freedom to make changes and improvements, and to distribute derivative works 

These 4 freedoms are taken directly from the [http://freedomdefined.org/Definition Definition of Free Culture Works]


By contrast, there are also many [[permissive free software licences]] which do not require share-alike terms to be applied, thus permitting users to make modifications and improvements and apply a modified and more restrictive license.

==History of ShareAlike Versions==

Over the years, Creative Commons has issued 4 versions of the BY-SA and BY-NC-SA licenses (1.0, 2.0, 2.5, and 3.0). 

*Attribution-ShareAlike Version 1.0 Generic - Released December, 2002[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0/]
**Attribution-NonCommerical-ShareAlike Version 1.0 Generic[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/1.0/]

*Attribution-ShareAlike Version 2.0 Generic - Released May, 2004[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/]
**Attribution-NonCommerical-ShareAlike Version 2.0 Generic[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.0/]

*Attribution-ShareAlike Version 2.5 Generic - Released June, 2005[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/]
**Attribution-NonCommerical-ShareAlike Version 2.5 Generic[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/]

*Attribution-ShareAlike Version 3.0 Unported - Released March, 2007[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/]
**Attribution-NonCommerical-ShareAlike Version 3.0 Unported[http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/]
*:The 3.0 licenses added a compatibility clause. Creative Commons may declare a license compatible with ShareAlike, allowing it to be used instead of the exact same license for derivatives.

==Adoption==

In June, 2009 the [[Wikipedia community]] and [[Wikimedia Foundation]] board approved the adoption of the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike (CC BY-SA) license as the main content license for Wikipedia and other Wikimedia sites.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Text_of_Creative_Commons_Attribution-ShareAlike_3.0_Unported_License&lt;/ref&gt; This decision was hailed by many as a win for Free Culture as well as visionary leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://creativecommons.org/weblog/entry/15411 |title=Wikipedia + CC BY-SA = Free Culture Win!}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Copyleft]]
*[[Wikipedia:Text of Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License|Wikipedia's cc-by-sa license]]

==External links==
*[http://creativecommons.org/about/licenses/ Creative Commons licenses explained]
*[[Wikipedia:Text of Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License]] 
*[http://freedomdefined.org/Definition]

[[Category:Copyright licenses]]
[[Category:Copyleft]]

[[da:Share-alike]]
[[id:Pembagian serupa]]
[[ja:継承 (クリエイティブ・コモンズ)]]
[[ru:Share-alike]]
[[vi:Giấy phép Creative Commons#Chia sẻ tương tự]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
