<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="965016" ns="0" title="Ohio State Buckeyes"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
|name= The Ohio State Buckeyes
|logo= Ohio State Buckeyes logo.svg
|university= The Ohio State University
|conference= [[Big Ten]]
|division= [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|director= [[Gene Smith (athletic director)|Gene Smith]]
|city= Columbus
|state= Ohio
|stateabb= OH
|teams= 19 men and 20 women varsity teams
|stadium= [[Ohio Stadium]]
|baseballfield= [[Bill Davis Stadium]]
|arena= [[Jerome Schottenstein Center]]
|arena2= [[OSU Ice Arena]] &lt;br&gt; [[St. John Arena]] &lt;br&gt; [[Jesse Owens Memorial Stadium]]
|mascot= [[Brutus Buckeye]]
|nickname= [[Ohio Buckeye|Buckeyes]]
|fightsong= [[Across the Field]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Buckeye Battle Cry]]
|Alma mater= Carmen Ohio
|rival= Michigan Wolverines
|color1= Scarlet
|color2= Grey
|hex1= FF2000
|hex2= AAAAAA
|pageurl= http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com/
|pagename= ohiostatebuckeyes.com
}}
'''The Ohio State Buckeyes''' are the intercollegiate sports teams and players of [[The Ohio State University]], named after the state tree, the [[Ohio Buckeye|Buckeye]].  The Buckeyes participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] in all sports and the [[Big Ten Conference]] in most sports. The [[Ohio State Buckeyes men's ice hockey]] program competes in the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]], and its [[Ohio State Buckeyes women's ice hockey|women's hockey]] program competes in the [[Western Collegiate Hockey Association]]. The school colors are [[Scarlet (color)|scarlet]] and [[grey]]. Ohio State's mascot is [[Brutus Buckeye]].

The Ohio State University is one of only four universities to have won a NCAA national championship in [[baseball]], men's [[basketball]] and [[American football|football]].  Ohio State has also won national championships in men's swimming &amp; diving, men's outdoor track &amp; field, men's volleyball, men's golf, men's gymnastics, men's fencing, co-ed fencing, and synchronized swimming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Schools with the Most NCAA National Championships | publisher = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] | url = http://www.ncaa.org/champadmin/champs_listing1.html | accessdate = 2006-08-14 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060616124822/http://ncaa.org/champadmin/champs_listing1.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the inception of the [[NACDA Director's Cup|Athletic Director's Cup]], Ohio State has finished in the top 25 each year, including top 6 finishes in three of the last five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = U.S. Sports Academy Directors' Cup Previous Scoring | publisher = [[NACDA Director's Cup|Athletic Director's Cup]] | url = http://nacda.cstv.com/directorscup/nacda-directorscup-previous-scoring.html | accessdate = 2006-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the 2005-2006 school year Ohio State became this first Big Ten team to win conference championships in football, men's basketball and women's basketball in the same season. They repeated this feat in the 2006-2007 season, which also included a February 25, 2007 men's basketball game which saw the Buckeyes defeat the [[Wisconsin Badgers]] in the Big Ten's first one-versus-two basketball game.

A few of the many outstanding sports figures who were student athletes at Ohio State include [[Jesse Owens]], “The Buckeye Bullet,”  (track and field), [[John Havlicek]], [[Jerry Lucas]], and [[Katie Smith]] (basketball), [[Frank Howard (baseball player)|Frank Howard]] (baseball), [[Jack Nicklaus]] (golf), [[Archie Griffin]] (football running back, the only two-time [[Heisman Trophy]] winner), and [[Chic Harley]] (three-time All-American football running back).  Hall of Fame coaches at Ohio State have included [[Paul Brown]] and [[Woody Hayes]] (football), [[Fred Taylor (basketball coach)|Fred Taylor]] (men's basketball).  Notable sports figures in Ohio State history may be inducted into the [[Ohio State Varsity O Hall of Fame]].

==Football==

{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: right; margin-left: 1em;&quot; width=&quot;250px&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; !bgcolor=999999| &lt;font color=990000&gt;'''OSU Heisman Trophy Winners&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| '''Year''' || '''Player'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |&lt;hr&gt;
|-
| 1944 || [[Les Horvath]]
|-
| 1950 || [[Vic Janowicz]]
|-
| 1955 || [[Howard Cassady]]
|-
| 1974 || [[Archie Griffin]]
|-
| 1975 || Archie Griffin
|-
| 1995 || [[Eddie George]]
|-
| 2006 || [[Troy Smith]]
|-
|}

{{main|Ohio State Buckeyes football}}
*'''National Champions''' : 1942, 1954, 1957, 1961, 1968, 1970, 2002
*'''Big Ten Champions''' :1916, 1917, 1920, 1935, 1939, 1942, 1944, 1949, 1954, 1955, 1957, 1961, 1968, 1969, 1970, 1971, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1975, 1976, 1977, 1979, 1981, 1984, 1986, 1993, 1996, 1998, 2002, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009
*'''[[Ohio Athletic Conference|OAC]] Champions''' :1906, 1912

==Men's basketball==
{{Main|Ohio State Buckeyes men's basketball}}

The Ohio State men's basketball team has played in 10 NCAA [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|Final Fours]], winning the championship in 1960, when they were led by [[Basketball Hall of Fame]]rs [[Jerry Lucas]], [[John Havlicek]], and [[Bob Knight]] off the bench. A Buckeye has been named first team [[All American]] 23 times, including five two-time All Americans and one three-time All American. Between 1960 and 1964 Ohio State won five consecutive Big Ten championships, an achievement that has yet to be matched.

In 2004, The Ohio State University fired men's basketball coach [[Jim O'Brien (basketball, born 1949)|Jim O'Brien]] for recruiting violations and self-imposed a one year penalty, including a ban on post-season play and reduction of scholarships. In light of these University self-imposed penalties, the NCAA Division I Committee on infractions merely placed The Ohio State University on three years probation for the violations, and gave heavier penalties to Coach O'Brien and a former assistant coach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | title = The Ohio State University and Former Men's Basketball Coaches Penalized for  Infractions | publisher = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] | date = 2006-03-10 | url = http://www2.ncaa.org/portal/media_and_events/press_room/2006/march/20060310_osu_infractions_rls.html | accessdate = 2006-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=May 2011}} The lightness of this judgment was seen as encouragement for schools to be proactive in responding to violations. Nevertheless, O'Brien successfully sued Ohio State for improper termination. Thad Matta, the current coach of the Buckeyes, took over O'Brien's spot in 2004. Ohio State recruited such talents as [[Greg Oden]], and [[Mike Conley, Jr.]] to start the 2006-2007 year. The Buckeyes finished the season with a 27-3 record; won the Big Ten tournament, and earned a number 1 seed for the NCAA tournament. After a very close game with state rival Xavier, and a thrilling 20 point come from behind victory against the [[University of Tennessee|Tennessee Volunteers]], the Buckeyes managed to hold off [[Georgetown University|Georgetown Hoyas]] 67-60 to reach the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|Championship Game]] for the first time since 1962, which they lost to defending NCAA champions [[University of Florida|Florida Gators]], 84-75. The Buckeyes ended the 2006-2007 season with a record of 35-4. In the 2009-2010 Season, the Buckeyes won the Big Ten Championship. In the 2010-2011 season the Buckeyes won the regular season Big Ten Championship, and the Big Ten Tournament Championship going 32-2 overall, and winning 20 straight home games, receiving honors of the #1 overall seed in the NCAA March Madness Tournament in the East Region. The Buckeyes were defeated by the [[University of Kentucky]] in the Sweet 16, 62-60.

==Women's basketball==
{{main|Ohio State Buckeyes women's basketball}}

Currently coached by Jim Foster, the [[Ohio State]] women's basketball team plays its home games in the [[Jerome Schottenstein Center]], which they moved into in 1998.  Prior to 1998, they played at [[St. John Arena]]. They have won 10 [[Big Ten]] titles, which is the most in the conference&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com/fls/17300/pdf/wbb/guide/0708_p156to180.pdf?ATCLID=945094&amp;SPSID=89262&amp;SPID=10422&amp;DB_OEM_ID=17300|title= Big Ten Championship Teams|accessdate=2008-02-23 |pages= 172|format= PDF|work= History and Tradition|publisher= Ohio State Athletic Department}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have 14 appearances in the NCAA Tournament, the most recent being in 2007. In 1993 they lost to the [[Texas Tech Lady Raiders basketball|Texas Tech Lady Raiders]] 84-82 for the National Title, while they captured the NIT title in 2001, beating the [[New Mexico Lobos]] 62-61.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.womensnit.com/2001_postseason1.htm|title= 2001 Postseason WNIT|accessdate=2008-02-24 |work= www.womensnit.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Notable alumni include former [[All-Americans]] [[Katie Smith]] and [[Jessica Davenport]].

==Golf==

Ohio State's two golf courses, the Scarlet and the Gray, were completed in 1938.  [[Scarlet Golf Course|The Scarlet]] was designed by architect [[Alister MacKenzie]], who designed the [[The Masters Tournament|Masters]] course at [[Augusta National]].  However, his original design was not implemented fully, and the greens were the only part of the course that truly resembled his designs.  Golf magazines annually rate the Scarlet Course as one of the top collegiate courses in the nation. The Scarlet recently underwent a $4.2 million renovation under the supervision of Jack Nicklaus.  Ohio State has won the [[NCAA Division I Men's Golf Championships]] in 1945 and 1979.  Five times, Buckeye men have won the NCAA golf individual championship: John Lorms in 1945, [[Tom Nieporte]] in 1951, Rick Jones in 1956, [[Jack Nicklaus]] in 1961 and Clark Burroughs in 1985.

==Baseball==
{{main|Ohio State Buckeyes baseball}}

Ohio State has played baseball since 1881,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com/fls/17300/pdfs/OSUbaseballrecords.pdf|title=Records by Year|accessdate=2008-02-25 |format= PDF|work= History and Traditions|publisher= Ohio State Athletic Department |pages= 94}}&lt;/ref&gt; winning a national championship in 1966 along with 14 Big Ten regular-season titles and eight Big Ten tournament titles. The Buckeyes baseball team was the first Ohio State sports team. The team is currently coached by Greg Beals and play their home games at [[Bill Davis Stadium]], which opened in 1997. Going into the 2008 season the Buckeyes all-time record is 2228-1427-38. Notable alumni include [[Frank Howard (baseball)|Frank Howard]], [[Nick Swisher]] and two time All-American [[Steve Arlin]].

==Synchronized swimming==
{{Unsourced section|date=May 2011}}
In the team event, Ohio State has won 24 collegiate championships between 1977, the first year of the collegiate national championships, and 2004. Head coach Mary Jo Ruggieri led the team to 17 wins between 1977 and 1995, and Linda Lichter-Witter added seven more since 1996. Ohio State also has taken 61 individual honors in that span, including 11 by Karen and Sarah Josephson.

==Men's Gymnastics==
The Ohio State gymnastics team has won three national titles and nine Big Ten titles, and has produced 4 Nissen Award winners (The Heisman Trophy of Men's Gymnastics). The team is currently coached by Rustam Sharipov. The Buckeyes have all their competitions at [[St. John Arena]] in [[Columbus, Ohio]].

Some of the more notable Buckeye alumni include Don Perry, the first OSU All-American in the sport (Trampoline - 1954 - 4th place), brothers Seth and Noah Riskin - Co-national Champions (Parallel Bars - 1985 - 1st place), and Mike Racanelli - Ohio State's first Nissen winner in 1990. Racanelli also went on to win Gymnastic's first ''Ohio State Male Athlete of the Year'' Award that same year, given out annually to the athlete who displays the best performance in his sport (regardless of grade).

Following later in Racanelli's footsteps were other Nissen winners Kip Simons (1994), Blaine Wilson (1997) and Jamie Natalie (2001). Blaine Wilson (1995, 1996, 1997) and Jamie Natalie (2000, 2001) also went on to win ''Ohio State Male Athlete of the Year''. Raj Bhavsar was the only other Men's Gymnast to win ''Ohio State Athlete of the Year'' which he accomplished in 2002.

On the Olympic and World Championship stage, OSU Men's Gymnastics is well represented, by gymnasts and coaches. The Olympian list includes: Miles Avery (asst coach 1996, 2000, 2004, 2008), Peter Kormann (Athlete in 1976, Head Coach 1996, 2000), Raj Bhavsar (2004, 2008), Jamie Natalie (2000), Gil Pinto (1988), Kip Simons (1994) and Blaine Wilson (1996, 2000, 2004).

Two gymnasts who trained at the Ohio State facilities under coach Miles Avery, but were not NCAA Athletes due to eligibility rules, were [[Paul Hamm|Paul]] and [[Morgan Hamm]] - twin brothers from Wisconsin. Paul later went on to win the first ever Olympic Gold medal in the Men's Gymnastics All-Around competition for the United States.

In 2011, Senior co-captain, Brandon Wynn, won his second national championship on rings. Brandon Wynn, Ty Echard, Kris Done and Jeff Treleaven earned All-America honors. In all, the seven All-America honors tie the second-best single-season performance in program history and are the most laurels since the 2005 campaign.

== Ice hockey ==
{{main|Ohio State Buckeyes men's ice hockey|Ohio State Buckeyes women's ice hockey}}
Ohio State men's ice hockey team was established in 1961 and played at the [[OSU Ice Rink]] until 1999 when they moved into [[Value City Arena]]. The Buckeyes compete in the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]] (CCHA). They have won one conference championship in 1972, the first year of the CCHA, and the tournament in 1974 and 2004. The Buckeyes have made it to the [[NCAA Men's Ice Hockey Championship|NCAA tournament]] in 1997, 1998, 1999, 2003, 2004, 2005, and 2009, and went to the semi-finals in 1998. They have only retired one number, #22 [[Paul Pooley]].

The OSU women’s ice hockey team was started in 1999 and competes in the [[Western Collegiate Hockey Association]] (WCHA). The Buckeyes have yet to make an NCAA post season appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=U.S. College Hockey Online|url=http://www.uscho.com/stats/history/ohio-state/womens-hockey/2010-2011/|title=Ohio State Women's Hockey Team History|accessdate=June 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable Buckeye alumni include Olympians [[Emma Laaksonen]], [[Tessa Bonhomme]], and [[Lisa Chesson]].

==Tennis==

The Men’s and Women’s Varsity Tennis teams have showed success both individually and as a team. Both the men's and women's teams share the outdoor tennis facility, the Stickney Tennis Center, dedicated in 1993. When the weather takes them indoors, both teams play at the Varsity Tennis Center, which was recently completed in November 2007. The outdoor facility has 12 courts and the indoor has six courts and are both located in [[Columbus, Ohio]].

Men's Tennis - [[Big Ten]] Championships - 1915 (co-champions), 1943, 1991, 2001, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010.
[[NCAA]] Men's Tennis Tournament Team Appearances (since 1977) - 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010.  The Men's tennis team has 23 NCAA Singles Appearances, 11 NCAA Doubles Appearances and eight All-Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohio State Buckeyes Web site&quot;&gt;[http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com Ohio State Buckeyes Web site]&lt;/ref&gt;

Women's Tennis - Big Ten Championships - 1974, 1975, 1976, 1977, 1978, 1979 - Note: The Big Ten officially began sponsoring championships for women with the 1981-82 season.  Since then, Ohio State has yet to win a Big Ten Championship.
NCAA Women's Tennis Tournament Team Appearances - 1996, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2008, 2009.  The Women have five NCAA Singles Appearances, four NCAA Doubles Appearances and two All-Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohio State Buckeyes Web site&quot;/&gt;

==Soccer==
{{see|Ohio State Buckeyes men's soccer}}

==Olympians And Track==
[[Image:Jesse Owens1.jpg|thumb|200px|Jesse Owens]]Ohio State has produced over two hundred Olympic athletes, most notably [[Jesse Owens]] who won four Olympic gold medals at the [[1936 Summer Olympics|1936 Berlin Olympics]] and is one of the greatest Olympians in history. In all, 48 Ohio State athletes have combined for a total of 77 Olympic medals which includes 33 gold, 28 silver and 16 bronze medals. Ohio State's track team is coached by Hobert Gregand, and plays all home meets at [[Jesse Owens Memorial Stadium]]. The Buckeyes' track team is also famous for being the first Buckeye team in any sport to win a national title.

==National Championships==
The Ohio State University has 62 total team national titles.  Of these, 23 are NCAA championships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckeye Champions&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Buckeye Champions | publisher = Ohio State Buckeyes | url = http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com/ViewArticle.dbml?&amp;DB_OEM_ID=17300&amp;ATCLID=925232 | accessdate = 2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Ohio State Basketball quick facts | publisher = Ohio State Buckeyes | url = http://ohiostatebuckeyes.com/fls/17300/pdf/mbb/quick-facts.pdf?SPSID=87813&amp;SPID=10421&amp;DB_OEM_ID=17300 | accessdate = 2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Ohio State Finishes 14th at Cheerleading National Championship | publisher = Ohio State Buckeyes | url = http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=89177&amp;SPID=10642&amp;DB_OEM_ID=17300&amp;ATCLID=967672 | accessdate = 2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Buckeye athletics program also has 299 individual national champions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Buckeye Champions&quot;/&gt;

*Men's
**Baseball: '''1966'''
**Basketball: '''1960''', 1986 (NIT), 2008 (NIT)
**Fencing: '''1942''', '''2004'''
**Football: 1942, 1954, 1957, 1961, 1968, 1970, 2002
**Golf: '''1945, 1979'''
**Gymnastics: '''1985, 1996, 2001'''
**Swimming &amp; Diving: '''1943, 1945, 1946, 1947, 1949, 1950, 1952, 1954, 1955, 1956, 1962'''
**Outdoor Track &amp; Field:''' 1929'''
**Volleyball:''' 2011'''
*Women's
**Synchronized swimming: 1977, 1978, 1979, 1980, 1982, 1983, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2009
**Pistol: 2003, 2004, 2009
*Coed
**Cheerleading: 1993
**Fencing: '''2004, 2008'''
**Pistol: 2000
&lt;br&gt;'''Bold''' indicates an NCAA championship.

==Big Ten Champions==
===Men's===
*'''Baseball''': 1917, 1924, 1943, 1951, 1955, 1965, 1966, 1967, 1991, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1999, 2001, 2009
*'''Basketball''': 1925, 1933, 1939, 1944, 1946, 1950, 1960, 1961, 1962, 1963, 1964, 1968, 1971, 1991, 2000, 2002, 2006, 2007, 2010, 2011
*'''Cross Country''': 1923
*'''Football''': 1916, 1917,  1920, 1935, 1939, 1942, 1944, 1949, 1954, 1955, 1957, 1961, 1968, 1969, 1970, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1975, 1976, 1977, 1979, 1981, 1984, 1986, 1993, 1996, 1998, 2002, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010
*'''Golf''': 1928, 1945, 1951, 1977, 1978, 1979, 1980, 1982, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1995, 1996, 1997, 2004
*'''Hockey ([[CCHA]])''': 1972, 2004
*'''Gymnastics''': 1983, 1985, 1987, 1993, 1994, 1996, 1997, 2001, 2002, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008
*'''Indoor Track''': 1942, 1948, 1949, 1950, 1993
*'''Outdoor Track''': 1942, 1948, 1992, 1993
*'''Soccer''': 2000, 2007, 2009
*'''Swimming''': 1938, 1943, 1946, 1947, 1949, 1950, 1951, 1952, 1953, 1954, 1955, 1956, 2010
*'''Tennis''': 1915, 1943, 1991, 2001, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009
*'''Volleyball''' ([[Midwestern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association|MIVA]]): 1969, 1972, 1975, 1977, 1978, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1986, 1987, 1993, 1995, 1996, 1997, 2000, 2004, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011
*'''Wrestling''':1923, 1951

===Women's===
*'''Basketball''': 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989, 1993, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009
*'''Field Hockey''': 2006
*'''Golf''': 1983, 1984, 1985, 1988, 1993, 1997, 1999, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005
*'''Gymnastics''': 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987
*'''Rowing''': 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2006
*'''Soccer''': 2010
*'''Softball''': 1990, 2007
*'''Indoor Track''': 2011
*'''Outdoor Track''': 2011
*'''Swimming''': 1982, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986
*'''Volleyball''': 1989, 1991, 1994

==Media==
On April 2, 2009, Ohio State signed a 10-year media-rights agreement with IMG College and RadiOhio, worth nearly $128 million, the largest such agreement in college sports.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncaa.org/wps/ncaa?ContentID=47819 Ohio State announces media deal]&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Ohio State University Marching Band==
{{main|The Ohio State University Marching Band}}

The Ohio State University Marching Band (nicknamed &quot;The Best Damn Band In The Land&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Director Dr. Jon Woods claims, &quot;Supposedly at a pep rally one year, Woody Hayes stood up after the band played a song and said, 'That's the best damn band in the land!' That's all it took.  When Woody says something, it's law.&quot;&lt;br&gt;{{cite news |last=Miller |first=Rusty|title=From O-H-I-O to TBDBITL with the OSMB |publisher=[[Associated Press]] |date=2006-11-15 |accessdate=2007-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is currently under direction of Dr. Jon R. Woods. This all brass band has 225 members, and was first formed in 1878. The band has traditions including a [[Marching band#Field marching|field march]] that forms a &quot;Script Ohio&quot;, during which, a senior [[sousaphone]] player gets to &quot;dot the i&quot; in the word Ohio.

==School colors==
[[Image:Brutus in TX 2006.JPG|thumb|Brutus Buckeye]]
The Ohio State school colors of scarlet and gray were chosen by a committee of three students (Curtis C. Howard, Harwood R. Pool, and Alice Townshend) prior to the school's first graduation ceremony in 1878.  The committee's original recommendation was to be orange and black.  The committee soon discovered that Princeton already used the colors, however, and changed their recommendation.&lt;ref&gt;J. H. Galbraith, &quot;Choosing the University Colors,&quot; The Ohio State University Monthly, Dec. 1914-Jan. 1915, pp. 11-13&lt;/ref&gt;  For this reason some references claim that Ohio State's original school colors were orange and black.  This claim is not quite accurate, in that the committee never filed the original report with that recommendation.

==Pageantry==
:'''Team Colors:'''  [[Scarlet (color)|Scarlet]] and [[Grey]]
:'''Outfitter:''' [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]]
:'''Fight Songs:''' [[Across the Field]], [[Buckeye Battle Cry]]
:'''Often Played Songs:''' [[Hang on Sloopy]], [[Le Régiment de Sambre et Meuse|Le Regiment]]
:'''Alma mater:''' [[Carmen Ohio]]
:'''Nicknames:''' [[Ohio Buckeye|Buckeyes]] (officially adopted in 1950&lt;ref&gt;Walsh, Christopher (2009). ''Ohio State Football Football Huddleup'', Triumph Books (Random House, Inc.), ISBN 978-1-60078-186-5, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;), The Bucks, The Silver Bullets
:'''Mascot:''' [[Brutus Buckeye]]
:'''Rivalries:''' [[Michigan Wolverines]], [[Illinois Fighting Illini]], &amp; [[Penn State Nittany Lions]]
:'''Marching Band:''' [[The Ohio State University Marching Band]], known as TBDBITL, or The Best Damn Band In The Land. Famous for &quot;[[The Ohio State University Marching Band#Script Ohio|Script Ohio]]&quot; and the &quot;[[The Ohio State University Marching Band#Ramp Entrance|Ramp Entrance]]&quot;. The dotting of the &quot;i&quot; in &quot;Script Ohio&quot; by a sousaphone (tuba) player who high-kicks out and does a giant bow to the crowd was voted the #1 greatest sports tradition ever, in [[Athlon Sports]], [[ESPN]], and ''[[Sports Illustrated]].''
:'''Radio Network''' [[The Ohio State Buckeyes Radio Network]]; [[WBNS (AM)]] 1460 The Fan and 97.1 FM for
:'''Announcers''' [[Paul Keels]] (Play By Play); [[Jim Lachey]] (Color (football)); [[Marty Bannister]] (Sideline (football)); [[Ron Stokes]] (Color (basketball))

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ohiostatebuckeyes.com/ Ohio State athletics website]
*[http://www.latare.com/buckeyesdigest.htm Ohio State Buckeyes news and video feed]

{{Ohio State University|Athletics}}
{{Big Ten Conference}}
{{Western Collegiate Hockey Association}}
{{MIVA Conference}}
{{Ohio Sports}}

[[Category:Ohio State Buckeyes|*]]
[[Category:Sports in Columbus, Ohio]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]

[[es:Ohio State Buckeyes]]
[[fr:Buckeyes d'Ohio State]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
