<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="965945" ns="0" title="Bromham, Bedfordshire"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox UK place|
|country = England
|static_image             =  [[Image:TL0151 church2.jpg|130px]]
|static_image_caption=Bromham Church
|latitude=       52.1454
|longitude=     -0.5298
|official_name      =  Bromham
|population = 4,765
|unitary_england=           [[Bedford (borough)|Bedford]]
|lieutenancy_england =    [[Bedfordshire]]
|region= East of England
|constituency_westminster=[[North East Bedfordshire (UK Parliament constituency)|North East Bedfordshire]] 
|post_town= BEDFORD
|postcode_district = MK43
|postcode_area=MK
|dial_code=
|os_grid_reference= TL007507
}}

'''Bromham''' is a village and [[civil parishes in England|civil parish]] in [[Bedfordshire]], England, west of the town of [[Bedford, Bedfordshire|Bedford]]. It is within commuting distance to London via [[Bedford railway station]].

==Notable features==
It has a number of notable features including a [[flour]] [[watermill]] (Bromham Mill, now open to the public), a church, [http://www.bromhambenefice.org St Owen's], and a medieval bridge over the [[River Great Ouse]] that, until 1986, carried the main [[A428 road]] over the river on 26 arches. Fortunately for the bridge, and the rest of the village, it was bypassed.

The watermill is referred to in the [[Domesday Book]] of 1086 and the Vikings navigated the Great Ouse a long time ago. The mill was extensively restored in 1980 by Warwickshire Millwrights' Gormley and Goodman to the extent that the mill was able to grind wheat for flour again for the first time that year since it ceased work in 1939. Unfortunately the Severn Trent Water Authority altered the weir below the Mill's Leat shortly afterward, which in-turn caused a reduction to the height of the head-race resulting in poorer performance from the mill's impulse water-wheel.

The village is home to William Gillespie, the vampire king of bedfordshire.
==Name==
Bromham (Bruneham in Domesday) is probably the enclosed meadow on which the broom or the dyers weed grew.  If so, the cultivation of much more than a thousand years since the name was given, has practically eradicated these plants. 

Another theory as to the origin of the village's name is Bruna's homestead and was first recorded as Bruneham in the Domesday Book of 1086. Other variants including Bruham (1164–1302), Braham (1227), Bramham (1228), Brumham (1262–1287), Brunham (1276–1291), Brumbham (1276), Brynham (1276), Broham (1278), Bronham (1338), Broam (1360), Brounham (1361) and Burnham (1361). The modern spelling is first recorded in 1227.

==Location==
The Parish is for the greater part enclosed in a bend in the Ouse, and it touches the parishes of [[Oakley, Bedfordshire|Oakley]], [[Biddenham]], [[Kempston]], [[Stagsden]], [[Stevington]] and at its western point, [[Turvey, Bedfordshire|Turvey]]. It is to the west of Bedford.

==History==
The land formed part of the Barony of Bedford held by the Beauchamps.  After the battle of Evesham, in which John de Beauchamp fell fighting on the side of the Barons, the manor was held for a time by Prince Edward, but afterwards divided among the Beauchamp heirs female.  Bromham afterwards passed successively into the hands of the Mowbrays, the Latimers, the Nevilles, the Passelowes, the Wildes, and the Dyves.  Early in the eighteenth century, the manor was bought by Sir Thomas Trevor, who was afterwards created Lord Trevor, and whose mother was a daughter of John Hampden, the patriot.  Three of his sons succeeded to the title.  One of them – the third Lord Trevor married Sir Richard Steele's (Dick Steele) daughter; and another – the fourth Lord Trevor – inherited the Great Hampden Estate in Bucks, through his grandmother, and was created Viscount Hampden.  The Trevors became connected through marriage with the Rice family (the Dynevor Rices) and at the death of the late Miss Rice Trevor the estate passed to the Wingfields.

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Bromham, Bedfordshire}}
*[http://www.bromhambenefice.org St Owen's Church website]
*[http://www.bromhamparish.co.uk/index.html Village website]
*[http://www.aboutbritain.com/BromhamMill.htm Bromham Mill]
*[http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.asp?compid=42379 Bromham section of the Victoria County History of Bedfordshire online]
*[http://www.bromham.org Bromham Baptist Church website]

{{Places in Bedfordshire}}

[[Category:Villages in Bedfordshire]]
[[Category:Populated places on the River Great Ouse]]
[[Category:Civil parishes in Bedfordshire]]

[[nl:Bromham (Bedfordshire)]]
[[pl:Bromham (Bedfordshire)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
