<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9671226" ns="0" title="DXLL-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=February 2009}}
{{Unreferenced|date=March 2008}}
{{Infobox Broadcast |
  call_letters             = DXLL-TV|
  station_logo             = [[Image:ABS-CBN logo.svg|200px]]
  station_slogan           = In the Service of the Filipino Worldwide|
  station_branding         = ''ABS-CBN 3 Zamboanga City''|
  analog                   = 3 ([[VHF]])|
  digital                  = |
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = [[ABS-CBN]]|
  founded                  = January 1, 1995|
  location                 = [[Zamboanga City]]|
  owner                    = [[ABS-CBN Broadcasting Corporation]]|
  sister_stations          = [[DXFH-TV]] ([[Studio 23]])|
  callsign_meaning         = |
  former_affiliations      = [[GMA Network]] (1972–1994) under RT Broadcasting, Inc. (RT-3)|
  former_callsigns         = |
  effective_radiated_power = |
  homepage                 = '''[http://www.abs-cbn.com/ www.abs-cbn.com]|'''
}}
&lt;!-- PLEASE DO NOT POST COPY-PASTED INFORMATION BEYOND THIS AREA.--&gt;
'''ABS-CBN Zamboanga''', channel 3, is an owned and operated television station of [[Philippines|Philippine]] [[television network]] [[ABS-CBN Broadcasting Corporation]] located at the former [[Philippine Broadcasting Service]] (PBS) Studios at San Jose Road, [[Zamboanga City]] and Transmitter at Tetuan St. [[Zamboanga City]]. 

The station became an affiliate of ABS-CBN on January 1, 1995 after airing GMA programs before when the station was still owned by [[RT Broadcast Specialist]]. Ownership of this channel took over to ABS-CBN Regional Network. The TV station became one of the top-rating networks in Zamboanga alone.
Its radio station [[MOR Zamboanga]] 98.7 DXFH-FM, formerly known as Star Radio (1995–1997) and ABS-CBN Radio (1997–2001), was first aired in the first quarter of 1995.
ABS-CBN Zamboanga can be also heard/seen on the island of Basilan and areas of Zamboanga del Norte and Zamboanga Sibugay.

==Timeline==
*ABS-CBN Zamboanga was first aired in late 1986 through its affiliate, the now defunct [[First United Broadcasting Corporation]]. Programs were aired from 12:00 noon to 11:00pm, weekdays, and 9:00am to 12:00 m.n. on weekends. Programs on FUBC-9 were Cuentas Claras and FUBC News. In 1991–1992, programs on [[DWRR 101.9|WRR101.9]] were aired on its radio station 99.5FM. For more information, see the article [[First United Broadcasting Corporation]] ([[DXLA-TV]]).
*January 1, 1995– ABS-CBN was moved to TV-3, which is now wholly owned by ABS-CBN Regional Network Group.
*March 1995, Cebu City- The station was one of the first stations airing Cebu-produced ABS-CBN programs; the others being TV-2 Cagayan de Oro and TV-4 Davao during the launching of three Visayan teleseries &quot;Kang Kinsa Isabwag ang Mga Bulak,&quot; &quot;Siya ug Ako sa Kangitngit&quot; and the original &quot;Milyonaryong Mini.&quot; The Network Group was successfully expanded in Visayas-Mindanao in 1996, and later Luzon in 1997.
*DXFH-FM, its radio station, was launched on the first quarter in 1995 as Star Radio on 98.7&amp;nbsp;MHz. DXFH was originally owned by Sundance Apolinario of 4H Class 1980 (Hence the acronym FH).

==ABS-CBN Zamboanga programs==
*[[MagTV]] Chavacano (Di Aton Este!)(2008)
*[[Zambo Jambo]] (1997–2005)- the only variety show produced locally by ABS-CBN Zamboanga
*Let's Talk with Rene Fernandez (1996)- 15-minute talkshow
*[[TV Patrol Chavacano]] (premiered 1992)- the Zamboangueno counterpart of TV Patrol, airing news from Zamboanga City and Zamboanga Peninsula, as well as the ARMM areas of Basilan Sulu and Tawi-tawi
*Buenas Tardes Zamboanga (1996–1997)- news magazine as part of &quot;''Banat Visayas, Sulong Mindanao''&quot;
*Justicia: The Zamboanga Files (1997–1999)- Chavacano drama series
*Dulce Y Dolor (1999–2001)- Chavacano drama series
*Bisto! (2001–2002)- Telemagazine
*Sustansya Para Sa Masa (1999–2005)- cooking TV show produced and hosted by Lulu Gerolaga in cooperation with DOH-IX
*WOW! (2004–present)-telemagazine

Aside from these programs, ABS-CBN Zamboanga is one of the network's regional stations in Visayas and Mindanao that also airs blocktime shows produced in Davao and Cebu.

==See also==
*[[ABS-CBN]]
*[[List of ABS-CBN channels and stations]]

{{ABS-CBN Mindanao}}
{{Zamboanga TV Stations}}

[[Category:ABS-CBN stations| ]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1995]]

[[ceb:DXLL-TV]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
