<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9713674" ns="0" title="List of Happy Tree Friends characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
 | refimprove=August 2008
 | fansite=December 2008
}}
This is a list of [[fictional character]]s from ''[[Happy Tree Friends]]''. There are 22 main characters, and some other supporting characters.

To celebrate the 10th anniversary of the series in 2010 as the creators of ''Happy Tree Friends'' announced that there will be more than one more character added to Happy Tree Friends in the near future of these a sheep named Lammy and her companion Mr. Pickels as a pig named Truffles for vote took place during the month of March and the winner was Lammy and her Mr. Pickels, who joined the show in their latest episode while Truffles lost the vote and it is currently unknown about [[Mondo Media]] will do with him.

[[File:HTF characters.png|right|600px|thumb|All characters from the show from left to right (excluding [[#Lammy &amp; Mr. Pickels|Lammy]] and [[#Lammy &amp; Mr. Pickels|Mr. Pickels]]): [[#Disco Bear|Disco Bear]], [[#Petunia|Petunia]], [[#Nutty|Nutty]], [[#Flaky|Flaky]], [[#Cuddles|Cuddles]], [[#Toothy|Toothy]], [[#Splendid|Splendid]], [[#Giggles|Giggles]], [[#Russell|Russell]], [[#Flippy|Flippy]], [[#Lifty &amp; Shifty|Shifty]], [[#Handy|Handy]], [[#Lifty &amp; Shifty|Lifty]], [[#Pop &amp; Cub|Cub]], [[#Lumpy|Lumpy]], [[#Pop &amp; Cub|Pop]], [[#The Mole|The Mole]], [[#Sniffles|Sniffles]], [[#Mime|Mime]], [[#Cro-Marmot|Cro-Marmot]]]]

==Main characters==
===Cro-Marmot===
Cro-Marmot is a prehistoric [[green]]ish-[[yellow]] [[marmot]] frozen in a block of ice who wears leopard skin loincloth and holds a wooden club in his hand. He appears to be greenish-yellow due to the ice's hue that blends in with his natural color. He is somehow able to perform many tasks offscreen while entirely encased in ice, such as throwing snowballs, somewhat akin to how Handy can perform construction and other tasks without any visible hands. To keep himself frozen, Cro-Marmot stays mainly in cold areas, and sometimes drives an ice cream truck. He lives in a giant [[snow globe]], or rather a small [[igloo]] inside a giant snow globe. His hobbies include serving people [[ice cream]], [[snowboard]]ing, and [[surf]]ing. He rarely dies in the series, the reason being that the ice he's usually encased in protects him from disaster, thereby rendering him almost invulnerable to most unfortunate events. Also, most of his &quot;deaths&quot; are debatable. When they aren't, they involve a form of heat, disasters (such as explosions or collapsing bridges) or being eaten.
The only episode in which he is not frozen is Dino-Sore Days, as that episode occurred during the prehistoric times when he was unfrozen. In Dino-Sore Days, he appeared as a black-and-white character similar to the classic [[Mickey Mouse]] or [[Oswald the Lucky Rabbit]] cartoon; with white gloves, shoes and black limbs, bigger nose, and longer ears. In the opening of the irregular episode, it states that it was copyrighted in the year 1927. Cro-Marmot usually appears in the series as a background character, and has hardly any showcase appearances, but has been marked his first appearance bigger than a cameo since Snow What? That's What! and Dino-Sore Days (either could be considered accurate) and in the episode, Wipe Out. In a featurette of the Second Serving DVD, he was interviewed, and it was revealed he's an accomplished writer, painter, and pianist, and he has his own brand of foot powder, held a tour on Broadway, known for his loud antics and energetic performances, and has been called the &quot;Sexiest Happy Tree Friend&quot; in 1992. However, since the interviewer was unable to get any responses out of Cro-Marmot, she got into a violent rant with the creators.
Cro-Marmot is the second character to have a full head of hair besides Disco Bear. Also, besides Lumpy and Sniffles, he is the third character in the series without a set of buckteeth, with just one tooth on the bottom part of his jaw. His name is a pun of the word, [[Cro-Magnon]]
Even though he made a cameo in the episode, Tongue Twister Trouble, it was actually his official debut in the series. It also makes him the only HTF character to have a debut episode where he wasn't a starring character until Snow What? That's What! He is the least popular character and has starred in the least episodes. Even if it's not a starring role most people want to see him die more often. The staff agree saying that they do not like his character and are planning to make him like an actual tree friend by freeing him from his ice block.

===Cuddles===

A canary-yellow [[rabbit|bunny]] with pink cheeks and pink bunny slippers. His white fluffy curly hair tuft and cotton tail look exactly the same. His ears move to match how he feels. For example, if he's happy they'll stay up, and when he's sad they'll droop. Cuddles is one of the primary characters in the series. Like Giggles, Toothy and Lumpy, he appears in many of the episodes.
Cuddles was the second character to be created in Happy Tree Friends (the first being Shifty). Creator Rhode Montijo first drew him in a piece of paper with the phrase [[Borg (Star Trek)|Resistance Is Futile]] above and that was how the creators got the idea for the show. His voice is even performed by the co-creator of the show, Kenn Navarro.
Cuddles' personality is somewhat mixed. On one hand he can be dangerously mischievous and fairly self-centered. Both of these characteristics have led to both his death and other characters' deaths. On the other hand, he is most of the time friendly and caring, making his personality more complex than the others. As revealed in Sweet Ride, he is referred to as a [[skater]]boy. He was seen to have multiple houses, but his official one is known to be a Hollow Tree, as it is the only one to appear more than once (In a Jam and Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow)
He is particularly good friends with Toothy, Flippy, Petunia, Flaky, and Lumpy, although it was pointed out that Cuddles and Giggles are very close friends, making an official couple. Their relationship is most prominent in the Fall Out Boy music video: The Carpal Tunnel of Love, where it was explored for the first time.  This was also looked into a little more in the episode &quot;I Nub You&quot;.  With 54 deaths, Cuddles is the character who has been killed the most times in the ''Happy Tree Friends'' franchise. He is also the character who has, so far, been killed by Disco Bear, Lumpy and Flippy the most (though, to be fair, Flippy and Lumpy generally kill everyone in episodes in which they are featured). While he dies a lot in the Internet and TV series, Cuddles has survived in many episodes such as: [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Doggone It, Sea What I Found, A Change of Heart, A Sight for Sore Eyes, Letter Late Than Never, Double Whammy Part 1 but not part 2, We're Scrooged!, Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm episode, (debatably) Mime to Five, I Nub You, YouTube 101: Subscriptions, (debatably) A Bit of a Pickle, Star Kringle and the HTF Break shorts, Deck the Halls, We Wish You, and Take Your Seat]]. He tends to die by getting sliced, impaled, crushed, or even decapitated such as in Happy Trails. It hints out that he actually can't chew carrots which is  evidenced by the 'Feed' option of his Smoochie. In addition, it mentions he collects powerful antique [[electric toothbrush]]es and his fur has an [[sunscreen#Sun Protection Factor|SPF]] of 100, protecting him extended exposure to the sun.
He may look like a cute, cuddly, and sweet rabbit (which is why his name is Cuddles) on the outside, but on the inside he's known as quite a rebellious Tree Friend. His talents include extreme sports like skateboarding, surfing, and soccer. He even appears as a daredevil in Mime to Five. Cuddles loves listening to rock music, and he was once a member of &quot;The Happy Tree Band&quot;, before his untimely demise.  As evidenced in the Happy Tree Friends Break: Seize the Day, Cuddles suffers from [[epilepsy]] the same way Handy does (Shown in In a Jam)
He has also appeared on one of the episodes of The God and Devil Show on God's keys, when they were chasing Robert Downey Jr.

===Disco Bear===

A golden bear with an orange afro and two sideburns who likes to dance to disco music (thus his name). He wears 1970s style clothing, including a yellow leisure jacket, yellow bell-bottom pants, and orange and white dancing platform shoes. His main catchphrase is &quot;Oh yeah!&quot;. If he gets interested in anything, he will growl in a deep voice. He sometimes puts everyone around him into life-threatening trouble while dancing, but mistakes their movements of pain for funky dance moves. He is mostly seen either showing off or trying to impress the female characters, such as Giggles and Petunia and sometimes kills them in the process. While he sometimes flirts with Flaky, he has a tendency to ignore her. In Ski Ya, Wouldn't Wanna be Ya!, for example, he pushes Flaky out of the way as he enters the scene, then goes off to flirt with Giggles and Petunia. When Flaky is outside his door later in the episode, however, he seems to be happy to see her, but debatably, Flaky took revenge of Disco Bear wanted to kill him. In Rink Hijinks, he carelessly bumps Flaky into a floor buffer when he's trying to show off his roller skating skills
Despite his failures in wooing the ladies, he seems to be well off financially as he is seen with a private ski cabin in Ski Ya, Wouldn't Wanna be Ya!, a fancy home (which looks like a bachelor pad decorated with the 1970s era furniture, modern art paintings, a heart-shaped bed, a hotel-like bathroom, and packs of romantic candles) in the TV series, a hot tub in Wishy Washy, a sports car in Blind Date, a hairspraying-dryer chair in Easy Comb, Easy Go and his own submarine in Sea What I Found. His financial status could be a result of a previous music career in the 70s at the height of the disco era. In Ipso Fatso, as Disco Bear wakes up and dances to the bathroom, one can see a gold record hanging on the wall in his bedroom, indicating he may have once released a hit album that earned him a small fortune before the disco era came to an end. Further, his silhouette can be seen on a disco record in a jukebox in A Change of Heart, possibly hinting he released that album
His deaths usually involve his head, his eyes, or explosions. Like many other characters; the others are random. Like Lumpy, (and to a lesser extent, Splendid), Disco Bear has a high-pitched scream as seen in episodes Blind Date, Doggone It, Wishy Washy, Who's to Flame?, Sea What I Found, and As You Wish despite his voice being the deepest of all HTFs. Disco Bear has poor eating habits, eating hot dogs, eggs, bacon and other fatty foods while moaning over fruits and vegetables, as seen in A Change of Heart and Ipso Fatso. Because of this, he's overweight, occasionally suffers from low self-esteem, is not able to run that much, and has heart problems. Besides disco dancing, he's talented at rollerskating, downhill skiing, and throwing frisbees long distances
It's been stated in several DVD commentaries and in the HTF forum that when the internet series started, most people in the staff (except for Rhode Montijo) didn't like Disco Bear because they found him annoying. Warren Graff said that it wasn't until the TV series started that they began to like him.
Disco Bear, being a fan of the 70s, has more often than not been seen playing and dancing to music throughout the series, such as a Jukebox in A Change of Heart, a pair of headphones he was dancing to in Hello Dolly, he even has an alarm clock that plays 70s music as the alarm in Ipso Fatso.
Even though Disco Bear dies a lot, he survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|&quot;Stayin' Alive&quot;, &quot;The Wrong Side of the Tracks&quot;, &quot;A Change of Heart&quot;, &quot;Easy Comb, Easy Go&quot;, &quot;Happy New Year&quot;,&quot;Disco Bears All&quot; &amp; &quot;YouTube 101: Subscriptions&quot;]]

===Flaky===
A [[red]] [[porcupine]] whose quills are full of white flakes representing dandruff, thus the name. Flaky is one of the most popular characters in the series and has the personality of being a very cautious and timid character, and as evidenced in Snow Place to Go, he/she may also have [[necrophobia]] (fear of death/dying) and possibly a fear of sharks.  Flaky's gender is listed as being unknown.  It is shown that Flaky has an interest for baseball in Flaky's Baseball Smoochie, leading some to suspect that he/she is a male, while others see this as a sign that Flaky is a [[tomboy]].But lacks physical qualities that other female characters share, particularly eyelashes.
Flaky has often been viewed as a coward or very shy. However, Flaky's actions in both the internet episodes and the TV series go against this as he/she has been brave and on several occasions saved his/her own life. He/She is often seen around Cuddles, Sniffles and Flippy. Additionally, when hanging around with Cuddles, Flaky is often forcefully dragged into situations that lead to one or both of their demises, despite his/her warning Cuddles about possible dangers that could occur as seen in Water You Wading For, Let it Slide, and The Wrong Side of the Tracks. His/Her deaths tend to involve he/she either being skinned, burned, or eaten.
Flaky is a very helpful character, as evidenced by a couple of the TV episodes. All these factors suggest that Flaky is not only overly cautious (as opposed to being a coward), but also one of the more kind characters of the series; for example, daring to organize a surprise party for Flippy, a character who is well-known for being mentally unstable. However, as seen in the episode Snow Place to Go, he/she seems to be unstable herself - near the end of the episode, he/she begins to go insane and makes a companion with a [[garden gnome]], singing &quot;Rock-A-Bye Baby&quot; to it after being trapped in the Arctic with no food or civilization. In Ski Ya, Wouldn't Wanna Be Ya! he/she passes out when he/she is on the ski lift.
In Party Animal, it is revealed that he/she is [[allergy|allergic]] to [[peanut]]s, as he/she gets a [[purple]] [[rash]], big lips, and bloats like a balloon. He/She also has a [[fear of flying]], and is prone to [[vomiting]]. The fact he/she is a porcupine often causes trouble - his/her quills often impale other characters and destroy objects unintentionally. Because of Flaky's quills, Flippy even once used his/her as a weapon with which he killed Cuddles in Keepin' it Reel. Also, he/she is sometimes skinned, as in Class Act and Let it Slide, when he/she falls down a tight space, his/her quills stick-out when going down. When he/she comes out of the other end, his/her muscles are exposed.
The excessive dandruff has sometimes been exploited by other characters. In the Second Serving DVD, he/she was given his/her own breakfast cereal called Flaky Flakes, which resemble cornflakes with red and white pieces mixed in. His/Her dandruff is also used to create a snowing effect for a play in Class Act. A running gag in the series is whenever he/she runs, shakes, or is struck by something, his/her dandruff would always fall out
Flaky's first and third kills were done after he/she himself/herself, has been killed. In the episode, Rink Hijinks, when Disco Bear carelessly pushes him/her, he/she falls onto Lumpy's floor buffer, causing his/her quills to fly out of control and pierce Disco Bear to death. In Party Animal, after he/she got popped like a [[balloon]] by The Mole, his/her quills pinned him to the wall. His/Her second kill is from Let it Slide, because Lumpy accidentally turned off the water, he/she loses her quills all over the water slide, separates the water slide, and later on, when Cuddles slides down, he is sliced in two by the separated slide; due to this, it is assumed Flaky caused Cuddles' death, but it's not likely because the screw popped out before Flaky even went down the slide. As well as being friends with Cuddles, Flaky is also shown to be close friends with Flippy as they are shown doing activities together such as playing hide &amp; seek, going camping, and going to the movies. In Party Animal he/she even organized a surprise birthday party for him. This has led fans to believe that Flaky has a crush on Flippy, making them an unofficial couple due to the gender dispute. However, his/her friendship with Flippy has led to his/her death several times because of Flippy's flip-outs. Interestingly, in Party Animal, Flippy did not kill Flaky even though he instigated the flip-out and he was right in front of him/her (although he/she looked very different, puffed up, and Flippy didn't kill The Mole either). In Double Whammy Part 1 his/her screams snapped him out of one of his flip-outs.
He/She has been killed many times, but survived in, [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Water You Wading For, Out of Sight, Out of Mime, I Get a Trick Out of You (not seen but heard), Stealing the Spotlight, (debatably) From A to Zoo, The Wrong Side of the Tracks, Ipso Fatso, A Change of Heart, Double Whammy Part 1, Easy Comb, Easy Go, Happy Trails pt. 1 (but not part 2), Chew Said a Mouthful, and Something Fishy]]. There is a big debate whether Flaky is a girl or a boy, some people believe that Flaky is a boy because of his/her smoochie and for other reasons. Other people believe that it is a girl whether it is because of his/her voice or because they want more females on the show.

===Flippy===
Flippy is a male bear. He wears dog tags around his neck and a green beret with checkered crest on his head. He is a retired veteran soldier in the Army. He fought in the Weaponized Animal Regiment (The W.A.R), and he has an obsession with making booby traps inspired by the Viet Cong, as well as a flashback of his experience of being held captive by them (as seen in Easy For You to Sleigh). In addition, his attire seems to resemble to the U.S. Army Special Forces, which played a role during the Vietnam War. As he fought for years, he was promoted to the rank of sergeant. According to writer Warren G, Flippy is mostly based on [[John Rambo]]. During the Internet and TV series, it is unknown if Flippy has retired from the Army or if they are simply in a time of peace. Flippy rarely appears in the series, most likely due to his repetitive behavior in most of the episodes in which he appears. Flippy most likely has even more kills than Lumpy (who has 151+ kills in 92 episodes), since he has over 65 kills and has only appeared in 15 episodes so far. The kill ratio between Flippy and Lumpy is 4 1/3:1 59/92, respectively.

Flippy is the only character in the series to cause the deaths of other characters on purpose in every episode which he appears (the one exception being Autopsy Turvy (Double Whammy Part 2), where all of his kills happen by accident). He has a severe case of post traumatic stress disorder. Whenever he sees or hears something that reminds him of war (e.g., gunshot-like sounds,crackling campfires and ketchup), he goes insane and kills everyone around him and sometimes himself, believing that he is still in war. While insane, several physical features about him change: his eyes turn a different color, usually green or yellow, his voice changes from high and cute to low and [[evil]], and his teeth become sharp. In the early Internet shorts, his teeth simply became crooked. In later episodes when he flips-out he blinks changing his pupils from normal [[Pac-Man|pac-man]] pupils to round pupils, his irises turn green (sometimes yellow), his voice deepens into an angry growl, and his teeth get sharp; there has even been an instance (Remains to be Seen) where his eyes became small, circular, with a light blue iris. If he is in his evil state, he (along with Lumpy, The Mole, Cro-Marmot,and Nutty's one eye) doesn't have Pac-Man shaped pupils. When he is flipped out, he is known as Evil Flippy , or in W.A.R. Journal as Flipqy.

Although Flippy can be the most cruel and dangerous character in Happy Tree Friends, he is considered to be one of the most sociable and kindest of characters, when not flipped-out. This is proven in several episodes where he is seen doing social activities with some of the other characters such as going to the movies and playing hide and seek. In most of the episodes where he appears, he is shown as a friendly and social before he goes insane, or as many people say, &quot;flipping-out&quot; (thus his name). Additionally, when he &quot;flips-out&quot;, he does not remember the bloody rampage that follows. However, in Double Whammy Part 1, (and possibly starting from Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow when he resists his evil side for the first time) he finally realizes his problem and goes to Lumpy the psychiatrist for answers. After three attempts to cure him, Lumpy fails. At the end of the episode Autopsy Turvy (Double Whammy Part 2), Flippy finally cures his post tramatic stress disorder, but is run over soon after by a [[Chinatown bus lines|chicken truck]].

He appears to be good friends with Flaky as they are shown doing activities together like going to the movies, playing hide and seek, and going camping (although Flippy has killed Flaky several times). Flaky is the one who organizes his birthday party in Party Animal, proving that she knows personal dates about him, such as the day when he was born, implying that they are quite close. This has led some fans to believe that he has a crush on her. He didn't kill her in Party Animal, while she was vulnerable, and Flaky's scream snapped him out of his flipped-out mode in Double Whammy Part 1. Despite that they appear to be good friends, Flaky develops a phobia of him in the later episodes. She gets so scared of him, that she gathers the courage to kill him, going to the point where she stabs him in fear, when he tries to help her in Without A Hitch. He also has an allergic reaction to [[peanut]]s (or [[venison]]) just like Flaky, but he doesn't puff up like her. Flippy also appears to be an extremely heavy sleeper, as seen in Easy For You to Sleigh and Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow.

Flippy rarely dies in the series. When he does die, his deaths involve vehicles/machinery or explosions and he is almost always not flipped-out. Flippy is also one of the six playable characters in the [[Xbox 360]] [[video game]], [[Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm]]. He is also one of the most popular characters in the show.

He has his own action show called W.A.R. Journal, part of the Happy Tree Friends Action Series: Ka-Pow! show. According to the first episode, Flippy was originally not a particularly good soldier. He demonstrated an inability to throw his knife straight while under pressure, killed both of his teammates, hid in the carcass of one of his dead teammates in [[fear]], and accidentally threw a slice of pizza at the enemy commander rather than his knife. He flips out for the very first time when he hides inside his comrade's dead body to not be killed by the Tiger Army. Most likely, the first time he flipped out, he did it because his consciousness needed to protect him, so his instinct told him to Fight or Flee, and he fought. He ended up losing his hands in a fight with the Tiger Commander, but he was apparently able to reattach them some time between the events of W.A.R. Journal and the regular Happy Tree Friends series (unless these episodes, like the regular Happy Tree Friends series, revert everything back to original at the start of each new episode). The only episodes that Flippy dies when he appears are [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Happy Trails Pt. 2: Jumping the Shark, Class Act (debatable), Remains to be Seen, Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow, Autopsy Turvy/Double Whammy Part 2 and Without A Hitch]].

===Giggles===

Giggles is a [[pink]] [[chipmunk]] who has a white diamond-shaped marking, a white oval on her torso and wears a big red bow on her head. She has the personality of a young girl, as she enjoys frolicking through [[flower]]s, having tea parties with Petunia, ice skating, and having a shy and sweet demeanor. Her name comes from her habit of giggling often. She appears to be allergic to [[rose]]s which was revealed in her Valentines Smoochie. Giggles is one of the primary characters in the leader of the series and appears along with Cuddles, Toothy, and Lumpy in the advertisements. She may have also been one of the first characters to be created along with Cuddles and Shifty.
Giggles is a very affectionate character and is often seen [[hug]]ging and [[kiss]]ing several of the characters. She is particularly close to Cuddles whom she has a crush on as hinted in several episodes (especially in Remains to be Seen when zombified Giggles and Cuddles did the famous [[Lady and the Tramp]] kiss (although with a brain instead of pasta) and in the Fall Out Boy: The Carpal Tunnel of Love music video where for the first time their romantic relationship was really explored. They also kissed technically, but they were killed by impalement from a pole, their bodies slid to where it looked like they were kissing. However, she's been seen with others characters. In Blind Date, she was supposed to go on a blind date with The Mole, in the Love Bites episode Cold Hearted she was seen with Cro-Marmot and The Mole, and in the Love Bites episode Sea of Love she was on a date with Russell.
She is best friends with Petunia. The two run a [[lemonade]] stand together. She is also friends with Toothy because he is friends with Cuddles. Her deaths usually involve being crushed, her chest or her head (it is mostly sliced off, or stuff is ripped out of it). One of her most gruesome injuries is in Eyes Cold Lemonade where her face is sliced off by nails and lemonade is spat in her face. Despite this, she doesn't die in the aforementioned episode.
Giggles is also very environmental in Every Litter Bit Hurts going so far as to chain herself to a tree to prevent Lumpy from cutting it down. When she sees someone polluting the environment, she'll lose her temper and yell at them
She is also considered as a damsel in distress. When she's in trouble, Splendid usually comes to the rescue, but injures or kills her in the process. For example, in From Hero to Eternity, Splendid explodes Cuddles and ruptures Giggles' eardrums. In another example, he accidentally decapitates her in Helping Helps while trying to rescue her from a flood.
Even though she dies quite a bit, she survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Stayin' Alive (debatably), Happy Trails pt. 1 (But not part two), Tongue Twister Trouble, Eyes Cold Lemonade, From Hero to Eternity; We're Scrooged, Out of Sight, Out of Mime, I Get a Trick Out of You, Concrete Solution, Let it Slide, Ipso Fatso, As You Wish, Easy Comb, Easy Go, A Change of Heart, (debatably) Ski Ya, Wouldn't Wanna Be Ya!, Wipe Out, Dunce Upon a Time, Blind Date, Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow, Chew Said a Mouthful, Milk Pong, Cold Hearted, Sea of Love, the YouTube Live Episode, Swelter Skelter, I Nub You, Sight Kringle, Star Kringle, and the HTF Break Shorts Deck the Halls , We Wish You, and Take Your Seat]]

===Handy===
Handy is an [[orange (colour)|orange]] [[beaver]] with unexplained amputated arms (thus his name). The stumps are covered with bandages. He wears a tool belt and a yellow worker's helmet (the typical dress of most construction workers). He has mostly been portrayed as an adult but a couple of times he has been portrayed as a child such as in Happy Trails pt. 1 when he was on a school bus with many other characters and in Remains to be Seen when he and some other characters were dressed up and [[trick or treating]] on [[Halloween]]. His dam mostly consists of tools that are operated by hand.
Despite his lack of hands, he is still capable of building many things big or small, though we never actually see him build it in the first place - it is usually off-screen, very similar to Cro-Marmot (with the exception of Wheelin' and Dealin', where he is seen putting the final touches on his race car). Usually, whenever he builds something for the female characters, they are pleased and often thank him by hugging him for it, like Petunia from House Warming and Giggles from Home is Where the Hurt is. This has led some fans to believe that they have a crush on him.
Whenever we see him try to do something which would usually require hands, however, he fails and pulls his main trademark frustrated look, indicating that he forgot that he doesn't have hands. Usually when he finds a compromise, it will lead to his own death and sometimes the death of others. His deaths involve either glass, his organs, getting impaled, getting cut in half, or his head. As he has bandages on what is left of his arms, it can be assumed that he lost them in a work-related accident. He also seems to feel no shock or remorse seeing others die or get injured
It is possible that in the TV series, Handy has gained an interest in flying, as seen in Who's to Flame?, Gems the Breaks, A Change of Heart, and Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow. Sometimes he stays in the air from when he first appears in the episode until his death. From the episode, In a Jam, it became apparent that he has photosensitive epilepsy, the flashing lights triggering a seizure as his eyes go wonky, he jitters, and foams at the mouth
Similar to Cub, Cuddles, Petunia, Lifty &amp; Shifty, and to a lesser extent Sniffles, Handy rarely survives the episodes he has appeared in. The only episodes in which he survived were: [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|House Warming, Spare Me, Happy Trails pt. 1 (but not part 2), Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow, Double Whammy Part 1, Something Fishy, Milk Pong, Doggone It (Debatably), the HTF Break Short Happy New Year and the YouTube Live Episode]].

===Lammy &amp; Mr. Pickels===
A lavender [[sheep]], or possibly a lamb, with a tuft of white wool on her head. It's a little hard to see, but she does have a tail similar to her head wool. She also wears a white wool jumper and a purple ribbon in her &quot;hair&quot;. Being a sheep/lamb, Lammy [[bleat]]s instead of [[laugh]]ing, as well as when she's in a panic, as shown in the episode &quot;A Bit of a Pickle.&quot; her first victim is unclear. whether it was Petunia or Flaky is up to debate. So far, she's survived in every episode she's ever been in.

Mr . Pickels is normally an average [[pickle]], but through Lammy's eyes, he wears a top hat, has a curly mustache, and sometimes carries a cane. He's always smiling, but his personality is very similar to Flippy (while he's Flipped Out) in the fact that he kills almost everyone in sight except for Lammy. His first victim is either Petunia or her teddy bear, depending on what episode it is. He doesn't seem to have any shame in what he does, for he always has a smile.

===Lifty &amp; Shifty===
Lifty &amp; Shifty are two green [[kleptomania]]c [[raccoon]] [[twin#identical twins|identical twin]] brothers with dark green mask-like markings around their eyes and rodent-teeth (a little like Lampwick from Disney's [[Pinocchio (1940 film)|Pinocchio]]). They frequently steal merchandise from the other Happy Tree Friends (thus their names), as well as treasure hunting, ransacking houses or anything to get rich quick with the exception of Flaky, Lammy, Cro-Marmot and Splendid. They mostly steal from Lumpy (in Meat Me for Lunch they stole meat from Lumpy's deli mart, in Milkin' It they stole a cow from Lumpy's farm, in Concrete Solution they stole his wallet, and in Junk in the Trunk they abducted his [[pet]] [[elephant]]). They probably rob Lumpy so frequently because his lack of intelligence and common sense makes him an easy target
Although they have the same gender, color, markings, bushy tails, and personality, Shifty wears a fedora and he bosses Lifty around and Lifty's voice is slightly higher pitched, to distinguish the two. It is known that Shifty is the older brother of the duo, since Lifty is a little shorter and has a higher pitched voice. Despite the smirks on their faces, they almost always end up dying in the episodes in which they appear. Their green color implies [[money]] and [[greed]] relating to their [[criminal]] personalities. They also have a trademark evil [[snicker]] (usually a different one for later episodes). Like most siblings, Lifty and Shifty argue about who's at fault when something goes wrong, but when trouble's afoot, they work together. Both twins are pretty greedy and sometimes resort to seeing their twin die rather than give up their loot or be caught, as seen in Milkin' It when Shifty threw Lifty out of a [[hot air balloon]] as not to get caught by a cable. Also, in Sea What I Found Shifty had a chance to save Lifty, but instead just stole the jewels.
Despite their numerous illegal activities, they do mix with other characters and contribute to recreational activities (such as going on a [[rollercoaster]] and participating in a Christmas play) without causing any trouble. On rare occasions they earn cash honestly and have even been heroic, such as in Happy Trails Pt. 2: Jumping the Shark, when they provided a [[life raft]] to help the characters escape from an island
Lifty &amp; Shifty occasionally make money by themselves without stealing, like when they sold [[dog]]s who have [[post-traumatic stress disorder]] just like Flippy and become aggressive and [[evil]] when they hear a [[whistle]] in Doggone It and when they sold bottles of hair growth formula to Disco Bear in Easy Comb, Easy Go. They also trade or sell things to Nutty, such as in Dunce Upon a Time and the Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm episode. Lifty rarely tries to be the boss but Shifty mostly is.
Lifty &amp; Shifty die a lot due to their lack of teamwork and their greed. Like Cuddles, Petunia, Sniffles, and Splendid, they tend to die some of the messiest deaths in the series. When they do, their deaths involve machines/vehicles, being mashed together or sliced apart, impalement or some form of heat. In the internet shorts, Lifty &amp; Shifty died in every episode they appeared in. In the TV series, they survived in Ipso Fatso, Concrete Solution and Easy Comb, Easy Go. They also survived in the YouTube Live Episode and Happy New Year. However, it is possible they survived in Happy Trails pt. 1 as they were on the island with the surviving characters in part 2 but they weren't seen in part 1, In the &quot;Collect Them All&quot; section, Lifty bowls a 300 score at the game of bowling, and Shifty has a gambling problem. They both also seem to have an unusual desire for [[meat]], as seen in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Meat Me for Lunch, Ipso Fatso, And the Kitchen Sink, Milkin' It, Dunce Upon a Time]], and their title card. They also have a knack for car building, being able to assemble/reassemble a car in Junk in the Trunk and maintaining their own race car in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Wheelin' and Dealin']].

===Lumpy===
He is a light [[blue]] [[dinosaur]] [[moose]] with apparently very low intelligence, bad teeth (although they are clear white), distorted eyes and mismatched antlers (they always change directions). Known to be the big [[brother]], or perhaps [[babysitting|babysitter]] of many of the other characters. He usually means well but he's clumsy and extremely [[stupidity|stupid]]. Furthermore, he screams like a girl. His catchphrase is &quot;Ah Ha!&quot; for when he gets an idea or finds the solution to a problem. He also says &quot;Huh?&quot; when he is confused and &quot;Mmm-hmm!&quot; when he is satisfied. Although Lumpy generally never kills anyone by design, he is portrayed as a villain for the first time in Dunce Upon a Time. However the first episode he killed another character intentionally was Happy Trails Pt. 2: Jumping the Shark.
He is the only character with a standard nose with two nostrils (all of the smaller Happy Tree Friends except Sniffles have heart-shaped noses). Plus, he is the only character whose hands don't turn mitten-esque. He is also one of the only characters without Pac-Man-shaped pupils (along with The Mole, Lifty &amp; Shifty (not always), Nutty, Evil Flippy, and Cro-Marmot). Lumpy has appeared in the most episodes out of all the Tree Friends, and most fans consider him the odd one out due to his height and lack of a normal Happy Tree Friend style face. There were some arguments about his appearance being too close to &quot;[[Bullwinkle J. Moose|Bullwinkle]]&quot; and &quot;[[Montgomery Moose]]&quot;, the group's leader of [[The Get Along Gang|The Get-Along Gang]], so his right antler was drawn upside down. He's a [[hillbilly]] judging by his voice, his lifestyle, and the clothes he sometimes wears
Lumpy has had many occupations in many episodes, including [[teacher]], [[farmer]], [[bus driver]], [[convenience store]] [[clerk]], [[police officer]], to name a few. He is usually a fill-in character like Wooldoor Sockbat from [[Drawn Together]]. He is often shown in tremendously incongruous situations, such as [[lounging]] lazily, shirtless, and in a [[hammock]], while the rest of the Happy Tree Friends gang are playing in the snow, as seen in Snow What? That's What!. He is also the tallest main character standing about twice as tall as all the other characters. The only characters to match him in height have been minor characters, such as Giggles' Mom, or Ka-Pow! characters, like the Tiger General.
Lumpy by far has the series' highest kill count. His low intelligence is often the cause of other characters' deaths, and sometimes his own. In fact, Lumpy has caused the death of every character at least once, except for Cro-Marmot, Lammy and Splendid. Cuddles is, so far, Lumpy's most frequent victim. Lumpy's deaths usually involve metallic objects, electronics, dismemberment, getting crushed by atomic bombs, tripping over strange objects, swords, or animals. Due to his strength and size, he tends to survive more punishment before finally dying compared to the other tree friends. As a result, his deaths are usually extremely painful. He mostly lives in a trashy trailer and drives a Lincoln Continental. His MySpace account mentions that his favorite foods are [[cheese]] and [[sandwich]]es, his favorite dessert is [[cheesecake]], and that he likes to talk to [[lettuce]] as seen in the Collect Them All Section
Lumpy is not a playable character in the PC version but is in the [[Xbox 360]] [[video game]], [[Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm]], although he does appear as an icon on the HUD (heads up dislplay). In the minds of many viewers Lumpy has an extremely dysfunctional brain, however, it is notable he has the most responsibility of the characters. A good example of this is From A to Zoo where it's his job to look after five of the younger characters. At times he is rather bossy as in, Peas in a Pod, A Change of Heart and See What Develops.
Lumpy has survived in the most episodes of all. He has survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Banjo Frenzy (technically not Lumpy), Spin Fun Knowin' Ya, Wheelin' and Dealin', (debatably) Treasure These Idol Moments, Nuttin' but the Tooth, You're Bakin' Me Crazy, Meat Me for Lunch, Off the Hook, Happy Trails (Part 1 &amp; Part 2), Out of Sight, Out of Mime, Let it Slide, Icy You, Remains to be Seen, Stealing the Spotlight, From A to Zoo, Party Animal, As You Wish, Snow Place to Go, Gems the Breaks, A Change of Heart, Chew Said a Mouthful, See What Develops, Aw Shucks!, A Sight for Sore Eyes, Tongue in Cheek, Easy Comb, Easy Go, Junk in the Trunk, Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow, Double Whammy (Part 1 &amp; Part 2), Kringle Tree, Kringle Karols, Kringle Frosty, Read 'em and Weep, Can't Stop Coffin, A Sucker for Love, Pt. Two, Peas in a Pod, Something Fishy, Without A Hitch, I Nub You, A Bit of a Pickle, Strain Kringle, Ski Patrol, YouTube Live Episode, See You Later, Elevator and the HTF breaks, Seize the Day, Deck the Halls, Moppin Up and We Wish You]].

===Mime===
A [[purple]] male [[reindeer]] with sharp ears, antlers on top and who wears face makeup and a navy blue/dark purple and white, striped shirt. He never speaks, because he is a mime, causing others to have a hard time understanding him. Apparently, most of his possessions are imaginary yet can be stolen (or even shown to be real), as evidenced in Easy For You to Sleigh, Mime to Five, Concrete Solution, Keepin' it Reel, and I Heart U. Sometimes the things around him are imaginary, such as walls in Dunce Upon a Time, which he uses in the name of showmanship. He has even done some seemingly impossible things, such as making an audible honking sound while riding a unicycle in Concrete Solution and making noises while interacting with his 'imaginary' furniture. It was once said that he's mute, but in some episodes, like in Happy Trails pt. 1, Out of Sight, Out of Mime, Something Fishy, Keepin' It Reel, and I Heart U he has made audible noises (e.g., choking noises, snoring, or blowing noises) making it evident that he can speak, he just chooses not to (although he has been known to not scream even when in severe pain as seen in Double Whammy Part 1 when his insides were set on fire). This has led to other characters' deaths, such as in Who's to Flame? when his choosing not to talk to Lumpy, a fireman, over the phone eventually led to the destruction of the entire town
He is talented with [[circus]] skills like [[juggling]] (which he can do with one hand) and creating [[balloon animals]], though his attempts to entertain his fellow Happy Tree Friends often have fatal consequences. Mime is very fond of peanuts, going so far as to stick his hand in a blender to eat them. In Mime and Mime Again, Out of Sight, Out of Mime and Class Act he had a tail, however he appears without it in later episodes. Despite this, he has his tail, again, in the most recent Kringle episode, Chill Kringle and See You Later, Elevator..
Mime is usually seen riding a [[unicycle]] in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Party Animal, Concrete Solution, Who's to Flame?, As You Wish, A Hole Lotta Love, See What Develops, Junk in the Trunk, and Double Whammy. Sometimes]], he stays seated on his unicycle throughout entire episodes
Mime is the only character who doesn't die in the two TV episodes (Who's to Flame? and Mime to Five) he starred in, and he didn't have any co-stars in these episodes. He also survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Mime and Mime Again, Easy For You to Sleigh, A Change of Heart, Easy Comb, Easy Go, In a Jam, I Heart U, Chill Kringle, and in the HTF Breaks Happy New Year and Take Your Seat]]. He lives in a tent, on which the inside looks like a regular house with invisible or imaginary furniture as seen in Easy For You to Sleigh, and Mime to Five. He dies quick and painless deaths more than any other character except in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Happy Trails pt. 1, Home Is Where the Hurt Is, Party Animal and Double Whammy Part 1]]. Like many other characters' deaths, they usually involve his head, metallic objects or machinery/vehicles

===The Mole===
A blind lavender [[Mole (animal)|mole]] with dark [[sunglasses]] (or possibly [[sunglasses#Teashades|teashades]]) with a [[mole (skin)|mole]] by his nose. He wears a long purple turtleneck on his sweater. Like Mime and Cro-Marmot, he doesn't speak. This could be due to the upper part of his turtleneck covering his mouth, though more likely he is [[muteness|mute]], seeing as he never makes a sound even through his most excruciating deaths. Though he is not [[deafness|deaf]], he does seem to have hearing problems, as seen in Party Animal. Because disaster often follows his blind wandering, his actions and characteristics resemble those of Mr. Magoo. Despite being completely blind, he is often seen driving. He is also one of several characters without Pac-Man-shaped pupils (along with Lumpy, Nutty, Evil Flippy, and Cro-Marmot)
According to the commentary for Pitchin' Impossible, The Mole was originally supposed to be a [[James Bond]]-like secret agent with all kinds of spy gadgets around him but it was removed when the series was created. It was until the episode, Mole in the City, that his secret agent identity was explored. He also has an arch-nemesis known as The Rat, most likely because they both have careers in international espionage.
A running gag in the series is The Mole doing things that require vision, such as reading a magazine or lighting a match to see in the dark. He usually has jobs that require good vision, which, in most episodes, leads to many characters' deaths (Lumpy and Handy in particular) and sometimes his own. According to the commentary for Concrete Solution the writers do this just because they need something bad to happen, and The Mole and Lumpy are considered the worst people for almost any job. If the episode has to run smoothly, they use a tree friend capable of doing any given job correctly
He is good friends with Handy and Lumpy as seen in Concrete Solution and Sniffles in A Hole Lotta Love, with the former implying that the Mole has no sight, Handy has no hands, and Lumpy has no intelligence.
In the web shorts, The Mole rarely dies, but usually causes harm to the other tree friends due to his disabilities. In the TV series, he dies much more often, but still survives a lot of episodes (he has, thus far, survived in 25 episodes). His deaths usually involve his head, getting impaled or crushed, explosions, or loss of body parts
When looking at the storyboard for Flippin' Burgers, on the Second Serving DVD, The Mole was originally going to be featured in that episode as well as getting killed by Flippy. It was shown that Flippy rips the Mole's skin off with a hanging hook. The idea was removed when the episode was finalized
He is the only character during the first season of the television series that has 3 starring roles without starring alone. He co-starred with Handy, Lumpy, Russell, and Splendid. In the &quot;Collect Them All&quot; in the First Blood DVD, it claims that The Mole has blue eyes. He also seems to love [[plush toy|stuffed animals]], as evident in Pitchin' Impossible
In many episodes, he is seen doing many random things with body parts from dead characters, like using Mime's head for a [[jack-o'-lantern|jack o'lantern]], using Sniffles' head for a [[bowling ball]], mistaking Disco Bear's severed head for a [[watermelon]] and weighing it on a scale, mistaking Giggles' heart as a piece of litter, and mistaking Cuddles' eye for an [[apple]]. Also, in the comics, he was seen bobbing for apples, but he mistook Handy's heart for an apple. He has also, on occasion, eaten body parts, which likely only happens because he doesn't realize what he's eating. Another misuse of body parts can be found in the music video for the Carpal Tunnel of Love by Fall Out Boy. When Toothy's eyeball landed in a tub of [[ice cream]] he put it in Cuddles and Giggles' ice cream soda, which they spit out. The Mole survives in most of the episodes he appears in, but he does die in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Happy Trails pt. 1, Class Act, Remains to be Seen, From Hero to Eternity, Party Animal, Don't Yank My Chain, Doggone It, Concrete Solution, Who's to Flame?, Gems the Breaks, A Hole Lotta Love, Idol Curiosity, Home Is Where the Hurt Is, Aw Shucks!, A Sight for Sore Eyes, Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow, The Carpal Tunnel of Love, Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm Episode, and Wrath of Con(debatably)]]

===Nutty===
A light [[green]] [[squirrel]] with one [[yellow]] diamond shaped marking on his head and a large curled-up tail that moves when he's excited. Nutty has an addiction for [[candy]] or anything that is sugary. He has a big swirly lollipop, candy cane, small all-day sucker, and a candy apple stuck to his fur, which he even treats as his wardrobe, as evidenced in Chew Said a Mouthful, although this sometimes changes. In his debut in the episode Nuttin' Wrong with Candy the candy attached to his fur fell off, therefore Nutty was seen without candy stuck to him for the first time
One of his eyes bears a slight resemblance to Flippy's 'flipped-out' eyes. It's apparent that his googly eye is an amblyopia, or lazy eye, as it's almost always looking down and drops down whenever he looks somewhere else
As a result of his huge sugar intake he is often hyperactive and jittery, and giggles more than he talks (sometimes he even giggles while he dies). He was first heard saying that he wishes for a scrumptious lollipop in As You Wish. One drop of sugar makes him hyper to the point that he could create a tornado like &quot;[[Tasmanian Devil (Looney Tunes)|Taz the Tasmanian Devil]]&quot;. He sometimes foams at the mouth when deprived of candy or any other sugar-related items. As seen in the False Alarm episode, he can go insane due to long hours without candy. It also shows that once he loses one addiction he can start a new one almost immediately, hinting he probably has an addictive personality. He also becomes momentarily sad after finishing his candy
Nutty will do whatever it takes to get the sugar he wants. If he doesn't get what he wants he becomes very irate. Nutty will eat other types of &quot;food&quot; occasionally (like in Class Act, when he eats part of Sniffles' body and some cardboard, thinking it was a candy cane, or in Concrete Solution when he eats a whole bag of cement mix, mistaking it for a bag of sugar), but it's a very rare case. He will also eat regular food, like pancakes, but he usually drenches them in syrup first
He is one of the few characters to have an account on the website MySpace, where it mentions he has fourteen dental cavities. This is probably not helped the fact that he brushes his teeth with a lollipop and sugar, and uses soda as mouthwash. He drinks coffee ground from jellybeans and still has to add more than a bowlful of sugar to the beverage to make it sweet enough for him
In the Second Serving DVD, he has his own breakfast cereal called &quot;Sugar Frosted Nutty Honey&quot;, but there are hardly any cereal pieces in it - the picture only shows a large pile of sugar in the bowl. Nutty can be seen eating this cereal in Concrete Solution.
Nutty is usually featured in episodes which revolve around candy, except for Eye Candy, where Toothy was used instead. It was rumored that when Eye Candy was made, Nutty had already been prominently featured in another episode, which was why that choice was made.
Nutty's love for candy has often led to the demise of both himself and others, but it is his hyperactive personality that has made him one of the show's most memorable characters. Nutty cares more about candy than he does about his friends. In Party Animal, he pushes aside an allergy-stricken Flaky to consume chocolate. In A Sucker for Love, Pt. One he tried to steal a lollipop from Cub. In Chew Said a Mouthful he stole a gurney with a badly injured Toothy so he could get a jawbreaker. In Concrete Solution he stole a bag of sugar from the Happy Tree Caf, and he stalked Cuddles for his ice cream in Sweet Ride. He seems to lack common sense (which is evidenced in many episodes), something that commonly leads to his death. His deaths usually involve his mouth, getting impaled, getting crushed, split apart, shredded, or breathing problems
The only episodes he has survived in are [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Nuttin' but the Tooth, I Get a Trick Out of You, Out of Sight, Out of Mime, Who's to Flame?, (debatably) Mime to Five, A Change of Heart, In a Jam, A Sucker for Love, Pt. One (but not part two), Milk Pong, Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm Episode, the HTF Break short Bite Sized the YouTube Live Episode, and Something Fishy]].
And He is Hamon's Happy Tree Friends Character

===Petunia===
A indigo and dark blue [[skunk]] with a sky blue arrow marking on her forehead, which is connected to the triangle shaped marking on her back and sky blue lines on her long tail who always wears a [[pink]] [[flower]] on top of her head and a pine scent car air freshener or deodorizer around her neck. She likes to play with dolls and strollers and also likes having tea parties with her friends. Petunia is often seen in the series with Giggles. They appear to be best friends, as they run a lemonade stand together, play together, and exercise together. While Giggles has appeared more in the series, Petunia's deaths are the most gruesome in the series (such as having her face pressed against a burger grill by Flippy. being flattened by Cro-Marmot, being sucked through the drain of a sink, having her organs pop out by bed springs, and having her bottom half skinned, then being ripped to pieces and consumed by a [[demon]] in Read 'em and Weep). Her deaths generally involve her head or household appliances, such as sinks
In the Internet series, she and Giggles had almost identical personalities. When the TV series came out, however, the creators have gave her obsessive compulsive disorder More specifically, she is a &quot;neat freak&quot;. She takes showers five times a day as it reveals in the &quot;Collect Them All&quot; section, and if things are either dirty or out of their proper place, she starts to hyperventilate. She will do anything to clean it up again. In the TV episode Wishy Washy she got incredibly filthy and was unable to clean herself, so she went crazy and killed herself with a potato peeler trying to get clean. Her OCD is also brought up in other episodes, Home Is Where the Hurt Is and Wingin' It. Plus, in the arcade game, Socks To Be You, she is seen hyperventilating with a paper bag while sorting her socks. Oddly enough, in Take a Hike when she drinks dirty water, her mouth is a mess, but she doesn't get upset or bother to clean her face (though she was severely dehydrated and delusional at the time)
Petunia, like Giggles, has been used as damsel in distress on some episodes, which is evident in House Warming, Gems the Breaks, Who's to Flame?, Dunce Upon a Time, and Read 'em and Weep. She, like Giggles, is also a Girl Scout, as seen in Read 'em and Weep. Whenever Petunia has too much to drink, she'll have to go to the bathroom really badly, as seen in Happy Trails pt. 1 and Wingin' It (in Happy Trails, she actually wets herself just before her death).
Petunia rarely survives. While she dies a lot, she has survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Meat Me for Lunch, Ipso Fatso, A Change of Heart, Milk Pong, Wipe Out, You're Bakin' Me Crazy, I Get a Trick Out of You, Stealing the Spotlight, Mime to Five, (debatably) House Warming, Easy Comb, Easy Go, Swelter Skelter, Ski Ya, Wouldn't Wanna Be Ya!!and the HTF Break short Take Your Seat]]. During the Internet episodes, she died in almost every episode she appeared in, though she survives more often in the TV series. She was the first victim of (debatably) Handy, The Mole, (debatably) Disco Bear, Giggles, Cro-Marmot, Toothy, and Lammy/Mr. Pickels

===Pop &amp; Cub===
Pop, a light brown bear. He is another adult character. Some people refer to him as the stereotypically clueless, bathrobe-wearing, pipe-smoking 1950s style sitcom father. Pop only appeared without Cub in Something Fishy (excluding his BBQ smoochie and Milk Pong), though Cub has appeared in multiple episodes without Pop. He was originally going to appear in Happy Trails Pt. 2: Jumping the Shark, but the creators considered it weird for Pop to kill Flaky. Instead Flippy took his place which explains why Flippy had Pop's voice. Though Pop is likely an adult character, he is not as large as other adult characters like Lumpy and Giggles' Mom.
His son Cub often dies as a result of both his attention and inattention - although it's clear that he loves him. In the web series he usually didn't know of his son's deaths (as evidenced in Chip Off the Ol' Block, Snip Snip Hooray!, Water Way to Go and Hello Dolly), but he is more aware of them in the TV series (as evidenced in And the Kitchen Sink, Ipso Fatso, Sea What I Found, Who's to Flame?, Every Litter Bit Hurts, As You Wish and Gems the Breaks). He isn't very bright as seen in Easy For You to Sleigh where he disables the noisy smoke detector, leading to both their deaths from carbon monoxide poisoning. When he tries to save his son, he often kills him by mistake and sometimes kills himself too. The only time Pop killed Cub intentionally was in Read 'em and Weep, when Cub was possessed by a demon (though Pop kills him after Lumpy had already exorcised the demon from Cub). In both the Internet shorts and the TV series, he survives almost every episode in which he appears. When he does die, a lot of these deaths involve fire, impalement, or explosions.
Pop is one of the few characters in the show who has a much more intelligible way of speaking. He almost speaks clear words in some of the episodes he appears in and even reads a story of &quot;The Night Before Christmas&quot; to Cub in Easy For You to Sleigh.
There is evidence in Can't Stop Coffin that Pop may very well be a widower, due to the fact that in their cameo, he and Cub are seen mourning at a gravestone which probably belongs to his dead wife. Pop surivies in most of the episodes he appears in, but he does die in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Havin' A Ball, Flippin' Burgers, Class Act, Stealing the Spotlight, Easy For You to Sleigh, Who's to Flame?, As You Wish, Aw Shucks!, Every Litter Bit Hurts, Mime To Five, See You Later, Elevator, Wrath of Con, and Wingin' It]].

Cub, a very young light brown bear, who is the son of Pop. He has the appearance and personality of a baby but the intelligence and mobility of a young child. He's the youngest and smallest character of the Happy Tree Friends and his eyes consist only of Pac-man pupils, giving him a more adorable appearance than the other characters, but he does die and get injured a lot.
He has appeared and died much more in the series than his father. And usually his deaths are a result of Pop's bad parenting, even though Pop clearly cares about him. If his father's not paying attention to him, he will often be seen wandering around operating machines by himself or carelessly drifting into death-inducing hazards, like the time Cub was sucking on an electric razor as if it were a pacifier, soon ending with Pop plugging it back in, much to Cub's despair. It is considered that Cub enjoys playing with Lumpy's body parts, like in Rink Hijinks, where he ripped out Lumpy's heart while trying to get a prize, and in Just Desert, when he found Lumpy's skull and put it up to his ear like a seashell.
Cub rarely survives (though he has survived nine times) in the series and his deaths are usually very gruesome, painful, and ironic. The only episodes that Cub didn't die in along with Pop are Out of Sight, Out of Mime, Don't Yank My Chain, See What Develops, Just Desert, and the HTF Break short Happy New Year. And the ones without Pop, he also survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Rink Hijinks and I Get a Trick Out of You]]. Also the episodes where Cub survived but was injured were &quot;A Hole Lotta Love&quot;, &quot;A Sucker for Love, Pt. One&quot;, and &quot;A Sucker for Love, Pt. Two&quot;. Cub's deaths generally involve tools, machinery or getting crushed
So far, Cub has only killed other characters twice. Lumpy was his first and only victim from &quot;Rink Hijinks&quot;. In the Halloween episode, Read 'em and Weep, he was being possessed by a demon from within a book and subsequently killed Petunia in his possessed form, although you could argue this was really The Demon's Kill, not Cub's
He's shown to be interested in becoming a fireman as seen in Who's to Flame and in As You Wish. The &quot;Collect Them All&quot; section reveals that Cub is lactose intolerant as he's seen eating the [[orange (fruit)|orange]] [[sherbert]], drinking [[grape juice]], and eating a [[popsicle]]. He also has a habit of drooling (which did not favor him well in &quot;Kringle Presents&quot;) and cooing. He usually seen licking a [[lollipop]] as seen in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|See What Develops, and A Sucker for Love, Pt. One]And Snip,Snip,Hooray!]] 
Cub is usually seen wearing a little beanie with a propeller on the top; it has only been off a few times. Because Cub is rarely seen without his cap, Pop thinks that if he sees the hat, then he's seeing his son; this could be seen in Water Way to Go and Concrete Solution. If he wants to know where he went, he leaves his hat to mark his leaving spot like a marking trail as seen in A Hole Lotta Love. Pop had also used Cub's hat to mark his grave by putting it on his tombstone, as seen in Read 'em and Weep.
In the Halloween episode [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Can't Stop Coffin]], when Pop &amp; Cub are seen mourning at a gravestone, it could possibly be Cub's dead mother.

===Russell===
A turquoise [[sea otter]] with typical [[piracy|pirate]] accessories like a Jolly Roger's hat, a striped red/white shirt, a hook, an eyepatch and two wooden peglegs. He enjoys fishing, sailing and eating seafood, one of his animal instincts, especially mussels, which was why he was named Russell. He also likes kite flying and even runs his own fast-food restaurant (Mime to Five). His hook started off on his left hand, but later on, it is on the right hand for the rest of the series. Russell's initial character design depicted him with a five o'clock shadow, though since his early appearances the creators got rid of it
He stopped having a five o'clock shadow since Get Whale Soon. Typically, his vocabulary consists only of &quot;Yar!&quot;, though in the episode Get Whale Soon, he also says things like 'Aha!' and 'Huh?' In the episode A Sight for Sore Eyes, he was heard apologizing to The Mole after he accidentally bumped into him
Sometimes, when put in a scary or violent situation, Russell will go insane and start laughing in a crazy manner and his eye turns into the color of gray, as seen in Get Whale Soon and Snow Place to Go. Because Russell spends most of his time in the water, he is rarely seen with the other characters, though he does appear in a few episodes with Lumpy, although nowadays he seems to appear with all the others as well. His deaths usually involve sea animals or getting impaled
From the episode, Sea What I Found, when Russell woke up and went to his closet to change his peglegs, it is evident that his legs are partially amputated. He is the second character to wear pants. Also, he's the third character without visible ears as seen in his Internet shorts introduction when he took his hat off for a few seconds, and in &quot;Something Fishy. Russell wears a stripy undershirt when he goes to sleep. He lives in a big pirate ship shaped treehouse and sleeps on a hammock.
Since he only has one eye and his vision is becoming blurry, he's recommended to wear a contact lens as seen in A Sight for Sore Eyes
He appears to be friends with Lumpy in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Sea What I Found]]. He has also been seen with Nutty and Handy in Ipso Fatso, Disco Bear in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|The Wrong Side of the Tracks and Sniffles in Double Whammy Part 1. And in Can't Stop Coffin]] he was seen playing baseball with Cuddles, Toothy and Cro-Marmot
So far, the only internet episode he survived in was [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Can't Stop Coffin]]. During the TV series he has survived in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|A Sight for Sore Eyes, The Wrong Side of the Tracks, Mime to Five, Chew Said a Mouthful, See What Develops, Easy Comb, Easy Go, Double Whammy Part 1 and Milk Pong]].

===Sniffles===

A [[nerd]]y blue-gray [[anteater]] who is one of the more intelligent characters in the series. He is the second character without a heart nose and a pair of buckteeth. He usually likes doing and reading science and math problems. To reinforce the 'nerd' image that Sniffles exudes, he is seen dressed up as a Star Trek character (probably [[Spock]], the [[Vulcan (Star Trek)|Vulcan]] ears being the giveaway) in Remains to be Seen, and also sports a pocket protector on his chest
Sniffles' IQ has proved to be extremely high in both the internet and TV series. He has built things that are far more advanced than most of the other characters (ex. a rocket from a school bus and even a time machine). Sometimes, however, these devices can malfunction and work against him, leading to his own death and the deaths of others. Like Toothy, he has a wide range of deaths, usually involving either his tongue, his head, his limbs, or his organs. He also has a multitude of jobs, including a doctor and a pilot. In addition, he is sort of a [[mad scientist]] (as shown in his Smoochie) mixing fluids which causes his death.
Sniffles also has a craving for ants, which is one of his animal instincts. However, whenever he tries to eat one, they kill him after torturing him in the most sadistic manners. Only in the episode Blast from the Past has Sniffles eaten an ant without being killed. In general, Sniffles' deaths are slower and more painful than most of the other characters. Tongue in Cheek had to be his worst and longest death, bringing him to tears from the extreme pain or sheer despair. On some occasions, however, he has had quick deaths, such as in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Spare Me, Class Act, The Wrong Side of the Tracks, Blast from the Past, Remains to be Seen, Ipso Fatso, Wingin' It, Idol Curiosity, Aw Shucks!, Concrete Solution, Gems the Breaks and Boo Do You Think You Are?]]. Similar to Cub, Sniffles rarely survives in the episodes he appears in. The only episodes that he survived are [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Happy Trails pt. 1, Stealing the Spotlight, Blast from the Past (with the time machine), See What Develops, Wipe Out, Easy Comb, Easy Go, Hear Today, Gone Tomorrow, We're Scrooged!, the HTF Break short Happy New Year and Happy Tree Friends: False Alarm episode]].
His mouth and nose are combined to make a trunk-like snout, with his lips at the tip. It used to be long in the Internet shorts, but later, in the TV series, it became much shorter. The reason for this was to add additional cuteness to his appearance.
Sniffles' home appears to be a lab, as seen in I've Got You Under My Skin, Blast from the Past, A Sight for Sore Eyes, Suck it Up and Tongue in Cheek episodes.
It is worth noting that Sniffles, although not one of the four center characters (Lumpy, Cuddles, Giggles, Toothy), is beginning to become more of a main character. He has the second most starring roles in the TV series at a total of 6 starring roles next to Lumpy, who has 16. He has also had a total of 17 starring roles if you add up his starring roles in TV and Internet episodes
In the &quot;Collect Them All section&quot;, Sniffles has a few allergies and he loves calculating long division problems
He has a MySpace account that shows that his idols are Albert Einstein, Spock, William Shatner and Splendid. Sniffles is the second character to idolize Splendid (along with Toothy), further evidenced in Suck it Up and A Sight for Sore Eyes. He is good friends with Nutty as seen in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|From Hero to Eternity]]. He is also friends with Giggles as seen in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Boo Do You Think You Are?, Happy Trails Pt. 2: Jumping the Shark, I've Got You Under My Skin, Every Litter Bit Hurts and Idol Curiosity]]. He has also been in a few episodes with Lumpy in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|In a Jam, I've Got You Under My Skin, See What Develops, Take a Hike, From A to Zoo, Class Act, A Hole Lotta Love and Blast from the Past]].

===Splendid===
A pale blue [[superhero]] [[flying squirrel]] with light blue patagiums (gliding wings), a light blue/white oval marking on his torso, and a red mask around his head. He is largely based on Superman; he can fly, shoot laser beams from his eyes, has super strength, super speed, supersonic hearing, can turn back time, and can breathe ice. He is often seen doing housework until he hears the screams of a character that needs to be rescued. His appearance is somewhat based on Rocky J. Squirrel from Rocky and Bullwinkle. Similar to Flippy, Splendid isn't featured in either the TV or internet series a lot due to his repetitive trend of killing the characters he rescues. Whenever he appears, he is the character the episode revolves around with the exception of Class Act.
The irony of Splendid being a superhero is that he often unintentionally kills the characters he rescues (Giggles in particular). This is usually either because of his ignorance or his own powers. Most of the time, he is oblivious to the other characters' deaths. He often flies away without checking to see if the other characters are actually safe with the exception of the episodes, Helping Helps and Wrath of Con. However, in Gems the Breaks, he purposely killed three characters (The Mole, Lifty &amp; Shifty). In most episodes he appears in he kills all characters present, though in some episodes (ex., See What Develops) other characters cause others' deaths. He believes that being a superhero is a pain in the neck
Some think that Splendid has never died in the Internet shorts. This all depends on whether or not the fans assume that Splendid was killed in the schoolhouse explosion in [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes|Class Act]]. (You can see Splendid fly in when everyone is hurt outside). His only confirmed death was in the TV episode Gems the Breaks, where he was overexposed to his one and only superhero weakness: Kryptonut, a parody of Superman's [[Kryptonite]] weakness. It looks like a green glowing acorn, except it's made out of rock. Not only will the Kryptonut make him lose his powers, but it'll also make him vomit profusely and give him a stomach flu. The two raccoons, Lifty and Shifty used it on him and manage to steal museum items. Splendid managed to boil them to death with his sulpher vision, but as soon he breaks the Kryptonut, he inhales it's air and his cheeks swell with vomit and he explodes.
While it would make sense that Kryptonut is Splendid's only weakness, Warren Graff has stated that &quot;He's not as immune as he seems to be,&quot; meaning he may die more often in future episodes.
He has his own action show called Splendid's SSSSSuper Squad, part of the Happy Tree Friends Action Series: Ka-Pow! show. In his first Ka-Pow! episode, Mirror Mirror, he met his evil red counterpart named Splendont. He was about to get acquainted with him, but Splendont snubbed him, and they began to fight each other to determine who is the better superhero. After Splendont shoved the moon towards Splendid and ran him into the ground, his doppelganger flew away, making this the first time Splendid has ever been defeated. He pressed his acorn-shaped watch to contact a team of other animal superheroes called the Supremely Sensational Stupendously Spectacular Super Squad for assistance. They were last seen trying to pry Splendid out of the pavement, but failed when the giant crowbar they were using broke

===Toothy===
A light [[purple]]/mauve [[beaver]] with very large, gapped teeth (from which his name is derived), which appears to be diastema and freckles. Although his character description on the official site says he has &quot;big ol' buckteeth&quot; larger than the other characters, but in Season 2, he occasionally has the normal buckteeth. He is generally a very friendly character who likes to play around now and then, particularly with the younger characters. He admires Splendid (possibly when Splendid saved him in the episode Better Off Bread), and even dresses up as him for Halloween. He is good friends with Cuddles as seen in Spin Fun Knowin' Ya, Class Act, From A to Zoo, Remains to be Seen, Who's to Flame?, Take a Hike, Snow Place to Go, Blast from the Past, Can't Stop Coffin, Autopsy Turvy (Double Whammy Part 2), Party Animal, Concrete Solution, Wrath of Con and the Strain Kringle. He is also good friends with Giggles, Sniffles, Lumpy, and Petunia. Toothy is one of the primary characters in the show, as he appears in many commercials and advertisements. 

There are a couple of ways in which he is famous: he is the first character to be killed ever in Happy Tree Friends (if one doesn't include Banjo Frenzy as an episode) and he is also the character who suffered a very horrible death in the episode that won an award at the Annecy International Animated Film Festival in France, the infamous Eye Candy. Also, Toothy has a wide range of deaths; usually involving his eyes or his head. 

He can be used in wide range of situations, unlike most of the other characters whose personality defines how they might act in a given situation. He mostly acts before he thinks (e.g. running away and throwing a lit candle behind him in Class Act). He is not generally considered addle-brained, even though there have been instances where he's acted rather oddly in certain situations (such as misinterpreting some instructions and pouring two barrels full of gun powder into a cannon, rather than the necessary two spoonfuls in Mime to Five). Also, Toothy is known to cry in a few episodes when he gets hurt (e.g., Blast from the Past where he flew off the slide and broke his arm). 

It is stated by one of the creators that Toothy is often used as a 'place holder' character due to his ordinary 'Generic Tree Friend' appearance, until they have decided upon a final character. For example, in the storyboard for Wipe Out Toothy was originally drawn in Cuddles' place surfing and getting impaled on a buoy. His lack of a definite character also means that when he is used as a 'place holder' he won't influence the shaping of the episode in ways the creators dont necessarily mean or want. Sometimes it is Toothy himself who plays the final role in an episode. 

Also, while Toothy does have a starring pop-up, he never actually got a real starring role in the TV series. The only episode he starred in was Autopsy Turvy, which wasn't an actual episode. 

Even though Toothy dies almost as often as Cuddles does, he has survived in Nuttin' but the Tooth, I Get a Trick Out of You, Kringle Karols, A Change of Heart, Wipe Out, Wingin' It, Read 'em and Weep, Can't Stop Coffin, (debatably) Banjo Frenzy, Cold Hearted,, the Youtube Live Episode, All Flocked Up, Something Fishy, and the HTF Break shorts, Deck the Halls, We Wish You and Youtube Copyright School. Many of Toothy's injuries and some of Toothy's deaths involve his eyes, as seen in Eye Candy, Keepin' it Reel, Chew Said a Mouthful, Idol Curiosity, and A Sight for Sore Eyes. 

In the HTF official forums, writer Ken Pontac said he feels Toothy is the most undeveloped character and needs more of a personality. Ken has said that they may give Toothy more of a personality in future episodes. This is already happening in some of the recent episodes (such as the Love Bites short Cold Hearted, where he is shown to be mischievous by interfering with Giggles' and Cro-Marmot's relationship). 

It seems in some episodes that Toothy loves to sing, and others think he's a good singer. As seen in Class Act, Deck the Halls, and We Wish You. Toothy has also cried many times such has Mime and Mime Again(debatably) Eye Candy, and Class Act.

==Other characters==
*'''Generic Tree Friends'''  Generic Tree Friends are not colored the usual colors; they are all-black, mysterious coloured but their eyes, nose, and mouth are shown. They are mostly used in masses when needed. Some of them look like a darker version of Toothy.
*'''Pig Child'''  The final character to appear in &quot;Mole and the City&quot;.
*'''Giggles' Mom'''  Appearing only in the episode &quot;Helping Helps&quot;. She was voiced by [[Dana Belben]].
*'''Old Prehistoric Sniffles'''  This prehistoric anteater appears in the episode &quot;Blast from the Past&quot;. He is voiced by [[Liz Stuart]].
*'''The Narrator'''  A narrator that gives instructions to Lumpy in the training video ''Ski Patrol''. The narrator was voiced by [[Mark Giambruno]].
*'''[[Fall Out Boy]]'''  The band members appeared in the music video as bears for The Carpal Tunnel of Love.
*'''Elephant Balloon Man''' - A male [[elephant]] from &quot;Mole in the City&quot;.  He is  killed by falling glass.
*'''FatKat''' - A blue [[cat]] with a single tooth, a large body and a tail that has a bandage wrapped around it. Not much is known about this character, and as far as anyone can tell he/she has only featured in the episode 'HTF break- Take Your Seat' where he/she screamed when Flaky was killed. Truffles (See Below) was also seen in this episode.
*'''Truffles''' - Truffles, a male [[aquamarine]] [[pig]], was the other new character choice during the 2010 poll. As he lost, it is unlikely that he'll ever be seen in an episode (except for a cameo in the debut episode of Lammy and Mr. Pickles, the winners of the poll). He does, however, appear for an extremely short period of time (just a fraction of him hiding in the background) in the episode, &quot;A Bit of a Pickle&quot; and a few others after that.

===Ka-Pow! characters===
{{Main|Ka-Pow!}}

====W.A.R Journal====

*'''Flippy''' is a green bear that has post-traumatic stress disorder and goes insane when in conditions that remind him of the war , and starts killing other characters. He is shown that he is not capable of doing things under pressure in the war and killed his teammates by mistake
*'''Sneaky''' is a green [[chameleon]] that can stretch his tongue and [[camouflage|blend in with any background]]. He was accidentally pinned to a wall by Flippy with his knife and was partly blown up shortly after. So far he is the only anthropomorphic creature in all of the HTF series that is not a mammal.
*'''Mouse Ka-Boom''' is an [[orange (colour)|orange]] [[mouse]] with a French accent. He specializes with explosives, is deaf, and has bandages on his ears. He says &quot;Le&quot; before any word. He was accidentally sliced in the middle by Flippy and blown up by his own explosives.
*'''The Tiger Army''' are the enemies that Flippy and his crew face.
*'''Tiger General''' is one of the evil leaders of '''The Tiger Army''' Flippy and his companions are sent to kill. He serves as the main villain of W.A.R Journal. He is missing an eye and has a claw for his left hand. He was crushed to death by a falling log after a long and bloody fight with Flippy.

====Buddhist Monkey====

*'''Buddhist Monkey''' ([[Jeff Biancalana]]) - A special character that starred in his own special episodes: &quot;Enter the Garden&quot;, &quot;Books of Fury&quot;, and &quot;Three Courses of Death&quot;. He is the only star-characters that never died. He seems to be a [[fictional character]] within the Happy Tree Friends World. Buddhist Monkey was originally supposed to be a main character, but the creators thought he didn't fit. Instead of getting rid of him they decided to give him his own show.
*'''Dark Shadow Lord''': The supposed main enemy of Buddhist Monkey and Ruler of the Ninja/Generic Tree Ninja clan. His name may have been mentioned as Char Sew, but it may be the Pig Ninja's, he appears to be an ancient [[Chinese dragon]].
*'''Generic Tree Ninjas''' - A special group of Generic Tree Friends from [[Japan]], who terrorize the sacred places where Buddhist Monkey lives. They're the Followers of the Unnamed Shadow Lord.
*'''Char Sew''': One of the Dark Shadow Lord's more elite warriors, a [[pig]] [[ninja]]. He has a [[Giant Enemy Crab|Giant Crab]] that he can control. He and the [[Crab]] were boiled to death in '''Three Courses of Death'''.
*'''Orangutan Master''' - Buddhist Monkey's teacher when Buddhist Monkey was younger.He is also the one who made Buddhist Monkey bald. It was hinted that he died some time before '''Ka-Pow!'''.
*'''Panda Mom and Panda Cub''': A mother [[giant panda|Panda]] and a baby Panda who live near Buddhist Monkey. The pair are the 'Buddhist Monkey' counterparts of Pop and Cub. It was hinted that she became poor due to [[poverty]] in '''Ka-Pow!'''

====Splendid's SSSSSuper Squad====
*'''Splendont''' - The Polar Opposite of Splendid. He was freed when Splendid plugged a volcano with a large rock, the pressure built up, and it was launched into outer space. The rock broke the mirror prison, setting him free. Although Splendid is blue with light blue patagiums, a light blue oval marking on his tummy, and wears a red mask, Splendont is red with dark red patagiums, a light red oval marking on his tummy, and wears a blue mask.
*'''Super Squad''' - The super hero team that Splendid summoned for help. The 4 members are: a female [[fox]] with the powers to create phantom hands, a female [[spider]] with multiple eyes and several bows on her head, a creature in a [[robot]]ic suit, and a [[jellyfish]]-like creature in a jar of water. They try to get Splendid out of the pavement, but failed because the giant [[crowbar]] broke.

===Enemies===
While most suffering in Happy Tree Friends is accidental, there are some antagonistic forces within the fictional world.
*'''Cursed Idol''' - A [[Maya civilization|Mayan statue]] which brings [[death]] and bad [[luck]]. This cursed Idol does none other than just sit there. When it appears, everyone who is near the statue dies brutally. This idol is based on the golden fertility idol in ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]''. It features in the episodes &quot;Treasure Those Idol Moments&quot;, &quot;Hello Dolly&quot;, and &quot;Idol Curiosity&quot;. It appears as a prop in many other episodes.

*'''The Rat''' - He has appeared only once and died by being split in half on a giant [[mousetrap|mouse trap]] in the episode &quot;Mole in the City&quot;.

*'''Demon''' - A [[carnivore|carnivorous]] [[demon]] with [[tentacle]]s who [[demonic possession|possessed]] Cub in &quot;Read Em and Weep&quot;. It was summoned when Pop reads a [[Satan]]ic-looking book, which resembles [[The Necronomicon]].

*'''Whistle''' - A cute little blue [[dog]] that Pop buys for Cub at the local [[pet store|pet shop]] in &quot;Doggone it&quot;. Although cute, lovable, and playful, Whistle has savage and murderous tendencies toward anybody in sight using his cuteness to deceive his victims. This [[puppy]] somewhat bares traits with Flippy: as Flippy's flip-outs are triggered by anything reminding him of war or the heat of battle, The Puppy's savage side is triggered by any high-pitched sound (i.e. a whistle blowing). Whistle is based on [[Ken Pontac]]'s dog who has the same name.

*'''Pod Lumpys''' - An army of green Lumpy [[cloning|clones]] who appeared in the episode &quot;Peas in a Pod&quot;.

*'''The Ants family''' ([[Kenn Navarro]], [[Warren Graff]] and [[Ken Pontac]]) - A family that has a mother ant, a father ant (deceased), a teenage daughter, the middle son, and a baby ant. Whenever they appear in an episode, it often involves Sniffles trying to eat them, only to be tortured and killed in the most sadistic manners.

==See also==
* [[Mondo Mini Shows]]
* [[Happy Tree Friends]]
* [[List of Happy Tree Friends episodes]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://mondo.happytreefriends.com/about_the_show/characters.html A list of characters on the Happy Tree Friends Official Website]
*[http://www.happytreefriends.com Happy Tree Friends Official Website]

{{Happy Tree Friends}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Happy Tree Friends Characters}}
[[Category:Lists of characters in television animation]]
[[Category:Happy Tree Friends|Characters]]

[[es:Anexo:Personajes de Happy Tree Friends]]
[[id:Pop (Happy Tree Friends)]]
[[it:Personaggi di Happy Tree Friends]]
[[hu:A Happy Tree Friends szerepli]]
[[nl:Buddhist Monkey]]
[[ru:  Happy Tree Friends]]
[[zh:]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
