<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9791638" ns="0" title="DePaul Blue Demons"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
| name             = DePaul Blue Demons
| logo             =
| university       = [[DePaul University]]
| conference       = [[Big East Conference]],
| division         = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
| director         = Jean Lenti Ponsetto
| city             = Chicago
| state            = Illinois
| stateabb         = IL
| teams            = 6 men &amp; 7 women
| stadium          = Wish Field (soccer)
| arena            = [[Allstate Arena]] (men's basketball)
| arena2           = [[McGrath-Phillips Arena]] (women's basketball)
| mascot           = DIBS
| nickname         = Blue Demons
| fightsong        = &quot;Blue Demons Fight Song&quot;
| color1           = Royal Blue
| color2           = Scarlet
| color3           =
| hex1             = 0000FF
| hex2             = FF0000
| hex3             =
| pageurl          = http://www.depaulbluedemons.com/
| pagename         = www.depaulbluedemons.com
}}

'''The DePaul Blue Demons''' are the intercollegiate athletic teams of [[DePaul University]], located in [[Chicago Illinois]]. The Blue Demons participate in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] and is a member of the [[Big East Conference]].

In 1900, when the first athletic team to represent DePaul University was organized, the monogram &quot;D&quot; was selected for the uniforms. From this originated the nickname &quot;D-men&quot; which evolved into &quot;Demons.&quot; The blue, which combines with Demons, signifies loyalty and was chosen in 1901 by a vote of the student body. The university's official school colors are [[royal blue]] (PMS 287) and [[scarlet (color)|scarlet]] (PMS 185).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.depaulbluedemons.com/trads/a-to-z.html DePaul Basketball A-to-Z – DePaul University Athletics.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sports==
DePaul University fields 13 sports, 6 men's and 7 women's:

{{Col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
'''Men's Intercollegiate Sports'''
* [[Basketball]]
* [[Cross country running|Cross Country]]
* [[Golf]]
* [[Soccer]]
* [[Tennis]]
* [[Track &amp; Field]]

{{col-2}}
'''Women's intercollegiate athletic teams'''
* [[Basketball]]
* [[Cross country running|Cross Country]]
* [[Soccer]]
* [[Softball]]
* [[Tennis]]
* [[Track &amp; Field]]
* [[Volleyball]]
{{col-end}}

===Men's basketball===
{{Main|DePaul Blue Demons men's basketball}}
The school is well known for its basketball program which gained prominence under [[Ray Meyer]] who led the team to the NCAA Division I basketball [[Final Four]] in the 1978–1979 season. The school's only national championship came in 1945 after winning the NIT tournament. The team has played at the [[Allstate Arena]] since 1980.

The men's basketball coach, [[Jerry Wainwright]], was fired on January 11, 2010. Assistant coach Tracy Webster will be the interim coach for the remainder of the current season. Wainwright still had two years remaining on his contract at the time of his firing. Wainwright's first season with his young team was erratic, beating No. 16 [[Wake Forest Demon Deacons men's basketball|Wake Forest]] 84-81 before falling to Old Dominion by a score of 87–43 (the worst defeat in the team's history), and then beating future Big East Champion, [[Syracuse University|Syracuse]], 108–69 on March 2, 2006. In the 2006–2007 season, the Blue Demons beat powerhouse #5 [[Kansas Jayhawks men's basketball|Kansas]], pulling off one of the greatest upsets in school history. They also beat 2006 NCAA tournament teams [[California]], [[Northwestern State]], [[Marquette University|Marquette]], [[Connecticut]], and [[Villanova University|Villanova]]. The team made it to the NIT and lost in the bracket final to Air Force.

The Demons opened up the 2008 season with two of their star players gone to the NBA. But freshman [[Dar Tucker]] and [[Mac Koshwal]] look to fill in those spots and senior Draelon Burns is already a star. Four games into the 2007-2008 season, Wainwright logged his 200th career win as a head coach. He has made six post-season appearances in his previous 12&amp;nbsp;years as head coach. The 2007–08 season saw the Demons with a 10–19 record, but there were high points in the year. DePaul had upsets over [[Villanova University]],  then ranked #15 nationally and ultimately a member of the NCAA Sweet Sixteen, and [[Northwestern University|Northwestern]]. However, things took a turn for the worse during the 2008-2009 season. DePaul went 0-18 in regular season Big East play, setting a school-record for longest losing streak, before winning their first [[Big East Conference]] [[Big East Men's Basketball Tournament|tournament]] game against Cincinnati.  During the 2009-10 season, head coach Jerry Wainwright was fired and replaced by [[Oliver Purnell]] of [[Clemson University]] after the season ended.

===Women's basketball===
DePaul's NCAA women's basketball reached the Sweet 16 for the first time in the program's history in 2006. Head Coach [[Doug Bruno]] is entering his 22nd year as head coach of the team. He recently completed a two-year term as president of the [[Women's Basketball Coaches Association]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wbca.org/Board.asp WBCA website]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Softball===
The DePaul women's softball team has participated four times in the [[Women's College World Series]] since 1999. It finished the 2006-07 season ranked sixth in the final USA Today/NFCA Poll.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nfca.org/news/index.php?id=2785 NFCA website]&lt;/ref&gt; The women's softball team has participated in the NCAA World Series several times in recent years. Head coach Eugene Lenti and his staff were named National Fastpitch Coaches Association Mideast Region Staff of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nfca.org/news/index.php?id=2793 NFCA website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Club sports==
DePaul offers a number of other intercollegiate club athletic teams under the Department of Recreational Sports.

===Ice hockey===
DePaul University has an ice hockey club team called the DePaul University Hockey Club that competes as an Independent team in the Central Division of [[ACHA]] Division II. The team plays a 25-30 game schedule against regional opponents from the Midwest and Great Lakes regions of the [[United States]], including: [[Indiana University]], [[University of Illinois]], [[Illinois State University]], and [[Northern Illinois University]]. Home games are played at the [[Northshore Ice Arena]]. In 2009 the team made the ACHA Division II National Championship Tournament for the first time in the team's history.

===Lacrosse===
DePaul University fields Men's Lacrosse at the non-varsity club level at the [[Men's Collegiate Lacrosse Association|MCLA]] Division II  level in the [[Great Rivers Lacrosse Conference]] in the GRLC Northeast Division. DePaul Lacrosse rivals include: [[Augustana College (Illinois)|Augustana College]], [[St. Louis University]], [[Palmer College of Chiropractic]] and [[Wheaton College (Illinois)|Wheaton College]] as well as other MCLA opponents. They play their home games at Diversey Harbor (Chicago Park District) and Techny Field in Glenbrook, IL.  
They promote 'epic flow' hair-styles and 'top cheese' shot-locations.

===Volleyball===
DePaul University's Men's Volleyball Club competes at the division 1AA level, hosts and travels to several tournaments per year, competing against clubs from across the nation.  The Blue Demons practice and play their home matches at the Ray Meyer Fitness and Recreation Center.  In 2011, the Blue Demons finished 3rd at the NCVF National Championships in Houston, Tx, their best finish in club history.

==Facilities==
* '''Allstate Arena''' in [[Rosemont, Illinois]] has been the home of Blue Demons men's basketball since 1980.
* '''Cacciatore Stadium''' is the 1000-seat softball field for Blue Demons Softball.
* '''McGrath-Phillips Arena''' is a 3,000 seat indoor arena located in the '''Sullivan Athletic Center'''. It is the home of women's basketball and volleyball.
* '''Wish Field''' is the home of Blue Demons men’s and women’s soccer programs.

==Traditions==
===Mascot===
DePaul's mascot is DIBS which stands for Demon In a Blue Suit. DIBS is present at every Blue Demons basketball game and makes frequent appearances at DePaul's Lincoln Park Campus and charity appearances around the Chicago metropolitan area. While the Blue Demon nickname has been around for many years, the Blue Demon mascot took the game floor for the first time in 1968 with a papier-mache head and old warm-up suit. Through the years, the Blue Demon has taken on many forms in its evolution and was dubbed DIBS in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.depaulbluedemons.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=15600&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=1285279 View the DePaul Blue Demons site]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Blue Demons fight song===
We will gather&lt;br /&gt;
'Neath your banner,&lt;br /&gt;
'Neath the scarlet and the blue,&lt;br /&gt;
While in song we&lt;br /&gt;
Tell your praises&lt;br /&gt;
Praises for old DePaul U&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Let the battle&lt;br /&gt;
wage and threaten&lt;br /&gt;
Yours the victory to claim;&lt;br /&gt;
As we fight beneath your standard: Proud!&lt;br /&gt;
Exulting in your name.&lt;br /&gt;
D - E - M - O - N S&lt;br /&gt;
(repeat first verse and conclude with &quot;D-E-P-A-U-L&quot;)

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.depaulbluedemons.com DePaul Blue Demons Official Athletics Website]

{{Big East Conference}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Depaul Blue Demons}}
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]
[[Category:DePaul Blue Demons|*]]

[[es:DePaul Blue Demons]]
[[fr:Blue Demons de DePaul]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
