<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9814451" ns="0" title="William E. Adams"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other persons|William Adams}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= William Edward Adams
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1939|6|16}}
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1971|5|25|1939|6|16}}
|birth_place= [[Casper, Wyoming]]  
|death_place= [[Kontum]], [[Vietnam]]
|placeofburial= [[Fort Logan National Cemetery]], [[Denver, Colorado]]
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image= [[File:Adams w.jpg|150px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; [[File:cmoh army.jpg|70px]]
|caption=  Major William E. Adams
|nickname= 
|allegiance= [[United States|United States of America]]
|branch= [[United States Army]]
|serviceyears= 1962 - 1971
|rank= [[Major (rank)|Major]]
|commands= 
|unit= [[52nd Aviation Regiment (United States)|52nd Aviation Battalion]], [[1st Air Cavalry Brigade, 1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Air Cavalry Brigade, 1st Cavalry Division]]
|battles=[[Vietnam War]]
|awards= [[File:Medal of Honor ribbon.svg|60px]] - [[Medal of Honor]]
}}
'''William Edward Adams''' (June 16, 1939 – May 25, 1971) was a Major in the [[United States Army]] who was killed in [[South Vietnam]] during the [[Vietnam War]]. He received the [[Medal of Honor]].

==Biography==
Adams was born in [[Casper, Wyoming]].  He attended [[Wentworth Military Academy]] in [[Lexington, Missouri]], and graduated from [[Colorado State University]] in 1962.&lt;ref name=&quot;csu20091022&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.news.colostate.edu/Release/4864|title=Medal of Honor recipients to be honored at Colorado State University October 24|date=October 22, 2009|publisher=[[Colorado State University]]|accessdate=November 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He joined the U.S. Army in [[Kansas City, Missouri]], with the serial number 521482167. He began his tour in [[Vietnam]] on Monday, July 6, 1970. On May 25, 1971, Adams, a major, volunteered to fly a lightly armed helicopter mission to rescue three wounded soldiers from a besieged firebase in [[Kontum]] Province, despite the clear weather which would provide the numerous enemy [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] around the location with clear visibility. Despite fire from [[machine gun]] emplacements and rockets, Adams succeeded in landing at the firebase while supporting [[helicopter gunship]]s attacked the enemy positions. After take off, however, the helicopter was hit by fire. Adams momentarily regained control and attempted to land, however the helicopter exploded in mid air and crashed. Adams, who was 31 at the time, was killed.

He is buried at [[Fort Logan National Cemetery]] in [[Denver, Colorado]]. His grave can be found in plot P O, Grave 3831.&lt;ref name=findagrave&gt;{{Find a Grave|19447|work=Claim to Fame: Medal of Honor recipients|accessdate=2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Memorials==
The Vietnam War Memorial on the campus of [[Wentworth Military Academy]] is the same make and model helicopter that Adams was flying when he was killed.  He is listed on the [[Vietnam War Memorial]] on panel 03W, row 054.

==Medal of Honor citation==
'''Citation:'''
:Maj. Adams distinguished himself on 25 May 1971 while serving as a helicopter pilot in Kontum Province in the Republic of Vietnam. On that date, Maj. Adams volunteered to fly a lightly armed helicopter in an attempt to evacuate 3 seriously wounded soldiers from a small fire base which was under attack by a large enemy force. He made the decision with full knowledge that numerous antiaircraft weapons were positioned around the base and that the clear weather would afford the enemy gunners unobstructed view of all routes into the base. As he approached the base, the enemy gunners opened fire with heavy machine guns, rocket-propelled grenades and small arms. Undaunted by the fusillade, he continued his approach determined to accomplish the mission. Displaying tremendous courage under fire, he calmly directed the attacks of supporting gunships while maintaining absolute control of the helicopter he was flying. He landed the aircraft at the fire base despite the ever-increasing enemy fire and calmly waited until the wounded soldiers were placed on board. As his aircraft departed from the fire base, it was struck and seriously damaged by enemy anti-aircraft fire and began descending. Flying with exceptional skill, he immediately regained control of the crippled aircraft and attempted a controlled landing. Despite his valiant efforts, the helicopter exploded, overturned, and plummeted to earth amid the hail of enemy fire. Maj. Adams' conspicuous gallantry, intrepidity, and humanitarian regard for his fellow man were in keeping with the most cherished traditions of the military service and reflected utmost credit on him and the U S. Army.&lt;ref name=MOHC&gt;[http://www.cmohs.org/recipients/wadams_citation.htm W. Adams' citation], Congressional Medal of Honor Society&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Biography|United States Army}}
*[[List of Medal of Honor recipients]]
*[[List of Medal of Honor recipients for the Vietnam War#A|List of Medal of Honor recipients for the Vietnam War]]
*[http://www.billmoorephotography.com/2011/11/14/veterans-day-ft-logan-cemetary/  See a photograph of Maj Adams Headstone]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*{{Cite web
  |url=http://www.mishalov.com/Adams.html
  |title=Medal of Honor &amp;mdash; ADAMS, WILLIAM E.
  |publisher=Mishalov.com}}
*{{Find a Grave|19447|work=Claim to Fame: Medal of Honor recipients|accessdate=2007-10-23}}

{{Persondata
|NAME= Adams, William E.
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= [[United States Army]] [[Medal of Honor]] recipient
|DATE OF BIRTH= June 16, 1939
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Casper, Wyoming]]
|DATE OF DEATH= May 25, 1971
|PLACE OF DEATH= [[Kontum]], [[Vietnam]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Adams, William E.}}
[[Category:1939 births]]
[[Category:1971 deaths]]
[[Category:Colorado State University alumni]]
[[Category:Army Medal of Honor recipients]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Purple Heart medal]]
[[Category:American military personnel killed in the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:United States Army officers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
