<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9815218" ns="0" title="Imeem"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Lowercase}}
{{Infobox website
| name = imeem
| logo = [[Image:imeempicture2007.png|imeem picture 2007.png]]
| screenshot =
| caption =
| commercial = Mixed
| type = Viral content sharing, [[social network service]]
| registration = free, required to play many full-length songs
| owner = News Corp.
| author = Community
| launch date =
| current status = Defunct
| revenue =
}}
The online service '''imeem''' was a [[social media]] web site where users interacted with each other by [[Streaming media|streaming]], uploading and sharing music and music videos. However, after [[MySpace]] acquired the service, it was shut down, in 2009.

The company was founded in 2003 by [[Dalton Caldwell]] (formerly of [[Geeknet|VA Linux]]) and Jan Jannink (formerly of [[Napster]]), and many of its core engineering team came from the original [[Napster]] file-sharing service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://groups.imeem.com/wezReoWJ/forums/7QGDMXob/3fjlDrG2/jan_jannink_cofounder/ |title='Jan Jannink, Co-Founder' thread in imeem forum |work=Groups.imeem.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company takes its name from &quot;[[meme]]&quot;, a term coined by biologist [[Richard Dawkins]] to describe the ideas and cultural phenomena that spread as if they had a life of their own.

Helping to pioneer the free, advertising-supported model for online music, imeem permitted consumers to legally upload, stream and share music and music playlists for free with the costs supported by advertising. In 2007, imeem became the first-ever online music site to secure licenses from all four U.S. major music labels to offer their music catalogs for free streaming and sharing on the web.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Erick Schonfeld Dec 9, 2007 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/12/09/imeem-pens-a-deal-with-universal-music-now-has-all-the-majors/ |title=Imeem Pens a Deal with Universal Music. Now Has All the Majors |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2007-12-09 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company also created the web's first embeddable music and video playlists. People could use imeem's widgets to embed songs and playlists from imeem virtually anywhere on the web, including on their [[MySpace]] and [[Facebook]] profiles or on their personal blogs.

Headquartered in San Francisco's [[South of Market]] district (SoMa),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_of_Market |title=South of Market, San Francisco - Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia |work=En.wikipedia.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; imeem had additional offices in [[New York]] and [[Los Angeles]]. The company's investors included [[Morgenthaler]] Ventures and [[Warner Music Group]].

On December 8, 2009, imeem was bought out by [[MySpace Music]] in a [[firesale]] for an undisclosed amount. However, it is stated to have been less than $1 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5iPjkT7BYe4XMf5Q71ZPcjAp9UUfgD9CFC8G80 MySpace buys imeem music site for under $1 mln]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business model==
Revenue generation at imeem was through a combination of direct and indirect advertising sales, sales of MP3 downloads, ringtones and concert tickets, and subscription revenue from premium services. The bulk of its revenue came from advertising; advertisers who ran direct campaigns with imeem included [[TheTruth.com]]/American Legacy Foundation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clickz.com/3634240 |title=Anti-Smoking Campaign Hits Up Music Site for Social Media Outreach |work=ClickZ |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kia Motors]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clickz.com/3631823 |title=Kia First Brand on imeem's New Google Phone Ad Platform |work=ClickZ |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Butcher |first=Dan |url=http://www.mobilemarketer.com/cms/news/advertising/2175.html |title=Kia Motors America breaks mobile ad campaign - Mobile Marketer - Advertising |work=Mobile Marketer |date=2008-11-25 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Dr Pepper]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adweek.com/aw/content_display/news/digital/e3i8fb28a31928f66a5de55613a9c4072a1 |title=Web Music Players Strike a New Chord |work=Adweek.com |date=2009-08-17 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://askamillennial.blogspot.com/2009/08/its-hard-working-in-marketing.html |title=Ask a Millennial: Why I Love Imeem |work=Askamillennial.blogspot.com |date=2009-12-14 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; among others.

The company was one of the pioneers of the ad-supported streaming music model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/2008/08/07/technology/imeem.fortune/index.htm | work=CNN | date=August 8, 2008 | accessdate=April 3, 2010 | title=Making free music pay off | first=Devin | last=Leonard}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, imeem became the first-ever online music site to secure licenses from all 4 major music labels to offer their music catalogs for free streaming and sharing on the web.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/2007/dec/10/business/fi-universal10 | work=Los Angeles Times | title=Universal to let site play songs in ad deal | first=Joseph | last=Menn | date=December 10, 2007 | accessdate=May 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under this model, artists and labels were paid a share of imeem's ad revenue in proportion to the popularity of their music on imeem, and had the right to register their content and determine how (or whether) that content is available on the site or through its embeddable widgets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2007/imeem-launches-pioneering-ad-supported-interactive-music-service-powered-by-snocap/]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This business model was made possible by imeem's proprietary content fingerprinting and digital registry technology. Initially, imeem licensed this technology from [[SNOCAP]], the digital rights and content management startup founded by [[Napster]] creator [[Shawn Fanning]].&lt;ref name=&quot;blog.imeem.com&quot;&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2007/social-network-imeem-partners-with-snocap-to-provide-innovative-content-promotion-and-ad-supported-revenue-model-giving-artists-labels-and-fans-protection-and-accessibility/]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, imeem acquired SNOCAP and its technology outright.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=McCarthy |first=Caroline |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13577_3-9912665-36.html?tag=mncol |title=As expected, Imeem bails out Snocap by acquiring it &amp;#124; The Social - CNET News |work=News.cnet.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; imeem continued to operate the SNOCAP digital registry, and used the technology acquired from SNOCAP to power its ad-supported streaming music service.

==Products==
The company provided two main services: '''imeem.com''', where people could discover, stream and share music and music videos for free, and '''imeem Mobile''', an [[Internet radio]] service for mobile devices. In addition, the company offered a premium service, imeem VIP, that gave people access to additional features on the imeem site.

===imeem.com===
Registered users of the site could stream and share millions of songs and tens of thousands of music videos free of charge, with the costs for licensing and streaming supported by advertising on the site and on imeem Mobile.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/legal/imeem-terms-of-use/]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of imeem's key features was the [[playlist]]. Users could create personal playlists, via a &quot;Create Music Playlist&quot; page, with music they had uploaded themselves or with music and video already available on the site. They could publish and share these playlists on imeem, where they could be played by, shared with, commented on, or tagged by other users.

Visitors could also share music, videos and playlists beyond imeem,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=&lt;!--start post navigation--&gt; Previous post Next post |url=http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2009/10/best-8-ways-to-share-mix-tapes/ |title=8 Best Ways to Share 'Mix Tapes' &amp;#124; Epicenter |work=Wired.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; either by embedding imeem players into external sites.

===imeem Mobile===
With the free cell phone application imeem Mobile, users could discover, purchase and enjoy music on their mobile device. It was available as a free download to users on the [[Android (operating system)|Android]] and [[iPhone]]/[[iPod touch]] platforms.

Users could create custom Internet radio stations based on their favorite artists, discover new music through personalized recommendations and buy DRM-free MP3 downloads directly onto their mobile device (on Android, downloads are from the Amazon MP3 application; on the iPhone and iPod touch, downloads are from the iTunes Store.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2009/imeem-mobile-now-available-on-the-apple-app-store/]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The app also enabled people to browse and stream their personal imeem music libraries to their mobile device. People could upload up to 20,000 songs of the music they own directly to imeem.com, and then access that music through their mobile devices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2009/imeem-mobile%E2%80%99s-new-mymusic-feature-helps-people-enjoy-their-music-anywhere/]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; To upload more than 100 songs, users had to subscribe to one of imeem's premium services.

The company introduced imeem Mobile on the Android platform in October 2008,&lt;ref name=&quot;venturebeat.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=October 20, 2008 | Eric Eldon |url=http://venturebeat.com/2008/10/20/imeem-launches-music-application-for-the-android-powered-g1-phone/ |title=Imeem launches music application for Android and the G1 phone |work=VentureBeat.com |date=2008-10-20 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and launched it for iPhone and iPod touch users in May 2009. At launch, it was the only streaming music application on the Android platform, which in turn led to it being one of the most popular applications installed on Android devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Erick Schonfeld Oct 20, 2008 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/10/20/imeem-for-android-takes-the-jukebox-in-the-sky-and-puts-it-in-your-pocket/ |title=Imeem For Android Takes the Jukebox in the Sky and Puts It in Your Pocket |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2008-10-20 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2009, imeem Mobile crossed a milestone of over 1 million installs on the Android and iPhone platforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;techcrunch.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=MG Siegler Jun 16, 2009 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/06/16/with-an-iphone-and-android-strategy-imeem-mobile-pushes-past-a-million-users/ |title=With An iPhone And Android Strategy, Imeem Mobile Pushes Past A Million Users |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2009-06-16 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The application received several awards, including a 2009 Crunchie Award for Best Mobile Application,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Michael Arrington Jan 10, 2009 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/01/10/congratulations-to-the-crunchies-winners-facebook-takes-top-prize-for-second-year/ |title=Congratulations to the Crunchies Winners; Facebook Takes Top Prize for Second Year |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2009-01-10 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Editor's Choice award from the blog AndroidGuys,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.androidguys.com/2008/10/27/androidguys-app-review-imeem-mobile/ |title=AndroidGuys App Review: imeem Mobile |work=Androidguys.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an award for 'Best Streaming Music App' in the 2009 Android Network Awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://androinica.com/2009/08/18/the-best-android-apps-part-1-the-android-network-award-winners-androidapps/ |title=The Best Android Apps [Part 1&amp;#93;: The Android Network Award Winners #androidapps &amp;#124; andrew |work=Androinica |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===imeem VIP===
In 2008, imeem launched a premium '''imeem VIP''' service that gave subscribers access to additional site features, most prominently the ability to upload more music (over 100 songs), and to watch videos up to [[1080p]] in resolution. There were three imeem VIP subscription tiers.  * The imeem &quot;VIP&quot; plans started at [[United States dollar|US$]]$9.99 per year for the &quot;VIP Lite&quot; plan, which gave subscribers access to streaming songs through the VIP Player, and 480p video (up from 360p for basic users). The &quot;VIP&quot; subscription option allowed uploading of up to 1,000 songs and viewing of 720p video, for $29.99 per year.  And the &quot;VIP Plus&quot; subscription allowed uploading of up to 20,000 songs and viewing of 1080p video, for $99.99 per year&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imeem.com/subscribe/upgrade/viplite/]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://help.imeem.com/forums/74648/entries/65660 |title=Hitlijsten, muziek top 100 &amp;#124; Myspace Music |work=Help.imeem.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Early history: 2003-2005===
The imeem service has changed drastically since its original inception as an messaging application that let people communicate by [[online chat]], [[blog]]ging, [[instant messaging]] and [[file sharing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2005/imeem-introduces-fun-secure-way-to-share-personal-content-with-friends-and-colleagues-online/ imeem Introduces Fun, Secure Way to Share Personal Content with Friends and Colleagues Online] {{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The service was billed as a &quot;[[Distributed computing|distributed]], [[peer-to-peer]], [[social network]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted Aug 15th 2005 5:55PM by Barb Dybwad |url=http://socialsoftware.weblogsinc.com/2005/08/15/imeem-launches-desktop-component-for-distributed-social/ |title=imeem launches desktop component for distributed social networking - The Social Software Weblog |work=SocialSoftware.WeblogsInc.com |date=2005-08-15 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Founder [[Dalton Caldwell]] began working on what would become the imeem messaging application during Thanksgiving weekend in 2003. Initially, he worked on the software from his home. In 2004, imeem moved into offices in downtown Palo Alto's 285 Hamilton building,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/magazines/business2/business2_archive/2005/11/01/8362807/index.htm | work=CNN | date=December 30, 2005 | accessdate=April 3, 2010 | title=Tech's Big Comeback | first1=Michael V. | last1=Copeland | first2=Om | last2=Malik}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Caldwell, Jannink and a small team of engineers continuing work on the software.

The company first unveiled its software in February 2005 at the [[DEMO conference]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2005/imeem-unveils-at-demo-worlds-first-all-in-one-instant-communications-software-im-blogging-photo-sharing-file-sharing-and-desktop-search/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and formally launched it that August.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2005/imeem-introduces-fun-secure-way-to-share-personal-content-with-friends-and-colleagues-online/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When imeem first launched, to use the service, users were required to download and install the desktop messaging and file-sharing software; the imeem Web site merely existed as a means for users to register and download the client. Though originally designed for messaging, it was the file-sharing function that took off. The client software supported the service's distributed database model: Every imeem client on the network had a database that would generate and store references to media content shared on the network; this system would accelerate access to content deemed to be close to the user. The service's media-sharing was peer-to-peer &amp;ndash; if a user shared photos or a podcast, then the data would only exist on the client database network; users who wanted to view the actual content would access it by peering directly with the publisher.

===2006===
In March 2006, imeem re-launched at the [[South by Southwest]] (SXSW) conference in [[Austin, Texas]], with a new focus on enabling people to interact through the imeem.com website, using media (photos, videos, music) to express their personalities and interests. Timed to coincide with the re-launch, imeem introduced new features enabling users to upload and play music and video on the site.

In September 2006, imeem introduced embeddable [[Adobe Flash]]-based playlists that gave people the ability to take music and video playlists they created (or found) on the site and embed them virtually anywhere on the web. The company's players quickly became popular with consumers using MySpace and other social networks, giving them a way to customize &amp; personalize their profiles with music.

As a result, imeem quickly gained traction, with the site's traffic growing to 10 million unique monthly users by the end of 2006. By March 2007, imeem's monthly traffic reached over 16 million unique monthly users.&lt;ref name=&quot;blog.imeem.com&quot;/&gt;

===2007===
In February 2007, [[MySpace]] took steps to limit the posting of imeem content on its site: any updates or comments with &quot;imeem&quot; even mentioned in them were removed upon posting. However, MySpace stopped blocking imeem in 2008.

In March 2007, imeem announced it was partnering with [[SNOCAP]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=March 7, 2007 by Pete Cashmore View Comments |url=http://mashable.com/2007/03/07/imeem-snocap/ |title=Imeem, SNOCAP Hook Up |work=Mashable.com |date=2007-03-07 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; the digital rights and content management startup founded by Napster creator Shawn Fanning, to enable legal uploading, streaming and sharing of music on imeem, utilizing SNOCAP's content fingerprinting and digital registry technology. The goal was to provide a way for consumers to upload and share music with their friends, for free, and to do so in a way where label and artists can both make money and have greater control over where and how their music was available.&lt;ref name=&quot;blog.imeem.com&quot;/&gt;

The partnership marked imeem's move to an ad-supported model, in which consumers could freely stream and share music and video content with the costs supported by advertising. Under this model, artists and labels are paid a share of the site's ad revenue in proportion to the popularity of their music on imeem, and have the right to register their content and determine whether that content is available on the site or through its embeddable widgets.

Ultimately, the imeem messaging and file-sharing application had proven to be something of a resource hog for power-users, since the database could grow to large proportions just by associating with a few individuals who were sharing a lot of content. This messaging product was ultimately phased out; the site became entirely Web-based beginning in June 2007.  While this distributed model was interesting and received positive press,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Broida |first=Rick |url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,1872017,00.asp |title=imeem Review &amp; Rating |work=PCMag.com |date=2005-10-12 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lifehacker.com/208719/not-just-another-social+networking-site lifehacker.com]&lt;/ref&gt; it proved to be difficult to attract many users since the only way to participate was to download the imeem client software. Over time, imeem integrated many of the client's features into its website and the innovative distributed database model was been centralized.

Throughout the first half of 2007, imeem had negotiated with the major labels to secure licenses for this new model. [[Warner Music Group]] and imeem announced a licensing agreement for imeem's new Web-based service in July 2007,&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2007/warner-music-group-and-imeem-announce-strategic-digital-partnership/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; followed by [[Sony Music Entertainment]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forbes.com/2007/09/26/sony-bmg-imeem-biz-media_cx_lh_0926music2.html |title=Sony BMG Reaches Deal With Imeem |work=Forbes.com |date=2007-09-26 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[EMI]] Music&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/press-room/press-releases/imeem-2007/imeem-strikes-strategic-music-and-video-partnership-with-emi-music/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in September. In December 2007, imeem signed a licensing agreement with [[Universal Music Group]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/2007/12/10/technology/imeem/ | work=CNN | date=December 10, 2007 | accessdate=April 3, 2010 | title=Making music free (and legal) | first=Rob | last=Kelley}}&lt;/ref&gt; becoming the first online music service to partner with all four major music labels to let people legally stream and share music for free online.

===2008===
On January 28, 2008, imeem announced that it was acquiring the music locker{{clarify|date=March 2011|reason=WTH is a &quot;music locker&quot;?}} service Anywhere.FM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businesswire.com/portal/site/google/index.jsp?ndmViewId=news_view&amp;newsId=20080128005365&amp;newsLang=en |title=imeem Acquires Web Music Player Anywhere.FM |work=Businesswire.com |date=2008-01-28 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 1, 2008, imeem acquired SNOCAP. It had already been making extensive use of SNOCAP's audio fingerprinting technology and music database.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Michael Arrington Feb 13, 2008 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/02/13/imeem-acquires-snocap |title=imeem Acquires Snocap |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2008-02-13 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the acquisition, SNOCAP's chief operating officer, [[Ali Aydar]] (ex-[[Napster]]), joined imeem.

On March 24, 2008&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imeem.com/groups/zJqqiqve/blogs/2008/03/25/25F8vby8/were_openminded_about_media |title=We're open-minded about media Post on imeem |work=imeem.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; imeem announced the launch of a developer's platform that will permit third-party developers to interact with imeem data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imeem.com/developers/ |title=Developer Info |work=imeem.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2008, imeem received a new round of funding from [[Sequoia Capital]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sean P. Aune View Comments |url=http://mashable.com/2008/04/15/imeem-funding/ |date=April 15, 2008 |title=Imeem receives additional funding from Sequoia Capital |work=mashable.com |date=2008-04-15 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2008, imeem launched imeem Mobile,&lt;ref name=&quot;venturebeat.com&quot;/&gt; a free mobile music application.  However, on the 22nd of that month, the company [[Lay off|laid off]] 25% of its staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Mark Hendrickson Oct 22, 2008 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/10/22/imeem-cuts-quarter-of-its-staff-might-be-looking-for-buyer/ |title=imeem Cuts Quarter of Staff, Might Be Looking for Buyer |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2008-10-22 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2009===
The company's troubles continued into 2009, as Warner Music wrote down{{clarify|date=March 2011|reason=What is &quot;wrote down&quot; supposed to mean in this context? Link to something. I think you mean &quot;wrote off&quot;.}} its entire $15 million dollar investment in imeem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kafka |first=Peter |url=http://mediamemo.allthingsd.com/20090507/warner-music-group-walks-away-from-digital-startups-lala-imeem-and-loses-33-million/ |title=Warner Music Dumps Imeem, Lala &amp;#124; Peter Kafka &amp;#124; MediaMemo &amp;#124; AllThingsD |work=MediaMemo.AllThingsD.com |date=2009-05-07 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It seemed possible the company could close in April 2009, but it was able to renegotiate deals with its major label partners,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnbc.com/id/30980872 |title=News Headlines |work=CNBC.com |date=2009-05-28 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and subsequently found enough new investors to continue service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sandoval |first=Greg |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1023_3-10234357-93.html |title=Imeem dodges bullet with new round of funding &amp;#124; Digital Media - CNET News |work=News.CNET.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sources told TechCrunch that imeem raised $6 million in this most recent funding round,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Michael Arrington Sep 30, 2009 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/09/30/imeem-wipes-the-slate-clean-with-6-million-funding/ |title=iMeem Wipes The Slate Clean With $6 million Funding |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2009-09-30 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Morgenthaler Ventures and Warner Music Group among those investing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kafka |first=Peter |url=http://mediamemo.allthingsd.com/20090615/exclusive-warner-music-group-gets-back-together-very-cautiously-with-imeem/ |title=Warner Music Backs Imeem Again-for More Equity &amp;#124; Peter Kafka &amp;#124; MediaMemo &amp;#124; AllThingsD |work=MediaMemo.AllThingsD.com |date=2009-06-15 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company launched imeem Mobile for the iPhone and iPod touch in May 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=MG Siegler May 13, 2009 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/05/13/imeem-about-to-expand-iphone-storage-by-way-of-the-cloud/ |title=Imeem About To Expand iPhone Music Storage By Way Of The Cloud |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2009-05-13 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2009, imeem Mobile crossed a milestone of over 1 million installs on the Android and iPhone platforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;techcrunch.com&quot;/&gt;

On June 25, 2009, imeem announced that it was removing all user-uploaded video and photos from the site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/2009/06/25/simplifying-imeem/ Simplifying imeem]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This move, and the lack of advance notice, was unpopular with many users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/imeem_wants_to_simplify_its_service_deletes_all_photos_videos.php |title=Imeem Wants to Simplify Its Service - Deletes All User-generated Photos and Videos |publisher=readwriteweb.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2009, imeem and Google announced the integration of links to music on imeem within Google search results; imeem was one of several online music companies involved in such efforts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.imeem.com/2009/10/28/music-search-a-sound-strategy/ ]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Closure==
On December 8, 2009, MySpace (owned by [[News Corporation]]) acquired imeem, and angered many imeem users when the new parent company closed down the beleaguered service on the same day, redirecting all imeem traffic to MySpace Music. Furthermore, MySpace social network did not pay artists or labels the money still owed to them by imeem  for music streaming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.biz/bbbiz/content_display/industry/e3i323ddc5ff8ac6142a67f644482d4deb6 |title=Digital Briefs: Snocap, Green Day, Google |work=Billboard.biz |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The controversial closure was criticized as a sign that MySpace was out of touch with the times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sparxoo.com/2009/12/11/did-myspace-botch-handling-of-imeem-acquisition/ |title=Did MySpace Botch Handling of imeem Acquisition? |work=Sparxoo.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; MySpace, on December 22, 2009, assured imeem.com users that their playlists are safe and that they are currently duplicating every users' playlist and will migrate them on to MySpace Music as soon as possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.strategyeye.com/articles/digitalmedia/id/24138955 |title=MySpace promises to give back imeem playlists |work=StrategyEye - Industry Intelligence |date=2009-12-22 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; MySpace assured that features and functionality that users were used to at imeem would soon find their way onto MySpace, and complement the existing platform alongside free full-song streaming, artist profiles, music videos, and more.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://faq.myspace.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/941#pm_cmp=imeemmoreinfo |title=Myspace |work=FAQ.MySpace.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; MySpace will email imeem users the instructions on how to claim their playlists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jason Kincaid Dec 21, 2009 |url=http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/12/21/imeem-myspace/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+Techcrunch+%28TechCrunch%29 |title=MySpace Reaches Out To Upset Imeem Users: Your Playlists Will Soon Be Resurrected |work=Techcrunch.com |date=2009-12-21 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On January 15, 2010, MySpace began allowing users to import imeem playlists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rosoff |first=Matt |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13526_3-10436396-27.html |title=MySpace restores Imeem playlists &amp;#124; Digital Noise: Music and Tech - CNET News |work=News.CNET.com |date=2010-01-16 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, songs that are currently not available via MySpace Music were not converted over, and there was no means provided to even recover the names of the missing tracks. Additionally, user &quot;favorites&quot; metadata was not able to be carried over, with the result that users who depended upon their favorites lists instead of normal playlists were unable to retrieve their music.  Other complaints include incorrect artist info, garbled tracks, and an increase in between-songs advertising.

==Technology==
The back-end software for imeem's services was primarily written in [[C Sharp (programming language)|C#]]. While most of the front-end Web servers ran under [[Microsoft Windows]], some used the [[Linux]] operating system. The Web site heavily used [[Ajax (programming)|Ajax]] programming and [[Adobe Flash|Flash]] animation.

Audio streams were delivered as 128&amp;nbsp;[[Kilobit per second|kbps]]-quality [[MPEG-2 Audio Layer III]] (MP3) format. Video was encoded in the [[Sorenson Video]] [[codec]] at &gt;700kbps, in the [[Flash Video]] (FLV) [[Container file format|container format]], with resolution resized to 400 pixels wide and preserving its aspect ratio, and with embedded mp3 audio at 96&amp;nbsp;kbps. While the video quality and resolution was significantly better&lt;ref name=&quot;illectro.imeem.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://illectro.imeem.com/blogs/2007/12/17/KAMDUrDZ/video_quality_around_the_inernets |title=Video Quality around the inernets Post on imeem |work=Illectro.imeem.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; than other video sites at that time (YouTube, for example, used 300kbps video)&lt;ref name=&quot;illectro.imeem.com&quot;/&gt; the late-arriving video sharing aspect of imeem was largely eclipsed by the original audio sharing component{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}. In 2008 imeem upgraded the video quality further and became one of the first media sharing sites to offer video encoded with the [[H.264/MPEG-4 AVC|MPEG 4 H.264]] codec and at the original source resolution.

The original imeem client software conducted most of its network activity using an [[Encryption|encrypted]] protocol, making it difficult to monitor user activity. Thus, conversations via the client's IM functionality and group chats were encrypted and only visible to participants. On startup, the application validated with a central server. This ensured that unauthorized clients could not connect and run malicious exploits (such as for monitoring network traffic or spoofing identities) against the network. Software updates were also delivered via the client and authenticated before they were installed.  The company's move to a Web-based file-sharing business model in 2007 made most of these considerations moot.

==Copyright infringement lawsuit==
{{expand section|1=information on filing of claims made by the suit|date=March 2011}}
[[Warner Music Group]] announced on July 12, 2007 that it had dropped its copyright infringement lawsuit against imeem by agreeing to license its music and video content to the site for a percentage of imeem's advertising revenue. Financial details were not disclosed. Under the agreement, imeem could carry music and videos from all of the record company's artists. Warner also released financial statements indicating that it invested $15 million into imeem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Warner Music has $15M investment in imeem |date=2008-08-08 |url= http://www.thedeal.com/techconfidential/the-note/the-note/warner-music-filing-reveals-15.php |work=[[TheDeal.com]] |accessdate = 2008-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Meems (groups)===
Users of imeem could link to each other through topic groups (which were originally called '''meems'''), based on common interests. Some meems were created by imeem itself, while others were user-generated. Media content could be placed in custom profile pages and topic groups, as well as in browseable content channels and charts. Meems could serve as basic [[Online community|online communities]] for artists, bands, clubs, films, schools, festivals, concert tours, friends, and sports enthusiasts. A late redesign of the site replaced most of the &quot;meem&quot; references with the familiar word &quot;group&quot;. Early on, it had been possible for links to be made between groups which had related subject matter, but this feature had only been implemented in the original client software. After the transition to the Web-only service model, it became impossible for users to add (or even remove) such links, although official imeem-created groups sometimes had links added at creation time, by an administrative means not available to subscribers.

==See also==
* [[Deezer]]
* [[MeeMix]]
* [[Project Playlist]]
* [[Spotify]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.imeem.com }} (defunct)
* [http://www.snocap.com SNOCAP site]

{{Digital Distribution Platforms}}

&lt;!--Move all of these to &quot;Defunct&quot; versions when they exist.--&gt;

[[Category:Blog hosting services]]
[[Category:Defunct websites]]
[[Category:Instant messaging clients]]
[[Category:Social networking services]]
[[Category:Virtual communities]]
[[Category:Internet properties established in 2004]]
[[Category:2009 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Internet radio in the United States]]
[[Category:Music websites]]
[[Category:Online music and lyrics databases]]
[[Category:Android software]]
[[Category:BlackBerry software]]
[[Category:Web 2.0]]
[[Category:Video hosting]]
[[Category:Video on demand services]]
[[Category:Entertainment websites]]
[[Category:Companies based in San Francisco, California]]
[[Category:Defunct digital music services or companies]]

[[bn:এমিম]]
[[es:Imeem]]
[[fr:Imeem]]
[[it:Imeem]]
[[nl:Imeem]]
[[pt:Imeem]]
[[fi:Imeem]]
[[vi:Imeem]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
