<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="984882" ns="0" title="Windows NT 3.1"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS version
| name                = Windows NT 3.1
| family              = Microsoft Windows
| logo                = Windows NT 3.1 logo.svg
| logo_size           = 100px
| screenshot          = Windows NT 3.1.png
| caption             = Screenshot of Windows NT 3.1
| developer           = Microsoft
| website             = 
| source_model        = [[Closed source software|Closed source]]
| license             = [[Software license agreement|MS-EULA]]
| supported_platforms = [[IA-32]], [[DEC Alpha|Alpha]], [[MIPS architecture|MIPS]]
| kernel_type         = [[Hybrid kernel|Hybrid]]
| first_release_date  = 27 July 1993
| first_release_url   = http://blogs.technet.com/mrsnrub/archive/2009/08/04/windows-nt-history.aspx
| release_version     = 3.1 (Build 528: Service Pack 3)
| release_date        = {{Start date and age|1994|11|10}}
| release_url         = http://blogs.technet.com/mrsnrub/archive/2009/08/04/windows-nt-history.aspx
| preview_version     = 
| preview_date        = 
| preview_url         = 
| support_status      = Unsupported as of 31 December 2000&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/lifecycle/?p1=3191 Microsoft Product Lifecycle for Windows NT Workstation 3.1]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/lifecycle/?p1=3183] Microsoft Product Lifecycle for Windows NT Advanced Server 3.1&lt;/ref&gt;
| date                = January 2009 &lt;!-- approximate date of template insertion for dating hidden maintenance categories --&gt;
}}

'''Windows NT 3.1''' is the first release of [[Microsoft]]'s [[Windows NT]] line of [[Server (computing)|server]] and business desktop [[operating system]]s, and was released to manufacturing on 27 July 1993. The version number was chosen to match the one of [[Windows 3.1x|Windows 3.1]], the then-latest [[operating environment]] from [[Microsoft]], on account of the similar visual appearance of the user interface.  Two editions of NT 3.1 were made available, Windows NT 3.1 and Windows NT Advanced Server.  It was succeeded by [[Windows NT 3.5]] in September 1994.

It could run on Intel [[x86]], [[DEC Alpha]], and [[MIPS architecture|MIPS R4000]] [[Central processing unit|CPUs]].

==Development==
{{see also|History of Microsoft Windows}}
Development of Windows NT started in November 1988, after Microsoft hired a group of developers from [[Digital Equipment Corporation]] led by [[Dave Cutler]]. Many elements of the design reflect earlier DEC experience with [[Virtual Memory System|VMS]] and [[RSX-11]]. The operating system was designed to run on multiple [[instruction set architectures]] and multiple hardware platforms within each architecture. The platform dependencies are largely hidden from the rest of the system by a kernel mode module called the [[hardware abstraction layer|HAL]].

Windows NT was originally intended to be [[OS/2]] 3.0, the third version of the operating system developed jointly by Microsoft and [[International Business Machines|IBM]]. When [[Windows 3.0]] was released in May 1990, it was so successful that Microsoft decided to change the primary [[application programming interface]] for the still-unreleased NT OS/2 (as it was then known) from an extended OS/2 API to an extended [[Windows API]]. This decision caused tension between Microsoft and IBM, and the collaboration ultimately fell apart. IBM continued OS/2 development alone, while Microsoft continued work on the newly-renamed Windows NT.

The first public demonstration of Windows NT, at the time called &quot;Windows Advanced Server for LAN Manager&quot;, was at a developer conference in August 1991,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Windows Products and Technologies History: Windows Server Products History |url=http://www.microsoft.com/windows/WinHistoryServer.mspx |publisher=Microsoft |date=30 June 2003 |accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the product was formally announced at the Spring 1993 [[COMDEX]] in [[Atlanta, Georgia|Atlanta]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]].

[[Application programming interface]]s in Windows NT are implemented as subsystems atop the undocumented [[Native API]]; it was this that allowed the late adoption of the Windows API. Windows NT was the first operating system by Microsoft to use [[Unicode]] internally.  Windows NT introduced the [[Win32 API]], a 32-bit implementation of the 16-bit Windows API.  Most 16-bit Windows applications could be ported to the new system with minimal changes and a recompile.  Win32 also provided native API support for many new features, such as networking and multithreading.

The project had a [[codename]] of just &quot;NTOS&quot;, which is preserved in the filename of the Windows NT kernel, &lt;tt&gt;ntoskrnl.exe&lt;/tt&gt;.
Since it was targeted to become the next version of OS/2, a more official name of the project was &quot;NT OS/2&quot;. This name is preserved up to now in some Windows NT [[driver development kit]] files.

==System support==
NT was designed from the ground up to be portable to other platforms.  All kernel and subsystem code was written in [[C (programming language)|C]] and [[C++]].  Any differences in core hardware architecture that could not be resolved by a simple recompile (e.g., memory architecture, multi/uniprocessor support) were offloaded to the [[Hardware Abstraction Layer|HAL]].

Also, NT's boot architecture borrowed heavily from the [[Advanced RISC Computing|ARC]] initiative, particularly on non-x86 platforms.

===i860===
&lt;!-- NOTE: Please do not insert reason for name &quot;NT&quot; until after reading article on Windows NT. --&gt;
Originally, NT was targeted at the [[Intel i860]] CPU, codenamed N10 (or &quot;N-Ten&quot;).
However, the i860 was &quot;horribly behind schedule&quot;, so the NT team used an emulator before i860 prototype systems designed in-house (code-named ''Dazzle'') were available. Support for the other platforms followed later and no public release of NT for i860 systems was made. The rationale for targeting the i860 first was to improve portability and avoid producing an x86-centric design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Mark Lucovsky |title=Windows A Software Engineering Odyssey |url=http://www.usenix.org/events/usenix-win2000/invitedtalks/lucovsky_html/ |publisher=USENIX |date=9 August 2000 |accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===x86===
NT 3.1 supported the Intel x86 32-bit family (80386 and later). Compared to 16-bit Windows 3.x, NT's driver support was somewhat limited. Windows NT 3.1 is the only version of Windows NT that supports multiprocessor 386-based machines.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web  | last =  | first =  | title = STOP screen when installing Windows NT 3.5 on 386 SMP machine | url = http://support.microsoft.com/kb/121043 | publisher =  | date =  | accessdate = 4 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===MIPS===
Windows NT also supported the [[MIPS architecture|MIPS R4000]] processor; specifically MIPS systems following the [[Advanced RISC Computing]] (ARC) specification.

===Alpha===
Early in the NT beta cycle, support was added for the [[DEC Alpha]] processor.  However, because the Alpha itself was delayed, Microsoft's developers did not have access to production Alpha machines to develop on until shortly before NT shipped.  Consequently, NT did not initially ship with Alpha support out of the box: the first packages of NT included a mail-in coupon to receive a free CD of NT 3.1 with Alpha support.

==Application compatibility==
===16-bit Windows===
Windows NT provided a 16-bit compatibility subsystem, called &quot;[[Windows on Windows]]&quot; (aka WOW), which allowed most Windows 3.x applications to run unmodified on NT.  Applications which made direct access to hardware, or depended on DOS-level drivers, were not supported.

In NT 3.1, all 16-bit applications ran within a single WOW process.  This meant that a single badly behaving 16-bit application could shut down the WOW session (and any other 16-bit applications running).  However, the operating system itself was insulated, so the WOW process could simply be killed and restarted &amp;mdash; a significant step forward for Windows' stability.

===32-bit Windows===
NT also introduced [[Win32 API|Win32]], a 32-bit implementation of the Windows API.  This permitted many 16-bit Windows applications to be recompiled for the system with minimal changes.  Win32 also allowed the growing body of 16-bit Windows programmers to leverage their skills on the new system.  The Win32 API was maintained (with some modifications) with [[Windows 95]], further solidifying its role as Microsoft transitioned users off of the 16-bit platform.

Win32 is a comprehensive API, offering OS services ranging from memory management to UI access.  NT prevents all user-level applications from directly accessing hardware.  This increases system reliability, at the cost of performance.  However, this also means that virtually all Win32 applications relied exclusively on the C/C++ Win32 API; the upshot is that porting such an application to another NT-supported system architecture (e.g., moving from x86 NT to MIPS NT) usually required no more than a recompile (some applications might require minor tweaking, such as if assumptions were made in code about [[endianness]]).

===[[OS/2]]===
Though &quot;NT OS/2&quot; was finally released as &quot;Windows NT&quot;, it is largely compatible with [[High Performance File System|HPFS]] disk volumes and the x86 version supports [[Text user interface|character-mode]] 16-bit OS/2 applications.  Many of the OS/2 APIs (particularly NetBIOS/LANMan networking APIs) already existed in almost identical forms in both 16-bit OS/2 and DOS/Windows, so these were incorporated into the Win32 API.  For most 16-bit OS/2 programs, minimal code changes were necessary to recompile as NT [[Win32 console|console]] [[Console application|applications]].

OS/2 and Windows also share the concept of [[Dynamic-link library|Dynamic-Link Libraries]] (DLLs).  Although the implementation varies somewhat between Windows and OS/2 DLLs, this additional similarity meant that even complex OS/2 applications could usually be converted to NT with little change to the overall design.

===POSIX===
Windows NT 3.1 included a subsystem that was minimally [[POSIX]]-compatible.  This was added largely to help spur sales in US government contracts, as many government agencies mandated POSIX compatibility for consideration.

Note that POSIX compatibility is an API-level requirement.  That is, one POSIX operating system won't necessarily be able to execute binary files compiled for a different system, even though both are POSIX compliant.  POSIX simply specifies that the source code should compile correctly for each system.

The POSIX subsystem in NT 3.1 primarily provided support for UNIX-style [[File_system_permissions#Traditional_Unix_permissions|file system permissions]] and [[long filename]]s (including permitting filename characters that are otherwise illegal for Windows files, and denying some that are normally legal).

===Internet Explorer===
Microsoft offered [[Internet Explorer]] starting with [[Internet Explorer 2|IE2]], and released up to [[Internet Explorer 5|Internet Explorer 5.0]] for Windows NT 3.x. Also, a IE 1.5 supported NT, but this patch was actually released after IE2 came out.

==Editions==
*Windows NT
*Windows NT Advanced Server

==Networking==
NT 3.1 included support for three [[network protocol]]s: [[NetBIOS Frames protocol|NBF]] (using the [[NetBEUI]] API), [[TCP/IP]], and [[Data Link Control|DLC]].

===NetBIOS Frames protocol===
At the time of NT's release, NetBIOS Frames protocol (NBF) was the most common protocol on Microsoft [[LAN Manager]]/IBM [[IBM LAN Server|LAN Server]] networks.  In NT 3.1, it was the only supported protocol for networking with legacy LAN Manager networks, as well as other NT systems.  Using NBF, NT could participate in file/print sharing, and NT Advanced Server could act as a [[Domain Controller]] (even sharing DC duties with OS/2 LAN Manager servers).

===TCP/IP===
Windows NT 3.1 was the first Windows operating system to include TCP/IP support as standard. The TCP/IP stack used was SpiderTCP, developed by [[Spider Systems]]. This was replaced in NT 3.5 with a new stack developed in-house.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Adam Barr |title=Microsoft, TCP/IP, Open Source, and Licensing |url=http://www.kuro5hin.org/?op=displaystory;sid=2001/6/19/05641/7357 |publisher=Kuro5hin |date=19 June 2001 |accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The TCP/IP stack included [[Winsock|WinSock]] and [[STREAMS]] support, but it was not supported for networking among Microsoft LAN Manager or NT systems.  Also, [[DHCP]] was not available, so IP addresses had to be manually configured.  Support for [[NetBIOS over TCP/IP|NBT]], DHCP, and [[Windows Internet Name Service|WINS]] was added in NT 3.5.

===Data Link Control===
Data Link Control (DLC) was supported as a transport protocol for the purpose of communicating with network printers, such as those using an [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]] [[JetDirect]] interface.  It could also be used by [[Host Integration Server|Microsoft SNA Server]] for communication with [[IBM mainframe]] systems.

==Further reading==
*G. Pascal Zachary (1994). &quot;Show Stopper!: The Breakneck Race to Create Windows NT and the Next Generation at Microsoft&quot;, Free Press, ISBN 0-02-935671-7

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.guidebookgallery.org/guis/windows/winnt31 Guidebook: Windows NT 3.1 Gallery] - A website dedicated to preserving and showcasing Graphical User Interfaces

{{Microsoft Windows family}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Windows Nt 3.1}}
[[Category:1993 software]]
[[Category:Windows NT]]
[[Category:Discontinued versions of Microsoft Windows]]

[[ar:ويندوز إن تي 3.1]]
[[az:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[ca:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[cs:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[da:Microsoft Windows NT 3.1]]
[[de:Microsoft Windows NT 3.1]]
[[es:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[ko:윈도 NT 3.1]]
[[hy:Վինդոուզ ԷնԹի 3.1]]
[[id:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[it:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[hu:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[pl:Microsoft Windows NT 3.1]]
[[sl:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[sr:Виндоус НТ 3.1]]
[[tl:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[ta:வின்டோஸ் என்டி 3.1]]
[[tr:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[vi:Windows NT 3.1]]
[[zh:Windows NT 3.1]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
