<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9923096" ns="0" title="Scientology cross"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Scientology Cross Logo.png|thumb|right|The Scientology cross has eight corners representing the eight dynamics of life.]]

The '''Scientology cross''' is one of the principal [[symbols of Scientology]]. It is most often used to represent the [[Church of Scientology]].

The cross closely resembles the Christian cross, but differs from it with the addition of four diagonal rays between the conventional horizontal and vertical arms. The eight points of the cross represent the eight [[Scientology beliefs and practices#dynamics|dynamics]] in Scientology:

# The Self
# Creativity, sex, and procreation (family)
# Group, society, community
# Species survival (humankind)
# Life forms in general
# Matter
# Spirit
# Infinity or Supreme being

The Church of Scientology says that &quot;the horizontal bar represents the material universe, and the vertical bar represents the spirit. Thus, the spirit is seen to be rising triumphantly, ultimately transcending the turmoil of the physical universe to achieve salvation.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.scripturalscientology.org/page13.htm Scientology Cross]&quot;, Church of Scientology International. Accessed 2007-07-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Scientology cross apparently dates back to the mid-1950s. Scientology's founder [[L. Ron Hubbard]] wrote in 1955 that &quot;the model of the cross came from a very ancient Spanish mission in [[Arizona]], a sand casting which [Hubbard] dug up&quot; &lt;ref&gt;''Ability'' magazine issue 14, 1955&lt;/ref&gt; He also occasionally referred to it as the &quot;sunburst cross&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hubbard, &quot;Operational Bulletin No. 5&quot;, November 1955&lt;/ref&gt; Hubbard was based in [[Phoenix, Arizona]] for a substantial part of 1952, though it is not clear whether his asserted discovery of the cross dates from this period.

Critics of Scientology have noted other possible derivations from [[occult]] sources. The Scientology cross is similar to the [[Rosicrucianism|Rosicrucian]] or [[Rose Cross|Rosy cross]] and the similar cross of [[Aleister Crowley]]'s [[Ordo Templi Orientis]]. Hubbard was briefly a member of the Rosicrucians and was involved in OTO &quot;magical workings&quot; in [[Pasadena, California]] some years before founding Scientology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religio.de/atack/occ3.html Factnet Report:  Hubbard and the Occult, pt. 3], by Jon Atack&lt;/ref&gt;

The practice of prominently displaying the cross in Scientology centers was instituted in 1969 following hostile press coverage in the [[United Kingdom]] and elsewhere, when Scientology's status as a legitimate religion was being questioned. In response, Hubbard ordered that &quot;Any staff who are trained at any level as [[Auditing (Scientology)|auditors]] (but not in A[dvanced] O[rganization]s) are to be clothed in the traditioned ministerial black suit, black vest white collar silver cross for ordinary org wear.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Hubbard, &quot;Religion&quot;, HCO Policy Letter of 12 February 1969&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Christian cross]]
* [[Crucifix]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Scientology}}

[[Category:Religious symbols]]
[[Category:Scientology beliefs and practices]]
[[Category:1955 introductions]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
