<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="995545" ns="0" title="University of Tennessee at Chattanooga"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name           = University of Tennessee at Chattanooga
|image_name     = University of Tennessee at Chattanooga seal.png
|motto          = {{lang-la|Faciemus}}
|motoeng        = We shall achieve
|established    = 1886
|type           = [[Public university]]
|endowment      = $77.3 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = March 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|chancellor     = Roger Brown
|city           = [[Chattanooga]]
|state          = [[Tennessee|TN]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|coor           = {{coord|35.0458|-85.2999|type:edu_region:US|display=inline,title}}
|undergrad      = 11,429
|postgrad       = 1,364 (graduate, pre-professional, doctoral)
|staff          = 422
|campus         = [[Urban area|Urban]], {{convert|102.3|acre|m2}} (1,947,436 Gross Square Feet)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.utc.edu/Administration/PlanningEvaluationAndInstitutionalResearch/factbook/documents/FACTSUMMARY00.pdf Fact Book]&lt;/ref&gt;
|nickname       = Mocs
|mascot         = Scrappy the Mocking Bird
|colors         = {{colorbox|#00386B}} Navy and {{colorbox|#E0AA0F}} Old Gold&lt;ref&gt;http://www.utc.edu/Administration/UniversityRelations/web_dgn.php&lt;/ref&gt;
|free_label     = Athletics
|free           = [[Southern Conference]], [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]]
|logo           = [[Image:University of Tennessee at Chattanooga athletics logo.png|100px]]
|website        = http://www.utc.edu
}}

'''The University of Tennessee at Chattanooga'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.utc.edu/Administration/UniversityRelations/u_style.php#Naming_the_University  Naming the University]&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[public university]] located in [[Chattanooga, Tennessee]]. The University, often referred to as UTC or simply &quot;Chattanooga&quot; (especially in reference to its collegiate athletics), is one of three universities and two other affiliated institutions in the [[University of Tennessee System]]; the others being in Knoxville and Martin.

UTC was founded in 1886 as then-private '''Chattanooga University''', which was renamed in 1889 as [[Ulysses S. Grant|U.S. Grant]] University. In 1907, the university changed its name to '''University of Chattanooga'''. In 1969, the university merged with [[Zion College]]/Chattanooga City College to form The University of Tennessee at Chattanooga as part of the University of Tennessee System.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.utc.edu/news/installation/Program.pdf Installation Ceremony program for Roger G. Brown]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Administration==
{{See|List of leaders of the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga}}

Chattanooga uses the [[semester]] system, with five optional &quot;mini-terms&quot; in the summer.  The leadership of the campus rests upon the [[chancellor]], who answers to the [[University of Tennessee System|UT System President]]. The current chancellor is Roger Brown.

==Student Government Association of UTC==
A voice for student leadership on campus, the SGA consists of senators representing districts/the college they belong to, such as the College of Arts and Sciences.

==Academics==
Chattanooga is best known for its nationally ranked [[Business]] program,&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.utc.edu/news/2009/03/businessweek-names-utc-in-top-100-list/&lt;/ref&gt; [[Engineering]], [[Nursing]], [[English studies|English]], [[Chemistry]], [[Accounting]] , [[Psychology]], and [[pedagogy|Education]] departments.  The university offers over 140 undergraduate majors and concentrations, and over 50 undergraduate minors.&lt;ref name=&quot;utc.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.utc.edu/Administration/Records/2009-10MajorCodes.php&lt;/ref&gt;  Chattanooga also offers nearly 100 graduate programs&lt;ref name=&quot;utc.edu&quot;/&gt; and concentrations, including a highly ranked&lt;ref&gt;Kraiger &amp; Abalos, &quot;Rankings of Graduate Programs in I-O Psychology Based on Student Ratings of Quality&quot;[http://www.siop.org/tip/backissues/July04/PDF/TOC.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt; master's program in [[Industrial and Organizational Psychology]] and [[Ph.D.]] programs in  Computational Engineering and [[Physical Therapy]]. In an effort to expand the horizons of its students body, Chattanooga recently began exchange with Kangnung National University of Kangnung, South Korea

==Media and publications==
;Print
* ''University Echo'' – Student newspaper
* ''Education About Asia'' – Educational magazine
* ''Sequoya Review'' – Literary magazine
* ''Modern Psychological Studies''– Journal published by the Department of Psychology 

;Radio
* WUTC
* The Perch –  Student-run online radio station

==Research==
* SimCenter is UTC's computational engineering and simulation center. In November 2005, SimCenter  was listed as the 89th most powerful supercomputer by [[Top500]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.top500.org/site/history/2580 UT SimCenter at Chattanooga | TOP500 Supercomputing Sites&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; On November 20, 2007, the University announced the center has been named a National Center for Computational Engineering.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}} More recently, The SimCenter provided the academic research for a new source of alternative energy unveiled by Bloom Energy Corporation in Sunnyvale, California.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.utc.edu/news/2010/02/national-simcenter-research-advances-alternative-energy/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
The University is served by [[Chattanooga Area Regional Transportation Authority|CARTA]] bus routes 4, 7, 10, 14, 19, and 28.  Route 14 only operates on weekdays during fall and spring terms, when the University is session.  The route runs within and without the Chattanooga campus on McCallie, Houston, Vine, Douglas, Fifth, and Palmetto Streets. A recent extension serves Third, O'Neal and Central Streets, as well as Erlanger Hospital, and a large parking lot at [[Engel Stadium]].  All students showing valid University identification cards (aka MocsCards) ride for free on all CARTA routes, year-round.

===Academic buildings===
''Note: Dates of construction given when known''

{|style=&quot;clear:right;padding:7px;background:none;&quot;  align=right
|-
|
[[Image:UTC Race Hall.jpg|thumb|Founder's Hall]]
|}

* Administration Building  – mailroom, parking services, motor pool and university police department
* Brenda Lawson Student Athlete Success Center – Scheduled to open in August 2008, the center will house the Wolford Family Strength and Conditioning Center and the [[Chattem]] Basketball Center
* Bretske Hall – Formerly the university cafeteria, prior home of the Geology Department
* Brock Hall – Foreign languages, geography, anthropology, history and sociology departments.
* [[Space Shuttle Challenger|Challenger]] Center – The widow of [[Dick Scobee]], a Challenger [[astronaut]], donated the building in her husband's memory. This educational simulation includes different space missions with project completed from mission control and a space station.
* Cadek Hall (pronounced &quot;SHODD-ik&quot;) – Home to the Cadek Conservatory, UTC Choral Department, and [[WUTC]] radio.
* Davenport Hall – Criminal Justice, Social Work, and Physical Therapy Departments
* Engineering, Mathematics and Computer Science Building (EMCS)
* Fletcher Hall – (1939) Business Administration and Political Science departments.  From 1939 to 1974, Fletcher housed both the local public library and the university library
* Founders' Hall – (1916) Chancellor's offices, University Relations
* Frist Hall – Office For Student with Disabilities, Mosaic Program , Communication Department.  Once part of the Chattanooga metro hospital complex
* [[Irvine W. Grote|Grote Hall]] (pronounced &quot;GROW-tee&quot;) – (1968) Chemistry and [[physics]] departments
* Guerry Hall (pronounced &quot;GEH-ree&quot;) – Houses admissions, honors program and reading room, Economics Department
* Holt Hall – Biology, English, philosophy, psychology, and religion departments
* Hooper-Race Hall – (1916) Records and registration, financial aid, and human resources departments. Recently, Hooper Hall reopened after a [[lead]] and [[asbestos]] abatement project
* [[George Hunter (Coca-Cola bottler)|Hunter Hall]] [[Pedagogy|Education]] Department
* Lupton Library – (1974) see below
* Metropolitan Hall – Nursing department. Formerly housed the [[Chattanooga Metropolitan Hospital]]
* Old Math Building – Demolished in the late 1990s.
* President's House – Development (fundraising) Department
* Patten House – (1893) Located in the [[Fort Wood National Historic District]]. Home of the Alumni Affairs Department.
* Dorothy Patten Fine Arts Center – (1980) Houses the Dorothy Hackett Ward theatre, the [[Roland W. Hayes]] Concert Hall and the George Ayers Cress Art Gallery, referred to as the &quot;FAC.&quot; Also houses the UTC Music and Theater Departments
* University Center – Bursar's Office, and Student areas include a computer lab, a recreation and game room, offices, main cafeteria, bookstore, classrooms and auditoriums; administrative areas include meeting rooms, administrative offices for the student development division, counseling and career planning, women's center, student placement and employment and cooperative education and Bursars Office
* University Hall – (1886) &quot;Old Main.&quot; Demolished in 1917

===Patten Chapel===
{|style=&quot;clear:right;padding:7px;background:none;&quot;  align=right
|-
|
[[Image:PattenChapel.jpg|thumb|Patten Chapel]]
|}

* Patten Chapel is one of the busiest sanctuaries in Chattanooga. Mostly weddings and memorial services are held there. A bride's room has been prepared and is always ready. Reserving the chapel should be done around a year in advance as its popularity sees events almost every weekend. Wedding receptions are not hosted at the chapel.

===Library===
The Lupton Memorial Library, named for [[Cartter Lupton|T. Cartter and Margaret Rawlings Lupton]] was constructed in 1974 to replace the aging John Storrs Fletcher Library (which has since been restored and renamed Fletcher Hall).  As of 2005, the library's collection includes nearly 2 million items, including the [[Fellowship of Southern Writers]] archives.  In early 2008 the University was granted funding to build a new library and is currently in the building phase of the project.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.lib.utc.edu/index.php/Library_Building_Project Library Building Project Wiki at UTC]&lt;/ref&gt;

The University broke ground in 2010 for the new $48 million {{convert|180,000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} library.  Construction is to be completed by Jan 2012. &lt;ref&gt; http://www.utc.edu/Administration/UniversityRelations/Chattanooga_Today/201002/campus.php &lt;/ref&gt; 

==Notable alumni, students and faculty==
*[[Hugh Beaumont (actor)|Hugh Beaumont]], actor (most notably portrayed [[Ward Cleaver]] on &lt;i&gt;[[Leave It to Beaver]]&lt;/i&gt;), 1927
*[[Burwell Baxter Bell]], [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] [[General (United States)|general]], 1968
*[[North Callahan]], author and historian whose papers and book collection now reside in the UTC Lupton Library, 1919
*[[Gibby Gilbert]], [[PGA Tour]] professional golfer, 1963
*[[Irvine W. Grote]], chemist, inventor of the active ingredient in [[Rolaids]] and [[Bufferin]], UC 1918; chemistry faculty, 1942–1969
*[[Dennis Haskins]], actor (most notably portrayed [[Mr. Belding]] on &lt;i&gt;[[Saved By The Bell]]&lt;/i&gt;), 1972
*[[Leslie Jordan]], [[Emmy]]-winning actor, 1982
*[[Terrell Owens]], [[NFL]] football player, basketball player, 1997
*[[Johnny Taylor (basketball)|Johnny Taylor]], basketball player, 1997
*[[Gerald Wilkins]], basketball player, 1984
*[[Pez Whatley]], football player and UTC's first black wrestler, later became a pro wrestler
*[[Barry Moser]], artist and professor, 1970.
*[[Charlie Long]], basketball player, football player (NFL/AFL ALL-Pro)
*[[Mindaugas Katelynas]], basketball player, 2005
*[[Buster Skrine]], [[NFL]] football player ([[Cleveland Browns]]), 2011
*[[Eldra Buckley]], [[NFL]] football player, 2007

==Athletics==
Chattanooga's colors are [[navy]] and [[gold (color)|old gold]]; their men's teams and athletes are nicknamed Mocs, and women's teams and athletes are Lady Mocs. Chattanooga athletics teams compete in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I (FCS for [[College football|football]]) in the [[Southern Conference]] and have been ranked as a national top 100 athletic program by The National Association of Collegiate Director’s of Athletics (NACDA) in the Division I Learfield Sports Director’s Cup.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gomocs.com/ViewArticle.dbml?&amp;DB_OEM_ID=17700&amp;ATCLID=3754165&amp;SPID=10571&amp;SPSID=88662&lt;/ref&gt;

;Basketball
{{Main|Chattanooga Mocs basketball}}
Chattanooga's men's basketball program has been among the best in the Southern Conference since joining the league in 1977–78.  The Mocs have won 10 SoCon Tournament titles, tied for first all-time with former member West Virginia and Davidson, 10 regular-season league championships prior to the change to the division format in 1995 and seven division titles for 27 totals titles.  In [[1997 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|1997]], led by coach [[Mack McCarthy]] and PG Wes Moore, the Mocs made a run to the Sweet 16 as a No. 14 seed, beating Georgia and Illinois before falling to Providence.  Before making the move to Division I, Chattanooga won the Division II National Championship in 1977. &lt;ref&gt;NCAA Division II Men's Basketball Championship History [http://www.ncaa.com/history/basketball-men/d2]&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2008, the team was ranked number 48 on the [[ESPN]] list of the most prestigious basketball programs since the 1984–85 season.&lt;ref&gt;Harold Shelton, Nick Loucks and Chris Fallica, [http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/news/story?id=3481014 &quot;Counting down the most prestigious programs since 1984–85&quot;], [[ESPN]], July 21, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mocs won the SoCon tournament [[2009 Southern Conference Men's Basketball Tournament|once again in 2009]].  Defeating the [[College of Charleston Cougars men's basketball|College of Charleston Cougars]] 80-69 in the championship game on their home court at the [[McKenzie Arena]], the Mocs punched their ticket to the [[2009 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Tournament]], their first since [[2009 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|2005]].

Jimmy Fallon from ''[[Late Night with Jimmy Fallon]]'' chose the Mocs as his team of choice going into the 2009 NCAA Tournament.  The Wednesday night (March 18) show included a live Skype chat with Head Coach John Shulman, as well as representatives of the pep band and cheerleading squads made in studio.  Fallon's band &quot;The Roots&quot; wrote and performed an ode to Shulman titled, &quot;The Don Juan of the SoCon&quot; and Shulman and his six seniors (Nicchaeus Doaks, Zach Ferrell, Kevin Goffney, Khalil Hartwell, Stephen McDowell and Keyron Sheard) made an in-studio appearance following their tournament game with UConn.

The Lady Mocs are the most successful women's basketball program in Southern Conference history with 15 regular season titles since 1983–1984, 10 consecutive conference championships at the end of 2008–2009 and 14 overall conference championships.&lt;ref name=&quot;gomocs.com&quot;&gt;http://www.gomocs.com//pdf4/656557.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

;Golf
The men’s golf squad won its third consecutive Southern Conference trophy and finished 18th in the NCAA Championships in 2009.

Women’s golf posted a 3.46 team GOA in the spring while advancing to the NCAA Division I finals in just the second year of the program since disbanding in the mid-1980s.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nmnathletics.com/fls/17700/Sidebars/Women%27s%20Golf/Postseason%20Guide_Wglf0809.pdf?SPSID=88666&amp;SPID=10574&amp;DB_OEM_ID=17700&lt;/ref&gt;

;Softball
The Mocs’ softball team has won 11 regular season titles and 10 SoCon Tournament Championships.  They have also made 7 NCAA tournament appearances.&lt;ref name=&quot;gomocs.com&quot;/&gt;

;Wrestling
Chattanooga is home to the only NCAA Division I wrestling program in the state of Tennessee.  The Mocs Wrestling team won their fifth consecutive Socon title in 2008–2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;gomocs.com&quot;/&gt;

;Football
The team plays in the Southern Conference in Division I FCS (formerly I-AA) (Socon). Terrell Owens played college football at UTC. The team posted consecutive winning seasons in 2009–2010 and 2010–2011. They play in Finley stadium, which has hosted the division-1 national championship for the last 13 years.

==Athletic venues==
* [[Chamberlain Field]] – (1908–1997)
* [[W. Max Finley Stadium|Finley Stadium]] – (1997–present)
* [[Maclellan Gymnasium]] and [[natatorium]] – (Gym opened 1961; natatorium opened 1968)
* [[McKenzie Arena]] – (1982–present) aka the Roundhouse, due to its circular shape and the city's association with the railroad industry.

==University nickname==
The school's athletic teams are called the Mocs.  The teams were nicknamed Moccasins until 1996.  (The origin of the name is uncertain; however, [[Moccasin Bend]] is a large horseshoe-shaped bend in the [[Tennessee River]] directly below [[Lookout Mountain]].)

The mascot has taken on four distinct forms, with a [[water moccasin]] being the mascot in the 1920s, and then a [[Moccasin (footwear)|moccasin]] shoe (known as &quot;The Shoe&quot;) was actually used as the school's mascot at times in the 1960s and 1970s.  From the 1970s until 1996, the mascot was [[Chief Moccanooga]], an exaggerated [[Cherokee]] tribesman.

In 1996, due to concerns over ethnic sensitivity,&lt;ref&gt;George Dohrmann, [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/11280858.html?dids=11280858:11280858&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Mar+19%2C+1997&amp;author=GEORGE+DOHRMANN&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=1&amp;desc=COLLEGE+BASKETBALL+%2F+NCAA+TOURNAMENT%3B+Big+Mack+Has+%27Em+Loving+the+Mocs%3B+McCarthy%27s+Team%2C+in+the+Sweet+16%2C+May+Even+Rate+Over+Barbecue+in+Chattanooga &quot;Big Mack has 'em loving the Mocs; McCarthy's team, in the Sweet 16, may even rate over barbecue in Chattanooga&quot;], [[LA Times]], Mar 19, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; the Moccasins name and image were dropped in favor of the shortened &quot;Mocs&quot; and an [[anthropomorphism|anthropomorphized]] [[northern mockingbird]], in accordance with the state bird, named &quot;Scrappy&quot; dressed as a railroad engineer.  The school's main athletic logo features Scrappy riding a train (a reference to Chattanooga's history as a major [[railroad]] hub and to the song &quot;[[Chattanooga Choo Choo]]&quot;).  The mascot takes its name from former [[American football|football]] coach [[Andy Moore (American football)|A. C. &quot;Scrappy&quot; Moore]].

==Fight song==
The fight song for Chattanooga is &quot;Fight Chattanooga&quot;.

==Band==
{{Main|University of Tennessee at Chattanooga Marching Mocs}}

The marching band is referred to as the &quot;Marching Mocs&quot; and performs at all home games

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.utc.edu/ Official UTC website]
* [http://www.gomocs.com/ Official Chattanooga athletics site]
* [http://www.mocfans.com/ Fan Message Board]
* [http://www.utcpolice.org/ UT Chattanooga Police Dept]



{{Tennessee public universities}}
{{UTsystem}}
{{Southern Conference}}
{{Marching Bands of the Southern Conference}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tennessee, University Of, Chattanooga}}
[[Category:University of Tennessee at Chattanooga| ]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Chattanooga, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Coalition of Urban and Metropolitan Universities]]

[[cs:University of Tennessee at Chattanooga]]
[[de:University of Tennessee at Chattanooga]]
[[fa:دانشگاه تنسی در چتانوگا]]
[[fr:Université du Tennessee à Chattanooga]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
