<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="9973267" ns="0" title="Eelam War II"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict 
|    conflict = Eelam War II
|      partof = the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]
|       image = 
|     caption = 
|        date = [[1990]] – [[1995]]
|       place = [[Sri Lanka]]
|       casus =  
|      result = Indecisive
|  combatant1 = [[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
|  combatant2 = [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
|  commander1 = [[Ranasinghe Premadasa]] (1989–93)&lt;br&gt;
[[Dingiri Banda Wijetunge]] (1993–94)&lt;br&gt;
[[Chandrika Kumaratunga]] (1994–1995)
| commander2  = [[Velupillai Prabhakaran]]
|   strength1 =
|   strength2 =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
}}
{{Campaignbox Eelam War II}}
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}
{{Sri Lankan Conflict}}
'''''Eelam War II''''' is the name given to the second phase of armed conflict between Sri Lankan military and the separatist [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]].  The war started after the failure of peace talks between the Premadasa government and the LTTE. This phase of the war was initiated by the LTTE who massacred almost 600 sinhalese and Muslim police personnel after they were ordered by the Premadasa government to surrender to the LTTE.  The truce was broken on June 10, 1990. The LTTE in October expelled all the 28,000 Muslims residing in [[Jaffna]].

==Civilian killings==
===Palliyagodella massacre===

{{main|Palliyagodella massacre}}
The Palliyagodella massacre is an incident in October 1991 in which LTTE cadres massacred 109 Muslim men, women and children in Palliyagodella. The background to this massacre was the growing tension between the LTTE and the Muslim community. The Palliyagodella villagers had asked the Sri Lankan military for protection from LTTE extortion. The Sri Lankan forces issued shotguns to the Muslim villagers but these were inadequate to beat off LTTE attacks. Female LTTE cadres and child soldiers were involved in this attack.not only this attack this LTTE attacked to the sacret bodhi tree in anuradhapura &amp; the temple tooth in kandy,sri lanka.

===sri maha bodhi attack===
This incident happened in Sri Lanka in 1985. LTTE cadres killed more than 146 people in that attack.  The background to this attack was the confliction between tamils &amp; sinhalease.

==See also==

*[[Sri Lankan Civil War]]
*[[Eelam War I]]
*[[Eelam War III]]
*[[Eelam War IV]]

==External links==
*[http://www.defence.lk/ Ministry of Defence, Sri Lanka]
*[http://www.peaceinsrilanka.org/ GoSL Peace Secretariat]
*[http://www.ltteps.org/ LTTE Peace Secretariat]
*[http://www.slmm.lk/ Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission]
*[http://www.theacademic.org/ Lanka Academic, news site sponsored by Sri Lankan academics worldwide]
* [http://www.sangam.org/ Sangam.org]
* [http://www.c-r.org/our-work/accord/sri-lanka/key-texts.php Texts of key agreements in the peace process and an analysis of the process by Conciliation Resources]
* [http://www.asiafoundation.org/Locations/srilanka_publications.html Report on the Sri Lankan peace process by Asiafoundation]
* [http://www.hweb.org.uk/content/view/27/4/ hWeb - Sri Lanka’s recent history of ethnic conflict and political crisis originates from its colonial legacy]
* [http://nesohr.org/human-rights-reports/StatisticsOnCiviliansAffectedByWar.pdf?PHPSESSID=8204ff9bfa58e205f71a95c3899f8835 NorthEast Secretariat report on Human rights 1974-2004]
*[http://www.hweb.org.uk/content/view/27/4/ hWeb - Sri Lanka’s recent history of ethnic conflict originates from its colonial legacy]
*[http://www.peaceandwar-ha.blogspot.com/  Peace&amp;War: Humanity Ashore Pictorial]

[[Category:Eelam War II|*]]
[[Category:1990 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:1991 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:1992 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:1993 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:1994 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:1995 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:20th-century conflicts]]
[[Category:History of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Wars involving Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Battles involving Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Battles of the Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Military history of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Tamil Eelam]]
[[Category:Guerrilla wars|Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Counter-terrorism in Sri Lanka]]


{{SriLanka-stub}}

[[de:Bürgerkrieg in Sri Lanka]]
[[nl:Conflict in Sri Lanka]]
[[no:Etnisk konflikt i Sri Lanka]]
[[fi:Sri Lankan sisällissota]]
[[sv:Inbördeskonflikten i Sri Lanka]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
